<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/130/0 images: 298-329</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0167118 COPY NO,7.Qth kiay, 196?6Memorandum by the Secretary of Sta.tc for Foreign AffairsThe Middle East stands on the brink of war as a result of theEgyptian action in removing the United Nations Emergency Force (UNEF)and threatening a blockade of Israel&apos;s sea. route to the South through theStraits of Tiran.     The Middle East is a region in which apart from our general interest in world peace we have great material, strategic andpolitical interests,2,      If an Arab/Israel war broke out, and if it remained, isolated,our best intelligence assessments are that the Israelis could probablywin, but only after a hard battle and much destruction.    Even thatjudgment is heavily hedged around,,3,      If the Israelis stood in danger of losing the Americans have declared that &quot;they could not stand by and see Israel driven into thesea&quot;.    Squally, if the Israelis were winning, could the Soviet Unionstand aside and see the countries they support suffer defeat?4,      I conclude that v/hile it is possible that Israel might restore free passage through the Gulf by her own military action, the greater risk isof an Arab/Israel war escalating.    We ought therefore to contribute what we can within our resources to international action to prevent such a warhappening,, 45,      The Israelis will only be deterred from acting themselves to reopen the Straits of Tiran if they feel reasonably assured of aninternational settlement that keeps the Straits open for at least theiroil supplies.    And international action must from their point of viewseem likely to be both swift and effective.     Time is not on their side.Their Government is already under heavy criticism for not having reactedas soon as Egypt struck to remove the United Nations unit at the starits and before Egypt had had time to assemble her present massive forces.It was this sense of urgency that led the Cabinet to authorisecontingency naval planning on an ad referendum basis with the americans and preliminary diplomatic consultations with other maritime powers aboutasserting the international interest in keeping the Straits open.MENTIS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
7,     Since then France has proposed four-power discussions on the crisis.    We immediately welcomed this and I took it up directly withMr. Kosygin in Moscow.     The Prime Minister has been in personaltouch during the weekend with President de Gaulle, Mr, Kosygin and president Johnson about speeding up such discussions and Lord Caradonhas been pursuing the possibility of four-power discussions at the united nations.8.      It is now clear that the Soviet Union is not ready for any immediate four-power discussions, though I would not by any meansrule this out eventually.    We must actively keep the option open.    Butfor the reasons given above we cannot risk delaying the efforts to obtainthe widest possible support for the idea of international action to keepthe Straits open.    If we are to have the best chance of Security Councilauthority for such a course, there should be active discussions of it nowamongst friendly maritime powers.     The contingency naval preparationswith countries other than America ought also to proceed speedily if thepossibility of multilateral escort forces is to be a credible element ina settlement.    It may be that the international task force may neverneed to be activated.     But its practicability is an essential factor indeterring both immediate war and in producing a final peaceful settlementthat will not involve either Israel or Britain and other countries in a surrender of their essential interests.9,     What are mess British interests and how can they be safeguarded?They are described in paragraphs 8 to 16 of the accompanying paper (at appendix) by Foreign Office officials.     The point to which I wish to confine myself here is that there is now no course that avoids putting these interests at some risk.     They were endangered from the momentPresident Nasser ejected the United Nations from the Straits,     Thereal question is which course of events puts our interests least at riskfor the shortest period of time.     There are three main possibilities:-(a) War started by Israeli action against the blockade of the Straits.(b) A settlement recognising free passage of the Straits.(c) A settlement acquiescing in the closure of the Straits.10.     Course (a).    We would try to avoid being sucked into an Arab/Israel war except as part of United Nations peace-keeping.    But as theofficials1 paper makes clear, even if we succeeded in staying out, our interests would suffer from identification with Israel in Arab and soviet propaganda.      If the Americans became involved, we should have theagonising choice of measuring the further damage to our interests of supporting them, against the different but grave damage to our interestsQf parting company with the Americans on such an issue,U.      Courses (b) and (c).    The main difference between (b) and (c) isthat under (b) the risk to our interests of Arab retaliation is short-term and we can recover from it.    Under (c), on the other hand, the risk toour interests is delayed, but is likely to be much more permanent in theend.   if Egypt is allowed to settle on the basis of blocking the Straits andretaining her diplomatic/military victory, the longer-term consequences of this appeasement are likely to include the following:-
The Jordanian regime will be toppled,,The South Arabian settlement will be impossible except onMasser&apos;s terms.Other regimes where our interests are concentrated (e. g. inthe Persian Gulf) will be open to Nasserist/Soviet penetration.A war to destroy Israel will become inevitable.12.      There are great risks whatever we do (and in doing nothing) butI conclude that it will be wisest to persist with the course on which weare already set.     This means pursuing our efforts at the United nations for a suitable Security Council resolution and at the same time go ahead with the planning of practical multilateral means of keeping the straits of Tiran open.Go B.Foreign Offic e, S. W. 1.29th May, 1967
Appendix to,G(67)88MIDDLE EAST CRISISMemorandum by Foreign Office officials.    The Originj^jmd J^nature of the CrisisIt is the aim of this paper to deal with fundamental issues to recommend a policy for Her Majesty&apos;s Government,,      It doesnot attempt to give any detailed account of how the present crisisarose so suddenly and unexpectedly,, or speculate at any length onthe motiviations of the parties involved.      On the face of it,it has resulted from a series of opportunist moves by PresidentNasser:   a decision that he would have to intervene if Syrianterrorist attacks in Israel led to a large scale reprisal raid,as the Israelis were threatening;    a consequent ostentatious move-ment of large forces into Sinai to deter an expected Israel attackon Syria;   as part of this movement, a request to the united nations Emergency Force (UNEF)  to stand aside from the border;when the Commander of the Force objected, a demand for its      i,withdrawal;    and finally, when that demand was quickly accepted(perhaps to the surprise of the Egyptians) a decision to close theStraits of Tiran to Israel ships and &quot;strategic cargoes&quot; (mainlyoil) bound for Israel.2.   It has always been an ultimate objective of the U.A0R0 underPresident Nasser to eliminate Israel;    but in recent years certain conditions have effectively guarded against the risk of a major^AoR./Israel war.     They were:(a) the presence of the UNEF in Sinai and on the Straits ofTiran;(b) the Egyptian belief in Israel&apos;s military superiority;(c) the belief that the United States Sixth Fleet would ultimately prevent Israel being overwhelmed.0ve*&quot; the past week (a) has been eliminated and (b) and (c)haVe hecn put in doubt.     We still think it unlikely that the/UoAoRo
A,r, is so confident of success that it will attack Israel,$ the closure of the Straits of Tiran, which Israel has alwaysid would be a  a^u^jbellj.,  indicates a willingness to riskinflict which is in contrast with Egyptian attitudes over thej St ten years.i,   The effects of the two Egyptian coups - the expulsion ofIEP and reclosing of the Straits of T.ia?an - has been twofold:first, to bring the Middle East to the brink of war, and second,to alter drastically the balance of power in that area to theadvantage of the Soviet Union and her clients among the Arabtatas, at the expense of the United States,  ourselves, Israel,and friendly Arab states.This change has been achieved by methods which cut at the root of international behaviour.     We have not enough information from which to judge whether or not the U.A.R. was directlystimulated by the Soviet Union, but its course of action has beenfacilitated by Soviet  policies.      The Soviet Union has for longpursued, without haste, a policy of increasing its position, andthat of its ideology,  in the Middle.East,      It started byfavouring Israel against the Arabs, but in the mid-fifties changedsides, and has been able to outbid us for the favours of some Arabcoiintries by open partisanship for the Arabs against Israel,supplying large quantities of arms, and mendacious propaganda^pified by the &quot;Pravda&quot; statement of 2h May which gaveConditional support to the U.A.R. Government&apos;s actions.      But,  aelsewhere, the Soviet Union aims to avoid direct involvement inBar,There is a danger that the momentum of these successfulises in brinkmanship will cause the Egyptians to take/more
more risks.     There is disturbing evidence from all the arab countries of the way in which the events of the past week arebeing celebrated as Arab victories and as a prelude to a snccess-ful campaign against the existence of Israel,     Almost all Arabs,even those who are opposed to President Nasser and are threatened by the present turn of events,  share the sense of nationalhumiliation which the defeat of 19*4-8 brought with it;    and a dangerous head of steam is being built up which could get out ofthe control of governments and lead to an attack on Israel.6,    Our estimate, although the Israelis have expressed theirconviction to the contrary, is that there is no such present intention on the part of the U.i;.R,      It is probably more likely that, having achieved these two successes, the Egyptians, with russian support, will for the time   being adopt the role ofpeaceloving guardians of the new situation whilst perhaps offeringsome ifconcessions&quot; of no substance.     Any steps taken by cotmtrieswishing to amend, the situation will be represented as pro-israel and anti-Arab - a point of great importance to us with our stake in the Arab world (sec paragraphs 8 to 15) - and will be unpopular with the Afro-Asians in New York,  especially if they can point tosome alleged &quot;compromise&quot; package offered by the UoA.Ro      Theattitude of the Security Council when faced with a real and urgent threat to the peace has been one of the more depressingaspects of this whole business.7*    The most crucial immediate danger point is the closure of the Straits of Tiran to Israel shipping.     The Israelishave declared since 1957 that they would treat this as aS&amp;gusJjelJJL.     On the one hand,   they are anxious to avoid warbecause they know they would at   best suffer heavily;    they/have
nave postponed the need for a decision to resist, by delaying the arrival of ships at Elath;    and they sent their Foreign Ministerto Paris, London and Washington to look for some alternative.On the other hand, the Israel Foreign Minister has said thatcapitulation is impossible;    and for Lhe Israelis acquiesence inthe present situation would only be a postponement of an inevitableconflict to avoid ultimate strangulation.     After this experienceit is all the more likely that Israel will embark on the productionof nuclear weapons.II,   British InterestsA.    Political8,    We are deeply involved in the Middle East,  through CENTO,car commitments in the Persian Gulf and South Arabia and our traditional relationships with non-revolutionary as well asrevolutionary Arab States.      So long as this remains the case, wehave an overriding interest in orderly rather than violent change and in preventing the spread of communism or the establishmentof other forms of Soviet control over the area.     We thus stand to be major losers if President Nasser&apos;s present cheap victoriesare acquiesced in.     His enhanced prestige will enable him to intensify with greatly increases chances of success his campaign against wArab reactionaries and Western imperialists1&apos;, probably with,increased Soviet support.      Although all Arab nationalistswill applaud him, many of those who are disposed to co-operate with the West will be deeply worried and discouraged if nothing is done to stop him.     And our own policies of   orderly disengagedffient in South Arabia and of modernisation in the Gulf will be madeeven more difficult of fulfilment.     These political reverseswould have economic consequences (see paragraph 11 below).
cjo    We also have an interest in acting in the Middle Eastin concert with our friends and allies, European as well asAmerican.     The days are past when we could take effective action on our own.     Our national interest requires us to avoidinvolvement on our own in inter-Arab quarrels or in the Arab-Israel dispute but rather to give   our support to international action through the United Nations and, as necessary, outside itto uphold international order,10.   We must recognise that in a   crisis such as the present,even if we were to seek to stand aside entirely, we should be widely believed in the Arab world to be on Israel&apos;s side, abelief already being fostered by Soviet propaganda,     YiQ cannot therefore by inaction avoid damage to our interests and longterm risks to our whole position in the area.B.    Economic11.  We have extensive economic interests   in the Middle east which can be summarised as oil, trade,  sterling balances heldby Arab countries, and transit bu sea and air.     Whatever the outcome of the present situation they are likely to suffer.The consolidation of the U.A.R. victory could lead to the rapidundermining of the Arab States where our economic interests are concentrated and expanding.     Oil supplies would no   doubtcontinue but under more difficult terms and they would probablycome under the control of basically hostile and pro-Soviet regimes.In case of war, apart from the disruption   of trade and the....   ....possible general effect on sterling which would result from political uncertainty or war, we would, even though we stoodaside, be regarded as pro-Israel.     Action taken to supporttlle principle of freedom of passage will be interpreted asanti-AraD8     On the Arab/lsrael issue, through conviction/or
0r necessity, all Arab Governments stand together.     A clashWxth them on it incurs risks of the following consequences(a) the closure of the Suez Canal to our ships;(b) interference with oil supplies, either atsource by Arab states or in   transit;(c) some sort of an Arab boycott against us;(d) withdrawal of sterling balances e.g. by Kuwait.But if Israel takes military action, irrespective of what wedo or do not do, we may then in any case be exposed at least to some of the above consequences.      This is because,  evenif we take no positive action, we shall   be represented as pro-Israel or anti-Arab.12.   If we take positive action along with the Americans but without the french, the latter might try to represent in theCommon Market context that we are dependent on the United Statesand to that extent non-European.13.   Against this, it is an important general economic interestto defend the principle of free navigation.C.    Strategic111.   There is no direct British strategic interest in the Straitof Tiran in the sense that the carriage of cargoes through theStraits is essential to Britain.     But nevertheless we have ageneral interest in the principle of freedom of passage throughinternational waterways (for legal position see Annex &apos; C* ) .Moreover, as is argued below, the successful flouting of this principle in this instance might be expected to encourageinfringement of it and a generally more intransigent attitudeby the Egyptian G-overnment in other places and on   matters in thMiddle East where our interests would be directly involved.
15.  Any action which arouses Arab hostility incurs thefollowing risks.      (They could also arise eventually if theUoAoRo continued its present course unchecked.)(a) the closure to us of the Suez Canal with the consequence that our access by sea to the Indian Oceanwould have to be by way of the Cape.     This would givenew significance to Simonstown and generally increase our dependence on South Africa on a continuing/ basis;(b) the loss of overflying and landing rights in allArab countries.      If these rights were lost in thePersian Gulf States, the consequences would be thatwe should be unable to use the CENTO route to theMiddle and Par East unless Turkey and India (almostinconceivably) gave us staging rights.     In thesecircumstances the only alternative open to us wouldbe the more expensive and much longer Westabout route,which would be, at   best, only a partial palliative.In any event we have not yet made ail the preparationnecessary for its regular use;(c) there could be unwelcome repercussions which made our task in South Arabia harder;mwe should seriously jeopardise our position in Libya.16.   In addition, the following risks might   be incurred in non-Arab countries:(a)    the Cyprus Government might exert pressure againstthe Sovereign Base Areas with the consequence that our future use of them and possibly,  therefore, our ability to make a military contribution to CENTO would be impaired;/(b)
(b) we might want to withdraw naval forces from the Par1East to assist at the Straits of Tiran (or -\edsewherein. the.,.Mi^dl&apos;e-- Easten ATX-theucdntf Mat-feo^) esbalated-)1but by doing so might encourage the Chinese to seize the opportunity to intensify pressure   on Hong Kong;(c) we might, in the early stages, at least, need towithdraw temporarily our blockading force in Beirato assist at the Straits of Tiran with the consequenceof opening a potentially large breach in our   policyof sanctions against Rhodesia, and we should be doing this in a manner likely to draw censure from the .Afro-Asian countries.17.   In concluding this section however   it should be said thatofthere can be no certainty of avoiding some or all/^he disadvantagesdescribed above if we remained entirely passive.     For instance,if there were an Israeli-Egyptian conflict,  even though we keptout, we would in any case be regarded by the ^arabs as pro-Israel,with the attendant risk of sabotage of   pipelines, oil installa-tions etc,, as certain of the Arab States have already threatened.Moreover, whether encouraged by success without war, or under the pressure of war, the Egyptian Government might well take actionwhich would directly involve us, for example by trying toblockade Israel in the Mediterranean, by threatening to close the Canal or even by actually closing it by one means or another.111&apos; Possible Course of Eevents(-)   Resistance by Israel leading to an Arab/Israel War18.   The Israelis have apparently abandoned for the moment a plan for an air strike against the Egyptian guns and ships at thetraits of Tiran.      It is just conceivable that such a/strike
strike might be effective.      Our assessment is, however,that Egyptian prestige is too far engaged and that, evenif the action began in this limited way, it would lead toa full-scale air battle over Israel and the U.A.R., and land battles in Sinai and to a lesser extent on otherfronts.19,   It is still the British and American intelligenceestimate that Israel could probably d efeat, though atthe cost of heavy damage,  the U.A.R. and other Arabforces likely to b e involved in fighting against her.However, the odds have shortened, and are continuing to shorten, since the Arab build up on the Israel frontiersbegan.20.  There is a school of opinion in Washington that thebest way of meeting the present situation might be forthe Israelis to put Ilasser to the test on the closure ofthe Straits of Tiran and exercise the right of self-defenceif there was interference with shipping.    The Israeliscould then deal with the Egyptians without westernintervention except in support of international actionto bring hostilities to an end.    The objection to thisthesis is that, unless the Israel victory was extremelyrapid, there would be a very real risk of the,J&apos;-S.S.R, giving military support, probably in the air, to toe Arabs.   At this point,  the danger of a Soviet/Americanconfrontation would be imminent.    The decision in Washingtonappears to have gone against this course.
21.   If the battle went against Israel, the U.S. Governmentwould be &quot;under the strongest pressure to intervene militarilyto prevent Israel being overwhelmed.    Here again the riskof direct U080S.R./U0 S.  confrontation would be imminent.(B)   Acceptance of the new situation by Israel22.   As time passes there is a growing chance that underAmerican pressure and exhortations and promises of a&apos;political solution, the Israel Government, having failed toact initially, will continue to hold off.23.   If this situation continued indefinitely and notolerable compromise was achieved internationally, thiswould amount to capitulation.    The consequences for israel and the West would then be very serious.    The shift in thebalance of power in favour of the Soviet Union would havebeen confirmed.   The credibility of the UoS.  cover to Israel would have been destroyed,  the invincibility of theU./1.R. acting under cover of Russian support would havebeen established.    The lessons of the past indicate thatit would only be a matter of time before there were further attacks on Israel,    On the non-revolutionary Arab states,and on western interests in the area.(c) A compromise solution brought about by international action2k . Various possibilities are discussed below.Possible Courses of Action by Her Mai esty&apos;s Government hgjjgssons of History.  1.938 and 195625.   It is inevitable that the character of the events whichhave produced this critical situation should have suggestedcomparisons with 1938 and 1956;    and it would be as well to/have
have in. mind the lessons to be drawn from those years.The lesson of 1938 is that, if a Power pursues aggressiveand. predatory policies amid widespread criticism and getsaway with it, that Power will tend to go further and thatits ambitions may well grow pari passu with its successes.There may well be no end to the process.    The lesson of1956 is that there is no sense In going to war on something which is not a legitimate caaus belli    (nationalisation ofthe Suez Canal in the terms of 1956 conditions) and inemploying methods of doing so vmih go against establisheddemocratic and international practices - unless the nationso proceeding has overwhelming power or overwhelming backing.1938 suffered from wholly faulty diagnosis of the purposesof those involved;    it now appears that there was lessfaulty diagnosis in 1956, in the sense of an appreciation of Middle Eastern people and their purposes, but a totallyfalse estimate of what, in a given situation, we should or could do.   We need not make these mistakes &apos;this time.26.   Perhaps a nearer parallel than either 1938 of 1956 isthe Cuba  crisis of 1962,  the difference In this case being that there is a double confrontation - between the U.S.and the U.S.S.R., and between Israel and the Arabs, and neither the U.S, nor the U0S.S0R.  can wholly&quot; c control theirProteges.A 7..
AAIHETdeclaration of intent)  as inapplicable to present conditions,and the Macmillan statement of Ik May 19&amp;3 does not promise,much less commit us to, action outside the United Nations.For us to intervene in an Arab/Israel war on the Israel sidecould cause us to los e the whole of our economic and strategic interests in the Arab countries.    Indeed, however hard weendeavour eel to maintain an impartial position our national interests would &quot;be threatened,    since the Russians would inevitably give full political and propaganda support tothe Arabs, and w e and the Americans would be Identified withIsrael.28.   If the Israelis had the upper hind, we would,  especially inview of the danger of Russian involvement, need to use suchinfluence as we had to restrain Israel from going too far beyondrestoring the status quo ante 16 May.29.   If the Israelis were losing the battle, and the U.S.Government had to intervene militarily to -prevent Israelbeiag overwhelmed, we would bo under strong pressure from theU.So Government to join with them.    We w ould be faced withthe difficult problem of balancing the damage to our middle east interests if we did,   against the damage to Qur relations^ULL-Acceptance nf triic new Situatipnjpy^j^rael,,,&apos;   We would in this case liave to face the serious consequencesr oup own position in the Middle East of this major change inith the U.S. if we did not.e talanee of power (se^,pagraph 22 ab ove) and for the/world
world of this successful f lout ing of the internationalordor.flnnrke G:   A Compromise Solution brought&apos; about by International31,   There are four possibilities at present under das cussion,which *bou.ld be pursued separately or in combination.    Theywould remain possible even if,  in spite of our attempts toprevent it, war breaks out.(i) East/west Co-operation32.   The French are right in saying that the problem couldbe settled by Quadripartite co-operation.    Although there are good European reasons for welcoming this French initiative,the Foreign Secretary&apos;s talks in Moscow have shown that thereis no chance of getting any help from the Russians so longas they believe that there is a chance of the U.A.R. gettingaway with its two victories.    At best, there is no possibilityof any early result from this.( ^) i^tion^at the. Unit edt-i Nat ions33.   Unless the Israel Government takes military actionagainst the U...        in the near future, U.N. pressure is likelyto mount for a compromise solution to preserve peace now atthe expense of Israel.    The Secretary-General has already pointed towards this in his report, which contains references to:(a)   an assurance given him by President Nasser that theU.A.R. will not Initiate offensive action againstIsrael, and the Egyptians&apos;  aim to return topre-1956 conditions and full observance of theiagypt/lsrael armistice agreement;
(b)    the possibility of the revival of the Egypt/Israel Mixed Armistice Commission providing fora limited form of United Nations presence inthe area.;(a)    the need for control of activities in the Israel/Syria demilitarised zone;(d) the existence on the one hand of legal doubts about the right of innocent passage through theStraits of Tiran and the Gulf of Aqaba, and on theother the dangerous consequences that could ensuefrom restricting passage;(e) the need for a breathing spell in which to seeksolutions for these pioblems.3k.   Cotaitries which wish to avoid taking up a political position will join with the pro-Arab group in drawing attentionto doubts whether the Straits of Tiran are an internationalwaterway.   As the Annex B shows, the natter is farthercomplicated by the question of belligerent rights.    these doubts will combine with the fear of war to incline member states towords an inequitable compromise.35.   For the Israelis the essential feature of any settle-ment will be the degree of freedom for  shipping to transit theStraits,   President Nasser has declared in the mostuncompromising terms his intention of blocking the passageof all Israeli ships,  and ships of other nationalities bearingstrategic goods (which we understand to include oil)  to Elath./They
rphey also assert the right to stop and inspect ships inorder to enforce their restrictions.    If Israel w ereprepared to accept a compromise at a 11, the minimum terrasit would be reasonable tc press her to accept are probably the present positL on with an understanding that oil would notbe regarded as a strategic material, and perhaps with somerestricted access for Israeli shipping.    But as part of sucha compromise Israel and other powers would probably have to acquiesce in the position that the U.A.R. has a right toexercise some degree of control over the Straits of Tiran(iii) Unilateral action by Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentto open the.. Straits of Tiran36.   Her Majesty&apos;s Government might inforn the U.A.R. Governmentof their intention to maintain, with naval escorting vessels  ifnecessary, the right of passage through the Straits of Tiranby British ships.   We could then call on others to followour lead.   Her Majesty&apos;s Government have a duty to protect british shipping and this action would be applauded by theBritish public,    it the same time it v/ould help to get theStraits open to all shipping.37,   The objections to this course are these:-(a)   President Nasser would probably accept the challengeand stop the passage of our ships unless we had a credibledeterrent available.    The escorting vessels, which would take time to assemble, would not themselves be able to force a passage if resisted, and w e should also have to assembleforces likely to deter the U.A.R. and accept that a consequencecould be full scale war with the U../;.R.    It is very doubtfulwhether unilateral British action would deter.
(b) By taking the lead in this way, even in a Britishas distinct from an Israeli interest, we woulddangerously expose our interests in the Arab world,and drew on ourselves reprisals o(c) We cannot count on others following our lead;and opinion in many countries would be prejudicedagainst the idea of action of this kind by us onaccount of Suez.(iv) Inter ratio nal,action to open the Straits of Tiran38.   It is possible that the Israel Government could be more easily restrained from acting to open the Straits of Tiran ifthey were persuaded that countries supporting the principle of freedom of navigation would take effective action to open theStraits.     The Israel Foreign Minister told the Prime minister on-&apos;.2h\ May that this was the course his Government would prefer.It would have the advantage of being action to defend a principle of international law of great importance to allmaritime nations rather than action specifically to assistIsrael;   and a number of countries (including the United Kingdom)ffotoitted themselves in 1957 to support the principle of freedom of transit for all through the Straits of Tiran.39*   The Minister of State, Mr. George Thomson, has discussedsuch a scheme with the Americans and reached agreement ad^S SE  lSS ; on both sides.      Its essential elements are:(a)   Continued action in the United Nations to get aswide support as possible for the principle offeedom of passage through the Straits of Tiran;so that even if there was a Soviet veto inter-national support for some action could be shown./(b)
(b) A joint .declaration by interested Governments t*assert the freedom of passage through the Straits.(c) The assembly of naval forces north of the suez canal in the Eastern Mediterranean as adeterment to Egyptian interference;    and theprovision of escorts for shipping passing through the Straits.      Further discussion would be required as to the possible role of a deterrent force in the Red Sea.40.   This plan could be presented as having widesupport at the United Nations;    and as genuinely international action in defence of an international principlerather than as action to assist Israel.     But It wouldbe misleading to suggest that these optimumconditions could ever be achieved.     A declarationwithout teeth would not serve the purpose.Anything involving naval action outside the united nations is likely to be seen as thinly disguised Anglo-American action in support of Israel.     We can expect for it limited practical co-operation, fromone or two friendly European countries, support in principle from a few others,  and reactions ranging from disapproval to hostility in the rest of the world./hi.
jil.   This is a grim picture;    but as explained elsewhere inthe caper we shall incur odium on other counts even if weremain passive moreover against the difficulties described inthe previous paragraph must be set the following considerations:(a) Soviet and U.A.R. tactics in this are based on theassumption that we and the Americans will not takeforceful action and will restrain the Israelis.(b) The revivified prestige of the TJ.A.R. could disappearalmost as quickly as it appeared that the run ofunexpected successes had been reversed.     A show ofdetermination could, therefore,  change the situationvery quickly, and former friendships might be resumed.1+2,   Such a course could not be recommended if the other possibilities were not so much more grim;    viz. a full-scaleArab/lsrael war within a matter of days or hours, or a majorsetback of western interests in an area of great importance,combined with a damaging blow to the international order.ik3.   The practical aspects and the time scale of this courseof action are set out in Annex A.     The legal aspects are discussed in Annex B.kk*   Conclusion(i) The effect of Nasser&apos;s action has been to alterdrastically the balance of power in the Middle East tothe advantage of the Soviet Union and her clients amongthe Arab States.(ii) We should naturally look to the United Nations to redress the balance.     But on present showing it is most unlikely to do so.(iii) Action by us either alone or with our friends/would
voixjA be interpreted as action cn behalf of Israel.     this;0Uld entail grave risks for our important interests inthe Arab world and in particular for our Middle East oil.(iv) On the other hand, failure to act could be even more damaging.      It might lead to an Arab/Israel war with itsrisk of a direct confrontation between the United Statesand the U.8.&apos;SoRo      Or, if Israel were obliged to acceptthe blockade of Aqaba, it would result in a Middle Easteffectively dominated by President Nasser under Sovietprotection.     All our interests there, including our oil,would then be at Soviet mercy,(v) Whatever decision we take,  therefore, even if it isto do nothing, may result in serious damage to our interests.     We have to choose the course which offers theprospect of least damage.(vi) Opinion, especially in the United Nations, seems to teemoving in the direction of a compromise which would accept the withdrawal of UNEP and Egyptian control ofthe Straits of Tiran and include only nominal concessions to Israel.     This would be tantamount to an Israelisurrender and would have the same damaging consequences(see (iv) above).(vii) Some sort of equitable compromise is necessary ifwe are to avoid the dangers of war or capitulation.     Wehave to decide what terms would be accptable and what action we can take to  achieve them.(vlli) An equitable compromise would have to provide atthe very least for the passage of oil tankers through theStraits of Tiran to Elath.      In return the Israelis might/be
be persuaded to acquiesce in the exercise by the egyptians of some degree of&apos;control of the Straits.(ix) The present trend in the United Nations showslittle chance of achieving such a compromise unless we and our friends demonstrate our determination t o take any action,  including the use of naval force, which may benecessary to assert the right of free passage throughthe Straits of Tiran.(x) We should therefore. press on with the proposals,worked out with the -Americans, for a public declaration by the maritime powers and the provision of naval backingon an international basis.1*5*   Rec ommend at i ons(a) We should show our readiness to play a significantpart in action with a substantially international character, inside or outside the United Nations,to keep the Straits of Tiran open to internationalshipping including of course British shipping.(b) We should work diplomatically and.,at the united nations for an equitable compromise.FOREIGN OFFICE,  S.W.T.29 May, 1967
1, On Tuesday, 14th May, 1963, the then Prime Minister,Ivir, Harold Macrnillan, gave the following written answer to aQuestion by Mr, Gilbert Longden (Vol. 667, Col, 142 W):Israel and Arab States (President Kennedy&apos;s Statement)Q, 7.     Mr. Longden asked the Prime I/linister whether he will publiclyassociate Her Majesty^s Government with the recent officially declaredUnited States policy to the effect that, should Israel or any of the arab states appear to violate frontiers or armistice lines, the United Statesof America would take immediate action both within and outside theUnited Nations to prevent such violation.The Prime Minister;  Yes.    I am glad to endorse the Presidentsstatement.    Her Majesty ls Government are deeply interested in peace and stability in this area and are opposed to the use of force or the threat of force there as elsewhere in the world.    17c are equally opposed to theinterference by any country in the internal affairs of another, whetherby the encouragement of subversion or by hostile propaganda,    i cannot say in advance what action we would take in a crisis, since it is difficult to foresee the exact circumstance which might arise.We regard the United Nations as being primarily responsible for themaintenance of peace in the area.      If any threat to peace arises, we will consult immediately with the United Nations and will take whatever action wc feel may be required.20      In the course of the Foreign Affairs Debate on I6th December,1964, Mr. Butler asked the Prime Minister (Vol0 704, Col. 413):I should like to ask him, in relation particularly to Israel, whetherbe endorses the statement made by the former Prime Minister,Mr, Harold Macrmllan, on 14th May, 1963, in which he said, supportingPresident Kennedy&apos;s pledge on the Middle East:&quot;We regard the United Nations as being primarily responsiblefor the maintenance of peace in the area..    If any threat to peace arises we will consult immediately with the united nations and will take whatever action we feel may be required&quot;.(Official Report, 14th May, 1963:  Vol. 667, c. 142)If the Government would endorse that statement, then I think that itwould give great satisfaction to Israel and would be a stabilising factor in Middle Sast politics.ANNEX a tripartite DeclarationParliamentary Statements by Mr.  Macmillan in 1963 and the Primei inister in December, 1964, and April, 1965
The Prime Minister replied (Vol. 704, Col, 416):I hope that I can deal with his questions about the Middle Eastquite simply.    We certainly endorse what the right hon. Gentlemanthe then Prime Minister said, some two or three years ago, in thequotation made by the right hon. Gentleman,3a      On Tuesday, 13th April, 1965, Viscount Lambton asked the PrimeMinister:&quot;if Her Majesty&apos;s Government are still committed to the tripartite agreement&quot;.The Prime Minister &apos;s answer and the subsequent exchanges went asfollows (Vol. 710, Cols. 1153-5):Tripartite DeclarationQ, 1,     Viscount Lambton asked the Prime Minister if Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment are still committed to the tripartite agreement.The Prime Minister (Mr. Harold Wilson):   The tripartite declaration of 1950 was intended to express the policy of Britain,France and the United States at mat time.    It has not been retracted,I expressed the Governments deep concern for the peace and stability of the Middle East when, in the course of the Foreign Affairs debate onloth December . 1964, I endorsed Mr. Macr.aiilan&apos;s statement of 14th May,1963,Viscount Lamb ton&apos;  I thank the right hon. Gentleman for his replyand at the same time congratulate him on the fact that his illness was not of the type to necessitate his having a rest.    Does his reply mean thatEngland and France still stand by all the intentions of the tripartite agreement ?The Prime Minister;  However hard the hon. Member tries he willnot manage to attack those who sit on this Front Bench with the vehemencehe used in attacking those who preceded us.     The noble Lord will realise that at the time of the 1950 Declaration there was a very different situation,in that the three Powers virtually controlled such arms movements as there were.     There is now a big difference in the situation, but we feelthat the statement made in 1963 is the right one for us to follow, and Igive the assurance for which the noble Lord asked.Mr. Shin well;  Is my right hon. Friend aware that there aredifferences of interpretation in respect of the tripartite agreement?In the book which I understand my right hon. Friend is now reading on the Suez crisis - or what was alleged to be a crisis - he will find that President Eisenhower and the late Mr, Dulles gave a quite differentinterpretation from that given by Mr, Harold Macmillan or the UnitedKingdom Government,    Will he take an early opportunity of defining the meaning of the agreement?
The Prime Minister:  I went to some lengths on this matter in the debate a fortnight ago on the Middle Eastern question,.     Certainly in all our contacts with Middle Eastern countries we have been emphasising -particularly in what is the most vital issue at the moment;  the questionof the water scheme - the need for maximum restraint by all the countries concerned.Mr. Grimond:  Is the Prime Minister aware that it is just becausethe situation is so different now from what it was when the agreement was brought up that v/e feel that it should be renegotiated?    Am I right in thinking that the agreement is an agreement to maintain the frontiers of Israel, and that if it were invoked we might be forced to go to the aid of one side or the other to put back a frontier, quite irrespective of therights and wrongs of the initial controversy which had led to the violation of that frontier ?The Prime Ministers   The original Declaration, as the right hon.Gentleman knows, was signed at a time when the signatories could regard themselves as virtually the arbiters of Middle East policy.     This is nolonger the position today, partly because of the intervention of the soviet union and other countries, partly because of certain aspects of Israeliand Arab nationalism going far beyond national frontiers in the area.We regard our interest in it now as going far beyond the maintenanceof particular frontiers, as the right hon. Gentleman has suggested, and certainly if the circumstances became appropriate, I am sure that thereis nothing that the House would like better than to get some kind ofagreement on arms supplies, arms control and the banning of nuclear weapons in that area.
ANNEXBINTERNATIONAL ACTION TO OPEN THE STRAITS OF TIRANPRACTICAL ASPECTS AND TIMESCALEFor the purposes of the calculations which follow., it has been assumed that the objective is to build up a force which could (with adequate support from units in the Eastern Mediterranean) escortmerchant ships through the Straits of Tiran.    It is assumed, throughout,that no British or United States units will be able to pass through the suez canal from North to South during the period in question.2,      Assuming that the Escort Force required would consist of threeEscorts, four mine counter-measure vessels (MCMs) and one supportingtanker, now long would it take to assemble this Force in the Red Sea atthe mouth of the Gulf of Aqaba ?At the very earliest an Escort Force, which might initially haveto be mainly Anglo-American, could reach the area, of the Straits ofTiran by 7th June.     This does not take account of the period requiredfor the assembly of a deterrent task force in the approaches to the red sea, if one were decided upon, but it is estimated that this could reach the area by approximately the same date.     The limiting factor is the speed of the coastal minesweepers, which will arrive at Aden on 2nd June.HMS Hermes, accompanied by a frigate, will reach Aden on 31st May.In the event, the time factor v/ould be dictated by the number of nationsparticipating.3,      How long could tills Escort Force remain on station, even if thereweie no losses requiring replacement?If need be, the British element of the force could remain on stationfor two or three weeks, at the cost of some stress to the crews of theminesweepers, which are very small.     This is the best guess that canbe made in the absence of a detailed plan and the actual time would depend upon the intensity of activity and the availability of support facilities.     Toretain the force for a longer period would raise problems of roulementand entail bringing large forces to the area and require the prevision of increased support facilities for the minesweepers.    We are informedthat the actual task of sweeping any mir.es which may already have been laid in the Straits of Tiran would only take a few hours if they v/ere ofan unsophisticated type.     Other types would take longer.    It is notabsolutely certain that any have been laid.4,      What other naval forces of allied maritime nations are alreadywithin reasonable range?The USS Fiske (Destroyer) is at Massav/a and the USS JosephP, Kennedy (Destroyer) is due at Aden in two days1 time,    A UnitedStates converted seaplane tender, the Valcour, is at Jedda.    Laaddition, there are one French coastal minesweeper and a very small-French patrol vessel at Djibouti.    No other allied vessels are knownto be in the area, south of the Canal.    A number of NATO navies have considerable naval forces in the Mediterranean.
5o      If there were a call for inclusion in the force of a DIjG (guidedmissile destroyer), how long would it take to get this DLG into position?We are told that the DLG could arrive off Aden within six days ifthe order were given today.6,      One of the additional measures which might be taken against theUnited Arab Republic might be the employment of electronic counter -measures.    &quot;would these require additional vessels or aircraft in theimmediate area of the Gulf of Aqaba?No.    It is understood that these measures would be undertaken by the unites taking part in active operations and would not call for any additional forces in the  traits of Tiran area.     The most likely area ofsuch operations would be in the Eastern iViediterranean, where they wouldbe undertaken by forces already there074      To what extent, and how soon, can the United Kingdom SovereignBase Areas (SBAs) in Cyprus become self-defending ?We are told that the SBAs could be made self-defending against possible air and ground attack within the timescale of the preparationsof escort, operations in die Gulf of Aqaba.(a.)    Air defence squadron of lightning fighters is already in Cyprus,    Anothersquadron could be flown to Cyprus well within the period of preparation(i, e, before 7th June).    A section of Bloodhound air defence missiles isat present in Libya and could, together with Bloodhounds from theUnited Kingdom, be deployed at the SBAs in Cyprus within the sameperiod.(b)    Land defence the additional ground forces necessary for the defence of theSBAs could be flown from the United Kingdom within the preparatoryperiod.8.      Additional Naval Units in the AreaApart from Portuguese naval units in the Mozambique area, thereare, as far as can be reliably ascertained without making enquiries inthe capitals concerned, no other NATO warships anywhere within reasonable range south of the Canal.    But we believe that Ethiopia has at iVlassawa, in addition to the 1,800-ton training ship &quot;Ethiopia&quot;, fivesmall coastal patrol craft and that Iran has in the Khorramshahr areaone or possibly two frigates, four coastal minesweepers and one landingship converted for use as a coastal patrol craft.    Clearly none of thesehas any direct military relevance,9.      Pr eparationsThe fact that preparations were being made would become public knowledge.
ANNEXCNOTE ON LEGAL ASPECTSA,       The right of innocent passageIt is well-established in international lav/ that in time of peace:(i)   The ships of all States are entitled to a right of innocent passage through the territorial sea of another State,(ii)  Passage is innocent so long as it is not prejudicial to the peace,good order or security of the coastal State.(iii) The coastal State must not hamper innocent passage through theterritorial sea.(iv) The coastal State may take the necessary steps in its territorial sea. to pr-event passage which is not innocent,(v) Subject to (vi), the coastal State may without discriminationamongst foreign ships, suspend the right of innocent passagetemporarily in specified areas of its territorial sea if suchsuspension is essential for the protection of its security.(vi)   There shall be no suspension of the innocent passage of foreign ships through straits which are used for international navigationbetween one part of the high seas and another part of the high seas or the territorial sea of a foreign State,(See Articles 14 to 16 of the Geneva Convention of 1958 on the territorial sea).2.       There would appear to be no doubt that ships to and from Eilat(and other ports in the Gulf of Aqaba) are entitled in time of peace to aright of innocent passage through the Straits of Tiran under these rules,and in particular that rule (vi) applies in respect of them.     This is soirrespective of whether there is any area of high, seas in the Gulf ofAqaba or whether it comprises only territorial waters of the coastalStates,3.       In order to gain access to Eilat it is, of course, necessary topass through Egyptian or Saudi territorial waters both in the straits of Tiran and in the Gulf of Aqaba itself.     There may be some doubt as to whether rule (vi) applies in respect of, for instance, Egyptianor Saudi territorial waters at the northern end of the Gulf, but it isbelieved that an international tribunal would, in the light of the relevant provisions of the Geneva Convention, be likely to treatrule (vi) as applying throughout the length of the Gulf.4,       There is, however, the question whether the UAH, havingregard to the present state of tension between her and Israel, is entitled under the above rules to prevent the passage of ships carryingcargoes of strategic value to Israel on the grounds that such passagecannot be regarded as innocent.     There is clearly room for argumenton this point, but the better view probably is that the innocency of a
passage must be judged by whether the vessel, while in the course of passage, constitutes a threat to the security of the coastal State and does not depend on the use to which its cargo may ultimately be put.It may, therefore, be argued that the free passage of a vessel carryingstrategic materials or oil to Israel does not itself constitute a threat tothe security of the UAR, chat Israel is perfectly entitled to acquire the equipment necessary for her self-defence and oil for her peaceful needs,,and therefore the passage of such vessels may not be interfered with inthe absence of a situation entitling the UAR to exercise belligerent rights.Nevertheless, having regard to the present relations between Israel andthe UAR., the contrary view might prevail in an international tribunalsuch as the International Court of Justice.B.       Is the UAR entitled to exercise belligerent rights against Israel?5,      The UAR is not entitled to exercise belligerent rights unless sheis at war with Israel,,    Merely to claim to exercise belligerent rights isnot, in itself, sufficient to create a state of war,     Thei-efore, in theabsence of a declaration of war by either Israel or the UAR, it isnecessary to consider the relations actually existing between the twoStates.6,      The relationship is a complicated one.    It stems from the hostilities that broke cut in 1943 and the Armistice Agreement of1949 between Egypt and Israel,     From the legal point of view, itis complicated by the fact that Egypt does not recognise Israel asa State and that Israel no longer regards the Armistice agreement as in force.7,      Nevertheless, before 1956, the view of Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentwas that with the lapse of time it became increasingly difficult to maintain that there was a state of war between Egypt and Israel,    Although some doubt arose as a result of the Suez crisis, the view that any state of war has been eradicated by the passage of time now seems to be the betterone.8,      Even as long ago as September, 1951, the Security Council(Res, 95) considered &quot;that since the armistice regime, which has beenin existence for nearly two and a half years, is of a permanent character,neither party can reasonably assert that it is actively a belligerent orrequires to exercise the right of visit, search and seizure for anylegitimate purpose of self-defence&quot;,9, On the other hand, the UAR has long maintained that, in spiteof the Armistice Agreement, it is in a state of war with Israel, whileconfirming their adherence to the Armistice Agreement.10,      In these circumstances, while the legal position must remain open to argument, it would be a perfectly respectable view to say that egypt is not entitled to exercise belligerent rights against Israeli ships.
Co       Assertion of the right of innocent passage11(       On tlie assumption that the UAR is not entitled to interferencewith the right of innocent passage through the Straits of Tiran, what action by Her Majesty&apos;s Government and other Governments, otherwise than under the authority of the United Nations, is permissible to assert theright ?12.      In the Corfu Channel Case the International Court held in effectthat if a State has a right which it is entitled to exercise and another state wrongly or forcibly persists in interfering with its exercise, thefirst State is not bound to submit to the lawless use of force by the secondbut may lawfully assert its right by the threat or use of force.     Thus, in circumstances in which Albania was denying the right of passage throughthe Corfu Channel by the use of shore batteries, the Court upheld theright of the United Kingdom to send warships through the straits withthe crews at action-stations prepared to use force in self-defence duringthe passage if attacked from the shore.    On the other hand, the Courtdeclared that subsequent action taken by the Royal Navy to remove minesfrom the Channel was a violation of Albanian Sovereignty.13.      It appears to follow from this judgment that it would be legitimatefor the Royal Navy to escort British flag vessels through the Straits ofTiran and to resist by force any forcible attempt by the UAR to preventpassage,,    -But the threat or use of force against the UAR except for thepurpose of actually exercising the right of innocent passage, would beillegal.


</content>
</cab>
