<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/130/0 images: 357-400</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL &quot;       g 4 3OCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYlS GOVERNMENT)C167194 COPY NO.  fi/f6th june. 1967CABINETARRANGEMENTS FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY IN THEEUROPEAN COMMUNITIES; DRAFT WHITE paper note by&apos; the Chairman of the Official Committee onEarly in May the Cabinet decided (CC(67) 27th Conclusions,Conclusion (3)) that, in addition to the Prime Ministers statement tothe House of Commons (Cmnd. 3269), a further publication, or seriesof publications, should be laid before Parliament about the impact of joining the European Communities.    Since then White Papers on theCommon Agricultural Policy (Cmnd. 3274) and on the Legal and constitutional Implications (Cmnd. 3301) have been published.     Adraft White Paper on Arrangements for Trade and Industry in theEuropean Communities is now submitted by  the Official Committee onthe Approach to Europe for consideration.2.      The publication of a White Paper on trade and industry wouldenable Ministers to say that, in addition to all the material which hasbeen published on British membership of the European Communitiesduring the past ten years, and to that given in the recent debates in Parliament including the Wnite Paper on the general political andeconomic issues, they had published informative White Papers on thelegal and constitutional, agricultural, commercial and industrialaspects of British membership of the European Communities;  and thatthe material they had published was much fuller than that provided atthe time of the previous negotiations with the Six in 1961-63.     the agreed basis on which the paper has been drafted is that it should be purely factual and should not discuss the implications of entry.     It ispossible that a White Paper on the lines of the draft may attract some criticism on two counts; first, while it is reasonably comprehensive,there are a few issues of interest to industrialists which are not covered in the White Paper, for example, direct investment in theCommunity.     Second, that because it does not discuss the implications of entry, it gives little indication to the businessman of the likelyeffects of membership on his own particular industry.     Officials considerthat there are satisfactory answers to any such criticisms.    As regardsthe first, the WTiite Paper is concerned with arrangements for trade andindustry, not with financial questions; and it would be difficult to give an adequate account of Community and United Kingdom policies on investment and capital movements without risk of prejudice to our negotiating position.     Second, since it is not possible to go very far in discussing the implications of entry without knowing or assuming the-1-
conditions of entry, any assessment of the impact of United kingdom membership on individual industries is most uncertain, and publicassessment of it (which over so wide a field would be of inordinatelength) is best left to the Confederation of British Industry and theother industrial organisations concerned.3.     The Official Committee on the Approach to Europe recommend,therefore, that a White Paper on Trade and Industry, on the lines of thedraft attached, should be published and that, when this has been done,it would be right to resist pressures for further White Papers on british membership of the Communities unless and until developments in the negotiations with the European Communities now in prospect sorequire.(Signed)    W. A. NIELDCabinet Office, S. W. 1.6th June, 1967.-2-
DRAFT WHITE PAPER ON ARRANGEMENTS FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRYIN THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIES/Note on inside cover/Further Information on the European CommunitiesUnofficial English translations of the two Treaties of Rome and ofthe Treaty of Paris, prepared by the Foreign Office, are available from her Majesty^ Stationery Office.    The current version of the Treaty of paris, establishing the European Coal and Steel Community, was published in 1965*   Revised translations of the two Treaties of Rome, establishing the European Economic Community and the European Atomic Energy Community,were published earlier this year.    These translations replace earlierversions of the three Treaties published by HMSO in 1962.   HMSO also hascatalogues of Community publications, many cf which are available.    Someof the more important are published in English but, in general, items not published in English are stocked by HMSO in the French language versions.The most important source of information on the Communities1activities is the Official Journal (Journal Officiel) of the european communities.   This is not published in English, but the French versionis available from HMSO.    It is here that the official texts of allregulations, decisions, agreements and other legislative instrumentsgoverning the operations and activities of the Communities are firstpublished authoritatively.   There are about 200 issues a year and theannual subscription is  5.Unofficial English translations of European Economic Community and european Atomic Energy Community regulations, prepared by the ForeignOffice from the official texts published in the Journal Officiel, are published by HMSO.   Full details of titles available can be obtained fr.,mHMSO in Sectional List No. 68.   Prices vary from 3d. to 6/- per copy.Unofficial translations of some regulations and of other officialannouncements from the Journal Officiel are also published from time totime in the Board of Trade Journal.A brief description of e.c. publications available is to be found in&quot;Commerce, Industry and HMSO&quot; (free from HMSO).Information about the activities of the European Communities is also available from the European Community Information Service at23 Chesham Street, London, S.W.1.
gM^lHITB^ PAPER ^TjVRiy^GEMENTS JOB. TRADJ^ AMD&apos; IN TOE&quot; BURO^&amp;NlJoMUJgpES &quot; &quot;   &quot;introduction.   The Concept of the Common Market2.   The Foreign Trade of the European EconomicCommunity3.   The Common External Tariff and the UnitedKingdom Tariff4.   The Pattern of Trade between the UnitedKingdom and the European Economic Community5.   Eree Movement of Labour6-   Right of Establishment and Freedom toSupply services. Company and Patent Law8. Transport Policy9. Rules Governing Competition10. Fiscal Provisions11. Approximation of Laws-12*. Social Policy13. Economic Planning%. The European Coal and Steel Community15. The European Atomic Energy Community1 - 67-1516-2223 - 2627 - 3132 - 3637 - 4142 - 4344-6364 - 6869 - 7273 - 7778 - 8788 - 9495 - 100TABLE OF CONTENTS
DRAFT WHITE PAPER-AlffiAIJG-EMTS FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY IN THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIESINTRODUCTION1. The purpose of this White Paper is to describe in outline arrangements in the three European Communities which directly affect trade and industry,comparing them where appropriate with arrangements In the same fields in theUnited Kingdom. This comparison is not intended to carry any implications for the position which the United Kingdom might take up in negotiations for membership.2.     The three European Communities are -(l)   the European Economic Community (e.c.), established by the Treatyof Rome, which came into force on 1st January 1958;(2)    the European Atomic Energy Community (EURATOM), established bythe second Treaty of Rome, which also came into force on1st January 1958;(5)   the European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC), established by theTreaty of Paris, which came into force on 25th July 1952,The present member states of each of the three Communities are Belgium,the Federal Republic of Germany, France, Italy, Luxembourg and theNetherlands,     Under a Treaty signed in April 19&amp;5 and likely soon toenter into force the Executives of the three Communities are to be amalgamated into a single new body to be known as the Commission of theEuropean Communities.3.     Chapters 1-13 of this White Paper are concerned with the european economic Community and the provisions of the Treaty of S.ome.Chapters 14 and 15 refer respectively to the European Coal and steel community and the European Atomic Energy Community.4.     The vfoite Paper on the Legal and Constitutional Implications ofUnited Kingdom Membership o^ the European Communities, Cmnd. 3301 ofMay 1967, contains a description of the structure and powers of thevarious institutions of the Communities which is part of the relevantbackground to the present paper.    The arrangements of the European economic community for agriculture have been described in Cmnd 3274 of May 19^7.
THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY1.   THE CONCEPT OF THE COMMON MARKET(Articles 1-37 and 226)Basic Principles (Articles 1-8)1.     The task of the Community, as described in Article 2 of the Treatyof Rome, is to promote throughout the Community a harmonious developmentof economic activities, a continuous and balanced expansion, an increasedstability, an accelerated raising of the standard of living and closer relations between the member states.   This task is to be achieved &quot;by establishing a Common Market and progressively approximating theeconomic policies of member states&quot;.    The Treaty provides for the steps needed to establish a Common Market in which there is free movement of goods, persons, services and capital.   It contains rulesto ensure fair competition;     makes provision for harmonisation oflaws in so far as this is needed for the orderly functioning of theCemmon Market;   and provides for the evolution of common policies for agriculture, transport, foreign trade, regional development and economicand social matters.   It may therefore be said to aim at the gradualachievement of economic union on the basis of the Common Market.2,     The Treaty requires that the Common Market shall be brought into existence over a transitional period of twelve years (1st January 1958to 31st December I969) which is divided into three stages eaoh of fouryears.     During the transitional period, the Customs Union and thevarious common policies are to be developed in parallel.   The community is now in the final stage of the transitional period.   The customs union will have been completed by 1st July I968;   the common agricultural policy will have established a single market for most importantagricultural products by the same date;   but some major questions, suchas fiscal, social and transport policies,  still await decisions.3.     In many if its previsions the Treaty gives enly an outline of the policies to be pursued, leaving detailed implementation to the Councilof Ministers and the Commission through regulations, directives,decisions and recommendations. keJSustomsJJnign^and^^eoJ^Gm^of^^   (Articles 9-37 and 226)4.     The Treaty requires that during the transitional period tariffs and import restrictions on trade between member states should be reducedprogressively, and that national external tariffs should be alignedin stages with a common external tariff (CET).     Revenue duties, whichare applied to raise revenue and not to protect domestic production-1-CONFSDENTIAL
and are therefore charged at the same rate on domestic products and imports, are permitted to continue.   The process of tariff reductionwill end with the completion of the Customs Union on 1st July 1968,There will then be no tariffs   or quota restrictions on trade between member states.     Imports from third countries which have no associationagreement with the Community will be subject to the common external tariff (which replaces national external tariffs) but will be entitledto free movement within the Community except in so far as restrictiveaction is authorised undor Article 115 (soo paragraph 9),5,     During the transitional period the Commission can authorisemember states to take protective measures in derogation of the Treatyrules where serious difficulties affect a particular sector of the economy (Article 226).6.     During and after the transitional period, under certaincircumstances, the Council or the Commission can authorise underArticle 25 of the Treaty of Rome tariff quotas for particular member states - i.e. the right to import specified quantities of a productat a rate lower than prescribed in the common external tariff.   Suchquotas are reviewed periodically.     In 1966, less than 3 per cent of Community imports entered under these arrangements.   The following are examples of tariff quotas which were first granted some years ago and which are still authorised -(i)   Germany and the Benelux countries have been grantedtariff quotas at 5 per cent for aluminium, on which thecommon external tariff is 9 per cent.(ii)   Germany, Belgium and the Netherlands have been allowed quotas for the duty-free import of raw lead, on which the common external tariff is 1.32 units of account (equivalent to united States dollars) per 100 kilograms.(iii)   Prance  and Germany have been granted quotas for theduty-free import of newsprint, on which the common external tariff is 7 per cent.All these quotas are for specific quantities and are subject to annual review.-2-
CONFIDENTIAL &quot;        o K (J2,   THE FOBEI&amp;N TRADE OF THE EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMvIUNITY&quot;(Articles 11 CM 16&quot;,&quot; 131-136 and 238)The Common Commercial Policy7,    The Treaty of Rone requires the establishment of a Connon ConnercialPolicy for trade with third countries and prescribes that after the expiry of the transitional period the Policy &quot;shall be based on unifornlyestablished principles, particularly in regard to tariff amendments, tothe conclusion of tariff and trade agreenents, to the establishing ofuniform practice as regards neasures of liberalisation, to export policyand to connercial protective measures&quot; (Article 113).     During the transitional period nenber states are &quot;to co-ordinate their connercialrelations with third countries&quot; (Article 111).8.    From the outset the Conmission has conducted tariff negotiations onbehalf of the Connunity, e.g, in the Dillon and Kennedy Rounds.     As aresult of the inplenentation of the Common Agricultural Policy manyaspects of trade in agricultural products are Connunity matters.Commercial relations with certain countries are governed by association and trade agreements negotiated by the Connission on behalf of theCommunity (see paragraphs 10 to 15 below).9.    So far, however, the Council of Ministers has made no decision on proposals by the Commission covering sone of the major aspects ofcommercial policy.     These include proposals for the gradual unification of measures aimed at liberalising trade;   for import quotas to cover theCommunity as a whole;   for connon protection against dunping;   for harnoni-sation of export aids in trade with third countries;   and for trade withstate trading countries.     Meanwhile., nenber states are not prohibited bythe Treaty fron inposing quantitative   restrictions on trade with non-nember countries, subject to their obligations as nenbers of the GeneralAgreement on Tariff s and Trade (GATT), and fron concluding bilateral agreements with then;   and in practice they maintain their own agreements with, for instance, the Soviet bloc countries and with Japan.     UnderArticle 115 member states nay be authorised to refuse entry to goods onwhich they retain restrictions when these are re-exported to then by other member states.^ rj.g-Qgnts with non-member states10.   Articles 131-136 of the Treaty of Rone made provision to associate amember of non-European countries and territories have special relations withBelgium, France, Italy and the Netherlands,     Under the Yaounde Conventionbetween the Community and 18 African states free trade is to be progressivelyestablished between the e.c. and each of the African states.     Aid is nadeavailable and there are rules for establishment, paynents and novenent ofcapital.    The Convention expires on 31st May 1969;   under one of itsarticles, the contracting parties will start to exanine one year before that date the arrangements which night be envisaged for a further period.
11.   Certain of the provisions of the Treaty of Rome applied to Algeria,including entry to the Community for Algerian goods on preferentialterms.   Certain countries   -   Morocco,   Tunisia, Libya,Surinam, the Netherlands Antilles and a few other territories - havebenefited from the so-called &quot;Morocco Protocol&quot;, which allowed France,Benelux and Italy to continue their previous customs treatment of importsfrom the country concerned.    Goods imported under this Protocol arenot, however, entitled to free circulation elsewhere in the Community.Under Declarations of Intention attached to the Treaty, most of these arrangements were to be superseded by association agreements whichwould govern the relationships between each of the countries and territories mentioned above and the Community as a whole.   TheDeclaration relating to Surinam and the Netherlands Antilles has alreadybeen implemented.   There have been discussions with Morocco, Tunisia andAlgeria about association agreements but these have not yet been concluded.12.     Under Article 238 of the Treaty which provides for associationagreements with third countries there are agreements between theCommunity and G-reece and Turkey which provide progressively for free trade.   Ultimately both countries can apply under the agreements for membership of the Community as European countries.   In I966 theCommunity concluded an association agreement with Nigeria (yet to be ratified) which provided for preferential entry to Community markets for all Nigerian products.   Four tropical products - peanut and palmoils, cocoa beans and plywood - are covered by duty-free quotas.   Inreturn Nigeria gives preferential tariff treatment to a limited range of imports from the Community.   This agreement, like the Yaounde&apos;&apos;Convention, is due to be renegotiated by 31st May 1969.13.     Under Article 238 the Community has concluded trade agreements with Israel and Iran under which the Community has made temporary tariff reductions on a non-discriminatory (i.e. most favoured nation) basis forthe benefit of these countries.   Under an agreement with the Lebanon,the Community and the Lebanon grant each other most favoured nation treatment and the Community undertakes to increase its technical assistance to the Lebanon.14.   A Protocol attached to the Treaty allows imports from the SovietZone of Germany to be admitted duty free into the Federal Republic ofGermany.   Re-exports of these goods to other member states are subject totheir national external tariffs.15.   Discussions on association agreements under Article 238 ef theTreaty are in progress between the Community and Austria, Spain, IsraelKenya, Tanzania and Uganda.
lo.   The eommon external tariff (CET) of the European Economio community is in general a single tier tariff Under which the same Customs dutiesare charged on imports of each Item from all souroesj   although duties on imports from countries which have association arrangements with theCommunity are being reduced and will eventually be eliminated.17,   The United Kingdom tariff is a three tier tariff.   Imports from most countries pay the full or &quot;most favoured nation&quot; rates of duty.Separate and reduced rates or no tariff at all are, however, applied to imports from the Commonwealth Preference Area, which includes SouthAfrica, the Republic of Ireland and Burma as well as commonwealth countries;   and to Industrial imports from the member countries of theEuropean Free Trade Association (EFTA).     These latter two groups ofimports, which together account for a little less than half our totalimports, enter the United Kingdom in most cases free of duty.   The mainexceptions to duty-free entry from the Commonwealth are motor oars, clocksand watches and goods containing silk and man-made fibres.   Revenueduties are charged on tobacco, wines and spirits, hydrocarbon oil, matchesand mechanical lighters;   but with only minor exceptions the rate ofrevenue duty on Commonwealth imports is the same as the excise duties oncomparable British goods.   Those commodities which benefit from commonwealth preference enjoy an average tariff advantage of about 12 per cent,   whenspread over all imports from the Commonwealth the average margin ofpreference Is about 7 per cent.   Many Commonwealth countries, as well asthe Irish Republic, South Africa and South West Africa, grant preferencesto the United Kingdom.     It has been estimated that slightly more than half of the United Kingdom&apos;s exports to the preference area enjoy somemargin of preference;    and that the average margin of preference on all british exports to the area is about 7 per cent.   Nearly all our industrialexports enter EFTA countries free of duties.18,   If the United Kingdom entered the Community, the CET and, in thecase of certain agricultural products, variable levies would be appliedto imports from all countries which were not members of the Community or which did not have association agreements with the Community, except where special arrangements had been negotiated.   EFTA and commonwealth countries and the Republic of Ireland would be among the countriesaffected If they did not join or make association agreements with theCommunity.19.   The general pattern of duties in the CET and in the United Kingdom,tariff is broadly similar.   Zero or low duties are charged on raw materials,and higher duties on semi-manufactures and manufactures.   The average ofthe CET is rather lower than that of the United Kingdom most favoured nation tariff, and it contains fewer very high rates of duty.   The present-5-CONFSDENTIAL
differences between the two tariffs will, however, be narrowedconsiderably as a consequence of the recently concluded Kennedy round of tariff negotiations.   Although the precise effect will vary fromproduct to product, the Kennedy Round will lead to an averagereduction in duties of 35 per cent to AO per cent in both the UnitedKingdom most favoured nation tariff and in the CET, to be implemented in stages over a period of about four years.   At the time at whichthis White Paper went to press the final details of the tariffchanges resulting from the Kennedy Round had still to be worked out.The rates quoted in paragraphs 21 and 22 are therefore those rulingat present:    schedules will be published in due course showing the revised rates agreed in the Kennedy Round negotiations.20.     The adoption of the CET in place of our own tariff would havedifferent implications for different industries in this country and for different overseas suppliers.   Most foodstuffs are covered by theprovisions of the common agricultural policy which have been described in the White Paper on Agriculture and the Common Market (Cmnd 3274),rather than by the CET.   Manufactured goods would become subject tothe CET at the reduced rates resulting from the Kennedy Round of tariff negotiations.     The temperate commodities (with their main Commonwealthsuppliers) which would be affected either by the CET or by levyprovisions under the common agricultural policy Include cereals (Australand Canada), butter (New Zealand and Australia), cheese (New Zealand,Australia and Canada), beef (Australia and New Zealand) mutton and lamb(New Zealand and Australia) fruit (Australia., New Zealand and Canada),and sugar (we import cane sugar from a number of Commonwealth countries and dependent territories).     Imports of certain tropical commoditieswould also be governed by the application of the CET or, in the eventof the Commonwealth supplier becoming associated with the Community,by the Community arrangements for the commodity concerned.21.     As already pointed out, the duties on most raw materials arezero in both the CET and the United Kingdom tariff, and there would thus be no change in the tariff position for our imports of suchcommodities. -   This would be the case for raw wool and cotton, mostmetallic ores, unwrought copper and tin, natural rubber, crude oil andmost unprocessed hides and skins, many of which are important Commonwealthexports.   A few materials of major importance such as aluminium, lead,zinc and newsprint are dutiable in the CET (currently at ratesbetween 6 per cent and 9 per cent) but are subject to zero or very lowduties in the United Kingdom:    and a few are dutiable here but notin the CET.    The bulk of the latter category are, however, materials of which most of our imports enter duty-free from the commonwealth preference Area.   Examples are asbestos and coir fibre.
22.  Anong semi-manufactures and finished manufactures, duties on textilesof natural fibres are broadly similar in both tariffs.     For example the most favoured nation duty on cotton yarn is now 7is&quot; per cent in the United Kingdomtariff and 8 per cent in the CET.     The corresponding rates for natural cottonfabrics are 17g per cent and 14 per cent to 16 per cent.     However, this isa sector in which the absence of duties on Commonwealth imports into the UnitedKingdom is particularly significant.     United Kingdom duties on textilescontaining nan-made fibres whether from Commonwealth or other sources aregenerally higher, particularly for yarns.     The comparative tariff position on primary iron and steel products is described in the chapter on the european coal and Steel Community (paragraph $b).     For machinery United Kingdom dutiesare on average rather higher than those in the CET.     Duties on motor vehiclesare similar in both tariffs, for example on passenger cars 25^ per cent inthe United Kingdom and 22 per cent in the CET:   but on engines for motor-vehicles the United Kingdom duty is substantially higher at 24 per cent thanthe 14 per cent in the CET.     Among chemicals, the United Kingdom duties onplastics are generally low, but for most other chemical products substantially higher than those in the CET.     This is, however, a sector in which the relationship of the two tariffs nay be more substantially altered than elsewhereas a result of the completion of the Kennedy Round negotiations.     Duties inthe United Kingdom tariff are substantially higher than those of the CET forclocks and watches, optical and photographic equipment, musical instruments and many kinds of precision instruments.     For these the United Kingdom dutiesare now mostly in the range 25 per cent to 50 per cent while the correspondingCET duties are between 10 per cent and 20 per cent.-7-CONF5DENTSAL
It-.    THE PATTERN&apos; Off TRADE BETWEEN THE UNITED KING-DOM AND THE european economic COMMUNITYUnited Kingdom exports23.   The pattern of United Kingdom exports in 1958 and 1 966 is shown inTables 1 and 3.   Since 1958 there has been little change in the value ofUnited Kingdom exports supplied to the Commonwealth and as a consequencethe share of our exports taken by the Commonwealth has fallen from 38 per cent to 26 per cent.   Exports both to the e.c. and to efta have increased substantially and these markets are now of much greater importance in theUnited Kingdom pattern of trade than in 1958.   In 1958 1L per cent ofour exports went to the e.c. and 11 per cent to efta: the corresponding figures for 1366 are 1 9 per cent and 15 per cent.   Most of the Increasein exports to the e.c. and efta has been in the manufactured goods category(which accounts for over five-sixths of United Kingdom exports): but therehas also been strong growth in our exports of food, beverages and tobaccoto these markets.Inports2L.   The pattern of United Kingdom imports in 1958 and is shown inTables 2 and A..   The proportion of total United Kingdom imports supplied bythe Commonwealth fell from 35 per cent in 1958 to 28 per cent in 19^6:while the proportions supplied by the e.c. and efta rose respectively from1lf per cent and 11 per cent in 1958 to 18 per cent and 1L per cent in 1 966.To some extent these changes reflect the growing importance of manufacturedgoods in the commodity pattern of our imports.e.c. trade25.   The pattern of e.c. external trade is shown at Table 5.   Thedevelopment of trade within the e.c. resulting from the dismantling of tariffs has not prevented a rapid rise in trade with countries outside theCommunity.   Exports from member countries to third countries increased by85 per cent between 1958 and 1966; imports rose slightly faster, by over90 per cent.   Imports of manufactured goods increased particularly quickly,and made up 38 per cent of all imports in 1966 compared with only28 per cent in 1958.   Imports from the United Kingdom increased proportionate^faster than total imports from outside the Community, and the UnitedKingdom share of these total imports rose from 7 to 9 Ver cent.-8-CONF.DENTEAL
Balance of visible trade26.   The estimates of the balance of visible trade between the UnitedKingdom and the e.c. shown in Table 6 are derived from United Kingdom tradestatistics. In 1958, trade between the United Kingdom and the e.c. was approximately in balance.   Prom 1958 to 1963, exports in general grewfaster than imports, and there was, except in 1960, an annual increase inthe visible balance of trade in favour of the United Kingdom which reached  200 million in 1963.   Since then, however, this favourable balance has steadily declined and in 1966 amounted to  23 million.   Exportsrose more slowly during 1964 and 1965, partly owing to deflationarymeasures in Italy and slower growth in Prance, but improved again in 1966.Imports, on the other hand, rose rapidly in 1964 and, after a check in 1 965,resumed a faster rate of growth in 1966.
-1 0-5.   FREE MOVEMENT OF LABOUR(Articles 48-51)Provisions of the Treaty of Rone27.   Article 48 of the Treaty of Rone provides for the free movement of labour to he secured by the end of the transitional period, i.e, not later than 1970.Subject to limitations justified by reasons of law and order, public safety and public health, workers will have the right to accept offers of employmentactually nade.     They will have freedom of movement and residence for thispurpose, and a conditional right to remain in the territory of a nenber stateafter having been employed in that territory,     All discrimination based onnationality which affects enployment, remuneration and other working condition.-is to be abolished.     The Article does not apply to employment in public administration.Progress made by the Community towards free movement of labour28.   The Treaty does not lay down any tinetable other than the terminal dateof 1 970 for the achievement of freedom of movement of labour.     The approach is being nade stage by stage, and takes into account the experience of member states in operating the Regulations made by the Council under Article 49 ofthe Treaty.     At first the member states were permitted under these regulations to give priority to their own nationals in filling vacancies.     This generalsafeguard was abolished in 1964:   but member states are permitted, under regulation 38-64 which is currently in force, to give priority to their own nationals for a. period of two weeks only in any occupation or region wherethere is a considerable labour surplus.     In practice, most member states have ceased to use this safeguard because they have not found it to be necessary.Workers from any member state are given priority in the filling of vacanciesover those coming from countries outside the Community.     But the community as a whole has been short of labour, and despite the priority given to EECnationals member countries have found it necessary to bring in substantial numbers of workers from outside the Community in order to meet their labour requirements.Social Security for migrant workers29.   Article 51 of the Treaty of Rome requires the Council to adopt social security measures necessary to ensure the free movement of labour, inparticular by introducing a system which will ensure to migrant workers andtheir dependants that -(a)   all qualifying periods of insurance, etc., under the domesticlegislation of the member countries shall be added together for benefit purposes;and
(b)   benefits shall be paid to persons resident in the territories of member states.The above requirements have in fact been implemented in e.c. Regulations 3and 4, on the social security of migrant workers.Entry of foreign workers into the United Kingdom for paid employment; presentpractice30.   Article 4(i)(b) of the Aliens Order 1953 requires a foreign nationalwho wishes to enter the United Kingdom to take up employment to produce tothe immigration officer a permit issued by the Ministry of Labour.     Eachapplication is treated on its merits:   but in any case issue is subject toa minimum age limit of 18 years, an upper age limit of 54 is usually applied,and. there are three general conditions -(a) the proposed employment of a foreign national is reasonable and necessary in the circumstances;(b) the employer has made adequate efforts to find suitable labour from among British subjects, citizens of the Irish Republic and foreign nationals who are regarded as permanent United Kingdom residents;(c) the wages and other conditions offered are not less favourable thanthose commonly accorded to British employees for similar work inthe same trade and district.Permit holders may not change their job without permission and their permitsare valid for a maximum of one year in the first instance, although they canbe extended.     After four years in approved employment, a foreign worker naybe pernitted to settle permanently free from restrictions,31.   During the past three years, 1964-66, an average of 24,800 permits ayear have been issued to e.c. nationals for work in the United Kingdom.     this represents 39 per cent of the total of all permits issued to foreigners.-11-CO N FIDE NTS AL
6.   RIGHT OF ESTABLISHMENT AND FREEDOM TO SUPPLY SERVICES(Articles 52-66)32.   In the Treaty of Rome (as in commercial treaties in general) the term&quot;establishment&quot; covers not only the setting up and management of independentcompanies, subsidiaries etc. but also engagement in particular activitiesboth by individuals and by companies.   (These are &quot;non-wage earningactivities&quot;.   &quot;Vfage-earning&quot; activities are covered by the provisions forthe free movement cf labour examined in chapter 5.)     Activities undertaken in the course of a temporary visit or through correspondence (e.g. theprovision of professional or technical advice), and which do not entail the setting up of a permanent establishment are covered by the term &quot;services&quot;.The Treaty provides for the progressive abolition during the transitional period (under directives which are to be issued by the Council) of restrictions against nationals of one member state (including companies)who wish to engage in non-wage earning activities or to supply services in another member state.     These obligations do not apply in the field ofpublic administration.33.   Directives are to be issued on mutual recognition of diplomas,certificates and other evidence of qualification.34.    Companies formed in accordance with the law of a member state andhaving their registered office or principal place of business within theCommunity arc to be treated in the same way as individual nationals of member states^35,    In 1961, in implementation of the Treaty provisions, the e.c. Councilof Ministers approved a general definition of the restrictions which are tobe removed and a timetable for the issue of directives on the removal of restrictions on specific activities.     The issue of directives has fallenfar behind the timetable and so far only seventeen have been issued.Among them are directives which deal with rights of establishment or supplyof services in specified activities such as farming, mining, manufacturing and crafts industries, the production and distribution of electricity, gasand water, the film industry, reinsurance, wholesale trade and real estatedealings and business services.     A particularly difficult area in whichmuch   remains to be done is the implementation of the necessary measures tosecure mutual recognition of diplomas and professional qualifications.United ICingdora. practice36.   United Kingdom legislation and practice on establishment and services is generally liberal, and only in a few limited fields are foreign nationalsnot accorded equality of treatment with United Kingdom nationals.   As inthe e.c., however, there are problems over the recognition of professional qualifications gained outside the United Kingdom.-12-CONFIDENTIAL
7.   COMPANY AND PATENT LAWCompany Law37,   Apart from the provisions on establishment discussed in the previouschapter of this paper, action affecting company lav/ might be taken under other provisions of the Treaty, notably Article 100, which authorises theissue of directives for harmonising the legislative or administrative arrangements of member states affecting the operation of the Common Market,and Article 220, which requires conventions to be negotiated between member states so far as is necessary to ensure the mutual recognition of companies, the maintenance of their legal personality when registered officesare transferred from one country to another, and the possibility of mergersacross frontiers.     A number of conventions under Article 220 have beenprepared but none has yet entered into effect,38o   The Community have studied various schemes for making it possible toremove the legal and fiscal obstacles to mergers of companies in differentmember states and to the operations of companies across the frontiers of member states.     One of the schemes under consideration is a convention to provide for a European company incorporated under European law.     Thistypo of company would exist side by side with companies formed under national lav/,J94   The various Community studios v/hich are in progress have not preventedmember states from revising their own domestic company legislation.Patents and Trademarks2^0    Patents, trademarks and industrial designs are to be covered by con-ventions the forms of v/hich are yet to be decided.4-1 ,  For some years the Community have been considering proposals for aconvention for a European patent.       Her Majesty&apos;s Government has already expressed an interest in subscribing to a Convention on the lines proposed.A translation was nade by the Board of Trade and published inNovember 1962 by HM.Stationery Office (SO Code No. 51-367).-13-
8.   TRANSPORT POLICYTransport policy in the EEC42.    The e.c. is required by the Treaty of Rome to adopt a commontransport policy.   Not much formal progress has yet been made in establishing such a policy and it is more appropriate at present to speak of trends and probabilities than of legal instruments and decisions.    Nevertheless, the attitudes of the Six governments have drawn closer on important issues which determine the nature oftransport policy.     In June, 1965, the Council of Ministers adoptedoutline arrangements for the organisation of the transport market.Details and priorities have since been revised, but that outlineremains the agreed basis of discussionj   subject to changes in detail and timing, the common transport policy is evolving accordingly.   Thefinal aim is a Community-wide transport market in which there will be regulated eompetition between transport undertakings and betweenforms of inland surface transport - rail, road and (where it operates)inland navigation.     National policies and control systems are tobe progressively aligned so that, In both national and internationaltransport, competition in those sectors of the transport market whichare most important economically will be regulated on uniform principlesthroughout the Community.     Under Article 84 of the Treaty it is opento the Council of Ministers, acting unanimously, to draw up commonpolicies for sea and air transport.   The Council have not yet exercisedthese powers.Transport policy in Great Britain43*   The White Paper on Transport Policy (Cmnd, 3057 of July 1966) gave an outline of the Government&apos;s policy which is now being worked out indetail in preparation for the introduction of a Transport Bill in thenext Session of Parliament.     Much of the White Paper is concerned withspecifically internal problems - the road programme;     urban transport;regional transport planning;   re-organisation and modernisation of ports;   and economic planning and research, particularly as regardsinvestment criteria.   Among the countries of the European Economic Community,these aro at present matters which are mainly the concern of national governments, not of the Community as a whole:   although there are manysimilarities between the way transport is developing in Europe and theUnited Kingdom.   There are also some problems common to this countryand the Common Market:-14-
(i)   The role of railways in the transport systen of the present day, and efforts to &quot;bring about technical and financial conditions which enable then to fulfil it.   Most common market countries have railways which are to a greater orlesser degree in deficit.   They are concerned about theoptimum size of the railway network;   about the extentto which railway services should be provided for socialrather than commercial reasons;   and about the financialrelationship between the state and the railways.(ii) The development of a regulatory system for road haulage tobring about the most economically advantageous balance oftraffic between road and railoThe official control of freight rates, on which the Common Marketproposals have tended, in the past, to lay considerable stress, but which has been given less emphasis in the latest proposals, has noparallel in present British policy.   On the other hand, there is nothing in the e.c. proposals comparable to the idea of integratingroad and railway freight services by means of the national freightorganisation, although there is nothing to suggest that such are organisation would be incompatible with a common transport policy.-15-
9.   RULES GOVliai-TETC- COMPETITION AND. REGICIJAL POLICIES(Articles 85-94)STATE AJJJS44,  Any form of State aid which distorts or threatens to distortcompetition by favouring certain undertakings or the production ofcertain goods to an extent which adversely affects trade between member states is deemed to be incompatible with the Common Market (Article 92(1))All systems of State aids are subject to examination by the Commissionin conjunction with member states (Article 95).     Tne State is first askedto comment on its system of aids.     If the Commission then decides anaid is incompatible with the Common Market, a prescribed time limit is established within which the aid must be modified or abolished.     in exceptional oases, the Council of Ministers may allow, by unanimous vote,aids prohibited under Article 92.     The Commission must be informed of newaids, which are then examined under the sane procedure;   they may not bebrought into effect if the Commission finds that they are not compatible with the Common Market (Article 93(3)).      The Council may, however, decideby qualified majority that certain types of aid may be exempted from this latter provision (Article 94).45.   However, some types of aid (e.g. social aid to individuals or to remedy a national disaster) are regarded as compatible with the common market under Article 92(2);   and others may be deemed to be compatible(Article 92(3)).     This latter category covers inter alia &quot;aid intendedto promote the economic development of regions where the standard ofliving is abnormally low or where there is serious under-employment&quot;,aid for projects of common European interest and aid to promote thedevelopment of certain activities or certain economic regions.     It alsocovers such other types of aid as may be specified by the Council byqualified majority vote on a proposal of the Commission.M&amp;IQHAI POLICIES46.   Tho permissive dispensation covering regional aids illustrates the strong interest of the e.c. in the development of regional policies as anessential aspect of the efficient management of economies in transition,an interest now common to all the major industrial countries of the world.Tho countries of the Six suffer, in differing degrees and for differingreasons, from all tho problems of regional imbalance which are experienced in the United Kingdom.     These include continuing and increasing mobility of populations with a tendency to congregate in huge urban areas, such asthe District of Paris, the industrial areas of V/est Holland and thoindustrial triangle of Milan-Turin;   problems of increasing rural-16-CON FIDE NTS AL
depopulation;   and the under-developnont of large areas of countries whichhavo a potential - and have demonstrated this in the past - such asSouthern Italy.     It is recognised that there is a need to diversifythe industrial structure of those areas which aro over-depondont ondeclining industries, and to rebuild the outworn urban environment of someof the oldor towns and cities, particularly in industrial areas.Objectives of e.c. Regional Policies47,   There is a close similarity between the objectives of policjr v/hioh havoboon expressed by e.c. G-overnmonts, whether singly or together, and UnitedKingdom objectives.     The Six recognise that regional programmes must beoo-ordinatcd and integrated with each country&apos;s general economic programme;that wide divergencies in economic growth between regions adversely affectoverall ooononic balance;   and that the absorption of under-employed labourand the reduction of uneconomic expenditure in congested regions can contribute substantially to gonoral economic growth.     They accept thata high level of employment should be provided for the available labour force, and that economic development should bo diversified, so that as faras possible every man and woman in each region of the Community can contribute moro effoctivoly to, and participate in, the prosperity of the member countries.     The Six are agreed on the need to pay particular attention to those areas where the living standard is lowest, or wherethere are  special difficulties.     of adaptation to modern circumstances.Instruments of Policy48.   Strong emphasis is placed in the Community on the nood to provide an under-dovcloped or loss prosperous region with good &quot;infrastrn.icti.iro&apos;&apos; -that is to say with good communications (particularly roads);    industrialservices - water, energy and telecommunications;   houses;   educationfacilities (particularly in moro advanced technological methods);   and afull range of cultural and social amenities.     Member states also providea very wide range of financial incentives to individual enterprises insuch regions.Direct Inducements49.  These embrace -(i)   Grants and subsidies,(ii)   Availability of credit, and favourable rates of Interest,(iii)   Tax reliefs.Grants towards the cost of machinery and buildings, for the creation orexpansion of establishments providing new employment^ ore provided by all members of the Community except Germany.     They range between some5 per cent to 30 per cent (calculated variously on the costs of land-17-CON&apos;FtD NTlAL
purchase, plant construction and equipment, or combinations of then).     Forexample, indus-feriallsts in Belgium can obtain up to 30 per cent of thototal cost of fixed assets in some fifteen development regions.     in italy, 20 per cent of total costs is available in the South;   and in france amounts varying between 5 per cent and 20 per cent, depending on whether the business is to bo extended in the under-developed South West,or in a new establishment in one of the Northern zones of readaptation(where employment in the coal, iron ore, and textile industries iscontracting).     In G-omany the main incentives to encourage the redeploymentof industry in problem areas are loans at reduced rates of interest,interest rebates, and in some parts of the country, state guarantees fornecessary finance.50.   The Six countries also provide low-interest loans, and Governmentguarantees for such loans for plant     construction, land purchase and activities such as industrial research.       These loans are particularlyaimed at medium term periods (10-1 5 years).     The rate of interest canbe as low as 1 per cent in times of recession.51.   There is also a wide variety of tax concessions.     In France, forexample, it is possible in one development area   to obtain a depreciationallowance of 25 per cent in the first year on the cost of constructionof buildings.     In the South of Italy, there is a broad band of exemption -from a ten year holiday from profits tax to a 50 per cent reduction of transportation rates for materials necessary for new or convertedindustry.52,   Building and planning controls are not so extensive as in theUnited Kingdom, but a system similar to tho British industrial developmentcertificate and office development permit control is exercised in France.53,  Altogether, the attitude to regional development inside the Connunityshows a lively awareness of the importance of   tho subject,characterised by the consideration and introduction of new methods,by increasing collaboration in this sphere between individual member governments and the Commission and a general widespread interest in regional dovelopnent on the part of public opinion and the institutions in the Connunity.-18-
Rc^ongJ^Proplens and Policy Ob jectivesin. th^ United ji^^dop^    The United Kingdom has had a long experience in dealing with regionalproblems, beginning with those of heavy unenmployment in the pre-war years.     &apos;^he principal problems today are to ensure a contribution tofurther economic growth by more balanced economic development;   to provideeffective physical planning so as to make the best use of public investment;and to make plans for the population growth likely between now and theend of the century.     There is on the one hand the need to make use of reserves of manpower in some regions and to introduce a greater variety of manufacture into the older industrial areas.     On the other, there isthe need to counteract the inflationary effects of excessive regionalconcentrations, and thus to facilitate the even management of the national economy.     In physical planning terms there is a need to develop new townsand cities, rebuild outworn urban environments, plan for modern communications,social and industrial services;   and to protect the amenities and beautyof the countryside.    All this we share in common with Community countries.55.   The instruments of policy which the Government havo adopted can bogrouped as follows -(a)   Control^qf D^gA9 ^&quot;lenJi:    These consist of -(i)   industrial development certificates (i.d.o&apos;s) which are needed to support -applications for planning permission for industrial building above a minimum size.       In tho caseof office building in the Midlands and the South East,office development permits aro required;(ii)   building licences which are necessary for non-industrial building outside development areas costing  50,000 ormore ,(k)    J E iLJ ^2gSg5^ :   These include building grants;   theprovision of advance or bespoke factory buildings for sale or for renting;   regionally differentiated investment grants;resettlement grants for industry or labour;   retraining grants for labour;   and loans, which the Board of Trado can make toindustrialists for the purchase or building of premises, forthe purchase of plant, machinery and equipment, and for working capital.Tho Government of Northern Ireland also makes special arrangements ofits own.-19-
^6,   It is clear that the problems, policy objectives, and instruments ofGovernment policy in the United Kingdom and in tho Six, are broadly similar, although the emphasis in particular countries may bo different.The science of harmonious regional development and planning, which socksto bring together the requirements of employment, housing in an urbanenvironment, and good communications, is still new, experimental andsubject to change.     It is a field in which European countries already have considerable experience in exchanging views.PJ]S&apos;IRICT1YE TRADE PRACTICES AND MONOPOLIES (Articles 85-90)The policies.,.of the Community57.  Article 85 of the Treaty of Rome prohibits agreements and concertedpractices between undertakings which are liable to affect trade between member states and which have the object or effect of preventing,restricting or distorting competition within the Common Market,Agreements or practices which benefit production or distribution or,vpromote progress may, however, be exempted from this prohibition if thoyfulfil certain conditions.     The Treaty also prohibits, in so far as thotrade between member states may be affected, abuses of a dominant position by one or more undertakings (Article 86).58.   Under a Council regulation, firms are required to registerrestrictive agreements with the Commission, who have power to grantpermission for those to continue which arc consistent with the exemptionsin the Treaty.     Firms nay also approach the Commission for clearance thatoertain practices do not fall within the prohibitions in Articles 85 and 86.59.  If the Commission, acting either at the request of a member state or of persons concerned or ex official, finds that there is an infringement,it can address to the enterprises concerned recommendations designed toput an end to tho infringement and if necessary can take a &quot;decision&quot;obliging then to terminate the infringement.     The Commission has powerto demand information and carry out investigations.-20-
60,   The Commissions present policy is to select for decision a limited number of test cases from among tho many thousands of registered agreements.Decisions are subject to review by the Court of Justice to whom a fewoases have been referred.     Thus the Community Is in the early stages of developing a corpus of case law.United Kingdom practicefaf Under United Kingdom law, restrictive agreements in the home marketmust be registered with the Registrar of Restrictive Trading Agreements.They are then brought before the Restrictive Practices Court, and mustbo discontinued unless the parties concerned show that they are consistent with the public interest under certain strict criteria laid down in the restrictive Trade Practices Act of 1956.     Tho Government Intends tointroduce amending legislation which will provide an administrativeprocedure for exempting from registration certain types of agreement.There is therefore some similarity with, the e.c. approach;   in bothoases agreements must be notified to the authorities, and must bejustified as beneficial under certain special criteria.62.   The United Kingdom has separate provisions for resale price maintenance.     Under the Resale Prices Act 196k-, resale price maintenanceis illegal except on classes of goods for which a claim for exemptionhas been made.     The claims for exemption fall to be considered by thoRestrictive Praotices Court, where a positive case must be made in their favour.63.   Monopolies are dealt with by an administrative procedure, underwhich tho Board of Trado may refer monopolies to tho monopolies commission.     Tho Commission then investigates and reports, and theBoard of Trade have powers to remedy mischiefs which the Commissionfinds to exist.       In a similar way mergers may be referred to the monopolies Commission, and the Board of Trade can act on the Commissionsfindings,-21-
10-    FISCAL PROVISIONS(Articles 95-99)Tjidirect Taxation64.  The Treaty of Rome provides (Article 95) that a member state shall notimpose, directly or indirectly, on the products of other member states anyinternal charges of any kind in excess of those applied directly or indirectlyto similar domestic products.     Furthermore, a member state must not impose on the products of other member states any internal charges of such a natureas to afford indirect protection to other products.     Under Article 96, whereproducts are exported to the territory of a member state any drawback ofinternal charges shall not exceed the internal charges imposed on them,whether directly or indirectly.     Article 99 provides that the commission shall consider how to further the interests of the Common Market by harmonisingthe legislation of the various Member States concerning turnover taxes,excise duties and other forms of indirect taxation.65.  Discussions have begun within the Community on harmonising the system for collecting certain revenue duties including those on alcohol, petroleum and tobacco, but no decisions have yet been taken.66,   Progress is more advanced on the harmonisation of turnover taxation andin February 19^7, the Community agreed to adopt by 1970 a common system of value added tax.     There is so far no agreement, however, about common ratesfor this tax.     The value added tax, which already exists in France, is aturnover tax imposed at each stage at which a sale takes place.     Under thissystem, the seller deducts from the tax chargeable on his sales all the taxhe has paid on his purchases.     The other member states of the Communityoperate a so-called &quot;cascade&quot; system of turnover tax under which a tax islevied at a percentage of the sale price on the total value of the goods or services each time a transaction takes place:    under this system, there areno deductions for tax previously paid.67.  Under both systems the tax paid is refunded when the goods are exportedand a compensating charge is made on imports.     The Commission have concluded that it is frequently difficult or impossible to calculate accurately therefunds and charges due on exports and imports where the cascade tax is inoperation.     The same difficulty does not apply in the case of a value added tax.6c;.   In the United Kingdom &quot;cascade&quot; turnover taxes do not exist.     purchase tax is levied at one stage only on goods entering into consumption in thehome market:    it is not levied on exports and is charged on imports.     Arebate of certain taxes entering into the cost of production is grantedon exports. M22-CONFIDENTIAL
11 .   APPROXIMATION OF LAWSTlrticlGS 10CM02)INDUSTRIAL STANDARDSEEC Activities69,   Under the provisions of Articles 100-102 of the Treaty of Rome for theremoval of non-tariff harriers to trade, a number of Directives havealready been prepared by the e.c. Commission with the aim of establishingeommon technical regulations within the e.c. for a wide range of equipment in sectors where standards are laid down in legislation, including motorcars, agricultural tractors, pressure vessels and measuring instruments.Host of these Directives are still under examination and have yet to beadopted by the Council:   but once they have been adopted, member countries would adapt their national legislation to the terms of the Directives.Co-operation between the United Kingdom and the EEC70.   The United Kingdom already works closely with the e.c. countries on theharmonisation of industrial standards.   The United Kingdom and the eec countries are members of the International Standards Organisation (ISO)and its counterpart in the electrical field, the InternationalElectrotechnical Commission (LEC).   As these bodies are primarily concerned with formulating voluntary or non-statutory standards, theUnited Kingdom is represented   by the British Standards Institution at meetings of both these organisations.   There are two parallel bodies whoseaim is to encourage the wider adoption of ISO and TEC recommendationswithin Y/estern Europe - the European Committee for Standards Co-operation(CEN) and, in the electrical field, the European Committee forElectrotechnical Standards Co-operation (CENEI.).   The British standards institution again represents the United Kingdom at meetings of these organisations, which unite the national standards bodies of both theEFTA and the e.c. countries.   National standards bodies of EFTA and eec countries, together with those of Finland, Yugoslavia, Greece, Spain, PolandCzechoslovakia and Hungary are also members of the International Commissionon Rules for the approval of Electrical Equipment (CEE) , which is primarily concerned with domestic electrical equipment.   The e.c. countries have theirown organisation (CENELCOM) which is becoming increasingly active in alignintheir views of matters under discussion in CENEL.-23-CONF1DEMT1AL
71.   The various national standards bodies operate on broadly the sanebasis, although the degree of Government involvement and financialassistance varies.   Government interest in standards work has been increasing recently as its importance for international trade has become more widely recognised.   The United Kingdom Government has joined theGovernments of France and of the Federal Republic of Germany in settingup a Tripartite Committee for Standardisation, on which the three governments and their national standards bodies are represented.   The aim off the Committee is to accelerate work in the European and, ultimately,the world standards bodies through prior agreement between the three countries.   The French and German members of this Committee are givingvaluable assistance to the United Kingdom to ensure that the metricengineering standards now rapidly being adopted by British industry arein line with best continental practice.United Kingdom Activities72,   Both at Government level, and through the British standards institution, the United Kingdom lends its full support to the developmentof international standards, voluntary and statutory, and to theharmonisation of our national standards with world or, where these do not exist, European standards.   The Government and the BSI, each in theappropriate fora, both play a prominent part in international and european discussions on standardisation.    The Government are now activelyencouraging the adoption by industry of the metric system and have formed a Standing Joint Committee on Metrication, whose membership is drawn both from the Government and industry.   Programmes for the changehave been or are being devised for the different sectors of industry,and considerable progress has already been achieved.   It is expected thatthe bulk of industry will have made the change before 1975.-22*.-CONFSDENT1AL
12.   SOCIAL POLICY(Articles 117-128)SOCIAL SECURITY CONTRIBUTIONSKEC Practice73.   Article   117 lays down that the operation of the Common Marketwill favour the harmonisation of the social systems of the member states, and Article 118 indicates that one of the functions of the commission is to promote close collaboration between member states in matters relatingto social security.74,   In the e.c. countries the social security contributions for thevarious schemes in force (there are often separate schemes for particular groups of employees, e.g. miners, railway workers, public servants) are usually related in some way to earnings.   The benefits payable under theschemes are also related to earnings.   The actual contributions and theallocation of these contributions as between employers and employees varyvddely between the different countries.   Thus, expressed, as a percentageof reckonable earnings (usually up to a prescribed upper limit), Italiancontributions total over 51 per cent (employer 45 per cent, employee6 per cent), French contributions total 38 per cent (employer 32 per cent,employee 6 per cent), Germany 27 per cent (employer 14 per cent, employee13 per cent),and the Netherlands 29 per cent (employer 14 per centemployee 15 per cent).   These contributions cover industrial injury benefits(which are a charge on employers only) family allowances (with the exceptionof family allowances in Germany where the position can be compared with theUnited Kingdom) and medical care, which is provided as an insurance benefitrefer the sickness insurance schemes of the Six.   For some of the schemesthere are also Exchequer contributions.United Kingdom Practice75.   Although in recent years a measure of earnings relation has been introduced in the United Kingdom, the system of sooial security contributions and benefits is still predominantly flat rate, that is, the contributions landbenefits are not, in the main, related to earnings.   Expressed as a percentage of average male industrial earnings, the social securitycontributions paid by employers and male employees in the United Kingdom cometo about 11 per cent (employer 5.5 per cent, employee 5.4 per cent). Inaddition there is a direct Exchequer supplement amounting to approximately.1 3 per cent of the total social security contributions paid by employersand employees.   Employees as well as employers contribute to the cost ofindustrial injury benefits.   Medical care is provided under the national health Service, which is financed mainly from taxation; only one-seventh ofthe cost comes from social security contributions.   Family allowances are paid for wholly out of taxation.-25-
y t     It should &quot;be noted that because of wide differences indefinition, scope, coverage and method, as well as the difficultyof making allowance for national variations in wage rates, fringebenefits and other indirect labour costs, international comparisonsin the field of social security are very difficult to make.   Itshould also be noted that there are in fact considerable differences in the practice of individual member countries of the e.c..EQUAL PAY AND PAID HOLIDAYS77,     Article 117 of the Treaty records that member states agree on the necessity of promoting improvement in the living and working conditions of workers.   Article 118 provides that the commission shall promote close collaboration between member states in the socialfield..     Article 119 requires member states to ensure and subsequentlymaintain the application of the principle of equal pay for the samework as between male and female workers.   Progress in the Communitytowards equal pay has been uneven and most member states have notyet reached the stage of full implementation of this article of theTreaty.   The United Kingdom G-overnment is fully committed to theprinciple of equal pay and is currently holding discussions with theTrade Union Congress and the Confederation of British Industry onthe Problems of implementation of this principle.   Article 120 of theTreaty provides that member states shall endeavour to maintain theexisting equivalence of paid holiday schemes.     While this remains the long-term objective, there is at present no proposal to issue anyresolutions or recommendations relating to Article 120.-26-confidential 
13. ECONOMIC PLANING(Article 145)Planning in the Communityy3a    Community policy and machinery on economic planning derives fromArticle 145 of the Treaty of Rome which states that the Council ofMinisters of the e.c. shall -&quot;ensure that the economic policies of the Member States are co-ordinated.&quot;In April 1964, the Council adopted a proposal submitted by theCommission for the creation of a Committee for medium-term economic policy to lay the foundations of economic planning on a Community basis.A draft programme was published in April, 1966s discussed by the Economicand Social Council and the European Parliament and adopted by the Councilof Ministers in February of this year.79.   The programme falls into two parts.     The fir-st is an examinationof the probable economic development of the Community between I966and 1970.     It was drawn up by a sub-committee of experts who drewextensively on the national plans and forecasts of member countries(see below).     The second analyses the deficiencies of existing policies and makes recommendations for co-ordinating and strengtheningthem collectively.80.   Action is proposed in respect of most of the central problems ofeconomic policy outside the fiscal and monetary field, though some refer to the latter as well.     The chief policy recommendations in the draftprogramme concern -Planning and control of public expenditureMaintenance of productive investmentIndustrial rationalisation and reconstructionRegional developmentScience and technologyPrices and incomes policyLabour market policy and vocational training81.    The underlying theme is that growth in the Community is dependenton a steady improvement in suu-oly conditions, and that growth inproductive potential must keep up with growth in demand.     It is recog-nised that the role of the public sector and social investment is extremely important, and that public expenditure will have to growfaster than output as a whole in the period considered.     In acknow-ledging that economic growth in the Community will in future be increasingly determined by the rate of growth of productive capacityrather than demand, the medium term programme emphasises aspects ofeconomic management that are the common concern of this country as well.-27-
82,   The forecasts in-the programme will be progressively revised.In adopting it, member G-governments accepted the responsibility of following the policy guidelines laid down, but the way in which thesethemes are implemented is a matter for individual member countries.Country activities in this field will be examined from time to time by the Medium-term Economic Policy Committee.     The Committee is not,however, vested with powers to enforce compliance with itsre c ommend at ions.National Plans in the SixCo-operation within the framework of the medium term programme isbuilt on the design and experience of national plans, devised in individual countries of the Six in the light of their local circumstances.All the members of the Community except Germany have national plans ofvarious types with a currency of four or five years.     It is difficultto generalise about them, since they differ considerably from each otherboth institutionally and   in respect of techniques employed, of thedevelopment of particular policies and of the planning of particularindustrial sectors.     The degree of direct Government intervention in the Six economies varies, although in all cases (outside public services proper) substantial public sectors exist and public corpor-ations play a significant part in the implementation of economic plans in most of the countries of the Six (see footnote).*In France, the state controls inter alia coal, gas and electricity,the two major airlines, the aircraft industry, a wide range of financial institutions including the four major banks  and part of the oil industry.     In Germany, the state has considerable interests in shipbuilding, non-ferrous metals and iron ore.     In the Netherlands, among other tilings, some coalmines and part of the share capital of the airlines and of the chemical.and steel industries arepublicly owned.     In Italy, state ownership and control has spread widelyin industry through the operation of the three great public corporations:151 (industry generally), ENI (potrochemicals, natural gas and oil) andEFIM (mechanical engineering);   there have been several major extensions .to state   ownership in Italy since the Community was formed.
84.   France has been involved in systematic economic long term planningsince the end of the war and pioneered the influential concept oftencalled &quot;indicative planning&quot;.   Her plans contain both sophisticated forecastsand a detailed statement of the G-overnment&apos; s policy intentions.   Planningis also well established in the Netherlands, where it has been explicitlymore concerned with forecasting,   Italy and Belgium first began long term planning in the 1960s.   The great effort to raise the level of economic activity and the standard of life In Southern Italy plays an important role in the Italian plan.Planning in the United Kingdom85,   The present stage of economic planning In Britain began with thecreation of the National Economic Development Council and Office in 1961,Although similar in some respects to the French Commissariat du Plan, theNational Economic Development Office operates outside the machinery ofGovernment policy making and services the Economic Development committees for individual industries.86.   Since 1964-* the G-overnment has developed a wide range of institutionsto promote effective planning.   With the creation of the Department ofEconomic Affairs and the drawing up of the National Plan, medium term policyformation and medium term forecasting have become much more closely linked.Economic Development Councils have been extended to cover most of the majorsectors of the economy.   Regional Planning Boards and Councils have been created to strengthen and promote regional policy.   Consultation with theTrades Union Congress and the Confederation of British Industry has been greatly extended both formally and informally.87,   The principal aim of British planning was and is to encourage a higher rate of national eoonomic growth, though much effort is also devoted tothe attainment of other economic and social objectives.   The National Plan,published in September 1965, was both a forward survey of Britain&apos;s economic development for the following five years and a guide to action by G-overnmentand industry in this context.   The measures taken in July 1966 meant that many of the assumptions and projections in the National Plan woreinvalidated.   Nevertheless, action on the check-list contained in the Plancontinues to be vigorously prosecuted.   The G-overnment and the national economic Development Council have reaffirmed their belief in the continuedvalue of planning and the form which the next National Plan should takeia under examination by the Ministries concerned and the National economic development Council.-29-
1A.   THE EUROPEAN COAL AND STEEL COMMUNITY (ECSC)vhe^Coal and Steel Industries of the Community88.   Coal and most iron and steel products are covered by the Treaty of paris establishing the European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC).The Treaty provides for free trade within the Community, harmonisedexternal tariffs, and a common pricing system and rules of competition.The High Authority, the executive body, may also advise on investment projects, but has no direct powers to promote or, in general, to prevent such projects.   The Community Is financed by a levy of (at present)0,25 per cent on production, and can provide funds for such purposes as industrial redevelopment and workers1 housing and retraining.   The UnitedKingdom has long standing and close formal links with the Community in theCouncil of Association with the High Authority,89.   The coal industry of the Community had a total production in 19^6 ofabout 202 million tons, and underground manpower of 359j000.   The steelindustry produced about 83.8 million tons of crude steel.   The Prenchcoal industry is nationalised, and there are publicly-owned shareholdings inthe main Dutch and Italian steel-producing combines.90.   Producers of coal and steel must fix their prices at selected basingpoints (usually pithead for coal, and major producing centre for steel).These prices are published and the full cost of transport from basing point to buyer must be charged.   The object of these rules is to avoiddiscrimination.   Producers may however, reduce (&quot;align&quot; down) the deliveredprices to a buyer when that is necessary to match the price at which abuyer can buy from another supplier working to the same rules, or tonatch the delivered price of import offers from third countries (exceptfrom Eastern Europe).   Por coal, alignment is permitted only \/ithincertain limits related to previous levels of sales in specified areas.91.   With one minor exception no Community country has tariffs on importedcoal and imports of third country coal are made at the discretion of member governments; each member admits limited quantities.   Por steel thecountries of the Community at present all apply the same tariff rates whichaverage 8.55 per cent.   The agreement reached in the Kennedy Round is for acommon tariff of about 6 per cent ad valorem. There are varying types anddegrees of support by member G-governments for indigenous coal; agreement hasrecently been reached for a system of subsidiation of coking coals supplied tothe Community&apos;s steel industry.   Por coal and ooke supplied by producers to the-30-^r^PinEMTBAL
steel industry in the same country the cost of the subsidies will te bornehy the Government concerned, but for supplies traded between nembe.s* $featesthe subsidies will be partly financed by the importing countries through thescheme of multilateral compensation.The United Kingdom Coal and Steel Industries92,   United Kingdom coal production in 1$66 was about 175 million tons,and underground manpower 338,000.     The steel industry produced about24.3 million tons of crude steel.     The coal industry is, and the major part of the steel industry shortly will be, nationalised.     Public owner-ship is admissible under the Treaty.93,   In the United Kingdom the prices of non-domestic coals are related topithead prices, but there are no published price lists.     The price of domestic coal depends on the zone in which it is delivered.     At present,the Iron and Steel Board sets the maximum prices for iron and steel productssold in the United Kingdom market by domestic producers;    the pricing policy of the new National Steel Corporation has still to be decided. .94,   There is no United Kingdom tariff on coal imports, but imports are prohibited except from the Sterling Area.     For steel, imports from theCommonwealth and EFTA are duty free;    the tariffs on other imports aregenerally 10 per cent ad valorem with alternative specific dutieseffective on some products;   at current depressed price levels, the incidence of the specific duties averages about 12-15 per cent.     Theagreement reached in the Kennedy Round will reduce both ad valoremand specific duties by a fifth.     The ECSC subsidy for coking coal has noparallel in the United Kingdom.-31-
15.    THE EUROPEAN ATOMIC ENERGY COMMUNITY (EURATOM)The ActivJJijgs, of EURATOM95,   The main objective of the European Atomic Energy Community (EURATOM),as set out in detail in the second Treaty of Rome, is to contribute to the raising of the standard of living of member states and to the developmentof trade with other countries by creating the conditions necessary for the speedy establishment and growth of nuclear industries.     The EURATOMTreaty Includes provisions governing the development of research, the dissemination of information, health protection, investments, jointundertakings, the establishment of a supply organisation and of machineryfor security, supervision and safeguards as well as a common market innuclear materials and equipment,96.   A common external tariff was established a year after the Treaty had come into force, for those nuclear products listed in detail, in theTreaty.     Eor some products, the tariff was based upon the lowest rateof duty in force in the six member countries, and for others the rates were the results of negotiation in the Council of Ministers.97-   The Community atomic energy programme is carried on side by side with national programmes of its member states, which it does notsupersede.     Thus alongside national centres such as Karlsruhe in Germanyand Petten in North Holland there are EURATOM establishments to whichall members contribute and which operate for common benefit.    The formerItalian centre at Ispra became wholly operated by EURATOM in i960.    Theysupplement purely national projects which individual members finance andcontrol.Co-operation between EURATOM and the United Kingdom98.    An Agreement was signed on 4th February 1959 betxveen EURATOM and theBritish Government for co-operation in the peaceful uses of atomic energy.The Agreement provides for regular exchanges of information andco-operation in research between the two signatories.    A continuingCommittee was set up under the Agreement, which usually meets once a year under the joint Chairmanship of the Minister of Technology and thePresident of the EURATOM Commission.   Regular exchanges of scientificinformation and experience have taken place on operational techniques and the use of experimental equipment for research and testing, on the-32-
technology of heat transfer in two-phase flow, on solid state science and on radiation damage, on materials research, on the economics of heavy-water reactors, on the techniques for forward projection of demand,and on the economics of desalination schemes using nuclear power.   at regular meetings between officials from both sides, nuclear powerprogrammes have been reviewed and studies have been initiated on long-term prospects for nuclear energy in the European Community and in theUnited Kingdom.The United Kingdom Atomic Energy Programme99.     The United Kingdom atomic energy programme is directed to thedevelopment of economic forms of nuclear power.    The United kingdom atomic Energy Authority carry out research and development to the proto-type stage.    Industrial consortia which are Authority licensees haveconstructed full size power stations for the Electricity Board.   the United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority has combined with the threeindustrial consortia to form the British Nuclear Export Executive (BNX)for the purpose of promoting sales of nuclear equipment overseas.    the structure of the British nuclear industry is currently under review.100.   The second stage of the United Kingdom nuclear power programme hasbeen started.    The advanced gas-cooled reactor (AGR) is now being constructed cn a commercial basis.   Work is also well advanced on other projects including the steam generating heavy water reactor prototype(SG-HW), on a prototype fast reactor (PER) and on the reactivation of theCapenhurst uranium separation plant (USP).   Nuclear power stations in theUnited Kingdom are owned and operated by the Electricity Boards, and responsibility for the co-ordination of nuclear power in relation toother forms of energy rests with the Minister of Power.
TABLEJLArea Pattern of United Kingdom Exports and ImportsExportsEECContinental EFT.Comonr/ealthOther CountriesTOTALi1)1958		1966			Per cent increase  million	oFtSlaT	  million	Per,cent		-1258^66^448	14	956	19		* 113352	11	740	15		4- 1101239	38	1305	26		. *   5 &apos;1210	37	2041	40		4-  693250	100	5042	100		*  55WMLl    Imports	1958		1966			Per cent inorease 1958-66		  million	Per cent of total	  million				e.c.	538	14	1104	18		4- 105	Continental EFlJ-1 ^	436	11	841	14		+   93	CoKiaonwealth	1336	35	1643	-28		4-   23	Other Countries	1524	40	2366	40		4-   55	TOTAL	3834	100	5954	100		4-   55	(1)  Including Finland(1)
confidential &apos;Area and Commodity PalBLEllotalOf whichI Pood, beverages andtobaccoBasic materials andfuelsManufactured goods  million per cent of total exports  million per cent of total exportsof commodity  million per cent of total exportsof commodity  million per cent of total exportsof commodity1958448(14)26(13)59(24)355(13)EEC1966956(19)65(20)75(26)788(18)COKTI1958352(11)( 5)71(29)263do)Area and Commodity Pat1TABLE 4TotalOf whichfood, beverages andtobaccoUasio materials andfuelsHanufftotured goods  million per cent of total imports  million per cent of total importsof commodity  million per cent of total importsof commodity  million per cent of total importsof commodityEEC1958538(14)152(10)95( 7)288(29)19661,104(18)193(11)189(11)708(29)CONQ1958436(11)131( 9)166(12)136(14) i(i) Including Finland
FIDENTIALty Pattern of United Kingdom ExportsCONTINENTAL efta.\^CommonwealthOther countriesTOTAL TRADE195819661958196619581966195319663521(11)95)17129)263id)740(15)( 9)97(54)593(14)1,239(38)72(37)30(13)1,093(40)1,305(26)73(22)30(10)1,155(27)1 ,210(37)87(45)82(34)1,004(37)2,041(40)160(49)87(30)1,739(41)113,250(100)194(100)242(100)2,714(100)5,042(100)327(100)283(100)4,275(100)[Pattern of United Kingdom ImportsJONTINSNTAIj EFTaU)Commomve althOther countriesifTOTAL TRADE953196619531966195319661958196636ii)1319)166I)136I)841(14)215(13)222(13)397(16)i!,336(35)644(43)426(32)260(27)1,643(28)669(39)463(27)490(20)1,524(40)562(38)658(49)292(30)2,366(40)638(37)815(48)876(35)3,334(100)1,490(100)1,345(100)977(100)5,954(100)1,714(lOO)1,689(100)2,472(100)
External Trade of the e.c.\excluding intra-tmde)TOTALof which united KingdomContinentalEffii(l)Rest of world food, beveragetand tobaccoBasic materials and fuelslanufacturedSPORTSTOTALof which united KingdomContinentalEffi (1)Rest of world food, Averagesand fcbaccoBasic materialsa&quot;d fuelsfenufacturedgoods  million!1,953Per oontof total(!) Inolud:mg Finland5,747     10O4209434,3841,4362,6951,5915,6674741,3663,8275425274,5237167625472810082468109801966(3)  million	Per cent of total	Per oent increase 1958-66!0,977	100	91994	9	1371,750	16	863,233	75	882,336	21	634,234	39	574,156	38	16110,504	100	85908	9	922,830	27	1076,766	64	77806	8	49789	8	508,759	83	94
United Kingdom balance of visible trade with the eec cn a balance of payments basisTABLE 6   million f.o.b.	1958	1959	1960	1961	1962	1963	1964	1965	1966UK Imports	483	511	604	624	651	710	847	889	986UK Exports and re-exports	488	546	598	698	809	917	937	949	1,009Balance of visible trade	+   5	I 35	-  6	+ 74	+158	+207	* 90	+ 60	+    23NOTE:    A positive balance is favourable to the United Kingdom(4)


</content>
</cab>
