<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/130/0 images: 849-920</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r DOCUMENT^ ^PROPERTYOF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)C(67) 100 ^-*-2- COPY NO.     g15th June, 1967CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE?  CIVIL. REVIEWS; education and SCIENCEMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer attach for the information of my colleagues the civil reviewcarried out by officials on education and science expenditure.    Thissets out in detail the various choices open to us, which are summarised in the relevant section of the official report &quot;Public Expenditure: Areasof Choice&quot; circulated as C(67) 102.Li, J, C.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,15th June, 1967
Review of Civil Expenditure to 1971-72Education and ScienceTABLE OF contents part part IIPART IIIANNEXES A1-A1UANNEXES B1-B8ANNEX CANNEX DIntroduction PagesParagraphs 1-8 1-5Summary of Expanded ProgrammeParagraphs 9-13 5-summary of Reduced ProgrammeParagraphs 1h-26 9-15(details of expanded programme) 16-14.1(details of reduced programme) U2-63Teacher Supply (Englandand Wales) 61+-67Higher Education 68-69
CONFIDENTIALReview of Civil Expenditure to 1971-72Education (including school meals, milk,public libraries and museums)PART I - introduction, The National Plan postulated an increase in education&apos;s shareof G.N.P. from 5.h per cent in 196^-65 to 5.9 per cent in 1969-70.Tables 1 and 2 give some selected figures.Table public expenditure on education (includingschool meals and milk) as 1; percentage of G.N.P.Great Britain1950-51 3.21960-61 h.h1963-6U 5.2196h-65     5.h1965-66     5.6 (provisional)Table public expenditure on education (excludingschool meals and milk) as a percentage oftotal taxation receipts of public authoritiesGreat Britain1963-6U     1h.8196U-65     1U.71965-66     1U.6 (provisional)2.    The 1967 P.E.S.C. figures show an increase in expenditure on education and libraries from  1989m. in 1967-68 to  2U52m. In 1971-72,Table 3 summarises the figures and compares them with the recostedP.K.S.C. 1966 figures.1
confidential table 31967 Survey PricesducationD.E.S.S.E.D.TotalibrariesB.E.S.S.E.D.Totalwhich)DtEi S which)JS.E.D.1?67	-68	1968-69		196S	-70	1970-71		1971-72PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO	PESO1966	1967	1966	1967	1966	1967	1966	1967	19671761	1746	1862	1846	1956	19 28	2049	2019	2140190	190	203	203	214	216	224	225	2361951	1936	2065	201+9	2170	2144	2273	2244	237647	50	50	55	53	60	55	65	713	3	3	3	3	3	3	4	450	53	53	58	56	63	58	69	752001	1989	2118	2106	2226	2207	2331	2313	24511808	1796	1912	1901	2009	1988	2104	2084	221219/s	193	206	206	217	219	227	229	2403.     For education in Great Britain the P.E.S.C. 1967 figure for1971-72 is about 27 per cent higher than the recosted P.E.S.C. 1966figure for 1966-67.  an annual increase of 5.2 per cent compared,with..8 -per cent a year between I96U-65. and 1969-70 postulated in theNational Plan (and an estimated actual annual increase of over per cent between 1961+-65 and 1966-67).k.     The main policies underlying the P.E.S.C. 1967 figures are:-(i)   Provision for the larger numbers of children resultingboth from bigger age-groups and the trend towardsvoluntary staying on at school beyond the school leaving age, and from the raising of the school leaving again 1970-71.    It is estimated that these factors will2
increase the school population in England and ,/ales from.3m. in 1967 to 8.7m. in 1872 i.e. by nearly 20 per cent,and in Scotland from 889,000 to 1 million i.e. by12 per cent.(ii)   An increase in the number of teachers in schools in orderto make possible the elimination in England and wales ofclasses over 2+0 in primary schools and over 30 in secondary schools (requiring respectively staffing ratiosof 1:26.3 and 1:15.7) at the earliest possible date.    Itis estimated that the number of qualified teachers (full-time equivalent) will increase by nearly 25 per cent from305,000 in 1967 to 380,000 in 1972 and that staffingratios over the same period will change from 1:28.5 to1:26.8 in primary schools and from 1:18.3 to 1:l8.h in secondary schools (after improving to 1:16.9 in 1970-71,lust before the school leaving age is raised).   InScotland it   is  estimated that the number of certificatedteachers will increase by 12 per cent,(iii)   Provision of courses of higher education, in accordancewith the Robbins recommendation, for all those who are qualified by ability and attainments to pursue them andwho wish to do so.   Numbers of students in universities,colleges of education and full-time advanced further education are estimated to increase from 339,000 in1966-67 to 2+16,000 in 1971-72 i.e. by nearly 23 per cent.I.    Table 3 shows that the P.E.S.C. 1967 figures for England andWales for 1970-71 are some  20m. less than the recosted P.E.S.C.1966 figures - mainly because of the smaller numbers of teachersnow expected in schools.    (See paragraph 21 and Annex C.)   This sumhas to be deducted from the expanded programme summarised in Table kand added to the reduced programme in Table 6 in order to arrive atProgrammes respectively about 5 per cent greater and 7i per centliess than those in P.E.S.C. 1966.   For Scotland the P.E.S.C. 1967
figures for 1970-71 exceed the recosted P..E.3.C. 1966 figures by 1.7m. mainly because of the likely increased numbers of further education students.   This sum has to be added to the reducedIprogramme and deducted from the expanded programme to give the totals shown in tables h and 6 respectively.6.Pour points affect the consideration of the alternativeprogrammes.First, the 1970&apos;s will be a period of considerablestrain for education, because the school and college population willbe rising rapidly under the impetus of the renewed surge in thebirthrate in the late 1950&apos;s (as well as the growth in enrolmentrates).   This contrasts with housing:    the rate of family formationWill be reflecting the trough in the birthrate between the late&apos;hO&apos;s and the late &apos;5Cfs.    Second, a number of welfare objectivesI can be achieved by educational policies which thus contribute to aI general attack on the problem of child poverty.   Examples are toI be found in Annexes A1 , 2 and U.7.    Thir d,   eighty-five per cent of current expenditure on education is local authority expenditure eligible for rate support grant.   As the law now stands, the rate support grant, once settledfor a given period, cannot be reduced and can be increased only for major rises in costs (i.e. pay and prices).   The current rate support grant settlement covers 1967-68 and 1968-69.    For later years thereis no difficulty in fixing rate support grant by reference to ahigher or lower total of estimated expenditure.   Even then, because it is a block grant, there is no certainty that local authorities will adjust their actual expenditure in the way intended by thecentral Government.   The relevant figures in this memorandum assume that these difficulties will in practice be effectively circumvented,,8.    The fourth point is that the review as originally set in motionrelated primarily, thought not exclusively, to expenditure in 1970-71,,and this paper has been prepared accordingly.   Departments were however subsequently asked to pay particular attention to the k
possibility of reductions in expenditure in 1968-69.   Thetechnical problems in relation to current expenditure attractingrate support grant, discussed in the previous paragraph, are relevant here.   It is understood, however, that it would be possibleto take into account the higher income accruing to local authorities from any increase in charges (e.g, for school meals) in the currentbiennium by setting them off against the increased costs arisingfrom e.g. an increase in pay which would justify a rate support grant increase order in the autumn of tnis year.   If this could bedone, the the additional income accruing to local authorities froma nigher cnarge for school meals (see footnote to table 6) couldbe used to reduce total expenditure in 1968-69.   The postponement of the raising of the school leaving age woald also yieldsubstantial savings in 1968-69 (see paragraph L. of Annex B3).PART II - SUMMARY OF EXPANDED programme .    Table k summarises the expanded programme which, after allowing for the adjustments referred to in paragraph 5, adds h.7 per centin 1970-71 to the basic programme in P.E.S.C. 1966.   Details aregiven in Annexes A1-14J    the numbering corresponds to the items in Table U.5
Table UCost in1. Acceptance of targetsrecommended in PlowdenReport involvingadditional expenditure.,       D.E.S.. S.E.D.2.   Following from NewsomReport, assistance tosecondary schools,especially in educationalpriority areas, in parallel with 1 .D.E.S.S    .D.3.   Improvement tosecondary school buildings.D.E.S.3.E.D.k*   Additional voluntarystaying-on at school.D.E.S.S.E.D.5.   Integration of publis schools (first stage).D.E. million1968-69 1969-70 1970-71 1971-72 1979-80222.06.   In-service trainingof teachers.D.B.S.S.E.D.7.   Addition to further education building programme.D.E.S.S.E9D.8.   Additional capital invest-ment for sport and the youth service.D.E.S.S.E.D.60.220.110.110.137h.080.5137k0.330.310,25.1101 .0220.88o.h70.660.U20.1151.5680-1005020U5
Table 4 ContinuedCost in 1968-69 1969-70 1970-71 1971-72 1979-9,   Improvements touniversity buildings(Great Britain)D.E.S. - 1 3 510.   Extra places in medical schools(Great Britain)D.E.S. 12 2 311.   The Open University(Great Britain)80D.E.o.12.   Implementation ofRobertson Report on pre-service and in-servicetrainingS.E.D. 0.1 0.2 0.2 0.213.   Hostel provisionfor colleges of educationS.E.D. 0.1 0.3 0.h 0.314.   MiscellaneousD.E.S. 1 2 h kS.E.D. - - 0.6 0.6Imputed Rent - 1 1 grand Total hi 92        128        163of which D.E.S. Uk 85        118        151S.E.D. 3 7 10 12Notes;(a) The order of these items does not express any departmentalorder of priority.(b) The figures quoted, for the four years 1968-69 to 1971-72represent in most cases the maximum additional expenditurepossible.   It will be clear from what is said below where lessambitious alternatives are feasible.(c) The estimates for 1979-80, some of which are based onthe  &quot;more ambitious&quot; programme described in paragraphs 29-33of the report on public expenditure to 1980 (E.D.(0)(66)99),7
are inevitably very rough.    In several c^ses it does not makesense to give any figure,(d)   Totals will not add because of rounding.plowden Report10.   The main recommendations are:-(i)   positive discrimination for schools in socially handicappedareas (educational priority areas) -  20m. in 1970-71;(ii)    expansion of nursery education, staffed largely by nurseryassistants, so that it should be generally available by1977 -  16m. in 1970-71;(iii)    a national training scheme for teachers&apos; aides in primary schools and a national pupil/staff ratio for theemployment of aides -  13m. in 1970-71 ;(iv)    improvements to primary school buildings - nil in 1970-71(outside educational priority areas),  9m. in 1971-72.Newsom Report11.   Many recommendations in the Plowden Report reflect those madein the Newsoin Report of 1963 on secondary education and action in educational priority areas should be taken on both together.Additional expenditure in secondary schools is needed for larger numbers of non-teaching staff, more and better equipment, morebooks etc.Improvements to Secondary School buildings12.   Approved school building programmes in England and Wales from1965/66 to 1967/68 made provision for some  25-30m.   worth of startseach year to be devoted to the improvement and replacement of oldschools. The approved programmes for 1968-69 and 1969-70 are larger and include substantial allocations for raising the school leaving age;   but they allow only about  10m. a year for improving andreplacing old buildings.   The Departments 1967 P.E.S.C. forecastsassume  10m.   for improvements in the starts programme for 197C-71and 1971 -12, which have still to be settled.    It is however clear8
from experience in drawing up lists of projects for inclusion inthe 1968-69 programme that , 10m.   a year will leave much to be tackled,jt is therefore proposed that the programmes assumed in the 1967P.E.S.C. forecast should be increased by  20m.   in each year of theyears 196?-70 to 1972-73.   A small increase for improvements isalso proposed for Scotland.Tn-Service training of teachers13.   Additional expenditure is proposed to cover (a) increased costs incurred by the Education Departments and other bodies in runningtraining courses, and certain miscellaneous expenditure, (b)subsistence allowances for teachers attending courses, (c) capitalprovision for training centres.Other Items14.   Details of the remaining items - voluntary staying on at school,integration of the public schools, additions to the further educationbuilding programme, additional capital investment for sport and the youth service, improvements to university buildings, extra mediacal school places, the Open University, the miscellaneous group and, forScotland only, implementation of the Robertson Report   and increasedhostel provision for colleges of education - are given in Annexes   Ah*A5 and A7-14 below.   The total additional cost of these items is asfollows:-Table 5 million1968/6?     1969/70     1970/71      197V721.5 2h 36 1+part III- SUMMARY OP REDUCED PROGRAMME15. Table 6 summarises the reduced programme. In 1970-71, againafter allowing for the adjustments referred to in paragraph 5* it represents a reduction of 7.8 per cent on the P.E.S.C. 1966 basic programme.   Details are given in Annexes B1-8.9
Cost inTable 6 million1968-69 1969-70 1970-71 1971-72 1979-801, Charge 2/6d for school dinners.D.E.S.5 *!E.Da2,  Abandon statutory provision of milk inprimary and secondary schools (except for those in need)D.E.S.S .E .D.2.   Postpone raising school leaving age:    by four years in England and Wales, by two years in ScotlandD.E.S.S.E.D.L,   Reduce capital and current expenditure on further education (England and Wales)D.E.S.5.  Reduce expenditure onuniversities (Great Britain)D.E.S.6,   Reduce student supportS.E.D.7.   Reduce expenditure on public libraries and museums(England and Wales)D.E.S.8,   Reduce numbers ofuncertificated teachers(Scotland)S.E.D.9.   Reduce replacementcomponent in school building programme(Scotland)S .E.D.25   )13311160.30.531uX131.9430.512103.30.6hi5.0,142.0442.513105.2131 .1465.2]152.1h62.01310105.4181.1SeeNote (c)below .52.01 .0
below11,   Reduce social and recreational expenditureS.:i.D. 0.1 0.2 0.U O.J4Imputed Rent -j -j grand total 96        137        161+        178(of which) D.E.S. 91 121+        1U5        1o0S.E.D. 5 13 19 18*   In addition there would be increased income from thecharges of about  12m. a year in each of the four year.Notes^   The order of these items does not express any departmentalorder of priority.(b) Generally speaking the figures represent the maximum reductionsfeasible.    It will be clear from what is said below to what extent these maxima may be modified.(c) By 1980, on the assumption that the school leaving age (item 3)is postponed as postulated, the total saving from all itemswould be of the same order as in 1970/71 .m   Totals will not add because of rounding.Charge 2/6 for School Dinner16.   The present charge of 1/- per dinner was fixed in 1957 when thecost of the dinner was about 1/I0d;    it is now about 2/6d and thecost of providing school dinners in 1966-67 was about  80m, (excludingcapital expenditure).   The estimate for 1970-71 , with a charge of)/-, is  10hm.   An increase in the charge would reduce net public expenditure by increasing revenue from parents and by reducingdemand:    the estimate of savings in Table 6 reflects the latter1,1CONFIDENTIALrpn^ 6 continued.._Cost in 1968-69 1969-70 1970-71 1371-72 1979-8010.   Reduce grant to grant-aided secondary scnools(Scotland)v SeeS.E.D. 0.3        0.U,        0.5        0.5     Note (c)
CONFIDENTIAL - A .691element only.   It is assumed that remission scales would be modified to prevent hardship.Abandon provision of milk17.   Administratively the withdrawal of milk would be preferable tocharging for it.   There is a nutritional case for retaining milk injirimary schools:    the savings fro; withdrawing it would be about 10m.- 11m. a year.   The medical evidence on secondary schools is less clear.    The savings from withdrawing milk from them alone wouldbe nearly  5m. a year.   It is assumeo in both cases that milk wouldnot be withdrawn from 10% of the pupils who might otherwise sufferhardship.Postpone Raising School Leaving Age18.   The Education Acts provided for the school leaving age tobe raised to 16 at a date to be fixed.    In 1 96h, it was announced that plans were being made so that the age could be raised in the autumn of 1970.   Projections of numbers of pupils of secondary school age and of teachers available for 1970-71 indicated that staffing ratioswould then be most favourable for the operation.     In England andWales, assuming that the operation were postponed for at least fouryears the savings would be as indicated.     Wider considerations affecting this issue are discussed in Annex B 3.19.   In Scotland, some of the building starts needed for raising theschool leaving age are taking place this year and a four-year post-ponement of the R.S.L.A. date would disrupt some authoritiesprogrammes.   Postponement for two years, on the other hand, wouldgive more time to build up numbers of certificated teachers in preparation;   and the Scottish savings are based on this assumption.Reduce Further Eduaation Expenditure (England and Wales)20.   Total current expenditure on further education in 1970-71(including awards to students) is forecast at  200m. , capitalexpenditure at  53m.   To achieve the savings indicated it would benecessary:12
13(i)   to reduce rate support grant with a view to reducingcurrent expenditure directly;(ii)   to reduce building programmes in order both to saveexpenditure on new building and also, indirectly, to check the rate of expansion of future current expenditure.In making any reductions it would be necessary to avoiddisrupting developments at advanced level (see Annex D) and those associated with industrial training.Reduce Expenditure on Universities (Great Britain)21.   It is estimated that the savings indicated would be made on current expenditure if the average staff/student ratio were 1:9instead of the present 1:8 and existing Robbins numbers were adhered to.   The annual growth factor would need to be reduced to 0.l4Per cent per student.   On capital expenditure no savings will be possible inthe period under review without putting at risk the Robbins targets for higher education up to 1973:    see Annex D.Reduce     Student   Support22.   Savings could be achieved by one or more of the following:-(i)   reducing the maximum value of awards by, say 10 per cent;(ii)   reducing or abolishing the vacation element in themaintenance grant;(iii)    increasing the value of the parental contribution;(iv)    introducing some form of loan scheme for awards.Items (i)-(iii) would all save similar amounts in a full year.The savings indicated in Table 6 are cased on (i) above for Englandand Wales which could in practice be carried out by not increasingthe money value of awards in the autumn of 1968 when the nextreview of awards is due.   For Scotland the basis is item (iv) above,under which about  130 of the present grant would be replaced bya Government-guaranteed bank loan.
piling expenditure on public Libraries and Museums (England and .Vales)23,   Capital expenditure could be reduced by holding loan sanctionsln j\967-68 and subsequent years to the 1966-67 level of PJ.\ .5m.( U.7m. at 1967 Survey prices).   For current expenditure the nextrate support grant exercise in the autumn of 1968 could be used tofreeze local authorities&apos; estimated expenditure in the two following years at the 1968^69 level.   Such a freeze would become progressively more severe.Other Items (Scotland)24,   Small savings would be yielded by the following items, whichare described more fully in Annex B 8:(i)   Reduction in numbers of uncertificatedteachers:    if therecommendations of the Roberts Committee on this pointare implemented and the teaching force better deployed,some 700 of the least effective uncertificated teachersmight be replaced by 1970-71.   The disadvantage of largerclass sizes would be outweighed by the improved quality of the teaching service,(ii)   Reduction of replacement component in school building programme.(iii)   Reduction of grant to grant-aided schools:    an arbitraryreduction to achieve  0.5m. in a full year would causefees to increase by nearly 40 per cent,(iv)   Reduction of social and recreational expenditure:    both current and capital expenditure could be cut.Teacher Supply (England and Wales)25.   In P.E.S.C. 1966 it was estimated that there would be 388,000teachers in primary and secondary schools in 1971-   The P.E.S.C.1967estimate is 37h,00O (at a cost of  556m. in 1970-71).   The downwardrevision is the result of the latest information about wastage rates.Details are given in Annex C1U
26.   There are three points to make about the new estimate:-(i)    It is still provisional.   A full analysis of the datawill not be available until later in the year, when the(ii)   But the new estimate represents a serious blow to theprospects of eliminating oversize classes by the mid-1970sand no further reduction   in expenditure on teachers is contemplated by D.E.S.(iii)    It would not be possible to make further reductionsby 1970-71 short of ceasing to employ teachers already in service or not employing those already&apos; in the collegesor entering the colleges this year.-Higher Education27.   Higher education is discussed in Annex D, which shows that theRobbins targets for 1973 may need revision when a study of studentnumbers now in progress is completed later in the year.   Meanwhileno changes are contemplated by D.^.S. in expenditure on higher education which would have the effect of reducing the plannednumber of students.15
ANNEX AImplementation of Plowden Report (Q.B. )ENGLAND AND wales.    The Central Advisory Council&apos;s report, published in January 1967,was the first comprehensive survey of primary education inEngland and Wales for over 30 years.     It focused attention onthe largest single sector of the educational system;    inJanuary 1966 there were about k.hm children in primary schoolscompared with 2.8m in secondary school.     The report pointed outthat: -(i)   the development of nursery education has &quot;been severelyrestricted, mainly &quot;because of the shortage of teachers;(ii)   classes in primary schools are much larger than in secondary schools.     In 1966 the respective staffingratios were 1:29.7 and 1 :18.6.     Statutory Regulationsrequire that primary school classes should contain notmore than hO pupils and secondary classes not more than30;(iii)   current expenditure per pupil in primary schools hashardly increased in real terms since 1962-63;(iv)   primary schools have not &quot;benefited as much as secondary schools from school building policies.     The programme for the reorganisation of all-age schools launched in1955 conferred only incidental advantages on primary schools but yielded many new secondary schools;   theWhite Paper of 1958 gave priority to the improvement of secondary rather than primary schools;    the specialallocation for raising the school leaving age in 1970-71will again largely benefit secondary schools.     Yet theSchool   Building Survey of 1962 showed that a larger proportion of primary school premises were unsatisfactory.
MATN RECOMMENDATIONS:    (a) EDUCATIONAL PRIORITY AREAS2.     Extra help was proposed for primary schools in these areas by:-(i)   appointing   more teachers, at the expense of the restof the country;(ii)   special allowances to all teachers in these schools;(iii)   more teachers&apos; aides in these schools than elsewhere;(iv)   priority in higher &quot;building programmes and a specialallocation for minor projects (those costing less than 20,000 each);(v)   expanded nursery provision in advance of the national scheme;(vi)   adjusted Exchequer grant to the local authorities concerned.3.     These proposals involve some difficulties, in identifyingpriority areas as defined by the Council, in modifying the quota system to divert teachers to these areas, in makingspecial salary allowances, and in adjusting the systemof Exchequer grants on the lines proposed by the Council.But in C(67)9 the Secretary of State for Education and Science hasalready indicated his general support for the principle ofpositive discrimination in favour of schools in sociallyhandicapped neighbourhoods;    the Cabinet have agreed that thequestion should be considered further in the context of family endowment.(b)   NURSERY EDUCATIONk.     The main features of the Plowdtn recommendations were;-(i)   nursery education from the age of 3 to 5 plus should beavailable on a voluntary basis for all children;   for80% of term on a part-time basis;17CONFIDENTIAL
(ii)   in the short term this should not require any additionalqualified teachers:    those at present teaching under&apos;s in primary schools would he available;(iii)   a major scheme should he launched for the recruitment and training of nursery assistants:   70,000 would heneeded for 1980;(iv)   &quot;between 175,000 and 250,000 additional nursery school places would have to he provided, at a cost of over 100m spread over ten years.5.     The current expenditure per pupil was estimated at over 100 a year, or some  80 m   a year in all &quot;by the 1980&apos;s.     against this could he offset existing expenditure, between  30m and kOm a year, on educating children aged 3 and 5 in infant andnursery schools and classes.     An influential minority of the plowden Council recommended an economic fee of 5s. a half day foreach child in a nursery school, with appropriate remissions forpoorer children.      (This is in line with the existing arrangements in day nurseries.)6.     The Council argued that a large proportion of the additionalteachers&apos; aides and nursery assistants could be found from amongmarried women who would not otherwise be employed, and that theoutput of the   mothers who would be enabled by a big expansion ofnursery education to return to work would reduce by about  20mthe real resources cost of the proposals.     This saving is not allowed for in Table 7 below,(c)   CURRENT expenditure.     The main recommendation is for a rapid increase in the numberof teachers&apos; aides in primary schools, rising to 50,000 by the mid-1970&apos; s.     The manpower and financial considerations noted inparagraph 6 above are relevant here also.18
(d)   CAPITAL expenditure.     The Council recommend improvements to remedy the worst defectsin all primary schools at a cost of between  50m and  70m (at 1966survey prices) over seven years.      (in comparison, the school building programme is already running at well over  100m a year.)They also recommend a special allocation of minor works toeducational priority areas at an annual cost of  2m for five years.(This, with comparable expenditure in secondary schools, was the specific recommendation to which the Secretary of State was seeking approval in C(67)9.)TOTAL expenditure. Table 7 below brings together the current and capital costs of the Plowden recommendations on the assumption that a start ismade with implementing them in 1968-69.TABLE 7COST OF PLOWDEN RECOMMENDATIONSPRIMARY  m1968-69      1969-70      1970-71       1971-72Training of aidesOther current^Capital51k85689571715Total (A)10192239NURSERYTraining of assistantsOther currentCapital1293312k5133611Total (B)12182220Grand Total (A   +   3)223759*Including special allowances for teachers in educationalpriority areas.     These are estimated as follows:-1968-691 969-701 970-711971 -72 m1122Source   Plowden Report Tables hO-1+5:    (Capital expenditureadjusted to take account of the new cost limitsintroduced 1966 .)
SCOTLAND10.   The first of the main recommendations of the plowden committee - the establishment of educational priority areas -has a relationship with one made in Scotland by the RobertsCommittee which was set up in the light of the serious shortageof teachers in certain areas to consider measures to secure amore equitahle distribution of teachers.     This was that schoolswhich were difficult to staff should be designated schools of temporary shortage and the staff serving in them should receiveadditional payments of salary as well as travel payments.     If itwere accepted that the Plowden, and in Scotland the Roberts,recommendations on special allowances to schools in particular areas should be implemented the cost in Scotland would be  0.5min a full financial year.11.   If the other main recommendations were to be implemented toany extent in England and Wales it would be desirable for broadly similar steps to be taken in Scotland.     On the assumption thatimplementation is started in 1968-69 the estimated cost would beas shown in table 8 below.TABLE 8iSMz^     1262=22     1970-71      .1.971-72PrimaryTraining of AidesOther currentImprovements in worstprimary schoolsNurseryTraining of NurseryAssistantsEmployment of NurseryAssistants(9,000 by 1980)Provision of additionalnursery accomodation to take  80 per cent of 3-5 age group0.71.10.60.10.21.00.U1.51.11.00.50.61.51.02.01.00.k1.81.1+20
21Machinery12.    (i)   Selection of educational priority areas,(ii)   Rate support grant,(iii)   School Building Programme,(iv)   Establishment of training facilities for aides andnursery assistants.
22Annex A2Neweom Report (G.B.)1.     It is proposed that action might be taken to improvesecondary schools, particularly in the educational priority areas,in parallel with improvements to primary schools resulting fromplowden.   Additional expenditure in secondary schools (beyond thatimplied by improved staffing ratios and the improvement factor in non--teaching costs per pupil allowed for in PESO forecasts) is needed for -(i)   non-teaching staff - e.g. laboratory technicians, librarystaff, school secretaries, teachers&apos; aides;(ii)    laboratory equipment, audio visual aids (e.g. teachingmachines, language laboratories, film projectors,television sets, CCTV, etc.);(iii)    text books and library books, etc.;(iv)   special allowances for teachers in educational priorityareas.Machinery2.     Rate support grant.
Annex A3Improvements to Secondary School Buildings (G.3.)ENGLAND AND wales.     The School Building Programmes from 1965-66 to 1967-68 made provision for the improvement and replacement of old schools.    the programmes approved for 1968-69 and 1969-70, which include largeallocations for raising the school leaving age, will allow nothingspecifically for improvements which were however always regardedas a proper charge against the small margin of up to  10m. that the programmes were thought to offer when their value was fixed.    It isintended, when allocating the programme,  to approve a small numberof improvement projects, mainly for primary schools, within thelimits of the margin.2.     The School Building Survey of 1962 showed how great was theneed for the improvement and replacement of old buildings.   Theprogress resulting from the special allocations in the programmesup to 1967-68 is small in relation to the size of the problem.Moreover, while the priority for primary schools is justifiedbecause a larger proportion of their buildings are pre-1939 (andpre-1902), it means that little progress is being made withsecondary school improvements.   Old secondary buildings, many ofwhich are not purpose-built, are proving increasingly inadequate for the needs of modern secondary education.   Reorganisation oncomprehensive lines, for which no special allocations have been&apos;made, underline their deficiencies, as nothing is being done to relieve the overcrowding from which many of them suffer.    the increases proposed, on the assumption that the additional programmes in 1969-70 to 1972-73 were divided equally between minor (thosecosting less than  20,000 each) and major projects, would generatethe additional expenditure, including expenditure on land, fees and equipment, shown in Table 4 above.23
SCOTLAND3.    In Scotland the school building programme might alIncreased to give expenditure of nearly  1m. in 1970-71worst secondary schools.Machinery4.    School building programmes.2k
Annex AhVoluntary Staying on at School (G.3.)ENGLAND AND wales.     Table 9 shows the numbers of 16 year olds in maintainedschools in 1959 and 1965, and the estimated figures for 1971,just before the school leaving age is due to be raised.TABLE 9Secondary School Pupils		1959	1965	197116 year olds		88,000	153,000	168,000As percentage of age-	-group	15.4	20. h	25.617 year olds		38,000	82,000	89,000As percentage of age-	group	7.0	10.3	13. h18 year olds		1h,000	28,000	31,000As percentage of age	-group	2.6	3.7	h.72.     Given the maintenance of recent trends the numbers aged 16 to18 will increase by 25,000 between 1 965 and 1971, or by over 3 ineach age group.    In the Northern half of the country the proportions staying at school beyond 15 are much lower than those shown, and there is wide evidence of a waste of talent (seefurther Annex B3).    If the rate of increase could be doubled the extra numbers at school would be about 16,000 in 1969, &apos; 20,000 in1970, 25,000 in 1971.   With the raising of the school leaving again 1971, mainly 17 and 18 year olds only would be involved in 1972,when the extra numbers would fall to about 10,000.3.     Little or no additional capital expenditure would be required,since the extra pupils could for the most part be housed in an existing or planned V and VI form accommodation.    It is doubtful if any extra teachers would be recruited,,   Additional non-teachingcosts of the order of  150 per pupil would be incurred.   additional expenditure would also be required on school maintenance allowances(these, ranging up to about  100 a year according to the pupil*s
age, are payable by local authorities to parents with incomes at or close to supplementary benefit level who have children at schoolover the leaving age).    The total cost of allowances at the moment is about  1.8 million a year, rising to  2.0 million in 1971-72*A doubling of the allowances,  together with some relaxation in themeans test, might be expected to treble these cost figures.    Inview of the regional disparity in numbers staying at school afterthe leaving age already referred to, regional discrimination inmaintenance allowances might be possible.    This has not been allowed for in Table 10 below.k.     Table 10 gives the additional expenditure which would be involved in this proposal.TABLE 10Additional Expenditure m.1968-69     1969-70     1970-71     1971-72Non-teaching costs       2.h 3.0 3.8 1.5Maintenanceallowances 3.8 3.8 3.9 h.0Total 6.2 6.8 7.7 5.5SCOTLAND5.     In some areas the proportion of children staying on at schoolis much lower than the Scottish average and many children who wouldprofit from a longer period at school and who could take S.C.E.passes are leaving school prematurely.    The rates and the contribution scale for higher school bursaries have been unchangedfor some years now and bursary expenditure has fallen from 753,000 in 1963-6U to  587,000 in 1965-66.    In real terms the fallhas, of course, been much more and there has been strong pressure from the Association of County Councils and the Association of directors of Education to improve the present position.   The
waste of ability undoubtedly applies particularly to children fromXow-income families and an increase of  0.3m. in expenditure on higher school bursaries   could give some help to these families and encourage more children (2,500 by 1971-72) to take advantageof the educational opportunities open to them.    If additionalpupils stayed on longer at school they could largely be accomodated in existing classes, but some expenditure will be incurred on their non-teaching costs.Table 11 m.1?68-6g     1969-70     1970-71     1971-72Additional expendi-ture on HigherSchool Bursaries 0.2 0.3 0.3 0.non-teaching costs        - 0.1 0.1 0 1Machinery6.    Administrative action and rate support grant.27
28Annex A5integration of the Public Schools (England and Wales)j,    The Public Schools Commission is expected to present an interim report at the end of 1967, and to recommend that half ormore of the places in public schools should be filled by pupilswith a wide range of ability selected according to need for boardingeducation.   Fees would be paid (on a mean test) out of public funds.This would probably mean, at least at first, payments by theExchequer.2.    The figures given in Table k assume that 6,000 new placesare taken up each year beginning the academic year 1968-69, atan average cost to public funds of  1+00 each.Machinery3.    Grants to individual pupils: this might require legislation.Longer-termk,    It is difficult to estimate the longer-term effects of the commissions likely proposals: the best guess at present for theend of the 1970&apos;s is a net expenditure of  20 m.
Annex A6In-Service Training of Teachers (G.B.)ENGLAND AND wales.     Over  50m. annually is spent &quot;by public authorities on the initial training of teachers.    About  1m. apart from the teachers&apos;salaries (about  2m.) is spent on providing in-service training forthe teaching force of over 300,000.    This does not do justice tothe need to ensure that, in a situation in which educationaltechniques are undergoing rapid change, individual teachers aregiven the opportunity, in a professional career which may extendover more than kO years, to keep up to date with current trends.12 analyses the	addi tional TABLE 12	expenditure	proposed.	In-	Service Training							 m.	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	1 971 -72Capital	- &apos;	0.5	1 .0	1 .0Grants	0.5	1 .0	1 .5	2.0Courses and Misc.	1 .0	2.0	U.5	6.0Total	1 .5	3.5	7.0	9.0SCOTLAND2.     Some provision has been made in the teacher-training programme for a unit in the West of Scotland and for one to be located in the East of Scotland but because of the demands on investment to provide basic teaching places this second unit has only a limited priority.    It is proposed that the planning ofin-service facilities be accelerated, and expenditure as followshas been included to cover the investment required, the maintenancecosts of the units, and the salary costs of teachers who areseconded for the longer courses:-
0.10.530Table 13 m.1968-69    1969-70     1970-71Additional capitalexpenditure 0.1 0.3 &apos;0.hAdditional current expenditure - - 0.2Machinery3(a)   Administrative action and rate support grant (England andWales).(b)   Grants from S.E.D. and rate support grant (Scotland).
Annex A7Addition to Further Education Building Programme (Q.B.)1.     The development of polytechnics and other specialist centreson the lines foreshadowed in Cmnd. 3006 should permit concentration on full-time and sandwich higher further education, hut residential accommodation would be needed on a considerably greater scale thanthe value of starts programmes so far assumed will permit.    Inthe early stages this is expected to he contained within the hasicprogramme up to and including that for 1968-69.    Thereafter extrastarts of  5m. in each of the three years 1969-70 to 1971-72in England and Wales, and projects worth nearly  1m. in all inScotland, are proposed.Machinery2.     Building programmes.31
Annex A8Additional Capital Investment for Snort andthe Youth Service (G.B.)ENGLAND AND wales.     Total expenditure on sport and the youth service is expectedto rise from  3.6 million in 1967-68 to  h.2 million in 1971-72.Capital expenditure (which accounts for some two-thirds of this)comprises grants to local youth and sports clubs for thedevelopment of their facilities and, for sport, for the provisionof national recreation centres.    The additional expenditure isproposed for these items, for the establishment of specialisednational facilities for some sports, and for the replacement oftheyouth service training establishment at Leicester.scotland .     The Secretary of State has been asked to make a grant towardsthe cost of the facilities required in connection with theCommonwealth Games to be held in Edinburgh in 1970.   No grantcommitment has been entered into but, if it is accepted that agrant should be offered, provision will require to be made for it.The amount of capital grant might he about,, 0.h million payable asfollows:-Table 1 k m.1968-69     1969-70     1970-71     1971 -72Grant for commonwealth Gamesfacilities 0.1 0.2 0.1Machinery3.     Capital grants from the Departments.
ANNEX A9Improvements to university &quot;buildings (G.B. )1.     On the basis of their capital survey the University GrantsCommittee submitted a case some time ago for building starts foreach of the years 1 970-71 and 1971-72 equivalent to over  h2min each year in terms of new cost limits.     The PESC basic programme provides only for the expenditure arising from  30mprogrammes (at new cost limits) for each of these two years.These programmes are likely to be fully committed to developing the new universities and former colleges of advanced technologyto economic size, meeting urgent obsolescence and providingminimal development at the other 26 universities.     An increase of 5m in each of the starts programmes for 1969-70, 1970-71 and1971-72 would go part of the way towards meeting the U.0.0*8assessment of their additional building requirements over thisperiod to replace buildings seen to be in the first priority for replacement in October 1967 and would take no account of subsequent obsolescence.Machinery2.     University building programme:    D.E.S. Vote.33
ANNEX A1QExtra Places in Medical Schools (G.B. )1.     The Report of the Royal Commission on Medical Education(the Todd Report), expected to appear early in 1968, will draw attention to the urgent need to increase the intake of medicalstudents if a serious shortage of doctors is to he avoided;    oneproposal is likely to he for the establishment of five new medical schools over a period of years.     When these are fully in operation the annual output of doctors from them is estimated to be about900.     The Commission has agreed that the provision of one newmedical school, on which work could start late in 1968-69, wouldbe consistent with its thinking.2.     The figures shown in Table k are for the estimated capital cost of this school and of another, work on which might start in1970-71 .    No assessment has yet been made of the additionalrecurrent cost likely to fall in this period:   a substantial partof the expenditure consequent on the Report is expected to be onthe new medical schools.      It is not possible at this stage toestimate the cost of other recommendations to be made in theReport, which are likely to include the expansion of some existingmedical schools.Machinery3.     University Building Programme:    D.E.S. Vote.3k
Annex A11The Open University (G.B.)1,     The scheme for launching the Open University set out in lord Goodman&apos;s Report of May 1966 has been approved in principle by Ministers, although no date has been fixed fbr its implementation.The scheme involves television programmes on B.B.C.2 building up from ten hours a week in year 1  to 30 hours a week in year 3 and subsequent years.    The main items of expenditure will be:Table 15 m.CAPITAL Frovision of UniversityCentre 0.hTwo Outside T.V. BroadcastingUnits &quot;        0.h5Total .......    0.85RECURRENT(When fully operational)    Television Programmes 2.0Radio Programmes 0.25Administration, etc. 1.25Total.......    3.grand Total.,    h.35(The figure of  1.25m. for administration takes account of theestimated cost of running the university centre and regional centres(premises and staff), viewing centres, and correspondence andtutorial support.     1m. was mentioned for this in the Goodman Report.)2.     The estimated build up of the expenditure if the scheme wereto be launched in 1967-68 is shown in Table 16:-Table 16 m.CAPITAL RECURRENT TOTAL1967-68 0.35 0.5 0.h1968-69 0.5 1.5 2.01969-70 - 3.5 3.51970-71 - 3.5 3.5
3.     The possible transfer of Open University programme from B.B.C.2to a fourth television network must also he taken into account.The White Paper on Broadcasting of December 1966 made it clear that until 1970 at least the fourth network would not be allocated; atthat time the claims of Independent Television, and the possibilityof using the network for a specialised service of educationaltelevision linked with the Open University, would be considered.If the latter course of action were taken, expenditure on the OpenUniversity by 1980 would be much greater than in 1970-71.Machineryk.    An announcement to go ahead, followed by extensive planning of both educational and broadcasting aspects of the scheme.36
ONFIDENTIALANNEX A12Implementation of the Robertson Report (Scotland)The Robertson Committee was set up to consider in the lightof likely development in further education what scale and organisa-tion of facilities were required for the professional training of teachers in further education.    The Committee&apos;s main recommendations,apart from those dealing with the pattern of training courses,involved the setting up of a training unit for further educationteaching and the release, by education authorities, of teachersfor training without financial loss.    If this latter recommendationwere implemented education authorities would incur additional expenditure as follows:-Table 17 m.1968-69     1969-70     1970-71     1971 -72Cost of in-service training of further education teachers       0.1 0.2 0.2 0.237
ANNEX A13Hostel Provision for Colleges of Education(Scotland)The Robb-ins Committee drew attention to the low proportion of students resident in colleges of education in Scotland and suggestedthat it would have to be increased.    Some provision for hostelthis has been limited because of the need to devote resources toteaching accommodation.   Expenditure as in Table 18 would enablebetter progress to be made towards reaching the Robbins recommenda-tion that residential accommodation should be provided for two-thirds of the additional students entering higher education.places has been included in the current building programmes, butTable 1 8 m.1968-69     1969-70     1970-711971-72Colleges of EducationCapital0.10.30.30.1Current0.10.238
confidential annex A 14 7 18MiscellaneousEducational Technology (G.B.)(a) The National Advisory Council for Educational Technology,running costs are expected to increase from the initialfigure of  20,000 p.a. to  30,000 by 1970-71 and about 50,000 by the mid-1970&apos;s.     In addition, promotionactivities and development work would involve expenditureof up to  200,000 annually by the mid-1970&apos;s.(b) Sponsoring by the Department of the production of teaching films:   annual expenditure, about  100,000.(c) The establishment and equipment of pilot local orregional library and resources centres for schools and teachers:    100,000 annually for some 5 years, beginningin 1969-70, is proposed.(d) A national library of recorded material:     100,000 annuallyfor the recording of B.B.C. and I.T.V. educationalprogrammes;   an additional  50,000 annually if closedcircuit television recordings produced by L.E.A.&apos;s and institutions of higher education were included.(e) Development of existing organisations such as the NationalCentre for Programmed Learning (Birmingham) and theBritish Universities Film Council: *  100,000 annually.Adult Education (G.B.)(a) Raising the level of Department grant to the -ResponsibleBodies (the university Extra-Mural Departments and W.E.A.Districts) and to the national associations concernedwith liberal adult education:    250,000 by 1970-71rising to some  600,000 in the mid-1970&apos;s.(b) A new capital programme for adult education (there is no separate provision at present), mainly for adulteducetion centres.39
(c)   In Scotland adult education baa not developed as muchas in England and Wales and an increase in current expenditure would be very desirable to give a boost tothe service.3.     Educational Research (G.B.)The 1967 P.E.S.C. forecasts provide for expenditure on educational research to be increased from just over  600,000 in1967-68 to nearly  750,000 in 1971-72.This is based on the continuation of existing policies, includingresearch linked with the activities of the Department&apos;s newPlanning Branch.     A greatly expanded programme of research in thefield of educational planning would be valuable.4.     University Computers (G.B.)Extra funds are proposed in 1970-71 and 1971-72 as an additionto the Flowers programme as now seen.5.    University Contribution to Local Radio (England and Wales)The B.B.C. have been authorised to set up 9 local radio stations on an experimental basis.     The recent White Paper on broadcasting suggests that the local university where there is one might be among the bodies which might make a financial contributionto the costs of the station.     The location of 7 of the stations isnow known:   all are near universities.     Universities might make use of these facilities largely for extra-mural purposes;   theycould also broadcast refresher-type courses for professional people,and make a cultural contribution to the general coicmunity.6.     Improvement of Education Authority Library Service (Scotland)There has not been a Libraries Act in Scotland similar to therecent English one and the service has not expanded in the same way.There is therefore scope for some increased expenditure for the library service provided by education authorities.tkOnAMBT TVHl ATfTlT AT
7.   Total CoatThe cost of these items is set out in Table 19--Table^miscellaneous;    (G-.B.) m	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72Educational Technology	0.1	0.3	0.6	0.7Adult Education	0.1	0.7	1.3	1.6Educational Research	0.1	0.2	0.4	0.5University Computers	-	-	1.0	1.0University contribution to local radio	0.4	0.6	0.8	1.0Increased Library expenditure	-	-	0.2	0.2	0.7	1.8	4.3	5-01+1
h2ANNEX B.1Charge for School Dinner (G.B.)1.     This issue is dealt with both in the present paper and in thegeneral paper about charges for services which is being prepared,on the instructions of Ministers.     The reason for this doubletreatment is that about one-fifth of the net savings expected to result from a substantial increase in the school dinner charge(i.e. to 2/6d) would be attributable to increased revenues fromthe higher charge;   the balance would be due to reduced consumption.Thus to a large extent the saving on this item would be due to a real cut back in the scope of the service.2.     In England and Wales about 4.65 million children take theschool dinner daily (68.4 per cent of the pupils present).     Thenumber and percentage have been rising steadily:    10 years ago the corresponding figures were 3*06 m. and 47.9 per cent.     InScotland the percentage of children taking a meal is 45 comparedwith 29 10 years ago.     The charge for the dinner is fixednationally and there are remission scales under which children from needy families (where the family income is at or nearsupplementary benefit level) get meals free.     In England andWales the free meals taken as a percentage ,,of all meals were7.7 per cent in 1957 and 7.1 per cent in 1966, although the total numbers taking free meals have risen from 218,000 to 330,000 over this period.     In Scotland the percentage of free meals was16.0 in 1957 and 17.4 in 1966f     numbers taking free meals have risen from 36,000 to 57,400 over the same period.     The presentcharge of l/- was fixed in 1957 when the cost of the dinner wasabout 1/lOd;   it is now about 2/6d and the cost (excludingcapital) of providing school meals in 1966-67 was about  72m.in England and Wales,  8m. in Scotland.     The estimate for1970-71 at a charge of l/- is  89m. in England and Wales, 9.4m. in Scotland.
3.     Since the charge has not been increased for 10 years it isnot easy to predict with accuracy the consequences of anincrease;   the margin of error increases with the size of theincrease contemplated.     Tables 20-21 give estimates for 1968-69to 1970-71, on the assumption that the charge is increased inthe autumn of 1967.     It is also assumed that remission scaleswould be modified to improve the position of the needier families.Thus with   an increase in the charge from l/- to l/6d a family with a gross income of about  18 a week and four dependantchildren, all taking school meals, might be required to pay forone child instead of the present three, giving a saving to the family of 7/6d per week.Table 20ENGLAND AND WALESFinancial Increased Revenue Reduction inff      Year expenditurebecause of reduced demand m  mTOTAL reduction assumed in net fallexpenditure      paynrs m1968-691969-70/6d   1970-711971-721414.515.51644.55.561819212210*1968-691969-701970-711971-722020.522.5231112.513.5153133363825*1968-691969-70m   1970r 711971-72111111.512242937.5423540495450*Some reduction in capital expenditure for the school mealsservice - estimated at  lm in 1968-69 rising to  4m. in1971-72 - would also be possible with a charge of 2/6d.
	Table 21		SCOTLAND	 m.Charge of	Estimated total reduction in expenditure		  1968-69	1969-70   1970-71 1 1971-72l/6d.	1.3	1.5         1.6         1.72/-d.	2.7	3-1         3-3         3.42/6d.	4.0	4.4         5.0         5.2 1              i4.     An increase in the charge to 2/6d might result in a halvingof the number paying for meals.     Savings from reducedexpenditure would progressively increase as a result of continuing rationalisation of the service to match the reducedoutput of meals.     The figures assume the completion of this process by 1971-72.Machinery5.     The Government already have power to vary the charge.From 1967 the 100 per cent school meals and milk grant is to be discontinued,   savings resulting from a higher charge in theautumn of 1967 would be taken into account in assessing localauthorities&apos;  claims for a rate support grant increase order for1967-68 and 1968-69 and thereafter in the next settlement of rate support grant in autumn 1968.     In Scotland there will not be ateachers&apos; salary increase in 1967-68 and it may not be possible,because of the limited expenditure which would be covered in theRate Support Grant increase order for 1967-68, to recover from theauthorities all the savings for that year resulting from thehigher charge.Uh
ANNEX B 2Abandon provision of milk (G B)1.     Local education authorities are required by statutory regulations to supply l/3rd of a pint of milk free of charge dailyto every child attending a maintained primary or secondary schoolwho wishes to take it.     They are also empowered to supply milk for children at other types of school.     Tables 22 and 23 showfor 1966-67 the estimated number of children in the differentcategories who take free milk:-Table 22 (England and Wales)Number taking milk        As percentage ofthose attendingMaintained primary schools 3,830,000 93.2Maintained secondary schools 1,640,000 60.5Non-maintainedschools 430,000 78.5Notes   Expenditure on school milk is estimated at  13.9m. in1966-67 (including  4.5m. in secondary schools),rising to  16.Om. in 1970-71 ( 4.8m.).Table 23 (Scotland)Numbers taking milk Percentage of pupils taking milkPrimary 431,000 91Secondary 222,000 812.     Savings could be achieved by withdrawing milk or bycharging for it.     The arguments against the latter are thatthe administrative arrangements for collecting the small sums involved would be laborious, and, unless additional aides were employed which would reduce the savings, the teachers would beantagonised.     Administratively withdrawal of milk would be preferable.     The medical case for retaining milk is stronger for primary schools than for secondary schools..    Assuming thatalternative arrangements would have to be made for 10$ of
of pupils who might otherwise suffer, savings would be asshown in Tables 24 and 25.Table 24	(England and Wales)		 hi.		1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72Primary schools	9-4	9-4	10.0	10.3Secondary schools	4.0	4.0	4.3	4.4Total	13-4	13.4	14.3	14.7Table 25 (Scotland) m.PrimarySecondaryTotalMachinery;1969-70	1970-71	1971-721.2	1.3	1.40.7	0.7	0.71.9	2.0	2.13.     (i)   Withdrawing milks   amending legislation.(ii)   Charging for milks   amendment of statutory regulations and administrative difficulties mentioned above.(iii)   Rate support grant.4-6
47ANNEX B3Postpone Raising School Leaving Age (G.B.)ENGLAND AND wales&quot;.     In England and Wales the effect of raising the school leaving age in 1970-71 will be to keep in secondary schools about350,000 pupils who would otherwise have left.    It is not possibleto recruit at short notice a large number of extra teachers to match the in-school number of pupils.   Whenever the age is raised,it will be necessary gradually to build up the teaching force inadvance.   The later 1960&apos;s are a period of relatively staticsecondary school population: it is possible to build up the staffing ratio to take the extra load in 1970-71 before the secondary school population   begins to rise again in the next decade.   Table 26 shows the effects of raising the age (i) in1970-71 and (ii) in 1974-75:-Table 26Secondary Schools (England and Wales)1966   1968   1970   1972   1974   1976Pupils (millions)(i) R.S.L.A.1970-71 2.8     2.8     2.9     3.5     3.7     4.0(ii) R.S.L.A.1974-75 2.8     2.8     2.9     3.1     3-3     4.0Qualified teachers*(thousands) 150     154     170     188     20?     225(incl. F.T. equiva-lent of p.t.)Staffing ratio(i) 18.6   18.1    17.2   18.4   17.8   17.5(ii) 18.6   18.1    17.2   16.6   16.1    17.5*Latest projection used for PESO 1967forecastsNote It is estimated that a ratio of 1  : 15.7is required to secure the elimination ofclasses over 30.
2.    Possible savings arising from postponement of the school leaving age for four years would fall under three heads:-(i)   Teachers:For the reasons given in Annex C below no savings areexpected by the Department.(ii)   Non-teaching Costs (other than training and salaries of teachers):Assuming a continuation of the present trend towardsvoluntary staying on, estimated savings, which begin in1971-72, are shown in Table 27 below,(iii)    Capital:The Department plans to devote special allocations of 119m. (starts) over the four years 1968-69 to 1971-72to the extra accommodation required for raising theleaving age.   The projects concerned would generateabout  i+i+m. of expenditure (including fees, sites, andequipment) in 1970-71.    If the age were not to be raised in 1970-71 and these allocations were cancelled the moneycould be saved.Machinery3.    Administrative action through school building programmes.Savingsk.     Table 27 gives the details of the savings, on the assumptionthat the incidence of expenditure would be similar to that forminor projects (those costing less than  20,000).Table 27Savings m.1968-69   1 969-70   1 970-71    1971 -72Capital30.743.543.526.2Non-teachingcosts /19.830.743.543-546.0/ Including school meals (at 1/-) and milk (est. at 4m. a year).
Kxtent of PostponementThe reason for assuming a postponement of four years is tove savings in capital expenditure in 1970-71.    There is noeducational argument for choosing four years.    There is no date in the 1970&apos;s when the staffing ratio would provide conditions for raising the age more favourable than those in 1970-71.    Itwould be possible to achieve some savings by a shorter postponement:the incidence of the additional non-teaching costs would be postponed and some rephasing of the capital expenditure would bepossible.General6.     Over the past two years essential advance preparations for raising the age in 1970-71 have been gathering momentum.    Someexpenditure on the acquisition of sites, the planning of buildings and curriculum development (including the retraining of teachers)has already been incurred or committed.   From the local educationauthority&apos;s point of view raising the age is not an isolatedproblem: it is part of the problem of dealing with growing numbersof pupils.   Plans for the reorganisation of secondary education and building programmes have been prepared on the basis that the agewill be raised, and to go into reverse now would lead to considerableconfusion and some waste.7.     Despite the marked increase in the proportion of childrenstaying voluntarily at school to 16 (from 18per cent in 1956 to 26per cent in1965) and beyond,&apos; the Crowther, Newsom and Robbins Reports have provided evidence that large numbers still leave at 15 who couldprofit from continued education,  including higher education.8.     The effects of postponement would not be spread evenly overthe country.    Compared with the national figure of 26 per cent,  theproportion of chose staying at school to 16 in 1 965 ranged from 17 percent in the northern region to 31 per cent in the southeast; the gap hassteadily widened.    To postpone raising the age would thus prolong8ocial and geographical inequality.
7 2 SOne immediate effect of the raising of the school leaving ageBritain about UOO,000 people who would otherwise have entered itin 1971.   This would come at a time when the working population is for other reasons virtually static.    On the other hand, thechange should make for a better-educated population in the long run.10.   In Scotland the effect of raising the age in 1970-71 asproposed would be that nearly UO,000 secondary pupils who would otherwise have left would be kept in the schools.    Some of thebuilding starts for the R.S.L.A. are taking place this year anda long postponement of the operation would, at this stage, cause a considerable disruption of the authorities&apos; plans.   A postponement of two years, however, would enable authorities to make up anyunavoidable delays and complete all their building for theoperation in good time.   Any postponement of the R.S.L.A. would,of course, help the build-up of certificated teachers.    Thefollowing table gives the likely saving if there were a postponement of two years:- -tin 1970-71 will be to remove from the working population of GreatSCOTLANDTable 28(Scotland) m.1969-701970-711971-72Capital savings0.51.5Reduction in non-teachingcosts (37,000 pupils in1.02.050
confidential annex BkReduce Expenditure on Further Education(England and Wales)1.     Further education courses are provided in some 500 technical-,and commercial colleges, 150 art colleges and UO agriculturalestablishments.    There are several hundred evening institutes (mostof which use the buildings of secondary schools during the evenings),In 1965 there were nearly 1.7m. students in colleges of further education, together with 1,25m. in evening institutes.     It isestimated that by 1970 the numbers will rise to 2.1m. and 1.6m.Expressed as full-time equivalents, numbers will increase from560,000 in 1965 to 750,000 in 1970.2.     Tuition fees for home students in general cover about per cent of the economic cost.    Students under 19 usually payno fees.   Students on full-time degree courses get mandatory awards;those on other full-time courses often get awards at the discretion of the local education authority.3.    Further education has been one of the most rapidly expandingsectors of the educational system, as Table 29 shows:-Table 29Outturn PricesCm.ay pa[estisiated)^Expenditure   1959.6o 1960w6l 1961-62,,1962-63 1963-64 1964-65 1965-66 1966-67 1067-681967^ survey prloeerentincluding*ard$ totudents)Pit&amp;l57.2 66.2 77.7 90.2 106.5 120.5 144.3 162.8 171.519.3     20.9     24.7      25.5      25.4     28.1      29.3      30.1      30.5
^     This expansion has resulted from the Governments acceptanceof the Robbins&apos; targets for higher education, the need to facilitate the growth of courses linked with industrial training, and thedevelopment of management education.5, Growth has been particularly rapid in the more advanced courses,as Table 30 shows.Table 30Expenditure on Advanced Further Education1959-601 960-611 961 -621962-631963-641964-651965-661966-671967-68Machinery6.    Reductions in expenditure would be achieved by -(i)   Reducing rate support grant(ii)   Reducing capital allocations, by holding back the starting of individual building projects.    This control is exercised directly by the Department.    But it would notbe possible without considerable dislocation to concentrate the impact of the cut on courses of a particulardescription because most colleges provide facilitiesfor a wide range of courses, the accommodation for whichis not readily separable.    To achieve significantreductions in expenditure by 1970-71, starts should belimited in 1969-70 to about  20m. compared with  31m.already allocated for 1967-68.    Table 31 indicates what52(Actual)14.2J16.8:20.hj(Provisional Actual 18.2J outturn prices&quot; M     22.7]27.6)&quot; &quot;     36.0](Estimate) 42.8](Forecast) 48.8*
savings would be effected &quot;by reductions of 5 per cent in bothcurrent expenditure (including awards) and capital expenditure.Table 31Savings in F.E. Expenditure m.	Current	Capital	Total1968-69	9.2	1.9	11.11969-70	9.4	2.3	11.71970-71	10.0	2.6	12.61971 -72	10. k	2.9	13.353
ANNEX B5University current expend!ture(G.B.)1,     The 1967 PESO returns include provision for universities&apos;recurrent expenditure on the basis of the cost per studentachieved in 1966-67, the last year oi the current quinquenniumrevalued in 1967 terms and increased by a growth factor of2% per cent a   year.   An informed analysis of the practicablelevel of recurrent grant over the next quinquennium (theacademic years 1967-68 to 1971-72) must await the examinationof the University Grants Committee&apos;s proposals for the quinquennial estimates which will take place during the summer.All that has been settled so far is the provisional amount forthe academic year 1967-68 -  11+7.5m.20     To enable a saving of  9m. to be made in 1970-71 thegrowth factor would need to be reduced to 0.h per cent a year.The saving would not, however, be presented in specific termsggiven the necessary absence of prior consultation and the block grant principle by which universities are free to decidethemselves how any particular saving can be achieved.   Thefigures given in Table 6 are a straight progression, but it isnormal in the Quinquennial Settlement to fix only the first and last years as bases and allowances must be made for adjustment of the intervening years.5k
ANNEX B 6Reductions In Student Support (G.B.)ENGLAND AND wales, Table 32 sets out the number of award holders in Englund andiVales assumed in PE3C 1967:-Table ,32 (England and Wales)NUMBERS OF AWARD HOLDERS ASSUMED IN PESC 1967Financial Years	1968-69	1969-70	1970-71	1971-72University undergraduates (E. &amp; W.) Colleges of education Further education (i) Degree &amp; comparable (ii) Others	132,000 98,000 33,500 24,000	133,560 101,500 36,000 25,900	134,850 104,200 38,700 27,800	136,170 106,700 40,800 29,300University Departments of Education	5,232	5,566	5,632	5,683Total	292,732	302,526	311,182	318,6532,    The award, based on a means test, comprises at the maximumtuition fees and a grant of  370 for maintenance,.   In PESC 1967public expenditure on awards is estimated at  89m. in 1968-69rising to  93m. in 1971-72,    (The rate of increase is slower thanthat of student numbers because it is assumed that with rising real earnings parental contributions will increase.)3,    Savings could be achieved by:-(i)   reducing the maximum value of awards by, say, 10 per centin real terms i.e. by not increasing their money value to match increasing costs.   This would be the most straight-forward means:    Table 33 below shows the estimated savings:-
Table 33 (England and Wales)SAVINGS AT.. 10 PER GENT REDUCED VALUE..J3EI  m1968-69 1969-70 1970-71 1971-72Universities	2.8	h.3		k	.4Colleges of Education	2.1	3.2	3.3	3	.4Further Education					Degree &amp; comparable) Other                    )	1 .2	2.0	2.1	2	.2University Departments					of Education	0.2	0.2	0.2	0	.totals	6.3	9.7	10.0	10.2	(ii)   reducing vacation element in grant.   The element in thetotal grant ascribed to vacation allowance could bereduced by  20, from  35 to  15 (or for students incolleges of education, where vacations are shorter, from 27 to  7).   With a student population of 300,000 it isestimated that this would give savings of nearly  6m. in afull year (full savings would appear in the second year).The complete abolition of the element in the grantascribed to vacation allowance would give savings ofabout  10m. in a full year,(iii)   parental contributions on the present income scales areexpected to reduce the cost to public funds of awards byabout  30m. in 1970-71.   The contribution is equivalent to30-33 per cent of the parents&apos; tax payments.   If this proportion were raised to about 40 per cent , beginningin autumn 1968, the savings by 1970-71 would be 8m.- 10m.   Amending regulations would he necessary.(iv)   loan schemes   It is already clear that savings from a loan scheme would appear within a reasonable space oftime only if the outlay in the initial stages were provided by the private sector, covered against risk bya premium payment from the Government which would be the56CONFIDENTIAL
only public expenditure associated with the loan element.The effects of two examples of schemes are outlined below.It is assumed in each case that the administration wouldbe entirely in the hands of a commercial organisation!that the Government would pay a premium of 15 per cent of the amount of the loan;    that repayment would begina year after graduation and would be spread over ten yearsand that the student population would be 300,000.   Theearliest possible date for the introduction of either ofthese schemes, which would require legislation, isautumn 1969J    substantial savings would not appearbefore 1971-72.   The two schemes are:-(a) in addition to receiving their present grants,students would be empowered to borrow each year theparental contribution assessed as under the existing arrangements.   By the third year this scheme wouldinvolve a total loan of about  30m. per annum.Savings (including extra tax receipts by abolishingincome tax allowances for the parents of studentsin receipt of loans) would begin in year   three and thereafter would be about  5.5m. per annum;(b) each student would receive an outright grant of  200per annum together with the right to borrow up toan additional  1h0 per annum.   The total loanelement would be about  h2m. per annum by the thirdyear.   Savings (including extra tax receipts) wouldbe about  1.9m. in year one,  3.8m. in year two, 15.7m. in year three and thereafter957
SCOTLANDk.    In Scotland it is proposed that about  130 of the presentgrant should be replaced by a loan, and that the banks shouidprovide Government guaranteed loans of up to this amount.   Theminimum award of  50 would, of course, be abolished.   No premium wouldbe payable by the Government, as banks would be covered againstrisk by a guarantee for students who defaulted in their paymentsor for whom payment was waived on grounds of hardship.   If sucha system were introduced from the autumn of 1969 the savings would be as follows:-Table 5U   (Scotland) ffi1969-70   1970-71    1971-723.3 5.2 5.UI58
ANNEX B7Public Libraries and Museums (England and Wales)ff/iPTTAL expenditure ,    The forecasts of capital expenditure on local authoritylibraries and museums in PESC 1967, which are similar to there-costed figures for PESC 1966, reflect the level of loansanctions shown in Table 35.Table 35Loan Sanctions  m.196U-65   1965-66   1966-67   1967-68   1968-69   1969-70   1970-71    1971 -725.2        4.7 4.5 8.4 8.4 8.4 8.4       10.52.    The holding of loan sanctions in 1967-68 and subsequent years to the 1966-67 level would produce over the four years 1967-68 to1970-71 a total of  18m: sufficient, as Table 36 shows, to covercertain important groups of projects.Table 36Projects Deferred  sicLoan sanction already promised for 1967-68Other likely projectsknownOther possible projectsknown costing over 50,000* each2.75.69.217.5*8maller projects are likely to be financed from revenue, forwhich starts of  0.8m. a year from 1967-68 are assumed.   the resulting expenditure is allowed for in the figures inTable 37.i 3.    Table 37 shows the resulting savings:Table 37  m.SAVINGS1968-691969-701 970-711971-722.93.63.94.7
^     guch restrictions would hold up some large projects, postponemuch-needed improvements and retard the provision of libraryservices in new housing areas.qttprTCNT expenditure      Por the purpose of rate support grant (R.S.G.) the government accepted estimated expenditure at an average annual increase ofover 8 per cent at constant prices on the estimated figure for1966-67.   For PESC 1967 a similar rate of increase has beenprojected to 1971-72.    Table 38 compares the PESC 1967 figureswith the recosted PESC 1 966 figures:-Table 38PESC_figures  m.1967-68   1968-69   1969-70   1970-71    1971-72PESC 1966(re-costed) 39.4        41 .6        43.8        46.3PESC 1967 43.3        47.1 51 .2        55.7        60.66.    There is a wide and growing margin between the two sets of figures.   The next R.S.G. exercise (autumn, 1968) could he used tofreeze estimated expenditure in the two following years at the1968-69 level.   This would yield the savings,  compared with PESC1967, shown in Table 39.Table 39Savings  m.1969-70 1970-71 1971-724.1 8.6 13.5Note: Even with these reductions the figures for 1969-70 and1970-71 would be higher than the re-costed PESC 1966 figures.This explains why an increase in expenditure will herecorded on the special PESC forms to he used for the civilreview,7The effects of such a freeze would progressively increase.Debt charges would he increasing, even on the reduced capital programmes psotulated above.   The economies which would he enforced
would hit first the supply of hooks and second the recruitment ofstaff.   Since a rising population would be making increasing demands on the service average standards would decline.8.     Very little can he done by library authorities to increase their income.    Small additional sums might he raised by increasingfines, charges for the reservation of hooks and for gramophonerecords, the hire of premises etc.    There are serious obstacles to the introduction of charges for the lending of hooks, whichwould be the only means of raising substantial sums: during thepassage through Parliament of the Public Libraries and MuseumsAct   196U   all political parties agreed that the introduction of charges would seriously reduce the use made by the public oflibraries and be both economically and socially unsound.    such charges are at present prohibited by law.Machinery9.    Capital:    administrative actionCurrent:    rate support grant61
ANNEX B8Other Scottish Itemspanhiption in numbers of uncertif lea ted teachers,      Tne General Teaching Council in Scotland has set up a working party to consider the problem of uncertificated teachers and there will undoubtedly be pressure from them and the teachers&apos; organisations to reduce the number of uncertifioatedteachers, especially as the supply of certificated teachers willhe improving.   Education authorities, however, might wish to retainas many uncertificated teachers as possible In order to reduce thesizes of classes and to staff particular black sp o ts.    If theRoberts Committee recommendations were implemented and if the teaching force were deployed to greater advantage about 700 of theseriously sub-standard teachers in employment might be replaced by 1970-71 .Reduction of re-placement component in the school building programme ,    A reduction in capital expenditure in the schools sector couldbe obtained by cutting back starts on the small replacement component of the programme.    There would be some difficulties in securing theappropriate reduction in expenditure in the years required, as purereplacement projects are very few and adjustments of the programmesmight require to be made to avoid affecting other needs.   savings of the approximate order shown below could be expected,- however,if starts in 1968-69 and 1969-70 were reduced from  26m. to  23.5m.Table UPgnu1 ?68-69    1969-70   127Q.-.7J    122 -Zg.0.5 1.5 2.0 1.0^eduction of grant to grant-aided secondary schools3.    An arbitrary reduction could be made in the amount of grantpaid to grant-aided schools where at present the maximum percentageof grant from the Exchequer is 60 per cent.   A cut to save  0.5m,in a full year would mean an increase in fees by nearly hO per cent.
g^fll and Recreational Expenditurell.    In this sector developments in recent years have been rapid and in the recent R.S.G. negotiations with the local authoritiesthey were proposing a rate of growth of about kO per cent between1965-66 and 1967-68 (from  1.1m. to  1.5m.) which was subsequentlyreduced to 30 per cent.    There is still scope, however, for savings on current expenditure as shown in (i) below which wouldsimply mean a falling off in the rate of increase rather than an actual decrease in expenditure.    On the capital side, localauthority expenditure on community and youth provision was estimated to more than double between 1965-66 and 1967-68 andthis expansion was designed to remedy the effects of inadequate and insufficient provision in previous years.    Some reduction inthe rate of increase would be possible, however, through controlof loan sanctions, to reduce starts, and make savings as in (ii)below:-Table k1gm.1968-6?,     1969-70     1970-71     1971 -72(i)   Current expenditure   0.1 0.1 0.2 0.2(ii)   Capital expenditure 0.1 0.2 0.263CONFIDENTIAL
1966	310	309	308	2971967	321	320	316	3051968	334	334	326	3151969	346	351	340	3291970	362	368	357	3471971	376	388	374	3651972	389	407&apos;	390	3801973	-	420	403	3941974	-	440	415	4071975	-	456	426	4191976	-	473	436	&apos;4301977	-	489	445	440Notes   No forecast was made in PESC 1965 for yearsafter 1972.2.    The improvement between PESC 1965 and PESC 1966 in the yearsafter 1968 resulted from an estimate of the results of the.productivity exercise in the colleges of education.     The PESC 1967forecasts take account of the latest available information onend-of-course wastage (the number of teachers who after completingtheir training do not enter the maintained schools) and, more6UANNEX CTeacher Supply (England and Wales)1.    Table 42 shows the number of teachers (including the full-timeequivalent of part-time teachers) in maintained primary and secondary schools forecast in PESC 1965, 1966 and 1967.     In eachcase the figures assume 111,000 students in the colleges ofeducation by 1973, the Government&apos; s present target, and no further increases thereafter.TABLE 42No. of teachersThousandsMarch    PESC &apos;65 PESC &apos;66 PESC &apos;67 formatforecast forecast--*  &quot;&quot;All teachers   All teachers   All teachers Qualified tea
important, on in-service wastage rates (the rates at whioh teachersleave the schools).    Recent figures have shown that the forecasts of wastage rates made in the Ninth Report of the National AdvisoryCouncil on the Training and Supply of Teachers, and used with smallmodifications for PESO 1965 and PESO 1966, were too optimistic.The PESO 1967 forecasts show a decline in numbers in the years 1968to 1972 to about, or even below, the level assumed in the 1965forecasts.     It is now estimated that the results of the productivity exercise will be more than offset by higher wastagerates.    The latest forecasts are still provisional (pending areappraisal later in the year), and, as always, subject to widemargins of error.3.    It is declared Government policy to secure the elimination ofover-size classes in primary and secondary schools (classes over 40and 30 respectively) at the earliest possible date.     This requiresstaffing ratios (excluding unqualified teachers) of about 1:26.3and 1*15.7 respectively.     Table 43 gives the latest estimates of staffing ratioss1966	TABLE 43 Primary 29.7	Staffing ratios (qualified teachers Secondary 18.6	only)1967	29.5	18.3	1968	29.2	18.1	1969	28.8	17.6	1970	28.0	17.2	Note:   This table1971	27.3	16.9	assumes the raising1972	26.8	18.4	of the school1973	26.5	18.1	leaving age in 19701974	26.3	17.8	71.1975	26.3	17.6	1976	26.3	17.5	1977	26.3	17.4	65
4     Table 43 shows that the staffing ratios required to eliminateoversize classes in primary schools will be achieved in 1974 butthat no further progress will be made by 1977.     In secondary schools the ratio will improve steadily until 1971 and then fallback, with the raising of the school leaving age, to about thepresent figure.     Thereafter there will be slow progress, but by1977 the ratio will still be well in excess of the level requiredto make possible the elimination of oversize classes and, indeed,little better than the estimated figure for 1969.5.    The new forecasts represent a severe setback to the prospects for improving teacher supply.     So long as this remains theGovernment9s primary educational objective, it would be out of thequestion to contemplate further reductions in teacher numbers.Indeed, there is in the Department&apos;s view a strong case for including some extra building starts (say    4m.) in 1971-72 as a first step towards a higher target of student numbers in the colleges of education than the current one of 111,000.     (Theexpenditure involved would be  0.2m. in 1970-71 - for land - rising to  0.9m. in 1971-72 and  2.3m. in 1972-73.)     But furtherphysical expansion would not significantly affect teacher supplyuntil the later 1970*s, and in the meantime * other ways of recruiting more teachers will have to be employed.6.    Table 44 shows, on the basis of the latest forecasts ofteacher numbers, the extent to which the 1967 estimates of expendi-ture on teaching costs in primary and secondary schools fall short of the recosted estimates made or implied in PESO 1966.Table 44Reduction in expenditure on teaching costs comparing PESC 1967with PBSCn^oTTrecosted) gu1968-69 151969-70 211970-71 251971-72 25**
**No forecast of expenditure for 1971-72 was made inPESC 1966.     The comparison here is with theexpenditure arising from the 1966 forecast of teachernumbers.67CONFIDENTIAL
confidential annex   DHigher   education the Government are committed to the Robbins principle thatcourses of higher education should be available&apos; for all those whoare qualified by ability and attainment to profit from them and whoffiSh to undertake them.   The Robbins Committee estimated in 1963*on the basis of their projections of the output of qualified schoolleavers, that 392,000 places (G.B.) in full-time higher education(universities, advanced further education and teacher training)should be available by 1973. including 218,000 in universities jand the Government are also committed to these targets.2,    Since 1963 the output of &quot;qualified&quot; school leavers has exceeded the Robbins Committee&apos;s projections!    and as an interim measure, plans have been made to accommodate in advanced courses offurther education the extra students (20,000 or so by 1973) who arelikely to be qualified for, but unable to obtain, university places.The Education Departments are now engaged in a reappraisal of theRobbins recommendations on the growth of student numbers in the 1970?this will take account of the latest projections of &quot;qualified&quot;school leavers, the distribution of numbers between the three sectorsthe comparative cost of courses both between and within the threesectors   and, so far as is possible, the probable demand for highlyeducated people.   An interim report should be available before theend of the year,3.   Until this report has been considered, it would be wrong to sethigher targets than those recommended by Robbins and, up to 1973.accepted by the Government.    But equally the Education Departments&quot;ould not regard any lowering of sights as justified, especiallyn view of the continuing need for more highly qualified manpower,he economies in further education in England and Wales canvassed
in the reduced programme (Annex Bk) would have to exclude bothadvanced courses, to which the Government&apos;s plans for polytechnicswill give a stimulus, and those associated with industrial training.The planned growth of the colleges of education is directly related to the needs of the schools for teachers and the recent deterioration in the prospects for teacher supply in England and Wales (Annex C)makes it necessary in the view of D.E.S. to consider further expansion.k,    The three university building programmes up to and including1969-70 have been announced at a total value of  93a. and most ofthis sum has already been allocated to individual projects.   these programmes will enable the new universities and the former colleges of advanced technology to build up their numbers.   Because only small sums will be available for the improvement or replacement ofobsolescent buildings in the older universities, the expandedprogramme (Annex A9) includes proposals for an extra allocation forthese purposes.   Any cuts in the approved programmes would furtherdislocate the plans that were upset by the deferment operation ofJuly 1965 (which had the effect of postponing the start of  15m.worth of projects) and increase the overcrowding which hascontributed to recent student unrest.   Severe cuts might make itimpossible to achieve the Robbins target for 1973.
in the reduced programme (Annex BU) would have to exclude bothadvanced courses, to which the Government&apos;s plane for polytechnicswill give a stimulus, and those associated with industrial training.The planned growth of the colleges of education is directly related to the needs of the schools for teachers and the recent deterioration in the prospects for teacher supply in England and. Wales (Annex C)makes It necessary in the view of D.E.S. to consider further expansion.Ii,   The three university building programmes up to and including1969-70 have been announced at a total value of  93m. and most ofthis sum has already been allocated to individual projects.   these programmes will enable the new universities and the former colleges of advanced technology to build up their numbers.   Because only small 8urns will be available for the improvement or replacement ofobsolescent buildings in the older universities, the expandedprogramme (Annex A9) includes proposals for an extra allocation forthese purposes.   Any cuts in the approved programmes would furtherdislocate the plans that were upset by the deferment operation ofJuly 1965 (which had the effect of postponing the start of  15m,worth of projects) and increase the overcrowding which hascontributed to recent student unrest.   Severe cuts might make itimpossible to achieve the Robbins target for 1973*69CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
