<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/35/24 images: 170-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at10Downing Street,.S.W.1, on Wednesday, 11th August, 1943, at 11 -30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Deputy Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.j,. -     The following tThe Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister-Resident at AlliedHeadquarters in North-West Africa(Item 4).re also present: .The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.
Contents.minute no      .                              Subject. page 1      India       .... .....      ....      ........      ....    223Co-ordination of political warfare organisations.2      U.S.S.R.....      ....   ......      ....      .............      ....    2233     Yugoslavia      ....      ....      ....      ............      ....    2244      Italy     ....      .... ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    224
It was pointed out in the Memorandum that under the Govern-ment-of India Act the Viceroy already had. all necessary powers ofcontrol over Departments of the Government of India. He had,however, no statutory powers over the agencies established in India,for purposes of political warfare, by Departments of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom, It was therefore suggestedthat he, should now be given specific authority, in his personal capacity and not as Viceroy, to settle on behalf of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment, by direct instructions to those agencies in Indiamatters relating to the conduct of political warfare against japan on which prompt orders were required for the purpose ofco-ordinating the functions of those agencies with those of Depart-ments of the Government of India. It was proposed that this authority should be given in the form of a Directive, the draft ofwhich Was reproduced as an Appendix to the Memorandum.The War Cabinet were informed that this proposal had thesupport of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretaryof State for War and the Minister of Information -though theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs wished to reserve for laterdiscussion the questions of the appropriate channel of communica-tion with the Viceroy, the need for a political adviser to be attachedto him; and the arrangements which, would be necessitated by theappointment of a Supreme Commander for the South-East AsiaCommand.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that the reservations which he had made were concerned with wider issuesaffecting the relations between the Viceroy and the Foreign office in matters of foreign policy in respect Of the Far East. He wouldbe glad if a senior official from, the Foreign Office could be appointedto the personal staff of the Viceroy as his adviser on foreign affairs;and, if such an appointment were made, questions would ariseregarding the channel of communication between this adviser andthe Foreign Office. He contemplated that, if at a later stage the headquarters of the SoUth-East Asia Command were moved outsideIndia, the Supreme Commander should have on his staff an adviser on foreign affairs; and it would; be important to preserve continuity,possibly by arranging that the Viceroy&apos;s personal adviser on foreignaffairs should at that stage be transferred to the supreme commander.The War Cabinet had some preliminary discussion of thesequestions. It was, however, agreed that they required furtherconsideration; and that meanwhile there was no reason to delay theissue of the proposed.&quot; Directive regarding the co-ordination ofpolitical Warfare activities in India.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Viceroy should be given specific authorityto co-ordinaie the activities of political warfare organi-satiohs operating from India.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for India to communicate to the Viceroy, on behalf of the War Cabinet, a directive in the terms set Out in -the Appendix toW.P. (43) 361. &apos;,2. The War Cabinet considered an exchange of telegrams between the Prime Minister and Premier Stalin:&apos;&quot;. A-record, of &quot;the discussion, and: of the conclusions reached,is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet
Yugoslavia;; .. r, - a- : 3. The Secretary- of State for Foreign Affairs said, that, as(Previous        his colleagues ;vyo^^Reference: Yugoslav Government. The King had dismissed his existing&apos;w.M..(43)87th Ministers and had appointed a new Government composed-,of conclusions, -.     officials.Minnie 3.). The Secretary-, of State for-Foreign Affairs said ithat hethought that the. King Would presumably now wish to go toxEgypt;in order to be hearer his owns the new Government. he assumed that, if ^We should concur in it.     * 1The. War Cabinet . &apos; ifEndorsed this view.Italy. :(Previous        .. Reference:  *W.M. (43) 113thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The War Cabinet were informed of the latest developments of the Italian position. A record is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1,11th August, 1943.
mm


</content>
</cab>
