<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/57/2 images: 14-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIA MJLJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT 7Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1944.SECEET. Copy No.    3W.P. (44) 602.31st October, 1944.WAR CABINET.RESETTLEMENT OF MEN RELEASED FROM THE ARMED FORCES.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service.1. In accordance with the undertaking I gave at the meeting of the WarCabinet on the 27th September, 1.944 (W.M. (44) 128th Conclusions, Minute 4), Iset out below a statement on the provision being made for the resettlement of men released from the Armed Forces.2. Benefits on Release.Men released from the Armed Forces under the general scheme for releaseby age and length of war service will receive eight weeks&apos; resettlement leave with full pay, ration allowance and, where applicable, family allowance, dependants&apos;allowance and war service grant. Payment will be made by an advance on theday of release, the remainder being paid at regular intervals. In addition, therewill be a further period of leave and payments on the same scale in respect offoreign service. There will also be an issue of civilian clothing the retail value.of which may be put on an average*at  12. Thus in the case of a private soldierwith a wife and one child and who has served five years, including three yearsoverseas, the total paid to the soldier and his wife during the period of leavewill be about  73. If he has had three years&apos; service with no service overseas,the amount payable will be about  41. These payments exclude any war servicegrant payable, the value of the civilian clothes and the war gratuity and post-warcredits. If these payments were included, the total amounts received in the two cases would be not l$ss than  143 and  98 respectively.There will be a number of men transferred from the Forces to urgentreconstruction employment after the defeat of Germany.   These&apos; will receive thebenefits set out above except that their period of leave will be three weeks only&apos;and certain payments will not be made until after the war.   These men will onlyform a small proportion of the total.The cost of the leave payments and civilian clothes is very roughly estimatedat about  300 million. In addition the post-war credits which are already beingearned by service in the ranks are likely to amount at least to  150 million. Ithas, moreover, been decided that all ranks are to receive a war gratuity, theamount of which has not yet been settled, but the total is not likely at any rate to fall short of  200 million.3. Reinstatement.The Reinstatement in Civil Employment Act, 1944, applies to all men whoentered upon a period of whole-time service in the Armed Forces since the-25th May, 1939. At the first opportunity at which it is reasonable and practicable,employers are under an obligation^ to take back into their employment formeremployees to whom the Act applies, and who make proper application when their war service comes to an end. An employer who has obligations to such an applicant must, if he can, offer him employment in his old occupation on terms-and conditions not less favourable to him than he would have had in that occupa-tion if he had not joined the Forces. If he cannot offer employment as described above, he must offer the best alternative employment, if any, that is reasonable and practicable. Where an applicant has been taken back into employment underthe Act, the employer is required to keep him in employment for the following26 weeks or for so much of that period as he can.   The period is extended to[28484]
52 weeks where the previous employment was a continuous period of not lessthan 52 weeks. There is a right of appeal to Reinstatement Committees for persons who claim that they have rights under the Act which are denied them.4. Vocational Training..Vocational training for an extensive range of trades will be given at Govern-ment Training Centres, Technical Colleges and specially selected employers&apos;works under general conditions as nearly as possible resembling those in whichthe person training will subsequently work. The training will be provided free of charge and there will be training allowances which will be increased if thetrainee has a wife, children or similar dependants. Additional allowances willalso be paid if the training requires residence away from home. The rates of allowances have not yet been fixed.5. Further Education and Training Scheme.This scheme has been designed to secure an adequate supply of personsfully trained to undertake posts of importance in the professions, industry(including agriculture) and commerce. Candidates must have capabilities andpotentialities&apos; sufficient to suggest that their training would justify expenditureof public money. The award to a successful applicant will be in the form of agrant for maintenance and fees enabling him to take the full course of trainingwhich he may need. The amount of the grant will vary according to his existing obligations, his financial resources, if any, and the length and nature of the courseapproved. In the case of a married applicant, a reasonable maintenanceallowance will be paid in respect of his wife and children, if any, subject to somelimitation if the applicant or his wife has an income. Under this scheme a married man with two children may receive, apart from the value of his fees, asmuch as  400 a year for three or four years.6. Interrupted Apprenticeship.In accordance with the general scheme announced to Parliament on the28th September, men and women whose apprenticeship has been interrupted by war service will, on return to civil employment, be enabled to complete theirapprenticeship- at wage rates commensurate with adult status and responsibilities.A time allowance will be given in respect of the period of war service so that theapprentice will not be called upon to serve the whole of the period of apprentice-ship which was unexpired when the apprenticeship was interrupted; also the timeserved by a person at his trade while in the Forces or elsewhere will be taken intoaccount. The apprentice will receive payment from the employer at a rate a little less than the journeyman&apos;s rate, and the Government will pay to the employer onethird of the latter rate. Tor example, in the case of a journeyman&apos;s rate of-845. per week the apprentice will receive as wages from the employer either 70s.or 77s. as appropriate, and the Government contribution to this will be 28s.Each industry will prepare its own scheme to fit in with the general principles set out in the schame that has been announced. The employer and the apprenticewill be required to enter into an agreement to comply with the conditions of thescheme for the particular industry.7. Resettlement Advice.Resettlement Advice Offices will be opened in every town in which there is an employment Exchange and will be staffed by specially selected and trainedAdvisory Officers. Their function will be to give every possible assistance by wayof information and advice to any persons needing help in settling down again in civilian life.8. Disabled Persons. &apos;   -The Disabled Persons (Employment) Act, 1944, contains provisions for -helping ex-Service men who have suffered some kind of disability and need specialhelp or assistance in their return to civil life. Courses in vocational training and,where necessary, short courses of industrial rehabilitation at special centres will beprovided free. A maintenance allowance with supplementary allowances for wife and children will be granted during the course, and all&quot;necessary travelling expenses will be paid.All employers with twenty or more workers will be required to employ a quota of registered disabled persons whilst, in addition, certain occupations which are regarded as specially suitable for disabled persons may be earmarked for them.
-special arrangements, can be made under the Act to enable persons to earn a living who would be handicapped by disability from doing so under ordinaryconditions. Schemes of this kind, which will be started or assisted by theMinistry of Labour and National Service, include courses of training andmaintenance allowances.The rates of maintenance, allowances have not yet been fixed, but under thecurrent scheme for disabled men the rates are 50s. a week for an adult singles a man with an addition in the case of a married man of 10s. a week for his wife andv   &apos; 4.9. for each child.9. Pension Rights.Pension is awarded by the Ministry of Pensions in respect of disablementaccepted as attributable to or aggravated by service during the present war. Therate of pension is dependent on the degree of disablement and the rank held in theForces. Where the degree of disablement is assessed at 20 per cent, or over, apension is granted; where the assessment is less than 20 per cent., a gratuity or a weekly allowance for a limited period may be awarded. If medical, surgical orrehabilitative treatment is required on account of the pensionable disablement, itis provided by the Ministry of Pensions if it is not already available from otherState sources such as under the National Health Insurance scheme. Artificiallimbs and eyes, surgical boots, spectacles, dentures and other appliances which arerequired as the result of war service are also provided by the Ministry of Pensions.In addition to a disablement pension, a claimant may, subject to certain conditions, be granted allowances in respect of wife and children, educationallowances for children and a special allowance if the disablement necessitatesconstant attendance.The cost of disablement pensions and allowances for Service cases of this war is estimated to be at least  20 million during the year 1945. This figurewill increase substantially in subsequent years, but the actual amount and rateof increase is dependent on circumstances which cannot yet be forecast with anyaccuracy.10. Resettlement Grants.An Interdepartmental Committee is now considering whether provision should be made by way of grants or loans to assist in the establishment in business or in work on their own account of ex-service men and others who had to give up their business by reason of war service. The Committeewill be reporting very shortly. It will also consider whether provision should be made for assistance in respect of continuing civil liabilities of personsreleased from the Forces, e.g., by the adaptation of the existing scheme of war service Grants.11. Summary of Cost.Any estimates of the cost of the above provisions can only be very rough andwill depend on the assumptions made, but the following summary will indicate the probable order of magnitude of the sums involved.(1) Estimates of non-recurrent costs.  (a) Benefits on Release.........     300,000,000(&amp;) Post-war Credits     .........     150,000,000(c) War Gratuities       .........     200,000,000(2) Estimates of Annual Cost.(a) Schemes of training and resettlement      40,000,000 (possibly falling to  30,000,000after 3 years)(&amp;) Pensions       ...      .........      20,000,000 (rising)E. B.(Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,31st October, 1944.




</content>
</cab>
