<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 2-2</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42 159th Meeting 26th November 1942

Beveridge Report on Social Services.

K.W. Publish Fr or Sat. Unwise to hold it up.

P.M.G. in statement to say Rpt. only just recd. will need careful consn.

A.G. unlikely to quarrel with that – and T.U.C. also want this for examn.

Whitely. No debate before Feb.

K.W. Rpt. to go to R.P. Cttee and thence to Cabinet.

P.M. Cost.

K.W. £100M. immediate (P.M. £86M).

P.M. If produced as part of post-war plan, wd. have figured largely. All these things have to be considered together. Finance can’t be left out of it.

Like this Rpt. but must see how it fits in to p-war plan as a whole.

Ought to finish Art 7 convns. with U.S. If we promise this largesse, far

ahead of U.S. standards, they may say “we are being asked to pay for

this”.

S/Doms. U.S. reaction may be good – they may be impressed by our boldness.

Hope we shan’t take too long in considg. on Dept. level – shd. come to Ministers soon. Well in advance of Feb. Debate.

P.M. Most serious reaction is on finance. Rate of Taxation.

K.W. These recommns. must be considered in relation to claims of other services on the money available.

A.E. Reminder, too, on publn. of necessary expenditure on armaments after the war.

P.M. Two stage ending of war. While we finish off Japan, after collapse of Hitler, there will be interval during which United Nations will go forward in companionship : and during that these plans can be matured.

L.P. When opinion crystallises, pity to let it appear tht. Govt. dragged reluctantly to support it. Cd. we not welcome it in principle?

5

P.M.&amp;K.W. Indicated some dissent.

M/Inf. Date. Tuesday because Front Line due out on Monday.

H.O. Wd. prefer Wed. from that point of view.

M/Inf. Agreed – Vote Office on Tuesday morning. Press Wed. a.m. – advance copies this wk. end.

Bev. to broadcast? – Agreed : after publication.

P.M. May I see W.A.J.’s formula for referring to this in his reconstruction statement?

Indicated lines on which this might be drawn.

6

</content>
</cab>
