<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 3-3</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42) 160th Meeting 26th November, 1942.

I. Man Power.

L.P. Gap 980.000 add. No exaggeration – some wd. say optimists.

Deficiency to be shared betwn. Services and supply.

Before balance can be struck W. Cab. must decide proportions betwn. 3 Services.

We cd. then allocate : and M/L. cd. settle intakes for early ’43.

No squeezing or pruning wd. materially affect the mass of the gap.

Cuts in Service wd. have some effect on supply demands.

If Navy ships succeeded only small man-power saving thro’ economy.

If we want max. no. aircraft, only economy savings in R.A.F.

Balance wd. fall on Army.

S/Doms. What conception is build-up for supply?

L.P. Scrutiny of Service Dept. demands is prcdg. I made cut of 150.000 in order to forestall suggn. that gap cd. be closed by those economies.

S/Doms. My point was capital or maintenance?

M/S. Our trend must be upwds for 4/6 months. After July ’43 our demands are only 5.000. First half only 67.000 [Correct these figures]

W.O. Capital equipment not yet reached. But communn. requirements already cut by 25%.

M/S. Switch of prodn. twds. non urgent requirements goes on continuously.

S/Doms. Have demands bn. cut in light of experience?

W.O. To some extent – but experience is limited.

L.P. You can’t affect supply demands for man-power substantially (without or) except by reducing Service strengths.

S/Air. We are short of men.

7

P.M. You have made expansion programme wh. isn’t being realised – prob. for lack of aircraft.

S/Air. M.A.P. told me tht. given men and tools bomber programme wd. reach 100% output by end ’43.

P.M. R.A.F. shd. be held back until aircraft catches up.

Army supply shd. be held back to equalise with Army strengths.

Navy must have their programme.

M.A.P. Key people shd. not be cut – or taken out.

M/L. a) Army is short of tradesmen. With co-opn. Supply Dpts I can take away less in total. If I can have a few highly-skilled men, they can train others in Army. This wd. be less injurious to industry.

b) Change-overs. Hope M.A.P. will improve on this.

M.A.P. Hope so.

P.M. Ammunitions for A.D.G.B. I wd. have no more than we had in Politz even tho’ no more guns.

G.A.F. not in posn. now to bring the same weight on us as in 1940/41.

M/L. Cd. R.A.F. Regt. not be used now in dual capacity. For Ground-staff.

S/Air. Of 75.000 – 25.000 = A.A. Gunners

25.000 = exposed Fighter Aerodromes

25.000 = training and oddments.

P.M. Navy Priorities – a) Anti U-Boat. b) Merchantmen.

L.P. Then, subject to small cut, give R.N. the personnel requd.

P.M. Wdn’t object to holding some vessels (not anti U-Boat) in reserve.

M/L. Cd. we at least confirm the figures of 1.6m. as maximum supply?

I must then consult with B/Trade and other Ministers.

L.P. Cab. shd. understand what this means. 500.000 of less essential industries.

P.M. Let Cab. decide that this is the target at wh. M/Labour shd. aim.

8

Agreed.

H.O. Have cut C. Def. by 1/6 (⅓ in N.F.S.). But shall need some more for replacement of wastage.

P.M. a) Blitz 1940/41 shd. be taken as more than worst we must guard against.

b) Parachute attack. We know now how little force they cd. put in.

Affects scale of airfield defence.

M/L. Cd. there be re-examination of demands for part-time service in Home Guard and C. Defence.

W.O. We are 1¾m. now : we are aiming at 2m and W.O. askg. for another ¼m. I can stop the last.

M/L. I wd. like to refrain from directing more people in.

P.M. Re-assess invasion risk. We shd. have enough warning to build up again.

W.O. Consider a H.G. Reserve. When trained, let him off subject to refreshers.

M/L. Since our victories, tendency to “case-up”.

Propose therefore statement on man-power shortage in S. Session.

House shd. know salient facts.

P.M. Certainly – when we have got nearer the end of our examination.

P.M. R.A.F. Total Squadrons.

My weekly returns don’t look anything like this expansion.

Bomber squadrons 61. in this country.

Fighter “ 96)

Coastal “ 40)

Army Co-op 16)

Oddments 6) 219

S/Air. Figures in Table X will certainly be fulfilled as at end ’42.

Admittedly 1944 is less certain.

P.M. 1st shot. 2nd shot.

9

-1 Navy 300 400

-350 R.A.F. 700 700

-450 Army 400 600

3rd shot.

Cut Navy 100.000 )

R.A.F 350.000 )

Army 450.000 )

S/Doms. Can’t we afford fewer Fighters vice bombers – as R.A.F. strength drops.

S/Air. Fighters determined more by overseas requirements than anti-raids.

P.M. Cdn’t night fighters be made dual-purpose?

P.M. In Torch. We prescribe 60.000 fighting men.

The nos. who went were 180.000. The 120.000 were tails.

S/Doms. These rear-ward formns. help the other Services.

L.P. Cd. Services and Supply Dpts say what they can do.

P.M. I will prescribe a task for you to work out.

W.O. Cd. the nos. be related to Jan ‘43’ onwds.

</content>
</cab>
