<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(42) 165th Meeting 7th December 1942

Foreign Affairs

A.E. a) Jews. Fresh massacre Poland. Small Powers pressg. us for declaration promising vengeance. U.K. U.S. and U.S.S.R. jointly. Considering this.

b) Mack recalled. Says story of our unpopularity in N. Africa is quite untrue.

Parade there – most enthusiasm for B. troops. B. national anthem.

Genl. Bettois at Gib : thought gradually work in others eg. Catroux. Darlan will go in end because unpop. with French.

Noguls unreliable therefore Morocco a cause for anxiety.

L.S.A. “Massacre” at Oran – any news?

A.E. None.

A.V.A. No news from Godfrey.

M/L. Jibuta?

A.E. Hope it’s going well : but no def. news.

A.E. Bettois “the mystic of Pétain was appalling”. Giraud 48 hrs too late.

P.M. Dangerous if this so handled tht. U.S. had to decide to ruin Darlan at all costs while we backed de Gaulle. Quite a risk of this.

A.E. If you are patient enough, there’s chance of bringing these people together.

Later on U.S. shd. employ some of these well disposed French like Bettois.

Keep on altering complexion of administration by introducing people well disposed to us until they say they can get along w’out Darlan – i.e. let French themselves remove him

Mission of M/Production to U.S.A.

P.M. Welcome home – bringing sheaf of a certain size wh. we’ll go into later.

19

M/P. Puttg. in memo. to supplement President’s lt.

My policy was to negotiate with Services, bring F.D.R. in only in deadlock.

Shipping – 27 m. tons for import programme only : other promises for help with mil. shipping needs.

Will Ministers suspend judgement on F.D.R.s letter until they see the whole picture.

Aircraft was most difficult. After v. gt. tussle, Arnold’s good will is behind the new agreement : based on 80% fulfilment of 80.000 combat aircraft. We will get our whole allocation if they reach 80% and a bonus if they get more.

A.V.A. Escort vessels. Principle 1 : 1 : 35 being observed in latest allocation.

Prisoners of War.

P.M. Stokes’ Ques. Propose to tell the truth – no time to consult them (ie for prev consultn. with Dom.Govts) thought matter was urgent.

A.E. Nuisance when we were waitg. for Swiss appeal.

G. say they will release our men for a week at Xmas.

P.M. W’out waiting for Swiss appeal – let us say on hearing of this G. offer we have decided to unshackle G. prs. – wh. we only adopted in hope of securing better treatment for our men.

A.E. This was made by Cttee. We have acted thro’ Swiss Govt.

P.M. We shall never get a better way out.

A.E. Will inform Swiss tonight tht. we propose to say this tomorrow.

Will draft statement for P.M. to make tomorrow after Ques.

20

</content>
</cab>
