<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 15-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(43) 4th Meeting 7th January 1943

I. Colonial Policy.

P.M. Referred to Halifax’s telegram No. 75 dated 5.1.43 – Hull spoke before consulting President.

A.E. Hull is extraneous – discussion arose independently of him.

C.O. When Hailey and Halifax saw President, the President said he liked the idea but not the word. He must therefore have known of the proposal.

A.E. These ideas discussed here when Halifax was last here.

S/Doms. And Doms. want some statement.

P.M. Time taken off the war in order to find a formula to gratify the Americans.

Why shd. we apologise? We showed the world a model of Colonial development.

Only criticism is that we haven’t spent enough in Colonies.

A.E. Or defend them.

P.M. Not so. When the war ends, we shall find we have defended them all.

L.P.S. This did not come from pressure fr. U.S. or Doms.

Gt. pressure here for statement of Colonial policy ever since loss of Malaya.

Halifax was over : I told him statement of policy was possible : he then mentioned it to Hull.

P.M. Pressure – yes, fr. fretful people not in on the war.

A.E. Smuts, who is in on the war, favoured it.

S/Doms. This may get U.S. in to share responsibility for defence.

C.O. I thought decln. abt. P. State (accompd. by clear statement tht. P. State remained responsible for adminn.) was reverse of giving away : rather asserting determn. to hold on to our responsibilities. I, havg. heard Back-Bench talk, believed tht. a decln. on these lines wd. be generally welcomed.

49

P.M. Why bring this up now : We are busy enough with the war.

If you do nothing, it will blow over.

A.E. What did Viceroy have?

L.S.A. Only the telegram wh. went to Doms.

L.S.A. While I object to tying our hands, I see nothg. in revised text of declaration to wh. I need object on these grounds. In fact, I think I can support the document.

A.E. I never liked Mandates Commn. manned by repves. of countries with no Colonial experience.

C.O. Togoland administered by Commn. more backward than Nigeria.

Gt. advantage in this that it assert “personal” responsibility of P. State.

P.M. Quotations from Ld. Croft. a) No tribute exacted from Colonies.

“The British Way” b) No restriction of access to raw materials.

A.E. Wd. you rather not re-define our Colonial policy?

Ld. Ch. This is not a decln. of B. colonial policy: it is of colonial policy in general : and analogous to Atlantic Charter.

C.O. I believe this is our right policy : not toned down to pacify U.S. opinions.

H.O. The Atlantic Charter is in v. genl. terms : advantage in this that it circumscribes the Charter qua Colonies.

P.M. V. well, w’in our domestic circle : but why hurry into any public statement or bringing in foreign countries.

C.O. Business considns. alone wd. force us into consultation councils eg Caribbean.

Advantages therefore in bringing U.S. in early.

L.P.S. These bodies will be consultative, not executive. What harm then if U.S. backed out as out of L/Nations?

A.E. &amp; L.P. This will rescue us fr. dangers of Atlantic Charter.

Ld. Chanc. Declaration itself – Paras 1-3 unexceptionable.

50

Pinch in para 4 “can’t be pursued without … co-operation betwn. Nations”.

C.O. But that is just what I want. Co-opn. with other Colonial Powers. E.g. in transport, regional consultn. is inevitable.

P.M. Delay the statement as long as possible and have proper consultation.

Doms. criticise.

C.O. But revised draft gives effect to their criticisms so far as we accept them.

M/P. Revise para 4. “The Parent States will ….. but the policy can ….. the more successfully ….. “

A.E. GB. U.S. and Dutch to sign.

P.M. What about the French?

H.O. No one to answer for that.

L.S.A. Ques. is wthr. this shd. be done unilaterally or internationally. If latter (which I don’t much care about) then there is no harm in this document.

C.O. I want it because of its position value.

D.O. Next step: show it to High Commrs. tomorrow.

Send it to Doms. with reasoned statement of our views on their criticisms.

Ld. Chanc. “Parent State”. Danger of its being used v. us. E.g. W. Indies don’t regard us as Parents. Will support argument “it’s high time you gave them up”. Why not use “Trustee State”?

Wd. also prefer not to speak of “equal status”. Lookg. for trouble of Dominion States in India.

K.W. Debate “equal status” – agreed and retain Parent x/

P.M. “Parent or Trustee”.

C.O. Danger of “trustee” is suggn. of impermanence.

L.S.A. Para. 2. “eventual aim”. Prefer “task”. Not a future aim for us.

S/Doms. Not “equal status and equal opportunity”. We haven’t achieved those.

51

H.O. “Purpose” – Agreed.

K.W. Delete “aim” fr. para. 1. Then stet in para. 2. Agreed.

M/L. Position of India. Don’t you leave her as neither one thing or the other.

L.S.A. She is neither. She is not a parent nor a child.

C.O. Will be determined de facto. If when the time comes she has in fact a strong economic or strategic interest, then she can come in to the Reg. Commn.

M/L. I don’t object to C.O. view. If that is understood, I am satisfied.

It is Amery’s memo that puts me off.

Conclusion:

P.M. We’ve given further considn. How do Doms. like revised draft.

This is what we now suggest.

Explaining why we don’t accept all their amendments.

Then come back to War Cabinet.

Give Doms. a reasonable time to reply.

P.M. We stand on W.P.(42)506, don’t we? (My re- definition of Atlantic Charter). Not denied.

P.M. More publicity (including films) for our Col. administration.

II India. Gandhi’s Fast.

L.S.A. G. like Hitler, finds his patience exhausted. His six months end 9/2.

Viceroy and Lumley recommend that he shd. be left free in the Palace (?)

Other courses wd. cause more serious trouble.

P.M. Why give way to h-strike by G?

52

L.S.A. Won’t do this with any other pr. The G. situation is, however, so difft. tht. we can’t afford to let him die in prison. Not my view but I don’t feel justified in over-ruling those on the spot.

M.A.P. He is such a semi-religious figure tht. his death in our hands wd. be a great blow and embarrassment to us.

Medical opinion is that he will die in 3 days. Only ques. is where he dies.

L.P. If you agree with Govr. he will certainly release him as soon as he begins to fast.

Therefore you have to take the risk that he bluffs you.

If you choose the policy of release, say now you will release at once.

M.A.P. Let them decide there.

L.P. But we must know what they will do. And I believe they will let him out at once : won’t bring him back if he breaks his fast : and wd. bring him back if he begins to agitate.

A.E. This will v. unequal treatment for him as cpd. with other leaders.

And this is clear reversal of our original decision.

L.S.A. It is. But are we to over-ride him.

P.M. Put to him the original decision and ask why he has changed.

L.P. I knew G/India wd. never stand up to this. That’s why I advocated his removal fr. outside the jurisdiction of the G/India.

L.S.A. Cd. we afford to have v. Executive reigning on this.

Position is difft. now. We’ve detained him for 6 mos. and we’ve beaten him.

L.P.S. That is argument for letting him out now. I wd. rather do that.

Simon. Ask Viceroy to reply – you have bn. shut up : Govt. have put this down : and we’ll let you out because we aren’t concerned about your power to do any harm any longer.

P.M. Let him out as an act of State, rather than an act of submission to G’s will.

53

I wd. keep him there and let him do as he likes.

But if you are going to let him out because he strikes, then let him out now.

Cab. feel v. strongly on principle of release because of strike.

Wd. prefer to release as act of grace because detd. 6 mos. and we’ve beaten him.

P.M. Tell V. we’re astonished.

When we locked him up we clearly understood no release because of strike.

If his release is essential, then as act of State etc. as above.

And get his answer before any further action.

P.M. to see the telegram.

III N. Africa.

P.M. We shd. work for this. I agree with sense of telegram.

54

</content>
</cab>
