<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 50-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(43) 55th Meeting. 15th April, 1943.

I. Agricultural Policy.

P.M. W.P.(42) 1013., tho’ not taken by Cab., shd. be regarded as approved.

On new memo. first ques. “what is the hurry?” If you begin these discussons they are bound to become public = … as in H.O. memo. We’ve said we won’t commit ourselves to Bev. Rpt., wh. will benefit many more people. “Will please the farmers.” No: they’ll take this &amp; then clamour for more.

M/Ag. In past ag. has bn. v. diff. to deal with. One of our main objects = try to guide the industry into acceptg. moderate post-war policy wh. wd. fit in with comm. policy likely to be desired. Gt. advantage therefore in bringing them along on this via havg. them to formulate more extravagant demands.

Proposed procedure = wht. Govt. have promised to do on Bev. Has accepted certain principles but reserved final decisions. This is what we want to do with ag. – reserving final decision.

Cost - H.O. has misconceived the £50 m. Doesn’t represent cost of maintaining B. ag. It = what it wd. cost to stabilise c/living, incldg. imported food. C/E has suggd it wd. be £20 m. I’m not sure it need be anything. Can’t estimate closely now diffce in cost of what we cd. buy abroad &amp; what we cd. produce at home .

Result of 2 yrs. work with Dpts concerned - incldg. B/T. &amp; Ty. officially.

P.M. Bev. argument - our hand was forced there.

M/Ag. This is right moment to get industry to agree to this moderate scheme. Commd. to some extent by statement of M/W. Portf. On 1/12 tht. Ag. Minrs. will begin discussions in early spring.

T.J. Political advantages in opening now. After the war, consumer interest will be more clement than now. More likely to reach now a common measure of agreement.

On 26.11.40. Govt. announced “healthy &amp; will-balanced agriculture” pledge - for long enough after the war to put

161

permanent policy into force. Multitude of separate interests - need for time to talk - can be non-commital.

P.M. Can they be non-commital.

K.W. At least consult Doms. first?

T.J. No. On some aspects at least we had better talk here first. eg. hill-sheep.

P.M. No danger of stopping that subsidy during war or for one year after.

T.J. Wd. like to talk with them about eg. Marketing Bds., canning etc.

K.W. Qua finance, no commitment until we review at the end with other claims. That is accepted. I don’t object to M/Ag. plan so long as no discussion of prices or money - &amp; I hope the Ministers wd. be v. careful about talking to farmers.

S/Doms. But the whole thing is based on prices + money.

M/L. At R.P. Cttee it was left tht. we wd. see whole picture after memo. by M/F. on distribution. Economies in distribution wd. enable the producers to get a better return w’out extra cost to Exchequer.

Are we to approach all these problems fr. angle of producer?

Cost of food distribution has increased greatly in recent years, esp. in perishable goods.

Qua M/L. wd. like to see another ¼ m. exmployed on land, as cpd. With pre-war. i.e. 1.25 m. via 1 m. Now = 1.1 m.

S/Air. You wd. be swimming v. tide of mechanisation.

M/L. No: mechanisation wd. increase nos. employed, tho’ they might be difft. in kind.

W.A.J. If you have discussions, with no money or acreage, what is left? The answer is principle of mixed farming together with close public control of farming operations.

H.O. Agreed don’t want ag. to go back to slump condns. Wd. like this discussed before end/war.

But a) not sure this policy is right. Needs further examination. Shd. we go for protective foods? Subsidies or concealed thro’ prices.

162

Difft. from Bev. because here you will be dealing with interests, &amp; powerful political interests at that. Therefore, we shd. make up our minds &amp; decide before we discuss.

b) haziness about the cost, W.A.J. Rpt. says cost = £50m. + loss on imported food of £36m. This together = initial cost of Bev.

c) P.R. Cttee set up for this v. purpose: priorities, competing claims etc.

Safer therefore to examine it in that Cttee &amp; get agreement among ourselves before discussions begin.

S/Doms. Dissent because gaps.

a) Money can’t be fixed until decided how much marginal land to be brought in: &amp; prices paid to many producers will mean excessive profits to others.

b) Can’t be complete policy w’out distribution.

c) Consider fr. pt/view feeding the people.

M/L. Nationalisation of land. Effect of dealth duties. If thereby you make it imposs. for landowner to carry out his duties or functions, you must do something. E.g. allow the landowner to pay death duties by surrendering land to the State. Serious about this because it stands in the way of a prosperous agriculture. The Land Commn. Method is a less honest method.

A/E. How will M/ Ag stand if he opens talks with farmers w’out liberty to take money. May find that he well get so far &amp; will then have either to ask us to authorise money or break off at a diff. time.

Cherw. Where M/Ag. says this is the moment when “they” will be reasonable – does he mean producers or consumers.

S/Doms. Whole basis = fixed prices. Wtr. they involve subsidies or not depends on world prices. But you will commit yourself to fixed prices.

M.A.P. You must be able to offer them fixed prices - that is the quid pro quo. If you can’t offer that, you can’t negotiate.

A.E.&amp;P.M. Both liked the proposals in themselves - but doubted wtr. time was ripe for talks, when war may go on for 2 more years.

163

No good talking w’out makg. up mind on propts. share to go to ag. Then surely we’ll be told ag. is ahead of Beveridge.

Last thing I want is endless buzz of ardent discussion of post-war problems - esp. when the war may come to a stalemate.

Farmers have a guarantee for whole war and 1 year.

Conflicts too with policy of filling the shop-window before pulling up the blind.

H.O. Yes - this must go to P.R. Cttee on priority.

And cg. Bev. Debate - trouble if ag. appears to be getting ahead in queue.

M/L. R.P. Cttee. shd. finish the work before any other Cttee. muscles in.

T.J. We wdn’t think of discussing post-war policy on marginal land - that is purely a war-time expedient.

S/Doms. But even post-war you’re proposing to make the less efficient land pay.

M/P. Rent looks after that.

T.J. “Reasonably good land” is our basis – not “marginal land”.

P.M. You needn’t give your fin. help by way of fixed prices.

M/Ag. Apart fr. ques. shd. I discuss with farmers, there is the ques wtr. we agree with this policy.

D.O.T. Dissented.

S/Air. Yes - soil fertility is not end in itself: nutrition. Hope those ques. will be discussed further on R.P. Cttee.

P.M. Mustn’t be rushed. Must see the whole picture.

K.W. R.P. Cttee shd. look at this again in light of this discussion. Then submit to P.R. Cttee on the priority point.

P.M. V. bad to bring these things out one by one. Must wait &amp; put out whole programmes, so that one may balance another &amp; one may rub the rough corners off another.

164

L.P. Studied on techn. aspects by R. P. Let those techn. issues be reviewed again by R.P.: then Cab. on pol. issues: then back to P.R. to put it into the picture.

P.M. Yes: discuss to max. among ourselves, but no discussion outside. That was trouble with Bev – premature public discussion.

L.P. Get far fwd. in our own discns because internatl. confces crop up &amp; we have to take premature &amp; hasty decisions ad hoc.

S/Air. This memo goes v. the small family farm.

</content>
</cab>
