<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/2/0 images: 61-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
W.M.(43) 70th Meeting. 18th May, 1943.

Widow’s Pensions.

S/Doms. Widows with dependent children - shd. they go back to Public Assistance when their children cease to be dependent.

M/H. If you did otherwise - difft. anomaly: 2 widows one with children no longer dependent the other never having had children will be treated differently. What logic in that?

K.W. This is inherent in Govt. decision tht. the special arrangemt. shd. be confined to women with dep. Children.

Cdn’t have provided for childless widow w’out providing same for spinsters.

L.P. We faced this when we decided that some widows shd. remain on Publ. Assistance &amp; tried to meet it by assimilating P.A. &amp; A.B. rules.

M/H. Title of Bill &amp; Fin. Resn speak of widows with dept. children. }

/x

M.A.P. Meet that by continuing benefits to widows once qualified. }

M/L. Need has to be re-assessed, certainly, but Asst. Bd. cd. do that. No adminve. Diffy.

Proposal is merely “once on Bd., remain on Bd”. Not to apply to widows who never applied for relief while children were dependent.

L.P. Nibbling at an arrangement wh. isn’t easy to defend anyhow.

S/Doms. Take a/c of feeling v. the Poor Law.

K.W. Must have time to consider, including x/.

Agreed: bring up again to-morrow, after Ty., AYL and M/H

have considered.

Parliamentary Secretaries.

K.W. Cttee (Ld. Chanc., H.O. and K.W.) apprd to consider salaries &amp; taxation of Junior Ministers. Read report.

a) Suggest I shd. ask them if they want it.

b) If a minority of decent men object to it, I wd. drop it – to

avoid unpleasant Debate.

H.O. ? All of us see all of them together.

193

K.W. Yes – no approach to Labour Party until near the time.

M.A.P. Is this enough to make it worth while?

Whiteley. Some Lds of Ty. are receiving less than salary of M.P.

K.W. This is not true at £1.500 p.a. It may be for those at £1.000.

A.E. Agreed - as at x/ under strict secrecy.

Agreed.

No record.

III. Ceylon Constitution.

C.O. Amendments in para. 5 made to meet views expressed by War Cab.

By altering to meet views here we’ve made it less likely to satisfy views there.

Ceylon Leg. meets again 25/5: resoln down in favour of complete post-war independence: feared that this will pass unless we make this announcement first. If we are to do that Govt. must have it this week. Cdn’t make the announcement after such a resolution has bn. passed.

L.P. Agreed - P.M. shd. be consulted first.

C.O. Govt. thinks it’s worth while to make this statement - tho’ I don’t put the chances v. high.

L.P. Reserved Bills reduced fr. 17 to 3.: &amp; control over domestic affairs is conceded.

C.O. This our last word.

M/P. ? Nec. to refer to P.M. - as his points are met.

C.O. Add to draft telegram statement tht. Cab. feel v. strongly this shd. go off at once. To make it clear “now or never”: no use trying it later

Agreed.

IV. Mr Gandhi’s Request to see Mr. Jinnah.

L.S.A. Disagree with Viceroy for following reasons –

194

a) Can’t let those 2 meet w’out admitting logical consequence that the Working Cttee &amp; Jinnah’s people would have to see G.

G. is doing this only because stock has fallen. It wd. fall further if we refused &amp; let that be known.

This is 3rd try-on: rebellion: fast: now this.

b) U.S. touchy about Phillips have accepted that decision on basis tht. no one is being allowed to see G.

c) Snub to Jinnah will be good thing.

d) Difficult to insert our condns later. We must stipulate those before we allow these 2 to meet.

Recommend therefore action as in para. 7 of memo. –

informing G. &amp; J. of reasons.

S/Doms. Welcome every effort by Hindu &amp; Moslem to settle their differences, but can’t do it on G’s present policy. He must recant before he can be allowed to start.

M.A.P. Care how to turn this down, if you do. Refusal to let leaders meet will be misinterpreted. Extremely careful public statement must be made at once if you’re going to refuse.

My view = only safe ground: you can’t allow G. to communicate with anyone until posn. &amp; policy of Congress has bn. cleared. If he repudiates his policy, you will then be forced to let him converse etc.

W.O. Indeed, release him.

Simon. G. interned for security. Inconsistent with that to allow him to have series of mtgs. with various people. If he is allowed to write to, &amp; then interview Jinnah, where will you stop.

H.O. Took the same view. He is in because it isn’t safe to let him out.

Then it isn’t safe to let him start pol. conversations inside.

L.S.A. This merges with the other – take the line tht. this can’t be allowed until Congress recants.

L.P. &amp; W.O. Base decision on his policy.

W.O. Precedent. After 1931 Civil Disobedience campaign Willingdon refused to see G. until Congress had recanted. 195

Draft telegram to Viceroy to be considered by War Cab.

to-morrow.

196

</content>
</cab>
