<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/51/21 images: 245-250</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cm(?3) 20thConclusionsCOPY NO    5CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onMONDAY 2 APRIL 1973at 5. 00 pmPRESEN TThe Rt Hon Edward Heath mp prime minister the Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone The Rt Hon Anthony Barber mp lord Chancellor Chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Lord carrington secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Prior mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Geoffrey Rippon QC mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Robert Carr mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Sir Keith Joseph mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher mp secretary of State for Education and science the Rt Hon Gordon Campbell mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon The Earl JeUicoeLord Privy seal the Rt Hon Maurice Macmillan mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Peter Walker mp secretary of State for Trade and industry the Rt Hon Peter Thomas QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Joseph Godber mp minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Rt Hon Sir Goeffrey Howe QC mp minister for Trade and Consumer Affairs
1THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO present mr Paul Channon MP Mr Patrick Jenkin mp minister for Housing and Constiuction Chief Secretary, treasury the Rt Hon Francis Pym mp parliamentary Secretary, TreasurySECRETARIATMr J J B hunt mr P benner mr R L BaxterSUBJECThousing -potaeY411
The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of State forthe Home Department (CP(73) 46) reporting the conclusions of the ministerial group on land and house prices (GEN 148).    They also had before them a memorandum by the Secretary of State for the environment (CP(73) 45) on the financial implications of thepropo sal s0THE HOME SECRETARY said that in paragraph 23 of the white paper on the second stage of the programme for controllinginflation (Cmnd 5205) the Government had undertaken to bring forward proposals to increase the availability of building land and reduce the extent to which disproportionately high profitscould be made from transactions in land.    The Ministerial group which had been set up under his chairmanship to consider the matter had however  ound it inevitable that they should review the whole ofpolicy in the field of land and housing.    Their recommendations fellunder six headings -i. Stabilisation of mortgage funds.    This was to bediscussed by the Cabinet at their next meeting.ii. Supply of building land.    The group had producedfour main proposals: first, new guidelines for developmentcontrol should establish a general presumption in favour of housing development, unless there were serious planningobjections;  secondly, land should be made available for housing in certain limited parts of Green Belt areas wherethere would be no loss of amenity; thirdly, there should belegislation to make possible the increased use of partnershipschemes between local authorities and private enterprise;fourthly, developers should pay a share of the cost ofproviding essential services.iii. Land hoarding charge.    The intention to introduce a land hoarding charge had already been announced by theChancellor of the Exchequer,    A point for decision was whether the charge should be deductible for tax purposes.The majority view in the group was that it should not.iv. Voluntary housing movement.    The housing corporation and the National Building Agency shouldbe reorganised and strengthened.    This was the mainarea of additional expenditure,v. Local authorities.    The Government should continueto encourage local authorities to build for rent where necessary, to carry on with slum clearance and to sellcouncil houses;  and should also encourage them to buildhouses specifically for sale.
vi0       Improvements.    After mid-1974s when the existing arrangements for improvement grants, which had largelybeen designed to create employment in development areas,,would come to an end, there should be a revised policydesigned to concentrate resources in housing stress areas.The Secretary of State for the Environment would find the netadditional cost of the proposals from within his Departmentsexisting allocations, largely by reductions in expenditure on trunk roads and miscellaneous local services; and corresponding savings would be found by the Secretaries of State for Scotland and for Wales.In the time available, it had not been possible to work out theproposals in full detail;  but he was confident that they could be presented in a White Paper in a form which, although somewhatgeneral, would appeal to public opinion and help to create confidence in the building industry.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that he did not wishto object to the proposals on merits.    On the other hand he could not agree to any further significant net public expenditure,and he was obliged, therefore, to stipulate that the proposals, if accepted, must be financed by specific savings in expenditure.This must apply also to the proposed expenditure in Scotland andWales.    To the extent that the savings envisaged did not materialise,the proposals should not be proceeded with.    Furthermore this shift of priorities within the programmes for which the Secretary of Statefor the Environment was responsible necessarily reduced his ability to contribute to the general savings on public expenditure,, and would thus place a greater obligation on other spending Ministers.The following points were made in discussion of the financial implications of the proposals -a. There was a particular difficulty in Scotland arisingout of the assurance that the Government had given, to supportthe&apos;developmelit&quot;Tirf&apos;&quot;North Sea gas and oil, that there would beincreased expenditure on the improvement of trunk roads,ports and the infrastructure generally.    It would be politically difficult to cut these programmes, and necessaryin consequence to look elsewhere for the savings.Similarly in Wales it might also be necessary to findsavings in different fields than those proposed for England,b. The proposed cuts in the expenditure of theDepartment of the Environment, particularly that on roads, would pre-empt one of the main possibilities for reconstitution of the contingency reserve and? asthe Chancellor of the Exchequer had indicated, wouldmake it more likely that cuts would have to fall on other
programmes.    Some of these were highly sensitive, and itwas arguable that the Government should not restrict its freedom of manoeuvre in this way without fuller knowledgeof what would be involved.c.        The major item of expenditure, apart from theproposals for mortgage finance which were to be consideredthe following day, arose out of the proposal for expanding the role of the voluntary housing movement.    comparatively little of that expenditure would fall in 1973-74 and 1974-75and the question arose whether it was necessary at this stagefor the Government to commit themselves to the heavy expenditure proposed for the subsequent years.In further discussion it was argued that the Government wouldbe very severely criticised if they allowed the level of housebuilding to fall substantially.    The proposals in the paper were expressed in too general terms to make much impact, and few of them were calculated to secure short-term results.    In the short run it seemed likely that land prices would continue to rise;speculators would continue to make high profits; and the Governmentwould bear the blame.    It was suggested that too many three-bedroomed houses were occupied by elderly coup.les, who shouldbe provided with more suitable accommodation, so that the largerhouses could be used by these who most needed them.    Attentionought also to be given to the substantial hardships borne by youngmarried couples who were forced into expensive furnished accomodation, but who would be glad to buy if accommodation of the right size and price were available.    More ought to be done to encourage the conversion of large properties for the use of twoor more families, since this was one of the few courses of accionthat could yield quick results.    So far as the land hoarding charge was concerned, if it was based on the value of the land when the planning permission was granted, a subsequent steep rise in thevalue could make the charge ineffective as a deterrent^ and fromthat point of view there might be merit in basing it on a currentvaluation.    Finally it might be desirable to say something in theWhite Paper about the problem of empty office accommodation,which was linked in the public mind with the housing shortage.On the other hand it was argued that housing was a field in whichit was not possible to secure dramatic short-term results.    Thecurrent rate of private building starts was the highest achievedsince the war, and (leaving aside the question of mortgage finance)it would not be unduly difficult to ensure that they did not fall back.The steps now proposed were all in the right direction and most ofthem could be taken without legislation.    It was urgently necessaryto set them in motion as quickly as possible.
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that therewas no doubt about the political importance of housing and the need to maintain the impetus of the housebuilding programme.    Theproposals for mortgage finance would be considered at the meetingthe following day and a draft White Paper should be circulated to show the remaining proposals in more detail.    The Cabinet were broadlyin agreement with the proposals for increasing the supply of land,although it would be important to show that the use of Green Beltland would have little effect on amenity and also that larger areas were being added to the Green Belts,    It would also be necepsaryto consider further the basis of the land hoarding charge.    As regardsthe proposals for housing, the alternatives were to maintain the levelof starts in the private sector at roughly its present high level or totake steps to increase it even further by expanding the role of the voluntary housing movement.    It would be worth considering further whether the second course could be taken without committing theGovernment at this stage to the high levels of expenditure envisagedfor the years 1975-78.    It might also be useful to consider whether,from the expenditure point of view, the stabilisation of mortgagefinance and the expansion of the housing programme could beregarded as alternatives; and, if they could, which merited thegreater priority.    If it were decided that the housebuildingprogramme should be expanded, it would be necessary to take account of the limited capacity of the construction industry;  andthis might call for compenrating reductions, on a selective basis,of other types of new building requiring broadly similar skills and resources.    This was something which should if necessary beconsidered by the Secretaries of State for the Environment andfor Employment,    These, however, were matters to which it wouldbe necessary for the Cabinet to return in the light of their forth-coming discussion about mortgage finance.The Cabinet -L, Took note, with approval^ of the summing upof their discussion by the Prime Minister.2.        Invited the Secretary of State for the Environmentto circulate a revised draft of the White Paper on thefollowing day,3,        Invited the Secretary of State for the Environment,In consultation with the Chief Secretary, Treasury, toconsider the basis of the land hoarding charge.Cabinet Office3 April 1973

</content>
</cab>
