<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/34/39 images: 336-347</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT----- 164Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1943.SECRET. Copy No.      3 3.       .    - yW.P. (43) 89.March 1, 1943.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.INDIA&apos;S WAR EFFORT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.AT the beginning of last year I circulated for the information of mycolleagues a survey (W.P. (42) 54) of progress in the development of the Indianwar effort since the beginning of the war. The attached memorandum surveysthe further progress made during 1942, under two heads : (1) the Armed Forces;(2) Supply and Munitions.L. S. A.India Office, March 1, 1943.I.-EXPANSION OF THE ARMED FORCES.Situation on the Entry of Japan into the War.IN December 1941 the Army in India had an over-all strength of some600,000 men, British and Indian. In addition, Indian Army units totallingapproximately 300,000 had been despatched to overseas theatres. This figureincluded two divisions in the Middle East, three divisions in Iraq, two weakdivisions in Malaya and two Infantry Brigade Groups in Burma, as well as alarge number of L. of C. and Base units for the maintenance of these formationsand protection of the lines of communication. India&apos;s overseas forces were infact at this time Larger than those of any other country of the British Empire.2. Of the 600,000 men of the Army in India, however, more than 50 percent, were recent recruits still undergoing recruit training at the various training-centres, whilst some 150,000 were occupied in their peace time duties of watchand ward on the North West Frontier and Internal Security duties within India.The only field formations in India itself were three divisions undergoing training and three further divisions in process of formation, but consisting of little morethan the infantry battalions and entirely lacking artillery and practically alladministrative units. Of the three more or less complete Indian divisions, one,the 17th, was the only one which had anything like completed its training, andit had been offered to the War Office and earmarked as general reserve for despatch to an overseas theatre as required. Two of its brigades were in factdespatched to Malaya within the month and the balance of the division to Burmaduring January 1942. Furthermore, India had during 1941, in response to urgentdemands, despatched all her available administrative units overseas, so that atthat time there were literally no base and L. of C. units available to maintainany field army divisions in the field in India. Further heavy calls for adminis-trative units for Malaya were complied with during December, and over 2,000[25102] B
infantry reinforcements were also sent there for the two Indian divisions whichhad borne the brunt of the early fighting in Malaya, The total number of A. Aguns in India was eight, of which four were despatched in January for thedefence of Rangoon.3. The equipment situation was equally serious. None of the divisions inIndia, with the exception of 17th Indian Division, had more than a tiaining scale of any weapons except rifles. There were practically no Anti-Tank rifles at allin India, very little anti-gas equipment and practically no steel helmets. as mentioned above, artillery was extremely short and the field artillery was stillarmed almost entirely with the obsolete 18-p.rs. and 4-5-inch Howitzers. Signalequipment, and particularly wireless, was also practically entirely lacking. Thisshortage of equipment not only prevented the equipment of any divisions foractive operations, but also seriously retarded the training of the divisionsthemselves.Situation at the beginning of March 1942.4. By the beginning of March 1942 Singapore and Rangoon had bothfallen. Before the fall of Rangoon two further Indian Infantry Brigades drawn from the 14th Indian Division had been sent as reinforcements to Burma as wellas most of the administrative units raised in India during January and February.The 34th Indian Division, less one Brigade Group, had been despatched to Ceylon.Very little had. therefore, been done to provide any backing of administrative units for a field army for the defence of India itself. The divisions in India atthe beginning of March were as follows (all Indian) : -14th less one Inf. Bde. Gp..) More or less complete in artillery and23rd complete )    administrative units.19th 1 forming, but consisting of little except Infantry Battalions,With the fall of Rangoon and shortly afterwards of the Andaman Islands, ceylon and the whole Fast and North-East coasts of India were open to Japanese attack,a coastline as long as from Hamburg to Gibraltar. It was obvious that theavailable troops were insufficient to protect the whole of this vast coastline, and itwas, therefore, decided to concentrate what, troops there were available for thedefence of the two most vital areas, Ceylon and Bengal.5. India*s situation at this time was in fact somewhat similar to the positionof the United Kingdom after Dunkirk. Well trained troops were scarce andequipment scarcer still. In the air the situation was equally&apos; bad owing to demands of an even higher priority elsewhere on the still limited R.A.F. resources and to the length of time which it takes to move reinforcements to India. Ceylonindeed had 2^ fighter squadrons equipped with Hurricanes, but for the defenceof Eastern India there were only two fighter squadrons, equipped with obsoleteAudax aircraft. Anti-Aircraft guns and reinforcements of Anti-Aircraftregiments were beginning to arrive from the United Kingdom, and the grounddefences of Ceylon were now beginning to take shape. * The Calcutta area,however, was still practically defenceless.6. By denuding the defences of the North-West Frontier of all reserves a force was concentrated in the East of India consisting of- 23rd Indian Division.14th Indian Division less one brigade.Three Independent Brigade Groups,and sufficient administrative units were scraped together to give this force alimited mobility which it was hoped would be sufficient for defensive operations.During the month of March welcome reinforcements arrived in the shape of the70th British Division, less one brigade group, from the Middle East, and this wasadded to Eastern Army and retained by the Army Commander as his reserve.At the same time the defences of Ceylon were increased by the addition of thethird brigade of the 70th Division, one East African Brigade and two Australianbrigades, giving a total force in Ceylon comparable to two full divisions.Situation at the end of May 1942.7. By the end of May the Japanese had to all intents and purposes completed the occupation of Burma. Except for a small number of administrative units andsome battalions of the Burma Frontier Force recruited from Indians, most ofthe indigenous units of the Army had ceased to exist.   The 17th Indian Division
and1 2nd Burma Division (composed largely of British and Indian units) with,battalions in many cases reduced almost to cadres and lacking all vehicles and90 per cent, of their equipment had crossed, over into Assam, where they were,being collected under the cover of the 23rd Indian Division holding an outpostline on the Assam-Burma frontier. The 17th Indian and 2nd Burma (laterrenamed 39th Indian) Divisions required a long rest and complete refittingbefore they could be fit for active operations again.8. On the other hand, substantial reinforcements had begun to reach india from the United Kingdom, while a steady stream of equipment had commencedto arrive from the United Kingdom and North America. The 5th british division, less one brigade left in Madagascar, arrived towards the end of May,and after a short stay in Poona was moved to join the 70th Division in EasternArmy reserve at Ranchi. Reinforcements of Field, Anti-Tank and A.A. Artilleryhad arrived and more were on their way from the United Kingdom, whileredoubled efforts had been made to increase the numbers and rate of raising ofnew Indian artillery units. Furthermore, with the arrival of long-neededequipment, it had been possible to bring the following Indian divisions up toa stage nearing completion, although the infantry were still equipped withweapons on a scale roughly 50 per cent, of what they should have had :  Eastern A rmy 14th Division.23rd Division.26th Division. (A static division formed for the defence of the Calcuttadistrict from three brigades brought from the reserve for the North-West Frontier.)Southern Army \u^t ^-V-011 X But both still short of artillerv and signals.20th Division j &amp;Ceylon 34th Division.16th Infantry Brigade (from 70th Division).21st East African Brigade.Two Australian brigades. &apos;The A.A. defences of Ceylon had been still further strengthened and some A.A.ground defences had also been provided for Calcutta and the surroundingindustrial areas and for the Assam oil-field. None of the divisions, however,had a light A.A. regiment, which is included in their organisation.9. The immediate threat to Ceylon and Southern India by sea invasion had,moreover, decreased owing to the breaking of the monsoon and to considerableJapanese naval losses in the Pacific war zone. Furthermore, the monsoonprecluded any invasion of Assam before October and made extremely difficult any japanese offensive operations along the coast of Eastern Bengal towardsChittagong and Calcutta. As events turned out, the Japanese offensive operations against India ceased with the breaking of the monsoon, and it soon became apparent that the Japanese had reduced their air forces in Burma considerably.India was thus left with a period of four or five months to build up her forces,before any further active operations took place.Situation in October 1942.10. During the next four months very considerable progress was made withthe arming, equipping and training of field formations in India, and also in the raising of additional administrative units for their maintenance. By thebeginning of October sufficient administrative units had been raised and trainedto provide the Eastern Army, which now consisted of one British and five indian divisions plus one Tank Brigade equipped with Valentine tanks, with thenecessary mobility for active operations. In the Southern Army, the 19th indian division was approaching readiness for war, and the 25th Indian Division, whichhad replaced the 20th Indian Division when- the latter relieved the AustralianDivision in Ceylon, had been nearly completed with units and were hard at worktraining. In addition, the 2nd British Division arrived, and was concentratedfor G.H.Q. reserve at Poona, the 5th British Division in the meantime having. .  [25102] b 2
moved on to Iraq. The R.A.F. had also received invaluable reinforcements, andin conjunction with the 10th united States Air Force had commenced offensive operations against the Japanese in Burma. Japanese retaliation up to the endof October had been limited to a few raids against our aerodromes in NorthernAssam.11. While, therefore, the situation regarding the defence of India hadimmeasurably improved, much still remained to be clone before offensive operations against the Japanese in Burma on any large scale could be undertaken. Althoughsufficient administrative units had been raised to provide for an active defenceof India itself, the great variety of units necessary for offensive operations was still lacking and, furthermore, very large quantities of equipment of all descrip-tions for these units were necessary before large-scale offensive operations could beundertaken. This was one of the major reasons which influenced the Commander-in-Ohief, India, to decide against the formation of two further Indian divisions,which had originally been included in the 1942 programme of expansion, andto turn all energies towards the raising and equipping of the administrative unitsessential for offensive operations. Amongst these might be specially mentionedEngineer units for road and aerodrome construction, Motor Transport Companies,Signal units and Ordnance Workshops. The raising and training of these unitshas continued steadily, but as so many of them contain technicians it can but bea slow process. A great difficulty has also been encountered in the provision ofViceroy&apos;s Commissioned and Non-Commissioned officers for these new units.Recruiting from the &quot; Martial classes &quot; recruited in the pre-war Indian army is now gradually drying up, and the monthly intake of these classes is only justsufficient to maintain existing units. All further expansion has now to be carriedout with Madrassis (Southern Indian classes), who were only recruited to a verysmall extent before the war. There is. therefore, a very great dearth of trainedV.C.Os. and N.C.Os. for the new units. The experiment of providing NorthernIndian V.C.Os. and N.C.Os. for Madrassi units was tried and failed, as indeedmight have been expected seeing that there is as much difference between theNorthern Indian and Madrassi both in language and customs as between, say. a norwegian and&apos; a Greek. Large training establishments for Madrassi entryV.C.Os. and N.C.Os. have been established, but these will not begin turning out any great numbers before the second quarter of 1943. British N.C.Os., as wellas officers, are being provided for Madrassi A.A. and Field Artillery Regiments,but the shortage of British man-power does not permit of this experiment beingcarried further. In spite, however, of her own difficulties, India provided anumber of Engineer, Signal and Administrative units for P.A.EC. during september and October. She has also continued to supply Mideast with the personnel for M.T. Companies and labour battalions throughout the year.12. During August and September the disorders following the arrest of theCongress leaders necessitated the employment of practically all Field Armyreserves for Internal Security. Luckily this did not coincide with any Japaneseoffensive.Situation in December 1942.13. The present situation in India and Ceylon is that (in addition to theforces on the N.W. Frontier, internal security and training units, &amp;c.) two british and six Indian divisions are ready for service, but one of the indian divisions has still only 50 per cent, of its infantry equipment and all the indian divisions are short of artillery-. Four more Indian divisions should be ready foractive service in the next two or three months, and two Indian Armoured divisions and two (Independent) Tank Brigades between May and July 1943, making atotal by that date of two Indian Armoured divisions, three (Independent) tankbrigades and two British and ten Indian divisions. In addition to this, of course,there are still the one Indian Armoured division and five Indian divisions inMideast and P.A.I.C. There are now in India 548 Heavy A.A. guns and892 Light A.A. guns, and the static defences not only of Ceylon, but also of theCalcutta area and Assam and Bengal generally, are now practically up to the target level. Owing to the unexpected set-back in the Middle East in June, 1942,the Royal Air Force programme for India was delayed to a considerable extentowing to the necessity of diverting to the Middle East reinforcements that were actually at that time on their way to India, but, in spite of this, the R.A.F.programme for 1942 for India is now only 2 to 3 months behindhand and, owingto the great improvement of the situation in the Middle East, it is anticipated
that some of this delay will be made good. The construction of some200 aerodromes for these air forces, which was of necessity given the highest priority, has strained to the utmost India&apos;s exiguous engineering resources, andhas incidentally delayed considerably the construction of other essentials, suchas new road construction, new factories, storage for ammunition, &amp;c. the offensive operations towards Akyab and limited operations on the Assam-BurmaFrontier continue, while the work goes on of raising and training the adminis-trative units and the collection of the equipment necessary for large-scaleoffensives. Enough has, I think, been said to show that, in spite of very great difficulties, India has in 1942 made a very considerable contribution to theEmpire&apos;s war effort.14. The date when India&apos;s preparations can be completed is now dependentalmost entirely on the shipping allotted not only for the carriage of equipment,although this is the most important item, but also for the carriage of the necessaryBritish personnel to provide officers, and in some cases N.C.Os., for the new units.Royal Indian Navy.15. Between the outbreak of war and December 1942 the personnel of theService has increased to more than eight times its peace-time size and more than half the increase was made during the 14 months ending in December last. this service now contains more than 12,000 men. This increase in personnel has been accompanied by a great expansion in the number of vessels of various types, ofwhich 76 (including 30 Chartered) were in commission in December 1942 and314 were under construction. These comprise Sloops, Bathursts, Bangors,Trawlers, Motor Launches, Motor Torpedo Boats, and Landing Craft forcombined operations.STATEMENT SHOWING PRESENT AND PRE-WAR STRENGTH OFTHE ARMY AND AIR FORCES IN INDIA.The Army.(a) Strengths.20 Cavalry Regiments (2 British, 18 Indian), mostly horsed.8 Field Artillery Regiments (7 British, 1 Indian), mostly horsed.8 Indian Mountain Regiments.35 British Infantry Battalions.95 Indian Infantry Battalions.Total, 229,000 all ranks, of whom 182,000 were Indians.In addition to providing for Frontier Defence and Internal Security, this included three brigades for use in a field army role in or ex India.Upon this nucleus the following field army formations have been raised in addition to the equivalent of ten divisions still retained for North-west frontier defence and Internal Security : Three Indian Armoured Divisions.Three Indian Tank Brigades.Two Indian Motor Brigades.Seventeen Indian Infantry Divisions.Eight Independent Infantry Brigades.One Indian Parachute Brigade.Of these, the following are serving in overseas theatres of war (excludingCeylon) :  One Indian Armoured Division.One Indian Motor Brigade.Five Indian Infantry Divisions.In addition, the equivalent of three Indian Infantry Divisions were captured in Malaya.The above include British units which are part of Indian formations, butexclude complete British formations which are not part of the expansion of indians armed forces.I 25102] b 3
Air Forces in India.-September 1939.4 Medium Bomber Squadrons.* R.A.F.3 A/C Squadrons, R.A.F.1 B/T Squadron, R.A.F.1 A/C Squadron. IA.F.5 Coast Defence flights, I.A.F.V.R.* Two of these squadrons were sent to the Middle East and two to Malaya. the equipment of other squadrons was obsolete or obsolescent.December 1942.1 Heavy Bomber Squadron.2 Medium Bomber Squadrons.5 Light Bomber Squadrons.14 Day Fighter Squadrons (a).8 G.R. Flying-Boat Squadrons (b).3 G.R.M.R, Landplane Squadrons.1 Torpedo-Bomber Squadron.1 Long-Range Fighter Squadron.5 Bomber and Fighter Recce. Squadrons.2 Transport Squadrons.(a) Includes G.R./L-P. Squadron temporarily equipped on Hurricane II, but now revertingto Hudson III.(b) Includes 321 (Dutch) Squadron, which counts as two squadrons, but all squadrons are well Iselow strength.(b) Rate of Recruitment.1. Total numbers recruited for the Indian Arm)&apos; from September1939 to December 1942        ......   &quot;   ......... 1.348,0002. Total number recruited in 1942     ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 725,0003. Strength of Indian Army in India Command (including Ceylon),December 1942    ...&quot;      ...............&quot;... 1.226,0004. Strength of Indian Army overseas. December 1942      ...       ... 270,000Notes. (i) The figures at 3 and 4 above include British Service personnel serving with Indian Army formations and units, but exclude British Army formations-and units.(ii) The wastage rate for Indian ranks is approximately 25,000 per mensem
II. SUPPLY AND MUNITIONS.Production in India in 1942 was adversely affected by (a) the threat to India from the East, which resulted in partial closure of thePort of Calcutta and an unprecedented strain on the internal trans-portation system, and also necessitated the transfer from the Calcuttaarea of several of the projects which had been put in hand as a resultof the recommendations of the Roger Mission.(b) shipping difficulties arising partly from (a) and partly from other causes,which delayed the delivery of machinery and stores required by industry.(c) the political disturbances in August 1942.(d) the general uneasiness in Eastern India which affected labour, particu-larly during the spring of 1942, and at the end of the year.Notwithstanding these hindrances, production in 1942 was on a rising curve,as is shown by the fact that the value of orders handled by the Government ofIndia, Supply Department, in 1942 ( 167 million) was nearly double that in 1941.This figure excludes orders placed by the Supply Department overseas, orders placed in India through trade channels, and the value of the finished output ofGovernment ordnance factories.Progress under various heads is summarised below.(1) Munitions.Most of the projects approved by His Majesty&apos;s Government on the recom-mendation of Lord ChatfielcTs Committee are now complete, but a number of thoseimplemented as a result of the Roger Mission are still delayed owing to thenecessity for re-siting some of them to meet the strategical requirements of theEastern theatre of war. These are expected to come into production graduallythroughout 1943, and the second half of that year should see a big advance. Inspite of the incomplete condition of the various munition projects and the other factors which have adversely affected production, there has been considerable increase in all branches of munition production.Several new warlike stores have been manufactured in India for the first time, such as anti-tank mines and certain scientific stores, notably binoculars,prismatic and sighting telescopes, and the figures for production in 1942 indicatethat manufacture has been firmly established. Although both weapons andammunition are mainly produced by the Ordnance Factories, large quantities ofcomponents are supplied by trade workshops, and here, too. the outturn figures, ascompared with those of 1941, show a very considerable increase in all directions.Amongst these may be mentioned empty shell, armour-piercing shot, bodies forgrenades, mines and bombs, gun-carriage and cooker components, gun-sights,Bren magazine-boxes and bayonets. Some of the simpler scientific stores are alsomanufactured completely by the trade.The output of Armoured Fighting Vehicles has risen to three times the figure for 1941, and would have been higher but for the difficulties in obtaining chassisimposed by the shortage of shipping from North America, from which sourcethey are obtained.(2) Personnel.With the assistance of the Ministry of Labour and the Supply Departments,gratifying progress has been made in 1942 in the recruitment of British personnelrequired for India&apos;s munitions production. All the posts which difficulty wasbeing found in filling at the end of 1941 have been filled, and good progress hasbeen made in filling further demands made by the Government of India, bothmanagerial posts and foremen.I am sure that I can count on the continued co-operation of my colleagues incomplying with the heavy and important requirements of the Government ofIndia for minimum essential technical personnel.(3.) General Supplies.With few exceptions, factories, workshops and mills in India that can produce articles required for modern war are doing so. In Calcutta, the centre of the jute industry; in Bombay and Ahmedabad where the cotton mills areproducing cloth for uniforms and many other war purposes; in Cawnpore, the
chief supplier of leather goods; in Bihar where the coal and iron mines areproducing materials for the vast steel works in Bihar and Bengal; and in many other factories up and down the land the industrial war effort of India is being pursued.(4) Machine tools, &amp;c.Every effort is being continued to obtain as many key machine tools as canbe spared from the United Kingdom and also from the United States where the india Supply Mission is now well established and doing fruitful work. Apartfrom these imported machine tools, India, which before the war had to importpractically all her requirements, has developed manufacture of simple types andhas increased her monthly outturn from 220 in 1941 to 280 by the end of 1942.Apart from this, arrangements have been made, with the active help of theMinistry of Supply, to develop the manufacture of special machine tools in liveselected workshops throughout India and seven highly skilled technicians haverecently gone to India from this country and balancing plant is being sent fromthis country and from America to help the effort.Help is also being given by the .Ministry of Supply in the establishment and development of capacity for the manufacture of small tools requiring heattreatment and for hand tools; technical advisers are being sent to India for thispurpose and plant supplied from this country and from America in an effort to bring capacity nearer to the heavy demand. Plant is also being provided toincrease the outturn of bolts, nuts and rivets for which the current demand isdouble the capacity of 20,000 to 25,000 tons a year.(5) Steel. .The basis of India&quot;s heavy industrial war effort is her steel industry.Before the war her capacity was 750,000 tons finished steel per annum. Capacityhad increased by the end of 1942 by two-thirds to 1.250.000 tons. The targetis 1.500,000 tons and this should be reached in 1944. when an expansion of theworks of the Steel Corporation of Bengal, India&apos;s second largest steel producer,becomes operative. This expansion has received the ready support and assistanceof the Ministry of Supply in the provision of the necessary plant.(6) Shipbuilding and repair.A considerable step forward has been taken during 1942 in regard to shipbuilding and ship repair, which were formerly handled by two different Govern-ment organisations in India. In June 1942 the two Branches were brought under one Directorate General, which was set up in Bombay. The broad policy is thatconstruction must not interfere with repairs.As regards construction, at the beginning of 1942 32 vessels were under construction, from Basset Trawlers to 16-foot dinghies. 27 vessels were completed during the year, and 291 are now under construction, again ranging from BassetTrawlers to dinghies. These figures do not include an extensive barge-building&quot;programme undertaken for the port of Bombay. Progress with Bassets and other vessels requiring imported machinery has been disappointingly slow owing todelayed deliveries of machinery and some losses at sea. The shortage of steel,especially plates, has also been a crucial problem. Progress is only moderatelysatisfactory.With regard to repairs, considerable new capacity has been, and is being,established at Bombay. Karachi, Cochin and Vizagapatam, by such methods as theerection and extension of workshops, the provision of increased berthing capacity,the conversion of an enemy prize ship into a repair shop, the provision of piersand dolphins and the expanding and reconditioning of docks. On the west coastduring 1942 labour strength has increased by 33^ per cent, over 1941 strength, butthere is still a great shortage of skilled men and skilled supervision. The east coast yards were, for the greater part of 1942, not working to capacity. TheP.I.N. Dockyard labour had risen by the end of 1942 to between five and six timesits pre-war strength.During 1942 the R.I.N. Dockyard carried out major repairs to 3 Britishand 1 U.S. Cruisers, 2 British Destroyers and 1 British Depot Ship, 72 other british Warships received ordinary repairs in the Dockyard and 34 outside the dockyard. Some work on smaller Warships has been undertaken and completed at ports other than Bombay. 98 Tankers, with a tonnage of 572,000. and 1,295Merchant Ships, with a tonnage of 7.220.000, were repaired between May and december 1942.
Extensive progress has also been made in providing ships with defensiveequipment including protection by degaussing, and the production and fitting ofplastic armour.(7) Aircraft repair and manufacture of components.In the course of 1942 it became clear, as the strength of the air forces inIndia increased, that the primary need was to make provision for the repair andmaintenance of aircraft sent to India from the United Kingdom and north america, and that this must take precedence over any attempt to produce aircraft in India. The small, but efficient, factory at Bangalore (established two yearsago under American management, with capital provided jointly by the Govern-ment of India, the Government of Mysore and an Indian financier), which had never been able to achieve much production for lack of materials and parts, wastherefore brought wholly under the Government of India&apos;s control, and is nowbeing developed as a repair and maintenance depot for American types of aircraft. At the moment progress is somewhat retarded by a delay in the arrival of American technicians. Meanwhile the shortage glider project, sponsored by theMinistry of Aircraft Production, was abandoned at His Majesty&apos;s Governmentsinstance, and the organisation built up by Tatas for that purpose is to form thebasis of a new project under the auspices of the Government of India, providingfor aircraft repair in the Calcutta region and for the assembly of importedaircraft and the manufacture of spare parts in the neighbourhood of Bombay.In addition, various Provincial Government and railway workshops have beenadapted for the production of components and repair work on a regional basis,and these have been supplemented by a system of approved contractors. All these developments will be controlled by a new Aeronautical Stores Division of theSupply Department, to organise and control which three experienced officers, withother technical personnel, are being sent out to India. Most of the developmentsare still in the initial stages, but considerable achievements are expected in 1943.The following are a few examples to illustrate the wide range and increased output of stores required for the war effort.(8) Engineer Stores.Increases are recorded of electrical equipment such as bare copper wire:cotton covered instrument wires, square dry cells, inert cells, electric motors andtransformers. A new factory for the production of D class field cable will comeinto operation in May or June 1943. Telegraph stores show an increase and output may be doubled when the new Posts and Telegraph Workshop atJubbulpore comes into operation this year. Road making machinery is mostlyimported but production of bitumen boilers and mixers and cement and asphaltmixers has now been established. Under structurals notable features are : a largeAdmiralty floating dock with a lifting capacity of 50,000 tons which is nearing completion (enquiries are now under way for a repeat order); strategic bridgesfor India and the Middle East; radio location towers and ordnance factoryexpansions.(9) Textiles and Clothing.Production of cotton piece-goods, which in 1941 was 275 million yards,increased in 1942 to 700 million yards. Tents increased from 3 to 4-^ millions,blankets from 4 to 4-^ millions. Parachute silk cloth cords from 3-3 to 51 million yards. A special feature during 1942 was the manufacture of basic cloth for anti-gas clothing with a production of 1^ million yards monthly.The number of garments produced increased from 78 million in 1941 to 106million in 1942. Pre-war annual production was less than 1 million garments.In 1941 no parachutes were produced. In 1942 the number, including silkstatichutes and cotton parachutes for dropping stores, was 31,500. 4^- millionanti-gas garments were produced against none in 1941. Web equipmentproduction increased from half a million to 2-]- million sets.Boots increased from 3 to 3f million pairs and other footwear from 4-J- to 121million pairs. Vegetable tanned leather from 18^ to over 25 million lbs. andchrome tanned leather from 13^ to 154. million square feet.(10) A.R.P. Stores.Production of stirrup pumps increased tenfold to 410,000 in 1942: trailerpumps from 12 to 140; electric sirens from 100 to 820 and steel helmets from100,000 to 320.000.
(11) Rubber.Output of plantation rubber has increased, slightly to 16,280 tons and wildrubber from nil to 8 tons in 1942 with an estimated output in 1943 of 500 tons.Reclaim rubber increased from nil in 1941 to 900 tons in 1942 and an estimated5,000 tons in 1943.(12) Miscellaneous.Other increases are recorded in production of chemicals, paints, gases,petroleum products, timber, vehicle assembly and body building and in a numberof miscellaneous items in which extensive use has been made of small scale orcottage industry.



</content>
</cab>
