<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/42/12 images: 122-125</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M,AJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 462.lSth October, 1943.WAR CABINET.BRITISH COMMONWEALTH CONVERSATIONS ON CIVIL AIRTRANSPORT.Note by the Secretary.BY direction of the Prime Minister, the attached minute from the LordPrivy Seal to the Prime Minister, setting out the broad aims of British civil airtransport policy and the findings of the British Commonwealth and EmpireConversations, is circulated for consideration by the War Cabinet.(Signed) E. E. BRIDGES.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,18th October, 1943.Prime Minister.CIVIL AIR TRANSPORT.WE desire our share of civil aviation in the post-war world. That is thefirst aim of British policy. We seek to build up British air transport as far as isconsistent with our financial burdensIn three broad spheres of activity, we lay down the special interest and over-riding claims of Britain : (1) The internal traffic of the United Kingdom must be reserved completelyfor Britain.(2) Traffic within the Colonial Empire must be controlled by application ofthe principle of cabotage, which reserves to each country all trafficpicked up at one point within its territories and set down at another.(3) In traffic on the great Empire routes, Britain desires a full measure ofparticipation, in co-operation with the Dominions and India.After these three prime objectives of policy, it is the aim of Britainto secure as much international traffic as may be obtained.So far as European air traffic is concerned, it is our desire to secure a greatmeasure of the trade. Our geographical position and our vital commercialinterests entitle us to expect that Britain can become and should become adominating factor in the air transport system of the Continent.It is recognised that, in pursuing these broad aims, great care must beexercised in elaborating the policy owing to the need for international agreement,in particular the need to go forward in accord with the United States and Russia.Other nations must also receive their just and proper share of the air traffic of theworld. But the essential first stage in the development of the policy is consulta-tion with the Dominions and India. For this reason British Commonwealth andEmpire Conversations were opened in London on the 11th October, 1943.The Conference resulted in a wide measure of agreement on principles andpurposes, while avoiding even the remotest suggestion of &quot; ganging up against &quot;the United States.[26243]
The unanimous findings of the Conference (subject, of course, to reference tothe Governments) were, in brief, as follows : (1) The Freedom of the Air was defined : I. The Right of innocent passage.II. The Right to land for non-traffic purposes.III. The Right to land passengers, mail and freight from the countryof origin of the aircraft.IV. The Right to pick up passengers, &amp;c, for the country of origin ofthe aircraft.These Four Freedoms were accepted by the Conference, subject to aninternational agreement.(2) An outline international convention was approved, dealing with thesuggested machinery for the regulation and operation of international airroutes. This document is, of course, a contribution to be put forward indiscussions with other countries. Decision must necessarily wait upon aninternational conference.(3) A committee of the Conference under the chairmanship of theMinister of State examined international air transport in relation tosecurity. After deliberation, this committee emphasised the need forsubordination of an International Air Transport Authority to such securityorganisation as may be created by the United Nations. The Committeerecommended that signatory States should be entitled to suggest, and the AirAuthority should be entitled to recommend, the joint or&apos; internationaloperation of certain routes or zones, and that immediate consideration shouldbe given to the possibility of establishing a European operating agency.(4) Finally, it was determined unanimously that an all-British route beprovided, linking the United Kingdom, the British Dominions. India and theprincipal British Colonies. Each Dominion, the United Kingdom and Indiashall, it is proposed, operate sections of the route adjacent to its territories.And the operating Governments shall constitute a co-ordinating committeeto deal with all matters affecting the Route as a whole.Although this decision of the Conference lacks definition and must not beregarded as in any sense a final document, it affords us the confident assurancethat the Empire will rise to the level of the immense opportunities which airtransport offers to us. It opens to all the British nations a vision of immense scopeand a task of constructive statesmanship worthy of our peoples and of the placethey occupy in the world.The next stage in the development of this policy is to approach the UnitedStates. The unanimous conclusions reached at the Conference give us the rightto go to Washington, presenting a policy which carries the approval of the Empireand which, although broad in outline, is nevertheless firm enough to become thefoundation of a sound structure.After consultation with the United States and with Russia, it will be ourpurpose to seek, at an international conference, an agreement among the nationswhich will establish conditions for air transport throughout the world operatingequitably in the interests of each country, and advantageously in the interests ofmankind.B.



</content>
</cab>
