<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/188/6 images: 69-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
UMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(76) 31 COPY NO      g 15 March 1976CABINETWHITE PAPER ON CASH LIMITSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer.        The Government is committed to publishing details of the cashlimits for 1976-77 around the beginning of the financial year.   I invitemy colleagues to approve,  or publication on Budget Day, the text of theWhite Paper attached to this memorandum.2.       My colleagues are familiar with the reasons which led us to announce, in the White Paper &quot;The Attack on Inilation,, (Cmnd 6151)that an extensive use would be made of cash limits, starting in 1976-77,and Departments have co-operated closely with the Treasury in settingup the arrangements described in the attached document.   For this I amvery grateful.   We now have to show our determination to make theseMw control arrangements work.3.        In the White paper the main emphasis has been placed on theapplication of cash limits to the Governments own expenditure.   Thisis what the man in the street will understand; and it is here that ourPerformance will be most closely watched.   But the arrangements which*** being made for local authorities&apos; capital programmes and for theBAUonalised industries are also important to the credibility of the operation.4.       These new arrangements are important, and have been widely**Ieomed, but we must avoid presenting them as the sole remedy forMl the existing problems we face in controlling expenditure, or indeed** being immutable in all circumstances.   The principal exclusions&amp;om cash limits are listed in Appendix I.   As to the circumstances in*hlch cash limits may be changed, I draw attention to paragraphs 18 and 19of the text.   It will be most important not to create the impression in theWhite Paper that reviews of cash limits will be lightly undertaken, or that increases in the limits will follow automatically.    But it would be^nirealietic to deny that reviews during the course of the financial year are possible.   An undertaking has already been given to local authorities aboutthe circumstances in which the cash limits on the rate support grant wouldho reviewed.   If nothing was said in the White Paper on this point therewould certainly be questions about it, and it seems better therefore to include* considered statement to which questioners can be referred.1
5. The cash limit figures included in Tables 1 and 2 of the textreflect the position as known to the Treasury on 12 March.    In one qrtwo cases provision has still to be included for some of the measuresto alleviate unemployment which I announced on 12 February.   I ask my colleagues to agree that amendments to reflect these changes, andothers which may arise before the cut-off date for printing, may besettled between the Chief Secretary and the Ministers mainly concerned.D W treasury Chambers15 March 19762
CONFIDENTIAL-PROOFS ONLYCash Limits on public ExpenditurePresented to Parliament by the Chancellor of the exchequer by Command of Her majesty april 1976LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE O.QOa,et. ,(
CASH LIMITS ON PUBLIC EXPENDITUREIntroduction1. In planning total public expenditure, the Government have to ensurethat the resources taken by the public sector are sensibly related tothe total resources available in the economy as a whole. They also haveto control the amount actually spent in the current financial year, sothat it fits into the plan set out in the annual budget. Different techniques are required for medium term planning and forbudgetary control. In mating projections for a period of years ahead,it is impossible to predict the movement of prices with any assurance,either generally or for particular goods and services purchased by thepublic sector; public spending plans for the medium term are thereforeworked out at constant prices. ,3. For expenditure control in the current year, on the other hand, itis essential to control the actual cash spent, and it is with this that thepresent White Paper is concerned. The traditional basis for this controlhas been provided by Supply Estimates approved by Parliament. How-ever, even in periods of modest inflation, the Estimates presented withthe Budget have not provided a good indication of the amount of moneylikely to be spent during the year. This is because the Estimates aregenerally calculated at the price levels prevailing when they are prepared,taking account only of pay increases known at the time. supplementary estimates have therefore been needed to finance subsequent pay settle-ments and price increases, and for most services they have been regularlyprovided to cover such increases. Thus, for the most part, the budget estimates did not operate as a direct control on the amount of cashspent; and when inflation gathered pace, and especially as the prices ofdifferent goods and services increased at very different rates, they becameeven more inadequate as an indicator of the amount of cash that wouldbe needed during the year.4. The problem of rapidly escalating prices first arose acutely in thecase of public sector building programmes. Tender prices rose by 88per cent in the two-year period ending December 1973. This led tothe imposition of cash limits on several building programmes in central and local government in 1974-75 and 1975-76. However, the problem has been more widespread. The Government therefore announced in theWhite Paper &quot;The Attack on Inflation&quot; (Cmnd 6151) that work wasin hand to bring about the extensive use of cash limits in 1976-77 inthose services where they can impose greater financial discipline andprecision, and where they can contribute to countering inflation by making it clear both to the spending authorities and to suppliers thatthe Governmeafs purchases of goods and services will have to be cutback if prices rise too high.
5. The Supply Estimates do not cover all public expenditure. In par-ticular, though they govern the grant finance provided to local autho-rities and nationalised industries, these bodies have other sources ofrevenue and their expenditure is outside the Supply Estimates framework.It would not be appropriate for cash limits to apply to the whole of their expenditure since the nationalised industries are trading bodies and thelocal authorities have discretion over the amount of money they raisethrough the rates. There is nevertheless some scope for applying cash limits to them even where grant finance is not involved; for example cashlimits have beep applied lo local govcrpmcnt building programmes.6. The remamder of this White Paper describes the arrangements whichare being introduced in 1976-77. In the light of experience they maybe modified in later years.Cash Bmlts on central Government expenditure. For the reasons already explained, cash limits will differ both fromthe figures in the public expenditure White Papers and from those in theSupply Estimates. They will represent a planned limit on the amount of cash that the Government propose to spend on certain services, or blocks of services, during the coining financial year. For those services financedwholly from, the Supply Estimates, they can be thought of as a plannedceiling for the services concerned on the total of the Main Estimates andany Supplementary Estimates combined.S. In 1976-77, cash limits will be applied to about three-quarters of central Government voted expenditure other than social security benefits.The general approach will be that they will be applied in all areas where-within the existing statutory framework they are both feasibleand&apos; w31 effectively improve on existing control systems. Services alreadysubject to cash control will continue to be covered. The main exclusionswfU&apos; be those services where, once policy and rates of payment have been determined, the total of disbursements in the short term will depend onsuch factors as1 the number of qualified recipients-e.g, social security benefits, expenditure on family practitioner services, agricultural support and some forms of regional assistance. A list of the main exclusions isat Appendix 1. ;9. For cash&apos; control purposes the- various expenditures will be groupedinto &quot;Ijlocfa&quot;. These ate designed to be large enough to provide spendingauthorities with scope for finding the most economical and effective wayof carrying out their programmes within the limits, whilst at the sametime ensuring effective financial control. In general, no block is the responsi-bility of more than one Department, though in the case of the ScottishDepartments this.rule.has been modified in order to avoid unduly smallblocks. In a few &quot;cases a block includes central and local government expenditure on closely related Services. Expenditure which the CivD Ser-vice Department U&apos; responsible for approving (mainly pay and generaladministrative expenses) generally falls in separate blocks from those con-taining expenditure which the Treasury is responsible for approving.
10. The blocks containing central Government expenditure are listed inTable 1. The table shows the Department responsible for each block, and gives a brief description of the expenditure covered by it. The blocksincluding expenditure approved by the Civil Service Department are sepa-rately identified. Some blocks include expenditure which is not withinthe definition of &quot;public expenditure&quot; as the term is used in the annualpublic expenditure White Paper; these items are mainly transfers withinthe public sector which fall on Votes, but which are excluded from the definition of &quot;public expenditure&quot; to avoid double-counting. In a few casesthe blocks include elements of expenditure which do not fall on Votes, but which for control purposes are grouped with closely related votedexpenditures. A more detailed analysis of the Vote Subheads and other expenditure comprised in each block is at Appendix 2.Local authority expenditure11. Under the present statutory arrangements, local authority current expenditure cannot be directly controlled by central Government. Cashlimits are however being placed on the amount of financial assistanceprovided to local authorities by the central Government through the rate support grant and supplementary grants. This means that limits have beenplaced on the amount of grants that may be made under Increase Ordersfor England and Wales, and for Scotland, for the financial year 1976-77.Fuller details were given in Departmental Circulars.* These limits areincluded in the list of cash limits on central Government expenditure inTable I-12, Blocks including local authority capital expenditure are listed in Table2. The form of control varies from case to case depending on the practicalarrangements and the statutory powers available. Some are controlled by reference to the amount spent, some by reference to the amount of money which may be borrowed to be spent during the year, and some by reference to the value of work which may be, started during the year.The form of control is indicated in the table.Nationalised Industries13. The nationalised industries will be treated differently. They are majortrading bodies, and it is their net borrowing requirement and not their capital investment which has a direct impact on the public sector borrow-ing requirement. The constraint to be applied in their case should there-fore be closer to that experienced by a private company i.e. it should apply to the amount of cash which they can raise. The intention is, there-fore, to relate cash control to estimates of their financing needs to be met by loans; grants and public dividend capital.- A joint Departmental Circular for England and Wales of 31 December 1975 and scottish Office Finance Circular 73/1975.
14. The major nationalised industries now send to their sponsoringDepartments and the Treasury every month-as opposed to every quarterunder the previous arrangements an up-to-date statement of their finance-iog requirements for the year and their proposals for meeting those require-ments. They discuss with Departments any significant changes in theirforecasts. This system will be developed further. [Table 12] of the FinancialStatement and Budget Report shows for 1976-77 estimates of the financingrequirements of each of the nationalised industries, covering both theirfixed investment and their working capital, and how the industries expect to meet these requirements. These estimates will be treated as a formof cash limit, and used as the basis for monitoring the industries&apos; financingrequirements. But the limits cannot be immutable because, like private sector companies, their revenues and expenditures depend on trading con-ditions. There may well be causes quite beyond the control of a particular industry, reflecting not at all on its efficiency, which would make it exceedits borrowing estimate. An example would be a change in the forecastcash flow of an energy industry caused by an exceptional winter.15- Nevertheless, Ministers intend that the nationalised industries winbe required to explain significant departures from the control figures which may emerge from the scrutiny of the monthly financing statements.There will be no presumption that a financing deficit will be met by afurther injection of external finance.16. Borrowing during 1976-77 by the regional water authorities will bemonitored by arrangements similar to those for the nationalised industries.[Table 11] of the Financial Statement and Budget Report contains the relevant estimate for their borrowing requirement from the National loans fund.    &apos;Northern Ireland17. The expenditure of the Northern Ireland Office and of Northern. Ire-land Departments (and local authorities) are shown in Table 1, and willbe subject to cash control in the same way as the corresponding expendi-tures in the rest of the United Kingdom.Calculation and operation of cash Bnttts18. The cash limits represent the maximum amount which the government propose should be spent on the services comprised in each block during thecoming1 financial year. They thus take account of the planned volume ofexpenditure- shown in the public expenditure White Paper (Cmnd 6393),and also,allow for increases in prices and incomes consistent with the policyin the White Paper &quot;The Attack on Inflation&quot; (Cmnd 6151). Once fixed,the limits will not normally be revised daring the course of the year unlessspecific policy decisions have been taken to change the level of provisionof a particular service. For certain services, such as the roads and hospital building programmes, where the timing of expenditure on existing projectscannot be precisely controlled, some arrangements are needed to allow alimited amount of flexibility between successive financial years and between
current and capital expenditure. The extent to which such arrangements are required will be decided in the light of experience.19. Cash limits will require spending departments and authorities, inmanaging their expenditure, to provide within these limits for any increases in costs due to pay or price increases. If the rate of inflation were to turnout substantially higher than that allowed for in the cash limits, theGovernment would have to take stock of the position in the light of allthe circumstances of the time. This is not, however, a situation whichthe Government envisage, nor, if it were to arise, should their responsebe taken for granted.20. Expenditure on each cash control block will be carefully monitoredso that corrective action may be taken should it appear likely that the cashlimits would otherwise be exceeded. Departments will establish &quot;profiles&quot; ofthe rate at which money is likely to be spent on each block during the courseof a year in order to assist ******* in this task. After the end of the financialyear, the Government will publish outturn figures on each Woe.
CASH LIMITS1976-77l!jr, h ,    ,   Ceatrai GoTcnuneirt Mocks (&quot;Department- &apos;     l;&apos;ittocA Number    Description 6$ Expenditure1Ministry of Agriculture, MAFF 1*P)Fisheries and. FoodfnteCYent$board&amp; : KAP 1*- :Agrlem,tatil PrtWuce . i    ^1- -h   ^ i&apos;y &apos; - - IBAP2   &apos;Cabinet OfficeCO 1*Central Office of Information COI1*COI2Charily Commission CC 1*Civil Service Department      CSD lCSD2CSD 3CEO 1*CEI&apos;MOD ICrown Estate OfficeHM Customs and ExciteMinistry of defence department of Education      DES 1*and Science^)DES 2DES 3DES 4DESSCashLimit mPay and general administrative expenses 87.1Agricultural and food servicesand fisheries support : 62.5Pay and genera] administrative expenses 6.4FcttMflbsidies (pa&quot;)P) B.7Pay and general administrative expenses 4.6Pay and general administrative expenses 7.home publicity 13,0Pay and general administrative expenses 1.6Central management of theCivil Service 22,3Computers and telecommunications-launkations 47.0Civil Service catering 1.0Pay and general administrative expenses 0.8Pay, general administrative expenses and capital expendi-ture 153.9Defence Budget 5,835.0Pay and general administrative expenses 17.9Current and some capitalexpenditure on schools,further education, teacher training, youth service and educational research 73.2Current and some capitalexpenditure on universities 700.3libraries, museums, galleriesand the arts 88.9Science Budget-research councils 226.1
Department Block Number     Description of Expenditure Cask x-Limit mDepartment of Employment   DEM 1*Department of EnergyDepartment 0f the environment^)Exchequer and AuditDepartmentExport Credits GuaranteeDepartmentOffice of Fair TradingForeign and CommonwealthOfficeForestry CommissionFriendly Societies&apos; RegistryGovernment Actuary&apos;sDepartmentDEM 2DEM 3DEN 1*DEN 2DEN 3DOE 1*DOE 2   ;DOE 3DOE 4DOES&apos;DOE 6DOE 7DOE 8DOE 9EA.1*ECGD 1*OFT 1*FCO 1*FCO 2FCO 3fci*FC 2FSR 1*GAD 1*Pay and general adminHtrativeexpenses 145.4Manpower Services Commission 400.other employment services 33.6Pay and general administrative &apos;expenses 8.9Nudear energy J24.4Research and development and industrial sponsorship 82.5Pay and general administrative expenses 175.0Motorways and trunk roads,new bus spunts, etc 528.0Certain railways and waterwaysgrants : 1 60.1 &apos;Various central and miscel-laneouj services J38.7Property Services Agency:Pay and general administrativeexpansw .YOA.&apos;Office and general accommodationservioes - 259.2Overseas representation:accommpdation services 31.2Rents (tflt) * * tRate support grant and supplementary grants lorlocal authorities in Englandand Wales(*)Pay and general administrativeexpeuorPay and general administrativeexpensesPay and general administrativeexpensesPay and general adnrimstrativeexpeoaeaOverseas representation,   tu,.overseas information and external relationsBritish CoaacirPay and general administratrvaexpensesForestryPay and general administrativeexpensesPay and general administrativeexpenses6,644.14.21272.4mm36A19.58*0.5
DtpartmeniMotto Mm&amp;er    Description of ExpenditureCteftLimit m&amp;H3S 1*OHSS2HOI&apos;HO 2HO idh*DI2til 3IR 1*utirLCD 1&apos;LCD 2ND01*NIO i*mo?OS 1*oom (&apos;ODM2, Health ServiceComnuasbsuEt&apos; -OSt of Population opcs 4*Censuses and SurveysCbnsumer ProtectionDepartment at Htedth-wlSocial SecurityHome office department of IndustryBeattf of Inland RevenueLaid RegistryUBffChanocllor&apos;sDepAttmmNational Debt office department for NationalSavingsNorthern Ireland OfficeOrdnance SurveyMb*iry of overseas development   -Pay aiid general administrativeexpensesHealth and personal social services &apos; pay and general adnMetftratheexpensesOverseas information:broadowtingLaw, order and protective servicesPay and general administrativeexpensesRegional and industrial policyand research and developmentAssistance to shipbuildingPay and general administrativeexpensesPay and -general administrativeexpensesPay and general administrativeAdministration of legal aid fund and judges&apos; salariesPay and general administrativeexpespesPay and general administrativeexpensesPay and general administrativeexpensesLaw, order and protectiveservices; grant to the police authority for NorthernIreland, and accommodationPay, general administrative expenses and capitalexpenditurePay and general administrativeexpensesAid Programme (net)Pay and general administrativeexpense!Pay aad general administrativeexpensesPay and general administrativeexpensesFood subsidies (parrJt^Consumer protection481.8,968.5191.629.5130.9552107.937-9344.021.723.716.50.338.434.489.723A12.0515.80.712.63.6409.4114
Department Btwek ttum&amp;er    DweHpntm if Expenditure OathLimit mPrivy Council Office -.	*O0&apos;l*	Pay add general adrriinistratfw			expenses	0i3Public Record Office	PRO 1*	Pay and, general administrative			expenses	1.public Trustee Office	PTO 1*	Pay and general administrative			expensei	10Public Works Loan	PWLCl&apos;	Pay and general administrative	Commission		expenses	02Hex Majesty&apos;s Stationery	HMSO 1*	Pay and general administrative	SJAOffice		expenses		HMSOZ	Stationary and printing	46.9Department of Trade	DOT 1*	Pay and general administrative			expenses	42.1	DOT&apos;2	Shipping services&apos; &apos;	to	DOT 3	Civil aviation	60.8	DOT 4	Tourism, regulation of domestic			trade and industry and	T*l		consumer protection^		DOT 3	Export promotion	, 48.7Her Majesty&apos;! Treasury	HMT 1*	Pay and general administrative -			expenses	15.0	HMT2	Economic and financial			management	16.0	HMT 3	Secret Service	30.5Treasury Solicitor	TS 1*	Pay and general administrative			expenses	4.0SCOTLANDScottish OfficeSO 1*Department of Agriculture     DAPS Iand FisherireafbttScotlandScottish Courts SCA 1*AdministrationScottish Development SBD 1DepartmentSDD 2SDD 3Scottish economic planning DepartmentSEPD 1Pay and general administrative expenses)?) 53.9Agricultural services and fisheriessupport 28.0Pay and general administrative expenses 4.3Motorways and trunk roads,grants to shipping and air services, Feterhead harbouretc.P) 72.other environmental services 2.3Rate support grant for localauthorities in ScatUndf!) $71.7;Regional and industrialdevelopment 60.3iff
Department Bletk tiwnber    Detaription of Expenditure CashLimitScottish EduoMiaai.DepartmentSBD.X -SED2  v;Scottish Hook and Health    SHHDlDepartmentr&apos; SHHTJZDepartment of the Registers DRS 1*^ScotlandQueen,tandtord   &apos;  &quot; QLTR 1*Treasurer&apos;* Remembrancer ..Registrar Geoeral&apos;s Office,&quot; cargo(S)l*Scotland , ,,Scottish Record Office .SKO 1*New buildrng for schools,teacher training and furthereducational) 7.3Current, and some capita)expenditure on schools,teacher training, educationalresearch, further education,youth services, sport, social work, rtbnuies, galleries,museums and other arts     &apos;       50.5Health 554.9,Law, order and protectiveservices 10,7Pay and general administrative expenses 1.$Pay and general administrative expenses 3.pay and general administrative expenses &apos; 1.*Pay and general administrative expenses 0.3WALESWelsh Office^W01*&apos; ;. I: : W01, WO. 3WO 4WO 5W^6Pay and genenl administrativeMotorways, trunk roads andother expenditure on toadsOther enviroosnemal servicesLibraries, ttnteuma, gafieriMand other Arts Health and personal socialservicesRegional and industrialdevelopment9.566.93.71*6220j0NORTHERN tttfiEAND    way]DEPARTMENTS i^,! &apos; . -.&apos;ttij-,!-.-.^r,Services analogous to Q.B.servjees covered by cashlimits7083
Notes on Table 1(&apos;) Central Government blocks are arranged by country-England, Scotland, Wales andNorthern Ireland-aad, within each.country, in alphabetical order of the departments responsible for each block. , 3j     ,(?) Blocks covering expenditure which the Civil Service Department are responsible forauthorising are indicated by an asterisk. The Treasury are responsible for authorisingmost of the expenditure in the other blocks.(J) Expenditure on food subsidies falls into two blocks controlled by the InterventionBoard for Agricultural Produce and the Department of Prices and Consumer Protectionrespectively.(*) Expenditure by the Department of Education and Science, local authorities and other public bodies on new buildings for schools, further and higher education arc subjectto a single cash limit, shown against block DES/LA 1 in Table 2, page 11.(*) These cash limits do not include Government grants for British Rail passenger and freightservices, which are limited to a ceiling of  000.0 million for passenger services and  60million for freight services in the calendar year 1976.&apos;(*) The cash limit announced on 21 November of  480 million for England and Walesapplies to increase orders for 1976-77. The figure given here represents the sum of rate support grants and supplementary grants plus the limit on increase orders.(T) The cash limit on DOT 4 applies to net expenditure. Receipts are expected to exceedexpenditure and therefore the cash limit is negative. This means that the block is to be managed in such a way that net receipts will not be less than  15.1 million.(S) SO 1* covers the pay and general administrative expenses of the Scottish Office, Depart-ment of Agriculture and Fisheries for Scotland, Scottish Development Department,Scottish Education Department (part only), Scottish Economic Planning Department and scottish Home and Health Department (except the State Hospital).P) SDD 1 contains some items of expenditure which are the responsibility of the ScottishEconomic Planning Department.(10) The cash limit announced on 21 November of  55 million for Scotland applies toIncrease Orders for 1976-77. The figure given here represents the sum of rate support grant and the limit on increase orders for 1976-77.(it) The cash limit on SED 1 applies to the value of education building projects to be started in 1976-77, and not to actual expenditure incurred in the financial year.Expenditure by the Welsh Office and local authorities in Wales on new buildings forschools and further education is subject to a single cash limit, shown against WO/LA 3in Table 2, page 12.
CASH LIMITS 1976-77Local Aofttority Capital Erpcadhure BlocksTabteJ _&apos;Dtpartmenl Bhck Number (ij Description of Expenditure CathUmittmENGLANDTsjsjaiiiiwm of f*mrtinand ScienceDcparfantaKrof BnsptoymenlDepartment of theEnvironmentDepartment of Health and. jSockl Security..Home OfficeDES/LA l&quot;^      Schools, teacher training andfurther education!2) 226.9DBM/LA tA     Employment services 10.7DOE/LA 1+ Capital expenditure within thelocally determined sector inEngland and Wales 383.2DOB/LA 2&quot;*&quot;     Key seclor loan sanction for capital expenditure on roads and other transport, inEngland and Wales 97.4DOE/LA 3A     Improvement of local authority and new town housing;acquisition of existingdwellings; fending to private individuals foe bouse purchase(grow) and improvement;improvement grants to private sector, etc 1,026.8DOE/LA 4*&quot;      Housing tsModalionsP) 447.0DOE/LA S a.     Reclamation of derelict land and coast protection work 21.2DHSS/LA 1 *    Peetonel social services 31.5HO/LA 1A       Police, coum, probationand community services 64.1SCOTLANDScottish Office SO/LAI ASO/LA 2AScottish Development SDD/LA 1ADepartmentSDD/LA 2^Capital expenditure on roads and other transport)4) 78.4Land drainage, flood protection,other local services andgenera) administration^) 102.7Improvement of local authority and Scottish Special housing association housing; tending to private individuals for house purchase (gross) and improvement; improvementgrams for private sector, etc.      117.housing associations^) 38.6
DepartmentBhek Number     Deseripeim of ExpemSilmt CaskLimit mScottish EducationDepartmentScottish Home and health departments ED/LA 1 ^     Schools and further education        49.0SED/LA 2A      Personal social services 7.9SED/LA 3 a.      Museums, galleries, librariesand other arts, teacher training, youth services and recreation 17.3SHHD/LA 1A   Police, fire, courts and community services 11 -1WALESWelsh OfficeWO/LA 1a.      Improvement of local authority and new town housing;acquisition of existingdwellings, tending to private individuals for house purchase(grow) and improvement;improvement grants to private sector, etc.WO/LA 2W       Housing associations^)WO/LA 3V       Schools and further education^)WO/LA 4W       Personal social services59.014.89.82.2Notes to table 2(0 The symbols against the block number indicate the form of cash control applied to the block. The forms of control are as follows:-v   The cash limit on these blocks applies to the value of projects approved/started in1976-77.a  The cash limit on (hoe blocks applies to total capital expendituis ia 1976-77 on theservices covered.t-   The cash limit on these blocks applies to the proportion of capital expenditure to be financed by borrowing in 1976-77.(J) The cash limit for DES/LA 1 covers the total value of starts on school, further and higher education building programmes in England.0) The cash limits on the three blocks for housing associations apply io the value of projectsapproved both by local authorities and by the Housing Corpora lion,i*) The two Scottish Office blocks txmiain items of expenditure which are the responsibilityof more than one Scottish Department.(J) The cash limit for WO/LA 3 covers the total value of school and further educationbuilding programmes in Wales.
Appendix IPrincipal Excfautau from Cash Limits in 1976-77Programme General description Provision inCmnd6393for 1976-77im at 1975Survey pricesI, Defence                            Pensions 256.3 national Accounts adjustment 20.02,   Overseas Aid and other         Contribution W e.c. (net) 170.5overseas services ..3    Agriculture, Fisheries ana       Agricultural support 380.3Forestry4.   Trade, Industry and              Regional development grants 243.0Employment                    Selective assistance to industry inassisted areas 47.0Regional employment premium 212.5Concorde, RB211 and other aircraft andaeroengine projects 25.]National Enterprise Board 225.0Selective assistance to individual industries, firms and undertakings 132.9Refinancing of home shipbuilding lending   52.3Investment grants 23.0Refinancing of fixed rate export credits 337.0Redundancy fund payments 90.5S.   Nationalised industries&apos; capital BritishMatjonai Oil Corporation 2500expenditure6.   Roads and Transport           Bus fuel grants 33.7Ports 45.17.   Housing                            Subsidies 1.413.3Option mortgage scheme 113.net investment on housebuilding and______                        land U3S.other Envifortmemsl servKts  Community ownership of developmentland except administration 30.39:   Law, Order and Protective     Legal aid except administration 56.8Services10.   Education&apos;and Libraries.       Student awards In Great Britain 212.8Science and ArtsII. Health and Personal Social     Family practitioner services 850.2Services12.   Social Security Whole rjrogounrne except administration 9,578.013.   Other Public Services           Bresitanrmg (capital expenditureX1) 22-214.   Common Services               Civil superannuation 182.1Rates on government property 122,10) The grant to the BBC home service is also excluded from cash limits. It is a transfer withinthe public sector and does not count as pubttc expenditure.
Programme&apos;General descriptionProvision in cmnd 6393for 1976-77fm at 1975Survey prices.    Local authority currentto      expenditure aided by specific14.      grantsVAT paid by local authorities.15.   Northern Ireland705.38MOther public sector expenditure and receipts excluded fromcash limitsNorthern Ireland Departmentsservices analogous to GB services(mainly trade, industry andemployment, housing, health and personal social services and social security)Agricultural support, analogous to GB-Northern Ireland Office, analogous to law, order and protective services in GB657.1,21.?.,50.0-62.0Total exclusionsTotal public expenditure programmes17,734.045,835.6
Appendix 2Comporittoa at Central GoTewaeutBlocks_^ stfmaies ClassificationBlock   xMINISTRY OF AGRICULTUREFISHERIES AND FOOD] .* Pay add general administrative expenses2.   Agriculture and food services andfisheries support?)INTERVENTION BOARD FORAGRICULTURAL PRODUCE1* ptty and generaf administrative expenses2.   Food subsidies (net)CABINET office,* Pay and general administrative expenses(act)CENTRAL OFFICE OF information,* Pay and general administrative expenses(net)2.   Home publicity (net)CHARITY commission.* Pay and general administrative expensesCIVIL SERVICE department.   Central management of the CivilService (net)2.   Computers and telecommunications3.   Civil Service catering (net)CROWN ESTATE office.* Pay and general administrative expensesHER MAJESTY S CUSTOMS ANDEXCISEI.* Pay, general administrative expenses and capital expenditureMINISTRY OF defence* Defence budget (net)DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION ANDSCIENCES)1.* Pay and general adnumatrative expenses(net)2.   Current and some capital expenditureon schools, further education, teacher training, youth service and educationalresearch3.   Current and some capital expenditureon universities4.   libraries, museum, galleries and the arts (net)5.   Science Budget Research Councils (net)UI4A will 7A t(l-3,S),A2-5,A6,Clm 8C1-3HI 4Al-9,AZ,B4-*,SZt2,3,4),C3-3ni 1 A7-8,AZ,B1-6,S8,BZ,CZ,D5-9,E3in 8 A2-8,A9,AZ,Br-2.BZ,CZIX 10 A-C.AZ,XV 1 II,LJHI 3 Fl-2Ht 3 Gxnr 2ixrvscxrvsAXIII 19XIII12XIV 4xrv9XVII 9XIII 6 AI-5.AZI lOAA^A^MO^lA^IBKpartX2).^XIB5X6DX 1 Al(2a),A5-6rD(excIuding Dl(2b)),DZ,E1(1,3).E3,EZX 6A,B1,B2,B2,B4(J-3),C1-2,CZX 1 B1,B3-4,CM,C5.C7-8,CZX3 A3X 14-22^6X7-13
DEPARTMENT OF employment.* Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)2.   Manpower Services Commission (net)3.   Other employment services (netX*)DEPARTMENT OF ENERGY1.* Pay and genera) admiaistcativeexpenses (grots)2.   Nuclear Energy3.   Research and development, industrialsponsorshipDEPARTMENT OF THEENVIRONMENT1.* Pay and general administrative expenses2.   Motorways and trunk roads, new busgrants etc03.   Certain railways and waterways grants4.   Various central environmental services;Sports Council; development commission; royal pahtces and parks;Nature Conservancy Council; historicbuildings and ancient monuments;environmental research and new towns&apos;industrial and commercial investment(net)(*)5.* Property Services Agency: Pay andgeneral administrative expenses (net)6.   Office and general accommodationservices7.   Overseas representation accormaodation services (gross)8.   Rents (UK)9.   Rale Support Grant and supplementarygrants for England and WalesEXCHEQUER AND AUDITDEPARTMENTl.* Pay and general adarinistrativeexpanses (gross)EXPORT CREDITS GUARANTEEDEPARTMENT1* Pay and general administrative expenses (gross)IV 15 ane*) H-3,DZ(2),El,E3-4,F1.2,F5,G2-3,H14-5,IZ,J(exospt App IH(UA2.Y))IV 15 air 15 B2,E2,E6,EZ(2),F3-4,I1-2430H5).J(App M(IIA2,Y))IV8 Gl,G2(l-4,7-8)IV6 Al-8,A12^\Z3LC2-3IV8 Cl-3,D4,El-2,FKM),F2-3,FZ,G2(S-6),G4,GZ,H,Il-2VII1GVKI 3Al(la-b,e, 2a-b*,3a-b*)VIII. 6A1-5XIII 8AI 3VI 1AI-5AZ(2,3)31,C1,D,E1-3,EZ,FJ-JVI 2A2(2),C1VI3D2-4,E3,G1,GZVI 3A4.Bl-2.B3V14HIVI6F1Vin lFl-if so^parUXFaJ^lOXF6-17,F23,FZ,HU1VHI 2A,B-C,D1,EVin 3AI(Jc-d,2c-d,3c-d),AZ,BHIDII2BXIV 1CI HBltoarOC1)XIV lAl-2^41AZ(3-4),D.DZ, El (P*rt)0 EZ0 2AMXIV lA3,AZa)^2XVII1XUI5A1IV I2A4-5.D2.E1
OFFICE OF FAIR TRADING(.* Pay *ed general mAninKtntfivecRpcaact (gro*s)FOREIGN AND commonwealth office .1.* Pay and general admloutrattvoexpenses (*)1.   Oversees representation, overseas information and external relations3.   British CouncilFORESTRY commission.* Pay and general administrativeexpenses2.   Fpseaoff (gross)FRIENDLY SOCIETIES&apos; REGISTRY1.* Pay and general administrativeexpensesGOVERNMENT ACTUARY &quot;5DEPARTMENT1.* Pay and general sdrninisinUiveexpenses,DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH and social SECURITY1.* Pay and general administrative expenses (grow)2.   Health and personal social services(net)HOME OFFICE   f , ^     .1.* Pay and geoej4&quot;s^odw*trt^expew2.   Overseas information broadcastingw . Hi.3.   Law, order and protective services,civil defence and wireless telegraphyregulation (gross)IV 13 Al-2II 1A1,A2(1-2,4&quot;S),BI,B2.(l-3,5),Cl,C2(l-3)H !A2(3),AZ(2),B2(4),B3BZ(l);(partX*).BZ(2),C2(4),CZII 3A1 AZ32-5.BZ.CI-2II 5A1-2,A4A2,(1-2),D1-J,D4(2-8)1DZ,En8D4dXpart)(W)XIV3(partK&quot;)XIV SBn 3Dm io(Appi^-c)HI 10(AppI,D-H)TV 14XTV 8 MJO&amp;SXHSA1-7.B1-2xu a(&quot;)afc?)O2,04-3,G7-8,I(i3)IX 6 Al(2), A2.D1 J)2(AppA), DZIX 7 Al,A7A10,AZeX8)JS5-6IX 8 A20)^W)MA6a).Aa-9,Bia),B2,Ci-2,Dl .   .1X9 A2r4 .IX 11IX 12 Alxni24B    ..II 4 A,AZ(1),AZ(2)      &apos;      &apos; -* &quot; &apos;IX 7 A2-6,A8-*,Bi(2-5),B2-3IX 8 A3(3-4),A4,A6(l-(Z),A7^Aie^l34Bl(3),C3,D2-3 ,DC9A3-7     &apos;IX 11 AI(A3,A51Bl(2),CI-2,C4-6IX 12 BlXin 24 A.C1-2
DEPARTMENT OF industry* Pay and general administrative expenses2   Regional and industrial policy and &apos;reseach and development3.   Assistance to shipbuildingBOARD OF INLAND REVENUE1.* Pay and general administrative expensesLAND REGISTRY1.* Pay and general administrative expensesLORD CHANCELLOR&apos;S department.* Pay and general administrative expenses2.   Legal aid fund administration andjudges&apos; salariesCtiNATIONAL DEBT office.* Pay and general administrative expenses (net)DEPARTMENT FOR NATIONAL SAVINGSI.* Pay and general administrative expenses     Xffilf(net)NORTHERN IRELAND office.* Pay and general administrative expensesIV 3 AHl(a,bM(a,b))IV 16 AI-2, AZIV 1 B1-Z.D1-2IV 3 Al(l(c)-4(c)),A2-5,AZJJI-7,BZIV 4 Al-ZIV5A1,E1.2,EZ,F1IV 16 A3IV 16 ClIV 7 Cl,C3,C4XIII 7XIII 17A2.A4IX 1DC 3 AppAl(a)XUI 92.   Law, order and protective services,grant to the police authority for northern Ireland; and accommodationORDNANCE SURVEY1 .* Pay, general administrative expenses and capital expenditure (gross)MINISTRY OP OVERSEASDEVELOPMENT1.* Pay and general administrative expenses(net)2.   Aid programme (net) t15&apos;PARLIAMENTARY commissioner and HEALTH SERVICECOMMISSIONER1* Pay and general administrative expensesOFFICE OF POPULATION CENSUSESAND surveys.* Pay and general administrative expensesXV 2 Al-Z,BX-Z,DI-Z,El,Gi,HU2,L,Nl-ZXV3A131-2XV 4A1-Z3I-ZXV 2 E2.G2-Z.H2-541-Z.J U2,Kl-Z,M 1-4XV 3 AZXV 4 DI-5XTU 20 AMnSD6(4)II 9 A1-2.AZO 5 FI,FZ,Q1n 8 A-E excluding D4(l)(part00)and D6(4)n 10 B1-3.BZXIV i E (part)&quot;)XIII25Xllt 12 Al-7
DEPARTMENT OF PRICES and consumer PROTECTION1.* Pay and general adnunfetmrve expenses2.   Food subsidies3.   Ceiwm*erVjwwctionPRIVY COUNCIL office * Pay and general administrative expensesPUBLIC RECORD office* Pay and general administrative expensesPUBLIC TRUSTEE office* Pay and general adnrirnstrative expensesPUBLIC WORKS LOAN commission ,* Pay and general administrative expensesHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office.* Pay and general administrative expenses2.   Stationery and printing (net)DEPARTMENT OF trade.* Pay and general administrative expenses2.   Shipping services .   Civil aviation4.   Tourism, regulation of domestic trade andindustry mi oaasamer protection5.   Export promotionHER MAJESTVS TREASURYh* fmM-aaH general administrative expenses2.   Economic and financial rnanagerneiit(&quot;)3.   Seem serviceTREASURY SOLICITOR1.* Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)SCOTTISH office.* Pay and general administrative expensesof main Scottish Departments .DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE.AND FISHERIES FOR SCOTLANDt.   Agricultural services and fineriessupportIV 19 Al,B2(lH2),BZ(2)Cl-2III 5IV 19 A2-]0,B!,B2(3),B5,BZ,C1),C3-*.CZXIII 3XIII13XIII 26 AlXIII10 AlXIV 3 A2(4-5),A4-5,B2(1),B3(1),C2-31Dl-2(&quot;)XIV 3 AI,A2U-3),A1,AX,AZ,B1,B2(2).B*2),BX,CZ(U)IV 11 C9(l)^l,Fl,Gl-2VI 7 Al (except AJ(l(c) JpaxtX16)VI 7 Al(l(c)partX16),A2-6,A8-n,AZVI BA, B1-4,B8-9,B11,BZ( (a,d)),BZ(2)IV II A1--33I, Z,F2-3,FZ*H;GZIV 11 Ci-8,C9(2-8),CZXIII 4B1-2,B5,BZ(2),C1-2,CZ(2),D1,DZXHI 4 Al-2,B3,Bft,CM,CZ(I,3)117rX4Al(i),B,CI(l-2)III 6 DI-3.DZ.FIII 9 CJIV 171VII 2 ElVIII 4 Hl-2IX 13 ApplA(l),Cl,D2,E2(l),E6,Fl(la),H20),Ji(2W2X2IXIII 22 AI-J,AZ iID uAl-9,AZ,B4WS,BZ(2-3),Cl,D4-6,DZ,E1-9,EZ(2-4)^!Z,G] -8,GZm 9 AM.AZ.Si-3,CM,CZ
SCOTTISH COURTS administration.* Pay and general administrative expensesSCOTTISH DEVELOPMENTDEPARTMENT1.   Motorways and trunk roads, grants to shipping and air services, Peteiheadharbour etc(&apos;g)2.   Other environmental services (net)3.   Rate Support GrantJX 2 Al-2^1-4VI 4 A1-7.AZ.GVI 5 B,Cl,C24iM,BVin 4 D3,G,H3,J(excI J4),LIXVII2SCOTTISH ECONOMIC PLANNINGDEPARTMENT1.   Grants-in-aid to the Highlands and islands Development Board and theScottish Development Agency, tourism,publicity, land and buildings and new towns industrial and commercialinvestment (net)(i*)SCOTTISH EDUCATION department.   New building for schools, teacher training and further education2.   Current and some capital expenditureon schools, teacher training, further education, educational research, youthservices, sports, social work, libraries,galleries, museums and other artsIV 17 B,C,D,E1-2JH1.IX2,Bl(lb),Cl(lb)X2 AI(2),A3,Bl(la).BI(2),Cl(la),Cl(2),E,F-H,JX4AX 23-25XI 3SCOTTISH HOME AND HEALTHDEPARTMENT1.   Health (net)2.   Law, order and protective services(gross)XI 2 A-F(20)G(except GZ(2) ),I, 31-3(except Jl(4))IX 13 B1,C2-7,D1,E2(2-3),E3,E5,B7,Fl(lb),Fl(4),Gl,H3-4.ilDEPARTMENT OF THE registers of scotland.* Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)QUEEN&apos;S AND LORD TREASURERSREMEMBRANCER1.* Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)REGISTRAR GENERAL&apos;S OFFICE,scotland.* Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)SCOTTISH RECORD office *. Pay and general administrative expenses(gross)XHI18 AIIX 5 AI(I-2),BI-3Xni 16 Al-3XIII14 Al-ZIt
WELSH OFFICEpi)J.* Psy and general administrative expenses(gross)Z   Motorway! and trunk roads, etc.3.   Other environmental services:Sporta Council, historic buildings, new towns&apos; industrial and commercialinvestment, ctcX22)4.   Libraries, museums, galleries and otherartsS.   Health and personal social services.   Regional Development. WebbDevelopment Agency, Tourism, etc.VTX4EIXn 23 Al-3 AZVI 6 Al-3, AZ(2),BI-5,C2VHI5E,Gl-5,GZ,I,Kl-2X 3 A,B,CXI 4 Atti),C-F, (except F3),H-J (exceptJ3(2)),LW 1BB1.C1-2Foomrtes to Appendix 2(i) This block includes loans from the Consolidated Fund to the Agricultural MortgageCorporation.P) 93% of 111 Bl, Accommodation costs, is included in block MOD Land S%. attributed to programme 4 J Industrial Innovation, is in block DOE 6.(*) The following voted expenditure on education building is included in block DES/LA 1:X 1 AI(2bLAM32,C4,C6,C9,Dl(2b)3&apos;(2)32-(4) maximum block, tochides National Dock Labour Board construction financed by levies ondock etnpIoiyBrs.,(3) This biock mtiuocs extra receipts payable to the Consolidated Fund in respect of tollsreceived from the Severn Bridge.(*) Tms block includes loans from the National Loans Fund to new towns.O The greater part of XTV1 Et, Acquisiuons and new-works, is included in DOE 6, but that part attributable to the Aid Programme is included in block ODM 2.(*) This block includes extra receipts payable to the Consolidated Fund in respect of thetxrhangr of British armed forces&apos; vouchers in Germany.(&apos;) About 50% of meat receipts from consular fees are excluded from cash limits.(10) 90% of II 8 D*0), Commonwealth Education Co-operation, is included in FCO 2, andthe remainder, which is attributed to the Aid Programme, is in ODM 2.(ii) All of XIV 3, Stationery and printing, is included is HMSO1 and 2, except a small part,attributed to programme 22 Overseas Information which is in FCO 2.01) Patients&apos; pocket money, which b part of XI1 A and F, is excluded from the cash limit.(&quot;) Grants to local authorities in respect of provision of secure accommodation, which arepart of XI11, an excluded from cash limits.(&quot;) This block includes expenditure from the Consolidated Fund for Judges&apos; salaries,(is) This block indudea payments to the Internationa] Development Association through theNational Loans Fund; expenditure from the Consolidated Fund for the UK contribution. -  to the e.c. Aid Programmes; and extra receipts payable to the Consolidated Fund inrespect of repayment of loans.n
(is) About 10% of these coastguard expenses are in DT2; the rest fall into DTI.(&quot;) This block includes expenditure from the Consolidated Fund on the civil list, the grant to the royal trustees and the grant to the Tithe Redemption Annuities Account.(is) This block includes extra receipts payable to the Consolidated Fund in respect of tollsreceived from the Erskinc Bridge.(&quot;) This block includes loans from the National Loans Fund to new towns.(20) Patients&apos; pocket money which is part of XI 2 AI is excluded from cash limits.(2i) Voted expenditure on education building in VIII 5 J2-3 is included in block WO/LA 3.(a) This block includes loans from the National Loans Fund to new towns.(M) Patients&apos; pocket money which is part of XI 4 AI is excluded from cash limits.Printed in England for Her Majesty&apos;&quot; Stationery Office by Williams Lea, LondonDd K      3/76

</content>
</cab>
