<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/25/0 images: 48-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this  DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF   HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1948SECRET Copy No. 3 0CP. (48) 6827th February, 1948CABINETPREPARATION OF LEGISLATION FOR THE 1948-49 session memorandum by the Lord President of the council the Committee on Future Legislation have considered in consultation withthe Ministers concerned and with Parliamentary Counsel, what preparatory workon legislation for the 1948-49 Session should now be put in hand, withoutprejudice to the decisions which the Cabinet will have to take later in the year on the final content of The King&apos;s Speech. In carrying out this task we have thought it desirable to consider also what legislation it will be necessary or desirable to pass in the 1949-50 Session, which will be the last/possible) of this parliament.2. We have assumed that the 1948-49 Session will run from October 1948to August 1949, and that the 1949-50 Session will run from October 1949 to the dissolution. We recognise that if the Parliament Bill does not become law inthe current Session our proposals will have to be readjusted.3. In accordance with the procedure followed last year our proposals coveronly major and medium-sized Bills; but we are collecting information aboutminor Bills and we hope that the Cabinet will authorise us to arrange for somework on the preparation of Bills of this class to be done during the next sixmonths. When the final programme for 1948-49 comes to be settled it will also have to include the usual annual Bills (e.g., Finance Bill, Expiring Laws Con-tinuance Bill) and a certain number of essential Bills, the need for which cannotbe foreseen at present. In particular we may conceivably be faced with theneed for substantial amendment of some of the major measures passed in thefirst three Sessions of this Parliament (e.g., the Coal Industry NationalisationAct, the National Health Service Act, the National Insurance Act).4.   We have paid special regard to the following points: (a) A substantial number of Bills should be ready for introduction as soonas the new Session begins and the bulk of the programme should beready for introduction before the Christmas Recess.(b) The Government cannot expect to carry through a heavy programme oflegislation in the 1949-50 Session and any major Bills in the 1949-50Programme must be ready for introduction not later than October1949.(c) Too heavy a burden of legislation should not be placed on any one department.5. We recommend that the provisional programme of major and medium-sized Bills for the 1948-49 Session should be : (a) Bills to be ready for introduction in October 1948(i) Major Bills-Legal Aid.Legal Aid (Scotland).Iron and Steel.Water (Scotland).Criminal Justice (Scotland).Magistrates&apos; Courts.Sea Fish Industry.34992 b
(ii) Medium-sized Bills Wireless Telegraphy.Coast Protection.Patents and Designs.Civil Defence (short Bill).Licensing.Pests.Milk (Special Designations).Motorways.(b) Bills to be ready for introduction before Christmas 1948(i) Major Bills Agricultural Marketing.Food Policy.Housing.Housing (Scotland).National Parks and Amenities.Cable and Wireless,(ii) Medium-sized Bills Nurses.War Damage (Public Utilities).Breaking-up of Streets.Superannuation.Notes on these Bills are given in Annex I.6.   We would draw the attention of the Cabinet to the following points: (a) First drafts of the Iron and Steel Bill and the Milk (Special Designations)Bill have already been prepared.(b) We have authorised the Ministers concerned to give instructions to parliamentary Counsel on the Legal Aid Bill, the Wireless TelegraphyBill and the Coast Protection Bill and have agreed that the Secretaryof State for Scotland should put in hand the preparation of the legal aid (Scotland) Bill, the Water (Scotland) Bill and the criminla justice (Scotland) Bill. So far as can be foreseen, these Bills arecertain to figure in the 1948-49 Programme.(p) The inclusion of a Sea Fish Industry Bill in the 1948-49 programme will depend on the decisions reached by the White Fish IndustryCommittee and the Cabinet on the proposals of the Fisheries ministers for reorganising the white fish industry. ,        ,(d) We had some doubt about the inclusion of the Milk (Special Designafdons)Bill and the Motorways Bill in the 1948-49 Programme on the groundthat any considerable use of the powers to be conferred by these bills in 1949 or 1950 would create demands for pasteurisation machinery and for civil engineering resources which could not be met. We were,however, assured by the Minister of Food that any demands forpasteurisation machinery would arise only gradually and by theMinisters of Transport and Town and Country Planning that theearly enactment of the Motorways Bill was most desirable in orderto enable the routes of future motorways to be planned and protected against encroachment.(e) Two of the most important Bills in the 1948-49 Programme will be theAgricultural Marketing Bill and the Food Policy Bill. It wassuggested to us that these Bills might conceivably be combined, butit may be inexpedient to attempt to include so much in a single Bill.We think it important that the questions of policy connected withthese measures should be brought, before the appropriate CabinetCommittee and the Cabinet as soon as possible. &quot; &apos;(/) The Home Secretary urged us to include in the 1948-49 Programme aSports Grounds (Licensing) Bill which would require sports groundsaccommodating large crowds to be licensed in the interests of public safety. In his view the Government ought to take steps to avoid are currence of the accident which took place at Bolton in 1946 by giving effect to the recommendations made in the report on that accident.As against this it should be noted that the risk of a further accidentdoes not seem to be very great and that the proposed Bill would notbe welcome to football clubs or their supporters.
7. We ask the Cabinet to note that the following Bills (notes on whichare given in Annex II) may have to be included in the 1949-50 legislative programme : (a) Major Bills Rent Control.Merchant Shipping (Safety at Sea).(b) Medium-sized Bills &apos;General Medical Council.Dentists.National Parks (Scotland).Libraries (Scotland).Shops (Closing Hours).Adoption.Sugar Industry.Land Drainage., Limitation of Actions.Justices of the Peace.Civil Defence (longer Bill).It will be observed that the list includes a Rent Control Bill to give effect to therecommendations of the Ridley Committee. The Minister of Health considersthat it is necessary to legislate on this subject in the lifetime of this parliament and is satisfied that the Bill could not be ready for inclusion in the 1948-49Programme. On the other hand, we think that there is much to be said for avoiding what is bound to be a most complicated and controversial Bill in thelast Session of this Parliament.8. Lastly, we wish to stress two general points connected with the prepara-tion of legislation for the last two Sessions of this Parliament: (a) it is more than ever important that Ministers should make realisticestimates of the time required for the preparation of their Bills andshould themselves see that any estimates given are adhered to. Inpast Sessions we have frequently found that the time required tosettle questions of policy has been underestimated and that ministers at times have shown more energy in urging the claims of their bills for inclusion in the Legislative Programme than in getting instruc-tions on their Bills sent to Parliamentary Counsel in good time.. (b) The mention of a Bill in this memorandum should not be regarded asauthorising the Minister concerned to anticipate The King&apos;s Speechesfor the next two Sessions by promising that the Bill will be introduced in one or other of these Sessions. In any case this should never bedone without consulting the Leader of the House of Commons.9.   To sum up, the Cabinet are invited : (1) To agree that, pending the formulation of a final Legislative programme for the 1948-49 Session, Parliamentary Counsel should proceed withthe preparation of the Bills listed in paragraph 5, in so far as this can be done without prejudice to the demands of the current Session&apos;slegislation.(2) To authorise the Committee on Future Legislation to arrange for thepreparation of an appropriate number of minor Bills to be ready for introduction in October 1948.(3) To authorise the Committee on Future Legislation to review from timeto time the progress made with the preparation of legislation forthe 1948-49 Session and to make such minor adjustments in the provi-sional programme as may seem desirable.(4) To note that the Legislative Programme for the 1949-50 Session willpossibly have to include the Bills listed in paragraph 7.H. M.Office of the Lord President ofthe Council, S. W. 1,27th February, 1948.34992 b 2
ANNEX IMajor Bills to be Ready for Introduction in October 1948DepartmentLord ChancellorsDepartmentScottish office ministry of Supply   ...Scottish office scottish office home Office   ......Ministry of Agricultureand Fisheries and scottish OfficeBillLegal Aid    ......Legal Aid (Scotland)Iron and SteelWater (Scotland)Criminal Justice(Scotland)Magistrates&apos; Courts ...Sea Fish IndustryRemarksTo implement the Rushcliffe Committee&apos;srecommendations.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.The counterpart of the English Legal Aid BUI.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To reorganise the iron and steel industry.Estimated number of Clauses: 40-50.To amend the Water (Scotland) Act, 1946,and to modify the Scottish water rating system.Estimated number of Clauses: 50.The counterpart of the English criminla justice Bill.Estimated number of Clauses: 60-70.To give effect to the recommendations of theRoche Committee and to make certain other reforms.Estimated number of Clauses: 50.To provide for the reorganisation of the whitefish industry.Estimated number of Clauses: 45.Medium-Sized Bills to be Ready for Introduction in October 1948DepartmentPost OfficeBillWireless Telegraphy.Ministry of Health and   : Coast ProtectionScottish office board of TradeHome Office and scottish office home Office and scottish office ministry of Food and scottish OfficePatents and Designs ...Civil Defence(short Bill)Licensing     ...      ...Ministry of Agriculture      Pestsand FisheriesMilk (SpecialDesignations)Ministry of Transport      MotorwaysRemarksTo provide for the control of electricalinterference with wireless telegraphy andother services using etheric waves and generally to impae&amp; and make permanentthe legislation on wireless telegraphy.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To assign responsibility for the carrying out and maintenance of certain sea defenceworks and to enable Exchequer grants to bepaid towards the cost of such works.Estimated number of Clauses: 30-40.To implement the recommendations of theSwann Committee.Estimated number of Clauses: 30-40.To enable local authorities to start nucleuscivil defence services.Estimated number of Clauses: 5.To provide for public control of licensed premises in New Towns and otherwise toamend the licensing law.Estimated number of Clauses: 20-30.To amend the Rats and Mice (Destruction)Act, 1919; to confer on the Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries permanent powers for the control of pests in England andWales; and to enable Exchequer grants tobe made to local authorities for pestdestruction.Estimated number of Clauses: 35.To make it compulsory for retailers inscheduled areas to sell only milk conformingto a special designation under the Milk(Special Designations) Regulations.Estimated number of Clauses: 15.To empower highway authorities to constructmotorways and other roads reserved forspecial classes of traffic. .Estimated number of Clauses: 17.
Major Bills to be Ready fob Introduction before Christmas 1948DepartmentMinistry of Agricultureand Fisheries and scottish office ministry of FoodScottish office ministry of Town and country PlanningPost OfficeBillAgricultural MarketingFood Policy ...Ministry of Health   ...      HousingHousing (Scotland) ...National   Parks   andAmenitiesCable and WirelessRemarksTo give effect to recommendations of theLucas Committee.Estimated number of Clauses:  100.To define the functions of the Ministry ofFood and to give permanent statutory authority for the exercise of its power.Estimated number of Clauses: about 50.To give effect to the recommendations of theSilkin and Hobhouse Committees.Estimated number of Clauses: 50-70.The counterpart of the English Housing Bill.Estimated number of Clauses: 50-70.To provide for the establishment of nationalparks, the improvement of access to the countryside  and for  the  protection of&apos;amenities in England and Wales.Estimated number of Clauses: 60.To deal with the transfer of Cable and Wirelessassets in the United Kingdom to the PostOffice and with the incorporation of theCommonwealth Telecommunications Board.The number of Clauses cannot yet beestimated.Medium-Sized Bills to be Ready for Introduction before Christmas 1948DepartmentMinistry of Health and scottish office treasury       ......Ministry of TransportTreasuryBillNursesWar Damage(Public Utilities)Breaking-up of StreetsSuperannuationRemarksTo give effect to the recommendations of theworking party on the training and recruit-ment of nurses and to alter the constitutionof the General Nursing Council.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To provide for a scheme of contributions from and payments to public utility undertakings in respect of war damage.Estimated number of Clauses: up to 40.To give effect to the recommendations of theCarnock Committee on the breaking-up ofstreets by statutory undertakers.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To amend the Civil Service superannuationcode, and in particular to provide for ascheme of pensions for widows and depen-dants of civil servants and for the prematureretirement of inefficient civil servants.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.ANNEX IIMajor and Medium-Sized Bills which may have to be Introduced in the1949-50 SessionDepartmentMinistry of Health   ...Ministry of transport ministry of Health and scottish office ministry of Health and scottish Office(a) Major BillsBillsRemarksRent ControlMerchant Shipping(Safety at Sea)To give effect to the recommendations of theRidley Committee.Estimated number of Clauses: 100.To ratify the conclusions of the international conference on the Safety of Life at Sea to beheld in London in 1948.Estimated number of Clauses: 50.(b) Medium-Sized BillsGeneral MedicalCouncilDentistsTo reform the constitution of the general medical Council, to give the right of appealto the Courts from General Medical Councildecisions, and to prescribe a pre-registrationyear in hospital for doctors.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To alter the consitution of the Dental Boardand to effect changes in dentists&apos; training.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.
department Scottish office scottish office home Office and scottish office home Office and scottish office ministry of Agricultureand fisheries ministry of Agricultureand FisheriesLord ChancellorsDepartmentLord ChancellorsDepartmentHome Office and scottish Office(6) Medium-Sized Bills (continued)BillNational Parks-(Scotland)Libraries (Scotland) ...Shops (Closing Hours)AdoptionSugar IndustryLand Drainage      ...Limitation of ActionsJustices of the PeaceCivil Defence(Longer Bill)remarks to give effect to the recommendations of theScottish Committee on National Parks.The number of Clauses cannot yet  beestimated.To amend the existing law relating torlibraries in Scotland.Estimated number of Clauses: 15-20.To give effect to the recommendations of theGowers Committee.Estimated number of Clauses: 20.To give effect to certain recommendations ofthe Curtis Committee and to amend theAdoption Acts in other respects.Estimated number of Clauses: 30.To continue the Sugar Industry Act, 1942.The number of  Clauses cannot  yet  beestimated.To bring up to date the existing legislation relating to land drainage.The number of  Clauses cannot yet  beestimated.To give effect to the recommendations of theTucker Committee.The  number  of Clauses cannot  yet  beestimated.To igive effect to the recommendations of theRoyal Commission on Justices of the Peace.The number of Clauses cannot yet beestimated. , ,To deal with the general obligations to be imposed on local authorities, public utility undertakings and industry in respect of shelter and other matters.The number of Clauses cannot yet beestimated.


</content>
</cab>
