<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/25/0 images: 61-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  majesty&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1948 *SECRET copy No. 30CP. (48) 713rd March, 1948CABINETTHE CZECHOSLOVAK CRISISMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsConclusionsCzechoslovakia is in process of being absorbed into the Soviet Orbitas a result of a coup d&apos;Etat on typical Communist lines. Action committees have seized all strategic points in the State with the connivance of the police and armed forces and a purge of the whole country is in progress. We must expect trumped-up charges against our Czech friends and possibly againstmembers of the Western Embassies.2. This outcome is highly detrimental to our interests, but there is nothingwe can do about it in Czechoslovakia itself except to express our disapproval.The French and United States Governments have joined His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the issue of the declaration of 26th February, at Annou I.3. Subject to the views of the United States and French Governments, we propose to preserve frigid but correct relations with the new czechoslovak government and to maintain our contacts with the Czechoslovak people sofar as we can. In pursuance of this policy we should not remove our Ambassadorfrom Czechoslovakia any more than we have from other Eastern european countries. We have now heard from the United States Government that they wish to recall 4their Ambassador from Prague. I intend to discourage this.We should mark our disapproval of the Social Democratic Party who. by joining the Communists, made it possible for the latter to seize power, lest we encourageother continental Socialists (e.g., Signor Nenni) to think they can also aid andabet the Communists with impunity.4. We should organise our publicity with a view to appearing as strongas we can, lest other friends of Great Britain (e.g., the Scandinavian countries)should be encouraged to think they must compound with the Russians while there is yet time. In the long run we shall only retain our friends if we arestrong.Course of Events in Czechoslovakia5. The crisis in Czechoslovakia came to a head on 17th February, whenM. Gottwald, the Communist Prime Minister, suspended a meeting of the coalition Government after certain non-Communist Ministers had complained that the Minister of the Interior (also a Communist) had failed to carry out aCabinet decision annulling the appointments of Communists to positions in thePolice Force by which that force was in effect being packed with Communistnominees.6. On 20th February the Czech Socialist Party, People&apos;s Party and SlovakDemocrat Ministers, having received no satisfaction, refused to attend a cabinet meeting and submitted their resignations to President Benes.7. The Communist Party then issued a statement to the effect that the crisis,which the non-Communist Parties had provoked, involved a threat to public security and that they had discovered a plot- against the State.   They alleged35018 b
that the resigning Ministers had put themselves in the position of a subversiveopposition. The Communist Party had therefore decided to mobilise all the forcesof the working people in support of the Government.8. In actual fact, the non-Communist Ministers had of course resigned onthe broad issue that majority decisions of the Cabinet were being blocked toy.; the communists when unacceptable to them.9. Meanwhile, Communist &quot;Action Committees&quot; were formed all overthe country and seized a number of Ministries, public offices, the - Prague^ radiostation and the administration of certain towns. Arms were issued to the com-mittees in large numbers. The Communist-controlled Ministry of the Interiorhas published an edict to the effect that any member of an Action Committeecan be dismissed by a higher committed if Mis is recommended by the local com-mittee concerned. Thus the whole machinery of Action Committees can in effectbe directed from above. In Slovakia, the non-Communist members of the SlovakBoard of Trustees, i.e., the local administration, were arrested and Slovakia thusalso came under Communist control through a virtual: coup d&apos; tat. In bothSlovakia and the Czech lands those Trade Unions which were under Communistcontrol were mobilised for action, and in particular the Printers&apos; Union refusedto be a party to the printing of any but pro-Communist publications,,i^^this, wayhelping to stifle the free and democratic expression of opinion. The newspapersof the Czech Socialists and People&apos;s Parties have been informed that ho morepaper will be allocated to them. The Communist Minister Of Information was able to control the radio. For instance, he successfully prevented the Ministerof Food (a Social Democrat) and the Minister of Posts (People&apos;s Party) frombroadcasting.&apos; &quot; &apos; :r;ji   &apos;       &apos; t&quot; &apos; &apos; .*mmi.  s ** / ;: 10. On 23rd February it was announced that the Czech Social DemocratParty had decided to accept M, Gottwald&apos;s offer to them to join the communists in forming the nucleus of a reconstituted coalition which Would not include theresigning Ministers. But this decision was, according to reliable press reports,only announced after the police, under the orders of the Communist Minister ofthe Interior, had occupied the Party&apos;s premises and thrown out those of theleaders who did not wish to co-operate with the - Communists:: -wj&apos; -.: ,11. On 25th February it was officially announced that President Benes had accepted the resignations of: the rion-Communist Ministers, and that he, had approved a new Government under the leadership of M. Gottwald. In this government the Communists have taken over all the remaining Ministriesnecessary to make their control complete, including those of Justice, foreign trade and Education. They already held the key Ministries.of the Interior(including control of theipolice), Information, Social Welfare, Finance,, Agricul-ture and Internal Trade. Minor remaining: posts have been allotted to theSocial Democrats and to some renegade members of the Peopled Party, and the czech Socialist Party. The Government includes two &quot; riori-party&quot;! men.namely, M. Masaryk arid General Svoboda, who remain at their posts as ministers of Foreign&apos; Affairs. arid National Defence resepectiyely. GeneralSvoboda has promised the Communists the support of the armed -forces through-out the crisis.12. A full-scale purge affecting every branchOof, Czechosloyak life, is inprogress. President Benes has resisted so far as he could, but he has beenpowerless, and may, it is rumoured, resign. There has been little or no attempt by the population to resist. The Czechoslovak people were hypnotised by thedanger approaching them from the east. M. Masaryk, the Minister foi5 ForeignAffairs, had already lent himself to the, Russian manoeuvre by advertising the alleged revival of the German danger arid by criticising the plans of&apos;the, western powers in Germany, and has finally taken office in the hew Croverriihent: Theleading Social Democrats, including both M. Lausman and M. Fierlinger, Have alsojoined the new Government, though they have littler if any, power..   , &apos;,13. There is no open sign in this of Soviet interference, but we have knownfor.some time that trouble, was to be expected from the Communists in Czecho-slovakia and the sudden arrival in Prague just before the crisis(brbkeb^M - orina Deputy Soviet Minister of Foreign Affairs arid former ambassador in Prague&apos;,can hardly have been a coincidence, moreespecially &amp;s he feturriednto Moscowimmediately it was over. ,
14. It wili be seen from the foregoing that the crisis has been artificially anddeliberately provoked in Czechoslovakia. The same methods of force and intimidation-dation already exploited in the other Eastern European countries have been usedto bring about the suspension of free parliamentary institutions and the establjsh-ment of the disguised dictatox*ship of a single party under the cloak of aGovernment of National Union. This last point has been made clear in the joint declaration issued on 26th February by the Governments of the TJnited Stales,France and Britain.; It is impossible to regard this as in any way a, democraticor parliamentary solution, and the violence of the methods used by the Com-munists is more than ever significant, seeing that elections to enable the czechoslovak people to express their real opinions freely were due to be held inthe next three months. Some further reflections on the crisis and on the policywhich we should now pursue are contained in Mr. Dixon&apos;s telegrams No. 19,Saving, and No. 179, of which copies are to be found at Annexes I and II.The Lessons of the Czech Crisis15. Czechoslovakia is now lost to Western Democracy and the western world except in so far as the Russians, acting through the &quot;Czech Communists,allow contacts and trade to continue. If this process is not to be continued stillfurther West it seems desirable that we should analyse the lessons to be drawn from the case of Czechoslovakia in the hope that it may save us from a similardefeat in the case of Italy and perhaps later in France, where our interests wouldbe vitally endangered&apos;.116. The first and most fundamental error of the non-Communists in Czecho-slovakia was made two years ago. After the last elections, when the Communistsgained over 30 per cent, of the seats in the Czech Parliament and were the strongest, party, the non-Communists pushed the Communists forward into theleading positions, assuming that they would be sure to make a mess of govern-ment in the difficult post-war period and would be discredited. How they couldbelieve this after what had happened in Poland in 1945 has always been amystery. The Communists naturally made their control of the Ministry of theInterior a condition for their co-operation and from the moment that the policefell under the control of a Communist Minister the die was cast. It is only fair to say that as the Communists at the elections in the spring of 1946 obtained30 per cent, of the seats in Parliament, were the largest party, and controlledthe principal trade unions, it would have been a difficult decision for PresidentBenes to take to exclude them from the Government, especially as the under-standing reached with the Russians before liberation had been that a NationalFront to include all the parties would be formed. However, the lesson is therefor all to see.17. In all the countries within the Soviet orbit, including Czechoslovakia,the essential key which the Communists were able to use in order to gain controlof the situation has been control of the Police and to a lesser extent of the armed forces: Experience shows that it is absolutely impossible for the ordinary processes of democracy to continue if the Communists are able to use the Police to intimidatetheir opponents and to trump up charges of plots and conspiracies. therefore the control of the Ministry of the Interior by reliable non-Coriimunists is a primarynecessity for any further attempt to resist the spread of Communism elsewhere.18. Even if the Police, and Gendarmerie are under: non-Communist control,it is equally essentialstoensure! that they are not penetrated, or, if some degree of communist penetratiop is unavoidable,! that the key positions are held by reliablemen and that the nerve centres for controlling the forces concerned are definitelysecure and dan be relied upon in an emergency. ,     ( -si. 19. Control of the Armed forces is also essential. In the Czech case,President Benes would no doubt have been able to regain control of the situationin spite, of the police being underCommunist control if General Svoboda,, theMinister of Defence, had not thrown hi his iot,with,the Communists, and prevented the armed forces from taking any part in the crisis, when the Communists tookdirect action to seize Ministries, towns, Sic. -^. .20. ; The Communist control of thie Ministry of Information is another keywhichjthe. Communists have! used with, great effect, since it cbntfols broadcasting and the press., oi ^ioi-fjp-&apos;/h^\.rintu:; ffw, -kr^Mili &apos;*rj icrviswidoi v-:m -yiajjim35018 ^kdmmrmi rndJ tm kmim   y.av -
21. The open political methods of the Communists when they are in a coalition Government are shown from the Czechoslovak example to be no lessdahgerous than their subversive and penetration methods. Even the apparentlybourgeois M. Gottwald turns out to be a wolf in sheep&apos;s clothing. The Communistsused their position in the Czechoslovak Government, as they have done elsewhere,in order to create dissension in other parties, and by spreading and exploitingslanders and false accusations against individual Ministers gradually to eliminatefrom power all those who were not their stooges. Their current aim in all thecountries of Eastern Europe is the creation of a people&apos;s Front, which means a Government in which the key positions are held by Communists and in whichrepresentatives of other parties who are reliable stooges or fellow travellers take&apos;part and give an air of respectability to the whole combination. The Communistsattain this state of affairs by various methods, but the result is always the same.Therefore the cardinal error is ever to let them into a Government in the vainhope that they will play the game according to Westminster rules. In countrieswithin the Soviet orbit this has been difficult to avoid, but there is no reason why we should encourage it elsewhere, or encourage or: countenance parties (such assign or Nenni&apos;s) which persist in playing the Communist game.22. One of the points which have gone most against us in Eastern Europehas been the fact that we cannot help our friends there, and that the russians had armed forces on the spot or in the vicinity and could act whenever they wishedto do so. The fact is that continental electorates are impressed by power, andin the East of Europe we have not had power. In Western Europe it may be different. Nevertheless, I think we should draw the lesson from the Czechoslovakcrisis and perhaps also from the incidents in the Gulf of Mexico and the Antarcticand avoid emphasising our weakness. It may be economically and even in some respects politically necessary to stress the economies we are making in the armed forces of the Crown, but in foreign affairs it is a very grave disadvantage. : Ifwe are strong we shall have friends, and if we are not strong our friends will makethe best terms they can with our enemies.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,3rd March, 1948.ANNEX ICopy of telegram (No. 19, Saving) of 27th February, 1948, from His Majesty&apos;ambassador, Prague, to the Foreign OfficeMy telegram No. 149.The following supplementary reflections may be useful: 2. The most striking feature of the events of the past week is the speedwith which they have developed. On 21st February, when the twelve Ministersoffered their resignations to the President, parliamentary institutions were stillfunctioning more or less normally and the inroads which the Communists hadbeen able to make on the four freedoms were still comparatively small;Discussions had been going on in committees of the Government and of theNational Front about the date of the elections and about the Constitution andthere was a general assumption behind all the talk that more or less free electionswould in due course be held. Calculations were being made as to how this or that manoeuvre might benefit one party or another for electoral purposes and thepoliticians of the Right and Centre appeared to be untroubled by any sense ofimpending calamity. Four days later the dictatorship of the Communist Partyover all walks of life had been proclaimed and installed and the Cabinet crisisas such was over. The whole character of the State had been changed in less thana hundred hours.3. There is naturally some disposition on the part of Czechs generally to blame the leaders of the Czech Socialist and People&apos;s Parties for having prepare the trap in which they have been caught and for having by jtheir resignationsgratuitously presented the Communists with their opportunity. Goftwaid ishimself reported to have said that he blessed the persons who advised the ministers to resign, and those Social Democrats who have an understanding of the situationand are not followers of Fierlinger are particularly quick to reproach the&apos;leadersof the other parties for their responsibility.
4.   Such reproaches are wide of the mark.  We now know that the meetingof works&apos; councils which had been fixed several days previously for Sunday,22nd February, had been intended by the Communists to be more than a meredemonstration.  It was to have been the first step on the road towards the seizure of power which we have every reason to believe they had been ordered by moscow to follow.   The Czech Socialists and People&apos;s Party leaders knew or guessedthis to be the case.   It was their object by resigning on Friday, 20th February,to capture the initiative from the Communists, disrupt their plans and bring the weight of the presidential authority into the scale before it was too late.   Theyhad grounds for being confident that the enterprise would succeed since their information and their hopes were shared with the President and their courseof action had his approval, as we now know.  If they are to be blamed, it is for not anticipating the force and speed of the Communist reaction and also for placing the whole of their reliance on a man whose health was precarious and whose record showed his resolution to be dubious in a supreme moment of crisis.President Benes has said before that one of the weaknesses of Czechoslovakia isthat it contains too many calculators.  On this occasion he himself has been thearch-calculator.   The great demonstrations of strength put on at short notice bythe Communists on Saturday, 21st February, and Sunday, 22nd February, madea deep impression on him and there can be no doubt that he was even moreimpressed by the evidence which must have reached him of Russian support.An obvious step would have been to call on the army of which he is commander-in-chief, but I suspect that his calculation was that if he stood by the democraticpolitical leaders to the extent of using the forces of the State the result wouldhave been bloodshed and open Russian intervention, which his whole outlook andtemperament made it impossible for him to contemplate.5. It is unnecessary to have any special knowledge now to realise that the communists, though the preparations were kept closely secret, must have beenprepared for some time to take power by violent means. The events of the last few days make this perfectly clear. The committees of public safety or &apos;&apos; ActionCommittees &quot; as they are called, which have sprung up all over the country andin every department of life, local government, public administration, ministries,universities, factories, workshops, professions, &amp;c, must have been prepared wellin advance. The purges have been going on too quickly and smoothly for the lists of victims not to have been already drawn up. The incriminating materialallegedly found in the premises of the other parties cannot have been forged ata day&apos;s notice. And it must have been some time ago that the Communistsperfected the organisation which has enabled them to bring the workers on to the streets at a momenfs; notice in armed and roughly disciplined formations.Neither the Czech Communists nor the Soviet Government can have expectedthat the democratic world would fail to understand the blatant and bare-facedcharacter of the coup. If they had wished to throw dust in our eyes matters wouldhave been handled more insidiously and the process of communication would have proceeded as elsewhere in stages. The inference is that the-Soviet Governmenthave decided that their interests require immediate and complete consolidation oftheir position where they are able to impose it, and that they have abandoned anypretence of caring about the opinion of the West.6. But, if I may risk a generalisation, there still seem to be far too manyordinary Czechs who, though depressed and even disgusted by the prospects, havenot yet realised the significance of what has happened and who still cling to the belief that everything will be all right in the end That is why our publicity andparticularly our broadcasts are of such importance.ANNEX IICopy of Telegram (No. 179) of 1st March, 1948, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador,Prague, to the Foreign OfficeYOUR telegram No. 2383 to Washington., Following considerations and recommendations regarding our attitude to new Czechoslovak regime are based on appreciation contained.in my telegramsNo. 149 and 19, Saving, and on the assumption that Anglo-Czechoslovak rela-tions will inevitably be conditioned by wider issue of relations between WesternGreat Powers and Soviet Government which evidently cannot remain unafftcted by events in Czechoslovakia.
2 The pattern of the coup d&apos; tat suggests that objective is complete- com-munisation of the country, T^e process ^ipPp^fcrMi^fPg^^bare-faced than anything we have seen in. Poland xu- satellite countries, partly because it will be necessary to trample down tradition and recent connexionsof Czechs with the West and Western ideas,&apos;, and partly, taa^iiiMtw*Qm o*the coup seem to have been determined that the job must be completed quickly.3 It seems to me that the immediate crux in relations of new regime with western Powers may arise on questions of persecuting prominent democraticCzechs and allegations of espionage, &amp;c.; against officials [? omissionJ western powers If, in the process of eliminating Western influences, the^ Government doproceed to trials of democrats * on charges of treasonable collaboration with western Powers, this will add greatly to indignation of our public opinion and make it difficult to maintain even a semblance of normal relations with the newCzechoslovak regime though relations of the kind maintained with [group undecypherable] Bulgaria might be maintained.4 The new Czechoslovak Government have not yet declared their hand inthis respect and it is possible that, so long as men like Gottwald and Clementisare in power, some degree of moderation may prevail, but my information isthat we must expect real power here to be exerted by men like Slansky (a sadistic[group undecypherable: ? type of] Jew) and Cepicka (a criminal type) andthat influence [group undecypherable] westernised figures like Gottwald andClementis is likely to diminish. : r A, ;- 5. The final word will no doubt be given by the Soviet Government who may now feel that they can disregard reaction of Western Powers to proceedings in czechoslovakia and may indeed be planning to oust us from here. Their object would be to have a freer hand in governing the country and to eliminate whatinfluence they suspect we might be able to exert either by urging moderation onrulers of ,the\ country or by maintaining a flicker of resistance among &apos; theinhabitants. . ;6. It would follow that if only to counter objectives of the Soviet government it would be in our interest, to maintain our normal representation as long as we canwith Czechoslovak Government. The further positive advantages of doing soare that: (a) We may be able [omission] immediate future to put,brake on if only in a&apos;:!&apos;  slight degree. i-,&apos;.;,,v-.T r  s.      h; 1(&amp;) The mere fact that we are still fully represented here will be an encourage-ment to decent Czechs, whereas reduction in pur representation wouldbe a discouragement. &quot;At,the moment our prestige with these peoplestands very highi&apos; Withdrawal, which may be a Soviet objective,would of course be deeply discouraging and would, in fact, make thepresent state of affairs seem to [group undecypherable] Czechs littledifferent from the period of German occupation. We should also infuture be reproached with haying abandoned Czechoslovakia to herfate.       &apos;&quot;&apos;&quot; * .,,&apos;,&apos;;V v &apos;respect.mm;lh m:hmJh^r/;ii:x&apos;^%Ml7. During this interval when Czech leaders may be temporarily sobering up after their heady, [group undeeypherahle : : ? success], our right policy seems to beto make them uneasy as to intentions of Western Great Powers. ; It may be thatthe best tactics are an ominous silence, but I am now inclined to recommend thatthe most effective would be for my United States colleague, my French colleagueand me, each in our own way and speaking for ourselves, to try to increase anyuneasiness on the part of the new Government. I believe that my United Statescolleague&apos;s mind is moving on the same lines., In our own case I would recommendthat I might be authorised, on basis of frigid but correct relations, to speak on my own authority to Clements, the Communist Undersecretary, on the following[group undecypherable] I would say,that the British public regard what has happened as a barefaced Communist coup d&apos;4idt.\&quot;&apos; *i? &quot;..&quot;&apos;-  .&apos;,,:(2) I would ask him;what the foreign policv of Czechoslovakia is apd&apos;whether;; ?W Jr the;Ministry-f or Foreign Affairs expects td have any say in the matter.-1 &apos;$J8P1 would warn him that framed up charges against democratic figures/&apos;    would complete the indignation felt in the.&apos; West against, property ^edings
45(4) I would say that His Majesty&apos;s Government are not resting on the decla-ration of 26th February which merely voiced the immediate reaction ofthe three Great Powers to events in this country and that the wholequestion of our attitude towards Czechoslovakia is under consideration.(This would be with the object of reinforcing point (3) and may possibly assist in keeping the Soviet Government guessing as to futuremoves by the Western Great Powers.)8. I am telegraphing separately about economic relations, on which I would propose deliberately to leave Clementis guessing.Please pass to Moscow, Paris and Washington as my telegrams Nos. 30, and 6 respectively.[Repeated to Moscow, Paris and Washington.]


</content>
</cab>
