<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/25/0 images: 239-240</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS   DOCUMENT  IS   THE PROPERTY OF   HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1948SECBiET Copy, No. 3QCP. (48) 86IQth March, 1948CABINETPAPER FOR A FASCIST PERIODICALMemorandum by the President of the Board of trade at their meeting on 24th July, 1947 (CM. (47) 64th Conclusions, Minute 5),the Cabinet considered the question of supplies of paper for the Mosley periodicalAction; they agreed to &quot; adjourn consideration of the question whether thePresident of the Board of Trade should grant the application of the proprietorsof Action for a supply of paper.&quot; It was not apparently the intention of theCabinet to discuss this matter further unless there was some new development.The Board of Trade have dealt with the matter by leaving all applications and letters unanswered.2. As has been previously pointed out, this or any other periodical firstpublished before 16th August, 1940, can&quot;be printed and published now, althoughthe publishers must restrict consumption to (at present) 40 per cent, of pre-war consumption. In accordance with the Cabinefs decision no paper has beenlicensed for this journal but there are certain stocks held by printers and merchants for the supply of which no licence is required. The publishers ofAction have apparently purchased paper from such sources (as it was expectedthey might do) and have now republished the journal under the title Unionincorporating A ction. In the first issue they referred to the fact that the Boardof Trade have withheld any licence for the supply of paper to them, as a resultof which a number of people have written to their Member of Parliament suggest-ing that this is unfair discrimination and asking them to take the matter up with me.3. I propose to reply to all such letters (and if necessary in the House)that while we have not prevented the appearance of this publication, and wouldnot use paper control as a method of imposing censorship, we are not preparedto issue a licence permitting paper producers to supply paper for the purpose.I invite the concurrence of the Cabinet to this course of action.H. W.Board of Trade, S. W. 1,lUh March, 1948.35071


</content>
</cab>
