<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/25/0 images: 241-243</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (4-8) 37COPY NO. -lO19416th March,   1948.CABINETSERVICE ACCOMMODATION IN THE UNITED kingdom memorandum by the Minister of Health.In connection with the memorandum by the Minister ofDefence (CP. (48) 77) my colleagues may wish to have from me anote as to the operative arrangements for the provision of houses by Government Departments,  including the provision of married quarters by the Service Departments.2. Such provision has to come out of the labour force for housing and. proposals have, therefore,  to be considered as a partof and in relation to the general housing programme,  including theprovision of houses for miners and agricultural workers.-An Inter-Departmental Committee has for some time beenin existence for this purpose,  presided over by an officer of myDepartment and attended by representatives of.....all Government...................-.........--.....-Departments interested in the building of houses.*3. To this Committee are submitted the house-building programmes of the various Departments.      Tho time at which aproposal can start in a particular district and the rate at whichit can proceed depends on the volume of building work already inhand in the area.      My Department examine this question locallyin relation to particular building proposals for -which theindividual Department are in fact ready to go to contract duringthe quarter immediately ahead, and every endeavour is made, withinthe limits of the building resources available in the particular area, to enable a start to be made, but in a certain number of areas the building programme is still so overloaded that a start with any new proposals has had to be deferred.-At the lost meeting the results to the service departments wero:-Start authorised DeferredAir Ministry 20b 120Admiralty 50 NilWar Office 185 44V Consideration of cases deferred will bo resumed nextquarter in the light of the% progress made with building in thearea in the meantime.-1-
IB DU. Practical building progress must depend n,t onglobal a Hoc at ions &quot;but on building resources available inthe area.     -Proposals which, are included in the approvedprogrammes of Government Departments are treated for thepurposes of the Committee 00 having equal priority,  and(unless the Cabinet should decide that the provision for theServices is to have a higher priority than the provision forother Departments including atomic energy for the Ministryof Supply,  houses for the  police, for the Forestry Commissionand for the- general housing programme including miners and -agricultural workers),  I suggest that, the existing machineryprovides the most effective way of giving the maximumassistance within the limits of the building resources available.A.B.Ministry of Health,  S.W. 1i16th March,  1948.r


</content>
</cab>
