<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/25/0 images: 249-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJ STY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.The circulation of this paper has bee/i spjicrJy limited. *        / . 9/10It is issued for the personal use of WV^M^TOP SECRET Copy No. LQ...CP. (48) 891 8th March, 1 9U6.CABINETTHE REPORT OF THE RUSSELL VICK COMMITTEE ONTHB BLACK MARKET IN PETROLMemorandum by the Minister of Fuel ana. power informed the Cabinet in CP. (48)  16 that I wassetting up a Committee to enquire into black market dealingsin petrol.      The Committee,  who will report in the next few-days,  have informed me in advance of their findings andrecommendations, and these are summarised in the Annex to thisPa per,2. No-one will,  I think,  dispute the Committee&apos;s viewthat the black market draws its main supplies from petrol issued for goods vehicles,  that its extent is Serious and that it canonly be stopped by preventing the transfer of the petrol to private motorists.      Accordingly,  in view of the fact that petrol rationing seems certain to continue for seme years,  I  proposethat we should accept their main recommendation that colour anda chemical should be added to commercial petrol,  so as to make itclearly distinguishable from other petrel.3. We cannot afford t; wait until the second of the twochemicals menti oned by the Committee becomes available, and Iwould therefore propose,  if the Cabinet approve, t, discussimmediately with the Petroleum Beard how and in what minimuntime the recommendations for the addition of colour and onechemical can be put into effect.      The Committee themselvesbelieve that this can be done - on the evidence submitted tethem - in 6-8 weeks.4* On the other hand I am very doubtful whether we should adopt the proposal for further legislation regarding the-penalties to be imposed on those convicted of black marketactivities.      Such legislation would no doubt be highly controversial and I do not think wo should contemplateintroducing it until we ore certain that it is essential.I should hope that the deterrent effect of distinguishing one type of petrol from the other (supported by propaganda t- arousepublic opinion against the black market) may be sufficient techeck malpractices, and I would propose therefore for the timebeing te proceed under Defence Regulations and to leave it the Courts to punish misuse of petrol with the penaltiesprescribed by those Regulations.      It is also possible to arrangeby administrative action for petrol supplies to be cut off or reduced where a motorist or garage proprietor has been convicted of block market dealings, though &quot;second, penalties&quot; of this kind should in my view only be imposed in flagrant and absolutelyclear cases,  and on the personal decision of the Minister.
5. Nor do I think that it would be wisu to adopt therecommendation of the Committee in regard to the keeping ofcoupon record sheets.      This is designed to assist enforcementrather than to act ss s deterrent,  and until it is found thatthe deterrents are not sufficiently effective,  I would not wishto impose on motorists and garage proprietors obligations whichexperience has led us to believe will be largely ignored.The obligation to keep the records can be placed, on motorists ata later date if it is found to be. necessary.6. I would like to have tho Cabinet&apos;s approval for theseproposals so that the details may be worked out as soon aspossible and on announcement of the Government&apos;s decisions modewhen&apos;the Report is published after Easter.?i. T. N . G.Ministry of Fuel and power, .S.W. 1..18th March,. 19U3.
annex summary OP THE REPORT OF THE RUSSELL VIGK COMMITTEEON THE BLAC-K MARKET INPETROL1&apos; The black market in petrol is extensive and widespread.It-consists of a large number of small transactions in which many thousands participate,  rather than in the operations of a few largeracketeers.      It is difficult to estimate tho volume of petrolbought and sold illegally, but the Committee guess that in 19k?it may have amounted to 150,000 tons,  i. e. 5?i of the total petrolconsumed and a little over 10% of the total consume a in private cars.      Even so, there was on excess of coupons issued over petrelsupplied amounting to no less than 390,000 tons.      Thus the potentisupply to the black market v/as very much higher then the actualvolume or petrol thought to have &quot;been sold there.2. Petrol finds its way into tho black market mainly fromgoods vehicle operators and to a less extent from fanners.      both these classes  of consumers have needs which have got to bo met onewhich cannot be precisely estimated.      It frequently happens,therefore,  that they are issued with more coupons than they require3&quot; The demand for black market petrol comes from privatemotorists who do not get as largo a ration as they would like,  andhave loot-respect for the low (partly -because of inevitableweaknesses in its administration and enforcement)  and or-.,  pre pare ato evade the regulations freely.U. The solution to the problem can only be found by levisinga means whereby those who have surplus petrol cannot make itavailable to those who want it.5. As a deterrent against illegal transfers the distinctivecolouring of petrol is likely to exercise a powerful effect.      Butthe colouring of &quot;commercial&quot;  petrol will not alone prove effectivechiefly because all known colours can be fairly easily removed.It is therefore necessary,  in addition to dyeing the patrol,  to addchemicals,  which are much more difficult to remove. k6. Since it would offend against the principles ofjurisprudence to prosecute a motorist for having in hoc tank asubstance the nature of which had been concealed from him, the&apos;nature of the chemical on the presence of -which any proceedingswould have to be based must be revealed.7. Ideally two chemicals should be added.      The nature ofone of those,   1Z&apos;, which would be very difficult indeed to eliminotwould, be revealed and used as the basis of proceedings, while theother,   &apos;P&apos;, would be kept secret  and used for detection purposes.However, adequate supplies of  &apos;Z&apos; will unfortunately not beavailable for.two years and the only known alternative is a dollarproduct.      Therefore a second, best plan may have t,   be adoptedconsisting of the addition  of a dye plus the chemical  &apos;F* whosenature will, of course,  have to be revealed.      &apos;F&apos; will give avisible reaction to a simple chemical test which .could be carriedout by a policeman at the roadside and cannot be removed at alleasily.    &quot;&quot;Both the dye and the chemical should be added at the petroleum Board&apos;a distribution depots to all consignments of petrolsupplied against commercial coupons.      The cost of the dye and the chemical &apos;P&apos;  is estimated at  25,000  per annum.
8. The present penalties for block market dealings arenot adequate to deter either motorists or garage  proprietors.The Committee recommend, with the support of the Motor Agents1Association and the motoring organisations that -(a) a garage proprietor who is found to hove commercialpetrol in a private pump should be deprived of allpetrol f o r t w e 1 v e m on t h s;(b) s garage proprietor who supplies a  private motoristwith commercial petrel from a commercial pump should&apos;    be deprived of commercial petrel for twelve months,though it would he- a defence to prove that he tookall reasonable steps to prevent the occurrence and.. did not know of it;(c) the owner of a private cor,  whether present  or not,and the driver end. person in charge of a car ot thetime of th e  o ff should have their drivinglicences suspended for twelve months if commercialpetrol is found in the cor;(d) the registration hook of o  private cor which is foundto have commercial petrel should he endorsed and nopetrol allowance issued for the ear for twelve months,whether it is in the some ownership or net.9* Legislation should be introduced to moke possible theimposition of these penalties by the Courts.10. In order to assist the Police in finding garages whereillegal dealings are taking place,  and the motorist in showing that he came by any commercial petrol legitimately, all motoristsshould be required to keep a coupon-record sheet,  shewing howtheir coupons have been used and detaining the signature of thesupplier of  petrol at the time of purchase.      In making thisrecommendation the Committee also hove the support  of the MotorAgents&apos;&apos; Association end the motoring organisations.11. The Committee hove discussed the problem with the chief constables&apos;  Conference who think that a scheme en the lines ofthat recommended by the Committee would, have- public respect andbe capable of proper enforcement.


</content>
</cab>
