<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/33/46 images: 390-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   January 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 46.January 29, 1943.TO  BE  KEPT  UNDER   LOCK  AND  key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.THE SHIPPING SITUATION.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.IN their Fourth Report (W.P. (43) 28) the Shipping Committee estimateimport requirements during the first six months of 1943 at a total of 12-5 million tons (5-5 million tons food, 6-0 million tons materials and 1-0 million tonsmunitions and miscellaneous), and probable imports (excluding additionalAmerican assistance and the effects of any cuts in Ion dings to the Indian Ocean)at 8-5 million tons.2. There are four means by which the gap of 4 million tons can bebridged :-(a) Additional American assistance.(b) Reduction of consumption below the levels assumed in W.P. (43) 28.(c) Reduction in stocks below the levels assumed in W.P. (43) 28.(d) Reduction in shipments to the Indian Ocean area.A merican A assistance.3. At their meeting on the 21st January (L.P. (43), 5th Meeting, Minute 2),the Lord Presidents Committee were informed that, according to the latest reports received from Sir Arthur Salter, the War Shipping Administrationestimate that the cargo to be loaded for this country in United States shipsduring, the first five months of 1943 is likely to amount to about 1 -15 million tons.Sir Arthur considers that this estimate may be on the conservative side. it includes, however, cargo (about 50,000 tons per month) hitherto carried in UnitedStates ships which were already engaged in the &apos;! Bolero &apos;&apos; movement before therecent agreement, and the estimate must be written down accordingly in order toarrive at a figure for additional American assistance. In the first six months of1943 imports derived from additional American assistance are not. therefore,likely to exceed 1 million tons- indeed, after allowing for losses, it may be saferto assume a figure of 800,000 tons.Reduction of Consumption.4. As will be seen from paragraph 12 of W.P. (43) 28, the Shipping-Committee, in drawing up their estimates, have assumed a figure for the netconsumption of materials during the first half of 1943 lower by 1-2 million tonsthan the original planned figure of 7-7 million tons. I understand that theMinister of Production has explained in a minute to the Prime Minister thereasons why further reduction is at present inadvisable in the consumption ofraw materials during the period, and that, if the gravity of the shipping positionimposes any reduction in imports of raw materials below the figure of 6 million tons included in the Shipping Comnuttee&apos;s estimate of import requirements, hewould propose to meet the situation by a further measure of destocking.The Lord Presidents Committee have examined the various measures forsecuring economies in the consumption of food which the Shipping Committeehave listed in paragraph 18 of their report. They have authorised the Ministerof Food to introduce such further dilution of bread up to a maximum limit of[24964]
10 per cent. the rate previously approved was 5 per cent. as can be secured by using barley surrendered by the brewers against such oats as they may be able topurchase in the open market. Taking into account the total quantity of grainslikely to be available for dilution from all sources, the Ministry of Food hope tobe able to maintain an average rate of dilution of about 8 per cent, up to the endof June. This should represent a saving of 235.000 tons of imported wheatduring the period, the additional saving compared with 5 per cent, dilution ratebeing 94.000 tons. My Committee consider that the economies to be derived fromthe remaining measures listed in paragraph 18 of W.P. (43) 28 are not sufficiently large to justify the nutritional disadvantages involved, and do not. therefore, feel able to recommend their introduction.Thus, the total saving to be derived from further reductions in consumptioncannot be put at a higher figure than, say, 90,000 tons.Reduction i/i Stocky.5. In paragraph 13 of their report, the Shipping Committee state that, in estimating import requirements of food at 5-5 million tons and of raw materialsat 6 million tons, they have assumed a rise of 100.000 tons in food stocks and a fall of 500.000 tons in material stocks over the first half of 1943. This impliesa level of food stocks at mid-1943 of some 400.000 tons and a level of materialstocks some 2-3 million tons above the minimum distribution levels as estimated in the Third Report of the Shipping Committee (W.P. (42) 497,Appendix &quot;&apos;B&quot;). As stated in the preceding paragraph, the Minister ofProduction proposes, should imports during the period fall below 0 million tons,to meet the situation by reducing stocks of materials below the level assumed bythe Shipping Committee. At the meeting of the Lord Presidents Committeeon the 21st January, the Minister of Production said that it would, if necessary,be possible to make do with an import of 5-5 million tons of materials duringthe first six months of 1943. For the purposes of the present calculation, therefore,we may perhaps assume a saving of 500,000 tons for raw materials under this heading.Reduction in Shipments to the Indian Ocean.6. The total contribution towards bridging the gap which can be expected from American assistance, from economies in consumption and from furtherdestocking thus amounts to a maximum of 1-39 million tons. The only other steps which can be taken in order to meet the remaining deficit of 2-61 million tons isa reduction in sailings from the United Kingdom and North America to theIndian Ocean area. For the month of January these sailings have been reducedto 40 ships and some 000.000 tons may be expected to accrue to the United kingdom import programme as a result. In paragraph 16 of the report of the Shipping-Committee, it is pointed out that, if the limitation of sailings to the Indian Oceanto 40 ships a month were continued for the period up to and including June 1943.the total increment to United Kingdom imports in the first half of the year would amount to some 2 million tons. The Service Ministers will, no doubt, comment onthe effect which this step would have on our war effort in the Middle East and far Fast areas. Meanwhile, my Committee do not feel competent to advisewhether or not it should be taken. They feel bound, however, to draw attentionto the very serious situation which will arise if our importing capacity is notsupplemented in this way.7. Even if this step is taken, there still remains an estimated deficit of some600,000 tons, which would appear bound to impose either further consumptioneconomies beyond those which my Committee have felt able to recommend, or thereduction of stocks below the figures assumed by the Shipping Committee whenthey have been adjusted, in the case of raw materials, to take account of thefurther destocking to the extent of 500,000 tons referred to in paragraph 5 above.A. further review of the position at a very early date would, therefore, appear tobe desirable. Meanwhile, my Committee have approved the proposal regardingthe allocation of imports between the Ministry of Food and the Ministry ofProduction set out in paragraph 23 (/) of W.P. (43) 28.J. A.Privy Council Office,&quot;Great George Street, S.W.1,January 29, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
