<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/228/0 images: 48-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1I1S DOCUMENT  13 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT )SECRET.COPY NO.CP. 60  (32;.C A3 INK T.Proposed Statement on Agriculturel andFisheries Policy.Note by the Minister of Agriculture end Fisheries.In considering the subject of agricultural and fisheries policy dealt with in CP. 21 (32) and CP. 46 (32) the Cabinet will probably find it convenient to have before them a draft of the sort of statement which might be made to the House of Commons either by the Leader of the House or by myself, and I therefore circulate the annexed proposed statement for consideration.(Intld.)    J.G.inistry of Agriculture and Fisheries, 10, Whitehall Place, S.-7.1.1st February, 1932,
g g gJ^AJ5Jja1^^ and Fisheries Policy.,1. At the present time practically the whole ofBritish agriculture, like the whole of industry,  is suffering from the effects of the general fall of commodity prices which has occurred since the autumn of 1929.    The Government considers that the most effective immediate action which can he taken to help the industry generally is the impositi&amp;n of tariffs on imports, and, accordingly, with the exception of wheat, (which is being dealt with by the method ef Quota), and of meat, all agricultural and horticultural produce, other than produce already chargeable with a Customs duty, has been included within the scope ef the Import Duties Bill new before the House.2. Under that Bill as introduced all agricultural and horticultural products, with the exceptions I have referred to, will be subject to the general tariff of 10 per cent, ad yalcrem, or its equivalent in specific duties.    An additional Customs Duty may be imposed on any particular product if recommended by the Import Duties Advisory Committee provided for in this Bill, and in this connection malting barley and certain horticultural products will receive particular attention.3. As an immediate step for dealing with maltingbarley, the administrative feasibility of levying an additional Customs duty on malting barley is being examined with a view to this question being referred to the Import Duties Advisory Committee at the earliest po-impossible date if a practicable scheme for differentiatirg at the port between malting barley and feeding barley can be evolved.    The alternative method of a quota is also under consideration.
4, The Import Duties Advisory Committee will also be asked-to recommend what duties should be imposed on the commodities at present covered by the Horticultural Products (Emergency Customs Duties) Act, 1931, when duties under that Act expire. 5, The foregoing proposals refer to immediate action forthe benefit of agriculture through the instrument of tariffs. The Government also attach great importance to a long-range policy designed to facilitate economic development in those branches of the Agricultural Industry which, in the long-run, are likely to be the most remunerative, and which lend themselves to most rapid development.     The three branches of agriculture which offer opportunities for this development are milk, potatoes and pigs.6. The Government intend to pursue a comprehensive policyin regard to milk and milk products involving tariffs on imports (which are being dealt with under the Import Duties Bill), the reduction of disease among dairy herds and the improvement of marketing.     The Government consider that reorganisation of the milk industry is necessary, and they would welcome the co-operation of the industry in the formulation of a scheme. 7. As to potatoes, the Government undertake to appoint a Re-organisation Commission,if desired by potato growers,with instructions to prepare a scheme for the organisation and marketing of the home potato crop and to consider such practicable complementary action as may appear to be necessary for the regulation of imports of main crop potatoes.8. Uith regard to bacon an ad hoc Committee charged withthe task of preparing a scheme for the organisation of the Bacon Industry is being appointed forthwith, and, provided a satisfactory scheme is evolved, the Government is prepared to adopt some form of quantitative regulation of imports,
1 &quot;    499. As to marketing,.generally the Government realise the necessity-of developing the National Mark movement, and plans and investigations to this end will be proceeded with as rapidly as circumstances permit.10. The Government recognise the services whichagricultural research and education have rendered to the agricultural community,   and they have reason to know that these services meet with steadily growing appreciation among farmers.      So far as financial circumstances permit, we propose to maintain and develop the organised system which already exists.11. A policy of land settlement will be pursued withinthe limits of the financial resources available. 12. v/hile the Government do not propose to make anychange in the present system of regulating agricultural wages they are fully alive to the necessity of securing observance of the Orders made under the Agricultural Wages (Eegulat ion) Act, and they wish to call the attention of agricultural workers to the facilities which exist for the investigation by the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries of complaints that the requirements of these Orders are not being observed.Fisheries.Immediate help to practically every branch of the Fishing Industry will be afforded by the Customs Duties proposed in the Import Duties Bill.      Any further action which may be necessary in connection with the Fishing Industry will be taken after full consideration has been given to the Report of the Economic Advisory Council on the Fishing Industry which will shortly be presented to Parliament.

</content>
</cab>
