<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/228/0 images: 430-432</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1932.SECRET.-CP. 88 (32). Copy No.....%......CABINET. &apos;Reports by Local Governments on the Political Situation in India.I circulate for the information of my colleagues the latest weekly reports from the Local Governments in India.S. H.India Office, 1st March 1932.Government of India.Delhi reports that Congress activity is now concentrated on the boycott of foreign cloth. Generally, the boycott is now the chief activity, and attempts, are being made in Bombay to extend it to banks. Provincial reports are satisfactory and show no tendency anywhere for activities to increase, while in several Provinces definite improvement has occurred, for instance in Bihar and Orissa, United Provinces, Assam, Central Provinces and North-West Frontier Province. Particular evidence of this is the decrease in the number of convictions. There is now no doubt of growing interest in the reforms in North-West Frontier Province, where the forthcoming elections are attracting much attention.Bombay.An almost complete lull in open Congress activities continues in the Mofussil districts, where the movement is now principally represented by secret propaganda -and the boycott of foreign goods. Excise shop auctions have heen completed in a number of districts without interference. In Bombay city picketing of cloth shops continued and extended to foreign sugar shops from the 20th, with occasional picketing of the Exchange Banks and Mint. The Imperial Bank was picketed on 25th by 28 volunteers, all of whom were arrested. An attempt to hold an All-India Congress Day on the 21st proved a failure, but led to some rowdiness in the evening, when crowds were twice dispersed by lathi charges and 81 persons were injured. One municipal refuse cart was burnt by hooligans. On the 22nd some damage was done by a small mob to a jeweller&apos;s shop in Javeri bazar on the pretext of alleged export of gold. Boycott of British cotton brokers is reported to have been intensified during the last few days.Action under Ordinance 2 : The number arrested under section 3 was 14, and the number of orders issued under section 4 was 103. The total number detained under section 3 is 302. Total number of orders in force under section 4 is 789. Arrests for breach of orders under section 4 are about 33. Congress funds amounting to Rs. 3,ti68 with interest payable thereon for last year were declared forfeited under Ordinance 4.Madras.The situation remains unchanged. One more association has been declared unlawful, making a total of 109. There is no sign, as yet, of a revival of civil disobedience activities. Thirteen convicts were released on apologies during the week.Bengal.The situation in five divisions and in Calcutta is as follows : Dacca, marked&apos; improvement; Rajshahi, Congress activities local only; Chittagong, Presidency, Burdwan, quiet, except in two sub-divisions of Midnapore ; Calcutta, very quiet. A spate of seditious leaflets continues and great efforts are being made to bring the -students into the movement after the examinations are over. Arrests under section 3, -30. Orders to the number of 231 were issued under section 4. Total in force ((corrected figure), 1,713.743      60   3.32
United Provinces.Further gradual improvement is reported. Open agitation is becoming less; conspicuous. Demonstrations are mainly confined to large towns and certain districts, and sporadic efforts at picketing and boycott are reported on a small scale. Silent boycott and secret organisation continue. Section 3 of Emergency Powers Ordinance has been used in one case and 58 orders have been made under section 4. Convictions during the week under the Ordinances were 262 and under the ordinary law 428. The total to date is 5,998 and releases number 1,034. The number of convictions is-gradually declining, but is still high in several districts.Central Provinces.Except for some increased activity in Chanda district, reports from all divisions show continued improvement in the situation. There have been no incidents worth reporting. Prosecutions number 238 and convictions 222. The Unlawful Association Ordinance was enforced in Chanda and the Chanda War Council was declared&apos; unlawful.Punjab.Except in Lahore, the civil disobedience movement throughout the Province-continues insignificant. In Lahore, since the 24th February, determined efforts by women to picket shops on the Mall have attracted crowds, estimated at 2,000, and including some students, which were successfully dispersed by the police with the infliction of a few minor injuries only. Picketers were all arrested without difficulty. The trade situation is unchanged ; forward buying is below normal, but some commission agents have placed orders on their own account. Bitterness of communal relations is evidenced by speeches at numerous meetings, by bad articles in the Press and by minor incidents in the districts arising from cow-killing or religious disputes,, in which prompt local action has prevented serious results. This communal nervousness, intensified by the Kashmir disturbances, is responsible for the rcrpproche-ment between Hindus and Sikhs, from which the Congress expects to profit.Arrests for political activities under the ordinary law were 40, under Ordinances-77 ; total 117, of which 71 were in Lahore city. Totals to date, 166 and 517 respectively. One terrorist was arrested r:nder section 3, making five to date. Two orders have been issued under section 4, making 41 to date. The total of persons under restraint for the infraction of such orders is nine.North-West Frontier Province.Restrictions under section 144 have been withdrawn for three more than as in the Peshawar Tehsil. There has been some recrudescence of Red Shirt activity in Peshawar, leading to picketing and attempts to boycott the election. Picketing in the district is local and on small scale, and not serious. The despatch of a large party of picketers to the Punjab from Nowshera Tehsil was prevented by the timely arrest of the organiser. Picketers previously sent to the Punjab were from the area north of Mardan. Attempts to boycott the election are an almost complete failure at present, and a very large number of claims relating to electoral rolls have been submitted during the last few days. In spite of these activities improvement is being-maintained in Peshawar district, and the situation is practically normal in other districts.Under section 3, arrests during the week were nil, and the total detained was 19.. Under section 4, orders during the week numbered 560, and the total of orders in force 1,944.   Trial of prisoners at Haripur jail is now complete.In the frans-frontier area there is no change in Dir. Some excitement continues-at Bajaur, but there are no signs of hostile action yet. Haji of Turangzai is sounding the Mohmand tribes with a view to a Jehad, but airy immediate response is-unlikely.Bihar and Orissa.Nearly all districts report all quiet and a general improvement with a decrease in convictions and an increase in apologies. In Muzafarpur, especially in Sitarmarhi subdivision, demonstrations of villagers from outlying villages against Government lmildings continue, and further attempts at flag-hoisting are anticipated. Two orders-were passed under section 4, Emergency Powers Ordinance, and several villages have been warned of liability to collective fines. Section 3 has not been brought into-force.   Convictions up to 20th February total 3,960.
Burma.There have beeu no events of importance during the last week. The only gaug of any size still holding out is that of Myat Aung, which is being kept on the move and which it is hoped will be accounted for shortly. No casualties have been reported among Government forces. Twenty-seven under-trials were released and 593 are reported as still in custody. The increase is due to last week&apos;s figures being incomplete. The paddy market continues firm and the price has risen slightly during the week.   Collection of taxes continues to make satisfactory progress.Assam.The situation during the past week has considerably improved. Firm action has checked aggressive activities in Sylhet district, and Assam Valley remains quiet generally.Ajmer Merwara.Nine persons were arrested during the week in Ajmer Merwara ; five under the Criminal Law Amendment Act and four under Ordinance 5 of 1932. There has been little active trouble, and it has been confined to ineffective picketing of cloth shops, abortive efforts to organise processions and occasional attempts to hoist the Congress flag on public buildings.Coorg.Eighty-two arrests and 59 convictions have been recorded up to date. The situation is still satisfactory. In Bangalore there have been 105 convictions to date, and only two persons have been arrested since the last report, one of whom was released on making a full apology in court.   Agitation appears to have ceased.

</content>
</cab>
