<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/206/16 images: 111-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALfcuMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(79) 16 COPY NO11 June 1979CABINETHOUSE OF COMMONS PROCEDUREMemorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster1. We must decide our attitude to the changes in the procedure of theHouse of Commons which were proposed in the first report from the SelectCommittee on Procedure for Session 1977-78.    We promised in The Queen&apos;sSpeech that members of the House of Commons would be given an opportunityto discuss and amend their procedures, particularly as they relate to thescrutiny of the work of Government.    Since then a Motion urging rne toensure that the House has an early opportunity to take decisions on theproposals of the Procedure Committee has attracted over 250 signatures;and a debate has been promised shortly after the Whitsun Recess. Therecan be no doubt of the determination of the House to have an opportunity todecide on the proposals of the Procedure Committee.THE PROCEDURE COMMITTEES RECOMMENDATIONS2. The Report dealt with public bills, subordinate legislation,European legislation, Select Committees, financial control and theorganisation of sessions and sittings.    These are all important matters butthe immediate interest is in Select Committees and the proposals for:a.        A new structure of 12 departmentally-related SelectCommittees, replacing the existing Expenditure Committee, theSelect Committees on Nationalised Industries, Science andTechnology, Overseas Development, Race Relations and Immigration,and the Select Committee on the Parliamentary Commissioner forAdministration (PCA), together with their sub-committees, which inthe case of the Expenditure Committee include sub-committees onDefence and External Affairs; Environment; Trade and Industry;Education, Arts and Home Office; and Social Services andEmployment.    Some Committees would have powers to set upinvestigative sub-committees, up to a total of 7 in all.1CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALb. Powers enabling the new Select Committees to &quot;order&quot; theattendance of Ministers to give evidence and to &quot;order 1 the productionof papers and records.    In the event of a refusal on the latter, theCommittee could claim precedence over public business for a debatein the House unless time were provided by the Government on thesixth sitting day after the first appearance of the Motion.3. The details are set out in Annex A (on the structure of SelectCommittees) and Annex B (on their powers).    In these Annexes I also considerpossible alternatives to the Procedure Committee1 s proposals.DEPARTMENTAL COMMITTEES4. The Procedure Committee1 s proposals are designed to makeParliament more effective in scrutinising the work of Government. Thisaim is right in principle and in accordance with our philosophy on theprotection of the liberties of the subject.    We endorsed it in our Manifesto.I have set out in Annex A (paragraphs 3-7) the reasons why departmentally-related committees should be more effective than the present pattern. Theywould provide more systematic coverage for the areas of policy, with lessduplication.    Better knowledge of Departments&apos; work should improve thequality of Committee reports and enhance the contribution they can make toinformed public discussion.    This could be of particular significance in theeconomic field where there is a need to promote well informed public debate.I have also described the risks in setting up Departmental Committees. Theycould become centres of attention and influence, detracting from the status ofthe Chamber.    They could create more work for Ministers and officials,although we face that outcome even with the present pattern of SelectCommittees.    We must balance these risks against the need for moreeffective Parliamentary scrutiny.    I believe that we should strike areasonable balance accepting the principle of departmentally-relatedcommittees for which there is strong support in the House, while safeguardingthe efficient conduct of government.THE NUMBER OF COMMITTEES5*       The Procedure Committee&apos;s proposals for 12 DepartmentalCommittees and up to 7 Sub-Committees are described in Annex A.    I haveexamined the option of reducing the numbers (paragraph 8 of Annex A). Iam sure however that if we so reduced the number there would be pressurefor more sub-committees.    I should therefore prefer to accept theProcedure Committee1 s own proposal for 12 main Committees and to takecredit for doing so.    We must, however, guard against a proliferation ofinvestigative sub-committees and the setting up of large numbers ofconcurrent enquiries.    I therefore propose that we should seek to reducethe permitted number of these sub-committees from 7 to 4.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL6. The existing &quot;subject&quot; Select Committees (page 2, Annex A) shouldbe replaced by the new structure.    We should, however, retain the SelectCommittee on the Parliamentary Commissioner for Administration in orderto provide a focus for the PCA system (paragraph 11, Annex A).    Under myrecommendations 12 main Committees and 4 Sub-Committees would replace5 main Committees and 14 Sub-Committees, an overall reduction of 3. Inaddition, we shall be considering separately proposals for Select Committeeson Scotland and Wales.POWERS7. The Procedure Committee1 s proposals (paragraph 2(b)) would havefar-reaching consequences.    In no circumstances should we agree toempower Select Committees to &quot;order&quot; the attendance of Ministers or theproduction of Departmental papers.    We do however have a choice in thematter of debate on any refusal to produce papers.    We could offer a newprocedure under which the Government would be required to provide timefor a debate, not at the instance of the Select Committee alone, but inresponse to widespread demand in the House as a whole - as evidenced, forexample, by a Motion signed by a stated number of Members or by a vote(see Annex B).    On the other hand, the Procedure Committee have notproduced any evidence of general difficulty or dissatisfaction with the wayin which the present powers of Select Committees have operated in practice,although they have shown that they may be in some respects unclear oranomalous.    We could therefore take the line that the case for a new powerto force debate has not been established, and that the matter could be lookedat again after the new structure has been in operation for some time. Irecommend that we adopt this course of no change.PARLIAMENTARY HANDLING8-       The Procedure Committee proposed in their Special Report a seriesof Motions which would give effect to their main proposals on structuxje andpowers.    They would like us to allow the House to debate these Motions on afree vote.    We should not accept this mode of proceeding although a freevote is essential.    We should have to table amendments to meet the pointsI have set out above, and this would draw direct attention to the differencesbetween our proposals and those of the Procedure Committee.    Instead weshould table our own Motions for the appointment of the new Committees,for the restrictions on sub-committees and for the same powers as thosewhich Select Committees have traditionally possessed.    Our Motions wouldhe subject to amendment and amendments would undoubtedly be tabled. Weshould still have to allow a free vote but we should have more control overthe debate and we should be better able to rely on our supporters in adivision.    Once our Motions were carried Members could be chosen to serveon the new Committees in time for them to start work after the Long Recess.Amendments to Standing Orders could follow later.3CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALCONCLUSIONS9, I therefore propose that we should:a. Provide an early debate on the main proposals in theProcedure Committee&apos;s report which relate to Select Committees.b. Recommend to the House that the Procedure Committee&apos;sproposals for 12 departmentally-related Committees should beaccepted, subject to closer restrictions on the power to appointinvestigative sub-cornmittees, and to the retention of the SelectCommittee on the PCA.c. Recommend that no change in powers should be made at thisstage.d. Table Government Motions accordingly.10. I will in due course bring forward a further paper on the remainingrecommendations of the Procedure Committee which need not be debateduntil the autumn.N St J SPrivy Council OfficeU June 19794CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEX ASTRUCTURE OF SELECT COMMITTEESProcedure Committee&apos;s Recommendations1.      The Procedure Committee recommend the establishmentof 12 new departmentally-related Select Committees, withbroad terms of reference,  simply drawn (eg &quot;to considerdefence&quot;) and permissive rather than mandatory incharacter.    They would cover:AgricultureDefenceEducation,  Science and ArtsEnergyEnvironmentForeign AffairsHome Affairs (to cover the Home Office and theLord Chancellor&apos;s and Law Officer&apos;sDepartments)Industry and Employment (to cover both Departments)Social ServicesTrade and Consumer AffairsTransportTreasury (to cover the Treasury and the CivilService Department)2-      Together the Committees would cover the responsibilitiesQf all Government departments and the nationalised industries;and they would replace the present subject Committees andtheir sub-committees. *   They would &quot;for the present&quot; beempowered to consider matters relating to Scotland, Wales andNorthern Ireland,  and there would be provision for theaPPointment of up to 7 investigative sub-committees. Therewould be a joint sub-committee on nationalised industries,and the Foreign Affairs, Home Affairs and Treasury Committee/would each
CONFIDENTIALwould each have power to appoint two sub-committees.Twelve Committees and up to 7 sub-committees would thusreplace 6 Committees and 14 sub-committees. Theremainder of the House of Commons select committee system,including the Public Accounts Committee, would remain asat present.Subject and departmentally-related Committees.3.       The present subject Committees have grown up piece-meal over the years, with no coherent structure or cleardefinition of their scope.    Their coverage is uneven, withsome areas of policy not covered at all and others coveredby more than one Committee.    Individual Committees haveoften interpreted their orders of reference in their ownway,  and the sub-committees of the Expenditure Committeehave not/* ie   the Expenditure Committee, with its   General subm committee and sub-committees on Defence and ExternalAffairs;  Environment;  Trade and Industry; EducationArts and Home Office;  and Social Services and Employmenthe Select Committee on Nationalised Industries, withits sub-committees A - E;the Select Committee on Overseas Development;the Select Committee on Race Relations &amp; Immigration;the Select Committee on Science and Technology, withits General Purposes sub-committee and sub-committeeson Genetic Engineering and Technological Innovation;andthe Select Committee on the Parliamentary Commission6for Administration.2
CONFIDENTIALhave not,  for example,  felt that their restriction toexpenditure matters inhibits them from consideringsuch wider policy issues as youth unemployment (examinedby the Social Services and Employment sub-committee),planning procedures (examined by the Environment sub-committee),  or fishing limits and conservation or thewages and conditions of South African workers (examinedby the Trade and Industry sub-committee).    A moresystematic structure is clearly needed if Parliamentaryscrutiny is to be effective.4.      Departmentally-related Committees have theadvantages of providing a more logical structure, givingeach Committee a well-defined area of interest and aclear-cut relationship with its department (or departments).They should be able to build up a knowledge of theirdepartments1 work and a degree of expertise in theiraffairs which would make the Committees&apos; enquiries morepenetrating and also more economical in the effort demanded,both from their own members and their permanent staff andadvisers and from Ministers and officials of the departmentit   If.    They could make a more positive and authoritativeCo. ,ribution to the wider national debate on the majorissues facing their departments,  for example in the criticalareas of economic and industrial policy.5- There are also risks.    More expert Committees couldbecome centres of influence which would detract from theimportance of the Chamber.    They might weaken collectiveresponsibility.    They could create more work for Ministersand their departments.6- A balance must therefore be struck between theadvantages of more effective Parliamentary scrutiny and therisks of greater friction and extra work.    The possible/sources3
CONFIDENTIALsources of friction and of extra work do not, however,lie in the structure of Select Committees but in theirattitudes and the way in which they operate. Astructure of departmentally-related Committees wouldbring some areas of policy,  for example in the fieldsof economic and monetary matters^ explicitly within theorders of reference of Select Committees for the firsttime, but for other departments it would be no morethan a rationalisation of existing practice.    The newstructure would not itself change existing relationshipsbetween the Committees,  Parliament as a whole, Ministersand their departments;  and the increase in the commitmentsof Ministers and their departments need not be greaterthan must be expected even if the existing Committees ndtheir sub-committees continue on the present basis. Theincrease in the activities of Select Committees which hastaken place in recent years reflects a more generalassertiveness on the part of Members which is unlikely to &apos;be suppressed by resistance to changes in structure.7.        Apart from the implications for Ministers anddepartmental officials,  the Procedure Committee considerthat some increase would be needed in the number andquality of the Select Committees&apos; permanent staff andspecialist advisers.    Arrangements for such appointmentsand any restrictions on their numbers would be matters forthe House itself,  and for the House of Commons Commission,but the Government could exercise a restraining influencethrough their representatives on the Commission.    The Houseauthorities do not, however,  consider that any major newrecruitment is needed and tell me that if the House decidedon the full implementation of the Procedure Committee &apos;srecommendations,  they could staff the new system.4
CONFIDENTIALAlternatives to the Procedure Committee&apos;s ProposalsThe Procedure Committee recognised that there isroom for argument about the number of new Committees,and various alternatives can be considered.    The numbercould be reduced if a single Committee were to covermore departments with related functions.    A structurewhich linked Environment with Transport, Trade withIndustry and Employment,  and Foreign Affairs with Defencewould give a total of 9 committees.    Alternatives of thiskind could have some advantage in areas of study wheremore than one department is concerned and where somespecial machinery for co-ordination between Committeesmight otherwise be needed.    On the other hand,  a. proposalsfor fewer Committees would be criticised as restrictingtheir   cope and making them less effective;  there would bepressure - which would be difficult to resist - forlarge; Committees and greater discretion to set up sub-committees.    The resulting structure might not be verydiffe   it in practical terms,  but relationships betweensub-committees, main Committees, Ministers and theirdepar  ients might be more confused.    Neither alternative,nor as    variation of them,  is obviously superior to theProcedure Committee&apos;s own proposal and all could becriticised as producing anomalies in the relative weightof the subjects to be covered by individual Committees or1n th, particular groupings that were chosen.The existing informal Liaison Committee of SelectCommittee Chairmen has worked satisfactorily in the pastand would provide a machinery for resolving problems inareas which are of interest to more than one Committee.The Procedure Committee recommend that the Liaison Committeeshould be placed on a formal basis.    This seems a sensibleProposal, but a decision is not needed at this stage.cont/ . .5
CONFIDENTIALGiven the support for the Procedure Committee&apos;s proposalsin general, and the political advantage of acceptingthem wherever possible,  I recommend accepting thestructure of 12 departmentally-related Committees as theyput it forward.9. We must, however, guard against a proliferation ofinvestigative sub-committees and the danger of anexcessive number of simultaneous enquiries which couldunduly district departments from discharging theirordinary business.    I therefore propose that there shouldbe a limit on the Committees&apos; power to appoint sub-committees, without the approval of the House as a whole,to a joint sub-committee on Nationalised Industries (seeparagraph 10 below) and to one rather than two sub-committees for each of the Treasury, Foreign Affairs andHome Affairs Committees.    Paragraphs 5.35 - 5.44 of theProcedure Committee&apos;s report, which indicate the purposesfor which such sub-committees might be appointed, couldbe quoted in support of such a restriction.Other Subject Committees10. We must stand firm on the principle,  endorsed by theProcedure Committee,  that if departmentally-relatedCommittees are appointed, parallel subject Committees shouldbe abolished.    Opposition is likely to be strongest inrespect of the Select Committee on Nationalised Industries,for the reasons which the Procedure Committee consideredbut rejected in paragraphs 5.35 - 5.39 of their Report.There should be a single body able to consider questionscommon to more than one industry, but a joint sub-committeeof the departmentally-related Committees which are concern^with the nationalised industries should be sufficient.Thereshould be no difficulty in arranging for the new Committeesto take over unifinished business from the old where itwould be worthwhile for them to do so.6cont/-
CONFIDENTIALp^ect Committee on the Parliamentary Commissioner forAdministration1. We ought, however,  to consider the special casetich exists for retaining the Select Committee on thearliamentary Commissioner for Administration, whichas functions similar in some respects to those of theublic Accounts Committee.    On the one hand theepartmentally-related Committees will be familiar withhe work of the departments concerned and could bexpected to develop an approach to questions of malad-inistration that took account of a Departments work aswhole.    On the other,  there are advantages in retainingcommittee to keep the PCA system as a whole undereview, and to consider individual cases on the basis ofrinciples common to every department.    I recommend thathe C mmittee should be retained.oncl usions2. To sum up therefore:(a)   Departmentally-related Select Committeeswould create a more comprehensive andrational system for Parliamentaryscrutiny of the Executive.    This neednot produce significantly more work forMinisters and their departments than islikely to develop from the existingstructure.    I recommend that the principleshould be accepted,  and also the ProcedureCommittee&apos;s specific proposals for 12Committees.cont/..7
CONFIDENTIALWe should guard against a proliferationof investigative sub-committees or anexcessive number of simultaneousenquiries.    We should therefore reducefrom 7 to 4 the number of investigativesub-committees which could be set upwithout the approval of the House as awhole.The existing subject Committees must notcontinue alongside a structure ofdepartmentally-related Committees that isintended to replace them, but specialconsiderations apply to the SelectCommittee on the Parliamentary Commissionfor Administration, which should beretained.8
CONFIDENTIALANNEX BPOWERS OF SELECT COMMITTEESThe Procedure Committee&apos;s Proposals1.     The Procedure Committee propose that &quot;selectcommittees should be empowered to order the attendanceof Ministers to give evidence to them and to order theproduction of papers and records by Ministers, includingSecretaries of State&quot; (recommendation 64),  and that &quot;inthe event of a refusal by a Minister to produce papersand records required by a Select Committee the Committeeshould be empowered to claim precedence over publicbusiness for a debate on a Motion for an Address or foran order for the Return of Papers,  unless time isprovided by the Government by the sixth sitting dayafter the first appearance of the Motion&quot; (recommendation65),Ex: -ting Powers of Select Committees2.   The existing powers of Select Committees to sendfor persons,  papers and records are set out in amemorandum by the Clerk of the House which is reproducedat Appendix C of the Select Committee &apos; s report. Itemphasises that Select Committees normally act informally(by request rather than by order),  and that their formalpowers in these matters are somewhat uncertain, rarelyused and almost entirely dependent upon their endorsementby the House as a whole.    A Select Committee may thusmvite a Minister (like any other Member) to attendbefore them, but would require a resolution of the Houseto enforce that request if the Minister did not agreeto attend.    Similarly,  a Select Committee may not atPresent demand any papers held in the custody of aCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL2Minister which if required by the House itselfwould need to be sought by an Address to the Queen.Attendance of Ministers3. The Procedure Committee&apos;s proposals,  if takenliterally, would make three major changes.    In thefirst place they would enable Select Committees toorder the attendance of any Minister, and not onlythe Minister departmentally responsible.    We shouldresist the suggestion that a Committee of the Houseshould be entitled to do this.    Such a power couldbe used in an attempt to expose differences betweenMinisters, thereby undermining the collectiveresponsibility of Government.    The Government shouldretain the power to decide which Minister shouldrepresent them before a Committee or whether theyshould be represented by a Minister or an official.Production of Papers and Records4. Secondly, the proposals would   give SelectCommittees the power to &quot;order&quot; the production .ofany Ministerial papers and records.    An unqualifiedpresumption that all departmental papers werepotentially accessible to&apos;Select Committees wouldclearly be unacceptable.    There will inevitably beoccasions when Ministers consider that it would notbe in the public interest to disclose documents orinformation.    Cabinet and Cabinet Committee papers;sensitive information or papers dealing with defenceand foreign relations,  law enforcement, security andintelligence, or the currency and the reserves;papers on the appointment and conduct of the Judiciaryand confidential communications between them.and theLord Chancellor on judicial matters; papers theCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALdisclosure of which would infringe the privacy ofthe individual;  and documents offering advice orcomments by officials to Ministers must all continueto be protected.    If thought necessary, explicitrestrictions could be made.5.   In practice there have been     few complaints ofMinisterial reluctance either to appear before SelectCommittees or to provide information.    Subject to theircomparatively minor reservations about departmentalorganisation and consultation with non-departmentalbodies (paragraphs 7.15 and 7.16 of their report), theProcedure Committee were broadly satisfied with the co-operation which Select Committees already receive fromGovernment Departments,  and with the Memorandum ofGuidance for Officials appearing before SelectCommittees (reproduced as Appendix D of the ProcedureCom:.ittee1 s Report).    Under the procedures set out inthi:. Memorandum,  including the sidelining procedure,Ministers and officials provide, as necessary and attheii discretion, sensitive information which is notto      publicly disclosed.    Some detailed changes tothe Memorandum of Guidance will be needed in the lightof   he Procedure Committee&apos;s report, but otherwisethe existing procedures should be maintained.Enforcement6-   Thirdly, the proposals would enable a SelectCommittee to force a debate on the Floor of the Houseif a Minister refused its order to produce papers orrecords.    This right would place a very considerablePower in the hands of a Committee which might not berepresentative of general opinion in the House. Ifthere is to be a procedure for forcing a debate, itshould be activated only in response to a much widerCONFIDENTIAL
4expression of opinion by the House as a whole. Aprocedure could be devised which would require theGovernment to provide time for a debate, not at theinstance of the Select Committee alone, but inresponse,  for example, to a motion signed by astated number of Members or to a vote.7. On a secondary point, the use of the term &quot;order5&apos;must be avoided.    It is a general Parliamentary principlethat Members of either House - including Ministers - are&quot;invited&quot; and not &quot;ordered&quot; to attend Select Committeesor to produce papers (and in the case of attandance bya Peer the Lords must be moved to give leave). Further-more, although the   Procedure Committee themselvesrecognised that the argument in the event of a refusalwould be essentially political and that recourse tocontempt proceedings would be inappropriate, the term&quot;order&quot; is usually associated with contempt proceedingsand should be avoided on that account.    Any procedurefor enforcing the wishes of a Select Committee must hea matter for the House as a whole, not as a matter ofprivilege, but by the normal means of confidencemotions or the withholding of supply.8. I recommend against conceding any changes inpowers at this stage.    If it becomes necessary to doso, we must ensure that -(a) The Government continue to be able to decidewhich Minister should represent them before aSelect Committee.(b) Ministers continue to be able to protectcertain documents and information from disclosure.CONFIDENTIAL
5(c) Select Committees do not have a power to&quot;order&quot; the attendance of Ministers or theproduction of Ministerial papers: their powersshould be in terms of an &quot;invitation&quot; or a&quot;request&quot;.(d) Any power to force debate on a Ministerialrefusal to attend or to produce papers andrecords; should require clear evidence of wide-spread concern in the House as a whole.CONFIDENTIAL

</content>
</cab>
