<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/6/0 images: 534-537</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1946.SECRET. C0PyN0&apos;CP. (46) 48.Qth February, 1946.CABINET.POLITICAL BROADCASTING.Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.*ON the 20th December, 1945, the Cabinet had before them a Memorandumdealing with political broadcasting (CP. (45) 335). It was amended and theLord Chancellor and I submitted an Aide-Memoire to the Prime Minister whichhe thought represented the views of the Cabinet (see Annex I).The Lord Chancellor and I subsequently met the Chairman and Director-General of the B.B.C and we discussed the matter in the light of the aide-Memoire. At the end of our meeting we showed a copy of our document tothe representatives of the B.B.C. and, later in the day, furnished them with copiesfor their consideration.The Director-General replied on the lines taken by him and his Chairmanduring our discussion (see Annex II).The Cabinet is asked to approve the outcome of the negotiations and to agreethat discussions should take place with the Opposition.a., &apos;&apos;      , &apos; ; . A. G.Gwydyr House, S.W. 1,6th February, 1946.* CM. (45) 64th Conclusions, Minute 2.ANNEX I.Political Broadcasting.THE Government do not think it desirable to attempt to reduce to writtenrules the principles which should govern the B.B.C. in regard to politicalbroadcasting.The principles to be adopted must depend on good sense and good will, andit is as impossible to formulate exhaustive principles on paper as it is, for instance,impossible to define what conduct is unbefitting an officer aiid a gentleman.The few short principles indicated should therefore be regarded as a mereaide-memoire of the conversations.38Aide-Memoire.Note. In these proposals &quot;persons of ministerial rank&quot; are understood as the Prime Minister, Cabinet Ministers, other Ministers and parliamentary Secretaries.BEFORE any broadcast by a person of ministerial rank is arranged by theB.B.C., reference should be made to whatever Government Department the PrimeMinister prescribes for dealing with such matters. If the initiative fora ministerial broadcast comes from the Government side, the Government Depart-ment prescribed will make the necessary arrangements with the B.B.C.[31274]
2. When it is proposed that a broadcast shall be made by a person of ministerial rank which in the opinion of the B.B.C. or of the Department charged by the Prime Minister with responsibility for dealing with these matters mightbe regarded as controversial rather than as a statement of national policy, theDepartment should arrange for consultations to be held between the political parties through the usual channels with a view to deciding whether theOpposition should be given an opportunity to broadcast a reply; and where it is agreed as a result of such consultations that the Opposition should have anopportunity to reply, the B.B.C. should be required to afford the necessary facilities. If the B.B.C. think that facilities for a broadcast on behalf of anyother political party should be afforded, the Government should be informedwithout delay of this view. The proposal could then be taken up, if desired, inconsultation between the parties through the usual channels.3. On certain occasions, the practice of broadcasting a brief rejoinder bythe Government, as in the case of pre-war budget broadcasts, should be arranged.ANNEX II.Broadcasting House, London, W. 1,Dear Mr. Greenwood, 25th January, 1946.IN confirmation of the talk which the Chairman, Sir Allan Powell, and Ihad with you and the Lord Chancellor on the 23rd January, I am writing to puton record the B.B.C.&apos;s agreement with your view that in the long run good senseand good will are more essential to the conduct of political broadcasting than a set of elaborate rules. We accept your enclosed paper on Ministerial broadcastsas an aide-memoire of our conversation with the two provisoes which both you and the Lord Chancellor felt were reasonable : 1. That in the event of the Parties disagreeing after consultation between themselves, then the B.B.C. should exercise its own responsibility of deciding whether there should be a broadcast reply or not.2. That the freedom of the B.B.C. to provide facilities for a broadcast onbehalf of any Party other than the Opposition should extend also to persons. The Government would be informed without delay of sucha view on the part of the Corporation and any other Parties concerned could also be informed. But in such cases the final responsibility would rest with the Corporation.As I explained to you, we would envisage this procedure as a rare occurrence.But we must have an understanding which does not force the B.B.C. into theposition it was in some years ago when the three senior Privy Councillors wrotea remonstrance that the then existing agreement on political broadcasting&quot;eliminated and silenced any M.P.S who were not nominated by the party leaders or Party whips.&quot;With kind regards,Yours sincerely,W. J. HALEY.The Et. Hon. Arthur Greenwood, C.H., M.P.,Gwydyr House, Whitehall, SW. 1.



</content>
</cab>
