<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/35 images: 402-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  April 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)90th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 90 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, April 12, 1940, at 4 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., , The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.   !     Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,   The    Right    Hon.    Winston    S.M.P., Lord Privy Seal. Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley, M.P.,   The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Secretary of State for War. Bt., M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present :The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.General  Sir  W.   Edmund  Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.21144]
WAR CABINET 90 (40).- Contents.minute no.                                        Subject. page 1      Press     ........................     301False reports of events in Scandinavia.2      The Western Front   ...       ...............     301Action if Holland or Belgium is invaded.3      Operation &quot; Rupert&quot; ...............     301
1. The First Lord of the Ad?niralty referred to statements made at that morning&apos;s meeting of the War Cabinet as to thefalse reports which had appeared in the Press on the previous day that British troops had recaptured Bergen and Trondhjem.He was informed that the enquiries made of the Admiralty hadnot, as was alleged, been answered merely by a statement thatthese reports could not be confirmed. On the contrary, thoseconsulted had stated categorically that the reports were withoutfoundation. While it would be undesirable to institute a public-enquiry, he thought that the matter should be fully examined, andthe Press representatives confronted with the real facts. TheAdmiralty would afford all facilities for this to be done.The War Cabinet Invited the Minister of Information to arrange for thismatter to be examined.The western front.Action if holland or belgium is invaded.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 8.)2. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChairman of the Military Co-ordination Committee covering aReport by the Chiefs of Staff as to the action to be taken if Germanyinvades Holland or Belgium (W.P. (40) 126).A report of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.Operation&quot; Rupert.&quot;(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The War Cabinet had a further discussion on this operation, which is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File ofWar Cabinet Conclusions.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,April 12, 1940.False reports ofevents in scandinavia.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 89thConclusions,Minute 13.)




</content>
</cab>
