<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/58/5 images: 70-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government cc(76) 5thConclusionsCOPY NO85cabinetCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 12 FEBRUARY 1976at 10.15 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for Scotland&quot;^He Rt Hon Merlyn Ree s mp secretary of State for Northern Ireland^he Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Hon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for wales the Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy Seal
The Rt Hon Fred Mulley MP The Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and Science     Minister for Overseas development the Rt Hon Robert Mellish MP The Rt Hon John Silkin mp parliamentary Secretary, Treasury Minister for Planning and LocalGovernmentSECRETARIATSir John hunt mr G R Denman (Items 1, 2 and 6)Mr J A Hamilton (Items 3 and 4)Mr T F Brenchley (Item 2)Mr W I Mclndoe (Item 5)Mr E J G Smith (Items 1, 2 and 6)Mr A D Gordon-Brown (Item 1)Mr A M Macpherson (Item 3)Mr C J Farrow (Item 4)CONTENTSftem                                                         Subject page 1.                    PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS royal Commission on the Legal Profession 12.                   FOREIGN AFFAIRSVisit of the Federal German Chancellor 2Iceland 2Falkland Islands 43.                   EMPLOYMENT MEASURES 54.                 FUEL BILLS 85%                   THE CIVIL SERVICEPolitical Activities and a Post-entry Union Shop 106.                   DIRECT ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLY 13
PARLIAMENTARY     1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in affairs the House of Commons during the following week.    In discussionof the previous day&apos;s vote on the salary of the Secretary of Statefor Industry, it was noted that a Motion was to bo put downinstructing the Clerk of the House to publish the lists of members who had participated in the voided vote; and that consideration would be given to possible means of preventing crowding around the lobbies during divisions.Royal Commission     THE PRIME MINISTER informed the Cabinet that, following0&amp; the Legal discussion with the Ministers principally concerned of the proposalsProfession for a Royal Commission on the legal profession which had been putforward by Mr Jack Ashley MP and others, he would be announcingin the House that afternoon that a Royal Commission was to beestablished.    The Bar Council and the Law Society had the previous day issued a joint statement that they would welcome theopportunity to participate in such an inquiry.    The RoyalCommission would cover England and Wales; the question what action might be appropriate in Scotland was under consideration.The Cabinet -Took note.1
2. THE PRIME MINISTER said that he and the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary had met the Federal German Chancellor,Herr Schmidt, and Foreign Minister, Herr Genscher, at Chequersthe previous weekend.    They had had a series of usefuldiscussions.    In general it appeared that Herr Schmidt was anxious to have meetings like this to balance the regular Franco-German consultations and to show that he considered Anglo-german relations as equally important.    Herr Schmidt had now a much better opinion - which he had expressed publicly - of Britain&apos;economic prospects.    There had been a long discussion oneconomic affairs, particularly on structural unemployment.    Theviews of the two Governments were similar on many aspects, butthey diverged on two.    The Germans had a large coal surplus andwere tlosing pits.    Herr Schmidt had attacked rail monopolies asinefficient and supported road hauliers as efficient; it had beenmade plain that we did not share this analysis.On Iceland Herr Schmidt was worried about the effects of thedispute on the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO), but be had explained the distance we were prepared to go to reach a compromise and that we were ready to accept mediation.Herr Schmidt would not himself act as a mediator, and had suggested using again the good offices of Dr Luns, the secretary general of NATO,    The Prime Minister had raised the questionof offset payments against the cost of our forces in Germany.Herr Schmidt had shown signs of wishing to be helpful but couldnot commit himself at mis stage in view of his forthcomingelection.    On the Tindemane Report on European Union, bothsides had agreed that the European Council in April should havea general discussion only, with substantive discussion beingdeferred until a further meeting of the European Council later in the year.The Cabinet -1. Took note of the statement by thePrime Minister.. FOREIGNAFFAIRSVisit of theFederal GermanChancellorand?*Oviou8Hrence: C(76) 4th^elusionsTHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thaton the previous day he and the Minister of Agriculture had had a discussion with the Secretary General of the North atlantic treaty Organisation (NATO), Dr Luns, and had then brought himover to talk to the Prime Minister.    Dr Luns was by now convinced of the incorrigibility of the Icelanders, but was neverthelessnaturally more concerned with the NATO aspects than with the fishing aspects of the problem.    Six points had been put to Dr Luns2
for him to convey to the Icelanders in a further effort to demonstrate our reasonableness.    These were; the idea of ashort-term agreement to which the Icelanders had recently turnedwould be acceptable to us; on catch we thought that the time had come for Iceland to put forward figures for discussion; we wereprepared to conduct secret negotiations if that was what theIcelanders wanted; we were willing to withdraw our trawlers acertain distance offshore as part of a settlement; if an agreement could be reached we were ready to keep it secret for a period which would allow for withdrawal of our frigates followed by a48 hour interval prior to the announcement of the agreement;meanwhile, we would welcome NATO observers on board our ships off Iceland so that they could see for themselves where theresponsibility lay for incidents.Dr LuntJ had telephoned the Icelandic Foreign Minister,Mr Agustsson, after the meeting and had told him that he wouldhave points to put to him through the Icelandic Ambassador to NATO, whom he would be seeing on his return to Brussels today.Despite the reasonableness of these points, Dr Luna shared ourpessimism about the chances of a settlement.    The fact was thatif the Icelandic Prime Minister, Mr Hallgrimsson, had to make a choice between breaking up his coalition and ceasing to be PrimeMinister on the one hand or breaking off relations with the UnitedKingdom on the other, he would prefer the latter.In discussion the following points were made -a. There was an element of propaganda in the icelandic Governments use of their scientists1recommendation of a cod catch of 230, 000 tonnes in 1976;a figure as low as this would have serious unemploymentconsequences for the Icelandic fishing industry and it was clear that they were willing to base their policy on a figureof 265, 000 tonnes.    We had offered to let the Icelandersdecide what the total allowable catch should be and were willing to accept as our share 28 per cent of this figure,subject to maximum and minimum tonnage figures.    Ifthe Icelanders chose 265, 000 tonnes, 28 per cent would fall between the maximum and minimum tonnages we had proposed.    We were also ready to consider otherconservation measures such as the size of mesh,b. The Icelandic gunboats continued to show a veryaggressive attitude.    There was a real danger of a shipbeing lost.    To cover the 41 trawlers now on station wehad a large defence force:  at present this consisted of threefrigates, a Royal Fleet Auxiliary, a Royal Fleet tug and twocivilian defence tugs with a third on its way there to join them.3SECRET
c. The implications of our policy for NATO must continue to be kept in mind.    The suggestion for NATOobservers was a valuable one and should help to counterIcelandic propaganda accounts of incidents on the fishinggrounds.The Cabinet -2.        Took note of the statement by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and of the points made in discussion.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said thatthe situation was a worrying one.    On hearing that the ArgentineForeign Minister, Senor Quijano, was to be in New York on11 February, he had sent the Parliamentary Under Secretary ofState for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs, Mr Rowlands, to talk to him, with a brief aimed at defusing the emotional situation created by the recent attempt of an Argentine destroyer to arrestthe Royal Research Ship Shackle ton.    Mr Rowlands would askwhat proposals the Argentines had regarding talks on sovereigntyand would tell them that we were ready to defend the falkland islands in the face of an Argentine attack.    Nevertheless, wemust ourselves recognise that defence of the Falkland islands would be a difficult task and that a situation could arise which wouldinvolve a national humiliation.    He had asked for a militaryappreciation to be prepared and when it was ready he would be putting in a paper to Cabinet.   It would be necessary for Cabinetto decide whether the Falkland Islands were really to be defendedor not.    The Islanders themselves numbered only some 2, 000 andwere totally dependent on us for their defence.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR DEFENCE said that he welcomed the proposal that Cabinet should study this problem.    Even to send a frigate to the Falkland Islands would take 15-J days at present whenthe nearest frigate was at Trinidad.   A problem would arise whenthe Mediterranean Shackleton wanted to leave Port Stanley.    Even if a frigatehad been sent there it would be no match for an Argentine destroyer.Indeed, Argentina could deploy more than one destroyer.    Theyhad a good navy and if it were all put to use it could only be counteredby a major task force including an aircraft carrier.    Because ofinadequate landing facilities, there was no possibility of reinforcingthe Falkland Islands by air.The Cabinet -3. Took note of the statements by the foreign and Commonwealth Secretary and the Secretary ofState for Defence.
3.        THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Ministerial Committeeon Economic Strategy (MES) had discussed at some length earlier in the week proposals by the Chancellor of the Exchequer for afurther package of measures to alleviate unemployment.    Theseproposals had received a wide measure of support in MES, andhe was now inviting the Chancellor of the Exchequer to inform theCabinet of the measures before they were announced in parliament that afternoon.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the packageof measures he would be announcing that afternoon involved a totalgross expenditure of  220 million,  137 million of which would be spent in 1976-77.    His proposals were grouped under the threeheadings of manpower and training, construction, and industry.Under the first heading  55 million would be spent over three years to create 30-35, 000 extra training places in industry.    this included the provision of  5 million to finance a scheme fornon-craft operative training in the engineering industry which mr Hugh Scanlon had been advocating.    The TemporaryEmployment Subsidy Scheme was to be extended, first by increasing the maximum period of entitlement from 6 months to12 months, and secondly by reducing the minimum size of a qualifying redundancy from 25 to 10 workers.    The total grosscost of these extensions would be about  16 million.    It was not proposed to increase the amount of the subsidy because the marginal cost to the Exchequer of the extra 20, 000 workers thatmight thereby be brought within the scheme would be nearly  50a head, and the offsetting savings were likely to be much lessthan this.    Moreover, the net effect on the public sector borrowing requirement could be as high as  30 million.    He proposed toextend the School Leaver Subsidy Scheme to cover Christmas 1975school leavers at a cost of about  5 million.    He also proposed toincrease the funds allocated to the job creation scheme whichproduced jobs quickly and did not displace other workers.    the manpower Services Commission wanted to be assured that thescheme would not, for lack of funds, have to taper off during thewinter when there might be a great need for it,    He would therefore be allocating a further  30 million to create temporaryemployment under the scheme.    The assistance he proposed for industry would amount to an additional  55 million to new industryschemes under the Industrial Investment Programme, which would help to secure the re-equipment and restructuring of importantsections of the country&apos;s manufacturing base.     1 million wouldbe allocated to the Development Commission for the building ofmore small factories in rural areas; and the National EnterpriseBoard would be placing orders for standard machine tools to thevalue of  5 million for future disposal at commercial rates.Finally, in respect of the construction industry, he was allocating5
 50 million to be spent on housing improvement work.     6 million of this would be spent in Scotland and  4 million in Wales.Housing improvement was labour-intensive, and would make a valuable social and political impact.    In addition to all theseproposals, he intended to allocate  8 million for correspondingmeasures in Northern Ireland,    He would also be making some reference in his statement to consultations between himself andthe Secretary of State for Education and Science about ways inwhich local education authorities might be encouraged to maketraining places available in further education colleges and otherestablishments for unemployed young people in the 16-19 age group.The total gross effect of the package he would be announcing wouldbe to provide some 140, 000 jobs; but because of the displacementeffect -vhich this additional employment would have cn the labour market, the net addition would amount to some 70, COO jobs.The cost cf the package would be very much greater than either of the two previous packages, and he believed that it would be welcomed by the Trades Union Congress who were particularly anxious that additional industrial training places should be madeavailable and that assistance should be given to the construction industry.    The effect of the package on the balance of payments would be tolerable, but it would absorb a substantial portion of the contingency reserve for 1976-77: and of the total contingency reserve of  900 million for 1976-77 well over half had beenearmarked already and severe restraints would have to be appliedto any further claims.In discussion, it was argued that the proposals now to be announcedought first to have been considered in detail by the Cabinet.    Itwas difficult for Ministers who were not members of MES to discover the details of proposals being discussed, though theymight have a substantial interest.    For example, the intentionto allocate  50 million to help the construction industry raised the question whether all this money should be devoted to housingimprovement.    There were other construction projects, equallylabour-intensive and socially valuable, on which the Governmentcould be spending money, for example, the improvement of fire prevention measures in old people e homes, many of which weregravely at risk in this connection.   It was suggested that theChancellor of the Exchequer should not restrict the expenditureof  50 million for the construction industry to the particular task of housing improvement, but should allow the money to be appliedto labour intensive building schemes on improvements which theGovernment considered to be socially desirable.    This would giveMinisters who had not yet been able to study the package theopportunity to put forward bids for building work which they considered to be important.    If this could not be done, it was argued that any later allocation of funds for construction should be
applied to areas other than housing.    Moreover there was a strong case for doubling the amount that was to be made available to assistthe construction industry in view of the high level of unemployment towhich it was subject, particularly in such areas as Merseyside andGlasgow.It was pointed out, however, that the concern over the recentunemployment figures had placed the Government under intensepressure to take speedy action; indeed an undertaking to this effecthad been given during the unemployment debate in the House ofCommons on 29 January.    This had made it necessary for theMinisters primarily concerned to move quickly.    The centralproblem was to increase the level of additional expenditure withoutplacing in jeopardy the decisions which had already been taken to restrain public expenditure.    This suggested that expenditure to alleviate unemployment should be concentrated on a limited number of effective measures rather than being thinly spread over manyprogrammes.    It was the considered view of MES that the packagewas well-balanced, and relevant to the employment situation and tothe wider needs of the economy.   Furthermore, the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer had to retain some freedom of manoeuvre in thepreparation of his Budget proposals and it would also be wise to keepsome measures in reserve in case it became necessary to introduceanother unemployment package later in the year,THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that because of the timetable promised by the Government, the ministers primarily concerned had been obliged to produce an unemploymentpackage urgently.    Although some members of the Cabinet hadreservations about the procedure which this degree of urgencyentailed, the Cabinet agreed generally that the measures which theChancellor of the Exchequer would be announcing that afternoon were an effective and well-balanced response.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.7
! FTJEl, 4, The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary of1 &quot;ILLS State for Energy (C(76) 11) containing proposals for measures to dealwith the danger of disconnection of gas and electricity supplies to oldI people as a result of increases in fuel prices.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY said that with the doubling of prices of fuel in two years and the difficult economicconditions there was an increased   likelihood of people being facedwith disconnection of gas and electricity supplies because of their inability to pay the bills.    The problem was particularly serious inthe case of pensioners.    They were prone to hypothermia and because they valued their independence might not avail themselves of the assistance which was available.    There was an additionaldifficulty in that they were a generation with a very high sense ofresponsibility and were liable to take Government publicity about theneed for fuel economy to the point of damaging their health.    Therewere already arrangements whereby the gas and electricity industries,having extended credit for at least five or six weeks from the date ofj an account, and given warning of the riskB of disconnection, suspendedsuch action for 14 days for people apparently suffering genuinehardship and referred them to the Supplementary BenefitsCommission.    The relevant agencies then considered whetherfinancial help could be given or other arrangements made to deal with existing debts and to avoid further debt arising.    Various easypayment schemes and some pre-payment meters were available tohelp people to keep up with their payments subsequently.    However,while very few in number, cases continued to be reported whichthrough human error appeared to have slipped through the safety net.He considered that further action was necessary and had consulted the chairmen of the Electricity Council, the Area Electricity Boards andthe British Gas Corporation on the possibility of a temporary suspension of disconnection for households consisting solely of pensioners.    They had expressed concern that such a course could lead to a great increase in feckless behaviour.    To meet their concern he proposed that the suspension should last only until the endof May.    It would also be limited strictly to households consisting ofstate pensioners living on their own and not including any otherincome earner.    On this basis the industries would be uneasy but would be willing to apply the policy.    It was very difficult to estimatewhat the cost might be.    The figure of  6 million in his memorandum was a maximum theoretical possibility which he did not regard as atall likely.    It would be his objective to make the industries carry the costs themselves.    As a second measure he proposed to establish an informal review with the industries under the chairmanship of theParliamentary Under Secretary of State, Lord Lovell-Davis, of themethods of payment by gas and electricity consumers.    The large increases in prices made such a review appropriate.    In reachingconclusions they would be able to take account of practice in other8
countries.    He would like to make a low key announcement of these measures to Parliament on 16 February: a report was being published that day explaining why it was not possible to assist poorer consumersby a rearrangement of the tariffs of the fuel industries.    If thisreport were not accompanied by some positive measures it would create an unfortunate impression.In discussion it was argued that it would be wholly inappropriate tomake an announcement of these measures at the present time.    no opportunity had been given to consult the Scottish Boards about theeffect of the proposals in that country.    Moreover, the ScottishNational Party was mounting a nation-wide political campaign basedon an exaggerated assessment of the risks of hypothermia and themeasures proposed would be widely interpreted as a confirmation oftheir propaganda.    On the other hand, it was pointed out that if theGovernment took no action it would continue to receive bad publicityeven though the scale of the problem was in fact very small.    It was however suggested that the statement should be amended so as to givecredit both to the positive action which had already been taken by thesupply industries and by the Supplementary Benefits Commission.Care would also be needed in the presentation to avoid any impression of duplication with the inquiry by the National Consumer Council intothe impact of higher fuel bills which had been established in December.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet supported the two proposals by the Secretary of State forEnergy and agreed that they should be announced in Parliament on16 February,    The Secretary of State for Energy should howeverrevise the terms of the statement to take account of the points madein discussion and in particular to ensure that the position in Scotland was satisfactorily covered.The Cabinet -L Took note, with approval, of the PrimeMinister &apos;s summing up of their discussion.2.        Agreed the proposals in C(76) 11.3.        Invited the Secretary of State for Energy to revise his draft statement in consultation with the secretaries of State for Scotland, Northern Ireland,Prices and Consumer Protection, and .Social Services and to make an announcement toParliament on 16 February,9
5,        The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Lord Privy Seal(C(76) 9 and 10) about the restrictions on the political activities ofcivil servants and the application of the closed shop principle to theCivil Service.THE LORD PRIVY SEAL said that the present rules governing thepolitical activities of civil servants were based on the report of theMasterman Committee in 1949 and were introduced in a White Paperpublished in March 1953.    They divided the Civil Service into three groups: the &quot;politically free&quot; (all industrial and non-office grades);the &quot;intermediate&quot; (up to Executive Officer level); and the &quot;restricted&quot;(Executive Officer and above).    There had been increasing pressure from all the Civil Service unions for a relaxation of these restrictionson the basis that any civil servant should be allowed to engage in political activities provided that the Department concerned judged, inany particular case, that this would not run counter to the publicinterest.    In a letter dated 9 September the Lord Privy Seal had invited the views of his colleagues on a number of possible options for negotiation with the Staff Side; he himself had favoured a proposal toextend the &quot;intermediate&quot; group to include the grades immediatelybelow Principal level.    The replies of his colleagues, however, had shown a wide measure of disagreement over how far the present restrictions should be relaxed.    Following the refusal by the RoyalCommission on Standards of Conduct in Public Life to consider asubmission on this question from the National Staff Side the latter hadformally requested that an independent committee of inquiry beappointed.    The recent public criticism of the Civil Service and theprospect of a retrenchment of staff numbers  made It the moreimportant that a positive response should be made to this request.Moreover, when the Prime Minister had informed the Leader of theOpposition of the limited relaxation of the restrictions which theOfficial Side had tentatively offered to the Staff Side, she had indicated that the Opposition would not accept even this relaxationwithout, at any rate, an impartial and open examination of the issues involved.    His first memorandum (C(76) 9) therefore proposed that anindependent committee of inqui ry should be set up along the lines ofthe Masterman Committee whlfh reported in i949.The question of the post-entry union shop raised in his secondmemorandum (C(76) 10) was mire difficult.    The pressures for this had come chiefly from the CIv:I and Public Services Association(CPSA), whose National Executive would be considering strongresolutions in support of the closed shop principle at its meeting in mid-March,   Although there was no real unanimity amongst the other unions on the subject, they were all anxious to secure the elimination of &quot;free riders&quot; and to maximise the payment of contributions to theirfunds.    The problems posed lor the Civil Service by the closed shopprinciple included both the potential conflict of loyalties and the
implications for civil servants who might refuse to join a union.Since however it was the Governments legislation which had openedthe way to Staff Side pressure on this front, it would be difficult to reject the principle of a closed shop from the outset or to refuse tonegotiate on it.    He believed, therefore, that the best course wouldbe to open the subject to public debate in the same way as the issue ofpolitical activities.    H3 had reason to think that having shown initialhostility to this course of action, the CPSA would come to acquiesce in it.    Butitwould be important that a decision to refer the matter toan independent committee of inquiry should be announced before theCPSA&apos;s National Executive meeting In mid-March,    He had considered whether the two issues should bo dealt with by the same or byseparate committees of inquiry: he himself favoured a singlecommittee both because of the manpower and cost implications and because he believed that a single committee would be more likely toarrivs at a balanced view.In discussion some Ministers argued that both issues should besettled by the Government, without reference to an Independentinquiry, the first as a matter which should be decided simply in termsof the public interest and the second as a matter which properly fell to the Government as employer,   A substantial majority, however,took the view that, particularly in the light of the Staff Sidefs requestand the attitude of the Opposition, it would be reasonable to refer the question of political activities to an independent committee of inquiry,   A further consideration in favour of this course was thelength of time which had elapsed since the subject was last reviewed by the Master man Committee.    Doubt was however expressedwhether, as the Lord Privy Seal had suggested, it would be appropriate for the committee to be chaired by a Law Lord (ratherthan, for example, a distinguished layman with experience of public administration) or, so far as political or other representation was concerned, to be drawn primarily from the ranks of the retired.As regards the proposal that a committee of inquiry should also dealwith the question of applying the closed shop principle to the CivilService, it was pointed out that, despite misrepresentation to thecontrary, the legislation promoted by the Government did not favourthis principle but merely allowed its application to be the subject of negotiation between employers and employees.    To treat the CivilService differently in this respect by referring the question to acommittee of inquiry would thus be contrary to the governments general policy.    This would be resented by the Trades UnionCongress and also by other sections of the community, eg newspapereditors, who would like their case to be similarly distinguished.    Theright course was for the Government as an employer to negotiate on theclosed    shop principle and to consider what exceptions or adaptionsto the general principle might be required in the case of the CivilService,U
It was however also strongly argued that the question of a post-entryunion shop in the Civil Service raised unique issues which touched atthe heart of public administration and at the reputation of the service for impartiality and loyalty to the Government of the day.    There wasa good case for firmly resisting demands for a closed shop,particularly since there was no evidence of weakness in theorganisation and strength of unions within the Civil Service, which aclosed shop might be designed to remedy.    Indeed if the Governmentrejected a closed shop on constitutional grounds there was reason tothink that this would command considerable sympathy with the rank and file.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were clearly in favour of the proposal to refer the question ofpolitical activities to an independent committee of inquiry.    In thelight of the discussion he would consider further, in consultation withthe Lord President of the Council, the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the Lord Privy Seal, the composition and terms of reference ofsuch a committee.    Equally clearly the Cabinet rejected the proposalto refer the question of a post-entry union shop to a committee of inquiry and felt that the Government should reach its own decision onthe matter.    The Cabinet had not reached a final view on what thatdecision should be: and he would arrange for a representative group of Ministers to consider the issue further and to recommend to theCabinet the Hne which the Government should take with theNational Staff Side.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.12
6.        The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs and the Secretary ofState for the Home Department (C(76) 2 (Revise)) covering a draft white Paper on direct elections to the European Assembly.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that sincethe Cabinet last discussed the matter in January he had been inconsultation with the political Parties.    The Ulster Unionists were inprinciple opposed to direct elections; Plaid Cymru wanted Wales tohave her own voice in the Community^ institutions, were opposed to direct elections, but if they took place would like to know how Welshrepresentation compared with that of smaller Member States; the liberals supported direct elections, were anxious about the representation of Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland in relation tothat of the small Member States, stressed the need for a link between Assembly members and the British Parliament, and urgedthat some form of proportional representation was required; theConservative Party and the relevant sub-committees of the national executive Committee of the Labour Party had deferred comment until after publication of the White Paper; and the Scottish nationalist party had said that the first priority was direct Scottish represen-tation on all the Community^ institutions, endorsed the principle of direct elections, but reserved their position in practice untilScotland w&amp;b in their view appropriately recognised.The proposed White Paper was in three parts.    The first partdescribed the current situation, the second discussed mattersrequiring Community decision, and the third listed issues for subsequent national decision.    It did not debate whether or not thereshould be direct elections - we were committed to them by our accession to the European Economic Community (e.c.), confirmed by the referendum, and reiterated by the Prime Miniser and himselffollowing the Cabinet decision the previous November.    discussion should be concentrated on the second part of the White Paper, andparticularly on the total size of the Assembly and its distributionbetween countries.    This was bound to give rise to much dispute.There would have to be some weighting in favour of the smallercountries, but the present Assembly proposals were weightedheavily in their favour and the contrast between the representationproposed for Luxembourg, the Irish Republic and Denmark with thatlikely to come from Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland was verystark.    He believed therefore that we should strive to achieve adistribution giving a closer relationship between seats and population.The French felt the same; they did not in any case wish to see rapid progress towards direct elections and this issue could easily delay theintroduction of the system beyond 1978.13
He proposed that in the light of the Cabinet&apos;8 discussion he and theHome Secretary should present the White Paper the following week,that the Lord President of the Council should arrange for it to bediscussed by the Parliamentary Labour Party (PLP) and then by theHouse of Commons, In time to give guidance to the Prime Ministerand himself when they dealt with this matter at the European council meeting on 1 and 2 April,In discussion it was argued that the proposal raised a number ofissues of fundamental importance which required thorough dUcuasion,The timetable indicated in the White Paper, which envisaged finalisingthe terms of a draft Convention on direct elections at the EuropeanCouncil on 1-2 April, was far too precipitate.    The commitment inthe Trer-ty of Rome was to &quot;elections by direct universal suffrage inaccordance with a uniform procedure&quot;; but the Member States haddeferred that commitment and there was no reason why they shouldnot similarly defer a move in that direction.    Moreover on examination the proposals set out in the draft White Paper werevague - more suitable to a Green Paper at best - the debates in thePLP and Parliament would be diffuse, and it would be very difficultfoi the Prime Minister and the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretaryto know what their mandate was at the European Council.    Theintroduction of direct elections would move us towards a federalEuropean state and would confuse democratic legitimacy, introducing a separate centre of sovereignty with its own set of representatives,claiming the elected right to speak for the United Kingdom.    Therewas no popular pressure for such a development.    The increasedlegitimacy given to the European Assembly would be bound to lead indue course to increases In Its powers, and thus to the down-grading ofParliament.    Direct elections would moreover encourage thetendencies towards the break-up of the United Kingdom, a process which would be exacerbated by the sharp disparity between represen-tation at the European Assembly of Scotland, Wales and NorthernIreland with that of independent Member States of similar size.    Allthese issues, together with the considerable organisational difficulties involved, should be considered by a Speaker&apos;s Conference or similarbody.On the other hand it was argued that we had already accepted the commitment to move to direct elections and the draft White paper was an honest exposition of the associated questions which had to be faced.    Although, as a matter of record, the European Council had set work in hand with a view to finalising the text of a draftConvention on direct elections at the next European Council in April,in fact It was most unlikely that final decisions would be taken then,and possibly might be delayed until much later.    The illustrative draftConvention set out In Annex B to the White Paper came from the14
Assembly, and in no way committed the Government.    The text ofthe draft White Paper should be amended to make this plain, and toavoid any implication that we were committed to finalising the text inApril.    These changes would make it even more obvious that the government&apos;s proposals were mainly of a Green Paper rather than a white Paper nature.    The representation of Scotland, Wales andNorthern Ireland in relation to the smaller Member States would admittedly be a difficult issue, on which we would have to press our views.    The introduction of direct elections, far from increasing thepowers of the European Assembly, would in the immediate future havethe opposite effect.    The question of increased powers would be deferred until direct elections had been instituted, and then theGovernments of Member States would be more chary about the granting of additional powers.    It was important that the Prime Minister andthe Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary be in a position to influence the discussion on direct elections which would begin at the EuropeanCouncil in April.In further discussion the following additional points were made -a. The Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary hadsugge sted that the Cabinet should spend a whole day at chequers after the Budget on considering our objectives in the eec.    This proposal was to be welcomed.    Discussion at theEuropean Council in April would inevitably not reach finality:and the issue could thus be discussed more fully at Chequersbefore any irrevocable decision was taken.b. Against the background of the considerable changes inthe Community which would follow the admission of Greece andpossibly certain other Mediterranean countries direct electionswould in practice be of less importance than had been argued.c. Elections to the European Assembly on a single day,or short spread of days, between national general electionscould cause considerable complications for domestic politicsif the election went against the Government of the day.    the relationship of elections to the European Assembly toelections to local authorities and the Scottish and WelshAssemblies required further thought.d. There had been no consideration of other important issues *uch as the methods of election, the organisation and financing of the European elections, and the relationship between members of the European Assembly and the UnitedKingdom Parliament.   It was pointed out however that thesematters fell within the area for national decision, which would15
follow the issues for Community decision.    The principles andbasic framework of direct elections should be determinedfirst, and these issues later.e, Further thought should be given to the question ofnationals of other Member States voting in this country in theEuropean Assembly elections.f. Since we had the stongest democratic traditions, weshould gain in influence in the European Assembly, particularly on the control of expenditure and on the representation of thegeneral will of the people rather than of pressure groups for individual interests.The Cabinet then considered the text of the draft White Paper.Amendments were agreed to paragraph 7 and Annex B to make plain that the draft Convention summarised there came from the european assembly and that the Government was not committed to it; to paragraphs 10, 27 and 42 to avoid the implication that the Governmentwas committed to finalising a text of the Convention at the EuropeanCouncil on 1-2 April; and to paragraph 18 to strengthen the referenceto the need to take into account the relationship of the representationof the smaller Membex States with that of the constituent pares of larger Member States.    Other amendments were also agreed.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that a clear majority of the Cabinet agreed that the Foreign and commonwealth secretary and the Home Secretary should present their proposals toParliament the following week, but as a Green Paper rather than a white Paper, and as amended in discussion.    The Lord President ofthe Council should arrange for the Green Paper to be discussed by thePLP and then to be debated in Parliament.    Following this the cabinet would have opportunity to discuss the line to be taken at the EuropeanCouncil on 1-2 April, and thereafter there would be the proposed whole-day discussion of our e.c. objectives before final decisions on theConvention on direct elections were taken.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister &apos;summing up of their discussion.Cabinet Office12 February 197616

</content>
</cab>
