<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/29/24 images: 214-219</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3/f 0Tjflg,DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERMENT,secret. ^gpTTIfe) Wt. COPY 362nd October 19U2.-WAR CABINET,ADMISSION TO THE UNITED KINGDOM OFCHILDREN FROM UNOCCUPIED FRANCEMemorandum &quot;by the Home Secretary.J1,     I am exceedingly sorry to bother my colleagues with a subsidiary point which has arisen in connection with thedecision of the War Cabinet on the 28th September (W.M.(42)130th Conclusions, Minute I4.) that the admission to this country of refugees from Unoccupied France should he limited (a) to children who had a parent or parents already in this country,subject (b) to the Home Secretary having discretion also to admit orphan children who had a near relative in this country.2.     The cases in which a child is in Unoccupied France and aparent is in this country are exceptional.      It is right to accord exceptional treatment to these children, but the numberwill be very small, perhaps not more than 20.3.     No representations have as yet been made to the Home Officeabout orphan children with near relatives in this country.    Most-orphan children are believed to be in institutions and their position will not be affected by the deportation policy of the vichy Government,k*     The children whose position is most pitiful are those whobecome in effect orphans as the result of the deportation of their parents.      The fate of their parents will often be uncertain andas a result of the Cabinet decision it will be necessary torefuse to admit such children unless evidence is forthcoming that both of the parents have perishedo5*     Nothing ought to be done which is liable to encourage the vichy Government to think that their deportation policy will bemade easier by the readiness of the United Kingdom to admit thechildren if the parents are deported.      But the admission ofsuch children only as have close relatives in this country is unlikely to have any such effect.     The parents of many of them have already been deported,-      The number who will be eligiblefor admission is quite small, and there is no reason to thinkthat a decision to admit to the United Kingdom individual casesof children who have a close relative here will influence the vichy Government to deport parents whom they would not otherwisedeport,6.     Strong sympathy will be excited in many quarters in thiscountry for this small group of children who are left in theposition of de facto orphans in France and have near relatives inthe United Kingdom ready and anxious to look after them.     TheRefugee Organisations recognise that there must be a limitation on the numbers admitted, and I do not think there would be any-substantial difficulty in making a clear line of demarcation bydefining close relative as meaning a grandparent; &quot;an uncle or am.a brother or a sister.1*      I shall be grateful, therefore, if the War Cabinet will be sogood as slightly to amend the previous decision so as to authoristhe Home Secretary to admit to this country refugee children from Unoccupied France if there is already in this country either

H.M.HOME OFFICE.2nd October 19h2aa parent or a near relative - near relative &quot;being defined as suggested above-In accordance with the previous Cabinet decisionthis policy would &quot;be applied to children of Allied Nationalwhether they are or are not Jewish. j




</content>
</cab>
