<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/168/17 images: 344-414</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY JS government cp(73) 37 COPY NO     $ j21 March 1973CABINETPRICE AND PAY CODE: DRAFT WHITE paper memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer, Since the Green Paper was published on 26 February there havebeen wide-ranging consultations at official and Ministerial level.    A listof the main organisations which have offered comments on the document is annexed.    In addition, Departments have had advice on the price andprofit control from accountants and from the chairman-designate of thePrice Commission.2. The draft White Paper trices account of all these comments and of points made in Parliament.    It incorporates decisions taken by the group of Ministers directly concerned Tuider the chairmanship of the PrimeMinister.3. On pay, the only significant change from the Green Paper is to tighten up on the payment of increments in accordance with confederation of British Industry (CBI) advice,    Otherwise, various loose ends have beentied up, the drafting clarified and a number of relatively minor changes made to meet points made by employers.    (The Trades Union Congresshave unfortunately not responded to the Governments invitation to offercomments on the Green Paper).    The essential features of the Pay Codefor Stage 2 have thus remained substantially unchanged since they were set out in the January White Paper (Cmnd 5205)o4.        On prices, there have been a number of alterations both ofstructure and of substance.    The proposals for price and profit control in the Green Paper were more tentative than those on the pay side and hadnot been so fully worked out.    As a result of the discussions withaccountants and with various representative bodies a large number of changes have been made in order to make the system more workable andeasier to understand.
5. There have also been some changes of substance designed to meetthe CBIfs criticism that the Green Paper as it stood would discourageinvestment.    The most important of these are the widening of the definition of allowable costs to include bought-in services such astransport and maintenance; the dropping of the requirement to reduceprices whenever unit costs fall as a result of increased volume;  and theintroduction of a lower productivity deduction for labour intensiveactivities,,    These changes are incorporated in paragraphs 35, 31 and 40respectively.6. Subject to Cabinet approval, it is proposed to publish the white paper on Monday 26 March, and to make the Order containing the Code on sunday 1 April.    This will activate the conrpnlsory powers in Part II of the counter-Inflation Act and bring to an end the standstill on pay.    the standstill on prices will remain in being until 28 April.70        I invite my colleagues to approve the draft White Paper and the timetable in paragraph 6 above.A treasury Chambers21 March 1973
SECTION 1Introduction1.     This Unite Paper deals with the operation of Stage Two of the.counter inflation programme.2. On 17 January the Government outlined its proposals for StageTwo in Cnmd 52155 and on 23 January the necessary legislation was introduced in Parliament. On 26 February the Government published in Cmnd 52-4-7 a Consultative Document on the Price and Pay Code andthis has since been debated in Parliament and has been the subjectof intensive consultations with representatives of industry and commerce, of consumers and of the professions.3.     The Counter Inflation Act, 1973 received Royal Assent on22 March.   Under the powers it gives, the Price Commission and pay board /&quot;have already been established/   Their main function underthe Act in Stage Two is to implement the Price and Pay Code.   Thestatutory instrument containing the Code must therefore be made soonso that they can begin that task.   Section 2 of this White Paper isa draft of the Code, in preparing which the Government have been ableto take account of the consultations of recent weeks.   The government propose to make the order containing the Code in its final form on1 April.   This will supersede the draft in this white Paper and theproposals in the White Paper of 1? January and the Green Paper of26 February.   The 1 April order will activate Part II of the Act,with its powers for regulating prices and pay, and will mark theend of the pay standstill, though   the standstill will continue until28 April for prices.   Both the Price Commission and Pay Board will beoperational from 1 April.4.     This White Paper deals with more than the Price and Pay Code,however Section 3 describes the administration of dividend control which will be operated by the Treasury in Stage Two*   Section 4-explains how Stage Two will be applied to a group of cases which arenot within the statutory control powers of the Price Commission and
- Pay Board.   They include business and agricultural rents, prices and pay which are determined by the Crown or are already governed by statutory bodies and certain prices and charges such as insurancepremiums which will be directly controlled by the Government.Section 5 deals with the arrangements for notification and reportingwhich, in the light of consultation, the Government now propose inorder to support the work of the Commission and the Board.5.     Most of the matters referred to in paragraph 4 - notificationdividends, business and agricultural rents - will require the making of separate Orders by Ministers under the Counter Inflation Actat the beginning of Stage Two,The Objectives6,     The object of the programme is to bring inflation under control.It is now generally accepted that this is necessary if we are to achieve sustained growth, higher real incomes, especially for thelow paid and pensioners; and the confidence required for higherindustrial investment.   Moreover inflation is fundamentally unfairand imposes severe strains on our society.Progress in Stage One7.     A start has been made in Stage One in bringing inflation under control in spite of an exceptionally rapid rate of increase in world prices of foodstuffs and basic raw materials.   While costs of basic materials and fuel purchased by manufacturers rose between november and February by almost 11 per cent, and costs of food manufacturesrose by 16 per cent, prices for home sales of all manufactured products rose over the same 3 month period by only 1 per cent.   Theindex of hourly wage rates remained almost steady between november and February, with the result that the percentage increase on a yearearlier fell from 16.5 per cent to 13.5 per cent.   However, it takestime for changes in pay costs to have their full effect on prices.Pay increases at pre-standstill rates will continue to put up costs and prices for some months yet, and the beneficial effects on pricesof the pay standstill will not be felt in full till later in 1973.
8.     /&quot;Moderating the rate of cost and price inflation was one ofthe agreed objectives in the tripartite talks between the Government,the TUC and CBI last autumn.   The Government have during Stage Onecontinued to pursue the other two agreed objectives.   The Budgetreflected the Government1s intention of maintaining a high rate of growth and included provision for a substantial increase in retirement pensions effective from 1 October.   As a result of this, retirement pensions will have been increased by the present Government in 3upratings by nearly twice as much as the increase in prices^Stage Two and beyond9.     Stage Two moves on from the standstill.   It is not an abandonmBntof restraint, or a return to the pre-standstill situation.   It there-fore contains price restraints which are still strict, but alsorealistic.   There are no automatic percentage increases and everyprice increase has to be justified.   On pay, Stage Two provides foran increase which is substantial by any normal standard, and it givespreference to the low paid and those who have been left behind therest of the community on equal pay, on hours, on holidays and onoccupational pensions.10.   Stage Two lasts only until the autumn.   /&quot;Subject to theprocess of consultation and any necessary Parliamentary approval, theGovernment at present envisage that the next stage of the policy will begin about the end of October^/7   In Stage Two some inequalitiesof treatment unavoidable in any programme to control an inflationlike that of last autumn are bound to remain, both on prices and on pay.   It is the Government&apos;s intention during the summer to consultboth sides of industry on the policy for Stage Three, and the decisionsbased on these consultations will, where necessary, be embodied inthe Code, subject to the approval of Parliament.11. In this way, the Code, can, for example, be altered to reflectas necessary whatever arrangements are eventually agreed for making progress towards the resolution of problems of pay relativities andanomalies in Stage Three, /&quot;including the timing of any adjustments
to pay in such c&amp;sesJ/   Similarly, it can be modified to take account of the growing requirements of investment in the private sector, and the needs of some nationalised industries to return to commercial viability.12.   The Government continue to hope that it will be possible to operate Stage Three on a voluntary tripartite basis and the consulta-tions during Stage Two will be aimed at achieving this.13.   In the interests of the community as a whole, the Governmentseek the cooperation of all in industry and commerce in the operationof Stage Two.   These are fair proposals designed to benefit everybodythrough the exercise of reasonable restraint.14.
CONFIDENTIALSECTION draft Price and Pay Code15. .    The Code has a dual function.     First,  the Price Commissionand Pay Board are required to exercise their powers so as to ensurethat it is implemented.      Secondly, all those concerned with the determination of prices and pay should have regard to it.16.     The Code is therefore addressed both to the Agencies and toall those concerned with price and pay determination.     Part I dealwith prices and Part II with pay.Part I -PricesGeneral Principles17.      The general principles relating to prices are:-(i) to limit the extent to which prices may be increased onaccount of increased costs, and to secure&apos; reductions asa result of reduced costs;(ii) to reinforce the control of prices by a control onprofit margins while safeguarding investment;(iii) to reinforce the effects of competition, and to secure its full benefits in the general level of prices.Field of Application18.     With the exceptions specified in paragraphs 19 to 2/, below,the prices of goods and services supplied to the United Kingdomhome market are within the scope of the control.19.     The prices of goods and services exported (whether directly or through an agent) are not controlled.20.     The following are not controlled:-(i) prices paid to overseas suppliers for imported goods and services;(ii) prices of goods and services where the application ofthe control would be inconsistent with :     international agreement or arrangement.      For this pu       e, an inter-CONFIDENTIAL
national agreement or arrangement is one between states or organisations of states, not between firms;(iii) prices at sales by auction, where such sales are a normal practice in the particular trade;(iv) prices of goods sold on terminal commodity markets inthe United Kingdom such as the London Metal Exchangeor the price of which is directly determined by reference to such markets;(v) prices of second hand goods (other than second handroad vehicles sold by distributors);(vi) charges for the carriage of goods or passengers on international journeys;    charges for air navigationand landing services and to ship, passenger and goodsdues, provided that they relate wholly or mainly tosuch traffic;    charges for international mail and tele-communication services;(vii) prices of ethical medicines supplied to the UnitedKingdom market to the extent that regulation of their prices is within the scope of any agreement relatingto those prices made between the Secretary of State for social Services and representatives of manufacturers ofthose medicines- but only so long as such an agreement is in force;(viii)  prices in contracts with the Secretary of State for defence for warlike stores and services which are within the agreement between Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentand industry governing the pricing of, and control ofC 2)profit from non-competitive contracts.    &apos;    These prices will be subject to the controls provided in that agreement.(ix) insurance premiums.     These will be subject to restrict-ion by the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry;  ^(x) subscriptions to certain membership organisations as inparagraph 103.U)(2)(3) - See Appendix A
Application to Food and Farming Products21.     The prices of manufactured food and drink,  like those of manufactured products generally, are within the scope of thecontrol as are those of semi-processed foodstuffs such as butter,sugar and quick-frozen vegetables.22.     The prices paid to United Kingdom producers or producers&apos;organisations or to overseas suppliers for fresh foods and similar products, which are subject to fluctuations on world and united Kingdom markets because of seasonal factors or changes inthe relationship between supply and demand, are not controlled.This applies in particular to meat,&apos; including bacon and poultry,fish, eggs, fruit and vegetables.     However, enterprises which-resell these products, whether home produced or imported, at any subsequent stage will be subject to control.23.     The retail price of milk for liquid consumption and themargins of milk distributors, will continue to be-subject to the-existing controls by the Minister and the Secretary of State forScotland.^So long as these controls apply, the price of milkwill not be subject to the Code.*24.     What is said in paragraph 22 in relation to the prices paid for fresh foods applies also to prices of other primary products of animal or vegetable origin, which are subject to fluctuations from-seasonal causes or causes external to the United Kingdom.Charges25. References in the Code to prices include references to charges,unless there is explicit provision to the  contrary.U)  (5) - See Appendix CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALDefinition of Enterprise for the purposes of the Code26. For the purposes of the Code an enterprise means either an enterprise as a whole or a separate constituent company or sub-division provided that in the latter case separate accounts forsuch sub-divisions:-(i) are, or can be made, available for all relevant periods;(ii) are not materially distorted by transactions conductedotherwise than on armslength terms;(iii) would, if combined with one another and with the accounts.  of all other activities or transactions of the enterprise, produce results consistent with those shown by the accounts of the enterprise taken as a whole.27.    where an enterprise is engaged in a combination of activitiessuch as manufacturing and distribution, or either of these and theprovision of services, these activities may be treated as separateunits for the purpose of the Code provided that adequate accountssatisfying paragraphs 26 are or can be made available for each ofthem.28.   Any reference in the Code to an enterprise includes a referenceto a separate constituent company or sub-division as defined inparagraph 26 or to a separate unit as in paragraph 27.Costs and Prices29. Prices which are within the control may not be increased unless there is an increase in total costs per unit of output. No increase may exceed the increase in total costs per unit.$0. Where there is an increase in total costs per unit, only certain increases, referred to in the Code as &quot;allowable cost increases&quot;, may
be taken into account in arriving at the permitted price increase,and they will be subject to a productivity deduction.Price Reduction31.   Prices should be reduced whenever possible.   Where there is a fall in raw material prices or other allowable costs, this shouldbe fully reflected in price reductions.   Reductions are however notrequired to exceed the fall in total costs per unit of output.    Inaddition prices should be reduced as required in paragraph 61 where an enterprise approaches or exceeds its profit margin reference level.Base Date32.   The starting point for the calculation of permitted price increases is the level of costs per unit of output at 1 October 1972.In calculating permitted price increases, cost increases firstincurred after 30 September 1972 may be taken into account, to theextent that they have not already been reflected in prices.   however the permitted price increase may not include any element of recoupmentof costs incurred before the date on which the price increase takeseffect.Calculation of Permitted Price Increase33.   A permitted price increase should be calculated by:-(i) expressing allowable cost increases per unit, as reducedby the productivity deduction, as a percentage of total costs per unit.   For this purpose costs per unit shouldbe those at the time of the price decision; and(ii) applying this percentage to the current selling price.34.   Where price increases are being made on a group of related products (under paragraphs 48 or 4-9) the allowable cost increases, asreduced by the productivity deduction, shall be expressed as a percen-tage of the total costs of the product group at the time of the pricedecision, and this percentage should be applied to the current selling price.
CONFIDENTIALAllowable Cost Increases35.   Subject to the following paragraphs, a cost increase may beregarded as an allowable cost increase for the purpose of paragraph30 if:-(i) it was first incurred for any reason after 30 September1972(6&apos;); and(ii) it was incurred for one of the following:-(a) labour -S^(b) materials,    J components, fuel and power;(c) rent of premises&quot; or rates;(d) interest charges, as defined in paragraph 38;(e) certain bought-in services, that is transport, hireof equipment, maintenance, insurance, storage,contract engineering.Pay not consistent with the Code36.   Increases in expenditure on pay or other conditions of serviceafter 6 November 1972 are allowable cost increases only to the extent that, as appropriate:-(i)   they were consistent with the policies set out in cmnd 5125* with the requirements at the relevant time ofthe Counter Inflation (Temporary Provisions) Act 1972and of any notice or order under it; or- (ii) they are consistent with the Code or with the Counter-Inflation Act 1973.37-   Examples of increases in expenditure which are not allowable cost increases because they are inconsistent with the Code are:-(6) (7) (8)   See Appendix A
(i) any part of a pay increase which exceeds the pay limit; or(ii) any part of increases in pay under settlements made at local or plant level which, when aggregated with increases under a national agreement, exceeds the pay limit forthe group concerned; and(iii) any part of increases in earnings arising from pieceworkor other payment by results schemes which exceeds the pay limit,unless the increase is specifically exempted from the pay limit by part II of the Code.Interest Charges38.    Increases in interest charges payable by an enterprise areallowable cost increases, unless(i) they represent a distribution of profits rather thana true interest charge; or(ii) they are interest charges of a kind not normally chargedagainst the profit and loss account of the enterpriseconcerned; or(iii) where they arise on loans between related undertakings,they relate to loans which are not strictly required forthe business, or are at a rate of interest higher than would be charged in a transaction at arm&apos;s length.Changes in indirect taxation39-   To the extent that changes in indirect taxes since 30 September1972 have not already been reflected in prices, an appropriatereduction to allowable cost increases should be made.    Where suchtaxes have been increased, an appropriate addition may be made.
(i) any part of a pay increase which exceeds the pay limit; or(ii) any part of increases in pay under settlements made at local or plant level which, when aggregated with increases under a national agreement, exceeds the pay limit forthe group concerned; and(iii) any part of increases in earnings arising from pieceworkor other payment by results schemes which exceeds the pay limit,unless the increase is specifically exempted from the pay limit by part II of the Code.Interest Charges38.   Increases in interest charges payable by an enterprise areallowable cost increases, unless:-(i) they represent a distribution of profits rather thana true interest charge; or(ii) they are interest charges of a kind not normally chargedagainst the profit and loss account of the enterpriseconcerned; or(iii) where they arise on loans between related undertakings,they relate to loans which are not strictly required forthe business, or are at a rate of interest higher than would be charged in a transaction at arm&apos;s length.Changes in indirect taxation39-   To the extent that changes in indirect taxes since 30 September1972 have not already been reflected in prices, an appropriatereduction to allowable cost increases should be made.    Where suchtaxes have been increased, an appropriate addition may be made.
40,   In order to ensure that the benefits of increased productivityare passed on to the consumer, a deduction should be made fromallowable cost increases which are to be passed on as price increases.Enterprises are required to absorb 50% of allowable cost increasesarising from increases in labour costs, as defined in paragraph 40A,unless the share of labour costs in total costs exceeds 55%.   Inthat case enterprises are required to absorb only an amount equalto the percentage of total costs which would apply if labour costsrepresented 55% of total.costs.40A. For the purpose of paragraph 40 labour costs exclude:-employers&apos; national insurance contributions; training costs;the cost of improvements under paragraph 123 (equal pay),paragraph 154- (recognised terms and conditions), paragraph 155and paragraph 137 (redundancy and incapacity benefits).
41.   Allocation of costs to particular controlled goods or services for the calculation of allowable cost increases may be necessarywhere an enterprise:(i) sells in both home and overseas markets; or(ii) makes sales at home, some of which are within and someoutside the scope of the control; or(iii) makes sales of different products or groups of products which are within the control, and has to divide costsbetween them for the purposes of the Code.Where such an enterprise:-(i) has made allocations which represent a fair divisionof costs in its circumstances, over part or all of thefield; and(ii) has done so on a consistent basis,it should continue to use this basis for all calculations relevant to the Code.    In other cases enterprises may make such allocations bydividing costs in proportion to the value of sales in each area, oron any other basis which represents good accounting practice, providedthat it adheres to the chosen basis for all calculations relevant tothe Code.Stocks42.    In calculating the cost of current sales, enterprises may need to include an element for stocks of raw materials, of components orof finished goods, drawn on for those sales.    When making suchcalculations in order to arrive at allowable cost increases, enter-prises should adhere to the practice they have followed consistentlyfor the treatment of such costs, for pricing purposes.
(i)(ii).Transfer Prices43.   Where the Price Commission are satisfied that prices, either of purchases or of sales, which an enterprise proposes to regard asa basis for the calculation of allowable cost increases or of net profit margins, differ from what they would be if the goods or services had been transferred on an arms length basis, they maysubstitute modified cost increases or profit margins which in theirjudgement fairly reflect what would be appropriate on that basis.Cost of certain small enterprises44.   Where the Commission are satisfied that:-significant cost increases have occurred or are about to occur in a sector of industry or commerce which includes a considerable number of small enterprises,especially those providing services; andthe information available to them indicates that thesecost increases are likely to be of broadly the same order for a substantial number of such enterprises, in respecteither of some or of all the goods or services whichthey supply,the Commission may calculate and publish average allowable cost increases for some or all of the goods or services supplied by thatsector.    These increases should then be taken as the allowable cost increases for the relevant goods or services.45.   Where the allowable cost increases of a particular enterprisediffer from those published by the Commission under paragraph 44, thatenterprise may apply the normal provisions of the Code relating toallowable cost increases.   It will be the responsibility of the enterprise to satisfy the Commission if required that this was -justified..46.   In calculating average allowable cost increases under paragraph44 the Commission will take account of:-
(i) all relevant information available to them on cost increases for the goods or services concerned, includinginformation supplied by any trade association or other body which they consider is representative of the enterprises concerned; and(ii) any other relevant provisions of the Code.47.   The Commission will publish information about any averageallowable cost increases which they have determined under paragraphs44 and 46, together with an indication of any price increases whichthey regard as justified under the Code on the basis of thoseaverage allowable cost increases.
CONFIDENTIALProduct Costs arid Allowable Cost Increases&quot;Single Product&quot; Enterprises48.   Where an enterprise makes a single product or a single range of products the calculations required by the Code may be carriedout by reference to the costs and prices of that enterprise as awhole.Multi-Product Enterprises:    Related Products49.   This paragraph applies to enterprises making a variety of products.&apos;  Where(i) allowable cost increases arise from one or more of a range of related products; and(ii) a price increase in respect of them is permissibleunder the Code,the enterprise need not relate the price increase for individualproducts within the range closely to the cost increase for eachproduct, provided(a) it has been established practice to treat the range of products in this way; and(b) the average increase in price, weighted by the valueof sales in a recent period, will not exceed the sumof what the Code would permit on the products affectedby the cost increases.50.   In cases not covered by paragraphs 48 and 49 the calculationsrequired by the Code should be made by reference to individual products51.   In paragraphs 48, 49 and 50 &quot;products&quot; includes services.
Anticipation of Cost Increases52.   Prices may not be increased in anticipation of cost increases,except as described in this paragraph and paragraphs 53 and 54.(i) An enterprise may determine and announce a price increaseconsistent with the Code which takes account of.knownfuture allowable cost increases, provided that the price increase is not implemented before the allowable cost increases are incurred.(ii) An enterprise may seek the agreement of the Commissionto a price increase consistent with the Code which takes account of known future cost increases, subject to thesame proviso as in (i).53.   Where:-(i) a future allowable cost increase is already known; and(ii) it is proposed to quote a price for supply on demandwhich will not be increased for at least 6 months fromthe date on which it takes effect,an enterprise may average the future allowable cost increase overthe period in (ii) provided that:-(a) the total amount raised will not be increased by theaveraging; and(b) the averaging is in accordance with a well established practice in the trade concerned,,54.   This paragraph applies to tenders to the extent that they areat fixed prices.   In framing such tenders, those concerned shouldhave regard to the Code, but where tenders are the custom of the trade
CONFIDENTIAL(i)     competitive tenders may provide for estimated futureallowable cost increases..(ii)   non-competitive tenders may provide for estimated futureallowable cost increases if the contract is to run for&apos;at least 6 months from the date on which work is to begin.Escalation and Variation of Price Clauses55*   Price increases under escalation or variation or price clausesshould be applied only to the extent that the increases are consistent with the Code.   If however the application of the Code would causeor increase a loss on a particular contract, taken as a whole, theterms of the escalation or variation of price clauses may be appliedto the extent necessary to avoid the loss, or the increase in it.In addition to new contracts, this paragraph applies to existing contracts, and to increases in prices under those contracts to theextent that they relate to cost increases after 5 November 1972.Quantity or Quality Change, and New Products56.   A change in the quantity or quality of goods, or a change ina discount, is equivalent for the purposes of the Code to a changein the price.57.   Quality change in goods or services, quantity change in salesunits, or artificial creation of new products should not be used asa means of avoiding the requirements of the Code.   Where the Commissionform the opinion that this has been done, they may seek price reduc-tions or disallow cost increases.Losses58.   This paragraph applies to enterprises which are making a loss,or are under the Code at risk of doing so:-(i)     where an enterprise is making a loss, it may increase prices to cover its costs, notwithstanding the provisions: relating to allowable cost increases,
(ii) the provisions relating to allowable cost increases(including the productivity deduction) need not beapplied to the extent that they would cause the enterpriseto operate at a loss,(iii) in all other cases, including low profit cases underparagraphs 69 and 70) the allowable cost increaseprovisions and the productivity deduction apply.Prices and Profit Margins59.   Prices should be determined so as to secure that net profit margins do not exceed the average level of the best two of the last five years of account of the enterprise concerned ending not later than JO April 1973 (the &quot;reference level&quot;).60.    &quot;Net profit margin&quot; means the margin of net profit expressed as a percentage of sales or turnover.   &quot;Net profit&quot; means the net profit, determined in accordance with generally accepted accountingprinciples consistently applied by the enterprise concerned, whicharises from trading operations within the control after taking into account all expenses of conducting and financing them, includingdepreciation and interest on borrowed money, but before deductingCorporation Tax or Income Tax.Action where Profit Margin likely to be exceeded61.    Where: -(i) the reference level has been exceeded; or(ii) in the light of interim accounts or other evidence, the reference level is likely to be exceeded, after taking account of seasonal and other distorting factors,abatements in allowable cost increases or price reductions shouldbe madoc   The abatements or reductions should be sufficient to
reliminate the actual or anticipated excess over the reference level as soon as reasonably possible, and to offset any excess which hasalready arisen in a period subsequent to 30 April 1973.   Abatementsor reductions are however not required in respect of any excessarising in the period ending with that date.
Unit for Profit Margins62.      In calculating net profit margins under paragraph 59 enter-prises may opt to use:-either    (i)    the profits of the enterprise as a wholeor (ii) the profits of separate constituent companies or sub-divisions as defined in paragraph 26 or 27provided that they then adhere to the basis chosen for all thepurposes of the Code to which net profit margins are relevant.Allocation of Profits to Controlled Prices63.      Enterprises which opt for (i) in paragraph 62 may use the resultant profit margins for the determination of all their pricesunder the Code.      Those which opt for (ii) in paragraph 62 must use the profit margin derived from the profits of the appropriateconstituent company or sub-division for the determination of pricesof those units.64.     Allocation of profits between prices within the control andthose which are not ma3&apos; be necessary for the calculation of net profit margins.     The requirements of paragraph 41 apply to suchallocations of profits as they do to allocations of costs.Profit Margins and Indirect Taxes65.       In making comparisons between net profit margins as a percent-age of sales and the reference level, due account must be taken ofthe effect on percentage margins of changes in indirect tax on goods and services sold so that the comparison is not materiallydistorted.     The comparison with earlier years should be made on abasis which excludes purchase tax from sales in the period up tothe end of March 1973 and excludes VAT from 1 April 1973 onwards.Where excise duties have been included in the sales figures, these duties should be included throughout,  adjusted as necessary to take account of the partial replacement of excise duties by VAT. ^&apos;\65A.    Where an enterprise does not already have accounts showingseparately the purchase tax element in the turnover of previous years, that element should be estimated on the basis of the best(7) - See Appendix CONFIDENTIAL
available information.     Where total purchase tax can be ascer-tained from purchase invoices this total can be deducted from taxinclusive sales.     Where such purchase invoices are not available the purchase tax element may be estimated by applying to thevalue of purchases of goods charged to different rates of purchase(7 A)tax appropriate factors derived from those rates.  &apos;   &apos;   The price commission will publish information on the application of estimating methods for this purpose.
CONFIDENTIALModified Base Period for Profit Margin Calculation66.     Where an enterprise has traded for less than 5 complete yearsof account,  or has traded at a loss in one or more of the last 5 years, the reference level for paragraph 59 may be calculated asfollows:- .(i) if there have been 4 years of trading,  the average ofthe best 2;    if 5 or 2 years,  the best year;(ii) if there have been less than 2 years of trading thelimitation on profit margins will not apply;(iii) any year in which an enterprise made a loss may betreated as equivalent to a year of no trading and sub-paragraphs (i) and (ii) may be applied accordingly.67.      For a new enterprise formed from a reconstruction or amalga-mation of existing enterprises the reference level will be calculated as defined in paragraph 59 by using the aggregate nettrading profits of the constituent enterprises expressed as a percentage of their aggregate sales.68.     Where the Commission are satisfied that the reference levelof an enterprise, calculated as in paragraph 59 or 66,  requiresmodification,  for example    because of a substantial reconstruction of the enterprise during the base period, or a substantial changein the character of its business, they may agree or stipulate a modified reference level which in their judgement gives effect tothe principles of paragraphs 59 to 66 and paragraphs 69 and 70.Relief for Low Profits69.     Where the net profit calculated as described in paragraph 59or paragraph 66 represents a return on capital of less than 5 percent,  the enterprise concerned may calculate the level of net profitneeded to produce a return of 5 per cent on capital and may treat the corresponding net profit margin as its reference level.&quot;Capital&quot; means the net assets employed excluding any part of them which is represented by borrowings, the interest on which isdeducted in arriving at net profit as defined in paragraph 60.
70. At the option of the enterprise paragraph 69 may be read asreferring to a net profit margin of 1 per cent on turnover ratherthan to a 5 per cent return on capital.Investment71.     Where the Commission are satisfied that in a particular case it is necessary in order to encourage investment to modify theapplication of the limits on allowable cost increases or on profit margins,  they may permit some departure from those limits.      in deciding whether, and to what extent, to permit such a departurethe Commission should have regard to the following criteria:-(i) whether there is satisfactory evidence that if  this is done the investment will take place;(ii) whether the application of the limits would:(a) deprive the enterprise of funds essential for thatpurpose which it could not reasonably be expected,or v;ould not be able,  to raise in some other way;&quot; &apos;- or j -.(b) reduce the prospective rate of return on the investment to a level which would deter the enter-prise from undertaking it;(iii) whether there is satisfactory evidence that the enter-prise had absorbed cost increases to an exceptionaldegree as a result of voluntary price restraint and hadconsequently had abnormally depressed profit marginsin the twelve months preceding 1 October 1972.Particular Sectors72.     The paragraphs which f follow deal with the application of thispart of the Code to certain important sectors.     Unless there isexpress provision to the contrary in those paragraphs, however,paragraphs 17 to 71 must be taken as applying to all enterprises.
Manufacturing75.   Paragraphs 17-71 above apply in their entirety.DistributionLimitation of gross percentage margins74.   In the determination of prices for sales of goods within thecontrol, gross percentage margins of wholesalers, retailers or otherenterprises engaged in distribution should not exceed the level of gross percentage margin in the last complete account year of the enterprise concerned ending before 1 May 1973 less, in either case,an appropriate reduction for the abolition of SET.74-A. For all the purposes of the Code &quot;gross percentage margin&quot; means the aggregate difference between the cost to the distributor of thegoods he sells in a period and the value of his sales in that period,expressed as a percentage of the sales value.   The difference shouldbe calculated according to the normal accounting practice consistentlyapplied by the enterprise.   In arriving at sales and costs of salesindirect taxes should be treated on the same basis as for calculatingnet profit margins in paragraph 65.75*   The provisions   of the Code relating to allowable cost increasesdo not apply to enterprises engaged in distribution.Distributors&apos; Stocks76.   In   most cases prices determined by distributive enterpriseswill have to take account of the cost of goods drawn from stock forsale.   Such enterprises should adhere to the practice they have followed consistently for pricing purposes in arriving at such costs,and at the relevant gross percentage margins.Distributors making a Loss77.   Where an enterprise engaged in distribution is making a loss, itmay increase prices to cover its costs, notwithstanding the limitation
CONFIDENTIALon gross percentage margins.78.   Where the costs of any goods to wholesalers or retailers riseparticularly sharply (that is to say, substantially out of line withthe general movement in the price level), the Commission may:-(i) consult any body or person whom they regard asrepresentative of enterprises affected by the rise in costs and take into account information supplied bythem 5 and(ii) (having regard to the situation of the product group asa whole and to the volume of trade), consider whetherthe maintenance of existing gross percentage marginswould disproportionately increase the profit margin on those goods; and whether the trade practice affecting themargins on the products in question therefore requiresmodification; and(iii) issue guidance on the form which they consider such modification should take.79.   Where a distributors net profit margin has exceeded the reference level, or where in the light of interim accounts or otherevidence it is likely, after taking account of seasonal or otherdistorting factors, to be exceeded, price reductions should be madecorresponding to any actual or expected excess in respect of aperiod after 30 April 1973.Gross Percentage Margins and Indirect Tax80.   For the purposes of paragraph 74 to 79 the gross percentage marginshould be calculated on the same basis as for net profit margins inparagraph 65.
Agriculture81.     Part I does not apply to agricultural enterprises engaged inthe production and sale of unprocessed agricultural produce.   where such enterprises are engaged in manufacturing or processinghowever, their prices are controlled by reference to allowablecosts and net profit margins.     Where they are engaged in distri-bution,  their prices are controlled by reference to gross percentage margins and net profit margins.Nationalised Industries82.     Paragraphs 83 and 84 apply to the following nationalised industries:-National Coal board electricity CouncilArea Electricity BoardsCentral Electricity Generating board north of Scotland Hydro-Electric board south of Scotland Electricity board british Gas corporation british Steel corporation post office British Airways board british Airports authority british Railways board british Transport Docks board british Waterways Board83.     Part I of the Code applies to the nationalised industrieslisted in paragraph 82, according to the nature of the businessof the industry, as it applies to private sector undertakings,except that:-(i)      these nationalised industries, when in deficit, may not increase prices by more than allowable cost increases in order to reduce that deficit.    Paragraph 58(i) willnot therefore apply, but the other provisions relatingto private sector enterprises making a loss will apply,
including in particular paragraph 58(ii) and the exemption from the productivity deduction:    and(ii)    paragraph 71 will not apply.84.     The application of the Code is subject to paragraph 85 in thecase of the National Coal Board and to paragraphs 85 and 86 in thecase of the British Steel Corporation.    In the case of the PostOffice and those industries concerned with air and sea transport,it is subject to the exclusion from control under paragraph 20(vi)of charges for international traffic.     The prices of subsidiary companies of nationalised industries, including subsidiaries ofthe National Bus Company, National Freight Corporation and theScottish Transport Group, are governed by paragraph 88(ii).   Theprices charged for electricity by Area Electricity Boards and theScottish Boards will be subject to the provisions of the Codeapplying to manufacturers.Coal and Steel85.     Prices charged by producers for coal, coal-based solid fuels,and most iron and steel products are outside the scope of thecontrol by virtue of paragraph 20(ii).     They are subject to inter-national obligations through United Kingdom membership of theEuropean Coal and Steel Community.prices of non-ECSC ironand steel products, are controlled like those of other manufactured products.     Prices of coal merchants and iron and steel merchantsin the United Kingdom will be subject to the control on gross percentage margins and net profit margins applied to wholesalingand retailing.86.     Enterprises which produce both ECSC and non-ECSC iron andsteel products will be subject to price control on the latter only.Where a non-ECSC product is made from an ECSC product, an increasein the price paid for the ECSC product will constitute an allowable cost increase.       Where the non-ECSC product is made from an enter-prised own ECSC product, the price at which the enterprise offers the ECSC product for sale (or, if it does not offer it for sale,the prevailing market price in a comparable transaction) should be(10) - See Appendix
(11) - See Appendixused in calculating any allowable cost increase,     For the purposeof calculating the limit on profit margins, only the profits fromconverting ECSC products into the final non-ECSC products will be relevant.Other Public Sector Trading Enterprises87.      The Commission will apply to proposals for price increases which are referred to them by Government Departments engaged insubstantial trading operations the same principles as to proposals by the nationalised industries.88.     The Code applies to the prices of the following enterprises,according to the nature of the business of the undertaking, as it applies to the prices of private sector enterprises:-(i) trading services of local authorities^^, localauthority joint boards, public utility undertakings and other similar public sector undertakings (not beingnationalised industries);    and(ii) companies registered under the Companies Acts which are wholly or partly owned by Her Majesty&apos;s Government, orby a nationalised industry.Water Undertakings89.     Water undertakings, whether public or private,  are subject to statutory limitations on deficits, on surpluses or profits, onprofit distributions and on borrowing.      They are also required by statute to provide an adequate supply of water.    Their water rates are already controlled to a large extent through these limitations.They will be required to comply with the principles of the Code andin particular with the paragraphs relating to allowable cost increases, but not so as to over-ride their statutory obligations.Services90.     In general, paragraphs 17 to 71 of the Code apply to theprices of service enterprises as they apply to those of manufacturers,
so that the system of allowable cost increases and the limitation on net profit margins per unit of sales or turnover apply to them.There will be an offset to allowable cost increases as a result ofthe abolition of Selective Employment Tax for service enterpriseswhere this has hitherto been paid without refund.    Paragraphs /,4 to47 permit the Price Commission to calculate average allowable cost increases for certain small service enterprises where the circum-stances are appropriate.     Paragraph 70 would permit service enter-prises with low profits to calculate their reference level for thelimit on net profit margins by reference to either turnover orcapital employed.     The following paragraphs deal with theapplication of the Code to some particular service sectors, and explain any modifications of the&quot;general principles which apply tothem.Banking91t     /&quot;Drafting not yet completed/
Construction92.     In determining prices construction enterprises should haveregard to the Code as it applies to manufacturing enterprises,in particular, paragraph 54 which applies to tenders for construction work at fixed prices and paragraph 55 which applies to variation of price clauses in construction contracts.Transport93.     The Code applies to transport undertakings as it does toother service enterprises.      Charges for international freight and passenger traffic are outside the control under paragraph 20(vi).Charges of nationalised transport undertakings, passenger transport authorities, local authority transport undertakings and transport companies owned by nationalised industries are governed byparagraphs 82 to 84 and 88.94.     Charges of private road haulage undertakings are subject tothe provisions relating to allowable costs and to the   limitations onnet profit margins.Vehicle Sales and Services95.     Charges for repair, maintenance and servicing of vehicles are subject to the provisions relating to allowable costs and to thelimitation on net profit margins.96.     The prices of vehicles sold by distributors, whether new orsecond-hand, are subject to the limitations on gross percentagemargins and on net profit margins.97.     Paragraph 27 applies to enterprises which both sell and maintain vehicles.Hotels and Catering Enterprises98.     What is said in paragraph 90 applies to these enterprisesalso, in respect both of charges for food and drink for accommodation.
Professional Services99.     Fees and charges for professional services by firms or by individuals who are self-employed are governed as prices by Part I.In general, what is said in paragraph 90 applies to them.    The pay of professional staff who are employees is however governed by part II, as is the remuneration from public funds of doctors and dentists.100.   Where scales or rates of charges of general application,whether calculated at an hourly rate or ad valorem, are in use ina profession under instructions or advice  issued by a professionalorganisation, those scales or rates must be treated as maxima andmay not be increased without the agreement of the Commission.Where rates above scale have normally been agreed and have becomenormal charges,  such rates need not be reduced but the margin bywhich such rates exceed the scale may not be increased.    TheCommission will apply the provisions relating to allowable cost increases to increases in scales or rates and those provisions willalso apply to increases in fees calculated on a time basis.101.   Where there are no scales or rates of general application, therates or scales charged for a professional service may not beincreased except to reflect increases in allowable costs.    increases in labour costs under paragraph 35(ii)(a) may not include any element in respect of proprietors&apos; or partners&apos;, as distinct fromemployees&apos;, time.102.    The limitation on net profit margins will apply to profits of firms or individuals providing professional services irrespective of the method by which fees are determined.     Where the number ofpartners in a professional practice has changed the reference levelmay be calculated by reference to the number of partners.    in applying the allowable cost regime to scales or rates of charges the Commission will have regard, under the provisions of paragraph6l,  to profit margins in the profession generally.
Membership Organisations103.    Subscriptions charged by organisations which:-(i) exist for charitable, representational orrecreational purposes;    and(ii) are non-profit making;    and(iii) do not carry on a trade or business as their mainactivity,will not be controlled.104.    Prices charged in any trading activity carried on by an organisation which meets the requirements of paragraph 103 aregoverned by the Code, unless the customers of the tradingactivity are confined to members of the organisation.
CONFIDENTIALPART II:    pay general Principles105. The general principles relating to pay are:-(i) to limit the rate of increase in pay in money terms toa level more in line with the growth of national output,so as progressively to reduce the rate of price inflation and improve the prospects of sustained faster growth in real earnings;(ii) to apply the limit fairly, irrespective of the form ofany increase or the method of determining it;(iii) to facilitate an improvement in the relative positionof the low paid;(iv) to leave to those who normally determine pay decisions on the amount, form and distribution of increases withinthe limit.Field of Application106, Part II of the Code applies to:-(i)    all pay including wages and salaries at whatever level,allowances, payments by results, payments in kind, fringebenefits and lump sums;(ii)    all methods of determining pay v/hether at national, local,plant or any other level; and whether determined bycollective bargaining, by arbitration, by statutory wagefixing bodies, on an individual basis, or by other means;and(iii)    all types of employment (except self employment covered in Part I); and to both full-time and part-time employees in whatever size of undertaking.
All those concerned with the determination of pay should haveregard to the Code.107.   Throughout ^/part II of  the Code &quot;pay&quot; means remuneration(except self-employment incomes covered in Parti) and includesother terms and conditions of employment.108.   References throughout the Code to &quot;settlements&quot; includereferences to the determination of pay by any method.109.   Where the Code refers to a group, the group will normally bethe same as that used for the purpose of determining &quot;pay in thepreceding 12 months.    It will, however, remain open to those concerned.to vary the composition of their groups.   Where pay is fixed on an individual basis, the Code applies to the individualas to the group.Intervals between Increases110o   No group may receive an increase in pay under a settlementmade after 6 November 1972 less than twelve months after the grouplast received a principal increase.111. . Paragraph 110 does not apply where:-(i)     an earlier date for such an increase was specified(other than by reference to changes in indices or ratesof pay for other groups) in a previous settlement made before 6 November 1972;   or(ii)     the last increase was deferred as a result of the stand-still under the White Paper (Cmnd 5125), in which casethe 12 months count from the date from which the lastincrease would have operated but for the standstill.112.   Pay increases which consist solely of one or more improvementsof the kind described in paragraphs 123, 125, or 127, are notprincipal increases for the purpose of paragraph 82 and may be given within 12 months of any other increase.
The Pay Limit113.   The pay limit for a group represents the maximum amount bywhich the average pay per head of the group may be increased in a12 month period.   This amount is the sum of(i)   k per cent of the average pay bill per head of thegroup for the preceding 12 month period;   and(ii)    1 per week per head.A precise method of calculation is set out in the Appendix.   If insuf-ficient information is available for this, the best availablealternative method should be used (examples are given in the Appendix).Those concerned will be responsible for satisfying the Pay Board, if required, that the method used is the best available.11h.    Subject to the individual limit in paragraph 121, it will befor negotiators and others concerned with pay determination to decide on the amount and distribution of increases within the pay limit, andon the division between increases in wages or salaries and improve-ments in other conditions of service.   They should, however, have full regard to the objective of improving the relative position of thelow-paid *115.   The pay limit applies to the 12 months following the firstincrease after 6 November 1972 which counts against the pay limit.But where a group in accordance with paragraph 111 (ii) wishes toreturn to its normal operative date, so that its settlement runs forless than   12 months, the limit will apply to the period of thesettlement at the weekly or monthly rate that would have applied hadthe settlement been for 12 months.1160   In calculating the average pay bill per head(i)   the number in the group should be taken as the average over the preceding 12 months;
(ii)   the pay hill should include the cost of all forms of pay increases which count against the pay limit and should headjusted to offset the effect of absences from work due toabsenteeism, sickness, short-time working or t o stoppagesfrom any other cause.(iii)   Part-time workers should be counted according to theproportion which their hours bear to the standard hoursof the group,    (They should be counted on the same basis in calculating the sum of  1 per week per head of the group.)117*   Employers&apos; contributions in respect of their employees for national insurance, selective employment tax, pension schemes andredundancy payment schemes and (subject to paragraphs 119 and 120)the cost of overtime hours actually worked should be excluded fromthe pay bill and will not count against the pay limit.118.   Y/ith the exceptions specified in subsequent paragraphs of the code, improvements in terms and conditions of employment other thanwages and salaries should be costed and taken into account in deter-mining whether the total cost of a settlement is within the pay limit.
CONFIDENTIALOvertime, Shift, Rest Day and Weekend Working119.    All payments for work done in normal working hours withinthe meaning of Schedule 2 to the Contracts of Employment Act 1972 -which broadly includes any hours paid at overtime rates which the employee is required to work under the terms of his contract -should be included in the pay bill.     The effect on such payments of any improvement in pay will count against the pay limit.    Forexample, improvements in shift pay, whether related to improvementin basic rates or not, will count against the pay limit;    as willimprovements in night duty allowance where the night duty is apart of normal working hours.120.    If there is any widening of the percentage differentialbetween the rate of pay for work done outside normal working hours (for example overtime,  shift, rest day or weekend working)and the effective rate of pay for standard hours (for exampleif the overtime multiplier is increased from time and a third totime and a half), the additional cost will count against the pay limit.      In calculating the cost it should be assumed that theamount of such working in the 12 months from the operative date ofthe settlement will be at least as much as in the preceding 12months.Individual pay limit121.    Increases subject to the pay limit must not exceed  250 ayear for any individual.      If the individual works part time thislimit must be reduced according to the proportion his hours bearto the standard hours of the group.      Increases which are not subject to the pay limit  (for example increases in this categoryarising from overtime or certain personal increments) do not count against the  250 limit.Other improvements in pay and conditionsEqual Pay122.   Orderly progress towards achievement of the requirements ofthe Equal Pay Act 1970 may be made outside the pay limit on thebasis set out below.(11)    See Appendix
gm     ki r&quot; i     r- *, I w I &amp; I123.    Subject to paragraph 12/, an increase for this purpose is outside the pay limit to the extent that, by the end of 1973, itreduces by up to one third any differential between men&apos;s andwomen&apos;s rates which existed at 31 December 1972 and which isrequired by the Equal Pay Act to be eliminated by 29 December 1975.Any increase in excess of this counts against the pay limit.124.    No increase outside the pay limit is allowable under paragraph123 if any other increase affecting the group concerned has theeffect of widening the percentage differential between mens&apos; andwomens&apos;  rates in question.Hours125.    Reductions in standard working hours may be made outside the pay limit if they reduce standard working hours to not less than40 hours a week, net of meal breaks.126.    Reductions    in standard working hours other than as providedfor in paragraph 125 count against the pay limit.     The true cost should be set against the pay limit but the cost should not betreated as less than proportional to the reduction (so that forexample a reduction of one hour in 40 should be treated as equiva-lent to not less than a 2\ per cent increase in pay), except wherethe Pay Board is satisfied in the light of the evidence that the true cost is less.Holidays127.    Improvements in holidays do not count against the pay limitunless they increase the total holidays for any group to more thanthe equivalent of 3 weeks a year excluding:-(i) up to six occasional or public holidays(ii) rest days taken in lieu of weekends or overtime;    and(iii) rest days granted before 6 November 1972 in lieu of a shorter working week.128. Improvements in holidays other than as provided for in paragraph127 count against the pay limit on the basis of their true cost.
Personal Increments129.   Where personal increments(i)    are part of a pre-determined range or scale; and(ii) conform to defined principles and practice which before November 1972 governed the exercise of any managementdiscretion in individual casesthen, to the extent that they do not exceed those paid to individuals in similar circumstances in previous years and subject to paragraph 130, any net addition to the annual pay bill per head forthe group concerned will not count against the pay limit and theincrements do not count against the limit of  250 a year for theindividual.130.   The following count against the pay limit and against theindividual limit of  250:-(i)     improvements in the ranges or scales in incrementalsystems covered by paragraph 102;(ii)     any net addition to the annual pay bill of a groupresulting from the payment of types of personal incrementother than those in paragraph 102; and(iii)     any element in personal increments which relates tofactors not personal to the individual concerned, suchas cost of living increases or company profits (otherthan under a profit sharing scheme as it existed before November 1972).Promotion and Regrading131.   Increases commensurate with greater responsibility may begiven outside the pay limit to individuals or groups of individuals who are promoted or the level of whose work is reassessed byapplication of established procedures and criteria.   Where this test
CONFIDENTIALis not satisfied any increase in pay counts against the pay limit.Artificial regrading and changes of job specification should not beused as a means of avoiding the provisions of the Code.New Employees and New Work132.   New recruits to existing jobs should not be paid more thanthose they replace or more than the rate paid currently by the employer concerned for the same job.133.   The rate for new work should not be more than the current ratepaid for the same or most nearly similar work by the same or other employers.   Where rates vary in different localities, the rate paidshould not be more than the rate in the same locality.Recognised Terms and Conditions13h.   The cost of increases to meet the purposes of Section 8 of the(12)Terms and Conditions of Employment Act 1959,        the Road HaulageWages Act, 1938 and similar legislation, and the Pair Wages resolution of 1946 will not count against the pay limit.Pensions135.   New or improved benefits under occupational pension or deathbenefit schemes which are tax approved, or under comparable schemesnot requiring tax approval, and any reimbursement of a corresponding increase in employee contributions may, unless paragraph     applies,be given outside the pay limit.136.   Where a change in a pension scheme has the effect of increasingthe pay, net of any pension contribution of a substantial proportionof the group of employees covered by the scheme, that increase counts(1 ^)against the pay limitN ^unless:-(12)(13)See AppendixSee Appendix
(i)   a revaluation of the scheme, made in accordance withgenerally accepted principles for such revaluations,has shown a surplus in respect of those receiving theincrease, the value of which equals or exceeds theincrease;   or(ii)   there has been a corresponding reduction in   benefits to those receiving the increase;   or(iii)   the change had been proposed before 6 November 1972,Redundancy Payments137.   New or improved benefits under schemes for payments to workers who leave an employer&apos;s service because of redundancy (as defined forthe purposes of the Redundancy Payments Act, 1965) are outside the pay limit, as are benefits which become payable after 6 months of incapacity.Profit-sharing Schemes138.   Payments under the terms of profit-sharing schemes as they stood before 6 November 1972 will not count against the pay limit.Any other payments or benefits under such schemes must be countedagainst the pay limit.
CONFIDENTIALShare Option and Share Incentive Schemes139. If the rate at which shares or options had been acquired by-individual participants under a scheme operating before 6 November1972 was fixed, without managerial discretion, by a predeterminedformula related directly to company performance or other quantifiedcriteria   the operation of that scheme on the terms ruling before that date is outside the pay limit.    In addition the acquisition of shares through any arrangements by which employers facilitate thepurchase of shares by employees is outside the pay limit provided(i) there are no special restrictions attached to the shares;(ii) the shares are purchased at a price equal to their market value; and(iii) there are no related loans or deferred payment arrangements.140. No options may be granted under other share option schemes orsh?res issued under other share incentive schemes.   The terms ofschemes under which shares already issued are still subject to restrictions, or options already granted remain unexercised, may notbe improved.Other Benefits141. The cost of any new benefits and of any improvement or extensionof existing benefits or other terms and conditions of service willcount against the pay limit unless specifically exempted in the Code.These benefits include:-Benefits in cash or kind, including the provision of cars partlyor wholly for private use, living accommodation at less thaneconomic cost, etc.Loans at below market rate, eg for house purchase.1 &apos;/\\ * I iLunch or other meal vouchersSeasonal and holiday bonuses
CONFIDENTIALResponsibility allowancesLondon allowance or other geographical allowanceOvertime and shift premiums (see paragraphs 119-120)Stand-by paymentsLay off and sick pay14-2. Reimbursement of expenses incurred in the course of employment(including removal expenses) does not count against the pay limit.When expenses are reimbursed by fixed allowances, these may beincreased outside the pay limit, provided that the increase can be fully justified on the ground of increases in the relevant costs.Particular Methods and Systems of PaymentNational, Local and Plant Increases14-3. Where settlements or pay determinations for a particular group are concluded at more than one level (for example, a settlement atnational or industry level is supplemented by settlements at local or plant level) the total increase for the group for the twelvemonths beginning with the first increase which counts against the pay limit should be kept within that limit.   Paragraph 110 appliesseparately to each level of settlement.144. When local or plant negotiations take place before nationalnegotiations the recommended method of achieving the purpose ofparagraph 143 is by including in the local or plant settlement anoffsetting provision precluding employers from making subsequentpayments as a result of a national agreement which would result in atotal increase in the pay of the group concerned in excess of the pay limit.   Those undertaking national negotiations should have regardto the requirement that any increase settled nationally, if notoffset as above, should be taken into account in any subsequent local or plant negotiation, so as to ensure that the total pay increase ofany group concerned does not exceed the pay limit for that group.
Payment by Results145.   Increases in pay under a scheme of payment by results, includingpiecework and commission payments, or under an arrangement linked tosuch a scheme will count against the pay limit except where they arise under the terms of the scheme from direct and measurablecontributions by the employees to increased output.   This applies to increased payments arising from changes in base rate, conversion rateor other calculator, piecework prices or times, the fixed element orfrom any other change in the terms,146. For those covered by schemes of payment by results who do not benefit from a general pay increase the twelve month period referredto in paragraph 11$ will be the twelve months following the end ofthe standstill.14y. For those covered by schemes of payments by results who alsobenefit from a general increase which counts against the pay limit,account must be taken in calculating the amount available for thegeneral increase, of any increase under the scheme of which countsagainst the pay limit.   For this purpose it must be assumed that thepercentage of such increases in pay arising under the scheme duringthe twelve months following the general increase will be at least as great as in the preceding twelve months.Productivity and Restructuring Schemes148. Except as in paragraph 149, increases in pay under productivityor restructuring schemes introduced after 6 November 1972 count against the pay limit.149. Where:(i)       there was on 6 November 1972 an agreement to implement a programme of productivity schemes, or a restructuring,for specified groups of employees in which the amount of pay or the precise method by which it was to be calculated was clearly specified, leaving only the
practical details of application of the scheme to particular groups to be settled;and(ii) the employer or group of employers covered by the agree-ment had on 6 November already implemented the programme in respect of some of the employees concerned,-implementation of the programme in respect of the specified groupsmay proceed.   Resultant increases in pay will not count against the pay limit.
CONFIDENTIALSettlements reached before the Standstill150. Settlements reached, but not implemented, on or before November 1972 which provide for specified increases on specifieddates (and not by reference to changes in indices or other rates of pay) may be implemented in full and, subject to the requirements ofthe standstill, from their due date or dates.   The requirements ofthe standstill are that no such increase may be implemented with effect from a date earlier than 28 February 1973; that thereaftersuch increases may be implemented 90 days after their due date provided this is not less than twelve months after the previous settlement;and that no such increase need be deferred beyond the end of the paystandstill.151* Where increases provided under such settlements are principalincreases or have due dates after the end of the pay standstillthey will count against the pay limit.   In such cases the pay limitwill apply to the 12 months following that increase.   Where thetotal cost of the settlement within that 12 months equals or exceeds the pay limit it may not be added to, unless in ways which do not count against the pay limit.New long-term agreements152. Settlements may be made providing for staged increases at notless than twelve month intervals which are consistent with the Codebut implementation of the later stages will be subject to theprovisions of the Code at the time.
PAHS? Ill - GENERAL153.     Where the Code cannot be directly applied to particular cases or sectors without modification, the Price Commission andthe Pay Board will, in exercising their powers, apply the Code withsuch adaptations or modifications as appear to them to be necessaryto give effect to its principles and objectives.
CONFIDENTIALSECTION 3DIVIDENDSA^Tfi nj stration and General Principles134.   Dividend control will continue to be administered by theTreasury.   The principles of this control set out in this sectionare not, therefore, included in the Code.   Where appropriate, effect will be given to them in the Order that will be laid by the treasury under Section 10 of the Counter-Inflation Act 1973 as soon as part ii of the Act comes into force.155.   It is not envisaged that the Agencies will play a part in theadministration of dividend restraint during Stage 2, but the Act makesthis possible if it should be thought appropriate at a later stage and permits questions relating to dividends to be deferred to theappropriate Agency.136.   The control of dividends will, as in the standstill, operate on declarations; however the Act also gives power to control payments of dividends should this be necessary.   Except as indicated in thefollowing paragraph, companies incorporated in the United kingdom will not be permitted, without the consent of the Treasury, to declare dividends for any company account year which exceed by morethan 5% the amount of ordinary dividends declared by the company forthe preceding company account year.   Other analogous distributionsout of the assets of the company will also be prohibited, except with the consent of the Treasury.   Fixed rate dividends, however,since they cannot be increased, will not be subject to control.Field of Application157*   Dividend control will apply to all companies incorporated inthe United Kingdom except:-(a)   Investment trusts as defined in Section 359 of theIncome and Corporation Taxes Act 1970;
(b) close companies to the extent that they increasedistributions in order to comply with the special taxrules concerning such companies;(c) companies entirely in the beneficial ownership of another company or companies (except those in the ownership of an investment trust) where ordinarydividend payments are exclusively inter-companytransactions.158.   Effect will be given to the control for quoted companiesby making an order applying the relevant provisions of the Act tosuch companies, except for those in the categories mentioned above.The order will specify in detail the coverage of the control, thebasis of comparison for purposes of calculation and other relevant factors.159.   Companies other than quoted companies will not be covered bythe order.   They will nevertheless be subject to the same limitations on dividend declarations as quoted companies and will be expected tocomply with them.   If necessary, the restrictions will be appliedto individual unquoted companies by means of a notice given underthe Act.160.   The exemption for close companies will apply only to the extent that an increased distribution is necessary to avoid a shortfallassessment or an apportionment of their profits and companies will doubtless wish to consult their tax advisors about their position.Where a higher distribution is necessary it can be made at any time within a period from the end of the relevant accounting year whichthe Inland Revenue consider to be reasonable.The Dividend Limit161.   In computing what dividends may be declared for a company&apos;s account year, the starting point will be the total amount of ordinarydividends declared for the last account year in respect of which a profit and loss account of the company laid before it in generalmeeting was compiled.   The money amount of these dividends may then
. be increased by 5 per cent to give the total amount of the ordinarydividends which may be declared for the succeeding company accountyear.162.   In the case of dividends to be paid after 5 April 1973, thebasis of comparison will need to take account of the changes incorporation tax which will come into operation on that date.   the comparison will be between:-(a) gross dividends paid before 6 April 1973; and(b) franked payments (that is the aggregate of dividends andsuch proportion thereof as corresponds to the rate of advance corporation tax in force for the financial year in which the dividend is paid) made after 5 April 1973*The 5 per cent increase applies to the amount of the gross dividenddeclared for the company&apos;s preceding account year.163.   Pro rata adjustments should also be made (i) to take accountof changes of one month or more in the length of a company&apos;s account-ing period; and (ii) where there has been a reduction in the company&apos;s share capital, or where a company&apos;s share capital has increased since the declaration of the final dividend (or its equivalent) forthe preceding account year and the increase reflects the value ofnew cash subscribed or other real consideration.   Normal capitalisa-tion issues may be made, but an increase in capital which is theresult of a capitalisation issue will not rank for increased dividend.Application to Takeovers, New Companies, etc164.   The Act empowers the Treasury or one of the Agencies to issueconsents to allow companies to declare dividends which are greaterthan the normally permitted level.   Such consents will only be granted in exceptional circumstances, and any application for such treatmentmust be made in writing well before any relevant board meeting.
165.   It is not possible to specify in advance precise rulesapplicable to all cases.   The following however indicates the way in which the control will operate in particular circumstancesTakeover DefenceWhere the Treasury are satisfied that an actual takeoverbid situation exists (ie where it is the intention to acquiremore than 50% of the voting shares of the company subject tothe bid), companies wishing to defend themselves from thebidder by increasing their dividends will normally be allowedto do so.New CompaniesNew companies formed by the reconstruction or amalgamation of existing companies will normally be allowed to declaredividends not exceeding the aggregate of the dividends declaredin the preceding account years by the parties to the merger,plus 5%; in such circumstances the new company will need to consult the Treasury about their dividend position.   Othercompletely new companies will not be subject to control inrespect of dividends declared for their first two account years.Newly Quoted CompaniesFormer private or unquoted public companies will not be subjectto dividend control in respect of the first account year duringwhich they became a quoted company or the succeeding accountyear.RecoveriesCompanies which have recovered from an adverse trading position will normally be permitted to increase their dividends to thelevel of an earlier more typical year.   They will not, however,be allowed the 5 per cent increase on top of this concession.
Pre-Standstill CommitmentsSome companies may have issued formal document to investors(for examples, prospectuses or rights issue offer documents)before the Prime Minister&apos;s announcement of dividend restraint on 6 November 1972 in which they made statements of intentabout future dividend declarations.   Provided the treasury are satisfied that a real commitment exists and that it was relevant to the actions of the people to whom the prospectuseswere addressed, it is the intention to allow such commitments to be honoured.
SECTION 4Price and Pay Determination Outside the Code166.   This Section described how Stage Two will apply to prices,charges and pay in certain fields which are not automatically withinthe scope of the Price Commission or Pay Board under the Counter-Inflation Act 1973.Pay of Crown Servants and Government prices and charges167.   The Government will apply the Code to pay settlements withwhich it is concerned, and will arrange notification of settlementsto which it is a party to the Pay Board.   The draft Code describesin paragraph 87 the principles which the Price Commission will berequired to apply to proposals for price increases referred to themby Government Departments engaged in substantial trading operations.In relation to other prices and charges for which it has responsibility,the Government intend to follow the principles of the Code.    In many important cases however the Government is already holding chargesbelow the levels which the Code would permit.Statutory Determination of Pay or Prices168.   Statutory bodies which determine pay or prices will be requiredto have regard to the Code.   The Government propose to use the powers given by the Counter-Inflation Act to modify their Statutory obliga-tions accordingly.   The necessary orders will be made at the beginningof Stage Two.169.   In the case of bus fares and domestic air fares the right ofappeal to the Secretary of State against a decision of the traffic commissioners and the Civil Aviation Authority respectively willremain, but in determining any appeals the Secretary of State willhave regard to the Code and may consult the Commission.   Rights ofappeal to the National Ports Council against ship, passenger and goods dues will also be retained.   In determining appeals it isintended that the National Ports Council should have regard to the code.
CONFIDENTIALControl of Prices and Charges by Ministers170.   The draft Code provides in paragraph 20 (vii), (viii) and (ix)that control through the Code will not apply to three categories ofprices and charges, which are instead to be regulated by Ministers.171.   Prices of drugs (&quot;ethical medicines&quot;) purchased wholly or mainly for use in the National Health Service have for a number ofyears been regulated by agreement between the Secretary of State for social Services and his predecessors and the manufacturers.   Thissystem is effective and it is proposed that the prices of thesemedicines should continue to be regulated through this agreement,rather than through the Code, so long as it remains in force.172.   The second special category is prices in certain contracts with the Secretary of State for Defence for warlike stores or services.The pricing of non-competitive Government contracts in this field isregulated under arrangements agreed between Her Majesty1s Governmentand the CBI in 1968.   These arrangements provide for equality ofinformation for purchasing Departments in the pricing process, andfor the post-costing of fixed price contracts.   There are alsoprovisions governing the rate of profit.   In the circumstances ofthese contracts the Government consider that the best course is tocontinue to. regulate these prices under the agreed arrangements.173.   The third category is insurance premiums.   They will be controlled by the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry under the Counter-Inflation Act.   The Secretary of State already has statutory respon-sibilities for the protection of insured persons through his over-sight of the solvency of insurance companies and, as was explained to Parliament, it would not be satisfactory to separate responsibilityfor controlling the level of premiums from responsibility for thecompanies&apos; solvency.Interest business of banks17U.   /&quot;Drafting not completed^/
Business and Agricultural Rents175.   The standstill on both business and agricultural rents willcontinue in Stage Two, and the necessary Orders vill be made forthis purpose.   There will be minor changes in the arrangements which applied during the Standstill to business rents to removecertain unintended effects and anomalies.   The control will not however be extended to new lettings.   Studies relating to largerterm policy for business rents have been put in hand and the Government&apos;conclusions will be made known as soon as possible.
SECTION 5MACHINERY AND PROCEDURENotification, reporting and record keeping:    prices176*   There will be three different procedures for ensuring thatthe price policy is effectively monitored and implemented: pre-notification of proposed price increases to the Price Commission,regular reporting to the Commission and record keeping subject tospot checks by the Commission.    The requirements for pre-notification,reporting and record keeping will be embodied in orders made underthe Counter-Inflation Act.   The Commission will not discloseinformation which is properly confidential except as printed inparagraph 4(2) of Schedule 4 on the Counter-Inflation Act.177.   The requirements for enterprises in different sectors will be defined mainly in terms of the value of sales in the domestic marketduring their last financial year ending not later than 31 December1972.   For this purpose the sales of an enterprise which is part ofa larger group will be aggregated in the sales of the group as awhole notwithstanding the provisions in paragraph 181.   Mixedenterprises are covered in paragraph 185 below.    The definitionsfor different sectors are given in the table below.Category I       Category II       Category 111Priornotificationand reporting  millionReporting  millionRecord-keeping  millionManufacturing, mining,public utilities,transport, postal services and tele-communications over 50 5-50 1-5wholesalers, retailers,and other DistributivetradesServicesConstructionProfessionsover 20National scalesor ratesover 105-20over 10over 0.50.25-100.25-51-100.1-0.5
1?cJ.    Certain enterprises whose sales in the domestic market arebelow the figures in the first column oi&apos; the table above, but whichhave a relatively large share, or are of special importance, in themarket for particular goods will be required to pre-notify.    Theseenterprises have already&apos; been told that they will be   named in thefirst notification order.   Any further changes in the notificationrequirements will also be embodied in orders.Ire-Notification179*   Prenotifying enterprises will be required to provide fullsupporting data when they apply to the Price Commission for a price increase.    If no reply is received within 28 days of the receipt ofthe application, the Price Commission will be deemed to have consented to the increase.    If the Price Commission cannot complete itsexamination within 28 days it may, before the expiry of that period,inform the applicant that the application is still under consideration.The Commission must give a decision within a further 14 days (that is,a maximum of 42 days from the date of the receipt of the application)if it decides to modify or reject the proposed increase and thereforewishes to prevent it being implemented.    This is because it must give 14 days notice of this intention to the applicant who may make further representations to the Commission within that period.    If aprice increase is approved, it can normally be implemented at once.180.   The Price Commission will deal with all notifications as speedily as possible.    Where it is important because of the natureof a product (eg certain processed foods or other products heavily dependent on raw materials which fluctuate in price) that a decision is given in less than 28 days, every effort will be made to do so.It will be open to the Price Commission to make special arrangementsfor such products.181.   Category I enterprises will not be required to pre-notify price increases on every product or service.   Provided that the price increases are consistent with the Code, pre-notification is notrequired where either of the following conditions is met:
a.    Where the product or service is part of a range on whichthe total sales of the enterprise do not exceed  5m for manufacturing, mining, public utilities, transport; and 2m for service enterprises.   For this purpose, the followingdefinitions should be used:(i) the &quot;range&quot; should be the minimum list heading of the Standard Industrial Classification withinwhich the product or service falls.(ii) The &quot;enterprise&quot; should be as defined inparagraph 177*(iii) The &quot;sales&quot; should be the total receivable income from sales in the domestic market during the lastaccounting year ending before 31 December 1972.b.   Where an enterprise applies for an receives consent fromthe Price Commission for a price increase on a productand notifies the Price Commission in the application thatit intends to increase the price of other products of itsown manufacture incorporating that material.   In this event it need not pre-notify, unless specifically requested bythe Price Commission to do so, price increases on those other products which are wholly consequential on the approvedincrease in the price of the material.182.   Other enterprises required to pre-notify under the provisionsof Paragraph 178 will pre-notify all price increases on the goodsor services specified in the Order.183.   Applications for the Commission&apos;s approval by   pre-notifyingenterprises will be required to include information about the enterprise&apos;s profit reference level and current profit margin and about the increases in total and allowable unit costs on which theproposed price increase is based.
184-.   All enterprises, whether or not otherwise required topre-notify, must pre-notify any proposal to increase prices winchwould not be consistent with the Code except under the provisions ofparagraph 71.185.   Iiixed enterprises (that is, those engaged in wholesale, retailor service operations as well as manufacturing) will be required topre-notify increases in the price of their manufactured productswhere the sales of these products in the domestic market (includingsales through their own wholesale or retail outlets) exceed  50million.   Iiixed enterprises are also required to pre-notify increased charges for service activities where the turnover exceeds  20 million.Paragraph 184 will apply to these enterprises as to other pre-notifyers.186.   Where nationalised industries have statutory Consumer Councils,they will notify those Councils of proposals for price increases atthe same time as they notify the Price Commission.   The nationalised industries will be able, where appropriate, to modify their proposals to the Commission in the light of comments from the Councils.Kenorting187.   Initially notifying and reporting enterprises will be requiredto provide the Commission with sufficient information to establish the reference level for the profit margin limit including whereavailable audited accounts for the reference level period.   If a firm so wishes because of seasonal or other distorting factors, itmay submit a quarterly breakdown of this information.   The initialinformation provided by distributors will in addition need to besufficient to establish the base period gross margin.188.   Notifying and reporting enterprises will be required to providethe Price Commission with quarterly reports on total domestic sales,on profit margins, and, where any prices have been raised in the quarter and have not been pre-notified, full information about thebasis for these price changes.   Where audited financial accounts arenot available, figures derived from management accounts may be used
CONFIDENTIALprovided that these can in due course be reconciled with auditedfinancial accounts.   Distributors will not need to provide information on prices but will need to cover gross- margins.   The first of these reports, which v/ill be described in an Order under the Counter-Inflation Act, will be made by these enterprises for a quarterending between 25 &amp;ay 1973 and 28 July 1973*   This will enablecompanies to report for the quarterly periods they normally use.   Allreports should be made not more than 6 weeks after the end of theperiod to which they relate.Record keeping;189.    Those required only to keep records need not submit them tothe Price Commission except on request, but should have availablecomparable records   quarter by quarter of sales and profit marginsand of costs relevant to any price increases made in the quarter.They will also need to have available sufficient information toestablish the reference level for profit margins.    Smaller concernsneed not keep records.
Notification, Reporting and Record Keeping:    Pay190.    The general procedures for ensuring that the pay policy iseffectively monitored and implemented will be as follows:(a) major settlements affecting 1,000 employees or more,whether or not in a single undertaking, will be&quot; reported to the Pay Board and will require theapproval of the Board before they can be implemented(subject to the initial exceptions in paragraph 195below) ;(b) settlements affecting 100 employees and less than,000 will be reported to the Board but can be implemented without the Board&apos;s prior approval;(c) employers of 10 or more employees will be required tokeep pay records in any suitable form from which information to check compliance could if necessary beextracted.The Commission will not disclose information which is properlyconfidential except as provided in paragraph 4(2) of Schedule 4.of the Counter Inflation Act.191.    In all cases the information required, will be limited towhat they need to determine whether the settlement is consistent with the Code.     It will include the numbers and categories of employees concerned,  the terms and operative dates of the settlement and other settlements affecting the pay of any of the employees concerned in the preceding   12 months, and estimates of the pay billfor the 12 months before the settlement, calculated in accordancewith the Code, of the pay limit for the group, and of the effectof the settlement on the pay bill for the following 12 months.Settlements subject to Pay Board consent1Q2,    Settlements covering 1,000 employees or more (other than thosereached and due for implementation before 8 April) which are referredto in paragraph 195 below, will be required not to be implemented
until after the Board have given their approval.      Subject tothe Board&apos;s approval these settlements can be implemented fromtheir due date,  retrospectively if necessary.193.    If employers or their representatives who have notified asettlement to the Board in accordance with the arrangements inparagraph 192 do not receive a reply within 28 days, the board will be deemed to have given its approval.    If however the Boardso inform the applicant they may extend the period for consider-ation by up to a furthpr 28 days.     The Board will of course giveits decisions within shorter periods wherever possible, parti-cularly to reduce any period of retrospection to a minimum and taking account of the need to give 14 days warning notice of its intention to issue an order or notice restricting pay.    This willbe made easier if the parties voluntarily keep the Board informed about negotiations in advance of reaching a settlement.194.   The provisions of the Wages Councils Act 1959 and the Agri-cultural Wages Acts will be modified so to require Councils orBoards to have the approval of the Pay Board before notifyingemployers of proposals to increase statutory minimum remuneration.Once the Pay Board&apos;s approval has been obtained the normalstatutory procedure for making Wages Regulation Orders will proceed as at present.Major settlements reached and due to be implemented before8 April 1973195.   The requirement to obtain the Board&apos;s approval before imple-mentation of settlements covering 1,000 or more employees will notapply to settlements reached and due to be implemented before8 April 1973, whether they are settlements deferred by the stand-still or settlements for which a date before 8 April is the normaloperative date.      Such settlements must however be reported to theBoard,  in the same way as smaller settlements (see paragraph 196below) and will be subject to restriction if they do not conform with the Code.     Where such settlements have already been reportedto the Department of Employment, arrangements will be made with the
consent of those concerned to pass the information on to theBoard so as to avoid duplication.Reports of Settlements Reached196.    Employers or their representatives, who conclude settlementscovering 100 employees or more, whether or not in a single under-taking, will be required to notify the Board within 7 days of theterms of the settlement and other prescribed information.    this requirement will apply immediately to all settlements reachedsince 6 November 1972 and to other settlements as they are reached.197.   Apart from the larger settlements covered by paragraph 192above such settlements can be implemented without the prior approval of the Board, but will be subject to restriction by theBoard if they do not conform with the Code.Special arrangements for certain sectors198.   Orders or notices will be made at a later date requiringcertain special notification arrangements covering for examplelarge construction sites and the operation of payment by resultsschemes .Record keeping199.   Employers of 10 or more employees will be required to keepfor at least 12 months any form of record from which informationsufficient to check compliance with the Code could if necessary beabstracted.      Existing records will suffice provided they meet this requirement.Special ArrangementsFood200.   The draft Code makes it clear that prices of manufacturedfood will be controlled, both directly and through the profit margins of the manufacturers;    and that the prices charged by whole-wholesalers and retailers for all food, whether fresh of manufactured,
will be controlled through their gross margins and profit margins.201.    As announced in the Consultative Document (Cmnd 5247), aspecial panel of the Price Commission will be set up to deal with prices of food and drink.      This panel will carry out the commissions functions in relation to the prices of semi-processedand manufactured foods, which will be controlled in the same way as manufactured products generally.      The Commission will  also beable to carry out special inquiries into the circumstances affecting the price of any fresh food.Construction202.    As announced in the Consultative Document, the government propose that a special Construction Panel should be established toconsider how the requirements of the Price and Pay Code can most,effectively be applied to the construction industry,  taking accountof the special features of this industry.     The intention is thatthe panel should include members of both the Pay Board and thePrice Commission and the Government hope that both sides of theindustry will be willing to be represented on it.203.   Most construction work is done on the basis of competitivetenders and such tender prices will not be subject to prior approval by the Price Commission.     Construction firms with a turnover ofmore than  10 million a year will be required to submit to theCommission reports of their costs, prices,  turnover and profits at monthly intervals.     Firms with a turnover of between  1 million and  10 million a year will be required to maintain adequate records of their costs, prices and profits and to make them available tothe Commission if called upon to do so.204.    Firms engaged on or receiving contracts for constructionservices which are worth individually more than  5 million, andwhich include clauses providing for variation of prices, will berequired to provide the Commission with an outline description ofthe work, a copy of the contract, the items to which variation of price applies, and where applicable the amount of money received in
payments under the variation of price provisions during the  last three months.205.    On the pay side the Secretary of State or the Pay Board willbe making an order covering special notification arrangements for large construction sites at a later date.
[ Appendix AOn lines of Appendix to Cmnd 524-7][ Appendix BExamples of calculations under Price and pay Code ]


</content>
</cab>
