<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/28/0 images: 35-40</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
POCUIVIENT IS THE PROirBETY OP HIS BRITANNIC&quot; MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT)b iii UCP. (h8)  1o62 2ND JUNE.  1914 8COPY HO.CABINETSUPPLEMENTARY INJURIES BENEFITS POP MINERSMemorandum bv the Minister of Fuel and power at their meeting on 6th May the Cabinet were informed (G.P.(h8) 117)  that counter-proposals put forward by the National Coal Board for a supplementary injuriesbenefit scheme financed by roughly equal contributions fromthe Board and the miners had been emphatically rejected bythe National Union of Mineworkers, and that the Board were proposing to negotiate further on the basis of revised proposals involving a contribution of only 2d.  a week fromthe win-, rs.2. The Cabinet agreed (CM. (48) 31st- conclusions minute 7)  that the Board should be invited  to explore tpossibility of reaching a settlement on the basis of a contribution from the Board of not more than hd.  a ton,subject to a substantial contribution from the miners.3* The views cthe Board in a le-ttefollowed by renewed xiiocrd and thef the Government were communicated  tor of 7th Mag/ (Annex I;.      This wasegotiat-ions bet-ween the National Coalcourse andtional Union of Mineworkers,  theresults of which are recorded in Lord Hyndley&apos;s letter to meof 19th June (Annex II).      These two letters set out clearlywhat has transpired since the Cabinet last- considered thismatter and indicate the stage which has been reached in thenegotiations.      It is now necessary to decide whether thescheme described in Lord Hyndley&apos;s letter should or shouldnot be approved by theU. The major issue which arises is in regard  to the adequacy of the workmen&apos;a, contribution.      The Union would havebeen content with somewhat smaller benefits under a non-contributory scheme and    it was only with the utmost difficult,that the Board were- able to maintain the position that their offer of hd. per ton of output was absolutely dependent on asubstantial contribution from the workmen.      The Boardconsider that the Union&apos;s offer of a contribution of bd. perman per week, which was ultimately accepted, represents thelimit to which they were prepared  to go.      While it willaccount for only about- 12g- per cent, of the total contribution income under the Supplementary Scheme, it is equal to thefull amount contributed by the workmen under the Genera.].Industrial Injuries Scheme which,  of course,  provides muchmore valuable benefits.     In other word3 the high accidentit-e in the mines means theany scheme in this industryooundoe raucn more expensivethan in other industries./26
.*3&apos;o that the workmen&apos;.3 contribution roes much less far.5. A subsidiary issue is the fact that the scheme doesnot limit,the benefits to &quot;underground workers.     xhe reasonfor this is explained in paragraph 7 of Lord Hyndlcy&apos;s letter.6. I cm satisfied that the National Union of Mineworhershave been pressed by the National Coal Board as far as theyare prepared to go and I do not feel we  could possiblyjustify&apos;a refusal to endorse the provisional agreement reached between the Board and the union.      As indicated in th; see anaparagraph of Lord Hyndley&apos;a letter,  the scheme requires theapproval of the Minister of National Insurance and of theMinister of Fuel and Power.      It will be necessary toexamine  the scheme in detail before formal approval can begiven,    but subject to the fc, I recommend tact it should be approved in principle now.Ii. (.t.Ministry of Fuel and Power,  S.W.  x.,22nd June, 19U8.
AlWEX ICopy of. letter of 7th May,  IQlio. frog theP ermanent Bee ret- ar v._Ministry of Fuel and power to the Chairman of the Wat-ions I coal board, The Board wished  to know whether there was any element in the further proposals which they contemplateputtinr   to the N.U.M.  which the Government would reject anpresentation to them.The Minister has considered  the proposals asset out in Hutchinson&apos;s letter of 22nd April in consultationwith his colleagues.      You will appreciate that it is not always possible to say that a particular element would necessarily be rejected irrespective of the content end iomof the scheme as a whole,  and any scheme as agreed in detailbetween you and the Union would need to be considered beforethe Government could reach firm decisions on all points,levertheless I am able to give you the following indications of the Government-&apos; s views.The Minister was invited  to csk you to explore tfespossibility of devising a scheme under which the Board wouldcor tribute up to Lid.  per ton, with possibly a higher rate of contribution for any tonnage over the existing level of -out-put, making it clear that the Government would not regardany scheme as acceptable unless it provided for a substantial contribution from the workers.      This contribution need notbe by way of a flat rate but might vary according to theworkerfs wages,  e.g.  Id. per pound of wages.The Minister hopes that you will find it possibleto negotiate further with the Union and to agree on the out-line of a scheme which will conform with the Government-8sviews.At the stage when the details of the scheme have tobe filled in - more particularly as regards the  amount ofsupplementation for various degrees of incapacity - theMinister v/ould be glad if the N.C.B. would bear in mind the wide experience of the Ministry of National Insurance in this field and would ensure that close and informal liaison ismaintained between your officials and their&apos;s so that thepractical details and administrative questions can,  so faras possible,  be disposed of before formal submission of thescheme under Section S3 of the Industrial Injuries Act.(Signed)    DONALD FMHGUS30N
ANNEX IIGqtjv of letter of. 1,9 th; June,,, 19I48.,, fromthe Chairman -of_the &quot;National Goal board to the Minister of Fuel and Power.I promised, to write to you about the state of our negotiations with the National Union of Mineworkers on theproposed Supplementary Injuries Scheme.2. We have now been able to reach agreement on the main principles of the Scheme which will,  we hope, be approved undo??Section 3j5 of the National Insurance (Industrial Injuries)Act, 1946 and   under Section 37 of the Goal industryHattonelisation Act,  1946*3. Briefly the Scheme is designed to be contributoryand compulsory for all persons below the rant of under-manageremployed in or about a colliery by the Board or by a licenseeunder Section 36 of  the Goal Industry Nationalisation Act.The Beard have agreed  to contribute  to the funds of the scheme at the rate of lid.  a ton of saleable production of deep-minedcoal, i:&apos;less  the amount required for old cases (see paragraph 10below) and they have asked the licensees,  through theirFederation,  to agree to do the same.     All employees eligiblefor benefits would contribute lid.  a week: if 18 or over and 2-gd.a week if under 18 (Women 3d.  and 2d.).hi The following supplements would be paid out of the funds of the Scheme so long as the corresponding benefit is payable under the Industrial Injuries Act -(a) to injury benefit - 20/- a week, or,  in the caseof persons under 18, four-ninths of the Statebenefit;-(b) to disablement pension - an addition of 333 percent:(c;    to death benefit paid  to a widow or a woman havingthe care of a deceased workman&apos;s child - 20/- aweek.5. You will see that we have adopted your suggestionthat the Board should contribute on a. tonnage basis up to amaximum of ud.  a ton.      We tried  to secure a higher rate    of contribution than Ld.  a weed from the men and we also saidthat, if a flat rate would operate unfairly, we would not object- to  the worker&apos;s contribution varying according to hisrages.S. The Union at first flatly refused to consider anycontributory scheme. .    They pointed out that under theIndustrial Injuries Act, miners would for the first time beexpected to contribute towards payments for industrial injury.Thiy said that the scheme they had put forward had beenprepared on the- assumption that  the men would not be calledupon *to contribute;    the benefits for which they had askedwere very moderate and,  if  they had expected to contribute,they would have ashed for higher benefits.      If  the benefits for which they had asked could not be provided,, the men could
not be. expected to contribute as well as to accept lowerbenefits.     We maintained, however,   that the scheme must bea joint one and that as a matter of principle we expected the men to contribute.     We finally agreed  that their contributions should be the same as under the industrial injuries Act, which was the utmost they would consent to pay.?. The Union objected just as strongly to our proposalto limit the scheme to underground workers.      They said that many surface workers had formerly worked underground, were nolonger fit to do so  and were more prone to accident inconsequence. -   We finally compromised by including- surface workers in or about a. colliery but not those employed ate nc ill a i&apos; y ac tivities.6.   - The Scheme cannot now be given statutory effectso as to come into force before the 2nd August, but we haveagreed to arrange payment of the supplements from 5th July,the &quot;appointed day&quot; under the Industrial Injuries Act.9. For the purposes of administering the Scheme anddetermining disputed cases we propose to set up joint nationaand local committees.      So long as a man is not working,   thesupplement will be paid by the local National Insuranceofficer,, but when he returns to work the Board will take overpayment direct.10. As regards old cases now receiving workmen&apos;compensation, we have agreed to pay totally incapacitatedpersons  1 per week in addition to their compensation.      Wehave also agreed,  subject to certain overriding income limitssimilarly to supplement the compensation of partiallyincapacitated persons not in employment by 10/- a week andthose who are working by 5/- a week.      These payments are,of course,  ex gratia and there is no question of contribution from the workmen.      As I have said,   the cost will be deducted from the Board&apos;s contribution of bd.  per ton of saleableoutput.11. We have kept in close touch throughout with theMinistry of National Insurance who rad.se no objection tothese proposals,  and. our legal staff are collaborating withthe legal advisers of that Ministry in drafting the Scheme.Finally,   the Government Actuary is prepared  tocertify itas aotuarially sound.( S i signed)    HYNDLEY.


</content>
</cab>
