<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/28/0 images: 44-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1948SECRET Copy No.CP. (48) 15821st June, 1948CABINETTHE ANTARCTICMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate to my colleagues herewith a memorandum on our dispute withthe Argentine and Chilean Governments in regard to the Antarctic.This paper has been seen by the Ministers primarily concerned and takes account of their views. The Minister of Defence has suggested that we mightbe able to take a stronger line if we could obtain some additional naval backingin the Falkland Islands Dependencies from the Australian and New zealand governments, and the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations would be willing to approach these two Commonwealth Governments as soon as we can give them a clear picture of our future Antarctic policy.But before deciding to send a naval force to the Antarctic, we must clearour own minds as to whether we really want to take a stronger line and go through with it. It would in practice mean that we should remove all foreignparties from what we consider to be British territory and defend our rightsby force if necessary.This of course would be an entirely different course from that which I amrecommending in the present paper and which represents a policy of compromiseand negotiation. If. however, this policy fails, we may eventually be faced withthe alternative suggested by the Minister of Defence.E. B.foreign Office, S.W. 1,21st June, 1948.35515bthis  document is  the property of his  britannic  MAJESTYJ5 government        &apos;-34
2MEMORANDUMI. Eeceut British policy the past history of British and foreign acts of administration in the antarctic continent and of our local dispute with Argentina and Chile was covered in two papers recently prepared for the Cabinet (CP. (47) 263 of17th September, 1947, and CP. (48) 12 of 5th January, 1948). The general lineof policy laid down by the Cabinet in recent years has been to maintain and where possible strengthen British legal title to sovereignty in Antarctica, but to avoid the use of physical force to reassert our authority in disputed areas. Publicly,His Majesty&apos;s Government are committed to the view that any dispute as tosovereignty in the area should be submitted in the first instance to the Court ofInternational Justice at The Hagne^ but we are unable to take either Argentinaor Chile before the Court without their consent because neither of them hassigned the Optional Clause. Both Governments refused our suggestion that thedispute should be submitted by agreement to the Court, taking the view thatthere should be direct negotiations first.II. Contemporary Political Developments2. In recent weeks the immediate object of our policy has been to preventour dispute with Argentina and CMle over the Falkland Islands Dependenciesfrom becoming the subject of intervention by the Bogota Conference of the Pan-American Union. The United States Government and certain other latin american Governments supported us in this and the Conference passed by without prejudicing our position.3. We did, however, feel obliged in deference to the views of the australian government to oppose the State Departments plan (which they hoped might serve as an effective method of preventing discussion at Bogota) for an 8-power conference on the whole Antarctic question, to be attended by the United Statesand the seven Powers with formal territorial claims in the Antarctic, viz. : UnitedKingdom, Australia, New Zealand, France, Norway, Argentina and Chile.4. We also resisted successfully a further suggestion by the State Depart-ment that we should declare our willingness before or during the Bogota Con-ference to go into tripartite discussions with Argentina and Chile over the localdispute in the Falkland Islands Dependencies.5. This policy of inaction was valid so long as the Bogota Conference lasted,But it provides no advance towards a settlement, and the time has now come when His Majesty&apos;s Government must consider urgently what steps they can take to prevent a repetition, next season, of the unpleasant incidents which occurred this season in the Falkland Islands Dependencies. These incidents arelikely to become more numerous and assume greater importance as the practical experience of the Argentines and Chileans in Antarctic waters increases, andas they come to realise more clearly that British policy stops short of the useof force.III. recommendations. It is accordingly recommended in paragraphs 14, 15, 17 and 22 below that: (i) An early approach should be made through the diplomatic channel tothe Argentine and Chilean Governments with a view to reaching an agreed settlement of the territorial dispute in the Falkland IslandsDependencies before the opening of the next Antarctic season inOctober;(ii) The prior approval in principle, and if possible the active support, ofthe United States Government should be obtained for the proposedcourse of action;-^Extract from a reply to a supplementary question in the House of Commons on25th February: &quot; i have ottered, is Shis case and others, on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government,to have the legal title settled in the International Court of Justice and, until that title is settledI am not prepared to take any other steps.&quot;   (Hansard, Col. 1932.)
(iii) The Governments of Canada, Australia, New Zealand and South africa should be informed in detail of our proposals and given a few days in which to comment should they so wish.IV. The Immediate Problem7. The American plan for an 8-Power Conference, though its scope and purpose is still not very clear, appears to be designed primarily for securing an agreed regime or regimes for the Antarctic Continent as a whole. The islands and the peninsula of Graham Land which constitute the most important area in dispute with Argentina and Chile are, however, to some extent distinct fromthe main part of the continent in that they do not lie within the Antarcticcircle.* They should, therefore, or at any rate could be treated separately, andthe United States Government have made it clear that they would like HisMajesty&apos;s Government to reach a direct settlement with Argentina and Chileover this immediate issue.8. The next few months will probably provide the last opportunity forreaching such a settlement. If the dispute is allowed to drag on until next seasonopens, two things are likely to worsen the British position, namely: (a) The fact that Argentine and Chilean activities are almost certain next season to be even more ostentatious and extensive compared with oursthan they were last, and(&amp;) The fact that opinion in both North and South America is likely toharden against us in such a dispute.The general conclusion of the studies made by the Chiefs of Staff and the Depart-ments concerned is to the effect that the Falkland Islands Dependencies are not of such value to His Majesty&apos;s Government that large sums of money shouldbe forthcoming for developing or defending them; whereas the Argentines are both closer to the scene and, at present, more willing to spend money and effort in these areas.V. Minimum Requirements oe His Majesty&apos;s Government9. Without concessions on both sides there would of course be no possible basis for a direct settlement with Argentina or Chile; and once it is admitted that His Majesty&apos;s Government are not going to fight for the whole of their claim, the questions to be faced are : (a) what minimum rights we must hold on to, and(b) how we can forgo the remainder with the least loss of prestige andthe least prejudice to other British territories at the periphery of theEmpire.10. The first question has been discussed by the Foreign Office with theColonial Office and the Ministry of Defence, with whom it has been agreed thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government must at all costs retain South Georgia (where thereis a permanent population and a lucrative whaling industry at present contri-buting some  40,000 per annum to the revenue of the administration), deception island (with its important harbour) and King George Island in the SouthShetlands. The Law Officers of the Crown, who were consulted last year, enter-tained no doubt that South Georgia belongs to the United Kingdom, and verylittle doubt that the United Kingdom has a valid title to sovereignty overDeception Island, and a strong, but not incontrovertible, claim to the remainingSouth Shetland Islands, of which King George Island is one.11. The retention of the three islands named above is regarded as essentialon strategic grounds, since their possession is required to ensure command ofDrake Passage. But surrender of the whole of the remainder of the Dependencies,even if acceptable from the strategic point of view (the Chiefs of Staff would prefer to retain as many islands as possible in the South Shetland and SouthOrkney groups and Signy Island in particular), would represent, a retreat beforepressure which would be most damaging to British prestige, and would mean* The Graham Land Peninsula, properly speaking, extends from a point on the Antarctic-continent considerably to the South of the Antarctic circle, but it would be convenient in any negotiations regarding Graham Land to confine discussions to that part of the peninsula and adjacent islands lying North of the narrow isthmus between Marguerite Bay and the Weddell Sea.35515 * B 2
abandoning the prospects of economic development under British control to which our pioneering work in this region has fully entitled us. We should, therefore,endeavour in the proposed negotiations to retain some parts at any rate of(1) the remaining islands in the South Shetlands group, and (2) the GrahamLand peninsula and the islands adjacent to its West Coast. An acceptablecompromise would be to agree to relinquish claims to (a) that part of GrahamLand and the adjacent islands west of 65&quot;, and (b) territories within the area east of 53&quot; and south of 560 (involving surrender of the whole of the SouthSandwich Islands and the South Orkney Islands). We might also be prepared,if necessary, to relinquish Elephant Island, Clarence Islands, and Gibbs Island(the three principal island groups at the north-eastern end of the South Shetlands).12. In exchange, we should require, apart from Argentine and Chileanrecognition of our sovereignty (or at least withdrawal of their own claims) incertain islands, mutual guarantees of freedom of navigation and freedom toundertake whaling, sealing and other commercial and scientific operationsanywhere in the Dependencies under appropriate licences to be issued by theGovernment exercising local sovereignty and subject to the international agree-ments in force. Recognition of any existing licences should be part of theunderstanding.13. The answer to the second question referred to in paragraph 9 (whichhas also been discussed with the Colonial Office) is in my opinion that Britishprestige will suffer less from giving up the remainder of the territorial claims in free discussion with the two parties during the next few months than it would if His Majesty&apos;s Government were driven out under pressure of some new Pan-American initiative or of renewed Argentine-Chilean naval action which wecannot effectively match.VI. Approach to Argentina and Chiie14. It is accordingly recommended that His Majesty&apos;s Government should now make a serious effort to come to a settlement bilaterally with the Argentinesand Chileans. In the event of the Argentines and Chileans refusing to negotiate with us except at a tripartite conference, it is recommended that we should agreeto such a conference rather than break off discussions.15. The lines on which His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadors at Buenos Aires andSantiago might approach the two Governments are as follows : (a) We share their desire to avoid a continuation of the disputes whichhave taken place this year in the Falkland Islands Dependencies, andare ready to examine with them, on a friendly and confidential basis,the means of reaching a settlement.(b) We maintain our view that the proper procedure for reaching such asettlement is to secure a reference to the International Court on thequestion of legal title to all the areas under dispute.(c) However, in order to make it easier for the Argentine and ChileanGovernments to agree to such a course we wish to inform them confidential -tially that, while there are certain territories over which we consider our title particularly strong and which we would not be prepared to relinquish except on the decision of the International Court, we shouldbe willing to consider the possibility of not pressing our claims to thewhole of the area if a general (and financial) settlement, satisfactory to all three parties, could be reached by negotiation.(d) If the two Governments cannot settle on the basis of (e) they should at the least accept a reference of the whole matter to the Court, bearing that mind that, as stated in (&amp;), we should probably prefer our claims to certain areas mainly as a matter of form.(e) So far as continental territory within the Antarctic circle was concernedany settlement reached would be without prejudice to the claims ofother Powers or to any international arrangement which might atany future time be reached in regard to the Antarctic proper.(/) Both parties would agree in advance that any proposals that might bemade or any concessions that might be offered by either side in thecourse of the discussions would be without prejudice to the legal position as between the two parties or to any action which that partymight take in the future to establish their title.
i (g) In the event of a territorial settlement being agreed, the three parties should proceed forthwith to. set up joint machinery for the adminis-tration of whaling, sealing and other commercial activity in the territories covered by the agreement and for the co-ordination of scientific activity.(h) Pending the  outcome of  the  discussions  both  sides  should  bindthemselves (i) not to establish any further occupied posts in the disputedterritory or to despatch any expeditions to the area other thanthose required for the relief and maintenance of existing posts,and(ii) to refrain from political propaganda in support of their claims.16. It is hard to say what would be the reaction of the Argentine andChilean Governments to an approach of this kind. We must, however, be preparedfor the possibility that they will regard it as a sign of weakness and will eitherrefuse to negotiate or so protract the discussions that they run on into the nextAntarctic season when, as they will no doubt realise, circumstances will strengthen their physical and perhaps also their legal position yet more. It is, therefore,essential that we should have some spare strings to our bow.VII. Approach to United States of America17. The first obvious need is that we should have United States approvalof our proposed course of action, and that they should indicate to the other partiestheir wish to see a settlement satisfactory to both sides. We should point out to the United States Government that our scheme (especially point (e) above)would safeguard their own position in regard to the arctic areas of the mainland(where they are contemplating making claims themselves) and would leave the door open to any wider arrangement which they might wish to sponsor for the antarctic continent.18. The above recommendations are made, however, in the full knowledge that American support of the general kind described in the preceding paragraphmay not suffice to prevail on the Argentine and Chilean Governments to accept our proposals. So long as the discussions lasted the Argentines and Chileansmight be willing to abate their propaganda, but they could not be expected to interrupt their preparations for the next season&apos;s Antarctic campaign. As soonas the talks were broken off the situation envisaged in paragraphs 5 and 8 would automatically arise, and we should be faced with the danger of last season&apos;difficulties being reproduced on a much larger scale in October or early November.For political reasons we could not run this risk. If, therefore, we failed to reach an early agreement with the Argentines and Chileans it would be essential forHis Majesty&apos;s Government to find other means to obtain a settlement.19. The only solution in such circumstances would be to obtain more active support from the United States than is envisaged under the present proposals.In order to obtain this support it might be necessary to abandon our oppositionto the United States idea of an 8-Power Conference. It is hard in any case to see how we can maintain for long our opposition to such a Conference ifthe Americans want it badly enough; nor would we appear to have anything to lose from it although the Australians are at present opposed, as explained inparagraph 3 above, apparently largely for reasons of national prestige.20. An important incidental advantage of abandoning our opposition tothe United States 8-Power proposals would be that the mere threat of an inter-national regime in Antarctica might itself directly help our negotiations withthe Argentine and Chilean Governments. The main Argentine and Chileanmotive in all this is prestige and the desire to paint their national colours onthese areas. It might be an inducement to them to reach agreement with us if we were able to hint that, failing a settlement by which the islands were divided amicably between the three claimants, we might declare for their inclusion in the area to be covered by the 8-Power Conference and for an internationalregime over all the islands as well as the continent, a proposal which we knowwould meet with the fullest United States support.
VIII. Tmportance of the Time Factor21. Time would be an all-important factor in our calculations. The packice in the Northern areas of the Dependencies melts as early as October and anAntarctic expedition takes several months to organise and equip. Unless, there-fore, we are able to persuade the Argentines and Chileans by early Septemberthat their interests lie in reaching an agreement with us, their preparations mayhave reached so advanced a stage and their national pride have once more becomeso deeply involved as to make a retreat extremely difficult. It will, therefore, be essential to take the action proposed in the two preceding paragraphs in Augustat the latest that is to say we could not afford to postpone our approach to theUnited States Government much beyond 15th August. Our bilateral discussionwith the Argentine and Chilean Governments (or alternatively our tripartiteconference) should, therefore, be timed to produce results before this date.IX. Dominion Governments Informed22. It is not part of the present proposals that we should at this stagetell the United States Government that we might be prepared to reconsider our attitude over the 8-Power Conference. The United States Government will nodoubt pursue this idea if they wish to do so. On the other hand it is essentialthat the four Dominions concerned, and especially the Australians, should be madefully aware of the difficulties which lie ahead of us in reaching a direct settlement with Argentina and Chile over the Falkland Islands Dependencies and of thepossibility that circumstances may force us to fall back on the American proposals should a direct settlement not have been reached by 15th August.






</content>
</cab>
