<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/28/0 images: 206-208</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ifI % \ 147EI3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERT3MES!?)SEC RET C.P. (U-8)  1767th July,  19U-8.CABINETVISIT OF LORD HENDERSON TO germany memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate herewith, for the information of mycolleagues,   a report &quot;by the Parliamentary Under-Seeretary ofState, Lord Henderson, on his visit to Germany from 2nd July tohth July.E.B.Foreign Office,  S.W.1..7th July, 19h8.COPY NO.NOTE BY THE PARLIAMBNTARY UNDER-SECRETARY OF STATE FORFOREIGN AFFAIRS TlQRD RENDERSON! ON VISIT TO GERMANY,2ND - UTH JULY,  19*4-8.1.       BerlinThere is complete unanimity of view in support ofyour declared policy not to leave Berlin.      This view is heldnot only throughout all ranks of the Control Commissionpersonnel whom I met, but also by the German representatives(S.D.P., C.D.U.  and L.D.P.) with whom I talked.      In both thesequarters it is recognised that the exclusion of the western allies from Berlin would be the first step to their exclusion from Western Germany,  and that Russian influence up to the Shinewould endanger both France and Italy.      The moral resistance of the Germans is good.      But there is no doubt that they areapprehensive lest we should for any reason allow Berlin to pass into exclusive Russian ambit.      If this should happen, confidence in the Western Allies would completely disappear.The next point which is exercising the minds of theGermans most at the present, moment is currency reform in Berlin.They are disappointed that the Deutschmark has not been madethe sole currency in the Western Zones of Berlin and they fess?that the present arrangement will virtually ensure that theeconomic life of the Western Zones will inevitably become an integral part of the economic life of the Eastern Zone and theRussian Sector of Berlin.
The air lift in the British Zone is increasing daily.The total lift &quot;between Saturday midday and Sunday middayreached a substantial total (about 500 tons), and it isexpected that during the present week the maximum will beachieved on the basis of the number of &apos;planes available.To the Bakotas and Yorks will be added as from (probably)Tuesday the air lift of 10 Sunderlands, which will accountfox- something between 1+0 and 50 tons per day.      Two suggestions have been made,  and I believe are being considered,   namely -(a) use of gliders, and(&quot;b) use of bombers to assist not so much.in food lift as industrial lift (coal).I gather that the saturation point of air lift will not beachieved with the number of  &apos;planes already allocated forBerlin supplies, but that it might be possible, by usinganother despatch aerodrome, if- additional  &apos;planes were madeavailable,  to increase the present maximum target which, withthe use of the Sunderlands,  is expected to reach about 800tons a day.While Russian intentions may be unpredictable I foundno one who believed that they were thinking in terms of war to achieve their objectives in Berlin.      It is consideredthat s political and diplomatic policy of firmness withoutprovocation,  supported by sustained air lift of supplies to berlin,  Is the one best calculated to bring about a resumptionof car freedom of movement into and out of Berlin through the corridor.2.        unemployment - Social Measures.I had discussions on the problem of unemploymentarising out of currency reform and the capital levy,  the diversion of available suitable labour to essential industries,and. the social measures that might be considered and adopted.These related problems have been foreseen and certain steps have already been token,  but there are some very obviousdifficulties to be overcome.      I was told, for example,  that in large parts of the Ruhr housing accommodation is greatlyovercrowded,  2.1+ persons to a room.      The question of increasingman-power for Ruhr industries is governed by the ability toIncrease the already very inadequate housing accommodation inthat part of Germany,  and concentration on the repair ofexisting houses is regarded as the first priority - not thebuilding of new houses.(Signed)    HENDERSONForeign Office,  S.W.1.6th -July, 19U8.


</content>
</cab>
