<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/28/0 images: 287-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
197IIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY. OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)G ONFIDENTIALC.?.(li3)  lok COPY NO.21.IhTH JULY,  19h-8CABINETIKTERC-OVERNMENTAL MARITIME CONSULTATIVE. organisation memorandum by the Minister of transport at their meetings on 28th November, 194-6C*M*(h6) 101st Conclusions, Minute 3) and 21st January, 19h7.C*M.(h77) loth Gonolusions, Minute 3) the Cabinet approved in principle the proposals for an Intergovernmental Shipping-Organisation,  set out in my paner (CP. (h6) h33) and in theMinister of State&apos;s paper (C.P.(h7) Ik).2. A delegation composed of representatives of theMinistry of Transport and the Foreign Office attended theunited Nations Maritime Conference held at Geneva inFebruary this year,,    After a remarkably harmonious conferencelasting seventeen days,  the attached Convention for settingup an Intergovernmental Maritime Consultative organisation was signed on behalf of eighteen countries,  including theUnited Kingdom, the United States and nearly all the other important maritime and trading nations,all signatures being subject to ;iacceptance!i.    This Convention closely followsthe lines proposed in the submissions aiyproved by theCabinet and satisfactorily meets the specific points raised in the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on 28th November, 19h7, and reported on by the Steering.Committee on international organisations (CP.(h7) Ik) -    Thus(l)    The new organisation is to be a Specialised agency of the United Nationsj(2)    It will have as one of its most important functionsthe discouragement of discriminatory practicesby governments in shipping matters:;The Scandinavian countries did not sign the convention at Geneva as they were doubtful about the desirabilityof having an organisation covering more than purelytechnical questions, but they are expected to accept itin due course.    China was the one country to vote against theConvention because she was hurt at .being excluded from the nucleus of the first Council.    The U.S.S.R. were not represented at the Conference, having previously taken the line that no such organisation was necessary.
198(3)    Overlapping with, &quot;bodies such, as the InternationalLabour Organisation will be prevented by-Article Ho which provides that -:&apos;Tta,e Organisation shall co-operate withany specialised agency of the UnitedITations in matters which may be the common concern of the Organisation and of suchspecialised agency, and shall consider such, matters and act with respect to themin accord with such specialised agency.&quot;j(If.)    The headquarters of the new Organisation will bein London.3* I would lilce to draw attention to a few other important points:-(a) Seme concession in drafting was made to thosenations without merchant shipping of theirown who regard the absolute aim of removing alldiscriminatory and restrictive practices by governments from shipping as designed tomonopolise the world&apos;s shipping for certain countries^   The Convention recognises that assistance and encouragement may be given to national shipping provided it is not based on measures &quot;designed to restrict the. freedom of- shipping cf all flags tc take part in inter-national trade.fi    (Article 1(b)).(b) Per similar reasons provision is made forconsideration by the Organisation of complaints of unfair restrictive practices by shippingconcerns, but the procedure ensures that everyeffort has to be made tc settle such mattersthrough commercial channels.   Article h of theConvention lays it down that 11 In those matters which appear to the Organisation capable of settlement through the normal processes ofinternational shipping business the organisation shall so&quot; recuiiimiend.&quot;   An interpretative notehas been added tc Article 53 of the HavanaCharter (dealing with restrictive businesspractices In the field, of &quot;services&quot;)  so that ifquestions under this heading have to come before an international forum they will be handled by the Intergovernmental Maritime consultative organisation, as a body suitably composed andconstituted to deal with maritime questions.(c) The constitution of the new Organisation has been so framed as to secure that the Council shall havea key position in it.   On this Council theUnited Kingdom can rely upon a majority of nationswhose interests and outlook in maritime matters are generally similar to our own.If.. The Convention (Cmd. 7*1-12) was laid before bothHouses of Parliament on 2oth Hay and has not been the subjectof any question or motion.    It has also been submitted to the steering Committee on International Organisations and noobjections to ratification have been received from otherDepartments.    I accordingly request authority to ratify theConvention by arranging with the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs for the deposit of a formal instrument of
&quot;acceptance&quot; with, the Secretary-General of the united nations.    I would propose to time our ratificationin consultation with, the other important maritime countries who have supported our efforts to &quot;bring about thisConvention.   The Convention is to come into force when21 countries, including seven having at least one million gross registered tons of -shipping each, have- ratified it.It is important that the Scandinavian countries should come in, as I hope they will decide to do.Ministry of Transport, W.I.,14th July, 1948;.-
SHIPPINGMiscellaneous No. 6 (1948)United NationsMaritime Consultative OrganisationFinal Act of conference with Annexes and Convention establishing the Organisation[with Appendices]Geneva, 6th March, 1948Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs to Parliament by Command of His MajestyLONDONHIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICEsixpence    netCmd. 7412
TABLE   OF   CONTENTS&apos; page 1. Final Act of Conference ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      32. Annex &quot;A.&quot; Resolution on the Establishment of the preparatory committee of the Inter-governmental Maritime consultative organisation     ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ....       ...       ...      5&apos;i. Annex &quot; B.&quot;   Draft Resolution on the Safety of Life at Sea Conference      64. Annex &quot;C.&quot; Resolution relating to the Report of the preparatory committee of Experts on Co-ordination of Safety at Sea and inthe Air..............................      75. Annex &quot; D.&quot; Draft- Agreement on the Relationship between the united nations and the Inter-governmental Maritime consultative organisation     ...       ...      ...       ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...      76. Convention for the Establishment of the Inter-governmental maritime consultative Organisation ...       ...       ...       ...      ...       ...     137. Appendices to the Convention    ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...     24
UNITED NATIONS MARITIME CONFERENCEGeneva, 6ih March, 1948Final ActmThe United Nations Maritime Conference was convened by the Economicand Social Council of the United Nations bv the following resolution adopted on 28th March, 3947:  &quot; The Economic and Social Council requests the Secretary-General:(a) to convene a conference of interested Governments to consider theestablishment of an inter-governmental maritime organisation.The Draft Convention prepared by the United Maritime Consulta-tive Council on this matter, concerning the scope and the purposeof the proposed organisation, will serve as a working paper formingthe basis of discussion for the Conference. The Conference willalso consider if the scope and purposes of the Organisation should include the removal or prevention of unfair restrictive practices by shipping concerns;(b) to circulate the above-mentioned Draft Convention to all the Govern-ments invited to the Conference;(c) to inform the Governments which are invited to the conference that any comments which they may wish to make on specificarticles of the Draft Convention or amendments which they may wish to propose in advance of the Conference, should be submittedto the Secretary-General for circulation to all Governments partici-pating in the Conference and for consideration by the Conferenceitself;(d) to draw up a provisional agenda for the Conference, including the items mentioned above;(e) to invite all the members of the United Nations and the followingGovernments to participate in the Conference:  Albania, Austria, Bulgaria, Eire, Finland, Hungary, Italy,Portugal, Roumania. Switzerland, Transjordania, Yemen.The Economic and Social Council expeesses the hope that the Govern-ments invited to the Conference may give their respective delega-tions full powers enabling them to sign such Convention on theestablishment of an inter-governmental maritime organisation asmay be concluded at the Conference.The Economic and Social Council requests the Secretary-General to invite the specialised agencies, inter-goveramental organisations and international organisations in this field, as may be appropriate, tosend observers to the Conference. The Conference shall meet, if practicable, in the autumn of 1947, at a place to be determinedby the Secretary-General after consultation with the President ofthe Council.&quot;The United Nations Maritime Conference met in the City of Genevafrom the 19th February, 194S. to the 6th March, 194S.
The Governments of the following States were, represented at theConference by Delegations: -The Governments of the following States had observers at theconference:  The following organisations were represented by observers:  A. Inter-Governmental OrganisationsInternational Labour Office-World Health Organisation.International Civil Aviation Organisation.International Telecommunications Union.International Meteorological Organisation.B. Non-Governmental OrganisationsInternational Co-operative Alliance.International Chamber of Commerce.International Law Association.International Transport Workers&apos; Federation.The Conference had before it and used as a basis for discussion the draft agreement for an inter-governmental maritime organisation prepared by theUnited Maritime Consultative Council. This document was submitted as a working paper for the Conference in accordance with the resolution adoptedby the Economic and Social Council on 28th March, 1947, at its 4th session,on the recommendation of its Transport and Communications Commission.On the basis of its deliberations, as recorded in the records and reportsof the respective committees, and of the plenary sessions, the Conferenceprepared and opened for signature and acceptance a Convention on theInter-Governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation.In addition, the Conference adopted the following resolutions:  1. A Resolution for the Establishment of a Preparatory Committee ofthe Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation;(Appended hereto as Annex &quot; A &quot; to this Final Act).Argentina.Australia.Belgium.Brazil.Canada.Chile.China.Colombia.Czechoslovakia.Denmark.Dominican Republic.Egypt.Eire. -Finland.France.Greece.India.Italy.Lebanon.Netherlands.Norway.New Zealand.Pakistan.Panama.PolandPeru.Portugal.Sweden.Switzerland -Turkey.United Kingdom.United States of America.Cuba.Ecuador.Iran.Union of South Africa.2. A Resolution on the Safety of Life at Sea Conference;(Appended hereto as Annex &quot; B &quot;to this Final Act).
3. A Eesolution relating to the Report of the Preparatory Committeeof Experts on Co-ordination of Safety at Sea and in the Air;(Appended hereto as Annex &quot; C &quot; to this Final Act).The Conference also approved the substance of a Draft Agreement onRelationships between the new Organisation and the United Nations(appended hereto as Annex &quot; D &quot;) and decided that it be used as a basis for negotiations by the Preparatory Committee with the United Nations inconformity with section 2 of the resolution establishing the Committee.jp. In witness whereof the respective representatives have signed this^Final Act:Done in the City of Geneva this 6th day of March, 1948, in a singlecopy in the English, French and Spanish languages, each text being equallyauthentic. The original texts will be deposited with the Secretary-Generalof the United Nations who will send certified copies to each of the Govern-ments invited to send representatives to the Conference.[Here follow the signatures]ANNEX &quot;A &quot;A Resolution on the Establishment of the Preparatory Committee of theInter-governmental Maritime Consultative organisation the United Nations Maritime Conference convened on 19th February,1948, in Geneva by the Economic and Social Council of the United Nations;Having agreed that an international organisation to be known as theinter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation shall be established,andHaving agreed upon a Convention for the Organisation,Hereby resolves that a Preparatory Committee should be established,And resolves, further, that:&apos; 1. The Preparatory Committee of the Inter-governmental maritime consultative Organisation shall consist of representatives of the followingtwelve States: Argentine, Australia, Belgium, Canada, France, Greece,India, Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, the United Kingdom, and the UnitedStates of America.2.   The functions of the Preparatory Committee shall be:  (a) to convene the first session of the Assembly of the Inter-governmentalMaritime Consultative Organisation within 3 months from the date on which the Convention of the Organisation comes into force;(b) to prepare and submit to the Governments represented at the united nations Maritime Conference, and to any other Governments whichhave signed or accepted the Convention, at least 6 weeks beforethe first session of the Assembly of the Organisation, the provisionalagenda for that session and necessary documents and recommen-dations relating thereto, including:  &apos;(i) proposals for the implementation of the functions of theOrganisation and a budget for the first 2 years of theOrganisation,(ii) draft rules of procedure,(iii) draft financial and staff regulations;35326 c*
(fa) to suggest a scale of contributions by members to tbe budget of theOrganisation;(d) to prepare a draft annex to the General Convention on the privileges and Immunities of the Specialised Agencies (2) in accordance withPart B of the Resolution adopted by the General Assembly of theUnited Nations on 21st November, 1947, relating to this subject;(e) to enter into negotiations with the United Nations with a view tothe preparation of an agreement as contemplated in Article 57 ofthe Charter of the United Nations (2) and in Article 45 of theConvention, using as a basis the draft agreement approved bythe United Nations Maritime Conference.In carrying out the functions of this section due. consideration shall be givento the deliberations and decisions of the United Nations Maritime Conference.3. The first meeting of the Preparatory Committee shall be held in Genevaimmediately after the conclusion of this Conference.4. The Preparatory Committee shall elect a chairman and adopt itsown rules of procedure.5. The expenses of the Preparatory Committee other than those of themembers of the committee shall be met from funds which governments may advance to the committee or from funds which may be loaned by theUnited Nations. The Preparatory Committee shall explore the feasibility of obtaining a loan from the United Nations and, if mutually acceptable, mayenter into a loan agreement. The obligation under any such loan wouldbe considered by the Governments represented at the Conference as a firstclaim for repayment by the Inter-governmental Maritime consultative organisation within the first 2 years of its existence. In the event of advances of funds to the Preparatory Committee from Governments, suchadvances may be set off against the contributions of the Governments con-cerned to the Organisation.6. The Preparatory Committee may enter into agreement with theSecretary-General of the United Nations concerning the possible provisionof personnel and other secretarial services under mutually satisfactory arrangements.7. The Preparatory Committee shall cease to exist upon resolution ofthe First Session of the Assembly of the Inter-govemmental maritime consultative Organisation.ANNEX &quot; B&quot;A Draft Resolution on the Safety of Life at Sea ConferenceWhereasThe United Nations Maritime Conference has approved a convention for the establishment of an inter-governmental maritime consultative organisation whose scope includes matters relating to maritime safety, andWhereasThe conference for the purpose of revising the Convention on safety of Life at Sea of 1929,(3) will be held in London in April 1948, andf1) &quot; Miscellaneous No. 6 (1946),&quot; Cmd. 6753. .(2) &quot; Treaty Series No. 67 (1946),&quot; Cmd. 7015.(3) &quot; Treaty Series No. 34 (1932),&quot; Cmd. 4198.
whereas the matters to be considered by the Safety of Life at Sea Conferencefall within the field of responsibilities covered by the InternationalMaritime Consultative Organisation Convention,The United Nations Maritime Conference-recommends that the Safety of Life at Sea Conference examine the convention onthe Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation with a viewto drafting provisions in its final acts which will take into account they^tlut-ies and functions relating to maritime safety which have been accorded.  to the Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation.ANNEX &quot;G &quot;A Resolution by the United States Delegation relating to the Report ofthe Preparatory Committee of Experts on Co-ordination of Safety at sea and in the AirWhereasPart VII of the Convention of the Inter-governmental maritime consultative Organisation places upon the Maritime Safety Committee. the duty of co-ordinating its activities with those of other inter-govern-mental bodies in the field of transport and communications having an interest in maritime safety, andWhereasA special Preparatory Committee of Experts, representing inter-govern-mental organisations in the fields of aviation, meteorology, shipping and telecommunications, has recently met in London to consider principles for the co-ordination of activities in those four fields,whereas the report of the Preparatory Committee (circulated to the conference as Document E/Conf.4/8) will be considered at the forthcoming conference to revise the Convention for the Safety of Life at Sea, to he held inLondon in April 1948.ResolvesThat this Conference direct its President to inform the Conferenceon Safety of Life at Sea that the conclusions contained in paragraph 21of the Report of the Preparatory Committee of Experts were taken intoconsideration by this Conference when drafting Part VII of the Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation Convention whichestablishes the Maritime Safety Committee.ANNEX &quot; D &quot;Draft Agreement on Relationship between the United Nations and theInter-Governmental Maritime Consultative organisation article 57 of the Charter of the United Nations (hereinafter called &quot; the charter &quot;) provides that specialised agencies, established by inter-govern -mental agreement and having wide international responsibilities as defined35326 o* 2
in their basic instruments in economic, social, cultural, educational, health and related fields, shall be brought into relationship with the United Nations.Part XII of the Convention on the Inter-governmental Maritime Consul-,tative Organisation provides that the Inter-governmental Maritime Consul-tative Organisation (hereinafter called &quot; the Organisation &quot;) shall be broughtinto relationship with the United Nations as one of the specialised agenciesreferred to in Article 57 of the Charter of the United Nations.Therefore the United Nations and the Organisation agree as follows:  Article IThe United Nations recognises the Organisation as the specialised agencyresjionsible for taking such action as may be appropriate under its basicinstrument for the accomplishment of the purposes set forth therein.Article IIReciprocal Representation1. The United Nations shall be invited to send representatives to attend the meetings of the Assembly of the Organisation, the Council, the MaritimeSafety Committee, any subsidiary organs, and such, conferences as theOrganisation may convene, and to participate, without vote, in the delibera-tions of these bodies.2. The Organisation shall be invited to send representatives to attend meetings of the Economic and Social Council of the United Nations and ofits commissions and committees, and to participate, without vote, in the deliberations of these bodies, with respect to items on their agenda relatingto matters within the scope of the activities of the Organisation.3. The Organisation shall be invited to send representatives to attend meetings of the General Assembly of the United Nations for purposes of consultation on matters within the scope of the activities of the Organisation.4. The Organisation shall be invited to send representatives to attend meetings of the main committees of the General Assembly when matters within the scope of its activities are under discussion and to participate,without vote, in such discussions.5. The Organisation shall be invited to send representatives to attend the meetings of the Trusteeship Council and to participate, without vote, inthe deliberations thereof with respect to items on the agenda relating to matters within the scope of its activities.6. Written statements of the Organisation shall be distributed by the secretariat of the United Nations to the members of the General Assembly,the Economic and Social Council and its commissions, and the trusteeship council as appropriate. Similarly, written statements presented by theUnited Nations shall be distributed as soon as possible by the Secretariat ofthe Organisation to all members of the Organisation.Article IIIProposal of Agenda ItemsSubject to such preUminary consultation as may be necessary, theOrganisation shall include on the agenda of the Assembly, Council, and the maritime Safety Committee, items proposed to it by the United Nations.Similarly, the Economic and Social Council and its commissions and the trusteeship Council shall include on their provisional agenda items proposedby the Assembly or Council.
Article IVBe commendations of the United Nations1. The Organisation having regard to the obligation of the United nations to promote the objectives set forth in Article 55 of the Charter and thefunctions and powers of the Economic and Social Council, under Article 62of the Charter, to make or initiate studies and reports with respect to inter-national economic, cultural, educational, health and related matters andto^make recommendations concerning these matters to the specialiseda-ji-ncies concerned, and having regard also to the responsibility of the united nations, under Articles 58 and 63 of the Charter, to make recommendations for the co-ordination of the policies and activities of such specialised agencies,agrees to arrange for the submission, as soon as possible to the Assembly orthe Council, as appropriate, of all formal recommendations which the united nations may make to it.2. The Organisation agrees to enter into consultation with the united nations upon request, with respect to such recommendations, and in due course to report to the United Nations on the action taken by the organisation or by its members, to give effect to such recommendations, or on the otherresults of their consideration.3. The Organisation affirms its intention of co-operating in whateverfurther measures may be necessary to make co-ordination of the policyand activities of specialised agencies and those of the United Nations fully&apos;effective. In particular, it agrees to participate in, and to co-operate withany bodies which the Economic and Social Council has established or mayestablish for the purpose of facilitating such co-ordination and to furnishsuch information as may be required for the carrying out of this purpose.Article VExchange of Information and Documents1.   Subject to such arrangements as may be necessary for the safe-guarding of confidential material, the fullest and promptest exchange of appropriate information and documents shall be made between the united nations and the Organisation.2.   Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of paragraph 1 (a) the Organisation agrees to transmit to the United Nations regularreports on the activities of- the Organisation and programmes of operation for each ensuing year;(b) the Organisation agrees to comply to the fullest extent practicablewith any request which the United Nations may make for thefurnishing of special reports, studies or information, subject tothe conditions set forth in Article XV; and(c) the Secretary-General of the United Nations shall upon request,consult with the Secretary-General of the Organisation- regardingthe provision to the Organisation of such information as may beof special interest to the Organisation.Article VIAssistance to the Security council the Organisation agrees to co-operate with the Economic and social council in furnishing such information and rendering such assistance to theSecurity Council as that Council may request, including assistance incarrying out decisons of the Security Council for the maintenance orrestoration of international peace and security.
(*) &quot; Treaty Series No. 67 (1946),&quot; Cmd. 7015Assistance to the Trusteeship Council.The Organisation agrees to co-operate with the Trusteeship Council inthe carrying out of its functions and in particular agrees that it will, to thegreatest extent possible, render such assistance as the Trusteeship council may request, in regard to matters with which the Organisation is concerned.Article VIIINon-Self-Governing territories the Organisation agrees to co-operate with the members of the united nations concerned in giving effect to the principles and obligations set forth in Chapter XI of the Charter with regard to matters affecting the well-being and development of the peoples of non-self-governing territories.Article IXRelations with the International Court of Justice1. The Organisation agrees to furnish any information which may be requested by the International Court of Justice in pursuance of Article 34of the Statute of the Court. (4)2. The General Assembly authorises the Organisation to request advisoryopinions of the International Court of Justice on legal questions arisingwithin the scope of its activities other than questions concerning the mutualrelationships of the Organisation and the United Nations or other specialised agencies.3. Such request may be addressed to the Court by the Assembly, orby the Council acting in pursuance of an authorisation by the Assembly.4. When requesting the International Court of Justice to give an advisory opinion, the Organisation shall inform the Economic and social council of the request. -Article XPersonnel arrangements. The United Nations and the Organisation recognise that the eventualdevelopment of a single unified international civil service is desirable fromthe standpoint of effective administrative co-ordination, and, with this end in view, agree to develop common personnel standards, methods andarrangements designed to avoid serious discrepancies in terms and conditionsof employment, to avoid competition in recruitment of personnel, and tofacilitate interchange of personnel in order to obtain the maximum benefit from their services.2. The United Nations and the Organisation agree to co-operate to thefullest extent possible in achieving these ends and in particular they agree to (a) participate in the International Civil Service Advisory Board estab-lished for the purpose of contributing to the improvement of recruitment and related phases of personnel administration in all of the international organisations(b) consult together concerning other matters relating to the employmentof their officers and staff, including conditions of service, duration of appointments, classification, salary scales and allowances, retire-ment and pension rights and staff regulations and rules with a viewto securing as much uniformity in these matters as shall be foundpracticable;
11205(c) co-operate in the interchange of personnel, when desirable, on atemporary or permanent basis, making due provision for theretention of seniority and pension rights;(f?) co-operate in the establishment and operation of suitable machineryfor the settlement of disputes arising in connexion with theemployment of personnel and related matters.Article XIr Statistical services. The United Nations and the Organisation agree to strive formaximum co-operation, the elimination of all undesirable duplicationbetween them, and the most efficient use of their technical personnel intheir respective collection, &apos; analysis, publication and dissemination of statistical information. They agree to combine their efforts to secure thegreatest possible usefulness and utilisation of statistical information and to minimise the burdens placed upon national Governments and other organisa-tions from which such information may be collected.2. The Organisation recognises the United Nations as the central agency for the collection, analysis, publication, standardisation and improvement of statistics serving the general purposes of international organisations.3. The United Nations recognises the Organisation as the appropriate&apos;agency for the collection, analysis, publication, standardisation and improve-ment of statistics within its. special sphere, without prejudice to the rightof the United Nations to concern itself with such statistics so far as theymay be essential for its own purposes or for the improvement of statisticsthroughout the world.4. It is recognised as desirable that the collection of statistical information should not be duplicated by the United Nations or any of the specialised agencies whenever it is practicable for any of them to utiliseinformation or materials which another may have available.5. In order to build up a central collection of statistical information for general use, it is agreed that data supplied to the Organisation for incorporation in its basic statistical series or special reports should, so faras practicable, be made available to the United Nations on request:Article XIIAdministrative and Technical services. The United Nations and the Organisation recognise the desirability,in the interest of administrative and technical uniformity and of the most efficient use of personnel and resources, of avoiding, whenever possible, theestablishment and operation of competitive or overlapping facilities and services among the United Nations and the specialised agencies.2. Accordingly, the United Nations and the Organisation agree to consult together concerning the establishment and use of common admini-strative and technical services and facilities in addition to those referredto in Articles X, XI and XIII, in so far as the establishment and use of such services may from time to time be found practicable and appropriate.3. Arrangements shall be made between the United Nations and theOrganisation in regard to the registration and deposit of official documents.4. Officials of the Organisation shall have the right to use the laissez-yasser of the United Nations in accordance with special arrangements to be negotiated between the Secretary-General of the United Nations and thecompetent authorities of the Organisation.
Budgetary and Financial arrangements. The Organisation recognises the desirability of establishing close. budgetary and financial relationships with the United Nations in order thatthe administrative operations of the United Nations and of the specialised agencies shall he carried out in the most efficient and economical mannerpossible, and that the maximum measure of co-ordination and uniformitywith respect to these operations shall &quot;be secured.2. The following arrangements shall govern budgetary and financial -relationships between the United Nsstions and the Organisation:  (a) In the preparation of the budgetary estimates of the Organisation,the Secretariat of the Organisation shall consult with theSecretary-General of the United Nations with a view to achieving,in so far as practicable, uniformity in presentation of the budgetsof the United Nations and of the specialised agencies for thepurpose of providing a basis for comparison of the several budgets.(&amp;) The Organisation agrees to transmit its budget or budgetaryestimates to the United Nations by 1st July of the preceding year or such other date as may be agreed upon by the United nations and the Organisation. The General Assembly shall examine thebudget or budgetary estimates of the Organisation and may make recommendations to it c-oneerning any item or items contained therein.(c) Representatives of the Organisation shall be entitled to participate,without vGte, hi the deliberations of the General Assembly or any committee thereof or established by it at all times when the budget of the Organisation or general administrative or financial questions affecting the Organisation are under consideration.(d) The United Nations may undertake the collection of contributions from those members of the Organisation which are also membersof the United Nations in accordance with such arrangements asmay be defined by a later agreement between the United nations and the Organisation,(c) The United Nations shall, upon its own initiative, or upon therequest of the Organisation, arrange for studies to be undertakenconcerning other financial and fiscal questions of interest to theOrganisation and to other specialised agencies with a view to theprovision of common services and the securing of uniformity insuch matters.(/) The Organisation 3grees to conform, as far as may be practicable, tostandard practices and forms recommended by the United Nations.Article XIVFinancing of Special services. In the event of the Organisation being faced with the necessity ofincurring substantial extra expense as a result of any request which theUnited Nations may make for special reports, studies or assistance inaccordance with Articles V, VI, or VII, or with other provisions of thisAgreement, consultation shall take place with a view to determining themost equitable manner in which such expense shall be borne.2. Consultation between the United Nations and the Organisation shallsimilarly take place with a view to making such arrangements as may befound equitable for covering the costs of central administrative, techincal or fiscal services or facilities or other special assistance provided by theUnited Nations.
Article XVInter-Agency agreements the Organisation agrees to inform the Economic and Social Council ofthe nature and scope of any formal agreement contemplated and to notify the Council of the conclusion of any formal agreement between the Organisa-tion and any other specialised agency, inter-governmental organisations, ornon-governmental organisations.v, Article XVILiaison1. The United Nations and the Organisation agree to the foregoing provisions in the belief that they will contribute to the maintenance of effective liaison between the two organisations. They affirm their intentionof taking whatever further measures may be necessary to make this liaisonfully effective.2. The liaison arrangements provided for in the foregoing articles ofthis Agreement apply as far as appropriate to the relations between suchbranch or regional offices as may be established by the two organisationsas well as between their central machinery.Article XVIIImplementation of the agreement the  Secretary-General of the  United Nations and the appropriate authority of the Organisation may enter into such supplementary arrange-ments for the implemenbation of this Agreement as may be found desirable.Article XVIII   .RevisionThis Agreement shall be subject to revision by agreement between theUnited Nations and the Organisation.Article XIXEntry into force this Agreement shall come into force on its approval by the general assembly of the United Nations and the Assembly of the Organisation.Convention for the Establishment of the Inter-governmental maritime consultative organisation the States parties to the present Convention hereby establish the Inter-governmental Maritime Consultative Organisation (hereinafter referred to&quot;as &quot;the Organisation&quot;).Part I. Purposes of the organisation article 1The purposes of the Organisation are: (a) to provide machinery for co-operation among Governments in thefield of governmental regulation and practices relating to technical matters of all kinds affecting shipj)ing engaged in international trade, and to encourage the general adoption of the highestpracticable standards in matters concerning maritime safety and efficiency of navigation;
(b) to encourage the removal of discriminatory action and unnecessaryrestrictions by Governments affecting&apos; shipping engaged in inter-national trade so as to promote the availability of shipping services to the commerce, of the world without discrimination; assistance and encouragement given by a Government for the developmentof its national shipping and for purposes of security does not initself constitute discrimination, provided that such assistance and encouragement is not based on measures designed to restrict thefreedom of shipping of all flags to take part in international trade;(c) to provide for the consideration by the Organisation of matterscerning unfair restrictive practices by shipping concerns inaccordance with Part II;(d) to provide for the consideration by the Organisation of any matters concerning shipping that may be referred to it by any organ orspecialised agency of the United Nations;(e) to provide for the exchange of information among Governments on matters under consideration by the Oi&apos;ganisation.Part II. FunctionsArticle 2The functions of the Organisation shall be consultative and advisory.. . Article 8In order to achieve the purposes set out in Part I, the functions of theOrganisation shall be: r(a) subject to the provisions of Article 4, to consider and make recom-mendations upon matters arising under Article 1 (a), (6) and (c)that may be remitted to it by members, by any organ or specialised agency of the United Nations or by any other inter-governmentalorganisation or upon matters referred to it under Article 1 (d);(b) to provide for the drafting of conventions, agreements, or other suitable instruments, and to recommend these to governments and to inter-governmental organisations, and to convene suchconferences as may be necessary;(c) to provide machinery for consultation among members and theexchange of information among Governments.Article 4In those matters which appear to the Organisation capable of settlementthrough the normal processes of international shipping business the Organisa-tion shall so recommend. When, in the opinion of the Organisation, any matter concerning unfair restrictive practices by shipping concerns isincapable of settlement through the normal processes of international shippingbusiness, or has in fact so proved, and provided it shall first have been thesubject of direct negotiations between the Members concerned, the Organisa-tion shall, at the request of one of those members, consider the matter.Part III__MembershipArticle 5Membership in the Organisation shall be open to all States, subject tothe provisions of Part III.
Article 8Any State not entitled to become a member under Article 6 or 7 may applythrough the Secretary-General of the Organisation to become a member and shall be admitted as a member upon its becoming a party to theConvention in accordance with the provisions of Article 57, provided that,opaia the recommendation of the Council, its application has been approvedby two-thirds of the members other than associate-members.Article 9Any territory or group of territories to which the Convention has beenmade applicable under Article 5S, by the member having responsibility forits international relations or by the United Nations, may become an associate-member of the Organisation by notification in writing given by such member or by the United Nations, as the case may be, to the Secretary-General ofthe United Nations.Article 10An associate-member shall have the rights and obligations of a memberwader the Convention except that it shall not have the right to vote in theAssembly or be eligible for membership on the Council or on the MaritimeSafety Committee and subject to this the word &apos;&apos; member &apos;&apos; in the convention shall he deemed to inelude associate-member unless the context otherwise requires.Article 11No State or territory may become or remain a member of the Organisationcontrary to a resolution of the General Assembly of the United Nations.Part IY. OrgansArticle 12The Organisation shall consist of an Assembly, a Council, a MaritimeSafety Committee, and such subsidiary organs as the Organisation may atany time consider necessary; and a Secretariat.Part Y. The AssemblyArticle 13The Assembly shall consist of all the members.Article 14Begular sessions of the Assembly shall take place once every 2 years.-Extraordinary sessions shall be convened after a notice of 60 days wheneverMembers of the United Nations may become members of the Organisa-tfom by becoming parries to the Convention in accordance with the provisionsof Article 57.Article 7States not members of the United Nations which have been invitedto send representatives to the United Nations Maritime Conference convenedGeneva on 19th February, 1948, may become members by becomingJ parties to the Convention in accordance with the provisions of Article 57.
one-third of the members give notice to the Secretary-General that they desire a session io he arranged, or at any time if deemed necessary by theCouncil, after a notice of 60 days.   -Article 15A majority of the members other than associate-members shall constitute a quorum for the meetings of the Assembly.Article 16 *The functions of the Assembly shall be (a) to elect at each regular session from among its members, other thanassoeiate-members, its President and 2 Viee-Presidenis who shallhold office until the nest regular session;(6) to determine its own rules of procedure except as otherwise provided in the Convention;(c) to establish any temporary or, upon recommendation of the Council,permanent subsidiary bodies i  may consider to be necessary;(d) to elect the members to be represented on the Council, as provided in Article 17, and on the. Maritime Safety Committee as provided in Article 28;(e) to receive and consider tee reports of the Council, and to decide upon any question referred to it by the Council;(j) to vote the budget and determine the financial arrangements of theOrganisation, in accordance with Part- TX;(g) to review the expenditures and approve the accounts of die Organisa-tion;(h) to perform the functions of the Organisation, provided that in matters relating to Article 8 (a) and (b), the Assembly shall refer suchmatters to the Council for formulation by it of any recoiiiinenda-tions or instruments thereon; provided further that any recom-mendations or instruments -submitted to the Assembly by theCouncil and not accepted by the Assembly shall be referred backto the Conneil for further consideration with such observations asthe Assembly may make;(i) to recommend to members for adoption regulations concerning maritimesafety, or amendments to such regulations, which have been referred to it by the Maritime Safety Committee through theCouneil;(;) to refer to the Council for consideration or decision any matters withinthe scope of the Organisation, except that the functioa of making recommendations tinder paragraph (i) of this Article shall not be delegated.Part YI__The CouncilArticle 17The Couneil shall consist of 16 members and shall be composed asfollows:  (a) six shall be Governments of the nations with the largest interest in providing international shipping services;(b) six shall be Governments of other nations with the largest interestin international sea-borne trade;(c) two shall be elected by the Assembly from among the Governmentsof nations having a substantial interest in providing internationalshipping services; and
(rf) Two shall be elected by the Assembly from among the Government.  of nations having a substantial interest in international sea-bornetrade.In accordance with the principles set forth in this article the first council shall be constituted as provided in Appendix I to the present Convention.Article 18Except as provided in Appendix I to the present Convention, the Council.shall determine, for the purpose of Article 17 (a), the members, Governments-&apos;0bf nations with the largest interest in providing international shipping services, and shall also determine; for the purpose of Article 17 (c), themembers, Governments of&quot;nations having a substantial interest in providingsuch services. Such determinations shall be made by a majority vote ofthe Council, including the concurring votes of a majority of the membersrepresented on the Council under Article 17 (a) and (c). The Council shallfurther determine, for the purpose of Article 17 (b), the members, Govern-ments of nations with the largest interest in international sea-borne trade.Each Council shall make these determinations at a reasonable time before each regular session of the Assembly.Article 19Members represented on the Council in accordance with Article 17 shallhold office until the end of the next regular session of the Assembly.Members shall be eligible for re-election.Article 20(a) The Council shall elect its Chairman and adopt its own rules ofprocedure except as otherwise provided in the Convention.(b) Twelve members of the Council shall constitute a quorum.(c) The Council shall meet upon one month&apos;s notice as often as may benecessary for the efficient discharge of its duties upon the summons of itsChairman or upon request by not less than 4 of its members. It shall meet at such places as may be convenient.Article 21The Council shall invite any member to participate, without vote, in its deliberations on any matter of particular concern to that member.Article 22(a) The Council shall receive the recommendations and reports of the maritime Safety Committee and shall transmit them to the Assembly and,when the Assembly is not in session, to the members for information,together with the comments and recommendations of the Council.(6) Matters within the scope of Article 29 shall be considered by theCouncil only after obtaining the views of the Maritime Safety Committeethereon.Article 23The Council, with the approval of the Assembly, shall appoint theSecretary-General. The Council shall also make provision for the appoint-ment of such other personnel as may be necessary, and determine the terms and conditions of service of the Secretary-General and other personnel,which terms and conditions shall conform as far as possible with those ofthe United Nations and its specialised agencies.
The Council shall make a report to the Assembly at each regular session on the work of the Organisation since the previous regular session of theAssembly.Article 25The Council shall submit to the Assembly the budget estimates and thefinancial statements of the Organisation, together with its comments andrecommendations.Article 26 *The Council may enter into agreements or arrangements covering the relationship of the Organisation with other organisations, as provided forin Part XII. Such agreements or arrangements shall be subject to approval by the Assembly.Article 27Between sessions of the Assembly, the Council shall perform all thefunctions of the Organisation, except the function of making recommenda-tions under Article 16 (i).Part YII. Maritime Safaty CommitteeArticle 28(a) The Maritime Safety Committee shall consist of 14 members elected by the Assembly from the members, Governments of those nations having an important interest in maritime safety, of which not less than 8 shall bethe largest ship-owning nations, and the remainder shall be elected so asto ensure adequate representation of members, Governments of other nations with an important interest in maritime safety, such as nations interested inthe supply of large numbers of crews or in the carriage of large numbers ofberthed and unberthed passengers, and of major geographical areas.(6) Members shall be elected for a term of 4 years and shall be eligiblefor re-election.Article 29(a) The Maritime Safety Committee shall have the duty of considering any matter within the scope of the Organisation and concerned with aidsto navigation, construction and equipment of vessels, manning from a safetystandpoint, rules for the prevention of collisions, handling of dangerouscargoes, maritime safety jirocedures and requirements, hydrographicinformation, log-books and navigational records, marine casualty investiga-tion, salvage and rescue, and any other matters directly affecting maritimesafety.(b) The Maritime Safety Committee, shall provide machinery forperforming any duties assigned to it by the Convention, or by the Assembly,or any duty within the scope of this article which may be assigned to it byany other inter-governmental instrument.(c) Having regard to the provisions of Part XII, the Maritime SafetyCommittee shall have the duty of maintaining such close relationship withother inter-governmental bodies concerned with transport and communica-tions as may further the object of the Organisation in promoting maritimesafety and facilitate the co-ordination of activities in the fields of shipping,aviation, telecommunications and meteorology with respect to safety andrescue.
article 30The Maritime Safety Committee, through the Council, shall -(a) submit to the Assembly at its regular sessions proposals made bymembers for safety regulations or for amendments to existingsafety regulations, together with its comments or recommenda-tions thereon;(6) report to the Assembly on the work of the Maritime SafetyCommittee since the previous regular session of the Assembly.Article 31The Maritime Safety Committee shall meet once a year and at other times upon request of any 5 of its members. It shall elect its officers once a year and shall adopt its own rules of procedure. A majority of its members shall constitute a quorum.Article 32The Maritime Safety Committee shall invite any member to participate,without vote, in its deliberations on any matter of particular concern tothat member.Part YIII. The SecretariatArticle 33The Secretariat shall comprise the Secretary-General, a Secretary ofthe Maritime Safety Committee and such staff as the Organisation may require. The Secretary-General shall be the chief administrative officer ofthe Organisation, and shall, subject to the provisions of Article 23, appoint the above-mentioned personnel.- Article 34The Secretariat shall maintain all such records as may be necessary forthe efficient discharge of the functions of the Organisation and shall prepare,collect and circulate the papers, documents, agenda, minutes and informa-tion that may be required for the work of the Assembly, the Council, the maritime Safety Committee, and such subsidiary organs as the organisaion may establish.Article 35The Secretary-General shall prepare and submit to the Council thefinancial statements for each year and the budget estimates on a biennialbasis, with the estimates for each year shown separately.Article 36The Secretary-General shall keep members informed with respect to theactivities of the Organisation. Each member may appoint one or morerepresentatives for the purpose of communication with the Secretary-General.Article 37In the performance of their duties the Secretary-General and the staffshall not seek or receive instructions from any Government or from any authority external to the Organisation. They shall refrain from any actionwhich might reflect on their position as international officials. each member on its part undertakes to respect the exclusively international character of the responsibilities of the Secretary-General and the staff andnot to seek to influence them in the discharge of their responsibilities.
The Secretary-General shall perform such other tasks as may be assigned to him by the Convention, the Assembly, the Council and the maritime Safety Committee.Part IX. FinancesArticle 39Each member shall bear the salary, travel and other expenses of itsown delegation to the Assembly and of its representatives on the Cou&quot;^;l,the Maritime Safety Committee, other committees and subsidiary bodies:Article 40The Council shall consider the financial statements and budget estimatesprepared, by the Secretary-General and submit them to the Assembly withits comments and recommendations.Article 41(a) Subject to any agreement between the Organisation and the united nations, the Assembly shall review and approve the budget estimates.(b) The Assembly shall apportion the expenses among the members inaccordance with a scale to be fixed1 by it after consideration of the proposalsof the Council thereon.Article 42Any member which fails to discharge its financial obligation to theOrganisation within one year from the date on which it is due shall haveno vote in the Assembly, the Council, or the Maritime Safety Committeeunless the Assembly, at its discretion, waives this provision.Part X.-Voting.   Article 43The following provisions shall apply to voting in the Assembly, theCouncil and the Maritime Safety Committee: -(it) Each member shall have one vote.(b) Except as otherwise provided in the Convention or in any inter-national agreement which confers functions on the Assembly, theCouncil, or the Maritime Safety Committee, decisions of theseorgans shall be by a majority vote of the members present and voting and, for decisions where a two-thirds majority vote isrequired, by a two-thirds majority vote of those present.(c)&quot; For the purpose of the Convention, the phrase &quot; members presentand voting &apos;&apos; means &apos;&apos; members present and casting an affirmativeor negative vote.&quot; Members which abstain from voting shall beconsidered as not voting.Part XI__Headquarters of the organisation article 44(a) The headquarters of the Organisation shall be established in London.(b) The Assembly may by a two-thirds majority vote change the site ofthe headquarters if necessary.(c) The Assembly may hold sessions in any place other than the head-quarters if the Council deems it necessary.
Part XII.-Relationship with the United Nations and other Organisations. . Article   45The Organisation shall be brought into relationship with the united nations in accordance with Article .57 of the Charter of the United nations as the specialised.agency in the field of shipping. This relationship shall beeffected through an agreement with the United Nations under Article 63&apos;ofthe Charter of the United Nations, which agreement shall be concluded as provided in Article 26. &quot;&apos;-    1 &apos;;-&quot; -Article 46The Organisation shall co-operate with any specialised agency of theUnited Nations in matters which may be the common concern of theOrganisation and of such specialised agency, and shall consider such matters and act with respect to them in accord with such specialised agency.Article 47The Organisation may, on matters within its scope, co-operate with otherinter-governmental organisations which are not specialised agencies of theUnited Nations, but whose interests and activities are related to the purposesof the Organisation. article 48The Organisation may, on matters within its scope, make suitable arrange-ments for consultation and co-operation with non-governmental inter-national organisations.Article 49Subject to approval by a two-thirds majority vote of the Assembly, theOrganisation may take over from any other international organisations,governmental or non-governmental, such functions, resources and obligationswithin the scope of the Organisation as may be transferred to the Organisa-tion by international agreements or by mutually acceptable arrangementsentered into between competent authorities of the respective organisations.Similarly, the Organisation may take over any administrative functions whichare within its scope and which have been entrusted to a Government underthe terms of any international instrument.Part XIII. Legal Capacity, Privileges and Immunities-Article 50The legal capacity, privileges and immunities to be accorded- to, or inconnexion with, the Organisation shall be derived from and governed bythe General Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the. specialised agencies approved by the General Assembly of the United Nations oh21st November, 1947, subject to such modifications as may be set forth inthe final (or revised) text of the Annex approved by the Organisation inaccordance with Sections 36 and 38 of the said General Convention.Article 51&apos;   Pending its accession to the said General Convention in respect of thei Organisation, each member undertakes to apply the provisions of Appendix. IIto the present Convention. .&apos; ?35326 c* 3
Part XIY.-AmendmentsArticle 52Texts of proposed amendments.to the Convention shall be communicated by the Secretary-General to members at least 6 months in advance. oftheir consideration by the Assembly. Amendments shall be adopted by a two-.thirds majority vote of the Assembly, including the concurring votes of a majority of the members represented on the Council. Twelve monthsafter its acceptance by two-thirds of the members of the Organisation, otherthan associate-members, each amendment shall come into force for amembers except those which, before it comes into force, make a declaration that they do not accept the amendment. The Assembly may by a two-thirds majority vote determine at the time of its adoption that, an amendment isof such a nature that any member which has made such a declaration andwhich does not accept the amendment within a period of 12 months afterthe amendment comes into force shall, upon the expiration of this period,cease to be a party to the Convention.   . Article 53Any amendment adopted under Article 52 shall be deposited with theSecretary-General of the United&apos; Nations, who will immediately forward acopy of the amendment to all members.&quot;      &quot; Article 54A declaration or acceptance under Article 52 shall be made by the communication of an instrument to the Secretary-General for deposit withthe Secretary-General of the United Nations. The Secretary-General willnotify members of the receipt of any such instrument and of the date whenthe amendment enters into force.Part XY.-InterpretationArticle 55Any question or dispute concerning the interpretation or application ofthe Convention shall be referred for settlement to the Assembly, or shallbe settled in such other manner as the parties.to the dispute agree. nothing in this article shall preclude the Council or the Maritime Safety Committeefrom settling any such question or dispute that may arise during the exerciseof their functions.Article 56Any legal question which cannot be settled as provided in Article 55 shallbe referred by the Organisation to the International Court of Justice for an advisory opinion in accordance with Article 96 of the Charter of the united nations.Part XYI.-Miscellaneous provisions article 57Signature and AcceptanceSubject to the provisions of Part III the present Convention shall remain open for signature or acceptance and States may become parties to theConvention by:  &apos;
(a) signature without reservation as to acceptance;(b) signature subject to acceptance followed by acceptance;or(c) acceptance.Acceptance shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument with theSecretary-General of the United Nations!Article 58i Territories(a) Members may make a declaration at any time that their participation in the Convention includes all or a group or a single one of the territories for whose international relations they are responsible.(ft) The Convention does not apply to territories for whose international relations members are responsible unless a declaration to that effect has been made on their behalf under the provisions ofparagraph (a) of this article.(c) A declaration made under paragraph (a) of this article shall becommunicated to the Secretary-General of the United nations and a copy of it will be forwarded by him to all States invitedto the United Nations Maritime Conference and to such other states as may have become members.(fZ) In cases where under a trusteeship agreement the United Nationsis the administering authority, the United Nations may acceptthe Convention on behalf of one, several, or all of the trustterritories in accordance with the procedure set forth in Article 57.Article 59Withdrawal(a) Any member may withdraw from the Organisation by writtennotification given to the Secretary-General of the United Nations, who will immediately inform the other members and the Secretary-General of theOrganisation of such notification. Notification of Withdrawal may be given at any time after the expiration of 12 months from the date on which theConvention has come into force. The withdrawal shall take effect uponthe expiration of 12 months from the date on which such written notificationis received by the Secretary-General of the United Nations.(6) The application of the Convention to a territory or group of territories under Article 58 may at any time be terminated by written notificationgiven to the Secretary-General of the United Nations by the memberresponsible for its international relations or, in the case of a trust territory of which the United Nations is the administering authority, by the united nations. The Secretary-General of the United Nations will immediatelyinform all members and the Secretary-General of the Organisation of suchnotification. The notification shall take effect upon the expiration of 12months from the date on which it is received b3&apos; the Secretary-General ofthe United Nations.Part XYII.-En+ry into ForceArticle 60The present Convention shall enter into force on the date when 21 States,of which 7 shall each have a total tonnage of not less than 1 million grosstons of shipping, have become parties to the Convention in accordance with article 57.
Article 63The United Nations is authorised to effect registration of the convention as soon as it comes into force.In witness whereof the undersigned being duly authorised by theirrespective Governments for that purpose have signed the present Convention!Done at Geneva this 6th day of March, 1948.[Here follow the signatures]Appendix I(Referred to in Article 17)Composition of the First CouncilIn accordance with the principles set forth in Article 17 the first council shall be constituted as follows:  (a) The 6 members under Article 17 (a) being-Greece. Sweden.Netherlands.                                    United Kingdom.Norway.                                          United States.(6) The 6 members under Article 17 (/j) being Argentina. Canada.Australia. France.Belgium. India.(c) Two members to be elected by the Assembly under Article 17 (c)from a panel nominated by the 6 members named in para-graph (a) of this Appendix.(d) Two members elected by the Assembly under Article 17 (d) from among the members having a substantial interest in internationalsea-borne trade.The Secretary-General of the United Nations will inform all Statesinvited to the United Nations Maritime Conference and such other states as may have become members, of the date when each State becomes partyto the Convention, and also of the date on which the Convention entersinto force.Article 62The present Convention, of which the English, French and Spanis?tests are equally authentic, shah be deposited with the Secretary-Generalof the United Nations, who will transmit certified copies thereof to eachof the States invited to the United Nations Maritime Conference and to such other States as may have become members.
14730 Wt. 752/65 5/48 f.o.p. 353262Appendix II &apos;(Referred to in Article SI)Legal Capacity, Privileges and ImmunitiesThe following provisions on legal capacity, privileges and immunities shallbe applied by members to, or in connexion with, the Organisation pendingtheir accession to the General Convention on Privileges and Immunities of^Specialised Agencies in respect of the Organisation:Section 1The Organisation shall enjoy in the territory of each of its members suchlegal capacity as is necessary for the fulfilment of its purposes and theexercise of its functions.Section 2(a) The Organisation shall enjoy in the territory of each of its memberssuch privileges and immunities as are necessary for the lulSLaient of itspurposes and the exercise of its functions.(6) Representatives of members, including alternates and advisers and officials and employees of the Organisation, shall similarly enjoy suchprivileges and immunities as are necessary for the independent, exercise oftheir functions in connexion with the Organisation.Section 3In applying the provisions of Sections 1 and 2 of this Appendix, themembers shall take into account as far as possible the standard clauses ofthe General Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the specialised agencies.


</content>
</cab>
