<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/28/0 images: 339-341</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OP HiS  BRITANNIC  gSJESWS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  July 1918SECRET Copy No. 3CP. (48) 18719th July, 1948CABINETNEWFOUNDLAND:   CONSTITUTIONAL position memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commoxweaiite: relations in his memorandum of 20th March, 1947 (CP. (47) 98)r my predecessorreferred to the steps which were to be taken to enable the people of Newfoundlandto choose their future form of Government. My eoBeaguss may Eke to know the developments which have since occurred.2. The first referendum took place in Newfoundland on 3rd June last withthe following results : (1) For the continuation of Government by Commission for a period of5 years 21.944 votes.(2) For Confederation with Canada 63,110 votes.(3) For restoration of Responsible Government as It existed in 1933 69,230 votes.Thus the referendum was inconclusive, since no form of Government secured an absolute majority of the votes cast.3. A second referendum is therefore necessary and will be held on 22nd July.On this occasion the form of Government which secured the lowest vote (i.e..Commission Government) will disappear. The choice will thus be betweenResponsible Government and Confederation with Canada.4. At my request, the Governor of Newfoundland (Sir Gordon Macdonald)visited London earlier this month with the Commissioner for Justice (aNewfoundlander). The discussions which they had here with the Under-Secretaryof State, officials of the Commonwealth Relations Office and ms (in some of whichthe Canadian High Commissioner joined) showed that no real difficulties ofprocedure are likely to arise if the forthcoming vote is in favour of the restorationof Responsible Government.In that event, the 1933 Constitution will be revived by Letters Patent, whichmust be laid before Parliament for a period of twenty-one days, and are subjectto a negative resolution. When that period has expired, the Governor will arrange for the holding of a General Election. On learning the result of theelection, he will ask the leader of the majority party to form a Government.The new Government should be able to take over on or about 1st January next.5. Should there be a substantial majority in favour of Confederation with canada, no major complication should arise, although the change-over wouldbe more protracted than in the case of a return to Responsible Government.Whatever the detailed machinery for bringing Newfoundland within the confederation, legislation will be required by Parliament in London: we may hope that it would not be controversial, though if there should be disorder in newfoundland see paragraph 9 below this might affect the prospect. Weare already discussing procedure on a provisional basis with the canadian government.6. But it is the Governor&apos;s considered view that if there should be a majorityfor Confederation, it is almost certain to be a narrow one. - If that happens,it will be for Canada to decide whether or not she regards the majority as large35640
enough to justify the entry into Confederation of a new Province with so large a dissentient minority. This possibility, and its consequences, were discussed with Sir Gordon macdonald; and they are now being discussed in Ottawa bythe United Kingdom High Commissioner with the Canadian authorities. On our side, we are making it clear to the Canadians that (1) we should regard any majority, no matter how small, as conclusive: but(2) we recognise that there are two parties to Confederation and the decision must, therefore, primarily rest with Canada.7. I think it unlikely that the Canadian Government will reach a decision until after the referendum.8. If Canada should decide to proceed with the admission of Newfoundlandinto Confederation, we must proceed as rapidly as possible with the necessarylegal steps : but owing to Parliamentary complications in Canada it is unlikelythat they can all be completed before 1st April, 1949. If Canada decide notto proceed, we shall have no alternative but to restore Responsible Government.It will then be for Newfoundland to decide for herself, through her Parlia-mentary institutions, whether to retain Responsible Government or to seek entryat some later date into Confederation.9. There is one final point. The Governor has expressed to me the viewthat, especially if there should be a close contest, there is a serious risk of civildisturbance in the Island. In his view, this risk springs from the fact thatentry into the Confederation would be an irrevocable act to which a substantialminority of the people of Newfoundland would be permanently committed against their will. The danger, he feels, would be all the greater because the great number of the supporters of Responsible Government are concentrated in and around the capital, St. John&apos;s, whereas the supporters of Confederation arescattered throughout the country.10. As a precautionary measure, and after discussion with the PrimeMinister, I have thought it right to ask the First Lord of the Admiralty whether he can arrange for a warship to be available in Western Atlantic waters at thetime of the referendum and able to move in to St. John&apos;s at short notice oncall. I hope very much that in fact there will be no disturbances; but we mustbe prepared to maintain order so long as we are in charge of the Island.P. J. N.-B.Commonwealth Relations Office. S.W. 1,19th July, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
