<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/184/1 images: 5-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75) 76 COPY NO   8 28 July 1975CABINETDRAFT WHITE PAPER ON INFLATIONNote by the Secretary of the Cabinet1. A Group of Ministers, under the chairmanship of the PrimeMinister, has been overseeing the negotiations with the Confederation ofBritish Industry (CBI) and the Trades Union Congress (TUC) and also thepreparation of the White Paper which has to be published on Friday 11 July.2.        The Group cannot reach final recommendations to Cabinet until after meetings of the CBI and TUC General Council tomorrow, 9 July.The Prime Minister has however directed me to circulate the attached draftof the White Paper so that members of the Cabinet who are not on the ministerial Group may have a chance of reading it during the course oftomorrow.    This is however on the clear understanding that on a number of points, and in particular on the question of reserve powers, the Group hasnot yet reached final conclusions.    Their conclusions will be reported to cabinet on Thursday 10 July.    In the meantime special steps should betaken to ensure the confidentiality of this draft.Signed   JOHN hunt cabinet Office8 July 1975L0 HCRET
SECRETINFLATION1.   Inflation is the most serious economic problem facing the country.Our rate of inflation has been much higher in the 19-70&apos;s than in earlier periods and recently it has accelerated sharply.   In common with many countries we have experienced in the past 2 years a bigincrease in the rate at which costs and prices have risen.   like other countries we suffered in 1972/73 the great increase in thecost of imported-food and raw materials and in 1973/74 the even greater increase in oil prices which have cut back what is availableto us to maintain and improve our national standard of living.But whereas most other countries have succeeded in bringing down their rates of inflation, we have not.   Our prices are 25$ above those a year ago.   The figures for our competitors are nearer 10$,2.    This is unacceptable.   There is a strong belief throughout thecountry that the inflation must be curbed.   The Government is determined to achieve this, and believe they will have the support andco-operation of the whole nation in doing so.As the Chancellor said in his statement on 1 July,&quot;A sharp reduction in the ra.te of inflation is an over-riding priority for millions of our fellow citizens,particularly the housewives and pensioners.   It is alsoa pre-condition for the reduction of unemployment and theincrease in investment which the Government, the TUC andthe CBI all want to see.&quot;3.    The Government reject a solution to the problem of inflationwhich relies on the generation of large-scale unemployment and under-utilisation of our productive equipment.   This would be wasteful,socially evil and against our long-term economic interests.But if we continue with pay settlements at levels at and above 25$.we shall not match the performance of our rivals with whom we need toremain in competition if we are to survive.   The largest element inour prices, both on the home market and for exports, is the cost,direct or indirect, of domestic labour:   in other words, what we payourselves.   It is the rapid increase in labour costs which nowaccounts for much the greater part of our inflation.MrSECRET
40     The solution therefore lies in reducing our rate of increasein wages and salaries.   The Government, the TUC and CBI are agreedthat this rate should be brought down to a level which will ensurethat by the late summer of next year the year-on-year increase inprices will be no more than 10$.   They have also agreed on the pay limit needed to achieve this objective.   This is described in the succeeding paragraphs.-5.   The universal pay limit of  6 a week, and the other measureslinked with it, are a simple but rough and ready approach to the needfor pay restraint, which is appropriate to an emergency situation.The limit rightly gives preference to the low paid in a period ofnational difficulty.   It is not intended to be a long-term approach,and it will be essential to devise more just and flexible arrangementsfor controlling domestic inflation and preventing any resurgenceof present rates of price increase in the future.   It will be along step forward to reduce inflation to 10$, but further effortswill be needed to get down to the rates of our competitors, and staythere.- 6.   The Government realise that the sacrifices called for will not be-easy.   This applies particularly to the early months of the policybecause of the inflation already in the pipeline.   But the alternative is much worse.   A continuation of present rates of inflation would gravely damage the social and economic fabric of the nation and threatus with external bankruptcy.   To cure inflation by unemployment would cause widespread misery, industrial strife and the degenerationof our productive capacity.   The only sensible course is to exercisepay restraint and to reduce our domestic inflation without sacrificingour long-term economic goals.SECRET
THE LIMIT ON INCOMES8.     The Government have said &quot;that they are . determined to bring the rateof domestic inflation down to 10 per cent by the third quarter of1976 and to single figures by the end of 1976.9.     To achieve this the TUC have agreed that there should be a limit of  6 per v/eek on pay increases for those with incomes up to  10,000a year.   Those with -incomes of  10,000 or over should forego any increase for the present.   This is the maxinum increase in paycompatible with the objective of achieving the 10 per cent rate of inflation by the third quarter of 1976.   The CBI as well as the TUChave agreed to support the pay limit and they, like the TUC, willrecommend their members to adhere to it. ,10,   Annexed to this White Paper is a copy of the guidance which the tuc will be issuing to negotiators.   It sets out the requirements which should be observed by those implementing pay settlements overthe .12 months from 1 August.11.   Strict adherence to the  6 limit is crucial to the achievement of the objective.   If it is not observed the economy will be seriously damaged and we shall all suffer.    The Government will ensurestrict observance throughout the public sector.    Private sector employewill be expected similarly to observe the limit.    Furthermore theGovernment intend to introduce a number of measures to encouragecompliance with that limit.12.   The Government have already announced that in line with the limit on pay increases, increases on dividends must be limited to 10 percent.   An Order to give effect to this was made on 1 July,   -The powersnecessary to enforce this limit are already available to the government but under present legislation they expire on 31 March 1976 and theGovernment propose to ask Parliament to extend them for a further year.   The charges and profits of the self-employed will continueto be subject to the price control.5SECRET
COLLECTIVE BARGAINING13,     The Government have made and will continue to make every possible effort  &apos;to achieve the necessary restraint on incomes &quot;by consent.   They have said thatthey are opposed to criminal sanctions on work people.   It has been amplydemonstrated that these doii&apos;t work,   Nor do the Government favour detailedintervention in collective bargaining.   They are very glad therefore that it hasbeen possible to reach agreement with the TUC on new guidance to negotiatorswithin the framework of the Social Contract, which is consistent with the anti-inflation target,34.     However, neither the Government, the TUC nor the CBI believe that it wouldbe acceptable if de-centralised collective bargaining were to lead to acceleratinginflation.   The Government therefore propose to support the guidance given by the tuc to negotiators with effective sanctions.   These will include some further powers in the public sector to ensure that they can discharge fully their,responsibility for securing observance of the pay limit in that area,   ^They willalso take powers, which will be held in reserve and activated only by a fresh vote of Parliament, to introduce legal control over particular employers who do notobserve the limit.   They expect however that the recommendations made to their members by the TUC and CBI, together with the policy measures described below,will be sufficient to make that unnecessary^
&quot;THE pay limit and its application in the public sector the Government as Employer &apos; . &apos;       -15*   The government are directly involved as employer in pay settlements affecting 2 million people.   These include the civil ..service, the national health service and armed forces.   In these fields the government will of &quot;course ensure that settlements complywith the pay limit.16.   The government will &quot;be asking the review bodies for the armed forces, for. doctors and dentists&apos; remuneration, and for top salaries in the public sector, to comply in their recommendations with the pay limit.   It will also &quot;be necessary to suspend the operation of pay research in the non-industrial civil service for the period of thepolicy.Local authorities -. &apos;,million people.   Within this total the government is directly concernedwith pay settlements for teachers and the police.   But there is noother major group of local authority employees whose pay comes underdirect Ministerial control.   Nevertheless it is necessary that localauthorities should abide by the policy set out in this White Paper.18.   To this end the government will have discussions with the newjoint Consultative Council.   It will be a major item in the new approach that rate support grant payable to local authorities will be   jrestricted so that no increase in grant will be payable for expenditure which results from settlements in excess of the pay limit.   &quot;Moreoverlegislation will be brought before Parliament to enable the governmentfto restrict payment of rate support grant   to - individual localauthorities which do not observe the pay limit.,19.   /Ks regards the rate support grant settlement for next year,1976-77 j the calculation of the grant will be on the basis that pay settlements both in the remainder of this year   and in next yearconform to the pay limit.   No extra grant will be payable either inthe main settlement or in increase orders for 1976-77 on account ofsettlements which exceed the norm.   Furthermore the total of grantwill be calculated on the basis that there will be no increase in local authority staff beyond /present/ numbers.   And no allowance17.   Local authorities and public transport authorities employ 2*1-
will &quot;be made in any increase orders for 1976-77 for any :i nor ease in staff which 00cur during- the years]20.   In addition the Government will be prepared to use its powers ofcontrol over local authority borrowing, including access to thecapital market, to reduce the capital programmes of particular localauthorities, -if this proves necessary to offset any excess expenditureon pay settlements.21. [Finally , if there is a serious breakdox-m in the observance of the pay limits by local authorities, the Government will consider taking powersto impose Ministerial supervision on all major local authority pay settlements.]6SECRET
The nationalised industries22.     The Government intend that the policy should be strictlyapplied by the nationalised industries,by other public corporations and boards, and by G-overnment-owned companies.     To ensure this, theGovernment are holding discussions with the chairmen of the principalnationalised industries.   Together these industries are responsiblefor pay settlements affecting about two million people.23.     In accordance with this policy, the existing arrangements for financial control and budgeting will be strengthened so as toensure that no additional funds are made available to these industries in order to finance pay settlements outside the limit.In addition, any element in proposed price increases due to disregard of pay limits will be disallowed in the same way as is intended forthe private sector (see paragraph ?  below).   Thus, the consequenceof any excess pay settlement would be the institution of measures tosecure - offsetting cash reductions in the industry, which would be bound directly or indirectly to affect employment in the industry.
THE PAY LIMIT AI\TD ITS APPLICATION IN THE PRIVATE SECTOR24.     The Government have no direct control over, pay in the private sector.   Butthere is a legal price control over most goods and services produced for the home market.   Moreover the Government purchases a substantial part of the output ofsome industries and provide extensive assistance to industry.   This gives theGovernment a number of economic instruments with which to support the pay policy.An employer who adheres to the policy will not suffer but where pay settlementsare excessive the instruments will be applied.-The Price Code25.     The Government will not allow firms which make excessive pay settlements to reflect these settlements in higher prices to&apos; the consumer.   With every applicationto the Price Commission for a price increase, employers will have/to notify detailsof any pay settlement underlying the application.   The Government will advise theCommission whether settlements conform to the limit.  ^The arrangements fornotifying settlements to the Government are described in paragraph 32^,7   &quot;/here an employer breaks the pay limit the whole pay increase will be disallowed for price increases.   This disallowance, which will require new legislation, will applyeven if the employer is covered by one of the low profit safeguards in the PriceCode.   Similar arrangements, will be applied to nationalised industry prices.   a consultative document describing the proposed changes in detail will be publishedshortly.26.     From now on the Government, in handling applications for assistance underthe Industry Act 1972, will interpret the national interest as includingobservance of the pay limit.   The Government will not give discretionary assistance under the Industry Act to companies which have broken the pay limit.   7/hen it isin full operation the National Enterprise Board, in discharging its duties, willalso take these considerations into account.27. The Government will also take account of a firm&apos;s record of observance of the pay limit in its general purchasing policy and in the awarding of contracts.8SECRET
The Self-Employed28.   Last year self-employed people whose expenses amount tolass than 10 per cent of turnover were exempted from thePrice Code.   They will now he brought hack under the Code.   Anumber of self-employed groups who are remunerated from public fundsdoctors, dentists, chemists, opticians and suhpostmasters - willcontinue to be outside the Price Code, but in settling their remuneration the Government will take account of the pay limit.
^&quot;Rerorve Powers &quot;in &quot;the Private! Sector29*    Bxe Government trust that the measures&apos; described above vri.ll be adequate to secure compliance with the policy by private sectoremployers.   As stated above, the Government will be talcing furtherpothers to reinforce its ability to secure full observance of thepolicy throxighout the public sector.   If however in the case of theprivate sector the Government were to find that the policy needed tobe enforced by applying a legal power of compulsion to individual employers who&apos;break the limit, they would not hesitate to do this.30.   In order that the Government should be in a position to do this they propose to invite Parliament to enact reserve powers which, ifapplied in particular cases, would make it illegal for the employer to exceed the pay limit.   These powers ireuld be activated by statutory instrument recruiring Affirmative Resolution by both Houses ofParliament if it became clear that the pay limit was being endangeredwith resultant unfairness to the great majority of those who werekeeping to the limit.]or (in the event of Ministers&apos; deciding to go for reserve powerscovering both public and private sector employers)[reserve powers29A.   The Government trust that the measures described above will be adequate to secure compliance with the policy by all employers.   if however they T^ere to find that the policy needed to be enforcedby applying a legal power of compulsion they would not hesitate to do this.30A.   In order that the Government should be in a position todo this they propose to invite Parliament to enact reserve powers which if applied in particular cases, would make it illegal for the employer to exceed the pay limit.   These powers would be activatedby statutory instrument requiring Affirmative Resolution by bothHouses of Parliament if it became clear that the pay limit wasbeing endangered with resultant unfairness to the great majority ofthose who were keeping to the limit.]9a
PROGRESS OP THE POLICY31.     It is not enough to have a policy.   It must he complied with.   the pay limit must be given effect in pay settlements and the effect of lowerpay increases must be carried through to prices.   The Government need toknow that this is happening before they can for example take reflationarymeasures or introduce the special price restraint programme on essentialsdescribed in paragraph 38.32.     The Government intend therefore to undertake jointly with the tuc and CBI a regular review of developments in the economic situation inorder to determine progress towards the objectives of this policy.   Forthis purpose the parties will need to be accurately informed of the truefacts on pay settlements and the Government propose to require notificationby employers of major pay settlements.   This monitoring will be carriedout as an extension of the Deps.department of Employments existing activities.The pay of 90 per cent of employees is determined by settlements covering1,000 or more and it is intended to secure information about all suchsettlements on a consistent basis.   [The Government will therefore be seeking compulsory powers to oblige employers to notify the details ofintended pay settlements.]33*     Not only will this information serve to keep the Government andthe community fully informed of compliance with the policy, it will alsobe used to support the Price Commission in the disallowance of any excessincreases in pay.10SECRET
PRICES AND THE PROTECTION OF THE CONSUMER34.   The government recognise and share the concern that if pay isrestrained prices must also he restrained.   They would like to beable to freeze prices but this is simply not possible..   At any time there are in the pipeline many increases in costs which are comingthrough in prices and this is particularly true at present following the big increases in pay and other costs of recent months.    It takestime for these costs to affect prices in the shops.    Similarly if pay increases are slowed down it takes some time before price increasesslow down also.   Nevertheless, if pay increases.do not slow down,there can never be a slow down in price increases.35.   Although the government cannot freeze prices they intend to takethe following measures to keep price increases to a minimum and toprotect the consumer. ./&apos;Price Controls .  %.36.   The government will continue the present strict price controlenforced by the Price Commission under the Price Code.   They willlegislate to extend the control powers for a further year beyond 31March 1976, when price control would have ended under the existing law.The price control already ensures that a lower rate of increase in pay is reflected in a lower rate of price increase.   However, particularly with present levels of unemployment, the government do not intend to push price control to the point where it would endanger employment and investment.Better Consumer Information37*   The government propose to encourage the expansion of the presentnetwork of consumer advice centres in local authority areas to assistconsumers who have complaints or queries about particular retail prices in their district.   The government will encourage more work on localprice comparisons indicating best value for money and accelerate theprogramme of price display and unit pricing.
Prices of essentials38,     Certain goods are of particular importance in family expenditure, and theeffect of inflation here can fall harshly on low-income families.   Once the pay limit is being effectively observed, the Government intend to ensure that therate of increase of prices of a range of such goods will be specially held back.^The CBI and the Retail Consortium have indicated that they will be prepared tosupport the G-overnment&apos;s objective and to begin immediate discussions with theGovernment on how to achieve this .7EITHER: -Fooji subsidie^s39.     The present subsidy programme saves over 6p in the   on food prices and benefits in particular the elderly and others on low incomes.   In due course food subsidies will have to be&apos; phased out and the Government had intended to start this phasing out early in 1976.   The phasing out will not now start during theperiod of this policy.  Jvleanwhile the amount of money provided for food subsidieswill remain at its present level.Rents40.     Local authority rents were frozen by the Government between March: 1974and March 1975, but increases are now in the pipeline because of earlier increases in pay and other inflationary costs.   In the Government&apos;s view it would be wrong to attempt to delay these increases.   The costs would just have to be borne inother ways by the ratepayer or taxpayer.   7/hat we must, now do is to tackle theproblem by breaking into the sequence of large pay increases followed by large rent increases.12SECRET
NOTE:   Ministers in misc 91 recommend that the total new expenditureon food/rent subsidies under these paragraphs should not exceed about 150 million in 1976-77 in view of the general public expenditure/public sector borrowing requirement position.   Paragraphs 39 and 40 oonoentrate thewhole sum on food subsidies:   paragraphs 39A and 40A divide the sum betweenfood and local authority rents.12ASECRETORFood Subsidies&quot;39A.. . The-present subsidy programme saves, over 6p in.the   on food prices ..and benefits in particular the elderly and others on low incomes.   TheChancellor of the Exchequer announced in the April Budget that it would benecessary to phase out the food subsidies over a period, starting early in1976.   As a contribution to protecting the living standards of low incomefamilies and the pensioners during the period of the policy the government propose to spend millionj more on food subsidies during 1976 then theamount provided for in the April Budget.Rents40A.     Local authority rents were frozen by the Government betweenMarch 1974 eJl&amp; March 19751 but increases are now in the pipeline because of pay increases and other inflationary costs.   During the period of the policy the Government propose to limit rent increases so that rents do not risefaster than prices generally.   This will mean that on average rent increasesnext spring should be of the order of 60p per week rather than  1 a week ormore.   The Government will provide an extra  80 million to meet the costof this.
Nationalised industry pricesill..    It has been necessary to make particularly steep increases innationalised industry prices this year because most of the industries were deeply in deficit.    The phasing out of these deficits is notyet complete.   However, the substantial progress already made, andthe fact that the pay limit provides for a lower rate of pay increase,together offer good prospects that the rate of price increase in the nationalised industries as a whole should be markedly lower nextyear.Import costshf2.     We must do all we can to keep down costs and prices which are within our own control.   Some prices, like the cost of imported oil,food and raw materials, are not within our control however.   A bigincrease in import prices would impose on us a further reduction ofour standard of living and it would then take longer for this policy_to._a.chieve- our inflation target&quot;; &apos;15SECRET
DEMAND JIAKAGEMSNT43.     It is essential that the policy set out in this 7/hite Paper should heassociated with an appropriate policy for -demand management.   The substantialcurrent account deficit, and the very large imbalance in central governmentfinancing, superimposed on the recent very rapid rate of domestic price inflation,together leave the Government no other alternative than to pursue a cautious demand management policy.   Expansion of the economy, when it comes, must be based on greatercompetitiveness of United Kingdom firms in world markets, and on the assurance- of adequate resources for investment without the risk of demand pressures inparticular sectors once more giving a stimulus to inflation.   Deliberate action bythe Government to increase domestic demand by boosting consumption levels, inadvance of the achievement of the inflation target and of a soundly-based externalposition, would be to repeat the policies of 1973.   The Government are determined toavoid a repetition of past mistakes, and will&quot; set their demand management policy to ensure that the growth of the economy in the medium term is founded on a properallocation of resources to exports and investment.44.    As the Government, the CBI and the TUC have constantly stressed, the UnitedKingdom must have an adequate level of productive investment, on which our futureliving standards depend.   If we are to secure this, w.e must be ready to -pay for it.In a mixed economy profits are the main way of financing investment in the private sector.   But in 1974, profits were at historically low levels, and the real profitsretained by companies were less than that needed just to finance the replacement ofexisting capital equipment and to maintain adequate stocks and work in progress.Accordingly the Government will take account in formulating its taxation, monetary and prices policies, of the need to avoid any deterioration in the prospects for future investment and employment.24SECRET
45*    A particular feature of the present situation is the need to contain the demands on resources made by the programmes of public expenditure.    The Government are engaged in reviewing public expenditurein the medium term as a matter of urgency, with a view to securing a continuance of the reduction of...the public sector borrowing requirementwhich was initiated in the April budget.45A.   However, as the Chancellor indicated in his statement on 1 July,the recent rate of inflation has emphasised the need not only to limitincreases in money earnings throughout the economy, but to look more carefully at the cash requirements of the public sector.   The presentsystem of planning and control of public expenditure puts the main emphasis on the volume of resources used rather than the cash cost and hassubstantial advantages, especially for control in the medium term.   Howeverat a time of rapid inflation, and with important changes in relativeprices, this system needs reinforcing in appropriate programmes by placing a limit on the amount of money which the Government are preparedto pay in the year ahead towards the purchase of the planned volume of resources.46.   Cash limits already -apply to a number of services financed by central government and they were recently extended to several constructionprogrammes in central and local government.   They are not a suitable .method of controlling services such as social security benefits whereexpenditure must depend on the rate of benefit and the number of claimants.But there is a range of expenditure where they can impose greater financialdiscipline and precision, and where they can contribute to counteringinflation by making it clear both to programme managers and to suppliersthat the Government&apos;s purchases of. goods and services will have to be cutback if prices rise too high.   Experience with the programmes to which cashlimits already apply have shown that their application needs careful prepartion to be effective.   Work is in hand to bring about the more   extendeduse of cash limits in 1976-77*
S&quot;XU&quot;fiFTMonetary Policy47.     The Government do not accept that the growth of the money supply in the past year and a half, which has been moderate, has been a factor in accelerating our rate of cost inflation.   It will however be important to ensure that in the period ahead the price targets which wehave set outselves are not endangered &quot;by too loose a control over theexpansion of bank credit.   The Government will therefore, by theappropriate use of the instruments affecting monetary factors, takewhatever steps are necessary to keep the growth of the money supplyunder   firm    control.   At the same time they will, though the Bank ofEngland&apos;s guidance to the banking system, see that priority in lendingis given to the essential sectors of the economy.16SECRET
S&apos; EC EE TCONCLUSION49.   The Government seek the support of the nation in breaking the inflation which threatens our economy.    The measures the Government,the TUC and the CBI are taking are designed to last right throughthe next pay round until price inflation has been brought down intosingle figures and we have reached agreement on how to arrange ouraffairs so as to avoid a resurgence.50. This is a plan to safeguard the standard of living.   If we don&apos;twork together to achieve it we shall get more unemployment, moresocial injustice, less investment, less public expenditure, lesscontrol of our own economy and our own destiny, more restrictionson us through distrust of our economy overseas.   If we do achieveit, we can look forward once again to a steady improvement in living standards.17SECRET
annex the GUIDELINES on PAY/This section may consist mainly of a reproduction of TUC guidelinesfrom a TUC document.   What follows is what would he contained in.the document if the guidelines were established not by the TUC but by theGovernment.^The Government requires negotiators to apply the following guidelinesin pay settlements coming into force on or after /T August^The Pay Limit2.   Increases in pay in the period should be limited to  6 a week per head for each full-time adult employee.   Increases to part-timers/and juveniles7 should be pro rata.3.   Negotiators may average the  6 per head among a negotiating groupso as to apply it.in a way which preserves any existing pay structurerecognised as equitable, but wherever possible the increase should be.applied simply in a flat rate form.   The increase should be applied asa straightforward supplement to earnings and should not flow through to overtime&apos; and other premium rates.   The limit of  6 per headrepresents the total increase however earnings are determined.High Incomes4.   Those whose incomes are at the levelof  10,000 or more a year should receive no increase at all.The 12 month Rule &quot;5.   The 12 month interval between principal pay increases must continueto apply, and no group should get any improvements less than a year after their previous increase.   Negotiators should not advance theiranniversary dates and settlements reached in accordance with theseguidelines should continue for the following 12 months.Other Improvements in Pay and Conditions6.   Negotiators would be expected to offset other improvements in pay and conditions against the pay figure except as set out below.7.   Equal Pay.   The government remains committed to the achievement of equal pay by 29 December 1975 and improvements in pay and conditions to secure conformity with the Equal Pay Act will be allowed above the
pay limit./Jk   Occupational Pensions.    Improvements in occupational pensionswill be allowed above the pay limit/.8.    Hours and Holidays.    Reduction in standard working hours may alsobe made outside the pay limit if they reduce working hours to not lessthan 40 hours a week (net of meal breaks).   Where however there has been an agreement to increase hours to more than 40 a week that agreementmust stand.   Similarly, improvements in holidays may be made outsidethe pay limit provided that they do not increase the total holidayentitlement to more than the equivalent of 3 weeks a year (not counting7 occasional or public holidays or rest days taken in lieu of weekendsor overtime).   The cost of making any other reductions in hours orholidays must be set against the pay limit.Personal Incrementsffi.   Personal increments of wage for age scale:.increases may continueto be paid provided that the incremental arrangements are such thatthey normally involve no overall increase in the total pay bill from year to year.   No increases in the amounts of increments, or otherimprovements in incremental scales should be given-JParticular Methods and Systems of Payment10.   National, local and plant increases.   Where settlements may be concluded at more than one level, eg. where a national settlementmay be supplemented at local or plant level, the total increase in pay should be kept within the pay limit.11.   Payment by Results.    Increases in the earnings of employees whoare paid under any scheme of payment by results, including pieceworkand commission payments, or under an arrangement linked to such ascheme, should not exceed the pay limit.   This restriction does notapply, however, to- increases in pay arising from direct and measurablecontributions by employees to increased output under a scheme which wasin operation before 9 July 1975 and the terms of which have not been changed.12.   Productivity and Restructuring; Schemes.    No productivity orrestructuring scheme should be implemented unless it has been agreedbefore /T August/ 1975 or any increases in pay under the scheme are found within the pay limit for the group concerned.
FORMS OF PAY DETERMINATION OTHER THAN NEGOTIATION15*    Comparability- exercises.    The pay limit must override systems of pay determination based on historical comparison with other groups.This will entail, for instance, the suspension for the period of thesystem of pay research in the civil service and the government will invite the Pay Review Bodies for Top Salaries, Doctors and Dentistsand the Armed Forces to frame their recommendations in accordancewith the policy.14.   Wages Councils.    The government will similarly expect the wages councils to abide^the requirements of the policy.15.   Arbitration.    The pay limit should apply to all settlementswhether reached by negotiation, conciliation, arbitration or by other methods of pay determination, whether statutory or otherwise.   Thegovernment hope that, where employers and unions have difficulty in reaching agreement on pay increases which are within the pay limit,they will consider the possibility of conciliation or arbitrationunder their existing^arrangements or through ACAS.   But the parties concerned must accept responsibility for settlements .which emerge fromarbitration and for keeping them within the new pay limits.Transitional Arrangements -16.   This policy wili apply to all pay increases effective on or after /T August/.    This may however give rise to inequity in a few cases where groups have been expecting shortly to conclude agreeementsunder the existing TUC guidelines, not having had a pay increase sincethe statutory controls ended in July 1974-.17.   As a transitional easement therefore the government accepts that:a. agreements concluded and brought into force after /T1 July;7for annual operative dates up to and including 1 September shouldnot be subject to the new pay ,linits, provided that such agreements are in conformity with a firm offer made by the employer and attested in writing, before /T1 JulyT&quot;; and provided that the .. group has not had a principal pay increase in the preceding 12months;b. arbitration awards may be implemented in full if the formalreference to arbitration was made before /Tl JulyJZ.   Similarly
Wages Councils&apos; and Agricultural Wages Boards&apos; proposals agreed at meetings held before /11 July/7 may be implemented;c.    any group which was due an increase before /T1 July7\ not having had a principal increase in the preceding 12 months, andwhich accepts an offer from their employer for an increase in accord with the current TUC guidelines to take effect on or before1 September, should not be subject to the nw pay limit.Prior Commitments18.   A number of collective agreements made during the current payround includes specific commitments for pay increases over the coming12 months in the form of staged increases or annual settlements madein advance for dates after 1 September or threshold payments.    Thenew pay limit should be applied to employees covered by these agreements as to all other employees in order to avoid unfairdiscrimination as between one group and another.19-   The government therfore intend that where, under&apos; existing agreement, further increases are due to be paid at any date after/T August.7 they should be limited in their total amount to what would .be due to the groups concerned under the new policy.This means that:a. any part of a staged increase above the new pay limit should not be paid; and if the increase were at the limitsallowed by the policy no further increase should be paid duringthe following 12 months; -b. the same provision as a. should apply to any principalsettlement for an operative date after 1 September which hasalready been concluded;c. threshold payments may continue to be paid in accordancewith the current agreements but any made after /T Augusty&quot;should count against the group&apos;s pay limit for the new roundand, if the threshold payments reach the level of the pay limit,no further payment under the threshold agreement or anyprincipal increase should be paid for the subsequent 12 months.mi f -


</content>
</cab>
