<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/99/0 images: 207-209</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT)C. (59) 1792nd December, 1959CABINETMARITIME SAFETY COMMITTEE OF THEINTEi,-GOVERNMENTAL MARITIME CONSULTATIVEORGANISATIONMemorandum by the Attorney-general as I shall be on my way to the United States when the Cabinet considerthe memorandum by the Minister of Transport (C. (59) 178) about the maritime Safety Committee of the Inter-governmental Maritime consultative organisation (I. M. CO.), I think I should let the Cabinet know the views which I have expressed on the legal cuestions involved in the proceedingsnow pending before the International Court of Justice.2.      The issue before the Court is the construction of an Article in theConvention establishing the Organisation.   The text of the Article is setout in the Annex to this memorandum.   The Article is badly drafted, but its interpretation is not, in my opinion, a matter of great difficulty or doubt.3.      The Article clearly provides for the election of fourteen members all of whom must have &quot;an important interest in maritime safety&quot; and eight of whom &quot;shall&quot; be the largest ship owning nations.    In my view the meaning of the words &quot;ship owning nations&quot; is sufficiently clear.   I cannot conceivethat the International Court would hold that it was the task of the assembly to enquire into and decide   as to the beneficial ownership of ships registered under the flags of Panama and Liberia.   The expression &quot;ship owning nations&quot;is, prima facie, a reference to the shipping registered in a country.   to prove thnt Panama and Liberia have not an important interest in maritimesafety would be most difficult.   I do not think such a contention could succeed.If it did, Panama and Liberia would not qualify for membership of theCommittee at all.   It has been contended that the construction I place on theArticle would mean that the election of the eight largest ship owning nations would be automatic.   I think it would.   The Article appears to me designedto secure that those nations must be members of the Committee.   More thaneight of such nations can be elected.4.      Last June, after the Assembly of the Organisation had decidedto refer the question to the International Court for an advisory opinion,I was consulted on this.   I expressed the view that the arguments suggested to me were so tenuous as to be unworthy of presentation to the international court.5.      On 16th November I was sent the draft of a memorandum which it wassuggested might be submitted to the Court by Her Majesty&apos;s Government.This draft repeated the arguments which I had been asked to consider in June,together with one further argument, namely that as the Assembly had refused to elect Panama or Liberia, it was to be presumed that the Assemblyhad acted in accordance with the Article.   This argument appeared to me tobe, if anything, rather weaker than those which I had already considered.COPY NO.  Jl i-1-CONFIDENTIALO
I reconsidered the whole question and I remain of the opinion that these arguments are unworthy of presentation to the International Court.   i feel it would be injurious to our interests before the International Courtif we sought to present such arguments.   It might well lead to theirtreating our arguments in other cases with less respect than they deserved.6.      Personally I should be mOst reluctant to put forward arguments of this character, arguments which I think would be generally felt unworthyof a Paw Officer of Great Britain.R. E. M-B.Law Officers&apos; Department,   W. C. 2.1st December, 1959-2-
annex . M. C. O.Article No. 20 of the convention the Maritime Safety Committee shall consist of fourteenmembers elected by the Assembly from the members, Governmentsof those nations having an important interest in maritime safety,of which not less than eight shall be the largest ship-owning nations,and the remainder shall be elected so as to ensure adequat erepresentation of members, Governments of other nations with animportant interest in maritime safety, such as nations interestedin the supply of large numbers of crews or in the carriage oflarge numbers of berthed and unberthed passengers, and of majorgeographical areas.-3-

</content>
</cab>
