<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/99/0 images: 221-222</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y*S GOVERNMENT)C. (59) 1328th December, 19 59CABINETPENSIONSMemorandum by the Lord chancellor on Wednesday, 16th December, an Opposition Member(Mr. G. V/. Reynolds) will seek leave under the Ten-Minute Rule tointroduce a Bill to increase the old age pension.   The legislation committee discussed on Oth December the tactics for dealing withthis motion and concluded that the political issues were difficult and important enough to put before the Cabinet.2.      There are two courses open to us:   either to arrange for our supporters to speak and possibly to vote against the motion or toallow the motion and then block the Bill on Second Reading.   Eitheris likely to be embarrassing.3.      My colleagues will know that, with Ten-Minute Rule Bills towhich we object, the latter is the more usual coarse.   In thisparticular case our promise during the Election campaign that old age pensioners shall share in the benefits of the expanding economymakes it difficult for us to oppose the motion.   Indeed, our supportersmight prove very reluctant to do so, although, if the motion goesthrough, there should be little difficulty about blocking the Bill at alater stage.   On the other hand, the public, to whom the significance of the Ten-Minute Rule procedure is not familiar, are likely to interpret leave to introduce the Bill as equivalent to an undertaking by the Government to raise the rate of pension at once;   and,especially at Christmas-time, this is not the sort of misapprehensionit is pleasant to have to dispel.   If we do decide not to oppose the motion, there might be some advantage in making the position clear to the Lobby in advance.4.      Alternatively, a strong case on merits can be made againstthe Bill and hence against the motion.   A ten-shilling increase in the pension would either have a catastrophic effect on the national insurance Fund or would mean a substantial increase in thecontributions of both employers and employees, with all the effects on the economy which were argued fully in the Election campaign.It could be presented as a piece of gross financial irresponsibilityand there is clearly much to be said for not letting our case go bydefault in the debate next week.COPY NO. Lf g
5.      This happens to be the second Ten-Minute Itule motion putdown for 16th December and the Chief &quot;Whip intends to try to securethat it is deferred until after Christmas, on the ground, accepted in principle by the Opposition, that it is preferable not to have morethan one such motion on any one day.    But even if this move issuccessful, the motion is certain to be put down for a later date anda decision will be required.6.      Opinion in the Legislation Committee was divided as betweenthe tactics discussed in paragraphs 3 and 4 and the Cabinet areinvited to decide.K.House of Lords, S. W. 1.Gth december, 1959

</content>
</cab>
