<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/65/0 images: 2-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.COPY NO.CABINET    50(30).Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street,.S.W.1., on Tuesday, September 2nd,. 1930,  at 11.0 a.m,PRESENT:The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.Chancellor of the Exchequer, (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor, K.C.V.O.,K.C.,Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon.Wedgwood Benn,D.S.O.,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretary of Statefor India.The Right Hon.Lord Thomson,C.B.E.,D.S.O.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood,M.P,,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.William Graham, M.P.,President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon.J.H.Thomas,M.P., Secretaryof State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon.J.R.Clynes,M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Thomas ShawyC.B.E.,M.P.,Secretary of State forWar.The Right Hon.Vernon Hartshorn,0.B.E. ,M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan,Bt.,M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation.The Right Hon.W. Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of State forScotland.Mr. R.B.Howorth,C.B. ,..........Acting Deputy Secretary.
R3HT .      l. The Cabinet were informed by the 0.Minister      Health that, after further .consideration and in agreement with theSecretary of State for Scotland and the,Minister(previous reference of Agriculture and Fisheries:, it was proposed to cabinet- 46(30)Conclusion 1&amp;)...      invite the Cabinet to vary the conclusion referred to in the margin to the extent thatthe Departmental Committee named in thatConclusion should consider the Rent RestrictionActs exclusive of the &quot;tied&quot; cottage question^and that a separate Departmental Committee to beappointed by the Minister of Health and theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries, should beset up to inquire into and report upon the &quot;tied&quot;cottage question in England and Wales.. THE SECRETARY OF STATS FOR SCOTLANDinformed his colleagues that, while he did not anticipate that it would be necessary to set upa separate Scottish Committee on the &quot;tied&quot;cottage question, he desired to be authorisedto appoint such a Committee should the need for it arise,The Cabinet approved the proposalssummarised above.
THE TARIFF 2. THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER reminded&quot;BiTIFICATION OF his colleagues that the question of the ratification of the Tariff Truce had beendiscussed at the Emergency Meeting of the cabinet held on August 6th, 1950, when the Conclusions(Previous reference cabinet 49(30) mentioned in the margin were reached, and conclusion 1).explained that the President of the Board ofTrade 3.esired more definite instructions before leaving for Geneva at the end of the present woelc.THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE, afterreviewing the history of the question, stated that since the matter was last before the Cabinet hisanxiety with regard to the proposal not to ratify the Convention had greatly increased.     There hadalready been inquiries from Germany, Italy andother Powers as to the intentions of the BritishGovernment in regard to ratification, and he was certain to be questioned on the subject on his arrival at Geneva,     He had come to the conclusionthat our position at Geneva would be underminedand would become quite impossible economically ifwc refused at this stage to ratify.     Ratificationwould in no way embarrass tho Government.     A changein fiscal policy could only be effected by theBudget and by giving notice on the 1st February,1931, Great Britain could, if necessary, be entirely). free front obligations under the Convention by the1st April, 1931.
Ratification was an essential step before thenegotiations on tariff reductions in the case of commodities (Textiles and Machinery) could he opened,and no progress could he made until Great Britain hadratified.    He failed to see how ratification could, have any prejudicial effect on the discussions at theforthcoming Imperial Conference.he had received a letter from the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies written in favour of ratification.The Prime Minister, with whom he had briefly discussed the matter last week, remained substantially of thesame opinion as is expressed in the above mentionedCabinet Conclusion.THE LORD PRESIDENT OP THE COUNCIL supportedratification;    not to ratify would,, in hisGeneva, as formulated, after discussion atGeneva, by a Member of the Government.THE SECRETARY OP STAGE FOR DOMINION affairs pointed out that practically every British trade and commercial interest had expressed views hostile to-ratification.     Since the signing of the Conventionmany ]3uropean Powers had increased their tariffs,, andfrom Great Britain&apos;s point of view the damage had therefore been done before ratification.     While it was doubtful whether anything of importance would emerge from the economic discussions at the ImperialTHE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF TRADE added that opinion, be a reversal of economic policy at
Ratification was an essential step before thenegotiations on tariff reductions in the case of commodities (Textiles and Machinery) could be opened,and no progress could be made until Great Britain hadratified.    He failed to see how ratification could have any prejudicial effect on the discussions at theforthcoming Imperial Conference.THE PRESIDENT OP THE BOARD OF TRADE added thathe had received a letter from the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies written in favour of ratification.The Prime Minister, with whom he had briefly discussed the matter last week, remained substantially of thesame opinion as is expressed in the above mentionedCabinet Conclusion./      THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER read to theCabinet/a letter which he\had rco^^W^ from the^J^inisterfcj^ Agricjulture and Fisheries^ expressing,,*th&apos;c opinionthat the Government should not tie their hands in anyway in regard to the proposals for a Tariff Truce.THE SECRETARY OF STAGE FOR DOMINION affairs pointed out that practically every British trade and commercial interest had expressed views hostile to ratification.     Since the signing of the Conventionmany European Powers had increased their tariffs,, andfrom Great Britain&apos;s point of view the damage had therefore been done before ratification.     While it was doubtful whether anything of importance would emerge from the economic discussions at the Imperial3o
Conference- Xf^ronlxL be- dis&amp;atroiis within, a few weeks of the Meeting of the Conference for the British Governmentto proclaim that whatever proposals the Dominions might make,could not and would not be given effect to, and so to givethe Dominions the opportunity of putting the responsibilityfor the failure of the Conference on to His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment.    In this connection reference was made to the statements in- the House of Commons by the Prime Minister and the Secretaryef State for the Dominions, to the effect that no question wouldbe ruled out from consideration at the Conference, By ratifying the Convention the Government would, in effect, declare that theonly source of revenue from which prospective deficits couldbe met would be direct taxation,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS asked certain questions and expressed himself as satisfied with the repliesgiven by the President of the Board of Trade.    In his view itwould be necessary on an early opportunity to make an announce-men-t that the Government had no intention of changing the traditional Free Trade Policy of the Labour Party.THE SECRETARY OF STATS FOR WAR favoured postponement, ifpossible, of any decision until after the Imperial Conference.If,, however, postponement was impracticable, he agreed that theGovernment must ratify the Convention.Considerable discussion took place in which most of theKemb-ers of the Cabinet present participated.    In the course ofthis discussion the President of the Board of Trade replied toa number of questions, and assured the Cabinet that the powers which had made alterations in their tariffs since the Convention,had done what they were fully entitled to do under the agreement reached in March last.   With one or two exceptions the alter-ations made consisted of relatively minor adjustments.     Hedissented from the view that ratification would tie our handsat the Imperial Conference.   Failure to ratify would leadforeign Powers to infer that Great Britain was about to revise her whole fiscal policy.   It was Impossible to postpone4t the
question of - ratification ..uirtil after&apos; the ImperialConference, a decision to ratify or not to ratifymust he taken now.THB CHiJACSLLOi? OF THE EXCHEQUER reminded theCabinet that the Tariff Truce proposals had resulted from the Economic Conference at which the.resolutionshad been unanimously passed in favour of the abolitionof tariffs.     After the Convention was ratified,negotiations for tariff reduction would be commenced.If the British Government desired these negotiations,then they must ratify the Convention.   If they did notratify the Convention the situation would be infinitelyworse than if Great Britain had never participated inthe discussions.     Hot only would she be blamed for thefailure of the scheme, but the impression would be given that she v/as about to change her fiscal policy and inevitably a situation would result which would producetariff wars.With the full consent and approval of theCabinet, Great Britain had taken a nost prominent partin the negotiations leading up to the Convention, and hecould not imagine what ill could possibly result fromratification.Following on ratification, the negotiations inregard to tariffs affecting textiles and machinery would take place and it would be possible to judgebetween November and February what the attitude ofForeign Powers was likely to be.    If the negotiationsturned out badly it would be possible to reconsider theposition in February.     If Great Britain failed to ratify now, fell the blame for the ^maintenance of high
tariffs in Europe would rest upon her, but if sheratified and the subsequent negotiations failedowing to obstacles raised by foreign Powers, then the blame for failure would be upon them.The construction which would be put uponGreat Britain&apos;s failure to ratify would be that theGovernment had an open mind jsn fiscal policy.   a refusal to ratify would mean complete surrender to theProtectionist Party.   .He could not see how ratification could inthe slightest degree hamper the proceedings of theImperial Conference.    It had been made perfectly clear,in Parliament, beth by himself and Lord. Arnold, thatwhile the Government were prepared to discuss any proposals at the Conference, they could not agree toany taxation on food or a.ny general Protectionistpolicy.With regard to the argument that the Govern-aent should keep their hands free so as to be able,if necessary, to impose import duties in the nextBudget^ he, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, wished tomake it quite clear that whatever the position mightbe, such a proposal, so far as he wa3 concerned,was out of the question^     In conclusion, theChancellor expressed the view that in this matter thenational honour of the country was at stake, andthat the only thing to be done was to ratify theConvention and to enter as quickly as possible diet thenegotiationsj    if these were successful the Governmentwould be entitled to great credit, and if they failedno responsibility would rest on the Government.
The Cabinet (by a majority) agreed -.-That the President of the Board of Tradshould be authorised to announce at theforthcoming Meeting of the Assembly ofthe League that the British Governmenthave decided to ratify the CommercialConvention (&quot;the Tariff Truce&quot;) before 1st November, 1930.Whitehall Gardens, S.Y/.1.2nd September, 1930.

</content>
</cab>
