<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/65/0 images: 114-134</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Ill(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S&apos;GOVERNMENT)f^E C R E T. Copy No.cabinet    59 (50).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.1., on THURSDAY, 9thOctober,  1930, at 3.0 p.m....AGENDA.1.      FOREIGN AFFAIRS.     (if required).2.      IMPERIAL CONFERENCE,  19 50.(a) Proposed publication of a white Paper.(Reference Cabinet 55 (3Q) Conclusion 4.).,Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade/(CP. 322 (30)    -   already circulated). j(b) Draft Statute of Westminster. /(Reference Cabinet 55 (30) Conclusion 2). memorandum by the Attorney-General,  covering Ialternative revised drafts.(CP. 323 (30)    -    already circulated).(c) Oil Concessions in British Territory.Extract from 250th Draft Minutes of theCommittee of Imperial Defence, covering memorandum by Petroleum Department, Board of Trade,(CP. 328 (30)    -    to be circulated).3.      INDIAN AFFAIRS.Question to be raised by the Secretary of Statefor India.4.      INDIA.    POSITION OF THE COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF ON THE. GOVERNOR-GENERAL&apos;S EXECUTIVE COUNCIL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India..(CP.  325 (30)    - already circulated)&apos;.5.      THE GOVERNMENT AND RATIONALISATION..Memorandum by. the President of the Board of Trade.(CP. 326 (30)    -   circulated herewith).1 .
6.      IMPERIAL DEFENCE POLICY.Extract from Draft Minutes of the 250th Meetingof the Committee of Imperial Defence, coveringFifth Annual Review by the Chief of StaffsSub-Committee.(CP.  327 (30)    -    to be circulated).(Signed)   M. P ,,4.,.. hankey,Secretary, Cabinet,Whitehall Gardens, 3.W.1.6th October, 193O.
TfTffjS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVERNMENT)S E C R E T.Copy No.CABINET    59  (50).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.1.,on THURSDAY, October 9th, 19JO,at 3.0 p.m.PRESENT;-The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield,Secretary pf Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord chancellor.The Right Hon.Vernon Hartshorn, O.B.E.,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, Bt.,M.P., President of theBoard of Education.;The Right. Hon.A.V. A-Lexander, M.P. ,First Lord of thej    Admiralty.The Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of Frieth,K.C.V.O.,K.C., lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M..P.,Minister of Labour,The Right Hon.W. Graham, M.P.,President of the-Board of Trade.The Right Hon.William Adams on,- M.P.,Secretary of Statefor Scotland./   For Items 1-6 only.Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. ,G. CM. G. ,. . .-...... Secretary.
DEATH OF THE 1. The Cabinet placed on record a tribute ofSECRETARYOP STATE their admiration of the great services of theirFOR AIR.colleague, the late Lord Thomson of Cardington,the Secretary of State for Air, and their profoundsorrow at his death in the wreck of the AirshipR.101.
FRENCH CO- The Prime Minister informed his colleagues thatOPERATION .he had sanctioned a submission to the King for threeHonours to French representatives who had renderedassistance in connection with the wreck of R.101.THE AIRSHIP 2.   The Prime Minister informed His colleaguesR.1C1.  that, in view of the short time available, he hadFuneralArrangements.       taken the responsibility of sending a wreath fromthe Cabinet to be placed in Westminster Hall withthe remains of those who had perished on board theAirship R.101.He expressed the hope that as many of hiscolleagues as possible would be present at the memorial Service in St. Paul&apos;s Cathedral on the morrow.The Prime Minister further reported that it hadbeen arranged that the Prime Ministers and Headsof Delegations present at the Imperial conference should attend the funeral together and walk fromWestminster Hall to Euston Station.   After that point the funeral would partake of a private and personal,  as distinct from a public, character.He hoped some of his colleagues would be able toattend,
f previous reference:Cabinet 5P(50), Gon-conclusion 5.)3.    The Secretary of State for India, afterreferring to the last  decision of the Cabinet inregard to the jirga of Afridis, said that aftercommunicating the Cabinet&apos;s decision he had receivedmost urgent messages from the Viceroy to the effect-that if the British representative (Mr Pears) hadto meet the Afridi jirga without any definite andfirm programme of the Government&apos;s intentions, hewould, be placed in an impossible position.   TheSecretary of State gave evidence of the very arrogantmood of the Afridis, who were trying to raise theFrontier against us and had made a series of mostextravagant demands,  including, for example, the custody and control of the Ehyber Pass;    the releaseof Gandhi, the leader of the Peshawar &quot;Red Shirts&quot;and all political prisonersv   payment by theGovernment of India of a fine of 56.000 rupees for having broken its contract with the Afridis,  etc.The Secretary of State himself had approved thedecision of the Cabinet at the time, but he hadrealised, particularly after reading the Viceroy&apos;personal telegrams, that to send a representativeof the Government of India into the conferencewithout empowering him to say that the government intended, to make the road was useless.    After con-sultation with the Prime Minister he had telegraphedthat the British representative was to take the line that His Majesty&apos;s Government agreed to the con-struction of the roads and posts on the Kajuri Plainas an essential demand on the jirga, and that toenable this to be achieved the Government would be willing to permit the Chief Commissioner to advancetroops if it was essential to do so to secure theobject stated, and Mr Pears might therefore enter the North-T-Ves t&quot;rontier.Measures fordealing with &apos;the A^idis .
the jirga knowing that he had this authority.The telegram reiterated that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment were most anxious that the essentialobject of the construction o^ the roads and postsshould be achieved without disturbance , and limited his essential objectives to this.    Itwas made clear also that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentremained definitely opposed to any measures designed to &quot;make an example&quot; of the Afridi Tribe,either as a whole or even particular sections of it.as retribution for past misdeeds.    The Secretaryof State added that Mr Pears had not as yet net the  full jirga, though he had met some 500 Afridipensioners or serving soldiers and explained theposition to them.The Prime Minister regretted that,  owing tothe urgency of the matter, he had had to actwithout consulting his  colleagues, with theexception of the Lord Chancellor, with whom he had had an opportunity to confer.The Cabinet approved the action taken, by the Secretary of Statefor India with the approval ofthe Prime Minister:.
(previous reference:Cabinet 48(30),  Con-conclusion 3.)4.    The Secretary of State for India reportedto the Oabinet the arrangements made for the indian round-Table Conference, which were in a satisfactorystate, most of the members being already on their way to London.Seme discussion took place in regard to thearrangements for the Cpening Meeting, and it wassuggested to the Secretary of State that a reference should be made to the matter in theKing&apos;s Speech.-5-The Round-Table Con-ferenoe.
INDIA. &apos;. 5.    The Secretary of State for Indiaconsulted his colleagues in regard to theThe Governor-General, successor to the present Governor-General.The Secretary of State said he would liketo consult some absent members of theCabinet who were specially interestedin regard to the particular name whichcommended itself to his colleagues and himself before taking further steps inthe matter.Subject to this,   the Secretaryof State for India was authorised totake action without again consulting theCabinet.
(Pr previous reference:Cabinet 58(30), Oon-clusion 5.)6 . The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the Secretary of State for India (CP ,-325 (30))drawing attention to the fact that an opinionhad been expressed with great authority on various occasions in favour of terminating the practiceof making the Commander-in-Chief a member of theGovernor-General&apos;s Executive Council;    and propos-ing, if the Cabinet approved, to write to general sir Philip Chetwode^ Commander^-in-Chief-designate,to inform him that he proposes to submit to HisMajesty (by whcm the appointment to the Council ismade and during whose pleasure it is held) thathe be appointed to the Council but on the under-Standing that his appointment may have to be terminated before his tenure as Commander-in-Chiefexpires,  either as the&apos;result of legislation oreven as the result of administrative action ifthe change is so generally recommended as to make this desirable.The Secretary of State, in his Memorandum,also asked his colleagues, in agreeing to thisproposal, to register an opinion that the Govern-ment retains its freedom to carry out at once by administrative act, after the necessary consulta-tion with the Government of India, any changesin the mechanism of the government of that country which, in the light of the Round-Table Conference,appear to them desirable and do not require legislation, without necessarily waiting for acomplete scheme, involving administrative as wellas legislative changes, to be presented as a whole\o Parliament.The Position of1 ommand er- in^Chief on theGovernor-General&apos;sExecutiveOounoil.
The Cabinet agreed -That the Secretary of Stat e forIndia should be authorised to notify the Commander-in-Chief-designate, as proposed above,that his appointment as amember of the Governor-General&apos; executive Council is liable tobe terminated either as the resultof legislation or of administrative action.
i0   IMPERIALCONFER! NOE,1^50.Const it tit ionaland economic policy .(previous reference:Cabinet 55(30), Oon&quot;clusion 2.)imperial preference.7.    The Prime Minister gave his colleaguesa summary of the present position of the main workof the Imperial Conference.    On the constitutional issues considerable progress had been made, and aCommittee had been set up, under the chairmanship of the Lord Chancellor, which would submitdrafts of the proposed arrangements.   the atmosphere on these questions was satisfactory.On the Economic side, the speeches made atthe Plenary Meeting on the previous day hadalready been circulated to the Cabinet.   As theresult of that meeting he had thought it advisable to continue the^discuss ion at more private meetings,which had begun that morning, when the difficultiesof accommodating the Dominions by a preferentialtariff had been explained.    The subject was tobe resumed next Monday, when the President of theBoard of Trade would explain the measures proposed for meeting the desire for improved trade without involving a tariff.   The Cabinet, however, wouldhave to take certain decisions before then.The Cabinet then discussed the question ofthe attitude to be adopted towards imperial preference and dumping, after which the.President of the Board of Trade gave a summaryof the line he proposed to adopt at Monday1smeeting .The Cabinet agreed  (a) As regards Imperial Preference,(i) That all taxes on food andraw material must be ruled out;(ii) That so long as there are Dutiesthere will be Imperial Prefer-ence:
(b) To approve generally the line which the President of the Boardof Trade proposed to take, whichwould include a proposal for an examination of the figures,  tosee exactly what they mean:    ageneral and sympathetic statementof the position:    a reference toBulk Purchase,  Import Boards and price Stabilisation, all of which,after a preliminary discussion, hewould propose to pass to a Gom-mittee:    support to an examina-tion of particular industries which exist both in the Dominionsand in the United Kingdom, witha view to devising some systemof allocation between those partsof each industry which the Dominionswish to retain for themselves, andother parts for which they wouldrely cn imports (e.g,,, in the ironand steel industry), a subject which was recognised to requirethe co-operation of industrialists:some arrangement on the analogy of the Argentine Agreement,enabling an interchange of goods to take place on the basis of a fixed credit:    proposals for bringing home to industrialiststheir failure to take advantageof the Preferences that had been offered to them in the Dominions:and a number of relatively minorpoints emerging from the Memo-randa of the Board of Trade andfrom the Joint Memorandum of theTrades Union Congress and theFederation of British Industries,etc.    In regard to inter-Imperialmachinery, such as an annual meetingbefore or after the Assembly of theLeague of Nations, an ImperialEconomic Section on the analogy of the Economic Section of theLeague of Nations, and an ImperialSecretariat,  it was recognised asadvisable to proceed with cautionand on very gqneral lines, raisingit late in the discussion and allowing the matter, if possible,to be raised by the Dominionsthems elves :(c) To take note that a Committee ofthe Imperial Conference would examine the question of dumping,with special reference to wheat.
u nemploytvtentpolicy.The industrial situation.(previous reference:Cabinet 58(SO), Con-elusion 2.)8.    Arising out of the consideration of theEconomic Policy of the Imperial Conference, a discussion of a general character took place inregard to trade conditions and the increase in umemployment, towards the end of which someemphasis was laid on the large number of men andwomen, including young people, particularly insome centres, who a^e being supported by theState without work and without training facilities
unemployment policy.    *The industrial situation.(Pr ev i previous reference:Cabinet 58(30) , Con-conclusion ion 2 .)8.    Arising out of the consideration of theEconomic Policy of the Imperial Conference, a discussion of a general character took place inregard to trade conditions and the increase in-unemployment, towards the end of which someemphasis was laid on the large number of men andwomen, including young people, particularly insome centres, who a^e being supported by theSta,te without work and without training facilities
9 .The Cabinet bad before them a Mote by thePresident of the Board of Trade (CP.-322 (30))circulating for the consideration of his colleaguesa draft White Paper on the External Trade of theUnited Kingdom, the Dominions and India with british and foreign countries.    If the draft was approved he proposed, before publication, to makeam alteration to enable the figures in Table IIfor Canada to be compared directly with the figures in Table I.The Cabinet approved the publica-tion of the figures In CP.-322(30) as a White Paper.
10.  The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary (CP.-328 (30))  covering the followingpolicy regardingdocuments relating to^oil concessions in Britisht er^-itory :-(i) A Memorandum by the PetroleumDepartment, Board of Trade(O.I.D. Paper No. 1G17-B)  onthe policy to be pursued inregard to the control of Companiesholding oil concessions in british territory.    In accordance with thegeneral policy laid down in 1904,oil concessions on Crown lands inthe British Colonies and india have up to the present been grantedonly to Companies under british control.   It was now suggested thatthe present policy should be modi-fied to allow foreign-controlled companies to operate,  subject tocertain conditions set forth in para.6 o^ the Memorandum.(ii) An Extract from the draft Minutesof the 250th Meeting of the Committeeof Imperial Defence, held on September29th,  19 30,  containing the followingC onclus ions:-(a) To refer the Memorandum for decision to the Cabinet, witha recommendation that there wasno objection to the policy proposed from the point of viewof Imperial Defence:(b) To recommend that the memorandum should be placed before therepresentatives of the Dominionsduring the Imperial conference for their consideration.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve in principle the changein policy proposed by the Presidentof the Board of Trade in C.P.-328&apos; 30) , while reserving details until after the matter had been discussed at the Imperial Conference:(b) To take note that the Secretary ofState ^or the Colonies  desired toreduce the proposed period of noticeof two years before the policy came into effect, at any rate in the caseof British Guiana:(c) To take note that in regard toIndia the policy might be effectedas the result of the Indian Round-Tab le Conference, owing to the.
recommendation of the statutory commission in fpvour of the separation of Burmah:fd) To approve the circulation tothe Imperial Conference of theMemorandum circulated by thePresident o^ the Board of Trade(C.I.D. Paper Wo. 1017-B).
imperial defence policy.(previous reference:Cabinet 56(28), Oon-conclusion ion 8 ,)11,The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary (C,P.-327 (30))  covering the PifthAnnual Review of the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee(C.I.D. Paper No.l009-B), together with an Extractfrom the Minutes thereon of the 250th Meeting ofthe Committee of Imperial Defence held onSeptember 29, 19 30.The Cabinet took note of the fifth Annual Review of the Chiefsof Staff Sub-Committee.
unemployment policy.The Attitudeof the Govern-in ent t war dsIndustrial Re-organisation .previous reference:Cabinet 58(SO), Con-clusion 8.)12.The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade (CP,-326(SO)) recalling two questions that had been posedin a Memorandum by the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs  (CP .-227 (30))  on IndustrialRe-organisation, namely, whether the Governmentwere to accept the responsibility of associatingthemselves with &quot;rationalisation&quot;, and, second,who was to carry out that policy .    On the under-standing that the Cabinet were persuaded that theycould not stand aside from the promotion of ration-alisation, the President of the Board of Tradestated that, as the Board of Trade was the Depart-ment principally concerned, he was prepared toaccept the suggestion made by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs that he should beresponsible for carrying out that policy.The proposal of the Presidentof the Board of Trade wasapprov ed .
&apos;NF,XT MEETINGOF CABINET.13 .    The Prime Minister warned his colleagues that,  owing to the complications of the tim.e-table of the Imperial Conference, it was difficult toensure adherence to the date fixed for the CabinetSubject to this it was agreed  That the Cabinet should meet onWednesday next, October 15th, at, Whitehall Gardens, S.w.1,October 9,  19 30.

</content>
</cab>
