<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/65/0 images: 446-475</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
jWlS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S- GOVERNMENT).RJB-G R E .T+ Copy No.CABINET    75  (50).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.   10,Downing Street,&apos; S.V. 1. ,  on WEDNESDAY,december 17th, 1930, at IG.30 a.m.AGENDA.i-      FOREIGN AFFAIRS.     (if required).2.      THE TRADE DISPUTES BILL.H.A.  4-3 (30)    -    Copies of the Bill will not beavailable for circulation beforethe Meeting.3.      EDUCATION:    THE VOLUNTARY SCHOOL PROBLEM.(peference Cabinet 72 (30)  Conclusion 9).&apos;Memorandum by the president of the Board b.&apos;f/^ -Education.(&quot;CP. if 1 3 (30;    -    circulated herewith)..&apos;if.      ELECTORAL A&amp;gQRM BIhu :    the  ALTERNATIVE VOTE .(Reference Cabinet 72 (30) Conclusion 3).Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(C.?j. if07 (30V    -    already circulated;..Further Memorandum by. the Home Secretary.(CP. 419 (30;    - &apos; already circulated).:5i 1 -     CONCLUSIONS OF THE HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.(Reference .H.A..C  17th Conclusions (30)    -    to... be circulated).&apos;(i) Agricultural Marketing Bill.v..&apos;,;&apos;      .(H.A. 47 (30)    &quot;    already circulated;.(11) Yarmouth Naval Hospital Bill.(H.A.. 35 (30)    -    to be circulated).t.
8.    BUSS I AM &quot;DUMPING&quot;.(Reference Cabinet 72(30) Conclusion 1)Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.,(CP. 416(30)    -    already circulated.9.    INDUSTRIAL RE-ORGANISATION.(Reference Cabinet 61(30) Conclusion 4)Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade,(CP. 420(30)    -   already oiroulated).10.    THE COTTOiITU ATI CN.(Reference Cabinet 66 (30) Conclusion S)Memorandum by the Home Secretary and the Presidentof the Board of Trade, :&apos;(CP. 421(30)    -   already circulated).11.    DYES TURFS  (IMPORT REGULATION) ACT,  19 2,0.     (If required)(Reference Cabinet 71(30) Conclusion 2).TO TAKE NOTE OF:12-    INDIAN NORTH-TOT FRONTIER:    THE AFRIDI -S situation.(Reference Cabinet 66(30) Conclusion 21)Note by the Secretary ef State for India coveringExtracts from Situation Reports, etc.(CP. 411(30)    -   already circulated).2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.15th December, 1930.(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet..C    EXPORT CP WiR MATERIALS  AED YfAKELTPS .(Reference Cabinet 57(30) Conclusion 12)Note by tbe Secretary of State for Poreign. Affairs&quot;covering Foreign Office Memorandum,(CP.  406(30)    -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Minister of Labour,(CP. 412(30)    -   already circulated).Note by the Secretary,   covering Report by the Chiefsof Staff Sub-Committee on Russian Plying Boats.(CP. 423(30)    -   to be circulated) .7 .    PROPOSED EXTENSION OP HOBS INC  (RURAL WORKERS ) ACT,  1926Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland,(CP. 417(30)    -   already circulated).
M 439ADDENDA   TO   AGENDA.(i)  Additional Item.THE NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE. (PROLONGATION OF IISURANCE)BILL.Memorandum by the Minister of Health covering draftBill.(H.A.  50  (30)    -   to be circulated).(ii)  (a)    Add the following Paper to Item 4,(ELECTORAL REFORM BILL:     THE ALTERNATIVE YOTE.)   :-Polling Places for Electors in remote Islands.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland.(CP. 425(30)    -   to be circulated).(b)    Add the following Paper to Item 6,(EXPORT OF WAR MATERIALS AND WARSHIPS.):-Deputation from the Shipbuilding Employers on thesubject of Naval Yforh. &apos;Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.(CP. 424(30)    -    circulated herewith).(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary,  Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.16th December, 1930,(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GCYEERMEWT)S E .C RE T. Oopy No.CABINET      73 (50).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.10,Downing Street, S.W.I.,  on WEDNESDAY,December 17th,  1930, at 10.30 a.m.
gTS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT):%C R E, T. Copy No.CABINET    75 (30).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.I.,  onWEDNESDAY,  17th December,  1930,  at10.30 a.in..PRESENT: -The Right Hon. J.  Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (In the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of theExchequer.iThe Right Hon.J.H.  Thomas,  M.F. ,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of frieth,K. C.V.0., E.C., lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P.,Secretary of State for home Affairs.the Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C.B.E., M.P.,Secretary of State for War.me Right Hon.Vernon Hartshorn,  O.B.E.,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.lie.Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, Id.P.. ,Minister of Labour.me Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan,. Bt.,M.P., President of theBoard of Education.(1$ Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M.P. ,First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.B.. ,-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield,Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon...Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgrood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C., M. P., Secretaryof State for India.The Right Hon.Lord Amulree, G.B.E.K.C.Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Christopher Addison, M.P.,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries,The Right Hon.W. Graham, M.P.,President of theBoard of Trade.The Right Hon.William Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of State forScotland.The Right Hon.George Bans bury, M.P.First Commissioner of Works.The following were also present: -Sir William Jowitt, K.C., M.P.,Attorney-General.Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B..,, G.C.M.G.......    Secretary.
DISPUTFSF 1* Cabinet had before them a MemorandumEILL* h? the Attorney-General (E.A.-48 (go)) submitting(Previous thS Q^ 6 t0 arcend the Trade DisputesoSb^S?0?i ^ Tr&amp;de Uni0nS agt.&apos; 1927&apos;   He asksd for the(30), Con- authority of the Cabinet to introduce the Pillclus ion 5.)in its present form, which was the result o^ aseries of negotiations he had undertaken with theExecutive Committee of the Trade Union Council andthe Liberals.The Lord president of the Council statedthat the Committee of home Affairs had examined the Bill from the drafting point of view,and considered it satisfactory.The Prime Minister thanked the Attorney-General for his conduct of the difficult negotiations which had been essential to thecompletion of the Bill.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the draft of theTrady Disputes and Trade unions bill in the form&apos; attached toE.A. 4-c (pO),  subject to any drafting or other minor alterations that might benecessaryj(b) That the names of the following ministers,  (or so many of them as is permissible), should appear on the back of the Bill:-The Prime Minister,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,The Home Secretary,The Secretary of State forSeo tland,The Attorn ey-Gene ral,The Lord Advocate.
(c) That the Attorney-general should have authority tointroduce the Bill on Thursday,December  loth, with a view toits immediate circulation togethwith an explanatory White Paper.-2-
THE DYF-SfHJFFS(IMPORT REG U-LATX3N)  ACT,1320 .i &quot;previous reference:Cabinet 71(50), Con-elusion 2 .)f.R.2. TTie Cabinet bad before them a Memorandumby tbe President cf tbe Board of Trade (C,P.-427( 3G) )  stating that cn the previous Monday theBlouse cf Lords had amended the Expiring laws continuance Bill so as to extend the operationof the Dyestuf^a  (import Regulation) Act,  1920(which is due to expire on the 14th January next),until tho end of 1931.    The Government now hadto decide what attitude thc^r would adopt when the expiring Laws Continuance Bill came before theHouse of Summons the same day,  and the Presidentcf the Board of Trade, propes ed in his memorandum that the Government should ask the House torefuse to accept the amendment and to return theBill to the Lords in the form in which it was originally submitted to that House.    If, however,the Lords ins its ted on their amendment, he fcarsdit would be necessary to accept  it in order toavoid losing the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill.In that event, the President of the Board of Tradesuggested in his Memorandum alternative means for meeting the reasons put forward in the House ofLords  for the continuance of the prohibition.The President of the Board of Trade, inreply to the Chancellor of the Exchequer, saidthat he was satisfied that it was constitutionalto include tho Dyes tuffs (import Regulation)Act,  1920,  in tho Expiring Laws continuance bill.After careful consideration of thequestion from the point of view, not only cfthe Dyestuffs Act itself, but also from that
of the other legislation (including the rent restrictions net) which would be lost if the expiring Laws Continuance Bill was rejected by the House of Lords,   the Cabinet agreed  (a) That the loss of the expiring laws Continuance Bill would create a position of suchembarrassment that it couldnot be faced;(b) To ask the house of Commons torefuse to accept the House ofLords&apos;  amendment to the expiring Laws Continuance Bill,&quot;and to return the Bill to the lords in the form in which itwas originally submitted to that house;(c) That,  if the house of lords should persist with theiramendment,  the Government,having made  their protest onthe previous day, should recommend the House of commons to accept it.
The Voluntary by the President of the Board of Education (C.P&apos;&apos;.-School Problem .418 (36)) reporting that,, as the result of discus-(Previous sions vith selected Members of Parliament of variousReference:Cabinet 72 religious opinions, he had arrived at a more widely(30), Con-clusicn 9) . accepted form- of an arrangement,  under whichVoluntary Schools required for the present re-organisation of education could be assisted out ofpublic funds.    It was stated that the proposals were the same,  in all essential principles,  asthose included in the second Clause of the Billlast summer.    Particulars of the detailed modifiea-tions were given, and the new propose Is were setforth in full.    At the end of the Memorandum thePresident recommended that he should be empoweredto announce that the Government are now in a positionto put forward what  they regard as a satisfactory solution of the Voluntary School problem.   ButV -before introducing a Bill embodying their proposals the President of the Board of Education would inviterepresentatives of the chief parties interested,na ely, the Local Education Authorities, the Ohurchof England, the Free Churches,  the Catholic Churchesand the Teachers to meet him in conference in orderto discover how far actual agreement could be arrivedat.   He proposed that the conference should be heldfat the beginning of January, in order that theGovernment may be in possession of its views assoon as Parliament assembles.Attention was drawn to the very short time which tne Cabinet had had for the study ofthis important memorandum.      The Secretary
reported that he had. received it for circulation on Monday, December 15tnj anci- i-thad been sent to Ministers the same evening.The Cabinet agreed --(a) That further time was requiredfor study of the detailsof the proposed arrangement;(b) That the President of the Boardof Education should avoid sayinganything in Parliament whichwould indicate that the cabinet had made up their minds onthe details of the plans,  but should announce that a Con-ference would be held early inJanuary, 193&apos;&apos;j between repre-sentalives of the Government,the Local Education Authorities,the Teachers,  the Churcn ofEngland,  the Roman catholic church and Hon-Conformists,at which it was hoped that agreement would be reached;(c) That a Cabinet Committee shouldbe appointed to act with thePresident of&quot; the Board ofEducation in these negotiations,composed as follows:-The Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,The Minister of Health,The Firs t Commissioner ofWorks.
ELECTORAL 4. The Cabinet had before fhm &quot;the foilcrcrlngREFORM.Memoranda in regard to Fleetoral Reform:-(Previous A Memorandum by the Fame SecretaryReference: (C.P.-437 ( 3C)) which had beenCabinet 72 considered at the previous Meeting(30), Con- of the Cabinet:elusion 3.)A Most Secret Memorandum by theHome Secretary ( C ..P .-419 (30))setting forth particulars ofthree suggestions which had beenmade in regard to the form whichthe Alternative Vote might take;and recommending what is known as&quot;Lord Craigmyle&apos;s Scheme&quot;:A further Memorandum by the EomeSecretary (C.P.-42B (SO,)) refer-ring to the Prime Minister&apos;sannouncer.!&apos;ent that the Parliament-ary Elections Bill will beintroduced before the christmas recess,  and stating that if thisis to be d.one the &quot;long title&quot;of the Bill must be settled atonce.    For this purpose the cabinet were asked for decisions on anumber of points, including thefollowing:-whether the 14 double-member constituencies should be exempted from the operationof the Alternative Vote:&quot;Whether the City of london should be omitted from theClause abolishing pluralvoting,  or whether-&quot; there might not be some advantages in leaving the business premisesqualification alone and insimply making it illegal to vote more than once at thesame election:Whether the Cabinet&apos;s decision that further provision shouldbe made for the absent votercould be maintained in view ofccmp lie at ions which had cometj to light regarding the diffi-cultiss  of registration officers, the complexity ofthe proceedings at an election,the effect  of enlargements ofthe principle cf absent voting onthe secrecy of the Ballot Actand the probability that any extension o^ the principle would lead to demands for still furtherextensions:A number of points relating- tothe use of motor-cars at elections:
rjiffi^nilirij^^ outthe decision of the cabinet for legalising the payment ofspeakers and including all such-payments, whether employed or voluntary,  in the candidate&apos;sexpenses:A Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Scotland (0.P.-425 (30))in regard to the difficulty ofproviding adequate polling facili-ties for electors in inaccessibleIslands off the North and WestCoast of Scotland., asking  for inclusion in the Bill of a pro-vision empowering the. returning officer, in the case of Scottishconstituencies which includeislands., to take the poll in anyisland polling district at a later date than that prescribed .croriginally fixed,  if,  in hisopinion,  it is impracticable totake the Poll on the earlier date.Attention was drawn to the fact that the two latter Memoranda had been circulated so late that many members  of the Cabinet had not had time to acquaint themselves with their contents     The HomeSecretary explained, as regards C.P.-42S (se). thathis Department had had to work under the greatestpressure in arder to draft the Bill, including the&quot;Long Title&quot;,  and had not been able to complete it without further decisions.In dealing with this Memorandum the methGdpursued by the Cabinet was to concentrate mainly on the draft of the &quot;Long. Title&quot; as it now appeared in the Bill,  and to take their decisions  on eachpoint as it arose.   The Bill itself was not discuss-ed in detail,The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the Home Secretary should adopt Lord Craigmyle&apos;s  Scheme for. the Alternative Vote as the basisof the Bill: -(b) That  as regards polling facilitiesfor electors in inaccessible
islands off the North and Y\restooast of Scotland,  no decision could be taken on such short notice.    The Secretary of Statefor Scotland was asked to discussthe matter with the Home Secretary:(c) That in the draft &quot;Long Title&quot; ofthe Bill attached to CP.-428 (30)provision should be made for theabolition both of thehusinesspremises qualification for regis-tration and of plural voting:(d) That in the &quot;Long Title&quot; referredto above,  for the phrase &quot;authorising the employment of paid   speakers atelection meetings&quot; there should- besubstituted &quot;regulating the employ-ment of speakers at election meet-ings&quot;:-(e) That in the &quot;Long Title&quot; referredto above, the word &quot;motor&quot; shouldbe omitted before &quot;vehicles&quot;:(f) That the Home Secretary should give instructions to the Parlia-mentary Draftsman to ensure thatthe &quot;Long Title&quot; shall enableprovision to be made in the Billfsr preventing unlimited expend!-ture on such matters as nationalbill-posting or private broadcastingfor election purposes, and thatthe language used should bescrutinised so as to ensure that local as well as national politicalorganisations are covered by thelast six lines of the draft &quot;LongTitle&quot;.(NOTE:    It was further suggestedthat the arrangements inthe last six lines should apply not only to organ-is at ions but also to individuals.   This point was left to the Hom^secretary to decide.)(g) That the &quot;Long Title&quot; should bedrawn,  if possible, so as to enablethe question of double-member constituencies to be dealt withby either of the following alter-nat iv e m etho ds :(i) To apply to them the principleof the Alternative Vote^UfccL ix^o(ii) The division of the constituencyinto two parts .(h) To leave any other-points to theHome Secretary. .
(MOTE. The first- eleven lines of the&quot;Long Title&quot; as amended by theOabinet in Conclusions  (c) to(e)  above (subject to Draftsman&apos;salterations) would read as follows:-&quot;DraftbilltoAmend the law relating to Barlia-mentary elections and electorsby requiring such elections tobe on the principle of thea It international iv e vote, ab o 1 ishingUniversity constituencies andthe business premises qualifi-cation for registration andplural voting,  facilitatingvoting by electors  changingtheir residences, regulating the employment of speakers atelection meetings, regulating the use of vehicles at  elections,and reducing the maximum scale of election expenses, and toprovide.&quot;,  etc . .(No attempt has been made toapply the decisions of theCabinet to the last six lines,which will have to be re-drafted in accordance with Conclusions(f) to (h) .)(NOT&quot;.:    The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs left during the abovediscussion.)
THE AGRJ3TJLTURAL 5. The Cabinet Had before them a MemorandumMARKETING BILL.by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries(Previous (H.A.-47 (30))  covering a draft AgriculturalReference:Cabinet 53 Marketing Bill, together with the Minutes of the(30), Con-elusion 1.) Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 17thConclusions  (30), Paragraph 1).    In these latterMinutes it was stated that the Attorney-general had drawn attention to the elaborate and compli-cated procedure which would have t*vbe followedbefore a scheme to regulate the marketing ofagricultural products could be brought intooperation, and had suggested that the irachineryof the Bill was capable 0^ being greatlysimplified.    The Conclusions of the Committee ofHome Affairs were as follows:-(i) To invite the Minister cfAgriculture and fisheries and other Ministers con-cerned, to confer with the attorney-General with regardto the question of the simpli-fication of the procedure proposed in the Bill:(ii)  Subject to (i) above, to recom-ment the Cabinet to approve theAgricultural Marketing Billin the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-47 (30),  subject to agreement being reached betweenthe Chancellor of the Exchequerand the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries in regard to thequestion raised on Clause 3 (a)and (c), and subject also to any drafting or other minor alt era-tions that may be found necessary or desirable.IThe Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriesinformed the Cabinet that since the meeting of&quot;the Committee of Home Affairs, he had discussed the Bill very fully with the Attorney-Generaland agreement had been reachedi      He thought,.
associate the Attorney-General with the consultation on the subject which ho- hoped tohave the same afternoon with the Chancellor ofthe Lx che quor.The Cabinet agreed  That the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries should have authorityto circulate the agricultural marketing Bill, in the form of thedraft annexed to H.A.  47 (p0)*subject to agreement between theChancellor of the Exchequer,  theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries,and the Attorney-General, and subject also to any drafting or other minor alterations that might be foundnecessary or desirable.
THE YJRMOETHNAVAL HOSPITALBILL.(PrevicusReferenee:Cabinet 53(30), Con-elusion 1(ryy.6.   The. Cabinet had,Jbefore them a Memoranduml?y the First Lord of the AdrmLralty (H0A.-35 (30))oovering &quot;the- draft Taxi^nrth. larval RospitaJ...-31iJhL,.--- .together with the Minutes of the Committee ofHome Affairs theyeon (H.A.C . 17th Conclusions(3C) , Paragraph 2) .    It was pointed out in this minute that this Eill was assigned by the Cabineten September 18,  19 30, to the o-ategery of measures^for which time might be arranged during theSeesion, but whieh could not find a place in theGovernment programme.    The reccxrooendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs was as follows:-To authorise the introduction inthe House of Lords of the YarmouthNaval Hospital Bill in the formof the draft annexed to H.A.-35(30). subject to such drafting&apos;or other minor alterations asmay be found necessary or desir-able,  on the understanding thatthe introduction of the Bill willbe deferred until arrangements can be made to ensure lbs passage into law as speedily as possible after its introduction.The Cabinet agreed  To approve the recommendationof the Committee of HomeAffairs,  subject to.thePrime Minister&apos;s being able&apos;&apos;to make the no-cessary arranges-.merits with the parliamentary secretary to the Treasury forthe rapid passage of the bill into law as scon as passibleafter its intre**Luction.
THE EXPORT CP j.      The Cabinet bad before them the followingWAR materials and WARSHIPS. documents relating to the Export of War materials and &quot;airships:-(previous reference: A Note by the Secretary of StateCabinet 57 for Foreign Affairs  (CP. -406 (.30 ))(30),  Con- covering a Memorandum prepared inelusion 12.) his Department regarding theexport  of war materials and war-ships..    This Memorandum summarisedall the available evidence regardingthe policy of the Italian Govern-ment in the matter o^ the exportef v,-ar material and warships,including extended credits,  and reached the conclusion that thereare very strong grounds, but no definite evidence, for believing that the Italian Government gives&quot;financial assistance to Italianfirms competing for foreign warshipconstruction.    On the wider questionof removing obstacles from our export trade in warships and warmaterial it was pointed out thatthe loss of business to british .firms is  chiefly due to their inability to offer sufficiently long credit  facilities .    Tllus-trations 0* this were.given inregard to past and prospectiveorders by various  foreign0 ov government ents,  including larg e c on-tracts likely to be placed in thenear future by the Governmentsof Portugal and Roumania.    The view was expressed, however,  that theapplication       the Export credits scheme to the export  of arms,ammunition and war material fromthis  country could  ot be enter-tained,  as,  apart from the necessityIntro-due ing legislation, it would place His Ma j eo tyr s Government inan almost untenahle position asregards their policy of limitationo f arm am e nt s iA Note by the Minister of Labour(CP,-412 (30)) stating that,  from thepoint of &quot;vie? of employment,, thes proposal to extend the applicationof the Export Credits Scheme to theexport of munitions might &quot;be welcome,but  expressing the view that, havingregard to the Governmenfs disarmamentpolicy, it was impossible to press the proposal,   even though othercountries may be granting financialassistance to similar purpose es :A Note by the Secretary (C.P.-423 (30))circulating for information a draft report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee of the Committee of ImperialDefence in regard to large orders for
Flying Boats placed with Italy by soviet Russia:A Memorandum by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty. (CP.-424 (30))reporting representations by aDeputation of the ShipbuildingEmployers&apos;  Federation urging that,in view of the unprecedented slump in shipbuilding, there might be an acceleration e-f G-overnment warshipwork.    In reply, the First lord had explained the difficulties ofcomplying with the request andhad not been able to give any encouragement to the Deputation,though he had undertaken to report their views .The First Lord of the Admiralty reportedto the Cabinet further information that had reached him in regard to an extension,granted by italian firms to the Soviet Government,  pf theperiod of payment for certain merchant ships,as well as of the grant of credit facilities bythe Italian Government.      He also producedevidence of French Government activity with aview to the stimulation. .of ship-building.The Cabinet, realising that there wasprims facie -evidenoe of a new situation detrimental to British ship-building,  and that the whole subject required further investigation, agreed -That the question of the Exportof Uar Materials and Warships, andkindred matters raised in the papers before the Cabinet and atthe Cabinet Meeting, should bereferred for consideration by aCabinet Committee composed asfollows:-The Lord Privy -Seal,The Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,The Secretary of State for War,The Secretary of State for Air,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The President of the Boardof Trade.
ffOUfflNG- (POTRALWQRFER2)  ACT,1926 .Proposed Con-continuation a^.(previous reference:Cabinet 33(50),  Oon-clusion 4c,)3.    The Cabinet had before then a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Scotland (G.P^-417 (30))urging the extension for another period of fiveyears of the Housing (Rural Workers) Act\ 19 26,and stating that if the extension were made itwould have to apply also to England.   He recommended the introduction of the necessary Bill early in1931.The question was adjourned until a later Meetings
RUSSIAN&quot;BUMFTNG&quot;(PreviousRefcrenc e:Cabinet 72( SO)    C on-conclusion I,)9.    The Oabinet had before thorn a Memorandumby the President of the Board of Trade (CP.-416(50))  summarising the information available inhis Department concerning the sale of Russiangoods on the British market in conditions whichare alleged to constitute &quot;dumping&quot;.    In view ofthis information he proposed to continue to adopting Parliament the line that the only way in whichaction can be taken is by duties or prohibitions,and he was perfectly satisfied that the loss toour trade from any action of that kind, would be greater than any gain;    His Majesty&apos;s government therefore did not propose to take any powers to prohibit cr restrict the importation of goods intothis country on the ground of &apos;me prices at whichthey are offered.In the course of the discussion theattention of the Oabinet was drawn to allegationsrecently forwarded to the Prime Minister bySir Edward Hilton Young, and published by him in the press, of conditions akin to slaveryin the Russian timber exporting trade.      TheCabinet were reminded that in Answers inthe House of Commons it had repeatedly beensuggested that in such cases the proper course was for the importer or complainant to makeformal application to the Board of Customs and excise, but that so far no response had resulted.      A further suggestion was that itmight be useful to arrange for a Question to
be put in Parliament so as to enable a reply to be given in which attention wouldbe drawn to the neglect to take the courseindicated above.The Cabinet approved theattitude of the Presidentof the Board of Trade in cp. if-I 6 (50).
Re- organisationef Industry.previous reference:Cabinet fl(30),  Con-elusion 4,)10 o The- Oabinet- bad&quot; before them- a- Memorandum-by the President of the Board of Trade (C.P.-420(30))  containing the latest information in regardto the re-organisation of the wool, textile and ironand steel industries.The Cabinet took note of theab ov e.
11, The Cahine-t had before them a Jaint Memo-randum by the Secretary of State for Home affairs and the President of the Board of Trade (CP.-421(30)) reporting the results of their visit toManchester on Thursday, November 2Sth, in order tocontinue their discussions with representativesof the Spinning section.The Oabinet took note of theab ov e.
(previous reference:Cabinet 66(30), Con-elusion 2112 . The Oabinet took note of&quot; a-, further Memo-randura by the Secretary of State for India (0411 (30))  circulating  extracts from North-west frontier Situation Reports.Tbe Cabinet took note of tbeabove.fid.TEEPT^NTTER.Tbe AfridiSituation.
the NA JET3NAL 13. The Cabinet had b ef or c them- a Mj^or-aaidumHEALTH mSDRiiNGE(PROLONGATION        by the.Minister of Health and the Secretary ofOP INStJRANOE)BILL. State for Scotland (K.A.-50 (30))  circulating aeopy of the National Health Insurance (Prolongation(previous reference: o-p Ins-urance) Bill, together with a copy of theCabinet 71(30),  Con- White Paper explaining the provisions of the Bill,conclusion 4.)The Lord. President of the Council informed the Cabinet that the Bill had been before theCommittee of Home Affairs the same morning and - &apos;.that the Committee had agreed to recommend theCabinet  To approve the introduction inthe Eeuse of Commons of theNational Health Insurance(Prolongation of Insurance) Billin the form of the draft annexed to H,A.-50 (30), with a view tothe passage of the Bill into law before the Christmas Recess(E.A.C 18th Conclusions  (30),Paragraph 2.)The Cabinet approved the recommendationof the Committee of Home Affairs.
agricultural policy.(?previous reference:Oabinet 72(30),  Con-clusion 1.)PROPOSEDEG GNOMICCONFERENCEAT OTTAWA.(previous reference^erence  :Cabinet 69(30), Con-conclusion ion 6 .)14. Referring to the decision of the Cabinet,at the Meeting mentioned in the margin, to setup a Committee to consider Agricultural Policy,the Prime Minister informed his colleagues thatthe enquiries he had instructed the Secretary toundertake had shown that the proposed Committeewould be duplicating to a considerable extent thework now being undertaken by the Committee onthe Proposed Economic Conference at Ottawa, setup on November 19th.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that hehad noted the same duplication.    If the committee set up at the Meeting referred to in the marginwas to consider the whole question of Agriculturehe thought its  composition would have to be re-considered .The Cabinet agreed  To leave the co-ordination of thematters before these two committees to the Prime Minister in consulta-tion with the Chancellor of theExchequer.o
-TIRFLE S SBROADCASTING .Propos edBroadcast onUnemployment.(previous reference erence:Cabinet 31(28)    Con-clusion 8 .)15. The Prime Minister informed his colleagues that arrangements had been made for the broadcastof three political speeches on the subject ofUnemployment.    Lots had been cast as to the orderof the Parties, with the result that the liberal party was to broadcast on February 2nd, 1931,  theLabour Party on February 9th, and the conservative party on February 16th.   He wished to consult hiscolleagues as to who should speak on behalf of theGovernment Party.On the suggestion of the Lord President of theCouncil, the Cabinet agreed  To leave the decision to thePrime Minister, in consulta-tion with the parliamentary secretary to the Treasury.c
CABINET 16 .    In the early part of the Meeting thePROCEDURE,Prime Minister drew attention on.ee more to the(Previous fact that several Memoranda, raising difficultReference:Cabinet 72 questions, had been cireulated to the Cabinet(30),  Con-clusion 11.)        so late that it had not been possible for membersf-^-- to study them, with the result that the businessof the Cabinet had been conducted under consider-able difficulties.The Prime Minister also asked his colleagues to instruct their respective Departments tonumber the pages of their Memoranda, for convenience-ence of reference.o
NEXT MEETING 17.    The Prime Minister informed the.CabinetOP CABINET.that he did not propose to summon a further meeting of the Cabinet during the present yearunless this was necessitated by some emergency.In the ordinary course he anticipated that atleast one Meeting would be required abouta week before the Opening of Parliament.2, Whitehall Gardens, S/:r.l,December 17, 1930 .

</content>
</cab>
