<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/46/9 images: 82-87</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.....d^....Se*s**?^.MOST OCCltCT.Copy No......*!J.HiTOP secret.M. (44) 63RD CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE confidential Annex(11th May, 1944 - 6.15 p.m.)RUSSIA(previous reference:W.M.(44) 47thConclusions,Minute 2)THE PRIME MINISTER recalled that on 29th Aprilhe had received a telegram from M. Molotov complainingof the presence in Roumania with Marshal Antonescuof a British Mission whose purposes were unknown tothe Soviet Government.     On.2nd May he had replied to M. Molotov pointing out that his suspicions werewithout foundation and stressing the fact that HisMajesty&apos;s Government had throughout made every effort to work in harmony with the Soviet Government inrelation to Roumania.     At the same time, our ambassador had been instructed to give a fullexplanation to M. Molotov and had done so on 5th May.The Prime Minister had now received a further telegramof 10th May from M. Molotov,. denying that our ambassador had given any explanations concerning theBritish Mission and stating that the Prime Minister&apos;message in spite of all ingenuity was unconvincing.He felt that he could not continue to correspond with M. Molotov whose attitude led him to despair ofthe possibility of maintaining good relations withRu russia.The question was raised whether it might not become desirable to lay before the House of commons in Secret Session the difficulties which we wereexperiencing in dealing with the Soviet.THE SECRETARY OP STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs explained that the Mission in question had been sentto Roumania last November by S.O.E. in order to make contact with M. Maniu.     Unfortunately the missionhad been captured shortly after they had arrived in roumania.     Since then messages had been received fromthe Mission through the wireless transmitter possessed by M. Maniu.On frequent occasions since 1941* we had told the Russians that we were in contact with M. Maniu.When he had been in Moscow in October, 1943s M, Molotovhad encouraged him to keep in touch with M. Maniu.Accordingly when S.0.E. had consulted the ForeignOffice about the proposal to send the Mission to roumania the Foreign Office had agreed.     Althoughthe Soviet Government had hot actually been informedthat it was intended to send the Mission to Roumaniatheir representative in Cairo, M. Novikov, had seenall messages received from the Mission.     We hadthroughout made it clear to Marshal Antonescu that

there could be no question of his dealing with usapart from the Soviet and United States Governments, andthere was no foundation for the suggestion made byM. Molotov that we were carrying on clandestinediscussions with the Roumanian Government.      It mightbe that the real object of M. Molotov&apos;s complaint wasto establish a case for sending a Soviet Mission to greece.     He suggested that the proper course was forthe reply to M* Molotov to go from the Foreign Officethrough our Ambassador,&apos; who would be instructed to givethe full facts to M. Molotov0     On the questionwhether the Prime Minister should send a reply toM. Molotov the alternatives were:-(a) That Sir A. Clark Kerr should tell M. Molotovthat in view of the tone of-his communications to the Prime Minister no reply would be sent to his telegram of10th May.(b) That the Prime Minister should send a very short reply to the effect that a very fullexplanation would be given through theordinary channels.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs addedthat what had happened emphasised the importance ofmaking it clear in any public statement about theConference of Dominion Prime Ministers that theDominions were in entire agreement with the UnitedKingdom Government both on questions -of strategy andon questions of foreign policy.The War Cabinet -Agreed to the course proposed by theSecretary of State for.Foreign affairs and invited him to submit to the PrimeMinister for approval the draft instructionsto our Ambassador.Offices of the War Cabinet,S.W.1..




</content>
</cab>
