<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/265/0 images: 74-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1936.CONFIDENTIAL.                                                Copy  No. 43CP. 291 (36).CABINET.RETENTION OF THE LEGATION GUARD  AT ADDIS ABABA.        Memorandum  by  the Secretary of State  for Foreign  Affairs.    IT  was  decided  during the  summer of  1935, owing to  the persistentdeterioration  in the relations  between Italy  and Ethiopia  and  the  virtualcertainty that hostilities would  break out  between the two countries at the endof the rains in the early autumn, that it would be necessary, in order to ensurethe safety of the British Legation in Addis Ababa and that of  the many Britishsubjects and protected persons in the capital, to reinforce the existing LegationGuard of two non-commissioned officers and seven other ranks  of the 8th LightCavalry,  Indian Army,  by  a company of the 5th battalion 14th Punjab  Regiment(Sikhs).  This reinforcement, consisting of 4 British officers,  4  Indian officers,129 other ranks  and 11 followers,  reached Addis Ababa early in September oflast year accompanied  by  some 70 tons of ammunition, stores and equipment..On their arrival the Legation was  rapidly put into a state of  defence, with theresult that when, at the beginning of May 1936,  serious disorders broke out onthe departure  of  the Emperor  and  the  fall  of  the  Central  ethiopian government,  hundreds of foreigners whose  lives would  otherwise have beenjeopardised were able to take refuge in the  Legation compound.  The  Guard were also instrumental in either  evacuating the personnel of,  or repulsing attacks against, the United States, Belgian and Turkish Legations.    Addis Ababa was occupied  by the Italian forces on the 5th  May immediately before the beginning of the  rains.  During the months that have elapsed since,a strong garrison, varying between 12,000 and 30,000 men, has been maintained inthe Abyssinian capital.  Although  up to date, doubtless because of climatic andother difficulties, little  attempt  appears to have been made by  the Italian high command  effectively to pacify the country  in the immediate vicinity of thecapital, where there has  been  considerable insurgent  activity throughout therainy season, such raids as  have been made  against the town itself have been repulsed with no great difficulty and without any signs of a disposition on thepart of the urban native  population to rise against the forces of  occupation.In these circumstances, and  notwithstanding the  fact that the railway betweenAddis Ababa and Diredawa has also been raided on a  number of occasions and traffic interrupted for a week or more, His  Majesty&apos;s Charge&quot; d&apos;Affaires at addis ababa, who has been consulted on the subject, considers that owing to  the strengthof the Italian defensive position,  and  with  the  advent of  the  dry season, no appreciable threat can  be  said to exist against the. security of  the capital or its population.   Moreover, Mr.  Roberts  has pointed  out that even  in the unlikely event or  raiders  being able to penetrate into the centre of the city, it would notbe possible for  the British and British-protected residents, whose  number hasbeen greatly reduced since the beginning of the Italian occupation, again to takerefuge in the Legation compound.  Marshal Graziani has forbidden any suchconcentrations of foreigners. For all these reasons Mr. Roberts has  expressedthe opinion that the Legation Guard can  safely  be withdrawn forthwith.      8869  [14027]
     Apart from other considerations, such action is desirable in the interests ofthe troops-themselves.  Owing to the necessity of guarding against any incidentlikely  to  react adversely  upon Anglo-Italian relations,  the  liberty of  the  menhas  had perforce to  be seriously curtailed since  the  Italian occupation.   the moral  and behaviour of  the troops have been  excellent up to date.   But the unfortunate effects of being confined behind barbed wire fences during a  long-period  of  inclement  weather and at  an altitude  of  over  8,000  feet  need noillustration.  Both His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires and the Officer commanding the  Guard, Colonel Charter, have let it be known that the men  are  showing-increasing anxiety  to return to  India, and  that if they did not shortly receiveorders to do so their disappointment would be keen.  These considerations applya fortiori to the small contingent of nine cavalry other ranks  who have now beenstationed  in Addis Ababa for a period of over three  years.   These formed theMinisters escort  in  normal times.  It is not considered,  however, that thewithdrawal of these troops in advance of the main contingent would be advisable,since it might react adversely upon the moral of the latter.     Although since the first week of the Italian  occupation there has been no complaint  from the High Command in  Addis Ababa concerning the retentionof the British Legation Guard,  the presence of these troops has more than  onceformed the subject of informal  representations by  the Italian Government, themost recent  of which  took place two or three  weeks ago.  His Majesty&apos;ambassador  in  Rome has advised that  the withdrawal of  the Guard may beexpected to exert a beneficial influence  on Anglo-Italian relations.     On the 26th  October His  Majesty&apos;s Representative in Paris, acting on instructions,  explained  to the French  Government why the  withdrawal of theGuard was contemplated  at an early date. -.No objection has been raised by theFrench Government, although it does not appear that they for their part intendimmediately to withdraw  the French Legation Guard of some sixty native troopsThese  men, however, were only  moved to Addis Ababa after the riots at thebeginning  of May; they have, therefore, only been in their  present station forsome five  months.   The French  position is  also complicated  by the presence inDiredawa, where there is an important French colony and  where are  situatedthe workshops  of  the railway, of a battalion  of French troops approximately800  strong.  But this force must be regarded  as being  in an entirely different category to the Legation Guards at Addis Ababa; and the problems which arise from its presence in Italian-occupied Abyssinia are for settlement direct betweenthe French and Italian Governments.     As the British Legation is situated on the outskirts of Addis Ababa on theDessie Road, in a locality in which there was, at any rate at the  end of July,considerable insurgent activity, it is proposed to ensure that on the withdrawalof the  Guard the Italian High  Command will assume  full responsibility for the safety  of the Legation staff and property.  This is not to imply that an Italianarmed  force will enter  the compound, but merely that all necessary protectivemeasures will be taken.     In the circumstances  I would suggest that authority be given  to withdraw the Legation Guard when  the moment appears opportune.                          -                                         A. E.Foreign Office, October 30, 1936.

</content>
</cab>
