<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/265/0 images: 257-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
y       (T H I S___DO CUM E N T   IS_THE__PROPERTY   0 F     HIS   B R I TAN In I C_____MA JEST Y&apos;S__GOVERNMENT)  EC RE T.                                               COPY&apos;                             C A B I H JS. Tn.P. 516 (36),                  VOLUNTARY EUTHANASIA LEGALISATION BIBB                   Memorandum by the Minister of Health               I wish to draw the attention of my colleagues to the     Voluntary Euthanasia Legalisation Bill, the second reading of which     is to be moved by Lord ponsonby in the House of Lords on the       Ffcft December.   Put briefly, the object of the Bill is to provide     that subject to certain safeguards,  a duly licensed medical     practitioner may, at the request of  any person of sound mind who is     over the age of SI and is suffering  from illness involving severe     pain and of an incurable and fatal character, administer     Euthanasia, that is, may terminate life by painless means.   The     administrative responsibility ior the  procedure laid down in the     Bill including the making of a number of regulations is imposed on     my Department, although strictly speaking the subject matter of the     Bill has little or no connection with  public health.               The Bill proposes a number of safeguards against abuse     but  it  is plain that the general object of the  Bill is likely to be     a matter of acute controversy.   I understand that great     differences of opinion on this subject are to be found in the     medical  profession itself.    It was  originally  intended that the     second  reading should be moved by the  late Lord Moynihan and the     Society  who are behind the  Bill (a body formed  in 1935 and known as     the  Voluntary Euthanasia Begalisation  Society)  can claim a number     of well-known medical men amongst their supporters.   On the other     hand, I  am advised that a considerable section  of the profession     would regard the Bill with  repugnance.               The Bill is also  certain to  arouse controversy  outside     the  ranks of the medical profession.    In effect, it is a Bill to     regularise suicide in certain defined  circumstances and as such it
K.W.Hovember 20th, 1936.will be opposed by members of the Roman Catholic  Church.Judging by statements appearing in the  publications  of  theSociety promoting the Bill, opinion amongst prominent membersof other religious communities is divided.          In the circumstances, I suggest that  the attitudeof the Government towards the BillTs receiving  a  Second Readingshould be that whilst the question of whether the Bill  shouldreceive a Second Reading or not was one for the House itself,no undertaking for facilities for the Bill  could  be  given bythe Gove government nt.

</content>
</cab>
