<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/265/0 images: 298-300</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet, December, 1936SECRET.CP.  326  (36)                               THE CABINETTHE  ROLE  OF THE BRITISH ARMY      MEMORANDUM BY  THE  SECRETARY  OF  STATE FOR WAR     1. The Cabinet&apos;s decision, with regard to the role of the Army, was stated in theWhite Paper* issued on 3rd March of this year :          &quot; The Army has three main functions to perform.   It has to maintain garrisons    79     overseas in various parts of the  Empire, to provide the military share  in Home  General     Defence, including Anti-Aircraft Defence, Coast Defence and Internal  Security,   3237     and  lastly, in time of emergency or war, to  provide a properly equipped force     ready to proceed overseas wherever it may be  wanted &quot;.     This decision was based on the recommendations of the Defence  RequirementsSub-Committee which   were  accepted  and  supported  by  the Defence  Policy and requirements Sub-Committee.                                                   **     2. The Defence  Requirements Sub-Committee in reviewing the size of the Armyproposed  a role  for it which would require  the provision of a regular Field Force of four divisions, a mobile division, two Air Defence brigades and Army Co-operationSquadrons  of the Royal Air  Force,  together with the  necessary complement  of-.H.Q., Corps, and Lines of Communication Troops.     As regards the Territorial Army,  the  Defence  Requirements Sub-Committeerecorded  that the Army Council aimed at supporting the Regular Field Force by theTerritorial Army, fully equipped on  a modern scale, and  remarked that, as regardsMobilization Equipment and War Reserves, the Territorial Army is little more than a paper force ; the Committee, therefore, proposed the modernization of the 12 territorial divisions in order to give them the necessary material to take part in a modern war.     3. These recommendations as regards the Regular  Army  were  endorsed by the ministerial Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements.  The Sub-Committeeadded that they had  scrutinized  the  proposals regarding  the  Territorial  Army with much care,  and had been informed that, even  if they  were now  approved,  littlecould, in fact, be  done during  the  next three years towards the actual piwision othe  material needed to modernize  the  Territorial  Army  and to  equip it for war.They observed that &quot; there is a limit to what industry can do in the first years, and questions of priority therefore arise, for it is clear that the  prior needs of the RegularArmy, not to mention those-of the Navy and the Air Force, will strain to the utmostour productive capacity.&quot;  &quot; Nevertheless,&quot; they continued &quot; we are fully aware of thedifficulties which beset  the Territorial Army in peace, and we consider all possible steps should be taken to improve their recruiting and efficiency.   Moreover,  we appreciate that it is the desire of the Territorial Army to be assured that, in the event of its being used to reinforce the Regular Army, -it shall do so in its  own units and formations, andnot by draft finding.&quot;     As a result of their deliberations  the Sub-Committee  submitted  the  following conclusions!, amongst others, to the  Cabinet:     &quot;(i) To reserve the decision as to  whether or when the proposals for reconditioning           the Territorial Force can be  implemented for three  years, or until such           time as the industrial situation of the country and  its capacity for output           brings these proposals within the range  of  actual  possibilities by which           time other factors in the  decision may have become clearer.           Jfc             jjfe             Jfe              Jfc             M,           -TV                           TP              *7p             *Jf* Statement Relating to Defence, Cmd. 5107, para. 30.t CP. 26 (36) : para. 21. .COPY  No.  /  g
* 10th Meeting, 1936.t Hansard. Vol. 317, No. 6, col. 733.% Hansard, Vol. 317, No. 6, col. 732.5 Statement relating to Defence, Cmd. 5107, para. 33.    (iv) To  authorize  the  War Office to  state  publicly that the  function of  the            Territorial Field Force is  to  serve wherever it is needed, and that it will            if necessary, be used as a second line, not as drafts, but serving in its own            units and  formations  to reinforce  the  Regular Army  if it goes  abroad.            And, further, that it is the policy of the  Army Council  to  complete  the            peace establishment of the  Territorial Force within  the  next three years,            but that its equipment can only proceed slowly for the present, as priority            must be given to the Regular Army.&quot;     4. The Cabinet approved the report of  the Defence Policy and  Requirements Sub-Committee generally and provisionally on  the understanding that the programmes contained  therein  were &quot; liable to modification  in the light  of new considerations .   .   .  .   and any other new factors  that  may arise, and subject to the conclusions which follow.*     Of these conclusions the two following are pertinent:           &quot; (/)  Section   V.   Army  Programme  and  Requirements.  That  the     approval given to the Army Programme and Requirements,  like the  remainder of     the Report,  is  provisional and  liable to  review  in  the  light  of  changing     circumstances and possibly later decisions  as  to the priority in which  the     requirements of the several Services are to be provided in view of the international     situation and other factors.          (A)  Paragraph  21. That in approving the sixth recommendation referring     to the  Territorial Force,  the Cabinet should take note  that  if, contrary to     expectation, it should be found possible to make a start with the Territorial Force     side of re-equipment before the end of three  years there would  be no objection to     a re-opening of the question with a view to fresh decision.&quot;     5. It will therefore been seen  that the Cabinet are at present committed to  the principle of a Field Army of 5 Regular and 12 Territorial Divisions, and that the only reason for postponing the equipment of the Territorial  Divisions is the doubt whether any substantial  progress  could be  made  with it pending the completion  of  the equipment of the Regular Army.     6. It will be further  noted that certain definite obligations within the role of  the Army fall  properly within the sphere of the Territorial Army,  and it cannot be  too strongly emphasised that this force is an integral part of the British  Army.     In addition to the Home Defence  obligations, the Territorial Army has a definite foreign service liability.   In the words of the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence  :          &quot; It has been accepted that it will provide  the means for  supporting and     expanding our small Regular Army, and officers and men actually sign an agree-     ment to serve outside this country in an emergency .  . . .&quot;f     Our normal garrisons throughout the  Empire are based on the minimum necessary for internal security and local defence until reinforced.   In a war of any magnitude it might be necessary to employ at least a portion of the  Territorial Army  on garrison duties overseas.    Moreover, such a war cannot be fought on the principle of  limited liability, for, to quote again the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence :          &quot;...  Great Britain can never give up until  she is safe again.   That means,    however much we may regret it, that  we shall have to make the maximum effort    until the victory is complete.&quot;%    That maximum effort must be made with a minimum of delay, which presupposesthat the Territorial Army will be available to  support  the Field Force  as rapidly  as circumstances require and permit.    7.  The above  arguments lead logically to  the question of the equipment  of the Territorial  Army, for  if it  is  the  case that &quot; if the  Regular Army  should require support abroad, the Territorial Army  will be called upon to give that support, serving not in  drafts but  in its own units  and formations,it &quot;must be properly equipped &quot;  ready to serve wherever it  may be needed.
     The recommendations of the Defence Policy and  Requirements Sub-committee with regard to implementing the proposals for reconditioning the Territorial Armyare given in paragraph 3 above.  The Cabinet approved this recommendation subjectto the reservation that  &quot; if contrary to expectation, it should be found possible tomake a start with the Territorial Army side of re-equipment before the end of 3years,  there would be no objection  to  a re-opening of  the question with  a view tofresh decision.&quot;  The Director General of  Munitions Production  is of opinion  that itis now possible to make  such a start and that the industrial situation of the countryand its capacity for output brings the proposal within the range of practical possibility.     lie has also made it clear that if it is desired to make possible the use of at  least a portion of the Territorial Army within the next two years (and there can be no doubtthat  this is the case), then  steps must  be  taken forthwith  to provide the necessaryexpansion of productive  capacity.   8.  This does not  mean that  the  output is immediately available, but that  it canbe created if due notice is given, and this without the extravagant expenditure andinterference with industry that would be involved in emergency measures.    Further,and this is an important point, even the increased war potential created by our presentre-armament proposals will fall far short of the maintenance requirements envisaged by the Defence Requirements Sub-Committee.  If, therefore, equipment is postponedand  is left to be carried out simultaneously with maintenance after the declarationof war, the resources  then available will be  insufficient to bear the strain.     If, on the other hand, a start can be made now on the equipment of the  TerritorialArmy, it will, by broadening the basis  of supply, assist materially in the solution ofthe problem of war potential for an army on mobilization.     9. What is wanted is  peace equipment and  such mobilization equipment and reserves as will enable formations to take the held at the earliest date that the  training of personnel will allow.  We must  aim at  reducing any delay after  the outbreak of war to this minimum.  We cannot rely on having time, as we had in the last war, to buildup and equip an army.   Our regular forces are considerably smaller  and  at presentfar less adequately equipped,  if  modern developments  are  taken into  account, thanthey were in 1914.     The programme of equipment must necessarily be spread over a  number  of yearsand, even if authority is given to proceed with it  now, we  cannot hope to  completemore than a small part of it by 1939.  The sooner we start the sooner we  shall reachour ultimate goal.     10.  Experience has  shown that some interval is bound to occur between a cabinet decision and the actual placing of orders resulting  from  that decision, and therefore,if the policy is accepted, the sooner the  decision is reached the better.     Some reluctance  to undertake contracts in connexion with supplying the deficiencyprogramme is still noticeable among firms who fear that they may incur large capitalexpenditure which they  will be unable to  recover when the programme is  completed.The knowledge that repeat orders are coming or can actually be given  will  get rid ofthis reluctance and will  induce the firms to expand and  accelerate their efforts.     It is  obviously  desirable,  as much from  the  point of  view of  His Majesty&apos;sGovernment as from that of their suppliers, that the ultimate goal of endeavour  shouldbe clearly  known from  the start.   Lack of such  knowledge is  already the cause ofhindrance and delay.  A  case in point is  the design of the new  filling factory.  the size of the factory must  obviously depend  upon the demands that will ultimately bemade  upon  it.   Until  those demands  are  ascertained it  would  appear  unwise toproceed too far with the construction of the factory.     The knowledge that the equipment of  the Territorial Army was to be proceeded with would also assist materially recruitment for that Force.     I am, therefore, asking my colleagues to reaffirm  their decision with  regard tothe role of the British Army and in accordance with that  decision  to authorize  the equipment of  the Territorial Army as and  when opportunity  occurs.  Priority, ofcourse, would be given to the needs of the  Regular Army.                                                                         D. C.   THE WAR  OFFICE,       3rd December, 1936.(B36/8) 70 12/36  W.O.P.  109

</content>
</cab>
