<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/117/0 images: 7-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1964CP. (64) 51 Copy No.  5218th February, 1964CABINETTRADE UNIONS AND THE LAWNote by the Minister of LabourFollowing the Cabinefs discussion on Thursday, 13th February (CM. (64) 11thConclusions, Minute 9) I am circulating for the information of my colleagues theattached Report of the Official Committee on Trade Unions and the Law.J. G.Ministry of Labour, S.W. 1,19th February, 1964.4341
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No.    5 2Reportof theOfficial Committee on Trade unions and the LawMay 1964
REPORT OF THE OFFICIAL COMMITTEE ON TRADE unions and THE LAW  .Terms of Reference and MembershipThe Committee was set up in accordance with a decision of the Home AffairsCommittee (H.A. (63) 7th Meeting, paragraph 4) with the following terms ofreference:&quot; To consider the law relating to trade unions and employers&apos; associations,and to report what changes, if any, are desirable.&quot;2.   The membership of the committee was as follows:Sir James Dunnett, K.C.B., C.M.G., Ministry of Labour (Chairman)Sir Charles Cunningham, K.C.B., K.B.E., C.V.O., Home office mr. D. W. Dobson, C.B., O.B.E., Lord Chancellors office mr. G. E. Dudman, Law Officers&apos; DepartmentMr. A. C. B. Reid, Lord Advocated DepartmentMr. P. H. St. John Wilson, C.B., C.B.E., Ministry of labour mr. H. W. W. Huxham, C.B.E., Ministry of labour mr. D. C. Barnes, C.B., Ministry of labour mr. W. A. H. Druitt, C.B., Treasury Solicitors office mr. S. D. Musson, C.B., M.B.E., Registry of Friendly SocietiesThe secretaries were:Mr. J. Palmer, Cabinet office mr. J. S. Cassels, Ministry of LabourContents of Report3.   We have divided our report into four parts, as follows:ParagraphsPart I: Unofficial Strikes......      ...      ...... 5-76Part II: The Conduct of Trade Union Affairs...... 77-131Part III: Other Possible Changes in the Law  ...... 132-160Part IV: Concluding Remarks............ 161-163,4. Our conclusions are summarised in Appendix I. Appendix II examinescertain problems involved in making collective agreements legally enforceable. in considering possible courses of action we have studied law and practice in certain other countries, and information about these is set out in Appendix III.
REPORT OF THE OFFICIAL COMMITTEE ON TRADE unions and THE LAW  .Terms of Reference and MembershipThe Committee was set up in accordance with a decision of the Home AffairsCommittee (H.A. (63) 7th Meeting, paragraph 4) with the following terms ofreference:&quot; To consider the law relating to trade unions and employers&apos; associations,and to report what changes, if any, are desirable.&quot;2.   The membership of the committee was as follows:Sir James Dunnett, K.C.B., C.M.G., Ministry of Labour (Chairman)Sir Charles Cunningham, K.C.B., K.B.E., C.V.O., Home office mr. D. W. Dobson, C.B., O.B.E., Lord Chancellors office mr. G. E. Dudman, Law Officers&apos; DepartmentMr. A. C. B. Reid, Lord Advocated DepartmentMr. P. H. St. John Wilson, C.B., C.B.E., Ministry of labour mr. H. W. W. Huxham, C.B.E., Ministry of labour mr. D. C. Barnes, C.B., Ministry of labour mr. W. A. H. Druitt, C.B., Treasury Solicitors office mr. S. D. Musson, C.B., M.B.E., Registry of Friendly SocietiesThe secretaries were:Mr. J. Palmer, Cabinet office mr. J. S. Cassels, Ministry of LabourContents of Report3.   We have divided our report into four parts, as follows:ParagraphsPart I: Unofficial Strikes......      ...      ...... 5-76Part II: The Conduct of Trade Union Affairs...... 77-131Part III: Other Possible Changes in the Law  ...... 132-160Part IV: Concluding Remarks............ 161-163,4. Our conclusions are summarised in Appendix I. Appendix II examinescertain problems involved in making collective agreements legally enforceable. in considering possible courses of action we have studied law and practice in certain other countries, and information about these is set out in Appendix III.
PART I.-UNOFFICIAL STRIKESNature and significance of unofficial strikes5. An unofficial strike is a strike which does not have official trade unionbacking. In practice unofficial strikes very commonly have two other characteristics.First, they almost always take place with little or no warning. The strikers aretherefore usually acting in breach of their individual contracts of employmentsSecondly, a great many unofficial strikes take place before a procedure for the peaceful settlement of disputes under a relevant collective agreement has been used. Such procedures exist in all important sections of industry but would not cover undertakings to which collective agreements do not apply because the employer is not a member of an employers&apos; association and has not concluded aseparate agreement of his own.6. As we say later (paragraph 25) we do not recommend any change in thelaw as it applies to unofficial strikes as such. Any remedy that could becontemplated would have to deal with all strikes in breach of an undertaking,whether the undertaking binding the individual under his contract of employment or the undertaking which the parties to a collective agreement have assumed. Achange of this kind could affect official strikes as well as unofficial. In practice this is no disadvantage. Official strikes in breach of undertakings are not commonand where they occur there is no reason why they should not be dealt with in thesame way as any other strikes in breach of undertakings.7. Unofficial strikes are important first because of the direct disruption and delay they cause to industry. The damage is almost certainly greater than appearson the surface. The delays in delivery which result may lead to the cancellation of orders, and if an industry or company has a reputation for being prone to suchstrikes the resulting uncertainty about delivery may deter customers from placing orders at all.8. Even more important is the fact that unofficial strikes are a symptom of a breakdown in the authority of the trade unions. Traditionally industry has had very great freedom in matters of industrial relations. Over the greater part ofindustry terms and conditions are settled on a voluntary basis by collectivenegotiations between employers or employers&apos; associations and trade unionsrepresenting employees. This system presupposes that the organisations concerned are able to represent the views of their members and see that effect is given to terms to which they agree. The whole structure is undermined if in fact one sideor the other cannot carry out its undertakings.9. Indeed the very considerable prestige of leaders of the trade union movement and their claims to have an important influence in national affairs canonly be justified if it can be said that they carry their membership with them andthat in committing themselves to a policy they are not only speaking for themselvesbut are able to commit their members as well. Seen in this light the importance of unofficial strikes and the problems that underlie them needs no stressing.Incidence of unofficial strikes10. No figures for unofficial strikes are published, but the Ministry of labour has kept estimated figures since 1960. In the three years 1960-62 there was anannual average of about 2,650 strikes, of which no less than 2,480, or about 94 percent were unofficial. The average number of days lost through stoppages in eachof these years was slightly below 4 million, and of these approximately 53 per centwere due to unofficial strikes (though this proportion would have been much higherbut for the effect of two official one-day token stoppages of engineering and shipbuilding workers in 1962 which led to the loss of 3-1 million days). Manyunofficial strikes are of short duration: in 1962 over 60 per cent of them were overin two days or less. In 1962, 609,110 workers took part in unofficial strikes. Theyare practically all local.* Normally in order to avoid a breach of contract an employee intending to strike must give the equivalent of notice of termination and withdraw his labour only when the period of notice has expired.Most industrial workers are required under their contracts to give one week&apos;s notice of termination,and that is the minimum they will be required to give under the Contracts of Employment Act, 1963.
11. The number of strikes each year is now at a much higher level than inthe years before the war: in the five-year period 1935-39 the annual average wasabout 860. Although there are no separate figures for unofficial strikes before thewar it is clear that the incidence of unofficial strikes has greatly increased.12. Of the 2,350 unofficial strikes which took place last year over half 1,203 were in coalmining. There has always been a high proportion in this industry, butin recent years it has gone down somewhat. Other industries with substantial numbers of unofficial strikes in 1962 were construction (296), engineering (193),motor vehicles and cycles (109), metal manufacture (78), shipbuilding and marine engineering (72) and water transport and docks (63). In the period 1960-62, ascompared with the previous three years, there were marked increases in the numberof strikes in construction, engineering, motor vehicles and metal manufacture, andin all these industries a very high proportion of strikes is unofficial.13. In the first nine months of 1963 both the number of strikes (official andunofficial) and the number of days lost through them were well below the comparable figures for 1962: there were 1,500 strikes as compared with 1,993,and li million days lost as compared with nearly 5 million.* It is too early to say whether this is more than a temporary improvement.Causes of unofficial strikes14. A number of factors have helped to create conditions in which unofficial strikes are likely to occur. The period since the war has seen a great increase inthe power of local trade union officials at the expense of national leaders. This isthe result of full employment and rising prosperity. When as a result ofunemployment workers are in a weak position in relation to their employers theyare bound to rely on collective action on a wide scale to defend their interests, andthis means that effective power rests with the national leadership. Conversely, ina time of prosperity national agreements in practice often set only minimum standards and further negotiations to establish extras of various kinds go onlocally. Employers are inclined to give way in the face of strikes or threats of strikesrather than have production interrupted and so give their competitors an advantage.They may in any case want to offer extra pay in order to attract sufficient labour.Moreover, with the main objectives secure, greater attention is concentrated on other matters which are essentially matters for local settlement overtimearrangements, shift-work rotas and so on. In addition many workers (nearly halfin manufacturing industry) are paid on piece-rate systems which are subject tolocal negotiation.15. The key figure in these local negotiations tends to be the shop steward.Shop stewards are workers&apos; representatives within the individual firm, elected bythe workers themselves and authorised to act as officials by the unions to whichthey belong. A single firm will often have employees belonging to a number ofdifferent trade unions in its employment and therefore shop stewards of differenttrade unions.16. It is here that a breakdown in the line of responsibility from union executives is prone to occur. Generally speaking trade unions are organised bydistricts which are sub-divided into branches, each of which has a branchsecretary, who may be full-time but much more often is not. A large firm mayhave a branch secretary allocated to it, but many branch secretaries cover a large area and many firms, and are able neither to keep in close touch with what is going on in each firm nor to ensure that the union&apos;s policy is consistently carried out bythe shop stewards in each firm. In some cases also district or local organisers, whoare full-time union officials,-take part in local negotiations to the exclusion of the branch secretary. Moreover, shop stewards within a firm are bound to take acommon line in dealing with management. It may not always be easy to reconcilethis necessity with the divergent official policies of the various unions to whichthey belong, and the tendency therefore is for shop stewards&apos; committees to act independently without being held accountable for what they do. They naturallytend also to assume all the powers they regard as necessary for the purpose of the* This includes the 3J million days lost through token stoppages in engineering and shipbuilding(see paragraph 10).
negotiations they have to carry out, including the right to call strikes. They may feel that agreed disputes procedures hamper them unnecessarily, especially if theseinvolve long-drawn-out negotiations at district and national level.17. We do not wish to imply either that shop stewards are synonymous withtrouble-makers or that they are responsible for all unofficial strikes. Shop stewardshave a vital job to do and the great majority of them do it conscientiously. Someunofficial strikes are led by people with no official position in their unions, and insome industries there are no shop stewards. Nevertheless it is true that it is veryoften shop stewards who call unofficial strikes and they illustrate in acute formthe problems of organisation facing the unions to-day. The present situation lendsitself to abuse and the activities of extremists. It would obviously help if therewere more full-time officials. But the real remedy, so far as the trade unions areconcerned, may lie in fundamental reform rather than in efforts to strengthenexisting structures.18. It would be a mistake to think that the faults which give rise to unofficial strikes lie only with the trade unions. Employers contribute their share. Theattitude of many employers towards their workpeople is out of date. They have failed to come to terms with the shift in the balance of power in industry. Theyhave not recognised that rising standards of education and training are producing a work force which is no longer content to be given orders but feels it has theright and the ability to have a say in the making of decisions which affect it. Someclaim to stick to rights they are no longer able to exercise, such as the right to dismiss employees without giving a reason. Some are slow to recognise the rightof trade unions to represent their workpeople, and consult workers&apos; representatives to the minimum practicable extent.19. The changing pattern of industry has also created new difficulties. the trend towards larger units and higher mechanisation is profoundly alteringproblems of human relations. Managements tend to become more remote and communications are more difficult. Highly mechanised production lines makeheavy physical demands on the worker, while at the same time many jobs are sodull that any diversion is welcome and small matters such as tea-breaks assume anexaggerated importance. Many firms have been slow to respond to these problems,and too few give adequate considerable at the highest level to personnel matters.20. To sum up, the causes of unofficial strikes are complex. There is no simpleremedy for them based on repressive legislation. Many of the problems cannot bemet by legislation at all. The only kind of legislation worth considering wouldhave the aim of assisting industry to deal with the problems, and it would onlysucceed if it were generally accepted as being reasonable and fair as between employers and workers.Aims which legislation might have21. The trade unions. It appears that the main aim of legislation shouldbe to assist or put pressure on the trade unions to put their house in order and toencourage changes which are necessary to their efficiency. The hope would be to restore the authority of union leaders. This the unions could in part bring about by such means as the appointment of more full-time officials. It would also bedesirable for structural weaknesses at local level to be put right. The multiplicity ofunions in many industries and firms is a major defect; here unions based on individual industries offer a theoretical solution, but in practice progress only seems likely by means of amalgamations and ad hoc agreements on spheres of influence,and this is bound to be slow.22. The trade unions, or at least some of the leaders of the trade union movement are already taking some action, and it would be necessary to take account of this. On the instructions of the 1962 Trades Union Congress theT.U.C. General Council is reviewing &quot; the possibility of reorganising the structure of both the T.U.C. and the British trade union movement with a view to making it better fitted to meet modern industrial conditions &quot;. Trade union amalgamationstake place from time to time. Trade union executives are on occasion prepared totake a firm line with militant shop stewards: for example, the E.T.U. expelledMr. Charles Doyle who led the unofficial overtime ban in the electricity supply industry in January 1962. Attention is also being given to training for shop stewards.
23. There are clearly limits to what legislation could do, and it would benecessary to watch the danger that legal sanctions might do no good and might do positive harm to those trade unions which are already doing whatever is reasonable and practicable to bring matters under control.24. Employers. As regards employers the aim should, it seems, be to induce them to come to terms with the real needs of their present situation and to establishprocedures whereby decisions can be made rationally and without recourse to force on either side. Progressive employers have long been showing what can bedone by such means as strengthening communications within the firm and sobridging the gap between the board-room and the shop floor; by taking full account of labour /management relations at the highest level of decision-making;and by improving the selection and training of supervisors, who are key figures atshop floor level. Fundamentally this entails a basic change in attitude and a readiness to accept trade unionism and to give up theoretical rights which cannot in practice be exercised in return for the recognition by workers&apos; representatives ofthe need for co-operation and responsibility.Possible changes in the law: the trade unions(i) Criminal penalties for taking part in unofficial strikes25. The most obvious direct approach would be to make unofficial strikes assuch illegal. However we reject this as totally unacceptable in principle. It would obviously be unthinkable to let the question whether a strike is illegal or not dependon whether it has trade union backing especially as a dispute involving severalunions may be recognised as official by some and not by others. It would also bringimmense pressure to bear on trade union leaders to recognise all stoppages asofficial and so drive the moderates into the camp of the extremists.(ii) Criminal penalties for striking in breach of contract26. Another scarcely less direct approach would be to make it a criminal offence to strike in breach of contract, but this too is not a practical possibility.It would be a drastic step to import criminal sanctions into the civil question ofbreach of contract, unless there were special circumstances such as the need tosafeguard essential supplies or to safeguard human life or valuable property.*27. Employers would be reluctant to instigate or assist prosecutions becauseof the harm it would do to relations with their employees. Moreover in the largerstrikes it would be extremely difficult to enforce the law against all the strikersinvolved. The number of prosecutions would be so small in relation to the numberof known offences that the law would be brought into disrepute. And it wouldbe contrary to accepted practice to create a criminal offence with the certainknowledge that it would not be fully enforced.(iii) Criminal penalties for inducing strikes in breach of contract28. A further and at first sight more attractive possibility would be to makeit an offence to induce a strike in breach of contract. A similar idea was advanced by Mr. Aidan Crawley, M.P., in support of an amendment he proposed to the contracts of Employment Act during its passage through Parliament. Mr. Crawleyenvisaged that one effect of his amendment (which is discussed below inparagraphs 39-42) would be to enable the Crown to institute proceedings for criminal conspiracy at common law against people who persistently and flagrantlyinduce others to strike in breach of contract. (In fact the actual amendment would not have had this effect.)29. However we do not think that it would in fact be desirable for it to be a criminal offence to induce strikes in breach of contract. Some of the objectionsin paragraph 27 would apply: employers would be reluctant to assist prosecutions,and the number of prosecutions would be very small in relation to the number ofknown offences. Even given the co-operation of an employer, the securing of thenecessary evidence on which to base charges of inducing breaches of contractwould present additional difficulties. There would be a further objection to* Section 5 of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875, makes it an offence for aperson to break his contract of employment wilfully or maliciously if he knows or has reasonable cause to.believe that the probable result will be to endanger life or expose valuable property todestruction or serious injury. For section 4 of the Act, see paragraphs 150-152 below.
the particular suggestion that the possibility of indicting people for criminalconspiracy at common law should be revived. This would entail amending one ofthe provisions of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875, which isregarded as laying the foundation of elementary trade union liberties, and the revival of machinery of the law which has not operated since 1875 would inevitably appear repressive and reactionary.30. We have so far discussed and rejected suggestions for creatingcriminal offences of various kinds in connection with strikes. We deal below inparagraphs 39-57 with the possibility of altering the law as it affects civil remediesfor strike action.(iv) Strengthening of trade union rules so as to deal with unofficial strike leaders31. Theoretically at any rate another approach to the problems of unofficial strikes as such would be to establish some degree of control over the drafting ofthe rules of trade unions so far as they relate to members or to officials, includingshop stewards, who exceed their powers, e.g., by leading an unofficial strike.However, this would not in itself be enough. It would be necessary to have some means to compel unions to exercise their powers.32. In fact however unions do in general already have adequate powers todiscipline their members. What they sometimes lack is the will to exercise them.It does not seem feasible to compel them from outside to do so by direct means.That could only be done by prescribing that the rules should provide for an automatic penalty for given offences (such as leading unauthorised strikes) and giving someone outside the union a right to force it to apply the rules. But itwould be unthinkable to give this power to employers and it would throw undueresponsibility on any public authority, such as the Chief Registrar of friendly societies, to give it to him. Besides, automatic penalties would mean that itwould not be possible to take the differing circumstances of different strikesinto account and would result for example in the unfair penalising of shop stewards when the real impetus for a strike came from the men themselves or fromother individuals, who could not always be easily identified. Finally, faced withthe alternatives of making a strike official or expelling a strike leader, unionscould be pardoned for choosing the first alternative.(v) Possibility of compulsory arbitration33. During the war strikes were banned and there was provision for compulsory arbitration in the event of disputes, i.e., either party to a dispute hadthe right to invoke arbitration and the decision of the arbitration tribunal waslegally binding. Compulsory arbitration continued after the war for a considerable time after the ban on strikes was lifted, but it was finally discontinued because in practice the benefits of compulsory arbitration lay entirely with the unions andit therefore no longer had the support of employers.34. It might be thought that compulsory arbitration could provide a solution to unofficial strikes by enabling grievance to be settled quickly and impartially.In fact however its introduction would be unlikely to help. A choice would haveto be made whether to allow unofficial spokesmen as well as official union leadersaccess to arbitration. If they were allowed access it would wholly undermineexisting agreed procedures for the settlement of disputes, which, whatever theirdefects, have been devised by those concerned to meet their own needs and aretherefore at least as likely to be effective as machinery imposed from outside.Even more, it would also wholly undermine the authority of official union leaders. If on the other hand only official union leaders had the right of access,presumably only after existing voluntary procedures had been exhausted without success, there is no reason to think that compulsory arbitration would be anymore successful than it has been in the past in preventing unofficial action. even when strikes were illegal during and immediately after the war large numbers of unofficial strikes nevertheless took place and legal sanctions were powerless toprevent them.(vi) Setting up of fact-finding machinery35. We understand the Ministry of Labour is exploring the possibility of apilot experiment in the use of fact-finding machinery to investigate unofficialdisputes. At present Ministry of Labour officials intervene in unofficial strikes in
an attempt to conciliate only in exceptional circumstances, and even then confinethemselves to discussion with employers and official union leaders. This is because to do otherwise would inevitably give some degree of recognition to the unofficial strike leaders, and both employers and trade union leaders are opposedto this. On the other hand, a purely fact-finding body might avoid the pitfallsthat would await a conciliator. Such a body would not prejudice in any way theuse of agreed disputes procedures. Its task would merely be to establish and make public the causes and circumstances of disputes with the minimum of delay.Many unofficial strikes are hasty and ill-considered, and the setting out of thefacts and the opportunity for public comment on them could often be expected to lead to second and wiser thoughts.36. The Minister of Labour already has power to set up inquiries into the causes of particular disputes but not to appoint standing fact-finding bodies for an indefinite duration. At present Courts of Inquiry and similar bodies are normallyappointed only to investigate major disputes, and the members of these bodies areof appropriate eminence. It would therefore be a new departure to hold inquiriesinto relatively frequent and minor disputes such as unofficial strikes.37. The Ministry has opened discussions informally with the british employers&apos; Confederation and the T.U.C. about the possibility of carrying out apilot experiment in the use of fact-finding machinery to investigate unofficialdisputes in the engineering industry in the Ministry&apos;s Midland Region. As a first step it is essential to secure the agreement of employers and trade unions,particularly those in the area concerned. The intention is to set up a teamconsisting of an independent chairman (who might be from the Ministry of Labouror might be someone of independent standing unconnected with the Ministry),an employers&apos; nominee and a trade union nominee. The team would be availableto investigate at short notice actual or threatened unofficial disputes in theengineering industry in the Midlands and it would operate either at the requestof an employer (or his federation) or of a trade union with members directly concerned or at the initiative of the Ministry. The team would be required toestablish the causes and circumstances of the dispute to the best of its ability,and for this purpose would see representatives of the unofficial strikers, of the employer and of the trade unions. The team would not be asked to make recommendations. It would report to the Ministry of Labour as quickly as possible and the Ministry would send copies of the report to the various parties concerned(including the unofficial spokesmen) and also make it available to the Press andthe public.38. We strongly support an experiment on the lines outlined above. Asindicated in paragraph 36 above the Minister of Labour has not got power toappoint standing fact-finding bodies for an indefinite duration. Although it isthought his existing powers are adequate for the purposes of an experiment onthe lines proposed which is limited in time, legislation would be necessary if thepractice of establishing standing fact-finding bodies is to be extended. We therefore recommend that if the experiment is undertaken and proves successfulconsideration should be given to extending the Minister of Labour&apos;s powers toenable him to set up standing fact-finding bodies to investigate the causes of disputes as and when they occur.(vii) C/vz7 remedies against those who induce others to break their contracts ofemployment39. Mr. Aidan Crawley, M.P., proposed an amendment at the committee stage of the Contracts of Employment Bill which would have had the effect ofrepealing section 3 of the Trade Disputes Act, 1906, and making it possible tobring an action against a person who induces employees to break their contracts of employment in pursuance of a trade dispute. A similar suggestion was embodied in an amendment moved by Mr. Graham Page, M.P., at the report stage.40. This suggestion starts with the psychological disadvantage that it proposes a return to the situation which existed before the 1906 Act, and thereforehas the appearance of an attack on long-established rights. This is not its onlydisadvantage. Employers already have the right to sue employees who go on strike in breach of their individual contracts, but very rarely exercise it because they recognise that it would worsen rather than improve relations and that no
worthwhile damages would be awarded. An action for damages against a strikeleader for inducing breaches of contract might result in the award of largerdamages, but these would often be difficult or impossible to recover because theindividual concerned could not pay, and the danger of worsening relations would remain. It might also become the practice for a resumption of work to be conditional on a promise that no legal action would be taken.41. If the immunity of individuals were to be removed it would be logicalalso to remove the immunity of the trade unions as such. At first sight this hasattractions. Unofficial strike leaders are very often shop stewards, who are union officials. The danger of having damages awarded against it might be expected toencourage a union to discipline shop stewards who exceed their authority and todisown their actions.42. Again however there are serious difficulties. The damages awardedagainst a union might be very substantial indeed, and the result of legal action might very well be therefore not to bring about an increase in union authority butto ruin the union financially, the reverse of what is intended. There would indeed be a serious risk that extremists would foresee this possibility and engineerunofficial strikes precisely in order to overthrow the unions. We therefore conclude that a change of this kind in the law would not be desirable.(viii) Making collective agreements legally enforceable43. A number of people, including for example Professor Kahn-Freund whois Professor of Law at London University and an authority on labour law, havesuggested that collective agreements should be made enforceable at law. an amendment which had this intention was moved by Mr. Graham Page, M.P., atthe committee stage of the Contracts of Employment Bill. He also moved an amendment at the report stage which evidently had the intention that all the relevant terms of a collective agreement, including agreed procedures for settlingdisputes, should become part of the terms of individual contracts of employment,and that any inducement to cause a breach should be actionable. In some waysMr. Crawley&apos;s views discussed in paragraphs 39-42 would be met by makingcollective agreements enforceable.44. Although an individual employer and employee may either expressly orby implication incorporate terms in a collective agreement into the contract bindingthem, which is of course then enforceable in the courts, most collective agreements are not enforceable as such. Section 4 (4) of the Trade Union Act, 187L preventsagreements between one trade union and another being enforced as such in thecourts, and any collective agreement between a trade union and an employers&apos;association which is legally a trade union (as many are) Comes into this category.Others although not affected by the 1871 Act, e.g., where the agreement is between a union and a single employer, may not be enforceable in the courts because theparties to them did not intend to create a legal relationship.45. Collective agreements are legally enforceable in many other countries.Making them enforceable in this country would clearly have importantconsequences. We have considered carefully the manner in which this might bedone and the possible results that might be achieved.46. It is worth noting at this point a long-established voluntary arrangement the boot and shoe industry. The industry is covered by an agreement which provides that &quot; no strike or lock-out shall be entered into on the part of any bodyof workmen, members of the National Union, or any manufacturers represented on any Local Board of Arbitration &quot;. Under a Trust Deed a guarantee fund,contributed to equally by both sides, was vested in trustees. If any strike Orlock-out takes place and lasts more than three working days the employers&apos;federation or the union as the case may be may make a claim for damages or a penalty to be paid out of the guaranteed fund, and if it is successful the other party to the agreement is to make the fund good by the same amount within28 days.47. The immediate relevance of making collective agreements enforceablewould be that it would enable employers to proceed against trade unions for failing to observe agreed procedures for the peaceful settlement of disputes. (The reversewould also be true: trade unions could sue employers who ignored agreed
procedures.) Pressure would thus be put on the trade unions to take effective action to discipline those who lead unofficial strikes, who are always tradeunion members and very often shop stewards, and hence trade union officials,as well.48. It is sometimes alleged in defence of the existing legal position that tradeunions in negotiating agreements are acting only as agents on behalf of their members. Making collective agreements enforceable would mean that the parties would at any rate to a large extent be regarded as principals rather than agents.To do so broadly corresponds with the facts of the situation, provided that sufficient allowance is made for the limits to which trade unions can be expectedto go in securing compliance by their members.49. An immediate result of making collective agreements enforceable wouldbe that it would oblige employers to observe the terms relating to wages, holidays,etc. In practice however this would be less of an advantage to the trade unionsthan might at first appear. In general, terms are already observed by employers.Moreover section 8 of the Terms and Conditions of Employment Act, 1959,provides a procedure whereby employers may be legally obliged to observe termsnot less favourable than those established in a relevant collective agreement. this procedure may be used even against employers who are not parties to the collective agreement in question, and therefore goes further than makingagreements enforceable would.50. There are serious difficulties in the way of making collective agreementslegally enforceable in the same way as other contracts. There would in the firstplace (as mentioned in paragraph 55) be strong opposition to the whole conceptfrom the trade unions. To counter this (as well as on more general grounds) itwould be desirable to propose that jurisdiction should be exercised not by theordinary courts, but by special Labour Courts some of whose members would bedrawn from the ranks of trade unionists. Again, it would be necessary to impose a limit on damages, which might otherwise be so large as to ruin trade unions.The unions would no doubt also try to reduce their potential liability. They mightfor example seek to secure the incorporation in collective agreements of provisionslimiting their responsibility to doing all they could to prevent strikes. Thiswould, however, itself be an advance, since it would be part of the aim of makingcollective agreements legally enforceable to secure this very result, and manytrade unions would in consequence have to do a good deal more to resolveunofficial disputes, e.g., by disciplining shop stewards, than they commonly do atpresent. Finally employers would still have to decide whether they were willingto take the risk of worsening industrial relations by bringing an action to enforcean agreement; though this unwillingness might be less if the jurisdiction lay withspecial Labour Courts.51. In the light of these considerations the broad outline of a scheme forthe enforcement of collective agreements might be as follows:(i) it would be open to an employees association which is a party to a collective agreement, to any employer affiliated to such an association and to any employer who is himself directly a party to a collective agreement to bring an action against a trade union or trade unions or individual trade union members for breach of a collective agreement;(ii) trade unions and trade union members would likewise be able to sueemployers and employers&apos; associations on the same grounds;(iii) actions might also be brought against individuals, whether members of arepresentative organisation or not, for inducing or conspiring to secure a breach of a collective agreement;(iv) actions would be brought before a Labour Court (or Courts) composedof lawyers acting as chairmen and of experienced employers and trade unionists;(v) the Labour Court(s) would have power to give binding and enforceabledecisions;(vi) there would be prescribed scales of maximum damages and the LabourCourt(s) would make such awards as seemed reasonable within themaxima;
(vii) the Labour Court(s) would also have power, pending a final settlement,to grant an injunction ordering an organisation, or an employerbelonging to an organisation, which is party to a collective agreement to cease from or bring to an end a breach of the agreement;(viii) failure to comply with an injunction, or to comply so far as is reasonablypossible, would be punishable by a fine as a contempt of court.52. The question of damages is crucial. It would be necessary to fix anupper limit to the amount of damages that could be awarded against trade unions and against individual trade union members. We have not worked out scales indetail, but a possible scale of maximum damages against a union for a breach of a collective agreement might for example be on the following lines (the figures hereused being arbitrarily chosen):Not more than  50 per day in respect of a breach involving less than100 members;Not more than  100 per day in respect of a breach involving 100-999members;Not more than  200 per day in respect of a breach involving 1,000-4,999members;Not more than  500 per day in respect of a breach involving 5,000 ormore members.Damages against individual trade union members might for example be restricted to  15 for breach of a collective agreement and  50 for inducing others to breaka collective agreement.53. It would be fundamental to any scheme that a Labour Court would have discretion to judge how far a union should be held responsible for a particularbreach and would be free to allot blame as between the union, unofficial strikeleaders and the individual members themselves. It would also be free to take account of any actions of an employer which, while not in contravention of a collective agreement, might have been calculated to provoke a breach by hisemployees. The inclusion of people with industrial experience as members of a labour Court would both assist the court in the exercise of its discretion and help to make its decisions acceptable to industry and to the public.54. A further discussion of the problems which would arise in connectionwith the type of scheme outlined above is attached as Appendix II.55. We consider that such a scheme would provide as practicable a meansas any of giving legal effect to collective agreements. There can however be little doubt that the trade union movement would be most strongly opposed to anyproposal for making collective agreements enforceable. They could be expectedto represent legislation on these lines as a major attack on the freedom and immunities they have enjoyed since 1906.56. Against this particular argument it could be pointed out that legislation would by no means turn the clock back to 1906. It would affect only strikes in breach of a collective agreement, in other words strikes in circumstances wherethe union had already, at an earlier date, freely renounced its right to call astrike. The financial penalties to which a union could be exposed would be strictly limited a vital difference and a union could always plead that it had doneits best to honour an agreement, even if without success.57. We make no recommendation as to whether the balance of advantage isin favour of legislation on the lines we have discussed or not. If however it wereproceeded with, it would certainly be essential to make it abundantly clear thatthe intention was not to attack or in any way weaken the trade union movement,but rather the reverse. It would help to do this if the same legislation were toinclude measures which would obviously be of direct benefit to employees and unions. We discuss possible measures of this kind in paragraphs 60-76 of our report.(ix) Amending the law on trade union mergers and changes of name58. As we say above in paragraph 21 it seems likely that progress in improving the structure of the trade union movement will in practice be made bymeans of further amalgamations. At present for two or more unions to amalgamate
each of the unions concerned must hold a ballot of its members, and for a vote in favour to be valid at least 50 per cent of the members must vote in the ballotand the voting must be at least 6 to 5 in favour. A merger can also be effected by a union transferring its engagements to another union, which thus takes itover. A special resolution has to be passed in the union making the transfer by a two-thirds majority of those attending a general meeting, and the union has alsoto obtain the consent of two-thirds of its members at meetings or in writing, unlessthe Chief Registrar of Friendly Societies dispenses with the need for this.59. In July 1963 a deputation from the T.U.C. urged the Minister of Labour(then Mr. Hare) to introduce legislation to amend and bring up to date the lawon trade union mergers and changes of name,* which they said caused serious difficulties in present-day circumstances and hampered progress. Mr. Hare saidthat he was in sympathy with the views expressed by the deputation, whichconfirmed his own opinion that the law needed review. The Home AffairsCommittee gave the Minister of Labour authority to have a Bill prepared with aview to presentation by a Private Member (HA. (63) 20th Meeting, paragraph 2).This has been done and the Bill is to receive its second reading on 31st January.Possible changes in the law: employers(i) Dismissals procedures60. Legally an employer has the right to dismiss any employee at any timeprovided that he gives the notice required by the contract. He is not obliged togive any reason. In practice the extent to which employers are able to exercisethis right varies very considerably. The recent disputes at Ford&apos;s show that an employer may get into a position where it is very difficult to sack a confirmedtrouble-maker because of the reaction it will cause among his employees.61. In general, procedures for settling whether dismissals are justified onwider grounds have not been well developed in this country. In coalmining andthe docks there is joint machinery for dealing with appeals against dismissals.In industry generally dismissals may give rise to disputes and be dealt with throughdisputes machinery, but the issues are not usually resolved by arbitration but by negotiation in which the relative strengths of the two sides count at least as muchas the merits of the case. A few progressive firms have set up special committees on which workers are strongly represented to consider appeals against dismissal.62. In October 1961 the British Employers&apos; Confederation and the T.U.C.agreed to have joint talks about dismissals procedures after discussion of thequestion in the National Joint Advisory Council. These have not so far made anyprogress.63. In June 1963 the International Labour Conference adopted a recommendation (No. 119) on termination of employment at the initiative of the employer. Paragraph 4 of this provides:&quot; A worker who feels that his employment has been unjustifiablyterminated should be entitled, unless the matter has been satisfactorilydetermined through such procedures within the undertaking, establishmentor service, as may exist or be established consistent with this Recommendation,to appeal, within a reasonable time, against that termination with theassistance, where the worker so requests, of a person representing him to a body established under a collective agreement or to a neutral body such as acourt, an arbitrator, an arbitration committee or a similar body.&quot;The Recommendation does not necessarily have to be given effect statutorily, andsuch means as collective agreements may be used. The Governments attitude tothe Recommendation is at present under consideration; under the I.L.O.Constitution it must be announced to Parliament if possible by June 1964, and atthe latest by December 1964.64. We think that the present position is out of line with needs in industryto-day. The idea that the parties to the contract of employment are equals, andthat it matters no more to one than the other whether the employment relationship* Under section 11 of the Trade Union Act Amendment Act, 1876, a registered trade union needsthe consent of at least two-thirds of its members to change its name.
is ended, is unreal. It would be reasonable to put on the employer an obligationwhen dismissing an employee to show, if challenged, that the dismissal is reasonable in economic and social terms.65. We recommend therefore that consideration be given to the possibilityof introducing legislation on dismissals under which:(i) the concept of &quot; justifiable dismissal &quot; would be developed so that an employer may only dismiss an employee if the employee&apos;s performanceor conduct, or the efficient running of the undertaking, makes itjustified; and(ii) employees who consider that they have been unjustifiably dismissed mayappeal to an independent tribunal, perhaps a Labour Court constitutedon the lines described in paragraph 51 above.66. Such legislation would promote a sense of security at work and wouldfit in well with the other measures the Government are taking with the sameobject (e.g., the Contracts of Employment Act and the improvement of provisionfor redundancy). From the point of view of the reduction of unofficial strikes its immediate relevance would be:(i) that it should reduce the number of disputes over dismissals anddismissals give rise to over 10 per cent of all stoppages; and(ii) that it should enable employers to dismiss trouble-makers whose conductjustifies dismissal without the fear that it will provoke retaliation fromtheir employees.67. In framing legislation it would be necessary to consider whether it is practicable to cover very small undertakings, where personal frictions might givea valid motive for a dismissal which would nevertheless be difficult to justify in front of a tribunal.(ii) Compulsory recognition68. In certain other countries, including Sweden and the United States, thereare statutory procedures whereby employers may be compelled to recognise theright of trade unions to negotiate on behalf of their employees. In this country it is a recurring grievance of trade unions that they have to fight for recognition,and there are a significant number of strikes on the issue each year. We have therefore considered whether it would be desirable to legislate on the subject.69. It would be undesirable to lay down any hard and fast rules as to whatproportions of employees must be organised for recognition to become obligatory,as is done in the United States. Small craft unions would either be squeezed out or might secure a permanency of recognition which would hamper change. Nor doesit seem practicable, as is done in Sweden, to compel an employer to negotiate withany trade union which has even one member in his employment. It would benecessary to steer a middle course between these contrasting approaches.70. There seem to us to be two chief dangers to be avoided in any proposalsfor legislation. They are:(i) encouraging splinter unions to form and obtain recognition through thestatutory machinery, which would not be in the long-term interests ofanyone; and(ii) hampering employers who wish to withdraw recognition from some unions in undertakings where there is a multiplicity of them.71. It might be possible to avoid these dangers by establishing machinery onthe following lines:(i) a trade union which is refused recognition by an employer could appealto an independent tribunal, perhaps a Labour Court constituted on thelines described in paragraph 51 above;(ii) the tribunal would conduct such inquiries as were necessary to determine:(a) whether any other union was organising the field and if so whetherit was recognised or actively seeking recognition;(b) the attitudes both of other unions which were recognised or activelyseeking recognition and of the employer;
(c) the degree of support for the union making the appeal among the employees it claimed to represent;(iii) if the tribunal found as a matter of fact that:(a) the employer already recognised a union or unions which acceptedthe employees concerned into membership; or(b) there was more than one union claiming recognition in respect ofthe employees concerned:then the tribunal would not make any award on the appeal;(iv) if (iii) did not apply, the tribunal could make an award obliging the employer to recognise the union, if it found that the union had areasonable degree of support and considered recognition justified inall the other circumstances.72. It would of course be necessary to define what recognition meant. Itwould probably be necessary to draw up lists of subjects suitable for negotiation and for consultation. While it would clearly not be possible to compel the partiesto reach agreement on any subject, it would be possible to compel the employer to lay before the union his proposals for settling the matter in hand and his reasons for turning down proposals by the union. It might in this way be possibleto create a situation in which an employer would rather grant recognition in thefullest sense than continue to ignore the existence of the unions.73. Legislation on these lines would have a strong influence on thedevelopment of trade unions for white-collar workers, whose organisation andrepresentation is one of the outstanding problems to-day both for the trade unions and for industrial relations generally a problem which grows with the growingproportion of the workforce in white-collar jobs. This could well be an advantage,in that the white-collar unions should be able to provide intelligent andenlightened leadership and if they became larger and more influential it should help to promote responsible and progressive attitudes in the trade union movementas a whole.74. The proposal is not entirely free from difficulties and it leaves someproblems unsolved. The machinery suggested would deal only with the main bodyof straightforward cases in which a single union is claiming the right to representa body of employees for whom there are no arrangements already in existence and the employer is refusing it. It would not function in the difficult situationswhere recognition is already accorded to a union for the employees concernedor where it is being sought by more than one union for the same employees.75. Moreover, although legislation would no doubt be welcome to theunions it is doubtful whether it would command general acceptance. There hasbeen little pressure for compulsory recognition. Many employers in industry evenif they accept the need for manual workers&apos; unions do not think that it is in theinterests of good relations for their staff to be represented through unions, andprefer to deal with them individually. They might argue also that, if a union is not strong enough to force an employer to recognise it, it is unlikely to have much success at the bargaining table.76. On balance we do not feel able to recommend legislation on the lines wehave discussed at the present time. There is a further possibility, also requiringlegislation, which would stop short of enabling unions to obtain compulsoryrecognition and which we think would be worth consideration at a convenient opportunity. It is that a tribunal of the kind envisaged might be empowered to hear claims by trade unions for recognition and make recommendations on them which would, however, not be binding. With the support of public opinionmachinery of this kind might prove useful, though it would probably not be effective against a determined employer.
PART II-THE CONDUCT OF TRADE UNION AFFAIRSIntroduction77. There has been some public disquiet in recent years over the way tradeunions conduct their affairs. It has had two main sources. First, in someemployments union membership is obligatory, or virtually so, and this has raiseddifficult questions concerning the protection of the rights of the individual, inparticular because expulsion from a union or refusal of admittance to a unioncan debar a person from the employment of his choice. Secondly the electioniregularities which were exposed in the Electrical Trades Union (E.T.U.) have caused anxiety because it is a matter of public concern that organisations whichhave an established and powerful position in industry and in national affairs as many unions do-should be run honestly and responsibly.78. Except as regards political activities, the law does less to regulate theinternal affairs of trade unions than those of other voluntary associations.Political activities apart, there is no control over the rule-making of anunregistered union and very little over that of a registered union. A breach of union rules can in general be challenged only by a member and his onlyredress outside the union is by way of costly proceedings in the Courts. Evenhere he may be handicapped, for whether the union is registered or unregisteredaccess to the Courts is restricted by section 4 of the Trade Union Act, 1871,which precludes a Court from directly enforcing certain classes of trade unionagreement. These include rules entitling a member to benefit, as well as rulesrequiring him to pay a subscription or penalty. Registration of the union makesvery little difference to redress of members&apos; grievances. Safeguards found in the laws governing other registered associations (notably, provisions for investigation and for the settlement of disputes) are missing here, and except on political fundmatters the Chief Registrar of Friendly Societies has no power to intervene betweenthe member and his union.79. As regards a trade union&apos;s power to exclude from membership thepresent law is in line with the law applicable to voluntary associations generally.That is to say, an applicant for membership has no legal redress if he is refused admission and a member has no legal redress if he is expelled or suspended inaccordance with the union&apos;s rules. The case for further safeguards in this spheremust therefore rest wholly on special considerations affecting trade unions inparticular.80. The law as regards the political activities of trade unions is worth noting,since here, exceptionally, there are statutory requirements which limit trade unionfreedom. The relevant provisions are in sections 3 to 6 of the Trade UnionAct, 1913.81. No union, registered or unregistered, may spend money on politicalobjects unless the furtherance of those objects has been approved as an object ofthe union by a resolution adopted by a ballot of the members. The vote must beheld under rules approved for the purpose by the Registrar. The Registrar has tobe satisfied &quot; that every member has an equal right, and, if reasonably possible,a fair opportunity of voting, and that the secrecy of the ballot is properly secured &quot;(sections 3 (1) and 4 (1) of the 1913 Act).82. If the resolution is approved, the union must adopt rules which requirethe Registrar^ approval providing for a separate political fund; for the rightto contract out of contributing to the fund; that a contracted-out member isnot to be victimised; and that contributing to the fund is not to be a conditionof admission to a union (section 3 (1) of the 1913 Act). The Registrar issuesmodel rules, and unions have in practice adopted them with only minorvariations.83. A member who alleges that he is aggrieved by a breach of any of these rules may complain to the Registrar, who after hearing the complainant and theunion may, if he thinks a breach has been committed, &quot; make such order forremedying the breach as he thinks just in the circumstances &quot;. The order isenforceable in the County Court (section 3 (2) of the 1913 Act).
Should trade union rules be subject to the Registrars approval?84. It might be thought that it would be desirable to increase the Registrar&apos;spowers in relation to trade union rules. He might have power to see for instancethat rules about admittance and expulsion are not unreasonable or undulyrestrictive and that voting procedures are efficient and not open to abuse.85. In our view the amount of progress to be attained in this way would infact be small. While it is undoubtedly true that some unions have rules whichare in some degree obscure or inconsistent, or which have implications notoriginally intended, in general it is not the rules themselves which are importantso much as the way in which and the extent to which they are observed inpractice.86. For example, union executives often have very great discretion to expelmembers.* While these powers sometimes go beyond what is strictly necessaryto safeguard the interests of a union, the rules must obviously contain somepowers to deai with members who are acting against a union&apos;s interests.Everything depends on the way these rules are exercised in practice. Again, unionrules on voting procedures can be made to work fairly and satisfactorily, providedthat the will to do so is there. When however a determined minority has seizedpower and intends to retain it by all the means at its disposal, the best of rulesabout voting will be flouted.87. To give the Registrar any general oversight over trade union ruleswould certainly be bitterly resented as an incursion into the freedom of the tradeunions, and there would be some justification for this. It would be very difficultto give the Registrar powers which were effective and which at the same timegave the unions the liberty of action which is necessary to them if they are to operate freely and independently.88. One yardstick by which to judge this is provided by the InternationalLabour Convention (No. 87) concerning freedom of association and protectionof the right to organise, which the United Kingdom has ratified. In part this reads:&quot; Article 2Workers and employers, without distinction whatsoever, shall havethe right to establish . . . organisations of their own choosing without previous authorisation.Article 31. Workers&apos; and employers&apos; organisations shall have the right todraw up their constitutions and rules, to elect their representatives in fullfreedom, to organise their administration and activities and to formulatetheir programmes.2. The public authorities shall refrain from any interference whichwould restrict this right or impede the lawful exercise thereof.&quot;Any interpretation of the Convention would ultimately be a matter for theInternational Court of Justice, but it seems clear that as interpreted within theI.L.O. itself t the Convention would preclude any extensive control by the Registrarover the rules of unions.89. We do not suggest that what this Convention provides is conclusive or that the Government should necessarily be deterred by it from otherwise desirablereforms, but it does give a useful indication of the limitations on outside control which are widely accepted as necessary to a free trade union movement.90. We conclude that it would not be desirable to make union rules subjectto the Registrar^ approval. The fact remains however that union rules do oftenleave a good deal to be desired and it would be useful to take any suitableopportunities for getting voluntary improvements, even though it is not likely thatany very substantial progress can be made in this way.* The General Executive Council of the Transport and General Worker&apos;s Union has power to expel a member &quot; for such reasons and on such terms as they deem expedient&quot;.t The I.L.O. bases itself mainly on the conclusions of a Committee of Experts on the Applicationof Conventions and Recommendations.
91. In examining proposed changes in the rules of registered unions the registrar already frequently points out obscurities, inconsistencies and unlooked-forimplications and suggests improvements. Some unions accept these suggestionsmore readily than others, in particular those unions which send their rules for examination in draft before formal adoption. It would be helpful if the Registrarcould endorse and expand this practice on an informal basis.92. Another possibility might be for the Registrar to draw up and publish a set of model rules. It would however be preferable if the T.U.C. were itself to do this, though there is no sign at present that it is likely to do so or would reactfavourably to a suggestion that it should. It would no doubt be argued that thecircumstances of every union are different and that each union must draw up therules that suit its own circumstances. We think however that the Governmentshould keep in mind the possibility, should a favourable opportunity occur, ofurging the T.U.C. either itself to draw up model rules or to assist the Registrar in doing so on the understanding that there would be no compulsion on any union to accept them.Protection of the rights of individual trade union members93. The case for giving the individual better protection against exclusion froma trade union rests on the effect this can have on his employment prospects. If anindividuals exclusion from a union would result or be likely to result in his losinghis job or being refused employment for which he is qualified he is entitled to an assurance that he will not be excluded from union membership without good cause.Where exclusion from a union would not have these consequences it is of very much less importance whom a union chooses to expel or to refuse to admit.94. Extent of the closed shop*. There is no comprehensive information about the extent of the closed shop in this country, but in general terms it may besaid that it exists far more widely in practice than is recognised in formal agreements.For example, in the coalmining industry, the railways, road passenger transport,civil air transport, docks, shipbuilding and ship repairing, the iron and steel industry,printing, London wholesale food markets and major sectors of the engineering industry there is a high degree of trade union organisation and in practice in manyundertakings membership of a trade union is a condition of employment. Formalagreements are however rare, though there is one covering London busmen andthey probably exist widely in the printing industry.95. In some industries and in some localities unions have reinforced theclosed shop by securing control over the supply of skilled labour. The intake of apprentices may also be limited and membership of the union, or the section of itappropriate to skilled workers, may be strictly controlled.96. Should the closed shop be banned? If the closed shop were effectivelybanned it would deprive the unions of their power over the individual^ prospects of employment and therefore make it unnecessary to consider measures for the better protection of the rights of individual members. The closed shop was in factmade illegal so far as employees of any local or other public authority were concerned by section 6 (1) of the Trade Disputes and Trade Unions Act, 1927, andthis remained the law until the Act was repealed in 1946. It would however hardly be worth considering the re-enactment of this provision as it deals with only onesector of employment.97. It is clear from the outset that legislation against the closed shop wouldbe strongly resisted by the trade union movement. It has always been regarded asa legitimate aim for unions to try and secure 100 per cent membership, and legislationagainst the closed shop would be seen as an attempt to prevent the unions fromachieving this aim. It does not seem altogether unreasonable that if a worker&apos;terms and conditions of employement depend in practice on the activities of a unionhe should be required to be a member of it. Possibly, too, some employers wouldregret it if the closed shop were banned. It can help to stabilise employee/management relations and make it easier to set up and run efficient machineryfor local consultation and negotiation.* The term &quot; closed shop &quot; is here used as meaning an arrangement under which it is a conditionof employment that an employee shall be a member of a particular trade union, and that a newlyengaged employee, if not already a member of that union, must join it within a short time of hisengagement.
98. If rigidly imposed, however, the closed shop penalises a person whodoes not wish to join a union, for example on conscientious grounds. There has beena recent case of this kind involving a park-keeper employed by Romford borough council, Mr. Robert Kenyon. In January 1959 the Romford Council decided that trade union membership should be a condition of employment, but that existingemployees at the time of the decision should not lose their jobs if they refused tojoin unions. Mr. Kenyon was already an employee; he voluntarily joined theNational Union of Public Employees after the CounciFs decision but later let hismembership lapse. The Council took the view that once having joined the unionhe should have remained a member. After continued refusal to re-join Mr. Kenyonwas sacked at the end of August 1962. Only an outright ban on the closed shopwould prevent this sort of case.99. The position in the United States and in Sweden is of some interest. Inthe United States the closed shop in the sense used in this paper is not forbidden byfederal legislation: the Taft-Hartley Act permits collective agreements under whichemployees must join the appropriate union within 30 days of engagement, but atthe same time the Act safeguards the right of employees to join and remain membersof unions in these circumstances. The Taft-Hartley Act does however make it an&quot; unfair labour practice &quot; for an employer to refuse to engage people who are not already trade union members at the time of the engagement, a practice which would effectively limit the field of recruitment. In Sweden little is heard of the closed shop,but this is not because of legalisation but because the (voluntary) 1938 BasicAgreement at any rate as interpreted by the employers does not permit it.100. The difficulties of legislating against the closed shop are formidable. Thelaw would be difficult to enforce against employers because it would often be hard to establish that the reason why an employer refused to engage a particular workeror to retain him in employment was that he was not a union member or a memberof a particular union. Closed shop arrangements are often not formalised and expressed in writing. The employer could easily advance numerous other reasonsfor his action. If there were a strike against the action of an employer in engaginga non-unionist or retaining in employment an existing employee who had leftor been expelled from the union it would put the employer in a very difficult position.Redress against the union if the strike were official might be provided, but if thestrike were unofficial there would be the familiar difficulties in the way of proceedings against strike leaders or strikers. Moreover the employer might anticipate the likelihood of a strike and dismiss the employee himself: in that case any sanctionwould have to operate against the employer, but this would seem unfair becausehis only motive in acting as he did would be that he did not want his undertakingbrought to a halt by a strike.101. We conclude that it would not be practicable, nor on the whole desirable,to introduce legislation with the aim of banning the closed shop. We do howeversuggest later, in paragraphs 112 and 113, certain principles whose voluntaryacceptance would make the closed shop much less likely to lead to hardship.102. Appeals machinery for individuals excluded from trade unions. Exclusion may take one of two forms. A person may be refused admission to a tradeunion; and a trade unionist may be expelled from membership. There is at present no redress open to a person who is refused membership of a trade union; he hasno right of action on any grounds. A member who is expelled can seek redress only if there has been a breach of the rules, as was done successfully in the case ofBonsor v. Musicians&apos; Union; if he has been expelled in accordance with the rules,and the appeals machinery laid down in the rules has been observed, he has no grounds on which to appeal to the Courts. When one considers the very greatdiscretion to expel members which union executives generally have, the individual^need for protection against unreasonable expulsion becomes apparent. That thishas not, in practice, been a very live issue, shows that unions have on the wholeexercised their powers with restraint.103. For any right of appeal against expulsion to be effective, it must bepossible for a person to appeal on the ground not only that his expulsion is notin accordance with the rules but also that, although it is in accordance with therules, the union could and should in the circumstances have refrained from imposingso severe a penalty.
104. As regards the right of appeal against non-admission to a union, clearlyan individual would need to be able to appeal on the grounds that he is qualifiedunder the rules for admission and should therefore be admitted. He should also beable to appeal against the use of a discretionary power not to admit him on thegrounds that its effect was unreasonably harsh in his case.105. Even if appeal rights existed on these lines, they would not preventyet another type of case arising. This is the type of case that arises if exclusionresults not from discretion harshly used but because the rules themselves are harshand rigid. An example is provided by the case of Faramus v. Film Artistes&apos;Association. In that case, Mr. Faramus joined, as he thought, the Film Artistes&apos;Association and for several years earned his living as a &quot; crowd &quot; actor in films.It was then discovered that he had, many years previously, when aged 18 and 20,served two prison sentences of three months and six months, and the unionthereupon excluded him from membership because one of the rules of the unionsays that &quot; no person who has been convicted ... of a criminal offence . . . shallbe eligible for or retain membership &quot;. The Court of Appeal held that Mr. Faramuswas not eligible for membership, and that the union committee had had no authorityto admit him to membership. Their finding has been upheld in the House of Lords.The union rule was clearly framed with the intention of protecting members frompetty theft, to which they were particularly exposed in following their profession,but equally clearly it had in this case a more far reaching effect than was everintended.106. We do not think it would be practicable to provide for appeals in this sort of case, where it is the substance of the rules, and not themannerin which theyare applied, that is at issue. To do so would in effect mean making the rules of tradeunions subject to approval of an appeals body, and in principle there would be little difference between this and requiring rules to be approved when they are drawnup. Cases of the Faramus type are unlikely to be common, and if unions can be induced to review their rules and remove anomalies they will become rarer still.107. In our view it would be desirable, as a minimum, for the followingappeals machinery to exist:(1) It should be open to a person who can show that his exclusion from a tradeunion has resulted or is likely to result in the loss of his job or in the refusal of employment for which he is qualified to appeal against hisexclusion to an impartial tribunal.(2) He could base his appeal on one or more of the following grounds:(i) that he had been expelled from membership contrary to the rules;(ii) that he had been expelled as a result of an unreasonably harsh useof discretion under the rules;(hi) that he had been refused membership although qualified for it under the rules;(iv) that he had been refused membership as a result of an unreasonablyharsh use of discretion under the rules.108. The most satisfactory way for this appeals machinery to be establishedwould be for the T.U.C. or the unions to do it themselves. In the United Statesboth the United Automobile Workers and the Upholsterers have establishedindependent review boards of outside persons to which members can appeal for final decision against alleged violation of their rights. In this country, however,independent appeals bodies for unions are as yet unknown, and there is no reasonto think that they are likely to be established in the near future or that the T.U.C.would at present respond to suggestions that they should be established.109. Legislation would be an alternative. An appeal might lie to a LabourCourt constituted on the lines discussed in paragraph 51. Alternatively appealsbased on breaches of the rules might lie with the Registrar, who already dealswith appeals against breaches of political fund rules and has considerable experienceof the rules of unions as well as experience in settling disputes arising from breaches of the rules of voluntary associations. In that case only appeals based on the harshuse of discretion (and probably also appeals based both of this and on breaches inrules) would go to a Labour Court. Any statutory right of appeal should presumably
operate only after any machinery provided in a union&apos;s rules has been exhausted;and decisions on an appeal should be final and not subject to a further right ofappeal in any other Court.110. Legislation would almost certainly be hotly resented by the trade union movement, who would see in it an unwarranted interference with their traditionalfreedom of action. The unions which would be foremost in resisting it would bethe craft unions, which would fear that their ranks would be opened too widely,and unions representing workers in declining trades which restrict entry with theobject of reserving what employment is available for their existing members. Thesefears would not be entirely groundless, though they would no doubt be considerablyexaggerated. To some extent the unions&apos; fears might be met by enabling exemptionsto be granted to unions which themselves set up satisfactory machinery for theimpartial hearing of appeals.111. On balance we do not think that legislation would be warranted inpresent circumstances. It may, however, be that in the future if the closed shopbecomes more extensive or abuses of the rights of individual union membersbecome commoner it will be necessary for the Government to take action. In that case we suggest that the Government should first attempt to persuade the T.U.C.to establish effective appeals machinery on the lines suggested in paragraph 107and should only seek to do so by means of legislation if that fails.112. We also suggest that in the meanwhile it would be desirable for theMinistry of Labour to take suitable opportunities to urge that where the closed shop is accepted there should be reasonable safeguards for management and individual workers. We have in mind the following in particular:(i) that managements should be entitled to recruit anyone they wish on thebasis of ability to perform the work, subject to the understanding thathe will normally be required to apply for admission to the appropriateunion if not already a member and will be admitted by the union;(ii) that, if a worker is expelled from the union, he should not automaticallybe dismissed; if the union feels that he should be dismissed, the case should be looked at by a suitable review body, e.g., a joint committee under an independent chairman whose verdict would have to beaccepted;(hi) that there must be exemptions for workers who on religious orconscientious grounds refuse to join a union; here again if the unionso wishes a case could be looked at by a review body;(iv) that non-union members already in employment at the time the closed shop is accepted should not be dismissed for failure to join the union.113. If these principles were adopted the problems we have been discussingwould largely be solved. We recognise, however, that progress in securing their application will at best be slow and is unlikely to provide a complete answer inthe near future.114. Other matters which might be the subject of appeals. If machinery forappeals against exclusion from a union of the kind we have discussed is to be setup, consideration should be given to the desirability of enabling appeals on certain other matters affecting the rights of individual members to be decided through it.In the first place suspension from union membership should also probably besubject to appeal, since it might have results equivalent to expulsion.115. Again it might be that there should be a right of appeal against theimposition of other penalties also. The justification would partly be to prevent thevictimisation of a member who had won an appeal against exclusion but partly the wider grounds that if trade union membership is necessary to retain employment trade unionist cannot have recourse to resignation from his union if he considersthat he is unjustly treated.116. Another form that victimisation could conceivably take would be the withholding of benefits to which a member is entitled under the rules. As mentionedpreviously (in paragraph 78) members of unions have no direct remedy in thecourts if they are not paid such benefits. It seems reasonable that any appealsmachinery should provide a remedy.
(117. Trade unions are also precluded from suing for arrears of subscriptionsor for penalties imposed in accordance with the rules. There seems no good reasoneither for this or for preventing union members from suing for benefits to whichthey believe themselves entitled. In any legislation it might be desirable to repeal the relevant parts of section 4 of the Trade Union Act, 1871, and to allow bothmembers and trade unions to seek redress through the statutory appeals machinery.)118. If appeals machinery is set up voluntarily either by the T.U.C. or by individual unions, it may be that all union members or would-be members shouldhave access to it, regardless of the effect of union membership on employmentprospects, and the appeals body should be competent to hear all cases in which a trade union member is aggrieved by treatment he has received from the union.119. If there is legislation it is doubtful whether, in the face of the opposition of the unions, it would be wise to extend the scope of the appeals machinery wider than is strictly necessary to safeguard employment prospects. Even so the appealsbody might be given power to adjudicate in any dispute between a union and oneof its members which was referred to it by mutual consent. It may be that if this were done it would in time become widely accepted practice to refer disputes byconsent. The advantage to the individual would be obvious, but from the standpointof a union it could also be valuable as a means of demonstrating that it treated its members fairly.The prevention of irregularities in trade union elections120. Irregularities in trade union elections came into prominence because ofthe E.T.U. case. Following an election in December 1959 for the post of general secretary of the union Mr. Haxell was declared to have defeated Mr. Byrne.Mr. Byrne brought an action for conspiracy against Mr. Haxell and others, and inJuly 1961 a court found the case proved and granted a declaration that Mr. Byrnewas the General Secretary of the union.121. The legal action was only the culmination of allegations which had beenmade for a number of years about the influence of the Communist Party in theE.T.U.&apos;s affairs and the fraudulent manipulation of elections. Because theseallegations had been bringing discredit on the trade union movement the T.U.C.General Council began to correspond with the E.T.U. about them at the end of1958. The correspondence brought no results, but after the judgment in the caseof Byrne v. Haxell the General Council decided to recommend Congress to expelthe E.T.U., and this was done in September 1961. In January 1962 the new anti-Communist executive took office and the E.T.U. applied and was accepted forreaffiliation.122. At the time that the E.T.U. scandal was at its height the Governmentcame under considerable pressure to legislate with the object of preventingrecurrences. The possibility was considered of giving trade union members a rightof appeal to the Registrar against alleged election irregularities. When the T.U.C.were consulted they took the strongest exception to any such proposal. They saidthat the E.T.U. case was in no way typical and had in any case ended satisfactorilyand that the trade union movement could and should deal with these matters on itsown. It was decided not to pursue the proposal further at the time in view of theneed to secure the T.U.C.&apos;s co-operation over the setting up of the N.E.D.C. and because the T.U.C. had by then expelled the E.T.U.123. One of the T.U.C.&apos;s anxieties over the possibility of a right of appeal tothe Registrar was that there might be a flood of appeals of a trivial kind whichwould damage the reputation of the trade union movement. Rule books oftencontain complicated provisions on the conduct of elections and minor breaches of the rules, with no fraudulent intent, probably occur fairly frequently. This iscertainly a point which would have to be watched in any proposals for legislation.124. The T.U.C. were probably right to say that fraudulent elections are rare.There has been a recent case of irregularities over an election for the seat on theAmalgamated Engineering Union&apos;s executive committees representing the No. 4division (Manchester and the Midlands). However in this case there was no questionof a falsification of the ballot: the allegations concerned canvassing by districtcommittee members in support of one of the candidates in breach of the union&apos;srules. The irregularities were dealt with satisfactorily, but this is not surprising
because it was the executive committee of the A.E.U. which complained of them.Redress is clearly very much more difficult when it is the actions of a union&apos; executive committee which are suspect.125. The evidence of the E.T.U. case on the ability of trade union members to get redress for fraudulent elections is not altogether reassuring. The legal action,when it was finally brought, was protracted and expensive. Allegations ofirregularities had been going on for years, and members had ncdoubt been deterred from pursuing these in the courts by the difficulty and cost of litigation. Althoughthe T.U.C. finally expelled the E.T.U. this was only after the legal case had beenfought and won, and the T.U.C.&apos;s previous actions had been half-hearted andineffective.126. It is not at all obvious that there would be speedy and effective action if another trade union fell under the domination of an extremist minority determined to keep itself in power by all the means at its disposal. There are clearly attractionsto the idea of providing a cheap and ready means of appeal so that irregularitiescan be dealt with at the outset, and not only after a number of years when thesituation has become really serious.127. Here too the most satisfactory solution would be effective appealsmachinery established by the T.U.C. In the absence of effective action on the partof the T.U.C. there is a case for legislation giving trade union members a right to appeal to the Registrar on the grounds:(i) that a member entitled under the rules to vote in an election has beenwrongfully debarred from doing so;(ii) that the rules relating to the conduct of an election have been broken withthe intention of promoting the interests of one candidate as against another.128. If there were legislation it would almost certainly be necessary to apply the appeals procedures to all elections to office down to an including branch level.The union&apos;s own appeals machinery would have to be used before an appeal couldbe made to the Registrar. The Registrar would have to be given power to deal effectively with complaints. This would need to include the right to order discoveryof documents and to compel the attendance of witnesses and examine them onoath. He would have also to have power to make orders giving effect to his findings.The powers might be analogous to those in section 3 (2) of the 1913 Act in relationto breaches of political fund rules, i.e., he should be able to make &quot; such order for remedying the breach as he thinks just under the circumstances&quot;. It would be reasonable also to give the Registrar power to order payment of costs either bythe complainant or by the union or by individuals responsible for a breach.129. If appeals machinery of this kind were set up it would be reasonable for it to be an alternative to appeal to the Courts, but proceedings in one tribunal should preclude the jurisdiction of the other and there should be no appeal againstthe Registrar^ decision on a complaint.130. A further possibility might be to give the Registrar power to conductelections at the request of unions. Unions may already employ agents to supervisetheir elections. For example under the E.T.U.&apos;s new rules the conduct of electionshas been placed in the hands of the Electoral Reform Society. It is doubtful,however, whether it would be worth adding the Registrar to the list of agentswilling to carry this out. There is no evidence that this would fill a need whichcannot already be adequately filled by others, and the Registrar would not be ableto meet requests for assistance of this kind out of the existing resources at his disposal.131. We do not think that legislation on these lines would be justified atpresent unless it formed part of a general overhaul of trade union law. The most favourable moment for introducing it was when the E.T.U. scandal was at itsheight, but even at that time the T.U.C. felt bound to oppose it root and branch.Nevertheless it could well happen that an influential trade union might again fallunder the domination of an unscrupulous minority, and there will undoubtedly bea need to watch the danger. Should this happen we think that the Governmentshould urge the TUG. strongly to take effective action and, if it is unable or unwilling to do so, should consider introducing legislation on the lines we have discussed in paragraphs 127-130,
PART III.-OTHER POSSIBLE CHANGES IN THE law a. Legislation on industrial relationsIntroduction132. It is often suggested that industrial relations might be improved either by imposing a statutory &quot;cooling-off&quot; period before strikes can take place or by making secret ballots compulsory before strike action is taken. We have examinedboth these suggestions.133. It is clear from the outset that neither of these suggestions could work effectively where unofficial strikes are concerned, because they would need to been forced by penal sanctions and this would be impracticable where unofficialstrikers are concerned (see paragraphs 25-29 above). Their use would have therefore to be restricted to defined circumstances where official trade union action is involved.This being so it is necessary to bear in mind that if the freedom of action of official union leaders is limited it may tend to encourage unofficial action.The compulsory cooling-off period134. The idea of a cooling-off period is that it would be legally forbidden to start a strike until some fixed period, e.g., a month, had elapsed since the date on which a dispute was announced. It is argued in its favour that the enforceddelay would give the two sides time to reconsider their attitudes and provide an interval in which the emotional temperature could fall. There would be anopportunity for the intervention of third parties in an endeavour to secure asettlement. Very often it is also suggested that an impartial inquiry should bemade while the strike is in abeyance. Finally, the cooling-off period might givepublic opinion a chance to form and make itself felt.135. The idea of a cooling-off period has been developed furthest in theUnited States and it is convenient to examine the possibility in the light of thelaw in the United States. There is in the United States statutory provision for acooling-off period in two circumstances:(i) when a party to a collective agreement wishes to terminate or modify it;and(ii) when a strike threatens to cause a national emergency.136. Cooling-off period before a collective agreement terminates. TheTaft-Hartley Act requires a party wishing to end or modify a collective agreement to give written notice at least 60 days before the termination of the agreement,and to offer to meet the other party to negotiate a revised agreement. If no agreement is reached the existing contract continues in full force for the 60 days or until it expires, whichever is the later. Meanwhile, after 30 days the FederalMediation and Conciliation Service has to be notified that a dispute exists. It isan unfair labour practice to strike in contravention of these requirements.137. It is generally thought that this provision makes little difference to thecourse of events in practice. It seems very doubtful whether it would have anymore decisive effect in the United Kingdom. The interval between the making ofa claim by a trade union and the conclusion of new terms is normally quiteprotracted, so that it would make little practical difference to negotiation if thetrade union(s) concerned had to give written notice of their wish to modify thecurrent agreement when submitting a claim. Moreover in the United Statesfixed-term contracts are the rule, whereas they are not usual in this country(though there have been some examples recently); the idea therefore does nothave the same significance here because there is not the same urgency and tensionover modifying an agreement of indefinite duration as there is over renewing a fixed-term agreement which is coming to its end.138. Nor would it make much difference if the parties had to inform theMinistry of Labour that a dispute existed so as to enable it to try and promote a settlement. The Ministry already has adequate information about the course
of industrial negotiations, and can and does get in touch with the parties witha view to conciliation whenever events have moved to a stage where this seems likely to be helpful.139. Cooling-off period if a strike threatens a national emergency. TheTaft-Hartley Act lays down an elaborate procedure for actual or threatened strikesthat may imperil national safety or health. The President may appoint a boardof inquiry to investigate and report but without making any recommendations.On receiving the report the President may direct the Attorney-General to ask the federal courts for an injunction against the strike as likely to imperil nationalsafety or health. If granted, the parties must during the next 60 days try to settletheir differences with the help of the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service.Meanwhile the President must reconvene the board of inquiry to make a further report at the end of 60 days (unless the dispute has been settled), including in ita statement of the employers&apos; last offer. In the 15 days following the 60 the NationalLabor Relations Board must hold a vote among the workers as to whether they want to accept this offer; five further days are allowed in which to certify the resultof the vote. On receiving the certification the Attorney-General must move thecourt to discharge the injunction, thus freeing the parties to proceed with thestrike. The President has to submit to Congress a report of the entire proceedingswith such recommendations as he wishes.140. The procedure just described has many critics in the United States.Although the cooling-off period is an asset in that it gives the public that muchrespite from a strike there seems to be little evidence that it leads the parties tothe dispute to soften their attitudes. Efforts at conciliation are apt to be nullified,because everyone knows that if there is no settlement beforehand there will be asecret ballot on the employers&apos; final offer at the end of 60 days. This latter provision was no doubt framed in the belief that trade union members might be less militantthan their leaders and prefer to accept terms against their leaders&apos; advice, but infact in every case where a vote has been held under the emergency procedure theemployers&apos; last offer has been rejected. Finally, the boards of inquiry under theprocedure are precluded from making recommendations: they can only find andreport the facts. This appears to limit their usefulness.141. In this country the Minister of Labour already has the necessary powers under the Industrial Courts Act, 1919, to appoint a court of inquiry to examinethe causes and circumstances of any trade dispute and report to him. Courts of inquiry are free to make recommendations as to how a reasonable settlementmight be reached. A court of inquiry&apos;s report has to be laid before Parliament &quot; assoon as may be &quot;. Experience has shown that an impartial and public examinationof the facts and circumstances of a dispute often helps a good deal to bring theparties together and so to lead to a settlement.142. The procedure governing courts of inquiry has great flexibility. It isdoubtful whether it would help much to add to this elaborate machinery on thelines of that in the Taft-fiartley Act. In particular, it seems unlikely that an enforcedstrike-free period would be any more successful in promoting revised attitudes herethan it has proved in the United States. It seems at least as likely to cause attitudesto harden.143. Cooling-off periods: conclusion. Our conclusion is that there is no advantage to be gained in this country by legislation providing for a cooling-offperiod in either of the circumstances in which it is compulsory in the United States.Compulsory secret strike ballots144. Legislation to make compulsory a secret ballot of union members beforethe calling of a strike is a favourite suggestion of those who subscribe to the viewthat ordinary union members often do not really want strikes but are unable to resist being led into them by extremist minorities. It is thought that if members could declare their views under the protection of anonymity this distaste for strikeswould come to the fore.145. Some support is given to this view by two recent instances. When theengineering unions held a ballot of their members in the spring of 1962 on thequestion of whether their wage claim should be backed if necessary by an officialstrike they failed to obtain a majority for strike action which was a severe tactical
disadvantage in the prosecution of the claim. More recently, the N.U.G.M.W.and A.E.U. held secret ballots of their members at Ford&apos;s to decide whether theyshould strike unless the company took back those of their members who wereamong the 17 men whose dismissal was the subject of a court of inquiry, and inneither union was a majority for a strike forthcoming. In both cases, however,there were special factors. In engineering some of the more influential union figures were against a strike, though they were naturally reluctant to risk unpopularityby public opposition. At Ford&apos;s the dispute was one with a long and unusualhistory, in which the political affiliations of those involved played their part.146. It is true that individual workers who oppose a strike may often find it difficult to resist the pressure of those in favour and even to obtain a fair hearing.This is inevitable in view of the deep-rooted aversion among workers from anythingsmacking of &quot; blacklegging &quot;. A secret ballot would help those in this positionto make their views felt. But it is also true that leaders cannot afford to go oncalling strikes against the real wishes of the majority. The men may come out for fear of being called blacklegs, but experience shows that they will not continue todo so indefinitely. An instance that might be cited is the unofficial strike at Morris(Tractor and Transmissions) Ltd., in April 1962, which eventually broke down andwas followed by vociferous criticism of the shop steward leaders and demands fortheir resignation by ordinary members. An unsuccessful strike is a serious blow to the authority of either a union or an unofficial leader.147. Since it would be impracticable to require a ballot before an unofficialstrike, it appears that the only practical form legislation could take would be togive the Minister of Labour power to order a union to hold a strike ballot on anyparticular occasion. The hope would be that the powers might help to avert majordisputes where it appears that the majority are against a strike, particularly on occasions when responsible leaders are subject to pressure from militant elementsto take drastic action. The sort of occasion on which the powers might have been used occurred in October 1962, when there was a one-day national railway strike.148. However, this would be a double-edged weapon. If the result of a votefavoured a strike it might tie the hands of union leaders in a way which wouldhamper a negotiated settlement (though to some extent this risk might be reducedby ensuring that the wording of the specific question put to the vote was sufficientlyflexible). The fact that the Minister had the power to order a strike ballot would lead to pressure for him to use it on occasions when it could not help and might doharm. Moreover when a vote was ordered, the fact that it had been ordered by an outside authority the Government-could well be enough in itself to make tradeunion members close their ranks and vote for a strike for the sake of &quot; solidarity &quot;.It may be added that trade union leaders would strongly resent the legislation,which they would see as an attempt to drive a wedge between them and their members. They would also say and on the whole experience bears this out thatunion members are far more given to demanding militant action than their leaders.149. Our conclusion therefore is that it would not be desirable to legislate in any form so as to compel unions to hold a compulsory secret ballot before callinga strike.B. Section 4 of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875150. Section 4 of the Conspiracy and Protection of Property Act, 1875, as extended by the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1919, makes it an offence for an employeeof a gas, electricity or water undertaking to break his contract of employmentwilfully or maliciously, if he knows or has reasonable cause to believe that theprobable result will be to cut off the supply completely or to a great extent. Thesection also imposes a duty on undertakings to post a copy of the section in aconspicuous place and failure to do so is an offence.151. In practice the obligation to post copies of the section is not generallyobserved, and since they are not posted it would be difficult to secure a conviction of an employee under the section. The section is therefore at present virtually adead letter. The question arises whether it should either be enforced or be repealed.152. The gas, electricity and water undertakings are unwilling to post copiesof the section because they feel that it would be provocative; in the past whennotices have been posted they have invariably been defaced. Nor do they see in
the section a means of improving industrial relations. There is force in this view.On the other hand to repeal the section now without putting anything in its place would give the impression that the Governments opposition to unofficial strikes and other unofficial action had weakened, and this would be undesirable. Weconclude therefore that for the time being this section should be retained, eventhough no active steps are taken to enforce it.C. Registration of trade unions153. Although there is provision for trade unions to register with the ChiefRegistrar of Friendly Societies it is not compulsory. We have considered whetherit would be desirable to make all trade unions register.154. At the end of 1961 there was a total of 635 registered and unregisteredtrade unions representing a total of 9,883,000 employees. Of these unions 241(i.e., 38 per cent) were not registered, but their total membership, If million, wasonly 15 per cent of the total number of trade unionists. Of the 17 unions with over100,000 members all but three are registered. (The exceptions are the NationalUnion of Teachers which claims not to be a union in the legal sense the Unionof Post Office Workers and the National and Local Government Officers&apos;Association).155. It is clear from this that compulsory registration would not in itself have any very significant effect for the trade union movement as a whole. Registrationconfers certain advantages of a fairly minor character on trade unions, e.g., inrelation to the holding of property, but does not appear to give trade union members a degree of extra protection, or to have any other effect, which would justify forcing unions to register. The statutory provisions relating to political activities and to amalgamations and transfers of engagements in any case apply equally to registered and unregistered trade unions. If registration were compulsoryit would presumably apply to such employers&apos; associations as are legally tradeunions. This would have no particular advantage and could be inconvenient forthe organisations concerned.156. We conclude that there would be no advantage at present in making alltrade unions register. Nor do we recommend in our report any changes in the law which we consider would warrant making registration compulsory. In particularwe have rejected the suggestion that union rules should be made subject to theapproval of the Registrar, a measure that would almost certainly make compulsoryregistration necessary (see paragraph 90).D. Other possible changes in trade union law157. Immunity from actions for tort. It is frequently pointed out that section 4 of the Trade Disputes Act, 1906, gives trade unions immunity from any action for tort whatever (other than the very limited class of actions referred toin sub-section (2) of the section) and that as a result a union cannot, for example,be sued for such torts as libel or malicious prosecution. It can well be argued that this protection need and should be limited only to acts done in contemplationor furtherance of a trade dispute. However the practical advantages of imposingthis limitation would be slight and as any amending legislation would be extremelycontentious we conclude that it would not be worth considering.158. Minor improvements. There are a number of minor &quot;changes in the law which would be useful. There is for example uncertainty whether some of theprovisions of the Trade Union Acts apply to all unions or to registered unions only,and this could be clarified with advantage.159.  The following possible improvements in particular may be mentioned:(1) Audit. Registered unions with more than 500 members or  5,000 assetsmight be required to employ professional auditors.(2) Valuation of superannuation benefits. Registered unions withsuperannuation funds might be required to have the funds valued everyfive years, and new schemes might be certifiable by an actuary.(3) Registering and recording of alterations of rules. It might be providedthat no alteration of rules of a registered union is to be valid untilregistered (at present there are anomalies, and alterations do not haveto be sent to the Registrar before the union&apos;s annual return is sent in).
(4) Contents of rules. The law might require that registered union&apos;s rules should set out the statutory right of members to be sent a copy of therules for not more than Is. on request, to have a copy of the annualreturn to the Registrar free on request, and, if the union provides deathbenefit, to nominate a person to whom the benefit is to be paid.(5) Withdrawal of Certificate under Trade Union Act, 1913, section 2 (3). Section 2 (3) of the Trade Union Act, 1913, enables an unregisteredtrade union to obtain a certificate from the Registrar to the effect thatit is a trade union. The Registrar has power to withdraw a certificatein response to an application by any person if he is satisfied that the certificate is no longer justified. He might be given power also towithdraw a certificate on his own initiative and to require a unionperiodically to give evidence that a certificate is still justified.160. These minor changes would not individually or together justifylegislation, but we recommend that they should be considered if a future revisionof trade union law offers a suitable opportunity.PART IV.-CONCLUDING REMARKS161. The main body of trade union law is virtually the same to-day as it became 50 years ago with the passing of the Trade Union Act, 1913, though ofcourse legislation in the industrial relations field generally has been developedconsiderably since then. There are probably fewer legal constraints on the tradeunions in this country than in any other major country of the world.162. We have examined the law in the light of present day needs and problems. Our conclusions are summarised in Appendix I. We consider that thelaw should be amended to allow workers a right of appeal against unjustifiabledismissal and also (if a pilot experiment now under consideration is successful)to widen the Minister of Labour&apos;s powers to investigate industrial disputes. Wehave studied the possibility of making collective agreements enforceable at law and while we do not make any recommendation on this point we think it merits furtherconsideration. We also draw attention to some useful minor adjustments whichcould be made at an appropriate time. In one limited field, that of trade unionmergers and changes of name, legislation is already being proceeded with.163. The T.U.C. has itself acknowledged, as perhaps it might have donesooner, that the trade union movement must take stock of its role in the modernworld. The 1962 Congress instructed the General Council to examine and report&quot; on the possibility of reorganising the structure of both the TUG. and the british trade union movement with a view to making it better fitted to meet modernindustrial conditions &quot;. As our report shows we consider that the TUG. couldcontribute much to resolving major current problems, first by making the tradeunion movement more efficient and secondly by setting up appeals machinery which will ensure.a high standard of conduct in trade union affairs. The needfor reform is becoming more urgent and if the T.U.C. does not carry it out, and cannot be persuaded to, then in the long run the more drastic remedy of legislation,and with it greater oversight of trade union affairs by the State, may become inevitable.
Appendix I summary OF CONCLUSIONSPart I. Unofficial strikes1. It would be unacceptable in principle to make unofficial strikes as suchillegal (paragraph 25) and impracticable to impose criminal penalties for strikingin breach of contract (paragraphs 26-27); nor would it be desirable to imposecriminal penalties for inducing strikes in breach of contract (paragraphs 28-29),or to attempt to strengthen trade union rules so as to deal with unofficial strikeleaders (paragraphs 31-32).2.   Compulsory arbitration would not help (paragraphs 33-34).3. It is recommended that, if a pilot experiment is undertaken and provessuccessful, consideration should be given to extending the Minister of Labour&apos;spowers to enable him to set up standing fact-finding bodies to investigate the causes of disputes as and when they occur (paragraphs 35-38).4. It would be undesirable to alter the law so as to permit civil actions againsteither individuals or trade unions for inducing employees to break their contracts of employment in pursuance of a trade dispute (paragraphs 39-42).5. A scheme for making collective agreements enforceable at law is discussed,but the committee makes no recommendation as to whether on balance legislation to this effect would be desirable (paragraphs 43-57).6. It is recommended that consideration be given to legislation under which an employer would have to be able to justify a dismissal and an employee wouldhave a right of appeal to an independent tribunal against unjustifiable dismissal(paragraph 65).7. The possibility of introducing statutory procedures under which unionsmight claim recognition from employers is considered, but legislation is notrecommended (paragraphs 68-76).Part II.-The conduct of trade union affairs8. It would not be desirable to make union rules subject to the Registrar^approval (paragraph 90). It would however be helpful if the Registrar cbuldencourage and expand on an informal basis his practice of suggesting improvements in rules to registered unions (paragraph 91). A favourable opportunity might alsobe taken of urging the T.U.C. to draw up model rules or to assist the Registrar in doing so (paragraph 92).9. It would not be practicable, nor on the whole desirable, to introduce legislation with the aim of banning the closed shop (paragraph 101).10. It would be desirable for a person whose employment prospects were affected by exclusion from a union to have a right of appeal on the grounds thatthe exclusion was against the rules or resulted from a harsh use of discretion underthe rules (paragraph 107) but legislation would not at present be warranted. If theneed grew the Government should urge the T.U.C. to set up appeals machinery and, failing this, should legislate (paragraph 111). In the meanwhile the Ministryof Labour should take suitable opportunities to urge that where the closed shopis accepted there should be certain reasonable safeguards (paragraphs 112-113).If appeals machinery is to be set up certain other matters besides exclusion mightbe brought within its scope (paragraphs 114-119).11. Legislation providing for appeals against irregularities in trade unionelections would not be justified at present. If the danger of irregularities againbecomes serious, the Government should urge the T.U.C. to take effective action and, in the absence of this, should consider legislation (paragraph 131).
Part III. Other possible changes in the law12. There would be no advantage in legislation providing for a &quot; cooling-off&quot;period before a strike (paragraph 143). Nor is any form of legislation enablingunions to be compelled to hold a secret ballot before calling a strike desirable(paragraph 149).13. For the time being section 4 of the Conspiracy and Protection of PropertyAct, 1875, should be retained, even though no active steps are taken to enforce it(paragraph 152).14. There would be no advantage at present in making all trade unionsregister (paragraph 156).15. It would not be worth amending section 4 of the Trade Disputes Act,1906, to limit the immunity of-trade unions from actions for tort to acts done in contemplation of furtherance of a trade dispute (paragraph 157).16. It is recommended that certain minor improvements in the law listed inparagraph 159 should be considered if a future revision of trade union law offersa suitable opportunity (paragraph 160).Appendix IIPROBLEMS INVOLVED IN MAKING COLLECTIVE AGREEMENTSLEGALLY ENFORCEABLEMore detailed examination of possible system of enforcement1. The broad outline of a possible way of enforcing collective agreements is described in paragraphs 51 and 52 of the report. The essence of it is that actions for breach of a collective agreement should be capable of being brought in speciallyconstituted Labour Courts, which would have powers to award damages withinprescribed maxima and to grant injunctions ordering an organisation or an employer in breach of an agreement to honour it. The following paragraphsexamine some of the problems that would arise if it were decided to proceed withthe scheme.2. The basis for the assessment of damages needs thought. It might simplybe proved financial loss. However it might be possible to widen this a little as in sweden where &quot; the interest of the person concerned in the maintenance of the contract and other circumstances other than those of a purely economic nature &quot;are to be taken into consideration. It might even be possible to sever any directconnection with the actual loss and give a Labour Court discretion to award any amount it thought fit within the prescribed maxima in any given case. However,this would be tantamount to permitting a criminal penalty to be imposed for the purely civil wrong of breach of contract, and it is doubtful whether this would be either justifiable or acceptable to public opinion. It would, therefore, probably be preferable to base damages only on loss, whether or not this was interpreted inthe rather broad sense adopted in Sweden.3. The extent to which responsibility for the observance of collective agreements, if they became legally enforceable, should be put on the individualemployer and employee would also need to be considered. It would almost certainly be right for an employer who is a member of an employers&apos; association to be treatedas if he himself were directly a party to the agreement. Otherwise his compliancecould only be secured by means of an action against the association to which hebelongs, which would be unnecessarily complicated.4. On the whole, it would probably also be right to put responsibility on theindividual employee for observance of an agreement. The damages which could be awarded against him would have to be strictly limited (as suggested in paragraph 52of the report), and it is probable that employers would bring actions againstindividuals only rarely, as rarely in fact as actions for breach of the individualcontract are brought now. The point of putting responsibility on the individual
would be partly to emphasise the general duty of every member to observeagreements and to give recognition to the balance of responsibility between tradeunion leaders and their members which actually exists in practice.5. There would also be a further and more important point. It would makeit possible for individuals to be sued for inducing others to break a collective agreement. This could hardly be done if employees had no individual responsibilityfor observing agreements. The damages for inducement would also have to belimited, though as suggested in paragraph 52 of the report they could be fixed ata higher level than for a simple breach of an agreement.6. The injunction procedure envisaged at (vii) and (viii) of paragraph 51 ofthe report could be used in an attempt to secure a return to work. Many unofficial strikes are too short-lived for the procedure to have any relevance, but where a longer strike was concerned it would be an added means of bringing pressure tobear on a trade union to take action.7. For a scheme of this kind it is not clear whether one Labour Court would suffice or whether there should be several. Cases would often involve nationalcollective agreements and it would be convenient for these to be heard in a singlecentral court in London. On the other hand there would no doubt be a flow oflocal cases and this, combined with the possible total volume of work, might makeit desirable to set up a number of courts in the main industrial areas.8. A disadvantage of the whole proposal is that it might encourage excessiveformality in the drawing up of agreements and perhaps even the employment ofcounsel to represent the two sides in negotiation. For this reason it would bedesirable to reduce to the minimum the formality of proceedings in a LabourCourt. It would also be desirable for the machinery to operate as speedily aspossible.9. It might be necessary to take special steps to prevent the effect of a schemeof this kind being evaded. Trade unions might for instance be tempted to cancelexisting agreed procedures for the settlement of disputes and not replace them.Perhaps the simplest way to counter this would be to lay down a disputesprocedure to bind the parties to collective agreements in the absence of an agreedprocedure, and it might be that this should include arbitration. It might also bedesirable to ensure that collective agreements could not be cancelled overnight soas to free either party from the obligation to use the disputes procedure.10. A scheme of this kind would obviously have implications for statutorywage regulation, for the working of the Terms and Conditions of Employment Act,1959, and for the Crown. Statutory wage-fixing machinery serves the purpose of ensuring, first, that negotiations take place to fix minimum terms in the industry concerned and, secondly, that the terms are enforced. If collective agreements wereenforceable at law the second of these purposes would largely be fulfilled. So also would some of the purposes of section 8 of the Terms and Conditions ofEmployment Act, 1959 (for which see paragraph 52 of the report). It would in fact be possible to give the Minister of Labour power to make a collective agreementlegally binding throughout an industry, so making it unnecessary to bring a claim under the 1959 Act that an employer should observe the recognised terms. Theposition of Crown servants would raise various special problems which would need to be examined.11. There is another implication of a scheme of this kind which should be mentioned. The practice has recently been growing of concluding collective agreements for a term of, say, three years which embody wage increases (and sometimes other improvements) to take effect at specified intervals. On the wholethis development is welcome, because it enables firms to estimate future costs and prices with greater accuracy and because it reduces the risk of disputes inherent inmore frequent wage negotiations. However, some employers are undoubtedlydeterred from concluding agreements of this kind because they fear that theunions will renounce them whenever it suits them to do so. This fear would largelybe removed if collective agreements were legally binding.
Appendix IIITRADE UNIONS: LAW AND PRACTICE IN CERTAIN OTHERCOUNTRIES1. This appendix briefly describes and comments on the law and practice on matters relevant to the committee&apos;s work in Australia, the Federal Republic ofGermany, Sweden and the United States.AUSTRALIA*Law and practice2. Collective agreements, conciliation and arbitration. Australia^ industrial relations system is based on compulsory conciliation and arbitration. The system is laid down in the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Act, 1904-61.The Act provides for a Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commissionand a Commonwealth Industrial Court. The Conciliation and ArbitrationCommission has the duties its title suggests, and consists of a president and anumber of deputies with the qualifications and status of judges, together withCommissioners, who are independent persons but do not need to have any formalqualifications. The function of the Commonwealth Industrial Court is to interpretand enforce awards, and it consists of a Chief Justice and a number of otherjudges.3. As soon as there is an industrial dispute, actual or threatened, its existencemust be notified to the Commonwealth Conciliation and Arbitration Commission.Thereafter there is a duty on the Commission to try and get the parties to agreeby means of conciliation. If they do, the agreement may be made legally binding.If conciliation fails the Commission decides the dispute by making an awardwhich is legally binding on the parties. It has power to fix penalties for a breachor non-observance of any term of an award, not exceeding  A 100 for an organisation and  A10 for a member of an organisation. For constitutional reasonscollective agreements arrived at without a dispute cannot be made legally binding,but in practice the parties ensure that a dispute technically takes place so as toenable a binding award to be made. An award is binding not only on the organisations concerned but also on the members of the organisations individually.An award remains in force for the period specified in the award, but the period is not to be more than five years. Even when the specified period has elapsed theaward remains in force, unless the Commission orders otherwise, until a newaward is made.4. Actions to enforce awards come before the Commonwealth industrial court. If an organisation or person bound by an award has broken or failed to observe its terms, the penalties laid down in the award may be exacted; the court may order the money to be paid either into public funds or to any organisation or person the Court directs. The Court has power to order compliance with an award,and failure to comply may be punished as contempt of Court. A trade union maybe fined as much as  A500 a day for contempt of Court, as well as having costsawarded against it. A trade union is expected to take rigorous action to get its members back to work in the event of an unofficial strike. Indeed it might well beexpected to expel members who refuse to obey an order to return to work. Failingsuch rigorous action, the union would certainly be held responsible and have to face penalties for a strike. If an officer of a trade union or employers&apos; associationincites members of the organisation not to observe the terms of an award he is liable to a penalty of  A100.5. Strike action-There is nothing to prevent a strike where no award is inexistence or over matters not covered by an award. In practice however the rightto strike has been confined within narrow limits because awards cover a very high proportion of the workforce and they frequently contain a clause prohibiting* This appendix describes the federal system only. Each state has its own separate machineryfor settling matters confined within its own boundaries.
stoppages or other coercive action during the currency of an award, with theresult that strike action cannot legally be taken for any purpose and the machineryof the Industrial Court can be used to exact penalties for striking. (This does not prevent a trade union declaring a dispute as opposed to calling a stoppage over a matter not covered by an award with the object of securing an award inits favour by the Commission on the matter in question.)6. Protection of the individual. The Conciliation and Arbitration Act alsorequires unions to include in their rules certain provisions relating to membership and to secret ballots in union elections.(a) Prohibition of unreasonable rules7. Union rules may not impose on members or applicants for membershipconditions, obligations or restrictions which, having regard to the objects of theAct* and the purposes of registration of organisations under the Act, areoppressive, unreasonable or unjust. A union member may apply to theCommonwealth Industrial Court for an order declaring any rule to contravenethis prohibition, and if, after the application is heard, an order is made, the rulebecomes null and void. Conversely the Court may, upon complaint by a unionmember, order the performance or observance of any rule by any person obligedto perform or observe it, under a penalty of  A50.8. Any organisation or person interested, or the Industrial Registrar, may apply to the Court for an order cancelling the registration of a union on theground that the union&apos;s rules are contrary to the law (including the Act), or thatthe rules have not been observed, or that they have been administered in such a manner that conditions, obligations or restrictions which, having regard to the objects of the Act and the purposes of the registration of organisations underthe Act, are oppressive, unreasonable or unjust, have been imposed on members or applicants for membership.(b) Entitlement to union membership9. A person employed in connection with an industry or engaged in an industrial pursuitt is entitled to be admitted to membership of the appropriateunion, subject to payment of dues and to his not being of general bad character,and to remain a member as long as he complies with the rules. This entitlementcannot be cancelled by the union&apos;s rules. Disputes over entitlement can be referred by the union or by the man&apos;s actual or potential employer to the Court fordetermination. Conversely the Court can order that a member of a union shall cease to be a member from a prescribed date and for a prescribed period.(c) Protection against victimisation10. It is an offence by a union, carrying a penalty of  A100, for the union(or a union branch or committee) to impose any penalty on a member for working in accordance with the terms of an arbitration award (S. 188).(d) Secret ballots in union elections11. It is a condition of registration that union rules should provide thatelections within the union should be by secret ballot, with provision for absentvoting, nomination, returning officers, conduct of the ballot, scrutineers anddeclaration of the result. It is also a condition that the rules must ensure, as faras is practicable, that no irregularity can occur in connection with the election.A member who claims there has been an irregularity in connection with an election can apply to the Registrar for an enquiry by the Court, which has powersto order the inspection of ballot papers, lists, etc. If the Court finds an irregularityhas occurred it&quot;may declare the election void and direct the Registrar to. make arrangements for a fresh election.* To promote goodwill, to encourage conciliation, to provide means for preventing and settlingindustrial disputes, to provide for the observance and enforcement of agreements and awards made insettlement of disputes, and to encourage the organisation and registration of representative bodies ofemployers and workers.f This includes those qualified to be and desiring to become employees in that industry or industrialpursuit.
12. Powers of unions over members. As against these rights of membersagainst their unions, Australian unions&apos; powers vis-a-vis their members are insome ways more extensive than in Britain. This is due to the highly developedsystem of conciliation and arbitration in Australia which has made the unionssemi-official bodies.13. Although union membership is voluntary in the sense that no one canbe compelled by law to join a union, there is often little or no choice for theindividual. One arbitration award directs that only members of certain unionsshall be employed. Some awards give unionists absolute preference for engagement,sometimes with the requirement for an employer to dismiss workers who do not join a union within a certain period. Others give unionists a qualified preference,requiring employers to engage or not to dismiss them when in competition with non-unionists.14. More generally, the Australian pattern of registration, arbitration and enforcement of awards means that the terms of the workers&apos; contract ofemployment are regulated by union awards. There is little room for him to contract with his employer outside the relevant award or agreements.Conclusions15. The Australian system involves a degree of control over the internal affairs of trade unions and a curtailment of the right to strike which is in markedcontrast to the situation in the United Kingdom. Although the system may seemrestrictive from the trade union point of view in modern conditions, when it tookshape early in the century it was designed rather to protect and help them. Thiswas because in a period of industrial unrest towards the end of the nineteenth century the employers had succeeded in defeating the unions in a series of ruinousnationwide strikes. It was therefore to the unions&apos; advantage that disputes shouldbe settled by arbitration rather than by recourse to force.16. Despite the extensive degree of statutory control over industrial relations the Australian system has not been outstandingly successful over theyears in preventing disputes. In 1957 there were 1,103 stoppages in Australia.Of these 119 were settled under federal legislation, 63 under state legislation,188 by private negotiation and 733 by other methods. The explanation of thelarge number of disputes settled by &quot; other methods &quot; is that about two-thirds ofall strikes lasted one day or less and were therefore settled before statutorymachinery could be brought into play, and no doubt many of these were unofficial strikes of the kind familiar in this country.17. However in the last few years the Australian strike record has improved and the record for the five-year period 1957-61 is somewhat better than that ofthe United Kingdom. To some extent the improvement may be due to thelong-term effect of alterations in the law in 1956 which gave greater prominenceto conciliation before recourse is had to arbitration. There are however many other contributory factors, of which economic factors are thought to have hadthe most decisive effect.FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANYWorkers&apos; and employers&apos; organisations18. Trade unions were abolished in Germany in 1933, and an entirelyreorganised trade union movement has developed since the war. The main central organisation is the General Confederation of Trade Unions (D.G.B.), foundedin 1949, which has 16 affiliated unions with a total membership of over 6J million workers. The unions are organised on an industrial basis, and the limits betweenthe jurisdictions of the various unions are settled by a committee of the DG.B.All of the unions have adopted a standard set of rules on strike procedure.A strike is not to take place until there has been a secret ballot of those concernedin which 75 per cent of the votes favour a strike. The D.G.B. has strike fundsat its disposal which it can use if it considers a strike in the interests of the entiretrade union movement.
19. Salaried employees have a separate central organisation, the GermanUnion of Salaried Employees. It covers rather less than half a million employees.They are organised on an occupational, rather than an industrial, basis.20. Employers&apos; associations were likewise abolished in 1933. The present general Confederation of Employers&apos; Associations was established in 1950.It covers industry, commerce and agriculture. Employers&apos; associations within an industry are grouped together in a central body for that industry which represents the employers in matters of national, as opposed to local, concern.Law and practice21. Collective agreements. Collective agreements are enforceable at lawunder the Collective Agreements Act, 1952. They are however enforceable only between the parties themselves, i.e., the trade union (or unions) and the employer(s) or employers&apos; association(s) which are signatories to it. This placesa trade union in a weak position in trying to oblige an individual employer to observe the terms of an agreement which an association of which he is a memberhas concluded: any action has to be brought against the association in an effort to force it to sue its constituent employer. Likewise however an employer cannotbring an action against individual employees for breach of the terms of a collective agreement.22. Individual contracts of employment may not contain terms less favourable to the employee than terms in a relevant collective agreement.23. The authorities may make a &quot; declaration of general applicability &quot; asa result of which the terms of a collective agreement must be observed throughoutthe industry concerned in the district or area to which the collective agreementapplies.24. Actions for the enforcement of collective agreements are brought beforeLabour Courts, which exist at District, Land and Federal level, the senior courtshaving appellate functions. The courts are composed of career magistratestogether with persons appointed on the recommendation of employers&apos; and workers&apos; organisations.25. The Labour Court can award damages in actions for breach of collective agreements, and these can amount to the full loss suffered by an employer as aresult of a strike in breach of an agreement.26. Strike action. The right to strike is circumscribed in a number of ways.During the currency of a collective agreement the parties may not resort tocoercive action in any matter which is regulated by the collective agreement. Ifthey do so they risk an action in the Labour Court and the award of damagesagainst them.27. In addition nearly all collective agreements contain provisions onconciliation which put into effect the terms of a Model Conciliation agreement which was negotiated between the D.G.B. and the employers in 1954. A procedure for conciliation by a joint &quot; Conciliation Office &quot; is laid down, and it applies inthe event of a dispute between the parties on any matter. If the Office fails tobring the parties together it may make recommendations. These do not haveto be accepted, but if they are they have the force of a collective agreement. Nocoercive action is allowed until the conciliation procedure has been exhaustedwithout success.28. The Labour Courts have also under the Civil Code developed a &quot; theoryof social adequacy &quot; in relation to strikes. As a result, according to an experton labour law in Germany, an industrial dispute is now regarded as illegal ifit is of such a nature as to make it impossible to settle it by the conclusion of a collective agreement. All unofficial or wild-cat strikes are illegal. Trade unions(or individual strikers) which organise or take part in an illegal strike are liableto an action in tort and damages may be recovered against them. Strikes withina single undertaking are also virtually forbidden under the Works Councils Act1952 (see next paragraph).29. Works councils. Under the Works Councils Act, 1952, works councils are established statutorily in every undertaking with five or more employees.The works council consists of employee&apos;s representatives directly elected. The
employer and the works council are to hold joint meetings once a month.Any differences the employer and the works council are unable to resolve by negotiation may be referred to a conciliation committee composed of equal numbers of assessors appointed by each side together with an independent chairman. The employer and the works council are expressly forbidden to &quot; carryout any acts of industrial warfare against each other &quot;, and this means thatstrikes at plant level are virtually forbidden by the law.30. The works council has the right of &quot; co-decision &quot; together with the employer in the following matters in so far as they are not determined by statute or collective agreement:(a) arrangement of daily working hours and breaks;(b) time and place of payment of remuneration;(c) holiday arrangements;id) vocational training;(e) administration of social services within the undertaking;(/) matters relating to order and conduct;ig) fixing of job and piece-rates;(h) laying down of pay systems and the introduction of new systems.Whenever agreement cannot be reached on one of these matters by negotiationor conciliation, the conciliation committee is to make a binding decision ifnecessary by a majority vote.31. Works councils in undertakings with more than 20 employees also haverights where engagements, regradings, transfers and dismissals are concerned.A works council may refuse its consent to actions by an employer as regardsthese matters on a number of specified grounds (e.g., that the employer isexercising discrimination on grounds of race or political or trade unionactivity), and if the local Labour Court on application upholds its view the employees action is reversed. There is also provision for co-decision inmatters affecting the running of the undertaking which will have far-reachingconsequences for the employees.32. Dismissals. Employees are legally protected against &quot; sociallyunwarranted dismissal&quot; by an Act of 1951. A dismissal is &quot;sociallyunwarranted&quot; unless it is based on reasons connected with the person orconduct of the worker or on the &quot; pressing operational requirements&quot; of theundertaking. An employee who considers he has been unjustifiably dismissedmay appeal to the Labour Court. (He may appeal first, if he wishes, tothe Works Council, but is not bound by the Works CounciFs decision if itgoes against him.) If the Labour Court upholds the employee&apos;s case he maybe reinstated or receive compensation in lieu up to a maximum of 12 months&apos; pay.The burden of proving that the dismissal was justified rests on the employer.33. Examples of unofficial strikes. There are only reported to have beentwo unofficial strikes in the last two or three years. In the first, in December1961, 450 workers in a shoe factory struck on the grounds that they were be ingtreated inhumanly, and demanded the dismissal of two members of themanagement. The union concerned did all it could to get the workers back towork without success. However, after a few days they were summarily dismissed,v/hereupon the union decided to support them financially. The employers broughttwo successful law suits, the first against some 60 &quot; ring leaders &quot; in the disputeand the second against the union for intervening illegally. The damages amountedto the full loss of the firm due to the strike.34. The second strike took place in a porcelain works in Coburg. Theunion became involved and was in consequence sued and had to pay all damagessuffered by the firm as a result of the strike, as well as costs.35. Protection of the individual. In Germany there is little formalprotection for the individual trade unionist against the powers of his union.There appears to have been little demand for it. This is no doubt in part becauseof the moderate policy of most unions in the post-war period, plus the strengthof anti-strike and other industrial relations legislation. The closed shop cannot
validly be written into a collective agreement in Germany, and in consequenceany strike aimed to achieve a closed shop is illegal. Moreover, as mentioned inparagraph 18, the D.G.B. requires unions to provide in their rules that no strikecan be held unless it has been authorised by a secret ballot in which at least75 per cent of the voters favour a strike.Conclusions36. Germany has an outstanding record of industrial peace in recent years,and such stoppages as have taken place are almost invariably official. One reasonappears to be that the organisation of trade unions on an industrial basis has enabled the trade unions to exercise a good deal of authority over their members.In general an unofficial strike is regarded as an act lacking discipline and loyalty to trade union leadership, and is therefore regarded with contempt. No doubtalso the need for a co-operative effort to recover from the devastating effects of the last war has been an important factor.37. It seems that the Works Council Act has had a very beneficial effecton relations at local level, with the result that many of the sort of grievancesthat might give rise to unofficial strikes are settled at the outset round theconference table. On the other hand it also seems that the legal penalties attachedto striking in most circumstances, and in particular to unofficial strikes, has hada powerful deterrent effect. This is reinforced by the fact that the LabourCourts, which have a good reputation for impartiality, have shown little disposition to handle illegal strikers tenderly.SWEDENWorkers&apos;. and employers&apos; organisations38. Roughly 65 per cent of employees in Sweden belong to trade unions.There are two main trade union federations. The larger is the Confederation of swedish Trade Unions (L.O.), which has affiliated to it 44 trade unions with atotal membership of about H- million workers, predominantly manual. The unions are mainly organised on an industrial basis, but there are exceptions, such asthose covering foundrymen and workers in the printing and building trades.Unions affiliated to the L.O. must include certain provisions in their rules. Inparticular the right to make final decisions on agreements and disputes must be vested in the union&apos;s executive council, and the promotion of unofficial strikesor a refusal to return to work when instructed by the union to do so are to begrounds for expulsion from the union. The L.O. has extensive powers overaffiliated unions. It may for instance participate in wage negotiations and make proposals for agreements. There is a strike fund under L.O. control. Noaffiliated union can call a strike of more than 3 per cent of its members withoutL.O. permission, and the L.O. contribution to strike pay (about 33s. per workerper week) is withheld if a strike it has not authorised takes place.39. The other main trade union federation is the Central Organisation ofSalaried Employees (T.C.O.), which comprises 36 unions with a total membership of about 400,000. The T.C.O. has a considerable degree of control over its affiliatedunions, though it is less marked than that of the L.O. There are in addition to theT.C.O. two other federations of unions representing salaried employees, the total membership of which is about 80,000.40. The Swedish Employers&apos; Confederation (S.A.F.) is the main central organisation of employers. It is composed of 44 employers&apos; associations coveringdiffering branches of industry, and covers a total of about 16,000 undertakings.The S.A.F. has a good deal of central control. Collective agreements, to be binding on an affiliated enterprise, have to be approved by the S.A.F. The S.A.F. also controls the actions of employers in industrial disputes. Strikes have to be reported not onlyto the relevant employers&apos; association but to the S.A.F. Lockouts are controlled by the S.A.F.
Law and practice41. Collective agreements. Collective agreements are legally binding underthe Collective Agreements Act, 1928. While a collective agreement is in force neitheremployers nor workers may engage in a strike, lock-out or other coerciveaction either because of a dispute over the interpretation or application of theagreement or in order to alter its terms. Employers&apos; and workers&apos; organisationshave a duty to try and prevent such action. Any employer, employee or employeesor workers&apos; organisation failing to observe the terms of a relevant collective agreement or of the Collective Agreements Act, 1928, is liable for damages for loss incurred as a result. In deciding the extent of the loss &quot; the interest of theperson concerned in the maintenance of the contract and other circumstances otherthan those of a purely economic nature shall be taken into consideration &quot;. liability to damages may be reduced or extinguished altogether according to the degree ofblame to be attached to the offending party or parties. No individual can besentenced to pay damages of more than 200 kronor (about  14).42. Actions for the enforcement of collective agreements are brought by theaggrieved party or parties to the agreement before the Labour Court under theLabour Court Act, 1928. The Labour Court consists of a chairman and six assessors.Of the assessors two are appointed on the recommendation of employers&apos; interestsand two on the recommendation of workers&apos; interests. Apart from awardingdamages the Labour Court can impose fines and issue distraint and sequestrationorders for failure to comply with its decisions.43. In 1938 the L.O. and S.A.F. concluded the Basic Agreement (known asthe Saltsjobaden Agreement) which was designed to provide the basis for peacefulself-government in industry. The Basic Agreement among other things lays down a negotiating procedure for the settlement of industrial disputes, other than disputesover the making or renewal of collective agreements and certain other limited types of dispute. Collective agreements between members of the L.O. and the S.A.F.with few exceptions provide that the parties are to observe the terms of the BasicAgreement. Hence the parties to collective agreements are normally legally obligedto observe the disputes procedure in the Basic Agreement. The disputes procedureprovides for local negotiation, to be followed, if it is unsuccessful, by centralnegotiations. No coercive action may be taken until the procedure has been used.If the dispute concerns the interpretation or application of a collective agreement it must be settled either by arbitration or by the Labour Court.44. It will be seen that a sharp distinction is drawn in Sweden between&quot; rights &quot; disputes, i.e., disputes over the interpretation of a collective agreement,and &quot; economic &quot; disputes, i.e., disputes over the terms to be included in a new agreement. Once a collective agreement has expired there is no restriction on theuse of force by either party to support the terms it demands for a new collective agreement.45. As regards matters settled locally the general position may be stated asfollows. An employer may conclude a collective agreement (which will of course be legally enforceable) with his employees. If there should be a dispute over whatthe terms in such a local agreement should be the parties would be able legally touse force in support of their claims. However if they are covered as will normally be the case by a current national agreement they will be legally obliged to follow the negotiating procedures laid down in that agreement before resorting to force.46. As a matter of general practice it may be said that national collective agreements in Sweden are extremely comprehensive and detailed, and thereforereduce to the minimum the area for local negotiation and the possibility of localdisputes. Wages are not settled locally, and a dispute over the application of apiece-rate system would be regarded as a rights, not an economic, dispute. collective agreements are usually for a fixed term of one year or two years. Notice of termination is generally required, the most common period being three months,failing which the agreement is automatically renewed for a year. Practically allindustrial agreements are timed to expire between the end of January and the endof March, so that there is a &quot; collective bargaining season &quot; at the turn of the year.47. Recognition. The Right of Association and Collective Bargaining Act,1936, gives the right of negotiation to an employer and the association to which hebelongs and to trade unions representing employees employed by the employer.
The right of negotiation is defined as &quot; the right to restitute negotiationsrespecting the adjustment of conditions of employment and respecting the relationsbetween employers and employees in general&quot;. Any trade union with membersemployed by an employer may oblige the employer to attend a meeting for negotiations and &quot; where necessary &quot; the employer must make proposals supportedby reasons for the settlement of the question concerning which negotiations wereinstituted.48. In practical terms the Act compels the two sides to sit down round a table to negotiate. It does not compel the employer to reach agreement. If forinstance all but a few of an employees workers belong to one trade union, and heis covered by a collective agreement with it, the employer could be obliged tonegotiate with another union representing the minority but he would be free to insist that he could only agree to terms which were identical with those he hadalready agreed with the other union.49. It is understood that the 1936 Act has made little practical difference wheremanual workers&apos; unions are concerned, but that it led to a great increase in collective bargaining for white-collar workers.50. Notification of industrial disputes. Under the Conciliation Act(Amendment) Act, 1935, seven days&apos; notice of a stoppage of work must be givenboth to the other party and to the public conciliation service. Failure to give duenotice may lead to prosecution and a fine not exceeding 300 kronor (about  21).Under an Act of 1920 certain duties are put on the conciliation service with a viewto bringing about the peaceful settlement of disputes.51. Dismissals. The Basic Agreement includes provisions on dismissal,lay-off and re-engagement. Before giving notice to a worker with more than nine months&apos; service an employer must give his trade union at least two weeks&apos; warning.An exception is made for dismissal for misconduct. Disputes over a dismissal canultimately be referred to a joint body called the Labour Market Council. In reaching a decision the Council is to take account of the employees interests and of such factors as the length of service and family responsibilities of the worker concerned.52. An example of an unofficial strike. One of Sweden&apos;s rare unofficial strikestook place in Gothenburg in the spring of 1962. It started when 50 stevedoresstopped work as a protest about wages, and the dispute quickly spread to nearly all the dock workers in Gothenburg about 1,600 men. For some time the men had been covered by a temporary, experimental, collective agreement, but it had just expired and they were again covered by the agreement previously in force:this was the source of discontent.53. As soon as the dispute started union representatives arrived from Stockholm and harangued the men, and after a vote they all returned to work.After inquiries by the L.O. and S.A.F. the employers brought an action againstmore than 40 of the stevedores in the Labour Court for breach of the collective agreement. The Court took a serious view of the strike and awarded the maximumdamages of about  14 against each of the workers, plus costs of about  3 each.54. Protection of the individual. Sweden is a country where trade unionaspirations and methods are widely accepted and there is in general not muchfriction between unions and their members. Unions exercise considerable authority over their members as regards wage agreements, as indeed does the L.O. over its constituent unions. Conversely, L.O.&apos;s statutes oblige affiliated unions to include in their rules provision for:(a) the right of all workers within their jurisdiction to become members, withcertain exceptions within the Union Committee&apos;s discretion, e.g., if theapplicant has embezzled union funds or been a strike-breaker, etc.; and(b) the right of individuals to transfer their membership to another union free of charge if they move to a job covered by a different union.55. It is generally agreed that the Swedish trade union movement, thoughhighly centralised, is genuinely democratic. The L.O. rarely exercises its powerover unions as regards negotiations, and is well aware of its obligation ofresponsibility to the rank and file. But it does not hesitate to act where necessary,for example, against unofficial strikes. When a group of workers in petrol
distribution went on unofficial strike out of dissatisfaction with the 1960negotiations, their union expelled them and re-accepted them individually and only on condition that they accepted the constitutional position.56. The closed shop is not an issue in Sweden. The Employers&apos; Confederationregards it as contrary to the 1938 Basic Agreement and will not accept agreementsincluding it, and unions do not press for such agreements as they are in generalable to achieve a high level of organisation without it. Even where closed shopagreements exist, they do not prevent workers from choosing the union they wishto join; this right has been consistently upheld by the Labour Court on the grounds that its denial would be contrary to the right of association. In both L.O. andT.C.O. unions, disputes over refusal of admission to or expulsion from a unioncan, after examination within the union, be submitted to the courts and ultimately to the Supreme Court.57. In Sweden, then, protection of individual members against arbitraryaction by unions has been extensively achieved not by legislation but by generalagreement among unions and unionists and by adherence to a common standardof democratic behaviour.Conclusions58. There is a high degree of discipline amongst both employers&apos; and workers&apos; organisations in Sweden, with strong central organisations and alsoconstituent organisations which are prepared to discipline their members. The tradeunions are constituted mainly on an industrial basis, and, assisted by union dueswhich are high by British standards, are well organised at all levels. The impositionof central authority is made easier by Sweden&apos;s comparatively small working population-3 - 3 million people. Another important factor is that in generalemployers have accepted that it is in their own interests to recognise and concludeagreements with the trade unions. Moreover both sides following a disastrousperiod of industrial strife up to about 1935 have accepted the advantages ofpeace in industry and the need to do everything possible to reach agreement.59. Swedish law has been adapted to assist the maintenance of authority andorder in industrial relations, particularly through the enforcement of collective agreements in the Labour Court.UNITED STATES OF AMERICAHistory60. Industrial relations in the United States stem from a tradition in whichjudicial decisions and federal legislation* have had much more effect thanin this country. In the &quot; injunction era &quot; before 1932 the employer^ main methodof frustrating union aims was to apply for an injunction, enforceable on pain ofpenalties for contempt of court, against union actions that could be claimed to bein restraint of trade. The readiness of courts to grant immediate interiminjunctions which could themselves often cause attempts to organise strikes to&quot; fizzle out &quot; and to convert these, after full hearings, into permanent injunctions,had a grave and prolonged effect on union activities. This era ended in theNorris-La Guardia Act, 1932, which divested federal courts of injunctive powers in labour disputes except under stringent conditions.61. The Wagner Act, 1935. The Wagner Act expressed the thesis that even after 1932 there was an inequality in bargaining strength between employers and workers that should be redressed in favour of the latter. Its aims were to encourageand protect the organisation of workers and to compel employers to bargaincollectively. Provision was made for workers to choose a trade union to representthem, with which their employer had to bargain, and employers were forbidden to engage in certain &quot; unfair labour practices &quot; e.g., interference with workers intheir right to form a union and bargain collectively. A National Labour relations board (N.L.R.B.) was set up to investigate charges of unfair labour practices.* This appendix does not cover State legislation.
62. In the years following 1935, union membership and strength grewrapidly. But the war, during which pledges of no strikes and no lockouts weregiven by the unions&apos; and employers&apos; federations, broke the normal course ofindustrial relations. In 1946 a tremendous wave of strikes led to the loss of116 million working days-an all-time record. Feeling was widespread that thependulum had swung too far in the unions&apos; favour, and the Taft-Hartley Act, 1947,was a deliberate attempt to redress the balance in favour of the employer.63. The Taft-Hartley Act, 1947. This long and complicated measureretained the basic Wagner concepts of the workers&apos; right to organise and chooserepresentatives, employers&apos; unfair labour practices and an enforcement agency,but attempted in six ways to modify the power unions had achieved: the ideaof union unfair labour practices was introduced; the procedures for determiningworkers&apos; representatives were changed (with the aim of enabling workers to avoidor rid themselves of unions if they wished); an attempt was made to imposecontrols on unions&apos; internal affairs; provision was made for actions for breach of contract to be brought between an employer and a union; a cooling-off period was imposed on a party to a collective agreement wishing to modify or end it;and political contributions were forbidden. An emergency procedure for dealingwith strikes or lockouts that could lead to a national emergency was also included.The unfair labour practice provisions of the Act were amended in certain respectsby the Landrum-Griffin Act, 1959.64. These provisions have not all been equally effective. In general howeverthey do seem to have hampered union activities and recruitment to a certain extent.Since 1947 the growth of the unions in membership and strength has greatly slowed down if not ceased. However there are many other contributory reasons for this,and there appear to be good grounds for saying that Taft-Hartley has not itselfsucceeded in its aim of producing more equality in bargaining power.Particular aspects of United States legislation65. Enforceability of collective agreements.- Under Taft-Hartley a union canbe sued by an employer for breach of a contract or collective agreement, or for damages by any person injured by a &quot; secondary &quot; boycott or a sympathetic ordemarcation strike. But in fact actions for breaches of agreement are rare exceptions.Employers, it seems, are in general unattracted by this course of action, and union leaders show little concern over the provision, about whose exact scope and meaningthere has been a good deal of legal disagreement. Individual workers, however, have brought actions, and in two recent cases quite substantial compensation wasawarded to workers who had been prevented from working by unions&apos; actions.66. Recognition. One of the aims of the Wagner Act was to compelemployers to bargain collectively. Workers in an undertaking are empowered tocall for a secret election to determine whether they should be represented by a trade union, and, if so, which one. If a majority in a given unit vote for a particularunion, that union is given exclusive bargaining rights with the employer, and the employer has to negotiate with it with a view to arriving at a collective agreement,refusal to do so being designated an unfair labour practice.67. In carrying these provisions into practice a great deal of authority is placed on the N.L.R.B. For instance the Board determines what is to be a&quot; bargaining unit&quot;, i.e., an area of employment in which a group of workers maybe covered by a union for the purposes of collective bargaining. It is obviously ofcrucial importance whether the Board decides a whole factory is a unit, or whether for example it regards different groups of craft workers within the factory as constituting separate units. Likewise the Board is compelled to specify whetherparticular issues are negotiable issues or not if for instance an employer agrees to bargain about wages but not about paid holidays. In enforcing the Act theN.L.R.B. has powers to investigate charges of unfair labour practices and issue orders. The orders are not self-enforcing and there are no penalties for non-observance as such, but the Board can seek an enforcement order from a court,and once one is granted failure to comply may be punishable as contempt of court.68. Under Taft-Hartley the employees in an existing bargaining unit havea right to ask for a decertification vote to decide whether bargaining authority should be withdrawn from a union previously designated as representing them.
69. Strikes: Union unfair labour practices. Unfair labour practices byunions include strikes with a number of different aims: forcing an employer tojoin an employers&apos; organisation; forcing a self-employed person to join a tradeunion; forcing a neutral employer to stop dealing with another employer with whom the union has a dispute a far-reaching provision; forcing an employerother than the workers&apos; own (a &quot; secondary &quot; strike) to bargain with a union notcertified by the N.L.R.B. as representing his workers; forcing an employer to bargain with one union when another has been certified as representative of theworkers concerned; and forcing an employer to assign particular work to workersin a particular union, trade, craft or class (&quot; jurisdictional&quot; strikes). It is worth noting here that, when an unfair labour practice is alleged, under Taft-Hartley theN.L.R.B. (not the aggrieved party) may at its discretion apply for an injunctionrestraining the party complained of pending investigation a partial return to thepre-1932 position.70. These restrictions, as administered by the N.L.R.B., have undoubtedlyhad some effect in limiting the tactics unions use against employers, without beingregarded as unduly harsh. The inclusion of secondary boycott among unfair labourpractices is generally thought more significant than any of the strike provisions.It is of interest that &quot; jurisdictional&quot; strikes are among unfair labour practices.It is widely agreed that this has done something to reduce demarcation disputes,especially by encouraging unions to avoid trouble by private arrangements among themselves.71. The cooling-off period. Taft-Hartley requires a party wishing to end ormodify a collective agreement to give written notice at least 60 days before thetermination of the agreement, and to offer to meet the other party to negotiate a revised agreement. If no agreement is reached the existing contract continues in fullforce for the 60 days or until it expires, whichever is later. Meanwhile, after 30 days the Federal Mediation and Conciliation Service has to be notified that a disputeexists. It is an unfair labour practice to strike in contravention of these requirements.72. It is generally thought that this provision makes little difference to thecourse of events in practice. Renegotiating an agreement is normally a prolongedprocess anyhow, and negotiations rarely reach a decisive stage until a few days before the expiry date. Moreover, the Supreme Court has held that the cooling-offperiod is required only in the case of negotiating a new contract; in a case whereworkers went on strike in breach of a no-strike clause in a collective agreement inprotest against alleged employer unfair labour practices it was held that thecooling-off period did not apply and 60 days&apos; notice was not necessary. (This is in line with the assertion of Taft-Hartley that none of its clauses may be construedin such a way as to interfere with or impede or diminish the right to strike except as specifically provided for in the Act.) In fact, therefore, the cooling-off periodhas a scope so limited as to exclude many of the situations where such a provisionmight be thought to be valuable.73. Disputes threatening a national emergency. An elaborate procedure is laid down for strikes that threaten to cause a national emergency. In such a case,the President may appoint a board of inquiry to investigate and report but without making any recommendations. On receiving the report, he may direct the Attorney-General to ask the federal courts for an injunction against the strike as likely toimperil national safety or health. If granted, the parties must during the next 60days try to settle their differences with the help of the Federal Mediation and conciliation Service. Meanwhile the President must reconvene the board of inquiry to make a further report at the end of the 60 days (unless the dispute has been settled), including in it a statement of the employees last offer. In the 15 daysfollowing the 60 the N.L.R.B. must hold an election among the workers as towhether they want to accept this offer; five further days are allowed to certify theresult of the election. On receiving the certification the Attorney-General must move the court to discharge the injunction, thus freeing the parties to proceed with thestrike.74. This procedure has many critics. It can serve as a way of temporarilydelaying strikes, which may lead to a settlement but may also cause attitudes on both sides to become rigid and inflexible. The prohibition on boards of inquiryfrom making recommendations removes what might be their most useful function,and their reports are produced under such pressure of time that they are often
perfunctory. During the 60 days there is little prospect of effective mediation the union has nothing to lose by awaiting the employees final offer. Moreover, evenin the fairly high proportion of cases where a settlement has been reached duringthe emergency procedure, it does not follow that the procedure was the cause of settlement and many observers doubt if it makes any contribution, or any difference,to the final settlement reached.75. Protection of the individual. Legal protection for members against theirunions in the United States rests mainly on the provisions of Taft-Hartley. It is an unfair labour practice by an employer to discriminate as regards the engagement oflabour or tenure of employment, or its terms or conditions, with a view toencouraging or discouraging membership in any labour organisation. But anagreement between an employer and a union can require workers to join the unionwithin 30 days of engagement (though such an agreement can be rescinded by amajority vote against it in an election held under the auspices of the N.L.R.B.).*Where a union security agreement of this kind is in force the only ground on whicha union can exclude an employee from membership and then bring pressure onthe employer to discharge him is failure on the part of the employee to pay areasonable ii.e., not exorbitant) initiation fee or failure to pay dues. Otherwise theunion is committing an unfair labour practice.76. The Taft-Hartley Act does not prevent individual states from legislatingagainst &quot; union security&quot; agreements of any kind, and in fact some 20 states have adopted so-called &quot; right-to-work &quot; laws. (State legislation applies normallyto intra-state commerce, as opposed to the more important field of inter-statecommerce which falls under federal jurisdiction.) By and large the states concerned have been southern or mid-western states where industry is less developed andthe unions are in any case weak. It appears likely that a good deal of the support for &quot; right-to-work &quot; legislation comes from people who have a greater interestin weakening the trade unions than in protecting the rights of the individual.77. The special case of the &quot; agency shop &quot; is worth mention. Under thisemployees who are not members of a trade union have to pay a contributionequal to the union subscription which is used, e.g., for a welfare scheme or forthe administration of a collective agreement. In some instances the contributions of employees who do not join a union out of religious principles are devoted tocharity. &quot; Agency shop &quot; agreements have been held in some states (not all) not toinfringe right-to-work laws, since the laws only prohibit compulsory membership of a union. Such agreements are however rare.78. Unfair labour practices by unions include restraining or coercing workersin the exercise of rights guaranteed by the Act (e.g., picketing so as effectively to obstruct non-striking workers from entering the employer^ premises); acts of violence and threats of force or violence on the picket lines or in connection withstrikes; threats to workers that they will lose their livelihood unless they supportthe union&apos;s activities; strikes or boycotts forcing an employer to assign particularwork to workers in a particular union, trade, craft or class (unless the employer is failing to conform to an N.L.R.B. order determining the bargainingrepresentation for employees performing such work); and requiring workerscovered by a valid union shop agreement to pay initiation fees which the N.L.R.B.finds excessive or discriminatory.79. Taft-Hartley also requires a union, to qualify for use of the N.L.R.B.&apos;sfacilities, to file copies of its constitution and bye-laws and an annual report of its financial position. The provision that they must also file affidavits by all officers that they are not Communist or Communist supporters has been superseded bythe Landrum-Griffm Act, 1959, which bars from union office anyone who is or has been (within the past five years) a Communist Party member or who has been convicted of any one of a number of serious offences. This Act also requiresunion officers to be elected by secret ballot and limits the periods between elections,prohibits the use of union money on behalf of any candidate, gives all candidatescertain rights in the campaign and at the poll, and allows complaints againstbreaches of these provisions to the Secretary of Labour. If the Secretary decidesafter investigation to bring a court action and the court finds the election invalid,it may direct a new election to be held under the Secretary&apos;s supervision.* In fact it has been the N.L.R.B&apos;s policy to discourage &quot; switching &quot; and it is not easy to defeata union that has consolidated its bargaining rights.
80. Legal protection for individual members is therefore extensive, but itseffectiveness in practice appears to be questionable. This is due mainly to theoligarchic tendencies of union leaderships. In a 1959 study Professor B. C. Robertswrote: &quot;In some unions the rights of members have been flagrantly violated byunion leaders intent on keeping power at all costs. . . . American leaders appearto have achieved a position of supremacy that goes far beyond what is normalin many other countries.&quot; Leaders are often effectively chosen by the unionmachine rather than the rank and file and are largely free from influence by thelatter after appointment. Centralisation, too, has often created local units too large to be democratic in their conduct of affairs. Perhaps most important, it isnot at all easy for many union members to demonstrate dissatisfaction with their leaders by leaving their union. The complexity of the &quot; union shop &quot; provisions ofthe law combines with &quot; no-raiding &quot; pacts sponsored by the A.F.L.-C.I.O. torender workers&apos; choice between unions, or between membership or non-membership, very limited.81. Efforts to curb the excessive power of union leaders are clearly reflected in the Landrum-Griffin Act and. have been exemplified by the continuing struggleto unseat the most notorious of union &quot; bosses &quot; James Hoffa of the Teamsters&apos;Union. It cannot yet be said that these efforts have succeeded. Some unions arekeenly conscious of this problem. The United Automobile Workers and theUpholsterers have both established independent review boards of outside persons to which members can appeal for final decision against alleged violation of their rights. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. has laid down a code of ethical practices designed toensure fair treatment of individual members, which all affiliated unions are urged to adopt. As yet, however, the power of individual members to play a fulldemocratic part in their union affairs and influence the action of their leaders,if necessary by the sanction of withdrawal from the union, is not sufficientlyensured.Conclusions82. The strike record in the United States is considerably worse than in theUnited Kingdom. This does not at first sight suggest that United States procedurescould be adopted in the United Kingdom with advantage. However there are many factors that may account for this other than the merits of the systemitself. One such factor is that local and plant negotiation is normal in the UnitedStates and this clearly increases the risk of strikes. However the same factor means that the trade unions are strongly organised at local level and are so able towield their authority at this point.83. Unofficial strikes are comparatively infrequent. In general mostcollective agreements run for fixed terms and contain detailed disputes procedures,usually providing for arbitration. These appear to be generally observed, and failure to do so results in the committing of an unfair labour practice and the legalrestraints on these may follow, apart from the important exception of a strikeagainst an employer^ unfair labour practices. No doubt the statutory recognitionprocedures have also helped to reduce the possible area for dispute and to enablethe unions to establish and wield their authority effectively within undertakings.

80. Legal protection for individual members is therefore extensive, but itseffectiveness in practice appears to be questionable. This is due mainly to theoligarchic tendencies of union leaderships. In a 1959 study Professor B. C. Robertswrote: &quot; In some unions the rights of members have been flagrantly violated byunion leaders intent on keeping power at all costs. . . . American leaders appearto have achieved a position of supremacy that goes far beyond what is normalin many other countries.&quot; Leaders are often effectively chosen by the unionmachine rather than the rank and file and are largely free from influence by thelatter after appointment. Centralisation, too, has often created local units too large to be democratic in their conduct of affairs. Perhaps most important, it isnot at all easy for many union members to demonstrate dissatisfaction with their leaders by leaving their union. The complexity of the &quot; union shop &quot; provisions ofthe law combines with &quot; no-raiding &quot; pacts sponsored by the A.F.L.-C.I.O. torender workers&apos; choice between unions, or between membership or non-membership, very limited.81. Efforts to curb the excessive power of union leaders are clearly reflected in the Landrum-Griffin Act and have been exemplified by the continuing struggleto unseat the most notorious of union &quot; bosses &quot; James Hoffa of the Teamsters&apos;Union. It cannot yet be said that these efforts have succeeded. Some unions arekeenly conscious of this problem. The United Automobile Workers and theUpholsterers have both established independent review boards of outside persons to which members can appeal for final decision against alleged violation of their rights. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. has laid down a code of ethical practices designed toensure fair treatment of individual members, which all affiliated unions are urged to adopt. As yet, however, the power of individual members to play a fulldemocratic part in their union affairs and influence the action of their leaders,if necessary by the sanction of withdrawal from the union, is not sufficientlyensured.Conclusions82. The strike record in the United States is considerably worse than in theUnited Kingdom. This does not at first sight suggest that United States procedurescould be adopted in the United Kingdom with advantage. However there are many factors that may account for this other than the merits of the systemitself. One such factor is that local and plant negotiation is normal in the UnitedStates and this clearly increases the risk of strikes. However the same factor means1 that the trade unions are strongly organised at local level and are so able towield their authority at this point.83. Unofficial strikes are comparatively infrequent. In general mostcollective agreements run for fixed terms and contain detailed disputes procedures,usually providing for arbitration. These appear to be generally observed, and failure to do so results in the committing of an unfair labour practice and the legalrestraints on these may follow, apart from the important exception of a strikeagainst an employer^ unfair labour practices. No doubt the statutory recognitionprocedures have also helped to reduce the possible area for dispute and to enablethe unions to establish and wield their authority effectively within undertakings.


</content>
</cab>
