<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/58/39 images: 314-319</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESYyS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 689.24:th November, 1944.WAR CABINET.TRAVEL BY MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT TO FRANCE.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.1. A number of applications have recently been received from Members ofParliament for exit permits to go. to France for the purpose of renewing personal and political contacts. (An analysis of these cases is appended.) His Majesty&apos;ambassador at Paris sees no objection to this provided it is made clear to allconcerned (a) That no hotel accommodation is available for the public in Paris.(6) That neither the Embassy nor S.H.A.E.F. could give them facilities for board, lodging or transport.(c) That friends in France would therefore have to house and feed them..2. This proposal is related to the general question of permitting freerintercourse between this country and France. From the point of view of foreignpolicy it is desirable that such intercourse should be encouraged and facilities provided at the earliest practicable date. At an interdepartmental meeting onthis question between the Foreign. Office, Home Office, Trade and TransportDepartments on the 10th November, it was provisionally agreed to recommendthat as soon as public transport to France is available, any person without reference to the reason for the journey should be eligible for an exit permit.3. Certain other Departments have an interest in this proposal; and thegrant of an exit permit to any person would, of course, be subject to (a) security and national service clearance;(b) the grant of a French visa; and(c) arrangements being made for his maintenance without breaking the currency export restrictions.4. It was felt, however, that the question whether Members of parliament should be allowed to go in advance of the provision of public transport and there opening of travel generally, was one for Ministers to decide. Mr. Ronald Tree,M.P., and Mr. Hamilton Kerr, M.P., who have been invited by Mr. Duff Cooperto visit him, have since given notice that they will raise the matter in the Houseat the earliest opportunity.5. Under present conditions travel to the interior zone of France is confined to officials travelling on duty and persons proceeding on business of national importance certified as such by the appropriate Government Department. Theonly transport available is military aircraft and there is no authority to make a charge for the use of such transport. The demand for places at present isunderstood to be about equal to the supply, but, as soon as French visas begin tocome through for business men, waiting lists will begin to form. The justification for providing free travel in such cases is that the journey is certified to be ofnational importance. These considerations lead to the conclusion that, despite thevery strong reasons for encouraging travel to France, the present limitations makeit impossible at present to extend facilities to any class of private traveller.6.   The case for the special treatment of Members of Parliament as regardstravel to France before public transport.is available, would rest on the basis that[28685]
the Parliamentary duties of a Member of Parliament entitled him to travel toFrance and to transport at the public expense for this purpose. This constitu-tional argument, if admitted, would, of course, apply to Members of any Party,including the Communist Party, Independents, Commonwealth, LLP., and alsoMembers of the House of Lords. (If the proposals for allowing freer travel toFrance when public transport is available are approved, Members of parliament will then be able to go in the same way as anybody else.)7. It has been the view acted upon by the Government throughout the war,that a Member of Parliament cannot, as of right, claim an exit permit to go toany part of the world in wartime on his mere statement that his parliamentary duties require him to- do so. It appears to have been accepted by the House ofCommons in the course of the debate of October 1941, in the case of Mr. McGovern,as right and proper that there should be control over the movements of members who wish to proceed overseas. Criticism was directed to control over their move-men ts between this country and Ireland. The policy which was adopted on thisborder-line issue and has&quot; been repeatedly affirmed by the Cabinet was that members might claim in the course of their Parliamentary duties to go to northern Ireland, which is a part of the United Kingdom, but that they had nosuch claim to go to Eire and must make out a case to the satisfaction of the HomeSecretary that a journey was to the national advantage, before an exit permitcould be granted. (See, e.g., W.M. (43) 92nd Conclusions, Minute 1, and 152ndConclusions, Minute 3.)8. As regards recent decisions on travel to France, on the 29th August,1944 (W.M. (44) 112th Conclusions, Minute 5), the War Cabinet decided that itwould be desirable to maintain the position that permission should be requiredfor any visit to France, and that the Foreign Secretary, who had been approached by a Member, should reply that in present conditions in that country it was notpossible to arrange for any private visits by Members.. Subsequently, CaptainGammans, M.P., asked the Prime Minister whether, in view of the fact that members of the United States Congress had visited France and the fightingzones in Western Europe, similar facilities will be provided for Members ofParliament. The Deputy Prime Minister replied : &quot;I hope it will shortly bepossible to arrange for Members of Parliament to visit France. It will, of course,be for the Supreme Allied Commander to decide whether their visits can includefighting zones.&quot;9. It could be argued that it is of importance to the national interest that members of Parliament should be able to inform themselves of the conditionsin newly liberated Europe, and that the early resumption of political contacts will improve mutual understanding between the nations. It is also important, itcould be held, that, subject to military considerations, they should be able toinform themselves of the service conditions of men in the forces where largenumbers of British troops are engaged. On the other hand, it does not seem thatthese objects would be jeopardised by their journeys being delayed for the month or two before public transport is likely to be available.10. Until then it would seem best to avoid conceding that Members ofParliament, in virtue of their Parliamentary position, have the right to travel toFrance or to any other destination outside the United Kingdom. Such an admission would destroy-the position which has been carefully preserved since thebeginning of the war and might at once lead to embarrassing results in relationto travel to other destinations before any announcement of a relaxation of restric-tions could be made. The adoption of the policy of free travel to France would,indeed, rapidly result in its extension to travel to all destinations and it wouldbecome practically impossible to maintain a refusal of exit permits to Membersof Parliament who might be indiscreet or mischievous in the United States. Itis understood that the French will be prepared to grant visas to any Members ofParliament who are granted exit permits.11. It would, moreover, be difficult to justify singling out Members ofParliament for travel for private reasons before other persons, includingrefugees from France, Many applications for travel facilities based on the strongest compassionate grounds have been received, and it has been necessaryto refuse them all in view of the extremely limited transport facilities and theirprovision at public expense. In would in practice be extremely difficult to decide whether a Member of Parliament wished to travel for political or privatereasons; a political flavour could no doubt be given to any journey.   It is most
necessary for the continued acceptance of restrictions tha,t the public shouldbelieve that they are administered impartially; and select,o:) of Members ofParliament for facilities of this kind might be strongly criticised by those whohave admittedly urgent and compelling grounds for making a journey, but areprevented from doing so.12.   Still less could the provision of a passage at public expense be justified!13. The House itself would probably accept this policy provided it is made clear that the restriction is a temporary one and that exit permits will begranted to Members on application when public transport becomes available,on the terms suggested by Mr. Duff Cooper and subject, of course, to a Trenchvisa being granted and to observance of the currency export restrictions.14. Unless the War Cabinet feel strongly otherwise, my view is, on balance,that for the reasons given in this memorandum, Members of Parliament as suchshould not be granted facilities to visit France until the transport situation is such that present restrictions on civilian travel can be relaxed, and that, likeothers, they can go by public transport at their own expense.H. M.Home Office, S.W. 1,24 ^ November, 1944.APPENDIX.Analysis of Applications for Members of Parliament to travel to France.(1) Commander King-Hall, M.P., has been refused (it is understood thisis the case referred to by the Foreign Secretary at the Cabinet Meeting29th August, 1944). &apos; &apos;(2) Mr. Vernon Bartlett, M.P., has been allowed to travel in his capacity -as newspaper correspondent with the support of the Ministry of Information.(3) Captain Peter Macdonald, M.P., has been allowed to travel as a businessman sponsored by the Department of Overseas Trade.(4) Sir Arthur Evans, M.P., as President of the Inter-Parliamentary Union,applied for permission to visit Paris in order to meet M. Boissier, Secretary ofthe Union. In actual fact, M. Boissier travelled to this country and metSir Arthur; and the request has not been pressed.(5) Mr. A. C- Bossom, M.P., applied to the Foreign Office to know whetherit wouid be possible for him to visit certain of the devastated areas in Franceduring the next short recess. This application was referred to the.Home Officeand was refused. Mr. Bossom&apos;s.request that his wife might be allowed to visither mother in Paris had been turned down by the Foreign Office slightly earlier.(6) The Labour Party wished to send Mr. Laski, Mr. Noel-Baker, M.P., Mr.Morgan Philips, and Mr. William Gillies to France to renew relations with theFrench Socialist Party. The War Cabinet considered the matter on the 6thNovember, 1944, and decided that while there was no reason why a delegation from the Labour Party should not go to Paris, on balance it was not desirablethat a Minister should go as a member of the delegation. Exit permits were granted on the 7th November to all but Mr. Noel-Baker. No M.P. was includedin the party.(7) Sir Robert Bird, M.P., recently took the initiative in reviving theAnglo-French Parliamentary Committee and approached the Foreign office with the suggestion that arrangements should be made for a delegation of thisCommittee to attend the reopening of the French Consultative Assembly. TheForeign Office were successful in dissuading him from pressing this until con-ditions in France improved.The following applications are outstanding  &apos;(8) Sir Oliver Simmonds, M.P., has applied for an exit permit to travel toFrance for a week. He gives no particulars of his business and merely stateshe is travelling as a Member of Parliament.(9) Mr. Ivor Thomas, Mr. J. H. Martin and Dr. Fiaden Guest have applied for facilities to visit France in order to resume political contacts. Theseapplications are apparently not being pressed at the moment.
(10) Captain Malcolm Bullock, Hon. Secretary of the Franco-British Society,has applied informally to visit France to make new contacts with a view todelivering talks and lectures on France on his return.(11) Mr. Ronald Tree, M.P., and Mr. Hamilton Kerr, M.P., have applied for permits to visit Mr. Duff Cooper who, in this instance, is ready to afford themhospitality.   (They were formerly his Parliamentary Private Secretaries.)I have written to Sir Oliver Simmonds and Mr. Ronald Tree and Mr.Hamilton Kerr informing them that the matter is being considered by theCabinet, but.that at present I am unable to accord them facilities. It would be embarrassing to discriminate between Members according to the willingness ofthe Ambassadors to accommodate them.



</content>
</cab>
