<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/98 images: 558-561</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   September 1941.SECRET. Copy No. 65W.P. (G) (41) 98.September 23, 1941.WAR CABINET.ALLIED MILITARY CONSCRIPTION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.ON the 15th August, 1940, my predecessor, with the concurrence of all theMinisters concerned, undertook in a note to the Allied Governments to &quot; inviteParliament to pass legislation conferring the necessary authority upon the AlliedAdministrations in the United Kingdom to call up their nationals for militaryservice in accordance with their existing national laws, or such other provisionsas the Allied Governments may wish to make.&quot; This undertaking has been repeated on more than one occasion in the House of Commons.2. Steps preparatory to the conferment of these powers upon the AlliedGovernments have been taken. A comprehensive registration of Allied nationalshas been carried out, and powers to conscript their merchant seamen have alreadybeen given to the Allied Governments by the Allied Powers (MaritimeCourts) Act.3. The preparation of legislation to give the Allied Governments power toenforce military conscription has, however, given rise to certain misgivings onthe part of the Minister of Labour and the Home Secretary. The MaritimeCourts Bill met with limited but tenacious opposition in the House of Commons,and my colleagues feel that there will be considerable opposition to an allied military Conscription Bill from those who consider that it will give insufficientprotection to certain members of the Allied communities in this country who may be opposed to their Governments on religious, racial or political grounds.Consideration has been given to a number of schemes for safeguarding not onlythe prerogatives of the Allied Governments, but also the position of the variousminorities. A plan was drawn up and mentioned in the War Cabinet on the26th May, but certain of the Departments concerned later foresaw serious difficulties about this scheme, and it has not been possible as a result of further examination to find any satisfactory compromise.4. The Minister of Labour will be in charge of the legislation, and, withthe concurrence of the other Ministers concerned, has now propounded a scheme by which Allied nationals in this country, who are not already embodied in their national forces or reserved from militaiw service because of the importance oftheir civil employment, will be given a free right of option between joining their national forces or the British forces. This will automatically solve minoritydifficulties, and has a. good deal to recommend it on practical grounds. But, asit involves a considerable derogation from the sovereign powers of the AlliedGovernments, it cannot be assumed that they will readily agree to it.5. In deference to the views of my colleagues, I am, however, prepared toput the proposition to the Allied Governments in the terms of a note which annex. But, as this proposition differs from the scheme already submitted to theCabinet, involves a breach of the undertaking which has been given to the Alliesand in the House of Commons, and may cause some political difficulty with theAllies, I feel I should first consult my colleagues on the action which it is proposedto take.A. E.Foreign Office, September 23, 1941.11493   [22938]
Your Excellency, . . ... ....... September    , 1941.Your Excellency will recall that in a note of the 15th August, 1940, lord halifax made certain proposals for the purpose of facilitating the employmentof male Allied nationals in the United Kingdom in the common Allied war effort.These proposals were based upon the two broad principles that the obligations forwar service on Allied nationals should so far as possible be the same as those on british subjects, and that the Allied Governments temporarily established in thiscountry should have the right of prior call upon the services of their own citizens.It was stated that His Majesty&apos;s Government contemplated submitting legislation to Parliament to enable the Allied Governments to call up their nationals formilitary service in accordance with their own national laws, and it was hopedthat it might be possible to arrange that the Allied Governments should be in aposition to direct their nationals to war service in a civilian capacity, in particular to service in the mercantile marine. In order to facilitate the suitable employmentof other Allied nationals, it was proposed that tihey should all be registered under arrangements concerted between the British Ministry of Labour and the appro-priate Allied authorities with a view to their being placed as rapidly as possiblein industrial or other civilian employment.2. These proposals received a general welcome from the Allied governments and considerable progress has been made in giving effect to them. A comprehensiveregistration of Allied nationals has been carried out and special offices have been set up to facilitate the placing of Allied citizens in useful employment. The AlliedPowers (Maritime Courts) Act has been passed by Parliament to enable theAllied Governments both to maintain discipline and to direct their merchant seamen, where necessary, to serve upon Allied merchant ships. It is only in thefield of military conscription that progress has not so far been made, and thishas been due, as I am sure your Excellency appreciates, partly to the necessityfor dealing first with the larger tand more urgent question of Allied merchant seamen, and partly to certain very real difficulties of law and policy, whichthe particular problem of military conscription presents for His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.3. The question of military conscription has, however, been under constantconsideration between the various Departments, as a result of which certain conclusions have been reached which I am instructed to communicate to yourExcellency with the request that they may be laid before theGovernment and that the Foreign Office may receive as soon as possible any comments which the Government may wish to offer before any final decision is taken as to the form of the legislation to be submitted on thissubject to Parliament.4. The present position, as I understand it, is that the Allied Governmentsestablished since last year in the United Kingdom have been engaged, since their arrival, in calling up their nationals of military age under their own lawfor service with their respective national Forces as reconstituted in this country.It is assumed that calling-up notices have by now been served upon the greaterpart of the available Allied manpower in this country, and that, in most cases,the persons concerned have responded voluntarily in accordance with the obliga-tions laid upon them by their own national law, except in so far as they have been reserved from military service in view of the greater importance of their services in civilian war worh  The Government will no doubt have noticedwith satisfaction that -a recent judgment delivered by the Lord Chief Justice ina Divisional Court of the High Court of Justice has recognised the right ofan Allied Government to call up its citizens in the United Kingdom under itsown law, and established that Allied citizens who respond to this call-up andenlist in the Allied forces are subject to the provisions of the Allied Forces Actafter joining their units. This judgment, against which an appeal has beenentei&quot;ed, does not, and cannot, of course, authorise the enforcement, either under
United Kingdom or Allied Law, of Allied conscription on Allied citizens whorefuse voluntarily to report to the Allied military authorities, as the compulsionof such persons to comply with their calling-up notices and to report for medical examination or enlistment can only be exercised by the intermediary of the courts and police authorities of the United Kingdom, who cannot take the necessary action without the authority of specific legislation by Parliament.5. The Service Departments of His Majesty&apos;s Government have,&apos;however,been guided by the principle that Allied nationals should, as a general rule, serve in their own Allied forces&apos;, and they have refused to accept Allied citizens forthe British forces, except in certain very special cases. Moreover, the HomeOffice have co-operated by withholding the grant to Allied citizens of military age of exit permits to leave this country, unless the Allied Government concerned had previously released them from their military obligations.6. , Compulsory powers to enforce conscription upon Allied nationals aretherefore only required in respect of a minority whose total number, making due allowance for those in reserved civilian occupations, appears from availablestatistics to be very small. Indeed, the residuary figure for all the Allies isthought to be not more than 5,000 in the aggregate. The experience of the past year has, however, shown that this minority is composed to a considerable extentof persons who are unwilling to serve with their national forces on the groundthat, by reason of long residence in this country, they have lost touch with theircountry of origin, and have a strong preference for serving in the British forces,or for some other reason. After careful consideration of all aspects of theproblem, His Majesty&apos;s Government have arrived at the conclusion that Parlia-ment and public opinion in this country would not accept a proposal to put such persons automatically under the authority of a Government established in thiscountry, and would insist upon some special arrangements being made for theseminority cases.7. His Majesty&apos;s Government consider that in the circumstances effect can best be given to the general principle that Allied nationals should have the sameobligations for military service as British subjects by providing that Alliedcitizens who do not join their own Allied forces shall become liable to the NationalService Acts of the United Kingdom, which would be amended for the purpose.The question then becomes one of the machinery to decide whether a givenindividual is to join his own Allied forces or the British forces. This could bedone in one of two ways, either by setting up a special tribunal with authorityto examine individual cases and to grant in certain circumstances an option tojoin the British forces, or by conceding a free right of option between the allied or British forces in each individual case.8. His Majesty&apos;s Government feel sure that the Allied Governments will agree that the procedure of a special tribunal would be open to a number of grave objections. Such a tribunal would, in accordance with the traditions ofthis country, have to sit in public, and applicants would have to be allowed tostate their case fully. Political considerations and arguments would certainly be ventilated during the proceedings and would obtain wide publicity.Unfortunate and misleading impressions in regard not only to the Allied armed forces but also to Allied political affairs might well be created. Moreover, thequestions which would have to be considered by such a tribunal in conjunctionwith all the possible difficulties of evidence and procedure, which might arise orin certain cases be deliberately fostered, would clearly lead in many instances togreat delay and embarrassment being caused before a final decision was definitelyreached.9. If, on the other hand, a free option between the Allied and British forces were conceded to all the persons concerned, the difficulties connected with the.establishment and operation of the tribunal would disappear, while the principleof equal obligations for military service would be no less maintained. I would emphasise that His Majesty&apos;s Government do not suggest that the free optionshould have retrospective effect, and it would be made absolutely.clear that it didnot in anyway apply to existing; members; of. the Allied armed forces or to personssubsequently joining the Allied forces of their own&apos;free will. Moreover, in orderto avoid as far as possible the risk of options for the British forces oh frivolous
grounds, it is proposed that Allied nationals electing to place themselves underthe British National Service Acts should be admitted only to the British pioneer corps, unless they possessed special experience or qualifications which made themparticularly suitable for the Royal Air Force.10.   I would therefore express the hope that the Governmentwill be prepared to accept a scheme whereby Allied nationals within the age limit of United Kingdom military conscription (18 to 41), who are not alreadyserving in the Allied or British forces, will be made liable by an Act of Parliamentto compulsory military service, to be performed on choice either in the Allied or british forces. His Majesty&apos;s Government regret that the solution of this problem which they propose is not in strict accordance with the general promisegiven to the Allied Governments last year. But, as already explained, they are convinced by the experience they have gained since then that it would not bein the Allied any more than the British interest that recalcitrants should beallowed to state publicly the reasons why they do not wish to join their national forces, and that it would be greatly preferable not to attempt to force such persons to serve against their will in their national forces. It is not believed that allied nationals would prefer to join the British Pioneer Corps instead of their national forces unless they had very strong reasons for the choice. If so, it would notappear to be to the advantage of the Allied forces not to take in the men.11. I should be grateful if your Excellency would submit to your Governmentthe new proposal outlined in the present note and would be so good as to informme of their attitude.

</content>
</cab>
