<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/173/0 images: 369-414</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Reportof the Departmental Representatives on the Conferences as to the Valuation of Railway Undertakings,
CONTENTS.Introductory - - - ... -Scope of Inquiry     - - r,- - 1 1 &apos;Valuation of Railways in cumulo    - - &quot; ..Scope of Valuation w cwmwfo , . , ...        - - .-       . - .. ,Definition of Railway Undertaking for. purpose of Valuation ;      -   -     -Principle of Valuation - - - - ...   uv -Abandonment of &quot; Statutable &quot;Deductions and &quot; Gross Values &quot; in England and Wales-(a) Maintenance -(b) Rates - - . .-Application of the Profits&apos; Principle and definition of net receipts -Methods of determining &apos;&quot;&apos; Tenanfs Share &quot; - &apos;       -Special problem of the Anglo-Scottish Railways    - -Apportionment between Rating Areas in England and WalesProposed Central Valuation Authority for England and WalesProposed &quot; Joint Valuation Authority &quot; for the Anglo-Scottish Railways -Appellate Tribunals - ......Powers of the Valuation Authorities - - -Revision of Valuations        ........Summary of Recommendations      -      . - -  .      -Addendum   - - - - - -PAGE3- 3 4. 4 666 71 I71012 12 13 14 14 14 15 16APPENDICES.Appendix.I.I. I. I.I. I. I. I.(i)-(ii).(iii). (iy). (v).(vi). (via), (vii). (viii).I. (ix). I. (x). II. III.IV.V.Rating and Valuation Bill: Conference with representatives of Railway,Companies, conference with representatives of the County Councils&apos; Association, the Association of Municipal Corporations, and the National Conference of Assessment Committees       - - -Second Conference of representatives as in I. (ii)        - - - -Second Conference of representatives as in I. (i)Conference between representatives of the Government Departments con-cerned, Scottish County, Burgh and Parish Rating Authorities Third Conference of representatives as in I. (ii) - - -        -Third Conference Supplementary Note        -Third Conference with representatives as in I. (i)       -Conference between representatives of the English and Scottish Local Authorities, the Railway Companies and the Government Departments concerned     - - - - - - -Second Conference of representatives as in I. (viii)     -Third    - - - - - - -Comments and Suggestions of the Railway CompaniesDefinition of &quot; Railway Undertaking &quot; suggested by the Assessors of Railwaysand Canals (Scotland)      -Comparison between &quot; Tenanfs Share &quot; in England and Wales and &quot; TenantsAllowances &quot; in Scotland - -Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Act, 1854, Sec. 26  -PAGE 1720 242527 31 33 3335 38 39 424344 46
To the Minister of&apos;Health, the Secretary eor Scotland,and the Minister oe Transport.SirsWe were appointed on the 13th June, 1923, for the purpose of holding a series of conferences with representatives of the Local Authorities on the one side and of the Railway Companies on the other, and were directed, after hearing what the two sides had to say, to report as to the provisions for dealing with the Valuation of Railway Undertakings, which were required to complete the Draft Rating and Valuation Bill.It was hoped that this procedure would be most likely to elucidate the many technical problems for which, solutions had to be found and also to lead to the greatest measure of agreement as to the lines upon which the new clauses should be drafted.2. Representatives of the following Associations and Authorities attended our conferences :     -     -English Local Authorities.  ....   - :County Councils Association. Association of Municipal Corporations.National Conference of Assessment Committees (England and Wales).Scottish Local Authorities. - ... -   .  .The Association of County Councils.       .... The Convention of Royal Burghs. Parish Councils.Representatives of certain of the larger Burghs also attended the meeting in Edinburgh referred to in the next paragraph.Railway Companies.&apos;The Railway Companies&apos; Association.In addition, Mr. J. A. King, Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland), attended the conferences when matters affecting Scotland were under consideration, and placed his wide experience and knowledge freely at our disposal.3. We held ten meetings as follows : three with the representatives of the English Local Authorities at the Ministry of Health;one with the representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities in Edinburgh;three with the representatives of the railway companies at the Ministry of Transport; andthree with the representatives of the English and Scottish Local Authori-ties and of the railway companies jointly at the Ministry of Health.Copies of the agreed Notes of the proceedings at these meetings are annexed (Appendix I).In addition we attended a meeting of a sub-committee representative of the English and Scottish Local Authorities and of the railway companies, which had been appointed for a purpose to which reference is made later.While we were anxious to push on rapidly with our inquiry, we found it essential to allow ample time for discussion between the parties concerned, and our last conference was held on the 4th of December last. .&apos;4. Scope of Inquiry.--attained giving preliminary consideration to the Draft bating and Valuation Bill and to the Memorandum issued by the Ministry of Health m September, 1923, we came to the conclusion that we could not do better than adopt paragraph 5 (i) of the Introduction to that Memorandum as the basis of our inquiry. Paragraph runs as follows :-(i) Provision is made in the draft Bill for the valuation by a Central Valuation Authority of railway and certain other undertakings as a whole and the apportionment of the total rateable value to the parishes concerned.*   (2)23720   Pk 320   150   3/25   E &amp; S A 2
There are, however, in the case of railways, certain considerations whin] make it specially desirable to deal by specific statutory enactment with various points of principle, such as (for example) the definition of a raihva undertaking for purposes of valuation, the application of the profits principle, the method of determining the value of the tenants share the manner in which maintenance charges are to be dealt with, and the formula for apportioning the total rateable value of the undertaking among the parishes concerned.In particular the formation of the two Anglo-Scottish railway groups necessitates some provision for the valuation of their undertakings by a joint authority and the apportionment of values between the two countries-and for this purpose it is necessary, in view of the divergence of English and Scottish Law and practice in regard to railway assessments, to provide a common statutory basis for the guidance of those who will be responsible for making the valuations and for dealing with appeals in regard to them.On these matters conferences are being arranged between representatives of the Government Departments concerned and of the railway companies and local authorities, and pending the result of these discussions it has not been possible to insert specific provisions in the draft Bill.As a Committee on the Valuation for Rating of Amalgamated Railways situated partly in England and Wales and partly in Scotland, of which we were members, had reported on the 10th of November, 1922, it was unnecessary for us to go over the ground covered by that Committee ,or by the many authoritative bodies which had previously reported upon the valuation of railways for rating purposes, except in so far as it was essential for our present purpose.5. Valuation of Railways in cumulo. This Committee stated in their Report (paragraph 15) that We think an essential preliminary to any permanent solution of the difficulty which will arise when the Scottish railways are amalgamated with English railways is that the principle of valuing railways in cumulo which has been in force in Scotland since 1855, should be adopted in England and Wales and thus made applicable to the two amalgamated railways which will extend into both countries.   We are, therefore, strongly of opinion that this step, should be taken with the least possible delay; and in the succeeding paragraph they point out that the adoption of this principle, i.e., the valuation of railways as a whole and the apportionment of the total rateable value to the local rating areas concerned, had been recommended by various Royal Commissions and other bodies which had considered the subject.It is embodied in the Draft Bill so far as concerns England and Wales, and we are now in a position to report that it is unanimously accepted by the representatives of the English and Scottish local authorities and of the railway companies.6. Scope of Valuation in cumulo.-At the outset of our conferences with the various parties concerned, considerable differences of opinion emerged as to the railway-owned properties or subjects to be covered by the railway valuations m cumulo. On the one hand, the National Conference of Assessment Committees (England and Wales) desired that the following properties should be excluded:(i) Docks, harbours and wharves, (ii) Canals. , (iii) Hotels and refreshment rooms.(iv) All road services, including services for the collection and delivery of railway traffic.(v) Electricity, gas and water works.(vi) Construction Avorkshops, as distinct from repair shops.(vii) Properties let out and capable of separate assessment.On the other hand, the railway companies themselves submitted confidential proposals (annexed as Appendix II) which, if adopted, would bring into tn valuation in cumulo all hereditaments used or occupied by a railway company, other than house or cottage property, and lands and premises let to tenants wfl pay rates thereon direct to&quot;local authorities, and included even steamboat service , though the Southern Railway in this single particular dissented.We were from the first ourselves impressed by the advantages of adopting most comprehensive definition,which the parties could be induced to accept,  bi
a definition appeared to us, first,, to be fully in harmony with the principle of a valuation in cumulo based on the profits principle, and, secondly, to avoid the difficulties attendant upon all attempts to isolate the profits of particular parts of a railway undertaking. Finding that the railway companies themselves desired the most comprehensive definition possible, we suggested tentatively as a point for considera-tion whether the valuation in cumulo might be taken further and made to embrace all the receipts of a railway company, including general interest, &amp;c, and on the other side such items, for example, as chief rents. The definition of the receipts which would form the basis of valuation might on these lines have been brought into correspondence with the net revenue which is to form the basis of rates and charges under the Railways Act, 1921, and which is in effect the amount available from0the operations of the undertaking for distribution among its stock-holders and for general reserves and other special purposes. In support of an extended definition of this kind it could be urged, apart from its avoidance of practical difficulties, that all railway profits are earned under statutory concession, that the railway undertaking is worked as one, and that Parliament, in giving a railway company the power to carry on ancillary businesses, does so only because such powers make the undertaking a more efficient railway.The proposal, however, did not commend itself to the railway companies, and we found it necessary to examine in detail, in conjunction with the various representatives, the arguments for including or excluding each class of subject.After considerable discussion, it has now been agreed by all parties to the Conference that the definition of a railway undertaking for the purposes of a valuation in cumulo should not include -(i) Hotels.(ii) Licensed refreshment rooms.(iii) Hereditaments (heritages) specifically let by the companies and in the occupation of other persons and capable of separate assessment.The original proposal put forward by a majority of the railway companies for the inclusion of steamboat services has been dropped, while the National Conference of Assessment Committees and the other bodies representative of the local authorities have agreed to the inclusion of road services, electricity, gas and water works and construction shops.The Committee, which reported on the 10th of November, 1922, recommended that railway-owned canals should be excluded from the valuations in cumulo, but, after giving further consideration to the matter, we recommend their inclusion. The County Councils Association (England) favour their inclusion, and although the representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees and the Association of Municipal Corporations remained of opinion that canals should be treated separately, the latter recognised that the point is of no great importance, and agreed to waive their objection to inclusion. The representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities also recognised that the reason which had impelled them to ask for exclusion, being connected with apportionment to local Rating Authorities, could be otherwise dealt with and withdrew their request for exclusion.The railway companies hold that the canals should be included as part of the undertaking to be valued in cumulo, but, recognising that it would hardly make any appreciable difference in any of the valuations, would have been prepared to accept exclusion had all the local authorities pressed the point strongly.With regard to. railway-owned Docks and Harbours, the opinions of the local authorities are divided. The Scottish Local Authorities are unanimous in pressing for their inclusion in continuance of the practice which has obtained in Scotland for many years, certainly since 1854, and the County Councils Association (England) agree to their inclusion. On the other hand, the National Conference of Assessment Committees and the Association of Municipal Corporations are opposed to their inclusion.The railway companies attach the utmost importance to the inclusion of docks and harbours and to the principle that, in the valuation of railway undertakings, the values of the parts should not exceed the values of the whole. They fear that, if docks and harbours, which they urge form an integral part of the railway undertaking, are excluded from the valuation of the undertaking as a whole, this principle would, m practice, be departed from. They have also stressed the practical difficulty which would be experienced in making a physical division between the docks and the railways proper.
While we do not think that undue weight should be attached to the last mentioned argument by the railway companies, especially inasmuch as some such division as that to which they refer must be made when the docks are valued as they must be, for the purpose of apportionment to the local rating areas in which they are&apos; situated, lwe consider and recommend that railway-owned docks, harbours and wharves should be Included in the undertaking to be valued in cumulo.It is worthy of note that the decision to include or to exclude an ancillary service in the definition of &quot; railway undertaking &quot; will not affect one way or other the value which will attach to a dock, works,-hotel or other entity situate in any particular rating area. But inclusion may tend to increase or reduce the values attaching to the running line of the railway company according as the ancillary service does or does not bring in profit sufficient to support the valuation attached to it in the valuation list or listsin which it appears.Moreover, the greater the number of classes of railway-owned properties which are included in the valuations in cumulo, the greater the degree of simplification which will be attained by minimising the practical difficulties attendant upon making a division of overhead charges. This is a matter of special importance in the case of workshops for the construction and repair of rolling stock, &amp;c.7. Definition of Railway Undertaking for purpose of Valuation. It will be necessary to include in the Bill a definition of &quot; railway undertaking &quot; and, as the Committee of 1922 pointed out, this definition must be uniform for the two countries, as it will otherwise be impossible to apportion the receipts of the two Anglo-Scottish Railways. The form which such definition should take is, we consider, a matter for the Parliamentary draughtsmen. A detailed definition has been submitted by the Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland), and is set out in Appendix III to this Report. In his suggested definition an attempt is made to specify in detail all the properties or subjects to be included in the valuation in cumulo, but we think that such an attempt may be dangerous and that the matter would be better dealt with by drafting an inclusive definition in general terms which would specify in particular only those properties or subjects which are to be definitely excluded from the valuations in cumulo.The exclusion from the valuation in cumulo of advertising hoardings and spaces which are let out will apparently involve an amendment of the Advertising Stations (Plating) Act, 1889, which makes the railway company rateable and not the person to whom the space or hoarding is let. In Scotland such hoardings and spaces are valued as part of the railway undertaking and the Railway Assessor sees practical difficulties in excluding them. The English Local Authorities attach great importance to the separate valuation of these hereditaments, and we think that uniformity must prevail, though power could be reserved to enable them to be valued in Scotland as part of the railway undertaking, among the other adjustments which will in any case be necessary.8. Principle of Valuation. After prolonged discussion, it was agreed by all parties to the Conference, that the. profits principle, which has been applied to the valuation of railways both in England (for the past 80 years or more) and in Scotland (certainly since 1855), holds the field, though the National Conference of Assessment Committees have not waived their view that other methods might legitimately he employed in determining the aggregate value of a railway company.It was generally recognised that, in the absence of express direction, the Courts would continue to apply it, and no alternative was proposed as a basis for statutory direction.- 9. Abandonment of &quot; Staiutable&quot; Deductions and &quot; Gross Values &quot; in England and Wales :Maintenance. It has been generally agreed by the parties to the Conferences that deductions to be allowed in respect of maintenance should be based on the actual expenditure properly charged to revenue under that head together with sums properly set aside to meet future renewals and depreciation. ,  ,In the past, it has been the practice in England and Wales, under the bead o maintenance deductions, to allow, in addition to actual expenditure chargec revenue,  provisions  which  were  considered   to   be  necessary  even al*&apos;.u^100 corresponding sums were not in fact set aside as reserves.   The representative the London Underground Companies ask that this practice should be cpntmu^ but we consider that, if these deductions are based upon actual expenditure (: provisions properly made, there is no justification for any further allowance.
220In Scotland it has been the practice to&apos; deduct the actual expenditure on maintenance including sums expended from reserves. The adoption of the suggested basis would, therefore, result, so far as Scotland is. concerned, in sums reserved for maintenance being allowed to rank currently as deductions for this purpose instead of being held over until they are actually expended.Bates. It has also been agreed by all the parties, except the National Conference of Assessment Committees, that the aggregate rates actually paid by the railway companies from year to year should be treated as a &quot; working expense &quot; of the &quot; railway undertaking &quot; and be deducted before arriving at net receipts. There will then be no further need for the parochial deduction of rate payments.If the arrangements in the two foregoing paragraphs are adopted,- no &quot; statutable &quot; deductions would fall to be made in England or Wales, and the valuations would be directed to the determination of &quot;net annual values.&quot; Ithas been agreed by all parties that the determination of gross values in England and Wales serves no useful purpose in connection with railway valuations in cumulo.10. Application of the Profits Principle and Definition of Net Receipts. We recommend that statutory direction should be given to the effect that the estimate of the rent which a tenant might reasonably be expected to. pay, taking one year with another, should be based upon a percentage or proportion of defined receipts of the railway company, after deduction of the expenses of management, working and maintenance. The receipts to be included are all those arising from the railway and other businesses carried on by the company other than the excluded items of hotels and licensed refreshment rooms and steamboat services.11. Method of determining &quot;Tenants Share.&apos;&quot; Having ascertained the &quot;net receipts&quot; of the &quot;undertaking,&quot; it then becomes necessary, in pursuance of the &quot;profits principle,&quot; to apportion to the hypothetical tenant a share of such &quot;net receipts,&quot; the balance representing the landlords share or the annual rent.The ascertainment of the tenants share in&apos; the case of parochial valuations in England and Wales involved a detailed valuation of the tenants capital, i.e., the rolling stock and other tenants chattels, and the determination Of percentage allowances thereon to cover interest, profits, risks, &amp;c. In addition to the labour and expense to the rating authorities and the railway companies which this complicated process involved, the determination of the tenants share proved a fruitful source of dispute1 arid litigation. Moreover, as&apos; in England and Wales the valuation of the tenants capital is based upon current values, the application of the existing method of determining the tenants share would, in view of the substantial increase in present values of rolling stock and other tenants chattels, result in greatly diminished values, and in some cases would probably bring out a deduction as great as the whole, thus leading to the conclusion that the railway hereditaments had no rental value. 1In Scotland the judicial decisions have given a different basis1 for determining the tenants share to be deducted in arriving at the valuation in cumulo. It takes account of the cost *and not of the current value of the tenants plant, and the&apos; percentages allowed are^ materially different.It, therefore, became necessary to consider whether it was feasible to get rid of, at any rate, some of the complexities inherent in the existing method of dealing with tenants share,&quot; and, in particular,, whether any scheme could be evolved which would avoid determination of the tenants capital and the percentages to be allowed thereon.       p-: - -    --With this object in view the Conferences were largely devoted to the consider-ation of the ways in which this end could be attained. The first suggestion propounded by us was that the tenants share of the &quot; net receipts&quot; might be ascertained on the basis of a fixed percentage of the &quot;net receipts&quot; as defined, such percentage being deduced from the experience of the past.All parties were agreed at the outset that there would be great advantage m adopting a proportion of the &quot; net receipts &quot; as the rental value of the undertaking, provided a satisfactory plan could be devised for determining what this proportion should be. ..   ..; . . - -It was recognised that the great work of listing and valuing the tenants plant,&amp;e. (or of taking out its. prime cost),.would be avoided, that dispute and litigation in regard to the, true amount and the -percentages to be allowed thereon would also avoided, and, last but not least, that, the operative-valuations&apos;would no longer&apos;    &apos; - 1&apos;i- mill&apos;&apos; 111 j i.   11&quot; i iiic&apos; pGrcGiitict^jc exposed to the risks of.violent fluctuation which, are inherent in- a system whichA i
leaves them dependent upon the difference which emerges when two calculi1 f of entirely different order are compared. &quot; c    . &quot; 10nsTo aid the parties in the consideration and discussion of this suggestion tl railway companies furnished particulars of the valuations in. operation on the 1st f April, 1914, throughout the whole of their systems in England and Wales. simila figures were furnished by the Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland) in respect of the Scottish railways. On the basis of these figures a statement was prepared by the Ministry of Transport showing, in respect of the four amalgamated railway companies, the relation between the tenants share and the net receipts for the year 1913. In the case of the two Anglo-Scottish railways, separate figures were shown for the English and Scottish portions respectively. A copy of this statement is annexed (Appendix IV), but it may be convenient to summarise the results as follows&quot; Tenants share &quot; of the four amalgamated railway companies as at 1st April 1914, expressed as a percentage of the &quot; net receipts &quot; for the year 1913_      &apos; jEngland and Wales. per cent.Southern        -      -      -      -     -      -      -      -      - 54-97Great Western -      -      -      -      -      -      -      -      - 54-16London, Midland and Scottish (former English companiesonly)    -      -              -      -      -      --      -- 60-26London and North Eastern (former English companies only) 57 - 64Average for the four groups     -      -      -      -      -      - 57 - 62iScotland.London Midland and Scottish (former Scottish companiesonly).......... 77.66London and North Eastern (former Scottish companies only) 75 - 43Average for the two groups    -      -      -      -      -      - 76 - 66In the Report of the Committee the percentage of &quot;tenants allowances&quot; for Scotland is given as 70 per cent.; and a word of explanation as to the apparent discrepancy between this and the figures which appear above is, perhaps, desirable. A reference to Appendix II of the Report, in which a comparison is made between the systems of valuation followed in England and Scotland, will show that the deductions made from gross receipts to arrive at the respective valuations are relatively less in Scotland than in England. Eor example, the whole cost of the maintenance and renewal of permanent way is deducted in England, whereas only half of such cost is deducted in Scotland; and only about 58 per cent, of the local rates (the occupiets share) is deducted in Scotland as compared with the total rates in England, where the whole is paid by the occupier. The net receipts therefore arrived at by the assessor for valuation purposes are greater than the &quot; net receipts,&quot; and the percentage of tenants share to the former will be less than to the latter. The figures given above and in the statement (Appendix IV) (subject to all necessary reserves as to their accuracy) afford a fair comparison of the actual position in england and Scotland respectively, without regard to the adjustments which would be necessary to give practical effect to the existing differences in the valuation and rating laws of the two countries.After the suggestion as to a fixed percentage had been discussed in full conference, first with representatives of the local authorities and of the railway companies separately, and later with the parties jointly, it became evident that there was no possibility of agreement unless a small number of persons representative of both sides could be got together for the purpose of negotiating terms for submission to the full conference. A sub-committee was appointed for this purpose by the local authorities and the railway companies. It was considered desirable that the departments should not be represented on this sub-committee, but at the^ request of both parties the Departmental representatives attended the last meeting with a view to seeing whether they could help the parties to reach a settlement. after holding several meetings, the sub-committee reported to the full Conference on the 4th December, 1924, that they had not been able to agree on a percentage of &apos; net receipts &quot; to represent the tenants share.We have taken note of the arguments advanced in these discussions(i) By the railway delegates in support of the contention that the proportions which have ruled in the past in England and Wales would nov give too small a share to the tenant;(ii) By the local authorities&apos; delegates to the contrary effect.
221They may be stated shortly as follows v 1. The Hallway Case.(a) That a marked advance in the value of the tenants plant should be reflected in the assessment of the tenants share.(6) That the landlords share should not be affected by an advance in value or in cost to anything like the same extent as the tenants share, if at all, because the hereditaments owned by him are of a more permanent nature.(c) That any argument based upon comparison of the return obtained by the landlord on his capital with the return obtained by the tenant on his must be deceptive, because a large amount of landlords outlay is now dead.(d) That any argument based upon comparison with the valuation of the hereditaments which would be arrived at if the &quot; contractors principle&quot; (which is based upon percentage of capital value) were adopted is false, because it is not the cost or value of a hereditament but the demand for it which governs the rent which a landlord can obtain.(e) That the conditions as regards competition and other matters which now affect the operation of railway concessions are very different from those which obtained at earlier times, and that they must all be taken into account in assessing the value of railway hereditaments.(/) That in considering any argument based upon the recent advances in the valuations of other industrial hereditaments it must not be forgotten that the railway companies&apos; charges are subject to statutory limitations, and that they have to undertake great liabilities in connection with their concessions.(gr) That the railways were not undervalued in 1914, and that, notwith-standing the Railways Act, 1921, their net receipts had declined. 2. The Local Authorities&apos;&apos; Case.(a) That tenants share should not be determined in relation to the present value of a tenants plant, &amp;c, and that original cost is a sounder basis if tenants capital is to be the foundation.(b) That, as cost of replacement is entirely borne by the account from which the net receipts are derived, there is no reason why tenants capital should in any case be increased beyond cost.(c) That any division as between landlord and tenant which has regard solely to tenants capital and the percentages to be allowed thereon for interest, profit, &amp;c, is unsound, because it casts all fluctuation in the fortunes of the undertaking upon the landlord, treating the tenant as a secured and preferential partner. Thus Scottish law and practice makes value for rating purposes depend upon the difference between a continuously advancing tenants share and a net receipt, which has fluctuated in the past but in future is to be more or less stabilised, while English law and practice leave rating values dependent on the extremely fluctuating factor of current values.(d) That in making a hypothetical division of this kind, regard should be had to the return to which the landlord is entitled, as well as to the return to which the tenant is entitled.(c) That valuation on the system which is chiefly applied to other industrial hereditaments (viz., the contractors principle) would give con-siderably higher results, and that during the last ten years there has been a considerable increase in the rateable value of industrial hereditaments whereas railway values have decreased.(/) That when regard is taken of the ratios between rateable values and net receipts which have ruled in the past, as is done in the table above, it is necessary, as regards England and Wales, to take account of the fact that the net receipts there brought into the comparison are those of the most profitable of all years (1913), and that the rateable values brought in are founded upon the net receipts of a variety of years spread over at least two decades, and that comparison based upon an up-to-date application of the existing principles made in 1914 would have shown upon the estimation of the local authorities, a tenants share substantially lower than that shown m the return.tl -t^?1^6 We ^Q no* ^nc^ *n any 0^ *nese arguments any ground for contending ia  the profits principle is inappropriate for railway valuation, or that it isz  23726
opposed to the basic principle of all valuations for rating purposes, namely th determination of the rent at which the hereditaments may reasonably be expected to let, taking one year with another, the contentions put forward on behalf of the local authorities, coupled with the recognition by the railway companies that a strict application of past practice and percentages in regard to the determination of tenants share would in some cases produce absurd results (though they think that the Courts might be relied upon to, apply,that, practice so as to produce equitable results), appear to us to lead conclusively to the view that some new. and equitable plan should be found, for dividing net receipts. ast between landlord and tenant, and this view has in fact,,been apcepted by both the railway companies..and, thelocal authorities;, ,. ,t      , ,,     , &quot; .    ,.,      .       , ,,,    .., . ,. ,    ,  ,The present unsatisfactory position is, not,, we think, to be, remedied by the abandonment of the.basic principles which have received, the repeated sanction oi the Courts.during the past 80 years ox. more, but by, a fresh, consideration of the methods of. applying these principles in the, light pf, existing circumstances.The ideal solution which (would, have,, included,, the. statutory enactment of an agreed proportion is net available,. The. statutory enactment of a proportion or proportions which, haye not been,.agreed by the interested parties is a solution to which we should, perhaps refer.. It would free both sides from the incubus of costly litigation on this important matter, and it would leave the result in no uncertainty. The difficulties and objections to this course are, however, so obvious that we are inclined to assume that it will not.be adopted. In a matter of this importance the figures upon which any percentage could be based would require proof and justification. The equitable considerations to be taken into account are many and varied and difficult to appraise, and there would seem to be much force in the argument urged especially by the railway companies that they are not matters which can appropriately be embodied in a Bill and determined in the ordinary course of Parliamentary procedure.These Conferences have resulted in offering an alternative, which, though it is open to the objection which has been taken by Judges of the High Court on wider grounds to the system of the past, viz., that it leaves them without sufficient guidance in determining the equities of a matter of very great importance, has the great advantage that it is accepted by all the interested parties.All parties are agreed as to the purport of the Clause which should direct this important step in the process of determining the rent which the hypothetical tenant would pay, namely : (1) That some proportion or percentage of net receipts (as defined) shall be taken to represent this rental value, and(2) That definite direction shall be given that in this matter neither the Assessing Authorities nor the Appellate Tribunals shall be bound by any practice or decisions of the past or that other words best calculated to give a fresh start and a free hand to determine an equitable division of net receipts as between landlord and tenant should be used.We have been advised by the present Lord Advocate and by the Legal Adviser of the Ministry of Health that it would be possible to draw a direction on these lines which might reasonably be expected to be effective in freeing those charged with the task from the trammels of the past.The parties made it clear that they desired to be left free to use any arguments which bear upon this equitable division.12. The Special Problem of the Anglo-Scottish Railways. We turn now to the problem which arises from the amalgamation of English with Scottish railways.It will be seen from the report of the Committee which dealt with this question in. 1922 that they were satisfied that it would not be practicable to remove the valuation difficulty arising from the decision of Parliament to adopt a longitudinal grouping of the railway^s by requiring separate accounts to be kept for the Scottish portions of the two Amalgamated Railway Systems.The Committee, while making certain suggestions for bridging the gap until Parliament could give effect to the valuation reforms which are needed to secure a lasting and satisfactory solution to the problem, came to the conclusion that any temporary arrangements such as they&apos;recommended could not properly be extender, for any prolonged period and that reform of the valuation of railways had become urgent. They recommended that legislation on the lines indicated in their should be introduced at the earliest possible date, ,
moo L 6 (0On the assumption that the apportionment between the two countries would h applied to an intermediate figure arrived at after deducting the tenants share f om Net Receipts,&quot; the Committee expressed the opinion that a division based non a combination of ton-miles and passenger-miles would give the most equitable Uesu&apos;ts. Before such a formula could be applied, however, it would be necessary to determine the weight to be given to each of the two factors, and the Committee suggested that this question and the general working out of the formula were matters to be settled after examination by experts.In the discussions between representatives of the English and Scottish local authorities, it appears to have been generally agreed that the division should take place at the earliest stage, namely, net receipts. Two other bases of apportionment between the two countries were suggested, and as these, upon examination, appeared likely to offer satisfactory solutions to this particular problem, we have not thought it necessary to pursue the suggestion of the Committee to a conclusion.The two alternative bases of apportionment, both of which have been suggested by the Scottish representatives, were primarily designed for a division of &quot;Net Receipts&quot; and are as follows&apos;:- ,(1) That the first division of &quot; Net Receipts &quot; between the two countries should be based upon the ratio in which the interest and dividends upon the capital of the two Anglo-Scottish Amalgamated Companies, as allotted to the proprietors of the former English and Scottish Companies respectively, under the Amalgamation Schemes, accrued to the two interests. This ratio to be varied in succeeding years by allowance on the one side or the other for all capital expenditure upon the development or extension of the heritages in the respective countries.(2) That any division of &quot; Net Receipts &quot; between England and Scotland should be based upon the percentage which the &quot; Net Receipts &quot; of the Scottish Railway Companies (now amalgamated with the Anglo-Scottish Companies) for the years 1913 and 1922 taken together, bore to the aggregate &quot; Net Receipts &quot; of all the railway companies now included in the London Midland and Scottish and the London and North Eastern Companies respectively in those years.It was finally agreed by all parties that, for the purpose of apportioning &quot; Net Receipts,&quot; the ratio between the net receipts of the years 1913 and 1922, taken together, would form an equitable basis for the first five years. A somewhat similar basis had already been suggested by the railway companies.We are satisfied that this basis would secure a fair and equitable division of the &quot; Net Receipts &quot; between the two countries provided that any physical addition to the rateable hereditaments (or heritages) in either country since 1922 is taken into account by the Valuation Authority in making the original apportionment. In determining the shares of each country, regard should be had to the fact that the railways of the Scottish Companies extended into England.It would appear necessary that after the period of five years or such other interval as may elapse between successive valuations any representative body of local authorities which may obtain a certificate from the Minister of Health or Secretary for Scotland, as the case may be, that it is a proper body for the purpose oi the railway company concerned should be entitled to make application to the Joint valuation Authority (hereafter referred to) for a revision of, the basis of apportionment: and that upon such application being made, or if the Valuation Authority itself is of opinion that such a step is advisable, the authority should reconsider the basis of apportionment and, if it thinks fit, amend the same and submit the amended scheme to the Railway and Canal Commission sitting as a specially constituted Anglo-Scottish Tribunal for confirmation, with or without modification.The agreed proposal, then, is to apportion the net receipts of the two railway groups concerned, as ascertained by some joint authority between the two countries, m the mean ratio of the actual receipts for the two years 1913 and 1922 an easy Solution and a simple formula and then to leave the national valuation authorities o base separate valuations in cumulo upon their respective shares according to . leif own laws and customs, but -and this is important free to make a fresh start m the matter of tenants&apos; share.It will at once be perceived that this involves a separate determination of the uants share in the two countries (though under a common direction), and it may
be asked whether it would not be more logical, equitable and convenient to impose upon the Joint Authority the task of settling that share for the whole railway and of deducting it before apportionment.It may be said that it would be practicable for a Joint Authority, but not for the national authorities, to ascertain the tenants&apos; share by the process of valuing the tenants&apos; capital.It may also be suggested that the Joint Authority ought to carry a valuation in cumulo for the whole railway to the furthest possible point, stopping short only at the special adjustments required to adapt the valuation to national law.To these contentions we think that sufficient answers can be advanced, namely, a theoretical answer, a practical answer and an answer based upon procedure. The answer in logic is that the alternative to an operative valuation in cumulo (which is incapable of attainment unless the valuation law of the two countries is assimilated) is an ascertainment of the profits in each country upon which such valuation can be made, and that a scheme under which part ot the valuation is made by one authority and part by another is itself anomalous. And undoubtedly it is easier to find a satisfactory formula of apportionment if net receipts and not some intermediate valuation is to be divided.Practically it must be recognised that the English Authorities will not willingly agree to a common determination of tenants share since they fear that any equalisation-tion must be effected at their expense in view of the higher proportion of tenanfs share in Scotland which has prevailed in the past. The railway companies would be equally likely to object to equalisation at their expense.Finally, as regards convenience and consistency, it must be remembered that whatever the embarrassments which may arise from the possibility of different decisions by the English and Scottish Courts on points really common in the case of the Anglo-Scottish railways, they would be no greater and might well be less than those likely to arise if the English portion of those railways are dealt with by one authority and one set of courts while the other large English railways are dealt with by another authority (albeit presided over by the same chairman) and another set of courts.The remedy for these difficulties must, we think, be found in providing such opportunities for appeal as will centre in the same judicial body the final interpreta-tion of the fundamental direction upon which each of the national authorities will be proceeding.The actual proportion of tenants share may differ not only between the two portions of an Anglo-Scottish railway, but between the different railways in England (including the English portions of those railways) inter se. If such differences do, in fact, arise, they must be held to reflect some difference in circumstances, but it is obviously essential that the same principles should be applied in determining tenanfs share for each railway or portion of a railway.Further, both the English Local Authorities and the Railway Assessor in Scotland expressly assured us (and the railway companies did not in the end appear to dissent) that they anticipated no difficulty in justifying in their national courts valuations which dealt with the tenants share separately. We are driven, therefore, to say that as regards the Anglo-Scottish railways a valuation of the railway n cumulo cannot be achieved, and for it must be substituted an apportionment of net receipts upon which will be based the valuation in cumulo in each country separately according to the law and practice of that country.13. Apportionment between Bating Areas in England and Wales. It has been agreed by all parties that the Central Valuation Authority for England and Wales should be charged with the duty of propounding for submission to Parliament such scheme of apportionment as would, in their opinion, give the most equitable distribution, and it has been suggested that the authority should be directed to have regard, among other relevant circumstances, to the existing distribution of railway values in preparing such scheme.It has also been agreed that until such a scheme has been propounded by the authority and adopted by Parliament, apportionment in proportion to existing local values should be adopted, subject to adjustments rendered necessary by neiv hereditaments or extensions of existing hereditaments.We recommend that provision should be inserted in the Bill to give effect to this agreement.14. Proposed Central Valuation Authority for England and Wales. The question of the constitution of the Central Valuation Authority has been discussed at soffl&apos;
  d oth with the parties to the conferences, but these discussions revealed difference f Opinion. The railway companies have indicated that they are not greatly 0 cerned as to the constitution of this body provided there is a right of appeal on C0 suggestions of fact as well as of law to an Appellate Tribunal with a subsequent right ^appeal on points of law only to a higher court. They do not claim representation 0-iori the Valuation Authority. The County Councils Association and the Associa-tion of Municipal Corporations are in favour of the authority prescribed by Clause 29 of the draft Bill.This body is termed in the Bill the Central Valuation Authority, but we under-stand that in view of the probable restriction of its functions it may be renamed the Railways Assessment Authority, by which name we hereafter refer to it. Clause 29 provides that the Authority shall consist of a chairman and other members, whose number is not fixed, that the chairman shall be nominated by the Minister of Health, and must be a person who has held judicial office, and that the other members shall be appointed by the Minister of Health on recommendation to be made by the-London County Council.County Councils Association.Association of Municipal Corporations.Metropolitan Boroughs Standing Joint Committee.Urban District Councils Association.Rural District Councils Association.Association of Poor Law Unions.The National Conference of Assessment Committees are not, however, prepared to accept this constitution, and desire that the Central Valuation Authority should be appointed by the existing Assessment Committees.At one of the conferences held with the English Local Authorities only, the following suggestion was made by one of the Departmental representatives : That the Railway Assessment Authority for England and Wales should consist of a chairman, who should be an experienced lawyer, and two members who should be persons experienced in English rating practice.This suggestion has not been accepted by the representatives of the English Local Authorities though it has, perhaps, not received their final consideration.We suggest that in Clause 29 (3) of the draft Bill there should, in any event, be substituted for the words ...&quot; a person who has held judicial office &quot; the words &quot; an experienced lawyer &quot; (c.f., Railways Act, 1921, Section 20).15. Proposed &quot; Joint Valuation Authority &quot; for the Anglo-Scottish Railways.  With regard to the authority to deal with the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways, the representatives of the local authorities, both English and Scottish, are of opinion that it should be possible for the two National Authorities acting jointly to determine the quantum of the &quot; net receipts &quot; of each of the Anglo-Scottish amalgamated companies, and to apportion the same. They agreed, however, that in the event of any disagreement it would be necessary to refer the matter to an arbitrator or &quot; oversman &quot; for decision.It has -been obvious throughout our conference that the local authorities of both countries desire the least possible interference with their existing machinery for valuation which is consistent with the introduction of the cumulo principle in England and Wrales and the special circumstances of the Anglo-Scottish railways. This feeling has led the English authorities to insist upon a representative body as opposed to a technical assessor or assessors and both sides to look with favour upon the plan which most narrowly confines the functions of the inevitable joint authority.The ascertainment of the net receipts of the two groups and the apportionment when ascertained upon a formula which has to be determined are important functions, and we consider it essential that these tasks should be entrusted to an authority oi standing. It would, we suggest, appropriately consist of three persons one an experienced lawyer (who should be the Chairman of the Railway Assessments Authority for England and Wales), one a person who is an expert in English rating practice, and third the Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland). Such a body would be a judicial and not a &quot; bureaucratic &quot; authority.
16. Appellate Tribunals. (1) The draft Bill provides, as regards England and Wales, that appeals on fact as well as on law should go from the Railway Assess-ment Authority to the Railway and Canal Commission, and thence on points of law only to the Court of Appeal.(2) No course has been suggested with regard to joint matters affecting the Anglo-Scottish railways other than that appeals on fact as well as on law should go from the Joint Valuation Authority to the Railway and Canal Commission sitting with an English and a Scottish Judge, and thence direct to the House of Lords on points of law only.These latter arrangements appear to be generally acceptable to the railway companies and to the English and Scottish local authorities, but as we pointed out during our discussions with the parties, the constitution of the Appellate Tribunal or Tribunals is a matter to be settled by the legal authorities. It is one requiring very full consideration, and though, perhaps, it is outside our province to make detailed recommendations the practical success of the agreed solution may turn largely upon the judicial machinery which is established. We have had the advantage of discussing the matter with the present Lord Advocate and his predecessor.Some of the questions to be determined by the Courts will be &quot; domestic &quot; to one or other country and others common to both.Questions of the latter kind are the ascertainment of net receipts, and the determination and application of the formula of apportionment as between England and Scotland. The interpretation of the fundamental direction as to valuation (referred to in paragraph 1) is also a matter of vital &quot; common &quot; concern.17. Powers of the Valuation Authorities to call for and to have access to Accounts, dhc. It has been agreed by the representatives of the local authorities that the Railway Assessment Authority for England and Wales, and the Joint Valuation Authority for the Anglo-Scottish railways, should have statutory powers similar to those conferred upon the Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland) by Section 26 of the Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Act, 1854 (see Appendix 5). The railway com-panies state that they are prepared to give the Valuation Authorities full access to their books, accounts, vouchers, &amp;c, and also to give them such information in regard to the accounts as they may resonably require, but they desire to be protected from unreasonable or vexatious demands for figures or returns, the compilation of which might involve the companies in considerable labour and expense. They have undertaken to examine the section of the Scottish Act to which reference is made above, and to suggest, if necessary, a form of words which would be acceptable to the railway companies.We recommend that the powers of the Scottish Assessor in this respect should be extended to the Valuation Authority for England and Wales and also to the Joint Valuation Authority, leaving the railway companies to suggest such amend-ments to the Clause when drafted as they may desire.18. Revision of Valuations. Clause 33 of the draft Bill provides for quinquennial revision of the valuations of Railways in England and Wales and also empowers the Central Authority, on the application of the Railway Company or of any rating authority or county council concerned, to reconsider the valuations at any time after the expiration of one year from the date when the existing values come into force.All parties to the Conference have agreed to the provisions of the draft Bill in this respect, and they have also agreed that similar provisions as regards the periodicity of the valuations should apply to the Anglo-Scottish railways.We consider, however, that applications from the railway companies or the rating authorities for revision of the valuations before the expiry of the normal period should be made to the valuation authority of the country immediately concerned, who may, if they are satisfied that revision is necessary or desirable, thereupon make application to the Joint Valuation Authority for a fresh determination of &quot; net receipts &quot; and an apportionment of the same.At present, the Scottish Assessor is required by statute to value the railways in Scotland annually, and, if the suggestion made above is adopted, it will be necessary to amend the Scottish Statute law in this respect.
224SUMMARY OF RECOMMENDATIONS.It may be conveBient in conclusion to summarise the recommendations which except as stated in this Report have been agreed at these conferences. At the same time, in view of the importance of many of the issues raised, their inherent difficulty and the differences of view which exist as to their ideal solution, this summary should not be read in isolation from the body of the report.(I) To substitute valuation in cumulo for the present parochial valuations in England and Wales.(2) To provide a definition of the hereditaments to be included in the scope of such valuations which will exclude :  Hotels and Licensed Refreshment Rooms;Hereditaments let out by the companies and capable of separate assessment, and include all other hereditaments used or occupied by a railway company, thus including railway-owned docks, harbours, canals, works, offices, garages, &amp;c.(3) To make this definition extend to Scotland. i      ,(4) To amend, if necessary, the Advertising Stations (Rating) Act, 1889,so as to make advertisement hoardings and spaces to be assessed upon the occupiers.(5) To give statutory direction that the profits principle is to be followed in estimating the rent which a tenant would pay taking one year with another.(6) To define &quot; net receipts &quot; for this purpose.(7) To direct that valuations should be directed to the determination of net value and that instead of deducting estimated average cost of maintenance and local rates at the final stage, the actual expenditure out of revenue account upon maintenance, and rates and the sums properly set aside out of revenue to meet future replacements, should be allowed to rank as deductions in taking out net receipts at the initial stage.(8) To direct assessment authorities in each country to determine the rental value of a railway undertaking by taking some proportion or per-centage of its net receipts as defined. A definite direction should be given to the effect that in this matter neither the assessment authorities nor the appellate tribunals should be bound by any practice or decision of the past, the object being to leave the authorities and tribunals free to determine an equitable division of net receipts as between landlord and tenant, and the parties free to use any arguments which bear upon this equitable division.(9) As regards the two Anglo-Scottish railways, to direct that the net receipts of each railway (as defined) should be apportioned by a joint authority between the two countries.(10) To direct the valuation authority of each country to make a valuation in cumulo of the part of the undertaking situated in its area in accordance with its domestic law and practice upon the basis of such apportioned share.    &apos;* *- &quot; - ;   &apos;f- -(II) To direct that the apportionment of net receipts as between England and Scotland in the cases of the L. M. &amp; S. and L. &amp; N. E. Companies should for a period of&quot; five years be in the ratio of the net receipts of the Scottish companies to the net receipts of the other companies, now included in the group for the years 1913 and 1922 taken together; &apos; -    ;(12) To make provision for revision, of this ratio if required: (13) To expand the&quot; provisions in the Draft Bill for apportionment as between rating areas in England and Wales by directing that pending approval of the proposed scheme apportionment should be in proportion to existing values, subject to such adjustments as are necessary in view of physical alterations.(14) To provide the necessary machinery for assessment and appeal (see suggestion at end of report).(15) To arm the assessing authorities with the necessary powers of access to accounts, &amp;c. .
A few questions of detail, upon some of which it may he thought desirable to include special provisions in the Bill, appear to claim further consideration, e.g. :-The precise definition of &quot; net receipts &quot; for valuation purposes and the treatment of cases (if any) in which no profits are earned.The definition of &quot; land used as a railway &quot; for the purpose of deter-mining to what parts of the properties the rating abatements under Part II of the Second Schedule to the Bill are to apply. The application of the scheme to joint lines.Upon these questions we would propose to confer with experts representing both sides and to submit a further report without any long delay.We desire to express our appreciation of the valuable services rendered by Mr. A. Matheson, D.S.O., who has acted throughout as secretary to our conferences.CYRIL HURCOMB. A. CARSON ROBERTS. WALTER HOGG.A. MATHESON,Secretary.24 January, 1925.ADDENDUM.RAILWAY VALUATION. Assessing Authorities and Appellate Tribunals./. Common Work for Great Britain. (The ascertainment of Net Receipts and the apportionment thereof as between E. &amp; S.).By a Joint Valuation Authority constituted as follows : (1) A Judicial Chairman appointed by the Lord Chancellor after consultation with the Lord President C. of S. Scotland.(2) An Assessor appointed by the English Assessing Authority. j(3) The Scottish Assessor of Railways and Canals.Appeal to lie to a Special Joint Tribunal which, if the Lord Chancellor and Lord President approve, shall be the Railway and Canal Commission with the English and Scottish Judges both sitting.The question has been raised whether the ascertainment of net receipts for all railways in whichever country should be referred to the specially constituted Joint Tribunal as a means of securing uniformity, but such a course is open to the strong objection that it involves for example for purely English companies the opportunity for objection being taken at two separate stages (viz., firstly to the determi-nation of net receipts, and secondly to the valuation derived therefrom) before two distinct tribunals (viz., the Joint Tribunal and the National Court of Appeal).Final appeal to the House of Lords.II. The domestic English and Scottish&apos; Work. For England the C.V.A. of the Draft Bill.The provision perhaps to be supplemented by directions that the chairman together with (say) two members of the body and two expert assessors shall sit to hear and determine objections.Appeal not to the Railway and Canal Commission but to the High Court, or, if the Lord Chancellor so advises, direct to the Court of Appeal and, if need be, to the House of Lords.For Scotland the Assessor of Railways.Appeal, as the Scottish authorities determine and provide in the Scottish clauses, presumably to the Valuation Judges and, if need be, to the House of Lords.
225APPENDIX I (i).RATING AND VALUATION BILL.1 A conference with representatives of the railway companies took place at the Ministry of Transport on Wednesday, 14th November 1923.   The following were present :-Mr. 0. W. Hurcomb       ...   Ministry of Transport (in the chair). Mr! A. Carson Roberts -      -      -   Ministry of Health.Mr. W. Hogg.....Scottish Office.Mr. W. V. Wood    -      -      -      &quot; \.Ministry of Transport. Mr. A. Matheson -JSir Francis Dunnell     -      -      - \London and North Eastern Railway. Mr. A. J. Brickwell      -      -      - JMr. F. W. Showers       -      -      -   Great Western Railway.Mr. P. M. Payne    -      -      -      -   London, Midland and Scottish Railway.Mr. S. E. Hitchcock      - -   Southern Railway.Mr. L. B. Carslake       -      -      -\London Electric Railway, Metropolitan District Rail-Mr. F. C. Buller   -      -      -      - J       way, &amp;c. Mr. F. Dawson       -      .&apos;     .      -   Metropolitan Railway. Mr. A. B. Cane      -      -      -      -   Railway Companies&apos; Association.2. Mr. Hurcomb briefly explained the objects of the conference and the Governments desire to evolve a workable scheme which would equitably give effect to the principles of the proposed reforms and meet with as wide a measure of agreement as possible. He stated that the Ministry of Health and the Scottish Office had jointly asked that the Ministry of Transport should be associated with them in this meeting with the railway companies&apos; representatives to discuss the valuation of railways for rating purposes; that it was proposed subsequently to hold similar meetings with representatives of the local authorities, and then, if necessary, joint meetings with the representatives of the railway companies and the local authorities.3. (1) It was agreed that paragraph 5 (1) of the Ministry of Health Memorandum provided a convenient agenda for the conference and the representatives of the railway companies then handed in a printed memorandum containing their comments and suggestions upon the points raised therein. Certain preliminary points were first discussed.(2) Constitution of Control Valuation Authority. Mr. Hurcomb directed attention to the proposed constitution of the Central Valuation Authority which now provided for a paid chairman who has held judicial office.The railway companies concurred in the desirability of securing a qualified and permanent chairman with legal experience.(3) Appellate Tribunal. Concurrence was also expressed in the provision that appeals against valuations made or decided by the Control Valuation Authority should go to the Railway and Canal Commission and thence, on points of law only, to the Court of Appeal.Mr. Hurcomb mentioned that the proposals of the Draft Bill were still subject to the consideration and approval of the Lord Chancellor. He also stated that it had been suggested that appeals from the decisions of the Joint Authority, which would require to be set up to deal with the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways, should also go to the Railway and Canal Commission sitting with an English and a Scottish judge, but that this question, like that of the Appellate Tribunal in the case of the Central Valuation Authority for England and Wales, required further consideration by the legal authorities.(4) Revision of Valuations. The representatives of the railway companies expressed themselves as satisfied with the provisions of Clause 33 of the Draft Bill, which provides for the quinquennial revision of &quot; special properties &quot; (including railways) and also for reconsideration of values at any time after the expiration of one year from the date when the existing values come into force.4-. Determination of the Valuation in cumulo.-(l) Tenants Share. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the departments were desirous of getting rid, as far as possible, of the complexities inherent in the existing methods of valuing railways and that they desired to aim at a method which would give the greatest possible simplification consistent with the ascertainment of fair valuations. In particular, they would welcome any scheme which would avoid separate determination of tenanfs capital and of the percentages to be allowed thereon. He stated that it had been suggested that the tenanfs share of the profits might be ascertained on the basis of a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net income,&quot; such percentage being deduced from the experience of the past. The representatives of the railway companies agreed to the suggestion of a fixed percentage provided a reasonable percentage could be arrived at. In this connection they drew attention to the increase in the value of tenanfs capital since the war.(2) Maintenance. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that a further simplification might be possible if agreement could be reached on the question of maintenance and he suggested that only those amounts actually charged in the railway companies&apos; accounts in respect of maintenance, i.e., the sums charged to revenue either by way of actual expenditure or provision, should be allowed. The representatives of the railway companies agreed, and pointed out that this was in fact what was intended by paragraph (2)m 0Wn lnemorandum of suggestions.Mr. Buller, however, stated that the Underground railways had been allowed by the rating authorities to deduct from their gross receipts the provisions which were considered to be necessary,iii   23720 c
even although corresponding sums were not in fact set aside as reserves, and he expressed the view that his companies would be entitled to continue this practice in future.Mr. Buller&apos;s reservation on behalf of the Underground Companies was noted.(3) Suggested &quot; short cut &quot; for arriving directly at &quot; Rateable Value.&quot; (i) On the assumption that agreement would be reached with the local authorities; it was suggested that the maximum simplification would be attained if &quot; rateable value &quot; were determined by taking a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net income.&quot; It would not be reasonable to ask either party to take a complete &quot; leap in the dark &quot; and it was therefore further suggested that any such percentage should be based on the experience of the past The representatives of the railway companies agreed in principle to this suggestion on the understanding that the percentage to&apos; be taken would be fair to all parties.They undertook to give further consideration to this suggestion and to ascertain what data are available for arriving at the suggested percentage.(ii) The question was raised whether the same percentage&apos; would be applied to all railways, but the discussion made it clear that this could not be determined until the available data had been examined.(iii) Mr. Hurcomb asked whether the railway companies would prefer that the percentage (or percentages, if it were necessary to fix different percentages for different railways) should be fixed by the Bill, and said that he thought the Scottish Office might attach particular importance to this course if it were at all practicable, a view which Mr. Hogg emphasised. Sir Francis Dunnell replied that the railways also preferred this course. It was pointed out that this would depend on whether the railway companies could furnish sufficient data to enable a fair ascertainment of the percentage (or percentages) to be arrived at before the Bill is presented to Parliament. Failing that, it would be necessary to leave the percentage (or percentages) to be determined by the Central Valuation and/or Joint Valuation authorities, subject to appeal to the Railway and Canal Commission or to confirmation by Parliament.(iv) The representatives of the railway companies, as at present advised, saw no objection to provision being made for a periodical review and, if necessary, alteration of the percentage (or percentages) by the Central and Joint Valuation Authorities, subject to : (a) the right of appeal, or(b) confirmation by Parliament.5. Definition of &quot; Railway Undertaking.&quot; (1) On behalf of the railway companies generally, Sir Francis Dunnell explained that the definition, paragraph (1) in the Railway Companies&apos; Memorandum, was designed to bring all the businesses carried on by a railway company, including steamboats, docks, canals, hotels, and refreshment rooms, into one &quot; cumulo &quot; for valuation purposes. Special points were, however, raised by individual companies. Mr. Hitchcock on behalf of the Southern Group demurred to the inclusion of steamboats, on the ground that such profits had never been rateable and would not be so in the case of other owners of steamships.Mr. Payne stated that he interpreted paragraph (1) of the Memorandum as meaning that all hereditaments used or occupied by a railway company should be valued by the Central Valuation Authority, but not necessarily as one hereditament. The London, Midland and Scottish Company would have no objection to separate valuations of specific properties such as docks, canals, and hotels, provided that in all such cases the valuations were made by the Central Valuation Authority. In particular, he desired that hotels owned and/or run by railway companies should be valued by the Central Authority and not by the Local Rating Authorities. On it being pointed out that the Local Authorities might have strong objections to hotels being valued otherwise than locally, Mr. Payne stated that, in that event, he would probably not press the point.After some discussion it was generally agreed that all railway properties agreed to be rateable, should be valued by the Central Valuation Authority with the exception of properties let out and capable of separate assessment and with the possible further exception of hotels.On the question whether the ancillary businesses and railway working should be brought into one valuation Mr. Carson Roberts stated that considerable opposition on the part of the Local Authorities might be anticipated to the proposal that docks, canals and other ancillary businesses should be included in the railway &quot; cumulo.&quot; The representatives, of the Government undertook to give further and full consideration to the proposal of the railway companies.(2) The representatives of the railway companies agreed that all properties let out and capable of separate assessment, should be excluded from the valuations &quot; in cumulo.&quot;In this connexion, Mr. Carson Roberts particularly mentioned advertising hoardings. It was agreed that their exclusion would involve amendment of the Advertising Stations (Rating) Act, 1889.6. Application of the Profits Principle. (1) Discussion then proceeded on the Railway Companies proposal (para. (2) of the Memorandum handed in) that the net receipts &quot; above the line &quot; in Account No. 8, plus lump sum tolls and rents other than those arising from house and cottage propert3&apos; and land and premises let to tenants who are separately rated thereon, should be taken as the &quot; Net Income &apos; for valuation purposes. Mr. Hurcomb pointed out that this new proposal was getting very near to the &quot; Standard Revenue &quot; as denned by section 58 of the Railways Act, 1921, the chief difference being that items such as &quot; General Interest &quot; were not included in the Companies proposal in regard to valuation. He, therefore, tentatively suggested, for consideration that, if the Conference came to the conclusion that the maximum degree of simplification should be arrived at, &quot; Net Income &quot; for valuation purposes might be the net revenue obtained by a railway company corresponding to that ascertained for an amalgamated company (i.e., under section 59 of the Railways Act of 1921, excluding only rents from properties let out and separately rated.Sir Francis Dunnell undertook to ascertain the views of the railway companies on this suggestion.(2) The reservation with regard to renewal and maintenance is dealt with in paragraph 4 (2) hereof.7. Apportionment between Rating Areas in England and Wales.-(1) The representatives of the-railway companies indicated that they would support the views that, the annual values of stations should not be based on a fixed percentage but that such values should vary with the fortunes of the
undertaking as a whole. This might involve the adoption of a sliding scale of percentages for arriving at the values of stations, depots, workshops, &amp;c, or the allotment to them of a prescribed proportion of the &quot;     lulo &quot;(2) Mr. Brickwell stated generally the companies&apos; reasons for rejecting the other statistical bases, wkichhad been suggested from time to time for the apportionment of the values of running lines between rating areas, in favour of vehicle-miles. The statistics which had been considered by the railway companies included gross receipts, geographical miles, track-miles and train-miles.He stated that the companies recognised that any basis of apportionment which would create any serious disturbance in the existing distribution of values would be strongly opposed by the local authorities, and that the companies had come to the conclusion that a division on the basis of vehicle-mileage would not only be fair but would most nearly reflect the existing distribution.(3) Mr. Carson Roberts enquired whether it would be possible to test in advance, the results of armortionment on the basis of vehicle-miles. It appeared that, as coaching1 vehicle-miles were not at present available, it was very doubtful whether anj such test could be applied before the Bill was presented to Parliament. Mr. Hurcomb enquired whether any partial data were available.and whether the existence of car-mileage figures for test periods on the Metropolitan District Railway would make it possible to apply such a test to the system. Mr. Buller said this could be done and undertook to furnish the results to the Conference.It was, therefore, agreed that, failing any adequate test of the suggested basis of apportionment which would satisfy the local authorities, it might be necessary to leave the question of apportionment to be settled by the Central Valuation Authority, after consultation with the railway companies and the local authorities.(4) It was explained that, before the Government could propose to the local authorities the adoption of vehicle-mileage as the basis of apportionment between rating areas, it would be necessary to consider not only the relative values of a coaching vehicle-mile and a wagon-mile for valuation purposes, which the representatives of the railways contemplated as probably necessary, but also the relative values of the mileage of different categories of vehicles whithin these main divisions.(5) Mr. Hurcomb asked whether the companies had given consideration to passenger and ton-miles as a basis of apportionment between rating areas. Mr. Showers and Mr. Brickwell stated the use of these statistics for apportionment between parishes was quite impracticable.8. Anglo-Scottish Railways Apportionment between England and Scotland.-(l) It was noted that the railway companies suggested (paragraph 5 of their Memorandum) that the annual value of stations, workshops, &amp;c, should first be deducted and that the balance appertaining to the running lines should be apportioned between the two countries.(2) In answer to Mr. Hogg, Mr. Payne stated that the companies had no particular interest in the amount of the share thrown up for each country, provided the sum of the two shares did not exceed the &quot; cumulo &quot; value.. It was agreed, however, that it would probably be necessary to adjust the share allocated to Scotland to bring it into accord with Scottish Law and practice, e.g., &apos;.&apos; Gross value &quot; in Scotland instead of &quot; Nett &quot; as in England.(3). (i) With regard to the railway companies&apos; suggestion that the value of running lines should be apportioned between England and Scotland on the basis of vehicle-mileage, Mr. Hurcomb pointed out that the recent committee, of which Mr. Brickwell was a member, had definitely recommended passenger and ton-miles as the basis of division between the two countries.(ii) The representatives of the railway companies agreed that the objections to passenger and ton-miles on the score of impracticability and expense, did not apply in the same degree for the purposes of a division between the two countries.Sir Francis Dunnell stated that the railway companies would have no objection to the use of a passenger and ton-mile formula for this purpose, and the representatives of the companies undertook to consider the question of the relative weight which should be given to a passenger-mile and a ton-mile in apportioning the values of the running lines between England and Scotland, and to test the results of apportionment on that basis.9. Quarter Rating. This question was mentioned and Mr. Carson Roberts took note of the views of the railway companies as set out in paragraph (6) of their Memorandum.10. It was understood that the suggestions thrown out during the Conference on each side were tentative in character and it was arranged that a short note of the proceedings should be drawn up and agreed.The railway companies undertook to let the Chairman of the Conference know as soon as they were hi a position to meet the departments again. &apos;        .
APPENDIX I (ii).RAILWAY RATING CONFERENCES.Rating and Valuation Bill.1. A conference with representatives of the County Councils&apos; Association, the Association ofat the municipal Corporations, and the National Conference of Assessment Committees took place Ministry of Health on Friday, 14th December, 1923.   The following were present: Ministry of Health. (In the Scottish Office.Mr. A. Carson Roberts Mr. W. Hogg     -Mr. C. W. Hurcomb   -Mr. W. V. Wood Mi\ A. Matheson Sir Charles E. Longmore -Mr. John Goitlding   -Mr. W. B. Keen Mr. P. Elton Longmore   -Mr. F. H. Owers Mr. F. W. Rattenbury Mr. J. Spain Sir Robert E. Fox Mr. E. Darnell Mr. D. DlnwiddyClia^Ministry of Transport.County Councils&apos; Association.Mi-. Mr.Association of Municipal Corpora-tions.^National Conference Committee.of AssessmentMr. H. J. Hoare......Mr. H. A. Learoyd......Mr. G. Trevelyan Lee     -      -Mr. W. Moon.......Mr. F. Ogden Whiteley.....Mr. Thomas White......A. W. Balmer    -      -      --G. W. Coster......Sir James Curtis       ......Mr. R. A. Leach......Mr. Geo. Leigh......Mr. Herbert Davey -.....Major Harry Barnes -      -      -      -2. Mr. Carson Roberts briefly explained the objects of the Conference and the Governments desire to evolve a workable scheme which would adequately give effect to the principles of the proposed reforms and meet with as wide a measure of agreement as possible.He suggested that paragraph 5 (1) of the Ministry of Health Memorandum on the Draft Rating and Valuation Bill might be taken as a general indication of the subjects for consideration by the Conference.He stated that a meeting had already been held with representatives of the railway companies on the 14th November last and that it was the intention of the Departments concerned to hold a similar meeting with the representatives of the local authorities immediately thereafter, but that the intervention of the General Election had rendered it necessary to postpone such meeting until the present date.He added that it was proposed to hold further separate meetings with representatives of the local authorities and the railway companies, and then, if necessary, joint meetings with representatives of both parties. He suggested that, in this manner, progress could best be secured and the maximum measure of agreement would no doubt be attained.The representatives of the Associations indicated agreement to this suggested method of procedure. 3. Reform of Method of Valuing Railways EssentiaL-Mx. Carson Roberts pointed out that reform of the method of arriving at railway valuations was essential, apart altogether from the Draft Rating and Valuation Bill, and that, in considering the method of valuing railways in the future, it was not necessary for the Conference at this stage to consider or discuss the agency for giving effect to such valuation. The question of the agency would be discussed between the representatives of the local authorities and the Ministry of Health at a later stage.4. Proposal that Railways should be valued in cumulo. He said that the only item in the Draft Bill, which had been circulated, of importance in connection with the conferences now entered upon is the adoption of the principle of valuation in cumulo. That is fundamental and, if there is any difference of opinion on it, it had better be discussed forthwith, as it has to be a settled question before the several important questions which present themselves for discussion can be dealt with.Sir Charles Longmore entered a caveat in regard to the position which might possibly be taken up by the County Councils&apos; Association; and, subject to this reservation, it was generally agreed that the other questions should be discussed on the assumption that the parochial principle was to be abandoned.5. Determination of Railway Valuations in cumulo.-(1) Tenanfs Share-Ms. Carson Roberts stated that the Departments were desirous of getting rid, as far as possible, of the complexities inherent in the existing methods of valuing railways, and that they desired to aim at a method which would give
fl greatest possible simplification consistent with the ascertainment of fair valuations. In particular, tl Ybuld welcome any scheme which would avoid separate determination of tenanfs capital and the itao-es to be allowed thereon. He pointed out the results of applying the present method of ^tprmimng tenanfs share, and stated that it had been suggested that the tenanfs share of the profits &apos; &quot; ht be ascertained on the basis of a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net income,&quot; such percentage being deduced from the experience of the past.In reply to a question, Mr. Hurcomb stated that the representatives of the railway companies had ereed in principle to this suggestion, provided a reasonable percentage could be arrived at, but that thev drew particular attention to the increase in tenanfs capital since the war.Subject to further consideration of the matter by their respective associations, the representatives of the Associations agreed in principle to the suggestion of a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net income &quot; to represent tenanfs share, provided a satisfactory percentage could be found.Maintenance Deductions. The next suggestion discussed was that of whether the time had not come in so far as the railways are concerned, for adopting the actual charges falling upon the annual revenues as the measure of these deductions, instead of substituting &quot; estimated average cost &quot; as theirmeasure.This change would mean that the actual expenditure upon maintaining the hereditament would be allowed to stand in the accounts from which the net receipts are extracted, and that no &quot; statutable &quot; deductions in respect of maintenance would be made.It would also mean the abandonment of &quot; gross value,&quot; and direct ascertainment of net value.At the outset representatives of the Associations inquired as to whether this would not increase the risk of expenditure upon capital additions or betterment being brought in to reduce the total upon which the assessments are to be based, and it was agreed that adequate security against this is equally essential, whether the proposed simplification be adopted or not.Another point raised was that of whether it was not equally necessary, when sums actually set aside as renewal funds are allowed to ranis as expenditure in taking out the net receipts, to secure that these renewal funds are not depleted by expenditure upon capital or betterment. And a further point was that of whether there would be risk that the maintenance deduction thus made might be inflated by the accumulation of unduly large renewal funds.It was understood by all present that this suggested simplification was to be considered upon the assumption that adequate security against risks of the above order is provided, and it was suggested that the one simple and sound way in which this could be provided was by giving to the valuing body which treats with the companies, whatsoever it is, such access to the accounts as would enable them to accept the results thrown out, and that this is necessary in any event.Assuming that a satisfactory solution is found in regard to the matters just referred to, the question of whether the proposed simplification is desirable appears to resolve itself into one of whether the actual expenditure upon maintenance and renewal in the year or years taken into account for valuation purposes will be of too fluctuating a nature.If it can be taken that the Amalgamated Railways are now undertakings of such extent that the cost of maintaining and replacing their lines, &amp;c, will be so distributed between the years (or groups of years) that they do not cause fluctuations which would affect the valuations to a degree which needs correction, the change suggested would have two beneficial results: (i) It would simplify the valuation processes and by eliminating gross value remove one important occasion of dispute and litigation, viz. :   the settlement of the &quot; statutable &quot;allowances.(ii) It would confine the deductions to the actual charge falling upon revenue in respect of maintenance and replacement.(3) Suggested &quot; Short Cut &quot; for arriving directly at &quot; Rateable Value.&quot; On the assumption that agreement would be reached on the suggestions with regard to &quot; tenanfs share &quot; and &quot; maintenance,&quot; Mr. Carson Roberts suggested that the maximum simplification would be attained if &quot; rateable value &quot; were determined by taking a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net income.&quot; He pointed out that tins suggestion, if adopted, would, having regard to the probable effect of the Railways Act, 1921, in the direction of stabilising the net revenue of the railway companies, go a long way towards stabilising also the rateable values of railways. It would not, however, be reasonable to ask either party to take a complete &quot; leap in the dark,&quot; and it was therefore further suggested that any such percentage should be based on the experience of the past. He enquired whether the representatives of the Associations had any alternative means to suggest for arriving at the percentage, but, although they generally agreed that a percentage based on past experience would provide the most satisfactory basis, they asked that the matter should be held over until they had an opportunity of discussing it with their respective Associations. .At the request of Major Barnes, Mr. Carson Roberts undertook to circulate a pro formd to the Association showing the suggested &quot; short cut.&quot;0. Definition of &quot; Railway Undertaking.&quot; Mr. White stated that the National Conference of Assessment Committees were, as at present advised, opposed to the inclusion of such properties as V atenvorks, gasworks, electric power stations, repair shops, road vehicle garages, and town offices, and considered that these should be valued separately by the local rating authorities.Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the railway companies generally had proposed that the clennitlon should embrace all the businesses carried on by a railway company, including docks, canals, hotels, refreshment rooms, road services and steamboats, and that all these, together with railways proper, should be brought into one amiulo for valuation purposes. One of the amalgamated companies demurred, however, to the inclusion of steamboats, and it was probable that the companies would not, if the local authorities dissented, press for the inclusion of hotels. They a so agreed that properties let out and capable of separate assessment should be excluded from the valuations in cumulo. - &apos;-
Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out that the proposal of the railway companies had a direct bearing on the question of the income of the railway companies which should be brought into valuation, and suggested that the Associations should give, further consideration to the matter in the light of the suggestions contained in the following paragraph dealing with the application of the profits principle.The matter was reserved for further consideration.   .7. Application of the Profits Principle. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the railway companies had proposed that the net receipts &quot; above the line &quot;in Account No. 8 (see form of Accounts in Part I of the First Schedule of the Railway Companies, (Accounts and Returns) Act, 1911), plus the lump sum tolls and rents other than those arising from house and cottage property and land and premises let to tenants who are separately rated thereon, should be taken as the &quot; net income &quot; for valuation purposes. The &quot; below the line &quot; items which would be excluded under this proposal include &quot; interest and dividends from investments in other companies &quot; and &quot; General interest.&quot; It was, however clear that if effect were to be given to the proposal of the railway companies to bring within the&apos; valuation in cumulo all businesses conducted by the company, all items in Account No. 8 other than those relating to properties,let out and separately rated should be embraced.by the definition of &quot; net income &quot; for valuation purposes. Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out that the railway companies&apos; proposal, amended as suggested above, would bring &quot; net income &quot; for valuation purposes very near to the &quot; standard revenue &quot; as defined by Section 58 of the Railways Act, 1921. The Associations said that they would require time to consider the suggestion that &quot; net income &quot; for valuation purposes might be taken as the net revenue obtained by a railway company corresponding to that ascertained for an amalgamated company (i.e., under Section 58 of the Railways Act, 1921, excluding only rents from properties let out and separately rated), in conjunction with the railway companies&apos; proposal with regard to the definition of &quot; railway undertaking &quot; (see paragraph 6).8. Apportionment between Rating Areas in England and Wales. (1) Mr. Carson Roberts explained that the apportionment of the valuations in cumulo to the rating areas was a matter which concerned the local authorities chiefly, because from a careful analysis of the figures for a period of 10 years, it appeared that, owing to the effect of differential rating under the Public Health Acts in urban areas, the average poundages levied on the railway companies in urban and rural areas respectively were very similar.(2) It was pointed out that, if the inclusive definition of &quot; railway undertaking &quot; proposed by the railway companies were adopted, docks, for example, would still require to be separately valued, and their inclusion in the railway cumulo would, therefore,,not affect the rating authority or authorities in whose area they were situate.(3) With regard to the valuation of stations, workshops, and similar buildings, Mr. Carson Roberts stated that he thought the Central Valuation Agency, whatever it was, would require to rely upon the Local Rating Authorities to supply the requisite figures and to propose valuations to the Central Agency.(4) Valuation of Stations, tfcc-^-Mr. Carson Roberts enquired whether the Associations had given consideration to the suggestion that had been made by the Royal Commission of 1896, and more recently by the Departmental Committee on Local Taxation in Scotland, that the annual value of stations, depots, workshops, &amp;c, should not be based on a fixed percentage related to the site and the buildings, but should vary with the fortunes of the undertaking as a whole. Both the Commission and the Committee recommended that a minimum of three per cent, with a&quot; sliding scale should be adopted. Another alternative would be to make the&apos;valuations vary from their initial or existing amounts with the total of the cumulo figures.The representatives of the Associations stated that the point had not been considered, but undertook to ascertain the views of their respective associations on the matter.(5) Apportionment of Values of Running Lines. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the railway companies had, after giving careful consideration to other statistical bases, which had from time to time been suggested, including gross receipts, geographical miles, track-miles, train-miles, and a combination of passenger-miles and ton-miles, come to the conclusion that a division on the basis of vehicle-miles specially taken out would not only be fair but would most nearly reflect the existing distribution.In answer to enquiries, Mr. Hurcomb stated that although some of the representatives of the railway companies appeared to. contemplate that equal, values would, for this purpose, be assigned to a wagon-mile and a coaching-mile, they expressed no final views and the question of the weight to be - given in the formula to each class of vehicle-mile was for further consideration.Mr. Dinwiddy, after quoting figures to show that a distribution on the basis of route-miles, track-miles, train-miles, or apportionment of the cumulo value on the basis of the parochial gross receipts would seriously disturb the existing distribution of values, suggested, for the consideration of the Conference, that gross value plus rates should be apportioned amongst rating areas, and that the &quot; statutables &quot; in respect of each rating area should be ascertained and deducted to arrive at the &quot; rate-able value &quot;in each area. He considered that a sufficiently approximate estimate of the &quot; statutables &quot; in each parish could be arrived at without difficulty. He suggested that the basis of the apportionment of gross values plus rates should be passenger-miles and ton7miles, and contended that the railway companies would experience no great difficulty in estimating with sufficient accuracy the number of passenger-miles and ton-miles for each parish. He thought that passenger-miles and ton-miles should be weighted according to their respective gross earning capacity.Mr. Carson Roberts stated that whatever statistical basis or bases were recommended for tno purpose of apportionment amongst rating areas, it would be necessary, to apply a satisfactory test with a view to ascertaining the effect on the incidence of. values as between rating areas, before such basis or bases could become operative. It appeared very doubtful whether the data necessary for such a test would be available in time to admit of the basis of apportionment being fixed by the Bill, and in these circumstances it would probably be necessary to leave the Central Agency to propound a scheme
22and to submit it to Parliament for confirmation. In the interval, it might, therefore, be necessary t( apportion the values of running lines amongst the sating arqas pro rata to the existing values in eachThe matter was reserved for further consideration.9. Anglo-Scottish Railways-Apportionment between England and Scotland._Mr, Carson Robertspointed out that the Committee, - which had reported towards the end of last year had definitely recommended passenger and ton-miles as the basis of division between the two countries and enquired whether the representatives of the associations were in a position to express any views on the matterIt appeared that this question had not been fully considered by the associations and the matter was, therefore, reserved for further consideration.10. It was understood that the suggestions thrown out during the Conference were tentative in character and it was arranged that a short note of the proceedings should be drawn up and agreed with Major Barnes on behalf of the three associations.11. It was arranged that the next meeting should be held at the Ministry of Health at 11 0 a m on Friday, 28th December. , .   ..... &quot;Formula for showing in outline the suggested method of determining the aggregate value of railways.(a) Gross Receipts    -      -      -      -j -   -      -      -Deduct   - - ... .     .      .       . &quot;(b) Working Expenses      -      -      -, -   - -   . - . -   . .&apos; .   . .(c) Revenue charges for Maintenance and Renewal - &apos;   - -      . .__- ;          _(d) Net income        -      -      - .      . .&apos; -;.  v&apos; &quot;&quot;&quot;Deduct x per cent, of d for Tenants&apos; Share -      - ...                             - -_&apos;(e) Rateable value (plus rates)  -      -(/) Deduct rateable value (plus rates) of stations, &amp;c. ... _    -          _[g) Rateable value (plus rates) of Lines     -      . .      . .      .__i;__Notes.  :      &apos; - ^ . ... . . ...(i) Items (a) (6) and (/) above will depend upon the properties to be brought within the scope of the valuation in cumulo.(ii) The amounts to be deducted under (c) above would be the maintenance and renewal charges appearing in the revenue account, plus the amounts transferred to renewal fund during the year. The renewal expenditure, in so far as it is borne by a renewal fund, would not rank for deduction.(iii) Item (g) would be the amount for apportionment amongst the rating areas.(iv) A further simplification may possibly be attainable, if both sides can agree to the deduction of rates paid at the outset instead of carrying them through for deduction in detail after the apportionmentto rating areas.c 4
APPENDIX I. (iii).RATING AND VALUATION BILL.(i) A second Conference with representatives of the County CounciPs Association, the Association of Municipal Corporations, and the National Conference of Assessment Committees took place at the Ministry of Health on friday, 28th December, 1923.   The following were present: Mr. A. Carson Roberts Mr. C. W. Hurcomb   -Mr. W. V. Wood Mr. A. Matheson Sir Charles E. Longmore Mr. E. T. Gardom Mr. John Goulding   -Mr. W. B. Keen Mr. E. H. Owers Mr. E. W. Rattenbury Mr. J. Spain      -M. Johnson Darnell Mr. D. Dlnwiddy Mr. H. J. Hoare Mr. A. A., Learoyd Mr. G. Trevelyan Lee Mr. H. G. Pritohard Mr. Thomas White Mr. A. J. Balmer Mr. J. A. Battersby -Mr. G. W. Coster Sir James Curtis Mr. I. Dixon Mr. R.. A. Leach -Mr. Geo. Leigh  -Mr. T. Percival -Mr. Herbert Davey -Major Harry Barnes -Mr. S. Mr. E.- Ministry of Health (in the Chair) -&quot;j-Ministry of Transport.County Councils Association.[Association of Municipal Corpora-tions.National Conference of Assessment Committees.2. Determination of Railway Valuations in cumulo. (1) Tenanfs Share. The representatives of the associations agreed that it was highly desirable to avoid separate determination of Tenanfs Capital and the percentages to be allowed thereon. They also agreed in principle to the suggestion of a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; Net Income &quot; to represent Tenanfs Share, provided a satisfactory percentage could be determined.With regard to the basis upon which the percentage should be fixed, the associations were unable to suggest any better basis than the experience of the past, but Mr. White, on behalf of the National Conference of Assessment Committees, suggested that the matter should be kept open to allow of further exploration.Major Barnes stated that the National Conference would like the percentage to be determined before the Bill is introduced, but Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out that it was doubtful whether sufficient data would be available to enable a fair ascertainment of the percentage to be arrived at before the Bill is presented to Parliament, in which case it would be necessary to leave the percentage to be determined by the Central Agency, whatever it is, subject to confirmation by Parliament.(2) Maintenance. It was agreed that, instead of estimating the average annual cost of maintenance, those amounts actually charged in the railway companies&apos; revenue accounts in respect of maintenance, i.e., sums charged to revenue either by way of actual expenditure or provision, should be allowed, provided that adequate safeguards are set up to ensure, e.g. (a) that such sums do not include expenditure on capital additions or betterment, (6) that renewal funds are not depleted by expenditure upon capital additions or betterment, and (c) that maintenance charges allowed are not inflated by the accumulation of unduly large renewal funds.In this connection, Major Barnes pointed out that the Railway Rates Tribunal, which had been established under the Railways Act, 1921, would presumably, for the purpose of fixing the standard charges, examine and consider maintenance and other expenditure, and he suggested that, in regard to this matter, some form of co-operation between the Central Valuation Agency and the Railway Katee Tribunal might eventually be found useful.3. Definition of &quot; Railway Undertaking.&quot; All three associations were agreed that the following properties or subjects should be excluded from the railway valuations in cumulo : (i) Docks, harbours and wharves.(ii) Canals.(iii) Steamboats.(iv) Hotels, as distinct from refreshment rooms and dining cars.(v) Omnibuses and other road services, apart from collection and delivery of railway traffic.(vi) Electricity, gas and water works, if any, the products of which are mainly sold to the public.(vii) Properties let out and capable of separate assessment.
2APPENDIX I. (iv.).RATING AND VALUATION BILL.1. A second Conference with representatives of the railway companies was held at the Ministry of Transport on Monday, 7th January 1924.   The following were present: Mr. C. W. Hurcomb     -      -      -      -      -   Ministry of Transport (in the chair). Mi&apos;. Carson Roberts    -      -      -      -      -   Ministry of Health. Mr. W. Hogg.....-   Scottish Office.Mr. W. V. Wood......\Ministry of Transport.   .Mr. A. Matheson - / jSir JVRANcis Dunnell   - - l^ndon and North Eastern Railway.Mr. A. J. Brickwell    ----- J      .Mr. P. W. Showers.....Great Western Railway. ^Mr. P. M. Payne......London, Midland and Scottish Railway.Mr. S. E. Hitchcock.....Southern Railway.Mr. L. B. Carslake.....\London Electric Railway-Mr. F. C. Buller -      -      -      -      -      - /Metropolitan District Railway, &amp;c.Mr. F. Dawson     ------   Metropolitan Railway.    .2. Determination of Railway Valuations in cwmwZo.-Sir Francis Dunnell stated that the railway companies, after giving further consideration to the matter, had come to the conclusion that the percentage representing tenanfs share, should be left to be determined by the Central and/or Joint Valuation Authority, subject to appeal to the Railway and Canal Commission.He saw considerable practical objection to the suggestion that such percentage should be confirmed by Parliament.The representatives of the Departments indicated their views that it would be necessary that some general statutory direction should be given to the Central Valuation Authority, which, while relating*  23726The representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees considered that the following properties should also be excluded from the railway cumulo : (i) Electricity works. &quot;1(ii) Gasworks. f-Whether or not the products were solely used for railway purposes.(iii) Waterworks.       J(iv) All road services, including collection and delivery services.(v) Construction shops, as distinct from repair shops.The representatives of the associations indicated, however, that their conclusions in this matter were not final and that if it could be shown that the proposal of the railway companies that the definition should embrace all the businesses carried on by a railway company, would not be disadvan-tao-Carbonaceous to the local authorities, they were prepared to give further consideration to the proposal on the understanding that all relative revenue, including general interest would be brought into account. They asked that the railway companies should be requested to furnish the aggregate pre-war valuations of all the properties or subjects which would be embraced by the definition proposed by the railway companies, the aggregate valuations of separately rated hereditaments connected with railway working, omnibuses and other road services, apart from collection and delivery of railway traffic, steamboat services, canals, docks, harbours and. wharves, hotels, refreshment rooms, and other separate businesses, to be shown separately. The valuations of properties let out and separately rated to the occupiers should be excluded. It was agreed that the railway companies should be asked to furnish this information.4. Apportionment bet-ween Rating Areas in England and Wales : (1) Valuation of Stations, die.  With regard to the suggestion that the annual value of stations, depots, workshops, &amp;c, should vary with the fortunes of the undertaking as a whole, the representatives of the Association of Municipal Corporations and the National Conference of Assessment Committees stated that they were opposed to any change from the existing practice.Mr. Keen, on behalf of the County Councils&apos; Association, stated that he saw no reason why stations should rank as a first charge on the valuations in cumulo, and he considered that the values of stations should vary with the fortunes of the undertaking.After some discussion, it was agreed.that the existing practice of basing the annual value of stations, depots, workshops, &amp;c, on a fixed percentage related to the site and the buildings should remain undisturbed.(2) Apportionment of Values of Running Lines. It was agreed that the determination of the apportionment of the values of running lines amongst rating areas in England and Wales should be left to the Central Valuation Agency, subject to confirmation by Parliament.It was also agreed that, if the railway companies so wished, rateable value plus rates should be apportioned and that the rates should be deducted locally.Mr. Dinwiddy also suggested the advisability of local deduction of &quot; statutables,&quot; or, alternatively, separate apportionments of gross values plus rates, and &quot; statutables,&quot; and further suggested a basis for the apportionment of &quot; statutables.&quot; Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out, however, that this proposal could more properly be dealt with by the Central Agency when they were considering the question of apportionment.
any percentage to the experience of the past, would free the Authority from existing case-law and from the difficulties which arose from differences in the law as it now stood in England and Wales and in Scotland. The representatives of the railway companies doubted the necessity for any such direction but agreed that the Central Authority must be enabled to decide the question of the percentage representing tenanfs share on a basis of equity unhampered by the legal decisions of the past.At each quinquennial valuation the whole matter will be reviewed and appeal will be open to the parties.3. Definition of &quot; Railway Undertaking.&quot; (1) Mr. Hurcomb stated that the representatives of the local authorities had pressed for the exclusion of the following properties or subjects from the railway valuations in cumulo:     - ..   .(i) Docks, harbours and wharves.(ii) Canals.(iii) Steamboats. ;&apos;(iv) Hotels, as distinct from refreshment rooms and dining cars.(v) Omnibuses and other road services, not used in connection with the collection and delivery of railway traffic.They had originally proposed the exclusion of many other subjects such as gas, electricity and water works, and even town offices-but would probably be prepared to include all properties except those in the list mentioned, and, of course, properties let off and separately rated.He added that the local authorities were, however, keeping an open mind on the question pending the receipt and consideration of the information asked for in the letter from the Ministry of Transport to the Railway Companies Association, dated 31st December 1923.The representatives of the railway companies undertook to supply the information asked for by the local authorities at the earliest possible date.(2) Sir Francis Dunnell stated that he considered that all rateable hereditaments owned and worked by railway companies should be included in the &quot; cumulo,&quot; but that, if the local authorities pressed for the exclusion of canals, steamboats, hotels, and road services other than those engaged in collection and delivery, the railway companies would not continue to press for their inclusion. The Southern Railway Company in any case objected to the inclusion of steamboats.The railway companies, however, attached considerable importance to the inclusion in the &quot; cumulo &quot; of docks, harbours and wharves, owing to the great difficulty which would be experienced in separating the earnings of docks and harbours from those of the railways proper. They urged that the local authorities should be asked to give further consideration to the matter in the light of this difficulty. .. . -(3) With regard to the suggestion that refreshment rooms, as distinct from hotels, should be included in the &quot; cumulo &quot; the representatives of the railway companies are anxious to settle with as few rating authorities as possible.It was agreed that the inclusion of refreshment rooms in the &quot; cumido &quot; would make for simplification.   Such a course would not necessarily debar a valuation on the profits principle.(4) In answer to Mr. Hurcomb, Mr. Brickwell explained that it was the intention of the railway companies that all joint lines, including &quot; J &quot; Joint Lines, should be included in the &quot; cumulo,&quot; and that the values of the running lines of the joint systems should be based on the average of the values found of the lines of the owning companies.4. Application of the &quot; Profits Principle &quot; : (1) Items in Account No. 8 to be taken into account.-Mr. Hurcomb asked whether the companies had considered the suggestion made at the previous meeting that the valuations should be based on,the profits ,of the concession as a whole, rather than on the profits of the rateable hereditaments.Sir Francis Dunnell stated that even if the &quot; cumulo &quot; embraced all businesses carried on by a railway company, the railway companies were unable to agree that &quot; general interest &quot; should be brought into account for valuation purposes. He pointed out that the rating of the profits of investments as distinct from a consideration only of the profits arising from the rateable hereditaments would be contrary to existing principles of rating.(2) Maintenance. The representatives of the Government then asked whether the companies agreed that if sums set aside; from revenue as provisions for., maintenance were allowed to rank as deductions in arriving at rateable values, regard should be had to the factor of interest, and pointed out that in railway accountancy., depreciation and other provisions. did not ordinarily have regard to this factor.This matter will require further consideration.(3) Access to Accounts, &amp;c, by Central Authority. The representatives of the railway companies agreed that the Central and Joint Valuation Authorities should have statutory powers similar to those now conferred upon the Assessor of Railways (Scotland).5. ,JRates. The representatives of the railway companies stated that their proposals involved the deduction of the aggregate.rates.actually paid, as a working expense before arriving at the &quot;&apos; cumulo to be apportioned amongst, the.rating areas..6. Apportionment between Rating Areas in England and Wales. The railway companies saw no objection to the basis of. apportionment being left over for determination by the Central and/or Joint Valuation Authority. . .,.They undertook to furnish later the results of their consideration, of the relative weights to be given to coaching-miles and wagon-miles for apportionment purposes.7. Anglo-Scottish Railways Apportionment between England and Wales. The representatives of the railway companies undertook to . furnish at an early date the results of applying a passenger-mue ton-mile formula to the existing aggregate valuations in England and Scotland, and also to gr?e particulars of the formula.
230APPENDIX. I., (y). .VALUATION OE RAILWAYS FOR RATING PURPOSES.] A Conference between representatives of the Government Departments concerned, Scottish County. Burgh and Parish Rating Authorities&apos;was held at the Office&apos; of the General Board of Control, Edinburgh, on Friday, 2nd May, 1924.The following were present: Representatives of Government Departments. iMr W Hogg       - -   .   &apos;.- - -   Scottish Office.I] W. V. WooCDOMBj 0BE: : : l)-^ of Transport.Mr. A. Carson Roberts - - - - -   Ministry of Health.Representatives of County Rating Authorities.Mr. G. A. Cumming         - -      , - .- Joint County Clerk of Banff shire.Mr. J. Stormonth Darling - - - - County Clerk of Roxburghshire.Mr. John McGhie -         - - - - - - County Clerk of Lanarkshire.Major C. H, Scott Plummer - - - -, Convener of Selkirkshire.Mr. John Robson -          - - - - - County Clerk of Dumfriesshire.Mr. J. E. Shaw    -          - - - - County Clerk of Ayrshire.Sir John D. Don Wauchope, Bart. - - - - Vice-Convener of Midlothian.Representatives of Burgh Rating Authorities.&apos;Mr. Duncan Graham      - - -. - . - City Treasurer, Glasgow.Mr. Alexander Hendry. - - - -. - Town Clerk, Denny.Sir Henry S. Keith       - - - - - Provost of Hamilton.Mr. W. H. Blyth Martin - - - - Town Clerk, Dundee.Mr. James R. Rust        - - - - - City Treasurer, Aberdeen.Mr. John T. Sorley       ,-- - - - - City Chamberlain, Aberdeen.Mr. Alexander Stevenson - - - City Treasurer, Edinburgh.Mr. P. A. Thomson - - ... Town Clerk, Ayr.Representatives of Parish Rating Authorities.Mr. H. A. Reynard        - - . .   Secretary, Association of parish councils in Scotland.Mr. Robert Stewart      - - - - -   Inspector of Poor, Perth.Col. Arch. Young, C.B.E.,        -.       --        - -   Chairman of Edinburgh ParishCouncil. -Mr J A King     - - - - -&apos; -&apos; H.M. Assessor of Railways, &amp;c,for Scotland.Mr. Robert Paton -v       - - -  - City Chamberlain, Edinburgh.Mr. A. Matheson, D.S.O.(Ministry of Transport), Secretary.2. Mr. Hogg described briefly the method of valuing railways for rating purposes which had hitherto been in operation in Scotland, and pointed out that the grouping arrangements which had been effected under the Railways Act, 1921, rendered it impossible for the Assessor of Railways and Canals (Scotland) to carry out his statutory duties in relation to the valuation of railways. No separate accounts for the Scottish portions of the Amalgamated Railways were now available nor could they be made available without entailing great expense upon the railway companies. Such accounts would serve no useful purpose apart from valuation!The difficulty with which the Scottish Assessor is faced synchronises with a demand for the amendment of English rating law, and a Bill, copies of which had been furnished to the representatives of the Scottish local authorities, had been drafted. The draft Bill provides for the valuation by a Central Valuation Authority for England and Wales of railway and certain other undertakings as a whole and the apportionment of the total rateable value to the parishes concerned.Mr. Hogg added that the railway companies and the English rating authorities are favourable to the application of the &quot; in cumulo &quot; method to railways in England and Wales, and he assumed that Scotland had no desire to depart from that method.   The Conference agreed.Mr. Carson Roberts explained that the provisions in the Bill referred to the railways which were wholly situate in England and Wales, and that a gap had been left in the Bill for a provision or provisions dealing with the valuation of the Anglo-Scottish railways and the apportionment of values between the two countries. He added that the constitution of the Central Valuation Authority proposed in Clause 29 of the draft Bill was by no means settled, and that it was probable that the constitution of the proposed Central Agency might be materially varied before the Bill was presented to Parliament.3. Proposed Joint Authority for Anglo-Scottish Railway Groups.-Mc. Hogg stated that tbe problem before the Conference was to find a satisfactory solution to the difficulty with which the Scottish Assessor is now faced and at the same time to simplify the existing law and practice as to valuation. The representatives of the Departments concerned proposed that the railways situate partly  ind 2
Scotland and partly in England and Wales should be valued by a Joint Authority, and that for this purpose the Scottish Assessor should act jointly with a &quot;representative or representatives of the English Central Agency, and that the Joint Authority should also apportion the values so arrived at between the two countries. If more than one representative of England were appointed to the Joint Authority steps would require to be taken to ensure that the Scottish Assessor would have voting powers equal to those of the English representation on the Authority. He added that the railway companies had agreed in principle to a Joint Authority over which a judicial,chairman would preside, but the matter has not yet been discussed with the English fating authorities. ,     .....Sir Henry Keith stated that once the principle of valuation had been defined, the actual valuation became a matter of administration and the work of experts. The representative body proposed to be set up by Clause 29 of the draft Bill would prove of no value. The only practicable solution was to appoint an expert Assessor for England and Wales and, if joint action were necessary, that he should act with the Scottish Assessor for the purpose of valuing the Anglo-Scottish railways and apportioning the values between the two countries, subject to some right of appeal.Mr. Stormonth Darling raised the question whether it would not be sufficient to have one Railway Assessor for Great Britain, but it was generally agreed that the differences in law and practice in England and Scotland rendered it desirable to have a separate valuation authority for&apos; each country.After further discussion, the setting up of a Joint Authority on the lines indicated by the Departmental representatives was generally agreed to.The representatives of the Scottish local authorities desired to place formally on record their unanimous opinion that the system of entrusting railway valuation to a single expert Assessor had worked quite satisfactorily in Scotland.4. Appeals from Decisions of Joint Authority. Mr. Hogg stated that it had been proposed, subject to the concurrence of the Lord Chancellor and the Lord President of the Court of Session, that appeals from the decisions of the Joint Authority should go to the Railway and Canal Commission sitting with a Scottish and an English Judge, and thence, on points of law only; to the House of Lords. The railway companies had agreed to this proposal.The representatives of the Scottish local authorities agreed to the proposal.5. Definition of &quot;Railway Undertaking.&quot; After discussion, the representatives of the Scottish local authorities expressed the view that docks and harbours should be included, but that canals, steamboats and omnibuses should be excluded from the railway valuations &quot; in cum,ido,&quot; and also that hotels, as distinct from unlicensed refreshment rooms and dining cars, should continue to be excluded.6. Maintenance Deductions. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that it had been suggested that the actual charges in respect of maintenance falling upon the annual revenues should be adopted as the measure of the deductions to be allowed for maintenance. This would mean that the actual expenditure charged to revenue for both repairs and renewals and sums set aside to meet future renewals and depreciation, would be allowed. The only difference between the method suggested and that hitherto followed by the Scottish Assessor is that sums set aside for renewals and depreciation would be allowed to rank currently as immediate deductions for this purpose, and not be held over until they are actually expended. A similar suggestion has been put forward by the railway companies, and the English local authorities have agreed, provided that adequate safeguards are set up to ensure, e.g. (a) that the sums allowed do not include expenditure on capital additions or betterment, (6) that renewal funds are not depleted by expenditure upon capital additions or betterment, and (c) that maintenance charges are not inflated by the accumulation of unduly large renewal funds.The representatives of the Scottish local authorities agreed to the Departmental suggestion as to the deductions in respect of maintenance, subject to the safeguards proposed by the English local authorities.(Mr. Reynard referred to the statutory deduction made by the Scottish Assessor of half the cost of the upkeep of the permanent way and raised the question whether this deduction was to continue to be allowed twice in arriving at net rental. Mr. King pointed out that, although in the Report of the Dunedin Committee it was stated (para. 102) that the deduction of the half cost referred to was twice allowed once by the Assessor and again by the parish authorities yet no double deduction of the whole permanent way upkeep charges was involved so far as railways and profit-earning tramways were concerned. In section 9 of the Act of 1867 it is provided that the statutory deduction of half the cost of maintaining the permanent way to be allowed under section 3 of the Act by the Railway Assessor, in arriving at the gross rental, should not again be allowed by the Parish Councils in arriving at the net rental. This provision was recognised and followed in practice. Double deductions under section 37 of the Poor Law Act, were, however, granted, under authority of the Court, in the case of certain undertakings other than railways and profit-earning tramways.)7. Ascertainment of &quot; Tenanfs Share.&quot; Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the Departments are desirous of getting rid, as far as possible, of the complexities inherent in the existing methods of valuing railways and they desired to aim at a method which would give the greatest possible simplification consistent with the ascertainment of fair valuations. In particular, they would welcome any scheme which would avoid separate determination of tenanfs capital and the percentages to be allowed thereon.The application, of the present method of determining the tenanfs share would, in view of ^ the substantial increase in present values of rolling stock and other tenanfs chattels, result in greatly diminished valuations in England. The particular difficulty in regard to Scotland, is that there is now no purely Scottish rolling stock, such stock now being common to the whole Amalgamated Company. Moreover, workshop machinery and plant in each country will no longer be employed exclusively jpf each country and rolling stock of the Amalgamated Companies in the one country may be repaired an renewed in the other. .   ,It.has been suggested that the tenanfs share of the profits might be ascertained on the basis o a fixed percentage of a defined &quot; net receipts,&quot; such percentage being deduced from the experience oi the past.
Both the railway companies and the English local authorities have agreed in principle to s share being taken as a fixed percentage of net receipts, provided a reasonable percentage could bTarrved at. In this connection, the railway companies drew particular attention to the increase in tenanfs capital since the War.Figures were in process of being collected with a view to ascertaining whether it would be hracticableto determine the percentage before the Bill is introduced.&apos; Mr McGhie stated that, while he agreed in principle to determining the tenanfs share on the basis&apos; of a percentage of the net receipts, he was strongly opposed to stereotyping the percentages allowed upon tenanfs capital in Scotland in the past. He referred, in particular, to the allowance of &apos;&quot;) per cent, for depreciation which appeared to have been allowed for twice over, once under the head of tenanfs allowances and again in the name of &quot; repairs and renewals &quot; under working expenses.The representatives of the Scottish local authorities agreed in principle to this proposal, subject to the caveat by Mr. McGhie, and expressed the view that the percentage should be put into the Bill, provided a figure could be agreed between the parties concerned.8. Apportionment between England and Scotland. Mr. Hogg pointed out that the Committee, which had reported in November, 1922, had definitely recommended passenger and ton-miles as the basis of division between the two countries.He stated that the representatives of the English local authorities had stated, when the suggestion was put to them, that this question had not been fully considered by their Associations and thcTmatter was, therefore, reserved for further consideration.The railway companies stated that they had no particular interest&apos;in the amount of the shares thrown up for each country, provided the sum of the two shares did not exceed the &quot; cumulo &quot; value. They had suggested that the value of running lines should be apportioned between England and Scotland on the basis of vehicle-mileage, but after some discussion, their representatives stated that the companies would have no objection to the use of a passenger and ton-mile formula for this purpose. They had undertaken to consider the question of the relative weight which should be given to a passenger-mile and a ton-mile in apportioning the values of the running lines between England and Scotland, and to test the results of apportionment on that basis.Mr. Hogg pointed out that there was a difference of opinion amongst the members of the recent Committee as to whether the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways should be apportioned between the two countries before or after deducting the values of stations, sidings, workshops and other buildings. The difficulties lay in the different percentages adopted in valuing stations in the two countries and in the different treatment of sidings and machinery. The majority of the members of the Committee held that the Joint Authority would most correctly proceed by deducting in the first instance a value, ascertained on some uniform basis, for stations, workshops, &amp;c. This method of procedure would necessitate a uniform definition of stations, sidings, &amp;c, in both countries, and also a common basis upon which to determine the value of such properties. In Scotland, the valuation of stations is determined by taking 5 per cent, of the estimated cost of construction (including the solum). The 5 per cent, was fixed by section 3 of the Act of 1867. In England, while the valuation is, roughly speaking, based upon a percentage of the value of the land and buildings, there is no statutory direction on the point, and the method of valuation and the percentage varies in different rating areas.The minority of the members of the Committee (Messrs. Paton, King and Bain) held that, as the figure to be apportioned between the two countries was an &quot;intermediate figure&quot; and not a final valuation, it should be divided in toto between the two countries, leaving the question of the valuation of stations, &amp;c, to be dealt with by the valuation authorities of each country according to their respective law and practice. The whole Committee were agreed that, failing the adoption of a uniform definition of stations, sidings, &amp;c., and a common method of valuation of such properties in both countries, there would appear to be no alternative but that the &quot; intermediate figure &quot; should be divided in toto.Reference was made to the recommendation of the Royal Commission on Local Txaation of 1896, that the 5 per cent, rigid allowance should be discontinued, and that a minimum of 3 per cent., with a sliding scale, should be adopted.. This recommendation has been endorsed by the Dunedin Committee, who added that the sliding scale ought to depend upon the profits of the railway.Mr. Paton, after giving his reasons for adhering to the view that the &quot;intermediate figure&quot; ascertained by the Joint Authority in respect of the Anglo-Scottish railways should be divided in toto, between the two countries, stated that the more important burghs in Scotland were strongly opposed to any reduction in the statutory 5 per cent. , (He pointed out that other buildings and properties in Edinburgh, which were comparable to stations, were assessed at from 6 per cent, to 7 per cent: of their structural value.) He had, however, no objection to the principle of the sliding scale, provided that the datum percentage is satisfactory.Sir Henry Keith and Mr. McGhie stated that they were in favour of the sliding scale recommended by the Royal Commission and the Dunedin Committee (i.e., a minimum of 3 per cent, with a sliding scale varying up to a maximum (not specified) according to the value per &quot; train &quot; or other statistical mileAf lineS of railway-though Sir Henry would accept a fixed figure of 3J per cent.). ^ Alter further discussion, the representatives of the Scottish local authorities indicated that they were unanimously in favour of the whole value of each of the Anglo-Scottish railways being apportioned m toto between the two countries, leaving each country to deal with its own stations, &amp;c.Mr. Carson Roberts asked that the Conference should give further consideration to the question a &quot;r in view oi tne possibility of a shift of workshops from one country to another, or the counto   n 0^ wol&apos;&apos;;&apos;snol;)s m one country without a corresponding increase in the workshops of the otherCo F   ^     nry Keith&apos;s Proposal. On Mr. Hogg requesting an expression of the views of the nierence on the suggestion that the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways should be divided Would611    i tW0 countries on the basis of passenger-miles and ton-miles, Sir Henry Keith stated that he in whi Wh Pre*er tnat the nrst division between the two countries should be based upon the ratio c the interest and dividends upon the capital of the two Anglo-Scottish amalgamated companies,D 8
as allotted to the proprietors of :the: former English and Scottish companies respectively, under the amalgamation schemes, accrued * to the two, interests,   This ration to be varied in succeeding years b allowance on the one side or the other for all capital expenditure upon the development or extension of the heritages in the respective countries.He further stated that the valuations in each country could be separately determined, according to the law and practice of each country, upon the same basis, i.e., by taking out the profits available for distribution upon the stock and shares assigned to the proprietors of the railways in each country and applying a percentage to the respective totals of such profits to arrive at the valuations for each country. This, he urged, would make for the maximum simplification and render it unnecessary to set up a Joint Authority. All that would be necessary would be that the Scottish Assessor should act with an English Assessor to determine each country&apos;s share of the divisible profits.Mr. Hurcomb pointed out that, while he recognised that Sir Henry Keith&apos;s proposal provided for adjustments in the ratio in the event of capital additions or improvements in one country or the other he thought it would also be necessary to provide for adjustments of the ratio in the event of anv material alteration in the revenue earned in one country as compared with that earned in the. other where such alteration was due to an increase in traffic without a corresponding increase in capital expenditure. He suggested that it might be desirable, assuming that some such basis as that suggested by Sir Henry were adopted for the initial division between the two countries, to take power to apply an activity formula, based, say, on passenger and ton-miles, as a corrective in future years.Sir Henry Keith said that his proposal, apart from allowances or additions in respect of capital expenditure which was profit-earning on either side of the Border, would remain as a fixed ratio for the allocation of increased or diminished valuation in proportion to the increase or decrease of future revenues of the undertakings, available for distribution.After further discussion, the representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities asked that figures should be got out which would enable them to examine the probable effects of adopting either Sir Henry Keith&apos;s proposal or that suggested by the Departmental representatiyes.10. Directions as to Apportionment. The representatives of the Scottish Local Authorites stated that they should prefer that the formula to be used for the apportionment between Scotland and England should be inserted in the Bill.11. Apportionment between rating areas in Scotland. Various suggestions as to a basis for apportionment between the rating areas in Scotland were discussed, but no definite conclusion was reached.   The matter was left over for further consideration.12. Periodicity of Valuations. Mr. Hogg drew attention to the following statement in the Ministry of Health Memorandum (page 12) : &quot; The Bill (Clause 33) provides for the quinquennial revision of special properties by the Central Authority, but the reconsideration of values, which will normally be undertaken after the expiration of four years, may on the application of the occupier or of any rating authority or county council concerned, be undertaken at any time after the expiration of one year from the date when the existing values came into force.&quot; .In Scotland the valuations of public railways are fixed annually in cumulo (on a three years&apos; average) by the Railway Assessor. Except in the Metropolitan area, where the valuations are revised quinquennially under statute, no fixed period is laid down in England and Wales, and practice varies considerably.He added that the railway companies are in favour of quinquennial valuations of railways being made general, and if this is agreed to the existing Scottish law would require to be amended in this respect.The representatives of the Scottish local authorities agreed to the provisions of Clause 33, as drafted, being made applicable to Scotland.13. It was understood that the suggestions thrown out during the Conference were tentative in character and it was arranged that a note of the proceedings should be drawn up by the Secretary and agreed by Mr. King on behalf of the Scottish local authorities.14. It was arranged that a further meeting would be held when the figures asked for were available.
2County Councils&apos; Association.Association of Municipal Corporations.National Conference of Assessment Committees.RATING AND VALUATION BILL.Conference on Railway Valuation. 1 A third Conference with representatives of the County Councils&apos; Association, the Association of Municipal Corporations, and the National Conference of Assessment Committees took place at the Ministry of Health on Saturday, 14th June, 1924.   The following were present : Mr. A. Carson Roberts .   -      - -.     -      - Ministry of Health.. ,. : , .   u ... .   (In the Chair.)   . . .Mr. W. Hogg     ...... .   Scottish Office.Mr. C. W. Hurcomb    -      -      - . -.&apos; . .Mr. W. V. Wood p .    -.     - ,.. -. i.- n   .-      -f- -n  &apos; Ministry of Transport.Mr. A. Matheson-      - -J    - -Sir Charles E. Longmore -   - :--     -:    - J&apos;&apos;Mr. John Goulding   -      -      -      -      -      -Mr. W. B. Keen -      -      -      -      -Mr. F. H. Owers -      -      -      -      -      -  -   -Mr. F. W. Rattenbury    , -      - -Mr. J. Spain . .    - -      -.     -      -Mr. S. M. Johnson.     -  ... -      - ;.. , - ..   -Mr. E. Darnell -;     ...      .      .      -Mr. D. Dinweddy       -      -      -      -      -&quot; &apos;  -Mr. H. J. Hoare -      -.....Mr. Holt    -   h - - -      -      -Mr. H. A. Learoyd     -      -      -     - - *     -      -Mr. G. Trevelyan Lee   h -.     -.     -.     -      -Mr. W. Moon      -      -      -      -      -      -   : -Mr. Smith   -      -      -      -      -      -      -      -Mr. F. Ogden Whiteley    -      - .-Mr. Thomas WhiteMr. G. W. Coster - - - &quot; -Mr. G. Craightll - - - - -Mr. J. Dixon      -      -      ...Mr. T. Percival.....-Mr. Herbert Davey  -     -      -      -     &apos;-.Major Harry Barnes - v- &quot;&apos;  .&apos;     . 1   .2. The new Agencies to be set up. -Mr. Carson Roberts stated that many of the replies received in regard to the draft Bill had indicated a desire to restrict the functions of the Central Valuation Authority substantially to dealing with railways. While he was not in a position to say that these views had definitely been accepted, he suggested that discussion might prooeed on the assumption that the work of the Central Agency would substantially consist of Railway Valuation.The question whether an agency :consistihg of two expert-assessors with-a chairman of judicial qualification would be preferable to the Central Valuation Authority proposed in the Draft Rating and Valuation Bill was then discussed. ... ...Mr. Carson Roberts asked for the views of the Local Authorities on the following suggestions : (1) That the &quot;Joint Authority&quot; to deal with the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways should consist of three members, namely, an experienced lawyer who would be chairman, a railway assessor, for England and Wales, and the Scottish Assessor of Railways and Canals.(2) That the &quot; Railway Assessments Tribunal &quot; to deal with the valuations of the Great Western, Southern, the London Underground and remaining railways situated wholly in England and Wales, should consist of the chairman of the &quot; Joint Authority,&quot; the English Assessor on that body, and a second English Assessor, who would act only when the railways wholly within England and Wales were, being,dealt with. ../ &quot; This alternative was submitted for consideration because-(i) It appears to offer a solution of the problem of how to arrange for joint action between the English and Scottish Assessing Authorities. (N..B. -As noted below the/representative bodies expressed the view that this joint action should be confined to the narrowest limits by aPplying the apportionment to net recipts; but, even so, some of the. more contentious questions arising in connection with the valuations would require joint treatment.)(n) It appears to provide a more convenient&apos;and appropriate Court of First Instance for nearing and adjudicating upon the objections to the draft valuations which may be raised by the railway companies on the one hand or by the local authorities either jointly of individually on the other hand. ...rrir- . representatives of the associations considered it desirable to reserve any final expression of to hfw? 0D , ma*ter until it had received further consideration and until the work which would fall opinio t Ih Englisn Assessing Agency and by the Joint Agency had been more fully defined, but exni-p11 l ?       effect that there was no call for changing the plan proposed in the Draft Bill were pressed by some of the county and municipal representatives. . \uthmffPPr       0f any scheme which would  substitute a State-controlled office for a Central only as contemplated by the Draft. Bill. was expressed on behalf of   the associations;D 4APPENDIX I (vi).
and it was, therefore, understood that the alternative which the Conference was asked to consider should be one under which the English Assessors and their staff should be selected and their remuneration settled by the local authorities acting through a committee of selection.(The Chairman would probably require to be nominated by the Lord Chancellor after consultation with the Lord President of the Court of Session.)The question appeared to resolve itself into one of whether the local authorities should select 15 to 20 lay representatives or two experts, to sit, along with a chairman of judicial qualification for hearing argument and giving decisions upon the technical questions arising out of railway valuation&apos; In neither ease would there by any new Government office set up for the purpose.3. (1) Apportionment between England and Scotland. Mr. Hurcomb reminded the Conference that, in regard to the two Anglo-Scottish Companies, it would be necessary to settle a basis of apportionment, which shall be applied either (a) To the initial item, viz., Net Receipts;(b) To an intermediate total representing a rental value of lines plus stations and other localised items, i.e., Net Receipts after deduction of Tenanfs Share; or(c) To a similar total after deducting local values (stations, &amp;c).After discussion, the representatives of the English Local Authorities were generally agreed that any formula of apportionment between the two countries should be applied at the earliest possible stage, namely, to a division of &quot; Net Receipts.&quot;(2) Mr. Hurcomb pointed out that the Committee on the Valuation for Rating of Amalgamated Railways situated partly in England and Wales and partly in Scotland, which had reported in November, 1922, had suggested that the figure, whatever it is, to be apportioned between England and Scotland should be divided on the basis of ton-miles and passenger-miles.This basis involves the working out of a formula in which a ton-mile and a passenger-mile would be given their appropriate values.At a recent meeting with the representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities, it \vas suggested by Sir Henry Keith that the first division between the two countries should be based upon the ratio in which the interest and dividends upon the capital of the two Anglo-Scottish Amalgamated Companies, as allotted to the proprietors of the former English and Scottish Companies respectively, under the amalgamations schemes, accrued to the two interests. This ratio to be varied in succeeding years by allowance on the one side or the other for all capital expenditure upon the development or extension of the hereditaments in the respective countries.During the discussion in Edinburgh upon Sir Henry Keith&apos;s proposal, it was pointed out that it would probably also be necessary to provide for adjustments of the ratio in the event of any material alteration in the revenue earned in one country as compared with that earned in the other, where such alteration was due to an increase in traffic without a corresponding increase in capital expenditure. Assuming that some such basis as that suggested by Sir Henry were adopted for the initial division between the two countries, it was suggested that power should be taken to apply an activity formula as a corrective in future years.Figures were being got out with a view to enabling the local authorities to examine the probable effects of adopting Sir Henry Keith&apos;s proposal and these would be circulated.Major Barnes stated that the National Conference of Assessment Committees were considering alternative methods of apportionment between England and Scotland, and he suggested that further consideration of this matter be deferred until the proposals of his association were before the Conference.   He undertook that the proposals would be submitted at an early date.This suggestion was agreed to.4. Tenanfs Share. Mr. Carson Roberts reminded the Conference that, with the view to placing the calculation of &quot; Tenanfs Share &quot; upon a basis which would be simple to operate and less exposed to fortuitous fluctuations, it is desirable that the percentage of &quot; Net Beceipts &quot; to be treated as &quot; Tenanfs Share &quot; should be prescribed. The question before the Conference was how to arrive at a satisfactory percentage. He suggested that the problem might be tackled in one of three ways, namely : (1) To leave the determination of the percentage (or percentages, if different percentages were to be applied to the various companies) to the Central Agency, subject to a right of appeal.(2) That the Government should insert a figure (or figures) in the Bill. (3) That the representatives of the local authorities and the railway companies should get together and endeavour to agree upon the percentage (or percentages) to be put in the Bill.The representatives of the local authorities agreed that course (3) should be adopted and each association undertook to select and submit the names of three representatives to meet the representatives of the railway companies early in July next.Sir Charles Longmore suggested that Mr. Carson Roberts should take the chair at any such meeting and that he should be accompanied by the other Departmental representatives. This was agreed to.5. Definition of &quot; Railway Undertaking.&quot; Further discussion took place on the question of what properties should be treated as part of the railway undertaking for valuation purposes, in the light of the statement which had been circulated showing the aggregate rateable value (1st April, 1914) and net receipts for 1913.It was agreed that this question be reserved for discussion at the joint meeting which it is proposed to hold with the representatives of the railway companies.6. It was agreed that a short note of the proceedings should be drawn up and agreed with Major Barnes on behalf of the three associations.
t) 0RATING AND VALUATION BILL. Third Conference on Railway Valuation, Saturday, 14th June, 1924. Supplementary Note by the National Conference of Assessment Committees. 1 At the outset of the proceedings Councillor Thomas White, Chairman of the National Conference of Assessment Committees drew attention to the document received on the 11th June, 1924, headed &quot; Valuation of Railways for Rating Purposes &quot; with the sub-heading, &quot; A short statement of the points on which agreement appears to have been reached,&quot; and said that the representatives of the conference could not accept the position that so far agreement had been reached on any of the points set out therein, the position being that the whole matter was under discussion and agreement must finally rest with the National Conference.He also stated that the Representatives of the Conference had expected to have been put in possession of examples showing the result of the application of tentative formulae to the &quot; Tenanfs Share &quot; which would have helped them to conclusions on the matter.He also expressed the dissatisfaction that would be felt by the conference with any valuation based either on capital, gross receipts or net receipts that did not show a substantial improvement on present position.He also stated the the Representatives of the National Conference could not agree at present to the adoption of the net revenue or profits principle as the basis for valuation, and that the valuers to the Conference Railway Sub-Committee had been instructed to investigate the desirability and practicability of various alternative methods of valuation based on capital value, gross receipts and net receipts, and that on their report the Representatives of the National Conference would give further consideration to the matter.2. The paragraph set out at the head of page 4 of the Note of the Conference is not to be read as indicating that in any way the Representatives of the National Conference depart from the form of the Central Assessment Committee outlined in the Memorandum of the National Conference of AssessmentCommittees.Councillor Thomas White was not able to remain till the end of the Conference.3. Paragraph 3, page 4, of the Note is not to be read as indicating that the Representatives of the National Conference are agreed to the valuation of railways in the future being determined on a basis of net receipts, their position in this matter has been made clear by Councillor Thomas White, the Chairman of the National Conference, in his opening statement set out in paragraph (1) of this note.4. Paragraph 4, page 6, is not to be read as indicating that the Representatives of the National Conference had agreed to confine the discussion with the railway companies to the question of a per-centage of net receipts being taken as the tenanfs share, possible alternatives being that the landlords share might be fixed on a percentage of gross receipts, net receipts and capital value, and they reserved the right to indicate their views on all or any of these alternatives at the meeting with the railway companies.APPENDIX I. (vn)RATING AND VALUATION BILL.Conference on Railway Valuations.1. A third Conference with representatives of the Railway Companies was held at the Ministry of Transport on Monday, 23rd June, 1924.   The following were present :-Mr.Mr. Mr.Mr.Mr.Sir Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr. Mr.Carson RobertsC. W. Hurcomb W. V. WoodW. HoggA. MathesonPrancis Dunnell A. J. Brickwell F. W. Showers P. M. Payne S. E. Hitchcock L. B. Carslake F. C. Buller F. Dawson  -A. B. Cane -- Ministry of Health (in the Chair). &apos;\Ministry of Transport (part of the time).- Scottish Office.- Ministry of Transport, Secretary.&apos;\London and North Eastern Railway.- Great Western Railway.- London, Midland and Scottish Railway.- Southern Railway.-\London   Electric   Railway,   Metropolitan- f   District Railway, &amp;c.- Metropolitan Railway.- Railway Companies&apos; Association.- The New Agencies to be set up. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that it had been suggested : (1) That the &quot; Joint Authority &quot; to deal with the valuations of the Anglo-Scottish railways should consist of three members, namely, an experienced lawyer who would be chairman, a railway assessor for England and Wales, and the Scottish Assessor of Railways and Canals.*  23720 KAPPENDIX I. (vi) (a).
(2) That the &quot; Railway Assessments Tribunal &quot; to deal with the valuations of the Great Western, Southern, the London Underground and the remaining railways : i.e., situated wholly in England and Wales, should consist of the Chairman of the &quot;Joint Authority,&quot; the English Assessor on that body, and a second English Assessor, who would act only when the railways wholly within England and Wales were being dealt with.The Local Authorities had reserved their opinion on this alternative to the &quot;Central Valuation Authority &quot; proposed in the draft Rating and Valuation Bill (Clause 29), but it had been submitted for consideration because : (i) It appears to offer a solution of the problem of how to arrange for joint action between the Enghsh and Scottish Assessing Authorities-;(ii) It appears to provide a more convenient and appropriate court of first instance for ... hearing and adjudicating upon the objections to the draft valuations which may be raised by theRailway Companies or by the Local Authorities.Mr. Hogg pointed out that the share assigned to Scotland would require to be adjusted to accord with Scottish rating law and practice, and that some adjustment of the Scottish share would be necessary whether the figures to be apportioned between the two countries were &quot; net receipts &quot; or &quot; net receipts less tenanfs share.&quot; -;.-),-&apos;-3: Mr. Carson Roberts reminded the Conference that at the previous meetings it had been provi-sionaUy agreed that the apportionment between England and Scotland should be on the basis of passenger-miles and ton-miles, and that the railway companies had undertaken to furnish the results of applying a passenger-mile ton-mile formula to the existing aggregate valuation in England and Scotland and to give particulars of the formula.He added that at a recent meeting with the representatives of the Scottish local authorities, it was suggested by Sir Henry Keith that the first division between the two countries should be based upon the ratio in which the interest and dividends upon the capital of the two Anglo-Scottish amalga-mated companies, as allotted to the proprietors of the former English and Scottish companies respec-tively, under the amalgamations schemes, accrued to the two interests. This ratio to be varied in succeeding years by allowance on the one side or the other for all capital expenditure upon the develop-ment or extension of the hereditaments in the respective countries ; such variation would not, of course, vary the quantum to be divided between the two countries, but only the shares to be assigned to each. It would probably also be necessary to provide for adjustments of the ratio in the event of any material alteration in the revenue earned in one country as compared with that earned in the other, where such alteration was due to an increase in traffic without a corresponding increase in capital expenditure. Assuming that some such basis as that-suggested by Sir Henry Keith were adopted for the initial division between the two countries, it was suggested that power should be taken to apply an activity formula as a corrective in future years as and when the Tribunal found that the variation was such as to demand an adjustment.Subject to any fresh suggestions which the railway companies might have to offer on the subject, it appeared that the most suitable activity formula for this purpose would be one based on passenger-miles and ton-miles, and if that were finally agreed upon it would be necessary to have placed upon record the number of passenger-miles and ton-miles run upon the English and Scottish sections of the two Anglo-Scottish railways respectively during an appropriate period immediately preceding the date of the initial division to enable the &quot; Joint Authority &quot; to make the necessary comparison when considering the application of the formula in future years.The representatives of the railway companies, while indicating that the companies were not specially concerned with the basis to be selected for the division between the two countries, undertook to con-sider whether the necessary data for a corrective formula, such as had been suggested, could be made available.4. Tenants&apos; Share. With regard to the percentage.of &quot;net receipts &quot; to be treated as &quot;tenanfs share,&quot; Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out that the question before the Conference was how to arrive at a satisfactory percentage. He suggested that the problem might be tackled in one of three ways, namely : (1) To leave the determination of the percentage (or percentages, if different percentages were to be applied to the various companies) to the Central Agency, subject to a right of appeal. (2) That the Government, should insert a figure (or figures) in the Bill.(3) That the representatives of the local authorities and the railway companies should get together and endeavour to agree upon the percentage (or percentages) to be put in the Bill.The representatives of the local authorities were strongly opposed to course (1), and it was under-stood that the railway companies were averse from the adoption of course (2). The representatives of the English local authorities had signified their willingness to meet the representatives of the railway companies with a view to seeing whether agreement could be reached as to an equitable percentage (or percentages) to be put into a Bill. &apos; &quot;The representatives : of&apos; the railway companies agreed to enter into joint conference with the English and Scottish local authorities on the understanding that the discussions would proceed &quot; without prejudice &quot; to any,of the parties concerned.- Sir Francis Dunnell asked that Mr. Carson Roberts should take the chair at the joint meetings. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the-representatives of the English local authorities had already made the same request, and asked that he should, be- accompanied by the other Departmental representatives, In agreeing to this procedure, the Departmental representatives hoped that it would be possible ai a later stage for the parties to leave the negotiations to a small number of persons representative of eitliei side, who would endeavour to reach agreement between themselves. .It was arranged, subject to agreement with the - representatives of the local authorities, that one first joint conference should be held at the1 Ministry of Health at 11 a.m. on Thursday, 10th July, or Friday, 11th July.    -      &apos; &apos;:&apos; &apos;v -&apos;&apos;! fcH.&apos;-v?
o o ii&amp; a (appendix I, (vm).RATING. AND VALUATION BILL.Conference on Railway Valuations.1. A joint meeting was held at the Ministry of Health on friday, 1.1th July, 1924 between represer. tatives of the English and Scottish local authorities, the railway companies, and the Government Departments concerned.The following were present: Mr. A. Carson Roberts    -   . -Mr. C. W. Hurcomb   -     &apos;-. &quot;  -Mr. W. Hogg     -   . -     -Mr. J. A. King   -      -Mr. A. Matheson      ,-  .English Local Authorities.  County Councils&apos; Association : Sir Charles Longmore. Mr. P. H. Owers. Mr. P. Spain. Mr. W. B. Keen.National Conference of Assessment Committees : Councillor T. White. Mr. A. W. Balmer. Mr. j. A. Battersby. Mr. G-. W. Coster. Mr. (J. Craighill. Mr. R. A. Leach.Mr. George Leigh. .      ,Mr. Tom Percival. Mr. Herbert Davey. Major Harry Barnes. .&quot;   ; Mr. Isaac Dixon.-   Ministry of Health (in the Chair). -      -      -   Ministry of Transport. ,, -;&apos;     -   Scottish Office.   , ; &apos;-&quot;      -      -   Assessor&apos;of Railways (Scotland).- ,    -   Ministry of Transport (Secretary to the Conference).English Local Authorities cont.Association of Municipal Corporations :Mr. Ogden Whiteley. Mr.. Lee.Mr. D. Dinwiddy.Railway Companies :.&apos;Sir Francis Dunnell. ,   Mr. Carslake. Mr. Brickwell. Mr. Showers; &apos;    Mr. Payne. Mr. Hitchcock. -.....Mr. E. Dawson.Mr. F. C. Buller. Mr. A. B. Cane.Scottish Local Authorities : Sir Henry Keith.&apos; . Colonel A. Young. Mr. McGhie. / gMr. James Eaibbairn.e 25. Statutable Deductions-Mr. Carson Roberts pointed out that the proposal, which had already been accepted by the railway companies .(subject to the reservation made on behalf of the London Under-ground Companies; to, which reference is made below) and by the local authorities (subject to the provision of necessary safeguards), namely, that in taking out &quot; net receipts &quot; the actual expenditure upon &quot; maintenance &quot; together with any sums- set aside and earmarked to that purpose should rank for reduction, were adopted, it necessarily followed that any interest earned by the provisions so set aside and earmarked should be taken into account, or, alternatively, that the provisions for &quot;maintenance &quot; should be assumed to be on a sinking fund basis.        .(.,..&apos; -.. nThe representatives of the railway companies agreed to this conclusion.Mr. Carslake, on behalf of the London. Underground Companies, pointed out that the Underground Companies had been allowed by the Rating Authorities to deduct from their gross receipts the provisions which were considered to be necessary, even although corresponding sums were not in fact set aside as reserves, and he enquired whether this,practice would be continued, in future. , In reply, Mr. Carson Roberts stated that if the suggestion that the deduction should be based upon actual expenditure plus provision made, be adopted, there appeared to be no justification for varying the basis one way or the other, but it was open to Mr. Carslake to raise the point when negotiating with the local authorities on the question of the &quot; percentage &quot; to represent tenanfs share.0. Definition of Railway Undertaking. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the local authorities had not vet readied final conclusions on the question of what properties should be included in &quot; railway under-taking !&apos; for valuation purposes, and that the matter had been reserved for discussion at the proposed joint conference.7. Apportionment to Rating Areas in England and Wales. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that it had been agreed with the representatives of the English local authorities that the question how the aggregate values are to be apportioned between rating areas in England and Wales must be left over for settlement after information has been obtained in regard to the effect of the various plans which have been or may be suggested, and that in the meantime apportionment in proportion to existing values must be adopted the Railway Assessment Agency for England and Wales would be charged with the duty of pro-pounding for submission to Parliament such scheme of apportionment as would in their opinion give the most equitable distribution and it has been suggested that they should be directed to have regard among other relevant circumstances to the existing distribution of railway values in preparing this scheme.The representatives of the railway companies stated that the method to be adopted for apportion-ment between rating areas was relatively unimportant to them. Mr. Carson Roberts assured the repre-sentatives that the railway companies would be fully consulted before any particular scheme of apportionment was adopted.
2. Mr. Carson Roberts stated that the meeting was arranged with the object of exploring ho\ might be possible to reach agreement on the question whether some specified percentage of &quot; net rec of the railway undertakings might be taken to represent the &quot; tenanfs share &quot; or, alternatively, the t value of the railways.He pointed out that the question of such a percentage might be dealt with in one of three namely : (1) To leave the determination of the percentage (or percentages, if different percentage to be applied to the various companies) to the Central Agency, subject to a right of appeal.(2) That the Government should insert a figure (or figures) in the Bill.(3) That the representatives of the local authorities and the railway companies slum together and endeavour to agree upon the percentage (or percentages) to be put in the Bill,v far it -ipte&quot; iteableways,s wereId getHe understood that the local authorities were strongly opposed to course (1) and that the railway companies were equally opposed to course (2). There remained course (3), and he urged that the parties should make a serious attempt to arrive at a satisfactory and equitable solution of the problem with which they were faced. The discussion would, he added, proceed on the basis that it would be &quot; without prejudice &quot; to either side.3. Mr. Councillor White, Chairman of the National Conference of Assessment Committees, submitted several contentions in favour of the view that the new statutory provisions in regard to the valuation of railways should be such as would increase rather than decrease the present rateable values.He argued : (i) That during the past ten years there had been considerable increase in the rateable values of other hereditaments and in particular of other industrial hereditaments, whereas railway values had decreased; and that this position had arisen in spite of the fact that legislation had practically secured to the railway companies profits equal to those attained in their best pre-war year 1913.(ii) That the comparison brought out on the statistical returns between net receipts and rateable values was a comparison of the net receipts of this year 1913 with valuations based upon the net receipts of earlier years; and that it could not be taken as a correct return of the valuations which would have been produced by a complete and up-to-date application of the accepted principles for governing these valuations in the past.(iii) That if the principles of the past, as settled in practice and by judicial decisions, were now strictly applied to railway valuations in England and Wales there is reason to believe that in many eases nil or even minus values would be arrived at.(iv) That the valuations of railways and railway-owned docks and canals would have been much higher, if, instead of arriving at hypothetical rental value on the revenue or profits principle, the con-tractor^ or capital value principle which is applied to many other industrial hereditaments had been used.He stated that the N.C. of A.C. were exploring three possible bases of valuing railways related, respectively, to (i) Net receipts, (ii) Gross receipts, and (iii) Capital values.He indicated that &quot; Capital Value &quot; might for the purpose of valuation be estimated in several different ways, one of which might be the market value quoted on the Stock Exchange, and submitted further argument directed to showing that capital value of the hereditament is not an unreasonable or improper basis to adopt in connection with railway valuations.He particularly emphasised that the National Conference of Assessment Committees had not anti-cipated a conference prior to September, and consequently they were not ready with proposals at this meeting, but as a matter of courtesy he informed the Conference, without prejudice, that investigations on these lines were at present being considered by the National Conference Advisers, and he named them in order that, if the Conference desired, they might discuss such proposals.4. Sir Francis Dunnell expressed some astonishment at hearing it contended that the railways were undervalued in 1914, and stated that the railway companies were not prepared to discuss the question on an assumption that the pre-war valuations, which many of the companies thought were too high, were to be increased. He suggested that the Conference should not discuss whether the valuations of 1914 were too high or too low, but should apply itself solely to the discussion of an equitable basis or method of valuing railways under existing conditions fair both to railway companies and to rating authorities.He agreed that the application of the existing law and practice, as determined from time to time by the Courts, might result in greatly diminished values of the railways and that, under existing conditions, absurd results would emerge. And, therefore, he agreed that some new or modified basis of valuation must be found, either by agreement or by the proposed Tribunal of Appeal.He thought that whatever method were adopted it would be necessary that there should be an opening for revision from time to time in the interest of either side.He entirely disagreed with the contention that valuation could properly be based upon capital values in the case of railways. He pointed out that this would bring in many millions of capital value which were not, on any conceivable principle, rateable. He also drew attention to the very different position, in regard to competition and other matters, of undertakers embarking on railway enterprise now and 50 years ago.5. As regards the proposition that railway valuations might properly have relation to the capital values of the hereditaments instead of to the receipts (net or gross), the further discussions disclosed marked difference of opinion on the side of the Local Authorities. The representatives of the Association of Municipal Corporations expressed definite disapproval., as also did Sir Henry Keith on behalf of the Scottish Burgh authorities. &apos; The proposal received tentative support from the representatives of the County Councils&apos; Association, Sir Charles Longmore arguing that a principle which was applied to asylums, to schools, and to many other hereditaments where rents were not in fact paid, was not inappropriate in the case of railways. On the other hand, Mr. Brickwell argued that circumstances which made the contractor^ method obviously inappropriate in the case of canals, applied also in the case of railways. Also that a proposal to value railways on a principle differing from that applied to other public utilities earning revenue was inadmissible.As regards the comparative advantages of adopting net or gross receipts as the basis, it was subsequently announced that the N.C. of A.C. were not prepared at this stage to submit any arguments.
(6 e) i)6 Mr Keen argued that it is wrong in principle to pay regard to increase in the value of Tenanfs C  ital while paying no regard to increase on the landlords side, as the present system does; and that five^admission that anomalous results would now be produced by following that system was conclusive vidence of the falseness of the principle and of the need for its amendment.   He contended that increase of net receipts should benefit both parties.He suggested that there is no better basis for determining tenanfs share than that of having regard to the corrected proportion of the past and introducing such amendments therein as present circumstances appear to demand.7 Mr. Dinwiddy, Mr. Keen and Mr. Dixon each developed arguments that the railways in 1914 were under-assessed on existing methods of valuation. Mr. Dixon pointed out that the valuations operative in 1914 were, in many cases, several years old, and that the net receipts of the railways had increased from 1901 to 1913 by about 33  per cent.; and argued, further, that the annual value of the railways was enhanced by the provisions of the Railways Act, 1921, standardising 1913 net revenue, and practically guaranteeing adequate remuneration for any further capital expended.8 Sir Henry Keith urged that, in view of the fact that the valuation of railways had hitherto been on a revenue basis, the division between England and Scotland should be a fair division of the net receipts of the Groups operating in both countries, leaving the Assessment Authority of each country to work out its valuations therefrom according to the law of the country concerned. He had suggested what seemed to him a practicable method of making this division, but it was agreed that the question of what is the fairest basis for the division was not a matter to be discussed at this joint conference.9. Mr. McGhie stated that the local authorities in Scotland were of opinion that the railways in Scotland had been undervalued in the past. He considered that the share allowed to the tenant had been too high, and he contrasted the 25 per cent, allowed in Scotland on Tenanfs Capital with the 15 per cent, to 17-J per cent, allowed in England. He added that occupiefs income tax had in the past been allowed as a deduction in arriving at railway valuations, that he could see no justification for such allowance and he suggested that it should be disallowed in future.10. Mr. Dinwiddy, using figures of capital expenditure which he had extracted from railway returns, contrasted the small percentage which the rateable value bore to the landlords capital expenditure with the large percentage which tenanfs share bore to tenanfs capital expenditure.He suggested that an equitable way of arriving at tenanfs share would be to estimate the tenanfs share under two heads, viz., (1) Interest at a percentage upon the capital that would be required to be found by the tenant and (2) profit at a proportion of the net receipts. He quoted a recent case where this principle had been adopted by the Court in Scotland in connection with an appeal against the valuation of a gas undertaking.Sir Francis Dunnell indicated that the companies would be prepared to consider this suggestion. But attention was drawn to the desirability of adopting a plan which did not involve continuous valuation of the tenanfs plant.11. Major Harry Barnes submitted that the fixation of a standard revenue under the Railways Act, 1921 on the 1913 basis involved the fixation of a combined landlords and tenanfs share at the 1913 total, that any increase in the tenanfs share necessarily carried with it diminution in the landlords share which was the basis of rateable value, and conversely that no increase in the landlords share could take place without a corresponding diminution in the tenanfs share.He further pointed out that the amount of the sum total of rateable value obtained by the application of the profits principle on the parochial system was only now available, and showed a very low percentage on the capital value of the undertaking, however estimated, and that if the proposal to base rateable value on capital value was not entertained, the best method of securing a rateable value comparable to that yielded by other classes of hereditaments would be by a diminution of the tenanfs share.   He pressed the companies to consider the propriety of agreeing to an equitable reduction.12. Mr. Dixon queried whether the fixing of 1913 as a standard year and the requirement for a standard net revenue to be ascertained was not good ground for ascertaining also a standard rateable value as for that year, and supplementing it from time to time in accordance with developments of the undertakings.13. Mr. Carson Roberts suggested that greater progress would be made if a much smaller number of representatives of the parties got together, say four or five from the local authorities and a similar number from the railway companies. Such a body could, he added, more readily define the issues between the parties, and later on those issues could, if necessary, be discussed at a larger conference.This suggestion was generally agreed to by the representatives of the County Councils Association, the Association of Municipal Corporations, the Scottish Local Authorities and the railway companies, ine representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees stated, however, that it would be necessary to refer the matter to their executive. Mr. White stated that it was doubtful , her ^&apos;le National Conference would be ready to resume the discussions before September; but ie undertook to communicate with the Departmental representatives as soon as they were ready.. :J&apos;- 1* was agreed that a note of the proceedings would be drawn up by the secretary and en dilated, in draft, to the various associations represented at the Conference, and it was provisionally arranged that the next joint meeting be held on Friday, 19th September.B 3
APPENDIX i: (ix).RATING AND VALUATION BILL. Conference on Railway Valuations.1. A second joint meeting was held at the Ministry of Health on Friday, 19th September 1924 between representatives of the English and Scottish Local Authorities, the railway companies and the Government Departments concerned. &apos;The following were present:  ;Mr. A. Carson Roberts      - - - - ;Mr. 0. W. Hurcomb   - -     - - ;- -Mr. W. V. Wood  -      -      - - -Mr. W. Hogg  ,.   .-, - .Mr. J. A. King    -      - &apos; ? . - - -: Mr.-A.. Matheson  -      -English Local Authorities : County Councils&apos; Association :Mr. W- J- Freer.Mr. J. Goulding.Mr. J. H. Gould. ,vi,   .,.   ....Mr. J. G. McGrath. .     -Mr. F. H. Owers.Mr. F. Spain.National Conference of Assessment Committees .Councillor T. White. Mr. A. W. Balmer. Mr. J. A. Battersby. &apos; Mr. G. W. Coster. Mr. G. Craighill. Mr. R. A. Leach. Mr. George Leigh. Mr. Tom Percival. Mr. Herbert Davey. -    Major Harry Barnes. Mr. Isaac Dixon. . Mr. L. R. Jones. Mr. A. Body. Mr. H. Bewlay.- - - - Ministry of Health (in the Chair). &apos;&apos;- Ministry of Transport.- - Do. .   - .    - Scottish Office.-;      - Assessor of Railways (Scotland).. - Ministry of Transport (Secretary to the Conference).English Local Authorities cont.Association of Municipal Corporations : Mr. Lee. Mr. Darnell. Mr. D. Dinwiddy.Railway Companies :Sir Fbancis Dunnell. Mr. Carslakb. Mr. Brickwell. Mr. Showers. Mr. Payne. Mr. Hitchcock. Mr. F. Dawson. Mr. F. C. Btjlleb.Scottish Local Authorities : Colonel. A. Young. Mr. McGhie.2. The note of the joint meeting held at the Ministry of Health on Friday the 11&apos;th July 1924, which had already been circulated, was accepted, without amendment, as a correct record of the proceedings of that meeting.3. Mr. Councillor White referred to the suggestion made by Mr. Carson Roberts at the previous meeting to the effect that a much smaller number of representatives of the parties should be got together for the purpose of defining the issue between the parties (see paragraph 13 of the note of the meeting held on the 11th July), and he stated that the executives of the National Conference were not prepared to assent to any arrangement which would result in the diminution of the sub-committee appointed by their executive to carry on these negotiations.4; Mr. Carson Roberts stated that, in his opinion, it was essential, if progress were to be made, that a small &quot;body, consisting of representatives of the local authorities and the railway companies only, should be set up with a view to ascertaining whether any agreement could be reached with regard to the relation to be established between landlords and tenanfs shares. He suggested that such a body should be empowered to examine the possible bases upon which agreement might be reached; that they should, however, have ho power to settle anything, but should report to the full meeting before anything is settled. - &apos;&apos;&quot; 1      i;.   ..;He further suggested that, in view of the special position of the National Conference of Assessment Committees in relation to valuation, it appeared desirable that the National Conference should be given a larger representation than the other associations of local authorities concerned. He made it clear that the proposed body would not be empowered to settle any question of principle and that any such settlement must be left to the full meeting, and no question of delegation of powers really arose.Mr. Councillor White stated that his executive would.be prepared to appoint representatives to such a body, on the understanding that they should not thereby be committed to any proposals which the body might suggest.After some discussion, it was agreed that a body of 17 representatives should be set up for the purpose outlined by Mr. Carson Roberts and that it should be constituted as follows :  National Conference of Assessment Committees&apos;--      -   4 representatives. Association of Municipal Corporations     -      -      -      -      -   3 ,,County Councils&apos; Association -------   2 ,,Scottish Local Authorities.....-      -   3Railway Companies 5
238APPENDIX I. (x).RATING AND VALUATION BILL.Conference on Railway Valuations.A third joint meeting was held at the Ministry of Health on Thursday, 4th December 1924, between representatives of the English and Scottish Local Authorities, the railway companies, and the Government Departments concerned.The following were present&apos;:: Mr. A. Carson Roberts - - - - -   Ministry of Health (in the Chair).Mr. C. W. Hurcomb Mr. W. Hogg Mr. J. A. KingMr. A. MathesonEnglish Local Authorities :-County Councils&apos; Association : Mr. W. J. Freer. Mr. J. Goulding. Mr. F. H. Owers. Mr. F. Spain. Mr. W. B. Keen.National Conference of Assessment Committees Councillor T. White. Mr. A. W. Balmer. Mr. J. A. Battersby. Mr. G. W. Coster. Mr. George Craighill. Mr. A. Gard. Mr. R. A. Leach. .  . Mr. George Leigh. Mr. Herbert Davey. Major Harry Barnes. Mr. Isaac Dixon. Mr. E. H. N. Ryde. Mr. H. Bewlay. Mr. A. Body. Mr. L. R. Jones.- Ministry of Transport.- Scottish Office.- Assessor of Railways (Scotland).- Ministry of Transport (Secretaryto the Conference).English Local Authorities cont.Association of Municipal Corporations :Mr. H. A. Learoyd. Mr. Ogden Whiteley. Mr. Lee.Mr. D. Dinwiddy. Mr. Smith.Sir Arthur Bryceson, Mr. Ho are. i -. Mr. Lord. Mr. Holt.-&quot; Mr. Harry G. Pritchard (Secretary).Railway Companies:Sir Francis Dunnell. Mr. Carslake. &apos; Mr. Brickwell, ,1 &quot;Mr. Showers. Mr. Payne. Mr. Hitchcock. Mr. F. Dawson. , ,   ; Mr. F. C, Buller.Scottish Local Authorities: Sir Henry Keith. Colonel A. Young. Mr. McGhie.Councillor White reported that the sub-committee consisting of representatives of theEn^ish and Soettish Local Authorities and the railway companies, set up for the purpose fa ^Js and whether any agreement could be reached with regard to the relation between ^/andlord s and tenants shares had not been able to agree on a percentage of &quot;Net Receipts    to represent the^Uarson Roberts suggested that the most useful procedure at this final CQnffnX%ubm?tted ito attempt to fill in gaps hi the scheme for future valuation of railways which ^s to be. submitted Us a result of these discussions, and to bring within the narrowest limits which full agreement could not be attained. For this purpose he proposed to take in ro^qS^g matters which had arisen, and to invite further discussion wherever there appeared to be nope oi reaching fuller agreement.I. That each railway undertaking should be valued as a whole with subsequent apportionment to ; rating areas.e  it was further agreed that this body should get together at the earliest possible date and that thev should report to the full meeting not later than the 31st October.It was also arranged that the National Conference would arrange the meetings and that Mr. Davey would act as convener.., .... &apos;5. Mr. McGhie enquired whether Mr. King, the Assessor of Railways for Scotland, would be included in the Scottish representation.Mr. Carson Roberts explained that in view of Mr. King&apos;s official position this would not be possible&apos; but that Mr. King would be available as advisor to the Scottish representatives.6. It was agreed that the next meeting of the full Conference should be held at the Ministrv of Health at 2.30 p.m. on Friday the 7th November. J
This principle had been accepted by all parties, subject to the inclusion of appropriate provisions in regard to the treatment of the two Anglo-Scottish systems (paragraphs VIII. and X. below).II. That for this purpose a Railway Assessment Authority for England and Wales should be provided This had also been agreed, but in regard to how and by whom this authority should be appointeddifferences of opinion between the different groups of English Local Authorities had been noted and it did not appear that any useful purpose could be served by discussing this point further at this conference.Upon the following points all parties concerned, except the National Conference of Assessment Committees, were agreed.(i) That the authority should be constituted on the lines proposed in Clause 29 (3) of the Draft Bill, though the list of representative bodies entitled to make recommendations to the Minister was not accepted by all the parties to the Conference.(ii) That the railway companies and local authorities (individually or collectively) should have opportunity to present objections to and to be heard by this authority before any valuations were made effective.(iii) That there was no objection to the proposal that the. chairman of this authority should be an experienced lawyer or person of judicial experience approved by the Lord Chancellor after consultation with the Lord President of the Court of Session in Scotland.The National Conference of Assessment Committees desire it to be noted that they adhere to the views set out in a memorandum on the Draft Rating and Valuation Bill which they addressed to the Minister of Health, namely : Note to Clause 29. &quot; It is recommended that clauses be substituted providing that a National Association be formed comprising all the assessment committees in England and Wales.&quot; That the executive of such association be the central valuation authority.&quot; That the chairman be appointed at the discretion of such central valuation authority.&quot;III. The definition of &quot; railway undertaking &quot; for the above purpose. It has been agreed that this definition should not include(a) Hotels;(b) Licensed refreshment rooms;(c) Hereditaments (or heritages) let out by railway companies and capable of separate assessment.Other matters where agreement as to inclusion or exclusion had not yet been reached were discussed and a note of resolutions recently adopted by the representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees were put in at this point.   (See Appendix.)Steamboat Services :It was agreed that these are not a rateable subject.Works for Construction of Rolling Stock, &amp;c. :The proposal for exclusion put forward by the -National Conference of Assessment Committees was dropped.Railway-owned Canals:The representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees and the Association of Municipal Corporations were still of opinion that canals should be treated separately, but, recognising that the point was of no great importance, the latter association agreed to waive their objection to inclusion.The representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities also recognised that the reason which had impelled them to ask for exclusion, being connected with apportionment to rating authorities, could be otherwise covered and withdrew their request for exclusion.Railway-owned Docks and Harbours :No agreement was reached the representatives of the railway companies press strongly for inclusion, and to this the representatives of the Scottish Local Authorities and of the English County Councils agree, but  the representatives of the National Conference of Assessment Committees and of the Municipal Corporations&apos; Assocation were strongly opposed to inclusion. No other proposal for exclusion was pressed on behalf of any group.It had been agreed by all parties concerned that the valuations in cumulo in England and Wales should be directed solely to the ascertainment of Net Values. It had also been agreed by all parties, except the representatives of the Underground Railway Companies, that the actual expenditure upon repairs and renewals charged to revenue and sums properly set aside to meet future renewals and depreciation should be allowed to stand as expenditure when taking out Net Receipts for valuation purposes.Thus there would no longer be any estimation of &quot; gross value &quot; or any &quot; statutable deductions to bring into account.The representatives of the Underground Railway Companies urge that, in addition to the sums actually charged to revenue in respect of repairs and renewals, an adequate provision for future renewals and depreciation, whether actually made or not, should be allowed as a deduction when taking out Net Receipts for valuation purposes.V. It is also generally agreed, although the National Conference of Assessment Committees declined to commit themselves to this view, that payments in respect of Rates should be allowed to stand when taking out the Net Receipts and that no deductions in respect of rates should thereafter be made from the parochial values.
237VI Adoption of &quot; the Profits Principle.&quot; The Representatives of the National Conference of nt Committees and of the Municipal Corporations&apos; Association urged that the assessmentAsscssnw   ghoui,j De ieft free to adopt this or.any other principle in determining the aggregate value authon        un^ertaiii1-[g-   The railway representatives were completely opposed to any departure the profits&apos; principle  and the representatives of  the county councils and of the Scottish Authorities agreed that it was the only principle for these valuations..j fiuq discussion, in which it was argued that in the absence of direct statutory requirement to f &apos;i r another principle, there was the strongest probability that the Courts would continue to maintain the- profits principle, and that, if the Conference failed to agree on this fundamental point, it was &apos; lossible to progress with any of the other matters which it was desirable to settle, it was agreed that the discussion should proceed on the assumption that the profits principle was to rule.VII Tenanfs Share of Net Receipts. -As it appeared to be useless to make any further attempts to each agreement on the actual percentage or percentages to be adopted, consideration was given to the nroposalthat it should be left to the assessing authorities, subject to jndicial review, to determine the nereentao-c of the defined net receipts which should be taken as the valuation for rating purposes and that the clause should direct that neither the assessing authorities nor the appellate tribunals should be bound by the decisions or practice of the past.All parties were agreed that there should be a fresh start with a free hand to make a fair determination as to what percentage of the net receipts should, under the conditions now existing, be taken as the hypothetical rental value and that each side should be free to use any argument bearing iiijon this fair determination before the assessing authorities and the appellate tribunals. It was, therefore, suggested that the directing clause should be so drafted as best to secure these ends.On the assumption that the &quot; Profits Principle &quot; was to rule, this suggestion was, after full discussion, accepted by all parties.The National Conference of Assessment Committees have not, however, waived their view that other methods might legitimately be employed in determining the valuation of a railway undertaking.VIIL Apportionment between England and Scotland.   Two formulae proposed by the Scottish representatives were discussed; one had relation to the return upon the capital as allotted under the amalgamation awards, the other to the ratio between the net receipts of English and Scottish Companies, respectively, in the years 1913 and 1922, taken together.The Scottish representatives, when asked which they would prefer, announced that they had agreed to recommend the second. It appeared that agreement had nearly been reached on this, but the Representatives of the Municipal Corporations&apos; Association of England urged that if any basis of apportionment is prescribed it should be in accordance with the Report of the Departmental Committee, dated 10th November 1922, on the valuation for rating of amalgamated railways situated partly in England and Wales and partly in Scotland.It was pointed out that it was desirable to know at what stage the apportionment was to be applied before considering the formula, and that a formula which was appropriate for dividing net receipts might not be appropriate for dividing a valuation total.It appeared that the formula had been discussed between the English and Scottish Local Authorities&apos; representatives in connection with a division at the initial stage, viz., Net Receipts, that nil tin- English representatives were of opinion that this is the stage at which the division should be made, and that the Scottish representatives would be content to apply it either at this stage or after the division as between landlord and tenant had been effected, provided the clause designed to give a new start for determining tenanfs share unbound by decisions and practice of the past extended to Scotland.When the railway representatives were asked if they had any views on the matter, Sir Francis Dimnell said that Mr. Payne wished to make a submission. Mr. Payne&apos;s point was that, as tenanfs capital could now only be valued as a whole, he regarded it as necessary that tenanfs share should also be dealt with as a whole.Major Barnes stated in reply that for the purpose of any argument based upon the valuation of tenanfs capital the formula adopted for dividing net receipts might also be used for dividing tenanfscapital.And Mr. King, the Scottish Assessor, assured the Conference that if he were given the net receipts tor Scotland he would be able to determine the valuations of the Scottish portions without serious difficulty.The Conference then proceeded to consider the formula as applicable to Net Receipts. After further discussion it was agreed that division on the basis of the ratio between the net receipts of 1913 and 1922 should rule for the first five years.It was understood that physical additions to the rateable hereditaments (or heritages) in either country are to be taken into account by the Joint Authority during these five years. Also that at the end of this period revision may be applied for by either side.IX. Apportionment between Rating Areas in England and Wales. It had been agreed (a) That the Railway Assessment Authority for England and Wales should be charged with the duty of propounding for submission to Parliament such scheme of apportionment as would in their opinion give the most equitable distribution.(6) That in considering such scheme the Railway Assessment Authority should be directed to have regard, amongst other relevant circumstances, to the existing distribution of railway values; and(c) That until such scheme is propounded and adopted by Parliament, apportionment in proportion to existing local values must be adopted, subject to adjustments rendered necessary by new hereditaments or additions&quot;to existing hereditaments.
X. Joint Authority for the Anglo-Scottish Railways.It was pointed out that if the division between England and Scotland were to be limited to a division of &quot; Net Receipts,&quot; the duties of the Joint Authority would be comparatively simple.   Both the English and the Scottish Local Authorities expressed the view that the matter could be dealt with by the English Authority acting jointly with the Scottish Assessor. Appellate Tribunal.The question how the Appellate Tribunal or Tribunals should be constituted was reserved for consideration by the Legal Authorities.XI. Powers of the Valuation Authorities to call for and to have access to Accounts, cfec-It had been agreed by the Representatives of the Local Authorities that the Railway Assessment Authority for Enoland and Wales and any Joint Authority should have statutory powers similar to those conferred upon the Scottish Railway Assessor by Section 26 of the Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Act, 1854.Sir Francis Dunnell stated that while the railway companies were prepared to give the Valuation Authorities full access to their books, accounts, vouchers, &amp;c, and also to give them such information in regard to the accounts as they might reasonably require, the railway companies desired to be protected from unreasonable or vexatious demands for figures or returns, the compilation of which might involve the companies in considerable labour and expense. He undertook to examine the section of the Scottish Act to which reference is made above, and to suggest, if necessary, a form of words which would be acceptable to the railway companies.APPENDIX.NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF ASSESSMENT COMMITTEE. Resolutions taken on the 4th December 1924, at the Meeting of the Railway Sub-Committee at the Connaught Rooms on points to be submitted to the Joint Conference at the Ministry of Health on the same day.1. We agree to a Valuation in Cumulo.2. We agree to a Central Assessing Authority on being satisfied as to its Constitution. 3. We agree to a Tribunal of a special character other than the Railway and Canal Commission. 4. We do not agree to the Central Assessing Authority and the Tribunal being undirected. 5. We agree to Valuation on the profits&apos; method subject to the following directions being given to the Central Assessing Authority and the Tribunal(a) That the Tenanfs pre-war Capital be taken at its pre-war value.(b) That the percentage allowances on the whole of the Tenanfs Capital does not exceed ten per cent.6. We do not agree to the inclusion in the Cumulo of Docks and Harbours. 7. We do not agree to the inclusion of canals.8. We agree to the inclusion of Works for the manufacture of Locomotives, Carriages and Wagons subject to such modifications as may be found necessary to make after consultation with the Authorities affected.APPENDIX II.THE RAILWAY COMPANIES&apos; ASSOCIATION. Rating and Valuation Bill. Comments and Suggestions of the Railway Companies on paragraph 5 (1) of the Intkoiutcttont to the Memorandum issued by the Ministry op Health.1. Definition of &quot; Raihvay Undertaking&quot; for the Purpose of Valuation. The expression &quot;railway undertaking &quot; shall, for the purpose of valuation, be all hereditaments used or occupied by a railway company, other than house and cottage property and other lands and premises let to tenants who pay rates thereon direct to local authorities.Some statutory provision will be necessary to divide station assessments for the purpose of licence duties and inhabited house duty.2. Application of the Profits Principle.-This should be by taking account No. 8 of I he hum of accounts and statistical returns as set out in Part I of the First Schedule of the Railway Companies&apos; Accounts and Returns Act, 1911, and utilising the net receipts arising from railway (including joint lines), omnibuses owned by the company, steamboats, canals, docks, harbours, wharves, hotels, refreshment rooms and dining cars, with the addition of lump sum tolls, and the rents other than those arising from house and cottage property and lands and premises let to tenants who pay rates thereon ill:vet to local authorities. From the resulting figure should be deducted an item representing the tenanfs share, namely, interest, profits, depreciation and risks on the capital value on the date of valuation of rolling stock, machinery, tools, stores, furniture, horses, and other equipment and floating cash provided to carry on the undertaking and to earn the receipts. The result will be the net cumulo valuation of the railway.If the valuation is made quinquennially it would appear to be the fairest method to take i lie average figures for the preceding five years so far as the accounts are concerned, as distinct from tenant \s capital, which should be on the latest figures.The first valuation will have to be on the basis of the last years accounts.It is, however, recognised that it may not be fair in certain cases to adopt the proposed method without modification.   The following points require special consideration: (a) Receipts from Steamboats.-The inclusion of the net receipts arising from steamboats is contrary to the existing law and is objected to by one of the principal railway i mipames.
C appendix III.DEFINITION OF &quot;RAILWAY UNDERTAKING&quot; SUGGESTED BY THE ASSESSOR OF RAILWAYS AND CANALS (SCOTLAND). With regard to the definition of the word &quot; Undertaking &quot; as applied to railways, the following is suggested for consideration, so far as Scotland is concerned ; although it could, mutatis mutandis, be applied also to England and Wales :-&quot; The word &apos; undertaking &apos; used in the Act 17 &amp; 18 Vic. cap. 91, Acts amending the same, and this Act, in relation to the valuation of railways situated in Scotland, shall mean (a) all lands and heritages belon ging to or leased by each railway company and all buildings and erections used as stations, offices, waiting rooms, platforms, loading banks, sheds, stores, stables, workshops, water-works, gasworks, electricity works, docks, harbours, basins, wharves, depots, sidings (situated on land owned or leased by each railway company, or on land as regards which a free and unrestrictedit is contended that such net receipts have never been brought into account for rating purposes arid to do so now would be contrary to the intentions of the Bill.(b) Renewal and Maintenance. Where any railway does not set aside a normal charge for maintenance, or provision is not made for full renewal, there shall be allowed in respect of such maintenance&apos;or renewal such sum as would represent a full normal charge.3   Method of Determining the Value of the Tenanfs Share. This should be done by taking the value the 31st December of the year preceding the cumulo valuation to be made of the present day cost to acquire the rolling stock, machinery, tools, stores, furniture, horses, and other equipment and floating ash provided to carry on the undertaking and to earn the receipts.   In Account No. 8, and by allowing on such valuation a percentage representing interest on capital, profits and depreciation, and risks, his an allowance in respect of tenanfs profit from receipts from traffic carried in wagons of private owners and various station receipts, such as lavatories, platform tickets, advertisements, &amp;e. the resulting sum should be deducted from the cumulo valuation.4 Formula for Apportioning the Total Rateable Value of the Undertaking among the Parishes concerned._rpjjg oumulo should be divided between the rating areas as under : (1) By taking out the annual value of the stations, works, docks, depots and other heredita-ments used in connection with the working, maintenance and renewal of the railway and rolling stock, and crediting such values to the areas in which such hereditaments are situate.(2) Thereafter dividing the remainder among the rating areas according to a formula based on the total vehicle mileage run on the whole railway, viz. : As the vehicle mileage run in the rating area is to the vehicle mileage over the whole system, so is the rateable value of the running line in the rating area to the total rateable value of the running line over the whole system.it will be well to have a statutory definition of what is to be included in the running line and whatin the stations.The &quot; Running Line &quot; assessment should cover not only the land and rails, but also the telegraph and telephone wires, signals, signal boxes, instruments and apparatus therein, and points and crossings in or connecting with the running lines.in Scotland the interest on stations and works is statutory, viz., 5 per cent, (see Section 22 of the Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Act, 1854, amended by the Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Amendment Act,. 1867, section 4). if the amount of Interest is to be laid down in the proposed Bill, the net annual value of the stations and works should be arrived at by taking a maximum of 4 per cent, on the value of the land, and a maximum of 5 per cent, on the value of the buildings in use and rateable machinery. It is pointed out that if a rigid scale of 4 per cent, on the value of the land and 5 per cent, on the value of the buildings in use and rateable machinery be laid down in the Bill an inequitable rating may or will result in the case of certain railway companies owning a large number of stations situated at short distances from each other and the values of which are at the maximum, costly power stations and sub-stations, subways and other indirectly productive works, since in such cases the application of the rigid scale might yield an assessment in excess of the cumulo value of the entire undertaking. It is therefore submitted that the Bill should lay down the principle that in cases of the nature above mentioned a sliding scale should be adopted in lieu of the 4 per cent, and 5 per cent, scales and that such scale should be so adjusted as to depend on and accord with the profits of the undertaking.(5) Provision for valuing Anglo-Scottish Railways by a Joint Authority and Apportionment of the Value between the two Countries having regard to Divergence of English and Scottish Law.  It is recommended that the law be so amended, that one valuation is made of each of the railways extending through the two countries; first crediting the annual value of the stations, works, docks, depots and other hereditaments used in connection with working, maintenance and renewal of the railway and stock to the areas in which such hereditaments are situate, and afterwards allocating in respect of the Scottish portion a lump sum which might be arrived at on the basis of vehicle mileage, or the net receipts of the undertakings as they existed in 1914.(6) Quarter Rating. Under the present system of rating the 75 per cent, relief enjoyed by Railway companies is confined to districts outside the Metropolis. This constitutes an inequality in rating and is one of those anomalies which the present Bill (the object of which as pointed out in the Memorandum is to remove anomalies inherent in the present system) should seek to remove, since the reasons for granting such relief apply with at least equal if not more force to the areas within the Metropolis as to those areas outside london. it is therefore submitted that Part ii and the Second Schedule of the Bill ought to be amended and such necessary provisions be inserted inthe Bill so as to extend to the areas situated within -london the relief proposed to be given by the Bill by way of reductions in lieu of quarter rating to areas outside the Metropolis.
right of user has been conferred) and all other buildings, erections, and places of business used lor the traffic purposes of such company, or in connection with the management, maintenance, or workino- of the railway or any part thereof, and (b) all lands, buildings, erections, privileges and others Fet within or adjoining to or abutting upon any of the works hereinbefore mentioned, and used for the convenience of persons using the railway (including such fixed or assessable erections as may be placed thereon by occupiers), the following subjects, amongst others, being held to come under&apos;this interpretation, namely, tea rooms, confectionery stalls, fruit or flower stalls, book-stalls, tobacco stalls, and hairdressing or bath rooms ; also cabstands, advertising spaces, storage ground in depots or yards, also warehouses, stores, sheds, offices, stables, and the slopes of railways; but declaring that the said word &apos; undertaking &apos; shall not include any canal, ferry, hotel, licensed refreshment rooms, dwelling-house or garden or other accommodation occupied m connection therewith -nor shall it include offices* or places of business5&quot; leased and occupied by any railway company,&apos;as separate subjects, and used as booking or goods or parcel receiving offices, or as stables, or for any like purpose, where such are not situated within or adjoining to the undertaking as hereinbefore defined.*APPENDIX IV.RATING AND VALUATION BILL. Conference on Railway Valuations.A comparison between &quot; tenanfs share&quot; in England and Wales and &quot; tenanfs allowances&quot; in Scotland, expressed as percentages of &quot; net receipts &quot; arrived at on the same basis.This memorandum and the accompanying table are circulated, with all necessary reserves, as an assistance to discussion with a view to agreement being reached as to the percentage which the rateable value of the railways should bear to their net receipts, or, in other words, the percentage of the net receipts which should be regarded as the tenant&apos;s share. It might be possible to fix a figure which would apply-to all four groups or to fix different figures for each group. In the case of the Anglo-Scottish groups the same percentage might be fixed to apply over the two groups, or a different percentage for each group ; or, in either case, one percentage might be fixed for that part of the railway undertaking which is situated in England and another for that part which is situated in Scotland.A table is enclosed showing the rateable values as at 1st April, 1914, of the hereditaments in England and Wales belonging to the four amalgamated railway companies (excluding &quot; J &quot; Joint Lines), together with the aggregate net receipts for the year 1913 of the English companies. The notes attached to the table sufficiently explain the basis of compilation. The percentage of rateable value to net receipts over the whole of the hereditaments in England and Wales belonging to the four amalgamated railway companies (excluding &quot; J &quot; Joint Lines) is 42-38 per cent, and the percentages for each group are as follows : Southern 45-03 per cent.Great Western - - - - - - -   45 - 84London Midland and Scottish (former English companies only) -   39-74      ,,London and North Eastern (former English companies only). - -   42 - 36      ,,Owing to the differences in the rating law and practice of the two countries, it is not possible to make a comparison between rateable values in England and Wales and gross yearly values in Scotland, but if it be assumed that &quot; tenanfs share &quot; in England and Wales is the complementary figure to &quot; rateable value &quot; in relation to &quot; net receipts,&quot; as shown in the table under alternative definitions of the under-taking to be valued, a comparison between &quot; tenanfs share &quot; in England and Wales and &quot; tenanfs allowances &quot; in Scotland can be made.On this assumption the &quot; tenanfs share &quot; of the four amalgamated railway companies as at 1st April, 1914, expressed as a percentage of &quot; net receipts &quot; is as follows : Southern - - - - - - - - 54 - 97 per cent.Great Western - - - - - - - 54-16London Midland and Scottish (former English companies only) - 60-26      ,,London and North Eastern (former English companies only) - 57-64      ,,Average for the four groups     - - - - - - 57-62      ,,The &quot; net receipts &quot; for the Scottish portions of the two Anglo-Scottish railways for the year 1913, arrived at on the same basis, and the &quot; tenanfs allowances &quot; in respect of the valuations based on the account of that year, are as follows : 	&quot;Net Receipts.&quot;	&quot; Tenanfs Allowances.&quot;	Percentage of &quot; Tenanfs Allowances &quot; to &quot; Net Receipts.&quot;London Midland and Scottish (former Scottish companies only)..... London and North Eastern (former Scottish coinpanies only)..... Totals -	  3,197,451 2,575,924	  2,482,978 1,942,937	77 - 66 per cent. 75-43 76-66	5,773,375	4,425,915	*Note. It is to be understood, of course, that the annual values of the subjects here referred to sli be deducted from the valuation in cumulo of each of the amalgamated Railways of which they form pa This,is necessary in order to prevent the occurring of any double assessment.
239In the Report of the Committee the percentage of &quot; tenanfs allowances &quot; is given as 70 per cent and a word of explanation as to the apparent discrepancy between this and the figures which appear in the hist preceding paragraph is perhaps desirable. A reference to Appendix 2 of the Report in which a comparison is made between the systems of valuation followed in England and Scotland, will show that the deductions made from gross receipts to arrive at the respective valuations are relatively less in Scotland than in England. For example, the whole cost of the maintenance and renewal of permanent way is deducted in England, whereas only half of such cost is deducted in Scotland - and only about 5S per. cent, of the local rates (the occupier&apos;s share) is deducted in Scotland as compared with the total rates in England, where the whole is paid by the occupier. The net receipts therefore arrived at by the Assessor for valuation purposes are greater than the net receipts shown above and the per-eentage of tenanfs share to the former will be less than to the latter. The figures in the table and in this statement (subject to all necessary reserves as to their accuracy) afford a fair comparison of the actual position in England and Scotland respectively, without regard to the adjustments which would be necessary to give practical effect to the existing differences in the valuation and ratino- laws of the two countries.For a detailed note of the basis of calculation of tenanfs shares in the two countries reference is made to the statement at pages 41-42 of the Report.CORRECTED STATEMENT.Rateable Values as at 1st April, 1914, of the Hereditaments in England and Wales belonging to the Four Amalgamated Railway Companies (excluding &quot; J &quot; Joint Lines), together with the Aggregate Net Receipts for the Year 1913 of the English Companies.Aggregate Figures for Companies Constituting the Amalgamated companies in-Group 1. (Southern Railway.Rateable Value at 1st April, 1914.Net Receipts, 1913.Group 2. (Great Western Raihvav.)Rateable Value at 1st April, 1914.Net Receipts, 1913.Group 3. (London Midland &amp; Scottish Railway.)Rateable Value at 1st April, 1914.Net Receipts, 1913.Group 4. (London &amp; North Eastern Railway.)Rateable Value at 1st April, 1914.Net Receipts, 1913.Total for the Four Amalgamated Companies.Rateable Value at 1st April, 1914.Net Receipts, 1913.Railway Lines Stations, &amp;c. Electric Light and Power WorksRailway (including Electric Light and PowerWorks)     -Oranibusesand other Passenger Vehi-cles not running on the Railway (Motor Garages, &amp;e.) -      -      .Steamboats (Marine Premises) -Canals -Docks,    harbours and Wharves Hotels and Refresh-meat Rooms Other    separateBusinesses -Estate    Tenanciesnot    separatelyAssessed   -1,S0S,24G 567,9882,8342,370,0082-1908 10352,853 18,9352,44-8,9515,133,535110Dr.103, 24.70030 103.55G9782975,438,3032,200,949 000,07014,7911,941,810.607105 4,221329,47S14,7508,3023,299,3390,503,74911,535Z)r.27,714 Dr.14,213657,304 00,3307,196,9914,085,372 1,598,10819,1265,702,6663465,727 30,31904,03878,1873,2415,884,5243,060,449 1,188,4004,63514,510,439Dr. 4,48512,916 40,732Dr. 3,659247,9943,8784,259,484927,859 175,459 29,86614,807,815;4,472,76010,050,440Dr. 2,81863,461 -Dr. 11,938349,039110,52510,558,70911,218,016 4,020,62041,386115,280,0281,0696,860 42,502621,828141,7443,2418,30236,198,1634,302164,693 14,4181,166,240449,8274,17516,105,57438,001,818iSOTKS. (a) The figures of rateable values are taken from returns specially furnished by the railway companies, and do &quot;not include the rateable values of &quot; J &quot; Joint Lines.   The divisions of values between railway lines and stations are, in many instances, based upon estimates! (6) The figures of net receipts are taken from the Railway Returns for the year 1922, page 15, after excluding &quot; J &quot;Joint Lines and Scottish railway companies, and include lines in Scotland owned by the English companies,but not lines in England owned by the Scottish companies, (c) Apart from (6) the rateable values and the net receipts under the respective headings may not be strictlycomparable, as, e.g., net receipts of hotels and refreshment rooms include the net receipts of dining carswhich are reflected in the railway valuation.   It must further be borne in mind that the &quot; railway &quot;valuations reflect certain &quot; below the line &quot; income [e.g., lump sum tolls) not shown in net receipts fromrailway working (A/c No. 10).The figures are circulated with all necessary reserves, as an assistance to discussion.
APPENDIX V.Section 26. Valuation of Lands (Scotland) Act, 1854.Assessor of railway and other companies may summon witnesses and call for detailed statements as to revenues, &amp;c, of companies, and for books and writings, etc. : and if such statements, &amp;c, are refused, the right of appeal shall be forfeited.26. For the purpose of making the valuations of the lands and heritages of railway and canal and other companies by the assessor of railways and canals under this Act, it shall be lawful for such assessor of railways and canals to require the attendance before him of any persons as witnesses, and to examine such witnesses on oath, and also to call from time to time upon any railway or canal or other company to be included in his valuation for detailed statements of the yearly revenue of its undertaking, distinguishing the different sources thereof, and the amount derived from each such source and also, in the case of railways and canals, of the cost as aforesaid of each of its stations, wharfs, docks, depots, counting-houses, and other houses and places of business (including the solum on which such stations and others are erected), and also of the parishes, counties, and burghs in which such stations, wharfs, docks, depots, counting-houses, and other houses and places of business are severally situated, and of the lineal measurement of the. whole, any, each, and every part of its line, and to call for production from time to time of any books, vouchers, or other writings in the possession of any railway or canal or other company relating to or bearing upon any matters aforesaid, or to or upon the subject of the inquiries of such assessor under this Act; and if any such company, or its manager or secretary, or the chairman of its board of directors, all for the time beiiif, shall wilfully refuse or delay to furnish any such statements, or to make any such production,&apos; when required by the assessor of railways and canals as aforesaid, such company shall not be entitled to appeal against or object to the valuation of such assessor of railways and canals for the year in which such refusal or delay takes place, anything in this Act to the contrary notwithstanding.

</content>
</cab>
