<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/173/0 images: 1293-1300</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
788jT,g DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANHIO- MAJESTY * S GOVERNMENT.0- A B I H E T.SECRET.                               SCOTTISH    OILS   LIMITED. %,AC.P. 275/25, --------.......--------- $ UMEMORANDUM BY THE PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OP TRADE *-I have now obtained full information as to the position of the Scottish Shale Oil Companies from their accounts ffcr the year ending 31st March, 1925 whioh have now been completed, and the facts are as follows1.     Scottish Oils Limited own the ordinary shares in I six Scottish Shale Oil Companies with whom the admiralty had a contraot for the supply of 30*000 tons of oil per annum at  18 a ton whioh expired on the 31st March, 1925, i The contract was entered into in 1920 *     The current market price of similar oil has now fallen to about  6 a ton and the Companies estimate that they derived from this contract during the year ended 31st March, 1925, a profit in excess of what they would have received from commercial sales amounting to  6 per ton or a total of  180,000*     The Companies now ask through Scottish Oils Limited for assistance to enable them to meet the position whioh has arisen owing to the termination of the Admiralty contraot and state that unless they can obtain such assistance from the Government they will be obliged to close down gradually the Shale Mines which they are operating.2.     A summary of the working results of the Bix I Companies furnished by SoottlBh Oils Limited shows profitsderived from the Shale operations of  120,470 before

oharging depreciation which is aaid to amount approximately to  80,000 a year.     In the event of temporary assistance being given for one year, the 3ix Companies would be prepared to waive temporarily charging depreciation and to base their case upon the estimated results of the oost of the current year&apos;s operations;    if however, a scheme of assistance extending over a longer period were devised the Companies would claim that depreciation should be taken into aooountt 3,     It is anticipated by the Companies that the profit (before Charging depredation) of  120,47o will be turned into a loss during the current year since (a) the Companies have now no contract with the Admiralty and (b) prioes for the commodities produoed by the Companies have fallen.On the other hand since the prioe of ooal has fallen there will be a saving under that head but the aggregate loss which the Companies foresee in 1925-26 based on current market prices is estimated at  93,000 before charging depreciation.Apart from the Companies shale operations and sales oftheir various products the Companies between them deriveprofits from the following sources, vlzs-  -Interest from investments of the Companies.....c* ...     27,60?Profit made at Vitriol Works ... 30,90 2fl &quot;on refining Persian Oil   28,856 87,365Less sundry deductions...... 6,867*   .  80 / 498
It will therefore be seen that the estimated loss on the shale   operations is covered within  13,000 by the separate revenue indioated above and the Companies have indicated that this margin of loss might conoeivably be wiped out if certain of the works were closed down, although that would necessitate dismissing a number of workmen.     In all the Companies employ over lo ,000 people.     Assuming the profit and Loss Account were balanced for the year 1925-26 without allowing for depreciation there still remain to be met interest on debentures  16,000 a year and dividends on preference shares a further  21,000*     Thus the estimated realised deficit is the measure of the above interest and dividend charges, viz,,  37,000 per annum.The latest accounts of the six Companies made up to the 31st March, 1925, give the following particulars1,    Aggregate net profits (after chargingdepreciation)       122,2252*    Various Reserves ...  ...   ...   ...  ...        418,000 540i225Against these reserves there are various loans and investments aggregating  719,000*     The turnover for the six Companies Is estimated for the year ended 3lst March, 1926, based on ourrent prioes at  1,958,907&apos; without any contract with the Admiralty.With a turnover of the magnitude of praotically  2,000.000 and a balance of profit and Loss and Reserves of  54o,000 (fully oovered by investments) it cannot be said that the present financial position of the combined
Companies is unsatisfactory nor is the position one which the Companies themselves are not capable of taking care of. They ask, however, that they may receive assistance from tho Government and suggest that that assistance should be given by moans of a new contract to be entered into, with the Admiralty at prices in excess of current market prices and they state that unless they receive assistance they will certainly close down the shale mines although the process of closing would be gradual and would depend on prices *     They say that if prices became worse the closing down would be rapid while If prices improved only a portion of the works would be closed down for the present.     Certain of the works are clearly not producing a profit and apart from the question of creating unemployment would no doubt be closed down,Soottish Oils Limited on behalf of the six Companies have now proposed that they should be assisted by a Contract for delivery at Companies * works in one of the following forms:-L For a quantity of 110*000 to 120/000 tons ofShale Oil Fuel per annum for a period of (say) 10 years at  6* 5, o. per ton,2* For 6o,000 tons of shale Oil Fuel per annum for 5 years at  8, 7. o per ton,3, For 30^000 tons of Shale Oil Fuel per annum for 5 years at  11, 5, o per ton,4. For 6o,000 tons of Shale Oil Fuel for one year at. 7 per ton.In the oase of proposals (\),  (2) and (3) the contracts are Intended to wipe out the anticipated loss of  93,000 for the current year and to provide for d,epreoiation, thus keeping intact the whole of the Company&apos;s accumulated reserves.     The Companies say that they would be prepared
to agree that, in the event of&quot; profits from shale being realised by the Companies, 5o% of such profits -should be applied to reduoe the price to be paid under the contract down to a minimum of  5 per ton.     On the other hand, the Companies would require to be froe to reduce or cancel the quantity of oil to be delivered in the event of losses being incurred without taking depreciation into consideration.Proposal (4) is put forward as a temporary arrangement and is designed to cover only the anticipated loss of  93,000 for the current year, without making any provision for depreciation, and in this case there would be no profit-sharing scheme and no option for the company to cancel any part of the oil contracted for,The Company have put forward their proposals in the form of an Admiralty contract.     They were asked to put them in the form of the minimum oash payment which would enable (or induce-) them to oontinue the whole, or alternatively 8 out of 12 of their mines and works,     They have not done this,     But converting the proposed prices into oash subsidy, the subsidy asked over the approximate present price of  5*10*0 per ton of gas oil appears to be approximately as follows:-1,     90*000  *.*  ...  *o*  *&apos;* p$at for lo years e  171,000  , *,   , t ,  o.,  ...   ... f o r    5    &quot;3.  172,500..............    &quot;      for    5    &quot;4.     90*000        for     one     year.It is olear from the figures given in the first part of this memorandum that the Companies have resources whioh would enable them to continue their business if they desired to do so, and, If all sources of revenue are brought into aocount, the cash 103s on the current year would be very small.The Companies desire, however,  to be protected by government assistance against losses on the shale oil part-&apos;-5-
of their business, while retaining their other sour*ee of profit, and they say that In the event of such assistance not being forthcoming they will olbse down part at any rate of the shale mines and works.It ie diffioult to forecast what steps the Companies will actually take, but I am inclined to think that if assistance ie refused they will close a part of their mines and works forthwith and retain the more profitable part in operation for the present until they can aee more definitely the probable oourse of prices of their produote.As the Admiralty are not anxious to obtain the Companies&apos; oil at present, and do not attach any considerable importance to keeping the mines In existence, the only &apos;ground for giving assistance is to prevent the serious unemployment whioh would be caused by the closing of the mines and works.     I think however that it would be diffioult to justify giving suoh assistance to companies In the comparatively satisfactory financial position of these undertakings as compared with that of    undertakings in other Industries, particularly the analogous case of coal mines.     As I explained to the Cabinet, I feel the greatest difficulty in agreeing to any proposal upon which the coal-mining Industry could found a claim to a subsidy.     The only ground on whioh the Government oould justify a subsidy to the Shale mines would be that the Government were using part of their profits in the successful Anglo-Persian venture to relieve distreos in another under-taking In which they are also interested and whioh forms part of the larger enterprise.P+ 0,-1,.    iBoard of Trade,3rd June, 1925*
SOUTH-EASTERN EUROPE /^^S-^^^ [May ^ L925 ] CONFIDENTIAL. 2 ? &amp;     (25^*)   Section 1&apos;[C 7237/798/19] No. 1.M emorandum.ONE of the reasons, and the most important, given by the S.C.S. Government for denouncing the Grasco-Serbian Treaty of Alliance in November 192f4, was the handicap imposed ^ upon their export trade by the incompetent management of the Salonica-RELATIONS BETWEEN SERBIA AND GREECE.I CIRCULATE a memorandum, prepared in the Foreign Office in reply to an enquiry of mine.The policy which I propose to follow is to hold as much aloof as possible from this dispute, and, if it becomes acute, to endeavour to make it a League question ; not one for individual action by this country.If any of my colleagues consider that the future of Salonica or the other questions involved require closer examination, I suggest that the papers should be referred to the Committee of Imperial Defence.(Initialled) A. C.Foreign Office, May 26, 1925.[963 y 1]in tnis connection itis worth while to quote from a minute by Mr. Nicolson on a conversation which he had with M. Veniselos on the 24th January last: &quot; I asked what the Greek Government would do supposing one of the first conditions made by the Serbs for tho renewal of this treaty was that this option should be surrendered, and the Serbian hold on the railway formally recognised. M. Veniselos said that this was a point on which the Greeks would never surrender; nor did he think the Serbs would raise it, since M. Nincic had said nothing to him about the railway when they met in Paris. I said that none the less I felt pretty certain that the Serbs would raise the point, and the Greeks might find themselves faced with the alternative of losing either their railway or their treaty. M. Veniselos looked glum, and murmured something about Greece not being a vassal of Serbia.&quot;This almost exactly defines the stage negotiations have now reached in Belgrade. The Serbs, besides claiming control of the railway, have also advanced a demand for the enlargement of the free zone at Salonica by on area of 38,000 square metres. This latter proposal is also one which the Greeks say they cannot possibly entertain.The Serbs are quite clearly in the strongest position 1. Because  they know what they want, Le., Salonica, or the control of theGhevgeli line as a means to that end. 2. Because they know that, although it is a matter of comparative indifferenceto them, the renewal of the treaty is of paramount importance to Greece. 3. Because there is a suspicion amounting almost to certainty, that they haveItaly behind them. &apos;With regard&apos;to the demand for an extension of the free zone&apos;, it is not likely that it was put forward with an idea of its being used as a counter-weight with which to bargain for the control of the railway. [963 y-1]

</content>
</cab>
