<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/173/0 images: 1338-1341</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
o 9 r.......... OfcJj3^E 0 RIf.COmiXTTBB OH THE EFFECT OF TBE IflOKEASE Off ,THE DEATH PuTIJiS ON ASRIOITIffuBilL INTERESTS,REPORT.I. At their meeting on May 28th.  1925 (Cabinet&quot; 27 (25)Conclusion..l), the Cabinet agreed that a Committee composed ofThe Chancellor of the Exchequer    (in the Chair),The Rome Secretary,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The Minister of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries4.The Secretary for Scotland,,The First Commissioner of Works -should consider the question of the effect of the arrangementsincorporated in the Finance Bill for the increase of death-duties and the relief of super-tax on agricultural Interests,with a view,  if possible, to some alleviation of those interests.,2c      The tncreased; rates, of Estate Eftity   proposed, for par-ticulars of which see Appendix, affect all estates betweenthe limits of  12,500 and  1,000,000*      The total increasedyield of the Estate Duties is estimated at  10,000,000orin a full year of which approximately one-fifteenth        ,sayas 600.000 per annum may be regarded/attributable to land used for agricultural purposes, some of which of course&apos; possesses a prospective building value.3. The Committee have examined various proposals,for relieving agricultural     owners;   of the burden of theincreased Estate Duties.      Certain proposals are impracticable on account of their great cost*      The suggestion of the Land Union that for duty purposes estates should be valued on the
expenditure on maintenance is open, amonf other objections,to tho fatal criticism that it would confer the preatest benefit in those cases where tho land owner has been in a position to expend large suras on maintenance and would give little or no relief in those cases v/hero the owner has been unable through poverty to improve his property,      The Committee have also considered a scheme for giving remission of Estate Duty in respect of the capital agricultural value of land, the remission to take- the form either of b flat rate of deduction (say 20$) from the duty,,  or of a differential scale of reductions under which in any particularestate the larger tho proportion of the value of the agricultural land to tho value of the estate as a whole, the higher would be the rate of relief given-      Fhile a scheme on the second of these lines would have the advantage of helping those cases where the need is greatest, the Committee feel that the scheme must necessarily involve additional complications which it is very desirable, if possible, to avoid and that it would bo preferable to adopt a scheme in which the relief is more closely allied to the additional burden whioh the Budget has imposed.unanimously in favour of a proposal that the increased rates of Estate Duty proposed in the Finance Bill shall not be applicable to tho capital agricultural value of agricultural land which will accordingly remain chargeable at the old. rates, this concession will only affect what is purely agricultural value and will not be extended to any element in the value of land used for agricultural purposes which may be due to suitability for building.      Moreover it is not proposed that the concession should operate so as to reduce the aggregate value of an estate for the purpose of ascertaining the proper rate of duty.      It is estimated that the concession will cost about  500,000 per annum herein after  careful consideration, the Committee are
a full year, an amount which tho Chancellor of the Exchequer is willing to provide.    The plan will only necessitate theaddition of a brief clause in the Finance Bill and itsfew-administration will present-   -* difficulties,,The Committee accordingly recommend tho Cabinot -To authorise the addition to tho Finance  , Bill of a provision exempting the capital agricultural value of agricultural land from the increased rates of Estate Duty and subjecting such land to duty at the old rates.      The concession not to apply to any element in the value of agricultural land which may be due to suitability for building and not to operate so as to reduce the aggregate value of an estate for the purpose of ascertaining the proper rate of duty.Signed on behalf of the Committee,&apos;&quot;rII3ST01T S.  CHURCHILL. Chairman,Tre a su ry Ch a mb e rs , 9th June,  1925.
APPENDIXESTATE. DUTY, - ALTERATION OP SCALE.Principal Value of EstateRate per oent for each range,Present KatesProposed Katesisoee15 10 12 15 18 21 25 30 35 40 45 50 55 65 75 85 100 120 140 170 200 250 325 400 500 750 1,000 1.250 1,500 ;?,000ding :*  !100 i500 j 000,000 I,000 !,500 I,&apos;boo I000 I ,000 !,000 ,000 ,000 ,000 .000 &apos; 000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000Not Exceeding   500 000 ,000 000 500 000 000 ,000 000 000 000 ,000 000 000 000 ,000 000 000 000 ,000 000 000 000 000 000 000 000 000 000 000 000 0001,5, 10,.12,15,18,121,25,30,35.40&apos;45.&apos;50;55; 65, 75, 85, 100,120;140. 170, 200, 250, 325, 400, 500, 750. 1,000,. 1,250, 1,500, 2.000.	1		1	2		2	3		3	4		4	5		5	5		6	6		76	and	7	8	7		9	8		10	9		11	9		12	10		13	10		14	11		1511	and	12	1612	and	13	17	13		1813	and	14	1914	and	15	2015	and	16	2116	and	17	2217	and	18	2319	and	20	2421	and	22	2522	and	23	2624	and	25	2726	and	27	2827	and	28	29	30		30	32		32	35		35	40		40Increase in rate per cent\JNo change	1		1	1	or	2	2		2		2		3		3		4		4	4	or	54	or	5	5	5	or	65	or	65	or	65	or	65	or	64	or	53	or	43	or	42	or	31	or	21	or	2No change

</content>
</cab>
