<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 13-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic  Majesty/s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.  February  1918.SECRET.G.T.-3502.THE  LABOUR  SITUATION.Report from the Ministry of Labour for the week ending the 30th January, 1918,                                  Summary.Part I: General Remarks.    Agitation among the  engineers on the question of man-power proposals,  andthe Labour Conference at Nottingham are discussed.Part II: Press Comments.    The chief matters engaging the attention of the  Labour press have been theman-power proposals and the food question.Part III:  District Reports.    Widespread agitation on the subject of man-power is  reported from almostevery district.Part IV:  Disputes.    (a.) Involving Stoppage. Strikes on the  Clyde have  ended,  and  the mostserious strike in progress is that among bricklayers in  South Wales.    (6.) Not involving Stoppage: The 12^ percent, award still continues to causetrouble. The most serious dispute is one upon the question of a standard rate forwoodworkers on aircraft in London  and elsewhere.                            I. General Remarks.Labour and Man-Power.    Indications  abound that  the opposition to the man-power  proposals  of theGovernment is intense only among the younger members of the A.S.E.  The agitation,in so  far as it is organised by Labour as. opposed to  the I.L.P.  and its confreres,appears to be oonfined to members of the A.S.E., whether openly or under the guiseof a movement of shop stewards.   The meeting at the Albert Hall on Sunday lastwas definitely a  meeting  of members of the A.S.E.  On Friday the 25th a meetingof the National Administrative Council of Shop Stewards and Workers&apos; Committees.was held at Manchester.  The list of delegates has been received.  They are, withoutexception, members, of the A.S.E.  At  that meeting Smillie (junior), who  presided,expressed the opinion that there would be a strike on  man-power on the Clyde,but he did not think it would be  successful from the point  of  view of  the  shopstewards.    On the following day the Metal, Engineering,  and Shipbuilding AmalgamationCommittee held  a rank and  file conference at Manchester, in which  opposition tothe man-power proposals was expressed.  Again the great majority of representa-tives were members, of the A.S.E., and even so the resolution was  not unanimous.    Information received justifies a conclusion that the attitude of the A.S.E. and itsassumption.of superiority are much resented by the other unions, and that the feelingof hostility is growing. It is  improbable that the man-power proposals are populareverywhere,  but  a feeling of loyalty to the nation exists  generally,  and  it is beingfortified  by  the opposition of what is  termed &quot;the autocratic union.&quot;  So high is      [1100-14]                                                     B
 this feeling that it is quite possible that active hostility by the A.S.E. (which may be anticipated as so probable as to be a practical certainty) will actually rally the rest of the Labour world to the support of the Government.     On the other hand, it  has to be  recognised that the A.S.E. is united on the question.  Many of the older men are wholeheartedly in favour of  the national aims, but they have been united with the younger members by the slight which they think has been put on their society by the Government.     It. is not likely that a strike of the engineers, against the weight of popular opinion and conviction, could be other than unsuccessful, but  there is no doubt that the &quot;revolutionary &quot;  section  is  very  active,  intelligent,  and well organised. A good deal of treason is being talked,  and the idea of &quot; peace by negotiation&quot; is making  headway, induced  largely by the mental apathy resulting from war- weariness.  Some of the leaders are talking very big, and appear  prepared to go to extreme lengths, and in the general atmosphere of sentimentality  and unreason which is prevalent at the moment, the Russian Revolution has awakened much wider echoes than would have been the case at a time when men&apos;s minds were not  unbalanced by the strain of the prolonged war conditions, and were more capable of seeing the facts in their true light. It would  be rash to venture any prophecy as to wdiat will happen. The Government has to a large extent lost its authority in the eyes of the workers, and there is a general impression that it is bound to obey their demands.   Drastic action to restore authority may succeed or may provoke a really serious situation. The Labour Party Conference.     In so far as  the proceedings of  the Conference  at Nottingham  represented a struggle between the  combined  forces  of  the pacifists,  the  I.L.P.,   and  the revolutionaries on the one side,  and orthodox trade union forces  oni the other, its results  may be deemed a victory for the orthodox and loyal  party.   It cannot be doubted that those results are a disappointment to the I.L.P., which  had based the most extravagant  hopes on the excitement and the  revolutionary atmosphere of the proceedings of the first evening.   The enthusiasm of the reception  of MM. Litvinoff and Longuet, and the comparative coolness which greeted  M. Vandervelde  and M. Renaudel are stated to have  been marked, and there can be little  doubt that on Tuesday evening, after the reception of the foreign delegates, the extremists believed that they had captured the Conference.     In  the end, however, their disappointment was pronounced, and the majority, mainly  consisting  of  miners  and textile workers, cautiously refused  to accept the proposed immediate  amendment of the  constitution  of the  party.    In  similar fashion, but  by a much more important  majority, the resolution condemning t,he participation of Labour in the Coalition Government was defeated.   It is clear from the general  trend of  the Conference  that extremist views, though held  by many individuals,  especially among the younger men, and largely by  members of the Con- ference  who have no claim  to be there  as representatives of manual labour, are not accepted by the mass of the  working classes.    There was,  however, a plain intention on the part of the Labour Party to attempt to sweep-the polls at the next election, and a certain confidence is manifested in the probable success of the attempt.    On the question of peace  the Conference was indeterminate, though Mr. Arthur Henderson&apos;s somewhat cryptic phrase  &quot;a people&apos;s  peace&quot; was  much in evidence.With the decision to  hold an inter-xYllied Labour Conference as a preliminary toa. proposed &quot; International&quot;  in Switzerland, it is impossible to  quarrel.  Whetheran &quot; International &quot;  would be as welcome to the  German  Government now  as  theproposed Stockholm Conference was last summer may  well be questioned.                             II. PRESS COMMENTS.    The Labour Party Conference did not conclude sufficiently early to receive com-plete treatment in the Labour and Socialistic press.Man-Power.    The question  of  &quot;man-power  &quot;  has perhaps,  however, attracted  even moreattention than  that of the Labour  Party Conference, and the comment is  hardlyreassuring.
     The  extremist  papers  are  openly adverse  to any further recruitment.   The &quot; Labour Leader,&quot;  for example,  asserts that numbers  who  supported the earlier conscription acts are now  hostile, and attributes this to the   disappearance of enthusiasm &quot; and the &quot;hopelessness  of miltary; victory.&quot;  The &quot;Herald&quot; thinks that a &quot; storm is brewing,&apos;&apos;&apos;  and  in describing the  agitation which is taking place, remarks significantly that the &quot; influence of the Russian  Revolution is becoming perceptible.&quot;   The &quot; Call &quot;  takes rather a different line, attacking Sir Auckland Geddes  for &quot; his effort  to  excite  the hatred and contempt of men in less vital industries.&quot;  It gives figures apparently with the object of proving that the British nation having  contributed seven  and a half million men has done all that can be expected of it.  The &quot; South Wales  Pioneer &quot; is  more moderate than usual,  and argues that the chief causes  of the Bills undoubted unpopularity are the  Govern- ment&apos;s refusal to take dilutees first and its further refusal to begin peace negotiations immediately.  The &apos;&apos; Leeds Citizen &quot;  regards the new Bill as the logical outcome of all the previous war legislation, which has been directed against the working classes; &quot; it removes the last  phase of protection from the workers.&quot;     The more  moderate section of the Labour press appears to be  in two minds, though the &quot; Woolwich  Pioneer &quot; has  flare  headlines asking  whether the &quot; con- tinuance of the war  is worth while.&quot;   The succeeding article is, however, merely a description of  the Woolwich mass meeting, which in  point of fact declared itself ready, if necessary, to go  through with  the war.  The  &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times &quot; predicts that Sir Auckland Geddes will have &quot; a job &quot; to get his men, but then goes on to express its sympathy for &quot; old service men &quot; who have to go back to the front. It would appear that these papers are rather afraid to commit themselves definitelyto either side.     The &quot; patriotic &quot; section has  much less to say  on the general subject than last week, but the &quot;  Clarion &quot; thinks that dilutees ought certainly to be combed out before the real pre-war worker. The Attitude of the Engineers.     The A.S.E. do not meet  with much sympathy in the attitude which they have adopted, except, perhaps, from such  papers as the &quot; Llerald,&quot;  and  even here  thewriter contents himself with a statement of the position.     The &quot; British Citizen &quot;  and the  &quot;  Clarion &quot; are very outspoken.  The former addresses &quot; a straight word to the A.S.E.,&quot; and the latter asks whether their attitude is not &quot; the negation of democracy.&quot;    The &quot; New Witness,&quot; on  the other hand, is afraid that the attitude of the A.S.E. is being misunderstood, and is confident that they are prepared to give the men, but are afraid to trust the Government. War and Peace.    Those of the pacifist papers which commended the Prime Minister &apos;s declarationof war aims have seemingly come to the conclusion that their policy wTas mistaken.    The Independent Labour Party papers denounce the later speech and answersto questions put by trade union delegates.  The &quot; Bradford Pioneer &quot;  finds them;&apos; utterly unsatisfactory &quot; in that he calls on the Germans to give up  everythingwhich they have won, without giving them back even a part of what they have lost.The &quot; Labour  Leader &quot;is very, frank about its attitude towards the earlier speech,which it welcomed only with the idea of &quot; exploiting the Prime Minister to gain anearly  democratic peace&quot; his last speech is  a reversion to the &quot;knock-out blowpolicy.&quot;   The &quot; Herald &quot; continues  to make  play with its new method of inter -rogative accusation, addressing a series of questions to  Mr.  Lloyd George with theobject of showing that he represents a reactionary &quot; section of the community,&quot; andproceeding to criticise the whole of his &quot; peace and war  record.&quot;    &quot; Justice &quot;  contains a declaration of &quot; war aims and peace terms &quot; on behalfof the National Socialist Party.  This is a skilful  piece of  work,  and makes agood point in  suggesting that dynastic government is much more out of date thancapitalism,  and should therefore be dealt with first.    The titles of various of the articles are suggestive of the state of mind of thoseresponsible  for  the  papers.  The  &quot;South Wales  Pioneer,&quot; for example, chooses&quot;The Peace Ahead,&quot; and the &quot; Yorkshire Factory Times,&quot;  &quot;Peace Near.&quot;
Food.    The food question continues to attract as much attention as any other topic.    All aspects are dealt with, but the three points which receive most attentionare profiteering in substitutes, which always occurs when there  is a shortage ofcontrolled  commodities  (this  point is  especially  emphasised by  the &quot; YorkshireFactory Times &quot;);  the queues, which are thought to have been more prevalent thanever;  and  Lord Rhondda&apos;s speech about &quot; grousing,&quot; which is  bitterly attackedby the &quot; Call  &quot;  and &quot; Herald.&quot;    With regard to the queues, &quot; John Bull &quot; thinks that they must lead to &quot; revolton the part of the  people,&quot; and the  &quot; Clarion &quot; complains bitterly of the  lack offoresight on the part of the  Ministry of  Food, which  is always &quot;going&quot; to dothings, but never does until the pressure of circumstances forces it to take hastyand ill-considered  action.                           III. DISTRICT REPORTS.London.    The unrest in the London area centres to a  large extent around the strike of&quot;Sheet Metal Workers upon the wages question, which is referred to in Section IV.    Great  hostility towards the Man-Power Bill  is   still  reported;  this  findsexpression  in a resolution demanding that the Government shall consider negotia-tions  for jDeace on a  basis of self-determination  of  all nations.  At a meeting ofthe Amalgamated Society of Engineers in the Albert Hall, however, this resolution-was followed by another, stating &quot; that  should action prove  German Imperialismto be  the only obstacle to peace, the workers would co-operate in  the prosecutionof the war.&apos;&apos;  This meeting, which was  so crowded that an overflow meeting hadto be held,  was addressed by pacifists like Robert  Smillie and&quot; Robert Williams.Failing the adoption of the first resolution, opposition to the Man-Power Bill wouldbe maintained.  A similar resolution was passed at a meeting at Woolwich on the20th.   A resolution  of woodworkers, on somewhat  more extreme lines,  demandedthat the Government should accept the Russian  basis for peace negotiations.    The food problem continues to be serious, but at Erith, where a strike occurredduring the week-end  before last, the situation is said to have improved.West Midlands.    In this district opposition to the Man-Power Bill seems  similarly to  be basedupon  a distinct feeling that peace is now possible, and that therefore the proposalsof  the Government are unnecessary.    Resolutions to this  effect were passed  by the Conference  of  the   NationalEngineering and Allied  Trades at Coventry, together with further resolutions tosecure unity of action in the event  of a strike policy being adopted.    At Birmingham, at a meeting concerned primarily with the  release of R.Wallhead,  discussion of  the man-power proposals developed on similar lines.   Onespeaker maintained  that proper proposals had not been placed before  Germany,and if such proposals were put forward, and rejected,  the  Trade Unions wereprepared to fight to the last man and shilling.    The 12^  per cent, award continues  to  attract considerable attention.   At ameeting held  at Smethwick it  was proposed that every worker over 21  years ofage should receive the bonus.   One speaker said  that if the affair  had rested withMr. Churchill every  worker would have had the advance.          [it.                                   \&quot;Yorkshire  and Midlands.     Opinion upon the question of man-power seems  in this district to be somewhatdivided.  At  Sheffield it is  stated that  not one  single man in  the  workshopshonestly desires enlistment, and among the  steam enginemakers opposition to theMan-Power Bill and support of the Clyde manifesto is advocated.    The Amalgamated Society of Engineers held  a meeting on Monday, at which itwras decided to oppose the Bill.  The women at Sheffield are said to be encouraging;the men in their attitude, and this is thought locally to be the result  of food queues.
     At Leeds, on&apos;the other hand, the feeling is more moderate.  The men in the shops have refused their delegates authority to vote for a resolution which accuses the Man-Power Bill of a deliberate attempt to crush Trades Unionism.   It is said that the Yorkshire members of the Amalgamated  Society of  Engineers  are on the whole against drastic action, and are prepared to remain at work.  Resolutions at an Amalgamated Society of Engineers&apos; meeting were,  however, passed recommend- ing no further dilution of labour, and no agreement between the Government and Trade Union executives without the consent of alL members.     At Nottingham the extremists are  expected to make a  determined effort for peace&quot;by means of a strike policy;  this tendency is no doubt aggravated  by  the acuteness of the food question, on account of which it is feared locally that rioting may shortly take place.     In general a certain distrust of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers seems prevalent.    Their action  towards other Trade Unions  and  the  Government is severely condemned.     The Society  of Steam Enginemakers  and Toolmakers  strongly  opposes  the domination of the &quot;Autocratic Union.&quot;     Strikes in the Doncaster area are threatened on account of the food question. and in Leeds anger is prevalent among the women at the failure of supplies. North-Western.     Opinion in this area seems to be growing more favourable to the Man-Power Bill.  The Barrow shop stewards desire proof that it is the Prussian Military Party the Government are out  to destroy.  In Manchester the Shop Stewards Workers&apos; Committee are stated to be of the opinion that a general strike is improbable.  A resolution was passed stating  that  &quot; this committee is not a  body to  deal with technical grievances arising out of the cancelling  of occupational exemption from military service, and must therefore leave such grievances to  be dealt with by the official organisations concerned.&quot;     It  is not at  all clear  whether this1 indicates lack  of support or  whether the extremists want to leave the tackling of a problem which is not likely to enhance anybody&apos;s prestige to the official unions.     The great food demonstration held at Manchester on the 26th  did  not prove the success that had been anticipated by its promoters.   Only  about 5,000  were present, owing to several of the unions backing out  at the  last moment.   The speeches of the Lord Mayor and Mr. Clynes, in reply to the manifesto which was issued, appear to have had  a good effect.North-Eastern.     The Amalgamated Society  of Engineers do not seem to be wholly agreed upon the man-power question.   All agree that the dilutees must be taken first, but while the Els wick Works consider the time inopportune for peace negotiations,  a New- castle branch of the A.S.E. criticises strongly the speech of  Sir A. Geddes, andvoices a suspicion that the war is prolonged by capitalist interest. Wales.     The food problem continues  to  be the most fertile cause  of unrest  in SouthWales.   Posters demanding equal treatment for rich  and poor and denouncingprofiteering have been distributed at Clydach.  The temper of the miners is growingugly, and it is to be hoped that a system of rationing will be enforced  before threatsof a general strike materialise.    A special conference of the South Wales  Miners&apos;  Federation  was  held  onMonday, and it was decided to take a ballot on  the Man-Power Bill throughout thecoalfields.  Resolutions denouncing the Bill have been carried by the extremists atMerthyr and elsewhere. Scotland.    The industrial position is much easier, but the Man-Power Bill continues toattract  considerable attention.  It is very difficult to judge the  situation, and theC.W.C. themselves appear to be apprehensive as to the amount  of support on whichthey can rely.       [1100-14]                                                     C
     They are making a determined effort to keep the  district committees  firm totheir original resolution, calling upon the Government to withdraw the Bill.     Smillie (junior), a leading shop steward, has stated that the situation was notnearly so bad as press reports suggested, and there is little  doubt that the  A.S.E.have aroused a good deal of hostile  feeling,     On the other hand the acute nature of the position is  attested by a demonstrationheld  under the  auspices of  the Russian  Revolution  Demonstration Committee  onSunday,  27th.  This meeting, which was attended by sonie 10,000 people, was littlebetter than a peace demonstration, and very  extreme   pacifist  resolutions  werecarried with acclaim.   The need  for really  effective  counter-propaganda  increasesas the weeks go by.                                    IV.  DISPUTES.(a.) Involving a stoppage of work.     The outstanding strike of riveters on the Clyde,  in which about 4,000 men  areemployed by as many as twenty-eight firms, has now come to an. end.           The trouble arose out of dissatisfaction with recent awards by the Committee on Pro-        duction, more&apos; especially that dealing with the riveting pricedist  on  standard and  ordinary        vessels.   The strike did not cease as quickly as was  anticipated last week, owing to the        refusal of  the men on the lower reaches of the river to accept a resolution to resume work        passed by those on &quot;the upper.  Eventually,  on the 25th, the men in the  lower reaches        agreed to return on the &quot;28th, having by their earlier opposition lost a Week&apos;s  work.           The settlement of this strike restores the industrial situation on the Clyde  to the normal,        though a staydn strike which followed the alteration of a premium bonus system at Messrs.        Barr and Stroud&apos;s js reported to have resulted in a lock-out.     Meanwhile at Belfast a. renewal  of the  strike of ironworkers at Harland andWolffs and Workman, Clark, and  Co.&apos;s, which  took  place  before   Christmas,has occurred.           A provisional  award in this case was issued by the  Committee on Production in Decem-        ber, but the men  had become impatient with the delay in issuing the main  award, though        other cases were in question.  On the 22nd  a mass meeting decided to &quot; down tools &quot; on        the succeeding day.   On the 23rd accordingly 4,000 men ceased  work.   On the following        day the award was received by telegram, and the men decided to accept it and return to        work  on Monday,  the 28th.     In addition  to these cases the  Shipyard Labour Department  has  ten  newcases  of strikes to report,  involving some 1,400 men.   This is  a figure additional tosixteen cases already reported, but of the total number in as many as twenty-two workhas been resumed.           Four  of  the  new strikes occurred in the Newcastle area,  but the most important of        these, involving some 650 men, only lasted for one day, being  due to the death of a workman        during the performance of  his duty.           A strike involving 1,100 employees of Messrs. Stothert and Pitt,  Bristol, took place on        the 19th, in order that the workers might take part in a food demonstration.   They complain        that their hours of work make it  impossible for them to purchase food.     The Ministry of Munitions reports four cases of strikes as having arisen out ofthe 12- - per cent, bonus; one of these still continues.           The most] important strike from the point of view of the output of munitions is that of        the bricklayers in  South  Wales, which, however, on the latest information,  shows marked        signs of weakening, and it is understood that a large number of men have returned to work.           A hot unimportant strike of women workers has taken place among the women ivtfrkcrs        at  Messrs. Firth and Sons, Sheffield, owing  to  the firm&apos;s omission to pay the increase in        wages  recently conceded;  1,600  were involved, and they returned to work on the 22nd on        receiving a definite. promise of the advance.  The local shop  stewards displayed an interest        in  the dispute, and it is thought that they  desire to secure  the sympathy  of the women        workers.  The action of  the Clyde  Workers&apos; Committee in connection with the East Hope        Street affair will be recalled.     The Coal Controller has six new stoppages to report,  the total number of meninvolved in the  strikes which have been in progress  during the week  being about8,000.           At the Brownlee Colliery (North Staffordshire) 1,200 have stopped work owing to  the        alleged difficulty in obtaining workmen&apos;s coal.  A stoppage also occurred at Low Laithes  in        lorkshire, as a protest against  the new recruiting scheme,  and a further  stoppage near
        Burnley  owing to food difficulties-this is a recurrence of the recent strike.  Ihe stoppage        at the OakMe Colliery, South Wales, which&apos; involves 14,000 men, arose  apparently  out        of sympathy with a man who had refused to unload a tram of rubbish.     The War  Office  Contracts Department has only one new ease of stoppage ofwork to report, and this arose out of the dismissal of  two trade union officials atMessrs.  Carrie and Sons,  Ilkeston.            The strike of labourers on aircraft work at Ainlree, which involved between 2,000 and        3 000 men,  came to an end on the 22nd, but the series of small strikes among sheet-metal        workers in&apos;the London district continues, and a slight extension has, m fact, taken place  a        deputation of the men are reported to have visited the Ministry  of Munitions, and pending      i  the result of this action the strike is expected to continue.(b.) Not involving a stoppage of work.     The total number of disputes not involving a stoppage of work reported by theShipyard Labour Department is 123.    Of these 31 are new cases and 15 have beensettled during the week.            The 12  per cent, award to piece and premium bonus workers on the Clyde is regarded        as unsatisfactory, and a stay-in strike is in progress at Messrs.  Weir&apos;s, Cathcart.            A dispute which may involve a serious strike of shipwrights is in progress at Armstrongs&apos;        Naval Yard, Newcastle, over  a question  of demarcation with labourers belonging to the        A.S.E.            The shipwrights in the Cardiff  area continue to  demand a 50 per cent, increase of over-        time rates, but have decided to suspend for one week their action in refusing to work over-        time, in order to enable the Technical Adviser to approach the employers.            Cases of dispute arising out of  the 12J jper cent, award continue to be reported.     This question also figures in the report from the Ministry of Munitions,  whichmentions five cases from various parts of the country.            Among the  cases  reported   the  most  interesting  is  one  at  Lincoln,  where  a        strike was threatened  because a number of Christadelphians  refused,  for  conscientious        reasons, to join a trade union.  They were eventually suspended.            The demand for an increase in the standard rate for aircraft woodworkers is not only        causing trouble in the London area, where  the situation is  still serious, but also at Bristol        and elsewhere.   When there are no open disputes there is reason to believe that the output        is being affected.            Members  of the Electrical Trades Union held a meeting in  the. Holborn Trades Hall        on the 28th January, on the question of a strike to compel an increase in wages.   The        actual resolution passed has not been ascertained, but is believed to have included a threat        to &quot; down tools &quot; on the 2nd February in the event  of their  demand not being accepted.     Three of the nine cases reported by the  War Office  Contracts Department  arenew ones, and of  the total five are reported to have been settled.            Only one of these cases is of more than local interest, and that has  resulted  in an        agreement by which all masters in the Liverpool and district leather trade are to adopt  a        uniform method  of effecting increases in  wages.    The  majority of the other cases have        arisen out of awards relating to various points in the clothing trade.     Only one of  the eleven cases reported by  the Coal Controller has arisen duringthe week, and this is of trivial importance.            The inter-union dispute at New Sharlston, in Yorkshire, has ended for the time being by        the men joining the Miners&apos; Association.  An attempt will, however, be made to obtain  a        complete settlement by reference  to  the Parliamentary  Committee of the Trades  Union        Congress.            A strike of 1,500 workmen at the National Aircraft Factory, Wallington, is threatened for        the 3rd February, as a protest against the prevailing food conditions.   The men at  Messrs.        Cubitts, Waddon, are threatening to&apos; take similar action.&quot;     The  Chief Industrial Commissioner reports that as  many as 90 out of the 200cases  of differences received during the  past week  are claims arising out of the 12*per cent, bonus,  and  a very high proportion of these  come from men  engaged onengineering and  shipbuilding.     Ninety-five cases have been  referred  to  arbitration, and here again  a  highproportion consists of  cases arising out  of 12f per cent.     No report  has been received this week from the Committee  on Production.D. J.  SHACKLETON.o

</content>
</cab>
