<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 44-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
?IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

WAR CABINET.

SECRET.

G.T.3508.

AIR POLICY COMMITTEE

The Sixth Meeting of the Committee was held at 2,  Whitehall Gardens, S.W. on S.W. on WEDNESDAY, JANUARY 30th,  1918, at 4.15 p.m.

The subject for discussion was:-

Possibility of utilising seaplanes from Cyprus or elsewhere for operations against the Turkish communications in Syria and Palestine (War Cabinet 318/7).

The Committee had before it a Memorandum by the Chief of the Air Staff (A.P.C.9).

PRESENT.

General Smuts (in the Chair).

Sir E. Geddes.

Lord Derby.

Lord Rothermere.

The following also attended :-

Colonel W.M.St.G.Kirke.,D.S.0.(for the Chief of the Imperial General Staff).

Admiral G.P.W.Hope., C.B.? Deputy First Sea Lord.,(for the First Sea Lord).

Sir David Henderson.

Sir H.Trenehard.

Commodore Paine.

Captain Scarlett.

Major J.Upton Kelly) Joint

Captain E.Abraham) Secretaries.

After the subject had been introduced by the Chairman, GENERAL TRENCHARD expressed the opinion that could be expected from raids on a single line of railway would not repay the expenditure of energy and money required for the attempt. Cyprus was too distant to be a suitable base. The Island, more-over, was off the track of ordinary marino traffic, and shipping was too short to start special service of supplies for an air-base in Cyprus.  If an aerodrome were begun there, its work would probably be hampered by receiving s?anty or intermittent supplies. He added that there were better targets in other areas.

SIR E. GEDDES expressed tho opinion that a single line of railway was hardly worth bombing. It was a difficult target, and any damage done to it oould be very speedily repaired.

GENERAL SMUTS pointed out that this line supported the whole Turkish campaign in Palestine. The Question before the Committee really was :  how can we use aircraft so as to interfere with the Turkish communication on that whole route ?


GENERAL TRANCHARD said that, after making allowance for more urgent claims elsewhere, Constantinople was the best objective we could operate against, as Turkish communications could be equally well out there.

LORD DERBY asked whether it would not be possible for an aeroplane to land in proximity to a bridge on the railway in question, and after blowing it up, to get away again.

GENERAL TRENCHARD stated that this had been tried in France, but generally without much success. In any case aeroplanes must start from land in some place from which the objective was accessible. Seaplanes could not come to ground.

COMMODORE PAINE pointed out that bridges are normally over steep places, with little landing space near them. GENERAL HENDERSON drew attention to the fact that the Turks had made some six attempts of this sort on our pipe-line through the desert, where landing was easy. These attempts had not been successful.

LORD DERBY pointed out that no aerodrome in Egypt was close enough to serve as a base for the operations contemplated.

SIR E. GEDDES instanced the small effect caused by eight direct hits on the GOEBEN.

LORD ROTHERMERE said that our enterprises must in any case be limited by our resources, which were not endless.

SIR E. GEDDES said that possibly if a definite bridge could be indicated as a target, with suitable ground near it to land, aeroplane might be sent up from a seaplane-carrier.

COMMODORE PAINE pointed out that we had no ship of the requisite kind in the Mediterranean. A big machine laden with heavy bombs could not start from a deck.

LORD ROTHEREMERE stated that Handley-Pages could go from Mudros to Constantinople.

It was pointed out that one had failed to return, by reason of engine failure. Landing at Mudros was newgood, and there was space for a large establishment.

The general consensus of opinion was that, for the time being, Cyprus could not be considered a suitable base for operations against the Turkish communications.

ADMIRAL HOPE handed in a Memorandum in general accord with General Tranchard&apos;s "A.P.C.9."

LORD DERBY stated, after looking at the man, that the scheme suggested in the Deputy First Sea Lord&apos;s letter was the obvious thing to do.

It was decided that :-

The general question of a bombing in the Mediterranean should be gone into by the Air Staff, in conjunction with the Admiralty and that a report should be made to the Air Policy Committee for further discussion. SIR E. GEEDES asked what proof we had that bombing towns produced much material result as distinct from moral result.
GENERAL TRENCHARD instanced the bombing of aerodromes. The main result in that case was to produce delay; either by causing the squadrons using it to move, or by making crators in the ground, which had to be l?v?llod before machines could start. Often there was serious damage to hangars.

SIR E. GEDDES agreed that the advantage of bombing troops, rest camps and aerodromes was clear; but he doubted the real value of bombing towns.

GENERAL TRENCHARD pointed out that this was done by order of the war Cabinet. The moral effect should be at least as good as in London, where the result on munition work was noticeable.

SIR E. GEDDES then asked whether the necessarily limited attack by seaplanes could be used with advantage against, say, Wilhelmshaven. Would the moral effect against a disciplined population be sufficient ? Was it possible for an attack from the sea to be sufficiently intensive to give adequate material as well as moral effect ?  The added provision of large numbers of carriers was a very serious matter as opposed to land aerial operations and those carriers so limited the density of attack tnat it might perhaps be rendered inffective. 

GENERAL TREACHARD was of the opinion that we had not force enough to undertake anything on a sufficient scale.

LORD ROTHERMERE pointed out that Hamburg would be a good objective, although he thought that more could be effected from the land than from the sea.

GENERAL SMUTS said that this question of bombing enterprise from the sea should be gone into.

SIR E. GEDDES agreed, as before, undertaking a programme of building carriers, it should be laid down what should be attempted and what could be expected.   His view was that the limitation of the carrior factor practically ruled out heavy bombing attacks from the sea even when machines were available.

It  was decided that :-

The Air Staff  in conjunction with the Admiralty, should carefully review the situation in the North Sea, and that their report should be placed before the Air Policy  Committee for further consideration.

2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.

January 31st, 1918.

Circulated to Members only.

</content>
</cab>
