<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 190-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(ft                          Oolonel Joner     1fff 01? HIS BR CAJMC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT)SECRET.WAR   CABIUH.   GOvEfiflHENT DEPARTMENTS AJfD WAR LABOUR QUESTIONS.(Copy of letter dated End February, 1910, from the 2ngineering Smployers1  Federation to the Prime Minister.)  -24 Abingdon Street,     Westminster,         LONDON, S.I2.1,  2nd February, 1918.The at. Eon. David Lloyd George,       Prime Minister,          10 Downing Street,                  S.*. 1.Pear Sir,          Surely after so much experience of war labour thetime has come to decide whether or not the confliot betweenGovernment Departments on war labour questions 13 to boallowed to continue.          V.e have had within the last few days one or two veryawkward incidents -    (1) The extension of the 12jj$ Order to pieceworkers, &amp;c.          by way of ifo on earnings was published the other          day in the newspapers as e Cabinet decision.   The          juinistry of Munitions thereafter formally intimated          the decision&quot;.   The Shipyard Labour Department at          the Admiralty which is responsible, amongst other          industries, for Marine Engineering, has not only          sot intimated to the establishmenta within its          scope but is unable to give any information as to          whether or not the 7-g  is to be paid.  The result          is that this week in^the establishments under the          jurisdiction of the Ministry of ionnitions the 7-i           ?7ill be said and in the establishments under tho          jurisdiction of the Admiralty the 7-^1 will probably          not be peid.(2)  Proposals have been madeforthe restriction of femaleend boy labour on nigfctshift, &amp;c   The Ministry ofMunitions acting on the advice of the Health of theMunition Workers&apos; Committee formally submitted theseproposals to us.   The Admiralty in respect of theestablishments under their jurisdiction are evidentlyunwilling that such proposals should be considered.The result is that the employers have had to say tothe Ministry that if the question of general policyconceived in the interests of the workpeople cannot
           be decided by the principal departments of the           Government,  it is ridiculous to press these on           behalf of any one department as a national           necessity.          The-so two incidents are fresh in our minds, manyothers could be cited shewing the conflict either active orpassive between these two important departments of theGovernment.          It would tie presumption on our part to impress uponyou the extraordinaryly delicate situation we have to facein the matter of laV-iir at the moment, but we think it isan imperative duty on our part to submit to you as urgentlyas we can the necessity for putting the control of war labourinto the h&amp;n&amp;rf of someone or some department whose sole dutyit will be to &apos;U-o.k ct..-;ter this special subject and who willhave the auth-.-r:.tv rriibjest to the Cabinet to ensure that allthe -department of tho  Government who are interested in warlabour conform to one recognised and definite policy.          The only other observation we dosire to make at themoment is that it ap-pears to us.necessary to recognise that theregulation of war labour is a subject apart.          The activities of the Ministry of Labour being fullyoccupied in connection  with post-war problems, conciliation andother matters, not directly affecting the regulation of warlabour, may not be a suitable department to deal with thisspecial subject and even at the risk of being accuse6 ofconstituting setting up a new department, we feel it would bedesirable to consider this extraordinarily important activityfrom this standpoint.                              Yours fa i thfully,                     (Signed)   ALLAH M* SMITE.                               Chairman of the Management                                                  Committee.

</content>
</cab>
