<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 453-453</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
  .                   &apos;Th*8 Document is th*                   -     2&amp;9                     Hts Britannic Maiesfys government.)?   VWfimJ relating to the v&apos;ar Work of the Board of Agriculture for     /^VScotland for the week ending 6th February. 1918.^ffTOP PBODUCTIOII.       During the week the weather has continued to be very favourable   for outdoor operations and reports reach the Board from all quarters   that cultivation has been proceeding without interruption.  Con-   siderable areas of land have been eeeded with v;heat and the land  is   said to have been  in first-rate order for sowing.   1* Compulsory Orders under Defence of the Eealm Peculation 2M.l(e).       Compulsory orders have been issued by the Board requiring  the   tenants of the following farms to cultivate additional areas of  land   specified in the Orders;-                     Fang.                           County.            Uaidleind........................Wigtown.            Kains , Dunlop...................   Ayr .            Pitlour  Grass Parks..................   Fife.            Garden Park, ICerse^ell Estate. ........   Lanark,            Prestwiolc Municipal Golf Course......   Ayr.   2* The Oats (Scotland and Ireland. -Restriction) Order, 1918.       This Order of the  Food Controller which came into force on 1st   February prohibits the  export of oats from Scotland to Ireland  or   England except under licence *  Its chief purpose is to ensure that   Scotch-grown oats  leaving the country are used only for  seed rur-   poses. In the case of  England, each separate consignment must  be   licensed by the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries, but  this Board   have arranged, with the  concurrence  of the Irish Department, to   issue  general licenoes  covering the whole season to merchants   exporting to Ireland.   A very large  number of applications for   licences have been dealt with during the past week, and  it is   believed that no serious inconvenience hae been caused to the regu-   lar trade in seed  oats  between Ireland and this country.   THIv SCOTTISH JOuT-HAI OF. AGRICULTURE.       The first number of the Board&apos;3 Quarterly Journal was issued on    1st January.  Copy of  first  issue  is attached to this Beport.11 -  BECKUITIITG  I?T ASRICUXTUKE.   Military Service Aotaf  19^.6.        (a) The number of  certificates  issued by the Board  in   connection with the scheme for vouching  agricultural workers in   terms  of Army Council Instruction 1175  (i.e. cases remitted by   Recruiting Officers)  is  as follows:-                 Areas.                Certificates issued.            Aberdeen......................      364            Ayr...........................      116            Berwick-on-Tweed..............    1,220            Fort George...................    1,624            Glencorse.....................      958            Hamilton......................      207             Inverness.....................      428            Perth.........................      704            Stirling......................      4456,086     (b)  The number of certificates  issued  in terms  of  the  ScottishOffice Memorandum to Tribunals  Ho. B.  144  (i.e.  oases remitted byTribunals)  is 900.

</content>
</cab>
