<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 465-465</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J                                                    Colonel JonesIS DOVmm  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS ERITAKBIO MAJESTY^ GOVERMaM1..                                                          -     300-*-*-                  WAR CABINET.w &apos;                CQLLECTIOIvf ,,QP WASTE PAPER.        Copy of. letter from Sir George R.i.ddell tq        &quot;Trivat e Seore&quot;tary .t o the&quot; &quot;Prime llinister.                   The Newspaper Proprietors Association Limited.                           6 Bouverie Street,                               London, E.C4.                                   6th February, 1918.My dear Davies,        As we understand that the collection of waste is to heconsidered by the Cabinet Committee appointed to report upon th^paper question? I think it well to  let you know that a longdiscussion on the subject took place at today&apos;s Newspaper Con-ference, representing the London and Provincial Press.   LordBurnham was not present, but there  was a large and representativeattendance.  The following resolution was unanimously passed, viz       &quot;That it is desirable that the collection of wastepaper    should remain under the direction of the Wastepaper Committee    of the Paper Commission and that its transference to the    Ministry of Munitions is wholly unnecessary.&quot;        The Conference were informed that generally speaking thvsdllections are now regarded as being fairly satisfactory, andthat the Paper Commission have improved and are still furtherimproving their organization for the collection of waste.  Underthese circumstances, it was felt undesirable to remove thecollection to another department which would have to set up anew organization and which is only concerned with the collection,of wastepaper as ancillary to its main operations.   TheConference think that the proposed  transfer might retard instead.of improving the collection.        I shall be much obliged if  you will kindly hand thisletter to the Chairman of the Committee when appointed..                       Faithfully yours,                         (Signed)  GEORGE A. RIOT8LL,.4   See War Cabinet 323., Minute B,

</content>
</cab>
