<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/41/0 images: 493-501</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
* This Document is the Property ot                                         320His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government,SECRET.                               Intelligence Bureau,                                          Department of Information.                                               DRW/020.             WEEKLY REPORT ON RUMANIA.  XX.                  (February 7, 1918)     The inevitable clash between Rumania and the BolshevikGovernment in Petrograd, foreshadowed in last Report, has nowculminated in a declaration of war by the Bolsheviks on Rumania.Mr Trotski, in his announcement of the opening of hostilities,sums up his case against the Rumanian &quot;oligarchy&quot; which, he says,&quot;in its dishonesty and criminality forms a clique the like of whichcannot be found on the face of our planet, though that is farfrom being of virgin purity.  The destruction of this gang isa matter of honour for the democracy of Europe&quot;.   The two concretegrounds of attack on the Rumanian authorities that the BolshevikGovernment alleges are (1) the action of the Rumanian authoritiestowards the Russian forces in Rumania,  and (2) the interference andcontemplated interference of the Rumanians in Russian affairs,particularly their invasion of Bessarabia and their associationwith the Ukrainian Rada and other anti-Bolshevik movements in Russia.These had best be examined separately.     (1) Rumanian Action against Russian Troops in Moldavia.               In the last Report the determination of the Rumanianauthorities to disarm and dismiss from the country such Russianforces as they considered dangerous to internal order was consideredfrom the point of view of its likelihood of involving Rumania inhopeless complications with Russia.    This has In many casessucceeded.  The war-weary troops have willingly abandoned theirarms in exchange merely for a receipt and free passage back toRussia.  In other cases there has been trouble:  the 9th Armyannounced its intention of marching with all its material of war
through laei;  the 6th Army Corps attacked the Rumanians atpalticeni, and the Siberian forces at Galatz began a bombardment ofthe town.   One of the chief grounds for Trotskfs complaint againstthe Rumanian Government is that they have discriminated betweenBolshevik and non-Bolshevik troops In Rumania.   There Is, possibly,justification for this complaint, though the Rumanian answer wouldbe that if they are on friendly terms with non-Bolshevik elementsit is because these are willing to help them to defend the countryand behave properly towards the civilian population.  As to therespective strengths of the Bolsheviks and other parties among theRussians on the Rumanian front It is very difficult to give anyaccurate information.   In the elections last November for theConstituent Assembly Russian soldiers on the Rumanian frontreturned 12 Social Revolutionary deputies, 3 Bolsheviks and 4Ukrainians.  Since then the proportion has probably changed and itis quite probable that the numbers of the Bolsheviks haveconsiderably increased.   Rumanian calculations put them at about200,000, but possibly there are far more than this.  There is,however, every reason to think that-the Rumanian army will nothave very much difficulty in dealing with the refractory elementsIf they are able to do BO without intervention from outside.In the first brushes between the Rumanians and Bolsheviks inRumania the latter have shown a willingness to surrender and alack of military organisation vhich, from the Rumanian point ofview, offers a promise of a speedy and successful termination to thecrisis.   The question of the Rumanians&apos;  ability, however, to holdout against a general Bolshevik offensive from Russia and thepossible renewal of  an Austro-German campaign is another matterand must be considered later.
     (2) Rumanian &quot;Interference&quot; in Russia.               Trotski!s second ground for complaint against theRumanians is that they have allied themselves with elements workingagainst the Russian Revolution in Russia itself.  He is alludingto the understanding &quot;between the Rumanian Government aid theUkrainian Rada and to the action of the Rumanians in Bessarabia.As to the first point it is true that the Rumanians have been workingwith the Rada through the medium of General Shcherbachev who, tillthe other day, was recognised even by the Bolshevik Government asCommander-In-Chief on the Rumanian front.  It is difficult to Bayon what ground even the Bolsheviks could have expected theRumanians to do anything blse but co-operate with the General informal command of the Russian forces In Rumania.  The Rumanianmilitary authorities have necessarily modelled their action on thatof General Shcherbachev.   On December 8, for Instance, they joinedin the general armistice arranged with the Germans, though theycarefully pointed out at the time that this armistice had forthem no political significance whatsoever and that they were unableto join in peace negotiations wiiich might compromise the RumanianGovernment in the eyes of its Allies.  The armistice was prolongedtill January 14 and now has been extended till February la.Through General Shchorbachev the Rumanians have been in touch withthe Ukrainian Rada.   Possibly they have been guilty of misjudgingthe political situation and indulging In unreasonable hopes ofthe strength of the Rada!s position In the Ukraine and of thereadiness of the Ukrainians to continue the war against theCentral Powers.  They can hardly, however, be criticised for such amistaken judgment (if it prove mistaken), since the Allied Powers,and particularly the French, hold, or held, the same views.   TheRada still attaches great Importance to the support of the Rumanian
army;  possibly ^he-.latter-sh u^                            theinvitations of the Rada to advance into Russian territory exceptin so far as this advance is dictated by the urgent necessity forsecuring Rumanian food depots in the Ukraine generally and theOdessa region in particular.  As to what course will be taken mustdepend on the result of the  military operations against theBolsheviks.The Bessarabian Situation.     A more immediate question is the military intervention of theRumanians In Bessarabia.   In previous Reports some account has been.given of the growth of the Bessarabian National Movement.  Duringthe month of November this Movement crystallised in the formationof a provisional Government called Sfatul Iparii (Council of the Lar.d,;consisting of 150 delegates from various representative bodies inthe country.  The Bolsheviks criticised this body as a BourgeoisAssembly which did not reflect the wishes of the peasant andproletarian classes, and their attitude towards it was practicallythat of their attitude towards the Ukrainian Rada.    On paper atleast the Council has a thoroughly democratic appearance;  the bulkof the delegates are either representative of the soldiers orpeasants.  Moldavian soldiers in Bessarabia, for instance, have 36delegates;  other scattered military units are represented by 8;the Provincial Council of the peasants has elected 31.   Thedifferent nationalities of Bessarabia are also given adequaterepresentation:  the Ukrainians 15, the Jewish Bund 13, Germans 2,Bulgars and Gagauti (Chriastianised Tatars) 5, Poles, Greeks and  .Armenians 1 each;  the remainder are representatives of the variousZemstva and national societies of the province.   The SocialDemocrat and Social Revolutionary parties, however, are onlyrepresented by one delegate each and this is presumably the
justification for tho Bolsheviks&apos;  attack on the Council as an anti-refeblutionary iSidy.   They refuse to recognise such a Council andwill only treat with a Government supported by a ConstituentAssembly, presumably elected by Bolshevik Sovyets.  Qn December 15the Council declared that it represented the &quot;Moldavian Republic&quot;with full Independence of action till such time as a Russian FederalRepublic should be formed.   Its programme is, on paper, anextremely advanced one.  It provides for universal, equal andproportional suffrage;  for the transfer of all the land to thepeasants without compensation to the landlords;  for the equalityof all races, ceeeds and languages;  and &quot;for peace withoutannexations and indemnities on the principle of complete self-determination of peoples in agreement with the Allies and all thepeoples of tbe Russian Federal Republic&quot;.  The Bolshevik answerto this would be that the Rada made similar promises, but thatthey were merely a sop to democratic feeling and intended as ablind to cloak their protection of the interests of the landlords an$bourgeoisie.  The Council arrogates to itself full powers inBessarabia until the election and meeting of the ConstituentAssembly.  Its Executive body is called the &quot;Council of   . GeneralDirectors&quot;, responsible to the Sfatul ^arii and consisting of 10Ministers.  The urgent questions confronting them they state to bethe suppression of anarchy, the provisioning of the country and thecontrol of the deputies1 mandates.   1ft is to secure the first twoobjects that they have invited the Rumanian armies to enterBessarabia.  Bolshevik troops in Bessarabia, as in Moldavia, havelooted the villages and seized on food supplies, and in theInterests of both the Bessarabian and Rumanian Government it wasnecessary to secure control of the latter.  Since the BessarabianCouncil disposes of only small forces (certainly well under 40,000men and probably considerably less), they were unable themselves tocope with the problem.  Accordingly by their invitation several
Rumanian divisions have occupied various points in the country,especially Kishinyov and Bolgrad.  Bessarabia is not, however, yetcleared of Bolshevik elements and the Rumanian position is not yetsecure.Probable Results of the &quot;War&quot;.     Hostilities between the Bolshevik and Rumanian Governmentswere formally begun on January 27 (considerable fighting had alreadytaken place).  It would appear to be certain that they are bound totake an acute form before any accommodation can be reached.Trotski declares himself to be convinced - and there is everyreason to suppose that he is genuinely convinced - that he istaking action against an &quot;oligarchy steeped in crime&quot; and isinterfering in Rumania in the Interests of the Rumanian people asa whole.  He, therefore, obviously hopes that his interventionwill be followed by a spread of Bolshevism in the Rumanianarmy akin to its recent spread in the Ukraine.    This is, of course,a possibility, but it seems most improbable.  In the first place,the moral and discipline of the Rumanian army are higher than everthey were and it is unlikely that they oan be so easily overthrown.Secondly, the pure theory of Social Democracy is practicallyunknown among the Rumanian peasants, for in Rumania there ispractically no Rumanian town proletariat and the Rumanian peasantis far m^re interested in increasing his small independent holdingof land than in introducing any system of State communism.Thirdly, the old distrust and dislike of Russia in Rumania has beenso accentuated, first by the treachery of the Tsarisfi Government                                     otowards Rumania, which, rightly or wrongly, is an article of faithwith every Rumania^ and secondly by the abandonment by revolutionaryRussia of its promised military support of Rumania by the influenceof indiscipline and outrage on the part of Russian troops in
Rumania, as to prove a counterweight to any of the Bolshevik&apos;Government overtures.  The:   mere fact that Bolshevism is Russian inorigin militates against its success in Rumania to-day.   It seemslikely, therefore, that the Rumanian army will put up a strongresistance against any Bolshevik offensive.  There is,moreover,reason to suppose that they will he successful in maintaining thisresistance.  They are fa^t better organised in discipline thanany troops the Bolsheviks can dispose of and they are undercapable military leaders.  There are two weaknesses, however,in their position:  (1) The shortage of food.  Even with thesupplies which they may succeed in guarding in Bessarabia, where,fortunately, last yearTs harvest was a good one, the Rumanians rillhardly have sufficient, and they will probably find it necessary tooccupy parts of Southern Russia.  The danger of extending theiractivities too far into Russia must, of course, be considered,though if these are confined to Odessa end the Government ofKherson they might perhaps be safe.  (2) The renewal at this momentof an Austro-German-Bulgarian offensive against them.  It is hardto say whether this is probable or even likely as there are internalconditions, more especially in Austria-Hungary and Bulgaria, but alsoin Germany, which might render a renewed campaign against Rumaniamost inacceptable to public opinion.  If, however, the militaryparty in Germany is strong enough to take such a decision and isable to dispose of adequate troops to carry it out successfully,the Rumanians would be placed in a most perilous position.   Insuch a case, since the securing of their food supplies againstthe Bolsheviks is a vital necessity, they would probably be quiteunable to cope with the German offensive on a large scale.Policy, therefore, might suggest the advisability in such a caseof their proposing to open negotiations with the Central Powers;time would  thereby be gained and if the Entente Powers were kept
informed of the progress of negotiations much interestinginformation might be elicited.   It is hard to see how, short of acomplete capitulation of the Rumanian Government and army, whichwould only be the result of a pronounced defeat, the negotiationscould be successful.   The Dobrogean question and the status ofthe Rumanian army and Government, for instance, would prove hard tosettle.   Negotiations would, therefore, probably be prolongedalmost indefinitely, and time would be gained for the Rumanians tosecure themselves against the Bolsheviks alike from a military andeconomic point of view.     At present the Rumanians quite recognise that, owing to theirisolated position, there is no likelihood of receiving material.assistance from the Western Powers.  They live, however, in thehope and expectation that their Entente Allies will make a strongprotest to the Bolshevik Government as to the unreasonablenessof their attitude towards Rumania;  and what they are longing formore than anything else is that a public statement should beissued to the Rumanian nation more categorical than has yet beenmade, i.e. to the effect that the whole question of the reunion,should they wish it, in one State of the Rumanian race should betaken up and supported by the Entente Powers.   President Wilson&apos;srecent speech, for instance, caused consternation in Rumania, whereit was considered to be an entire abandonment of Rumania1 s nationalclaims.   Suoh unconditional support of the just aspirations of theRumanian people would more than counter-balance in their eyes anyoffers from the Central Powers;  but if no such promise from theEntente Powers is forthcoming it is hard to see what inducement canbe offered to Rumania not only to continue the fighting, but torefrain from linking up their fortunes politically and economicallyafter the war with the Central Powers.  The main thing is to
7.2.18.maintain the moral of the Rumanian army and people, and this canonly be maintained by some such categorical assurance that theirpast and future efforts will not have been wasted, ,in that theywill have secured the full democratic solution of their nationalquestions.

</content>
</cab>
