<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/173/11 images: 49-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HANDLING THE MINERS&apos; AND POWER ENGINEERS5 DISPUTESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Employment10 I attach as an appendix an analysis of the position with the NationalUnion of Mineworkers (NUM) and the possibilities for dealing with this andwith the power engineers1 dispute,    I can summarise it as follows,2. It is now clear th&amp;t this is a conflict between the Government andthe NUM militants,,    But the general public is not aware of theconstitutional importance of Daly&apos;s open challenge to the authorityof Parliament.    We have to accept that some people will regard itas justifiable.    It is therefore important that Governmental reactions to Daly-s woids should not be strident, especially since the mineworkershave not yet acted illegally.3. But it is not yst clear to the public:a. That the Code dees substantially improve the mineworkers&apos;relative pay position and does prevent other groups fromoutstripping them again,b. That their settlement is not due until the beginningof March and that the overtime ban iss therefore,, directed against the concept of the Code and Stage 3, rather than againstthe National Coal Board offer,c. That overtime has to be worked in the pits for industrial and technical reasons (rather than forced on individual mineworkersbecause of low pay) and is a contractual obligation for the workers concerned; that the hours v/worked are only overtime in the sense that different rates apply, which have always been negotiated onthis basis; and that the Government in making the unsocial hoursprovision in the Code, have recognised that the rates for someperiods of work have up to now been inadequate.It is important that these points should be repeatedly explained at the sametime as the nature of the militant challenge,CP(73) 131 COPY NO       0727 November 1973CABINET
4. The strategy that we choose will depend on our view of theconstitutional issue involved and the general economic setting,,    Butthe remainder of the analysis skows that every strategy we can adoptafter the next NUM Executive Meeting requires the same immediatetactical position:aa        The Government must make absolutely clear that therewill be no concession^ and that the overtime ban will bring nothing more,b.        This requires the Government to make equally clear to the electrical Power Engineers Association that no concession outsidethe policy can be made to the power engineers.5.        I invite my colleagues8 agreement to the conclusions set cut inparagraph 25 of the analysis. 11M V MDepartment of Employment27 November 1973
APPENDIXHANDLING THE MINERS&apos;  AND POWER ENGINEERS&apos;   DISPUTESA.     THE MINERS&apos;   DISPUTEOBJECTIVESThe point of conflict between the Government and NUM militantsis clear:GOVERNMENT want to get the overtime ban removed quickly anda settlement  consistent with the counter inflation policy.NUM MILITANTS want to induce a miners&apos;   strike in order tobreak the counter inflation policy.2.       Government and militants  can achieve their objectives only through a ballot of the miners.    The militants because the NUMrules require a ballot for a strike:    the Government because thereseeems to be no prospect that the moderates on the NUM Executivewill call off the overtime ban except after a ballot.    So the aim off both sides is to get a ballot at the time and in the  conditionsmost likely to achieve their objectives...;V. V&apos;-.&apos;- T::&apos;;*vfi:E ft&apos; i :-&quot;.&apos;,;-&apos; fi: ft&apos;     ft:NUM STRATEGY3.      The militants believe that the disruption caused in the coal-fields by the overtime ban tends to make the membership moredisaffected and readier to take full strike action.    Their strategyis therefore to defer the ballot and continue the ban until therehas been sufficient change in the attitude of the miners to produce the.necessary 55 per cent majority for strike action.    So(a) they will wish to avoid advancing the NUM Executivemeeting from 13 December and to leave open whether to go fora ballot then or continue the overtime ban.    If they decide on a ballot,  they may go for a result before Christmas;     or take the usual 3 weeks and have the result at the New Year.Either  case would,  if the ballot favoured strike action,enable them to begin the strike from early January, which hasbeen their consistent aim;     and(b) if on 13 December they are not confident of the ballotresult,  they are likely to seek to contine the overtime banand defer decision on a ballot until after Christinas.    Butit is most unlikely that they would delay a ballot beyondearly January.    They will want a strike to begin not later than the end of that month,  so that its full impact will be felt during the winter.    Although k weeks&apos; notice of a strikeis required under existing agreements, we cannot rely on it being given,  and the union could meet this by givinganticipatory notice concurrently with a decision to ballottheir members.4.      There is, however,  the remoter possibility that they maysimply continue the overtime ban if they think that the energysituation is such that the ban alone will quickly secure Governmentsurrender.(secret)
GOVERNMENT STRATEGY5.       If the Government make no concession and the ballot goesagainst strike action, the Stage 3 pay policy will stick.    Alreadysettlements covering l-J million people have been notified to the pay Board for determination that they are within the Code,  andothers are negotiating.     The problems of dealing with other possiblelchallenges - in the railways and the docks - will be greatly eased.  if,  on the other hand,  the Government has to make a concession,  themilitants everywhere will be encouraged to try their hand againstthe policy.Period to 13 December6.      The Government have no power to determine the timing of thenext NUM Executive meeting or its decision on a ballot or theterms of the ballot.    We depend on influencing the NUM Executivethrough direct pressure and on influencing the opinion of miners and the public generally in favour of acceptance of the Coal Boardoffer.    We must do everything possible     1(a) to get the NUM Executive to meet earlier than 13 December ;j(b) to influence the decision in favour of a ballot at thenext NUM meeting.DIRECT INFLUENCE7.      The Prime Minister will be meeting the whole NUM Executiveon 28 November in order to put to them the full implications oftheir position in seeking to go beyond the limits set byParliament.    They will not, however,  be asked directly to ballotbecause they would reject such intervention and the Governmentcould not in any event accept the outcome of the ballot as deciding whether the Pay Code should be breached or not.    In view of the wider implications  (particularly if domestic fuel restrictions were to be imposed as suggested in paragraph 9 below),  it may become necessary for the Prime Minister to meet the TUC EconomicCommittee.    But such a meeting is not likely to have any effect onthe NUM Executive at this stage.INFLUENCE ON MINERS8.      The Coal Board have publicised their offer in the press and propose at an opportune moment to circulate details of it tominers individually.     I believe they should  continue to publicisethe offer and consider whether they should send details to individual miners now and be prepared to repeat this at the timeof a ballot.    They will also be discreetly using their officials&apos;contacts within the coalfields to influence moderate opinion.INFLUENCE ON PUBLIC GENERALLY9.      The Coal Board advertisements will help and the Governmentshould continue to  emphasise the merits of Stage 3 generally,the genesis of the statutory policy in the inflationary    aftermathof the 1972 coal strike,  the relative advantage of the policy tothe miners,  and the implications of the line being taken by the num Executive - on the lines suggested in paragraph 2 and 3 of the
paper covering this appraisal.     It might also be desirable -particularly if the NUM on Wednesday intransigently pi-ess their claim -  to  introduce urgently emergency restrictions on powerconsumption in order to highlight for the public the implications of the miners&apos;   action and the Government1s resolve to conservefuel   supplies.    There would .no doubt need to be preliminaryconsultations with the TUC and CBI together with Ministerialstatements to make clear the need for  such drastic action.Period after 13 December10.     If a ballot  is taken as a result of that meeting,  theGovernment must  await the outcome.    The message to miners and thepublic from the NCB and the Government  should continue with even greater vigour. 1 ..  - n - -11.     If the ballot is deferred,   the impact of the continued over-time ban on the fuel  stocks will be a determining factor.    We await the DTI latest estimates of the stock position and the assessmentwhich follows is very provisional. II12.    But,  failing further early restrictions on power consumption,if no decision on a ballot is taken before the end of the year,we will be approaching possibly only 4 weeks&apos;  coal stocks at power stations by the time the outcome of the ballot is known late inJanuary.     If this favours strike action,  the ability to hold out would probably not  extend beyond mid-February.     If the powerengineers1   out of hours ban was continuing and there was the usualrate of breakdown in January,  this period could be reduced further;and if the power  engineers,   coming up to their February settlement,were to continue to refuse to undertake out of hoturs duties and make it  impossible to operate a refined system of selective powercuts,   crude rota  switching would have to be employed,  providinglittle.or no protection for  essential services.13.    Early drastic action to curtail  energy consumption would benecessary to  extend the period of endurance by any appreciableamount.    There is anyway a strong case for curtailing at once theconsumption of energy in order to make clear to the public thefull  effect of the miners&apos;  action (as suggested in paragraph above).Overtime ban continuing after 13 December14.    So if the NUM Executive fail  to decide on 13 december to ballot,  the Government would have to decide between- further action to bring pressure on the NUM to ballotwithout any concession;    or- intervening to force a resolution.Further pressure on the NUM15.    The Government could increase the pressure on the NUM to holda ballot by:
(a) intensifying the severity of the curtailment of energy. consumption because of their  indefinite continuance of the overtime ban;     and in what would then be a crisis situation with people being thrown out of work&apos;-v.: I(b) calling in the TUC General  Council to a meeting withthe Prime Minister at which to invite them to urge the num to reconsider their position in view of the Impact onthe economy.Even if action on both these fronts had been taken soon after thisWednesday&apos;s meeting,  they could be repeated with advantage if the num failed to  call a ballot on 13 December.16.    This could build up the weight of public opinion hostile tothe miners to the point where the NUM moderates would  carry the dayon the ballot.     But there would be the risk that the militantswould be encouraged to  continue the overtime ban in the belief that the Government  could not hold out much longer;     that the TUCwould feel bound to give some wider trade union cover  to the NUMaction;    and that the public,  while feeling    angry with the miners,would begin to blame the Government for not giving them the money.17.    These risks will be easier to assess nearer the time;    butthey emphasise the importance both oif continuing firmness onStage 3  generally and of ensuring that  the public are fully a\fareof the facts.     We  should be prepared to use the Conservative Partyorganisation to the full,   ensuring that ministers and backbenchersare fully briefed,  that agents do  in fact distribute leaflets  etcin the constituencies and possible briefing area chairmen andagents  in person so as to enable them in tarn to hold briefing-meetings of constituency chairmen and agents.    There is nothingimproper- in using the Party organisation to put across a policy approved by Parliament.Intervention to force a resolution18.    There are two ways in \\?hich action could be taken beyond this to force an early conclusion:(a) by using legal  sanctions against the NUM under the IRand Counter  Inflation Acts.     This would include seeking NIRCagreement to a ballot under the IR Act.    The Annex states thepossibilities and the drawbacks.     I do not believe that useof the law would help secure our objective of an early ballotand an ultimate settlement within the policy.    It would more probably turn the issue into one of opposition to the IR Actand solidify miners behind the NUM militants in opposition tothe Government.(b) by conceding the NUM claim,   either by my giving a consentunder the Counter Inflation Act;     or by offering a specialenquiry in the light of the Pay Board relativities report which could lead to extra payment  from the miners1   operative date in March.A consent would be plain capitulation and an inquirycould produce a 1972 Wilberforce situation.    The case for either  course is that,  by avoiding the effects of a continuing
overtime ban or even a coal strike,   a  concession might enable growth  to  continue and  even possibly,   leave some prospect  of a  continuing policy.    But  even if some control could still be maintained over pay  settlements similar treatment would have to be given to others with similarcases,   or equal  strength,   and there would be a marked increasein the cost  of Stage 3 and in inflation.    The remnant ofpolicy would be very vulnerable thereafter to other militantpressure and there might well be more industrial unrestrather than less.     This and the effect on investment if thePrice Code remained unchanged would lessen the chances ofsecuring uninterrupted growth.    Such a line of policy is,   inmy view,  politically impossible.IF NUM BALLOT LEADS TO A STRIKE19.     In the event of a strike we  can expect the miners to staysolidly behind the NUM.    They would certainly outlast the fuel supplies.     If therefore a strike were called,   the Government wouldhave to  consider,  as one possible  course,  getting the miners backto work by concessions outside the  Code,   in effect alt earing thepolicy to ensure that all those with the strength and will to damage the  economy  seriously could be paid what they demand,  whilethe rest are held down.     I regard this as politically intolerablebut other courses which might be open in this situation go beyondthe remit for this paper.B.     THE POWER ENGINEERS20.    The handling of this dispute depends on the line taken withthe miners.    So long as the Government are standing firm with theminers,  any concession to the engineers would simply encourage theminers to persist in their attempt to break the policy.21.    Although the EPEA seek to put a more respectable front on it,their action to secure their out of hours agreement outside the pay limit is as much an attempt to break the policy approved byParliament as is the miners&apos;  overtime ban.    To allow their agreement through would have extensive repercussions  (eg onagreements made before or during the standstill in construction,engineering and  electrical  contracting).22.     In the period up to the next NUM Executive meeting,  and whilethe ballot is taken if the NUM decide on it then,  the same line should be taken with the power  engineers as with the miners.     TheGovernment  should publicly emphasise that there can be no settlementoutside the limits set by Parliament,  that the Council1s offer goesa long way towards implementing the out of hours agreementparticularly for the junior engineers who mainly do the call outduty,  that the EPEA should negotiate their Stage 3 settlement  inorder to find out what is available under the Code beforeinconveniencing the public.    The Electricity Council  (who till now have preferred to  stand aside or even join the EPEA inrepresentations to Government)  should be urged particularly topublicise the benefits of their recent  offer to the junior powerengineers and their willingness to negotiate within the Code onthe alleged relativities problems.
23.    Following the NUM Executive meeting with the Prime Minister(and depending  on the outcome of the EPEA&apos;s approach to the pay board this week),   I should see the EPEA in order to emphasise tothem that there can he no settlment outside the Code and to urgethem to call off the ban.2k.    After 13  December the tactics with the EPEA will again dependon the handling of the miners.     If the Government were then taking action to bring further pressure on the NUM to ballot and maintaining that  they would not  submit to blackmail,  the responsiblmembership of the EPEA might well  cause its leaders to back off from refusing the co-operation necessary for  selective power  cuts.CONCLUSIONS25.     It is possible that the overtime ban might be operated insuch a way and for long enough to px^oduce,   in conjunction withother  difficulties,  the effect of a  full-scale strike.     Since thiswould present  the same choices as intimated in paragraph 19 above,I have regarded this,   too,   as outside the remit for this paper.Nor have I attempted to consider the wider  implications for  energyor economic policy generally,  subject to these constraints:(a) it would,  in my view,  be good tactics in handling thesedisputes to take action to limit all fuel consumption,   andto implement any other measures that may be required on theeconomic front,  sooner rather than later;(b) there are six conclusions to be drawn from this paper:-Miners(i)    The NUM Executive all accept that they have to take a ballot some time.(ii)     If the ballot favours acceptance,   the Government are homeand dry with Stage 3&quot;    There is nothing to be gainedbefore then by concessions by the NCB or Governmentbecause these are more likely to persuade the militantsto keep the overtime ban going while they gouge out more.    The best hope of an early ballot lies in theGovernment making absolutely clear quickly that therewill be no concession and that the overtime ban will bring nothing more.(iii)     It is best  for the Government to stick out the overtimeban until the ballot on the ground that this is a challenge to Parliament on which it will not yield.    There-should therefore be no intervention by concession before *tthe ballot is taken.(iv)    We should  consider whether any further steps  could betaken,  immediately the ballot is announced,  to encourageminers to vote against  strike action.(v)    If the ballot goes in favour of a strike,  the minerscan outlast the Government  in the current fuel situation.It should be made clear to the  country that Government,Parliament and people are facing intolerable blackmail,whichever  course we then follow.
Power  engineers(vi)    No concession outside the Code could be made to the- .EPEA without strengthening the miners1  position.    TheGovernment  should make plain to them too that their outof hours ban will bring nothing more and press them to end it.    Their action,   if sustained,  makes it harderto deal with, the mineworkers;    but there is not methodof stopping  it  separately that does not seriouslyincrease the risk of strike action by the miners.
ANNEXUSING THE LAW IN ORDER TO TRY TO GET A BALLOTThis could take the form of(a) Legal  sanctions.    Use of the Industrial Relations Act powers fora cooling-off period or against the overtime ban as an unfairindustrial practice.    But these would not advance a ballot;    theywould simply remove attention from the real issue and allow themilitants to focus on opposition to the IR Act.    And fining the num under the Counter-Inflation Act would rally miners to  thesupport of their union,  again blurring the issue of whether they accept the Coal Board offer or not./ v: &apos; . - - &apos; .... - &apos;   &quot; -   i-     IS   .   &quot; M   l      -C:&quot;W&apos;^(b) Ballot under the IR Act.    If a ballot under the Act were held,the Court itself would frame the question which could only be toask whether miners favoured continuing the overtime ban.    although a result showing that they did not would indicate tacitacceptance of the offer,   there is no likelihood that a majorityagainst the ban would be achieved.    A subsequent NUM ballot on strike action would almost certainly support a strike.But  (i)    there is no  certainty that we could get the ballot held.The Court might not grant an application on the ground thatthere was no doubt,  from the NUM consultations leading to theban,   that the miners supported it.    Even if the applicationwere granted,  the NUM might instruct miners not to vote,especially as the NUM would be most unlikely to comply withthe accompanying Court requirement that they should stop theban meanwhile and there would therefore be contemptproceedings against NUM leaders;     and(ii)  although announcement of the Government1s intention to seek an enforced ballot might just possibly push the NUM intoholding its own,  the more likely outcome would be a continuing overtime ban with the NUM in contempt and theminers solid behind their leadership in voting for strike action in any subsequent NUM ballot.(secret)


</content>
</cab>
