<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/115/0 images: 256-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:nt is the property of her britannic majesty&apos;s government. p. (63) 19 copy no. ^20th november^JI^SScabinetthe future of EUROPEAN FARMING LAND INj&amp;SNYAMemorandum by the Chief.Secretary&apos;to the^ Treasury and paymaster GjgneralI have not had an opportunity in the normal way to discuss withthe Commonwealth and Colonial Secretary the proposals contained inhis C. P. (63) 18 of 19th November, for increased expenditure on thepurchase of European-owned land in Kenya.    But the following comments may be of help to my colleagues in considering this issue.2.      The Colonial Secretary&apos;s present proposals seem to involve animportant departure from the policy previously followed.    For whileit has been apparent that previous policy on land purchase has had asa useful by-product the giving of help to Europeans in Kenya, its overtpurpose has been the settlement of Africans on land previously occupiedby European farmers.3.       The present proposal, however presented, can only be putforward as being in the interests of Europeans.    For of the 650, 000acres so far bought under the scheme, only 108, 000 have so f ar been settled by Africans.    From the point of view of African settlementthere is therefore at present no case whatever for an extension of thescheme.4.      Paragraph 7 of the Secretary of State&apos;s paper brings out the extremely expensive nature of this method of assisting Europeans. 3.1 million is a very high price for assisting 110 European farmers;but what is still more disturbing is that the Colonial Secretary forecaststhat the review which he proposes in his memorandum would bring this cost up to &quot;as much as  21 million or thereabouts&quot;.    This aspect of the matter is accentuated by the fact that a number of Europeanfarmers in Kenya are of South African origin and citizenship and itat least would appear doubtful whether the United Kingdom taxpayershould be called upon to provide for them.5.       That the method proposed by the Colonial Secretary for dealingwith the problems of the Europeans in Kenya on independence is notuniversally regarded as right even by Europeans in that country is brought out by the note which I attach as an Annex to this paper of a conversation which I recently had with a European member of the kenya legislature.-1-
6,       There are considerable difficulties involved in dealingseparately with this issue shortly in advance of decisions whichwill have to be made on other financial aspects of the settlement to be made with Kenya on independence.    I understand that the kenya Government are putting forward various large demands for financial assistance, and it would seem sensible to consider thequestions as to whether or not to expand further the LandSettlement Scheme in the context of the priority which the Kenya government themselves give to this as against other proposals under the independence settlement.7.      In my view it would suffice on the Second Reading of theIndependence Bill for the Colonial Secretary to point out thatthere is at present plenty of room for further action within thepresent Land Settlement Scheme and to add that it will in any event be necessary to conduct the normal financial negotiationswith Kenya on independence.J.A.B.-C.Treasury Chambers, S, &quot;W. 1.20th November, 1963
annex extract from a note of a conversation between theChief Secretary ?.nd Mr. Alexander, a European member ofthe Kenya Legislature, and an Opposition Delegate to the KenyaConstitutional Conference, at Lancaster House, on25th September, 1963.&quot;. . , Immediately he appreciated that I was a TreasuryMinister, he began by saying that he thought the Land SettlementScheme an appalling waste of public money.    Even though it was our money he thought it could have been very much better spentif it were available in other directions.    Its purpose, as he understood it, was to facilitate settlers selling their farms andgetting out.    He thought this was wrong.    Ke had every intentionof staying himself in Kenya, and though it was of course amatter for each individual European to decide what he wanted to do, he thought it was completely wrong for the United KingdomGovernment to provide what amounted to help and encouragement to settlers to leave the country. &quot;


</content>
</cab>
