<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/115/0 images: 276-278</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1963CP. (63) 2226th November, 1963CABINETBANK EMPLOYEES: LEGAL EXPENSES OF CAMERON INQUIRYMemorandum by the Minister of labour the Chief Secretary and I would be grateful for the advice of our colleagues on the question of the legal costs of the organisations of bank employees which appeared before Lord Cameron when he conducted his inquiry earlier this yearinto staff relations in banks. This inquiry was set up by my predecessor following a request from the International Labour Organisation to which the NationalUnion of Bank Employees (N.U.B.E.) had made a complaint that thearrangements for employee representation and negotiation in the banks, four ofwhich were named, constituted a breach of the International Labour convention on the Right to Organise and Bargain Collectively, which the Government hasratified.2. At the beginning of the inquiry, Lord Cameron made it known that ifthe organisations concerned chose not to be represented by Counsel this wouldnot be to their disadvantage. The banks chose however to be represented by counsel and the employee organisations (N.U.B.E., the six staff associations andthe Central Council of Bank Staff Associations) felt they must be represented on equal terms.3. At the close of the hearings, the employee organisations made representations that they had incurred heavy legal costs which they could illafford and that a substantial contribution should be made by the Government.Lord Cameron strongly supported this plea in a letter to my predecessor fromwhich the following extract is taken:&quot; It would, I feel, be unfortunate in the extreme if in such an Inquiryas this, the very heavy burden of expenses should fall on the shoulders of parties ill equipped to bear it, and whose presence was not the result oftheir invocation of the power of a Minister to order Inquiry, but on thecontrary as the consequence of a request to Her Majesty&apos;s Government byan international authority to make or cause to make Inquiry into the facts of a complaint lodged with that authority. I therefore transmit the plea whichhas been made, with the expression of my own view that it is one which is essentially reasonable and that if possible means should be found to giveeffect to it.&quot;Lord Cameron mentions in his Report, which is being published on28th November, that he put his views on this subject to my predecessor in a letter.I shall therefore be forced to disclose his recommendation.4. In my view there is a very strong case for making a contribution:(i) The expenses in question were incurred as a result of the organisationscoming forward to take part in an inquiry which was instituted by theGovernment at the request of the I.L.O. in order to deal with charges of breach of a Convention which the Government had ratified. Althoughthe I.L.O.&apos;s request followed a complaint by N.U.B.E. (which the report has shown to be ill-founded and irresponsible), N.U.B.E. may well nothave realised that their complaint would lead to a full-scale inquiry.This was not foreseen by my Ministry, and the I.L.O. have not previouslymade a similar request.Copy No.5l3555THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT
(ii) Despite Lord Cameron&apos;s assurance at the beginning of the inquiry, it wasthe banks&apos; decision to engage Counsel that set the pattern, and the employee organisations could scarcely have been expected to refrain from ensuring that their interests would be defended on equal terms.(iii) Lord Cameron&apos;s Report includes recommendations for a much-neededimprovement of relations in the banks and for the development of negotiating machinery. I am anxious to seize this opportunity of trying to resolve the long-standing differences between the banks, N.U.B.E.and the staff associations. If the one recommendation which LordCameron has addressed directly to the Government on the subject of legal costs is ignored, this will certainly damage the chance of making progress on these other recommendations with the parties. refusal of assistance would, however illogically, be widely regarded as an act of vindictiveness against N.U.B.E. who are in financial difficulties, and could jeopardise the continued independent existence of the bank staff associations at the very moment when the Report has vindicated them.5. The Chief Secretary feels unable to agree to a contribution for the following reasons:(1) In view of Lord Cameron&apos;s assurance at the start of the inquiry, there wasno need for the employee organisations to engage Counsel; they engagedCounsel of their own volition, and can have no reasonable expectation of assistance from the Government.(2) In the Chief Secretary&apos;s view no particular weight should be given toLord Cameron&apos;s recommendation on costs because he had no authorityto make any recommendation on this matter, and has no competence to assess possible repercussions.(3) The chain of events leading up to the inquiry can be traced back to anirresponsible complaint by N.U.B.E., which has been rejected byLord Cameron. It is not unreasonable therefore that they should haveto pay; indeed, in a legal action the costs of the other parties might well have been awarded against them.(4) It would be impracticable to isolate this case, and if assistance is granted,,organisations taking part in inquiries, for example under the industrial courts Act, might be encouraged to engage Counsel and would havea precedent for assistance with their costs. Indeed, it might be impossibleto reject any recommendation for costs made by a Judge or even by other independent chairmen.6. I agree that any assistance given would need to be related specifically tothis particular inquiry. In my view, a valid distinction can be drawn between this inquiry and others for which the Ministry is responsible. This is the only formalinquiry which has been set up by the Government at the I.L.O.&apos;s request. Thesubject matter, namely the examination of specific allegations of breach of anInternational Labour Convention, is quite outside the usual run of Ministry ofLabour inquiries, and gave scope for cross-examination and legal argument whichis normally absent in inquiries into industrial relations matters. If any additionalsafeguard is thought necessary, it would be possible where parties to inquiries setup by my Ministry propose to be represented by Counsel, to inform them that therecan be no Government contribution to their legal expenses.7. For obvious reasons, the employee organisations have not been asked forinformation about their costs. It is thought that they might be in the region of 10,000 to  12,000.1 am not asking for reimbursement in full, but for a contribution which in my view ought not to be less than 50 per cent.J. G.Ministry of Labour, S.W. 1,25th November, 1963


</content>
</cab>
