<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/21/0 images: 175-178</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENT)SECRETCP.(47)  267 COPY NO.23RD SEPTEMBER,  1947CABINETINTERIM REPORT OF THE WORKING PARTY&quot;ON STABILISATION OF wages memorandum by the President of the Board of TradeI would like my colleagues to consider the attachedstatement as an alternative to that attached as AppendixB to the paper CP, (47) 264 by the Minister of Labourand National Service.R a S . C .Board of Trade, S.W.1..23RD SEPTEMBER,  1947.
&apos; ANNEXALTERNATIVE DRAFT OP STATEMENT FOR DISCUSSIONWITH THE NATIONAL JOINT ADVISORY COUNCILIn his statement to the House of Commons on 6th Augustlast the Prime Minister made the following appeal to the two sides of industry;,  employers and workers:-&quot;I appeal to workers in all industries and employ-ments not to press at this time for increases of wages   -or changes in conditions which would have a similareffects especially where these increases are put forward on the &quot;basis of maintaining differentials betweenvarious categories of workers on the basis of formerpractice.      Equally, I would appeal to employers notto seek to tempt workers away from essential industries,thus creating a vicious spiral.&quot;The - Government feel that some amplification of this state-ment is needed for the guidance of both sides of industry.With greater exports and reduced imports there will be fewergoods to buy at home in the coming months and perhaps years.Higher wages now unless they result from higher productioncannot alter this fact.     Thus increases in wage.rates willnot enable wage earners to buy more, because the goods willnot be there;    they will merely increase the&quot;already severeinflationary pressure.     They will also seriously endangerour chances of achieving the export targets just announced,and thus of obtaining our essential imports;    for in a worldwhere competition will rapidly grow more severe, it is vitally important to keep down our costs of manufacture and transport.For these reasons,  increases in wage rates at the present timecannot be in the national interest, nor in the real interestof those who receive them, save in the most exceptional cir-cumstances.      The Government expect all parties to wage negotiations to base their actions on this principle.There are a very,few industries of fundamental importance which are seriously undermanned, and it may be necessary thatin some of these wages and conditions should be made more attractive, in relation to those in other industries, ifenough work people are to be encouraged to enter them.     Insuch industries,  some improvements may be necessary and serve the interests of &quot;us all by increasing their production and efficiency.     But the usefulness of any such improvements willbe destroyed if&quot;in other industries which compete with them for labour similar increases are made, so that the relative positionof the undermanned industries is not improved.In these circumstances,  the Government have decided andwish it to be clearly understood that, if notwithstanding these considerations wages are increased or hours reduced in any industry, there can be no presumption, whatever may have beenthe practice in the past, that the resulting costs will infuture be taken into account in settling controlled prices or margins or other financial matters requiring Government   .action.
The Government trust that all concerned&apos;will recognise-and accept tho need for this policy and that industries.not subject to price control will govern themselves by the same principles.     It is no less important that this policy shouldbe made effective in the present crisis than that our exporttargets should be achieved;    and indeed, unless it is made effective,  the achievement of. those targets will be gravelyendangered.     For inflation high costs and continued under-manning of key industries will upset the balance of our whole economy and frustrate all cur efforts to win through.The task of preventing this calls for the immediate co-operation of everyone in every industry and trade, employersand workers,  at all levels.As an immediate and positive step towards this end ithas been suggested to the National Joint Advisory council that any claim for Improved wages or conditions of employmentformulated before the Prime Minister&apos;s statement on 6th  -August should be re-examined, whether or not an appeal hasalready been lodged and whatever the stage that any jointnegotiation may already have- reached.     The National joint advisory Council have accepted the necessity for this sugges-tion, and- appeal to all the industries and trades concerned to give immediate effect to it.


</content>
</cab>
