<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/55/45 images: 486-491</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.SECRET Copy No.W.P. (44) 545.28th September, 1944.WAR CABINET.RELEASE OF CAPACITY FROM WAR PRODUCTION.Memorandum by the Minister of Production.IN my paper W.P. (44) 517 I outlined the effects of the programmeadjustments which seemed to follow from the assumption adopted by the WarCabinet (W.M. (44) 116, Minute 8) that the European Avar would end by the31st December. 1944. The Cabinet has authorised action to be taken on the lines indicated in that paper. Over the next few months it will involve releasingfrom munitions work a considerably larger number of workers than had previously been planned.2. I think that I should take an early opportunity of telling the House ofwhat is proposed, and I accordingly append the draft of a statement which Ipropose to make after Questions on Tuesday next, if my colleagues agree. I feelthat the House will undoubtedly ask for a debate on this important subject. Ihave therefore included in the draft an offer of a debate, and I ask my colleagues to agree that this offer should be made. I suggest that such a debate mightconveniently take place after the debate on the Minister of Labour*s White paper on the reallocation of man-power. The debate on reconversion would be more valuable if the House of Commons had discussed beforehand the Minister ofLabour&apos;s White Paper.3. The statement has been drafted with a watchful eye on American opinion in view of the negotiations concerning Lend-Lease in Stage II. The latestannouncement in the United States on reconversion was strictly related to theperiod after the cessation of hostilities in Europe. And although there havebeen some quite substantial cut-backs in certain parts of the United Statesmunitions programmes, we have to be very careful to avoid an announcement herein terms which would give the impression that we are taking advantage of american promises of Lend-Lease assistance in Stage II to get ahead of themin switching over to civilian production. The draft therefore contains the state-ment that only a small proportion of our resources can be released before theend of the European war, and that civilian standards cannot be appreciablyimproved until some little time after its end. In order, however, that there shouldbe no misunderstanding with the Americans or any possibility of accusations of bad faith, I should propose, if my colleagues agree, to let the Americans know,through Mr. Philip Reed, the Head of the Mission for Economic Affairs inLondon, the general scale of the programme adjustments we have already decidedto make and what are the man-power implications of those adjustments/ I&apos;, wouldalso propose to inform our Washington representatives. It is, I think, essentialthat the joint committee set up by the Prime Minister and the President shouldnot get.a mistaken impression of these developments through the Official Reportor from the press.4. I took the opportunity of discussing with the National ProductionAdvisory Council the machinery by which releases of labour and capacity wouldbe tied in with the requirements of civil industry. The President of the Boardof Trade was present, and dealt with his side of the subject, which is the useof the resources released. No statement was of course made to the Council aboutthe assumption as to the end of the Avar upon Avhich we are noAv Avorking.0. L.Ministry of Production,Great George Street, S.W. 1,28th September, 1944.[28298]
ANNEX.Draft Statement to Parliament.THE House will, I think, be interested to hear something- of the governments plans for the release of capacity from war production and the reconversion ofindustry to civil use at the end of the European war. This is a subject whichclearly cannot be dealt with comprehensively in a statement after Questions, andthe Government would willingly agree to a debate if this is asked for; but thematter is of such great public importance at the present time that the House would perhaps like to have, by way of preliminary, a bare indication of the governments plans.2. The production of munitions must continue to take first place. Japanhas still to be beaten and, for that matter, so has Germany, but when germany has been beaten the maintenance of a large naval striking force, the adaptation of equipment for tropical conditions, the transportation and maintenance of anarmy over supply lines of 10.000 miles and the equipment of the Air Force to flyover great distances are commitments which will continue to absorb a large partof our industrial capacity. Neither must we forget our other military commitments including those for the armies of occupation. To meet all these commitments we expect that by the end of the first twelve months after theEuropean war is over we shall have to retain at least as much of our munitionscapacity as we can release for civilian products.3. But in spite of these commitments, the military situation now clearlyentitles us to go further than before in making assumptions about our require-ments for the European war and the probable stocks of munitions we may have left at the end of it. Broad calculations of this kind are now being made, andsome of them converted into reduced programmes for individual stores. We are accordingly now in a position to make known our plans for using capacity for civilian production as and when the scale of munitions production can be pro-gressively reduced to new levels. I must make it clear, however, that only a small proportion of our resources can be released from war work before the european war is over. It follows, of course, that we cannot look forward to any appre-appreciable improvement of civilian standards until some little time after that.4. There are two distinct processes involved. The first is the framing ofour munition programmes so as to avoid excessive production, particularly inthose stores which are not required for the Japanese war. The second is the preparations which firms will wish to make themselves for change-over to civilianproduction.5. On the first point I will describe very briefly our objectives and the means by which we proposed to attain them. Whilst we must maintain the necessaryproduction of munitions we must also ensure that when the time comes munitionscapacity is released to those types of civilian production which are of the greatestnational importance and we must arrange as far as possible that releases of capacity take place in areas where the possibilities of re-absorption on suitablework are greatest, bearing in mind the particular needs of the development areas.6. As regards the second point, my Right Hon. Friend, the President of theBoard of Trade has already taken steps to inform industry that within certainlimits, and of course on the understanding that urgent or vital war production is not interfered with, his Department will consider applications for facilities toprepare drawings or to make prototypes, &amp;c. In this way the inevitable dislocation-tion involved by changes of this nature will be minimised.7. Information upon each of these aspects is now being given to the supply departments. This information, which is being daily expanded and kept up todate, is designed to show what capacity, if released, can quickly be used for civilian production of the kind most urgently needed, whether for capital equipment, for housing, for civilian consumption or for export. I will not dilateupon the well-established machinery which exists to consider the plans for changes in production drawn up by the Supply Departments in the light of theinformation given to them. This machinery provides for full consultation between all the Departments concerned at Headquarters, as well as for Regionalexamination or handling of particular aspects of the problem.
8. Discussions with an individual firm before the general plan has been drawn up will seldom be possible still less with an industry, because the pro-duction of each munitions store is spread over many different civil trades.Furthermore, we cannot guarantee equality of treatment between different industries or between different firms in the same industry. In deciding on newprogrammes and the firms affected we must be guided by the national interest.If we can also secure substantial equality of treatment we shall try to do so,but I must plainly tell the House that this will generally be impossible.9. The Government recognise very fully the difficulties which will confrontindustry, both managements and workpeople, during the process of reconversion,but these difficulties will have to be surmounted. I warn the House that perfectsynchronisation cannot be achieved, but our experiences in the large changes of programme which have been smoothly made over the last two years will standus in good stead.




</content>
</cab>
