<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/93/0 images: 32-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET      15 (58).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.  10,Downing Street,  S.W. 1.,  on TUESDAY,  22ndMARCH, 1958, at llo0 a. m.AGENDUM.FOREIGN AFFAIRS:    THE SITUATION IN CENTRAL EUROPE.CZECHO-SLOVAKIA.(Reference Cabinet 14 (38) Conclusion 2).Report by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee onthe Military Implications of German aggression against Czecho-Slovakia.F. P.   (35) 57 - already circulated.Oral Statement by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.(Signed)    M.P.A.  HANKEYoSecretary to the Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.21st March,  1938.REVISE. COPY NO.
SECRET. CABINET      15(58). COPY NO.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10 Downing Street,  S.W.L ,  on TUESDAY,the 22nd MARCH,  1938,  at 11.0 a.m,PRESENT:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,Prime minister the Right Hon,Sir John Simon,  CCS. I.,G.C.V.O.,  O.B.E., K.C, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.The Viscount    Halifax, L Gt,G.C.S.I.,  G.C.I.E.,  Secretary ofState for Foreign AffairscThe Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M. P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.W.  Ormsby Gore, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.S.O. ,  M. P. ,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.,Secretary of State for Air.M.C.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C, McP. ,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K.G.D.S.O.,M.C, President of the Board ofEducation.(Tn the Chair).The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord President of the Council.The Right    Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. , G.C.S.I. ,GoBoE.,  CMcGo, McP. ,  Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.,The Earl De La Warr,Lord Privy Seal*The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,Gt* C S * I * ,  G.CI.E. secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, CB.E. , K.C,M.P., Minister for Co-ordinationof Defence.The Right Hon.L.  Hore-Beiisha,  M. P. ,Secretary of State for War.The Right Kon,,       Walter Elliot, Mo C. , M.P. ,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right HornW.S.  Morrison, M.C, K.C. , M.P. .Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M. P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.E. La Burgin, M.P.,Minister of Transport.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, Mo Co, M. P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Earl Winterton, M.P*,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.Colonel Sir M.P*A- Hankey, Q.C.B., G.C.M.G., G.C.V.O.Secretary.
THE SITUATIONIN central europe.rizecho-slovakia.(previous reference:Cabinet 14 (38)Conclusion 2.)- 11 fit)1,      The Cabinet had before them a report prepared by the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee and circulated to the Committee on Foreign Policy onthe Military Implications of German aggression against Czecho-Slovakia (p,,p.  (36) 57),  the dominant conclusion of which was that no pressure which this country and its possible allies couldexercise would suffice to prevent the defeat ofCze cho-Slo vaki a.In addition to the above the following two papers which had been prepared for considerationby the Committee on Foreign policy had been circulated to the Cabinet, namely -The draft of a proposed communication to the French Government on the situationin Central Europe (F.P,  (36) 56);    andThe Draft of a statement to Parliament(P.P.  (36) 58)but, as a result of a meeting on the previous evening of the Committee on Foreign Policy, ithad been decided to redraft these memoranda and theyhad consequently been withdrawn from the agenda paper^The Prime Minister said he had asked theCabinet to meet exceptionally for the reason thata statement would have to be made on ForeignAffairs in the House of Commons this week, and it seemed probable that the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs would first have to communicate the gist of it to the French Government before it wasmade.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said there had not yet been time to circulate aredraft of the documents referred to above, and that
his object that day was to consult the Cabinet on thequestion of general policy       One result of what had happened in Austria was to render Czecho-Slovakiahighly vulnerable by opening up a new and open frontier to the possibility of German attacks     Both at home andabroad; therefore, there was grave anxiety aboutCzecho-Slovalia especially owing to the Frenchcommitments to that country,,      Two alternative proposals had been made for meeting this position;    first, thatthis country should guarantee Czecho-Slovakia, and second, that she should guarantee support to France if France took action .1n accordance with her Treaty,      he himself and? he thoughts the Prime Minister also had begun their examination with some sympathy towards theidea   of a guarantee *     Clearly, however, a decision could not bo a^reached without some kno?/ledge of themilitary position,     Consequently., the Chiefs of staff had been asked to present an immediate and clearAppreciation of the situation.     The     Report was an extremely melancholy document, but no Government could afford to overlook it.      In this connection, he read the following extracts from paragraphs 87 and 89 of theReports -&quot;We conclude that no pressure that we andour possible allies can bring to bear,either by sea, on land or in the air, couldprevent Germany from invading and over-running Bohemia and from inflicting a decisive defeat on the Czecho-SlovakianArmy.     We should then be faced with thenecessity of undertaking a war againstGermany for the purpose of restoringCzecho-Slovakiars lost integrity and thisobject would only be achieved by the defeat of Germany and as the outcome of a prolongedstruggle.     In the world situation to-day
it seems to us that if such a struggle wereto take place it is more than probable that both Italy and Japan would seize theopportunity to further their own ends, and thatin consequence the problem we have to envisageis not that of a limited European war only,but of a world ware&quot;&quot;The alliance with Yugo-Slavia, Roumania,Hungary, Turkey and Greece would be of limited assistance to Great Britain and France,and they might ultimately constitute anadditional embarrassing commitment by virtueof our moral obligation to assist them against german invasion.&quot;In addition,  the Report gave a deplorable account of theFrench air position (paragraph 16) as well as of our own position in respect of anti-aircraft defence (paragraph 10).In view of this Report,whatever hissympathies and anxieties, he felt he was not in aposition to recommend a policy involving a risk of war.Consequently, he had to consider the alternativeso     his suggestion was that we should endeavour to induce theGovernment of Czecho-Slovakia to apply themselves to producing a direct settlement with the Sudeten-Deutsch.We should also persuade the French to use their influence to obtain such a settlement.     He emphasised that the settlement he contemplated was between the czecho-Slovak Government and the Sudeten-Deutsch, and notGermany,.     In addition, it might be possible for theBritish and French Governments to approach the GermanGovernment with a view to acceptance of the settlement in Czecho-Slovakia.If the Cabinet would agree to a policy suchas the above based on methods of diplomacy and publicopinion, he would propose to instruct His Majesty&apos;ambassador in Paris to see one or more representatives...of the French Government and to talk to them quitefrankly on the basis of an aide memo ire.     He preferredthe idea of a conversation rather than a note.     The
3 5policy was likely to prove unpalatable to the French.Perhaps the Cabinet did not realise how unpalatable,Nevertheless; he saw nc escape unless we were going to adopt a course which he could not recommend0Moreover, however upset the French Government might be,he did not see what other alternative was open to them than to acquiesce0      It was a disagreeable business whichhad to be done as pleasantly as possible, and he thought the best method was by personal explanation.      Sir EricPhipps would be asked to explain the military situationand to emphasise our own position under the locarno treaty which would have to be placed rather in the forefrontHe would be asked to make clear that we bad undertaken veryconsiderable commitments, which we would fulfil, but also toleave no doubt that we could not accept new commitmentswithdrawing the decision on peace and war from our government and leaving it in the hands of the FrenchGovernment.     He would be told to emphasise our strong desire to maintain the closest possible relations with france but to urge that nothing could be so detrimental to those relations as to leave the decision on peace and war to France alonec      He proposed to inform the Frenchand Czecho-Slovakian Governmen ts of the pos ition on thefollowing afternoon and that statements should be made to both Houses of Parliament on Thursday afternoon0     He hadredrafted the proposed Parliamentary statement and he wouldbe glad if two or three of his colleagues would help himto put it into final shape0     The passage on the subjectof rearmament was still left blank in his redraft and he hoped that someone else would prepare iteThe Prime Minister said that the first thing wasto secure Cabinet approval to a general policy     Subject
to that he thought that the plan of the foreign secretary was feasiblec      In support of what theForeign Secretary had said, he drew the attention ofthe Cabinet to a passage in paragraph 20 of the Chiefsof Staff Report in which it was pointed out that -&quot;At present about 75 per cent, by weight ofCzecho-Slovakia&apos;s trade passes over german territory, and it would be possible for theGerman Government by abuse of tolls andtariffs on the Danube and the railways to force Czecho-slovakia into submission by economic pressure alone, without resort tohostilitiesc     This process would be facilitated if Germany secured the co-operation and control of Hungary0,:Suppose that we had made some belligerent threat toGermany and the Germans had resort to economic pressurewithout the use of force, we should find ourselves ina humiliating position.     He also drew attentionto   a   passage    in   paragraph   88   where    it   waspointed out that, in the circumstances of the present case, the potential threat of pressure of sea power would not necessarily deter Germany from action againstCzecho-Slovakia0     All this showed that if a decision were taken to guarantee Czecho-Slovakia, we should be ina most disadvantageous position when we came to implement ito      It was not necessary to be an expert tosee how difficult it would be for this country andFrance to prevent Czeoho-Slovakia from being over-runfrom germany      The French had committed themselves toan intention to make the attempt and were, of course,most desirous of getting us behind themQ      It was difficult to believe, however, that if the subject were discussed seriously between the two nations, theFrench would not be glad to find some method to relievethem of their engagement0     To all this there were two
corollaries:    the first that we should speed up our existing plans for rearmament - which would be far moreuseful than to announce new plans.     It would be necessaryto emphasise the importance of this in a statement toParliament by including rather a long passage.     Second,the sooner we could reach agreement with Italy the bettercThe conversations in Rome were proceeding with almostembarrassing ease and rapidity, having regard to thestatement to which the Government had committed itselfover Spain,The Foreign Secretary, in this latterconnection, said he was to see the Italian Ambassador thesame afternoon^Contributions were made to the subsequentdiscussion from various points of view.One view was that the policy proposed by theForelgn Secretary would be badly received in the House ofCommons, particularly by one group of supporters of theGovernment who desire a firmer policy     Moreover, itwould not please anyone very much.     It was further suggested that the policy would be tantamount to an invitation to Germany to take the next step in herprogramme.      It was recalled that the last German couphad been delivered in the Rhineland.     The public had notminded that very much as it had been widely felt thatGermany was entitled to move troops within her ownterritory.     Nevertheless, the Government had taken ratherstrong steps.     A meeting of the Locarno Powers had .been summoned in London, a questionnaire had been addressed tothe German Government and Staff Conversations had takenplace.     The present proposals to meet even more drastic action by Germany - to say nothing of a most menacingsituation - might be contrasted unfavourably: with the case
of tile Rhine1and*     The real danger, it was suggested, wasnot so much the menace to Czecho-Slovakia as the possibleToss of French friendship,,      If Germany entered Czecho-Slovakia, France had committed herself to take action,.She would probably be beaten and we should be thencompelled from the point of view of self-interest to join in the struggle, for we could not afford to stand aside and see France go undero     Our aid might well arrive too lateand France would be of no more value as a future ally0Was it not better, in these circumstances, to recognise the inevitable and plunge in at once to France&apos;s aid?It was true,as shown in the Chiefs of Staff Report, that theprospects of such action were most unfavourable0      TheChiefs of Staff, however, had been instructed to leaveRussia out of the c&apos; leu la t ion and possibly they had under-rated certain weaknesses in Germany as well as the drainof the China campaign on the strength of Japan,Admittedlyy however, the position as regards aircraft andguns was bad to--day0     Would the relative position be anybetter tomorrow?      The Chiefs of Staff, it was pointed out,had not dealt with the prospective situation a year or twohence when the smaller nations of Central and Eastern Europerr ght have all collapsed before German aggression.      Itmight be, as the Chiefs of Staff indicated, that, formilitary operations to-day, these small Powers were a debitrather than an assets     Under the hegemony of Germany, theywould become an immense source of strengthoto that country. TodajGermany was ill- prepare a for a long war.      Two years hencewith this access of strength ;.he might be much betterprepared for that contingency^      It was urged, therefore,that disadvantageous as might be the circumstances to-day for interventionr they would be still more so tomorrow0In fact, by abandonning Czecho-Slovakia and the small
nations, we should be assuming a new commitment that wouldmature a few years hence, namely, to meet Germany either in isolation or at least in co-operation with Prance.      Inaddition, it was urged that conversations with Italy wouldnot succeed if we abandoned Czecho-Slovakia, as theItalian Government would foresee the submission to germany of all her neighbours in succession,,     Among alternative suggestions were the following:-(l)    To tell the House of Commons that the whole situation in Europe had been changed by recent events?    that they could not expect theGovernment to formulate an entirely new policywithin ten days:    to add that the democraticPowers must stand together:    and to announce that the Government were in touch with the FrenchGovernment with a view to an early Conferenceand that their intention was to propose staff conversations.(2)    To approach the Czecho-Slovak Government and inform them that, if they were prepared to makereasonable proposals for dealing with the Sudeten-Deutsch, we should be prepared to support themand to act as a go-between with Germany.,(3)    Towards Germany, to adopt a firm line includingperhaps a 12 months guarantee of Czecho-Slovakia,during which proposals for dealing with thegrievances of the Sudeten-Deutsch and the GermanGovernment could be worked out.(4)   If it was not possible to help the Czecho-Slovaks,?ur policy should be to keep the Germansguessing.(5)   That, in any event, the proposed statement inParliament and the aide memoire to be presented by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paris at the endof his interview should be redrafted in such away as to show the utmost cordiality and goodwillto France and sympathy to Czecho-Slovakia.
The view that was accepted more generally and increasingly as the discussion continued was that the policy proposed &quot;by the Foreign Secretary and supported by thePrime Minister was the best available in the circumstances.Several Members of the Cabinet,  including the Prime Ministerand the Foreign Secretary,  admitted that they had approached the question with a bias in favour of some kind of guarantee to Czecho-Slovakia, but that the investigation atthe Committee on Foreign Policy   had changed their views.It was suggested that the policy proposed by the foreign secretary was likely to be generally approved by parliament and the country.    It was becoming increasingly clear thatthe people were not in favour of any new commitment.    a recent expression of views by important representativesof the City of London was mentioned in this connection.It was agreed, however, that there was an underlyingresentment at the idea of constantly having to knuckleunder to the Dictators for lack of sufficient strength.The best way to meet this view was to announce an acceleration of re-armament and opportunities for personal service.The question was discussed of whether a communication to France was necessary.    The Cabinet were reminded that theGovernment&apos;s attitude on the question of Czecho-Slovakiahad been made clear last November as well as in a Note to paris a fortnight ago on the subject of German aggression in Austria.    Conversations with the French Government wouldhave to take place as soon as the position of thatGovernment was more stable.    It would be unfair to let theFrench Government enter on those conversations on theassumption that our policy had changed.
While there was no suggestion that the foreignpolicy of this country could be subordinated to the views ofthe Dominions, the Cabinet were informed that a policy offurther commitments would be very unpopular in all theDominions, except possibly New Zealand, and might lead even to a crisis in our relations with some of the Dominions.At bottom, however, the difficulty was realised tobe that the position was such that even if we had the strength;we could not protect a country in the geographical positionof Czecho-Slovakia. Neither could the French,  and theRussians were separated from Czecho-Slovakia by the territory of Poland and Roumania-    No one could help in time.    Afterthe fall of Czecho-Slovakia, the French would remain behind the Maginot lines.    The Germans, owing to the strength oftheir Air Force,  could damage us more than we could damagethem.    At least two months would elapse before the UnitedKingdom could give any effective help to France.    meanwhile the people of this country would have been put in a positionof being subjected to constant bombing,  a responsibilitythat no Government ought to take.   ^In regard to the position two years hence, theCabinet were reminded that the Royal Air Force would at anyrate be armed with up-to-date aeroplanes and the anti-aircraft defences with modern weaponso    In addition to this improve-ment in quality,  there would be in existence an organisedactive and passive defence.In all the above circumstances it was generally felt that any policy of bluff would be dangerous, and thatit would be better to proceed on the idea that our perform-ance was almost better than our promise.    It would be a
mistake to plunge into a certain catastrophe in order toavoid a future danger that might never materialise.Various suggestions were made in the course ofthe discussion, which the Foreign Secretary undertook toconsider:    e.g., a strengthening of the parliamentary statement and of the proposed aide memoire by cordialreferences to France;    by developing at some length theextent of our commitments under the Locarno Treaty;    bymentioning the situation &quot;in the Far East;    and by proposing a Conference with the French Government and/or staff conversations.There was unanimous agreement that a reference should be included in the Parliamentary Statement as to improving our defensive position, and that the Minister forCo-ordination of Defence, in consultation with the service ministers, should draft it.The Cabinet were informed that the investigationsof tiie Secretary of State for Air had shown that some70,000 additional workers would be required for   theaircraft industry by co-operation between industry andlabour.      Further reinforcement would be required forengines and equipment.      A survey of the position as to rawmaterials shov/ed that this should occasion no insuperable difficulties.      By the end of the year it was estimatedthat the capacity in material (extrusions, etc.) would be ona sufficient scale to provide for as many as 800 aeroplanesa month.      Given the necessary labour there was everyhope therefore of a very material acceleration during thenext year, and this would not involve any alteration inthe present plans which had been framed to provide for alarge Force,  the date of completion depending on the labour available in the factories.      It was urged that if theStatement went into any detail, it should be made clearthat the sole need was not labour, but that industry as awhole must be organised.
The Cabinet were reminded that at the present timethe Defence Services v/ere working under instructions to cut down estimates $  and it was suggested that this was hardlyconsistent with an announcement that we were acceleratingour armamentSoOne suggestion was that in order to meet the strong desire exhibited by the people of this country to rendersome personal assistance in the present situation,  and atthe same time to improve our defensive position, some plan should be worked out, not involving conscription (since thatwas debarred by recent announcements of Government policy),and voluntary registrationbut appealing for voluntary help/in such matters as air raidprecautions;  ambulance services;  and so fortho    The objectshould be to strengthen the passive resistence of the nation-The Prime Minister thought there was a great deal to be said for this latter suggestion, but no scheme ought tobe adopted without careful investigation,  and that wouldrequire time?The Cabinet were reminded of the danger of obtainingmasses of volunteers,  and then having nothing for them to do.One suggestion for meeting this difficulty was that men might be obtained in great numbers from industry.   Correspondingsacrifices couldbeasked for from those who were relying on normal trade conditions for the delivery of goodscThe Minister for Co-ordination of Defence pointedout that the trend of the discussion seemed to indicate thatthe Cabinet were prepared to drop the earlier decision thatthe re-armament programme must be carried out without interference with industry.    Ke asked the Cabinet to adopta decision to this effect,
The Cabinet agreed:(a) To approve the policy proposed by theForeign Secretary and summarised onpage 3 above, namely, to undertake no new commitment involving a risk of war:to endeavour to induce the Government ofCzecho-Slovakia to apply themselves to producing a direct settlement v/ith the sudeten-Deutsch:    to try and persuade the French Government to use their influence to forward such a settlement:and if circumstances should render thisadvisable to arrange for a joint orparallel approach by the British andFrench Governments to the GermanGovernment with a view to acceptance ofany settlement which might be reached inCzecho-Slovakia?(b) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should be authorised to instructHis Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paris onWednesday, March 23rd,  to explainverbally to the French Government thepolicy of His Majesty&apos;s Government,and the military and other considerationson which it was based;(c) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should prepare, for the use ofHis Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Paria, an aide memoire baaed on the discussion atthe Cabinet, which he could communicateat the end of the conversation to theFrench Governments    (See also Note to conclusion (d) below,)(d) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should prepare a draft of thestatement to be made in both Houses ofParliament on Thursday, March 24th;that he should consider the inclusiontherein of suggestions made in thecourse of the meeting for strengthening the earlier draft by cordial references to our desire for close relations withthe French Government:    by emphasising the extent of the commitments we have assumed under the Treaty of Locarno;and by suggesting a Conference with theFrench Government     Reference might alsobe made to events in the Far East,Notes The Foreign Secretary was also asked to consider mention inthe aide, memo ire referred toin conclusion (&quot;c) above ofthe above points so far as appropriate, as well as of (fa? j*/Jreference to Staff Conversations/with the Grench Governments
That the Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence, in consultation with theService Ministers, should draft a passage in the statement for Parliamentrelating to the improvement of our defensive position;That the following Ministers shouldassist the Foreign Secretary in thepreparation of the draft statement toParliament, namely -The Prime Minister (if available)The Chancellor of the exchequer the President of the Board of Trade
FURTHERDEFENCEMEASURES.(PreviousRef6ren.ce:Cabinet 14 (38)Conclusion 4.)2.     Arising out of the discussion referred toin the preceding conclusion, the Cabinet agreed:(a) That the assumption on which the reconditioning of the Serviceshas been based, namely, that thecourse of normal trade should not beimpeded, should be cancelled:(b) That the question of announcing somescheme of harnessing the widespreadpopular desire to render personalassistance in the present difficultInternational situation should be reserved until suitable proposals have been produced and examined indetail.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.22nd March, 1938.

</content>
</cab>
