<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/18 images: 192-199</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   March 1941.SECRET.ii i 11       ii i -----tW.P. (41) 45.March 1, 1941.TO BE, KEPT UNDER LOCK anti K&amp;Y.It is requested chat special care may be t^ken toensure the secrecy of this document.POSSIBLE REVISION OF ITALO-YUGOSLAV FRONTIER IN ISTRIA.(Map attached.)Memorandum by the Foreign Office.SIR S. CRIPPS recently reported a suggestion by the Yugoslav Minister in moscow, M. Gavrilovitch, to the effect that the action of his countrymen,particularly the Croats, might be strongly influenced if His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment would convey to the Prince Regent that they would not make a separate peace with Italy on the basis of the status quo, but would recognise the claim of yugoslavia to the Istrian Isthmus as far as Gorizia and to the Italian islands offthe Yugoslav coast.2. His Majesty&apos;s Minister in Belgrade, in commenting on this suggestion,says that there may still be a latent fear in Yugoslavia that we might conclude aseparate peace with Italy at Yugoslavia^ expense, and that the prospect ofsecuring the Istrian isthmus and islands off the Yugoslav coast would appeal tothe Slovenes and Croats respectively. He also thinks that such an offer might serve as a counter-attraction to any offers which may have been made by theGermans, although beyond rare and vague hints about Istria he has not heardany expressions of desire for further territory.3. A preliminary examination has been made into the merits of a possiblerevision of the existing Istrian frontier, which is the result of direct negotiations between Italy and Yugoslavia, viz., those culminating in the Treaty of Rapallo ofthe 12th November, 1920, and in the Treaty of Rome of the 27th January, 1924.*There is little doubt that Italy had the best of the bargain, and the preliminaryreport suggests that Yugoslavia has a good claim on ethnographic grounds toby far the greater part of the Istrian isthmus (the western coastal strip alonebeing inhabited by Italians) and to all the Italian islands off the Dalmatian coastwith the exception of Lussin. The ethnographic claim does not include the citiesof Trieste, Gorizia, Fiume or Zara. The Yugoslavs in the districts in questionamounted in 1910 to roughly 488,000, whereas there were only about 50,000Italians outside the three cities of Trieste, Gorizia and Fiume. Economic and strategic considerations would modify the Yugoslav claims slightly in favour ofItaly.4. In short, there appears to be a strong case on an ethnographical basis for a revision of the existing I talo-Yugoslav frontier in Istria. The liberation of these Yugoslavs from Italian rule could also be justified on the ground thatthe Italians have done all they could to denationalise them by the suppression ofYugoslav schools, the exclusion of Yugoslavs from office, &amp;c.* It must be remembered that the history of this question is a thorny and complex one. ThePeace Conference at Versailles, and President Wilson personally, attempted to reconcile the conflicting claims of Italy and Yugoslavia, but unsuccessfully; and it was left to the disputantsthemselves, as shown above, eventually to come to an understanding, albeit an unsatisfactory one from Yugoslavia^ point of view.[22265]Copy No.
5. The Secretary of State is about to leave Turkey (where he will have seenSir S. Cripps, who would probably have mentioned the Yugoslav Minister&apos;proposal) in order to.visit Greece, and he has been trying to arrange that, while in Greece, he should have a secret meeting with the Prince Regent, or, failingthat, with either the Yugoslav President of the Council or Minister for ForeignAffairs.6. The King a few days ago sent a message to Prince Paul with the objectof eliciting, if possible, what his country&apos;s attitude would be towards the threatened German advance southward. We understand that a reply to this message has now been sent to the Secretary of State at Angora through the yugoslav Ambassador there, but we do not yet know its terms. From past experience we must expect that it will evade the issue. In these circumstances, itmight be of great assistance to the Secretary of State in any discussions he mayhave with the Yugoslav Government to be given discretion to inform them thatHis Majesty&apos;s Government are disposed to admit the case for revision of the Italo-Yugoslav frontier in Istria.7. It is true that His Majesty&apos;s Government have hitherto adopted thegeneral rule that during the war they cannot discuss any territorial changes, butthe decision of the Yugoslav Government at the present juncture is of such importance that it wOuld be worth while to disregard this rule on this occasionif by so doing we could induce Yugoslavia to intervene forcibly on behalf of greece.Foreign Office, March 1, 1941.







</content>
</cab>
