<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/143/0 images: 181-200</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
LoCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYTS GOVERNMENT)C(69) 86 COPY NO017th July, 1969CABINETWHITE PAPER ON SOCIAL INSURANCE benefits memorandum by the Secretary of State for Social ServicesMy colleagues will recall that the White Paper &quot;national superannuation and Social Insurance&quot; (Cmnd. 3883) described our proposals for -a fully earnings-related system of contributions, pensionsand other long-term benefits and for the establishment of a national superannuation Fund for pensions, widowhood benefits and death grant,the remaining benefits being paid from a Social Insurance Fund,,    TheWhite Paper said that the new arrangements for short-term sickness and unemployment benefit and the consequential changes in other insurance benefits, including maternity benefits and guardians allowances, and in industrial injuries benefits, would be announced separately,    I now seek the Cabinefs approval of the attached draft White Paper on these benefits which has been approved by the Social Services Committee.Short&quot; term benefits2,      The present provision for most short-term benefits (sickness and unemployment benefit and widows and maternity allowances) consists ofa flat-rate benefit title (governed by payment of the present flat-rate contribution), and of an earnings-related supplement which we introduced in 1966 and which is based on earnings between  9 and  30 a week.Our earlier White Paper (Cmnd, 3883) proposed that there should be asingle earnings-related short-term sickness benefit payable for up to sixmonths, after which the new earnings-related long-term sickness benefit which was described in that White Paper would become payable   However,in the course of the further work which has been done on sickness and unemployment benefit it has become clear that the replacement of thepresent two-tier system by a single earnings-related benefit creates someserious problems, e.g. in relation to the benefit formula itself and the structure of waiting days for sickness and unemployment benefit, and ithas not been possible to find solutions that are likely to be generally acceptable except at the cost of considerably greater expenditure.    We had,of course, hoped to get employers to take over responsibility for the earlyweeks of sickness, but our discussions with the Trades Union Congress(TUC) and Confederation of British Industry (CBI) have shown the impossibility at present of devising a satisfactory scheme on these lines.
3.      In this situation it is proposed that we should &quot;mark time&quot; on short-term benefits.    Unlike the long-term provision for the retired, thewidowed and the sick, there is already a substantial element of earnings-related provision for the short-term sick and unemployed.    The general public are just getting used to this new structure, and this is an important consideration when one remembers there are some 15 million short-termbenefit claims each year.    To keep changes in this part of the scheme tothe minimum will enable our publicity for the new scheme to be concentrated on its more novel aspects, e.gD for national superannuation and invaliditypensions.    A mark-time approach would also give us time to think againabout such major issues as the proper division of responsibility between employers and the State for workers who are sick for short periods.Moreover, in view of the rising level of sickness experienced and the investigation into the reasons for this which we have instituted, it would be premature to launch a completely new system of short-term benefits atpresent.    Finally it would be a good deal cheaper than any wholly earnings-related scheme that would be likely to be generally acceptable.4,      The proposals outlined in Part II of the attached White Paper have therefore been devised so as to reproduce as closely as possible the presentprovisions for unemployment and short-term sickness benefit and formaternity benefits and widows allowances with the minimum adaptationrequired to adjust them to the substitution of fully earnings-relatedcontributions for the present dual system.    The object has been as far aspossible to ensure that at the same earnings levels people will qualify forthe same benefit as at present, although of course, as promised in theWhite Paper, we shall provide that married women&apos;s rates of short-termbenefit are the same as those of other insured persons.    In the case of guardians allowance, however, which is payable in respect of orphans, Ipropose that this should cease to be an insurance benefit.    The presentcontribution conditions are purely nominal; it would be difficult to reproduce them in an earnings-related scheme, and the benefit is more closely analogous to family allowances.    I therefore propose that, likefamily allowances, it should be paid without an insurance condition andthe cost (which is about S.\ million a year) borne directly by the Exchequer.Industrial injuries benefits5,      In view of the limited nature of the changes proposed for short-term benefits, I propose to limit the changes in industrial injuries benefits tothose which ought to be adjusted to fit them to the new national insuranceprovisions, i.e. injury benefit and industrial death benefit.    Injury benefitneeds to be adapted to accommodate to the earnings-related addition toshort-term sickness benefit so as to deal with the possibility of substantialover-compensation.    As the new scheme matures, the time v/ill come whenfor widowed mothers and older widows the national insurance entitlementwould in many cases exceed the amount of industrial injuries widow&apos;pension if industrial injuries provision were continued on its present basis.In this situation the justification for the continuance of a preferential pension for industrial widows becomes very doubtful and could be embarrassing.-2-
CONFiDEMTSALIt would, however, be very difficult simply to remove the pensionpreference for industrial widows without providing anything in its place.Iam currently discussing with the TUC and. the CBI proposals for modification of the present industrial injury provision for injury benefit and death benefit, which will leave some preference over national insurance provision.    The White Paper accordingly makes only a general reference to changes in these benefits.Finance6,      The estimated cost of the benefits of the Social Insurance Fund,compared with the cost of corresponding benefits under the present scheme, is given in Table 3 of the White Paper,     The additional cost inthe early years is mainly accounted for by the proposals announced in cmnd. 3883 for giving married women the same rates of sickness and.unemployment benefit as other contributors.    This estimate does not,however, include the co6t of the new attendance allowance, the rate andprecise conditions for which have still to be settled.7.      In his memorandum on the Governments proposals in Cmnd.  3883the Government Actuary estimated that the contributions then proposed would be sufficient to maintain a balance of income and outgo in theSocial Insurance Fund if short-term benefits were on about the sames cale as in January, 1969j and would provide contributions for industrial injuries benefits and the National Health Service at about the same levelin relation to earnings as they were then.    Taking account of the latest estimates of sickness experience assumed for the purpose of his reporton the recent National Insurance Bill, the Government Actuary nowestimates that a contribution of about 2, 2 per cent of earnings from employers and employees would, together with the 18 per centcontribution from, the Exchequer already proposed, be required to finance the benefits proposed to be paid from the Social Insurance Fund(apart from attendance allowance),    This allows for a contribution tothe National Health Service of \ per cent a side which would yield rather more in relation to 1969 earnings than the present Health service contribution (the vixcess would be abeut  40 million a year - equivalentto nearly 0, 1 per cent a side on the contribution).    However, the actualrate of contributions to be specified in the Bill will depend on our final decisions on the new scheme as a whole and the size of the Health service contribution; and the rate to be charged at the outset of the scheme willhave to be kept under review in the light particularly of the trend ofuneirployment and sickness experience.conclusion. I seek the Cabinet1 e approval of the attached draft White Paper for early publication.R.H.S. C.Department of Health and Social Security, S.E, 1.17th July, 1969-3-
Proof for Official Use OnlyDEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND  SOCIAL SECURITYSocial InsurancePROPOSALS FOR EARNINGS-related short-TERM AND INVALIDITY BENEFITSPresented to Parliament by the Secretary of State for Social services by Command of Her majesty july 1969
CONTENTSParagraphIntroduction        ................ part I       Objectives       ...........      ..      .. part II     Benefits......      .......... 15Unemployment and Sickness Benefits   ..      ..      .. 17Invalidity Pension         ..      ..      ..      ..      .. 25Attendance Allowance   ..      ..      ..      ..      .. 28Maternity Benefit ..      ..      ..      ..      ..      .. 29Widow?s Allowance       ..      ..      ..      ..      .. 30Guardian&apos;s Allowance    ..      ..      ..      ..      .. 31Child&apos;s Special Allowance       ..      ..      ..      .. 32Industrial Injuries Benefits       ..      ..      ..      .. 33Part III     Financial Implications............ 37PageAppendix   Contributions and pensions under the national superannua-tion scheme expressed at 1969 levels  ..      ..      ..      .. 17
SOCIAL INSURANCEPROPOSALS FOR EARNINGS-RELATED SHORT-TERM  ANDINVALIDITY BENEFITSIntroduction1. In the While Paper &quot; National Superannuation and Social Insurance &quot;*the Government announced thai the present national insurance scheme will bereplaced by a new scheme of national superannuation and social insuranceunder which employees will pay wholly earnings-related contributions and earnbenefits based upon them. There will be two separate funds -one for national superannuation and one for social insurance.2. That White Paper dealt with national superannuation and other long-term benefits and explained Ihc new system of earnings-related contributions.Stamped cards and flat-rate contributions will be abolished for all employeescovered by P.A.Y.E. and Ihe new contributions will be collected through theP.A.Y.E. system. This further White Paper sets out the Government^ proposalsfor social insurance benefits. It explains how the earnings-related benefits forthe fust six months of sickness, unemployment and widowhood, already inlro-reproduced in 1966, will fit into the new scheme. It also describes the consequentialchanges in other benefits. It also gives more detail on what is proposed forthe long-term sick and disabled.3. Since the publication of&quot; National Superannuation and Social Insurance &quot;last January the Government have held consultations with both sides of industryand other interested organisations. These consultations are continuing and extend to the proposals in (his While Paper. The new scheme has been widelydiscussed in the Press and those who have sent in their comments include notonly representatives of particular groups but individual citizens. Everyone has adirect personal interest in the future of social security and the Government have welcomed the fact that so many people have expressed their views. legislation is planned for the 1969-70 Session of Parliament. The target date for starting thescheme is April 1972.4. Part I of this White Paper explains the objectives of the proposed social insurance benefits. Part II describes the benefits. Part III deals with the financial implications.*Cmncl. 3883.
objectives5. in 1968 there were over 11 million claims for sickness or injury benefit and over 3 million claims for unemployment benefit. on average, over a thirdof the working population makes at least one claim for one or other benefit eachyear. people with good health and a steady job may seldom need to claim. for those whose employers provide generous sick pay, state benefits are less impor-tant. but for many millions of others, sickness and unemployment benefits arestill the main source of income when they are unable to work.6. these benefits must be high enough for the risks of sickness and unemploy-ment to be faced without anxiety and the realities met without hardship. most people have financial commitments which they cannot quickly abandon whenfaced with a sudden and drastic drop in income. the scale of commitments which people undertake for rent or mortgage, for hire purchase or privateinsurance depends upon what they earn. even the higher paid can be in financial difficulty if they cannot work but a family man with low earnings needsvirtually his whole wage packet for daily living. thus his social insurance benefit needs to be a high proportion of his weekly earnings and to take specialaccount of the size of his family. need cannot be met by flat-rate benefits alone.thus in 1966, the government added to the old flat-rate benefits new earnings-related supplements for the first six months of sickness, unemployment andwidowhood.7. on the other hand, benefits must not be so high that people have no incentive to return to work when they are sick or unemployed. nor mustpeople who are at work and paying their contributions feel that they would beno worse off if they did not work at all. in recent years there have been criti-cisms that the present benefit rates are too high a proportion of earnings. partof this problem is due to low pay in some areas and in some occupations. butpart was due to the failure to increase family allowances as prices and earningsrose. while the allowances paid for children as part of sickness and unemploy-ment benefit were regularly raised, family allowances were not. this meant that,with these extra allowances for his children, a low earner could receive morewhen he was sick or unemployed than when he was earning. this was one ofthe reasons why the government increased family allowances. the higher the allowances for children which are paid whether the father is working or not,the lower the allowances for children need to be which are paid as part of sick-ness and unemployment benefit.8. under the proposals already published, people in employment will pay a wholly earnings-related social insurance contribution through the p.a.y.e.system. the stamped contribution card, a familiar symbol of social security for more than half a century, will cease to exist in the day-to-day dealings ofemployers, workers, employment exchanges and social security offices. many of
the present conditions and arrangements for short-term social insurance bene-fits are based upon this record of contributions. So some changes must beintroduced for this reason alone. But the Government have had to considerwhether to go beyond this and substitute for the present short-term benefits,consisting of a flat-rate part and an earnings-related supplement, a fully earnings-related system as envisaged in paragraph 87 of &quot; National Superannuation and social Insurance &quot;.9. Consultations on the proposals in that White Paper have shown that thereare strong arguments for keeping the present structure of short-term benefits for the time being. The general public and employers are only just getting usedto them and they are working well. At a time when the new national superannua-tion scheme is being introduced, a radical change in the structure of short-term benefits should be avoided unless there is a need for substantial further improve-ment in the level of these benefits. This is not so.10. One possibility which the Government have carefully investigated is thetransfer of responsibility for payments for the early weeks of sickness from thesocial insurance scheme to employers. The case for this transfer is that it would avoid the considerable waste which can occur where employers&apos; sick pay schemes and sickness benefit overlap. Often the result of all the administrative workundertaken by the Department in awarding sickness benefit, and by employers in awarding sick pay, is to provide the worker with his normal pay or somethingclose to it. Indeed if his pay is fully made up by his employer, he may receive more when sick than at work, because sickness benefit is not taxed. After discus-sions with both sides of industry, the Government found that, because of cost and other serious practical difficulties, a transfer could not be arranged intime for the start of the new scheme. However, the number of workers coveredby voluntary sick pay schemes is likely to grow, and the Government will later on explore further the possibility of introducing a statutory scheme which wouldprovide a minimum, of sick pay for all employees. This is a further reason why this is not the time to make radical changes in the present structure of short-term benefits.11. The Government have decided, therefore, that for the time being thepresent main structure of short-term benefits will continue but changes will haveto be made to fit in with the new system of contributions. Details are given inPart II.12. At present, providing 156 contributions have been paid, flat-rate sickness benefit can be drawn indefinitely. Under the new scheme short-term sickness benefit will be paid for up to 28 weeks. After this, the new long-term sickness benefit described in paragraphs 88 and 89 of &quot; National Superannuation and social Insurance &quot; will take its place. This new benefit, to be known as &quot; invali-dity pension &quot;, will be calculated in the same way as the new earnings-relatedretirement pension. In practice, most of those who will receive the new benefit will be in their fifties and sixties. The latest available figures (Table 1) show that,of 396,000 people who had been sick for more than 26 weeks on 3rd June 1967,291,000 (73 per cent) were over fifty. For those who will never be well enough toreturn to work, the new invalidity pension will be paid until it is replaced byretirement pension.
TABLE IDuration of sickness benclilPersons sick on 3rd Juno 1967Tlioiismiils*	Men				Women						Over				Over		All	Up to	26 &amp;	Over	All	Up to	26 it	Over	dura-	26	up to	52	dura-	26	tip to	52	lions	weeks	52	weeks	tions	weeks	52	weeks			weeks				weeks	All ages	738	438	59	241	228	132	14	82Up to 19	24	21	1	1	29	27	1	20 to 29	71	64	3	5	48	42	2	430 to 39	91	74	5	12	24	15	T	840 to 49	129	89	9	32	41	19	3	1950 to 59	214	III	20	83	81	26	6	4960 to 64	193	70	21	103	4	2		165 to 69	15	7	1	7	 	 	&apos; 	 *l!eeause of rounding, sub-lolals do not necessarily agree with totals.13. The Government have been particularly concerned to improve the benefitspaid to disabled people. The new invalidity pension and the new attendance allowance&apos;1&quot;&apos; have been specially designed to concentrate improvements in benefits on distillled people who have the severest hardship; on people of working agewith an injury or illness which keeps them oil&apos; work for a long period and onpeople who can never work again.14. The proposals in (his While Paper, and those already announced for national superannuation, complete the Governments plans Tor a major recon-st met ion of the present national insurance scheme which they promised whenthey came to power. Much remains to be done to bring these plans into opera-lion and inevitably many years must elapse before the scheme can come fully into effect. But (he Government arc satisfied that the road Ihey have chosen isthe right one for I be people of this country. The next slcp is legislation in thenext session of Parliament.*Cmnd. 3883, paragraphs 90-91.
BENEFITS15. In &quot; National Superannuation and Social Insurance &quot; all details of social insurance benefits were illustrated in terms of earnings and benefits as at April1968. But those figures were only illustrations. At the core of all the Govern-ment&apos;s proposals is the recognition that both benefits and the earnings &quot; ceiling &quot;up to which contributions are paid, must be reviewed regularly every two years.The April 1968 figure of national average earnings was  22 5s. a week but it isprovisionally estimated that in April, 1969 the figure had risen to  24.f this new level of earnings is used for illustrative purposes in this White Paper. Thepensions that would be paid on this new earnings level if the new scheme were fully mature are shown in the Appendix (Table 5).16. The Government have already announced increases in pensions and benefits which will come into effect in November this year. The main ratesfor a single person will be increased from  4 10s. to  5 and, for a married couple, from  7 6s. to  8 2s. To avoid confusion, these new rates are quotedthroughout this White Paper. The Government have also announced the highercontributions which have to be paid to earn the new pensions and benefits.The increases in contributions were deliberately designed to ease the transitionbetween the old scheme and the new. Table 4 in the Appendix compares thecontributions which would be payable in the new scheme, on the basis of April1969 earnings, with those payable under the present scheme as from November1969.Unemployment and sickness benefits(i) Amount of benefit17. Unemployment and sickness benefits will, as now, consist of two parts.The first part will be, as at present, flat-rate a personal benefit of  5, withthe standard allowances for dependants. People with average weekly earnings ina specified income tax year of  8 6s. 8d.* (at April 1969 levels) or more will earnthis full flat-rate benefit. Reduced rates of flat-rate benefit will be earned by those with average earnings of at least half this amount. Married women will receivethe same personal rate of benefit as other contributors.18. The amount of the flat-rate benefit will be reviewed every two years, as explained in paragraph 101 of &quot;National Superannuation and Social Insurance &quot;,and the level of earnings needed to qualify for flat-rate benefit will go up in proportion to the increases in benefit.tHere, as in Cmnd. 3883, &quot; national average earnings &quot; is used, for convenience, lo mean the average earnings of adult male manual workers in manufacturing industries and certainnon-manufacturing industries and services, as obtained from the Department of employment and Productivily&apos;s half yearly enquiries into earnings.This is the level of earnings which, under the proposals for national superannuation,produces a pension of  5.
19. The second part of benefit will be based on (he claimants average weekly earnings (calculated as one-fiftieth of the earnings on which contributions havebeen paid in a tax year). It will consist of one-third of weekly earnings between 8 6s. 8d. and the earnings ceiling (one and a half times national average earnings- 36 at April 1969 levels).(ii) Entitlement to benefit20. Most people who are treated as employed persons for national insurancepurposes also come within the P.A.Y.E. system and vice versa. In general,therefore, earnings which are covered by the P.A.Y.E. system will count for sickness and unemployment benefit (as contributions will have been paid outof them). Earnings in each income tax year will give the right to benefit in any period of sickness or unemployment starting in the next &quot; benefit year &quot;. Whenflat-rate sickness or unemployment benefit is calculated, allowance will he madefor any period of sickness or unemployment during the tax year from which the calculation of earnings is made.(iii) Duration of benefit21. An employed person will be able to receive a maximum of: (a) 168 days (28 weeks) of flat-rate sickness benefit;(b) 312 days (52 weeks) of flat-rate unemployment benefit;(c) 156 days (26 weeks) of earnings-related supplement payable with eitherbenefit (or maternity allowance or industrial injury benefit).It will be seen (hat (he maximum period for which unemployment benefit canbe drawn will he the same as under the present scheme. A person who hasused up his or her entitlement lo unemployment benefit will be able to requalifyby further earnings as an employed person. Under the new scheme, however,sickness benefit will be limited lo twenty-eight weeks, as the new invalidity pension will replace it when sickness lasts longer than this.22. Under the present scheme spells of sickness and unemployment whicharc not separated by more than 13 weeks are linked together to form one&quot; period of interruption of employment &quot;. This rule is used in deciding whether there are waiting days before benefit is payable and in calculating the maximum period for which benefit can be drawn. This rule will continue unchanged.So also will the rules about waiting days.&apos;&quot;(iv) The self-employed23. As explained in Cmnd. 3883, (he self-employed will continue lo pay flat-rate contributions. They will be able lo qualify for flat-rate sickness benefit under much the same arrangements as at present. For this purpose each con triebution as a self-employed person will be counted as one week of earnings at 8 6s. 8d. If sickness continues after (he twenty-eighth week the self-employedwill be entitled to invalidity pension as set out in paragraph 25.There arc three wailing clays for Hal-rale benefit. No payment is made lor these claysunless there are at least 12 clays of sickness or unemployment within the 13 weeks beginning with the first waiting clay. There are 12 waiting clays at the start of each period of interruption of employment before earnings-related supplement becomes payable.
(v) New Entrants24. Under a social insurance scheme, the right to benefit is earned by contri-butions paid during an earlier period. This creates difficulties for people (e.g.,school-leavers) when they first join the scheme. There are therefore special rulesunder the present scheme to allow them to qualify for flat-rate sickness and unemployment benefit without having paid the full amount of contributions which would normally be required. Similar arrangements will be made underthe new scheme. There will also be special arrangements, as now, to enablewidows who do not qualify for a widow&apos;s pension (or qualify for a pensionbelow the standard flat-rate benefit) to draw flat-rate sickness and unemploy-ment benefit.Invalidity Pension25. Anyone who is still sick after drawing sickness benefit for twenty-eight weeks will be able to receive an invalidity pension. This will be calculated inthe same way as the new earnings-related retirement pension with the exceptionthat credits will be given for the years remaining up to pension age. Normallya credit of one-half of national average earnings will be given. For this purpose,self-employed contributions will also count as if they have been paid on halfnational average earnings.26. The rate of pension will consist of 60 per cent of earnings up to halfnational average earnings and 25 per cent of any further earnings up to themaximum (one-and-a-half times the national average). How this will work inthe case of men becoming sick at different ages is shown in the following table.The examples show what will happen when the scheme is fully mature. (Therewill be a gradual build-up to these rates during the first twenty years of thescheme as described in paragraph 61 of Cmnd. 3883.) The table assumes averagepre-sickness earnings ( 24 a week at April 1969 levels).TABLE 2Age of			Life	Singlefalling	Earnings	Credits	average	benefitsick			earnings	rate59	40 years at  24	6 years al  12	 22  9s.	 9 16s.49	30 years at  24	16 years at  12	 19 17s.	 9   3s.39	20 years at  24	26 years at  12	 17  4s.	 8 10s.29	10 years at  24	36 years at  12	 14 12s.	 7 17s.20	1 year at  24	45 years at  12	 12  5s.	 7   5s.27. Flat-rate increases will be paid for a dependent wife and children as inthe case of short-term benefits, but there will be a different test of dependencyfor the wife who works. Under the present scheme a man who is sick cannot get an allowance for his wife (or other adult dependant) if her net earnings archigher than the standard amount of the allowance  3 2s. a week. This rulewill continue to apply to sickness and unemployment benefit. For the wivesof invalidity pensioners, however, the test of dependency will be the more generous earnings rule which applies to retirement pensioners. (This rule will allow them to earn up to  7 10s. a week net without any reduction of benefit
with a &apos; tapering &apos; reduction for any earnings above that level.) This will be ofgreat help to families where the man has been sick for a long time and the wifeis working. The new rule will also apply where the wife of a retirement pen-sioner is under 60 and is working. Although it is a much more complicatedrule to work it can be applied to these two groups because the number ofclaimants is relatively small and the claims generally last a long time.Attendance allowance for the very severely disabled28. In the earlier White Paper, the Government announced the introductionof a new social insurance benefit attendance allowance. This is to help thosewho have for some time been so severely handicapped that they need a greatdeal of help from other people. The allowance will be flat-rate. Those who arealready very severely disabled when the allowance is introduced will he able toreceive it. The allowance will be paid in addition to invalidity pension, retire-ment pension or widow&apos;s benefit. There will also be a corresponding allowanceunder the supplementary benefits scheme to help people, such as those disabledfrom birth, who have been unable to earn and thus pay contributions and have little or no resources of their own. Rut a wife who has not herself been payingcontributions will be able to receive attendance allowance as a social insurance benefit earned by her husband&apos;s contributions. Further details of this newbenefit will be announced later.Maternity Benefit29. As at present, maternity allowance will be paid for eighteen weeks (the expected week of confinement and the eleven previous and six subsequent weeks).The earnings conditions and rales of benefit will be the same as for sickness benefit (sec paragraphs 17-19 above). There will continue to he a lump summaternity grant.Widow&apos;s Allowance30. Wiclow&apos;s allowance, like sickness benefit, will continue to consist of two parts. There will be a flat-rale benefit, but as now al a higher level, and anearnings-related supplement based on the husband&apos;s earnings.Guardian&apos;s Allowance31. At present, guardiaifs allowance, al a Hal-rale of  2 9s. ji week, is paidto people caring for children who are without parents. The benefit will beretained in much the same form as now. But in future it will be financed, likefamily allowances, direct from the Exchequer instead of from (he national insurance Fund.Cltild&apos;s Special Allowance32. CliikPs special allowance is paid for a divorced woinan&apos;s children afterthe death of their father if he was maintaining or liable to maintain them andif she has not remarried. The allowance, which is at the same rates as for thechildren of a widowed mother, will be retained in the new scheme.
Industrial Injuries Benefits33. The only benefits of the industrial injuries scheme which will be changedare those for which there are broadly corresponding provisions under the mainnational insurance scheme industrial injury and death benefits. No change will be made in industrial disablement benefit the most important benefit ofthe scheme. This will be continued as a &apos; loss of faculty 1 benefit paid to thosedisabled by industrial accident or prescribed industrial disease, and there willbe no substantial change in the associated allowances.34. Injury benefit which is paid for the first six months of industrial in-capacity will be adjusted to take account of the new arrangements for sickness benefit. It is intended, however, that injury benefit will continue to be higherthan sickness benefit. The opportunity will be taken to bring the benefit more closely into line with the short-term social insurance benefits of the main scheme,and to deal with certain aspects of &apos; over-compensation &apos;.35. The new national superannuation scheme will greatly improve pensions for widows. The earnings-related pension to which older widows or widowed mothers will become entitled would, as the scheme matures, in many casesexceed the flat rate of industrial widow&apos;s pension, if this were to continue in itspresent form. There is, therefore, little place for a special pension for industrialwidows and the Government intend that industrial widows will, as far aspossible, rely on the pensions under the national superannuation scheme. Someelements of preference will, however, be retained.36. Details of these changes will be settled when the current consultations with both sides of industry have been completed.
PART IIIFINANCIAL IMPLICATIONS37. Under the existing scheme all national insurance contributions are paid into one Fund and all national insurance benefits are paid out of it. Under thenew scheme, as explained in Cmnd. 3883, this single Fund will be replaced by two Funds, the National Superannuation Fund and the Social Insurance Fund,so as to reflect the different nature of the benefits concerned and to help people to understand the purposes for which they are contributing. The Social In-surance Fund will receive the appropriate proportions of the total contributions paid by employers and insured persons* and the Exchequer contributions. Themoney in the Social Insurance Fund including the appropriate proportionof the total reserves of the present schemes will bring in interest which will,as now, help towards meeting the scheme&apos;s expenditure.38. With April 1972 as the target date for starting the new scheme, substantial additional cost on social insurance benefits will first arise during 1973-74, whenemployed married women who have chosen not to contribute to the present scheme will qualify for sickness and unemployment benefit and the effect ofthe new rules for calculating the short-term social insurance benefits will first be felt. Thereafter, leaving aside the inevitable fluctuations due to changes inthe levels of sickness and unemployment there will be a steady rise in the costof the benefits paid from the Social Insurance Fund, mainly because of increasing numbers of insured persons and the increase in the average rate of invalidity pension as the scheme matures. The estimated cost of the benefits for the first twenty years of the new scheme compared with the estimated cost of continuing the present benefits, is set out in the following table.*Cmncl. 3883 (paragraph 56) proposed thai, of the total contribution rate of 6j per centpayable by employees, 4.1 per cent would be for national superannuation and the remaining2 percent would be for social insurance benefits, industrial injuries benefits and a contribution towards the National Health Service.
TABLE 3Estimate by the Government Actuary of the cost of social insurance benefits including industrial injuries benefits, for present and proposed schemes (calculated at April 1969 earnings levels)  million	1973-74	1977-78	1982-83	1987-88	1992-93Short term sickness benefit Present scheme      ...... Extra cost    ......	270 51	270 63	273 63	278 63	290 69Proposed scheme	321	333	336	341	359Unemployment benefit Present scheme Extra cost    ......	108 21	110 27	112 30	118 32	122 32Proposed scheme    ......	129	137	142	150	154Invalidity pension (long term part of sickness benefit under present scheme) Present scheme Extra cost    ......	136 8	136 35	138 54	142 81	146 101Proposed scheme	144	171	192	223	247Maternity Benefit Present scheme Extra cost    ......	47 8	49 10	52 11	57 12	60 14Proposed scheme    ......	55	59	63	69	74Industrial Injuries Benefits*  ...	116	117	120	122	125Total cost of benefits Present scheme      ...... Extra cost    .........	677 88	682 135	695 158	717 188	743 216Proposed scheme    ......	765	817	853	905	959*These estimates are based on the cost of the present scheme excluding that part of widow&apos;benefit which will be met from the National Superannuation Fund.notes :1. For the above estimates the rates of benefit proposed for November 1969 in the national insurance (No. 2) Bill 1969 have been adjusted to their April 1969 equivalents.2. As in Cmnd. 3883 a long term unemployment rate of 2 per cent has been assumed. a variation of 0.1 percent in this assumed rate would alter the benefit cost by about  10m. a year.3. Account has been taken of the latest estimates of sickness experience (see the Govern-ment Actuary&apos;s Report (Cmnd. 4074) on the National Insurance (No. 2) Bill 1969).4. The estimates in the Table are provisional pending the comprehensive actuarial reviewbeing undertaken in preparation for legislation implementing the proposals in Cmnd. 3883and in this White Paper. Moreover no estimate can yet be included for the new attendance allowance.5. As in the estimates in Cmnd. 3883, the cost of widow&apos;s allowance is assumed to be met from the National Superannuation Fund.
39. The Social Insurance Fund will, like the National Superannuation Fund,be run in principle on a pay-as-you-go basis. There are, however, difficultieswhich are special to the Social Insurance Fund. Unlike the National Super-annuation Fund it will be particularly susceptible to short-term fluctuations dueto such factors as sickness epidemics, or changes in the level of unemployment.Therefore the rate of contribution needed to provide the Social Insurance Fundwilh an adequate working balance will necessarily be subject to more frequentvariation than the rate required for the National Superannuation Fund. Thisis one of the reasons why it is proposed to separate the two Funds.40. In his Memorandum on the Governments proposals in Cmnd. 3883 theGovernment Actuary estimated that, allowing for the ending of the marriedwomen&apos;s option and the introduction of invalidity pension, the contributionsthen proposed would be sufficient to maintain a balance of income and outgo inthe Social Insurance Fund if short-term benefits were on about their present scale;and that they would also provide contributions for industrial injuries benefits and towards the cost of the National Health Service at about the same level asthen in relation to earnings. This was on the basis that the employee would pay 2 per cent of earnings subject to a ceiling of about H times national average earnings. The employer would contribute the same percentage of earnings but without a ceiling. The Exchequer would contribute to the Social insurance fund approximately the same proportion of contributions from insured persons and employers as at present and as is proposed for the National SuperannuationFund, i.e. about 18 per cent.41. Taking account of the improvement in benefits set out in Part TI of this white Paper, and of the latest sickness experience, the Government Actuarynow estimates that to finance the benefits apart from attendance allowance aswell as allowing for a National Health Service contribution of half a per cent a side, the contribution of 2 per cent of earnings from, employers and employeesmight need to be increased. On present indications this increase might need to be about 0.2 per cent a side, but the actual rate of contributions specified inthe legislation to be introduced in the next session of Parliament will dependon final decisions on the proposals for the new scheme as a whole and for theNational Health Service contribution. The rate required when the schemestarts may need to be higher or lower; it will in any case have to be kept underreview in the light, particularly, of the trends in sickness and unemploymentexperience.
APPENDIXContributions and pensions under the national superannuation scheme expressed at 1969 levelsCmnd. 3883 proposed that employees should contribute (for all purposes) atotal of 6J per cent of earnings covered by the scheme, and that the pensionprovided (when the scheme is fully mature) should be 60 per cent of earnings up to half the national average, plus 25 percent of earnings between a half andone-and-a-half times the national average.Tables 2 and 3 of Cmnd. 3883 show the contributions and pensions of thenew earnings-related scheme in terms of 1968 earnings, contributions and benefitlevels. The following tables give comparable figures relating to 1969, makinguse of the contributions and benefit rates which will come into force in November1969 and of a figure of national average earnings provisionally estimated at 24 a week for April 1969. Accordingly the earnings ceiling of the new schemeis assumed to have risen from  1,700 a year (about  33 a week) to  1,900(about  36 a week).TABLE 4Total present-scheme and new-scheme contributions (including amounts for the industrial injuriesscheme and the National Health Service) paid by employees (not contracted out)Level of weekly earnings	Present scheme (November 1969 rates) Employee^ total weekly contribution (flat-rate plus graduated)		New scheme Employee^ total contribution (expressed as a weekly rale)		Change in contributions	(1)	(2)		(3)		(4)	Men	s.	d.	s.	d.	s.	cl. 12(1 national average) ...	20	9	16	2	- 4	7 18 H national average) ...	26	6	24	4	- 2	2 24 (national average)	30		32	5	-1- 2	0 30 (II national average)...	34	0	40	6	-1- 6	6 36 (I+ national average)...	34	0	48	7	-1-14	7Women						 S............	15	0	10	10	- 4	2 12............	18	1	16	2	- 1	11 18............	23	10	24	4	-1-	6 24............	27	9	32	5	+ 4	8 30............	31	4	40	6	^ 9	2 36............	31	4	48	7	-1-17	3The figures for women in column (2) are for those contributing under the present flat-ratenational insurance scheme. For married women and widows who have opted not lo do so(and who will therefore be liable only for the industrial injuries contribution of 8d. a week)the figures in column (2) wilt all be 14s. 4d. less; and 14s. 4d. therefore needs to be added tothe figures in column (4).
TABLE 5Fully mature ncw-sclienic pensions for a single person, illustrated at April 1969 earnings levels,and compared with the present-scheme pensions payable in November 1969Proportion of national average earnings achieved by pensioner over working life (1)	Col. (1) at 1969 earnings levels (2)	Fully mature new-scheme pension at 1969 earnings levels (3)	Present-scheme pension in November 1969 (4)				Flat rate	Graduated	jr.	     s.	I	s.\ (changeover point in the pension				formula)	12	7   4	5	2j    ...............	18	8 14	5	8 .1 (average)        .........	24	10   4	5	11Li    ...............	30	11 14	5	II1J (the schemed ceiling)......	36	13   4	5	11(ti) Earnings and pensions arc given in weekly rates, with earnings rounded to (he nearest  and pensions to (he nearest shilling.(It) The graduated pension amounts shown in column (4) are those for a man, whoseearnings are assumed to have remained throughout at the proportion of the national averageshown in column (I).HER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office government Bookshops49 High Holborn, London, w.c.l13a Castle Street, Edinburgh r.n2 3ar109 St. Mary Street, Cardiff cv\ IjwBrazennosc Street, Manchester m60 8as50 Fairfax Street, Bristol its I 3m:258 Broad Street, Birmingham I7 linen hall Street, Belfast iit2 SayGovernment publications are also available through any bookseller18Printed in England Tor Her Majcsty&apos;s Stationery Ollicc by Waterlow &amp; Sons I.id. London &amp; Dunstablc.Dd. 136854   K 7/69!


</content>
</cab>
