<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/143/0 images: 206-214</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C(69) 88COPY NO.18th July, 1969CABINET-SERjnCEg,AND FACILITIES FOR MEMBERSOF parliament memorandum by the Lord President of the council the Sixth Report of the House of Commons T Services Committeeig published today.    A copy is attached to this memorandum.    TheReport makes a series of recommendations for improvements in theservices and facilities available to Members in the House of Commons.2,     The main recommendations of the Committee may besummarised as follows;-(i)      Provision should be made at public expense forsecretarial assistance for Members - or an allowance made to meet the cost up to a masimumof one full-time secretary for each Member.(ii)      Members should be allowed free trunk telephone(iv)      Certain minor improvements should be made inthe photocopying, stationery and filing facilities available to Members.3.     In addition, there are outstanding previous recommendations made in the Second Report cf the Services Committee this Session,concerning several improvements in Members&apos; travel concessions.The main recommendation was that &quot;a substantial increase in the carallowance11   (at present a flat rate of 4jd. per mile) should be made.Another proposal, which received some publicity, was that Members1wives should be grassfeed four free first-class return rail vouchers ayear.4.     In the light of the present widespread concern in the House ofCommons about Members&apos; facilities, and in the subject of Members&apos;pay and allowances generally, it is clearly important that an early statement should be made on the Governments attitude towards theServices Committee&apos;s recommendations.   I consider that this statementcalls on official business.Members should be able to send all letters on official business free of postal charges.-1-CONFIDENTIALDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
should be framed with the aim both of satisfying Members that theGovernment is making a serious attempt to meet the justifiedcriticism of their present facilities, and also of reducing the immediatepressure for a general rise in Members&apos; remuneration.    statements made by the Prime Minister and myself at Question Time in the Houserecently have emphasised the importance the Government attaches tothis Services Committee Report.5.     The recommendations regarding free trunk calls, free postagefor Members&apos; official correspondence, and the minor improvements in photocopying, stationery and filing facilities, have already beenagreed in principle by the Treasury, and their acceptance, therefore,presents no problem.6.     The acceptance of these alone would, however, be widelyregarded in the House as falling below Members1 expectations and,especially since free trunk calls have been long foreshadowed, mightbe treated as a serious &quot;let-down1.7.     Ixf, order, therefore, to make a statement of the governments attitude to the Report more acceptable to the House, I consider it must make reference to the recommendation for free secretarial assistance(paragraphs 4 and 5 of the Report).    This is by far the most important and far-reaching of the Committee *s recommendations, and would undoubtedly be popularly accepted by Members as a substantial improve-ment in their amenities and financial position.    This proposal emerged,however, late in the Committee&apos;s discussions, and there has therefore been no opportunity for Treasury Ministers to express a view.8,     I recommend therefore that, before the Recess, I should (byanswer to a written Question) confirm the Governments acceptance ofthe recommendations summarised at (ii), (iii) and (iv) in paragraph above, and give an undertaking that the Government will studysympathetically and urgently the Committee^ recommendation onsecretarial assistance, promising to announce the government&apos;s decision on this immediately after the Recess.    It would also be helpful if my answer could include the Governments decision on therecommendation about an improvement in Members1 car allowances.T. P. P.Privy Council Office, S.W.1,18th July, 1969
SIXTH REPORTFROM THESELECT COMMITTEE on house OF COMMONS(SERVICES)Session 1968-69SERVICES AND FACILITIES FOR MEMBERSOrdered by The House of Commons to be printed15th July, 1969LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY office is. Od. net
Thursday, 1th November, 1968Ordered, That a Select Committee be appointed to advise Mr. Speaker onthe control of the accommodation and services in that part of the Palace of westminster and its precincts, occupied by or on behalf of the House ofCommons, and to report thereon to this House: Ordered, That the Committee do consist of Sixteen Members: &apos; -And the Committee was nominated of Mr. Batsford, Mr. 0&apos;Malley,Mr. Chapman, Sir Frank Pearson,Mr. Robert Cooke, Mr. Peart,Mr. English, Mr. Pym,Mr. Hooley, Mr. John Silkin,Dr. David Kerr, Mr. David Steel,Mr. Selwyn Lloyd, Dame Joan Vickers andMr. Maxwell, Mr. Whitelaw.Ordered, That Five be the Quorum of the Committee.Ordered, That the Committee have power to send for persons, papers and records; to sit notwithstanding any adjournment of the House; and to reportfrom time to time.Ordered, That the Committee have power to appoint Sub-Committees andto refer to such Sub-Committees any of the matters referred to the Committee.Ordered, That Two be the Quorum of every such Sub-Committee.Ordered, That every such Sub-Committee do have power to send for persons,papers and records; to sit notwithstanding any adjournment of the House;and to report to the Committee from time to time.Ordered, That the Committee have power to report from time to time theMinutes of the Evidence taken before Sub-Committees and reported by themto the Committee.Ordered, That any Sub-Committee which may be appointed to deal with theorganisation of, and the provision of services in, the Library do have theassistance of the Librarian.Thursday, 5th December, 1968Ordered, That power be given to the Select Committee on House of Commons(Services) to report the Minutes of their Proceedings from time to time.Monday, 5th May, 1969Ordered, That Mr. Maxwell and Mr. John Silkin be discharged from theSelect Committee on House of Commons (Services) and that Mr. Ensor andMr. Mellish be added.Thursday, &amp;th May, 1969Ordered, That Dr. David Kerr be discharged from the Select Committee on house of Commons (Services) and that Mr. Garrett be added.Tuesday, 13 th May, 1969Ordered, That Mr. Hooley be discharged from the Select Committee on house of Commons (Services) and that Mr. Eddie Griffiths be added.The cost of printing and publishing this Report is estimated by the stationery office at  36 Os. Od.
select committee on house of commons (services)3SIXTH REPORTThe Select Committee appointed to advise Mr. Speaker on the control of the accommodation and services in that part of the Palace of Westminster and itsprecincts occupied by or on behalf of the House of Commons and to report thereon to this House, have made further progress in the matter to them referredand have agreed to the following Report: SERVICES AND FACILITIES FOR MEMBERS1. Many Members have made representations to Your Committee that theirpresent salaries are not sufficient to enable them, in addition to paying theirliving costs, to meet out of their own pocket expenses necessarily incurred in thedischarge of their duties. Suggestions for meeting this situation can be listedas follows: (i) improved travel allowances within the United Kingdom.(ii) An office for each Member and for his secretary.(iii) Free secretarial assistance.(iv) Free trunk telephone calls on Parliamentary business.(v) Free postage on Parliamentary business.(vi) Free photocopying service.(vii) Improved allowances for Members attending Council of Europe etc.Offices2. An office for each Member and his secretary can only be provided by anew building, and this was recommended in the Fourth Report of the services committee of last Session and agreed to by the House early in this Session.Travel allowances in United Kingdom3. Your Committee have also in their Second Report of this Session recom-mended a number of improvements in travel concessions, which are still underconsideration by the Treasury and Your Committee urge a speedy decision.Secretarial Assistance4. A facility much sought after by Members is the provision of a personalsecretary, either full-time or part-time, at public expense. The majority ofMembers employ their own secretary or share one with other Members. only about half of these secretaries arc accommodated within the precincts, anduntil new accommodation is built it will be impossible to increase this number.There is also the firm of Ashworths which provides a regular secretarial service to approximately 30 Members. An investigation is currently being made intothe possibility of providing a central dictating system.5. Nevertheless Your Committee recognise from the evidence received thatthere is a growing feeling that such a basic facility as the provision of a secretary is essential. This requires a decision in principle. Your Committee are alsomindful of the fact that the cash salary established in 1964 at  3,250 has fallen in value in real terms to  2,262 and that no machinery exists for its review.They therefore recommend that, regardless of any possible later review of salary, provision should be made at public expense for secretarial assistanceor an allowance to meet the cost up to a maximum of one full-time secretaryper Member.
Free Trunk Calls6. The present system of telephone facilities is that all local calls can be madefree of charge, but that Members must themselves pay for all calls outside theLondon telephone area. The cost of such calls can be set off as an expenseagainst income tax. This system, however, not only entails considerable expense to Members, but makes an invidious distinction between LondonMembers, who can, if they wish, conduct their constituency business on the telephone free of charge, and other Members, who have to pay.7. When the new automatic telephone exchange comes into operation inthe second half of 1971, Members will be able to make any call within theUnited Kingdom free of charge. The extra cost of this will be largely met bythe great saving achieved by the reduction in telephone staff. To introduce such a system now, with the present manual exchange, will add to the costborne on the Vote of the House.8. Your Committee, however, submitted that free trunk calls should beintroduced before the new automatic exchange is installed. The treasury have agreed to this submission on the following conditions: (i) That free trunk calls should be limited to Members and theirsecretaries.(ii) That Members private trunk calls as well as all international callswill be charged for as at present.(iii) That it will be inadmissable for Members to accept any arrangement whereby charges are reversed on incoming trunk calls.(iv) That the new system shall be subject to review after twelve months sothat the position can be reconsidered if it has become apparent thatthe cost of these calls has risen unreasonably.9. There is however a danger of the exchange becoming overloaded, withthe result that the delay in making calls will greatly increase. This dangercould be mitigated to some extent if the existing 53 trunk-barred telephoneboxes were to be made available for all calls, as the lines from these boxes godirect to an outside exchange and not through the switchboard. 30 boxes nowconnected to the switchboard could also be converted to outside lines. AHthis work could be completed in about two or three weeks. In addition, some extra lines could be installed on the existing switchboard and connected to an outside exchange. This work would however take considerably longer.Your Committee do not consider that an STD telephone should be installedin single or double rooms, because it would have to be changed again whenthe automatic exchange comes into operation in two years&apos; time. your committee consider that it is essential that these alterations should be madeby the Post Office before the new system is established, in order to ensure asfar as possible that the existing switchboard is not greatly overloaded. Itwill also help if as many official trunk calls as possible are made from dialtelephones. They therefore recommend that the work should be put in hand at once so that the system of free trunk telephone calls for Members can starton 1st October.Free Postage10. Members are now entitled to free postage for letters to GovernmentDepartments, Nationalised Industries, local Committees and Boards of the
iselect committee on house of commons (services)5Health Service, the Clerks and Heads of Departments of Local Authoritiesand officials of the House, it has been suggested that the facility of freepostage should be extended to all correspondence on Parliamentary business,including correspondence between Members. The latter facility is particularlyneeded during recesses, when the letter board in the Members&apos; Lobby is notin operation. Your Committee consider that free postage on official business is the natural corollary of free trunk calls. The Treasury have accepted this in principle. It will also probably help in reducing the risk of overloadingthe existing switchboard. Your Committee therefore recommend that allletters on official business should be allowed to be sent free of charge.II. It has been suggested that, in order to prevent abuse, an upper limit onthe number of free letters should be fixed. This would, however, be difficultto administer, as the correspondence of each Member varies greatly. Forinstance, if a Member is responsible for a Private Members Bill going through parliament his correspondence is bound to increase far beyond the normal.Your Committee prefer an alternative idea, that a specially designed House ofCommons envelope should be provided, in place of the existing &quot; OfficialPaid &quot; envelopes. The fact that they would be distinguishable from all otherenvelopes should help to reduce the possibility of their use for unofficial letters.Your Committee recommend that free postage on official business should alsostart on i st October.Photocopying Service12. There are a number of photocopying machines provided for the use ofMembers and their secretaries. At present Members are allowed six freecopies (recently increased from three), but have to pay fourpencc a copythereafter. The machines must be used only for Parliamentary business,i.e. not for letters to constituencies etc.13. Many complaints have been received about these restrictions particularlywhen a Member has copies of documents made on behalf of a group ofMembers. Some Members want an entirely free service with no limit on thenumber of copies. Your Committee consider, however, (hat this goes too far,and might lead to great abuse of the facility. They have suggested, and theTreasury have agreed, that the number of free copies should be increased to twelve and that if a paper is being copied on behalf of a group of members the number of free copies should be multiplied by the number of Members inthe group. For instance, a group of 20 Members would be entitled to 240free copies. It is unlikely, therefore, that a Member acting on behalf of a group would incur any expense to himself, as now happens. Your Com-mittee recommend that this new rule be introduced immediately.Stationery Allowance and File Pockets14. Your Committee recommend two other small concessions which havealso been agreed to by the Treasury.   These arc: (i) That Members should be allowed a free supply of stationery up tothe value of  25 instead of  20.(ii) That Members should be entitled to a free supply of one hundredfile pockets for their filing cabinets instead of the existing twenty-five.Your Committee recommend that these two changes should also take effect immediately.
Allowances for Members attending Council of Europe etc.15. Your Committee submitted to the Treasury some time ago a reportindicating the extent to which the daily subsistence allowances paid to members who are Delegates to the Council of Europe Assembly and similar bodies fallwell below those paid to Delegates from all the other Western european countries. The report made suggestions for a phased improvement and forcertain allied changes which would bring the allowances nearer to thoseoperating in Europe generally. The proposals of the Treasury are still awaited,though Your Committee has stressed the urgency of the situation. In themeantime, Your Committee recommend one change to bring the arrangementsmore into line with those of other parliaments. They recommend that theseallowances be carried on the House of Commons Vote, instead of on that ofthe Foreign and Commonwealth Office, and that the system of administrationof them should be transferred to the Overseas Office of the CIerk&apos;s Department.Conclusion16. Your Committee hope that the improvements in the services and facilitiesset out in this Report will go some way to meeting the needs of Members, andwill help them to carry out their Parliamentary duties more efficiently.15th July, 1969.Printed in England by Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office at St. StepheiVs Parliamentary Press(395471)   Del. 152761   K5.0  7/69SBN 10 237469 4


</content>
</cab>
