<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/32/0 images: 47-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
mnTTMHjNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJSSTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).WAR    CABINET.614.From ;- General Delme Radcliffe, Italy. To    :- C.I.G.S., far Office.Handed in 3 a.m.14th Nov.1917. Received 2.20 p.m.l4th Nov.1917571. November 13th.Situation this evening (13th November).3rd Army. Attempts of the enemy to cross Piave at Grisolera mid at another point in some strength a little higher were frustrated and his boats destroyed. Further down, front of 23rd Corps is being shortened by withdrawing to line Piave -Vecchio. The enemy made another attempt to cross at Intestadura. Italians coast detachment consisting of coast guards, some Territorial Militia and dismounted cavalry was attacked but succeeded in driving back the enemy, smashed his boats and took 76 prisoners including three officers and two machine guns.Lodgment at Zenson had not been cleared out this evening. Enemy has been, however, driven back to river bank where it is difficult to dislodge him owing to the wood and reeds.   Enemy strength at this point believed to be between three and four battalions.   Further up stream the enemy forded the left branch of the river to the Grave Islands near Stabiuzzo.   Force holding bridge head here consists of one assault battalion, one section of Mounted artillery and a labour company withdrew to the right bank and at 3 p.m. bridge was blown up and Grave islands bombarded by artillery.4th Army.   9th and 1st Army Corps nothing to report. 18th Corps; enemy occupied Fonzaso basin.   Covering troops-withdrawn to Monte Roncone and Monte Tomatico.1st Army.   On front 22nd and 20th Corps Italian troops were withdrawn to line of resistance passing over SesimolStenfle
Stenfie and Zorno.   Movement carried out successiuny under cover artillery fire.   Further north the Vestone and Monte Baldo battalions Alpine troops were withdrawn under repeated enemy attacks towards the new position.   10th Army Corps; Austrians attacked Monte Msio and were repulsed.3rd Army Corps.   At 6 this morning the enemy attacked in some strength the Concei Valley and Ponale near west side of Lake Sards,.   Attack was decisively repulsed with&apos;heavy loss. Artillery on east side of the Lake co-operated against the enemy on the west side.   Enemy has attacked at many points along the whole front today.   Italian troops are reported to be defending their positions well at all points.   The disquieting features of the situation ere the increasing determination of the enemy offensive on the Asiago Plateau and the continuance of his lodgment at Zensen.   Should the enemy succeed in forcing his way through to the Valley of the Brenta our resistance of the whole line will collapse.   Unless the enemy can be driven back or destroyed at Zensen it appears probable that he will gradually strengthen and increase his occupation on the right bank of Piave and so threaten whole line.   There are hardly any reserves in the hands of the Italian Commanders and available troops are concentrated in most cases close to front line.   To assist in checking the enemy at Zensen army reserve of the 3rd Army had to be brought up.Italian Staff is afraid that if the fighting is continued for many days along the whole front troops may be worn out by being kept constantly on the qui-vive and getting no relief may give way at some point.

</content>
</cab>
