<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/32/0 images: 230-237</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
. ..  % O^Bidi ;      (This Document is ; r . 1       v ;. u;o ctntHnnic iViafeay^ UvvenajK[MmSECRET. Intelligence Bureau,Department of Information. DBW/018.WEEKLY REPORT ON BULGARIA. XVIII. (17 November, 1917).The Visit of the German Emperor.The German Emperor suddenly arrived in Sofia on October 11 on a short visit.     This was something in the nature of a.surprise and was certainly connected with the unrest which has recently been manifested between Bulgaria and her Allies.     Some of the reasons for this have been set forth in previous Reports. 3oth in Socialist circles In Germany and in Austrian circles generally a growing dissatisfaction with Bulgarian war aims, both as an obstacle to peace and as inconsistent with Socialist principles and with Austrian plans with regard to a Balkan settlement, had been increasingly manifested.     In spite of German official assurances and the encouragement doled out to Bulgaria by the Kolnische Zeitung, Deutsche Tageszeitung and other Jingo organs, the Bulgarian press had exhibited great resentment at the supposed change of front on the part of its Allies. The Bulgarian reply had been to exert pressure on the Central Powers by the encouragement of opposition intrigues with the Entente, the nature of which were discussed in the last report.These were the circumstances in which the German Emperor arrived in Sofia.     He was greeted by the Bulgarian press with enthusiastic eulogies, and even the most discontented Bulgars were apparently pleased by the compliment which the Emperor was paying their country.     On the evening of October 11 a banquet was held in his honour at the palace, followed by a reception, whish party leaders of such alleged Ententophil sentiments as
i/alinov, Gochov and others attended and -were presented to the Emperor,     In the speeches made by Tsar Ferdinand and the German Emperor on this occasion there were only discreet references to war aims.     Ferdinand spoke of &quot;the national goal Mie have hotly ctriven for - the union of all the Bulgers - &quot; as &quot;attained&quot;.     He also, in reminding the Emperor of his previous visit in 1916 to Nish, used the words: &quot;the shortly-before-liberated ancient Bulgarian city of Nish&quot;.     The Emperor, in reply, expressed his hope of seeing &quot;a great, happy, secure Bulgarian Empire embracing under one sceptre In powerful unity its separated sons&quot;.The Bulgarian press takes it for granted that the Emperorfs visit implied a reassurance to Bulgaria that her war aims were approved by Germany.   Such is also the impression which our agents abroad have gathered, and the only staterent which conflicts with it is that based on the remark of the Bulgarian Archimandrite Stephen, which has been learnt from the Russian Legation in Berne, that &quot;the German Emperorfs visit had left a disagreeable impression on the Bulgarians&quot;.     This statement can probably be explained by other facts.   Certainly, in Count Hertling1s message informing Mr Radoslavov of his appointment as Imperial Chancellor, the words wore used:   &quot;I shall administer the office which has been confided to my care in unshakable adherence to the Alliance and in the steady maintenance of existing treaties and agreements&quot;. In this connection it is interesting to notice that the German organ in Sofia, the Deutsche Balkan-Zeltung, speaks of Bulgarian war aims as &quot;well-known&quot;, and goes on-    &quot;Some days ago the leading statesmen of Bulgaria once again defined them as follows;    the people sees its national wishes fulfilled,  aid no one doubts that what has been conquered will be retained.     The Commander-In-Chief
of the Bulgarian Army expressed himself as follows: 1 the chief thing is that wo have in our possession everything which we yearn for and we will surrender it to no one.     fe shall and will remain there where we were and aref&quot;.    (The Bulgarian press announces that estimates of the Statistical Department put the present population of the Kingdom of Bulgaria proper at 5,510,000, and, including the &quot;liberated&quot; provinces, at 8,100,000).     From another source we learn (October 26) that the Austrians and Germans have agreed that the Bulgarians shall retain all that part of liacedonia which they have occupied.   There is a clause, however, that &quot;in the event of Bulgaria attacking Saloniki, the agreement will be subject to modifications by v;hich larger territories would be given to her, notably the Saloniki area&quot;.   This may or may not be the case;   but the question of a Saloniki offensive, which, according to many speculations, is likely to follow on the conclusion of operations in Italy, was probably mooted in Sofia. Such an offensive would only be agreeable to the Bulgarians if supported by German military assistance, but very likely on this point agreement was reached between Bulgaria and her Allies.As to other war aims, it may be noted that an address was sent to the German Emperor by the chief administrative Committee of Dobrogean organisations, asking for the release of all Dobrogeans now prisoners in Germany, Austria-Hungary and Rumania;   the request has apparently been granted - presumably in connection with assurances given to the Bulgarian Government that the Central Powers approved of the demand made by all parties in Bulgaria that the whole of Dobrogea should become permanently Bulgarian. In this connection it may be noted that the Bulgarian press has lately devoted even mere space than usual to propagandist articles showing the Bulgarian character of Dobrogea.     An address was also
sent by the Committee of Popular Education in the Morava District to Radoslavov declaring &quot;that the visit of the great Emperor of the G* rmans - our truo Allies in our struggle for the union of all Bulgarian territories - is an Important historical event In the life of the Bulgarian people and a triumph of their national policy. God grant that it may attain to final victory in order that the Bulgarian district of Timok with Zajecar, the Nisava region with Pirot, and the Morava district with Nish, together with the )%e^, gulden Dobrogea may remain inseparable parts of Great Bulgaria under the Bulgarian sceptre&quot;.   The fact that this telegram is published by the Balkan-Zeitung under the heading &quot;For A United Bulgaria&quot; shows that the telegrams cannot have been altogether unpleasing to the German authorities.It may, then, be taken for granted that even though all difficulties between Bulgaria and her German Ally have not been done away with, relations have decidedly improved, and tho Bulgarians have obtained the assurance that all possible support will be accorded to their Jingo programme, which, it may be once again &amp; repeated, includes the whole of Dobrogea, Greek Macedonia (or at least that part of it to the East of the Struma), all Serbian Macedonia and Old Serbia, and, above all, the Morava Valley (or at least Pirot and the Timok departments\      What Bulgaria has undertaken to do in return for such an assurance is not cloar. Bulgarian officers have been taking part in the operations on the Italian front, but it is doubtful if Bulgarian troops could be sent there.     Possibly all the Germans asked for was Bulgaria&apos;s promise to co-operate, though not to conduct alone, an Impending offensive against Saloniki.
The Opening; Hoe ting of the Sabraniye.There is an annoying absence of news as to the proceedings of the Sabi-aniye.   It reassembled on October 15 when the Speech from the Throne was read.   This contained little but deserved eulogies of the late Queen Eleanora and less well deserved eulogies of the German Emperor.   The Speech then went on to deal with Tsar Ferdinand1s reply to the Papal Note and accused the Entente Powers of having tt nbear the responsibility before God and &quot;before history for refusing this noble peace offer&quot;. The Parliamentary measures proposed by the Government deal with matters such as the improvement of public officials1 pay, a tax on war profits, and the creation of a Medical Faculty at the University.     The Opposition apparently will not confine themselves to discussing these somewhat academic subjects.   The various party leaders demanded that a day should be set aside to deal with interpellations on foreign policy and that the Government: should consult parliament In all important matters. Radoalavov agreed to set apart a day for this discussion, but, as. far as can be gathered from the meagre reports in the Bulgarian press, gave a rery unsatisfactory reply to the attacks of the Opposition.     It may be noticed that whereas most of the Opposition leaders are apparently agreed on the character of these interpellations, the Narrow Socialists (Pacifist Internationalists) as usual have their own list of interpellations.Food Situation.Secret reports go to show that General Protogerov, whose appointment as Food Controller was discussed in earlier reports,
has been a great success and that the economic position of the peasants is relatively good since they have got large prices for the sale of produce to Germany and Austria,   It is, therefore, doubtful If mudh hope can be based on the economic situation as likely to lead to anti-war agitation.   But politically the Agrarian deputies (now split into two groups) are probably the persons strongest against the war, as they are less compromised with the Germane than any of the professional politicians, such as members of the Government or Geshov, Malinov, and other pseudo-Opposition leaders.Bulgarian Peace Intrigues.Bulgarian agents are particularly active in Switzerland at present.   In previous Reports the propagandist campaign conducted by Mr Geshov!s supporters in collusion with the Radoslavov Government, whose agent, Professor Milev, is assisting them in Switzerland, has been dealt with, and it was there pointed out that Radoslavov can use on Geshov and Danev the powerful stimulus of reminding them that the Parliamentary Enquiry into their administration has not yet ended, after several years of sitting, and that they are practically on ticket-of-leave.   Danev leads a small party of three in the Sabraniye and for the last two years has taken but small part in public life and interested himself in his Chair at the University of Sofia.    He has now, obviously as result of another reminder from Radoslavov, dispatched to Switzerland an agent called Shipkov with instructions to &quot;reinstate Ferdinand in the eyes of Great Britain and America&quot;. Mr Shipkov naturally gives himself out as a Russophil, though possibly, as in the case of Dr Stoyanov, Professor Milev, and the Geshovists Bufov and Todorov, the Deutsche Bank is acting as his financier.      The Broad Socialist leader Mr Sakyzov, who has
lately returned from Stockholm, ia acting as the chief medium for Bulgarian intrigues with Russian Maximalists at Zurich, who forward his overtures to the Petrograd Sovyet.   A new Bulgarian paper is to he launched shortly in Berne, Le Journal de la Dobroudja, and the Bulgarian agents have  apparently great hopes of imposing upon the Governments of Russia, Britain and America.With regard to the United States, an interesting article appears in the Mir (October 18).   In the last Report ifr was pointed out that the Geshovist Party is regarded in Bulgaria as the suitable medium for propagandist work in America.   The strange utterances of the Bulgarian Minister in Washington, Mr Panaretov, were there alluded to.     In its article &quot;America and the War&quot;, the Ilir argues in a satisfied tone that America is maintaining an independent position with regard to the war.   The Entente Powers &quot;have deafened the world with talk of their new Ally America, but those same Americans do not use the word Allies&apos; of them&quot;. America, we learn, refused even to break off relations with Austria-Hungary, and relations were broken by Austria-Hungary, herself.   The same is the case with their attitude to Bulgaria. The Mir then quotes Mr Panaretov1s utterances as reported in the limes (September 28), and is delighted to find that America has taken no notice of Serbian protests against Panaretov&apos;s intrigues. The Mir writes throughout in a tone of great satisfaction and is obviously under the impression that the Bulgarian cause is favoured in America.   What the Mir understands by the Bulgarian cause Is exactly what Mr Radoslavov and his German Allies understand, i.e. the attainment by Bulgaria of the territorial war aims which have been outlined above.   It has been shown in previous reports that tho Mir hopes that Bulgaria will attain the happy position of
getting all she wants with the help of the Central Powers and then keeping it by favour of the Central Powers&apos; enemies. Courted by both sides she will be able to play one against the Other.   Mr Balfour1 s recent words In the House of Commons should have an admirable educational effect in waking up Bulgarian public opinion to the fact that the Entente Powers are neither so simple nor so unscrupulous as to be led into such a line of policy towards Bulgaria.   Possibly, President Wilson&apos;s Becent speech on Berlin-Baghdad, if it reaches Bulgaria, may have a similar eduoational effect.17.11.17.

</content>
</cab>
