<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/32/0 images: 461-461</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ol^His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government,) ^422THFOfoiATIOH REGARDING ^IJ^S ICBO^irSSD FRO!: AIT AGEFT Iff ,S\nTZERLA3jCDiiDespatched 8tfr November.   .    Reeeived&apos; 15th November..&quot; 1-   &apos; TURKISH PLAITS&apos; III PALESTINE:v These do not include an offensive.   The forces at the disposal of the TURKS and GERIiARS in PALESTINE are not- sufficiently &quot;large to justify .an attack upon the BRITISH Army on -the gaza -front *2.   - TURKISH PLAITS IF gSSOPOTAHlA! -In.KESOPOTAillA an offensive, may he undertaken hut Agent states that the recent indications, are that-here-also -TURKEY will--remain on the defensive Owing to. lack of men. - .    -    &apos;.... In GEHEVA Report 3SE 38(a), informant stated that LUDEIIDORFP had. opposed the fffiSOPOTAMIAH CAMPAIGN:   he &quot;now adds that FAXKEMHAYN held slailar views, hut that&apos; the Campaign was -undertaken, wholly&apos;.&apos; : owing, to the pressure put upon GERIiAHY by E1WER-PASHA,&apos; and: the Turkish Military.Party, .   These latter were losing their influence as.a:result of the fail of BaGHDaD,.&apos;and pointed out that while &apos;. g&amp;RiiANY- had.- -supplied them with plenty of munitions, she had rendered no-direct military assistance,   TURKEY,&quot; on the other hand,, had- sent divisions to GALICIA, and. to the DOBRUJA, as well as-to the MACEDONIAN-frontThe GERj^aIIS had been obliged to give way to the &quot;pressure, but.it was now believed thatrwhile new divisions weKe being organised and military preparations made for an alleged&apos;off ens ive, no-thing of the. kind would take place in PALESTINE, and an offensive in *..-MESOPOTAMIA was. very doubtful!.   It was further-expected that the German forces sent to the EAST would never go either t&amp; PALEST HIE&apos; or. to HL30P0TAMIA.-Agent vas told by a friend (who had actually heard the remark) that - HII.DEHBURG had said . that he did not intend to make the mistake . the. All&apos;--IES had&apos; made in this war and scatter his forces all over the world;The. whole...T.tlRCO-GERl!AN scheme was planned with the object of misleading the&apos;people by declaring that an offensive would be undertaken while actually-ohly considerable defensive preparations; was being made,3,     GERMAN. niFLUFiTCE&quot;&apos;&apos;FrITH RESPECT TO THE TURKISH QUESTION,.;;-.GERMANY&apos; cOnt-rnual-ly^ insists to the TURKISH Government that the . future :of TURKEY,will -be &quot;settled at ;the&apos;PEACE U-OFFEREHCE -and not on any. battlefield., -and; that ilfls immaterial to the TURKS whether, the-ALLIES advance into: AS LA. IrlliOR o-r^not,&apos;- The TURKS, however, : while they : have In the past accepted this point of view, have become very restive under these assurances,..and have called upon their ALLIES for immediate assistance. As a- result, FALKSLHAYN visited MESOPOTAMIA and SYRIA and Military plans were prepared, but none of those included the restitution of TURKEY&apos;s lost Provinces. -..4.&quot;    PROJECTED -^EDQNIAJ.-&apos; OFFENSIVE:j       ^ An offensive against .the Macedonian Front is planned for nextI Springy.  One new German division has already gone to MACEDONIA and,v ! after the attack on Italy is finished, further GERMAN divisions are to 1 be sent to that front.

</content>
</cab>
