<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/32/0 images: 550-551</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.)SECRET.51OPERATIONS .From: -General Barter, Russia.To:-C . I. G. Swar Office.Despatched   18.11.17.Received 3,40 a.m20.11.17.1361.Telegraphic communication has been stopped for somedays.   &quot;Military situation is that General Dukhonin probably with consent of the Bolshevicks has assumed supreme command and has detailed orders to troops in the front line to stand fast at their posts.    There is no news from front except that Russians successfully counter-attacked Germans on fairly wide front near Baranovichi after latter had occupied Russian lines.     The attitude of- the army at large as regards recent political struggle has been one of complete apathy which reflects the attitude of the whole of the uneducated masses of the population.     Railways played important part in the struggle.     They are not Bolshevick but they wanted to put stop to contest and therefore refused to convey food to Petrograd or troops to Kerenski.     Political situation as far as can be ascertained here is that Kerenski, who has fled,  is everywhere discredited.     For the present the superior organization of the Bolshevicks has enabled them to gain temporary powers, but against them are all educated olasses as well as commercial, and majority of peasant proprietors and the Cossacks.       Reaction will probably take place before long and there are vague but perceptible indications of distrust of another violent movement with which Cossacks may be actively associated.    I am informed Alexieff, Kerenski, Miliukof are on their way to H.Q. of Cossacks in the Caucasus^ but this is only rumour.      Injudging
judging new Government it should be noted that Avksentieff, who formerly denounced Lenin&apos;s intrigues with Germans,  is to form part of the new Government which is controlled by Lenin.     If I may venture opinion I would suggest that Allied Governments should not recognize the new Government until it has furnished categorical and satisfactory statements regarding intention of prosecuting war.      The recognition of the new Government by the Viestern Powers Is of immense importance to them as they would lose great deal of influence throughout Russia if this recognition were withheld.      I think new Government should be emphatically informed that however Russia may act in the question the Western Povrers cannot admit any proposal which would leave Germans free to initiate another Y&apos;ar of aggression in the future.     From my experience of Russians and from investigations on spot I press my conviction that only energetic and emphatic action on the part of Allies can have any influence on any revolutionary Russian Government. I do not think such action would materially increase danger to foreigners in this country, but in any case the result is of such vast importance that this consideration should not be allowed to influence right.

</content>
</cab>
