<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/32/0 images: 557-558</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
n517IS jUOUMSKI IS THE 230233?Y OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTYfS GOVER&amp;aEIilT.)S E C R 3,3?. G.T.-2697WAR     CABINET.MAN-BOWER IN SHIPYARDS,Copy of letter from the Shipbuilding Employers1 Federation, the Shipyard Trade Unions1 Standing Committee;   and the Boilermakers1 Society, to the Prime Minister.9 Victoria Street,Westminster, S.W. 1. 14th November, 1917.Sir,Representatives of our respective organisations met at Newcastle last week in Conference mutually convened to consider the question of man power in shipyards and the closer relationship between employers and workmen.Being fully conscious of the vital importance of merchant shipping production both in the direct prosecution of the war and in maintaining the food supplies of the Nation, all present learned with satisfaction that tne Government had made arrangements to divert largely increased supplies of steel to merchant shipbuilding.   Both empldyers and workmen1s representatives,felt it to be their bounden iuty\ not only to compose in as satisfactory and friendly way as possible all differences that might arise in the every day working of shipyards, but also to mako arrangements to ensure the fullest productive capacity being obtained from the labour already in ship-yards and to facilitate the introduction of the additional labour that is imperatively necessary if the Governments programme of merchant shipping production is to be realised^As a result of two days discussion definite lines of co-operative action 7/ere agreed upon and it was folt that a Joint Deputation from the Employers1 Federation and the Trade Unions should ask you to do them the honour of meeting them in order that they may submit definite constructive   suggestions to you in this connection.   They suggest that the Deputation might wait upon you on Wednesday afternoon next 21st inst3The Deputation will develop their proposals more fully when they meet you, but in the meantime wo are desirod to summarise them as follows:-(l)     That craftsmen and others experienced in shipyard work now serving with the Colours should be returned to shipyards..(a) If they are still stationed in this Country:(b) If they aro temporarily in this Country,lopnded. invalided, or on leave j   taul
(o)   If they are 3erving abroad but are not being employed on work of a technical nature.(2) That on all matters connected with the demand and supply cf labour in shipyards the National Service Department should have full and sole control.(3) That on all other matters relating to labour, adminis-tration and policy should be co-ordinated in the hands of the Ministry of Labour alone.(4) That a Joint Advisory Committee of employers and workmen&apos;s representatives should be attached to both the National Service Department and the Ministry of Labour for the purpose of -(a) Advising the National Service Department upon - andworking out the practical details of - any schemes for making full use of existing labour and for placing additional labour in shipyards; and,(b) For influencing the direct settlement between em-ployers and workpeople of all disputes anddifferences arising between them, and generally advising the Ministry of Labour on matters connected with the policy or administration of labour questions.It is recognised that organisation on the foregoing lines for shipbuilding might need to be accompanied by similar or-ganisation for all labour questions in other industries as well, but during the past year there has been so much overlapping between Government Departments that our respective constituents are convinced that the time has come when some more drastic reorganisation is required.   As all questions affecting labour fall broadly under the two groups indicated above it is believed that the activities at present carried on by so many different Departments could be co-ordinated without serious difficulty and brought under the control of the two Departments referred to.We are, Sir,Your obedient Servants,(Sd.) GEO. J. CARTER.&quot; A.R. DUNCANtt FRANK SMITH.&quot; ALEX. Y7ILKI1&quot; R.W. LINDSAY&quot; JOHN BARKERPresident. Secretary. Chai rman Secretary. Chairman. Asst, - G-f n. SecretaryShipbuilding-Employers&apos; Federation.Shipyard TradeUnions&apos; Committee.Boilermakers&apos;Society..NOTE BY THE SECRETARY.This question is raised as one of urgency, as the prime Minister has been asked to receive an immediate deputation on the subject.(Intd.)    M.. P. A.. HANKEY.

</content>
</cab>
