<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 39-40</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 JWis wmmm is the property op his britamio majesty*s govtotimt).3 0 IB T. WAR      0 A B I N E T.4505, RELATIONS Off UNITED STATE 3 IgHOMM BfrJPIRE vised). AND BULGARIA!Thm following copy of a recommendation from the Military Representatives at Versailles as to the Relations of the United States with th&amp; Ottoman Empire and Bulgaria has bean forwarded by the United States1 representative to the American Government.(Signed). M. P* A. HAMJ5Y, L Whitehall Gardens, S.W.11th May, 1918.In reply to the question submitted by the American Military Representative at the instance of his Government as to whether it would be advisable for the United States to declare that a state of war exists at the present time between the United States and both the Ottoman Empire and Bulgaria, or either of them, the Military Representatives after consideration of the subject from a military standpoint agree to the following joint recommendation(a) Am immediate declaration that a state of war exists between the United States and the Ottoman Empire i&amp; desirable. 1(b) &quot;In view of the moral effect on Bulgaria of the ah oreaction, it is advisable to postpone a declaration that&apos; a state of war exists between the United States and Bulgaria until it shall haye been found impossible by diplomatic negotiation to detach the latter country from her alliance with the Central Powers, but a limit should be placed upon the time allowed her for consideration of this subject,to be&apos; immediately followed by a declaration of a state of war should she within that time limit fail to take satisfae-tory aetion*(c) It is distinctly understood, however, that no situation resulting from a declaration of the existence of a state of war between the United States, on the one hand, and the Ottoman Empire or Bulgaria or both of them, on the other, shall be allowed to divert any American troops from the Western front which is in need of, and will be in need of, every man that the United States can send to it until the situation on that front is radically changed.Although
Although it 18 imperative that the United States- permit no diversion of the assistance desired by the Allies on the &apos;&quot;&apos;esternj front, the military Representatives are of opinion that the- fol-&apos; lowing military advantages would result from the action recommended above(1)   The moral effect and influence on the people of those countries that would follow such a declaration, in the ease of the Ottoman Empire and subsequently if necessary in the case of Bulgaria, showing the Allies to be really in unison in every theatre of the tfar.(2)   The fact that this declaration would enable the UnitedStates to participate in the Eastern Theatre and co-operatj there with her Allies, should opportunity offer; which she] cannot do under present conditions and which the necessityI for legislative action might prevent her from doing in time should the declaration be left until the emergency presents itself, .(S)   Those elements of the peoples of the Jaiddle Iiiast whos owing to the uncertainty of the situation, are nov? hesitating to put forth strong efforts against the Turks  I will be encouraged to throw in their lot decidedly with the Entente Powers when they find that the vast potential power of the United States is now to be opposed to the Government of the Ottoman Amp ire.

</content>
</cab>
