<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 42-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off HIS BRIMHIO llAJEoTYrS GOVERIMUQ?).  27&apos;.U B      C I B i ii E I1, PAY Ai-ID SEPARATION ALLOWANCES IN THE---&quot; *Nota-M the Secretary of State for Y/ar. he desirability of counteracting pacifist propaganda in Italyby doing something to improve the miserably inadequate pay andseparation allowances of the Italian Army has been repeatedlybrought to the. aotico of the British Government,Note 12 of tho -Military Representatives at Versailles on the Joint Plan of Campaign for 1918, which was adopted by the Supreme War Council en February 1st, included a recommendation (paragraph 5) that the Allies should assist Italy financially &quot;in order to prevent the creation of economic conditions which would diminish tho strength ef the interior resistance of the country&quot;,   I under-stand that at the actual discussions between the Military Rcpresen-tatives the question of Pay and Allowances was specifically in viow, but that the wording was purposely left vague in ordor to avoid the possibility of wounding the susceptibilities of tho Italian Governsaont,5?hQ attention of the War Cabinet was drawn to the matter on January 15th (War Cabinst 32 , Minute 2) and again on March 7th (War Cabinet 361, Minute ?)*   On that occasion any decision in the matter was deferred pending a discussion on the subject betwoen the foreign Secretary and Baron Sonnino, which, however, does not appear to have taken plaoe.On April 4th, 191G9 Brigadier-General DelmcVRadeliffe, in a report to the War Office on the moral of the Italian Army laid stress on the effect of tho insufficient separation allowances accounting for the hostility of Italian women to the war.   Ho suggested the separation allowances should be raised from tho present rate of 85 cts. a day for wives and 40 ets* for each child, to at least 1 Lira 25 ctsM and 50 ots respectively.   He also drew attention to the discontent which had arisen in the Army itself owing to the non-fulfilment of the expectation raised by the Italian Press that troops in the war zone would have their pay raised from 40 cts. to 80 cts* a day, and suggested that this should new be carried out and the pay of the troops in the inter-ior raised at the same time to 25 cts, a day.In a telegram of April 27th, General -Delmo-Radcliffo reported, after consultation with Senor Bisselati, that if funds could bo placed at Senor Bissolatifs disposal sufficient to deal with tho suggested increases tho effect on tho moral of the country and tho Army v/euld ba excellent, and the announcement which Seuor Bissolati would make as to the origin of this would have a good political effect also,U?he Italian Government were already taking certain measures themselves to ameliorate the position of the soldiers but the utmost the Italian Treasury could afford was a total expenditure of  3,625s000 monthly.     fhe additional amount required, according to the estimates furnished by the Oammando supremo and the Ministry of War. is  943.500 por month, made up as followsIncreasedI 0 B B T,
Increased Separation Allowancos      750,000 a month.Increase of Pay to troops inthe Front Line. 106,000        KIncrease of Pay to troopsin the interior., 87,500       nI realise that the additional burden on the Treasury that would be involved in furnishing this assistance to the Italian Government is considerable,   At the same time, in view of the immense importance of maintaining the moral both of the Italian Army and of the Italian people at large, I strongly urge the T/ar Cabinet to undertake this expenditure on the understanding that tho Italian Government will make it clear to all the parties affected that the increases in pay.and allowances have been duo to the generous assistance of the British Government.I beg that this matter may be brought before tho War Cabinet for immediate desists       If anything is to be dono, it should bo done at oneo, before the strain of a big enemy offensive comes on the Italians.   If it was done now it might have a great effect in cheering the Italians at tho very nick of time,(Initialled )*War Office,. 11th Hay,. 1918.

</content>
</cab>
