<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 108-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Prom:hi   Gen * G .T ,M. Bridge s,Britlsh MU :i ta ry Rop resentafciTO,WashingtosuTo:-    War Office eReceived at 4 p*m.   10*5,18/&apos;Bo24*Summarising various1 cables to youe    The Pershi.ng-El.lner agreement of April 24th and the subsequent modification made by the Supremo War Council at Abbeville May 2nd is understood by the American War Department as follows :^   By the Pershing-Milnor agreement- of April 24th preparations were made to ship troops in May in the following sequenceFirstly^ 118;758 men,-, that is to say six divisions of a strength of 19.793 sacho      The figure 19;793 for each division iscompiled as follows \**Divisional H*Q:s 238Infantry and machine gun units 17.223Engineer regiment and train &apos; 1,779Field Signalling battalion 4884 camp infirmaries 65Secjpaij.J.  20 ,,000 so called replacement troops, two thirds of which have usually been infantry; but since these troops ape sent asPeracing asks; there is no guarantee that infantry will bo sent. He lias already asked this month for 3,,000 out of tbe 20,000 to be medical units *Thirdly*    88^292 artillery and ammunition supply and trains. The figure 83,292 is accountered for by 9^,965 men left behind by each of the four divisions which sailed in April and 89072 divisional troops left behind by each of the six divisions sailing in May*Fourthly.   There remajn 8;.000 to complete first combatant corps in France oFifthly.    14.372 to complete the second combatant corps in France;andSixthly.
Sixthly *    90,000 so-called Servieo Battalions of tho rear troops, which means troops to complete the first and second phase of build? lug up one complete American Army consisting of five combatant   * Corps, complete with-numerous army troops and general troops which have all been detailed to be sent over in five phases.The agreement made by Supreme War Council meeting of May 2nd now modifies the above as followsFirstly,   In May six divisions., the 4th, 30th, 27th, 33rd, 80th and 78th making a total of 118,758 will be shipped; Secondly.   20,000 replacement troops, such as General Pershing may require;Thirdly.   As many of the 88,292 divisional troops of the Pershins-Milner agreement of April 24th as can be carried over before June 1st.    As interpreted by War Department here on June 1st the programme, as outlined by Pershing-Milner agreement, ceases, and another similar programme headed by six divisions, that Is to say 118,758 Infantry and machine gunners, etc, begins.    As has been shown above, out of the 19,795 in the 1st echelon of each division only 17,223 are machine gunners and infantry.   Therefore to complete the 120,000 infantry monthly required by General Foch&apos;s memorandum the 17,000 replacement troops should be infantry and machine gunners.    In some units the training is backward. General Trotter tells me some 10 per cent of men going over in May in two divisions have less than eight weeks service.Can you let me know the numbers of the divisions allotted for training to British Army. At present this information 13 not obtainable here. *Note. * 82nd, 77th, 55th, 28th, 30th &amp; 4th Divisions,are allot-ted for training with British. - General Bridges informecU

</content>
</cab>
