<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 139-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel W. Dally Jones.102THIS DOOUMMP IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAIIHIC MAJgSTTfS GOVERiOllg,\7AR CABIXHT.T;.45S9MIHISTRY OF HEALTH BILL.HoraorarKte by the Minis to r of Reconstructionon Mr.Hayes Fisher^ Memorandum of the 15th hay (G.T.4533).Mr. Hayes Fisher raises four points which have all been discussed in detail by him with myself. But some of his statements call for a &quot;brief comment in order that misunderstanding may he avoided. (1)   As regards the Consultative Council provided for hy Clause 4, it is not the case, as MrcHayes Fishor states, thefct &quot;nothing is said in the Bill about the powers of this body&quot; *    The Cornell is limited by the terms of the Bill to &quot;giving advice and assistance&quot;; that is to say, it has no executive functions and no power to bind the Minister,    Mr.1X0703 Fisher refers to the Order in Council under which its procedure will be regulated as if the Order could invest it with powers beyond those conferred by Clause 4,    This is, of course, not the case, and Mr,Hayes Fisher has had before him since March a draft of the Order which is suggested.       Mr,Hayes Fisherfs references to the view?, of the British Medical Association and the Insurance organisations about the powers of the Council arc scarcely relevant to tho issuo.    The question is not what these bodies originally ashed for, but what they have been induced to accept,    !Ehey vri.ll not oppose Clause 4 as it stands if the rest of the Bill, and the Order regulating the Cotuicil^procedure
procedure, are left as they stand *    But the Bill is tfte Jesuit of concessions by all. parties-, ..and..jn^t &quot;be-r-egarded as a whole.Mr.Hayes Pishor is fully cognisant of the naturs of the proposal Order in Cotncift; and I attach a copy. It trill bo seen that so far from being able to &quot;put the Minister in shackeass&quot;.   the Consultative Council are limited to advis&amp;ns on any of the matters specified in Article 12 (l) which the Minister may refer to them, the Minister retaining Ms discretion as to the nature perl extent of tho references.1 hope that Mr,Hayes Flshor will not continue to suspect mo of being a party to a conspiracy to undermine Ministerial&apos;., responsibility.   But if ho asks me whether Ministers have to look forward to cn extended use of advisory committees, my answer is in the affirmative.    Ho mentions the Home Office and Board of Trade.    Within the last few months the Hone Office have made arrangements for &apos; regular consultation with groups of police authorities throughout the country;   and the formation of &quot;a strong Advisory Council&quot; and other specialised advisory bodies is a prominent feature of the re-organisation of the Board of Trade which the Government have approved. (2)   For the reasons indioated in my memorandum on the Bill (G-.T.4399) I am strongly of opinion that a definite and final statement i;?. favour of a policy of Poor Law Reform, should be made o;i the introduction of the Bill and that &quot;the first paragraph of the First Schedule is the minimnm&apos;&quot;proViaiorL&quot;TequrJj:&apos;ed to convince the House and the Public tha&amp; the Government are in Earnest on this matter *
(3)   I am glad that %.Hayes Fisher-does noVwish to -Oppose tho tit la Ministry of Health, which I om sure irlll help the proves of the Bill.   I agree with him In principle thitfct health and local government services bhotald not ho divorced thiloss very good reason is dhown for divorcing them  in particular cases. (4)   I bolieve that on overwhelming case can he made in the House for Centre 1 Reform first, ancl I am certain that the only way to secure the reform of local health authorities is to put an end to the division and friction between the main central authorities which at present supervise local health services tnder separate Ministers and through separate boclias of officials.0.ADDISOH.16th Kay, 1918.
MIWISTHZ   m    3001TSTRUCTIOHDRAFT 0? ThJ3 MINISTRY OP ICAIffH ( OCHSULTATIVE COUNCIL) ORDER IH COUWCIL, 1918.Whereas by Section 4 of the Ministry of Health Act, 1916, it lfl enacted thsb it shall bo lawful for His Majesty in Council by Order to establish a Consultative Council for tho purpose of giving to the Minister of Health advice and assistance on matters relating to his powers and duties, consisting ef persons of both sexes having practical ex-perience of looal government (including the administration thereof by County Borough and district Councils), of public health, of national health insurance (including the work of approved sooloties and insurance oommitteenj, of housing problems of hospital work, of gefeeral and special medical practice, of research, and of pharmacy:flta therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, and by virtue of tho authority oommitted to Him by the Ministry of Health Act, 1918, and of all other powers enabling Him in that behalf, Is pleased to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows:-1. (1)   Shore nhall be established a Consultative Councilof the Ministry of Health consioting of____members.(2)   Tho following persons shall bo the first members of the CotaJll:2.       (l)   Subject to the provision of this Order as to tho retirement of the first members of the Council, the term of office of a member of the Council shall be throe years.
(2)   Grae-^ihird of th3 members otto thai the. first members of the Council shall go out of off loo annually 0:1 the appointed days and their p.&apos;:see shall be. filled by such persons as the Minister of Health appoints,(3)   A person going out of office may be re-appointed, provided that no person may nerve continuously as a member of the Council for more than six years.(1), The first members of the Council shall hold officefor a period of three years from the__day of_1918.(2)   (jn the expiry of the said period of three years one-third of the members of the Council, to be selected by lot, shall returc annually, bub may, subject to the provisions of this Order, be re--appointed*The Minister of Health shall bo the President, and the Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Health shall be the tlce-Prosident of the- Council.The Council shall elect a Chairman, and the Chairman shall hold office during the  fcest yoar of tho initial period, and during tho remainder of the initial period shall be eligible for re-appointment as Chairman in cither or both of the succeeding years.,    Thereafter the Chairman shall hold office for a period of one year,b ut shall bo eligible for re-appointment as a member of the Council, and, if re-appointed, for re-election as OhairmenfProvided that if during his term of office the Chairman ceases to bo amember of the CounelJv the Council shall oloct a now Chairman.The Prosident, or in his absence tho Vice-presidents or in tho absence both of the President end the Vice-president, the Chairman, shall presMo at every meeting at:
the Council at srhich lie is presenteSuch person as the Einister of Health appoints shall &quot;be the Secretary to the Council and shall hold office during the pleasure of the Minister.(1)   The Council shall meet at such times., and notice of meetings shall be given to the members of the Council in such manner as the Council may, uith the approval of the Minister, determine.$rovided that the Council shall meet at least once in each quarter.(2)   At a meeting of the Council t__^nhall be aquorum *(3)   JTo act or proceeding of the Council shall be questioned on account of any vacancy in their body,(4)   There may be paid to the members of the Counc&amp;l such travelling expenses and subsistence allowances, and compensation for loss of remunerative time, as the Minister may, \7ith the approval of the Treasury, determine.The Council may for special purposes approved by the Minister appoint subcommittees of their members^- and any sub-committee so appointed may^ rrithin the limits approved by the Minister, add to their numbers persons not being members of the Council.If a member of the Council is absent from consecutive meetings of the Council, except for some reason approved by tho Minister of Hoalth, his office shall become vacant.On a oasual vacancy occurring in the Council by reason of tho dearth, resignation, or absence of a member the Minister of Health shall appoint another person in Ills place, and the person so appointed shall hold office until the time when the person in whose place he is appointed.
would regularly have gone out of Office, and shall then go out of Office.

12. (1) The Council shall consider and report upon the matters from time to time referred to them by the Minister including:-

(a) drafts of Orders in Council, and of Regulations, Orders, and Special Orders;

(b) matters involving questions of important principle and scientific difficulty;

(c) any other matters relating to his powers and duties; 

and the Minister shall place at the disposal of the Council the information required to enable them to consider the matters thus referred to them.

(2) It shall be open to the Council to propose to the Minister from time to time th? matter relating to his powers and duties shall form the subject of a reference to the Council, and the Minister shall receive and consider any such proposal.

(3) Subject to the provisions contained in this Order the Council may regulate their own procedure.

</content>
</cab>
