<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 218-227</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel W, Dally Jones.12victoria 8210. ^Thi3 l)0Cl,metlt &apos;S tne Property Of ..gr0wm0rb, sowbst, london.His Oritnnnio Majesty*s Government.) .v^fD &quot;oFa^cultore&quot; AND fisheries. 1&quot; &apos;co^g&quot;^^^ a// communications toFOOD  PRODUCTION   DEPARTMENT.-&quot;^ssssss^itedikkctok general.72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. (1)15th May, 1918.Sir,I beg to submit the following Report on the work of the( Feod Production Department for the week ended 14th May, 1918:-The Weather.Fine sunny weather, broken only by a few w*.rm showers, has been experienced during the past week.The warmer weather has greatly improved the condition of crops and pasture alike.    Complaints of wlreworm continue to be received from many districts.LOCAL ORGANISATION DIVISION. Agricultural Executive Committees * Birmingham - The Executive Committee, to which no quota was assigned in the 1918 programme, have secured the ploughing rind cropping of 1,188 acres of grass land, 700 acres of which have been planted with oats, 280 acres with wheat, and 100 acres with potatoes.Cheshire - The Executive Committee have been authorised to take possession of 50 acres of Petty Pool Park belonging to Lord Delamere which was once cultivated, but is now a game preserve covered with bracken.    Potatoes will be planted on the land by the aid of prisoner of war ploughmen who are quartered in the vicinity.Devon - The Torquay Corporation are cultivating 73 acres of land which forms part of their water undertaking at Burrator.   Half the land has been planted with oats and the other half with potatoes.
Sussex, East.    The greater part of 60 acres of a farm at 1Rottingdean, the property of a Land Company, was left uncropped in 1 Authority was given to the Agricultural Executive Committee in September last to take possession of the 60 acres, and the warning thus received has so stimulated the Company that all the uneropped land has been broken and 40 acres of it sown with corn.    A similar warning has produced an additional 10 acres of corn on the adjoining land.Prosecutions.   A farmer near Whitstable (Kent), and farmers near Wincanton and Udells (Somerset), have each been fined  50 and costs for noncompliance with orders to plough up grassland.     In Leicestershire the Secretary of the Birstall Golf Club has been fined  10 and costs for failure to comply with an order to break up 22 acres of grass land which had been selected in consultation between the Committee, the Golf Club and the owners. Drainage of Land,     In Cheshire the Birkett scheme has now been almost completed and has benefited 2,500 acres of land.     650 acres have been released for ploughing for the 1918 harvest in addition to a substantial acreage which has been brought into use for grazing as a result of the drainage.    There will be a further considerable acreage fit for ploughing when the land has been underdrained,     9 miles of the River Mardyke in Essex have been cleansed, 2 miles by the owners themselves and 7 miles by the Commissioners of the Levels in co-operation with the Executive Committee,      The area drained by this river and its tributaries is 50,000 acres,      15 miles of these channels remain to be cleansed, but the beneficial results of the work already done have been proved during the heavy rains of the last month, when, it is stated,,, the water has been carried away from Bulpham Pen twice as quickly as had been known for 20 years.      In the East Riding of Yorkshire the Committee have served notices for the cleansing of the Barmby Moor Drains in addition to the works already undertaken.
Determination of Tenancies - During the week 4 Orders have been made authorising landlords to determine tenancies on account of bad fArming in respect of 22 acreb, and 2 Orders have been msde by&apos; the Board determining the tenancies of 23 acres.HORTICULTURAL DIVISION. Marketing Organisation - 4 County and 15 Village meetings on this bubjeot have been held.    County Marketing Organisations have been formed in 4 additional counties.Provision- of Land for, Allotments - Reports received from 1,159 districts show that 297,973 applications have been made for plots under the Cultivation of Lands Order, 1917 (No. 2), rod thai 270,545 plots containing 19,617 acres have been provided.During the week 10 Local Authorities have undertaken to acquire, in addition to the area mentioned above, 61 acres (826 allotments).Representations have been made to the King by residents in Hampton Wiok and Teddlngton asking that a portion of the Royal Paddocks at Hgmptan Wick should be made available for allotment cultivation during the present emergency.    His Majesty has been grsciously pleased to direct that about 7 acres of the Paddocks should be allocated for that purpose to the Teddington Urban District Council for the duration of the War and such further period as may be provided for the tenure of land taken under the Cultivation of Lands Order.9 acres of land, In Regents Park are now being cultivated as allotments by the Military rmd the Park Authorities, Fruit and Veftetable Preservation - It has been arranged to hold Exhibitions illustrating the preservation of fruit and vegetables at Nottingham, Birmingham, and Dorchester.    During the week 83 public Demonstrations have been given in Bottling, Drying and Canning.    The increased demand for Canners and Cans Indicates that the Canning of fruit is generally becoming more popular in the country.
Greenhouse Cultivation - An inspection hag been made of the Northing area which shows that the 50$ reduction, which growers volunteered to make in the area of glasshouses devoted to flowers has in fact been effected.   Moreover, many growers have substitut tomatoes for grapes.   A considerable area of glass is being devot to such crops as vegetable marrow, mushrooms, and early potatoes, Market Gardeners and Food Production - Reports show that, as a result of appeals made by the Department, Market Gardeners in Worcestershire have reduced their area under luxury food crops aaj have planted a considerably increased area with onions and potatoiTECHNICAL DIVISION; Feeding.of.Dairy Cattle.   The Technical Committee are considering what steps may be taken to instruct farmers in new methods of feeding dairy cattle.Breaking up Grasslands   An enquiry is being made as to the result of breaking up grassland last season in certain heavy-land distri with a view to obtaining definite information as.to the necessity of summer-fallowing clay land in preparation for wheat. Wireworms en Newly-broken Grassland.    A circular letter has been addressed to Agricultural Executive Committees and published, in, t press, drawing attention to methods which have been found most successful in dealing with wireworms and leather jackets.   Alter-native crops to replace failures have been suggested. Seed Testing Station.   The total number of samples received up to date is 7,367.   Reports have been issued in all cases, with the exception of about 60 samples, the examination of which is in han(LABOUR DIVISION.Military Service.   An arrangement has been made between the Board the Ministry of National Service and the War Office whereby 30,0 Grade 1 men between the ages of 19 and 31, who are now engaged onlI&apos; &apos; Isagricultural work, will be released for Military Service before  I
the 50th June,     The Department are allocating a quota to each county in order to secure the number of men required.      The number of Grade I men posted for service under the Proclamation of the 19th April will be counted towards each county quota,    The War Office and the Ministry of National Service have promised to allooate as many German prisoners ard. War Agricultural Volunteers as possible for agricultural work in order to replace the men withdrawn from the land.The Ministry of National Service has now issued instructions that no agricultural blacksmiths affected by the Proclamation of the 19th April are to be called up pending the receipt of further instructions.As the result of representations made by the Department, the Ministry have also instructed their Recruiting Authorities that the withdrawal order of the 9th April is not intended to de-certify makers, erectors or repairers of agricultural traotors, nor attendants, drivers of mechanics employed thereon.    Instructions have been given that any calllng-up notices issued, under order, to men so employed shall be cancelled.Soldier Labour.    A consolidated return relating to the whole of the soldiers employed on the land has now been substituted for the previous return which dealt only with the soldiers supplied for the 1918 programme under the War Cabinet decision of the 27th June 1917,    This return shows that 61,057 soldiers have been attached to depots to date for agricultural work, and of these men 57,689 are out on farms.    Nearly the whole of the balance is accounted for by men not available for farm work by reason of their being on the staff, under training, sick, etc.An additional 19 soldiers have been supplied for training as traotor drivers, making a total of 4,007 men sent out for such training to date,
Prisonera of War.    Five additional prisoner camps were openedduring the week, making the total number of prisoners now employedon the land as follows:-Prom 64 ordinary agricultural camps ...... 5,47511   116 prisoner ploughmen camps.........4,165Employed from other camps................, 1.008Released aliens employed in agriculture... 1,91212,560160 additional schemes are now with the War Office, providing for the employment of a further 9,892 prisoners.In view of the large contribution of men for Military Service which is to be made by agriculture during the next few weeks, it is Imperative that those prisoners already voted to the Department, but not yet at work, should be available at a very early date, as there is little prospect of substituting the whole time farm workers called up, except by this kind of labour.WomenTa Branch.Recruiting. Open air meetings have been continued in London during the past week, and have attracted considerable attention.380 women of a very good type have been interviewed at Leeds during the past fortnight.Training *   During the past week the opening of 20 new practice farms has been sanctioned, making provision for 74 women.   Special attention is paid to horse work at the Training Centre at Drayton St Leonards.    There are 20 horses on the farm, aXl of which are looked after by the women, thus giving them every opportunity to learn carter*s work.8,766 women are accounted for in the Land Army asfollowsIn Instruction Centres ........................ 1,138On farm work................................ 6,663Employed by Forage Committee ,.................    237*     &quot; Timber Department..................    147Waiting for references to be placed inTraining Centres............................    367Waiting in Depots .............................     51Waiting in their own home .....................    163Total ............, 8,76.6
7fomen!s Institutes.   The Women&apos;s Institute which has been recently formed at Wroxall, Isle of Wight, is undertaking a variety of useful work with a view to increasing food production.   Basket making has been started with the support of a local tradesman.   Co-operative rabbit keeping and increased vegetable cultivation have been undertaken, and a Market Garden Produce Show is to be held in July.CULTIVATION DIVISION. The following statement shows the position as regards the provision of tractors owned by the Department:-Consigned to County Committees and Tractor Schools up to and including 7th May, 1918Consigning instructions given duringthe week ......Less tractors withdrawn... ...On offer to countiesConsigned to Scotland - &quot; &quot; Ireland... ......156 1152 1913,680155 100343 4,278The following types of machinery and implements for use with tractors have been issued to countiesCultivators 9/11 tine   ..a &quot; Disc patternPressers 3 ring Trailer boxes&quot; &quot;    Stones patent0 0 0 0   0   01,250 671 202 760 100The following is a list of horse-drawn implementsconsigned to Agricultural Executive Committees:-Carts and Lorries Cultivators Disc Harrows DrillsHarrows and Drags PloughsRollers and Pressers1,431 1,556 784 1,397 3,073 5,197 2,453Yorkshire.   During the week ended May 3rd six tractors cultivated 325 acres in 360 hours in the North Riding of Yorkshire.   One of these tractors cultivated 81 acres in 60 hours;   another, a Fordson, cultivated 66 acres in 40 hours.
Hampshire.    During the week ended May 3rd, Fordson Tractor No.711 ploughed 30j acres on a paraffin consumption of 86 gallons. The Championship Shield.    The National Pood Produotion Champion-ship Shield for the month ended April 5th was won by Pordson Traotor No. P 69, operating in Lincolnshire (Holland).    The work performed, which included ploughing, cultivating, harrowing and rolling; reached an aggregate amount of work equivalent to 143 acres ploughed in 23 days.    The fuel consumption averaged 2,86 gallons of paraffin and .1 gallons of petrol per acre,    Thij consumption includes fuel used while travelling from field to fie which amounted to over 60 miles.&quot; SUPPLIES DIVISION. Fertilisers.   A notice has been issued to manufacturers and merchants explaining the provisions of the Fertilisers Prices Ord 1918, with reference to the licensing of sales.    A General Notie has also been issued to farmers setting out the prices for the ensuing year.    Merchants, dealers and co-operative societies hav been invited to become Approved Agents for the sale of fertiliser on condition that they undertake to store 10% of the quantities t be purchased by them during the year.    This arrangement Is especially Intended to meet the needs of allotment holders and small growers, and the Approved Agents are required to stock and sell fertilisers In small quantities,-&apos;Sulphate of Ammonia.   The returns for the month of April, 1918, ^how that stocks of this fertiliser at makers1 works are extreme 1; small, only 7,570 tons being returned as In hand at the end of tin month as against 10,640 tons in the same l*onth last year.    The deliveries during the month exceed the actual production by 8,700 tons.Superphosphate.   During April 1918 the stocks In the hands of   1 manufacturers of superphosphate fell from 50,000 tons to 31,000 tons;   57,000 tons were delivered to purchasers.
The deliveries of Compound Manures were also very large: and amounted to 82,000 tons, the stock on hand being reduced to 28,400 tons.Basic Slag.   The deliveries of basic slag amounted to 42,000 tonswhich was slightly in excess of the production.Lime.   The returns for April 1918 show a decline in the deliveriesof lime, but the figures are substantially larger than twelvemonths ago, and the arrears in deliveries have been considerablyreduced.Seed Maize.   A large number of enquiries have been received by&apos;the Department from people intending to grow maize this year, and the sale though not very large will be widely distributed. Seed Oats.   Owing to the failure of some crops in the south of England, there has&apos; been a further demand for Scottish oats and Irish Black Tartarian for replanting the land.   The. Department have been able to execute these demands promptly.-The Department have now disposed of all the Manx Seed Oats purchased by them.   2,968 quarters have been distributed to growers in England and Wales and 3,225 quarters have been sent to France. Wart Disease of Potatoes.   Several cases have occurred recently in which seed potatoes sent from Scotland have been found to have been grown on farms where wart disease exists.   These consignments have been traced to their destinations, and the consignees have been warned not to plant the potatoes.   In cases where the potatoes had been planted before it was possible to warn the growers, they have been instructed to report at once any sign of wart disease in,the growing crops, and to advise the Department when the crop is to be lifted so that an Inspector may be present.Potato Spraying.   183 lectures on potato soraying have been given in Hants, Wilts and Dorset,Revision of Testing of Seeds Order.   It was agreed when the Testing of Seeds Order was first issued that a revision would be necessary as soon as sufficient time had elapsed to ascertain how the Order wab working.
Representatives of the English, Scottish and IrishDepartments of Agriculture have met to consider suggestions submitted by the Seed Trade Associations with regard to revision.declaration of the germination and purity of cereal seeds, andthe establishment of specified standards for vegetable seeds. Itis hoped that by the latter means the administration of the Order!will be considerably simplified. IIILinseed as a Fodder Crop. The whole of the English-grown linseedl which the Department acquired for sale for seed purposes has been]disposed of, and the Flax Production Department is transferring to this Department a further quantity to meet orders still being received.,  A supply of Plate seed, held by a Bristol firm on the Department&apos;s instructions, ia still available. IThe principal alterations proposed are the compulsoryI am,Sir,Your obedient Servant,Director-General.The Rt. Hon.&quot;.-Rowland E.. Prothero, M.P.President of the Board of Agricultureand Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
