<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 254-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-iyHs/iiia. 19  17,5.1918.ySlM.lA.RY OF BIQQK&amp;PB FORMATION.z) -    1 7      J May 10 - 16. 1918.* ^ONMGE.    Hitherto raw materials required by the European Allies have been to a large extent&apos;brought in the first instance to the United Kingdom and transhipped to their destinations.   This&apos; involves a waste of tonnage and entails two journeys through the danger soneo The War  2rade Department are asking the Commission Internationale da Revitaillement to males arrangements in future for the European Al-lies to import their materials direct, except in cases whore an actual economy on tonnage can be effected by the Allied Governments drawing upon British stocks,PIB&amp;AME.    rihe Finnish Government have concluded with Germany a commercial treaty which will remain in force up to Jan, 1st 19 0*  he Finnish Diet have yet to confirm the treaty and only four clauses have so far been published.   Commercial circles in Finland are much disturbed by the published clauses end fear that the unpublished clauses may be worse.   Business men in Finland are wholly Opposed to tho pro-Gorman economic policy of the Finnish Government.   lrhey ap-prehend that the new treaty will mean the commercial ruin of Finland as an Independent economic State.j)E[1MARK.    The Danish Commission which is going to Washington to die-cuss the possibility of a general Agreement between Denmark and the United States will include Mr. Clan of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, a member of the Danish Chamber of Manufacturers and an im-portant Danish shipowner.   Meanwhile, the general discussions are proceeding.   The Daniisc Government have stated that Denmark cannot agree to limit her exports of agricultural produce for more than six months as the Danish farmers cannot know until the next harvest whether they will be able to maintain their stooko of cattle and horses.
y g       A V OThe Germane are at present obtaining comparatively few horse^ from Denmark and these are not of the quality desired. Apparently the Danish surplus of horses has been very considerably reduoed.It has been ascertained that the Allies at present control approximately 600,000 tons deadweight of Danish steam and motor ton-nage out of a total of 822,117 tons.   The Allies also oontrol 4,300 tons of Danish sailing tonnage out of a total of 54,000 tons.The Danish fishermen at Esbjorg and Frederiekshaven are re-ceiving supplies of petroleum and motor oil from Germany and oon-siderable quantities of oil are shortly expeoted.   Only small motor boats and sailing vessels are at present fishing.   The larger deep soa vessels are laid up for lack of petrol.   This season, however, the deep sea cod have oome close in shore and small vessels aro re-imrning with oatohes of from 4,000 to 5,000 lbs*The Danish Government is prepared to prohibit any further export of Danish hides during the next 8 months.    Some 35,000 light hides have already been sold to Sweden in exchange for 1,500 tons of tarm-ing extracts.    Some 60,000 hides could still, however, be shipped to the United Kingdom during the next 8 months in exchange for pro-portionate supplies of tanning extracts and ohromates .   The price asked for the Danish hides is higher than the price quoted by H.M. Government.The Germans are considerably in arrears in their deliveries of steel to the Danish shipyards.   They have delivered only 4,000 tons out of 22,000 tons due under the German-Danish Agreement of December 1917.   Under the new Agreement they have agreed to deliver 1,100 tons monthly.   Vessels built with these materials will be excluslve-ly reserved for the Danish coasting trade, or trade with Germany, Finland and Russia.NORWAY.   We are inviting the Eorwegian Associations to renew their old Agreements with H.M, Government subject to any revisions rendered necessary by the new Agreement between Borway and the United States.
The British licencing authorities are prepared to roe tune iramediate-ly the in sue of export lioenooo for ooramodities formerly imported by the Associations,    H*M* Government will honour outstanding oertifioatos of the Associations if the latter so desire;   but the certificates must be confirmed, and tho shippers will have to renew their applications-    The &quot;general embargo on exports? from the United Kingdom to Norway may now be regarded as raised, and all goods not affected by specific embargoes will be allowed to go for-ward.    The specific embargoes will be reconsidered in the light of the new general Agreement.In order to control Norwegian exports under the new Agreement the Norwegian Government have prohibited, as from May 10th, the ex-port from Norway of all commodities except under Government licence.NiSEHEBIABIS.    3?ho United states Government recently offered to allow three cargoes of grain to proceed to Holland In Dutch requisitioned ships provided three corresponding,/ vessels were sent from Holland to a United States port.    It is reported that the Germans have re-fused to issue safe conducts for those substitute vessels until tip German-Dutch Economic Agreement, now under discussion, is concluded. Sir Wo Sovmley understands that the terms of the Agreement at pro-sent offered to the Dutch are inacoeptable*SWITZERLAND.    She United states Government are sending two cargoes of wheat to the Mediterranean for Switzerland escorted by American war-Iships.    though the German Government have promised to allow a safe passage to Allied ships carrying supplies for Switzerland if they are distinctively marked, it will be at least three months before their instructions can reach the German submarine commanders*    Mean-while Switzerland is In effect blockaded by Germanyo   She United States Government have announced to the Federal Government that they are determined to relieve the food position in Switzerland
without delay and that they accordingly Intend to break the Gexman blockade.   Thia aetion of the United States Government, and the French offer of coal noted 1st at week, have considerably stiffened the attitude of the Swiss In their negotiations with tho German dele-gates at Berne.The Federal Government have on several occasions thought of breaVj ing off these negotiations owing to the offensive attitude of the German delegates, but were deterred by fear of the distress which TOuld follow the stoppage of the German coal supplies,   The Swiss Government now hope that Germany will allow Switzerland to export wood and peat to the Allies as well as goods manufactured from row materials Imported into Switzerland from overseas.   The Federal Hov-ernment have provided themselves with a means of resisting German pressure by prohibiting the export, except under licence and subject to home requirements of hydro-electrical energy.The Agreement for a farther restriction of the export of Swiss cotton goods to Germany, and for preventing the accumulation in Swit-zerland of stocks imported from overseas, was signed at Berne on May8SPAIN.    Early in the week the Spanish Government decided to. requlsi-tion the whole of the Spanish mercantile marine.   The Spanish shipi, owners were, however, Invited to present their views and they unan-imously opposed the scheme.   The Spanish Government have now decided not to requisition the shipping but to set up a close control of feeights   and voyages,ARGEgTIEB.   The Argentine Government have intimated that they are will ing to renew their convention with the Allies Governments for the purchase of the Argentine cereal surplus.IBIS SUBMARINE BLOC  ADS. The following is a summary of the losses to merchant shipping, due to enemy activity, vfoioh were reported In the period May 10 - 16 inclusive.    Smacks and trawlers are omitted:-
Steamships (5)0 tone groas &amp; over)British......*    85,541 tons grossAllied &amp; Heutral   89.863galling      (100 tone gross &amp; over)British c,e0o*, e*Allied &amp; lentral       516    &quot;      &quot;Grand Total *** 65,920 tons grossTotal British., d&amp;9V*H.,.W. CAjUdSSS DAVIS, p.p, John Palmer.War Trade Intel 11 geneeirntDo^ *

</content>
</cab>
