<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/51/0 images: 273-285</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Doct:.       is the F roperty of    / 205His Britannic Majesty&apos;? Government.) IS !ES C!^ -IrS1 31ij \Tl mt&quot; &quot;*&apos;*&quot;tm&quot;mu&quot;m&quot;*m,m       &quot;f^n^nwMINISTRY  OF  FOOD.Report for Week ending Wednesday, May 15, 1918.Sit/ PART I-ACTION TAKEN.Control of Supplies.Allied Requirements. In view of the existing difficulties of railway transport and of handling supplies at docks, besides the pressure on cold storage space, it has been decided not to ask Mr. Hoover for the further export of 42,000 tons of frozen beef for June and 42,000 tons for August mentioned in last week&apos;s Report.Sir Guy Granet has been notified that recent shipments of Canadian frozen beef have caused serious complaint both as regards weight and quality and that boneless beef has shown imperfect preparation. He has also been informed that butter from the United States is giving dissatisfaction owing to poor quality.Sir Guy Granet has again been asked to endeavour to divert the main flow of foodstuffs from North America from Liverpool to London.Sir Guy Granet cables that the following are payments for each commodity made through the Allied Provisions Export Commission to March 30th : $Hams, bacon     - .....101,193,152.80Lard -     -     -     -     -     -     -     -     &quot; &quot;1 13 731 957 06Lard, French Government -     -     -     -     -) &apos;    &apos;Neutral lard     ------- 1,211,305.55Oleooil    -           ...... 2,339,013.29Cotton seed oil  -            ..... 1,299,225.90Preserved corned beef, civilian   - 1,861,121.46Preserved corned beef, military - 4,822,224.09Frozen meat.....-     - 13,070,099.15Butter     -------- 3,244,382.29Pork and beans, military   -     -     -     -     - 265,939.29Dried fruit-     ------- 32,447.50Condensed milk....... 1,122,255.29Cheese     -------- 186,602.54Onion seed........ 28,091.76Whale oil -....... 16,947.32Total      -     -     -     -     -  144,424,765.29For the Aveek ending May 11th Sir Guy Granet estimates the commitments of tonnage at 17,833 with a food value of 8,670,580 dollars.Bacon, Earns, and Lard. The measures for relieving the congestion at Liverpool suggested by the investigations made by Sir H. Stuart at Liverpool, are being carried out. Some cargoes are sent by rail in their entirety to London to be sorted and allotted here on arrival. The Railway Executive Committee have arranged for two trains to be sent daily. An endeavour is also being made to divert some ships from Hull to London.It is hoped that a new Order fixing maximum retail prices for half a dozen cuts will be made shortly, but as the cost of imported bacon has risen it is not likely that prices can be much reduced.Butter. A further purchase of 160 tons of butter has been made in the United States of America at 401- to 44 cents per lb., f.a.s. in New York. During the week ending 11th May, 2,319 tons of butter arrived from Australia, 2,531 tons from New Zealand, 436 tons from the United States of America, 235 tons from South Africa, 35 tons from India, 20 tons from France, and 327 tons from Denmark, making a total of 5,903 tons. On the same date the stocks in hand were 12,857 tons and the quantity still on passage 20,384 tons.A  (33)5683-3  Pk 1   130  5/18   E &amp; SA
Cereals. An Order amending the Grain (Prices) Order, 1917, dated 6th May, 1918, cancels clause 9 of the Principal Order, the effect being that after May 15 the prices of home-grown wheat, rye, barley, and oats, whether sold for the purpose of seed or otherwise, must not exceed the maximum prices set ont in the Order, and also that grain bought before that date specifically for the purpose of seed may be used for any other lawful purpose.Cheese. Advice has been received of further shipments of 3,645 tons of cheese from New Zealand, 800 tons from Australia, and 24 tons of old season cheese (the last of the unshipped stock) from Canada.1,037 tons of cheese have arrived from the United States of America, and 2,611 tons from New Zealand ; in the former country there remain 7,245 tons of unshipped stock and there are 1,200 tons on the way ; in the latter country there are 25,073 tons in store and 10,532 tons are on the water.Dried Fruits. The Greek Currants (Maximum Prices) Order, 1918, dated 1st May, 1918, fixes a maximum price for any currants produced in Greece which have not at the date of the Order arrived in the United Kingdom.The Dried Fruits (Restriction) Order, has been revoked as from 1st May.Fresh Fruit.-The Gooseberries Order, 1918, dated 11th May, 1918, prohibits the picking of gooseberries for sale on or after May 13, and the sale of any gooseberries on or after May 14. The restrictions remain in force until June 1 as regards England and Wales, and June 10 as regards Scotland.The Beehive Section (Maximum Prices) Order, 1918, dated 10th May 1918, fixes the maximum prices of beehive sections. A large quantity of these sections has been imported from the United States by the Ministry of Food with a view to assisting the production of honey.Intoxicating Liquor. A return of bulk barrelage at present sent into and out of the different districts is being required from all brewers excepting home-brewing publicans. The Committee appointed by Lord Rhondda at the request of the President of the Board of Trade to effect economies in fuel and transport have advised that brewers be asked to formulate voluntary schemes for concentrating brewing in each district, and limiting the area within which beer may be delivered from any area.On Tuesday, May 14th, Mr. dynes received Sir George Younger, M.P., and Col. John Gretton, M.P., who stated that considerable apprehension is felt in the trade lest, if these restrictions become operative, free brewers may be unable, when normal conditions recur, to recover the trade which has taken much time, effort, and capital to establish. It was arranged that the Chancellor of the Exchequer and Mr. Clynes should receive a deputation on the subject.Meat. The number of coupons available for the purchase of butcher&apos;s meat has been reduced from three to two, but the value of the remaining two has been increased from 5d. to 6cL each. This hears heavily on the retail butcher whose already limited turnover is still further reduced ; this step is not necessitated by any falling off in meat supplies, which for the time of the year are abundant, but by the heavy supplies of bacon. .Live stock is coming forward more freely than had been anticipated and arrivals of frozen meat are so large that there is great difficulty in. finding storage space for the meat; it may therefore become necessary to permit the third coupon again to be used for meat or in some other way to increase consumption in order to prevent delay in the discharging of steamers now arriving from North America. If the ration were increased it could be maintained for a considerable time.The sale of frozen meat is restricted to some extent by its poor quality ; grave complaints are made of it, and the reluctance of both butchers and public to accept it accentuates the difficulties of the situation.Steps are being taken to obtain from all retailers accurate returns of purchases and sales of meat, and to check these returns against coupons. The inspection of retailer&apos;s premises is being improved in order to stop evasions of the Meat Rationing Order.Milk.-Major Astor has forwarded to Lord Rhondda the resolutions of the Sub-Committee on the Government control of the wholesale distribution of milk (which were printed in last week&apos;s Report) in a covering letter from which the following comments of the parent Committee are extracted : &quot; We trust that the Government may now be prepared to give effect to the recommendations, made by us in February, to control the wholesale
distribution of milk as a temporary war measure in view of the fuller information which we are now able to offer them as to the methods by which these recommendations may be carried out.&quot; On the evidence now before us we are not prepared to agree to the desirability of purchase recommended in paragraph 8 of the Report of the * Sub-Committee. We believe that before coming to any decision as to the desirability of such a step more evidence is required both with regard to the financial terms and to the practical needs and effects of purchasing the entire wholesale milk trade of the country; at the same time, however, we recommend that immediate steps be taken to determine the basis on which the interests concerned could be acquired should this be deemed advisable at any time by the Government.&quot;In our opinion the Government should also examine the possibility and advisability, and also the conditions of compensating the interests concerned for any damage done to them by control Avithout actually purchasing such interests.&quot;There is no direct connection between the control of the wholesale milk trade and the control of the United Dairies Combine. The former is an emergency war measure, which should be regarded as merely temporary. So far as the latter is concerned, war conditions enable the Government to effect by agreement, or failing agreement, by compulsion, what would in normal times require specific anti-trust legislation.Potatoes. An announcement has been made that farmers who are able to satisfy the Ministry of Food on and after May 15 that they are unable to find purchasers for their potatoes in lots of 4 tons or more at or above the base price then ruling will be entitled to receive payment for their potatoes from the Ministry of Food at the rate of 11. per ton. If potatoes are sold to dealers at a figure which is below 11. per ton, but not below the current base price, the seller can claim the difference from the Ministry of Food.Base prices for potatoes delivered on and after May 15 have been fixed as follows : England and Wales, 11. per ton (i.e., no subsidy will be payable in respect ofpotatoes grown in England and Wales). Scotland.   Southern counties, 6L 10s.,,      Midland counties, 6i.,,      Northern counties, 51. 10s. Ireland.    51.Tea. A Conference has been held with officers of the Colonial Office, the Board of Trade Department of Import Restrictions, and a representative of the Nyasaland tea importers. It was decided that Nyasaland tea might be imported if tonnage were available.The first purchases, of China tea on behalf of the Ministry of Food have now been made and some shipments are&apos;being effected.Organised Distribution.Local administration. The number of applications for sanction to increase the membership of the Food Control Committees, on behalf of labour women, and of the Co-operative Movement, are decreasing. In the past week only six applications were received, and authority was given to seven Committees to increase their numbers.On Monday, May 13, Mr. Clynes received a deputation from the Wallasley local authorities on the subject of the resignation of the local food committee and the difficulties which have occurred between the Committee and the Divisional Commis-sioner.. The discussion appeared to remove all misunderstanding and it is understood that a. fresh committee will be forthwith elected.Meat rationing. The Ministry of Food have issued revised instructions having immediate effect, regulating the sale of offal, and making other amendments in the Meat Rationing Scheme., , -Certain kinds of edible offal, horseflesh, meat of goats and kids, and certain meat pies, may be sold without coupons.In order to encourage the sale of non-exempted meats of all kinds the coupon values given in the Table of Equivalent Weights have been considerably increased.The Commissioner for the London. Division has drawn attention to a difficult problem with regard to West End butchers, arising out of the restrictions imposed
on the sale of meat. Their position, and that of the butchers in the East End of London may, he says, be regarded as reversed since the War. To-day the East End butcher is, he points out, making good profits, while the trade in the West End is so greatly diminished that many of the butchers with shops in highly-rented localities are losing so heavily that they find themselves unable to meet their liabilities. At the same time these latter butchers are supplying a want as retail distributors to thickly populated areas in that part of London, and that being so, they contend that they should be subsidized by Government. The Commissioner suggests that they will have to combine and work out a basis for themselves, although this would entail the closing of a proportion of the shops concerned. Some solution of the difficulty appears to be required without delay.Supplementary Rations.- On Tuesday, May 14th, Mr. Clynes received a deputation from Manchester munition workers, on the subject of supplementary rations for women on heavy work.Certain modifications in the present system of dealing with applications for extra rations on the grounds of ill-health were submitted to Mr. Clynes on Tuesday, May 14th. Captain Tallents outlined the following fresh arrangements which had been suggested to him by Dr. Hutchison : (1) The schedule of diseases in respect of which Committees may grant extra rations without reference to London should now be extended.   Dr. Hutchi-son had mentioned as instances of diseases of this kind :  Duodenal ulcers.Graves disease (exophthalmic goitre). Pernicious anaemia. Asthma in old people.Failure to digest starch or bacon (generally in old people). Severe loss of blood (fats and meat). Nephritis (fat only).Dysentery, malaria, or shell-shock in the case of ex-soldiers, but not healed wounds.Convalescence from serious illness or operation, including child-birth, in which the child does not survive.Dr. Hutchison is prepared to consider this list carefully, and to suggest the period for which extra rations might be granted by the Food Control Committee concerned in each instance. Generally speaking it was thought that one month would be a reasonable time. He will also consider in each case whether the alternative of an extra meat or fat ration might be given. As soon as his list is complete he wishes to consult the Reference Committee of the Colleges of Physicians and Surgeons, with a representative of the Central Medical War Committee.(2) Every Food Control Committee should be authorised to grant on medical certificates extra rations in cases of - emergency for one week, pending confirmation in London.(3) Food Control Committees might be authorised to grant extra meat to make raw beef juice for babies below one year on a medical certificate, such a grant to be limited to a fortnight.(4) White flour applications should in future be dealt with in the first instance by Local Food Offices, who should be empowered to make a grant for a period not exceeding six weeks. Applications for renewal should be made  probably through the Food Office to the Ministry of Food, and should contain full particulars of the reasons for the claim certified or given by the doctor in the case. Steps will be taken to bring to the notice of doctors the latest available information as to the cases in which grants should be made. In suitable cases of renewal a permit to obtain white flour for 12 months should be granted. This suggestion is subject to the approval of the Royal Commission on Wheat Supplies.(5) Maternity Centres providing meals for mothers should be allowed to serve meat without requiring the production of coupons.(6) Boys passing the age of 18 and preparing to take up military service at, e.g., 18 , should be empowered to get the supplementary card &quot; C.&quot;(7) The proof instruction with regard to expectant mothers should at once be issued, the alternative being given between one meat coupon and one
PART II. SUMMARY OF THE FOOD POSITION.The progress recorded in the following paragraphs and tables confirms the views expressed in recent reports that May would witness a change in the food position : (1) The stocks (Table F) are generally satisfactory, as will be seen by their comparison with those held on May 1st, 1917, or in previous months of the current year. In two cases, however, their size is apt to be misleading. The stock of bacon and ham has increased, but, on the other hand, the substitution of bacon for meat on an additional coupon makes a large stock and heavy supplies essential. Again, the stock of sugar is unusually high. It must, however, be remembered that the sources of supply have been curtailed, and that when the Cuban imports are over there will be little to look forward to for some time. Unless we begin the winter with a large stock, and care be exercised in its conservation, a reduction in the ration may be necessary in the beginning of next year.(2) Rationing has undoubtedly proved successful in lessening the rate of consumption, despite the leakages which naturally have accompanied its inauguration in, at any rate, some districts. The increase in the ration has had several advantages. It has shown that a rationing system is elastic, and has done much to convince the public that the restrictions on consumption will be relaxed when circumstances and the considerations of future safety permit.(3) Contrary to anticipations, the rationing of certain foods has not been accompanied by a rise in the consumption of breadstuffs, which, as shown in Table E, has remained singularly steady for several months. No doubt the plentiful supply of potatoes has conduced to this result. &apos; A consider-able fall, such as that experienced during the summer in 1917, can.hardly be anticipated.    ............. 1............................a 3whole fats ration per week. The form M. 55 as at present drafted, has to be further amended so far as the declaration to be made by the expectant mother herself is concerned.(8) The Department would consult the Local Government Board as to the best means of linking up the notification to tuberculosis patients with the grant of extra rations.(9) The Ministry of Food will consult the British Medical Association as to the form in which a check could best he made upon the improper grant of medical certificates by local doctors to the detriment of other doctors in their neighbourhood, who act according to the spirit of the Ministry of Foods intentions.Enforcement of Orders.A comparison of the recent returns show that in the past week the number of prosecutions have fallen off considerably, particularly in London, which only sent in 39 cases as against 180 in the previous week, but the Home Counties Division sent in nine more cases than the week before, heading the list of Divisional Returns with 78 prosecutions. In three Divisions Newcastle, Glasgow and Inverness-it is satisfactory to find, as showing the care exercised in bringing pi-osecutions, that the percentage of successful convictions was .100. The total number of prosecutions for the week was 617, 552 of which were successful. The average fine for England, Scotland and Wales was 8L 11s. id., for Ireland 6s., showing the increase in the former case of 31. 16s. lOd. and in the latter a decrease of 2s. It is remarked by the Commissioner for the North Wales Division that there is a reluctance on the part of the Food Committees in that Division to take proceedings and that they are content with warning offenders only. Prosecutions were issued this week under 64 Orders  six more than in the previous week.The largest number of returns amounting to 82 wras in connection with the Potatoes (Growers Returns) Order. There was a marked decrease in cases in con-nection with the Public Meals Order, there being only nine this week against 40 the week before.
j     :: .   Imports.The imports of food in the week ended March .11th were considerably above the relatively high average of the past four weeks. The total quantity of the principal foods and feeding stuffs received, as shown in Table A, amounted to 291,800 tons compared with 253,800 tons in the preceding week. Arrivals of wheat and wheaten flour were again at a high level and amounted to 124,200 tons, compared with an average of 68,700 tons since the beginning of the year. Converted into equivalent grain the increase on the week before was 32,000 tons. Other cereals more than recovered their fall of last week. Both rice and maize arrived in large quantities. The average weekly aggregate of all cereals, including wheat, for the four weeks to May 11th was 184,100 tons, compared with 93,500 in the previous four weeks.From the exceptional figures of last week meat and bacon and hams declined heavily, the former from 20,100 tons to 12,300 tons, the latter from 38,100 tons to 18,300 tons. Only 18,700 tons of sugar were received, which is less than half the amount received a year ago. Cheese was much better than for several weeks past but slightly below the weekly average of 1917. More than 8,600 tons of tea were received as against 4,300 tons in the corresponding week of last year.Imports of oil seeds, nuts and kernels during April showed a great improvement on those of March, and on those a year ago. In the first four months of this year total arrivals have been 9 per cent, less than in the first four months of 1917.Consumption.Meat. For the week ended May 11th the aggregate supplies at the Central London Markets were 3,432 tons, a decline on the week before of 9 per cent. There were falls in both home and imported supplies, in the former of 124 tons and in the latter of 200 tons.: Total supplies at the four markets included in Table B were practically the same for the week ended May 4th, as for the week before. There was again an increase in home-fed meat and a decrease in foreign meat amounting to 200 tons for each kind. Heavier imports of meat are not having as sustained or as great an effect as desired on the marketed supplies of home-killed meat. For January of this year the percentage of foreign meat in the total at these four markets was 44, for February 51, for March 62, and for April 61, but for the week under review the percentage was only 54. A similar tale is told by the preliminary returns for April of the number of animals slaughtered (Table C). Except in pigs, where there is a further heavy decline, the figures show no marked changes on March. Compared with a year ago the number of cattle and sheep killed were each about 30 per cent, lower, but a month ago the corresponding falls were 35 per cent, and 39 per cent, respectively. From March to April 1917, the index fell 7-1- points for cattle and 7 points for sheep ; this year the fall in cattle was only 2 points and in sheep there was a rise of 1 point.&quot;Market returns show that the number of cattle stalled in England and Wales was 7 per cent, less in the week ended May 4th than in the preceding week. The number of sheep increased by an equal percentage.The following tables gives a comparison with 1917 : Number of Cattle Stalled.				Week ending	Number of Markets.	1918.                     1917.		Percentage Change.April 20th -,,   27th -      -      -May 4th    -&apos;     -    , -11th  -     -            -	408 355 370   &apos; 339	19,586 19.445 19,294 18,004	32,390 28,032 29,504 30,410	- 39-5 - 30-6 - 34-6 - 40-8Number of Sheep Stalled.				Week ending	Number of Markets.	1918.	1917.	Percentage Change.April 20th -,, 27th - - - -May 4th    -      -      -      -V nth -     -     -	387 337 357 326	59,506 61,073 60,969 47,496	100,980 99,673 85,495 84,251	- 40-0 - 38-7 - 28-6 - 43-6
Fish. The quantity of fish passing through Billingsgate Market during the week ending March 11th was 2,052 tons as compared with 2,176 tons in the week before and with 2,240 tons in the corresponding week of 1917. VArrivals at other Inland markets for each of the four weeks April 13th to May 4th are shown below : 		1918.   Week ending						jviarkei.					April 13th.	April 20tli.	April 27th.	May 4th.	Tons.	Tons	Tons.	Tons.   ., ,Birmingham       ...	281	336	365	336Bradford    ....	57	60	59	51Bristol       .      .      .	48	46	55	44Glasgow	232	269	354	313Leicester   -	131	148	94	,     119Liverpool  -     -      -     -	231	234	,    206	282Mauchcster -     -            -	321	316	301	299Nottingham       -	49	100	62	51Total -	1,350	1,509	1,496	1,495Stocks.Stocks on May 1st were in general higher than on April 1st.Estimates of cereal stocks will have to be modified when the results are known of the stocktaking on the farms made on May 1st. Figures now available point to an increase in stocks of wheat during April, this being the first month of the present cereal year during which stocks have risen. Maize and rice have also increased during the past month, but barley and oats have fallen. Stocks of wheat are much larger than a year ago.All other stocks, with the exception of coffee, cocoa, oilseed cake and margarine, rose during the month. Particularly marked was the increase in bacon and hams, from 9,300 tons to 30,100 tons. Stocks are, however, still 15,700 tons below last May. Other meats also rose and are all higher than a year ago.The stock of sugar has again substantially increased. The contrast with last year when the stock was only 18,000 tons, is striking; but, as pointed out in previous Reports, the apparent security in the sugar position is heavily discounted by the necessity of building up unusually large stocks by the autumn in order that adequate supplies for the winter may be assured, only very small imports can be expected when the Cuban crop is exhausted.a 4
Table A..--Imports&quot; of Principal Food and Feeding Stuffs.Article.			A verage vVoekly Net Imports4 in 1913.	Average Weekly Imports.		Total Imports.	Week ending May 11th, 1918.	Week ending May 4th, 1918.	Week ending May 12th, 1917.		19 Weeks from Doc. 30th, 1917, to May 11th, 1918.	Corros-ponding Period. 1917.	19 Weeks from Dei.&apos;. 30th, 1917 to May 11th, 1918.	Oorrcs-ponding Period, 1917. .2,	3.	4.	5.	6. &quot;	7.	8.	9.Tons. 64,68.5 59,505 6,490	Tons. 55,475 42,230 11,635	Tons. 124,450 12,265 3,105	Tons. 101,378 9,712 8,849	Tons. 37,414 31,337 7,371	Tons. 92,576 8,023 4,806	Tons. 710,870 595,420 140,042	Tons. 1,758,950 152,445 91,3211,600	2,020	557	5,125	2,124	3,026	40,353	57,4994,195	6,441	1,975	2,126	2,585	2,354	49,114	44,73315,624 2,648 3,482 2,474 2,886 18,659	30,990 7,061 4,382 793 4,531 31,136	6,868 653 2,701 1,814 1,237 2,392 40,338	j 5,267 1,629 1,460 2,137 3,867 37,333	(   9,694 1   1,437 2,080 805 1,567 2,149 26,270	8,243 1,288 2,821 2,298 2,230 3,071 21,830	184,188 27,298 39.523 15,298 29,772 40,838 499,124	156,623 24,474 53,604 43.662 42,363 58,354 414,761860	523	7,859	1,408	548	1,370	10,404	26,029183,108	191,211	206,214	180,291	125,381	153,936	2,382,244	2,924,8182,765 46,825	3,780 51,265	4,325 27,925 41,915	21,565 17,464 46,450	8,205 2,405 22,287	7,903 6,661 34,533	155,890 45.690 423,465	150,160 126,560 656,12549,590	55,045	14,165	85,419	32,891	49,091	625,045	932,845232,698	252,363	280,379	265,770	158,278	203,033	3,007,289	3,857,66350,526 8,607	1,525	4,255	2,554 2,640	f7,956 4,709	f 1,875 2,499	fl36,385 89,467	f32,144 47,480Net Imports.*			A verage Monthly Net Imporls* in 1913.	Average Monthly Net Imports. *		Total Net lmports.*	Month ending April 30th, 1918.	Month ending March 31st, 1918.	Month ending April 30th, 1917.		4 Months Jan -April, 1918.	Corres-. ponding Period. 1917.&apos;	4 Mouths Jan.-April, 1918.	Corres-ponding Period, 1917.Tons. 124,781	Tons. 69,524	Tons. 94,520	JLOUS. 120,314	ions. 94,676	Tons. 104,315	Tons. 378,704	Tons. 417,261143	355	20,662	29,435	1,172	21,177	4,688	84,707 .1. Wheat -2. Wheaten flour3. Beef (fresh, refrigerated and frozen).4. Mutton (fresh, refrigerated and frozen).5. Moat, nuenii-merated (re-frigerated and     pro-served).6. Bacon - &apos;   -7. Hams -8. Lard   -9. Margarine   -10. Cheese 11. Butter -12. Sugar (refined and      un-refined). 13. Sugar, glucoseTotal     -1.4, Barley -15, Oats -16, Maize -TotalAll principal foods and feeding stuffs.17. Rice -18. Tea    -19. Oil seeds and nuts and kernels.20. Oilseed cake* Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind, f These figures relate to net imports for the four months. January to April.
Table B-Statistics illustrating Consumption of Meat., Tons.Average weekly supplies during June and July .1913:   Central Market, London ----- 8,245 ,y. &apos;. Manchester Market ;     -     - -     .  -     -      855Glasgow Market   - . -       -       -       &apos;- ;  &apos; 798Liverpool Market ------      221; :,4 r:-HJ .    n     Total &apos;:&apos; ^ 10,119 1Supplies of Meat entering the Central Market, London, and Manchester, Glasgow,and Liverpool Markets.Period.	Home-fed.				Foreign.				Home and Foreign.				Weekly Average.				Weekly Average.				Weekly Average.				11916.	1917.		1918.	1916.	1917.		1918.	1916.		&quot; 1 1917.     j	1918Jan. Feb. Mar. April May \ June July       -Aug.   :; -Sept. Oct. Nov. Dec.	Tons. 5,629 4,863 4,756 4,215 3,720 3,452 3,371 3,584 4,406 5,288 5,422 5,095	Tons. 4,401 4,422 4,546 4,211 3,919 3,369 3,345 4,396 4,844 5,670 5,656 4,702		Tons. 2,747 2,306 1,792 1,928	i Tons. 3,851 4,143 i 3,460 3,519 3,268   i 3,939 -3,775 ; 3.334 3,576 3,618 3,426 3,306	Tons. 4,279 2,977 2,971 2,957 2,537 2,986 2,844 2,350 2,300 2,197 1,825 2,099		Tons. 2,142 2,388 2,892 3,455	Tons. 9,480 9,006 8,216 7,734 6,988 7,391 7,146 6,918 7,982 8,906 8,848 8,401	Tons. 8.680 7,399 7,517 7,168. 6,456 6,355 6,189 6,746 7,144 7,867 7,481 6,801		Tons. 4,889 . 4,694 4,684 5,383	1917.		1918.   -		1917.		.   1918.		.1917.		,1918.	.. Week . ended:																								27th Apr.	3,638		2,149		2,752		2,934		6,390		5,083	4th May	3,573		2,333		2,864		- 2,727 !		.  6,437		.5,060...	A (33)6683-3
Table C-Animals Slaughtered in 7,006 Private and Public Slaughterhouses in Great Britain in April 1917, March 191.8, and April 1918.	Cattle.	Calves.	Sheep and Lambs,	Pigi.April 19L7  -......-March 1918 -      -     -     -      -     1                     -April 1918........-	79,905 56,309 54,912	15,939 17,553 16,767	234,421 160,188 165,347	113,650 49,681 40,065Percentage Increase or Decrease : April 1918 compared with April 1917	-31-30/o	+ 5.-n	-29-5 \	-64-7%April 1918 compared with March 1918      ...	- 2-5X	- 4-50/0	4- ^2 1	-19-3%Index Numbers of Animals Slaughtered (measured as percentages of the levels of September 1917).Cattle.Calves.Sheep and Lambs.Pigs.1916-17.SeptemberOctoberNovemberDecemberJanuaryFebruaryMarchApril* -1917-18.SeptemberOctoberNovemberDecemberJanuaryFebruaryMarchApril* -96* 102&quot; 104 104^90*96* 89100 115* 115&quot; 116.V63*60*636173*7775*6166* 104* 157 1661001061 97&quot; 771 81&quot;12118317592184&quot;78*68*71*657063100 104 10181171* 35 43 44134154*1611931163&quot;1421401361001121091126&quot;113k91* 59&quot; 48* Provisional figures.Table D.-Index Numbers of Quantities of Milk carried by Seven of the Principal Railway Companies in England and Wales.(Weekly averages measured as percentages of the level in September 1917.)1917.		1918.		1918.	September	100	January -	851	Week ended :j	October -	97*	February	871	- April 13th   -	97*November	93*	March   -	93*	April 20th   -	. 98*December	85*	April	97*	April 27th   -	101				May 4th	100*
Tarle E. Index Numbers; of Consumption of Bread, Mea.t, and&apos;Provisions.	Retail Consumption of Bread and PjjOUJt (measured as percentages of the level of May lit 17).								1916.	1917.	1918.		(4 weeks ended)  January 5th February 2nd March 2nd -March 30th April 27th -May 26th  -June 23rd -July 21st  -August 18th September 15th . October 13th November 10th December 8 th	-!	99 100 97i 99&quot; 95 94 954 98, lOlf	944 99&quot; 1024 &apos; 104.1 101&quot; 100 95 914 894 904 (92) 97&quot;(96) 100 , 100	96 1004 iooJ 100 100	The numbers in brackets are adjusted for the probable change in the stock of flour held at home before and after the reduction in price on September 17th.Consumption of Meat (measured as percentages of the average monthly consumption in 1916).	Home Fed.			Foreign.			Home and Foreign. Index Numbers combined.			1916.	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.	1918.	1916.	: 1917.	1918.January	116	941	631	106	94	31	115 .	941	581February	1041	86	52	95	88^	794	103	864	551March	106	951	541	102	774	931	1054	93	604April	9H	90	*61	99	80$	*102	95i	881	*67May  -	854,	90		109	581		89	854	June -      -      -	864	75		101	58		88^	721	July -     -	84&quot;	831		122	67^		891	81*	August	191	954		102	44		92	88	September -	99	951		114	65		101	91	October	1051	108		86	65		102	1011	November -	1101	1024		86	501		107	95	December -	117	94		78	32		112	85	* Provisional figures.Consumption of Provisions, based on returns from multiple shops and co-operative societies. (measured as percentages of the levels of October 1917).. .--	Butter.	Margarine.	Lard.	Bacon.	Hams.	Cheese.(4 weeks ended) 						September 2nd, 1916 -	213	 	85	179	119	146September 30th, 1916 -	207	 	85-	166	110	140October 28th, 1916    -	194	 	85	160	114	140November 25th, 1916 -	176  &apos;		120	169	113	130December 23rd, 1916 -	175	-	113	179	137	124January 20th, 1917    -	150	  :	98	148	106	102February 17th, 1917 -	135	 	10!	160	106	108March 17th, 1917	127	 	94	134	92	92April 14th, 1917	141	 	.    82	129	97	86August 4th, 1917	212	84	90	170	148	108September 1st, 1917   -	214	89	94	165	118	108    .: September 29th, 1917 -     -	191	93	95	138	109	107    ,October 27th, 1917    -     -	100	100	100   ,	100	100	100November 24th, 1917 -	54	-    95	66	85	86	102December 22nd, 1917 -     -	......54 .....	106	43........	.....824-	-.........89	......&apos; 92January 19th, 1918   -	.    43 i o	85	.  37	66&quot;	68	54February 16th, 1918  -	37	97	30	491	431	51March 16th, 1918	. 43 -	96	28	60	38	52April 13th, 1918       -     -	67	60*	54 -	75	58	43* The apparent heavy fall in the consumption of margarine is due to the invoicing to the Ministry of Food of 3,700 tons that would otherwise have been distributed by one of the firms making returns.A   5683-3 C
Table F.*-Stocks of the Principal , Foods and Feeding Stuffs in theUnited Kingdom.Article.		May 1st, 1918.	April 1st, 1!)18.	May 1st, 1917.		Slocks in the United Kingdom&apos; including estimated Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including flour) -         -         -         -Barley   ------Oats      ------Beans    -        -        -        -        -;       -Peas      -         -         -         -         -         -		Tons. 1,525,000 331,000 473,000 75,000 38,000	Tons. 1,512,000 372,000 682,000 77,000   , 30,000	Tons. 1,063,000 419.000 392.000 43,000 19,000		Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, kc.		Maize    -         -         -         -Rice (including ground rice and rice flour) Grain Meals      -----Sugar    -         -         -         -		118,000 120,000 46,000 287,000	83,000 118,000 41,000 218,000	148,000 76,000 16.000 18,000		Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and in Importers&apos; Warehouses.		Butter Margarine                   -         -         -         -Lard      ------Cheese   -       . -Condensed Milk           -         -Meat: Beef (chilled and frozen) Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon and Hams Poultry, Game, and Rabbits     -Other Meat     -fish - &apos;-        -         -       . -       iJT.		8,100 2,100 4,400 10,300 12,700 46,700 37,900 30,100  &apos; 13,900 16,600 17,300	3,300 2,400   1 1,800 9,700 f6,600 45,300   ; 33,600 9,300 13,500 11,100 15,200	18,200 3,300 28,500 4,200 15,200 16,200 24,100 45,800 5,500 13,700 12,800	i -	Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.		Tea Coffee Cocoa		42,500 44,200 31,200	41,600 46,700 37,000	39,600 71,000 59,600		Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports and in the hands of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.		Oilseeds, Ac.      -         -         -         -         -Oilseed Cake and Meal  -        -        -      i -		209,500 43,100	175,600 57,800	443,000 94,200* The. figures for wheat and flour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland warehouses, mills, and bakers shops, as well as estimated stocks on the farms : those for barley, oats, beans, and peas include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills, in maltsters&apos; hands, and estimated farm stocks. In regard to all other articles, home produce is, with very small exceptiqns, excluded.t In manufacturers&apos; hands only. tNumber of Live Stock in England and Wales.----	April 4th, 1918 (Estimated).	December 2nd, 1917 (Census).	June 4th, 1917.	m. -  -   . June 5th, 1916.Dairy Cattle -Total Cattle  -Ewes kept for breeding Total Sheep -        -Sows kept for breeding Total Pigs i - &apos;   &apos;   -	2,486,000 5,863,000 6,143,000 13,914,000 235,000 1,534,000	2,579,000 5,891,000 6,745,000 12,684.000 263,000 **2,439,000	2,465.000 6,227,000 -   6,872,000 17,170,000 254,000 1,919,000	2,420.000 6,216.000 7,047.000 17,95L000 283,000 2,168,000** Includes pigs belonging to]cottagers.
Table  --Percentage Increase in Retail Food Prices in the United Kingdom, at each of the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot;Normal Prices in July .1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 19U.Article.										1st Jan.	1st Jan..	1st Jan.	1st July 1917.	1st Sept.	1st Jan.	1st Mar.	1st Apr.	1st May	1915.	1910.	1917.		1917.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.Beef :-									British Ribs	7-0	35-3	64-2	96-1	97-4	80-5	83-7	84-4	84-8Thin flank	11-2	45-2	83-5	132 - 2	130-9	100-9	101-6	98-8	98-3Chilled or frozen 									Ribs  -	16-3 ,	46-7	85-4	119-6	122-1	116-4	116-8	133-5	147-9Thin flank -	26-7	63-1	101-2	1565	157-9	137-3	136-6	150-3	164-7Mutton : 									British Legs	5-8	27-9	58 - 7	100 0	97-7	76-8	80-1	85-5	85-9Breast	11-7	413	84-2	142-2	138-2	92-5	96&apos;0	81-1	81-4Frozen Legs	16-3	41-8	86-4	134-4	136-0	134-0	135-7	161-8	176-5Breast	24-8	62-7	122-0	190-8	190-9	161-8	361-8	147-1	168-5Bacon, streaky*	7-1	30&apos;7	56-3	76-4	96-0	138-7	139-4	139-8	1386Fish	40-9	96-7	131-1	127-1	136-1	195-9	219-6	219-5	220-5Flour	20-3	49-0	88-5	109-3	109-2	51-8	51-8	51-9	51-9Bread      ...	15-8	41-7	73-3	100-3	996	54-4	54&apos;4	54-4	54-3Tea -	13-6	48-2	50-9	73-7	78-9	98-2	90-2	79-2	73-3Sugar, granulated	67-0	93-3	170-0	1877	190-0	189-3	187-3	186-7	237-5Milk	6-7	28&apos;8	56-6	59-7	61-0	99-5	102-5	101-5	64-6Potatoes  -	P6-1	\4-8	121-7	144-3	38-9	37-1	36-5	37-0	39-2Margarine	4-4	6-9	25-0	73-5	66-0	65-9	68-5	68-8	68-8Butter, fresh	13-8	33&apos;9	72-9	64-7	90-8	103-4	104-4	104-7	104-5Butter, salt	12-1	31-5	70-6	65-3	90-1	105-4	108-8	109-0	109-2Cheese, Canadian or U.S.*	10-0	31-7	74-8	108-0	94-7	91-3	91-7	91-2	94-0									Etrps. fresh	63-4	104-9	175-0	95-3	142-4	242-1	239-9	211-1	201-8* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative, f Decrease.Table H. Retail Prices of Subsidiary Foods in April, 1917, and Subsequent Months compared with the Prices in July, 1914, in London andother large Towns.[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	April 1st,	July 1st,	Sept. 1st,	Dec. 1st,	Jan. 1st,	Feb. 1st,	Mar. 1st,	April 1st,	May 1st.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1917.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918.Butter beans   -	160	140	110	113	113	113	113	113	113Haricot beans (white)	230	180	140	140	140	140	140	140	140Peas, split (yellow) -	140	210	210	212	220	220	220	220	220Lentils, split (red)   -	210	230	220	232	232	232	232	232	232Oatmeal, Scotch	140	150J	150+	141	100	100	113	113	113Rice, Rangoon	90	100	100	1O0	103	103	117	117	117Sago	140	180	180	189	200	200	209	227	245Tapioca -	120	160	150	159	170	177	177	185	200Condensed milk	65	110	110	120	, 139	139	139	143	152Lard, British  -	125	120	120	128	125	125	 	 	^ . &apos;:.,   American	130	110	120	139	. 139	143	157	164	164J 125 in Scotland.

</content>
</cab>
