<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/94/0 images: 59-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
sptrjg nnflTTMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)7*G R E T. COPY NO.cabinet      30 (58)Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10 downing street, S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, 29th JUNE, 1938,at lloO a.m.AGENDA.1.     FOREIGN AFFAIRS.2.     AIR MISSION TO UNITED STATES AND CANADA:    CREATION OFA WAR POTENTIAL FOR AIRCRAFT PRODUCTION IN CANADA.(Reference Cabinet 26 (38) Conclusion 6)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.CP, 143 (38) - circulated herewith.Draft Conclusions of a Meeting of Ministers.CP. 148 (38) - to be circulated.3.      DEFENCE OF INDIA:    CONVERSATIONS BETWEEN THE WAR OFFICEAND THE INDIA OFFICE.(Reference Cabinet 5 (38) Conclusion 11 (b))Statement by the Prime Minister.4.      TRING MUSEUMa(Reference Cabinet 26 (38) Conclusion 8)Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,covering draft BilloC.P. 144 (38) - already circulated.5,      THE POULTRY INDUSTRY 0(Reference Cabinet 44 (37) Conclusion 1)Joint memorandum -um by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries and the Secretary of State for Scotland.CP. 146 (38) - circulated herewith.
60    SARAWAK AND BRUNEI:    DEFENCE OF MIRI AND SERIAOILFIELDS:    DENIAL SCHEME.Note by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence,covering extract from draft Minutes of the 327thMeeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence,together with Memorandum by the Oversea defence sub-Committee.CP. 145  (38) - circulated herewith.(Signed)   M.P.A. hankey secretary to the Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.24th June, 1938.
60    SARAWAK AND BRUNEI:    DEFENCE OF MIRI AND SERIAOILFIELDS:    DENIAL SCHEME.Note by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence,covering extract from draft Minutes of the 327thMeeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence,together with Memorandum by the Oversea defence sub-Committee.CP. 145 (38) - circulated herewith.(Signed)    M.P.A. hankey secretary to the Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.24th June, 1938.
CABINET        30(53).CONCLUSIONS of a meeting of the Cabinejt heldat 10 Downing Street,  S.-W.1. , on WEDNESDAY,the 29th JUNE, 1938, at 11.0 a.m.COPY No.PRESENT:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M-P.Prime Minister.le Right Hon.Sir John Simon, CCS.I.,G.C.V.O., O.B.E., K.C., M.P. ,Ohancellor of the Exchequer..e Right Hon.Lord Maugham,Lord Chancellor.e Right Hon.The Viscount    Halifax, K.C,CCS.I. , G-.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs..e Right Hon.Lord Stanley, M.C., M.P. ,Secretary of State forDominion affairs.e Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald,  M*P. ,Secretary of State for theColonies.e Right Hon.A. Buff Cooper, D.S.O.,  M.P. ,First Lord of the Admiralty.e Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, M.P. ,Secretary of State for Air*e Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P. ,President of the Board of Trade.e Right Hon. -nanThe Earl Stanhope, K.G., D.b.u.,M.C., President of the Board olEducation..e Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M* C j M.p* minister of Labour,(in the Chair.)The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt. ,  CCS.I.,CB.E. , CM.G-. , M.P. , Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Earl De La Warr,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,CO.S.Io,  G&quot;.CcIflE.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon.Sir Thomas Inskip, C.B.E., K.C,M.P., Minister for Co-ordinationof Defence.The Right Hon.L. Hore-Belisha,  M. P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.John Colville, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon.WoSo  Morrison, M.C., K.C., M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheriescThe Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M. C , M. P. ,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.E.L. Burgin, M.P*.Minister of Transport.The Right Hon.The Earl Winterton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., G. C M. C , G.C.V.O.Secretary.
SPAIN. ^&apos;    The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsTnd is criminate reported that Sir R0 Hodgson, His Majesty&apos;s DiplomaticBombing- ,^     -I Representative with General Franco s Government, was on neutral Corn-mission, his way home with a reply on the question of indiscrimm-ate bombing.   He was due to arrive the following after-(previous reference:     noon.   He himself had sent a telegram to His Majesty&apos;cabinet 29(38), Con-     Ambassador in Rome giving him instructions to see the elusion 6.)Italian Foreign Minister and to make certain representa-tions with a view to inducing Signor Mussolini to use his influence with General Franco to stop the bombing.Later on in the Meeting the Secretary of State read the Earl of Perth&apos;s reply.The Secretary of State then read a telegram received by the Admiralty from the Rear-Admiral CommandingThird Cruiser Squadron stating that Admiral Moreno(General Franco&apos;s Governor at Palma.) had informed him of orders he had received f^om General Franco in personimperatively forbidding attacks on British merchant ships,and stating that all bombing was to cea.se for four days from the 28th June.As to the proposed Neutral Commission, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs recalled that the original proposal had been that it should include representativesof the United Sta.tes of America, Norway and. Sweden.Owing to the hesitating attitude of the United StatesGovernment the Swedish Government had threatened towithdrew.   With a view to avoiding this, he (the Secretaryof State) had persuaded, the Dutch Government to join inthe Commission.    The Dutch and. Swedish Governments had.insisted, as a condition, upon the approval of both parties to the Spanish conflict being obtained.    TheBarcelona Government had accepted, but General-Franco&apos;sGovernment was objecting to either a Swede or a Norwegian
being included.    The alternatives appeared to be eitherto drop the proposal and put. the onus on General Franco,/o go  on^with a Norwegian,  if possible, or with the addition ofrepresentatives of other nations, such as Switzerlandor Poland:    if those were not acceptable, the UnitedKingdom Government should go on with the proposal by itself.    It. was possible, however, that. General Francomight accept a Swiss representative-    What the Secretaryof State proposed to do, therefore, was to try and secure a Swiss/member of the Commission, though he would likeauthority from the Cabinet, in the last resort, to formthe Commission with British representatives only.This was agreed to.In reply to a question about General Franco&apos;suggestion that some port in the part of Spain occupiedby the Government should be set aside for the importationand. exportation of certain.in commodities, which by agree-ment would be exempt from the risk of bombing, theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointed out thatthe suggestion raised the question of belligerent rights.The President of the Board of Trade said he hopedthat no decision would be taken by the Foreign secretary on this subject without considering the views of theBoard of Trade, which were being forwarded.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreedto this.    The proposal had originally covered variouscommodities, including food.   He gathered now that itwas rather more restricted, including such items asmedicaments.   He understood also that part of theproposal was that there should be international observers .arrived at the port having on board other^eflSmoditiesbesides the res trie tedjJJ^feC^^Would it not be possiblef or usjjjs^flly^^tot-ake note of the arrangement, if it
S3The President of the Board of Trade suggested thatthe proposal might be brousht before the Cabinet Committeeon Foreign Policy before it was decided.   He did notthink that the Board of Tra.de could agree to any list of commodities less than those included in the list applied,for non-intervention purposes.    Some of the ports that had been suggested would, be useless, because they werenot equipped with sufficient facilities to deal with thevolume of goods involved -The Prime Minister suggested that the proposal wasnot necessarily useless because the port would not provide a complete substitute for the facilities o^ the ports now used.The Cabinet agreed  (a.)  That as regards the proposed NeutralCommission to report on the cireum-stances of indiscriminate bombing in spain, the proposals of the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs as setforth above should be approved:    thatis to say, he should proceed, with his proposals for forming a Commission toinclude representatives of countries such as Norway^ Sweden, Holland,Switzerland and Poland, but in thelast resort, if he could not obtainacceptance of representatives of thesecountries, he should form a Commissionto include British representatives only,if that should prove acceptable:(b) That before a decision was taken on general Franco&apos;s proposal for the selection of a port in territory ofthe Barcelona Government which wouldbe exempt from bombing, the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs should discuss the question with Sir R, Hodgson,and to take note that he would not take any action in the matter without cons ider-ation of the views of the President ofthe Board of Trade.
CENTRAL. EUROPE. 2.   The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsCzechoslovakia, reported that the negotiations between the Governmentof Czechoslovakia, and the Sudeten Deutseh were proceed-(previous reference:       ing and. he himself was keeping up pressure on theCabinet 29(38), Con-      former.    The latest news from Herr Henlein was not tooelusion 7*)discouraging&quot;,    first, because he reported, that herr hitler would not upset any settlement he might reach,nor demand a plebiscite:    and, second^ owing to M.Frank&apos;s interview \?ith the British Minister at Prague.His own vie^, however, was that they were not likelyto reach an agreement.   He thought it probable that atsome point we should have to try and persuade both sidesto accept the view that they had. obtained a good, dealand should be content.   He himself, on the previous day,had seen the German Ambassador, who had said that theGerman Government had. 100$ confidence in Dr. Hodza,but less in Dr. Benes.The Lord President of the Council said that LordLondonderry, who h8.d. just returned from Berlin, had found Field-Marshal Goering somewhat worried about theposition in Germany, as well as about the Austriansituation, and. did not want the inclusion of a Czeeho-Slovak population in the German Reich.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said he had. made representations to the German Ambassadorabout  certain high officials of the former AustrianForeign Office who were reported to be in internmentgamps and euhjJeQtgd. to ill-treatment.   The AmbassadorM ?$pliM that Pietatorg also had their publioopinions to esnsiUert
THB PAR EAST.        3.    The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsChina and       said that he had heard from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassadorjapan.in Tokyo two days ago that the Japanese Government had(previous       no intention of invading South China.Reference-Cabinet 23 He warned the Cabinet of his intention to bring(38), Con-elusion 3.) before them next week certain large issues involved*Sl(5k)/.ln the Far EaSt*On the previous afternoon the Chinese Governmenthad decided to declare a moratorium on loans payablefrom June 30th.
IT4LY.4. The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsiInternal reported that he was about to circulate a Despatch fromSituation0r. Rome which showed that the bread, situation was very bad.Some time ago Signor Mussolini had. had. to decree a 20%(previous reference:    admixture in the bread.    The result had. been riots in cabinet 46(57), Con-   various towns.   Now the Duce had had. to rescind the elusion 2.)Order, - which was not the custom of Dictators.
AIR PROGRAMME.5.,  The Cabinet had before them the followingAir Mission tothe Unitedstates ofAmerica and canada.documents:-Creation of aWar Potentialor aircraft production inCanada.A Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Air (CoP,-14-3 (33)) on the subjectof the Air Mission to the United. Statesand. Canada, and the creation of a. war potential for Aircraft Production inCanada, in which he suggested, inter alia, the despatch of a Special mission to Canada for the purpose of negotiatingad referendum a considered scheme:(previous reference:Cabinet 26(38), Con-elusion 6.)The draft Conclusions of a Conferenceof Ministers (C,P.-148 (38)), who had met to consider the proposals containedin CoP^-143 (38)..    The recommendations made to the Cabinet in these draft conclusions are reproduced as an appendix to these Minutes *In the course of a discussion the Secretary ofState for dominion Affairs laid stress on the realpolitical value of these proposals.-    If the Canadianindustry could, be linked to the British Defence Pro-grammes in the manner suggestedy/further valuableresults might follow.   He urged that the Mission mustbe purely technical in character and must avoid touch-ing in any way on politics:    otherwise the PrimeMinister of Canada, who had. already adopted an attitudeof antagonism towards proposals for a Tre.ining Estab-lishment in GanadaH might easily turn against theproposal.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence thoughtthat the Canadian Minister of Defence was playing a somewhat lone hand in this matter in Canada.   He hadreceived a letter only that, day from the Ministerasking him to see  certain Canadian manufacturers.The Prime Minister, as Chs.chairman of the Conferenceof Ministers, asked the Cabinet to realise that thiswas not a proposal for an increase in the strength ofthe Royal Air Force, but for increasing its war potential.   Some time must elapse before the scheme
P o0 0could come into operation, and. it was  contemplated thatthe orders given should be the minimum to keep the war potential effective.    Tn these circumstances, if theAir industry in this  country were to oppose this planthey would, be in a weak position.   He admitted, thatrather a heavy price would have to be paid, to bring ttescheme to fruition.    The cost of the large bombers,machine for machine, would be from 25^ to &apos;SZ\% greaterthan at home, and there were likely to be a good, manydelays and. difficulties.    If the only object were to getaircraft quicker, the money could be spent more effectively.    &quot;Tie Conference of Ministers, however, hadtaken a wider view.   First, there was the insurancevalue of the scheme in the event of the prospectivedamage in time of war to our own factories.    It wouldbe o^ immense importance to have manufacturing i&apos;esourcesin operation beyond the range of enemy aircraft. another of these wider points wa.s that if Canada, could becomeinterested in the provision of aircraft to this  country the aloofness of thai Dominion from Imperial defence and its dissociation from the problems of the United.Kingdom might be reduced.    It was not inconceivable thatthe whole attitude of Canada towards the^Empire mightbe changed..   already.dy there had been some instances ofinterest in Imperial defence in the case of the Navy.Another point was the deterrent to our possible enemiesof this vague anr&quot; incalculable potential existing over-seas.    Those were the reasons for the recommendationof the Conference of Ministers, notwithstanding thedifficulties s.nd objections to the plan-Coming to detail, the Prime Minister pointed outthat there were two propositions.    The first  consistedin the setting up of a factory capable of producing-8-
very large bomber aircraft.   He wished to impress uponthe Cabinet that if they decided, to send a Mission,unless that Mission were to report that the propositionwas hopeless or there were to be a complete change inthe situation in Europe, the Government would be practic-ally committed to going on with the scheme.    mhe secondproposition contemplated, alliances between British and canadian firms for producing smaller aircraft.   he understood that the Secretary of State for Air did notattach quite the same importance to this proposal, whichwould have to be fully explored, by the proposed. Mission.By adopting this proposal the Cabinet would not be committed to carrying it through.The Chancellor of the Exchequer supported the PrimeMinister&apos;s statement, and, in addition, pointed out thatthe manufacture of very large bomber aircraft would, be avery difficult task for a small industry lacking experi-once.   Would it not be rather risky, he asked, to give theorder unless we were sure that it could be carried out?He asked whether the type of aeroplane was finally decided.The Secretary of State for Air said that he would be willing to re-examine the question of the type.    Thereason for the adoption of so large an aeroplane was that,it would have to be able to fly the Atlantic,    &quot;&quot;he effectof the scheme abroad, would, be largely weakened if smallermachines were adopted which had. to be transported, acrossthe Atlantic on board, ship.   The idea of the &quot;marriage&quot;of British and Canadian firms was to build up an aeroplaneindustry in Canada.   He admitted, that the Canadian indusrty was not in a position to build the engines for the largeaeroplanes, and that these would, have to be sent from england,    it was true (as suggested by the Lord President)-9-
that that would detract from the production in Canadaof aeroplanes which could fly the Atlantic-   mhe diffi-culty could be surmounted, however, even in time of war,by sending over a reserve of aeroplane engines fromthis  country.TheJPrime Minister suggested that the possibility should also be considered of/oending the large bombers/by sea and fitting the engines^/here, to save the doublejourney across the Atlantic.The Secretary of State ^or Foreign Affairsreinforced the Prime Minister&apos;s view as to the valuableeffect in foreign countries of this proposa.1.   He had.reason to believe that the Germans were already impress-ed by the order for 400 aeroplanes placed in the UnitedStates of America.    This new proposa.1 should increasethat effect.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that,  asmention had. been made of the Navy, he would, report thata. Canadian manufacturer had suggested, to the controller of the Admiralty that the Government of the United^ingriom should give an order for the construction ofa Destroyer in Canada, and had. expressed the view thatwhen it was  completed, the Canadian Government would want to buy it .   The Controller had suggested that itwould be a better plan if the Canadian Government wereto place the order and. to return to the Admiralty oneof the Destroyers that had been provided for them.He hoped the Cabinet would approve his giving every encouragement in this direction..The Secretary of State for Air said that the survey of war potential, which formed the subject, of Conclusion(5) of the Conference of Ministers, was now in hand.
He regarded the Canadian project as a long-range one,but he felt much concern with our lack of war potentialcompared with Germany,   He d.id not&apos; think that the peopleof this country woul^ accept a pos ition of great inferiorityin this respect o   He took the view thai finance ought not to become a limiting factor in this matter,^he Cabinet agreed.&quot;  (a) To approve the.recommendations of theConference of Ministers (AppendixJ&apos;(b) mo take note that the Secretary ofState for Air was willing to re-examine,in the light of the discussion, the type of very la.rge bomber that hadbeen selected for manufacture inCanada.-11-
3FENCE of)IA.Conversationsgetween the War[office and the india Office.((ire viousEeference:fgabinet 5 (38)Conclusion 11(b).)6.     The Prime Minister recalled that, arisingout of the discussions of the Cabinet on the role of the Army, he had authorised the initiation of conversations between the India Offf ,e and the WarOffice on certain questions relating to the defenceof India (see Conclusion referred to in the margin).The results of those conversations had now been communicated to him and raised issues of a general,political and financial character.     He thought thebest plan would be to refer it to a CabinetCommittee which would have technical advisers in attendance.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defencereminded the Cabinet that in the case of theCommittee of Imperial Defence or any of its Sub-Committees, technical advisers had a duty to express their opinion not only when it was asked for butalso&quot;to give it freely and spontaneously as membersof the Committee.     The Chiefs of Staff had alwaysmaintained that their position at a CabinetCommittee was not quite the same.The Prime Minister thought that the Chiefsof Staff were right and that there was a distinction ofthat kind.     He was quite prepared, however, to dispense with it on the occasion of the CabinetCommittee.Tap Secretary of State for War pointed outthat for this subject the Service Ministers might wish to bring particular experts and not necessarilytheir Chiefs of Staff.The Secretary of State for India said thathe would wish to be accompanied by technical experts.-
The Minister for Co-ordination of Defencesuggested the dispensation should apply to any expertspresent0The Cabinet agreed;(a) That a Cabinet Committee composed as follows the Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence (in the Chair)The Chancellor of the exchequer the Secretary of State for india the First Lord of the admiralty the Secretary of State for WarThe Secretary of State for AirWith such technical advisers as theymight deem necessaryshould consider and report on theresults of the conversations betweenthe War Office and the India office on the subject of the defence of India?(b) That for the purposes of this CabinetCommittee, the technical expertsattending the Committee should have thesame duty as have the Chiefs of Staffin the Service Departments at meetingsof the Committee of Imperial defence to express their opinions freelywhether asked for them or not.
7.   In pursuance of the Conclusion mentioned in the margin, the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer ( CP.-144 (38))covering a draft Bill to enable the Trustees of theBritish Museum to accept the bequest of the lateLord Rothschild of his museum and collections atTring.    The Chancellor stated in his Memorandum thatit was desirable th8t the Bill, which was suitablefor introduction in the House of Lords^ should beavailable as soon as possible in order that anysuitable opportunity of making progress with it mightbe taken.   As there was no Meeting of the Committeeof Home Affairs in the immediate future he asked thatthe Cabinet should authorise the introduction of theBill without reference to that Committee.The Chancellor of the Exchequer was askedto send a copy of the draft Bill in advance to the archbishop of Canterbury.The Cabinet agreed:To approve the proposals of theChancellor of the Exchequer as setforth in CP. 144 (38) and summarised above.
agricultural policy.The PoultryIndustry.(previous reference:Cabinet 44(37) , Con-conclusion ion 1 o)8. The Cabinet had before them a Joint Memorandum bythe Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and theSecretary of State for Scotland (C.P.-146 (38))statingthat the problems of the Poultry Industry had. now reached, a stage when it was urgently necessary to define the Governments policy towards them, and proposing that legislation should be introduced assoon as  convenient to provide for the following matters(l) The establishment of an independent PoultryCommission with powers -(a) to  control the distribution of breedingstock, hatching eggs, and day-old. chicks;(b) to regulate the marketing of eggs and.poultry by the standardisation ofgrading, packing, etc., up to the pointof final sale to the consumer;(c) to deal with matters of detail ancillaryto the above functions0(S) ^he quantitative regulation of imports ofegge (and other poultry products) where necessary  (a) to safeguard the home industry againstunstable market conditions resultingfrom excessive arrivals from overseas;(b) to safeguard, any operations that may beundertaken by the home industry, bystorage during the spring flush, with aview to modifying the extreme seasonalv8.proletariat.ions of supplies and prices .(3) Financial provision for -(a) a progeny-testing station, additionalresearch into problems of poultrymortality and additional educational and. advisory work amongst poultry-keepers ;(b) loans to assist egg packing 3ta.tionsset up by producers1  co-operative societies and grants to demonstrationpoultry packing stations.After setting out  estimates of cost, the authors ofthe Memorandum commended, the above proposals to their colleagues as the least that could, reasonably be proposed, to meet the industry s difficulties, andsought authority to make an early statement of theGovernment&apos;s policy ,
The Prime Minister thought that the two ministers were to be congratulated on a scheme which provided an inexpensive solution of   a    difficult problem.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, inreply to a question as to how and by whom the quantitative regulation of imports of eggs and otherpoultry produce(referred to in (2) above) was to becarried out, said that the idea was to put it in the handsof the Board of Trade.     The object c? this proposal wasto regulate the imports in cases where an abnormal supplywas received, for example, in an exceptionally warm winteras had occurred during the winter of 1936-37.The President of the Board of Trade said thatour Trade Treaties with various countries provided forthe regulation of   imports,, but only on the understanding thatthe regulation was applied here also     He was prepared,therefore, to regulate the importation of eggs in thecircumstances mentioned by the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries, but only on the condition that the proposedPoultry Commission not only had the powers to regulateeggs in this country but exercised them.      Otherwise wewould be acting contrary to the Treaty,The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriesmentioned certain precedents which led him to think thatthere was nothing in the proposal contrary to the Treaty.The President of the Board of Trade thought itwould be possible for the Poultry Commission to take action under the powers with which it was proposed toprovide it &quot;to regulate the marketing of eggs and poultryby the standardisation of grading, packing, etc., up tothe point of final sale to the consumer&quot;.     He againinsisted, however, that the Commission must exercise those
powers if the Board of Trade were to control importation.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriessuggested that two Ministers should discuss the point.TEhe Prime Minister agreed-.     He thought it essential that the Board of Trade should have the powerto regulate importation.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs asked that the Foreign Office should be consultedwhenever it was proposed to use th.0^.3 powers partly from the point of view of the trade position, but partlyalso from that of the political position at the time.Eggs came largely from countries which were subjected to german trade pressure and it was important for theForeign Office to know if their trade was affected.The Minister of Agriculture ant Fisheriesundertook that the Foreign Office should always be consulted.The Secretary of State for Scotland pointedout that this applied to all countries equally under our most favoured nation treatment Treaties0The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, inreply to a question,said that the proposals would notapply to people who kept chickens in a small way but onlyto those engaged in the industry,The Chancellor of the Exchequer said there wasone point in the proposals that he must reserve, namely,that the cost of the Poultry Commission was to be a c*hargeon the Exchequer without any provisions being made forrecovering the cost from the industry.     That wae apoint of principle with the Treasury,     They had alwaysinsisted in similar cases that the industry concerned should pay0     In the present case, the Commission was tobe an integral part of the Poultry Industry and could, in
no way, be described as a national necessity,,      The cost,therefore, ought to be borne by the industry.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries agreedto reserve the point, but explained that in an industry which included all sizes of concerns to very smallproducers, it would be administratively impossible toraise  the funds to pay the expenses of the Commission,,He thought it would be wise, therefore,  for theExchequer to make the payment0The Cabinet agreed;(a) To approve the proposals of theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheriesas set forth in CP, 146 (38) and summarised above:(b) To take note that the Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries would confer with the President of the Board ofTrade in order to complete thearrangements for the quantitative regulation of imports of eggs andother poultry products where necessary:(c) That the Ministry of Agriculture andFisheries should consult the ForeignOffice in all cases where the regulation of imports was deemeddesirable:(d) That the Foreign Office should notoverlook the bearing of any decision taken on countries with which wehave most-favoured nation Treaties:(e) To take note of the reservationentered by the Chancellor of theExchequer against the cost of thePoultry Commission being made a charge on the Exchequer.
9.    The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence (C.P.-145 (38))on the subject of the Defence of the Miri and SeriaOilfields,  circulating for the information of hiscolleagues an Extract from the Draft Minutes of the32?th Meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence(Minute 8), together with a Memorandum by the OverseaDefence Committee (CI.D. Paper No. 469-C).   TheConclusions reached by the Committee of ImperialDefence were as follows&quot;(a) To recommend the approval of theproposals of the Oversea. DefenceCommittee relating to the DenialScheme for the Miri and SeriaOilfields, as contained in 0.I.D,Paper No. 469-C:(b) That, in view of the fact thatthese involved the acceptance ofa contingent liability for com-pensation by the United. KingdomGovernment, the covering approvalof the Cabinet should be obtained.&quot;The Cabinet approved recommendation (a)of the Committee- of. Bxper-ial...Deiiencja. asset forth above.
LEAGUE of nations. ---1CouncilMeeting.(previous reference:Cabinet 24 (38)Conclusion 8)10o     The Cabinet took jaote-that-the-^-cj?e-hary ofState for Foreign Affairs, after consultation withthe Prime Minister, had arranged that the delegation to the forthcoming meeting of the Assembly of theLeague of Nations would be as follows:-Delegates.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Lord Privy Seal.Captain The Right Hon. Euan Wallace, M.P.,, Financial Secretary to the Treasury.Substitute Delegates.Mr. R.Ao Butler, M.p.Mr. R.H. Bernays, M0P.,Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministryof HealthoMiss Irene Ward, MoP.Sir William Malkin,Legal Adviser to the Foreign Office.
MfficialjpCRETS ACT.Reference:jfabinet 22 (38)Conclusion 13)PRIVILEGES OPifflfBERS OPffARLLAMEWT.previous reference: Cabinet 24 (34)^Conclusion 3)11*     The Prime Minister brought up as a matterof urgency a question that had come prominentlybefore Parliament in the last day or two regardingthe position of Members of Parliament under theOfficial Secrets Act.     The Prime Minister said that two points were involved -(1)   The elucidation of facts as to the actionof Mr. Sandys, MoP., and(2) The general question as to what was theposition of Members of Parliament underthe Official Secrets Act.Was a Member of Parliament entitled to go to anofficer in the Services and to obtain information from him on the ground that he occupied a position of privilege?     That would give Members of parliamentary strong lever against any Government and there wouldbe no safety for the secrets of the country ifMembers of parliament had such powers.     He himselfcould not subscribe to such an interpretation.Certain newspapers were taking rather a strong lineagainst the Government in this matter but he did notthink that the Government ought to be influenced bythat.     He recalled that the Leader of the labour opposition Party had suggested that in the discussion on the Motion on the following day, the Prime minister should make a statement as to what the attitude of theGovernment was with regard to the Official secrets act and Members of the House of Commons.      For thereason that the question was being referred to a select Committee,   he     would propose to say thatthe right time for the Government to express their view was after the Report of the Select Committee wasreceived.     He would be willing to add that if he were asked to give evidence before the Committee hewould be prepared to do so, although in that event it
would be personal evidence and not given on behalf of theGovernment.     He asked if the Cabinet were willing that heshould make a statement on those lines on behalf of theGovernment.In the course of a discussion which followed, theHome Secretary pointed out that in the Debate on thefollowing day one speaker after another was likely to demandspecial rights for Members of Parliaments     He was most anxious not to stir up a controversy on the Official secrets act.     The Press were already making difficulties and a debate was likely to increase them,     He hoped, therefore,that the Prime Minister would at the outset state theposition in such terms as to make clear that the question was sub judice and that some Back Bench supporter of theGovernment might state the position from the point of viewof the GovernmentoThe Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries thoughtthat the matter should be treated as a House of Commonsquestion.The Secretary of State for Air thought that this might result in very serious consequences0     He supported the view of the Home Secretary that the case in favour ofthe Governments point of view should be stated by a BackBencher.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence pointedout that it was notorious that information had been leakingto Members of Parliament in this matter for some time,particularly from the Air ForceoThe First Lord of the Admiralty recalled a pre-warcase which he was having investigated where the First Lordof the Admiralty (Mr. Churchill) had indignantly repudiatedinformation obtained from a member of the Service.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out the undesirability of this Debate, particularly as thequestion was to be referred to a Select Committee and asked what v/as the attitude of the Speaker of the Houseof CommonsoThe Prime Minister said that the Speaker ofthe House of Commons, while agreeing that the proprietiesrendered a Debate undesirable, was not prepared to stopit oThe Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed outthat all kinds of questions would be raised in the Debate.First, there was the question of the officer who had given the information to Mr, Sandys2    second, that cf the member of Parliament and whether he was justified inusing information given in this way?    third, whetherthe Government had been justified in pressing the Memberof Pa??liament to reveal the source of his information.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs suggested that the Prime Minister might put pressure onthe Speaker to change his view0The Prime Minister doubted whether this wouldbe su.Jessfulo     He pointed out that the line of theOpposition was likely to be that the Government had been guilty of ineptitude which had resulted in grave weaknessesand were now anxious to take refuge from the criticism of the House under the Official Secrets Act0     He thought the Home Secretary&apos;s plan was a good one,,The Home Secretary said the difficult point wasthe third of those mentioned by the Chancellor of the
Exchequer, namely, the interrogation of the Memberof Parliaments      It v/as difficult to defend but anessential point.     He promised to send the primeMinister a note on this point.The President of the Board of Trade thoughtthat the feeling in the House was going to be very strong in this Debate.    It. would be difficult tomaintain that Members of Parliament were to be puton the same footing as the general public in thismatter.      One suggestion he had heard was that ifMembers of Parliament were not to be dealt with underthe Official Secrets Act, the House of Commons itself should have powers to deal with any Member who abusedhis privilege0The Home Secretary thought that to get away from the Official Secrets Act would be a slipperyslope9     If Members of Parliament were exempt, thePress would insist on exemption and the Act would soon become a dead letter0The Chancellor of the Exchequer said theAct applied to Members of Parliament as much as to anyone else0      The question of privilege was rather a difficult one.     No one could forecast, however, whatview the House of Commons might takePThe prime Minister said it was not clear what privilege could be claimed by Members ofParliamento
The Secretary of State for War said, that if, as theprime Minister said, the proper time for the Government&apos;views to be expressed was after the inquiry, he ought not to speak in the Debate on the following day.The Prime Minister said he would s,ay in his speech that the Secretary of State for War would be willing to give evidence   before the Select Committee if they so desired, butas the question was sub judice, wo-gld not speak in the Debate.The Minister of Health said it was very difficult to forecast what course the Debate would take and suggested thatno hard and fast decisions ought to be taken.The Lord Chancellor said that the Cabinet should leavefull discretion to the House of Commons Members as to the line to be taken in the Debate.    (This was agreed to. )In the course of the discussion the Secretary of Statefor War mentioned a Private Notice Question which had been addressed to him by the Leader of the Labour opposition party as to the Court of Inquiry v/hich had been announced.He himself had not been present at the meeting of the ArmyCouncil at which the inquiry had been decided on.    he presumed that the proper answer was that this was purely amatter of military discipline.The Prime Minister pointed out that Members ofParliament might say that this was a matter sub judice tothe Select Committee.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the answer to the question was quite plain.    The discipline ofthe army required that persons who have broken certain
regulations must be subjected to a certain procedure. Thatdid not appear to touch the question of Mr.  Sandys or ofMembers of Parliament generally.The Secretary of State for War then gave detailsof the episode in which Mr.  Sandys had been concerned.After some further discussion, the Cabinet agreed(a) To approve the line which the Prime minister proposed,  as summarised above, namely -That in the Debate on the following day he should refuse to state the views ofthe Government on the grounds that thematter was to be referred to a SelectCommittee of the House of Commons.    Heshould further have discretion tointimate his own willingness to assistthe Committee by giving personal evidence.(b) To take note that the Home Secretary would send the Prime Minister a note on the Powerof Interrogation under Section VI of theOfficial Secrets Act,(c) That the Secretary of&apos;State for War shouldnot speak in the Debate on Thursday, 30thJune, for the reasons given above in (a).(d) That the Prime Minister and his cabinet colleagues in the House of Commons shouldbe given full discretion to vary the above decisions and to take the course that they considered best adapted to the circumstancesof the Debate.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.,29th June, 1938.
APPENDIX.AIR MISSION TO UNITED STATES AND CANADA.Conclusions of a Conference of ministers held in the Prime Minister&apos;s Room, Houseof Commons, S.W.1. , on Friday,  24th June,1938, at 3ol5 r^m.,(l)    That the Secretary of State for Air shouldhe authorised to send immediately aspecial Mission to Canada for the purposeof negotiating ad referendum a consideredscheme (afber close local investigationsand discussions with all parties concernedincluding financial and commercial interests whose hacking is essential tothe success of such a plan) for theproduction of large &quot;bomber aircraft on thegeneral lines indicated in (b), (c). (d),and (e) of paragraph 7 of CP.  143 (38),and subject to the conditions andqualifications set out in paragraph 8 ofthat Paper, and subject also to theMission&apos;s being able to secure reasonably satisfactory financial terms from theCanadian manufacturers-( 2)    That it must be recognised that it would be extremely difficult for His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom to refuse.seendorsement of a satisfactory scheme sonegotiated by the Mission unless inter-national problems changed appreciably inthe interval,     Accordingly it will be understood that if the Mission are ableto negotiate a scheme satisfactory in all respects, including the financial terms to be arranged v/ith the Canadianmanufacturers,  the Government will confirm that scheme in the absence in the interval of any appreciable alteration in theinternational situation.(3)    That the Mission should be authorised to explore v/ith the Canadian interests concerned the proposal in (a) of paragraph 7of CP,  143 (38) for the alliance of individual Canadian firms with UnitedKingdom firms, with a view to the productionunder licence in Canada of an allocatedportion of orders for specified types of aircraft (other than the large bomber classcovered by (l) and (2) above) placed by theAir Ministry with the United Kingdom firms.It being clearly understood that HisMajestyrs Government in the United kingdom are in no way committed in principle orotherwise at the present stage to theadoption of this part of the proposals ofthe Secretary of State for Air.
(4)    That the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs and the Secretary of State for air should he invited to settle in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer, theterms of a telegram to he sent to theCanadian Government in the event of theCabinet approving the recommendations setout in (1; , (S) and (3) above.(5)    To take note that the Secretary of Statefor Air has agreed to circulate to theCabinet in due course the results of a comprehensive survey now being undertaken by the Air Ministry of the whole positionrelating to war potential, for aircraft production from all sources.      Theinformation in question will summarise allthe different war potential schemes, andwill indicate in each case what each scheme will provide and how much it is estimated to cost.( 6)    To take note that the Secretary of State forAir has undertaken to furnish the Chancellorof the Exchequer as soon as he can possiblydo so with the supplementary estimate for thecurrent financial year in respect of theexpenditure in 1938-39 on the Air Ministry&apos;sapproved programme for the production of12,000 aircraft by March, 1940j   with theestimate for the expenditure on thisparticular service in the financial year1939-40, and with the estimate of the costof the service to be met after 1939-40.( 7)    To take note that in the view of the Chancellorof the Exchequer it was imperative thatnormal Treasury financial control and responsibility in regard to the numerousand growing activities of the Air ministry should be re-established without delay inorder that the relations between theTreasury and the Air Ministry in regard tothe financial control of the Treasury overexpenditure by the Air Ministry should be assimilated to the arrangements in force inregard to other spending Departments.

</content>
</cab>
