<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/133/0 images: 85-88</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
INDUCEMENT PAYMENTS FOR TEACHERS INCERTAIN SCOTTISH SCHOOLSM.e-G?memorandum by the Seeretary of State for ScotlandThere is an issue concerning incomes policy which I feel I mustbring before my colleagues now;  it relates to the introduction of a limitedscheme of inducement payments to teachers in schools in Scotland whichare seriously affected by a shortage of staff.    The matter has beenconsidered by the Ministerial Committee on Prices and Incomes, andI have the concurrence of the First Secretary., as Chairman of theCommittee, in taking it to Cabinet.2.     At their meeting on 3rd August, the Ministerial Committeeaccepted in principle my proposals for a scheme of inducement payments and agreed that there should be an immediate announcement of this, buttook the view that they should not be implemented except as part of thegeneral revision of Scottish teachers1 salaries due from April, 1968.The ground for this view is that the credibility of our prices and incomes policy would be called in question if we were seen to be offering specialadditional payments to certain teachers during the currency of the presentsalary settlement for Scottish teachers which is not due for revision until april, 1968,    I believe on theother hand that there are powerful arguments for my going ahead now and introducing the scheme from 1st October, 1967and that these outweigh any possible risk of damage to our incomes policy.3.     My proposals for a scheme of inducment payments are baped onthe recommendations of a Committee under the Chairmanship ofDame Jean Roberts set up in 1965 to consider means of bringing about amore equitable distribution of teachers in Scotland, where areas such asGlasgow., Lanarkshire and Renfrewshire are very badly affected by the teacher shortage.     The setting up of the Committee followed the failureof two attempts by the previous Government in 1963 to introduce aspecial allowance for teachers in certain parts of the greater Glasgowarea.4.      The Committeers central recommendation was that anadditional allowance of  100 per annum should be paid to teachers in schools designated as schools seriously affected by staffing shortage.This is the essence of the scheme I propose to adopt.      The designationof schools would be limited in such a way that not more than 4, 000teachers (10 per cent of the teaching force) would receive the additional allowance.     The cost, at  0. 4 million a year, is equal to rather lessthan 1 per cent of the total salary MIL     (The Roberts Committee also recommended payment of travelling allowances to teachers in designatedschools and this would increase the overall cost somewhat, but I am not proposing specific provision on travelling expenses at present. )-1-CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY rS GOVERNMENT)65CX67)J47 COPY NO.___5th September, 1967CABINET
50     In my view there are compelling reasons for introducing thescheme of inducement payments from 1st October, 1967 and not leaving the matter to be dealt with in the next general revision of Scottishteachers1 salaries.    These are, very briefly -(a) It is essential for me to take action to improve the distributionof teachers and to ease the situation in those schools whichare acutely affected by staffing shortage - and to be seen to be doing so now.    In March this year some 4,500 pupils were receiving only part-time education^    I am satisfied that my proposals will bring about a. substantial easement in theproblem areas.,(b) I am under the strongest criticism on our failure to take any action on the Roberts Report - in our hands since April, 1966and published in July, 1966.    My position has been made evenmore difficult by our acceptance of the arbitration award onteachers1 salaries in England and &quot;Wales.(c) Proposals have been advanced in the Burnham Committee for additional allowances for &quot;priority schools&quot; in England andWales as going some way towards meeting one of the PlowdenCouncilrs recommendations,    &quot;While these proposals arerather different from mine, essentially they are directed tothe same end0      Agreement may well be reached on them withinthe next month or two.    My position will be impossible ifaction on Plowden, published in January, 1967, overtakesaction on Roberts, published six months earlier.(d) We have declared our intention to see additional expenditure incurred on school premises in under-privileged areas.Many of the schools in these areas are very badly placed for staff, and in most cases an improvement in staffing isa more immediate priority than improvement of the buildingsthemselves.    A policy which concentrates on the buildings but does nothing for staffing can hardly expect to commend itselfto public opinion - least of all with the Roberts Report beforeus for well over a year and nothing whatever done on it.6.      There is a further practical point which I cannot ignore.     I shallhave to bring into being in the course of October the new salariesnegotiating machinery for which the Remuneration of Teachers (Scotland)Act provides.    With the new machinery in being I shall cease to hold the controlling position which I now have in matters of this kind.    If Igo ahead now, I can introduce the scheme of inducment payments at my own hand and in the form which is likely to be most effective.    If Idelay, in line with the view of the Ministerial Committee, then there isno assurance that any   scheme can be introduced since the whole matterwill be caught up in negotiations for the general revision of salaries,and any resultant scheme may be. more costly and less effective than Iwould like to see.-2-
7.      I do not underestimate the considerations of incomes policywhich led the Ministerial Committee to conclude that any scheme ofinducement payments should be proceeded with only as part of the revision of salaries from April, 1968.    I cannot think, however, thatsuch risk as there may be of damage to the prices and incomes policyoutweighs the considerations that I have mentioned in paragraphs 5 and above.    The issue is not just a marginal one of timing as betweenOctober, 1967 and April, 1968s  it affects our whole standing in relationto Scottish affairs,    I must therefore ask my colleagues to agree that Ishould go ahead with the scheme of inducment payments from 1st October.WAR.Scottish Office, S.W.1.4th September, 1967.-3-


</content>
</cab>
