<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/133/0 images: 256-258</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY TS GOVERNMENT)PUBLIC EXPENDITURE;  LONG-TERM FINANCIALASSISTANCE FOR OVERSEAS STUDENTSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer my colleagues will recall that following decisions taken inNovember, 1966 (CC(66) 5 8th Conclusions, Minute 4) inviting furtherconsideration of certain proposals for reducing public expenditure Iapproved increases in the fees of overseas students undertaking higherand further education courses in this country.2.   A number of short-term measures (including the setting up of ahardship fund) have been introduced to assist existing students.    Inaddition, Her Majestyrs Government is meeting the extra cost for both present a.nd future students financed from Exchequer funds.3o    The Committee on Overseas Development has discussed thepossibility of a longer-term scheme to help students not financed by her Majestyrs Government who will be embarking on courses of higherand further education here in the future.     The general view of theCommittee is that a scholarship scheme, estimated to cost  500,000a year when in full operation, should be instituted.4.    Treasury Ministers are not opposed in principle to such a schemealthough they cannot accept that it should be regarded as an interim arrangement with the possibility of future expansion,5.    However, it is proposed that the scheme should be financed bythe provision of additional funds outside the aid ceiling.     TreasuryMinisters are opposed to this (and reserved their position in the overseas Development Committee) on two grounds.6.    First, this is a form of aid.    Assistance to overseas studentsis a recognised and well-established part of the existing aid programme.If we wish to do more in this way, we have to do less in others.    the limitations we have to place on public expenditure programmes reqiiirethis process cf adjusting priorities and the future composition of the aid programme is not so rigidly predetermined as to rule out such an adjustment.7.    Second, we cannot afford a straightforward addition to the aid programme^    The current exercise on public expenditure has alreadyhighlighted the difficulty of keeping down expenditure in 197 0-71.COPY NO.20th October, 1967CABINET
8,    E agreement cannot be reached on the use of normal aid money analternative arrangement would be to transfer an appropriate sum fromthe education block to the aid block.    This would be on the basis thatthere would be no net increase in the total of the Votes and noencroachments on the estimated long-term saving of  5 million a year which was mentioned in the public announcement in December,19660   For the purposes of illustration this would involve, in the caseof the education block, a reduction of  5 00, 000 in the agreed public expenditure survey figure for 1970-71 after adjustments have beenmade to accommodate the extra cost of the open university,,recommendation ,    I invite my colleagues to agree with me that, if we proceed withthe proposed scholarship scheme -(a) The cost should be met from within the basic aid programme.(b) Failing that, the money should be found by an appropriate transfer from the education block to the aid programme,,J-io Jo CaTreasury Chambers, S.W.1,18th October, 1967-2-


</content>
</cab>
