<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/133/0 images: 263-355</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T IS THE PPvOPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTIES GOVERNMENT)C(67) 16.5 COPY NO,_23rd October, 1967CABINETFUEL PQUCY;  DRAFT WHITE PAPERIviemorandum by the Minister of power attach the draft of a White Paper on the Government1 s fuel policy.     This is designed to fulfil a twofold purpose.    First, it isintended to describe our fuel policy as a whole, which was recently approved by Ministers, following the intensive interdepartmentalexamination of the issues involved which has been conducted overthe last year or so,    Second, it is to be regarded as the prospectusfor the Coal Industry Bill which is to be introduced early in the new session.     This Bill will raise the National Coal Board?s borrowinglimit and will seek Parliamentary authority for the new measures of short-term assistance to the coal industry which are described inparagraphs 117 and 126 to 129 of the draft White Paper,     The 3oard&apos;present borrowing limit is expected to be reached by the end of thisyeara    The Bill will therefore need to be law by Christmas!  and, inorder to allow time for it to pass through all its stages, the Bill andthe White Paper will need to be published by about 13th November.2.      The draft White Paper has been revised in the light of discussion in the Steering Committee on Economic Policy.     The Committee sugges-ted that, having regard to the extent of our dependence on oil supplies from foreign sources, I should strengthen the point made in the draft white Paper that fuel policy would be kept under continuing review,    Ihave now given this point greater prominence in paragraph 6 of theintroductory chapter;  and I would also invite my colleagues to notewhat is said in the final paragraph of all (paragraph 136),3,      My colleagues also asked for the omission of references formerlyin paragraphs CO and 91 to the presumptive case, in the longer term, for reducing the level of the oil tax;  and for the rewording of the finalsentence of paragraph 101 to say only that, subject to the re-examinationof the security of oil supplies which is now in progress5 no greaterdiscrimination against oil should prove necessary.    These changes,which I have agreed with the Foreign Secretary, have now been made,together with consequential amendments in paragraph 93 and inParagraph 15 of Appendix lu4.      Explicit reference is now made in paragraph 81 to the critex-iawhich the nationalised industries should adopt in pricing and investmentpolicies, as set out in the forthcoming White Paper on the Economicand Financial Objectives of the Nationalised Industries,
5e      A new paragraph (paragraph 125) has been included to describe the proposed measures of assistance for areas worst hit by collieryclosures,,60 My colleagues suggested that a popular version of the white paper should be prepared, as was done when the National Plan was published.,    Arrangements for this are in hand07.      I invite rny colleagues to approve the draft White Paper for publication in the week commencing 13th November,R0 W, M0Ministry of Power, S.W01023rd October, 1967
MINISTRY OF POWERFuel policy presented to Parliament by the Minister of power by Command of Her Majesty1967Cmnd.london her MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICEnetDENTIA
MINISTRY OF POWERFuel policy presented to Parliament by the Minister of power by Command of Her Majesty      ,1967LONDONHER MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY office net
CONTENTSChapterParagraphs    page part IIntroduction ...1-part II: Recent Developments and the prospects for the 1970&apos;s2Natural Gas ...10-243    Electricity Nuclear Power and Power StationFuel Use.................. 25-364    Oil    ...      I..      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 37-535    Coal  ...      ..................- 54-706 The Objectives and Determinants of Policy      ... 71-857 Long-term Policy    ...      ...      .........       86-1108 Policy for the Transition   ............ 111-1319 Conclusion.................. 132-136AppendicesI    Statistical and Economic Analyses        ......II    Natural Gas ............      ...III Nuclear Power Costs       ..................IV Technical Developments in British Coal MiningTablesA    Trends of Primary Fuel Use       ...      ...      ...    -B    Primary Fuel Use in 1970 ....      ......      ...      ...      ...C    Inland Energy Demand (&quot; The January, 1967, estimates &quot;)D    Inland Energy Demand (&quot; The April, 1967, estimates &quot;)E    Pattern of Inland Demand in 1970 adjusted for ContingentSupport for Coal.....................F    Generating Costs of Nuclear and Conventional Power StationsG    Internal Rate of Return on Extra Investment in the second part III: The Co-ordination of PolicyNuclear Power Programme
List of ChartsChart1 Pattern of primary fuel consumption in the United Kingdom,1956 and 1966      ...     ..................2  Map: natural gas transmission system and principal gas fields ...3   Sales of electricity and gas in Great Britain, 1957-1966 ......4  Sales of electricity and gas by sectors, 1957-1966        ......5 Output capacity of public electricity supply industry in GreatBritain, 1966 and 1972    ..................6 Fuel used for the production of electricity in the United Kingdom,1957-1966  .........-...............7 Inland deliveries of oil for energy consumption in the UnitedKingdom by sectors, 1957-1966 ...............8 United Kingdom oil refinery capacity and output, inlanddeliveries, bunkers, imports and exports of refined products,1957-1966..................     ......9 Inland coal consumption by sectors and exports from the UnitedKingdom, 1957-1966      ..................10  Coal: manpower and productivity, 1957-1966   .........11   Coal production, consumption and undistributed stocks, 1957-1967 ... ...     ...     ...     ...     ...     ...12  Pattern of primary fuel consumption in the United Kingdom,1966 and 1975      .....................13  Primary fuel consumption in the United Kingdom, 1966, 1970and 1975    ................&apos;.........14  Energy demand by sectors, 1957, 1966 and 1975 .........15 Manpower and investment requirements of the energy sector,1966, 1970 and 1975       .........
FUEL POLICYPart I.  introduction. The discovery of natural gas in the North Sea is a major event in the evolution of Britain&apos;s energy supplies. It follows closely upon the comingof age of nuclear power as a potential major source of energy. Together,these two developments will lead to fundamental changes in the pattern of energy demand and supply in the coming years ; and it is the prospect ofthese changes that has caused the Government to re-examine fuel policy.A review was needed, not to re-examine the policy objectives set out in theWhite Paper of October, 1965, (Cmnd. 2798) which still stand, but to re-assess the balance between the available primary fuels (coal, oil, nuclear power and natural gas), and to set the framework for the most beneficial developmentof our energy supplies.2. Britain&apos;s primary fuel use is about 300 million tons of coal equivalenta year; by 1970 it may be about 310 million tons, and by 1975 about350 million tons. A decade ago coal supplied 85 per cent, of our primaryfuel, and oil most of the remainder. Today we are still basically a two-fuel economy but oil&apos;s share has grown to 37 per cent, of the total and coaTsshare has dropped to under 60 per cent.Chart 1Pattern of Primary Fuel Consumption in the United Kingdom1956COAL 84-9% IHYDRO-ELECTRICITY 0-5%01 L 14-6% jfl1966COAL 58-7%JCLEAR&amp; HYDRO-ELECTRICITY 3-4%C- OIL 37-5%. NATURAL GAS 0-4%There is no shortage of either coal or oil in the ground, but whereas for coal we need not look beyond our own borders, for oil we are at presentwholly dependent on foreign sources. This presents problems.3. The pattern of availability and supply is changing. The quantity of natural gas already found in the North Sea is sufficient to replace town gascompletely in the course of a few years and, at the right price, to bring abouta major expansion of the market for gas. Nuclear power has emerged from its early experimental stage into a proven and increasingly competitivesource of energy, with supplies of uranium and plutonium sufficiently assuredto place no limitation on its further expansion within the foreseeable future.Though the predominance of coal and oil as primary fuel sources will con-
tinue for many years to come, they will in the future be competing for themarket with nuclear power and natural gas. We are moving from a two-fuelto a four-fuel economy.4. The Government^ aim is to see that our growing energy requirements are supplied in the way which yields the greatest benefit to the country.Policy for the fuel sector must therefore have regard to economic and social policy in other fields. In particular, the Government must ensure, throughfuel policy, that national considerations which individual consumers do not take into account in choosing between competing fuels are given their dueweight among the factors determining the pattern of fuel supply and demand.Such national considerations include security of supply, the efficient use of resources, the balance of payments, and the economic, social and humanconsequences of changes in the supply pattern.5. In the fuel industries, as in other large modern industries, it is necessaryto plan the provision of resources in plant, men and management years before there is any certain knowledge of what the conditions of supply and demand will be. These decisions concern not only the fuel industries them-selves but also the Government, because of the important role that the fuelsector plays in the economy as a whole. More particularly, the Ministerof Power (in the case of electricity in Scotland, the Secretary of State) hasstatutory responsibilities for the development plans of the nationalised fuelindustries, whose annual capital investment is of the order of  1,000 million.By the nature of this investment, the decisions which must be taken in thenext year or two will affect the energy pattern for many years ahead ; forexample, a new power station takes five or six years to build and may havea working life of thirty years or more. Forecasting based on economicanalysis is, therefore, central to fuel policy, and for this review the Govern-ment have sought to establish the best possible quantitative basis. Theyhave had to look not merely at the prospects for the next three or four years,but a decade or so beyond.6. The fuel industries are undergoing rapid technological and economicchanges, the results of which cannot at present be definitely assessed. Theeffect of external factors on the security of our supplies of imported fuelhas also to be taken into account. The Government^ aim has been to lay down long-term policy guidelines which can be modified and adjustedin response to new developments and to provide a coherent framework withinwhich specific decisions can be taken as the need for them arises. within this context, future decisions need to be based on up-to-date information ;there will be periodical revision of the relevant economic analyses and estimates in the light of changing circumstances; and the Government willkeep policy under continuing review. Thus, if present forecasts provewrong as in some respects they certainly will there is scope for adjustmentfrom year to year.7. It is the prospective balance between the primary fuels which is mostaffected by the major developments in the energy sector. They have direct and important implications for the present secondary fuel industries elec-tricity and gas-which are covered in this White Paper. But a number ofother aspects of fuel policy mainly affecting the secondary fuel industries arebeing studied separately.
8. The White Paper is thus mainly concerned with policy for the primaryfuels. Part II describes recent developments and assesses prospects for eachof the four primary fuels in turn. Part III draws together and analyses these developments and sets out the Governments policy.9. Throughout the review, the Minister of Power has been greatly assisted by the co-operation and advice of the managements of the fuel industries the oil companies as well as the nationalised industries. In addition, theMinister has consulted his Energy Advisory Council, on which trade unions and industry generally are represented as well as the fuel industries.
Part II.  RECENT DEVELOPMENTS AND THE prospects for THE 1970&apos;s2.  Natural GasThe Present Town Gas Industry10. We possess a well-developed town gas industry which is alreadyexpanding fast under the impetus of major technological change in methodsof gas production and improvement in gas appliances. Sales are increasingat a rate of nearly 10 per cent, a year and are expected to exceed 4,000million therms this year. In recent years the traditional methods of makinggas from coal have been rapidly superseded by oil-reforming processes and, by this year, planned gas production was about two-thirds from oil and only one-third from coal. This change was accepted by the Governmenton account of its important savings in cost.11. Under the Continental Shelf Act, 1964, North Sea gas has to be offered to the gas industry if it is to be supplied for use as a fuel, so thatthe Gas Council and Area Gas Boards have the task of bringing this newprimary fuel into use. Coming at a time of rapid expansion and technolo-psychological  change in the industry, it brings the prospect of even faster growth and change.Discovery of North Sea Gas12. Drilling for oil and gas in the United Kingdom sector of the north sea began on 26th December, 1964, with a well on the Dogger Bank, andthe progress since then has been impressive. Gas was first found by theBritish Petroleum Company Ltd. (B.P.) 45 miles east of the Humber inthe autumn of 1965 and supplies from this find began to flow into thenatural gas pipeline system in July, 1967. Four important gas fields havenow been discovered (see map overleaf) in some of the fields it may be that two or more separate gas reservoirs will be identifiable:  Field                      Groups LocationWest Sole      ...  B.P..........45 miles east of the HumberLeman Bank ...  Shell/Esso, and Gas        30 miles north-east of theCouncil/Amoco     Norfolk coastIndefatigable ...   Gas Council/Amoco and   55 miles north-east of the shell/Esso Norfolk coastHewett......   Arpet and Phillips     ...   15 miles north-east of the norfolk coastGas has been found in other places but it remains to be seen whether these other discoveries are commercially exploitable. The search continues; up tothe end of September, 1967, 54 exploration wells had been completed or werebeing drilled by 15 different licensees.* Paragraph 77 of Cmnd. 2798.
Chart 2Natural Gas Transmission System and Principal Gas Fields
13. It is not possible yet to make precise estimates of the gas reserves,but the recoverable reserves in the fields already discovered are roughlyput at 25 x1012 cubic feet. This is enough to build up to a production rateof some 3,000 million cubic feet a day (m.c.f.d.) within five or six years andto continue at that level for perhaps fifteen years, thereafter gradually declin-ing if no more gas is found. 3,000 m.c.f.d. is equivalent to about 11,000million therms a year, nearly three times our present consumption of towngas. Experience in other parts of the world suggests that it would be mostunusual if more gas were not found. The rate of discovery in the UnitedKingdom part of the North Sea so far has been very fast. For example,it was not until eleven years after the discovery of the first natural gasdeposits in Holland in 1948 that the field at Groningen was found. A yearlater the reserves were officially estimated at 2-1 x1012 cubic feet. Only thisyear the official estimate of proved reserves there was increased from 39 x1012cubic feet to 58X1012 cubic feet. Though there can be no certainty as yet,it is a reasonable assumption for planning purposes that production fromthe United Kingdom part of the North Sea could reach 4,000 m.c.f.d. in1975.14. The Governments immediate objective has been that North Sea gasshould be brought rapidly into use to enable the country to benefit as soonas possible from the advantages of this new indigenous primary fuel. Speedyuse of the gas will also be an incentive to the exploration needed to extendour information about the size of the North Sea reserves. Planning and engineering work is going forward rapidly. But, particularly for the longer term, much more needs to be known before it will be possible to establishprecisely the role to be played by natural gas in our energy supplies. Itwill take time to assess the ultimate reserves ; the purchase price is still under negotiation between the Gas Council and the producers the Govern-ment&apos;s view is that it should be fixed as low as possible consistent withencouraging exploration ; and the scale and nature of the markets for gas in-inevitably depend to a large degree on the selling price. These are all keyfactors in the balancing of supply and demand for the gas, and because ofthe uncertainty about them the longer-term strategy for absorption must allowsufficient flexibility to accommodate fresh knowledge as it builds up.Considerable attention has already been given to the question of whatabsorption policy will bring the greatest benefit to the economy, thoughmuch of the analysis cannot yet be completed and only provisional conclu-sions can be reached. The following paragraphs outline the salient factors and estimates relevant to gas absorption as they are seen at present andindicate more precisely the nature of the problems to be resolved.Natural Gas and the Town Gas System15. Natural gas can be used to produce town gas, either by using it in place of oil products to enrich the lower calorific-value gas produced in the oil-reforming process or, with some modification of the reforming plant, as areforming feedstocks The natural gas imported from Algeria (about 100m.c.f.d.) and the first supplies of North Sea gas have been used in both those ways.   But in those overseas countries where natural gas is used* Natural gas has to be reformed in order to produce town gas because its calorific value(about 1,000 British Thermal Units per cubic foot) is about double that of town gas.
extensively,* it is not normally reformed into town gas but supplied direct to consumers, f In Great Britain the capital cost of converting the appliancesof all the thirteen million gas consumers, over a period of ten years, will beabout  400 million, equivalent to a present valuej in 1968-69 of nearly 300 million. But conversion will make it unnecessary to build new gas-making plant to meet increases in demand and to replace existing plant;and with the higher calorific value of natural gas it will bring effective(increases in the capacity of mains and storage. The present value of thecost of the new plant which would be required if the system were not con-verted, together with the running costs of reforming the natural gas, would be over  600 million. Thus conversion will reduce costs (at present value) by atleast  300 million over the ten year period it will take ; and with the cheapersupply system the cost advantages will continue. The Gas Council have estimated that, over thirty years, the present value of the difference (includingsavings from increased capacity) could be of the order of  1,400 million.The industry is, therefore, planning a phased programme of conversion ofthe town gas system to direct natural gas supply. About half the total cost of conversion will fall in the first five years.16. Natural gas, produced and delivered on shore through sea-pipes bythe producing companies, must be carried to the distribution networks. the gas Council plan to supply natural gas to all Area Boards by 1970, andwill provide a national gas transmission system for this purpose. The gridalready built to carry Algerian natural gas will be absorbed into the nationalsystem and another 1,300 miles of pipe will be purchased and laid. The first of the new pipelines, from Easington in Yorkshire, where gas comes ashorefrom B.P.&apos;s West Sole field, is already transmitting gas and the construc-tion of a second line, to connect the shore terminal at Bacton in Norfolk tothe existing natural gas pipeline, is in progress. Over the next five years,total expenditure on transmission and distribution will be close on  800million.The Market for Natural Gas17. Sales of town gas last year were equivalent to about 1,000 m.c.f.d.of natural gas. In the traditional gas industry markets where gas, because itis clean and easy to control and needs no storage, can command a premiumover an equivalent amount of heat from coal or oil, natural gas will takeover. In its absence, gas users would want a continued supply of town gasmade from other materials. This premium market is now made up of roughly13 million domestic and commercial users, and about 80,000 industrial users.Sales to domestic users have grown by more than 12 per cent, a year on average in recent years, and they can be expected to continue to grow fast.Secondly, there are other markets, especially in industry, for uses in whichtown gas is not competitive, but where natural gas would command somepremium over coal or oil, though less than for the first category. In theseuses the alternative fuel to natural gas would normally be one of the light or* See the Annex to Appendix II.f Appliances designed for town gas have to be converted before they can use natural gas.$ &quot; Present value &quot; is a concept used for comparing flows of money arising over differentperiods of time, using a rate of interest to discount future values to their present equivalent.In these calculations and others throughout the White Paper the rate of interest used was per cent, unless otherwise stated.
middle oil distillates though coal has not yet been displaced entirely. Finallythere are the uses (including much of the bulk industrial market) where,apart from any saving in handling and storage, natural gas may have little or no special advantage over fuel oil or coal and the price per therm is themain consideration.18. Apart from fuel use, natural gas could be important to the chemical industry as a feedstock or raw material, mainly for the production of ammonia and methanol.Balancing Supply and Demand19. In looking at the prospects for natural gas, the Government are naturally concerned not only with the price advantage which gas may have over other fuels but also with the savings in real resources which are likelyto be made when natural gas is used instead of another fuel. The Govern-menfs studies* have suggested that the saving in resources from introducingnatural gas is likely to be highest where it commands the greatest pricepremium. Hence resource savings are in general likely to be highest wherenatural gas is replacing manufactured gas, intermediate where it commandsa moderate premium in price over oil, and lowest in the bulk industrialmarket. This is a conclusion of major significance in the development of arational strategy for gas absorption. However, the price to the gas industrydepends on the economics of natural gas production which favour a rapidbuild-up in supplies and a depletion period which is not too long. to confine suplies of the gas to premium markets means both a slower build-up and a longer depletion period, and the price to the gas industry is likely tobe higher. In order to build up supplies quickly to the chosen depletionrate some gas would have to go to the bulk industrial market where, as stated above, the resource savings are likely to be lower. To some extent,therefore, these considerations pull in opposite directions.^20. Costs, and therefore prices and the development of markets, will alsobe affected by the load factor of the supplies. Supply considerations bothproduction and distribution favour a high load factor so that the gas wellsand other facilities that have to be provided to give sufficient capacity to meetthe maximum demand shall be more fully utilised. The additional production costs involved in a lower load factor are likely to be reflected in the pricepaid for the gas, which will probably vary according to load factor. The gas industry&apos;s present &quot; system load factor &quot;f is about 60 per cent, and has beendeclining. Although virtually all types of gas sales, whether domestic,commercial or industrial, have variable load factors, it is the space heatingload, the fastest growing part of the domestic market, which accounts for alarge part of winter peak demand. Of all town gas sales about 60 per cent,go at present to domestic consumers, about 25 per cent, to industry and theremaining 15 per cent, to commercial uses. Industrial consumers normallytake gas at more constant rates throughout the year, and an increase in theproportion of industrial sales could raise the average load factor of the system.In a number of other countries some large industrial consumers, particularlypower stations, are supplied on an interruptible basis and switch to other* For a fuller exposition of the analysis, see Appendix II.t The average weekly gas available during the year expressed as a percentage of the availability in the peak week nearest the end of the year or early in the following year.
fuels when demand for gas from other consumers increases. Such specialcontracts may provide for gas being used only during the summer months,so reducing the seasonal swing in demand ; or they may provide that thesupply may be cut off at short notice at any time when the peak load on thesystem requires supplies to be diverted to other consumers. The possibilityof using such contracts depends, however, upon large quantities of gasbeing available at prices which would be sufficiently attractive to industrialconsumers to enable them to accept the disadvantages of an interruptiblesupply. A preliminary study of possible seasonal use of gas at power stationshas been carried out by the Gas Council and the Central Electricity general-ing Board, and a trial conversion of one boiler at Hams Hall power station isbeing made. This station, which is coal-fired, was chosen because of itsproximity to the existing natural gas transmission line ; its selection impliesno decision that natural gas used at power stations would necessarily displacecoal.21. Supply and demand can also be balanced by meeting peak demandswith gas that has been put into storage when demand is low. The gas industry has always used gas holders to help meet short term variations in demand, but newer methods of storing natural gas in underground strataand in liquefied form enable much larger quantities to be stored. Experienceabroad has shown that both these forms of storage are practicable andeconomic. The Gas Council are investigating possible sites for undergroundstorage and are constructing at Canvey Island four frozen ground storagesfor liquefied natural gas, which may be supplemented by further units at other points on the pipeline system. Standby plant too can provide addi-tional supplies of gas to meet peak demands and it may be economic to convert some of the present oil-based plant to manufacture gas interchange-able with natural gas. These various methods are not necessarily alternativesand can all be used in combination.22. The rate of absorption of gas, the rate of depletion of gas fields, therate of build-up and the load factor at which supplies can be accepted are all closely linked with the price at which natural gas can be purchased bythe gas industry. The rate at which the gas can be absorbed will depend toa large extent on the price at which it is made available ; a low price wouldmake it possible to increase the speed of absorption and hence allow more rapid depletion of the fields. Conversely, higher prices would tend to be associated with a slower build-up and longer depletion periods. Again,the optimum method of load balancing will turn to some extent on the degree to which the purchase price varies with load factor. If the average pricepaid for supplies taken at a high load factor is substantially less than for supplies at a lower load factor this might make it economic to developseasonal and interruptible business which would not be worth while if the differential were smaller.23. To bring the gas into use and to convert appliances, very substantialamounts of capital will be needed, approaching  300 million a year over thenext five years, and the capital charges on this new investment have to bemet. For most consumers, it is likely to be some time before the full costadvantages of natural gas are reflected in prices. In some cases where bulksupplies can be made with relatively little new investment, particularly forloads in summer only, it should be possible to reflect the savings earlier.
One important point of principle that will affect prices to consumers hasalready been established that is that the Gas Council, who will buy natural gas from the producers, will sell it to the Area Boards on the basis of a uniform tariff, subject to variations for the load factor. Prices to consumerswill, however, continue to reflect differences in the Area Boards&apos; distribution and other costs.24. We are only at the start of the development of the North Sea gasfields and the uncertainties are too great for it yet to be possible to settle the long-term strategy on gas absorption. But we know already that the reserves are very substantial and this is the reason for the Government^decision to authorise construction of a nation-wide transmission system whichwill enable natural gas to be introduced rapidly and supplied to all partsof the country by 1970. The cost of this system and of the conversion of consumers&apos; appliances will be considerable, but so will benefits to the economy in terms of foreign exchange savings and lower energy costs.
Chart 3Sales of Electricity and Gas in Great Britain
Chart 4Sales of Electricity and Gas by Sectors
3.  Electricity Nuclear Power and Power Station Fuel UseDemand25. Electricity is essential for some uses but in the rest of its market itcompetes with other fuels. The competition will grow more intense withthe coming of natural gas. Between 1953 and 1963 the rate of increasein electricity sales averaged 9-2 per cent, a year but it has since slackened off to an average of 5-4 per cent, a year. Last year, with the check to industrial activity, the increase over the previous year was only 3-9 per cent. Forthe years ahead up to 1975 the average rate of increase is likely to be rather higher than in the last year or two, though well below the average growth rate for 1953-1963.26. The industry must provide sufficient capacity to meet the maximumdemand of all consumers at any one time ; and to cope with plant out ofservice, errors in forecasting, and abnormally bad weather, the Governmentauthorise capital expenditure by the generating Boards to provide a margin of generating plant of about 17 per cent, above the maximum demandexpected in average cold weather. To provide the generating plant andother equipment required to meet the growth of load, heavy capital expendi-ture is necessary ; in recent years the industry&apos;s total capital expenditure hasaveraged  480 million on generation and transmission and  200 million ondistribution. The industry&apos;s plans are based on the maximum demand inGreat Britain reaching 61,000 megawatts (MW) by 1972-73, compared witha maximum demand of 39,991 MW to date. A total of 35,000 MW of plantis under construction ; of this 25,000 MW will be coal-fired, 6,000 MW oiland dual-fired (i.e., coal or oil), and 4,000 MW nuclear.The Generating Programme27. The pattern of fuel use by the industry can change only slowly as new plant is introduced and, because it takes five years or more to build andcommission a new unit of generating plant, the pattern is already largelyfixed as far ahead as the 1970&apos;s. The only means of affecting it sub-stantially during the next few years would be by giving one fuel specialpreference over others by adjustment of the operation of the power stations(coal has had special preference of this kind over oil since 1965) or byconverting conventional stations from one fuel to another.28. Most of the 25,000 MW of coal-fired generating plant now under construction, almost all of which was committed before 1965, is sited onthe East Midlands and Yorkshire low-cost coalfields so as to reduce thedelivered cost of coal to the minimum. The bulk of the plant was planned in conjunction with a large north-to-south transmission capacity throughthe 400 kilovolt grid, and when the new stations now building are com-missioned there will be sufficient generating capacity in the Midlands andSouth Yorkshire to load the transmission capacity fully. Further concentra-tion of generating plant in this part of the country would require additionaltransmission which, in addition to its cost, would raise questions of amenity.This need would be avoided by siting future power stations in the generalarea of the demand they are to meet.
Output capacity of Public Electricity Supply Industry inGreat Britain
29. The 6,000 MW of new oil-fired and dual-fired plant is being built atsites close to oil refineries. The cost of generation at these stations, with oiltax at the current rate of 2-2d. a gallon, is expected to be below that ofcontemporary coal-fired stations. Policy in the last few years has been to limit new oil-fired stations to sites where they show exceptional cost advantage and not to allow the conversion of coal-fired stations to oil unless there were very special reasons, such as to stop serious air pollution.30. The first nuclear power programme has given the electricity supplyand plant manufacturing industries valuable practical experience in design-ing, building and operating nuclear power stations. All but two of the stations in the programme are completed ; their total capacity of 3,300 MWrepresents two-thirds of the programmed total of some 5,000 MW due for completion by 1969. All these stations are of the Magnox type, which hasbeen thoroughly proved by operational experience, and reactors commis-sioned so far have shown a high reliability. The earlier stations in theprogramme have not been competitive with contemporary conventionalstations, but there has been a steady fall in construction costs from  185per kilowatt for Berkeley, one of the two stations commissioned in 1962,to an estimated cost of  108 per kilowatt for Wylfa, which is due to commission in 1969. The thermal efficiency of Wylfa is expected to be31+ per cent compared with 25 per cent for Berkeley. As a result of these advances the later stations in the programme will be competitive with con-temporary coal-fired stations for the supply of base load electricity in the parts of the country where they are situated, away from the coalfields.31. Under the second nuclear power programme, tenders were received in 1965 by the Central Electricity Generating Board for a power stationto be built at Dungeness (Dungeness &quot; B &quot;) using the Advanced Gas CooledReactor (AGR), which suggested that stations of this type would generateelectricity more cheaply than even the most favourably-sited contemporarycoal-fired stations. The Government decided that, for planning purposes,it should be assumed that on average about one nuclear power station ayear would be commissioned from 1970 to 1975, giving a $otal for the secondnuclear programme of about 8,000 MW by 1975. The programme was intended to be flexible and was framed in the context of electricity demandforecasts for the period which were higher than the present ones.Comparison between Conventional and Nuclear Stations32. Since 1965, the Central Electricity Generating Board and the Southof Scotland Electricity Board have received tenders for AGR stations atHinkley Point and Hunterston which confirm the downward trend of nuclearcosts ; and there has also been a very considerable increase in the rate ofordering of nuclear power stations in the United States. Accordingly, afresh and detailed examination of the economics of the second nuclear power programme and of nuclear costs in the longer term has been under-taken ; the detailed results are given in Appendix III. The examinationbroadly confirms the prospects held out in 1965. Total generating costs at each of the first two AGR stations are expected to be lower than theestimated costs* both for Drax (near the Yorkshire coalfield), the latest* At coal and oil prices ruling in May, 1967.
coal-fired station being built, and for the oil-fired station under constructionat Pembroke. Further considerable reductions in nuclear costs are confi-dently expected for the period after 1975 from further developments in theAGR system. There is also the fast reactor which will be able to use forfuel the plutonium and spent uranium from the thermal reactors of the first and second programmes. Following extensive and successful operation ofthe experimental fast reactor at power outputs of up to 14 MW, a fastreactor on a commercial scale (250 MW) is being built by the Atomic energy authority at Dounreay and is expected to be completed in the early 1970&apos;s.Assuming progress is maintained, it should be practicable to incorporate largefast reactors in the nuclear power programme for stations to be commis-sioned towards the end of the 1970&apos;s.33. The choice between nuclear and conventional generation rests mainly on estimates of the advance of nuclear technology on the one hand andof the future movements in the cost of conventional fuels on the other. Nocommercial scale AGR is yet completed and operating, and in a youngtechnology the risk of disappointment must exist. On the other handexperience with the Magnox stations has been reassuring; indeed the laterones may well do better than forecast. Ample design margins are includedin the AGR stations now being built or committed, and the scope for development in later stations should be considerable. The construction costs of AGR stations commissioned in the later 1970&apos;s are expected to be littlegreater than those of conventional stations. The possibility of reducingnuclear construction costs more rapidly is being intensively studied.34. Conventional stations have much higher fuel costs than nuclearstations: operating on base load, the relative proportion of fuel costs to total generating costs is two-thirds at conventional stations and only one-fifth at nuclear stations. There are uncertainties about the future trend of fuel prices ; the influences bearing on these are examined in&apos;other sections ofthis White Paper. Moreover, apart from straight comparisons of costs ofgeneration, other considerations must be taken into account by the industryin assessing the merits of adding one type of station rather than anotherto the system. Nuclear power stations cause no air pollution. They canbe sited near areas of consumption without affecting the cost of generation,and so there is less need for additional high voltage transmission lines. a regular sequence of new nuclear stations is desirable if the full develop-ment potential of this new technology is to be realised.Generation from Natural Gas35. Natural gas can be used for electricity generation and a particularpossibility is its use in the summer only. In this way, supplies to power stations would take up some of the summer &quot; valley &quot; in the gas load curvecaused by the very seasonal demand for gas for heating purposes (though this, of course, has implications for the load factor of the supply of otherfuels for electricity generation). Obviously such schemes are likely to show the greatest advantage at power stations where a pipeline runs nearby. no decisions are possible at this stage but, as mentioned in paragraph 20, a smallpilot-scale conversion of one boiler is being undertaken at Hams Hall power station to gain cost and operating experience as a guide to policy.
Future Fuelling Plans36. The electricity industry takes over 30 per cent, of all primary fuelused ; decisions about power station fuelling are thus of special importance for fuel policy. Chart 6 opposite shows the industry&apos;s use of primary fuelsover the past decade. The coal-fired stations now in operation or under construction mean that large quantities of coal will continue to be neededthroughout the 1970&apos;s and beyond. But with three main primary fuels, coal,oil and nuclear (together with some hydro-power mainly in Scotland), andthe prospect of adding natural gas, the aim of the industry is to achieve amore balanced pattern of generation ; in this way the Boards seek to minimisetheir costs and to safeguard the system by spreading their risks between thedifferent fuels and different technologies available. With the relative costfigures quoted in Appendix III, and the present preponderance of conventionalstations, nuclear stations will predominate in new capacity planned for thecoming years but there will continue to be scope for some new conventionalstations at specially favourable sites.
Fuel used for the Production of Electricity in the United Kingdom(Primary Fuel Input Basis)
4. OilDemand37. Oil at present provides about 37 per cent, of Britain&apos;s total energyrequirements, as against some 15 per cent, ten years ago. The average annualgrowth rate for oil supplies over this period was 11  per cent., but in themost recent three years it dropped to 9\ per cent, a year. Chart 7 shows the growth of sales in the more important sectors of consumption. Between1955 and 1960 growth in oil use was dominated by expansion in fuel oil which rose from around a quarter of the total to nearly a half. Since 1960fuel oil use has continued to rise but its proportion of the total has stabilised.Between 1960 and 1966 the most striking growth in oil use was of naphtha forthe gas and chemical industries. The use of motor spirit has risencontinuously.38. In the future the rate of growth in fuel oil and other heavy oils isexpected to slacken as a result of competition from other fuels, notablynatural gas and nuclear power. Naphtha used by the gas industry will bethe first product to be displaced by natural gas, and natural gas may alsodisplace naphtha for the manufacture of some chemicals ; as a result theproportion of total oil use represented by naphtha is unlikely to continue itsrise in the longer term. Natural gas may also displace other oil products from the premium and bulk industrial markets.39. Oil has no substitute for some purposes particularly for road and air transport and it is noteworthy that such uses, together with refinery fuel,currently make up about 40 per cent, of the total demand. In the sectorscompetitive with other fuels, oil has gained its markets mainly at the expenseof coal, through its convenience and cheapness, despite the tax of 2d. a gallon (now 2-2d. a gallon or approximately  2-2 a ton) imposed in 1961.Over the last ten years there has been a substantial decline, in real terms, inthe pre-tax price of fuel oil in the United Kingdom, largely as a result of economies made by the companies in their downstream operations.40. In the course of the present review, the Government have re-examined the likely development of home refining capacity, the availability of thevarious oil products, the adequacy and security of oil supplies, the balance ofpayments implications, and the future competitive position of oil.Home Oil Policy41. Successive Governments since the War have pursued a policy of encouraging home refining largely for balance of payments reasons so thatthe cost of refining is incurred within this country instead of abroad. Thispolicy also stimulates secondary and associated industries such as petro-chemicals, adds to security because it is easier to switch sources of crude oil than sources of products, and gives rise to substantial inflows of foreign capital for refinery construction. It also enables advantage to be taken of theincrease in the size of tankers, which for crude oil are much larger thantankers built to carry products.42. There will always be trade in oil products between countries as wellas between companies, in order to balance the requirements of markets withthe output of particular products from refineries and the yields of different
Inland deliveries of Oil for Energy Consumption in theUnited Kingdom by Sectors
crude oils ; this exchange produces a more economic supply pattern than could be achieved by complete self-sufficiency. The Governments objectivehas therefore been that home refining should suffice to cover inland demand and bunkers in total, with marginal product imports balanced by exports ;it was expected that the proceeds of the product exports would generally bemore than sufficient to cover the cost of imports. Owing to commissioningdelays and other difficulties with new refinery capacity, progress towardsachieving this objective has been slower than had been hoped (see Chart 8opposite). As a result, net product imports in 1966 were little lower than in1965, the peak year since the immediate post-war period. However, firmplans known to the Government should take refinery capacity in 1970 to atleast an annual rate of 110 million tons (about 102 million tons of output),sufficient to allow of some net exports.43. The Government encourage companies to build refineries either alone or in combination with others as soon as their share of the United kingdom market and their prospects for exports justify it. The development of furtherplans will depend on the companies&apos; assessment of the market prospects foroil both in total and by sector, but even on the present plans the capacity for net exports of products should be maintained well beyond 1970. Refiner-ies now under construction or planned (other than those of a specialist nature)range in size from 3 to 6 million tons annual capacity and are large enoughto take advantage of the important economies of scale in refinery construction and operation.44. One of the new refineries now under construction is designed toproduce electro-grade petroleum coke for the first time in the United King-dom, with significant import saving and export potential. The UnitedKingdom oil industry already supplies its products for use other than as afuel to important and technologically progressive industries, notably thepetrochemicals industry with its own very wide variety of products. Thusoil is an integral part of many aspects of modern life and is used, forexample, to make the synthetic fibres used in textiles, most types of plastics,detergents, paints, synthetic rubbers, pesticides, weedkillers and&apos; fertilisers ;and for lubricants and road making (with bitumen). The oil industry spendsheavily on research into the various possible uses for oil products, and hassubstantial investment in industries such as petrochemicals. The value of oil to the economy, therefore, goes far beyond its use as a fuel, importantthough that is.45. In the future, the demand for oil is not expected to grow at thesame rate as in the recent past. Moreover, changes are expected in themarket pattern and in the pattern of products imported and exported.Fuel oil, motor spirit and naphtha for the gas and chemical industries are the main imported products at present and middle distillates are our main net exports (lubricating oils are, by value, an important net exportalso). With the growth in refining capacity and changes in both the overallrate of expansion in oil use and the proportions of the various oil products,the net import of fuel oil, which is already falling, should turn into a netexport, and the net imports of motor spirit and naphtha should decline to relatively small amounts. The likelihood is that, over the period underreview, fuel oil and middle distillates will continue to be available fer
Chart 8United Kingdom Oil Refinery Capacity and Output, Inland Deliveriesand Bunkers, Imports and Exports of Refined Products90-t------------8CH
export. But for these prospects to be realised markets will need to befound and this may not prove easy, since other countries pursue home-refining policies similar to our own.46. The changes in market pattern could give rise to problems of refinerybalance for which oil companies may have to seek solutions in various ways by investment in additional cracking plant, varying the type of crude oilused, exporting more of the surplus products or cutting refinery runs (whichwould involve importing products no longer made). In general, however,the studies made of possible export outlets and of the likely impact of natural gas suggest that the problems of refinery balance will be manageable.Adequacy and Security of Supplies47. The Arab-Israeli war and its consequences, combined with the civil war in Nigeria, have been a sharp reminder of the long-standing problemof security of supply. A wider question sometimes posed is whether worldoil reserves are adequate. There is certainly oil in the ground to meet theworld&apos;s demand well beyond the period under review, and the danger is rather one of being denied normal supplies by political or other eventsoutside the control of the industry or the Government. In the longer termthis danger is limited by the fact that producing countries are at least asdependent on trade in oil as we are ourselves. But war or civil strifemay cause interruptions, and production or exports may be stopped for political reasons or in the attempt to gain a sharp increase in unit revenue,even though this might affect the long-term growth of outlets for Oil.Statistical exercises are undertaken regularly to test the country&apos;s ability tosurvive interruptions of varying severity and duration.48. The problem is to weigh against the risks of interruption the costs of the measures necessary to reduce or eliminate them. There are severalways by which the risk of disruption is reduced without denying the country the benefit of the cheaper oil sources. Nearly all our supplies come fromcompanies which can draw upon a wide variety of sources and have veryflexible supply arrangements, and which own or operate on charter muchof the world&apos;s tanker effect. Supplies can therefore be re-organised withspeed and efficiency in the event of an interruption. Over the past tenyears a great deal has been done to diversify the sources of our supplies.The Middle East, which provided over three-quarters of Britain&apos;s oil tenyears ago, now provides only about half in normal times, though the pro-portion from Arab countries remains high. A number of completely new sources have been developed of which Libya, Nigeria and, in the middle east, Abu Dhabi are the most important.Contingency Measures49. The United Kingdom&apos;s ability and that of other consuming coun-tries to ride out an interruption of our supplies helps to deter producing countries from withholding their oil. A number of contingency measures are available to help overcome interruptions in oil supplies. For example,if one source is denied to us, emergency arrangements can be made to step upproduction from others. Also, in normal times, the world tanker fleet isnot used to full capacity for carrying oil; the resulting reserve helps to
meet transit crises such as closure of the Suez Canal or the Levant oilpipelines. But the most important contingency measure is the possessionof stocks of oil in the consuming country. The companies supplying thiscountry have agreed with the Government to hold sizeable stocks in additionto their normal commercial requirements. The stock targets, which areconfidential, are designed to enable the United Kingdom to resist the denial of a large part of her supplies for a considerable period. It was because&apos;of this stockpiling policy that we were able to weather the serious initialdislocation to supplies earlier this year.50. Current policies have therefore been put to the test. Nevertheless,the Government are making a far-reaching re-examination of ways in whichthe security of the country&apos;s oil supplies might be further strengthened.The review will consider the reliability of the sources from which the UnitedKingdom is normally supplied and ways in which supply might be furtherdiversified, including the possible development, necessarily long-term, ofthe vast reserves of oil locked in non-conventional sources such as theWestern Hemisphere oilsands and shales. It will examine the adequacy of stock levels, and the development of tanker capacity, bearing in mind that the very large tankers now being built will not only yield notable costsavings but also reduce Britain&apos;s dependence on the Suez Canal, which theyare not designed to use when fully laden. In many of these measures, theinterests of the Government and those of the oil companies coincide. Thecost of any further measures will have to be weighed carefully against theireffectiveness and the risks of further interruptions.Balance o  Payments51. Oil imports cost this country substantial sums of foreign exchange,and the Government consult the oil companies about ways to minimisethese costs. In 1965, it is estimated that the net delivered cost of oil to thebalance of payments was about  300 million, or about  4-1 per ton of oil retained in the United Kingdom (that is, after taking credit for thevalue of oil exports). This is considerably less than the c.i.f. value of the oil, as shown in the Trade Accounts, which was about  500 million (after deducting exports of over  100 million). The difference is accounted for bythe use of British tankers, inward investment by foreign companies, and,in the case of British companies, items such as the costs of headquarters,research and other services and the companies&apos; profit margin, all of which arise in or accrue to the United Kingdom. In addition, overseas oil businessbrings further benefits to the balance of payments. Although the overseasearnings both profits and earnings from services of British oil companiesfrom producing and selling oil elsewhere are now lower in proportion toassets than a decade ago, they are still a major contribution to the balanceof payments. Other overseas oil business is also carried on through London.The total net benefit to the balance of payments from all this overseasbusiness is estimated in 1965 to have been around  200 million, includingexports of capital equipment.52. The estimated foreign exchange cost of United Kingdom imports in1965 of  4-1 per ton is an average for all retained imports, both crude oil and products. It is important to assess the foreign exchange content of those products which compete with other fuels, though the allocation of foreign
exchange costs between the various joint products of the refinery processinvolves some arbitrary assumptions. Studies of individual products havebeen made which indicate that in the case of fuel oil (the principal productconcerned) the foreign exchange content of home refined fuel oil in 1965was, on average, around  2-6 per ton, and of imported fuel oil around  4-6per ton, an average of just over  3-0 per ton for all supplies of fuel oil. Thebalance of payments implications are further discussed in paragraph 80and in Chapter 7 below.Future Costs53. It is difficult to predict the course of oil prices. There are a numberof reasons for expecting them not to increase. The industry is continuallysearching for ways of cutting costs, as for instance by the use of very largecrude oil tankers to reduce freight charges and increase flexibility and securityof supply. Competition is strong both between companies and betweensources of supply, and the surplus of crude oil seems likely to persist formany years despite the expansion in world demand. Here and elsewhereoil will be up against increasingly strong competition from natural gasand nuclear power. On the evidence available, it seems likely that oil willremain competitive with coal, and that pressure to force up crude oil prices will be held in check by the danger of loss of markets. . .
5.  Coal54. The principal purpose of the measures which the Government tookin 1965 to assist the coal industry was to improve its competitive strength bysupporting its reorganisation and concentration on the most efficient collieries.In a. capital reconstruction,  415 million was written off the debt of theNational Coal Board, in large part to take account of a revised assessment of the value of the industry&apos;s capital assets. The industry was also to be supported during the period of reorganisation by various measures of pro-tection and other help, including maintenance for the time being of the oil tax and the virtual ban on coal imports, as well as by discrimination against the use of oil at power stations and in public buildings. Even so,the Government took the view that it would not be prudent to count on a coal market in 1970 above the range of 170 to 180 million tons, includingexports.Demand55. In spite of this support and the vigorous marketing efforts of theNational Coal Board, coal demand has declined so fast that it is belowthe bottom end of that range already. During the year ended September,1966, inland consumption and exports fell by 10 million tons, and in thelast twelve months they have fallen by a further 12 million tons. As aresult, consumption and exports during the current calendar year areexpected to be about 165 million tons. This compares with a total of 188million tons in 1965 and 177 million tons in 1966. The fall in demand is not confined to any one group of consumers: all groups are taking less coal.56. This is not a peculiarly British problem but is shared by coal pro-ducers in the European Coal and Steel Community, who have had to facecompetition not only from other fuels, but also from imports of coal fromthe United States of America and Eastern Europe, which are at presentrunning at a rate of 25 million tons a year. In Western Germany, internaldemand for coal in 1966 fell by nearly 13 million tons to 116 million tons.In the much smaller coal industries of France, Belgium and the Netherlands,where the combined demand in 1965 was 101 million tons, consumptionfell in 1966 by 7 million tons. In the countries of the European Coal andSteel Community as a whole, colliery stocks almost doubled between 1964and 1966 to a total of 31 million tons, and by June, 1967, had risen to36 million tons. No useful comparison can be made with the coal industryin the United States, where geological conditions are so much more favour-able that production techniques can be used which enable a miner to producemany times more coal a year than in this country, and pithead prices are less than half those at British mines.Modernisation57. The National Coal Board have continued their work in modernisingthe getting of coal by mechanisation and the use of new techniques. Thepercentage of output power-loaded* rose from 75 per cent, in 1965 to 86 percent, in 1966-67 and is now over 88 per cent. Many more powered roofsupports, which reduce the amount of labour required at the coal face, arebeing installed.   In March, 1966, they were used on only 27 per cent, of* For an explanation of technical terms, see Appendix IV.
Inland Coal Consumption by Sectors and Exports from theUnited Kingdom
the mechanised faces; now they are used on 42 per cent. A major research and development effort is being devoted to the design of machines to eliminate the need for men to cut stable-holes at the end of faces for the coal-cuttingmachines. These and other technical advances are discussed in Appendix IV.Despite this progress, and the corresponding decline in wages and associatedcosts relative to total costs (from 54 per cent, to 51 per cent, over the last twoyears), the coal industry, alone of the fuel industries, remains labour-intensiveand has a relatively low capitalisation.58. The National Coal Board&apos;s objective is to develop means of pro-duction which are not only highly mechanised but operate largely by remotecontrol, so that much of the labour force will eventually consist of highly skilled technicians ; in this objective the Board have the full support of theunions in the industry. The advanced experimental colliery at Bevercoteshas started production and the Board intend that these new methods of mining, adapted in the light of experience, and with due regard to costs,shall be progressively applied to the majority of collieries so that in the1970&apos;s they become the normal method of coal production.&apos;&quot; *Reduction in Number of Collieries59. The number of collieries continues to diminish. It has long been theBoard&apos;s policy to close each year a number of collieries where working hasbecome grossly uneconomic, as well as those where the coal is exhausted.In continuation of this policy 38 collieries were closed in 1964-65, 53 in1965-66, and 46 in 1966-67. Most of the closures have occurred in the older coalfields in Scotland, the North-East, the North-West and South Wales.At the present time the number of collieries operating is about 420.Productivity -60. Productivity, expressed as output per man shift overall, was 34-8 cwts.in 1964-65, 36d cwts. in 1965-66, and 36-6 cwts. in 1966-67. So far thisyear the seasonally corrected figure has been about 38-0 cwts. Difficulty in maintaining manpower in competition with other industries, particularly inthe profitable Midlands coalfields, led to many collieries being under-mannedin 1966 and contributed to the failure in that year to make any significant increase in productivity.61. The benefits of mining by remote control can be obtained onlygradually and are not likely to make a substantial contribution to increases in productivity in the next three or four years. It is from methods which havealready been proved, like the powered support, and from the concentration of output upon well-equipped collieries with good natural conditions, that themain contribution to higher productivity is to be looked for during thisperiod. The process of concentration has now been going on for many years but there are still substantial benefits to be achieved. In 1966-67 the output per man shift overall of the industry&apos;s 300 collieries with the highest produc-tivity was 42-0 cwts., and of the 250 collieries with the highest productivity,43-6 cwts. These figures are 15 per cent, and 19 per cent, respectively abovethe average output for all collieries. The best twenty collieries had anaverage output per man shift overall of about 70 cwts., while for the worsttwenty the figure was only 18 cwts.   A significant improvement in the
Chart 10Coal : Manpower and Productivity
industry&apos;s overall productivity is therefore realisable simply from furtherconcentration of output on the better collieries. The Board consider that itshould be technically possible to obtain by 1970-71 an increase in labour productivity of about a third on the 1966-67 level, and they look to anincrease to two or even three times the 1966-67 level by 1980. Howevertechnically promising the new technical developments may be, a big increasein productivity can only be achieved by the co-operation of management and miners in adopting new methods and in concentrating output upon thebest collieries. It will depend no less upon the industry&apos;s ability to obtainthe labour it needs to man the best collieries.62. The rise in productivity has not so far been sufficient to offset the extra costs imposed by lower total production (with consequent narrowerspread of overheads), by shortages of manpower for a substantial period atmany of the best collieries, and by the general upward movement of wagesand material costs. The average cost of coal per ton (before interest) roseby 4-6 per cent, between 1964-65 and 1965-66, and by 6-4 per cent, between1965-66 and 1966-67, notwithstanding increases in productivity of 3-7 percent, and 1-4 per cent, in these years. This indicates the magnitude of thetask facing the Board if they are to achieve their declared aim of reducingcosts in the coming years, so as to improve their competitive position.Manpower63. The number of men on colliery books fell by 28,000 in 1964-65, by41,000 in 1965-66, and by 26,500 in 1966-67. At present it is about 395,000.The fall in manpower, which has been going on for ten years, has inevitablyoccurred principally in the older coalfields, most of which are now includedin development areas. It has in the main been a carefully controlled reduc-tion. It reflects both the increase that has been taking place in productivity and the decline in production. As productivity rises, fewer men are needed for the same output. On this account alone, without any further fall in the.current level of coal demand, an increase of a third on the 1966-67 rate of productivity would lead to a reduction of about 105,000 in the number of miners by 1970-71 about 26,000 a year. This compares with an averagedecline of about 30,000 a year over the last decade. The total manpowerreduction that will be necessary in future years depends also on the size ofthe market for coal. The more successful the industry is in improving produc-tivity and reducing costs, the greater will be its chances of holding its markets ;the less successful, the faster the switch to other fuels.64. So far, manpower reductions have been achieved largely throughnatural wastage. Normally when a colliery is closed the National coal board have offered the men employment at other collieries within dailytravelling distance or helped them to move to the Midlands coalfields.Unemployment among miners at 1-0 per cent, in 1964-65, 1-0 per cent, in1965-66, and 1-3 per cent, in 1966-67 was in each year below the national average. In the last twenty years coalmining has had plenty of men at times of relatively high unemployment and, not surprisingly, has been shortat times when other employment was easy to find. The industry needsa continuing recruitment of juveniles and young men to maintain the balanceCosts
of its labour force, even at a time when it is reducing its total manpower.The rundown in mining employment does not create a new problem, but may aggravate an existing one in those places where other jobs are alreadyharder to come by than elsewhere. As in the past, many of the collieryclosures will occur in development areas where alternative jobs are relativelyfewer. In some localities there will be difficulties to be overcome in avoid-ing hardship among the elderly and disabled. As the number of collieriesfalls it becomes more difficult to find suitable work for these men withoutunreasonable travelling.Opencast Production65. Opencast production has continued to supplement deep-mined pro-duction, to the extent of about 7 million tons a year in the last three years.Much of the coal produced in this way is general-purpose bituminous coalcomparable to the ordinary output from deep mines, and goes to power stations, but some special qualities of coal are produced which are in short supply in particular places. It is cheaper to produce coal by opencast thanin deep mines. In 1966-67 the average costs per ton, before interest, were80s. 7d. and 98s. 5d. respectively. The Board consider that, with the useof bigger machines at large sites, there should be scope for reductions in cost and that opencast coal should continue to be produced much more cheaply than coal from deep mines. This method of working can, however,cause temporary damage to local amenities. Through screening opencastsites by the erection of embankments and the planting of semi-mature trees,the disturbance caused to local people has been reduced and the Board are working closely with local authorities, in some cases actually to improveamenities on restoration of the land, for example by removing long-standing dereliction and by providing new facilities for sport and recreation.Until the early 1950&apos;s much of the equipment required for opencastworking had to be imported but, with the encouragement of the national coal Board, manufacture now takes place largely in this country and the producers have been able to develop export markets for their equipment.The case for continued opencast working, taken by itself, is quite strong,but it has to be related to the circumstances of the industry as a whole.At a time of coal surplus, account has to be taken of the effects on total production and on the level of employment in deep mines.Stocks66. In 1964, 1965 and 1966, the National Coal Board were successful in matching production to the falling demand so that undistributed stocks were kept from rising. They varied between 18 and 22-j- million tons, equi-valent to five to six weeks&apos; supply. At the end of last winter, with demandfalling faster than production, undistributed stocks began to rise in com-parison with the previous year. At present, they are about 7 million tonsabove their level at the corresponding time last year. The Board are taking steps to limit production, and thereby the rise in their stocks, particularly by limiting non-juvenile recruitment, but they must have regard to the potential damage to the industry of reducing their manpower suddenly, andthey are aware of the consequences for the country, both economic and social, of doing this at a time when unemployment is already high. Thereis thus a serious conflict of objectives.
Chart 11Coal Production, Consumption and Undistributed Stocks
Transport of Coal67. The cost of transporting coal adds on average about  1 per ton or20 per cent, to its cost of production. Savings in transport costs can leadto a useful improvement in coal&apos;s competitive position and the majorcoal users have been co-operating with British Railways and the national coal Board in seeking means of achieving them. In particular, power stations and other bulk users are increasingly supplied by special permanently-coupled trains which move continuously between colliery and point of con-sumption and are rapidly loaded and discharged while in motion.68. Shrinking production and geographical concentration have meant thatthe coal industry has offered a declining amount of traffic to the railways.In 1964, 1965 and 1966 the tonnages of coal and coke transported were 147million, 138 million and 132 million respectively, accounting for about 35per cent, of the total freight revenue of British Railways. The annualtonnage leaving the collieries by road has remained steady at about 36million tons.Capital Investment69. The Board require to invest a substantial amount of capital eachyear to replace worn-out assets. In addition, modernisation calls for more complicated and more expensive equipment. Because of this, and despitedeclining production, the Board&apos;s new investment in fixed colliery assetshas remained at about the same level in recent years, namely  77 million in1964-65,  74 million in 1965-66, and  77 million in 1966-67. The 1965White Paper on the Finances of the Coal Industry (Cmnd. 2805) noted inparagraph 18 that the Board intended after the capital reconstruction to aim at generating from their own earnings the funds needed for futurecolliery investment. This aim was not achieved in 1966-67, since theBoard&apos;s internal resources, in the form of depreciation provisions, proceeds of disposals and surplus, fell short of new colliery investment by about 19^ million. The shortfall was made good by increased borrowing fromthe Exchequer. In addition to investment in collieries, the Board have continued to invest in ancillary activities and in new enterprises such asthe exploration for oil and gas on the Continental Shelf.Profit and Loss70. In 1965-66, the capital reconstruction led to reductions, totalling 35-6 million, in charges to profit and loss account for interest ( 21-5 mil-lion), depreciation ( 10-5 million) and obsolescence ( 3-6 million) ; and a deficit of  24-8 million, which reflected the deferment at the governments request of increases in coal prices, was written off against the Reserve Fund.A general rise in coal prices took effect in the spring of 1966, and in theyear 1966-67 the Board had a small surplus of  0-3 million but made no contribution towards meeting the difference between depreciation of assetsat historic and replacement cost, for which their objective is  10 million a year.
Part III.  THE CO-ORDINATION OF policy.  The Objectives and Determinants of Policy71. The foregoing outline of the prospects for the fuel industries points to our being on the threshold of a major change in the energy economy.The advent of two new primary fuels, natural gas and nuclear power, is a development of great economic importance for the country and the objectof the Government^ review has been to examine its implications in depthso as to evolve policies for fuel which will bring the greatest benefit to thecountry.72. With four primary fuels in the place of two, and a good deal of un-certainty about a number of important factors, it was necessary in the review to examine a series of possible alternative lines of development and to make assumptions about the main variables and uncertainties. the statistical methods used are described in Appendix I. The main assump-tions made for statistical purposes at the start of the review were asfollows : (a) Alternative high and low quantities were taken for supplies of north Sea gas, and it was assumed that they would be available ineach case at prices which would permit the full quantity being sold to consumers.(b) The second nuclear power programme of 8,000 megawattsof capacity coming into commission between 1970 and 1975 wouldbe completed as planned ; and a third and larger programme wouldbe initiated during this period for stations to be commissionedafter 1975.(c) The coal industry would achieve the full increase in productivitywhich the National Coal Board considered possible.(d) No coal would be imported.(e) Oil would continue to be available at a price competitive withcoal.(f) The gross domestic product would grow at a rate of about 3 percent, a year.(g) Three possible courses on the protection for indigenous fuels shouldbe examined protection removed ; protection about the same as now ; protection roughly doubled.As the work progressed the results of other studies were fed into thesestatistical investigations. The studies included the examination of nuclear power costs and of possible future trends in coal and oil prices to establishwhether the assumptions in the statistical exercise were sound. As more information on the North Sea came to hand, the assumptions on natural gaswere brought up to date.73. Despite the depth of these studies major uncertainties inevitablyremain.  The development of fuel policy is a continuing process and further
changes may be appropriate as further information about, for example, theNorth Sea gas reserves becomes available. The policy in the White Paperrests on present information and knowledge and the best judgments theGovernment can make about the future.74. Table A below illustrates in round figures the likely pattern of fueluse in the mid-1970&apos;s on the assumptions indicated in the footnote. more detailed figures are given in Appendix I.Table ATrends of Primary Fuel UseMillion tons coal equivalentCoal       ............Oil        ............Nuclear and Hydro-electricity ...Natural Gas      .........Total Inland Demand for Energy  ...    251-3       297-7	(m.t.c.e.)	1957	1966	1975(Actual)	(Actual)	212-9	\1A-1	120*36-7	111-7	1451-7	10-2	35 	1-1	50251-3	297-7	350* Exports of coal estimated at about 2 million tons.Footnote. The main assumptions underlying the pattern of primary fuel use in 1975shown in Table A are that North Sea gas reserves would support a level of production at anaverage rate of 4,000 m.c.f.d. and that the price of the gas would be such that it could be sold; that there would be no conversion of coal-fired power stations to oil; that the secondnuclear power programme would be fulfilled; that oil tax would be at a rate of 2d. a gallon;and that no coal would be imported. Gross domestic product is assumed to grow at anaverage rate of 3 per cent, per annum.75. Projections for so long a period ahead are inevitably subject to considerable uncertainty and the figures should be regarded as illustratingtrends, not as setting targets. It is important to note the assumptions onwhich they are based, as summarised in the footnote to the table. The con-siderations involved are further discussed elsewhere in the White Paper.But, subject to this proviso, the indications are that: -(a) By 1975 nuclear power and natural gas may be supplying as muchas a quarter of all our energy requirements. How much natural gaswill eventually be produced will not be known until much moreexploration is completed; but studies of nuclear energy point to nuclear power making a rapidly increasing contribution in the later 1970&apos;s, possibly amounting to almost a quarter of our totalenergy requirements by the end of the decade.(b) The inescapable result of the growing use of these new fuels willbe to limit the market for coal; but even without them coal wouldhave continued to decline unless it were still more heavily protected.(c) In order to alter relative prices in favour of coal sufficiently to slowdown its decline significantly, it would be necessary to protect it ata level which would lead to misuse of resources and would putBritish industry at a disadvantage with its competitors.
(d) The decline in the demand for coal, which is already faster than was anticipated in the 1965 White Paper,* could therefore only be reversed by deliberately holding back the expansion of nuclear powerand the introduction of natural gas, and by heavy additional pro-tection or a massive subsidy.(e) Oil is unlikely to maintain its fast growth of recent years ; but withgrowing consumption for transport and similar exclusive uses, itwill hold or slightly increase its present share of the total energymarket.76. In the light of the Government^ aim of shaping developments in the energy sector so as to bring the greatest strength to the economy, it isnecessary first to test the emerging trends against certain specific objectives of fuel policy, namely those relating to adequacy and security of supply,fuel costs and prices, the effects on the balance of payments and the efficient use of the nation&apos;s resources the objectives formulated in para-graph 35 of the 1965 White Paper. * The problems are social as well aseconomic and involve people, notably because the fortunes of whole com-munities are tied up with those of the coal industry ; these problems are considered in the context of the formulation of central and regional economic policy. It is not possible fully to represent all these considerations in a statistical exercise, though in some cases it has been possible to examinethem quantitatively as well as qualitatively. The conclusions are as follows.Adequacy of Fuel Supplies77. The prospects for fuel supplies up to 1980 have been examined insome detail with a broad look ahead at developments whose main impactwill come later still. The only fuel for which it seems justifiable at this stage to contemplate a degree of conservation because of eventual physical scarcityis North Sea natural gas (see Appendix II); for the remainder there seemsno reason why the possibility of exhaustion of reserves should be regardedas a constraint in determining the best way of meeting the nation&apos;s energyrequirements. Ultimately, no doubt, all fossil fuel could be used up, butthis is too far in the future to be taken into account, and changes in science and technology can be expected to develop alternative sources of energyin time. This is not to say that there could not be shortages of a particularfuel from time to time, since neither supply nor demand are easily regulatedin the short term.Security of Supply78. The considerations relating to oil supplies are discussed in paragraphs47 to 50 ; and further studies are in hand to explore ways of improving the security of these supplies in the light of the repercussions of the middle east war. But in the meantime the Government have judged it right to base planning on the assumption that regular and competitively pricedsupplies of oil will continue to be available to us, as they have been in increasing quantities over the past years. In formulating policy it is necessaryto take a balanced view of the risks involved ; with a two-fuel economy the* Cmnd. 2798.
risks in depending too heavily on oil from abroad were likely to become increasingly severe as oil continued to increase its share of total energy use.This was an important reason for protecting coal against competition fromoil. But nuclear power and North Sea gas are hardly less secure than coal and the security of our fuel supplies will be enhanced to the extent thatthey take up markets which would otherwise have gone to oil. This reinforcesthe case for continuing to accept a degree of risk with oil supplies for thosemarkets which it retains, so that we may benefit from its cheapness and convenience as our foreign competitors do.Cheap Energy79. Subject to these overriding considerations of adequacy and securityof supplies, the Governments basic objective can be summarised as cheapenergy. This does not imply that fuel prices should be held artificially lowcompared with the real costs since this would lead to waste of resources.What is important is that we should take full advantage of the cheapness andtechnical merit of nuclear power, North Sea gas and oil (subject to the foreign exchange and investment considerations which are discussed below).Balance of Payments80. All fuels except indigenous coal involve some direct cost in foreign exchange. In general this will be highest for oil, intermediate for natural gas, and lowest for nuclear power. Virtually all our oil comes from overseasin the first instance. Its cost in foreign exchange varies according to itssource, whether it is refined here or overseas, whether the suppliers are british or foreign and whether it is transported in British or foreign ships.An indication of the net balance of payments costs of oil and of some of the factors which enter into the calculation is given in paragraphs 51-52 : theestimated average foreign exchange content of retained oil imports in 1965was  4-1 per ton (rather less for fuel oil see paragraph 52). Both north sea natural gas and nuclear power also have some foreign exchange content,although rather lower than for oil. Many of the companies engaged in theNorth Sea are subsidiaries of foreign companies and the North Sea opera-tions involve both an inflow and an outflow of foreign exchange. The precisecosts in foreign exchange of North Sea gas will depend on the price to bepaid for the gas and on which companies supply it. In the case of nuclear power, the uranium fuel for the reactors all comes in the first instance from overseas. Current requirements are being met from the substantial stockalready held in this country, but this will have to be replaced in time andit is appropriate to regard all incremental requirements for uranium as involving-ing a cost in foreign exchange. For A.G.R. stations this cost would appear tobe in the region of 10s. a ton of coal equivalent. The present oil taxrepresents an average loading of about 40 per cent on the delivered pre-taxprice of fuel oil to large industrial users and, as a measure of protection for indigenous fuels, this is a much higher level of protection than appliesin most other sectors of the economy. From the detailed studies whichhave been made of the balance of payments costs of the different fuels, theGovernment have concluded that, leaving aside fiscal considerations, there-is no justification for contemplating any increase in the tax. In reaching a view about the appropriate rate it is important that weight should be given
Capital Investment and the use of Resources81. The Government seek to ensure that the nationalised fuel industriesuse the resources they employ as efficiently and economically as possible.This is of especial importance in relation to their capital investment which isat present around  1,000 million a year. In the [forthcoming] White paper on the Nationalised Industries the Government have set out guidelines forthe industries to follow in regard to investment. Very briefly, they are that,having adopted the best possible methods of appraisal of projects (whichwill normally mean the use of discounted cash flow techniques) and appro-priate pricing policies (which, whilst recovering accounting costs, would aim to relate prices to costs at the margin), the industries should look for a return of at least 8 per cent on all new investment undertaken for purelycommercial reasons. During the review of fuel policy, as the electricity industry and nuclear power in particular are more capital intensive than other parts of the fuel sector, the effect on supply and demand patterns of using different rates of interest was examined ; but over the range con-sidered, they were not found to be very much affected.Manpower and Social Implications82. The manpower and social implications of developments in the fuelsector are important not only for economic reasons but also for the humanproblems involved. To achieve a major shift in patterns of employmentinevitably takes time and can cause serious hardship to individuals. In the energy sector, the coal industry faces the most difficult, problems of redeploy-ment, rendered more acute by the fact that contraction is greatest inthose areas where alternative employment is most difficult to come by.Further contraction and concentration of the industry are necessary andinescapable. The Governments aim is that they should be brought aboutwith the least possible waste and hardship. In the past the National coal board have had remarkable success in reducing and redeploying the industry&apos;smanpower without serious redundancy. In any process of industrial changesome social disturbance is unavoidable. The Government believe that by further support for the National Coal Board in their redeployment measures,by direct assistance to the elderly and disabled who are least able to fendfor themselves and through vigorous pursuit of the policies for promotingnew and more varied employment in the development areas, the continuingcontraction of the coal industry can be carried through to the advantageof the economy and with the minimum of hardship to individuals.Technology83. Scientific and technological advance are vital in the energy sector, as elsewhere in the economy, in order to increase efficiency and reduce costs.The fuel industries&apos; record is good and Part II of this White Paper has indicated that the momentum of advance should increase rather than slacken.In addition to serving their own internal efficiency, the fuel industries are able to contribute substantially to the promotion of technological progress to the indirect effects on the balance of payments of the availability of cheapfuels in making British goods more competitive for exports or import-substitution.
in other industries, as purchasers of new equipment and as suppliers of rawmaterials. Much may be expected of the expansion of nuclear power as aspur to the wide range of engineering industries involved in research, develop-ment and construction of nuclear plant and equipment for the home and export markets. The many roles played by oil, both within and outside the fuel sector, have already been noted ; and natural gas may be of growingimportance as a chemical feedstock as well as a fuel. Technologically theBritish coal industry is among the most advanced in the world; in relationto many other countries it is particularly far advanced in its approach tothe use of electronics and computers. Exports of coal mining machinery in1966 were worth about  15 million. More generally, low cost energy should extend the range of British economic activity and strengthen the competitive-ness of British industry. The Government^ recent decision to assist in establishing large-scale aluminium smelting capacity is a striking example of the opportunities offered by cheap energy.Transport84. The effect of changes in the fuel sector on other industries has been examined. In particular, declining coal sales and the concentration of newcoal-fired power stations on the coalfields mean less traffic for railways and coastal shipping. On the analysis carried out in the review, the Governmentare satisfied that no additional fuel policy measures are needed on this account,over and above those required to secure the orderly transition of the fuelindustries themselves. But it is necessary for the transport industry to beable to plan ahead on the basis of the best possible information on themain future flows of coal, and the National Coal Board are in close touchwith the British Railways Board.85. Major changes in the fuel economy take place relatively slowly and accordingly, in looking at the foregoing considerations, the. Government havetaken a long view. But in moving towards whatever long-term pattern of energy supplies is desired, account must be taken of transitional problems,some of them of considerable economic and social importance. In the two following chapters, the Government have set out first their long-term policyand then the shorter-term measures required to deal with transitional problems.
7.  Long-term Policy86. The first decision for the Government is whether a pattern of energysupplies in the mid-1970&apos;s of the general shape indicated by Table A* isdesirable. As explained in paragraph 75, the figures in that table are in no sense production targets for the various primary fuels, but rather an illustration of the balance between them which underlying trends are likelyto have brought about by the mid-1970&apos;s. They also point the direction inwhich the fuel sector is likely to develop in the still longer term: a continuingcontraction of the coal industry, a slower rate of expansion for oil, rising useof nuclear power and perhaps further growth in natural gas.87. The developing pattern of primary fuel supplies offers substantialbenefits. The introduction of the newer fuels will mean cheaper energy.In the coming years they will not only take up the natural increase in Britain&apos;senergy requirements, but will also capture some existing markets from oil and coal. The recent growth of oil, both in new markets and in displacement ofcoal, has been very rapid: over the past nine years oil has risen from 15 to37 per cent, of our total energy use and, if the introduction of nuclear powerand natural gas were impeded, oil would inevitably gain an increasing shareof the energy market. In a two-fuel economy, the time might have come when, despite oil&apos;s advantages as a fuel and its value in so many other roles,dependence on foreign sources for so much of our energy became a matterof serious concern.88. The experience of the Middle East war emphasises the importanceof developing the newer fuels on grounds both of security and cheapness.North Sea gas and nuclear power will slow down the advance of oil andthey will take up some of the markets which coal would otherwise be likelyto lose to oil. To the extent that they do so, there will be Benefits to thebalance of payments and an improvement in the security of fuel supplies.With a four-fuel economy the proportion of its energy requirements forwhich the country has to rely on imported fuel in the mid-1970&apos;s would belittle higher than it is today, and there should be no greater need to considerlimiting the growth of oil on security grounds. It should be noted that oilprices already reflect the cost of existing diversification and oil stockpiling bythe companies.89. Further decline in the markets for coal could not be prevented evenby holding back the expansion of nuclear power and the development of natural gas unless the present level of coal protection were raised to an extent which would lead to a big increase in the general level of energy prices, or unless coal prices were heavily subsidised. But excessive protection for coal would lead to a misallocation of manpower and capital to the detriment ofthe economy as a whole.90. We cannot afford to penalise our competitive standing as a nation by adding unnecessarily to our energy costs. Developments in recent years have reduced our competitive advantage in fuel costs vis-a-vis Europe: whileAmerican fuel costs are markedly lower than ours. It follows that we need to take the fullest advantage of the new primary sources of energy natural gas and nuclear power in order to assist industry in its competitive struggle ;* See paragraph 74.
and that it is essential for the coal industry to continue its drive for greater efficiency and lower costs, so that it too can play its part in the provision ofcheaper energy.91. Nevertheless, while the balance of payments position is difficult, asat present, some discrimination against oil is justifiable to conserve foreign exchange. But, as indicated in paragraph 80, the present rate of tax on oilalready represents a high level of protection for coal.92. The other major potential constraint on accepting a shift to the cheaper fuels is the rate at which it is practicable for the coal industry to contract and for the Government and the industry to deal satisfactorily withthe resulting employment and social problems. The Government considerthat a contraction to the level of demand for 1975 suggested by Table should be manageable, but they have accepted the advice of the national coal Board that the rate of contraction implied by the corresponding figuresfor 1970* would cause unmanageable difficulties for the industry during thenext few years. It might also cause serious difficulties for the economy inthis period.93. The Government have decided that it is in the national interest toaccept the long-term trends implied by Table A as a basis for planning.However, the figures in Table A make no allowance for the possible con-version of coal-fired power stations to oil or for any relaxation in the presentvirtual ban on foreign coal imports. It will be necessary to consider at alater date whether to relax these measures and what effect on coal demand in the 1970&apos;s this would have. For the present, the problems raised by the already fast rate of contraction of the coal industry up to 1970 preclude suchrelaxation; and during this period it will be necessary to take additional measures to help the industry and to secure an orderly transition. these measures are described in the next chapter. The longer-term decisionsimplicit in the Government^ general conclusions are as follows.Natural Gas94. Natural gas is to be introduced rapidly into the economy. Strategyon gas absorption will continue to be evolved as more knowledge is gainedabout reserves, prices and markets. At this stage a rapid build-up in supplies is envisaged, on a basis allowing for the absorption of all that the fields sofar discovered are expected to produce in the mid-1970&apos;s, with a modestallowance for additional discoveries. Most of the natural gas available will go to the premium markets where it will largely be displacing oil, but therewill be some supplies to bulk industrial users, to assist the early build-upin supplies and to balance load thereafter. In these markets there will be some displacement of coal as well as oil.95. This policy will mean a shorter life for the gas fields than a policy ofslow depletion and will involve using some of the gas in markets where theresource savings are relatively low. The Government believe, that thesedisadvantages are outweighed by the value of giving an incentive to thefurther exploration needed to improve our knowledge of the ultimate reservesavailable, and by the benefits to the economy and the balance of payments which a fast build-up of supplies will bring.* See Appendix i, Table d.
96. Rapid absorption of natural gas will not bring dislocation or chaosto the energy market. 4,000 m.c.f.d. represents only about 15 per cent, of thetotal demand for energy expected in 1975 : an important slice of the marketbut not revolutionary in its impact. But, for the gas industry, it does repre-sent a revolution involving the wholesale displacement of existing gas-makingplant and methods, a nation-wide conversion programme, and an expansionof sales by nearly fourfold between now and the mid-1970&apos;s.Nuclear Power and Power Station Fuel Use97. In the last few years, in recognition of the strong interest it has inthe well-being of the coal industry because of the many coal-fired power stations which will remain in use for many years ahead, the electricity industry has been giving preference to coal in operating its stations. TheGovernment have decided on a new scheme extending to 1970-71, the detailsof which are given in paragraphs 116-117 below.98. The 1965 White Paper* established for planning purposes a secondnuclear power programme of 8,000 MW and the Government envisage thecompletion of that programme by the mid-1970&apos;s. That White Paperalso stated that proposals for oil-fired power stations would be the subjectof special scrutiny. In order to keep down costs and prices it is important that the electricity industry should be able to make use of cheap sources of primary energy. Power stations not yet started cannot at the veryearliest come into commission before 1973. The generating Boards should base their choice of fuel for new power stations on an economic assessment of the method of generation which will enable them to supply electricity atthe lowest system cost consistent with security of supply and load balancing.In deciding whether to give consent to new stations, the Minister of Powerand the Secretary of State for Scotland will also take into account suchwider economic considerations as may be relevant.99. It would be consistent with this policy for the generating Boards to seek consent in the longer term for the conversion of stations from oneprimary fuel to another where this would reduce system costs. The electricity industry will, however, require very large quantities of coal in the 1970&apos;sand has a strong, continuing interest in the health of the coal industry. Forthis reason, linked as it is with the short-term structural problems of thecoal industry, the Government do not in general envisage the conversion ofcoal-fired stations to other fuels in the next few years, though there maybe scope for some use of natural gas on a seasonal basis and there maybe cases where the requirements of clean air dictate conversions from coal to other fuels.Oil100. Although the Government have decided, particularly in the light ofthe current balance of payments position, that it is right to continue to favour indigenous fuels against oil, it remains their broad policy to avoiddiscrimination between oil companies trading in the home market. good progress has been made towards the goal of home refining capacity to match the country&apos;s requirements and this remains a major objective of policy,* Cmnd. 2798.
though with recognition of the fact that some trade in oil products between countries will still be necessary for the oil companies to balance theirinternational refining operations. The home refining policy depends also on the maintenance of a reasonable and balanced level of demand for thevarious oil products.101. The repercussions of the Middle East war could have significantimplications for certain aspects of oil policy. As stated in paragraph 50,the Government are conducting a thorough re-examination of ways of strengthening the security of our supplies. They nevertheless consider it right to base fuel policy on the expectation that regular supplies of oil atcompetitive prices will continue to be available and they believe that itwould be wrong to deny to British industry the advantages that oil can bring. The greater part of the expected growth in demand is due to the growing needs of those markets, notably transport, where oil has no sub-stitute ; in the competitive part of its markets oil&apos;s rate of growth is expectedto slacken. Although oil use as a whole in 1975 is expected to representa higher percentage of total energy requirements than now, the increase willbe small by contrast with the past. Subject to the outcome of the re-examina-tion now in progress, no greater discrimination against oil should prove necessary on grounds of security.Coal102. The Government have concluded from their analysis of coal&apos;s positionand prospects in relation to competing fuels that, on any tenable view ofthe longer-term pattern of energy supplies and costs, the demand for coalwill continue to decline. This is not the result of Government policy: itreflects a continuing trend in consumer preference.103. The Government do not underrate the difficulty of the task con-fronting management and men in trying to maintain and increase the efficiency of an industry which is gradually contracting. But because coal will continue for a long time to provide such a large and indispensable part of thecountry&apos;s fuel supplies, it is of the greatest importance for the efficiency of the industry to be still further increased and costs reduced. The Govern-ment have concluded that the modernisation of the coal industry and itsconcentration on the most economic coalfields and collieries must go forward.Only in this way can the coal industry remain viable.104. The precise level of coal demand in the 1970&apos;s will depend on theextent to which productivity can be raised and costs brought down: withouta substantial rise in productivity and the consequent saving in manpower,the cost of coal will be so high that coal demand will fall more quicklythan implied by Table A. Either way, a further decline in colliery manpoweris inevitable.105. To the extent that manpower, and hence production, are not reduced in step with rising productivity and falling demand, undistributed stocks will rise above the level necessary to ensure proper distribution and security ofsupply: this has recently begun to happen on a large scale. With thepresent outlook for demand, there is serious risk of these additional stocksremaining unsold indefinitely.  In any case they are a large additional burden
on the Exchequer, which has to finance them, and a continuing discourage-ment to the men and management of the industry. The Government there-fore consider it important that production should be continually adjusted to the level of demand and that excessive stocking should be avoided. How-ever, time will be needed both for the industry&apos;s management to make thenecessary adjustments inside the industry and for the men becoming redundancies-dant to be re-deployed into other employment. Similarly, time must elapse before the measures now being taken by the National Coal Board can resultin cost reduction. The greater the Board&apos;s success in reducing costs, thehigher coal demand is likely to be in the mid-1970&apos;s.106. Most of the colliery closures will be in the older coalfields in development areas. The measures it is proposed to take to improve thebenefits to men leaving the industry or transferred to other collieries, andto facilitate the redeployment of ex-miners to other suitable work in the transitional period, are set out in the next section ; for the longer term,the Government^ regional policies take full account of the trends of miningemployment.107. As already indicated, the Government have decided that protection for coal cannot be reduced at the moment, but they have considered whetherthe existing forms of protection are the best. At present, apart from theassistance from the electricity industry, coal is helped by the 2-2d. a gallon tax on oil and the virtual ban on imports of coal. Imports of coalcompeting with home production would add to the difficulties of the UnitedKingdom coal industry and the lifting of the import ban cannot becontemplated at the moment, but the Government will keep this question under review.108. An alternative to action against other fuels to protect coal would bea general subsidy for coal. The cost of a subsidy sufficient to have the same effect as the present tax on oil would be very heavy, representing a significant increase in taxation ; and if it were to replace the oil tax the revenue so lostwould additionally have to be made up from new taxation. A subsidy would reduce energy prices but would not alter the real costs of energy supplies tothe country. It would also have the effect of protecting coal against natural gas and nuclear power. The Government have concluded that a generalsubsidy for coal is undesirable for these reasons, but they have acceptedcertain commitments for the transitional period as explained in the nextchapter.109. Taking a broad view of the industry&apos;s prospects in the long term, theGovernment are satisfied that it should be able to provide on an economic basis a substantial though declining part of the country&apos;s fuel requirements.Over the next few years however, the industry will need continuing assistance.110. In neither of the last two financial years were the Board able to generate from their earnings all the funds needed for colliery investment:the higher revenue secured from the coal price increase in the spring of 1966was entirely absorbed by rising costs. Any further substantial addition to prices would tend to depress the demand for coal still further and so increasethe difficulties of dealing with manpower. In these circumstances the Boardcannot be expected to find from their own resources all the finance for the
expensive modernisation programme or to bear a large proportion of the costof the measures necessary to ensure that the reduction in manpower is con-ducted without undue hardship. Parliament will therefore be asked to provide further investment funds to continue the finanoing of the industry&apos;s modernisa-tion, in so far as these cannot be provided from current revenue without undue increases in the price of coal. The proposed financial arrangementsfor the measures needed to deal with manpower in the transitional periodare set out in the following chapter.
8.  Policy for the Transition111. The new pattern of energy supplies in the 1970&apos;s will bring usimportant advantages. It promises increasing quantities of high grade cleanfuels from our own resources to meet our growing needs ; it frees us fromthe risk of becoming over-dependent on foreign sources ; it will lower ourenergy costs ; and it will promote technological advance. But it will meanradical changes in the fuel sector, some of them difficult to make. It is in theinterests of the community as a whole that they are squarely faced, but it isequally important that they should be made with the minimum waste ofeconomic and human resources.112. The Government are conscious of the particular difficulties whichthe transition from the present pattern will cause for the coal industry and themining communities ; and they have decided on a number of special measuresto help the industry through the transitional period to 1970.Rate of Contraction in the Coal Industry113. The Governments aim is that the industry&apos;s contraction during thenext few years should be brought about with the least possible hardshipin mining communities and without interruption of the modernisation of theindustry. They accept the advice of the National Coal Board that a rundownof about 35,000 men a year would be manageable for the industry. On past experience, and taking account of natural wastage, such a rundown should not create a national problem. But it will require special attention to problems in particular areas; measures to this end are described in later paragraphs.The Government have accordingly decided that planning for the industry&apos;scontraction up to 1970-71 should be based on this rate- of rundown. Itis, however, their intention to maintain close consultation with the national coal Board about the programme of colliery closures.114. In the light of an assessment of employment prospects this winter,the Government have requested the Board to defer until after the end of1967 all closures except those necessitated by the exhaustion of reserves. Inaddition, the Board will decide, in the light of the advice of the Chairmen ofthe Regional Economic Planning Councils, whether any of these closuresshould be further delayed until the end of March, 1968, and this arrange-ment will also apply to closures in areas of high unemployment which are due in the first quarter of 1968. These exceptional measures are designedto meet the problems of this winter only, and thereafter colliery closureswill be in accordance with the planned contraction of the industry upto 1970-71.Demand for Coal115. On the basis of the estimates discussed with the nationalised fuelindustries, and taking into account the latest views on the likely use of natural gas by 1970, the Government consider that inland coal demand in that year would be unlikely to exceed 146 million tons with perhaps a further 3 million tons for exports. With the further increases in productivity that can beexpected from modernisation and the closure of uneconomic collieries, coal production in 1970 might be as much as 155 million tons, some 6 million tonsmore than the likely demand.   For the reasons mentioned in paragraph 105,
the Government consider it desirable that any coal unadvoidably produced inexcess of demand should, if possible, be used rather than added to undistri-buted stocks which are already high.116. The only sector in which it would be practicable to increase coalconsumption significantly is electricity generation. The electricity industryexpected to take 70 million tons of coal in 1970 out of the estimated totalinland demand for coal of 146 millions tons. They were also expected touse 15 million tons coal equivalent (m.t.c.e.) of oil, 4 m.t.c.e. of natural gasand 16 m.t.c.e. of nuclear power and hydro electricity.* In the gas industrythere is also scope for some additional coal consumption, though on a verymuch smaller scale. The Government have examined with the electricity and gas industries by how much they could increase their consumption ofcoal in the period to March, 1971, above what they would expect to use onthe basis of straight commercial calculations. As a result the two industriesexpect to be able to burn up to 6 million tons more coal per annum up to1970 if this should prove necessary. The need for, and the cost of, this additional coal burn will depend on various factors, notably the trends in thesupply and demand for coal, and will be kept under close review by theGovernment.117. Under the arrangements referred to in the 1965 White Paper, f thecost of additional coal use by the electricity industry was borne by electricityconsumers. The Government have decided that, in the light of the new situation facing the coal industry, it would be wrong to expect electricity and gas consumers to bear the cost of these new arrangements, which arebeing introduced for wider social and economic reasons. The government intend, therefore, to ask Parliament to provide for the cost, not exceeding 45 million, to be met out of public funds.118. Despite the further help to be given to coal at power stations andgasworks, the Government recognise that in the period up to 1970 it maynot be possible to adjust production at all times to current demand, and thereby to avoid increases in undistributed stocks, but they have asked theNational Coal Board to take all reasonable steps to this end and will keepthe level of stocks under review.119. Production of coal at opencast sites employs comparatively few men for each ton of coal won, and reduction of opencast production thereforegives rise to fewer manpower difficulties than reduction of deep-mined pro-duction. Though opencast production is profitable and relatively small, thereis no advantage to be gained from continuing opencast production where this can be avoided, at a time when surplus coal is being put to stockat considerable cost. The Government have therefore decided not to give further authorisations for opencast production except in special cases where,because of quality or location, the coal to be produced is not in competition with coal from deep mines ; and they have asked the National Coal board to have regard to these factors in operations at existing sites.* These estimates represented a reduction in the amount of natural gas and oil previouslyassumed to be used for electricity generation (see Table D of Appendix I).f Cmnd. 2798 paragraphs 18, 51 and 82.
Energy Pattern in 1970120. If, as at present envisaged, the demand for coal needs to be sustainedat 155 million tons in 1970 the pattern of inland demand for energy inthat year is estimated as follows : Table BPrimary Fuel Use in 19701966 1970(Actual)Mil/ion tons coal equivalentCoal      ...      ......     ......     ...    174-7 152*Oil         ......      ............     111-7 125Nuclear and Hydro-Electricity         ......      10-2 16Natural Gas      ...............       1-1 17Total Inland Demand for Energy     ...    297-7 310* Plus an estimated 3 million tons for exports, making a total demand of 155 million tons.121. As a consequence of the extra use of coal at power stations in theyears up to 1970-71, there is likely to be little scope between now andthen for the conversion of coal-fired power stations to use other conventionalfuels all the year round. If it were necessary for the power stations to usean additional 6 million tons of coal in 1970, their use of oil in that year would be likely to be down to 11 million tons coal equivalent, and their use of natural gas only 2 million tons coal equivalent (equivalent to anannual rate of 125 million cubic feet a day). Natural gas in that quantitycould be taken, in the summer only, at power stations fired normally by either coal or oil. The gas industry&apos;s potential market for bulk sales of natural gas to power stations would be limited accordingly. production from the North Sea should be capable of reaching an annual average rateof 2,000 m.c.f.d. by 1971 and, allowing for the use of natural gas in reformingplant in place of oil, the industry has estimated that it might absorb some,500 m.c.f.d. for premium uses in that year. It will, however, have to lookelsewhere than power stations for any substantial bulk markets needed to match the supply in these years.Social and Regional Measures122. The manpower situation facing the coal industry is not new andthe prospective reduction in mining manpower is fairly close to the average rate for the last ten years (see paragraph 63). Natural wastage willcontinue to account for the major part of the expected rundown and therewill still be some scope for redeployment within the industry so that thenumber of redundant miners remaining unemployed for any length of time should continue to be a relatively small percentage of the total reduction.But, as noted in paragraph 64, it is in some of the development areas thatthe decline will have its most serious impact. Quite apart from anyredundancies among miners, the loss of job opportunities will intensify theproblems these areas are facing.
123. One of the chief objects of the Government^ regional policies hasbeen to help the development areas to overcome their difficulties and build a more broadly based industrial structure. The Government have overthe past few years introduced, or progressively strengthened, a wide range of measures affecting these areas. The development areas include the coalfieldsof Scotland, Wales and Northumberland and Durham, and as such theyare already assisted to a very considerable extent. For example, in orderto encourage new industrial development, 45 per cent, grants for investment in new industrial plant and machinery are available in development areas,compared with 25 per cent, grants elsewhere, and building grants areavailable up to a level of 35 per cent, in certain cases. The Board of Tradeprovides factories on favourable terms, and the number of factories built,in advance to provide an inducement to firms to move to development areas has been greatly increased. Exchequer grants (of up to 85 per cent, of thecost involved) are available to local authorities for the acquisition and rehabilitation of derelict land and the provision and improvement of basicservices, if these contribute to the development of industry. The control overthe issue of industrial development certificates which are required for allsignificant industrial building is operated with great stringency outsidedevelopment areas, so that firms are encouraged to develop in those areas where industrial development certificates are readily available. As a resultof this policy, in recent years the development areas have received a con-siderably greater share of new industrial building. In order to ensure thatthere is a sufficient supply of skilled labour available for incoming industry,the number and capacity of Government Training Centres have been greatlyexpanded and these have been increasingly directed towards the development areas, and the Government also give direct financial and practical assistanceto employers to help with training. In addition, the Government introduced the Regional Employment Premium (see Cmnd. 3310), which ^ame into effect in September.124. The Government are confident that the combined effect of these measures will ensure that, despite the continuing contraction of basic indus-tries, including coal, the economic prospects of the development areas as awhole will improve and the average level of unemployment there fall.There are, however, certain coalmining areas where general measures of assist-ance to the development areas as a whole are unlikely to be sufficient. Theseare localities where male employment is at present overwhelmingly dependenton coalmining and which are in many cases situated at some distance fromthe main urban centres or from centres of new industrial development withinthe region, so that access to the newly developing industries in the development areas as a whole will not be easy. While the areas concerned are limited,the numbers of people living and working in them are considerable.125. In such areas the Government therefore propose to take special measures over and above those for development areas as a whole. Therewill be extra inducements to attract industry to move into or expand in them. New industrial estates are planned at selected sites in South Wales,Durham and Northumberland, and consideration is also being given to theacquisition of further land for industrial development in Scotland ; the siteschosen, will serve many of the colliery districts threatened by closure.  Where
there are reasonable prospects of securing tenants, there will be a continuingbuilding programme of advance factories to replace those let. The Govern-ment are also prepared to make extra funds available for improving theinfrastructure of these areas and for other measures of assistance. immediate steps are being taken to authorise additional expenditure on roads in orderto improve local travel-to-work opportunities. Other use of these additional funds requires further study to ensure that the localities derive the maximum benefit from them ; it could include such objects as improving access to thearea and clearing derelict land. The Government are also setting in handa more searching and detailed study of the economic prospects and potential of these areas ; and into the possibility of additional measures. In these studies the Government will draw on the advice of the Regional Councils andlocal authorities.126. There are special problems arising from pit closures for the oldermen who will find it difficult to get employment elsewhere. The scope for transfer within the industry will necessarily become more limited for the older miners, while employment in other industries will often require travelor transfer away from isolated mining communities. As announced by theMinister of Power on 18th July, a scheme is being prepared whereby mine-workers who are 55 or over and who become redundant after that datethrough colliery closures will have their incomes supplemented for a periodof three years, subject to an age limit of 65, so that they can adjust them-selves to their new circumstances. This will cover the major proportionof those expected to suffer redundancy, and will assist both individuals andthe communities in which they live. The supplement will be based on previous earnings in the industry and will be conditional on a minimumqualifying period of service. It will be paid in addition to unemploymentbenefit and will be increased after the entitlement to unemployment benefitexpires, in order to maintain substantially the same total level of payment for unemployed men. The effect of the scheme will be that, in the majorityof cases, these redundant miners will be able to receive about 90 per cent,of their previous take-home pay for the three year period, but the actualpercentage will vary according to family circumstances and previous earnings.The scheme will also provide that the men will receive their mineworker&apos;pension at the end of this period, without waiting for the normal age of 65.The Government intend to ask Parliament to provide for payment by theExchequer of the whole cost of this additional assistance for mineworkersover 55 becoming redundant up to March, 1971. About 26,000 miners areexpected to benefit under the scheme, and the total cost is estimated to be 35 million.127. In order to facilitate the redeployment of mineworkers and other employees and thus help the elimination of uneconomic colliery capacity,the Exchequer makes grants under the Coal Industry Act, 1965, towardsthe cost of the benefits provided by the National Coal Board in respectof redundancy payments, loss of superannuation and employment prospects,removal and resettlement expenses, including housing, subsidised transport and supplementation of earnings for men transferred, and the maintenanceof social welfare and other benefits in kind. The estimated cost of thebenefits over the five years 1966-67 to 1970-71 was about  80 million, and
grants are payable in respect of half the Board&apos;s expenditure in excess ofan annual sum of  3-8 million, subject to a total limit for grants of  30million. Expenditure on these benefits in the year 1966-67 was approxi-mately  6 million. Taking account of the revised estimates of the numberof men likely to be affected by colliery closures and changes in the cost ofthe benefits, the Board&apos;s expenditure during the remaining period up to march, 1971, is now expected to be about  70 million. The Governmentwill ask Parliament for power to make grants to the Board not exceeding two-thirds of their expenditure on these benefits in each of the four years1967-68 to 1970-71, within a total limit of  45 million.Borrowing Powers of the National Coal Board128. Exchequer advances provide the principal means of borrowing bythe National Coal Board. Under the Coal Industry Act, 1965, the Board&apos;total outstanding borrowings after the capital reconstruction amounted to 545 million at March, 1965. The Act set the borrowing limit at  750million ; this limit was expected to meet the Board&apos;s borrowing requirementsuntil about March, 1971. The purposes for which the Board expected to need external finance within that limit were set out in the White Paper onthe Finances of the Coal Industry (Cmnd. 2805). The marketing difficultieswhich the industry has experienced since 1965 have been reflected in theBoard&apos;s financial position and borrowing requirements. The Board havenot been able to finance as much of their investment from internal resourcesas they had expected and the large increase this year in undistributed coalstocks has had to be financed by borrowings.129. At March, 1967, the Board&apos;s total outstanding long-term borrowingsamounted to  610 million. The Board&apos;s borrowings follow a seasonalpattern, rising in the summer and autumn when coal production exceeds sales to a peak in November or December, and falling in the winter when coalsales are at their highest. This year, borrowings to finance the exceptionalincrease in coal stocks have been superimposed on the normal seasonalincrease, with the result that the Board&apos;s total borrowings have risen sharplyand are already approaching the statutory limit of  750 million.130. In estimating the amounts that the Board are now likely to requireto borrow in the period up to March, 1971, it is necessary to have regardto the problems that will face the industry during the period of transition.The Governments decision that the rate of contraction of the industry should be moderated in that period may, despite the measures to increasecoal consumption, result in further additions to coal stocks. The level ofcolliery investment will be kept under close review to ensure that it is instep with developing fuel policy, but it may be some years before thisinvestment can be financed wholly from internal resources. The possibilitymust also be faced that increases in productivity may not be sufficient to offset increases in costs and that, unless coal prices are raised, the Boardmay incur deficits on revenue account. A general increase in coal prices would tend to accelerate the decline in the market for coal and might therefore be inconsistent with measures to support the demand for coal.Without prejudice to decisions that will need to be taken in the future inthe light of the policy for financing the nationalised industries and of the
criteria for prices and incomes policy, it is proposed to increase theprovision for financing deficits from  30 million under the 1965 Act to  50million.131. Having regard to the foregoing considerations, the Board&apos;s borrowingrequirements for the period to March, 1971, are estimated as follows:    million. Outstanding long-term borrowings March, 1967 ......      6102. Additional long-term borrowings 1967-68       ......       903. Provision for day-to-day and seasonal fluctuations in temporary borrowings for working capital    ......       704. Net capital investment in collieries and ancin 1968-69 to 1970-71    ......5. Additional coal stocks      ......6. Provision for deficits       ......7. All other contingencies    ......llary activities60255045950The Government will introduce legislation to raise the Board&apos;s borrowinglimit to  900 million, or such greater sum not exceeding  950 million asthe Minister may by order specify subject to the approval of the House ofCommons.
9.  Conclusion132. The post-war years have been characterised by rapid change in the energy sector. In coal, with the introduction of new, pioneering techniquesof mining and the re-organisation of the industry, productivity has risen by 50 per cent, over the last ten years. Oil has grown to become a majorsource of energy and the base of new and vitally important industries.Nuclear power made its commercial debut in Britain and is on its way tobecoming the principal fuel for new generating capacity. And now natural gas has been discovered in the North Sea on a scale which guarantees a fourth source of primary energy.133. For British industry this dynamic and vigorous pattern of develop-ment and change in the energy sector is of great significance because ofthe all-pervading impact of fuel costs on the economy. The continuingtechnical advances and improvement in efficiency in coal and oil and the emergence of nuclear power and natural gas are therefore developmentswholly to be welcomed for their promise of ample, efficient and competitivelypriced energy supplies.134. In great industries providing the livelihood of hundreds of thousands of people, rapid change and progress cannot be brought about without somepainful readjustment, sometimes affecting whole communities. The coalindustry has a fine record of successful adaptation to new methods and organisation as a result of the close and enlightened partnership of manage-ment and men and their joint recognition of the challenge facing them. Thedevelopment of nuclear power and the discovery of natural gas will allow the coal industry no respite in its continuing drive for greater efficiency.It must expect to lose markets to the newer fuels because of their inherentadvantages in ease of handling, cleanliness and price, and even if it were possible to arrest this change in the pattern of fuel supplies, it would be tothe disadvantage of the economy if the Government were to attempt to doso. But the economy would also suffer by too abrupt a decline in coal,which would put at risk the success of the industry&apos;s re-organisation andresult in needless hardship and waste.135. The Government have therefore sought to provide in their policy the conditions in which all the fuel industries will find incentive for themost vigorous further development and progress aimed at supplying industry with energy at the lowest possible cost in resources, while tempering the impact of this policy on the coal industry by transitional measures to assistit in its re-organisation. In framing these measures the Government havebeen at pains to avoid, to the maximum extent possible, distortion of thedesirable long-term pattern of development in the energy sector.136. The concentration in the White Paper on primary energy reflectsits dominating importance for fuel policy as a result of recent developments.The magnitude of these developments highlights the need to think of fuel policy as an evolving subject, requiring constant review and susceptible to continuous adjustment. This need arises not only from change withinthe energy sector itself but also from the impact of broader economic and social circumstances, themselves liable to change.  In their continuing review
of fuel policy the Government^ aim will be to make possible the supplyof energy at the lowest total cost to the community having regard to thewhole range of relevant considerations economic and social-and to national and regional economic policies.
Appendix ISTATISTICAL AND ECONOMIC ANALYSESIntroduction1. This Appendix describes briefly the aims, methods and results of themain statistical exercise carried out in the course of the review of fuel policy.As part of the normal continuing functions of the Ministry of Power,forecasts of future fuel demand and supplies have regularly been prepared,mainly for internal use. On this occasion, in view of the discontinuitybrought about by the prospect of large quantities of natural gas and economicnuclear power, it was decided to carry out a much more widely rangingexercise. New methods of statistical and economic analysis were introduced,designed to examine the implications of a wide range of assumptions about future trends in the fuel industries and in the economy.2. This exercise was carried out concurrently with separate but relatedstudies concerning the prospects for individual industries (on mining man-power and productivity, costs of nuclear power and other primary fuels atpower stations, patterns and rates of absorption of natural gas, and thebalance of the oil industry both at home and overseas). The method of operation had to allow for the results of these studies, and other new informa-tion, being fed in as the work went on. In particular, it was possible tomake a progressively better assessment as to the likely availability of natural gas from the North Sea, though it will be some years before the full extentof the reserves there can be gauged with any accuracy.3. A primary object of the exercise was to provide a basis for decidingon the best fuel policy at this particular time. Accordingly the statisticalexercise had to examine the effects of a variety of possible policy decisions.The Initial Assessments4. The broad aim of examining all possible lines of development andselecting the most economic is simple enough in concept, but its implement a-tion, even in simplified form, is immensely complicated. The demands forthe various forms of energy interact on each other to a major extent andthey are all affected also by outside influences, which cannot always bequantified precisely. To start the exercise at all it was necessary to make aconsiderable number of assumptions which were subject to validation andto correction as the work proceeded. For some factors a single value couldbe assumed (for any particular date); for others it was necessary to examinethe results of variations. The latter class of factor included items withingovernment control where the effect of different policies had to be examined.Fuel policy is operated by government through actions which affect theprice of fuels (such as taxation or the financial obligations fixed for the nationalised industries) or which affect availability (such as import control).5. The first step was to identify the area to be explored what were themain factors to be taken into account and within what ranges were theylikely to lie. Some of the principal unknowns on which assumptions had tobe made were:(a) the quantity of natural gas likely to be available from the North Sea ;the most economic method of absorption ; its price to the gas industry:
(b) the relative selling prices (including transport and other chargeswhere appropriate) of the various fuels :(c) the economic rate of development of nuclear power:(d) the rate and pattern of growth of the economy:(e) the level and pattern of protection for indigenous fuels.6. After consideration of the likely range of possibilities for each of these factors, the Ministry of Power made rough estimates of the range of demandfor each fuel. The estimation of these ranges involved the preparation ofa considerable number of fairly detailed sets of estimates, each designed tobe consistent from fuei to fuel, for various combinations of assumptions.7. The fuel industries* then provided estimates of their costs, based either on given estimates of demand or on their own estimates of demand related to the specified assumptions. The secondary fuel industries also suppliedcorresponding estimates of their requirements of primary fuel. after examining the replies, the Ministry selected a small number of combinationsof assumptions. Estimates of demand for these selected cases were madeas consistent as possible from fuel to fuel in discussion with the fuel industries,and the industries prepared corresponding estimates of the use of resources(costs, manpower and capital investment). In addition, the foreign exchangecosts involved were estimated by the Ministry.8. A summary of the Ministry^ estimates of inland energy demand for1970 and 1975 for these selected cases is given in Table C (&quot;the January,1967, estimates &quot;). The possible position in 1980 was also examined. Thefigures are very speculative and are not reproduced here, but they did notindicate any change in trend which would affect conclusions as to thedesirable path in earlier years. The differences in the assumptions betweenthe various cases in the table were as follows:Case   I This assumed immediate removal of the oil tax.Case II The oil tax was assumed to be 2d. a gallon throughout theperiod, with no special preference for coal at power stations.Case III The oil tax was assumed to be 4d. a gallon generally, but 6d.a gallon for power station use. (This case sought to quantifythe possible effect of a general increase in the oil tax, coupled with a virtual ban on new oil-fired power stations and minimum use of existing ones.)In each case, supplies of natural gas at an average of 1,000 million cubic feeta day (m.c.f.d.) were assumed for 1970 ; for 1975, the A alternative assumed2,000 m.c.f.d., the B alternative 6,000 m.c.f.d. The other principal assump-tions, common to all cases, were (a) that the gross domestic product would grow at an average rate of3 per cent, per annum, measured from 1964 ;(b) that the relativity between coal and oil prices in competitive sectorswould remain unchanged (apart from any tax changes);(c) that 10 per cent, of the total natural gas from the North Sea would go to power stations.* For petroleum, the industry provided estimates of demand on the basis of the specifiedassumptions. Subsequently the Ministry of Power compiled its own estimates of costs,manpower and capital investment, in consultation with a number of leading companies.
Table CEstimates of Inland Demand for Energy on Varying Assumptions(&quot; The January, 1967, Estimates &quot;)	1966 (Actual)	1970			1975					Assumptions Natural gas (North Sea)      ...       m.c.f.d. Natural gas (North Sea) (energy uses) m.t.c.e.		1,000 12-5			---	---A - -2,000 25		---	---B--6,000 75	---Oil tax per gallon      ............		Case I Nil	Case II 2d.	Case III 4d. (6d.)	Case I Nil	Case II 2d.	Case III 4d. (6d.)	Case I Nil	Case II 2d.	Case III 4d. (6d.)Estimates of demand for energy Gas sales: million therms Domestic     ...      ............ Industrial     .........      ...... Commercial and other      ......... Power stations       ............	2,147 935 574	3,550 1,530 670 350	3,450 1,470 630 350	3,250 1,390 560 350	4,900 2,300 800 700	4,600 2,160 740 700	4,200 2,050 650 700	6,000 9,800 1,600 2,100	6,000 9,800 1,600 2,100	6,000 9,800 1,600 2,100Total    ...............	3,656	6,100	5,900	5,550	8,700	8,200	7,600	19,500	19,500	19,500Electricity sales: thousand million kWh. Domestic and farms         ......... Industrial     ............... Transport    ............ Commercial and other     .........	63 0 67-9 2-5 27-4	76 89 3 38	78 89 3 38	81 89 3 39	109 118 3 55	113 118 3 59	117 118 3 62	95 118 3 51	95 118 3 54	95 118 3 57Total    ...............	160-8	206	208	212	285	293	300	267	270	273Fuel use: m.t.c.e. Coal and coke    ............ Oil.................. Nuclear and hydro-electricity   ...... Natural gas        ............	69-2 12-4 10-2	69 18 17 1	72 16 17 1	78 11 17 1	71 25 37 3	74 25 37 3	91 12 37 3	60 24 35 9	63 21 36 9	76 9 36 9Total    ...............	91-8	105	106	107	136	139	143	128	129	130
Coal: million tons										Power stations       ............	68-7	69	72	78	71	74	91	60	63	76Gasworks    ...............	16-9	6	5	5	1	 	 	_	- :_	_Gas ovens    ............	24-8	24	24	24	23	23	23	23	23	23Industry      ...............	25-2	16i	19	211	9	10	14	3	5	8Domestic     ...............	27-5	21	21	21*	15	151	16	141	141	141Other inland...............	11-6	7	8	9	54	6	61	41	5	51total	174-7	1431	149	159	1241	1281	1501	105	1101	127Exports       ...............	2-8	3	3	3		14	14	14	14	14Total    ...............	177-5	1461	152	162	126	130	152	1061	112	128-1Oil: m.t.c.e.										Power stations       ......     ......	12-4	18	16	11	25	25	12	24	21	9Gasworks    ...............	8-4	74	7	5i	7	7	41	 		Road and air transport     .........	30-0	37	37	37	461	461	461	461	461	461Refinery fuel...............	7-8	10i	10	91	121	12	101	91	91	71Industry      ...............	36-0	43	41	39	50	481	451	25	23	20Domestic     ...............	3-7	4	4	4	5	5	5	4	4	other inland...............	13-4	18	17	16	191	181	171	18	17	16Total    .........     ...     ...	111-7	138	132	122	1651	1621	1411	127	121	103Total inland demand for energy: m.t.c.e.										Coal..................	174-7	1431	149	159	1241	1281	1501	105	1101	127Oil    ..................	111-7	138	132	122	1651	1621	1411	127	121	103Nuclear and hydro electricity      ......	10-2	17	17	17	37	37	37&quot;	35	36	36Natural gas  ...     ............	1-1	14	14	14	28	27	27	77	77	77Total    ...............	297-7	3124-	312	312	355	355	356	344	3441	343N.B.-Although the total energy figures are shown to be lower where the natural gas supply is high (alternative B), this does not mean that consumedwould have less useful heat. In fact in alternative B a slightly higher requirement for useful energy has been assumed, but it requires a lower primary fuexinput. 1toCO
9. The different estimates in Table C were designed to illustrate the effects on demand fuel by fuel (and thence on the use of resources to meet thedemand) of varying the assumptions as set out in paragraph 8 in respect oftwo factors the quantity of North Sea natural gas to be absorbed into thesystem and the level throughout the period of the protection for coal, whichwas represented in the statistical exercise by taking alternative rates of oiltax. These two factors were selected for this special initial scrutiny becauseof their particular importance for the review. The first was a major factor of exceptional uncertainy at the time these estimates were being prepared.The second was the principal variable relative to policy decisions.10. The alternative assumptions for 1975 reflect the extent of the uncertainty as to how much natural gas might become available from theNorth Sea. The estimates of total gas sales, sector by sector, were providedby the gas industry for each combination of assumptions; they represented the best estimates available at that time from the concurrent exercise on the absorption of natural gas. The Ministry of Power had the task of decidingby how much earlier estimates of requirements for other fuels needed to be altered to allow for the greater use of gas. Data on which to base such estimates were scanty as there was no previous experience of a comparablenature in the United Kingdom, and data from abroad were only partlyappropriate. In general, for those sectors of final consumption wheregas is in competition with other fuels, the estimated sales of the competingfuels were reduced proportionately to the extent necessary to compensate forthe extra gas. In most sectors the reduction made in the competing fuels wasprecisely equivalent to the increase in gas, but in the domestic sector it wasconsidered that the lower prices overall would lead to some increase in total consumption of useful energy. It was assumed that half the average saving in expenditure on fuel (allowing for the switch from one fuel to another whichwas expected) would be applied to buy extra fuel for space and water heating ;and that the other half would be spent on needs other than fuel, includingthe new appliances needed to convert from one fuel to another. In theindustrial sector gas is only in competition with electricity to a limited extent,and the adjustments were restricted to fuels other than electricity.11. To assess the effects of variation in the rate of oil tax, some measureof the price elasticities of the separate fuels in response to a sudden major change in relative prices had to be determined. This elasticity is of complexform because fuel consumption depends on the appliances in use, whichchange only gradually over a period of years. Previous experience providedlittle guide, particularly for such a wide range. The system adopted by theMinistry was to calculate the relative proportions of demand for coal and oilrespectively, in each sector of final consumption affected, for any given coal/oil price ratio by rough interpolation or extrapolation between the assessedproportion in two particular cases the first assumed the continuation of current trends, implying that oil&apos;s already appreciable advantage over coal for most uses would increase slightly ; the second assumed that the pricerelationship would swing back to a level at which it was judged that therelative proportions would remain the same as now. In the calculations itwas assumed that the effect of a price change would become progressivelyless the further one moved from the break-even point. The effects on the gas and electricity industries of a change in oil prices are also complex.  Oil
feedstocks are currently a major item in the gas industry&apos;s costs and a risein the price of oil for gas making would tend to raise the price of gas. Theeffect will progressively diminish as natural gas is brought in. Oil is a smaller element in the electricity industry&apos;s costs, and the effect on electricityprices of a rise in the price of oil would be much less than the direct increasein the prices of competing oil products to consumers. Electricity sales to domestic and other non-industrial users were therefore assumed to benefit from the overall effect of higher oil prices.12. For a number of important factors, provisional single figures wereinserted in the January, 1967, estimates. The intention was to assess the likely sensitivity of results to variations of these other factors with the objectof concentrating further work on those which were likely to have a markedeffect on decisions. It would have been quite impracticable, and of no value,to have carried through a full range of calculations for each of the manyhundreds, or perhaps thousands, of possible combinations of assumptions ;it would not even have been possible for the industries to provide estimates of the use of the various resources to meet the demand for a great number ofdifferent combinations. The assumptions used for the two factors examined in the January, 1967, estimates covered wide ranges and were intended togive an indication of the effects of intermediate values.Other Factors to be Examined13. There were four main factors for which it had been thought that a detailed examination of alternative assumptions might be required, but ithas not been necessary to carry this out. The methods of estimating theeffects of a change in the oil tax, as described in paragraph 11, were alsoappropriate for judging the effects of variations in the relative prices of coal and oil (though the effect of a progressive change in prices would be less thanthat of an immediate change in tax); the work undertaken on this subjectled to the conclusion that the pattern of demand for the various fuels wouldnot be greatly affected by any likely variation in these price relativities.Separate work on nuclear power costs (referred to in* paragraph 2) made it possible to dispense with alternative assumptions as to how much nuclear power there would be by 1975, and to work on the basis that the existing programmes would be fulfilled. Scrutiny indicated that the rate of interest on new investment, within accepted limits, was unlikely to have any significant effort on the demand forecasts. As regards the rate of growth of the economy,earlier work had given a measure of the effect of alternative assumptions andhad indicated that policy was unlikely to be very sensitive to variations inin this factor. One particular reason for this view was that, although in conditions of fast expansion the total demand for fuel would be higher, coal&apos;sproportional share might be lower, if only because the industry wouldprobably have to pay higher wages to retain the necessary manpower, withadverse effect on prices.Selection of the Most Desirable Policy14. The most desirable course of policy, other things being equal, wouldbe the course which held out prospects for meeting the demand for energyat the lowest cost. But qualifications to this general statement included thefollowing:(a) As has already been noted, some of the assumptions made con-cerned factors (such as the size of natural gas deposits in the North61
Sea) which are not, or not mainly, within the control of the Govern-ment, and for which there was insufficient data on which to basea reliable estimate. In considering the most desirable course ofpolicy, a view has to be taken of the possible range of the factor inquestion, and, if the choice of the best policy is sensitive to wherein the range eventually proves right, as to the likelihood of anyparticular value of the factor. It may sometimes be best to selecta course of policy which will give good results whatever the valueof a particular factor, rather than one which will give the best resultsfor one particular value but poor results for some other values.(b) In certain circumstances, the money cost of a particular resourcemay not be an accurate measure of its real cost to the nation. Forexample, if the displacement of miners adds to unemployment in the short term, manpower at marginal collieries may be regarded ascosting less in national terms than the wages actually paid. Allow-ance must therefore be made, in this and other contexts, for thepossibility of a divergence between money costs and resource costs.It is not always practicable to put precise figures on these differences,but the concept can nevertheless be applied by taking a range ofassumptions and comparing the outcome in terms of the total resourcecost of meeting demands for energy. The results of this approachhave not yet been worked out in detail, but the principle has been an important aid in reaching the decisions outlined in the white paper.(c) Two fuels which both give the same useful heat to a consumer maynot have the same value to him. One may be more expensive touse than the other, because, for example, the appliances requiredcost more, or stocking costs more, or labour costs of use are higher ;or the consumer may simply prefer one to the other, perhaps becauseof reasons of its greater convenience, and may be willing to pay forhis preference. In an attempt to quantify these differences in value,the concept of &quot; convenience factors&quot; was introduced; theseexpressed the premium which one fuel could command over another of equal calorific value in competition with it. Work on this conceptis still in the early stages ; its practical application raises awkwardproblems which have yet to be solved.15. Qualitative assessments of the importance to be attached to the various factors affecting the desirable level of protection made it possible to arriveat interim conclusions for the purpose of the White Paper without going through a whole range of detailed calculations. The appropriate level ofprotection for coal in the longer term was judged unlikely to be higher than is represented by an oil tax at the present rate. Not only was the present level of protection as high as seemed likely to be justifiable in the longer term for general balance of payments reasons, but the difficulties of re-employing the displaced miners should be surmountable in the longer term and the economy should gain substantially by their moving to more productiveemployment; the avoidable costs of coal production would not be very much less than total accounting costs in the longer term ; and the costs to the economy of a high level of protection were substantial.
The April, 1967, Estimates K16. In the light of the conclusions outlined in paragraph 15, attention was concentrated on the practical problems which would arise if coal demandwere to decline at the rate expected with oil tax continuing at 2d. a gallon.Case II of the January, 1967, estimates was no longer entirely satisfactory forthis purpose because events had moved on, much more being known aboutthe potential availability of North Sea gas. It now seemed likely that,000 m.c.f.d. might be available by 1970, rather than the 1,000 m.c.f.d.assumed in the January, 1967, estimates. This was more than the gas indusrty was likely to be able to use in its traditional markets, and presented com-plicated problems of reassessment of demand patterns; in the separateexercise on the absorption of natural gas, discussed in Chapter 2 and appendix II, studies were made of the desirability of burning natural gas in power stations and the bulk fuel market.17. To illuminate the problems arising from a continuation of the oil tax at 2d. a gallon (the rate prior to the imposition and subsequentconsolidation of the 10 per cent, surcharge) and the more rapid absorption of natural gas, the Ministry of Power provided the new estimates set out inTable D (&quot; the April, 1967, estimates &quot;). These estimates formed one of themain bases for discussion at the Minister of Power&apos;s Conference with the chairmen of the nationalised fuel industries in May. They are on the basisof a 2d. a gallon tax on oil. The principal changes in assumptions ascompared with Case II of Table C are as follows:(a) The natural gas assumed to be absorbed by 1970 is double theprevious assumption. For 1975 a single assumption of 4,000 m.c.f.d.has been used, instead of 2,000 m.c.f.d. and 6,000 m.c.f.d. respectivelyin the A and B alternatives.(b) The proportion of natural gas going to power stations has been taken as 30 per cent, in 1970 and 25 per cent, in 1975. In the January, 1967,estimates 10 per cent, was assumed throughout.
Table DEstimates of Inland Demand for Energy on Specified Assumptions(&quot; The April, 1967,	estimates &quot;	)		1966	1970*	1975	(actual)		Assumptions re natural gas (North Sea)			Total      ............       m.c.f.d.		2,000	4,000Energy uses      .........        m.t.c.e.		23-1	47-iEstimates of demand for energy			Gas sales: million therms			Domestic       ...............	2,147	3,600	5,100Industrial      ...............	935	1,900	3,800Commercial and other        .........	574	750	1,000Power stations...............	-	2,050	3,400Total	3,656	8,300	13,300Electricity sales: thousand million kWh.			Domestic and farms............	63-0	78	107Industrial      ...............	67-9	89	118Transport      ...............	2-5	3	3Commercial and others......	27-4	37	57Total      ...............	160-8	207	285Fuel use: m.t.c.e.			Coal and coke      ............	69-2	65(68)	65Oil    ..................	12-4	16(13)	20Nuclear and hydro-electricity     ......	10-2	16	37Natural gas...............		9	14Total      ......     .........	91-8	106	136Coal: million tons			Power stations...............	68-7	65(68)	65Gasworks      ...............	16-9	3	 Coke ovens......      ...      ......	24-8	24	23Industry        ...............	25-2	18	9Domestic       ...............	27-5	21	15Other inland...............	11-6	8	6Total      ...      ...      ...      ......	174-7	139(142)	118Exports..................	2-8	3	2Total      ...............	177-5	142(145)	120Oil: m.t.c.e.			Power stations...............	12-4	16(13)	20Gasworks      ...............	8-4	6	3Road and air transport       .........	30-0	37	46*Refinery fuel...............	7-8	10	11&quot;Industry        ...............	36-0	40	42-1Domestic       ...............	3-7	4	other inland...............	13-4	17	18Total      ......      .........	111-7	130(127)	146Total inland demand for energy: m.t.c.e.			Coal    ...............	174-7	139(142)	118Oil      ..................	111-7	130(127)	146Nuclear and hydro-electricity        ......	10-2	16	37Natural gas    ...............	1-1	25	49Total      ............   .....	297-7	310	350* In 1970 alternative estimates are given of coal and oil usage at power stations. The firstfigures assumed no discrimination against oil other than the tax of 2d. a gallon. Thebracketted figures assumed a continuation of the current short-term arrangements which provided for an additional loading against oil.
Chart 12Pattern of Primary Fuel Consumption: United Kingdom
The Outcome of the Exercise18. The practical problems human, social and economic of contractionin the coal industry had been very much in mind since the exercise began.At the Fuel Policy Conference in May the issue was sharpened: assuming that the estimates of total demand for each primary fuel in Table D werecorrect (and they received a broad measure of agreement), could the consequentcontraction of the coal industry be achieved without risk of damage to itsmorale and management which might do disproportionate harm to theindustry&apos;s future contribution to the economy? Following discussion at theConference, the Government concluded that the contraction of the coalindustry to the level for 1975 envisaged by the figures should be manageable ;but they accepted the advice of the National Coal Board that the rapidrun down in the period to 1970 would cause unmanageable difficulties forthe industry. They considered that it would also cause unacceptable socialhardship and serious difficulties for the economy in this early period. Thedecision was taken to try to hold the demand for coal by 1970 at around155 million tons if this was practicable and necessary.19. In the light of this political and managerial judgment, it was necessaryto analyse and quantify the implications and consequences in financial andeconomic terms of holding coal demand at this level. The only practicableway of supporting demand for coal to this extent was to use more than expected at power stations (and possibly also rather more at gasworks). this meant that there would be less scope for using natural gas at power stations and also implied a considerable degree of special preference for coal overoil there. Table E summarises the pattern of inland demand that may resultin 1970 if demand for coal is sustained at 155 million tons, including 3 million tons for exports.Pattern of inland demand in 1970 adjusted for contingent support for coal at 155 million tons including 3 million tons for exportsThese figures assume a 2d. tax rate on oil and a 3 per cent, per annumgrowth in gross domestic product from now on; and that additional coal would be used at power stations and the extra cost of this arrangement would be met from public funds.Table EEstimates of demand m.t.c.e.Coal: Power stationsNuclear and hydro-electricity ...Natural gas: Power stations   ...Oil:   Power stationsOtherOther1966(Actual)68-7106-012-499-310-2197076761111416215Other1-1Total inland demand for energyElectricity sales (thousand million KWh)Gas sales (million therms)   ......297-7310160-83,6562056,700** For energy use.  Includes natural gas supplied to power stations.66
Primary Fuel Consumption in the United Kingdom
20. It is to be noted that the adjustments relate to a transitional stage in fuel policy evolution. The revised demand estimates for 1970 in Table Ereflect a particular constraint which operates in the next few years, say,between now and 1970-71. They do not, therefore, affect the 1975 figures in Table D. Chart 13 shows the estimated primary fuel use in 1970 and 1975,compared with 1966.21. Chart 14 illustrates the changes in total energy demand by sector inthe period up to 1975 and compares them with the corresponding changesbetween 1957 and 1966. The absence of any significant change in thethermal value of energy used by domestic consumers throughout the period is the result of increasing efficiency in the use of domestic fuels ; higher standards of comfort in the home and greater use of appliances are beingsecured without any marked increase in the total fuel supplied. The sameapplies, to varying degrees, in other sectors for example, the principalreason why the growth in transport fuel requirements has been slower overthe past decade than it is expected to be in the years ahead is the rapiddecline in the last few years in coal use, at low efficiency, on the railways.22. Chart 15 illustrates in very broad terms the principal features of theestimates of manpower and investment requirements for the fuel industriesthat emerged from the calculations mentioned in paragraph 7. Thesetentative estimates do no more than give a very approximate indication ofthe probable pattern of the needs for these resources in the energy sectorup to 1975.23. Much more remains to be done on work which has had to be lefton one side while problems of immediate practical importance were dealtwith, but the analyses already carried out leave little doubt as to the validity of the decisions already based on them though the uncertaintieswhich cannot yet be resolved underline the need for flexibility in fuel policy.Future Developments24. Trends of development in any major sector of the economy call forcontinuous review and study and for periodic major reassessment. Thecurrent review has, at one and the same time, offered an opportunity todevelop and apply new techniques of analysis and shown the need for their further elaboration. A major new development in the technique of analysisis now in train. With the help of experts from the fuel industries, theMinistry of Power is engaged in constructing a series of mathematical modelsof the fuel economy and the results of the work will be incorporated in thegeneral body of quantitative analysis as it reaches fruition. The gestationof new techniques such as these is a long process and it will take time tocreate a fully integrated series of mathematical models which will successfullysimulate the activities of the fuel economy and relationships with the economy generally. Concurrently with the work on detailed computable models, togive the best presentation of the fuel economy consistent with the information and facilities which can be made available, the aim is to produce greatlysimplified computable models which can be constructed relatively quickly and got into operation, however crudely, in a matter of months rather thanyears.  The results from such simplified models may not prove sufficiently
Energy Demand by Sectorsprimary   fuel requirements  by  fuel producersdemand    by    final   consumers    of    energy   (heat   supplied    basis)*-FOR   DEFINITIONS   SEE   PAGE. 17  OF THE MINISTRY   OF    POWER STATISTICAL  DIGEST   1966.
reliable for practical application, but it is hoped by this means to anticipatesome of the teething troubles which will inevitably be met in the more detailed work. The simplified models may also help in assessing the significance of various factors and indicating how far they need to be takeninto account in detailed models. The analyses carried out in the course ofthe current review, and previously, have already provided an insight intothe possibilities and problems involved in work of this nature.25. The structure of the main model, both in the detailed and simplifiedversions, consists of a separate supply sub-model for each of the principalfuel industries, linked to each other and to a demand sub-model in such away as to express their interactions on each other. The aim will be toobtain such answers as the demand for each fuel and the related costs and prices, investment and manpower, on the basis of information (or assumptions)as to the prospective state of the economy and as regards government policy on such matters as taxes and subsidies and financial objectives for the nationalised industries.

Appendix IINATURAL GASAnalysis of Problems of Determining the Optimum Rate of Depletingthe North Sea Gas Fields1. North Sea natural gas is a valuable national asset with an important contribution to make to the economy. Substantial reserves have been provedbut, while there is every reason to believe that further discoveries will be forthcoming, there will inevitably be uncertainty for some time to come about the total amounts of natural gas which the United Kingdom area ofthe North Sea holds. In spite of this uncertainty, however, the Governmenthave had to come to terms with the problem of analysing the rate at whichideally this new resource should be used up. This Appendix describes ina simplified and condensed form the background to the Governmentsanalysis.2. A point of clarification is needed on what a particular &quot;rate ofdepletion &quot; implies in practice. In a typical case, production from a gas fieldis built up over the first few years, while the initial wells are being drilledand pipelines and other facilities installed, to a &quot; plateau &quot;. As the gas inthe field is depleted, output tends to decline and can only be maintained atthe plateau level by drilling additional wells and installing compressors.Eventually, after a period of years, it becomes uneconomic to drill morewells and output gradually tails off. Production will normally be planned to give a certain level of output on the plateau which can be expressed as a proportion of the recoverable reserves (recoverable reserves may be no more than 70 to 80 per cent, of the gas actually in place). Within limits,the output, and so the length of life of the field, can be varied by drillingmore or fewer wells and installing pipelines and ,other facilities to match the desired off-take. A field would be described as having a twenty-yeardepletion period if its annual output on the plateau were one-twentieth ofthe recoverable reserves, but this level of production might in practice bemaintained for only about twelve years, though gas would flow over a spanof thirty years or more, including the build-up and tail-off periods. Similarly,a field designed to produce one-thirtieth of the recoverable reserves annuallymight only maintain this level of output for twenty years or so, while yieldingsome gas over a total period of around forty years. To say, as in para-graph 13, that with 25X1012 cubic feet of recoverable reserves the plateauproduction level might be 3,000 million cubic feet a day is to imply thatthe depletion period would be 20 to 25 years, but the plateau level wouldbe maintained for less and total production for a longer time.3. The rate of depletion is an important issue only in the case of a natural resource the reserves of which are limited and for which there is noclose substitute available at a comparable cost. In the United States, the ratio of proved reserves to annual production of natural gas is at present about 17:1. But there, new reserves are continually being discovered andit would not be prudent at this stage to assume that the United Kingdom&apos;part of the North Sea will be as prolific a source of gas as North America.
Since there is also no firm prospect that either manufactured gas or importednatural gas could match our North Sea gas in price, the depletion issue is relevant to our situation.4. As to the production side, there are technical and economic limitationsto the rate at which fields can be depleted, but generally the maximumtechnically efficient rate would be faster than the optimum economic ratedetermined by the balance between discounted costs and discounted revenues.While there is no single optimum depletion period applicable to all fields,economic considerations do not favour a very long depletion period because it would leave some of the gas reserves unused, and producing no return,until far into the future. But whatever plateau production level is chosen,there are clear advantages from the production and distribution point ofview in having a rapid build-up to that level. The pipelines and other equipment needed to bring the gas into use have to be large enough to takesupplies at the plateau level of output and the sooner they are used to full capacity the better.5. Turning to the markets, the sooner the gas is brought into use, the sooner the benefits in reduced fuel costs are realised. However, as noted inparagraph 19, the savings in resources are different in different markets. the assessment of the resource savings can only give a broad indication of theirpossible scale. It involves complex judgments and calculations of theresource costs, over many years ahead, of the fuels that would be displacedby natural gas and those that would be a substitute for it when the reserves are exhausted. These calculations involve attempting to allocate resourcecosts to some. oil products which are produced jointly with others in therefining process. However, the analysis suggested that the savings wouldbe substantial where natural gas replaced town gas, intermediate in thosemarkets where it can command a moderate premium over oil, and small inthe bulk market. This conclusion, therefore, argues,in favour of reserving the gas for the premium markets in preference to the bulk market. but because of the present size and nature of the premium markets, this would inevitably mean a rather slow build-up and probably too slow a depletionrate.6. Thus, there are conflicting considerations. The approach adopted wasto attempt to calculate how the resource savings could be maximised.Beyond a certain point in time, the greater resource savings obtainable fromreserving the gas for use in premium markets will clearly be worth less, whendiscounted to a present value, than the savings from the bulk use of gasnow or in the next few years. At present, it is only possible to quantifysome of the factors which must be brought into account-and even then only within a substantial margin of error. The potential growth of traditional,&quot; semi-premium &quot; and non-premium markets for gas has to be assessed (thiswill depend on the selling price of the gas, which in turn will partly dependon the price paid by the gas industry to the producers); assumptions haveto be made about the price of natural gas over the years and at different rates of use ; and, if the period of depletion extends very far into the future,the possibility that technological progress might provide a cheaper substitute for natural gas in at least some of its markets has to be borne in mind.However, accepting the need for qualification in the light of the great
uncertainties, the broad conclusion was that something over twice the levelof the reserves so far discovered would need to be assured before, from thepoint of view of resource savings, it would be desirable to sell the gasextensively to the bulk market.7. There are, however, other important considerations which could affectthis conclusion. The importance of load factor and the complexitiesinvolved are mentioned in paragraphs 20 and 21 ; there is the question of how likely it is that more gas will be found in the United Kingdom part ofthe North Sea and of the availability of natural gas abroad, since importednatural gas might be the cheapest alternative to indigenous natural gas ; andthere is the value of a rapid build-up to the chosen depletion rate in giving an incentive to further exploration which would both increase the information about the ultimate reserves and, it is to be hoped, add to our resources of gas. Also, the introduction of natural gas has to be seen against the widerbackground of fuel policy as a whole, its effect on other fuels, and its value to the economy.8. With so many uncertainties, the analysis could only be directed to determining the immediate course of action for the absorption of natural gason the knowledge available and on conservative assumptions about future developments. Firm conclusions which may be drawn now are that the rapidintroduction of natural gas into existing and new premium and semi-premiummarkets will reduce costs and save foreign exchange ; and that sales to thebulk energy market will improve load factor and assist the rapid build-upin supplies, and so help to secure a low price. On present knowledge of theNorth Sea reserves, however, deliberate encouragement of bulk sales beyond this would not be justifiable if they would be at the expense of premiummarkets.9. As a general guideline at this stage, the greatest gain to the economy will be obtained by a policy of rapid absorption, with most of the gas goingto premium markets (where it would largely be displacing oil) and some bulksales to make possible a rapid build-up of supplies to the most economicaldepletion rate. This will mean some displacement of coal by natural gas inthe bulk energy market, but the coal markets that will be lost in this way would in all probability fall to oil if natural gas were not available.
Annex to Appendix IINatural Gas in Other CountriesIn some overseas countries-particularly in the United States natural gas has been widely used for some time. In none of them is there a perfectparallel to our own situation but their experience in the build-up of supplies,depletion rates and pattern of demand is worth noting when considering ourown absorption strategy.United States of America2. The beginnings of the natural gas industry in the United States date from the early nineteenth century when natural gas was first discovered.For many years its use was confined to the localities in which it was foundbecause of the lack of means to transport it over long distances. With thedevelopment in the 1930&apos;s of large-diameter steel pipelines capable of operating at high pressures, it became possible to transmit the gas to marketsaway from the producing fields. Since the last war growth has been veryfast: whereas in 1945 natural gas provided less than 13 per cent, of thecountry&apos;s energy consumption, it now accounts for over one-third.3. The United States is thy world&apos;s largest producer of natural gas, witha production of about 50,000 million cubic feet a day. Proved recoverablereserves have almost doubled since 1945 and it has been estimated that future discoveries may be two to five times the reserves so far found. Ofthe amount marketed, nearly 60 per cent, is consumed in industry and about one-fifth of this is used in power stations. The domestic market now takesover 30 per cent, of marketed production.4. Because of the long distances over which gas is piped, the load factorat which gas is taken is of particular importance. To even out seasonalchanges in demand, underground storage of gas has been developed on alarge scale and nearly three hundred storages are now in use. In addition,gas is sold to some large consumers on an interruptible basis ; this allowssupplies to be cut off or reduced in winter when&apos;demand from otherconsumers is at its maximum.Holland5. The discovery in 1959 of vast reserves in the province of Groningenhas made Holland potentially the largest producer of natural gas in western europe. Prior to this discovery, town gas was supplied by a large numberof separate undertakings, the gas being manufactured, or purchased fromcoke ovens, refineries and some small natural gas fields. For the bringing into use of the new reserves in Groningen, a new organisation, Gasunie, was established, responsible for constructing the natural gas transmission networkand for purchasing and supplying the gas to the undertakings and to large industrial consumers. Consumers&apos; appliances are being converted touse supplies of natural gas as it becomes available ; by the end of 1966 about70 per cent, of the two and a half million consumers had been changed over.6. Deliveries into the natural gas grid began at the end of 1963 and lastyear totalled nearly 3,500 million cubic metres (about 350 m.c.f.d.), or  per cent, of total energy consumption.   Internal sales are expected to
increase fivefold; by the mid-1970&apos;s. Because the reserves are so large, parthas been allocated for export and contracts have been made with France,Belgium and Germany to supply quantities which will total over 20,000million cubic metres a year (2,000 m.c.f.d.).France7. Most of the indigenous natural gas supplies are at present obtainedfrom the Lacq field in the south-west of France ; further deposits of gas haverecently been found in this area. Although the Lacq field was discovered in1951, the large amounts of sulphur in the gas created technical problems and commercial exploitation did not start until 1957. Production of de-sulphurised natural gas is about 5,000 million cubic metres a year (500m.c.f.d.). This is over 90 per cent, of the total production of natural gasand represents about 5 per cent, of France&apos;s energy consumption.8. Nearly half the production is sold to consumers in the south-west,including a few large industrial consumers and a power station established in the vicinity of Lacq. In order to achieve as rapidly as possible a build-upto the optimum rate of production, it was necessary to seek markets in themore industrialised parts of France, and more than 1,000 miles of new pipe-lines were constructed by the nationalised gas industry, Gaz de France, tosupply the north-west and the Paris and Lyons areas. These pipelines areleased to Compagnie Francaise du Methane, which is jointly owned byGaz de France and the state-controlled producing company at Lacq, andthey supply both the distribution networks of Gaz de France and largeindustrial consumers.9. To achieve a rapid build-up, large amounts were sold initially to power stations but, as demand from other consumers increased, supplies to power stations were reduced and the gas so released has been used to meetthe growing requirements of the gas industry and large industrial consumers.At first the gas industry used natural gas mainly for enriching or reforminginto town gas, but a programme to convert all the consumers to direct supply is being undertaken and about one-third of its six and a half million con-sumers have so far been changed over to natural gas. Gaz de France nowtakes over half the gas transmitted by Compagnie Fraricaise du Methane.10. Indigenous supplies of natural gas are being supplemented by imports.Since 1965, liquefied natural gas has been imported from Algeria and anagreement has recently been concluded for larger quantities. The firstdeliveries of gas from Holland are due this year.Italy11. Natural gas was first discovered in the Po Valley in 1946 and, although in recent years gas has been found in other parts of Italy, this area stillprovides most of the country&apos;s production of about 8,800 million cubic metresa year (about 880 m.c.f.d.), which accounts for 10 per cent, of the total energyconsumption. The conventional gas industry in northern Italy was small and,in order to exploit as rapidly as possible this indigenous supply of energy,pipelines were laid to the industrial centres there and the gas was sold mainly to industrial consumers and power stations. By 1955, production had reached
3,600 million cubic metres a year, of which more than 90 per cent, wasconsumed, in industry. The proportion taken for non-industrial purposes has,however, been increasing and now represents over 25 per cent. changes made in recent years in industrial tariffs have aimed to encourage themaximum use of supplies in premium uses.12. The demand for gas in northern Italy can no longer be satisfied fromthe Po Valley fields and a contract has been made for the import of liquefiedgas from Libya. Discussions on the provision of additional supplies are alsotaking place with other countries.
Appendix IIINUCLEAR POWER COSTS1. Following the encouraging tenders in 1965 for the Advanced Gas-CooledReactor (A.G.R.) station being built at Dungeness, which is the first station in the seoond nuclear power programme for commissioning in 1970-75:, theGovernment announced in the 1965 White Paper* that a total of 8,000megawatts (MW) of nuclear capacity might be built under this programme.Since then the Central Electricity Generating Board have received tenders for Hinkley Point &quot; B &quot;, the second station in the programme, and the Southof Scotland Electricity Board for a station at Hunterston. In the UnitedStates there has been a massive increase in the rate of ordering of nuclear power stations. In view of these developments, a fresh examination of theeconomics of the second nuclear power programme and also of nuclearcosts in the longer term has been undertaken.Second Nuclear Power programme . Table F shows the estimates of nuclear and conventional generatingcosts per kWh given in the 1965 White Paper and the Central electricity generating Board&apos;s latest estimates. The figures include the royalty payable to the Atomic Energy Authority on A.G.R. nuclear stations of 0-014d. perkWh and have been calculated on the basis of the &quot; ground rules &quot; used bythe Central Electricity Generating Board in making comparisons of gene-rating costs a 20 year amortisation period for nuclear stations and 30 years for conventional stations, 1\ per cent, interest rate (and 5^- per cent, for interest during construction), a constant life-time load factor of 75 per cent.,and a&apos;credit of  2 a gram for plutonium.Table FGenerating Costs of Nuclear and Conventional Power Stations1967 1965\pence per kWhNuclearDungeness &quot; B &quot;         ......	......     0-52	0-47Hinkley Point &quot; B &quot;     ......	......     0-48	&apos;-Coal		Cottam   ............	......     0-53	0-54Drax      ............	......     0-56	0-52Oil		Pembroke (with tax)   ......	......     0-53	0-52,,       (without tax)	......      0-42	0-41t Paragraph 68 of Cmnd. 2798 (apart from Hinkley Point &quot; B&quot;, which was ordered in1967). The figure for Dungeness &quot; B &quot; has been increased to include a royalty payment tothe A.E.A. of 0-014d. per kWh.3. The total generating cost of Dungeness &quot; B &quot; is now expected to be0-05d. per kWh higher than the 1965 estimates. This increase is mainly theresult of including further items in the expected construction cost, but thecost of the reactor &quot; island &quot; or purely nuclear plant has not increased apart* Cmnd. 2798, paragraph 70.
from inflation. The estimated generating cost of Drax has risen by aboutOQ4d. per kWh as a result of the increase in coal costs in April, 1966, andrevised estimates of capital costs. There has been little change since 1965in the estimated generating costs of Pembroke and Cottam, but these stations were ordered in 1963 and 1964 respectively, and their costs do not give an accurate guide to the costs of stations ordered now, for which constructioncosts would be higher. The estimated cost of Hinkley Point &quot; B&quot; islower than that of Dungeness &quot; B &quot;, and there are good grounds for believ-ing that there will be further cost reductions in subsequent A.G.R. stations.By 1975 their generating costs are expected to approach those of a conven-tional station using untaxed oil. These cost reductions would come frommiscellaneous design and engineering improvements, from improvements in fuel technology (as in the case of the Magnox plant which formed the basi&amp; ofthe first nuclear power programme), from larger size of stations (four reactorsinstead of two) and from economies from repeat orders.4. Estimates of generating costs on the basis of pence per unit, on theassumption that the power stations under consideration will have a fixed loadfactor (75 per cent, for example) throughout their lives, are useful for somepurposes but can be misleading in comparing plant with markedly differentcapital and operating costs, such as nuclear and conventional power stations.Nuclear power stations have higher capital costs but much lower operating costs than conventional stations and it is reasonable to assume that they willbe operated at higher average load factors. For this reason, in makingcomparisons of nuclear and conventional power stations, the central electricity Generating Board calculate the costs which they would need to incur throughout the life of either type of station. This method shows theeffect on the Central Electricity Generating Board&apos;s total costs, rather thanthe isolated costs at the individual, stations, by allowing for the fuel savings which would accrue as more efficient plant comes into service in the future and displaces older conventional plant in the power station merit order.It minimises the disadvantage in fuel costs of the conventional plant ascompared with nuclear plant; the cruder method Of assuming a constanthigh load factor tends to distort the comparison in favour of nuclear plant.5. Using the method described in the previous paragraph to calculate the operating savings of nuclear stations compared with coal-fired stations, theinternal rate of return on the extra investment in nuclear stations can be calculated by recognised discounted cash flow techniques. For the 5,500 MWof the second nuclear programme after Dungeness &quot; B &quot; and Hinkley Point&quot; B &quot;, the additional capital cost compared with a similar programme ofcoal-fired stations is expected to be some  170 million, or about  30 per kW(including interest during construction and the cost of the initial loading ofuranium fuel for nuclear stations). The &quot; ground rules&quot; employed in calculating the return on this extra investment are the same as those used bythe Central Electricity Generating Board (see paragraph 2) on which Table Fis based, except that interest during construction is taken as 8 per cent,(against the Central Electricity Generating Board&apos;s figure of 5\ per cent.),and a higher cost of the initial charge of uranium fuel is assumed in line withthe Central Electricity Generating Board&apos;s estimate of the cost of replacementuranium fuel. - In the light of increasing experience with the existing Magnoxstations and with the experimental A.G.R. at wind scale,.these ground rules
might be thought pessimistic in two respects. First, a longer amortisationperiod might be justified ; and second, a higher availability and thus a higherlifetime load factor, or else greater system savings, might be attainable. both these changes, if reflected in the ground rules, would favour nuclear power.Nevertheless, it has been felt proper, for the time being at least, to retain the use of the more severe ground rules.6. For purposes of calculating the operating savings of the nuclear plantas compared with coal-fired plant, a range of coal prices from 3d. up to 6d.per therm at pithead was considered, equivalent to 3-7d. to 6-7d. inclusive of costs of transport, handling, preparation and ash disposal. The presentinclusive costs of the cheapest and most expensive coal that the central electricity Generating Board purchase from the National Coal Board are3-9d. and 6-6d. per therm: the average cost is 5d.7. The results of these calculations of the internal rate of return on the extra investment are given in Table G below :Table GInternal Rate of Return on Extra Investment in theSecond Nuclear Power ProgrammeCoal Costs Coal Costs EstimatedPithead Inclusive Internal(pence per therm) (pence per therm)  Rate of Return*3-0 3-7 13%4-0 4-7 19%5-0 5-7 25%6-0 6-7 31%* On extra capital required for 5,500 MW of capacity based on nuclear (instead of coal).The precise balance of optimism and pessimism in making future estimates of generating costs is to some extent a matter of judgment. There are inevit-ably uncertainties for example, in the estimates of capital costs, in the timing of completion of construction, and in plant availability. In view ofthese uncertainties, but bearing in mind that it would be wrong to aggregateall the most favourable or all the most unfavourable factors, the rates of return shown in Table G should be regarded as the mid-points of rangesextending 2 or 3 percentage points in either direction.8. Consideration has also been given to whether the estimates in TablesF and G include all the avoidable costs properly attributable to nuclear power stations in the second nuclear power programme and, in particular, whetherthe prices paid by the generating Boards for the supply and re-processing of nuclear fuel and the disposal of radioactive waste fully reflect the costs incurred by the Atomic Energy Authority. The Government have accepted that the Atomic Energy Authority&apos;s activities of a commercial nature oughtin principle to be accounted for separately in a Trading Fund, and that allassets in the Fund should be charged the proper Treasury interest rate andearn in addition an appropriate surplus. Although the full costs arisingfrom the provision of uranium and the re-processing of radioactive waste arenot at present covered in the Trading Fund as such, they are expected to beby the early 1970&apos;s, and by then the Atomic Energy Authority will be
recovering all avoidable costs. As regards the Atomic Energy Authority&apos;sresearch and development expenditure, the royalty at the rate of 0-014d. perkWh. to be paid by the generating Boards to the Atomic Energy authority on A.G.R.&apos;s in the second nuclear power programme has rested primarily on the assumption that they will show a cost advantage over alternative methods of generation. This royalty will not recover all the past costs ofthe development of the Magnox and A.G.R. systems, but it is expected tocover amply all forward avoidable costs likely to be incurred by the atomic energy Authority in further development work for the second nuclear power programme.9. Although the rate of return on incremental capital should be the mainyardstick, estimates have also been made of the price at which coal couldcompete with nuclear power, that is, the price of coal at which extrainvestment in nuclear power would show only an 8 per cent, return, whichis the minimum rate of return which the Treasury recommend should norm-ally be earned on new investment in the public sector. The &quot; break-even &quot;price of coal considered in this way is estimated to come to about 2-9d. pertherm, inclusive of transport and handling charges and, allowing for the uncertainties mentioned in paragraph 7, may lie between 2-6d. and 3-2d.per therm (or between l-9d. and 2-5d. at pithead). The upper end of thisrange is, of course, the important figure in considering the choice betweencoal and nuclear power. These figures compare with those quoted inparagraph 6 (a range of 3-9d. to 6-6d. per therm with an average of 5d.)for the present inclusive prices paid by the Central Electricity GeneratingBoard for National Coal Board coal. It should be noted, however, that theCentral Electricity Generating Board are already purchasing very largequantities of coal for use in existing stations, and will continue to do so for many years for use in the new coal-fired power stations now being built.Thus, even if extra coal could be supplied to the Central Electricity general-ing Board at or below the break-even price, this cheaper coal should beconsidered to be available to dispense with a corresponding quantity ofthe coal being burned in existing stations, for which higher prices werebeing paid. It is thus the higher priced coal that must be considered asbeing displaced by nuclear power.Post-1975 Nuclear Costs10. Consideration has also been given to the possible trend of nuclearcosts after 1975. The reliability of post-1975 estimates must be considerably less than those for the 1970-75 period, which to some extent are based onactual tenders. Quite apart from the prospects for fast reactors, there isample scope for further development of A.G.R. technology, and the factorsmentioned in paragraph 3, which should have a continuing effect, providegrounds for expecting cost reductions. The precise size and timing of the reductions are bound to be subject to considerable uncertainty but, on thebasis of current price levels, it seems reasonable to assume that by about1980 A.G.R. generation costs should be down to a level at least 20 per cent,below those of the A.G.R. stations now under construction, and should thenbe fully competitive with generation from untaxed oil.
Appendix IVTechnical Developments in British Coalmining1. Any assessment of the likely future market for coal must take accountof the coal industry&apos;s potential for raising productivity and reducing costs,particularly at a time of very rapid technological change. This Appendixdescribes some of the important developments in mining practice which aretaking place.2. The coalmining industries of the world use various systems of mining,depending on the depth, thickness, type, and disposition of the coal deposits.In Britain, these natural conditions now generally demand the applicationof what is known as the &quot; Longwall Advancing &quot; system. This involves the extraction of the area of coal to be worked by advancing the face forward on a broad front (commonly 150 yards to 200 yards) leaving behind theroadways serving it, which are supported usually by packs of stone andsteel lining in the area of extraction. These roads have then to be main-tained in good condition to provide for transport of men and materials to andfrom the face and for ventilation. The roof over the working area at the face has to be supported by roof supports. In established modern practice the coal is won mechanically by a machine (&quot; power loader &quot;) which cuts theseam while travelling along the face and simultaneously loads the cut coalon to an armoured face conveyor situated in front of the line of roof supports.At each end of the face there is usually an excavation (&quot; stable hole &quot;) in thecoal seam, extending a few yards ahead of the face line, into which thepower loader is driven at the end of its run so that it can be got ready andadvanced into position to commence the next run. These stable holes, which provide approximately one-tenth of the face output, are not usually preparedby power loaders ; the coal is usually undercut by machine, blown down byexplosives, and loaded out by hand.3. In the past decade, the mining industry in Britain has made greatprogress in the development of longwall coalface machinery and the intro-duction of mechanical mining into the collieries. Emphasis was placedinitially on the development and installation of robust, highly productive,power loaders and their associated conveyor systems ; during the period1956 to 1966 the proportion of deep mined output cut and loaded by mechinisation-cal equipment rose from 15^ per cent, to nearly 86 per cent. The powerloaders of today commonly absorb 150 horsepower and can cut a 2 foot-deepslice of coal at a rate of 20 feet per minute.4. During much of the period, there has also been intensive research anddevelopment activity aimed at producing better types of roof support. the traditional method of supporting the roof by means of props and bars,1 setand withdrawn manually, is a labour-consuming operation and is ill-suited to, and can limit the output of, modern mining machines; it can also causeaccidents. The collaboration of Britain&apos;s mining engineers, scientists and manufacturers has pioneered a system of self-advancing hydraulically operatedroof supports, otherwise known as powered supports, which are the equal in design and performance of any in the world ; and there are ample statistics toshow that their adoption on a mechanical face, irrespective of the type of power loader, leads to increased output, higher productivity and above all
2  $ JLgreater safety. A face so equipped can operate on a complete coal-winningcycle (excluding the formation of stable-ends) of well under 2 hours. Thesecond major phase of mechanisation has, therefore, been to equip faces withpowered supports as rapidly as practicable ; whereas there were no produc-tion installations in 1956, over 50 per cent, of current output comes from such faces.5. As a direct consequence of the adoption of the techniques outlined above, the industry is now able to break away from the traditional cycle of operations, whereby the winning of coal was limited substantially to one shiftper day. Fully continuous production of coal for periods of up to perhaps 20hours per day has become possible, and the introduction of multishift pro-duction is a step in that direction. This is an important development in miningpractice. At present about half the machines on mechanised faces are usedon a two-shift basis, and a further third are used on three or more shifts aday.6. The combined effect of these various developments is that each in-dividual coalface has become a production unit of considerable complexity.The average daily output per face has more than doubled since 1957 and now stands at just over 470 tons a day ; but many faces regularly achieve a daily output of more than 1,000 tons and a few have exceeded 2,000 tons.The capital investment involved in a typical mechanised face, equipped withpowered supports, is about  150,000.7. The industry has not yet been able to exploit to the full the potentialwhich technological development has put at its disposal. The expensive coal-face equipment is mostly being used for a disappointingly short time eachshift, with the result that production costs are kept high by the high capitalcharges. Many problems and difficulties will have to be overcome before this situation is put right, and several of them are not technological. Never-theless technology has its contribution to make and a great deal of technicalthought and effort continues to be devoted to finding solutions.&quot; &quot; &quot;*8. One of the outstanding and most recalcitrant technical problems arises from the fact that there is not yet a widely acceptable and proven methodof forming and advancing the stable holes and roadways at a rate whichwill ensure that face line operations can proceed without delay. Face-endoperations are still, in the main, carried out manually and are both slow and very demanding in manpower. Attempts are being made to develop mechan-ical methods of performing them ; specially designed powered support systemsfor face-ends are under trial. Operating methods and power loading machinesof greater versatility are now aimed at dispensing with the stable hole, and&quot; stableless &quot; systems are being introduced into British collieries. Machineshave been designed for and applied to the ripping operation to form theroadways at the required rate of advance, but so far there has been difficultyin controlling dust concentrations, in handling and disposing of the debris,and in cutting hard strata at a satisfactory speed. During the past yearsubstantial progress has been made, but a number of problems remain. until they are solved, and fully dependable machines of wide applicability havebeen developed, the face-end operations will remain the final major technicalobstacle to realisation of the full benefits of mechanisation of the coalfaceand its associated roadways.
9. Looking further ahead, there is the prospect of extended use of remotecontrol, and possibly even automation, of coalface operations. Two experi-mental longwall faces, which were operated during 1963 and 1964 with veryencouraging results, served to demonstrate that the remote control of someof the operations between the face-ends is possible. A further programmeof such faces has been planned and four faces were in operation at thebeginning of this year. An important unsolved problem is that of automaticsteering of the face machine so as to keep it cutting coal and prevent itwandering into the roof or floor, and this is being given a high priority atthe National Coal Board&apos;s research and engineering establishments.10. Elsewhere underground there have been comparable changes in tech-techniques and equipment. In order that face operations shall not be broughtto a halt by short stoppages elsewhere underground, there has been a marked increase in the use of underground surge bunkers. Continuous improvementsare also being made in other services to the coalface in order to economisein manpower: they include better systems for handling materials, for transportof coal and men, and for disposal of debris from roadways and headings.Substantial progress has been made in the installation of remote controlof the underground conveyor transport system so as to dispense with, orgreatly reduce, the employment of men at transfer and loading points and atbunkers. There are now about 100 such systems in operation. Remote orautomatic control, with the aid of electronic monitoring systems, is also beingwidely applied to the running of other underground machinery.11. On the surface, efforts to reduce costs include the widespread use of automatic winding control gear, automatic tub and mine-car control circuits,the use of modern methods of packaging and handling materials and supplies,and automatic loading of wagons. In coal preparation plants the automaticmonitoring and control of washery feed and preparation processes, such asblending for improved consistency of quality, is being extended.12. This increase in the complexity and sophistication of mining opera-tions has given rise to a need for improved communications and informationsystems. Substantial sums are being invested in modern electronic com-munication equipment, both for control purposes and to provide managementwith factual performance data. Nearly thirty coalfaces now have electronicmonitoring and indicating equipment and its use is being extended rapidly.Information about the operation of power loaders, conveyors, winding gear,and in some cases about the position and speed of operation of the coal-cutting equipment, is fed to a central control point on the colliery surfaceor underground.13. Perhaps the best known of the industry&apos;s activities in these fields arethe proposals for the collieries at Bevercotes (Nottinghamshire) and Longannet(Scotland). At Bevercotes it is planned to operate a completely new mine asthe first colliery to have a fully integrated system of remote control through-out the colliery and to operate as nearly as possible on a continuous basis ;coal production has started and it is expected that when the colliery is infull production it will produce 1-5 million tons of coal annually with a labour force of 700, giving an output per man shift of about four times the presentaverage. The Longannet scheme embraces the working of a single seam by a
Printed in England by Her Majesty&apos;s Stationery office at St. Stephen&apos;s Parliamentary Press(329584)  Dd. 133226  8, 150  10/67complex of four separate producing units, the output from which will be fedon to a central underground conveyor system carrying the coal through a five mile long tunnel to reach the surface at the stocking ground of a newpower station which is now being built. The ultimate objective is to have all the plant and equipment controlled automatically from a central controlpoint on the surface, possibly with auxiliary control centres nearer to theseveral coalfaces.




</content>
</cab>
