<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/133/0 images: 359-384</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&amp;ENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES:  DRAFT WHITE paper i/Ioznorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer was invited by the Steering Committee on Economic Policy to circulate to the Cabinet a revised draft of the White Paper on nationalised industries^     This is attached,2.       This draft takes account of the comments of my colleagues at the steering Committee on Economic Policy and subsequently?  and of theviews of the Trades Union Congress, the Confederation of BritishIndustry, and the Chairmen ox the nationalised industries,    I intend to deal with these views orally at Cabinet,3,       I invite my colleagues to agree to early publication of the WhiteC(67) 167COPY NO,24th October, 1967CABINETPaper,Treasury Charnber s, S , W, 1,23rd October, 1967CONFIDENTIAL
2 s 9Revised 23rd October, 1967NATIONALISED    INDUSTRIESA REVIEW OP ECONOMIC AND FINANCIAL OBJECTIVESDRAFT WHITE paper i,    On 7th September, 1967 the Government announced that all futuremajor price increases in the nationalised industries would bereferred to the National Board for Prices and Incomes.     This decision is intended to show clearly that prices and incomes policy criteriaapply equally to price increases in both the public and private sectors.     It will allow the National Board for Prices and Incomes tosee whether such increases can be reduced or avoided by increased efficiency or changes of practice.     It is however the Government&apos;responsibility to formulate the general policy framework within whichprice changes should be reviewed and to agree with the industries thejjpeconomic and financial objectives.   Before the announcement inSeptember, therefore, the Government had initiated a review of thesematters, and this White Paper sets out the conclusions and the main considerations which should apply to the investment and pricingpolicies of the industries and to future   financial objectives.general,    The statutory duties of nationalised industries are set out inthe nationalisation Acts.     Broadly they are to meet the demand fortheir products and services in the most efficient way and to conduct their finances so that over time they at least break even, afterBaking a contribution to reserves.     The statutes however gave noguidance on what was meant by efficiency in economic terms, andprescribed only a minimum standard of financial performance.   Thiswas defined in terms of surplus (or deficit);   it differs from theordinary concept of profit (or loss) in that provision must be madefor all items properly chargeable to revenue under the statutes,3*    It was later found necessary to make this requirement morespecificj    and further guidance for the industries was set out inthe White Paper on the Financial and Economic Obligations of the nationalised Industries in 1961 (Cmnd. 1337).   This interpreted the
statutory provisions as meaning that Industries should aim to balancetheir accounts &quot;taking one year with another&quot; over a period offive years, after providing for interest, and depreciation athistoric cost *   Provision should also be made for the differencebetween depreciation at historic cost and replacement cost andallocations to reserve sufficient to make some contribution towardsthe industry1a future capital development programme (which would otherwise fall on the Exchequer) and as a safeguard against prematureobsolescence and similar contingencies *   Financial objectives or&quot;targets&quot; were to be determined for each undertaking in the light ofits needs and capabilities in relation to these criteria.   Inpractice targets have normally been expressed as a rate of return on the undertakings assets though other methods of expressing them were not ruled out? a list of the targets currently in force is inTable 2.4*    In the six years since 196l much has happened.   There have beenimportant technological changes and discoveries of new natural resources which affect the long-term prospects of the fuelindustries *   There have been changes in the pattern of demand which affect the transport and aviation industries.   Despite contractionsin one or two industries, the overall capacity of the nationalisedsector has been growing fast to meet increased demand.   All this hasled to investment on a scale f&amp;r greater than was foreseen six yearsago.   In consequence, calls upon scarce resources of manpower and capital are now very heavy; and the need to measure these calls, to assess priorities, and to allocate resources upon an economically and socially rational basis has become even more important*5*    The Government&apos;s objectives for industry are to increase the productivity of both labour and capital employed; to raise the rateof new capital formation, to ensure that new equipment is astechnologically advanced as possible and is effectively deployed;to increase the profitability of new investment; and to obtain themaximum return in terms of the production^ of goods and services.?he nationalised industries have a vital role to play in the
attainment of these objectives as well as in the development of thegovernment * s wider social and economic policies.   Wit^the nationalisation of steel, their net assets are now valued at nearlygll,000 million and they invest annually around  1,600 million,over half of which is at present financed by the Exchequer.   their annual investment is equivalent to the whole of that for privatenanufacturing industry; they contribute about 11 per cent of the gross domestic product and they employ around 8 per cent of the total labour force.   When the Government&apos;s proposals for furthernationalisation in the docks are implemented, they will provide mostof the economy&apos;s basic needs for energy, transport, communications,steel and export facilities; and the efficiency with which so large a sector operates will have a significant Impact on the evolutionand rate of growth of the whole economy.   In their case the objectives outlined above cannot be achieved merely by maximisingcoerrs. ithe financial returns of each industry: significant eats-and benefitscan occur which are outside the financial concern of the industryand it is the special responsibility of the Government to ensurethat these &quot;social&quot; targets are reflected in the industries&apos; planning.Investment ,6.    Investment is fundamental to economic growth and largelydetermines the way in which industries develop.   The investment programmes of the nationalised industries are framed in the lightof the Government*s policy for the sector (fuel, transport, etc.)concerned.   Investment is often a necessary condition for the achievement of reductions in costs, and the choice between differentways of satisfying consumer demand requires careful and sophisticatedcalculations.   The development plans for industrial sectors mustgreatly influence investment decisions made by individual public corporations, and, conversely, the pattern of investment decisionsthat is expected provides souse of the basic information on whichteoad industrial policies are formulated by the appropriate Government
Departments in consultation with the industries.     There is no simpleautomatic rule for ensuring the consistency of decisions, and it willremain the job of sponsoring Departments to ensure that the strategyof economic development for their sector evolves appropriately in thelight of changing circumstances and technological advances.     Withinthe framework set by these strategies, investment decisions mustbe made against the appropriate criteria..7,    Investment projects must normally show a satisfactory return in commercial terms unless they are justifiable on wider criteriainvolving an assessment of the social costs and benefits involved,or are provided to meet a statutory obligation.     Subject to these considerations, the Government&apos;s policy is to treat the industries as commercial bodies and the underlying concept behind the controlof nationalised industries&apos; investment by rate of return is that themost efficient distribution of goods and services in the economy as awhole can be secured only if investments are made where the returnto the economy is greatest.   This holds true whatever the level of investment in the economy.     The rate of return on new capital isnot the same as the overall return on net assets;   the two maydiverge quite widely, for reasons discussed below.8.    The Government expects the nationalised industries to use thebest possible methods of appraisal.     Discounted cash flow techniques,which are already widely used by the nationalised industries are recommended for all important projects.     By taking account of theeffects of the timing of cash outlays and receipts, these techniquesenable proper comparison to be m adebetween alternative projects.They can be applied in different ways, and the industries are free to adopt whatever method suits them best, but the Government willexpect projects which are submitted to it for approval to be expressed in present values by the use of a test rate of discount.9*    This test rate of discount must be sufficient to ensure thatresources are efficiently used, and represents the minimum rate of return to be expected on a marginal low-risk project undertaken fork
commercial reasons.   It is essential that the nationalised industries should use consistent methods of appraisal and should adopt the sametest discount rate,10.   The Government have decided that 8 per cent is a reasonable figure to use for this purpose in present circumstances.   This figure is broadly consistent, having regard to differing circumstances inrelation to tax, investment grants, etc., with the average rate of return in real terms looked for on low-risk projects in the private sector in recent years*   Some nationalised industries have been usingsimilar rates for investment appraisal in recent years.   Followingdiscussions with the industries about the application of these methods to their individual circumstances, the Government is now asking the nationalised industries to use this rate until further notice.   It isintended to apply to expenditure and receipts related to investment projects before allowing for tax; this is appropriate in the case of nationalised industries which although subject to tax in the same way as private industry, do not receive investment grants on their main activities,*11.   The test rate of discount is different from the rate of interest which the nationalised industries will pay on new borrowing from theExchequer since they borrow at rates reflecting Government credit.Access to this source of funds should not imply any relaxation ofthe economic criteria appropriate to investment for commercial purposes.   The surplus over their interest liabilities provides partof the finance for the industries&apos; investment programmes.       &amp;12,   The test rate of discount, being a uniform rate for all industries, does not include allowance for the risks of individualinvestments.   Exercising Judgment as to what risks are worth takingIs essentially a function of management.   Whenever possible, estimates should be made of the likely range of outcomes, and investmentundertaken only when management Judges that prospects are, on balance,*m^m*^^*aamgg*mKmnamammmmtt i imannviianrnuMMiBiWMHiauMiuii &quot; ismim uinmmmiiMMMiiMiniMMiii minim uiiiim.....    i    mmi iiujiuiwiu.....amhimhmmmpmm ii \m       MavaMmnannHMMMMnB*The rate to be used by the British Steel Corporation has yet tofce settled.   As part of manufacturing industry the Corporation will receive investment grants and these will have to be allowed for in determining the appropriate test rate of discount.
favourable.   In these calculations the cost of capital should be taken as 8 per cent, so that prospective gains and losses can be comparedin a consistent way.   In some types of case, however, it may beimpossible to make meaningful estimates of the degree of risk inquantitative form, and in these cases it will be desirable to use asore stringent criterion - that is, a higher test discount rate than the recommended one - in appraising exceptionally riskyprojects.    avteW, the alternative receipts and outlays assumed inDiscounted Cash Plow calcuMions themselves represent the various possible expected outcomes.   Risk is thus built into the cash-flowfigures used and there is no need to allow for it separately in thediscount-rate chosen.   Similarly the test rate of discount does not include an allowance for inflation; it is therefore necessary to base investment appraisals on the assumption that the prices ofinputs and outputs are not affected by changes in the general price level,   (Clearly, however, it is necessary to allow for expectedchanges in relative prices)*13,   The use of this test rate of discount in investment calculationsdoes not of course imply that nationalised industries should neverinvest new capital in the supply of goods and services which do not show a return of at least 8 per cent in real terms on the capital employed.   There are circumstances in which it is desirable for social or wider economic reasons to provide such services; and it isdesirable in a few cases to provide services at some directfinancial loss.   But all projects need to be assessed in a systematicway allowing for uncertainties in the forecasts of demand and of technological developments so that their direct return can beestimated before any other considerations are taken into accountsUu   The economic value of investments cannot always be measured by reference to the financial return to the industry concerned.   Manyinvestments also produce social costs and benefits which can inprinciple be valued in financial terms and which, when taken intoaccount, will provide a good economic justification for them.
Examples of these are extensions to the underground network inLondon which take account of congestion costs.   Equally so there arecases like the railway branch lines where the Government may takesocial and regional considerations into account in requiring an industry to undertake continuing operations which are themselvesunprofitable; hut these generally involve current rather than capitalexpenditure.   Often the social costs and benefits arising from aparticular investment are not significantly different from those associated with other investments offering similar financial returns,and to measure an investment by its financial return can for most practical purposes be regarded as giving a reasonable approximationto its value to the community.   But where there are grounds forthinking that the social costs or benefits do diverge markedly fromthose associated with the alternatives the Government will take thisinto account when assessing the investment.   Indeed it must take a wider view than that of the industry itself, since the Governmentsobjective is to secure the maximum social return on the capital invested, while the industry&apos;s concern is properly with thefinancial return.15.   Techniques of social cost/benefit evaluation are being developedrapidly though there are often difficulties and uncertaintiesinvolved in making the calculations.   Social cost/benefit studiesmay prove valuable in comparing investments within broad sectors ofthe economy (transport, fuel etc.) where comparison cannot be madeon financial terms because pricing arrangements in different partsof the sector are not comparable; they may also be necessary to assess the return to the economy of certain very large projects.   Some ofthe costs and benefits however lie in fields where nationalised industries are not in a position to make estimates; and in order tobe sure that assumptions are applied consistently, overall cost/benefit studies of major projects are best carried out by theGovernment Departments concerned, in collaboration with theindustries.io.   Equally, it does not follow that all investment)passing the
test rate are automatically undertaken.   The test rate of discountiaessentially a device to ensure that the calls of the public and private sectors upon resources do not get out of line with eachother over the long term.   After a nationalised industry has preparedan investment programme based on the demand it expects to meet atrational price levels, and appraised in the way just described,the Government then has to consider it in the light of developmentselsewhere in the economy, especially short-term ones, and of othercalls on resources.   The Government are thus concerned with the phasing of investment which needs to be considered in the light of real resources available.   The sums involved are now so large inrelation to other public and private sector expenditure that theremay also be special problems of financing.   Alternative public sector borrowing arrangements will be kept under review, but nothing would be gained by going back to separate stock issues for the nationalised industries.   These would involve serious problems of market management and would not create any additional savings.   Iftherefore some easing of pressure in the short term is indicated, theGovernment may arrange for the deferment of desirable but not immediately essential investment.   But if in the long term the levelof investment in the nationalised industries as a whole is consideredexcessive, then the proper course would be to adjust the testdiscount rate.
Priceslj.    The use of correct methods of investment appraisal will only heeffective if the nationalised industries also adopt, within the context of national prices and incomes policy, pricing policies rele-vant to their eeonamic circumstances.     The circumstances ofdifferent industries vary greatly.     Nevertheless there are certain general considerations.     The Government&apos;s policy here startsfrom the principle that nationalised industries&apos; revenues should normally cover their accounting costs in full - including the serviceof capital and appropriate provision for its replacement.     But imporvant though this is, it is not in itself sufficient to produce arational pricing policy.     Prices, if they are to contribute towards a more efficient districibution of resources, must alsoattract resources to tfee&amp;e- aafrao where they can make the most effective contribution to meeting the demands of users,18.     It is therefore important that, while covering overallaccounting costs wherever possible, pricing policies should be de-vised with particular r reference to the costs of the goods and services provided.     Unless this is done, there is a risk ofundesirable cross-subsidisation and consequent misallocation of resources.     The ainu    of pricing policy should be that the consumershould pay the true costs of providing the goods and services heconsumes, in every case where these can be sensibly identified.There are of course exceptions to the general rule.     In some cases there will be good commercial reasons  for charging prices whichdiffer from costs.     In others it may be simply impracticable to cost separately relatively minor operations.     In a few cases,cross-subsidisation may be justified by statutory requirements or bywider economic or social considerations.     But - these cases apart -to cross-subsidise loss making services amounts   to taxingremunerative services provided by the same undertaking/isas objectionable as subsidising grom general taxation services ihichhave no social justification.
X9.     Another reason for charging prices different from costs may-arise when there is persistent spare capacity, either for relativelylong periods or at certain times, places or seasons.     This capacity is unlikely to be used economically unless charges adequately reflect the difference between the costs of meeting additional demand wherespare capacity exists and the higher costs where additional capacityhas to be provided to meet demand.     Thus where there is additional demand which could be met without major investment in new plant,it is desirable that prices should be reduced if this would stimulatedemand - if necessary to the level where the escapable costs ofparticular services are just covered.     If this is not done a require-ment for new investment may be created in industries supplyingcompeting services without surplus capacity.20.     In some industries - such as electricity and commuter servicesof the railways - the load at periods of high demand rather thanthe growth of total sales determines the need for new capital invest-ment.     In such cases plant may be under-utilised for much of thetime and so far as is administratively possible the price systemrecognises this characteristic of demand by providing adequateincentives to encourage users to shift from peak to off-peak,   Pro-vided off-peak charges do not fall below the levels needed to cover the variable costs incurred, differentiation can be increased with advantage until the balance between peak and off-peak is   economi-cally most efficient.     The effect on revenue is neutral su long as lower receipts from off-peak users are offset by higher receiptsresulting from higher charges made to peak time users;   indeed anet revenue gain is likely.     Two-part and   differential pricing sy-etems are also used to improve financial results without distortingthe allocation of resources when there are important elements in costs which cannot easily be allocated to specific services orproducts (e.g. costs incurred jointly by several services or costs which do not vary proportionately with output).     In apportioningthese costs among consumers, there is a wide choice of methods ranging from complex multi-part tariffs designed to ensure that each customer
Ji)9pays for the costs he imposes, to simple quantity discounts whichmay he appropriate in cases where large quantities are more econo-mical to supply than smaller amounts.     The actual calculation of thedifferent elements of such a price system is itself a complicatedtask;   hut the broad objective is clear enough.21.     In addition to recovering accounting costs, prices need to be reasonably related to costs at the margin and to be designed to promote the efficient use of resources within industry.     Where and when there is spare capacity, as there may be at some points in thebusiness cycle, or excess demand, short run marginal costs (i.e. theadditional costs of increasing output in the short run) are relevant;the object is to   persuade customers to make use   of spare capacityor to curtail excess demand.     In the longrun, the main consideration is the cost of supply^on a continuing basis, those services and products whose separate costing is a practical proposition (i.e. longrun marginal costs), though the   problems of transition to a newtechnology or to a new source of supply may imply the need, in the medium term, for prices to diverge from long-run costs.     $heselong-run marginal costs naturally include provision for the replace-ment of fixed assets needed for the continued provision of s services,together with a satisfactory rate of return on capital employed.22,    New technological developments can greatly reduce the longrun marginal cost of providing some services, and it is right tohave regard to these in pricing policy.     But a gradual adjustment of prices in the light of reasonable expectations is generallypreferable to sudden large changes occurring discontinuously whenmajor assets are replaced.     Strict adherence to long run marginalcosting in such circumstances could lead to a period of revenuedeficits requiring a temporary but heavy subsidy from general taxation and this would be difficult to justify.     The systems of largepublic under takings are in any case of such a size that there arepractical limits on the rate of modernisation, and unlessplant is well tried, rapid innovation may lead to breakdowns and heavy costs.     Too rapid a reduction in prices might stimulate demand
tee- ra*w4i that shortages^result or demand e-an only be met by costlymeasures to increase supply in the short run.     It might also reacton demand for the products of other nationalised industries;   pricesneed to be set in the framework of Government policy for the sectoras a whole.23. MoT All costs caxm&amp;b be allocated to specific services oractivities, and some industries, where the area of unallocablecosts is large, may find difficulty in going all the way towards apricing structure which accurately reflects the costs of particular services while at the same time covering total costs.     Two-partpricing is a device commonly employed to reconcile the twoobjectives, and in other cases a sufficient incentive to attractcustomers to areas where costs are lower might be provided by makingprices proportional to costs at the margin but at a level sufficientto cover total costs.2lx.    %t will be clear from the preceding paragraphs that thereis nothing rigid or doctrinaire about the pricing policy which theindustries are expected to follow.     Indeed the whole system offinancial objectives within which the industries operate is avery flexible instrument.     Targets are set for a periedof years(usually five) at a time;   and provided that industries, on balance,meet their targets over the period as a whole, they can, and should,carry out their pricing so as to fit in with the Governments generalpolicy for prices and incomes.     Insofar as the industries observe the principles set out in the White Paper, the Government does not intend to interfere in the day-to-day responsibility of management to propose increases, and will endeavour to leave management themaximum discretion in adjusting their price structure to meet corn-petition and to take advantage of commercial opportunities.25.     Nevertheless, nationalised industries supply many of the basicneeds of consumers and industries;    successive Governments have,therefore, maintained a very clase interest in the pricing decisionsof the industries, and, in practice, Ministers have been consulted and given an opportunity to comment before final decisions have been
h *tt been taken to increase prices on any significant scale,price stability In this sector is of especial importance to the economy.     On the other hand, if nationalised industries&apos; prices were allowed to get seriously out of line with costs this would lead to artificial stimulation of demand and a heavy burden of support on the general taxpayer.26.     Arrangements for price consultation with Ministers^have newbeen formalised as part of the voluntary early warning systemdescribed in the White Paper Prices and Incomes Policy:    &quot;An early warning&quot; System (Cmnd.2808),     The powers  of the Prices and incomes Act 1966, apply to the nationalised industries in the same way as to private industry.     But because of the importance of theindustries to the economy, and the need to demonstrate that thepublic sector is co-operating to $he full in carrying out thePrices and Incomes policy, the Government has decided in future torefer all major price increases in the nationalised industries to theNational Board for Prices and Incomes (N.B.P.I.).     In examiningsuch cases - against the background of the industry&apos;s overallfinancial objective - the N.B.P.I. will consider the underlyingjustification for any increase, its timing and the extent towhich costs could be reduced by increased efficiency.Costs27.    To make the best use of resources, it is not enough merely to ensure that prices properly reflect costs, Important though thisis.    Continuous and critical attention has to be paid to coststhemselves in order that an industry may play a full part in bringing about a more efficient and faster growing economy.     Itwould obviously be wrong if any industry, public or private, were allowed to exploit a degree of monopoly power so as to attain satis-factory financial results by covering unnecessarily high costs byequally unnecessary price increases.     The objective of price8tabioity can only be reconciled with the important aim of earninga proper return on capital if costs are kept under firm control.Since it is likely that, for a variety of reasons, the prices of
Iksome of the resources, especially manpower, will rise from time totime, managements* task is to seize every opportunity ef reducingcosts &quot;by employing improved methods or techniques.     This calls forimagination, careful planning, and a willingness to experiment.New plant technology, automation and better use of manpower willall play their part.28,     The principles of the productivity, prices and incomes policy apply equally to workers in the public and private sectors.It will therefore be for management and workers in the nationalised industries to continue to strive to increase efficiency and productivity and thus to meet the cost of pay increases whileensuring that the community as a whole benefits from higher pro-duct ivity.     Nationalised industries have a good record in thisrespect.     Nevertheless, there is always scope for further improve-ments and it is clear from international comparisons (though thesemust always take account ef different circumstances in different countries) that we still have some way to go in using manpowermore efficiently.     There is a national shortage of qualifiedengineers of which the nationalised industries are large employersand they therefore have a special obligation to employ engineerseconomically and to use their talents fully.      There is also a short-age of certain kinds  o f skilled worker and the industries areexpected to make the most of their human resources, both &quot;by usingless skilled labour so far as possible and by continuing enlightenedtraining policies.29.    One of managements&apos; main tasks is to look continuously forpossibilities of labour savings, and to encourage at&apos;all levels a positive attitude towards ideas of all kinds that might reduce thequantity of labour needed to provide the required level of service.This involves effective consultation and collaboration between management and men with a view to using labour more efficientlyby improved organisation of existing plant and methods, and intro-ducing new plant and methods which require less labour.     Inappraising both investment proposals and suggestions for reorganisation
the Government will expect the industries to make  allowance for the likelihood that the real cost of labour will rise continuouslythrough time as general productivity increases.     This means thatIndustries will have to become gradually less labour intensive intheir methods over time.     Similarly, if an appreciable rise in therelative prices of any of their other inputs is expected, managementwill rightly take this into account in its long term operational and investment planning.30*    Normally the best use cannot be made of new plant and equipmentunless changes in working methods are accepted by management and employees.     When costly automated equipment is installed theoptimal utilisation   rate should be higher than it was when lessexpensive plant was used, and in some cases tariff structures may need revision with the object of keeping the equipment fully used.All this requires considerable flexibility of approach by bothsides of industry to manning questions, and there can be no room forinefficient, out-dated or restrictive practices particularly in theoperation of costly and technologically advanced equipment.31.     In view of the rapidity of technological changes, and thenecessity of making the best possible use of source manpowerresources, it is essential that the nationalised industries shouldcontinue to plan their future manpower requirements and keep these plans under review in the light of their own changing demand andthe anticipated supply position for the categories of manpowerwhich they require.     Where manpower plans indicate a long termreduction in total manpower requirements, appropriate measures should be taken (i.e. by control of recruitment and wastage) eo thatthe planned reduction can be effected with the minimum of dislo-c at ion and redundancy.32.    The Government has, of course, had frequent discussions in thepast about productivity and labour utilisation in the nationalised industries?     In view of the great importance of productivity at thepresent time - and the fact that successful investment depends upon it - the Government has reviewed its policy in this area and has
taken a number of important decisions.     In the first place (as was announced on 7th September) the N.B.P.I. will be strengthenedto enable it to make all necessary enquiries into the efficiency ofthe industries whose proposals for price increases are referred toit.     These enquiries will cover the industries * machinery for keeping down costs including the appropriate forecasting and decision-making techniques.     The Board plans to recruit a small number of specialist staff to concentrate on this work and toprovide continuity.     This staff will be reinforced as necessary by outside consultants.     In addition the Government departments directly concerned will continue to develop in consultation withthe industries indicators of performance which will provide regular and systematic information about each industry1s success in con-trolling its costs, increasing efficiency, and economising in theuse of manpower and capital resources.     The Government intends topay particular attention to the trends shown by these indicatorsin the course of the annual Investment Review discussions with each industry.     The main object will be to discuss with the industrieswhat they have done in the past year and what they plan to do overthe period of the review to improve efficiency in all its aspectsand to add to the common pool of experience.     Furthermore the nationalised industries should often be able to pass on to otherparts of the economy the fruits of their experience in this field.The Government hope therefore that the nationalised industriesgenerally will exchange views among themselves and will make public as much information as they can about successful productivity techni-ques and in particular will give some account in their annual reports of what they have achieved in the past year and what theyplan to do in the coming years.Financial Objectives33.     Clear financial objectives will continue to be necessary sothat the industries know what is expected of them by the Government.Thus they serve both as an incentive to management and as one of the standards by which success or failure over a period of years may be judged.     The alternative would be an indefeneible lack of control
jver the return achieved on a very substantial public investment. 315There are, inevitably, simplifications and compromises to be made in formulating an overall financial objective for a large industrial under-taking in the form of a simple figure.     It is not  always possible inpractice to reconcile a prescribed rate of return on new investment,and a system of pricing which accurately reflects costs, with a pre-determined overall return on total assets.     Deviations may be inevit-able if there are sudden developments in technology affecting the lives or the use of large amounts of existing assets.     Nevertheless,despite these difficulties the system of financial objectives has provedits value in practice:    it cannot provide a perfect formula for theresolution of all pricing and investment decisions, but it does give, a framework within which such decisions can be reached.3I4..    For these reasons the setting of objectives for those industries which have not got &quot;them or the replacement of those which expire cannotbe solely an arithmetical exercise, and in its discussions with theindustries the Government will take into account the considerations -return on new investment, soundly based pricing policy, social obli-gations not covered by a subsidy, efficient operation, national prices and incomes policy - mentioned above.     Unlike the common test rate of return on new investment, these objectives will in practice be differentfor each industry and for the various Area Boards because they willreflect different statutory and social obligations, conditions of demand, domestic costs and other factors peculiar to the individualundertaking.     It will not be true therefore that a higher targetnecessarily indicates a more efficient industry.35.    The financial target system described above is essentially aflexible one.     It has already been explained in paragraph 2k      thatindustries are required to fulfil their obligations over a run ofyears taken together, and not necessarily to meet their targetsevery year.     This in itself is a valuable means of reconcilingfinancial discipline with reasonable price stability.     But the targetsystem can also be adopted to meet the varying circumstances of individual industries.     Targets have so far been set mostly in terms of&amp; percentage return on the net assets of the whole undertaking, which
is readily comprehensible and provides an accepted standard by which to assess efficiency in the use of capital.   It also takes someaccount of changes in the scale of an undertaking.   But this is notthe only criterion which can be devised.   Objectives for different parts of an industry&apos;s operations, or expressed in other ways, might1)6 appropriate in certain industries and at certain times.   It mightfor instance be desirable to express an objective as a fixedmoney sum; though this would require more frequent revision with changes in the scale of operations or in the value of money, itcould not be confused with the return to be expected on new investment or the rate of interest on borrowings.   It will also bedesirable to set some targets for a shorter period than five years.Finally, it follows from the fact that targets should reflectsound investment and pricing policy and not vice versa that if thereare significant changes in the circumstances of an industry theGovernment would be ready to review its target within the period for which it has been set and revise it upwards or downwards *36.   In certain cases the circumstances of a particular industrycoupled with Government approval to the application of widereconomic and social factors, may involve overall losses.   But evenhere a clear financial objective will be necessary as an aid to management and it will be desirable to set this in a way which willprovide a realistic incentive to efficiency and morale within theindustry.   A two-part objective - providing for a certain determinedlevel of losses, possibly subject to specific subsidies, on partof the operations and seeking an adequate return on the rest - isone possibility; tapering subsidies are another.P* the Industries37%   The aim of strengthening the United Kingdom economy can onlybe achieved if resources are more economically used and moreefficiently deployed than in the past and all undertakings fullyobserve the Governme*% policy on prices and Incomes,   nationalised industries, which command much greater resources thmm all but the
very largest private undertakings, should expect to he numberedamong the most progressive and efficient concerns in the country.Where there are significant., social or wider economic costs and benefits which ought to he taken into account in their investment and pricing these will be reflected in the Government1s policy for the industry: and if this means that the industry has to metagainst its own commercial interests, the Government will accept responsibility.   (Where necessary the Government will make a specialpayment to the industry or make an appropriate adjustment to its financial objective).   Except in such cases the industries should provide goods and services which consumers want and are willing topay for at prices which reflect their own costs as accurately aspossible, and keep these costs at the lowest levels consistent with providing satisfactory conditions of employment and earning a proper return on capital.   In planning their future investment,the industries should have regard to the considerations set out inparagraphs ,   6 to Igs     above, and should take into account economicforecasts prepared by the responsible Government Departments.   Intheir approach to problems of pricing, cost reduction and staffing,the industries should have regard to what is said in paragraphs1? to 30L&quot; above.The Role of the Government38.   Though the responsible Ministers and their Departments are infrequent contact with the nationalised Boards about matters affecting Government policy, it is not the Government&apos;s intentionto interfere in the day to day management of the industries.Nevertheless the Government must accept a large measure ofresponsibility for the general lines of economic development whichare followed in this vital sector of the economy, and in its relations with the nationalised industries will have in mind the considerations outlined in this White Paper, and in particular that increases in costs should whenever possible be absorbed by greater efficiency rather than be passed on to the consumer, and that price
increases should be capable of being publicly justified.39.   The annual investment review provides a regular occasion for reviewing the state of each industry.   Then the Government normallygives firm approval for the agreed level of capital expenditure forthe forthcoming financial year and provisional approval (subjectto some limitation on the extent to which funds are to be committed)for the following year; and also gives its views on the outline of investment proposed for subsequent years.   The programmes for mostindustries extend five years ahead, and with industries in whichinvestment takes a long time to mature, this longer-term look isof key importance.   The implications of the investment programmes for the Exchequer - and hence for the short and long-term balance ofthe economy - must always be considered, though it is not intendedto express financial objectives in terms of self-financing ratios.It is also during the investment review discussions that theGovernment is able to take account of the general balance of investment between individual nationalised industries, and betweenthem collectively and the rest of the economy, in order to ensureco-ordinated development in the context of planned growth of the economy.Conclusion40.   This White Paper is intended to show how investment, pricingand efficiency policies will be taken into account in settingfinancial objectives, rather than to make any change      &quot;the basicrelationship between the Government and the nationalised industries.It reviews the features and principles which are common to allnationalised industries and which underlie their relationship to theGovernment.   The circumstances of the industries are however verydiverse and will be taken into account in formulating detailedpolicies for the sectors concerned.
Table 1NATIONALISED industries?65-			-66										Exchequer	Labour Force at March	Average Net Assets	Net	Net Income as a	Fixed Investment	Exchequer	Loans as a			Income	P ercen tage of Assets	in the U.K.	Flnand ng	Percentage of tfxed							Investment	1966						(2)	r	 m.	 m.	-    %	 m.	Cm.		&apos;000sHoffice	1,408	114.4	8.1	209.8( 1)	95.0	45.3	412Lai Coal Board^ ^	845U)	0.5	0.1	88.0	30.0	34.1	519triclty Council and riis in England and wales	3,425	238,9	7.0	598.8	294.8	49.2	226K.S.B.	250	12.5	5.0	14.9	11.7(3)	78.5	4fj).	292	15.6	5.4	46.1	26.3	57.0	17Council and Areas Gas Boards	853	46.1	5.4	119.0	61.4	51.6	122	123	11.8	9.6	17.6	- 2.8	- 15.0	19t,	95	5.1	5.4	16.9	5.2	30.7	19(5) ;british Railways Board	1,908	-71.2	- 3.7	121.1	35.0	28.9	388Bon Transport Board^	199	5.5	2.8	24.6	18.0	73.2	74Wish Transport Docks Board^	92	4.5	4.9	6.8		;	?1With Waterways Board&apos;&apos;	13		- 4.9	0.8		62.5	3insport Holding Company 53	161	17.6	10,9	17.2	-	-	102Ifotal, all industries	9,664	400.6	4.1	1281.0	575.1	44.8	1,916(1)   Includes Giro Development Expenses or  0.1 million financed from Exchequer advances.(27  These figures exclude deficit grants of  132.4 million for British Railways and 1.5 million for British Waterways, but even so do not give directly a self-fl nanclng ratio as borrowings may be affected by changes in vorking capital requirements.(3)   Includes  1.8 million advanced to finance market purchases of the Board&apos;s own stockfor cancellation.(4)   Reflects only part of the capital reconstruction under the Coal Industry Act 1965.Approximately  200 million remained at 26th March 1966 to be written off from theReserve Fund.(5)  For the calendar year 1965.(6)The N.C.B. &apos;s financial year ran from 28/3/65 to 26/3/66.
Table nationalised INDUSTRIES!   FINANCIAL OBJECTIVES 3IndustryOb.1eoti.vePeriod CoveredElectricity Boards(England and Wales)s* So.y olioN.S.H.E.B.6-as BoardsPost OfficeBo 0* A. C.B.E.A.British RailwaysLondon Transport board national Coal Boardaverage12.2$ gross (A)12.1$ gross (A)(see footnote C)average10.2% gross (A)8$ net (B)12^6 net (B)6j  net (B)1962-63(E)1962-631966-671966-671962-63 - 1966-67001963-64 - 1967-681966-67 - 1969-701963-64 - 1967-68have the statutory obligation of reducing their deficit and breaking even as soonas possible(see footnote D) 1963-67to break even after interest and depreciationincluding  10 Billion a year to cover thedifference between depreciation at historiccost and replacement cost (F)Targets for the British Airports Authority and the British transport docks Board are now under discussion.NotesAo    Income before interest and depreciation, expressed as a percentageof average net assetsB.    Income before interest but after depreciation at.,historic cost,expressed as a percentage of average net assets.Co    As an interim measure the N.S.H.E.B. agreed to apply such tariffincreases as would give a similar percentage increase in revenue asthe tariff increases applied by the S.S.E.B.Do    L.X.B&apos;s objective was to earn an average balance of revenue of  4 million a year, after interest and depreciation at historic cost.This was equivalent to % net.   L.T.B&apos;s target is however in abeyance in view of the Board&apos;s financial position.E. The Minister of Power announced on 19th December 1966 in answer to a parliamentary Question (O.R. Cols. 232-233) that the objectives ofthese two industries would continue in 1967-68.   New objectives areto be negotiated for these industries to operate from 1st April 1968.F. The N.C.B. were relieved of their objeotive temporarily in April 1965but this has now been revived and will continue in 1967-68.
NATIONALISED   INDUSTRIESNet Income as a Percentage of Average Net AssetsTable 3tit Officedonal Coal Board (2)tctricity Council andSards in England and Wales,S,H,e.B. (3)LkfiJ). (3)(5)Su Council and area boards],0i.C. (4)J&amp;A. (k)irltlsn Railways Board (1)Won Transport Board C1)Jrltish Transport DocksJwrd (1)British Waterways Board (1)pnsport Holding Company (1)jMtish Transport(omission (1)fill Nationalised Industries1955	1956	1957	1958	1959	I960	1961	1962	1963	1964	1965-56	-57	-58	-59	-60	-61	-62	-63	-61.	-65	%	%	56	%	%	%	%		%	%	%4*4	6.9	7*5	6 JO	8.6	8.5	6,5	6.2	7.8	6.9	8.1	6.7	3.5	2.6	1.6	2.3	3.2	5.2	6.7	4.9	0.1U.6	4.7	5.0	5.6	5.5	5.0	5.5	6.1	6.9	6.5	7.01.8	3.1	3.3	3.6	3.9	4.3	5.1	5.0	k.2	4.7	5*04.6	5.6	4.3	4.0	4.3	4.7	4.9	5.8	5.6	5.6	5.43.6	4.1	4.0	3.3	3.3	4.0	4.3	4.6	5.2	5.9	5.43.3	2.9	-1.2	-7.1	3.4	2.7	-26.5	-12.1	-6.6	15.2	9.67.8	4.6	7.6	4.8	7.7	6.5	0.7	2.1	8.3	5.8	5.4mm	-	-	-	-	-	mm	mm	-4.1	-3.3	-3.7m	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	4.5	4.0	2.8-	-	-	-	-	-		-	5.2	5.3	4.9-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-6.3	-5.9	-4.9-	-	mm	-	-	-	-	-	9.5	11.6	10.91.9	0.2	-0.6	-2.1	-1.3	-2.1*	- 2.9	- 3.1	am	-	an2.9	3.6	3.1	2.6	34	2.8	2.2	2.9	4.1	4.3	4.1(1)  On a calendar year basis.(2)   In 1963 the accounting changed from calendar to financial years and the figures for thatyear have been adjusted to represent a 12-month period. ,(3)   In 1964 N.S.H.E.B. and S.S.EJ3. had a fifteen-month accounting year on changing, from acalendar to a financial year basis.   The figure have been adjusted to represent atwelve-month period.(k)  Allowance has been made In the B.0.A.C and B.E.A. figures for prior year adjustment.    This is substantial in t e case of B.O. A.C.(5)  S.S.E.B. was formed in 1955 and the first accounting period was 9 months only.    The figures have been adjusted to represent a 12-month period.(6)  Net Income is Gross Income less depredation at historic cost and forseeable obsolescence.
Table 4 322NATIONALISED INDUSTRIESGross Income as a Percentage of Average Net Assets1955 1956 1957 1958 1959 1960 1961 1962 1963 1964 1965-56      -57      -53    -59      -60   -61      -62   -63      -64   -65      -66iOff Icetlonal Coal Board (2)ictriclty Council andSards in England and WalesS.H.E.B. (3),U.B. (3) (5)Council and Area Gas Boards.O.A.C. (4)IU (4)British Railways Board (1)loafon Transport Board (1)Srlttsh Transport Docks Board (1)British Gateways Board (1)transport Holding Company (i)British Transport Commission (1)111 Nationalised Industries%	%	%	%	%	%	%	%	38	%	%10.0	11.6	12.2	12.6	13.2	13.0	11.0	10.8	12.4	11.4	12.77.8	14.0	10.8	9.5	8.2	9.4	10.8	14.3	15.2	13.7	7.79.2	9.3	9.6	10.5	10.6	10.2	10.7	11.3	12.0	11.6	12.13.3	4.6	4.8	5.0	5.4	5.8	6.8	6.6	5.9	6,5	6.911.0	12.0	11.4	9.8	10.0	10.0	9.9	10.3	10.3	10.9	10.97.3	8.4	8.3	7.6	7.7	8.6	8.9	9.2	9.7	10.5	9.812.1	12.3	6.5	5.7	12.7	13.7	-8.4	8.1	11.1	31.5	23.719.6	15.3	17.3	13.5	15.8	14.7	10.4	11.5	17.1	17.5	17.7-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-	-1.0	-0.1	-0.6-	-	-	-	-		y\   -	-	7.8	6.9	5.4-	-	-	-	-	-	mm	-	8.0	8.0	7.6-	. -	-	am	-	-			-1.1	-1.1	-	-	m	m	-	mm	-	mm	15.9	18.1	17.64.1	2.7	2.4	1.0	2.3	1.3	0,6	0.2	mm	-	-7.0	7,8	7.5	7.2	7.8	7.6	7.1	7.9	9.0	9.4	9.0(1)  On a calendar year basis.(2)  In 1963 the accounting changed from calendar to financial years and the figure for that year has been adjusted to represent a 12-month period.(3)   In 1964 N.S.H.E.B. and S.S.E.B. had a fifteen-month accounting year on changing froa acalendar to a financial year basis.    The figures have been adjusted to represent a twelve-month period.(4)  Allowance has been made in the B.O.A.C. and B.E.A. flgires for prior year adjustments.    This is substantial in the case of B.O.A.C,(5)  S.S.E.B. was formed In 1955 and the first accounting period was 9 months only.    The figures have been adjusted to represent a 12-aonth period.(6)    Gross Income covers trading surplus and other Income before changing depreciation,taxation and interest on borrowings.General note on TablesTables 3 and 4 show net and gross income respectively as a percentage of average net assets.Industry by industry, in a new series which replaces that usad in Cmnd. 1337.    The new series is more closely related to the financial results of the industries as they appear In their published annualaccounts.The figures in Tables 1, 3 and 4 have been compiled for the purposes of oo apart son on a standardisedbasis from information In the annual accounts of the Industries and differ in sobs respects from theindustries&apos; own presentation of their rigures which use the differing bases of calculation of grossand net returns agreed when the financial objectives were settled.


</content>
</cab>
