<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/212/0 images: 55-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                       C A B I N E T.I                    TiiiC cihngNai .g, g. .01.               21emorandum prepared in the Treasury.        (Circulated in accordance with Cabinet  3  (3J),0 ouclusion 5)        1.      The Consulting Engineers invited &quot;by the Channel Tunneli        Committee to ^ive expert advice reoort that no definite        opinion can be piven on the  feasibility of the construction        of  a traffic tunnel until the ground has been tested by a        pilot tunnel,  the cost of which they estimate at  5,600,000.. IA       2.      It is suggested that  expenditure of this  magnitude on        investigating  the mere possibility oi the work can only be        justified on the assumption  that  the * advantages  to result        frera the completed work may  be very great,        3.      In estimating the advantages, it is not  enough to shww        that such a tunnely ii it could be made, can be  run as a        profit-making  concern.    It  is necessary also to take account        of  the amount  of capital already  invested which  will be        rendered unproductive.   The  one institution that might be        expected to be interested in,  ana likely to praxit directly        by  the scheme,  is the Southern Railway.   In their case a        large part of  the capital sunk in their stations at Doverr. J       and Folkestone will cease to earn interest.   Their boats        now running on the Dover-Calais and Folkestone-  Boulogne        routes and possibly some running  on the other routes will be        withdrawn, and the capital invested in them will be lost at                     -I       least in part.   Similar considerations.apply in  a minor        degree to the  Harwich route  of the London and Forth    astern        Railway.   The  shipping lines established in the  short sea        trades may be  expected to suffer also.H                                  -l-
           4.     In the present circumstances, the amount of employment           that may be expected to be created by any proposed enterprise           is &quot;a relevant consideration.   In this respect the Channel Tunnel           proposal is unpromising,  he Consult-in- Engineers estimate that           during the 5 years assumed lor the construction ox the pilot and           drainage tunnels,250 men will be employed directly and 7d0 in-           dirsctly on this side,and during the 3 years needed to construct           and equip the main tunnels,  1 5Q directly and 4,000 indirectly.           These, though not negligible,  are not large numbers,and against           them must be set the amount  of labour displaced.  The CommitteeParagraph  sair that none will be displaced.   But this is an unreasonable   133.           assumption,and they are in fact convicted out of their own  paragraph   129.&quot;   mouths, since thoy also say that the extension of ?ar&apos;;:eston Quay           now under consideration by the London and Worth Pastern heilway           will be  deferred until the fate of the Channel proposal is known.           It is obvious that from the  start of z e construction of the pilot           tunnel  there is  no company likely to bo affected but will restrict           to the utmost expenditure on she provision of new steamers,new           landing  facilities and harbours and piers generally.  The unem-           ployment direct  and indirect  thus result in./ may go far to counter-           balance  the employment direct and Indirect estimated&apos;to be created           if the  scheme is adopted. Moreover, supposing the tunnel is           constructed there will be a  permanent loss of employment by men           now in  the service of the Southern Railway Company,the DoverParagraphs 99 and    harbour  doard and the shipping Companies engaged in srert sea trades.  133.            5.      It is certain that there will be a loss of capital           now profitably employed.  It  is -probable that there wili be no           increase of employment.   These who support the scheme should           be able  to point to clear and definite advantages outweighingParagraph  these disadvantages.   But the report is significantly barren   134.           of any  attempt to show such.   It  expressly disclaims any           attempt  to weigh the advantages likely to accrue to one set
of individuals against the dieadvantages likely to accrue to otherso  &apos;i&apos;he case rests as Lord Ebblsham points outin his minute- of dissent on two arguments : -                        fa! that the funnel must promote an                    increase in the general flow of passengers                    and goods traffic, with consequent benefit                    to tho commuhity;                        (b) that the experience of the past                    teaches that, although the transitional                    period may be accompanied by hardship, in                    the end major improvements in transport                    are of economic advantage;6.     These are propositions that might have beenenunciated by anyone without any inquiry.   Neither is new.As regards the first, it may be admitted that there willbe an increase in the flow of passengers and goods, butit is relevant to consider of what nature the increase islikely to be.   In so far as the number si British passen-gers going abroad for purposes of pleasure is increased,there will be an economic loss to this country,  moreover,at present some three Britons crocs to every one foreigner...If this proportion is merely maintained there will again.be a loss by reason of any increase:  it will require avery substantial alteration In the proportion, for the likelihood of which there is no evidence, if any appreciable benefit is t.-g accrue.     The Goods traffic most.likely to be encouraged bythe construction of the tunnel is the import trade
in fragile and perishable articles.   They c-onsist frr---..the most part of luxury imports of fruit., flowers and vegetables.          It d^es net seem that the  evidence taken bythe Committee supports their view that the increase willbe beneficial.   As regards goods traffic the  GlasgowChamber of Csirnerce indeed consider  that the tunnel,though it will not assist the heavy  trades betweenGlasgow and the Continent, might bo  of advantage totraders In the Midlands and the South of England..   Butthe Birmingham and Dover Chambers are definitely opposedto the scheme.   For the manufacturerst &quot;such  expressions of opinion as we have received are for the most parteither adverse *r indifferent to the idea of a tunnel!! and manufacturers are apprehensive that  it might st:ix .ilatethe import of foreign goods to the detriment of their own production.&quot;   As to the shippers &quot;the Companies engagedin running cargo b^ats on the cross-channe1 short seatrades are alarmed, at the prospect of a channel tunnel,&quot;Agriculture, including the Ministry  of Agriculture andFisheries, is distinctly apprehensive of the effect of a tunnel on certain classes of predu.ee, though the reporttries to show that this appi-ehension is exaggerated.The railways arc unenthuslastio.   The Southern Railway &quot;and the London and North Eastern Railway emphasise the losses which they will incur.   The  Southern Railwayanticipate a loss of about  5C0,000 per annual, profitsnow earned by their steamer services.
They will also apparently have to meet the liability under their guarantee of. the interest on certain redeemableDebenture stock; raised, by the Dover Harbour Board, and theywill be obliged to incur additional capital expenditure to accommodate their system to the use of a tunnel    On theother hand, since the gouthern Railway will probably becalled upon to operate the tunnel, they should be able as a set-off to obtain favourable terms from the Channel TunnelCompanies,but insofar as they dq this, the cost of thescheme will be increased.7.    The second proposition, namely that in the endmajor improvements in transport are of economic advantage,is not of much help in considering the present scheme.I\TP doubt the Committee have in mind e.g.  the introductionof steam navigation ^r of railways, bu&apos;1&quot; these  arerevolutionary changes of a general hind,  to which thsopening of a tunnel is not really comparable.     Moreovernot all enterprises which have been claimed as &quot;major improvements in transport&quot; have proved to be economic advantages, eg.  canals, while of recent innovations,airships and airplanes have yet to prove themselves.8.    These &quot;arguments&quot; go no way towards justifying theCommittee1s conclusions which may be described as ant riumpi1  of hope over evi denc e .9.    Certain alternatives to the tunnel are discussed inthe Report at some length, but the possibility of making theexisting steamer service more adequate at a cost considerably less than the  30 millions or so contemplated withequanimity by the Committee is not ex-,mined.   Are the shipsas fast as they might be?   Are the facilities  forembarkation and disembarkation of passengers and goods asperfect as they should be?   Could the Harbours be dredged
       to take somewhat larger ships?   Could not the frontier formal-       ities &quot;be regularly carried out  in the train instead of on the       quay?   - There are questions which perhaps  the Committee       considered to be ruled out by their terms of reference but they        cannot be ignored b; the Government in taking, a decision.       10.   One point remaining, deserves special attention.       The Report of the Committee is  considerably more, optimistic as to       the feasibility of the construction of the tunnel than is       the report of the Consulting Engineers, who gave expert and       highly paid advice.    The Engineers say -            &quot;The feasibility of construction of the tunnel depends -             upon the nature of the ground to be tunneled through.             I&apos;To definite opinion oan be given until the ground             has been proved by the construction of the pilot74.          tunnel.   Difficulties would no doubt be encountered             but we hesitate to say that they would be insurmount-             able.&quot;                  The Committee say -            &quot;On the available evidence it appears probable that thegraph         geological and engineering difficulties likely to be? (2).        encountered could, be suff.icie.utly overcome.    There             must however remain an element of doubt regarding the             practicability of contracting a tunnel until the             proposed pilot tunnel, estimated to cost  3,600,000             has been successfully driven right across the channel.&quot;                  The contrast needs no comment.       11.   In addition, it may be observed that the Committee       consider that the work should be carried out by private       enterprise^  and should not be accorded any special financial       assistance by Government.   It appears that the English and       French Channel Tunnel Companies propose to find the capital       required in equal shares, and that the English Channel Tunnel       Company  in the first instance would confine themselves to an       issue of ordinary shares sufficient to cover the cost of the       English  section of the pilot tunnel.   Considering only this
 first  stage,  it  seems very  doubtful whether  a  Company will be  able  to  raise the sum of between  2,500,000  and  3,000,000  needed  to  cover  the English  share of  the  cost by  an  issue of ordinary shares  In  this  country for1 the purpose  of  carrying  out work  which may,  In the end,  only prove  that  a  traffic  tunnel is not feasible.   It  is certainly true that  an  issue  for so speculative  an object to  attract  investors  would  have to offer an exceptionally.hig.h rate of  interest.    In spite  of  the C ommit t e e &apos; s re- commendation  the probability  is that, if His Majesty&apos;!, s Government  favour  or  acquiesce in  the proposals  of the Report,  strong pressure will  be brought upon them  to make themselves  responsible  for  the exploratory work.  If the scheme is found  not to  be feasible, there will be  a  dead loss which  will  fall  on the State: if  the scheme  is pro- nounced  to  be feasible  the  State may  eventually get  some return for  its initial  outlay, &quot;teut it will then fee very difficult to  dissociate his Majesty&apos;a Government from res- ponnibility for  the scheme  and any interest  that can re- present  that  the scheme is  to it.&quot;  disadvantage will  be vocal with claims for  compensation.     12.    To sum  up, it  is suggested that the conclusion of  the Majority  Report  that the construction of  a  Channel Tunnel would be  of economic advantage to this  country is net supported by any  evidence of concrete and  substantial advantage.   No  material reduction in the time taken on the journey is claimed.   No  decrease in fares is  suggested. Even transhipment  of  goods  from truck to truck is not avoided. Manufacturing, agricultural,  shipping and railway Interests have no  enthusiasm for  this scheme,.   The benefit to unemployment  is  /
negligible or negative .    The feasibility? of the enterprise is estimated, more optimistically in the report thanby the Consulting Engineers.     No attempt has been madeto show that the existing cross-channel service is inadequateor (if it is inadequate) that it could not be made adequateby an expenditure which would be insignificant in comparisonwith the cost of the tunnel.    In the circumstances theTreasury are of opinion that, so&apos;far as regards economic grounds, the evidence furnished is net such as to justifythe Government in offering any financial support orencouragement to the project.Treasury Chambers,S.W.12T.1I May, 193C.

</content>
</cab>
