<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/212/0 images: 481-483</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 j o. ,uDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .0 R E X.193(30).COPY NO.CABINET.UNEMPLOYMENT POLICY,     The accompanying Recommendations of the Conferenceof Ministers appointed by the Cabinet at their Meeting-on May 8th, 1930, (Cabinet 26(30) Conclusion 2) are circulated by direction of the Prime Minister.                           (Sgd.)   M.P.A. HANKEY.                             Secretary to the Cabinet.2, v; hit e ha 11 Gardens, 3eW.l,      June 3rd, 1930.
                UNi^lJOYnEUT POLICY.     The Conference of Ministers appointed by the Cabineton May 8th, 1930, met to-day, and agreed to make thefollowing recommendations to the Cabinet:-     (1) That a Conference of Local Authorities should be         convened for Tuesday, June 17th,  at 10.0 a.m.,         to be presided over by the Prime Minister.     (2) That it should be a one dayTs Conference and it         should be asked to appoint a Consultative         Committee which should meet at once under the         Chairmanship of a Cabinet Minister and get         down to details.     (3) That invitations should be sent in the name         of the Prime Minister to the following bodies:               Authority.                     Approximate,               -*-                      Number ml              -,  ,                            Delegates.           England.                            M-Lj-*           The County Councils Association.   Up to 60           Municipal Corporations Associa-                                 tion.        &quot;   &quot; 60           Urban District Councils Associa-                                 tion.        &quot;   &quot; 40           Rural District Councils Associa-                                 tion.        &quot;   &quot; 30           London County Council.             &quot;   &quot; 10           Metropolitan Borough Councils              Standing Joint Committee.       &quot;   &quot; 15           Scotland.           Convention of Boroughs.            &quot;   &quot; 30           County Councils Association.       &quot;   &quot; 15    (4) That an Agenda should be prepared on the        lines of Appendix I and circulated in advance.(3d.)   J.  RAMSAY MACDONALD.             Chairman.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,    June 3rd, 1930.
o e ftL &apos;y. 0                      AlfPa^IX____I.       gQIHTS TO 3a COHSIDBHfJD IH OQflJSI&amp;LlOfl UITH THE              ffOR MjSETIHG- WITH LOCAL AUTHORITIES.1.   What can be done to expedite tho  progress of v,ork  already      approved and in hand? .   What can be done to advance ether works or sections  of      works included in the local authority&apos;s programme but      not yet be gun?3.   Have Highway authorities any suggestions to mike for      enlarging existing programmes by the  addition of  works      which could bo put in hand at an early date?4.   Are there any Glasses of work not covered by existing      programmes which Highway Authorities  could usefully      put in hand with assistance from the Bead .?acd?5 -   What particular suggestions can Local Authorities make      for expediting procedure and removing cause of delay,      under the following, among other, heads:-(a)Acquiring and obtaining possession of land *(b)Engagement of additional staff and engagement of outside experts and consultants.(o)Arrangements for transaction of business during the summer recess, e.g. by delegation of powers.

</content>
</cab>
