<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/212/0 images: 502-508</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
364IIS DOCUMENT. IS THB PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT&apos;)P.  197 (30).                        CAB I M E T.                     THE CHANNEL TUNNEL.             The accompanying COPY of the Statement announcing        the decision of the Government in regard to the Channel        Tunnel, .which has been issued as a White Paper (to-day)        in accordance with Cabinet 31(30), Conclusion 6(a), Is        circulated for purposes of record..                             (Signed) T. JONES,                                 Deput7r Secretary to the Cabinet.con NO.Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1*  June 6th, 1930.
   THE     CHANNEL             &quot;TUNNELSTATEMENT   OF   policy presented to Parliament by Command of His Majesty,                   June 1930                       LONDON: PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICETO BE PURCHASED DIRECTLY FROM H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE AT THE FOLLOWING ADDRESSES:    ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAV, LONDON, W.C.2; 120. GEORGE STREET, EDINBURGH;        YORK STREET, MANCHESTER; 1, ST. ANDREW&apos;S CRESCENT, CARDIFF;                15, DONEGALL SQUARE WEST, BELFAST;                  OR THROUGH ANY BOOKSELLER.                        I93O                      Price id. NetCmd.  3.591
The Channel Tunnel.STATEMENT OF POLICY.   THE recent  comprehensive enquiry  into  the question of thChannel Tunnel was initiated by  the  late Prime Minister,  aftcconsultation with the Leaders of the Opposition Parties,  in  Apri1929.   It  differed  from  the  four  previous enquiries  unclertakeiduring the present  century in this respect, that whereas on  thosioccasions the military and economic aspects were dealt with simultaneously the latter rather perfunctorily- in the present  instanathe  enquiry  was  begun  by  an exhaustive  investigation of tineconomic and  civil aspects of the project.   The Government wish to  take this  opportunity  to  place  01record their  thanks to the  Channel  Tunnel Committee  for tinthoroughness and impartiality of their enquiry.  It  is unnecessary to enter into  the  details  of  the  Channel  Tunne]  scheme,  athese are set forth in the  published Report.  The Committee read the broad conclusion that &apos;&apos; the construction of a Channel Tunnelby creating new traffic and thus  increasing  trade, would  be oeconomic advantage to this country.&quot;   One of the five signatories to the Report, however, dissents fronthis  view, and &quot;is opposed to the  scheme on economic grounds.&apos;   The weight of the majority conclusion, however,  is diminish^by the important qualifications and hesitations of the Report, ansupporters  of the tunnel  must be disappointed to find how man;elements of doubt and  uncertainty  exist, and  how lukewarm is tlisupport to the project from trade and industry.   If such a project iproceeded with it must command a backing which is sure of  itseland is not only lukewarm.   The main element of uncertainty is in regard to the feasibilitof construction.  The three great firms  of engineers consulted bthe Channel  Tunnel Committee  state  in  their Report that  &quot; ndefinite opinion can  be given until  the ground has been proved b;the construction of the pilot tunnel.  Difficulties would no doubbe encountered, but we hesitate  to say that they would be insurmountable.&quot;   The Channel Tunnel Committee are rather more optimistic amexpress the.view that &quot;on the. available evidence it appears  probablthat  the geological and engineering difficulties likely to be encouiitered coukhbe successfully overcome,&quot; but they point out that  thenmust &quot;remain an element of doubt regarding the practicability oconstructing the Tunnel until the proposed pilot tunnel, estimateito cost   5,600,000,  has  been successfully driven right  across thChannel.&quot;   If  this  operation were&apos; successfully  accomplished and  it estimated to take five&apos; years the main tunnel  could then be con
strueted at a further cost estimated at  25,000,000.  Even this largefigure, however, does not include the cost of the exchange stations,the open approaches from the mouth, of the Tunnel to the exchangestations, the  electric locomotives,  the. necessary rolling stock,  the electric generating stations and the land required.  The,total cost,therefore, would considerably exceed the  80,600,000 provided forin the Committee&apos;s Report for  the pilot and main tunnels.  Inaddition, a considerable amount of capital invested in the  existingcross-Channel system would  be rendered unproductive.   Nothing can be done unless the Government licence the building of the  tunnel, and to that extent they make themselves responsiblefor encouraging the public to subscribe to the funds required.  Ifthe completion of the work were delayed owing to  a failure to getthe public to  provide the necessary sums the Government, howevercareful they may be to warn the promoters that in no circumstances will public money be provided to complete the work, cannot escapesome  moral obligation to see the project through.  What justifica-tion is there for the Government to incur such serious responsibility on. such an uncertain report?   Once  the Channel  Tunnel  is constructed,   the  Committeeanticipate no difficulty in  regard  to its operation and upkeep.   The Committee believe &apos;&apos; that the  Channel Tunnel  could be built,  maintained  and  operated  by private  enterprise  at a  cost which  would  permit of the  traffic through it being conveyed at ratesnot higher  than those at present in  force on the  short  cross-Channel route.&quot;      ....   There is no suggestion  of lower rates.   A careful study of the  Report  reveals  a  conspicuous absence ofenthusiastic.support to the scheme from any large trade, industry or interest.   The farming  community, especially in the  south  andsouth-east, are reported to be apprehensive,  though the Committeebelieve their  apprehension to be exaggerated.  Nevertheless, thoseapprehensions have not been allayed, for  since the publication ofthe Report, the Government have received a strong representationfrom, the National  Farmers&apos; Union in favour of the rejection ofthe Tunnel proposal.   The bodies representing industry and trade who were consulted by the  Channel  Tunnel  Committee  &quot;have  in  the main  been reluctant to  commit themselves to any definite view on the effectof a Channel Tunnel.&quot;   Chambers of Commerce, with certain exceptions, are on general grounds in  favour  of its   construction, but  this is &quot;subject to a reservation on its possible  adverse effect on  trade.&quot; manufacturers are apprehensive  that  it  might  stimulate   the import of  foreigngoods  to the  detriment of  their own production.  In fact,  that  partof the enquiry is reported as indecisive.   Naturally, the shipping &quot; Companies engaged in running cargoboats  on the cross-Channel  short sea  trades  are  alarmed at theprospect  of  a Channel  Tunnel.&quot;  The  general  attitude  of theRailway Company principally concerned is reported to be  &quot; one ofcaution.&quot;  In short, nowhere in the Report is there to be found any   Wt. -2000 6/30 F.O.P. 21192                             B 2
sign of a strong demand for the Tunnel  from any of  the  majorindustries or interests.                             -  , .    ,     ,   That  the  Tunnel  would  largely  increase  the  number. oipassengers crossing the Channel  is generally admitted, but doubtshave  been expressed as to whether  this will  prove, an  economic advantage  to this country.   In  so far as the number  of Britishpassengers going abroad for purposes of pleasure is increased, therewill  be  an :economic loss- to this  country.   It  will  require  asubstantial  alteration in  the proportion  of  foreign  to Britishpassengers, of which there:is no evidence, if any appreciable benefit is to accrue.-            :l               -.            . , -  &apos;   , .    ,   From the point of view of relief to unemployment, the resultsof the enquiry are especially disappointing in comparison&apos; with theexpenditure involved.&apos;   During  the  five&apos;  years  required for  theconstruction of the pilot tunnel only 250 men would be  employeddirectly  and  750 indirectly.   In  this phase the men ,engaged inthe tunnel workings would, owing, to the peculiar character  of thework,  consist mainly of specialists,  and could not be drawn fromthe general ranks  of  the unemployed.  During the following threeyears 1,550 men would be employed  directly- and 4,500  indirectly.It has been calculated that the total labour^ direct  and indirect, tobe employed annually for the first five years,, on the English side,is only equivalent  to  that which could be provided  by the expendi-ture of about  250,000 per annum  on road construction in  thiscountry.   Further, it seems probable that,  from the start of  the eight years  of  the  construction period, and, indeed,-  during the pre-liminary period of  negotiation and  preparation,-^which must  be considerable, there is no Company. likely to be affected but  willrestrict  to the  utmost  expenditure   on  new  steamers, landingfacilities, and harbours  and piers generally,  and this is  confirmed by a statement in  the Report that one Railway Company  is aireadyunderstood to have deferred  a decision in  regard to  a proposed extension until  it  is  known  whether  or (not the  Channel: Tunnelscheme is to  go forward.   Thus, the unemployment, direct  and indirect, may  go  some way to  counterbalance the  employmentcreated by the  scheme.                .&apos;    :;  i               .&apos;   ..   The  question  has been  raised  whether  it  is  desirable that capital should  be sunk in this  enterprise,  at the present time,having regard to the small effect on  employment, i to. the fact thatthe investment would not even begin  to fructify for a decade, .andto  the  body  of  opinion  that  when . the . rationalisation  andreconditioning of British industries (from  which a speedier, returncan  be secured) is seriously  undertaken^  the  subscription of,,thiscapital will have an  adverse effect on our industrial requirements.    The  Government have received many .other criticisms of thiskind, but enough has been said to show that no overwhelming: casein favour  of the  construction of the Tunnel, has been  made ,outon  economic grounds.,                 . .  .. .    .:, .       .,&apos; ,... f    The  Report has  been  examined  in its, economic  aspects: bothby; the Economic Advisory Council and by  the Government Depart-
merits concerned.  There is general agreement that *the evidence inthe Report regarding the&apos;advantages of a Channel Tunnel&quot; to thecountry  as  a^ whole is&apos; not--sufficient  to  justify  His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment  either  in  itself  constructing  the  Tunnel  or  givingfinancial assistance &apos; to veiiable it - to  be constructed.    &apos;   This leads up to the military aspects.1 &quot;And here the government consider that the military aspect also has its economic side.   If this island  is  to  be&apos;connected with  the Continent by. a  tunnel, theGovernments advisers on defence matters have always insisted, and still insist, that it shall be adequately protected,  and,  as will nowbe seen,  this would cost a great deal of  money.     -         &apos; - &apos;   The Governments first  aim  was to ascertain the  nature and cost of  the  defences required.   The investigation  has been verythorough, and that  is why  it has  not been possible to  issue this statement earlier.   The  whole area has been reconnoitred on the spot by the General  Staff, and,  besides the Service Departments,various scientific advisers of the Government have been  consulted.   In  a  short  statement of this  kind no attempt can  be made  to describe the multiplicity of the forms of attack to which the tunnel would  be exposed  under modern  conditions,  nor  the  ingeniousmeans  proposed for its protection.  It may  however be mentioned,that the provision of an adequate defence to a  Tunnel,  emerging,as contemplated in the Report, near the coast,  is so costly and sounsatisfactory  that the military  authorities press strongly  for analternative site further inland,  which, however,  :is understood  to involve heavy  additional  expenditure  on  railway construction.Apart from this, it is estimated that the capital cost of the necessarydefences wrould not be much less than from  1 million to  2 million,according to the site selected for  the  Tunnel  and its exchangestations.  In addition, there would  be a heavy annual charge forupkeep  and maintenance of the garrison, including additional AirForces.  Moreover,  Governments would&apos;be pressed to keep the defences abreast of the march of military progress,  and that would entail from time to  time additional expenditure.   One thing to which the  Governments advisers strongly object is  the acceptance of a new and expensive military  commitment  ata time when our imperial  defence forces have been reduced to a level which leaves  no margin beyond our  existing commitments.So long as there are great military establishments  in Europe, theTunnel, if not adequately  defended, becomes  a potential danger;if  it is properly defended,  a military commitment is incurred,  inwhich considerable forces would be locked up and immobilised.   The views of the Governments military advisers may be summed up in a phrase attributed to the late  Lord Balfour : &quot;So  long  asthe ocean remains our friend, do not let us deliberately destroy its power to help us.&quot;   Such,  in bare outline, was the case as presented to a meeting ofthe Committee  of Imperial Defence on the 29th May.   As it isessential  in  an enterprise  where  heavy preliminary  expenditure would  have  to be  incurred  by the  promoters  on works  of anexploratory  character,  that  as  far  as  is  humanly possible, the
-decision&apos;should be.a national one, not likely to be upset by changes of Government, the Prime Minister invited the two former PrimeMinisters  to be present, and they were good  enough to attend themeeting.  They were supplied, not only with the papers: preparedfor the  Committee of Imperial Defence, but also with those of theEconomic Advisory  Council, and in fact  with all the material onthe subject at the disposal of the Government.    The Committee of Imperial Defence were unable to discover asingle advantage from a military point of view which  would follow from  the  construction of a  Channel Tunnel.   Onthe  contrary,  itwould result  only.in an increased military commitment,  involvingin certain happily remote contingencies  an element of danger, toprovide against which   a heavy capital  and annual  expenditure would have to be  incurred.    Following  on  the  meeting  of  the  Committee  of  ImperialDefence,  the  whole matter was  examined  by  the Government,which, in  addition  to economic and military considerations, reviewedpossible diplomatic  reactions.   Having regard  to  the element of doubt as  to  the feasibility  of construction,   the weakness of theeconomic  case, the  great cost,  the  long  period  before which thecapital  expended could  fructify, and the small amount of employ-ment  provided, the Government have  come to the conclusion thatthere  is no justification for a reversal of the policy  pursued by successive Governments for nearly fifty years in  regard to theChannel Tunnel.June 4, 1930.

</content>
</cab>
