<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 244-249</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
!THIS  DOCUMENT  IS   THE  PROPERTY OP  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  June 1950SECRET Copy No. 3 2CP. (50) 12615 th June, 1950:    CABINETCOUNCIL OF EUROPE:   FOURTH SESSION OF COMMITTEEOF minister&apos;s memorandum by the Minister of state circulate, for the information of the Cabinet, the following account of theFourth Session of the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe, which washeld in the Ministry for Foreign Affairs in Paris on 3rd June. The Agenda isattached as Annex I.2. The Chairman of the Committee was General Plastiras, Prime Ministerand Foreign Minister of Greece, who is fluent in no language but his own. after a short introductory speech he handed over the conduct of the meeting to hisPermanent Under-Secretary, M. Politis, and took no further active part in theproceedings except to pronounce them closed. The Belgian Foreign Minister was represented by M. Duvieusart (then Minister of Economic Affairs and now PrimeMinister) and the Danish, Icelandic and Swedish Foreign Ministers by the headsof their Missions in Paris. The Secretary of State was represented byMr. Ernest Davies.3.   The decisions of the Committee may be summarised as follows:  (1) The Committee of Ministers approved the Conclusions of the JointOrganisation which met in London on 18th May (see CP. (50) 116);and the Secretary-General was instructed to inform the Chairman ofthe Consultative Assembly accordingly.(2) The following decisions were taken in regard to the report of the Committeeof Ministers (under Article 19 of the Statute) to the consultative assembly:  (i) The Committee had before them a draft by the Secretary-Generalcontaining, in addition to a factual summary of the Committee&apos;sactivity during the past year, various proposals for the futurework of the Council of Europe and for the inclusion of various items in the Agenda of the Consultative Assembly. These were considered unsuitable for inclusion in a document which underthe terms of the Statute is meant to be a statement of pastactivities. On our suggestion, and with strong support from most of the other Delegations, it was agreed that the reportby the Secretary-General should confine itself strictly to facts.The Secretary-General was instructed to recast his draft,eliminating from it the passages to which the Committee hadtaken exception.(ii) The proposals of the Secretary-General for the future work of theCouncil and any other lead which the Committee of ministers may wish to give to the Assembly will be embodied, if this isthought necessary, in a separate document. A draft of thiswill also be prepared by the Secretary-General and will besubmitted to members of the Committee of Ministers for their comments.38877B
(iii) Officials representing the Foreign Ministers will meet, probablyat the beginning of July, and approve the factual reportmentioned at (2) (i) above. They will also give prehminaryconsideration to the draft paper mentioned at (ii) before it goesto the Committee of Ministers on 3rd August.(3) No discussion took place on the Agenda for the next Assembly, but thead hoc Joint Organisation of members of the Committee of ministers and the Assembly will meet in Strasbourg on 24th June to consider this.Member Governments have been requested to submit any suggestionsthey may have by that date.(4) At the suggestion of M. Schuman, the delicate question of the position ofAssociate Members was deferred until the next meeting of the Com-mittee of Ministers in August. There is no objection to this, since there are no questions connected with the impending entry into theCouncil as Associate Members of Germany and the Saar which call for immediate solution; and the danger that discussion of the matter might leak and prejudice the course of the debate in the GermanBundestag next week was thus avoided.(5) Satisfactory arrangements about relations between the Organisation for european Economic Co-operation and the Council of Europe havingbeen made the previous day at the O.E.E.C. Council, the committee approved them. It was decided, on M. Schuman&apos;s suggestion, to acceptthe report of the O.E.E.C. Sub-Committee (the text of which is at annex II) as the directive laying down relations between the two bodies.The result is that documents will be exchanged and that O.E.E.C.experts will be able, subject to detailed safeguards, to be heard by theSecretary-General of the Council of Europe in the presence of Membersof the AssemblyY Committees, the United Kingdom representative atthe O.E.E.C. Council meeting (Mr. Gaitskell) having withdrawn theUnited Kingdom reservation on this last point. Mr. Davies made ashort statement on the lines of that made by Mr. Gaitskell to theO.E.E.C. Council on the previous day.(6) The Committee received rather coldly and postponed consideration of aproposal by the Secretary-General to establish branch offices of the secretariat in various capitals, including London.4. The meeting was uneventful and its results, so far as they went, satis-factory. In particular, it was fortunate that any embarrassing discussion of theposition of Germany was avoided. M. Schuman was helpful and co-operativethroughout. The press paid little attention to the Committee&apos;s proceedings, partly because they took place on a Saturday afternoon, but chiefly because they wereovershadowed by the discusions on the &quot; Schuman Plan.&quot;K. G. Y.Foreign Office, SWA,15 th June, 1950.
ANNEX IAgendaJ.   Adoption of the Agenda.2.   Examination of the Conclusions of the ad hoc Joint Committee (at itsLondon meeting on 18th May).3.   Instructions to be given to the Secretariat-General for drafting the Reportto the Consultative Assembly, in accordance with Article 19 of the Statute.4.   Position of Associate Members with regard to the various activities ofthe Council of Europe.5.   Questions for inclusion in the Agenda of the Second Session of the consultative Assembly.6.   Human Rights.7.   Any other business.ANNEX IICOUNCILReport of the Committee appointed on 4th April, 1950, to consult withthe Sub-Committee of the Committee of Ministers of the Councilof Europe(Cover Note by the Secretary-General)The Council of the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation,having considered the Resolution of the Committee of Ministers of the Councilof Europe (C (50) 94), of 1st April, 1950, appointed, on 4th April, 1950, a Committeeof three Members, consisting of Italy, Sweden and Switzerland. This Committeewas instructed to consult with the Sub-Committee set up under the above resolution on the problems referred to in paragraphs 1 and 2 of it, and to submit a report onthe subject to the Council of the Organisation.On all points which the Committee considered to come within its terms ofreference, the attached Report of the Committee contains proposals for the solutionof the main problems raised by relations between the two organisations.The Council is invited to take note of the proposals in this Report and, ifthey meet with its approval, to instruct the Executive Committee to put them into effect.Report of the Committee1. After preliminary discussions between ourselves, we met on 26th may the Sub-Committee of the Committee of the Council of Europe consisting of hisExcellency M. Menemencioglu, the Turkish Ambassador at Paris (Turkey),M. F. Seydoux (France) and Mr. J. Coulson (United Kingdom).2. As a result of these consultations we have the honour to submit thefollowing proposals to the Council:  Allowing for the different constitution and character of the two organisations,these proposals are meant to ensure fruitful co-operation between the Organisationand the Council of Europe. By helping to develop relations between the twoorganisations and between their two Secretariats, their implementation shouldmake it possible to avoid duplication.we consider that, in order to assure the desired uniformity and continuity,correspondence between the two organisations, whatever its origin or subject,should, as in the past, be dealt with by the two Secretaries-General.IIWe consider that the intervention of the Chairman of the Committee ofMinisters of the Council of Europe in the communication to the Organisation ofeconomic and financial proposals originating in the Consultative Assembly or its committees (point I of the Resolution of the Committee of Ministers of the CouncilOf Europe of 1st April, 1950, (C (50) 94), is a satisfactory procedure.38877 &quot; b 2
The proposals of the Council of Europe would be examined by the council which would reach a decision on each of them. However, the proposed procedure should make it possible, in most cases, for the Organisation to comply with the requests made to it.bill the two Secretaries-General should be responsible for the exchange ofinformation between the two organisations (point II of the above Resolution).This question has three different aspects:  A. Documents Exchange between the two organisations the procedure so far adopted, described in C (49) 206 (Final), will continueto be employed for the despatch to the Council of Europe of restricted documents of the Organisation.Without excluding the possibility of despatch in urgent cases, in the future,the Organisation would send documents of this kind at regular intervals to theCouncil of Europe, classified under headings and accompanied by short notes whichwould make it possible to relate the various documents to the respective fields of activity to which they refer.Unrestricted documents would, of course, continue to be exchanged betweenthe two Organisations.B. Consultation of Organisation Experts by the Council of EuropeThis question was raised in a letter from the Secretary-General of the Councilof Europe, dated 8th March, 1950, informing the Secretary-General of the desireexpressed by the Committee on Economic Affairs of the Consultative assembly that it should be authorised to consult the national and international experts ofthe Organisation.We consider that the Council might adopt the following principles in thismatter:  (a) (i) The consultation would take place between the two Secretaries-General, on the understanding that the Secretary-General of theCouncil of Europe could be accompanied by members of the Com-mittee which had requested the consultation.(ii) The subject of each consultation should be limited and clearly defined in advance.(iii) The subject should be within the competence of the Organisation andshould concern questions which had already been studied by theOrganisation.(iv) No statement on these consultations should be made to the presswithout the prior approval of the Organisation.(b) The following procedure might be adopted for the examination by theOrganisation of a request for a consultation:(i) Any request for consultation submitted by the Secretary-General ofthe Council of Europe to the Secretary-General of the organisation would be submitted by the latter, with comments, to the Council.(ii) The Council (or the Executive Committee, if the Council decided to delegate its powers to that body) would have to decide on each occasion on the action to be taken on the request.(c) At the consultations, the Secretary-General would speak on behalf of theOrganisation in accordance with the provisions of sub-paragraph 4of the Annex to the Convention on European Economic Co-operation of 16th April, 1948.The Secretary-General could be represented by a member of his staff.C. Assistance given by the Secretariat of the Organisation to the Secretariat ofthe Council of Europe for the preparation of the economic work of thevarious organs of the Council of Europe.As part of normal relations between the two Secretaries-General and subjectto the volume of work, the Secretariat of the Organisation would provide theCouncil of Europe with economic data and statistics of value to the latter.
C. BAUER,A. CATTANI (Chairman),E. von SYDOW.In connection with the suggestion made in the Report by the Chairmanof the Council to the Consultative Group of Ministers (C.G.M. (50) 3) on25th March, 1950, that an office should be set up at Strasbourg to supply informa-tion on the activities of the Organisation, we have suggested to the Sub-Committeeof the Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe that publications of theOrganisation should be put on sale by the Secretary-General of the Councilof Europe during the plenary sessions of the Assembly.The members of the Consultative Assembly would thus easily be able to obtainpublications of the Organisation. In addition, it should be possible to arrangefor the regular distribution of press communiques to them.3. The Sub-Committee of the Committee of Ministers of the Council ofEurope approved all the above proposals. A single reservation was made by one member concerning the attendance of members of Committees of the consultative assembly of the Council of Europe at consultations between the two Secretaries-General.


</content>
</cab>
