<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 254-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
2^i/6oTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJfeSTY-S GOVERNMENT     VThe  circulation  of this paper has b^enstrictly limited.       f) AIt is issued for the personal use ofO^v/ Uj-U^VVW-v   J^^&amp;^K .50TOP SECRET Copy No.C.P.(50) 128ZOTH JUNE, 1950CABINETINTEGRATION OF WESTERN EUROPEAN coal and STEEL INDUSTRIESNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate herewith,for consideration by the Cabinet:-(i)     a report by the Committee of officials appointed by he Prime Minister to advise on the French ForeignMinister&apos;s proposals for the integration of thewestern European coal and steel industries, to whichis appended a report by a working party appointed bythe Committee;(ii)     a note summarising the views of the Economic PlanningBoard on the working party&apos;s report.(Signed)   NCRMAN brook cabinet Office, S.W.I.20TH JUNE, 1950.

SEC IETINTEGRATION OF WESTERN european coal AND STEEL INDUSTRIESReport by Committee of officials. The accompanying report has been prepared by a working party which we deputed to consider practical means of implementingwhat we shall refer to as &quot;the Schuman proposals&quot;.     The working party has taken M. Schuman&apos;s proposals and the glosses put upon themby M. Monnet and others as the starting point and has endeavoured toascertain the unifying principle underlying them;   it has then attempted to clothe those proposals with a concrete scheme which might be acceptable to His Majesty1 s Government and to the French and otherGovernments concerned.     The working party and the Committee have both examined the Schuman proposals primarily from their economicaspect and in relation to their effects upon the coal, iron and steel industries of Europe.     We are, however, all very conscious of thefact that if a scheme satisfactory in its economic effect could beevolved, it would bring not only economic advantages but also great political benefits in the shape of improved Franco-German relations.2. The working party&apos;s report starts with an analysis of theproposals and their implications, under the following heads:-Paragraphs(i)    Background(a) Size of the industries at stake 4 - 10(b) International trade in coal, iron 11 - 14ore and steel(ii)      The Schuman proposals, and interpretation   15 - 19of their meaning.(iii)     Effect on the United Kingdom.(a) Access to raw materials 21 - 25(b) Access to markets (tariffs, 26 - 29quantitative restrictions,subsidies, etc. )(c) Wages 3 0(iv)     Current conditions in the European coal andsteel industries.(a) Coal 33 - 43(b) Steel 44 - 533. The conclusions of the working party, derived from the foregoinganalysis, are as follows:-&quot;(i)   The coal and steel industries of Europe are fundamental to theEuropean economy and in both of them large-scale development is taking place and further development is planned.

(ii)      There is some prospect that Europe may be faced with conditions of over-supply in both coal and steel.(iii)      There are forces at work - some active, some latent - whichtend to prevent the most efficient development of Europe&apos;scoal and steel resources and which in a period of over-supplymight well lead to the intensification of undesirable trade practices by industries and nations, the consequences of whichwould affect not only the welfare but also the security of Europe.(iv)     It is not clear what basic economic principle lies at the root ofthe Schuman scheme, but we have suggested that to meet theconditions described above there is a case for an approach tofreer market conditions in the European coal and steel tradesunder the supervision of an International Authority.(v)     Owing to the different position of the various coal and steel industries these conditions would have to be introducedprogressively, with transitional safeguards to avoid seriousindustrial and social dislocation.(vi)     But the United Kingdom is probably in at least as strong aposition as the other members of the group to set the pace.In short it is our view that there is a case for concertedinternational action on economic grounds in regard to the coal and steel industries of Europe, that the more we depart from scarcity conditions, themore imperative the need for international action will become and that,therefore, the sooner a suitable organisation is established the better.&quot;4. We endorse the working party&apos;s analysis in this part of theirreport and agree with the general conclusions drawn from it.   In theremainder of their report (paragraphs 55 - 123) the working party have setout their recommendations on the functions and constitution appropriate to aninternational authority which the United Kingdom could join.    We summarisethese proposals below and submit our advice upon them.Investment5.     Summary. (Paragraphs 58 - 67).   In view of the dangers of wasteful overinvestment in the coal and steel industries of Western Europe as a whole andthe threat of over-production leading to a price-cutting struggle for markets,the working party recommend that investment in tlie coal and steel industries of member countries should be co-ordinated by an International authority in order to promote the most efficient and economical development of these industries.6. There was a difference of view on the working party on thequestion whether the International Authority should be endowed withmandatory oowers (i. e. power to veto investment plans of which itdisapproved) or merely with advisory functions.T.     Recommendation.    We consider it preferable that the Higher Authority&apos;spowers should, if possible, be advisory and not mandatory in this respect.If, however, it should appear that it is necessary to concede mandatorycontrol of investment, within suitable limits, in order to secure generalagreement to a scheme otherwise satisfactory, some of us would beprepared to make this concession.

Output and marketing regulation8.     Summary,    (paragraph 68).   Experience before the war showedclearly the extreme difficulties of regulating output in the coal and steel industries and the consequences of over-production both to the enterprisand-workers as a result of short time, intermittent working and conse-quent violent fluctuations in costs and prices.     The working partyaccordingly suggest that the new Authority should forecast demand and supply from time to time and, in the event of a serious disequilibriumthreatening, concert measures to deal with the situation which wouldhave regard to the interests of both producers and consumers as wellas to the long-term efficiency of the industries concerned.9.     Recommendation.    We endorse this oroposal, although we-recognise that its efficacy is limited.Equalising and improving living conditions.10.   Summary; (paragraphs 69 - 74).    It has bee :t stated, as one of themain aims of the Schuman proposals, that living conditions of theworkers employed in the coal and steel industries of member states should be improved and equalised.     This is assumed to mean levellingup rather than averaging and not to require the use of resources of onenational industry to subsidise improvements in conditions elsewhere.It is difficult in this field to find for the Authority useful functionswhici would not entrench on matters of national wages policy outsidethe Authority&apos;s proper sphere or usurp functions belonging to the established negotiating machinery of the various countries.     Theworking party conclude that the most effective means of achieving theseaims would be through the establishments of a &quot;floor&quot; in each country by the statutory enforcement of wage rates agreed by both sides, andthe publication of detailed information about wages in member countries as en encouragement to the Trade Unions where they were weak and wages low.     Governments of member countries should encourage joint consultation.11.   Recommendation.   We endorse these proposals,al-^owcjh we recognise-vKctt tHeir efficacy is lirtM+ed.Supervision of Trade (Commercial) Agreements:   DiscriminatoryPractices.12.   Summary,   (paragraphs 7 5 - ?6).    The working party recommendthat the coal and steel industries of member countries should berequired to notify the Authority of any proposed agreements between members affecting production, markets and prices, so that theAuthority may satisfy itself that these agreements are in the common interest and are not prejudicial to efficient development of the coal andsteel industries of Europe.     The working party also propose that member Governments should render null and void any such agreementof which the Authority disapproves.13. The working party recommend that the Authority should under-take, either on its own initiative or at the instance of member Govern-ments, investigations into alleged discriminatory practices affectingcoal and steel, and publish its findings and recommendations.

14.   Recommendation.    We endorse these proposals, except that wewould at the outset not endow the Authority with the proposed mandatorypower in regard to commercial agreements, but would be prepared to concede this if it was necessary in order to obtain a satisfactory settlement.Price Policy.Summary,    (paragraphs 77 - 85).     The working party show thatthe co-existence of free markets in some member countries with pricecontrols in others will cause considerable difficulties for a group whichwas seeking inter alia to eliminate dual pricing and to secure, so far aspracticable, equal access to supplies and markets as between members.The working party conclude that only if prices of coal and steel over thegroup as a whole were controlled according to some common principlecould the United Kingdom successfully maintain its policy of long-termstabilisation of coal and steel prices without the protection accorded byquantitative restrictions on imports and exports of coal and steel.16.   Recommendation.      We are in agreement with this conclusion.     TheMinistry of Fuel and Power, while not dissenting from the analysis con-tained in paragraphs 21 - 23 Of the working party&apos;s report, point outthat the immediate abolition of dual pricing for coal would result in anincrease of price of some grades of coal to both industrial and domestic consumers in the United Kingdom.Tariffs, quantitative restrictions and subsidies.i17.   Summary,    (paragraphs 86 - 93).     The Schuman proposalsenvisaged the abolition of customs duties on coal, iron ore and steelbetween member states, but did not mention quantitative restrictions orsubsidies.     The working party recommend that it should be declared tobe an ultimate objective of the new Authority to secure the removal of tariffs, quantitative restrictions and subsidies.     But the process wouldhave to be gradual and it would be necessary to insist on certain tran-transitional safeguards in order to avoid undesirable social and industrialdislocation.     Accordingly the working party recommend that thefollowing conditions should be substantially satisfied before the proposed arrangements are brought fully into effect: -&quot;(i)   All participating countries should have adopted a commongeneral price policy, either of freely competitive prices orof prices fixed according to principles common to all the member countries, e. g.  on a basis that ensured the elimination of dumping, dual pricing and selling below costof production (including a reasonable margin for profit).-(ii)   The elimincition of abnormally and unfairly low rates of wagesand unfavourable conditions of labour.     There are serioustheoretical and practical difficulties in defining &apos;un airlylow&apos; wages and we think that in practice it would have to beleft to the authority to decide what could be regarded as reasonable and fair in the light of the general living standards and the productivity of labour in each of the member countries.

(iii) There should be no artifical discrimination in regard tosubsidies, transport rates, supply of capital, etc. , asbetween the steel industry and otner industries withinthe participating country. &quot;This proposal, however, would be without prejudice to the right of member Governments to impose quantitative restrictions for a limited period for the protection of their balance of payments.     The proposal would also raise difficulties in connection with obligations under theGeneral Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.) and possibleproblems in regard to Imperial preferences.     These are discussed inparagraphs 91 and 93 of the working party&apos;s report, but they are not considered to be insurmountable.18.    Recommendation.    We generally endorse the views of the working party, although some of us fear that the proposal may make it moredifficult to resist attempts in other fields to get the United Kingdom toparticipate in, e, g, , a Customs Union or schemes such as that proposed by JVI. Stikker.,Research, (paragraph 94)19. We endorse the working party&apos;s suggestion that the authority should be authorised to promote research work on an internationalbasis in certain fields.Sanctions,    (paragraph 96)20. We also agree with the view that the Authority should not beempowered to impose sanctions in order to enforce agreement onmember countries, though sanctions, if appropriate, might be acceptedto enforce agreements willingly entered into by members.     these would themselves form part of the agreement.Strategic Interest,    (paragraph 101)21. We endorse the working party&apos;s appreciation of possible effects of their proposals on the strategic interests of the UnitedKingdom and agree that the United Kingdom must reserve its right toprotect speciality production vital to its defence.Constitution of the Authority,   (paragraphs 113 - 123)22. The working party classify the activities of the proposedAuthority as follows:-(i)      To investigate and report, e. g. , in regard to discriminatorypractices;(ii)     To co-ordinate and mediate, e. g. , in regard to investment,marketing schemes, prices, etc. ;(iii)     To supervise, e. g. , the operation of schemes agreed between members;   and(iv) To act as a court of reference.

They conclude that the proposed functions do not require for their effective discharge the establishment of a supra-national authority,nor need the Authority be  given any outward form which marks it asa prototype of federal institutions for Europe.     The working partyrecommend that the Authority should consist of independent persons(nominated by Governments) who are representatives neither of governments nor of the industries concerned.     The Authority shouldbe responsible in its collective capacity to an inter-Governmentalbody which could be specially established for the purpose and mightconsist either solely of Government representatives or of representa-tives of Governments and both sides of industry.     The main functionsof this second body would be to consider regular reports from theAuthority on its operations and to provide a forum for the discussionof recommendations of the Authority which had given rise to disagree-ment among the member countries.     The Authority should also nave astrong staff appointed by the Authority and under its sole control.Suitable consultative machinery would have to be devised to facilitatecontact at the working level between the Authority and the various parties concerned, e. g. member Governments, managements and workers in the coal and steel industries and consumers of coal andsteel.23.    Recommendation.    A detailed constitution for the Authority willhave to be elaborated at a later stage.     We consider that the Authorityitself should, as far as possible, consist of independent people, that itshould be responsible to an inter-Governmental body consisting ofGovernment representatives only and that it should start by havingonly advisory functions, though we recognise that later on in the lightof experience certain functions of a mandatory character might beentrusted to it, particularly in respect of approval of commercial ^agreements between national industries (referred to in paragraph 4-4^,and in relation to investment (paragraph i&apos;&quot;).Signed on behalf of the Committee,E.E. BRIDGES,Chairman.20TH JUNE, 1950.

THIS DOCUMENT IS   THE  PROPERTY OVfi HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1950SECRET - ,FG (WP) (50) 3816th June, 1950CABINETWORKING PARTY ON PROPOSED FRANCO-GERMAN COAL ANDSTEEL AUTHORITYSCHUMAN PROPOSALS FOR AN INTERNATIONAL COAL ANDSTEEL AUTHORITY IN WEST EUROPEReport by Working Party of OfficialsWe were appointed on 24th May, 1950, to consider practical measures for implementing the French proposals for. the pooling of the coal and steel industries of West European countries on the assumption that the coal and steel industries ofthe United Kingdom would eventually be brought within the projected scheme.I2. Tlje declared aim of the Schuman plan is to promote peace, a unitedEurope and the efficient development of the coal and steel resources of Franceand Germany and of such other countries of Europe as are willing to join thescheme. The motives behind the plan are thus partly political and partly economic.But the distinctive feature of the plan is that the political ends are to be soughtthrough economic means. The tasks, with which the &quot; common higher authority &quot;is to be charged, are wholly economic. As a first step, therefore, we must besatisfied that the economic principles underlying the plan are acceptable and,secondly, that the organisation for giving effect to them is workable. It will dono good to the cause of peace or European unity to embark on the scheme unless it passes these tests.Copy No.     I gII3. The French Government has propqsed that Franco-German production ofcoal and steel as a whole should be placed under a common higher authority, withinthe framework of an organisation open to the participation of the other countries of Eurppe. Invitations tp take part in the scheme have so far been extendedto West Germany, Belgium, Luxembourg, Holland, Italy and the UnitedKingdom, all of which are countries producing significant quantities of coal or steel. We have not found it possible to join in the initial negotiations on theterms proposed by the French.Size of the Industries at Stake4. The relative sizes of the industries which would be &quot; pooled &quot; under theFrench proposals may be judged from the production figures set out in Table I.The countries listed here are those whose Governments were invited by the FrenchGovernment to take part in the forthcoming conference.38875 b
millions of metric tons	Production of coal(a)		Production of crude steel		1938	1949	1938	1949United Kingdom.........	231-8	218-6	10-6	15-8Western Germany        ......	153-8	120-9	17-9	9-2France and Saar          ......	61-2	66-0	8-8	11-0Belgium and Luxembourg	29-6	27-9	3-7	6-1Netherlands        .........	13-6	11-8	01	0-italy        ............	1-9	1-5	2-3	2-1	491-9	446-7	43-4	44-5(a) Hard coal and lignite in terms of hard coal equivalent.5. It will be seen that the output of the British coal industry is nearly equal tothat of all other countries put together, Western Germany provides over one-quarterof the total, France (with the Saar) about one-seventh. Belgium and the Nether-lands also produce appreciable quantities of coal, but Italy produces very little. in western Germany output is much below pre-war level, and in all other countriesexcept France, post-war figures are lower than in 1938.6. In steel production the United Kingdom industry is again the largest,though with a smaller proportion of the total (about one-third). France (with the saar) contributes about one-quarter, Western Germany one-fifth, and Belgium one-seventh. The Italian industry is small, that of the Netherlands very small indeed.Compared with 1938, the steel output of Western Germany has fallen even morethan her coal production,, whereas all the other countries (except Italy) showsubstantial increases.7. In each country steel production is heavily dependent on imports of basic materials or fuel. The figures in Table 2, taken from the Economic commission for Europe (E.C.E.) Report on European Steel Trends, show the extent to which inthe post-war period each country has been dependent on supplies of iron ore, scrapand fuel from other European countries. Both the United Kingdom and western germany get almost half their iron ore supplies from other European countries,while France is similarly dependent for half her metallurgical fuel. Belgium, the saar and the Netherlands import all their iron ore, while Luxembourg and Italyimport all their metallurgical fuel.Table IIDependence on Imports of Essential Raw Materials from other european countries (in the Post-war Period up to 1948)unit: percentagesUnited Kingdom .Western GermanyFrance      ...SaarBelgiumLuxembourgNetherlandsItaly   ...Proportion of total consumption represented by imports from EuropeIron ore (metal content)	Scrap	Metallurgical solid fuels (hard coal equivalent)45	10	45		100				100	20	2550		100100		10	35	100Table Coal and Steel Production, 1938 and 1949
8. The importance of coal and steel in the economies of the several countries can be measured in a number of ways. Statistics bearing on this point have beenassembled by the Central Statistical Office in a note appended as Annex I. the salient facts are as follows: The proportion of the working population employedin the two industries is highest in Belgium (6-2 per cent.) closely followed by theUnited Kingdom (5-7 per cent.). Western Germany and France have much lowerfigures (2-8 and 2-4 per cent, respectively), and the Netherlands (1-4 per cent.)and Italy (0-5 per cent.) lower still. The proportion of the national income derivedfrom coal and steel production is also highest in Belgium (7 - 7 per cent.) with western germany (7 - 0 per cent.) and the United Kingdom (6 - 6 per cent.) close behind, and lower figures in France (5 0 per cent.), the Netherlands (2 1 per cent.) and Italy(1-4 per cent.).9. These proportions, however, do not give a true measure of the importanceof coal and steel in the national economy. Coal is the chief source of the energyon which a modern industrialised economy depends. In the United Kingdomabout 85 per cent, of the total energy consumed is derived from coal (the restcoming from petroleum and hydro-electricity). In Western Germany and Belgiumthe proportion is even higher, and in the Netherlands not much lower. Even inFrance, where water-power has been extensively exploited, about three-quarters ofthe total supply of energy is derived from coal. Only in Italy is the proportionless than half.10. The importance of steel rests on the fact that it forms an essential rawmaterial of constructional engineering and a large sector of manufacturing industry. The engineering industry is important in all these countries. It islargest in the United Kingdom, which produces over 40 per cent, of the totalengineering production of the six countries. The industry of Western Germany(25 per cent.) is also very large, as is that of France (19 per cent.). The othercountries have smaller industries but in all cases engineering production forms animportant part of the national income. The steel-using industries have also aspecial importance as export trades. This is particularly marked in the UnitedKingdom, where in 1948 about one-third of total exports consisted of machinery and equipment. In other countries the proportion was between 10 per cent, and20 per cent.International Trade in Coal, Iron-ore and Steel11. Table III summarises the international trade of the six countries in coalduring 1937 and 1949. France is the biggest importer, followed by Italy and the table IIIInternational Trade in Coal, 1937 and 1949millions of metric tons	Imports				Exports				1937		1949		19	37	1949			From		From		To		To	Total	others	Total	others	Total	others	Total	others		in group		in group		in group		in groupUnited Kingdom					40-3	16-6	19-3	3-7Germany(a).......	4-6	4-1	2-1	6-1	38-6	23-3	13-4	9-2France(6)      ......	24-6	22-4	16-5	7-3	1-0	0-9	0-4	0-3Belgium and								Luxembourg	6-2	5-7	1-2	0-9	4-3	4-0	1-4	1-1Netherlands  ......	5-4	5-2	4-1	2-7	4-0	3-4	0-4	Italy(c)         ......	12-6	9-9	8-7	2-9				(a) In 1937 Germany includes the Saar.   In 1949 Germany refers to Western Germany excluding the Saar.(b) Includes the Saar in 1949.(c) Figures exclude coke.Netherlands. A large proportion of the total coal imports of the group comes fromother members of it, though not as much as before the war when almost the whole
;:;    ;: Table IV ^International Trade in Iron-ore, 1937 and 1949millions of metric tons	Imports				Exports				1937		1949		1937		1949			From		From		To		To	Total	others	Total	others	Total	others	Total	others		in group		in group		in group		in groupUnited Kingdom	7-2	0-4	8-8	0-4				Germany(a)  ...	20-6	7-3	4-4	0-4				France(ft)     ...      ...	0-9	0-5	0-4	0-1	19-3	17-8	7-2	7-belgium and								Luxembourg	12-4	11.-5	9-1	6-5	2-3	2-0	0-3	0-3Netherlands......	0-6	0-1	0-7	01				Italy	0-2	...	01			...		(a) In 1937 Germany includes the Saar.   In 1949 Germany refers to Western Germany excluding the Saar.(b) Includes the Saar in 1949.Western Germany come from outside countries, notably Sweden and French north africa. German imports in 1949 were much smaller than pre-war, even allowing for the difference in the geographical coverage of the figures. The only largeexporter in the group is France, the sales being almost entirely to other members.13. Table V summarises the trade of the six countries in steel and steel pro-ducts. It shows the United Kingdom and the Netherlands as the heaviest importers,taking 75 per cent, of their irnported supplies from other members of the table VInternational Trade in Steelia) 1937 and 1949millions of metric tons1	Imp		orts		Exports				1937		1949		1937		1949			From		From		To		To	Total	others	Total	others .	Total	others	Total	others		in group		in group		in group		in groupUnited Kingdom	1-8	1-0	1-1	0-8	2-1	0-2	1-7	01Germany(ft)   ......	0-5	0-4	0-1		2-8	0-7	0-4	0-france (c)    ......	0-1	0-1	0-2	0-1	1-9	0-7	2-1	0-5Belgium and								Luxembourg	0-4	0-3	01	0-1	3-7	1-2	3-5	1-2Netherlands  ......	10	0-9	0-8	0-7	0-3	0-1	0-4	0-1Italy   .........	0-4	0-1	0-3		0-1			(a) Includes ingots, semi-finished steel, finished steel including tyres, wheels and axles.(b) In 1937 Germany includes the Saar.  In 1949 Germany refers to Western Germany excluding the Saar.(c) Includes the Saar in 1949.group. The exporters in order of importance are Belgium-Luxembourg, Franceand the United Kingdom. One-third of the Belgium-Luxembourg exports and one-quarter of French exports go to other countries in the group, three-quarters ofwas so imported. Only the United Kingdom and Western Germany are largeexporters. Markets within the group take much the greater part of the german exports, but a much smaller portion from the United Kingdom.12. Table IV gives a similar summary of the international trade in irpnroreduring 1937 and 1949. The largest importers are Belgium, Luxembourg, tlie UnitedKingdom and Western Germany. Belgium-Luxembourg get. their supplies inainlyfrom France, but the greater part of the imports into the United Kihgdprp and
all United Kingdom exports go to countries outside the group. On balance thegroup is a heavy exporter of steel to countries outside the group. For the six countries together both imports and exports are below pre-war.14. Since the war the coal and steel industries of the group have enjoyedthe advantages of a sellers&apos; market, but these conditions are beginning to come toan end for both steel and coal. The Steel Division of E.C.E. has recentlyestimated the demand for European steel in 1953 at 62 million tons, comparedwith present estimates of future crude steel production of up to 70 million tons(allowing no higher output for Western Germany than the current restricted limit of 11 -1 million tons). Likewise in the case of coal there has recently been a marked improvement in European supplies, and the prospect of a surplus of some gradesat any rate has to be reckoned with. The prospect of a surplus steel capacitywould be brought nearer if the agitation of the West German Government forsome relaxation of the present restriction of her steel output was successful on thestrength of participation in the Schuman Plan on a basis of equality. The positionin regard to both steel and coal would be aggravated if the scale of economic activity throughout the world were to be reduced. It is, therefore, no more thanprudent to assume that the Authority would, at no far distant date, have to operate in conditions of oversupply. The French, in particular, are no doubt fully conscious of the dangers of this position. This means that the newly created authority would be faced with considerably more difficult problems in the way of adjustingexisting patterns of production and distribution than they would if the tide of demand was likely to continue to run strongly in advance of supply. In shortthe Authority may well be faced with the task of dealing with the same typeof situation which gave birth to the pre-war steel cartels and the beginning ofinternational regulation in coal.Ill15. The French proposal is that the Authority should be charged with thefollowing far-reaching tasks:  (a) the modernisation of production and the improvement of its quality inthe shortest possible time;(b) the supply of coal and steel on identical terms to the French and to theGerman markets as well as to the markets of the other member countries;(c) the development in common of export to other countries outside thegroup;(d) the equalisation as well as the improvement of living conditions of Workersin the coal and steel industries.- 16. The following specific proposals have been formulated for the imple-mentation of these tasks:  (i) the immediate abolition of all coal and steel customs duties between member States;(ii) a ban on differential transport rates for coal and steel traffics between member States;(iii) the application of production and investment schemes;(iv) the creation of an amortisation fund (fonds de reconversion) for financing the rationalisation of production; and(v) the establishment of compensating machinery for equating prices.The last three are specifically described as examples of transitional measureswhich will have to be instituted to take account of the different conditions nowprevailing in the industries of the various countries.17. The unifying principle behind all this appears to be the creation of conditions which will promote the most economic distribution of coal and steel production in the area covered by the proposed Authority. The original Frenchmemorandum speaks of creating conditions &quot; which will spontaneously providefor the more rational distribution of production at the highest level of productivity.&quot;The implications of this principle are examined in paragraphs 18 and 19. Later,in paragraphs 20 to 30, we consider what changes in the existing practices and policies of the United Kingdom might be required, if it were accepted. Some ofthe implications have been explicitly set out by the French in one or other of their38875 c
statements; others seem to be logically inherent in the general principle. We donot, of course, know at present, and will have to try to discover later, how far the French and other possible members of the Authority would wish to carry outthe logic of this principle in practice. It certainly does not seem to be their inten-tion that the principle should be applied in its full rigour from the outset, and as already indicated there is a number of (somewhat vaguely formulated) transitionalmeasures to mitigate the effects of its application. Nevertheless it seems worth-while to consider what might ultimately be implied in a strict application.18. The possible implications of the unifying principle may be set out underfour heads as follows:  (i) Equal Access to Raw Materials. The member countries should accordequal access to supplies of raw materials (such as coal, coke, iron-ore and scrap to all countries in the group. This in turn could be held to imply that (a) The ex-works or f.o.b. prices charged for raw materials by one member country to another should be no greater than, or atleast closely related to, those charged to its own industry.(b) There should be no discriminatory charges for the transport of these materials.(c) Member countries should not seek to enjoy (by bilateral agreements,Imperial Preference, &amp;c.) special advantages over other member countries in the supply of raw materials from non-member countries.(d) In the event of a shortage, the available supplies would be sharedout equitably between the industries of the producing andimporting countries.It would seem that of these (a) and (b) are essential to the principle,and that (c) and perhaps (d), while logical extensions, might be regardedas not essential to it, and, in any event, as asking for a greater degreeof impartiality than could reasonably be expected to be attained inpractice.(ii) Equal Access to Markets. The principle must imply equal access tomarkets, including the removal of all custom duties and quantitative regulation of imports on the movement of coal and steel between member countries. An attempt might also be made to stretch this principle to prohibit the seeking or preservation of advantages, such aspreferential tariffs, enjoyed by members in non-members&apos; markets.(iii) No Subsidies to Industries of Member Countries. The principle implies that there should be no subsidies of any kind special to the coal andsteel industries of member countries, including remissions, granted orprocured by Governments, of local or national taxes, or artificiallycheap supplies of materials, capital or other facilities. The principlecannot, we think, mean that the industries must be taxed at equal ratesin different countries, but only that special favour must not be grantedto the coal and steel industries as such.(iv) No Competition through Wage Depression. The principle can be heldcompatible with the elimination of artificially low wages and oppressiveconditions of work. The French memorandum requires the &quot; equalisation-tion as well as improvements of living conditions of workers in those industries.&quot; It is well known that the French are conscious of beinghandicapped vis-a-vis the Germans by the higher rates of wages andsuperior social services the French provide, and, even more than we,would like to see German wages raised. It is not, however, clear how they could justify this demand by reference to the principle of pro-promoting economic production and distribution of coal and steel, and wemust probably regard it either as an end in itself or as part of a broaderconception of natural justice and social or political expediency. Cer-tainly it cannot be logically argued that the proper economic develop-ment of the coal and steel industries of the member countries demandsan artificially created equal level of wages, out of line with the generalwage level in the respective countries, and unrelated either to thedifferent national incomes and standard of living or to difference in productivity. We must therefore assume that, for any period for whichit is worthwhile to look ahead, considerable difference in wage levels
will persist, and that the most that can be hoped for from the applicationof the principle of &quot; natural justice &quot; is:  (a) the strengthening of the position of the trade unions in countries where they are weak;(b) the raising of wages which are abnormally low in relation to thegeneral wage level of the country concerned;(c) an increase in wages in low-wage countries with increases in productivity;(d) some equalisation in regard to hours of work, holidays with pay,the relation between ordinary and overtime rates, and other similar matters with which the International Labour Organisa-tion (I.L.O.) have traditionally concerned themselves.19. In short the basic conception might be defined as the removal over aperiod of all barriers within the group to the movement of coal and steel between member States and the prohibition of all discriminatory practices which militatedagainst the production of coal and steel in the most efficient units. Added to thisconception, however, is the further idea that natural justice demands that in the boundaries of such a group (within which full freedom of movement of labour is inevitably subject to practical limitations) gross inequalities of wages and conditionscannot be allowed to persist. On this basis it would be the job of the Authorityto see that these conditions were first created and subsequently maintained. Afterthe &quot; transitional period &quot; was over and this might be a period of many years and a truly free market prevailed, it could be argued that the economic forcesgenerated by the market could be relied upon to bring about the rationalisation of production of coal and steel without direct intervention by the Authority in the affairs of particular concerns. The Authority would not require the power to direct the closure of a particular works or even to ban the opening of a new one. Thoseunits, which could not live under the competition of other works anywhere withinthe group, would be forced to close down because they could not pay. Likewisethe more efficient units would be free to expand and undercut the less efficient ones.This is quite a consistent and logical proposition, though it does not seem that weare now being asked to subscribe more than partially to this free trade concept.The reference in the Schuman declaration to the pooling of resources, and the tran-transitional measures proposed so far as their meaning is intelligible suggest rather the idea of a grouping of the European coal and steel industries, deliberatelyplanned to produce the kind of production and distribution pattern which would,after a prolonged period of major dislocation and social readjustment of a verypainful character, emerge from conditions of perfect competition; and to achieve this end by stages which would not involve the painful readjustments which would inevitably accompany the unregulated transition in the case of two such industries as coal and steel. The French may also argue and with some force in the case ofsteel that the iron and steel industry is by way of an exception to the general theorythat given the proper framework of free markets, competition will produce theperfect distribution of productive resources, since the economies of scale are such that there is inherent in the industry a tendency towards quasi-monopolisticconditions which, even in free market conditions, require some international super-vision if waste is to be avoided on the one hand and public interest safeguarded onthe other. In the light of all these considerations we think, therefore, that the ideaof central planning from an international vantage point, rather than the completeplay of free competition, is likely to dominate the scene for some years to come.Effect on United Kingdom of Extension of Free Trade Principles20. Nevertheless, it will be useful to review the changes in present UnitedKingdom practices and policies which would be required by the application of theprinciples discussed in paragraph 18 above, since, whatever the French con-ception may be, some of these elements of a free market will certainly be required,even though their full impact may be modified by the transitional arrangements which will emerge from any discussion or negotiations which may take place.Access to Raw Materials(a) Coal21 The principle of equality of access to raw materials raises in a new form the problem of dual prices for coal.  The elimination of dual prices would
create a grave financial problem for the National Coal Board. The extra revenuederived from charging the commercial price for coal exports amounted in 1949to nearly  20 million and the loss of this sum, and of a large though perhaps not quite so large sum in 1950 and 1951. by which time prices may be expected to drop somewhat, would be a most serious matter. It is true that the Board wouldnot be obliged to abandon dual prices in the markets of non-members, but inpractice they would find it very difficult indeed to charge, say, Holland at oneprice and, say, Denmark at another, some 20/- a ton higher. Moreover, while thePoles have hitherto shown no sign of wishing to cut their prices, a reduction ofprices among members of the group might well touch off a change of policy whichwould render impracticable the maintenance by members of the group of higher prices in the markets of non-members. Even apart from that it has to be remem-bered that the United Kingdom has still a long distance to travel before the levelof coal exports begins to approach a level which could be regarded as satisfactory in the long run. To start another system of discriminatory pricing would clearly not be conducive to the recovery of the coal trade which is necessary to the long-term prosperity of the country. Again in the case of bunkers for foreign-going vessels, discriminatory prices are specifically ruled out by the International Mari-time Conventions. The financial effect upon the Coal Board would therefore almost inevitably be the elimination of dual pricing throughout their export market, anda loss over the next year or two of up to  20 million in foreign exchange and tothe Board&apos;s profits. It is true that in the long run the United Kingdom might be compensated to some extent by participation in markets created by the closure of uneconomic French and Belgian collieries as a result of the operations of the schuman Plan, but it is more difficult to see how such compensation, partial andinadequate as it would probably be, could also be secured in the markets of non-rmembers in which, for the reasons given above, dual pricing would also have to be abandoned. Possibly some bargain could be made with certain of those countries by which they would undertake in return for the concession to increase the propor-tion of their requirements taken from the United Kingdom at the expense ofnon-members of the group, e,g., Poland. The immediate financial loss wouldnonetheless be a very serious matter to the Board, especially because of the uncer-tainty about future cost levels occasioned by claims for increased wages and other benefits by the miners.22. Against these important considerations, however, should be set the factsthat the attack on dual prices at the Organisation for European economic co-operation (O.E.E.C.) and elsewhere, strongly supported by the Americans is strong, persistent and continuing; that the present advantage is at most temporary and might even have evaporated by the time the negotiations on the Schuman Planare translated into agreement and operation; that the elimination of dual prices(for which in the Schuman context the steel industry are prepared) would be a powerful concession to throw into the politico-economic balance now, the valueOf which for prestige or bargaining purposes is a wasting asset; and that it would render more acceptable the complementary request, the financial importance ofwhich is also great and to which considerable importance must be attached, that prices for export should not be allowed to fall below the internal price.23. In addition to its effect on the problem of dual prices for coal, the strict application of the principle of equality of access to raw materials might also haveawkward consequences. Member countries might claim a share of the UnitedKingdom output of coking coal, for example. At present the highest qualitycoking coals are, in effect, reserved for the internal market, and any obligation to share their supply with steel industries of member countries would be at best mostunwelcome and at worst might affect production of steel in the United Kingdom.(b) Steel24. The export premium on steel sold to other members of the group would presumably have to be eliminated, but this is a matter of less importance in view ofthe trends of demand and supply.Scrap25. A price and allocation problem might also arise with steel scrap,although few of the member countries import scrap. Domestic supplies of steelscrap are at present bought by the United Kingdom steel industry ata price which is kept staple by agreement between the industry and the scrap
trade, the arrangement being currently reinforced by statutory controls overprices and exports. Home scrap has, for a considerable number of years sincebefore the war, been entirely reserved for the home industry. The principle of equal access might theoretically suggest that these special arrangements should begiven up and industries abroad given equal access to domestic supplies of UnitedKingdom scrap although the British industry has for many years been an importerof scrap. If a uniform policy is to be adopted by the member countries an arrange-ment on the British lines might be worked out between the members both as to price and distribution. In this connection it is significant to note that the E.C.E.Report on European Steel Trends states that -&quot; A market organisation which would ensure a reasonable profit to thescrap dealers and an adequate, regular and cheap supply to the steel pro-producer could play an important role in lowering the cost of production of steel in Europe &quot;;and again that &quot; perhaps collective measures should be taken in order to avoid too widefluctuations in the scrap market, which in the long run benefit neither the scrapsupplier nor the scrap consumer.&quot;Policies on these lines aiming at stability of scrap prices have been an important element in the general policy of steel price stability pursued in the United Kingdom.Equal Access to Markets(i) Tariffs26. The principle of equality of access to markets would involve the permanentabolition as between members of the tariffs on coal and steel. This would give riseto difficulties in relation to the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.)which are discussed later in paragraph 91. In the case of coal this would make no difference to the United Kingdom industry since none of the countries in theproposed bloc levies protective customs duties on coal at present. As regards ironand steel it would mean the eventual abandonment by the United Kingdom, sofar as trade between members is concerned, of the comprehensive system of tariffsnow imposed on iron and steel imports ranging according to product from 20 percent, to 33-j per cent, ad valorem. The consequences of such a step cannot be pre-dicted with any certainty. There is, however, no good reason for thinking that theUnited Kingdom steel industry should not be able in its main lines of production to remain over a long period fully competitive with continental producers; thepresent technical position is strong. Under stable conditions of fair trading, there-fore, the industry should be able to thrive without artificial protection. Under freecompetition, there would no doubt be somewhat greater specialisation amongEuropean producers, in which process the United Kingdom industry mightexperience both some gains and some losses. The process of expansion and develop-ment would, therefore, be selective and would not be spread evenly over all sectionsof the industry and this in turn might affect other manufacturing industries at home,but it is idle at this stage to speculate about the changing pattern of production which might emerge. In the short run the United Kingdom steel industry couldnot avoid some apprehensions arising from the different price policies which haveprevailed in the European steel industries. In the United Kingdom the iron andsteel industry has followed a policy of relative price stability, i.e., prices have notbeen slashed in time of low demand and consumers have not been exploited intime of high demand. This policy has been pursued with Government approval asbeing in the national interest and in recognition of certain relative rigidities arisingfrom agreements with trade unions on wages and employment, the cost of fuel and transport and the high capital costs of new plant. On the other hand continentalproducers have followed an opposite policy in time of slump prices fell to bareprime costs and in time of boom high profits were exacted which tided over the bad times. Violent and erratic short-term movements in relative prices can, how-ever, result in an erratic flow of imports sometimes at uneconomic prices and can have a seriously adverse effect on an industry equipped for large-scale productionand geared to a relatively stable price level. These risks would to some extent be mitigated by the abolition of dual prices, a prohibition on subsidies and adequate safeguards against dumping and other forms of unfair competition. Safeguardsof this kind, supplemented by a confident expectation that in course of time the38875 D
proposed Authority would work towards a more uniform price policy among themembers, should introduce that element of stability in which the competitive position of the United Kingdom steel industry would remain strong. It wouldprobably be necessary, at any rate during the transition stage, to associate theabolition of tariffs as between members with the following arrangements (a) agreement on price policy on exports to member countries;(b) safeguards against dumping and other forms of unfair competition.(ii) Quantitative Restrictions27. The principle of equality of access to markets would in principle involverelinquishing the right to impose quantitative regulation of imports of coal or ironand steel as between members. The strict application of this doctrine would,however, have tq be moderated, with safeguards against abuse (a) in the circumstances set out in the preceding paragraph;(b) to protect the balance of payments;(c) in the transition period when the free market is being established, so thatany necessary adjustments of productive resources and the social consequences thereof can take place in an orderly fashion.In the case of coal, however, the abolition of quantitative restrictions would bean undiluted advantage to us when we have more coal to export.(iii) Preferential Tariffs28. It is possible that pressure might come from other members of the groupfqr us to give up Imperial Preferences granted by the Commonwealth on our exportsof steel. This is no more than a contingent threat which it should be possibleto stave off on the ground that (a) we are not seeking the abolition of othermembers&apos; preferences in third markets, and are not abating ours in our colonial territories; and (b) in the Dominions the preferences are granted by the DominionGovernments, as part only of the general trade relations between the UnitedKingdom and the Commonwealth, and there is no reason why preferences inthe case of steel should be treated in isolation; and (c) the Commonwealth is outside the group; and it is no part of the present proposals that the details ofthe common export policy to be pursued by members of the group vis-a-visthird countries should be worked out in advance of a general agreementConstituting the group: A rough estimate of the trade at present covered by imperial Preference is contained in Annex II.Elimination of Subsidies29. The elimination of subsidies would present little difficulty for the UnitedKingdom since they are now negligible. During and shortly after the war, HisMajesty&apos;s Government was paying amounts totalling about  25 million a year,in respect of the high cost of imported iron ore, imported pig iron and importedsteel. These payments have now been largely eliminated, but His Majesty&apos;sGovernment is still paying the difference between the cost of imported finished steel and the controlled price of British steel (about  3 million per annum) and theduty on imported iron and steel. (It will, of course, be appreciated that these payments which are now falling owing to a reduction in imports and in theirprice-are not subsidies to the steel industry, but rather subsidies to steelconsumers.) The Ministry of Supply also incurs a loss of about  ^ million perannum on working certain steel plants which it acquired during the war. Thereare no corresponding problems on coal unless it were held that the raising orprovision of capital under Government guarantee was a form of subsidy.Wage Conditions30. As regards wages and conditions of employment the United kingdom has much to gain by an approach to greater equality of wages and living conditionsof the workers in the coal and steel industries of the other European countriesprovided that this is achieved by raising the standards of the lowest towards thoseof the best and that the resources of one national industry are not employed to subsidise improvements in conditions elsewhere.
31. From the foregoing discussion it will be seen that if an approach to a free trade group in coal and steel is the ultimate objective of the Schumap property -ppsals and this is to be the governing principle by which the Authority is guided,It would require changes in United Kingdom practices and policies, some ofwhich would involve the taking of risks, but none of which would be impracticableor on balance inherently disadvantageous in the long run. Provided that acceptablearrangements could be made about the problems of the transitional period andthere are, we think, good economic reasons why the United Kingdom should join in an organisation designed to give expression to this principle.JV32. There is not sufficient information readily available to enable any detailedappreciations to be made of the probable impact on the countries of the group of the free trade principle discussed in the previous section. It is evident, however,that if there is any substantial difference in relative costs (allowing for the cost oftransport) or in the economic environment (e.g., as regards the degree of protectionby tariff, restrictions on imports, subsidies, &amp;c.) affecting general costs in which thevarious industries have grown up, the concept of a free movement for coal andsteel within the group could not be introduced overnight without setting up veryserious strains and stresses. In the absence of reliable statistical data the following paragraphs compare in very general terms the relative positions of the various industries.A. coal production Costs33. The following table gives the available data of comparativecosts for the third quarter, 1949:  uctionTable VIUnited KingdomFrance(a)Western Germany(Sterling per metric ton)Wages    .........Roof  supports,  repairs,stores, &amp;c.    ......Coal and powerOther costs (includingdepreciation) ...Total costsS. 29	d. 15	Per cent. 64-9	s. 45	d-9-0	Per cent. 62-5	s. 23	d. 9		Per cent. 40-36 2	8-4 6-9	14-9\ 5-8/	17	9-8	24-3	/is \ 6	10 6-	7	26-9 1L-26	5-7	14-4	9	8-1	13-2	12	8&apos;	8	21-644	10-5	100	73	2-9	100	58	10&apos;	5	100For Belgium the latest information relates to the year 1947 when total costsamounted to the equivalent (in terms of current sterling exchange) of 95s. \0d. perton, of which wages costs formed 64 - 3 per cent.34. It will be seen that total costs in the continental countries are higher thanin the United Kingdom and that, except in Germany, wages form a very similarproportion of total costs. As regards the German figures, however, it should be mentioned firstly that their wage costs (although wages have recently been increased)seem widely out of line with the pre-war position, and are lower than those of other western European coal producers so that the apparently very high proportion ofother costs may conceal substantial items which are really of a capital character andwhich will later disappear; secondly, that the potential productivity of the german coal industry must be regarded as very much higher than the current figure so that,if wage costs remain relatively stable, a rise in German productivity might wellresult in substantial cost reductions.
Productivity35. The following are the overall productivity figures for pre-war and thelatest post-war periods available:  Table VIIOutput per man shift(Metric tons)1937 1948       March 1950United Kingdom          ...... J-W 1-13 j&apos;27Western Germany         ...... 159 u-sg 1.34 (Sept. 1949)Zf z  ......  :::  ::: o-83     ... 0-75France      ...      ... 0-76- 0-94Belgium     ............ . 1-44Netherlands         ......... I&quot;77 1 - 14It will be seen that the United Kingdom is the only country which has surpassed its pre-war figure which, however, was low relatively to the best Continental per-formance. In the particular case of Germany, which is still well below the pre-warlevels, the latest months show a rising tendency which is expected to continue.Prices36. Detailed information is not readily available of actual inland prices orproceeds from inland sales in each of the countries concerned. The followingindex, based on rough estimates of average proceeds of sale for the third quarter,1949, gives, however, some indication, taking United Kingdom (45s. Id. per ton) as100 of the variation in inland price levels (values converted at current sterlingexchange rates):  United Kingdom............. 100West Germany ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 120France     ...      ...      ............ 155Belgium.................. 215It will be seen that marked differences exist in the internal price levels, and it follows that the United Kingdom is in a stronger position than the other countries inregard to internal price level. These variations also indicate the wide divergencebetween internal prices within the group.Import Restrictions and Tariffs37. Belgium is at present protectively restricting coal imports. Holland and western Germany also operate coal import licensing systems, whilst in france the volume and source of coal imports is directly controlled through the medium of a Government-sponsored solid fuel importing agency. Thus in each of thesecountries the Governments still possess, and in most cases operate, effective machinery for quantitative restriction of coal imports. In this situation the factthat customs duties are not levied on coal imports has little significance.Subsidies38. The German coal industry is at present working at an overall financial loss which, in relation to calculated costs, amounted to over 2 marks per ton forthe month of January 1950, the latest for which information is available. It hasbeen noted above, however, that present German production costs include certaininflated elements which may be non-recurrent items of a capital nature. Apartfrom the $15 million grant which was made in 1948 by the Economic Co-operation administration (E.C.A.) to the German authorities in return for refraining froman increase in German coal export prices at that time, and which has since been passed on to the German coal industry by way of a loan for capital expenditure,there have been, and still are, Government subsidies in Western Germany to the marginal uneconomic mines.39. In the cases of France and Belgium, heavy Government subsidies havebeen paid to their coal industries since the war. In both countries it is declaredGovernment policy to eliminate these subsidies, and steps have in fact been takento reduce them, but in neither case have they been eliminated and it is believed
that in one form or another (e.g., by Government credits and grants) substantial sums are still being paid to the coal industries concerned. In, the case of France, thesubsidisation of the coal industry is mixed up with the coal price equalisationscheme. Under this scheme, the cost of which is borne by the Government, but which is operated jointly by the coal industry and distributors, the prices of imported coal, i.e., distributors&apos; sale prices, are reduced to levels appropriate tothe prices of corresponding French coals fixed zonally. Hitherto; this scheme hasbeen very costly to the French Treasury (e.g., 27,000 million francs in 1948), butthis cost has been progressively reduced (particularly since the latter part of 1949)by increases allowed in sale prices. The French may have had their own scheme in mind in the reference to the Schuman proposals to international price equalisation-tioh arrangements. &apos;Development Plans40. For coal, there has been no exchange of information on development and investment plans corresponding to the detailed discussions which have taken placeon steel within the O.E.E.C. Steel Committee. We have only the following fore-casts of coal production for 1950-51 submitted by the countries concerned to theE.C.E. Coal Committee. (These forecasts are shown for comparison side by side with the 1937 and 1949 actual figures.)Table VIII	1937	1949	1950-51	(actual)	(actual)	(forecast)		(million metric tons)	Western Germany   ...	139-1	103-2	117-france ...      ......	44-3	51-2	54-5Saar    .....	13-4	14-3	15-2Belgium        ......	29-8	27-8	29-5Holland        .......	14-3	11-7	12-united Kingdom	244-2	218-6	228-0It will be seen that, with the important exception of Germany, relatively minorfurther additions to output are forecast. Thus, the investment plans in the industries concerned are intended mainly for the purpose of improving efficiency and produc-tivity on roughly the existing levels of output. It seems clear that any attempt toco-ordinate investment for the group as a whole would mainly involve the task of deciding on relative efficiencies in maintaining output at a fairly static level ratherthan that of choosing between alternative projects for expansion.United Kingdom Competitive Prospects&apos;-&apos; 41: Our ability to compete successfully with other countries will ultimatelydepend on our productivity in general and our costs of production in particular.In this respect, we are undoubtedly in a very strong position vis-a-vis France andBelgium. In regard to Germany, our relative position is, as noted above, much moreuncertain. Whilst we may confidently expect that our productivity will in future be much closer to that of Germany than before the war, it is by no means certainthat on present relative wages (which have increased relatively far more in theUnited Kingdom than in Germany since the war) we shall be more competitivethan we were then. None the less, with our easy access to the ports, good port facilities, favourable sea freight rates with return cargoes, wide range of goodquality coals, goodwill, and suitability of United Kingdom coal to consumers&apos; plant,our position has considerable strength. Moreover, it should be remembered that itwas mainly by a system of subsidising exports out of a high level of internal coal prices, and with the help of specially reduced rail rates, and a wages freeze, thatthe Germans were able to make the inroads they did on our pre-war export trade.In regard to Polish competition, our main danger lies in the favourable naturalconditions with high productivity enjoyed by the Polish coal industry and in thepossibility that the Polish Government will make an all-out effort, employing everydevice of subsidy and State trading, to raise their exports to the highest possible level as a means of securing foreign exchange. Their policy may also be affectedby political considerations. Our strength lies in a. much more favourablegeographical position of our coalfields for exports, in the wide range and carefulpreparation of coal qualities we shall be able to offer, in our rail, port and shipping facilities, and perhaps too in political preferences. . . .38875 E
Summary42. So far as coal is concerned, the main practical problem will be to ensurethat we are not put in the position of having to negotiate on the present modest scale of our export trade. Whilst there are the beginnings of a coal surplus inEurope in general purpose steam coals, there still remains a large unsatisfieddemand for our specialised high quality coals (coking, gas, low volatiles, includinganthracite, &amp;c.) which we expect to have available for export in increased quantitiesas output improves. The speed at which supplies might be increased and exportsrecovered is an important element in the situation which makes it of particular importance that we should, if we enter the Group, be able to negotiate on thebasis of our ability to engage in a vigorous export sales policy, based on a large and secure home market, and to use our position as a great importer of raw materials and food-stuffs to secure concessions in trade negotiations with third countries.43. On balance, therefore, we regard our long-term prospects in the coalexport market as good, with our main risks in (i) the difficulty of re-establishingourselves in the short run in markets we regards as our natural outlets owing toinsufficient output in the next two or three years, and (ii) the possibility that thedifference between our wage costs and those of our competitors may be widenedstill further to a point at which our other advantages vis-a-vis Germany and Polandwill be insufficient to preserve our position.B. SteelPrices44. No comparative data are available on relative costs in the iron andsteel industries of the proposed group. Prices in domestic markets afford somerough basis of comparison, but these for obvious reasons must be taken with greatreserve, since they may reflect not only differences in relative costs, but alsodifferences in market conditions, price policy and varying degrees of governmentalprotection and assistance. The following table provides a rough guide in indexform of the relative prices prevailing at the beginning of the present year in the domestic markets of the various countries for representative types of steel:-Table IXComparative Domestic Prices January 1950(United Kingdom = 100)	United							Kingdom	France	Germany	Belgium	Luxembourg Italy		NetherlandsAngles    ......	100	127	109	121	129	200	145Joists	100	107	100		123		...Plates     ......	100	134	104	119	125	222	145Hot rolled strip ...	100	112	103	...	117		130Rails      ......	100	126	112	133	140		Sheets    ......	100	124	115		...		Merchant bars ...	100	111	91	101	109	176	12745. Despite the many qualifications which must be attached to figures of thiskind they suggest that there does not exist as between the various industries andmarkets of the group a sufficiently close approximation of costs and prices to permit the early introduction of free trade principles of the sort discussed in Section IIIabove without very considerable industrial and social readjustment in at least someof the countries concerned. If is, therefore, clear that the United Kingdom wouldnot be alone in seeking adequate safeguards in the transition period. Indeed, thereis reason to suppose that we could afford to set the pace in the progress towardsfreer market conditions within the group in the knowledge that the other membersstand at greater risk than we unless suitable safeguards are introduced.Tariffs46. There are also wide disparities in the tariffs of the various countries asshown in the following table which gives particulars of current tariff rates. the aim is merely to give a simplified indication of general levels and in consequencethe figures are in some degree imprecise.
Iron and Steel Tariff Rates	Present			Germany	Italy	U.K. as			as a %	when	a%of	France	Benelux	of 1939	Annecy	existing			home price	rates	home prices			11-67 RM= ^ l	are effectiveIron ore	Free	Free	Free	Free	FreeScrap  ...	Free	Free	Free	Free	FreePig iron	25%	5%	1%	12% 16%	10%Semis ...      .	20%	8%	2% 3%		15%Bars	20%	10%		45%	22%Strip   ...	22%	15%-18%	6%	25%	22%Wire rods	20%	12%	15%	...	22%Sections	25%	11%	3%?	44%	22%Rails   ...	331%	18%	4% 3^%	19%	20%Sheets ...	25%	16%		19-35%   ,	23%Tinplate	25%	18%	4%	...	23%Wire   ...	33*%	19%	4%	15%	22%Tubes	20%	19%	3-8%	15%	20%Extras ...		Taxes	Doubled	Turnover	License		17% of	to those	tax	fee 10%		c.i.f.	not giving M.F.N.	3%	or lessNotes1. The Germans are preparing a new tariff, as their existing tariff is that of 1939. Presumablythey will attempt to regain protection equivalent to that of 1939.2. The Italian rates given are not yet effective, but legislation is expected within the next fewmonths.3.   Slightly higher rates apply to certain high value special steel imports into the United Kingdom.47. The traditional policies of the countries concerned are that, whereasLuxembourg (with virtually no home market) and Belgium (with less than half hersteel output sold in the home market) have been low tariff countries, France, Italyand Germany have been strongly protectionists: the relatively moderate rates of duty in Germany and France were adequate when coupled with the Cartel agree-ment. The United Kingdom imposed no import duties on steel prior to 1932, butsubsequently substantial tariff protection was developed, although the &quot; two-decker &quot; scheme winch operated from 1935 to the outbreak of war meant that thehigh level applied only to imports which were not agreed to by the United kingdom as part of the arrangements with the Steel Cartel. The agreed, or quota, imports were admitted at a duty rate of 10 per cent, ad valorem immediately before the war.Quantitative Restrictions48. In current conditions import duty as a means of protection has been over-shadowed by quantitative restrictions. The O.E.E.C. countries have recently freedsome proportion of their general imports from quantitative restrictions, but in theiron and steel field, the main producing countries apart from Benelux, viz., France,Germany and the United Kingdom, have so far relaxed only to a very limited extent, although there may be further relaxations in the comparatively near future as a result of the continuation of the O.E.E.C. exercise. Italy has argued that shecannot relax pending the reorganisation of her tariff. As regards the UnitedKingdom, the tariff is out of date in its specific duty aspects (which were designed as anti-dumping measures) and needs revision from this point of view before anysubstantial relaxation of import licensing can be introduced.Subsidies and Other Restrictive Devices49. Although in the pre-war period Germany, at least, subsidised her steelindustry from time to time and adopted other internal devices to assist her steel andsteel-using industries in their efforts to earn foreign exchange (e.g., currency mani-pulation), and Belgium had indirect subsidies through the banks, it is difficult nowto point to any specific Governmental or industry devices in the proposed groupdesigned to provide artificial competitive advantages. There have been allegations of some system of differential railway rates being adopted by the Germans to assistexports. This is a matter which has been investigated generally by the High Corn-mission in Germany, under its powers to prevent discriminatory practices.  The
resulting changes in differential rates have, however, up to date been small. It ispossible that arrangements made for Government financing of Dutch and Italiansteel producers have, or will have, the effect of a hidden subsidy to some degree, butinsufficient is known of these arrangements to justify any positive conclusion.Development Plans50. Each of the countries concerned embarked on development schemes soon after the war, largely to repair the ravages of war or the delays in modernisation.Under the pressure of the need to overcome as quickly as possible the acutepost-war shortage of steel in Europe, these schemes were launched by the individual countries according to their own assessments of requirements, and not untilmid-1949 was any serious co-operative attempt made, under the auspices ofO.E\E.C. and E.C.E., to assess the overall position. Consequently, although theE.C.E. report issued at the end of 1949 concludes that the aggregate productionof crude steel planned by European countries for 1953 exceeds by some million tons the aggregate markets likely to be available, practically the wholeof the steel melting capacity from which such output could be provided is eithercompleted or in hand. (There may have been some retrenchment recently, but itcan only be of a relatively minor character; a more precise indication will emerge from a review of the forward position which O.E.E.C. is soon to undertake,but it will not be completed for a month or two at the earliest.)51. Particulars of production capacities are not available. We do know,however, from O.E.E.C. returns what production the participating countries haveplanned in 1952-53 (and such planned production is doubtless close to capacity)as compared with actual production in 1937. Whether, given adequate demand,the planned production is achieved depends on possible modifications in investmentiplans (for which there appears to be comparatively little scope) or progress of execution, and on raw material supplies, but if all goes according to plan thepercentage increases in output in 1952-53 compared With 1937 will be:  	Per cent.France         ...      ...	&apos;;.. &apos; ... . 45Germany      ...      ...	......      minus 29Belgium       ...      ...	.      ...      ...      &quot;...      26Luxembourg ...      :..      ...	.; &apos; &apos;-:..     ...     ...    20 -Netherlands   ...	...     ...      ...      ... 2,000Italy   ...      ...      ...      ...	:..      ...     44United Kingdom     ...      ...	...      ...      ...      31For this purpose the German output in 1952-53 is assumed to be the 11-1 million tons permitted maximum under the level of industry plan. She has, however, a capacity currently available of about 14-15 million tons.52. These programmes of development are involving the countries in veryconsiderable capital expenditure as appears in the following estimated costs ofexisting development plans:    millionItaly ...GermanyHolland       ......France......................    100Belgium-Luxembourg       ...      ...      ......      ...      50United Kingdom    ...      ....      ..........      ...    250These estimates may need revision in the light of rising costs, &amp;c, and in thecase of Germany it is not clear whether the cost of a contemplated new strip millis included.53. Two points stand out from these figures. Firstly, the relative scale ofdevelopment in France and Germany has been artificially determined by therestrictions imposed on Germany from outside and, therefore, bears no relationto the distribution that would have occurred had decisions been taken by a commonauthority on the economic merits of the case. If, therefore, the establishment ofan Authority were to accelerate the release of Germany from some of the Currentresrictions on her steel industry, the Authority would be confronted with some very awkward problems on the distribution of development between the French
arid German industries. Secondly, certain countries :(e.g., Italy, Holland) which show a very high rate of expansion, are the least well endowed with natural resources for operating a steel industry on competitive terms and it is improbable that these industries could survive for long, save in conditions of scarcity, withoutprotection or some form of subsidy, the maintenance of which would be clearlyinconsistent with their long-run obligations as members of a group of the type which we have discussed. .,m ;-. - v .......54. The conclusions of the preceding sections may be summed up asfollows:  (i) The coal and steel industries of Europe are fundamental to the Europeaneconomy and in both of them large-scale development is taking place and further development is planned.(ii) There is some prospect that Europe may be faced with conditions ofover-supply in both coal and steel.(iii) There are forces at work some active, some latent which tend to preventthe most efficient development of Europe&apos;s coal and steel resources andwhich in a period of over-supply might well lead to the intensification of undesirable trade practices by industries and nations, the conse-quences of which would affect not only the welfare but also thesecurity of Europe.&apos; (iv) It is not clear what basic economic principle lies at the root of the Schumanscheme but We.have suggested that to meet the conditions described above there is a case for an approach to freer market conditions in theEuropean coal and steel trades under the supervision of an international authority.(v) Owing to the different position of the various coal and steel industriesthese conditions Would have to be introduced progressively, withtransitional safeguards to avoid serious industrial and socialdislocation.(vi) But the United Kingdom is probably in at least as strong a position asthe other members of the group to set the pace.In short it is our view that there is a case for concerted international action oneconomic grounds in regard to the coal and steel industries of Europe, that themore we depart from scarcity conditions, the more imperative the need for inter-national action will become and that therefore the sooner a suitable organisation is established the better.55. The Schuman declaration assigned to the proposed Authority a numberof very far-reaching tasks which are set out in paragraph 15 above. These taskswere not elaborated in the Schuman declaration and have since received scantillumination from the French authorities. We think, therefore, that it would bemore profitable not to speculate on the content which the French may wish to assign to their statement, but to define the tasks which in our view could usefully be discharged by an international coal and steel Authority, in Europe in which theUnited Kingdom could participate. For this purpose we assume that the basicobjective is that discussed in Section III of this memorandum and elaborated indetail in paragraph 18. We also assume that the Authority&apos;s concern will be withthe co-ordination of the international trade aspects of coal and steel and not directly with internal management of the coal and steel industries.56. What are the interests which would make it economically desirable forus to co-operate in an international coal and steel Authority? Firstly, we areconcerned to see a satisfactory balance of supply and demand maintained at a level of prices which will stand in reasonable relation to costs of efficient produc-tion. Secondly, we should like to maintain a price level which, consistently withthe foregoing, should not be subject to wide fluctuations either upwards or down-wards, as a means of assisting general economic stability. Thirdly, we should liketo see production concentrated in those countries and areas which are able toproduce most efficiently and at lowest cost.  Fourthly, we would want wages in1   : -38875     - -\ * / &apos; f
competing countries to be raised nearer to our own level, and, in no case, a strugglefor markets giving rise to a price-cutting war.   These desiderata imply:  (a) a long-term need to co-ordinate development programmes in order tosecure, so far as is reasonably practicable,(i) that investment in the industries is not seriously excessive in rela-tion to the prospective demand; I(ii) that investment should take place in those countries which can produce most efficiently;(b) a short-term need to harmonise output and marketing policies withdemand, to deal with any serious disequilibrium between demand and supply generally and within the economies of the members of the group in particular;(c) the formulation of such proposals as may usefully be concerted for equalis-ing and improving living conditions in the industries concerned.57. The existence of an international Authority for these purposes is justified by:  (a) the fundamental importance of coal and steel to the economies of western Europe;(b) the fact that underinvestment in these industries takes a long time to correct and can check industrial development generally;(c) the fact that over-investment in these industries can give rise to a veryserious waste of resources and to market dislocation;(d) Any short-term glut or shortage of production can cause such grave reper-cussions on the economies of producers or consumers that there arestrong grounds for seeking an agreed solution by co-operation and co-ordinated measures. In the event of a glut there is the prospect of a damaging commercial war with repercussions on wages and conditionsof work. In the event of shortage the interests of importing countries may be sacrificed to the interests of the producing country, and the fearof such a situation is itself a powerful inducement to embark onuneconomic, nationalistic and autarkic policies.Investment Regulation58. The justification of the Authority by reference to investment considera-tions clearly implies that it should be endowed with some effective influence on whether or not investment should take place. Moreover it seems well-nigh certainthat the French will attach particular importance to some surrender of sovereignty in this respect more perhaps as a point of principle than because it is likely to makea great deal of difference in practice. Even so, however, they would inevitably attach importance to the Authority&apos;s power to prevent an increase in Germany&apos;s steel-making capacity unless it was agreed to be justified by a prospective demand whichcould not be economically met from the existing capacity of the member countries;59. Assuming, therefore, that it may be a pre-requisite of any agreementconsistent with the objective of promoting peace and of providing through economicmeans the political ends of a Franco-German settlement, that the Authority mustbe endowed with the power of final decision over at least some part of the invest-ment field, then we must consider whether from our point of view the endowmentof the Authority with that power would (a) represent a tolerable degree of intersference with national sovereignty, and (b) be likely, on balance, to redound to theadvantage of this country.60. It might be thought that, if the answer to (b) was affirmative, then the answer to (a) would be affirmative also. But this does not follow. Endowed with full powers the Authority might decide, having reviewed the National Plan, nowalmost completed by the National Coal Board, that the scale of investment proposed,for example, for the Durham coalfield was not justified; that a plan which perhapsalready contemplated the closing down of a considerable number of collieriesshould be carried still further, and that any resulting shortage of supplies of cokingcoal should be made good by the Ruhr, on the ground that this quality of coalcould be produced and delivered more cheaply there than in Durham. the possession of full powers of this kind might, therefore, lead to the Government(to which the Board&apos;s National Plan will have been referred) being obliged toaccept, against its better judgment, a decision by the Authority which would lead
to unemployment in the Durham coalfields, and thereby to social and political problems, and perhaps a serious industrial dispute. Irrespective of the benefits whichthe country as a whole might derive from other decisions of the Authority, it mightbe held that surrender of sovereignty in a matter of that kind could not be tolerated.61. Turning now to (&amp;)-the probable balance of advantage to this country ;it is, for example, known that Italy has expensive reconstruction schemes in mind,the economic justification of which may not be clearly established. Moreover itis certain that there is now being maintained in existence a considerable capacityof coal output, both in France and in Belgium, which is already uneconomic andholds out no promise of ever becoming economic as a result of any scale of invest-ment within the bounds of reason. M. Monnet has expressed the view that the onlyadjustment immediately called for in France would be the closure of mines witha present annual output of some 10 million tons of coal. The projects which theUnited Kingdom has in mind in this field are less likely to be exposed to anyjustifiable criticism, and, in general, we are less prone to embark on or maintainuneconomic projects than certain other potential member countries where national or industrial prestige, military considerations, or uneconomic relief works havetraditionally tended to lead to this type of development. The conclusion from thisappears to be, therefore, that the endowment of the Authority with a power of final decision over investment which is pretty plainly uneconomic would be likelyon balance to redound to the advantage of this country.62. The question of the extent of this power remains to be discussed. Thedifficulty of any close comparison between the merits of rival schemes is great even within an industry in a single country. It would clearly be greater still if two ormore countries were concerned. Not only are the ultimate costs of long-termprojects, such as the erection of a new steel works, or the sinking of new collieries,exceedingly difficult to forecast accurately, but the level of demand, at the timewhere the investment begins to bear fruit, is also speculative to a greater or less degree. These difficulties could not fail to be appreciated by the Authority, andeven were it endowed with the fullest powers of decision over investment it would inevitably hesitate long before attempting to interfere with some national or commercial project. Indeed, unless it were its policy to work, as far as possible, bypersuasion, publicity and argument supported by the prestige of its members andthe good judgment and integrity they display, reserving its powers to deal only with blatantly uneconomic projects supported by obviously specious argument, itwould be courting, not only failure for itself, but also for the whole future of what has been called &quot; functional internalisation &quot; as an approach to a united Europe.63. Whether it would be either necessary or practicable to impose somelimitation on the powers of the Authority to determine investment programmesor projects is open to some doubt. The value of the possession of residual powers which could have been invoked in the last resort, but in fact never were, is withinthe experience of all of us. Equally, we have experienced the difficulty of defining,to the satisfaction of lawyers, what are regarded as important issues which mustbe safeguarded, and those of less importance which could be left alone. We can hardly hope, therefore, in a document of the kind here in question, that it will bepossible precisely to define the circumstances in which member countries mustsecure the consent of the Authority without the danger that ways of evading thosedefinitions may, given the will, be devised.64. Perhaps, therefore, a practical solution might be found in an adaptation of words from the United Kingdom socialisation statutes to the general effect thatprogrammes and projects involving substantial expenditure on capital account must be subject to the approval of the Authority. It would be understood thatthe Authority would have the right to call for supplementary information and estimates on particular aspects of the programmes or projects, as well as havingrights of inspection, and to veto them in a whole or in part. Alternatively, theAuthority might be required to draw up rules, for approval by the Governmentsof the member countries, defining the limitations within which it proposedto work.65. Besides the power of veto the Authority should have, in strict logic, thethe power to require investment on supplies required for member countries(e.g., production of anthracite in the United Kingdom). But it seems improbable that there would be any real pressure on this point, and it should be sufficient toleave the Authority simply with power to recommend.
66. An alternative but less radical solution to that put forward in para-graphs 58-65 would be to withold from the Authority the power of final decision and rely on it being able to secure by agreement between the members such adjustments in their programmes as appeared to the Authority to be necessary.On this basis the Authority&apos;s influence would have to rest primarily on:  (a) its ability to secure agreement through the respect and reputation whichit commanded; i(b) the publication of its recommendations; and: (c) a requirement that Governments which felt unable to conform to theAuthority&apos;s recommendations would make public their reasons.The French would presumably regard this as very little advance on the functionsnow exercised by O.E.E.C. in regard to steel development save that the forum for reviewing proposals would be a more independent and specialised and perhaps moreauthoritative body. On the other hand the coal and steel industries have indicated to us that they would not favour the more extreme solution and indeed we weregiven to understand that the steel industry would regard this step with greater mis-giving than a move towards freer market conditions by the elimination of tariffs.The view of the industries is that at least for an experimental period the arrange-ment should rest on the basis of consultation and recommendation only.67. There is a difference of view in the Working Party as to which of the abovealternatives (i.e., powers to decide or only to recommend) would be preferable andthis is a point on which a decision by Ministers would be required.Output and Marketing Regulation68. The importance of the duty which would fall on the Authority for dealingwith any short-term glut or shortage of supplies needs little emphasis. Consump-tion of steel and coal is notoriously unresponsive to price stimuli, and, in the caseof steel in particular inability to produce at, or near to, capacity has a serious effect upon costs; while in the case of coal, the recourse to unemployment benefits which subsidised short-time working before the war seems unlikely to be practicable,even if it were desirable. It was these basic factors in the situation which gave rise to the pre-war steel cartels and other international agreements in steel and coal and it must be the aim of the present proposals to establish a system which, while retaining the advantages of these agreements, at the same time imposes adequate safeguards for the interests of others besides those concerned in production. Itshould therefore be the duty of the Authority to forecast from time to time the expected availability of steel and coal in relation to the estimated demand for them,and to keep under continuous review the state of the market in regard both to supplies and prices. In the event of any significant disequilibrium becomingmanifest the Authority should require the parties to come together and to contrivean agreed solution which the Authority would feel able to endorse as being in thegeneral interest of producers and consumers alike. In particular, if the disequili-opprobrium were to prove both serious and persistent it would be a duty of the Authorityto seek a solution that was consistent with the most efficient development of theindustry in the long run and to ensure the inefficient units were not kept alive onthe backs of the efficient.Equalising and Improving Living Conditions69. We turn now to the important field of wages and living conditions ofthose working in the coal and steel industries. The equalisation as well as theimprovement of living conditions featured prominently in the Schuman proposals,but the idea was not elaborated further. In paragraph 18 (iv) and 30 we have attempted to indicate the significance of this concept and the field in which work could usefully be done. We assume that the improvements are to be achieved by levelling up and not by averaging conditions between the various countries, andthat the resources of one national industry are not to be employed to subsidiseimprovements in conditions elsewhere. We have considered what action an inter-national Authority could usefully take without entrenching on matters of national wages policy outside its proper sphere or usurping functions which properlybelong to the established negotiating machinery of the various countries.70. In the first place it should, we suggest, be provided in the treaty estab-lishing the proposed Authority that the Government in each country should do
what it could to encourage the maintenance and development of satisfactorymachinery for negotiating wages and conditions of employment in the industries in its country.71. The treaty should also oblige Governments to provide machinery forsecuring that wages and conditions of employment that may be negotiated in industries in their countries are observed by all the employers in the industry intheir country. At present this condition applies to all industries in this country under the Conditions of Employment and National Arbitration Order (S.R. and O.,1940, No. 1305). This Order is a temporary one originating in war-time, but thereis some reason to suppose that this part of the Order may be indefinitely extended and in any case there appears to be no reason why the principle of this part of theOrder should not be made permanent for the coal and steel industries in all thecountries in the proposed scheme. The establishment by this means of a firm&quot; floor &quot; to conditions in the industries in each country would facilitate efforts bythe more progressive employers to improve the terms and conditions of employment.72. The Authority should be given the function of collecting and publishingdetailed information about wages in the industries in each particular country, andit could publish authoritative studies showing the comparative real value of wagesand earnings in each country. This would provide a basis from which the tradeunions could work to secure the improvement of the wage structure in the lessfavourably situated countries.73. With regard to conditions of work as distinct from wages, a useful directpart could be played by the Authority in respect to conditions affecting safety and health. These are already governed by national regulations and are the subjectof international conventions, while there are precedents for some regulation in thefield of hours of work and holidays. It is suggested that the Authority might begiven the function of collecting and publishing information and making recom-mendations concerning working conditions other than wage questions, and thatthe Governments in the scheme might undertake to consult the Authority beforeformulating their policy on matters arising at the I.L.O. which concerned the coal and steel industries.74. The Governments in the scheme should undertake to encourage themaintenance and establishment of machinery for joint consultation between repre-sentatives of management and workers on all questions of common interest(including the improvement of efficiency in the industry) other than those dealtwith by the wage negotiating machinery. The Authority might arrange to collectand circulate information about successful schemes of joint consultation of this character.Supervision of Trade Agreements75. As a complement to the arrangements proposed in paragraph 68, thecoal and steel industries of member countries should be required to notify theAuthority of any agreements affecting production, markets and prices which they propose to make with one another in order that the Authority may satisfy itselfthat they are not against the public interest and are not prejudicial to the efficientutilisation of the European coal and steel resources. In the event of disapprovalby the Authority, member Governments would undertake to render the agreementsnull and void.Discriminatory Practices76. In order to promote the most efficient distribution of production, theAuthority should be empowered to undertake either on its own initiative or atthe request of a member country, investigations into any discriminatory practices which are, prima facie, deemed to be prejudicial to the efficient production anddistribution of coal and steel. Governments should undertake to obtain on behalfof the Authority such information as the Authority requires for this purpose. this could embrace such issues as access to supplies of raw materials and fuel, access tomarkets within the group, unfair competition through subsidies or other discrimina-tory practices. The Authority^ findings and recommendations would be published.Some (but not all) types of discriminatory practices would be offences against theG.A.T.T; and the International Trade Organisation (I.T.O.) Charter, and in thesecases the Contracting Parties to G.A.T.T. or the I.T.O. could assist the authority in dealing with an offender.38875 g
Price Policy - - . -   . 177. The original Schuman communique proposed that the Authority should secure &quot; the supply of coal and steel on identical terms to the French and to theGerman markets as well as.to the markets of other member countries.&quot; This ispresumably to be interpreted as proposing, not that different suppliers of coal andjsteel should all charge the same price, but that any one supplier must charge,broadly the same price (ex works or f.o.b.) to all his customers within the group;whether they are his fellow nationals or not. This would rule out both &quot; dualpricing &quot; (higher prices for export than for domestic markets) and &quot; dumping &quot;(lower prices for export) so far as sales within the group were concerned. Wehave assumed that this must be regarded as one aspect of the principle of equalaccess to supplies and markets as between members of the group. We have alsoassumed the development of measures to harmonise demand and supply in accor-dance with our own economic interest as described in paragraph 56 (b) above.The application of these principles to the price policies of individual member countries raises problems which we now turn to examine.78. There seems to be a choice between three broad methods of fixing prices for transactions within the group which would differ from one another in theextent and nature of the interference with market prices, viz:  (i) to leave prices substantially to the free play of supply and demand;(ii) to allow the separate national Governments to control prices in their homemarkets or not as they choose;(iii) to agree that prices should be controlled throughout the area on someagreed common principle approved by the Authority.79. The Free Market Solution. This is the most obvious method of eliminat-ing dual prices, of harmonising demand and supply (albeit only in the long run)and generally of affording equal access to supplies and markets. The solution would presumably accord with the present economic philosophy of France, Ger-many, Belgium and Italy, but it is doubtful whether these countries would beprepared to carry their philosophy to this logical conclusion, and whether it wouldaccord with the degree of control which the French propose (initially, at least,and for political reasons, perhaps for some years ahead) should reside with theAuthority. Even under this system some interference by Governments might be needed for the prevention of dual pricing in times of shortage, for by a free marketsolution we do not mean the establishment of the perfect competition of economictextbooks, but only the absence of interference by national Governments or aninternational Authority with the general level of prices which emerges from theoperations of the market. Where the industry is effectively integrated either bysingle ownership (e.g., the National Coal Board) or by an effective central organisa-tion in close touch with the Government (e.g., the United Kingdom iron and steelindustry), the prevention of dual pricing should not present serious difficulty toa Government which wished to achieve it. In less integrated industries it wouldprobably give rise to a troublesome problem of enforcement. The free marketsolution would, however, involve the abandonment of price stabilisation in the domestic market which at present governs both steel and coal.80. Independent National Price Policies. Under the second system national governments would be free to choose whether or not to control prices in their own home markets. If, as is possible, the various members of the Group choosedifferently, the combination of free and price controlled national markets in the trading area of the group would be extremely troublesome Thus in a period of shortage the price controlled economy would have to restrict exports in order tomaintain supplies for the home market at any desired level, unless it were able toadopt a system of dual pricing which equated external demand with the suppliesit was prepared to make available for export. In a period of surplus it would haveto restrict imports in order to maintain internal prices at a relatively higher level than those in the free markets outside. The price controlled economy would, there-fore, be forced either to abandon its price control policy or impose export or import controls to maintain it. Yet by doing the latter it would come up against the prin-ciple of equal access to supplies and markets. Theoretically the restrictions on exports and imports would be defensible in relation to the principle of equal access,if they were so operated as to fix exports and imports to and from members of thegroup at the levels which would obtain under free market conditions. But it.isdifficult to determine what this distribution would be except by establishing the
free market. There is here a real dilemma which will persist, particularly in thecase of steel, so long as the United Kingdom follows a policy of long-run stability of prices and its continental competitors pursue a free market policy with a wideprice swing. It is difficult in these circumstances to see any practical solutionexcept to allow the national Governments to take action to protect their domesticprice policies, with some provision for appeal to the Authority by an aggrievedmember country which felt that its interests were being unfairly and gravely jeopar-dised by the export and import policies and practices of the price controlledconomy. Acceptance of this solution does, of course, open the door to the practiceof substantially reserving the home market for the home producer which may notbe easy to reconcile with the most efficient distribution of production over the area as a whole. So long, however, as divergences in national policies of this kind con-tinue, it would be an appreciable advance to have an independent body of inter-national standing which could serve, not as the arbiter but as a mediator, to facilitatea fair solution of particular problems that may arise between members.81. A system of this type, in which the prices paid to the producer in one country are controlled at levels which may be very different from those ruling infree markets outside, also raises difficulties of quite another kind. Any country(either the controlling country or another) whose needs as consumer are satisfiedpartly from the controlled and partly from the free industry will be receiving someof its supplies at different prices from others. This will raise problems of fairdistribution, and of the prevention of uncovenanted profits to importers, which mayimpel the consuming country to institute some scheme, e.g., a central purchasingagency for bulking imported and home produced supplies (or supplies from different foreign sources) and charging an average price to the consumer. A policyof this sort has been followed in the United Kingdom in relation to imports of steel.Under the type of scheme discussed in this Report it might be necessary for theoperations of such central purchasing agencies to be supervised by the Authority inorder to prevent their use as instruments of the illegitimate protection of domesticindustries.82. Co-ordinated national controls. The third possible solution is theinstitution of a system whereby the prices of each national group of producers are controlled domestically on some agreed common principle, under the general super-vision of the Authority. The objects of the Authority should be to ensure-(a) that prices should be kept reasonably stable; and(b) that they should reflect differences in the true long-period costs ofproduction of different groups of producers.The achievement of the first objective would remove the dangers to the UnitedKingdom stabilisation policy which, as has been explained above, are inherent in the first and second types of price system. The achievement of the secondobjective would ensure that the price system would act so as to encourage, andnot to hamper, the production of European coal and steel in the most efficient way.The share of the market obtained by different industries would be determined bytheir relative prices in combination with transport costs. High cost producerswould find their markets restricted and would tend gradually to be displaced bythe more efficient centres.83. To achieve these ends the Authority need not itself fix prices but couldsupervise the prices fixed within countries. It would secure the general adoptionof some common formula such as the basing of prices on the costs of the efficientproducer, and would have regard in its supervisory activities to the interests ofrival producers and of consumers as well as to stability and the general objectives of the plan.84. It should be noted that the existence of separate national price-controlsmight well produce the same kind of problem for consumer countries as it was shown above (paragraph 81) would arise under independent national policies,though it seems probable that the extent of the possible price disparities wouldbe much smaller. As suggested in paragraph 81, some system averaging prices couldbe adopted to deal with this problem if required.85. Conclusion. This review of the various alternative systems of price-determination has shown that the co-existence in a &quot; free trade bloc &quot; of competitiveand price-controlled industries would be fraught with many difficulties. A Govern-ment wishing to maintain controls in such a group would have to retain the power
to impose quantitative control of exports and imports. The abandonment ofsuch controls, which is necessarily one of the ultimate objectives of the scheme,would be feasible only if all markets were freed or if all were controlled accordingto some common principle; and only the latter of these two alternatives wouldenable the United Kingdom to abandon quantitative restrictions while maintaining the policy of stabilising coal and steel prices.i .Tariffs, Quantitative Restrictions and Subsidies86. The Schuman Plan proposes as a step towards the rationalisation of thecoal and steel industries that all coal and steel customs duties between member states should be abolished. It is probably significant that this proposal is unaccom-panied by any reference to the removal or abatement of quantitative regulation ofimports or of subsidies to the coal and steel industries, although these can be equally effective in protecting inefficient industries and preventing the most efficientdistribution of production. It was no doubt realised only too well by the authorsof the Plan that during the transition period these secondary defences would be badly needed by some of the industries of Europe. There may, indeed, even have been some expectation that they might be fortified by marketing arrangements madeunder the aigis of the Authority, which would moderate the full rigour of the freercompetition implicit in the abolition of tariffs. In the earlier part of our report we have suggested that the concept of freedom for the movement of coal and steel in Europe in order to promote efficiency would require the parties to work towardsthe reduction and eventual removal not only of tariffs, but also of quantitativeregulations and subsidies. We have also suggested that if this be the aim, we areat least in as strong a position as our European competitors to set the pace.87. It should, we think, be an objective of the participatng countries andthe Authority that a situation should be reached in which all tariffs and quantitative restrictions on coal and steel are removed on trade between participating countries.88. For the reasons which we have discussed in Sections III and IV of our report, it is recognised that these conditions cannot be achieved immediately, andit is only on the following conditions that the arrangements could be brought fully into operation:  (i) All participating countries should have adopted a common general price policy, either of freely competitive prices or of prices fixed accordingto principles common to all the member countries, e.g., on a basis thatensured the elimination of dumping, dual pricing and selling below costof production (including a reasonable margin for profit).(ii) The elimination of abnormally and unfairly low rates of wages andunfavourable conditions of labour. There are serious theoretical and practical difficulties in defining &quot; unfairly low &quot; wages and we thinkthat in practice it would have to be left to the Authority to decide what could be regarded as reasonable and fair in the light of the generalliving standards and the productivity of labour in each of the member countries.(iii) There should be no artificial discrimination in regard to subsidies, trans-port rates, supply of capital, &amp;c, as between the steel industry andother industries within the participating country.89. It would be obligatory on participating countries to abolish all tariffs and quantitative restrictions provided the foregoing conditions were substantiallyfulfilled and, in any event, no country should employ such restrictions to an extentgreater than is required to meet divergences due to the above considerations.90. It would be the responsibility of the Authority to report annually on theprogress made in achieving these conditions of fair trade. When the authority is able to report that discriminatory practices are substantially eliminated, itwould be obligatory on participating countries to abolish all protective devicesother than any which may be approved by the Authority. This would, of course,be without prejudice to the right of member Governments to impose quantitative restrictions for a limited period for the protection of their balance of payments.91. In regard to the removal of tariffs, it is necessary to call attention tocertain implications of the proposal in relation to our international obligations.Duties will presumably be collected by each of the members of the group on allother goods, and each member country will levy its own duties, &amp;c, on iron and
steel &apos;(cbal is normally duty free) entering their eountries from any&apos; Gouhtry whichis not a partner to the Schuman Plan. Since such ah arrangement would be-inplain&quot;conflict with the: obligationsaccepted -Under the G.A..T.T, it &apos;would&apos; benecessary for the participants in the Schuman Planpt6-obtain- the&apos;consent of theparties; participating in the G-navy-Ti to the creation of jsuchr an, anomalousarrangement; those parties might then seek to impose the Jptal ^withdrawal of allImperial Preferences on iron and steel as a condition :pf, their consent,,;! : . acrd92. If Imperial Preference continues for iron and steel, it would presumablybe feasible, though troublesome, to set up a system o &quot; certificates of origin &quot; so asto limit the benefits of British imperial Preference id: British... iron and steel--presumably coal presents no problem: the French wpuld no doubt take similar measures in respect of the French Union. But there might be a claim from theparties to the Schuman Plan for access for their iron arid steel to Commonwealthmarkets on the terms which United Kingdom iron and steel now enjoys. . Sucha claim would be wholly at variance with the ideas underlying both imperial preference and the most-favoured-nation clause. Commonwealth countries, onthe other hand, might not demur to the total withdrawal of all preferences oniron and steel, though of course they may on general principles regret the degreeof integration of the United Kingdom with Europe which the Schuman Planimplies. ; .93. There is also the point that the United Kingdom has bound itself togive certain preferences to Commonwealth countries in respect of pig-iron and steelimports into the United Kingdom. Accordingly, any proposal to abolish the tariff on imports of these items from participants in the Schuman Plan would need tobe approved by the Commonwealth countries.Research94. The Authority should be empowered to promote and co-ordinate, whereit is useful to do so on an international basis, research and other work calculated to improve the productivity and efficiency of the coal and steel industries (e.g., the formulation of standardised costs systems, product Classification, standardisation of equipment, reciprocal visits by technical and productivity teams).Amortisation Fund and Machinery for Equating Prices95. The French proposals for the transitional period involve some financialreadjustments in relation to an amortisation fund and machinery for equatingprices. For the present we do not consider any useful purpose would be served by attempting to discuss these ideas until the intentions of the French have beenmade clear. There are, of course, obvious objections to the principle, which seems to be inherent in these ideas, of payments of subsidies by the industry ofone country to that of another.Sanctions v-96. It is not considered that there would be any advantage in giving theAuthority express powers to impose sanctions in order to compel member countries to follow particular policies, but there would not necessarily be any objection to(and indeed there might be some need for) sanctions to enforce agreementswillingly entered into by members. The nature of such sanctions would depend upon the terms of the various agreements of which they formed an integral part.The ultimate sanction for dealing with a member country consistently frustratingpolicies which commended themselves to the other members, or consistentlybreaking agreements into which it had voluntarily entered would, of course, beexpulsion from the group, but&apos;this would be a very far-reaching act which mighthave the effect of defeating the aims of the group:Local Legislation required \-97. A treaty embodying the features contained in the proposals which wehave made in this Section of our Report would require implementation by local legislation. The existing position in the member countries no doubt varies widely,and, while there has not been opportunity to consider the full implications so faras Great Britain is concerned, the following measures appear necessary.38875 &apos; &apos;   &apos;   . H    -
98. In the nationalisation acts for coal and steel, the appropriate minister would need, in addition to the approval of capital programmes and the powers ofissuing general directions in the national interest, a power to issue directions inaccordance with any decisions or recommendations of the Authority.99. The control of coal production is probably effectively in the hands of-the National Coal Board and the Ministry of Fuel and Power, but in the case of iron and steel there will be several hundred firms engaged in production and distri-bution which will be outside the control of the Iron and Steel Corporation of GreatBritain. In the case of these firms, therefore, it would be necessary for the Ministerto be given statutory powers on such matters as (a) the acquisition of information about transactions entered into by them when, in the opinion of the Authority,further elucidation was required, (b) the prevention of the carrying out of projects and agreements undertaken or made without the sanction of the Authority; (a) will involve powers to enter and inspect and require production of books and furnishingof information, backed up with the usual criminal sanctions. The enforcement of(b) involves some difficulty; it would be possible to make the projects and agree-ments null and void, but this in itself might not effectively prevent their execution,particularly abroad. So far as the United Kingdom is concerned the problem wouldbe substantially simplified by the fact that the British Iron and Steel Federation, onbehalf of the steel industry, has already indicated its unwillingness to enter into any international agreements which do not meet with the approval of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.Definition of &quot; Steel &quot;100. This would be a matter for negotiation, not raising any special problems.The following list of ranges of products is generally accepted by the UnitedKingdom:  (a) Iron-ore.(b) Scrap.(c) Pig-iron, including foundry iron and ferro-alloys produced in the blast furnace.(d) Steel and ferro-alloys produced in the furnaces and converters.(e) Steel processed by hot rolling and forging.(/) Steel casting.(g) Cold rolled and cold drawn steel products (i.e., cold rolled sheet and stripand wire drawing).(h) Tubes seamless and welded.(i) Tinplate.(/) Rivets, bolts and nuts.(k) Iron castings.Strategic Interest101. It is to the interest of the United Kingdom strategically that in generalits iron and steel industry should be as strong, as self-sufficient and as securelylocated as possible. We do not think, however, that participation in the schemewhich we have proposed would be likely to involve any major adjustment of theindustry which would impair its development in these respects to an extent which need give rise to anxiety on the part of the United Kingdom. The United kingdom has also a particular concern to see that no regrouping of the industry takes place as between the United Kingdom and the continental countries which would diminishits domestic self-suffiiency as regards the special alloy steels and other specialitysteel items essential in defence production. On this ground it would be necessaryto suggest that certain specialised fields should receive protection if required andbe excepted from the general application to the area of the free trade principle.The greater the community of policy on defence matters (e.g., through the north atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) ) that is maintained between all or amajority of members of the group, the less difficulty in practice is likely to springfrom this proviso.Consequences of Non-Participation by the United Kingdom102. It may be convenient at this point to consider briefly what might be theconsequences to the United Kingdom steel and coal industries, if we declined tobecome members of this group.
(i) Coal103. The effect of the Schuman proposals on the British coal trade can be best envisaged if we assume that all those who have so far been invited to joindo, in fact, join except the United Kingdom. Before the war the French and Italianmarkets were the two most important outlets for United Kingdom coal exports,and any substantial recovery of United Kingdom export trade would have toinclude a substantial contribution in the way of higher exports to those twocountries. The formation of the new group in any effective form would strengthen the economic links between Germany and the other members, especially with france, and any reversion to quantitative restrictions, such as those imposed by france, Belgium and Holland before the war, would tend to be interpreted in a manner favourable to Germany, and, in the case of France, this could be doneunobtrusively through the National Coal Importing Agency. The extent to whichthe importing members of the group would be likely to discriminate unnecessarilyin favour of Germany should not, however, be exaggerated.104. The abolition of dual prices would bring down the prices of german coal not only in the markets of the member countries, but also in Europe generally,so that the effect upon the Board&apos;s finances of not joining the group would be much the same as if it had joined. (The group export prices might conceivably beinflated by the costs of French and Belgian production if a transitional priceequalisation scheme involving subsidies from one national industry to anotherwere adopted.) A further disadvantage would be that the United Kingdom wouldbe somewhat less likely to participate in the market created by the closure of uneconomic collieries by members of the group than it would be if we were alsoa member.105. The National Coal Board, on the other hand, fear that inclusion in thegroup would prevent them retaining their commercial flexibility, and the UnitedKingdom its bargaining strength, as an exporter of coal and an importer of food and raw materials, vis-a-vis both member and non-members of the group. It seemsto us, however, unnecessary to assume that membership of the group would so erodeour natural bargaining advantages.106. In regard to the position of Poland, it is difficult to see how, with bothPoland and the United Kingdom outside, the group could effectively control thecoal export market since, together, they account for a considerably greater volumeof export trade than the members of the group. The Coal Board suggest that whereas from inside the group the possibility of co-operation with Poland wouldbe poor, outside it, the United Kingdom would be free, at least to attempt, to reach an understanding with them. In our view, however, the chances of reaching asatisfactory arrangement with Poland would be greater if we could confront themwith a combination of all the coal-producing countries of Western Europe than would be the case if the United Kingdom were operating separately from the group.(ii) Steel107. In the group which we have been considering the output of steel is substantially greater than that of the United Kingdom. Furthermore, the removalof all artificial barriers to trade and the ending of discriminatory practices shouldmake possible the organisation of production in the area at an appreciably lowercost than would be possible under present conditions. The economic power of a group so strengthened would be considerable, and if conditions of trade warexisted between it and the United Kingdom they might be able to inflict consider-able damage to United Kingdom industries by striking at sources of supply of iron-ore and at the export markets for United Kingdom steel.108. It does not, however, seem realistic to assume conditions of permanenttrade war, although for a time the struggle might be acute. Sooner or later agree-ments would doubtless be made between the United Kingdom and the group, andthe practical question is whether the results of such agreements for the UnitedKingdom would be better or worse than those of membership in the group. the answer to this question turns in part on the terms on which we would be able tojoin the group. If we could make it a condition of joining that we did notsurrender either Imperial Preference or the right to make bilateral trade agree-ments affecting trade in coal and steel, we should obtain terms certainly more readily and possibly more advantageously in bargaining about trade inside the
group than outside. But it does not seem likely that the advantage would be veryconsiderable. Even if isolated the United Kingdom would remain a very powerfuleconomic unit with important elements of bargaining strength. Though thearrangements which it might secure in bargaining with the group might be in some respects less advantageous than it would have obtained as a member, there doesnot seem to be any danger of really grave economic loss resulting,   1,109. Qne further possibility should be mentioned under this heading., Ifthe other countries decided to form a group without us, their best chance of makinga success of it would, in our view, rest upon the enlargement of their geographicalscope so as to include some if not all of the Scandinavian countries in whose marketsour coal and steel producers have a traditional interest: indeed, if the Swedes couldbe induced to join the organisation while the United Kingdom remained outside,the members would have preferential access to not merely markets of importanceto the United Kingdom but also to an important source of vital raw materials.110. It is, however, in our view mistaken to seek to view this problem in isolation as one of iron and steel only. The Scandinavian countries to whom we hope to sell iron, steel and coal, hope in turn to sell us bacon, butter, timber,pulp, &amp;c, and their prospective production of these commodities is likely to beon a scale which will lead them to regard the United Kingdom as a desirablecustomer. Such countries are unlikely to accede wholeheartedly to suggestionsfrom producers in the proposed group that consumers should, without a markedprice advantage, direct their buying effort in coal and steel towards the output ofgroup members and away from the United Kingdom. On the other hand, UnitedKingdom steel producers would have to face the problem of supplying steel to thosecountries under the handicaps imposed by discriminatory tariff. The effect of thishandicap upon the profitability of this part of their output is difficult to assess, butthere is reason to think that although the situation which might confront them wouldbe awkward, the difficulties would not be insurmountable; and if these countriesshow as exporters a strong motive for trading with the United Kingdom, we might expect that the producer members would not succeed in efforts to exclude UnitedKingdom steel and coal altogether from such markets, but there would be some lossof volume and profitability. ,11L On the other hand, if the membership of the group were confined merely to producers, e.g., France and Germany only, these producers would have as acondition of earning profits to sell much of their output in &quot; neutral markets *&apos;Whether in Europe or elsewhere. In such circumstances the United Kingdom steelindustry should be able to hold its own.112. In this section we have so far been concerned merely with weighing upthe effect of the United Kingdom V non-participation on its commercial bargainingstrength. This suggests that by staying out the United Kingdom might suffer some,but not intolerable, disadvantage over a continuing period. There is, however, the wider consideration which must not be overlooked, viz., that non-participation fromthe outset would deny to the United Kingdom the larger economic advantages dis-Cussed earlier in this Report which would accrue from international co-operativeaction of the sort we have envisaged.Constitution of the Authority113. Finally we have considered the type of Authority which could appro-piriately undertake functions of the kind proposed in this Section of our Report.These functions can be classified broadly as follows:  (i) To investigate and report, e.g., in regard to discriminatory practices;(ii) To co-ordinate and mediate, e.g., in regard to investment, marketingschemes, prices, &amp;c.;(iii) To supervise, e.g., the operation of schemes agreed between members; and(iv) To act as a court of reference..114. In regard to (i) and (ii) it is inherent in our proposals that the authority would be empowered to take the initiative and in certain circumstances to exercise a power of veto (see paragraphs 58-64) as well as to act at the instance of member countries.115. Having regard to the nature of the functions, we do not think that theAuthority need be supra-national hi order to ensure the effective discharge of its
responsibilities. Nor need the Authority be given any outward form which marksit as a prototype of federal institution for Europe nor carry any implications forthe future political unity of Europe.116. Moreover we do not envisage that the Authority will acquire ownership of assets of the coal and steel industries of member countries or pool receiptsor profits of these industries and thereby acquire any responsibilities in regard tothe internal management of national industries.117. We do not think that any of the existing international bodies in Europecould successfully carry out the functions which we contemplate if only because itwould at this stage be psychologically impossible to fall back on any of these institutions and because national representation on them is different from that inthe group so far envisaged by M. Schuman.118. It is desirable in our view that the Authority should consist of inde-pendent personalities who are neither representatives of the coal or steel industriesnor delegates of member Governments. Only thus can it acquire the prestige andreputation for fair-minded and objective judgement that are essential if it is to command the respect of the countries and industries with whose affairs it will be concerned. Nominations should be made by Governments who sign the ConstituentTreaty, possibly on a numerical basis roughly similar to that of the international authority for the Ruhr, where the United Kingdom, France and Germany havethree members each and the Benelux countries one member each, and should befor a period of years rather than for life. Provision should be made to ensure that new appointments do not have to be made simultaneously. The Authority shouldalso be indenpendent in the sense that once its functions and powers have beenestablished by a treaty between member covmtries, the Authority would itselfdetermine how it should carry on its work.119. Though independent in this sense, the Authority should nevertheless beresponsible in its collective capacity to member Governments collectively. Theindividual members of the Authority should have no several responsibility to orbe subject to instructions of the Goverments which nominated them.120. The Authority would require a strong staff in order to provide thefirmest possible basis for its recommendations or decisions. This staff should beappointed with the minimum regard to national or geographical considerations.It should be appointed by the Authority in order to ensure its independence andshould be under the Authority&apos;s sole control.121. Whether the Authority is taking decisions or merely making recom-mendations, it should clearly endeavour to secure in advance the maximum measureof agreement with Governments and interests affected. Different problems would necessitate consultation over a different range and it would, therefore, be a mistake to define too strictly the consultative machinery to be used by the Authority, pro-vided that it adequately takes account of the interests of member Governments,managements and workers in the coal and steel industries and consumers of coal and steel. There is no reason why the Authority should not have wide discretion to make its own arrangements in this sphere.122. In paragraph 119 above we refer to the collective responsibility of theAuthority to member Governments. For this purpose we think that it would be convenient for the member Governments to set up some representative body orcouncil through which the Authority would discharge its collective responsibility to Governments. This second body could consist either wholly of government representatives or, on the model of the I.L.O., of representatives not only of Govern-ments but also of workers and industrial interests not confined to the coal and steel industries. This second body or council would normally meet infrequently, sayonce or twice a year, unless specially convened.   Its main tasks would be (a) to consider regular reports from the Authority on its operations;(b) to deal with any problems of representation on the Authority not coveredby the normal rules of procedure (e.g., replacement of members of theAuthority who prove to be unsuitable for office);(c) to provide a forum for the discussion of recommendations of the authority which had given rise to disagreement.   Governments could bring before38875 &quot; * i
ifit cases in which decisions or recommendations of the Authority cp -flicted with their other obligations, and liaison could be maintained between it and other organisations on which participant governments were represenfed, e.g,, Q.E.EC., rJ.A.T.p. and the Allied high commission;^d) to approve the adj^inistratiye bpdget of t^e Authority. J123. Lastly, we do not think that having regard to the functions which wehave proposed for the Authority there is any need or indeed any room for specialappeal machinery.Signed on behalf of the Working Party,W. STRATH (Chairman).Treqsury, 16?/i June, 1950.
ANNEX IDEPENDENCE OF NATIONAL ECONOMIES ON COAL AND IRONAND STEEL INDUSTRIESNote by the Central Statistical Office\.-Coal Production and ConsumptionTable 1 gives coal-rproduction figures for each of the territories covered bythe French proposals. It will be seen that the United Kingdom produces about one-half of the total coal output of the group, Western Germany (the only area in which brown coal production is substantial) about one-quarter, and France about one-ninth (or with the Saar pne:seventh).Table 1Coed Production, 1938 and 1949Millions of metric tons			Hard coal	Total	Per cent, of	Hard coal,	Hard coal,	equivalent	(hard coal	total for a)l	1938 ;&apos;	&apos; 1949	of brown	equivalent),	countries,	- &quot;&apos;		coal, 1949	1949	1949&apos; &apos;0)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	c$United Kingdom	231-8	218-7		218-7	49 0Western Germany	138-5	104-8	16-1	120-9	27-france ...	46-5	51-2	0-6	51-8	11-6Saar    ...      ......	14-4	14-2		14^2	3-2Belgium-Luxembourg	29-6	27-9		27-9	6-2Netherlands   ......	13-5	11-7	0 1	11-8	2-6Italy    .........	1-5	1-1	0-4	1-5	0-3Total      ......	475-8	429-6	17-0	446-8	1000Belgium and the Netherlands also produce substantial quantities, Italy verylittle. The output of hard coal is below pre-war level in all cases except France, theshqf t-fall being much greater in Western Germany than elsewhere.&apos; Table 2&quot; goes some way to show the relative importance of coal as a source of energy in the different areas. The percentages given in column (3) in fact understatethe importance of coal, since electricity &quot;generated from coal is included in column (4).Table 2Consumption of Energy, in Different Forms (Coal Equivalent), 1949	Consumption of energy	Percentage of total derived from								(1)	(m. m. tons coal equivalent) (2)	Coal, coke and lignite (3)	Electric power (4)	Mineral oil (5)	Total (6)United Kingdom Western Germany France ...      ... Belgium-Luxembourg Netherlands   ... Italy    .........	231-0 113-6 100-3 32-4 19-4 26-1	74-6 73-6 67-4 75-9 58-2 32-3	13-4 21-7 17-7 16-0 19-6 50-0	12-0 4-7 14-9 8-0 22-2 17-7	100-0 1000 100-0 100-0 100-0 100-0Exact information about the proportions in which electricity is derived from coal and water-power is not at present available, but in all the countries, except
France and Italy, more than 60 per cent, of the electricity is generated from coal;in France the proportion is between 20 and 60 per cent., in Italy under 20 per cent.Allowing for these differences it is evident that dependence on coal as a source of energy is greatest in the United Kingdom, Western Germany and Belgium, and least in Italy, with France and the Netherlands occupying an intermediate position.Table 3 shows the extent to which each country depends on imports for itssupplies of coal (the figures are for 1948, 1949 figures not being as yet available).The United Kingdom does not normally import coal and Western Germanyimports only a little. France, Belgium and the Netherlands import a considerablefraction of their supplies, though less than one-half in each case; while Italy isalmost entirely dependent on imports.Table 3Dependence on Imports of Coal, 1948	Hard coal (million tons)		Imports as per cent, of consumption	Consumption	Imports	United Kingdom    ......	201-0		Western Germany   ...	.....  76-8	5-0	6-5France	62-6	19-7	31-4Saar v&quot;......	5-7	0-6	9-8Belgium-Luxemb ourg	30-4	5-3	17-4Netherlands.........	13-4	3-4	25-4Italy            ...      ......	8-9	8-0	89-9Table 4 shows the extent to which each country depends on foreign markets for the sale of the coal it produces. Apart from the special case of the Saar, nocountry exported as much as 20 per cent, of its output in 1948.Table 4Dependence on export markets for coal, 1948	Hard coal (million tons)		Exports as per cent, of Production	Production	Exports (excluding bankers)	United Kingdom    ......	212-8	11-7	5-5Western Germany   ...	88-4	16-5	18-6France	43-3	0-4	0-9Saar   .........      ...	12-6	-           .7-5	59-5Belgium-Luxembourg	26-7	1-5	5-6Netherlands  ......	11-0	10	9-1Italy	3-0		The proportion was greatest in Western Germany and least in France, withthe United Kingdom, Belgium and the Netherlands in intermediate positions.II. Steel Production and ConsumptionTable 5 gives figures for the production of crude steel in the various areas.The United Kingdom has the biggest share of the total, just over one-third in1949, with France and Germany each contributing about one-fifth and Belgium-Luxembourg one-eighth. This distribution is very different from that of 1938,when output in the United Kingdom, France and Belgium was much lower andin Germany much higher. Italian production is relatively small, that of theNetherlands very small.
		1949		1938						M. metric tons	M. metric tons	Per cent, of total united Kingdom    ...      ...	10-6	15-8	35-5Western Germany   ......	17-9	9-2	20-7France	6-2	9-2	20-7Saar   .........      ...	2-6	1-8	4-0Belgium-Luxembourg	3-7	6-1	13-7Netherlands  ......      ...	0-1	0-3	0-7Italy   ......     ......	2-3	2-1	4-7Total......	43-4	44-5	100-0In each country production is heavily dependent on imports of basic materialsor fuel. The figures in Table 6, taken from the E.C.E. Report on European SteelTrends, show the extent to which in the post-war period each country has beendependent on supplies of iron ore, scrap and fuel from other European countries.Both the United Kingdom and Western Germany get almost half their iron oresupplies from other European countries (largely from Sweden), while France issimilarly dependent for half her metallurgical fuel. Belgium, the Saar and theNetherlands import all their iron ore, while Luxembourg and Italy import all theirmetallurgical fuel.Table 6Dependence on Imports of Essential &apos;Raw Materials from Other european countries (in post-war period up to 1948)PercentagesProportion of total consumption represented by imports fromEuropeUnited Kingdom&quot;Western GermanyFranceSaar......BelgiumLuxembourgNetherlandsItaly......Iron ore (on basisof iron content)45451001005010010Scrap1020Metallurgical solidfuels (coal equivalent\355025100100The figures in Table 7 give a rough picture of the dependence of each country on imported steel. The two columns of figures are not strictly comparable, but may be taken as giving a fair general indication of the importance of imports ineach country&apos;s consumption of steel.Table 7Dependence on Imported Steel, 1949United KingdomWestern GermanyFrance and SaarBelgium and LuxembourgNetherlands   ......Italy    .........Consumptionof finished steel(hot rolled)10-05-86-11-31-11-7Millions of metric tonsImports of steel(crude, semis and finished,and iron castings)1-130-050-180-140-850-34Although the United Kingdom is the heaviest importer, the Netherlands andItaly are proportionately more dependent on imported supplies (about half theUnited Kingdom imports consists of semi-finished and finished products from belgium and Luxembourg).38875 kTable 5Production of Crude Steel, 1938 and 1949
Table 8Dependence on Export Markets for Steel, 1949United KingdomWestern GermanyFrance and SaarBelgium and LuxembourgNetherlands   ......Italy    .........Productionof crude steel15-89-211-06-10-32-1Millions of metric tonsExports of steel(crude, semis and finished jand iron castings)1-720-442-123-550-380-05Table 8 shows the extent to which each country depends on foreign markets for the sale of its steel. Belgium is chief exporter, being both absolutely, andproportionately to its production, well ahead of other members of the group.France and the United Kingdom also export a substantial part of their production on the export trade, while Western Germany, the Netherlands and Italy exportrelatively small quantities.III. Size of Engineering IndustriesTable 9 illustrates the relative size of the output in each country of the chiefsteel-using industry, i.e., the engineering industry, before the war and in 1949. it shows the United Kingdom industry as far the largest in the group, providing overTable 9Relative Sizes of Engineering Industries, 1938 and 1949PercentagesEngineering output as percentage of total for the listed countries1938United KingdomWestern GermanyFrance ...BelgiumNetherlands ...Italy    ......Total28-542-914-64-12-97-1100-0194942-525-018-74-93-95-1100-0two-fifths of the combined output. Western Germany comes second with a quarter, and it is a striking fact that the two leading countries have almost exactlyexchanged their percentage shares between 1938 and 1949. France is third with less than a fifth of the whole, while Italy, Belgium and the Netherlands are all inthe region of 4-5 per cent.IV. Em ploymentThe importance of the coal and iron and steel industries as employers of labour is illustrated in Table 10. For this purpose working population figures were esti-mated from the last population census and the trend of total population. Thefigures for employment in iron and steel are also very tentative, owing to difficultiesof definition.Table 101948United KingdomWestern Germany   ...France and SaarBelgium and LuxembourgNetherlands   ......Italy    .........Employmentin coal7243173461774013000&apos;sEmployment in coal andEmployment iron and steel as per cent, ofin iron and       \a)Working (b) Totalsteel population population520 5-7 2-5322 2-8 1-4152 2-4 1-266 6-2 2-713 1-4 0-591 0-5 0-2
The proportion of the labour force engaged in the coal and steel industries isgreatest in Belgium and the United Kingdom, being about equal in these twocountries. In Germany it is only about half as great as in the United Kingdom,and in France rather less than this, while in the Netherlands and Italy much lower proportions obtain.V. Importance of Coal and Steel Production in National IncomesTable 11 gives figures for the net output of the coal and steel industries inthe various countries and shows what proportion they form in combination of thenational income. The estimates are rather rough, but the general picture isprobably reliable.  Belgium has the highest percentage (7 - 7), followed closely byTable 11Proportion of National Income represented by output of Coal and Iron and SteelNet value of	Net value	Total of	Net national	Proportion ofcoal output	of steel output	(1) and (2)	income	(3) to (4)( m.)	( m)	( m.)	( m.)	(per cent.)(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	477	174	651	9,928	6-6284	95	379	5,410	7-0124	107	231	4,600	5-059	50	109	1,420	7-722	3	25	1,200	2-1.2	35	37   -	2,700	1-united Kingdom ...Western Germany...France and Saar ...Belgium andLuxembourgNetherlandsItaly ......Western Germany (7 - 0) and the United Kingdom (6 - 6), and at a greater distance;by France (5-0). In the Netherlands and Italy the proportions are relatively small.VI. Importance of Coal and Steel Products in ExportsTable 12 shows for each country the proportion of exports of coal, steel and machinery to the total exports of the country in 1948. Exports of coal from western Germany were large, both absolutely and as a proportion of total exports;exports from the United Kingdom were large absolutely but formed a relatively small fraction (3 -1 per cent.) of total exports. In other countries coal exports were small both absolutely and relatively. In exports of steel Belgium shows much thehighest figures both absolutey and relatively.  Again, the United Kingdom figureTable 12Importance of Coal, Iron, Steel and Engineering in each country &apos;s export trade, 1948Exports in 1948 in million dollars(excluding exports to dependent overseas territories)		Solid	Iron and	Machinery and	Total	fuel	steel	equipmentUnited Kingdom	5,439	166	265	1,799	(100%)	(3-1%)	(4-9%)	(33-1%)Western Germany	637	282	40	63	(100%)	(44-3%)	(6-3%)	(9-9%)France       .........	1,029	21	107	148	(100%)	(2-0%)	(10-4%)	(14-4%)Belgium-Luxembourg	1,609	33	411	167	(100%)	(2-1%)	(25-5%)	(10-4%)Netherlands         ......	869	23	23	118	(100%)	(2-6%)	(2-6%)	(13-6%)Italy............	1,067	2	29	209	(100%)	(0-2%)	(2-7%)	(19-6%)is large absolutely but fairly small as a proportion of the total. Both in western germany and in France steel exports formed a higher proportion of total exportsthan in the United Kingdom. In the figures for exports of machinery andequipment the most striking feature is the very high figures for the UnitedKingdom, where they form one-third of total exports. For other countries the absolute figures are much smaller but the proportions are still large, ranging from10 per cent, in Western Germany to 20 per cent, in Italy, with France, belgium and the Netherlands in intermediate positions.38875 L
ANNEX IT.Imperial Preferences on Iron, Steel and Coal1. Total exports of &quot; finished steel &quot; to Commonwealth and similar destina-tions amounted to 916,000 tons in 1949, divided as follows:  	Total	Total	Average		finished	estimated	value	Country	steel	value	per ton f.o.b.		(000 tons)	 000	 	South Africa       ......	136	5,829	42	-81East Africa         ......	58	2,516	43	09West Africa         ......	56	2,060	37	05Southern Rhodesia	41	1,402	34	-42Australia    ...      .......	170	8,298	48&apos;	93New Zealand       ...      ...    ,	107	4,569	42.	87Canada	67	2,827	42-	16India	53	2,554  .	48&apos;	54Pakistan     ...      ...      ...	24	1,018,	41	62Ceylon..........	18	695&apos;	39.	48Hong Kong	2d	83:8	4L	63Eire ...	29	1,289	43&apos;	88British West Indies	43	2,042	47&apos;	96Malaya      ......      ..;	35	1,523	43&apos;	31Burma       ...      ......	5	230	42-	59Other British countries   ...	54	2,377	43&apos;	73	916	40,000	43.-	75(Source: British Iron and Steel Federation figures, derived from Trade and Navigation Accounts^2. Imperial preferences on coal exist, but not to any significant extent, andthey may perhaps be ignored for the purpose of this enquiry. As for iron and steel,in the Colonies covered by the Congo Basin Conventions, in Nigeria, the gold coast, the Free Ports and Malaya there is no imperial preference on iron and steel.Elsewhere the level of imperial preferences varies greatly from product to product,and according to the area involved. Indeed the existence of alternative specificand ad valorem duties, and in some places a combination of the two, makes anygeneralisation about the overall value of preferences most hazardous, particularly where the existence of a local steel industry in the Commonwealth country con-cerned gives to the Government a strong incentive for excluding cheap steel fromany source.3. Any Table, even of typical preferences for individual Commonwealthmarkets, is apt to be misleading because the rates vary so much from one type ofsteel product to another. The following list, however, which includes a selectionfrom those Colonial territories where an Imperial Preference is in force, may be of use in indicating steel duties not uncharacteristic of the Commonwealth:  Australia......South AfricaNew ZealandCanada   ...Southern RhodesiaIndiaPakistan ...Northern RhodesiaTrinidad......Jamaica  ...MauritiusIrish Republic   ...BurmaM.f.n. rate A53% ad vol.20% ad val.12-1% ad val.10% ad val.excise duty plusRs. 435. per ton plusl/5th total duty1*5% ad val.20%30%Rs. 2s. per 100 kilog.15% ad val.Preferential rate A2.10.0;FreeFree5% ad val:Free1$ excise duty (Rs. 4s.per ton) or 10% adval., whichever is higher, plus l/5thtotal dutyFree10%20%Rs. Is. per 100 kilog.10% ad val.Estimated averageadvantage to UnitedKingdom per tonoverall A2.10.0 1. 6.0 8.12.0 2.10.0 4. 0.0 1.10.0* 2. 0.0 4.15.0 4. 0.015.0 2.13.0 3. 0.0* As estimated by B.I.S.F.
4. The following table summarises in the most appropriate way the estimatedvalue in 1949 of United Kingdom trade in iron and steel with the Commonwealth(including Burma and the Irish Republic, but excluding Anglo-Egyptian Sudan)and offers a tentative forecast of corresponding value for 1950:  Value of United Kingdom Exports of Finished Iron and Steel to commonwealth the United Kingdom output of finished steel in 1949 was about 12 million tons,of which If million tons (worth about  78 million) were exported. Clearly theloss of these preferences would put at risk a significant proportion of our output and of our exports of finished iron and steel.5. On the other hand, France in some case now enjoys preferences withinthe French Union, to which French steel exports in 1949 amounted to about 181 million. This figure, in view of the fact that, e.g., Morocco, Somaliland andFrench Equatorial Africa grant no preferences, is comparable with the figure of 40 million in the table in paragraph 4. Of this, about  15-J- million might be reckoned as subject to preference and as representing therefore the advantage, asregards steel exports to the French Union, which we in common with others mightgain, to offset our own loss in the Commonwealth, by the abolition of preferencesall round.(  million)Total of which subject to preference19494030195050-5540

TOP SECRETVIEWS OF THE ECONOMIC PLANNING BOARD1. The Economic Planning Board considered the report of theworking party on the proposed Franco-German coal and steelauthority on 19th June, 1950.2. They considered that there were three primary questions to be answered: -(i)     Was it desirable that there should be some organisation todeal with the prospective over-supply of iron and steel and coal inEurope ?(ii)     If so, was the organisation proposed in the working party&apos;sreport on the right lines?(iii)     How far was an abrogation of sovereignty involved?3. On these questions the Board reached the following conclusions:-(i)     There were economic advantages to be gained from some inter-national regulation, of iron and steel and coal in Europe, and in additionpolitical advantages would accrue from an agreement on this question,(ii)     The United Kingdom should aim in the first instance at anindependent body which had advisory but not mandatory powers.     TheBoard recognised that the original Schuman plan envisaged considerablemandatory powers for the controlling Authority and that it might not bepossible to secure an agreement if the United Kingdom refused to concedeany mandatory powers.     Some of the Board felt that if it were necessaryto secure an agreement, certain mandatory powers might be  concededrelating to investment and to international commercial agreements, as envisaged in the working party&apos;s report.The Board considered that in this new field there should be aperiod of experiment in which the Authority&apos;s tasks should be broadlydefined, more soecific tasks being allotted to it later in the light of experience.     For the time being it should suffice if the Authority were todeal with:-(a) investment programmes(b) quantities of output(c) the co-ordination of price policy - the securing ofagreed policies of price stabilisation.(iii)     The Board endorsed the views of the working party on tariffs,quantitative restrictions and subsidies set out in paragraphs 86 to 93 oftheir report and the views on strategic aspects in paragraph 101.     TheBoard were somewhat sceptical about the possibility of assigning to the

proposed Authority any effective functions about the regulation of wagesand conditions of labour in the iron and steel and coal industries, as envisaged in the original Schuman uroposals.Cn the constitution of the proposed Authority, the Board agreed with the wording party that its members should be independent of governments and industries, provided that adequate technical knowledgewas possessed by or available to them.    While not committing themselvesto the recommendation of a second-tier body, the Board considered thatat some stage there should be adequate machinery for consulting bothsides of industry.The Board considered that the United Kingdom could accept such abrogation of sovereignty as would be involved if the mandatorypowers mentioned above were conceded.2 0TH JUNE, 1950.

,4.45CONFIDENTIALCP.(50) 129The attached paper is relevant to Item 1 of the agenda for the meetingof the Cabinet on Monday, 19th June,at 11. 0 a. m.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,16TH JUNE, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
