<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 388-391</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  June1950The circulation of this paper has been-strictly limited. It is issued for -the&apos; personal use of: .: ?*.?*?n&amp;7.. Ar?^.-....................TOP SECRET . , Copy-: No..C.P.(50) 14027th June, 1950CABINETIMPLEMENTATION OF THE IRON AND STEEL ACT,  1949Memorandum by the Minister of SupplySince CP. (50) 112 was discussed in the Cabinet on 15th June, I have further considered the desirability of proceeding forthwith to select members of theIron and Steel Corporation with a view to their formal appointment on1st October, 1950, and the transfer of the securities to the Corporation on1st January, 1951.2. My consideration has strengthened the fears I expressed in my previouspaper that I would have the utmost difficulty in persuading persons of ability and experience either in the steel industry or outside to accept appointment to theCorporation. I would like to remind my colleagues that on behalf of the Govern-ment I stated in the House on 16th November last year:  &quot; Men who may well be best suited for this responsible task might under-standably be reluctant to commit themselves to accepting such a position, andthrow up their present jobs, as long as they think there is a possibility,however, remote, that the Corporation may not, after all, be established . .Trie success of the nationalised industry will depend to a considerable extent on the calibre of the men serving on the Corporation and it Would be follyto rush our selection of these people unnecessarily.&quot;3. The view expressed in this statement (which would, no doubt, be quotedagainst us if we proceeded to appoint the Corporation now) is still sound, andalthough I have not, of course, put the matter to the test, I am convinced thatsuitable candidates will be apprehensive that in the event of a Tory victory at anearly election, they would have to forfeit their present jobs with very uncertainprospects about their future employment.4. The problem of the Chairman is particularly acute, for while it is in my view desirable that the members from the steel industry appointed to the corporation should, if possible, be drawn from the ranks of young and able administrators, it isimportant that the Chairman should be a man of sufficient standing as to command general respect throughout industry.5. I have endeavoured to discover whether, under the Iron and Steel Act orunder other powers possessed by the Government, it would be possible to givereasonable security of tenure to the people who are appointed to the Corporation,so that they would at least know that if the Corporation were disbanded as a resultof a Tory victory at the polls, they would be entitled to worthwhile compensation.I am, however, advised by the Treasury Solicitor that any provision in a Letter of appointment which embodied a right to compensation in the event of the dissolution of the Corporation would be of doubtful practical value; moreover, such a pro-vision would be politically dangerous.38929
6. While I appreciate to the full the very real objections to postponing the implementation of the Iron and. Steel Act and while I would riot myself advocate itspostponement for long enough to require amending legislatiori, I riiust again; repeatthat to proceed at the moment would in all probability land us with a Corporationwhose members would hot possess the qualities required for the tasks which willconfront it. This will be particularly serious because the successful operation: of the nationalised iron and steel industry will in my opinion depend largely on theleaderhip shown by the Corporation in the early and formative: days of its existence.Jft C* 7.   I do not think it is possible, as has been suggested, to.make tentative.C...VS enquiries of a number of individuals about their willingness to serve on the Cor-poration and then to decide in the light of their response whether we are to postponeor not. The only hope of getting good people is by informing them and the industry that the Government has definitely decided to proceed forthwith with the imple-mentation of the Act.   Once such a statement had been made no retreat is possible.8. The only other action that remains open to us if we are to proceed, and if my fear of the un-co-operative attitude of men in the industry proves justified is toappoint the best outside people we can find. I believe that the salaries suggested would attract some individuals of ability who would be prepared to take a risk, but such a Corporation would be far from the ideal one. And the absence of any effective representation from the steel industry itself would lay us open to political criticism.9. I have considered the sort of statement that could be made on behalf ofthe Government should we, in the light of the facts set out above, decide to postponeimplementation for the time being. Jf we decide to adopt this course, the Schumanproposals afford us a reasonable justification. Paragraphs 98 and 99 of the working party report on these proposals (annexed to CP. (50) 128) state .... &quot;In the nationalisation acts for coal and steel, the appropriate Minister would need, inaddition to the approval of &quot;capital programmes and the powers of issuing general directions in the national interest, a power to issue directions in accordance withany decisions or recommendations of the Authority. The control of coal production is probably effectively in the hands of the National Coal Board and the Ministryof Fuel and Power, but in the case of iron and steel there will be several hundredfirms engaged in production and distribution which will be outside the control ofthe Iron and Steel Corporation of Great Britain. In the case of these firms,therefore, it would be necessary for the Minister to be given statutory powers onsuch matters as (a) the acquisition of information about transactions entered intoby them when, in the opinion of the Authority, further elucidation, was required,(b) the prevention of the carrying out of projects and agreements undertaken ormade without the sanction of the Authority; (a) will involve powers to enter andinspect and require production of books and furnishing of information, backedup with the usual criminal sanctions. The enforcement of (b) involves some difficulty; it would be possible to make the projects and agreements null and void,but this in itself might not effectively prevent their execution, particularlyabroad .... &quot;10. The sort of Government statement I therefore have in mind would be onthe following lines: -&quot; The Iron and Steel Act provides for the transfer of the securities on anyday between 1st January, 1951, and 1st January, 1952. The power to decide the actual date rests with the Minister of Supply.&quot; In considering what the best date of transfer should be, the Governmenthave in mind the possible effect of the Schuman proposals on the structure of the nationalised industry and the consequential need there may be, if thiscountry co-operates, as we very much hope it will, to amend the scope of theAct, the functions of the Corporation and its relationship with the Government.It would obviously be undesirable for the Corporation to be established on abasis which may need to be altered extensively a few months later. Moreover,it is clearly desirable that as far as possible, both the Chairman and membersof the Corporation should be selected, and should take the saddle with a know-ledge of the obligations we may be undertaking in connexion with the schuman plan. The Government have, therefore, decided that the balance of advantagelies in making the date of transfer in the Spring or at the latest in the summer of next year, by which time it is hoped that the implications for this country
of any international scheme emerging from the discussions can be more clearlyseen. The Minister of Supply will in due course make an order underSection 11 (1) of the Act fixing the operative date.r &quot; In making this announcement the Government reaffirm their conviction thatthe socialisation of this great basic industry is essential for the carrying out oftheir policy of full employment and industrial prosperity. They believe, moreover,that this country can more effectively contribute to European Co-operation inrespect of the iron and steel industry, if that industry, like coal, is publicly ownedand controlled.&quot;/&apos; G. R. S.Ministry of Supply, JVC. 2,27th June, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
