<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 396-397</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENT   J g printed for the Cabinet. June 1950CONFIDENTIAL Copy No.CP. (50) 14221th June, 1950CABINETMETHOD OF PREPARING ELECTORS LISTSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland propose certain changes in the method of preparing Electors lists which would cost about an extra 200,000 a year.Last autumn we effected an annual saving of  500,000 by making the revisionannual instead of twice yearly. This proposal would absorb  200,000 of this saving,partially offset by a possible saving of  10,000 on clerical assistance in the offices of registration Officers. Unless there are overriding reasons I am reluctant to incurthis extra expenditure. I am not clear from the memorandum of the HomeSecretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland that there are such reasons.The present system, which dates back to 1920, provides for the publication ofthe old Register with one list of additions and another list of deletions. The proposal of the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland is to issue the ElectorsList in the form of a revised draft Register incorporating both the additions anddeletions.As I understand the present position a would-be voter may fall into one oftwo categories:  (1) He may know, either by having voted at the last local or parliamentary election or by having received election literature^ that he is on theold Register.This is the majority category. Anyone in it is concerned only to see that his name remains on the Register. He can do this simply by reference to the list ofnames to be removed. This does not seemi to involve any more trouble than would reference to the complete draft Register which is now proposed.(2) He may not know whether he was on the old Register or not.This is the minority category. Anyone in it, in order to verify his position,must refer to the old Register to see if his name is there. If it is, he can then refer to the list of deletions to make sure that he is not being omitted. If his nameis not there, he can refer to the list of additions to see if it is being added. this category has thus to refer to two documents. I am not clear, however, that this second category is numerous, or that the present position causes real difficulty to anyone who is interested to secure his vote.Generally, in view of our need for economy in every possible direction, I cannotfeel that we should be justified in incurring the extra expenditure involved in preparing a single draft Register.R. S. treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,21th June, 1950.38932


</content>
</cab>
