<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 398-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P..(50) 143 COPY NO.28TH JUNE, 1950CABINETILLEGAL STRIKESMemorandum by the Attorney-general as my colleagues are aware, there have in the past fiveyears been a number of strikes, most of thern without Trade Unionsupport, which contravene the Conditions of Employment and national arbitration Order, 1940 (which we deliberately continued in operation)and participation in which is, therefore, a criminal offence which can be prosecuted under the Defence Regulations.   I have so far refrained from taking any criminal proceedings.I am, however, feeling increasing difficulty in allowing the law about illegal strikes to be flouted and I think that there may be strong criticism if I continue to treat the Order as a dead letter.I wish, therefore, to consult my colleagues in regard tothe question of instituting criminal proceedings should the necessaryevidence be available in connection with the strike of meat lorrydrivers which is at present taking place.    Before doing so, however,I should perhaps (in view of some misunderstanding which arose inregard to the matter at a recent meeting of the Emergencies Committee)restate the constitutional position of the Attorney-General in relation tohis colleagues in such matters.    Without going into the authorities, it is perhaps sufficient to repeat what I said in a letter to the colonial secretary on 11th January, 1949, in connection with the position of colonial Law Officers:-&quot;I think the true doctrine is that it is the duty of the attorney-General in deciding whether or not to authorise a particular prosecution to acquaint himself with all relevant facts including, for instance, the effect which a prosecution, successful or unsuccessful (as thecase might be) would have upon public morale and order  .and with any other considerations affecting public policy.In order so to inform himself he may, but he is not obligedto, consult with any of his colleagues or with the Cabinet but their assistance must be confined to informing him ofparticular considerations which may influence his owndecision and must not consist in recommending what &apos;thatdecision should be.    The responsibility for the eventualdecision lies solely upon the Attorney-General and he is notto be put under pressure by his colleagues in the matternor is he entitled to ask them directly for, nor ought they togive, their opinion as to what his decision ought to be. &quot;HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

In these circumstances, I would like to ask my colleagueswhether any circumstances are known to them which they think ought to take into account in deciding whether or not to prosecutein the case of the present strike in the event of the police havingadequate evidence on which such a prosecution might be founded.I should perhaps add that, while my responsibility is toenforce the law as it is, it is, of course, for the Government(particularly in matters which are the subject of regulations) todecide what the law should be.    It may be for consideration whetherthe Conditions of Employment and National Arbitration order should be continued in force after the end of this year, when itwould otherwise expire.    I do not know to what extent its provisions for compulsory arbitration have been found of value but I certainlydo not delude myself into thinking that the prosecution of a handfulof individuals in the course of a strike is likely to have anyparticularly useful effect.   I have never favoured the use of the police-court for the purpose of breaking strikes, unless indeed something in thenature of a seditious conspiracy is involved.   So long, however, as theGovernment see fit to maintain the existing law, I cannot continuouslyshut my eyes to its existence.H. S.Law Courts, W. C. 2. ,28TH JUNE, 1950.


</content>
</cab>
