<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/40/0 images: 402-411</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS   THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS   BRITANNIC   MAJESTY*S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1950SECRET Copy no cp. (50) 14421th June, 1950CABINETFLOUR EXTRACTION RATEMemorandum by the Minister of FoodAttached as an annex to this memorandum is a paper prepared by my Depart-ment on the flour extraction rate.The detailed analysis of the position set out in this paper in my opinion clearlyshows the balance of advantage to fall on the side of reducing the extraction rate to80 per cent, in one move. The reasons which have led me to this conclusion canbe summarised as follows:  (1) The original purpose of raising the extraction rate was to save shipping space and later to save wheat at a time of world scarcity. But there isnow no need to save shipping space and wheat is no longer scarce.(2) We are already committed to buy more of our wheat imports from dollar countries; any extra wheat we might need to provide for the reductionin the extraction rate could be drawn from sterling sources.(3) The improvement in household flour, bread and cakes which would result would obviously be most welcome to the public.(4) The manufacturing trades would also welcome it.(5) Production efficiency would be increased.(6) There are no nutritional objections.(7) Feeding-stuffs supplies would be increased in quantity and quality at a timewhen future supplies in sufficient volume are by no means assured.(8) The consequential cost can be met out of savings on the budget estimateof cash requirements for cereals and cereal feeding-stuffs in the financialyear 1950-51.(9) From a balance of payments point of view the net result would be unlikely to exceed an additional (non-dollar) cost of about  2 millions in a full year.I recommend that my Department be authorised to make the necessary administrative arrangements, in consultation with the milling and baking industries,to enable the lower extraction flour to be put on sale as soon as practicable. Thisshould be possible as from about the end of July or early August, and I would propose to announce the actual date as soon as the necessary consultations havetaken place with the industries concerned.M. W.32Ministry of Food, S.W. 1,21th June, 1950.
annex proposed REDUCTION  IN   UNITED  KINGDOM  FLOUREXTRACTION RATE,  1950Review of United Kingdom Flour Extraction Rates since 19391. Before the last war there was no control of the flour extraction rate, butwheat flour was, generally speaking, milled from wheat at an extraction rate of around 70 per cent. Soon after the outbreak of war the extraction rate was raised to 73 per cent., and again later to 75 per cent, in order to save shipping space.With the further deterioration in the shipping position the rate was again raised in March 1942 from 75 per cent, to 85 per cent. From about the same date it became necessary to incorporate home-grown barley in the grist with the same objectof minimising imports. The extraction rate remained at 85 per cent, (with the useof adulterants) until the autumn of 1944, when the Lord Presidents committee decided to reduce the rate to 80 per cent, in two steps, first to 824 per cent, andat the beginning of 1945 to 80 per cent. With the deterioration in the UnitedKingdom stock position due to the world wheat shortage and the increasing demands of liberated Europe and Occupied Germany, it was necessary to raise the extraction rate three times between February and May 1946 successively to 82^ percent, 85 per cent, and 90 per cent. In September 1946, however, the rate revertedto 85 per cent., where it has remained ever since.The Demand for a Lower Flour Extraction Rate2. There is a widespread demand for a reduction in the present extraction rate of 85 per cent. The present rate was generally accepted without complaintduring the war owing to the desperate need to release as much shipping space aspossible for the movement of war materials, but the demand for a reduction hasbeen more or less continuous ever since the end of the war, and there has been afresh series of questions on the subject in Parliament since the General Election aswell as a debate in the House of Lords on 20th and 25th April. Arguments for areduction in the present rate come, on the one hand, from milling and flour-using industries and the consuming public, all of whom want a whiter loaf, and, on theother hand, from the farming interests, who want a larger supply and better quality of wheat offals for animal feed.3. Apart from the general consumer preference for a whiter loaf, technical consideration are advanced by the milling, baking, biscuit-making and flour con-fectionery industries which by themselves undoubtedly tell in favour of anextraction rate lower than 85 per cent. The production of an acceptable flour of85 per cent, extraction involves the use of more fuel per unit of output, puts a bigger strain on milling plant and machinery, and increases costs of production;the flour produced has inferior keeping qualities, and the costs of production ofsome flour products-notably biscuits are increased, output and productivity perman hour are reduced, and the keeping quality of the final product is less satis-factory. It will become increasingly difficult to resist the pressure of the trade for a reduction in the present rate, but the strength of the demand for a reversion to the pre-war extraction rate for such products as biscuits would be greatlyweakened if the extraction rate of flour for all purposes were to be reduced.4. The desire of farmers for more and better wheat offals is also soundlybased. Wheat offals have a higher protein content than coarse grains and are a particularly valuable ingredient in compound feeds. Before the war the supplyof home produced wheat offals alone averaged some 1,650,000 tons a year, but atthe present extraction rate the supply, despite the substantial increase in flourconsumption, is only some 750,000 tons a year; moreover, offals of the present typeresulting from the milling of 85 per cent, of the wheat into flour are markedlyinferior in nutritional properties, having a higher fibre and lower protein andcarbo-hydrate content.5. Most of the countries of north-west Europe whose tastes and food con-sumption habits most closely resemble those of the United Kingdom have withinthe last year or so reduced their wheat milling rates. For example, in France,Belgium, the Netherlands, Denmark, Sweden and Switzerland the pre-war wheat flour extraction rates ranged from 70 per cent, to 75 per cent.; in all these countriesit was raised to the neighbourhood of 90 per cent, (and sometimes more) duringthe war and then reduced somewhat, but still kept at a higher level than the public
taste desired, while world supplies were short in the years 1945-48. When bread rationing in these countries was ended at varying dates between April 1948(Switzerland) and November 1949 (the Netherlands) the wheat flour extractionrates ranged from 80 per cent, to 86 per cent., but since then all of them have reduced their rates to 80 per cent, or lower. The fact that the bread, cakes,biscuits, &amp;c, in these countries, which are being visited by an unprecedented numberof British tourists, are made from a lower extraction flour than our own, is likelyto intensify the public demand for a whiter loaf in the United Kingdom.Conversely, the home catering industry has represented that a whiter flour would assist them in meeting the tastes of foreign visitors.6. Neither the necessity to conserve shipping space, which was the principalreason for the raising of the extraction rate early in the war, nor the acute worldshortage of wheat supplies which necessitated the raising of the extraction rate inthe United Kingdom for a time to 90 per cent, in 1946, are any longer valid argu-ments for retaining a higher extraction rate than would be desirable on other grounds; there is plenty of freight available and ample supplies of wheat in theworld. But it does not necessarily follow that the extraction rate should, therefore,revert to pre-war level. The widespread desire for a whiter flour and the desire ofthe agricultural industry for increased supplies and better quality of milling offalsmust be considered against a number of other factors which are dealt with in thefollowing paragraphs.Nutritional Considerations7. The nutritional considerations involved in a reduction of the flour extraction-tion rate are dealt with in the Appendix to this paper. They can be summarisedas follows:  (a) Some reduction could safely be made in the present extraction rate with-out any danger to the nutritional status of the population.(b) To reduce the extraction rate to the pre-war level would be undesirablein the present state of our knowledge of the nutritional problems involved.(c) It would be prudent to limit any reduction that may be thought desirableto a minimum of 80 per cent, for the present.The Interim Report of the Conference on the Post-War Loaf (Cmd. 6701 of 1945)recommended that, pending further research, 80 per cent, extraction flour the rate to which we had reverted early in 1945 should continue to be used in the making of bread. The Standing Committee on Medical and Nutritional Problems, ofwhich the Chief Medical Officer of the Ministry of Health is Chairman, recom-mended on 24th April, 1950, that the extraction rate should not be reduced belowa level at which the flour, as distributed by the millers, would contain less thanthe minimum quantities of token nutrients recommended in 1945 by the Conferenceon the Post-War Loaf.Supplies and Prices8. For every 1 per cent, by which the flour extraction rate is reduced it isnecessary to import about 65,000 tons more wheat. But feeding-stuffs supplies areautomatically increased by a similar quantity of wheat offals, thereby reducing ourimported coarse grain requirements by an equivalent amount. Any change in therelative world supply position of wheat and coarse grains (in so far as we havethe resources to acquire them), therefore, has a bearing upon the determination of the optimum extraction rate. At present there are ample supplies of wheat inthe world to enable us to reduce the extraction rate to 80 per cent.; equally if itwere thought desirable to raise the extraction rate, there is an abundant supplyof feedgrain available for export to make up the consequent loss of offals, but wheat and coarse grains which can be bought without the expenditure of dollars are bothin short supply. The two essential questions to be asked from the balance of pay-ments point of view are, therefore:  (a) whether our requirements of cereal feeding-stuffs (on which we have spentno dollars in recent years) can with reasonable certainty be met at thepresent flour extraction rate without recourse to dollar supplies; and(b) whether a reduction in the extraction rate would be likely to increase our dollar expenditure on wheat.9. As regards (a), an appraisal of the supply position for cereal feeds up toMay 1951 involves a large element of speculation; it is impossible to predict either
what effect the increase in feeding-stuffs prices will have on farmers&apos; purchases of coarse grains, or what volume of imported supplies will become available to theMinistry from crops, most of which are not yet harvested and some not evenplanted. It is possible perhaps even probable that we shall be able to obtainall the barley we need, but it seems almost certain that we shall not be able toobtain either all the maize or all the wheat offals we require. The supply of wheatoffals has recently been reduced owing to the reduction in the off take of flour andslower rate of shipment from the Argentine. The shortage of maize is due princi-pally to the failure of this year&apos;s Argentine crop. The only substantial alternative sources of non-dollar maize are Russia and the Danube countries, and it is very unlikely that they can supply our full needs. In these circumstances an increasein the supply and quality of wheat offals by a reduction in the flour extraction rate would provide a valuable alternative feed and compensate to some extent for theinadequate supply of maize,10. As regards (b) above, it has long been axiomatic that our marginal require-ments of wheat come from dollar sources. But immediately the United Kingdomacceded to the International Wheat Agreement, under which she incurred a con-tingent liability to buy dollar wheat, this position no longer necessarily held good.It will be valid only for so long as the International Wheat agreement exporting countries refrain from requiring importing countries to take their &quot; guaranteedpurchases &quot; at the minimum price. But immediately they do the United kingdom will be obliged to take the guaranteed quantity whether she wants it or not and non-dollar sources will in that event become the marginal suppliers. In thesecircumstances, any additional wheat which might be needed to provide for thereduction in the extraction rate could be drawn from sterling sources.11. In addition to the supply prospects, the relative prices of wheat and coarse grains must be taken into account. It is, of course, impossible to predict the futuretrend of world prices, but it is safe to say that the price of non-dollar maize hasrecently moved up in relation to the prices of other grains owing to the Argentinecrop failure, and is likely to remain relatively high for some time to come. Indeed,if as now seems likely, we shall be able to buy at least some of our wheat in 1950-51at well below the maximum price under the International Wheat Agreement, someof our wheat imports may actually cost us less than maize. The minimum f.o.b.prices of wheat from the main exporting countries under the International wheat agreement in 1950-51 range from  19 165. per ton for Australian wheat shipped from the southern and eastern ports (the bulk of the crop) to  21 3s. M. forManitobas and Hard Winters shipped from the Atlantic ports. It is too early yet to say whether we shall be able to buy wheat so cheaply as this, but it may wellbe that wheat will be cheaper than maize during the period under review. on price grounds, therefore, as well as on supply grounds, the circumstances favour a reduction in the extraction rate.The Effect of a Reduction in the Extraction Rate on Flour Consumption12. The question is likely to be asked &quot; Will a reduction in the extraction rate increase the consumption in bread and flour and so lead to an increase inour wheat import requirements? &quot; It is impossible to give a definite answer to thisquestion. The improved palatability of the loaf may tend to increase bread con-sumption but as against this the better keeping quality of the loaf and of thelower extraction flour may well result in less household waste. On the whole,it might be prudent to expect a modest initial increase in bread consumption,followed by a decline as the novelty of the whiter loaf wore off. It is also conceiv-able that the larger supply and better quality of wheat offals would bring aboutsome reduction in the illicit usage of flour for livestock feeding. On balance, itis not thought likely that there would be an increase in weekly flour off take to thelevel on which we are at present basing our forward estimates 97,000 tons perweek.  Indeed there might well be some reduction.What is the Optimum Extraction Rate in Present Circumstances!13. If it is accepted (a) that the time is ripe for some reduction in the flourextraction rate and (b) that on nutritional grounds it should not be reduced below80 per cent, it remains to consider what precise rate is desirable and whether thereduction should be made in two stages (as it was when the rate was reduced from85 per cent, to 82^ per cent, at the end of 1944 and from 82^ per cent, to 80 percent, at the beginning of 1945) or whether the change should be made in one step.The balance of advantage would seem to lie in the direction of one change from
85 per cent, to 80 per cent. The main reasons for preferring one change to two are as follows:  (a) considerable expense is entailed in the mills each time an alteration inthe extraction rate is made;(b) flour quality in general is upset for at least a fortnight before the millssettle down;(c) when it is known that the extraction rate is to be reduced (and it isnecessary to give the millers and bakers at least a month and preferablysix weeks&apos; notice) flour stocks will fall to a very low level over a periodof six weeks to two months. This period would be prolonged if there seemed to :the trade to be a possibility of a further reduction in the nearfuture. Two successive reductions in the rate should consequently be avoided if possible;(d) flour mills will at first be running short time while old stocks, both in the. millers&apos; and bakers&apos; hands, are cleared, and will then run overtime whilestocks are being made up to their normal level. Additional labour costs will thereby be incurred with a corresponding increase in the flour subsidyFinancial Considerations.14; It is estimated that if all other factors were to remain constant theadditional cost which would fall upon the Ministry were the extraction rate to bereduced to 80 per cent, would be at the rate of some  6 millions per annum, ofwinch about half a million pounds would fall on the bread subsidy and theremainder on the flour subsidy. This additional cost would be reduced somewhatif purchases of wheat and flour after August 1950 were made at prices below themaximum under the International Wheat Agreement. Assuming the reductionin the extraction rate came into force on 1st August, 1950, the additional costduring 1950-51 would not be greater than  4 millions. But the additional wheatoffal produced would save an equivalent quantity of imported coarse grain, prob-ably barley, and as there is a loss on imported barley at present that loss mightbe reduced by half a million pounds. The net effect for 1950-51 is thereforeestimated to be an increase of about  3^- millions in both the trading loss and cashrequirements as set out in the Ministry&apos;s revised estimate for May 1950 underthe heading &quot; Cereals including Cereal Feeding Stuffs.&quot; The revised estimate of cash requirements including this increase would still, however, be  4 millions lessthan the original estimate of  90 millions allowed for in the Ministry of Food&apos;estimate under this heading. Total food subsidies for 1950-51 were estimated at 410 millions in May, and the implication is that the change would raise subsidiesabove the ceiling fixed by the Chancellor. It is, however, still early in the financialyear, and a movement of  3^ millions above the ceiling at this stage cannot beregarded as a serious threat to the sanctity of the subsidy ceiling.15. From the balance of payments point of view the cost of the change maybe very tentatively estimated at about  2 millions in a full year, since the f.o.b. costof the&apos; additional wheat we should require (335,000 tons) might be about  6 perton more than the f.o.b. cost of the coarse grains which we should otherwise bebuying; but it must be emphasised that the actual cost would depend on therelative prices of wheat and coarse grains, which cannot be foreseen. The cost would, in any event, be a non-dollar item.Ministry of Food, S. W. 1,June, 1950.APPENDIXNUTRITIONAL IMPLICATIONS OF A LOWERING OF the extraction RATE OF WHEATExisting Commitment Regarding the Extraction Rate1. The extent to which the extraction rate could be lowered without detriment to health was considered by the Conference on the Post War Loaf in 1945 (Cmd.6701). This Conference comprised representatives of the Ministries of Food,Health and Agriculture and of the milling and baking industries. The Conferencerecommended that the post-war loaf should contain not less than certain minimum
quantities of three &quot; token &quot; nutrients, and interpreted the word &quot; minimum &quot; as that level &quot; below which it may be inferred from experience that good health is not likelyto be maintained.&quot; In Table 1 the agreed minimum quantities are shown side by side with typical figures for present-day flours of 85 per cent., 82  per cent, and80 per cent, extraction. It will be noted that a reduction to 82^ per cent, wouldsupply a small margin over these quantities; a reduction to 80 per cent, would justmeet the Committee&apos;s recommendation.Effect of Lowering the Extraction Rate on Nutrient Intakes2. The overall picture of food supplies has, however, altered since theConference reported, and some revisions have been made in our estimates of dietaryrequirements. A more realistic appraisal of the nutritional effects of lowering the extraction rate of wheat will therefore be obtained by examining the actual levels of nutrient intake.3. Average figures for the whole population can most readily be obtainedfrom statistics of the total supplies &quot; moving into civilian consumption.&quot; Suchstatistics are available in the recently issued White Paper (Cmd. 7842). In Table 2the relevant figures have been abstracted and are compared with (a) estimatedfigures for 1949-50 based on the three levels of extraction (the total intake of flourbeing kept constant) and (b) estimated requirements based on the reports of theNational Research Council (United States) and of the British Medical Association..In addition to the &quot; token &quot; nutrients, figures are given for total protein and forriboflavin. To demonstrate the relationship between the extraction rate and thenutrient content of the diet the table also indicates the dates on which the extractionrates have been changed.4. It will be seen from Table 2 that, for the five nutrients examined, theestimated intakes at all three levels of extraction exceed both the N.R.C. and theB.M.A. requirements.5. The figures in Table 2 refer, however, to national averages. The question arises as to whether the intakes of selected groups within the population may differ from these national averages. The only data at present available for guidance on thispoint are those obtained in the National Food Survey for urban working-classfamilies. Since there are seasonal trends in food intake (especially of milk), figuresfor the five nutrients have been calculated for two typical months, June and september 1949, assuming the same three extraction rates. These figures are givenin Table 3.6. These figures show that in June 1949 the intakes of all five nutrients were satisfactory even if the 80 per cent, extraction rate was in operation. In September1949 they were adequate for all three &quot;token&quot; nutrients and for total protein.The riboflavin intake was, however, below the N.R.C. requirement, at all extractionrates. This low level of ribofiavin in September was associated with the seasonallylow level of milk consumption a low level which is in future likely to be limitedto only a few weeks in the period of autumn milk shortage.7. In general, therefore, it appears that from the nutritional aspect the extraction rate can be reduced from the existing figure of 85 per cent, either to82^ per cent, or to 80 per cent, without lowering the nutritive value of the nationaldiet below recognised requirements, provided always that the present levels of totalfood consumption can be maintained.TABLE 1Minimum Recommended Levels of &quot; Token &quot; Nutrients and Actual Levels atVarying Extraction Rates(mg. per 100 g.)&quot; Token &quot; Nutrient	Minimum quantities recommended by Conference	Quantities provided by the following extraction rates				85%	82i%	80%Iron   ............ Vitamin Bl   ... Nicotinic acid	1-65 0-24 1-60	2-1 0-30 1-70	1-95 0-27 1-70	1-63 0-24 1-65
TABLE 2Total Supplies of Nutrients Moving into Civilian Consumption compared with Requirements per Head per Day(Pre-war to 1949-50)Nutrient													1949-50		Requirements		Pre-war	1940	1941	1942	1943	1944	1945	1946	1947	1948	1949																				N.R.C.	B.M.A.												85%	82* %	80%	1945	1950Total protein (g.) ...	79-9	78-7	82-4	86-6	85-3	87-1	89-3	90-3	90-7	84-4	87-5	88-4		*	65	71Iron (mg.)......	12-4	12-7	12-9	15-5	16-0	16-2	14-6	17-1	16-6	15-7	15-5	15-5	15-2	14-4	11-8	11-8Vitamin (mg.)	1-2	1-3	1-5	1-7	1-9	2-0	1-8	1-9	1-8	1-8	1-8	1-8	1-8	1-7	1-27	1-02Riboflavin (mg.)   ...	1-6	1-6	1-6	2-0	2-0	2-1	1-8	2-0	2-0	1-9	2-0	2-0	2-0	1-9	1-74	1-53Nicotinic acid (mg.)	13-4	13-6	13-0	14-0	14-6	16-0	14-8	17-0	14-9	14-2	14-4	14-9	14-9	14-6	12-7	10-2Extraction rate	70%	Oct.	May	March	1942-Sept.	1944:	Jan.	*	1947,	1948 and	1949							1939-	1941-		85%		1945-			85%								April	March	Oct	-Dec. 1944:		Feb.											1941:	1942:		82i%		1946:											73%	75%				80%									* Changes during 1946: 26th February-9th March ......... -   82\%10th March-llth May      ......... 85%12th-May-21st September......... 90%22nd September onwards   ...     ...... 85%
TABLE 3Intake of Nutrients by Urban Working Class Families calculated for varyingExtraction Levels, compared with Requirements	June 1949			September 1949			Requirements		85%	82* %	80%	8^%	82F/o	80%	N.R.C.	B.M.A.Total protein (g.) Iron (mg.)    ...... Vitamin B\ (mg.) Riboflavin (mg.) Nicotinic acid (mg.) ...	74 13-6 1-52 1-70 12-3	13-3 1-46 1-62 12-3	12-6 1-40 1-59 12-1	71 12-9 1-47 1-54 12-6	12-6 1-41 1-46 12-6	11-8 1-35 1-43 12-4	61 11-0 1-16 1-59 11-6	66 11-0 0-96 1-43 9-6



</content>
</cab>
