<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/239/0 images: 50-53</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Memorandum /by the 5ccretary,,01 St-ate for India.         I circulate for the information of my colleaguesa telegram from the Government of India giving an appreciation of the probable reception of the White paper in India.                           S.H.7th March 1933.Copy NoDOCUMENTJS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT&apos;G A B. I N I T.C R S TProbable Reception of the White Paper           in India.
Telegram from Government of India dated 6th March 1933-         The following is our appreciation of the probableIndian reaction to the TThite Paper.  An attempt to forecaston such a subject would, at any time, be difficult, andat the moment the political situation is curiously confusedowing largely to an increase in divergences of opinion onthe main lines of policy manifested in Congress and advanced by the nationalist circle.  This appreciation must thereforebe tentative and in general terms only.  It can however be predicted with certainty that during the first fortnight or so after the publication of the documents the volume ofdenunciation will be great, and may seem almost to submergehelpful and constructive comments.  There will be some danger that the stream of abuse may drive certain individuals intotaking up a more hostile position than they would really wish.&quot;Reasons for anticipating highly unfavourable initial reactionare two.  One is the natural tendency of most vocal sections ofIndian political opinion to denounce the contents of publicationfor the same a priori reasons as evoked vehement and indiscrimin-ate condemnation of the Communal Award and the Franchise Report.The other is that the form in which the document has inevitablyhad to be cast exposes it in an exceptional degree to the riskof misrepresentation.  3y endeavouring to ensure that theofficial summary bringing cut the liberality and magnitude ofthe proposed change shall appear first in the majoritynewspapers, we hope to mitigate this danger to some extent.It is probable also that the White Paper will be discussed inthe Central, and Local Legislatures and this will give us andthe Local Governments an opportunity of explaining theproposals and of refuting misrepresentations.  But it seems certain that, as the general effect  of the document on first                                                  reading
reading is to emphasise the limitations rather than extent ofself-government to &quot;be conferred, the preliminary verdict on itin this country must be more adverse than even advancedNationalists v?ill consider justified after closer study.  Weanticipate in particular during the first few days sweepingNationalist condemnation of long list of non-votable subjects and of proposals regarding the viceroy&apos;s and the Governors&apos;powers, Finance end Defence.  Provided, however, that the damage done by this wave of denunciation at the outset is not really extensive, prospects of subsequent cautious consilidation of opinion in favour of the majority of the proposals in the document appear reasonably good. The fact that it has beenpossible, within two and a half months of the conclusion ofthe Conference, to produce so detailed and fer-reaching a bodyof proposals will furnish further proof that the Cabinetgenuinely desires to push ahead quickly with Indian reformsand should impress the bulk of the politically-minded classeshere with the reality and nearness of the impending changes.Further cause for encouragement can be found in a tendency towards more realistic or less sentimental approach to thepolitical problems which has been discernible during the lastyear among the Indian educated classes. To estimate the reactions of individual groups and parties to the document must be largelymatter of guessv/ork and is particularly difficult in case ofthe Hindu Liberals and Congress,  attitude of former has beer-far from helpful since the return of the delegates from theConference.    It would seem that they are seeking commonplatform with right wing of Congress. As however latter shows signs of anxiety not to be loft on one side by constitution,this tendency may perhaps be expected,while stifeeningcriticism of constitutional proposals, to stop short of anything like non-cooperation.    Congress itself is                                                    increasingly
increasingly divided internally about the future as is shown by number of recent incidents, among them being publicd s agreement between Malaviya and Gandhi about untouchability,the brisk controversy regarding Council entry under the newconstitution, defection from the party of few individuals suchas Jamnadas Dwarka Das, and the abandonment by others, suchas Rajagopalachariar, of all active concern with civildisobedience. Extremists doubtless hope that the White Papermay provide them with a fresh opportunity for whipping upagitation against the Government, but, on the whole, it looksas if increasing numbers will be in favour of abandoning thepresent negative policy.  As regards the other groups andparties we do not anticipate many difficulties or surprises,though possibility of minor complications arising at later stageover question of personnel chosen for Joint Select Committeeshould not be overlooked.  Legislative Assembly groups andleaders may generally be expected to adopt fairly reasonable attitude, as also Justice party in Madras and Constitutionalistsand Landlords in United Provinces and Bihar.  Muslims will doubtless generally be well disposed, though the possibilityof some Muslim majority provinces, particularly the Punjab,considering the proposals not sufficiently advanced cannot be altogether discounted.  Undoubtedly the first few weeks afterpublication of the White Paper will be critical period, but after taking all factors into account we consider the omensat present more favourable than otherwise.

</content>
</cab>
