<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/239/0 images: 252-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed Jor the Cabinet.  March 1933.SECRET.                                               Copy No.      3DCP. 83 (33).CABINET.the  MILK. INDUSTRY&quot;.Report of Milk  Re-organisation Commission.      MEMORANDUM  BY  THE  MINISTER OF  AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES..     1.   IN a statement of the Governments agricultural policy in the House of Commons on the 11th February, 1932, my predecessor said :          &quot; In regard to milk and milk products, the Government aim particularly     at the improvement of marketing and have decided to set up a reorganisation     commission under the Agricultural Marketing Act, 1931. with a view to the     formulation of schemes.&quot; The Commission was constituted on the 18th April. 1932, under the Chairmanship of Sir Edward Grigg.     2.   After an exhaustive review of the whole problem,  the Commission has now reported, and the following are among its main findings :       (i) The disparity between prices for milk for liquid consumption (about 1^. a           gallon) and for manufacture  (5c?. a gallon) has reached a point at           which the stability cf the whole industry is threatened.     (ii) The present machinery for the  negotiation of milk  prices, namely,  a           voluntary joint committee  of  producers, distributors  and mahufac-           turei&quot;8, having no power to enforce its decisions, is insufficient to meet           the needs of the industry.     3.   The Commission recommends a milk marketing scheme under the A&amp;i- cultural Marketing Act on the lines of that set out in Appendix A to its report. The scheme provides that a Central Producers&apos;  Board  shall  be a  party to all contracts for the sale of milk and shall accept responsibility  for surplus milk for which no buyers can be found. The scheme further proposes that the country shall be divided into 11 regions, in each of which there shall operate a milk poolreturn-&apos; being a uniform price to all milk producers in the region.  The regional pooling&apos; plan  is to be modified to some extent by the payment of compensation to regions in which a large proportion of milk is consigned&quot; to manufacture. This compensji-. tion is to be provided out of the proceeds of a levy to be paid by producers on all sales  of milk  for liquid  consumption.   Although no figure  has been published.. the Commission considered that a levy of the order of Id. a gallon would suffice-    A  milk  marketing  scheme on  the  lines  of that recommended  by.v-.tlie Commission has been submitted to me by the National Farmers&apos; Union withi%, he last few days.   In accordance with the procedure laid down by the Marketing Act of  1931 notice of submission has been published in the  Gazette and, in1, due course, objections to the scheme will be heard at a Public Inquiry.  Subsequently, the scheme  will be submitted  for an  affirmative  resolution of each House of Parliament, will, if  so sanctioned, come provisionally into  force, and finally  a poll of milk producers will be taken, to confirm or reject the scheme.
     4.  The Commission has made a number of other recommendations,  which.may conveniently be placed into two groups :                                      (A)     Recommendations to which effect can be given by administrative  action orby negotiations between the interests concerned :       (i) The encouragement of clean milk production.     (ii) The revision of the statutory grades of milk.     (iii) The routine clinical inspection of all dairy cattle.     (iv) A departure from the present basis of determining manufacturing milk           prices.                                     (B)     Recommendations, involving legislation of a far-reaching character, for theestablishment of two bodies additional to the Producers&apos; Board, namely :       (i) A statutory board representative of distributors and manufacturers.           designed primarily as a counterpart to the Producers&apos; Board.     (ii) A statutory joint council comprising the Producers&apos; Board, the Dairy -           men&apos;s Board and three impartial appointed members; the main  power           of this body would be  to determine contract terms and prices.It is to these recommendations that special importance attaches.     5.  After careful review of all the circumstances, I do not propose to ask for authority to promote legislation to give effect to the recommendations set  out inparagraph 4  (B),  because  the objects of  the  Commission in this respect can, ifsubsequently  found desirable, be  attained  very  largely by arrangements  under clause 11 of the Agricultural Marketing Bill, which would enable the Producers&apos;Board to negotiate with distributors and manufacturers and to refer to  impartialpersons for consultation  and. if desired, for arbitral decision.     6.   The Commission has put  forward other proposals relating to imports of milk products, but these must be dependent upon negotiations with the Dominionsand foreign countries. Meanwhile, the dairy produce market is under the shadowof  rapidly accumulating  stocks  both here  and overseas, particularly in theDominions.   This  situation is under close consideration  by the dominions secretary, the President of the  Board of Trade, and myself,  and discussions onbutter imports have been in progress  for the last six weeks, on the initiative ofNew Zealand. These discussions, of course, interlock closely with the negotiationswith foreign countries, e.g., Denmark, for trade agreements, and this aspect of thesituation is being fully borne in mind.  It may be desirable to  consider temporaryarrangements to steady  the  markets in dairy products, but any such  proposals will, of course, be brought before the Cabinet at a later date.     7.   Scotland. Two schemes applicable in parts of Scotland are at presentbefore  the  Secretary of State for  Scotland.   The relationship between these schemes and the English scheme will require consideration by the Secretary ofState and myself.  This is in hand.                               CONCLUSION.     So far as the milk marketing  scheme under the 1931 Agricultural MarketingAct recommended by the Commission is concerned, this is following the statutoryprocedure.   As regards the establishment of a  dairy men &apos;s  board and a joint council, I ask for authority to announce that the Government is not prepared asat  present  advised  to introduce further new legislation to  set up a  statutorydistributors&apos; organisation  as recommended by the Milk Commission.   In effect,however, the intentions of the Commission as to consultation between distributors,manufacturers and producers before fixing milk prices, with or without arbitrationhy persons nominated by the Government, can, if desired, largely be secured underlegislation already before Parliament.                                                   (Initialled)    W. E. E.&quot;.  . in Ministry of Agriculture and, Fisheries,            March 25, 1933.

</content>
</cab>
