<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/62/24 images: 234-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJEST&apos;Y&apos;S GOVBKKMJSKTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1945.i he circulation of this papju; has been strictly limited. It is issued for the personal use of top SECRET&apos;W.P. (45) 119.19th February, 1945.Copy No.WAR CABINET.,SUMMARY OF NAVAL AIR OPERATIONS 1st NOVEMBER, 1944, to 1st FEBRUARY, 1945.Memorandum by the First Lord oe the Admiralty.Section I. Aircraft Carriers Disposition and Movements.1. Fleet Carriers.H.M.S.IndefatigableH.M.S. Implacable. After H.M.S. Indefatigable had sailed to join the pacific Fleet on the 20th November, the only Fleet carrierin Home waters was H.M.S. Implacable, and this shiphas taken part in two operations off the Norwegian coast.In the first of these, on the 27th November, Barracudas,Fireflies and sea fires destroyed a southbound convoy inAlst Fjord. The s.s. Rigel (3,800 G.R.T.), carryingGerman troops, was sunk, and three ships, the Korsnes(1,700 G.R.T.), another of 900 tons, and an armed escort vessel, were all set ablaze and driven ashore. Fightersalso attacked the s.s. Spree (2,900 G.R.T.) north-east ofAlsten and a 500-ton coaster and an L.C.T. in Mosjoen.All three ships were left on fire. A 5,000-ton merchant ship at Gravik was attacked several times with cannon,and three vessels, two armed trawlers and a 900-tonauxiliary, proceeding to her assistance were straffed intheir turn and set on fire. The 5,000-ton ship was laterseen to be listing and burning fiercely amidships. none of our aircraft was lost. This operation was hampered by a severe Arctic gale, which forced the escort carriers,H.M.S. Premier and H.M.S. Pursuer, to return before taking part and also caused damage to H.M.S.Implacable on the passage home to Scapa.With the escort carriers H.M.S. Trumpeter and h.M.S. Premier in company, H.M.S. Implacable was again off the Norwegian coast early in December. On the7th, Avengers from H.M.S.. Premier, escorted byWildcats from H.M.S. Trumpeter, successfully laid tenmines in Salhuss Trommen. One Wildcat was lost whenit force-landed in the water. The following day a forceof 12 Fireflies and 9 Wildcats set on fire two merchant ships, both of 800 tons, and a self-propelled barge nearLostvaag, while another barge was damaged by cannonstrikes. . -[29252]
H.M.S. Indomitable These carriers came under the orders of Rear-Admiral,H.M.S. Illustrious. Aircraft Carriers, British Pacific Fleet, on the 10thH.M.S. Victorious December, when the commands of East Indies and h.M.S. British Pacific Fleets were created.  At the moment, noIndefatigable   Fleet carriers are attached to the East Indies Fleet.  -H.M.S. FormidableH.M.S. Indomitable A strike of 28 Avengers, 16 Hellcats and 16 CorsairsH.M.S. Illustrious  took off at dawn on the 20th December to attack the oil refinery at Pangnalan Brandan. Finding this area com-pletely obscured by cloud, the strike attacked the harbour, railway yards and oil installations at BelawanDeli. Low cloud made observation difficult, but severaloil fires were seen and one Sally was shot down over the target area. Later the same day, airfields in the Yabangarea and small surface craft off Wleelhoe were success-fully attacked by our fighters.  We suffered no casualties.H.M.S. Indomitable These carriers flew off 32 Avengers, 12 Fireflies and h.M.S. 32 fighters on the 4th January to bomb the oil refineryIndefatigable   at Pangnalan Brandan, which had escaped attack the.M.S. Victorious    previous month.   This time the weather was excellentand the whole weight of the attack fell within the target area, where the power house and all vital buildings, aswell as storage tanks, were hit and &quot;set on fire. Sevenenemy aircraft were shot down and seven more destroyed on the ground. In addition our fighters straffed twoengines and set a small tanker on fire. No casualties were caused by enemy action.H.M.S. Illustrious On the 24th January a striking force of 47 AvengersH.M.S.&quot; Indomitable and 10 Fireflies, escorted by. 48 fighters, took off with.M.S. Victorious destroy the oil refineries at Palembang in Sumatra.H.M.S. Thirteen of the Japanese fighters that -attempted toIndefatigable interfere were shot down and six more probably shot down. Preliminary reports indicate that the strike wasvery successful; a power house, three crude oildistilleries, two distillation plants and two other unitsall being hit while many other buildings were damaged.A fighter sweep of 24 aircraft neutralised enemyairfields, destroying 34 aircraft on the ground and damaging 25 others.   We lost nine aircraft.On the morning of the 29th January, 48 Avengers and12 Fireflies, escorted by 40 fighters, were again flown off to attack the Soeng Gerong oil refinery, while 24 otherfighters supported this effort by striking at adjacentairfields.      -First reports indicate that bombing conditions were.  . good and photographs show that hits were obtained ona large cracking plant and its fractionary columns.Many other buildings were also hit, while re-runningstills were set ablaze and spreading fires were seen to beaccentuating the damage.Although fewer enemy fighters were encountered thanon the 24th our pilots shot down 8 Japanese aircraft,probably destroyed a further 3, and destroyed a further 4on the ground.Our own losses were 15 aircraft, but eight of the crewswere recovered.Seven enemy aircraft which later got through toattack our surface forces caused no damage, and six ofthem were shot down either by CAP aircraft or by ships&apos;gunfire.H.M.S. Illustrious was hit in the Island by a; shellfrom our own forces and sustained casualties amountingto 12 killed and 21 wounded.
2. Light Fleet Carriers.H.M.S. Colossus These three ships commissioned in December and areH.M.S. Vengeance now working up. Each is of 17,000 tons, operates aboutH.M.S. Venerable    thirty-six aircraft and has a complement of 1,360 officersand men.  A photograph of H.M.S. Colossus is attached.H.M.S. Pioneer H.M.S. Pioneer was commissioned on the 5th january and is now working up. She is similar to a Light FleetCarrier but is fitted up as an aircraft maintenance ship.This precludes the operation of aircraft.3. Escort Carriers.(i) H.M. Ships Vindex, Nairana, Tracker and Campania have again beenemployed in escorting convoys between the United Kingdom and Russia.During the passage of RA. 61, which was covered by H.M.S. Vindex,H.M.S. Nairana and H.M.S. Tracker, only one U-boat was sighted and it divedbefore an attack could be delivered. The convoy reached a Home port safely onthe 8th November.On the 1st November, two fast liners carrying repatriated Russians sailed from the United Kingdom with H.M.S. Campania in company. Fighters fromthis carrier shot down a BV. 138 flying boat during the passage North andJW. 61a reached Kola Inlet on the 6th November without further incident. On-the homeward journey (RA. 61a), Swordfish from H.M.S. Campania investigateda radar contact and found it to be an abandoned Norwegian ship, the s.s. Nornoy.Two days later, the 13th, Wildcats repeated their previous success, shootingdown another BV. 138 before it had time to report the convoy. All the shipsarrived safely on the 16th November.-JW. 62, escorted by H.M.S. Campania and H.M.S. Nairana (both veteransof the Russian convoy run) sailed on the 29th November. Contact was soon madewith the enemy, for on the 2nd December the convoy was sighted by an aircraft which our Wildcats were unable to intercept because of the darkness. Submarinescares kept the escorts on the alert for the next few days, but nothing materialiseduntil the evening of the 6th December when one of H..M.S. Campania&apos;s aircraftdelivered an accurate depth-charge attack on a surfaced U-boat which probably sank it.All ships arrived in harbour in the early hours of the 7th December.The return convoy, RA. 62, sailed on the 10th December with the sameescorts in company. Three contacts were obtained during the day and two attacks made by the escorts without result. Early the following morningH.M.S. Cassandra was torpedoed but was eventually towed stern first to Kola.Later that day, a surfaced U-boat was damaged by R.P.s from one ofH.M.S. Nairana&apos;s aircraft. Shadowing aircraft gained contact with the convoyand kept it till the morning of the 12th when the pilot of one of H.M.S. Nairana&apos;sWildcats shot down a BV. 138. During the afternoon, the enemy made twoabortive attacks with torpedo bombers. Two Ju. 88s were shot down by gunfireand one Wildcat, last seen on the tail of a Ju. 88, did not return. During the13th, seven radar contacts with submarines were reported and,from the fourattacks by aircraft a certain kill and two cases of damage resulted. Anothercontact was attacked the following day resulting in a probable kill. Thereafter,no more incidents were reported and the convoy reached the United kingdom on the 19th December.JW. and RA. 63, which sailed on the 31st December and 11th Januaryrespectively, escorted by,H.M.S. Vindex, were more fortunate than previousconvoys in meeting nothing worse than severe weather conditions. During a galeon the 16th the convoy hove to for several hours and aboard H.M.S. Vindexa wind speed of 75 knots and a roll of 38Q were registered. No ships were lost in either convoy.(ii) In addition to the anti-shipping operations carried out in company withthe Fleet carriers, one Escort carrier, H.M.S. Pursuer, sent her Wildcats intoTrondheim Leden on the 14th November and there they sank an armed trawler.After destroying the radar station at Titran, all the aircraft returned totheir ship.Aircraft from H.M. Ships Nairana, Campania and Premier struck atshipping between Stadtland and Alesund on the 29th January. Four merchant ships totalling 6,500 tons were damaged by bombs and R.P.s and, in addition,gunsites and buildings on the shore were straffed.[29252] B 2
(iii) Mining operations in the Norwegian leads have been continued duringthe last three months by aircraft from HM. Ships Premder, Trumpeter andPursuer. Three such /operations have been carried out in addition to the onealready mentioned in which H.M.S. Implacable was concerned.Salhusstronomen was mined on the 20th November, 1944, and again inJanuary and mines were laid in Ranwoysund on the 16th December. Wildcatsshot down a shadowing aircraft and drove off torpedo bombers which attacked the force on the 12th January.  Two Wildcats were lost but the pilots were saved.(iv) Five escort carriers, H.M. Ships Atheling, Battler, Shah, Ameer andBegum,, have been in Eastern waters during the period under review attachedfirstly to the Eastern Fleet and then to the East Indies Fleet. They have beenvariously employed in trade protection and ferrying duties. HM. ShipsEmpress, Khedive and Ruler have now joined the East Indies Fleet and h.M.S. Battler has returned to the United Kingdom.The escort carrier H.M.S. Ameer provided fighter cover in the amphibiousoperation for the recovery of Ramree Island off the Arakan coast on the21st January, but no further information is at present available.(v) H.M.S. Unicorn continues in service in Eastern Waters as a repair ship.She is now on passage to join the British Pacific Fleet and has 19 aircraft onboard which she is ferrying to Sydney.(vi) Four escort carriers are now in service with the British Pacific Fleet;H.M. Ships Slinger, Speaker and Striker are replenishment carriers and H.M.S.Fencer is employed on ferrying duties.(vii) H.M.S. A ctivity and H.M.S. Battler are both aircraft transports. Theyare not allocated to&apos;any particular fleet but operated directly under the orders of the Admiralty.(viii) Six escort carriers, HM. Ships Tracker, Atheling, Rajah, Reaper,Ranee and Patroller, are now lent to the United States Navy and are employed inferrying United States Naval aircraft. They are still manned by their Britishcrews.(ix)- Decklanding training has been carried out. on several of our escortcarriers as operational commitments permitted. HM. Ships Speaker, Slinger,Ranee, Trouncer and Ravager have all been used at various times for this purpose.In the last three months, 281 pupils have qualified and 88 have been givenrefresher courses.(x) H.M.S. Pretoria Castle, the trials carrier, is refitting and will completemid-February.4. M.A.C. Ships.The programme of building up the East Indies and British Pacific Fleetsnecessitated the withdrawal of many escort carriers from trade protection and,as a result, the responsibility for providing air cover for Atlantic convoys hasdevolved largely on the M.A.C. ships. They have satisfactorily carried out their duties in the face of weather which has made&quot; flying operations extremelyhazardous. Fifteen of these ships are in service at the present time, two of themflying the Dutch flag.Section II. Detached Naval Squadrons Operating from Shore Bases.5. Squadrons of naval aircraft varying in number between six and threeat any one time have operated with Coastal Command during the past threemonths. As most of their attacks are made at night and many of them by&quot; blind bombing &quot; using the radar bombsight, it is difficult to assess results but many successes against E-boats and the enemy&apos;s light coastal shipping have beenclaimed. One squadron has operated from Belgium, firstly at St. Croix,Ouistreham and latterly from Knocke.Section III. Aircraft and Equipment.6. British Aircraft. .(i) The Seafire XVII will be produced concurrently with the XV startinglater in the year. The improvements in the Mark XVII include - 5-inch gunsand a strengthened undercarriage.Another variation of the Seafire, the Mark 45, will appear in small numbersthis year, but not until next year will the final version be available. Its speedis over 430 m.p.h.
(ii) The Firefly III will not now come into service, but will be replaced bythe Firefly IV which, although it has the same engine, has improved designfeatures and an increase in speed is expected.(iii) Design work is proceeding on the modification of Mosquitos for Navaluse and a prototype with folding wings and arrestor gear should be flying thisyear.7.. American Aircraft.(i) The Corsair is likely to become a formidable strike aircraft as well as an excellent fighter when the modifications are completed to permit the carriage oftwo 1,000-lb. bombs.(ii) The latest Avenger aircraft, the Mark III, has slightly increased powerand is fitted with an automatic pilot.(iii) The American aircraft still in service, particularly the Hellcat andWildcat, continue to prove their worth.APPENDIX I.Wastage August-October 1944.Lossvs of Naval Aircraft incurred during period August, September, October,1944.   Reports received up to and including 31st January, 1945.Type.	Operational Squadrons.			Squadrons working up.			Training and Ancillary.			Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.	Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.	Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.T.B.R. ... S.S.F.......... 2S.F.   ...       ...       ... A.B.R. ...       ...... Total Operational Types   ... Non-operational Types   ...... Total......	125 158 14	476 484 19 2	8-8 10-9 24-6	3 15 2	72    j      1-4 129        3/9 21   !     3-2 1 1		81 16 1 8	-568   1    4-8 223   1     2-4 ! 52   i     0-6 37   J ... 7-2,		297	981	10-1	20	222	3-0	i 106   i     880		4-0					i ...     1     ...		398   1  1,567		8-5	297	981	10-1	20	222   j    3-0 i		504	2,447   1     6-9	
APPENDIX II.Wastage^-August-October 1944.Aircraft.	;                      First Line.					; &quot;                              Training and Ancillary.          -            -. .						Operational Types.					Operational Types.				Non-Opera- . tional Types.	Total.	T.B,R.*	. S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R. and L.R.	Total.	&apos; T.B.R.	S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R.&apos; and L.R!	Miscellaneous.	(a) Lost or missing in operational flying (6) Destroyed on  ground or on H.M. Ships -      by enemy action    ...      ...      ... 1 (c) Lost in ships whilst in transit        ... ,     ..: (d) Written off charge owing to accident &apos; (e) Written off charge owing to age, reduction to spares, &amp;c.        ...      ......\ -   ..: (/) Unclassified     ...      ...       ...      ... :     ... . Totals         ...      ... :	:    40 59 28 1   .	92 72 &apos; 8 1	5   ; 10 .   1		137 141 37 2	61 20-	;   11 5	1	3 &apos; &apos;&apos;;. 5 m	119 ..276	-   195 ;   306	&apos; 128 &apos;	173	16		317	81;	16	1	8 &apos;,	398	&apos;   m\ ;&quot;&apos; * Includes 1 D.B. Squadron. ,  ,Note.-Written reports have not yet been received in respect of 75 of the items included in above&apos;tables. These have been included in the appropriate:groupswhere possible.   Certain cases included in group (d) may belong to group (a), since some accidents are subsequently shown to be attributed to enemy action.APPENDIX III.Casualties to Naval Flying Personnel, 1st November, 1944, to 31st January, 1945.- Operational. Killed.      Missing..   Prisoner of War.Officers ...Ratings ...Accidental:Officers ..&apos;.Ratings .7.610884121: 7Oi









</content>
</cab>
