<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/23/0 images: 18-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(63)4 12 November 1963. 10. a.m.

1. Parliament. (oral) [Enter Ch.Whip.

L.P.S. Arrangements for Debate on Address. Announce 14 Jan. as reassembly after Recess.

Ch.Exch. See C.P. Quote these figures in debate to point extravagance/skinflint contrast – ?economic debate on Thursday.

2. Foreign Affairs. (oral)

a) Viet Nam

F.S. We have recognised, with many other Govts. (except Fr.).

b) Berlin

F.S. Latest U.S. convoy gone through. No S. reaction to notification of harmonised procedures. We aren‟t very troubled – less so than U.S. But we will keep in line with them.

c) E.W. trade

S.S.I.T.R.D. Must resist in N.A.T.O. U.S. attempts to restrict European credit to S.U. Ball will press : but we must continue to resist.

3. South Africa C.P.(63)8 &amp; 10 [Enter M. Avn.

F.S. See U.S./Nov. resn. Present policy prevents us from supporting cl.4. Hence restrictions in para 4. But may have to go further : P. Dean. rejects idea of separate vote on cl.4., as diminishing too much our support for resn. as a whole.

Therefore extend our policy (as in para, 5) by accepting cl.4 as a recommendation and subject to our own interpretn. : i.e. we wd. “note” cl.4, with emphasis on “Exclusively” or “primarily” concept. Not easy for B/T to administrate : but altve. –Afro/Asian resn. wh. we shd have to veto or abstain on – even worse, especially since U.S. probably wdn‟t veto A/Asian resn.

L.Ch. Avoid “primarily” : say will do our best to ban materials intended

for …

L.P. Too weak. Accept F.S. proposal, realising it is humbug.

S.S.I.T.R.D. We have necessary powers qua machinery : but not as regards chemicals, raw materials etc. Cd. take these powers : but a bad, and extricable precedent.

And S.A. might retaliate by cancelling arms order – wh. Fr. might capture if she merely abstained on resn. But our trade with Black Africa more valuable than trade with S.A.

M.H. Simply follow U.S practice – see para 3.

M.Def. I agree : add words “intended for repression”.

M.A.F.F. Yes on arms : but not on materials – here accept U.S. wording.

Com.Sec. I agree : v. little material (as distinct from plant) wh. is exclusively limited to arms production.

M.Avn. Note guided weapons machinery : therefore keep “intended for repressive use”.

Ch.Secy. I agree : must be consistent with ourselves.

L.Ch. Beware of following U.S. into economic sanctions.

P.M. Humbug anyhow : but insert “for repressive use”.

L.P. Say we have already banned arms for repression : now ready to extend to material wh. cd. be used for same purpose. F.S. to work out formula and agree with M.Def and S.S.I.T.R.D. Then vote for resn. with explanation wh. wd. combine U.S. words in para 3 with thought of “repressive use”.

Group of experts? I will explore further with P. Dean. Beware of having to appear as apologist for S.A.

</content>
</cab>
