<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/23/0 images: 20-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(63)6 20 November 1963. 10.30 a.m.

1. Organisation and Finances of BOAC. C.P.(63)17

[Enter M.Avn. : Ch. Whip

M.Avn. R.V. better : but more pressure to publish C. Must resist at all costs.

Less critical of Corpn.: not critical of Govt. at all.

Compensn. for S.&amp;S. agreed : they have sent letters of resign.

Statement tomorrow.

H.S. Cannot publish C. R.V. v. creditable performance by My. Avn. Adopt it clearly not bowdlerised version of C

M.T. Cf. Stedeford report – wh. we also kept secret. But must stand firm.

L.Ch. I agree. But ?include Annex II of original draft.

M.Avn. Yes: proposed to do this.

P.M. ?Wise to omit trooping refces.

M.Avn. Like V.C.10‟s not directly relevant to losses. Deal with both in debate.

L.P.S. Para 25 too harsh? F.O. pressed BOAC to go into Kuwait.

M.Avn. Dealt with in para 23.

P.M. Does R.V. justify sacking S.&amp;S.?

M.W.P.(D) Add to draft statement indicn. of immensity of future task, rather than past deficiencies, as reason?

M.Avn. Better to treat as almost routine change – tho‟ must admit compensn. if pressed, at least as regards Slattery.

Com.Sec. Emphasise future combinn. of Ch. &amp; Mg. Dr. as reason.

M.Def. Can‟t prescribe to Guthrie how he shd. run the show.

L.P. Can‟t withhold compensn. terms, since i) related to salary, wh. is published. ii) Paid from Exch. while Corpn. in deficit.

P.M. Probably must disclose Slattery : perhaps Smallpeice also : leave to Minister; but no disclosure unless pressed.

L.Ch. Amend pen. sentence of pen. para on p.1. Omit “to put BOAC on its feet financially”.

H.S. Last para: amend to “some losses are likely to continue”.

M.Avn. And confine last para on p.1. to “ … strengthen the management of Corpn.”. End.

Board may resign – but unlikely. Will announce new appts. to Board in debate.

[Exit .Avn.

2. London Bus Dispute. (oral)

M.Lab. LPTB want to make offer – shortage of crews etc. Embarrassing : staved off by Ch.Exch. &amp; M.T. But review necessary. Best by N.I.C. : but TGWU refused. Therefore appoint ad hoc body under Phelps Brown and announce today before busmen‟s meeting tomorrow. Must accept risk of large award.

M.T. Shortage of crews v. acute : and salaries now badly out of line.

Ch.Sec. Agree : a revaluation problem and therefore appropriate to N.I.C. Failing agreement on that, must base enquiry on some non N.I.C. ground – i.e. including transport, as well as wages, aspects of problems. Composition of enquiry shd.d reflect this – e.g. Buchanan?

M.L. He wd. recommend the earth! But T. of R. agreed with Tsy.

Ch.Sec. Still have an extra “transport” member.

M.D. Why have enquiry at all?

L.P. Because otherwise wages become a political issue.

Ch.Sec. And busmen have already had, this year, more than wages policy allows. Therefore revaluation essential.

M.T. And to prevent L.P.T.B. giving too much on straight wages grounds.

M.W.P.(D) Must emphasise “transport” aspects of enquiry. Will discuss with M. Lab.

Ch.Sec. And add “transport” expert to panel.

M.T. Have Buchanan – who wd. resist an experimental method of working.

M.Lab. Will consider fourth name.

M.Edn. Watch precedent for teachers‟ salaries.

L.P.S. Nevertheless, widen to 4 or 5 members.

M.Lab. Will consider : but announce Chairman today. Will make clear that Govt. expect return to normal working. Men will probably accept. But if they refuse, will arrange enquiry to be delayed!

</content>
</cab>
