<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/23/0 images: 24-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(63)10 9 December 1963. 4.30 p.m.

1. Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland. C.P.(63)28

[Enter Ch.Whip : Att.Gen.

L.Ch.(for Background: draft reply circulated. See paras 52-57 of Cmnd.

Com. Sec. 2093. R.W. claiming a veto: not admissible on basis of para 57.

absent) O-in-C. must be laid tomorrow.

L.P. Can‟t he maintain that stage of para 52 not yet reached?

L.Ch. No. R.W. not dissenting from apportt. of assets and liabilities: he is saying that something shd. be added as extra security.

P.M. And if not settled by 30 Dec. no incentive to Terrl Govts. to participate : and we are left carrying baby.

Ch.Exch. But Fedl Govt. have deliberately roused sh‟holders to protest.

L.Ch. Apportt. must be in O-in-C.: hardship cases need not be, tho‟ must be settled before 31 Dec.

Insert after 1st para on p.5., refce. to possiby. of further O-in-C. for other matters, if agreed in time.

Att.Gen. Present sitn. not provided for in para 57. If it were not for 31 Dec right course wd. now be to reconvene confce.

[Enter Tennant &amp; Watson.

L.P. Act speaks of Territories: para 57 of “govts”, i.e. including Fedl. Govt.

M.D. Even so, there is substantial agreement on apportt. : and “substantial” implies something unsettled, or absence of complete agreement.

L.Ch. And we have given Fedl. Govt. “adequate opportunity of commenting”. But, altho‟ they agreed on apportt., they dissent on lack of guarantee; this makes it difficult to say “substantial agt” on assets &amp; liabilities. Deferment of dissoln after 31 Dec, may re-open agreement already reached on e.g. Kariba, railways etc.

P.M. A bad case for us to defend in Parlt. ?Lay O-in-C. tell Com. Sec (in Kenya) to visit Salisbury, to explain our action and to offer amending O.-in-C. of necy. (and if possible – v. little time).

L.P. ?Better to admit that there is not substantial agt. and proceed by legn., reserving O-in-C. for things wh. are genuinely agreed.

S/S.ITRD. But ? have another inter-Govtl. confce. before proceeding by legn. on

items not included in O-in-C.

L.Ch. Veto on assets &amp; liabilities is, in fact, a veto on dissoln.

M.Edn. L.P. and R.W. are wrong: say that RW‟s claim goes beyond para 57.

P.M. Must make clear in reply that guarantee out of question. For rest, propose a discussion with Col. Sec?

M.D. Since we know that we shan‟t agree, unwise to discuss at risk of dissoln. programme failing?

L.P.S. Discussion can only be on basis of O-in-C. being laid.

P.M. Agreed we must hold to 31 Dec?

M.H.L.G. Why not wait till e.g. mid Feb.?

M.P.B.W. Or why pretend we are in conformity with para 57? Why not go ahead and do it.?

Tennant. Delay invites political objn. by Territories : risks re-opening of agreements already reached – e.g. railways, Fedl. public service etc.

Home Sec. Stick to 31 Dec. : reject interpretn. of para 57 as giving R.W. a veto.

L.Ch. And add no possy. of agt. Therefore go ahead. Add all other Govts. agree.

P.M. Concept of veto obviously nonsense.

Therefore adhere to 31 Dec.: re-word letter: ? send Col. Sec. to Salisbury about other non O-in-C. topics.

L.Ch. Better to deal with other O-in-C. topics in letter and get Greenfield etc. here.

P.M. ? Consult Col. Sec. Judges have got to be dealt with anyhow.

L.P., L. Ch. to collaborate in redrafting letter.

L.Ch. On O-in-C., see revised preamble in order to mention Fedl. Govt. &amp; dissoln.

Para 17 shd be para 2.

P.M. Any change risks charge of bad faith? And enables Fed. Govt. To propose amdts? Alter order: but leave preamble.

[Exeunt Att.Gen : Tennant, Watson

[Enter: M.P.N.I

2. Pensions : Widowed Mothers‟ Allowances. C.P.(63)27

L.P.S. As in memm.

Do a) &amp; c) : reject b) &amp; d) and any amdt. of earnings rule. Add an enquiry on one of proposed bases. Third may be best.

But see footnote on p.2 : does it kill (c)?

M.P.N.I. c) wd. benefit 5000 plus 126,000 (of 140,000 w.m.‟s) by increasing allces. Can defend proposed package as helping w.m.‟s also by raising age. Fact-finding enquiry no use: adopt third proposal, particularly because goes wider than N.I. Advisory Cttee cd. go.

Ch.Secy. Do a) &amp; c) – wh. help great majority of widows.

Wd. prefer factual enquiry, partly because recommendatory enquiries are suspect and partly because change in social circs does call for new fact finding exercise..

P.M. If nat asscn. rates improved also – cost?

M.P.N.I. Don‟t know : but wd. extend too widely.

Ch.Secy. Altvly. add on addl. disregard for N.A. for w.m.‟s.

M.H.L.G. I agree : they are hardest hit of all. Fact finding enquiry best.

M.Lab. I agree : but not another enquiry at all.

Ch.Whip. Proposals now too complicated to meet pressure for aboln. of earnings rule for w.m.‟s. Best to resort to this : repercussions not serious – few w.m.‟s become retirement pensioners.

L.P.S. If so, include widows with w.m.‟s.

M.H. We must concentrate on those in need: therefore adopt a) &amp; c).

Home Sec. Fact finding enquiry politically unwise: other types of enquiry dangerous.

M.P.B.W. I share Ch. Whip‟s view: amend earnings rule.

M.P.M. Combine a) c) &amp; aboln. of earnings rule?

Ch.Exch. No! Better to add e) to a) &amp; c).

M.P.N.I. If can‟t abolish rule, leave it alone. Advisory Cttee. wd. resist any increase; and not justifiable on merits, whereas abolition, for w.m.‟s only, is defensible.

P.M. Settle for a), c), disregards, and (e).

Home Sec. Round £7.5 and £5.5 down to £7 &amp; £5 under (e).

P.M. Agree : no enquiry.

M.P.N.I. Please not earnings rule!

P.M. Very well : then pre-Grigg widows!

Leave it at a) c), disregards and (e) at £7 &amp; £5; no Grigg.

L.P.S. An enquiry wd. take edge off decision against pre-Grigg widows.

M.W.P.(D) On lines of second choice.

P.M. Or say Govt. is itself reviewing posn. of widows – better than indept. enquiry.

Ch.Secy. I cd. fluff it in winding up?

L. Ch. No. Don‟t concede under pressure.

P.M. L.P.S. to draft my answer to tomorrow‟s P.Q.

[Exit M.P.N.I.

3. Indonesia : Decca Radar Installations. C.P.(63)30

[Enter M.Avn.

Ch.Sec. Str. Exp. Cttee. have reconsidered. Strong arguments – including risk to technicians – for leaving things as they are. But political arguments on either side even stronger. Withdrawal of technicians depends on making arms embargo public.

M.W.P.(C) Ambassador sees great difficulty in extricating technicians. Lives might not be endangered: retaln. against other U.K. interests more likely.

Even so, political arguments – N.A.T.O. etc. – v. strong.

M.Avn. No military arguments : no benefit to I. for 2 years. And action must be co-ordinated with U.S. sub-contractor. But political arguments v. strong. Must be ready to compensate Decca - ? £1½ m.

M.Def. P.Q. on Wed. Must show determination not to help I. But might defer P.Q. in order to get technicians out.

Must stop it – more technicians to go out.

S/S.ITRD. Is it worth jeopardising U.K. interests of £130-150 m?

L.Ch. But intolerable to help them kill our soldiers.

P.M. Bargain continuance against cessation of confrontation policy?

M.W.P.(C) No chance of that!

P.M. Get P.Q. postponed:: then get on with discontinuance.

[Exit M.Avn.

4. Railwaymen‟s Pay Claim. (oral).

Ch.Exch. Beeching will pay award from 1 Jan. i.e. = 5.1% increase annually.

We can‟t do more. Salaried staff only to get 3% or 3½%.

M.Lab. Agree reluctantly: but not an inch further.

Average increases are 4½%-5% : but impetus growing and I am very worried. We can‟t now get back to 3½% rate.

Ch.Exch. Must rely on NEDC. – but profits as well as wages!

M.Edn. If railway settlement provokes alarm, remember mandatory technique.

</content>
</cab>
