<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/23/0 images: 30-30</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)2 9 January 1964. 10.30 a.m.

1. Parliament. (oral) [Enter Ch. Whip : S/S. Air.

L.P.S. As in statement.

Defence debate on 16 Jan. Amdt. to Oppn. Motion agreed. Oppn. proposal for consultn. with Govt. on defence. P.M. to speak and, without rejecting this, expose some of objections wh. Oppn. themselves have raised in past. Govt. can‟t accept oblign. to consult Oppn.

2. Foreign Affairs. (oral)

a) Cyprus

F.S. G. &amp; T. Foreign Ministers coming: to be seen informally before Confce. on Wednesday.

Ivan Smith (Australian) to be Sec. Gen.‟s repve. in Cyprus. But T. Govt. may reject U.N. repve. at confce. (If there is one ? Plimsoll.)

L.P.S. Dangerous to appear to turn confce. into U.N. affair.

P.M. But shall we get agt. without some U.N. intervenn.

F.S. Must get off hook somehow. But don‟t decide now on U.N. obsn. at confce. N.A.T.O. no use either. Therefore play it slowly and decide step by step.

Our report to Sec. Gen. put in today: to be published tomorrow.

3. Indonesia. C.P.(64)5

F.S. M.D. now agree with Tunku no aggressive action: but political soln. by persuading U.S. to be tougher. Against U.N. intervenn. until identified Indn. participation in raids. Therefore as in my memm – subject to covert action if necy. Can‟t contemplate indefinite continuance of present posn.

P.M. D.O.P. on Tuesday. Then recall High Cmr., Ambassador, C in C etc. then to Cab.

S/S.Air. Consider economic pressure also.

C.S. Why shd. U.S. protest against our buses for Cuba (ordinary trade) but continue aid to Indonesia?

4. Widows‟ Pensions. C.P.(64)4 [Exit S.S. Air : Enter M.P.N.I.

M.P.N.I. As in memm. See para 3 for objns.. cf. 1956 – Bill to give preference of 5/= for widows and no argument for disregard: and whereas 19,000 w.m.‟s now on N.A., 25,000 were left on N.A. in 56.

This wd. be precedent for disregarding a N.I. benefit : and N.A.B. wd.

have to distinguish between w.m.‟s and other “lone” wives.

Since N.I. benefits are now greater than N.A. benefits, we shd. stand firm.

All 14,000 might not be left on N.A. : but some wd. be.

Ch.Sec. Feeling on disregard has grown since ‟56: and big changes in N.I. have recently been matched by changes in N.A. This wd. be an exception.

Difficult to justify exclusion of some 14,000 widows.

Ch. Duchy. I agree. Politically v. damaging.

M.P.N.I. But continuing disregard means that we shall never reduce numbers on N.A.

L.Ch. But w.m.‟s are wholly distinct class. Abandoned wives can get maintenance.

M.H.L.G. But, given rise in standard of living, not a matter of condemnation that people who have suffered some misfortune remain on N.A.

M.H. Justify on basis of w.m.‟s as a unique category.

P.M. Agree : disregard &amp; make best of it.

5. Valuation for Rating. C.P.(64)7

M.H.L.G. As in memm. Real trouble is not present level but concern about impact of continuing rise on fixed incomes. Therefore stress review, not as imposing more on taxpayer but as sharing burden with greater discrimination.

Ch.Duchy. Can‟t we do this more quickly, for electoral reasons?

M.H.L.G. But only great increase in Exch. payment wd. make real difference to average householder. Many are not in hardship : and those who are will be helped by current Bill. For future more discriminating help is needed – and Allen and review will ensure this.

L.P. But purely residential (non industrial) areas are hard hit.

Ch.Sec. But no action now cd. affect next year‟s demand, wh. is being settled now. And shift to Exch. wd. reverse downward trend of taxn.

Ch.D. At lease declare in principle that some more discrimty. system necy.

P.M. ?And try to accelerate Allen or give him new directive.

L.P. But educn is a national affair: unreasonable that elderly person shd have to contribute disproportionately.

M.E. Even so, educn. shd. remain a local service. Provided this is clear, there is a case for considering some shift from rates to taxes for a national service.

Ch.Sec. Ratepayer pays only about 25% of edun. (i.e. domestic ratepayer.)

H.S. Rates burden rising fast and does not (as taxes do) pay enough regard to ability to pay. Somehow or other, we must make this adjustment.

Ch.Sec. That is what review is about.

P.M. I agree with H.S. Can I say something publicly fairly soon?

M.H. But it must be discrimry.

Ch. Secy. Yes : rates lowest in relation to taxes before war.

L.P. Only because of industrial re-rating.

M.H.L.G. But is relief to be only for householder? If extended to industry, Exch. contribn. wd. make sure less difference to average householder, if applied indiscrimly. And no control over way in which L.A.‟s wd spend it!

P.M. M.H.L.G. to bring forward in week or two possy. of accelerating Allen or making public statement about review.

M.H.L.G. L.P., Ch.S. &amp; M.Edn. (and S/.S.S) to discuss in preparation.

</content>
</cab>
