<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/23/0 images: 37-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.(64)9 4 February 1964. 10.30 a.m.

1. Foreign Affairs. (oral) [Enter Ch. Whip.

a) Indonesia

M.W.P.(C) 3 ptite F.M.‟s confce. in Bangkok tomorrow. (Summit not fixed : not before late Feb.) Agenda mainly interpretn. of cease fire. Must inject our own ideas.

b) France

de G.‟s press confce. a flop : nothing to say except familiar self- aggrandisement.

2. Cyprus. (oral)

C.S. Position tense. All parties, except Mak, have accepted proposals. M.‟s reply, (?today), without rejecting, may stipulate unacceptable conditions.

Must then negotiate further: ?U.N. umbrella, but no control.

M.W.P.(C) France won‟t contribute : Germany may.

3. Agricultural Policy. (oral)

M.A.F.F. Cereals. Near agreement. Formula on remedial action now settled; our farmers may object but st. quantity at 9.75 m tons acceptable.

As package, all parties (incl. U.S.?) shd. agree.

Meat. Control not fiscal (ie. price) as with cereals, but physical, (i.e. quantve. quotas). Exporters want agt. that (a) if we exceed st. qns they may exceed quotas; b) if we exceed st. qns and import price falls we will consult with them to restore balance. Must negotiate as best we can; but discussn. v. difficult. May have to fall back on looser agt. about phasing of imports.

S/S.S (a) by breaking price, wd. precipitate (b).

M.A.F.F. Not in their interest to do this: but must protect selves (by right to increase quotas) against excessive price redn. resulting from our exceeding our st. qns (These will be set at output over next 3 yrs).

Ch. Duchy. (b) all right : (a) more doubtful in wording.

Ch.Exch. I agree. [Exit M.W.P.(C)

M.A.F.F. Our own farmers accept quantities : but dislike corrective action, wh. wd. reduce price.

S/S.S. Scots NFU‟s won‟t accept (a) or (b), unless same deal on incomes.

P.M. Increase s.q. for mutton?

M.A.F.F. Can‟t justify higher s.q. than consumpn. is rising. Must have better reason for a break.

P.M. Do we want to break, in order to preserve good will in hill counties, or shd we try for agt.?

M.L. Any Agt. must be consistent with Price Review. ?Better to rest content with cereals settlement: leave meat on looser basis.

L.Ch. ?Limit meat agt. to beef.

M.A.F.F. No : can switch to mutton and therefore won‟t agree to one alone.

Must have another shot : will reconsider wording.

S.S.ITRD. If Scots won‟t accept, ?better to work for complete break.

M.D. No: even if working for break, must appear serious. Therefore offer at least to consider corrective action.

P.M. But brake on prodn. inconsistent with growth policy.

My instinct not to push this through this year; better to accept a break, provided good and genuine reasons.

L.Ch. Might sell the idea on basis that, if some restriction on s. q‟s accepted, we can then be reasonable about incomes. But not otherwise.

P.M. Hill farmer, who can‟t easily switch from lamb to beef, needs a better s.q.

M.A.F.F. But not at expense of N.Z.!

Agree must try to get good Price Review at same time as this settlement.

P.M. Agree: go ahead, on basis of formula, on this hypothesis : but abandoning (a) &amp; confining selves to some even more carefully worded version of (b).

[Exit M.D.

4. British Sugar Corporation. C.P.(64)24

M.A.F.F. As in memm. Arrangement introduced in 30‟s on basis that divd. wd. not exceed 7% without Minister‟s consent. Growing discontent by shareholders, in light of value of assets. Hence proposals for capital reconstn. and divd. freedom. Now ready to be put to shareholders.

They may not accept, particuly. alienation of 25% of equity and “limitation” of divd. to 8% and 9%.

If don‟t proceed, B will resign : we shd. have to instal Govt. directors, who wd. be at loggerheads with sh‟holders directive.

Must face criticism of releasing divd. on basis of public money; and

criticism that 25% is first step in natn.

But, if we don‟t do this, we shall leave a condition ripe for natn. Better to tackle it ourselves.

Ch.Exch. For last 25 yrs, has been a fixed interest no - risk concern.

Why suddenly transform into agency enterprise? Why embarrass incomes policy by releasing divd.?

L.Ch. But why shd. sh‟holders accept alienation of 25% and risks of commercial operation? If so, why shd. we put it forward? It doesn‟t give them anything to wh. they aren‟t entitled already. Even so, it is best course.

M.A.F.F. Shareholders may reject. But scheme follows E.P.C. decision last year, and in any event is unavoidable.

M.P. Attractive scheme. No question of watering cap: simply bringing issued cap. into line with real cap.

Ch.Sec But real cap has been created not by commercial risk taking but by Govt. action. Might well provoke threat of natn.. Therefore leave alone.

M.T. It is because we have left it alone that problem has arisen. Can‟t leave it any longer.

L.Ch. I agree. Real answer is natn. That is not on : therefore proposal is right course.

L.P. I agree.

M.P.B.W. They can legally put the co. into liquidn. &amp; realise the assets.

Therefore adopt proposal. Oppn. may hesitate before pressing for natn.

S/S.ITRD. 75% of shareholdings required for voluntary liquidn. Tsy hold 15%. Influence over institl. shareholders shd. safeguard rest.

M.A.F.F. An unreal hypothesis. More likely that Board will resign. Sh‟holders will then elect own directors, who wd. quarrel incessantly with Govt. directors whom we shd. have to appoint. And instl. sh‟holders wd. sell.

Ch.Exch. Why? A guaranteed 7% is not a bad return.

M.H. I agree. Better to take no action. No real risk of distribn of assets.

But are we committed by what M.A.F.F. has done in discharge of E.P.C. remit? If so, we must adopt proposal.

Ch.Exch. E.P.C. remit was confined to making them risk-taking enterprises.

Release of capital doesn‟t follow automatically.

M.A.F.F. No. Must be one or other. If genuinely risk-taking, capital reconstrn., leading to more efficient concern, essential.

L.P. Threat of natn. will arise anyhow, since coy. has monopoly of processing home grown sugar.

P.M. ?Ride for one more year, rather than risk natn controversy – to Tate and Lyle also.

M.A.F.F. T.&amp; L. favour this scheme.

L.P. But electorally, a minus, not a plus.

MW.P.(D). I agree.

M.Edn. So do I. It will touch off whole debate on natn.

Ch.Duchy. All the better for us!

L.Ch. Not if it starts with a case where there is a good case for natn.

Can we persuade dissident shareholders to drop it for a time?

Ch.Sec. And can‟t accept increase of divd. in relation to period when coy. was under Govt. Control?

M.A.F.F. On this basis Bd. will resign!

Ch.Sec. Resign. because not allowed to increase divd. not a bad posture for Govt.

M.H. Say too generous : must therefore reconsider?

M.P. Alternatively, endorse scheme in principle : but ask sh‟holders to defer for a year.

L.Ch. And let that become known at meeting in March?

P.M. ?Get them – ?with T. &amp; L.‟s help – to defer for a year.

M.A.F.F. Until Oppn. may be in power and natn. wd. be certain?

P.M. Very well. Having negotiated to this point, we can‟t draw back.

Otherwise, breach of faith.

L.Ch. Unless can persuade them to defer for a year – in their own interests.

Ch.Exch. We are only committed to see if satisfy. scheme for restoration of risk-taking can be worked out.

L.Ch. But see last sentence of para 3. We are already committed.

Ch.Secy. Defer increase of divd. for one year?

M.A.F.F. Doubtful if sh‟holders wd. accept.

L.Ch. Not bad for us if they reject it on these grounds.

M.A.F.F. I will see if they will accept it. But they may reject it as a breach of faith – &amp; resign. Ch‟man is already committed.

M.P. Don‟t underrate importance of putting corporn. in posn to raise fresh cap. in due course. Cash resources v. small.

M.A.F.F. I will try – with Ch. Exch. – to get increase to 8% deferred for a year. But chairman may refuse even to put to sh‟holders.

P.M. Can‟t risk that. But he might put to sh‟holders: matters less if they reject or ask for more negotns. That might be convenient.

5. Decimalisation. C.P.(64)18

Ch.Exch. No enthusiasm for this. Sensible investment in long-term: and salutary for business methods etc.

But extra demand on resources unwelcome; choice of system difficult; compensation awkward &amp; expensive; and on C/L unfortunate. Best to lie low till after election.

Ch.Duchy. Not a vote winner.

M.P. But a good thing in itself.

L.Ch. No.

M.P.B.W. I agree: enough modernisation already. Decimals &amp; metrics less popular now that we are not going into Europe.

P.M. Just stall. don‟t say No.

</content>
</cab>
