<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/86/0 images: 307-335</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IIS DOCUMENT lb THE&apos; PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNTO KAJSSTlf*S GOVERNkERT). __E C R E 7. COPY HO._) CABINET    72(36 J.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held 10, Downing Street, S.W.I, on SUNDAY, 6th DeceuiDer, 1936, at 5.30 p.m. PRESENT;-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, iu.P. Prime Minister. (In the Chair;.:e Right H(?n.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P. Lord President of the Council.le Right Hon.Sir John Simon.  G.C.S.I*, X.C.V.O., o.i3.E., K.C., Lx.P., Secretary of State for Home Affaire*ic Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K.G., g.c.w.i., g.c.i.e., Lord Privy Seal.le Right Hon.W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P. Secretary of State fox&apos; the Colonies...e Most Hon.Tne Marquess of Zetland, g.C.s.I., G.c.I.E., Secretary of State for India.he Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.C., L.P.,Secretary of State foi Scotlana.he Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., g.C.C.I., G.B.Bj.&apos;, C.i...Ct., ivl.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.he Right Eon. v.s. Morrison, M.C., K.c, i/;.p.Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.&apos;he Right Hon. Six Kingsley Woou, M.P i Minister of Health.f  Right Hon.^he Earl Stanhope, K.g. , D.S.O.,M.c., First Co.-^..issioner of  &apos;ores.The Right Hon.Neville Ghamberlain, M.P. Ch^ncellox of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Anthony Euen, M.C., M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon.Malcolm MaoDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State for Dominion Affair tiThe   Right Hon.A. Duff Cooper, D.&apos;S.O., k.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.The Viscount Swinton, g.b.e., ii.C, Secretary of State fox- Air.The Right Hon.Walter Runciman, M.P*, Px-esiaent of the Boax&apos;d of Trade.The Right Hon.Sir ThOfiMS.fi Inskip,  3#B E*| K.C., M.P., Minister for Co-oruination of Defence.The Right Hon.  } Olivex- Stanley, uI.G., M P.,President of the Board of Education.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M*P#, Minister- of Laboux-.The Right Hon. A......L. Hore-Bslisha, M.P., Minister of Transport.l .. nicey, G, .      G.C.M.G., O.C.V.O......Secretary.
INTENTION TO MAfcHY.(previous Reference: Cabinet 71 (36) Conclusion 1.)1. proposed . Lmpson Divorce 3111.la     The Cabinet resumed consideration of the question referred to in the margin.The Prime Minister reported that in the course 56) of his conversation with the King on the previous evening, His Majesty had asked him to consider a proposal that he should abdicate and that at the sameetime as the Abdication Bill was passed through Parliament there should be a second Bill, the effect of which would be that Mrs. Simpson&apos;s divorce would become absolute from the moment of the passing of the Act.     He himself had informed the King that anything that could be done to end the present crisis would be very desirable.     He had promised to put the proposal to the Cabinet and try to get it accepted. There had been a conversation that morning between some of his colleagues and himself and the opinion had been rather strongly against the new proposal. The King had been informed of this first reaction of Ministers through Mr. Monckton.The Cabinet gave the most careful and sympathetic consideration to this proposal.     It was realised that the proposed Bill would facilitate the King&apos;s abdication by eliminating the period of several months during which His Majesty would have to wait for the making absolute of the Simpson Divorce.     It was appreciated also that on grounds of State there were strong objections to this interval during which the King, after abdication, could hardly remain in this country and would find himself obliged to reside abroad exposed to the full glare of Press publicity.     The Cabinet were reminded also that in Scotland and some other parts of the British Empire a     divorce decree became absolute at once.     It was recalled also that in England the period between the declaration of the decree nisi
and its &quot;becoming absolute was sometimes shortened by the divorce Judge for particular reasons, though this was done in the interests of third parties and not of the petitioner.On the other hand, the Cabinet could not escape from the position that the passage of the proposed Bill could be represented as a bargain between the King and the Government and that in agreeing to it &apos; y the Government would be condoning something that/could /not be condoned on moral ground^     They would thus be | abandoning the moral position which they had taken up.     The effect of this could hardly fail to be to lower thefer prestige in the- Country, in the Empire and abroad in difficult times when the position of authority of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom was a matter of the first importance. The above were the main reasons but the Cabinet felt also that the passing of the proposed Act, which would free the King from disabilities to which the ordinary citizen still remained subject, would not be beneficial to Monarchy itself.For the above reasons the Cabinet, in spiteof their anxiety to assist the King in his difficultposition, agreed:That they could not proceed with the proposed Bill to end the period within which the decree nisi declared in the case of Simpson v Simpson would be made absolute.
ITHE KING&apos;S INTENTION TO MARRY. Proposed Statement in Parliament. ^Previous reference Cabinet 71 (36) Conclusion 1.2.    The Cabinet had before them the draft of a statement which had been orepored on the previous day for the Prime Minister to make in the House of Commons on Monday, December 7th.The discussion on the matters referred to in Conclusion 1 above had tended to strengthen the desire of the Cabinet to afford to His Majesty the fullest opportunity of weighing his decision and it was felt that the draft before them did not sufficiently take this important consideration into account.A number of suggestions were made for modifying the draft in this direction.The Cabinet agreed:(a) That the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Home Secretary and the Lord Privy Seal should, in the light of the discussion, prepare a redraft of the Prime Minister&apos;s statement in the House of Commons.(b   That the Lord Privy Seal, as Leader of the House of Lords, should make a similar statement in the House of Lords,(A copy of the statement as finally approved is contained in the Appendix).
IB KING&apos;S PTBRTION rliamentary estions as i the action Pinions.3.    In the course of the discussion of the matters referred to in the preceding Conclusions, the suggestion was made that pressure was likely to be put on the Government in Parliament to state precisely what had been the nature of the opinions exoressed by Dominion Governments. The Cabinet agreed:That if such Questions were asked, the reply should be to the effect that the Dominions had expressed their opinicns direct to the King and that His Ma esty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom were not entitled to make any announcements as to what their advice had been.
I    !1 E NEXTI MEETING OP THE I CABINET.4. The Cabinet agreed that the Meeting arranged for Monday, December 7th, need not take olace.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I. 6th December, 1936.
APPENDIX.Yes Sir.      I am jlad to have the occasion Of making a further statement on the position.In considering this whole matter it has always been and remains the earnest desire of the Government to afford to His Majesty the fullest opportunity of weighing a decision which involves so directly his own future hapoiness and the interests of all his subjects.At the same time they cannot but be aware that any considerable prolongation of the present state of suspense and uncertainty would involve risk of the gravest injury to National and Imperial interests, and indeed ne-one is more insistent on this aspect of the situation than His Majesty.In view of certain statements which   have been made about the relations between the Government and the Xing, I should add that, with the exception of the question of morganatic marriage, no advice had been tendered by the Government to His Majesty with whom all my conversations have been strictly personal and informal*    These matters were not raised first by the Government but by His Majesty himself in conversation with me some weeks ago when he first informed me of his intention to marry Mrs. Simnson whenever she should be free.    The subject has, therefore, been for some time in the King&apos;s mind and as soon as His Majesty has arrived at a conclusion a3 to the course he desires to take he will no doubt communicate it to his Governments in this country and the Dominions.  It will then be for those Governments to decide what advice,  if any, they would feel it their duty to tender to him in the light of his conclusion.I cannot conclude this statement without expressing - what the whole House feels - our deep and respectful sympathy with His Majesty at this time.

IKING&apos;S EMTION f/ARRY..**     THE PRIME MINISTER gave the Cabinet son^ft%6u^rT^t-of his talk, with the King on the previous evening. Contrary to Mr Ohurohill&apos;s report, he had found the King in excellent health, and he had learned that,after he himself left, the King had been talking with his Staff until 1 a.m. and had been the lile and soul of the party.    The only thing was that he was not sleeping very well, but that was not peouliai to the King. With the Prime Minister th * King had been in very good form, talking rationally, quietly and oalmly. What had been worrying the Prime Minister himself was |ha thought of thn King drifting about for four months or so with the possibility of matters going wrong for him at the end.    This had been troubling the King, too. His Majesty now made a suggestion whioh he thought would make him happy and at the same time enable him to abdioate at once.    It was important that the matter should not be represented as a bargain.    He himself had replied that anything that could be done to end the present orisis woulu be very desirable.    He had promised to put the proposal to the Cabinet and try to get it aocepted.    The idea was that Parliament should passa Simpson Divoroe Bill, whioh would do away with the remainder of the period before the deoree was made absolute.    It would be passed together with the Abdication Bill.    The divoroe would beoome absolute from the moment of the passing of the Aot.    He did not want to say any more, nor to prejudioe the disoussion by those present.    He would prefer to hear their views first.    They must bear in mind the danger of any break between the King and his Ministers.    He had discussed the matter With some of his oolleagues that morning, and Mr Monokton had been asked to tell the King the first weight of opinion of those who had disoussed-1-
the matter.   Mr Monokton was expeoted haok the same evening, and he would know the King&apos; sf irst reaotion to those opinions.    Mr Monokton had been going to and fro between the King and himself, whioh saved the Prime Minister from oontiuually running up and down between Fort Belvedere and London.    As it was, he had found it necessary to visit the King several times in the last three days.    Mr Monokton had oome up early that morning and hid returned to the King at midday to show him a draft of the Statement whioh it was proposed to riake in Parliament.    The opinion of those present that morning had been rather strongly against the new proposal.   Mr MonoKton had reported this to the King and was ooming baok to report the first impression of Kis Majesty to the attitude of Ministers.    He himself was anxious not to press the King too hard for a deoisio: at the moment.    It they did this the Cabinet would be getting near the position where they might have to rive advioe to tho King, and that was 11 hat he wanted to avoid The King himself was most anxious to avoid the oreation of anything in the nature of a &quot;King&apos;s Party&quot;. He gathered that Mr Ohurohill had not made muoh impression on the King.   His Majesty was deliberately staying away from London as he did not want to oourt demonstrations, oheering, and the like.    In reply to a question the Prime Minister said that under the present proposal the King&apos;s abdication would be voluntary.    The matter would be prooeeded with rapidly.   He himself would have to make an announcement and state that the Bill of Abdication would be introduced on the following day. He would then point out the appalling difficulties of the King&apos;s wandering about while waiting for the decree to be mane absolute, pestered everywhere by the Press. He would recall how the King had always done his duty from his boyhood;    for example, in the War and after;-2-
and would suggest that, for reasons of State, the Government ought to do something to help him in his diffioulty so as to get the whole question settled.THE SECRETARY OF state FOR WaR thought that the proposal would he diffioult to defend.    It would amount to a Ppeoial Aot to allow the King to oomndt adultery, as the law of the land stood.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR AIR said that if it oould he shown morally and constitutionally that the proposal was impossible, he did not want to adopt it. He did not want to put the matter from the point of view of the King being given a faoility not available to the ordinary man.    As a barrister, however, he reoalled that the Oourts had a disoretion to grant a shorter period on oertain grounds.    He did not want to put the oase, however, from the point of view of enabling the King to satisfy his wish for a shorter period. On the oontrary, he would put in the foreground the national nnd Imperial reasonsfor shortening the period as muoh as possible.    If the King were to abdicate without suoh a shortening there would be a very diffioult situation for his suooessor, with the late King wandering about in a state ol unoertainty.    The real justification, therefore, was not the personal desires of the King, but national interests.    If this were refused, what answer would the Goverrarent have to those who said &quot;Give the King time&quot;?   If that question were posed the Government would be in a very diffioult poa. tion, after foroing the issue, before the deoree was made absolute.It was reoalled that the King&apos;s Prootor did not intervene without the approval of the Attorney-Gene ral.-3-
THE PRIME MINISTER said that that point had been examined, and it was found that no guarantee oould be piven that the oonipletion of the divorce would not be disputed.    The odds were that if the Kin? were to abdioate there woula be no intervention.THE HOME SECRETARY said that if intervention dependedl only on the action of the King&apos;s Prootor there might be ways of ensuring that nothing should happen.    As a matter] of faot there was no application as .vet before the King&apos; s| Proctor.    There was, however, another method by whioh objection oould be taken to the divoroe by any member of the publio.   His view, in whioh Mr Monckton oonourred,! was that if the King- remained the dangers or intervention! were enormously inoreased.    as the King oould not pet a morganatic narriage it was by no means impossible that those who wanted to stop the marriage might be able to obtain evidenoe and file an affidavit.    That sometimes happened, and in this oase the risk would be enormously inoreased by the King* remaining on the Throne.    If he abdicated the risk would be greatly reduced.   There was also the risk of oollusion being raised.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE AMD FISHERIES said that a barrister, who was well known to some of his oolleagues | as well as to himself, had been instructed to intervene but was so far without evidenoe.    There was some ground also to believe that Mr Simpson was talking as though he oontemplated changing his previous attitude.THE BORD PMVY SEAL pointed out also that whatever the Government might desire, it would meet with the opposition both of those who wore anxious above all things to avoid abdication, and those who were opposed to the divorce on moral grounds.     Both these parties, though holuing opposite views, mipht be working for the same object.   Mr Churohill also might oomment on the Bill that while he realised the strength of the argument-4-
It drove him to the oo DC lUS ion of a moral shook, to the Empire.    He might then suggest that a projeot for a morganatio marriage would he l^ss of a shook.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR pointed out that the morganatio marriage Bill would also have the advantape of keeping the King on the Throne.THE HOME SECRETARY pointed out that the morganatio marriage proposition affeoted the Dominions, all of whioh were opposed to it.    The other proposition, though shocking, applied only to England, not even to Sootland.    That did not mean that it would not shook the Empire, hut it was rather a different propoaition.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR thought that even the Soots would objeot that the Bill would be taking away from a particular individual (Mr Simpson) a right which he possessed.THE HOME SECRETARY thought that Mr Simpson&apos;s assent would have to be obtained.THE MI MISTER OF HEALTH thought thet the Dominions would be as aiuoh shocked by the proposed Bill as this oountry.    He recalled that any shortening of the period for making the deoree absolute was, under existing praotioe, made not for the benefit of the petitioner but of third parties.TH&quot; SECRETARY OF STaTE FOR INDIA saw the force oi the objeotions to the new proposal, but asked what was the alternative.    Had ths Oabinet the material for considering that point?   He did not know what the King proposed to do if the Cabinet opposed his proposal.THE PRIME MINISTER said they night not know that for twenty-four hours.THE SECRETARY OF STnTE FOR INDIA oontinued that this made the decision diffioult.    There were now two possible oourses.    The effects of one had been mentioned, but what was the effect ol not taking this course?-5-
THE PRIME MINISTER pointed out that the King might deoide to remain on until the deoree was made absolute.THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said he had given muoh thought to this matter of the alternative.    He had only heard of this new proposal on the previous evening and had felt, considerably shooked. Afterwards, however, he had striven to find reasons in favour of it; but espeoially after the conversation that morning ho had felt it oould not be justified.    The strongest reason against the proposal was that it struok a blow at the moral authority of the Government.    Suppose the Government refused legislation, what would be the effeot on the King?   The Cabinet said that there must be no appearanoe of a bargain.    Mr Monckton, however, had made olear that the King1 s abdication did depend on the aoceptanoe of this other proposal, and that if the latter was not approved it would alter the whole situation.    Assuming that the King&apos;s attitude remained what it had been throughout, one of great friendliness to the Government, and His Majesty were to ask for time and for agreement that he should discuss the matter with some of his friends, and suppose the result of suoh disoussions should be that the King wished to remain as King until the divoroe was through, &quot;hat was the position?   He himself did not think the King would find it possible to take this line.   He would soon come to realise that the position was an impossible one. He therefore would like to give the King the time he wanted for consideration and not to give him advice or to adopt any fyv*i*ten a4i i&gt;it &quot;.   When the publio really realised that the Cabinet were not pressing the King they would demand that the situation should be ended.    The King would realise this, and that in his own Interest he oould not delay his decision, owing to the risk of the lady losing her divorce.    By this course, also, the-6-
Government would out the ground from under the feet of Mr Ohurohill, who was playing for time and trying to represent the Government as putting pressure on the King, whioh had never been the oase.    Pdblio opinion would then begin to realise the reasons for giving the -King more time, and that the alternatives were -(1) a morganatio marriage,(2) the lauy to beoome Queentwo of the Dominions at any*ratehad informed the King was impossible;whioh left only the following:-(3) renunoiation by the King of his proposed marriage,and(4) abdication.There was a seotion of publio opinion whioh advooated the King&apos;s renunciation.    There was no reason for exoluding the possibility, even if it was rather remote, that the King might oome to renunciation;   for example, by the lady&apos;s own aot.    If that proved impossible, the public would see that abdication was unavoidable. He thought, therefore, that the best plan was to leave time for publio eduoation and the crystallisation of publio opinion.THE MINISTER OP HEALTH asked if the King would be allowed to oonsult others?THE OHANOELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER thought this required consideration and raised a constitutional question.THE PRIME MINISTER agreed with the Chanoellor of the Exchequer&apos;s summary of the position.THE SECRETARY OF STaTE FOR DOMINION AFFAIRS read to the Cabinet messages that had been sent direot to the King by the Governments of Australia and New Zealand respectively.    The Australian Government made it dear that the Government, the Parliament and the people were opposed either to Mrs Simpson beooming Queen or to a morganatic marriage, and did not think that any-7-
Government that oould be formed in Australia jiifould support those proposals.    The New Zealand Government thought that a marriage whioh involved Mrs Simpson beooming Queen was both impraotioable and inconvenient. In an earlier personal message the Prime MlnlSHer had then suggested the possibility that a morpanatio marriagt would not present insuperable diffioulties. Sinoe, however, the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom had shown that there were diffioulties, they regretted that they oould only support his attitude.    He had not yet reoeived the text of a Minute by the South Afrioan Cabinet, but he had reoeived a confidential foreoast to the effeot that the South Afrioan Government objected to a morganatio marriage but thought that full marriage was even worse.    So far as Oanada was oonoerned Mr Mackenzie King, as he had already reported, was not sending a direot message to the King as he wanted to avoid any appearance of pressure, but he had authorised the Prime Minister to show the King his earlier personal message, whioh had now been approved by the/Cabinet. So far as the Irish Free State was oonoerned there was no fresh information.THE FIRST COMMISSIONER OF WORKS said it was neoessar on the morrow to dispel the impression that had been put about that the Cabinet had advised the King to abdicate.(At this point a draft of a Statement, whioh had been prepared on the previous day for the Prime Minister to make in the House of Commons on Morday afternoon was handed round   Appendix I.)
The Secretary of State for Scotland suggested that the best plan would be to jettison the a.p. Herbert Divorce Bill, but to proceed only with the clauses therein applicable to the present situation.The Home Secretary said the first objection was that this Bill would only operate in the ouse of future decrees nisi and would not help the King.The second objection was that It would be diffioult for the Oovernment to propose to the Committee to move Clause 9 up to the top.     The Bill would no longer then have the appearance of general legislation but would only be a more elaborate way of doing what was proposed.The Secretary of State for Sootland admitted that the objections were great, but said       he had been moved to make the proposal by theobjection &lt;ftf the idea of a bargain with the King /      which lay behind the proposal before the Cabinet as well as to the suggestion that the King, after abdication, would be followed about Europe by Press photographers for four months.     He felt this the more because north of the Tweed the interval before a divorce decree was confirmed did not apply.The Secretary of State for War supported the views of the Chancellor of the Exchequer.     In his view, it    impossible to introduce special legislation.     That position could be explained to the King, but it might be intimated to him that such influence as the Government possessed would be utilised to try and avoid interference in the divorce proceedings.
The Prime Minister said the King Knew this but that such influence oould only be used provided that it would not interfere with theThe Secretary of State for War continuing said it was Important to get rid of the idea that had been spread about that the Government was putting pressure on the King.     Prom this point of view, he 1 thought the draft statement for Parliament admirable.     A criticism, however, was that of the two alternatives the Government hud not perhaps done enough In the direction or urging renunciation.     He asked the Cabinet to consider the possiblity of a representative deputation being received by the King to urge this course. It might consist of ths Prims Minister and one or two of hie colleagues, some of the leading Peers, Leaders of ths opposition In the House of Commons, the Archbishops and perhaps the heads of the Non-Conformist Churches.     Unless something of this kind were dons, he thought ths Government might be criticised as accepting the possibility of abdication too easily.Ths Secretary of State for the Colonies drew attention to ths extraordinary clash of public opinion on this question.     gfcoy^wsLe a strong party that were for supporting the King at any cost including many of the younger people who aup^pe^Nted^&quot;Lord Rothermere.     Ths longer uncertainty continued, the wider would be the division intythc camps.The secretary of State for India agreed. The posBiblity of a morganatic marriage might be dead but not the feeling in favour of it. There
was still a strong driving force in favour of the morganatic marriage plan.     If there were an appreciable delay, it might achieve alarming proportions.The First Commissioner of Works said that movement would be met by the arguments that the lady in question was unsuitable either to be  ueen or to be the King&apos;s wife.The First Lord thought that the best plan was not to press the King too hard just now. If the situation were to get out of hand, it might become necessary to fa.ll ba^ok on the unsatisfactory alternative that had been proposed that day to the Cabinet.     He would, however, not adopt it to-day but wait for a few days.The First Commissioner of Works agreed. He had been attracted by the new proposal at first but the Government could not face the suggestion of a bargain.     It would be better even to face the alternative of the King having to wander about awaiting the confirmation of the divorce.     If public opinion were to turn in the direction of perceiving that there was really nc bargain, the proposal might be considered.The Secretary of utate for Foreign Affairs agreed that the new proposal could not be endorsed at the present time.     He thought, however, thut the result would be pressure for the morganatic marriage proposal for the reason that public opinion wanted to avoid the dilemma of the two^alternatives put by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.     There would be a oertaln amount of pressure in that direction from the Press controlled by Lord Beaverbrook and Mr. Harmsworth as well as from the News Chronicle.
The Prime Minister pointed out that there was no support for that proposal in the provinces and&lt;   that British opinion oould not be judged from the London Press.The secretary of State for the Colonies pointed out that it was in London that there was risk of public demonstrations.The Prime Minister esid there had been heavy propaganda in favour of the proposed morganatic marriage Attempts had been made to produce demonstrations on football grounds, but in only one case had there been any response.     Come of the Lord Mayors and Mayors}   had been approached^so far without success.  The President of the Board of Educationwanted stronger reasons brought out against the proposal for a morganatic marriage.     It could be said, for example, that it would threaten a break-up of the Empire.(The Prime Minister left the room at this point to see Mr. Monokton.)The Lord President of the Council said the idea was prevalent that the Cabinet were threatening the King as a man to bring an end to the present situation.     That view was rather general. Another view was the very strong deBlre to keep the King. A third current belief was that the Cabinet was pressing advice on the King.     A foarth point was that which no one appeared to appreciate-the position of the Dominions.(The Prime Minister returned at this point.)The Prime JJinister said that Mr. Monckton had not had much to say.     The King was, of court,..
disappointed at the first reaction of Ministers hut had not expressed himself strongly on tho subject. Mr. Monokton thought that the Cabinet should wait and that the King would not take long to roach his decision.     He proposed to see Mr. Monokton further after the meeting.The Home Secretary said it would he necessary to obtain some assurance that the King accepted the last paragraph of the proposed statement which might have to be modified, more especially 11 the policy was to give the King more time.The Prime Minister mentioned one correction whioh Mr. Monckton had proposed after showing the draft to the King.The iriinibtex* of Transport wanted to omit the whole of the draft statement except the last paragraph and to alter the last two and a half lines to read &quot;as soon as His Majesty has made up his mind he will, no doubt, announce it to his Government&quot;. He thought that tho earlier paragraphs gave too muoh the impression that the Government were pressing the King.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence referring to the fifth paragraph of the draft suggested that questions would be asked in Parliament as to what were the &quot;indications&apos;* that the King had already reoeived the views of his Governments.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this had referred to the advice given by the Dominion  Governments.     He thought, however, that the whole of the fourth and fifth paragraphs might now be omitted in view of the general desire of the Cabinet to give
the King more time.     He pointed out, however, that If these paragraphs were omitted there would be no hint of renunciation by the King.     If the polioy was to press renunciation on the King, as some of his colleagues had suggested^there ought to be some reference to it.The Minister of Transport asked why In the fourth paragraph after the reference to morganatic marriage. It had been thought necessary to state that there were other courses open to His Majesty&apos;s consideration.The Home Secrotary said the idea had been to enlighten public opinion.     Many people had not thought of renunciation of the marriage.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that after reading the dooument In the light of the new background, he would like to see the whole tone of the dooument altered.     It read a little too much like an ultimatum and should be much more friendly in tone.The Secretary of State for MJc agreed that the Cabinet had changed their minde considerably, but they must avoid giving the impression that there was ample time.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs referring to paragraph 6 said that if an admission was to be made that there were &apos;Alternatives&quot; there was Bornething to be said for leaving this passage in. Probably, however, a supplementary question would be asked as to whether the King was aware of the alternatives.
The Minister of Labour said that on the morrow there        certain to be questions about ths advicegiven to the Dominions.Ths Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs agreed that questions would be raised as to tne nature of that advice.     Ths reply should be thut the King must be left to consider the matter quietly without all the different advice that ho had been receiving being made public.Ths Minister of Health said the Government would have to meet the charge that they had &quot;wangled* the Dominions.The Socretui-y of Stute for Dominion Affairs repeated that if the advice from tne different parts of the Commonwealth was mads public, the King would bs limited in his considerations&apos;.Ths President of the Board of Eduoation thought that the Government would be preueed only on the subject of the morganatic marriage proposition.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs pointed out thut the Press, including the Dominions Press, included columns of objections to the morganatio marriage proposal.The Home Gecretury euid that the answer to a question as to what was the Dominion view would be that whutovor viows they had had been addressed direot to the King and it was not for His Majesty&apos;s Government In the United kingdom to repeat them. General Hertzog was already reported In the Press to have taken that line in public.The Minister for Co-Ordin^tlon of Defence agreed thut if anything was said of the views of the
Dominions, the Government would get into deep watery^.The Chancellor of the Exchequer was disposed to leave out the third and fourth paragraphs of the statement, but to insert in the third line of the sixth paragraph after the word &quot;Governments&apos;* the words &quot;in this oountry and the Dominions&quot;.The Minister for Co-* rdination of Defence suggested that in the fourth line of the sixth paragraph the word &quot;further* should be omitted.The Chancellor of the Exchequer agreed. The President of the Board of Education was anxious to strengthen the arguments against the morganatic marriage proposal.The Prime Minister said this was Impossible until the whole story oould be told.The Secretary of State for Air urged that the statement should be recast with the objeot of giving the King more time to think matters over.The Prime Minister thought that the statement \ should now be left to the Chancellor of the Exohequer and the Home Secretary to redraft in the light of the discussion.     He thought the genersl view was that the Cabinet could have nothing to do with the new proposal.     He feared it would be a disappointment | to the King.The Secretary of State for the Colonies asked if any decision was to be taken about the proposed deputation to the King to urge renunciation. The s*n*ysaia he was not prepared to decide that at the moment.     At the present time, it would do no ko on anu he did not much like the idea.     He would think it over but was not willing to take any
decision that evening.     Conceivably, the proposal might he useful at some later stage.The Home Secretary pointed out that one deputation might lead to a demand for another.The Lord Privy Seal said he could see the point of the Government being able to eay that they had made every effort to try and induce the King to ohange his mind.The Prime Minister said he had frequently said to the King:    &quot;You oould give up Mrs. Simpson&quot;. The King had always rejected this.The Lord Privy Seal said the object of a deputation would be to get into the minds of the public how much the Cabinet hated the prospect of abdication.The Prime Minister said he might perhaps sound the King as to whether he would receive a deputation.The Secretary of State for War was oertain that the King would dislike it extremely.The Prime Minister promised to think the matter over but would not decide that day. te^iis own opinion^ he^ wub against it.The Secretary of 3tate for the Colonies suggested that the Prime Minister might tell th  King that the opinion of all his oolleagues was in favour ofrenunciation and that they would like to make one morejsffortjln^ ma *tvf      a- dl&lt;fa *tLa*,The Prime Minister queried whether thestatement would be true.The Lord President of the Council tho right itwas not true.    Any statement of the kind would have- 17 -
to be nude in a very personal sort of way to beeffective and not by mean* of a deputation.The Secretary of r tate for War thoughtthat there was a faint chance that Mrs. Simpson mightJoin in making similar representations to the King.The idea^ of pressure by the Cabinet would impi-SBS Tthe people.The Secret ry of State for Foreign Affairs thought that^irfT* the proposed statement had been made in the House of Commons, public pressure would die down a little.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affaire reoalled that in the event of the King&apos;s abdication, legislation would be necessary.     He had now heard from Canada, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa that all were willing to assent to legislation In the United Kingdom Parliament, though some of them would afterwardB want to pass confirmatory legislation.     He did not wholly despair of some co-operation from the Irish Free State.The Prime Minister said that in view of the very full discussion, it would be unnecessary for the Cabinet to meet as arranged on the following day.H -hltehall Gardens, s.W.I. I*1    eceraber, 1936.- 18 -
APPENDIX I.PRAPT STATEMENT FOR PAKLIA1 ffi]VL AS DISCUSSED BY THE GASInW ON ST)! DKt51$ 1936.Yes Sir.     I am glad to have the opportunity of making a further statement on the position.In considering this matter the whole house will desire to have regard to the   necessity of assuring to His Majesty the full opportunity oi weighing a decision which involves so directly his own future happiness and the interests of all hie subjects.At the same time they cannot but be aware that any unnecessary prolongation of the present state of suspense and uncertainty would involve risk of the gravest injury to National and Imperial interests.After the   statement which I made on Friday dealing with the suggestion that what in called a morganatic marriage might be legalised,&apos; it must be considered what other courses are open to His Majesty&apos;s consideration.His Majesty might, of course, decide to renounce the present project of marriage.     But if it is adhered to the alternatives left would appear to be strictly limited and no doubt His Majesty, before expressing his desires, will consider such indications as he has already received of the views of his Governments.As soon as His Majesty has arrived at a conclusion as to the course he desires to take he will no doubt communicate it to his Governments, and it will then be for his Governments to decide what further advice, if any, they would feel it their duty to tender to him in the light of his conclusion.-1-
In view Oi the statements which have &quot;been made about the relations between the Government and the King, I should add thatj with the exception of the question of morganatic marriage* no formal advice has been tendered to gis Majesty with whom all my conversations have boen informal.     These matters were not raised first by the Government but by Mis Majesty himself in conversation with me some weeks a^o when he first informed me of his intention to marry Mro. Simpson whenever she should be free.     The subject hay,  therefore, been for nome time in the King&apos;s mind and His Majesty has been graciously pleased to give an assurance that he fully recognises the necessity of a very early dccision.
Yes Sir.      I eon jlad to have the occasion of making a further statement on the position.In considering this whole matter it has always been and remains the earnest desire of the Government to afford to Mis Majesty the fullest opportunity of weighing a decision which involves so directly his own future happiness and the interests of all his subjects.At the same time they cannot but be aware that any considerable prolongation of the present state of suspense and uncertainty would involve risk of the jravest injury to National and Imperial interests, and indeed no-one is more insistent on this aspect of the situation than His Majesty.In view of certain statements which   have been made about the relations between the Government and the Xing, I should add that, with the exception of the question of morganatic marriage, no advice had been tendered by the Government to His Majesty with whom all my conversations have been strictly personal and informal.    These matters were not raised first by the Government but by His Majesty himself in conversation with me some weeks ago when he first informed me of his intention to marry Mrs. 3imr&gt;son whenever si e should be free.    The subject has, therefore, been for some time in the King&apos;s mind end as soon as His Majesty has arrived st a conclusion as to the course he desires to take he v/ill no doubt communicate it to his Governments in this country end the Dominions.  It will then be for those Governments to decide what advice,  if any, they would feel it their duty to tender to him in the light of his conclusion.I cannot conclude this statement without expressing - what the whole House feels - our deep and respectful sympathy with Hi3 Majesty at this time.

</content>
</cab>
