<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/10/0 images: 168-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Any further communication should b^VJ addressed not to any individual by namf/)bu&apos;t0&quot;&quot;&quot;      ^     ^The Director,Board of Agriculture and Fisheries, Food Production Department, 72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. 1. and should quote the Reference Number and Date of this letter.Registered Telegraphic A duress : &quot;Growmore, Sowest, London.&quot; Telephone: Victoria 8240.Sir,I have the honour to submit the following Report for the week ended 10th April:-The weather conditions during the past week have continued&apos;&apos; - --;&quot;.Abb -bbb V:^:-to be exceedingly unfavourable, and work on the land has in most parts of the country been rendered all but impossible.     This has not merely put a stop to ploughing and seeding, but has also done much damage to the wheat and oat crops sown during last winter. It has also greatly delayed the delivery of seed potatoes, and, in many cases, entailed loss from frostage en route.     The general position with regard to the harvest of 1917 becomes increasingly serious, and unless there is an immediate and settled improvement in the weather, most of our forecasts and hopes of increased pro-duction this year will.be doomed to disappointment.Owing to the above-mentioned circumstances, and the..........intervention of the Easter Holidays, the returns from each county of the acreage of additional land actually ploughed, which were anticipated in last week&apos;s Report, have not yet been received.&apos;     A summary of them will be submitted as soon as they are available, but in no case could reliable figures be forthcoming before May 1st.I.    LOCAL ORGANISATION, Work of County Execut.iyj^Coinmittees.The County Executive Committees continue to increase their activities; and the specific instances of action which are enumerated in this Report by no means constitute the greater part of the work done by them during the week, even with regard to theof Agriculture and Fisheries,Food Production Department,72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. 1. 11th April, 1917.
extended and improved cultivation of land, quite apart from matters such as the supply of labour and the arranging of programmes for tractors which are summarised later in the   Report and, therefore, not referred to here,     The Committees constantly issue specific directions for cultivation as to fresh pieces of land, give advice to the occupiers where these are willing to act upon advice with-out compulsory directions, negotiate changes of tenancy and so on; thus, the Norfolk Committee dealt in these ways during the weak with more than 50 pieces of land, the Cornwall Committee with 27, the Somerset Committee with 12, the Flintshire Committee with 17.The following are cases of specific action which may be. of Interest:-Bedfordshire - The Committee have been authorised to takw posses-sion of 84 acres of land at Odell, on which they will grow cereals, employing the farm foreman to do the work under the supervision of a member of the Committee.Plrmingham - The Executive Committee have arranged for voluntary changes of tenancy of two farms aggregating 185 acres. Cornwall - As a result of the Prime Minister&apos;s meeting with the District Commissioners, the Executive Committee are taking fresh steps to urge the Cornish farmers to increase the cultivation of cereals, especially that of barley, which can be sown in Cornwall up to the middle of May, as well a3 to increase the yield by the extended use of Sulphate of Ammonia.     The Committee are holding meetings all over the county to further the campaign. Kent.- The Executive Committee are taking possession of 120 acres of building land near Birching^an, in addition to tho 200 acres already reported, and have arranged for its cultivation.     They have also been authorised to take possession of two farms in Romney Marsh, aggregating 170 acres.
4 f&quot; A151Norfolk - The Committee are taking possession.of 40 acres at Hingham, and 6 acres at Barriham Broom.Somerset - The Committee have taken possession, for allotment purposes, of 1-g acres of land at Yatton, and 3 acres at Bath Easton.   They have also taken possession of 33 acres of land at Combe Florey, and of \\ acres of market garden at Gdcombe, which they are letting to neighbouring occupiers. Suffolk, East - Under the auspices of the Committee &apos;&apos;Win the War Committees&apos;&apos; have been formed in practically every parish to organise the cultivation of allotments, the collective purchase of human or animal food, the destruction of rats and sparrows, and economy of food and money.Wiltshire - The Committee have arranged to cultivate a farm of 111 acres at $hiteparish which had been much neglected by the owner, who has recently died. As an instance of the successful use of pressure without recourse to compulsory powers, it may be stated that in one case the Committee have secured the breaking up of 40 acres out of a holding of 100 acres, which was entirely in grass.Yorkshire, East Riding - The Committee have taken possession of 10 acres at Hunmanby which are being cultivated by an ad j c ining tenant.Animal Pests.The Local Government Board has decided to allow expenditure for the destruction of rats and house sparrows to be met out of the rates by District and Parish Councils and Parish Meetings,    /. notice to this effect, indicating the approved methods of securing the destruction of these pests, has been published in the Press and circulated to County Executive Committees.The County Executive Committees have been asked to put pressure on the landlords to reduce the number of rabbits,
and to allow farmers to lay traps on either side of the banks of woodlands. The Committees have also been urged to induce the owners of rookeries to destroy considerable numbers of rooks, and approved methods of doing so have been suggested. The Department propose to take powers to secure such destruction in cases where the owners fail to carry it out voluntarily.Cultivation of Lands Order, 19rM No^il-Reports have now been received from 727 Boroughs or Urban Districts.   These show that 104,998 applications for plots have been received, and that 84,129 plots, representing a total area of 6,067 acres, have been provided.Horticultural Section. About 100 persons have been recommended as District Horticultural Representatives- these are being considered and appointments made.II.     TECHNICAL AND ADVISORY.The arrangements for supplying material weekly to local papers are now in working order.   The War Agricultural Committees have been informed of the establishment of the Technical Committee which has been put at their service.A poster on economy of use of feeding stuffs for horses and stock is ready for issue. Bulletins are in prepara-tion on mole draining and the feeding of calves and store cattle.III.   LABOUR.Soldier Labour - The demand for soldier labour during the past week has been considerable. A return has been furnished by the Military Authorities showing the number of soldiers actually out on the land.   The figures relate to 1st April and are as follows * -Ploughmen ..................... 20,792Home Service Men...... f.......    9,699Agricultural Company iAen ......    5,80436,295
As it is known that additional men have been sent out during the present month, the number of soldiers actually being employed on farms at the present time must be at least 38,000. Prisoners of W-ar - A feature of the Commissioners&apos; reports has been the satisfaction expressed by farmers with the work of Prisoners of War, wherever they have been employed. The time seems ripe for a further effort to arrange with the War Office and the Home Office for an increased supply of this labour which, if forthcoming in large quantities, will greatly relieve the situation during the coming season.-Women&apos;s BranchUp to April 9th, 6,288 enrolment Cards from women volunteering for work on the land have been received. The London Committee called up 80 volunteers during the week, of whom 51 attended, 28 being selected for training.Reports coming in from the Counties shew that small groups of 6 to 10 volunteers are already being placed in employment.MACHINERY SECTION.The weather during the past week has been exception-ally unfavourable for motor ploughing, and a large proportion of the available tractors have been standing idle in consequence. Motor Tractors - A further 25 of the 515 tractors ordered from America have been received, bringing the total of Government owned tractors up to 163.    &apos;As it has been found necessary to cancel some of the agreements entered into in respect of privately owned tractors, the number of such tractors now under the control of the Department is 460, i.e. 10 less than the number mentioned in last week&apos;s Report.   The total number of Tractors now under the control of this Department is, therefore, 623.
28 additional motor engineers have been appointed bringing the total number of appointments up to 320. Steam Tackle - Applications for the return of 6 specially classified men have been made during the week.     14 such men have been ordered to be returned to civil employment during the week, bringing the total up to 190.IV. SUPPLIES,Fertilisers and Feeding Stuffs Section-Sulphate of Ammonia - The monthly returns of sulphate of ammonia show that 32,000 tons were delivered for agricultural use during Search.     In the same month last year the quantity was just over 10,500 tons.     The production is being well maintained and the&apos; stocks now remaining in makers&apos; hands are relatively small. Superphosphate - The production of superphosphate during the month has increased owing to the release of acid by the Ministry of Munitions, the production being 33,500 tons in March as corn-pared with 25,000 tons in February.     The quantity delivered amounted to 36,300 tons.Basic Slaff - The production of basic slag has also increased!), while the deliveries during   arch have been larger, and have amounted to 40,600 tons, as-compared with 34,600 tons.during February.     The stock in the hands of makers at the end of the month was reduced to 7,000 tons.Compound Manures - The quantity of compound manures sent out from makers works during March has been heavy, amounting to 78,000 tons, as compared with 54,500 tons in February .The circular sent to makers last week asking them to arrange for the immediate sale for all fertilisers in time for use on this season&apos;s crop was well received.     The replies indicate generally that the bulk of the stocks in hand are sold and that makers are using every effort to clear their stocks.
J. 3 0All cases in which there appear to be any available supply will be brought to the notice of the War Agricultural Committees and other buyers.Seeds Section * The weather during the past week has been very unfavourable for loading potatoes and damage by frost is reported by several consignees.The Seed Potato (Prices) Order, (No.2), issued on the 3rd April against the advice of this Department, has given rise to adverse criticism in Scotland, andj although it has increased the authorised price for seed, it has proved a hindrance rather than a help in securing supplies.Shipments from Ireland came forward steadily during the week, the rapidity with ?;hich this has been effected being largely due to the Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland, and the Department of the Controller of Shipping.During the week about 60C tons have been discharged at Bristol, 300 tons are on passage, and 3,100 tons are being loaded in Ireland.The Irish Department of Agriculture have intimated their willingness to supply an additional 1,500 tons of potatoes jmaking 8,000 tons in all.     This will greatly relieve the situation.I am,Sir,Your obedient Servant,Director-General.Hon. Rowland E. Prothero, M,P, Resident of the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
