<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/10/0 images: 509-511</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR CABINET^ff.Mr,VAL:..OP:BAS-  SUPPLY DEPOTS. JLm^gSiSS &quot;AND LIVERPOOL.TO;riLAMD .CSNTREB2 5M-rte, of Correspondence-between War-Office, -Ministry of Shipping (&quot;SSS &amp;K 3S* Cabinet and a Re port of the Port and Transit Executive Committee, -dated   13th Aprils 1917-fr.I,orMinistry of Shipping to Secretary War Cabinet17th April,-,.1917Sir;I &apos;.am directed by the Shipping Controller to request you to submit for--the consideration of&apos; the War Cabinet,.:the : enclosed copy of letters&apos;addressed to the War Office; urging the removal of the Army Base Supply.Depots from the ports of Liverpool and Avonmouth, to which no reply has been received. A report.&apos;from the Port and Transit-Executive Committee, .dated the 13th instant,, upon the position as regards Avonmouth is also, enclosed and I am to state that&apos;the Controller fully, concurs in. the conclusions thereof. -*As regards Liverpool I am to add that, Alie,there can be no doubt that&apos;the work of the port would be expedited by-the removal of-the Supply Depot,&apos; the Controller does not consider that the question- is of quite the same urgency; and -import ance - there at the present moment,&apos; -I&apos; am, etc,(Signed) GRAEME THOMSONII.-Ministry of Shipping, to. War Office2oih&apos;;March&apos;^1917-Sir,:.   I lam directed by/the Shipping Controller to state for the InfermaU.on- of &quot;the .Army Council&apos;.that his -attention-; has keen -drawm to.-the seri-dus -hindrance to - the normal.and legitimate work-&apos;of --the ports &quot;of - Avonmouth: and Liverpool which results from-the use of /parts of the dock premises,/-including transit sheds,-far the purposes - of Base Supply-Depots *    Not only do these Depots occupy, valuable, dock accomedatiqm which is needed for - shipping purposes, .but.&apos;the railway facilities of the ports- are put to an additional strain: when their, utmost capacity is nec-essai^,to-&apos; clear.
inward cargoes, if the off-loading of cargoes is to be ex-pedited1, and to maintain a steady and uninterrupted, flow of traffic from the ships -to the ultimate inland destinations * Without this there can be no further substantial improvement in the turn-round of vessels.As the time required to turn a ship, round is at present on tho average about 50$ longer than under peace conditions;&apos; pausing a loss of carrying power of about 10$. the Army Council will appreciate how important it is at the present, time that no means of shortening that time should be neglected *The Shipping Controller therefore desires in the strongest terms to urge the Army Council to give its earliest and most, earnest- considerations to the question of removing the Base Supply Depots from Avonmouth and Liverpool to inland-centres such as Gloucester- and Shrewsbury.It may be added that representations on this matter have been made on previous Occasions; in particular, in a letter from the Director of Transports to the Director of Movements on 22nd Sept ember \ I915V, in the report of the Mediterranean Transport- Commissions of 1st February; 1916* upon its visit to home ports, and at various meetings of the Port and Transit Executive Committee, the Army Council being represented upon both these bodies.I am, etc .-Despatched - Sd. (GRAEME THOMSM)J-1 i *Ministry of Shipping to War Office5th April, 19179-AI an directed by the Shipping Controller to inquire whether the Army Council has yet come to any decision upon the subject of my letter of the 20th ultimo; urging the removal of the Liverpool and Avonmouth Base Supply Depots to inland centres., I am to add that in the opinion of the Controller this is a matter of great urgency,I am, etc. Despatched     Sd,(GRAEME THOMSON)
IV.REPORT OF THE PORT AND TRANSIJP EXECUTIVE COMMITTEEDATED 15th. APRIL, 19-17She position in regard to the Homo Supply Depot at Avonmoiith was first raised by the Committee &amp; r the Diversion of Shipping on the 21st January, 1915.it was again raised by the Advisory Committee on congestion   at British ports on the 1st May, 1915.It was again raised by the Avbnmouth (Admiralty) Co-ordination&apos;Committee on the 16th September, 1915.All these Committess made urgpnt representations in-favour of the Depot being established   at some inland c cntre^ and insisted on the necessity of the removal of the serious restrictions it placed on the utilisation of the port of Bristol to the be st advantage.The War Office apparently Ignored the representations made by all these Committees.The Fort and Transit Executive, Committee w as formed on the 1st November, 1915.     On its formations, At reviewed the position in regard to the Depot, and it wa^Tormed by the War Office representative on the Committee that,, in view of the large expenditure that had been incurred, in developing the Depot, it was not possible to make any change.-The Port, and Transit Executive Committee has accepted this decision as final, having regard to the previous representations made to-the War Office, and since the date of its appointment, has taken all possible steps to minimise the inconvenience;   caused to the. Port by the existence: of the Depot,   It has obtained the release from time? to time of particular transit sheds, until at the present time only &quot;R&quot; transit shed, King Edward Dock, is being used for other than transit purposes.The fact remains that the establishment of the Depot pi the Port seriously impedes the flow of traffic through the Port.     A very great part of the stores are carried over the Railways   into the Depott, and are then distributed over the Railways from the Depot.     All this traffic could be handled at any convenient inland centre,, but the ia ct that it is concentrated at a port interferes most seriously with the railway facilities serving- the port.It is more than ever important to maintain the full efficiency/Of all popts on the- West Coast,     As&apos;matters stand, the traffic through Bristol,. (incj.udlng A vermouth)-, is seriously impeded by&quot; reason of the Homo Supply Depot, although the submarine campaign, may, at any time,, reader the further-utilisation:, of the port of Bristol an imperative necessity*

</content>
</cab>
