<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/286/0 images: 135-152</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTSECRET.0.P.105(39)Copy No.CABINET.Possibilities of Refugee Settlement in British Guiana.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.          I circulate for the information of myColleagues a copy of the Report of the British GuianaRefugee Commission to the Advisory Committee on political Refugees appointed by the President of theUnited States of America.          This Report is under urgent consideration inthe Colonial Office, and is to be considered by the j........Cabinet Committee on the Refugee Problem on Tuesday9th May.   The Committee will report to the Cabinet assoon as possible.          The Report is also under consideration by theCo-ordinating Committee for Refugees  in this countryson whose  behalf the Commission was sent to british guiana.M.M.fColonial Office,   4th May, 1939,
Confidential-Proof .palyReport   of  the   British   Guiana  RefugeeCommission  to  the  Advisory  Committeeon    Political   Refugees    appointed    bythe   President  of   the  United   States  of                        AmericaPresented by the Secretary of State for the Colonies to Parliament            by Command of His Majesty                 May, 1939                        LONDON    PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICE  To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the. following addresses:      York House, KJngsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh z;         26 York Street, Manchester 1;  1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;.                   80 Chichester Street, Belfast;                    or through any bookseller .  . &apos;   .&apos;   &apos; ;-,4,., -I:&apos;.:.     1939         ,.  -  ,&apos;j.r,;,.,    - .   &apos;          Price     net  . ,Cmd.
REPORT  OF  THE BRITISH GUIANA REFUGEECOMMISSION TO THE  ADVISORY COMMITTEEON  POLITICAL   REFUGEES   APPOINTED   BYTHE   PRESIDENT  OF  THE   UNITED  STATES                     OF  america the POSSIBILITIES OF LARGE SCALE  SETTLEMENT      IN  BRITISH  GUIANA  OF  REFUGEES   FROM      CENTRAL EUROPE.  In the latter part of 1938 the British Government  made a tentative offer of lands in British Guiana as a  possible site forthe settlement -of  the involuntary refugees created by  recent events in Europe.&apos; The Presidents Advisory Committee on political Refugees agreed to appoint an impartial  commissionto investigate these areas.Personnel of Commission.  2. The Advisory Committee accordingly appointed, a corn-mission consisting of Dr. Edward C. Ernst, Assistant Director,Pan-American Sanitary Bureau  (Chairman); Lt.-Col.  RichardU.  Nicholas, United States Army Engineering  Corps,  PanamaCanal;  Dr.  Joseph A. Rosen, Jewish Colonization expert andagronomist; Mr. Emile C.  Bataille, Colonization  expert  with canadian  experience;  Dr.  Anthony  Donovan,  Sanitarian,United  States Public Health Service; Mr. Desmond Holdridge,who had previous experience  of the Colony and the adjoiningregions of Brazil and Venezuela (Secretary).  The British Government then nominated as  members of theCommission Sir  Crawford Douglas-Jones, former Colonial Secre-tary of British Guiana, and Sir Geoffrey Evans, now EconomicBotanist of  the Royal Botanical Gardens at Kew, until recentlyprincipal of the Imperial College of Agriculture  at Trinidad, andwith a  very wide  experience of tropical agriculture.   The government of British Guiana was good enough to secondDr. D. W. Duthie, soil-ecologist, of the Department of Agri-culture.  For a considerable period the Commission  availeditself of the services of Dr. George Giglioli, an expert in Malariacontrol, which were generously loaned by the Sugar  Planters&apos; Association of British  Guiana. Terms  of Reference.   3. This  Commission  was  given  the following  terms  of reference:         To study and report on the  suitability and practicability     of large-scale colonization in British Guiana for involuntary     emigrants of European origin, from the physical, climatic     and economic points of view,  to estimate the  approximate     numbers that might be settled  there  (a)  immediately;     (&amp;) over a  term of years; to calculate the probable.cost of
    such settlement; if mass colonization appears feasible, to    recommend a general plan of settlement.Areas available for examinationt  The following areas were made available for examination:        (a) The  district  south  of 5&apos;0  north  latitude between the    Essequibo  River and the Brazilian boundary  on the west    of the territory, covering an area of  about 22,500 square    miles, of which 4,400 square  miles are open savannah and    the remainder forest.      (6) The  district south of 5&quot; north latitude lying between    the Essequibo  and Courantyne Rivers and the  Brazilian    boundary on the south of the territory, covering an area of    about 14,800 square miles which is almost entirely forest.      (c) An  area covering  about  4,600  square miles,  partiy    mountainous and principally forest country, in the North-    west District of the Colony, &quot;lying between the watershed of    the Barima  and Kaituma Rivers on the north  and the    watershed  of the Cuyuni and the North-west District river    system on  the south.  The  above areas include some 855 square miles of Indianreservation which would not be available for examination, andalso areas extending to between  3,000 and 4,000 square milesover which grazing, mineral and other rights have been granted for specified periods.  4. The Commission assembled in Georgetown, British Guiana,on  14th February, 1939.  5. It  will be useful  at this point to examine in some detail the general nature of the problem confronting the Commission.  In 1934 the  Assyrian Commission examined the Rupununisavannahs of British Guiana with a view to settling the Assyrianpeople in the hinterland of the Colony.  Its report was unfavour-able.  The conclusions of the Assyrian Commission were not, how-ever, necessarily germane to the problem with which this Corn-mission had to deal since  it presented a  number of  specialfeatures.  These are:        (a) The  extreme urgency  and necessity with which the    refugees were being forced to find new homes.      (6) Considerable sums of  money would presumably be    available  for the  establishment  and  maintenance of any    settlement  which might be possible.      (c) The   present  proposal  differed from  that of  the    Assyrian project in that it contemplated  the settlement of    a much larger number  of people  and on a scale which    would justify the considerable capital  investment  obviously    necessary for the development  of the  country  for  coloniza-    tion.17266
Methods of approaching the hinterland.  6. The hinterland of British Guiana, especially that area lyingsouth  of the  fifth parallel of north  latitude,  has been verysparsely settled and  contains to-day a  negligible  number ofEuropean colonists, owing principally to the extreme difficultyof access.  At present it may be reached by an arduous canoeor launch journey up the Essequibo and Rupununi rivers or byan  equally  arduous land  journey over  the Rupununi  CattleTrail,  through which are driven, with considerable losses/the cattle now raised on the savannahs of the far interior.  &apos;  A third method of approach,  and  perhaps the easiest one,is via  the Amazon, Rio Negro,  Rio  Branco and Rio  Takatuto  the British  frontier.  This  route,   however,  is  throughBrazilian territory  and  available only in the height of the wetseason.  It is open to river steamers drawing from four to  sixfeet of water from June until September,  approximately.  It may, therefore, be said  that any attempt  to settle people in substantial  numbers would  involve the construction of a road which  would  pierce the forest belt between  the sea  (or thosepoints  on the navigable rivers which may be reached by deepwater vessels) and  the savannahs which stretch broadly speak-ing from the 5th parallel to the second parallel of north latitudebetween the fifty-ninth and sixtieth meridians of west longitude.The time, money  and effort  involved in constructing even the cheapest kind of  transport route would certainly be so great that it could only be justified if settlement on a large scale were found  to be possible.Settlement on agricultural  basis.  7. It also seemed to the Commission  that initial settlementof  refugees  in any number  would have to be on a suitableagricultural  basis.  They would have to be self-sufficient, orvery nearly so in  the matter  of food supply.  It was felt that,were this feasible, there would then be the possibility of a normal  economic  entity  with  industrial,   agricultural,  andpastoral pursuits  complementing  each   other  and  permittingexport to world markets of those surplus products which mightbe  exchanged for  commodities impossible of production in  thenew settlements.  It therefore seemed  that an effort  should be made  to  findlands suitable for permanent cultivation, as opposed to the shift-ing methods used by Indians and others  at present in the regionunder  consideration.Search for suitable soil.  Such investigation as had been carried out previously seemedto indicate  that very little fertile  soil, suitable for permanentcultivation,  existed in  the hinterland of British  Guiana;  butas  mentioned in  Sir  Geoffrey  Evans&apos;s agricultural - report,Mr. Follett-Smith had  noted a promising  type of soil  in  thePakaraima  valleys and also  in the  foothills of the  KanukuMountains.                                          ;
Industrial investigation needed.  8. A further field requiring investigation  was the industrialone.  Under this  heading may be  grouped the study  of  rawmaterials, minerals, and power sources.Health considerations.  9. Also to be considered was the extreme importance of publichealth and sanitation to  the successful solution  of  the many problems of  tropical  colonization.    It seemed  necessary toascertain to what  extent  malaria-bearing mosquitoes occurred,to know the incidence of jungle yellow fever, intestinal diseases,and in general to be able to report on the whole array of maladiesoccurring in  one part or  another  of tropical regions generally.Further, there had to be studied the possibility of settling peopleon  suitable village sites where drainage and  other works of thesanitary engineer  could be  performed cheaply  and. effectively.Study of climatic conditions, in this connection, was of supreme importance.Status of aboriginal Indians.  10. Another consideration, which was at no time neglectedby  the Commission, is  the problem  presented by  aboriginalIndians now  residing in  portions of the Colony south of the fifth parallel,  and  it seemed that great care should be taken in introducing new population, lest injustices be unwittingly perpe-trated on the present inhabitants of the country.Division of field of investigation.  11.  In view of the foregoing considerations,  it seemed to this commission  that  its efforts could be divided conveniently into three main branches of exploration and investigation,  these&quot; tobe  (a) an examination of the possible transport routes throughBritish territory notably  the  Cattle  Trail and the  Bartica-Potaro Road, the first of which  might be improved,  and thesecond of which  might  be improved and extended  to thesavannahs.   (6) Exploration for soils which might be  suitablefor a permanent system of  agriculture,   (c) A  medical  investi-gation  to  determine  the incidence of tropical  diseases  and examine the possibilities of prevention or attenuation of dangersfrom these sources. .Field procedure.  12.  With these  objectives, therefore,  Sir Crawford Douglas-Jones,  Col.  Nicholas, Mr. Bataille,  Dr.   Donovan and  SirGeoffrey Evans, left Georgetown on 18th February, 1939,  pro-ceeding  to Bartica,  at the confluence  of  the Essequibo  anciMazaruni Rivers.   On the  19th they  proceeded by  lorry  overthe Potaro Road to Garraway Stream on the Potato River,  thusoffering Col. Nicholas the opportunity to examine it.  On  the  19th Dr. Ernst,   Dr.  Dutfiie, Dr.  Rosen, and Mr.Holdridge proceeded to  Garraway Stream by  the flying  boat,a four-passenger  Ireland machine,  which had been chartered
from Mr. Arthur James Williams, who has operated in british guiana a successful hinterland air service for the past six years.  Meanwhile a large quantity of  fuel,  provisions,  and heavy equipment  had  been proceeding up  the  Essequibo River bylaunch to Apoteri.  The gold workings in the vicinity of Garraway Stream  werevisited,  soil  studies  made,  and  mosquito  larvae collected.Flights were also made to the nearby Kaieteur Falls.  On 22nd and  23rd February the entire party with its equip-ment and servants  was  flown to Apoteri,  on the RupununiRiver, near  its junction with the Essequibo.   At the same timethe Commission^ supply boat arrived.  Soil studies were madein this region and several Indian cultivations of the shiftingtype visited.  Pits were  dug  for  soil profiles.  Dr.  Donovantook a number of blood samples from the Indians to be testedlater for yellow fever immunity.  On the 24th Dr.  Ernst, Dr. Duthie, and Mr. Holdridge flewfrom Apoteri  to Annai and thence down the Cattle Trail to  apoint near  Kurupukari where it crosses the  Essequibo River,and thence back to Apoteri.  Photographs of  the  Makarapanand  Arasuka  Mountains  were  made and these,  should it benecessary,  can  be  assembled  into a  map  on  the scale  of1:250,000 by Miller&apos;s aerial plane-tabling method.  On the 25th Dr. Rosen.,  suffering from exposure, was flownout to Georgetown  for temporary  treatment.  On the 27th and 28th the Commission and its  supplies  were flown to Bon Success, a Government post  on the Takatu River,which forms the frontier between British Guiana  and Brazil.At this point there  was waiting horse, cart, and bullock trans-portation which  had been arranged by radio with the rancherson the savannahs.  Col.  Nicholas  and Dr.  Donovan proceeded  by  horse  toWichabai  and Dadanawa,  and  from this point  on formed  aseparate unit which returned to the coast via  the Cattle Trail,so that some  estimate of cost of  road  building by that routecould be made.  Since the only fertile soils, in the sense of immediate suit-ability for  permanent cultivation,^as yet reported,  seemed tobe in the Kanuku  valleys, and  the comparatively  inaccessiblePakaraima  valleys, the remainder of the party moved to thehead of the Mocu-Mocu Creek, via Manare Ranch where a typecultivation  of Savannah  soils was studied.  Mr. Bataille returned on that same day to Georgetown to con-cern himself with industrial problems.Cultivation in Kanuku Mountains.  13. In the forested valley of the Mocu-Mocu,  the existence ofa good type of  soil was confirmed.  On a  10-acre clearing  aBrazilian settler  was growing  tobacco,  maize,  bananas, and various other  fruits, all of  good quality.  Investigation of the surrounding lands gave.the impression that the soil had  been
derived from the basic rocks  of the range.  It was therefore decided to choose a large Kanuku valley and  explore it  for similar or better  soils.Survey of Kanuku &apos;Mountains.  14. The main body of the Commission now moved west andsouth around the west end of the Kanuku range while Dr.Duthie and Mr.  Holdridge took off from Bon Success in  the flying  boat for  an  aerial reconnaissance of the mountains.Flying at 4,000 feet a complete series of obliques from which a map may  be constructed, was made.   Numerous valleys ofsuitable  conformation  were observed and of these  the  gorgewhere  the  Rupununi River cuts through the Kanukus seemedmost likely, especially in view of the fact that Mr. John Melville,a prominent rancher, had a cultivation near Makaparima, deepin the gorge.   15. The  main  party reassembled  in  Wichabai,  Mr. JohnMelville&apos;s ranch.  It now included Dr. Giglioli, previously men-tioned.  Dr. Rosen came back from Georgetown and visited theManare  Ranch, the  St. Ignatius Mission, and before returning to Georgetown, made a flight over the southern savannahs  and through the Rupununi  Gorge.Soils of  Rupununi  Gorge.   16.  It was now  decided that  Sir Geoffrey  Evans and  Mr.Holdridge, forming one unit,  should  penetrate the RupununiGorge on a soil prospecting trip while the rest of the party rodeeast and then south along the margin of the forest, visiting the numerous Indian villages and from Bourisnawa (Bush Mouth)going in to Marudi  Mountain, where an isolated gold workingcommunity existed and good  soil, suitable for permanent culti-vation,  had been reported.   17.  Going north  through  the  Rupununi  Gorge,  guided byMr.  Melville,  the  Evans-Holdridge  unit  encountered nearMakaparima an  excellent type of chocolate-colored soil asso-ciated with a  characteristic  palm, Orbignya sagotii.   On  theplantation which had, owing to inaccessability,  been abandonedthree years, there were growing Gros Michel bananas, Arabiancoffee, papayas,  eddoes, pineapples, and other cultivated plants.The details are covered in the appended  agricultural report. *   This  unit of  the Commission  was informed by Mr. John Melville and others, that  this fertile red soil was of large extent and to be found in  most  of the valleys of the Kanukus and the associated  granitic mountains  which stretch across the Colony between the second and third parallels  of  north latitude.  It also seemed clear  from the  reports collected that the soil was found in the neighbourhood of diorite dykes.  Further, it seemed that the Orbignya sagotii would probably be found growing in stands on this valuable soil; this  feature offered hope of check- ing its extent by aerial reconnaissance accompanied by landings for soil samples.                       * Not printed here.
 . i8. Returning to Wichabai, Sir Geoffrey Evans and Dr. Ernstproceeded to Georgetown for conference  with the Governor ofthe Colony who was about to go on leave.Indian villages.Medical examination.  Mr.  Holdridge  rejoined the  main body,  now operating atMarudi Mountain.  This  parry,  composed  of Dr. Duthie, SirCrawford Douglas-Jones and  Dr.  Giglioli,  worked its way through the line  of Indian villages  on the  eastern side of thesavannah.   The  relatively large Indian  population  presentedDr. Giglioli with an excellent opportunity  to obtain spleen rates,blood smears,  and a general view  of  health conditions.   his report is appended.1&quot;  Dr. Duthie had collected soil samples andstudied, with Sir Crawford Douglas-Jones,  aboriginal methodsof cultivation.Marudi Mountain.  19. Through 18 miles of thick rain  forest a trail carried theparty to Marudi  Mountain.  As previous  experience  in theRupununi Gorge  suggested, as soon as the land rose well abovewet season flood level,  ant  nests of red  soil were noticed  andas the mountain was reached  the  red soil became  extensive.At  the  gold workings,  Dr.  Godfrey  Davidson  exhibited  an excellent garden  growing on a ten-acre forest clearing  for the sixth consecutive  year without visible signs of exhaustion.  Thisis a very important point because it represents permanent culti-vation as opposed to the shifting type  which exploits the landfor about two years only.  It is interesting to note  that the existence of this soil, suitablefor permanent  cultivation, at Marudi Mountain,  was a  furtherconfirmation of the reports  that it tended  to  associate  itself with the granitic formations.Climate and Soil.  20. The Commission  now had evidence of a climate, which,considered  as a  tropical  one,  may be termed  healthful,  and positive indication that  there existed, in  substantial quantities,a type of soil that would support permanent and intensive agri-cultural effort.  Col.  Nicholas&apos;  report on   transportation problems  nowbecame essential  and shared importance only with the necessityof  determining the actual  extent  of  the  fertile soils  of the&apos;.&apos; Kanuku  type.&quot;  His report  was  expected to be  availablewithin a few days since the Commission^ radio reports indicated that the Nicholas-Donovan unit was about to reach Takama, onthe Berbice River, having covered  the Cattle Trail  by horse,and that Sir Geoffrey Evans and Dr.  Ernst had proceeded tothat place by river steamer,  with the intention of picking them up and conducting  a  medical and  agricultural  survey of the               - -----    * Not printed here.
Berbice District, an important matter in view of the fact thatit. might constitute a  point of disembarkation for prospectivecolonists.  21. Those  members of the  Commission who had visitedMarudi Mountain now rode back to Manare Ranch and thenceto the Ireng River where a camp was established, Bon Successno longer being available as  a landing place for the flying boatowing  to the falling  water.                             *Aerial  survey of Upper Essequibo  and Courantyne.  22. As has been mentioned, a characteristic palm, Orbignyasagotii, was usually,  but not always, associated  with the darkred soils, and it had been  felt that this palm  could  be dis-distinguished from  the air.  With a view to determining whetheror not the &quot; Kanuku type &quot;  soils could  be located by  aerialreconnaissance  based on  recognition of the associated palm,it was decided that all the remaining members of the Commissionexcepting Dr. Duthie and Mr. Holdridge, should  be flown backto Georgetown.   These  last should proceed  to Apoteri andfrom there fly south along the Essequibo to a point  near the mouth of the Kuyuwini, over the forest to the New River,  downthis to the Courantyne, and thence down to the Courantyneto the latitude of Apoteri, whence a due west course would return the  party to that place.  Accordingly, the flying boat took out Sir Crawford Douglas-Jones, Dr.  Giglioli  and the  Commission servants, returningthe  following day to take Dr. Duthie  and Mr.  Holdridge toApoteri.  On the morning of 3rd April, this  unit took  off froni Apoteriand flying at a thousand feet, with rather poor visibility, care-fully scrutinized the  forest below with the aid of field glasses.The Cocerite  palm,   usually associated with  a  poor  qualitysandy  soil,  was easily recognized,  likewise the  manicol palmof swampy  lands.  Immediately above Sawkins Island the  first Orbignya sagotiiwere seen and identified;  a landing was made in the river.  Thepalm was found and identified as  being unquestionably thesame as the palm which had  been observed in the neighbour-hood of Makaparima, in the  Rupununi Gorge.  Another landing was made at Oronoque Fall, the  old basecamp of the Boundary Commission, and the plane then returnedto Apoteri over  the planned route. ; Further details, to  be found in the agricultural report, tendto confirm the surmise that the areas of &quot; Kanuku type  &quot; soilfollow the. granitic formations.                          ,  ,,  It is also  of interest to note that on this flight of four hours,actual flying time, not a human being was seen nor  signs ofhabitation, beyond the abandoned base camp  of the boundary commission.  Even   the  Indians  had failed  to occupy  thecountry.
North-west District visited.  23. The Duthie-Holdridge unit  was  now  flown  back toGeorgetown and the  Commission assembled.   Dr.  Rosen  had made a flight to the North-west District which confirmed thegeneral  impression that, while interesting, and capable of somedevelopment,  it may be unwise for the  prospective settlers todisperse their  energies in two separate areas.Transport Routes.  Col.  Nicholas reported on the transport  routes inspected byhim and he concludes that a motor road offers greater  flexibilitythan a railway.  His figures indicate that it would be cheaperto pierce  the  forest belt with a road from  the high point of deep water navigation  on  the Berbice River to Annai, on thesavannah, than to pierce it by prolonging the existing Bartica-Potaro  Road.   The  time  for  construction  is,  in  each  case,estimated to be the  same.  He  points  out the necessity for detailed survey and  the possibility  of improving river trans-portation  by small portage railways, to serve the road buildersand the colonists in the initial stages of  development.Health Reports.  The  health  reports  of Dr. Giglioli and  Dr. Donovan wereencouraging and confirmed the impression already obtained thatthe  climate &quot;of  the far interior  of British  Guiana is entirelysuitable for carefully planned settlement by people of Europeanorigin.Suitable land on Berbice River.  Sir Geoffrey Evans was  also able to report that lands  of fairquality  existed on the Berbice River.           GENERAL&apos;CONCLUSIONS OF COMMISSION.  24. From the facts here  recorded, and dealt with in detail inthe appended reports  of the various specialists  on the Corn-mission, it may be seen that:        (a) The climate  of the area under  consideration does not     preclude possibility of white settlement.      [b) Severe tropical diseases, at present, do not occur with     dangerous frequency or  degree of malignancy.      (c) There are  considerable  extents  of soil suitable for     immediate  permanent cultivation, and  others  capable of     subsequent improvement.      (d) Bases for  a certain  industrial development  appear     to exist.      (e) Construction of  a  transport route  presents  no insur-     mountable difficulties.      (/)  The present inhabitants of the Colony would welcome     immigration by people of European origin.
Area south 0/5&quot; North suitable for colonization..  .  In view of these fundamental facts and the extent of the terri-tory offered for examination, the Commission feels that british guiana,  south of the fifth  parallel of  north latitude,  is potentialities-tially.  suitable  for  large  scale  settlement  by  emigrants  ofEuropean  origin, but it has  important reservations  to makebefore formulating definite proposals.  It should be  emphasized that great care must be taken notto confuse the implications of the general  term: &quot;suitable for large  scale settlement &quot;  with the more particular one:  &quot; opento immediate large scale settlement &quot;.Trial  period  of  experimental colonization.  Nevertheless, the potentialities are so suggestive  that a trial period of  experimental  colonization,  survey,  and  explorationwould be  entirely justified, because  there  are a  number ofimportant  points that could be clarified only  by actual settle-ment.   Thus, it is essential to  have experimental  proof  on aconsiderable  scale that white people can perform relatively hardphysical labour in this climate.  There are substantial  reasons to believe that they can,  and the few European men in thearea strengthen the belief.  It would be  most unwise to  risk large  sums  of  money andpossibly human lives until definite proof has been  obtained.Agricultural  possibilities.  25.  In the agricultural field, permanent cultivation is almostunknown at present in the area under consideration, and figuresfor acre-yields were  unobtainable; it is therefore impossible  to calculate with any degree  of  accuracy the possible density  ofagricultural population.   Previous reference to potentialities are based on  rough estimates of  fertile  soil  extent  and yield.Further, it will be realized  that in a new area, special problemswill arise.  Experimental farms are, therefore,  an essential part of anytrial colonization.  26.  Every   consideration  of  health,   sanitation,   workingefficiency and social  well-being, indicates that the unit of settle-ment should not be the family but the village.  Isolated familiesare more difficult to  protect from tropical illnesses owing to theimpracticability of eradicating malaria over wide areas; hospital and educational facilities are more easily provided in a village.The work  of a community is more easily performed by a villageunit than  by scattered  families.Model village.   27.  Holding this view, the Commission regards it as essentialto  set up  an experimental village which  would be  developedinto a prototype on the lines of which later villages could bemodelled.
Housing material.  Related to this matter of village construction is the questionof housing material, and it may be said that materials are locallyavailable; the only absolute essential to be imported from out-side the area would be screening.  Brick of excellent quality canbe  made from local  clay,  various palms such as the Ite  andespecially the Orbignya sagotii, provide valuable  roofing.   Tosupply material one of the  first necessities of the  experimental period would be a brick factory and sawmills to provide lumberand shingles.Purchase  of assets of Rupununi Development Company.  28. Since the settlers brought in must be fed until they have achieved some degree of self-sufficiency, it would be  advisable to consider carefully the possibility of purchasing the RupununiDevelopment Company.  This purchase would ensure the  newsettlers of an ample supply  of beef about fifteen hundred tonsof it  per  annum without  depleting the herd.  It would  alsoafford training in stock farming and  provide the material  forexperiment in herd and grazing betterment.  In connection withthe acquisition of the Rupununi Development Company, a smallpacking  plant would  be  invaluable,   the  by-products  beingutilized for the manufacture of much needed fertilizer and cattlefood.Access to  sea:  corridor receiving station.  29. If the  area south of the fifth parallel is to be colonized ona large scale it must have access to the sea and, for this reason,the transport route should be included as a  &quot; corridor &quot;  inany lands made available.   At the sea end of the  corridor thereshould be a receiving and quarantine station which would consistof buildings to be occupied  temporarily by successive  groups of immigrants.  Unless industrial considerations make Bartica theseaport of the future  colony, it is probable that the neighbour-hood of Takama,  on the  Berbice River, will make the mostsuitable seaport.Experimental Settlements.  30. It is  especially  recommended that any  receiving stationbe placed at a reasonable distance from existing centers of popu-lation since  these  are also reservoirs  of malarial and otherinfections.  31. To sum up, the experimental stage should comprise:         (a) The  establishment  of  a  trial   settlement on   the     &quot; Kanuku type &quot; soil.  The introduction of mixed farming    is advised and, in connection with it, there should be experi-    ments with dairy  cattle fed on fodder  crops and kept in    restricted pastures.  This should be an important training-    center.       (b) A pastoral  trial  settlement,  in the open savannah,   , where the possibilities of  improving the present herds may ;   be explored.  It would  also be a training center. :
       (c) A trial settlement located on the savannah, adjacent    to the mouth of  a fertile valley, affording opportunity for    combined agricultural and pastoral effort as outlined in    Sir  Geoffrey  Evans&apos;  report.   This  settlement should  be    developed as a prototype village from which the  design of    others could be derived.                               .  i       (In connection with these there should be, as mentioned,    a  brick factory,  a packing plant, a saw  mill, and logging    operations.)       (d) Receiving and quarantine centers at the seaward end    of the prospective  &quot; corridor &quot; mUst be established.  This brief summary presents the bare essentials of the pre-liminary experiments  regarded as  necessary.Eventual large scale settlement.  32. Since the  ultimate  object of  these experiments is thedevelopment  of  large scale settlement, the following  steps are recommended:         (a) A preliminary soil survey to determine with accuracy    the  extent of the  &quot; Kanuku &quot; and other fertile types of    soil.       (0) A detailed  road survey for the transport route.  Since    the  experimental settlers and their  equipment  must be    brought  in  with  existing means  of  transport,  it will be    necessary:           (i) to establish a number of well planned rest camps         with suitable housing and  sanitary arrangements along         the Cattle Trail, and/or the Bartica Potaro Road.           (ii)  to survey the Essequibo River for the location         of small portage rails round the  principal rapids.           (iii)  to  train men  in boat  building and  handling.         At present, a 40-foot Diesel powered launch completes         the journey  from Rockstone on  the lower  Essequibo         to Makaparima in the Rupununi  Gorge,  in seven days         with six tons of cargo.  It is able to  do  this from late         May until the middle of  December; a  small fleet of         such  craft would be  cheap to build and effective in         maintaining  the trial settlements in  their first,  most         difficult months.       (c) To  carry  out  soil  exploration  on  the  Pakaraima    Plateau.   Unfortunately  the urgency of the matter made &apos;   it  impossible for the Commission to visit this but  it must    be remembered that, owing to its altitude (2,000-3,000 ft.)    it  may, prove suitable as  a location  for hill stations.Choice of Colonists.Numbers required.  33. The Commission  considers  that  colonists  should  be chosen from  young married, but childless couples,  and singleyoung men and women.   They should be in good health and
of sturdy physique and they should be carefully chosen witha view to  fitting their  talents to the requirements of the trialsettlements.  This, rather than making an arbitrary number and attempting to name the experimental equipment to support them.   It is considered  that approximately 3,000 to 5,000 people will be required in the first year to man the various projects.  It is further  thought that the  optimum time to  bring incolonists would  be from the end of October on  to the end ofthe dry season.   Small technical and receiving groups requiredfor the preparatory work can be brought in at  any time.Training of women.  The women should be trained in  the Indian  technology atonce, since in housekeeping, they  will  be  required to preparefood with  unfamiliar food  plants, while such matters as the spinning of cotton and the weaving of  hammocks are of basicimportance and best  learned  from the  Indians themselves.Medical supervision:  Too much emphasis cannot be placed on the need for adequatemedical supervision at every  point.    No village,  camp, ortravelling party should be  without medical service  and  theremust be discipline and  organization to permit the unquestionedapplication  of  the  best  in  modern   tropical  public  healthmeasures.  The  success or failure  of any tropical colonizationeffort depends largely  on this item.Indian population.  34. As to  the  Indians  themselves,  there is good reason tobelieve that  they will  welcome  the coming of  white settlers.Careful study, tact and intelligent co-operation  will  do muchto  eliminate  possible causes of  friction.   A basic source of friction conflict   over   lands will  hardly  arise  since  the&quot; Kanuku  type  &quot; soil  is  avoided by the Indians as  requiringtoo sustained an  effort for their type  of  shifting cultivation.The3&apos; are an intelligent and well disposed people, susceptibleof a high degree of civilization; they look forward to the comingof colonists with keen anticipation since they see  in the projectthree features highly desirable in their eyes: education, medicalattention, and a market for their labor.  35. In concluding this general summary  of the  Commission^findings, it must be pointed out that the detailed information in the appended reports and on which it is based,  were gatheredduring extensive field  work made at a particularly  favorabletime of the year that  is, the dry season.  In  the rainy seasoncertain parts of  the northern savannahs are subject to inunda-tion.   It is,  however,  the opinion of local residents and  also of one member of the Commission  who  has seen the savannahsin the height of the rainy season, that  this does  not constitute a serious drawback as  the flooding is confined to well markedareas.   ,                           ......
  36. The  Commission  enjoyed unfailing  courtesy, co-opera-tion and good will in all its contacts while in British Guiana andits work was given every assistance.  Its members feel especiallyindebted  to  the officers of  the  Colonial Government,  theranchers  of the  Rupununi,  the&apos; officials  of the Real  DaylightBalata Company,  the Jesuit Fathers of St.  Ignatius Mission,and  innumerable  other  persons impossible  to mention  herewhose kindnesses  are nevertheless  remembered and acknow-ledged.  It  will not be amiss to point out that the Commission^ ability to cover  a large area  in a comparatively short  time withoutcurtailing the scope of its investigation was due entirely to theskill,  ability and knowledge of the interior of Mr. Arthur JamesWilliams,  whose flying  boat made possible its arrival in thedistant interior in a matter of hours, and whose self-developedradio system kept its various units in contact with each other andthe coast.   The use of the plane saved the  Commission at least two months in time.  37. The Commission desires to record  its appreciation of the valuable  services  rendered by its  Secretary, Mr. DesmondHoldridge,  and  those of Mrs. Holdridge who  ably  carried outthe duties of its agent in  Georgetown and upon whom devolvedthe laborious duty  of typing  drafts of the Commission^ andthe individual reports.              EDWARD G. ERNST (Chairman).              EMILE  C. BATAILLE.              JOSEPH A.  ROSEN.              C. DOUGLAS-JONES \  Nominees  of              G.  EVANS           J  British Government.              DESMOND HOLDRIDGE (Secretary).NEW YORK.  igth April,  1939.  NOTE. Lt.-Colonel Richard U. Nicholas and  Dr. AnthonyDonovan,  members of  the  Commission,  were unable  to  be present while  the  Commission^ report  was  under considera-tion  but their reports are attached as appendices5&quot; hereto.                        SUMMARY.  The Commission is of the  opinion that, while  the  territoryoffered for settlement in British Guiana is not an ideal  place for refugees from middle  European  countries, and while  theterritory could not  be considered suitable  for immediate large-scale settlement, it undoubtedly possesses  potential possibilities   ,that would fully justify the carrying out  of  a trial settlementproject on a substantial enough scale that would make it possibleto determine whether and how these potential  possibilities  couldbe realized.* Not printed here.
                             I6;  The Commission is, of the. opinion. that in the area availablefor settlement there are:-       (a) soils suitable  for permanent  agriculture,       (b) natural resources which  make  possible a co-related    industrial development,  and       (c) climate and health conditions are of such a  nature    that settlement  by  people  of middle  European origin is    feasible.  The points to be clarified are:         (a) whether the  actual area of  the  fertile soils  in  the    Kanuku  and  other  mountain  ranges  bordering  the    savannahs  are - as  extensive as  preliminary observations    suggest,       (b) whether substantial  areas  of the savannahs  could    be developed by suitable methods for closer agricultural and    pastoral undertakings,       (c) whether a. permanent system  of agriculture could be    established  on clearings  in the  rain forest  areas by  the    adoption  of  suitable methods,       (d) whether heavy industries could be developed  based    on the  most important natural resources  existing in this    area,  particularly  forest  reserves,  water   power,  and    minerals,       (e) whether light industries could be developed on  the    basis of locally produced raw materials,       (/) whether health can be maintained in both forest and    savannah areas at a reasonable cost,       (g) whether water and  land transportation  facilities could    be improved to make the interior reasonably  accessible    at a cost not entirely out  of proportion to  the settlement    capacity of the country.  The Commission therefore recommends the following plan:         (i) A number of receiving camps and  trial settlements    to be started at the  earliest possible date involving a  popu-    lation of  3,000 to 5,000 carefully selected  young men and    women  placed at properly chosen locations.       (2) A properly equipped  technical  organization  under    competent leadership to be set up from the very beginning    to supervise and direct the activities of these trial  settle-    ments and render them all  possible technical, financial and    other assistance.       (3) Each of these groups  must  contain  a number of    people  with specialized training who would  be capable of    securing the necessary information and in order to make the    settlements  self-contained.       (4) The approximate cost  of establishing  and  maintain-    ing these trial settlements for a period of  two years, with    a population of  5,000  people,  is estimated at $3,000,000.    This is  a rough figure and is to be accepted with caution.   (17266 29) WT. 571 4280  24, 40, 60 5/39 P. ST. G. 373


</content>
</cab>
