<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/8/42 images: 238-243</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THIi PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).S secret ET.W.P.(Q)(UO)2i*-2 COPY NO..2QTH SEPTEMBER. 19kQ.WAR CABINET.EVACUATION OF GOVERNMENT DEPARTMENTSt     &apos;GREY! MOVE.Report &quot;by the Lord Privy Seal.1. At a Meeting of Ministers on the si.rb.ieet of air raid warnings held under the Chairmanship of the PrimeMinister on the 16th September. 192+0, I was xnvited to review the plans for the ^rey&apos; Move (hitherto called thebellow&apos; Move) for the evacuation of Government departments and to report to what extent this measure of dispersalwould relieve the working of the central government machine and should be adopted.     I have examined thisquestion in consultation with the First Commissioner ofWorks and representatives of the Treasury and have reachedthe following conclusions;2. It should &quot;be explained that the plans made for theTGrey&apos; Move covered some 60,000 staff engaged oh workwhich, broadly speaking, does not require that they should remain in close touch with the Headquarters of Government.In this they differ from the staff included in the fBlack*Move, amounting to some 30,000 in all, who could onlybe moved from London if it were d.ecided to transfer the seat of Government to some other place.     Approximately 30,000of the staff included in the &apos;Grey&apos; Move have already leftLondon, though recently the movement has been reduced to avery small trickle.     On the whole the experience of mostDepartments shows that even in comparison with conditionsin London before air attack began no serious loss of efficiency has resulted.     As compared with the conditions under which Departments are now working in London the staffalready evacuated enjoy considerable advantages.     Somestrain, however, has undoubtedly been imposed on those whose work requires them to maintain close touch with ministers in London, particularly where transport facilities and communications have been interrupted.3. In the earlier months of the war Departments were reluctant to leave London since there seemed, at that time,no advantage to be gained to off-set the inevitableinconvenience to the staff of moving their homes and families.     The position has now changed.     Staffs who &apos;live at any distance from their Offices are finding it extremely difficult to malce the journey to and from their homes, while working hours have been interrupted by air raid warnings.     Having regard to the modifications whichhave been made by the Treasury since the beginnning of the-1-

war in such matters as billeting allowances, removalexpenses, etc., it is most unlikely that there will heany general complaint on the part of staffs ordered toleave London.U, Further evacuation under the &apos;Grey&apos; Move willease the working of the Central Government machine ina number of ways.     It will relieve the pressure on office accommodation in Central London.     At present there isonly reserve space for about 3,000 staff and if one ofthe big Departments were knocked out the Office ofWorks would be hard put to it to find alternative accommodation.     Again it will avoid the loss of efficiency from transport difficulties and interruption of work by air raid warnings referred to above.     Moreover,if the move is to take place at all, it will be easier to secure the necessary billets if it is undertaken now.I am satisfied, thereforet that it would be of advantage to resume the movement of Departments away from london under the &apos;Grey&apos; Move wherever this is administrativelypracticable.     There would be obvious difficulty indetaching many of the Departments included in the moveas long as the Government as a Whole remains in London.For example\ the less essential branches of the service departments and of, the Ministry of Supply could probably not be detached without loss of efficiency.     It wouldhe necessary., therefore, for the Treasury to make a careful examination of the position in consultation with theDepartments concerned.     I consider, however, that this examination should be carried out in the knowledge thatit is the policy of the Government to encourage a furtherremoval of Departments from London.5. One or two subsidiary points may be mentioned.At the present time there is some pressure from certainDepartments evacuated earlier in the war to be allowedto return to London.,      It would obviously be illogicalthat Departments, some of whom have been at work in their new locations for nearly a year, should be allowed to returnat a time when the Government is anxious to lighten theship in London and secure a wider measure of dispersal.I recommend, therefore, that permission to return in suchcases should be refused unless it can be shown to be urgently necessary on grounds of efficiency.     Secondly, it shouldbe understood that no substantial changes can be made inthe location of Departments already worked out by theOffice of Works.     While some of the locations selectedmay not be ideal for their purpose they are the best available.     It has, however, been necessary to abandon the plans for the evacuation of certain Departments toBournemouth in view of the fact that the town lies in an&quot;invasion&quot; area,6, Finally it is of great importance that undesirablepublicity should not be given to the removal of Departmentsso as to give rise to a belief that the Government is engaged upon a process of withdrawal from London.     Thiswould not only have a depressing effect upon publicopinion here, but might encourage the German Air staff to believe that attacks upon London were succeeding andshould be intensified.     Since the Government&apos;s intentionswill inevitably become known it is desirable that theMinister of Information should hold a Press Conference

and explain to the newspapers that this decisionrepresents a further extension of the process already&quot;begun and amounts to no more than a thinning out of thestaff in London in order to relieve the pressure uponaccommodation there.7. To sum up, I recommend:-(a) that further transfers of staff from london under the !Grey&apos; Move should now take place.     The Treasury should be instructed to consult with departments and to arrange for such transferswherever practicable;(b) that it should be understood that departments are not to be permitted to bring staff back to London except where it can be shown to be urgently necessary on grounds of efficiencyj(c) that the arrangements for the move shout-dbe under the general supervision of theTreasury acting in consultation with theOffice of Works and the Ministry of Transport.Excepting in matters of detail the existing arrangements in regard to location of departments,etc., cannot be altered.     Freshplans must however be prepared in the case ofthose Departments who were to have gone toBournemouth;(d) that the Minister of Information shouldbe invited to explain to the Press that themoves contemplated represent no more than an extension of the process already begunof thinning out Government staffs in london in order to relieve the pressure uponac c ammodat i on.(Int&apos;d)    O.R.A.Qhmond Terrace, S.W.1,20TH SEPTEMBER, 192+0.


</content>
</cab>
