<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/31/16 images: 190-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT.:Xmiito BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND MgVSIt is requested t:uu spc tal cure may be taken 1*insure thei thereby of this documents **&quot;y?COPY No.&apos; &apos;     &apos; /W,Ma. - (49) 112TH CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE, P.-Confidential, Anneoco(13th Alignst, 1942 - 12.15 p.m. )The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the First Lord of the Admiralty (war. (42) 355 )as tothe action which should be taken in the event of theRussians losing their last bases on the West Caucasiancoast*After the FIRST ,LORD had explained the xroposals jn his paper, TH; SSGRjJTARY OP. STAT31 FOR for is; GI7 affairs read out a draft telegram to our Ambassador in Russiaon this matter, following generally.the lines of theMemorandum, including the proposal that Turkey mightpurchase two destroyers and two submarines fj.5omRussia0The main point discussed was whether we should press the Russians to allow their warships to be interned by Turkey, or to sink them in order to avoidtheir falling into German hands.    (The only other course,namely, that the Russians should try to get theirwarships out through the Straits, was felt to be toodangerous (except perhaps, as regards submarines) since it would involve a real risk of hostilities between turkey and Russia.)The general view of the War Cabinet was thatthe balance of advantage would only lie in favour ofthe warships being interned in Turkey if we could saythat the chances of Turkey surrendering the ships, orcoming into the war against us, were negligible.   it seemed very doubtful whether we could confidently assertthat this was the case*   The fact that these ships were interned in Turkish waters might in fact lead to increased German pressure on Turkey.,   The general viewof the War Cabinet was that we ought not to express a preference for internment, at least until      had heardthe views of our Ambassador in Angora0The War Cabinets-(l) Agreed that the Foreign secretary should despatch the draft telegram to Sir A. Clark Kerr, subject to modification of the passage dealingwith the internment of the warships,in the light of the discussion^

VinB&amp;ra, together with a -^r^her&apos;;, telegramoh %e&apos;rpo :..   onally, and p. , r &apos; :o : e ,i^?to  &apos; &quot;fib - 1 &apos; &quot; - , i1- &quot; - &apos;* - &apos; issinking of tfc       &apos; s^-pbo   11Sir He Khatchbull-Hugossch&quot;shovld; in-particular-,, be asked whether as stainingthat the warships were interned^Tu    :&apos; couia be relied oa tc :--e*:--:tpre     .3 to sf-^ r:/!s^ thetfio 1   .Sir iU Cla^k Kerr should be r eminded ofthe sale of the German submarine atCarthagena to the Spanish Government,,and should also be asked to consultwitf&amp;i &apos;&amp;e Pielme.- Minister.. .on:, the. wholo -&apos;. -.Grea-1^ George::S&amp;se%$ S0.Wo 1 cyril

OUTWARD TELEGRAM

[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, and should be kept under Lock and key.]

[This telegram is of particular secrecy and should be retained by the authorised recipient and not passed on].

[CYPHER] DIPLOMATIC (SECRET)

FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO MOSCOW

No. 144 D. 7.05 p.m. 13th August, 1942

13th August, 1942

Repeated to Angora No.1279

With the Compliment of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs

IMMEDIATE MOST SECRET DEDIP.

 We have been considering position of Russian Black Sea warships and merchant ships in the event of loss of Black Sea ports.

 2. Tankers. Important Russian tanker fleet would be of great value to United Nations but in view of present situation over the Second Front it may be inadvisable, to press Soviet authorities at this stage to pass their ships out into the Mediterranean. If circumstances arise where tankers are no longer of any use in Black Sea or your suppose that the Soviet Government will wish to pass any of these tankers into the Mediterranean for use in Northern waters we shall be glad to make arrangements on similar lines to those of last autumn and to give them every assistance in our power. The same of course applies to other Russian merchant vessels in the Black Sea.

 3. Operations of last year were facilitated by the discharge of oil at Istanbul (Constantinople) for the Turks. Promise of similar transfer of oil might have important effefct on Turkish attitude particularly in the case of oilers of doubtful status.

 4. Turks have not right whatever to interfere with passage of merchant ships through the Straits but Admiral kelly has reported that they may open fire on tankers that approach the Bosphorus without first removing their defensive armament. This attitude is intelligible for Fleet oilers but in the past Turks have always permitted genuine merchant ships to retain defensive equipment. Since retention of defensive armament is essential for passage through the Aegean, we would, if Russians desire, represent to Turks the right of merchant ships to retain it.

 5. Warships have nolegal right to pass through the Straits and Admiral Kelly reports that they will not be allowed to proceed even as far as the Sea of Marmora for internment without first going to Eregli to be disarmed and to pick up Turkish naval escort. Attempt by surface warships to force passage of Straits would almost certainly be resisted by Turks. Hostilities between Turkey and Russia which would probably result from such an attempt would have incalculable


incalcmiablo-consequenees greatly outweighing advantages of passing a few vessels through to safety*  Wei therefbi^ouch hopesoviet authoritieswouldm6t-^Qt6i^^te^tr&apos;&apos;^ll*o course leastlikely to lead to subseojient bonpliOatioas would &quot;be that theSoviet warships should ^ sunk in deep waters The a&amp;ternativewould he that they should he interned in -Turkish poi^untilTurkey abandons her present neutral position,  !^ss wcjiM havethe attraction of saving the fleet for^ possible use at a later date on the side of the Allies.   But there is a danger that meanwhile the presence of this fleet in Turkish ports night leadto dangerous complications between turkey and Qem^y,  There isalso the possibility that in that case the Germans night use suchpressure as to force Turkey to surrender the ships to Gcsrmany,6*   The following suggestion has however ocourred te us.We ar$ at present under obligations to deliver to Turkeytowards the end of the year two Fleet destroyers and twosiibnarines.   It is conceivable that if the Russians agreed totriBdlif^&apos;^-^:&apos;Tijb^cs either before or after internment a sufficiently attractive number of netf destroyers, submarinesor even a cruiser, the Turks might be ready to release us from our obligations,  le in turn would transfer to the Russians fortheir northern Fleet the two new destroyers and submarines atpresent destined for Turkey,  The advMtageof a sale beforeInternneht would be that the crews nijpit be saved from internmentand if necessary passed out into the mediterranean in a Russiaarie^hcalt ship to assist in manning the ships that we transfer tothe Northern Fleet, .7,  We realise that the Turks would be afraid of Germanreactions it they entered into sueh a bargain0   Bat they nightbe temtited to do so if the off er of Russian ships were,sufficiently generous and if they felt certain that the only part of the bargain that the Germans need know was the&apos; sale oftasiaa ships, to-Turkey and not the transfer to the. Bssifans ofthe ships which we are under.contract to give to the Turks,8,  I shall be glad of your views as to whether it would be advisable or necessary to raise these matters with the SovietGovernment either now or later.



</content>
</cab>
