<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/87/0 images: 52-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
)(iHia DootMssra is to twmen op his brimhic MAJgsjrg goverjmem).ReraarkB by the Seoretary to the 77ar Cabinet on Mr. 0iutbMll!8 Memorandum of the 8th April, 1919,(G.T.-7087).&quot;Let the public five the facts whatever they are&quot;.   This sentiment with which Mr. Churchill concludes his criticism on the final instalment of the $aval Official History expresses concisely the reason that induced the Historical Sub-Committee to recommend that the preparation of the present work should be undertaken.    At that time the war had been in progress for more than a year end it was already recognised that the material on which any future history could be based was so voluminous that the only method by which the great efforts of the -fla-vy could be brought home to the public was for this material to be digested., end a history prepared from it by a fully qualified naval historian.The mass of material may be gauged from the fact that the Jixst Volume of the Offioial History covering only five month:, of the war is based upon the contents of 115 volumes, each of about 1,000 po^es, consisting of papers carefully selected as bearing directly on ooerations.     In addition to this, some hundreds of deck logs and signal logs have had to be consulted.    There is no reason to suppose that this proportion of volumes will be found to have decreased as the war progressed.After Treasury sanction had been obtained the proposal was submitted to the Admiralty and on March 17th, 1916, Their lordships signified their concurrence in the desira-bility of such a naval history being written and Sir Julian Corbett being entrusted with its compilation.On June 28th, 1916, the Prime Minister made the following announcement in Parliament:-&quot;In view of the demand which is likely to arise, and the desirability of providing the public with an authentic account, it has been decided to prepare for publication as sooa. as possible after the close of the war an Interim Official History deal in,. with its various aspects.   This History will be based on the material which is being collected and arranged by the Historical Section of the Committee ox Imperial Defence for an eventual Staff history.&quot;The work will be in throe sections, which will deal, respectively,   ith the Saval and Lllitery Operations and the fcenexVl Bffeots of the V/ar on Sea-borne Trade,&quot;The Haval Section hss been entrusted to Mr. Julian Corbett,  -nd the Military section to Ur. John Ifortesoue, while for the Trade Section the,Trustees of the C&amp;rton Foundation have  indly placed their Staff at the disposal of the Historical Section.WARCABINS T.OWICIAI HAVAL HISTORY OF THE WAR.&quot;The sections will be published separately, but pre-parod in concert.    The work is already well advanced.&quot;
The question of the progress of the History was mentioned again oin the House of Oomaona on November 20th, 4918, when Mr.Bonur law, replying to a question, stated that: &quot;The Historical Section of the War babinet is not in a position to publish the early volumes of tjae popular history of the war now.    It has always been the intention, and still ia, to commence publication immediately after the conclusion of peaoe,&quot;The last mention of the history in Parliament waa on March 15th, 1919, at which tine the proofs Of the first volume v/ere in the hands of tne Admiralty.    f/n that date Dr. Maoaamara stated that: &quot;It is hoped that the first volume Of the Official Naval History of the War will appear at the end of the year.11JCt is to this end that the Historical Section has been working, and the Cabinet have been kept informed of the progress of the Hisotry from time to time.Not only in this country has a keen interest been evinced by the public in this promised work, but enquiries nave been received as regards its progreas from Australia, , ite-.. Zealand, South Africa, Canada, the United States and France;   and permission to translate it into Preach has been requested from three independent sources.  ; The final proof has been set up in type and has been transmitted to New York, where it is probably already alao set up in type.    The maps. (18 in a separate case) are now also being printed off. Considerable expense has thus bean incurred.     Its actual amount is difficult to calculate owing to the work of the staff having been largely   devoted to arranging papers for a future Staff History.,    According to a statement sent to the Treasury in JuxB , the coat to the 31st March, 1919, was estimated to be  ?,,372.    -As ohe History ft as conuenced on February 1st. 1916, this represents a period of 3 years and 2 months.^In addition to the above there must be taken into account the cost of the maps v/nich (for paper ana printing) amounts to  12 pjr IjOOO oopiea for Vol. I.    As there are 18 maps and it is intended to print 9,500 copies in the first place, this amounts to about  2,000.The cost of the first volume will therefore be about  9,500* and the subsequent volumes considerably less.fl  It is hoped to camp!ate, the History in 4 voluiaea.     The first has gone for Press, the second will probably be ready by the sULiaer of 1920&quot;, the third by the summer of 1921, and the fourth by the sumuer of 1922,At the present rate of expenditure ( 3,418 per annum) the future cost will therefore be about  11,000, that is  3,700 per   fo-lume).
On the other side of the account ia the Royalty to be paid to the Government on the sale of the book, amounting to a flat rate of over 20/&apos;iShould the present policy be reversed and the History be held up until a properly edited collection of documents can be produced a further large expenditure will be incurred (with no return), including heavy claims from the publishers. This delay and expense vrill be very difficult to justify in view of the pledges to Parliament and the fact that the book has been passed by the Admiralty and announced by the Publishers.Copies of this history in proof were circulated to&apos; the members of the Cabinet on the 12th Harch, 1919, and a copy was sent at the same time to Mr, Churchill vrhose memo-randum in criticism of it is dated the 8th April.   The question of publication has since been continuously on the weekly list of subjects to be brought before the Cabinet, and I am informed that the Acting Secretary mentioned the matter more than once to Mr,. Bonar Lavr, who finally decided that it should await the Prime Minister&apos;s return from France, It was placed on the Agenda for the first time on Friday last the 15th instant,JOn Mr, Bonar La&quot;.;1 s decision being made knovm to the Secretary of the Historical Section, this officer wrote on the 18th June to the Acting Secretary that in the cir-cumstances he must be guided by his previous instructions to produce the book as soon as possible after the conclusion of peace and that he was working for publication here and in the United States on about the 15th October,To revert to the memorandum,. I understand from Sir Julian Corbett that Lir. Churchillfs main objectionms to his original treatment of the Coronel episode.   He had sub-sequentiy tiro conversations with Mr. Churchill who went through his own printed collection of documents and pointed out to Sir Julian Corbett what he considered as being the most important telegrams and minutes,-  After the permission of the Admiralty had been obtained these were inserted and appear in the final proof.   Certain objections of fir, Churchill on less important matters have also been met.It may be mentioned that in the first place the typescript was submitted to Mr, Churchill by Sir Julian Corbett am&quot; returned to him with thanks and with a request-that he might be allowed a further opportunity of reading the proof when in print.   From this it is clear that   he had then no objection to publication.In regard to criticisms from other quarters they have been of a most laudatory character.   Several naval officers of high rank and other persons well capable of forming a judgment have pronounced on it and not one dis-cordant note has been struck,   Mr, Churchill therefore stands alone in his objections to the book in its present form.It is submitted that whether or not Mr, Churchill!s opinion is to prevail over the declared policy of the Gov-ernment must be decided now.   The agreement be twee:? the Publishers and the Stationery Office has been signed and the book, on the authority of the Treasury, has been announced to the Public and the Trade.   If a decision has to be postponed
these announcements must be withdrawn with the result that in addition to the further expense that will he incurred the sale of the book will be seriously preju-diced.   This is a point to which the Publishers from their experience attach very great importance.   Their experience is borne out by that of the Historical Section in the case of the History of the South African &quot;Jar in which the postponement of publication after announcement undoubtedly was the main cause of its unsatisfactory sale.   It was only too evident then that the holding up of the book led the public to believe that it was done for the purpose of emasculation and little further interest was taken in it.   In short they believed they were not to be allowed to know the facts.(Sgd)   K.P.A, HANKEY.2, Uhitehall Gardens, S/f., 19th August, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
