<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/87/0 images: 197-208</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET. v    - ,-47 .     .        (/   165MEMORANDUMON THEPOLITICAL QUESTIONS REACTING ON THE MILITARY SITUATION IN SOUTH RUSSIA.(I.P. 890, 20th July, 1919.)BYMaj.-General H. C. HOLMAN, O.B., C.M.O., D.S.O.,Chief of the British Military Mission to General Dehikinin South Russia.
secret.MEMOKANDUMON THEPOLITICAL QUESTIONS REACTING ON THE MILITARY SITUATION IN SOUTH RUSSIA.(I. P. 890, 20th July, 1919.)BYMaj.-General H. C. HOLMAN, C.B., C.M.G., D.S.O.,- Chief of the British Military Mission to General Denikinin South Russia,
British Military Mission,South Russia,20th July 1919.The Secretary, , Intelligence, No. IP. 890.War Office, London, S.W.I submit the following memorandum, in continuation of my No. H. 3/703, of 10 th July, on the political situation : *I.-Reaction of Political Matters on Military Situation.1. General Denikin&apos;s military objectives and the success of his operations are so dependent on political considerations that it is necessary for me to attempt to furnish such political information as will enable His Majestys Government to form an apprecia-tion of the situation. The political questions reacting on the military situation fall into seven categories-(a.) Internal questions relating to the future system of Government in Russia. (6.) Relations with the Don, Kuban, Terek and Astrakhan Cossacks who, whilepossessing their own local Governments, admit his authority as Commander-m- Chief of all armed forces in South Russia, (c.) Relations with the mountain tribes. (d.) Relations with the three Trans-Caucasian republics. . (e.) Relations with the Ukraine and Crimea. (/.) Relations with the Allied Powers. (g.) Relations with Germany.II. Three Phases of Anti-Bolshevik Struggle before Formulation of programme.2. When General Alexeiev first raised his standard against the Bolsheviks the &quot;War cry ol his followers was &quot;No separate peace and no politics.&quot; The Volunteer Army consisted of officers, students and a few Cossacks, the fighting was hard and continuous, and it was possible to avoid political divergencies.3. In the second phase, the Kuban joined Alexeiev, and the Don, while falling in with Germany&apos;s policy and accepting German aid, continued the struggle against the Bolsheviks and secretly assisted him in many ways. Political workers also came clown to join him, and others formed organizations in Petrograd, Moscow and Kiev to finance the movement and gain the support of the Allied representatives.4. A Special Council was formed in which all the usual portfolios of a Government were allotted; but its functions were little more than advisory. The-cry was still &quot; no politics.&quot; In this second phase, though General Alexeiev&apos;s Council and entourage worked at many schemes of reconstruction, no programme was formulated.5. In the.third phase, when the opening up of the Dardanelles enabled us to send him such assistance as made possible a more extended military programme, when the Don had come in under him, when the Terek had been reconquered, and when the Peace Conference began to interest itself in internal Russian affairs, General Denikin, who had succeeded General Alexeiev, still declined to publish a programme. Communication was opened up with Kiev, politicians came and went, representatives were sent to Paris, and messengers passed between General Denikin and Admiral Kolchak. The form of the future Government of Russia was the burning question, and feelings ran high, but General Denikin still endeavoured to maintain &quot; no politics &quot; as the motto of the armed forces in South Russia, though on all occasions he and all his officers proclaimed a ;&apos; united and indivisible Russia &quot; and no separation.Ill-Proclamation of Aims of Armed Forces in South Russia.6. This phase passed, and on 26th April, General Denikin and his Council issued a statement of their aims under seven heads (a.) The destruction of Bolshevik anarchy and the introduction of law and order.(6.) The establishment of a powerful, united and indivisible Russia.(c.) The convocation of a National Assembly on the lines of universal suffrage.
(d.) The decentralization of power by means of regional autonomy and liberal selfgovernment, (e.) Guarantee of full civil and religious liberty.(/.&apos;) Immediate agrarian reforms with a view to meeting the need for land of the working classes.(g.) Immediate labour legislation securing the working classes from exploitation by the Government or capital.On 12th June General Denikin made a statement placing himself under Admiral Kolchak.7. From the very beginning, the Bolsheviks, with their genius for deception, represented the old Volunteer Army as a band of reactionary officers fighting to restore an absolute monarchy. The success of this policy of misrepresentation has been largely due to the incapacity of General Denikin&apos;s advisers to state their case. Colour has also been lent to the accusation by the fact that many of the officers are convinced monarchists.We should, however, rest assured that the armed forces in Russia will make good the promises contained in the statement of their aims.IV. The Original South-Eastern Confederacy.8. The forms of regional self-government, which have so markedly influenced the. struggle against the Bolsheviks, had their, origin in the South-Eastern Confederacy. The idea of this Confederacy arose from the desires of the&apos; Cossack land and stock-owning communities of the south-east to offer resistance to the international and communistic teachings of the Bolsheviks. Self-appointed representatives of the mountain tribes and agents from Georgia and Azerbaijan attended the conferences, but the idea n-as never translated into fact. The so-called Government of the Confederacy was merely an unwieldy debating society; but all representatives of its &quot;regions&quot; professed to be actuated by the desire to re-enter the Russian State when it had been purged of Bolshevism, and was again fit for decent society.The Confederacy dissolved at the Bolshevik invasion of the Don and Kuban, neither of which territories was alone capable of making an effective resistance.V. The Inception of the Kuban Rada.9. It was the Volunteer Army which first stemmed the tide by freeing the Kuban and thus making possible the foundation of the Kuban Rada. The Rada (corruption of Rathaus) started under the aegis of General Alexeiev and his Council, and at first took the direction of its sponsors; but the professional politician and speculator soon altered its character,&apos; and it is now a thorn in the side of General Denikin (vide paragraph 42).VI. The Don and German Scheme.10. The Don opposition to Bolshevism came from those elements which had originally supported General Alexeiev, but they fell under German influence, and the Krug (Don, Astrakhan and Terek equivalent of Rada) consequently took a separatist and comparatively reactionary direction. The Germans made no secret of their plan to General Krasnov,&apos;whose election as Ataman they forced on the Krug. It was to use the Cossack territories as a bridge to Central Asia. Krasnov was to be at first a semi-independent ruler of a Greater Don, to include the Donetz Basin, parts of the Voronej and Saratov Governments and the lower Volga. Then, when Russia, was capable of negotiating again, his State, strong and well organized under German influence, producing the coal and grain vital to the consuming Centre and North and controlling the routes for the oils and minerals of the Caucasus, could dictate its own terms of federation. It is doubtful if the full scheme was ever revealed to the Krug, but the Don Cossack is a&apos; good bargainer, always with an eye to the main chance, and the prospect was dazzling.VII. The Terek Krug.11. In the Terek, matters were complicated by the fact that three-fourths of the population were mountain tribesmen whose political sense was less advanced than that(7404) A 2
of the Cossacks, with whom they were continually at feud. Both, for different reasons, fell victims in March, 1918, to the Bolsheviks, by whom the Cossack Council, which was formed at Mozdok in the end of the year, was driven out of the country.The clearing of the Terek by the Volunteer Army in January and February of 1919 again made possible the formation of the Terek Krug, which held its first sittings under the auspices of General Denikin.VIII. Astrakhan and Kalmuck Krug.12. The Astrakhan and Kalmuck Krug had a short and unfruitful career on the Volga. It fled when the Bolsheviks entered Astrakhan, and, under the acting Ataman, Prince Tundutov, played an inglorious and very minor part in the German policy. Tundutov has been dismissed, and the Krug, purged of its pro-German element, is now living in a remote village in the Kuban, confining its attention to the provisioning of the Astrakhan Corps, which has been reduced to 2,000 men.IX. Don Failure and Recovery.13. The defeat of Germany caused the withdrawal of the German forces which had been protecting the Donetz Basin and the western flank of the Don. At the same time the grand Bolshevik&apos; offensive of 3,000,000 men was widely advertised. General Krasnov had only one card to play Allied, to replace German, assistance. This he freely promised to the Cossacks, and with some justification, for the French liaison officer, who styled himself &quot; Chief of the French Mission,&quot; was free in his promises of French divisions.   .14, When ihe Bolshevik offensive, heralded as it was by intensive propaganda, of which the gist was that the workers of Great Britain and France were on the side of the Bolsheviks against the &quot; Imperialists of Krasnov&quot; commenced, the Cossacks broke and left the front. The Krug impeached Krasnov&apos;s Commander-in-Chief and Chief of Staff, young and incapable generals whose sole qualifications were ambition and subservience to Krasnov.   Krasnov resigned and withdrew to Batum.15. By 1st April nearly all the Donetz Basin and the greater part of the Don had been overrun by the Bolsheviks, and Denikins fortunes were at their lowest ebb. Bolshevik forces had pushed along the left bank of the Don, had crossed the Manich River and were threatening the sole railway connecting Ekaterinodar with the Don and Donetz Basin. The population of Rostov, consisting largely of Jews and aliens, was in a panic, and it was feared that the remaining Cossacks would throw up the sponge.16. The courage with which the few stalwarts of the Don pulled the remnants of the Don Army together was beyond all praise. General Bogayevski, the new Ataman, who had commanded a regiment in General Alexeiev&apos;s Kuban expeditions; General Sidorin, the new Don Commander-in-Chief; Kharmalov, the President of the Krug; and General Popov, President of the Council of Ministers, were the Cossacks who deserve the greatest credit; while General Kelchevski, a non-Cossack Chief of Staff, provided the military science and experience.17. The clearing of the Don of the Bolsheviks commenced with the rapid advance of the Volunteer Army in the Donetz Basin, and of the Caucasian Army towards Tsaritsin, and, on 26th June, 1919, the Don territories were free of Bolsheviks.X.-The Mountain Tribes.18. As has been said, some members of the North Caucasus mountain tribes, with no form of mandate, attended the meeting of the South-Eastern Confederacy. The remoteness and inaccessibility of these tribes saved them from being overwhelmed by the Bolsheviks, but many sections of the Central tribes acknowledged the soviet&apos;s power for a time, in order to prevent the Bolsheviks from joining the Cossacks against them. The Soviet representatives played their cards with great skill, and carried the policy of fomenting discord between the Cossacks and mountaineers to a higher pitch thanvhad ever been attempted by the worst of the Imperial administrators.19. While the Germans were luring the Don to separatism with the double object of facilitating the commercial exploitation of South Russia and penetration into Central Asia, the Turks were out for the absorption of the Muhammadan mountain tribes, not only for what they represented to the artificial irredentism of the Young Turk, but to secure their hold on the Western shores of the Caspian and consolidate the Turanian block which was to extend to the heart of Central Asia.
m20. Though the full scheme, a mixture of Pan-Turanianism and Pan-Islamism, did not suit German ideas, and, indeed, caused a breach between them and the Committee of Union and Progress, the temporary support of the mountain tribes fitted in to her plan as completing the ringing round of Alexeiev&apos;s little force, then the only steadfast upholder of Eussian unity.21. The Western tribes, the Circassians, who form an integral part of the Kuban, and the Kabardins of the Terek, were, however, loyal to&apos; the Volunteer Army, provided some of its best fighters, and never recognized the gang of adventurers who afterwards developed into the &quot; Mountain Government.&apos; When the &quot;Government&quot; moved from Vladikavkaz to TirTis, and then to Temir Khan Shura, the capital of Daghestan, they lost touch with the Central tribes, the Ossetins, the Ingushi and the Chechens, who had so far taken little interest in their schemes.22. It was not till October, 1918, that this so-called &quot;Mountain Government&quot; blossomed out into a republic-the &quot; Government of the North Caucasus Republic.&quot; Its members were never elected or representative, even of Daghestan, where it has now established itself. The self-determination of small nationalities had no place in its policy, which was swayed b;p the oil and property-owning clique headed by Chermoev, who was working for the Turkish occupation of Grozni when the Armistice upset his plans.23. On the collapse of Turkey the sole raison d&apos;etre of the &quot;Government&quot; disappeared. The political adventurers of the Central mountain tribes, feeling guilty, and thinking the British would support General Denikin all round, sent representatives to enter into negotiations with him while his troops were still only at Stavropol, and the Bolshevik North Caucasian Army still unbeaten. Representatives of the Ossetins and Chechens offered large contingents, and the Ingushi offered the whole tribe, but Denikin had to refuse the latter offer, pending investigation, as so many new blood feuds had started between them and the Terek Cossacks that unconditional acceptance would have antagonized the Cossacks.24. The prospects of forming strong partisan detachments to harry the rear and left flank of the Bolsheviks were now good. General Lovchen was nominated by General Denikin to go down and co-ordinate the action of the tribes and Terek Cossacks. The co-operation of the British Command with this Mission was asked for, but was refused on the grounds that General Thomson was directing the combined action of the Terek and North Caucasus Government against the Bolshevik army in the North-East Caucasus.&apos; 25. General Denikin was sceptical as to the possibility of co-ordinating the action of such hostile elements without the assistance of officers experienced in North Caucasian conditions and without the binding force of a Russian Command. Moreover, he was himself conducting operations against the same Bolshevik army. He asked for information as to the nature of the British activities, but no answer was received, and General Lovchen&apos;s Mission was approved of by the War Office when too late. Lacking authoritative information from the British Military Mission, General DenikhVs Staff accepted the reports of officers of the Volunteer Army to the effect that they had asked General Thomson to work only for a military alliance and not to support an artificial Government, but that he had taken a large part in promoting this Government.26. They maintain that our action deprived them of the assistance they would have obtained, bore no military fruit itself, and resulted in a new lease of life to an artificial formation which should have died a natural death on the withdrawal of Turkish support.27. Public opinion was still more incensed against us. It was unable to under-stand why, if we could not send troops to assist Denikin against the Bolsheviks in the vital area, we could spare them for Trans-Caucasia, and why, whilst using Baku as a base, we should encourage a gang of adventurers whose chief object Avas the Grozni oilfields and who had sought Turkish assistance in their schemes. As in Trans-Caucasia so in the North Caucasus they believe the motive to be oil.28. The rapid clearing of the North Caucasus by the Volunteer Army in January and February, 1919, brought the question of the mountain tribes of the Terek to a head. General Denikin appointed as Governor-General of Terek and Daghestan, General Liakhov, an unconciliatory officer of the old school. He found tnat the hereditary hostility between the Terek Cossacks and the mountaineers had been increased by the events of the last year.29. The Chechens, who have always had a grievance, Avith some foundation, at their treatment over the oilfields, had burnt the new fields at Grozni and torn up some 25 miles of the railway.   When Grozni was re-occupied by DenikhVs troops the Checkens
at once assumed a hostile attitude, gave asylum to Bolshevik Commissars and eventually attacked the Volunteer Army detachments. Letters have been discovered proving that this hostility was fomented by the &quot;Government&quot; of the North Caucasus Republic which had managed to prevent the Chechens from learning the terms of tribal self-government offered by General Denikin. The &quot;Government&quot; which should have collapsed with its Turkish sponsors was now receiving support from the anti-Russian elements of Azerbaijan and Georgia.30. Early in April, General Denikin, accompanied by Lieut.-General Sir C. Briggs, went to Grozni, where 50 elders, representatives of the majority of the Chechens, were assembled to meet them. These Chechen representatives unanimously repudiated the North Caucasus Republic and accepted General Denikin&apos;s proposals for a very complete form of tribal self-government. On the return journey the Ingushi at Nazran and the Ossetins at Beslan met General Denikin and followed the lead of the Chechens.31. Four representatives of the North Caucasus &quot;Government&quot; were at Chali during the negotiations, endeavouring to prevent a settlement, but they were treated with contempt, even by the Daghestan Cavalry, the only formed body of troops the &quot; Government&quot; had raised. This regiment refused to escort them back through Chechniya, and went over to Denikin.32. The &quot; Government&quot; melted away without accounting for the loans made to it by Georgia and Azerbaijan, and it looked as if the bubble of the North Caucasus Republic was pricked for good.The hollowness of the claims of these adventurers cannot be too strongly insisted on. It is only in Paris and London that they have ever been seriously considered. The Circassians and Kabardins have not heard of their preposterous claims to this day. The Ossetins, Ingushi and Chechens have merely been stirred up by them-not a difficult task among these lawless hill tribes-without acknowledging them in any way, Even in Daghestan they were merely a storm centre, without any form of mandate or authority.33. The success of General Denikin&apos;s liberal policy was increased by the removal of General Liakhov and the appointment of General Erdeli as Governor-General. The tribal representatives who were attempting to replace the &quot;Mountain Government&quot; which had disappeared, invited General Erdeli to Temir Khan Shura, and the new Government was formed under his auspices.34. Unfortunately, this success called forth renewed efforts on the part of those to whose interest it was to prevent the restoration of order in Cis-Caucasia under Russian, supervision. There were already many Bolshevik and Turk agents in. asylum in remote parts, of tribal territory, and Azerbaijan and Georgian agents began to stir them up.   Reports were also received of a German agency working among them.35. General Erdeli&apos;s visit to Temir Khan Shura, the formation)of a pro-Russian-Government, and the consequent occupation of the Petrovsk Derbent railway, alarmed Azerbaijan. News of this development took some time reaching Ekaterinodar, and, unfortunately, before its significance could be realized in England, orders were received to the effect that General Denikin should withdraw his troops to a line parallel to and at a distance of 5 miles from the Petrovsk Derbent railway. Owing to faulty communications, this decision was conveyed to the Azerbaijan Government, published in the Press, and communicated to General Denikin&apos;s Commander at Petrovsk before General Denikin was informed.of it. He maintained that it was impossible for him to carry it out, as it meant the abandonment of those anti-Bolshevik elements of Daghestan who had invited him in, and whom he believed to be the real representatives of the tribes.&apos;36. This lack of co-ordination among the British representatives is already having serious consequences. Similar in cause and effect to the earlier Sochi incident (mentioned in paragraph 40), it has again shaken the confidence of Russians in the straight-forwardness of our policy, and has given Azerbaijan an excuse, as the Sochi incident gave Georgia, for declining to conform to British instructions.XL-Trans-Caucasian Republics Georgia.37. From the beginning, the relations between the Volunteer Army and Georgia were most unfortunate. Georgia had committed the two unpardonable sins of declaring -her independence and of going over to Germany. This led to a policy with which there could be no compromise. Turkey was to have Batum. Therefore, to^ give Georgia a port, she must annex a portion of the Russian Black Sea Province, a simple business requiring no excuses as long as Germany was dominant in Trans-Caucasia,.
A Georgian contingent was, therefore, sent along the coast, ostensibly to operate against the Bolsheviks in the Kuban, but in reality to further their own ends. It was commanded by a Russophile General, and its help was welcomed by the Volunteer Army, but it amounted to nothing. It met with a reverse, withdrew to the coast, and occupied the Black Sea Province, with the approval of the German. Command, which here was working not only for the disintegration of Russia, but for the strengthening of the anti-Turkish elements in Trans-Caucasia. The Volunteer Army retaliated with its only weapon-an economic blockade..-8. With Germany&apos;s collapse, self-determination came into vogue in Trans-Caucasia, and Georgia was in a position to add falsified ethnographical statistics, to the possession which she had gained of a Russian province with Germany&apos;s assistance.39. The &quot; war&quot; between Georgia and Armenia caused the former to withdraw troops from the Northern part of the Black Sea Province. The Georgian troops here, who differed little from the Bolshevik Red Guards, had been systematically looting Government and private property, and had so demoralized the working population that it was necessary for General Denikin to reoccupy the country, as the Georgians withdrew, to prevent a recrudescence of Bolshevism. Without consulting the British Military Mission with General Denikin, the General Officer Commanding the British troops in Trans-Caucasia gave the Georgian Government an assurance that the Volunteer Army would not advance. General Denikin claims that it would have been impossible for him to have complied unless we had been prepared to replace the Georgian National Guards with British troops. Unfortunately, he was not informed of the promise made, with an incomplete knowledge of the circumstances, on his behalf, till some time after his advance had commenced.40. The unfortunate incident which resulted from this, lack of co-ordination had wide reaching results. Both Georgians and Russians were incensed against us, and Georgia, employing the excuse that General Denikin had failed to comply with our demands, and, in spite of our declaration that the resumption of the offensive by either side would be considered as a hostile act, deliberately attacked, the Volunteer troops.41. The differences between the Georgian Government and their National Guards on the one side, and the exponents of United Russia and the Volunteer Army on the other are irreconcilable. Very careful handling and close co-operation between the British authorities in Trans-Caucasia and the British representative with General Denikin are necessary to prevent their essential differences from seriously compromising the chances of a settlement of the many delicate questions in this inflammable region, where disorder reacts on Persia, Turkey and Central Asia and threatens India.XIII. Revival of Idea of South-Eastern Confederacy by Kuban-Separatists.42. The Kuban Separatists do not represent the mass of the Kuban Cossacks, who are thoroughly loyal to Denikin.and have no desire to separate from Russia. The Separatists are a small group of politicians in the Rada of whom some may be harmless idealists. The majority are, however, undoubtedly corrupt and actuated by ambition. The group is strongly under Ukranian influence-some of the Kuban Cossacks are of Little Russian origin and it is probable that the agitation is encouraged by Germans and Bolsheviks. It is impossible to define the creed of the Separatists, since it varies according to circumstances and opportunities. The leader of the Kuban Peace Delegation in Paris, Bych, has asked the Peace Conference to recognize the Kuban as an independent state and to admit its representative to the Peace Conference. The local leaders content themselves with making violent speeches against the Volunteer Army and especially against Denikin&apos;s Advisory Council, and discuss plans for forming a separate Kuban Army and withdrawing the Kuban troops from the front. In May, when the victorious advance of Denikin&apos;s armies was well under way, the agitation of the Separatists became particularly violent and began to seem dangerous. Practically, however, the agitation has had little effect on the staunch loyalty of the Cossacks, but it has led to a good deal of administrative friction and to endless local polemics.43. A plan was formed to assemble in Ekaterinodar a conference of Separatist enthusiasts &apos;of south-east Russia. Invitations were actually issued and a vote for expenses passed by the Rada, but the plan fell through, and, instead, a conference of Don, Kuban, and Terek Cossacks met at Rostov-on--the-l)on on 26th June, 1919, to discuss proposals for the revival of the South-Eastern Confederacy in a new form. The Kuban separatists, modifying somewhat their plan for complete independence, put
forward a scheme for forming a confederacy of the States of South Russia (Don, Kuban, Terek, Georgia, Azerbaijan, Armenia, Ukraina), which might ultimately join up with similar confederacies to be formed in other parts of Russian territory. Russia was thus to be reconstructed from che bottom upwards in the form of a big federation of small independent states, the Central or Federal Government to be composed of representatives of all these States,XIII. Conversion of South-Eastern Confederacy into Scheme for Reorganizing Denikin&apos;s Government.44. The Conference was interrupted on 28th June by the murder in obscure circumstances of the President of the Kuban Rada, Riabovol, a federalist, but not an extreme separatist like Bych. The Kuban separatists did their utmost to make political capital out of the murder, but again found the masses indifferent. During the recess the leaders of the Don and Terek Cossacks devised an alternative plan. They realized that a loose congerie of embryo so-called states would never be strong enough to conquer or to maintain itself against Bolshevism, and that to form a Southern Confederacy without consulting or co-operating with Denikin and his Advisory Council would only lead to political strife which might destroy the army.45. On 7th July Denikin, visiting Rostov after a triumphal tour of the front, was met by Kharlamov (President of the Don Krug), and by General Baskakov, of the Terek Cossacks. They declared their devotion to the idea of a United and Indivisible Russia and, while asserting the claim of the Cossack countries to regional autonomy, proposed that Denikin should reorganize his Government, that he should include representatives of the Cossacks in his-Council and that, in addition, he should form a Council of State composed of representatives of the Cossack countries and of the various-provinces that have been or will be reconquered from the Bolsheviks. Denikin expressed his entire sympathy with this idea, and declared that he could do nothing without the co-operation of the non-official world.46. The scheme proposed by Kharlamov and Baskakov is now being earnestly discussed by all the parties concerned. Kharlamov spent several days in urging its acceptance on the Kuban leaders, the majority of whom are disposed to agree, seeing that otherwise they would be completely isolated. Denikins Special Council is. suggesting slight modifications, e.g., that, in addition to territorial representatives, the Council of State should include representatives of the church, science, commerce and industry. The Cossack (or South-Eastern) Conference will resume its meetings in Ekaterinodar on 20th July, and there is every prospect that Denikin&apos;s Government will be reorganized on the general lines suggested by the Don and Terek leaders.47. The new scheme will ensure unity and flexibility, will prevent dangerous separatist intrigues after the impending move of Denikin&apos;s headquarters from Ekaterinodar to a place nearer the front, wall give a broader administrative basis, and will in every way be much better adapted to the developing military situation than the present unrepresentative, mixed, but by no means wholly inefficient Special Council.XIV. Relations with the Ukraina.- 48. With the Ukrainian Government of Skoropadsky the relations of the Volunteer Army were unfriendly, firstly, because the Ukraina was under German protection, secondly, because the Volunteer Army, fighting for a United Russia, could not admit the existence of an independent Ukrainian State. When, after the withdrawal of the Germans, Skoropadsky&apos;s Government was overthrown by the Ukrainian Socialist Directory under Vinichenko and Petlura, the latter were regarded by the. Volunteer Army as open enemies. One of the causes of the Odessa failure was the encouragement given by the French Command to the Ukrainians at the expense of the Volunteer Army.49. The Ukrainian Directory was speedily overthrown by the Bolsheviks, and what remained of Petlura&apos;s forces after the rout was driven to the borders of Galicia. The Bolsheviks restored Russian as the official language in Kiev and other centres, and suppressed Ukrainian. The Directory maintained a shadowy existence in a train, and Petlura&apos;s troops now rank in the same category as the bands of the various brigand or semi-brigand Atamans who roam over the Ukraina, raiding and looting, coalescing and disappearing, capturing towns and retiring with the booty, disorganizing the Soviet forces and establishing no order of their own.50. The idea of. an independent Ukraina now has no real basis. Among the Atamans, the only one to be seriously reckoned with is Grigoriev, formerly an officer in
(7404)Bthe Russian Army, then an Ukrainian commander, later a Bolshevik general who, after the capture of Odessa, revolted and formed an irregular army of his own now operating with varying success between the Dnieper and the Dniester. His general policy is anti-Communist, pro-Peasant Soviets, and anti-workmen. There is an Ukrainian tinge in his policy, but how far it is policy and how far it is picturesque local colour it is hard to say. Grigoriev and the Volunteer Army must soon meet,and establish at least a military modus vivendi Denikin&apos;s attitude to Ukrainian separatism is expressed in a statement he recently made in a speech at Ekaterinoslav: &quot; The stakes on Petlura, Grigoriev and Makhno are lost &quot; The question of a certain regional autonomy for the Ukraina is one that can only arise later, when the bands are dispersed and normal conditions are more or less re-established. Skoropadsky and Petlura have seriously discredited the whole Ukrainian idea.XV.-Relations with the Crimea.51, After the withdrawal of the Germans and the arrival of the French the Volunteer Army was represented in the Crimea by a small force of officers and of men of inferior quality, mostly recruited on the spot. A local Government was formed of Kadets (Krym, Knaver, Nabokov and others). Communications with Ekaterinodar were very defective, the relations between the Kadet Government, the French, the Volunteer Army and the local democracy were constantly strained and the regime was unpopular. The brief Bolshevik occupation solved the problem. The Bolsheviks committed no excesses like those which marked their first occupation, but their system of arbitrary and rigid control brought them this time thorough detestation by the mass of the population.52. The return of Denikufs troops was universally welcomed. Now the Crimean contingent is far better organized and disciplined, and has at once re-established order. There will be no repetition of the unsatisfactory experiment of a separate Crimean Government. The Crimea will at first be administered by a Military Governor, like any other province, and, in due course, the Municipal and Zemstvo Councils will be restored. The Crimea may be said to have ceased to exist as a separate political problem.XVI. Relations with the Allied Powers.53. The Turkish collapse and the opening of the Dardanelles were the first rays of light General Denikins gallant and hard-tried little Volunteer Army had received. Cut off from the outer world, with no news but what they got from German and Bolshevik sources, they were entirely ignorant of the changes which were taking place in the national sentiments of the Allied Powers. They looked on themselves as the spiritual successors of the Allied Russia, which, they claim, sacrificed its original Army to save Paris and thus lost its chance of taking an equal place with us in the final triumph. They had refused all compromise with Germany and had consequently drawn on themselves active opposition from German agents on the Don and in Trans-Caucasia. Looking on the Bolsheviks as enemies of civilization and the Allied Powers as its upholders, they had no doubt of Our active assistance against the Soviet Power.54. They believed that when the British could come to their aid all their troubles would be over. Their confidence that the Soviet; would collapse when Allied troops appeared alongside them and the Allied Powers declared regular war on the Bolsheviks was founded on a true understanding of Russian character and an accurate knowledge of the state of mind of the peasantry of South-Eastern Russia.55. Ignorant of our military situation, they could not understand why we could not spare troops to help them when we were virtually at war with the Bolsheviks in the North and in Liberia.56. Our delay in sending help, the actions of the French in the Ukraina and Crimea and of the British in Georgia, and the puzzling attitude of the Peace Conference produced intense exasperation in the minds of most of those who had been living for so long in a state of nervous tension.57. General Denikins complaint about the method of conducting the Allies&apos; relations with him,, which was telegraphed by General Briggs on 23rd February (K. 233) still holds good to some extent. He complained &quot;that he had received instructions on various1 subjects, often contradictory, from British and French Generals and Admirals, but had never had direct dealings with any Allied Government, nor had he been informed of decisions vital to his interests which were made without due consideration or enquiry.
58. General Denikin&apos;s prospects were very black before the effect of British supplies began to be felt, und this desperate state was almost universally attributed to the failure of the Allies to fulfil what they believed to be our obligations. But, when once the re-arming and re-clothing of the armed forces was sufficiently advanced, and when the tanks had come, the effect was magical.We may fairly claim that the first great success was due almost entirely to British assistance, and the gratitude of many Russians is intense ; but we cannot and must not shut our eyes to the fact that many, including the extreme Monarchists and all the Jew-owned papers, persistently belittle our efforts, endeavour to conceal the extent of of our assistance and attribute our motives to self-interest.59. They are aided in their campaign by our failure, after six months, to establish trade, banking and communication facilities, and contrast this failure with the perform-ances of the Germans, who intro ,&apos;mced order in South-East Russia, whatever they may have done elsewhere, established postal and telegraph facilities and, within a few weeks of their arrival, exchanged commercial travellers with the merchant community of Rostov, gave out contracts for raw materials and booked orders for manufactured goods.XVII. Relations with Germans.60. The survivors of the old Volunteer Army, determined to wipe out the stain of the Brest-Litovsk treaty and to refuse all compromise with Germany, have been merged in the armed forces of South Russia; and Alexeiev&apos;s small council of stalwarts has,&apos;been awallowed up by politicians of a different temper. This dilution of the old uncomprising soldiers and politicians by men who, in the dark days of 1918, accepted Germany as the only possible saviour, is a fact to be reckoned with. German agents who assisted the Don are still at large in the country, and, though Denikin can be acquitted of any complicity in the matter, many of his officers have strong sympathy for the German officers, who are going through the same trials as those which they themselves experienced.XVIII. British and German Influence in the Future.61. Our difficulties and the causes of our vacillations are not understood by Russians, and we have no organization for explaining things. Germany, on the other hand, is not neglecting this matter and is still spending money freely in propaganda of a more subtle nature than she usually employs.&apos; 62, The consequence is that public opinion, especially among the by no means negligible extreme Monarchist party and the mercantile community, is imbued with the idea that Germany is not really crushed, and that, when once the Peace Conference dissolves, she will rapidly re-establish herself and prove the strongest factor in the restoration of order in Eastern Europe.Germany, they hold, is, after all, their neighbour, and her commercial and industrial reconstruction must be hand-in-hand with theirs.63. The train of thought of those Russians who believe in Germanys rapid recovery and hope to profit by it is difficult to understand. They fail to realize that what they may receive in facilities of import of manufactured goods and export of raw materials will be more than counterbalanced by the economic exploitation that is being planned. And that, moreover, it is to Germany&apos;s interest to keep Russia weak and disunited so as to play off one jealous &quot;region&quot; against another, while it is to the benefit of the British to assist in the formation of a well-ordered State from which the infection of disorder will not spread into Asia.XIX. Form of British Representation in South-East Russla64. It is not too much to say that on the wise handling of matters here depends the peace of Asia and Eastern Europe for many years to come, while recent events in Afghanistan and Central Asia have emphasized the fact that the speedy settlement of South-East Russia is of immediate importance to the British Empire in the East. But there is no hope of a speedy settlement calculated to ensure our interests while our actions south and north of the Caucasus remain unco-ordinated.The line of action imposed on our military officers by our policy towards the Trans-Caucasian States is frequently inconsistent with that whole-hearted support of General Denikins cause which is implied by our furnishing him with arms and supplies, and which I believe to be the real policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government.   The
misunderstandings that arise from this lack of co-ordination are intensified by bad communications, and the result is an appearance of vacillation and ill-faith which our material assistance cannot wholly counteract.65. I cannot too strongly urge that His Majesty&apos;s Government should seriously reconsider this matter, and I trust that the necessity will be seen of sending to South Russia a High Commissioner with sufficient prestige and such obvious support as will ensure that the problems arising out of General Denikin&apos;s struggle against Bolshevism and endeavours to establish a United Russia may be dealt with as one whole.66. The problems that demand attention have so - wide a range both of matter and geographically that the British representative should have a very strong staff.Besides the intricate racial questions which react on our possessions in the East, the very complicated problem of food supply and distribution, industrial and commercial reconstruction and finance directly concern British prosperity. But the measures we have taken to deal with them by the appointment of two junior Consuls &apos;and by flying visits of economic reporters astonish our friends by their inadequacy.67. All these things directly affect General Denikin&apos;s operations, but to burden an under-staffed military mission with them is to court disaster, and I trust that I may be given the support of the War Office in this earnest appeal for adequate British representation.I have the honour to be, Sir,H. C. HOLMAN, Major-General, Commanding British Military Mission, South Russia.Ekaterinodar,2Qth July, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
