<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/87/0 images: 282-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document fs the Property ofHis Britannic Majesty.s Government.DEPAHT.1CTT OF AGRICULTURE AND TECHNICAL INSTRUCTION FOR IRELAND.POOD PRODUCTION SCHEMES,    IRELAND.Memorandum proparod in corncliance with Chief SecretaryfsMinuto of 17th Maroh, 1917.Vie ok   ondod 37th August, 1919.Tho following ia a brief statement on tho work of the Department during tho past wook in furtherance of increased Food Produotign in   Ireland:-LOANS FOR AGRICULTURAL IMPLEMENTS.The nurabor of applications for loans for the&apos; purchase of agricultural machinery received during the past week was 35. and tho total value of machinery ordered to dato is  53,385.TILLAGE   SECTION.Satisfactory progress was made during tho week with the chocking of declarations lodged by grcwors of cereals in connection with the Government *o guarantood prices,   Tho general crop survey for statistical purposes is also progressing, satisfactorily.PROGRESS OF FARM WORK.A markod change in weathor conditions occurred within tho past few days, hoavy rain having fallen.   There has also boon a drop in tho toaporaturo?/  The rain will have a beneficial effect on pastures and root crops, and so far has not materially affected narvosting-operations.Reports received as to the condition of the croj in most parts of the country are on tho whole satisfactory.   The cutting of grain crops is now* in full swing,   Barley and Wintor   ^ Whoat arc likely to yield well, and oat crepe are cutting rather botter than was expected, though the straw is on the short side, and on light soils the yield of grain will be below average.quality, 27/8/19.The potato crop is said to be excellent in but in many districts   the tuberb are small, and
reduced yields are antiodpated, try stealks having ripened of rather prematurely owing to the dry season. The damage to the crop from blight has been less than usual.

FARM LABOUR.

Co. Kildaro. The dispueo between farmers and their labourers "whioh had persisted in Co. Kildaro for several weeks was settled as a result of conferences between representatives of the Farmers&apos; and Labourers&apos; Unions held at the end of last week.

Co. Moath.  A preliminary conference between representatives of the Meath Branch of the Irish Farmers&apos; Union and of the Irish Transport and General Workers&apos; Union, was hold in the Department&apos;s offices on Saturday last under the Chairmanship of the Secretary of the Department, when an agreement was provisionally reached. A further conference between the parties at Navan on Monday - the secretary and Asistant Secretary   for Agriculture of tho Department being present, the former   prosiding, - resulted in a final settlement of the County Meath dispute.  The terms of settlement covered the items of wages, hours of work per work, overtime payment and harvest bonus.

F L A X.

The fine weather has come to an end and rain is supplying the necessary water for flax rotting.   Even prior to the break in the weather, it was difficult to induce farmers to save flax seed. This difficulty was, in a large measure, due to the prejudice created in the minds of farmers through unsuccessful seed saving operations in the past two seasons occasioned by extremely unfavourable weather.

Reports from a number of districts indicate that the crop is bulking better than was expected prior to pulling time. No labour difficulties have been reported in connection with the harvesting of the crop.

In many quarters flax growers express discontent with tho prices for flax fixed by tho Flax Control Board.

MAINTENANCE OF LIVE STOCK.

During the period from 19th to 25th instant, inclusive, applications for licences were received as follows: -

To slaughter or export helfors 235

To slaughter bulls or bullocks 49

To slaughter veal calves 18.

</content>
</cab>
