<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/12/21 images: 340-349</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO IBB ESUFT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toillunST SECRET.OPERATION&quot;RUPERT&quot;.(previous reference sW.M.(40) 88thConclusions,Minute 5.)detailed plans. -lans to denyhe Germansalivare.W*M. (40) 89th CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE. 3.Confidential Annex^ -(12th April, 1940.)THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said that admiral of the Fleet Lord Cork and Orrery,who would be incharge of the Naval side of the operation,would be sailingin H.M.Sa AURORA from the Forth at Noon that day0   At thesame time H.M.S. SOUTHAMPTON, with General Mackesy and350 troops on board, would sail, together with two destroyers, from scapa for Vaags Fgordjj north of Narvik...The sailing of the SOUTHAMPTON had been postponed fromthe previous day after local consultations between the admiral and the General.   The four battalions which would,form the first part of the force to land, would followclosely.    It was hoped to get ashore and make touch withthe Norwegian troops in the neighbourhood of Narvik..  A.base for Naval operations would also be established, andfor this purpose oilers and net layers and a mine layer we^ebeing senteTHE PRIME MINISTER asked whether consideration had been given to the question of the immediate steps which should be taken, once we had secured Narvik, toprevent the Germans from forestalling us at Galivare,   Wereplans ready for the s&amp;ljbtage of the orefields, if thisbecame necessary?THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF saidthat full plans for the destruction of the oref ields hadbeen made, and that the officer and men charged with this

\German Troop-carryingAircraft.Action toconsolidateNorwegianResistance.particular operation were included in the Narvikexpedition..     The only restriction was that, under present arrangements, this personnel was debarred fromcrossing the border into Sweden without the sanction of the War Cabinet.THE SECRETARY OP STATE POR FOREIGN AFFAIRShoped that by the time that the War Cabinet were called upon to give this permission we should be ableto count on Swedish co-operation;   and that curpolicy should be directed towards that end*THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER asked whatsignificance attached to the reports of German troop^carrying aircraft going to Norway.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF saidthat these could supply valuable reinforcements oftechnicians and material, and pointed to the successfuluse which had been made of troop-carriers by general franco in transporting forces from MoroccooThere was general agreement that thisemphasised still further the importance of our securingNarvik as quickly as possible.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said thatwe had considerable naval forces, which should besufficient to prevent any German reinforcement of narvik by sea.Continuing, the First Lord said that themost important need at the present time was to get into touch with the Norwegians in every possible wayso as to encourage them in their fight, to urge themto hem the Germans in, to break up the communications,

and to tell them that we were coming quickly to their assistance.     The First Lord suggested that broadcaststo this effect should be put out in Norwegian, and thatattempts should be made to get individuals from theNorwegian Colony in England put ashore at various points to give the people encouragement and information,and to prepare channels of communication.     TheNorwegian Minister in London should be consulted as tothe best method of setting this action on foot.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that broadcasts in Norwegian were already being put out, but he would take immediate steps to see thatmaterial on the lines suggested by the First Lord was included.     He would also consult the norweigen minister without delay with regard to the First Lord&apos;sother suggestions.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY said that theNaval Staff were anxious to see Namsos occupied assoon as possible.     The possibility of doing this wasbeing studied but it was not thought right to interruptin any way the progress of operations against Narvik.-    THE PRIME MINISTER said that he also had intended to suggest that we should put a force ashoreat Namsos.     The Swedes were emphasising the vitalimportance of recapturing Trondhjem, which was the keyto the communications into Norway and Sweden, and it looked as if Namsos might be a useful jumping off place.THE FIRST LORD OF THE ADMIRALTY agreed, but said that the recapture of Trondhjem was an operation the difficulty of which should not be underrated.    TheGermans would no doubt soon be able to reinforce the place

from Oslo.     However, if we could recapture Narvikrapidly, then it might he possible to make use of the chasseurs Alpins against Trondhjjem.     We had as yet no information of what troops the Germans had at Trondhjem.Need for The need for information about the situation throughoutInformationfrom Norway.        Norway was vital, and reinforced the necessity for making touch with the Norwegians.The War Cabinet:-(a) Took note of the progress in the preparations for Operation &quot;RUPERT&quot;.(b) Invited the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to consult theNorwegian Minister in London witha view to -(i) The broadcasting in Norwegianof material on the lines suggested by the First Lord ofthe Admiralty;(ii) Arranging, if possible, forNorwegians now in this countryto be landed at various placeson the Norwegian coast toestablish connection withNorwegian forces, and toencourage the population inresistance to the Germans.(c) Agreed that it was important tosecure a footing at Namsos as soonas possible and took note that this possibility was being studiedurgently by the Staffs.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1.




</content>
</cab>
