<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/90A/0 images: 159-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUi-lSKT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVSRN:/IENT).g E C R E T. COPY NO.CABINET      45    (57).iMeeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10, downing street,  S. W. 1., on WEDNESDAY,  24th. NOVEMBER,  1957,at 11.0 a. m.AGENDA.1.     FOREIGN AFFAIRS.(a) Germany   -    (if required).(Reference Cabinet 40 (57) Conclusion 5.)(b) Spain   -    (if required).(Reference Cabinet 42 (57) Conclusion 2.)(c) The Far East:    Japan and China   -    (if required).(Reference Cabinet 52 (57) Conclusions 5 and 4. )2.    THE MEDITERRANEAN AND THE MIDDLE EAST ( INCLUDING EGYPT).(Reference Cabinet 40 (57) Conclusion 6. )Memorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.C. P.  283 (57)    -   circulated herewith.5.    PALESTINE:    GOVERNMENT POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 42 (57) Conclusion 5.)Memorandum by the Secretary cf State for the Colonies.CP. 269 (57)    -   already circulated.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.CP. 281 (57)    -   circulated herewith.4&apos;    PENAL LAW REFORM.(Reference Cabinet 58 (57) Conclusion 8(e).)Memorandum by the Home Secretary.Co P. 282 (57)    -   circulated herewith.
5.    AGRICULTURAL POLICY:    LEVY SUBSIDIES FOR agricultural products.(Reference Cabinet 42 (37) Conclusion 8. )Memorandum &quot;by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriescovering Report by Inter-Departmental Committee.CcP.  268 (37)    -    already circulated.Report of Cabinet Jommittee,CP.  275 (37)    -    already circulated.6.    WELSH CHURCH PROPERTY:    PROPOSED BILL FOR ADJUSTJEiNT of university COLLEGE SHARES,(Reference Cabinet 36 (37) Conclusion 11 and Appendix.)Memorandum by the President of the Board of Education.CP.  278 (37)    -   circulated herewith.7.    CONJLUSIONS OF HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.15th Conclusions (37) of Committee of Home Affairs -to be circulated^(a) Patents etc._(international Conventions) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 41 (37) Conclusion 9.)Memorandum by the President of the Boardof Trade,  covering draft Bill.Ho A. 50 (37) - circulated herewith(b) Conveyancing Amendment (Scotland) Bill.(Reference Cabinet 42 (37) Conclusion 11.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State forScotland,  covering draft Bill.Ho A.  52 (37)    -   circulated herewith.(e) Public Works Loans (jc.  2) Bill.Memorandum by the Financial Secretary to theTreasury,  cjvering draft Bill.H. A. 51 (37)    -   circulated herewith.8.    PRIVATE MEMBERS;  BILLS.For Friday,  3rd. December, 1957.(a) Local Authorities (Hours of Employment inconnection with Hospitals and Institutions)Bill.      Second Reading.    (Mr. Roberts (La.)).(L) Secretary of State for Wales, and Monmouthshire.Bill.    Second Reading.    (Mr.  Clement Davies (LN)).(c) Dogs&apos; Act (1871) Amendment Bill.    Second Reading.(Sir Robert Gower (U)).(Reference Cabinet 9 (37) Conclusion 17. )-2-
TO TAKE NOTE OP :-9.     COMMITTEE OF IMPERIAL DEFENCE;    PROPOSED REORGANISATION.(Reference Cabinet 11 (36) Conclusion 11. )Note &quot;by the Minister for Co-ordinpti-sn ef Defence,covering extract from draft Minutes of 301st Meetingof the Committee of imperial Defence, together withMemorandum by the Minister for Co-ordination ofDefence.CP. 284 (37)    -   circulated herewith.(Signed) M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1.19th. November, 1937.
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT)rj^C RET. COPY NO.CABINET    4.5   (57).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10,  Downing Street,  S.W.1.,  on WEDNESDAY,the 24th November, 1937,  at 11.0 a-m.PRESENT:The Right Hon. NevillePrime Minister.The Right Hon.Sir John Simon, G. C.S.I.,G. C.V. 0. ,  O.B.E. ,  K. C t M. P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.The Viscount Hailsham,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.Anthony Eden, M. C,  M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Malcolm MacDonald, M.P.,Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.The Right Hon.W.  Ormsby Gore, M.P.,Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Hight Hon.A. Duff Coope-, D.3.0. , M..P. *First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.The Viscount Swinton, G.B.E.,M.C., Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.Oliver Stanley, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade.-The Right Hon.The Earl Stanhope, K, G. ,D. S.O. , M. C. , President ofthe Board of Education.The Right Hon.Ernest Brown, M.C., M.P. ,Minister of Labour.mberlain, M. P.,(in the Chair).The Right Hon.The Viscount Halifax, K. G.G. C.S. I. ,  G. C.I.E, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt.,G. C.S.I.,  G. 3.E. ,  CM. G. .M.P., Secretary of Statefor Home Affairs.The Right Hon.The Earl De La Warr,Lord Privy Seal.The Most Hon.The Marquess of Zetland,G. C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Secretaryof State for India-The Right Hon-Sir Thomas Inskip, C3..E*,K.C., M.P., Minister for.Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon.L.  Hore-Belisha, M,P, ,Secretary of State&apos;for War.The Right Hon.Walter Elliot, M.0., M,P.,Secretary of State for-Scotland.The Right Hon.W. S. Morrison-.. M.Q-* ICC,M.P. * Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries..The Right Hon.Sir Kingsley Wood, MvP.,Minister of Health.The Right HornE.L. Burgin, MvPv,Minister of Transport.onel Sir M.P.A.  Hankey, G. C. B. , G. CM. G. , G-CvV.0.    ...    Secretary,
mf^S PAR EAST. 1.   The Prime Minister raised, as a matter ofSupply 0*&quot; Arms urgency, a question whether a British firm should beto Japan.allowed, to export to Japan a consignment of 200 machine-(pyevious guns designed for mounting in aircraft.   A. &quot;special reference:Cabinet 42       Licence&quot; authorising the export of these goods to Japan(37), Con-clusion 3*)     was issued to the firm in question on the 12th February,1937.   Half the price had. already been paid.   2^ of thema.chine-guns were due to leave this  country today,&apos; and.future instalments were due for despatch monthly inparcels of c0 at a time.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointedout that trouble might arise in Parliament, particularly if, as the war in China proceeded, women and. childrenor even British subjects we^e the victims of machine-gunsfired, from aeroplanes .The Cabinet were informed, that the licence for the exportation of these machine-guns had. been given lastFebruary, whai  the circumstances were entirely different from today.   The &quot;Special Licence&quot; was valid for an indefinite period and was only revocable if the Board ofTrade deemed that revocation was necessary either&quot;(a)  in the interests of Imperial security: or (b)  inconsequence of any international agreement to which H.M.Government are or may become a party&quot;.   Neither of theseconditions was fulfilled in the present instance.   no case could be made out for stopping them on the groundthat they were required for our own use.    If the contractwas allowed to proceed, it would not enable the japanese to obtain further guns without securing a fresh licence,which it would, be possible to refuse.   Under the pro-visions of the Japanese Trade mreaty the Government had.no power to put an embargo on the arms except for thepurposes mentioned.   The Cabinet were reminded also thatif an embarge was placed on these guns it would, be likely
to increase&quot;our difficulties at Hone x&apos;ong in -connectionwith the export of war material to China.The Cabinet agreed  That there should be no interferencewith the consignment of 200 machine-guns and that the firm in question should be allowed to ship them to japan.
CABTNE&quot;1 PRO- 2. The Prime Minister said that it had come to hisOEDTJRE.knowledge that a very secret document of the Committeeof Imperial Defence, which had not yet been circulatedto the Cabinet, had been seen by certain Parliamentary/Previous Private Secretaries and discussed by them.    There was reference:Cabinet 35     something to be said for Parliamentary Private Seere-(34), Con-clusion 4.)    taries seeing certain official Papers, but this shouldFK.u-5&quot;^37)i3. not ?.ppiy to the most secret, documents.   It was not avery long step from their discussion by ParliamentaryPrivate Secretaries among themselves to their discussionwith outsiders.   He hoped, therefore, that his colleagues would arrange that Parliamentary Private Secretariesshould, not see documents of the Cabinet or the Committeeof Imperial Defence, and that those documents which weremarked  &quot;To be kept under Lock and. ^ey&quot; would be shownonly at their discretion to Junior Ministers and totheir responsible expert Service advisers.   He had instructed the Secretary to the Cabinet to considerthe present arrangements regarding the circulation etcof specially secret Papers, namely, those subjected towhat was known as  &quot;Lock and Key&quot; treatment&quot;, so as toensure that in future all Papers of a specially secretcharacter should be brought, under that procedure.In order that the matter might not be lost sicht ofin the future, he proposed himself to circulate a. note to members of the Cabinet, the substance of which wouldbe incorporated in the next edition of the Memorandum on cabinet Procedure which is circulated periodically to members of the Cabinet.
fcMANY.jjie lord presidents Visit.fjonsultationsgth the Frenchpprmnent.[(previous reference:Cabinet 40 (37)IQonclusion 5.)3.     The Lord President of the Councilgave the Cabinet an account of what had passedduring his recent visit to Germany as well as his general impressions of the attitude of theGerman Government.The subject was then discussed by theCabinet.Towards the end of the discussion, theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs statedthat, on the previous day, he had received a personal telegram from His Majesty&apos;s ambassador in Paris intimating that the French President ofthe Council would like to see the Prime minister before the visit of hio Foreign Minister(M. Delbos) to certain countries in Eastern Europe.It had now been arranged that M. Chautemps andM. DelbOs should visit London on Monday andTuesday next, the 29th and 30th November.The Prime Minister said that M. Chau temps *proposal had been very opportune as clearly thefirst step resulting from Lord Halifax&apos; visit wouldbe to compare notes with the French Government.He expressed warm appreciation of Lord Halifax&apos;efforts.The Cabinet approved the followingAnswers to be given by the PrimeMinister in Parliament the same afternoon:Question:   To ask the Prime Minister, ifhe is in a position to makeany statement regarding the conversations which havetaken place between lord halifax and Herr Hitler, andother representatives of theGerman Government.Answer:       As my right hon. Friend theChancellor of the Exchequerinformed the House onNovember 12th, the visit ofthe Lord President of the
Council was entirely private andunofficial.      It had, however, asthe House is aware, &quot;been arranged that Lord Halifax should see herr hitler, which he accordingly didon November 19th at Berchtesgaden,being accompanied by Baron VonNeurath, the German Foreign Minister.During his visit,  the Lord presidentalso had the opportunity of ms etingGeneral Goering, Dr. Goebbels andother prominent leaders in Germany.These conversations were of a confidential character, and theHouse will not, I am sure, expectme to make any further statement inregard to them at this stage.      I am satisfied, however,  that the visithas been valuable in furthering thedesire, which I believe to be generally felt in both countries;, forthe establishment of closer mutual understanding.Question;    To ask the prime Minister, whetherthe French Prime Minister and minister for Foreign Affairs areshortly to pay a visit to thiscountry..Answer:       Yes Sir.     The French Prime Ministerand Minister for Foreign Affairshave accepted an invitation fromHis Majesty&apos;s Government to visitLondon on November 29th and 30thfor an exchange of views on theinternational situation with myself and my right hon. Friend theSecretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Note: A summary of the Lord President of theCouncil1 s statement   and   the main points arising out of the discussion is on record in the Secretary&apos;s file of the Cabinet Conclusions.
TO BE KEPT UNDER  LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to 1S5ensure the secrecy of this document.CABINET    43(57)SUMMARY OP THE DISCUSSION REFERRED TO IN the note AT THE END OF CONCLUSION 5 OF THE CABINET.The Lord President of the Council gave theCabinet an account of what had passed during his recent visit to Germany,  as well as his general impressions ofthe attitude of the German Government.Only the principal points are summarised below.His impressions were subject to the considerationsthat his visit was very brief, that he might have beendeceived,  or his judgment might have been at fault,  orthe German attitude might change.He had seen Herr Hitler, Baron von Neurath,General Goering, General Goebbels, Dr Schacht,  andGeneral 31omberg.He had encountered friendliness and a desire for good relations.They had agreed that there was no more desireto separate France and ourselves than to upset the berlin-Rome Axis.Our re-armament had been of assistance.General Goering, with Herr Hitler&apos;s approval, had said that &quot;Even with the colonial question in the fieldhe could see no circumstances in which the two countries would fight&quot;, and General Bloraberg had said that good relations between Germany and the United Kingdom were theonly thing that mattered.      Italy and France were secondary.He had been warmly received by the generalcrowds:      for instance,  at the Hunting Exhibition.With all those mentioned he had discussed theproblems of Central Europe, Austria. Czecho-Slovakia andDanzig.      Herr Hitler had expressed satisfaction withthe Austro-German Agreement of July last.      Of Czecho-Slovakia he had said &quot;She only needed to treat the Germansliving within her borders well and they would be entirelyhappy&quot;.^nsT SECRET.BRMANYhe Lordres^-ent&apos; sisit.onsulta-ions with the Frenchovernment.previous reference:cabinet 40(37)conclusion 5. )
Herr Hitler had strongly criticised widespreadtalk of an imminent catastrophe and did not consider thatthe world was in a dangerous state.     Herr Goering had said that not one drop of German &quot;blood would, he spilt inEurope unless it was forced on them.Lord Halifax&apos;s general conclusion, therefore, wasthat the Germans had no policy of immediate adventure.They were too busy building up their country, which was still in a state of revolution.     Nevertheless he v/ouldexpect a beaver-like persistence in pressing their aims in central Europe, but not in a form to give others cause - orprobably occasion - to interfere.As to the League of Nations, Herr Hitler regarded the present system and conception as unworkable and unreal.To a direct question he had replied that the matter was not one to which any answer could at present be given.      ButGermany would not join the League as at present constitutedand functioning.     Baron von Neurath had thought the Leagueuseful for social questions,  labour matters and as ameeting-place where Foreign Secretaries could get to knowone another.On the question of disarmament Herr Hitler saidthat &quot;we had missed every bus with his label on&quot;.      Hehad indicated the possibility of an abolition of bombing-aeroplanes, which, he said, had previously been rejected by the Colonial Powers, who wanted the right to bomb natives.Lord Halifax thought,  therefore,  that the basis ofan understanding might not be too difficult as regardsCentral and Eastern Europe, and that the question of theLeague could be discussed.     Was it possible, however, herr hitler had asked, to reach an understanding about colonies,on which British opinion, as Lord Halifax had emphasised,was most sensitive?     Herr Hitler had said &quot;If agreement could be reached it would be most satisfactory.      In the
contrary event he could only take note of the fact with regret&quot;.      General Goering, as he had said, had intimated that, even with the colonial issue in the field, war wasinconceivable.He concluded with a description of thepersonalities of the principal people he had met.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, whohad read not only the Lord President&apos;s report but alsothe notes of the German Interpreter, expressed great satisfaction with the way the Lord President had dealt v/itheach point in his conversations with the Chancellor.     his first main impression was that the question of coloniesloomed larger than before in the minds of the Germans.They were anxious to improve relations, but made quite clear that colonies must be dealt with.      They had suggestedthat their policy in Eastern Europe would not give rise to difficulties for other nations, but had given no indication of any quid pro quo for any colonial concession.      Germanyclearly did not now wish to connect Central Europe withthe Colonial question.      It was important to realise this for if the Cabinet&apos;s attitude was, as his was, thatColonial concessions could only be contemplated in returnfor a general settlement, this was clearly not Germany&apos;view.     He did not say that on this account the attempt should not be made, but the difficulties should be realised.The Lord President agreed that the Germans hadnot suggested a quid pro quo but neither had they given any impression of bargaining Central Europe against a colonial settlement, as some British newspapers had suggested.      Herr Hitler himself, however, had suggestedan advance towards disarmament by the possible abolitionof bombing aeroplanes - he had overlooked this jioint in hisown note, but it was included in the Interpreters notes.The idea of abolishing bombing aeroplanesinterested the Cabinet.      It was suggested that it might.- 3 -
have    the result of enabling the German   Army to dominateEurope, particularly if the risk of war with the UnitedKingdom was eliminated.      It would, however, have theadvantage of removing the risk of a knock-out blow atthe outset of a war.The Prime Minister recalled that the object ofthe visit had been not to reach an agreement but to make contact and to bring back to the Cabinet an impression ofthe German outlook and the possibilities of a settlement.He was satisfied that those objects had been achieved, andhe was extremely grateful to the Lord President forcarrying out so difficult and exhausting a task.      Heread a telegram from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Berlin(No.  296 of the 23rd November) which showed how valuablethe effect of the visit had been in Germany.      His ownfirst impression was similar to that of the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, namely, as to the importance inthe minds of the Germans of the question of colonies,though he also had noted that they had not suggestedanything in return to set against any concession that mightbe made.      For his part he would not make any offer in thecolonial field except as a factor in a general settlement.The difficulty was to find what contribution the germans could make.      That would depend upon the degree ofconviction we felt as to their good faith.     We shouldhave to obtain some satisfactory assurance that they didnot mean to use force in Eastern Europe.      There would be nothing to prevent the Germans from continuing what lord halifax had called their &quot;beaver-like activities&quot;, but hewould regard that as less harmful than (say) a militaryinvasion of Austria.     As to a colonial settlement, we now had some idea of the minds of the Germans.      It wasinteresting to note that they did not propose to fight for colonies, at any rate for some time to come.      The speech
which Herr Hitler had made at Augsburg immediately afterLord Halifax&apos;s visit seemed to suggest that they expectedto have to repeat their demand for colonies for six years.This country did not stand alone in this matter.     Forexample,  in the case of the Carneroons and Togoland, Francev/as equally concerned.      The first step, therefore, was tomake contact v/ith the French Government.Returning to  the question of a quid pro quo for colonies, he said t2iat it ought to include not only central europe but also some agreement on the League of Nations andon armaments, to which latter he attached special importance as they threatened to crush all the nations.      He could see little hope in any undertaking not to bomb fromaeroplanes.      That would be no more reliable than the GasProtocol, which had not saved nations from the cost of anti-gas preparations.      An agreement not to constructbombing aeroplanes, however, was a different proposition,since the tendency v/as increasing for a differentiation ofthe bomber type.      The most hopeful prospect,  therefore, fordisarmament was in a qualitative rather than a quantitativedirection;    that is to say,  some limitation of the size and power of weapons such as guns,  tanks or aeroplanes,following the precedent of the Naval Treaty of 1956.      Thatmight save a great deal of expenditure.As to the League, he took the same view as herr hitler.     At present it was largely a sham, owing moreparticularly to the idea that it could impose its views by force.     As long as the League had attached to it powers that it could not use it wou.ld be of little value.      Ifreformed it might become a great moral force, and thoughthe United States of America might not be willing to join the League, their attitude towards it would become much morebenevolent.
He thought it would be premature to initiate an examination, even by the Cabinet, of the colonial question at this moment.      That would come later.      For the present-the first step was a discussion with the French Government.The Cabinet were reminded of the leakage whichwas an invariable accompaniment of conversations with french Ministers.      Cn the whole, however, it was thoughtthat this was a risk which would have to be taken and thatno great harm need result.The Lord President of the Council asked that theutmost care should be observed not to give any impression that a bargain was to be struck between some concessionby Germany in Eastern Europe in return for a colonialsettlement.      Herr Hitler had made a great point of basinghis colonial claims on grounds of equity.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed his colleagues that on the previous day he hadIreceived a telegram from His Majesty1s Ambassador in Paristo the effect that the French Prime Minister wanted to meetthe Prime Minister before the departure of his ForeignMinister (M. Delbos) on a visit to Eastern Europe.      Thefirst suggestion had been that the Prime Minister should visitParis, but M. Chautemps had now accepted to visit london with his Foreign Minister (M. Delbos) on Monday and Tuesdaynext, November 29th and 30th.November 24th, 1937.
SPAIN.f previous reference:rabinet 41,%7), Con-elusion 3 .)Examinationof british ships ..(previous reference:Cabinet 29(37),  Con-elusion 4.)4. The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs said that he had no matter to raise for decision inconnection with Spain.   The French General Staff were reported to hol^ the view that the war might last anothersix or eight months.The First Lord of the Admiralty raised the questionof the right of the Spanish Insurgents to stop british ships .   When the matter had been examined last Septem-her the Admiralty had. thought it advisable to accordthis right, which had been granted to Japan, to theSpanish Insurgents:    but the moment had been deemed,inopportune and. to be likely to convey the impression of yielding to force.   At the present time Spanishships were masquerading as British ships, and, there wasa. ranger that the Insurgent, forces might -&amp;tuo and a ear eha British ship^ causing an &quot;incident&apos;&apos;.    The admiralty would like to give them permission to stop British ships.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pointedout that the boarding of British ships would be unpopularand difficult to defend in Parliament.    No &quot;incident&apos;had yet arisen, and the Spanish Insurgents had not --^^^- ^raised, the issue.   He had suggested to the Admiraltythat the National Flag might be painted on the hulls o^our ships.The First Lord pointed out that this would be ofno value as other ships could counterfeit the Flag aswell as the other features of our ships.The President of the Board of Trade thought thatthe painting of the Flag on *he hulls would be an addeddanger.    He agreed wiih the Admiralty that the right ofverification might lead to greater safety, but in view^ the pledges that the Spanish Insurgents had givennot to attack British ships, he thought no action wasnecessary at the moment.
The Cabinet agreed. -That at the moment the proposal of theFirst Lord of the Admiralty to accord to the Spanish Insurgents the right to stop British ships for verificationcould not be enterts.ined , but that thisdecision should not be Irrevocable if circumstances should change.
5.       The Secretary or State for ForeignAffairs reported that the situation in the Far east was deteriorating, particularly from the point ofview of British interests.     He instanced the trouble that had arisen in the Chinese MaritimeCustoms.     Difficulties in this respect had arisenfirst at Tientsin and, though those had beensurmounted, they had now arisen in a more acuteform at Shanghai, where the Japanese had seizedall the customs vessels.      The Governments of theUnited Kingdom, the United States of America andFrance had protested but the difficulty had now arisen as to what was to be done with the proceeds of the customs.     The amounts were only just sufficient to pay the interest on guaranteedloans       Instructions had been sent to our representatives to try and get the receipts paid into a neutral bank, but the Japanese would probablyinsist on their being paid into a Japanese bank.The Chinese would not agree to this, but we should probably have no alternative but to accepts     Theresult was that the Japanese were, in effect,taking cur property but we had not the focce to resist.     He thought the time might come when weshould have to approach the United States Governmentand ask if they would send ships to the Far Eastif we would do the same.The Prime Minister said it was clear thatwe could not put forceful pressure on the Japanesewithout co-operation of the United States and, while he had no objection   to the Foreign Secretary making an approach, he felt sure that  the reply would bethat American interests were not -sufficient tojustify the despatch of ships and that Ameri-cajipublic opinion was not much- concerned.- 8 -
THB PAR EAST.The BrusselsConference.(previous inference.Cabinet 42 (37)Conclusion 4,)6.v     The Secretary of State for DominionAffairs made a report to the Cabinet on the line6 ofhis telegrams from Brussels Nos, 80, 81, 82 and83 (Saving) of the 22nd November (Appendix).    Insumming up, he regretted to report that the resultsof the Conference had been somewhat inglorious butthere were at least some compensating features,more particularly the following:-(l)   Cordial relations and complete co-operation with the delegation of theUnited States of America had been andwas still being maintained:(2)    The Dominions delegates had kept instep with the United Kingdom delegatesthroughout:(3)    The door had been kept open for somepossible future initiative by the UnitedStates and ourselves with a view to securing peace.The Prime Minister; with the generalconcurrence of his colleagues,expressed the view thata very difficult situation had been handled effectively.The main lesson to be drawn was the difficulty ofpecuring effective co-operation from the United Statesof America.- 9 -
Iq3 medtter-lAN^an andKit? middleias? &apos; in-M/JDING(previous reference:Cabinet 40(37), Con-elusion 6.)&quot;    5&quot;.7.    The Cabinet had before them a. Memorandum by theMinister for Co-ordination of Defence (CP.-283 (37))on the situation in the Mediterranean and Middle East,including Egypt, to which he attached telegrams fromSir Miles Larrpson suggesting the strengthening of ourposition in Egypt, and an extract from the draft minutes of the 301st Meeting of the Committee ofImperial Defence.    The Minister stated that so far as any immediate threat to Egypt was concerned, theCommittee of Imperial Defence had been reassured by aReport on the shortage of oil fuel in Italy.   As an interim measure the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs had been asked to send a telegram to Sir miles lampson which should enable him to relieve the immediateanxieties of the Egyptian Government. In addition, inorder to provide material for a decision by the Cabinet,the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee had. been asked toconsider Sir Miles Lampson&apos;s telegrams.   The Ministerthen explained th^t some of his colleagues had. askedone of him to invite the Cabinet to reconsider/the decisionsgoverning the despatch of reinforcements&apos; to theMediterranean, namely -That nothing should be done which could,arouse Italian suspicions or be cor.st.ruedas provocative.After reviewing the arguments for and against the cancellation of this decision, the Minister intimated that, as Minister for Co-ordination of Defence, his first task was to provide for the security of theUnited Kingdom, which would be weakened by the despatchof forces to the Mediterranean or elsewhere.   Prom thispoint of view the ideal would be a restoration of relations with Italy to the position that existed before
1935*    &quot;but if this was impossible just now, the next-best would be a. gradual approach to better relations,during which we should exercise great patience.    In anycase, however, the vital importance of ga.ining time forthe completion o^ our re-armament should never be lostsight of.The Minister for Co-Ordination of Defencereported that the Chiefs of Staff Sub-Committee hadnot yet signed their report.     He had, however, seenan advance copy.      The report was a somewhat elaboratedocument which he could not undertake to summarisebriefly.      It contained a number of proposals for improving the situation in Egypt, of which he mentionedone or two examples.After discussion,  the Cabinet agreed:(a) That the Minister for Co-Ordinationof Defence should have authorityto agree with the Ministers concerned the despatch of such items of equipment as were recommended by the Chiefs ofStaff Sub-Committee and approved byhim and the Service ministers concerned in each ease:(b) That the report of the Chiefs ofStaff Sub-Committee should bereferred to the Committee of ImperialDefence which (with the primeMinister in the Chair) should have authority to take decisions on behalfof the Cabinet on all the matters which had not been dealt with bythe Minister for Co-Ordination ofDefence as in (a) above:(c) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs should be authorisedto inform His Majesty&apos;s ambassador in Cairo that careful consideration was being given to the proposals inhis telegram.
llR RAID PRE-Iautions bill.jfosition oflor them Ireland.&quot;(previous inference:Cabinet 40 (37)Conclusion 7.)8.     The Home Secretary informed the Cabinetthat a difference of opinion had arisen between theHome Office and the Government of Northern ireland as to the provision to be made for Northern ireland in the Air Raid Precautions Bill.     The NorthernIreland view was that Air Raid Precautions formed a part of Imperial Defence and, as such, should bedealt with by legislation of the Imperial Parliament,and, administratively, by the Government of NorthernIreland acting as agents for the United KingdomGovernment.     That view, of course, cut across theposition of local authorities under the Bill.Ministers from Northern Ireland had come to Londonand the matter had been discussed at some lengthduring the last two days.     He had induced theNorthern Ireland Ministers to accept a slightalteration in the Bill, which would make it clearthat Northern Ireland already had an obligation in thematter and that no new obligation was being imposed by the Bill.     The form of Clause 11 was to be altered so as to become an interpretative Clause ofthe present position.The Chancellor of the Exchequer thanked theHome Secretary for the settlement which he had secured.
9.     The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theHome Secretary (CP.-282 (37)) seeking the authority ofhis colleagues for the preparation and submission tothe Committee of Home Affairs of a comprehensive Billwith the object of improving the methods of dealingIV)with persons found guilty of offences.   After outlininghis proposals in detail the Home Secretary stated inhis Memorandum that he had consulted the Secretary ofState for Scotland in regar^ to them.   He understood,however, that in the Secretary of State&apos;s viewconditions in Scotland would not justify their general application in thai, country, but that he might wish toprovide for the application of a certain number of them.The Home Secretary intended, therefore, to keep in close touch with the Secretary of State for Scotland in thepreparation of the details of the legislation proposed..The Chancellor of the Exchequer said he had written a long letter to the Home Secretary giving his views on the Bill.     He concurred in the proposal that the Bill should be submitted to the Committee ofHome Affairs, but observed that it would require detailed examination by that Body.The President of the Board of Trade agreed tothe proposal on the understanding that the authority given by the Cabinet was quite general and that any point could be raised even though it were included inthe Home secretary memorandum.The Cabinet agreed:That the Home Secretary should have authority for the preparation andsubmission to the Committee ofHome Affairs of a comprehensiveBill with the object of improving the methods of dealing with personsfound guilty of offences.
10.    The Cabinet again had before them the following documents on the subject of Levy-Subsidies for Agricul-tural Products:-A Memorandum, by the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries,  covering a Report by anTnter-Oepar+mental Committee of Officials( CP.-268 (37)) :A Report by the Agricultural Policy Committeeof the Cabinet ( CP .-275 (37)) to whom theabove documents had been referred by theCabinet at their Meeting on 10th November(Cabinet&apos;41 (37), Conclusion 7).The recommendations of the Cabinet Committee hadbeen approved at the Meeting mentioned in the marginsubject to the possibility of the preparation of an agreed  draft of the reservation in recommendation (iii)and. to the discussion at the present Meeting of thequestion whether recommendation (i)  applied to eggs and poultry as well as to &quot;milk and other dairy products&quot;.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriescommunicated to the Cabinet certain points on which heand the President of the Board of Trade had reached agreement..     He reported, however, that there was one point outstanding, namely, as to whether     quantitative regulation was to be included in the Milk Bill.     he regarded this as essential.     The Government already had power under the Agriculture Marketing Act, 1931,t* make quantitative regulations in connection withmarketing schemes.     He understood that the Board ofTrade thought that the powers already existing under that Act were sufficient and ought not to be included inthe Bill.     He thought it important to include them.His first reason was political and arose out of the factt at nothing had been done to apply the powers of the1931 Act.     His second reason was that he was not certainthat the Milk Marketing Board was the best body fordealing with quantitative regulation of milk in thefuture.     The Board had its critite and it was impossible
to foresee its future.     He thought, therefore, it wouldhe wise that provision should he made by legislation that if the Marketing Board was revoked some other body should be able-to exercise these powers.The President of the Board of Trade said hewas concerned because he would be responsible for introducing any- legislation.     Up to a very short time ago, he had heard of no suggestions for fresh legislation.      He felt the matter required further examination and he was particularly anxious not to be committed in advance by a statement which the Ministerof Agriculture and Fisheries would be making in a fewdays time to the National Farmers Union.The Minister of Labour agreed with the Presidentof the Board of Trade.      In connection with the rise inthe cost of living, the main criticism was directed towards milk and he thought it most important to bevery careful in any legislation that was introduced.The Secretary of State for Scotland pointed outthat the necessary powers existed already.      The only question was as to v/hether they were to be tied up withthe Milk Marketing Board or not.      He would like tofollow the precedent adopted in the case of the LivestockMarketing Board and reserve the rights of the Government.The Minister of Health suggested that thematter might be dealt with if and when the position of the milk Marketing Board was threatened.The Prime Minister said it would be impossibleto complete the discussion that morning and, on his suggestion,  the Cabinet agreed:   .v To meet again the same afternoon in thePrime Minister !s Room at the,iIou-ec &quot;ofCommons at 5.30 p.riL...-to &quot;continue thediscussion on this point and to take theremainder of the Agenda PaperWhitehall Gardens, S.W.I.24th November, 1937.
APPENDIX,x^rom BELGIUM.(i)Telegram (en clair) from Sir R. Clive (Brussels)D.    22nd November, 1937.R.    23rd November, 1937.No. 80    (Saving).    BY BAG.Following from Mr. MacDonald:The Conference met in   private this afternoon andhad before it two drafts which had been put forward bythe United States, United Kingdom and French Delegations,the first being a draft report to Governments on the workof the Conference, and the second a draft declaration(see my telegram No. 91).Dr. Wellington Koo   expressed regret that the draftsdid no more than re-affirm general principles:    nothing was said regarding the &quot;common attitude&quot; contemplated inthe previous declaration of the Conference, nor was there any reference to the concrete proposals which he had madeat the 7th meeting (see my telegram No. 73 Saving)-.Referring to the previous declaration, he said that thiswas a clear case of treaty breaking and of armed forceused for the purpose.     The issue was of vast importanceto the world, and speedy action - moral, material,financial and economic - was necessary.     He againasked that concrete aid should be rendered to China andthat supplies should be withheld from Japan.     Friendlyremonstrances made no impression on the aggressor: that
indeed was why China had now been forced to fightand t$ defend not only her own existence but also thepeace and civilisation of the world.     China&apos;s resources were limited and the results of her efforts could notbut be modest.     The Powers represented at the conference with their unlimited resources should surely make somepositive, even though indirect, contribution.     failure to act would mean that no distinction was made betweenthe victim and the aggressor, and would represent anew defeat for the forces of peace.     He would make no detailed comments on the drafts, but reserve theright to propose amendments after consulting hisGovernment.M. Michel (Mexico)&apos; made a statement to the effectthat the conflict was aot merely contrary to theprinciples of international law and prejudicial to theinterests of China and other Powers, but also represented a serious menace to all weak countries.     No means of bringing about a just solution should be neglected andthe Powers should refrain from contributing to thefinancial and economic resources of the aggressor.The signatories of the Nine Power Treaty were bound to unite their efforts in defence of it and States membersof the League of Nations had the duty of calling (throughthe Far Eastern Advisory Committee) for the applicationof the relevant provisions of the Covenant.      He hopedhowever, that Japan would alter her attitude.The Conference proceeded to consider the draft report.       After some discussion on the question whether such a report were appropriate at this stage, it wasdecided to alter the title so as to make it a summaryof the essential phases of the Conference&apos;s work up to
date.       This summary would he published and its purpose would &quot;be to set forth the situation in an objective manner.No observations of consequence were made on thegreater part of the draft, one paragraph, which dealtwith the future of the Conference, being reserved for later consideration.The Conference finally adjourned until Wednesdayafternoon in order that Delegates might consult their governments regarding the two drafts..The text of the draft report in its present formis contained in Brussels Conference despatch Ho. 33.3-
From BELGIUM,(ii)Telegram (en clair) from Sir R. Glive. (Brussels).D. (by bag) November 22nd, 1937,R. November 23rd, 1937.No.  81. SAVING.Following from Mr. MacDonald:-Tae following is a brief appreciation of the discussions at Brussels during the last three days.     Contact betweenthe American Delegation and ourselves has been almostcontinuous.     On our return Lord Cranborne, Sir alexander cadogan   and I endeavoured to get ^r. Norman Davis to agreethat the United States and the United Kingdom should makea declaration of their readiness to offer good offices tothe two parties in the Far Eastern conflict whenever thesituation should seem favourable, keeping other Governmentsinformed of any developments.     We urged that if such a decla?-ration were made it would give the Conference a reasonableexcuse for adjourning its sittings at least until the new initiative had been given a chance to develop.But Mr. Davis was from the first strongly opposed tothis suggestion.     He used all sorts of arguments to combatit, urging especially that such a move was premature.      Inthe same way he resisted the suggestion that the conference should give our two Governments a mandate to offer concila-tion if and when they thought fit.     He said that he hopedthat such an initiative by the United States and the
United Kingdom would become possible a little later, butinsisted that it could not be until after the   conference had suspended its sittings.     In view of the later tele-grams which began to come in from Tokyo and Washington,and which indicated that an offer by our two Governmentsat the present moment would not be favourably received in Japan, we felt it impossible to press this pointfurther.The American Delegation and ourselves had in themeantime been considering various possible draft  declarationsby the Conference on its adjournment.      It would bewearisome to repeat in any detail the course of arguments which continued hour after hour.     It was at the suggestion of the Americans, which they pressed hard, that two docu-ments were prepared for adoption by the Conference:    thefirst, a summary of the Conference&apos;s proceedings up to date,and the second a declaration of the position in which theConference now finds itself.     But the documents whichhave now emerged and been laid, before the Conference arevery different from those which the Americans conceivedand drafted.     The original American deaft -of the firstdocument referred to above started with a more or lessobjective account-of the   Conference&apos;s proceedings, butfinished with five or six pages of indictment of Japancouched in fiercer language than even Geneva has s^etemployed.     The second document was in the form ofresolutions which, amongst other things, called upon thetwo parties in the Far East to cease hostilitiesimmediately.     The Americans also desired something in the
nature of a hint of possible pressure upon Japan at alater stage, though Mr. Davis kept agreeing that theprospect of , merican opinion agreeing to any such action had not yet materialised,Mr. Davis and his principal adviser, Dr. Horribeck,proved extremely obstinate in maintaining the view thatthis was the proper way to deal with the situation.     our discussions continued for the best part of two days.Towards the end of them, when Mr. Davis was in his mostobstinate frame of mind, I remarked that we might have thought his proposals wise if there had been the slightestchance of following our brave words with effective action.He himself had told Mr. Eden and the rest of us at thebeginning of the Conference that if we made two or threereasonable offers to Japan and these were rejected,American public opinion would be gradually worked upto a pitch at which it would support strong action.We had made two reasonable offers to Japan and both ofthem had been rejected.     But the effect on American opinion seemed to have been nil.     He and we knew frommessages from Washington that his Government did not feel that they could take any action which would require legislation.     lie himself had suggested that they wouldbe prepared to declare that they would rot recognise any alteration of the status quo in China, and that theywould not lend money to Japan for the development of anyconquest she made.     But now we learned that; his Govern-ment were not even ready to do that.     I did not criticise the American   Government for their attitude;   we in Londonagreed with them that any such declaration would be. to
say the least, premature.     But really if those were thefacts of the situation, what was the use of our asking the Conference to use the sort of strong language which hehad in mind?     These remarks were followed by a painfulsilence.      It seemed that for a whole minute Mr. Davis&apos;brain ceased to function.    T/lien he recovered his powerof speech progress with the drafting became more rapid.We are not proud of either of the documents whichhave been produced, but the first is now on the whole, wethink, a fair objective report of the Conference&apos;sexperiences up to date, and the second at least avoidsthe major foolishnesses which might have ;jone into it.     Despite the many hours of argument and counter-argument between the Americans and ourselves, relations be-tween the two delegations have remained cordial, and co-operation is still complete.The French delegation were conspicuous by their absence until this (Monday) afternoon.     But on being shown the two documents they at once asked that theyshould be made jointly responsible for them with the americans and ourselves.      The Dominion delegations have all approved both documents in principle, though theyare suggesting a few amendments of detail.      I am reportingseparately on the attitude of the Chinese delegation.It would not appear at present that any insuperable difficulties will be presented by other delegations.
Prom BELGIUM,(iii).Telegram (on clair) from Sir R. Olive (Brussels).D.    22nd November,  1937.R.    23rd November, 1937.No.  32     (Saving).Following from Mr. MacDonald:Dr. Wellington ICoo and Mr. Quo Tai-chi called thismorning on the United Kingdom Delegation and the AmericanDelegates were also present at the conversation.     Theywere given copies of the draft of the report and declaration with had been agreed with the united States Delegation, andwhich were to be circulated to the Conference today.After reading through these documents,  Dr. Koo statedthat he could not at the moment make any detailed comments.He would probably have a number of amendments to make.But he wished at once to say that the Chinese Delegationcould hardly avoid feeling disappointed:    they wanted moreencouragement from the Conference than could be found in the documents which he had just read.      The Chinese armies had now for some months been putting up a strenuous resistance to the Japanese onset,, but the morale of the Chinese people,and indeed of the Government, would suffer considerably ifit was felt that they had to continue that resistance with-out any hope of help from outside.      The Chinese armybeen provided at the outset of hostilities with certainreserves of ammunition, but the rate of expenditure hadbeen much higher than could ever have been anticipatedand the stocks were running very low.     It was essential for the maintenance of Chinese morale that some arrangements should be made for assuring the supplies of war material forthe Chinese armies.It was pointed out to Dr. Koo, as on the x^reviousoccasion, that in point of fact the Chinese Government
were free to purchase arras wherever they could find themand arrange shipment.     Mr. Norman Davis added that if anattempt v/ore made to organise the supply of arms to China,that would he certain to give rise to a demand in theUnited -States for the strict application of the NeutralityAct.     Mr. LlacDonald also pointed out that it would heinevitable that in the event of largo quantities of suppliesgoing through Hongkong to Chinas the Japanese Governmentwould find it convenient to declare a formal state ofwar and blockade.      The result might be that the ChineseGovernment would receive oven less war material than atprooent.Dr. Koo insisted that some steps should be taken tofacilitate the supply of war material:    ho did not suggestthat the Conference itself could do anything in the matter^but hoped that it might be possible to have discussions:&apos;on the side&quot; in a committee of reioresentatives of countries from which supplies might be expected.      It was explained to Mr. Koo that the difficulties, such as theywere,  in the various countries.. were of a differentnature and that any joint meeting would be unlikely tofacilitate matters.Rather fortunately Mr. Norman Davis took the lead inthis discussion and was emphatic in his declaration to theChinese Delegate that it would be impossible for the UnitedStates to take any active measures to encourage the shipment of war material to China.Dr. Koo explained that in addition to the materialdifficulties of obtaining arms and arranging transportthere was also the question of credits.      On this pointMr. Norman Davis was even more emphatic that any assistancein the matter of credits would involve legislation whichwas quite out of the question.
Both Mr. Davis and Mr. MacDonald assured Dr. Koothat they fully sympathised with the Chinese Governmentin their difficulties and were willing to do anything that might be practicable to assist.      They suggestedthat in the first pla^e Dr. Koo should coniivvunicate astatement of China&apos;s needs and proposals,; and e-.chGovernment would then examine this statement and see whether any special measures could be devised.      It was probably a matter that could bo dealt with best throughthe diplomatic channel in the various capitals where thenecessary experts were at hand to consult.
FROM BELGIUM,(iv).Telegram (en clair) from Sir R. Glive (Brussels).D.    22nd November, 1937.R.    23rd November, 1937.No.  83 (Saving).Following from Mr. MacDonald:In the course of a talk with Mr. Norman Davisyesterday, he read me a cable which he had received fromMr. Cordell Hull, in which the Secretary of State complained that articles were appearing in the American press sayingthat if the Brussels Conference failedj it would be the faultof the Americans.    Mr. Hull pointed out that if this chargewere freely circulated in the United States, resentfulfeelings would be aroused and Anglo-American relations would suffer a setback.    He hoped that we could do something at brussels to prevent such stories being written by thepress-men here.I assured Mr. Davis that he could count on our co-operation in combating such statements.    As he knew, our policy from the beginning of the Conference had been one ofunqualified co-operation with the United States delegation.Mr. Eden at the very beginning had expressed the hope that whatever policy of action or inaction the Conference mightadopt should be adopted on the full joint responsibility ofboth our delegations.    We were still working in that spirit,and I thought with some success.Mr. Davis said that he attached the greatest possibleimportance to Anglo-American co-operation in international affairs.    In his view America had only one vital interestbeyond her own shores, and that was the security of the
/?/*British Empire.    He then went on to say that the AmericanGovernment had themselves to &quot;blame for the difficulty theywere now in.    It arose partly from the President&apos;s Chicagospeech.    The expression &quot;quarantine&quot; used there had beenunfortunate.    He. Mr. Hull, and the President had discussed the whole situation and the projected speech three weeks before it was delivered, and at that time no expression suchas that had been in the speech.    The President had insertedit himself without further reference to him.    Now american public opinion had forced the President to retreat some way.He (Mr. Davis) had expressed some surprise about the use ofthe term to the President after his return from Chicago.Mr. Roosevelt explained that he had wished to find somephrase which conveyed a certain impression without implyinghostility against Japan.    Therefore he did not want to use the v/ord ^sanctions&quot;, nor any other words which might seem toindicate that hostile action was a possibility.    &quot;Quarantine&quot;was the best word that he  could find.    He instanced the caseof a community in which there was an outbreak of some felldisease; red flags were put on the houses of the victims,so that everyone might know what places to avoid.    Mr.Davis had replied to the President that in those cases ofcourse the red flag was very effective; but supposing abrigand armed with a machine gun entered the street, it wasnot much good putting a red flag on him.He said that he was very disappointed  at the way that american public opinion had failed to react  to Japan&apos;sintransigeance.    But he still thought that eventually theAmerican Government would be able to take some action such asa declaration of non-recognition of any alteration of thestatus quo in China, and of an intention to withhold any financial assistance to any Japanese development schemes inChina.    He thought that American opinion might develop tothis pitch in about a month&apos;s time.

</content>
</cab>
