<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 85-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DESPATCH Y 2.From Colonel A. Knox, Military Attache.Subject    REORGANIZATION OF THE RUSSIAN FORCES.British Embassy,Petrograd,20th February, 1917.Sir, -I have the honour to forward some notes on military matters.Reorganization.1. ^-Battalion regiments. The reorganization of the whole Russian Infantry ip 3-battalion regiments is in progress. As far as is known at present, only the four Guards divisions will remain of 16 battalions.2. It is understood that practically all corps are forming new divisions, yet information varies regarding the actual accession of strength. The Minister of War told me there would be 41 new divisions, exclusive of the Roumanian front. Colonel Langlois understood from General Gurko that the number would be 70, while Generals Wilson and Castlenau gathered from the same source that there would be 52. The Grand Duke Serge told me that there would be 45, viz., 10 on the northern front, 14 on the western and 21 on the south-western. I think this last estimate is probably correct as regards these three fronts, but it does not take into consideration a prior category of new divisions, the formation of which commenced before it had been decided to reorganize the whole Army in 12-battalion divisions. This category consists of 12 divisions, six on the northern and six on the western front.3. Those on the northern front are the 3rd and 4th Special Divisions, formed from the 6th and 12th Special Brigade, which were originally intended for the French front.135th-138th Divisions, formed chiefly from Opolchenis on a small regular cadre.Those on the western front are the 129th, 130th, 132nd, 133rd, 134th and 15th Siberian.The 131st was formed&apos;, but it is believed that it has been re-named 15th Siberian, as its cadre was drawn chiefly from the Hlrd Siberian Corps and its regiments were named after towns in Siberia.4. These 12 divisions are considered to be more or less ready, and several of them are in the front line. The 4th Special Division did not distinguish itself in the Riga fighting, the men it is said refusing to leave their trenches to attack.5. Field guns. The staff of the northern front stated that the 135th-138th Divisions have an average of 16 3-inch guns, and the staff of the western front said that their six divisions have 3 3-inch batteries each. The two Special Divisions as well as the Lett brigades are still without guns.6. If we deduct these 12 divisions the information gathered during a recent short visit to the northern and western fronts confirms the Grand Duke&apos;s estimate of 10 new divisions in formation on the northern front (180th-187th, 18th-20th Siberian) and 14 in formation on the western front (168th-178th, 5th Grenadier, 16th-17th Siberian). It is therefore assumed that his statement that 21 new divisions are in formation on the south-western front is correct. One division per corps exclusive of the Guard Corps gives 19 divisions, and two extra divisions are probably in formation by the staff of the front on the principle followed on the western front.(B17/J08)   25   3/17  H&amp;S   4291wo
\\7. The formation of the new divisions have begun in the Armies on the Roumanian front, so we can calculate on 15 additional divisions there. It is probable, however, that the reorganization on this front will be delayed by the state of the railways.8. We can, therefore, calculate on having on the western frontier by the beginning of May: Infantry divisions.Northern front.....................    44Western front   ......      ...............    50fSouth-western front     ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...     73Eoumanian front ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     491.2179. Caucasian Army. General Gurko told General Wilson that the Caucasian Army will also be organised in 12-battalion divisions, but &quot; later.&quot;10. Increase in strength. The 12 divisions of the prior category represent an actual increase in strength of 144 battalions. A division in the second category only represents an increase of four battalions when its parent corps had not more than two 16-battalion divisions. In the many cases where the parent corps had already three 16-battalion divisions, the reorganization means merely a tearing asunder of existing organizations.11. Net gain. It is thought that each of the new divisions on the northern front brings a net gain of four battalions, for in the cases where the parent corps has three divisions one of them is of 12 battalions. . Total 40 battalions.12. On the other hand the 14 new divisions in formation in the armies of the western front probably only represent a net gain of 28 battalions, but the two divisions forming at the staff of the front raise the total to 52 battalions. Similarly the net gain in battalions on the south-western front is estimated at 56, and on .the Roumanian front it will be about 40 battalions.13. Probable total for the whole four fronts 188 battalions. These figures are not official.14. I have seen a special army order for the formation of these new divisions, and it is gathered that the system followed on the northern and western fronts is similar. The order is dated 20th January, the reorganization is ordered to begin not later than the 23rd January, and to be completed by the 23rd January.15. The Vth (7, 10), XXVth (3rd Grenadiers, 46), XXXIVth (56, 104) and 1st Turkistan (1st Turkistan Rifles, 2nd Turkistan Rifles) Corps were ordered to form a third division each. The XXXIXth Corps (53, 102, 125) to form a fourth division. Each regiment in the four first-named corps was to detail six companies, while each regiment in the XXXIXth Corps detailed a battalion. Parent regiments detailing six companies were ordered to complete without delay to 12-company establishment.16. Maxim guns and specialist detachments. General officers commanding corps were ordered to arrange that each new regiment should have a detachment of eight Maxims, and parent regiments were told to provide men for the following specialist detachments : Communication detachment. Sapper detachment. Regimental police. Detachment for collecting rifles. Trench gun detachment. Non-combatant company.17. Each regiment was told to reduce its mounted scout detachment to an establishment of 1 officer, 1 serjeant, 2 corporals, 5 lance-corporals and 4 privates, handing over the balance to the new regiments.18. There is a difference of opinion regarding the soundness of the new scheme. The Minister of War disapproves of it. He says that it will be difficult to find good regimental commanders in sufficient numbers, and the staffs will be second rate. The Commander of the XYIIIth Corps is organising his three 16-battalion divisions into four 12-battalion divisions. He says he will feel like the Jew who when once upon a time walking from Berdichev into the country met two. highwaymen. He took off his hat and placed it on his stick and said &quot; Now we are two.&quot;
19. One advantage of the change is that it will be easier to draw back divisions into reserve for a rest.   My French colleagues think the idea is sound.20. Artillery. -^U^these divisions will be at first without artillery, and the special army order conveys the information that they will have no ammunition columns.21. Machine guns. It is thought that when the new organization is completed, the number of machine guns in battalions will average 4-5.There are three depdt machine-gun regiments, each with 16 companies for the training of drafts for machine-gun detachments at the front.Cavalry.The following is a list of cavalry divisions and brigades as far as they are known: Divisions.Guard...      ...      ...      ... ... ... ... ... ... 3Line ...      ...      ...      ... ... ... ... ... ... 17Caucasian Cavalry  ...      ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Composite Cavalry ...       ... ...&quot; ... ... ... ... 1Ussuri         ...       ...       ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Trans-Amur ...      ...      ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Don Cossack Cavalry        ... ... ... ... ... ... 52nd Composite Cossack Cavalry ... ... ... ... ... 1Orenburg Cossack Cavalry ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Siberian Cossack Cavalry   ... ... ...... ....... 1Ural Cossack Cavalry,       ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Caucasian Cossack Cavalry... ... ... ... ... ... 6Turkistan Cossack Cavalry ... ... ... ... ... ... 2Kuban Cossack Cavalry     ... ... ... ... ... ... 5Terek Cossack Cavalry      ... ... ...... ...... 1Trans-Baikal Cossack Cavalry .... ... ... ... ... 2Caucasian Native Cavalry ... ... ... ... ... ... 1Total divisions ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 50*     Brigades.Petrograd Frontier Guard................. 1Polish...      ...      ...      ...      ...     - ..      ...      ...      ... 11st and 2nd Baltic  ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      ... 2Arensburg Divisional (3 squadrons) ...      ...      ...      ... \Siberian Cossack     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      ... 1Caucasian Horse     ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... ^1st Independent Composite Cavalry        ...       ...       ...       ... 1Independent Composite Cossack   ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 11st Don Cossack     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 12nd Don Cossack    ...      .................. 1Total brigades ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...   9^-2. Dismounted squadrons. For some months each regular cavalry division has had a rifle (i.e., Jager) division of 3 dismounted squadrons. All regular divisions, with the exception of the Guard, have now 6 additional squadrons 2 from each of the regular regiments. The additional squadrons will be used to increase the rifle divisions in the regular cavalry divisions to rifle &quot; regiments &quot; of 6 dismounted squadrons and to provide a dismounted &quot; division &quot; of 3 squadrons in each Cossack Cavalry Division.Technical Troops.1. Engineers. Under the new organization each corps will have an engineer regiment, whose commander will have two assistants, and will have under him, in addition to a workshop and engineer park, a sapper battalion and a technical battalion.2. Sapper Battalion. The sapper battalion will consist of two sapper companies  a bridging and road-making company, with 280 feet of bridging material.
3. Techical Battalion.-The technical battalion will contain a telegraph company and a working telegraph company to work Government lines or to lay permanent lines.4. Engineer Companies. In addition to the above, each infantry division will have an engineer company, bearing the number of the division, and consisting of four sapper sections, a telegraph section and a section of engineer park.5. The following table gives some idea of the progress in the organization of technical troops:-	1914.	1916.	Remarks.Sapper battalions       ..	39	74	*1 division per ArmyPontoon battalions......	H		with 1 or 2 sectionsIndependent telegraph companies		50	in each corps.Wireless units......	7 companies.	15 division8.*		4	1 per front and 1 per			corps.	fAnd in addition 41	13 railway battalions.	29 railway battalions.	motor    cyclists   in	3 Trans-Amur railway	6  Trans-Amur   rail-	each regular cavalry	battalions.	way battalions.	division.		3  parks   of  horse-			drawn railways.	Automobile units      ..      ..	1 company.	21 companies.		Nil	39       ,,	Motor-cyclist companies	Nil	2              t		Nil	18 each division.	Is divided  into sec-			tions 1 section  of		-	4 cars in each corps			(in all 47 sections).Chemical (gas) detachments	Nil	15	Operations.The recent operations west of Riga may be divided into three phases :  (a.) Russian offensive, 5th to 10th January. (&amp;.) German counter-offensive, 22nd to 25th January, (c.) Further German counter-offensive, 30th to 31st January.(a.) Russian offensive. The Vlth Siberian Corps was detailed to make the decisive attack. On the night of the 4/5th January the imd and 1st Lett Brigades (eight battalions each) broke through the enemy&apos;s line north and south of Mangel without artillery preparation, the grenadiers moving out in advance and cutting the wire.1. The 2nd Lett Brigade moved straight on south-west and occupied, the village of Grabbe; the 1st Lett Brigade occupied the village of Scandal, but was driven back byi a counter-attack. . .2. On the left bank of the Aa the XLIIIrd Corps had some small success, but the 4th Special Division failed rather disgracefully.3. The 3rd Siberian Division had no success against the strong German entrench-ments in its immediate front. The 14th Siberian Division advanced, but was driven back by a counter-attack.4. The Russian guns opened a barrage at daylight on the 5th.5. The General Officer Commanding Vlth Siberian Corps threw in two regiments of the 14th Siberian Division from his reserve on the right of the 2nd Lett Brigade, and by 2 p. m. on the 7th after severe righting took &quot;Machine-gun Hill&quot; from the rear or south, the bulk of its defenders escaping across the Aa under heavy artillery fire.6. By the 10th the Russians had consolidated their line, two regiments of the 1st Lett Brigade having crossed the Aa and turned the German position.(b.) German counter-offensive. The Germans with (according to Russian accounts) guns superior in number and weight drove the Russians north to the line they now occupy. The Russians lost, heavily and 75 per cent, of the casualties were from gun fire.   The Russian guns were unable to find the enemy batteries.
1, Further German counter-offensive. On the 30th January, after some days&apos; rest, the enemy made strong infantry attacks, but was repulsed with the bayonet. On the 31st he subjected the Russian line to a severe bombardment.2. General Radko Diinitriev (the Commander of the 12th Army) was everywhere in the thickest of the fighting encouraging his men. The weather conditions were terrible, and numbers of the wounded were frozen to death. The Russians say they could not hold the advanced line as they could not entrench, but the real reason of their retirement was probably the weakness of their counter-battery work1. Surprise tactics. General Radko Dimitriev is full of the success of his surprise tactics and he thinks that if he had three or four corps in reserve he would have gone far. He has issued a triumphant order with elaborate instructions for carrying out surprise attacks by night without artillery preparation, the enemy&apos;s wire to be cut by hand. He writes that the enemy&apos;s weak point is the thinness of his line, his strength lies in the excellence of his communications, the number of his machine guns and the width of his barbed wire. His idea is to concentrate, if he is given them, some three or four corps some marches in rear to avoid exciting suspicion, and to break through with his own divisions, marching the reserve corps rapidly forward to develop the success.2. Casualties. In this operation the Russians lost 38,000 men, and though Radko estimates the enemy loss at 50,000, the estimate of 6,000 given on the same day by one of his staff is probably nearer the mark.   The Russians took 100 prisoners and 33 guns.3. Relative strengths. On the active front from the Gulf of Riga to Sarkanaiz the Russians had never less than 92 battalions. The enemy had only 22-25 battalions on the 5th January, and even on the Russian estimate, his strength never increased beyond 64-71 battalions. There is no doubt that the Germans were completely surprised, but the reason for undertaking the operation is not clear, for the Russians had insufficient force to develop a real success. Similar surprises may succeed in the future, but the Russians will not be able to hold what they gain till they get aeroplanes and learn to use them in co-operation with their guns.4. Artillery in Special Army. General Baluev, Commander of the Special Army, said that his army of 15 infantry and 3 cavalry divisions had 547 3-inch field guns. 83 4&quot;8-inch howitzers     )   -25 6-inch howitzers 21 6-inch 120 pood guns 29 4&quot;2-inch guns 10 6-inch Schneider guns jHe considered that at least 40 light field and 20 heavy guns per f mile of active front are necessary for a decisive attack, and that no attack on a front of less than 9 miles could have a chance of success. As his heavy artillery only admitted of an attack on a front of 5 miles, he suggested that he should take up a passive attitude, and that his surplus infantry might be transferred to some army where it might be of more use.Man Power.1. New proposal. It is stated that the General Staff Directorate who have always been more alive to the appalling waste of men than the strategists of Mogilev, proposed last autumn to General Headquarters to call out all men from 43 to 55. However, a petition signed by 27 members of the Council of Empire and Duma, pointed out that such a measure would finally upset the productive services of the country, and suggested as an alternative that many men might be taken for the front from the lines of com-munication, and that some system of tactics might be adopted less wasteful of life. This petition arrived at General Headquarters just as Gurko temporarily replaced Alexyeev, and its proposals were in principle adopted.2. Limit of age. The limit of age for men in units actually at the front was formerly 36, but was raised to 38, and has lately been raised once more to 40.3. Deserters. It is extraordinary how the peculiarities of the Russian govern-mental system weaken the Empire for national defence. In individualistic France a deserter is at.once exposed by his neighbours. The Russian communes hide deserters from the authorities for they profit by their labour. When the socialist, Albert Thomas, was out here, he demanded the militarisation of labour but was refused in autocratic Russia on the ground that such a measure would be a reversion to slavery.4. Shortage of labour. The authorities talk of a shortage of labour and Kirgiz have been brought to shiver at road-making near Riga, but workmen&quot; are allowed toy = 168 so-called &quot; heavy &quot; guns.
keep more holidays than in any neutral country. The perversity of the food regulations and the persistent mismanagement of the railways make one almost believe the charge that one hears on all sides that the Government is deliberately organising defeat.The Railways.1. Defective transport. The Russians ask for huge quantities of steel and say that they are unable to increase their own output owing to shortage of labour and defective transport. If asked why they cannot make their men work more than 22-24 days in the month, they say it would be no use if they did for the railways could not carry the necessary fuel and raw material. It is contended that the railways are the chief cause of the present chaos.2. Want of coal. The railways are going through a serious crisis owing to the exhaustion of the stocks of coal on many of the lines and the poor quality of the coal that is available. The water system was not used as it should have been in summer to accumulate stocks of coal at convenient centres in central and northern Russia partly no doubt because the men were not tied down to the mines and made to work throughout the summer. The poor quality of the coal has affected the engines which without intermission with reliefs of personnel who have never time to clean them. The long spell of continuous very cold weather and snow storms have strained locomotives, shortened trains and locked up rolling stock by frequent delays of 24 hours, resulting in sickness in the personnel.S. Mr. Burys suggestion^ It is suggested that the transport of articles of luxury such as mineral water from the Caucasus and fruit from Turkistan should be prohibited. Mr. Bury&apos;s idea is to recommend the reduction of the passenger service, but that is believed to have been already reduced to a minimum, and to increase the number of engines and wagons in circulation by recalling trained mechanics from the front to diminish the proportion of rolling stock permanently waiting repair. The last remedy is quite impracticable. Of the 15 million men called out upwards of 2 millions are dead, and 2 millions more prisoners of war, and it would be impossible to find the few remaining mechanics under six months.4. If we cannot suggest, and get the Russians to adopt some change in the system of management, we must procure them new and powerful engines. It would have been better to have ordered these in the spring of 1915 in America instead of forcing upon Russia orders for shell and rifles that seem never likely to substantiate. We were not warned as soon as that, but M. Tropov gave us ample warning a few months later. Our Treasury however refused the credits.Military Academy.1. The Military Academy has been re-opened since the 14th November. The junior years course of pecice time is now gone through in 2^ months, and the senior and &quot;extra&quot; years in 5 months more.2. The junior class which joined on the 14th November consisted of 250 officers selected without examination from the army in the field. Line corps nominated 3 and Guard Corps 5, while some 30 more were selected by the staffs at General Headquarters and the fronts. This class passed its first years examination at the end of last month, and has now returned to the army to replace a so-called &quot; senior &quot; class of about 200 officers who either passed one year at the Academy before the outbreak of war or else qualified at the entrance examination in 1914. This senior class will attend from the , 14th February till the 31st July, becoming on the latter date fully qualified for service on the General Staff.It was originally intended to call a second junior class from the 14th February till the 14th April, But the idea was abandoned as it was considered impossible to take 400 officers from the army at one time. The class that has just returned to the front will rejoin for its senior course from the 14th September till the 14th February, 1918. The scheme thus produces 200 staff officers on the 31st July, 1917, and 200 to 250 more on the 14th February, 1918.The lectures are given by officers specially detailed from the front for each class.I have, &amp;c,A. KNOX,Military Attache.* Mr. Bury is Vice-President of the Canadian Pacific Railway, and his services have recently been placed at the disposal of the Russian Government.
APPENDIX.Table op Guns on Fronts (except Caucasian) and in Rear on the14th January, 1917.				In formation,	Type.	On four	Reserve of	Formed in	ready by	Interior of	fronts.&quot;	fronts.	rear.	14th March,	Empire.				1917.	3-inch field (including 1900-1902 and	5,123	938	126	156	251Japanese   guns   and   90-4-gun					anti-aircraft batteries).					3-inch mountain, 1909 and 1910	- 284	54	16   &apos;	48	14 72*48-line howitzers	720	133		24	4845-line howitzers     ..      ,.	228	a a	24	,72	6642-line gun, Q.F.      ......	108	22	36	74	3042-line gun, 1877     ..	199	11	* *	* *	* *6-inch howitzers, field   .	186	26		8 (British)	166-inch howitzers, fortress	172	13		* *	^ m6-inch 120 poods gun..	299	10			a .6-inch Schneider gun	18				6-iuch 200 poods gun	68		* *	* *	6-inch 190 poods gun	65		- . . -		8-inch howitzer	29		t t		11-inch howitzer      ..	14			2	10-inch gun	6			* *	12-inch howitzer, Q.P.				8	12-inch howitzer Obukhov	6		*&quot; *&apos;-	15	90-mm. gun.......			42	108	120-mm. gun ..       ..       ..			24	106	155-mm. gun				oo	tO.P., very little shell......	400		* *	.  a	Trench mortars (3-inch short, 37-mm.,	286				47-m&quot;m. and 57-mm.)					* For re-armament of H.A. batteries, t Total order 150. X Total order 100.

</content>
</cab>
