<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 97-102</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A GENERAL REVIEW OF THE SITUATION IN ALLTHEATRES OF WAR.1. The policy formulated by the Allied General Staffs and reaffirmed at their last meeting at Chantilly on 15th November is the concentration of the maximum strength in the main theatres of war in Europe and the reduction of commitments in all secondary theatres of war to the minimum. As long ago as the 28th December, 1915, the War Cabinet decided that, &quot; from the point of view of the British Empire, France and Flanders are the main theatres of operations.&quot; This decision has governed and continues to govern the military policy in all theatres of war in which the British Empire is concerned.2. To begin with the secondary theatres : In Mesopotamia, the reorganization of our communications and the end of the rainy season have enabled our forces to resume active operations. With the object of improving our general position, inflicting losses on the Turks, and diverting Turkish reinforcements to Mesopotamia, General Maude undertook an advance on 13th December. After hard fighting on both banks of the Tigris, the Turks were compelled to abandon their extremely strong positions defending Kut-el-Amara, and to retire on Baghdad. An energetic pursuit on the part of our troops prevented the shattered army from putting up any effective resistance south of the city, and Our forces occupied Baghdad on March 11th. Since then we have secured control of the embankments of the Tigris up-stream, from which the city might have been flooded by the enemy, and have continued the pursuit of the enemy forces retiring up the Tigris. A detachment has also been pushed up the Diala River. Our present objects are to establish an adequate system of administration and supply in the Baghdad area ; to dispose of the enemy&apos;s detachments on the Lower Euphrates ; and to co-operate with the Russians in the further expulsion of the Turks from Mesopotamia.The Turkish Army which defended Kut has lost 7,500 prisoners and 39 guns captured by us, besides many others which have been thrown into the river. Its losses in killed and wounded have been very heavy, and it has practically ceased to exist as a fighting force. The fall of Baghdad deprives the Turks of their best base for operations both in Mesopotamia and Persia; it removes all danger of a Turkish advance in Persia, and in consequence relieves us of anxiety with regard to our Indian frontier.3. The collapse of their army in the Tigris Valley has compelled the Turks to withdraw from Persia also, and made possible a rapid advance by the Russian forces on that front. Although the country was still snow-bound and the arrival of reinforce-ments had not yet been completed, the Grand Duke Nicholas, in compliance with our request, ordered the Army in Persia to take the offensive at once in order to exploit the situation to the full. The Russians are now advancing on a front of 250 miles as fast as the wintry condition of the country allows. In the direction of Baghdad they are engaged with the Turkish rear-guards, west of Kermanshah, while further north they are endeavouring to force the passes south-east of Bane.With regard to Egypt, Sir A. Murray has been instructed to be as aggressive as circumstances will allow in order to keep as many Turks on his front as possible, to prevent them reinforcing their troops in Europe and in the Caucasus, and to render all the assistance in his power to the King of the Hejaz. His progress has already compelled the Turks to retire from the Sinai Peninsula and to evacuate a strong position at Shellal, 15 miles east of Rafa, and to reinforce their troops in Southern Palestine by at least two divisions, bringing their total forces opposed to Sir A. Murray to a strength of, at least, five divisions. The enemy is contending with great difficulties in southern Syria owing to the breakdown of his railway service, due to the want of rolling stock, oil and fuel, and owing to the lack of supplies in the country and the hostility of the population. While our future progress must depend on circumstances which cannot at present be foreseen, it is hoped that the forces at our disposal will allow of a further advance being undertaken.5. In Arabia, the position of the Turkish force, amounting to about 12,000 men, is becoming seriously endangered by the operations of the King of the Hejaz.   The enemy(B17/222)   80   8/17   h&amp;S   4306wo
is suffering from a shortage of supplies, his communications are constantly being raided, the Arabs are showing increasing activity, and there is a prospect of the northern Hejaz tribes joining the rising. There would now appear to be no danger of a Turkish advance on Mecca.6. In Armenia, the Russians have experienced considerable supply and transport difficulties, but they have improved their communications by the construction of several railways and by establishing a line of communication and supply by sea with the ports on the Black Sea coast. The Turkish armies opposed to them are suffering seriously from lack of supplies caused by the exhaustion of the country. They have, however, also paid much attention to the construction of new roads and railways, and their communications will by the spring of this year be superior to those of the Russians. This fact will to some extent counter-balance the considerable numerical superiority of the Russians in this theatre, and progress in Armenia is rather to be expected from pressure from the Tigris Valley, which our victories in Mesopotamia have facilitated, than from direct attack.7. In the Balkans the weather conditions, which have been specially severe, have prevented active operations during the winter, and there has been no important change in the situation since the capture of Monastir on 19th [November.One more British division and three French divisions have been transferred from France to Salonika during the last few months.   .The demobilization of the Greek Army and its transfer to the Morea have been carried out in accordance with the demands of the Entente Governments, and the danger of an organized attack by the Greeks on our communications has thus been removed.The role assigned to the Allied forces at Salonika last Autumn was to keep as many enemy troops as possible on the Greek frontier with a view to assisting a Russian offensive against Bulgaria from Roumania. The Allied operations have been successful in drawing both German and Turkish reinforcements to Macedonia, but the invasion of Roumania and the advance of the Germans to the Sereth have prevented a Russian offensive against Bulgaria.Without Russian co-operation an Allied offensive in Macedonia is unlikely to effect important results.The nature of the country, the co-ordination of operations by forces consisting of six different nationalities, the numbers opposed to the Allies and the fact that the enemy is acting on interior lines and can concentrate on this front with greater ease and rapidity than the Allies, render it impossible to attain results in any way commensurate with the effort involved. The situation is aggravated by the strain upon our shipping resources, which will become increasingly serious in the future.8. In German East Africa, operations are in progress with a view to rounding up the remainder of the enemy&apos;s forces which are still holding out in the south-eastern districts of the colony. The main enemy force, which had retired into the Rufigi delta, finding its communications endangered by the concentric advance of our columns, has retired southwards through the difficult bush country east of the Rufigi River. The enemy&apos;s western force, formerly located in the Mahenge area, has divided into small columns, two of which have succeeded in eluding and breaking through our detachments. One has now crossed the Songwe River, and is moving westward, pursued by a British force.   The other broke south, and is at present in the neighbourhood of the Portuguesefrontier.The enemy&apos;s troops are suffering severely from lack of supplies and transport which compels them to disperse their forces. It may still be possible for them to retire into Portuguese territory, but such a retreat would probably involve considerable losses, as well as the abandonment of a great part of their equipment, ammunition and stores. Our own transport difficulties are great, and in view of the early approach of the rains General Hoskins has decided to adopt a waiting attitude for the present. Active operations may be expected to recommence towards the end of April, and there is reason to hope that the campaign may be brought to a conclusion in the course of the next few months.The effective strength of the remaining enemy forces is estimated at about 600 Europeans and 6,000 natives.It has at length been found possible to entrust the completion of the campaign mainly to our native forces, leaving only a small nucleus of white troops to support them.The King&apos;s African Rifles have been increased from three to 13 battalions, and five native battalions and one West Indian battalion have been brought from West Africa. Other native units are being raised in East Africa and Rhodesia.   These measures have
already enabled us to transfer the majority of the South African troops to the Union, and the remainder are now awaiting transfer. . They have also enabled us to transfer one British battalion and some Indian battalions to Egypt,9. On the Italian front active operations have been impracticable during the winter. The Italians have greatly increased their output of artillery and munitions, but they still lack sufficient heavy artillery to undertake an attack on a broad front, and are therefore unable to make lull use of their numerical superiority. The possession by the enemy of the Trentino also constitutes a threat to the Italian communications, and may tend to limit their offensive effort in the direction of Trieste. On the other hand, their relative superiority over the Austrians both in numbers and in armament is now very great. As against 443 Austrian battalions and 2,489 guns, the Italians have 891 battalions in the field, with 4,024 guns. This advantage should allow of their making greater progress during the present year than they did in 1916, provided that German troops are not concentrated against them.In the Eastern Theatre the only operations of importance which have taken place recently have been on the Roumanian front. The defeat of the Roumanian Army has been due to inefficiency and disorganization of a wide and most deplorable nature, and to the lack of close and friendly relations between the Russians and Roumanians, aggravated by German intrigue and pro-German influence in Roumanian official quarters. The Rnssian and Roumanian Armies have in consequence been compelled to fall back behind the Sereth and to evacuate the Dobrudja. The enemy ceased offensive operations on this front about the end of January, and no change in the situation has taken place since that time.Six R.oumanian divisions still remain&apos;in the field, and it is stated that nine more divisions may be ready about the end of April when they have had time to rest and refit, but the disorganization of the Roumanian railway system, which is seriously hampering the delivery of the supplies and equipment required to enable these latter divisions to take the field, makes this doubtful.11. The effect of Roumanian intervention has been to increase the Russian front by nearly 300 miles, a factor which increases the difficulties involved in a defective railway service and ill-organized lines of communication.The Russians may find greater difficulty in advancing ,than they encountered last year owing to the increased support rendered by Germany to the Austrian armies. The latter have been completely reorganized by the Germans, who hold all the higher commands, and a large number of German divisions are now distributed along the front south of the Pinsk Marshes formerly held exclusively by Austrian formations. At the same time the comparatively small value of the Austrian troops must place an increasing strain on the German Army. The Russians are. better provided with artillery and munitions than they have been at any previous period, and are in a position to exercise considerable pressure on the Austro-German Armies.On the other hand, the recent outbreak of revolution in Russia is not without danger to the cause of the Allies from the military point of view. The Provisional Government have declared their intention to prosecute the war with the utmost vigour, and it appears certain that the Army welcomes the new regime. Nevertheless, the revolution is not yet over, and the possible effect of social and industrial excitement on the production of munitions and the other services of war must remain for some time a source of anxiety.12. During the past year between 15th February, 1916, and 15th February, 1917, Great Britain has supplied to Russia 659 guns and howitzers, 11,899 tons of explosives, 1,569,000 shells; 1,545 machine guns, 66,941 rifles and 763 million rounds of small-arm ammunition. Other war material includes 49 aeroplanes, 299 aeroplane engines, 519 motor cars, 1,012 lorries, and 6,402 tons of barbed wire.During the present year the War Office has already allocated contracts for 107 heavy guns and howitzers, 600 trench howitzers, 4,842,000 shells, 1,450 machine guns, and  2,300,000,000 rounds of small-arm ammunition;  besides a  large  number of aeroplanes, motors and tractors.The increase in the Russian heavy artillery during the past year may be judged from the following figures. On 1st April, 1916, there were, on the Russian Front, 5,193 field guns and 1,183 howitzers and heavy guns. On 1st January, 1917, there were 6,316 field guns and 2,066 howitzers and heavy guns. It was hoped prior to the outbreak of the revolution that there would be on 1st June this year 7,000 field guns and 2,461 howitzers and heavy guns. The latter figure might, however, have been con-siderably increased in view of further allocation of contracts by the French and ourselves, and to increased output of ammunition and of lorries.   The home output of ammunition(4306)
in Russia has more than doubled in the past year, but is now being greatly interfered with by railway disorganization, strikes and revolution.13. In the Western Theatre the French by the recapture of important positions at Verdun on 15th December have rendered that place secure. The line formerly held by the French north of Roye have now been taken over by the British. The British Army has throughout the winter carried out a series of minor operations and raids on an extended scale, in which considerable losses. have been inflicted on the enemy and many prisoners have been secured. In the course of the last month our continued pressure, especially in the Ancre valley, has led to a general German retirement in the region between Arras and Soissons, on a front of more than 105 miles. On ]7th March our troops occupied Bapaume, and the French advanced north-east of the Roye Noyon road. From direct and indirect evidence it seems clear that the enemy has withdrawn to what is known as the Hindenburg line, extending from Arras by Moeuvres, St. Quentin, and La Fere to Cerny en Laonnois, 16 miles east of Soissons.   This line has been heavily fortified.This retirement on the part of the enemy has no doubt been influenced by the enemy&apos;s experiences last year in the battle of Somme and by his desire to spare his troops the losses they would have suffered if he had accepted battle on this part of the front under the unfavourable conditions to him which are the consequence of the Somme fighting; to increase his reserves by shortening his line ; to gain the time that must elapse before we can be ready to mount an attack against his new positions ; and consequently to diminish the effect of our expected offensive and improve the opportunities for his own. It is estimated that from 15 to 20 German divisions may be saved by. a retirement to the Hindenburg line ; several divisions have recently arrived in Belgium, and there are at least 20 new divisions in Germany which have not been put in the field. There are as yet no signs of an immediate German offensive on this or any other front.14. With respect to material resources, our munition supply is now ample for all our requirements.As regards our output of artillery, we had in France at the conclusion of the Somme battle, about the middle of November, 3,911 field guns and field howitzers and 1,145 howitzers and heavy guns. These numbers have already been increased to 4,095 field guns and 1,468 howitzers and heavy guns. By the end of June it is hoped to have 1,916 heavy guns in France. The expenditure of ammunition required by modern methods of fighting is so great that guns become worn out in a comparatively short time, and therefore the extent to which the guns can be increased in number is affected by the necessity of having constantly to replace those already in the field.15. The most important question at the present time is that of man-power. Last autumn it became apparent that unless immediate steps were taken to increase the strength of our force in France by the spring of 1917, it would be impossible after next April to keep our army up to strength. I regret to say that the efforts made to obtain men have proved inadequate, with the result that we are now faced with the situation foreseen last year, and if heavy fighting takes place in April or before, the strength of the armies in the field will diminish, no matter what steps are now taken. The success of the forthcoming operations has therefore already been prejudiced, and unless immediate measures are taken to obtain more men, our chances of ultimately achieving such success as will give us the terms of peace we want will be correspondingly reduced.16. This situation is all the more serious in view of the revolutionary movement in Russia and the supreme effort which Germany is making to develop her man-power. It was not anticipated by the General Staff that Russia would this year be able to do more than keep the German and Austrian divisions, now on the Eastern Front, fully employed. The uncertain political situation makes it now uncertain that she will be able to do this. The military power of Russia depends largely on her capacity to keep her armies supplied with all military requirements more adequately than has been the case in the past. The revolutionary movement has already reduced the industrial output of the country, but it is too early yet to gauge the full military effect.At Easter, 1916, the total number of German divisions in the field -was 169, at which it had stood for some months. By 1st November, the number of divisions had increased to 197. The strain of creating these new formations and at the same time of finding the drafts necessary to replace wastage led to the passing of the Auxiliary Service Law during November, which placed all persons between the ages of 17 and 60 -at the disposal of the Government. It is estimated that the effect of this law was to set free for military service an additional 1,700,000 men, and by 14th February the number of German divisions in the field had reached 210.   It is now 218.
Other sources of man-power were tapped by the deportation of large numbers of Belgians for labour purposes and by the enlistment of Poles in the German forces. As -a result of these measures, it is believed that at least 29 new divisions are now in course of training, four of which have already appeared on the Western Front.In addition to these new formations, fresh divisions are being formed by the with-drawal of infantry from existing divisions having a strength of over 9 battalions, and if this reorganization is carried out, as it probably will be to the extent of bringing all divisions to the 9 battalion standard, 15 fresh divisions may be formed. It is, therefore, probable that in the early spring the total numbers of German divisions in the field may amount to 255, viz : Present, on 20th March        ............     218Now forming in Germany&quot;   ...       ...      ...      ...      25Reconstituted from existing units   ...       ...       ...       15258If this forecast should prove correct, the Allies will be faced during the coming season of active operations by 89 more German divisions than was the case at the beginning of last summer. As stated above, the divisions are weaker in infantry than they were a year ago, but the fact nevertheless remains that Germany will have in the -field a net increase of not less than one and a quarter million men with a corresponding-increase of guns.17. The reserves available in Germany to maintain these numbers in the field are estimated at the present time at 2,100,000. Of these some 700,000 will probably be absorbed by fresh formations, leaving 1,400,000 as a reserve to replace wastage in 1917.At the time when Germany had 170 divisions in the field her average permanent monthly casualties were estimated at 120,000. With 258 divisions in the field they may well be considerably more. By the end of November, 1917, therefore, and assuming that the rate of permanent casualties is as before, the whole of Gerrnam&apos;&apos;s present available reserve will be reduced to under half a million and she will have in addition the youths of the 1920 class, about 500,000 in number.18. Since May, 1916, the Austro-Hungarian Army has been increased by only i\ divisions. So far, however, from any increase in personnel, our information tends to show a definite decrease in the strength of units in the field. So far as is known no more fresh divisions are being formed. The reserves are estimated at 850,000, excluding men now in depots. If the average monthly wastage is maintained, these reserves should be exhausted by the end of 1917, leaving only the men born in 1900 to replace further wastage. It is, however, very unlikel)7-, owing to the way in which Austrian troops are now being supported by German, that there will be any repetition of the great capture of Austrian prisoners which occurred in June, 1916. It is, therefore, not unlikely that by the end of 1917, Austria may still have half a million men in addition to those born in 1900, estimated at 400,000.There is evidence that the situation in Austria is causing the German Government great anxiety, and this situation is likely to impose an increasingly severe strain on the German Army in the future.19. The Bulgarian Army contains elements of doubtful value, and no very determined resistance was made to the Allied advance on Monastir; it is probable that they will continue to require a-stiffening of German troops. The maintenance of the whole able-bodied male population in the field is proving a serious strain on Bulgaria&apos;s resources and the quality of the reserves is deteriorating. The Roumanian menace has, however, been removed, and in spite of war-weariness and the ill-feeling which prevails between Germans and Bulgarians they may be expected to fight to the last in defence of Macedonia.20. The condition of the Turkish Army is steadily deteriorating. The total numbers of Turkish troops in the field in all theatres of war are estimated at aabout 600,000, with a reserve on paper of perhaps 500,000, but these figures include a large number of boys, and men of 50, besides physically unfit. Even if the Turks can maintain their present effectives in the field throughout the coming summer, it would seem certain that then-quality will deteriorate greatly. The Turks now have six divisions operating in Galicia, Roumania and the Balkans, which imposes a great additional strain upon their resources in men, and has compelled them to utilize a large part of them strategic reserve.21. Although we can now gauge with considerable accuracy the nature and extent
of the effort which Germany is making, it would be undesirable at present to attempt any forecast of the duration of the war. There is, however, every indication that this years campaign will prove decisive, and we should, therefore, strain every nerve to put our maximum strength in the field during this spring and summer.22. This is not meant to imply that the war will necessarily end this year, or that ultimate victory depends upon our obtaining a decisive success in 1917, but that the nature of the effort which Germany is now making, taken hi conjunction with the general situation of the Central Powers, will not only preclude the possibility of a further effort on their part but may lead to the exhaustion of their resources by next winter. In these circumstances the failure of the enemy to achieve his object this year may prove disastrous to him, and consequently we should make every endeavour, firstly, to ensure that his effort should fail and, secondly, to turn this failure into a decisive defeat. At the same time, we should not regard success as unattainable except by a decisive victory this year.The decision may, in fact, be reached not by the breaking of the German line or the retirement of the German armies, but by the exhaustion of the Central Powers, and nothing would be more fatal than to give the impression that we are staking everything on the result of one battle or on our ability to win a great strategical victory. It is certain that the war is entering on a phase which will impose a far severer strain on all the belligerents than they have yet had to bear, and victory will rest with that side which displays the greatest resolution and endurance. We should, therefore, regard the forthcoming operations as a means of so weakening the strength of the Central Powers that we may compel them to submit to a peace on our terms in the shortest possible time ; but, at the same time, we should place no limit on the period in which such a peace must be secured. If all the Entente Powers confront the present situation in this spirit, they have every reason to be confident of obtaining the victory for which they are fighting.General Staff,War Office, 20th March, 1917.

</content>
</cab>
