<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 213-216</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MILITARY SERVICE: EXEMPTIONS.I HAVE to report that, in accordance with, the directions of the War Cabinet, meetings have been held which have been attended by representatives of the Depart-ments particularly concerned with exemptions ; and that we have come to the following conclusions: 1. We are informed by the Army Council that 555,000 A and B i men will be required during the four months of April to July inclusive. . We have not deemed it to be our function to enquire whether this number is justified or can safely be reduced.Most of the fit men of military age now left in civil life are in protected industries. We are informed that, broadly speaking, the number of fit men in civil life amounts to some 2,000,000, and that over 1,500,000 of this total are in protected industries. Of the fit men under 31 years of age, the number in civil life is estimated at about 700,000, of whom&apos;well over 650,000 are in protected industries.After allowing for the men whom the Army Council expect to obtain from other sources (including youths who attain the age of 18 years and men who will be yielded by Tribunals), 330,000 men fit for general service should be obtained from the protected industries if the requirements of the Army Council are to be met.We are not satisfied that to take this number would not gravely endanger the supply of essential needs ; and we recommend that the Departments should not be required to release more than about 250,000 men fit for general service during the four months in question from the groups of industries indicated in appendix A to this Report, the men to be surrendered from the various groups in the manner set out in the appendix. We do not suggest any fresh proposals as regards the release of men from agriculture or the mercantile marine ; but consider that the Army Council should be allowed to continue recruiting from these classes under any interdepartmental arrangements which may exist or may be made.2. The men to be obtained under our proposals from the protected industries can be yielded only if an adequate supply of reasonably competent substitutes, of whom a large proportion must be of good physique, is forthcoming.We suggest that the position be put clearly before Parliament, and that it be pointed out that there are only three possible courses now open to the country: (a.) To take no action and to allow the armies to dwindle, or else to instruct theCommanders-in-Chief in the field to avoid casualties ; (b.) To raise the military age;(c.) To introduce some method of redistributing available labour so  as  to concentrate it in essential industries.The Army Council have urged the adoption of the second course, not so much with the idea of placing the older men in the Army as of applying indirect pressure to induce them to enter employment in the essential industries in substitution for younger men now protected who would then be withdrawn. They would therefore,&quot; propose that this measure should be accompanied by a vigorous combing out of young-men in essential industries, and by the granting of conditional exemption to men over the present military age who are prepared to act as substitutes for young men in essential industries. We recognise that there is much to be said for this view, but it is in effect industrial compulsion disguised as military service. The general feeling of the Conference was against the proposal. If industrial compulsion is necessary, the necessity should be openly declared. We think that the opposition which must in any case be anticipated would only be increased by this attempt to disguise its real nature. In these circumstances we favour the third course (e).It is. of vital importance to expedite substitution by withdrawing, by degrees,.the men required for military purposes from the protected industries in advance of the provision and submission of substitutes, and thus to create and maintain a vacuum [411]
in the protected industries which would automatically draw in the substitutes when available; provision to secure this end is contained in the scheme for releasing men (appendix A). As long as no labour vacuum is created in the protected trades, so long will employers continue successfully to evade the acceptance of substitutes for the men who should be released for military service.The Conference generally had grave doubts whether suitable substitutes in adequate numbers would be forthcoming without the adoption of compulsion for restricting unessential industries and for transferring men from unessential to essential work. Having regard, however, to recent pledges and to what transpired during the past week or two in the discussions on the National Service Bill in the House, of Commons, the majority of the members felt that any measure of compulsion of this kind was at present impracticable; and therefore they supported a proposal put forward by the Director-General of National Service under which, in addition to the existing scheme of National Service Volunteers, special appeals are to be made for Substitution Volunteers to take the place of eligible men released from essential industries for military service. It is proposed that these appeals should be directed to particular trades likely to yield suitable men of the kind required; that they should be made through local committees representative of employers and employed in each of the trades ; and that the selection and transfer of the men to be placed, as Substitution Volunteers should be carried out by these committees. If after a limited period the method could be shown to have failed, the case for compulsion would then be overwhelming and should command general assent.3. The Trade Card scheme should be superseded by the schedule of occupations, with age limits, submitted with this report (appendix B).The Trade Unions concerned must be informed before the new arrangements are brought into force. We understand that the Government have under consideration a number of other important proposals affecting Trade Unions. We suggest that all the proposals should be put before the Unions at the same time.4. Liability to serve with the forces should be extended to friendly aliens of Allied countries who are resident in this country. It may be necessary to have reciprocal arrangements with Allied countries. We think that the best plan would be to take power to apply compulsion by Order to British subjects in any particular foreign country. The position of Irishmen and colonials resident in foreign countries would have to be considered in this connection.5. A draft Bill is annexed (appendix C) for some minor amendments in the Military Service Acts ; among the proposals are (a) the reduction of the period of grace allowed after the expiration of an exemption from two weeks or, in certain classes of cases, two months to seven days ; and (b) the giving of power to the Army Council to require a rejected man to be re-examined after not less than six months, and a discharged man after not less than twelve months, from his rejection or discharge.6. We think that we should be authorised to review the position at the end of a month in the light of the further information which should then be available as to military and industrial requirements.In conclusion, we would venture to press very strongly on the War Cabinet that the strain on the man-power of the country is becoming acute, especially in view of the heavy industrial and financial responsibilities which have to be borne by this country; and that, therefore, it is imperative that more men should not be taken for military service than are really needed, and that there should be the fullest economy in the use of man-power, not only in industrv, but also in the Army.R.*March 21, 1917.* I have signed the Report as Chairman of the Conference; but I dissent from section 2 of the Report - in that I consider the adoption of compulsion necessary for the provision of suitable substitutes in adequate numbers.  Mr. Shackleton wishes to state that this is also his view.
Minority Report Submitted on Behalf of the Admiralty, the Army Council,and the Ministry of Munitions.1. THE Admiralty, the War Office, and the Ministry of Munitions are unable fully to concur in the report submitted by the Conference. &quot; The three Departments concur in paragraphs 1, 4, 5, and 6 of the report, ^They disagree with, paragraph 2 as from the end of sub-section (c) and provisionally disagree with paragraph 3.2. In the opinion of the three Departments, the one fact clearly established by the Conference was If the Armies in the field are not to dwindle, if the necessary ships are to be; built, if munitions, aeroplanes, &amp;c, are to be provided, young fit men now engaged in essential industries must be recruited and their places must be taken by older men or by young unfit men.The problem, therefore, is to organise effective and certain substitution.3. Effective and certain substitution cannot be secured on a voluntary basis to meet the requirements.The substitutes must be secured on a scientific plan. The non-essential occupations-must be carefully scrutinised and scheduled to indicate those in whichv working conditions are as nearly similar as may be to those in occupations under the Admiralty and Ministry of Munitions for which substitutes are required.In this way and in no other way can substitutes be obtained who, from the nature and environment of their ordinary work, are suitable for introduction into the occupations from which men are being released for military service.4. It is wholly impossible to effect substitution by creating a vacuum, e.g., in steel production, aeroplane and gun shops, without rgducing deliveries to His Majesty&apos;s forces. &apos;    &apos;      W^jtIt is undoubted that to create a vacuum will mcilitate substitution, but output will he temporarily affected.It is impossible for the Departments concerned to risk a diminution in the output of war machines of all sorts. Further, the equipment of the Allies is only second, in importance to the equipment of the British forces by sea and land.5. The War Office believes that the simplest and most direct way of solving the present problems is to raise the military age immediately to 45, with powers to raise the age to 50 by Order in Council.This measure would demand no new administrative machinery to make it effective-It would yield both recruits and a mass of men who in exchange for conditional exemption would be prepared to act as substitutes. The report states that this is an attempt to introduce industrial compulsion.If this contention be correct, industrial compulsion has been in force for approxi-mately twelve months. Tens of thousands of men are at present engaged in civil occupations holding exemptions conditional on their remaining in that occupation.The indirect effect of the Military Service Acts has in this manner provided hands for shipyards, munition works, coal mines, and other work of national importance, and will continue to do so as long as the grant of conditional exemption is legal.The War Office urge that the advantage of adopting the course proposed by them is, as above stated, that no new administrative machinery is required, and that therefore it may reasonably be expected to yield almost&apos;immediate results. It is fully recognised that if such a proposal were to be adopted the whole situation would require to be fully explained to Parliament.It is a matter of,record that Parliament never seriously objected to the War Office Substitution Scheme, which was based upon the grant of conditional exemption to men of military age acting as substitutes. * C. As the suggestion to raise the Military age was not approved by the Conference, the three Departments would urge xrpon the Cabinet the immediate adoption of some measure to obtain with certainty the substitutes required. If the provision of such substitutes be certain, the Admiralty, Wrar Office, and Ministry of Munitions have mutually agreed that they can adopt a procedure on the basis of the memorandum of agreement and ^ schedule forming appendix B of the general report, which, in their view, will obtain men for the Army from the e sential industries in which the three Departments are]jointly or severally concerned.7. The inter-departmental agreement is based wholly upon the certain provision of effective substitutes which was understood by the Departments to have been accepted.&apos;
as fundamental &quot;by the Conference at its first meeting. From this %e Conference departed at its last meeting by a narrow majority composed of the Department of National Service, the India Office, the Board of Trade, and the Scottish Office. The Home Office did not vote, and the Ministry of Shipping was against immediate compulsion on political grounds.The Ministry of Labour and the Board of Agriculture were not represented at the meeting at which the change of plan was adopted.The Local Government Board was in favour of compulsion.8. The Admiralty, War Office, and Ministry of Munitions desire to place it clearly on record that, in their considered opinion, the certain provision of effective substitutes in adequate numbers to replace the young fit men now employed in essential industries is an urgent matter of the first importance, on which-the successful- termination of the war directly depends.APPENDIX A.Method of Releasing Men from Protected Industries.MEN are to be released from the several groups of protected industries during the four months April to July, as shown in the table below. A. &quot;quarter of the men are to be released from each group each month.Group.Number of Men of Military Age.To be Released for Military-Service.Badsred men, including men badged by the Ministry of Munitions for other departments, but excluding men in shipbuilding&apos; and marine engineering works and men badged directly by the AdmiraltyGoal minesRailways     ., ..Dock labourPoliceCivil Service..Other certified occupations, excluding agriculture, mercantile marine, shipbuilding aud marine engineeringTotal700,000450,000 210,000 43,000 25,000 50,000 400,0001,878,000124,00055,000* 21,000 7,000 l,000f 2,000 40,000250,000under existing; agreements/tho Home* In fixing this quota account has been taken of the fact that, under existing agreementsy4&amp;* Qffica hit &apos;ir &apos;1 r-lr-&quot; to provide from coal mines 20,000 men for the Army, 6,000 for timber cutting, and 4,000 for iron stone mining.f Subject to the provision that the military authorities shall be entitled to claim additional men from the police force for military service to the number of members of the Metropolitan Police Force who are released from guarding naval and military establishments (2,700 members of the Metropolitan Police Force are now so employed).The release of the men is not to be dependent on the prior provision of a substi-tute for any man, and the quota for each month is to be released as a matter of course, subject to the following provision if by the end of a month it has been found that sufficient substitutes have not been available during the month, the number of men to be released for the next month shall be reconsidered-^It will be seen that some groups of industries are being required to surrender a larger proportion of men than others. The numbers were fixed after consideration of the representations received from the several Departments. A copy of these representations is annexed (appendix D).The several Departments should agree with the Army Council within one week as to schedules of occupations, with age limits, for releasing their quota of the men now protected by them.It will be well that employers&apos; organisations and trade unions affected by the new arrangements should be informed before any public announcement is made.* For the men to be released by the Ministry of Munitions and the Admiralty, this matter is regulated by the memorandum of agreement which prefaces tne schedule of occupations (appendix B).printed at the foreign office by c. r. harrison. 22/3/1917.

</content>
</cab>
