<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 217-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.

G.T.- 245

WAR CABINET.

ORGANISATION OF NATIONAL SERVICE.

(Report by Mr. Henderson)

"The War Cabinet, having regard to the importance of securing complete co-ordination between the Department of National Service and the Ministry of Labour, especially with regard to tho part to be taken by the Employment Exchanges on the allocation of National Service Volunteers, decided that Mr. Henderson, on behalf of the  Cabinet, should confer with the heads of, the two Departments and of any Other Departments which might be affected, with a view to securing thorough co-ordination of their activities." War Cabinet 98 (13).

In accordance with this instruction, I saw Mr. Chamberlain and Mr. Hodge with their officials on Saturday, March 17th, and discussed the relations between their Departments.

On Tuesday, March 20th, I again met Mr. Chamberlain and Mr. Hodge with representatives of the principal employing departments, namely, the Ministry of Ennitions, Sir Board, admiralty and Shipping Controller. At this meeting ? considered the relations which should exist between these Departments on one side and the Department of National Service and the Ministry of Labour on the other.

It was clear that there were no important differences of principle or method between St. Ermin&apos;s and the  Ministry of Labour. Both Departments recognise that their relations are governed by the decision of the Cabinet that the Employment Exchanges should remain under the control of the Minister of Labour who undertook to place them at the disposal of the Director for the purposes of National Service. What is principally required is a more precise demarcation of jurisdictions and arrangements for adjusting incidental difficulties and for securing regular intercommunication across the dividing lines.

After careful consideration, I believe that the following arrangements are best adapted to secure efficient and harmonious administration and I accordingly recommend them to the Cabinet.

The Department of National Service.

The primary function of this Department is to collect labour for National purposes. Mr. Chamberlain should therefore be responsible to the War Cabinet for all measures leading up to the enrolment of the volunteers, including publicity and propaganda, the scheduling of industries according to their degree of National importance, and the promulgation of orders or regulations which have for their, object the diversion of labour from the less to the more essential employments. After enrolment, he should determine all questions affecting affecting the rights ? status of a National Service volunteer under his agreement, including appeals against removal, the settlement of disputes as to wages and the determination of subsistence and travelling allowances. It should be his duty to report periodically, to the Cabinet, and to the Departments affected, the number of volunteers enrolled, the number prima facie available for transfer, and the occupations for which they can be  regarded as available.

Conversely, all prospective, demands for labour should be communicated to the Director by the Departments in order that he may be in a position ? watch the movement of labour generally and to frame his measures for the restriction of industries accordingly.
The primary function of this Department is to place labour for National purposes.     The Emplojrment Department of the Ministry should therefore be responsible for meeting individual demands for labour whether from among the number of National Service Volunteers, far Munition Volunteers or the general pool.     It should also carry cut the process of substitution as part of its ordinary business of placing labour and.all officiate engaged on that work should be under the jurisdiction of the Ministry of Labour.   -In this connect ion I should like to call attention to the proposal put forward by the Director and supported by the majority of Lord Rhcndda!s Committee under which special appeals should be direct ed to part icular trades which are likely to yeild suitable men as substitution volunteers to take the place of eligible men released from essential industries.     On the whole, this proposal appears to me to be the most likely to provide a solution of the problem-of industrial men power.      I agree, moreover, that the appeal T/ould be most effective if made through local joint committees of employers and employed and I think that such committees should be invited to take an cctive share in the business of selecting and transferring the men.     But ,the actual process ought to be carried&apos;.out by the Exchanges which alone can provide the necessary machinery.     Otherwise there, would be.two sys-1&quot; ems running side by side., one for ordinary volunteers and one for substitution volunteers and the result would be confusion.Co-ordinal ion. of two Department s.It has been suggested to me, and I entirely approve the proposal,, that there should be a Joint Executive Committee of the two Department e meeting at regular intervals to consider quest iohs of policy, and to effect such adjustments of practice or procedure within the terms of the Cabinet decision as the development of National Service may render desirable.     The Committee might consist of representatives of each Department with Mr. Chamberlain as Chairman and llr. Bridgeman as Vice-Chairman and should have as its Secretary an official of some standing whose duty it would be to maintain contact between the Departments.One of tho fi st questions to which the Committee should direct its attention is the dist ribut ion of duties among the staff of the two Departments.     Hitherto there has been a certain amount of duplication of work.and it appears probable that considerable economic might be effected by a more careful delimitation cf function and the transfer of part of the staff of St. Ermiri&apos;s to the Employment Department .Ot he r Depart merit s tThe Priority Committee of the Ministry of Munitions should continue to settle all questions of priorit y within the Departments represented on it, but a representative of the l\Tat ional Service Department should be added.     In any case where the Director is notified of a prospective demand for labour from any other Department hp- shpuld have the right to sumnon the Priority Committee which shouli them meet under his chairmanship with two representatives of the Department affected and det ermine, the question of the priority to be accorded to the demand.No arrangements for the withdrawal of men. in bulk from one industry to another (apart from the ordinary removals of volunteers through the Employment Department) should be undertaken by the Director without the concurrence of the Departments affectod or by the Department without, the concurrence of the Director.The Minister of Labour and  itr. Chamberlain have seen and concurred in this report. -. &apos; -r(Initialled)     A.H..   .22nd March, 1C:17.

</content>
</cab>
