<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 297-302</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tflPORT OF Hending 23rd Mar.ph...,1917 ..M. OFFICE OF WORKS for weekApplications have been received toprovide accommodation for the staff of the FrenchShipping Commission, which it is proposed to house in Lord Denmanrs House, 4, Buckingham Gate; and for the Conciliation, and Arbitration Board on Government EmployeesT Wages-.. and the staff of the National War Loan Museum, both of which are being housed in the New&apos;Public Offices Extension.     The staff of the Pensions Minis try have been provided wi extra accommodation in the Tate Gallery, pending definite arrangements as regards their accommodation Further applications for additional accommodation for the Shipping Controller, Ministry of Munitions, etc, are also under consideration.The removal of the Claims Branch of the Inland Revenue Department into Australia House was completed during last week-end and twenty other removals between buildings and thirty internal removals have been carried out during the week.Gardens, and the alterations to Empire, India-and Canada Houses.for the Allies Supply Commission have been put in hand.The Ministry of Munitions now occupy the fourth, block of temporary buildings in Montagu HouseThe
The engineering services for the Gentral Unemployment Insurance Building at new are now practically completed,2* The first report of the Inspectors engaged on the Government Office Accommodation Investigation has now been received by the Accommodation Committee.-A. i j-It deals with Armament Buildings and the Inspectors reeort that the distribution of staffs in this building is unsatisfactory from the point of view of the most effective utilisation of the  space and the realisation of adequate supervision and control and consequent economy of staff.     They also call attention to the presence of an undue amount of furniture in the rooms and the high consumption of electric current for lighting due to the uneconomical distribution of staffs,3-     Lancaster Gate Hospital,    which was prepared by this Department for the Committee of American Ladies, has been formally opened; and Latchmere House Hospital for the War Department is also in occupation.4.     Ploughing.    The area in Richmond Park, which has been ploughed, is now about 45 out of 72 acres; delay has been caused owing to the break-down of a large Tractor Plough, which is now being repaired.     The whole area of 79 acres in Bushy Parkhas
has been ploughed and two teams of two horses are cultivating and harrowing the soil, which has been 1imedoThe chestnut fence is being erected:  and the manures,  salt and seedoats for both Parks have either been received or are now in transit.5*     Silver.town.   Good progress has been made on this work to date.     The only difficulty experienced is in connection with the plastering, which has to be carried on while the families are in occupation, and the completion of 151 houses is being delayed on this account.Every house on the site  (with the sole exception of those which are being entirely rebuilt) has been roofed, slated, glazed and rendered weather-proof: and 115 houses are entirely replastered, papered and painted,     A further 50 houses will be completed in a day or two, which will make a total of 136 houses, 18 shops and one church given over to dateThe total number of men on the site is 1,574, and the number will be reduced week by week as the work proceeds.     The total cost to date is approximately  65,000, which includes-wages, material, cartage and sub-contractors.Good
Good progress has been made on the Boys 1 School where all the defective gables have been removed and rebuilt, and it is anticipated that practically the whole of the new brickwork required will be completed this weekoThe work on the School Keeper Ts House, is practically completed with the exception of distempering, and the electricians have rewired the whole of the premises.6.     The following works are in hand for the Ministry of Munitions and the Y,rar Office:-Mew Store at Birmingham (Soho).    Drawings in course of preparation:  estimated cost  35,000*Extension, to.. Machine Gun Repair Shops at Birmingham Rifle Range a    Quantities and drawings prepared:  estimated cost  12,000.New Mess Room at Dagenham Dock_She.ll Stores. Tenders invited.Additional Store andFuse Stores at Gloucester National Filling Factory.    Tenders submitted to Ministry:  estimated cost  6,000.Ee.w,.. Guard Hut at Greenford Assembling Station * Tenders submitted to War Office:  estimated cost  3,250.Schemes
Schemes prepared for adaptation of buildings as Hostels at Hereford Town.Additional..Store Shed at Irwell Park, Munition. S tojp3S^J^anche,,stero   Drawings prepared.Hew Laundry at Pembrey Hatipnal Filling Factory. Tenders submitted to Ministry: estimated cost  1,000.Two Additional Sheds at Qu edge ley. (Gloucester) Array Ordnance Depot.    Tenders invited,Equipment of Inspection Bond at Llanelly Shell Factorya   Work proceeding satisfactorily.Erection of 11 Cottages for Fire Brigade Staff at Morecambe National Filling Factory. Drawings in course of preparation: estimated cost  12,000.Addjti.o.na1... S-tor&quot;e Shed at Shepherd r s Bush Munition Stores.    Tenders submitted to the Ministry: estimated cost  8,500.HejL,Pain,t, Stor.e, at St. HelenTs (Lanc3) Munition, S,to.res.   Work commenced:  estimated cost  4,000,The extension of Messrs. Clement Talbotfs Motor Works at Hotting Hill, has been completed. Total cost  2,500.The work in connection with the equipment of Munition Factories at Gretna,&quot;Henbury, Bristol and elsewhere is proceeding.Labour
Labpur,,Shpr,tage&apos;.   Difficulty is being experienced, in connection with certain jobs on account of the scarcity of bricklayers, carpenters and navvies8

</content>
</cab>
