<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 309-312</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET^ fl,T. 266.WAR CABIKBT ,Prisoners of War Sub-Committee)Minutes of a&quot;Meeting held at the War Office on Friday March16th 1917, at 4.30p.m.PRESENT, -The Rt. Hon. The Earl Derby, K.G., G.C.V.O., C.B.Secretary of State for War.(in the Chair)The Rt. Hon. Lord Newton Directornof Prisoners Dept.Mr. J. P. Hope M.P.,Chairman of the Prisoners of War Employment CommitteeLieut- Gen. Sir H.E. Belfield K.C.3., D.S.O., Director of Prisoners of War, War OfficeBrig.-Gen G,K. Cockerill, C.B., Sub-Director of Military Intelligence, War Office.Major C. L. Storr.Secretary.In accordance with War Cabinet Instructions (War&quot;Cabinet 95, Minute 1) the Committee, assembled to consider the folltfw-ing questions:-(a) The Exchange of British and German internedCivilians.(b) The employment of Prisoners of War.The Committee had before them a Memorandum by Lord ^ewton dated March 3rd,  1917 (Paper G.T. 92 (annuxure A)  ) in which it was pointed out that there were interned in Germany approx-imately 4,500 British civilians^ whereas there were in the British Empire about 3$,000 Germans,  30,000 Of whom were of military age; that a formidable agitation was in progress in Great Britain to secure a general exchange&apos; of these civilians; that the only justification for an exchange of so dispropor-tionate a nature rested upon humanitarian grounds; that there was reason to believe that statements regarding conditions at Ruhleben were greatly exaggerated, and that even if the dis-,parity
in numbers were reduced by tho addition of French civilians.tho difficulties of transporting the many thousands ofGermans by soa would remain almost insuperable,.Tho Cojamittoo wore unanimously of the opinion that;(l)   Any - increase of the resources in man-power 6f the Central lowers must tend to prolong tho 7ar, and that as tho &quot;Jar is to a groat extent one of attrition, tho &quot;Dost and really most humane course to follow is to place and keep out of action as many of tho enemy as possible.-(2)   Taking all the circumstances into consideration, and more especially in view of tho disparity of &quot;tho numbers involved, tho proposal of a general exchange of interned civilians should not, in tho interests of tho otato, be entertained and thoy should report to the VJar Cabinet accordingly. -2,        (Oho Committee further considered a surest ion thatendeavours should be mado through diplomatic channels tooffoot an arrangement with tho German Government whorob37officers and men who havo been in captivity for over two ;yoars, might-.be interned in Switzerland or in some otherneutral country,Tho Committee took into consideration the following points:-(a) That under existing conditions tho Swiss Crcvernment would not bo prepared to accommodate more than a limited, number of such prisoners of both nationalities,(b) That wo have undertaken to waivo any Claim on Norway for such purposes in favour of Aussia,Tho Committee recommended that:.(1)   Tho v/ar Office should designate- what neutralcountries wore open to least objection for this purpose,(2) If the &quot;Tar Cabinet approve the suggestion&apos;in principle, the viows of tho French Government should, in&quot;&quot; tho first instance, be ascertained.
The Committee considered the question of effecting an exchange of British and Indian Prisoners of War for Turkish..The Committee recommended that:(l)c The Turkish Government he invited throughthe proper channels to come to a mutual arrangement with H.1C, Government fcr the -   exchange of 600 prisoners on each side as a preliminary to a wider exchange,(2) The selection of the men to he exchangedshould, he left to the Captor Government .(3) Officers and men both of British and Indiannat ional it \ ;  j n st ri ct pi oport ion to t he i r relative numbers,  should be included under the terms of the exchange,(4) The Admiralty be asked to report  if, andwhen, Shipping could be provided for the conveyance of the prisoners *(5) . I1 he proposal should be fcr unconditional-repatriation and not for internment.(6) If the War Cabinet approve the proposalthe Russian Government  should be informed of the action taken.The Committee examined the question of theemployment of Prisoners of War,     They had. before them aletter (G .T . - 8.1) (Annexur e B) dated 20th January. 1917 fromthe Secretary to the Prisoners of War Employment Committeeto the Secretary to the War Cabinet which&quot; stated that thenumber of such prisoners applied for by GovernmentDepartments alone already far exceeds the available supply,and which suggested that 1prisoners of War.  especially those skilled in Agriculture and Engineering should, if possible be released - from Prance for work in the United Kingdom, thekr places in France being taken by Turkish Prisoners of War now in Egypt.After due consideration, the Committee decided that there were manV difficulties in the way of carrying into effect the above proposal,  and that no mat erial.advant ages were likely to be gained by its adopt ion.The Committee considered the suggestion that
;.chleowig Hoist ein deserters from the German- Army, ofwhom there were ah out 7,000 in Denmark, might be conveyedo and employed in the United Kingdom,      It was understoodhat the Danish Authorities favoured the proposal.The Committee decided that :Mr. Hope, MAP. Chairman of the Prisoners of War Employment Committee should take up the question in consultation with the Home Department  and Foreign Office.The Committee also considered a suggestion that the facts relating to the imprisonment  of two German Officers in retaliation for the imprisonment of two British Officers, Lieut. Lamble and Lieut, Sate should he published nd Lord Derty undertook to bring the suggestion before he War Cabinet.(Intd.) D,2, Whitehall Gardens, 16th March,  1917,

</content>
</cab>
