<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 422-427</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
G.T.- 289WAR CABIEE2.CffgpMCl Oil POOD SUPPLIES, .Draft Minutes of a Meeting held at the&quot;Treasury, on Kon&amp;ey,Ilarch 19th 1917, at 4 p0m.Present:Tho Chief Secretary for Ireland,   (in tho Chair) The Secretary for Scotland, The President of the Board of ....griciilture, Tho Pood Controller.Brigadier-General AtkinsLto-Col, Gordon Leith &apos; Mia5or Prank Tonic Major&quot; Toynbeeinjbutt ondanoo.Par Office   Director of Supplies andTransport,War Office Army Canteens Committees 7/ar Office * war Office.Sir Eo Llewellyn Smith	. Board of	Trade,	Sir T, Aobinson	Board of	Trade.	Mi1. Garnham Sopor	Board of	Trade.	?2&apos;ofessor Plux	Board of	Trade	Sir Arthur Lee	Board of	Agriculture	&amp; fisherieslor. E, G, Kaurico	Board of	Agriculture	&amp; Pishcries111&apos;. Strutt	Board of	Agriculture	b PishericsSir Henry Rexi	Ministry ilinistry	of Food;	Cairbain Bathurst		of Pood.-	Mr. Dennis	Ministry	of Pood.	Mr, Ii. ii&apos;0 Paul	Ministry	of Pood.,	-Professor Adams	Prime Ministers Secretariat,		Mr. Thomas Jones	*7ar Cabinet Secretari		at.
0$ Sir Tliomas i-obinson explained that we received 40,000SUPPLY,   to 50,000 tons of meat per month from the aiver Plato,   It Y?as wart of our arrangement with tho -liver Plate Companies that&quot;if thoy supplied 50,000 tons, we would let 0,000 to 10,000 tons free for civilian consiuiiption in order to keep the domestic trade alive,Sir II. Llewellyn&apos; Smith concurred.   He considered it a great mistake for tho -.rmy to rely only upon importoa. meat on account of the waste of carrying power.   He stated that the Railway Executive considered that there would &quot;be a saving of transport if the Army bought meat locally instead, for instance&quot;, of conveying it from London tc Scotland and gave it as his opinion that they would probably be forced to &quot;buy locally in tho giitunn.Lord Devonport said that the imports of meat kept boof prices steady and that the frozen mutton and lamb from Australia and Hew Zealand also contributed to the steadying of prices,.Brig.-General .itkins said that tho Tfar Office had not taken any very distinct line upon this subject; he thought&apos;it easier for the 7ar Office to supply itself with chilled meat; the prices of he me meat would be raised for the civilian population if the 7ar Office-wore to commandeer any of tho hone supplies..   She &quot;Tar Office could not quickly arrange to take up home meat; thoy might do so at tho large centres where offals could be disposed of.   He considered offal one of the great difficulties.   On the point of contracts with the River Plate Companies, the&apos;7ar Office would ask them to quote prico for 7,000 to 9,000 tons a month.   If the &quot;Car Office paid the prico why should it upset the contracts?Sir H. Llewellyn Smith said the Jar Office would have to pay good-will.Brig.-General Atkins asked if this would be a good time for tho war Office to go upon the. home market.   7ere oattlo in good condition at present ? If tho &quot;far Office could get the chilled neat or its oequivalent, they would take 7,000 to 9,000 a month for about .4 months.Sir K. Llewellyn Smith said that the supply for the civilian population would have to be purchased on the home market in any case.Mr. grothoro agreed that tho -far Office should purchase chilled neat for tho Army.Mr. Hall said that tho Board of f.gri culture deprecated tho Army buying in tho homo market and would prefer that tho extra demand caused by the Army should bo&apos;insensibly spread over all the country and not be confined to a few contractors.     The meat stock of tho country should support a larger draft but it would be advisable to wait until tiro Auttuan before making any call upon it.   He foared that if meat prices roso, the farmers would be deflected from milk to meat production
 ore! ;eyonport asked if the prices would not rise when the meat was withdrawn from civilian consumption,Hr.Hall replied that third was so, hut the rise would he less than if it were known that the- ;:ar Office were the buyer.lord Devonport thought that if the chilled meat were released., prices would fly up.(Mr,Duke entered the meeting and Professor Adams vacated the Chair)..IhwProthero agreed that such might he tho case hut said that he thought with Kr.Hall the risk of prices soaring to a great height would he much greater if the Army came into the field as a buyer than from the purchase of chilled meat.Sir Thomas gobinson considered that tho more disturbing element would be the withdrawal of the steadying effect on prices of the imports of chilled meat.Sit Thomas Pobinson, replying to a question, said that the prices of chilled meat wore always&apos; a bit lower than those of home meat. It depended.- on the daily supplies in sight.     Ho pointed out that thero was another solution to the problem:    if we could get three or four additional ships from the River Plate we cou^d build up Z&apos;. reserve.General Atkins said that the shipping Controller was threatening to stop all imports of refrigerated meat.Mr,Roper said that 2,500 tons of chilled meat came in weekly for civilian use *Mr,Mump then entered.Sir Henry Rew estimated that the monthly home m-odiction cf beef and mutton was 100,COO tons and the monthly imports were 25,000 tons,Mr.Prothero stated that the problem resolved itself into this : a   certain proportion of Plate chilled beef was set aside for civilian consumption, namely between 8,000 end 10,000 tons.     The only question was whether that amount should be appropriated by the army from civilian use and the civilians thrown on home supplies or whether it should be retained for civilian use and the Army forced to make good its needs by purchasing on the home market.     The Board of   girl culture thought it would affect;, prices less if the chilled meat were appropriated by the Army asTit were known that the -Jar Office were coming upon the home market, prices would soar.Lord Devonport said he was advised by Sir LOhcmas. Robinson who controlled all the imports of meat, that he issued the supplies of chilled meat in such a way as to act as a counterpoise to the- homo   supply and pri c c s.lord -Devonport did not want to be driven to firing prices for homo grown supplies, though he feared that was coming..Sir Henry Hew said that the.price influence of the chilled imports was most effective in London markets but it indirectly controlled the rest of the country.Sir H.,Llewellyn Smith said that far more thai one-fourth was consumed in London^Jo-
Mr.Prothero said that the ohillod meat was about fifteen -per cent and the home-grown, about 05 per cent of the total.Mr.PuPe asked whet good it was goin^ to do the   rmy to take hold of the chilled lb at.iGeneral Atkins said that the reserves for immediate use by Prance were very low and would disappear by the end of this month.Mr.Puke said it was an advantage to the public to keep up corn-pet ing sources of supply.Mr.Prothoro asked whether General Atkins could not postpone building up a reserve till the Autumn.     Tho present was the worst possible time to go on the market.Lord Devonport pointed out that if the Jar Office spoiled the market, he should have to protect the public,Mr. Pro thero held that the interference of the ..&apos;ar Office no?/ would destroy the milk trade.Captain Bathurst said that was the most dangerous aspect of the problem.General Atkins urged that he had been warned *oy the Board of Trade that shipments would be fewer.Mr.Roper suggested that the Par Office should put their machinery into operation gradually.Mr.Duke suggested a Committee representing the War Office-, the Board of Agriculture and the Food Controller who should withdraw supplies weekly, quietly, and generally - partljr from home supplies aid partly from overseas.Sir Pi.L,Smith thought there was little hope of increased tonnage from the Shipping Controller.General Atkins stated that the Shipping Controller had recently askod to have the meat rations in the I ledi terrene an reduced&apos;.It was generally agreed that an effort should be made. to . induce the Shipping Controller to provide additional, temporary supplies from the Plato for about three months.General Atkins said ho would be glad to drop the building of thetiMr.Duke said there was no doubt about that.reserve now if, in caso of extreme urgency, he could come on ;he stores of mutton and lamb.Mr,3opcr said that the mutton and lamb belonged to the Government already.General v;.tkins said he wanted 35,000 tons in reserve which was equal to a month1 s supply.     He would be willing to spread the obtaining of the reserve over four months, .   He said he would be. satisfied if ho had a call on 15,000 tons at the first of every month.Mr.Hall said that the Board of Agriculture would, be glad if the Army reduced the stocks in July, August and Sevrfccinber.
iTIESS DAYS.Mr.Duke asked whether meatloss days were desirable.Lord Devonport said the Board of Agriculture&apos;s riew was that if you cut down meat you increased the- call on wheat and that it was important to build up a reserve of bread-stuffs.     He proposed to meet that point by rationing breed in hotels and restaurants.     He was against imposing meatless days on the general population but thought it could be done advantageously in the case of hotels.Kr.Ke.ll pointed out that the rise of prices since the Food Controller published his recommendations had been very lasge in the s:ase of substitutes like haricot beans (57$) lentils (50$) end cheese too, had gone up.lord Devonport pointed out that the price of chesee had gone up/because the Army had requisitioned all the imports from Hew Zealand.It was agreed not to recommend a meatless day for the general population.iir. Pro thero explained that unless it was made clear that milk prices would be left to their own level, or the farmer were, told that he should have remunerative prices next winter, he would take advantage of the high prices of meat and we should have a milk famine in the Autumn.     Owing to the high price of feeding-stuffs, some farmers last year lost on milk.     Prices tfere already fixed for the- summer.Captain Bathurst said that efforts had been made to get farmers to assent to prices based upon the cost of production, but the factors were constantly changing, for example, since the summer contracts, the minimum wage had been granted to labourers and the prices of meat had risen.     The temptation was very great to go in for meat or even milk.Mr.Duke read a Press notice which it was proposed to issue in order to encourage the farmer to provide milk next winter.     The notice was agreed in principle, with the suggestion that a stronger word than &quot;remunerative&apos; should be used.     It was also fgreed that a Committee should consider the production and distribution of milk.j r.Duke said that by this arrangement there would be no need to regulate the prices of meat on the market.Sir H. Llewellyn Smith said tho i,.rmy would thus have a monthly recurring option on the stores of mutton and lamb in case of emergency.&apos; - a. - - -Mr.Luke suggested and it was cgreed, that lord Devonport, Mr. Prothero, General Atkins and Sir Thomas Bobinson should devise some machinery for acting in a cautious way on the home supplies of meat when the proper time arrived and should call in representatives of the Irish and Scottish Offices, if and when required.     It was agreed that it was undesirable to cut down home stocks now.
POTATOES. Lord Devonport outlined his proposals for dealing with potatoes which included two potato-less days in public eating-places and an appeal to the well-to-do to use substitutes.It was agreed that it was undesirable to fix potato-less days for the general population..   (Initialled)    H.E.D.24,3.17.

</content>
</cab>
