<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 429-434</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
G x 1W - 2 91.I.     Report by an interdepartmental committee of the Board of Trade, kinistry of munitions and foreign Office on the future control of the World&apos;3 ketal Supplies.II.     Memorandum by the kinist^fy of Blockaae on the condition of the World&apos;s foetal Market.*     * * * he-port onfuture Control of the World&apos;3 ketal Supplies.The present restrictions on export from the British Empire of ores and metals of importance for munitions pur-poses and upon dealings therein are sufficient to prevent the diversion to foreign countries during the War of supp-lies produced within the British Empire, as a result of the acquisition by foreigners of mineral properties there;    and 30 far a3 the proposals now under consideration for the con-tinuance for a period after the War of the regime of pro-&apos; Mb.ltion -and licensing are adopted in the United Kingdom, and throughout the British Empire, those safeguards will be maintained for a time. .But we understand that in the -opinion of the legal adviser of the kinistry of kunitions there is even during the War no power to prevent the transfer to foreigners of mineral properties in the United kingdom, ana that special legislation will be necessary for that purpose.     We recommend, therefore, that in view of the facts set out in this Memorandum II. k5  Government should &quot;cake into immediate consideration the desirability and practicability of such legislation.Clearly, however, restrictive action if limited to the United Kingdom would accomplish little towards the object which we have in view and would need to be supple-mcnted by similar action throughout the British Empire. We are not aware how far it is possible for restrictions of the kind which we have in mind to be imposed in various parts of the British Empire Overseas, by administrative action alone, without recourse to fresh legislation; and we recognise that in some cases objection may be taken to any measures which tend to limit even temporarily the flow of foreign capital for development purposes.     We think, how-P\MjU b- ever may be the Case with regard to permanent restrictions upon alien ownership there is ample justification for-1-
restrictions imposed only for the period of the. War and a limited time thereafter.     We accordingly suggest that the opportunity afforded by the discussion which we under-stand is to take place shortly at the Imperial Conference on the general question of the mineral development of the Empire. should be taken to arrive at a decision on the limited proposal which we now put forward;    and we desire to emphasise the importance of that decision being taken at the earliest possible moment and of prompt action should the decision be in favour of the course which we recommend.The question of the extension of these restrictions to the transfer of mineral properties owned by British subjects in foreign countries, involving as it does a number of legal and economic considerations, is, we recognise, one of great difficulty, particularly in the absence of ?ny strong-combination of British metal interests which could take up properties which owners desire to dispose of for any reason. But we consider that it would be desirable that any restric-tions to be imposed on the transfer of mineral properties in the United kingdom and the various parts of the British Empire Overseas should be extended as far as possible to sim-ilar properties owned by British subjects in foreign countries where those properties are owned by British subjects domiciled or Companies registered within the British Empire, 3nd we recommend that such extension of the restrictions 3hould be taken into immediate consideration.V/e desire to emphasise in this connection the great impo tance of the establishment at the earliest possible date of a strong metal combination which may be in a position to acquire British owned mineral interests abroad in cases where the owners have legitimate grounds for desiring to dispose of them immediately.(sd,) PERCY ASHLEY JLBoard of Trade) ii11       CECIL. L, BUBATfAhniistry of munitions) 11       GEORGE KIBSTCP(Poreign Office).
SECRET.&quot;WAR   CABI1TFAsty   liELOBiiliDDA by the KIHIST^ of BLOCAAIiEon the condition of the World&apos;3 lietal Market.-x-jhk;-x-x*-*The Centre of control of the world&apos;s metal market is rapidly passing from Germany-to the united States of America, and it is to be feared that the tendency of the American groups which are now threatening to monopolise the metal business is towards the Central Powers rather than the Allies,     Ve have ample proof from their intcr-cepted correspondence that they are keeping in close touch with their German connexions, and intend to develop their business with Germany on a large scale after the wa r.As a consequence of the Paris Conference, a proposal was put forward by the French Government to found an inter-alied metal Bank, with a view to combat the old German de- omination in the moral trade, but it is understood that this proposal has now been modified in the sense that eaeh of the Allies is to form its own iietal Bank and that all the Banks so formed are to work in close co-operation.      But there seems to be a serious danger lest, when these Banks at last become operative,  the field for their operations will have become very much restricted.      The American groups have earned immense sums by selling metals to the Allies and are much more powerful financially than ever were their Ger-man prototypes.     They are spending these sums in buying up all the best mining properties that they con acquire in every quarter of the globe.Of these groups the richest and most powerful is the Guggenheim group, vhose chief asset is the American Smelting &amp; RefiningCompany.      This group, in spite of the German name of iifs founders,  is said to be genuinely American and to have no political sympathies but to base its actionsolely on money-majcing considerations. The American Smel-ting and Refining Company has signed the Copper Agreement and has scrupulously observed its conditions, and has furnished immense quantities of material to the Allies. nevertheless, the group would appear to be convinced that their interests will lie eventually in co-operation with the Central Powers rather than the Allies.The following is a summary of their recent activities, as gleaned from intercepted letters and from other sources.-1-
1. They are in constant communication with Berlin through their European agent, Koning.2.     They are storing copper for the Germans for after-war delivery.3.     They propose to deliver 1.000 tons of nickel to Germany on the conclusion of peace.4.      They have offered their German clients special terms for financing the. payment of their purchases during the re-conatruction period after the war so as to counterbalance the anticipated difficulties of Germany&apos;s foreign exchanges.5.     Their European agent, honing, was invited to attend a meeting of the Government War metals Committee at Vienna and informed his principals that he hoped to be able to form valuable connexions at this meeting.5.     Owing to our lack, of smelting and refining plant we have had to hand over to them for treatment the output during the war of the Otavi Copper Mine Is^m&amp;fc j^ss in what wa.s recently German South West Africa, while negotiating with the Government of the Union of South Africa with regard to this transaction,  the Amer-ican group are at the same time negotiating with the former German owners of the Mine at Berlin on the lines that the metal from the Mine shall be allowed to go to Germany after the war.7.     Since the outbreak of the war they have taken up the tin business and have erected up-to-date plant for treating ores from mines in Bolivia which they have acquired, thus threatening the market for our Straits tin in the United States of America.8. They are making offers to purchase the Tohidy pro-perty in Cornwall which has the richest tin and wolfram mines in Great Britain and a small harbour suitable for shipment of the ore.9.     They have approached the owners of the fanalyk Concession and kindred British interests in Russia with suggestions of purchase.10.     They are showing great activitynin Russia and have established their offices in the palace at Petrograd which used to be the Turkish E^bassey.II. They have an agent in hoHand who is engaged in negotiations for mining properties believed to be in Sp-^in.12.     They have bought mines (chiefly copper) in Chile, Peru, Colombia and South America generally.13.     At the some time they are supplying us with verylarge quantities of copper for war purposes and weunderstand that we cannot possibly dispense with their 3u&apos;oplias of this met?!.
We have enumerated at some length, the activities of the Guggenheim group so far as they are known, to us as this group is the most formidable force with which we have to reckon and its method of working is be ins, adopted on a lesser scale by other American groups which are more decidedly in the opposite camp.     Yogelstein, for instance, who is the American end of Aron Kirs ell of Halberstadt and is frankly pro-Gorman, and the American ketal Company, which is the United States emanation of the hetallgesell-scliaft.     Both of these firms have made large sums of money out of the war, and are expending them on the pur-chase of mining properties, chiefly in South. America.The groups which pile reputed to be whole-heartedly on the side of the Allies do not appear to be particularly active in acquiring new mi ning properties.    It is even reported that the Anaconda Copper nine, which is controlled by kr.Ityan and may be classified as definitely pro-Ally, is shortly to change ownership.    If there is any truth in this rumour the probality is that the purchaser is the Guggerheim group, who aldne would seem to be in a position to finance so gigantic a purchase.Other neutrals,  enriched by the war, are also -joining in the hunt for minin,- properties.The Butch firm of Wc H. kccller &amp; Company is acting in close co-operation with Helbig,  the&apos; representative of KruppWs in examining manganese,  sine and other mining properties in Spain.The Kristianssans JJickel Works in Norway are reported to be buying shares in the British American Hic^ol Corpora-tion - ( but this is only a newspaper report and may be a perverted version of some approved arrangement between the t wo 0 o mpan i e a.)Both the Swedes and the Norwegians are actively engaged in developing their own mining resources, more especially of pyrites and molybdenum.Evidence of direct German activity in the purchase of mining properties is not very plentiful, but they have agents at work in Spain, Peru, Bolivia, Chile and Bra si1. In an intercepted wireless message Burchardt of Hamburg recently instructed Weiss of Lima to  L.ry for options ending one year after peace for tungsten,molybdenite, vanadium, tin copper or borate mines in Peru, Bolivia and Chile.It is difficult to&apos; suggest any means for countering the purchase of mining properties in neutral countries except the early organisation of our awn forces with a view either to direct competition or co-operation with the more friendly neutral groups, but it ought to be within our power to prevent mine3 which are already under British control passing into the hands of the Aid eric an metal ring.     We have evidence that this is happening, and unfortunately it-o-
it is a natural process which is likely to increase rather than 60 diminish unless some means are found of checking it.     British Companies with mineral rights of prospective value find difficulty in obtaining capital here and are tempted by high offers from the American groups who have plenty of our money to spend.    It is possible that considerable transactions of this nature may already have taken place without our knowledge,but in some cases the intending British sellers have had qualms about transferring their rights without first obtaining the approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government and in this way the following cases have already come to our notice.1.     The proposed sale to the Guggenheim group of valuable tiia and wolfram mines in Cornwall (referred to above).2,     A proposal by the Mazapil Company of Manchester to sell their coppery gold, silver and lead mines in Mexico to the American Metal Company (the Metall-gesellschaft) for a sum of  1.300.-000Prom other sources We have discovered that:-1.   The Ahglo-Colombian Development Company which works platinum and gold mines in Colombia and is affiliated to the Consolidated Goldfields of South Africa has disposed of more than half its shares to Adoplh Lewisohn &amp; Sons of New York.2.     Prom an intercepted letter we find that a copper and silver mine in Bolivia, called &quot;La Guernica&quot; recently owned in England, is being offered to a German firm.    The Peruvian who offers the mine assures his German correspondent that he need have no doubt about the title-deeds as he himself completed the purchase in London and can give an assurance that everything is in order.The above instances which have come to our notice by chance during the last few weeks may be only a few out of many such transfers, but in any case we think they^are sufficient to prove the necessity of taking some immediat step to put some check on the indiscriminate alienation of-mining properties at present under British control.

</content>
</cab>
