<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/8/0 images: 454-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
3 B *)COPY. SSQRBT.- iG.T. 296. War Office,Whitehall, S.W.27th March, 1917.Secretary,War Cabinet.Herewith ten copies of a further telegram, Ho. 908 dated 25th instant, from General Kanbury-Williams, in connection with the question of command of the Russian Armies, for circulation to the War Cabinet please.(Signed)     F. MAURICE.  .D.M.O.
SECRET.G.T.296. WAR CABINET.OPERA T. I Q 11 S.25. 3. 1917.Prom:-        General Hanbury-Williams.n-.. n   t   n   qRepeated Ambassador.908.Two delegates of workmens unions of this district went yesterday to Grand Duke Nicholas1 car and with (group apparently omitted) to present their respects to him as Commander in Chief.Grand Duke said that as he was no longer Commander in Chief he could not receive them in this capacity.   Later on Grand Duke was asked by large number of workmen, mechanics and railway employees who came to see him why he resigned command. The situation was explained to them but they found it difficult to understand that he had resigned as result of invitation of the Government.   They were most indignant and assured Grand Duke that they all, including the Army, loved him and wanted him.   He was their man. They subsequently telegraphed to work-mens delegates in ORSHA and other neighbouring towns, who arrived here shortly afterwards and a mass meeting was held in local government theatres.   A unanimous resolution was passed in strong opposition to action of workmen party in Petrograd; and another that the resignation of Grand Duke should not be accepted by the government.    They telegraphed to Petrograd and other centres to this effect.    They evidently do not intend that the Grand Duke1s car should leave here as some damage was done to it yesterday.   This movement, if ably developed and directed, can have the happiest results so far as proving an unsurmountable obstacle of further machina-tions in Petrograd of the SOCIALIST anti-war party.     Further -developments are awaited.   Meanwhile my colleagues and I con-tinue to maintain absolute support of the Government.    I amnot seeing Grand Duke unless at his simple request.

</content>
</cab>
