<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/196/3 images: 73-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT. 82CP(77) 53 COPY NO17 May 1977CABINETSALE OF BP SHARESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Energy1. In Nov. rnber last year Cabinet decided (CM(76) 39th Conclusions) inprinciple to sell  500 million worth of the Government&apos;s holding of british petroleum (BP) shares during the present financial year.    This decision was taken at a time of financial crisis as part of a package of measures toreduce the Public Sector Borrowing Requirement (PSBR) agreed with theInternational Monetary Fund.     Specific proposals for a sale have recentlybeen considered by a Ministerial Group.2- Since the original decision last November the Government1 financial situation has changed for the better while opposition to the proposedsale of BP shares has been expressed by a wide spectrum of political opinion.    Recently it has become clear that the next few months may be anunprofitable moment at which to sell, and that a number of problems involved in the sale have yet to be resolved.3- This paper puts the case for postponing a sale.    Furtherconsideration should be given to the way in which any sale should be conducted and a final decision should be taken in the autumn in the light ofthe situation at that time.CHANGED FINANCIAL CIRCUMSTANCES4- Since last November the PSBR for 1976-77 has turned out to be 1 billion lower than was then anticipated.    The forecast for 1977-78 is still very uncertain, but profits of nationalised industries are improvingunexpectedly fast and local authority spending is being held down very^ghtly.    More important, financing of the PSBR has been transformed by ahuga sale of gilts at rising prices and with falling interest rates.    At thesame time sterling has stabilised at $1. 72 and the exchange reserves haveheen massively replenished by capital inflows.    The strength of sterlingarid of sales of public debt owe much to a growing appreciation of the valueof North Sea oil, to the revised outturn for the PSBR and to internationalconcern about unemployment which has as its counterpart a less doctrinaireSECRET
attitude to deficit financing.    Anxieties about growth of the money supplyhave been removed by proof that it can readily be cut back, despite a largePSBR, under control of the &quot;corset&quot;.    In present circumstances the strengthof the public sectcr&apos;s financial position is such that there is no financialcase for any immediate sale of BP shares to raise funds.    It is of coursepossible, although unlikely, that the financial situation may deteriorate.The possibility of such a deterioration makes a case for retaining the option of selling BP shares in the autumn.UNRESOLVED PROBLEMS OF SELLING BP SHARES5. The proposed  500 million sale would be the largest ever singlemarketing operation of its kind.     Under present plans the cost in terms ofcommissions, etc, could reach as much as  20 million, which to many ofour supporters would be an entirely unacceptable handout.    Worse than this,the market price of the shares has recently fluctuated considerably and the selling price is proving very difficult to judge.    A mistake in the timing andtechnique of selling could easily cost approaching  100 million off the proceeds of a given volume of shares.    It now appears also that therestriction of unilateral relief for taxes paid by oil companies, proposed inthe Budget and expected to yield of the order of  150 million in this financialyear, may be deferred to avoid damaging the jcoarket value of the BP shares.The financial uncertainties surrounding the proposed sale thus total as muchas  250 million.6. A second important issue is the risk that a sizable block of sharesmight fall into the hands of a single buyer, worst of all a foreign government.    By now it is abundantly clear that international trade in oilwill become a major political and strategic interest over the next twodecades and that BP&apos;s world role in this trade is a vital national concern.The incentive for other Governments to seek to acquire a significant stake in BP is st rong.    If any foreign Government succeeded in building up a10 per cent holding, that holding could become an important bargaining counter with BP, and ultimately, with the United Kingdom Government,-^-s yet no technique has been confirmed which would assure that the shareswhich it is proposed to sell are not directly or indirectly bought up with themtent of forming significant holdings.TIMING OF THE SALE&apos;* The quoted price of BP shares fell from  9. 35 early this year to atrough of  7. 80 and has now recovered to just over  9. 00.    PresidentCarter&apos;s statement in favour of Alaskan oil itself caused a jump of some 0. 70 in the share price.    Major events likely to push the price up in theficxt few months include:SECRET
a. Alaska coming on stream (August).b. A further price increase by the Organisation of PetroleumExporting Countries (July).c. The United States decision to stockpile oil (already announced inprinciple would. Growing evidence of BP&apos;s own financial strength as witnessed by:i.     The fact that no rights issue is now envisaged within thenext three years.li.    Its acquisition of the Buchan field in the North Sea and ofvarious other interests around the world.iii.   The huge cash flow generated by the Forties field.All these factors make a further substantial rise in the share price almostinevitable.    For this reason alone it would be rash to sell any Governmentshares in BP before the autumn.    Taking account ^lso of the present strength of sterling and the public sector finances, as well as of theunresolved difficulties over the management of a sale, an early sale wouldseem entirely inopportune.recommendations. Colleagues are invited to agree that -a. There should be no sale of BP shares before the autumn.b. The proposed sale should be reviewed then in the light of thefinancial situation, BP&apos;s own prospects and movements in BP&apos;s share price.c. In the interim further consideration should be given to themodalities of a sale and to associated tax issues with a view to preventing the build-up of any significant single foreign holding, tominimising costs of the sale, and to maximising Governmentrevenue,A W Bdepartment of Energyl? May 19773SECRET


</content>
</cab>
