<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/31/10 images: 124-131</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(T&amp;XS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOTONIvaENT),It is requested that special care may be taken to ^ . jPfensure the secrecy of tins uocuinent.COPY NO.   10MOST secret.M. .(48.). 104TH CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 2eConfidential Annexe(.5th August: 1942   -   6.30 p0m0.)MIDDLE EAST.Military-Si situation.(previous reference?W.M. (42). 101st-Conclusions,Minute 1.)Tho War Cabinet had under consideration a Report by the Chiefs of Staff Committee on thesituation which might arise in the Middle East inthe event of Germany obtaining a major successagainst Russia (war.(42) 335) and a Report by the oil Control Board on the effect that the loss, of theAhadupA o^llggujjplios would have on our- war effortTHE DEPUTY PRIME MINISTER said that   in giving instructions that the Chiefs of Staff report should be circulated to, and considered by, theWar Cabinet,, in his absence, the Prime Minister had had it in mind that his colleagues should be aware of the issues at stake- and the main considerations affecting these issues, and thus be in a positionto take decisions when the time came,    It was clearlyundesirable to come to any hard and fast &quot;conclusion on this problem while it was under discussion bythe Prime Minister and Commanders-in-Chief in theMiddle East^and there was now no point in despatchingthe telegram ofc Annex I to the report. which was already partly out of date0THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF explained thatthe Report had been prepared in response to atelegram? from the Middle East Defence Committeedrawing attention to the grave issues with which we might be faced, and propounding the choice whichmight have to be made if the campaign in Russia wentvery badly for the Russians.   We might, in that event,find that we had insufficient forces to hold theNorthern Front and to defend Egypt from the threatfrom Libya.   We should then have to choose betweendeploying our resources so as to secure the persian oil field with the consequential loss of Egypt,or concentrating on the defence of Egypt with the risk that we should lose the Persian biloFor the reasons given in their Report, theChiefs of Staff had come to the conclusion, whichwas set out in paragraph 19(b) of the draft telegram to the Commanders-in-Chief, that, should the worstarise, every effort should be made to hold oh to theAbadan area, even at the risk of losing the NileDelta.   The&apos;problem was mainly cine of oil.    The lossof the Persian Gulf oil facilities could only bemade good by the services of an additional 270tankers.   Without these, a drop of up to25&amp; in our&quot;war effort.would become inevitablec;    The loss ofAbadan would probably result in the eventual loss ofEgypt and the grave weakening of our position in thewhole of the Indian Ocean area.1&quot;*Annex III to W.P.(42) 335^
mm
The following were the main points brought out in the ^-short discussion Wiich followed?a-(i)   THE MINISTER OP LABOUR AND mTlONAL SERVICE,said that the urgency of the problem;1 seemed to depend oh the Chiefs of &quot;Staffsassessment of the threat to the Northern.     Front.   In previous assessments of this nature, the mistake had always been made. &apos; - of under-rating the speed with which theenemy could advance.   The War, cabinet should decide this issue on the worstpossible basis and should assume that the- threat to the NorthemPront might developat least one month sooner than the estimatein the. Report.(ii)    THE VICE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERALSTAFF said that the Chiefs of Staff&apos;estimate was based on very carefulcalculations, worked out by experts, pnthe assumption that Russian resistance ontheir Southern Front had completelycollapsed^   There were only three routes &quot;leading from Russia through the Caucasus,and the nature of the country and the comparative ease with which these routesoould be interrupted should make it verydifficult for the Germans to build uplarge forces quickly.(iii)   THE MINISTER OF PRODUCTION said that itwould be equally upsetting to our plans to over-estimate &apos;the danger as to under-estimate it*.   There was obviously a vastdifference between the rate at which a tactical success in the Western Desertcould be exploited and the rate at which an Army could work its way through difficult and mountainous country on the Northern Fronts(iv)    THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA drew attention to the great importance of developing the lateral communications between the Northern and Western Fronts inthe Middle East.     He hoped that therailway from Karbala to Rutbah would be pressed forwardo(v)   THE - SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs suggested that the problem had been over^-,simplified.and doubted whether, when thetime came, the issue would be a olearrc^tdecision between abandoning Egypt or losing &quot;the Persian oil fields^ ^(vi)   THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said thatthere still seemed time to &quot;insure&quot; tosome extent against the possible loss ofAbadan by boosting, the Allied produotiph  \of tankerso   1

The first LoW of rTthe ^tMlralty&quot; undeptooK i - -to prepare a review of the tanker situation^including both the present estimated output from U,K* and U*S, production and theestimated rate of futaxre losses^    :Ti^0^gxbform the /starting point for.Aa,;Suhse^en^discussion on the possibilities of increasedtanker pr      Jtion,     The ^irst. Lord indicated that the:;:      ,.s no likelihood of our -being able to id tanker output in this countryto any ar.    aeiable extent and that we should therefore make   to look to the U.S,A, forany such increase.     Up -to date they hadbeen generous in their assistance   in. tanker tonnage,____________________       nV There was general agreement that, in the -circumstances, there would be no advantage in pursuing,the discussion in an attempt to reach a decision on &apos;the problem posed by the Gommanders-in-Chief,The War Oabinets-(a) Took note of the Report by theChiefs of Staff Committee and ofthe issues which were at atake in- .   - the Middle Easto(b) Invited the First Lord of the admiralty to prepare a review of the tanker position on the lines which he had suggested,.Great George Street, S,W,.lt




</content>
</cab>
