<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/9/27 images: 216-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   October 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)265th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 265 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at Paddock on Thursday,October 3, 1940, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Lloyd, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.The   Right   Hon.    Sir   archibald sinclair,  Bt.,  M.P.,  Secretary  ofState for Air.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of . State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The  Right  Hon.   Sir  Andrew  RaeDuncan,   M.P.,   President  of   theBoard of Trade.Sir Horace J.  Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury (Item 9).Admiral  of  the  Fleet - Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21801-1]b
WAR CABINET 263 (40).; 3Contents.M muteNo. Subject. page 1.      Naval, Military and Air Operations....       ....       ....       ....     149Air operations.Naval operations.Enemy attacks on shipping.Military operations Middle East.2.      France...................&apos;..............     149Policy towards the Vichy Government.3.      Germany and Italy    ....       ....       ....       ....       ....       ....     149Possible future strategy.Reinforcements for the Middle East.4.      Air Raid Damage      ....      ............      ....      ....     150Stepney shelter.Rescue parties.Clearing of debris: use of troops.Funerals.5.      The Far East............................     150The Burma Road Agreement.6.      The Far East............................     151Attitude of Japan.Position in event of U.S.-Japanese war.7.      The Far East............................     152Suggested visit of a United States naval force to Singapore.8.      Switzerland    ............................     152Violation of Swiss neutrality by British aircraft.9.      Air. Raids       ....      ........      ....      ....      ....      ....     152Compensation for damage.10.      Aircraft Production  ....       ............       ....       ....     153Proposed aircraft defence police.
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 264thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.naval operations.Enemy attacks on shipping.MilitaryOperations:Middle East.1. The Chief of the Air Staff reported that on the previous day 250 enemy aircraft had been over this country but had onlydropped a few bombs on the South Coast.   Casualties had been :-Our own 1 machine (pilot safe but wounded).Enemy 10 certain.1 probable.2 damaged.On the previous night the weather had been very bad but a few of our bombers had reached Berlin. We had lost 1 medium and2 heavy bombers.Our aircraft had bombed enemy concentrations and aerodromes at Assab.The Chief of the Naval Staff reported that the mediterranean fleet had returned to Alexandria. Two Italian U-boats had been sunk in the Mediterranean.The York and the Warspite had been unsuccessfully attacked by bombs and had shot down a number of enemy aircraft.On the previous day we had lost a merchant ship of 4,600 tonsand belated reports had been received regarding the sinking of3 other merchant ships far out in the Atlantic.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that therehad been no change in the situation in the Middle East. A numberof perimeter camps in the Desert had been observed. The italians had not yet mended the road between Sollum and Sidi Barrani.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.France. 2.   A further discussion took place on this subject and isPolicy towards recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinetthe Vichy Conclusions.Government.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 264th ----Conclusions,Minute 6.)Germany and 3.   The Foreign Secretary drew attention to two telegramsItaly- (Nos. 1265 from Angora and 638 from Sofia) reporting statementsPossible future that the German Government did not now expect to succeed instrategy. invading England, but that they hoped by bombing the midlands and South to bring about the collapse of the present Governmentand its replacement by a more amenable one.What then was likely to be Germany&apos;s probable strategy inthe next few months?Certain indications pointed to a move of German troops throughItaly to Libya, to take part in the Egyptian campaign; this seemedmore likely than an attempt to move through Spain and Morocco,or a move into the Balkans.Should further reinforcements be sent to Malta or the middle east? The Prime Minister thought that this should be consideredagain in a few days&apos; time.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.[21801-1] b 2Reinforcementsfor the middle east.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 260thConclusions,Minute 8.)
Air raid damage.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 264thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Home Secretary said that very little damage had been caused in the previous 24 hours. There had been a serious fire ata rubber factory in Lancashire.Reference was made to the fact that the &quot; All Clear &quot; had beensounded on the last two nights early in the night, and had been followed, after an interval, by another &quot; red &quot; warning. This had resulted in a certain number of people leaving their shelters andsubsequently returning to them. On the other hand, it was pointedout that the period of an hour during the previous night betweenthe &quot; All Clear &quot; and the further &quot; red &quot; warning had given greatrelief to civil defence services, and had speeded up traffic. Therewas, therefore, much to be said for continuance of the present practice.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that Mr. VictorCazalet, M.P., who had visited the large shelter in Stepney on theprevious night, had given a very favourable account of the conditionsthere.Reference was made to complaints of delay in digging outpeople who had been buried under houses.The Home Secretary said that, though he had heard of suchdelay in one or two isolated cases, on the whole the rescue parties had worked very quickly. The proposal that soldiers should helpin clearing debris had been satisfactorily settled at a conference the previous day. It was proposed that soldiers should lend a handW.M. (40) 26lst during next week, as a temporary arrangement, to overtake arrears,Conclusions, while a civilian labour force was being organised. Some discussionMinute 3.) ensued as to the funerals of the victims of air raids. The HomeFunerals. Secretary said that arrangements had been made for state funeralsat the State expense for all victims of air raids.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.StepneyShelter.RescueParties.Clearing ofdebris: use oftroops.(previous reference:The Far East. 5.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theThe BurmaSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P. (40) 400).Road It was argued in the Memorandum that, in view of theAgreement. Japanese aggression in Indo-China, and of the German-Italian-(Previous Japanese Pact, the question was not so much whether we should reference: re-open the Burma Road, as when we should do so. Lord LothianW.M. (40) 26lst had made it clear that the case for refusing to renew the BurmaConclusions, ROad agreement, as seen from Washington, was overwhelming; and minute 4.) he had reported Mr. Cordell Hull as saying that he &quot; greatly hopedthat we would re-open the Burma Road.&quot;In these circumstances, the Foreign Secretary suggested thatthe best and least provocative method of announcing our decision not to renew the agreement would be by means of a reply to a parliamentary Question on Tuesday, the 8th October, in the sense that the agreement had been concluded for a definite period, and contained no provision for renewal, and that in any case in viewof recent developments His Majesty&apos;s Government would have feltunable to agree to renewal, if this had been in question.The Prime Minister was clear that this was the right decision.He did not believe that the Japanese would declare war upon us as a result. We should be justified in taking the line that, whereaswe had expected the Japanese during the interval afforded by the currency of the Burma Road agreement to make a genuine effort toreach an all-round settlement, all they had done was to make theGerman-Italian-Japanese Pact. In these circumstances, we had no option but to carry out our duties as a neutral in the Sino-Japaneseconflict.
The Far East.Attitude ofJ apan.Position in event of UnitedStates-japanese war.6. In connection with the previous Minute, the foreign secretary said that the Dutch Foreign Minister, at a recentinterview, had remarked that the attitude of the Japanese in regardto their dealings with the Netherland East Indies had become much less stiff about the middle of August, i.e.. after the first great airbattle in this country in which we had defeated the German airforces. The Dutch Foreign Minister did not think that the japanese were in a position to embark on any important new military ventureat the present time.The Prime Minister drew attention to&apos; a recent telegramNo. 1901 from Sir Robert Craigie in which it had not been taken for granted, as it should have been, that the British Empire wouldbe involved in the event of war between the United States and japan.The Foreign Secretary said that he would make it clear toSir Robert Craigie that, if the United States were at warJapan, we should certainly declare war on that country.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.with it was significant that Sir Eobert Craigie, who three months ago had thought that Japan would declare war on us, if we did notclose the road, was now in favour of the termination of the agree-ment.The War Cabinet-(a) Unanimously endorsed the views of the Prime Minister andthe Foreign Secretary, and approved the procedure suggested by the latter, under which the announcementas to the non-renewal of the Burma Road agreement  would   be   made   in   Parliament   on   Tuesday,   the8th October.(6) Invited the Dominions Secretary to telegraph that day tothe Dominion Governments, fully apprising them of allthe circumstances, including the attitude adopted by theUnited States Government, and informing them of thedecision which we proposed to announce on the8th October. The telegrams to the Dominion Govern-ments should take the form that we should take this action, subject to their concurrence. There was no doubtthat the views of the Dominion Governments weresimilar to our own.(c) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct Sir stafford cripps to seek an interview with M. Molotov to apprisehim fully of all the circumstances, including the attitude adopted by Mr. Cordell Hull, and to inform him of thedecision which we proposed to announce on the8th October. In stating the case to M. Molotov, sir stafford Cripps might take the opportunity of drawing attention to the increasing harmony of opinion andidentity of interest between this country, the UnitedStates, Russia and China. These instructions would furnish the reply to telegram No. 805 from Moscow.(d) Invited the Foreign Secretary to send instructions to our ambassador in China that General Chiang Kai-shekshould be informed of this decision on Sunday, the6th October.(e) Invited the Prime Minister to communicate their decision in a personal telegram to President Roosevelt.
The Far East.Suggested visit of a UnitedStates naval force to singapore.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 241stConclusions,Minute 4.)7. The Prime Minister drew attention to telegram No. 1905from Tokyo in which it was suggested that a United States naval force might pay a visit to Singapore. He felt that this suggestion was one that we should follow up promptly. It might be possibleto combine a courtesy visit to Singapore by an American BattleSquadron with the holding of the British-American-DutchTechnical Conversations which had been suggested by Mr. CordellHull (Washington telegram No. 2147).The War Cabinet Invited the Chiefs of Staff to consider as a matter of urgency whether it was desirable that British-American-Dutch Technical Military Conversations should be held at singapore, and to submit to the Foreign Secretary definitesuggestion which he could communicate to Lord Lothian.Switzerland. 8.   The Foreign Secretary informed the War Cabinet that onViolation of the previous day the Swiss Minister had discussed the R.A.F.Swiss neutrality violations of Swiss neutrality with complete good humour. If weby British had to pass over Switzerland, he hoped that as far as possible weAircraft. would use the Geneva route.   Later on the weather might make it(Previous impossible for us to fly over his country, in which case he hoped that reference: we would make a virtue of necessity and draw attention to theW.M. (40) 254th correctness of our attitude. He was emphatically not in favour of conclusions, a policy of concentrating into, say, one week of intense aerialMinute 7.) activity all the visits to Northern Italy which we might otherwise have paid over a period of, say, six weeks.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Air Raids.Compensationfor damage.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 246thConclusions,Minute 4.)9. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer outlining a scheme of compensationfor damage to immovable property (W.P. (G.) (40) 251).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it had originally been proposed that the charge of 3 per cent, to be levied on thecapital value of all immovable property, should not be paid until after the war. The Lord Presidents Committee and the Consulta-tive Council at the Treasury had, however, both thought that some payment on account should be made now. This was clearly desirable,provided that suitable machinery could be devised for the purpose.It had been thought that this could best be done by using themachinery of Schedule A, and by levying an extra 2s. in the  .This would mean a payment of  2 10s. on a house worth  500 withan annual value of  25.In discussion, general agreement was expressed with the scheme.It would give great assurance, especially to the less well-to-doproperty-owners, to know that if their home or place of business was destroyed, they would get compensation for it. Further, thisscheme of compensation would prevent the value of the propertydeclining. The Exchequer would benefit from this, e.g., in deathduties.The President of the Board of Trade said that he had favoured an alternative scheme whereby persons whose property was liable tothe charge of 3 per cent, would be invited to liquidate the chargevoluntarily during the war, if they so desired; but if they did not so wish, no payment should be made until after the war. If,however, this scheme could not be accepted as an alternative to the extra 2s. in the   under Schedule A to be paid on account, he thendid not wish to press it.
aircraft production.ProposedAircraft DefencePolice.10. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Aircraft Production (W.P. (40) 391).The War Cabinet-Invited the Chief of the Imperial General Staff to discussthe proposals in this Paper informally with the Ministerof Aircraft Production.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,October 3, 1940.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would like tohave seen the scheme worked through the Insurance Companies,and he still thought that this might have resulted in reducedadministrative costs.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that this possibility hadbeen explored and was not regarded as practicable, but he wouldbe glad to discuss the point further with the First Lord.It was pointed out that a number of property-owners, e.g.,those whose businesses had been destroyed or whose property wasin areas which had been evacuated, could not be expected to payanything now.The Chancellor of the Exchequer agreed and said that thiswould be dealt with as a matter of administration. He proposed tomake this clear when introducing the Bill.The Chancellor of the Exchequer also drew attention to theprovision in paragraph 6 of his Paper for a voluntary insurancescheme for furniture and personal possessions above the incomelimits for free compensation. If possible, this scheme should bebrought in at the same time as the scheme for compensation forwar damage to immovable property.   This was agreed to.The War Cabinet Approved in principle the proposals set out in theChancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s Paper, and invited him to consult various Parties and Members in the House, andto arrange for a draft Bill to be submitted to the home policy Committee.




</content>
</cab>
