<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/198/15 images: 229-231</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
INT IS THE PROPERTYOF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(77) 105COPY NO14 November 1977CABINETNATIONAL INSURANCE CONTRIBUTION REVIEW 1977Memorandum by the Chief Secretary, treasury* In their paper (CP(77) 104) the Secretary of State for Social Servicesand the Minister for Social Security propose that the Class 1 joint contribu-tion rate to be paid from next April by employers and employees contractedinto the New Pensions scheme should be 16 per cent (6 per cent employees and 10 per cent employers) rather than the 16^ per cent (6j per centemployees and 10 per cent employers) which is provided for in the legislation and generrlly expected to apply.    The Government Actuary1 s calculationsshow that a 16^ per cent rate would produce a deficit in the national insurance Fund in 1978-79 of some  33 million;  whereas a 16 per cent rate would produce a larger deficit of some  402 million.    There would be asimilar cost to the Public Sector Borrowing Requirement.2. The Chancellor of the Exchequer and I think it would be imprudent togo for the lower contribution rate for the following main reascns:-i.       People are hoprixjg to see further tax reductions in the 1978Budget.    In particular, the Trades Union Congress will be looking for either further thresholds, or a reduced rateband of tax.    However, the scope for this will depend on how the economy develops between now axsd next  spring, and in partieul&amp;r rrnthe outcome on payc    The position could well be tight.    A sum ofover  400 million could be important to a politically viable Budget.ii.       The choice is between helping to make room for tax reductions in the next Budget, and announcing now a smaller increase in national insurance contributions next April than would otherwise have takenplace.    I have no doubt that the former would have a greaterperceived effect on take home pay.iii.       We shall be able to help more low income households throughtax reductions than through lower increases in national insurance contributions for those contracted into the new scheme.1
iv,       We should clearly not undermine the basis of the national insurance Fur.dP    But a .163- per cent rate will involve a substantialturn round from surpluses in previous years, including the largesurplus expected this year, to a deficit in 1978-79.    And there canbe no certainty that it will be possible to reduce this rate in the nearfuture,,    It is wholly defensible, therefore, not to plan for a largedeficit this year particularly cince the accumulated balance of theFund will still fall in real value next year measured in terms of thenumber of weeks of expenditure for which it provides cover, sincebenefits will be further increased next autumn,,    The assumptionson which the Government Actuary&apos;s calculations are based could, ofcourse, prove wrong.    But this could go either way - giving a loweror higher deficit on the FundL    If, for example, earnings increased,by more than ia assumed, so would unemployment, which would add to the deficitsCONCLUSION30 As explained in paragraph 2 ii0 above, there is a clear choice between a smaller increase, but still an increase, (a married man on average e irnings would pay 40p rather than 60p assuming an equal splitbetween employees and employers) and having nearly  400 millionavailable in the Spring Budget,    I believe the difference between these rates is too small to forgo the advantages of having so large a sumavailable for either income tax reliefs or the other options such a sumwould provide.    The Chancellor of the Exchequer and I therefore recommendthat the joint contribution rate to apply from next April should be set at16-r per cent, divided as to 10 per cent for employers and h\ per cent foremployees, as provided for in the present statute.JBTreasury Chambers14 November 1977


</content>
</cab>
