<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/9/16 images: 128-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)254th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document,WAR CABINET 254 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime Minister&apos;&amp;Room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Thursday, September 19, 1940, at12 noon.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C.Lord Privy Seal.R. Attlee, M.P.,The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook.Minister of Aircraft Production.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Item 9).The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State&apos; for theHome Department and Minister- ofHome Security.The Right Hon. Lord Lloyd, Secretaryof State for the Colonies (Items 6to 8).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. R. H. Cross, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Items 8 and 9).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1 to 7).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.
WAR CABINET 254 (40).minute no.1Contents.Subject. page naval, Military and Air Operations        .........      83Air casualties.Air operations.Naval operations: The Mediterranean.Military operations:   The Middle Bast.2      France   ...      ...      ...      ...       ...      ...      ...       ...      83The French fleet.3      Overseas Evacuation ...      ...      ...      ...       ...       ...      844      Air Raid Damage      ...      ...       ...      ...      ...       ...      84Magnetic mines.5      The Sudan      .....................      84Appointment of a new Governor-General.6      The Colonies   ...      ...............      ...      85Colonial Governors.7      Switzerland     ...      ...      ...       ...      ...       ...       ...      85Violation of Swiss neutrality by British aircraft.8      Malta    .....................      ...      85Provision of supplies.9      Shipping ...............      ......      86Merchant shipbuilding and other measures to increase the supplyof merchant shipping.10      United States of America     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      86Supply of munitions.
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 253rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Casualties.Air Operations.1. The Chief of the Air Staff said that the air casualties during the twenty-four hours ending 7 a.m. that morning had been as follows : -Enemy.By Fighters-BombersFightersDestroyed. Probable.  Damaged.36 5 710 11 12461619Our Losses.Twelve aircraft, but 9 pilots safe.Nearly 200 British aircraft had carried out bombing operations on the previous night, mainly against the invasion ports. Exceptfor attacks on Berlin, which would be resumed as soon as the weather was favourable, it was intended that our bombing effort should be concentrated almost entirely against these ports.Naval The First Sea Lord reported that H.M.S. Golden Eagle had hitOperations.       an aircraft which had been about to lay mines in the thames estuary during the night 17th-18th September.   The aircraft hadexploded in mid-air.The U-Boat which had been attacked by an aircraft of the fleet air Arm off Cape Wrath on the 14th September had almost certainly been destroyed.A report had just been received that our submarines wereattacking 8 enemy merchant ships off Texel.The On the 16th September an aircraft from Illustrious had setMediterranean,   one merchant ship on fire at Bengha-zi, damaged several other ships and sunk a destroyer.A further report had now been received about H.M.S. Kent.She had been attacked by two torpedo aircraft in bright moonlightat midnight on the 7th-18th September.   She had been hit by onetorpedo which was suspected to have been of the magnetic pistoltype.  Nubian had had her in tow by 3 a.m. and she ought to arrive in harbour that day.On the night of the 7th-18th September Ladybird hadbombarded the Escarpment Road, Sollum, at close range, while Junoand Janus had attacked enemy concentrations at Sidi Barrani.Military The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that there was noOperations: news of importance from the Western frontier of Egypt. TheThe Middle Italians appeared to be consolidating their position at Sidi Barrani.East. There were signs of an Italian advance on the Sudan front,south of Kassala. The enemy appeared to have crossed the RiverGash and to have completed the concentration of a columnconsisting of some 6,000 men, together with artillery, tanks andlorries. It appeared unlikely that any deep move into the Sudanwould be attempted before October. The R.A.F. were attacking the enemy concentrations.Part of force &quot; Niblick &quot; had landed at Port Sudan and was now reinforcing the Sudan.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.France.The french fleet.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 253rdConclusions,Minute 4.)2. Further information was reported in regard to the move-ments of the French Fleet, and is recorded in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.
OverseasEvacuation.(previous references:W.M. (40) 207thConclusions,Minute 13, andW.M. (40) 204thConclusions,Minute 7.)3. The First Sea Lord reported that four merchant ships hadbeen sunk. These included the City of Benares, which had bad onboard 100 children and 100 adults for Montreal. On present information the saved included only 18 women and 15 children.The Benares&apos; boats had been rushed by lascars and capsized.The view was expressed that there was much to be said, inpresent circumstances, for discontinuing the scheme for evacuatingchildren overseas.The War Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Information to arrange for suitablepublicity to be given to the torpedoing of this ship.(2) Invited the Home Secretary to report to the War Cabinetwhether,  in  present  circumstances,   the  scheme  forevacuatingchildren overseas should be continued.Air raid damage.Magnetic mines.(previous reference:4.   The Secretary of State for the Home Department and minister of Home Security said that considerable damage had beendone by air raids in the London area during the previous twenty-four hours.  Some 200 people had been killed and some 550 admitted to hospital.   On the other hand, the position on the&apos; railways was.M. (40) 253rd easier.  On the Southern Railway power supply and signalling had conclusions       been restored at Victoria (Central).   There did not appear to haveMinute 3.)        been any special concentration on railways during the previous night.The most serious development had been the continued dropping of parachute mines, probably of the magnetic type, some 12 of whichhad been dropped over the London area during the night of thel7th-18th September and some 25 during the night of the18th-19th September. The damage to the L.C.C. County Hallduring the previous night had almost certainly been due to a parachute mine. The blast of the explosion from these mines was so great that it had been found necessary to clear the area for400 yards round the spot, when a mine did not explode.The War Cabinet &apos;(1) Agreed that we should retaliate by dropping mines over berlin.(2) Invited the First Sea Lord to report to the Prime minister on the steps now being taken to fit mines with anattachment for this purpose.The Sudan. 5    The War Cabinet were informed that Sir Stewart Symes,Appointment of the Governor-General of the Sudan, had been in indifferent healtha new Governor- for some time past and would already have retired, had it not been general. for the war. His successor was to have been Sir Bernard Bourdillon,the present Governor of Nigeria; Sir Bernard&apos;s appointment hadin fact been announced, and the approval of the Egyptian Govern-ment obtained. With the outbreak of war, however, it had beendecided to extend Sir Stewart Symes&apos;s service, and to keep Sir B.Bourdillon in Nigeria for the time being.Sir Miles Lampson and General Wavell were both strongly ofthe opinion that Sir Stewart Symes&apos;s retirement should no longer be postponed.The War Cabinet-(a) Invited the Permanent Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs (subject to consultation with theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs) to make arrangements for Sir Stewart Symes to be relieved ofhis present office as Governor-General of the Sudanforthwith.
The Colonies. 6.   In  connection  with  the  preceding  Minute,  the  V/arColonial Cabinet-Governors. Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to submit a report to the Prime Minister as to the age, experience and suitability for office under war conditions of the governors of all Colonies likely to be of importance forthe conduct of the war.Switzerland.Violation of swiss Neutralityby british aircraft.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 251stConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs said that our reply to the recent Swiss Note had been handed to the Swiss Minister on the previous day. The minister had said that he thought the Note might result in public opinion inSwitzerland, and possibly also in the United States, reacting against this country. But he had also said that he appreciated that the Airauthorities in this country were faced with a difficult situation, andon the whole, he had taken the Note fairly well.The Swiss Minister had said that it would take him about24 hours to deliver the Note to his Government. The permanent under-Secretary of State thought that the Air Ministry could therefore assume that the reply had now been delivered.The War Cabinet took note of this statement, and agreedthat the Royal Air Force should now be free to resumeattacks on targets in North Italy.Malta- 8.   The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theProvision of Secretary of State for the Colonies (W.P. (40) 374) regardingSupplies. supplies for Malta.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that the policy approved before the war was that Malta should be provisioned for six months. When Italy came into the war, the Governor had stated that he had six months&apos; supplies available. Further, when asked at intervals whether he was satisfied with the position, hehad made affirmative replies. The Governor had now telegraphedto say that he was short of all supplies, except coal and wheat.Further, the Chiefs of Staff now considered that the level of essential supplies, both civil and other, in Malta should be built up as soon as practicable to eight months&apos; stock. If this recom-mendation of the Chiefs of Staff was to be adhered to, it meant thatsome 80,000 tons would have to be shipped to Malta every month.The Minister of Shipping said that we were very short of the fast ships which would be necessary to carry the stores through theMediterranean, but that he would do his best to meet these newdemands.The War Cabinet Gave approval in principle to the report and invited theFirst Lord of the Admiralty to prepare a plan to giveeffect to it.(b) Decided that Sir Stewart Symes&apos;s successor should beMajor-General H. J. Huddleston. Pending the arrival of Major-General Huddleston, Sir Stewart Symes&apos;second in command should take charge at Khartum.
Shipping.merchantship building,and other measures toincrease thesupply ofmerchantshipping.(previous references:W.M. (40) 27thConclusions,Minute 1,and 67thConclusions,Minute 8.)9. The War Cabinet had before them a joint Memorandumby the Minister without Portfolio, the Chancellor of the Exchequer,the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Minister of Shipping(W.P. (40) 365).The Minister of Shipping said that the shipping position this time next year would give cause for anxiety, because the rate ofreplacements of tonnage lost was deplorably low. He would likethe War Cabinet to realise that there would be a considerable reduction in our importing capacity this time next year, unless therewas an improvement in the tonnage situation.The Prime Minister said that within the next few months ourown new destroyers, now under construction, together with the arrival of the American. destroyers, should greatly improve theforces available for escort duties and it was hoped would reducethe present rate of tonnage losses.The War Cabinet-Approved the recommendations contained in the summaryof W.P. (40) 365.United States ofAmerica.Supply ofMunitions.(previous references:W.M. (40) 245thConclusions,Minute 6, andW.M. (40) 230thConclusions,Minute 8.)10. The First Sea Lord asked whether action could be takenin regard to the supply of large flying-boats by the United Statesof America.The Prime Minister said that the United States of america had made very large demands in regard to bases. No further action,however, had been taken by them in respect of the supply to us ofthe further 250,000 rifles, the 20 motor torpedo-boats, the 150 air-craft on order for Sweden and the 10 large flying-boats.The War Cabinet Invited the Permanent Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs to send an urgent message to Lord Lothianpressing for the supply of these further munitions and, inparticular, of the 10 large flying-boats.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,September 19, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
