<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/30/0 images: 49-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF &quot;HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTrv&apos;     , &quot;7^7vi,Printed, for tha Cabinet/ OctoberSECRET. Copy No. 31CP. (48) 23618th October, 1948    : ;r - .      ;/unuili ju XBIZONAL SCRAP EXPORTSJoint Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and minister of SupplyOUR colleagues.may like to have a short appreciation of the settlement which,&apos;after protracted negotiations, was reached with the United States Governmenton 30th September on the export of ferrous scrap from the Bizone. The agreement is in the form of an exchange of letters between His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in washington and Mr. Lovett, Under-Secretary of State; in addition, certain points of interpretation were dealt with in supplementary letters. The text of documents is given in the annex to this memorandum.2.   The main features of the agreement are that (a) Members of the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation willbe invited to set up in Paris an ad hoc committee, outside the juris-diction of the Organisation for European Economic Co-operation butworking in close co-operation with it, to make recommendations onallocations to the governments of the scrap exporting countries. TheUnited States Government will be represented on this Committee. Thefinal decision on the execution of these recommendations remains, ofcourse, with the governments of the exporting countries, and in the caseof the Bizonal area with the Military Governors, who will, in the eventof a dispute on these questions, refer to their respective Governments.(b) Apart from the existing authorisations of ferrous scrap of 300,000 tons to the United Kingdom, 200,000 tons to the United States and100,000 tons &quot;to other countries, the United States will get a further100,000 tons to equal the United Kingdom share. The UnitedKingdom will receive 75,000 tons more as a final shipment of booty scrap, without payment, and the United States a similar amount forwhich they will pay. The United Kingdom and the United states will thus receive 375,000 tons each before allocation machinerycomes into play.(c) The British and American authorities in Germany will co-ordinate their efforts with a view to exporting, in the year to 1st October, 1949, atleast 1 million tons more than the 850,000 tons outside the allocationmachinery.(d) Until the ad hoc committee functions an interim allocation has beenagreed by which exports of a further 125,000 tons each are authorisedto the United Kingdom and the United States (a similar quantity isbeing set aside to meet the needs of other scrap importing countries).These amounts will be charged against future allocations.3. Under these arrangements the United Kingdom can count on receiving375,000 tons outside the allocation machinery, with a reasonable expectation ofobtaining a further 400,000 tons from allocation, making an estimated total of775,000 tons between now and 1st October, 1949. This figure compares with a requirement figure for scrap imports of 1 million tons over the period, and itwould be idle to claim that in this respect, or in regard to the cessation of freeimports of booty scrap, the agreement is a satisfactory one.35997
4. On the other hand, His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;s position with regard to adequate supplies of scrap is safeguarded to some extent by a provision whichin effect gives the Military Governors discretion to introduce special measures if in their opinion adequate quantities of scrap for export are not becoming available. Scrap secured by these measures would be outside allocation, and weshall not hesitate to invoke this clause, if necessary, before the remaining75,000 tons of booty scrap have been secured. The organisation which we havebuilt up in Germany for the collection of booty scrap would thus continue its operation in a different form. Furthermore, we have achieved, in part at least,our object of establishing an international allocation machinery in which theUnited States will play its part on the same footing as any other country with a claim to imports of scrap from Germany. Moreover, we have now removed a cause of friction and misunderstanding with the Americans, and have prepare the way for an intensive effort, in collaboration with them, to maximise scrapexports from the Bizone. If this effort is as successful as the Americans them-selves hope, and as our representatives in Germany believe it may be, it is possiblethat the figure mentioned in the preceding paragraph, and with it our scrapreceipts during the current year, will be exceeded.E. B.G. R. S.18*A October, 1948.
UNITED STATESTreaty Series No. 72 (1948)Exchange of Notesconstituting an Agreementbetween His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdomand the Government of the United States of Americarelating toFerrous Scrap ExportsWashington, 30th September, 1948Presented&apos;by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to parliament by Command of His MajestycLONDONHIS MAJESTVS  STATIONERY OFFICEtwopence  netaid. 7538
EXCHANGE OF NOTES CONSTITUTING AN AGREEMENT between his MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNTIED KINGDOMAND THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED STATES OFAMERICA RELATING TO FERROUS SCRAP EXPORTSWashington, 30th September, 1948No. 1His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington to the United StatesActing Secretary of StateBritish Embassy,Sir, Washington, 30th September, 1948.I have the honour to refer to the discussions which have taken place between representatives of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdomand the Government of the United States of America on the subject of ferrousscrap exports, and to inform you that the matters agreed upon in the courseof these discussions have received the approval of my Government. Thesematters are set forth in the following memorandum: Memorandum on Ferrous Scrap(I) Proposal to O.E.E.C. Countries on Allocation MachineryA proposal will be put before the members of the Organisation of european economic Co-operation that an ad hoc committee be established in Parisconsisting of representatives of O.E.E.C. members and the United States as afull member. It is proposed that this committee, although outside thejurisdiction of the O.E.E.C. Council, should work in close co-operation with itand its committees. The functions of the committee shall be to make recommendations to the Governments of the countries participating in theO.E.E.C., including the Bizonal Area of Germany and the French Zone, onthe distribution of scrap exports from those countries. Final decisions withrespect to exports will be made, however, by the Governments of the exporting countries. In the Bizonal Area decisions will be made by the UnitedStates and United Kingdom Military Governors, subject to the provisions ofArticle (3) of this Agreement.(II) Instructions to Military GovernorsIdentical instructions shall be sent to the United States and United kingdom military Governors in Germany as follows: (1) It is the desire of the Governments of the United States and UnitedKingdom that the total collection and export of scrap from the Bizonal Area,after providing for the legitimate requirements of the German steel ind. .ry,be maximised.Initial authorisations outside of future allocations(2) The existing authorisation (approved 13th May, 1948) of 600,000 tons(namely 200,000 tons to the United States, 300,000 tons to the United Kingdomand 100,000 tons to other countries) is confirmed.
3 m(3)   In addition there will be the following supplementary authorisations:^(a) 100,000 tons to the United. States, to bring the United States shareto parity with the above-mentioned United Kingdom share of300,000 tons;(b) 75,000 tons to the United Kingdom as a final shipment of booty scrap without payment;(c) 75,000 tons to the United States, to correspond to (6) above, butnot.free of payment.(4) The above total authorisations of 375,000 tons to the United States,375,000 tons to the United Kingdom and 100,000 tons to other countriesshall not be charged to future allocations, and the two Military Governorsshall implement these authorisations-immediatety.Export availabilities from Bizonal Area. (5) The United States and United Kingdom Military Governors shallinform the ad hoc committee promptly after its establishment and from timeto time thereafter, of the anticipated volume of scrap exports from the BizonalArea. It is hoped that this figure for the year ending 1st October, 1949, willbe 1,000,000 tons or more over and above the 850,000 tons authorised aboveoutside of future allocations.Interim authorisations chargeable against future allocations(6) As an advance against contemplated early allocations within the framework of the regular allocating procedure, there shall also be authoriseda further 125,000 tons to the United States, 125,000 tons to the United Kingdomand 125,000 tons to other countries, such quantities to be charged against future allocations. The two Military Governors shall also implement theseauthorisations immediately. -(7) In the event that no recommendation is made by the ad hoc committee before 31st October, 1948, further interim authorisations shall be made onthat date and on the last day of each month thereafter in the ratio of 2-2-ifor the United States, United Kingdom and other countries, respectively,until such time as the regular allocation procedure is in operation.Implementation of allocations(8) In implementing this Agreement, the United States and UnitedKingdom Military Governors shall determine among other matters: (a) whether to implement allocations by control over contracts or controlover exports or both;(b) whether, if control over exports is adopted, the Joint Export-ImportAgency may approve contracts within agreed limitations in excessof the total outstanding allocations of any country;(c) whether, in appropriate cases, contracts shall provide for delivery of scrap within specified short periods in order to prevent unduetying up of allocations in individual long-term contracts;(d) whether and in what manner to instruct Joint Export-Import agency to take precautions to satisfy itself as to the competence of contractingparties to implement the terms of the contract.Effective date of foregoing authorisations(9) All scrap exported subsequent to the date of this Agreement shall becharged against the foregoing authorisations.35959 b 2
Booty scrap(10) There shall be no further exports of booty scrap after the date ofthis Agreement except for the 75,000 tons authorised under paragraph II (3) (b)above.Price(11) The price of scrap with appropriate differentials for loading points,quality of scrap, &amp;c, shall be uniform for all foreign buyers, and shall be setfrom time to time by the United States and United Kingdom Military Governorsunder such procedures as they may establish.Special measures(12) If the United States and United Kingdom Military Governorsconsider that adequate quantities of exportable scrap cannot be obtainedwithout special measures, they are authorised to approve the recovery of scrap by such measures. Scrap recovery under such arrangements, if approved,may be outside regular allocations but subject to such special allocationsas the United States and United Kingdom Military Governors may determineafter consultation with the ad hoc committee.Direct recovery of scrap(13) Nothing in this Agreement shall preclude operations by non-Germanorganisations for the recovery of scrap from disarmament and other sourcesnot readily accessible to German scrap merchants, provided such operations are carried on in a manner acceptable to the United States and UnitedKingdom Military Governors and that all recoveries of scrap (other than the75,000 tons of booty scrap mentioned above) are paid for at prices establishedby the United States and United Kingdom Military Governors and are withineither the regular or the special allocations determined by the United Statesand United Kingdom Military Governors.United States-United Kingdom Scrap Control Authority(14) The United States and United Kingdom Military Governors shallset up a United States-United Kingdom Scrap Control Authority in which each shall appoint a Co-coordinator to supervise and control the collection and export of&quot; ferrous scrap. This Control Authority shall be subject, throughwhatever organisation the Military Governors may determine, to the juris-diction of the Bipartite Board.(Ill) Reservation of Fusion AgreementNothing in this Agreement shall be deemed to modify the arrangementsset forth in the Fusion Agreement of 2nd December, 1946(x), as amended bythe Agreement of 17th December, 1947(2). Questions which may arise withrespect to scrap exports under the present Agreement will be resolved as contemplated in paragraph 5 of the Agreement of 17th December, 1947,having regard also to the provisions of sub-paragraph (3) (a) of the latterAgreement.Upon receipt of a note from you indicating your Governments approvalof the terms of the above memorandum, my Government will consi )that this note and your reply constitute an Agreement between the twoGovernments effective from the date of your reply.I avail, &amp;c.(Sd.)      O. FRANKS.(&apos;) &quot;Treaty Series No. 65 (1946),&quot; Cmd. 7001.(2) &quot;Treaty Series No. 4 (1948),&quot; Cmd. 7301.
Tlie United States Acting Secretary of State to His Majesty^Ambassador at WashingtonDepartment of State,Your Excellency, IQth September, 1948.I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your Note of30th September, 1948, proposing that an Agreement be entered into betweenthe Government of the United States of America and His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom on the subject of ferrous scrap exports. The termsof the proposed Agreement are set forth in the following memorandum :-[As in No. 1]This proposal and the foregoing memorandum are acceptable to theGovernment of the United States of America. As proposed in yourExcellency&apos;s Note, therefore, your Note and the present reply are regarded as constituting an Agreement between the two Governments, effective on thedate of this Note.Accept, &amp;c.(Sd.)      ROBERT A. LOVETT.I50I9 35959 wt- H93llS9 IO/48 FOP-No. 2
london printed AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from H.M. Stationery Office at the following addresses:York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 13a Castle Street, Edinburgh, 2;39-41 King Street; Manchester, 2; 1 St. Andrew*s Crescent, Cardiff-Tower Lane, Bristol, 1; 80 Chichester Street, belfast or THROUGH ANY BOOKSELLER1948Price id. net
Supplementary Letters vi 11&apos;:i .        (1)My. dear Mr, Saltzman, &apos; 30th September, 1^48.-&apos;Our two. Governments have to-day signed an exchange of notes embodying anagreement dealing with the subject of scrap exports from O.E.E.C. countries, andin particular from the Bizonal Area of Germany. In this connection my Govern-ment has instructed me to express the grave concern they still feel about thequantity of scrap likely to. be obtained under the authorisations and allocationsproposed or envisaged in the agreement.  0As I have previously stated in the course of the negotiations, there is an absolute minimum requirement on the part of the United Kingdom of 1 million tons of scrap from Germany in the year 1949, if we are to obtain the 15 million ingot tons production on which the European Recovery Programme for the UnitedKingdom, including a considerable measure of assistance to other european countries, is based. In my Governmenfs view the above-mentioned target figure for the United Kingdom may not under present availability prospects be obtained by some 300,000 tons or more, though the authorities in Germany will undoubtedlymake every effort to see that this shortfall does not in fact take place.In consequence, it may be necessary, in the view of my Government, to con-sider at an early date the adoption of special measures provided for in para-graph II (12) of the agreement. The object of this would be to establish the rightto recover scrap for export outside of regular allocations, by special measureswhich may not be available to German scrap recovery agencies. My Governmentestimates that at the end of two months from the present date we shall be in aposition to judge whether the fears above described are likely to be realised, and ifunfortunately a shortfall appears in any degree probable they would wish to propose that special measures should be adopted forthwith.My Government is, of course, content that the decision to adopt special measures should rest in the hands of the Military Governors as the agreementprovides. I am, however, instructed to express their fears to you and to say thatin their view it will be important to maintain, and probably to expand, any organi-sation, labour force, supervisory personnel, or scrap recovery equipment, at presentin the Bizonal Area or capable of being employed there, so that additional scrapsupplies may be obtained, as from a date perhaps two months from the presentdate. Further, it is my Governmenfs view that we should actively survey fromthe outset such sources of scrap in the Bizonal Area which have not yet beentouched by German commercial contractors and may not be suitable to be drawn upon by them.I should be glad if you would take full note of my Governmenfs views on theabove matters.Yours sincerely.(Signed) J. HUBERT PENSON, Minister,Adviser on German Affairs.Mr. Charles E. Saltzman, . -Assistant Secretary of State,United States Department of State,Washington, D.C.
In reply . .&apos;        &quot;      -refer to IRDepartment of State,Washington,My dear Mr. Penson, .    3Qi\ September, 1948.i,. I have your letter of 30th September, 1948, in which you express your government^ concern that the United Kingdom&apos;s import target for ferrous scrapfrom the Bizonal Area of Germany may not be realised. You further state that,in the view of your Government, it may be desirable at an early date to adoptspecial, measures in accordance with the provisions of paragraph II (12) of theagreement on ferrous scrap. *In connection with the latter point, I wish to bring to your attention theopinion expressed by several American experts in Germany that special measuresto recover scrap apart from the established German scrap dealers may not resultin increasing scrap recovery and, in fact, under certain circumstances may havethe effect of reducing the total quantity of scrap available for export.. Notwithstanding the above, note is taken and due consideration will be givento the matters discussed in your letter.Sincerely yours,(Signed) CHARLES E. SALTZMAN,.&quot; &apos;. -    . , Assistant Secretary..The Hon. J. Hubert Penson,J. \      Minister, Adviser on German Affairs,........        British Embassy.


</content>
</cab>
