<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/30/0 images: 82-84</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I  I. &apos; - . V    65ifills DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (kS) 2.1X521ST OCTOBER. 19 U8CABINETLOANS BY THE ECONOMIC CO-operation administration. -Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer my colleagues should know that we are on the point ofsigning a Loan Agreement with the Export-Import Bank of washington, as agents of the Economic Go-operation administration,  for an E.C. A.  loan of $310 millions in respectof the period April-December, 19h8,  the first nine monthsof the European Recovery Programme.2.     Details of the terms of the loan are set out in the AnneJKu3*      It will be remembered that S. R. P.  assistance takestakes two forms - free grants and loans, the latter beingapproximately 25% of the total aid allotted to theUnited Kingdom.      We have been notified by E. C. A.  that our total assistance for the first three quarters of theE.R.P. xoeriod i s as follows:-i2MApril-JuneJuly-SeptemberOctober-November$ millions	Grant	Loan300	100250	85&apos; 375	125925	310,it 235.,k* It is intended to publish the Loan Agreement as a white Paper early next week.R. S. C.Treasury Chambers.21ST OCTOBER, 19h8
ANNEX- TERMS OF THE LOAN1*     Amount of. loan;     $310 millions.29      Rate of Interest;    2-gfS* from 3Oth June, 1952, payable inhalf-yearly instalments beginning on 31st December, 1952*3c     Period;    19h8-1983 (i.e. a 35 year loan).First payment of amortisation will be made on30th June, 1956,  and thereafter half-yearly until 31st December, 1983.Arrangements have been made so that repayments will be smaller in the years immediately following 1956 than theywill be later.ho   - Waiver;     The Loan Agreement contains a provision that if the parties determine that it would be in their common interests, because of adverse economic conditions or for anyother reason,  to postpone any instalments of interest orprincipal or to alter any of the provisions relating to thepayment of interest or principal,  they may by mutual agreement in writing provide for such postponement oralteration.


</content>
</cab>
