<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/30/0 images: 239-273</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
been strictlyfor the pe,i-.of............^k...HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY CThe circulation of this paper hasiiteu. it is issued. use160HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)TM3 SECRETCP. (48) 261.9th November, 1948,o 1NO. ** LCiCYRENAIGaMemorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs and the Secretary of State for WThe problem at the meeting of the Defence   Committee on the 6thAugust, 1948, it was agreed, to work for an internationaldecision this year in favour of United Kingdom trusteeship forCyrenaica.     Our claim to this trusteeship was put forward bythe Minister of State at the meeting of the Council of foreign ministers in Paris in September.     In view, however, of theCouncil&apos;s failure to reach agreement on the disposal of anyof the former Italian Colonies, it now falls to the general assembly to decide on the future of these territories, includingCyrenaica, in accordance with the procedure laid down in thePeace Treaty with Italy.     It is expected that discussion ofthis question will begin in the Assembly in the course of thismonth.2. We shall now make every effort to secure the necessary two-thirds majority in the Assembly in favour of United Kingdomtrusteeship for Cyrenaica, but even when this has been achieved, there will still remain the problem of reconciling the trusteeship with the desire of the inhabitants for immediateindependence.     Cyrenaican opinion, as expressed to the FourIPower Commission which recently visited the former italian colonies, dislikes what it knows of trusteeship and favoursimmediate independence under the Amir Sayed Mohammed Idris alSenussi.     Many Cyrenaicans, however, including the Amir!himself, recognise that Cyrenaica cannot at present exist withoutadministrative and financial assistance from outside and would prefer this to come from the United Kingdom.     It is consideredIthat they would be prepared to accept this in the form of a[United Kingdom trusteeship which gave them a substantial degree[Of internal autonomy.lip. The measures which we are proposing to meet this[situation are described in the attached note, to which &quot;areAnnexed a draft trusteeship agreement, treaty and militaryannex, financial agreement and constitution.     TheseCf urnents have been prepared by the Former Italian ColoniesCommittee which was set up to consider such questions inpursuance of a previous Cabinet decision (CM. (48) 5thConclusions, Minute 2).
fjjg The success of our plans for Gypenaica depends uponcarrying the Amir with us at all stages, and it is considered desirable that he should be informed of our proposals beforethe General Assembly begins its discussion of the future of cyrenaica.5. It should be realised, of course, that these documents cannot be considered as definitive, as they may wellbe subject to amendment in the light of the circumstances inwhich they have to be negotiated or enacted.Re commendationsIt is hoped that our colleagues will approve thefour documents referred to in. paragraph 3 above and annexed to this paper, and agree to these documents being shown to the amir.lii. B.Ho S.9th November, 1940.
Note162*In order to earn and retain the goodwill of thelabitants of Cyrenaica, which is essential to the successfuluse of our strategic facilities there, we should, as soon aspossible after the territory has been placed under UnitedKingdom trusteeship, confer upon the Cyrenaicans as large a degree of self-government as is practicable in the present stateof their political development.     Any such measures must of necessity take into account the predominant position in theterritory of the Amir Sayed Mohomed Idris al Senussi, whois the acknowledge leader of the Cyrenaican people.2. If the General Assembly approves in principle thatthe United Kingdom shall be granted the trusteeship, the nextstep will be for His Majesty5s Government to present to theGeneral Assembly a draft trusteeship agreement, in which weshall include a provision authorising His Majesty&apos;s Governmentto recognise Saved Idris as Amir of Cyrenaica and Head of theGovernment of that territory, subject to the terms of a treatydefining the obligations of the Amir towards His Majesty&apos;sGovernment as administering authority.5. A draft trusteeship agreement is attached at Annex I.4. A draft of a treaty of the kind envisaged in thedraft trusteeship agreement is attached at Annex II.     This,while recognising Sayed Idris as Amir of Cyrenaica, requireshim to assume certain obligations, including the obligationto enact a constitution in consultation with His Majesty&apos;sGovernment (Article III) and to accept the advice of the british resident on certain specified matters (law and order, defence,etc) in which it is essential for us to maintain control(Article V).     Article III also provides that for a certainfixed period (the duration of which will be determined by negotiation with the Amir before the treaty is signed), theBritish Resident shall have power to enact ordinances havingthe force of law.     We Consider it essential, during the initial period of our trusteeship, when the Cyrenaican administration will be finding its feet and our civilian and military works will&apos;be initiated, that His Majesty&apos;s Government, retainoverriding powers in the event of the Amir being for any[reason unable to accept or act upon the advice of the Resident[under Article V.5.     -      Article VII of the draft treaty provides for themaintenance in Cyrenaica of such armed forces as His Majesty&apos;sGovernment may require.     The Annex referred to in this Article[obliges the Amir to lease to His Majesty&apos;s Forces such land!^s they may require and sots forth in detail the privileges[And immunities of His Majesty&apos;s Forces in Cyrenaica.[6.  The financial help which His Majesty&apos;s Governmentfwill give to Cyrenaica will be one of the most Importantiways of our consolidating our influence, and a draft of a financial agreement, to be Concluded Concurrently with thetreaty, is attached at Annex III.     This provides for the/appointment
-2-8 ointment zf a British Financial Adviser to the CyrenaicanF/ernment ana fur the granting of financial assistance t,,the Cyrenaican Government which will in the initial stagestake the form of a grant t,. cover agreed budgetary deficits.7. While the draft Constitution at Annex IV doesprovide for a Legislative Assembly with a majority of elected members and for a Council of Ministers with collective responsibility to the Amir, net only full executive authoritybut final legislative power is concentrated in the Amirhimself.     This is considered desirable for the following reasons(i) The present state of political development in cyrenaica dees not permit of any large degreeof representative government.(11) The Cyrenaicans themselves are .unanimous in their loyalty and devotion to the Amir and would themselvespress for a form of self-government in which fullexecutive and legislative&quot;power is vested in him.(iii) In view of the fact that the Amir will have undertaken by the treaty certain specificobligations towards His Majesty&apos;s Government, It woulcbe unwise to make their fulfilment dependent on atotally inexperienced Legislative Assembly.The Legislative Assembly can, however, initiate legislationjon all matters except those oil which, either by the treaty or the financial agreement, the Amir has undertaken to accept our advice.
ANNEX I&quot;&quot;OP secret draft TRUSTEESHIP AGREEMENT FOR CYRENAICA-PREAMBLEWHEREAS by Article 23 of the Treaty of Peace with italy Italy has renounced all right and title to the Italian   &apos;territorial possessions in Africa, which include the territory .known as Gyre mica;.   AND. WHEREAS it was provided that the final disposalof these possessions should be determined jointly by theGovernments of the Soviet Union, of the United Kingdom, of theUnited States of America, and of France within one year fromthe caning into force of the said Treaty, in the manner laiddown in the Joint Declaration of February 10th, 1947, issuedby the said Governments;AND WHEREAS it is provided in Article 3 of the saidJoint Declaration that, if with respect to any of these territories the Four rowers are unable to agree upon their disposal within the said period the matter shall be referred tothe General Assembly of the United Nations for a recommendation,and the Four Powers have agreed to accept the recommendation and to take appropriate measures for giving effect to it;AND WHEREAS the Four Powers have been unable toreach agreement within the said period on the final disposalof Cyrenaica and the&apos;matter has accordingly been referred tothe General Assembly for a recommendation;AND WHEREAS by a Resolution of the (date) the general assembly has resolved that Cyrenaica should be placed underthe International Trusteeship System established by theUnited Nations and that the United Kingdom should be designated as the Administering Authority for Cyrenaica;AND WHEREAS in accordance with Articles 75 and 77of the United Nations Charter the placing of a territory under the International Trusteeship System is to be effected by means of a Trusteeship Agreement:NOW THEREFORE the General Assembly of the united nations hereby resolves to approve the following terms of trusteeship for Cyrenaica.Article 1.*D (Territorial Definition).     /See Note IjArticle 2.His Britannic Majesty is hereby designatedAdministering Authority for Cyrenaica, responsibility for which/will-
will be undertaken by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom 01 Great Britain and Northern Ireland.-Hp - -Article 5.The Administering Authority shall ensure thatCyrenaica is administered in such a manner as to attain the basic objectives of the International Trusteeship System laiddown in Article 76 of the United Nations Charter, and shall &apos;ensure the achievement of ultimate Independence in a mannerappropriate to the particular circumstances of the territory.The Administering Authority shall collaborate fully with theGeneral Assembly of the United Nations and the trusteeship council in the discharge of all their functions as defined in Article 87 of the United Nations Charter, and shallfacilitate any periodic visits to Cyrenaica which they may deem necessary at times to be agreed upon with the AdministerinAuthority.Article 4.In order to promote the political advancement of;theinhabitants of Cyrenaica, the Administering Authority is authorised to(a) recognise His Highness the Amir El Sayed MohammedIdris El Senussi as Amir of Cyrenaica and Headof the Government of that territory, subject tothe terms of any Treaty or Treaties which may bemade between the Administering Authority andHis Highness the Amir in order to define therelations between them, to enable the administering authority to render such advice and assistance asmay be necessary, and to ensure the carrying outof the provisions of this Agreement and anyother international responsibilities consistent withthe United Nations Charter assumed in respect of cyrenaica by the Administering Authority;(b) make provision for a constitution for Cyrenaicawhich shall establish appropriate legislative,executive and judicial organs for the governmentof the territory;Article 5.   /See Note 2jThe Administering Authority shall be entitled toestablish naval, military and air bases, to erect fortificationto station and employ his own forces in Cyrenaica and to take all such other measures as are In his opinion necessary for the defence of Cyrenaica and for ensuring that thejt^itory plays its part in the maintenance of internationalIpelfce and security.     To this end the Administering:Authority may make use of volunteer forces, facilities andfassistance from Cyrenaica in carrying out the obligations[towards the Security Council undertaken in this regard by the/Administering
7    166(b) Shall not permit discrimination on grounds of nationality against nationals of any member ofthe United Nations in matters relating to thegrant of concessions for the development of thenatural resources of Cyrenaica and shall not grantconcessions having the character of a generalmonopoly;(c) shall ensure equal treatment In the administrationof justice to the nationals of all members of theUnited Nations.[The rights conferred by this Article on nationals of members ofthe United Nations apply equally to companies and associationscontrolled by such nationals and organised in accordance withthe law of any member of the United&quot;Nations.Article 7.Measures taken to give effect to Article 6 of this[Agreement shall be subject always to the overriding duty ofthe Administering Authority, in accordance with Article 76 ofthe United Nations Charter, to promote the political,(economic, social and educational advancement of the inhabitants[of Cyrenaica, to carry out the other basic objectives of theInternational Trusteeship System and to maintain peace, orderfind good government.     In particular such arrangements as mayjBeem just or necessary to the authorities in the territorypay be made(a) for the organisation of essential public servicesC3        and works;(b) for the creation of monopolies of a purely fiscalcharacter in order to provide Cyrenaica withthe fiscal resources best suited to local requirementsor otherwise in the interests of the inhabitants;[Admini storing Authority, as well as for local defence and the!maintenance of law and order within Cyrenaica.Article 6.Subject to the provisions of Article 7 of thiskgreeraent, the Administering Authority shall take all necessary:steps to ensure equal treatment in social, economic,industrial and commercial matters for all members of the united nations and their nationals and to this end(a)   shall ensure the some rights to all nationals ofmembers of the United Nations as to his own nationals in respect of entry into and residencein Cyrenaica, freedom of transit and navigationincluding freedom of transit arid navigation by air.acquisition of property both moveable and immoveable,the protection of person and property and theexercise of professions and trades;
(c)   where the interests of the economic advancement of the inhabitants of Cyrenaica may require it, forthe establishment for specific purposes, of otherH monopolies or undertakings having in them an element of monopoly, under conditions of proper publiccontrol;   provided that, in the selection ofagencies to carry out the purposes of this paragraph,other than agencies controlled by the government or those in which the Government participates,there shall be no discrimination on grounds of nationality against members of the United nations or their nationals.Article 8.Nothing in this Agreement shall entitle any memberof the United Nations to claim for itself or for its nationals,companies and associations the benefits of Article 6 of thisAgreement in any respect in which it does not give Cyrenaica,:its nationals, companies and associations, equality oftreatment with the nationals, companies and associations ofthe State which it treats most favourably.Article 9.The authorities in the territory shall take all practicable steps to promote the educational advancement ofslthe inhabitants&apos;of Cyrenaica.Article 10. . &apos;The authorities in the territory shall ensure in;Cyrenaica complete freedom of conscience and, so far as isI consistent with the requirements of public order and morality,Ifreedom of religious teaching and the free exercise of allI forms of worship.Article 11.Subject only to the requirements of public order,the authorities in the territory shall guarantee to theinhabitants of Cyrenaica freedom of speech, of the press, of assembly and of petition.Article 12.The provisions of any international conventions andjrecommendations already existing or&apos;hereafter drawn up by it he United Nations or by the Specialised Agencies referred toiin,Article 57 of the Charter which in the opinion of the ...Authorities in the territory may be appropriate to theparticular circumstances of the territory and which wouldjpwluce to the achievement of the basic objectives of theItiWjrnational Trusteeship System, shall be applied to theterritory.ft /Article 13
II. Article I.-   The territorial definition oftCy^renaica must await decision of the General Assembly.12/ Article V.     The wording of this Article is mutatis&apos;putandis identical with thot of Article V(c) of the existing/TrusteeshipArticle 15.m The Administering Authority may arrange for the co-operation of Cyrenaica in any regional advisory commission,regional technical organisation or other voluntary associationof States, any specialised international bodies, public or private, or other forms of international activity not inconsistent with the United Nations Charter.Article 14.The Administering Authority shall make to the general assembly of the United Nations an annual report on the basisof a questionnaire drawn up by the Trusteeship Council inaccordance with Article 88 of the United Nations Charter.Such reports shall include information Concerning the measures taken to give effect to suggestions and recommendations ofthe General-Assembly and the Trusteeship Council.     the administering Authority shall designate an accreditedrepresentative to be present.at the sessions of the trusteeship council at which the reports.&apos;of the Administering Authority-with regard to Cyrehaica are. Considered.Article 15.Nothing in this Agreement shall affect the rightof the Administering Authority to propose, at any future date,the amendment of this Agreement for the purpose of designatingthe whole or part of Cyrenaica as a strategic area or for anyother purpose not inconsistent with the basic objectives-ofthe International Trusteeship System.Article 16.The terms of this Agreement shall not be altered oramended except as provided in Article 79 and Article 83 or 85,as the case may be, of the United Nations Charter.Article 17.If any dispute whatever should arise between the administering Authority and another member of the UnitedfNations relating to the interpretation or application ofI the provisions of this Agreement, such dispute, if it cannotI be settled by negotiation or other means shall be submittedI to the International Court of Justice provided for in ChapterjXIV of the United Nations Charter.I NCJTES. -
Trusteeship Agreement for Tanganyika.     It is considered thattms wording will enable us to obtain the necessary strategicfacilities which we require in Cyrenaica and for tacticalreasons in the General Assembly it will be advisable to adhereclosely to the Tanganyika precedent.3. The draft trusteeship agreement contains, like all existing trusteeship agreements, no provision for a time limitor for a period of review.     It is likely, however, that weshall be under considerable pressure both in the general assembly and in Cyrenaica to agree to the insertion of sucha provision and, if necessary, it is proposed that whileresisting the inclusion of any provision for a fixed time limit to our Trusteeship, we should agree to the insertion of anArticle providing that after a period of, say, ten years theterms of the Agreement shall be reviewed in the light ofpolitical, economic, social and educational progress whichthe inhabitants of the territory may by that time have achieved.
TOP SECRET ANNEX II.DRAFT TREATY BETWEEN HIM MAJESTY AI-iDHIS HIGHNESS THE AMIR SAYED IDRIS EL SENUS8I1. His Majesty the Ling of Great Britain. Ireland andthe British Dominions beyond the seas (hereinafter referredto as &quot;His Majesty&quot;) and His Highness the Amir Saved Idrisel Senussi (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Amir&quot;):2. Whereas by a Trusteeship Agreement approved by theGeneral Assembly of the United Nations on the ......His Majesty was&apos; designated Administering Authority forCyrenaica, responsibility for which was &quot;to be undertaken byHis Government in the United Kingdom of Great Britain andNorthern Ireland;   and3. Whereas by Article 4 of the said trusteeship agreement His Majesty is in order to promote the politicaladvancement of the inhabitants of Cyrenaica, authorised to(a) recognise the Amir as Amir of Cyrenaica subjectto the terms of any treaty or treaties whichmay be made between   His Majesty and the Amirin order to define the relations between themto enable His Majesty to render such advice and assistance as may be necessary and to assure the carrying out of the provisions ofthe Trusteeship&quot;Agreement and any other international responsibilities consistent withthe United Motions Charter assumed in respectof Cyrenaica by Mis Majesty..(b) make provision for a constitution for Cyrenaicawhich shall establish appropriate legislative and judicial organs for the government thereof:4, Whereas it is desired that provision shall be ma.defor a constitution for Cyrenaica:5S Whereas His Majesty is now prepared to recognise the Amir as Amir of Cyrenaica, subject to the conclusion ofa treaty to define the relations between them and to enable his Majesty to render such advice and assistance as may benecessary and to ensure the carrying out of the provisionsof the Trusteeship Agreement and of such other int.eiu.^.t.ionanresponsibilities consistent with the United Nations can.ri-.or as may be assumed in respect of Cyrenaica by Mis majesty:Desiring to conclude a treaty for the purposesaforesaid, Have for this purpose appointedPlenipotentiaries, who, having exhibited tneirfull powers, found in good end due form, haveo.greed as follows:-Article I.His Majesty hereby recognises the Amir as Amir of cyrenaica,Article II./
Article II. 1&apos;1Hie Majesty shall be represented in Cyrenaica by aResident acting on behalf of His Majesty&apos;sk Government in the United Kingdom who shall be thechannel of communication between the Amir and HisMajesty&apos;s Government..    The Resident and his staffshall enjoy full diplomatic -privileges and immunities.His Majesty will be responsible for the exerciseand control of the   foreign relations of Oyrenaica.Foreign consuls in Cyrenaica snail address their communications to the Government of Cyrenaica through the resident.Article III.(i) His Highness the Amir shall enact for Cyrenaicaa constitution the terms oi which shall have been agreed between him and His&apos;Majesty. /Bee Mote 1/7(ii) The constitution for Cyrenaica shall providefor a legislative assembly and define its powers, &quot; Itshall provide that all laws for Cyrenaica shall bepromulgated by the Amir except that for a period of ........years from the entry into force of the present Treaty, HisMajesty, acting through the British Resident, shall also have the power&quot;to enact- ordinances which shall have the forceof law in Cyrenaica in those cases where His Majesty deemsit necessary to do so for the discharge of his obligations as administering authority for Cyrenaica under the trusteeship agreement.   /Bee Note 2A7(iii) Such legislation as may be required for thefull discharge of any international responsibilities and obligations accepted by His Majesty in respect of Cyrenaicashall be promulgated in Cyrenaica, and no legislation shallbe promulgated in Cyrenaica which may hinder the fulldischarge of such international responsibilities and obligations.Article IV.   The constitution of-Cyreriaica shall provide that matters of personal status affecting persons of the Moslemreligion shall be dealt with by Sharia courts.     It shall also provide, as may be expedient, for religious courtshaving jurisdiction in matters of personal status for otPerreligious communities in Cyrenaica.     Where a matter of personal status concerns persons of different religions,the civil courts of Cyrenaica shall hove jurisdictionunless all parties consent to the jurisdiction of areligious court.    The civil courts shall determine alldisputes as to the jurisdiction of religious courts.The Amir will appoint a legal adviser, on the recommendationof His Majesty.&apos; &apos; The salary of the legal adviser shall oea charge on the revenues of Cyrenaica, and he shall Deemployed on contract agreed between the H.C.Ps.    The legal adviser shall have access at all times to the Minister ofUustice and the Prime Minister.     All proposed Cyrenaicanlegislative measures shall be referred in draft to the
&quot;    172legal adviser for Ms advice.     All Judges of the civil courts shall be appointed by the Amir arid the observations of the legal adviser shall be obtained on proposals forthe appointment or dismissal of these judges.Article V.The Amir undertakes to aecept the advice of HisMajesty tendered through the Resident in the following matters:(a) maintenance of law and order, internal security,, defence, and the maintenance ofinternational peace and security;(b) the discharge of international obligationsapplicable to Cyrenaica, in particular thosearising from the Trusteeship Agreement;(c) currency and exchange control, import and export control, and external loans;(d) the promulgation of constitutional laws., andthe assumption by the Amir of any extraordinarypowers under the constitution;(e) the official posts in the Government or in thelocal administrations to be held by persons ofother than Cyrenaican nationality, as defined by Cyrenaican law, and their appointment,,functions, and conditions of service;(f) any law providing for succession to the Amir1 sthrone or for the establishment of a Regency;(g) the grant of exequaturs to foreign consularagents in Cyrenaica.Article VI.There shall be a separate financial agreementrelating to the internal finances of Cyrenaica,.Article VII.    &apos;To provide for the defence of Cyrenaica and toensure that Cyrenaica is in a position to play its part inthe maintenance of international peace and security, HisMajesty shall maintain in Cyrenaica such of his armed forces as he may consider necessary for these purposes.    To thisend the facilities and immunities to be granted in Cyrenaicato the forces of His Majesty are defined in the annex to thepresent Treaty.Article VIII.His Highness the Amir shall raise such armed forces as may be necessary for the internal security and local defence of Cvrenaica and also, at the request of his Majesty,to assist the forces of His Majesty in the fulfilment of thepurposes specified in Article VII.     His :.r jesty snail assist
$is Highness the Amir by the provision., as may be required,of senior officers and instructors and&apos;of equipment and bythe training of Cyrenaican personnel.    The&quot;condition on whichthis assistance sh-.il be provided shall be agreed betweenthe High Contracting Parties from time to time.Article IX.No territory in Cyrenaica shall be ceded or leasedor in any way placed under the control of any foreign power.Article X.His Majesty will make every endeavour to obtain forHis Highness&apos;s Government the services of any experts orofficials with technical qualifications of whom Cyrenaicamay stand in need.Article XI.The present Treaty shall be ratified,,   Ratificationsshall be exchanged-at ................. as soon as possible.The Treaty shall enter into force at the dote of theexchange of ratifications.    The present Treaty shall remainin force for so long as His Majesty is the administering authority for Cyrenaica under a Trusteeship Agreement of theUnited Nations.In faith whereof the above-mentioned Plenipotentiarieshave signed the present Treaty.Pone tnis ........... day of ............. at ........in duplicate in English and Arabic texts, of which the Englishtext shall prevail in case of divergence.
N N E X,part i174M His Highness the Amir will provide the land (includingexisting building s thereon) which His Majesty reouires for theconstruction of defence installations and military airfields,and for the -accommodation and training of units of HisMajesty&apos;s forces stationed in Cyrenaica, including the storage of their ammunition, equipment and supolies.    HisMajesty may erect on such Land such building is and install-ations as he may require.     When His Majesty relinquishesthe land he may remove and dispose of any installationswhich he desires.    Any compensation which should equitablybe paid to His Majesty in respect of installations riotremoved and which will pass to the Amir shall in default of agreement be decided by arbitration.     For the purposeof maritime defences the expression ;:land&quot; includes areaswithin the national or territorial waters of Cyrenaica.2. Where required by His Majesty for the purpose ofArticle VII, His Highness the Amir will exercise his powers in the matter of expropriation of land.     land required by the forces of His Majesty shall be registered as Cyrenaican State land and leased to His Majesty except where the High Contracting Parties agree in principlethat a temporary arrangement with private owners will be suitable.3. In determining the financial assistance to begranted by His Majesty under Articles 3 and 4 of theFinancial Agreementf account will be taken of the expenses incurred by^His Highness the Amir under Articles 1 and 2of this Annex in providing the land and existing buildingsrequired by His Majesty.4. The Armed forces of His Majesty whether stationed in Cvrenaica or not, shall at all times be grantedfacilities of movement within and across C-renaica, includingthe use of roads, railways and ports.   They may make useof Cyrenaican postal, telegraph and wireless telegraphytelephone and wireless telephone services.    Equitablecharges shall be p-id by the Armed forces for such facilities and services.5. Where it is agreed&apos; by His Majesty and His highness the Amir that capital expenditure on public utilities -midports required by His Majesty&apos;s Forces is also required forthe needs of the civil population, the necessary funds willbe provided by His Majesty by means of a loan to His highness the Amir or the appropriate public utility or port authority.Provision for the amortisation of the loan within a periodof years shall be made by the inclusion of an appropriateelement in the charges made to both civil and militaryUsers.    Both the period of years and the amount of tnecharges shall be agreed between His Majesty and His Hignnessthe Amir.    The amortisation charges so collected snail bepaid annually to His Majesty in reduction of the loan.
6.       - Where he so desires His Majesty may construct in cyrenaica nublic utilities solely for the use of his armed forces.   In any such case the cost of construction shallbe borne by His Majesty,B7. His Highness the Amir will safeguard, maintain and develop the civil airfields, ports, roads and railwaysof Cyrenaica as may be required for the nurposes specifiedin Article vli of the Treaty,    The expenditure involvedwill be taken Into account in determining the financialassistance to be granted by His Majesty under Articles 3and 4 of the Financial Agreement,8. His Majesty will defray the cost of repair or pay compensation for any damage or personal injury due to the actions of His Majesty&apos;s Forces in Cyrenaica, or membersthereof on duty other than damage caused in wartime by military operations.     Any disputes as to the liability ofHis Majesty under this paragraph, shall be determined by a mixed claims commission.    The composition end procedure of the mixed claims commission shall be fixed by separate agreement between the High Contracting Parties.   /See Notes3 and 4.J79, The liability to Cyrenaican taxation of individual -members of the forces of His Majesty in.Cyrenaica is governed by the provisions of Article 17 of Part 2 of this Annex.Save as therein provided, no demand for the payment of any form of Cyrenaican taxation shall be made against HisMajesty or any member of His Majesty&apos;s Forces.   Inparticular, no taxation shall be demanded in respect ofland used or occupied by His Majesty&apos;s Forces or in respectof any article imported&apos; into Cyrenaica for the use of those forces,PART 2.10,        In this annex:-(1) The expression &quot;members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces&quot;means -(i) every person holding a rank in the Naval, Military or air Forces&apos;of His Majesty who is in respect of the duties which he uerforms in Cyrenaica under the orders of theCommander&quot;of any British Naval, Military or Air Force in cyrenaica, Ineluding(a) members of the Women Ms Forces auxiliary to the saidforces.(b) members of the nursing staff, male and female,(c) uniformed members of the Navy, Army and Air Force1      Institutes;(ii) every civilian of any nationality other-than Cyrenaicanaccompanying or serving with the forces of His Majestystationed in Cyrenaica or in the navy, army and air force
institutes, who is either granted relative status as anofficer or holds a pass designating his status issued bythe appropriate British authority as hereinafter defined:&amp;(iii) the officers and instructors of the Cvrenaicanforces supplied by His Majesty in accordance with ArticleVIII of the Treaty, and who hold a rank in the naval,military or air forces of His Majesty;(iv) wives, and children under 21 years of age, of thepersons^referred to in (i), (ii) end (iii) above, /see note bAV(2) The expression &quot;appropriate British authority11means, in the case of members of His Majesty1s Naval Forces,the officer for the time being commanding His Majesty&apos;sNaval Forces in Cyrenaica;   in the case of members of HisMajesty&apos;s land forces the general or other officer forthe time being commanding the British troops in Cyrenaica:in the case of members of His Majesty&apos;s Air Forces, theair or other officer for the time being commanding the AirForces in Cyrenaica.(3) The expression &quot;British camp&quot; means the lendoccupied by any of His Majesty&apos;s- Forces in Cyrenaica for thepurposes of defence installations or military airfields orfor&quot; the accommodation of those forces including the storage-of ammunition equipment and supplies,11. (i) Mo Cyrenaican official shall enter or carryout any official&apos; function in a British camp wiehout the permission of the Officer Commanding the camp.(ii) No British camp shall be permitted to be used as a place of refuge for any person who is not a member ofHis Majesty&apos;s Forces from arrest by the Cyrenaican police or for the purpose of avoiding criminal or other proceedings in the courts of Cyrenaica.(iii) His Majesty1 s Forces shall have the right to generate light and power and to search for, and obtainwater bv boring or other means for their own use and to transmit and distribute such light and power or waterbetween the place of generation or origin and any. British campby means of cables, pipes, or in any other way wnansoevor.(iv) His Majesty&apos;s Forces shall have the right inBritish camps to construct and use W/T installations end toconstruct and use telegraphic end telephonic systems,,which systems may also be connected with the Cyrenaicantelegraph and telephonic systems.,12.    &apos;   (i) In all criminal matters, members of His^Majesty&apos;s Forces shall be subject to the jurisdiction ofBritish/
British service tribunals.     The Jurisdiction of theBritish service tribunals shall be exclusive of the--jurisdiction of all other tribunals in Cyrenaica unlessin any particular case the appropriate British authorityrequests or consents to the exercise of jurisdiction bya Cyrenaican tribunal.. (ii) This request or consent shall be given in-writing ana shall be addressed to the British Resident.(iii) Where a c&apos;ase, which is of legitimate interestto the Cyrenaican authorities because it arises out of aninjury to a local inhabitant or to local property or someother reason,   is submitted to a British service tribunal,the Cyrenaican authorities may request the appropriateBritish authority to inform them of the progress&apos; of thecase, and, when the case is concluded, supply a copy of the text of the judgment of the tribunal.(Iv)    The appropriate British authority willinvestigate and deal appropriately with any criminal offences alleged to have been committed by members of HisMajesty&apos;s forces which may be brought to their notice bythe- Cyrenaican authorities or which the appropriateBritish authority may find to have taken place.    Theappropriate British authority shall cause to be tried, andon conviction punished, any member of His Majesty&apos;s forcesalleged on sufficient evidence to have committed an offencein Cyrenaica.(v) The trial of any member of His Majesty&apos;s forces for en alleged offence against a member of the civilian population of Cyrenaica shall be conducted in open court(except where security considerations forbid this) and shallbe arranged to take place promptly j  Cyrenaica and if practicable within a reasonable distance from the spotwhere the offence is alleged to have been committed sothat witnesses &quot;shall not be required to travel greatdistances to attend the hearings.13.        His Highness the Amir will ensure the prosecution of persons subject to Cyrenaicanjurisdiction accused ofacts in relation to His Majesty&apos;s forces which, if committed in relation to the persons or property of the Cyrenaicanforces, would have rendered them liable to prosecution.14.        (i) Save as provided in Paragraphs (ii) and (iii)of this Article, a member of His Majesty&apos;s forces may onlybe arrested, searched or detained in custody oy trieappropriate British authority.(ii) A member of His Majesty&apos;s forces may be arrested by the Cyrenaican authorities when such arrest isnecessary in order to maintain public order.   In tins casethe arrested person will be immediately handed over to tneappropriate British authorities.
&apos;   (iii) The Cyrenaican authorities shall, on therequest of the appropriate British authority, search for members of His Majesty&apos;s forces alleged to be desertersor absentees without leave or to have committed, other offences and if they are found shall arrest them and handthem over to the appropriate British authority.(iv) In any case where there is any doubt whether an arrested person is a member of His Majesty&apos;s forces, acertificate signed by an officer of or above the rank of major in the military forces, or of equivalent rank in thenaval or air forces, shall be accepted by the Cyrenaicanauthorities as conclusive.1.5.        (i) His Highness the Amir will, at the request ofthe appropriate British authority&apos;t take all reasonable stepsto secure the attendance of persons amenable to their jurisdiction as witnesses before service tribunals of HisMajesty&apos;s forces in Cyrenaica (courts martial, courts ofenquiry, committees of adjustment and boards of officers or other service tribunals) assembled by the appropriateBritish authority.(ii) The appropriate British authority shall take all reasonable steps to secure the attendance of anymember of His Majesty&apos;s forces as a witness at any proceedings before Cyrenaican tribunals upon application made to him signed by the British. Resident.-16.        No member of His Majesty&apos;s Forces snail be liableto the civil jurisdiction of any Cyrenaican tribunal in any matter arising out of his official duties unless theappropriate British authority consents thereto.   If anycivil proceedings are instituted against a member of HisMajesty&apos;s Forces in any Cyrenaican tribunal, notification ofthe proceedings shall be given to the British Resident andno further steps shall be&quot;taken until 21 days have elapsedfrom the date of this notification,.    This period shall be-extended if the British Resident states that it has not beenpossible to conclude the necessary investigations in theabove time    A statement to the court by the British Residentthat the proceedings arise out of official duties will beaccepted as conclusive evidence of that fact.17.        (i) Members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces who are the owners of real property in Cyrenaica shall pay the same taxes inrespect of such property and its produce as Cyrenaicannationals.(ii) Members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces shall also pryin respect of any nrivately owned radio or receiving andtransmitting set&apos;, the fees for the time being in force in cyrenaica and applicable to such apparatus.(iii) Members of His Majesty&apos;:s Forces shall pay &quot;the tax or registration fee for- the time being in force in respectof the possession or use of a private motor vehicle or inrespect of any privately owned aircraft.
HOTBS1. Article III(i).     If is considered desirable thatat the time of the signature of the Treaty there should bean exchange of letters providing that the terms ol theConstitution/(iv) Members of His Majesty1 s Forces shall payimport or export duties on goods imported into or exported from Cyrenaica by them except goods imported for theirnersonal use or.consumption;   such goods shall, however,be liable to duty if disposed of in&quot;Cyrenaica to persons other then members of His Majesty&apos;s Forces.(v) Sovo as above provided, members of HisMajesty&apos;s Forces shall be- immune from all forms of taxatioiin Cyrenaica other than municipal rates for servicesenjoyed by them personally or in respect of propertyprivately owned by them.    This paragraph does not howeverapply to taxes or duties included in the price of goodsbought in Cyrenaica through commercial channels bymembers of His Majesty&apos;s Forces.18.        Members of His Majesty&apos;s forces shell be free to enter end leave Cyrenaican territory and to movetherein to and from and between British camps.19.        Service Police of His Majesty&apos;s forces may proceedto any place in Cyrenaica in the performance of their duties including the search for end apprehension and taking over of absentees or deserters.&quot;   They shall not however enter any buildings outside British camps otherthen buildings open to the public unless accompaniedby a responsible police officer (e.g. officer in chargeof a police station, or having similar status).20.       His Majesty1s forces in Cyrenaica may, if they so desire,, operate their own postal services.21.       The official correspondence of His Majesty&apos;forces and the couriers carrying such correspondenceshall enjoy in Cyrenaica the same immunities as grantedto those of diplomatic missions under international law.22.        Where it is provided in this Annex that, indefault or agreement between His Majesty and the Amir,a matter shall be decided by arbitration, sucharbitration shall be carried out by a special tribunalcomoosed of one member appointed by His Majesty, one member appointed by the Amir and one member appointedjointly by His Majesty and the Amir.    In the event oftheir being unable within............months of theoccurence of the dispute to agree on the person to beappointed as the third member, the President of theInternational Court of Justice shall be requested toapnoint the third member.     Both his Majesty and the Amirundertake to accept the decision of the tribunal ob Im-l,
Constitution shall be agreed beeween the Amir and ourselves before ratifications of the Treaty areexchanged.2. Article ITI(Ii).   The period in which theBritish Resident shall have reserved powers of legislation has been left blank for the present.   It is consideredthat a decision regarding the duration of this period should be taken after negotiation with the Amir.3. Article 8 of the Annex.,    It will be noted thatin article 16 of the Annex in is provided that membersof H.M. Forces are immune from civil proceedings in theCyrenaican Courts only in respect of actions committed by them while on duty.     Whilst &apos;the Courts would,therefore, be able to award damages against them inrespect of actions committed while off duty, it is atthe&quot; same time recognised that in certain cases    &apos; -individual members of the Forces may be unable to prysuch damages,,.   It is proposed that at the time of the signature&apos;or the Treaty there small be an exchange of notes expressing the agreement of H.M.G, to consider sympathetically the grant of ex oratxa payments in these latter cases,4. Article 8 of Annex,,    In view of the possibility that under   Article 8 H.M.G. may be held liable for -damage caused by the explosion of mines which have remained undetected since the&quot; conclusion of the north african campaigns, it is proposed that the exchange of notes envisaged in Note 3&quot;above should provide that article 8 does not cover such cases.5,     -   Article 10(iv) of Annex.    We cannot exclude fromthe jurisdiction of the local courts persons whom wecannot try by court, martial, wad consequently the immunity of such persons will have to be waived so as topermit their trial in the Cyrenaican courts when there isa real case against them.
ANNEX IIITOP secret HDRAFT FMANCIAL AGREEMENT BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY ANDHo Ho THE AMIR SAYED IDRIS EL SENUSSI.Article I.There shall be a British Financial Adviser to theGovernment of Cyrenaica who shall be appointed by the Amiron the recommendation of His Majesty.    The salary of theFinancial Adviser shall be a charge on the revenues of cyrenaica and he shall be employed on a contract agreed betweenthe High Contracting Parties,    (see Note 1).The Financial Adviser shall have access at all times to the Minister of Finance and the Prime Minister.     He shallhave the right to present his views at the meetings of theCouncil of Ministers where financial questions are discussed and shall be informed of the agenda of all such meetings.Article II.So- long as the revenues of Cyrenaica are insufficient to meet the necessary expenses of administration, His Majestywill grant financial assistance to Cyrenaica.Article III.(i) For a period of .... years from the entry into force6-f this Agreement, this assistance will take the form of agrant to cover agreed budgetary deficits.     The amount of thegrant &quot;will be decided in the light of budgetary estimatesagreed between the Amir and His&quot;Majesty, and the grant will bepaid on the basis of actual deficits as they are eventuatedwithin the agreed estimates.     (see note 2).(ii) Before the end of this period the High ContractingParties shall settle by agreement whether further grants;towards the expenses of administration during subsequent years are necessary and if so whether they should take the form of;fixed annual grants or of a continuance of the system In (i)! above.Article IV.Until (period) after Cyrenaica ceases to be inreceipt of financial assistance under Article 2 above thefollowing conditions shall apply.,    (i)   The observations Of the Financial Adviser shall beovowarned on all financial measures (a) before they are presentedj\tp the Council of Ministers, (b) before they are submitted tothe Assembly.     The observations of the Financial Adviser shallbe submitted to the Council of Ministers and also to HisHighness the Amir.
(ii) The Financial Adviser may submit recommendationsIfJf&apos; financial measures and if he so requests his recommendations[shall be brought before the Council of Ministers and High[Highness the Amir..  (iii) If the Financial Adviser considers that certainfinancial measures proposed by the Council of Ministers areinimical to, or that certain financial measures which theCouncil of Ministers are unwilling to adopt are necessaryfor, the financial stability of Cyrenaica&apos;, the financial adviser shall have the right to address a formal memorandum to the British Resident, of which a copy shall be presented to His Highness the Amir and the Prime Minister.     The questionshall then be discussed between the British Resident and thePrime Minister, and after such discussion His Highness the amir will accept the advice thereon of the British Resident,(see Note 5).Article V.This agreement shall be ratified at the same time as the Treaty signed this day and shall come into force at thesame time as that Treaty of which it shall be on integral part.NOTES.L.     Article I.    - One of the terms of the contract will be thatthe Financial Adviser cannot be dismissed without the consentjf the British Resident.lo     Article 111(1).     The period in which financial assistanceto Cyrenaica will take the form of a grant to cover agreedbudgetary deficits has been left blank, since it is consideredAiat this period should bear a relation to. the period during7hich the British Resident has reserved legislative powers[see Article III (ii) Of the draft Treaty).5.     Article IV.     The further period in which conditions ofirticle IV shall apply has, also been left blank since it is3dnsidered that this will also have to be decided afterlegctiation with the Amir.r
ANNEX IV

TOP SECRET

DRAFT CONSTITUTION FOR CYRENAICA

PART I

PRELIMINARY

WHEREAS by a Trusteeship Agreement approved by the General Assembly of the United Nations on (date) His Britannic Majesty was designated as administering authority of the Territory known as Cyrenaica.

AND WHEREAS by the said Agreement His Britannic Majesty was authorised to recognise the Amir Sayed Idris el Senussi as Amir of Cyrenaica, and to make provision for the making and promulgation of a Constitution

AND WHEREAS by a Treaty made between His Britannic Majesty and the Amir Sayed Idris el Senussi His Britannic Majesty has recognized the Amir Sayed Idris el Senussi as Amir of Cyrenaica and Head of the Government of that Territory

AND-WHEREAS by Articles 3 and 4 of the said Treaty the Amir undertook to promulgate a Constitution for Cyrenaica in accordance with the provisions therein set out

NOW THEREFORE in pursuance thereof it is hereby ordered by the Amir as follows:-

1. This Instrument may be cited as the Cyrenaican Constitution.

PART II

RIGHTS OF THE PEOPLE AND GENERAL PROVISIONS

2. Islam shall be the religion of Cyrenaica, but complete freedom of conscience and of religious teaching and the free exercise of all forms of worship and free right to religious teaching is ensured to all, subject only to the maintenance of public order and morals.

3. Cyrenaican nationality shall be determined, and its acquisition and loss regulated by a law.

4. The official language shall be Arabic.

5. No discrimination of any kind shall be made between the inhabitants of Cyrenaica on the ground of race, religion or language.

6. No person shall be denied the right of recourse to the Courts of Justice in accordance with the law.

7. (i) /


7. (i) No person shall be imprisoned or otherwise deprived of his personal liberty except in accordance with the law.

(ii) If any person complains that he is imprisoned or otherwise deprived of his personal liberty illegally, he, or any person on his behalf, may apply to the Civil Courts to determine this question. The Civil Courts shall deal with all such applications with the utmost despatch and shall order the release of any person whose imprisonment or detention is found to be illegal.

8. No person shall be held in slavery or involuntary servitude; provided that provision may be made by law for the performance of work or rendering of service by any person in case of emergency or as the result of his conviction by any Court.

9. No person&apos;s property shall be expropriated except in accordance with law and on payment to him of adequate compensation.

10. No tax shall be imposed on any person except in accordance with law.

11. Every person shall be entitled to submit petitions respecting matters concerning themselves or public affairs generally to the Amir.

12. Every person shall have the right to freedom of opinion and expression and to freedom of assembly and association subject only to the maintenance of public order and morals.

13. Any community in Cyrenaica that claims a religious cultural or social organization separate from the main Moslem population of the Territory may apply, in accordance with the provisions of a law which shall be enacted for the purpose, for its recognition as a separate community, and if the application is approved it shall be recognized as a separate community and shall enjoy such rights which may include the right to separate religious courts and incur such obligations as the said law shall proscribe.

PART III

EXECUTIVE

14. Amir Sayed Idris el Senussi shall be the first Amir of Cyrenaica. The succession to the Amirate shall be determined by a succession law.

15. The Amir shall be the Head of the Government of Cyrenaica and he shall do and execute in due manner all things that shall belong to the said Office according to the tenor of this Constitution and the laws of Cyrenaica.


16. The n.mif as soon as conveniently may be after the issue of this Constitution shall with all duosolemnity in a public place before the Chief CivilJudicial ana Sharia authorities and such other notablesas ho may doom appropriate to the occasion to summon,take an oath that&apos;ho will abide by and safeguard this constitution.     Thereafter every Amir on his accessionand every Regent or Regency Council before assumingOffice shall swear the same oath in like manner.17c Whenever the Amir shall be absent fromCyrcnaica or is from any cause prevented from orincapable of exorcising the powers vested in him by virtue of his office of ^miir, he shall after receivingth.. advice of the Council of ministers, appoint a Rodentor a Regency Council to discharge his obligations and exercise his rights and powers subject to such conditionsif any he may see tit to impose.     In the case of his absence from Cyrenaica the appointment shall be made before his departure.18. During the minority- of any Amir or when the amir is from any causu prevented from or incapable of exercising the powers Vested in him by virtue of his office of Amir and he is himself prevented from orincapable of appointing a Regent or Regency Council, theCouncil of Ministers shall appoint a Regent or RegencyCouncil to discharge the obligations and exorcise theRights and Powers of the Amir during this period,19. No Death Sentence shall be carried out until it hos been confirmed by the xUnir.20. Whenever any offender shall have boon condemnedto suffer death by any Court in Cyrenaica the Judgewho presided at the trial shall made a written  reportof the case to the Prime Minister who shall considerthe report in the Council of Ministers and thereaftersend it to the ,rmir with such expression of theiropinion, if any, that they may wish to give.21. The Afflir may grant to any offendjr convicted of any crime or offence in any Court or before, anyJudge, or Magistrate within Cyrenaica a pardon, eitherfree or subject to lawful conditions, or&quot;any remissionin whole or in part of the Sentence passed on suchoffender, or any respite of the execution of suchSentence for such period as the .,mir thinks fit, andmay as he shall See occasion remit any fines, penaltiesor forfeitures which may accrue or become payable in virtue of the judgment of any Court or Magistratein Cyrenaica.22. ^11 State property shall be Vested in the amir in trust for the people of Cyrenaica.     Stateproperty shall include all mineral deposits existingon or below the land of Cyrenaica.23.  (i) /
There shall bo a Council of Ministers.29. The Council of Ministers shall be composed ofa Prime Minister and such other Ministers as the .miiron the advice of the Prime Minister shall see fit toappoints30. The .mrir shall appoint the Prime Minister endhe may dismiss him or accept his resignation from office.31. (i)    Ministers other than the Prime Minister shallbe appointed by the Anlir on the recommendation of thePrime minister.     The Amir may accept the resignation of any such Minister or he may dismiss him on therecommendation of the Prime Minister.(ii)    The Prime Minister and Ministers shall becollectively responsible to the Amir for matters ofgeneral policy of the Government.     They shall also becollectively responsible for decisions of the Council23, (i)    The Criminal and Civil Courts shall notexorcise any jurisdiction in any proceeding whatsoeverover the ,-..mir or his official r^siciaic, or his officialproperty.(ii)     ,,11 legal or ether proceedings on behalf ofor contemplated against State property or the officialresidence or official property of the Amir or concerningthe activities of the Government shall be initiated andconducted in accordance with a law to be enacted forthis purpose.24. The ;emlr shall receive from the publicrevenues an annual grant determined by law. This grantshall bo paid te the ..miirMs civil list.25. ,,11 money and property comprised in the Mmlr&apos;iscivil list shall be kept&quot;distinct from the State revenuesand property.     The Amir shall have free disposition ofall property on the civil list during his life-time andby will&quot;after his death.260 The ,miir shall nominate a Rais el hiwan to administer on his behalf all property and money on thecivil list and in accordance with such directions as the,,mir may give,27.      .    ri.il legal proceedings on behalf of or againstproperty comprised in the civil list and all civil proceedings by or against the .miir other than those dealtwith in article 23 shell be preferred by or institutedagainst the Rais el hiwan end in. these proceedings thesame legal remedies shall be available to or againstthe Rais el Diwan -as in like circumstances would beavailable to or against a private person.COUNCIL OF IiINISThRS
PART IV

LEGISLATIVE

32. The Amir shall have full power and authority to enact, as hereinafter provided, in the form of Irades such laws as may be necessary for the peace order and good government of Cyrenaica provided that no law, except a law specifically amending this Constitution, shall be enacted which shall be in any way repugnant to or inconsistent with the provisions of this Constitution.

33. The Amir may only enact laws after he shall have received thereon either the advice of his Council of Ministers or a submission from the legislative Assembly in accordance with the provisions of Article 36.

34. No Irade shall become effective save on signature by the Amir and after publication in the

gazette.

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY

35. From a date to be fixed by Irade there shall be constituted a Legislative Assembly as in this Part provided.

36. The Legislative Assembly shall be entitled to submit for the consideration of the Amir such Bills as they may consider necessary for the peace, order and good government of Cyrenaica.

37. The Legislative Assembly shall consist of thirty five members of whom ten shall be nominated members and twenty five elected members.

38. The Prime Minister, if he is not a member of the Legislative Assembly, shall be entitled to address the Legislative Assembly on any matter. Any other member of the Council of Ministers shall be entitled to address it on any matter concerning a department of which he is in charge.

39. Any person who is qualified under Article 40 to vote shall be qualified to be an Elected Member of the Legislative Assembly, except that no person shall be qualified to be elected a Member of the Legislative Assembly who is related to the Amir within such degree of consanguinity as shall be prescribed by Law.

[See Note 1.]

40. Every Cyrenaican citizen [See Note 2.] of the age of 25 years and upwards shall be entitled to vote unless he be a person who

(a) Is a lunatic, or

40. (b) / 


40. (b)   Has boon declared to bo a bankrupt, -and has not boon discharged, or(c)   Is serving a torn of imprisonment.41.       -   The elected nemb.,rs shall be elected by thovotes of the citizens entitled to vote under theprovisions of article- 40.42. The creation of electoral districts and theprocedure for the recording of votes and the holding ofthe election shall be regulated by a law to be enactedfor this purpose.43. ,aiy member of the Legislative ^ssembly mayresign his seat by writing under his hand addressed totho .miir provided that no member shall without the permission of tho Legislative Assembly, resign hisseat while any proceedings are pending in respect ofhis election if it is alleged in those   proceedings thatany corrupt or illegal practice took&apos; place at thatelection, or while any proceedings aerc contemplatedor ponding in respect, of his conduct as a member ofthe ;:assembly,44. If any elected Homber of the LegislativeAssembly(a)     Shall oi.j 5(b) Shall bj absent, except on the ground of illness, fro., the&quot; sittings of theAssembly for a Period of threecalendar months&quot; during any Sessionwithout the leave of the assembly:   or(c) Shall by voluntary act acquire the nationality of a foreign state or shall have bo en found guilty of at reasonable act;   or(d) Shall be or become subject to anyof the disqualifications mentionedin , article 40;   or(e) Shall resign,tho Amir shall declare his seat to be vacant and shalldirect an election to be hold to fill the vacancy inthe manner prescribed.,45. Nominated members of the Legislative assemblyshall be nominated by tho amir.46. The Seat of a nominated member shall becomeVacant on the occurrence of any of the events mentionedin (a) to (-) inclusive of article 44, and in the evontof a nominated II ember becoming an elected ii ember of theLegislative, assembly.47.   ,xil /
47. All questions which may arise as to theright of any person to bo or remain a iiember of theLegislative Assembly shall be referred to and decidedJoy the Civil Courts in accordance with the provisionswot the law for the time being in force.48, The Legislative assembly shall elect oneof its Members who shall preside at the meetings thereof.. 49. All questions in the Legislative assemblyshall be determined by a majority of the votes ofMembers present ane voting including the President orpresiding Member, who shall in addition have and exercise a casting veto in case of an equality of votes.50.    (i)   Government Bills shall be introduced by thePrime Minister er other appropriate minister.(ii)   Subject to &quot;the provisions of this constitution and of the Standing Rules-add Orders of the LegislativeAssembly any. Member may introduce any Bill or i propose,any motion for debate in, or may present any petition tothe Legislative assembly.(iii)   The President of the ,assembly shall send acopy of every Bill other than a government Bill to thePrime Minister before it is introduced,(iv)   If the ^mir is of opinion that any Bill whichit is proposed to introduce is inconsistent with hisobligations under any treaty or Internotional Agreemententered into by him, he shall so inform the president and thereupon the President shall refuse to allow theBill to bo introduced unless ane until it has been amended to the approval of the Amir-.51, The privileges, immunities and powers to beheld, enjoyed and exercised.by the Assembly and theMembers thereof, shall be defined by law.52,     (i) The Amir shall appoint the date and place forthe commencement of each session of the Legislativeassembly,(ii) a session of the Legislative Assembly shall continue until prorogued by the Amir,i(iii) The Amir may at any time dissolve theLegislative Assembly;&apos; provided that, unless soonerdissolved, every Assembly shall expire at the end of aperiod of four years from, the date of trie commencementof its first session,jr        (iv) On the expiration or dissolution of an assembly the Amir shall direct fresh elections to beheld and shall, after the completion of such elections,make fresh nominations to the Assembly for the purposeor constituting a new Assembly.53.       (i)/
53o     (i) All elected or nominated members of theprevious Assembly shall, unless otherwise disqualified,bo eligible for election or nomination to the newAssembly.(ii) So far as practicable, elections andnominations shall bo&apos; completed in such time as toanabl-rthc first, session of the new .eeso..bly to commence within four months of the termination of theprevious assembly.PART V.JUDICIARY.54. The Courts hereinafter described shallsubject to the provisions of this Part of this constitution, and to the exemptions and immunitiesgranted by International Law and Treaties exorcisejurisdiction in all matters and over all persons in cyrenaica.55. The Courts of Cyrenaica shall consist of. . (a)   Civil Courts(b) Moslem Religious Courts(c) Such other Religious Courts as maybe established in accordance withthe provisions of Article 15.56.     (i) The Judges of the Civil and Moslem ReligiousCourts shall bo appointed by the Amir and shall not boremovable except in accordance with the provisions ofa lew/ to be enacted for this purpose.(ii) The Judges of any Religious Courtsestablished in accordance with the provisions ofArticle 15 shall bo appointed and removable inaccordance with the provisions of the lew/ enacted underthe said Article for the purpose of accordingrecognition to a community as a separate community.57. Civil Courts including a Court of Appealshall be established and their procedure regulated,by a law enacted for the purpose.   The Civil Courtsshall be vested with Jurisdiction to try and determineall civil and criminal matters, except matters whichin accordance with the Constitution are assigned toReligious Courts or which are assigned by law toother tribunals.58.     (i) Moslem Religious Courts shall bo establishedby a law to be enacted for the purpose, and shall havejurisdiction in matters of the personal status ofMoslems.58.    (ii)/
-9-.    19158.    (ii) The said law shall:(a) Define what shall constitute mattersof personal, status for the purposeof this Article, and(b) Make provision for the determination of suits relating to matters of personal status between Moslemsend non-Moslems.59. Whenever a question arises as to whetheror not a case is one within the jurisdiction of any-religious courts or any other Tribunals, the mattershall be determined by the Civil Courts.PART VI,FINANCE.60.     (i) The proceeds of all taxes, duties and otherimposts levied by tho Government of Cyrenaica shallbe paid into one Consolidated Fund.(ii) The interest on any public debt of theGovernment of Cyronaica, sinking fund payments andsuch other expenditure as may be determined by law,including the annual budget law, shall bo charged ontho Consolidated Fund.61. No sum shall be withdrawn from thoConsolidated Fund except under the authority of a warrant under the hand of the Amir and the Auditor-General addressed to the Ministry of Finance.62. Tho accounts of all departments of theGovernment of Cyrenaica shall be audited by the Auditor-General who, with his deputies, shall at all times beentitled to&apos;have access to all books, records, returnsor other documents relevant to such accounts.   Theseaccounts shall be rendered annually as required by theAuditor-General.   The Auditor-General shall reportannually to the Amir on tho exercise of his functions under this Article.63. The Auditor-General shall be appointed byIrado and shall not bo removable except in accordancewith the provisions of a low/ to bo enacted for thispurpose.PART VII..EMERGENCY SUSPENSION OF CONSTITUTION.64.     (i) If at any time the Amir is satisfied thata situation has arisen in which the Government of cyrenaica /
-io- . 192Cyronaica cannot bo carried on in accordance with the&quot;provisions of this Constitution, he may declare a stateof emergency and enact an Irade providing for the suspension of all or any of the Articles of this constitution.64.    (ii) Any such trade may be revoked or varied bya subsequent Irade.PaRT VIII.TRANSITIONAL AND OTHER.PROVISIONS,65. Notwithstanding any provisions aforesaid, ifthe British Resident shall consider it expedient that,for the purpose of giving effect to any treaty or agreement between the Amir and His Britannic Majesty,any measure proposed by him should have legal effect,he may declare that such measures have effect as if theyhad been enacted In an Irade and thereupon the saidmeasures shall have effect as if they had been soetmctod.66. Notwithstanding the -provisions of Article 43aforesaid, the appointment of the President of thoLegislate of tho&quot; Assembly shall be confirmee by the Amir.67. Notwithstanding any provisions aforesaid, anyperson may address tho Legislative Assembly, if the Amirso directs,68. Articles 65, 66 and 67 aforesaid shall remainin force only for .......... years.   At the terminationof that period tho Amir may enact an trade declaring that the said Articles shall have no further effect,whereupon the said Articles shall be doomed to haveexpired without prejudice to any act already done orrights acquired or obligations incurred under theprovisions of the said Articles.     /Boo Note 5V769. -All land and property in Cyrenaica formerlyvested either wholly or&apos;partly in the Italian state shall? from the dote of the enactment of this constitution, bo doomed to bo the property of thoCyrenaican state, provided that, where such land orproperty was acquired by the Italian State by mains ofconfiscation or expropriation, a law shall definewhether, to what extent and under what conditions suchland or property shall be placed at the disposition of the original owners.70. All land and property In Cyrenaicaformerly vested in any organisation, corporation or association in which the Italian State had an interest,shall from the date of the enactment of this constitution/
-ii- 193Constitution, bo doomed to be the property of theCyrenaican state; provided that a law shall determine whether, to what extent and under what conditions private individuals having an interest in the said organisations,corporations or associations shall receive compensation in respect of such interest.71. All laws a.nd regulations in force in cyrenaica on the date of the enactment of this constitution shall remain in force unless repealedor amended in accordance with the provisions&quot; of this constitution.NOTES..1. Article 39.   It is proposed not to disqualifyfrom election to the General Assembly persons who holdan office-of profit in the Amir&apos;s administration or are members of the Amir&apos;s armed forces or police force.While it is recognised that in principle it would bodesirable to do so, in practice the number ofCyrenaicans who are capable of satisfactorily discharging their duties as elected members is so small that itwould be undesirable to reduce their number bydis qualifi c at ion.2. article 40.   As at present drafted, this Articleprovides for universal suffrage, male and female.   WhileIf would be desirable on general grounds, particularly to moot General Assembly opinion, that women should havethe right to vote, it iserecognised that the constitutionof Moslem states, with the exception of Turkey, do not provide for female suffrage and&quot; it is most likely thatthe Amir will press for the restriction of the right to vote to male citizens only.   It is considered that inthis event we should agree to limit suffrage to malecitizens only since to insist on women having the rightto vote would outrage local opinion.c. Article 68.   It is proposed that the period inwhich the British Resident possesses reserve powers oflegislation should be fixed after negotiation with thoAmir and before the signing of tho treaty (see Note 2to the draft treaty).


</content>
</cab>
