<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/30/0 images: 274-279</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;    195fHlS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret copy NO.  UO.P.(U8)  2621QTH NOVEMBER. 19U8.CABINETREPEAL OF EIRE EXECUTIVE AUTHORITY (EXTERNAL RELATIONS)ACT 1936:    R^JJTtO^IRJ^ GOVERjNMEUT &apos; S &quot;aide MEMOIRE OF2QTK OCTOBER . 19U-S.memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations the Cabinet, at their meeting on 28th October,  (CM. (1+8)67th Conclusions, Minute 3)s  invited rne to submit amemorandum setting out the terms of a written communication whic1might be s&apos;ent to the Eire Government on the practicalconsequences of the repeal of the Eire Executive Authority(External Relations) Act, 1936.2. I circulate accordingly, for the consideration of mycolleagues, the  attached draft (Annex I) which has been prepared in the form of a.reply to the Eire Government&apos;s aide memo ire of20th October (Annex II - previously circulated as telegramNo. Iii). of 20th October from the United Kingdom representative in Eire).      This&apos;draft is designed to contain the minimum of detailed argument necessary to carry matters to the next stage,which, I suggest, should comprise -(a) anything further which the Government of Eire may wish to put to us in writing;(b) a rcu meeting with Eire legal and other officials todiscuss the position in detail.3.beforeitIf the cabinet is despatched.approve the draft reply, I propose,tcMr.  Pearson and Dr. Evattbringill ofit to the notice of Mr. Eraser,whom are at present in Paris.It will not, however, be possible to make the despatch of the    vreply conditional upon their concurrence in view of the short time remaining before the Dail meets.P.J. N.-B.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W.1.10TH NOVEMBER,  191+8.
ANNEX IREPLY TO EIRE GOVERNMENT,The United Kingdom Government- has received the EireGovernment1 a aide-memoire of the 20th October regarding the informal discussions which took place on Sunday, 17th October,at Chequers,  between Mr. MacBride and Mr. McGilligan and representatives of the Governments of the United Kingdom, Canada,Australia and New Zealand.The United Kingdom Government have been glad to learn that the Eire Government welcomed the frank and friendly natureof these discussions and desires to continue close relationship between Eire and the countries of the Commonwealth. For their part, the United Kingdom Government would also greatly welcome the continuance of such a relationship.As indicated during the discussions at Chequers,  theUnited Kingdom Government, who had given the position preliminary consideration, have been advised that the Eire Executive Authority(External Relations) Act, 1936,  is the sole constitutional linkwhich binds Eire to the British Commonwealth,  and that if thatAct is repealed, Eire would cease to be a member of the Common-wealth,  and would become o foreign State in relation to the UnitedKingdom and all other Commonwealth countries.      If Eire became aforeign State,  the most important of the practical consequences would appear to be that other foreign countries, whose commercial treaties with the United Kingdom include a &quot;most-favoured-nation&quot;clause, would be able to claim,  and to make good their claim beforethe International Court of Justice,  that the United Kingdom should extend to them and their nationals any special benefits or privilegeswhich the United Kingdom accorded to Eire or her citizens.      ThisIclaim might be made mainly in respect of trade relations and treat-ment of nationals.As regards trade relations,  the United Kingdom hastreaties with a large number of other- foreign countries,  such as the-1-
United States, Denmark and Argentine,  in which it has undertaken to accord those countries treatment not less favourable than that-accorded to any other foreign country.     If Eire became a foreign state,  such countries could claim that they should be treated notless favourably than Eire.      If the United Kingdom made no changein its treatment of Eire,  the consequences would be that exceptfor a few protective and revenue duties, tho United Kingdom -Government could have virtually no tariff (because every importantcountry would have to be granted the almost universal free entrynow enjoyed by Eire) j    and the x^reference system would disappear,sines we should no longer have in our tariff the scope to accordthe benefits on which the reciprocal system of preferences depends.Eor these reasons the consequence of the repeal of the external Relations Act would be that the United Kingdom Governmentwould be compelled to take action to terminate its commitments to accord preferential treatment in Customs matters to goods.As regards the treatment of nationals, if Eire became aforeign State,  any attempt to continue to treat Eire citizens in theUnited Kingdom otherwise than as aliens might provoke demands fromnumerous foreign countries under their Treaties with the UnitedKingdom that their nationals should enjoy similar privileges inthe United Kingdom.      It would not be possible to concede these demands since, if this were done,  the whole United Kingdom systemof Aliens Control would be undermined.     There would therefore beno alternative to bringing Eire citizens under the ordinary AliensControl applicable to foreign nationals.There are also a number of other points in respect of whichthe special relations between the two countries might have to be adjusted to take account of international lav/.I His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom have notedthat- the Eire Government, in their aide-memoire,  suggest that theforegoing difficulties could be overcome.     His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom would be glad to know what measures the Eire
Government have in mind to this end.      They are very readyto consider the Eire Government&apos;s view and to arrange for a discussion of the difficulties set out above,  if the eire government so desire.
ANNEX IIAIDE MEMOIREThe Irish Government has had under consideration thereport from Mr. MacBride and Mr. McGilligan of the informal discussions which took place on Sunday, 17th October, at chequers, &quot;between them and representatives of Britain, Canada,Australia and New Zealand.     The Irish Government welcomesthe frank and friendly nature of the discussions.The Irish Government notes with deep appreciationthe desire of the Commonwealth representatives who participatedin the discussions to maintain the close relations of friendship with Ireland and to continue the exchange of citizenship&apos; and trade preference rights that have hithertoexisted &quot;between Ireland and the Nations of the BritishCommonwealth.      As already indicated,  it  is the earnestdesire of the Irish Government to continue this relationship.The position, of the Irish Government is that, whileIreland is not a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations,it recognises and confirms the existence of a specially close&apos;relationship arising, not only from ties of blood and kinship,but from traditional and long established economic, social and trade arrangements based on common interest between Irelandand the Nations    that form the British Commonwealth.The Irish Government takes the view that thisrelationship can and should be maintained on the basis that therights and privileges involved, in so far as they are not covered by international agreements, are dependent upon longestablished custom and tradition and do not, therefore, involvethe creation of new rights and privileges entitling other nations to raise objections under &quot;most-favoured-nation&quot; clauses in any existing international agreement.It is the view of the Irish Government thata relationship with the countries of the Commonwealthfirmly based on these factors of tradition, custom and common interest, rather than on forms implying dependence or limitationof sovereignty, offers the best assurance of those relations of mutual understanding and fruitful collaboration whichthe Irish Government, for its part, is anxious to bring about.While this Note is addressed primarily to theBritish, Canadian, Australian and New Zealand Governmentsby reason of the special interest these Governments havedisplayed in relation to the intention of the Irish Governmentto repeal the External relations Act,  it is, of course,the desire of the Irish Government to maintain a likerelationship with the other members of the BritishCommonwealth of Nations.20th October,  19h8


</content>
</cab>
