<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/30/0 images: 280-291</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.P.(h&amp;)  263 COPY NO. &quot;31QTH NOVEMBER,  1 9M-8CABINETREPEAL OF EIRE EXECUTIVE AUTHORITY (EXTERNALSELAT P3HS )&apos; ACT ,  19T5T   POSSIBLE MEASURESTO MITIGATE PRACTICAL&quot; DISADVANTAGESMemorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations  .      A general review of the practical consequences whichwould flow from the repeal of the Eire Executive Authority(External Relations) Act, 1936 was given in paper C.P.M. (1+8)  20.The Cabinet at their meeting on 28th October (C.M.(l)-8) 67thConclusions, Minute 3), invited me to submit a memorandum setting out the measures which might be taken to mitigate the consequences of repeal, so far as these concern the United Kingdom and other commonwealth countries.2.      I now circulate, as an annex to this memorandum, a note on this subject, which has been prepared interdepartmentallyby the Departments principally concerned, on the basis thatEire becomes a foreign country and has to be treated as aforeign country.3.      The possibilities of mitigation, so far as these concern the United Kingdom,  can be summarised as follows:-(a)    Nationality QuestionsWithout infringing our treaty obligations, we could, ifwe so desire, by legislation do the following:-(i)    Eire citizens could be allowed to benaturalised as United Kingdom citizens oneasy terms;    and in addition,(ii)    existing Eire citizens could be given an option to retain their British subject status onthe lines of Section 2 of the british nationality Act.By these means Eire citizens in, or desirous of entering,our professions, or for other reasons wishing to avoid the disadvantages of aliens status in this country, could do so,provided that they were prepared to become United kingdom citizens, or to retain British subject status.     But individuals who become United Kingdom citizens will lose Eire citizenshipunless the Eire Government amend their present law.Eire citizens who do not become United.Kingdom citizens or opt to remain British subjects will have to be treated asaliens.      Thus, they will require leave to land in this countryand will have to register with the police after two months&apos;residence and thereafter on change of occupation, address,  etc.(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
The application to them of the existing system of aliens control would create serious administrative difficulties and might &quot;bringthe system into disrepute.      Eire citizens in the United KingdomcoLild &quot;by legislation be allowed to retain the franchise (m.f .n.obligations do not prevent this), but such legislation wouldbe controversial.Alternatively, it would in theory be possible, but only by amending legislation, to grant the status of Britishsubjects or United Kingdom citizens to all Eire citizens inthe United Kingdom or Colonies on a given date, subject to aright to &quot;opt out&quot;.      The difficulties about this are that(i)    many Eire citizens in this country would find itdifficult in the future to prove that they werehere on the given date;    and(ii)    it would be difficult for the United kingdom authorities to enforce the obligations attaching to nationality or citizenship on the persons concerned:    it would not oven be known how manyof them there were.Prom the administrative point of view it would be greatlypreferable to require those who want the status of british subject or United Kingdom citizen to &quot;opt in&quot; now, and thus to place their attitude on record. In any case, it would benecessary to make some provision for &quot;opting in&quot; - e.g. for/the sake of individuals who might not be in the United Kingdom orColonies on the given date.(b)    Trade relations the United Kingdom and Eire will have to discontinue thegrant of trade preferences to each other.      No mitigation ofthis is possible, except by denunciation of our commercial treaties or, possibly, by agreeing with foreign countries anew interpretation of our obligations under those treaties.Neither of these courses would be justified by the value tous of the advantages which would result in respect of Eire.In fact the value to us of our trade preferences in the Eiremarket is relatively small;    in existing conditions a reductionof the present level of our exports to Eire would not be altogether disadvantageous.      But the discontinuance of preferences will require consequential amendments in the recently concluded Trade Agreement;    and this may involve us inthe re-negotiation of other parts of the Agreement.      We shouldnot press for this re-negotiation, but Eire might do so.k.      Time-TableAs regards the time-table which must be followed inconnection with these changes, my colleagues will note, from paragraph 17(b)  of the note attached, that it appears that,when the repeal of the Eire External Relations Act comes intoforce, we should make some public statement as to our intentionto amend our legislation to take account of the fact that Eirehas become a foreign country.      If we do this, the amending legislation need not necessarily be passed until some monthsafter the statement, and the status quo as regards treatmentof Eire nationals and trade could continue in the meanwhile.
5.      If the Eire Act comes into force immediately it is passed,  such a public statement of -our attitude may he required at any time after truth November.      We understand,however, that the Act is likely to contain a suspensory clause-providing that it will not come into force for some months.If so, no public statement as to our attitude on the questionof Eire&apos;s foreign status will be required immediately the Actis passed, and questions in Parliament could be answered onthe general lines that the consequential measures requiredwhen the Act comes into force are being or will be considered in consultation with other Commonwealth Governments and  the eire Government.6.      Thus, whether or not the Eire Act contains a suspensoryclause,  it seems that we shall have a breathing space in which to decide how far we wish to take full advantage of internationallaw and practice to mitigate, in respect of nationality questions,the effect of the change in Eire&apos;s status.      These decisions could be taken when we come to consider the details of the amending legislation which might take the form of a singleMiscellaneous Provisions Bill.      At this stage, it seems thatwe need decide only that , in the interests, of simplicity ofadministration and good relations with Eire,  that legislation should in the first instance be drafted to furnish the maximum possible degree of mitigation.      The question whether we shouldcontinue to grant the United Kingdom franchise to Eire citizens -will, however, require careful consideration.7.      Possibilities of mitigation so far as other commonwealth countries are concerned are dealt with in paragraphs 5 and of the memorandum.      The problems arising in those countries will be very much less than that  arising here owing to thesmall volume of trade and travel between Eire and other commonwealth countries.      Naturalisation in the commonwealth country concerned is likely to furnish a principal mitigatorymeasure as regards  any nationality difficulties.      The effectof the abolition of preferences is not likely to be serious as regards trade between Eire and those countries.P.J.N.-B.Commonwealth Relations Office.1OTH NOVEMBER,  1948.
ANNEXREPEAL OF EIRE EXECUTIVE AUTHORITY(EXTERNAL RELATIONS)&apos; ^,tfT7TTO^&quot;interdepartmental Note onte on Possible Measures to MitigatePractical Pisaclvantages1. The measures which might be taken to mitigate theconsequences of repeal of the External Relations Act, foreseenin Paper C.P.M*(48) 20, fall into two main categories, viz:-(A)    General measures designed either(i)    to prevent Eire from becoming a foreign country despite repeal, op(ii)    to secure the concurrence of foreign government in the continued exchange ofspecial privileges with Eire, despite thefact that she has become a foreign countrytor (b) Particular measures to mitigate the conseauencesof Eire having to become a foreign country, andhaving to be treated as a foreign country.As regards general measures,  it is understood that&apos;e is no possibility of persuading foreign3s to agree to the continued grant ofjes to Eire, except,  conceivably, at the2. ......... ......__________,the advice given by the Law Officers indicates(a) that Eire must become a foreign country, unlessshe adopts some form of commonwealth  /ealth link involving the Crown (which is likely to be politically impossible for her);    and(b) that therecountriesprivileges ^ A,v, ,,    ^expense of modifying our existing interpretation of the most-favoured-nation clause with serious results for our export trade and for our nationals in foreign countries,3* The Eire Government and certain commonwealth governments are, however, understood to take a different view and to believe that some general mitigatory measures as defined in paragraph 1(a) could be adopted and defended againstremonstrances Toy foreign countries.    It is not known whetherthis belief is based on careful study of the legal position,or is wishful thinking.   What is certain is that if preferencesto Eire were to be continued in trade and other spheres after-Eire admittedly becomes a foreign country, the United kingdom would be open to claims from foreign countries for similar treatment, and that the whole m.f.n. system would be endangered.If foreign countries were to make good their claims (and as mentioned in paragraph 3 it is understood to be the opinion ofthe Law Officers that they would succeed in this),  it wouldbe necessary for us to terminate our commercial treaties withthe countries which had lodged the claims.    It would not bepossible to terminate only the m.f.n. clauses,  since they are-a-
*    205an integral part of the whole fabric of the treaties.   nor would it be possible to terminate our treaties only withthose countries which raised m.f.n. claims in the first place,since the same principle is involved in all the treaties,  andby denouncing some of them, wo should be admitting implicitlythat valid claims could be made against us by all countries with whom we have similar treaties.   Wholesale denunciation of these treaties could not be contemplated, since they embodya wide range of valuable safeguards for our enterprise andtrade in all its aspects in most foreign countries ofimportance.    These safeguards we should probably recover,if at all, only by making substantial concessions on our side.    In the light of the above it is clear that denunciation of m.f.n. obligations does not offer,  so far as the UnitedKingdom is concerned, an acceptable means of mitigating theconsequences of Eire action.k&apos; In these circumstances,  it is necessary to proceed on the assumption that Eire,  on repealing the external relations Act, becomes a foreign country and that the onlymeasures which can be taken to mitigate the consequences ofthis (as in paragraph 1(B) above), are those which could also be extended to foreign countries.5. As regards possible measures to mitigate theconsequences of repeal so far as other Commonwealth countries are concerned,  these are matters for decision by eachCommonwealth Government in the light of local circumstances.It may be that some of those countries will feel that theyhave so little at risk in respect of trade or nationals inforeign countries that it would be worth their while to acceptthe disadvantages which would flow from a. fresh interpretation of the m,f.n. clause in the sense suggested in paragraph 1(a)(ii)above.   It is at least possible,  however, that when other commonwealth countries come to balance the relative importanceof (i) their direct connections with Eire in the matter oftrade and nationals, and (ii)  their similar connections withforeign countries, they may well decide that the preservation of the latter is more important to them than the former.Certainly few of than will be in the position of Eire herselfto whom, having regard to the very small amount of her tradewith and travel to&quot;foreign countries,  a re-interpretation oreven the disappearance of the m.f.n. clause might be of relatively little importance compared with the political advantages of becoming wholly independent and in particular&quot;foreign&quot; to the United Kingdom.6. So far as particular measures,  on the basis set outin paragraph 1(B) above are concerned in relation to other commonwealth countries,  the nature of such measures will necessarily vary with the nationality,  immigration and. other relevant legislation of the Coiinnonv/ealth country concerned.Having regard, however,  to the very small flow of eire citizens and trade to Commonwealth countries other than theUnited Kingdom,  it may well be that those countries will decide that no measures of mitigation are really necessary and will, instead, treat Eire citizens and trade as though they were foreign, except where they have reason to suppose that foreign Governments might agree to the continuance ofexisting privileges on the de minPmis principle.    In thesecircumstances it does not appear ^haiT it would, serve any useful purpose to examine in detail the particular mitigatorymeasures which might be adopted by Commonwealth Governments.
7. it remains to consider particular mitigatorymeasures v/hich might be adopted by the United KingdomGovernment, on the basis that Eire would have to be treatedas a foreign country like any other foreign country, andthat hence, in principle, both tho United Kingdom and Eirewould have to discontinue (i) the exemption of persons from the disabilities and formalities imposed on aliens, and(ii) the trade preferences on goods.   The resultingdisadvantages for the United Kingdom con be grouped under three main headss-(A)   Possible reductions in availability of Eire man-power, and need for additional administrative arrangements in respect of on increased numberof aliens in the United Kingdom.(b) Possible loss of export trade and necessary imports.(c) Miscellaneous adjustments over a wide field,involving in some oases new legislation.8. Before possible mitigations are considered indetail, attention should be called to the fact that it is accepted that naturalisation conditions are not subject tom.f.n. obligations.   That being so, there are two generalmeasures which, if Eire would agree, would go far to mitigate the difficulties which would otherwise arise in the UnitedKingdom as regards the foreign status of Eire citizens.These are:-(a) that all Eire citizens who under the british nationality Act, 1948, will lose British subjectstatus on the 1st January, 1949, should have thatstatus preserved to them (subject to the right to&quot;opt out&quot;).    If this could be agreed, no problem would, arise except as regards Eire citizens bornafter&apos; 1st January, 1949*   But it is almost certainthat the Eire Government, would reject this solution.Limitation of this measure to those Eire citizensactually in the United Kingdom and Colonies mightbe more acceptable to the Eire Government, but theadministrative problem of distinguishing such eire citizens from the remainder would be very difficult and would, in any case, entail some form of individualregistration similar to that for &quot;opting in&quot; under sections 2 and 6 of the British Nationality Act,1948;(b) that the Eire Government should allow Eire citizens who become United Kingdom citizens to retain theirEire citizenship.    If this measure could be agreed,and it seems at least possible that the eire government might accept this, then all those eire citizens on whom alien status pressed too hardlywould have an easy way out of their difficultieswithout losing their Eire citizenship.9. The following paragraphs as to possible detailedmitigating measures are however drafted on the basis that neither of these measures is adopted.Loyalists (see paragraph 8(i) of C.P.M.(48)  20).The rights given to Eire citizens who ore also British subjects to remain British subjects on giving notice to the Secretaryof State could, be continued.    This would apply also to
Ui).   Eire citizens in the Civil Service and AmedF . ,o.?.s. (see paragraph 6&apos;uij of G7J*WT(TZg) 20).     Most-favoured-nacxon obligations would not stand in the way of amendment ofthe relevant United Kingdom Acts so as to permit the continuedrecruitment of Eire citizens into the Armed Forces.    no special mitigation would however he possible as regards entry into the Civil Service (or the professions) of Eire citizens&quot;who did not accept United Kingdom citizenship.(1 &apos;L 1)   Application to Eire citizens of the Aliens Order(see paragraph 6(iiiJ of C .P.M. (lib)&apos; 20).(o)    Leave to Land.    An alien may not land in the UnitedKingdom without&apos; the leave of an LTimlgration Officer who hasto consider in each case whether leave should be granted and,if so, whether any conditions should be attached.    citizens of Eire could not be exempted from this requirement withoutobjections being attracted under our most-favoured-nationobligations.    It would be possible to instruct the immigration officers to grant leave to land to all citizens of Eireunconditionally. - But oven if this were done they could not go through the port control in the same way as British subjects.This would delay the clearance of traffic and call for moreimmigration staff.To get round this difficulty,  it has been suggestedthat we might revert to the pre-war arrangement under whichtraffic between Great Britain and Ireland was free of immigration control,  reliance being placed upon the EireImmigration Services to keep out undesirable aliens.,    Such anarrangement would not,  it is thought, attract most-favoured-nation objections since the exemption from port control ofthe traffic from Ireland would extend to persons of anynationality and not merely to citizens of Eire.    Thereintroauction of the pre-war system, though it would obviatethe difficulty referred to in the preceding paragraph,  isunacceptable to the Home Office for a number of reasons.For instance, owing to the advent of air travel,  the system would allow Eire to be used as a &quot;back way5&apos; into Great Britainby undesirable aliens;    the Eire immigration services, howevercordial their co-operation in day-to-day matters,  cannot be relied upon to take the same attitude as their Britishcounterparts in cases &quot;raising political considerations;    and freedom for the present alien population to move freely betweenthe two countries would raise awkward problems  (e.g. it would allow persons deported from Great Britain and now living in eire to cane back to Great Britain).    Moreover, the Eireauthorities have indicated informally that &quot;they would not.bein favour of the restoration of the former system..Even if the difficulty over leave to land wereobviated by altering the point at which control is applied,  thedifficulty over police registration, dealt with under (c)below, would still remain.(b)    Labour permits.   At present any alien coming to thiscountry to take a particular job may not be given leave to landunless he produces a permit is-sued by the Ministry of labour to the prospective employer,   citizens of Eire could not be specifically exempted from this requirement owing to thernost-favoured-nation difficulty.    It would however be possibleto exempt all aliens coming from Eire regardless of nationality.On the other hand however, it would not be possibleto agree to my arrangement whereby all aliens reaching thiscountry from Eire are admitted without immigration control
as it would leave the door wide open to widespread evasionof employment control.If, however, as indicated in (iii)(a) above it ispossible without infringement of the most-favoured-nationobligations to allow citizens of Eire to land unconditionally,and Other aliens to land subject to conditions, citizens of eire would be put in. the same position as long-resident aliensexempted from employment restrictions other than thoseapplicable to British subjects.    The control over other alienswould remain in effect as at present except that the alienarriving from Eire without a permit but with a specific offer of employment, would have no guarantee that he would beallowed to &quot;take it.(c) Registration with thei Police.    An alien has to register with &apos;t&apos;he police after being in this country for twomonths and thereafter to report any change in his registrationparticulars (name, address, nationality,  date and country of birth, profession or occupation,  details of passport, etc.).He has to produce a photograph, and is given a policeregistration certificate.    The retention of police registrationfor aliens in general is essential,  and there seems to be no way of mitigating the application of these requirements to eire citizens that would not attract most-favoured-nationobjections.    (The effect of such application would be toplace a very heavy extra burden on the police and greatly toinflate records, without serving any useful purpose.   Moreover,the Home Office take the view that if Eire citizens had to be,registered as aliens in Great Britain under the existing systemof aliens control that system might well be brought into disrepute.    Eire citizens would,  of course, have to be registereas aliens in Northern Ireland also and, even if a way couldbe found in Great Britain of mitigating the requirement to register,  it seems likely that the Northern Ireland Governmentwould choose rather to apply the full rigour of the lav/.)(d) There are various other disabilities imposed uponaliens by the Aliens Order (e.g. registration at hotels) but their application to Eire citizens is not thought likely toproduce any difficulty that could not be easily resolved.Visas are not a statutory requirement but an administrativearrangement and can be dispensed with by reciprocal agreements(iv)    Franchise (see paragraph 8(iv) of C*P.M.(48) 20).Most-favoured-nation obligations do not exclude the grant offranchise to aliens, no doubt because the possibility of sucha concession was regarded as extremely remote.After the 1st January, 1949, the right of eire citizens to continue to vote in the United Kingdom and to sit in Parliament will depend, on the general provisions of Section3(2) of the British Nationality Act, 1948.    Section 3(2)will have to be repealed as being inconsistent generally withour most-favoured-nation obligations, and if it is desired that Eire citizens should continue to have the vote and be eligible for Parliament, special legislation for  the purpose would be necessary.    The legislation might prove very contro-versial.   Existing Eire citizens could of course retain theirfranchise rights by opting to remain British or by becomingUnited Kingdom citizens assuming that that option is kept open to them.
10. Trade    (paragraph 11 of 0.P.M. (k8)  20) . &apos; Damage-to United Kingdom interests might take two forms: -(a) we might, if sire no longer accorded uspreferences, lose some of our Eire market tofo re ign c omp e t i t o r s j(b) we might, if Eire insisted on re-negotiating thewhole of the recent trade agreement(i)    have to accept less satisfactory foodcontracts j(ii)    have to face in some cases prohibitivetariffs or quantitative restrictions imposed to protect some of Eire&apos;ssecondary industries.11* To take  (a) first.    If we cancel the preferences weaccord to Eire,  it is unthinkable that-Eire should continueto accord us their counterpart evon though she is probablyless tied than we are by obligation to third countries.(The only way in which the risk to our market in Eire couldbe avoided would be by creation of a United Kingdom-Eirecustoms union.    But, apart from important practicaldifficulties, this would raise treaty difficulties with countries other than those which are parties to the G.A.T.T.;the latter countries would be more or less committed inadvance to accept.a customs union arrangement.   Moreover,politically and economically alike it is hardly conceivable that Eire would contemplate such a proposal.    On the economicside, it- would be considered to mean ruin to the secondary industries she is building up)*   But Eire is so close tothe United Kingdom and the commercial ties between the twocountries are of such long standing that it is doubtfulwhether our preferences have seriously affected the pattern oftrade.    Some United Kingdom industries would no doubt protestat the loss of preference but, apart from any deliberate diver-si on of purchases by Eire, we should on the whole probablyhold our own on level terras with other foreign countries.Over&apos;any long period,  the close relationship between the twocountries would contribute to this.12. The possible upsetting of the recent food contractsis a more serious matter.   -We should not ourselves proposeto re-negotiate them on the grounds that prices must be adjusted in order to take account of -the disappearance of preferences, and though some third, country, e.g. Denmark,might challenge them in the new circumstances, the possibilityis not great.    But the Eire authorities might hot be aversefrom being relieved of some of the contracts for their agricultural produce which laave been concluded in accordancewith the price conditions laid down in the Annex to theAgreement.    If that is so,  then they may ask for a compre-hensive revision of the Agreement.    They may be encouraged todo so by pressure from their industrialists who may want theGovernment to &quot;retaliate&quot; for the loss of the preferences whiotthey enjoyed in the United Kingdom.13. Apart from the food contracts the advantage to Eireof the existing agreements (1S%8 and 1938) is the guarantee of free entry to the United Kingdom and preferences there.We, for our part, in addition to preferences accorded by Eire,have certain guarantees against tho increase of duties or the exclusion of our goods by quantitative, restrictions.   Exhypothesi, Eire will lose her advantages and will be the more-inclined, therefore,  to throw the whole agreement into the
melting pot*   The only bargaining counter we should, have ina new negotiation, apart from the food, contracts in respectof which no doubt price and quantity cancel out as the two sides of the deal, would be our readiness to admit specific-quantities of Eire goods underiour import licensing arrange-iaents.    It seems probable that we should have to forego someof the restraints (i.e. guarantees already mentioned againstincreased duties and quantitative restrictions) which we cannow impose on Eire.   But we have in the 19h8 Agreementrestored to Eire as much freedom of action as she is likelyto want for years to come and complete freedom would be likelyto offer little additional encouragement to the development of highly protected secondary industries.    Eire would take fewergoods from the United Kingdom but we should not regard this asdisadvantageous to the&quot;&quot; extent that the exports could be sentinstead to more desirable markets.lh. It will be seen from the above that there are nomitigatory measures which could be adopted to reduce the disadvantages to the United Kingdom resulting from the disappearance of the trade preferences.   But these dis-a vantages are not likely to prove serious *15* Customsi    As regards imports from Eire,  eitheracross the Land Boundary into northern Ireland or by ship to &apos;West Coast ports, the end of entitlement to Preference will mean that some goods previously admitted free will have topay duty, while others   will have to pay at higher rates thanformerly.    (Some items,  e*g* live cattle,  are exempt fromduty and will continue to be admitted free).    In the case of.goods sent in the normal way and properly declared to theCustoms,  the full machinery of Customs control which already exists will cope with the altered situation, and no special difficulty is foreseen.    There will,  of course, be increasedincentives to smuggling, particularly across the LandBoundary, but such incentives already exist in relation to.goods at present subject to duty,  or to import licensing, andthe change would be one of degree rather than kind.   no special difficulties are therefore envisaged in Customsadministration if Eire becomes a foreign country.16. Miscellaneous.   While Paper C.P.M.(h8)  20 dealt withthe most important practical consequences of repeal,  it hasnot yet been possible to make a survey of all the adjustmentswhich will be necessary if Eire becomes a foreign country,and until such a survey has been carried out,  it is obviouslypremature to consider all possible or necessary &quot;mitigations&quot;:.17. Some importance attaches to the tixaing of those measures, legislative or administrative, which -will be requiredin the United Kingdom as a result of the repeal of the External-Relations Act..&quot; As to this, it is understood(a) that the coming into force of the Eire Act does notin any way arfect administrative action in theUnited Kingdom which will continue to be governed,in respect of nationality,  customs, preferences,etc., by the United Kingdom legislation at presentin force until that is amended:    but(b) that in order to guard ourselves against claims from foreign countries, it would be desirable forsome public statement to be made,  or, possibly,the proposed Miscellaneous Provisions Bill, to bo-introduced, at or about the time of the cominginto force of the Eire Act;    and
that if we had taken action as in (b), the status quo as regards our treatment of nationals,preferences,  etc., might well run on for somemonths * -In the circumstances it seems that(l)    if, as now seems likely, the Eire Government include in their Bill a suspensory clause providing that itshall be brought into force on some date in 1949,no immediate definite statement by the UnitedKingdom Government as to the most-favoured-nation position will bo necessary^(2)    if the Eire Government include no suspensory clause in their Bill, it will be necessary for us to. announce, at the time the Act comes into force,our intention as to altering our practice in \relation to Eire.


</content>
</cab>
