<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/22/43 images: 400-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1942.SECRET;TO BE KEPT UNDER LOOK AND KEY, Copy No.WP (42) 113 h &apos;S rec1uesled that sPeGia! care may be taken tcMarch 7, 1942. ensur8 tha &quot;&quot;&quot;^9f. his desument   -war CABINET.CHINA:  SUPPLIES OF PETROL.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.AT the meeting of the War Cabinet on the 2nd March (W.M. (42)26th Conclusions, Minute 1) I informed my colleagues that enquiries were beingmade from the Soviet authorities in Kuibyshev regarding the possibility of sending supplies of petrol to China from Russia. I think that I should nowdraw their attention to the seriousness of the position which has been brought tomy notice as Acting Chairman of the Allied Supplies Executive.2. In a recent telegram* to the War Office the British Military Mission atChungking gave a brief appreciation of the measures required to enable Chinato play her part in the war during 1942. General Dennys pointed out thatChina&apos;s armies could not continue organised resistance for long unless they received regular supplies of raw materials, and that it was. absolutely essentialthat they should have petrol and S.A.A.3. Chinese petrol requirements are between 10,000 and 13.000 tons a month,of which they have a minimum of three months&apos; reserve. No supplies of petrolare immediately available in India, and present operations will severely reducethe quantities obtainable from Burma. It is possible, that the stores of petrolwhich have been accumulated in dumps along the Burma Road may be collected by lorries which will no doubt continue to operate as long as possible, but we haveno reliable estimate of the quantities of petrol which are stored in these dumps,and it is therefore essential to explore any possible alternative routes and sources of supply.4. Failing the provision of supplies from India which, as I have explained above, are not immediately available, the only possible alternative route which appears to offer any likelihood of making even a portion of the requirementavailable is the north-western route from Russia. This route consists of variousroads connecting the Turk-Sib railway at Alma Ata or Hi in Russian Turkestanwith Lanchow. Our information shows that in the past these routes have been used to carry freight of about 2,500 tons a month, most of which has consisted of petrol. Since the Russians entered the war, however, this traffic has practicallyceased.5. His Majesty&apos;s Charge d&apos;Affaires at Kuibyshev has reported that he hasraised with the Soviet authorities the possibility, of their supplying petrol to china. He added, however, that it would be better if such enquiries came fromthe Chinese Government as the Russians might resent enquiries being made by us* No. 398 of the 18th February.11660   [23546]
2and not by the Chinese. I am accordingly instructing His Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Chungking to approach the Chinese Government with the suggestion that theyshould themselves take the matter up with the Russians.In view of the vital importance of our keeping China in the war, I suggest the following action : (a) I should urge upon the Soviet Ambassador the importance of the soviet governments facilitating the development of supply routes to China;especially for the carriage of petrol.(b) Steps should be taken by the British Military Mission at Chungking toascertain how much petrol is contained in the accumulation dumps onthe Burma Road.A. E.Foreign Office, March 7, 1942.

</content>
</cab>
