<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/223/5 images: 31-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
. THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT

^J 7)  12 COPY NO \^[

Wy4y 1987

C/^^^ CABINET

&lt;^^^ THE LEGISLATIVE PROGRAMME 1987-88

&lt;^^^Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council

At the meeting on 18 June (CC(87) 20.  6) the Cabinet approved The Queen&apos;s

Speech on the Opwriyg of Parliament and invited me to arrange for The

Queen&apos;s SpeecheS^^n8 _Future Legislation Committee (QL) to carry out a

final review of frw&apos;Te^g.islative programme in the light of the decisions

that had been reacwej^V^he review has now been completed by QL and this

paper reports the oufeM&amp;lL

2. The starting point^*^T\Jne programme that was provisionally approved

by Cabinet on 26 March (CCt&amp;^X 12th Conclusions,  Item 5).    From this we

need to delete the Bill ow^i&apos;Twiation of Human Infertility, which Cabinet

decided to drop on 18 June\^w2Jro \Cr iminal Justice Bill, which was largely

lost at the Dissolution, neecfc^^^be added to the list, as do the three

hybrid Bills,   (Channel Tunner^Da^ford-Thurrock Crossing; Norfolk and

Suffolk Broads) which are be ing^e&apos;axj&apos;ied over from the previous Parliament.

The Local Government Bill, whichVlready in the provisional programme,

is now expanded to include a number^^fNArovisions lost from last Session&apos;s

Bill at the Dissolution.    Taking acco#J&amp;T of all these points, the

provisional programme that we now ha^^fiS^et out at Annex A.

3. Only four programme Bills in the rv^were not outlined in The

Queen&apos;s Speech. These are Ports (a mentifli^ of which was deleted from the

Speech by Cabinet on 18 June); Primary Health Care; Prohibition of

Torture; and Evidence (Scotland).

4. In overall volume,  in political vigour andYin {[.he complexity of many

of the Bills,  this programme is heavier than any^^i^we attempted since

1979 and I believe substantially before that.    Itl^iJA/stretch our

resources for drafting Bills to their limits. Moreov^^/it makes no

allowance for unforeseen measures.    These inevitably&apos;jrai^^. each Session,

and when they do, we shall have to improvise to accomntfJaa^Xthem. Within

the programme,  there are three Bills  that are going to maVe/^articularly

heavy demands on Parliamentary time.    These are Abolitioi^^^Wtomestic

Rates, Housing and Education.    They are all long and highbtf^jmtvoversial

measures on which policy issues are still under discussion.^~&quot;^ t^v6

absolutely vital that they are not introduced late and creataAa* s\

uncontrollable log jam in the tail end of the Session which cou^i^jjvolve

the loss of a Bill.    QL&apos;s normal request for Ministers to take a/e^o^E

personal interest in the preparation of their Bills, and to ensure&gt;^9^


timetables for the delivery of instructions are met, is therefore of

^special force for these three Bills; it is essential that their

^introduction does not drift beyond the first half of November.

&lt;Z~yy\ QL felt that we need to go rather further than this, however, and

x^tfe^noted in particular that The Queen&apos;s Speech does not commit the

\3over1^iment to the detailed contents of the Housing Bill.    It is clear that

p  fyVs- pns on private rented sector deregulation must be brought forward

thi^^el^aon and equally clear that reform of local authority housing

accoiii^swust wait until the following Session, but there is still room

for decisions to be made about the distribution of the remaining housing

reformsrtSSy we shall want to bring forward.    The advice to QL was that a

Bill that)*^ r led everything except local authority housing accounts would

run to mor^than 200 clauses, and QL were clear that a Bill of that size,

on top of twe other commitments, would be quite unmanageable if it made

anything later than the fastest possible start.    I am grateful to the

Secretary of State for the Environment for agreeing, therefore, that the

scope of this Ses^JoSVs Housing Bill should be restricted to what can be

prepared for introduction by the end of the second week of November at the

latest, and to thVjifecratary of State for Education and Science for a

similar undertaking\uri^e-epect of the Education Bill.    I must also ask the

Secretary of State for^&amp;t/otland for some matching help in reducing the

load of his Housing and/jRwpk (Scotland) Bill, which is currently estimated

at 100 clauses. ^$\\v

6. In a final search f or&lt;*f $ svtf:o reduce the load on our drafting

resources, QL have reviewed\xh^Axogramme and indentified the Prohibition

of Torture Bill as the one thS^jrtXht most easily be dropped.    QL would

very much like to postpone thr^I&amp;LlN and free the drafting resources that

it involves. v^vO

WATER PRIVATISATION &lt;&lt;/^

7. The paving Bill on Water (Powers^duwj^Oharges) has a firm place in the

programme but one of the main issues thavfcyrias preoccupied Cabinet in

discussion of the legislative programme &gt;cK&gt;s year has been the approach

that should be taken to a main Water Privatisation Bill in the present

Session.    Such a measure would be long (more than 200 clauses) and, on

present advice,  it would not be available before the end of January. At

the Cabinet meeting on 18 June it was agreed thafr^he possibility of

introducing such a measure should not be ruled put Mid that preparation

for it should be taken ahead,  though it was clea&lt; jKE&amp;o problematic to

warrant a commitment in The Queen&apos;s Speech. (f ))

8. QL fully appreciate and sympathise with the arg^map^pfor a swift

Water Privatisation Bill if that is possible, and theyv^n^PAfore

considered this issue as constructively and carefully as Miwp could.

Their conclusions, however, was that it was frankly impos^j&gt;}Jpi\to

accommodate such a Bill in the programme without some very\^ari]b deletion

to release both the drafting capacity and Parliamentary time would be

needed.    QL believe that only the deletion of one of the thrM^ini Bills

mentioned above (Abolition of Domestic Rates, Housing or Educaw^rf/ would

be adequate for the purpose.    Furthermore, continuing to keep ope/tK^fm.


option of a main Water Privatisation Bill would from now on divert

^  Parliamentary Counsel from the necessary work on the Bills that have

^^provisionally been accepted in the programme.    If we are to deliver this

^&quot;wery challenging programme, I must ask the Cabinet to delay no longer in

v_xA/aking a firm decision whether to accommodate the main Water Privatisation

at the expense of one of the deletions I have indicated, or to

\^&amp;fcJ&gt;ftone the Bill to the next Session,  for which it might be given advance

q^iting authority.

OTHE^^ITIONAL BIDS

9. Qfe jf  &amp;ived five further bids for additions to the provisional

programmevy&apos; They are set out at Annex B.    QL readily accept the need for a

short meiiw to prepare for electricity privatisation, and it may be

possible engraft this on to the paving Bill for water privatisation. QL

also appreciate the importance of the Financial Markets Bill in order to

provide an important safety net to certain operations in the City. With

some misgiving ahatrk. the highly technical drafting that will be involved,

therefore, QL recpmmend that this Bill should be accepted in the

programme, provia^L^f^Nis not given drafting priority over the

provisionally accepted/Bills that are already in preparation.

10. The remaining tmrejeUt&amp;&amp;s for additional places are Representation of

the People, Statisticsv^^rnade Act (1947) (Amendment) and Elections

(Northern Ireland).    Aga^rrst^he very heavy pressures described in this

paper, none of these bids &gt;s# m d to QL to have the very high priority that

is required for inclusion a^tWus stage.    We recommend that they are

refused a place for the preffeiK/^Xssion.

ADVANCE DRAFTING AUTHORITY

11. In my memorandum of 24 MarchMC^Cffri 4) I reported QL&apos;s view that the

practice of giving advance drafting^aut^rity to a few Bills each year had

undoubtedly had its uses but that we ^fQi&amp;ved that in future the

arrangements should be limited each y&amp;* A[o two Bills that were

exceptionally long, complex, and of car4&amp;* ? political importance. This

remains QL&apos;s view, but a final selection\Coes not have to be made

immediately.    The main Water Privatisation* Bill would,  if postponed, be

one very obvious candidate.    If Cabinet agree, the selection of Bills for

advance drafting authority might be remitted forjQL to make in the light

of the Cabinet&apos;s decisions on the legislative p/fSo&apos;gnamme for the present

Session.

CONCLUSION K^^yj

12. I invite the Cabinet -

i.      to decide whether a main Water Privatisation BiW^/ hould

be included in the programme for the present Sessioir^k*ra\\if so,

how it should be accommodated: \^^&gt;&lt;!\


ii. in the light of the decision on the Water Privatisation

Bill, to confirm the list at Annex A,  subject to the deletion

of the Prohibition of Torture Bill;

iii. to approve the inclusion in the programme of a paving

\   measure for electricity privatisation and of a Financial

^VMarkets Bill, the latter to be prepared as drafting

?^//resources become available;

v^vy^X to agree that the remaining additional bids listed in

^mnpW B should not be accepted into the programme this Session;

v*^w^ note the agreement of the Secretary of State for the

Envy rtji ent and the Secretary of State for Education and

Sciefyjfe that the Housing Bill and the Education Bill must

be introduced no later than the end of the second week of November;

vi. to endorse QL&apos;s view that the scope of the Housing and

Rent (ScotLaH?TV\Bill must be reduced;

vii. to invitaY^TV\Ministers responsible for Bills in this

Session&apos;s prog^*flmj^s\ to give close personal attention to

their timely pre^a^apion;

vm.  to remit to selection of Bills to be given

advance drafting auth^^^^for the 1988-89 Session.

Privy Council Office

7 July 1987


Annex A

THE PROVISIONALLY APPROVED PROGRAMME

	ESSENTIAL	

DOE	Urban Development Corporations	Short

FCO	Arms Control and Disarmament (Privileges	Short

	and Immunities)	

SO	Scottish Development Agency (Financial Limit)	Short

DTI	British Shipbuilders (Borrowing Powers)	Short

	PROGRAMME	

DOE	Abolition of Domestic Rates etc	Long

DOE	Local Government	Medium

DOE	Water (Powers and Charges)	Short

DOE	Housing	Long

DES	Education	Long

DE	Trade Unions and Employment	Medium

DTp	Ports	Medium

DTp	Merchant Shipping	Medium

MAFF	Farm Woodland, Forestry &amp; Diversification	Short

HO	Immigration (Amendment)	Medium

DHSS	Primary Health Care	Medium

HO	Liquor Licensing	Medium

DTI	Copyright and Industrial Property	Long

DHSS	Social Security	Medium

LCD	Legal Aid	Long

HO	Prohibition of Torture	Short

so	Education (Scotland)	Medium

so	Evidence (Scotland)	Medium

so	Housing and Rent (Scotland)	Long


SECOND READING COMMITTEE

FCO	Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency	Short

LCD	Transfer of Money Between Spouses	Short

LCD	Choice of Law in Marriage	Short

LCD	Domicile	Short

OAL	Museums and Galleries (Miscellaneous	Medium

	Provisions)	

CDL	Duchy of Lancaster Bill	Short

	CONTINGENT	

DOE	Local Government (Commissioners)	

C&amp;E	Customs Consolidation Act (Amendment)	

	LOST AT DISSOLUTION	

	Criminal Justice	

	HYBRID	

	Channel Tunnel	

	Dartford-Thurrock Crossing	

	Norfolk and Suffolk Broads	


Home Office	Representation of the People Short Programme. The main provision would extend the period during which British citizens may live abroad and still vote in Westminster and European Parliament elections. Provisions to change some registration and absent voting procedures might also be added. Opposition likely to oppose.

DTI	Financial Markets Medium Programme. The Bill&apos;s purpose is to resolve the conflict between the Insolvency Act and existing clearing arrangements of financial markets. Unlikely to be controversial, but highly technical.

DTI	Statistics of Trade Act  1947  (Amendment) Short Second Reading Committee. The main purpose of the Bill is to allow the release after 30 years of statistical information currently barred from release.

NIO	Elections  (Northern Ireland) Short Programme. The Bill would extend to Irish citizens the right to vote in Northern Ireland local elections and require candidates to make declarations dissociating themselves from proscribed organisations.

DEn	Energy                                 Very Short Programme. The Bill would provide the electricity industry with powers to prepare for privatisation.



</content>
</cab>
