<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/20/11 images: 152-161</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT; Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1941.secret. uopy No- 43W.M. (41)118th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 118 (41).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, November 24, 1941, at 5-30 p.m.PresentThe Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir Earle Page,Special Envoy from the Governmentof the Commonwealth of Australia(Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Viscount Simon, LordChancellor (Item 8).The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Lord Moyne, Secretaryof State for the Colonies (Items 1-9).Captain   the   Right   Hon.   H.   D.Margesson, M.P., Secretary of Statefor War (Items 1-9).The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Item 4).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Field-Marshal Sir John Dill, Chiefof   the   Imperial   General   Staff(Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P.,  Secretary of  State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary   of   State   for   Burma(Items 1-9).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 1-9).The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt.,  M.P.,  Secretary ofState for Air (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P.,    Minister    of    Information(Items 1-9).Admiral of  the  Fleet  Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-9).Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A.Portal,   Chief  of  the  Air  Staff(Items 1-9).Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.[23191-^1]Secretariat:Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. L. F. Burgis.
WAR CABINET 118 (41).Contents.Minute nNo. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations.................     173Air Operations.Naval Operations:Shipping losses.Military Operations:Libya.U.S.S.R.2      Foreign Affairs............................ 174Dr. Burkhardt.3      Far East............................      .... 1744      Shipping................................ 174Replacement of Allied tonnage.5      Royal Navy      ............................ 174Supplementary New Construction Programme, 1941.6      Disclosure of Confidential Proceedings      ....      ....      .... 1757      U.S. Bases............................ 175Defence questions.8      India      ................................ 176Release of Satyagrahi Detenus.9      Evacuation of Government Departments    ....      ........ 17710      U.S.S.R.........      ........................ 17711      Finland, Hungary and Roumania     ....      ....      ....      .... 177
Nairal, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 115thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.1. The Chiefs of Staff gave the following information in amplification of Cabinet War Room Records Nos. 807-813: Summary of aircraft losses since the 18th November : Home Theatre Enemy 9 destroyed.6 probable.11 damaged.Our Own 11 fighters.1 Coastal Command Aircraft.Libyan Battle Enemy 97 destroyed.8 probable.51 damaged.Our Own 49 destroyed.9 probable.6 damaged.Enemy losses included forty-two machines destroyed on theground.In home waters two enemy merchant vessels of 8,000 tons hadbeen hit, together with two smaller vessels and one E-boat.In the Mediterranean one. enemy cruiser and two merchantvessels had been hit and a convoy had been straddled with bombs.It was estimated that some 400 enemy fighters and 500 long-range bombers had been removed from the Russian front. Most ofthem would probably be located on the Western front and a small number sent to Africa. The scale of enemy bombing attack on thiscountry might therefore be expected to increase from the beginningof December.Naval H.M.S.   Devonshire   had   sunk   on   the  morning   of   theOperations.       22nd November a merchant raider 800 miles south-east of Freetown.Owing to the probability of U-boats in the vicinity, it had been impossible to search for survivors.During the meeting a message was received reporting a successful attack on an important convoy in the Mediterranean.Shipping Losses.        During the previous seven days 25,000 tons of shipping hadbeen sunk; 14,000 tons of shipping had been damaged by marinecasualty.Military The War Cabinet were informed of the details of the operationsOperations. in Libya. It seemed clear from the latest messages received that theLibya, Germans were fighting with great tenacity and that casualties on both sides had been heavy. South of Tobruk the position was veryconfused, but we had gone a long way towards rolling up the enemy&apos;sfrontier defences.u-8-S.R. On the Finnish front there had been no change.   In the leningrad sector fierce fighting continued without any material change. In the Central sector the German offensive against Moscowhad been resumed and the Germans were now within 30 miles of thecapital. Further south fierce fighting continued at Tula, and onthe Tula-Orel front the German thrust had made further progress.The German claim to have captured Rostov was probably correct,although its capture did not necessarily mean the loss of the bridges[23191-1] b 2
over the river. The Germans claimed to have captured the wholeof the Crimea, with the exception of the Sevastopol defensive area,but up to the present had made no attempt to cross the KerchStraits.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Foreign Affairs.        2.   The Foreign Secretary suggested that, in the event of dr. Burkhardt. Ministers meeting Dr. Burkhardt, the Vice-President of the Inter-national Ped Cross Committee, and formerly High commissioner at Danzig, who was now in this country, it would be prudent toavoid discussion of political matters.Far East. 3. The War Cabinet had a discussion on the latest develop-previous ments in the situation. The discussion and conclusions are recordedReference: ^n the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.W.M. (41) 112thConclusions,___Minute 1.)Shipping.Replacement ofAllied Tonnage.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 28thConclusions,Minute 8.)4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of War Transport (W.P. (G) (41) 135) asking for authorityto agree that any vessel purchased by an Allied Government underthe scheme for the replacement of Allied tonnage, approved by theWar Cabinet on the 13th March, 1941, might be transferred to theAllied flag if and when a complete Allied crew could be provided toman her. This would be on condition that all the ships purchased by the Allies under the scheme, whether under British or Alliedflag, would be chartered to us for the duration of the war on thesame terms as for British requisitioned ships, save for an adjust-ment to take account of any necessary extra expenses of crew.The War Cabinet agreed to the above proposal.Royal Navy.SupplementaryNewConstructionProgramme,1941.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 43rdConclusions,Minute 5.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (41) 280) stating that the reviewof Naval requirements and of the capacity available had now beencompleted, as had been proposed at the time when the War cabinet had approved the original New Construction Programme for 1941.He now proposed a supplementary programme for 1941, as set outin his Memorandum.The main discussion took place on the proposal that work should be begun now on the gun-mountings of one capital ship (theLion) and on one heavy 8-inch cruiser so that these ships could belaid down in 1942. It was true that these vessels would probably not be completed for about four years. But, since gun-mountingstook some months longer to complete than the ships, it was right toset this work in hand now, so as to avoid further delay if it was finally decided to lay the keels of these vessels in the following year.Discussion also took place as to whether the programme of tank-landing craft was adequate. The Minister of Labour and national Service said that the provision of man-power for theconstruction of these craft would be made easier if more modernmethods of construction were adopted.The War Cabinet-(i) Approved the supplementary New  Construction Pro-gramme for 1941 as set out in W,P. (41) 280.
(ii) Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty and the Secretaryof State for War to report to the Defence Committee(Operations), in about a fortnights time, on the possi-bility of increasing the programme of construction of tank-landing craft,(iii) The First Lord and the Secretary of State for War were invited to consult with the Minister of Labour and national Service on the point referred to at &quot;X&quot;above.Disclosure of 6.   The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that he hadConfidential recently had under consideration a proposed volume of memoirs,Proceedings. which involved disclosure of the substance of proceedings of theCommittee of Imperial Defence and Cabinet, and of confidential discussions between Ministers and their advisers. Application hadbeen made for permission to waive the existing rule in order topermit publication in the existing case.The Prime Minister said that he was satisfied that publicationat the present time would give rise to a great deal of controversyand ill-feeling, and that it would be undesirable to grant suchpermission during the war. It would be much better to leave thesematters over for decision after the war, when it might well bepossible to adopt a less rigorous attitude.The War Cabinet-Expressed general approval of the course proposed by thePrime Minister.United StatesBases.defence questions.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 32ndConclusions,Minute 4.)7.   The War Cabinet had before them (1) A Memorandum by the Chiefs of Staff (W.P. (41) 277), towhich was annexed a draft Agreement drawn up by theBritish and United States Chiefs of Staff, for sub-mission to their Governments, regarding outstandingDefence questions in the bases we had leased to theUnited States.(2) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs (W.P. (41) 281) supporting the recommendation in paragraph 5 of the Memorandum by the Chiefs ofStaff that the Canadian Government should be made aware as soon as possible of the proposed Agreement.In his view, we should leave Mr. Mackenzie King in nodoubt that we, like himself, thought it essential to secure,if possible, that the command in Newfoundland shoulddevolve upon a Canadian officer.The War Cabinet-(i) Approved the draft Agreement drawn up by the Britishand United States Chiefs of Staff,(ii) Authorised the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs tocommunicate with Mr. Mackenzie King as proposed at&quot; Y&quot; above.
8. The War Cabinet had before them a further Memorandumon this subject by the Secretary of State for India (W.P. (41) 283).Attached to this Memorandum was a telegram from the Governor-General, in which he stated that he considered it essential that anannouncement of common policy, to be followed by all governments in India, should be made as soon as possible by the Government ofIndia. The matter had aroused great public interest, and it hadbeen stated in the Assembly that the Government would give carefulconsideration to the question in a sympathetic spirit. If theimpression was now created that the matter had been left to theProvinces, the idea would gain ground that the Government of india had been overruled, and their prestige would be affected.The Secretary of State for India said that the substance of thedecision was not in dispute, and that the only matter in question was the form in which it should be made known. He thought that itwould be almost out of the question to overrule the Governor-General in a matter of this kind. Further, if questions were put tothe Government of India as to their attitude and position in thismatter, it was hard to see how they could avoid disclosing the factthat they had given instructions, albeit in the form of a personal and confidential message, to the Provincial Governors as to the line which they should adopt.The Prime Minister said that the broad effect of the WarCabinet&apos;s decision had been that they had accepted the proposal that the detenus should be released, provided that no form of public announcement was made and that the matter was done by means ofa personal and confidential message to the Governors. The present proposal was, in effect, that the former proviso, to which the WarCabinet had attached importance, should be waived, and that apublic announcement should be made after all. The Assembly had now adjourned until January, and he found it difficult to see whythe matter should not be dealt with on the basis agreed by the WarCabinet on Thursday, the 20th November. In this case, the detenuswould be released before the Assembly met again. In any event, he found it difficult to see why the War Cabinet should be asked to give an urgent decision in favour of a public announcement.In discussion, the view was expressed that it was unfortunate that the matter had been so handled as in some way to prejudge theWar Cabinefs decision before they had had an opportunity of fullyconsidering it. At the same time, it was impossible to ignore the somewhat difficult position which had now arisen.The War Cabinet-Invited the Prime Minister to send a personal telegram tothe Governor-General explaining the strong reluctancefelt to the proposed announcement, asking him to explain to the Prime Minister the reasons for his urgent request for a decision in favour of a public announcement; butindicating that, if he (the Governor-General) on full con-sideration felt bound to adhere to his request for authorityto make some form of public announcement, the WarCabinet would not withhold assent.India.Release ofSatyagrahiDetenus.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 116thConclusions,Minute 3.)
Evacuation of 9.   The War Cabinet took note, with approval, of a Memo-Government randum submitted by the Home Secretary and the Minister of home departments. Security, as Chairman of the Civil Defence Committee (W.P. (G)(Previous (41) 133).Reference: The main points in the Memorandum were as follows : W.M. (40) 273rd ^ That ^ Black Move, as a concerted move of essentialConclusions, Government Staffs from London to the Provinces, should minute 2) be abandoned.(2) That the Departments should be invited to remove from london any less essential staffs still left.(3) That, while the return of staffs to London should generally be forbidden, applications by Departments for the return of a few individual officers should be considered on their merits. &apos;(4) That publicity regarding this decision should be avoided.U.S.S.R. 10.   The War Cabinet had a further discussion on this matter,(Previous the Conclusions of which are recorded in the Secretary&apos;s StandardReference: Pile of War Cabinet Conclusions.W.M. (41) 114thConclusions,Minute 1.) _Finland,Hungary and roumania.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 116thConclusions,Minute 2.)11. The Foreign Secretary reported that he had put toM. Maisky the proposal approved by the War Cabinet at their meeting on Thursday, the 20th November, that an approach shouldbe made to Finland on the basis of a joint Anglo-Russian guarantee of her independence. M. Maisky had said that an approach onthese lines would not be well received by his Government, who took the view that all efforts to get Finland out of the war would behopeless. In the circumstances, the Foreign Secretary said that hehad not pressed M. Maisky to proceed with this proposal.The Foreign Secretary drew attention to a report from Swedenthat Finland, Hungary and Roumania would shortly sign the Anti-Comintern Pact. If this was true, it was a new fact which wouldhave to be taken into consideration, and might well prove the groundon which we should finally break with these countries.The War Cabinet *Took note of the above, and agreed that no action shouldbe taken in this matter for a few days pending a reply tothe telegram sent to M. Stalin by the Prime Minister (seepreceding Minute).Great George Street, S. W. 1,November 24, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
