<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/12 images: 116-121</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1943. m ,SECRET.W.P. (43) 312.15th July, 1943.WAR CABINET.BRITISH POLICY IN THE MIDDLE EAST.Note by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.IN accordance with the decision of the War Cabinet on the 14th July last(W.M. (43), 99th Conclusions, Minute 2), I submit herewith a series of recommen-dations in regard to our policy in the Middle East.A. E.Foreign Office, 15th July, 1943.Draft War Cabinet Conclusions on British Policy in the Middle East.1. It is approved in principle that the Middle East Supply Centre should be developed by stages towards a Middle East Economic Council, which would include representatives not only of the British and United States Governments, but also of the Governments of the main territories in the Middle East. This development should be carried out cautiously. The Minister of State would report progress -periodically, and should seek the approval of the War Cabinet before taking anystep which might have important effects in the political or economic sphere. Inparticular, he would, of course, ask for authority before any steps are takenleading to the formal establishment of a Middle East Economic Council.2. An endeavour should be made to reach an understanding with the UnitedStates Government as to our general policy in the Middle East.For this purpose a communication should be made to the United StatesGovernment to the effect that, while the Middle East is an area of essentialstrategic importance to the British Commonwealth and Empire, we hope that theUnited States Government will be willing,to collaborate with us in this area, andthat for this purpose a mutual understanding of each other&apos;s aims and interestsis much to be desired.3.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs would consider the best way.in which this matter could be taken up with the United States Government.   Atathis stage, the communication of. a written memorandum to the United StatesGovernment was unlikely to be the best method of approach, but a memorandummight perhaps be sent to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington as a basis on which he might initiate conversations with the President or the Secretary of4. It might be indicated to the United States Government that we hopedthat the Middle East Supply Centre might gradually assume the functions of a middle East Economic Council, and that we might have their continued co-operation and collaboration on this body.[25761]






</content>
</cab>
