<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/11 images: 238-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.SECRET.COPY NOW.M.  (40) 11th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 5.Confidential Annex.WESTERN FRONT.Possibility ofGerman Attackon Holland andBelgium.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 7thConclusions,Minute 4.)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR said thata telegram had been received from the military attache, Brussels, on the 11th January, stating thathe had received information from a most reliable source as to a German plan,with detailsof a projected attack against Holland Belgium inwhich the German Army was to launch an offensive against the British and French Armies from the north sea to the Moselle, whilst a detachment would occupyHolland.     The land offensive was to be combined withan air attack, of which the plan gave circumstantialdetails.The War Office had had no confirmatoryinformation of this German plan.     They considered,however, that sufficient German Divisions werepresent in the Aachen area to carry out an initialattack without further troop movements and with littlewarning.     At the same time certain features of thereport raised doubts as to its authenticity.The War Office had accordingly asked the military attache, Brussels, whether his informant was inpossession of original documentary evidence, and, inparticular, what were the grounds for believing thatthe attack would be put into execution within the nextfew days.

The reply from the Military-Attachestated that the information was derived from an aircraft which had crashed at Hasselt in Belgiumwith two German Staff Officers on hoard.     these officers were believed to have been carrying out a reconnaissance over Belgium.     Papers found in theaircraft contained the alleged plan for attack onBelgium - papers which the German Staff officers had endeavoured, but had failed to destroy, andwhich were now in the possession of the BelgianStaff.     The Belgians asked that the strictestsecrecy should be observed.     Meanwhile, it was stated that the German Embassy in Brussels was in astate of panic.The Secretary of State for War explainedthat he was conveying this report to the Cabinetbecause it was of a much more definite characterthan many of the reports which had lately beenreceived of German intentions against the low countries.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL staff said that the plan described i:aa feasible but wasnot an operation which he himself would favour.Colour was lent to it by the fact that if Hitler hadbeen feeling the psychological need for taking action, the present frozen state of the Low Countriesprovided him with the opportunity which the mud had hitherto denied him,       Whilst, therefore, the Chiefof the Imperial General Staff considered than an

attack across the flat country might he possible, hewas convinced that the frozen state of the mountainroads in the Ardennes precluded the possibility ofa successful attack being launched through Luxemburg.The necessary warning had been sent to Lord Gort, andGeneral Gamelin had also been informed.     Our plans for meeting such an attack, in co-operation with theFrench, had all been worked out and were ready to beput into operation immediately the need arose.     TheChief of the Imperial General Staff gave the WarCabinet a brief outline of these plans, and said thathe had discussed them very carefully on many occasionswith the British andFrench Commander-in-Chief;    andthat he had done so again during the visit to Francefrom which he had just returned.THE MINISTER WITHOUT PORTFOLIO confirmed that the demolition plans, for which he had been responsible for drawing up, were likewise ready to beput into immediate operation.Reference was made to the fact that the king of the Belgians had sent a message of an urgent character to Sir Roger Keyes, asking to see him, and that it hadbeen arranged that Sir Roger should arrive in Brusselsthat afternoon.The War Cabinet took note of theabove statements.Richmond Terrace,. S..W.1.,13th January, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
