<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/39/17 images: 176-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited. 8 7It is issued for the personal use of...........^$ ^u^ky.............MOST SECRET. Gopy N0....I.SLW4-i&quot;,(.45). 181st CONCLUSIONS. MINUTE 2,Confidential Annex(en:&apos;. September., 1943 - 11.30 a.mc)ITALY. The War Cabinet wore informed of the latest developments in the Italian position, as reported in tho following(Previous telegrams -Reference:W.M, (43) 120th      NAP    346, 347 and 348 dated 1st September fromConclusions, General Eisenhower:Minute 4)WELFARE 56V dated 2nd September, embodying a message sent to General SisonhoY/or from thePrime Minister and President RoosevoltoA mooting had taken place in Sicily on 31st August betweenGenerals Castollano and Zanussi and representatives ofGenera::. Eisenhower, including the two Staff Officers fromGeneral Eisenhower&apos;s Headquarters who had held the previousconversations with General Castollano in Lisbon.      GeneralCastoll/no had opened, the discussion by saying that, if theItalian Government were a free Government,  thoy would be perfectly ready to accept and announce the armistice termspat tho time which had been suggested.     The Italian Govcrn-mont was? however, no longer free;    the German hold overItaly was substantially stronger than it had been at the -time of tho Lisbon conversations:    and in these circumstances it was impossible for the armistice to be announced before themain Allied landings in Italy.     The Italian Government mustbe sure, before the announcement was ma do,  that the Alliedlandings would be in sufficient strength to ensure success and to guarantee the security of Romeo     The Italianemissaries then tried to olicit information regarding thostrength of the allied forces which were to be landed;    andit became clear that&apos; they were mainly concerned to ascertain whether a landing would be made in strength to the north of rome o      The Allied representatives made it clear that theywere not prepared to continue the discussion on the basis that the armistice would not be announced until after thelandings nor could thoy give any information on the strengthor location of tho proposed landings.      General Castellanothen said that before carrying the matter any further homust return for further consultation with his Government0Ho first wished, however, to raise three supplementary points:(i)      Could it be agreed that the Italian Fleet should move to Maddalena, &apos;-rather than to an Allied port, as thiswould softon tho blow of surrender to tho ItalianFloot and the Italian people?Ho was told that this variation of the terms couldnot be accepted.^ (ii)   What steps would be taken to protect the VaticanCity against tho Germans?He was told that tho protection of the VaticanCity was at one with the protection of Rome.(iiij) The Germans were bringing great pressure to bear\   on the Italians to got possession of allied prisoners captured by the Germans in Africa;-1-

and it was very doubtful whether the ItalianGovernment would bo able to resist this pressure.This statement was noted.General Castellans was then told that, in view of thodiscussion, tho Allies were willing that the limit.for accept-anco    of the armistice terms should bo extended until midnight on the 1st/2nd September in order that General Castellansmight bo able to consult his Government again0     A firm replymust? however, be given by that time.As a result of those conversations, General Eisenhowerhad come to, the c uiclusion that the Italian Government would be unwilling to accept and announce the armistice unless they were assured that allied troops would be landed in the Rome area .togive them some guarantee of protection against the Germans.General Castollano had indicated that he hoped to bo able toarrange that, if such troops were landed, Italian divisions near -Rome would do their best actively to oppose the Germans;    and itwas also hoped that Italians would carry out widespread sabotagoand other anti-German activities which would facilitate thoAllied operations.     General Eisenhower had therefore decided inprinciple to land an airborne force near Rome at the appropriate time., and was informing General Castellano to this effect, making it clear that the despatch of this force was contingent upon an Italian guarantee that the conditions outlined in tho conver-sations would be kept - in particular, that the armistice wouldbe signed and announced as desired by the Allies,  that theItalians would seise and hold the necessary airfields and stopall anti-aircraft fire, and that Italian divisions in the Romearea would take action against the Germans0In his telegram EAR 348 General Eisenhower had reportedth- t a signal h \&amp; since boon received from General Castellanoto bhe -effect that tho reply of the Italian Government was inthe affirmative and that he would arrive in Sicily on 2ndSeptember to arrange tho remaining details.On receipt of these telegrams the President and tho PrimeMinister had telegraphed to General Eisenhower in the following terms:-    &quot;We highly approve your decision to go on with. AVAL/JSTOHBand to land an airborne division near Rome on the conditionsindicated,,     We fully recognise military considerations must bedominant at this juncture.&quot;THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF reported that the Chiefs of Staff loadconsidered the position.at a mooting earlier in the day, and were of opinion that in the special circumstances the proposed landing of an airborne force near   Rome v/as justified.As regards the Italian suggestion that the armistice shouldnot be announced until after the landings had taken place,  theChiefs of Staff had always,   thought it important that tho announco-rncnt should be made, before the landings, so that the news could be broadcast and tho Italian Forces and people urged not to offer any opposition and to co-operate so&apos; far as practic. bio with the AlliedForceso     No such instructions could be transmitted in advance tosubordinates without grave risk of disclosure to the enemy;    and onthis account tho announcement could not safely be made until a few hours before the landings.      It v/as still thought desirable,however., that tho announcement should be made before the landingstook place;    and the Chiefs of Staff would deprecate any deviationfrom this &quot;plan.In discussion,  attention was drawn to the publication inthe Press of reports of armistice discussions with Italy0Reference was made,  in particular, to a circumstantial reportpublished that day in the &quot;Daily Telegraph&quot;.      Impending militaryoperations would bo gravely prejudiced if news of these discussionsreached the enemy, and oil this account it was specially important-2-

that all practicable steps should be taken toprevent tho publication of such reports bynewspaper, s in this country.The War Cabinet -(l) Took noto of tho present posit ion., as described in the telegrams which hadbeen road out at the meotihgo(2) Invited the Secretary of the WarCabinet to take up with the Ministryof Information the question whether further steps could not be taken toprevent tho publication in thiscountry of reports indicating that representatives of tho Italian and allied Governments had boon in touch,with   a   view to the conclusion ofan armistice.Offices of tho War Cabinet, S*Wi1*




</content>
</cab>
