<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/56/0 images: 47-47</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IfCOPY NO.CABI NETATOMIC ENERGY organisation memorandum by the Secretary of State for the colonies refer to the paper by the Paymaster-General (C.(52) 317),   I amputting in a paper my-elf only because I may not be present at the cabinet when it comes before them.2. I had a fairly extensive knowledge of the workings of the Ministry ofSupply and the Ministry of Aircraft Production during the war and I have had some touch with questions relating to nuclear physics when we were in opposition and I was an industrialist.    Thus I have very strong views on thesubject.3. I earnestly hope that the Cabinet will endorse the Paymaster-General^recommendations.    I can add very little to his arguments and I dc not wish to repeat them.4. (a)    Certain considerations appear to me to be decisive.     The Civil Serviceand Government Departments in all countries are not organised for this type ofwork.     The cantilever system of responsibility does not adapt itself readilyto the unusual or the unexpected, and Departments are better at detecting-deviation from the orthodox than at spurring people to leave the well-troddenpath.(b) There is a gulf fixed between administrative Civil Servants and technicalCivil Servants.     The status of the technical Civil Servant is not only differentbut also lower than that of his administrative counterpart.    These distinctionsare due to good reasons in the ordinary fields of administration but they are particularly inappropriate in a matter like the organisation of atomic energy.(c) Finally standardised rates of pay in the Civil Service for various gradeshave insuperable disadvantages in work of this kind.     Civil Service salariesrise like the tide, and once a Civil Servant in the Ministry of Supply got ahigher salary than a Civil Servant of a higher grade in the Ministry of Pensions,disorder would follow and civil disturbances would soon be detected in theAthenaeum Club. vWe must be certain that speed and flexibility are not sacrificed to the code.O.L.Colonial Office, S.W.1.confidential.(52) 36324TH OCTOBER, 195224TH OCTOBER, 1952

</content>
</cab>
