<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/56/0 images: 48-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)i,^^^-^^^----^-^^-.^-.^^^^^-^-^^.,-^---.-.    -co-...,.,.. ......................secret.(52) 364 COPY r-25th OCTOBER, 1952.CABINETATOJVIIC ENERGY organisation memorandum by the Minister of supply have read with interest the paper (C. (52) 317), submittedto the Cabinet by the Paymaster-General, in which he proposes:(a) that the atomic energy organisation should be removed from the Ministry of Supply and transferred to a statutory corporation;  and(b) that, since the necessary legislation could probably not be enacted for about two years, an &quot;independentMinistry&quot; should be created to &quot;undertake theunscrambling of the project from the Ministry of Supply&quot;.2. There is no doubt that a case can be made out in favour ofcontrol by a statutory body.   On the other hand, sound arguments can alsobe advanced in favour of the present system, which was adopted by the late government after weighing up the advantages and disadvantages of the two alternatives.3, It must, however, be remembered that we are not starting from scratch.   The problem is not just to decide which of the two systemsis theoretically the better (and I have no doubt that opinions will differ).In order to justify the disturbance and expense which the change wouldinvolve, the balance of advantage would, I submit, have to be overwhelming.4. There is no evidence that, within the overall financial limitsprescribed by the late Government, the progress of atomic research anddevelopment has in fact been held up by the dead hand of the Civil Service.5. Speaking generally, the existing organisation has carried outall its programmes on time.   All its major and highly complex establishmentshave, with the help of the Ministry of Works, been completed according toschedule.   Britain has become a major producer and the largest exporterof radio-active isotopes.   Preparatory work is shortly to start on thedevelopment of atomic power plant for industry.   An atomic bomb, superior to the Bikini model, has been successfully made and exploded, and we arenow going into production on a limited scale.   Plans for an expansion ofthe production programme are being considered, and will go forward as soonas the Government, with the advice of the Chiefs of Staff, decide the scale of effort which our strategy requires.
6. These achievements do not suggest that the organisationresponsible has been lacking in &quot;vision, elasticity and rapidity of decision&quot;or that it has been &quot;cramped in a straight jacket&quot;.7. In fact the organisation has been given an exceptionally freehand.   It has throughout virtually formulated its own policy.   It has been accorded special priority in the allocation of materials and housing.   ^Vithinthe expenditure approved by the Government, work has not been delayedby any over-exacting Treasury control.8. The only qualification to this general statement is in regardto salaries. There have been a few cases where it can be shown that thescale of salaries offered was insufficient to attract some key man neededfrom outside. However, these difficulties have now been removed by theTreasury *vhich allows higher rates to be paid when necessary.9. The view expressed by the Paymaster-General that there isa &quot;frightening rate of loss of key staff&quot; is not borne out by statistics, which show that our losses compare not at all unfavourably with the experience of outside industrial organisations.10. Nor is it right to suppose that a statutory corporation would bein any better position to assure security than a Government Department,   Inone important respect it would be definitely at a disadvantage.   Whereasunder the present system the figures of expenditure can be concealed withinthe total of the Ministry of Supply Estimates, a separate corporation would be obliged to reveal its expenditure to the world, as is done in America.11. It would be illusory to imagine that a corporation, dependententirely upon public finance, would be free to take its own decisions withoutregular consultation with the Government and without scrutiny by the public accounts Committee of the House of Commons .   (In the United states theexpenditure of the Atomic Energy Commission has to be justified anddefended in detail before Congressional Committees.12. It would be equally wrong to assume, as is suggested, that a statutory corporation would be able to dismiss its officers at will without incurring public and Parliamentary criticism.   In this  connection, it shouldbe emphasised that it is far from certain that anything like the whole of theexisting scientific, technical and administrative staff would be willing to transfer to an organisation which offered them reduced security of employment and whichlimited their opportunities of promotion to the field of atomic energy.13. Everyone will agree upon the importance of obtainingco-operation from industry,,   However, the Ministry of Supply has already proveditself able to co-operate most effectively with industrial firms over a wide field (for example, aircraft and guided weapons).14. In short, there is no. reason to believe that progress up to date would have been any greater, quicker or cheaper or that security would havebeen any tighter, if a statutory corporation had been in charge.15. It cannot be denied that Russia is ahead of Britain in theproduction of atomic bombs and may by now have a not inconsiderable stock.While we do not know how many years she has been working on the project,she has without doubt been devoting to it much larger resources than thiscountry.   If that is a reflection on Britain, it is a reflection not on the atomic
energy organisation, but on the policy of the late Government which decidedthe size of the atomic programme and the amount of money to be spent on it.16. For the reasons I have explained, I do not on balance considerthat the proposed change would be justified.   But, should the Cabinet take acontrary view, I suggest that the Ministry of Supply can quite well be crustedto carry out loyally the transfer of functions.17. I can see no merit in the Paymaster-General&apos;s proposal toset up a kind of interim receivership, involving the creation of an additionalMinistry (and presumably also the appointment of an additional Minister),   Itwould be exceedingly difficult to defend this in Parliament at a time when ourdeclared policy is to reduce Government staff and expenditure.18. The Bill to set up the interim Ministry might, as the Paymaster-General suggests, be short, but it would certainly not be uncontroversial.It would, of course, raise the whole question of the transfer of theresponsibility for atomic energy to an outside statutory body and would behotly contested by the Opposition.   Moreover, the issue would have to befought out all over again a year later when the main Bill was introduced.20. In the light of the above considerations, I recommend:-(a) that before a decision is taken, the advantages and disadvantages of transferring the control of atomic energyto a statutory body should be examined and reported on bya committee of Ministers, before whom all the relevant facts would be laid:  and(b) that, in the event of it being decided to make the proposed transfer, the present organisation should in the meantime beallowed to continue, thus avoiding the dislocation involvedin making two changes in two years.D.S.Ministry of Supply, W.C.2.25th OCTOBER, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
