<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/56/0 images: 276-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SUPPLEMENTARY DEFENCE EXPENDITURE 1952-53.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer am advised that the Ministry of Supply and the Army are likelyto overspend their votes this year by considerable amounts.   The figures are far from certain at this stage, but the excesses are likely to be at least 50 millions and possibly as much as  70 millions in the case of the Ministryof Supply., and from  25 millions to  30 millions in the case of the War Office,Supplementary estimates will be necessary in due course.2, Under ordinary Parliamentary procedure we ought to presentsupplementary estimates to Parliament forthwith as soon as anticipatedover-spendings of this magnitude are definitely foreseen.   Our predecessorswere criticised for not disclosing a large excess on the National Health service in 1949/50 until they brought in a supplementary estimate in the closing weeks of the financial year.   We shall be criticised ourselves if we adopt a similar procedure in this case as regards the Ministry of Supply and the Army.3. I should myself very much prefer to follow the usual procedure of early supplementaries in these cases.   I understand, however, that theprovision of time for these estimates with the necessary Consolidated FundBill would make such a serious inroad on the time available as to upset the timetable for the Transport Bill and the Iron and Steel Bill.4. In the circumstances I must be content to leave the presentation of the supplementaries until the New Year.   This will, however, make itnecessary to use the Civil Contingencies Fund to finance the Ministry of Supplywhen their present votes are exhausted.   This involves me in the difficulty thata Bill to continue authority for the present high limit on the Civil ContingenciesFund after 31st December next when the present authority expires has been introduced into Parliament and must have a Second Reading quite quicklyafter the debate on the Address.   I feel that if this Second Reading is sought for aBill asking for continuing the high limit on the Fund, and if Parliament is notinformed that we shall be using this Fund to finance a large amount of excessexpenditure on the Ministry of Supply of which Parliament is at present unaware,we should be asking for serious trouble and indeed could properly be convicted of deliberately deceiving the House.5. It is therefore essential that either on the Second Reading of theCivil Contingencies Fund Bill, or earlier if possible, an announcement shouldbe made in the House that a large Ministry of Supply supplementary is in prospect and that the Ministry will be financed from the Civil ContingenciesFund when their present votes are exhausted.   In the case of the Army, it is notpermissible to use the Civil Contingencies Fund, and we can at most postponeSECRET f    i,    .                                                                                       COPY NO.   ^    VC. (52) 391 -&apos;5th NOVEMBER, 1952.CABINET
action only so long as they can finance themselves from their existing provision which is, I understand, until the middle of February.   before then a supplementary estimate for the Army and a Consolidated Fund bill are unavoidable.6, Although the two supplementaries are on a different footing as regards the Civil Contingencies Fund, it is clearly difficult to defenddisclosing one supplementary and not the other.7. I seek the authority of my colleagues to my arranging for a suitableannounc ement.R.A.B.&apos;Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.5th November, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
