<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/56/0 images: 291-295</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
XTCONFIDENTIALC.(52) 397 COPY NO.7TH NOVEMBER, 1952CABINETSCALE OF THE CORONATION CELEBRATIONSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations at their meeting on 1st October (C.C.(52) 83rd Conclusions, Minute 6)the Cabinet invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to consider whether arrange-ments could be made to hold a Naval Review at the time of the Coronationwithout incurring special expenditure otherwise than on a firework displayand the charter of a liner in which distinguished visitors could steam round the Fleet.    This question has received preliminary consideration by theCommittee on Coronation Preparations, which has also considered revised estimates of expenditure on Coronation preparations submitted by theMinister of Works.    The present memorandum sets out the Committee&apos;views upon these and certain other cognate matters.Service Reviews2. The First Lord of the Admiralty considers that, by some adjustments in the Fleet&apos;s normal programmes of movement and maintenance, and by accepting a smaller participation by ships from foreign stations than had originally been intended, a Naval Review could be held broadly under theconditions laid down by the Cabinet.    He has submitted to the Committee thefollowing estimates of minimum and maximum expenditure upon a review onthese lines:- Minimum     MaximumWatering facilities, overtimetravelling and subsistence 10,000 10,000Admiralty entertainment 5,000 7,500Fireworks and salutes 7,000 7a 000Government entertainment ofdistinguished visitors (includingcharter of two liners)                                                   15,000 25,00037,000 49,500or, say, 35,000 50,000
The estimated expenditure on the entertainment of distinguished visitors(including the charter of two liners) has been framed on the assumption thatthe number of distinguished visitors to be invited in 1953 would be 1,000as compared with 3,000 in 1937, when the number of liners chartered wasfive.    Some doubt was expressed in the Committee as to whether, in fact,the estimates given for this item might not prove in the long run to be exceeded - mainly on the ground that the cost of the charter of two linersfor the uneconomic period of only a few days at the peak of the Coronationseason might prove to be higher than the Admiralty&apos;s estimate.3. The Secretary of State for War informed the Committee that he wouldnot feel justified in pressing for the only form of Army Review which wouldbe practicable, namely a march-past in Hyde Park, solely on account of thefact that a Naval Review might be held after all.    He has it in mind, however,to put forward an inexpensive proposal for showing the public next year someof the Army&apos;s most up-to-date equipment, possibly in connection with theRoyal Tournament.4. The Secretary of State for Air, on the other hand, considers that, ifa Naval Review is to be held, there should also be a review by The Queenof the Royal Air Force.    What he has in mind is an inspection of aircraft and their crews on the ground, followed by a short flying display, at an airfield near London, at an estimated cost of  16,500.Decorations off the Processional Route5. The revised estimates of expenditure submitted by the Minister ofY/orks raised one issue of which the Committee felt that the Cabinet oughtto be made aware.     The estimates of the Ministry&apos;s expenditure set outin the Annex to my memorandum C. (52) 197 contained an item of  10,000for decorations off the processional route.     The cost of reproducing in1953 the same scale of decorations off the route as in 1937 is estimated at 75,000, and the Minister represented to the Committee that expenditure of only  10,000 would expose the Governments efforts to unfavourablecomparison with decorations by local authorities and commercial organisa-tions and to accusations of discrimination against the Provinces,    Ifexpenditure were confined to the provision of textiles, to be affixed to buildings by members of Departmental staffs themselves, and to a modestmeasure of floodlighting, it should be possible to make a reasonable showingat a total cost of  50,000.    The Minister, therefore, sought authority for theexpenditure of an additional  40,000  for this purpose.6. The Committee felt that, additional expenditure on decorations offthe processional route would not be justified;  that the  10,000 already agreed to should be used to the best advantage in places which The Queenwould be visiting during the course of the Coronation celebrations;  and thatit should be indicated to local authorities that the Government regarded thedecoration of cities and towns generally as being a matter of localresponsibility.Expenditure by Local Education Authorities7. It is also necessary to decide whether education grant at the normalrate of 60 per cent should be paid by the Exchequer in respect of reasonableexpenditure by local education authorities on Coronation celebrations.&quot;Whilst the Government are not formally committed on this issue, there is little doubt that local education authorities are expecting such grant to be
paid as was done both on the occasion of the R.oyal Jubilee in 1935 and at the coronation of 1937.    If it should be decided that grant should be payable, thereis the further question whether any limit should be put on the amount ofexpenditure admissible for grant and, if so, what that limit should be.    TheCommittee felt that a limit ought to be imposed and that the minimum reason-able figure would be 2s. per head of the pupils.    This was the least thatwould provide something worth having.    It would, of course, be open to localeducation authorities to supplement any limited grant by expenditure from therates to whatever extent they might wish.8. The maximum possible grant charge which might be incurred by theExchequer if a limit of 2s. per head were imposed would be   360,000, butthe Minister of Education advised the Committee that, when allowance wasmade for the fact that many authorities would not spend up to any limitimposed, the actual grant charge to be incurred seemed likely to be of theorder of  100,000 to  250,000.9. Whilst the Committee recognised that it would be difficult to withholdgrant altogether, the view was expressed that, now that the people generallywere able to share more fully in celebrations brations in London through improvedtravel facilities, television, wireless and colour filming, it was for considera-tion whether it was really justifiable to spend so substantial a sum on celebra-tions extraneous to the ceremony itself.    In view of the very large suminvolved, the Committee felt that the issue was one which should be decided by the Cabinet and that in deciding it the Cabinet would wish to take intoaccount the effect of their decision upon the estimated total gross cost of the coronation.Total Gross Expenditure10. Annexed to this memorandum is a table showing, on the one hand, theestimates of expenditure approved by the Cabinet on the 19th June and, on theother hand, the current revised estimates as compiled on the basis of thelatest Departmental returns to the Treasury.     The figures are still underdiscussion between the Treasury and Departments and the revised estimates are not, therefore, final.    But they show a very considerable increase overthe estimates originally approved by the Cabinet, an increase which reflects the additional cost resulting both from new items already approved and fromunavoidable increases in the original estimates, e. g. on the adaptation  of westminster Abbey.    The revised estimates do not include any of the itemsdiscussed in paragraphs 2 to 9 above.    It will be seen, therefore, that if theCabinet approve the holding of Naval and Royal Air Force reviews, theestimated total gross expenditure will rise to over  2^ millions compared withthe sum of  Lff millions estimated in C. (52) 197;  and, if in addition, the paymentof an education grant is authorised, the total estimated gross cost will rise towell over  2^- millions.Summary11. The Cabinet are invited:-(1)     To decide:-(a) whether a Naval Review should be held at atotal estimated cost of from  35,000 to 50,000;(b) whether, if so, a review of the Royal Air force should also be held at a total estimatedcost of  16,500.
(2)  To agree that the present authorised expenditure by the Ministry of Works of  10,000 ondecorations off the processional routeshould not be increased.(3)   To decide whether, in i*espect of reasonableexpenditure by local education authorities on Coronation celebrations, education grant at the normal rate of 60 per cent should be withheld or paid, subject to expenditureadmissible for grant not exceeding 2s, per head of the pupils, at an estimated cost ofof from  100,000 to  250,000.S.Commonwealth Relations Office, S. W. 1.7TH NOVEMBER, 1952,\
ANNEXEstimates of Coronation ExpenditureSubmitted Approvedto Cabinet by Cabinet RevisedinC(52)197on19 th June,1952Submittedto CabinetinC(52)197Approvedby Cabineton19th June,1952Revised 000Ministry of Works Stands along the route      ... 332Westminster Abbey...... 220Annexe         ...      ...      ... 50Decorations, floodlighting andfireworks    ...      ...      ... 144Lavatories other than on stands 45Communications      ...... 9Protective work for buildings and parks   ......... 16Earl MarshaFs Office         ... 2Ceremony at Caernarvon   ... 10Ex-Servicemen&apos;s Review     ... 4Fire protection and custody ...  Visit to Scotland     ......  Improved standing room    ...  Contingencies          ...... 25Royal household 0003322205015045-916210425 00056027451150508 000 000 000205-5104-54-531220857130863 1,172-5130 130Various Departments Earl Marshall OfficeStationery OfficePost Office     ......Foreign office colonial office commonwealth RelationsOfficeGovernment HospitalityWar Office General UniformsAir Ministry General UniformsAdmiralty General....... UniformsPolice  ...      ......101010813101010813Total grossLess receiptsTotal net...20111010141467512759520771,5053601,145512752059520771,7163601462S0243715060352,295-5611-5*1,356      1,684* The increase in estimated receipts is mainly due to an increase in the number of seats to be madeavailable for sale and increased prices to be charged for them. When account is taken of a profit of  60,000 expected to be obtained from the sale of seats through agencies, seats in Government standsare expected to be broadly self-balancing, on the basis of charges of  4 (uncovered) and  6 (covered).The earlier estimate was that a profit could be made on the seats on the basis of charges of  3 10s. Od.and  5 10s. 0d.; but the erection of stands is going to cost more than was then estimated.43189

</content>
</cab>
