<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 24-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT is THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CM. (46)66th Conclusions.CABINET 66 (46).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 8th July, 1946, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, MThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education..P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P., The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Items 6-7).      Minister of Food.The Right Hon. Lord Winster, The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,Minister of Civil Aviation (Items M.P., Minister of State (Items 1-7).6-7).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-5).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.
CABINET 66 (46).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Council of Foreign Ministers ....      ....      ....      ....     179Second Paris Meeting.2      Greece   ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    1793      Austria................................     179Definition of German Assets for Reparations Purposes.4      Cyprus  ................................     1805      Palestine ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     1816      Civil Aviation............................     181Civil Aviation Bill.7      Petrol Rationing       ........................    1828      Government Publicity Service        ....      ....      ....      ....     183Future of the Social Survey.
Council of foreign ministers.Second ParisMeeting.(previous reference erence:CM. (46) 61stConclusions,Minute 2.)Greece.(previous reference:CM. (46) 54thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. The Prime Minister read to the Cabinet a telegram(No. 331 of the 7th July) which he had just received from theForeign Secretary describing the developments which had occurred during the last few days in the discussions at the Paris meetingof the Council of Foreign Ministers.2. The Minister, of State said that the Communist Party andother Left-wing Parties in Greece had announced their intention toco-operate in the forthcoming plebiscite. This meant that arrange-ments would probably be made between the Parties to ensure fairplay in the voting and in the counting of the votes; but it also meant that there was likely to be greater difficulty in maintaining public order during the period of the plebiscite. Though the new Govern-ment had suppressed some monarchist bands in southern Greece,lawlessness was increasing in the north, where there were some indications of the growth of an autonomist movement, which mightbe supported from beyond the frontier. It was important, there-fore, that Ministers who met the Prime Minister of Greece during his current visit to London should make it clear how important itwas that his Government should show firmness in maintainingpublic order in Greece at the present time and should discourage allrecourse to violence whether by Parties of the Left or of the Right.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had undertaken to see the Greek Prime Minister. He assumed that the cabinet would support him in discouraging any application for further financial assistance from His Majesty&apos;s Government. The Ministerof State said that the Greek Government would certainly need further help in financing a programme of economic reconstruction.The Foreign Office hoped to be able to communicate to theChancellor of the Exchequer, before he met the Greek PrimeMinister, details of the latter&apos;s proposals for this purpose. It was thought that these would envisage loans from the international bank for Reconstruction and Development.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he could promisesympathetic support for applications to the International Bank, solong as it was understood that His Majesty&apos;s Government were not expected to grant further loans to Greece. There was generalagreement with the view expressed by the Chancellor of theExchequer.In further discussion the suggestion was made that, if we wereto avoid continuing to contribute towards the maintenance of greece&apos;s armed forces after the end of 1946, it was desirable thatsome plan should be made for progressively reducing the strength ofthose forces between now and the end of the year.The Cabinet-Took note of the statement made by the Minister of Stateand of the points raised in discussion.Austria.definition of german assets forreparationspurposes.3. The Minister of State informed the Cabinet that difficulty had arisen over the definition of German assets in Austria. TheRussians had been interpreting the term &apos;&apos; German &apos;&apos; very broadly,and had been seizing property which was German only in the sense that Germany controlled Austria after the Anschluss. As it hadnot been possible to reach agreement on the Allied Council inVienna, the question was to be raised when Austrian affairs were discussed on the Council of Foreign Ministers. Meanwhile, how-ever, the Russian authorities in Austria were claiming the right
to settle the point in bilateral discussions with the Austrian Govern-ment. The Foreign Office had advised our political representa-tive in Vienna to urge the Austrian Government to hold off from such discussions for the moment. It had now been learned that theUnited States representative in Austria had put forward a proposalto the effect that any asset which existed in Austria before March1938 should not be subject to reparations, nor should any assetcreated since that date which had not been financed by the Germans.The most useful action we could now take was to support this American initiative, to encourage the Austrian Governmentto resist the demands of the Soviet authorities and to try to arrangefor the issue to be discussed in Paris as soon as possible.The Cabinet-Approved the course of action proposed by the Ministerof State.Cyprus.(previous reference:C.M.(45)38thConclusions,Minute 6.)4. The Secretary of State for the Colonies had circulated tothe Cabinet a memorandum (CP. (46) 260) outlining a statement on future policy in respect of Cyprus which he was anxious tomake in the debate on Colonial Affairs which was to be held in theHouse of Commons on the following day. The Secretary of Statewished to take this opportunity of making it clear that HisMajesty&apos;s Government had no intention of transferring Cyprusfrom British sovereignty, but intended to institute a more liberalregime in the island and proposed to establish a consultative assembly to consider the framing of a new constitution designedto give Cypriots an effective say in local affairs. He also wishedto announce a large-scale scheme for the development of the island and the improvement of its social services.The Cabinet were informed that the Foreign Secretary had asked that consideration of this paper should be deferred until after his return from Paris. He thought that, if any such state-ment were made while the Greek Prime Minister was visitingLondon, the stability of the new Government of Greece would been dangered. He also considered that his own position would bemade somewhat difficult if such a statement were made while theCouncil of Foreign Ministers was meeting in Paris.The Secretary of State for the Colonies, while he recognisedthat in these circumstances consideration of his proposals must await the Foreign Secretary&apos;s return, said that he would find itdifficult to avoid making any statement about Cyprus in the debate on the following day. The matter would be raised in the debateby supporters of the Government and he could not pass over it insilence.In discussion it was suggested that the Secretary of State should see the Government supporters who were likely to wish to raise thissubject in the debate and should urge them not to press him at thisstage to make any declaration of policy. It should then be possiblefor him to deal lightly with this matter in his reply to the debate.The Cabinet-(1) Took note that the Secretary of State for the colonies would take steps to discourage Government supportersfrom pressing for any declaration of policy in respectof Cyrus in the forthcoming debate in the House ofCommons on Colonial Affairs; and would devise, in con-sultation with the Foreign Office, a temporising state-ment which could be used in that debate.(2) Agreed to postpone, until after the Foreign Secretary&apos; return from Paris, consideration of the issues raised in CP. (46) 260.
Palestine.(previous reference:CM. (46) 64thConclusions,Minute 2.)5. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that it had beensuggested by the United States Secretary of State that, with aview to easing the forthcoming discussions in Congress on theUnited Kingdom Loan, it would be well if some reassuring statement could be issued on Palestine.The Cabinet felt that it would be a mistake to issue any state-ment which might appear to have been made for this purpose. they also thought it unlikely that any general statement which couldbe made at this stage on the issues dealt with in the Report of theAnglo-American Committee would have the desired effect on opinion in the United States. These objections would not, however, applyto the release of news about the progress of the current operations in Palestine. And it would be convenient if the High Commissionerfor Palestine were now able to announce that these operations werevirtually concluded, that the Jewish Agency&apos;s buildings were beinghanded back and that a substantial number of those detained hadbeen released.It was unlikely that this announcement could include further evidence of the connection between the Jewish Agency andthe Hagana. Though the documents obtained during the searcheswere being examined as quickly as possible, the examination mightnot be completed for some little time. Some objections had been raised to disclosing the earlier evidence in this connection, since this might compromise the sources from which it had been obtained.The Prime Minister said that he was proposing to go into thispoint with the Colonial Office and the security authorities.In further discussion it was suggested that it would be advisablein future statements on Palestine to use the word &quot; Zionist &quot;rather than &apos;&apos; Jew &quot; or &quot; Jewish &apos;&apos; wherever possible, as there were many Jews both in the United Kingdom and the United states who were not in sympathy with Zionist policy.14The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to ascertain from the High Commissioner whether it would bepossible to issue in the immediate future a statement about the progress of the operations in Palestine, onthe lines indicated in the Cabinet&apos;s discussion.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would consider further,with the Secretary of State for the Colonies and others concerned, the evidence which could be given of the con-nection between the Jewish Agency and the Hagana.(3) Re-affirmed their decision that for the time being nofacilities should be given for Members of parliament or representatives of Jews in other countries to visitPalestine.CivilAviation.CivilAviationBill.(previous reference:CM. (46) 25thConclusions,Minute 10.)6. The Cabinet were informed that, during the committee stage of the Civil Aviation Bill, an amendment was to be moved to omit paragraph 4 of the First Schedule, which provided that amember of the House of Commons should not be appointed a memberof any of the Corporations to be established under the Bill.There was general agreement that it would be inexpedient that members of the House of Commons should hold appointments as members of these Corporations. There were numerous precedents for a provision specifically disqualifying members of the House ofCommons from holding such appointments.
The Cabinets-Invited the Lord Privy Seal to resist the amendment pro-posing to delete paragraph 4 from the First Schedule ofthe Civil Aviation Bill.petrol rationing.(previous reference:CM. (46)38thConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister of fuel and Power (CP. (46) 257) proposing that petrol rationingshould be abolished as soon as the United States loan was approved.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that, despite the relaxation-tions granted since the end of the European war, the consumptionof motor spirit was still very severely curtailed. For some time now he had had to face persistent demands for the abolition of rationingon behalf of both industrial and commercial users and privatemotorists. There was very strong pressure in Parliament and in thePress, and it was becoming increasingly difficult for him to justifythe present restrictions. As a result of the reduction of militaryconsumption, the estimated stock in the United Kingdom during august would amount to 1,100,000 tons, which would suffice to meet all demands if rationing were abolished; and, though figures, showingthe stock position had not hitherto been disclosed, the fact that wehad sufficient petrol to abolish rationing was widely known.He estimated that, if petrol rationing were abolished from the1st August, the additional expenditure for the period up to mid-1947 would be 50 million dollars. It was true that all the petrolrequired for United Kingdom consumption could be supplied fromsterling sources, but, in the interests of our overseas trade and inorder to economise tanker transport, it had always been regarded asthe right policy to sell much of the available sterling oil overseas and to import dollar oil into the United Kingdom.It might be suggested that, as an alternative to abolishing petrol rationing, there should be a substantial relaxation of the existing restrictions. This, however, would create formidable administrative difficulties and would compel him to increase the staff engaged onpetrol rationing, which already numbered about 1,000. he recognised that the Chancellor of the Exchequer must look at theimport programme as a whole, but he was convinced that theadditional expenditure involved in the abolition of petrol rationingwould be amply justified both by the aid which it would give to thedevelopment of industry and commerce and by the wider facilities which it would provide for holidays and recreation.The Minister of Transport said that, though the abolition of rationing would not increase to any great extent the facilities forthe delivery of goods or the conveyance of passengers by road, he supported the proposal made in CP. (46) 257. The necessary tanker tonnage could be provided, and he estimated that, if rationing were abolished, he would be able to effect a saving of about 600 in the staffof the Ministry of Transport.The President of the Board of Trade said that the abolition of petrol rationing would make it more difficult to maintain the strict control which was still required over other dollar imports. Itwould also stimulate the demand for cars for the home market to an extent which would jeopardise the voluntary agreement by whichcar manufacturers now allocated 50 per cent, of their production to exports. Thirdly, the allocation of new tyres, of which there was likely to be a serious shortage for at least another year, was based onthe system of petrol rationing; and, if that system were abolished,the Board of Trade would have to devise alternative means of ensuring that the available supplies of new tyres were reserved forthe more essential uses, e.g., by doctors and nurses.
GovernmentPublicityService.Future ofthe social survey.(Previous ,Eef erence:CM. (46) 29thConclusions,Minute 10.)8. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the lord president (CP. (46) 254) reporting the results of the further enquiries which they had invited him to make into the proposal tocontinue the Social Survey as a Government agency.The Lord President said that since the Cabinefs last discus-sion there had been further interdepartmental examination of thisproposal under the auspices of the Treasury, and the results ofthis had been considered by the Ministerial Committee on HomeInformation Services. That Committee were satisfied that it wouldbe preferable to maintain a central Government organisation forthis work rather than employ outside agencies. It should be the aim to entrust all new Government work of this kind to the social survey, save in quite exceptional circumstances, and ultimately,with a few exceptions, to transfer all such Government work to it.For the time being, however, those Departments, e.g., the ministry the Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the approval of theLoan would not mean that we should be able to increase our dollar imports to an unlimited extent. The advantages of abolishing petrol rationing must therefore be weighed against the claims for largerimports of food, machinery, timber and other dollar imports. Ifpetrol rationing were continued, expenditure on the oil programme would amount to 250 million dollars out of a total United Statesdollar expenditure of 1,300 million dollars provisionally planned forthe period mid-1946 to mid-1947, on the assumption that the UnitedStates loan would be approved. On the other hand, if rationingwere abolished, there could be no guarantee that the additional expenditure could be restricted to 50 million dollars.In further discussion the following points were made : &apos;(a) Several Ministers stressed the fact that the abolition of rationing would provide a much-needed increase in the availablefacilities for recreation.(b) Against this, it was urged that greater effect in improvingmorale would be secured by the expenditure of dollars on increased imports of supplementary foods in order to add variety to the diet.(c) Even if the United States loan were approved, the economic position of the United Kingdom must remain precarious for thenext two or three years and it would be disastrous if the Govern-ment, after granting relaxations, such as the abolition of petrol rationing, were to find in two years&apos; time that the long-term stability of our balance of payments could not be restored.(d) If it was in fact administratively impossible to preventwidespread evasion of the existing rationing scheme, it would bemore difficult to justify the continuance of petrol rationing. Itwould be useful, therefore, if the Minister of Fuel and Power could produce some factual evidence by which the Cabinet could measure the extent of the evasion.In further discussion there was general agreement that thequestion of abolishing petrol rationing should be considered as partof a general review of import programmes to be undertakenimmediately a decision had been reached on the United States loan.The Cabinet-Agreed that the proposal for the abolition of petrol rationing should be considered as part of a general reviewof Departmental import programmes which should beundertaken under the direction of the Ministerial Com-mittee on Economic Planning immediately a decision hadbeen reached on the United States loan.
of Food and the Board of Trade, which had long-standing arrange-ments for continuous surveys to be carried out by commercial firms should be free to continue those arrangements.The Lord President recommended that the Treasury should keep a careful watch on the expenditure incurred on this work,and that the position should be specially reviewed in two years&apos;time.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a Government agency for Social Survey work should be maintained on the basis recommended in cp. (46) 254.(2) Agreed that the detailed arrangements for this purpose should be determined by the Treasury and should besubject to a special review by Ministers, in two years&apos;time, in the light of experience gained during the interval.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,8th July, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
