<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 104-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1946.SECRET.Copy No.CM. (46)71th Conclusions.CABINET 74 (46).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 29th July, 1946, at 11 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,(in theThe Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. EM.P., Lord President of the CouncilChair).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.(Items 5 and 6).The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 5).The Right Hon. James Griffiths,M.P., Minister of National Insur-ance (Item 4).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 6).Mr, John Dugdale,&apos;M.P., Parliamen-tary and Financial Secretary,Admiralty (Item 5).Field Marshal Viscount montgomery of Alamein, Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (Item 6).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Minister of State (Items 1 to3 and 6).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 3 and 6).Marshal of the Royal Air Force lord tedder, Chief of the Air Staff(Item 6).Vice-Admiral Sir Rhoderick McGri-gor, Vice-Chief of Naval Staff(Item. 6).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.General Sir Hastings Is may.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32426-5]
CABINET 74 (46).Contents:Subject.Foreign SecretaryWorld Food Supplies   ....Second Review of the World Food Shortage.World Federation of Democratic YouthBreak-up of the Poor LawDisposal of German Merchant Ships....Palestine ....Arrangements for Debate in the House of Commons.Discussions with the United States Government.Security Situation.
1. The Cabinet invited the Lord President to convey to theForeign Secretary their sincere sympathy and best wishes for hisspeedy recovery.2. The Minister of Food recalled that in April the cabinet had authorised the publication of a White Paper (Cmd. 6785)setting out the facts of the crisis in the world&apos;s food supplies. Hehad been pressed to publish further information supplementing and bringing up-to-date what had been published in April, and he pro-posed to present on the 1st August a white Paper giving a secondreview of the world food shortage.The Cabinet Endorsed the proposal of the Minister of Food to publish a White Paper bringing up to date the information givenin the White Paper published in April (Cmd. 6785) and giving preliminary indications of the prospects after thenext harvest.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of State (CP. (46) 290) about the application made by theWorld Federation of Democratic Youth for inclusion in the panel of non-Governmental organisations which were to be accorded theofficial status of consultants to the Economic and Social Council ofthe United Nations Organisation.The Minister of State recalled that at their meeting on the9th August, 1945, the Cabinet had agreed that facilities should begiven to persons coming from abroad to attend the World YouthConference held in London in November 1945. This Conference had established the W or Id Federation of Democratic Youth, which, had now applied for recognition by the Economic and Social Council.As the Annex to CP. (46) 290 showed, the Federation was LargelyCommunist-controlled and the existing bodies representative ofBritish youth, who were now engaged in establishing their owncentral organisation, would certainly refuse to affiliate with it. Hisprovisional conclusion was that the United Kingdom representative on the Economic and Social Council should, be instructed to oppose the application of the Federation for recognition, on the groundthat it was not representative of world youth and that its title and.claims were unfounded. In opposing the application the UnitedKingdom representative should take the line that the recognitionof any existing body as capable of speaking for the youth of theworld was in any case premature and that the first step should bethe formation of representative national bodies in the various states which could then combine to form a genuinely representative inter-national organisation.In discussion it was urged that, whether or not the federation was under Communist control, it was inappropriate that an organisation which had no functional basis and merely claimed to speak for the youth of the world should be accorded the official status of consultant to the Economic and Social Council.On the narrower question whether the World Federation of democratic Youth was under Communist control, several Ministersargued that the statements made in the Annex to CP. (46) 290greatly exaggerated the extent of Communist influence andmisrepresented the attitude of British youth organisations to theFederation. If we opposed the Federation, would this not merelyencourage the growth of Communist influence in it \The Minister of State said that his own past experience bore- out the statements made in the Annex about the tactics employedby the Communists to gain control of the World Federation of6-5] b 2
Democratic Youth. While he agreed that it would be inappropriateto accord recognition to the Federation as consultants over the wholefield of youth, it was clearly contemplated in Article 71 of theUnited Nations Charter that such consultant bodies should beappointed and it might well be argued that the Economic and social council should consult an organisation of this kind on particularaspects of their work affecting youth.The Lord President said that the evidence given in the Annex &apos;to CP. (46) 290 seemed to him to be fairly conclusive.   Perhaps,however, the Minister of State would discuss this aspect of thematter further with the President of the Board of Trade and theHome Secretary.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the United Kingdom representative on theEconomic and Social Council should oppose the inclusionof the World Federation of Democratic Youth in the panel of non-Governmental organisations to be accordedthe official status of consultants to the Council, on theground that it would be inappropriate to include any organisation in the panel for the purpose of representingthe views of the youth of the world.(2) Invited the Minister of State, after consultation with thePresident of the Board of Trade and the Home Secretary,to circulate a further memorandum dealing with thesuggestion that the World Federation of DemocraticYouth was under Communist control.4. The Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum by theMinister of Health, the Secretary of State for Scotland and theMinister of National Insurance (CP. (46) 284) covering the reportof the Official Inter-Departmental Committee appointed to prepare proposals for legislation to break up the poor law.The Minister of Health said that the recommendations in theCommittee&apos;s report, which were being examined in detail by theSocial Services Committee, did not necessarily represent the finalviews of the Ministers concerned. It was, however, necessary that officials should open discussions with representatives of localauthorities on those recommendations that affected the functions oflocal authorities and, for this reason, it had been felt that theCabinet should be asked to approve the general pattern of theproposals. The main recommendations affecting local authorities were set out in paragraph 4 of CP. (46) 284. A start had in fact been made with the discussions with local authorities, though ithad been made clear to them that the proposals put before them were only tentative.The following points arose in discussion : (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, while he hopedthat there would be a progressive diminution in the expenditure on assistance, the proposals would, on the present basis, represent a transfer of about  15 million a year from the rates to theExchequer. This would have to be taken into account in connectionwith the revision of the block grant, and he must ask that in discussions with local authorities it should be made clear to themthat the transfer would not mean an overall net relief to the rates.(b) The Lord President said that, looking to the interests ofboth central and local government, he was doubtful about the!proposal that local authorities should provide institutional!accommodation as agents of the central government. An arrange-iment of this kind was Unsatisfactory, since it compelled the central!government to interfere unduly with local discretion.   At the sanieBBreak-upof the poor Law.
time, the central government would find it very difficult to curjbunreasonable extravagance on the part of the local authorities ina matter such as the provision of institutional accommodation, andextravagance in this field might well lead to an agitation in favourof a further increase in the rates of retirement pensions. He would much prefer, therefore, that the local authorities should bear the costof providing institutional accommodation, on the understandingthat the fact that they were left with this burden would be takeninto account in connection with the revision of the block grant.The Minister of Health said that in principle he agreed withthe views expressed by the Lord President. In the present instance,however, it seemed to him that unless a change was made in thefinancial basis of the arrangements it would be impossible to getaway from the old poor law atmosphere. In any event the magnitude of the problem was very much reduced by the fact that allaccommodation for the sick poor would be transferred to the Stateunder the National Health Service proposals.(c) The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out that if a single person who was dependent entirely on a retirement pension of 26s.was received into an institution, he would pay 21s. towards the costof his maintenance and retain 5s. pocket money. If, however, anold couple dependent on their retirement pension of 42s. were toenter the institution, they would have to pay the whole of their pension towards their maintenance. Was there not a danger thatthis would lead to a demand for an increase in the rate of retirement pension payable to old couples \ He attached great importance to maintaining the existing rates of retirement pension.The Minister of National Insurance explained that the pointreferred to by the Chancellor of the Exchequer had not yet been finally settled by the Social Services Committee. In any event, itwas unlikely that many old couples in receipt of retirement pensions would wish to enter institutions.(d) The Minister of Health said that it was contemplated that local authorities would make suitable arrangements with the disabled Persons Employment Corporation in connection with theprovision of welfare services for handicapped persons.(e) The Minister of Health explained that the reference tomental disability in paragraph 4 (e) of CP. (46) 284 covered onlymental defectives and that the new National Health Service wouldbe responsible for persons receiving treatment for mental diseases.(/) The Minister of Health said that the intention was to do everything possible to encourage the replacement of large institu-tions by homes and hostels. Local authorities had been asked tomake special provision for the accommodation of the aged in their housing schemes.(g) It was pointed out that no recommendation had been made about the arrangements for dealing with the needs of childrendeprived of parental care, pending the receipt of the reports of theCurtis and Clyde Committees. The question which central Depart-ment should be responsible in this field would have to be discussed by the Machinery of Government Committee.(h) The Lord President drew attention to the statements madeby the Minister of Health in Cardiff on the 16th July and in durham on the 20th July, to the effect that the proposed legislation would be introduced in the 1946-47 Session. The Cabinet had sometime ago (CM. (46) 42nd Conclusions, Minute 7) endorsed the viewthat Ministers should avoid making any promises about the intro-duction of legislation in advance of The King&apos;s Speech; and,however desirable it might be that the proposed legislation should come into force in April 1948 concurrently with the National health service and National Insurance legislation, the fact remained thatif Ministers made public statements promising that particular Bills
would be introduced in the coming Session, they were both antici-pating The King&apos;s Speech and, in effect, gaining an unfairadvantage over other Ministers who also had claims on the availableParliamentary time.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Minister of Health, the Secretary of State forScotland and the Minister of National Insurance to circulate a further memorandum dealing with the aspectsof their proposals which affected central and localgovernment finance, with particular reference to thepoint noted in paragraph (b) above.(2) Subject to (1), approved as a basis for discussion with localauthorities the general pattern of the proposals forbreaking up the poor law outlined in paragraph 4 of cp. (46) 284.(3) Agreed that there could be no guarantee that the proposed legislation would be passed in the 1946-47 Session, andreaffirmed the view that Ministers should not make anypromises with regard to the introduction of particularBills in the 1946-47 Session without obtaining priorauthority from the Cabinet.Disposal of 5.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theGerman Minister of Transport (CP. (46) 279) making proposals for theMerchant disposal of the United Kingdom share of the German merchant fleet.Ships. Appended to this memorandum was a statement showing the alloca-(Previous        tion agreed to at the Assembly of the Inter-Allied ReparationsReference:       Agency, under which the final United Kingdom share of the GermanC.M.(46)2nd    merchant fleet consisted of 349,627 gross registered tons.   It was conclusions,     proposed that, subject to certain reservations set out in paragraph 5Minute 4.)&apos;     of CP. (46) 279, the ships should be offered for sale to UnitedKingdom owners, with the option of bareboat charter for a period not exceeding five years.   This was in line with the scheme already approved by the Cabinet for the disposal of United KingdomGovernment-owned tonnage.In discussion some Ministers expressed apprehension lest thedisposal of this German tonnage would damage the UnitedKingdom shipbuilding industry. The experience after the 1914-18war seemed to show that there was a danger of this; and, as evidence of the likely effect of the proposals, it was stated that a firm of shipbuilders on the North-East coast, who had wished toextend their dry-dock accommodation, had been informed by theAdmiralty that the extension could not be approved until theproposal had been looked at in the light of the situation whichwould result when this additional German tonnage was madeavailable. Would it not be possible to make the German shipsavailable on charter only and thus retain control of them ?The Minister of Transport said that the present situation wasmaterially different from that after the 1914-18 war, and he was satisfied that his proposals would not damage the United Kingdomshipbuilding industry. Only about 200,000 tons of shipping wouldbe available for offer immediately under the disposals scheme, ascompared! with over 1\ million tons after the 1914-18 war. More-over, though he did not wish to rule out disposal by sale, it seemed likely that much of the tonnage would be chartered.The Parliamentary Secretary, Admiralty, confirmed that theAdmiralty were satisfied that the proposals in CP. (46) 279 wouldnot affect the shipbuilding industry adversely.Other points in discussion were :  (a) The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs pointed outthat, apart from making available a 1,000-ton ship to Newfound-land, it was proposed to confine the offer of German ships to United
Kingdom owners. He understood that Newfoundland had askedfor at least one other ship of about 1,000 tons, and he suggestedthat arrangements should be made to meet this request.(b) The Secretary of State for the Colonies suggested that,before a final decision was made, the needs of the West Indies andcertain of the African Colonies should be considered.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, that the allocation of german merchant ships by the Inter-Allied Reparations Agencyhad resulted in a satisfactory share for the UnitedKingdom.(2) Approved the proposals in CP. (46) 275 for the disposalof the ships obtained, on the understanding that theMinister of Transport would discuss with the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs and the Secretary ofState for the Colonies the possibility of making avail-able some tonnage to meet the needs of Newfoundland,the West Indies and the African Colonies.6. The Cabinet were informed that the Prime Minister wouldnot be able to return from Paris in order to take part in the debate on Palestine in the House of Commons on the 31st July and the1st August. In these circumstances, the Prime Minister had suggested that the Lord President should open the debate on his behalf. The Foreign Secretary would also be unable to take partin the debate and the Prime Minister had agreed that the Presidentof the Board of Trade should open the debate on the second day.The Secretary of State for the Colonies would wind up the debate.The Lord President said that he had discussed with the PrimeMinister whether, as there had already been a partial disclosure of the proposals agreed on by the British and United States Dele-gations, a statement of those proposals should be made to Parlia-ment before Wednesday. His own view was that it would be unwise to anticipate the debate.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the revised arrangements proposed for the debate on Palestine and agreed thatno statement of the proposals agreed on by the Britishand United States Delegations should be made beforethe debate.The Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Cabinetthat he had gone to Paris on the previous afternoon with the PrimeMinister, in the evening the United States Secretary of State had discussed with the Prime Minister the recommendations of theBritish and United States Delegations. Mr. Byrnes had said thatthe main point in which the President was interested was that thereshould be no delay in beginning the admission of 100,000 immi-grants to Palestine, and had suggested that any announcement aboutthe recommendations should state that their transfer from europe would start not later than the 1st September. Mr. Byrnes had alsoquestioned the necessity for further joint consultation with jews and Arabs, taking the view that sufficient consultation had already taken place in that they had been asked for their views on theproposals of the Anglo-American Committee.On the latter point, the Prime Minister had remindedMr. Byrnes of his own assurance in the autumn of last year thatArab representatives would be consulted before any plan to alter the existing basis of government in Palestine was introduced; andhad pointed out that it could hardly.be argued that they had been consulted about the new plan now proposed.
As regards the transfer of immigrants, the Prime minister had made it plain that it would not be possible for His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to agree to a firm date in advance of the acceptanceof the plan for provincial autonomy. As soon as that plan hadbeen accepted, however, it would be possible to make a start withimmigration.Mr. Byrnes was seeing the leader of the United States Dele-gation that morning and would then speak to President Trumanby telephone. He would thereafter get into touch with the PrimeMinister again.The Cabinet-(2) Agreed to meet on the following morning in order toconsider the results of the Prime Minister&apos;s further meeting with Mr. Byrnes.The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for the Colonies (CP. (46) 301) regarding the invitations tobe issued to representatives of the Palestine Arabs and of the jews to attend the proposed conference on future policy in Palestine.The Secretary of State fpr the Colonies explained that invita-tions had already been given to the States Members of the arab league to send delegations. As regards the Palestine Arabs, the invitation should be addressed to the Palestine Arab HigherExecutive. The nominal chairman of this body was the Muftiand he proposed to make it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwould not be prepared to accept the nomination of the Mufti as a delegate. The High Commissioner would be consulted on thequestion whether a delegation nominated by the Arab HigherExecutive would be sufficiently representative or whether additionalinvitations should be issued. With regard to the Jews, it was proposed that an invitation should be extended to the jewish agency to nominate representatives. The recent operations hadbeen directed, not against the Agency as such, but only against those responsible for instigating and directing the campaign of violence and it was suggested, therefore, that when the invitationwas conveyed to Dr. Weizmann it should be made clear that HisMajesty&apos;s Government would not be prepared to accept as delegatesmembers of the Executive now in detention or Mr. Ben Gurion,who would have been detained had he been in Palestine. he proposed, in order to complete the Jewish delegation, to nominaterepresentatives of other interests in consultation with the foreign secretary and after taking advice from Dr. Weizmann, the Chair-man of the Board of Deputies of British Jews and such others ashe considered appropriate.In discussion the point was made that, if His Majesty&apos;sGovernment wished to obtain a settlement of this difficult problem,the Arabs and Jews must be allowed to send whatever repre-sentatives they wished. Experience in other parts of the worldhad shown that this was essential.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that an invitation to the conference should beaddressed to the Palestine Arab Higher Executive, theJewish Agency and such other Arab and Jewish repre-sentatives as the Secretary of State for the Coloniesmight consider appropriate, after consultation with theHigh Commissioner for Palestine and with Dr. Weiz-mann, the Chairman of the Board of Deputies ofBritish Jews and others.(4) Agreed that, while an attempt should be made to discouragethe Arab Higher Executive and the Jewish Agency fromnominating, in the one case, the Mufti, and, in the othercase, Mr. Ben Gurion or members of the Executive whowere now in detention, it would in the last resort benecessary to accept such nominations if they were made.ProposedConferencewith arabs and Jews.
The Secretary of State for the Colonies informed the Cabinetthat a telegram (No. 1226) had been received from the High Com-missioner for Palestine emphasising that the Arabs in Palestinewere now in a particularly ugly mood and that there was a real danger of disturbances. In particular, an announcement in theforthcoming statement of policy implying that 100,000 jews would be admitted to Palestine would precipitate trouble unless it was made clear that they would be admitted only afterthe discussions with Arabs and Jews had been satisfactorilyconcluded and the new constitutional settlement had been implemented. Even so, it might be difficult to hold the Arabsin check unless it could be made clear that effective steps werebeing taken to counter Jewish terrorism. The intensive search forterrorists which was to take place would not of itself be enough toreduce tension among the Arabs. The High Commissioner wassending the Chief Secretary for Palestine home to explain his views.In discussion the following points were raised :  (a) Search for Terrorists. The High Commissioner had reported in telegram No. 1226 that this search would now begin onthe following day.It was pointed out that this was earlier than had been expectedwhen the Cabinet agreed that the search should take place, and thatneAvs of the search would be available before the debate in the Houseof Commons. It was also suggested there might have beenadvantage in postponing the search until the Governments positivepolicy had been announced. The general view of the Cabinet,however, was that there was no reason to delay the start of the search.The question was raised whether the reference to action againstthe Zionists in paragraph 2 of telegram No. 1226 meant some wideroperation than the proposed search for terrorists. The Chief of theImperial General Staff said that he was satisfied that the phraseused did not refer to anything more than action against terrorists.(b) Search for Arms. The military authorities had asked theHigh Commissioner for permission to search ten Jewish settlementsfor arms which could be said to be primarily for the Irgun. As,however, they could not undertake this simultaneously with theproposed search for terrorists, the High Commissioner had informedthem that he would consider the matter further in ten days&apos; time.(c) Illegal Immigration. It was pointed out that, while theHigh Commissioner appreciated the difficulty of stopping the immi-gration quota, he had pressed strongly for the diversion of anyfurther illegal immigrants and in his telegram No. 1212 had urgedthat any further ships bearing illegal immigrants should be forced toreturn to the port of departure, except ships from Balkan countries under Russian control, which should be diverted to Tripoli orCyprus. There was evidence that a large proportion of illegal immigrants were recruited into the Jewish undergroundorganisations.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he understoodthat a ship containing nearly 2,700 immigrants had been inter -cepted on the previous day and was being conducted into Haifa.Another ship with 500 more Jews on board was expected shortly.Apart from political considerations, there were serious practicaldifficulties in accommodating more illegal immigrants in Palestine.They could not be admitted in excess of the authorised quota of1,500 a month and there were already in the camps in Palestineenough to exhaust this quota until the middle of September. TheSecretary of State said that he had discussed the position with thePrime Minister, who was inclined to the view that it would be a mistake at this juncture to divert illegal immigrants from palestine and had suggested that women and children might be allowed topass through the camps at once, but that the men should be detainedthere indefinitely.[32426-5] c
The Cabinet were informed that the Chiefs of Staff fely strongly that illegal immigration should be stopped. If it con-tinued there would be serious trouble with the Arabs and our presentforces in Palestine would not be able to cope with this and withtrouble from the Jews simultaneously. If we sent more troops to palestine we should have to slow down the army release schemedrastically. The indefinite detention of adult male immigrants incamps would hardly lessen the resentment of the Arabs. If theCabinet decided that illegal immigration must be stopped, the navaland military authorities could undertake the task of stopping it.The Chiefs of Staff considered that ships should be interceptedwithin three miles of the Palestine coast; prize crews should thenbe put aboard to take charge of the immigrants and sail the ships,or, alternatively, the immigrants should be transferred to british ships; they should then be returned to their port of departure ordiverted to some other destination, such as Cyprus or Cyrenaica.In further discussion attention was drawn to the difficulties and risks of a policy of refusing illegal immigrants admission to palestine. It was no use starting on such a policy unless theGovernment were prepared to adhere resolutely to it, whatever theeventualities, and the eventualities might be serious. The operationof boarding ships in the open sea and transferring the Jews toBritish ships might well lead to serious incidents. Thus there might be mass hysteria, suicides and even sabotage of the ships. Weshould also seriously damage our chance of getting co-operation from the United States in a long-term solution of the palestine problem. As to the disposal of the would-be immigrants, it was clear that it would generally be quite impossible to send them backto their ports of departure since it would not be practicable to force the authorities there to accept them. Moreover, when on a previous occasion Jews had been diverted to Mauritius, there had been a mostdifficulty legacy of trouble. Accordingly, several Ministerssuggested that, even though there was a risk of serious difficulties with the Arabs if illegal immigration continued, the alternative ofturning back immigrants who were within sight of the coast ofPalestine was unacceptable; and the solution proposed by the PrimeMinister might be the best in all the circumstances. In view ofthe advice given by the Chiefs of Staff, however, it was felt that no decision should be taken until the discussion had been reported tothe Prime Minister and his further views had been obtained.The Vice-Chief of Naval Staff said that information had beenreceived that eleven more ships were on their way to Palestine fromGenoa, the Piraeus, Antwerp and other ports. Most of these were small ships, but three of them were of considerable size.It was suggested that these ships should be prevented from leaving European ports. This should surely be possible, at least inthe case of ships leaving Greece and Italy, where we had troops anda considerable influence over the Government.The Minister of State said that the strongest representations!had already been made to the various Governments concerned. Itmust be appreciated, however, that it was not always easy to bring!pressure to bear, for instance, in the case of the Roumanian;Government.(d) Letter from General Barker. The attention of the Cabinet!was drawn to a newspaper report that a letter had been sent by the]General Officer Commanding in Palestine to officers under his]command forbidding British soldiers to hold any social intercourse]with Jews.The Secretary of State for War said that he had already instiltuted enquiries into this matter and hoped to be in a position to give!the Cabinet a report on it at their meeting on the following day. IThe Cabinet-(5) Approved the proposal to begin the search for Jewish]terrorists on the 30th July.
(6) Agreed to resume discussion of the question of illegal immi-gration at their meeting on the following day and invited the Lord President to convey to the PrimeMinister the views of the Chiefs of Staff and the general sense of the discussion on this matter.(7) Invited the Chiefs of Staff, in consultation withthe Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Ministerof State, to prepare for consideration on the following day a report on the steps which could be taken to preventships carrying illegal immigrants from leavingEuropean ports, particularly ports in Italy and Greece,and on the alternative destinations to which illegal immigrants could be diverted from Palestine.(8) Agreed to defer until their meeting on the following dayconsideration of the renewed proposal made by the HighCommissioner in telegram No. 1226 for the sequestrationof certain Zionist Funds.(9) Took note that the Secretary of State for War would reportto the Cabinet on the following day the result of the enquiries which he had instituted into the newspaperreport that General Barker had sent a letter to hisofficers forbidding British soldiers to hold any socialintercourse with Jews.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,29th July, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
