<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 124-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;  GO:PvNMENT_____Printed for the Cabinet.  August 1946.SECRET.CM. (46)76th Conclusions.Copy No. A 9CABINET 76 (46).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 1st August, 1946, at 10 a.m.PresentThe Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair Items 3-11).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council(in the Chair Items 1 and 2).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C, M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 3).The Right Hon. Lewis Silkin, M.P.,Minister   of   Town   and   country planning (Item 2).The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Minister of State (Items 4-11).Mr.   Geoffrey   de  Freitas,   M.P.,Parliamentary  Under-Secretary  ofState for Air (Item 4).Marshal of the Royal Air Force lord tedder,   Chief  of  the  Air  Staff(Items 4-7).The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Items 1and 5).The Right Hon. the Earl of Listowel,Postmaster-General (Item 8).Mr. J. B. Hynd, M.P., Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster (Item 10).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent TJnder-Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs (Items 4-11).Admiral Sir John H. D. Cunningham,First Sea Lord and Chief of naval staff (Items 4-7).[32426-7]Field-Marshal Viscount montgomery of Alamein, Chief of the ImperialGeneral Staff (Items 4-7).b
Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Major-General Sir Leslie Hollis.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.CABINET 76 (46).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Cabinet and Cabinet Committee Business during  the summer Becess      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     2612      Town and Country Planning (Development Rights) Bill....     2613      Future of the Iron and Steel Industry      ....      ....      ....     2634      Demobilisation....      ....      ........      ....      ....      ....     264Releases from the Royal Air Force in the last quarter of 1946.5      Palestine ....      ....      ........      ....      ....      ....     265Proposed Conference with Arabs and Jews.Illegal Immigration.6      Persia    ....................      ....      ........     267Despatch of Troops to Iraq.7      Anglo-Egyptian Treaty Negotiations............     2698      India     ................................     269Constitutional Position.9      British Nationality Law      ........      ....      ....      ....     27010      Germany ............      ................     271Exports of Coal from the British Zone.11      Proposal to Abolish Visas    ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    271
Cabinet andGabinetCommitteeBusinessduring theSummerRecess.1. The Lord President recalled that in June the PrimeMinister had circulated a note (CP. (46) 251) proposing that duringthe six weeks from the 5th August to the 16th September thereshould be no meetings of the Standing Ministerial Committees ofthe Cabinet and that the Cabinet itself should meet as rarely aspossible. It seemed clear that there would have to be at least oneCabinet meeting in the week beginning the 5th August and it was proposed to hold this meeting on the 7th August at 11 a.m. only those Ministers in London or within reasonable distance from itwould be expected to attend this or any subsequent meetings of theCabinet during the Recess. Subsequent meetings would normally be held on Wednesday mornings and the Cabinet Secretariat would try to let Ministers&apos; Private Secretaries know by Monday morning at latest, and if possible before the week-end, whether a Cabinet wasto be held in any given week. Every endeavour would be made toavoid meetings of Cabinet Committees and, unless in special circum-stances, any urgent business for such Committees would be takenby the Cabinet.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the arrangements proposed for the despatch of Cabinet and Cabinet Committeebusiness during the Summer Recess.Town and country planning(DevelopmentRights) Bill.(previous reference:CM. (45) 53rdConclusions,Minute 2.)2.   The Cabinet had before them (i) a memorandum by the Minister of Town and country planning (CP. (46) 296) seeking their views on certainoutstanding points connected with the Town and country Planning (Development Rights) Bill; and(ii) a memorandum by the Lord President (CP. (46) 311)reporting the views of the Ministerial Sub-Committeeon Compensation and Betterment on these points.The Minister of Town and Country Planning explainedthat, since the matter had last been considered by the Cabinet,he had altered considerably his proposals for the compensation of owners in respect of the restriction of their land to its existing use and that he now proposed to pay only in respectof out-of-pocket loss. Two alternative schemes had beenconsidered by the Ministerial Sub-Committee, who had come to theconclusion that the discount basis of compensation for out-of-pocketloss, details of which were set out in Appendix B to CP. (46) 296,was preferable. The Sub-Committee had also agreed that thelimitation of compensation to out-of-pocket loss should apply todeveloped land as well as to undeveloped land. Appendix C of cp. (46) 296 set out two alternative methods of assisting localauthorities in connection with the purchase of land. The Sub-Committee had preferred the scheme of grants outlined in Part I ofthe Appendix to the scheme for central purchase outlined in Part II.The proposed Bill would make substantial amendments in themachinery of planning, and this raised the question whetherplanning functions should not be transferred from county district councils and the City of London to county councils. So far as concerned authorities outside London, the majority of the Sub-Committee were in favour of a transfer of functions. With regardto the City of London, which presented a special problem, he was satisfied, after discussion with the Leader of the London CountyCouncil, that there would be no practical difficulties about a transferof powers from the Corporation of the City of London to theLondon County Council. It was proposed that the Bill should include provisions for the control of outdoor advertisements. Hewould discuss with the Chancellor of the Exchequer certain out-standing financial points relating to the payment of betterment bylocal authorities in respect of land acquired for statutory purposes and the extent of Exchequer contributions towards compensation payable for interference with existing buildings and uses whichcontravened planning requirements.[32426-7] b 2
The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he endorsed therecommendations of the Ministerial Sub-Committee. With regardto compensation for the restriction of land to its existing use, thegeneral view of the Sub-Committee had been that some payment would have to be made in respect of death duties paid on develop-ment values in cases where no compensation would be payable underthe formula approved by the Sub-Committee. He would discuss this matter with the Minister of Town and Country Planning andthe Cabinet would have an opportunity of considering it when thedraft Bill was submitted to them. He would also discuss with theMinister the details of the scheme of grants to local authorities in aid of the purchase of land.Further discussion concentrated mainly on the proposal that the planning functions of county district councils should be transferredto county councils.The Minister of Health said that he was opposed to theproposed transfer of functions. There was no real evidence that thecounty district councils were incapable of carrying out planning functions adequately, and it would be a mistake to divorce these functions from the functions in regard to housing, water supplyand sewerage which were still discharged by county district councils.There might well be a case for proposing a general reorganisation oflocal government, but to pursue a policy of removing one functionafter another from district councils would merely demoralise these authorities and expose the Government to severe criticism inParliament.On the other hand, it was urged that the typical district council had not the resources, particularly of staff, to discharge planning functions adequately, and that the device of grouping district councils into joint committees did not provide a satisfactory solu-tion. It was realised that there would be considerable opposition in Parliament to the proposed transfer of powers, and it wouldbe desirable for the Minister to consider what arrangements mightbe made to enable county district councils to have a say in the dis-charge of planning functions, and possibly even to enable planning functions to be delegated to district councils in particular caseswhere this could be justified.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the basis of compensation for the restriction of land to existing use should be on the lines set outin Appendix B to OP. (46) 296, and should apply todeveloped as well as undeveloped land.(2) Agreed that assistance to local authorities for the purchaseof land should be given by way of grants on the lines suggested in Part I of Appendix C to OP. (46) 296.(3) Approved the proposal to transfer planning functions fromcounty district councils to county councils and fromthe Corporation of the City of London to the LondonCounty Council, on the understanding that the Ministerof Town and Country Planning would consider whatprovisions might be inserted in the Bill for consultationwith district councils in connexion with the dischargeof planning functions and possibly for the delegation of functions to district councils in suitable cases.(4) Agreed that the Bill should include provisions for the con-trol of outdoor advertisements.(5) Took note that the Chancellor Of the Exchequer would consider further with the Minister of Town and country planning and the Secretary of State for Scotland what arrangements should be made with regard to (i) the payment of compensation in cases where death-duties had been paid on development values:(ii) the payment of betterment by local authorities inrespect of land purchased for statutory purposes;and
(iii) the extent of Exchequer contributions to the com-pensation payable for interference with existing buildings and uses.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Supply (CP. (46) 300) about the proposal to establish a Control Board to supervise the steel industry during the period before public ownership.The Minister of Supply said that he had hoped to be able to announce the membership of the Board in the House of commons before the Recess, but that he had been hampered by the attitudeof the Iron and Steel Federation, who, though they were preparedto co-operate with any Government agency charged with the con-trol of the industry, would not associate themselves with a Boardwhose duties included giving guidance and advice on technical matters arising in regard to nationalisation. As indicated in CP.(46) 300, he had, after consultation with the Prime Minister, theLord President and the Chancellor of the Exchequer, given an.invitation to Dr. Van. der bill to act as Chairman of the Board.Dr. Van der bill had intimated that he would be reluctant, toaccept this post, and had suggested that he might be empoweredto discuss with leaders of the iron and steel industry certain pro-posals which might induce them to alter their present attitude.Since CP. (46) 300 had been circulated, it had become clear thatthese proposals would not be acceptable to the Government since they would involve Government control without Government owner-ship. In these circumstances he thought that the best course wouldbe to explore, through Dr. Van der bill or otherwise, the possibilityof an arrangement under which the Iron and Steel Federation would facilitate the recruitment to the proposed Control Board of persons with experience of the iron and steel industry, on the understandingthat the Boa.rd&apos;s functions would not include the giving of advice on plans for public ownership, and that individual steel membersof the Board would not be called upon to give such advice. If ascheme of this kind were adopted, the Government would be free to obtain such technical assistance as they might require on thequestion of the scope and nature of the plans for public ownershipoutside the ambit of the proposed Control Board. His view wasthat, provided the Government obtained voting control by acquiringthe equity, there would be much to be said for retaining the structure-ture and identity of at least the leading companies in the industry;and if arrangements were made on these lines there would be lessneed for technical advice on questions of severance. The functionsof the Control Board under this plan would be to exercise thepowers now possessed by the Iron and Steel Control and to ensurethat a suitable development programme was carried through.The Lord President said that it was regrettable that the Ironand Steel Federation should have been unwilling to co-operate. he agreed with the solution proposed by the Minister of Supply. Theadvantage of proceeding by way of acquiring the major interest inthe equity of the undertakings was that this would enable well-known firms to retain a measure of identity, while giving theGovernment firm control. It would also enable the pace at whichthe industry was brought under public ownership to be regulated by the Government at will.In further discussion there was general support for the pro-posal made by the Minister of Supply. It was pointed out, however,that it would probably be undesirable to spread over a period oftime the acquisition of a controlling interest in the various firmssince this would create a general feeling of uncertainty throughoutthe industry.The Cabinet-(1) Authorised the Minister of Supply to explore the possi-bilility of securing an arrangement under which the
co-operation of the Iron and Steel Federation in the setting up of the Control Board would be obtained byexcluding from the functions of the Board the giving of advice on plans for public ownership.(2) Gave general approval to the proposal that control of theiron and steel industry should be secured through theacquisition by the Government of a controlling interestin the equity of the various companies, and agreed thatthe Minister of Supply should work out a scheme onthese lines in consultation with the Lord President andthe Chancellor of the Exchequer.Demobillsa-tion.Releases fromthe Royal AirForce in thelast quarterof 1946.(previous reference:CM. (46) 9thConclusions,Minute 7.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for Air (CP. (46) 312) proposing that the man-power ceiling fixed for the Eoyal Air Force at theend of 1946 should be increased by 25,000 by retarding releases in the last quarter of the year.The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Air said thatthe need for a higher man-power ceiling at the end of 1946 arosepartly from the disappointing results of the scheme for there-engagement of trained men and partly from the fact that theloss of effective man-power involved in the large-scale reorganisa-tion and regrouping of the Force was proving greater than had beenforeseen. Certain other contributory factors were set out in para-graph 2 of the memorandum annexed to CP. (46) 312. The slowing down of releases would undoubtedly cause great disappointment,but it seemed to be unavoidable; and the retention of 25,000 trained men would make a very great difference to the efficiency of the RoyalAir Force. The situation would be to some extent eased by thefact that the proposed retardation would still leave releases fromthe Royal Air Force slightly in advance of releases from the Army.^ The Chief of the Air Staff said that, whereas an efficient AirForce required about 80 per cent, of skilled men, by the end ofthe year the number of skilled men would on present plans be reducedto 15 per cent. It was vital to obtain a larger number of trained men by re-engagement and to increase the regular entry, and theRoyal Air Force were doing what they could to this end. the recruiting campaign had, however, had little support in the press and so far the results had been anything but encouraging. Evenif the proposed increase in the man-power ceiling were approved,the number of effective squadrons which it would be possible tomaintain was alarmingly small.In discussion, it was pointed out that, even on the basis of theoriginal ceilings proposed for the Forces at the end of 1946 therewas bound to be a serious shortage of labour, particularly for theproduction of consumer goods. The proposed increase in Royal AirForce man-power would accentuate still further the difficultiesoccasioned by this shortage and would also entail additional expendi-ture. It was therefore most desirable that every effort should bemade to persuade more trained men to re-engage and to make themost economical use of the available man-power in the Royal AirForce.The Prime Minister said that, while he agreed that releases from the Royal Air Force in the last quarter of 1946 should beretarded, he would like to examine more closely the question whetherthe Royal Air Force man-power ceiling at the end of 1946 need beraised by 25,000.^It was explained that in the normal course a public announce-ment of the groups to be released in the last quarter of 1946 shouldhave been made before the end of July, and that it would be essential to make such an announcement without further delay. Atthe same time it was undesirable that too much prominence shouldbe given to the announcement and, in particular, it was important
that nothing should be said which would imply that the reason forthe slowing down of releases was the need to retain larger Forcesin occupied countries. In these circumstances, the best course wouldbe to avoid making an announcement in the House of Commons,and to publish without comment the information about tlhe groups to be released in the last quarter.The Cabinet-(1) Approved the retardation of Royal Air Force releases inthe last quarter of 1946 proposed in CP. (46) 312 and agreed that as soon as Parliament had risen theMinister of Labour should announce without commentthese releases and the corresponding releases from theArmy which had been approved by the Defence Com-mittee at their meeting on the 19th July (D.O. (46)23rd Meeting, Minute 1).(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange forfurther consideration to be given to the questionwhether the man-power ceiling of the Royal Air force at the end of 1946 should be increased by 25,000.5. The Cabinet were informed that the Saudi Arabian and transjordan Jordan Governments had accepted invitations to the proposed conference on future policy in Palestine, but that replies had notyet been received from the Syrian and Egyptian Governments.The Prime Minister said that it was most important that theconference should meet at the earliest possible date.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies and theMinister of State to take all possible steps to expedite the meeting of the proposed conference on future policyin Palestine.The Secretary of State for the Colonies recalled that at their previous meeting the Cabinet had asked him, in consultation with sir John Shaw, the High Commissioner for Palestine, the Chiefsof Staff and the Minister of Transport, to draw up for their consideration a plan for the transhipment of illegal immigrantsin Palestine waters and their removal to Cyprus. After a full discussion with Sir John Shaw, he had telegraphed to the HighCommissioner, but he had not yet received the High Commissionersreply and he was, therefore, unable to lay a plan before the Cabinet.Meanwhile, another ship with 500 illegal immigrants had arrivedand a further ship containing some 2,000 immigrants was believed to be approaching Palestine. He had ascertained that Cypruswould be able to accommodate up to 8,000 or 9,000 Jews in camps;and the necessary legislative and other measures to make this possible were now being taken.The Prime Minister said that the Lord President had sent him a report of the Cabinet&apos;s previous discussion of this matter. Hewas much impressed by the difficulties of the proposed operation and feared that it would lead to incidents which would seriouslyembarrass the Government.The Minister of Transport agreed with the views expressedby the Prime Minister. The operation would also involve a waste of shipping.The First Sea Lord said that it was impracticable to interceptships with illegal immigrants on the high seas and divert them to cyprus. Nor, looking to the condition of the ships and thedesperate state of mind of the immigrants, did he regard it asfeasible to divert immigrant ships from Palestinian territorial waters to Cyprus.   Thus the only alternatives seemed to be either
to bring the ships into harbour and then transfer the immigrants Idirectly to other ships or to land them, place them in camps and Isubsequently re-embark them.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that, of these two Ialternatives, the Army would much prefer the former, i;e: \transhipment in harbour. The operation would undoubtedly be Idifficult and unpleasant and it would be well to know precisely!what would be involved. If the Cabinet so desired, he would obtain Ia plan from the Commander-in-Chief, Middle East.The Secretary of State for the Colonies recalled that the High 1Commissioner for Palestine was already preparing a plan and would no doubt be consulting the General Officer Commanding in IPalestine. It would be well to ensure that the Commander-in-1Chiefs proposals were formulated in the light of the results of 1these discussions.It was also suggested that the Commander-in-Chief might 1consider whether the difficulties of the operation could be reduced 1by removing to Cyprus only the adult males, the women and 1children being retained in camps in Palestine and set off against Ithe immigration quota.In further discussion it was suggested that, since the Cabinet!had last discussed the matter, a new factor had been introduced jby the announcement of the Governments long-term policy for]Palestine.   Under the new proposals, once the constitutional plan!had been accepted, it would become possible to allow 100,000 jews to enter the Jewish Province.   Might not the Jewish Agency, whowere responsible for organising illegal immigration, now be anxious,in their own interests, to stop this traffic, if it were made clear tothem that its continuance during the next few weeks might endanger or postpone the legal admission of 100,000 Jews ?   would it not be desirable to put this point to the Agency ?   It was truethat they had recently been wholly unco-operative, but it was proposed that the plan for future policy should now be discussed with them as well as with the Arabs and they might well be willingto alter their attitude in the light of the new situation.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he wouldtake this matter up with representatives of the Jewish Agency,though he had little hope of a favourable response from them.The Minister of State said that the Foreign Office were doing what they could to prevent illegal immigrants from leaving]European ports. He hoped that the Greek Government would take!effective action and, though the French Government were doubtful!about their legal powers, they had been persuaded to agree to doiwhat they could to help. On the other hand, the Russian,]Roumanian and Yugoslav Governments had not so far prove!co-operative.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to bring itsto the notice of the Jewish Agency that the continuancfof illegal immigration during the next few weeks coulcnot fail to affect adversely the chances that the plan foithe immigration of 100,000 Jews to Palestine would bfimplemented in the near future, and to try to enlist thiAgency&apos;s help in putting a stop to illegal immigration(3) Invited the Chief of the Imperial General Staff to ask theCommander-in-Chief, Middle East, to draw up a plaifor sending illegal immigrants to Cyprus.(4) Invited the Secretary of State for the Colonies to completthe arrangements for the reception of illegal imffil!grants in Cyprus, and the Minister of Transport t(arrange for the necessary shipping to be made availaMjfor their transfer to that country.
6. At their meeting on the 15th July the Cabinet had agreedthat an Indian Brigade should be moved to Basra-Shaiba in orderto deal with any trouble which might suddenly arise in the SouthPersian oilfields.The Cabinet now had before them (i) A memorandum by the Minister of State (CP. (46) 314)suggesting that the nature of the force which was to besent to Basra-Shaiba might give rise to an anti-Britishagitation in Iraq ; and(ii) A memorandum by the Secretary of State for India(CP. (46) 313) stating that the effect on Indian opinionof the despatch of troops from India to Iraq would beless unfavourable if the purposes for which they werebeing sent were frankly disclosed.The Minister of State said that the plans made by the Servicesseemed to go beyond what was originally contemplated. The IndianBrigade group which was being moved to Basra-Shaiba would take with it much heavy equipment, including a field artillery regimentof sixteen guns. Moreover, on the naval side, twelve landing craft,together with a number of other vessels, were being taken to Basra.Under the Anglo-Iraqi Treaty of Alliance His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment were not normally entitled to keep ground troops in Iraq and,though we had hitherto succeeded in retaining a certain numberof troops for the purpose of guarding military stores, the arrival of a fully equipped force would inevitably suggest to the Iraqisthat we intended to use their country as a base for an attack onPersia and might even appear to them as part of a plan to holddown Iraq during the execution in Palestine of a policy to whichArab States took objection. In these circumstances there was a risk of a popular outcry for the immediate withdrawal of our troops, possibly coupled with a request for revision of the Anglo-Iraqi Treaty.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that if the forcesent to Basra-Shaiba was to be an effective one it must be so equippedas to enable it to face any eventuality. Admittedly the most likelyform of trouble would be rioting rather than organised armedresistance and, if the Cabinet thought fit, it would be possible to omit from the force the field artillery regiment. He felt, however,that it would be a wise precaution to include the artillery, sinceeven if nothing worse that rioting had to be dealt with, the firingof a few shells might well be the means of saving a considerablenumber of lives. The mere omission of the artillery would notdeceive the Iraqis as to the purpose for which the troops were being sent to Basra-Shaiba, and he saw no alternative to stating franklythat we were taking this action in order to protect lives and property in Persia.The First Sea Lord said that the naval vessels referred to bythe Minister of State were needed to transport the force to Persiain the event of trouble.The Secretary of State for India said that it was necessarythat the troops which were being despatched from Indian ports on the 2nd August should be told where they were going, and that,in his opinion, it would be futile to attempt to disguise the purpose for which they were being sent. It should be made clear in any statement that this purpose included the protection of Indian lives and interests. He supported the view that the force should be fully equipped.The Prime Minister said that no purpose would be served by attempting to conceal the object for which the Indian brigade group was being sent to Basra-Shaiba. He recalled that when theCabinet had taken the decision to send this force the Foreign Secre-tary had said that he would inform the Government of Iraq of whatwas proposed. He understood that nothing had yet been said 10the Iraqi Government and there was therefore no clear evidence3-7] c
Avhat the attitude of that Government would be to the proposal.He thought that a communication should be made to the iraqi government before the force arrived at Basra-Shaiba, and he agreed with the Secretary of State for India that the Indian troops shouldbe frankly told why they were being sent to Iraq. Any public statement should bring out clearly the fact that His Majesty&apos;sGovernment were seeking to protect Indian and Arab lives and property as well as their own interests.The Cabinet -(1) Agreed that the plans made by the Service authorities forthe despatch of an Indian Brigade group to Basra-Shaiba should be implemented without alteration.(2) Agreed that no attempt should be made to disguise thepurpose for which the Indian Brigade Group was being sent to Basra-Shaiba, and that it should be made clearthat this purpose included the protection of Indian andArab interests.(3) Invited the Minister of State to arrange for a suitablecommunication to be made to the Iraqi government before the arrival of the force.The Cabinet then discussed the situation in the oilfields ofthe Anglo-Iranian Oil Company.The Tudeh Party appeared to have over-reached themselves and the latest information showed that the position was easier.Nevertheless, if further trouble was to be avoided it seemed essentialthat the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company should show a readier dis-position to promote a rise in the standard of living of their workers.It was true that the provision of houses and the development of welfare services had necessarily been slowed down by war condi-tions, but it seemed doubtful whether the Company were adopting a sufficiently enlightened attitude towards the wages claims madeby their workers.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that he had on theprevious day received a letter, written on behalf of the foreign secretary, suggesting that he should see the Chairman of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company and should also convene a meeting of the chairmen of all the British oil companies with a view to impressingon them the need for adopting an enlightened policy in the treat-ment of foreign labour employed by the companies. He would make arrangements to see the Chairman of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Com-pany on the following day and would also take up the question ofmaking a more general appeal. He felt, however, that it would bedesirable to supplement this by issuing a statement, which should begiven publicity in Persia, to the effect that His Majesty&apos;s Govern -ment were in favour of all possible steps being taken to raise thestandard of living of the workers.The Cabinet (4) Took note that the Minister of Fuel and Power, in con-sultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and theMinister of State, would arrange to see the Chairmanof the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company immediately witha view to impressing on him that the Company should adopt an enlightened attitude towards any reasonableclaims made by their workers.(5) Agreed that, after the meeting referred to in (4) had beenheld, the Minister of State in consultation with theother Ministers concerned should arrange for the issueof a suitable statement, which should be given publicitj&apos;in Persia, as to the attitude of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in this matter
jnglo-EgyptianTreatyNegotiations.(previous reference:CM. (46)58thConclusions.)India.constitutional position.(previous reference:CM. (46) 69thConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Cabinet discussed the latest developments in theAnglo-Egyptian Treaty negotiations, as reported in telegramsiNos. 33, 35, 39 and 40 from the Secretary of State for Air. these telegrams indicated that difficulties had arisen over three points (i) the timing of the programme of evacuation;(ii) the proposal in Article 2 of the draft Treaty that british forces should have the right to re-enter Egypt ifhostilities broke out in neighbouring countries otherthan those adjacent to Egypt; and(iii) the claim that the Egyptian Crown had sovereignty overthe Sudan.Though no reply had yet been received to the latest communicationaddressed to the Egyptian Delegation, it was desirable that theBritish Delegation should be given guidance as to the line whichthey should take on the points at issue.The Cabinet were informed that, so far as concerned the pro-gramme of evacuation, the Chiefs of Staff would see no objection toa compromise on a period of three to five years, but that they regarded a period of three years as the absolute minimum. Withregard to Article 2 of the draft Treaty, while the Chiefs of staff would prefer to see a provision in the Treaty guaranteeing thatBritish troops would be able to enter Egypt in the event of a dangerous situation arising in countries such as Iraq or Syria, they felt that the primary consideration was that we should secure aTreaty with Egypt and they would therefore be prepared to agreeto the limitation proposed by the Egyptian Delegation rather thanface a complete breakdown in the negotiations. The Chiefs ofStaff thought it essential that a firm stand should be made on thequestion of the Sudan.The Prime Minister said that he doubted whether anythingmaterial would be obtained by insisting on the acceptance of theBritish version of Article 2 of the draft Treaty. Since Egypt wasvital to our position in the Middle East, we were bound to go toher assistance in any case in which she was threatened; and itwould not help us to have a provision in the Treaty authorising the entry of British troops into Egypt in certain circumstances if theEgyptian Government were determined to evade their obligations under that provision. He agreed that a firm stand should be madewith regard to the Sudan. It would, of course, be open to theEgyptian Government to make a unilateral declaration on thismatter, but we should resist the inclusion in the protocol of anywords admitting the sovereignty of the Egyptian Crown over theSudan.As regards the proposal that Sidky Pasha should come toLondon, while it might in the end be necessary to agree to this, hewould prefer that the negotiations should continue in Cairo.The Cabinet-Agreed that the British Delegation should negotiate fora compromise on a period of not less than three years forthe completion of evacuation; should accept the Egyptiandraft of Article 2 of the Treaty, if it appeared impossibleto obtain the willing agreement of the Egyptian delegation to the British version; and should resist the inclusion inthe Sudan protocol of any provision implying recognitionof Egyptian sovereignty over the Sudan.8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secre-tary of State for India (CP. (46) 315) regarding the positionresulting from the withdrawal by the Muslim League of their acceptance of the Cabinet Mission&apos;s statement and from a subsequent interview between the Viceroy and Pandit Nehru. after discussion at the India and Burma Committee and consultationwith the Prime Minister, a telegram (Annex II to CP. (46) 315)had been sent to the Viceroy stating that it was impossible to allow
Mr. Jinnah&apos;s non-co-operation to hold up progress with the forma-tion of an Interim Government. The telegram had proposed thatthe next step should be for the Viceroy to see Mr. Jinnah and endeavour to persuade him, even now, to allow members of the muslim League to enter the proposed Interim Government. TheSecretary of State for India now proposed that a further telegram(Annex III to CP. (46) 315) should be sent to the Viceroy Iindicating the policy which he should adopt if Mr. Jinnah was unwilling to co-operate in the formation of an Interim Government.The Secretary of State for India reported that since CP. (46)315 had been circulated a telegram had been received from theViceroy to the effect that he was sure it would not be advisable for him to see Mr. Jinnah immediately. The Viceroy wished to puton Congress the responsibility for any attempt to satisfy the League.In discussion there was general agreement that, if the muslim league were unwilling to come in, it would be necessary to proceedwith the formation of an Interim Government with Congress only.The Cabinet also took the view that the Viceroy should not fiefurther pressed to see Mr. Jinnah. and that he should be left todecide in the light of his local knowledge of the situation whetherthe places in the Interim Government, to which it had been proposedto appoint representatives of the Muslim League, should or shouldnot be filled by other Muslims.The Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for India to send a telegram to the Viceroy on the lines agreed in the discussion.9. The Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum by theHome Secretary and the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs(CP. (46) 305) regarding possible changes in British nationalitylaw consequent on the passage of the Canadian Citizenship Act.This Act introduced, so far as concerned Canada, a fundamental change in the system of British nationality Law, since it proceededon the principle that the status of a British subject should be basedupon the possession of the local citizenship of a particular partof the Commonwealth; and it was necessary to consider what con-sequential changes should be made in the nationality laws of theUnited Kingdom and the other members of the Commonwealth. Tothis end it had been agreed to hold a meeting of experts from commonwealth countries in London in October or November, and before that meeting it would be necessary for the United KingdomGovernment to decide certain major questions of policy, namely :-(i) whether the United Kingdom was to participate in thenew system;(ii) what form that participation should take;(iii) in connection with the latter point, the manner in whichthe United Kingdom, the Colonies, India, Burma, New-foundland and Southern Rhodesia were to be brought within the new citizenship scheme; and(iv) certain special difficulties arising in the case of Eire.These questions involved intricate constitutional and legal problems and the memorandum suggested the appointment of a committeeof Ministers to consider them and report to the Cabinet.The Cabinet Agreed that the points set out in paragraph 5 of CP. (46)305 should be considered by a Committee consisting of thefollowing Ministers :- Lord Chancellor.Home Secretary.Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.Secretary of State for India and for Burma.Secretary of State for the Colonies.Minister of State.Attorney-General.BritishNationalityLaw.(previous reference:CM. (45) 55thConclusions,Minute 5.)
10. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (CP. (46) 316) regardingthe export of coal from the British Zone in Germany.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster recalled that at themeeting of the Overseas Eeconstruction Committee on the 21st June(O.R.C (46) 9th Meeting, Minute 3), it had been generally agreed by Ministers that the sound economic course was to retain a largerquantity of coal in the British Zone, but it had not been thought desirable to impose a complete suspension of exports whilediscussions regarding the future of Germany were proceeding at theCouncil of Foreign Ministers in Paris. Subsequently, however, theForeign Secretary had stated that, if the principle of treatingGermany as an economic unit was not accepted by the four Powers,the British Zone would be organised in such a way as to eliminate the burden which the British taxpayer had to bear; and it was clear that one of the most effective steps to this end would be toretain more of the coal produced in the British Zone.The quadripartite Fuel Committee was now about to meet inBerlin to consider the September coal allocations and it had beensuggested that the British representatives should propose that exports in September should be reduced from 900,000 tons to 450,000tons. The Fuel Committee was not normally able to reach agree-ment on allocations, but, if the Americans were prepared to support this proposal, it should be possible for us to implement it despiteFrench and possibly Russian objections.The disadvantage of the course proposed was that we shouldbe anticipating the report of the Committee of Experts appointed on the instructions of the Council of Foreign Ministers to examinemethods of increasing coal production in all four Zones and to make recommendations as to the principles on which production shouldbe allocated between domestic consumption and exports. Neverthe-less, since an increase in coal consumption within the British Zonewas an essential preliminary to economic improvement there, he recommonded to his colleagues that the course proposed should beadopted.In discussion Ministers recognised the force of the arguments advanced by the Chancellor of the Duchy. On the other hand, they felt that the political repercussions of taking action on the lines proposed before the report of the Committee of Experts had beenreceived would be serious. Moreover, a drastic reduction in thetotal coal exports from Germany would mean that less coal would goto Finland and Sweden, with the result that timber exports to theUnited Kingdom from these countries would diminish.The Cabinet-Agreed that, pending the receipt of the report of theCommittee of Experts, there should be no drastic cut in coal exports from the British Zone and that these exportsshould accordingly be maintained at approximately thecurrent level.11.   The Cabinet had before them : (i) a memorandum by the Foreign Secretary (CP. (46) 302)proposing the immediate relaxation of the restriction onthe admission of foreign tourists to the United Kingdomand the negotiation of agreements with those foreigncountries to which British visitors were most numerousfor the mutual abolition of the requirement of a visa;and(ii) a memorandum by the Home Secretary (CP. (46) 303)agreeing in principle with the Foreign Secretary&apos;sproposals, but pointing out certain difficulties whichwould arise from their adoption.
The Minister of State emphasised that the Foreign Secretaryattached great importance to securing greater freedom of movement for tourists. Among other advantages, the proposals would assist in the rehabilitation of countries such as Italy, Austria and Greece.They would also be in line with the objects of the conference on pass-ports and frontier formalities which was being organised under the aegis of the Economic and Social Council.In discussion there was general agreement on the desirability of reducing the formalities involved in international travel and encouraging tourists to visit the United Kingdom. It was pointedout that plans were being made for expanding the tourist trade ofthe United Kingdom in 1947 and that it was most important thatas many restrictions as possible should be removed before the 1947season began. At the same time it was felt that the removalof restrictions would be premature at the present moment, when there were still many displaced persons in Europe who would takeadvantage of any relaxation to obtain entry to the United Kingdomand when the need for controlling entry to the United Kingdom on security grounds was still great.The Cabinet-Agreed that the initiation of the negotiations proposed bythe Foreign Secretary for the mutual abolition of the visasystem should be deferred for the present.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,1st August, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
