<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 216-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OE HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1946.SECRET. Copy No. Zf 3CM. (46)84th Conclusions.CABINET 84 (46).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 3rd October, 1946, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary  of   State  for  DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 3).Mr. Hector McNeil, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 3-5).Mr. W. J. Edwards, M.P., Civil Lord,Admiralty (Item 4).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32563-3]b
CABINET 84 (46).Contents.Subject.parliamentary in the House of Commons.Enquiry into the PressIndian Pood Requirements   ....JapanMerchant Shipbuilding.International Employment Policy ....
parliament.the House0f Commons.1. The Lord President informed the Cabinet of the business which it was proposed to take in the House of Commons in thefollowing week.On the 8th October the Prime Minister would move the SecondBeading of the A tomic Energy Bill. The Minister of Supply would reply to the debate.On the 9th October the Report Stage and Third Reading of the hill Farming Bill would be taken. Thereafter there would beSecond Reading debates on three Scottish Bills.On the 10th October there would be a debate, on the adjourn-ment, on Housing in Scotland.On the 11th October the Prime Minister would move the SecondReading of the Roosevelt Memorial Bill. Thereafter, the remaining stages of the Atomic Energy Bill would be taken.The Cabinet were informed that the Leaders of the opposition were agreeable that further debate on India should be deferred forthe time being, possibly until the beginning of next Session.2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the lord president (CP. (46) 360) asking that they should now approve theproposal made in his earlier memorandum (CP. (46) 298) for theappointment of a Royal Commission to enquire into the ownership,management and control of the press and the news agencies.The Lord President said that he had reviewed his proposal in the light of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on the 30th July. He was satisfied that the tendencies to which the National Union of journalists had drawn attention were a menace to the freedom ofthe press, and that their demand for an enquiry had widespreadsupport in the Labour Party, both in Parliament and outside it. he did not think it necessary that the body appointed to undertake the enquiry should be set up under the Tribunals of Enquiry(Evidence) Act, 1921, since most of the information which it was desired to elicit could be obtained without the special powers conferred by that Act. Nor need the enquiry necessarily lead to legislation, since the publication of an authoritative report throwinglight on the existing state of affairs and laying down the general principles which ought to govern the conduct and management ofthe press might be enough in itself to check the present dangeroustendencies. A Royal Commission would be the most appropriate body to conduct the enquiry, and it would be helpful if a Judge couldbe secured as chairman.In discussion doubts were expressed about the wisdom ofinitiating such an enquiry. There would be very great difficultyin obtaining evidence of the alleged abuses, and there was a real riskof a white-washing report. Even if the enquiry did bring to lightabuses, its report would be an embarrassment unless adequate meansof checking those abuses could be devised. Would it in fact be practicable, without undue interference with the freedom of thepress, to restrict the growth of large newspaper combines or toprevent the selective presentation of news ? And was it notdangerous to launch an enquiry until the Government could seesome way of doing this ? Was, it not preferable to seek a practicalremedy for the present state of affairs by improving the presenta-tion of the Governments case through those newspapers which wereindependent and through other methods of publicity ?On the other hand, it wTas urged in favour of an enquiry thatthe Government could not justifiably refuse to enquire into abuseswhich were generally recognised to exist on the ground that themethod by which these abuses could be checked was not immediatelyobvious. The exposure of the facts in an authoritative report wouldin itself educate the public to a truer judgment of the reliance tobe placed on statements appearing in the press, and it was not unreasonable to expect that the Royal Commission, when it hadexplored the ground thoroughly, would be able to recommend[32563^3] - b 2
methods of control which would not infringe the liberty of the press.The Commission should be able to secure enough evidence for itspurposes, for it would be dangerous for newspaper proprietors to appear to be withholding information from the Commission. Thelarge newspaper combines were at present using their influence tocreate a mood of discouragement and depression in the country, andan improvement in the arrangements for presenting the Govern-ment&apos;s case would not in itself suffice to counter this.In further discussion there was general agreement that, before it was finally decided whether such an enquiry should be instituted,the Cabinet should consider the terms of reference and membershipsuggested for the proposed Commission, and a statement of thepowers which the Commission would have to obtain evidence.The Lord Chancellor said that, in view of the nature of theproposed enquiry, he hoped that the Cabinet would not ask himto use his influence to persuade a Judge to act as chairman of theCommission.The Cabinet Invited the Lord President, after consultation with thePresident of the Board of Trade and the Lord Chancellor,to submit a note setting out the suggested terms of reference and membership of the proposed Royal Commission,together with a statement of the Commission^ powers toobtain evidence.Indian FoodRequirements.(previous reference:CM. (46)80thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Cabinet considered the following memoranda on india&apos;s food requirements : CP. (46) 361 : by the Secretary of State for IndiaCP. (46) 366 : by the Minister of Food.CP. (46) 367 : by the Minister of Transport.The Secretary of State for India said that, owing to delays inshipments from the United States and obtaining export licences for maize bought in the Argentine, the Government-held stocks inIndia would now fall to the equivalent of less than four weeks&apos;off-take at the end of October, and less than three weeks&apos; off-takeat the end of November. A stock equivalent to five weeks&apos; off-takewas the minimum required to avoid breakdowns in distribution. Tosecure this, India must receive over 300,000 tons more cereals during october and November than were at present in sight. He had justlearned that export licences had now been obtained which wouldenable some 130,000 tons to be shipped from the Argentine, but this could hardly arrive before December.The Secretary of State emphasised the very serious political consequences of a breakdown of food supplies in India at themoment. To ease the situation, he urged that 100,000 tons of canadian wheat destined for the United Kingdom should be diverted to India, and that every effort should be made to expediteshipments of maize from the Argentine.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that the situationin Ceylon and the Far Eastern Colonies was quite as serious as inIndia. These territories had at present no stocks at all. The rationlevels were lower than in India and the population were entirelydependent on the regular arrival of ships to maintain supplies. Toprevent widespread starvation, at least 87,000 tons more cerealswould be required than were at present in sight. The UnitedKingdom had a direct responsibility for supplying these Colonies,and he must ask that their needs should rank at least as high asthose of India.The Minister of Food said that he fully appreciated the serious-ness of the situation, both in India and the Colonies. His ministry had been doing all they could to help. There was, however, a limit to the assistance which the United Kingdom could give.   We were
45CM. 84 (46).obtaining no wheat ourselves except Canadian wheat, and ship-ments from Canada were at the moment far behind the programme.To make good that programme Canada would have to ship over500,000 tons to the United Kingdom during October. This wouldbe a heavy task, and it was by no means certain that it couldbe achieved, especially as there might be more strikes in Canadawithin the next few weeks.United Kingdom stocks at the 1st October were 729,000 tonsof wheat and 248,000 tons of flour. Assuming that Canada mether commitments, they would rise to 924,000 tons of wheat and250,000 tons of flour at the 1st January. Even so, these stocks wouldbe small for the time of the year. He also feared that a directdiversion of wheat from the United Kingdom to India would givethe Canadians the impression that we could, in fact, have managedourselves with less than we had asked for from them.In discussion there was general agreement that the situation in ceylon and the Far Eastern Colonies was so serious that their essential needs must have first priority. It was argued, however,that in India also there was grave danger of famine, and that, apartfrom humanitarian considerations, it was politically important thatwe should take all the action we possibly could to help her duringthe next few months. The fact that we spared wheat from our own resources to help India in her extreme need should not imply thatwe could have done with less ourselves. India&apos;s need was for supplies during the next few weeks. By the New Year the dangerof famine should be over. Would it not be possible to make hera loan, to be repaid in the New Year ? Might we not, for instance,make her an immediate loan of flour, to be repaid with the Argentinemaize for which export licences had now been obtained ?The Minister of Food said that he would consider this and other possibilities. For instance, it now seemed that certain consignments of Canadian barley might be available for export to India from united States ports.As regards shipments from the Argentine, The Minister ofTransport said that four ships were available in the River Plateat the moment, and it should be possible to make others availablewithout much delay.The Cabinet -(1) Agreed that first priority should be given to meeting theneeds of Ceylon and our Far Eastern territories.(2) Agreed that, for the present, Canadian wheat destined for the United Kingdom should not be diverted to India.(3) Invited the Minister of Food to explore with the Secretaryof State for India means whereby India might obtainincreased shipments of cereals from Canada, the UnitedStates and the Argentine, with particular reference toArgentine maize and Canadian barley. These increasedshipments might possibly form a loan, to be repaid tothe United Kingdom in the New Year.(4) Invited the Minister of Transport to arrange for the speedyshipment both of the Argentine maize, for which export licences had now been obtained by the Government ofIndia, and of other cereals destined in the near future for India.4. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the First Lordof the Admiralty and the Minister of Transport (CP. (46) 359) onthe extent to which Japan should be allowed to build merchant ships.The memorandum recalled that on 8th March the cabinet had agreed that it should be left to the Far Eastern Commission todiscuss, as part of the wider problem of the future level of Japaneseindustry, the extent to which Japan should be allowed to retain hershipbuilding industry, and that our representative should notprejudge this discussion by demanding at the outset that Japan
should be prohibited from building any ocean-going vessels. TheSUnited States member of the Commission had now proposed that anlassured production capacity level should be fixed, below which the!various elements of Japanese industry would not be reduced; and the!level which he had proposed for the steel shipbuilding industry was!80,000 gross tons of new construction, of ships not exceedingi5,000 gross tons, and supporting facilities for the service and repair!of a merchant fleet of 1-5 million gross tons. The memorandum,!after recalling the arguments previously adduced against allowing!Japan to build ocean-going ships, recommended that our represents,-1tive on the Commission should be instructed to press that the upper!limit of size should be reduced from 5,000 to 2,000 gross tons. If japan were thus prohibited from building ships exceeding 2,0001gross tons, no objection need be raised to a total annual production!of 80,000- gross tons.In support of this recommendation the Minister of Trans-\port and the Civil Lord of the Admiralty said that the restriction offJapanese shipbuilding to ships not exceeding 2,000 gross tons was!justified on security grounds. With the plant and equipment requiredfor the construction of these smaller vessels, it would be impossiblefor the Japanese shipbuilding industry to SAvitch over to the con-struction of warships. If, however, the upper limit were fixed at,000 gross tons, they would be able to build ships capable of being used as warships and would also have shipyards which could be con-verted fairly rapidly for the construction of warships. Though itwas recommended primarily on security grounds, an upper limit of2,000 gross tons would afford a valuable measure of protection forthe British shipbuilding industry. This was likely to be faced witha serious contraction in a few years&apos; time; and the position wouldbe more serious if at that moment our industry had to contend with japanese competition.The Cabinet were informed that the Governments of Australiaand New Zealand favoured:, on security grounds, an upper limit of2,000 gross tons. The South African Government, though they feltless strongly on the point, agreed that some such limitation shouldbe applied for a period of. years.The President of the Board of Trade urged that this question should be determined solely from the point of view of security. Ifany account were to be taken of the advantages of such a restrictionfor British shipbuilding, equal weight must be given to itsdisadvantages for other British industries. If Japan were denieda mercantile marine, she would be driven to balance her payments by a more intensive export drive to the prejudice of other Britishindustries, particularly the textile industries. Unless, therefore,the Cabinet were satisfied that the restriction proposed was essentialon security grounds alone, it would be necessary to balance theinterests of one British industry against another.The Cabinet were informed that the Foreign Secretary badagain considered this question, in the light of the arguments out-lined in CP. (46) 359, but he still adhered to the view which he had expressed at the Cabinefs meeting on 8th March that the balanceof the arguments was against imposing severe restrictions on japanese shipbuilding. If we prevented Japan from building upa merchant navy, we should seriously prejudice her prospect ofestablishing a peace-time economy sufficient to support her popula-tion; we should impose on Allied Governments the burden ofcontributing to her support; we should provoke increased japanese competition for other British industries, notably textiles; and weshould create among the Japanese people a lasting hostility towardsthe Allied Powers.In further discussion it was argued that the prosperity ofBritish industries could not be safeguarded by destroying their competitors in ex-enemy countries; as our experience with germany had already shown, it was impracticable wholly to destroy the war potential  of  ex-enemy  countries without producing condition;
47CM. 84 (46).precluding the re-establishment of a peace-time economy. Safe-guards against the use of heavy industry for warlike purposes mustbe sought through effective arrangements for inspection and control.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of opinion in the Cabinet was against the proposal that,under the United States &quot; assured minimum &quot; scheme, the size ofthe ships which the Japanese shipbuilding industry would beallowed to construct should be limited to 2,000, rather than 5,000,gross tons.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct our representa-tive on the Far Eastern Commission to support theproposal, which was to be put forward by the United states representative, that the assured production capacity level for Japan&apos;s steel shipbuilding industry should be placed at 80,000 gross tons of new construction, of ships notexceeding 5,000 gross tons, and supporting facilities forthe service and repair of a merchant fleet of 1-5 million gross tons.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Lord-President (CP. (46) 364) covering a summary of the technical briefon employment policy which had been prepared for the use of theUnited Kingdom Delegation at the forthcoming discussions withrepresentatives of the Dominions in preparation for the Inter-national Conference on Trade and Employment.The Lord President said that the Departments primarily concerned had collaborated in the preparation of this brief; and theonly point which he need mention to the Cabinet was the extent towhich international monetary organisations should co-operate in giving effect to international policies for full employment. TheAlternate-Governor of the International Monetary Fund had recently suggested that international monetary machinery shouldnot be used for this purpose. The Lord President felt strongly thatthese organisations should co-operate though he endorsed thesuggestion that for tactical reasons it would be inexpedient in theforthcoming discussions to do more than suggest that these inter-national agencies should consider what contribution they could make towards the solution of the problems listed in paragraph 5 (iii)of the note attached to CP. (46) 364.There was general agreement with the Lord President^ view.Other points made in discussion were : (a) The Cabinet were informed that it was the view of theForeign Secretary that in the forthcoming discussions our repre-sentatives should stress the international, rather than the national,aspects of full employment policy. He had particularly in mind the importance of avoiding controversy with the United StatesGovernment on this question.It was pointed out that both aspects of the problem would haveto be discussed, if only because international agreements on thissubject could only be given practical effect in terms of national policies. It was also pointed out that at this first Conference theUnited States Government would not be represented.(b) The International Labour Organisation had given muchthought to the problem of full employment and had collected muchinformation bearing on it. In the forthcoming discussions our representatives should not overlook the possible advantages of associating the International Labour Organisation with any inter-national machinery for promoting full employment.
(c) The Prime Minister suggested that it would be useful ifsmall Committee of Ministers were appointed to keep in touch withthe progress of the international discussions on trade and employ, jment.  This was agreed to.The Cabinet-Took  note  with   approval  of   the  Lord  presidents memorandum (CP. (46) 364).Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,3rd October, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
