<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 256-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1946SECRET.CM. (46)39th conclusions copy No. 4^CABINET 89 (46)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers room at the House of Commons, on Monday, 21st October, 1946, at 4 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health (Item 4).The Right. Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson.M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. F. J. Bellenger,M.P., Secretary of State for War(Items 3-4).The Right Hon. A. Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. G. Tomlinson, M.P.,Minister of Works (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 3-4).The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Mr. J. B. Hynd, M.P., Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster (Items 3-4).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 3-4).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32676-4]b
CABINET 89 (46)Contents.minute no&apos;. Subject. page 1      India    ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      75Establishment of Interim Government.2      Parliament      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      75Business in the House of Commons.Date of Prorogation.3      Germany ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      754      Supply of Timber from Germany    ....      ....      ....      ....      79
India.Establishmentof interim government.(previous reference:CM. (46) 76thConclusions,Minute 8.)1. The Prime Minister said that it had been suggested tohim by the Secretary of State for India that a message should besent to the Viceroy conveying the Cabinets congratulations on thesuccessful achievement of a Coalition Government in India. TheViceroy might also be authorised to read, at the first meeting ofhis new Council, a message of greeting and good wishes from HisMajesty&apos;s Government. The Prime Minister read to the Cabinetthe text of the proposed messages.The Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for India to despatchtelegrams to the Viceroy in the terms of the drafts read to them by the Prime Minister.Parliament.Business inthe House ofCommons.2. The Lord President informed the Cabinet of the business which it was proposed to take in the House of Commons in thefollowing week.The debate on Welsh Affairs would be taken on 28th October.The President of the Board of Trade would open, and the Ministerof Health would reply to, the debate.On 29th and 30th October there would be a debate on the white paper on Central Organisation for Defence. It was agreed thatthe Prime Minister should open this debate, that the Minister ofSupply should speak first on the second day, and that the minister without Portfolio should reply to the debate.The debate on the Press would be taken on 31st October. TheLord President Avould reply to the debate. There would be advan-tages in leaving the decision to a free vote of the House; and theLord President undertook to consider this point.On 1st November progress would be made with legislationreceived from the House of Lords, and certain financial business would also be taken.The Lord President said that he proposed to announce on24th October that it was contemplated that Parliament would beprorogued on 6th November and that the new Session would be opened on 12th November.Germany.(previous reference erence:CM. (46) 80thConclusions,Minute I.)3.   The Cabinet considered the following memoranda: OP. (46) 383 : by the Foreign Secretary, seeking authorityfor the broad lines of policy to be advocated in the discussions on Germany to be held with United States officials in washington and at the November meeting of the Council of Foreign Ministers.OP. (46) 385 : by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the net cost of Germany to the United Kingdom Exchequer.OP. (46) 384 : by the Lord President, suggesting that the planning of the future German economy should be co-co-ordinated with that of the United Kingdom.OP. (46) 392 : by the Minister of Food on the pooling of cerealsupplies to the British and United States Zones.The Foreign Secretary said that the economy of the british zone of Germany had steadily deteriorated, as stocks held at thetime of surrender became exhausted. The population were livingon a very low calory standard and in wretched housing conditions.Too little coal was being retained in the Zone to provide renewalsfor essential plant and allow substantial progress in the repair ofwar damage; and the permitted level of industry was not provingadequate to enable the Zone to pay its own way. It had been increasingly clear for some months that this situation could not beallowed to continue much longer, but it had been difficulthitherto to recommend any drastic alteration on account of political considerations.    It had been necessary to make a determined[32676-4] b 2
attempt to work in concert with the other occupying Powers; butthe Russians had been unwilling to treat Germany as an economicwhole, the Americans had until recently favoured the &apos;&apos; pastbralisation &quot; of Germany, the French had made it their first object tosecure the detachment of the Ruhr and the Rhineland fromGermany, and France and other countries of Western Europe had insisted on obtaining coal from the Ruhr in quantities whichprecluded the restoration of the German economy. The time had now come to take stock of the position afresh. Discussions wereshortly to take place between officials in Washington on the meansof treating the British and United States Zones as an economic unit; and these would be followed by special sessions of the Councilof Foreign Ministers to discuss German questions.A large capital investment would have to be made in the british zone before it could become self-supporting and begin to repay themoney borrowed. He estimated that  250 millions might be needed for the British Zone and  125 millions for the American Zone.He proposed that an endeavour should be made to persuade theUnited States to provide the greater part of this capital. He had set out in CP. (46) 383 the measures of rehabilitation to be taken.We must press for a substantial upward adjustment of the permittedlevel of industry in Germany : it was known that the United Statesand the Russian Governments were in favour of some increase. Itwould also be essential to retain more coal in the British Zone,though he had undertaken that no public announcement to this effect should be made before the French elections in November.And we must be prepared to encourage German exports. TheBritish Zone could not pay its way without enough exports to financeimports, and some relaxation of the present restrictions was inevitable.The Foreign Secretary recommended that it should be our policy to proceed with the socialisation of heavy industries in western Germany and, if the Cabinet agreed, he proposed to makea statement to this effect in the House of Commons on the following day- .   . .        .        . . .,On constitutional questions, while conditions did not yet exist in which a central government could be set up in Germany, he recommonded that it should be our aim that, when- it was set up,it should deal only with certain reserved subjects, and that extensivepowers should be left to the Governments of the Lander. He pro-posed that the British Zone should now be organised in three Lander,namely North Rhine-Westphalia, Schleswig-Holstein, and LowerSaxony. Hamburg and Bremen should each be given anindependent status. Nominated governments should be set up assoon as possible in all the Lander and in Hamburg and Bremen,with instructions to draft constitutions for submission to theirParliaments as soon as these had been elected.In the course of a full discussion the principal points raisedwere as follows : (a) finance the Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to the heavy burden which these proposals would involve for the British taxpayer. The net cost of the British Zone in 1946-47 was nowthought likely to amount to  120 millions, which was the equivalent of Is. in the   on the income tax. The Foreign Secretary estimatedthat, in order to restore the economy of the British and UnitedStates Zones, further expenditure would be required over the next three years amounting to  375 millions. A determined effort mustcertainly be made to persuade the United States Government toassume the larger share of this burden. The Chancellor said thatduring his recent visit to Washington he had suggested that theUnited States Government should assume responsibility for four-fifths of the net expenditure on the two Zones, and the UnitedStates authorities had not finally rejected that suggestion. If, hoff-ever, this expenditure could properly be represented as a capita&apos;investment, he was disposed to suggest that it might be treated as
a loan. The United States might then be asked to find the greaterpart of the money, and some of the countries which had beenneutral in the war might also be asked to make a contribution.The Foreign Secretary pointed out that our net expenditureon Germany would be less if we were not deliberately limiting her economic revival in the interests of our security and the protectionof British industry and exports. It would be interesting if thefinancial benefit accruing to us under both these heads as a resultof our policy towards Germany could be assessed and offset against our expenditure on the British Zone. It would also be reasonable to offset against that expenditure the value which we had obtainedfrom the employment of German prisoners of war in this country.We had always insisted that the value of reparations labour shouldbe debited against the Soviet claim to reparations from Germany.(b) exports the President of the Board of Trade, while agreeing that steps should be taken to increase the total volume of exports fromGermany, suggested that there would be advantages in controlling the destination of those exports. It would be advantageous toBritish export trade if arrangements could be made to use a sub-stantial proportion of Germany&apos;s exports in this country and tosend British products to those countries which would otherwise have taken exports from Germany. There was much that we couldbuy from Germany, as was shown by the fact that a Britishpurchasing agency which had been sent to Germany with authorityto spend up to  10 millions had so far placed orders for only 50,000 worth of goods. It would also be in our interests if theexport of German goods to Eastern Europe could be encouraged.It was agreed that it would be helpful if the suggestions madeby the President of the Board of Trade could be worked out indetail, and if the Board of Trade and Ministry of Supply could also specify what types of German exports could be developed withleast detriment to British industry. This represented the short-term aspect of the proposal put forward in the Lord presidents memorandum (CP. (46) 384) that German industry should be sodeveloped that her exports became complementary to, rather thancompetitive with, British exports. It was desirable that this problem should be examined in detail both from the short-term andthe long-term point of view.As regards the second proposal in the Lord Presidents paper(CP. (46) 384), it was thought unlikely that the British Zone inGermany would be able to make any substantial contribution,during the next few years, of goods required for the economic development and maintenance of the United Kingdom. This partof the Lord Presidents proposals might, however, be considered as part of the long-term problem.(c) Re-equipment of German IndustryThere was general agreement that it would be necessary to import machinery into Germany if the efficiency of her industry wasto be restored without undue delay. We should, however, be careful to avoid finding ourselves in a position where german industry, re-equipped with up-to-date machinery, was in a bettercompetitive position than our own. Thus, it might be better to sendsome of our surplus machine tools to Germany and to import newtools for our own use, rather than to permit the new tools to be imported into Germany.(d) ReparationsThe President of the Board of Trade and the Minister ofSupply urged that there should be early delivery of reparationsplant allocated to this country. This plant was rapidlydeteriorating in Germany and much of it was urgently requiredhere for both civil and defence industries.
The Foreign Secretary explained that the -United states authorities had refused to proceed further with the allocation anddismantling of reparations plant until a decision had been reached on the economic unity of Germany. He proposed that the question should be discussed with them in November. Meanwhile, individualitems of capital equipment which were urgently needed in theUnited Kingdom might be removed from the British Zone.(e) SocialisationThe Cabinet favoured an early declaration that the heavy industries in the British Zone would be socialised. Such a state-ment should strengthen Socialist parties in Europe. It should alsoencourage the Social Democrats in Germany. The ChristianDemocrats had also obtained a considerable number of votes inthe recent elections in Berlin and were likely to be the dominatingparty in two out of three Lander in the British Zone; they would,moreover, be strengthened by fusion with the American Zone, wherethe party was already strong. But there was little doubt that theSocial Democrat Party was the more solidly grounded organisationand a more effective barrier against a revival of Germannationalism.It was important that the socialised industries should be run by the Germans themselves, under supervision. The iron and steelindustry and the coal industry had been vested temporarily in theCommander-in-Chief; and, now that the elections had taken place,it should be possible to hand them over to an appropriate Germanorganisation.(f) CoalAn adequate supply of coal was fundamental to any improve-ment in the economy of the British Zone. Political considerationshad hitherto prevented any considerable reduction in the volumeof coal exports, but&apos; it was hoped that after the French electionsit would be possible to retain a substantially greater proportion ofthe Ruhr coal production for use in Germany.(g) Pooling of Food supplies the Minister of Food drew attention to the prospect of aserious shortage in supplies of cereals to the British Zone over thenext few months.   From October to December, the United States!proposed to ship only 140,000 tons to the British Zone, whereas!425,000 tons were to be sent to the smaller American Zone.   If nolmore was provided for our Zone, rationing there must break down!On the other hand, a supply of 565,000 tons to the two Zones might enable them both to get through the year if it was shared equitablybetween them.  It was important, therefore, that the United StatesGovernment should be induced to agree that this quantity shouldbe divided proportionately between the two Zones.   He did not suggest any addition to the total to be sent to Germany.   TheUnited States Government would argue that we should obtainsupplies for our Zone from Canada, but shipments from Canadawere already behind schedule and supplies could only be diverted to Germany at the expense either of the United Kingdom, wherereduction in the bread ration might then be involved, or of thejBritish Colonies, where already it was only with great difficult]that famine was being avoided.The Foreign Secretary undertook to arrange for urgent representations to be made to the United States Government on this:point.The general conclusion of the Cabinet was that our policy irespect of Germany should now be redirected along the lines recommended in CP. (46) 383. While all agreed that Germany musbe rendered incapable of launching another aggressive war, therhad been a conflict between the other objectives of the Allied power in relation to Germany. On the one hand, her industrial structurwas being crippled by the removal of reparations plant and b
other measures designed to bring immediate advantage to allied countries. On the other hand, it was desired that Germany shouldbe enabled to maintain a tolerable standard of life and that thegreat industrial potentialities of the Ruhr should be used for thebenefit of Europe as a whole. These two objectives could not be wholly reconciled. There could now be little doubt that the emphasis should be on the latter objective, if only on financial grounds. Unless the Allies made a serious attempt to put germany on her feet again, each Zone would remain a continuing charge upon the occupying Power.The Cabinet-(1) Approved in principle the broad lines of policy recom-mended in CP. (46) 383 as a basis for the forthcoming negotiations in Washington and at the Council ofForeign Ministers.(2) Took note that the Foreign Secretary would announce, inhis speech in the House of Commons on the following day, the Governments intention to proceed with the socialisation of heavy industry in Germany.(3) Agreed that officials of the Board of Trade, Foreign Office,Control Office, Ministry of Supply and other Depart-ments concerned should consider the points noted inparagraph (b) above and should prepare a report for submission to the Cabinet after consideration by theappropriate Ministerial Committee; this might, perhaps,be the Committee on Overseas Economic Policy, whichthe Prime Minister was proposing to set up.(4) Invited the Foreign Secretary to make urgent representa-tions to the United States Government that the suppliesof cereals from the United States to the British and united States Zones of Germany during the next threemonths should be pooled, so that a breakdown in the rationing system in the British Zone might be avoided.4. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the lord president (OP. (46) 388) and the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster (OP. (46) 390) regarding the supply of timber fromGermany to the United Kingdom.The Prime Minister suggested that, before this question was further considered by the Cabinet, a preliminary inquiry should beheld to establish the facts. It would be convenient if the cabinet could have before them an agreed statement showing what action had already been taken to obtain adequate supplies of timber fromGermany, what further measures could be taken to secure increased supplies and what would be the cost of those measures, particularlyin terms of other United Kingdom resources.The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster and other ministers directly concerned, to hold an inquiry on thelines suggested by the Prime Minister into the possibilityof increasing the supply of timber from Germany to theUnited Kingdom, and to submit a report for considerationby the Cabinet.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,21st October, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
