<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 302-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE  PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1946SECRET Copy No.CM. (46)94th conclusions cabinet 94 (46)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, 4th November, 1946, at 11 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Sir   Frank   Soskice,   K.C.,   M.P..Solicitor-General (Items 1-6).Mr. H. A. Marquand, M.P., Secretaryfor Overseas Trade (Item 5).The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 5).The  Right  Hon.   Hector   McNeil,M.P., Minister of State (Items 1-6).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P.,     Parliamentary     Secretary,Treasury (Items 7-8).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(Items 1-6).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32746-1]b
CABINET 94 (46)Contents.minute no. .&quot;  . Subject. page 1       United Nations ....       .... -     ....       ....       ....      ....     115Indian Complaint against South Africa.2      War Crimes............................     116Trial of German Industrialists.3      India  .    .....   .   .... .... ;    ....      ..........     - 116Establishment of Interim Government.:4:Vi Palestine .... . &apos;\r&quot;; / ....      ....... &apos; &quot;1175      Import Programme for 1947   ....  ;.  ....       ....       .....    ....     117&apos;6     -Exchange Control Bill ;..........       ....      .... ;   ....     1197      Parliament       ....      .... ....      ........ 121Redistribution of Seats.8  ..   National Day of Remembrance    ......      .........  ,   .....; . 121:
J 1. On 25th October the Cabinet had discussed the complaint to be made by the Government of India at the General Assemblyof the United Nations about the treatment of Indians in SouthAfrica, and had agreed that the United Kingdom Delegation shouldbe instructed to support the view that this matter was one of domestic jurisdiction, which, under Article 2 (7) of the united nations Charter, was not appropriate for discussion by theAssembly. The Delegation had now reported that this view was likely to be opposed by several leading members of the LegalCommittee of the Assembly, and that the Indian case was expectedto find substantial support in the Joint Commission of the Politicaland Legal Committees, to which the matter had been referred. : the attorney-General himself was not convinced that the argument thatthe matter was &quot;essentially within the. domestic jurisdiction&apos;&quot;of South Africa could be sustained. He thought that, if this pointwere referred to it, the International Court of Justice might givea decision adverse to South Africa. The Delegation proposed,unless instructed to the contrary, to support Field-Marshal Smuts&apos;proposal to refer the matter to the International Court, but theywere impressed by the danger that this line would adversely affectthe United Kingdom Government^ relations with India.The Secretary of State for India said that there was very strong-feeling in India about the treatment of Indians in South Africa.If our representatives at the General Assembly took a line whichwas regarded as unfavourable to the Indian case there would be serious repercussions in India. He still considered that they shouldbe instructed to remain as completely neutral as they could, notonly on the merits, but also on the legal issue whether the matter was one in which the United Nations was competent to intervene.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that, as a leading member of the United Nations, we could not remain neutralon the question of jurisdiction. And from the point of view of theBritish Commonwealth, it was important to secure a decision thata matter of this kind was outside the jurisdiction of the united nations. If our view on this point was not accepted by theAssembly, we should argue that the International Court of Justiceshould be invited to give a ruling.Other Ministers spoke in support of this view. The point a tissue was not the merits of the Indian case, on which there mightbe two opinions, but the expediency of its being discussed by theUnited Nations. Ministers, thought it most important to avoidsetting a precedent for intervention by the United Nations: inmatters like this, which had hitherto been regarded as within the domestic jurisdiction of sovereign States. Once such interventionbegan, it would be difficult to set limits to it. Other governments should see the weight of this argument. Thus, the United StatesGovernment would hardly welcome discussion by the United nations of the rights of negroes in the United States. &apos; And in India, itselfthere were questions of differential treatment between differentcommimities which the Government of India would not wish to have discussed by the General Assembly.The Secretary of State for India said that, in spite of these considerations, he would have preferred that our Delegation shouldtake no part in the discussion of this ;matter at the general assembly.The Cabinet-Reaffirmed their earlier decision that the United kingdom delegation at the General Assembly should express noopinion on the merits of the question, but should supportthe view that this was a matter of domestic jurisdiction,which, under Article 2 (7) of the United Nations Charter,was not appropriate for discussion at the Assembly. Ifthis view was not accepted, they should support the claim that the question of jurisdiction should be referred for-1] b 2
decision by the International Court of Justice. our delegation should be made aware of the probablerepercussions on India herself and on other parts of theBritish Commonwealth if it were held that the united nations was competent to intervene in matters of this kind.2. The Prime Minister recalled that at an earlier stage ithad been contemplated that there should be a second internationaltrial of war criminals at which a number of German industrialistswould be indicted. It was now known that the United states authorities were opposed to this suggestion, and it might be assumed that a second international trial would not be held. The UnitedStates authorities were, however, proposing themselves to holdtrials of war criminals in the United States Zone; and they had asked us to surrender to them for trial five German industrialistsnow in the British Zone. It could be argued that, as we did not wish a second international trial to be held and did not ourselvespropose to try these men as war criminals, it would be convenient for us to surrender them to the Americans on the understandingthat they would try them swiftly and that a British observer wouldbe present. On the other hand, we should thereby be setting a precedent which might prove inconvenient if at a later stage theSoviet Government asked us to surrender someone who, in our view,was unlikely to get a fair trial in the Soviet Zone.Discussion showed that it was the view of the Cabinet thatwe should do nothing to support the holding of a secondinternational trial and, in general, should advocate a policy ofdiscontinuing trials for war crimes. At the same time it was important that we should not appear to be sheltering Germanindustrialists whom the United States authorities were anxious toput on trial. Any later demands for the surrender of war criminalsto other occupying Powers could be dealt with as they arose.The Cabinet Agreed that the Commander-in-Chief of the British zone in Germany should be authorised to surrender to theUnited States authorities the five German industrialistswhom they desired to put on trial in the United StatesZone as war criminals.War Crimes.(previous reference:CM. (46) 85thConclusions,Minute 4.)Trial ofGermanIndustrialists.India. 3.   The Secretary of State for India said that the MarquessEstablishment of Salisbury proposed to ask, by Private Notice Question in theof Interim House of Lords on the following day, that a White Paper shouldGovernment. be issued on developments in India since last July. He had it in(Previous mind, apparently, that the Paper should set out the correspondenceReference: and negotiations leading up to the formation of the InterimCM. (46) 89th   Government.Conclusions, The Secretary of  State  said that certain  parts  of  this minute 1.) correspondence had been published locally on the initiative of theIndian leaders themselves, and it would be difficult to refuse to make this available here. At the same time, it would be inexpedient to publish all the correspondence or to give a full account of thenegotiations.It was the view of the Cabinet that this request should be refused. In the course of the formation of any Coalition Govern-ment there were bound to be exchanges, both verbal and written,which could not advantageously be made public at any rate whilethat Government remained in office. This consideration shouldsatisfy the House of Lords.The Cabinet- ..Invited the Secretary of State for India to resist therequest for the publication by His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom of a full account of the negotia-tions leading to the establishment of the Interim Govern-ment in India.
Palestine. ...(previous reference:CM. (46) 91stConclusions,Minute 2.)ImportProgrammefor 1957.(previous reference:CM. (46) 68thConclusions,Minute 3.)4. \ At the Cabinet Is meeting on 25th October, the Secretaryof State for, the Colonies had referred to the possibility that theJewish Agency would make a public declaration dissociatingthemselves from terrorist activities in Palestine and had suggestedthat, if such a declaration were, made, it would be expedient to release the Jewish leaders who had been held in detention inPalestine since 29th June.The Cabinet now had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies (CP. (46) 414) reporting theresolutions adopted by the Inner Zionist Council on 29th October.One of these denounced terrorism and called1 upon the jewish community in Palestine to deny all assistance and support to theextreme terrorist groups.V TheSecretary ofState for the Colonies said that the resolu-tions as a whole were not as satisfactory as could have been wished;but in this particular resolution the Council had;taken a courageousstand against terrorism, which had been reinforced in public speeches subsequently made by senior members of the jewish agency. There were signs that representative Jewish institutions in Palestine were now anxious to re-educate the Jewish communitytowards a disavowal of violence. The Jewish leaders could not be detained indefinitely without trial: the resolution adopted by theCouncil provided a logical ground for authorising their release :and, if this opportunity were not taken, another might not occurfor some.time. He therefore proposed that the, High commissioner should be authorised to release the detained J wish leaders on 5th November. Authority should also be given for the release ofthree Palestinian Arabs now detained in the Seychelles and for thereturn to Palestine of two others who had been released from theSeychelles on health grounds but had hitherto been excluded from palestine. These decisions, if approved by the Cabinet, would be announced Simultaneously in Jerusalem and in a statement in theHouse of Commons.The Cabinet Approved the proposals put forward in CP. (46) 414 forthe release of the Jewish leaders detained in Palestine, andfor the release and readmission to Palestine of certainPalestinian Arabs who had been detained in theSeychelles.5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the lord president (CP. (46) 401) covering a report by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer on the import programme for 1947. This report had been approved by the Ministerial Committee on economic planning, subject to the points noted in paragraphs 2 and 3 of theLord Presidents covering memorandum about (i) the continuanceof petrol rationing, and (ii) the need for further study of the extentto which buyers of our exports could be required to pay for them ingoods or convertible currencies.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he must impress upon his colleagues the extreme gravity of the situation with whichthe Government would be faced unless drastic action were taken toimprove our overseas balance. On account of the delayed effect ofthe feeding-stuffs crisis in 1946, the rise in American prices andthe heavy rate of military and political expenditure overseas, wewere exhausting far too rapidly the loans from the United Statesand Canada and our other prospective resources of external finance for 1947 and 1948. 1 We had been buying too much, and not sellingenough, in the hard-currency countries (North America, sweden and the Argentine). From July 1947 onwards, sterling would beconvertible for the purpose of current transactions; and the currency of many of the European countries to which we wereselling would not be convertible. With the hard-currency countries,therefore, we should have an adverse balance, against which we[32746-1]b 3
should not be able to offset a favourable trade balance with theseEuropean countries. If present tendencies remained uncheckedwe should find ourselves, by 1949, if not earlier, unable to pay our way without imposing such drastic cuts on imports as wouldutterly discredit the Government. This situation must be avertedby a programme of vigorous action under three heads : First, we must practise a strict economy in imports from hard-currency countries. With this object in view the Treasury had drawn up the import programme for 1947 set out in paragraph 18of Appendix B to CP. (4(5) 401. The Chancellor proposed thatthis should be approved, subject to an increase of  10 million in theprogramme of supplementary food imports.Secondly, there should be no relaxation in the export drive;and the export target for the second half of 1947 should be fixed at 150 per cent, of 1938 exports in terms of volume.Thirdly, the Treasury should at once undertake, in consultationwith the other Departments concerned, an intensive study of theprospects of improving the trade balance in the period 1947-50 by (i) developing exports to hard-currency countries, if necessary Iat the expense of exports to other countries;(ii) developing alternative sources of imports in the sterling Iarea and in Europe;(iii) examining home food production with a view to reducingdollar expenditure on food;(iv) reviewing oil policy with a view to reducing dollar expenditure on oil; and(v) considering how far buyers of our exports could be Srequired to pay  for them  in goods or  convertible Icurrencies.In general discussion, the Minister of Fuel and Power saidthat there were some factors in the situation which might havethe result that the eventual outcome would not be so- grave as had been suggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. Our overseasbalance was at present disturbing mainly in respect of dollar countries.   The main cause of this was the increase in the level of \United States prices, which was largely due to the action of the united States Government in abandoning price control.   It waspossible that the level of prices in the United States might drop.Another important factor was the high level of our military and \political expenditure overseas.   Was it not conceivable that this might be substantially reduced, both in total and in the proportionrepresenting dollar expenditure ?   Again, the calculations in the memorandum assumed a reduction in the value of our invisibleexports.   These consisted largely of shipping earnings.   Was it not jconceivable that these might rise rather than fall as time went on ? !Discussion then turned on the proposal that petrol rationingshould be continued.IThe Minister of Fuel and Power said that the additional Iimports required to enable him to abolish petrol rationing repre-sen ted an expenditure of $30 million a year.  Against the generalbackground of possible changes in our overseas balance this was a Irelatively small additional expenditure.   He attached importanceto the early abolition of petrol rationing.   There was already aconsiderable amount of evasion and it was impracticable to tightenup the administration of the rationing scheme.   A breakdown of Ipetrol   rationing   might   undermine   public    confidence    and Ico-operation in other rationing schemes and bring into disrepute Ithe whole structure of the economic controls.    When he had I proposed the abolition of petrol rationing in July last (CM. (46) I66th Conclusions, Minute 7), the Cabinet had been impressed withthe argument that without petrol rationing it would be difficult to jensure the equitable distribution of tyres.   No difficulty was now Iraised on that score.   Ministers had also been warned that the 1Governments of Australia and New Zealand would press for the pabolition of petrol rationing in these countries.   New Zealand&apos;s Iposition had been met; but the Australians were now asking for an I
119CM. 94 (46)additional annual supply of 6 million gallons of petrol in order toenable them to abolish rationing.Discussion showed that it was the general view of the Cabinetthat, in the circumstances described by the Chancellor of theExchequer, petrol rationing in this country must be continued forthe time being. In view, however, of the extent to which the rationing scheme was being evaded, it was desirable that it shouldbe brought to an end as soon as practicable; and, in the review of oil policy proposed by the Chancellor among his remedial measures,a determined effort should be made to find means of influencingworld supplies and consumption of petrol so as to permit the earlyabolition of rationing in this country.Other points made in the discussion were : (a) The proposed imports of films in 1947 represented an expenditure of  17 million in hard-currency countries. Would it not be possible to reduce this by promoting increased productionof British films?The Prime Minister said that he would be glad if the Presidentof the Board of Trade would let him have a special report on thispoint.(b) Would it be possible to restrict overseas expenditure bytourists? The expenditure on imported films represented only 8s.per head per year, while tourists were now allowed to spend  75per head per year.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had resistedheavy pressure for a higher allowance than  75. This was, however,a point which he would continue to watch.(c) Early warning should be given to the public of theconsequences to our economy of failure to redress our balance ofpayments. While it would be impracticable to publish the fullstatistical picture set out in CP. (46) 401, every effort should bemade to bring the main facts home to the public, both as a spur to production and as an explanation of the continuing restrictions on imports.The Cabinefs conclusions were as follows (1) The import programme for 1947 should be as set out inparagraphs 14-18 of Appendix B to CP. (46) 401,subject to an increase of  10 millions in the programmeof supplementary food imports.(2) The export target for the second half of 1947 should be provisionally set at 150 per cent, of 1938 exports in termsof volume.(3) Petrol rationing in the United Kingdom should becontinued for the present, subject to the results of thespecial review of oil policy to be undertaken in pursuanceof Conclusion (4) below.(4) The Treasury should arrange, in consultation with theother Departments concerned, for an immediate studyto be made of the remedial measures described in sub-paragraphs (i)-(v) above.(5) The Chancellor of the Exchequer should consider how the broad facts of our overseas balance could best be presented to the public.6.   The Cabinet had before them : CP. (46) 411 : a memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer covering a draft Exchange Control Bill and a proof of an explanatory White Paper which it was proposed to publish simultaneously with the Bill; and cp. (46) 410 : a memorandum by the Solicitor-Generaldrawing attention to certain features of the Bill which were likely to excite criticism.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the main principlesof the Bill had been accepted by the Lord Presidents Committeeand the draft approved by the Legislation Committee. The Billcontained extremely wide and drastic powers; but the Solicitor-General, his own advisers in the Treasury and the Bank of England,and the Director of Public Prosecutions were all agreed that without such powers, the operation of which could be varied at short notice by order, the Government would not have a sufficientlyflexible instrument to counter the attempts at. evasion which would undoubtedly be made, and would be handicapped in their efforts to tackle the grave problem of the overseas balance to which he had drawn attention in the discussion recorded in the preceding Minute.Similar powers had been available for the last seven years underthe Defence (Finance) Regulations, and there had been no seriouscomplaints about the way in which they had been used.The Solicitor-General said that, although he had thought it right to draw attention to certain features of the Bill which wouldexcite criticism in Parliament and would not be liked by the Courts,he agreed that the control could not be enforced with powers lessstringent than those proposed in the Bill.The Home Secretary said that during the discussion in theLegislation Committee he had criticised certain provisions of theBill on the ground that the courts would be disposed to put the narrowest possible construction on the language used. Having gone into the matter further, he was now satisfied that there was no alternative to including these provisions in the Bill.The Lord Chancellor said that he could recall no peace-timelegislation containing such drastic powers, but he believed that theBill could be justified by reference to the difficulties of our overseasbalance in the next few years. The Chancellor of the Exchequermight consider whether he could not meet some of the opposition by providing for the appointment of an advisory body, on the analogy of the Consumers&apos; Councils under the Coal Industry NationalisationAct and the Central Health Services Council under the national health Service Bill, with the function of presenting an annual report on the exercise of the powers conferred by the Bill.In further discussion, attention was drawn to the difficultieslikely to be encountered in securing the Bill&apos;s passage through theHouse of Lords, and to the desirability of ensuring that its objectswere not misunderstood in the United States.The Chancellor -of the Exchequer said that he would considerthe suggestions which had been made in the discussion. He hadalready arranged to give advance information about the Bill to theSecretary of the United States Treasury, and he would see that thearguments in favour of this legislation were properly presented inthe Press when it was published.The Cabinet-(1) Approved, the draft Exchange Control Bill and agreed thata White Paper in the form of the proof annexed to cp; (46) 411 should be published simultaneously with&apos; the Bill.(2) Took note that, before the publication of the Bill, theChancellor of the Exchequer would seek an opportunityof giving the public a general picture of the overseasfinancial situation in relation to the powers sought inthe Bill. i,;
121CM. 94 (46)Parliament. 7,   The Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum by the redistribution Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for Scotland (CP.0f Seats. (46) 407) proposing that legislation should be introduced to amend(Previous the Third Schedule of the House of Commons (Redistibution ofBeferenoe: Seats) Act, 1944, so as to give the Boundary Commissions wider\V.M.(44)lllth discretion to preserve existing local government areas in carryingout the redistribution of seats.The Home Secretary said that the provisional recommendationsof the Boundary Commissions, which were based on the applicationof the rules in the Third Schedule, had been widely criticised onthe ground that, in order to obtain the correct mathematical results,the Boundary Commissions had had to dismember constituencieswhich were bound together either by existing administrative arrangements or by historical ties. He had discussed the matterinformally with the Speaker and the Deputy Chairman of the boundary Commission for England, and he understood that the commissions would welcome a wider discretion to preserve the integrity of existing local government areas. He therefore hopedthat the Cabinet would authorise him to introduce an amending bill at an early date. Once this had been passed, the boundary commissions would have to be asked to make a fresh review of constituencies, and he proposed that this review should be basedon the distribution of the electorate shown in the register published on 15th October, 1946, and should be completed in time to enable aRedistibution Bill to be introduced early in the 1947-48 Session.Meanwhile, it was desirable that the enquiries which were nowbeing held into the objections made to the published recommenda-tions of the Boundary Commissions should be stopped, and for thispurpose he desired to make a very early statement of the Govern-ment&apos;s intentions.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury said that theproposals in OP. (46) 407 would be welcomed by all parties inParliament.The Cabinet-Approved the preparation of a Bill to amend the Houseof Commons (Redistribution of Seats) Act, 1944.. on thelines proposed in CP. (46) 407; and authorised the HomeSecretary to announce, immediately after the opening ofthe new Session of Parliament, that the government intended to introduce such legislation at an early date.NationalDay ofRemembrance.(previous reference:CM. (46) 9thConclusions,Minute 6.)8. The Prime Minister said that he hoped that those membersof the Cabinet who had not already intimated that they would be present at the ceremony at the Cenotaph on 10th November wouldmake a special effort to attend.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,4th November, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
