<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 336-345</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY  OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1946SECRETCM. (46)98th conclusions copy No.CABINET 98 (46)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,&apos;   &apos;! on Tuesday^ 19tk November, 1946, at 11 a.m.A n4 6The Right Hon.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.Chancellor.Lord Jowitt, lord the RightSecretaryAffairs.The Right Hon M.P., secretary colonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Be van, M.P.Minister of Health.Present:C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. G. A.Minister of labour service.The Right Hon M.P., minister the Right Hon.Minister    of fisheries.Hon. Viscount Addison,of   State  for  DominionA. Creech j ones,of  State  for  theIsaacs, M.P.,and NationalEllen &quot;Wilkinson,of Education.T. Williams, M.P.,Agriculture     andThe Right Hon.M.P., Minister(Item 4).The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Works (Item 4).The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Minister of State (Items 1-3)..Sir   Frank   Soskice,   K.C.,   M.P.,Solicitor-General (Item 3).The following were also presentAlfred Barnes,of     transport the Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.The Right Hon. the Earl of Listowel,Postmaster-General (Item 6).Mr. J. B. Hynd, M.P., Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster (Item 3).Mr. William Leonard, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofSupply (Item 4).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under -Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-3).Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32768-2]b
CABINET 98 (46)minute no.1245Contents.!&apos;&quot;.&apos; i.&apos;\     * &apos;.\&apos;.&apos;&apos;V0 Yi &apos; IJ f. &apos;\ V-- &quot;Ay1!&apos;-&apos;&apos; A V-i ,.&apos;,o    ) &apos;:;.:A&apos;v &apos;\ (i ; &apos;Subject.      -iDutch East IndiesFood     ......................Butter for Canada.Germany....      ....Future of the Ruhr Industries.Fuel Supplies for Industry  ....Coal      ....Publicity Campaign for Increased Production.IndiaCompensation for Members of Indian Services.Page147147148149151162
pntoh east indies.(previous reference erence  :CM. (46) 29thConclusions,jlinute 2.)1. The Minister of State informed the Cabinet that agreement&quot;had been reached in Batavia between the Commissioners of theNetherlands Government and the Indonesian leaders. TheCommissioners Were leaving for Holland on 22nd November, andthere was reason to hope that the agreement would be ratifiedwithout delay by the Netherlands Government and Parliament.Both parties to the discussions in Batavia had expressed their appreciation of our good offices in furthering a settlement.The Prime Minister said that he had sent a message of congratulation to Lord Killearn on the successful outcome of thenegotiations. He proposed to send a similar message to LordInverchapel, in recognition of the valuable services which he hadrendered in the earlier stages of the discussions.The Minister of Food said that he was anxious to open withoutdelay negotiations for the purchase of food from the Dutch east indies. The Minister of State undertook to inform him as soon aspossible how such negotiations could best be commenced.2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and the Minister of Food (CP. (46) 426)regarding a proposal that 5,500 tons of Australian and NewZealand butter should be diverted from this country to Canada.The Cabinet were informed that this proposal was beingstrongly pressed by the Canadian authorities, who argued that their current shortage of butter was due to their efforts to supply theUnited Kingdom with cheese. If they failed to obtain these additional supplies their weekly butter ration would have to bereduced, until April next, from:6 ozs. to 4 ozs. Though the weeklybutter ration in this country was now only 3 ozs., this was supple-mented by 3 ozs. of margarine; and this total ration of 6 ozs. ofedible fats compared with a 6-oz. butter ration in Canada, where no margarine was supplied. The, Canadians had, however,unrationed supplies of cooking fats, as compared with the weeklyration of only 1 oz. in this country. .The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the main difficulty, about this proposal was its possible effect on futuresupplies of butter from Australia and New Zealand, who weremaintaining butter rationing for the specific purpose of meeting this country&apos;s needs. If, because we appeared to be able to sparesome of our butter for Canada, these Dominions ceased to rationtheir own butter consumption, we should lose a supply of about40,000 tons a year: , It was important, therefore, that the Canadianproposal should not be adopted unless the full agreement ofAustralia and New Zealand could first be obtained.The Minister of Food endorsed this view. So far as concerned the United Kingdom the immediate effect of diverting these supplies to Canada would be to reduce stocks, not to reduce the weeklyration; and he would be prepared to take the risk of reducing hisstocks if he were satisfied that future supplies from Australia andNew Zealand would not be prejudiced. He depended so largely onthe Canadians for other food-stuffs that he was anxious, if at allpossible, to meet them over this request. The Canadians should joinus. in seeking to obtain: the willing concurrence of Australia andNew Zealand in this proposed diversion; but he recommendedthat, if this could be obtained, the diversion should be made. Hewould try to persuade Canada, in return, to increase her suppliesof cooking, fats to this country;The Cabinet-Authorised the Secretary of State,for Dominion affairs and the Minister of Food to open discussions with the High1 Commissioners of Canada, Australia; and New Zealandwith a view to securing the concurrence of the Govern-ments of Australia and New Zealand in an arrangement whereby 5,500 tons of butter would be diverted from thiscountry to Canada.[32768-2]
Germany. 3.   On 29th October the Cabinet had decided that the principalFuture of        industries of the Ruhr should be socialised and placed underilie .Ruhr        German ownership. They now had before them a memorandum, pre.Industries.       pared by the Minister of State in consultation with the Chancellor(Previous        of the Duchy of Lancaster (OP. (46) 422), on the practical meansReference:       of giving effect to this decision.    The memorandum discussed-C.M.(46)92nd    (a) the general plan of action and the legal issues involved in it-Conclusions,     (b) whether responsibility for the socialised industries should restMinute 3.)       with the Government of the North Rhine-Westphalia Land or witha central German Government; and (c).whether foreign observersshould be appointed to assist the Commander-in-Chief in the controlof the industries. ,jThe Cabinet first discussed the: general plan of action proposedin paragraphs 4 to 10 and 13 of the memorandum.The Minister of. State said that it was proposed to proceed in three stages. In stage A the custody of all the industrial assets which were at present held by the Commander-in-Chief would betransferred to German custodians appointed by him. This stepcould be taken immediately, and would not affect existing rights and liabilities in the undertakings. In stage B German corporations, would be established to which the ownership of the inclustrieswouldbe transferred. This transfer would not take place until some time after the elections to be held in the North Rhine-Westphalia Land. in. the spring. Meanwhile, a detailed study would be made of thelegal complexities of the transfer of ownership in each industry.Stage C would begin when British occupation of the Ruhrended and a scheme of international control of the Ruhr industrieswas introduced. The powers of the British Zone Commander wouldthen devolve on the international controlling authority.The Lord Chancellor and the Solicitor-General agreed that&apos;      under this modified plan no legal difficulties would arise in stage A,when there would be no more than a transfer of custody.   Therewould be further time to study the legal problems involved in thetransfer of ownership in stage B.On the question whether the German corporations should beresponsible to the Government of the North Rhine-Westphalia Landor to a central Government, the Minister of State said that he andthe Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster took different views. Hehad ascertained that the Foreign Secretary was strongly in favourof conferring responsibility on the Land Government. Of thereasons summarised in paragraph 11 of OP. (46) 422, the foreign secretary attached special importance to those based on considera-tions of security and of conformity with the general policy offurthering political decentralisation in Germany. He was alsoinfluenced by the fact, that the French would be strongly opposedto any policy which implied that the Ruhr industries were to beintegrated with the rest of the German economy.,The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster argued that suchmajor national assets as the Ruhr industries should be owned bythe German community as a whole rather than by one localisedsection of it. If the Land Government owned the industries, itwould be put in a privileged position and would have great powerto exploit that position.   The right course, in his view, was to&apos; secure that the financial benefits and liabilities of these industries were shared by the whole of the German economy. Moreover, therewas the practical consideration that the predominant party in theNorth Rhine-Westphalia Land was by no means wholeheartedly iofavour of the socialisation of industry.   For all these reasons he. considered that means should be devised of making the corporationsresponsible to all the three Land Governments.&apos;    % The Cabinet were impressed by the weight of the arguments against: making the corporations responsible to one Land Govern-ment. Though all these industries were situated in one Land, theywere an asset of immense value and.were vital to the recovery ofthe whole Zone.   The underlying principle was that they should
be owned by the whole German people, and responsibility for them should therefore be as widely based as possible.On the other hand, the practical difficulties of a wider basisof responsibility than the Land Government were considerable.There was not at present any Zonal Government, and there were strong arguments against creating one. Thus, the boundaries ofthe Zone were not natural boundaries and a Zonal Governmentwould be an artificial creation hardly likely to be permanent. Itwould, moreover, be difficult to reconcile with the policy of fusionwith the United States Zone, and it might also be held to imply that we had abandoned any idea of a central Government ofGermany.If, however, there was to be no Zonal Government to which the corporations could be responsible, what alternative arrangements could be made? Apart from the individual Land Governmentsthere was no representative German body from which the corpora-tions could derive their legal powers; and these would have to be derived from the Commander-in-Chief.The Cabinet took the view that, while it was possible to lay down now the principle that the industries should be held on behalfof the German people, it was not yet possible to proceed with thetransfer of ownership. Their conclusion, therefore, was that action should be limited for the moment to that proposed for stage A,Le., the appointment of custodians. Decisions on the means ofestablishing corporations and transferring ownership could be deferred until after the forthcoming negotiations on the future ofGermany, when the form of Governmental organisation in theBritish Zone might be clearer. In these circumstances, thequestion of the appointment of foreign observers (paragraph 14 of cp. (46) 422) did not arise.The appointment of custodians was an important step forward.While their powers would not be founded, on any German legisla-tion, but would be derived solely from ordinances passed by theCommander-in-Chief, their appointment would be an earnest of thedirection in which future progress was to be made. All the threeLand Governments should be consulted about the choice ofcustodians, though their role would be to make recommendations and the final appointments would be made by the Commander-in-Chief with the approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government. TheCabinet should be consulted before the appointments were actuallymade.The Cabinet- .(1) Agreed that as a first step German custodians should beappointed who would hold the custody of the assets of the principal industries of the Ruhr..    (2) Took note that the Prime Minister would consider how the consultations with the Land Governments about the selection of custodians could best be carried out; andthat the recommendations would be submitted to theCabinet before the appointments were finally made.(3), Agreed to defer for the present decisions on the means of, establishing corporations to manage the Ruhr industries and of transferring the ownership to German hands.4. The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda on fuel supplies for industry - CP. (46) 419 : by the Minister of Fuel and Power, covering a scheme for fuel rationing prepared by officials of his Depart-ment and the Board of Trade, after consultation with theNational Production Advisory Council for Industry;CP. (46) 423 : by the Minister of Fuel and Power, out-lining an ; alternative scheme which the Minister himselffavoured; and cp. (46) 427 : by the Minister of Supply, asking that theiron and steel industry should be given all the coal required formaximum production during the period up to 30th April, 1947.
The Minister of Fuel and Power said that, although he halltaken part in the discussions leading to the submission of the scheme&apos;annexed to CP. (46) 419, he felt that this scheme was open to serioufcriticism, and be had, therefore, put forward the alternative prolposals summarised in paragraphs 7 and 8 of CP. (46) 423. F0ficoal, he proposed that, instead of reductions in the allocations, thereshould be cuts in the actual deliveries made against those allocaitions. This would avoid the need for any public announcement about the cuts. For gas and electricity, he proposed that the directtions to be issued should require that weekly consumption in the foufmonths December 1946 to March 1947 should not exceed the averagweekly consumption in November. He also proposed that deliverieof coal to hotels, clubs and places of amusement should be cut by!10 per cent, and that the direction restricting the consumption offgas and electricity should also apply to them. This alternative!scheme would produce larger economies and would also give the!maximum flexibility of administration so that full advantage couldlbe taken of any improvement in the output of coal and special!consideration could be given to the claims of expanding industries^The President of the Board of Trade pointed out that, as the]scheme annexed to CP. (46) 419 had been discussed with the1National Production Advisory Council for Industry, the council would have to be consulted before the alternative scheme now suggested by the Minister of Fuel and Power was adopted.Industry must know on what basis to plan for the forthcoming sixmonths, and the proposal to impose a percentage cut on allocationsgave industry such a basis. The alternative of cutting deliveries,which at present fell short of allocations to a widely varying extentfrom district to district, would involve an inequitable and unprecedented-dictable distribution of the short-fall; and, if the proposal to cutcertain industries by 12^ per cent, were abandoned, there would beno assurance of any reserve from which additional supplies couldbe made to firms which had special claims. The proposal to basethe cuts in gas and electricity on the average weekly consumptionduring November took no account of the needs of industries (e.g.,new factories in the development areas or factories which had recently switched over from war to peace production) where fuelconsumption was expanding. It was true that the scheme annexed to CP. (46) 419 left it to individual firms to make an estimate oftheir probable consumption during the coming months, but a plan of this kind had been worked successfully during the war. For these reasons he still favoured the scheme already discussed with theNational Production Advisory Council for Industry.Points in discussion were : (a) The Cabinet were informed that the Minister of Supplysupported the scheme for. coal proposed in CP. (46) 419 on theground that it Would enable firms to plan ahead economies involvingno loss of production. As regards gas and electricity, he preferredproposals relating future consumption to some definite standard,but he doubted whether the average weekly consumption inNovember would be a suitable basis and suggested that the proposeddirections should allow for adjustments to cover cases where theaverage consumption in December 1945 to March 1946 was morethan 10 per cent, above that in November 1945 and to allow forsome modifications in January 1947 where the pegging of consump-tion in December 1946 to the November basis had proved to bedisproportionate to requirements.(b) The Minister of Transport said that he favoured the scheme proposed in CP. (46) 419. He could not accept the statement inparagraph 2 of CP. (46) 423 that there had been a breakdown inthe transport of coal by rail.(c) The Minister of Works said that the imposition of a 5 percent, cut in either allocations or deliveries of coal to the building materials industries would have a disastrous effect on the expansionof these industries, which Avas necessary to meet the demands of the
housing programme: In most of these industries the fuel consumedwas used directly for production and there was little or no scope for economising in space heating. Thus, even a 5 per cent, cutwould have very serious effect. In brick production the amount of fuel used varied widely from one works to another and it wouldbe more economical to close down some works altogether than toimpose a uniform cut on all. He asked that the building materialsindustries should be wholly exempt from the scheme. If, however,any cuts were to be imposed on these industries, the Ministry ofWorks should be consulted about their application in order that theeffect on production might be minimised.The Minister of Health endorsed these views. The output ofbuilding materials was already dangerously low and the proposedcuts in fuel would involve a complete readjustment of the housing programmes of local authorities. If the cuts were to be made apublic announcement would have to be made about their effect on housing.(d) The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries said that theproposed cut in fuel would prejudice the production of agricultural machinery.(e) The Minister of [Labour and National Service urged that,whatever scheme was adopted, special consideration should be paidto the needs of firms in the development areas, since it was in these areas that cuts in fuel supplies would be most liable to causeunemployment.(/) The Lord President said, that there might be advantage in adopting the alternative proposals put forward by the Minister of fuel and Power, provided that the National Production AdvisoryCouncil for Industry were consulted about them. As regards gasand electricity, there should be some provision for allowingindividual firms who could make out a good case to consume morethan the average weekly consumption in November, and the standardmeter&quot; reading adopted as a basis should be that of the weekpreceding publication of the proposed direction in order to preventfirms from being excessively extravagant in the critical week.While he agreed that the steel industry should continue to be exempt from cuts, he felt that the Minister of Supply should seek tosecure fuel economies through greater use of scrap iron in placeof pig iron.(g) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, whatever plan was adopted, it should be brought into operation forthwith andshould have the necessary flexibility to allow for the expandingneeds of developing industries.The Minister of Fuel and, Power suggested that he should discuss with the National Production Advisory Council for industry a scheme based on the alternative proposals outlined in cp. (46) 423. He was satisfied that a scheme on these lines couldbe administered with sufficient flexibility to enable him to meet the reasonable needs of the building materials industries and otherindustries with expanding requirements.The Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Fuel and Power, in consultationwith the President of the Board of Trade, to discuss withthe National Production Advisory Council for industry at a very early date a fuel economy scheme on the lines indicated in paragraphs 7 and 8 of CP. (46) 423.5. The Lord President said that the Minister of Fuel and power and he had drawn up a scheme for a publicity campaign toincrease coal production. It was important that this scheme shouldbe brought into operation as soon as possible and he hoped that theChancellor of the Exchequer would agree that the cost should beborne by the Ministry of Fuel and Power for a period of, say, four
months until arrangements could be made for the National Coal IBoard to take over responsibility for the scheme.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would prefer thatthe National Coal Board should assume financial liability for the Ischeme from 1st January, 1947, when the mines would be vested inthe Board.The Cabinet-Approved the proposal to bring into operation forthwitha publicity campaign for increased coal production; and invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to discuss with theLord President and the Minister of Fuel and Powerwhether some financial adjustment might be made to cover the period between 1st January and the date when theNational Coal Board took over the responsibility for administering the scheme.India.Compensationfor Membersof IndianServices.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for India (CP. (46) 424) on the scales of compensation for loss of career and prospects to be paid to members of the IndianServices when their appointments under the Secretary of State wereterminated as a result of constitutional changes. The cost of theseproposals, which was estimated at about  10 million, would fall on indian revenues.The Cabinet-Approved the scales of compensation annexed to cp. (46) 424, and authorised the Secretary of State forIndia to invite the Viceroy to lay them before the interim government in India.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,,    19th November, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
