<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/6/0 images: 384-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(IIS DOCUMENT IB THE  PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1946SECRET Copy No.   4CM. (46)104th conclusions cabinet 104 (46)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 10th December, 1946, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power(Items 1-6).The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Hall, FirstLord of the Admiralty (Item 5).The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport (Item 5).The Right Hon. Hector McNeil,M.P., Minister of State.Mr. J. W. Belcher, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Board of Trade(Item 6).The Right Hon. F. J. Bellenger, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (items-7).The Right Hon. The Earl of listowel, Postmaster-General(Items 3-4).Mr. J. B. Hynd, M.P., Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster (Items 6-7).Sir Orme Sargent, Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.Admiral Sir John H. D. Cunningham,First Sea Lord and Chief of naval staff (Item 5).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. C. G. Eastwood.[32878-2]
CABINET 104 (46)minute no.123456789Contents.Subject.Foreign Affairs ....Egypt.Persia.Spain.United Nations....Disclosure of Strengths of Armed Forces.IndiaConstitutional Position.Burma   ....Constitutional Position.PalestineIllegal Immigration.Germany....Exports of Coal from the British Zone.Displaced PersonsDisposal of Royalist Yugoslavs in British ZoneSarawak....Civic RestaurantsSupply of Intoxicating Liquor.of Germany.Page.187187188189190191191192193
foreign affaire.Egypt.(previous reference:CM. (46)97thConclusions,Minute 1.)Persia.(previous reference:CM. (46) 52ndConclusions,Minute 1.)Spain.(previous reference:C.M.(46)97thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The Prime Minister drew the Cabinet&apos;s attention to thestatement which had been issued from the Foreign Office on theprevious day about the interpretation of the Sudan Protocol to theAnglo-Egyptian Treaty. There were indications that, now thatSidky Pasha had resigned, the new Prime Minister of Egypt might take the line that he would be ready to sign the Treaty if we with-drew our request for publication of the understandings reached between the Foreign Secretary and Sidky Pasha on the interpreta-tion of certain points, including the Sudan Protocol. The matter could not, however, be left on the basis of the partial statements made by Sidky Pasha since his return from London. In view of thestate of feeling in the Sudan, there must be no room for publicmisunderstanding about our interpretation of the Sudan Protocol.The Minister of Fuel and Power asked whether it was notunfortunate that the Persian Government should have been advised by the United States to report to the Security Council their decisionto send troops into Azerbaijan to preserve order during the forth-coming elections. Would it not have been preferable, as the foreign secretary had advised, to refrain from raising this issue on theSecurity Council 1 Persia seemed to be faced with the prospect ofchoosing between trouble with the Soviet Union or a Parliamentdominated by Communists; and neither of these developmentswould be welcome from the point of view of essential Britishinterests in South Persia.The Cabinet were informed that the Persian Governmentwould probably have reported the position to the Security Councilin any event, irrespective of the advice given by the United States.It was arguable that they were under an obligation to make thereport, as the Persian situation was still on the agenda of theSecurity Council.The Cabinet were reminded that on 18th November they had approved a proposal that at the General Assembly of the united nations His Majesty&apos;s Government should take the initiative in proposing a resolution on the political situation in Spain. In theevent a resolution on somewhat different lines had been proposedby the United States Government.The Minister of State explained the circumstances which had prevented the Foreign Secretary from carrying out his original proposal. The Cabinet, while regretting that it had not beenpossible for His Majesty&apos;s Government to take this initiative,recognised that the tactics to be adopted in a matter of this kindmust be adjusted to meet the changing situation at the general assembly.2. The Cabinet&apos;s attention was drawn to the discussions in theGeneral Assembly of the United Nations on the draft resolution calling on States Members to furnish particulars of the strengths oftheir Armed Forces.The Minister without Portfolio referred to the refusal of theSoviet Government to accept any procedure for verification of the returns made by Governments regarding the Forces stationed within their own territory; and he asked how this would influence theattitude of His Majesty&apos;s Government towards the type of informa-tion to be rendered about the strength of our Forces. Would itsuffice to give global figures only, without any detailed information about the disposition of our Forces %The Minister of State said that it would be necessary to makea return, in accordance with the terms of the resolution. The form which this return should take, and the amount of detail to beincluded in it, were matters on which the Foreign Office would beglad to have the views of the Governments military advisers.[32878-2] *       b 2unitedNations.Disclosure ofStrengths of armed Forces.
The Cabinet-Invited the Minister without Portfolio to obtain the viewsof the Chiefs of Staff, and thereafter to consult with theMinister of State, on the form and content of the returnto be made to the United Nations about the strength ofthe Armed Forces.India.constitutional position.(previous reference:CM. (46) 100thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Prime Minister and the Secretary of State for Indiagave the Cabinet an account of the discussions which had takenplace with the Indian leaders during the previous week. These had turned on the interpretation of paragraph 19 (v) and (viii) of theStatement of 16th May by the Cabinet Mission and the Viceroy.This contemplated that, after a preliminary session, the ConstituentAssembly would break up into three Sections containing the repre-sentatives of (i) Bengal and Assam; (ii) the Punjab, the North-west frontier Province and Sind; and (iii) all the other Provinces. EachSection was to determine the constitutions of the Provinces in that section and whether a group constitution should be set up for them.The issue between the Congress and Muslim leaders was whether thedecisions of these Sections should be taken by a simple majority vote,or whether the Provinces should themselves have the right todetermine their own constitutions and to decide whether thereshould be a grouping of Provinces. The Muslim League had adopted the former interpretation, and the Congress the latter. Theformer interpretation was that intended by the Cabinet Mission.In the recent conversations with the Indian leaders it had notbeen possible to reach agreement on this question, but Pandit Nehruhad agreed to accept the decision of the Federal Court on this andother matters of interpretation of the Statement of 16th May. Onthis point the Federal Court was in fact likely to endorse the inter-pretation intended by the Cabinet Mission. At the conclusion ofthe meetings a statement had been issued by the Governmentsetting out the point at issue and the position as regards reference tothe Federal Court. This statement had been read to the indian leaders in the form in which it was published, save for minor verbalchanges.The Constituent Assembly was now meeting, and it was hopedthat the Muslims would join it after the Federal Court had given itsruling.   Future developments were, however, uncertain.The Prime Minister said that he had been at pains to impress on the Indian leaders the gravity of the situation, but he could not say how far they would be able to preserve a due sense of responsi-bility or to induce it among their colleagues in India. He feared that Indian politicians generally were not fully aware of the dangerous possibilities ahead.The Cabinefs further discussion on this aspect of the situationin India is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of cabinet conclusions.The Prime Minister said that he proposed to make a statement in the House of Commons about the discussions with the indian leaders. Before doing so, however, he proposed to speak informallywith the leaders of the Opposition, in the hope that this mightprevent a public debate on his statement, which he would prefer toavoid at this stage.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of this report on the discussions with the indian leaders.(2) Took note that public statements on the present positionwould be made in the two Houses of Parliament, by thePrime Minister and the Secretary of State for Indiarespectively, on 11th December.The Cabinet were informed that Mr. Jinnah had invited the Prime Minister and other Ministers to a luncheon on12th December.    If these invitations were accepted, there would
be adverse comment from other Parties in India. The view of theCabinet was that it would be wiser that these invitations shouldbe declined.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that Ministers who had been invited to Mr. Jinnah&apos;sluncheon on 12th December should decline this invita-tion; and took note that the Secretary of State for india would explain to Mr. Jinnah why it was thoughtinexpedient that Ministers.should attend this luncheon.4. At their meeting on 5th December the Cabinet had agreedthat the Executive Council of Burma should be invited to send a delegation to this country to discuss the next steps in the consti-tutional progress of Burma. The Cabinet now had before them amemorandum by the Secretary of State for Burma (CP. (46) 448)reporting that the Working Committee of the iVnti-Fascist People&apos;sFreedom League (i\..F.P.F.L.) were ready to accept this invitationonly if His Majesty&apos;s Government first announced that they accepted in principle the four main demands of the Party, includingthe demand that Burma should be free to choose whether she should remain within the British Commonwealth.The Secretary of State for Burma was not prepared torecommend that ail these four demands should be granted in full.On merits, there were strong arguments for making no concession on any of them. At the same time, it would be inexpedient toalienate the A.F.P.F.L., for there was no alternative party in Burmaon whom we could rely. Aung San, the leader of the party, had indicated that a delegation would probably come to London if an assurance could be given to Burma similar to that which the PrimeMinister had given in regard to India on 15th March, i.e., an assurance that Burma, when its constitution was established, wouldbe free to decide whether it remained within the British Common-wealth as a Dominion or became independent. The Secretary ofState said that, if the Cabinet were ready to make such a statement in regard to Burma at any time, there was advantage in making it now. It was true that we should thus deprive ourselves in advanceof one of the main concessions which we might be able to make toany delegation which came here. Nevertheless, on balance, he agreed with the Governor in recommending that a statement shouldbe made on the lines suggested.In discussion there was general agreement that there could beno devolution of responsible government to Burma until after theelections in April. Some Ministers were not satisfied that it wouldbe desirable even after that date; for the Burmese had not so fargiven any convincing proof of their ability to govern themselves.At the same time, it was recognised that we must take account ofthe weakness of our military and administrative position in Burma.We were not in a position to impose our will by force. There werefew British troops there; Indian troops could not be used to main-tain internal security; and Burmese troops could not be relied upon for that purpose.The general view of the Cabinet was that it should be possibleto frame a statement, not perhaps so specific as that made in regardto India, to the effect that it was our policy to enable the Burmeseto achieve self-government and to determine their own future; thatthe means of making progress towards this end was a matter fordiscussion with Burmese leaders and for this purpose it was desired that a delegation should visit this country. The text of a statement on these lines should be submitted for consideration by the Cabinet.Other points made in discussion were : (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would be reluctant to agree to any further financial concessions to the Govern-ment of Burma.
(b) The Secretary of State for the Colonies referred to thepossible repercussions on Ceylon and Malaya of any furtherpromises of rapid constitutional development in Burma. It wouldbe unfortunate if Burma&apos;s progress towards full self-government appeared to be more rapid than that of Ceylon. The aspirations ofthe Malays would also be influenced by events in Burma, as they already had by events in Indonesia.(c) It was important that we should maintain adequate safe-guards for the frontier tribes.The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister and the Secretary ofState for Burma, in the light of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion,would prepare the draft of a statement to be consideredby the Cabinet at their meeting on 12th December.Palestine.illegal immigration.(previous preference:CM. (46)77thConclusions,Minute 2.)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the First Lordof the Admiralty (CP. (46) 434) proposing that officers commandingHis Majesty&apos;s ships should be authorised to arrest on the high seascertain specified categories of vessels suspected of carrying illegalJewish immigrants to Palestine, and given a discretion to divert to cyprus any such ship which was found to be carrying illegal immigrants.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that this proposal hadbeen made by the Commander-in-Chief, Mediterranean, after discussion with the High Commissioner for Palestine. There hadbeen consultations with the Foreign Office and the Colonial Officeand with the Minister without Portfolio; and, in order to meet theviews expressed in those consultations, he now proposed to modifyparagraph 5 of his memorandum by making it an additionalinstruction to the Commander-in-Chief that only in exceptional circumstances might he arrest or stop a ship flying a foreign flagoutside territorial waters if her impending arrival had not beenmade known to the Admiralty 48 hours or more beforehand.The First Sea Lord said that as faster and heavier ships were now being used for the transport of illegal immigrants to Palestineit was desirable that His Majesty:s ships should have more sea room for interception than was available within territorial waters. Theperiod of 48 hours provided for in the proposed instructions to theCommander-in-Chief would give the Admiralty time to consider in any particular case whether interception was likely to give riseto trouble; and it would be made clear that commanding officersmust use great discretion in the exercise of their authority to act in exceptional circumstances without having given this prior notice tothe Admiralty. Such circumstances might be inability to identify the ship or strong suspicion that she was in fact one of the shipswhose impending arrival had already been reported to theAdmiralty.The Lord Chancellor said that he was not satisfied that theproposal could be justified in international law. We had alwayslooked jealously on any action by another Government (eg., theUnited States, in connection with the enforcement of prohibition)that might be held to imply an extension of the 3-mile limit of territorial waters; and he felt that the legal implications of thisproposal should be more closely examined before it was approved.In further discussion there was general agreement that theproposed action should not be taken if it was open to question under international law. It was also for consideration whether in any event the United States Government should not be given some priorwarning of our intentions.The Cabinet Invited the Lord Chancellor, after consultation with thelegal advisers of the Foreign Office and the Admiralty, tosubmit to the Cabinet his considered view on the legal
implications of the proposal that officers commanding HisMajesty&apos;s ships should be given authority to arrest on thehigh seas certain specified categories of vessels suspected of carrying illegal Jewish immigrants to Palestine.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellor,f of the Duchy of Lancaster (CP. (48) 446) regarding the export ofthe   Ruhr coal to Western Europe.:)ae- The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that owing to industrial disputes in the United States there would be some inter -ruption in the supply of American coal to France and othercountries of Western Europe; and the Governments of thosecountries would demand on this account that they should be allowed) to draw increased supplies of coal from the Ruhr. The Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster explained the continuing economic difficulties in the British Zone of Germany arising from shortageof coal; and urged that, despite the representations which wereto be made on behalf of countries of Western Europe, the volumeof coal exports from the Ruhr should not be increased in january and the succeeding months. He recommended that we should seek to maintain the cut in total exports previously approved by theCabinet, and should also oppose any suggestion for a loan of coal to Western Europe over and above the official allocations. he further suggested that, in view of the new agreement regarding theeconomic fusion of the British and United States Zones ofGermany, we should ascertain whether the United States authorities would support us in proposing a complete moratorium on all coal exports from the Ruhr or, alternatively, a substantial further cut in coal exports as from January 1947.In discussion it was recalled that the current decision reportedto the Cabinet on 9th September, 1946, was that the total volume ofcoal exports from Germany should be reduced by 150,000 tons amonth in October and November, 1946, and by 350,000 tons a month in December to March inclusive. It would be premature to proposea further reduction at this stage. There had been no significant change in the economic situation; and the report of the Quadri-partite Committee of experts had not yet been considered by theCouncil of Foreign Ministers.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the British Element of the Control commission for Germany should be instructed to oppose any pro-posals for increasing the amount of coal allocated forexport from Germany during January to Marchinclusive; and also to oppose any suggestions for a loan of German coal to Western European countries over and above the official allocations.(2) Decided that for the time being no approach should be madeto the United States authorities about the possibility ofa complete suspension, or further reduction, of coal exports from Germany.7.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster (OP. (46) 445) on the future treatment ofof     certain Royalist Yugoslavs who had been captured by the germans in 1941 and since the end of the war in Europe had been maintained,as a military organisation, in the British Zone of Germany.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that it wasinexpedient that these men should continue to be maintained as amilitary organisation in Germany; and more of them were likelyto accept repatriation to Yugoslavia if their military organisation53rd were broken up and they were separated from their senior officers,ns, The opportunity had now arisen to enlist a number of them in a-)      Civil Watchmen&apos;s Service, which was to be recruited from displaced
persons of all nationalities and was to take over from British troops the responsibility for guarding certain military installations in theBritish Zone. The approval of the Cabinet was sought because itwas possible that force might have to be used in dispersing themilitary oranisation and segregating the senior officers. It wasspecially important that some 84 of the most senior officers should,be immediately removed from Germany. It would be convenient ifthe Cabinet could give authority for these to be brought to theUnited Kingdom if the Foreign Office were unable to arrange fortheir transfer to foreign countries.The Cabinet were informed that the Foreign Office were hopingto be able to arrange for the majority of these officers to betransferred to foreign countries. It was the view of the Cabinetthat none should be brought to the United Kingdom.The Minister of State supported the proposals put forward inOP. (46) 445, subject to two qualifications : (i) that no Yugoslavofficer above the rank of captain should be enlisted in the CivilWatchmen&apos;s Service; and (ii) that, in order to emphasise the civiliancharacter of this Service, its members should not be allowed to carrypersonal arms when off duty.The Chancellor of the Excheqtoer said that the Treasury shouldbe consulted about the pay and conditions of service proposed for members of the Civil Watchmen&apos;s Service.In further discussion Ministers expressed concern at the lengthof time for which these Yugoslavs had been maintained in theBritish Zone as a military organisation and asked whether some ofthem could not have been employed at an earlier date on useful work, e.g., in felling timber. Flad not the time come for moreresolute action to disperse all these groups of political refugees andother displaced persons in the British Zones of Germany and austria, who, in the aggregate, represented a substantial charge onthe British Exchequer \The Prime Minister said that he had recently called for a reportfrom the Foreign Office on this whole question. He would considerwhether this should be brought before the Cabinet.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals put forward in OP. (46) 445 forthe dispersal of the military organisation of RoyalistYugoslavs in the British Zone of Germany, subject tothe qualifications (i) that no Yugoslav officer above the rank of captain should be enlisted in the CivilWatchmen&apos;s Service; and (ii) that members of this service should not be allowed to carry personal armswhen off duty.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster toarrange for the Treasury to be consulted about the pay and conditions of service proposed for members of thisCivil Watchmen&apos;s Service.Sarawak. 8.   The Cabinet had  before them a memorandum by the(Previous Secretary of State for the Colonies (OP. (46) 444) describing the reference: efforts made by Anthony Brooke, nephew of the former Rajah ofC.M.(46)50th Sarawak, to revive opposition to the cession of Sarawak to his conclusions,     Majesty.Minute 4.) It was stated in the memorandum that Anthony Brooke had announced his intention to visit Sarawak and that, if he were allowed to do so, local opposition to the cession would be revivedIn all the circumstances the Secretary of State recommended thatAnthony Brooke should be prohibited from entering Sarawak, butthat the Governor should be instructed not to make an order to this effect until it was known that Anthony Brooke had obtained &apos;spassage for Sarawak or had arrived at Singapore en route for the
territory, or until he asked specifically whether he would be prevented from entering the territory.The Cabinet Agreed that Anthony Brooke should be prohibited from entering Sarawak; and invited the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies to send instructions to the Governor of sarawak on the basis proposed in paragraph 9 of cp. (46) 444 and summarised above.CivicRestaurants.Supply ofIntoxicatingLiquor.(previous reference:CM. (46) 96thConclusions,Minute 6.)9. The Secretary of State for Scotland recalled that, whenthe Cabinet had considered whether power should be taken in theCivic Restaurants Bill to enable local authorities to supplyintoxicating liquor in restaurants operated under the Bill, he had pointed out that a special procedural difficulty would arise in thelarger burghs in Scotland, where the local authority administeringa civic restaurant would, if seeking a licence, have to apply to licensing court whose members would also be members of the localauthority. He had now agreed with the Home Secretary that theBill should be amended so as to remove any doubts about thecompetence of the licensing court to grant a licence in such a case.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,10th December, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
