<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 181/3/0 images: 1-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PRECEDENT BOOK.Part I.Annexas.Annex I CABINETS SINCE 1916.Annex II SUBMISSION OP BUSINESS TO THE CABINET:ACTION IN THE CABINET OFFICE.Annex III       STATISTICS CP MEETINGS * MEMORANDA.Annex IV NOTES ON QU?3TION? OF PROCEDURE FORMINISTERS.Annex V TABLE OF MINISTERIAL APPOINTMENTS FROMSEPTEMBER,  1939.

(i)	Mr.	Lloyd George&apos;a Coalition war Cabinet, 1916-1919	Mr,	Lloyd George1a Coalition Cabinet. 1919-1922(ill)	Mr.	Bonar Law&apos;a Conservative Cabinet, 1922*1923(ir)	Mr.	Baldwin&apos;s Conservative Cabinet, 1923-1921.(*)	Mr.	MaeDonald&apos;a Labour Cabinet, 192i..(vl)	Mr.	Baldwin&apos;a Conservative Cabinet, 1921^-1929(m)	Mr.	MaeDonald&apos;s Labour Cabinet, 1929-1931(mi)	Mr.	MaeDonald&apos;s Coalition (&quot;National&quot;) Cabinet, 1931(lx)	Mr.	MaeDonald&apos;s Coalition (&quot;national&quot;) Cabinet, 1931-1935(x)	Mr.	Baldwin&apos;a Coalition (&quot;national&quot;) Cabinet, 1935-1937(si)	Mr.	Chaj*erlain&apos;s Conservative Cabinet, 1937-1939(xU)	Mr.	Chaaberlain&apos;s Conservative war Cabinet, 1939-19*40(xlii)	Mr.	Churchill&apos;s Her Cabinet, 191*0-1945(xtv)	Mr.	Churchill&apos;8 Caretaker Cabinet, 1945(xr) (xvi)	Mr. Mr.	Attlee&apos;s Labour Cabinet, 191*5 -IfSo /lttl*e.&apos;J &quot;Labour C*.bmict  l^sro-Kotesi   (1)   In the following tables the Cabinet is shownin order of precedence)   the Ministers outsidethe Cabinet are not shown in order of precedence;the Law Officers are only shown when included Inthe Cabinet.   Mo attempt has been aade to reflect^^l^*n*   ^t^j^^s^^s^^ji^C^^I fll^^^fn^^^  ^8^!n* *^^sads*ew;  ^klse^B^ ^e*]JL ^i^^^s^^fe3L^B^(^Government.(2)   For earlier Cabinets see Jennings, Appendix X.
Mar Cabinet (formed 7th December, 1916)Prime MinisterLord President of the CouncilChancellor of HanohequerMinister without Portfolio (Milnor)Minister without Portfolio (Headerson)Lord Lieutenant of IrelandLord ChancellorLord Privy SeelSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentSecretary of State for Foreign AffaireSecretary of State for the ColoniesSecretary of State for warSecretary of State for IndiaFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyMinister of the Blockade and Under Secretary of Statefor Foreign AffairsPr eel dent of the Board of TradePresident of the Local Government BoardPresident of the Board of AgriculturePresident of the Beard of EducationChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterChief Secretary for IrelandSecretary for ScotlandFirst Commissioner of WorksMinister for MunitionsPostmaster GeneralMinister of Food ControlShipping ControllerMinister of LabourPresident of the Air BoardPaymaster GeneralMinister of Pensions.In December 1917 there were four Minioters withoutPortfolio in the War Cabinet (Milner, Barnes, Carson endSmuts).   Ministers of Motional Service, Shipping, Blockade,and a Director of War Trade had been crested.In November 1918 the Lord Privy Seel wee in the WarCabinet, there wore two Ministers without Portfolio (Barneeand Saute).   A Minister of Reconstruction had been created.In July, 1918 the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancasterwas also Minister of Information.   There was alee aDireotor of War Trade.
(ii)asm mam* m^-imCabinet (formed November, 1919)Print MinisterLord Privy 6eelLord President of the CouncilChancellor of ExchequerMinister without Portfolio (Barnee)Lord Lieutenant of IrelandLord ChancellorSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentSecretary of State for foreign AffaireSecretary of State for the ColoniesSecretary of State for war and AirSecretary of State for IndiaFirst Lord of AdmiraltySecretary for ScotlandPresident of the Board of &apos;i&apos;radeMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of LabourMinister of TransportMinisters Mot in CabinetChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterPi ret Consuls si on*r of WorksMinister for MunitionsPostmaster GeneralMinister of PoodMinister of ShippingPaymaster GeneralMinister cf PensionsMinister of National ServiceChief Secretary for IrelandIn Dee ember, 1920 the Chief Secretary for Ireland vacincluded in the Cabinet with the Lord Lieutenant,   x&apos;heMinister of National Serrlee had gone.In December, 1921 the Attorney General vac Included inthe Cabinet but not the Secretary of State for Air or theMinister of Transport.   The Chief Secretary for Irelanderne in the Cabinet but not the Lord Lieutenant.   The Ministersef Munitions and of Shipping had gone
Cabinet (formed 23rd October, 1922)Prime MinisterLord Privy Seal (racant)Lord President of the CouncilLord ChancellorSecretary of State for Home AffaireSecretary of State for Foreign AffaireSecretary of State for the ColoniesSecretary of state for WarSecretary of State for IndiaFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyPresident of the Board of TradeMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesSecretary for ScotlandPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of LabourMefljL&amp;JtSCft Hftifri ^iffl ffab^PjO1^.Postmaster GeneralFirst Costal ssloner of WorksMinister of TransportMinister of PensionsSecretary for Air
Cabinet (formed 22nd May, 1923)Prime MinisterLord Privy SealLord Preeldeot of the CouncilLord ChancellorChancellor of the leeheceerSecretary of State for Home AffaireSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsSecretary of state for the ColoniesSecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for IndiaSecretary of State for AirFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyPresident of the Board of TradeMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesSecretary for JeatlandPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of LabourPostmaster GeneralFinancial Secretary to the TreasuryMlPlBteXf. ffflt ifl tfrt CabletChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterPaymaster GeneralFirst Commissioner of WorksMinister of TransportMinister of Pensions
(*)Cabinet (formed 2Uth January, 1921*)Prime Minister and Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsLord Privy SealLord President of the CouncilLord ChancellorChancellor of ths EjoshsauerSecretary of State for Horns AffairsSecretary of Stats for ths ColoniesSecretary of State for Warsecretary of State for IndiaSecretary of 8tats for AirFirst Lord of ths AdmiraltyPresident of ths Board of TradsMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesSecretary for ScotlandPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of LabourPostmaster GeneralChancellor of ths Duchy of LancasterFirst CommlssloBer of WorksMini star of PensionsMinister of Transport
Hinistsrs Hot In the CabinetPostmaster QeneralPayaastsr GeneralMinister of PensionsMiniate? of TransportIn November. 1926 the Secretary of State for theColonies had become Secretary of State for the DominionsIn 1926 the Secretary for Scotland became Secretaryof State for Scotland.Cabinet (formed kth November. 192k)Prime MinisterSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsLord President of the CouncilLord ChancellorLord Privy SeelChancellor of KaaehequerSecretary of State for Home AffaireSecretary of state for the ColoniesSecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for IndiaSecretary of State for AirFirst Lord of AdmiraltyPresident of the Board of TradeMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and PlshsriesSecretary for ScotlandPreeldent of the Board of EducationMinister of LabourChancellor of the Duchy ef LancasterFirst Commissioner of WorksAttorney General
Cabinet (formed 8th June, 1929)Prime MinisterLord ChancellorLord President of the CouncilLord Privy SealChancellor of the ExchequerSecretary of State for Home AffairsSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsSecretary of State for the Dominions and the ColoniesSecretary of State for WarSecretary cf State for IndiaSecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for ScotlandFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyPresident of the Board of tradeMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesPresident of the Board of EducationFirst Cosraissioser of worksChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterPaymaster GeneralPostmaster GeneralMinister of PensionsMinister of Transport
flfttlHJ (formed 25th August, 1931)Prime MinisterLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for the Hons DepartmentLord ChancellorSecretary of Stats for Foreign AffairsSecretary of Stats for IndiaSecretary of Stats for ths Dominions and ths ColoniesMinister of HealthPresident of the Board of TradeMlnlfUrt apt in tfto cafrinttLord Privy Sealsecretary of State for WarFirst Lord of ths AdmiraltyMlnlstsr of Agriculture and FisheriesPresident of ths Board of EducationChancellor of ths Duchy of LancasterSecretary of Stats for ScotlandFirst Commissioner of WorksPostmaster Senera!Mlnlstsr of LabourSecretary of State for AirPaymaster GeneralMlnlstsr of PensionsMlnlstsr of Transport
MJjs4jrf *rs. .Mot, &amp;,n the, 9afeaJM%Chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterPaymaster GeneralMinister of PensionsMinister of TransportIn May, 1935* the Postmaster (Jenoral was included inmi&amp;Sl (formed 10th November, 1931)Prime MinisterLord President of the Council end Lord Privy SeelChancellor of the KashequerSecretary of State for Home AffaireLord ChancellorSecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsSecretary of State for IndiaSecretary of State for the DominionsSecretary of State for the ColoniceSecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for ScotlandMinister of HealthPresident of the Beard of TradeFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesMinister of LabourFirst CeeralBsioner of Works
BW Ptifffffit WAUXOT (^ational^) CABffifr&apos;, 1935-4937*fllMfHtl (formed 7th Jane. 1935)Prime MinisterLord President of the CouncilChancellor of the EjoahequerLord ChancellorSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsLord Privy SealSecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for the DominionsSecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for IndiaSecretary of State for ScotlandSecretary of State for the ColoniesPresident of the Board of TradeFirst Lord of AdmiraltyMinister without Portfolio for League of Nations AffaireMinister without PortfolioMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of HealthMinister of LabourFirst Commissioner of WorksslitltWi fo* eB m qablBftPostmaster GeneralMinister, of PensionsMinister of TransportChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterPaymaster GeneralIn November, 1936. the offices of Minister withoutPortfolio for League of Nations Affairs and Ministerwithout Portfolio had gone, bat the Cabinet Included aMinister for the Co-ordination of Defence and the Ministerof Transport.* This Government was re-elected to office on22nd November, 1935*BffJ ! LsjiSiw
gttflfrt (formed 28th May, 1937)Prime MinisterChancellor of the ExchequerLord President of the CouncilLord ChancellorSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentSecretary of State for Foreign AffaireLord Privy SeelSecretary of State for the DominionsSecretary of State for India and BurmaSecretary of State for the ColoniesMinister for Co-ordination of DefenceFirst Lord of AdmiraltySecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for AirSecretary of state for ScotlandPresident of the Board of TradeMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of HealthMinister of LabourMinister of TransportMinister of WorksPostmaster GeneralChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMinister of PensionsIn 1938 the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancasterwas included la the Cabinet!   in 1939 * Minister ofSupply eas included in the Cabinet;   and a PaymasterGeneral wee appointed but eas not included in the Cabinet.-11*-
/ffTVg ***** QAPTWTffi(formed 3rd September, 2939)Prime MinisterChancellor of the ^aehequerSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsMinister for the Co-ordination of DefenceFirst Lord of ths AdmiraltySecretary of Stats for WarSecretary of Stats for AirLord Privy SealMinister without Portfolio (Lord Hanker)Lord Presldsnt of ths CouncilPresident of ths Beard sf TradsLord ChancellorSecretary of State for the Boms Department and Minister ofHome SecuritySecretary of State for ths DominionsSecretary of Stats for India and BurmaSecretary of State for the ColoniesSecretary of State for Scotlandttnister of Labour and Rational ServicePresident of the Board of EducationMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesMinister of SupplyMinister of TransportFirst Commissioner of WorksPostmaster GeneralChancellor of the Duchy ef Lancaster sad Minister of FoodMinister of PensionsMinister of InformationMinister of Economic warfareMinister of ShippingPaymaster GeneralIn 19*10 the offlss of Minister for the Co-ordination of
War Cabinet (formed 11th May, 1940)   (see below alee)Prime Minister and Minister of DefenceLord President of the CouncilLord Privy SealSecretary of State for Foreign AffaireMinister without Portfolio (Lord Hankey)Chancellor of the ExchequerPresident of the Board of TradeFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyLord Chancellorsecretary of state for the Home Department and Minister ofHome SecuritySecretary of State for Dominions AffaireSecretary of State for India and BurmaSecretary of State for the Coloniessecretary of State for Marsecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for ScotlandPresident of the Board of EducationMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesMinister of SupplyMinister of Shipping and TransportMinister of FoodMinister of Works and BuildingsPostmaster GeneralChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMinister of PensionsMinister of Aircraft ProductionMinister of InformationMinister of Boonomlo WarfareMinister of Labour and National ServiceIn 1941 a Paymaster General was appointed)   in 1942 aMinister of Fuel and Power sad s Minister Resident in WestAfrica were appointed)   in 1943 a Minister of Town and CountryPlanning, a Minister without Portfolio and a Minister Reeldentin Washington were appointed)   in 1944 a Minister Reeldent,Allied Forces HQ, Mediterranean was appointed and the officeof the Minister without Portfolio lapaed.lord Privy Seal oouncilMini at or of Labt
(xriil) continued-war Oahlaat is November, 1941Mow Ulsister mad Minister of DefenceLord Privy SeelLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for Foreign Affairsminister without Portfolio (Greenwood)Minister of SupplyChancellor of the SjeheauerMinister of Labour and National ServiceMinister of State (Lyttleton)War flnfciltt in Hoveabor, 191*2Prime Minister and Minister of DefenceSecretary of state for the DominionsLord Privy SeelLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsMinister of ProductionMinister of Labour and national ServiceMinister of State (Casey)War Cabinet in November, 191*3Prime Minister sad Minister of DefenceLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for Foreign AffaireChancellor of the ExchequerMinister of Labour and National ServiceMinister of ProductionSecretary of State for the Home Department aadMinister of Hone SecurityMinister of ReconstructionMinister of Stats Resident in the Middle Bastla November, 191*1* the war Cabinet was the same ae in191*3 except that the Minister of State Reel dent in the Middle-ll*-
9*Hm\ (ftnnd 25to-30ih May, 1945)Prime Ministersecretary of Stats for Foreign AffairsChancellor of the ExchequerLord President of the CouncilLord Privy SealPresident of the Board of Trade and Minister of Productionminister of Labour and National Servicesecretary of State for Home AffairsSecretary of State for Dominion AffairsSecretary of Stats for India and BunasSecretary of State for the ColoniesPi rat Lord of the AdmiraltySecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for ScotlandMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesMaflalttfff Hit      lit ff*ftlfl9lMinister of Aircraft ProductionMinister of Civil AviationChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterMinister of EducationMinister of FoodMinister of Fuel and PowerMinister of HealthMinister of informationLord ChancellorMinister Resident in Middle EastMinister of State (Mabane)Minister of National InsurancePaymaster GeneralMinister of PensionsPostmaster GeneralMinister of SupplyMinister of Town and Country PlanningMinister of war TransportMinister Resident in Went AfricaMinister of works
Cabinet (formed 28th July - 7th August, 191*5)Prime Minister, First Lord of the Treasury sad Minister sfDefenseLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsLord Privy SealChancellor of the KmsheojuerPresldsnt of the Board of TradeFirst Lord of the AdmiraltyLord ChancellorSecretary of State for ths Horns DepartmentSecretary of State for Dominion AffairsSecretary of State for India and Secretary of 8tats forBurmaSecretary of State for ths ColoniesSecretary of Stats for warSecretary of State for AirSecretary of State for ScotlandMinister of Labour and national ServiceMinister of Fuel and PowerMinister of EducationMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesUttfffWa. ffot Iff, tftfl MsnMlMlnlstsr sf Supply and Aircraft ProductionMinister of TransportMinister of FoodMinister of worksMinister of Town and Country PlanningMlnlstsr of National Insurance
MR. AIILES&apos;5 LABGOa CABINET. 19SQCabinet   (formed 28th February, 1950)Prime MinisterLord President of the CouncilSecretary of State for Foreign AffairsChancellor of the ExchequerMinister of Town and Country PlanningLord Privy sealChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterLord ChancellorSecretary of State for the Home DepartmentMinister of DefenceMinister of Labour and National ServiceMinister of HealthMinister of Agriculture and FisheriesMinister of EducationPresident of the Board of TradeSecretary of State for the ColoniesSecretary of State for ScotlandSecretary of State for Commonwealth RelationsMinisters Not in the Cabinet .^ev t   ?ncvU&quot;eeFirst Lord of the AdmiraltySecretary of State for WarSecretary of State for AirMinister of Fuel and PowerMinister of TraosportMinister of SupplyMinister of State for Economic Affairs
Minister of National InsuranceMinister of FoodMinister of Civil iriationMinister of PensionsPostmaster-GeneralMinister of WorksMinister of State for Colonial AffairsMinister of StatePaymaster-General

litira nf fflnalisrtparagraphs 1-3)to the Cabinet are either emof policy or on important matters in whichthere is a difference of opinion between Ministers andDepartments which cannot be resolved without refto the highest authority.    In addition to the wideof topics of vital importance these is avariety ofin which natters are brought to thewidely.    At any one periodscan pro-occupation with a particularfield. e.g. the current need to redress the adversebalance of payments;   or the development of a line ofpolicy may need very frequent review of activities in aparticular field.    At the seme time provision must bsmads for considering the wide range of misosllaneonsproblems, often unforeseen, thrown up in the day to dayactivities of Departments.    Thus the Cabinethave to turn, from discussion of acme vitalor international problem to consider some 11domestic legislation or some relativelytratlve issue.    Moreover, there is the constant activityof the Committee i of the Cabinet, whoee reports moat bethe nature of the Cabinet*e work it followsfirstly that the programme of ite business cannot be fore-east in detail very far ahead!   and secondly,in dear3.    a running list of .should he kept, coveringj-ting considerationof which notice has been given by(111)for which the Cabinet hasAJBda likely to be submitted in thelight of earlier conclusions;(iw) reports lively to be submitted by CabinetCommittees, or likely to result from thwork of Official Oommitteee.U.    On the basis of this list business is marshalled endthe Agenda for meetings prepared.     Every indication ofa lively submission should be followed up, and a breadindication of ite nature ascertained.    The date aywhich a decision is likely to be required should, ifpossible, be ascertained, particular regard being paid tethe ilmimnilt of the Parliamentary time-table end the dateby which any public statement must be mads.    Svery effortshould be made to have memoranda forward as early aspossible so that Ministers and Departments have
CP. (49)95.paragraph 2.CP. (49)95,paragraph 4.opportunity oftoo Agenda andfor circulation.    If toe re lalikely to beissue say shortly heitary should he informed:r, the Lord President*sPlaoalag Staffthey are oat oato think that ais not aware that athe Privatewith the)Off lee aad the CentralWhen Information is received fraw a Department thatie being prepared the following pointsapt-CD la it clear that the 1otherwise than by reference to the Cabinettdifference between Departmeate is giother means of resolving It have heweg. correspondence or dlMinisters or reference to a Minister withco-ordinating fanctl(11) Is it dear that the issue cannotappropriately be discussed at a Cabinetprlately be discussed at a CabinsEconomic Policy Committee. Froduettcc. Lard President*s Committootend fast rales can be laidthere ie no doubt-   eat there aresubjects which, at a particular stage, ithe desirable to bring before a Cabinetrather than the Cabinet itself.    Eachdoubt must be considered on ite merlte.arguments of practical convenience (thetiming of meetings in relation to thea decision)(iii)Some memoranda are clearlya decision aaat be reached vary rapidly, ifeffective action ie to he taken.    laexceptional easee a special mootingneeded, but ordinaaly the timing ofaction will be adjusted to the timesregular meetingo of the Cabinet.Where accessary, the following points shouldbe taken up;-of the(i*)the Chancellor of theor theis a standing instruction that proposalsinvolving aad additional charge oa theExchequer should act be brought to the Cabinetuntil they have heea agreed, or at leastProposals involvingtloaa should alee heplace with the Chancellorthe Treasury;   aad the Tnthe man-powerited.la the firstIcatlons of
(v) Have the otter Departmenta concerned teaaconsulted?Xt la desirable that if several Departmentsare affected their points of view should.If possible, he covered la a single submission,a Joint memorandum la the names of theMinisters concerned.    Seraally there will,at least, be interdepartmental discussion;   butif there is reason to think that there baa beena lack of liaison or of consultation steps shouldbe taken to see that Departments are fully la-formed of the position, e*g. by arranging faran advance copy of the saawirsnftimi to be centto tbea.6*    The current practice le that memoranda for submissionto the Cabinet are eeat In draft to the Cabinet Office.The reasons for tola arei (1) it le very desirable thatthere should be aa opportunity of examining mesawraadabefore the? are reproduced) and (11) it is important thatpresentation and reproduction should be aapossible.7.    svery draft memorandum should be carefully examinedand, if necessary advice taken.    The following pointsCP. (49)95 should, in particular, be watched:-J***S**ph ie. (1) Should the imtnaraitdua be submitted to the Cabinet?(Where previous notice baa been received tilei .. - a m in,    DUO   *Voften impossible, or undesirable, to reach adefinite conclusion until the draft is available.)(U) Is there any apparent inconsistency or any(ill) la there any obvious mis-stateraent?(lv) le the general layout open to improvement?(v) Are there any points of style which can properlybe modified?(vi) Are the Annexes, if any, properly constructed andrelated to the iiaanii uiwUshT   (It le sometl&amp;acpossible to suggest the   omission of a verydetailed Annex net wholly relevant to the issuedealt with in the memorandum or the relegationte an Annex of certain material la the*)(wii) la the presentation formally eorrect?   (Titlesfrequently need eons) alteration:   and refer one seshould be correctly given and, if missing,supplied.)(nil) Ie the security classification correct?8*    Minor verbal amendments Involved in general editingcan normally be made without reference to the Departmentoriginating the memorandum, but any more substantialchange should be discussed with the Minister*e Private)Secretary, who may occasionally feel unable to agree without
reference to the Minister.    If too mm.....nit- isobviously ill conceived or so sadly constructed thatit is Htcely to fail in its object special steps anyhave to be taken.     (In certain oil1 awsitenses it nay,for special reasons, be found desirable to submit thedraft (or a printed proof) to ths Prims Mlnlstsr andseek authority for circulation.)9.    It is sometimes necessary for a Department to brineforward some issue for decision, or to circulate commentson a imwsiirsndnjii already circulated, at a time when theMinister himself is not available to approve the draft.In that event one or other of the following methods shouldbe adopted according to circumstances:-(1)   If ths Minister is temporarily absent orInaooessibls, and the Department are satisfiedthat the views expressed are on lines whlohhe has already approved, the innoi sadwii nay becirculated in the ordinary way.    where possibleths Parliamentary Undersecretary of otate orParliamentary Secretary should have approvedthe draft.    If ths Department feel unable tocommit the Mlnlstsr, a note may be attached tothe memorandum Indicating that It has net beenpossible to submit the final draft to theMinister.    This expedient will rarely be foundnecessary.(U)   If the Minister is absent for a period, e.g*overseas or through illness, ths memorandumshould be submitted by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of atate;   or, if appropriate, by thsMlnlstsr In charge of ths Department.(Hi)   In certain clrsumetanoss It may, in the absenceof the Mlnlstsr, be desirable for thsDepartmental mssMKSJSivm or s nets of thsDepartment*e views to be circulated eitherby s senior Minister with co-ordinatingfunctions (e.g* the Chancellor Of ths Exchequermight circulate a note covering a memorandumprepared in the Board of Trade in the abssncsof the President of ths Board of Trade), or bythe Secretary of the Cabinet (see paragraph 10aslowj.10*   Ths number of &quot;notes by the Secretary of the Cabinet&quot;covering memoranda or telegrams should bs kept as snailas possible.    The device is however convenientespecially if additional information or a recent telegrammust be circulated very shortly before a meeting of theCabinet.    Such additional material is normally circulatedat ths request of the Prime Minister sad the covering netscontains ths formula &quot;by direction of ths Prims MinisterI circulate herewith for consideration by the Cabinet...&quot;A sscond class of notes by the Secretary consists ofnotes on points of procedure or organisation, includingnotes on the terns of reference and composition sfCabinet Committees^     If important, such notes should
to east in ton form of notes by toe Prime Minieter endeiroulated in bis name after authority ban been obtained.(It will be found convenient, where the note is straight-forward, to delar submission until a printed proof toebeen obtained.)3*]s*4b      H St^i^Lw-iJL^^ 3. ^JUi vj^e^ eSfll^^BJp! (o^^ Jp^l^^wJB^feiJ JJi^? j^JP^J^Q^J^^s^l^JP^J O^B^organisation, drafts of policy tusseraada are sometimeeprepared in the Cabinet Office for circulation, in thename of senior Ministers, including the Prime Minieter.the Lord President, the Chancellor of the HjEehequer.Eonaally such wswrtinflo arise from the work of CabinetCommittees5   and in certain circumstances, with a viewto facilitating discussion at Cabinet, the draft of a&quot;central&quot; or w3amaari*iJag* sttmerandam is submitted farcirculation by the Prime Minister.12.   Whenever possible Cabinet awmoraada should be printed,especially if they are long.    Sometimee shortage of tineprevents printing, but subsequent   printing shouldalwaye be considered especially if a memoranda, is suchthat it is likely to come under frequent reference.So tee on . jinte of procedure or organisation shouldalways be printed, those in the Prime Minister fs namebeing printed on shite quarto paper.    If possibleAnriOXSB should be eeat to the printer in advance of thememorandum if the latter is still subject to revision.13*  Menjoraoda should to circulated as long aa possiblein advance of the meeting at which they are to beconsidered.    A memorandum ether than one ooomientiag ona memorandum already circulated must be circulated twoolear^days^before the meeting at which it le to to14.   The circulation list is net standard, except thatmembers of the Cabinet receive copies of all memoranda,and the circulation of each memerandum must be determinedseparately (usually be deleting entries on the circulation&quot;skin&quot;).    The follow log points should be kept in minds-(i)   ^^^^^^e^J^^y18^ c Jp^J fned^Ith^t ^aJpaetasubject matter must receive aoplee.(11) Memoranda of general interest (e.g. en proceedingsof the United Rations. International LabourOrganisation, etc.) should be given fullcirculation.(ill) Botee on points of procedure or erganisatloashould be given full circulation.(IV) Memoianda of general political or constitutionalinterest should he given full circulation,unless the need for special eeorecy makes itundesirable to circulate beyond the Cabinetitself.(v) The need to keep subordinate Departmeate Informedmoot to carefully watehed.(vi) Circulation to the Service Ministers and theChiefs of Staff involves special considerations,SBttsssAftad in thelast OfficeCP. (49)95.paragraph 9.Circulation:gotetf la itmm,paragraph 12.
and it Is impossible to lay down definiteBroadly, the service Ministers should receivecopies of memoranda hearing on the use oradministration of the Armed Forces.    The Chiefsof staff should receive copies of &quot;constitutionalor &quot;politieal* memoranda which raise, directlyor indirectly, strategic issues.    ..herecopies are sent to the Chiefs of staffSecretariat but not to the Chiefs of Staff tlselves, the former should be informed accordingljlli*.   Bemetiosee the need for special soorooj demands ai*estrioted circulation, and duplicate copies (even formembers of the Cabinet) may have to be withheld.     *henthe circulation is specially restricted (either on thespecific instructions of the Prime Minister or of theMinister submitting the memorandum, or otherwise) a notemay bo attached drawing attention to the particularsecrecy of the document and to the fact that circulationhas been restricted.    In a few eases a memorandum of avery high degree of secrecy mey have to be recalled afterit has hewn considered by the Cabinet.iu   When parliament is in session the Cabinet usuallymeets at pressnt  twice a week, oa Monday and Thursday.In general a weting on Tuesday is preferable to one onMonday, but if the -tunning Comuitteee in the House ofConmens are likely to make any substantial flaws ndn on thetii-j of members of the Cabinet17*   In fixing the times of meetings account must occasion-ally be taken of e.g. meetings of the Privy Council,attiwhich involve the attendance of certain senior Ministers.For the regular meetings It is unnecessary to giveMinisters advance warning by telephone of the time ofIB.  Meetings narwiny take place la the Cabinetat 10, Downing Street;   but if the Cabinet must meet ata time when the Bouse of Commons is sitting and divisionsare likely, or when a senior Minister must be able toember  quietly, meetings are held, atPrime Minister*e request, in his room at the Bouse19.   In the arrangement of business forthe following points must be keptmlndt-(1)   Relative(11)   Weight of businessi   the Agenda should be neither!unduly heavy or unduly light.(ill) Nature of businessi related business mustobviously be taken together, and there inusually advantage in taking at one(It)   Attendance of members of the Cabinet and &quot;inviteel(e.g. the future of Royal Dockyards cannot
far a meeting at which theof Transport cannot be present).(v)   Standing 1 tarns. l.e. &quot;Foreign Affaire1&apos;.VJiseeomle Affalre%the business for the followingthe tines of meetings provisionally agimfti^r- with the fries Minister^ Private Secretary, and asubmission for the Prims Ministers authority drafted.This submission nets out shea it is proposed that theCabinet should meet and what business should be taken,and should haws attached to It a draft of the Agenda fithe first meeting and a &quot;provisional programme- indicating Iin general to it as the business for both meetings.     -bilesometimes the submission can be drafted before Thursdayit cannot be mads until after the meeting on Thursdaysince points affecting the business for the followingweek are liable to be thrown up.21.   A further submission to the Prims Ministerprepared following the Monday meeting, covering thedraft Agenda for the Thursday meeting.    This le thenormal practice, but occasionally. e.g. if there areno items additional to those listed en the &quot;provisionalmur be dispensed with.22. The draft Agenda in the form submittsd to thePrims Minister shows the names ofCP, (k9) 95, it ie proposed to invite for particular items, but if sayparagraphc XU-15. special point arises it should be dealt with in the23.   The ^neral form of the Agenda is standard, but thefollowing particular palate should be nr-tedi-(1)   Description of items I   the titles ofto be discussed usually cannot be adapted forthis purpose, and, as a rule, a general termis to ba preferred,     The beet guide laprovided by the hesdinga of earlier minutes.As Agenda papers   have a fairly wide clroulatioJit is essential that no unnecessary Information!Should be given. Ia particular, steps mastbe tan-on to see that items noted on the Asmare not a source of leakage of eg.ration(11)   Previous References:   the last &quot;previto any subject to he discussed should alwayss r^jMHeferences la the minutes of aprevious administration should not becot In special circumstances.    Occasionally]If the previous reference la liable to provokerequests for copies of, e.g. an earlierconfidential annex not generally circulated,it is better net given, although it shouldbe used when the ninutes are prepared.(ill)   &quot;Alee relevantwJ   When a memorandum ia relevantto a particular discussion but not itself tebe considered, it is put down as &quot;also relevantLikewise, when a subject is to be raised orally]it Is twenties! coovelent te put on theas &quot;relevant&quot; an earlierit.
(It)   &quot;Resumed discussion&quot;!   Sometimes ths Cabinetagrees to resume discussion of a iiswsjisisJuhi ata later masting.     Tbe formila used oo tbeAgenda lax   &quot;Hsstimsfl dl souse ion of memorandumfcj......&quot;2km   Particular ears must be taken as regards Ministersinvited to lie present for a particular discussion.Ministers whose Departments are concerned with the subjectmust be invited.    The point should, however, be raisedwith their Private Sscreterlss (unless this is clearlyunnecessary) before the draft Agenda is submitted ts thsPrims Minister.    It is sometimes found (1) that altboughbis Department may be to some extent concerned, a Ministerany not be anxious to attend, or (11) that the Ministeris unable to attend for seas good reason.Somstlmss, after ths Agsada has been submitted totbe Prime Minister, s Mlnlstsr asks whether he any attendfor a particular item,    la that event It is usuallynecessary to obtain the Prims Minister*s authority by note,if time psrmits, or through the Private secretaries at10, Downing street.Invitation of the Service Ministers and ths Chiefe ofStaff presents special problems.    In all eases ths pointshould be taken up with the Private secretary to theMinister of Defence, If possible before the draft ftgsndais submitted to the Prime Minister.    If the Ministerof Defence rsiismmenjli that the service -InLters should bepresent the Prime Minister&apos;s authority should be sought,sad the Private secretaries concerned warned accordingly.Special difficulty la apt to arise la the Invitation ofthe Chiefs of staff and special steps are aometimeaaccessary, eg. in spite of a negative reaemmeadatlon fromthe Minister sf Defence it may be desirable to bring thspoint before the /rime Minister.    In certain circumstancesthe Chiefs of otaff may be asked to be in attendance out-side ths Cabinet Room.25*   The order of items on the Agenda must sometimes beadjusted in order to bring near the beginning an lteafor which several Ministers mast be invited.    Is firm ruleican be laid down, but tbe objective should be to arrangetbe Agenda In such a way that unnecessary waiting iseliminated.    In timing items it is better to err ea thesafe side.    For &quot;Parliamentary Business&quot; five mlnatssshould be allowed!   for &quot;Foreign Affaire&quot; it la impossibleto allow a time since tbe Foreign Secretary may net la factraise any matters and Ministers invited for Item 2 shouldtherefore be invited to attend at the beginning sf thsCabinet,26.   Mot infrequently it is found necessary to arrange,after the Agenda has been circulated, for additionalbusiness to be taken, either on the basis of a nuimiiiiiUsaior of an oral statement.    The Prime Minister&apos;s approvalmust always he obtained.    Strictly this approvalshould be sought by ths Minister concerned (by minute orthrough the Private secretaries), bat it le sometimesmors convenient for the point to be raised by ths CabinetOffice,    Authority must be obtained whether a isaairniwUsiis being circulated or not.
27*   &apos;&apos;ben authority has beam obtained the AgendaJfco^l^^L^L^fc oWfr^Jao^^ftJoB  Ba*^fc^laHaj      ^L*Jb^  ^b^^&amp;(b^ ^^^(S(W^fcJ^nn-  ^b^^B^  e3ifi^^j   t$o9 ^Li^b^Qp  JP^^^^e^^^^^elJ^h   ^b^b^^^mi^fiiiflijiii       ncMislflonit 11 in as ac additional ltaa eneuldbo clrouXated with a note to that effect, drawingattention to the foot that It ie to be considered at aipBfcjB^^^^w^Bw^^o^B^^IUiB^ o^^Bs^^^^fcoB^flo^Jo^ ee^^fc   ^L*s9   ^P(53Ew^(^^^^l^H^(^  oPos^lnwB^n  ^s^B^o^fco!o)o?^(fcBwew^^s^the nweworsejdun ie being circulated,    when a subject ieto be rained orally steps should be taken to Informthe Minlstere primarily concerned, if they are not already28.   When a memorandnm oommeuting on one alreadycirculated ie received for circulation after the Agendabaa been issued, a note should be attached to the effectthat it is &quot;for consideration under Item...&quot; of tewAgenda for a particular meeting.BCTS.    This outline) newejnentsii en current practice waaprepared in March, 1948 for use by the Privatesecretary to tbe Secretary of the Cabinet.It wee revised in July, 1949-


,   1939 123 kVF19U0 512 10145&quot;im 132 544*1942 m 670*1943 ITS 5921944 176 767a lnala-1 W.P.(0) e*a w.p.(E) as wall as W.P.4 iMlttlM U.P.(R) as wall as W.P.MeaUngss 17 (CM.(45) 1-17)Masjsraadai   86  (CP. (45) 1 - 88)1945 48(u.M.( 45) 18-65)      267( CP. (45)89-355)28th July)1946 108 4661947 96 34519** 82 509

Annex IV.NOTES ON QUESTIONS OP PROCEDURE POP. MINISTERS.LIST OF PAPERS HELD IN PRIVATE OFFICE COPY CFPRECEDENT BOOK.CP.(47) 46	CP. (47) 178	CP. Lk9]	31CP. (49,	95CP. (50	1CP. (50.	65CP. (49,	X g 126CP. (49.	150CP. (49	167CP. (50	132CP. (50J	6CP. (50)	152Consultation with the Trades UnionCongress.Replies to Letters and Statements tothe Press.Parliamentary Secretaries.Questions of Procedure for Ministers.Scientific Policy.Abbreviations.Offices of Profit Under the Crown.Contracts Between Government Departmentand J/erabers of Parliament.&quot;1/inisters of Cabinet Rank&quot;.

Annex V.Table of Ministerial Appointments.HELD IN PRIVATE OFFICE COPY OF PRECEDENT BOOK.


</content>
</cab>
