<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/1/5 images: 78-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1939.SECRET^ Copy Nq  43W.P. (R.) (39) 5.WAR CABINET.INDIA   AT   THE   OUTBREAK   OF   WAR.FIRST1 Fortnightly Report submitted by the Secretary of State for India covering the period up to 11th September.1. General and Political Situation.FOR some months past, in fact since the crisis of September 1938, thegeneral line adopted by the Indian politician has tended to be either that india will do nothing to assist the United Kingdom in any war arising in Europe usually described as an &quot;Imperialistic war &quot; or else that India&apos;s active partici-pation will be only at a price, the nature and extent of which has varied, butin general has tended to be the guaranteed attainment of either completemdependence or Dominion Status. The chief exponents of Indian political views are, of course, for the Hindus, the Indian National Congress, and, for theMuliammadans, the Moslem League. There are Congress Ministries in office in all but three of the eleven Provinces, and these Ministries have tended sincethe commencement of the new Constitution, though perhaps with graduallyincreasing reluctance, to take their cue in all important matters from the CongressWorking Committee, the inner controlling &quot;Cabinet&quot; of that body. For sometime past there has appeared to be a strong possibility that, in the eventof war, all the Congress Ministries in the Provinces would, by concerted actionarid under instructions from the Working Committee, tender their resignations,with the almost certain result, since no alternative Ministry would be in a positionto command the confidence of the provincial Legislatures, that the administrationof the Provinces would have to be carried on by the Governors personally underthe special provisions for a breakdown of the Constitution inserted in the act of 1935.So recently as the 11th August last the Working Committee of the Congressredefined the Congress attitude towards a war situation in uncompromisingterms, to the effect that the Congress remains determined to oppose all attempts to &quot;impose a war on India&quot;; and that provincial Ministries should in no wayassist war preparations of the British Government, and must be prepared, ifthis policy leads to resignation or removal of the Ministries, to face that result.In the same Resolution a recent decision to send Indian troops to Egypt and singapore without consulting the Central Legislative Assembly was vehementlyattacked, and as a protest against this action Congress members of that bodywere directed to absent themselves from the next session due to be held in Simlathis month.Muhammadans, many of whom are dissatisfied with the position of theircommunity under the Act of 1935, have of late also shown a tendency to demanda price for their support. But, although a statement by the Punjab Premier,a- prominent Moslem, promising the fullest support of his Government recentlygave rise to acrimonious criticism in the Council of the Moslem League, anattempt to carry a vote of censure upon him failed, and there is little doubt thathe Punjab Government^ attitude, which is that of the Bengal (non-Congress)Government also, represents a large body of Moslem opinion.[19965] &apos; B
2Despite the official attitude of Congress, it has become increasingly plain thatIndians had not failed to realise that their own political future was inevitablyinvolved in the success of the democratic Powers, and the natural repugnance ofthe Indian outlook to that of the totalitarian States began to assert itself. Inparticular, it has become increasingly plain to the Governors of, at all events, themore important Congress Provinces that their Ministers were by no means readyto cast off their responsibilities, but, on the contrary, were not merely willing butanxious to stay in office and to play their part in attempting to bring the war to a successful conclusion. At the same time there has been a reluctance, notunnatural in the Indian character, on the part both of Ministers and of otherexponents of political opinion, to initiate any advocacy of a course other thanthat approved officially by the Congress. But during the last few days it has been clear that political India is waiting for a lead in this respect from the person who,despite the recent split in the Congress and the attempt by Subhas Bose tosupersede the moderates, is universally recognised as still the dominating politicalforce in India Mr. Gandhi, with whom the Governor-General had a two-hourstalk on the 5th September on the eve of his attending a further meeting of theWorking Committee to consider again the international situation. As the resultof this interview Mr. Gandhi has issued a statement to the press describing hisattempt by a personal letter to deflect the German Chancellor from his course, and making it clear that his own sympathies were with England and France from the purely humanitarian standpoint. He disclaimed any attempt at bargaining withthe Governor-General over the teimis of India&apos;s &quot; deliverance.&quot;The position as regards the general trend of opinion and the prospects ofco-operation may largely depend on the expected pronouncement by the working committee. But, in any case, there is no evidence of dangerous movements either in the civil population or the Army. Subhas Bose and his &quot; forward bloc &quot; of congress is establishing no hold on leftist opinion outside his own province of bengal.2. Terrorism.Eevolutionary societies, the ultimate aim of Avhose members is armedrebellion or perhaps individual acts of terrorism, are still active, particularly in bengal. The inauguration, two and a half years ago, of responsible governmentin the Provinces naturally necessitated some revision of policy on the part of these persons and induced some confusion as to what their aim should now be. Therehas been a considerable number of releases of ex-terrorist prisoners during the lasttwo years in various Provinces. There has been, however, no recent instance ofresort or immediately intended resort to terrorist outrages, and although thisendemic disease undoubtedly remains dangerous, it seems improbable that anyattempt to take advantage of the war as the opportunity for advancingrevolutionary and terrorist aims would encounter anything but vigorous condem-nation in India amongst most elements of the population.Special Emergency Measures Adopted by the Government of India.Immediately after the outbreak of war the Governor-General issued a defence of India Ordinance and a set of Rules made thereunder.   The Ordinancecorresponds closely, both in form and substance, to the English Emergency Powers;(Defence) Act and the Indian Defence Rules to the Defence Regulations.In accordance with the prearranged plan of the War Book, India adoptedimmediately on the outbreak of war measures parallel to those adopted here insuch matters as censorship and control of enemy aliens. In the latter respect.Indian conditions, geographical and social, have necessitated the adoption of a rather less liberal policy than has been adopted here.3. Military Affairs.Fortunately when war was declared India had already despatched approxi-mately two-thirds of the troops which, in accordance with the Chatfield Corn-mi ttee&apos;s recommendations, are classified as External Defence Troops. The mainreinforcements were a Brigade Group to Egypt with a Battalion to Aden, and
another Brigade Group to Singapore. Further details as to number and composi-tioii (British and Indian) of these troops, with other particulars, are given in theannexure, which will be kept up to date in subsequent reports.Two Bomber Squadrons R.A.F. were despatched at the same time to singapore.India has now been asked to despatch the remainder of the External defence troops to Egypt as soon as possible. This further reinforcement will consist ofa Divisional Headquarters and another Brigade Group.The Government of India are now considering what troops might be madeavailable for despatch overseas in an emergency in addition to the external defence Troops. The question of extending Ordnance factories in India is also being taken in hand.The Government of India have placed five Escort Vessels of the Royal IndianNavy at the disposal of the Commander-in-chief East Indies.The Cabinet conclusions on the recommendations of the Chatfield Com-mittee have now been published. The main item however the modernisation andre-equipment of the Army in India for which the grant of approximately 34.000,000 is being made, will now be seriously interfered with owing to thedemands of His Majesty&apos;s Government^ war effort on productive capacity.4. Foreign and Frontier Relations.Relations with A afghanistan are cordial. The Air Officer Commanding andthe Director of the Intelligence organisation have recently paid visits to Kabul.In recent years we have been helping the Afghan Government with sales of rifles and of aircraft, by training their Air Force personnel in India, and with acommercial credit of  500,000. A political credit of  250,000 is underconsideration. Given the stability of the present Afghan Government we can rely on its goodwill. There is, however, a potential danger to our interests inthe country and on the frontier in the relatively large number of Germans(96 excluding wives and families) employed in Afghanistan.The Afghan Prime Minister, who has always been nervous of Russian inter-ference, recently sounded us as to an assurance or mutual pact against aggression.The Afghan desire for this will have been increased by the Russo-German Pact.A proposal is being submitted to offer the Afghan Government an agreement for mutual consultation and assistance. Some of the advantages of this from our point of view would be to strengthen the position of the Afghan Governmentand to make sure of their co-operation for example, in rendering the Germancolony harmless.On the North- West Frontier, Waziristan, though now more peaceful, remainsa danger spot and the Faqir of Ipi is still at large; but the chief immediatecause for anxiety is a serious weakening of law and authority in the neighbouringBritish district of Bannu.   Measures to deal with this are under consideration.On the Arab shore of the Persian Gulf, the position appears satisfactory.The independent Sultan of Muscat has offered such assistance as is in his power(which, from the point of view of the Royal Navy in particular, is of some import-ance), and the protected Sheikhs of Koweit and Bahrein have given assurances of full support. Local defence schemes for the Gulf States have been approved(the small arms required for some of them are not yet available) and suchDefence Regulations as are immediately necessary have been issued under Orderin Council.The Government of India have some evidence of German intention to usePersia (where there is already a large German colony) as a base for organisingtrouble in India and elsewhere. Nepal has offered 8,000 troops for garrison dutym India. The Government of India, have expressed their thanks for this offer andpromised a further reply. Internally the position of the Maharaja-PrimeMinister is not very stable.In Tibet the child re-incarnation of the Dalai Lama has now been found, but,during the minority, power is divided between a Regent, a Council and aNational Assembly, with some resulting instability. The Government of india are now continuously represented by an officer at Lhasa.In Sinkiang since the time of the civil wars, which ended in 1937, when theChinese secured the ultimate victory over the Moslems with help from Russia,the latter has acquired an exclusive influence.   Indian residents in southern[19965] B 2
Sinkiang have been ill-treated and forced to leave, and our Consulate-General atKashgar has been prevented from functioning. The Consul-General has been senton a visit (for which permission was secured with great difficulty) to Urumchi, inthe hope of securing some alleviation.5. Indian States.The Rulers of Indian States during the period immediately preceding theoutbreak of war had under consideration the pi^oposed terms of accession to federation, to which an answer was due on the 1st September to the crown representative (see in this connection my Memorandum No. CP. 169 (39) of the27tb July). I have agreed with the Viceroy that present circumstances rendernecessary the suspension of consideration of the Rulers&apos; replies so far received and a postponement for the time being of further action in connection with the inauguration of Federation. The Rulers and the Indian Central Legislature arebeing so informed by Lord Linlithgow. At the same time he proposes to discussimmediate means of co-operation in India&apos;s defence and in the successful carryingon of hostilities with representatives of the Princes as well as with British Indianparty leaders.The outbreak of war was followed by manifestations from Indian Rulersgreat and small of their loyalty to the King Emperor and their willingness toplace all their resources at the disposal of His Majesty&apos;s Government. In theWar of 1914-18 States Forces were utilised both with Indian ExpeditionaryForces overseas and on lines of communication and for purposes of internal security in India. In addition, the States furnish a considerable number of2&apos;ecruits to the Indian Army.It has recently been publicly stated by the Maharaja of Bikaner that thefact that in various matters of detail explained in my MemorandumNo. CP. 169 (39) the Rulers of a number of States have not been disposed to agreeto the terms of Federation proposed for their acceptance will not affect his or hisbrother Princes&apos; loyalty to the cause in which the King Emperor&apos;s Forces are committed. It may be confidently expected that the States will not fall short inthe present war of the notable contribution made by them in the last &quot;War to theAllied cause.6. Economic Affairs.In regard to economic matters, close contact has been maintained for sometime past through the India Office between the authorities in the United Kingdomand the Government of India, and plans have been drawn up in India which arein conformity with those of the United Kingdom in regard to such matters astrading with the enemy and other measures of economic warfare. Arrangementsfor mobilising India&apos;s economic resources with a view to maintaining necessarysupplies in India and to meet Imperial requirements, are well in hand. Themeasures for which preparations had been made are being carried smoothly intoeffect, and all our information goes to show that the departments of the Govern -ment of India which are concerned with economic policy and administration arerapidly adjusting themselves to conditions of war.The rupee exchange has remained steady over the period immediately beforeand after the outbreak of war. A scheme of exchange control, concerted with theTreasury and the Bank of England, has been introduced.The monsoon has failed in some parts of India, and at one time there seemedto be a likelihood of a very serious famine. There has, however, been somerecovery and the results are not now likely to be of a far-reaching nature.Generally speaking the economic position of the peasantry is weak. Theywere hit very hard by the depression of eight or nine years ago. Some recoveryhad been made by 1937, but 1938 was a less favourable year. Prices are still onthe low side; a moderate rise would not be unreasonable, and would have a good effect on the general situation. But efforts will be required to ensure as far aspossible that the benefits of any such rise go to the producers and not to themiddlemen.Z.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,September 12, 1939.
ANNEXURE.1. Troops from India serving Overseas.Egypt 4 Field Btys. R.A. (British).2 Companies S. &amp; M.1 British Battalion.2 Indian Battalions.Ancillary troops (including one M.T. Company).Total-British ....      .........      .... 1,450Indian............... 3,000Singapore -4 Mountain Btys. R.A. (no mules).1 Field Coy. S. &amp; M.1 British Battalion.3 Indian Battalions.Ancillary troops (including certain additional Signal, Medical andR.I.A.S.C. personnel).Total-British ............... 1,000Indian............... 3,500Aden -1 Indian Battalion.Total-Indian ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 700Kenya 1 mountain Bty R.A. (no mules).Total-Indian ............... 100Iraq R.I.A.S.C. personnel.Total-Indian ............... 100Total sent overseas British troops ...       ...       ...       ... 2,450Indian troops ...       ...       ...       ... 7,4009,850Strength of troops (Combatant and Administrative Services) remaining inIndia-1st September, 1939-British............       ....        43,550Indian...............       131,500The balance of the External Defence Troops (details below) are now under orders to proceed to Egypt as soon as possible.Force Headquarters.4 Field Btys. R.A. (British).1 Field Coy. S. and M.1 British Battalion.2 Indian Battalions.Ancillary Troops.Approximate strength British..................       1,600Indian..................      2,450
Squadrons sent overseas 2 Bomber Squadrons to Singapore.Squadrons remaining in India 2 Bomber Squadrons.3 A. C. Squadrons.1 Bomber Tpt. Squadron.1 Indian Air Force Squadron (not yet complete).3 Offers of Troops to the Government of India.Nepal Two Brigades of 4 Battalions each.Indian States There is as yet no official intimation as to the number and character of thetroops offered by Indian States, but it may be assumed that they consist of theearmarked units which rulers are now pledged to make over to the militaryauthorities when required.

</content>
</cab>
