<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/7/69 images: 696-709</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)174th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 174 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Friday, June 21, 1940, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,   The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,M.P., Lord President of the Council.      Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,   The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Secretary   of   State   for   Foreign      Minister without Portfolio.Affairs.The following were also present:The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Viscount Caldecote,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. R. H. Cross, M.P.,Minister of Shipping (Items 7-9).Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Vice-Admiral T. S. V. Phillips, Vice-Chief of Naval Staff.Lieutenant-General R. H. Haining,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. H. L. d&apos;A. Hopkinson.Mr. G. N. Flemming.Major C. R. Price, R.E.
WAR CABINET 174 (40).Contents.minute no.                                         Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     .........      .........     537Air raids on Great Britain.Attacks on enemy aerodromes.Attacks on Germany.Attacks on submarines.Egypt.East Africa.2      The Military Situation        ...............     537Evacuation of B.E.F. from France.Middle East.3      Channel Islands        ..................     538-4      The Naval Situation..................     538The French fleet.The German fleet.The Italian fleet: sinking of an Italian submarine.Seizure of Swedish destroyers.Enemy attacks on shipping.Miscellaneous.5      France   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     539Arrangements for evacuation of the French Government.Transfer to custody in the United Kingdom of German air pilotstaken prisoner by the French.6      French Colonial Empire       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     539French Somaliland.7      France (continued) : Requests made by M. Corbin ...      ...     540Suggested dropping of food by aircraft for French troops.French shipping.The Emile Bertin.8      Deportation of internees      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     5429      Evacuation of children from Great Britain overseas     ...     54210      Belgium.........      ...      ............     543The children of the King of the Belgians.11      H.R.H. the Duke of Windsor......      ......      ...     54312      Egypt    .....: :    ............      ...      ...     54413      Urgent measures to meet invasion   ...       ...      ...      ...     544Internment of enemy aliens: repatriation of Italians.Suggested formation of a foreign legion.Decentralisation of control to regional commissioners.Calling up of men registered for military service.Declaration of an extended defended area. lUlDelegation of executive and financial powers, and avoidance of administrative delavs.14Man-power in the army545
Air Operations.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 1.)Air raid on great Britain.Attacks onenemyaerodromes.Attacks on germany.Attacks onsubmarines.Egypt.East Africa.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 171stConclusions,Minute 15.)1. The Vice-Chief of the Air Staff said that during theprevious day 4 raids had been plotted near and over the british isles, and 35 raids on the Belgian and French coasts. During the night of the 20th-21st June there had been no enemy activity.On the 20th June 4 patrols had reconnoitred enemy occupiedaerodromes in Northern France. Fifty J.U. 52 aircraft had been attacked on the ground at Rouen Boos of which 16 were thought tohave been damaged and 4 set on fire. Reconnaissances later in theday had shown 50 German aircraft on Merville aerodrome but ithad been too late in the evening to carry out an attack. EighteenBlenheims had set out to attack Schipol aerodrome (Amsterdam),but owing to weather conditions only 6 had attacked the target. all our aircraft had returned from these operations.Reports of the attacks carried out during the night of the19th-20th June on marshalling yards, aluminium factories, oil refineries and on the Dortmund-Ems Canal were very satisfactory,and mines had been seen to land in the canal The oil storage tanksat Brunsbuttel and the aerodrome at Norderney had been hit.During the night of the 20th-21st June, 62 aircraft had leftto attack chemical works, marshalling yards, and the air park atPaderborn. These operations had been interfered with by bad weather, and detailed reports from aircraft that reached the targets were not yet available. Two of our aircraft were missing and one had crashed in the sea, but the crew had been rescued.Mines had been laid at the southern end of the Great Belt andin the Ems.Aircraft of the Coastal Command had attacked 3 U-boats, onesuccessfully.The enemy had dropped pamphlets at Mersa Martruh on the19th June and had carried out a small amount of bombing and machine-gunning which had caused neither casualties nor damage.Three Italian aircraft had been shot down in the Sollum area and2 had subsequently been forced down and the crews taken prisoner.Dire Dawa aerodrome had been successfully bombed on the18th June by 11 Blenheims from Aden. In a combat over Yarvelloon the 19th June two enemy aircraft had been shot down and one machine on the ground had been bombed and set on fire; we had lost one Hurricane.Arrangements were being made to fly the former Emperor,Haile Selassie, to East Africa. He might have to proceed viaNigeria.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.A short discussion ensued as to air policy. This is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.The MilitarySituation.Evacuation of.E.P. from france.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Vice-Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that upto midnight the previous night 122,006 fit British troops and 2,174^casualties had been disembarked in Great Britain. No later detailed figures were available. Evacuation might be regarded as complete.Brest and St. Nazaire were clear of British troops. Two platoonswhich ought to have been evacuated from Cherbourg wereunaccounted for.La Pallice. -The operation had been completed, all Britishand Poles having been evacuated.St. Nazaire. 2,500 Polish troops had been taken off in  destroyers. No more troops were expected to arrive at St.Nazaire.
Le Verdon. 5,000 Poles had been evacuated.La Rochelle. Some 10,000 Poles had been evacuated.St. Male-No Poles remained to be evacuated.Bayonne. Arrangements were being made to evacuate5,000 Poles from Bayonne.There was no news to report from the Middle East.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.channel islands.(previous kef erence:W.M. (40) 172ndConclusions,Minute 12.)3. The War Cabinet were informed that the militaryevacuation of the Channel Islands had been carried out. Inaddition three transports with civilian refugees had left the channel islands on the previous day. The two Governors had left earlythat morning. That day would see the completion of the evacuation of such of the inhabitants as wished to leave.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 5.)The french fleet.The german fleet.Italian Fleet:sinking of anItaliansubmarine.Seizure otSwedishdestroyers.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 6.)Enemy attacks on shipping.Miscellaneous.4. The Vice-Chief of Naval Staff said that among the French warships which had arrived at British ports on the previous day had been the battleship Courbet, one destroyer, three submarines,three torpedo boats, one patrol vessel and two submarine chasers at portsmouth; and one destroyer, two submarines, three submarinechasers, six tugs and trawlers at Plymouth. The late arrival ofthe Courbet had been due to a message which had been put out byGermans in the French naval code.At 15-35 p.m. on the previous day the submarine Clyde,operating 60 miles north of Trondhjem Fjord, had sighted onebattle cruiser (probably the Scharnhorst) one pocket battleship andone destroyer proceeding in a North-Westerly direction. The Clydehad made one hit on the battle cruiser with a torpedo. From thelatest signals it appeared that some at any rate of the Germanvessels were making their way south again at full speed.Appropriate dispositions of British forces, including torpedo bombers of the Fleet Air Arm, had been made.H.M. Submarine Parthian reported having sunk an ItalianSubmarine off the North-East Coast of Libya at 3-30 p.m. on theprevious day. She had also attacked the Italian cruiser San Giorgioat Tobruk on the 19th without success, and reported greatlyincreased surface and anti-submarine activity.The Vice-Chief of Naval Staff said that in accordance withthe War Cabinet&apos;s decision of the previous day the destroyers whichSweden had acquired from Italy had been seized at the faroe islands. It was reported that none of them could steam on morethan one engine.In reply to a question by the Foreign Secretary, the Vice-Chiefof Naval Staff said that the Admiralty saw no objection to theSwedish Government now being told what we had done.The previous day seven merchant vessels had been torpedoed,six of them British. At least seven U-boats were believed to bein the Western Approaches. This was as many as at any time during the present war, while our smaller craft had been largelyengaged on other convoy duties.A convoy of three ships carrying Canadian troops had arrivedat Liverpool.
Twelve Swordfish aircraft had arrived at Malta.The floating dock at Malta had been badly damaged and it was feared that its back had been broken during an air raid early that morning.Two mines had been swept up off North Island, New Zealand.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.France.(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 3.)Arrangementsfor evacuation of the FrenchGovernment.Transfer tocustody inthe UnitedKingdom ofGerman airpilots taken prisoner by theFrench.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 173rdConclusions,Minute 3.)FrenchColonialEmpire.(previous reference:5. The Vice-Chief of Naval Staff said that the Admiralty hadbeen informed on the previous day that the French Governmentwere on the point of moving from Bordeaux to Perpignan in orderto be ready to evacuate to North Africa. It was thought desirable,with a view to forestalling any possible future complaints, thatBritish shipping should be in readiness to carry out the evacuation.Arrangements had accordingly been made to divert a number ofmerchant ships to Port Vendres, where they would remain in readiness. Two British destroyers had also been sent to PortVendres to act -as escorts.The latest news, however, was to the effect that the FrenchGovernment were remaining at Bordeaux for the time being. it seemed possible that their evacuation would take place from theWest Coast and a British cruiser was remaining at Arcachon until further orders.In any event, arrangements were being made for 5,000 French air Force mechanics and pilots and some remaining British subjects to be evacuated from Bayonne. Ships were available for thepurpose.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that lord lloyd, who had now returned to this country, had given a report as to the attitude of the French Government which fully confirmed the First Lord&apos;s report to the War Cabinet on the previous day.When Lord Lloyd had left Bordeaux on the previous night, it hadbeen definitely settled that the French Government would leave inan hour for Perpignan. Later, however, this move had been cancelled, and telephone communication had been opened with theFrench Delegates who had gone to Tours.Lord Lloyd had also brought with him a copy of a letter fromM. Herriot in very satisfactory terms in regard to the French Fleet,but he had now been asked that this letter should be treated asconfidential and should be destroyed. It looked, therefore, as thoughthe position had changed for the worse.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that, in spiteof our representations, the French Government had given us no satisfactory account of what they had done with the German airpilots whom they held as prisoners. It was a very unsatisfactorybusiness. It was just possible that the French intended to use thesemen as a bargaining counter in the negotiations for their armistice.The War Cabinet took note of the above&apos;statements.6. The Foreign Secretary reminded the War Cabinet that our action in sending instructions to the British Representatives in&apos; theFrench Colonies to do all that they could to ensure that the localauthorities should co-operate with us in continuing the strugglehad led to some criticism by the French Government and in w.M. (40) 172nd particular by M. Charles Roux. He proposed to send a further conclusions, telegram, a draft of which he read out, to the British Representa-Minute 5.)        fives in the French Colonies, which paid special regard to the need
for care if we were to avoid arousing French susceptibilities inthis way.French The  Lord  President  of  the  Council  asked  whether  the somali land.       desirability of taking steps to occupy Jibuti in case the Italiansshould try to seize it had been considered.The Secretary of State for War said that the local french commander had placed himself entirely under General WaveH&apos;orders, but in any case the French forces in that area were farstronger than our own and no attempt at occupation would bepossible without bringing troops from India. Up to the presentItalians had repeatedly flown over Jibuti, but had not yet bombed it.The Prime Minister thought that the French Commandermight be asked by General Wavell whether he desired any assistancefrom the British forces.The War Cabinet invited the Foreign Secretary to send to the British Representatives in the French colonial empire the telegram proposed by him.France (con-tinued).Requests madeby M. Gorbin.Suggesteddropping of foodby aircraft for french troops.Frenchshipping.(PreviousReference7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theFrench Ambassador had visited him that morning and had expressedthe opinion that the current of opinion in France which thoughtthat it was better to continue the struggle was gaining ground. Hehad urged that we should do all we could to encourage this move-ment, and to counter German propaganda to the effect that GreatBritain was already treating France as an enemy or as a colony.He urged, in particular, action on three points which would, in hisopinion, be very valuable in this sense.The Ambassador&apos;s proposals and the discussion on them are set out below. This discussion showed that it would be extremelydifficult to justify action on the lines proposed by the Ambassador.The Prime Minister also pointed out that the policy of theFrench Government would be determined, not by any action whichwe might take, but by the terms offered by the Germans.The Foreign Secretary said that he did not disagree with thisnor with the conclusions reached on the various suggestions, buthe could not help regretting that it was not possible even to alimited extent to follow the advice given by the French Ambassador,whose aim was, of course, exactly the same as our own.The French Ambassador&apos;s proposals were as follows : (i) We should send aircraft to drop food for French troopswho were continuing to fight in Eastern France.On this the Secretary of State for Air said that preparationshad been made to collect food and containers, but that, even if theFrench could indicate as many as six points for supplies to be dropped, it would only be possible to send six machines with one toneach. Further, owing to the short night, they would have a verynarrow margin of safety. He therefore thought that the results to be obtained were quite inadequate to justify the risk and diversion of effort which would be involved.There was general agreement with this view.(ii) We should allow French ships with food, &amp;o, to proceedto ports in Metropolitan France not occupied by theenemv.In connection with this proposal, it was explained that aW.M. (40) 173rd Meeting had been held on the previous afternoon, of representativesConclusions, of the Admiralty, the Ministry of Shipping and the Foreign Office,Minute 4.)
at which it had been agreed to recommend that French shippingnow in British ports should be allowed to proceed to French colonialports, excluding the Mediterranean, and that, in regard toMediterranean ports, some discretion should be given to the Rear-Admiral at Gibraltar.The Prime Minister said that the recommendations of thisMeeting had been brought to his notice on the previous evening,and, in consultation with the First Lord of the Admiralty, he had agreed that French shipping should be allowed to proceed to colonialports outside the Mediterranean.The proposal to allow French ships to proceed to the remainingunoccupied ports in Metropolitan France was, however, generally felt to stand on a different footing. These ports might at any moment be occupied by the enemy. Further, while it would bedifficult to justify holding up ship-loads of food destined fordistricts crowded with refugees, there was no evidence that foodcargoes were being held up. It was believed that most of the vessels were coal ships. &apos;It was agreed that no definite answer could be given to theFrench Ambassador until he could indicate more precisely whatships he had in mind, what the cargoes were, and to which portsit was intended that they should sail.The Minister of Shipping said that French ships for otherdestinations were still being held up in British ports overseas on various irregular pretexts. He wished to know whether he wouldbe right in continuing to hold such ships for, say, another 48 hours,until the situation should become clearer.It was generally agreed that this was tlhe right course to adopt.(iii) The French cruiser Emile Bertin with a cargo of goldnow at Halifax should be allowed to proceed toMartinique.On this it was explained that the gold to the value of 300 million dollars carried by the cruiser in question had been consigned bythe Bank of France to the Bank of Ottawa. It was not knownwhy it should now be desired to send it to Martinique and theCanadian Government were suspicious as to the genuineness of theorders given to that effect. Orders had been, given to the SeniorRoyal Naval Officer at Halifax to use persuasion and obstructionto stop the vessel leaving but not to take any warlike action.It was generally agreed that this course of action should becontinued.The War Cabinet-(i) Confirmed the instructions given on the previous eveningthat French ships detained in British ports should beallowed to sail for French Colonial Ports outside theMediterranean.(ii) Agreed that French ships for other destinations shouldcontinue to be detained on various pretexts, subject to possible reconsideration of the special case mentioned at(iii) (&amp;) below. -(iii) Invited the Foreign Secretary to reply on the following lines to the French Ambassador in regard to the threesuggestions which he had made.(a) It should be pointed out that we had begun to make preparations for transporting food by air for theFrench troops fighting in Alsace, but thattechnical difficulties and in particular the shortnight unfortunately made it impossible to carryout the operations.
(b) He should be informed of the decision at (i) above and should be invited to give definite informationas to the ships and cargoes which he suggested should be allowed to proceed to ports in metropolitan France and as to the particularports which he had in mind.(c) A temporising answer would have to be given asregards the French cruiser Emile Bertin atFlalifax.Deportation of 8.   The  Lord  President  of   the   Council  referred  to  the internees. Conclusion reached at the Meeting noted in the margin, that the(Previous ships which had been earmarked to take certain  TerritorialReference: Battalions to India should first be used to transport internees toW.M. (40) 166th Canada.   He had been informed that it was now proposed that conclusions, some of these vessels should be used to transport children to NorthMinute 4.) America.The Minister of Shipping said that he understood that theships originally intended for the transport of internees were in factbeing used for this purpose. One ship with 3,000 was sailing that night, and two others would sail in a few days&apos; time. Additionalships were being made available for the transport of children.It was suggested that it would be desirable to bring home tothe Dominions that, in the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government,shipping for the transport of internees or prisoners of war shouldhave priority over shipping for the evacuation of children.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that a message had been received from the Prime Minister of Canadaurging that no more requests of any nature should be made of theCanadian Government for the time being, as they had their handsfull.A suggestion was made that troopships outward bound toAustralia and New Zealand might carry internees.The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs toask the Governments of the Dominions, other than Canada,whether they would be prepared to accept internees orprisoners of war, or both, and, if so, in what numbers.Evacuation ofChildren from great BritainOverseas.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 170thConclusions,Minute 11.)9. In connection with the discussion on the preceding item,the Prime Minister said that he was perturbed as to the way inwhich the scheme for evacuating children overseas was developing.It was one thing to allow a limited number of children to be sentto North America; but a scheme for the evacuation of very largenumbers of children stood on a different footing and was attended by grave difficulties.In discussion, the following points were made : (a) It would be difficult to find the transport required fortransporting large numbers of children. The shipping companies disliked having more than a certain propor-tion of children on board ships, owing to the difficultiesof controlling them.(&amp;) Fast passenger ships had hitherto travelled unescorted. Ifthe Admiralty were to be asked to convoy these ships, itwould present a grave problem.
Belgium.The children ofthe King of the belgians.10. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed theWar Cabinet that he had received a note from the ApostolicDelegate to the effect that the Pope had obtained permission for thechildren of the King of the Belgians to leave France. The plan wasthat they should proceed to Lisbon and travel from ther,e to italy in the ship that was going to convey the Italian diplomatic party.It was represented that they were going to stay with their aunt in italy, though there was little doubt that they would in fact thenreturn to their father in Belgium. The Apostolic Delegate pressed strongly that we should allow these children to travel with the diplomatic party.The War Cabinet agreed That the Foreign Secretary should be authorised to informthe Apostolic Delegate that His Majesty&apos;s Governmentwould have no objection to the proposal that the children of the King of the Belgians should travel from Lisbon toItaly with the Italian diplomatic party.H.R.H. the duke of Windsor.(previous reference:W.M. (40.) 1ConclusionsMinute 4:)11. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs drew theattention of the War Cabinet to the fact that the Duke of Windsorwas reported to have arrived at Barcelona.The Prime Minister suggested that His Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Madrid should be instructed to get into touch with the Duke, to72nd Gffer him hospitality and assistance, and to ascertain his wishes.The War Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary to communicate with HisMajesty&apos;s Ambassador at Madrid on these lines.(c) On the other hand, if the ships were not escorted, the risks of the voyage were probably greater than the risks ofstaying in this country.(d) An offer from the United States to take 100,000 to 200,000children was expected. If this offer was received, theUnited States Government might perhaps be asked tofurnish transport for the purpose under the U.S. Flag.(e) It was clearly impossible to abandon the scheme, but thegeneral opinion of the War Cabinet was that the scheme should be damped down by the issue of a statementdrawing attention publicly to the difficulties and dangersinvolved.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Information in consultation withthe Ministers concerned, to prepare a draft broadcaststatement for consideration by the War Cabinet on thefollowing day.This statement should indicate that, while the Governmenthad not thought it right to put any impediments in theway of the scheme for evacuating children to theDominions, this scheme was bound to be limited in scope,owing mainly to the difficulties of providing transport.It should also be pointed out that the scheme was notunattended by risks to the children themselves, and thatthese risks might exceed the dangers to which they wouldbe exposed by remaining in this country.
Egypt. 12.   The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs informed the(Previous War Cabinet that he had seen the Egyptian Ambassador on the reference: previous day and had given him the reply from His Majesty TheW.M. (40) 173rd King for transmission to King Farouk, of which the essentialConclusions, passage was set out in telegram No. 483 DIPP of the 20th June.Minute 8.) &apos; The Ambassador had been outwardly helpful and had said that hewould telegraph to King Farouk urging him to accept the advice which was being offered him by His Majesty&apos;s Government.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.UrgentMeasures tomeet Invasion.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 170thConclusions,Minute 9.)Internment of enemy aliens.Repatriation ofItalians.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 161stConclusions,Minute 6.)13. The War Cabinet had a preliminary discussion on aEeport by the Chiefs of Staff on urgent measures to meet attack(W.P. (40) 213).Suggestedformation ofa ForeignLegion.Decentralisationof control toRegionalCommissioners.Calling up ofmen registeredf or militaryservice.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 172ndConclusions,Minute 13.)The Secretary of State for Home A ffairs and Minister of home security said that enemy aliens were being locked up as fast asaccommodation could be provided, and that the accommodationvacated by internees sent overseas would be filled at once. Reliablealiens were being combed out from those who had already been interned, but this would only result in the release of a limited number.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs suggested that steps might be taken to secure an Italian ship, now at a neutral port,which could be used to take Italians to Italy.This suggestion was welcomed by the Minister of Home security and the Vice-Chief of the Naval Staff, who undertook to examine it.The Prime Minister asked that the WTar Office should againconsider raising a Foreign Legion. Many enemy aliens had a greathatred of the Nazi regime, and it was unjust to treat our friendsas foes. Equipment might not be available for such a force immediately, but it could be found in due course. It would be aswell to have these men under discipline in the meantime. their services might be used in, for example, Iceland.The Foreign Secretary said that there were strong political arguments in favour of a quick comb-out of those aliens who were willing to fight for us.The Secretary of State for Home Affairs and Minister of home security said that the important thing was to ensure that the regional Commissioners would have on their staffs men of sufficientexperience and standing to deal on a regional basis, if need arose,with such problems as food, transport, and even banking. provided an adequate staff had been built up, the switch-over from central to regional control could be rapidly effected in emergency; but therewould be no advantage in making the complete change-over so longas central control was possible. It might, however, be desirable totransfer certain powers to Regional Commissioners in advance ofemergency, in order to facilitate the change-over.The Prime Minister thought that it would be undesirable tocall up men at a more rapid rate than was proposed by the Secretaryof State for War in his Memorandum on Man-Power in the Army(W.P. (40) 210). He suggested that the Minister of information should take action to explain to the public the un desirability ofswamping the military machine.
The discussion on the evacuation of children is recorded in minute 9.Declaration of Discussion took place on the suggestion that the area borderingan extended the coast from Tyneside to Portland, inclusive, should be declared adefended area,   defended area.The Secretary of State for Home Affairs and Minister of home security said that steps had been taken to declare a considerable part of this coastal area as a defended area, and that aliens hadbeen removed from the whole of this coastal strip. It was necessary,however, to have sufficient staff to control the movement of all personsin a defended area, and he was unwilling to extend the presentdefended area without further experience of the steps already taken.Delegation of In discussion, it was suggested that it might be desirable forexecutive and the Prime Minister to issue a directive to Departments to securefinancial powers, the avoidance of administrative delays. Further consideration ofand avoidance of this matter, and the drafting of a directive, were remitted to theadministrative    Lord President of the Council.clelays&apos; The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Secretary of State for War to re-examine thequestion of forming a Foreign Legion.(2) Invited the Minister of Information to take steps to explain to the public the undesirability of calling up menfaster than they could be absorbed by the military organisation.(3) Invited the Lord President of the Council to examine, inthe light of the discussion in the War Cabinet, therecommendations made in the Report by the Chiefs ofStaff, and to decide what action should be taken inregard to them.Man-Power in 14.   The War Cabinet again had before them a memorandum the Army. by the Secretary of State for War on Man-Power in the Army(Previous (W.P. (40) 210).Reference: The War Cabinet approved the proposals set out in this.M. (40) 172nd Memorandum.Conclusions,Minute 13.)Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,June 21, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
