<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/4 images: 52-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1942.MSECBET. Copy No. 29W.P. (42) 174.April 21, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.THE NEW GOVERNMENT AT VICHY.Memorandum by the Secretary of. State for Foreign Affairs.I CIRCULATE herewith to my colleagues an estimate of recent events inFrance by the Head of the French Department of the Foreign Office.A. E.Foreign Office, April 21, 1942.It has taken five days for the Laval Government to be agreed. During this time there was a continued barrage of announcements by the German wireless and very little was given out officially by Vichy.On the 17th April Marshal Petain presided over the Cabinet for the lasttime. All the Ministers handed in their resignations. Admiral Darlan,according to the official announcement, &quot; Successor-designate of the Head ofState, at the request of the Marshal, consented to assume under his directauthority the functions of Commander-in-Chief of the Land, Sea and Air Forces.&quot;After the meeting Petain conferred with Laval, but it was not until 5 p.m.on the 18th April that the new Cabinet was announced. The complete list isattached.On the 19th April Petain delivered the broadcast which had been expected and repeatedly postponed during the last four days. In it he said that Darlan,who remained his successor-designate, would take over the defence &quot; of ourterritory and our Empire. M. Pierre Laval will, under my authority, direct thehome and foreign policy of the country.&quot; The broadcast, which was very brief,ended with an appeal for unity. Petain&apos;s seal was thus attached to the sorriestepisode since the capitulation at Bordeaux.Laval, in conversation with journalists, is reported to have delivered himselfof some nauseating flattery of Petain, in the course of which he said that it wasnot correct to say that Petain had relinquished his powers; he (Laval) was thehead of the Government in virtue of the powers which the Marshal had delegated to him; and the MarshaFs authority was indispensable for the accomplishmentof his mission.This new arrangement cannot be satisfactory and will only last just as longas the Germans allow it to. It is a compromise. The Germans would probablvhave preferred that Laval should have clear control of the fighting service as well as of the administration. Petain seems to have stubbornly drawn the lineat that. He has put Darlan at the head of the three services and he has at lastsucceeded in having a Minister of War, who is a regular member of the Cabinet,appointed. (There has been no Minister of War since General Huntziger&apos;s death11697   [23734]
last autumn.) The Navy Minister is a brilliant young admiral who was made byDarlan. Air is placed in the hands of a general who is, I gather, a nonentity,and is not a full minister. Petain&apos;s presence is still of great value to the germans and so, for the moment, they accept the duality which has been agreed. Thisduality will be emphasised by the fact that Petain and Darlan are only onspeaking terms with Laval because the Germans have told them that they mustbe.   Darlan has announced that he has given up politics.It may also be announced, I think, that Petain refused to accept trade at andDoriot in the Government.In any case Laval will have quite enough to do internally for the present.There are indications that he will start with a clean up in Vichy itself. Hewill have to make France safe for the Germans, increase French production forthe German war effort, and increase the number of Frenchmen working in Germanfactories. These are important advantages for the Germans. By not having to occupy the whole of France they save several divisions for use elsewhere.Laval&apos;s Cabinet could not be much worse. Although Lucien Bonder remains,presumably at Petain&apos;s request, and the United States Embassy at Vichy speakwell of Barthelemy, who remains Minister of Justice, the rest of the civilians arecreatures of Laval.A Secretary of State has been appointed for the Colonies General Brevie.It seems possible, therefore, that for the moment the French Empire will be mainly regarded from the point of view of defence.Laval evidently intends to have one of his own creatures at the head of theMinistry for Foreign Affairs. M. Bochat is to be appointed to the Argentine in succession to Peyrouton, who preferred to resign rather than accept his dismissalfrom Laval.We can hope for nothing good from this Government. Mr. Matthews told me this morning that he has had a reply to the enquiry which he addressed tothe United States Embassy at Vichy about Petain and Darlan. The reply statesthat there is no indication that Petain contemplates resigning and that Darlanappears to have accepted his political defeat philosophically.Laval has staked his life on a German victory and will do everything in his power to assist in bringing it about.We do not know what further steps the United States Government have inmind. They have, technically, withdrawn Admiral Leahy, told United states citizens to leave France, and suspended the sailing of supplies to North africa and to France.   They will now presumably wait on events.
ANNEX.List of Ministers in M. Laval&apos;s Government.Wdr. General Bridoux.Navy. Admiral Auphan.Justice. Joseph Barthelemy.Finance. Pierre Cathala.Agriculture and Supply. Jacques Leroy-Ladurie.Education. Abel Bonnard.Labour. Hubert Lagardelle.Minister of State without Portfolio. Lucien Romier.Secretaries of State Air. General Jeannequin.Communications. Gibrat.Agriculture and Supplies. Max Bonnafous.Colonies. General Brevie.Health. Dr. Grasset,Secretaries of State to the Head of the Government Fernand de Brinon.Admiral Platon.Jacques Benoist-Mechin.Jacques Guerart.Police. Rene Bousquet.Secretary-General for Administration at the Ministry of the Interior:Georges Flilaire.Delegate-General for Franco-German Economic Relations : Jacques Barnaud.Secretary-General for Sports : Colonel Pascaud.Secretary of State for Information and Propaganda : Paul Marion.




</content>
</cab>
