<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/204/0 images: 80-84</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
\79JDOC UMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT.SAFEGUARDING OF INDUSTRIES.Matters requiring immediate consideration;.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade. I wish to submit for the decision of the Cabinet certain matters which require immediate attention relating to the arrangements in operation under the late Government for the Safeguarding of Industries by means of Customs duties.1.   The procedure for the Safeguarding of Industries which was in force under the late Government and is laid down in the White Paper (Cmd. 2327 of 1925) is still technically in operation, and although the White Paper has, of course, no legal force it would be open to any industry to make application for an enquiry under its provisions.    I suggest that an early opportunity should be taken after the re-assembly of Parliament to put on record that the Government do not regard the Safeguarding Procedure as any longer in force.2.    1 have already circulated to my colleagues the Report of a Committee of Inquiry into an application made-under the White Paper by a seotion of the Woollen Industry for the imposition of a Safeguarding duty on certain classes of woollen and worsted tissues.   The application was supported by the National Associa-tion of Unions in the Textile Trade as the result of a majority vote in the executive of the Association, but I understand that opinion was very far from being unanimous in favour of the course adopted.    It will be observed that the Committee came to the conclusion that the Applicant Industry had made out a good case for the imposition of a duty so far as regards the conditionsRETCOPY NO.C A B I N E T.
embodied in the White Paper.    They pointed out however that they were not called upon to report upon certain other considerations such as the effect of a duty on the export trade and&quot; on the home consumer, which were matters for the consideration of the Government in talcing its final decision.The Committee&apos;s report has not yet been published. It is, I think, highly desirable that it should be published without further delay and that at the same time a statement should be made as to the intention of the Government in regard to the application in order that the industry may be relieved from the present uncertainty as to the position it has to face.It appears to me to be clear that the Government should not ask Parliament to impose the duty applied for, and I should propose to publish the Committee&apos;s report and to make simultaneously-eously an announcement to that effect.3.     I attach (Appendix I) a list of the Safeguarding duties which were imposed during the last Parliament and are still In force. It will be seen that one of them, that &quot;upon lace, is due to expire in June, 1950, and others, upon gloves, cutlery and gas mantles, at the end of next year, while the remaining duties come to an end at varying later dates.   The Industries concerned in the case of the duties which expire next year will no doubt wish that they should be renewed for a further period and any action for this purpose would require to be taken in next year&apos;s finance Bill.   Similarly, If it were proposed to repeal the existing Safeguarding duties legislation to this effect would require to be Included In the next Finance Bill. An alternative would be to allow the existing duties to run their course while making it clear that the Government have no intention of considering their renewal.    In my opinion this last course is the wisest one to adopt. It will reqiilre no action In Parliament. There will undoubtedly be considerable pressure both In
Parliament and outside for an announcement of the Government^ intentions in regard to the Safeguarding duties, and it appears to me to be only reasonable that such an announcement should be made in order that the industries may be given the opportunity of adjusting themselves to the position.     I should propose, there-fore, If my colleagues approve, to announce at the first convenient opportunity after Parliament assembles that   whilst the Government have no intention of considering any applications for renewal of the existing Safeguarding duties they propose to let them continue for the respective statutory periods, unless in any particular instance it should be found at any time that grave damage is being done by the duty to some other substantial industry.-The Key Industry Duties must also be considered.     They were originally imposed by Part I. of the Safeguarding of Industries Act, 1921, for a term of five years, but the Finance Act, 1926, extended them, with seme additions and modifications, for a further period of ten years until the 19th August, 1936.     It is claimed for all these industries that the War showed that they were poorly developed in this country, but that their products were essential for defence purposes, or to the maintenance of our staple industries, or both.     In general they are small but highly technical industries.     A list of the Key Industry Duties is In Appendix II.     Again I suggest an announcement that the Government does not propose to disturb the present position.W.G.19.6.29,Board of Trade.
Appendix 1*Duties imposed -under the Safeguarding of Industries Procedure (Cmd. 2327).ArticleRate of Duty.Date of Expiration.Lace and Embroidery on net or dissoluble fabricutlery.eather Gloves ) )abric Gloves    )as Mantles.acking and Wrapping Paper.ableware of Translticent or Vitrified Pottery.utt ons *omestic Wrought , Enamelled Hollowware.331% ad valorem33*% 33^.6/- per gross on ) mantles. )4/6 per lb. on im-) pregnated hose)I   June 30th, 1930 December 21st, 1930December 21st, 1930. December 21st, 1930,16g$ ad valorem.        I  April 30th, 1931.28/- per cwt *33*% ad valorem. 3I 25% ad valorem.i  April 18th, 1932, April 27th, 1933.June 12th, 1933.
APPENDIX II.KEY INDUSTRY DUTIES.Imposed by Part I, of the Safeguarding of Industries Act, 1921, as amended by the Finance Act, 1926.Articles. Rate of Duty.Optical glass and optical instruments 50% ad valoremScientific glassware, lamp blown ware and 2,laboratory porcelain 33/&amp; %n     &quot;scientific instruments and gauges 33-V3??&quot;     &quot;V/ireless valves and vacuum tubes 33^3^&apos;      &quot;Ignition magnetos and permanent magnets 33^3$&apos;     &quot;Arc lamp carbons l/- a lb.Hosiery latch needles 33^3^ ad valoremlungs ten and ferro tung3ten 53^afo   &quot;       &quot;Molybdenum and ferro molybdenum 33^/5%   &quot;       11Vanadium and ferro vanadium 35^6%   &quot;       &quot;Compounds of thorium cerium and other rare ,earth metals 33j5%   &quot;       &quot;Synthetic organic chemicals, fine chemicals .and fermentation chemicals 3373 % 11       &quot;Amorphous carbon electrodes 33-y3^ &quot;       &quot;

</content>
</cab>
