<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 29-30</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TIE  GLYC3RIME  POSITIOH1918NOTES BY THS FOOD CONTROLLER.    I agree with, the Minister of Munitions  that, unless  additionaltonnage&apos;can be provided, thcro will be  a  shortage  of  glycerine  in1919, if the munitions programme for  that year is  to  stand  withan estimated reoujrement of 35,000 tons of  glycerine,  I am alsogenerally  in agreement with his recommendations.   If the  ministryof Shipping are able to carry out the tonnage programme  for theimportation of oils and oilseeds during the current year, theminimum requirements both of margarine  and  of glycerine  will be met,but if owing tc unforeseen contingencies  this programme  should  bematerially cut down, the output either  of margarine or ?f glycerineor of both would have to be reduced.  If more glycerine  is  neededeither for 1918 or 1919 more ships must be  provided.    The only alternative to the provision of the additional tonnageis the rapid completion of fat splitting  plants in India,  Ceylonand Australasia,   Some of the plant. I understand, is now  incourse of construction and  it should be possible  by making astrong effort to render some supplies of  glycerine available bythe end of this year.    I aii; rapidly reducing the minimum consumption  of oilsand fats for purposes other than the production of margarine andglycerine,  It -..111 be recalled that an January 11th, Iendeavoured, in view of the tonnage situation, to  stop the  useof/
        of linseed oil in the linoleum and leather o^oth trades, hut        on this matt or I v:ao overruled by the V.&quot;ar Cabinet at the        instance of the Board of Trade.4.          During the months of -January, February and March,        although tho amount of oilseeds and oil imported were V5%        short of the authorised tonnage programme, the allocation        made to the ;.&quot;:ap and candlo trades for glycerine was        within 2fs of the amount desired by the Ministry of Kunltiona.5.          I strongly endorse the Minister of Munitionsr appeal for        increased tonnage and if that should p rove impossible, I ask        for the :.:ar Cabinets1 instructions as to the proportion In        which available supplies of oil-seed should be allotted to        margarine, glycerine, other edible and industrial purposes.APRIL  3rd, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
