<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 65-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^SIXDC^FJ    THE, PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S SOVSRNMSNT. VSJL 0 R EJ,   &quot;*&quot;7AR CABINET.GvTi  4129,                         &quot;                   CONSCRIPTION IN IRELAND.ffi^Lpftndumv ^ vjie Attorney-General for Ireland.                          La?/ Room,                             Dublin Castle,                                 2nd April, 1918Dear &quot;Prime Kinister,              I think I am hound to state my views on thequestion of conscription for Ireland, and I Guhm.it a shortMemorandum of same.                        Sincerely yours,                             (Signed)  JAMES 0&apos;CONNOR.PRIME MINISTER        The question of conscription for Ireland has, I under-stand, been before the Cabinet.   I deem it my duty to give youmy views thereon in the belief that they will have some value ascoming from a member of the Irish Executive, who is a CatholicNationalist in close touch with popular opinion in Ireland, andwho has given both his sons to the service.        In my opinion the imposition of conscription would he ablunder.   It would inevitably lead to a rebellion.   It wouldcause the resignation, I should think, of more than one -memberof the Irish Executive - matters of no consequence in themselves,but bound to emphasize the fact that it is not merely extremistsor sinn fein opinion that is against the measure.        It would weld into an active and I may say virulentopposition to Government or to any attempts at settlement allIrish Nationalists, including the Bishops and Prrasts of myChurch,   It would create an animosity that fifty years wouldnot dissipate.        And, what is of the essence of the consideration, itwould prove ineffective, for
1,    The practical difficulties are immense, and the operationwould be slow, and involve the employment of a great number oftroops. .    Your conscripts would have a consuming hatred of the causethey were conscripted to serve,3.    Several Priests would be shot &quot;defending their flocks&quot;.4.    The attempt and its conssquences would seduce from  theirallegiance the Irish, the American Irish, the Australian  Irishand the New Zealand Irish Catholio troops at tho front, andwould introduce treason into your army.      The views I have  expressed hold good even if thsconscription measure were accompanied by a scheme of MidletonHome Rule, or by any measure of Home Rule, Colonial or other-wise.   This ia my profound conviction.      The course I suggest is:-1*    Pass &quot;Colonial&quot; Home Rule giving Ireland full fiscalautonomy at once for all Ireland on a democratic basis. I thinkIreland will accept nothing leas, end certainly will not accepta Parliament with a &quot;forty per cent&quot; Unionist clause in it.It would be wise to leave the question of Imperial contributionto be settled by the Irish Parliament.2.    On such a generous measure being passed, I think a bigrecruiting campaign could be started successfully in Ireland,and I think that the leaders of all Irish sections would unitein forwarding it.3.    Later, say after a Home Rule Act was in operation forthree  months, the  question of Irish conscription might bere-considcred.  I  foresee, even then, ^reat difficulties aboutit.      If the plan I suggest , or something like it,  be not&amp;4Ppted, your only policy in future will be naked coercion.      I am forced to the conclusion that the Midleton HomeRule plan will not be accepted having regard to the fact thatthe Irish people will regard it as an equivalent and aninadequate equivalent for conscription.                             (Sgd.) JAMES 0*CONNOR.                                     Attorney General for  Ireland.Law Room.   Dublin Castle.End April. 191S.

</content>
</cab>
