<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 67-68</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
u                                                    UTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Off EIS BRIT AMI C MAJESTY1 S GOVERMENT.VERY SECRET.   &quot;                              &quot;CAB METGaT.-4130.                       SUPPLY SERVICES IK FRANCE.              Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War,          In the event of the railway lines BEAUVAIS - AMIENS -     SERQUEX - ABA.NCOURT - AMIEHS being denied to the Allies, the     situation as regards supply generally requires sorious consider a-     tion.  In this connection it must be emphasised that the line     SERQUEX - ROMESCAMPS has had to be handed over practically     entirely for French use, thus compelling the policy that was in     force of supplying the British Armies mainly from the Southern     Depots to be set aside,     Although it is hoped that  the railway line may be releasedto a considerable extent of the French  traffic that it nowhas to carry, yet so much depends on the progress  of  operationsthat no guarantee that it will  be so released can  be  given.     It is furthermore desirable that tho general  policy ofsupply should be decided in the event of the two linesmentioned being altogether lost to traffic.     There are many points that require decision,  but the mainissues on which a 77ar Cabinet ruling is required are:-   fa)  The provision of coal to the French,        At present, from the BRUAY mine fields, some  750,000   tons monthly are extracted.  Of this total, about  45,000   tons are transferred to the  British  Army in exchange for   a similar amount sent direct from England to a  Frenoh   Southern Port,   Given that some 50,000 to 60.000 tons are used  monthly   for French Military and Civil purposes North of the Somme,   approximately 600,000 to 650,000 tons are sent  by  rail   South of AMI3J3S,   Y,Tith the  rail facilities blocked, this   would entail an increase of  our present monthly contribu-   tion of coal to the French of at least 50o.OOO  tons, making   in all 1,750,000 to 2,000,000 tons     it the present moment, there is considerable  congestionon the lines in the Bruay mining area and a large  accumulationof coal at Pit mouth.     The questions relative to this subject that requiredecision are               (l) Can we provide this  additional  coal ?                    And if&apos; so,               (2) Can the additional ships be found  ?   ^ The second main point is the supply to the  Frenoh       and Belgian Military aSdTiyil&apos; inhabitants. Injbhe Area       florth of.the Somme of the necesgary foodstuffs and       other commodities required by them.     The requisite foodstuffs are estimated at some 40,000tons per mensem;  oils, petrol and numerous other  articles forfactories and installations at  5,000 tons - say 50,000 tons in
all ^ich is probably a minimum estimate.The ouestions to be decided are:-                (1) &apos;?ill the necessary food,  forage, etc.,                   be furnished by the  British  Government  ?                         And if so,                ( ) are the ships forthcoming ?   Timber.   &quot;Tel  fhe timber operations of  the British Army  ForestryDirectorate in  the South of France now  provide  about  110,000tons of timber  of sorts for Army requirements.  Without railfacilities this would have to be provided by sea  from aFrench Southern Port to a Northern Port, or  from  overseas.The questions to be decided are:-                fl) Should this timber be supplied as  at                   present, or from home ?                         And in either  case                (2) Can the necessary ships be furnished T   (d) Installation essential to the British Army are       establi&apos;slieT*^F^ouenJ and Havre.  Unless  repairs, etc.now undertaken&quot;&apos;by these installations can be undertakenin England, a regular coast service between ROUEN -HAVRE and CALAIS or BOULOGNE,, must be instituted!VThiehever plan is adopted the question that requiresdecision is        fl)  Thether the necessary ships and Escort             can be found ?NOTB.     The supply of ITALY generally, the move of      personnel to the East, and the administration of the      Aerodromes in the NANCY Area, would have to be under-      taken by the &apos;7ar Office.  This, however, also has a      direct bearing on the shipping problem,                            (Signed)    DERBY.4th April, 1918..

</content>
</cab>
