<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 163-164</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Doc urnHis Brit&amp;onjcman  fo?.i-;k  and  food  controlMEMORANDUM  BY  THE  FOOD  CONTROLLER     I understand that proposals are now before the &apos; ar Cabinetfor extending the age limits for compulsory military service andotherwise Increasing the numbers of men transferred from civilianto military life.   I have not had an opportunity of seeing theseproposals,  but I desire at once to call the attention of the WarCabinet to  two points In which they may seriously affect questionsof food supply i-     (1) with. the present rations, each man transferred from civilianto military life means an increased consumption of meat of about4 lbs a week.    Every 100,000 men so transferred will thus involvean increased consumption of about 180 tons a week.   I do notthink that our meat supplies are sufficient to stand this additionaldrain,  and I would therefore urge that arrangements be made toreadjust the Home Army rations before any considerable numbers ofadditional men are called up.     The estimate of 4 lbs a head is for butcher&apos;s meat and offalalone,  talking the Home Army ration at 70 02. per week and the offalwhich is consumed in canteens (about 8 02. per week) as equivalentto another 4 02. of meat.   Bacon is omitted, as, with the presentrations, there would be in some cases an Increase of consumption   transference to the Army,  and In others a decrease (if the man Inquestion werethe/
holder of a supplementary ration card).    Therations taken Into account for the Army arethose now In force  for the home troops, and forcivilians are those that will be in force asfrom May 5th neat.     (2)  The calling up of men, unless  it isvery carefully safeguarded, may imperil  both foodsupply (e,g. in the flour mills) and foodrationing and distribution (if tho staffs of theLocal Authorities, Food Control Committees orWholesale Distributing firms are further depleted).I do not think It is possible to diminish theactual work done in any of thesw directions;indeed it is more likely that the work mayactually increase.          I would strongly urge that these pointsshould receive careful consideration before adefinite decision is arrived at.                      RHCKDDA.MINISTRY OF FOOD,   5th April, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
