<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 185-192</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PI 4 2Note by C.I.GtS* on the Eastern Situation,-* r ts v -          I attach a memorandum by Brigadier-General Knox onthe situation in the Eastern Theatre, and I desire to draw theattention of the War Cabinet to the conclusions at which hearrives.   The first of these conclusions is that no reliancecan bo placed on Trotsky&apos;s promises to resuscitate the RussianArmy.  I think this proposition is self-evident.   HieBolsheviks have succeeded in completely destroying alldiscipline in Russia;  they have undermined the influence ofthe officers;  they have abolished all authority whethermilitary, civil or religious;  they have disbanded the oldarmy;  they have lost the greater part of its war materialand equipment:  and, to sum up, they have produced a state ofohaos which only long years of firm and patient administrationwill be able to reduce to order once again.    The whole objectof the Bolsheviks, or at any rate of those of them who aresincere, is the overthrows! of the existing order of society,and no other result can be anticipated from their policy.It is possible that those of them who art m-t working in theinterests of Geimany :i,ey now be al aimed at the results theyhave achieved, they may see that they have ha.no.ed theircountry to a nation whose principles are absolutely opposedto there which they themselves profess., and that the triumphcf Germany must mean the defeat of Bolshevism,   At the sametine they have rendered. Pus si a prveilere tc oppose it, and theymust know that no existing Governments. - all oi which arecharacterized by then as capital:stio, bourgeois orimperialistic, - whether of Greet; Britain, Prance. Ameiicaor Japan axe going to assist them in producing that universalanarchy which they desire.   There is consequently no isasonwhy we should consult their wishes or suppose that their aimsin any way coincide with our own and we should accordinglytake such steps; irrespective of them, as the interests ofGreat Britain and of the Entente demand.          These interests, as General Knox points out,  are     (l)  the prevention,  so far as is possible,  of Germanydrawing labour and supplies from Russia,  and among thesesupplies must be placed the vast cuantities of stores and warmaterial now at Arkhangel  and Vladifrostock;     (2)  the checking of  German mil itary,  political andeconomic penetration into  European Russia.  Siberia,  Caucasia,Turkestan and Persia, and the protection  oi&quot; China and moreespecially of India from enemy inrluerices;     (3)  the prevention cf further enemy withdrawals of  troopsfrom Russia, either to the Western. Italian,  Macedonian orTurkish theatres.          Lord Robert Cecil in his memorandum on  the RussianSituation dated the 1st April, has advanced convincing  argumentswhy no further money or efiort should he  expended in assistingthe formation of the new army which,  exco-dveg tc Lockhart,Trotsky is new acvocat:np*    I am invit^b andthe real:f\&apos;accord nth hislat:; would urge that  the only  effective means towards                            v.o be icv-nc nr. early                    intei vo nJ. 3 c:i should form the-                          i -on oi0.1our on^ectcJapanese :ute-rventi on.    Thi ekeystone of our policy,  as none of oui  objects  can be gainedwithout military force,  and no Entente  r.ation;  other thanJanan
 Japan, is now in a position to apply sufficient force  in Russia.          Japanese intervention is now recognised,  even by those Russians such as M. Uaklakov,  the ambassador appointed &quot;by Keren sky1 s Government to Paris, who were formerly opposed to it, as the one hope of salvation.   To be effective it must be immediate, and it must be pushed  as far west as practicable, at any rate to Omsk, if possible to  Samara.   To obviate political difficulties the Japanese  should be given a joint-mandate by the Allies, backed if possible by an invitation from some local Siberian administration.   Their troops should &quot;be accompanied oy Allied Missions, and they should endeavour to rally all those Russians whe are  opposed to German domination.   Semencv&apos;s force would  form a nucleus round which these loyal elements should be formed, and the services of a British colander and of 3ritish officers should be utilised in organising, training and commanding the resultant corps whose employment would be directly controlled by the Japanese Commander-in-Chief*          Japanese intervention would hare the direct effeot of securing the stores at VIadivostock;  of restricting pari passu with the advance of the troops, the region from which Germany can draw supplies.;  of checking the withdrawl  of German troops from Russia, if not attracting them to that country from elsewhere;  and indirectly of encouraging all anti*German elements in Russia, Caucasia, Turkestan or Persia to oppose the enemy&apos;s designs.          I would emphasize the need  of Japanese intervention - being immediate.   \7e are already hearing of stores being removed by the Bolsheviks from Arkhangel and Vladivostock; in the interests cf cur operations in France np further reinforcements, should reach the Germans from the Russian front;  while the opening of the passes on the Persian frontier, which will take place this month, will probably lead tc an increase *f enemy activity in  that region.   For every reason we must decide at once and act without further delay.          I think Geiteral Knex1 s observations regarding the situation in Persia deserve most careful attention.   Tho policy he advocates is that urged by the General Staff for many months past.   It is that we should occupy Isfahan, raise local levies, consolidate our position, and eventually advance on Tehran and Resht.   T7e need have  no scruples about  violating Persian neutrality, we and the Russians have done that long ago, and we may rest assured that no such scruples will deter the Turko-Germans from prosecuting their designs on India. We should also pay no attention to the alleged unwillingness of Russia, to see British troops in  North- We stern Persia   Ho Russian Government exists, Russian public opinion is inaohate; in any case it is owing to Russia1&amp;  failure that our position in Persia and India has been jeopardized;  and if we are not to risk the loss of our Indian Srnpire we must come to an immediate decision as to our policy.   Rapidity tf action is essontial, a comparatively small expenditure of force now will probably be far more effective than a much larger expenditure some months hence.   Failure now to forestall a German coup d&apos;etat in Tehran or to prevent Turcc-German detaclxaents from penetrat-ing into Afghanistan may create such situations as will requirelarge
large armies to deal with hereafter,  while  rapid anddetermined action may still save the Armenians and otherelements of resistance in Caucasia and inspire them tocheck .the advance of the ill equipped and ill-fed Turkishforces now opposed to them.         Even in Persia our success will &quot;be largely dependentupon Japanese intervention in Siberia, as it is only by  suchintervention that the situation can be restored in Transcaspiaand the per.tt*atlon of Afghanistan by enemy bands across  theNorthern frontier prevented.        . With regard to Arokhangel, I am .1 oath to suggestat the present time any further expeditions, but, if Japanintervenes, I think that a small force sent there with asuitable naval escort should secure the stores, by evacuatingthe population and destroying the railway leading to Vol&amp;gda.         To sum up, -I am of opinion that    1.   Nothing of military value can be hoped for from        - Trotsky..    2.   Japanese intervention is becoming daily more urgent         and indeed vital.    3.   A speoial military effort should be made-to save         our stores at Arkhangel.                              *    4*   Energetic action  should be taken in Persia;attd I would add that unless we act and act at once on theabove lines we shall gravely imperil our position in IPranceand Italy.                            (Sgd.) Henry.Wilson,                                              0.X..G.S.General Staff,    War Office.        6th April,  1918.
MEMORANDUM BY 3RIGADIER GENERAL KKOX OH THE          SITUATION IN THE EASTERN THEATRE.Situation,          The Central Powers negotiated with the Bolshevikssufficiently long to allow the latter to complete the finaldisorganisation of the Russian Army, and then moved forwardto seize the material of war abandoned by the Russiansoldiery and to make a bid for the sympathy of the Russianeducated classes by establishing order,    They have sentarmed support to the Yfoite Guards in Finland in their contestwith the extreme socialists.  They have stopped half a dozenmarches West of Petrograd but they can occupy one capital atwill firing scarcely a shot.   Their troops are advancingEast through the Ukraine restoring order as a preparatory stepto the collection of supplies.   Their agents have been formonths carrying on an active propaganda among the Mohammadentribes cf the Caucasus and the Tartars of Trans-Caucasus.          The Turks have recaptured Trebizond and Erzerumand are moving forward to occupy the provinces of Kars,Ardahan and Batoum which they have recovered by the treatypf Brest Litovsk.          The Bolsheviks are working in conjunction withhostile agents in Northern Persia to reiee popular feelingagainst the Persian Government which has only authority inplaces where it can rely on British iorcee    GeneralDunaterville&apos;s BritiBh Mission whose object was to help theArmenians in the Allied interests had. been forced to retireto Hamadan,          In Siberia East of Tomsk there are 40(0C0 enemyprisoners of whom 8,000 are German Officers and for manyweeks reports have been received that they are being armed,          Erom Murmansk in Northern Lapland where there aresome hundreds of British sailors fcc Shirax where there is aBrigade of South Persian Rifles the only armed adherents ofthe Allied cause in 2,500 miles are some 60.000 Czecns inNorth-Eastem Ukraine, who are fighting for their livesagainst the Austro-German troops.          The 160^000^000 of the Russian people are as clay inthe hands of the invader.   The patriotic national ideals of tfirst Revolution have been temporarily eclipsed by the inter-nationalist programme of the Bolshevik leaders,  not one in tenof whom is a Russian.  The educated classes are paralysedwhile the uneducated masses have been for the moment misled bythe Bolshevik appeal to their cowardice and cupidity.          It would be suicidal madness for the Allies totrust to Trotsici^s promise to resuscitate the RussianArmy.          Kerenski had national feeling and failed, thoughassisted by the officers, in his appeal to the patriotism ofthe soldiers.          The Bolsheviks are internationalists pure and sizzle
and  they have  alienated every individual  who  knows  what  anarmy is and  could  assist in  its  formation.          About  1,000,000 tons of coal  and  stores,  the propertyof the Allies, now lie  at Arkhangel.  The stores  include about14,000 tons  of copper,  5,000 tonti  of  lead,  3,000  tons ofantimony, and  6,662 bales of leather.   The  evacuation of partof the stores  to the interior had  already commenced by the8th  March.   At Vladivostock  there  are about 600,000&apos; tonsof stores.Our  objects*          Our  objects must be during  the  war;-      (l)  To limit as far as possible the supplies  andlabour Germany obtains from Russia.      (2)  To check German penetration by  helping  everynationality  or element  of a  nationality that  is willing  tooppose German  intrigue,  and  to protect  the  Indian andChinese Empires  from the disintegrating effect of pan-Turanian propaganda^Steps Recommended.          To further the above objects  the  following measures  -are  recommenced:-          ^a)  The occupation of Arkhangel*          \b)  Japanese  intervention.          (c)  Certain military measures  in Persia.      [A) --Jte j^upat ioja.-^                      of--5,ooomen  would have a ^woroloUabjlec-tf.irst&apos;,  to&quot; prevent  the  .etores..froffl.:tf8*liing--4n^o&apos; the hands ot-fcfee Germans.   This  mightbe effected by &quot;blocking  the  railway which runs for 400 mile3from Vologda through practical^uninhabited  country, wh54e thestores were  removed or destroyed.  Secondly,  in the  event ofthe  Allies abandoning their  policy  of drift in the East bycalling in the Japanese^  to  prove to Russia by the presence ofa small international- force  that the Japanese were acting in .-vstrict aocord with  the other  Allies-  This  expedition wouldnot  be recommended if it  necessitated the employment of asingle man who would be  of use in France,  but it  is  thoughtthat it could be carried  out  &quot;by men of  the Royal Defence Corpswho  would never be  sent  to the Western  Theatre.   If  thisforce is to be of  any use  it  should start as soon as possible,so as to arrive  at Arkhangel  before the 25th April, when the iceflow usually commences and prevents navigation for about a week.      (B)  Japan  should land  troops at Vladivostock andpush them rapidly along  the  Siberian Railway,This  operation -does not present any great military difficulty at present butit has... been discussed for  t-/o months and advertised  in thePress&apos; and every day&apos;s delay  will increase the difficulty, forthe  Germans and  their Bolshevik allies may make arrangementsto meet it &quot;by  organising  the  prisoners  of war and destroyingbridges.The
          The population of Siberia is small - under 10,000,000in all.  The disorganised soldiery and the hooligans in thetowns are Bolshevik but the peasants are net for they are largepeasant proprietors and have nothing to gain from theMaximalist agrarian programme.  The Russians in 1905 supportedan Army of 1,000,000 men in Manchuria by a single line of railfrom European Russia.  The Siberian railway is now practicallydoubled throughout, and Western Siberia is as rich in food-stuffs as Manchuria.           The Japanese have given their Allies to understandthat they wish to come in alone and unaccompanied by armeddetachments of the other Powers.  In order to deprive the enemyof the plausible propaganda argument that the Allies havehanded over Russia to the Yellow Races, the Japanese must come -in with an Allied mandate and their intervention must beheralded by a sympathetic proclamation to the Russian peopleexplaining that help is being sent to Russia to restore herlost nationality and her Church and to r,epel the invader.It must be clearly explained that there will be no interferencewith Russian internal politics and above all the proclamationmust be addressed to the Russian people and not to the Bolshevikfraction who have * temporarily usurped the functions ofGovernment,          Russians have stated that they know they have topay the price to someone and they would prefer to pay Japanrather than Germany.  It would be advantageous though notessential that any territorial compensation demanded by Japanshould be agreed upon beforehand and published.          The Japanese forces should be aocompanied byAllied Military representatives to encourage active Russian  1elements of all parties to co-operate in the movement.          The Japanese should be encouraged to move as farWest as possible - to Chelyabinsk - whf** they would controlall Siberia or preferably to Samara, where they would controlthe Volga waterway and the cotton carrying railway toTashkent.  They would act as a mobile military base, a nucleusof regular armed force affording moral and if necessarymilitary support to the Russian emissaries and detachmentsin their front and on their flanks who would work constantlyto awaken the dormant idea of Russian nationality whileharraesing the enemy&apos;s propagandists and forces by everymeans in their powerc          Russian paper money is now worthless for no onehas paid any taxes for a year, and the Treasury has been fed bythe activities of the Government printing press.  The Japaneserelieving force would be enormously assisted in its task if itcould pay for its requirements in silver roubles which mightbe stamped &quot;Siberia&quot;.  It is thought that the United Statesof America where there are large accumulations of silver mighthelp in this respect.          The enemy has still some 47 divisions in the Easterntheatre but he is transferring them to the West as fast as hecan.  Nothing but a rapid Japanese advance can stop thistransfer which if allowed to continue is in danger of over-whelming the Allies in the Western theatre before the United                                                         States
ooStates of America can come to their aid.          German public  opinion will be desperately depressedby the active tntry of a new en way in the fourth year of war.          There is another aspect of the question,  japan is  4the only great military  power in the world untouched &quot;by thewar.  She has a growing  population and an ambitious Government.It is hotter for the future peace of the world that she should-be encouraged to turn her eyes to the West rather than Southto the Philipines and Australia or East to California.  To gofurther it is essential  that Japan Bhould &quot;bo actively enlistedon the side of the Allies and not alienated by our mistrust,for in the latter case,sha would moot certainly come to anagreement with Germany and between them they will divide upRussia and dominate the  world.          Japanese intervention is the whole corner-stone ofa rational policy and strategy in the Eastern theatre.  Withoutit the occupation of Arkhangel would be useless and anymilitary measures we might take in Persia would be only nibblingat the problem.  It is not a mere bread and butter policy ofdenying the grain and butter of Siberia to the enemy, it isthe one chance of saving civilisation from German Kultur,          It does not require the withdrawal of a single manor gun from other theatres.  It requires no allocation oftonnage,     (c)  The defection  of Russia has increased our difficultiesin the Middle East,  Since the beginning of the War the enemy-has made persistent efforts to oause trouble in this directionin order to compel us to detach force from the Western Theatre,--He early sent emissaries through Southern Persia to Kabul and adraft treaty waB actually signed with the Amir by whichGermany promised to send 100,000 modern rifles and 300 guns.Her designs were prevented by our advance in Palestine andMesopotamia and the situation in Persia was for the timerestored by Russian measures in the North and by the raisingOf the South Persian Rifles in 1916,          The main objeot of the foreign policy of theGovernment of India has  always been to protect India by a systemof buffer states from access by any great military power,  Eorthis reason Afghanistan  has been subsidised and the Northernboundary of the neutral  sphere of influence in Persia in theAnglo-Russian agreement  of 1907 was drawn from the ZulfikarPass at the North Western angle of Afghanistan,          The bogey of a Russian military expedition againstIndia has only disappeared to be replaced by the real danger ofGerman intrigue-.  This is a much more real danger for no largeforces are required.  The Germans posing as the protectors ofthe Turks have naturally attracted the sympathies of theAfghans.  A reverse to our prestige in the East such as the fallof the Government in Persia accompanied by the appearance of a  ,;small Turko-,German force in Afghanistan might be enough tocause the Amir to throw  in his lot definitely with the enemy.The proclamation of a Hholy war&quot; in the close neighbourhood ofthe Indian Empire where  there are 66,000,000 of Mohammadanswould call for a reinforcement of the handful of troops inIndia to an extent which is at present impossible.                                                       The
          The recent treatise have shewn clearly the enenry**designs in the if id die East.  Rpumania has been forced te cedeConstantza and Russia to cede the provinces of Kars, Ardahan andBatoum.  A bid was  made in the Brest Litovsk treaty for thesupport of national sympathy by a clause declaring the independ-ence of Afghanistan and Persia.          Enemy agents for work in Persia can land the Trebizondand march through Ejszerum to Tabriz, or easier still, they canrail through from Batourn to Tabriz via Julfa or they can railto Baku and take ship for Snzeli and thence march to Teheran.          Enemy agents to Afghanistan need no longer trampthrough Persia.  They can cross the Caspian from Baku and travel&quot;by the Central Asian railway to either of the jumping offplaces prepared by the Russians on the Afghan frontier atKumhk and Teriaez, or failing Japanese intervention they canreach either place travelling through Central Russia viaSamara and Tashkent.  There are numerous enemy prisoners inTurkestan and it will be an easy matter vhen the time comesto arm a detachment  oi them to make a show of strength in Kabul,          If the Caucasian Military Mission had reached itsdestination it might have aone much to block the new Germanhighway to the East,  The problem is now more difficult and onthat account demands immediate decision and energetic action,                          4          Troops are being sent from Baghdad to Ramadan,  TheSouth Persian Rifles accompanied by regular troops if possibleshould be moved forward from Shiraz to Ispahan,  Local leviesshould be raised and the position consolidated with a view toa subsequent advance on Teheran and Resht.  An independent lineof communication Bhould be opened from the Gulf, as the line frcmBaghdad to Hanadan is parallel to the front and dangerouslyexposed-  If necessary, nationalist opinion can be conciliatedby the explanation that the occupation is only temporary andthat the idea of an independent Persia will be supported afterthe war.          The occupation of Samara by the Japanese, or as aresult of their intervention, would control railway communicationto the Afghan frontier from the North-West, A small force ofregulars should be despatched by the ITushki route to Meshedwhence British influence might be extended among the Turkomanto Central Asian railway at Askha-bad,          The small additional forces required for thesemeasures can be detailed from the native army in India and neednot be withdrawn from any theatre of war.          The three proposals - the occupation of Arkhangel,  theintervention of the Japanese and an advance in Northern Persiaare all advocated.  The last two are interdependent,  their needis urgent and they should be carried into  effect at once,  forthe efficacy of the jieaaures advocated is  in direct proportionfrom a military and political point of view to the rapidity withwhich they are carried into effects26th March, 1913,

</content>
</cab>
