<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 211-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This Document is the Property oT  G&amp;4rrU,t Ju^CsQ^j 1,8&apos;April 5th 1S1 .    PENSIONS  181/6fa CAB/A//^/^---^S^pary  of Heport  for  period from 1 arch 29th to       5^       )f Feng ions.    8007 pensions and allowances have been  rantedduring the week to  Officers and 1-en and to  idows, children, anddependants.    The number since the berinnins of the .?ar is 1235510.2.   Pensions  to Soldiers.   During the week out of 3261 cases(including 50  rejected under previous &apos;.-ar rants) dealt ./ith by theAwards to Soldiers  Branch 2468 were awarded pensions, permanent ortemporary, 7e3  were granted gratuities and 20 vrere rejected.3.   Since the  beginning of the war 468650 fresh claims from soldiershave been dealt with.    Rejections prior to the introduction of thenew Warrant averaged 31$ of the claims, since that date they haveaveraged .6^.4.   Pensions  to Widows and Dependants.   During the week 706 widows(including unmarried wives), 922 parents and 49 other dependantswere awarded pensions  and 1234, children &quot;were granted allowances.5.   Forfeiture &amp;c  of flidow&amp; Pensions.   During ?arch there aere58 cases  of forfeiture and suspension and 32 administrations in trust.7 pensions were restored.6*   New Scheme  of Pensions to parents.   Und$r a recent concessionthe pre-war dependence of 56 parents $ho vere in pecuniary need has,during the week, been raised from an average of 6/- a week to anaverage of 11/9, w&amp;ilst 73 unpensioned parents In pecuniary needhave been granted an average pension of 10/- a week 96 cases havebeen refused ^pension.7.   Alternative Pens ions.   Disabled men.   Up to date 22permanent &amp;nd  534 -conditional alternative pensions have been awarded.:this represents an  increased annual charge of  25792 upon theminimum pens ions.   156 men under  treatment and training arereceiving alternative  pension allowances.   ridows.   Out of 3006claims for alternative pensions there have been 1556 awards  and 568rejections.   This  represents an increased annual charge of  26938upon the minimum pensions cf t^se widovjs.
8.   Amendment of Koyal Warrant.    The final draft of the nev/ arrant Is :?ith the Treasury.    It is hoped that it may take effectas from the 1st &amp;ay.9,   Fens ions  Appeal Tribunal.    Since 27th Inarch, 15 cases of appealfor pensions have been decided in favour of and 1 case against theappellant.10.  Retired Pay to Officers ,  Nurses, &amp;c.,    Up to date 1247 Armyand Kaval  Officers (Including Warrant Officers), 76 Hurses, 578widows, 522 parents and 907 children of Widov/a of Officers (includingWarrant Officers) have benefitted mainly by increases in rates ofpension,  from  a review of their cases under the Officers1 $arrantand Orders in  Council of last  year.11. Lack of Institutional accommodation.   The ^ed ^ross Society havebeen asked for 18,000 beds.   The Kent Local Committee have suggestedopening Hospitals on V.A.D. lines.12.  General Practitioner treatment in Ireland.   ii conference uponthis question  has been held in Dublin.15.   Discharged men.in Military Hospitals.   During the period 1stJuly 1917  to 31st December, 1917, 25,205 discharged men ./ere treatedin Military hospitals, 6423 being inpatients and 18762 outpatients.14.   Froportion of Disabilities  due to wounds and Disease,  of theofficers  and men invalided during the month of fcarch 5347 ;?ereinvalided on account of wounds  and injuries and 9844 on account ofdisease.    The corresponding figures since  the beginning of the varto the end of  March are 135,243 and 184,245.15,  Treatment of the Limbless.   Up to the end of March 11146artificial legs and 5746 arms had bean supplied or nere cn order..Surinr&apos; the month there ;/ere 767 admissions  to limb fitting hospitalsand 714 discharges.16.   Treatment of Orthopaedic  Cases.   A consultant Committee has beenformed to advise the Minister  as  to general arrangements for openingorthopaedic annexes and outpatient clinics  throughout the country.
17.   Facial Injuries.   The Treasury has sanctioned a grant forQueen Mary&apos;s Hospital, Frognal.18.   Treatment of the Blind.   541 blinded men are now inresidence at St. Dunstan&amp;s and its annexes and 2 5 officers areunder care.    32 men were admitted during ivlareh and 36 discharged.446 men and 28 officers have now passed through.19.   Treatment of the Deaf.   Reports from the Special AuralBoards for London, Lancashire and the 3.E. and 3.W. areas ofScotland show that a number of men discharged for deafness arebeing treated or taught lip-reading. .A report by the Board of Education on the London Lip-readingclasses shows that out of 34 students who have attended theclasses 10 had attained a satisfactory standard.20.   Treatment Schemes.   Schemes have been submitted by variouslocal committees.   A number of civil hospitals have acceptedthe Ministry1 s terms.21.   Numbers under Treatment.   During the week 871 cases wereadmitted for treatment in or at Institutions and 12567 men wereunder treatment at the end of the week.   The total number of menreported as  having been or still being under treatment is 23684.22.   Treatment of Officers.   During March 380 officers wereallowed treatment or expenses for past treatment and 8 weregranted constant attendance allowances.                          TRAINING AND EMPLOYMENT23.   Trade Advisory Committees,   The Sheet Ketal Workers andBraziers are opposed to a Committee for the Gas Ivieter takingTrade local efforts are being made in various trades.24,   Training bonus.   The training bonus of 5/- per week is tobe paid by Local committees in future.25.   Material for use of training classes.   There are stilldifficulties as to obtaining certain material for the use oftraining classes.26.   Training Schemes.   10 out of 16 Schemes submitted bylocal Committees have been sanctioned.   24 individual cases of                                                   training.
training outside approved schemes were sanctioned during the week,and 149 men t-rere admitted to and 42 discharged from training.The total number of men under traininc, at the end of the week was3321.   Up to date 5281 men have been or are under training,27,   Training of widows.   Up to the end of ---arch 185 war-widowshave applied for training; in 88 cases training has been sanctionedthere were 29 withdrawals and 15 rejections.28.   Training and employment of Officers.   A forestry courseat Oxford including 9 officers starts this month.   During themonth 82 officers have been provided with work.                       ORGANISATION.29,   Naval and kilitary .ar Pensions g-.c (Committees) Act 1917.Supplemental schemes for the inclusion of disabled men and theirwidows or dependants on local committees are being submitted.30.  War Pensions Gazette.   The twelfth issue of this gazettecontains a leading article by Lady Sybil Bradford on thedifficulty of war-tfidows combining care of home and children vvithwage-earning.31.   Intelligence, Notes.   The Canadian Pensions Order givesconcessions with respect to marriages after disablement andchildren born after disablement, and grants pcst-discharge pay toover-sea-service men.Italy is extending her Insurance policy scheme to officers.The United States hope to have their fighting forces insured 100per cent.Germany is about to relax the stringent provisions surroundingthe &quot;additional mutilation&quot; pension.                            STAFF.52*   Staff.    The staff on the books of the ministry nowcomprises 538 men and 541C women or 5748 in all.    This includes18 officers (exclusive of 39 seconded for light duty) and 90men discharged disabled during the present war.
6th April, 1918.33,  Resignations.  During March there were 8 dismissals and215 resignations - a percentage of nearly 3.9 of the total staff34.  Pay of temporary Staff.  The rates of pay of the temporarystaff, numbering 170 men and 5.238 women.-are-shown in anAppendix to the Ministry&apos;s weekly report35.  Employment of disabled officers and men.  The Departmentare employing 18 retired disabled and 39 light duty officers and90 discharged disabled men.                                         MATTHEW NATHAN.

</content>
</cab>
