<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 232-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

SECRET.

G.T.4166.

WAR CABINET.

APPLICATION OF THE AMENDED MILITARY SERVICE ? TO IRELAND.

(Copy of letter from Lord Robert Cecil to the Prime Minister 7th April, 1918.)

(Circulated by request of Lord Robert Cecil, with reference to War Cabinet 385.)

Prime Minister.

The only ground  in which the extension of Compulsory Military Service to Ireland at the present time could  be defended is that of urgent military necessity. There seems no reasonable doubt that that necessity exists. Our Military Advisers are unanimous and ?tic in their opinion that we want the mon which would be so obtained and the figures given bear out their opinion. Nor, as I understand, does any member of the Cabinet or indeed anyone else who has examined the matter dispute this - least of all the Director of National Service. Further, it is felt by many, including myself, that to ask the English, Scotch and Welsh to submit to very drastic provisions increasing the stringency of  military compulsion while leaving the Irish free would be so unjust as to imperil the whole war spirit of the country. Finally, there is ground for thinking that America would not understand a section of our people not being made to bear their fair share of the general burden after the very noble response she has made to our appeals for assistance.

On some such grounds as these the War Cabinet have accepted the principle of military conscription for Ireland. But they do not propose to make it immediately applicable to that country but to postpone its application till some later date to be fixed by Order in Council. I cannot think this wise.

It is said that certain preliminaries will be necessary before compulsion can be put in force. Be it so. That  is no good ground for postponing its enactment nor will anyone believe it to be the real ground - as indeed it is not.  The real reason for the proposal is to ?ive some security that Home Rule will be passed. To my mind this is false reasoning. We want the man for the army and we want them now. It is indefensible to postpone the measure for getting them so as to use it as lever for passing a political reform.  But apart from the principle of the thing, how long is the postponement to be?  Obviouslyit must be till the Home Rule Bill is safe. Otherwise the postponement would have no object, and when will the Home Rule Bill be safe?  Indeed, a prior question must be asked, What is it to be?  We were told/


                           i*   wyesterday that it would he founded on the Report of the  Gon-vention and the Prime Minister&apos;s letter.   The latter documentconsists  only of suggestions,  perhaps necessarily vague andsketchy.  Yet provisions vital to Unionist support such  as  thosefor the defence of Ulster&apos;s interests rests on it alone  forthere is nothing specially safeguarding Ulster in the Report.For are the two documents always in accord in other respectsas for instance in reference to the Police and Postal Services.It is therefore quite uncertain what form Home Rule Bill willtake; and if that he so who can say how long it will he  beforesuch a Bill is safe?  Would a second reading in the House ofCommons make it so - or even its passage  through that House?It is extremely doubtful and one asks is  Irish Conscriptionto be held up indefinitely, it may be for weeks or perhapsmonths while the anti-conscription forces are organising andpreparing for resistance?  I could not assent tc that.  Andthen what is to happen if the Bill fails?  la conscription  to30 on?  Something was said yesterday about the -possibilityof the Bill bein? rejected by Irish opinion and it was repliedthat we need not anticipate that.  But we must consider notonly this contingency but all others which may lead to thedefeat of the Bill if conscription is to  depend on itspassage into Law.  Unless that is what is meant it is difficultto see what can be the object of the suggested postponement.In itself delay is clearly objectionable.  Every hour thatconscription is put off endangers its success.  More time isgiven to stir up feeling against it and unless things go  badlyin prance the urgency of the measure though not less real willbecome less obvious.      Other considerations might be adduced   in the samedirection.  But are not these enough to shew that the plan  cfsuspending the Bill in its application to Ireland is radicallyunsound?  Surely we must hold to the view that we are facedwith a military emergency requiring drastic and immediateremedies.  Otherwise the whole policy is  indefensible, andif that be so there must be no hint of hesitation or corn-promise -  I venture therefore to propose that Ireland shallbe definitely included in the Kan Power Bill.  Home Ruleshould at the same time be promised and a Bill produced  -if possible this week * certainly before  the end of next week,It should be founded on the Prime Ministers letter and  theConvention should make its acceptance a question of confidence.If there be any of us-who cannot accept it they would of courseresign.  But speaking for myself I do not anticipate that Ishould have to take that course.  I do not indeed believe thatthe proposals will prove ultimately of advantage to Ireland.But I recognise that the events cf the last two or three years,Mr. Redmond&apos;3 patriotic action,  the assembling of the Ccn-vention, the attitude of the Southern Unionists have made agreat difference.  We are as I think honourably bound to makea genuine attempt to meet the Home Rule demand, and in orderto smooth the path of Irish conscription  I am prepared tcmake that attempt now.                            (Sgd.)  ROBERT CECIL.7th April,  191P.

</content>
</cab>
