<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 244-246</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

SECRET.

?4169.

WAR CABINET.

WITHDRAWAL OF BRITISH DIVISIONS FROM ITALY.

Note by Lord Milner covering a letter from Mr. George Trevolyan.

I circulate for the information of my colleagues of the War Cabinet the enclosed letter just received from Mr. George Trevelyan, who is once more on the Italian front. The whole letter is worth reading, but I call particular attention to what he says about the danger of withdrawing the 3 remaining British divisions from Italy.

There is no proposal to do this at the moment, but it is certain to be made sooner or later, and the temptation is great seeing how hard pressed we are in France. But it is a temptation to be resisted. Three more divisions in France would certainly make a difference, but they would be just 3 more divisions. Three British Divisions in Italy have a value out of all proportion to their mere numbers, if they keep the Italian Army fighting, when, left to itself, it might give in. The collapse of Italy would set the whole Austrian Army free, and under present circumstances it would be almost impossible for Austria in that case to refuse to send at least a portion of her Army to help the Germans in France.  Austria has about 50 Divisions employed against Italy. If only half of them were sent to France, they could hardly fail to turn the scale against us and the French.(Intd.) M.

2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.

April 7th, 1918.


3S CLOSURE.    BRITISH  RED  CROSS  SOCIBrr.FIRST BKITISK AMBULANCE UNIT FOR ITALY.Croce Hosea Brit&amp;nnioa,   Prima SezioneXniendenza lllaArmata   Zona Bi Guerra,                                 27th &quot;Maroh,  1918,PRIVATE AND CONFIDENTIAL.Dear Lord Milnes?,          In conversation with me in January last,  juat beforemy return to Italy,  you asked me to write you from time to timemy observations of the moralii^of the Italian troops at thefront, in pursuance of the subjects treated in my mem or an dueswhich you .saw in January last.          Of course if the Germane conquer the Allied Armiesin France in the present offensive, the Italian Army will not putup an effective resistance when itself subsequently attacked.That may be written off,  All my remarks are relative to thesituation that will arise if the German attack in France isstemmed at some point that, allows of the war being continuedunder conditions not desperate.  In such a case the power ofresistance of the Italian Army, or rather the willingness ofthe Italian soldier to continue the war will again be adoubtful and vital factor to be seriously considered in theAllies&apos; plans if the war ie to be continued even till thelatter part of this year.          I am inclined to make the following general statementsas to the morale of the Italian Army at the front.I.        There has been a great recovery of tone since lastNovember, and there has been improvement in training, drill,smartness and organisation!  pertly due to the example andtactful assistance of the British Army.2,        fhe doubtless necessary removal of a portion ofthe British forces in Italy had a disheartening effectpro tanto both on Italian officers, and men.  The British Alliesare popular and trusted.  The removal of what now remains ofJtheBritish forces in , Italy wo ^^^^^^^sISMS^^ I^^ouTcToVTalS-Tng out the moral lyncK pin, -^**-^-mM*1&apos;5,        The tendency to improvement in morale is counteractedby bad news from abroad.  The completeness of the eeilapeeof Russia this year disheartened the impressionable Italiansoldier who doubts the use of going on trying for victory,  andshrinks from the length of time which he imagines it must \in any case take to achieve victory even if it were held to  ,be possible.  The German success in Prance  of the last fewdays has impressed the Italian soldiers even more,  since it hpfcbeen obtained over the British in whom they really believed,If by the time this letter reaches you the German advance hasbeen stemmed their belief in the British will have survived,but their expectation of ultimate victory in the near futurtwill not have been restored.
4 Z - 4*      As regards their pay,  separation allowances, food and comforts generally on \.hich I laid such stress in the memorandum yon saw in January,  I find it hard to make out how much has boon done in tho last three months, though as  far as my range of observation goes it amounts to very little,    I do not know who,  if anyone,  has been charged with these  matters.   In the zones where I have had opportunity of  observation,  viz.  recently on Asiago  and now round rasubio,  the comfort  of the troops in the trenches seems to differ in different Divisions according  to the greater or loss capability of the divisional or regimental officers, e.g, as  regards warmth,  dry trenches,  etc.   The food has I think  been slightly improved  at least  in somo cases,  but the  men  still grumble very gene rally and very seriously that they get so little except rice.   Their  pay has certainly not  beGn increased, nor (as far at least as they are auarc) are  their families receiving  larger reparation Allowances, If these  things have  been done  on paper  at any rate the news of the fact has not yet got through to this part of the front.    I doubt in fact if anything has been done  about it at all,  but I prefer  to speak only of what has come undor my own  observation.     Similarly I cannot  see any sign in  these  regions of canteens and  amusements for  the soldiers on such a scale as uouid  make  a  real  difference to the amenities of their existence.    I hear Indeed rumours of  the Americans intend- ing  to help in those  ways.     I am aware  of tho  immense  difficulty of getting things done through  the  Italian authorities,  but I gravely doubt whether tho  Italian soldier will  put UID  with his present conditions  of  life  indefinitely,  o.g.  until two millionAmericans have been shipped across the Atlantic to  win tho war.                 Yours  very truly,                    ( 8igne d ).   G. 11. TELY5LYAH.The Viscount Liilnor, G.C.3.

</content>
</cab>
