<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/47/0 images: 250-255</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i-Xl^l! Doournent if the Property of      tajinic IV1ajesty&apos;s Government.)-lis BiSECRET.O.l/Salonika 5/12.Copy HoEIGHTH VISIT OP LIEUT.-COLONEL E.A. PLUNKETT,GENERAL STAFF, TO SALONIKA FRONT, 9th FEBRUARY -24th MARCH, 1918,             /While at Salonika I visited the Struma and Doiran^Ss^s^fections of the British Front, and also the Headquarters          of the 1st Serbian Army and the French and Italian Army          Headquarters,GeneralSituation!1.   The general situation is unchanged, and there is asyet no concentration or increased movement immediatelyin rear of the enemy1s lines to indicate an early offensiveagainst any part of the Allied Front,  At French G.H.Q.the Chief of Staff considered that a month must elapsebetween such indications being first available and thecommencement of a serious offensive.     In this case an enemy offensive Is unlikely to hemade this Spring (unless hostile preparations are soonobserved).  But the Autumn is always the most unfavourabletime for us, for our strength is at its lowest owing tothe climate, while the Bulgars though they suffer fromfever,  are not incapacitated by it to the same extent asEuropean troops.  Moreover, any German troops broughtfrom another theatre for the purposes of an offensive,would not be affected by the climate for the first fewmonths.     Consequently it is at the beginning of Autumn thatan enemy offensive would be most difficult to resist.GuiUaumat!s 2,   on 10th March, the Chief of Staff, French G.H.Q. at  Plans I            Salonika, informed me that Guillaumat was still considering            the situation, but that his plans were generally as                                                            follows
follows:-      (a)  To fight on the front line now occupied*      (b)  If driven back from the above line, the      Serbian Army to hold on as long as possible to the      position it now occupies, and then retire slowly;      the British Army and a certain number of other      Divisions (the exact number has not been determined      but would be between 2 and 5) to retire and defend      the BIrdoage position; and the French Army and the      Italians to form a mobile forae, west of L, Ostrovo,      covering Thessaly,,      (c)  A line of defenoe further South and covering      Thessaly was being reoonnoitred, and it was proposed      to employ Greeks to develop this,      A mixed British and French Commission has recentlyexamined the Birdcage position, and the following are extractsfrom the conclusions arrived at :**     &quot;Tho entrenched camp of Salonika Is not fit forimmediate occupation; time, material and labour areneoessary to make it so, hut its excellent defences, well**considered trace and numerous emplacements for guns, con-stitute a defensive position of serious value,   A numerousforce is neoessary for its occupation,     The Western Section is the stronger and can be furtherstrengthened by extending the defences to the right bankof the Vardar.,     The Eastern Section lacks depth, and from withoutthe defences the enemy can bombard the depots near thetown and Salonika itsolf.,   This defect can only beremedied by an unreasonable oxtension of the perimeter,whereby undoubted advantages of ground would be lost to  us.                                                  The
o *The &quot;best remedy lies in pushing forward as  faras possible the defences which the British  Arrayis organising between the front It holds and theentrenched camp&quot;.aumat&quot;Alliedions     3*    Guillaumat has cortainly done  his best  to-get on good         terms with the Allied Commanders  at Salonika, but in thehders I,  case of the Italians and Serbians the mistrust bequeathed by*         Sarrail has not been entirely dispelled.   I consider that         the presence of a G,S. Officer of each of  the Allied Armies         working in the Operations Section at French  G.H.Q. would         tend to prevent misunderstandings and friction.              Early in March, Guillaumat,  with a view to  forming a         general reserve consisting solely ef French  troops, instruct-         ed the Serbians to extend their front.   The Serbian General         Staff refused en the ground that  they had  continually premised         their men that after the arrival  of reinforcements they would         have a shance of getting out ef the line and having a rest,         and that it was unreasonable to ask the Serbians, after all         they had gone through, always to  remain in the line while a         proportion ef French troops were  always in reserve.   The         Serbian General Staff adopted a firm attitude and the matter         was not settled on 11th March when I left  Salonika.   I bel-         ieve a somewhat similar incident  occurred  between the French         and Italians.              The presence of a General Staff Officer of  each Allied         Army at French G.H.Q, would enable  such questions to be         thrashed out before the actual issue of instructions, and         the cancelling of instructions would thereby be  avoided. L^K&apos;  4*   Tne Serbians are holding out well,  and  have been much         encouraged by the arrival of 8,000  reinforcements and the                                                          prospect
prospect of shortly getting another 4,000 to 5,000 fromRussia.  But many of their officers and men have beenmobilised almost continuously since October, 1912, and arestale.   Consequently, it is of vital importance to procureall available Slav reinforcements for the Serbian Armyas soon as possible.   By this means the Macedonian front would be strengthened,both effectively and economically, - more so indeed than bymobilising a far greater number of Creeks - for the Serbianshave Commanders, Staffs and regimental cadres, all with muchwar experience, for twice as big a force as they have atpresent.  The men only are lacking,  A large amount oftrained material could be furnished easily and quickly fromItaly and untrained material from America.  As regardsItaly there has recently been a change In the hostile att-itude of that country to the Serbians and Jugo-Slavs, andthe question might again be taken up, either now or a littlelaters  Attention is again called to this matter as it isof urgent importance.5,  Many Serbian Officers at the Salonika front are familymen, with their wives and children in other countries, andtheir present scale of pay does not allow them t^ remitsufficient money to enable their families to live in anycomfort.  An increase of pay to all Officers, at an averageof 10 frsa a day per officer would amount, I believe, toabout  250,000 a year, and would do much to encourage themand keep them contented.   I am informed that Mr. Thornton,Lord Milner&apos;s Private Secretary, has the details of aproposal submitted from Salonika.   The outlook for the Serbian Army is not encouraging, andI consider that it is important to do everything possible to                                                    keep
keep the officers in good spirits.    Many of them havenever even visited Salonika for a change of scene andrest, chiefly because they could not afford even thesmall expenditure this would entail.6.  In the middle of March the situation was as follows4 Greek Divisions were at the front in Macedonia, thetransportation of a Fifth Division to Salonika had commencedand would take a month to complete, and the mobilizationof a sixth Division had just begun.     Beyond the above Divisions, there remain the JaninaDivision, which is - earmarked for employment in Epirus, andthe throe Divisions of the Peloponnese, which should beavailable for the Macedonian fronte     I discussed the situation with General Bordeaux, nowChief of the French Military Mission, and also with severalpeople, British and Foreign., who know Greece well and canjudge h07f things are going0    The general opinion isthat the attitude of the Greeks is changing in our favour,and that they are beginning to see that they cannot keepout of the war, and that their interests lie with theEntente rather than with the Germans.    The recent mutiniesat Lamia and Thebes, and the severe disciplinary measuresfollowing on them - civilians, officers and men to thenumber of 22 were executed in one day - have donegood rather than harm and have cleared the air*     Venizelos is by nature averse to taking suchmeasures and inclined to be over-lenient,   Consequently,drastic action by his Government has shown the peoplethat the Government is in earnest and mobilization willprobably continue smoothly until the first 6 Divisions                                                 are
                                                        -    198                                                             -0         are at the  front.    Once  in  Macedonia, well-fed and         distributed among  British and French troops, these         Divisions  should improve  rapidly  and constitute a force         of distinct military value for  employment against         Bulgars in Macedonia,     Greeks would probably  never         face Germans.              In the Pelopomiese,  however,  conditions are not         satisfactory.   The  Peninsula has  always been strongly         Royalist in sympathy,  and much  German propaganda is         being carried  on there.    Reports to this effect have         been sent  to Athens  by our Consular and other agents,         but the decisive action called  for has not yet  been         taken by the Greek Government.              The presence  of some British or French troops         successively at each mobilization centre, until the 3         Divisions  of the Peloponnese have  been mobilized and       -  transported to Macedonia, would have a salutary effect.         The Greeks  would not resent  such  action if taken with         decision,  and  the  moves could easily be carried out         during the  Summer  months.   When  once the men of the         Peloponnese Divisions  were removed from the influence         of German  propaganda and  local  polities, and wero under         training alongside disciplined  troops, their moral and         discipline  should  readily improve.              To sum up, I  consider the  opinion expressed by the         late Chief  of  the  French  Military Mission still holds         good, namely,  that though the Greeks will never be first-         rate troops they will  have a definite value for fighting         in Macedonia,  and  that, as we cannot abandon the         Macedonian front,  it is worth while sending the material         necessary  to complete  the Greek mobilization.                                      (Sd.) S.A. Plunkett,                                                      Lt.-Col. G.S.ar Office. 28 c 3 sIB t

</content>
</cab>
