<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/15/0 images: 61-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[CI (This Document is the :&apos;Pgopertyhof &quot;-His Britannic&quot;Majesty&apos;s i Government.)---------B. 0 R E T.WAR OABIIJRT 547 A.DRAFT MIMJTES of a Meeting held in Ma? Bonar La&apos;.?&apos;3 Room, House ofCommons, S.W., on WEDNESDAY,&apos;-MARCHW, 1919, at 9 p;a.RAILWAY-       With reference, to.War Cabinet 546, Minute 1, Sir EricCATION.Geddes explained the conclusions at which the Committee, appoint-ed by the Cabinet that morning, had arrived with regard to the.railway situation.   Sir Eric Geddes said that the Committee hadsat for the whole afternoon, and the position with regard tothe finance of the railwaymen&apos;s demands was thai before the War 50,000,000 per annum was paid in railway wages.   The additionof War Bonus, which was now being paid, cost a further 60,000,000.    The railwaymen&apos;s new demands would cost thecountry a further  41,000,000, thus making an additional costto the country,;over the pre-war wages paid, of  101,000,000.The War Gabinet had approved a 50 per cent, increase in thepre-war earnings of the men as a basis on which the RailwayExecutive could negotiate for a settlement (War Cabinet 536,Minute 3, dated February 35, 1919).    Those, negotiations startedfour weeks ago, and, as far as he (Sir Eric G-eddes) could gather?    not much advance towards a settlement had been made, &amp;nd therewas still disagreement when we were within 48 hours of a    :possible strike.    The opinion he had formed, v/as that the RailwayExecutive had not made material progress, and had no reliablefigures to negotiate upon.   Such figures as were produced thatafternoon were thoroughly unsatisfactory.   If it came to afight Mr Thomas would probably make^ this fact public,and wouldB. &quot;&quot;1-
say that the Hallway Executive&apos;s estimates were open to consid-erable criticism.   Apart from the merits of the ease,, the Gov-ernment. was&apos;;in a weak position, owing to the way in which thenegotiations had been conducted, andh, in view of this seriousfact, the Minister of Labour and himself did not think theGovernment could make a successful stand before the public.In their view the Government would have to tell the RailwayExecutive that in effect they must negotiate with Mr Thomas onhis own terms, which seemed: to him (Sir Erie Geddea) and theMinister of Labour to be hot unreasonable.,The President of the Board of Trade said that he realisedthe Railway Executive had taken some time ever the negotiations,but they had been in an uncomfortable position owing to eiroum-stances over which they had no control.   The War Cabinet wouldrecall the effect of the announcement by Mr Churchill of theintention of the Government to nationalise the Railways. Furtherthe Board of Trade had never been organised to deal with, railwaynegotiations on the present scale.   The Executive had had a^f;colossal task, and in a very short time had had to obtainfigures from all the Railway Companies, which had not been **.easy matter, as they were not drawn up on any uniform basis and\^ere, therefore, difficult of comparison.Sir Herbert Walker and Sir A. Butterworth thenentered the Meeting, the Minutes of which arecontained in War Cabinet 547.bWhit ehal 1 Ga rdens,., S .W. 1.,March&apos;SO, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
