<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/181/0 images: 173-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. 1121Printed for the Cabinet.   August 1926. SECRET. Copy No.     30CP. 317 (26).CABINET.SPECIAL REPORT  ON   UNEMPLOYMENT.No. 132.   July 1926.THIS Report gives a summary of the recently published returns of unemployment in the various industries. In Table (A) is shown the course of unemployment during July, while Table (B) on p. 2 gives an analysis of the number of persons on the registers at Employment Exchanges in Great Britain on the 26th July.(A.) Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges inGreat Britain.-	1924.	1925.	1926.						July 28.	July 27.	June 28.	July 5.	July 12.	July 19.	July 26.	Increase ( 4-) or Decrease (-) since June 28.Men . . Boys . . Women Girls .. Total..	794,340 34,559 189,161 30.201	912,566 33,383 220,414 31,268	1,223,615 43,032 327,277 45,852	1,223,255 42,900 332,593 46,322	1,221,912 43,108 333,196 45,978	1,210,106 43,077 332,720 45,365	1,188,248 45,095 324,850 47,227	- 35,367 +    2,063 - 2,427 4-    1,375	1,048,261	1,197,631	1,639,776	1,645,070	1,644,194	1,631,268	1,605,420	- 34,356Notk (1) : The above figures represent the number of persons registered at Local Offices as applicants for employment. In the main they relate to persons who had claims to benefit current and were not at work on the dates given.(2.) The figures above for the four weeks in July are exclusive of persons in the Coal-mining Industry who ceased work on account of the dispute which commenced on the 1st May.(3.) The latest figures available, viz., for the weeks ended the 9th and 16th August, 1926, are given in Part (D) of this Report.The percentage of unemployment (Great Britain) in the insured industries at the end of July 1924       .... .... .... ....     9-6,,    1925       .... .... .... ....   10-8,,    1926       .... .... .... .... 14*4 (men only 15*7)During the four weeks ended the 26th July, 1926, there was a decrease of 34,356 in the number of persons registered as unemployed. Table (A) above shows that this reduction was confined practically to the last two weeks of the period. It will also be seen that there has been an increase in the number of juveniles recorded as unemployed. This may be attributed to the fact that a large number of those who left school at the termination of the school term have not yet been placed in employment, ; . [14983]
(B.) Analysis of the Number of Persons on the Registers of Employment Exchanges in Great Britain at the 26th July, 1926.	Wholly Unemployed.	Temporary Stoppages.	Casuals.	Total.Men Boys.. Women Girls	703,551 27,701 99,828 26,743	407,731 17,222 224,226 20,463	76,966 172 796 21	1,188,248 45,095 324,850 47,227Total..	857,823	669,642	77,955	1,605,420It may be noted that while there has been a very slight reduction in the wholly unemployed figure during the last month, the total reduction in unemployment is, unlike last month, mainly accounted for by the comparatively large decrease in the number of temporary stoppages.(C.) Unemployment in Insured Industries.The latest date for which unemployment figures by industries are available is the 26th July, 1926, at which date the percentage unemployed in Great Britain and Northern Ireland was 14&quot;6, as compared with 14&apos;7 at the 21st June, 1926, with 11&apos;2 at the 27th July, 1925, and with 9&quot;6 at the 28th July, 1924. The figures at the 26th July in respect of industries showing appreciable variations in unemployment during the month, together with the increase or decrease as compared with the previous month, with the 26th April, 1926, and with a year ago are given in the table below : 	Number of Insured Persons	Increase (-f-) or Decrease (-with 				-) compared	Industry.	recorded as Unemployed														at. July 26, 1926.	June 21, 1926.		April 26, 1926.		July 27, 1925.	All Insured Industries. .	1,737,260*	-	13,873	4	643,431	4	410,350Coal-mining-	108,440*		17,711	4	10,560		76,003General   Engineering,   Engineers&apos;   Iron							and Steel Founding	107,572	-	7,448	4	37,359	4	29,660Woollen and Worsted	59,462	-	4,696	4	34,450	4	3,967Railway Service	27,770	-	4,317	4	18,394	4	18,079Manufacture of Tin-plates	17,668	-	3,844	4	13,152	4	13,802Rubber Manufacture	9,450	-	3,019	4	4,888	4	3,420Bolts, Nuts, Screws, Rivets, Nails, &amp;c,							Manufacture	5,602	-	2,406	4	2,856	4	1,984Electrical Engineering..          ..        ...	6,514	-	2,175	4	1,485	4	2,226Pig-iron Manufacture (Blast Furnaces) ..	16,217	 	1,877	4	12,791	4	9,763Constructional Engineering	6,249	-t-	1,554	4	2,984	4	3,205Stove, Grate, Pipe, &amp;c, and General Iron							Founding	10,811	+	1,944	4	8,986	4	7,670Steel Melting and Iron Puddling Furnaces,							Iron and Steel Rolling Mills and Forges	112,570	-t-	1,954	4	71,848	.  4	60,723Building	75,179	4	2,792	4	20,052		15,958Public Works, Contracting, &amp;c.	31,285	4 -	3,000	4	7,605	4	8,879Tailoring    j..	17,190	4	4,511	4	9,971	 	557Cocoa, Chocolate and Sugar Confectionery	10,712	4	4,568	4	4,827	4	3,735 9,737Jute	23,701	4	6,715	4	12,110	4	Cotton	162,628	4	18,610	4	105,920	4	97,509* These figures are exclusive of persons in the Coal-mining Industry who ceased work on account of the dispute which commenced on the 1st May.
The past month has witnessed very little improvement of any importance in the general industrial position. Employment in most of the principal industries continued to be adversely affected by the coal-mining dispute. The large increase of over 18,000 in unemployment in the Cotton Industry is in general attributed to an increasing shortage of fuel supplies. The depression in this industry is especially acute in the principal weaving centres where alternate week working appears to be more or less the general rule. Attention is also directed to the increase of 15 per cent, in the unemployment in the Jute Industry during the last month, bringing the total percentage of unemployment in this highly localised industry on the 26th July to the deplorable figure of 56&quot;2 per cent. The position in the Iron and Steel Industry and in Constructional Engineering was also somewhat more unsatisfactory. The increased unemployment in the Tailoring Industry is largely of a seasonal nature.In the group of industries comprised under the term &quot; General Engineering,&quot; there has been a welcome improvement during the month. The reopening of a number of works which had been closed during June has also resulted in a reduction in unemployment in the Tinplate Industry. Compared with last month the position in the &quot;Woollen and Worsted Industries, particularly in the former, is much more satisfactory.(D.) Latest Figures.The latest figures of unemployment published are those for the 9th August, giving the total number on the registers as 1,594,169. This is a decrease over the position on the 26th July amounting to 11,251, but an increase over a year ago of 396,538. The preliminary figure for the 16th August is 1,580,500, showing a decrease in one week of 13,669.ARTHUR STEEL-MAITLAND.Ministry of Labour,August 23, 1926.

</content>
</cab>
