<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/181/0 images: 204-210</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
m(THIS DOCUMENT U THiS j^RQ^jjiRTY OF HIS BBIlANNIC MAJESTY1S (H)YERN1*SNT). MEL.. Copy NoP. 31^26MLimmjasi^m qf ma mmdmmmm mThe Report of the Treasury Coianittee on Grants makes two proposals:- Unified Block Grants for all Services, to be introduced about 1930, and an Interim Scheme for Education Grants.The first of these proposals iB, of course, much the more important.    If practicable, I believe it provides the best solution of the problem and I hope the Committee will be authorised to explore it further.    It follows that nothing oust be done in the interval which would prejudice such a solution and if I thought, as the representatives of the Scottish Offiee appear to think, that the Interim Scheme for Education Grants proposed by the Committee would have this effect I should reject it.     I cannot see, however, how this danger can arise, ishile, on the other hand, it seems evident that we shall seriously prejudice the final solution if we leave things as they are in the interval.Ife&apos; are committed to the principle of a block grant for Education and we only postponed the introduction of that system&apos;for one year in order to allow time for consultation with Local Sducation Authorities.     If we tacitly let the proposal drop for three years, the impression will certainly be created that we have found a block grant impracticable. Moreover, every month that the present system continues involves us in further commitments in terms of an expenditure grant.    Education is bound to be an expanding service.    We may differ as to the amount of expansion which is necessary or
desirable at any particular time, but new Elementary Schools have to be built in new housing areas and a certain number of proposals for new Secondary Schools have to be approved. Each such approval conraits us to recognising a certain amount of new expenditure for grant.    The first step towards getting rid of an expenditure grant system is to convert the Exchequer commitments on such new work into terms of a definite sum of money per unit.    Moreover, it is only by this means that we can make adoiinistrative economies by getting rid of the present cumbrous procedure of approving expenditure on new projects in detail.    But it is impossible to superimpose specific grants per unit for new work on expenditure grants for existing work.    For instance, we cannot create a situation some years hence where grant in respect of some Elementary Schools would be paid at a specific rate per place and on other Elementary Schools at a percentage rate on expenditure.     If, therefore, we are to avoid incurring new commitments in a form which must tend to prolong the present system, we must at once make a move in the direction of converting existing grants into terms of block grants.Oar present grants on the various existing services, however, differ very widely in the degree to Tshich they are easily susceptible of expression in terms of a block grant. Certain of them, such as those relating to the upkeep of Elementary Schools, are, I think, susceptible of being converted at once into a uniform grant of so many shillings per child. Other services vary so greatly from area to area that it would be impossible at the outset to assess a uniform grant except at great cost to the Exchequer.     For instance, the amount of Local Authorities&apos; expenditure on lean charges on Elementary Schools depends entirely on the fortuitous circumstance.- of Tshether there is a large or a small proportion of Church Schools in the area, and expenditure on Technical Education varies very2.
widely according to local industrial circumstances.    In the case of these services, while we must aim at working ultimately to a uniform grant, a block grant must at the outset take the form of a more or les3-arbitrary sum agreed with each Authority as representing the amount of grant at present payable on existing services and commitments already approved.    Finally, there is the case of teachers&apos; salaries.     Here the range of variation is necessarily too great to permit of a uniform grant per child while, on the other hand, grant in respect of salaries cannot be stereotyped because any such stereotyping would leave out of account themautomatic increments under the Burnham Scales.    The political dangers of doing anything which would upset the Burnham Award are referred to in the Committee Ts Beport and I need only say that, in my view, any action which would involve a refusal to pay grant on Burnham increments would be incompatible with the undertaking contained in my letter to Lord Burnham of April 9, 1925.In these circumstances we must face the fact that it will not at any time be possible to convert all education grants into block grants at one blow, except on one condition, namely the swallowing up of education grants in larger Exchequer grants sufficient to satisfy all Authorities.    That condition cannot be realised at this moment or for the next two or three years, and the choice before us, therefore, is either to do nothing at the mctment or to do what we can.If I understand aright the first two paragraphs of the Memorandum of Dissent signed by the representatives of the Scottish Office, they are prepared, though reluctantly, to accept the necessity of converting parts of the education grant into a block grant during the interim period, while leaving the remainder on an expenditure basis, but they are
factoranxious to retain the existing rate  equalisation^(i.e. the difference between 36/- per child and the yield of a 7d. rate) in such a form as to make it clear that the Exchequer is not paying grant on teachers salaries at a flat rate of 6O/0 in all areas.     I think that the existing rate equalisation factor may need some modification, but I agree that any new grant formula should contain a rate equalisation factor as a distinct and separate element.The third paragraph in the Memorandum of Dissent Beems to rest on a misconception as to the character of the Development Grants contemplated by the Committee over and above the block grants for existing services,     It is, of course, essential that any Development Grant should nob be so applied as to vary, as between differeirb areas, th-3 amount of any uniform, rate of^grant per -qnlh which may be ad op bed for any part of existing educational services.,     Ifr for instance, we decide that the grant for the administration and running expenses, other than salaries, of $lomntazry. 3-chools shall be fixed at a uniform rate of 9/- per place, we must not   give special Development Grant to a particular local Authority for these services.     Development Grants to particular Authorities must be confined to -(a) services, existing expenditure on which varies a great deal between area and areac     Here the Board of Education must have in mindj wherever possible, a uniform rate of grant towards which it will work and Development Grants mist be distributed with reference to that rate.     Development Grants would thus have the effect of tending gradually to convert an arbitrarily stereotyped grant into a uniform rate per unit;
(b) services where the expansion can be expressed in terms of a specific rate per unit of new work done, e.g. a grant for every additional pupil in Secondary Schools;   and(c) non-recurring expenditure such as exceptional arrears of school repairs due to the war.Development Grant provided for these purposes would, it seems to me, be &quot;added to the block grant&quot; as suggested in the Memorandum of Dissent, except, of course, in the case of a non-recurring grant for exceptional purpose^ and could never &quot;resolve itself into an additional percentage grant&quot;.One of the worst features of the expenditure grant is that it is so difficult to get away from it.     Every possible proposal. has serious disadvantages but I understood last year that the Cabinet did not think it a bad thing that an attempt should be made to convert Education Grants into block grants experimentally in spite of the evident fact that no such experiment would be satisfactory as a permanent solution.    Now that the whole subject has been thoroughly explored by an expert Committee I hope that the Cabinet will accept their conclusions and will authorise me to engage in negotiations with Local Authorities on these lines.I should like to make it clear that in proposing to separate teachers&apos; salaries from other educational expenditure and to continue for the present to pay grant upon them on an expenditure basis, I do not contemplate leaving this part of the problem untouched,     I am introducing a new system of approved teaching establishments for every area.     Along these lines I hope to settle the number of teachers which will be maintained in every area for a period of years.     Local Authorities, finding that, in respect of services where a block grant is introduced, they are freed
from a great deal of detailed admnistrative work and control whereas in the case of teaching establishments they continue to be subject to such detailed control, will probably soon come to realise the advantages of accepting a block grant in respect of teachers1 salaries also.    As the cost of the establishment in any area begins to reach an equilibrium, i.e. as a normal relation is established between entrants, retirements and increments, this movement will be strengthened and if at a later date the Board, in agreement with the Treasury, can offer to Authorities a uniform flat rate of grant per teacher, it is.quite possible that many Authorities will prefer to take this offer and gain their freedom.    The resulting grant system would be very similar to that now in force in Scotland but the combination of a grant per teacher with a grant per child is by no means a perfect form of block grant and the Treasury Committee seems to me to be quite right in leaving this possibility open for future consideration when we have completed the first stage of our experiment.I should, however, make it clear that the moment at which a block grant can be actually applied must depend upon the provision of grants for new development.     I gather that this is recognised in paragraphs 35 and 36 of the ComrflitteeTs Eeport*     It may be possible to fix a grant per child in respect of the administration and general upkeep of Elementary Schools independently of any grants for development, though even here the question of exceptional non-recurring expenditure would have to be considered, but anything further than this will be impossible unless a definite prospect of Development Grants for the future can be held cut to Local Authorities.     I suggest, therefore, that a small Cabinet Committee should be appointed immediately
after the holidays to consider Tsfoat provision can he made by the Government before the next election for carrying out the educational programme which the Prime Minister laid before the Country two years ago.    The actual application of a block grant should be postponed until a decision has been arrived at on this matter.     Consequently, in putting before Local Authorities my proposals for a partial conversion of education grants into terms of a block grant, I should propose to avoid committing myself to the actual application of such a scheme from the beginning of the next financial year, though I should very much hope that the deliberations of the Cabinet Committee would enable the Government to come to a definite decision on educational policy before that time.E.P.20th1926.

</content>
</cab>
