<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/181/0 images: 463-465</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
( ^is.,DgouKient is the property o f, His^Britannio majesty&apos;s s i Government .)- SECRET - COPY No.     &quot;^O0.P.-346 (26) .-CABINET. CHEMICAL WARFARE POLICY.( Previous Paper:- CP.-544 (26).)The accompanying copy of a letter, dated October 13,1926, from the War Office, is circulated by direction ofthe Prime Minister for the consideration of the Cabinetin connection with Item 3 (d)  on the Agenda for theMeeting.of the Cabinet to be held on Monday, the 18th Inst.(Signed) M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet.Whitehall Gardens, S.W,:1, October 14,  1926.
... [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.]Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   October 1926.SECRET. Copy No,  100725-B.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.CHEMICAL  WARFARE  POLICY.(Previous C.I.D. Papers Nos. 327-B, 353-B, 354-B, 355-B, 361-B, 483-B 497-B 535-B, 546-B, 548-B, 552-B, 595-B, 706-B, 707-B, 708-B, 709-B, 715-B&apos; 716-B, 723-B and 131-A.)Copy of Letter from the War 0ffice to the Secretary, Committee of Imperial Defence. 0153/4964 (C. 1).Sir, War Office, S.W. 1, October 13, 1926.IN continuation of the two memoranda on the subject of Chemical Warfare Policy, already circulated as C.I.D. Papers 709-B and 723-B, I am Commanded by the Army Council to draw attention to a letter from the International . Red Cross Committee at Geneva (of which a copy has been received from the Foreign Office and a translation of which is attached) and to point out that, in&quot; the event of the Governments ratification of the Protocol prohibiting gas warfare, the logical and nor unlikely sequel appears to be that they will next be asked to co-operate in a complete exchange of information regarding the best methods of defence against gas.2. This would, of coarse, involve their taking other nations into their confidence as regards the latest pattern service container designed for use in our anti-gas face-pieces and as regards the results of all our chemical warfare research work generally. Nor could there be any guarantee that each of the other signatories would make a similarly frank disclosure of their research activities whatever they might contract to do.3. The Council are therefore of the opinion that this aspect of the question should not be overlooked when the policy to be adopted by the Government regarding ratification of the Protocol is discussed at the Imperial Conference.I am, &amp;c. , (Signed) H. J. GREEDY.(T 8713/7182/377.) Enclosure.CR 159 GV.To the British Minister for Foreign Affairs, International Red Cross Committee,London. 1, Promenade da Pin, Geneva,Sir, July 6, 1926.THE International Red Cross Committee has the honour to forward you a circular letter with regard to chemical and bacteriological warfare, and which it is forwarding to all the signatory Governments of the Geneva Convention. May we be allowed to draw your kind attention to this letter ?The International Red Cross Committee has the honour, &amp;c.(Signed)      LUCIEN CRAMER,Member of the International Red Cross Committee.[15165]
Annex to Enclosure.International Red Gross Committee.To the Signatory States of the Geneva Convention.Chemical and Bacteriological Warfare.Geneva, June 30, 1926. The XII International Red Cross Conference, which met at Geneva in October 1925, and at which delegates of thirty-nine Governments and of forty-four National Red Cross Societies took part, has adopted the following resolution : &quot;The XII International Red Cross Conference &apos;: 1. Notes, with great satisfaction, the fact that the Geneva protocol of the 17th June, 1925, confirming and completing the Washington Treaty of the 6th February, 1922, and the Treaty of Versailles of the 28th June, 19.19, has solemnly condemned chemical warfare and bacteriological warfare.&quot; It expresses the wish that this protocol be ratified as soon as possible and that the States which have not yet adhered to it may do so within a very short period.&quot; 2. In the event of this interdiction being violated, it considers that it is the duty of the Red Cross to endeavour to find in time of peace, in collaboration with the military and civil authorities, means to protect and give medical aid to its personnel, the belligerent armies and, especially, the civil populations against the effects of chemical warfare.&apos;&apos; 3. The International Committee is directed to keep itself constantly advised of the carrying out of this programme and to get into touch with the national Societies on this subject.&quot; 4. Generally speaking, the moral struggle and propaganda against the use of war gases and bacteriological warfare, as well as the scientific and technical preparation of the best preventive and therapeutic measures against such methods of warfare, should assume the first place in the considerations of the International Bed Cross and the National Red Cross Societies.&quot;Since the account of the XII Conference which has just come out gives the deliberations on this subject, the International Red Cross Committee officially brings this resolution to the knowledge of the Governments in execution of the decision of the XII International Conference, and warmly supports the wish expressed by the above-mentioned Conference that the protocol of Geneva of the 17th June, 1925, which condemns chemical and bacteriological warfare, should be ratified as soon as possible, and that the States which have not yet adhered to it should do so within a very short period.In this hope the International Committee has the honour, &amp;c.-  For the International Red Cross Committee :(Signed) GUSTAVE AD OR, President.EDMOND BOISSIER, Vice-president.

</content>
</cab>
