<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/181/0 images: 571-575</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TH IS DOCUMENT I3 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITTA.NIC   MAJESTY&apos;SC.P.S62( 26) .GOVERNMENT.CABINET.copy No.30Loans to Boards of Guardians in Ateasaffected by the Coal Strike.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.1.     I desire to consult the Cabinet on the question of the provision which is required to be made immediately Parliament reassembles to enable the Ministry to make advances to Boards of Guardians to meet current expenditure on relief due to the ooal stoppage.2,     Since 1st Kay Boards of Guardians in England and Wales have borrowed about  7,500,000 of which about  2,000,000 has been advanced by the Ministry of Health on the recommendation of the Committee presided over by Sir Harry Gosohen, K.B.3., and the balance by the Banks.3.      The Banks have proved themselves helpful to the Guardians throughout the emergency but for some weeks now they have refused in practically all the mining areas to allow further credits.    They consider that they have already lent to the extreme limit of prude no e and I am satisfied that it would be useless and probably unwise to press them to make further advances.     A few Boards are still carrying on without recourse to the Ministry but already the balk of the current expenditure in the mining areas is being met out of loans advanced by the Ministry and I must, before long, expect to have to finance every Colliery Union in which the strike continues.4.    The total Vote provision made for advances to Boards of Guerdians and distressed Local Authorities for the financial year 1926/7 amounts to  1,925,000 including Scotland.      This provision
has recently become exhausted and I have arranged with the Treasury for advances to be mads from the Civil Contingencies Fund pending further Vote provision in Sovember.     The Treasury have warned me that the utmost whioh the Fund will be able to advance for this purpose will certainly not exoeed  1,250,000, and, as it Is estimated that at least this sum will be required by the middle of November, it is essential that a Supplementary Estimate should be presented immediately Parliament reassembles and. that the necessary Parliamentary time in the first ten days of the Session should be made available for obtaining the Vote in Supply and for the passage of the Consolidated Pund Bill.5,     The advances to be made by the Ministry and the Scottish Board of Health will probably amount to  1,000,000 a month during the continuance of the stoppage and I propose, if the Cabinet agree, that the Supplementary Estimate should be for  2,250,000 made up of  1,250,000 for repayment to the Civil Contingencies Fund and  1,000,000 for a further month&apos;s advances.     Further provision will be required before the end of the financial year even if an early settlement of the dispute is come to, because the aftermath, of the strike will involve the Guardians in unforeseen expenditure.     But I suggest that at this stage I should only provide, sufficient for a month ahead in view of the effect whioh provision for a longer period might have In delaying the return of the miners to work.      If the stoppage oontinues during November a further Supplementary will be re quired in pocamber.6.     These considerations raise a further question, namely whether it would be desirable to require Guardians, as a condition of further borrowing, to reduce the scale on which relief is being given to the dependants of miners.7.      In the instructional letter whioh I issued on the outbreak of the dispute I expressed the opinion that relief to
the dependants of a miner should not exceed the sum of 12/- for the woman and 4/- for each, child.     These allowances were substantially below the rates already adopted in a number of mining Unions, partieulax-ly in those Unions in which the miners form a majority of the Board of Guardians, and there was consider-able difficulty at the outset in securing the adoption of the scales.     There is still some evasion in Unions in which the children are receiving meals at school, as the full value of the meals is seldom deducted, so that the assistance received for each child in these cases is in fact above 4/- per week.     With this exception the 12/- and 4/- scale is at the present time nowhere exceeded, but there have recently been representations that the scale should be supplemented in order to provide better boots for the children.8.     7/hile there is little doubt that the adoption of the scale in the instructional letter has produced substantial economy, there have throughout been Unions in which the scales of relief adopted have been below that circular scale, and there have been a number of cases in which the Guardians have represented that the expression of my view compelled them to adopt a scale which was higher than they would themselves have thought necessary. There can be little doubt that some reduction of the scale of relief at present generally in force could be made without inflicting undue hardship on the women and children.     A dispute of such extent and duration must necessarily involve discomfort and hardship In many instances, but the officers of the Ministry who have been instructed to keep in close touch with local sources of information, have been unable to find cases in which the Guardians or thair officers have failed to relieve destitution. The Labour organisations have made strenuous efforts to discover such, cases but have failed to produce any identifiable case which could be investigated.      In Scotland it is understood that actual cases were specified by the complainants and an examination by
medical and other officers of the Board of Health did not support the claim made that there was suffering from privation.      The general effect of the information received at the Ministry is that the children are bet tar fed and healthier, though often worse clad, than when their fathers are at work.It is significant that while there has been constant difficulty over the position of single miners, debarred under the Merthyr Tydfil Judgment from the receipt of relief during the dispute, no such questions have been raised about married men who are squally so debarred..      The inference that the scale of relief given to the wife and children is sufficient to maintain the miner in addition to his family, and is in fact in part unlawfully expended on his relief, is irresistible.9.     The foregoing circumstances together with the growing burden on local rates and. an increasing &quot;conviction of the unreasonable nature of the miners attitude are having their effect on Boards of Guardians and In a good many instances scales are being reduced by them without any direction from the Minister. On the whole I &amp;m disposed to allow and indirectly to encourage this process rather than to issue any fresh circular at tho present time requiring a general reduction.     The politioal diffioulty of such a circular is obvious.      It might even delay instead of hastening the return to work.     It would be denounced as open proof that the Government were definitely taking sides against ths miners.      It would certainly be resisted to the utmost in many of the mining Unions and there would be some oas?s in -which it could be enforced only by the appointment of Guardians to take the place of tho elected Guardians under   the Default Act of last Session. Such a general use of the Act to secure a reduction of relief would really be outside the purposes for which the Act was framed.10.     I propose, therefore, while not excluding the possible necessity for more drastic action if the strike should continue
Indefinitely, to confine myself at present to putting pressure upon Guardians to reconsider their expenditure in every direction as applications are made to me for further borrowing powers.     I should not, except in very special circumstances, propose to refuse borrowing powers because a reduction below the circular scale cannot be secured by agreement.25th October, 19 26 .

</content>
</cab>
