<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/261/0 images: 389-390</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1936.                                                       secret.                                                         Copy No.CP.  79 (36).CABINET.GERMANY  AND THE LOCARNO TREATY.            Memorandum by Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    M. FLANDIN in the course of his  last conversation at the meeting of the locarno Powers invited His  Majesty&apos;s Government to produce  at  our next meeting some statement  of our policy and procedure which might form a basisof discussion.  We resisted this appeal, and maintained that we would prefer to study M. Flandin&apos;s views before putting forward our own.    At the same time it is clearly desirable, if only for the purpose of clearingour own mind,  that  we prepare some statement  of  our  own views.  For thispurpose I circulate the attached paper to my colleagues.    In connection with paragraph 4 (iii), M. van Zeeland had formulated certain proposals (see Foreign Office despatch to Brussels No. 149 of the 14th March).They  were as follows :     (a) Automatic functioning of the action of the guarantors in the agreements           replacing the Locarno Treaties;    (b) Agreement regarding the establishment of contacts between the General           Staffs to lay  down the technical conditions in which the obligations           undertaken in the Pacts would eventually  be brought into effect;    (c) Increase of  the  material  precautions laid  down  in  the  multilateral           Pacts.    In my view the future structure of security in Western Europe should bein two parts :  First, non-aggression  pacts between Germany and France andBelgium, and perhaps Holland, which  would be  guaranteed by  Great Britainand Italy.   Second, a  superstructure consisting  of a pact of mutual assistance between Great Britain, France  and Belgium, which would be open to Germany.It must be  anticipated that  France and Belgirtm will desire that this pact of mutual assistance should approach as near as possible to what the Belgian PrimeMinister describes as  &quot; automatic functioning.&quot;  In any event, it is certain that both these Governments will ask that the pact of mutual assistance shall includeagreement  on the  establishment of  contacts between  the  General  Staffs of the signatory Powers.                                                                   A. E.Foreign Office, March 15, 1936.ri29in
                          SUGGESTED  PROCEDURE.    (A) Finding by the  Council, under Article 4 (2) of Locarno, that a breach of Article 43 of the Treaty of Versailles has been committed and notification ofthe finding to the Locarno Powers.    (B) Resolution by the Council on the following lines :     1. Condemnation of  Germany&apos;s action on following lines (Belgian draft) :     &apos;&apos; The Council of the League of Nations decides         (1) That the  scrupulous respect for all treaty  obligations is  a funda-    mental principle  of international  life  and an essential  condition of  the    maintenance of peace;        (2) That it is an essential principle of the law of nations that no Power    can liberate itself from the engagements of a treaty nor modify the stipula-    tions  thereof unless with the consent of the other contracting Parties;        (3) That the  breach of Article 43 of the Treaty of Versailles and the    unilateral repudiation of the Treaties of Locarno by the  German Government    is in contradiction with these principles;        (4) That by this unilateral action the German Government confers upon    itself no legal rights;        (5) That this unilateral action, by introducing a new disturbing element    into the international situation,  must necessarily appear  to be a  threat to    European security.    2.  Invitation to France and Germany to refer to either the Permanent Courtof International Justice  or the Permanent Court of Arbitration the question ofthe compatibility of the Franco-Soviet Pact with Locarno, and  any other matters which, it might be thought proper so to  refer.        (N.B. The Belgian proposal was to refer &quot; the German complaints &quot; to    the Franco-German  Conciliation Commission provided for  under Locarno.    The question whether the reference should be to conciliation or to one of the    above Courts depends on the matters which it might be decided to  deal with    in this way.)    3.  Arrangements to be laid down by the Council for the period pending and during negotiations proposed under 4.    . (a) Reaffirmation  of Locarno by  the signatory Powers other than Germany.           The following draft has been suggested :                 &apos;&apos; Nothing which has happened before or since  the said breach           has absolved the signatories  under the Treaty of  Locarno from any of           their obligations or guarantees,  which remain in their entirety until           a new convention is concluded.&quot;     (6) Stationing of  an International  Force, including  British troops, on either           side of  the  frontiers  between  France and  Germany  and between           Belgium and Germany.     (c) In view of the despatch of the International  Force, recommendation to           Germany, France and  Belgium  to suspend immediately all despatch           of troops  or  war material  into the  frontier  zones*  of  the three           countries, not to construct any new fortifications in those areas, and to           suspend work on existing fortifications.     4.  The Council takes note of the  German proposals 2 to 7 and invites the five Locarno Powers to negotiate on basis of :        (i)  These German  proposals so far as they concern  the five Locarno Powers.      (ii)  Revision of the status of the Rhineland on the basis of equality of rights           of neighbouring States.     (iii)  Compensation  to France  and Belgium for the diminution of security           which the revision of the status, of the Rhineland in the sense indicated           above would  represent for them.     March 15, 1936.* Extent of these zones to be specified ultimately

</content>
</cab>
