<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/72/8 images: 36-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Inde^SUBJECTCtilL PAY     cc (Et)x^ urnsNo.ContentsDate
10 DOWNING STREET
CONFIDENTIAL AND PERSONALCovering SECRETCABINET OFFICE70 Whitehall, London swia 2as   Telephone 01-233 ^3T9From the Secretary of the Cabinet: Sir Robert Armstrong kcb.cvoRef. AO523110 July 1981 foy&quot;Civil Service Pay: Cabinet 9 JulyI enclose a copy of the Most Confidential Record of the Cabinet&apos;sdiscussions on Civil Service pay on 9 July.    The existence of this Recordwas not mentioned in the Cabinet Conclusions and it should not, therefore,be referred to or quoted.I am sending copies to John Wiggins (Treasury), Jim Buckley (CSD)and Richard Dykes (Employment).    I should be grateful if they too wouldensure that the Record is not referred to and that it is only seen by officialswith a real need to know its contents.In due course, I should be grateful if copies could be returned to mein the Cabinet Office.(D J Wright)Private SecretaryC A Whitmore EsqCONFIDENTIAL AND PERSONAL
secretCopy No,CopiesMOST CONFIDENTIAL RECORDTOCC(81) 27th CONCLUSIONSThursday 9 July 1981CIVILSERVICEDISPUTETHE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that there had recentlybeen some partial abatement of the industrial action in the non-industrial Civil Service;   staff of the Passport Office were now workingnormally;   there had been a considerable falling off of disruptions inMinistry of Defence establishments;   the Air Traffic Controllers werenot taking any action this week.     The unions appeared to be continuingto concentrate on the revenue Departments, Scottish courts, SocialSecurity and Department of Employment offices, and the section of thePaymaster General&apos;s Office dealing with public sector pensions. Ifthe Government were to decide not to improve on its present pay offer,it was likely that industrial action would eventually crumble, but itcould well carry on for some time in particular areas and the costs tothe Government and the problems of recovering from the action weremounting.     If, on the other hand, the Cabinet wished to bring thedispute to an end it might be possible to do so by a stick and carrotapproach.    He could write to the Council of Civil Service Unions(CCSU) that afternoon to tell them that the Government had decidedthat unless the unions called off their campaign of industrial action by16 July, the date of 1 April 1981 for the pay increase would be withdrawnand the operative date decided later.     He would then instruct a seniorofficial of his Department to approach the Secretary of the CCSUprivately on Friday 10 July to explore the possible outlines of asettlement which the unions might be willing to recommend to theirmembers as adequate to bring the dispute to an end.     The officialwould make it clear that Ministers had not authorised anyconcessions;   the approach would be couched in terms of a personalexploration to see whether there were any proposals which might beput to Ministers for consideration, with some degree of probabilitythat they would be accepted.     The elements of a solution which mightbe explored were:-l.restoration of the operative date to 1 April;ii. consideration by the Government of one union nomineefor the inquiry;plus either or both of the following:1secret
secretiii. the offer for 1981 to be increased to l\ per cent, the extra2 per cent to be financed within existing Departmental cashlimits by further reductions in Civil Service staff costs;iv. an improvement on the present arbitration formula for1982 (that the Government was not committed to arbitration for1982 but did not rule it out) on one of the following lines:a. the Government would if necessary refer the disputeto arbitration in 1982, but would ask the House ofCommons to override the award if it was too high; orb. the Government would if necessary refer the disputeto arbitration in 1982, but would itself have power to setthe award aside on grounds of overriding national policy.While he wished to have authority to explore all the improvements ifnecessary, his aim would be to avoid, if possible, moving towards asettlement which included both the additional \ per cent in 1981 and theoffer of arbitration in 1982.In discussion the following main points were made -a. If an informal approach were to be made to the unions on10 July it would be better not to withdraw the operative date ofthe settlement in advance.     Withdrawal would alienate thosecivil servants who had loyally worked long hours to deal withthe consequences of their colleagues&apos; action, and would makeit much more difficult to negotiate a settlement.     It would bebetter for the Civil Service Department negotiator to beauthorised at his discretion, having explored the possibleterms of a settlement, to remind the union representatives thatthe Government would be bound to have to act on the possibility,of which he had already given public warning, of withdrawingthe operative date if the dispute were to continue.b. There were disadvantages in increasing the offer for 1981by \ per cent.     It would be questioned why this offer had notbeen made before;   this would have to be answered by referenceto the additional staff cuts envisaged.     The Secretary of Statefor Defence did not believe that he could find enough additionalstaff cuts in his Department, beyond those already planned,though he would do his best if this proved necessary. OtherDepartmental Ministers might also have difficulty in providingadequate staff savings, though they, too, would do their best.2secret
secretOn the other hand, if it proved impossible generally to find allthe necessary cuts, the increase in the pay offer to 7g per centcould be criticised as a fudge.     There was also a risk that theoffer of a further \ per cent to the non-industrial Civil Servicewould have repercussive effects on other public sectornegotiations.     It would be particularly damaging if it wereannounced before the nurses accepted - as it now seemed likelythey would - the offer of 6 per cent to them.c. The offer of arbitration in 1982, under either of the methodssuggested, could lead to difficult problems next year.Experience of the arbitral award made to the teachers in 1980had shown the difficulties in practice of inviting both Houses ofParliament to override an award.     Although it would bepracticable, and better, to confine the proposed override powerto the House of Commons in respect of the Civil Servicearbitration in 1982, this would not wholly meet the problem. Itwould be much more satisfactory if that arbitration could bemade subject to a right of the Government to set the award asideon grounds of overriding national policy.    The unions would, ofcourse, regard such a provision as much less satisfactory thana Parliamentary procedure, particularly as the situation nextyear could be one in which it might be very difficult for theGovernment not to exercise its right of override.d. Unless a firm offer were made quickly to the industrialcivil servants, they might join their non-industrial colleagues intaking action.     This reinforced the case for agreeing quickly ona settlement for the non-industrials,  so that a comparable offercould be made to the industrials.    It was also relevant that theindustrial Civil Service unions had explicitly stated that thealteration in their settlement date next year to 1 April, whichthey were seeking in their current negotiations, would enablethem to take joint action then with the non-industrial CivilService in future.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the Lord President of the Council should now beauthorised to try to secure an early settlement to the dispute on thelines he had proposed,  except that he should defer making any move towithdraw the operative date of the pay increase this year before theoutcome of the further informal negotiations was known.    There weredisadvantages in both the proposal to offer an additional \ per cent in1981 and to offer improved arbitration arrangements in 1982.     It was3secret
secre1clear that the Cabinet would prefer a settlement which did not includeboth elements;   and that, if arbitration were to be offered for the 1982settlement, they would prefer it to be subject to Governmental over-ride, without reference to Parliament.    The Cabinet had also notedthat, while all Ministers would do their best to secure additional off-setting staff economies should an enhanced offer of pay in 1981 provenecessary,  some Departments would face particular difficulty in thisregard.     Finally the Cabinet had authorised her, the Chancellor of theExchequer, the Lord President of the Council and the Secretary of Statefor Employment to supervise negotiations with the Civil Service unionswithin the framework of the Lord President of the Council&apos;s proposalsand in the light of their discussion.The Cabinet -Agreed that the Prime Minister, the Chancellor of theExchequer, the Lord President of the Council and theSecretary of State for Employment should havediscretion to authorise negotiations with leaders of theCivil Service unions on the lines proposed by the LordPresident of the Council, taking account of the pointsmade in their discussion.Cabinet Office10 July 19814secret

</content>
</cab>
