<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/181/11 images: 319-322</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
10 Downing Street22 January 1975C(75) 11 COPY NO22 January 1975CABINETREFERENDUM ON e.c. MEMBERSHIPNote by the Prime minister attach a draft of the statement which I propose to make in the House ofCommons tomorrow.    We shall have an opportunity to discuss this attomorrow morning&apos;s meeting of the Cabinet.H W
Pifift! fi hp Kiti a British MEMBERSHIP OF THE EUROPEAN COMMUNITIESSTATEMENT BY.THE PRIME minister mr. Speaker,  I will with permission make a statement aboutthe means by which the British people will decide the issue ofour membership of the European Community.the outcome of our renegotiation of the terms of membership isknown, the British people should have the right to decide,...through the ballot box, by means either of a General Election orof a Referendum, whether Britain should continue in membership of the European Community or should withdraw.3.      The Government has decided that this should be done bymeans of a Referendum.4.     Prolonged uncertainty and delay on the decision of the british people are in the interests neither of Britain nor of othermembers of the Community.    After fifteen years of discussion and negotiation it is an issue which all of us in this House andin the country want to see settled;  and uncertainty about thefuture of British membership is inhibiting the work of theCommunity.    The Government is committed to putting the issue tothe people before 10 October this year.    Provided that the outcome of renegotiation is known in time, we intend to hold the referendum before the summer holiday, which means in practicenot later than the end of June.    We shall therefore propose tothe House arrangements which would make it possible to hold the referendum on that timetable, tight though it will be.5.     When the outcome of renegotiation is known, theGovernment will consider what its own recommendation should be,whether for continued membership of the Community on the basisof the renegotiated terms, or for withdrawal, and will announceits decision to the House in due course.    That announcementwill no doubt provide an opportunity for the House to debate thequestion of substance.2.It is the declared policy of the Government that, once
Cs f\n. * ir&quot;! p rr IV] -T* I ft6.      The circumstances of this Referendum are unique;  and thematter is one on which strong views have long been held whichcross party lines.    The Cabinet has therefore decided that,  ifwhen the time comes there are members of the Government(including members of the Cabinet) who do not feel able to accept and support the Governments recommendation, whatever it may be,they will, once the recommendation has been announced, be free to support and speak in favour of a different conclusion inthe Referendum campaign.7.      As to the arrangements for the Referendum,  I told the house on Tuesday, the rules for the test of public opinion must bemade by this House.    The Government proposes within a very fewweeks to publish a White Paper on the rules and arrangements for conducting the Referendum.    The White Paper will set out thevarious possible courses and the Governments proposals on suchmatters as the information policy of the Government, thequestion of expenditure by campaigning groups, and arrangementsfor conducting the poll, counting the votes and announcing theresult.8.      The Government will find time for a debate on the white paper in this House before the Easter recess.    That debate will of course be separate from, and will   precede, the parliamentary debate which will be necessary on the outcome of thenegotiations.    The debate on the White Paper will enable theGovernment to take full account of the views expressed by Rt. Hon.and Hon. Members of this House,  and by public opinion generally,in drafting the necessary legislation for the Referendum.r.9.      The Government proposes to introduce the legislation aroundEaster-time.    As it will be constitutional legislation, we shallpropose that all stages should be taken on the floor of the House.If we are to be able to hold the Referendum before the summerholiday, the Bill will need to complete its passage through bothHouses and to receive Royal assent by the end of May.22 January 1975


</content>
</cab>
