<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/45/9 images: 134-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1944The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issuedRECORD OF A CONVERSATION BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTERAND MARSHAL STALIN AT THE SOVIET EMBASSY AT TEHRANON 30th NOVEMBER, 1943.I circulate for the information of my colleagues the attached record of the above conversation.for the personalMOST SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (44) 9.7th January, 1944.WAR CABINET.W. S. C.10 Downing Street, S.W.1,7th January, 1944.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT54MOST SECRET.RECORD OF CONVERSATION BETWEEN THE PRIME MINISTERAND MARSHAL STALIN AT THE SOVIET EMBASSY, 12-45 p.m,30th NOVEMBER, 1943.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he was half American and he had agreat affection for the American people. What he was going to say was notto be understood as anything disparaging of the Americans and he would be perfectly loyal towards them, but there were things which it was better to saybetween two persons.We had a preponderance of troops over the Americans in the Mediterranean.There were three to four times more British troops than American there. Thatis why he was anxious that the troops in the Mediterranean should not be ham-strung if it could be avoided, and he wanted to use them all the time. In Italythere were some 13 to 14 divisions of which 9 or 10 were British. There were two armies, the 5th Anglo-American Army, and the 8th Army, which was.entirely British. The choice had been represented as keeping to the date of&quot; Overlord &quot; or pressing on with the operations in the Mediterranean. But thatwas not the whole story. The Americans wanted him to attack, to undertakean amphibious operation in the Bay of Bengal against the Japanese in March.He was not keen about it. If we had in the Mediterranean the landing craftneeded for the Bay of Bengal, we would have enough to do all we wanted inthe Mediterranean and still be able to keep to an early date for &quot; Overlord.&quot;It was not a choice between the Mediterranean and the date of &quot;Overlord,&quot;but between the Bay of Bengal and the date of &quot;Overlord.&quot; He thought wewould have all we wanted in the way of landing craft. However, the americans had pinned us down to a date for &quot;Overlord &quot; and operations in the Mediter-ranean had suffered in the last two months. Our army was somewhat disheartenedby the removal of the 7 divisions. We had sent home our 3 divisions and the americans were sending theirs, all in preparation for &quot;Overlord.&quot; That wasthe reason for not taking full advantage with the Italian collapse. But it alsoproved the earnestness of our preparations for &quot; Overlord.&quot;Now a word about the Commander-in-Chief. The Prime Minister agreedthat it was vital to get the question settled. Up till August we British wereto have had the supreme command in &apos;&apos; Overlord,&apos;&apos; but at Quebec the president had asked him to consider the appointment of an American Commander-in-Chieffor &quot;Overlord&quot; and we British were to have the supreme command in theMediterranean. The Prime Minister has agreed because the Americans,,although equal in numbers to the British at the commencement, would soon havea preponderance in &quot; Overlord &quot; and their stake would be greater after the first few months. On the other hand, as the British had the preponderance in theMediterranean, the Prime Minister had his own ideas about the war there. he considered it right that we should have the supreme command in the Mediter-ranean. He had accepted the Presidents proposal and it now rested with himto nominate the Commander-in-Chief. As soon as the President did so, thePrime Minister would nominate the Mediterranean Commander-in-Chief andalso other commanders for important.commands, such as the air, navy, &amp;c. ThePresident had delayed the appointment for domestic reasons connected with highpersonages, but the Prime Minister had urged him to nominate the Commander-in-Chief for &quot;Overlord&quot; before they all separated in Tehran.MARSHAL STALIN said that was good.THE PRIME MINISTER then turned to the question of landing craft.He said it was the bottle-neck. We had plenty of troops in the Mediterraneaneven after the removal of the 7 divisions and there would be a big army in theUnited Kingdom, British and American. All turned on landing craft. Whenthe Marshal had made his momentous announcement two days before about Russiaf26687]
coming into the war against Japan after Hitler&apos;s surrender, the Prime Minister;had immediately suggested to the Americans that they (the Americans) might;find more landing craft for the operations they had been asked to do in the indian ocean, or that they might send some landing craft from the Pacific to help thefirst lift of &quot; Overlord.&apos;&apos;&apos; If so, there might be enough for alL But the Americans,were very touchy about the Pacific. He had pointed out to them that a new situation had arisen and more help might be given for &apos;&apos; Overlord &apos;&apos; in consequenceof the fact that after Hitler&apos;s defeat the prospects of the war against japan would be facilitated by what the Marshal had said.THE PRIME MINISTER said he wanted to explain the nature of thequestion between himself and the Americans, The Marshal would see that it was;not luke-warmness about &quot; Overlord &quot; but only because he wanted to get all heneeded for the Mediterranean and at the same time keep to the date for &apos;&apos; Over-lord.&quot; But it had to be hammered out between the Staffs and he hoped to do soin Cairo. Unfortunately the Generalissimo had been there and Chinese questionshad taken up nearly all their time. He was sure that in the end enough landing craft would be found for all.Now about &quot; Overlord.&quot; The British would have ready by the date fixed inMay or June 16 divisions with their corps, troops, landing craft troops and ack-ack and other services, a total of slightly over half a million men. These would consist of some of our best troops including battle worthy men from the Mediter-ranean. In addition the British would have all that was needed from the royal navy to handle transportation and to protect the Army, and there would be theMetropolitan air forces of about 4,000 first-line aircraft in continuous action.In addition the American import of troops was now beginning. Up till now theyhad sent mainly air troops and stores for the Army, but in the next four or five months the Prime Minister thought 150,000 men or more would come everymonth, making a total of 7 to 8 hundred thousand men by May. The defeat ofthe submarines in the Atlantic had made this movement possible. He was infavour of the operation in the South of France taking place about the same time as &quot; Overlord &quot; or at whatever moment was found correct. We would be holdingenemy troops in Italy and of the 22 to 23 divisions, as many as possible would goto the South of France and the rest would remain in Italy.A great battle was impending in Italy. General Alexander commands the15 Group of armies, consisting of the 5th and 8th Armies, and has about half amillion men under him. There are 13 to 14 Allied divisions against 9 to 10German divisions, but the weather is bad and bridges have been swept away.But in December we intend to push on with General Montgomery leading the 8thArmy. The landing would be made at the Tiber. At the same time the 5th army would be fiercely engaged holding the enemy. It might turn into a miniatureStalingrad. We did not intend to push into the wide part of Italy but to hold&apos; the narrow leg. MARSHAL STALIN said he must warn the Prime Minister thatthe Red Army was depending on the success of our invasion of Northern France.If there were no operations in May, then the Red Army would think that therewould be no operations at all this year. The weather would be bad and therewould be transport difficulties. If the operation did not take place he did not want the Red Army to be disappointed. Disappointment could only create badfeeling and he did not want this to happen. If there was no big change in theEuropean war in 1944 it would be very difficult for the Russians to carry on.They Avere war weary. He feared that a feeling of isolation might develop inthe Red Army. That was why he had tried to find out whether &quot; Overlord &quot;would be undertaken on time as promised. If not, he would have to take stepsto prevent a bad feeling in. the Red Army.   It was most important.THE PRIME MINISTER said &quot;Overlord&quot; would certainly take placeprovided the enemy did not bring into France larger forces than the americans and British could gather there. Supposing the Germans had 30 to 40 divisions inFrance, he did not think the force we were going to put across the Channel wouldbe able to hold on. He was not afraid of going on shore but what would happenon the 30th, 40th or 50th day ? But if the Red Army engaged the enemy and weheld them in Italy and perhaps the Yugoslavs and possibly the Turks came intothe war, then he was hopeful that we could win and that Germany would nothave enough troops.MARSHAL STALIN said that as regards the Red Army the first steps of&quot; Overlord&quot; would have a good effect and if he knew that the operation was going to take place in May or June, he could already prepare blows against
Germany. The spring was the best time. March and April were months ofslackness during which he could concentrate troops and material, and in May and june he could organise decisive blows against Germany. Germany would haveno troops for France. The transfer of German divisions to the east was continu-ing. The Germans were afraid of their eastern front because it had no Channelwhich had to be crossed and there was no France to be entered. The germans were afraid of the Red Army advance. The Red Army will advance if it seesthat help is coming from the Allies.   He asked when would &quot; Overlord &quot; begin.THE PRIME MINISTER said that he could not answer without thePresident, but the answer would be given at lunch-time, and he thought that theMarshal would be satisfied.






</content>
</cab>
