<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/41/16 images: 126-133</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1944;.SECRET.W.M. (44)16th Conclusions.Copy No.   52WAR CABINET 16 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Monday, 7th February, 1944, at 5-30 p.m.The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.PLord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P.. Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.of   State   for   ForeignSecretaryAffairs.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present :The Right Hon. S. M. Bruce, Repre-sentative of the Government of theCommonwealth of Australia.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon.   Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,  M.P.,  Minister of  AircraftProduction.The . Right   Hon.   Lord   Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Items6-7).The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Item 5).Admiral of the Fleet Sir AndrewCunningham, First Sea Lord andChief of Naval Staff (Items 1-4).Field-Marshal Sirof the Imperial1-4).The  Right  Hon.   Viscount   Simon,Lord Chancellor (Items 5-7).The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.The   Right   Hon.    Sir   ArchibaldSinclair,   Bt.,  M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,President of the Board of Education.Colonel    the    Right    Hon.    J.    J.LlewellIn, M.P., Minister of Food(Items 6-7).The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Hon.  Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Items 1-4).Marshal of the Air Force Sir CharlesF. A. Portal, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-4).Alan Brooke, ChiefGeneral Staff (Items -Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Lieutenant-General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Sir Gilbert Laithwaite.Mr. L. F. Burgis.f26907-2]
WAR CABINET 16 (44).Contents.MinuteNo. Subject. Page1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ....      ....      ....      73Air Operations:Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Pacific.Naval Operations.Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.Military Operations:Italy.Russia.2      Italy      ............................       ....       73Future of the Italian Fleet.3      Poland  .... ....      ....      ....      .... 744      Catterick Bridge        ....................   .   ....      74Explosion of an Ammunition Train.5      Indian States   ....      ....       ....       ....       ....       ....       ....      74Petty States in Western India.6      India     ....       ........................       ....       74Shipment of Food Grains.7      London Airfield for Transport Services    ....      ....      ....      76
Naval, Militaryand AirOperations.(PreviousReference:W.M. (44) 13thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Home Theatre.Mediterranean.Pacific.NavalOperations.Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.MilitaryOperations.Italy.Russia.1. The Chiefs of Staff reported the principal events of theprevious week.Owing to the moon and bad weather, the operations of BomberCommand had been limited to minelaying and light raids.United States bombers had attacked Frankfurt, Wilhelmshavenand Emden.CrossboAv &apos;&apos; targets had also been attacked.During January 24,000 tons of bombs had been dropped onGermany.  This was the highest figure reached in any month.Coastal Command had attacked 3 U-boats, possibly damaging 1.Enemy losses for the week, including claims by the UnitedStates Air Forces, amounted to 69 destroyed, 9 probably destroyedand 19 damaged.  Allied losses amounted to 39 bombers, 32 fightersand 6 Coastal Command aircraft.Bad weather had interfered with flying operations, but attackshad been made on enemy communications, airfields and battletargets.  Enemy losses amounted to 153 destroyed, against 53 Allied.Japanese aircraft claimed as destroyed during the weekamounted to 288, including 141 destroyed on the ground. Alliedlosses amounted to 20.The Chief of the Air Staff undertook to inform the WarCabinet of the total number of Japanese aircraft claimed asdestroyed during the previous twelve months.Confirmed shipping losses by enemy action for the previousweek amounted to 14,352 tons. Losses for January, includingbelated reports, amounted to 108,400 tons.Our naval forces continued to support the land operations.The maintenance position was satisfactory.In the Adriatic a 5,000-ton German tanker and other craft hadbeen sunk off the Dalmatian Coast.A German U-boat had sunk 5 merchant ships since the26th January.During the previous week German counter-attacks had beenmade on either flank of the Anzio bridgehead. During one suchattack one of our brigades had been isolated, but a counter-attackhad restored the position and had enabled the brigade to withdraw.On the main front further south heavy fighting had taken placeand Cassino had been outflanked; we were now endeavouring toclear the town.In the North the Russians had made considerable progress andwere now close to Luga station. Near Vitebsk the Germans hadreported Russian attacks, but these had not been mentioned so farby the Russians. Further south&apos; the Russian capture of Luck andRovno threatened important railway communications. Attemptsby the Germans to relieve the ten divisions surrounded north ofShpola had failed. The elimination of these ten divisions, togetherwith the probable destruction of another five divisions in theNikopol area, endangered the whole of the German positions in thissalient.The War Cabinet-Took note of these statements.Italy.Future of theItalian Fleet.(PreviousReference:W.M. (43) 147thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet of theposition regarding the future of the Italian Fleet. A record of theRrime Ministers statement is contained in the Secretary&apos;s StandardFile of War Cabinet Conclusions.[26907-21b 2
Poland. 3.   The Prime Minister gave the War Cabinet an account of(Previous an interview which he and the Secretary of State for ForeignReference: Affairs had had with the Polish Prime Minister.   A record isW.M. (44) 15th contained  in the  Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War  CabinetConclusions, Conclusions.Minute 1.)Train.Cattenok 4    Reference was made to the ammunition train which hadBndge. exploded while being loaded on the  previous  Friday.    SomeExplosion of an 8 persons had been killed and about 70 injured.   ConsiderableAmmunition damage had been caused in the immediate neighbourhood.The Secretary of State for War said that an enquiry wastaking place. But, as the station had been destroyed and the recordslost, it seemed unlikely that the cause of the explosion would betraced. There was no reason, however, to suppose that the explosionwas not due to an accident.The War Cabinet Took note of this statement.Indian States.Petty States inWestern India.(PreviousReference:W.M. (44) 13thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. At their meeting on the 31st January, 1943, the WarCabinet had had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary ofState for India (W.P. (44) 57), to which was annexed a draft Billto render legal the attachment of certain Indian States to other-Indian States. The War Cabinet had then endorsed the proposalof the Prime Minister that the Leader of the House of Commonsshould discuss with the Leader of the House of Lords whetherarrangements could be made for the Bill to be introduced in theHouse of Lords, and, if so, whether undue expenditure of Parlia-mentary time would be involved; and that the matter should befurther discussed in the light of this report.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs reported that, as. aresult of his discussions, he favoured the introduction of the Billin the House of Lords. The Leader of the House of Lords antici-pated no difficulty in this course. It was hoped that discussion ofthe Bill in the House of Commons would not be protracted.The War Cabinet-Approved the proposal to introduce in the House of Lordslegislation   on  the  lines  of   the  draft  contained   inAnnexure I to W.P. (44) 57.India.Shipment ofPood Grains.(PreviousReference:W.M. (43) 152ndConclusions,Minute 2.)6. The War Cabinet at their meeting on the 10th November,1943, had agreed that shipping should be provided for 100,000 tonsof food grains to India during the first two months of 1944.The War Cabinet now had before them (a) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India(W.P. (44) 63). After surveying the harvest returns and the presentprospects, the Viceroy stressed the importance of food in main-taining India&apos;s economic stability and in helping to close herinflationary gap. The Viceroy urged that it was of essentialimportance that, as recommended by the Gregory Food GrainsCommittee, His Majesty&apos;s Government should provide shipping tocarry imports of 1 million tons of wheat for current consumptionand half a million tons for reserve. The Secretary of State forIndia strongly supported Lord Waveu&apos;s recommendation.(b) A note by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs(W.P. (44) 76) circulating on behalf of the Secretary of State forthe Colonies a memorandum by the Colonial Office urging that itbe made a condition of import assistance to India that the Govern-ment of India agree in return to permit the export of 10,000 tons
of rice a month to Ceylon to meet the minimum essential require-ments of that island.(c) A Memorandum by the Minister of Food (W.P. (44) 77)stressing the importance of the export from India to Ceylon of10,000 tons of rice monthly from her crop,- and urging that, if it wasagreed that India should import wheat, she should, in view of theprobable serious shortage of oils and fats in the world, be asked torelease in the year ending the 31st October, 1944, 475,000 tons ofground-nuts, over 400,000 tons of which had duly been purchasedby the Ministry of Food.The President of the Board of Education, speaking on behalfof the Secretary of State for India, said that both he and theViceroy were anxious to secure the War Cabinefs approval to theproposals in W.P. (44) 63, both on psychological and politicalgrounds, and in order to buttress the position before the presentcrop came on the market in April or May. The Government ofIndia, who had just fixed a maximum price for millets and wereconsidering a maximum price for rice, had in these last few weekstaken definite steps towards a well-based all-India food policy. Onpsychological grounds, it would be difficult for India to agree toexport ground-nuts or rice unless India&apos;s demands for the importof wheat were met.The Prime Minister questioned the statistical basis of theGovernment of India&apos;s case. The high average production of thethree years ended 1938/39 i.e., some 53^ million tons -had beencited in W.P. (44) 63 as the normal crop. To this the high averagenet imports of 1,298,000 tons for the three years ending 1939/40had been added, to produce a total average consumption of54,793,000 tons. As the estimated crops only amounted to53,000,000 tons, a deficit in 1944 of about 1,000,000 tons resulted,to which there had to be added 500,000 tons for special defenceneeds. But for the four years ending 1941 /42 the average consump-tion was 52,331,000 tons, i.e., 2-g- million tons less than the figure citedby the Secretary of State. This difference would, of course, morethan make good the 1^ million tons calculated deficit.It looked, too, as though, in calculating the 53,800,000 tonsavailable, the fact stated in the paper, that the rice crop wasexpected to be up by 2 million tons and the wheat crop down by1 million tons, had been left out of account. That would appear tomake an extra 1 million tons available.He was gravely concerned in these circumstances at,a suggestionthat shipping, of which we were in such short supply, should be usedon a major scale to import food into India, given the effect of itsdiversion alike on operations and on our imports of food into thiscountry, which could be further reduced only at the cost of muchsuffering.The President of the Board of Education expressed hisreadiness to examine at once the statistical basis of the case, andadded that the Viceroy was ready to send an expert representativehome to explain the position in greater detail.The Minister of War Transport said that, while he had beenable to provide the cereals previously sanctioned by the War Cabinetfor India, there was no prospect of any further shipping being madeavailable by the United States, owing to the increasing demandsfor shipping for military purposes. It would be quite out of thequestion to find shipping for the million and a half tons now askedfor, which would represent 250 voyages from Australia to India.Any shipping allocated would inevitably reduce the UnitedKingdom import programme.The Minister added that he was ready to ensure continuanceof imports of rice in Ceylon for the present, at the rate of 10,000 tonsa month, either from Egypt or from Brazil.
London Airfieldfor TransportServices.(PreviousReference:W.M. (43) 148thConclusions,Minute 4.)7. At their meeting on the 1st November, 1943, the WarCabinet had referred to a group of Ministers for enquiry and reporta memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air, proposing theestablishment of a new airfield near London capable of accommo-dating heavy transport aircraft of the latest type.The War Cabinet now had before them the report of theCommittee, presided over by the Lord President of the Council(W.P. (44) 73), recommending that the Air Ministry should beauthorised to proceed with work on Stages 1 and 2 of the proposedscheme.The War Cabinet had a preliminary discussion of this Report,in the course of which the Prime Minister expressed doubts as tothe need, on military grounds, for starting work on this airfield atthe present time. He also questioned whether, in view of the otherdemands on our resources, we should be justified in making availableat this juncture the labour required. The Prime Minister asked tobe furnished with a statement showing the amount of labourrequired, month by month, on the basis of the scheme recommendedin the Committee&apos;s Report.Further discussion of the Committee&apos;s Report was. postponedto a later meeting.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,7th February, 1944.Other points taken were as follows: (a) Even on the basis of the figures in the memorandum by theSecretary of State for India, the shortage in Bengal was a very smallpercentage of normal consumption.(b) It was urged that shortage in Bengal was partly politicalin character, caused by Marwari supporters of Congress in an effortto embarrass the existing Muslim Government of Bengal, theGovernment of India and His Majesty&apos;s Government.(c) The course of prices and the actual food situation in Indiatended, moreover, to depend on political and psychological factors.India in the past had relied on Burma, both for very substantialannual imports and for reserves. With Burma in enemy hands, thesituation could be exploited for either political or economic reasons.(d) To the extent that the shortage was political, the Viceroy&apos;sgeneral position would be strengthened if he was given the meansto deal with it; and, provided shipping was available, the way tobreak a speculative market was to ship in wheat.(e) The Government of India were unduly tender withspeculators and hoarders. It was pointed out, on the other hand,that they were doing their utmost to establish a sound food policy.The Viceroy, too, had been very successful in carrying with him theimportant Muslim grain-producing provinces, and it was desirableto strengthen him by giving him the support for which he asked.On the suggestion of the Prime Minister, the War Cabinet &apos;Agreed that the matter should be further examined, withparticular reference to the statistical basis of the paperthat had been put before them by the President of theBoard of Education on behalf of the Secretary of State forIndia, in consultation with the Ministers of Food and WarTransport and the Paymaster-General; and that it shouldbe considei^ed again in the light of their report.



</content>
</cab>
