<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/25/26 images: 212-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(this DOCUMENT is THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT)&quot; 4. ,,t cnoriHi care may betaken toIt la requested tnatbpeuaicaiemajensure the secrecy of this document.Rji, C RET.gj?. (42) 2465th JUNE,  1942cWAR CABINET.THE POSSIBLE COURSE OP THE RUSSIAN campaign and ITS IMPLICATIONS.Note by the Secretary of the War Cabinet,covering an appreciation by the joint intelligence Sub--Committee&apos; and a&quot; noteby the Chiefs of Staff.COPY NO.by direction of the Prime Minister, and in accordancewith Conclusion 4 of W,M0(42)72nd Meeting,  the attachedappreciation by the Joint Into Hi once Sub-Comiaittee is circulated, together with a covering note by the Chiefsof Staff, for the information of the Y/ar Cabinet and theDefence Committee (Operations).(Signed)    eoeo  bridges.NOTE by THE CHIEFS OF STAPFThe Chiefs of Staff are in general agreement with theattached appreciation, except that:-(a) they think that it presents a picture rathertoo favourable to Russia, particularly as regardsforecasts of aircraft production.(b) the Russians may be unable to hold theGermans to the line forecast in paragraphs 67and 68 and shown in green on the sketch map.Great George Street, S.Wclo^9TH JUNE,  19420
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  June 1942.     ^&quot;^secret.Copy No.J.I.C. (42) 200 (Final).June 1, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.Joint Intelligence Sub-Committee.THE POSSIBLE COURSE OF THE RUSSIAN CAMPAIGN AND its implications.Report by the Joint Intelligence Sub-Committee.THE annexed paper is an attempt to appreciate the course events may take in Russia during this summer, and the implications those events may have forthe war as a whole. Our information about the dispositions, resources and war potential of our Russian ally is considerably less than our information about theenemy, and the appreciation should be read with this in mind.2. The main points in the appreciation to which we wish to draw attentionare set out below.3. The following, in summarised form, are the estimated relative strengths of the German and Russian land and air forces engaged in or available for operations in the Russo-German theatre of war this year : -German. Russian.Land. Land.Armoured divisions ... ... 19Motorised divisions ... - ... 15Light divisions      ... ... 7Cavalry divisions    ... ... 1Mountain divisions ... ... 5Infantry divisions  ... ... 115Infantry low-category divi-sions        ...      ... ... 20Total        ......   182Potential reinforcements 13-15 divisions, including 4armoured. The Germans have alsoengaged on or available for theRussian front 36 divisions from the armies of the other European axis power. This figure may be increasedby a further 23 divisions.A ir.Infantry divisionsCavalry divisionsTotal...Tank brigades...170-25023- 37200-28050Air.3,500 aircraft (including reserves). 4,000-4,500 aircraft (includingreserves).4. From the point of view of communications, topography and strategicpositions from which to launch an offensive, the Germans appear to be better[23913] b
2placed than the Russians. The Germans have an advantage in the efficiency oftheir armoured formations and are probably superior in command, mobility andtraining, both of land and air forces. The Russians, on the other hand, are likelyto be numerically superior and, in spite of their losses of large industrial areaslast year, should be able, in view of the expansion of Russian industry furthereast, adequately to equip and maintain their forces. They are likely to suffer from no shortage of aircraft. They now have the benefit of a year&apos;s experienceof war.5. The German troops will no doubt, with the improvement of weather conditions and the resumption of the offensive, recover from the trials of thewinter and still be an efficient fighting machine. On the other hand, once they realise that they cannot achieve victory this year, their morale may deterioraterapidly. Russian morale is high. In fighting spirit the Russian is probably to-day equal, if not superior, to the German. His morale is unlikely to collapseeven in the face of heavy losses. An important factor affecting the morale of theGerman troops in Russia may be the news of heavy bombing of German towns.Russian morale is not likely to be subjected to this strain.6. Germany&apos;s general economic position has deteriorated since June 1941,but the effects of that deterioration on her power to wage war will be gradual.This deterioration would be accelerated by heavy and sustained bombing ofGerman industrial areas during the summer. From the economic point of view,the Russians can, if necessary, withdfaw several hundred miles. Even after theloss of Leningrad, the Moscow industrial area and the Caucasian oilfields, theycould still maintain substantial air and land forces in the field, at any rate for aconsiderable time.7. Politically, the Stalin regime would be strong enough to withstand suchreverses.8. Since last summer the German air forces, have shrunk in numbers.During the winter the Germans have been unable to withdraw land formationsfrom Russia on a large scale for rest and refitting. The Germans are thereforeunlikely to be able to carry out large-scale offensives on many sections of the frontsimultaneously, as they did last year. The main battle is likely to take place inthe south, and the Germans, with their superior mobility and administrativeability, will probably gain initial successes. With such large forces engaged,however, on both sides, fairly evenly matched, and with so big an area for manoeuvre, it is unlikely that a decisive phase will be reached by August.9. Between August and October, however, events may move rapidly to aclimax. Both sides will undoubtedly have suffered severe casualties. The german air Force may be reduced from a total operational strength to-day of 5,800aircraft on all fronts to some 4,500 aircraft a force which will have to be main-tained on practically a &quot; factory to unit &quot; basis. The German High Commandmay be faced at about this time with the problem of whether to throw in their last reserves, even to the extent of dangerously denuding occupied countries, inthe hope of bringing about a complete Russian defeat before the winter, or to conserve their resources to meet the growing Anglo-American threat from theWest. The margin between success or failure may be very narrow and it may betouch and go which adversary collapses first. If the Germans realise that theycannot avoid a further winter campaign in Russia and are faced with the threat of Anglo-American invasion in the West, collapse on their part may, as in 1918,ensue with startling rapidity.10. On the other hand the possibility of a Russian collapse cannot be ruled out. We estimate that should Russia collapse the Germans would duringthe winter, after making provision for the garrisoning of Russia and otheroccupied territories, be able to build up to meet a threatened Anglo-Americaninvasion of the Continent next spring a force of some 2,500 aircraft and afield army, on the 1st April, 1943, of some 30-50 divisions, including 5-10armoured and 5-10 motorised divisions (rising by the 1st June, 1943, to 60-80divisions, including 20 armoured and 20 motorised divisions). Subject to conditions then prevailing, a part of this force could be employed by the Germansfor offensive operations in the Middle East.. Great George Street, S.W. 1.June 1, 1942.
ANNEX.The Possible Course of the Russian Campaign and its Implications.In this paper we draw a comparison between the situation of the opposingsides in the Russo-German war as it was at the outbreak of the campaign in1941, and as it is to-day. We also attempt an appreciation of the courseevents may take in Russia between now and the beginning of August, 1942,and of the implications of those events for the course of the war thereafter.2. Our information about the dispositions, resources and war potential of our Russian ally is considerably less than our information about the enemy and the report should be read with this in mind.Part I Comparison of Strengths.(A) Land Forces in the Battle Zone.3. In June last year the Germans had om and available for the russian front about 150 divisions including 19 armoured, 15 motorised, 4 light, 4mountain and 2 cavalry divisions. These were supported by about 40 divisionsprovided by the European Axis partners.4. At that date the Russians had in European Russia the equivalent of194 divisions, including 30 cavalry and 2 tank divisions and 62 tank brigades.5. On the 15th May, 1942, the number of identified German divisions onthe Russian front was 182, including 19 armoured, 15 motorised, 7 light,1 cavalry, 5 mountain, 115 infantry and 20 low category divisions, togetherwith 36 divisions provided by the other European Axis Powers. At that date the Russians had at or near the front the equivalent of some 200-280 divisions(including 170-250 infantry divisions, 23-37 cavalry divisions) and 50 tankbrigades.6. In June 1941 the German Army had some 25-30 divisions available asreserves for the Russian front. In addition, there were 6 divisions called on fromthe other Axis Powers.7. The Germans should now have available in the course of the next twomonths the following potential reinforcements : 4 armoured divisions.1 motorised division.1-3 mountain divisions.1 infantry division.6 Ioav category divisions.Germany&apos;s allies might contribute up to a further 23 divisions.8. Compared with the German forces, the Russians have a preponderance of some 30-80 infantry divisions, approximate equality in tank strengths, and apreponderance of some 28 cavalry divisions.9. On the other hand, the Russian Army has not the equivalent of theGerman spearhead formations, consisting of Panzer, motorised and mountaindivisions, but relies rather on the employment of masses of infantry supportedby a great weight of artillery and tanks.10. Of the 23 German armoured divisions (excluding those in Libya) 7 havebeen thoroughly rested and refitted and two are newly formed and have not beenin action. The mountain divisions have been brought up to strength. Perhaps12 infantry divisions have been withdrawn for rest and refit. Thus Germanyfaces the beginning ,of the new campaign with her free reserves lower than ever before. The spearhead force on which she must rely for her offensive will for themost part have had no more than a partial rest and refit behind the lines inRussia. *[23913]
Equipment.German.11. In spite of the losses incurred since the war with Russia began, thereis not likely to be a general shortage of equipment in the German Army. Theyhave big reserves of tanks and artillery, but there is a shortage of M.T.Russian. *12. A good deal of the equipment lost in 1941 has probably been replaced.The winter operations are not likely to have caused a serious drain on equipment,particularly on heavy guns and&quot;tanks. The Russian Army has adequate suppliesof small arms and mortars for the scale of equipment of their army.13. At the opening of the summer campaign, therefore, the Russians shouldbe able to place in the field, and, unless major disasters occur, maintain forcesat least numerically equal, if not superior, to the Germans.Morale.14. In 1941, the German soldier was confident of winning a quick andoverwhelming victory. Though he has fought extremely well during the winter,he now realises that the Russian is a formidable foe and that a quick victory is unlikely.15. The Russian soldier, on the other hand, realises that the German army is not invincible, and is imbued with a fierce determination to drive the invaderfrom his country. He has learnt a good deal about measures to counter Germanmethods of attack.Comparative Efficiency.16. The German Army is still a first-class fighting machine and can beexpected to plan and execute the attack with the same thoroughness as in 1941,although possibly with rather less confidence. The Red Army High Commandis inferior to the German, and the Russian forces cannot compare with theGermans in training and mobility. On the other hand, the Germans will find it more difficult to obtain surprise, particularly surprise in tactical methods. Thebalance is not weighted against the Russians to the same extent as in 1941.(B) Air Forces.17. The Germans are estimated to have had available for operations in the russo--German theatre of war at the beginning of last summer&apos;s campaign some5,000 aircraft, including reserves. The Russians are believed/ to have had acorresponding figure of some 7,500 aircraft.18. For the campaign now opening, it is estimated that the Germans have available some 3,500 aircraft, including reserves, against a corresponding figure for the Russian Air Force of from 4,000 to 4,500 aircraft.Comparative Equipment and Reserves.German Air Force.19 It is possible that the German Air Force will make use of a certainnumber of new ground attack aircraft on the Russian Front this year, although in the main not many new types will be employed. The quality of design, work-manship and maintenance is unlikely to deteriorate.20. Stored reserves have dropped heavily since June 1941. It is consideredthat the present output of operational types is in the neighbourhood of 1,200to 1,400 per month.Russian Air Force.21. Quality and design are rather below German standards, although not so much as might be expected. Maintenance is poor. The Russians do not keeplarge stored reserves but live from hand tp mouth. Production is believed to be some 2,000 operational types a month and should be ample to,meet requirements.&apos;
Comparative Training and Morale.German Air Force.22. Training is very thorough, but while there is nothing to suggest thatthere will be an actual shortage of pilots and crews during 1942. there is evidenceof a slight decline in the standards of training. The period at R.T.U. is beingcurtailed and pilots and crews are being put on operations before their operational training is completed. This is an indication that losses have at some timeexceeded the output of trained personnel and that any excess of output from the schools over the requirements of operational units has been used up.23.   Morale is still high but there is some evidence of a slight decline..        Russian Air Force.24. Training can be summarised as the survival of the fittest. Pilots of single-engined aircraft have been put on operations after 30 hours&apos; flying.Results are, however, better than might be expected in view of the inexperienceof most crews.   There is no question of shortage of manpower.25.   Morale is very high and is likely to survive even heavy reverses.A aerodromes.26. European Russia is well suited to the employment of air forces.Although it is possible to &quot; scorch &quot; aerodrome installations, it is impossible to deny the use of landing-grounds to an advancing enemy. Even in an advance onthe Caucasus itself, aerodrome limitations would not play a great part. On pastform the Russians are likely to be less efficient than the Germans in supplyingadvanced landing-grounds with the necessary ground organisation.(C) Economic.-   (a) Germany.27. Germany&apos;s general economic position has deteriorated since June 1941,but the effects of that deterioration on her power to wage war will be gradual.The following is a summary of the principal factors : A armaments. . - .28. The comb-out which has taken place in the armament industries mustaffect output during the coming summer. This decline might be as much as10 per cent. It need not be reflected in any reduction in deliveries of finishedarmaments to the forces, except in the case of aircraft, though stocks will decline-faster than they otherwise would.Transport.29. Since last summer a serious shortage of locomotives and M.T. hasappeared. Very severe losses of locomotives were suffered during the winter and, although it cannot be said that the fighting fronts will be directly weakened,this shortage is likely to cause considerable restrictions of transport facilitiesboth in Germany and in occupied territories. Repairs of locomotives are seriously handicapped by shortage of skilled labour, so that there is little prospect of Germany being able to increase her supply of them in face of an ever-deteriorating situation due to lack of. maintenance.30. Losses of M.T. were also very severe during the winter and thepresent- reduced production, which is less large than it might, have been owingto the turning over of existing M.T. manufacturing capacity to other work,is not likely to be sufficient to meet both current wastage and arrears. Tomeet this the Germans have available a pool of civilian lorries, but it isquestionable if this will provide lorries in sufficient numbers or of a suitablequality to meet all their needs. In any case, the shortage of lorries for civilian purposes will seriously handicap road transport both in Germany and the occupied territories.Oil.   , &apos;    &apos; * &apos;   &apos; ^ . -.. .. .,31. On the assumption that the German military machine will during the summer of 1942 consume oil at the same rate as during the summer and autumn of 1941, it will be necessary to cut civilian consumption in German Europe by[23913] &apos; c* 2
at least 25 per cent, as compared with a year ago, if  he very reduced stock position is to be maintained. This will be difficult, and will undoubtedly hamperessential transport not merely in the occupied territories, but also in Germanyitself. Combined with the shortage of civilian motor lorries and tyres and withthe shortage of locomotives, oil difficulties will undoubtedly help to retardindustry.   Local stoppages will occur.Other Raw Materials.32. Germany&apos;s ability to wage war this summer is hot likely to be directly affected by the shortage of any of the other raw materials at present in short supply. The effect of any shortages will be felt mainly in gradually decreasingoutput owing to the need of using less adequate substitutes and to the gradual reduction of stocks essential to the smooth working of manufacturing processes.Civilian Standards.33. The standard of living of the German civilian is dominated by thefood situation. The cuts in food rations made during April have reduced thestandard of nutrition of the normal consumer below the level necessary to maintainefficiency, although heavy and very heavy workers will receive just sufficient food.No further cuts in rations are probable before the 1st August, but in Octoberfurther cuts are probably inescapable. This knowledge can hardly be withheld from the population. Local food difficulties may be accentuated even during the summer months by transport troubles, although these will probably not seriously affect the situation until the winter.34. . In most other respects German civilian standards, though low, are not likely further to deteriorate during the summer. An important exception maybe housing, which will be affected in varying degrees by R.A.F. bombing.35. Although the standard of living of the German civilian will be lowenough during the summer to have some slight adverse effect upon productivity,there is no reason to suppose that deterioration on the civilian front will assumeserious proportions until the winter.(b) Russia.36. Provided a few important commodities now being supplied to russia by the Allies, e.g., rubber, tin, certain ferro-alloys and tool steel continue to he so supplied, it is estimated that the net loss of general industrial war potential toRussia since June 1941 does not exceed 10 per cent, to 15 per cent.A armaments.37. We lack data upon which to base an estimate of present output of complete armaments, but the following is an indication of the approximateposition in respect of certain major items : (a) Aircraft.2,000 operational types per month, i.e., not less than in June 1941.(b) Tanks.More than 2,000 per month proportion of medium and heavy to light types higher than previously. Total production higher than inJune 1941.(c) Guns, Artillery &quot;Ammunition, Small Arms and Small Arms Ammunition.Production figures not lower than in June 1941 of the campaign.(d) Mortars.Production is considerably higher than in June 1941 and is increasing.Manpower.38.   Present population of unoccupied Russia 130 to 140 million.Men of military age about 17 million.Industrial manpower about 65 to 70 million.This represents 75 to 80 per cent, of the pre-war total.
39. The loss of all the Caucasian oilfields would involve the loss of about75 per cent, of Russian oil production. On the other hand, the loss of territory-involved would result in a.decrease of about 50 per cent, in civilian oil require-ments. Accumulated stocks are thought to be considerable.If civilian consumption were curtailed and military consumption reducedby 25 per cent, below its present level, Russia&apos;s capacity to carry on the war wouldprobably not be limited by lack of oil for about a year after the loss of theCaucasus.  After that, lack of oil would probably reduce her war effort.Transportation.40. It is impossible to estimate statistically the adequacy of transport facilities. For heavy movement the Russians rely considerably on inland water-ways, especially the Volga. Their M.T. position is probably strained. , the capacity of the railways now remaining in Russian hands is limited, bearing inmind that only one main trunk lateral line, i.e., Moscow-Voronezh-Rostovremains, to provide for both military and industrial needs. It will probably bedifficult under the circumstances to avoid congestion at the junctions of thislateral with the main lines running East to the main industrial centres producingarmaments and war stores. Further East, transport requirements could be metto an extent not materially less than at the outbreak of the war.Food.41. There has been, as elsewhere in Europe, a general deterioration in thefood position.42. Bread is the staple diet and, outside Leningrad, the ration has apparently not been reduced (except to non-workers) since it was introduced last summer. The rations of other foods have been reduced by varying amounts, butaveraging about 50 per cent.; they are not always obtained in full.Russia still has just about enough food. The main difficulty is distribution.It is probable that the army, industrial workers and school children will be fedadequately, but other town dwellers will go short to a greater or less extent.(D) Summary.43. After nearly a year&apos;s fighting the-relative position of the antagonistsmay be summarised as follows : (a) The Russians have lost large territories and suffered heavy casualties.Their industrial war potential may have dropped by as. much as15 per cent. Their food situation has deteriorated, but it is not yetdangerous. They will be faced with transport and distributionaldifficulties. The threat of attack by Japan remains. On the otherhand, the Russians have confounded the prophets by withstanding theGerman attack for a year. The Germans themselves, and many others,expected the Russian Armies to have been overcome within a fewweeks of the initial assault. A vigorous nationalism has foundexpression in Russia. The Central Government is probably stronger than ever. The armed forces have acquired confidence and lost anyfear they may have had of German strength and methods of fighting.They have no doubt profited from their mistakes, but it would be too much to hope that their fundamental weaknesses in planning,organisation and administration have been entirely overcome.(&amp;) The Germans start the new campaign with.a formidable, well-trained and well-equipped force. The economic difficulties with which germany is faced are not such as to limit the power of offence of herarmies in Russia for some time to come. While Germany must be disappointed in the&apos;degree of the successes she has attained in Russiasince she attacked that- country, it must be remembered that she, has suffered no major defeat in the field. Nevertheless, the fact remainsthat the Germany facing Russia to-day is a less alarming antagonistthan she was a year ago. &apos;
39. The loss of all the Caucasian oilfields would involve the loss of about75 per cent, of Russian oil production. On the other hand, the loss of territory-involved would result in a.decrease of about 50 per cent, in civilian oil require-ments. Accumulated stocks are thought to be considerable.If civilian consumption were curtailed and military consumption reducedby 25 per cent, below its present level, Russia&apos;s capacity to carry on the war wouldprobably not be limited by lack of oil for about a year after the loss of theCaucasus.  After that, lack of oil would probably reduce her war effort.Transportation.40. It is impossible to estimate statistically the adequacy of transport facilities. For heavy movement the Russians rely considerably on inland water-ways, especially the Volga. Their M.T. position is probably strained. , the capacity of the railways now remaining in Russian hands is limited, bearing inmind that only one main trunk lateral line, i.e., Moscow-Voronezh-Rostovremains, to provide for both military and industrial needs. It will probably bedifficult under the circumstances to avoid congestion at the junctions of thislateral with the main lines running East to the main industrial centres producingarmaments and war stores. Further East, transport requirements could be metto an extent not materially less than at the outbreak of the war.Food.41. There has been, as elsewhere in Europe, a general deterioration in thefood position.42. Bread is the staple diet and, outside Leningrad, the ration has apparently not been reduced (except to non-workers) since it was introduced last summer. The rations of other foods have been reduced by varying amounts, butaveraging about 50 per cent.; they are not always obtained in full.Russia still has just about enough food. The main difficulty is distribution.It is probable that the army, industrial workers and school children will be fedadequately, but other town dwellers will go short to a greater or less extent.(D) Summary.43. After nearly a year&apos;s fighting the-relative position of the antagonistsmay be summarised as follows : (a) The Russians have lost large territories and suffered heavy casualties.Their industrial war potential may have dropped by as. much as15 per cent. Their food situation has deteriorated, but it is not yetdangerous. They will be faced with transport and distributionaldifficulties. The threat of attack by Japan remains. On the otherhand, the Russians have confounded the prophets by withstanding theGerman attack for a year. The Germans themselves, and many others,expected the Russian Armies to have been overcome within a fewweeks of the initial assault. A vigorous nationalism has foundexpression in Russia. The Central Government is probably stronger than ever. The armed forces have acquired confidence and lost anyfear they may have had of German strength and methods of fighting.They have no doubt profited from their mistakes, but it would be too much to hope that their fundamental weaknesses in planning,organisation and administration have been entirely overcome.(&amp;) The Germans start the new campaign with.a formidable, well-trained and well-equipped force. The economic difficulties with which germany is faced are not such as to limit the power of offence of herarmies in Russia for some time to come. While Germany must be disappointed in the&apos;degree of the successes she has attained in Russiasince she attacked that- country, it must be remembered that she, has suffered no major defeat in the field. Nevertheless, the fact remainsthat the Germany facing Russia to-day is a less alarming antagonistthan she was a year ago. *
at least 25 per cent, as compared with a year ago, if the very reduced stock position is to be maintained. This will be difficult, and will undoubtedly hamperessential transport not merely in the occupied territories, but also in Germanyitself. Combined with the shortage of civilian motor lorries and tyres and withthe shortage of locomotives, oil difficulties will undoubtedly help to retardindustry.   Local stoppages will occur.fOther Raw Materials.32. Germany&apos;s ability to wage war this summer is not likely to be directly-affected by the shortage of any of the other raw materials at present in short supply. The effect of any shortages will be felt mainly in gradually decreasingoutput owing to the need of using less adequate substitutes and to the gradual reduction of stocks essential to the smooth working of manufacturing processes.-Civilian Standards.33. The standard of living of the German civilian is dominated by thefood situation. The cuts in food rations made during April have reduced thestandard of nutrition of the normal consumer below the level necessary to maintainefficiency, although heavy and very heavy workers will receive just sufficient food.No further cuts in rations are probable before the 1st August, but in Octoberfurther cuts are probably inescapable. This knowledge can hardly be withheld from the population. Local food difficulties may be accentuated even during the summer months by transport troubles, although these will probably not seriously affect the situation until the winter.34. In most other respects German civilian standards, though low, are not likely further to deteriorate during the summer. An important exception maybe housing, which will be affected in varying degrees by R.A.F. bombing.35. Although the standard of living of the German civilian will be lowenough during the summer to have some slight adverse effect upon productivity,there is no reason to suppose that deterioration on the civilian front will assumeserious proportions until the winter.(b) Russia.36. Provided a few important commodities now being supplied to russia by the Allies, e.g., rubber, tin, certain ferro-alloys and tool steel continue to beso supplied, it is estimated that the net loss of general industrial war potential toRussia since June 1941 does not exceed 10 per cent, to 15 per cent.A armaments.37. We lack data upon which to base an estimate of present output of complete armaments, but the following is an indication of the approximateposition in respect of certain major items:  (a) Aircraft.2,000 operational types per month, i.e., not less than in June 1941.(b) Tanks.More than 2,000 per month proportion of medium and heavy to light types higher than previously. Total production higher than inJune 1941.(c) Guns, Artillery Ammunition, Small Arms and Small Arms Ammunition.Production figures not lower than in June 1941 of the campaign.(d) Mortars.Production is considerably higher than in June 1941 and is increasing.Manpower.38.   Present population of unoccupied Russia 130 to 140 million.Men of military age about 17 million.Industrial manpower about 65 to 70 million.This represents 75 to 80 per cent, of the pre-war total.
39. The loss of all the Caucasian oilfields would involve the loss of about75 per cent, of Russian oil production. On the other hand, the loss of territoryinvolved would result in a.decrease of about 50 per cent, in civilian oil require-ments. Accumulated stocks are thought to be considerable.If civilian consumption were curtailed and military consumption reducedby 25 per cent, below its present level, Russia&apos;s capacity to carry on the war wouldnrobably not be limited by lack of oil for about a year after the loss of theCaucasus.  After that, lack of oil would probably reduce her war effort.Transportation.40. It is impossible to estimate statistically the adequacy of transport facilities. For heavy movement the Russians rely considerably on inland water-ways, especially the Volga. Their M.T. position is probably strained. the capacity of the railways now remaining in Russian hands is limited, bearing inmind that only one main trunk lateral line, i.e., Moscow-Voronezh-Rostovremains, to provide for both military and industrial needs. It will probably bedifficult under the circumstances to avoid congestion at the junctions of thislateral with the main lines running East to the main industrial centres producingarmaments and war stores. Further East, transport requirements could be metto an extent not materially less than at the outbreak of the war.Food.41. There has been, as elsewhere in Europe, a general deterioration in thefood position.42. Bread is the staple diet and, outside Leningrad, the ration has apparently not been reduced (except to non-workers) since it was introduced last summer. The rations of other foods have been reduced by varying amounts, butaveraging about 50 per cent.; they are not always obtained in full.Russia still has just about enough food. The main difficulty is distribution.It is probable that the army, industrial workers and school children will be fedadequately, but other town dwellers will go short to a greater or less extent.(D) Summary.43. After nearly a year&apos;s fighting the-relative position of the antagonistsmay be summarised as follows : (a) The Russians have lost large territories and suffered heavy casualties.Their industrial war potential may have dropped by as. much as15 per cent. Their food situation has deteriorated, but it is not yetdangerous. They will be faced with transport and distributionaldifficulties. The threat of attack by Japan remains. On the otherhand, the Russians have confounded the prophets by withstanding theGerman attack for a year. The Germans themselves, and many others,expected the Russian Armies to have been overcome within a fewweeks of the initial assault. A vigorous nationalism has foundexpression in Russia. The Central Government is probably stronger than ever. The armed forces have acquired confidence and lost anyfear they may have had of German strength and methods of fighting.They have no doubt profited from their mistakes, but it would be too much to hope that their fundamental weaknesses in planning,organisation and administration have been entirely overcome.(b) The Germans start the new campaign with a formidable, well-trained and well-equipped force. The economic difficulties with which germany is faced are not such as to limit the power of offence of herarmies in Russia for some time to come. While Germany must be disappointed in the degree of the successes she has attained in Russiasince she attacked that country, it must be remembered that she has suffered no major defeat in the field. Nevertheless, the fact remainsthat the Germany facing Russia to-day is a less alarming antagonistthan she was a year ago.
(c) A year ago the German armies invading Russia came to that campaignfresh from an almost unbroken series of successes. The Germans stillhad a strong air force organised in depth. The United States werenot yet in the war and British and American war production had notswollen to the present substantial figures. It is doubtful whether thepossibility of Germany losing the war, or even failing to win it, had entered the minds of any appreciable number of Germans at home.To-day the case is altered. Though the forces facing Russiaremain formidable they are not, in the main, fresh forces. the commitments of the German air force stretch it to the limit. Themaintenance of the German forces remains possible economically, only at the expense of a progressive lowering of the standard of life inthe territories occupied by Germany and in Germany itself. the occupied territories are showing increased signs of unrest.(d) Japan hase come into the war on the same side as Germany.   This hashad the valuable effect of diverting from Europe forces that would otherwise be used against Germany and Italy, but there are as yetfew signs of any close strategic collaboration between Germany and her new ally, and German&apos;s access to the economic resources of theFar East is limited to the cargoes of a few blockade runners.Part II. Probable Course of Events.44. In considering the course the war in Russia is likely to take during the summer, while there are many factors to be taken into consideration, perhaps the best guide is the evidence provided by the war in Russia last year and thesituation examined in Part I of this Report.45. In 1941 the Germans initially used their armoured formations onthe same lines as they did in the Low Countries and France in 1940. By theautumn of 1941, however, the Russians profited by their battle experience andwere able to counter these deep threats by &apos;&apos; staying put &apos;&apos; in strongly defendedlocalities, cutting off the tanks from their supporting infantry and thensystematically hunting and destroying them.46. As a result of winter weather conditions and the improved anti-tankmethods employed by the Russians, which included defences in very greatdepth and mobile tank hunting units, the depth of penetration of Panzer unitswas reduced, and the Germans were forced to use infantry-cum-tank tactics the antithesis of their original technique. Russian armies, when cut off fromtheir rear, continued to fight on, and even vast losses did not break the determination of the Russian High Command nor prevent resistance from being organised as the withdrawal proceeded.47. A feature of the fighting in Russia has been the work of the Partisans.Parties of these guerillas would come through the German lines to the red army commanders for orders, and then return by night to carry out their tasks of destruction and sabotage. There is no doubt that the German difficultiesof supply, administration and protection of the long lines of communicationshave been greatly aggravated by these guerilla tactics.The Tactical Situation To-day (see Map).48. Leningrad is still closely invested and the Germans are favourablyplaced for an assault on the city.49. On the Central Front, there has been infiltration on both sides and each side holds posts well behind the line of the other&apos;s forward defendedlocalities. Preliminary operations would probably be required in order to clearthese up before major operations on this front could be staged.50. The Crimea has been cleared of Russian forces, except in thebeleaguered town of Sevastopol. This removes the threat to the right flank of anv German drive in the South.51. In the recent operations to the south of Kharkov the Germans seemto have largely succeeded in flattening out the pronounced Russian salientwhich extended south-Avestwards towards Dnepropetrovsk. The German counter-attacks from the south towards Isyiim now appear to be held.
52. The Russians have undoubtedly lost large numbers of men and muchmaterial in these operations. Nevertheless, by their fierce offensive towardsKharkov the Russians have also inflicted heavy losses, and have in all these operations forced the Germans to commit to battle formations which theywould have liked to reserve for use at a time of their own choosing, namely,in the projected summer offensive in the South.53. The tactical situation probably favours the Germans who are well placed for starting offensive operations according to the plan which we believethey will adopt, but which may now have been delayed.German Intentions.54. The evidence leads us to believe that the German main thrust willbe made in the South, and that holding attacks will be made on the rest ofthe front, but that there might also be an attempt to capture Leningrad.55. The main offensive will probably be made in the Sector from Kursk toTaganrog, and the centre of gravity will be in the South of this sector, where theproportion of motorised and armoured divisions will be highest.56. The objective of the attack in the South is likely to be, initially,Stalingrad and the line of the River Don north-westwards.Topography.57. The two main rivers in the South are the Donets and the Don. Therivers Donets and Don are obstacles to the German advance, but not such as of themselves to delay it to a serious extent if the resistance &quot;of the Russian armiesweakened.58. South of the line Kursk-Voronezh-Saratov the country is almost tree-less, except in the river valleys, and is ideal for A.F.V.&apos;s when the ground is dry.59. In the South, therefore, there is little to hamper the German advancetopographically. The terrain favours the attackers. In the central and northernsectors the country is considerably more wooded and favourable for defence, sothat the Russians should be able, except perhaps in Leningrad, to counter the limited German attacks which we expect in these sectors.Communications.60. Without considerably more information than we possess about theRussian dispositions, the effect of communications on the. Russian resistancecannot be gauged. A strategic reserve for each front, probably held underG.H.Q. control, is echeloned close in rear of each front. There is no centralstrategic reserve.61. Lack of rail communications and roads is likely to hamper the mobility of the Russians and the move of large reserves southwards would be aslow process. No quick concentration of Russian reserves for a counter-offensiveis feasible, and successful resistance will initially have to depend on local reserves and their correct placing.Distances.62. The shortest distance for the Germans to Stalingrad is from the Stalinofront, and is approximately 300 miles. From the Kursk area via Voronezh and north-east of the River Don is some 400 miles.63. Though we cannot estimate the time required to concentrate the Russianreserves, it is possible that the superior mobility of the Germans will enable themto form a good defensive flank to the North-East and reach Stalingrad before theRussians can effectively intervene.64. The initial advantage lies with the Germans. Their dispositions are atleast as favourable for attack as those of the Russians for defence; the groundfavours them; they possess a better fighting machine, better equipment, training and mobility. On the other hand, the Russian determination and staying-powermay be the greater and the Russians are likely to be numerically superior.
Chemical Warfare.65. The Germans have made preparations for gas warfare both in theArmy and on the Home Front. Although it is known that the Russians as a nation are &quot;gas conscious,&quot; recent evidence indicates that the Russian armed forces may not be fully equipped for chemical warfare. Should the Germansintend to use gas warfare, of which there are certain indications, the Russianswill find themselves initially at a disadvantage. With its initial use therefore,the Germans might achieve that surprise over tactical methods which has to-daybeen offset by the batttle experience of the Red Army.66. It is probable that the initial German attack will succeed. How far theGermans will be able to develop this attack must depend on :  (a) The air situation.   The gaining of local air superiority by either sidemight quite well be a deciding factor in the battle.(b) The initial Russian dispositions.   It is not too much to hope that these may be such as to check the German advance when it has lost itsmomentum.(c) The power of the Russians to stage a counter-offensive.   The experienceof 1941 should have gone a long way to improving the strategical ideas of the Russian General Staff.(d) The extent to which the Germans may be compelled to divert forces tomeet a threat of an Anglo-American attack in the West.67. The Russians may, therefore, initially suffer reverses, but they shouldbe able to diminish the momentum of the German advance and bring the advance to a standstill on a line which might be the Tula-Vorenezh-Kamensk railway(south of Voronezh) thence the River Donetz to Rostov.68. This line might be reached by the beginning of August 1942, or possibly even earlier if the Germans are able to exploit the recent operations in theIzyurn-Barvenkovo area south of Kharkov.69. We think it unlikely, however, that by August a decisive success by either side will have been achieved. Between August and October, however,events may move to a climax. Both sides will have suffered severe casualties. TheGerman Air Force may be reduced from a total operational strength of 5,800aircraft on all fronts to some 4,500 aircraft, a force which will have to bemaintained practically on a &quot; factory to unit basis.&quot; The German high command may at about this time be faced with the problem of whether to throwin their last reserves even to the extent of dangerously denuding occupied countries in the hope of bringing about a complete Russian defeat before thewinter or to conserve their resources to meet the growing Anglo-American threatin the West. The margin between success or failure may be very narrow, and itmay be touch and go which of the two adversaries collapses first.70 If the Germans realise that they cannot avoid another winter campaign in Russia and are faced with the threat of Anglo-American invasion in theWest, they may collapse with unexpected rapidity as they did in 1918.71. On the other hand, we cannot rule out the possibility of Russiacollapsing. Should she do so, the Germans would, during the winter, after making provision for the garrisoning of Russia and other occupied territories,be able to build up to meet a threatened Anglo-American invasion of the Continentnext Spring a force of some 2,500 aircraft and a field army on the 1st April, 1943,of some 30-50 divisions, including 5-10 armoured and 5-10 motorised, rising to60-80 divisions, including 20 armoured and 20 motorised, by the 1st June, 1943.Subject to conditions then prevailing, a part of this force could be employed bythe Germans for offensive operations in the Middle East.(Signed) V. CAVENDISH-BENTINCK.J. H. GODFREY.C. E. H. MEDHURST.J. M. KIRKMAN (for D.M.I.).C. G. VTCKERS.Great George Street, S.W. 1,June 1, 1942.
Chemical Warfare.65. The Germans have made preparations for gas warfare both in theArmy and on the Home Front. Although it is known that the Russians as a nation are &quot; gas conscious,&quot; recent evidence indicates that the Russian armed forces may not be fully equipped for chemical warfare. Should the Germansintend to use gas warfare, of which there are certain indications, the Russianswill find themselves initially at a disadvantage. With its initial use therefore,the Germans might achieve that surprise over tactical methods which has to-daybeen offset by the batttle experience of the Red Army.66. It is probable that the initial German attack will succeed. How far theGermans will be able to develop this attack must depend on :  (a) The air situation.   The gaining of local air superiority by either sidemight quite well be a deciding factor in the battle.(b) The initial Russian dispositions.   It is not too much to hope that these may be such as to check the German advance when it has lost itsmomentum.(c) The power of the Russians to stage a counter-offensive.   The experienceof 1941 should have gone a long way to improving the strategical ideas of the Russian General Staff.(d) The extent to which the Germans may be compelled to divert forces tomeet a threat of an Anglo-American attack in the West.67. The Russians may, therefore, initially suffer reverses, but they shouldbe able to diminish the momentum of the German advance and bring the advance to a standstill on a line which might be the Tula-Vorenezh-Kamensk railway(south of Voronezh) thence the River Donetz to Rostov.68. This line might be reached by the beginning of August 1942, or possibly even earlier if the Germans are able to exploit the recent operations in theIzyum-Barvenkovo area south of Kharkov.69. We think it unlikely, however, that by August a decisive success by either side will have been achieved. Between August and October, however,events may move to a climax. Both sides will have suffered severe casualties. TheGerman Air Force may be reduced from a total operational strength of 5,800aircraft on all fronts to some 4,500 aircraft, a force which will have to bemaintained practically on a &quot; factory to unit basis.&quot; The German high command may at about this time be faced with the problem of whether to throwin their last reserves even to the extent of dangerously denuding occupied countries in the hope of bringing about a complete Russian defeat before thewinter or to conserve their resources to meet the growing Anglo-American threatin the West. The margin between success or failure may be very narrow, and itmay be touch and go which of the two adversaries collapses first.70 If the Germans realise that they cannot avoid another winter campaign in Russia and are faced with the threat of Anglo-American invasion in theWest, they may collapse with unexpected rapidity as they did in 1918.71. On the other hand, we cannot rule out the possibility of Russiacollapsing. Should she do so, the Germans would, during the winter, after making provision for the garrisoning of Russia and other occupied territories,be able to build up to meet a threatened Anglo-American invasion of the Continentnext Spring a force of some 2,500 aircraft and a field army on the 1st April, 1943,of some 30-50 divisions, including 5-10 armoured and 5-10 motorised, rising to60-80 divisions, including 20 armoured and 20 motorised, by the 1st June, 1943.Subject to conditions then prevailing, a part of this force could be employed bythe Germans for offensive operations in the Middle East.(Signed) V. CAVENDISH-BENTINCK.J. H. GODFREY.C. E. H. MEDHURST.J. M. KIRKMAN (for D.M.I.).C. G. VICKERS.Great George Street, S.W. 1,June 1, 1942.








</content>
</cab>
