<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/66/0 images: 26-28</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1954SECRETC. (54) 5916th February, 1954SAUDI ARABIAN FRONTIER dispute memorandum by the Minister of state the Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet in November, .1952 (C. (52) 383)of his reasons for proposing to the Saudi Government that the frontier dispute should be put to arbitration. In April, 1953 the Saudi Government accepted thisproposal in principle.2. Since then, our problem has been to reach agreement with the Saudisupon pre-conditions for impartial arbitration. The Saudi official Turki binAtaishan has throughout been in Buraimi oasis with his followers, cordoned off by Trucial Oman Levies; the Saudis were unwilling to withdraw him; and, until he went, we certainly could not agree to arbitrate. Meanwhile, as a counter toTurki, we had established five posts of the Trucial Oman Levies in key placesnear the putative frontier to the west of Buraimi.3. After much discussion with the Saudi Ambassador here, who at themoment is back in Saudi Arabia, the Foreign Secretary is hopeful that we maybe able to settle acceptable terms. He has therefore instructed Her Majesty&apos;ambassador at Jedda to put the following proposition to the Saudi Ambassador:&apos; (a) That the Arbitral Tribunal should be asked to decide:(i) The common Saudi/Abu Dhabi frontier; and(ii) Sovereignty over the Buraimi zone (i.e., a circle of 20 kilometresround Buraimi village).(b) That we should be ready to agree:(i) To the withdrawal of Turki and his men from Buraimi oasis toundisputed territory in Saudi Arabia, and of the Trucial OmanLevies to undisputed territory on the Trucial Coast; and to thesubstitution in the oasis of a small police group of up to fifteenmen on each side.(ii) To the withdrawal to undisputed territory of our five Levy postsat present in the other disputed areas in the West, on condition that no armed men or administrative personnel shall be intro-duced into or maintained in the disputed areas by the SaudiGovernment.(c) That (a) and (b) are conditional on the maintenance of the oil operations of the Iraq Petroleum Company (I.P.C.) and the Anglo-Iranian oil company (A.I.O.C.) in the disputed areas.4. The Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Ruler of Abu Dhabi have bothagreed that the dispute should be taken to arbitration. They would, no doubt,prefer to see us turn Turki out of Buraimi and to hold by force the frontier whichwe think our proteges should have. That solution however might involve wide-spread hostilities with the Saudis; and the proposition that the Foreign secretary has put forward, if accepted, at least removes Turki from Buraimi by peaceful means.Copy No.   6-cabinet office record copy cabinet
secret copy No.   68C. (54) 5916th February, 1954CABINET OFFICERECCRD COPYCABINETSAUDI ARABIAN FRONTIER dispute memorandum by the Minister of state the Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet in November, .1952 (C. (52) 383)of his reasons for proposing to the Saudi Government that the frontier dispute should be put to arbitration. In April, 1953 the Saudi Government accepted thisproposal in principle.2. Since then, our problem has been to reach agreement with the Saudisupon pre-conditions for impartial arbitration. The Saudi official Turki binAtaishan has throughout been in Buraimi oasis with his followers, cordoned off by Trucial Oman Levies; the Saudis were unwilling to withdraw him; and, until he went, we certainly could not agree to arbitrate. Meanwhile, as a counter toTurki, we had established five posts of the Trucial Oman Levies in key placesnear the putative frontier to the west of Buraimi.3. After much discussion with the Saudi Ambassador here, who at themoment is back in Saudi Arabia, the Foreign Secretary is hopeful that we maybe able to settle acceptable terms. He has therefore instructed Her Majesty&apos;ambassador at Jedda to put the following proposition to the Saudi Ambassador:  (a) That the Arbitral Tribunal should be asked to decide:(i) The common Saudi/Abu Dhabi frontier; and(ii) Sovereignty over the Buraimi zone ii.e., a circle of 20 kilometresround Buraimi village).(b) That we should be ready to agree:(i) To the withdrawal of Turki and his men from Buraimi oasis toundisputed territory in Saudi Arabia, and of the Trucial OmanLevies to undisputed territory on the Trucial Coast; and to thesubstitution in the oasis of a small police group of up to fifteenmen on each side.(ii) To the withdrawal to undisputed territory of our five Levy postsat present in the other disputed areas in the West, on condition that no armed men or administrative personnel shall be intro-duced into or maintained in the disputed areas by the SaudiGovernment.(c) That (a) and (b) are conditional on the maintenance of the oil operations of the Iraq Petroleum Company (I.P.C.) and the Anglo-Iranian oil company (A.I.O.C.) in the disputed areas.4. The Sultan of Muscat and Oman and the Ruler of Abu Dhabi have bothagreed that the dispute should be taken to arbitration. They would, no doubt,prefer to see us turn Turki out of Buraimi and to hold by force the frontier whichwe think our proteges should have. That solution however might involve wide-spread hostilities with the Saudis; and the proposition that the Foreign secretary has put forward, if accepted, at least removes Turki from Buraimi by peaceful means.Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1954
5. As regards the oil interests in this affair (paragraph 3 (c) above), the I.P.C.,to whose land concession the marine concession of the A.I.O.C. is contiguous,acquired its present interests from the Ruler of Abu Dhabi before the Saudisadvanced their 1949 claim and brought the area into dispute. Much time and money have already been spent on oil prospecting there, and it is unreasonableof the Saudis to ask that those operations should now stop.6. The Saudi Government have hinted from time to time that they wouldbe ready to give a concession to those Companies in any disputed area which, asa result of the arbitration, might pass to Saudi sovereignty. The fact is, however,that the present concession of the Arabian-American Oil Company (Aramco) fromSaudi Arabia would automatically extend to any territory which Saudi Arabiamay require. If therefore the Saudi Governments offer of a concession were tobe accepted, we should first require to know that Aramco was agreeable: it wouldbe unwise for us to appear to wish to impair Aramco&apos;s rights.7. The Foreign Secretary has accordingly asked Her Majesty&apos;s ambassador at Jedda to make this plain to the Saudis. It is for them to speak first with Aramco.If thereafter the Saudi Government and Aramco were agreeable, then the two british Companies would be interested in negotiating concessionary rights in anydisputed area which might pass to Saudi sovereignty. There would be difficultiesin the way, since an Aramco type of concession might well not be appropriate fora British oil company or for an international company with mixed shareholding(such as the I.P.C.); but exactly the same financial results could be obtained bya concession on another basis.8. Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at Washington has been instructed to explainour proposition to the United States Government, and we ourselves have explainedit to the United States Embassy here. We want no misunderstanding with the americans about oil interests, particularly in view of the present Persian oilnegotiations, and our proposition to the Saudis therefore expressly preservesAramco&apos;s existing rights. There has been close consultation throughout with our oil companies, who say that they are well satisfied with the proposition that hasbeen made.S. L.Foreign Office, S.W. 1,15th February, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
