<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/66/0 images: 57-66</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1954CONFIDENTIALCopy No.C. (54) 6923rd February, 1954CABINET office record COPYCABINETOFFICERS&apos; RETIRED pay memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer have already suggested to my colleagues that the decision to make consider-able increases in Service pay makes it more difficult to continue to resist the claim for improvement of the retired pay of certain Service officers. (C.C. (54)8th Conclusions, Minute 4.)2. It is possible that the exchanges which took place in Parliament before christmas both in the Commons and in the Lords have, together with the publiccomment which they provoked, to some extent helped to make some concessionpossible with a smaller risk of incurring all the other liabilities mentioned in myearlier papers. If we are to make a concession I am sure that it should be thatwhich I outlined in C. (53) 206 as the least dangerous scheme. It is what is knownas &quot; the 10 per cent, scheme.&quot;3. Public attention has now been focussed sharply on the special grievanceof the 1935 consolidation, and there is no doubt that very many people, besides the officers themselves, genuinely believe that in some way or other these officers have been &quot; done down,&quot; that it would only be fair to redress their grievance andthat to do so need not produce a landslide. In other words, an atmosphere hasbeen built up in which it might just be possible to do what previously seemed tome impossible: that is, successfully to isolate from all other pension demands thecase of those who were affected by the 1935 consolidation decision. If the positionof these pensioners can be distinguished from that of all others, and if it is generally accepted that this decision is sound, it might be possible to proceed with the 10 percent, scheme, restricting the benefits exclusively to those retired officers and civilservants who retired before 1946. The fact that their situation is unique has alreadybeen recognised in the Pensions Increase measures of 1944 and 1947, and the argument would be that, having reconsidered what was then done partially to restore the &quot; cuts &quot; of 1935, the Government have now concluded that it wouldbe right to complete what was started in 1944 and 1947 and in future to treatall these pensioners alike, irrespective of the size of their pension.4. If, and only if, it were the general view of my colleagues that this would now be a reasonable and tenable solution, I should be prepared to drop my earlierobjections.5. But I must warn my colleagues not only that we shall still run some riskof highly expensive repercussions, but that, we shall get little gratitude for this concession and shall be pressed to improve on it, in particular in two respects:  (a) We shall be pressed to include in it Local Government officials, police,teachers, &amp;c. In paragraph 9 of C. (53) 206 I said that it would bedifficult in practice to exclude these pensioners, though in logic theirexclusion would be perfectly defensible. We must in my view stick tothe logic of the situation, building, on the argument of the 1935 con-solidation, and refusing to budge from it.45729
Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,22nd February, 1954.(b) My scheme restores the 1919 rates of retired pay for Service officers; itdoes not return to the 1919 system which would mean reinstating thesliding scale and giving a 20 per cent, increase over 1919 rates. Someof our critics are in fact demanding nothing short of this. There canin fact be no question of it. It would cost some millions directly andprobably many more indirectly. It would give to a retired general notsome  100 extra but some  400 extra. It would raise many pensionsawarded in the past above the 1950 rates. We must utterly reject it,basing ourselves on the argument that, while we recognise that a casehas been made out for restoring cuts, we are in no way prepared to restore the principle of a sliding scale.6. A decision to go ahead with this scheme will mean for the officers newprerogative instruments, and for the civil servants legislation amending the relevantSections of the 1944 and 1947 Pensions Increase Acts. The prerogative instrumentsshould give us no trouble. The legislation will, I am advised, be a simple mattertechnically (probably confined to one short clause) and I would urge most strongly that if we decide to do this we should get the legislation through with the utmostspeed and allow as little time as possible for the development of the pressuresthat we may; expect.7. I would also suggest that we should be well advised to announce our decision in a way which will fully set out our reasons for it, and which, in particular,will give the historical background in some detail. Only thus, I feel sure, can we hope to be in a position to parry ill-informed criticism on a topic of such technical and. historical complexity. Experience has shown that on this subject there is no limit to the number of statements contrary to the true facts which can be made,and made with apparent good faith.8. I understand that a very good effect was obtained by the full statement made in the House of Lords before the Recess. With this in mind I have arranged for the drafting of a White Paper which might be issued, and I attach a copy ofthis. It is, I am afraid, tough reading; but this is a tough subject and there is noeasy short-cut to understanding it. The Conclusion (paragraphs 29 following) is themost important part.R. A. B.
introduction. Much discussion has taken place in recent months in regard to thesuggestion that the retired pay of officers of the three fighting services who retired under the 1919 Code should be increased beyond the levels allowed by successive pensions increase measures. In particular there has &quot;been ademand for a restoration to all such officers of what is commonly known as&quot; the 9\ per cent, cut.&quot; Much of the discussion which has taken place hasshown widespread misunderstanding about many of the facts as well as thepolicy behind this situation. The Government therefore think it right that theyshould set out in some detail the history and underlying reasons for the 9  percent, cut; and should also set out their policy, with the considerations whichlead to it, on the general question of the improvement of the pensions of Crown pensioners to compensate for rises in the cost of living occuring afterretirement.  The main purpose of this Paper is to do this.2. It is not possible fully to do so without some explanation of the 1935consolidation, from which the &quot; 9\ per cent.&quot; cut stems, and the events leading to it. This in turn calls for a short description of the general principles ofthe systems both of Officers&apos; retired pay and of Civil Service pensions whichwere then in force.The SystemsOfficers&apos; Retired Pay3. In the three Services the rules and regulations by which an officerqualifies for retired pay are known as the retired pay code. This code, whichis distinct from the pay code, may be changed from time to time, and sincethe 1914-18 war there have been four distinct phases: soon after that warthe then existing arrangements were replaced by the 1919 code, with whichthis Paper is mainly concerned; this in turn was revised in 1938; there wasa substantial revision in 1945; and another revision in 1950.4. When the code is changed, and normally when the rates of pensionawarded within the framework of the code are changed (which may happenindependently of a change of code), the changes are not applied to officers who have already retired.5. The 1919 Code. This code provided for retired pay to be calculated on rank or age and length of service, with maximum rates for each rank. it also provided, and in this it was unique among retired pay codes, that thehigh rates then introduced should be regarded as attributable to the then high cost of living and that they should therefore be subject to revision, eitherupwards or downwards, on account of variation in the cost of living, to an extent not exceeding 20 per cent. It provided that the first review of ratescould take place in 1924 and that subsequent revisions might be made at three yearly intervals. The revisions were to apply to retired pay already in issue under the code as well as to that of officers retiring after the revision.6. A copy of that part of the Instruments which referred to the variation of rates with the cost of living is attached as Appendix I.7. The Instruments did not lay down in detail how the variations shouldbe effected. A formula had therefore to be sought for this purpose. Theeffect of the formula devised is set out in Appendix II. The practical result was that, for all ranks of officer equally, the top 20 per cent, of the 1919 rateof pension was to quote the Air Ministry order &quot; detachable and liable tovariation.&quot; It will be seen that the cost-of-living index had to fall right backto the 1914 level to reduce the pension by the full 20 per cent. And in factsuch a reduction would still have left the pension significantly above the 1914rate.Civil Service Pensions8. Civil Service superannuation benefits have (at all times material to thisquestion) been calculated by reference to length of service and to pay. Upto 1909, Civil Service pensions were calculated at l/60th of retiring pay foreach year of service with a maximum of 40/60ths. Since 1909 Civil Servicesuperannuation benefits have been in two parts: a pension of 1 / 80th of salaryfor each year of service subject normally to a maximum of 40/80ths and a lump sum: up to 1940 the lump sum was l/30th of salary for each year ofservice subject to a maximum of 45/30ths; in 1940 it became 3/80ths for eachyear of service subject normally to a maximum of 120/80ths. Up to 1940,pensions and lump sum were normally calculated on pay at the date of retire-ment: but since 1940 the calculation has been related to the average pay forthe three years immediately before retirement.9. No pension is paid for less than 10 years&apos; service, nor (subject tominor exceptions) until the minimum retiring age of 60 is reached.10. Thus whereas Forces Officers&apos; retired pay is awarded under a set ofrules which are separate and distinct from those regulating his pay, CivilService pensions are calculated by direct reference to salary in the period before retirement.   The result is that variations in Civil Service pensions45729B
have occurred as a direct and automatic consequence of variations in pay.It is therefore necessary to describe the Civil Service pay system at the relevant time.11. The Civil Service Bonus System. In the period following the1914-1918 War Civil Service pay was subject to a complex bonus systemdesigned to adjust pay according to changes in the cost of living. During andinmmediately after the war a series of ad hoc awards of cost-of-living bonuswere made. But in 1920, when the cost-of-living figure as measured by the retail price index was 130 per cent, above 1914, a more systematic schemewas introduced. This provided for bonus to be revised periodically on thebasis of the cost-of-living figures for the previous period, and to be added to basic salaries (i.e:, in principle 1914 salaries) as follows:  (a) on salaries up to  91 5s. a year, and on the first  91 5s. a year of larger salaries an increase directly proportionate to the increaseborne by the current cost-of-living figure over the 1914 figure (eg:,the first  50 of salary was increased to  102 10s. by a bonus of 52 10s. when the cost-of-living index was 105 above 1914);(b) on the element of salary between  91 5s. and  200 a year 60/130thsof the increase directly proportionate to that of the current cost-of-living figure as compared with that of 1914;(c) on the element of salary from  200 to  1,000 a year-45/130ths ofthe increase directly proportionate to that of the current cost-of-livingfigure as compared with that of 1914.12. It was laid down that the bonus arrangement applicable in (c) aboveof 45/130ths should apply equally to the element of salary above  1,000 ayear subject, however, to an overriding maximum of  750 a year of bonus.In the case of certain posts (in effect, Permanent Secretaries and DeputySecretaries of major Departments, whose basic salaries had recently been revised) the overriding maximum was limited to  500 a year.13. This system, more particularly as applied to the higher grades ofthe Civil Service, encountered a great deal of adverse criticism in subsequentmonths. This was the period of the Geddes Committee&apos;s Report, a period when great reductions in Government expenditure were being sought, afterthe honeymoon period immediately following the end of the war. In theresult, the Government announced on 26th July, 1921, the introduction of a&quot; supercut&quot; which was brought into effect by a Treasury Circular issued on23rd August, 1921. By this supercut the scale of bonus on salaries between 500 and  2,000 was reduced by increasing amounts as salaries rose and above  2,000 a year it was abolished altogether.14. The supercut was the subject of repeated protests on behalf of thestaff concerned during subsequent years. But it remained in force up to and including the final consolidation of the cost-of-living bonus, in 1935.15. These events inevitably affected Civil Service pensions, which, it hasbeen explained, are directly related to pay.16. At first, in contradistinction to the 1919 code for retired ForcesOfficers, there was no provision for the modification of pension, once awarded,in accordance with changes in the cost of living, though it was provided that only 75 per cent, of the bonus should count as pay in the calculation ofpension.17. The fixity of pension rates based on high rates of bonus was, however,strongly criticised in Parliament in 1922 when the cost of living was fallingrapidly and in February 1922 the then Financial Secretary to the Treasuryundertook to provide for future pensions to be subject to periodic reassessmentin relation to the cost of living as was the retired pay of Forces Officers.The new system was brought into effect immediately.18. From 21st February, 1922 onwards, pension awards were made intwo parts, computed on the basic salary (i.e., the salary at 1914 levels) andthe bonus respectively. The portion of pension which depended on bonus wasthereafter computed on the full 100 per cent, of the bonus and not, as hitherto,on 75 per cent., but was to be adjusted quarterly on the basis of any reductionin the cost-of-living figure for the preceding quarter.19. Such were the essential points of the systems then in force for dealingwith officers&apos; retired pay and Civil Service pensions. They differed in detail,necessarily, because the two codes were designed to meet different circum-stances. But they had this in common, namely, that under each a proportionof the pension was subject to variation in accordance with the cost of living.Working of the Systems up to 193520. The 1919 rates of Officers&apos; retired pay were fixed when the cost-of-living index stood at 107-5 per cent, above 1914. By July, 1924, when thefirst review was made, the index had fallen to 69-4 per cent, above 1914.Under the formula set out in Appendix II a reduction of about 7 per cent,in rates of retired pay would have been appropriate.   The reduction actually
made, however, was one of per cent. only. By 1927 when the next review was due the cost-of-living figure was 63 per cent, and the rate of reduction was increased to 6 per cent. In 1930 when the formula would if fully appliedhave produced a cut of 8 per cent., that actually made was one of 7 per cent.In July, 1931, there was a special review, the cost of living having fallen to45 per cent, above 1914: a deduction of 11^ per cent, could have been made,but that actually made was one of 8 per cent.21. Meanwhile, under the parallel system in the Civil Service bonus wasbeing reduced every six months or so, and pensions awarded from 21stFebruary, 1922, adjusted accordingly. By the summer of 1928 bonus was calculated on the basis of a cost-of-living figure which had fallen to 70 percent, above 1914.   It had been adjusted no less than sixteen times.22. These repeated adjustments nearly all downwards were very muchdisliked, and there was strong pressure for a modification of the system. Inthe event the Government decided on two occasions to mitigate its incidence:in September, 1929, the bonus was maintained at a level appropriate to a cost-of-living figure of 70 instead of to the 65 actually ruling at the time; andthe reduction for September, 1930, to February, 1931, was similarly mitigatedby adopting a basis of 65 instead of 60.23. Then in the autumn of 1931 came the financial crisis. This resultedin a strict application of the sliding scale formula both for retired officers andfor civil servants: civil service bonus was reduced to relate to the actual cost-of-living figure; and the rate of reduction for Officers&apos; retired pay was increased from 8 per cent, to 11 per cent.; further, a Royal Warrant of 1931shortened the periods between revision.24. Meanwhile the Royal Commission on the Civil Service had reported,and in their Report (Cmd. 3909) had recommended against further continuanceof the system of relating Civil Service pay to a cost-of-Jiving index. Theyobserved that.&quot; in the period immediately after the war some method such asthat embodied in the cost-of-living agreement was no doubt opportune. Itwas never intended that the scheme embodied in that agreement should becontinued indefinitely and we regard its further continuance as open to objection.&quot;25. This set in train the movement which led eventually to the abolitionof the cost-of-living bonus in the Civil Service and to the comparable con-solidation of the pay and retired pay of Forces Officers.Stabilisation26. It was in 1932 that the Government of the day took the decision toabandon the system under which the pay of Forces Officers and civil servants,and the pensions of those retiring under the 1919 and 1922 arrangements,respectively, varied with the cost of living. They accepted the recommenda-tion of the Royal Commission in respect of civil servants and a similarrecommendation made by the May Committee (Cmd. 3920) in respect of forces Officers. They decided thus because they considered that experiencesince the 1914-1918 war fully demonstrated the fundamental unsoundnessof a system under which the remuneration of Crown servants alone varieddirectly with the cost of living as measured by the index of retail prices.27. The decision was a decision of principle, and in this connexion itshould be noted that the May Committee expressly emphasised that they regarded the reductions they proposed (on pay and pensions), not as sacrificesnecessitated by national financial stringency, but as readjustments necessaryto establish fair relativities over the field of Government and local authorityservants,and wage earners generally.28. Final consolidation of pay and pensions did not, however, followat once on the Governments decision. In the face of the uncertain economicoutlook it was thought unwise to adopt forthwith a course which might well prove expensive. What actually happened next emerges clearly from thefollowing extract from Army Council Instructions accompanying a royal warrant of 1932 which declared that rates of Forces retired pay should notagain be revised until 31st March, 1934:  &quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government have had the whole question of the remuneration of the services of the Crown under review and have decidedthat emoluments should now cease to vary automatically with changes. in the index figure, but shall be consolidated. They have further decidedthat, subject always to the overriding consideration of the nationalfinancial position, final consolidation shall be deferred until 1st April,1934, and that in the meantime the rates shall be stabilised at the currentreduction from standard rates, viz., 11 per cent., which corresponds toa cost of living figure of about 49, subject to the proviso in the following paragraph.&quot; If during the above period of stabilisation the index figure remainsbelow 35 or above 60 for six consecutive months, the resultant situation will be reviewed in the light of all relevant considerations including thecost of living.&quot;45729
29. Consolidation was not, however, effected in April 1934. The ratesof retired pay then in issue were, however, improved from 1st July, 1934,the cut of 11 per cent, being reduced to 10 per cent. The cost of living hadnot been rising, and this increase was regarded as a partial restoration of economies made in 1931, when, for the first time, the sliding scale had beenfully applied. In August 1934, a Warrant announced that consolidationwould be at 9-J- per cent, below the 1919 rate; but as this meant an increasein rates, it was deferred &quot; until the state of the national finances permit.&quot;30. Final consolidation took place on 1st July, 1955 at a level 9\ percent, below the 1919 rate. This level was related, under the formulapreviously in use, to a cost-of-living figure 55 per cent, above 1914. In fact,however, the latest available cost-of-living figure stood at only 40 per cent,above 1914, which on the same basis would have justified a rate 12  percent, below the 1919 rate.31. Meanwhile, over the same period, parallel decisions were appliedto civil servants, consolidation for them also being based on a cost-of-livingfigure of 55 and not on the current figure of 40.32. It is sometimes said that the Government operated the cost-of-livingsystem only for so long as the cost of living was going down, and brought the system to an end as soon as it could be seen that it was going to rise.As has already been explained, the decision to stabilise and consolidaterates was first announced in 1932, when the cost-of-living index was stillfalling. The cost of living did not exceed the figure of 55, on which the stabilisation was ultimately based, until 1938. The mean cost-of-livingfigures for the years from 1931 till 1939 were as follows:  1931.........	.........      47i1932 ......	......      441933 .........	.........      401934 .........	...      ...      ...      411935 .........	...      ...      ...      431936 .........	...      ...      ...      471937 ...      ......	.........      541938 .........	.........      561939 .........	5833. The measures just described brought to an end the exceptional period during which Officers&apos; retired pay and civil servants&apos; pensions were variedwith the cost-of-living index. They constituted a return to the previous policy which had all along been applied continuously to those who retired before1919-under which a pension, once awarded, normally remains unaltered.34. It is hardly possible at this date to be dogmatic about the reactions of those concerned at the time to these measures. But there is little doubtthat the system as it had operated for some ten years or so was not popular,either in the civil service or in the fighting services; that interim stabilisationin 1932, i.e., the virtual suspension of the system, was welcomed; and thatconsolidation, i.e., the abandonment of the system was not opposed. So faras the Civil Service was concerned, though the Staff Side of the national whitley Council may have wished for consolidation at a higher level, theyhad no quarrel with consolidation itself; they had proposed it in their evidence to the Royal Commission. So far as the Services were concerned,proceedings in Parliament bear no evidence of complaints either at the time or during the years immediately following. Nor is there any other evidenceof a general body of complaint at that time.The General Question of Pensions in a Period of Falling Money Values35. Both the First and Second World Wars were followed by periods of rising prices and falling money values. Such a situation involves difficulties for public service pensioners and it is necessary to consider the actionapproved by Parliament after both World Wars to meet the situation.After the First World War the Governments of the day, faced withdemands for improvements in the pensions of those who had retired beforepost-war codes came into force, had responded with the Pensions Increasemeasures of 1920 and 1924.36. The essential principle underlying those measures which coveredpublic service pensioners generally (teachers, local authority staffs, &amp;c.) andnot only retired officers of the Services and civil servants was that whereasnormally the pensions of. former public servants are not adjusted to meetchanges in circumstances after retirement, in exceptional circumstances of severe deterioration in the value of money it is justifiable to give some help to those pensioners in serious need of help that is to those living on smallincomes. To go further, it was held, would not only be wrong in principlehaving regard to the fundamental basis of occupational retirement pensions,but would be manifestly unfair to those others in the community similarlyliving on small fixed incomes and perhaps, as tax-payers, bearing part of thecost of any additional help given to public service pensioners. Thus theState ought not at public cost to protect its own servants against a decline inthe value of money (including their semi-contractual pensions) which had
affected many others besides them. In conformity with this principle the1920 and 1924 measures gave no increases to those with incomes of morethan  200 a year (married) and  150 single. Thus, while all the Forces&apos;Officers, who retired under the 1919 code, had rates of pension designed to reflect the higher cost of living, their colleagues who had retired earlier andhad incomes of more than  200 a year got no help at all. The effects on civil Service pensioners were similar.37. Faced with a like situation in and after the 1939-45 war, all laterGovernments, the Coalition Government in 1944, the Labour Government in1947 and the present Government in 1952, have thought it right to follow the same policy: not to give assistance to all public service pensionersirrespective of serious hardship, but to give it where it was most needed to relieve real hardship as distinct from the relative hardships which a fall inthe value of money admittedly inflicts on all who live on fixed incomes, evensubstantial ones.38. Thus the 1944, 1947 and 1952 measures were in general designedto assist pensioners with dependants whose means were not more than  300, 450 and  550(0 respectively. These rising limits for determining whetherpensioners were eligible for assistance under the schemes took account of thefall in the value of money between the successive measures.39. In the 1944 measures the Government of the day recognised, however,the peculiar position of retired officer and civil service pensioners in that theyhad, up to seven years before the outbreak of war, been under a system whichpermitted pension adjustment in accord with the changes in the cost of living.As a result Section 2 of the Pensions (Increase) Act of 1944 provides (as dothe corresponding arrangements for Forces&apos; Officers) for increases of 10 percent, on pensions up to  400 a year, with smaller increases on pensions up to 645, irrespective of any other income. This is usually known as the &quot; auto-matic &quot; scheme. In the Act and corresponding arrangements of 1947, the pension limit for this special assistance was raised to  787 10s. It will beseen that even in this recognition of a special situation, deemed to warrant the singling out of retired officers and civil servants for special treatment notaccorded to other public service pensioners, it was thought right to limit theassistance to the lower and middle pension ranges and to exclude those with high pensions. And when in 1952 Her Majesty&apos;s Government submittedto Parliament the Pensions (Increase) Bill they felt that the funds availableshould be concentrated on relief of the greater hardship experienced by those with small pensions and little or no other means. The 1944-47 &quot; automatic&quot;scheme had virtually restored 1919 rates for all but those on the highestpensions, and the 1952 schemes therefore included no proposals for any extension of that scheme. In passing the Act Parliament endorsed thispolicy.40. The practical effect of all these changes over the years is seen inthe following table of typical cases:  OFFICERSPosition after Position afterMaximum standard rates                1944-47 1952 PensionsPensions Increase Increase measuresJuly,         measures (man (man with1914       I919(2)       1935          with dependant) dependant)Min.       Max.       Min.     Max.             Captain......       200Major   ...      ...       300Lieut.Colonel ... 420-450Major-General ...       700300 272450 407600 5431,000 905299	332	299	358440	450	440	476584	584	584	584905	905	905	905CIVIL SERVANTS(40 years&apos; service pensions under the Act of 1909)1914    1920    1922P)Code?) 	 	 					213	300	328	273	300	333	300	&apos; 359331	450	473	406	440	450	440	476449	600	601	529	569	569	569	569764	1,000	906	839	839	839	839	839(It is necessary to explain the basis on which the figures for Civil Servantshave been prepared. The second column shows the rates which wouldhave been payable under the code introduced in 1920, as explained inparagraphs 11-13 above, on a cost-of-living figure of 105. The figure didnot in fact fall so low as this until 1922. by which time, as already explained,(l) Taking account of &quot; disregards,&quot; incomes of  352,  502,  654, respectively. (Underthe 1944, 1947 and 1952 schemes the first  52,  52 and  104, respectively, of means otherthan pension were disregarded in assessing total means for purposes of determiningeligibility.)(2) Cost of living 107J.(3) Cost of living 105.
the code had been modified by the 1921 supercut, by making 100 per cent,of the bonus pensionable instead of 75 per cent., and by making the pensionsubject to quarterly variation after award. These rates are, therefore, taken as a fair starting point for comparisons with the 1919 rates for Forces&apos;Officers: and figures have been worked out to show the history of retire-ments at four rates of basic salary which would, on the 1920 code at a cost-of-living figure of 105, have provided a pension at the same rates as those shown for Forces&apos; Officers in 1919 at a cost of living of 107^.)Conclusion41. It is clear from this survey that during the period in question retiredForces&apos; officers have been treated in principle in the same way as retired civilservants have been treated. During the post-war period until 1931 bothofficers and civil servants received pensions which not only were awardedat varying levels as the cost of living moved, but were also varied after awardin sympathy with the cost of living. For officers this system started in 1919;and it was fully applied to civil servants in 1922. In both cases this systemrepresented a deviation from the normal principle that public service pensionsonce awarded are not altered, and was an exceptional arrangement expresslydesigned to meet the abnormal circumstances of the period immediately following the end of the First World War. These exceptional arrange-ments met with severe criticism both in principle from dispassionate observersand in practice from many of those personally concerned. The abandon-ment of the system for civil servants was recommended by a RoyalCommission; and when this recommendation was accepted and acted upon by the Government of the day it was generally agreed to be right that thedecision should also be applied to Service officers.42. The very close parallel between the histories of Forces&apos; Officers and civilians in this matter leaves no doubt in the mind of Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment that if there were to be any further changes in the position of those members of the Crown services who retired between 1919 (or 1922) and1945 it would be inequitable not to treat all four Services alike.43. The decision to consolidate cannot, however, in the case of eitherForces&apos; officers or civil servants, fairly be regarded as a breach of faith and,therefore, one to be reversed on that account. Indeed, the prerogativeinstruments of 1919 expressly stressed the exceptional nature of the 1919arrangements for Forces&apos; officers: from their beginning they had in themprovision for modification and cannot, therefore, be regarded as immutable.44. The fundamental principle of public service pensions, that onceawarded they are not normally subject to change in either direction, has beenupheld by successive Governments of all complexions, and Her Majesty&apos;sGovernment are in no way prepared to abandon it. In their view it is a principle that should be departed from (as it has been) only to the extent thatsevere falls in money values causing real hardship among pensioners mayjustify special increases as distinct from revised pensions where the degreeof hardship calls for it. Thus as recently as 1952 the last Pensions IncreaseAct was passed for public service pensioners and similar provision made forretired officers. There has since been no change in the circumstances tojustify further exceptional action of this sort.45. Thus in the Government^ view there can on the one hand be noreturn to the exceptional arrangements prevailing in the 20&apos;s and 30&apos;s forretired Forces&apos; Officers and civil servants; nor on the other is there anysufficient case for further general improvements in pensions for public service pensioners.46. But, having said this, Her Majesty&apos;s Government recognise that theoperation of the sliding scale between the wars has, in fact, given rise to aspecial grievance which is acutely felt by retired Service Officers. And indeed,though the earlier parts of this paper which set out the history demonstrate that the decisions of previous Governments were taken in good faith andwere at the time entirely reasonable, a sentiment on the part of the pensionersthat as things have turned out they have been unfairly treated is under -standable. The fact is that at one time pensions and retired pay fell as thecost of living did, but have remained fixed while it has risen, and risen fairlyconsiderably.47. It can be argued that this creates a special situation for these two groups of pensioner. Not only can it be so argued but Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment are aware that many people have been and are so arguing, and arereproachful of the Government for failing to accept the view that thecircumstances are unique and thus justify special action quite outside what may or may not be justified under the normal principles of pensions policyapplicable elsewhere.  The Government have taken note of these views.48. They are also conscious that in the pensions increase measures of1944 and 1947 the Governments of the day recognised the special positionof these two groups of pensioner by making special provision for what was, ineffect, a restoration of the &quot;1919 &quot; rates for those in the lower pension bands,
and a partial restoration in the middle pension bands. In effect those governments said: there can be no question of returning to the abnormalsystem of varying these pensions according to changes in the cost of living;the decisions of the early 30&apos;s were right and must stand; but there is a case for restoring, at any rate in the case of the lower pensions, the rates whichhad at one time been actually in force. They did not, however, think itjustifiable to restore these rates for all. The result was the somewhatillogical compromise enacted in Section 2 of the Pensions Increase Act of1944 as modified by the Act of 1947.49. Having now reviewed the matter in the light of all the circumstances,past and present, Her Majesty&apos;s Government have decided that it would nowbe right to revise the 1944 and 1947 arrangements to bring within their scopeall the retired Forces officers and Civil Service pensioners concerned and toallow to all of them the unconditional minimum increase of 10 per cent,already enjoyed by those with pension or retired pay of up to  400 a year.The Government will submit Warrants to Her Majesty to bring this aboutfor retired Forces Officers, and in the case of the civil servants will propose the necessary legislation to Parliament-50. For Forces&apos; Officers this will have the broad effect of restoring the&quot; 9^ per cent, cut&quot; for all those who were affected by it. Thus will be removedwhat for many years has seemed to many people to be a real injustice.
APPENDIX IExtracts from the Orders of the three Services Promulgating theNew Rates of Retired Pay, Variable with Cost of Living,introduced in 1919Royal NavyExtract from Admiralty Order in Council of the 22nd January, 1950,Schedule V, Section X, Paragraph 9&quot; The rates of full pay, unemployed pay, half pay, retired pay, allowances and gratuities, authorised under these regulations to be subject to review on or after 1st July, 1924.&quot;ArmyExtract from Army Order 324 of 1919, General Conditions, Paragraph 1. &quot; The new rates .... are granted in consideration of the present high cost of living and the rates of pay, half pay and retired pay will be subjectafter 5 years to revision either upwards or downwards to an extent notexceeding 20 per cent., as the cost of living rises or falls.  After the 1st July1924, a further revision may take place every three years.&quot;Royal Air ForceExtracts from Air Ministry Order 1003 of 1919Paragraph 7The new rates of pay and pensions have been drawn up in the light of thepresent high cost of living and it has therefore been decided that 20 per cent,of the rates should be regarded as detachable and liable to alteration eitherupwards or downwards according as the cost of living rises or falls. Norevisions of this kind will be made for five years, thereafter revisions will bemade every three years. These revisions will apply to all pensions which arebeing drawn on the new scales at the date of revision as well as to futureawards.  They will not apply to gratuities or the lower rates of half pay.Paragraph 9 CNo officer shall be entitled to claim hereafter any pay, pension or otheradvantage conferred by any provision in this scheme in the event of anysuch provision being at any time added to, varied or cancelled. It must be clearly understood that while every consideration will be given to the reason-able and legitimate interests of individuals, it will be competent for the Ah&apos;Council at any time to modify the administrative regulations under whichthe emoluments of the Royal Air Force are drawn. In particular no claimcan be founded on a regulation, the operation of which is merely contingent,e.g., a regulation prescribing a rate of pay which is revised before theclaimant attains the rank for which it is prescribed.APPENDIX this table illustrates the effect of the formula devised under the 1919 Codefor varying the retired pay of Forces&apos; Officers with changes in the cost ofliving.. Column A shows the per cent, abatement to which retired pay was subject when the cost of living stood at the corresponding levels quoted in column B.A	B	A	B	Cost-of-Living		Cost-of-LivingPer Cent.	Figure (above	Per Cent.	Figure (aboveAbatement	1914)	A batemeni	1914)20	0	9	59-12519	,  5-375	8	.64-500.     18	10-750	........   7	69-87517    &quot; ,	16 125	6	75-25016	21-500	5	80-625-   15    .	&apos;   26-875	4	86-00014   1	32-250 -	-      &apos;     3	91-37513	37-625	2	96-75012	43-000	1	102-12511	48 - 375	0	107-50010	53-750		

</content>
</cab>
