<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/66/0 images: 135-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF HER   BRITANNIC MAJESTYS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1954CONFIDENTIALC. (54) 801st March, 1954CABINETTHE ROYAL TOUR: GIBRALTARNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister I circulate for the information of the Cabinetthe text of part of a public statement by the Governor of Gibraltar about thearrangements for the visit of Her Majesty and the Duke of Edinburgh to Gibraltar,together with the text of a subsequent telegram from the Secretary of State forthe Colonies to the Governor.(Signed)        NORMAN BROOK.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,26th February, 1954.Extract from Statement by the Governor of GibraltarYou will, I know, understand that I am naturally preoccupied about thesecurity of Her Majesty and the Duke of Edinburgh during this visit, and I can assure you that all normal precautions are being taken by the police, the military,and the security services to ensure that her safety shall be protected. I hope thatfor your part you will help by following the orders of the police controlling thecrowds and that you will not inconvenience Her Majesty by crowding too close to the Royal car. But you will also understand that, despite the customs whichprevail in other parts of the world, the British Royal Family does not have to be driven in bullet-proof cars surrounded by squadrons of armed police! On thecontrary, complete confidence is reposed in Her Majesty&apos;s loyal subjects to ensurethat there are no demonstrations and no untoward incidents. I would not even have referred to such a matter had it not been for the unfortunate articles which have appeared recently in the Spanish press deprecating Her Majesty&apos;s visit, whichindeed have not only been out of place but have been specially lacking in the goodmanners and the good taste with which we have always associated our friends overthe frontier. As I have said, the object of Her Majesty&apos;s visit is to see and be seen by her loyal subjects in Gibraltar. Much as I would like to do so it would there-fore be out of place for me officially to invite any of our Spanish friends to be present at that time. On the other hand, I should like to extend a warm welcome to any Spaniards, and especially to those who work in such close harmony with us in Gibraltar, who wish to see The Queen, and for that reason I do not proposeto close the frontier on the 10th and 11th May.Copy No.   g2cabinet office record copyTelegram Dated 24th February from the Secretary of State for theColonies to the Governor of GibraltarThe Prime Minister and I are disturbed by your recent speech.The arrangements and security for the Royal Tour are a matter for the Palaceand the Cabinet, and any pronouncements relating to either must be made only after authorisation by the Cabinet.I shall be away, but the Prime Minister would like you to come to Londonbefore the end of next week to discuss these matters.You should take every step to prevent your visit being linked with yourspeech and as far as possible give impression of routine journey.45765

</content>
</cab>
