<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/66/0 images: 190-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[8 I(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)&amp;y--------------------&quot;V .       secret CABIWFT of w*------ -        *s i   i  i.yt ^,C.(54) 94 RtCOrtD COPY        COPY NO. 6^9TH MARCH, 1954CABINETIMMIGRATION OF COLOURED PEOPLEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department and Minister for Welsh affairs at their meeting on 3rd February the Cabinet considered thepossibility of restricting the number of coloured people from the Coloniesseeking employment in this country;  and, after discussion, they invited the Commonwealth Secretary and the Colonial Secretary to submit amemorandum summarising the present powers of other Commonwealth and colonial Governments to deport British subjects (C0C,(54) 7th Conclusions,Minute 4),2.     In the meantime, the continued immigration of coloured Colonialshas received some public attention.    A number of Departments havereceived letters from Members of Parliament indicating that various aspects of the problem are giving concern to their constituents,,    Complaintsare becoming more frequent that large numbers of coloured people are living on National Assistance or the immoral earnings of white women, and special objection has been taken to the way in which some coloured peopleacquire tenancies of old property and, by their conduct, make life difficult for white people living in the same building or area.    The result is thatthe white people leave and that the accommodation is then converted tofurnished lettings to coloured people with serious over-crowding andexploitation.    Complaints have been received from the Manchester area,but the problem appears to be most serious in some parts of London andthe Members of Parliament for the Paddington Divisions and forSt. Marylebone have drawn particular attention to it.3,     It also appears that a number of Members of Parliament on bothsides of the House are becoming increasingly concerned and severalapproaches have been made on the subject to junior Ministers.    In aQuestion addressed to the Prime Minister Mr. Reid, the Labour Memberof Parliament for Swindon, has suggested that a Committee should beappointed to report on the matter;  and, having expressed a wish to see a responsible Minister on the subject, he has recently been interviewed bythe Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State at the Home Office,    Mr. Reidexplained that his intention was that the Committee should have very wideterms of reference to enable it to investigate and set forth the facts andalso make proposals to deal with the situation.    He appreciates thepolitical difficulties of the subject and does not seek to embarrass theGovernment,    While recognising that some members of the opposition would bitterly oppose any action which could be represented as amountingeven in an indirect way to colour discrimination, he, said that he believedthat a large number, if not the majority, of Opposition Members sharedhis point of view but it is most unlikely that this is so or at any ratethat they would give expression to his sentiments.
4.     Mr. Reid suggested that he should put off his Question in order togive more time for consideration of the issues which he knew to be difficult and he has now deferred the date of reply until 18th March.    It seems desirable that we should consider, as a matter of urgency, what reply should be given.    So far as the essential facts are concerned, a Committeeis unlikely to add materially to the information which has already been collected by the official inter-departmental Committee,,    The issues involved are fairly clear and they involve the broadest policy considerations,which are really inappropriate for any Committee.    There are, therefore,grounds on which we could argue that a Committee could serve no useful purpose.    If we decide not to have a Committee, it will be simple to answer Mr. Reid&apos;s Question, and a rejection of his proposal will not giverise to any serious political difficulties.    It would not, of course, satisfythose Members who feel that some action ought to be taken, but we couldpoint out to them the serious difficulties involved in contemplating actionwhich would be a breach with our traditions and which would undoubtedlyland the Government in some political controversy.    It can be argued that, without a clear indication that both sides of the House would welcomepublic investigation of this matter, the Government cannot well beexpected to take action which would stir up so much trouble-.5.     On the other hand, there is much to be said for having the factscollected and published and the issues canvassed and thoroughly aired.It is evident that public opinion is quite uninformed on this subject, andthat is part of the reason for the reluctance to discuss the matter in public.    There is no indication that this problem will not continue to grow and the longer it is left the more difficult and dangerous it maywell become.6.     A temporising reply saying that the Government are consideringthe possibility of setting up a Committee would almost certainly give riseto just as much criticism as a firm decision to have such a Committee.It would be represented in some quarters that even to contemplaterestricting immigration from the Colonies would be a step towards breaking up the Empire, and in other quarters it would be regarded as evidence thatthe Government are in favour of a colour bar.    This latter argumentcould be very embarrassing at the present time.    I should be glad tohave the opinions of my colleagues as to the advice which should betendered to the Prime Minister on the reply to be made to Mr. Reid.7.      I am myself against entertaining the idea of a Committee.    I thinkthat the question is not yet sufficiently acute and that we should not, there-fore, add to our difficulties.D.M.F.Home Office, S. W. 1.8TH MARCH, 1954.2

</content>
</cab>
