<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/66/0 images: 205-205</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
lH(o(T$lif DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)secret cabinet office^54) 100 RECORD COPY     COPY NO.JJL13TH MARCH; 1954CABINETRETAIL MILK prices memorandum by the Minister of food have been considering the levels at which the retail price of milk should be fixed for the twelve months beginning 1st April next.The price of milk is at present 6-jrd. per pint, at which level it is fixed only until the end of March.    Last year we were able by theadoption of a seasonal price scale to make a modest saving in thesubsidy without arousing overmuch criticism on the score of increased prices.    I think there would be every advantage in repeating theprocedure this year.2.        I propose therefore to maintain the retail price of if-d. untilthe end of April, to reduce it to 6d. during the main flush period from may to July and to increase it to 7d. from August to the end ofMarch, 1955.3.        We run a greater risk of being forced into wasting milk thisyear than on any previous occasion and I am satisfied that it would be most unwise to enter the main flush period without reducing the price to6d.    But I think we can maintain a price of 7d. through the winter months without much effect on liquid consumption.4.        These price movements would reduce the All-Items Index by0o43 points in May and increase it from the reduced level by 0o 8C points in August.    The saving in the liquid milk subsidy during the financialyear would be about  6f millions net.    The average retail price overthe twelve months would work out at 6. 71 d, per pint as compared with6. 54d. per pint over the last twelve months.5.        In order to put these new arrangements into effect the presentprice order must be revoked and replaced by a new order.    The boards and the Distributive trade must know as soon as possible the retail prices to which they will have to work in the forthcoming year.I therefore invite my colleagLies to approve the early announcement ofthe range of prices proposed above.G0LL0G.Ministry of Food, S.W.113TH MARCH, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
