<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/51/11 images: 112-119</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cm (73)10th conclusions printed for the Cabinet. January 1975.Copy No. 0 2CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Friday, 23 February, 1973,at 11 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Sir Geoffrey Howe,qc, mp, Minister for Trade and consumer affairs mr.   Patrick   Jenkin,Secretary, treasury the following were also present:m p,   chief the Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. anson mr. R. L. BaxterMr. B. Murray
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cm (73)10th conclusions printed for the Cabinet. January 1975.Copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Friday, 23 February, 1973,at 11 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Sir Alec Douglas-Home, mp, Secretary of State forForeign and Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rtppon,qc, mp, Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell, m p,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the Right Hon. Sir Geoffrey Howe,qc, mp, Minister for Trade and consumer AffairsThe following were also present:Mr.   Patrick   Jenkin,Secretary, treasury m p,   chief the Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. anson mr. R. L. BaxterMr. B. Murray
SubjectPRICE AND PAY CODEDraft Consultative Document
CONFIDENTIALPrice and The Cabinet considered a Note by the Chancellor of the pay Code Exchequer (CP (73) 23), to v/hich was attached a draft ConsultativeDraft Document on the Price and Pay Code to be made under Clause 2Consultative    0f the Counter-Inflation Bill.DocumentThe Prime Minister said that the Counter-Inflation Bill required the Treasury to promulgate a Price and Pay Code, which wouldgovern the work of the Price Commission and the Pay Board andwould provide practical guidance for all those concerned withdecisions on prices and pay. The Bill also entailed a wide-rangingprocess of consultation before a Statutory Instrument containing the Code was made. The draft Consultative Document attachedto CP (73) 23, which was intended to provide the basis for these consultations, had been carefully examined by a small group ofMinisters under his chairmanship. It sought to establish the rightbalance between prices and pay; and, while dealing firmly with both questions, it had due regard to the need to enlist the co-operation of all concerned if the policy was to be a success. Since itwas essentially consultative in character, any pressures for changeduring the period of public discussion would tend towards weak-ening, rather than strengthening its provisions; and, although the document as published should desirably approximate as closely aspossible to the Code which would ultimately be established, nounnecessary concessions should be made in its form or content atthis stage. The draft had also been considered, from the presen-tational standpoint, by a small group of junior Ministers; and theirconstructive suggestions would be taken into account in the finalrevision.The Cabinet should give particular attention to certain criticalpassages in the text. Thus:(a) As regards the definition of allowable costs, it had been feltthat to accept all costs admitted for tax purposes would be too wide;and a more stringent definition had therefore been adopted, compris-ing only labour and material costs, bought-in components, rent, ratesand interest charges.(b) The Confederation of British Industry (CBI) had pressed strongly for the base date for allowable costs to be July, 1971, inorder that the period in which their members had observed voluntaryprice restraint should be taken into account. This, however, wouldhave destroyed the balance between the proposals on prices and pay.Instead, a base date of 30 September, 1972, had been accepted for manufacturing industry on grounds of accounting convenience,because it was the end of the last calendar quarter before the standstill.(c) A number of difficulties had been encountered in consideringthe deduction in respect of productivity. There had been a largeaverage increase in productivity in industry during the previous year;and some deduction from allowable costs was appropriate in order:   to ensure that it would be reflected in lower prices. It had therefore been suggested that industries should be required to absorb a specified
percentage of their labour costs, the appropriate percentage beingallocated on the basis of their productivity record over the period1963-71. But this system had been shown to result in wide and apparently irrational variations between the productivity deductionswhich would be required of different industries, and this would havebeen difficult to defend publicly. It seemed likely, therefore, that itwould be necessary to specify a single percentage figure, which would need to be set fairly high, in order that, even if there was some provision for reduction for those industries whose productivity waslow, there should be a substantial absorption of costs by industry asa whole. Further detailed consideration would need to be givento the question whether the deduction would be applied to all costsor only to increases in labour costs.(d) As regards the treatment of personal increments, it had beendecided that the private sector should be dealt with on the same basis as the public sector and that regular increments in any properlycontrolled system of incremental scales should not be subject to the pay limit. Certain companies in the private sector, however, paidvery large increments to individuals earning high salaries; and con-sideration was therefore being given to limiting the concession onincrements to those employees whose salaries did not exceed  7,500a year.(e) Other sections of the Consultative Document which hadneeded special consideration were those dealing with low profitsituations, long-term pay agreements, and the treatment of particularsectors such as food prices and the construction industry.In the light of the views which the Cabinet expressed on the document as a whole and on the main points which he had mentioned,the group of Ministers under his chairmanship would complete thepreparation of the Consultative Document in order that it might bepublished on Monday 26 February.In discussion the broad lines of the draft Consultative Documentwere accepted; and it was agreed that, although a number of amend-ments to the Code might result from the processes of public and parliamentary discussion, the Government would need to stand firm on its main principles. It would therefore be better to make any significant alterations which might be contemplated in, for example,the prices section before the draft was published rather than to concede such alterations under apparent pressure.In further discussion the following main points were made (a) Allowable costs. It was suggested that the exclusion of de-preciation from allowable costs could discourage investment. On theother hand, if 100 per cent depreciation was admitted as an allowable cost, following the precedent established in the tax field, this wouldprovide companies with undue freedom to justify price increases.Moreover, it would be difficult to find a satisfactory formula which would admit depreciation charges on a more restrictedbasis. Paragraph 50 of the Code specifically enabled the price commission to waive the limits on allowable costs increases whereit was satisfied that investment would otherwise be seriouslyimpeded.   The exclusion of depreciation might be made more
acceptable if it was emphasised that the draft Code related only to theperiod of Stage 2, and that a fresh Code would be promulgated for stage 3; but this could have the disadvantage of encouraging the deferment of investment until Stage 3. The case for admitting costs of services, such as transport, as allowable costs should also be examined.(b) Base date. It was pointed out that the CBI would argue that the adoption of a base date later than 1971 would penalisethose who took part in the voluntary restraint programme and would confer an unfair benefit on those who had not been prepared toco-operate in it. This argument, however, was unacceptable, par-ticularly since the voluntary restraint programme had allowed a percentage addition to prices, with provision for exceptions to the ceiling in some cases; and profits had in fact been rising stronglyduring the period of restraint. Further consideration should begiven, however, to the definition of the base year for retailers, inorder to avoid anomalies which might arise if the standstill affected the base year for some companies but not for others.(c) Food prices. It was suggested that even those food prices which were not controlled must be sufficiently covered by thearrangements for reporting price increases; and paragraphs 139 and140 of the draft Code should accordingly be strengthened. It shouldalso be emphasised publicly that food prices were controlled at the wholesale and retail levels.(d) Nationalised industries. It was pointed out that in somenationalised undertakings the present formula for allowable cost increases would not prevent a renewed increase in deficits. in electricity supply it was estimated that price increases of 6-7 per centwere necessary to prevent the deficit from rising, whereas increases of only 2\ to 3 per cent would be permissible on the allowable costformula. If the price of electricity was kept artificially low, however,demand tended to be distorted and there would be greater difficultiesin reverting to a normal commercial pricing policy at a later date.On the other hand success in Stage 2 would be jeopardised ifnationalised industries were allowed to raise prices by as much as7 per cent. It was therefore preferable, on balance, to accept some further increase in the deficits of the nationalised industries, in orderto restrain price increases. The Government could point to their decision to maintain subsidies to the nationalised industries as a positive contribution to the counter-inflationary policy.(e) Distributors&apos; margins. The draft text required wholesalersor retailers to reduce their percentage margins in order to take account of any disproportionate rise in the price of goods sold. Itwas suggested that it might be more satisfactory to leave the initiativewith the Price Commission to require firms to take such action.(/) The Pay Code. It was suggested that in the further con-sideration of the possibility of establishing a salary ceiling above which increments in excess of the pay limit might not be paid in stage 2 care should be taken not to penalise individuals who were about to retire and might therefore suffer a reduction in pension entitlement.  The possibility of extending the exemption in the Pay
acceptable if it was emphasised that the draft Code related only to theperiod of Stage 2, and that a fresh Code would be promulgated for stage 3; but this could have the disadvantage of encouraging the deferment of investment until Stage 3. The case for admitting costs of services, such as transport, as allowable costs should also be examined.(b) Base date. It was pointed out that the CBI would argue that the adoption of a base date later than 1971 would penalisethose who took part in the voluntary restraint programme and would confer an unfair benefit on those who had not been prepared toco-operate in it. This argument, however, was unacceptable, par-ticularly since the voluntary restraint programme had allowed a percentage addition to prices, with provision for exceptions to the ceiling in some cases; and profits had in fact been rising stronglyduring the period of restraint. Further consideration should begiven, however, to the definition of the base year for retailers, inorder to avoid anomalies which might arise if the standstill affected the base year for some companies but not for others.(c) Food prices. It was suggested that even those food prices which were not controlled must be sufficiently covered by thearrangements for reporting price increases; and paragraphs 139 and140 of the draft Code should accordingly be strengthened. It shouldalso be emphasised publicly that food prices were controlled at the wholesale and retail levels.(d) Nationalised industries. It was pointed out that in somenationalised undertakings the present formula for allowable cost increases would not prevent a renewed increase in deficits. in electricity supply it was estimated that price increases of 6-7 per centwere necessary to prevent the deficit from rising, whereas increases of only 2\ to 3 per cent would be permissible on the allowable costformula. If the price of electricity was kept artificially low, however,demand tended to be distorted and there would be greater difficultiesin reverting to a normal commercial pricing policy at a later date.On the other hand success in Stage 2 would be jeopardised ifnationalised industries were allowed to raise prices by as much as7 per cent. It was therefore preferable, on balance, to accept some further increase in the deficits of the nationalised industries, in orderto restrain price increases. The Government could point to their decision to maintain subsidies to the nationalised industries as a positive contribution to the counter-inflationary policy.(e) Distributors&apos; margins. The draft text required wholesalersor retailers to reduce their percentage margins in order to take account of any disproportionate rise in the price of goods sold. Itwas suggested that it might be more satisfactory to leave the initiativewith the Price Commission to require firms to take such action.if) The Pay Code. It was suggested that in the further con-sideration of the possibility of establishing a salary ceiling above which increments in excess of the pay limit might not be paid in stage 2 care should be taken not to penalise individuals who were about to retire and might therefore suffer a reduction in pension entitlement. The possibility of extending the exemption in the Pay
Code for improved pension arrangements to include payments forinvalidity should also be explored. The Code must not allow firms to evade the pay limit by artificial changes in job specification. But,although it was necessary that in Stage 2 the cost of any generalregrading scheme should count against the pay limit, it would be helpful if it could be indicated that further consideration could begiven to desirable restructuring schemes in Stage 3.(g) Publicity. The presentation of the Code, both to parliament and to the public would require considerable care. It would benecessary to emphasise that, although both domestic and inter-national pressures on the level of prices made some departure fromtraditional Conservative doctrine unavoidable at the present juncture,the Consultative Document was addressed to a Stage in the Govern-menfs pay and prices policy which was intended to be strictlytemporary and would be succeeded as rapidly as possible by a regimeallowing greater scope for the natural balance of economic forces to assert itself. In particular, it should be made clear that the Codedid not exclude either higher pay if more overtime hours wereworked or higher profits if output increased. Information shouldalso be made available about the relatively small number of firms, indifferent categories, who were likely to be affected by the requirements for pre-notification of price and pay increases and for reporting.Since the Consultative Document related to the Price and Pay Codefor Stage 2, it made no reference to matters which would not ariseconcretely until Stage 3, such as the treatment of pay anomalies.Further thought should therefore be given to the desirability of a parliamentary Statement, on the day when the Consultative Docu-ment was published, in order to explain the position on these other questions. Consideration should also be given to the inclusion ofan explanatory foreword in the Document itself.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thegroup of Ministers under his chairmanship, when preparing the finalversion of the Consultative Document, would have full regard to thepoints made in the Cabinefs discussion. They would also take account of the presentational points put forward by the group of junior Ministers who had studied the draft. He would try to arrangefor copies of the final version to be circulated to the Cabinet shortly before its publication.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.Cabinet Office,26 February, 1973.

</content>
</cab>
