<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/12/0 images: 346-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C^L,e,^La./-. ---:( /y,(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Oh1 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMETr)SECRET COPY NO.   O-^CP. (46)  5555RD SEPTEMBER,   1946CABINETREPATRIATION OF GERMAN PRISONERS OF WARNote by the secretary i circulate, for the information of the Cabinet,the annexed copy of a message from the Foreign Secretarygiving his views on the question of repatriating german prisoners of war.(Signed)    E.E.   BRIDGESCabinet Office, S.W.I.5RD&apos; SEPTEMBER ,   1946,annex  understand that the question of repatriatingGerman prisoners of war and making an announcement on thesubject will be raised by the War Office at the Cabinet on 4th September.      In general I am in agreement with theWar Office views on the importance of announcing there patriation scheme.      I do not,  however,  think that thisis enough.      I think that we should work out a scheme for sending nack German prisoners of war in a steady flow.This scheme should begin as soon as possible and we shouldmake a start with the 20,000 &quot;whites11 whom we hold.      these should clearly have priority and their return to Germany willhave a very valuable effect at the present time.      As regardsthe remaining prisoners I think we should make it clear tothem that those who have the best records and have workedbest will have superior chances of repatriation.      I triedthis with the Italians and found it worked very well.      Ifthe German prisoners are given some good inducement to workwe shall get more out of them and we shall also get rid ofthem quicker..If it is a question of shipping I hope that this can be provided. It is a very short journey from england to a German port and I am sure that a very moderate amountof shipping will be sufficient to keep up a steady flow of repatriation.1-

Finally I think the repatriation of the&quot;whites&quot; should begin at once.      There are shortly to be important local elections in Germany to beheld on 15th September and 13th October and these will be the first which have been held for 13 years the Russians have recently returned a large numberof German prisoners from their Zone and are makinga lot of election capital out of this in contrast with the inaction of the Western Powers.      In this connexion I draw your attention to the strikingleading article in the Manchester Guardian of28th August.      It will be a great help to the democratic forces in Germany which we are tosupport if a good batch of prisoners arrived just before the elections, particularly if we couldcouple this with the announcement of a firm schemefor repatriation to begin very soon.      I hope thatthis can be managed as    anything that we can do to improve the political situation in our ownZone at the present time is of extreme value.

Finally I think the repatriation of the&quot;whites&quot; should begin at once.      There are shortly to be important local elections in Germany to beheld on 15th September and 13th October and these will be the first which have been held for 13 years.The Russians have recently returned a large numberof German prisoners from their Zone and are makinga lot of election capital out of this in contrast with the inaction of the Western Powers.      In this connexion I draw your attention to the strikingleading article in the Manchester Guardian of28th August.      It will be a great help to the democratic forces in Germany which we are tosupport if a good batch of prisoners arrived just before the elections, particularly if we couldcouple this with the announcement of a firm schemefor repatriation to begin very soon.      I hope thatthis can be managed as    anything that we can do to improve the political situation in our ownZone at the present time is of extreme value.


</content>
</cab>
