<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/12/0 images: 364-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:   175K)CU^NT^IS^THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S  GOVaRPMENT)SECRETCP.   (46) 3585TH SEPTEMBER,   1946CABINETINCREASES IN BUYING AND SELLING- PRICES OF TINMgjriopanclijrn by the Minister of supply the present prices which we are paying for&apos; tin concentratesin Malaya,  Nigeria and East Africa are below what can beregarded as  a reasonable price in. present conditions of worldtin shortage and are affecting- the willingness of producers(especially in Malaya)  to increase output.    I propose toincrease as from 1st July txhe prices paid for tin in nigeria, East Africa and Malaya to put those prices on a comparable basis and in rough relationship with the buyingprice for tin established in recent negotiations between theU. S. x-.   and the Bolivian&apos; tin producers.    I propose  also toincrease as soon as possible the selling price for tin metalin the United Kingdom from  300 to  300,10.0 so as to cover the costs of purchases and to eliminate the present highsubsidy element in that price.    That issue price includes a charge for delivery to consumers&apos; works and would be subjectto premiums for higher qualities.The Treasury and Colonial Office agree these proposals.2.      The Lord President&apos;s Committee has  approved inFebruary and June 1946 (L.P.   (46)  7th Meeting;, Minute 5)and L.R.   (46) 23rd&apos; Meeting, Minute 4)  a series of increases in the selling prices of other non-ferrous metals (copper,zinc and lead)&apos;in order to bring the- United Kingdom pricesof those metals more in harmony with the prices ruling forour overseas purchases.    The United Kingdom issue price fortin has not been changed since the beginning of 1944.    ItsI    present level of  300 &quot;is out of harmony with world conditions,-my proposal to increase that price would, bring the United Kingdomtin price to 75/0 above the 1937-39 level.3.     The world production of tin at mine source in 1946 isestimated to be between 88,000 and 95*000 tons as comparedwith a peak in 1941 of nearly 250,000 tons (see Appendix).This excludes stocks of tin metal and tin concentrates foundin re-occupied or enemy countries of about 36,000 tons.In 1947,  an increase in production of about 60,000 tonsmay be anticipated as the Malayan,  Siamese and N.E.I. minesget back into production, but it will probably be the endof 1948 before supply&apos;catches up with world demand,  estimated to be not far short of 200,000 tons.&apos;   The U.S.A.   accounts for about half the world consumption and. every effort is Jpeiiigmade to increase production in Malaya as rapidly as possiblein view of the dollar earning value of the metal.COPY NO.       $ *

The Ministry of Supply is currently purchasing thetotal output of tin concentrates in Nigeria;, British EastAfrica and Cornwall;    these amount to about 11,000 tons(tin content)  and are  smelted in the United Kingdom onMinistry account.    This United Kingdom smelter has a 10 yearcontract running to 1950 with the largest single Bolivianproducer (patino)   accounting for about 20,000 tons per annum.The resultant  tin metal is purchased and distributed by theMinistry.    The United States Government purchases fromother Bolivian producers the balance of the Bolivian outputof tin concentrates  (about 20,000 tons)  for smelting inits smelter at Texas and is also anxious to purchaseconcentrates from other fields.5.      In Malaya,  the Ministry of Supply is purchasing the stocks and new production of concentrates and metals,the concentrates being smelted in Malaya on Ministry account.The metal is sold to various countries in accordance withallocations determined &quot;by the international Combined TinCommittee in Washington.    None comes to the United Kingdom.6.      The  above arrangements provide a supply&apos; of about 30,000tons per annum of tin metal from the United Kingdom smelterof which two-thirds is of Bolivian origin.    About 23,000tons a. year is being used in the United Kingdom leaving7,000 tons out of current production available for maintainingstocks in the United Kingdom and for export in accordance&apos;with the Combined Tin. Committee allocation.    Under thelong-term contract with patino in Bolivia the United Kingdomsmelter   has to purchase its concentrates at the LondonMetal Exchange price or the U.S.A.  buying price from otherproducers in Bolivia.    Under present conditions the latterdetermines the price to be paid.7.      The U. S.  Government arranged with the Bolivians fora price of  361.6s. per ton f. o.b.  Bolivia at 1st -July,  19k5fwith provision for a reduction by quarterly stages clown to 333. 10s.  Od.  per ton at 30th June,  19h-6.    They had hopedthat continuing arrangements at not higher than  333.10s.would result.    The Bolivians,  however,  have announced their intention to cease production at some mines on this price and have forced the U. S.  Government to agree to a modification of the above arrangements.    Under that modificationthe price will be revised retro-actively to operate from 1st January, 19h7 to 31st December,  19h-6 as follows:-Basic price  356.3s.Od.  f.o.b.  plus a sliding productionbonus based on the relationship of 19h7 to 19hh production.The maximum production bonus will &apos;bu applied as to 5.11s, Od.  per ton over the first six months of 19h-6 and asto  16. i3s.0d.   a ton over the  second six months.    The currentcost to us of metal from Bolivian ore (allowing for oceanfreight and insurance)  which is bought on the private contract(paragraph h)  is  380.12s. Od.   including the three cents bonus.8.      Our purchases of tin ore from producers outside ^Boliviahave hitherto been made on different bases and at differentprices,  all (except Cornwall)  below the new Bolivian price,viz.(a)    Nigeria.    Tin concentrates from this colony are highgrade and are&apos; required for mixing with the Bolivian material in the smelter at Liverpool.    From 19hl to 19h7 the Ministrypurchased on a costed basis the total production of tin in ore onan f. a. s. basis,  shipped the tonnage to Liverpool and paid a

refining charge.    The costod contracts, which were most unsatisfactory-, were terminated at 31st December, 192+5,and a price of  32+0 per ton of tin in ore f, a. s,  forthe first six months of 192+6 has been agreed.    This resultedfor that period in a cost to us of  358.5s.0d.  per ton of metal in the United Kingdom.(k)    East Africa,,      The very small animal tonnage isbeing bought in a tin price of  321 ,por ton less oceanfreight to the United Kingdom and refining charge.(c) Cornwall,,       Purchases  (about 1000 tons in all)are made from the larger producers on a coated basis andfrom the smaller producers at an agreed price.    The .average cost is around  1+50 per ton.(d) Malaya.    Here the price for metal ex smelter was fixed at  300 per ton on the re-occupation.    This wasexperimental and there has been little production so far.The  same price was applied to stocks found in the country.The selling price ox Malaya has been fixed at  351 per ton.All the Malayan tin is sold to other countries and asproduction increases it is expected that substantial tonnageswill go to the U.S.A.    The Governor has reported -&quot;Tin companies can make little or no   profit,  especially thoseoperating open cast mines at current prices.    This tends to depress production and leads operators to concentrate onsuch work as removing over-burden,  in preparation for producing ore when the price is higher,  and increases the costs of exiguous ore production by incidence of overheads&quot;.9,      The Empire producers have urged that the present positionis not&apos; satisfactory to them and is retarding production.    Theyclaim that the price paid by the U.8.A.   and consequently by theUnited Kingdom to the Bolivians should, form the basis on whichthe price to them should be fixed so that  in effect a world price is established.10.      The latest American price to the Bolivian producers(see paragraph 7)  contains a bonus which is,,  in part at least,a subsidy for political reasons to the Bolivian economy,which depends almost entirely on the export of tin;    butpossibly half of the bonus can be regarded as a true bonuson production.    I propose therefore to base our new purchase price for the Nigerians, East African and Malayan producersgenerally,   on the American price to Bolivia plus half theAmerican bonus  (in e.  6h cents plus 1-g- cents per lb - or 36ho 0. 0,  - fo o.o b.  South America).    This 65k cents f. o. b.  is equivalent to  57?.* 5*0,   a ton c. i. f. United Kingdom port,.The prices  I propose for Nigeria ( 357.10*0 per ton of tinin ore f., a3 3,  Nigerian port)  and for Malaya ( 370 metalf,o, b.  Malays)   are roughly comparable with this figure of - 372.5.0.  c,i*f.  United Kingdom after allowing for freightdifferentials and the differing methods of buying.    East Africawould be treated similarly.    Cornwall is regarded as aspecial case where existing arrangements would continue.11.      Discussions with the Nigerian and Malayan producershove been going on for some time,  but,  although, the newAmerican contract with the Bolivians applies back to 1st    January, -192+6,  it. is proposed to make our new buyingprices to Malaya. East Africa and Nigeria retroactive only from 1st July,

Ministry of Supply.5TH SEPTEMBER *  1946.JVW.APPENDIXEstimated World production of Tin at Mine1946TonsBolivia 40,000mfl1qvq 9,000Tii - 4/t3 000Nigeria 9/16,000OtheSs &apos;^/^ 000^World total       say 88/95,00012.      At the some time I propose to raise the selling price  -of tm metal in the United Kingdom (both for home and export purposes)  to cover costs.    This will mean increasingthe current home issue price of  300 a ton (on which a lossof  60/7Q a ton was made in the first half of 191+6)  to 380.10.-6 a ton.    The&quot; present export price - which is - 357 a ton - would be raised to the some level.The present domestic price of  300 a ton has beenin force since the beginning of 1944.    The - general policyof elimination of subsidy from United Kingdom prices has not been applied to tin at an&apos;earlier date owing touncertainty as to what the American reaction would be tothe proposals for a fairly uniform world price for buyingtin and as to what that price was likely to be.    It had been hoped in the earlier months of this year that it would bepossible to keep the price of our purchases of tin at a level not greatly in excess of our selling price of  300 a ton.It is now evident,  however,  (sec the quotation from a reportby the Governor of Malaya in paragraph 8(d)  above)   thatMalayan costs of production have so increased that a priceof  300 in Malaya was a barrier to the restoration ofproduction there.    In Nigeria,  our original offer topurchase tin concentrates during the first half of 1946on a basis that would have reprcsented a metal price of 32.5/330 a ton ex United Kingdom smelter proved unacceptable to the producers.    Further, the recent American settlement with the Bolivians  (see paragraph 7 above)  increased the -American price much more sharply than was expected.13..     It is to be noted that in the U. S. A.   tin prices arevery heavily subsidised.    It is estimated that metal producedfrom Bolivian concentrates in the U.S.A.   costs the Americansat least  380 a. ton ex smelter.    The U. S.A.   internal selling price is only  289.8.0.  a ton and the export price  (for very small tonnages)  339.10.0.    The Americans are believed to be considering some increase in their internal selling price,14.      Consumption of tin metal in the United Kingdom is now about 23,000 tons a year,  spread over a great many uses.-Tinplate is the greatest single user (accounting for about30Jb) ;    a substantial part of that tinplate goes into foodcontainers.    An increase in the United Kingdom issue pricefrom  300 to  380.10,0. would have  the effect of increasingtinplate prices by about 1/2d,   a box or 3;-o.15.      It is our intention to maintain these new buying andselling prices for tin until the end of 1946 but 1 would hopethat this&apos;settlement would hold for a longer period untilrehabilitation in the Par East has resulted in larger suppliescoming forward.


</content>
</cab>
