<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/12/0 images: 432-439</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s goyernment g Q printed for the Cabinet.   September 1946.SECRET.CP. (46) 344.11th September, 1946CABINET.1  CIVIL AIRCRAFT REQUIREMENTS.Note by the Prime Minister.ANNEXED to this note is a copy of a minute addressed to me by theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs reporting the results of the enquiries which, at my request, he undertook to make into the points raised when theCabinet (CM. (46) 77th Conclusions, Minute 3) discussed the joint memorandumby the Minister of Supply and the Minister of Civil Aviation (CP. (46) 317) on civil aircraft requirements.2. The main conclusions reached by the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs are : (a) full use should be made of the machinery provided by the Self Committeefor ensuring that in the design and production of new aircraft thereis adequate co-operation between the Ministries concerned and the operating corporations, and a suitable representative of the treasury should be added to the Committee;(b) the large number of different types of aircraft on order is justified inview of the wide variety of uses for which the aircraft are needed;(c) production orders should be given as soon as necessary to ensure theearliest possible production of the types and numbers of aircraft ofBritish manufacture shown in the table appended (Appendix II)to the minute by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs. with one or two exceptions, these orders cover only aircraft for which the operating corporations have stated definite requirements. No orders under the procedure proposed in paragraph 10 of Annex B to cp. (46) 317 for underwriting the production of aircraft for exportare included, since the arrangements for this are still under dis-cussion between the Treasury and the Ministry of Supply and theMinistry of Civil Aviation;Copy No.    ^ 5
(d) by fully using the machinery for consultation referred to at (a) aboveneedless delays should be avoided, but the period of four to seven years between the original statement of a requirement for a new typeof aircraft and its entry into operation is not likely to be reducedsubstantially;(e) there should be immediate consultations between the Treasury and the ministries of Supply and Civil Aviation with a view to strengthening the technical staffs of these Ministries;(/) a Press communique should be issued showing what is being done to foster the manufacture of British aircraft and putting the purchaseof strato--Cruisers in its proper perspective.3. After consultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer, I have instructed the Minister of Supply and the Minister of Civil Aviation to putinto effect forthwith the recommendations summarised in paragraphs 2 (a) and(e), and a Press communique on the lines suggested in paragraph 2 (/) was issued for publication on the 31st August, 1946. I have also approved the recommenda-tion in paragraph 2 (c) on condition that the procedure for ordering civil aircraft for the Corporations is, in future, based on the following principles : (a) Contracts for these aircraft should include guarantees by the manufac-turers as to performance and delivery dates, and provision forpenalties if these guarantees are not fulfilled.(b) While the orders should continue to be placed by the Minister of Supplyand not by the Corporations themselves, in order to secure theadvantages of bulk purchase and to co-ordinate military and civilproduction, the Ministry should place these orders&apos; as agents of andin agreement with the Corporations, who should carry the financial risks proper to the purchaser.4. I have asked the Ministers to circulate a further report to the Cabinetin six months&apos; time showing what progress has been made and dealing inparticular with the dates at which the new aircraft which are being ordered willbecome available, the arrangements made to stimulate the production of aircraft for export and the extent to which it has been possible to meet the shortage of technical staffs in the Ministries of Supply and Civil Aviation.c. R. a.10 Downing Street, S.W. 1.11th September, 1946.
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTANNEX.Minute from the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs to thePrime Minister.1. In pursuance of your instructions, I have made careful enquiries intothe points raised in the recent Cabinet discussion on civil aircraft requirements.Both Ministers and their staffs have given me most ready help, and I have hadthe advantage of personal conferences with them and with their chief officers.2. I have been supplied with long and detailed tables of the variety of aircraft now in use both by ourselves and by the Americans, and thediscussion of the issues are apt to be somewhat bewildering to anyone notintimately acquainted with the facts. But certain clear issues arise as well asthe need for specific decisions on production orders to which I will refer.Need for Co-operation.3. There is an outstanding need for the closest co-operation with all possiblegoodwill between the Ministries concerned as well as the operating companies,and I am satisfied that the arrangements now set up will secure this. It is unavoidable that between now and 1948 and 1950 the American types will havehad a substantial start and I can see that whilst it may be. necessary, as an urgent measure, to supply ourselves with some up-to-date American aircraft inthe interval, as agreed to by the Cabinet with regard to the six strato--Cruisers at its recent meeting, it is essential that we should continue to plan for the clevelop-ment of British aircraft manufacture so that it will have a secure leading position at least by 1950, as contemplated by the Self Committee. The Ministers concerned have promised to supply me with a considered memorandum on the issues of policy that would be raised by future possible purchases of foreign-built aircraft. This,however, will not be possible until after the Recess and need not in any wayinterfere with the decisions required to be taken now.4. The Joint Committee under Sir Henry Self, set up last May, is clearlyon the right lines and I am assured that henceforth it will be in regular sessionas a machinery for joint consultation between those concerned.5. It is essential that those who are expert in matters of design as well as of manufacture should be in close consultation from the start and be able topresent agreed recommendations in the elaboration of plans. I enclose(Appendix I) a copy of the present constitution of the Committee and its termsof reference. It is agreed that the Committee as it stands is rather large, butI am assured that certain parts of the work will be dealt with by sub-committees.In my view it is essential, and this is agreed by all, that the Treasury should berepresented by an important officer on this Committee. This does not mean thatthe Treasury will be committed in advance, but it would have the valuable resultof their being informed from the beginning of what is contemplated and whatexpenditure might be involved.Types.6. Points were raised at the Cabinet as to the multiplicity of typessupplied or arranged for delivery, and I have enquired carefully into this. It is evident that a considerable variety of types is required and that many require-ments are different for trans-oceanic or for flights across land, for long hops orshorter ones, for tropical conditions as well as for colder ones. The ministers have supplied me with a list of the 23 types outstanding and of their purpose.7. It appears from an examination of the list that of the 23 machinesreferred to in paragraph 11 of Annex B of CP. (46) 317, 10 are in provisionaluse as consisting of conversions of war-time military types. The others are new types already decided upon which in time will be replaced by new developments.For immediate purposes decision is required on the various forms of production orders which are referred to in paragraphs 24, 25 and 26 of Annex B of CP.(46) 317.Production Orders.8.   These proposals have been&apos; the subject of a meticulous examination at meetings with the two Ministers and their chief officers and they resolve them-selves into production orders affecting 8 types, and I enclose a table (Appendix II)[32382]
which has been provided for me. I understand that discussions are already inhand with the Treasury as to the details and I think a good case was made withregard to Brabazon I (paragraph 26 (6)).Brabazon IIB (Vickers VC2) (paragraph 25 (d)).Brabazon IIB (Armstrong Whitworth) (paragraph 25 (e)).Brabazon III (A. V. Eoe Version) (paragraph 26 (c)).Brabazon IV (D.H. 106) (paragraph 26 (a)).Brabazon VA (Marathon) (paragraph 25 (g)).Hermes (paragraph 25 (b)).Concordia (paragraph 25 (/)).The total expenditure forecast, as you will see, is about  25 millions.I should make special reference to the two machines Brabazon III andBrabazon IV. A firm requirement has been received for Brabazon III for 50machines and it is anticipated that more may be asked for. This machine is designed to replace the Tudor II, particularly for the Australian and Africanroutes, and I think we are well justified in embarking on the large commitmentinvolved. With regard to Brabazon IV, which is a machine that it is anticipated i will put us in the front in 1950 or 1951 and for which both Departments havehigh and confident expectations, the first proposal put before me was that 50of these machines should be ordered, involving an expenditure of  10 millionsor so. As a result, however, of the discussions which have taken place and of conversations with the Treasury, it has been agreed that the order could properly be limited to 14 machines with a large reduction in the total cost, although theexpenditure per machine is necessarily higher than would have been the case if the larger number had been ordered.Time.9. With regard to the long period of time that appears to be required sofar between the original suggestion of a requirement and the putting of the machine into operational service, the Minister of Supply has provided me withan excellent but very detailed memorandum, with which I do not think I needtrouble you. It is pretty evident that at present anyhow a period of from fourt seven years is involved both in Britain and in America and it is not easy atpresent to forecast it being shortened materially. The most important contri-bution towards shortening this period and dealing with numberless questions that arise in respect of design, trials, alterations, manufacture and so on, andthe most effective means that can be suggested, is clearly forecast in the Self-Committee in which all the different parties concerned are in regular consulta-tion and in &quot;that way will be likely to deal with difficulties both more efficiently and more promptly. Much of this will depend upon the persistent maintenanceof good relations between all parties concerned, and I think that the existenceof a central co-ordinating body such as the Self Committee is the most promisingway of securing this end.Staff.10. Finally, I want to express my emphatic agreement with the recommenda- ;tion referred to in paragraph 27, page 12, of C.P. (46) 317 to the effect thatthey are much concerned &quot; at the inadequate strength of the technical staffs ofboth the Ministry of Civil Aviation and the Ministry of Supply.&quot; This deficiencywas no doubt unavoidable at the turnover from war to peace conditions, andit was no doubt inevitable that in the emergencies of the war, the most efficientpeople had been devoted to war service requirements. The additional expertstaff required is almost exclusively needed by the Ministry of Supply, and it isclearly to be considered as a part of other demands and in this connection I think should quote from a memorandum sent to me by the Minister of Supply:  &quot; So far as the Ministry of Supply is concerned, this is part of the widerquestion of the allocation of scientific and technical staffs as between the&quot;Universities, industry and the Government Service. There have been severereductions since the end of the war in the scientific and technical staff ofthe Ministry in the process of scaling down to a suggested figure of approxi-mately 50 per cent, of the Ministry&apos;s war-time peak. This is causing graveembarrassment not only in the field of civil aviation but in the other expandingfields such as atomic energy, guided projectiles and microbiological warfare,all of which have special priorities. So far as civil aviation alone is con-cerned, it is estimated that to cope with the programme adequately, which in
effect means crowding into a few years the development that would havenormally been spread over 8 or 9 years, a further 255 scientific andtechnical officers and assistants will be necessary, together with ancillarytechnical staff plus an addition of 150-200 on fundamental research anddevelopment. It must be emphasised, however, that the &apos; scientific andtechnical staffs needs of civil aviation, important as they are, cannot be looked at in isolation.&quot;With regard to this vital matter of staff reinforcement, it is clear that wemust, if possible, put British civil aviation in a secure position and I can onlysay that this subject should be one of immediate and constant consultation between the Treasury and the Departments concerned.11. In the early stages of our discussions a Press Conference had beensuggested but it was evident that this might place the recent order for AmericanStrato-Cruisers in an unduly high light and that the right course to pursue wouldbe to place the whole picture together with a statement of the large ordersdesigned to foster British industry and I agree that subject to your approvalultimately a communique should be drawn up to be agreed between the two departments and the Treasury.2Qth August, 1946.APPENDIX I.Inter-Departmental Civil Aircraft Requirements Committee.1.   The composition of the Committee is as follows : Ministry of Civil Aviation Sir Henry Self (Permanent Secretary) Chairman.Air Vice-Marshal A. C. Collier (D.G.T.S.).Mr. R. H. Walmsley (D.A.R.).Ministry of Supply mr. F. C. Musgrave, U.S. (Air).Mr. S. Scott-Hall (P.D.T.D.).British Overseas Airways Corporation Lord Knollys (Chairman).British European Airways Mr. G. d&apos;Erlanger (Chief Executive).British South A merican A irtvays Air Vice-Marshal D. C. T. Bennett (Managing Director).2.   The terms of reference of the Committee are : &apos;(a) To review the present programme of design and construction of civil aircraft and the progress achieved to date.(b) To compare the position with that obtaining in other countries,notably in the United States, and to prepare recommendations onthe types of civil aircraft which should be developed in readiness for future use.(c) To prepare statements of civil aircraft requirements, together with a forecast giving the approximate number of each type of aircraftlikely to be required.
APPENDIX II.Orders which it is Proposed to Place as Soon as Necessary to Ensure theEarliest Possible Production.No. to be ordered.	Type.	Required for.	Cost per aircraft.	Cost (Total).1 75 25 50 14 50 25 27	Brabazon I (Bristol 167) . (See para. 26 (&amp;))* Bbabazon IIb Vickers V.C.2 version ^See para. 25 (d))* Brabazon IIb Armstrong-Whitworth version (See para. 25 (e))* Brabazon III A. V. Roe ver-sion (See para. 26 (c))* Brabazon IV (D.H. 106) (See para. 26 (a))* Brabazon Va (Marathon Mk. II (Mamba engines)) (See para. 25 (g))* Hermes ... (See para. 25 (&amp;))* concordia (See para. 25 (/))*	North Atlantic route (1 ad-ditional aircraft to ensure regularity of service) Replacement for Vickers Viking, for use by B.E.A on medium stage European ser-vices Primarily intended for over-seas markets.   Also provides a valuable alternative to the V.C.2 Intended primarily for Aus-Australian and African routes to replace Tudor II. Firm requirement for 50 received from B.O.A.C. A further requirement from B.S.A.A. is probable North and South Atlantic and Empire routes Medium Stage European ser-vices and for export market For use by B.O.A.C. on Empire routes in case Tudor II should prove unsatisfactory thereon. Otherwise it will be available for export Feeder line work with B.E.A. and foreign operators	  900,000 60,000 84,000 180,000 275,000 40,000 80,000 20,000	900,000 4,500,000 2,100,000 9,000,000. 3,850,000 2,000,000 2,000,000 540,000Total 267			Total ... 24,890,000	* References are to CP. (46) 317.



</content>
</cab>
