<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/12/0 images: 482-485</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1946.SECRET. Copy No.     6 3CP. (46) 349.Vdth September, 1946.CABINET.PENSIONS AND ALLOWANCES OF PERSONNEL OF COLONIALORIGIN ENLISTED IN EGYPT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.CONSIDERABLE discontent has been aroused amongst British subjects of colonial origin (Maltese, Cypriots and Palestinians) conscripted in Egypt duringthe war as the result of the regulations whereby both their family and dependents&apos;allowances and their service pensions are calculated at two-thirds of the ratespayable in the case of British subjects of United Kingdom origin. The questionof family allowances lapsed with the close of hostilities, but the whole matterraises the issue of racial discrimination within the British Commonwealth andshould, in my view, be considered by the Cabinet, As will be seen from the notereproduced below, the matter is very difficult and controversial, but I recommendthat a ruling be given that all personnel enlisted into His Majesty&apos;s Forces inEgypt, irrespective of their origin, are entitled to full United Kingdom ratesof pension.I am advised that as at the 31st May, 1946, 1,026 disability pensions werebeing paid to officers and men- enlisted in Egypt at a total difference in cost of 57 a week as compared with United Kingdom rates; while 307 widows of officersand other ranks were being paid pensions at a total difference in cost of  25a week as compared with United Kingdom rates.E. B.Foreign Office, S.W.1,19th September, 1946.Note.In April 1943 His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Cairo drew the attention ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government to the discontent aroused among Maltese, Cypriotsand Palestinians called up for National service with the British Military forces by the inadequacy of their family and dependents&apos; allowances, which were paid at a rate of two-thirds of that paid to Anglo-Saxons. In a note preparedby the Financial Counsellor to the Embassy reviewing the whole subject ofthe pay and allowances of soldiers in the British Army enlisted in Egypt, anew scale of rates was proposed, under which it was suggested that the Maltese,Cypriots, &amp;c,, should receive the same allowances as Anglo-Saxons. these representations were supported in a memorandum prepared by the chairmen of three man-power boards in Egypt, and in a joint memorandum by the central council of the Maltese Communities in Egypt and the British community councils of Alexandria and Port Said.2. The question was referred to the Treasury, who mentioned that the ratesin most cases corresponded to the present standard of living of such families inEgypt, and that to grant these families the same standard rates as those payable to Anglo-Saxon families might well have repercussions on the rates payable tolocal entrants in Palestine, Malta and other Mediterranean stations.3. Lordl Killearn, when informed of1 this, pointed out that those whoenlisted in Malta, Cyprus and Palestine did so voluntarily, whereas in EgyptBritish subjects were called up under the National Service (Egypt) Order-in-Council of 1942.   He explained, moreover, that, while the lowest cost of living13561   [32410]
in countries such as Malta might justify lower rates in those countries, in Egyptthe cost of living was much higher even than that in the United Kingdom. he therefore denied that the equalising of the rates in Egypt need create a precedent for so doing in countries with a low cost of living. (The Governor of Malta held the opinion that to raise the rates for Maltese stationed in Egypt would not leadto any demand by Maltese stationed in Malta for a similar concession.) LordKillearn maintained that, unless such discrimination were removed, a deep-seated sense of grievance and unfair treatment would remain.4. This view was supported by the Colonial Office, who, although they stated that they were not directly interested in Colonials making their homesin Egypt, explained that, while it might be true that Maltese and Cypriots wereaccustomed to a lower standard of living than Anglo-Saxons, in this country, too,the standard of life of different classes of the community differed, yet no one would dream of suggesting differential rates of family allowances for servingmen on that ground. It was therefore both politically unwise and practicallyunjust to db so in Egypt. They pointed out, too, that in the West Indies theWar Office had decided that it was not possible to make any differentiation in family allowances to take account of the varying standards of living amongdifferent strata of society.5. The War Office, however, were unable to agree that this situation should form a precedent for Egypt. They pointed out that a Maltese family in Egypt(as in Malta) had a distinctly lower standard of living than an Anglo-Saxonfamily, and that it was only in England or in barracks with other families(both Anglo-Saxon and Maltese) of a British unit that a Maltese family wouldbe expected to conform to the standard of living of the Anglo-Saxon family.In these circumstances both Maltese and Anglo-Saxons would be paid at thesame rate. They explained that a similar difference of pay as between Anglo-Saxon and Maltese existed in the Egyptian Police Force. In the West Indiesuniformity was necessary because of the difficulty of classifying for the purposeof allowances, as obviously either &quot; white &quot; or &quot; coloured,&quot; the various shadesproduced by inter-marriage in the colonies; but such uniformity was only obtained by paying all West Indian troops at the lower rate, to the disadvantage of thewhite families involved, who were fortunately few. On the other hand the samedifficulty was not encountered in Egypt where a clear line could be drawn betweenthe standard of living maintained by Maltese and Cypriot families and thatmaintained by Anglo-Saxons. - The War Office felt, like the Treasury, that if the changes advocated by Lord Killearn were adopted the relatively minor question&quot;in Egypt might well start them off on a very slippery slope.&quot;6. The question of pensions for persons enlisted in Egypt under the NationalService Order-in-Council of 1942 was first raised by His Majesty&apos;s ambassador in Cairo in April 1945. Lord Killearn explained that locally enlisted personnel,though serving in and as ordinary members of the British Forces in Egypt, andnot in particular territorial units of a British Colony, were not entitled! as of right to full pension rights and that this position was clearly unjust and unacceptable and constituted pronounced and unfair discrimination. Thequestion was reviewed by the Army Council in the light of these representations.They considered that the present basis should be maintained and that it wouldnot be justifiable to give preferential treatment to enlistments in Egypt. Thereexisted, however, a special provision by which the Council might obtain authorityto give awards, in suitable individual cases, at more than the two-thirds ratesubject to a maximum of full British rates. The Council also considered anarrangement under which appeals against refusal of pension by the council might be submitted for the opinion of an independent local referee, on the under-standing that his decision would be honoured by the Council (arrangements for putting this into effect are in train). In fixing pension levels basically at two-thirds of those payable in the case of Anglo-Saxons, the Army Council explainedthat not only differences in the cost of living but also differences in the standardof living in the countries concerned were taken into consideration.7. Meanwhile Lord Killearn remained unconvinced by the War Officearguments (with which the Admiralty associated itself) both on the subject ofpensions and on that of allowances. In his view the case of Egypt was quiteseparate from that of the other Mediterranean countries and the &quot; wider issues,&quot;envisaged by the Service Departments and the Treasury, were not involved.8.   Both questions remain a source of very real grievance in Egypt to-day.



</content>
</cab>
