<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/97/0 images: 18-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
rt^IJS/D^GSiiiiENT IS THE PROPERTY 0F&apos;HER. BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)C.(59) 55 COPY NO.  S\1 16th March, 1959 u     -CABINETPENSIONS (INCREASE) bill memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer have now given further thought to the possibility of early legislation to increase the pensions (including widows&apos; pensions) of retired public servants - civil servants, teachers, police, firemen.National Health Service employees, etc.   Retired members of the armed Forces would be covered by corresponding PrerogativeInstruments.   The Act would not apply to the nationalised industries:whether their pensioners should receive increases is primarily forthe Boards concerned, subject to Ministerial approval.   There would no doubt be pressure for them to follow suit.Should there be a Pensions (Increase) Bill?2.      Since the Pensions (Increase) Act, 1956, took effect on1st April, 1956, the cost of living has risen by only about 7 per cent,and on the policy followed by successive Governments over many yearsthat is not sufficient to justify fresh legislation.   Each Pensions(Increase) Act has been assumed to have dealt adequately, or asadequately as possible, with the situation up to its passing, nothing morebeing justified unless .and until there has been a subsequent furthersevere fall in the value of money.   But I am impressed by the fact that,under the 1956 Act, of those on smaller pensions no one who retired after31st March, 1952 got the full increase of 10 per cent; and since march, 1952 the cost of living has risen by 27 per cent.   Of those who retired on salaries of  1,500   or more, only those who had retiredbefore the end of 1947 got the increase;  and since the end of 1947 thecost of-living has risen considerably more.    Retired public servantsfeel strongly about the extent to which the real value of their pensionshas been eroded by inflation and several well organised campaignsare under way.   The Public Service Pensioners1   Council, for example,which claims to represent half a million of them, is bringing pressure to bear on all Members of Parliament.   There are also specific campaignson behalf of the oldest retired teachers, retired policemen, and so on.3.      I have come to the conclusion that the strict merits of theposition tend increasingly to favour some further assistance forretired public servants, and that it would be unwise to ignore thisgrowing pressure.   Provided that my colleagues agree that we can doso without making any concessions in other directions, except the onealready proposed by the Minister of Pensions and National Insurance inrespect of war widows at a cost of  1. 6 millions (to which I am preparedto agree), and are satisfied that we can, otherwise, hold the front on national Insurance and National Assistance benefits and on war pensions,I should be prepared to introduce a Pensions (Increase) Bill this sessionwith the object of obtaining the Royal Assent by the end of July.
4*     I understand^hai.such aBillwould have to be introduced before(the&quot; Whitsun recess,thai-.&apos;ls&apos;J;iibt.later.than, the week beginning 11th May.This gives far less&apos;tirn&apos;iev!fprv\its.pre^ratioh.ihan-has ever been allowed-inl-the past for one of these.confiplex and controversial measures.   &quot;We&apos; must therefore aim at - and&apos;persuade all interested parties to accept- -as simple a measiire as the subject will allow.A scheme for civil pensioners v5.     The doctrine underlying public service pensions is that theyare related to length of service and pay at the end of service; and once awarded are not normally varied thereafter.   But when therehave been severe falls in money values special increases are given,by the Government, as by other good employers, to relieve the worsthardship, particularly among those with the smallest pensions.   The1956 Act, like its predecessors, was based on this philosophy.   Itsdistinguishing features were that it did away with means tests and forthe first time brought the bigger pensions within the scope of the increases.    I am sure that we should not and cannot attempt anyreconsideration of basic principles and must resist in particular allpleas that old pensions should, as a matter of principle, be brought up to the level of current ones.   But I am also sure that we should not-go back on the more liberal approach of the 1956 Act.   That is, weshould not reimpose means tests and we should cater for the biggerpensions as well as the smaller.6. I propose that we should have a scheme the backbone ofwhich would be the following percentage increases applied to the totalpensions now in payment, including increases under earlier Acts:PercentageFor retirements before 1st April, 1952 12&quot;           11               in          1952-3 10&quot;          &quot;              in         1953-4 8&quot;          &quot;              in         1954-5 6&quot;          &quot;              in         1955-6 4&quot;          &quot;              in         1956-7 2About 400,000 pensioners (apart-, from Forces pensioners) would benefit.The only ones who would not would be those who have retired since 1st April, 1957.7.      The percentage increases would be applied to the total pensionsnow in payment, including any increases granted under earlier Acts.This would be&apos;a new departure:  under earlier Acts the percentage increases have applied to the basic pension, that is the pension as originally awarded.There are advantages in abandoning this and working on the pensionactually in payment.   To do so strikes me as reasonable in itself;and certainly it is likely to appear eminently reasonable to the pensioner who already has increases and who inevitably sees his pensionas a whole.   It also makes for ease of calculation by the payingauthorities and so speeds up the working out of the increases and gettingthem into payment.   But, most importantly, it has the effect of boostingthe increases for the older pensioners relatively to those for the newerones.   The effect is clear in the annexed table.   It will be seen, forexample, that the increase proposed for a postman who retired in 1939represents one of 21 per cent on the basic pension - as compared withthe 4 per cent increase on basic (and total) pension of the postman
,/SECRET13who retired in 1955-56;: &apos;Thls is as it should be; and there areadvantages in achieving it without specifically providing in thelegislation for increases of this sizie.8.     My colleagues will note that I do not propose repeating thediscrimination in the 1956 Act against those retiring on salaries ofover  1,300 a year.   There was then a cut-off date for them someyears erlier than for their colleagues who retired on lower salaries.This was all very well in 1956, when, for the first time, we were taking the revolutionary step&quot; of bringing in the higher pensioner at all.But it is now, I think, generally accepted that it is right that theyshould benefit and I see no justification for any discrimination asregards the date of retirement.   Neither am I proposing that thereshould be a ceiling to the amount of increase payable as there is inthe 1956 Act.   I deal with this more fully in a later paragraph.9.      This part of the scheme is designed for the services wherepensions are related to pay, so that pension levels have risen continuallyas pay has risen.   These cover the vast majority of cases; butthere are a few civilian pensions, such as those of Colonial Governors,Indian civil servants and some members of the Judiciary, which are fixed (or have in the past been fixed) so that the levels change only atlong intervals.   For these pensions which are at flat rates the mainscheme will need to be modified, probably.by regulations under the Act.A scheme for the Armed Forces10.    Retired members of the Armed Forces (includingwidows who are eligible for pension) are invariably granted pensionincreases at the same time as the civilians and, as nearly as may-be, of the same order.   But Forces pensions resemble the civilpensions referred to in the previous paragraph which remain at thesame level for long periods.   They do not vary when pay is changed, butare fixed according to the Pension Code in force at the date of retirement.   Thus, for example, an officer retiring from the armed forces in 1955 received retired pay on the 1950 Pension Code (withthe benefit, if he is over 60, of the 1956 pensions increase), whereasan officer retiring in 1956 received retired pay on the 1956 Code.In these circumstances I think that the right principle to followis to increase pensions payable under each of the Forces Codes by theamount -which a civilian pensioner will receive if he retired on thedate on which the Code in question took effect.   This seems the moststraightforward way of applying the new measure to the Armed Forces andwill give them benefits as good as or better than their civiliancounterparts.   I propose that officials of the Treasury and the service departments should work out details of a scheme on this basis.   About110,000 Forces pensioners, including existing widows, will benefit.Should there be a maximum increase?11.     In theory my plan could produce extreme cases (for example,a Permanent Secretary, retiring before 1952 with 40 years&apos; service) of increases of as much as  250.   But in practice anything more than 200 would be very rare.   Under the 1956 Act there was a maximum of  100 for new increase; but, in addition, increases arising fromthe removal of restrictions under the earlier Acts could produce a further  86.   The practical effect would therefore be much the same.-3-
Nevertheless I have considered whether we should impose a maximumagain this time, for the point may have political significance.   Thedifficultyis that if it were put at more than  100 it would look highto the majority of pensioners while penalising the more senior officers.Moreover, we must bear in mind that higher salaries for senior civil servants under the Coleraine recommendations will leave thosewho retired from corresponding posts several years ago with pensionsfar below the new level,   in this situation it seems to me that theright course is not to have a maximum.Minimum age for increases12.    t propose that we should maintain the principle that pensions increase is not normally payable before age 60, notwithstanding that under some schemes, such as those for police, firemen, and of coarse,for the Armed Forces, the pension itself may be payable at an earlierage.   To abandon this limitation would go a long way towards under-mining the hardship philosophy which we must maintain.   It would alsoadd several millions to the cost of the scheme;  and the taxpayerought not to be asked to foot a bill for increasing the pensions of people of working age who can get jobs at current rates of pay.Financial effects of the scheme13.     Under the scheme I have outlined a postman who retired in1939 after 40 years&apos; service on a pension of  98 (increased underearlier Acts to  173) will aie^fhave it brought up to  194.   A maleteacher who retired in the same year with the same length of service on a pension of  181 (already increased to  280) will now get  314.The effect in a number of other typical cases drawn from the mainpublic services is shown, in simple tabular form, in the Annex to this paper.   The total cost would be about  10y millions in the first twelvemonths, decreasing as time went on.   About 75 per cent of this would bea charge on the Exchequer;  the rest would fall - and remain - on therates.Some comments14.    The simple scheme I propose would relieve the worst hardshipand reduce the worst disparities, but it would perpetuate and evenaccentuate many of the smaller anomalies which result from the varyingpay histories of different public services and the varying incidence of previous Pensions (Increase) Acts.   Moreover the picture variesfrom service to service.   For instance, there might be room for larger increases for teachers and police who retired before 1946without raising the pre-1946 pensioners well above the later pensioners.But there would be no room for such increases for large sectionsof the Civil Service and local government staff, particularly whereservice has been short; nor for the Armed Forces.   These differencesare inevitable in any simple scheme for general application andquick effect, but they may lead to complaints and demands for moreequitable treatment.    These could not be met   (any more than waspossible in earlier Acts) without going for a fair more complicatedscheme and, hence, a far more complicated Bill than we have timeto prepare or to get through.-4-SECRET
15.    There would be criticism too from those who say that theright course is to bring all old pensions up to the level of those beingawarded today.   The Public Service Pensioners1 Council urge this in the letter which they have sent to all M. P. s., and they made thepoint when the Financial Secretary to the Treasury received adeputation recently.   The main objections to such a course are that:-(i )  it would involve a fundamental change in the&quot; principles on which public service pensiotsare based;(ii) it would be far more expensive, both immediately and in future, than what I propose in this paper; and(iii) it would have the effect of automatically insulatingpublic servants - as distinct from, and partlyat the expense of, all others on small fixedincomes - from the effects of inflation.Announcement and Consultations16.    Although pressure for a new measure (including pressure from our own supporters) is considerable, it is not as yet unmanageable.I therefore propose that our intention to introduce a Bill should be announced in my Budget Speech on 7th April.   We shall then getrepresentations from interested bodies on what should go in the bill and we shall be obliged to consult the Local Authority Associations,for part of the cost of the hew measure will fall on local authorities.My colleagues will remember that, even with the less exacting time-table for the preparation of the 1956 Bill, we were only able to giveLocal Authority Associations short notice of our proposals, and thatthis gave rise to complaints.   There may well be difficulty in carryingout more extended consultations with them this time.   We must thereforebe as sure as we can be that the scheme outlined above would not produce special difficulties for them.17.    I know that the scheme I have outlined is not perf   . and itwill not please everyone.   But it will give relief where relief is most needed - and give it quickly because it will be simple to administer. I am afraid that the Bill itself is bound to be complicatedbecause of the labyrinth of statutes to which it applies.   Neverthelessif it is confined to essentials it should not be unmanageable.Conclusion18.    I ask my colleagues to agree that a pensions increase measurecan be undertaken without offering any concessions on the existing level of National Insurance and National Assistance   benefits and war pensions, other than those to war widows already proposedby the Minister of Pensions.   If this is approved, I will arrange forthe   preparation by the Treasury, in consultation with other departments responsible for both civil and Armed Forces pensioners, of a Billproviding     for pensions increase on the lines set out inparagraphs 5- 13 above.   I will, of course, lay before them at theearliest possible moment a draft of the Bill for further consideration-5-
1515.     There would be criticism too from those who say that theright course is to bring all old pensions up to the level of those beingawarded today.   The Public Service Pensioners&apos; Council urge this in the letter which they have sent to all M. P. s. ,  and they made thepoint when the Financial Secretary to the Treasury received adeputation recently.   The main objections to such a course are that:-(i) it would involve a fundamental change in the principles on which public service pensioisare based;(ii) it would be far more expensive, both immediately and in future, than what I propose in this paper; and(iii) it would have the effect of automatically insulatingpublic servants - as distinct from, and partlyat the expense of, all others on small fixedincomes - from the effects of inflation.Announcement and Consultations16.    Although pressure for a new measure (including pressure from our own supporters) is considerable, it is not as yet unmanageable.I therefore propose that our intention to introduce a Bill should be announced in my Budget Speech on 7th April.   We shall then getrepresentations from interested bodies on what should go in the bill and we shall be obliged to consult the Local Authority Associations,for part of the cost of the new measure will fall on local authorities.My colleagues will remember that, even with the less exacting time-table for the preparation of the 1956 Bill, we were only able to giveLocal Authority Associations short notice of our proposals, and thatthis gave rise to complaints.   There may well be difficulty in carryingout more extended consultations with them this time.   We must thereforebe as sure as we can be that the scheme outlined above would not produce special difficulties for them.17.    I know that the scheme I have outlined is not perf   . and itwill not please everyone.   3ut it will give relief where relief is most needed - and give it quickly because it will be simple to administer. I am afraid that the Bill itself is bound to be complicatedbecause of the labyrinth of statutes to which it applies.   Neverthelessif it is confined to essentials it should not be unmanageable.Conclusion18.     I ask my colleagues to agree that a pensions increase measurecan be undertaken without offering any concessions on the existing level of National Insurance and National Assistance   benefits and war pensions, other than those to war widows already proposedby the Minister of Pensions.   If this is approved, I will arrange forthe   preparation by the Treasury, in consultation with other departments responsible for both civil and Armed Forces pensioners, of a Billproviding     for pensions increase on the lines set out inparagraphs 5- 13 above.   I will, of course, lay before them at theearliest possible moment a draft of the Bill for further consideration-5-SEGRET
of its content, but I must emphasise that if the time-table beforeus is to be met it will not be possible to depart significantly fromdecisions which we take now on the main features of the scheme.D.H.A.Treasury Chambers, S.W.I.16th March, 1959-6-SEGRET
ishnexExamples ef original,, present and proposed pensions after a full career in the, civil service, i local government.teaching and the policeTear of		retirement .	1939	1944	1 1948	1952		1956	1 1958Civil Service (40 years) (&amp;) Original pension Postman                    (b) Present pension (c) Proposed pension			98 173 194	118 175 196	151 188 211	177 189 208	23C	) 230 235	269 26^ 269Glerical Officer	\S) Original pension b) Present pension &apos;c) Proposed pension		175 271 304	1 92 273 307	219 267 299	252 269 296	31&apos;	311 317	360 360 360Higher Executive Officer                     (	&apos;a) Original pension ,b) Present pension [c) Proposed pension		323 441 494	337 445 498	384 449 503	.    433 462 508	544 544 555		623 623 623Assistant Secretary                 ^		Original pension Present pension Proposed pension	750 926 1,037	752 926 1,037	850 927 1,038	1,017 1,017 1 ,119	1,175 1,175 1,198		1,334 1,334 1,334Local G-overnment (40 years) (Pensions based on 40/60ths) General                     / \ n .   .    -,      w . -.  .   .                       (a) Original pension Division                    );(             . /       tt* 1                  (b) Present pension (now Higher             r S r,         a i        ^01.   .   .    \    (c) Proposed pension G-eneral Division;                -         r			173 268 300	190 280 314	227 295 331	263 284 312	31;	311 317	335 335 335Administrative Professional and     (a) Original pension Technical Grade (v) (Subsequently          (b) Present pension A.P.T. III, now A.P.T.II)                 (c) Proposed pension			300 416 466	435 487	352 432 484	393 424 466	45*	? 459 468	509 509 509Highest A.P.T. Grade	1 a. fb V o,	Original pension Present pension Proposed pension				659 71 2 783	715	719 733	793 793 793Teaching (40 years) Man, qualified        M Original penslon teacher                    )     Present pension (c) Proposed pension			181 280 314	185 283 317	244 313 350	287 313 344	34!	345 353	418 418 418Police (30 years) Constable	(a) Original pension (b) Present pension kc) Proposed pension		165 258 289	165 258 289	243 293 328	290 325 358	36i	) 369 376	422 422 422s.30-59SECEET

</content>
</cab>
