<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/97/0 images: 128-129</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;5 GOVERNMENT)C,(59) 72 COPY NO^23rd April, 1959CABINETINDUS waters memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Commonwealth relations the Indus waters dispute has been one of the two major irritantsto Indo-Pakistan relations which have resulted in disproportionateexpenditure on arms by both countries and at times to a threat of war between them.   Direct negotiations following Partition in 1947 wereabortive and since 1951 the International Bank for Reconstruction andDevelopment has been trying without success to secure a settlement.The Bank has now decided that, as a last resort, it must put forward itsown compromise plan for a solution of the problem on a &quot;take it or leave it&quot; basis, making it clear that if the plan is not accepted by both parties the Bank will withdraw its good offices.2. The Bank&apos;s plan will be communicated to the Indian and 1 akistanGovernments by the President of the Bank, Mr. Eugene Black, duringvisits to Delhi and Karachi beginning on 10th May.   In the meantime theBank has given the outline of the plan confidentially to the United States,Canada, Australia and the United Kingdom and has asked whether it canbe assured, before Mr. Black presents the plan to the Indians and thePakistanis, that these countries would be willing to find certain foreign exchange contributions suggested by the Bank.3. The total cost of the Bank&apos;s plan, at present costs, but with an element for contingencies, is 0985 millions.   Of this the United Kingdom,Canada and Australia, are between them asked to contribute 070 millions( 25 millions) in grants to Pakistan over the next ten to twelve years.This contribution is small in comparison with the sums to be contributed by the United States and the Bank and would be a price well worth paying for a settlement of this issue, even though for us to make grants to anindependent Commonwealth Government would create a precedent and costs during the progress of the plan are likely to rise and our eventualcommitment may therefore be substantially higher than the figure whichthe Bank is asking.4. The Bank has not made any recommendation on the division ofthe  25 millions as between the United Kingdom, Canada and Australiabut it would seem reasonable for the United Kingdom to contribute60 per cent, Canada 24 per cent and Australia 16 per cent (i. e.  15 millions, 6 millions and  4 millions respectively).SECRET
5.        A decision on a United Kingdom commitment is extremely urgentsince Mr. Black arrives in London on 4th May and it would be desirablebefore that date to secure agreement with Australia and Canada on the size of their contributions.   The Australian Prime Minister leaves Australiaon 28th April and it is most desirable to secure his personal support.We also intend to ask New Zealand to make a small contribution.6.         The Bank&apos;s plan is essentially a compromise one which will notbe entirely satisfactory to either India or Pakistan.   It is to be presented as a package and the Bank has not given us the full engineering details.They have, however, been advised by consultants in the United States,Canada and the United Kingdom and by a former British irrigationofficial, and their plan has been approved by General Wheeler, who is their chief engineering consultant.   There is, therefore, no reason tothink that a better plan could be devised which, given the historical andpolitical background, would stand any chance of acceptance.7.        If we and the other proposed contributors are not prepared tosupport the Bank&apos;s plan or if it is rejected by India or Pakistan, theconsequences will be extremely serious since India is committed to with&quot;draw waters at present available to Pakistan for her own new irrigationschemes in Rajasthan and if no provision for replacement is made a large part of the Pakistan Punjab will be starved of water supplies.    Pakistanhas made no secret of the fact that if necessary she would fight in such aneventuality.   Thus, if the Bank&apos;s plan is not accepted, we can anticipateat best a rapid and critical deterioration of Indo-Pakistan relations andprobably, as a result of the inevitable recourse to the United NationsSecurity Council, a major weakening in relations between the West andIndia.   On the other hand a settlement should go a long way towardscreating a new atmosphere between the two countries in which some ofthe other but less vital problems (such as refugees and arms supplies)might likewise be solved.   The reduced tension between the two countries should alsD take some of the heat out of the Kashmir   dispute.8. I have consulted the Chancellor of the Exchequer on this matterand we are agreed in recommending to our colleagues that the UnitedKingdom should agree to contribute  15 millions in grants over the next ten to twelve years provided that India and Pakistan accept the plan and provided also that Canada and Australia are willing to make contributions of the order of  6 millions and  4 millions respectively.H.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W.I.22nd April, 1959SECRET

</content>
</cab>
