<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/97/0 images: 141-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1959C. (59) 75 Copy No.   g 928th April, 1959CABINETCOMMONWEALTH EDUCATION conference memorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth RelationsIt has not been possible to reach agreement in the Committee on commonwealth Education Conference, of which I am Chairman, on the extentof the assistance in education which the United Kingdom might offer at theConference as part of a combined Commonwealth effort in education. It is nowbecoming urgent to determine the extent of the United Kingdom contribution,since much of the essential planning is held up for want of a decision.2. The majority of my Committee have accepted the recommendation ofthe Official Committee (with the Treasury reserving their position) that a programme of educational assistance to the Commonwealth, costing  7 millions over five years, is the least that the United Kingdom could offer in keeping withthe philosophy of Montreal. Such a programme would result in a continuingannual expenditure by the United Kingdom of about  If millions (of whichi\ million would be the cost of the Scholarship Scheme, to which we are committedanyway).3. The Chancellor of the Exchequer, however, does not feel able to agreeto expenditure of more than  5 millions over five years, leading to a continuingannual expenditure of  1-3 millions. What these two programmes involve isshown in Annex A to this paper.4.   The Chancellor^ reasons are (i) The United Kingdom Government is already spending substantial sumson this kind of activity through the Colonial, Development and welfare Fund and a variety of bilateral and multilateral schemes, our contributions to which have been rising steadily in the last year ortwo. Moreover, there are other potential commitments developingon this front, e.g., technical assistance for Nigeria, where the colonial secretary is asking for  1 million a year.(ii) There are objections in principle to singling out one particular subject in this way and giving it special financial treatment. This could be the start of a from the Treasury point of view-dangerous process whichmight undermine the hitherto generally accepted methods of handlingthese matters.(iii) The Chancellor suggests that education should be looked at in relationto the general needs and the economic and social planning of particularterritories. If this approach is not adopted there seems perhaps a danger in his view, first, of political trouble (he has drawn attention towhat the Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said in the LordsDebate on Nyasaland on 24th March reproduced in Annex B to this paper) and, second, of financial trouble in that the poorer territoriesmay not be able to finance the recurrent costs of greatly expandededucational schemes without damage to other services, perhaps no less important.55114
Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,27th April, 1959.5. The Chancellor is however prepared to go up to  6 millions if canada and Australia together would agree to put up  4 millions. My Committee has considered the possibility of making the United Kingdom contribution dependenton a matching contribution from the rest of the Commonwealth and has rejectedit as impracticable. I doubt very much whether the Canadian and australian government would be able to commit themselves in advance of the conference to a particular figure, since their preparatory work is far less advanced than ourown, still less to one which would be out of proportion to that offered by theUnited Kingdom: they would be being asked, although their joint population isonly half that of the United Kingdom, with much less in the way of university,technological and teacher-training facilities available in their territories, to guarantee expenditure at two-thirds the level of the United Kingdom. There isthe. further consideration that part of the additional funds which are now being sought will finance projects mainly of value to the dependent territories of theUnited Kingdom. I think it is reasonable to hope that Canada, Australia andothers will contribute together about  3 millions, which would give us a total forthe Conference of  10 millions or more. But I believe that a generous unilateraloffer by the United Kingdom is far more likely to provoke a generous response from all the other Commonwealth Governments than a process of bargaining.6. The difference between the majority of my Committee and the Chancelloris relatively small indeed, considering the task, even a  7 millions programme is thought by some of us to be over modest. But in my opinion there is, as amatter of presentation, all the difference between a figure of  10 millions anda figure of  8 millions to  9 millions although the Chancellor does not attachsignificance to this. I must remind my colleagues that we are convening this conference in fulfilment of our programme at Montreal. At that conference the discussion of education problems which we initiated played a big part andI think that some of the under-developed countries and the Colonies regarded itas the most important part of the Conference. All Commonwealth Ministersrecognised that a far greater effort in education is needed if the countries inthe free world are to hold their own, and Ministers representing the less developed countries made no secret of the tremendous gaps in their educational systems.I think we all came away conscious that we had somehow to achieve a new spirit and drive if the Commonwealth and particularly the newer and emergent members is to develop its resources as fast and as fully as it should. The United kingdom is quite naturally the leader in all this. Educationally, we are far ahead of anyother member of the Commonwealth and, as I see it, we have a responsibility notonly to assist the less developed countries but by our example to stimulate allthe other Commonwealth countries into making a determined effort in education.I am quite certain it is in our own interest to do this. Certainly, if we fail to help,some parts of the Commonwealth will look elsewhere for assistance. I therefore ask for the support of my colleagues for the  7 millions programme.H.
m.. CONFIDENTIAL 3BpANNEX AIt is proposed that the United Kingdom Government should offer educationalassistance in the following ways:  (i) The United Kingdom Government is committed to finding half the totalnumber (i.e., 1,000) of scholarships awarded under the scholarshipscheme. For planning purposes it is estimated that the average tenure of these would be two years. The number to be granted each year would therefore be 250.(ii) By supplementing the emoluments of scholarships offered by some of thenewer Commonwealth countries and the Colonies which may not be high enough to attract the United Kingdom student and which might otherwise remain unfilled.(iii) By subsidising Commonwealth teachers on teacher training courses toenable students from some of the poorer Commonwealth countries totake advantage of the extra capacity offered.(iv) To increase the supply of teachers for service overseas by subsidisingcertain key posts in the Commonwealth and making a resettlement grantwhen the teacher returns to this country.Some of these schemes would not be in full operation until 1962, or later. Thefollowing tables show the extent of the assistance that could be offered under theabove headings, at a cost of (a)  7 millions for 5 years; (b)  5 millions for 5 years Annual Costwhen scheme in Full Operation(a)  7 Millions Programme  Scholarship Scheme: 250 awards to be made each year 500,000Supplementing emoluments of scholarships offered byother countries       ............      ... 50,000Subsidy for 500 teachers at teacher training institutions , 300,000Measures to provide 500 teachers for service in Com-commonwealth posts............... 800,0001,650,000(b)  5 Millions ProgrammeScholarship Scheme: 250 awards to be made each year 500,000Supplementing emoluments of scholarships offered byother countries      .........      ...      ... 50,000Subsidy for about 350 teachers at teacher traininginstitutions    .................. 200,000Measures to provide about 350 teachers for service in commonwealth posts       ............. 550,0001,300,000ANNEX extract from House of Lords Official Report for 24th March, 1959The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs (The Earl of Perth)The second reason for the widespread backing of Congress is, I think, thatquite a few of the young who have been educated, not to top but none the less to reasonable standards, are extremely ambitious. They had the feeling that here was a chance for them if they supported Congress -that very soon they were goingto find jobs at the top; that is what they were after. The third reason was undoubtedly the fear of federation. That, I believe, was the widest fear, and i will come back to it, if I may, in a moment.

</content>
</cab>
