<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/97/0 images: 144-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y*S GOVERNMENT)C.(59) 76 COPY NO. fcj30th April, 1959CABINETSPACE RESEARCHMemorandum by the Minister of defence i have not had long enough to study fully the Lord presidents memorandum (C.(59) 73) on the important subject of space research.However, my first impression is that it does not go far enough.2.   We are moving into a vast and wholly uncharted new sphere of scientific exploration.   We can, as yet, have no clear conception aboutthe new possibilities, which will unfold   themselves in the next decade.But it is quite certain that, unless we undertake a worthwhile programmeof work in space research, we shall risk losing our position as a leadingscientific nation in this new field, and many of our most able youngscientists will be tempted to move over to America.3.   We must, of course, make the most of the offer of the UnitedStates to carry foreign instruments in American satellites.   But weshould not count on receiving these facilities on an adequate scale, moreespecially since the Americans will have to make them available to anumber of other countries as well.4.   The satellite and. the rocket which launches it constitute thelaboratory for space research.   We must therefore face up to the factthat, if we intend to do serious work in this field, we shall have toprovide ourselves with the basic facilities needed.   It would be hopelessto rely entirely upon occasional free rides in American satellites.5.   I have no doubt that in due course space research will yieldimportant fruits in the commercial field;  but it is no good imaginingthat the Americans will be prepared indefinitely to see us use Americanrockets, paid for by the American taxpayer, in order to help british firms to compete with American industry.6.   On the defence side, the United States Government have begun toshow some willingness to examine with us the military implications of space research.   It is most important to obtain from the Americans asmuch information as possible about the results of their v/ork in this field but, as in the nuclear sphere, their willingness to impart to us the fruits of their research will largely depend upon our ability to give themsomething at least in return.7.   For these and other reasons, I am sure that if we decide to go infor space research we cannot make ourselves wholly dependent upon the americans to launch our satellites for us.-1-SECRET
8.   By our decision to proceed with the development of BLUE STREAKand BLACK KNIGHT, we are already providing ourselves with themain elements needed for a British satellite programme.   The cost ofadapting these projectiles and of carrying out the first five launchingsis estimated at between  10 millions and  2 0 millions, spread over five years.   My preliminary enquiries suggest that, after this preparatorystage, a worthwhile programme of space research could be maintained at a cost of between  10 millions and  15 millions a year.9.   The Government are today spending about  270 millions a year on military and civil research of various kinds.   Having regard to theas yet unpredictable scientific fruits which it may yield, it would seemto be no more than a wise precaution to invest  2millions to  4 millions a year over the next five years, so as to put ourselves in a position toundertake space research thereafter, should we then wish to do so.10.   The Lord President recommends that, before deciding to go ahead with these preparatory steps, we should examine further the scope andimplications of the American offer.   I agree that we should make themost of this offer;  but, for the reasons I have explained, I am sure thatwe must also put ourselves in a position to undertake a modestprogramme of independent British launchings.11.    If it is felt that this matter requires further study before adecision can be reached, then I would strongly urge that no public statement should be made for the time being.   An announcement on thelines proposed by the Lord President would be hotly criticised in many quarters as wholly inadequate;   and if, after further study, we should decide to do more,we would be represented as having changed our minds under pressure.12.   While this matter is being considered I hope that the Minister ofSupply will be authorised to go ahead with the paper studies for the adaptation of BLUE STREAK and BLACK KNIGHT for use as satellitelaunchers.13.   To sum up, I recommend:-(a) that the fullest advantage should be taken of the American offer to launch foreign satellites or to carry foreign instrumentsin American satellites;(b) that expenditure of  10 millions to  2 0 millions spread over five years, should be authorised to put Britain in a position toundertake a programme of satellite launchings thereafter, ifthis should then seem desirable;(c) that, if further study is required before a decision on (b) abovecan be taken:-(i)    no public statement should for the present be made;  and(ii)    the Minister of Supply should be authorised to put in handdesign studies for adapting BLUE STREAK and BLACKKNIGHT for satellite launching.D.S.Ministry of Defence, S.W.I.29th April, 1959

</content>
</cab>
