<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/97/0 images: 173-176</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
.   THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government-: :-Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1959The. circulation of. this paper has been strictly limited. &apos; It is issued for the personal ese of......................&apos;........J.................TOP SECRET Copy No.C. (59) 805th May, 1959CABINETRETIREMENT PENSIONS AND NATIONAL assistance memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department andLord Privy SealAgainst the background of the demand for an increase in retirement pensionsand the knowledge of the promises our opponents are making and will continueto make, the Ministerial Committee on Pensions have considered three possible courses of action (A) To do nothing.(B) To increase national assistance.(C) To increase retirement pensions (and other benefits).The second and third are each susceptible of several variations, which are discussedbelow.(A) To Do Nothing2.   If this is politically feasible, it would have the advantages that (i) It would avoid Exchequer expenditure for which no provision has beenmade in the current year, at a time when departmental forecasts forthe following year already show disquieting increases.(ii) It would avoid further demands on Parliamentary time, which wouldbe very difficult to meet.(iii) It would leave us more room for political manoeuvre at a later stage.I return.to this at the end.(B) To Increase National Assistance3. We have considered a plan prepared at our request by the Minister ofPensions, which would consist of the following elements (i) An increase in the scale rates from 45s. to 50s. for a single person and from 76s. to 85s. for a married couple.The real (as distinct from nominal) value of the current55147
rates has remained substantially unchanged since 1948and the increase could and would be presented as a real improvement in standards. They could be effected by regulations requiring affirmative resolution in bothHouses and, in a full year, might cost about ...      :..(ii) An increase in the amount of the various types of income(disability, occupational and other pensions, earnings,&amp;c.) which are already disregarded in the assessment of need. These disregards have remained unchangedsince 1948 and a 50 per cent, increase would approxi-mately restore, but not increase, their real value. Withthe exception of the earnings disregard, it wouldrequire a short Bill and, in a full year, would cost about(iii) A revision of the treatment of capital assets, possiblyinvolving elimination of the war savings disregard.Similar considerations, including the need for legisla-tion, apply as to (ii) above and the cost in a full yearmight be about   ...      ...      ............(iv) An increase in the amount of the contributions assumed to be made towards household expenses by self-supporting members of the household (a minority ofcases), together with offsetting increases to meet the rent in full where the allowance for rent is nowrestricted by reference to an out-of-date &quot; local rule &quot;fixed nine years ago. These adjustments could beeffected as in (i) above and in a full year would cost about       ......      ...      .............about . We have considered whether, in order to reduce the demands both on theExchequer and on Parliamentary time, this plan could be restricted to those partsof it which could be effected by regulations that is, an increase in the scale ratesand the earnings disregard and the adjustments referred to at 3 (iv) above (costing about  30 millions altogether) or even to the scale rates alone (costing about 27 millions). The parts of the plan which would require legislation would addabout  2 millions to the cost, and we are conscious that, even if the financial resolution were drawn tightly enough to preclude new disregards, there wouldbe Parliamentary pressure to extend the disregards further.5. We are doubtful whether, if the plan does not comprise all the disregardsmentioned, it is one with which we could be satisfied. It must be presented,if at all, not as a sop to public opinion but as a real improvement in standardsfor the poorest section of&quot; the community. Moreover, the National assistance board, under Sir Geoffrey Hutchinson, whose recommendation of new scale ratesis a prerequisite of the plan, are known to feel strongly that the time has cometo improve all those disregards described. So the situation is this: there is atruncated plan, without legislation, which is better than nothing, but it wouldin the view of the majority of the Committee be better to increase the scales andlegislate on the disregards.6. It might be possible to make the plan more attractive by changes in thenomenclature of national assistance, especially when granted to retirement pensioners! e.g., by reintroducing the term &quot; supplementary pension &quot; or bysome such administrative device. Some of us attach great importance to a development on these lines but there are, at the same time, serious arguments against it and the various possibilities are being further examined. Such changescould not in any event be applied for some time.(C) To increase the retirement pension7. The cost of increasing the retirement pension alone by 10s., with an appropriate increase for married couples, would be about  130 millions in the firstfull year.  This alone could be effected by amendment of the current National 27 millions 2 millions 1 million 2 millions 32 millions
insurance Bill. But we do not believe that we either could or should confine theincrease to retirement pensions. If it were extended to the other National insurance benefits (widows&apos;, sickness, unemployment, &amp;c.) and to industrial injury benefits the cost would be nearly  200 millions in the first full year, iising every year. Forthis a separate Bill would be required. Nor could we avoid in such circumstancesan increase in war pensions and an increase in national assistance (though the costof a 5s. increase in the latter would be offset by savings resulting from the increasedbenefits). The total cost would be not less than  210 millions in the first full year.8. The immediate cost of the Labour Party&apos;s proposal of a 10s. increasewithout any additional increase for married couples would be about  115 millionsif applied to retirement pensions only and of the order of  160 millions if appliedto all benefits.9. The cost of a 5s. increase would be half the amounts given in the two preceding paragraphs.10. In order to cover the increased expenditure contemplated in paragraph 7by increased contributions, the increases necessary in the first full year would beas follows Additional contributions required Employed man      Employer Exchequer(weekly (weekly (annual contribution)    contribution) cost)For retirement pensions only   Is.   Id. Is.   Id.  20 millions for all benefits Is.   9d. Is.   9d.  30 millionsThese increases would preserve the present ratio between contributions from employers, employed and Exchequer respectively.The total increased cost to the Exchequer in the first full year on this basis would be as follows:    MillionsIf retirement pensions only were increased      20If other National Insurance benefits were also increased   ............      10For war pensions    ........Gross cost........Less National Assistance net savingNet cost (say)      .....1545- 342 in first full year11. These increases in the contributions would be higher than would beactuarially appropriate in relation to the increased benefits. In other words, theywould contain a degree of overload. If the increases in the contributions were limited to the appropriate actuarial amounts, the result would be an immediate increase in the deficit in the Fund i.e., a smaller extra burden on employers andemployed, but a larger extra burden on the Exchequer.But even if the overloaded contributions were charged as in the first table, theywould not suffice to meet the additional expenditure after the first year, so that thedeficits now in prospect (until the new Bill is in operation) would in any event thenbe increased unless the contributions were put up yet again. Although the new Billremoves the deficits now in prospect, the contributions which it charges would be far too low to cover also the cost of immediate higher benefit rates: they would therefore have to be increased if we are to avoid being faced with a fresh series ofdeficits.12. There are the following reasons why it would be undesirable to raise thecontributions (i) It would be incompatible with our defence of the current national insurance Bill on the ground that it reduces contributions for thelower-paid.
Conclusion and Recommendations13. It follows that, in our view, there are grave difficulties in an increasein the retirement pension at the present time. Some of these derive from theincrease in contributions, some from the Exchequer outlook and some from theeffect on our present National Insurance Bill and the need to amend it. Are wethen to do nothing or to increase national assistance? On balance, we favour thefull plan for increasing national assistance and dealing with the disregards, assketched in paragraph 3, though the Chancellor of the Exchequer wishes at thisstage to reserve his position. We are under no illusion that we may not get agreat deal of political gratitude, if we adopt this course. But there is much to besaid for it on merits: it is timely and honourable.14. We prefer the course mentioned in the previous paragraph to doing nothing. But the possibility of &quot; standing pat &quot; can be discussed at Cabinet.15. A very early decision is necessary if we are to have time to bring the planinto effect by, say, the beginning of September.16. We therefore (subject to the Chancellor^ position being reserved and tothe recommendations of the National Assistance Board) invite the Cabinet (a) to agree to the preparation of (i) regulations to raise the scale rates of national assistance by 5s. single and 9s. married ( 27 millions); and(ii) a Bill and regulations to make, broadly, a 50 per cent, improvementin the income disregards and a revised treatment of capital assets,eliminating the war savings disregard ( 5 millions).Failing that,(b) to consider whether we should be justified in adopting either of thefollowing alternatives, which could be effected without legislation but which we regard as open to real objections (i) to raise the scale rates alone, as in (a) (i); or(ii) to raise the scale rates and make certain adjustments in the earningsdisregard, &amp;c, leaving the main disregards alone.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W. 1,5th May, 1959.(ii) It would involve substantial amendments of the figures in that Bill.        *(iii) It would lay an additional burden on many who will receive little or no benefit from the income-tax concessions in the Budget.(iv) It would bring contributions to a level which the lower-paid worker atpresent wage-levels would find heavy and it would lead to both wage-demands and price-increases and the consequent danger to economic stability.(v) It would impose a heavy additional burden on the Exchequer.And it is in any case by no means certain that such a rise in the contributions wouldnot go far to nullify any political credit we might obtain from raising the pension.

</content>
</cab>
