<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/5/23 images: 352-385</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
1 (4Copy No.      /3CONGRESS AND THE war memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.As trie War Cabinet are aware from the telegramscirculated to them, the Working Committee of the indian national Congress framed on 1st March a lengthy resolution to be submitted for adoption at the meeting of the congress to be held on 15th March at Ramgarh.   This documentreiterates in uncompromising terms the assertion that nothing short of complete independence will be accepted bythe people of India, that Dominion Status or any otherstatus within the imperial structure is wholly inapplicableto India, and that the people of India alone can properlyshape their Constitution and determine their relations withother countries through a Constituent Assembly elected onthe basis of adult suffrage.   The resolution concludes.withthe statement that civil disobedience is the naturalsequence to the preliminary step of the withdrawal of congress Ministries and that Congress will resort to this step as soon as their organisation is considered fit orcircumstances necessitate it.2.        It appears to be generally assumed that theCongress will adopt this resolution without modification,and I asked the Governor-General to let me have his   .appreciation of the position as it now stands and of thepolicy which he thinks should be adopted in relation to it.I circulate as appendix A to this memorandum the Governor-General&apos; s telegram from which it will appear that heSECRETW.P.(G)(40) 7311th March 1940. WAR CABINET

maintains the view he has consistently held since hisrenewed contact with Mr. Gandhi on 5th February led to noresult - and indeed since the rejection by the Congress ofthe offer he made on 17th October - that we should waitupon events and that there is no necessity and no justification either for considering any modification ofthe offer already made or for taking any step at presenttowards implementing that offer in whole or in part.3.        My first general comment on the telegram is that the argument proceeds on the assumption that the only alternative to the policy of inaction advocated is to make concessions to the Congress.   As I suggest below, there seems to me to.be open to us a line of positive policywhich could in no sense be described as making concessions to Congress.   My second general comment is that if theCongress adopts at Ramgarh the he solution prepared for it,I cannot conceive that a policy of &quot;lying back&quot; will serveus for very long, even if there should be no early resort to civil disobedience.   At the same time I wish to make itclear that I am not advocating any immediate decision:    itseems to me clear that we must - as the Governor-Generalproposes - await a further report from him after theRamgarh decisions have- been taken and there is some-evidence of the reactions to them.4.        With the authority of His Majesty&apos;s Government theGovernor-General has publicly offered, by way of affordingto non-official India a share in responsibility for thepolicy and actions of the Government of India in the prosecution of the war, to expand his Executive Council andto appoint representative Indian politicians to it.   It istrue that this offer as originally made was an offer in thefirst instance to the Congress and was conditional on that body&apos;s achieving a modus Vivendi with the All-India muslim league in relation to the composition of the provincial

i nMinistries as the first step towards the resumption of office by Congress Ministers in the Provinces; it is alsotrue that the Congress declined to consider the offer.But apart from any expectation that it might serve tobring the constitutional deadlock to an end it seemedright that representative Indian public men should be associated with the Central Government in the prosecution of the war,.and should at least have an opportunity of expressing views about peace when the time comes; and i cannot see that the fact that the Congress party has declined, and will no   doubt if the offer is repeatedcontinue to decline, to associate itself with this measureaffords any reason for denying such association to therepresentatives, of other political parties, or. will givethe Congress any ground for claiming that they have forcedour hand.5. I propose, therefore, that the Governor-general should be invited to give further consideration to thepossible advantages of taking this step with a view toputting it into execution if, as may quite possibly bethe case, it is welcomed outside Congress ranks.6.        The question remains what is to be our policy inregard to the Congress Party on the assumption that that party adopts at Ramgarh on 15th March as the consideredstatement of its position the resolution prepared for it which I have summarised above.    It is relevant in thisconnection to bear in mind that if the Proclamations underSection 93 of the Act from which the Governors are atpresent deriving their powers to administer the &quot;Congress&quot;Provinces are to continue in force beyond the end of Aprilit will be necessary to secure not later than about themiddle of April from each House of parliament a Resolutionapproving their continuance; and in that connection, if no

earlier, it will be essential for the Government at theleast to have determined;not only how they propose to dealwith the immediate situation, but the principles and basisof their long-term policy.    The adoption by the Congress ofthe proposed resolution will be tantamount to a declarationof a definite   breach between the Congress and the Govern-ment, and the course of events thereafter will, I presume,follow one or other of two lines; either the Congresshaving passed its resolution will, for whatever reason,continue to abstain from taking any overt action and india will remain politically as quiet as it has been since the resignation of the Ministries at the beginning of November(I have attached as Appendix 3 an article by Mr. Gandhiwhich the Governor-General has sent me as confirming hisown view that civil disobedience is not likely to be animmediate problem), or alternatively the leaders of theCongress, acting either on their own convictions or throughinability to restrain their extremist followers,, willsooner or later initiate some form of civil disobedience.Even on the former hypothesis I cannot believe, as I havealready indicated, that a policy of doing nothing will serve us for any appreciable time.   There seems to me to-be every advantage in securing the initiative for our-selves, even if the Congress do not resort to civildisobedience; and, if they do, it would I think be essentialthat we should have some constructive plan of action.-Obviously if civil disobedience is launched the challengemust be taken up, and unless we have something positive to balance against forcible repression of resistance and ofthe communal disorder into which this would develop, publicopinion in neutral countries, and particularly in theUnited States of America, is likely to be extremely, perhapsdangerously, critical.   But I can see little or no

I178advantage in waiting for the initiation of the policy Iadvocate until we are forced into it by disorder or the threat of disorder.   Finally, I remain of opinion that theurineiple which has hitherto governed our approaches to theIndian problem, not excluding the great step forward takenin 1935, namely that the nature of India&apos;s constitution andthe extent of the powers it is to place in Indian hands areto be determined by the British Government and Parliament,is difficult to reconcile even now with the principles forwhich we are at war, that at the end of the war we shall notbe able to adhere to it, and that there is no hope of the emergence of an agreed solution or a defensible policy onthat basis.    I wish, therefore, to invite the War Cabinet toconsider the line of policy indicated in the documentattached to this memorandum as Appendix C which seems to meto represent the only basis on which a friendly and lastingsettlement of the Indian problem is likely to be attainable.I. draw special attention to the fact that this plan involves no undertaking to accept blindly whatever constitutionIndians produce, but leaves rejection open to the Govern-ment and Parliament of the day.   The plan does, however,indicate the kind of considerations which in the view of thepresent Government would weigh with any future governmentin coming to their decision.   And I would urge in support ofthis line of approach that even if no agreed solution wereultimately to be reached from it, its adoption would placeus in a strong position with world opinion; for, if the upshot were to be that as the result of absence of Indianagreement we had to retain the present measure of our control in India - or quite possibly even to assume a largermeasure of control - as the only alternative to leavingIndia to disintegrate in chaos, we could no longer be accused of &quot;imperialistic&quot; motives.

7.        I do not ask the War Cabinet to commit themselvesnow to this line of policy.   What I suggest is that theyshould authorise me to send it to the Governor-General withan indication that, subject to his comments, they would be disposed to give favourable consideration to it.    I will discuss in a moment the question of the time and circum-stances of announcing a plan on these lines, but I placein the forefront of the scheme as of essential importance ..as a factor in it, that it should be made clear to theCongress- that we decline to deal with that body as representing India; and that while it is in no way the concern of His Majesty&apos;s Government to attempt to dictatethe part, if any, which the Congress Party as such should play in any subsequent negotiations, the point on whichthey will require to be satisfied is that the agreement, iffortunately agreement should be forthcoming, is that of theaccredited representatives of the actual communities and interests concerned and not merely of political organisations.8.        An announcement in this sense is becoming a matter ofsomewhat urgent necessity since all indications go to showthat the minorities in general and the Muslims inparticular are becoming increasingly restive at the lackof support for their denial of the claim of the Congress to speak for India (cf. paragraph 16 of the Governor-General&apos;telegram for views from States also in this sense).   But i feel strongly that, important and urgent as this step hasnow become, it cannot prudently be taken without a positive policy to counterbalance it - hence my.-proposals in Appendix C.   as for the moment when such a policy shouldbe announced, we must judge by the course of events, and inparticular by the actions of the Congress at and following on the Pamgarh Conference.   But when the appropriate momentarrives I think the Governor-General might well summon a

small conference representative of. opinion in british india and the States and expound the plan to that conference in the first instance, inviting them to discuss .it with a view to setting in motion machinery to giveeffect to it.   Publication would, of course, have tofollow the next day.   And if, as may well prove to be thecase, the Governor-General considers that it would facilitate getting such machinery into being if he were to propose to proceed with the Federal provisions of the Act,I would give him full liberty to recommend this course.9-.        I do not imagine that an announcement in the senseI propose would end our troubles.   Every endeavour would, Ihave no doubt, be made not only by Congress to pass thebaby back to us.   Mr. Jinnah will ask all kinds of trouble-some questions, in reply to which I suggest that we should say that we do not feel called on to answer hypotheticalquestions, but that, having gone as far as we have-, we haveno other object in view than to promote a real and lastingself-government for India within the Empire.10-. It may be convenient if I summarise my contentionand proposals in the following terms:-(a) A purely negative policy in the face of the definitebreak with the Congress which now seems likely is of doubtful merit at the best and is in any caseunlikely to serve for long.(b) I agree with the Governor-General that to issue at- this moment a threat in the terms proposed by his home Member in the draft communique attached to his telegram would be highly inexpedient.(c) It is of great and increasingly urgent importance, ifwe are to retain the goodwill of the Muslims, the princes and the smaller minorities, to make it clear

to them and the Congress that we decline to regard thelatter as representing the whole of India and to dealwith it as such.(d) If we are to take that line with the Congress it isessential that we should have some positive policy toset against it.   Such a positive policy would also be essential, if only for the purpose of retaining the goodwill of neutral countries and particularly of theUnited States of America, as a counterweight to therepressive action we should have to take against civildisobedience whatever form it takes.(e) There is no hope of a peaceable settlement of ourconstitutional relations with India if these relations and the Indian Constitution itself are to be dictatedto India, or even to have the appearance of beingdictated, in the last resort by the British Governmentand Parliament.(f) If point (c) is agreed, it seems to me that some suchline of policy as that indicated in Appendix C is thenecessary consequence, and I ask for authority tosend it to the Governor-General for his comments,setting forth for his earnest consideration thearguments in support of it.(g) The precise moment for announcing this policy Is amatter to be determined in the light of events.   it ought not to be delayed beyond the outbreak or theserious threat of disorder, but the right moment forits announcement might well occur before.(h) The announcement of this policy might be made in thefirst instance to a small conference representativeof all the leading interests in India to be summonedby the Governor-General, publication followingimmediately thereafter.

(i) If the Governor-General feels, and has support for his view, that progress with the plan would be facilit-ated by the speedy inauguration of the Federalprovisions of the Act he should be free to do what he can to secure it.(j) Meanwhile, whatever his views on the larger questionsof policy, he should be invited to reconsider the expediency of appointing representative Indians tohis Executive Council and proceed with it even if,as is almost certain, the Congress maintains itsrefusal to cooperate.Z.INDIA OFFICE.

Q 0G tiSECRET.APPENDIX A.Telegram, from the Governor-General to Secretary of State for India, dated march 8, 1940.immediate.358-G. Following is my appreciation of the position in the light of theWorking Committee&apos;s resolution passed at recent Patna meeting, full text ofwhich will already be available to you.2. Before discussing background of resolution and reactions to it here, i will comment briefly on its content. It is, as you will agree, wholly unsatisfactoryfrom our point of view. It reiterates demand for independence and rejectsDominion Status (despite obvious practical difficulty of India&apos;s attainingindependence, even if she was internally united, which she is not, and strong opposition of Moslems (to say nothing of the Princes), to severance of the connection , at any rate at this stage, with His Majesty&apos;s Government). It repeatsdemand for settlement of future Constitution, by people of India alone, on thebasis of a Constituent Assembly based on adult suffrage. Practical objections tothis need not be stated. Political objections are equally obvious. Apart from thefact that we could not dissociate ourselves from any such deliberations, so far as british India is concerned, effect would be, thanks to superior quality of Congressmachine, to submerge the Moslems and other minorities; while one has only toconsider the level of education, &amp;c, of the populations of, e.g., the Eastern States,to appreciate the effect in the case of Princely India, even if. Indian Rulers were likely to be prepared to acquiesce in any such procedure. I do not believe thatthere is any misunderstanding as to our war aims and the Resolution (? omission)efforts that we have made to clear that point.3. Resolution further is completely at variance with general feeling in thiscountry. India has, as you know, lent fullest and most generous support in thewar. We could at this moment have ten times as many men recruited if we could use them and pay for them. So far as supply is concerned, we are workingovertime, and Congress supporters themselves are deeply interested in thefinancial results of the orders we are receiving. There is general sympathy forthe ideals animating the Allies, and general condemnation of cause taken up byHitler and Stalin. A friendly settlement with Congress, desirable as it is on other grounds, would be unlikely materially to improve our contribution in termseither of men or of supply, although it would dispose of nuisance value inter-nationally, and of local nuisance value in the event of civil disobedience, whichdetermined Congress opposition would undoubtedly represent.4. So far as the minorities are concerned, the resolution represents a furtherstiffening. It refers in terms in the first place to &quot; recognised &quot; minorities. Thiswould be very likely to cut out Europeans, and might also cut out Anglo-Indians,and just conceivably Sikhs. The position in relation to the scheduled castesequally is left obscure; but Congress would, one would judge, be likely to be reluctant to accept them as a &quot; recognised &apos;&apos; minority, and would press a claimto speak on their behalf as far as possible. Further protection to be granted tothe minorities as a result of the Constituent Assembly is now to be based onagreement &quot; so far as possible &quot; with arbitration in the event of disagreement onany point. I need not emphasise that these communal divisions will not admit ofbeing settled for ever by any judicial or arbitral finding, and that the partyagainst which finding goes, even if it had submitted to jurisdiction of tribunal,will remain resentful, intransigent, and as anxious to secure reopening as it islikely to find it difficult to control its followers.5. The Princes are to be steam-rolled, no account being taken of treaty obligations of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and &quot; foreign interests &quot; (without distinction between British interests and those of other countries) are to be protected only if they are not in conflict with the interests of the Indian people.[20970] b
6. The Working Committee have thus stated the Congress claim in a formmore extreme than ever hitherto employed, and one which denies the possibilityof treating Dominion Status as consistent with India&apos;s freedom or independence;a form, too, which we can fairly, I think, hold, takes no account of practicalrealities or difficulties, or of bare justice to others, and which is well calculated to disturb still further all the minorities, including the Europeans and the Princes.The threat of civil disobedience, which it then proceeds to make is, however, most carefully guarded, and no date is fixed. The decision to move into civildisobedience is made contingent on conditions indefinite, or likely, so far as theyare definite, to be difficult of realisation. In a word, the resolution gives congress the political credit of threatening us, without any early need to perform.7. I would judge that carefully-guarded form of really important part ofresolution, viz., the reaching of civil disobedience, is due to influence of Gandhi,whose frequently repeated reluctance willingly to contemplate civil disobedienceI am still disposed to believe; and that resolution, outspoken as it is, may beregarded as another effort, on the one hand, to maintain the solidarity of congress to which he attaches so much importance, and, on the other, to outbid, or bid upto level of, the Left Wing. Nehru is reported to have taken an active part in drafting, to have urged an active line in the interest of holding support of thecountry against the Left Wing, and to have been very intolerant as usual of opposition. Stewart reports a rumour (though other information received byDirector of the Intelligence Bureau throws doubt on it), that Patel advocatedreturn to office, supported by Prasad and Rajagopalachari, and was vehementlyopposed by Nehru (supported by Azad), and that Patel seemed likely to carry theday when Gandhi intervened in time to prevent Nehru walking out and securedpostponement of the decision.8.   Further contributory factors are doubtless :  (a) The hope that a really strongly-worded resolution, with a threat of direct action, would shake His Majesty&apos;s Government (whom Nehru appearsto believe still to be squeezable) and make them produce some further concession or statement before Ramgarh, which would strengthen thehands of the Right Wing at that meeting.(b) The anxiety to offset possible local difficulty with Bose, who is proposing to run an anti-compromise rally at Ramgarh. It appears that thereis considerable probability also of a large demonstration of Kisansunder Sahajanand and an aboriginal anti-Congress demonstrationunder Jaipal Singh. But whatever the underlying tactics, the fact remains that Congress is now committed publicly to threat of openresistance, and that negotiations in existing position would take place under that threat.9. So much for substance of resolution. I turn now to reactions to it. TheCongress press has generally taken it without any critical comment that matters.It has, as might be expected, been ill received by Moslems, and most significantfeature of developments over past month has been a marked and definite hardeningof Moslem attitude. Moslems are now for the first time, thanks to intransigeantattitude adopted by Congress, coming to analyse what is involved from their point of view as a minority community in attainment not merely of independence,but even of Dominion Status. They are beginning to appreciate that, short of a series of safeguards, which it might be very difficult to reconcile with ordinaryform of Dominion Status, the effect of it would, be to enthrone the majoritycommunities at the centre and to run a considerable risk of leaving the minoritiesat its mercy. The point has been taken, too, that a Dominion Government onceset up will in practice have very considerable, if not indeed complete, powers of modifying the Constitution (compare the case of Eire), and so, if necessary, of getting rid of paper safeguards embodied in it. And Hindustani Times hasunwisely, in last couple of days, indicated in a leader that it is essential that anyConstitution to be acceptable should vest the right of such modification in theDominion Government. I have had from one or two Moslem sources recently thesuggestion that what Congress are really concerned to do is to get us deeply committed to principle of Dominion Status of the fullest kind, with implication that there shall be no interference by His Majesty&apos;s Government save such as maybe provided for by any documents exchanged at the time of recognition of
Dominion; that special powers and responsibilities of Governor-General andGovernors must disappear; that there shall be power in the Dominion Governmentto make alterations in the Constitution; to control very largely the appointmentof Judges; to use the forces at the disposal of the Dominion Government for themaintenance of law and order in such manner as they may think fit; to handleappointments to the Services, &amp;c, without interference from outside, and the like.I should not be surprised, as matters stand to-day, to find the Moslems movingawajr not only from idea of any early independence, but from idea of any advanceas far as Dominion Status : and as you will have seen from Jinnah&apos;s letter to meof 24th February repeated to you in my telegram 26th February 292 S, the moslems are becoming increasingly insistent -and I am satisfied that they are serious in this that they will not accept any Constitution that is not satisfactory to them. The practicability of devising a Constitution satisfactory to congress in its present frame of mind and to Moslems calls for no comment.10. Minorities other than the Moslems have not been very much in evidence,but I have no reason to think that they are not beginning to be as much disturbedas the Moslems at possible implications of Dominion Status in the face of thepresent claims of Congress and at the risk that His Majesty&apos;s Government mayacquiesce in those claims. The Princes equally have said little, but it is clear from the attitude of Dewans of Kashmir, Hyderabad, Cochin and Baroda, whom have seen in the last couple of days and whose impressions I shall be able to check when Chamber meets at the end of this week from various of theirHighnesses, that they, too, regard with deep uneasiness the nature of Congressclaims and prospect of any surrender to those claims by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.11. Meanwhile, despite this political ferment in higher quarters, the formerCongress Provinces, so far as I can judge, are running very smoothly indeed.There is no sign of popular discontent or agitation, and one still gets some feeling of relief at lull in political debate so far as the ordinary man in the street isconcerned. Full weight in assessing importance of this must be given to professedanxiety of Congress to avoid a row. I give them full credit for that. But wemust also give weight to fact that, if they thought it to their interest to havetrouble, they would not hesitate to do so; and I have little doubt that a contributory factor, whatever they may sa,j in their resolutions about their readiness to proclaim civil disobedience, is uncertainty as to how civil disobediencewould work out from their point of view. I should judge myself that it would be.likely to lead to severe communal trouble certainty in United Provinces, possibly in Bihar and Bombay, and, while an open breach with us would no doubt for thetime being close the ranks and consolidate the present Right Wing control of the machine, it would be bound as time went on to result in a movement more towardsthe Left and a strengthening of the position of Leftist Elements, which are stillbut tender to take control in an increasing degree out of hands of Right Wing,who, I am certain, are as reluctant to part with it as ever.12. I ask myself in these circumstances (a) what Congress think theycan hope to gain ? (&amp;) what our tactics ought to be both immediately and indealing with them in terms of the remoter future.13. On the first of these points I am frankly puzzled. But I am increasinglydisposed to think there is something in the Moslem suggestion referred to inparagraph No. 9 above, in other words, that they want to get us committed tounqualified acceptance of the implications of normal Dominion Status and thenrequire us to hand over responsibility to a Dominion Government in which theywill be in a decisive majority under an agreement which (subject to an arrange-ment to cover Defence) would reduce our power of effective interference in theGovernment of India as a whole to a minimum, leaving the problem of the minorities and, to some extent, the problem of the Princes to be dealt with bythe new Dominion Government. There are indications that this consideration was present to [sic] Patna meeting and that that meeting was perfectly content to allow Gandhi to continue to play the hand in his own way. If there is anything in what I suggest the position is that Congress regard the stakes as high and well worth playing for. We have fortunately always been cautious, for we have made it clear in our declarations that an essential preliminary to progress is necessary measure of agreement between the various communities, &amp;c in India[20970] b 2
But it will be, in my judgment, more important than ever in such statements aswe may in future make to continue to emphasise that point, and to bring outthat, anxious as we are to see India progress to Dominion Status level, and readyas we are to give all possible help to her to do so, we cannot overlook tiheclaims and attitude of the great minorities and of Princes, to whom we haveformal obligations; and that it is essential that Indians should themselves reachthat degree of general agreement between major interests and communities herewhich would make government by resulting Dominion Government, without ourcontinual intervention a practicable proposition.14. It is conceivable, again, that Congress think that if we suffer a severereverse in the West, we shall be prepared to let them have what they want, and that,while now marking out their claim, they will continue to play for time till the posi-tion is clearer. If that is their idea, it is, I should have thought, based on a com-pletely false argument. Congress in such an event would be a nuisance to the extent that civil disobedience or the like on an extended scale might immobilise troops and might interfere with supply at a time when it might be of real importance that there should be no such impediment to our conduct of the war. But inthe event of a reverse, the support in men of Moslems, the Hindu fighting races,and Princes would be even more important than before, and I should be surprisedif the effect on supply were to prove to be really major in character; we should in any event in such circumstances be justified in taking action far more drasticagainst Congress and its supporters than we should contemplate at a time when there was still a prospect of agreement, and when they did not constitute an active and immediate menace, and, as I see it, it would be essential that weshould not hesitate to take that action.15. Finally, there is, of course, the ever-present pressure of Left Wing.Much as (on assumption for what it is worth that they, or certain of them, maybe prepared to be reasonable) one may sympathise with Right Wing elements in congress over such pressure, and desirable as it is not to break so long as we seehope of a settlement which v/e could regard as acceptable, there is a definite limit to extent to which we can allow our sympathy to affect our actions. What I have always been afraid of has been (compare paragraph No. 4 of my telegram No. 140 S.of 30th January) that we should do a deal with Right Wing and then find thatRight Wing, as a result of Left Wing pressure, was unable to deliver the goods.What is, in fact, happening now in an increasing degree is that Right Wing, inorder to preserve unity within Congress, are being forced in public to supportmore and more Leftist doctrines. The natural tendency in any political organisa-tion of this type is no doubt naturally to the Left. But Right are comingperilously near, though they would not admit this themselves, to having the paceset for them by Bose and his friends.16. Assuming then that analysis I have endeavoured to make above ofposition corresponds reasonably to facts, the next question is what should be our immediate orders ? I feel bound to report in this connextion that I have had inthe last few days a series of representations from various quarters that we shouldtake immediate steps to warn Congress in terms and officially that, if they con-template implementing their threat of civil disobedience, they would be dealtwith most severely as impeding progress of. war. The suggestion has also beenmade to me that we should warn Congress that the resolutions of the type passed at Patna, if reaffirmed at Ramgarh, would make further negotiation impossible;far less, His Majesty&apos;s Government would not be prepared to conduct discussionsunder a threat of blackmail such as this, and that if endeavours are madeto implement it, Congress as a political organisation will be proclaimed. Maxwell,my Home Minister, is very strongly in favour of a formal communique in terms which I will telegraph to you separately. Hydari and Shanmukham Chetty havestrongly urged that, unless and until His Majesty&apos;s Government make their position in relation to Congress intentions clearer and show that they are not going to contemplate any settlement on the basis indicated in Congress resolutionthere is no hope of opposition to Congress developing or consolidating in theformer Congress Provinces; but that once the necessarv indication has been givenwe need anticipate no delay in development of such opposition. That view isalso held by the other much more (sic) and by others in touch with political life inBritish India whom I have seen in last few days.
17. Arthur Moore, whom I interviewed on the 6th March, was also strongly in favour of something on these lines. (As you know I do not place his judgmentor balance very high and I am disposed to weigh what he says pretty heavily.But he has wide contacts in India and is editor of a leading paper.) He putsit that it is our business now to show up Congress to make it clear to the world that it is Congress that has destroyed the hope of Indian unity, has wreckedFederation, has lost chance of Dominion Status, has alienated the minorities andthe Princes and has as result of 2-j years&apos; experience of government in Congressprovinces so alarmed the minorities about their position that there is little hopewhen the Act is reopened of existing provincial scheme, well as it may be working in the Punjab and Bengal, being allowed to stand.18. I do not think that I am overstating it when I say that I get the very strong impression that the bulk of moderate opinion, whether European or Indian,in this country is losing or has lost sympathy with these exaggerated claims of congress; while for the reasons I have given above moderate opinion in non--Hindu circles is also gravely apprehensive that we may go some distancefurther to meet Congress claims; and is beginning to wonder whether what hasalready been promised by way of meeting the demands for self-government urgedon. us by all parties before the passing of the Act may not work out in practice to serious detriment of the minorities.19. Accepting all that feeling as one must some sympathy with impatienceand irritation of anti-Congress elements both at exaggerated claims of congress and at what they probably regard as our undue hesitation in dealing severely withthem, we have, as I see it to consider a variety of other factors in making up our minds as to a communique such as Maxwell suggests or to any radical change in policy such as would be welcomed at this moment by Moore andprobably too by ordinary conservative elements in this country, more particularly as burden of implementing it would fall on His Majesty&apos;s Government and noton them. It may be as you have recognised before that in fact experience will show that democratic experiment will not work in this country. But though with growing doubt I still feel it is essential that we should give it a furtherrun. The considerations that weigh with me in hesitating to take any extremestep are first of all Parliamentary reactions. I doubt if Parliament has yetcaught up with the gradual movement of opinion here and particularly amongMoslems which I have reported above. Feeling at home is still in favour as I see it of constitutional advance to Dominion Status, on assumption that that can besecured without any major rupture in India. We should have some difficultyI should have thought in carrying conviction to Parliament at this stage of case for any immediate and drastic reversal of policy; though that would notnecessarily be the case as regards a warning to Congress.20. Secondly, we have to consider material afforded to hostile propaganda,and the effect likely to be produced in America, by what would certainly berepresented as a reversion in India to a policy of repression and coercion on a scale which would inevitably be grossly exaggerated. We may have to face that,but it is not a thing to take on lightly.21. Thirdly, I have the feeling which may of course be ill-founded, thatthere may be a certain element of bluff in the existing Congress tactics. Theirgame is consistently to ask for far more than they can carry, or than they reallyhope to secure. It is quite likely, that as I said in paragraph No: 13 above,they may be prepared to take the risks involved in playing for very high stakes,and to take the change of difficulty in avoiding losing face if they fail. I feeltoo that they are at the moment very lacking in a target. They cannot fail tobe conscious that Lhey are coming under a good deal of criticism in moderatequarters here; they must be aware of hardening of Moslem opinion (which mayof course have made them all the more anxious to jockey us into acceptance oftheir claims before we take that hardening really seriously); while tone of thehome press, which was originally, thanks to their admirable publicity machine,so favourable to them, shows a change as result of fuller realisation ofcomplexities of this situation; and latest American Press reports suggest acertain lapse in the active interest (though that I fully accept may be only temporary and would disappear with active anti-Congress measures on our part)in that country.[20970] b 3
22. A decision on our part to throw down the gauntlet, to present Congresswith an excuse for resorting to extreme steps (by an unnecessarily stronglyworded communique, by a threat that, failing withdrawal of threat of civildisobedience, there would be no more negotiations, by publicly turning our backon Congress and declaring that we proposed to rely on help of moderate opinion and of Moslems, or the like), is then not a thing lightly to be contemplated, allthe more so because, great as may be the sympathy which moderate andconservative element here may feel for us, we shall not get much help from themwhen tussle comes. The Moslems would probably be delighted to see us at lastdefinitely at odds with Congress. The Europeans, who have their business interests to look after, would no doubt recognise that it was inevitable, and would support us, but they could hardly be expected to welcome a break and itsdisturbing consequences unless case was a decisive one. Finally (and this hasinevitably carried much weight with me), so long as Act is in being at all, one has to contemplate what alternative there is to Congress Government in respectof former Congress Provinces. My conclusion on that is that there is at themoment no effective alternative, and that, if we were to dissolve in the Provincesnow governed under Section 93 to-morrow, the chances, save conceivably in bombay, of Congress returning, if not in the same strength, at any rate withoutany very material diminution in their strength, are overwhelming and that thefact that the ordinary Indian elector, even if he is politically minded, does not really subscribe to extreme Congress claim that we should for practical purposeswithdraw, would not effect [sic] the result of election. They have the only reallyeffective political machine so far as Hinduism is concerned. The Oppositions tothem in Congress Provinces are still disorganised and show no real sign of gettingtogether (you will have noticed Erskine&apos;s account in his letter of 20th Februaryof the failure of Justice Party to contest as a party any seats in MadrasLegislative Council, while in the United Provinces, Congress have, I gather,maintained, if not improved, their hold in relation to Council seats there). Wemust, too, in settling our long-term policy, be careful, as I see it, not to commitour prestige too deepfy by taking up a position which we may be forced to evacuate (eg., a refusal to negotiate with Congress unless they call off any threat of civil disobedience); nor can we, as suggested above, leave out of account thepossibility of Congress returning from a general election, which must take placein 1942, with a decisive mandate for their own policy, though we need not perhapsfor the moment look so far forward as that.23. The picture which I have painted above is a disturbing one, as no oneknows better than I do. But we can, I think, feel entirely clear in our conscienceas to our own responsibility for it. We have done our utmost to bring the peopletogether. We have spared no effort to try to bridge the differences between the communities. It cannot fairly be represented as our fault if we have failed todo so. We could abdicate to Congress in conditions such as I have described above only at, we feel, quite definite betrayal of our responsibilities to the minorities and to the Princes. Nor, as I see it, would we be able to clearourselves of responsibility for results to India and to the Empire of suchabdication. Congress, in any event, cannot govern this country in face of Moslemand Princely hostility unless we are prepared to enable it to do so, and I cannotconceive our holding minorities in order as. agents of Congress, nor can Moslemor Princes govern it without our help, and there are signs in Moslem camp of a growing readiness to recognise that it may be necessary to retain British inIndia for many years to come as only means of holding balance between conflictinginterests here. I see nothing for it in the circumstances but to continue to reiterateour own readiness to help; our anxiety to help India as swiftly as practicable on road of constitutional progress; but also fact that obstacles to advance are Indianobstacles which we cannot ignore and necessity for agreement here as a conditionof advance; that we should continue to resist Congress demands for any concessions other than those we have already offered or for any overriding of minorities or Princes; and that, if they do go into civil disobedience, we should deal severely with them.24.   Fully realising Parliamentary and propaganda aspects of this issue,especially in wartime, I have not failed to ask myself whether there is any further move or gesture that could appropriately be made by us at this stage which- would be calculated to ease the situation either by giving Congress an opportunity
to abate their claims, or, if Congress are not prepared to abate those claims, bysatisfying Parliament and public opinion at Home and internationally that the fault does not rest with us, and that we are dealing with people with whom it isimpossible to negotiate. My conclusion is, I fear, negative. We have already offered in most public way everything that we have to offer. I am quite satisfiedthat on important matter of machinery we could not do business by means of a constituent Assembly, and that there would be no hope of Moslems acceptingsuch an arrangement. In any event, if we are to take Patna resolution seriously,Congress might well demand as a preliminary to participating in such an assembly, its restriction to &quot;the people of India,&quot; and an undertaking by usto accept its conclusions (and arguments which I gave against committing ourselves blindfold to accepting conclusions of any such body, even if it contained a European or official element, in paragraph No. 7 of my telegram of29th January, No. 127 S., still seem to me decisive), or require other unacceptableconditions.25. Two possibilities of a minor order are, establishment of consultative committee which we discussed last year, or expansion of my Council, in eitherevent leaving Congress to stay outside if it did not want to come in. I shouldmyself be opposed to either. To both there is, in my judgment, the same generalobjection that any further move at this stage on our part towards one of them,would be interpreted by Congress as an encouragement to think that they have only to shout loud enough and they will bring us all the way. (Their tactics have,of course, been to drown with abusive language any comment on situation, suchas your recent speech, which exposed weakness of their position, and to reiteratein complete disregard of arguments advanced in various quarters against them from time to time their earlier claims in all their plenitude.) The effect, too,I am satisfied, on Moslems and on other more moderate elements in this country would be very disturbing. They equally would feel that it was only a questionof time till, probably at their expense, we would come to terms with Congress.Futher, were we to take action on these lines and leave Congress to remain inthe wilderness, we should provide them, whether in Consultative Committee or inexpanded Executive Council, with sort of target which they are so anxious tosecure. They would be able to point to unrepresentative character of both in theabsence of Congress, and in the case of the Executive Council to suggest that that body had ceased to be as at present a purely administrative governing organ,taking an objective view, had assumed a political character, and was packed with political nominees entirely hostile to Congress whose influence would be felt inday by day government of the country. The lack of substance for any suchsuggestion would not in the least prevent Congress from broadcasting it as widelyas possible and from turning it, I suspect, to account.26. My own provisional conclusions at this stage on the picture as set out above are as follows. I am not disposed on a balancing of arguments to challengethe Congress position before Ramgarh by any warning so definite as Maxwellwould favour. I do not want, so far as there may be any division of opinion in working Committee (not that I attach much importance to that, for Gandhi &apos;sprestige and his skill in keeping that body together are too great), to cement themby appearance of a threat. Secondly, there is always the possibility, though I donot rate it high, that counsels of greater common sense may prevail at Ramgarh,or that the trend of discussion there may better enable us to appreciate Congresstactics and strategy.Thirdly, my personal relations with all parties being still friendly and thatfact holding out some hope, so far as Congress are concerned, of maintainingcontact and of resuming conversations later, I think that there would be dis-advantage from wider point of view in too positive and categorical a warning orthreat unless forced upon us, which would make those contacts impossible ordifficult for some considerable time to come. The furthest I should therefore be disposed to go before Ramgarh would be an arranged Parliamentary question asto steps, if any, which were contemplated to deal with Congress threat of civildisobedience. The answer to that might be that His Majesty&apos;s Government were fully alive to the importance of that issue; that, as would be observed, thesuggestion of civil disobedience in Patna resolution was entirely contingent, butthat if consistent efforts of His Majesty&apos;s Government to bring about peace in Indiabetween the communities and to secure united India unhappily failed, and if
Congress implemented their threat, appropriate action would be taken without amoments delay to deal with it.27. As regards general position, Ramgarh may help us to see our way more clearly. I should prefer to report again once it is over. But it may help you tohave my present view subject to its outcome and on the assumption that Congresstake no steps to implement their threat of civil disobedience, and keep withinthe law in their speeches and activities, I am, as you will have gathered from paragraph 24 above, strongly in favour of taking no action, and of lying back. Ishould greatly regret it, if as I visualise is quite possible, that policy, if approvedby His Majesty&apos;s Government, should expose you and His Majesty&apos;s Governmentto different passages in Parliament. I have shown above that I am fully alive to possible embarrassment in propaganda and in international field of a period ofseverely strained relations, or of a break necessitating coercive measures with congress. But my considered judgment is that we should now make no further move towards Congress beyond repeating our readiness to help (cf. paragraph 23above), &amp;c, and that we should be ready, if Congress make a break inevitable,.todeal with civil disobedience resolution and, without delay, to use to full powersof censorship and pressure so far as Congress is concerned and to spare no effort inmy power to bring home to Parliament and Public that responsibility for fact that india has not advanced to point, and now seems unlikely to advance to point, towhich we have and are anxious to bring her is not ours; and that predominantresponsibility rests with Congress and with the intransigeance of its profounduneasiness which that attitude has caused to minorities as well as to Princes.Enclosure to Governor-General&apos;s Telegram.Following is text of communique suggested by Maxwell (see paragraph 16of telegram) : &quot; Government of India have noticed that the initiation of some form of civildisobedience is being threatened in certain quarters as a means of extortingpolitical concessions from His Majesty&apos;s Government. They feel it their duty to warn the public of very serious consequences which would inevitably followadoption of such a political weapon in time of war. The war in which HisMajesty&apos;s Government is engaged is one in which future destinies of India, no less than of any other part of British Commonwealth, are at stake, and all other considerations must be regarded as subordinate to its successful prosecution. any move intended in any way to embarrass Government of this country or to prejudiceits war effort can only be regarded as calculated to assist His Majesty&apos;s enemiesand must be treated as such. While it is not and never has been the policy ofGovernment to suppress the legitimate expression of political views, they couldnot consistently with their responsibility for the defence of India, allow such a move to develop, and if it is attempted they will use their whole resources toprevent it. They have ample powers for this purpose and no loyal citizen need be in any fear of outcome. But in case any misapprehension exists that such a move may result in a settlement favourable to its organisers, His Majesty&apos;sGovernment have authorised the Government of India to make it plain that theywill not at any future time be prepared to negotiate or have any dealings withany organisation which has sought to embarrass Government in this emergency,nor will they allow any voice or representation to any such body or its leaders inany future constitutional discussions which may take place. On the other hand,such an attempt at present time, however unsuccessful, might have irrevocableeffects on plans of His Majesty&apos;s Government for future of India. The Govern-ment of India hope that all those who have real interests of India at heart will realise the extreme gravity of issues involved, and do their utmost to discourageand resist any revolutionary propaganda.&quot;
APPENDIX B.Text of Article published by Mr. Gandhi in his Periodical Harijan of March 9,entitled &quot; When? &quot;&quot; Everybody is asking me not whether, but when, I am to call the countryto civil disobedience. Some of my questioners are the most sober amongco-workers. To them the Patna resolution has no other meaning than that thestruggled coming is a question of days. It is proof that the country, or that part of it that has hitherto taken part in the struggle for freedom, is tired ofthe waiting and suspense. It is heartening to think that there are in the countryso many persons who count no sacrifice too dear for gaining independence.&quot; While, therefore, I admire the zeal of my questioners, I must warn themagainst being impatient. There is nothing in the resolution to warrant the belief that the atmosphere is suitable for declaring civil disobedience. It will be suicidalto declare it when there is so much indiscipline and violence within the Congressitself. Congressmen will make a serious mistake if they do not give full weight to my words. I cannot, will not, start mass civil disobedience so long as I am not convinced that there is enough discipline and enough non-violence in Congressranks. The apathy about constructive programme, i.e., spinning and sales ofKhadi, I take to be positive signs of unbelief. Battle through such (? instrumentsis) foredoomed to failure. Such persons should know that I am not their man.If there is no hope of attaining necessary measure of discipline and non-violence,it would be better to let me retire from leadership.&quot; Let it be clearly understood that I cannot be hustled into precipitatingstruggle. They err grievously who think I can ever declare civil disobedience,having been driven thereto by so-called leftists. I make no such distinctionbetween rightists and leftists. Both are my co-workers and friends. He willbe a bold man who can with any measure of certainty draw the line of demarcation between leftists and rightists. Congressmen and non-Congressmenshould also know that, even if the whole country were to turn against me, i must when the time comes fight single-handed. The others have, or may have,weapons besides non-violence. I have no choice. Being the author of thenon-violence technique in the political field, I am bound to fight when I feel theurge from within.&quot; It is inherent in the technique that I never know the timetable in advance.The call may come at any time.   It need not be described as from God.&quot; The inner urge is a current phrase easily understood. Everybody some-times acts upon the inner urge. Such action need not always be right. Butthere is no other explanation possible for certain actions.&quot; The thought often comes to me that it would be a good thing if Congresscould forget me. I do sometimes feel that, with my strange (? views) of life,I am a misfit in Congress. Whatever special qualifications I may possess, andfor which Congress and Country may have use, can perhaps be utilised if Iwere wholly cut off from Congress. But I know that this severance cannot bebrought about mechanically or violently. It will come in its own time, if it hasto come. Only Congressmen should know my limitations and should not be surprised or grieved if they find me stiff and unbending. I ask them to believeme when I say that I am incapable of acting without fulfilment of conditions laid down for declaring mass civil disobedience. M. K. Gandhi, Sevagram, the5th March, 1940.&quot;

4 n bAPPENDIX C.FRAMEWORK OF AN ANNO UNO BMENT BY HIS MAJESTY&apos; S&apos; GOVERNMENT,In 1919 parliament declared its policy to be &quot;the realisation of responsible government in British India as an.integral part of the Empire&quot;.    That policy standsunchanged, except that whereas in 1919 the union ofBritish India and the Indian States was viewed as a distantideal, the planning and experience of the last 20 years have demonstrated this union to be not only feasible butalso the only solid and practicable basis for self-government in British India.His Majesty&apos;s Government have more than once of latemade it clear that they are ready to promote the attainmentby India of full self-government as soon as possible afterthe conclusion of peace.   The discussion and controversy ofthe past six months have been directed in effect to themethods by which the change should be brought about.The bitter differences in India in recent months have only emphasised the fact that there is yet no such fusionof race, religion or culture in India as would warrant theassumption that the counting of heads can settledifferences about the principles upon which the 350millions of her diverse peoples are to assume the task ofgoverning themselves and the machinery to give effect tothese principles.   They must be settled by agreement between representatives of the various elements which compose herpopulation.   A Constitution which proceeded from any other basis than agreement on broad principles and essentialmachinery would inevitably lead to a break up of India intoviolently opposed elements, or would have to depend forsanctions to secure its peaceful evolution upon outsideauthority.   But the continuance of external control overthe organic working of a Constitution is incompatible withself-government, unless and except in so far as it rests upon

agreement between a self-governing India and the UnitedKingdom.   The absence of prior agreement among Indiansthemselves is therefore an impassable barrier in the wayof self-government and it is an obstacle which only they canremove.On the two principles - that a self-governing Indiamust not exclude the States and must rest upon agreementbetween the main sections of the population in Indiaitself - His Majesty&apos;s Government are prepared to proceed on the following plan.An All-India body to be set up to prepare a constitution for India as a separate member of the BritishCommonwealth of Nations.   This body must contain suchrepresentation of the Indian States and of the minority communities as is accepted by the States and the minorities;and the method of selecting its membership and the process by which it is to reach its conclusions must also be agreed by the Indian interests concerned.   When it has reachedconclusions covering the whole ground, but in any event notearlier than the conclusion of peace, this body to appoint representatives to meet representatives of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom to negotiate agreement onthe proposals.    If the British and Indian representativesreach agreement on the plan with or. without modificationpropounded by the constituent body their conclusions to beput to Parliament and to the constitutional body in india for ratification.His Majesty&apos;s Government wish to make clear their view that in the negotiations contemplated the UnitedKingdom representatives would not be concerned to questionIndian proposals because they themselves did not regard them as the best possible.   Their business would be tosatisfy themselves that the proposals are based upon broadand reasoned agreement amongst Indians, and are likely toproduce a stable and enduring Constitution.

So much for the new Constitution; but there remaincertain matters upon which His Majesty&apos;s Government feelentitled to ask for security, either by inclusion in theConstitution of appropriate provision or in the form of atreaty with the new India, and they think that these could with advantage be discussed between the representativesappointed to negotiate agreement on the proposedConstitution itself.   The matters in question are:(a) Arrangements for the defence of India as part ofthe Empire,(b) Security for the service of the sterling debt.(c) Sufficient control of the Services to secure theirreasonable rights, including their right to thecareer for which they were recruited.   Butrecruitment by the Secretary of State to end ata fixed date.   This does not necessarily mean the cessation of recruitment from this country.(d) The maintenance for some time at least of thecommercial safeguards of the kind in thepresent Constitution.(e) Such a position in India as will enable us todischarge our obligations to the States in sofar as the States are not completelyincorporated in the new Dominion of India.


</content>
</cab>
