<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/35/0 images: 140-143</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*f 1Mis pccu: eet-^-T? IS TiPROPERTY OF II1S BRITAEITIC majesty*S GO vTEuTMEET)4is0. 3IHBTCOAL SITUATIO:SECEETAEY^S NOTES of c Conference held at 11 Dor/hinrStreet, So       on Saturday 14th February, 1920;at 4oP*HoP R E STThe Rt* Eon. A.Bonar Law, K.P.    (in the   Chair)The Rt. Eon. Sir A.C-Ge deles s K.C.E.,hop., President of the Board ofTrr.de -The&apos; Rt * Hon.vSir Robert Rome, K.B.week.. E.P*, Minister of 3sabour.The Rt. Eon- Sir Eric geddes,G&quot; o C o 1&apos;&apos;; ftp    Ct i     e jjj o . s    i&apos;...   3?   ^Minister cf  transport the F0LLG7 TEG EBEE ALSO S5MSE1TTsiir &quot;;;.C0Bridpe.man, M.P., Parliamentary Sir Philip Nash,- K.C..M.G, CESecretary Board of Trade Ministry of Transport.Er A.E.L&apos;unoan, Coal Controller.Mr u *Gr.Eyiiard, CcBcE. ,Ministry cf Shipping.Mr Thomas Jones Secretary.
(1)(2)(3)(-:-)The Conference were informed that the coal situation was extremely grave *     There m imminent riskof a coal famine in cone districts am?, many M the PublicUtility undertakings ha&amp;&apos;  less thai; two days&apos; supplies.The position in Tirminghmu was very bad and there werein hand in London household reserves for only four days.The output in all aroas was is *,provine and tt&amp;s roughlyat the r?.te of 240,000,00c tons as compared with229,000,00.&apos;. in 1910 and 227,000,000 in 1918.     As industry had revived demand had incueased,but,up to the present,production had been equal to the demand.     There were substantial reserves of coal in South &quot;Tales and in thoITorth  astern district sufficient to remove the dangernow threatening if only they could be transported to the inland di tricts mainly affected.      It was necessary totransfer about 750,00   tons a month. (-100,000 by sea and350,00. by rail).The main reasons alleged fox&quot; the present critical situation wer., :The reduced coal output in the MidlandDistrict itself end the absence of stocks&apos;owing to the Yorkshire Coal strike and. theRailway strike.The transport by rail  j    -    i to London and elsewhere from the ITorth eastern and South.Tales districts of coal formerly borne by sea.Tho failure to return uag;ong re pidly fromthe ports.The failure to requisition and divert shipsfron cross-channel to coastwise traffic.(Against this it was urged that since Novemberthere had be n a considerable Increase in the coasting service and the amount conveyed toLondon last week was the highest since beforethe \!cX*     Any further:&apos; increase would meanintolerable congestion at the ports.)
The Conferonce were remindod that tho averred policyof the Govor*nmont was to limit export in tho interestsof equalising tho homo supply *The Conference decidods(1)   Thai, In vlou of poocihle labour troubles,priority of supply should be given for thepresent to public utility undertakings and the domestic needs of tho larger towns, even atthe risk of causing some industries to shut ,down.bad of dislocating the railway passenger service.(2)   That arrangements ohould bo made by tho Ministryof Shipping to convoy during the next monthan additional 20,000 tons of coal by sea toLondons(S) That during the same period 20,000 tons whichwould be convoyed by rail to London should bodiverted to the Midlands.(4)   That, subject to the power of the ports tohandio the traffic, the Ministry of shipping should co    ntinuo to requisition and divertas mcch shipping as possible so as to rcstercthe pre-war coastwise traffic *(5)   That the Minister of Transport, tho ShippingController and tho President of the Board ofTrade snould appoint three representatives who should meet: (a^- to review the present schemeof distribution; and (h) to ad&amp;Lso tho RailwayCompanies from day to day as to the transportprogrammes required in the host Intorosts of thocountry.(6)   That the Railway Companies c once mod should beInvited to set up an organfcs ation to co-operate with the above Committee, the representativecf    the Ministry of Transport to act as liaison .of f ic or.(7)   That the public should be informed by moans ofa question and answer In the House of commons on Monday that, owing to scarcity in the Midlands,the Government wore taking urgent measures to remedy the equation and those measures wouldprobably cause some dislocation In the trainservices * (The President of the Board of Tradeundertook to prepare tho question and answerfor the Leader of the House-)
IB) That, pith reference to U. liillerandfs request to thePri o Minister for an increase of 3000 tons a day intho supply of gas coal for Paris/tho President of theBoard of Trade should reply th wt? -owing to the graveposition at hone, it pas not possible *t present tocomply trith tho request-.liitohali Gardens, S*:;.14th Fobrxiiary, 1920

</content>
</cab>
