<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/35/0 images: 191-205</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
f.(TMsJDocument is th^ :rIZjQ jglir i j bMa 1 es tv&apos; i Qovarnmrnrh )britannic? E 0 R E T1THE GOAL STRIKE,NOTES of a Conversation between representatives of theGovernment and the Executive of the Miners&apos; Federationheld at 10, Downing Street, S.W.1, on TUESDAY, OCTOBERr261920, at 11 a.m. 5PRESENT t-FOR THE GOVERNMENT.The Prime Minister.Mr Bonar Law.Sir Robert Horne.Mr Bridgeman.The Coal Controller.Sir David Shackleton.Sir Maurice Hankey.Mr Thomas Jones. .THE MINERS&apos; EXECUTIVE.Mr Smillie.Mr Frank Hodges.Mr Robson.Mr Herbert Smith.Mr Brace.Mr Hartshorn.Mr Winstone.Mr Barker.    etc. etcMr HODGES stated the case for the miners:-   Our suggestionis an extension of your proposal of yesterday dealing withvalues.   We rule out any solution on the basis of outputquantities.    The values basis is an arithmetical mirror ofthe output proposal, but with other phrases, yet leaving theprinciple the same.   Your proposal, in point of time, wouldnot bring peace.    A variation in wages might take place four weeks from the resumption of work.    It is not in the country&apos;s
-interest or in the interest of the trade to have anotherdisturbance in four weeks.    Primarily, therefore, we would ask you to extend the period of time.    Secondly, let us takethe only reliable data the Government has, namely,  thatpublished by the Mines Department under the Goal industry act.    The 2/- should be paid until those data are availablefor us all, and if the data reveal that values are accruingwhich will enable the 2/- to be continued, then it&apos; should becontinued until and unless the permanent scheme would deter-mine that other changes were desirable.    If the Governmentwould agree on a date for the permanent scheme, e.g., january-ary 1st., the Government would be relieved then of anyfurther embarrassment.    We cannot get the data until towardsthe end of February.    When it is known, and no permanent scheme has been set up, then the wages of the subsequentQuarter would be modified by the information which we hadin respect of values.    So that if by increased output andvalues, even though the temporary scheme were still holdingthe field, we could arrive at figures which would determine the next advance of wages, if, e.g., there were  400,000available, we would ask for 4d. a shift increase at that time.If, on the other hand, output and values had gone down, sothat  400,000 or more would be required to make up the 2/-,we should be entitled to have a reduction.    At that point,which would operate in the April Quarter, we would ask you to agree that the owners&apos; profits should suffer becausevalues had not come up to a point to warrant the 2/-.    we ask you to expedite the setting up of the permanent scheme,and the laying down now of the date of the first report will help that.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Mr Hodges&apos; statement is really a -demand for an unconditional 2/---very skilfully obscured.-2-
The Government were prepared to submit the question of the2/- to arbitration.   We cannot agree to any arrangement which will drive us to draw on the taxpayers, or to put upthe price of home coal.    Your proposals might force us todip deeply into public funds.    The pool available for the experiment of paying immediately the 2/- is a limited one and a rapidly diminishing one.    It is diminishing at therate of  2,000,000 to  5,000,000 for each week of thestrike.Mr HODGES:    the longer thpetrike, the greater the expense.THE PRIME MINISTER:    The sum available will justify us inmaking the experiment for a limited time.    We are using the pool to enable you to get your constituents to agree to asettlement and to cover the period of experiment to ascertain whether the output is coming along.   Mr Hodges&apos; proposal ineffect is to give a guarantee of the 2/- until April.    Weare willing to use the money to enable the owners and themen to build up a pool out of which you can draw the extra%/-.   What really matters is a sound, permanent settlement and a favourable atmosphere for the negotiations for perman-ent peace.    That you would not get along the lines proposedby Mr Hodges.    I want the owners and men to come face totheface with/absolute necessity for concluding an arrangementat the earliest possible moment:    therefore our conclusion is that we must have an arrangement within the&apos; limits of ourmeans, without going to the Exchequer or to the consumers.We cannot go beyond an arrangement which will determineDecember wages by what is done in November.   We realise that within the first two weeks you cannot bring the output to a satisfactory figure;    you will want time to get into contact with the men, time to set up the Pit Committees,time to bring pressure on the owners and managers who are
not doing their best.    Therefore we propose that the first three weeks should not count, and that we should take thelast fortnight in November as the determining figure.Then in December, because of the complications of Christmas,we take the first four weeks in December as the determining factor for January.   With regard to a reduction in the 10per cent, of the owners&apos; profits, should that be on a fixedfigure?Mr HODGES: Yes.THE PRIME MINISTER:    All this is a purely temporaryscheme, without prejudice to the permanent scheme.    I am anxious to ha^e something to compel owners and men to cometo a rapid decision.Mr ROBSON:    Vttiat is in your mind?THE PRIME MINISTER:    In January.THE COAL CONTROLLER:    January 1st.Mr SMILLIE:    If the owners were here, they would sayyou could not do it.   You will have a dispute again quicklyif you lay/down impossible conditions as to the time.MSXK&amp;HEENX THE PRIME MINISTER:    I am told that we giveall the necessary time.Mr ROBSON:    Many of the bigger pits would have crushedin.Mr SMILLIE: In the shallow Lanarkshire pits we could do it and start right away; but in the majority of pitswhere the big output comes from there will be a big crush.THE COAL CONTROLLER:    The owners were prepared to take their risk on that fortnight.Mr HODGES:    We understand your scheme, and we cannotapprove it.   Your scheme is a scheme which in effect hasbeen turned down by the men, save in so far as the S/- is granted at once and not earned in advance.THE PRIME MINISTER:.   And we have brought the owners in.
Mr HODGES:    Our proposals deserve more careful consideration-tion.    We are not playing a game. It is the best contributionwe can make to help you to get over your difficulties.    Weare on the way to coming to an understanding of the commonneeds of the industry.    The strike has revealed the higgledy-piggledy character of the industry.   We need a sense of security in the men&apos;s minds, and also the knowledge thatthey must make their contribution.    We are not finessing;it is too critical.THE PRIME MINISTER:    What I object to is, not dippinginto the pool, but going beyond and putting up the price ofhome coal if output does not materialise.    I am looking ahead and not making difficulties.   Your scheme really means thatthe 2/- would be guaranteed for five months, whatever theoutptit.    In our scheme we gxxs (1) give you 2/- at once;(2) guarantee the September price   at the expense of the pool, certainly, and possibly at the expense of the Exchequer;(3) we are putting the owners in the same category as your-selves.   We cannot go beyond that, and you are asking us totake risks beyond that.Mr McGURK:    Where would the risk be?THE PRIME MINISTER:    We are taking the risk that prices would break. Now, supposing we get neither prices nor output,we would be forced to tell the public that we had got nothing.There is a great change in the coal market.    As a result ofthe Spa Conference the Germans are delivering 2,000,000 tonsa month to Prance, and. the Prench have now a surplus.   the americans are using their surplus ships to send coal out to scandinavia and the Argentine.    They have ships now on these as with coal , on the chance of a sale.    All that riskas to price we are taking.(THE PRIME MINISTER then referred to theRailway Settlement, in which he hadstriven to secure a fair bargain.)
Mr BONAR LAW:    Many, while glad of a settlement, willunfortunately attack us.Mr SMILLIE:    But suppose you put us in a position thatwe cannot deliver the goods?   What good will that do?Mr BARKER:    How much surplus have you in the pool?THE PRIME MINISTER:    We are losing  2,000,000 to  3,000,080a week by the strike, and offering to pay 2/- for the first two or three weeks after the resumption of work, when we shallnot be getting values.Mr HODGES:    The public had to pay for the advances in thecase of the railwaymen.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Yes,  and you remember the row, andthe campaign on the films against putting up the rates!(THE GOVERNMENT REPRESENTATIVES then with-drew; and were called in again at 2 o7 clock.)Mr SMILLIE:    Time is our difficulty.    To take Novemberas fixing December wages is a very difficult proposition forus to recommend.    Our difficulty is that we do not want tobe negotiating the new wages scheme at a time when we are threatened with a reduction of wages.    So we suggest thatyou should take the first three weeks in December as regu-lating wages for January, and that you should endeavour tosecure, before January is far advanced, the conclusion of ana- ti onal s e11 lement.THE PRIME MINISTER:    That, in effect, is a demand for aguar^tee of the 2/- to the end of December.    Supposing you said to us,  &quot;This is the only thing now between us&quot;, we would naturally strain and take greater risks;   but if this is justone out of several things, then it would make a difference.In reply to a point about ante-dating the Award, THEPRIME MINISTER said there was no precedent, when a strike wason,  for putting wages back to a point before the strike tookplace.
Mr BONAR LAW:    Suppose we meet you on this, is this asettlement?Mr SMILLIE:    This is the important thing.THE PRIME MINISTER:    We are taking the risk of pricesbreaking.Mr SMILLIE:    Sir Robert Home and Mr Duncan said that the probability is, if there is a settlement within a week, youwill be repleting stocks.    I take it that any stock&quot;put inwill be at export prices?SIR ROBERT HORNE:    Yes, we are agreed on that.THE PRIME MINISTER:    A ballot would put off the settle-ment for a fortnight.Mr BONAR LAW:    Supposing we agree, what would be yourprocedure?Mr SMILLIE:    We have not discussed that.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Time counts.(The Conference adjourned.)(At 5-45 the Government Representatives -The Prime Minister,, Sir Robert Home andMr Duncan   met and considered the pro-uosals put by Mr Smillie.)(At 4 p.in. the Government Representativesmet the Miners&apos; Representatives.)THE PRIME MINISTER:    We have considered your proposal,and with a desire to meet you, because this is the onlysubstantial   thing between us.    It is impossible for us toaccept your suggestion.    We want this new scheme to have afair trial   not a scheme apparently dependent on what isin the pool, but really a means of giving the 2/- withoutany fair hope of realising output.    If you wait until January1st. and the State is still losing money, ycu would say&quot;What is  the good if disturbing the coalfields now?    here is a permanent scheme not quite ready, we are makingadmirable progress with it.   Is it desirable that you should
make unrest by reducing tv,o o/j xeaucxng zne 2/- when we are so near a perman-ent settlement?&quot;    It would be a trap that we would get into.I am not using the word offensively.    We want a fair experi-ment on these lines, the Government taking the major risks.Mr Smillie says,  &quot;You must give us the necessary time toenable us to see if conditions improve&quot;.    There I agree.    i expressed the opinion that on an average of the coalfieldsa week would enable those concerned to get rid of the differ-ence created by the strike.    Since then I have made enquiries.These are the figures given me for Yorkshire.    The strikefinis lied on the 22nd.Mr HERBERT SMITH:    September 16th.THE PRIME MINISTER:    The output on the 23rd was 163,000 tons,on the 3oth it was 491,000 tons, and on the 6th. 688,000 tons.That is beyond the normal.    In about a week in South Wales,after the worst strikes, the pits were v/orking normally.    Ifthis strike is declared off on Thursday, the pits should bev/orking by November 10th. at their very highest.    If we gaveyou until January 1st. there are these two risks.    First, weshould be put into the position that we were disturbing thecoalfield   not that you were breaking faith.    It would notbe a bom fide trial of this particular experiment.    Secondly,we might find ourselves, if the output does not materialise,with a very bankrupt pool indeed, and one which you could not anticipate or improve in a few weeks&apos; time.    We should be forced to go back to the consumer and own up to an improvidentbargain.    You are asking us to take the whole of the risks.We say we will share them.   Your risk is the scaling down ofthe 2/-1    ours is that output will be late coming along, andthere may be a break in prices.    We are prepared to do this,to add a week to this morning&apos;s proposal.    Instead of thelast two weeks of November, we will go up to December 4, and
take those three weeks.    If we go beyond that, we get intothe region where it is not an output scheme.SIR ROBERT HORNE:    On this basis the January wages willbe on the three weeks of December, to&apos; the 25th, excludingChristmas week.Mr SMILLIE: &apos; Our Executive was a divided Executive onthis matter, but you have united them now.    They are notprepared to put that to the Conference.    I am amazed thatyou could come to us with such an offer,&apos; after what tookplace in the negotiations with the four officials of theFederation.Mr DUNCAN:    Someone did suggest  (i.e.,in the Conversationwith the four- officials) that it was a matter upon which wecould come and go.    I said &quot;We could give you a better pro-posal, two good weeks in November and four weeks in December&quot;.That was the best proposal for you.    It would give us twogood periods.Mr SMILLIE then reiterated the charge, that the terms nowproposed were less favourable than the terms which had beer-offered in the Conversations with the four officials. Hesaid:- You have come here now, and, having said you would go as far as I have said, you come to us with a less favour-able offer.After some controversy between Sir robert home and Mr Smillie as to what exactlyhad taken place  SIR ROBERT HORNE:    The material issue is as to the pool.We want you to get on to November as a part of the testperiod.    On your plan in November you will be getting the2/- and it. would be a dead period.    We want the test period to include part of November.Mr SMILLIE:    You do not take us as honest men!SIR ROBERT HORNE:    I am not impugning your good faith.
It makes a great difference if you are not on a test period.A fortnight of preparation is a pretty fair period.    In the yorkshire area the pits were not being looked after as they-are in this strike.    You want to put us in a difficult finan-cial position.Mr SMILLIE:    I want, as an individual,  to be able to go out now and say &quot;The country needs the coal, we want theoutput up for the sake of the country&quot;.    We cannot havedouble dealing.Mr BONAR LAW said there was nothing worse than thesereproaches, but the fact was that Mr Smillie assumed thatwhen Sir Robert Horne suggested that the two weeks shouldregulate the January wage,he (Mr Bpnar Law) had said to him&quot;Do you mean the wages change at the end of the two weeks&quot;.Mr SMILLIE:    But we could not get the figures a day afterthe two weeks.SIR ROBERT HORNE:    If you are put in a difficulty by thatsuggestion (i.e., on which there had been the misunderstand-ing), I ask now, Will you take the two weeks up to December11th to&quot;regulate the wages thereafter?Mr SMILLIE:    It&apos;is obviously impossible to get figures upto December 11th. in two days.SIR ROBERT HORNE:    We could do it.Mr SMILLIE: I said to our men,  &quot;The Government are pre-uarsd to give us two weeks in November, and two in December,and, if the figures justify it, the wages will continue&quot;.SIR ROBERT HORNE:    You eliminate any part of Novemberas counting at all.    My proposal is that the last two weeks in November should count.Mr HARTSHORN:    We must go out and urge the men to giveoutput, and you must put us in the position to do so.Mr SMILLIE:    Mr Hartshorn and I were on a Goal Mines-10-
Committee early in the War.    You laid down no conditions,and appealed for output.    There was no reward held out.   Wecould go out whole-heartedly, and sis did so.   You must remember that we held that 3/- was due to us before theStrike.THE PRIME MINISTER:    We have made substantial concessions to you, and what have you made to us?   We have gone so farthat there will be severe criticism of the Government.- MrBonar Law tells me that he put our proposals to two of hiscolleagues in the House of Commons  .two moderate men  and in their view the country will say that the Governmenthas surrendered.Mr HODGES:    Your offer is bad.    It is only a sense of dutywhich could force me to commend it, not because I believe init.    It is a scheme which has already been rejected.THE PRIME MINISTER: But we are guaranteeing the price, andare imposing terms on the owners.Mr HODGES:    Yon are imposing conditions on us which arewithout precedent.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Because we want oxitpxit and are notgetting it.Mr HODGES:    The Government is  trying to drive us from oneconcession to another.    We started our claim as from July14th, then conceded October 1st, and now you want it fromthe date when we resume work.Mr SMILLIE:    You may starve us, but we have gone thefurthest we can go.    Take the first three weeks in December,and do not interfere with wages until January.   You areforcing on us something which has never been asked from a trade Union.THE PRIME MINISTER:    In my profession I was paid by thefolio.Mr SMILLIE:    But there was no dilution.
Mr FINNEY:    Try again, Mr Prime Minister!    The men have turned down the datum line.Mr SMILLIE:    Would you,  in your profession, accept payment on the aggregate output of the profession?SIR ROBERT HORNE:    Would you accept payment on the indi-vidual plan? &apos;.Mr SMILLIE:    I never objected to payment by results untilthe management, during the Control period,  tried to get themen down to low rates and retarded, wages.    Coal-getters,unlike other trades, refused daily rates of wages.THE PRIME MINISTER:    I am sorry to get to a dead end over this.    If you can think of some new avenue   Sir robert home says we will go to December 11th, because there has-been a bona fide misunderstanding.    There is nothing worse than the appearance of bad faith.    I would support him onthat date.Mr BONAR LAW:    Agreed.Mr SMILLIE:    We shall be meeting the owners and trying toget a permanent scheme determining the proportions forthe mine-owners, the miners, and the State.    How can weset up a, new satisfactory wages arrangement if there is areduction of wages going on?THE PRIME MINISTER:    That bears out what I have beensaying.    A fortiori, would you be able to argue in Januarythat we should not bring wages down when you are so near apermanent settlement?    You are really asking unconditional surrender. We can.face the public saying that we have had agive-and-take arrangement, but they will not understand acomplete surrender on our part.Mr SMILLIE:    You told the Chairman of the Coal Commissionto report in four weeks.   Why not say now that on January 2the owners and the men must report?THE PRIMEMCNISTER:    But suppose they do not?-13-
SIR ROBERT HORNE:    The settlement of the permanent scheme must take some time, perhaps from three to six months.There would be all the tonnage rates to be dealt with.Mr HARTSHORN:    The permanent scheme raises an entirely different set of considerations from tonnage rate.    Thegeneral wage agreement should take a shorter time.(THE government representatives then withdrewand met the Miners&apos; Representatives again at 5-25.)Mr SMILLIE:    When we talked of three weeks, Sir RobertHorne said that there was no incentive to output in November.We now agree to take two weeks in November, and three weeks in December, and on the average output of those weeks todetermine the January wages.    It would be impossible to get to the full output before those two weeks.TEE PRIME MINISTER:    We are now at a very crucial pointin the negotiations,   and I should like to consider yourpresent proposal.    It may be necessary to get the Cabinettogether.    Before we separate I should like to put one ques-tion.   Do I understand that the proposal is this:    that thefive weeks should be the testing period, and that if the values do not realise the figures which are agreed upon between us, then the 2/- will automatically scale off?Mr SMILLIE:    That is your proposal.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Would scale off automatically from january 1st.    The employers&apos; would be automatically scaledoff, too.    The same principle will apply to the mine owners.If the values are not reached, both mine owners and minerswill automatically scale off.Mir SMILLIE:    The Prime Minister accepted in good faith theword of the owners.SIR ROBERT HORNE:    I will trust you.(The ConferenceJbhen adjojmigtj^lilJ^^^the Prix^elKnister undertaking, to cxrcu-late a written statement of the Government&apos;sproposals..) -13-
(A Meeting of the Cabinet was held at 6 p,m.(See Cabinet 57 (20) .)(At 7-45 p.m.  the Conference reassembled.when the following were present:-The Prime Minister. The Miners&apos; Executive,Mr Bonar Law.Sir Robert Home.Sir David Shackle ton.Mr Bridgeman.Sir Philip Lloyd-Greame.Sir Maurice Hankey.Mr T.Jones.THE PRIME MINISTER:    Since our last meeting we have hada meeting of the Cabinet.    I am anxious to.avoid any possiblemisunderstanding, and I had hoped to put into writing theGovernment&apos;s proposals.    For this hhere has not been enoughtime;    neither has there been time for me to see the owners,with the exception of two of them.    The owners have been summoned for a meeting tomorrow morning at 10-50.    It isessential to get their co-operation, as they are involvedin the question of output and will have to be scaled downif there is not the output.    The two owners I have seencannot commit the rest.    I shall have the written statementready for them by 10-50 tomorrow, and then I propose to meetyou at 12 Noon.Mr SMILLIE:-   We accept that, if no other arrangement ispossible.    In your first letter you mentioned that theowners were prepared to co-operate as to output.THE PRIME MINISTER:    But the scaling down is a seriousbusiness.Mr BONAR LAW:    Secrecy will be continued until tomorrow.Mr HODGES:    Can you give a reply to the last questionput by Mr Smillie at the end of our previous meeting?THE PRIME MINISTER:    No.Mr SMILLIE:    We regret the delay.THE PRIME MINISTER:    So do we;   but the mine owners
might turn us down.    It is important that we should get their hearty co-operation, and that they, should not go awaysulky.(The Conference adjourned until IS Moonon the following day.)(A Shorthand Mote was taken of all the subsequent Conferences with the owners and the Miners&apos; Executive.)2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,October 86, 1920.-15-

</content>
</cab>
