<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/43/32 images: 274-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   November 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 532.22nd November, 1943.WAR CABINET.DESIGN AND CONSTRUCTION OF POST-WAR CIVIL AIRCRAFT.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air and the Minister of aircraft Production.IN Paper W.P. (43) 83, an outline was given of five new types of civil aircraft and of certain converted military types, the production of which was recommended by the inter-Departmental Committee under Lord Brabazon to meet our post-war civil air transport requirements.2. The War Cabinet considered this Paper on the 25th February and directed that (a) Work on the design of the new types and the conversion of military typesshould proceed under Government direction as and when this couldbe done without impairing the war effort.(b) The Governments objective in arranging for preliminary work was tosecure the production after the war of British transport aircraft, civil and military, on a scale and quality in keeping with our worldposition; and(c) The Government should accept financial responsibility for the preparatorymeasure necessary, but that the Chancellor of the Exchequer shouldbe consulted before any expenditure was incurred beyond the prototype stage.3. After a review of the military commitments of the aircraft industry,certain firms were asked to submit tender designs for four out of the five newBrabazon types. The first of these types is a multi-engined landplanecapable of operating non-stop from London to New York. The Bristol aeroplane company were selected to design this type and have submitted a provisionaldesign for a machine of about 240,000 lb. all-up weight (four times the size ofthe York) with a cruising speed of about 250 m.p.h, and sleeping accommodation for 50 passengers. Alternatively, there is seating accommodation for close- on100 passengers, but this number of passengers could be carried only if a stopwere made at Newfoundland. This performance accords generally with the users&apos;requirements on which Lord Barabazon&apos;s Committee has reported.*4. The design involves many new features such as a pressure cabin,engines buried in the wing to improve aerodynamic efficiency, and the use of eight engines coupled in pairs. A major project such as this naturally demandsmuch experimental work and there are many aerodynamic and structuralproblems to be solved. It is, however, in the main stream of aeronautical develop-ment and will be of value for military as well as civil purposes.5. In the United States, the Consolidated Company are building a machineof 265,000 lbs. It reached the mock-up stage about six months ago. the americans have flying now the B. 29 bomber at 120,000 lbs., and the C. 89 Trans-port at 94,000 lbs.   There is at present under development for the R.A.F. no* Lord Brabazon&apos;s Committee was reconstituted last May to prepare for each new type alist of users&apos; requirements which would form the basis of detailed specifications.T26458]
landplane heavier that 80/90,000 lbs. There are many problems common to alllarge aircraft and it is essential from the military as well as the civil point ofview that our aircraft industry should get to grips with them without delay.Accordingly, we have given instructions for the work to proceed. It is estimatedthat the machine will not be in production for about six years.6.   A rough estimate of the capital cost is as follows :  First prototypeSecond prototype750,000500,000450,000400,000325.0003 aircraft additional to prototypes ... each12 aircraft additional to prototypes &apos; ... each20 aircraft additional to prototypes        ...   eachtThe Cabinet would wish to be aware that this work isin progress.a. h. m. S.R. S. C.22nd November, 1943.(



</content>
</cab>
