<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/14/0 images: 26-29</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S CfOVERNMTSECRET COPY NO.CP. (1+6) U0229TH OCTOBER,  19^6CABINETPROJECT FOR GROWING GROUNDNUTS IN EAST and central africa memorandum &quot;by the Secretary of State for the colonies and the Minister of food in their Report dated 20th September, 191+6, the GroundNot Mission in East and Central Africa recommended the settingup by His Majesty&apos;s Government of an enterprise to undertake the large scale production of groundnuts in Tanganyika,Northern Riiodesia and Kenya as an early and substantial contribution to the present shortage of oils and fats.2. Estimates based upon the recommendation of theMission suggest that the following production targets can beachieved during the next five years:-191+8...............    50,000 long tons of shelled nuts191+9 .............. .   200,000      &quot;        &quot;      11        &quot; &quot;1950............... hi 0,000    &quot;      &quot;    &quot;      &quot;        &quot;1951  and onwards ...  530,000     !&apos;        !l      11        &quot; &quot;3. Of the areas recommended for the project, whichtotal some 3*000,000 acres, 75% are in Tanganyika,  16-i inNorthern Rhodesia and 3% in Kenya.      All this land is atfpresent virtually uninhabited and completely undeveloped owinglargely to tsetse infestation.1+. Assuming that the project was started, at the beginningof I9I4.7, as recommended in the report, the total capital and operating expenditure and the net cash requirements would beas follows:-19U7 19U8 19U9 TotalTotal capital and OperatingExpenditure       3,630,000    8,7*4-0,000    13,080,000    25,^50,000%&quot;   Estimated/^proceeds of. :  crop NIL 1,510,000      6,020,000     7,530,000Net cash               3,630,000    7,230,000    7,020,000      17,920,000requirements     ______________   _______.___,_^___ A

-5- The Report has &quot;been referred to the new ColonialEconomic and Development Council who have strongly commendedit from the Colonial point of view, but preliminary studyat the official level suggests that before His Majesty&apos;sGovernment embark on so far reaching a project a fullinvestigation is necessary,  particularly of the financial&quot;aspects of the plan;    the availability of the equipment uponwhich so much depends, the availability of agents,  staff and labour;    the phasing of the programme;    the communicationsproblem;    the attitude of the Colonial Governments concernedwhose co-operation and assistance is vital,  and in particulartheir attitude regarding the provision of the necessaryrailv/ays, roads and ports;    the terms on which the colonial governments will take the scheme over in due course;    and allthe other issues which arise.6. The Minister of Food proposes to create within his department a Special Section which will be charged with theduty of examining the project in regard to the above and other relevant matters.      They will be required to make a report bythe end of November.7* It is, however,  clear that if &quot;land clearing operations are to be started early next year, with the object of producing a first crop in the Spring of 191+8,  action must be taken toobtain the necessary equipment forthwith.      It is, therefore,proposed that the Special Section to be established in theMinistry of Food shall not only be charged with an examinationof the project as a whole, but with making preparation forthe first year&apos; s activity.      This will mean entering intoa commitment of up to  3 millions in advance of a decision regarding the practicability and cost of the longer termscheme.      The precise -areas in which to start operations wouldbe determined by the Special SectionTs investigations;    but without authoritjr immediately to secure plant and seed,    nostart anywhere will be possible in 19U7-      The shortage offats is, however,  so acute that we recommend that this liabilityshould be accepted.      Any further liability will be dependentupon the result of -the examination of the scheme.8. The Special Section which it is proposed to establishin the Ministry of Food will be recruited from officials ofthat Department and the Colonial Office, with the addition ofsuch persons from commerce with expert knowledge of theproduction and handling of groundnuts as may be found necessary.9. A decision regarding the ultimate method of handling the project can best be taken when the proposed review of the longer term plan has been completed.      Our present view isthat a United Kingdom public corporation receiving its capitalas a loan from the Treasury should be sot up.      Until thiscorporation is set up it would be necessary for the Ministryof Food to make use of commercial    experience on an agencybasis,  e.g.  the United Africa Company and similar organisations,for carrying out the initial work.      In due course the project,if proceeded with would pass over, when firmly established,on terms to be agreed,  to the Colonial Governments concerned to operate as a public enterprise.i-i. C * J *J. s.


</content>
</cab>
