<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/5/59 images: 812-827</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.P. (R)(hp)  109April 3rd 19U0Copy No.WAR      CABINET&quot;Economic Warfare.27th Report submitted bythe Minister of Economic warfare covering the period March 17th-31st.(Previous Report:    Paper No. W.P. (R)(UO)98).(Initialled) R. H. 0.Richmond Terrace, S.W.1

MINISTRY OP ECONOMIC WARFARE.Report on Action Taken for the period March 17th-31st.War Trade Negotiations and Relations with NeutralStates.The whole question of the Allied war trade policy has been under review during this period,  as the result of thereceipt of a communication from the French Ministry of Blockade,urging that measures should he taken to tighten the blockade and to ration neutrals.    The question will be discussed withthe French Minister of Blockade in London on April 5th.2.       During the period under review the Anglo-Danish war trade Agreement was brought&quot; into force,  and the Anglo-NetherlandsWar Trade Agreement was initialled.    Discussions have opened inLondon with a Yugoslav Delegation, headed by Dr. Belin of the yugoslav National Bank.    Negotiations about import quotas forHungary are continuing.GENERAL3.       On March 19th the French Mission communicated amemorandum from the French Minister of Blockade urging that consideration should be given to measures for tightening theblockade and for rationing neutrals.    The Allies,  it was suggested;should select a number of commodities essential for war purposes,preferably those which neutrals ,have already stocked In excessivequantities, and should detain or    seize consignments of these commodities in certain circumstances.    In this connection theFrench memorandum advocated an extension of the navicert system to cover a greater number of consignor countries;    and the suspension of the issue of navicerts when a country&apos;s importshas reached a certain total.    It would at the same time be announced that all goods not accompanied by navicerts would be liable/

liable to &quot;be detained and even unloaded for enquiry.   . TheFrench memorandum suggested that this /policy might be inauguratedin our relations with Belgium,  the Netherlands,  Switzerland, andthe Nordic countries;    in the case of Italy,  there were very definite political factors to he taken into account, but thecontinually increasing figures of Italian oil imports showed the necessity for tightening our control measures.Ll.      Monsieur Monnet,  the new French Minister of Blockadewill visit London on April 5th to discuss the foregoingmemorandum,  and the general question of rationing neutrals.NORWAY.5.      Mr, Hambro and Lord Glenconner have visited Oslo todiscuss with the Norwegian authorities various questions connected with economic -warfare including the constitution ofthe Mixed Commission contemplated by the War Trade Agreement.6.      The Anglo-Danish War Trade Agreement was brought intoforce on the 22nd March.    Formal signature will take place onthe 2nd April.FINLAND .7-     With the conclusion of hostilities between finland and the U.S.S.R. it has been necessary to bring to an end thespecial regime whereby the Swedish and Norwegian governments could,  despite guarantees of non-re-export send to Finlandgoods required for the prosecution of the war,  and whereby HisMajesty&apos;s Government undertook to facilitate the replacement of goods so re-exported.    The Swedish, Norwegian and DanishGovernments have also been informed that Finland must for thetime being he excluded from the block of Scandinavian countries to which goods on the prohibited list may be freely exportedunder the War Trade Agreements.8.    Finland will thus be treated in the same way as anyother adjacent neutral with whom no War Trade Agreement has been signed, and guarantees will be required for goods consigned toher/

a boher either from Empire sources or passing through the ContrabandControls.   As an interim measure such guarantees will be furnished by the Finnish Legation in LondonBALTIC STATES .9.     Conversations are proceeding with the LatvianDelegation who have been informed of the general principles on which we should like to conclude a War Trade Agreement.BELGIUM.10.     The special agreement on lubricating oils has nowbeen concluded and has been brought into force as from March13 th.T HE NETHBRLAHD 3 .11. The War Trade Agreement was initialled on March 21stand it is hoped that it -will be brought into force at an early-date .SWITZERLAND.12.     The Swiss Delegation left Paris on the 21st Marchwithout initialling an Agreement.    We have suggested certain amendments of the final draft text, which the French Governmentare considering.13. His Majesty&apos;s Legation in Berne has been informed of the proposal to introduce a quota control for the import of raw cotton into Switzerland.HUNGARY.14.      Negotiations in regard to the import quotas to heestablished under the rationing agreement are continuing.    the quotas for lead and copper have not yet been agreed, but onany calculation they are exhausted.    The borax quota which hasbeen agreed is also exhausted.   Any new shipments of these three commodities will now be detained.YUGOSLAVIA/

15.     Letters have heen exchanged between His MajestylsLegation, Belgrade and the Yugoslav National Bank concludingan agreement rationing imports of raw cotton on a quarterlybasis.16.     Discussions are being held with Dr. Belin, Vice-Governor of the Yugoslav National Bank, supported by the yugoslav Minister.   Dr. Belin is in London in order to exploregeneral questions affecting Yugoslavia arising out of contraband control.    At his request,  draft War Trade and- Rationing Agreements have been communicated to him semi-officially.SOVIET RUSSIA.17.     It has been decided that the Soviet s.s. &quot;Selenga&quot;,which has been under detention at Hong Kong since the middleof January,  is to be handed over to the French authoritiesin the Far East, who will deal with the cargo of wolfram,antimony etc., on board,   A further Soviet vessel, the s.s.&quot;Vladimir Mayakorsky&quot; has been intercepted on her way from america with a cargo of copper for Vladivostock, and willalso be handed over to the French.IRAN.18.     In the middle of February it was reported that theGermans were on the point of purchasing some 8,000 tons ofIranian cotton, and consideration was given to the desirabilityof acquiring this cotton in order to prevent its sale toGermany,   This cotton has now been bought by Italian interests,and it is reported that this disposes of the balance of lastyear&apos;s crop of Iranian cotton.Contraband Agreements and General Contraband Questions.19.     General undertakings of non-enemy destination havebeen given by the following Roumanian subsidiaries of SoconyVacuum/- k -

Vacuum Oil Company covering all their imports passing through our control;   Vacuum Oil Company S.A.d.R. and &quot;Photogen&quot;Rafineria de Tetrol S.A.Mewcerts:20.     Pending the introduction of the navicert system for Egypt and the Anglo-Egyptian Sudan, the practice ofissuing &quot;Mewcerts&quot; is in force at Alexandria and Port Sudan.Mewcerts, which are issued hy War Trade Reporting officers at Alexandria and at Port Sudan, are to some extent analogous to Navicerts.    The chief difference is that Mewcert applicationsare granted on the receipt of satisfactory declarations of ultimate destination hy the issuing officer and without waiting for the consent o,f the Ministry, v/hich is, however,informed,  and may cause the Mewcert to he cancelled.   Afurther safeguard exists in the form of quantitative controlof Egyptian and Sudanese exports, particularly of cotton.Mewcerted cargo Is granted almost as high a degree of immunity from contraband control as is navicerted cargo.Consignments toiA.N. I.jO.21,     The practice of having goods for Holland,particularly from the Dutch East Indies, consigned to thisgovernmental import bureau has caused a certain amount ofanxiety lest the ultimate consignees whose names were unknownto us might in some cases be re-exporting to Germany in spiteof the control exercised by the A.N.I.C itself.    It has nowbeen arranged that we have the right to,call on the NetherlandsLegation to supply us v/ith the names of ultimate consigneeswhenever we choose,  it being understood that this right willbe reasonably exercised,  i.e., only invoked where some positivegrounds for suspicion exist.    This arrangement has so farworked fairly well,  though names have not always been furnishedspeedily enough to avoid certain delays to shipping.

-   d   -22.      Instances have occurred in which consignments forScandinavian and Baltic neutrals (including Russia) haveheen routed through Germany.    In order to put a stop to this practice,  steps are heing taken to see that navicerts are granted only on condition that goods do not pass throughGermany,   end also that Destination Undertakings specify thata non--German route will he used.11. Contraband Contro1,23.      During the fortnight ending 30th March 185 newcases of ships were dealt with and 68 previous cases,  inregard to whose cargoes or items thereof enquiries had beencompleted, were disposed of.24.      In 116 cases entiro cargoes were released,   either on first consideration or   after enquiries.25.     The system under which advance copies of manifestsof cargoes are received and considered before the ships&apos;arrival at ports in this country resulted, during the fortnightunder review,  in 129 cases being so dealt with and in 75 casesof the ships concerned being released by the Committee subjectmerely to the formal checking of the original manifests ontheir arrival at the Control Bases and of 10 ships being given &quot;Missing Kirkwall&quot; clearances.    In addition to theseimmediate releases,  in 16 other cases the Committee&apos;s decisionto release was given within 5 days or less of the arrival ofships at the Control Bases.    Of ships released h4 sailed underHold-Back Guarantees.26.      Ten ships are known to have evaded the patrolsduring this period.Navicerts.27.      In the two weeks ending 30th March,  5181 Navicertapplications were received.    From the inauguration of thesystem/

system to date 39?491 applications have heen received ofwhich 32,332 or 82;o have heen granted,  and 191 frilly navi-certed ships have passed our controls (including 78 which had&quot;ship navicerts&quot;),IV. Report of the Enemy j3-x^iqrtjs-Ccmj:]itteeM for the weekending Satiu^day,   23rd March, i 1940.28.      During the past fortnight the Committee reviewed12 ships.    The Committee decided that items of cargo from three of these should he discharged and placed in prize.In connection with another ship, which the Committee hadalready reviewed ordering certain items of admittedly Germanorigin to he discharged and placed in Prize, the Committeewas invited to consider a letter from the Netherlands Legationin London,  regretting the Gommitiee5s decision and stating  -that the 22 cases of steel which had. heen ordered to heplaced in Prize had heen ordered from Germany on 29.7.39and that the Netherlands Government was in all circumstancesresponsible for payment.    The Netherlands Legation had alreadybeen informed by the Ministry that consignments from theNetherlands Government to its Colonial Governments would runless risk of delay if they were covered by export-passes andstowed accessibly, but this was the first occasion on whichthe Netherlands Legation had paid any attention to theMinistry&apos;s letter.    The Committee decided.that a letter should be sent to the Netherlands Legation, referring&apos; to theMinistry&apos;s previous letter and pointing out that such difficulties as the present one&apos; might be avoided by suitableaction on the part of the Netherlands Government.29.      The Committee considered 113 specific applicationsfor exemption,   granting 45 (10 conditionally) refusing 55;and deferring consideration of the rest.   A large number of applications are treated summarily.


</content>
</cab>
