<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 28-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  April 1955SECRET Copy No.    5CM. (55)2nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1.,on Tuesday, 12th April, 1955, at 5-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord De l&apos;isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air(Item 1).The Right Hon. Patrick BuchanHepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury (Item 5).Secretariat;The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Minister of Supply (Item 1).48023-2b
contents minute no. Subject page 1      Northern Ireland        ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3Relief of Unemployment.2     European Defence      ...      ...............       33     Formosa ...............      ...      ...       44      Industrial Disputes      ............      ......       5Newspapers.5     Cotton   .........................       5
1. The Home Secretary said that the reductions which were now to be made in the orders for Swift fighter aircraft would havethe result that substantial numbers of workers would be dismissedfrom Shorfs aircraft factory in Belfast. The general level ofunemployment was much higher in Northern Ireland than in Englandand Wales, and plans for remedying that situation had been underdiscussion with the Northern Ireland Government for some time past.The hopes that had been founded on those discussions would be disappointed if large numbers of workers were thrown out ofemployment in Belfast as a result of adjustments in the Governmenfsown programme of aircraft production. This situation could be eased by placing with Shorfs an order for ten additional Canberraaircraft, some of which might be sold to India. This would providecontinuing employment for about 600 of the 1,300 workers whowould otherwise be discharged at once from Shorfs.In discussion it was pointed out that this proposal involved aserious financial risk. It was not certain that India would buy any ofthese Canberra aircraft. Nor were they needed for the first-line strength of the Royal Air Force. The Treasury would therefore beassuming a potential liability for their total cost, which would amountto about  1^ millions. This was a heavy liability to assume in respectof a short-term expedient, when the Northern Ireland Governmentwere failing to show sufficient initiative and energy in pursuing thelong-term remedy of attracting light industry to Northern Ireland.On the other hand, it was argued that the United KingdomGovernment would bear a direct responsibility for this particularincrease in unemployment in Belfast since this was a Government-owned factory. The aircraft industry in Belfast had already suffered severely by the interruption in the production of Comet aircraft, andpublic opinion in Northern Ireland would be gravely disturbed if afurther substantial contraction had now to be made in the labour force employed there by Shorfs. There were other possible overseas markets for Canberra aircraft, apart from India, and there was areasonable prospect that purchasers would be found for these tenaircraft.It was the general view of the Cabinet that every possible effort should be made to reduce the number of workers to be discharged from Shorfs aircraft factory in Belfast as a result of the government&apos;s decision to reduce their orders for the production of Swift fighter aircraft. But, when taking measures to this end, the Governmentshould again impress upon the Government of Northern Ireland the urgent need for effective action by them to diversify the pattern ofindustry in Northern Ireland.The Cabinet Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to consider, inconsultation with the Minister of Defence and Minister ofSupply, whether the prospects of finding overseas purchaserswere such as to warrant his under-writing the cost of placingan order for the manufacture of ten additional Canberraaircraft at Shorfs aircraft factory in Belfast.2. The Foreign Secretary said that there had been somedisturbing indications that the French Government might seek to delay their ratification of the Paris Agreements in order to be sure of securing all their objectives in respect of the Saar. He still hoped,however, that all the ratifications would be completed in time toenable the German Federal Republic to be admitted to the north atlantic Treaty Organisation at the meeting of the North atlantic council which was to be held early in May. He was now trying to persuade all the Governments concerned to work to a definite time-table which would make that possible.The Cabinet &apos;Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.48023-2 b 2
Formosa.(previous reference:C.C. (55) 21stConclusions,Minute 2.)3,  The Foreign Secretary said that the Prime Minister ofAustralia had been discussing with the United States Secretary ofState a proposal that, if the Chinese Nationalists were willing to evacuate their forces from the islands off the China coast, the interested Powers should jointly declare their readiness to assist in resisting any Communist attack on Formosa.  Such a guarantee ofthe security of Formosa would in his view be neither appropriatenor desirable: it was most unlikely to commend itself to publicopinion in this country.  Mr. Menzies had asked for an expression ofour views on this proposal, and it would be possible to put before him the difficulties and dangers which we saw in it. It was, however,desirable that he should also be made aware of the views of other interested Commonwealth Governments: it was known that theCanadian Government, in particular, would not favour such aproposal.   The Foreign Secretary had therefore prepared draft telegrams setting out the objections to this plan and suggesting thatthe Governments of Canada and New Zealand should be consulted before Mr. Menzies became involved in anything approaching a commitment to Mr. Dulles.   This alone, however, might seem toMr. Menzies to be a wholly negative response to his initiative, andit would be preferable that some constructive alternative should alsobe suggested. The Foreign Secretary had therefore considered whether there was any other means by which we might hope tosecure the evacuation of the Chinese Nationalists from the coastalislands without offering any guarantee of the security of Formosa.It seemed to him that it would be worth while to put forward, forconsideration by other interested Governments, a double proposal first that those Governments should give some assurance that, if afull-scale attack were launched against Formosa, they would regardthat as a provocative action and a breach of international peace andwould give their full support to any measures which the united nations might decide to take to deal with the situation; and secondly,that in the meantime any four-Power meeting which might be held inthe near future should consider what procedures might be adopted for international discussion of the current situation in the FormosaStraits. This alternative proposal would be broached, not only with australia, but also with Canada and New Zealand,   The foreign secretary read to the Cabinet the drafts of the telegrams which hehad prepared setting out the difficulties of the proposed guaranteeand explaining his alternative proposal.The Commonwealth Secretary said that care would have to betaken to avoid any impression that the United Kingdom Governmentwere consulting other Commonwealth Governments on the merits of a proposal evolved in private and confidential exchanges between mr, Menzies and Mr. Dulles. This difficulty might be averted if our proposals were related, not to those exchanges, but to Presssuggestions of a possible guarantee of Formosa. It would also be helpful if the proposed approach to the Governments of Canada andNew Zealand were delayed for a day or so after our intentions hadbeen made known to Mr. Menzies, so that he might have anopportunity of informing us of his preliminary views on it.In discussion there was general support for the proposal outlined by the Foreign Secretary.The Cabinet-(1) Approved in principle the proposals outlined by the foreign secretary for diverting the Prime Minister of Australiafrom pursuing his project for a multilateral guarantee ofthe security of Formosa.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to concert with the Common-wealth Secretary the form and timing of any approach to the Governments of Canada and New Zealand on thissubject.
5 CM. 2 (55)Industrial 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the disputes. Minister of Labour (CP. (55) 3) on the stage reached in the disputeNewspapers. between the Newspaper Proprietors&apos; Association (N.P.A.) and the(Previous unions representing employees of the national newspapers.Reference: The Minister of Labour said that he expected to receive the cm. (55) 1st report of the Court of Inquiry that evening and to publish it on theConclusions, following afternoon. It was likely that the main features of the minute 2.) report would be (i) condemnation of the wage claim made by theAmalgamated Engineering Union (A.E.U.) and the Electrical TradesUnion (E.T.U.) as wholly unrealistic; (ii) an expression of the viewthat the existing negotiating machinery in the industry was inadequate; (iii) a suggestion that the N.P.A. and all the unions concerned should consider urgently how this machinery might be improved; and (iv) a recommendation that in the meantime work should be resumed. He would himself do all in his power to promoteaction in accordance with the Court&apos;s recommendations. The A.E.U.and the E.T.U. might, however, prove obdurate and in that event thedispute was likely to continue for some time. It would not be right for the Government to press the N.P.A. to make concessions. he understood that the N.P.A. were considering possible means ofincreasing the existing supply of newspapers but the scope for suchaction was very limited.In discussion there was general support for the view that theGovernment would be ill-advised to urge the N.P.A. to make any concession on the wages claim.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Minister of Labour.Cotton.(previous reference:CM. (55) 1stConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Presidentof the Board of Trade (CP. (55) 1 and 2) on the possibilities ofGovernment action to relieve the current difficulties of the cottonindustry.The President of the Board of Trade said that he had described in CP. (55) 2 the steps which would be necessary if the cabinet should decide to restrict the import of grey cotton cloth from Indiawithout taking similar action against the import of such cloth from hong Kong. He did not himself recommend this course. It would do little to help the cotton industry, whose present difficulties were mainly due to loss of exports. On the other hand, it would be likelyto have a number of unfortunate commercial consequences including,in all probability, the loss of our present trade agreement with India.For the reasons given in CP. (55) 1 he would much prefer thecomplete removal of purchase tax on all textiles and clothing, forthis would help to secure increased production of the finer cotton goods upon which the long-term future of the industry depended.In addition, the Government would be able to claim that they were taking action to prevent unfair Japanese competition and wouldreap any benefit from tariff concessions which the Government ofIndia might now make on imports of cotton textiles from this country.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had been inclined to favour the imposition of a quota on retained imports of Indiangrey cotton cloth as a preliminary to the introduction of a measureof tariff protection. He was convinced that it would not be possibleto maintain indefinitely the system of duty-free entry for all Common-wealth goods. The position had, however, been altered by theprospect that, as a result of the recent visit to India of a trade mission from Lancashire, the Indian Government would lower their duty on imports of cotton textiles from this country sufficiently to increasesubstantially their present volume. It would seem right as a next stepto explain our general attitude to the Government of India and to
seek to obtain from them a firm statement of their intentions inregard to the duty oh imports of cotton textiles from the UnitedKingdom.The President of the Board of Trade said that, while he agreedthat the present moment was particularly inopportune forcontemplating protective action against Indian cotton textiles, theCabinet should not overTestimate the significance of any prospective increase in the volume of Indian imports of cotton textiles fromLancashire. The cotton industry had at first been reluctant to send a mission to India for fear that any resulting increase in exportsmight be used to justify inaction as regards imports into this country of Indian grey cloth. They had been assured that the government regarded these two matters as quite distinct. The estimated increasein exports of cotton textiles to India as a result of a possible lowering of the Indian protective duty amounted only to some 10 million square yards which, although useful, would fall far short of lancashire^ expectations of assistance.There was general agreement in the Cabinet that the Governmentcould not announce a decision to restrict the import of Indian clothinto this country at the very moment when the Indian Governmentwere considering the relaxation of their restrictions on imports ofcotton textiles from the United Kingdom. At the same time therewas support for the view that additional exports of 10 million square yards of cotton textiles, which were worth about  If millions, would hardly be enough to allay Lancashire&apos;s anxieties. The Cabinet were,however, informed that there was little practical scope either for negotiating a still further increase in the volume of our exports ofcotton textiles to India or for inducing the Government of India tomake other concessions in our favour. In these circumstances theGovernment would be strongly pressed to supplement by other meansany concession that the Government of India might make in relaxingtheir present restrictions on imports of cotton goods from Lancashire.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Presidentof the Board of Trade, in consultation with the Common-wealth Secretary, to prepare and submit for the PrimeMinisters approval the draft of a communication to theIndian Government explaining the difficulties with whichthe Government were faced as a result of the rise in thevolume of imports of Indian grey cotton cloth into thiscountry and the action which we might find it necessaryto take to solve these difficulties, and asking for as early and clear an indication as possible of the intentions ofthe Indian Government in regard to Indian imports ofcotton textiles from this country.(2) Agreed that, pending receipt of a reply to the communication to be sent under Conclusion (1) above, replies to parliamentary Questions on this subject should so far aspossible be confined to the statement that the Governmentwere now in negotiation with the Government of india on the question.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,12th April, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
