<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 223-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1955SECRETCM. (55)27th conclusions copy No. 43CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,- on Thursday, 28th July, 1955, at 2/ 30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir anthony the Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury,  Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Selvvyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister oi Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The R.ight Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister   of   Housing   and   LocaiGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P.,    Minister    of    Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.Also present:The Right Hon. Henry Hopkinson,M.P., Minister of State for colonial affairs (Item 1).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. H. O. Hooper.48552-3
oM25MinuteNo.1234567ContentsCyprus   ...Conference with Greek and Turkish Governments.Military Headquarters.PalestineJapanese War CriminalsLegislative Programme:  1955-56 SessionEconomic SituationNewsprint        ............ChinaRequest for visit by Parliamentary Delegation.Cabinet...............Procedure during recess.Page356799
Cyprus. 1.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Minister of conference Defence (CP. (55) 94) covering the report of the Committee whichwith Greek and they had appointed on 14th June to consider what proposals forTurkish further constitutional advance in Cyprus could be put forward at theGovernments, forthcoming Conference with representatives of the Greek and(Previous        Turkish Governments.Reference: The Foreign Secretary said that he had been anxious to avoidCM. (55) 23rd putting forward proposals which implied that the Cypriot claim to conclusions, self-determination would be admitted at some future date; for pastMinute 6.) experience suggested that this would give rise to increasing pressure for the withdrawal of British rule from the Island. He had hopedthat it would be possible to devise a practical alternative plan bywhich the Greek and Turkish Governments would accept thecontinuance of British rule in Cyprus in return for some form, of association with the administration of the Island. The colonial secretary was still very doubtful, however, whether proposals on those lines (Annex A of CP. (55) 94) would be practicable. Hepreferred the alternative (Annex B of CP. (55) 94) of a progressiveadvance to full internal self-government. The Cabinet should recognise that, if a plan of the latter kind were adopted, we should ineffect be relying on the Turkish Government to maintain, when that stage was reached, an effective veto against the grant of self-determination to the Cypriots. Much therefore would turn on theattitude adopted by the Turkish representatives at the forthcoming conference. If they should show a resolute opposition to Greekclaims in respect of Cyprus, it might still be possible to make some progress with proposals on the lines of Annex A of CP. (55) 94.In discussion there was general support for the view that a plan on the lines of Annex A of CP. (55) 94 was unlikely to win acceptanceat the Conference. Though it might prove expedient, as a tacticalmanoeuvre, to put it forward for discussion in the earlier stages, it seemed unlikely that a settlement could be reached on those lines. in cyprus itself little support would be forthcoming for a solution which involved associating the Greek and Turkish Governments in theadministration of the Island. The agitation in favour of closer association with Greece could not be checked by those means. the greeks, whether in Cyprus or on the mainland, would never willinglyagree that the Turkish Government should have any share in theadministration of the Island.It was the general view of the Cabinet that a solution was more likely to be found along the lines of offering progressive advance towards full internal self-government (Annex B of CP. (55) 94).Great care should, however, be taken to avoid any statement whichcould be construed as a promise to concede self-determination forthe Cypriots at any early date. Our strategic requirements in theEastern Mediterranean were such that we could not at present foreseea time at which we should be ready to surrender our sovereignty overCyprus. Our difficulties in Egypt had arisen because we had no claim to sovereignty over the site of the Canal Zone Base. We shouldrisk finding ourselves in similar difficulties in Cyprus if wesurrendered our sovereignty there. Neither strategically norpolitically could we afford tc make a second withdrawal from amilitary base in the Eastern Mediterranean. From this point ofview the wording of paragraph (a) (iii) of Annex B of CP. (55) 94went much too far in the direction of implying recognition of theright of the Cypriot people to self-determination: an undertaking toreach agreement with the Cypriot people about &quot; the future status &quot;of the Island would be construed as an intention to surrender british sovereignty. Some middle course must be found between a flatstatement that we would &quot; never &quot; surrender sovereignty and, on theother hand, a formula on which the Cypriots would found a firmexpectation that self-determination would be granted after a relatively short period.&apos; It was suggested that, for the words inparagraph (a) (iii) of Annex B, there  hould be substituted a simple48552-3B 2

Military Headquarters.(PreviousReference:C.C. (54) 5thConclusions,Minute 6.)undertaking to review the situation, in consultation with the Cypriotpeople, after a definite period, say ten years. During that time, everyeffort should be made to ensure that some sections of the Cypriotpeople had an interest in preserving the British connection.In further discussion the following points were made: -(a) It was at least possible that no practicable solution wouldemerge from the forthcoming Conference. Indeed, this seemed atpresent to be the most likely result of the Conference. In that eventwe should presumably be prepared to maintain our rights in Cyprusunder the existing constitution. The Conference would have servedto show that we had made a genuine effort to reach an agreedsettlement, and we* might on that account expect that a policy ofmaintaining our existing position would command a larger measureof support from world opinion.(b) There were some indications that the Archbishop of Cypruswas concerned about the effect of increased intervention by theGreek Government in the internal affairs of Cyprus. It was possiblethat some Cypriots might come to favour complete independencerather than closer association with Greece.(c) The Foreign Secretary said that he had again beenconsidering whether it would be wise to jam the broadcasts toCyprus which were being made from Athens. He was, however,disposed to doubt the expediency of this course. He thought itwould be preferable to develop the counter-propaganda which wasbeing relayed from broadcasting stations in Cyprus.The Cabinet endorsed the view expressed by the ForeignSecretary on this point.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion,said that it was the general opinion of the Cabinet that progresstowards a settlement of the constitutional question in Cyprus wasmore likely to be made along the lines of Annex B of CP. (55) 94subject to modification of paragraph (a) (iii) on the lines which hadbeen suggested in the discussion. The Foreign Secretary wouldconsider, before the opening of the Conference, how that plan couldbe adjusted to meet the Cabinet&apos;s desire that it should give theCypriots no encouragement to expect that self-determination wouldbe granted in the foreseeable future. The Foreign Secretary wouldalso consider at what point it would be expedient to put forward, inthe forthcoming Conference, definite proposals on these lines. Hewould have an opportunity to consult the Cabinet again before anyfinal proposals were put to the Conference on behalf of the UnitedKingdom Government.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider the proposals inCP. (55) 94, in the light of their discussion, and torefer again to the Cabinet before putting forward, atthe forthcoming Conference with representatives of theGreek and Turkish Governments, final proposals forconstitutional advance in Cyprus.The Cabinet also had before them a note by the Minister ofDefence (CP. (55) 82) covering a report by the Chiefs of Staff on thestrategic considerations to be taken into account in relation to futureconstitutional development in Cyprus. The conclusion of this reportwas that British military requirements in Cyprus could only be metif the control of its administration in matters of defence, externalaffairs and internal security remained in British hands.In discussion there was general agreement with this conclusion.Some concern was, however, expressed about the extent of themilitary installations which the Chiefs of Staff were planning toestablish in Cyprus, as indicated in the maps annexed to CP. (55) 82.These seemed to be disproportionate to the number of British








TloPalestine.(previous reference:CM. (55) 23rdConclusions,Minute 9.)485522. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (55) 87) outlining the results of his further discussions about the form of the announcement to be made by the United states secretary of State on the principles which should govern thesettlement of the dispute between the Arab States and Israel.The Foreign Secretary said that Mr. Dulles had modified his proposed statement to meet some of the objections which had been raised. The revised statement was set out in Annex 1 of CP. (55) 87.In this form, the announcement would not be a joint Anglo-Americandeclaration. The United States Government would alone beresponsible for the initiative and for the form of the announcement.A supporting statement would be separately made on behalf of theUnited Kingdom Government in the terms set out in Annex 4 of cp. (55) 87.The Foreign Secretary said that this plan met many of theobjections which the Cabinet had seen in the earlier proposal. he recommonded that it should be approved on two conditions (i) that the United States Government undertook to inform the IraqGovernment that, if a settlement of the dispute between the arab states and Israel could be reached on these lines, the United states would be prepared to join the Turco-Iraqi Pact; and (ii) that theUnited States Government agreed to make a substantial financial contribution, by &quot; off-shore &quot; orders, towards the supply of Britishtanks to Iraq.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Cabinet were informed that, as a result of approachesmade to him during the Geneva Conference, President Eisenhowerhad undertaken to do his utmost to arrange that, if ten of the eightytanks required by Iraq were supplied, by us on easy terms, the supplyof the remaining seventy would be financed by the United StatesGovernment on &quot; off-shore &quot; terms. The final decision of the UnitedStates Government on this point had not yet been notified to us. Ifit were favourable, it would be most important that the firstconsignment of these tanks should be sent to Iraq without delay.(b) The announcement which Mr. Dulles proposed to makecould be made more palatable to Arab opinion if Section I containedsome acknowledgement of the right of Arab refugees who formerlylived in Israel to return to their homes.(c) In Section III of the draft announcement it was stated thatthe existing armistice lines separating the Arab States from Israelwere &quot; not designed to be permanent frontiers in every respect.&quot; Thiswould be more acceptable to Arab opinion if the words &quot; in every respect&quot; were omitted.(d) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, on the new basis on which these. proposals were to be announced, it seemedunnecessary that we should accept a firm commitment to contribute 15 millions towards an international loan to Israel. A smallercontribution might suffice. The Foreign Secretary agreed that itshould suffice to say that the United Kingdom Government wouldmake an appropriate contribution to this loan.-3 b 3fighting troops which were to be retained in the Middle East. the size, and the probable cost, of these installations should be subjected to further scrutiny.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Minister of Defence to review the plans of theServices for the establishment of military installations in cyprus and to submit his views for consideration by the-Cabinet.
The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to suggest to the United SlatesSecretary of Slate lhal his proposed announcement on asettlement of the dispute between the Arab Slates and,Israel might be amended to lake account of the points noted in paragraphs (b) and (c) above.(2) Agreed that, subject to assurances by Ihe United StalesGovernment   on   their   ultimate   adherence   to   theTurco-iracii Pact and on. their readiness to make asubstantial financial contribution towards the supply ofBritish tanks to Iraq, the United Kingdom Governmentshould support the announcement of a United Stales plan for the settlement of the dispute between the Arab Slatesand  Israel on  the lines of the draft reproduced in annex I of CP. (55) 87.(3) Agreed that, if such an announcement were made, theForeign Secretary should make a supporting statement onbehalf of the United Kingdom Government in Ihe termsof the draft set out in Annex 4 of CP. (55) 87.Japanese war criminals.(previous reference:CM. (55) 23rdConclusions,Minute 10.)3.   The Cabinet considered a further memorandum by theForeign Secretary (CP. (55) 92) on the exercise of clemency towards^those Japanese war criminals who were still in custody.T/te Foreign Secretary said thai six of the eiglil Powersresponsible for the cuslody of the major war criminals had decidedthat these should be released on parole after the completion of tenyears&apos; imprisonment. As so many of Ihe responsible Powers hadalready decided to adopt (his principle, it was hardly practicable forus to take a different line. He proposed that we should concur inthe proposal favoured by the other Powers. The result would be thatIhe seven major criminals still in custody would all be released before april 1956.The Foreign Secretary said that there would be practicaladvantage in applying the same principle to those of the minor war criminals who were held in British custody. This would be in line with the action which was being laken by other Governmentsresponsible for Ihe custody of minor war criminals.In discussion it was suggested that, instead of adopting a rule that all these prisoners should be released afler they had completedten years&apos; imprisonment, it would be preferable to review the casesindividually on the basis that a life sentence would be treated as a sentence of (ifteen years&apos; imprisonment. On that basis a man whohad earned the maximum remission for good conduct would not servemore than ten years, but discretion would be reserved to detain llieworst cases for a longer period. It was also suggested that no public announcement of this decision should be made. It would, however,be desirable that the President of the Far East Prisoners of WarAssociation should be informed in advance of the policy which theGovernment were proposing to follow, so that he might lake stepsto forestall public criticism by. the members of his Association.The Cabinet (1) Authorised the Foreign Secretary lo notify the otherGovernments concerned that the United KingdomGovernment were agreeable that major war criminals stillin&apos;custody should be released on parole after completingten years&apos; imprisonment.
(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to review the case of minor: war criminals in British custody on the basis that a lifesentence would normally be treated as a sentence of fifteen years&apos;imprisonment.(3)&apos; Agreed that no public announcement of these decisions would be made, but invited the Foreign Secretary toinform the President of the Far East Prisoners of WarAssociation of the course which the Government were proposing to follow.legislative programme :1955-56Session.(previous reference:CM. (55) 22ndConclusions,Minute 7.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theLord Privy Seal (CP. (55) 95) on the legislative programme for thecurrent session, with particular reference to Bills needed for introduction when Parliament reassembled in October.The Lord Privy Seal said that, if the Bills listed -in Annex A ofhis memorandum were ready for introduction in October, hethought thai, with  the Bills already introduced, there should be enough legislative business to occupy (he House of Commonsimmediately after the recess. The situation in the House of lords would be less satisfactory, but it was hoped that they would be ableto make progress with  the two Bills dealing with Copyright and theAdministration of Justice.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) A Revenue Bill, which would reduce the scope of nextyear&apos;s Finance Bill, would be ready in October.(b) A measure providing for increased pensions wotdd also beready for consideration in October. It would be for Hie Cabinet todecide whether legislation on this subject should be introduced inthe current session.(c) A Bill to give effect lo (he Geneva Conventions could beready for introduction in October, but its introduction might provokediscussion on capital punishment. It had been suggested on this account that the Home Secretary should proceed, instead, with aBill dealing with the closing hours of shops.In discussion the view was expressed that means should be foundto enable progress to be made, a iitlle later in the session, with the geneva Conventions Bill. If we could reserve our position in regardto the clauses in the Conventions dealing with capital punishment,the Bill could go forward without provoking Parliamentarycontroversy on that question.(f/) The introduction of the Family Allowances Bill, which was ready, was being delayed at the request of the Chancellor of theExchequer.The Cabinet (I) Invited the Ministers concerned&apos;to ensure that there was no avoidable delay in preparing the Bills listed in Annex Ato  CP.  (55)  95  for introduction  when  parliament reassembled in October.(2) Agreed that the Shops (Closing Hours) Bill should beintroduced early in the autumn.(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to explore the possibility ofreserving our position in respect of the clauses in theX Geneva   Conventions   Bill   which   would   necessitate.   legislation on capital punishment and agreed that, if this^could be arranged, the Geneva Conventions Bill shouldbe introduced later in the autumn.
Economic 5.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that both the receptionSituation.        and the effect of the further steps taken to curb inflation were(Previous        proving better than he had expected. As he had stated in the HouseReference:      of Commons, there would be a further fall in our reserves in July.CM. (55) 26th   But his advisers did not take too serious a view of this, for theConclusions.    technical position, with sterling short in the world, was strong. MuchMinute 2.)       of the recent pressure on sterling could be attributed to the rumours,arising out of the Paris discussions, that we intended to introduce a floating rate of exchange.   Forward operations which the exchange equalisation Fund had made that week had proved successful. the anti-inflationary policy would be continued during the recess, and time would thus be given for the measures iaken to have their effect.It was not his present intention to make any important statement onexchange policy at the conference in September of the international monetary Fund at Istanbul.   If it proved necessary to make anychange in present policy, he would have an opportunity of consultinghis colleagues before that conference took place.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of chancellor of the Exchequer.this statement  by theNewsprint.(previous reference:C.C. (55) 25thConclusions.Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the President ofthe Board of Trade (CP. (55) 93) inviting their views on a proposal that Government control over the distribution of newsprint shouldbe brought to an end in six months&apos; time.The President of the Board of Trade said that the total supplyof newsprint had risen from about 500,000 tons in 1950 to about850,000 tons in 1955. Although the import of newsprint could notyet be completely freed, the Chancellor of the Exchequer had been willing to agree to a maximum limit upon imports which was wellabove the volume of supplies likely to be available. This meant thatthe Government were no longer effectively controlling supplies of newsprint through the restriction of imports. He would thereforelike to end the control over the distribution of newsprint. the newspapers themselves were divided on this question. Newspaperswhose contracts with suppliers would guarantee them an adequate supply of newsprint were anxious that the control should end.Others, whose supplies were less well assured, would prefer the controls to continue. But the mills producing newsprint in thiscountry had agreed to re-negotiate their contracts so at to make provision for the smaller newspapers and for the provincial presswhich might otherwise be in difficulties. In these circumstances hewould like to give notice in mid-August that all remaining controls(except import controls) would come to an end six months thereafter.The Chancellor of the Exchequer supported this proposal.The Cabinet Authorised the President of the Board of Trade to make anannouncement, as proposed in CP. (55) 93, foreshadowingthe withdrawal in six months&apos; time of the government control over the distribution of newsprint.
(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to review the case of minorwar criminals in British custody on the basis that a lifesentence would normally be treated as a sentence of fifteen years&apos; imprisonment.(3) Agreed that no public announcement of these decisions would be made, but invited the Foreign Secretary toinform the President of the Far East Prisoners of WarAssociation of the course which the Government were proposing to follow.LegisJaiive 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theProgramme: Lord Privy Seal (CP. (55) 95) on the legislative programme for the1955-56 current session, with  particular  reference  to  Bills  needed  forSession. introduction when Parliament reassembled in October.The Lord Privy Seal said that, if the Bills listed dn Annex A ofhis memorandum were ready for introduction in October, hethought that, with the Bills already introduced, there should be enough iegisiaiive business to occupy the House of Commonsimmediately after the recess. The situation in the House of Lordswotild be less satisfactory, but it was hoped that they would be ableto make progress with  the two Bills dealing with Copyright and theAdministration of Justice.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) A Revenue Bill, which would reduce the scope of nextyear&apos;s Finance Bill, would be ready in October.(/;) A measure providing for increased pensions would also beready for consideration in October. It would be for the Cabinet todecide whether legislation on this subject should be introduced inthe current session.(c) A Bill to give effect to the Geneva Conventions could beready for introduction in October, but its introduction might provokediscussion on capital punishment. It had been suggested on this account that the Home Secretary should proceed, instead, with  aBill dealing with the closing hours of shops.In discussion the view was expressed that means should be foundx to enable progress to be made, a iittle later in the session, with the geneva Conventions Bill. If we could reserve our position in regardto the clauses in the Conventions dealing with  capital punishment,the Bill could go forward without provoking Parliamentarycontroversy on that question.(d) The introduction of the Family Allowances Bill, which was ready, was being delayed at the request of the Chancellor of theExchequer.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Ministers concerned&apos;to ensure that there was no avoidable delay in preparing the Bills listed in Annex Ato CP.  (55)  95  for  introduction  when  parliament reassembled in October.(2) Agreed that the Shops (Closing Hours) Bill should beintroduced early in the autumn.(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to explore the possibility ofreserving our position in respect of (he clauses in the geneva Conventions Bill which would necessitatelegislation on capital punishment and agreed that, if this could be arranged, the Geneva Conventions Bill shouldbe introduced later in the autumn.(previous reference:CM. (55) 22ndConclusions,Minute 7.)
5. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that both the reception and the effect of the further steps taken to curb inflation wereproving better than he had expected. As he had stated in the Houseof Commons, there would be a further fall in our reserves in July.But his advisers did not take too serious a view of this, for thetechnical position, with sterling short in the world, was strong. Muchof the recent pressure on sterling could be attributed to the rumours,arising out of the Paris discussions, that we intended to introduce a floating rate of exchange. Forward operations which the exchange equalisation Fund had made that week had proved successful. the anti-inflationary policy would be continued during the recess, and time would thus be given for the measures taken to have their effect.It was not his present intention to make any important statement onexchange policy at the conference in September of the international monetary Fund at Istanbul. If it proved necessary to make anychange in present policy, he would have an opportunity of consultinghis colleagues before that conference took place.The Cabinet-Took note, with  approval, of this  statement by theChancellor of the Exchequer.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the President ofthe Board of Trade (CP. (55) 93) inviting their views on a proposal that Government control over the distribution of newsprint shouldbe brought to an end in six months&apos; time.The President of the Board of Trade said that the total supplyof newsprint had risen from about 500,000 tons in 1950 to about850,000 tons in 1955. Although the import of newsprint could notyet be completely freed, the Chaucellor of the Exchequer had been willing to agree to a maximum limit upon imports which was wellabove the volume of supplies likely to be available. This meant thatthe Government were no longer effectively controlling supplies of newsprint through the restriction of imports. He would thereforelike to end the control over the distribution of newsprint. the newspapers themselves were divided on this question. Newspaperswhose contracts with suppliers would guarantee them an adequate supply of newsprint were anxious that the control should end.Others, whose supplies were less well assured, would prefer the controls to continue. But the mills producing newsprint in thiscountry had agreed to re-negotiate their contracts so at to make provision for the smaller newspapers and for the provincial presswhich might otherwise be in difficulties. In these circumstances hewould like to give notice in mid-August that all remaining controls(except import controls) would come to an end six months thereafter.The Chancellor of the Exchequer supported this proposal.The Cabinet Authorised the President of the Board of Trade to make anannouncement, as proposed in CP. (55) 93, foreshadowingthe withdrawal in six months&apos; time of the government control over the distribution of newsprint.
7. The Foreign Secretary said that the Chinese Charged&apos;Affaires had delivered to the Foreign Office an invitation from theChinese Institute of Foreign Affairs for a Parliamentary delegation from the United Kingdom to pay a visit to China. Subject to theviews of the Cabinet, he proposed to reply that any official invitation of this kind should be made by the Chinese National Peoples&apos;Congress and should be addressed to the Lord Chancellor and the speaker. If such an invitation were received, it could be answeredin the sense that, while it was accepted in principle, no early datecould be fixed for such a visit in view of the large number of commitments to pay return visits to countries whose Parliaments hadalready sent delegations to the United Kingdom.The Cabinet Approved the reply which the Foreign Secretary proposedto make to this suggestion that a Parliamentary delegation from the United Kingdom should visit China.Cabinet. 8.   The Prime Minister said that it should not be necessary forProcedure standing Committees of the Cabinet to meet during August and during recess. September. During that period the Cabinet itself could dispose ofany urgent business which would ordinarily be submitted to thoseCommittees. This would not, of course, apply to the ministerial committees on Cyprus and Malta, which were to supervise the preparations for Conferences on those subjects during the recess.The Prime Minister said that he hoped it would not be necessaryfor the Cabinet to meet during the first tv/o weeks of August. Inthe second half of the month some meetings would have to be held for the transaction of urgent business; but his aim would be to holdnot more than one meeting a week attended by Ministers who were inLondon or within easy reach of it. The ordinary business of theCabinet would be resumed in September. It should not, however,be necessary for the Cabinet to meet more than once a week inSeptember, and Ministers who had been on duty in London inAugust would not be expected to attend Cabinet meetings inSeptember unless they were in. or within easy reach of, London.China.Request forvisit byParliamentaryDelegation.Cabinet Office, SWA,28th July, 1955..

</content>
</cab>
