<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 234-245</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of her britannic  majesty^  governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1955SECRET Copy No. 34CM. (55)28th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 15th August, 1955, at 2-45 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer (items-5).The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Sblwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Items 6-7).The Right Hon. A. R. W. Low, M.P.,Minister of State, Board of Trade(Items 7-11).The Right Hon. Henry&apos; Hopkinson,M.P., Minister of State for colonial affairs (Items 1-3 and 8-11).Sir Edward Boyle, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury (Items 7-11).Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. C. Chilver.
contents minute no.                                      subject      Irish Republic............2      Economic Situation    ...      ...3      Singapore        ............Constitution.Reinforcement.4      Meeting of Commonwealth Prime ministers      Soviet UnionVisit of Soviet Leaders to United Kingdom.Exchanges of Military Visits.6      Road Haulage Disposals7     JapanTrade and Payments Negotiations.8      Irish Republic ...      .........Invitation to Foreign Investors.9      Cyprus   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...Conference with Greek and Turkish Governments.Public Order.Broadcast by the Governor.10      Disarmament11      German War Criminals
Economic 2.   The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the economicSituation.        situation continued to be somewhat uneasy.   The Banks were(Previous        beginning to put into operation the policy of credit restriction; and,Reference:      in order to support their efforts, the Government would soon needCM. (55) 27th   to show practical signs of their intention to reduce expenditure in conclusions,     the public sector of the economy.   He had given much thought to minute 5.)       this and would be in a position to put specific proposals before theCabinet in the course of the following week.  In the last two weeks the pressure on our gold and dollar reserves had relaxed somewhat;but there was continuing uncertainty about the strength of sterlingsand he would be glad to have an opportunity for fuller discussion ofthis question with his colleagues before he left, early in Septemberfor the meeting of the International Monetary Fund.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) Inflationary pressures were likely to be increased by further round of wage claims in the autumn.  There was no prospedof any drop in the cost-of-living index; and wage claims affecting4 million workers were now in course of preparation.(b) There was evidence that conditions of over-full employmentwere affecting productivity in certain industries.(c) To the extent that it was applied to farmers, the policy of credit restriction might produce some falling-off in agricultural production, particularly of livestock.(d) The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said thatinflationary pressure would not be checked unless the Governmentshowed that they were taking effective steps to reduce public expenditure. He had drawn attention to this need in a memorandum(CP. (55) 98) which he had circulated to the Cabinet at the end ofJuly.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would take account of that memorandum in the specific proposals which hewould be submitting to the Cabinet in the course of the following week.(e) The Lord President said that, while he recognised the presentneed to reduce excessive demands for labour, he hoped it would bepossible to avoid delaying projects of capital investment which were necessary in order to increase our industrial productivity. Outcontinuing ability to export at competitive prices depended onprogressive modernisation of our industrial plant.   He would also^ 1.   The Prime Minister said that later in the day he would beRepublic. discussing with the Home Secretary and the Secretary of State for(Previous War questions arising from the recent raids on Army depots in this reference: country by members of the Irish Republican Army (I.R.A.). FurtherC.C. (55) 5th precautions would have to be taken to prevent the theft of arms and conclusions, ammunition from military installations in this country. He would,Minute 12.) however, prefer that these should be carried out as unobtrusively aspossible.In discussion there was general agreement with the view expressed by the Prime Minister. The Government should , notappear to be unduly alarmed by these developments. Close watchshould, however, be kept on I.R.A. activities in this country.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister would report at their next meeting the results of his discussions on I.R.A.activities in this country.
regret any postponement of plans for road development. In the pastwe had been told that we could not afford to improve our road system because times were too bad. It would be ironical if we were now to be told that the programme on which we were at last to embark had to be deferred because times were too good.The Cabinet (1) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would submit, for the Cabinefs consideration in the following week, further proposals for handling the present economic situation.(2) Agreed that these proposals should be considered&apos; at ameeting on 26th August unless the Prime Ministerdecided on further consideration that they should beconsidered earlier in that week.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of State for Colonial Affairs (CP. (55) 97) reporting theresult of the discussions which the Colonial Secretary had heldduring his first visit to Singapore on 1st August and indicating thelines on which the Colonial Secretary wished, subject to the cabinet&apos;s approval, to handle the further discussions which he was to have with the Chief Minister of Singapore on his return there on16th August.In discussion the following general points were made:  (a) The Colonial Secretary was anxious to keep the chief minister in power. If his Government fell, it would probably benecessary to face a period of direct rule involving serious disorders.(b) It should be borne in mind that Singapore and Malaya werethe last important Colonial territories to be granted this measure ofself-government. They were also the only Colonial territories left ina part of the world where other territories had gained their independence. As against this, it was pointed out that singapore and Malaya enjoyed a far higher standard of government and administration than other countries in South-East Asia: in none ofthose other countries had real elections yet been held. We shouldnot be induced by fear of adverse world opinion to move more rapidly towards the grant of full internal self-government than wasin the interests of the people themselves.(c) It was suggested that, when once a Colonial territory hadbeen given a measure of responsibility, fairly rapid progress towardsthe grant of a full internal self-government was inevitable. On thisview it was arguable that, so long as responsibility for defence,internal security and foreign relations was retained in our hands, itwas not to our advantage to delay the transfer of full responsibilityfor other matters.(d) There was general support for the view that it was too early to talk of revising a constitution which had only been granted a fewmonths before. While showing ourselves reasonable we must avoid the appearance of precipitate retreat under pressure. Certainly theCabinet could not commit themselves to an undertaking to revise the constitution in the direction of the grant of full internal self-government without being informed of the precise respects in whichthis would differ from the constitution recently granted and their implications.(e) The Cabinet were reminded that it had been found necessaryto revise at an early stage the constitutions first granted to the gold coast and Nigeria. They were also informed that the colonial secretary was proposing to broach with the Federation of MalayaSingapore.Constitution.(previous reference:CM. (55) 26thConclusions,Minute 5.)
proposals for modifying their relations with the United KingdomGovernment on defence and finance. It would be advantageous ifsimilar arrangements were made with Singapore. This might,however, involve reviewing, and indeed revising, the constitution of singapore in order to get the binding arrangement on defence facilities which was desirable. As against this it was argued that itshould be possible to make satisfactory arrangements about defencewithout amending the constitution, under which defence was are served subject.On the specific proposals outlined in CP. (55) 97 the following conclusions were reached:  (i) No objection need be raised to the proposal that theGovernor should in future accept the advice of the Chief minister on all matters relating to the appointment and dismissal of ministers and Assistant Ministers, and the allocation of duties between them,subject to the reservations suggested in paragraphs 3 and 4 of appendix B of CP. (55) 97 regarding the allocation of subjects to ex officio Ministers and the appointment of assistants to them. Itcould also be agreed that the Governor would in future accept theadvice of the Chief Minister regarding the establishment and corn-position of committees of the Council of Ministers, though retaining the right to insist that such committees should include any Ministerswhom he considered to be directly affected by their work.(ii) The Colonial Secretary might also agree, in the last resort,that the Governor should in future accept the advice of the chief minister about the prorogation of the Legislative Assembly. this concession should not, however, be made unless it proved necessaryin the last resort in order to prevent a breakdown of the negotiations.Even then it must be subject to the Governor^ power to over-rideMinisters in the interests of public faith, public order or good government. The Colonial Secretary should in no circumstancesagree that the Governor should be required to accept the advice ofthe Chief Minister on the dissolution of the Legislative Assembly.(iii) The changes outlined in the two preceding paragraphsshould be made by means of formal instructions to the Governor,in which the reservations mentioned would be incorporated. Theycould not be made by means of a &quot; liberal interpretation &quot; of theconstitution. They required, in fact, an amendment of theconstitution; and, although it would be inexpedient to propose any amendment at the present time, they should in due course be incorporated in the next revision of the constitution.\ (iv) The Colonial Secretary might propose that SingaporeMinisters should visit London next summer for discussions, but inmaking this invitation he should avoid any language which mightimply a commitment to revise the constitution. An appropriateformula would be &quot; to discuss the situation in the light of a year&apos;sworking of the constitution.&quot;(v) The Colonial Secretary should endeavour to secure that anyagreed statement on his negotiations should include a recognition by the Singapore Government that the present constitution was agreat step forward and given goodwill was fully workable, and an expression of the sincere intention of that Government so to work  the constitution.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of State for Colonial Affairs to informthe Colonial Secretary of the Cabinefs conclusions as recorded in paragraphs (i) to (v) above.Re-inforce- The Minister of Defence said that, if it became necessary toment. reinforce the British troops in Singapore, he had it in mind that one battalion should be sent from Hong Kong. Further reinforcementscould be sent from the Middle East, if the need did not arise before
Meeting of 4.   The Prime Minister said that he had been considering whenCommonwealth the next meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers should be held.Prime He was disposed to suggest a date in January, 1956.Ministers.The Commonwealth Secretary doubted whether other commonwealth Prime Ministers would expect to meet again so soon: the last meeting had been held in January, 1955. It was desirable that at their next meeting the Prime Ministers should consider the aspirations of the Gold Coast to full commonwealth membership, and it would be premature to raise this question earlyin 1956. January was not a convenient month for all Prime Ministers.In these circumstances he had been disposed to think that the next meeting might be held in the autumn of 1956.In discussion there was support for the view that it would be useful to hold the next meeting in January, 1956. While it was difficult to find a time of year which suited all Prime Ministers,experience had shown that it was easier to arrange a meeting in thefirst part of January than at any other time of year. A meeting inJanuary, 1956 would follow the meeting of Foreign Ministers whichwas to open in Geneva at the end of October, and would precede the visit which the leaders of the Soviet Union were to pay to the UnitedKingdom in April. It would therefore be a convenient moment foran exchange of views on international affairs. The Chancellor ofthe Exchequer said that he would also welcome the opportunity todiscuss economic questions with Commonwealth Prime Ministersearly in 1956. The Prime Minister said that, if there were any generalreluctance to come to London in January, the meeting might be heldin some other Commonwealth capital.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister would enquire Whetherother Commonwealth Prime Ministers would be ready toattend a meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers inJanuary, 1956.the beginning of October, since by that time troops could probablybe spared from Kenya or the Ganal Zone. If, however,reinforcements had to be sent earlier they would have to be drawn from the strategic reserve in the United Kingdom, which had beenprovided for tasks of that kind. He recognised the political disadvantages of taking troops from Hong Kong, but it would onlybe a question of taking one battalion out of eleven units there. the precise arrangements to be made, for example the extent to whichthe initial reinforcements for Singapore should be drawn from malaya and replaced by incoming troops, would be for consideration at the time.The Cabinet-(2) Invited the Minister of State for Colonial Affairs to informthe Governor of Hong Kong that in the event of disordersin Singapore it might become necessary to move one battalion from Hong Kong to Singapore.(3) Invited the Minister of Defence to keep under review, inconsultation with the Minister of State for colonial affairs, plans for the reinforcement of Singapore.
5. During the recent Conference of Heads of Governments in geneva the Prime Minister had, after consulting some of his seniorcolleagues, invited M. Bulganin and M. Khrushchev to pay a visit to the United Kingdom. They had at once expressel gratificationat this invitation and, immediately after their return to Moscow, had confirmed their willingness to visit this country in April. A furtherexchange of messages on this subject between the Prime Minister andM. Bulganin was read to the Cabinet. It was now expected thatthe visit would take place in the second half of April and would last for a little over one week.The Cabinet-(1) Took note that the Prime Minister and the Foreign secretary would jointly supervise the making of detailed arrangements for this visit.Exchanges of The Cabinet were  also informed that in the course ofMilitary Visits, conversations at Geneva M. Bulganin had suggested that exchanges of military visits might be arranged between this country and theSoviet Union. In pursuance of that suggestion proposals were nowbeing made to the Soviet Government for a number of H.M. ships to pay a formal visit to Leningrad about the middle of October.The Cabinet (2) Agreed in principle that suitable exchanges of military visitsshould be arranged between this country and the soviet union; and took note of the proposal that, as a first step,a number of H.M. ships should visit Leningrad inOctober.Soviet Union..(previous reference:C.C. (55) 10thConclusions,Minute 5.)Visit of soviet leaders toUnitedKingdom.Road HaulageDisposals.(previous reference:CM. (55) 23rdConclusions,Minute 4.)6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofTransport (CP. (55) 101) reporting the advice given bySir Malcolm Trustram Eve on the number of vehicles needed toenable British Road Services to operate their trunk services.The Minister of Transport said that, if this advice were accepted,the total number of vehicles to be retained by the British transport commission would be nearly 9,000, as compared with the figure of8,000 which he had indicated to Parliament. Even so, he thought itwould be right for him to accept the advice given in Sir MalcolmEve&apos;s report. Subject to the Cabinefs views, he proposed to publish the report and to announce his acceptance of its recommendation.Prospective purchasers were entitled to know how many vehicleswould be available for disposal.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Transport to publishSir Malcolm Trustram Eve&apos;s report, and to announce his acceptance of its recommendation that the British transport commission should retain 7,750 vehicles for operating the trunk services of British Road Services.Japan.Trade andPaymentsNegotiations.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 22ndConclusions,Minute 7.)7. The Cabinet had before them (i) a note by the Chancellorof the Exchequer (CP. (55) 103) covering a report by an inter-departmental committee of officials on the present state of thenegotiations for a new trade and payments agreement with Japan;and (ii) a memorandum by the Minister of State, Board of Trade(CP. (55) 104) setting out the views of the Board of Trade on thisquestion.The question submitted for the Cabinefs decision was whether our negotiators should make a further effort to secure our objectives in these negotiations, as set out in paragraphs 4 and 5 of the report
annexed to CP. (55) 103, without limiting the volume of Japaneseexports to our non-entrepot Colonies; or whether those colonies should be asked forthwith to limit their imports from Japan in 1956to the 1955 level.In the course of a preliminary discussion there was some support for the view that it would be difficult to defend a substantial increasein Colonial imports of Japanese textiles unless it could be shownthat the agreement gave us compensating advantages in other directions. In this connection it was pointed out that other interestsin Lancashire would also be critical if the agreement were concludedwithout any assurance that the Japanese Government woulddiscontinue their policy of subsidising the unecomonic expansion oftheir mercantile marine.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to re-consider the decision thatthe shipping question should not be raised again in thecourse of the negotiations for a new trade and payments agreement.(2) Agreed to resume their consideration of CP. (55) 103 and 104at a meeting in the following week.Irish Republic. 8. The Cabinefs attention was drawn to a recent statement byInvitation to the Minister of Industry and Commerce in the Irish Republic invitingForeign German industries to establish factories in the Irish Republic andInvestors. thereby to obtain the advantage of Commonwealth preferences. TheCabinet had before them a memorandum by the Minister of State,Board of Trade (CP. (55) 105) commenting on this statement.In discussion it was suggested that a warning might be given tothe Government of the Irish Republic that the settlement of 1948might have to be re-considered if it were to be used in this way forthe benefit of our foreign competitors. Although re-negotiation ofthe agreement of 1948 would put at risk important preferenceswhich the United Kingdom now enjoyed in the Irish Republic, theconsequences of such a re-negotiation might be even more serious tothe Irish. The United Kingdom was an important outlet for Irishagricultural produce.On the other hand, it was unlikely that any German industries would accept this invitation to establish factories in the irish republic. The Dublin Government had made similar offers before,without result, and it might be better to defer making any protestuntil there was greater risk of practical damage to our interests.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of State, Board of Trade, to watch this situation and to inform the Cabinet of any developments.Cyprus.(previous reference:CM. (55) 23rdConclusions,Minute 6.)conference with Greek andTurkishGovernments.9. The Foreign Secretary said that he had been considering the handling of the forthcoming conference with representatives of theGreek and Turkish Governments.It was arguable that, in view of the failure of the GreekGovernment to control the broadcasts from Athens Radio, we shouldnot proceed with the conference at all, and should inform the Greeksthat we were not prepared to enter into a conference with aGovernment whose radio propaganda was directly inciting people toviolence. His own opinion, however, was that on balance it. would beto our advantage to allow the conference to take place.On the composition of the conference, he thought we shouldtake the line that this was a conference between Governments andthere could be no question of admitting to it persons who, though not
Public Order.Broadcast bythe Governor.elected representatives, purported to speak for the people of Cyprus.The conference could, however, take account of written statementssubmitted on behalf of, e.g., the Ethnarchy and the Muslimcommunity in Cyprus.On the conduct of the conference, he still proposed to proceed without haste. After an introductory meeting he would himself makea statement, in which he would deal with the historical and strategicreasons for the British administration of Cyprus. He would say thatHer Majesty&apos;s Government had in mind certain proposals for thefuture but that he would prefer not to develop these before hearing the statements of the other two Governments. Thereafter the greek and Turkish representatives would make their opening statements,and the Foreign Secretary would sum up. He would then propose the appointment of a drafting committee to set out with precision theviews of each Government: this was important since, although theGreek representative would doubtless express extreme views in discussion, he would probably wish any formal statement of hisGovernmenfs position to be more moderate.The conference could next examine the extent of the agreementbetween the three Governments. If, as was to be expected, a widedifference of opinion was revealed, the conference would adjourn atthat point. He would hope that this handling of the discussion would serve to show that the deadlock was due, not to British Colonialism,but to the irreconcilable attitudes of the Greek and turkish governments; and that the British aim, as at the time of our originaloccupation of the Island, was to safeguard the Eastern Mediterraneanagainst Russian aggression.When the conference was resumed, he would produce the british proposals. Their precise nature would depend on the outcome ofthe previous discussions; and he would like in any event to consider their details further, with an eye to their reception by world opinion.There would be ample time to refer them again to the Cabinet before they were presented.The Cabinet (1) Approved the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposals for the conductof the forthcoming conference with representatives ofthe Greek and Turkish Governments.The Foreign Secretary said that it seemed advisable that all necessary preparations should be made to handle the disorders whichmight be expected to break out in Cyprus if the conference were notsuccessful.The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that certain measures had already been taken; for example, the pay of policehad been increased. A suggestion which was currently beingconsidered was the appointment of a Director of Operations toco-ordinate the activities of the police and the armed forces.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Ministerial Committee on Cyprus to consider what further measures were needed to ensure the main-tenance of public order in Cyprus if disturbances broke out after the forthcoming conference.The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that the governor of Cyprus wished to make a broadcast, primarily to refute the recentmisrepresentations by Athens Radio about the new detention lawin Cyprus. He favoured this proposal. The text of the broadcastwould be examined, in the Colonial Office.The Cabinet (3) Agreed that no objection need be raised to a suitablebroadcast on this subject by the Governor of Cyprus.
Disarmament.(previous reference:CM. (55) 5thConclusions,Minute 6.)10. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theForeign Secretary (CP. (55) 100) seeking the Cabinefs approval forthe general line which the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs wasto take in forthcoming discussions with the Americans, French andCanadians preparatory to the meeting of the Sub-Committee of theUnited Nations Disarmament Commission on 29th August.The Foreign Secretary said that, in his view, there were twooutstanding facts. First, it had now become clear that there wasno means of establishing an effective control over existing stockpilesof nuclear weapons or new production of fissile material, and thatit would before long become impossible to control the means of launching nuclear weapons. Secondly, the Russians had nowrecognised the full dangers of nuclear war and the existence of nuclear weapons seemed more likely to preserve than to threaten the peace of the world. These two considerations suggested that aconvention for the abolition of nuclear weapons might be a positivethreat to peace, since it would weaken the deterrent to war, whilethe fact that it could be evaded would lead to a dangerouscompetition in the clandestine accumulation of nuclear weapons. he therefore believed that our policy on disarmament needed to bere considered. We must be careful not to drift into acceptance of a plan which was in fact unreal.In discussion the following points were raised:  (a) There was general support for the view that, until other proposals had been formulated, there was no reason why we shouldnot stand by the Anglo-French proposals which had been submittedto the Disarmament Sub-Committee. Those proposals containedample safeguards. In particular, they provided that substantial progress should be made with disarmament in conventional weaponsbefore disarmament in nuclear weapons was begun, and that thereshould be no nuclear disarmament until an effective system of inspection and control had been devised. Therefore, so long as it remained impossible to devise an effective system of controllingnuclear disarmament, the deterrent value of nuclear weapons wouldbe retained. If we now withdrew our support for the Anglo-french proposals, we might give the impression that we had abandonedall hope of finding a practical scheme of disarmament and mightthereby give a tactical advantage to the Russians.(h) The Prime Minister suggested that the Minister of State forForeign Affairs might go rather further than was proposed inparagraph 7 of CP. (55) 100 in referring to the proposal which hehad put forward at Geneva for a practical scheme of inspection inEurope. He recognised that there would not be time for any formalconsultation with the North Atlantic Treaty Powers before theDisarmament Sub-Committee met in New York. But he had in factconsulted the Supreme Allied Commander, Europe, before he put this proposal forward at Geneva. There was, therefore, no reason why rather more should not be made of it than was suggested inparagraph 7 of the memorandum.(c) In paragraph 5 of CP. (55) 100 it was suggested that it wouldbe difficult for us to reach final conclusions on the means ofestablishing effective supervision over disarmament until we knewmore about the trend of American thinking on this subject. ThePrime Minister said that we should be unwise to wait too long uponthe Americans in this matter: it might be some considerable time before they produced any views of their own. We should not hesitate to go forward with our own enquiries into this aspect of the problem and to bring forward suggestions of our own as soon as we were ready.The Cabinet Agreed that the instructions for the guidance of the Ministerof State for Foreign Affairs at the forthcoming meeting of
the Disarmament Sub-Committee should be drawn on thelines proposed in CP. (55) 100, subject to amendment of paragraphs 5, 7 and 9 of that memorandum to take accountof the points noted in paragraphs (a), (b) and (c) above.German war criminals.(previous reference:CC. (52) 84thConclusions,Minute 6.)11. The Foreign Secretary said that the Germans were pressing for the immediate release of Admiral Raeder and Admiral Doenitz,who were still serving sentences of imprisonment as war criminals.The Governments of the United States and France favoured therelease of both these men. He was disposed to support the recom-mendation for the release of Raeder, who was aged 79 and brokenin health. He could be released on grounds of ill-health, as hadVon Neurath in similar circumstances. Different considerationsapplied, however, to Admiral Doenitz, who was only 64 and might still become prominent in political affairs in Germany.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Foreign Secretary should agree to the releaseof Admiral Raeder, on grounds Of ill-health, but should notconsent to the release of Admiral Doenitz.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,16th August, 1955.


</content>
</cab>
