<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 246-255</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1955SECRET Copy No.   *J j)CM. (55)29th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 26th August, 1955, at 2-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Harold Macmtllan,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. the Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Items 1-3).The Right Hon. A. R. W. Low, M.P.,Minister of State, Board of Trade(Item 3).Mr: H. A. Watkinson, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry ofLabour and National Service (items-2).The Right Hon. Henry Hopkinson,M.P., Minister of State for colonial affairs (Items 1-9).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Treasury.Lord Carrington, parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Defence(Items 4-9).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. F. A. Bishop.49603-1b
contents minute no. subject      Economic Situation    ......2      Industrial Relations3      Japan     ...      ...Trade and Payments Negotiations.General.Shipping.4     Cyprus............Public Order.5      Broadcasting    .........The Fortnight Rule.6      Disarmament7      Irish Republic.........8      Afro-Asian ConferenceLoss of Indian Airliner.9     Sudan    ............10     Food     .........\ Bacon Prices.
EconomicSituation.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 2.)1. The Cabinet reviewed the current economic situation. Theyhad before them memoranda on this subject by the Chancellor ofthe Duchy of Lancaster (CP. (55) 98) and the Lord President(CP. (55) 106).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that there had been nofurther deterioration in the economic situation since he last reportedto the Cabinet. The underlying trade position in July was lessunfavourable than might be assumed from the loss to the reserves,which had been due largely to an outflow of short-term capital causedby the expectation that some change was likely to be made in theexchange rate. The loss to the reserves in August was likely to be considerably less, though there would be a considerable deficit withthe European Payments Union. There was therefore no cause foralarm, though the time of year was approaching when the balanceof trade and payments were seasonally unfavourable.The measures so far taken to restrict credit were now workingeffectively, although they were to some extent being offset by thecapital requirements of local authorities and certain of the nationalised industries. The clearing banks were responding to therequest for a definite and positive reduction in their lending. Never-theless the economy was still overloaded, and the Government couldnot expect the public to accept the need for credit restrictions unless it could be shown that these would also be applied to the nationalised industries and to Government expenditure generally. Moreover, weshould soon be faced with demands for a further round of wage increases, inspired by overfull employment. Some further correctiveaction was necessary. He therefore recommended the simultaneousannouncement of further measures designed to restrain expenditurein the public sector and to reduce demand still further in the private sector. The timing of the announcement and introduction of these measures would have to be carefully considered, but he did not atpresent think that an early recall of Parliament would be necessary.There should be a substantial reduction in expenditure by localauthorities. By far the larger proportion of this expenditure was devoted to subsidised housing: in 1954 local authorities had spent 375 millions on subsidised housing, compared with  215 millions for all other purposes. This could not be reduced without a drastic,alteration in the housing subsidies which should, in his view, bereduced by about  100 millions. One method of doing this wouldbe to abolish the general housing subsidy, and to confine the subsidy to slum clearance and schemes to prevent overcrowding. This might\ be combined with a limit on the number of houses which localauthorities were allowed to build: the aim might be to reduce thetotal to about 100,000 a year. It might also be expedient to restore the control over private building. As regards their expenditure forother purposes, it would be desirable that a circular should be sentto all local authorities urging them to reduce wherever possible theburden of their demands on the economy.Turning to Government expenditure, he hoped that a substantial reduction could be made in the defence programme. As regardstransport, he would not be able to authorise an extension of thecurrent roads programme, and he hoped that some of the major schemes in the current programme, as well as expenditure on road maintenance, could be postponed. The substantial expenditure involved in the railways modernisation plan had not yet begun. the investment programmes of the electricity and gas industries shouldbe slowed down, but capital expenditure planned for the coal industryand for atomic development should not be reduced. Even education should make some contribution: schemes for school building shouldbe postponed or slowed down wherever possible. In the private sector, the Federation of British Industries had recommended thatthe Government should make a public appeal to industry to avoid unnecessary capital investment at the present time.In addition, the possibility of abolishing the bread subsidy wouldhave to be considered, though the effect of this measure on the cost49603-1 B 2
of living and on pressure for higher wages would have to be carefullyweighed.The Chancellor said that, in addition to these proposals, certainfiscal measures might also be necessary. He would prefer that afurther increase in the Bank Rate should be kept in reserve for thepresent. But he was considering an increase in the tax on distributedprofits; and he favoured an appeal to industry to do their utmost to avoid increases in dividends, profit margins and prices.The Chancellor said that in his view no further move towardsconvertibility should be made until the internal economy had been strengthened. He proposed to discuss with the Secretary of theUnited States Treasury, at the forthcoming meeting of theInternational Monetary Fund in Istanbul, the problems which would arise, particularly in the field of import control, if a further move towards convertibility were made in present circumstances.The Prime Minister welcomed these proposals for early actionto remedy the economic situation. He endorsed the views expressedby the Chancellor of the Exchequer on Bank Rate and on a further move towards convertibility. As regards public expenditure, he saidthat the Service Departments were now working out defence programmes related to a total figure of expenditure proposed by theChancellor. This would entail reductions in the strengths of the armed Forces which would provide an addition to the civilian labour force. From his discussions with the National Coal Board he was convinced that any reduction in the capital investment planned forthat industry would entail a further loss of coal output. He agreedthat the coal industry and atomic energy development should be exempt from the proposed restrictions on capital expenditure. a comprehensive plan on the general lines envisaged by the chancellor should be made ready by the time Parliament reassembled. Thisshould be a balanced plan and should include measures to showthat the Government were prepared to restrain profits. Politically,the Government were now in a position to pursue whatever policy was in the best interests of the country, and it was likely that firmaction would command a large measure of public support.The following is a summary of the main points made in thediscussion which ensued.Housing. The Minister of Housing said that he was preparing proposals forj\ a substantial reduction in the housing subsidies.   He believed thatthe right course was to discontinue the general housing subsidy butto maintain the subsidy for housing for special needs, such as slum clearance and relief of overcrowding. Indeed, as an earnest of theGovernments regard for social requirements, the subsidy for special needs might be slightly increased. This change in the scope of thesubsidy would in itself have the effect of reducing substantially theamount of house-building undertaken by local authorities. He wouldbe most reluctant to set a limit to the number of houses which localauthorities could build without subsidy. He was also very doubtful about the wisdom of attempting to bring down the annual total ofhouses built by local authorities to as low a figure as 100,000 a year,especially if it were likely that credit restriction would have the effectof reducing the volume of private house-building. He woulddeprecate the reintroduction of control over building generally. he believed that the Chancellors objectives could be achieved by an early announcement that the general housing subsidy was to be withdrawn :it might be expedient that it should be tapered off over a period of,say, two years.Reduction of housing subsidies was bound up with the questionof rent control. If the general housing subsidy were abolished, localauthorities would have to increase rates or raise rents. Those whoraisedrents would be likely to spread the increase over all their houses,and they could be encouraged to arrange differential rent schemes tomeet the needs of poor people.  An increase in the rents of local
n c/Roads.General.Relations.(previous reference:CM. (55) 15thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Cabinet were informed that substantial wage claims would be made in the autumn on behalf of workers in a number ofindustries and that disputes might arise in certain other industries.A major wage claim would be made on behalf of workers in theengineering and shipbuilding industries; and it was the presentinclination of the employers to make some concession on wages whileresisting pressure for shorter working hours. Agricultural workers were claiming a substantial increase in the minimum weekly wage, and authority houses would, however, widen the disparity between rentscharged by local authorities and those charged by private owners; andthis would sharpen the demand for relaxation of rent restriction.The Minister of Transport said that the proportion of thenational resources which was being devoted to roads was considerably less than before the war, despite the great increase in traffic. Theimportance of avoiding further delay in developing the transport system was emphasised in the memorandum circulated by the lord president (CP. (55) 106). The current roads plan did not involveexceptional expenditure and could hardly be slowed down. Once a major scheme had been authorised, it was cheaper to complete it as quickly as possible. As regards maintenance, the Exchequer onlycontributed to the maintenance of major roads, and this work was essential from the point of view of road safety. Economy in themaintenance of minor roads could only be obtained by way of anappeal to local authorities. The Minister said that he had intendedto propose an extended roads programme involving the expenditureof  90 millions over the next few years.In discussion there was support for the view that in presentcircumstances ambitious plans for road development would have tobe postponed.The following further points were also made in discussion (a) It might be desirable to postpone further work on some of thelarge Government buildings at present under construction.(b) Steps might be taken to make saving more attractive to smallinvestors.There was general agreement that the Governmenfs plan forremedying the situation must hold the balance fairly between thevarious classes of the community. The view was expressed, andcommanded support, that the Chancellors present plan was not sufficiently balanced. If house rents were increased and the bread subsidy were abolished and if, in addition, a reduction were to bemade in the subsidy on school meals, further restraints should be imposed on profits and dividends. Without these, the balance wouldnot be fairly held between the interests of different sections of thecommunity, and the plan would not succeed in reducing the pressure for higher wages. Various additional measures were suggested withthis in view. These included a capital gains tax, a compulsorylimitation of dividends, and a withholding tax on the Canadian model.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that all of these possibilities hadbeen considered but there would be great difficulties in putting them into effective operation. He would, however, consider again in thelight of the Cabinefs discussion how the plan which he had outlinedcould be modified so as to strike a fairer balance between the interestsof the various classes of the community.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion of the economic situation at a meeting on 5th September.
it was likely that further wage demands would shortly be made by railway workers.There was danger of a recrudescence of the inter-union disputewhen the time came for dock workers to exchange their employmentbooks at the end of September. The dispute in the Yorkshirecoalfield might also become more acute. London busmen might strike in the autumn on the question of hours of work.The wage increases already granted in 1955 amounted to 500,000 a week more than in the whole of 1954. There was little hopeof halting this trend unless the Government could make it clear thatthey were taking effective action to check the rise in the cost of living.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.Japan.Trade andPaymentsNegotiations.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 7.)General.3. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the state of thenegotiations for a new trade and payments agreement with Japan. Inaddition to a note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (55) 103)covering a report by officials on the negotiations, and a memorandumby the Minister of State, Board of Trade (CP. (55) 104), they also had before them a further memorandum by the Chancellor of theExchequer (CP. (55) 108) re-stating the objectives to be sought in thenegotiations, and a memorandum by the Foreign Secretary(CP. (55) 109) recommending that the question of shippingdiscrimination should not be raised further in the course of these negotiations but should be pursued separately.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the objectives set outin paragraph 5 of CP. (55) 108 did not represent any significantdeparture from our original demands. If we could secure thoseobjectives it would be reasonable, and consistent with theGovernment&apos;s general economic policy, to undertake to allow theColonies to import from Japan up to the amount of their requirements. On the other hand, we should be ready to restrictColonial imports if Japan would not enter into a satisfactory agreement and discriminated in an unjustifiable way against sterling area trade. As had been publicly stated by Ministers, the UnitedKingdom Government could not ask the Colonies to restrict their imports, contrary to their own interests, unless there were soundreasons for doing so on balance of payments grounds. It would therefore be unwise, at this stage of the negotiations, to threaten to restrict Colonial imports from Japan. To do so would prejudice the chances of securing our objectives and would be contrary to our interests in maintaining trade with Japan at a high level.The Minister of State, Board of Trade, said that, even if wesecured the objectives set out in paragraph 5 of CP. (55) 108, theadvantages which we should obtain would not, in his view, besufficient to justify a commitment to give Japan free access toColonial markets. Such a commitment would mean increasingColonial imports from Japan by about  7 millions, and this was bound to provoke strong criticism in this country in view of thecurrent difficulties of the textile industry in Lancashire and thegeneral balance of payments situation. The Japanese discriminatedadministratively against imports from the sterling area, and it was unlikely that we should secure reliable assurances that they would cease to do so. Moreover, the negotiations so far had shown thatwe were not likely to obtain all the trade concessions that we had hoped for when they started. On these grounds it would be wrong to undertake to give Japan any greater access to Colonial markets.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) It was becoming increasingly difficult to persuade theColonies to restrict their imports from Japan. There was a growing demand for cheap Japanese textiles.
(b) It was suggested that, in the present state of our balance ofpayments, it would be possible to urge the Colonies not to increase their imports from Japan, particularly if it was impossible to reach a satisfactory trade and payments agreement.Shipping. It was suggested in discussion that the possibility of restrictingColonial imports from Japan might prove a useful bargaining weaponwith which to persuade the Japanese Government to stop subsidisingthe uneconomic expansion of their mercantile marine. As against this it was argued that the shipping question was a long-term problem to which the possibility of restricting Colonial imports was not relevant.There was general agreement with the recommendation in cp. (55) 109 that the shipping issue should be pursued separatelythrough diplomatic channels and on other suitable occasions.The Cabinet (1) Accepted the recommendation made in CP. (55) 109 on theshipping question.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to discuss with theMinister of State, Colonial Office, and the Minister ofState, Board of Trade, the question of Japanese access toColonial markets, and to report further to the cabinet at their next meeting.Cyprus.Public Order.(previous reference:.CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 9.)4. The Cabinet were informed that, in pursuance of their decision of 15th August, the Ministerial Committee on Cyprus had considered what further measures could be taken to ensure themaintenance of public order in Cyprus if disturbances broke out during or after the forthcoming Conference. It had been agreed thata Director of Security should be appointed who could, if a state ofemergency occurred, assume operational control of the police andmilitary forces responsible for the maintenance of public order. Anacting appointment to this post had already been made. Steps were also being taken to strengthen the police forces in the Island. TheColonial Office were looking for men who had the necessaryqualifications and experience through service in Malaya or the Sudanor elsewhere.The Foreign Secretary said that unless the administration showedthemselves firm and resolute, the situation in Cyprus might easily get out of hand. Prompt action should therefore be taken to strengthen the police and security services in the Island. The Prime Ministerendorsed this view.The Cabinet Took note of the measures which were being taken to ensurethe maintenance of public order in Cyprus.Broadcasting. 5.   The  Prime  Minister  said  that  he  had  recently  hadThe Fortnight correspondence with the Leader of the Liberal Party in the HouseRule of Commons regarding the maintenance of the rule requiring theBritish Broadcasting Corporation to refrain from broadcasting(Previous discussions or ex parte statements on any issue which was to be reference: debated, within a fortnight, in either House of Parliament. In thisCM. (55) 16th correspondence Mr. Clement Davies had indicated his desire to conclusions, withdraw his agreement to the maintenance of this rule, and had minute 7.)       asked that his position should be made clear by the publication ofthe correspondence.  The Prime Minister had replied that he would
6. The Cabinet had before them a note by the foreign secretary (CP. (55) 110) covering a memorandum by officials on aproposal by Mr. Stassen (the special assistant on disarmament to thePresident of the United States) that the United Nations DisarmamentSub-Committee should appoint a technical panel to consider typicalor sample installations of types which would have to be coveredby an effective system of inspection.The Foreign Secretary said that it was recommended in thismemorandum that at the forthcoming meeting of the DisarmamentSub-Committee the Minister of State (Mr. Nutting) should give onlycautious support to Mr. Stassen&apos;s proposal, and that one of theconditions of our accepting it should be that nuclear productionplants should not be included. In his opinion it would be wiser thatthe United Kingdom representative should not raise difficulties about this American proposal at the present stage. The legislation in forcein the United States already prevented the disclosure of atomic ornuclear information. :,There was general agreement with this view.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to inform the Minister ofState (Mr. Nutting) of their view that he should not atpresent discourage this American proposal.Disarmament.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 10.)Irish Republic.(Previous \Reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 1.)7. The Prime Minister said that after the Cabinefs meetingon 15th August he had reviewed, in consultation with the HomeSecretary and the Secretary of State for War, the recent raids onArmy depots by members of the Irish Republican Army (I.R.A.)and had considered what further precautions should be taken tosafeguard arms and ammunition in military installations in thiscountry. It had been agreed that it would be inexpedient to allowsentries generally to carry loaded rifles, but other measures werebeing taken, unobtrusively, at regular Army establishments whichshould decrease the risk that further I.R.A. raids of this kind wouldbe successful. Arms and ammunition were, however, held at many other establishments, e.g., for Officers Training Corps at schools and universities and at Territorial Army establishments, at whichprecautions of this kind could not be applied. The War Office were considering what would be involved in calling in arms andammunition from such establishments as these, if the situationbecame more serious.Meanwhile, the arms and ammunition stolen from the ArmyDepot at Arborfield had been recovered by the police. Representa-tions about these raids had also been made to the Government ofthe Irish Republic.The Cabinet-Took note of the Prime Minister^ statement.have an early opportunity of explaining his change of attitude to representatives of the other political Parties at a meeting which was shortly to be held to discuss the question of Party political broadcastsunder the auspices of the Independent Television Authority. Atthat meeting there would be an opportunity to ascertain whetherthe Labour Party would continue to support the maintenance ofthe rule. The Cabinet could, if necessary^ review the matter furtherafter that meeting had taken place.The Cabinet Took note of the Prime Minister^ statement.
Afro-AsianConference.Loss of IndianAirliner.(previous reference:CM. (55) 9thConclusions,Minute 2.)8. The Foreign Secretary said that it had now been established that the loss of the Indian air liner which had been carrying part ofthe Chinese Communist delegation to the Afro-Asian Conferenceat Bandoeng had been due to sabotage at Hong Kong, a bomb havingbeen placed in the aircraft there by a Chinaman named Chou Chu,who had probably been acting as the agent of a Chinese Nationalistorganisation. This man had unfortunately left for Formosa beforethe authorities in Hong Kong had obtained sufficient evidence tojustify them issuing a warrant for his arrest. It was now proposedto issue a warrant, and to bring pressure on the Chinese Nationaliststo hand him over so that he might stand his trial on a charge ofconspiracy to murder. Information of the issue of the warrant wouldbe given in advance to the Chinese Communist Government, theIndian Government and the United States Government.The Foreign Secretary said that it was important that the UnitedStates Government should have sufficient advance notice to enablethem to be ready to rebut any suggestion that a United States agencyhad been concerned in this act of sabotage.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.Sudani.9. The Foreign Secretary said that the disturbances in theSouthern Sudan, which had begun with the mutiny of members ofthe Sudanese Defence Force, reflected the continuing resistance ofthe southern provinces to domination by the northern Sudanese.There had always been some doubt whether the country could remainunited without external rule; and, if it appeared that a division between north and south was inevitable, our policy might have tobe reconsidered. Meanwhile, we should continue to support theGovernment at Khartoum.The Governor-General would do his utmost to restore orderwith the troops already available in, or earmarked for, the Sudan.Any reinforcement of the British troops there would have presumablyto be matched by a corresponding increase of Egyptian forces; andwe should if possible avoid the necessity for bringing more Egyptiantroops into the Sudan.The Governor of Uganda had in a recent telegram (No. 601)offered suggestions for dealing with the current situation. these should be considered in the first instance by the Governor-Generalof the Sudan, to whom this telegram would now be repeated.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.Food. 10.   The Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food said thatBacon Prices during the summer there had been an unusually strong demand forbacon. Imported supplies had declined to some extent, and total supplies continued to be insufficient to meet the demand, even thoughthe retail price had been gradually increased. The price was now10 or 12 per cent, higher than at the time of decontrol, and theGovernment were making a profit of nearly  500,000 a week on imported bacon. But even if the price at which imported baconwas released to the trade had not been increased, retailers would doubtless have taken advantage of the strong demand to increase their prices. He was, however, inclined to think that the time had come at which the Government should not further increase the price at which imported bacon was released, even if that made it necessaryto allocate supplies to distributors for a short period before demandfell.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.


</content>
</cab>
