<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 313-329</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
T1US DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS&quot; GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1955SECRETCM. (55)35r.ii conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W..1,on Tuesday, 18th October, 1955, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir anthony the Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. H. P. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon..Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Tiiorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Osrert Peakh, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Gwilym&apos; Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heatitcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Items and 7).Dr. the Right Hon. Charles Hill, M.P.,- Postmaster-General.(Item 8).The   Right   Hon.Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpentbr,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Iterns 9 and 10).The Right Hon. Sir Reginald Manning-iiam-Buller, Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Item 7).Patrick   Buchan-Secretariat:vMr. H. O. Hooper.Mr. F. A. Bismop.49605-1b .

minute no.1345678910ContentsSubjectParliament       ...      ......Economic Situation. National Service.Disappearance of two Foreign Service Officers.House of Commons Disqualification ...Legislation.Case of Mr. C. A. Howell, M.P.Housing SubsidiesCapital PunishmentSoviet UnionVHsit of Soviet Leaders to United Kingdom.Middle East OilBuraimi  ...Post Office FinanceRoad Haulage Disposals BillCanalsPage345691011
B7^Parliament.EconomicSituation.(previous reference:CM. (55) 34thConclusions,Minute 6.)NationalService.(previous reference:CM. (55) 34thConclusions,Minute 1.)The Cabinet were informed that there would be pressure for a debate on National Service as soon as Parliament reassembled, andit was suggested that it would be preferable for the government&apos;s policy to be explained in a White Paper before such a debate tookplace.The Minister of Defence said that a While Paper could be madeready for publication by 29th October but it would not be possible,in the time available, to include in it detailed proposals on certain aspects of National Service which needed further consideration. TheWhile Paper would therefore cover substantially the same ground ashad been surveyed in the Prime Ministers speech at Bournemouth on 8th October. It would, however, be an advantage to be able to replyto the Questions which would be asked as soon as parliament reassembled by promising that a White Paper, even if it could not bemade comprehensive, would be published by 29th October, and thata debate would be arranged in the following week.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Defence, in consultation with theMinister of Labour, to prepare a White Paper on NationalService with a view to publication by 29th Oclober.Disappearance The Foreign Secretary proposed that, in view of the Questionsof two Foreign which would be asked as soon as Parliament reassembled suggestingService Officers, that the Government should institute an inquiry into the issues raisedby the disappearance of the two Foreign Office officials, theGovernment should without delay promise thai an opportunity wouldbe given to debate this matter. This might be done in-the course ofthe business statement by the Leader of the House on 25th October.He proposed lo seek the guidance of the Cabinet on the line whichshould be taken in such a debate. . ______The Cabinet were in agreement with this proposal. T/ie PrimeMinister said that he would consider whether to inform the opposition in advance of the Governments willingness to afford opportunity fora debate on this subject.The Cabinet (2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to circulate a memorandum for discussion at their next meeting on the line to be takenby Government spokesmen in a debate on the disappear-ance of the two Foreign Office officials.2. The Home Secretary recalled that the Ho use of commons disqualification Bill, as at present drafted, would not come intooperation until the next Dissolution of Parliament. After consulting the Prime Minister, he now proposed to move an amendment in (heCommittee Stage to provide that the legislation should come intoforce on the date of the Royal Assent, but that Members ofParliament adversely affected should be able to retain their seatswithout penalty until the next Dissolution. This would enable the rationalisation of the law on this subject, including that governingMinisterial offices and Ministers of State, to come into effect without49605-1 - 8 2House ofCommonsDisqualification.Legislation.(previous reference:CM. (55) 18th-Conclusions,Minute 5.)1. The Cabinet approved the terms of a Press announcement tobe issued from 10 Downing Street the following day about theParliamentary arrangements for debate on the economic situation.The Cabinet were informed that steps were being taken to notify the Opposition about these arrangements in advance.
Case ofMr. C A.Howell. M.P.(previous reference :CM. (55) 20thConclusions.Minute 2.) .delay, but would at the same time protect sitting Members who would otherwise be affected.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the Home Secretary&apos;s statement.The Lord Privy Seal said that his attention had been drawn to afurther case in which a Member of the House of Commons mighthave become disqualified by acceptance of an office of profit underthe Crown. It was thought that Mr. C. A. Howelf, M.P., had become&apos;disqualified since lie was a&apos;member of two panels constituted by theMinisfer of Tensions and National Insurance. It would be necessaryfor the Government lo move for the appointment of a SelectCommittee to investigate this case, when Parliament met.The Cabinet (2) Took note of this statement.housing subsidies.(previous reference:CM. (55) 32ndConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Cabinet had before tliem a memorandum -by theMinister of Housing and Local Government (CP. (55) 155) reporting the results of his discussions with local authority associations aboutreductions in housing subsidies, and setting out (in the Annex tohis memorandum) the detailed changes he now proposed in the ratesof subsidy.The Minister of Housing said that the rates he now proposed were in certain respects even lower than those he had previouslymentioned fo the Cabinet. In particular, he had not found it necessaryin his discussions with local authority associations to go above a level of  20 per house for houses provided in connection with slum clearance, although the rnte previously envisaged for these houseswas  24. Although the local authority associations had protestedvigorously against the proposals, they had not produced anyconvincing evidence that they would be unable lo maintain asatisfactory rate of council house building with the reduced subsidies.In discussion, the view was expressed that a reduction in expenditure on housing subsidies would be more acceptable to thepublic if (he rate of subsidy for houses provided in connection wildslum clearance was not reduced below the present level of  22 l.r.per house. To continue that level of subsidy would not, of course,meet the claim or local authorities for an increase on account of higher building costs and interest rates.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that from the point ofview of securing (he largest possible saving in government expenditure he would prefer that the rate for houses built inconnection with slum clearance should be kept to the lower figureof  20 which had already been announced lo the local authority associations. A really substantial saving on housing subsidies couldonly be obtained when some reduction could be made in the commitments for houses that had already been built. It would be helpful if some reference to the need to review subsidies on existing houses could be made when the Minister announced his proposals.It was similarly very desirable that there should also be some indication of the Governments intention to tackle, the problem of rent restriction.In discussion, it was pointed out that it had already been announced that the Government did not intend at present to alter the rates of subsidy payable in respect of houses already built. Asregards rent restriction, it was suggested that it would be unwise toindicate that (he Government had it in mind to deal with this problemunless their intentions could be carried into effect  promptly thereafter.
and the Cabinet had not yet considered in detail what course ofaction it would be practicable to take in this extremely dillicultmatter.it was the general opinion of the Cabinet that, in view of the close connection between the two subjects, it would not be possiblein announcing a reduction in housing subsidies to avoid making some reference to rent restriction. It might be enough for theMinister of Housing to.say that the Government recognised the relationship between the level of housing subsidies and the problemof rent control and were at present reviewing the whole structure of the Rent Acts. It was felt, however, that in the course of theParliamentary proceedings on (he Bill dealing with housing subsidies,it.might become necessary for the Government to go somewhatfurther than this. It was agreed that the Cabinet should considerthe draft of a statement on this subject at their next meeting.In further discussion the following points were also raised:  (a) The higher rale of subsidy of  24 per house for housesprovided by New Town Development Corporations or by&quot;expanded&quot; towns for the accommodation of &quot;overspill&quot;population from big towns was juslilied by the fact that these authorities had no pool of pre-war council houses over which anincrease in rents could be spread. New Town authorities wouldalso be unable to make up for a reduction in housing subsidies byan increase in rates in the same way as other authorities could.(b) The proposed higher subsidies for Hats in buildings abovefour storeys in height were necessary because the taller buildingsrequired strengthened construction and cost proportionately more.(c) The Secretary of Stale for Scotland said that the proposal(in paragraph 2(c) of (he Annex to CP. (55) 155) to take powers to recover from the Councils of &quot; exporting areas &quot; 50 per cent, of any contribution which was paid for the accommodation - of their&quot;overspill &quot; population by way of subsidy to other Councils, would raise particular dillicullies in Scotland, in view of the acute over-crowding in such places as Glasgow, fie would like to consider the implication of this proposal for local authorities in Scotland.The Cabinet - .....(I) Approved the proposals for amending the rates of housing subsidies, as put forward in CP. (55) 155, subject to therate for houses provided in connection with slum clearance being  22 I.v. per house.(2) Invited the Minister of Housing lo circulate to (he Cabinet,for consideration at their next meeting, a draft of the reference to the problem of rent control which he would propose to include in his announcement.(3) Invited the Minister of Housing lo consult the Secretaryof Stale for Scotland about the implication for scottish local authorities of (he proposal, in paragraph 2(c) ofthe Annex to CP. (55) 155, lo recover a part of (heGovernments expenditure on subsidies from the councils of &quot; exporting areas.&quot;4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary and I he Secretary of State for Scotland (CP. (55) 148)seeking authority lo announce thai the Government could not accept the main recommendations of the Royal Commission on capital Punishment and did not at present propose to introduce legislation lo deal with  the other recommendations.The Home Secretary recalled (hat, after considering the reportof the Royal Commission at their meeting on 29th July, 1954, the
Soviet Union.Visit of soviet leaders toUnitedKingdom.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions.Minute 5.)5. The Cabinet briefly discussed the question of the accommodation of the Soviet leaders during their forthcoming visit to the United Kingdom in April.It was agreed that it would be appropriate for the Soviet leaders to be accommodated at a suitable hotel in London, but thatarrangements should if possible be made for them to stay at privatehomes during their visits to Scotland and the provinces.It was also agreed that an Association football match would bea suitable sporting event for the Soviet leaders to attend.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to be.guided by the views expressed in their discussion in making the necessary. arrangements for the visit of the Soviet leaders.Cabinet had agreed not to accept the three major recommendationsof the Commission but had decided that no final decision should be announced until Members of Parliament had had an opportunityof expressing their views.   The Cabinet had also agreed that legislation should not be introduced to give effect to certain minorrecommendations of the Royal Commission.   The debate on theReport of the Royal Commission which took place in the House ofCommons on 10th February, 1955, turned mainly on a proposal,contained in an amendment to the Government Motion, that the death penalty should be suspended for a number of years.  In so faras the recommendations of the Royal Commission were discussed in debate, there was substantial support for rejecting the proposals to raise from 18 to 21 the statutory age limit below which the sentence of death might not be imposed, and to confer discretion on the juryto   decide   whether   extenuating   circumstances   would   justifysubstituting   a   sentence   of   life   imprisonment.    The   RoyalCommission&apos;s third main proposal, that the McNaghten rules inregard to insanity should be abrogated, had excited rather greaterdifference of opinion, but no satisfactory alternative had  beensuggested.Nothing had been said in the debate or subsequently which,would give the Cabinet cause to reconsider the conclusions they had reached, but no suitable opportunity had occurred for making anyfurther statement on the matter. The Howard League had, however,recently submitted a memorial urging that capital punishment shouldbe abolished or that at any rate the recommendations of the RoyalCommission should be adopted, and it was to be expected that assoon as Parliament reassembled there would be pressure for some further indication of the Governments intentions.The Prime Minister said that, although any announcement would doubtless give fresh impetus to the demand that the deatfi penaltyshould be abolished, nothing in his view had occurred to warrantany modification of the view which the Cabinet had previously taken.An announcement of the Governments decisions on the matter should therefore be made at the first suitable opportunity.The Cabinet Endorsed the proposal in paragraph 5 of CP. (55) 148 and authorised the Home Secretary to announce, when a suitable opportunity arose, the Governments decisions on therecommendations of the Royal Commission on capital punishment.
Middle East &apos; 6. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Foreign SecretaryOil. (CP. (55) 152) endorsing a report by oflicials which drew attention tothe need for expenditure on a scale more closely related to theimportance of our interests in the Middle East, particularly in the oil-bearing States. The report recommended that a working party should be set up to consider urgently what further action might betaken to safeguard these interests.The Foreign Secretary said that British oil companies ownedinvestments in the Middle East valued at  600 millions. The UnitedKingdom economy was now dependent on the oil produced in theMiddle East area  and, as the report showed, would  become increasingly dependent on this oil. An asset of vital importance to ushad grown up in that region witliin a period of fifty years and adequate steps should be taken to protect it.  Both the Egyptians andthe Saudi Arabians had been attempting to undermine our positionin the area and.it was evident that the Russians were now working to spread their influence there.   Although the defence of our positiondepended primarily on the solution of major political problems, theprospects of success for our policies would be considerably enhanced by an increase in Government expenditure.   Apart from sums spent-,     in  fulfilment of our treaty and similar obligations, the totalexpenditure of the United Kingdom Government in the area was atpresent less than  21 millions a year.   He hoped, therefore, that theCabinet would endorse in principle the recommendation in the official report that our expenditure in the area should be on a scale more closely related to our essential interests there and would approve the setting up of a working party to go into the matter urgently.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were generally in favour ofthese proposals.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in his view our pplicyin the Middle East had long needed some reinforcement of this kind.He therefore supported the proposal that a working party should consider urgently, but without prejudice as to method or commitmentas to the scale of any additional expenditure, what action might betaken.The Minister of Education said, with reference to para-graph II id) of the official report, that he was disturbed by thedifficulties which were being encountered in providing British teachers and teachers of English for countries in which we had importantinterests. Other countries, notably Germany, were apparently ableto subsidise the provision of teachers of their languages in foreigncountries and he had even heard of subsidised European teachersbeing sent abroad to teach English. It was a disadvantage that theBritish Council were not in a position to subsidise teachers of Englishsent abroad. He hoped it would be possible for his Department to bebrought into the proposed discussions.The Prime Minister said that the proposals were both timely and important and that a preliminary report should, if possible, besubmitted within two weeks.The Cabinet- .(1) Endorsed in principle the recommendation in paragraph 13of the report attached to CP. (55) 152 that the expenditureof the United Kingdom Government in the Middle East,and particularly in the oil-bearing States, should be on a scale more closely related to our essential interests there.(2) Agreed that a working party should be set up, with coniposi-tion  iid terms of reference as set out in paragraph 13 ofthat report, with the addition of a representative of theMinistry of Education, to examine what further action should be taken to safeguard the free flow of oil supplies.
(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary lo arrange that a preliminaryreport by this working parly should be submitted to theCabinet as soon as possible.
(3) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange that a preliminaryreport by this working party should be submitted to theCabinet as soon as possible.Buraimi. 7.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Foreign(Previous        Secretary (CP. (55) 153) about the dispute with Saudi Arabia overReference:       Buraimi.C C (54) 39thConclusions ^he Foreign Secretary said that wholesale bribery in the area by minute 4) &apos; tne Saudi Arabian Government had rendered the ArbitrationAgreement of July 1954 unworkable. It would now be unsafe to rely on any form of international decision to settle the disputesatisfactorily, and we therefore had no alternative but to base our future action and policy on a position of strength. This would involvereoccupying those parts of the disputed area to which we consideredour claim fully justified and which were vital to our interests and thoseof our client Rulers. That method had been adopted earlier in theyear in dealing with the Aden Protectorate and the Muscat frontiersagainst Saudi Arabia. We should again make a unilateral assertionof a reasonable line, defend it, and refuse to negotiate about it. Thiswould in fact mean that we should not occupy some territory to whichthe Ruler of Abu Dhabi had a good claim: we should emphasiseour forbearance in this respect, and in any case should avoid prejudicing our full claim in case we had eventually to submit tojudicial settlement.The retention of the Buraimi Oasis was essential to our positionin South-East Arabia and to our interests in the oil deposits whichwere believed to exist in the Trucial States and the Sultanate of muscat and Oman. But, under the Arbitration Agreement, the Saudishad been allowed to station fifteen policemen in Buraimi. It would benecessary to overpower this group without warning. This, togetherwith the other action necessary, including the resumption of control by the Muscat authorities of Hamasa, would be regarded as highlyprovocative by Saudi Arabia and many other Arab interests. If suchaction were challenged before the United Nations, the influence of theUnited States might be decisive, and we should therefore seek to convince the United States Government that the action we had takenwas justified and necessary on economic grounds.The Foreign Secretary therefore recommended that we should inform the United States Government, and immediately afterwardsthe Saudi Arabian Government, that the Saudi action had made a judicial settlement of the dispute impossible; that we should thenunilaterally declare the frontier we regarded as reasonable, making it clear that we would be prepared to make minor rectifications byagreement; that we should support the Ruler of Abu Dhabi inreoccupying the disputed area and removing the Saudi police fromBuraimi, and should give the Sultan of Muscat any help necessary to resume control of Hamasa; and that we should be prepared to defend the action we had taken by force, if necessary.The Prime Minister said that he agreed that unilateral action on.the lines proposed should now be taken. To announce beforehandour intention to break off arbitration and to take unilateral action would, however, involve the risk that such action might be forestalledor that an avoidable clash of arms might take place. He thereforepreferred that the disputed area should be reoccupied first, and an explanation given afterwards.Discussion showed that there was general agreement with thePrime Minister^ view, and the Cabinet were informed that themilitary arrangements which the proposed action called for wouldbe considered by the Defence Committee on the following day.The Cabinet also had a preliminary discussion of the possiblelegal consequences of the action proposed in CP. (55) 153.
9 CM. 35 (55)The Attorney-General said that the question of termination ofthe Arbitration might be the subject of litigation, if the Presidentof the International Court was asked by the Saudis to appoint two new members to the Arbitration, and possibly the Saudis would succeed in getting the issue before the International Court. In viewof this, it was important that our reasons for regarding the agreement as repudiated by the Saudis should be expressed as fully and preciselyas possible. We should have more chance of succeeding in establishing repudiation if we alleged and proved that the Pakistanimember of the Tribunal had been bribed. If we relied only on theconduct of the Saudi member and bribery in the disputed area, hewas not so hopeful of establishing before the Tribunal that the Saudishad repudiated the Agreement. It would be unfortunate if. afteracting on the lines proposed; a Court or Tribunal later declared thatthe agreement to arbitrate was binding upon us.It was the general view of the Cabinet that the legal consequences of the action which it was now proposed to take should be examined further by the Attorney-General, in consultation with the ForeignOffice and Commonwealth Relations Office.The Cabinet (1) Approved the recommendations in CP. (55) 153, providedthat the disputed area should be reoccupied before any announcement of our proposals was made to the UnitedStates or Saudi Arabian Governments.(2) Invited the Attorney-General, in consultation with theForeign Office and Commonwealth Relations Office toexamine further the legal consequences to the action proposed in CP. (55) 153.Post Office 8.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Postmaster-Finance. General (CP.&quot; (55) 146) seeking authority to publish in a White Paperproposals which involved a major recasting of Post Office finance and charges.The Cabinet were informed that these proposals had been examined by the Home Affairs Committee who felt that the cabinet should have an opportunity of considering them, particularly in viewof the increases recommended in telephone rentals and certain postal charges.The Postmaster-General said that the proposals resulted from a comprehensive review of Post Office finance and development. Ithad become necessary to raise the annual income of the Post office by the sum of  25  millions in order to meet increased wage andother costs, to provide for depreciation of the equipment of the telephone service on the scale appropriate to replacement cost andto enable the Post Office to return to &quot; self-contained finance &quot; byresuming the practice of making an annual fixed contribution to theExchequer as before the war. Of the additional revenue needed 19 millions would be raised by imposing increased charges for the telephone service. The telephone service to private subscribers andto some business subscribers in the provinces was now subsidised,to the extent of over  6 a year in the case of a private provincialsubscriber. The rental charges would now be increased very substantially from about  6 to  9 for an exclusive provincial privateline and from about  4 \0s. to  7 \0s. for a provincial shared privateline. Business subscribers would pay about  1 each more. these increases might well prove a deterrent to some of the 380,000 peoplenow waiting for the telephone. In raising nearly  7 millions ofadditional revenue from the postal services the burden was to themaximum extent possible being placed where the greatest losses werebeing incurred, particularly the express and re-direction services.49605-1 c
Post Office 8.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Poslmaster-Fiuance, General (CP, (55) 146) seeking authority to publish in a White Paperproposals which involved a major recasting of Post Ollice finance and charges.-------The Cabinet were informed that these proposals had been examined by the Home Affairs Committee who felt that the cabinet should have an opportunity of considering them, particularly in viewof the increases recommended in telephone rentals and certain postal charges.The Postmaster-General said that the proposals resulted from a comprehensive review of Post OHice finance and development. ^Ithad become necessary to raise the annual income of the Post Ofliceby the sum of  25% millions in order to meet increased wage andother costs, to provide for depreciation of the equipment of the telephone service on the scale appropriate lo replacement cost andto enable the Post Office to return to &quot;self-contained finance&quot; by,   resuming the practice of making an annual fixed contribution to theExchequer as before the war.   Of the additional revenue needed 19 millions would be raised by imposing increased charges for the telephone service.   The telephone service to private subscribers andto some business subscribers iii the provinces was now subsidised,-     to the extent of over  6 a year in the case of a private provincial&apos; subscriber.   The rental charges would now be increased  very-   substantially from about  6 to  9 for an exclusive provincial privateline and from about  4 \Qs. to  7 10s. for a provincial shared private&apos; line.   Business subscribers would pay about  1 each more.   these increases might well prove a deterrent to some of (he 380,000 peoplenow waiting for the telephone. !n raising nearly  7 millions ofadditional revenue from the postal services the. burden was lo themaximum extent possible being placed where the greatest losses werebeing incurred, particularly the express and re-direction services.49605-1 &quot; c v
The 2\d. letter rale woulcf^ however, remain, as would the 3d. call-boxfee for telephones, but letters weighing over 2 ounces would cost moreand the parcel rates would have to go up. All the new rates would be announced in the White Paper and would come into force on1st January, 1956.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he supported theproposals. The increased charges were anti-inflationary in character and would be helpful in the present situation. It was not possible tosay the same of the  300 millions investment programme which was envisaged in the proposals, but the amount was less than thePostmaster-General had thought necessary and lie recognised that thefigure must be accepted.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) Although telephone rentals were paid by private subscribers,unlike business subscribers, out of taxed income, this was not anadequate reason for subsidising the private subscriber. Private linesestablished in the provinces, were more expensive to install and .maintain and. Ihe private subscriber would continue to be subsidisedunder the present proposals, although less so than before.(/;) There might be criticism of the proposal to provide for the depreciation of the telephone service on the basis of replacement cost.None of the nationalised industries had adopted this practice. TheExchequer might lose more than it gained from this proposal ifindustry at large pressed to be allowed to provide for depreciation onthis basis against their tax liability.The Cabinet Approved the proposals contained in CP. (55) 146 and authorised the Postmaster-General to publish the White- Paper setting them out.Road HaulageDisposals Kill.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28tliConclusions,Minute 6.)9. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Transport (CP. (55) 154) setting out three new issues which had arisen in relation to the forthcoming Road Haulage Disposals Bill.The Minister of Transport said that these issues related to matterson which the Home Affairs Committee had felt doubt in consideringinore closely the scope of the forthcoming Bill. The issues were concerned with the future of the Parcels Company, the abolition atthe end of 1956 of the transport levy ami the proposed arrangementsfor dealing with the contract service vehicles.The Cabinet had decided at their meeting on 14th July that theParcels Company should be put on offer  for sale in October and thearrangements for doing this were now far advanced. It had been felt,however, that there was some risk that this company, which wasperforming a valuable public service, might pass into the hands of aspeculator who would have no interest but to break it up and sell the assets. If, on the other hand, sale could be postponed it might prove possible to devise an alternative method of disposal whichwould ensure the preservation of the Company as a public service by making use of the more flexible powers with regard to companydisposal which would be provided in the forthcoming Bill. he himself, however, did not rale highly the risk that any speculatorwould put forward a satisfactory offer  for this Company. the cancellation at this late date of the arrangements for sale would notmerely require a reversal of the Cabinefs previous decision but wouldevoke question and criticism among Government supporters, andwould not be well received by the Disposals Board itself. If an-offerwere received from an unsuitable purchaser, he could not intervene to adjudicate upon it unless he were invited to do so by Ihe british transport Commission or the Disposals Board after disagreementamong themselves, but lie could draw their attention to (heundesirabilily oTallowing the Company to fall into unsuitable hands.
Post Office 8.  The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Postmaster-Finance. General (CP. (55) 146) seeking authority to publish in a White Paperproposals which involved a major recasting of Post Office finance and charges.The Cabinet were informed that these proposals had been examined by the Home Affairs Committee who felt that the cabinet should have an opportunity of considering them, particularly in viewof the increases recommended in telephone rentals and certain postal charges.77/e Postmaster-General said that the proposals resulted from a comprehensive review of Post office finance and development.   Ithad become necessary to raise the annual income of the Post office by the sum of  25  millions in order to meet increased wage andother costs, to provide for depreciation of the equipment of the telephone service on the scale appropriate to replacement cost andto enable the Post Office to return to &quot;self-contained finance&quot; by,   resuming the practice of making an annual fixed contribution to theExchequer as before the war.   Of the additional revenue needed 19 millions would be raised by imposing increased charges for the telephone service.   The telephone service to private subscribers andto some business subscribers in the provinces was now subsidised,to the extent of over  6 a year in the case of a private provincialsubscriber.   The rental charges  would  now be increased  very substantially from about  6 to  9 for an exclusive provincial privateline and from about  4 I Or. to  7 IO.s. for a provincial shared privateline.   Business subscribers would pay about  1 each more.   these increases might well prove a deterrent to some of the 380,000 peoplenow waiting for the telephone.   In raising nearly  7 millions ofadditional revenue from the postal services the burden was to themaximum extent possible being placed where the greatest losses werebeing incurred, particularly the express and re-direction services.49605-1 c
7Road HaulageDisposals Uill.(previous reference:CM. (55) 28thConclusions,Minute 6.)9. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Transport (CP. (55) J54) setting out three new issues which had arisen in relation lo the forthcoming Road Haulage Disposals Bill.T/ie Minister of Transport said that these issues related to matterson which the Home Affairs Committee had felt doubt in consideringmore closely the scope of the forthcoming Bill. The issues were concerned with the future of the Parcels Company, the abolition atIhe end of 1956 of the transport levy and the proposed arrangementsfor dealing with the contract service vehicles.The Cabinet had decided at their meeting on 14th July that theParcels Company should be put on offer  for sale in October and thearrangements for doing this were now far advanced. It had been felt,however, that there was some risk thai this company, which wasperforming a valuable public service, might pass into the hands of aspeculator who would have no interest but to break it up and sell the assets. If, on the oilier hand, sale could be postponed it might prove possible to devise an alternative method of disposal whichwould ensure the preservation of the Company as a public service by making use of the more flexible powers with regard to companydisposal which would be provided in the forthcoming Bill. he himself, however, did not rate highly the risk that any speculatorwould put forward a satisfactory offer for this Company. the cancellation at this lale dale of the arrangements for sale would notmerely require a reversal of the Cabinefs previous decision but wouldevoke question and criticism among Government supporters, andwould not be well received by the Disposals Board itself. If an oilerwere received from an unsuitable purchaser, he could not intervene to adjudicate upon it unless he were invited to do so by the british transport Commission or the Disposals Board after disagreementamong themselves, but he could draw their attention to the undesirability of allowing the Company lo fall into unsuitable hands.The 2\d. letter rale wouki^ however, remain, as would the 3d. call-boxfee for telephones, but letters weighing over 2 ounces would cost moreand the parcel rates would have to go up. All the new rates would be announced in the White Paper and would come into force on1st January, 1956.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he supported theproposals. The increased charges were anti-inflationary in character and would be helpful in the present situation. It was not possible tosay the same of the  300 millions investment programme which was envisaged in the proposals, but the amount was less than IhePostmaster-General had thought necessary and he recognised that thefigure must be accepted.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) Although telephone rentals were paid by private subscribers,unlike business subscribers, out of taxed income, this was not anadequate reason for subsidising the private subscriber. Private linesestablished in the provinces were more expensive to install and maintain and the private subscriber would continue to be subsidisedunder the present proposals, although less so than before.(h) There might be criticism of the proposal to provide for the depreciation of the telephone service on the basis of replacement cost.None of the nationalised industries had adopted this practice. TheExchequer might lose more than it gained from this proposal ifindustry at large pressed lo be allowed to provide for depreciation onthis basis against their tax liability.The Cabinet Approved the proposals contained in CP. (55) 146 and authorised the Postmaster-General to publish the white paper setting them out.
As regards the transport levy, he had come to the conclusion, forthe reasons set out in his paper, that the Commission would have beenvery favourably treated, in accordance with the principles laid downin the 1953 Act, if the levy were terminated at the end of 1956. Butthe Commission had put forward an additional claim based onhardship which would entail a revision of the provisions of the1953 Act. This claim was so substantial that his colleagues had feltthat further consideration must be given to it. He hoped, however,that in any event the Cabinet would endorse his proposal to maintainthe levy at the same rate for the year 1956.In the case of the contract vehicles it had been felt to beanomalous to compel the Commission to sell and replace vehiclesneeded to carry out contracts which the Commission were legitimatelyentitled to undertake. He was arranging to discuss this matter further with the Road Haulage Association but he was averse to amending the 1953 Act to increase yet further the number of vehicles to beretained by the Commission.ft was pointed out in discussion that it could not be made acondition of sale of the Parcels Company that it should be preservedas a public service. A buyer would put the assets to the most economicuse he saw for them and it would not be practicable to attempt tocontrol his actions. On the other hand, it would be unfortunate ifthe Company, which was performing a useful public service, were to fall into the hands of a speculator who had no other intention but tobreak it up. The risk of such a buyer coming forward for a companyvalued at  7 millions was, however, considered to be remote. It was felt that this risk would have to be taken and that the Minister ofTransport should use such influence as he could bring to bear onthe Commission and the Disposals Board to minimise it.It was the general feeling of the Cabinet that the question of thetransport levy raised complex issues which should be explored furtherby the Minister of Transport in consultation with the Ministers most closely concerned. It would be appropriate if the problem of the contract vehicles were to be considered further at the same time.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the arrangements for putting the ParcelsCompany on offer for sale should proceed as planned,but invited the Minister of Transport to attempt inconsultation with the British Transport Commission andthe Disposals Board to minimise the danger of theCompany falling into undesirable hands.(2) Invited the Minister of Transport to consult further with theLord President, the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and the Financial Secretary, Treasury, on the issues whichhad arisen in connection with the transport levy and the contract vehicles respectively, and to report back to theCabinet.(3) Approved the proposal that, in any event, the transport levyshould continue at its present rate for the year 1956.10. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Transport (CP. (55) 151) recommending that anindependent committee of enquiry should be set up, on a widely representative basis, to examine the system of inland waterways.The Minister of Transport said that the recommendations of an expert enquiry, the Rusholme Board of Survey, were already available.The purpose of the further and more representative enquiry whichhe favoured would be to create a climate of opinion in which some progress could be made towards abandoning canals which weresurplus to transport needs, without undue obstruction by interestswhose main concern was in the amenities of the canals.
Tn a preliminary discussion, the Cabinet recognised that therewas considerable public sentiment on this question. If any further enquiry was entrusted to a small and expert body, the amenity andother groups interested in the matter might continue irresponsibly to resist the Government in their search for a practicable solution forthe problem of the surplus canals. On the other hand, a more representative enquiry might simply lead to the submission ofnumerous minority recommendations, so that the enquiry would not result in the guidance which the Government wished to obtain.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion of this subject at their next meeting.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,18th October, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
