<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/29/0 images: 350-357</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1955SECRETCM. (55)S$th CtomctosloifflsCopy No. J cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. I,on Thursday, 27th October, 1955, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton.Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade(Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister   of   Housing   and   LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. J. P. L. Thomas, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 2).The Right Hon. Lord De L&apos;Isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air(Item 2).The  MostReading,Hon.Q.C.,Foreign Affairs.the Marquess of minister of State forThe Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 2).The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Items 3-6).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Treasury (Item 1).Secretariat :Mr. H. O. Hooper.Mr. F. A. Bishop.
contents minute no.13.4567Parliament       ...      .......Economic Situation.National Service.Disappearance of two Foreign Office Officials.Armed Forces  ...      ......Education Grants.Road Passenger TransportMonopolies and Restrictive Practices...Calico Printing.New Hebrides.............Canals   ......Education        ...      ...      ...Teachers&apos; Superannuation.Technological EducationAssistance by Industry to Independent Schools.Pensions ...      ...      ...      ......Page3
Parliament.EconomicSituation.NationalService.disappearance of two ForeignOffice Officials.1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.After the report stage of the Budget resolutions on 31st October,there would be a debate on the economic situation on a motion tobe tabled by the Opposition. Whether the Prime Minister would speak in this debate would depend on the choice of Oppositionspeakers. If the Prime Minister decided not to speak, the Ministerof Supply might take part, with the Chancellor of the Exchequer inthat debate. This would leave the Financial Secretary, Treasury andthe Economic Secretary, Treasury, to deal with the Budget debate in the present week.It was agreed that the Minister of Defence and the Minister ofLabour would settle the terms of the Government motion on whicha debate on National Service would take place on 2nd November.This motion should, if possible, be so drafted as to allow government supporters some room for discussing general defence policy.It was agreed that a debate on the disappearance of two ForeignOffice officials should be arranged, if possible, for 7th November,when the Foreign Secretary would be able to be present.Aimmed Forces.EducationGrants.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 77thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Ministerof Defence (CP. (55) 145) seeking approval of a scheme for thepayment of special education grants in respect of children of membersof the Armed Services.The Minister of Defence said that the proposed grants would amount to a maximum of  75 a year in respect of each child of school age who was attending a boarding school, and  26 a year in respect of children who, on a change of station, were left withguardians in order to ensure continuity in a day-school education.The grants would be subject to income tax, while the recipientremained stationed in this country but would be - tax-free during periods when he was stationed overseas. The grants would be restricted to Service parents who were normally subject to frequentpostings; parents who stayed in the same place or moved onlyoccasionally would not qualify for them. In arriving at theseproposals a number of alternative possibilities had been examined and the present scheme, although less generous than had been hoped,was the most acceptable that could be devised. Subject to the cabinet&apos;s approval, he proposed to announce the scheme during thev  debate on National Service in the following week.The Secretary of State for War said that the value of the present scheme would be dependent upon a reasonably liberal interpretation of the condition that in order to qualify for a grant the Service parentmust be subjected to frequent postings. The scheme would bestultified if this condition were interpreted too narrowly. It had beensuggested that the basis of qualification might be a certificate thata Service parent, on reposting, was not likely to remain at the newstation for more than four years.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the proposed scheme,with which he agreed, was the best that could be done in thecircumstance?. Any improvement upon it would involveconsideration of the claims of other elements in the community whowere faced with the same or comparable problems. He recognisedthat the condition which related the grants to frequency of postingsmust be interpreted fairly.The Minister of Education said that local authorities were in aposition to be helpful in providing school places for Service children.It would help to assure their co-operation if they could be informed
of the new scheme slightly in advance of its announcement. TheMinister of Defence said that he would consult the Minister ofEducation on this point.The Cabinet Approved the proposals for education grants to Serviceparents set out in CP. (55) 145.3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the LordChancellor (CP. (55) 135) reporting that a Committee of ministers under his Chairmanship recommended that the British transport commission should not at the present time be directed to give up its control over certain bus companies.The Lord Chancellor said that the Transport Act, 1953, prevented the Commission from acquiring any more bus companies. It alsogave the Minister of Transport power to compel the Commissionto relinquish the control it then held over certain bus companiesby selling to the extent necessary its holdings in these companies.Some Government supporters, as well as private interests, particularlyBritish Electric Traction, Ltd., had pressed for these powers to beexercised. The Ministers who had examined this question had cometo the conclusion that on the merits of the case the commission should be allowed to retain, at any rate for the present, the controlling interest it at present possessed in a number of road passenger transport companies. Statements had, however, been made on behalfof the Conservative Party, including those set out in the annex to CP. (55) 135, which might be thought to commit the Governmentto the use of the powers to compel the Commission to give up itscontrol of bus companies. If these statements were taken in theirtrue context, it was clear that the Government had not undertaken to reverse the process of nationalisation, but only to bring it to ahalt. Moreover, the proposals of the British Electric TractionCompany and other private interests for acquiring control of theCommission^ holdings in these companies were not such as couldbe accepted by the Government; for, if the Commission were required to give up control, there was a danger that a virtual privatemonopoly might be created.The Committee accordingly recommended that the commission should not be required to give up its control of bus companies, and suggested that the Minister of Transport should, at suitableopportunities, explain the Government^ policy on this issue to their supporters.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in general agreementwith these recommendations.The Minister of Transport said that he would like to be givendiscretion to choose a suitable moment to explain the Government&apos;policy on this issue to Government supporters in order to avoid any risk of creating an atmosphere prejudicial to the remaining stages of road haulage disposals.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the British Transport Commission should notat present be required to give up its control of road passenger transport companies.(2) Invited the Minister of Transport, when he considered itopportune, to explain the Governments policy on this issue to Government supporters.RossiPassengerTransport.
monopolies and restrictive practices.CalicoPrinting.(previous references:CM. (55) 15thConclusions,Minute 4, and cm. (55) 22ndConclusions,Minute 6.)New Hebrides.(previous reference:CC. (53) 48thConclusions,Minute 4.)4. The Government had before them a memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade (CP. (55) 163) on the enforcement ofthe recommendations of the Monopolies Commission regarding the restrictive practices in the calico printing industry.The President of the Board of Trade said that the industry hadbeen referred to the Monopolies Commission as long ago as April,1951, and the Commission^ report, which was published in April,1954, recommended the discontinuance of the industry&apos;s &quot; percentagequantum &quot; and price-fixing arrangements, and of the redundancyscheme which provided for restrictive covenants when plant orpremises were disposed of. The &quot; percentage quantum&quot; and price-fixing arrangements provided, in effect, for a certainproportion of profits to be paid over to the less successful firms,in return for the maintenance of minimum prices. He had announced in February, 1955, that the Government were in generalagreement with the Commission^ recommendations. He had sincetried to get the industry to take voluntary action to end the profit-sharing and price-fixing arrangements, though the redundancyscheme would have been allowed to continue, provided that nofurther restrictive covenants were imposed under it. It was now clear that, while some individual firms would have agreed to do so,the industry as a whole were not prepared to take this voluntaryaction. They alleged that redundancy was again becoming a serious problem and wanted all the restrictive arrangements to be continued.In these circumstances, if the Government were to carry out theirpolicy on restrictive practices, there seemed no alternative but to take action under the Monopolies Act, 1948, to make the profit-sharingand price-fixing arrangements in the industry illegal. For thispurpose he proposed as soon as possible to lay an Order beforeParliament, which would require an Affirmative Resolution. he did not for the present propose to make any provision for carryingout the recommendation of the Commission relating to the redundancy scheme. He would, of course, inform the industry beforethe Order was published. At the same time he would not commit the Government on the question whether any action might be justifiedto eliminate redundancy in the industry.Discussion showed that the Cabinet accepted the need for taking this compulsory action under the Monopolies Act, 1948. The profit-sharing and price-fixing arrangements prevented competition andthe development of efficiency and should be brought to an end, eventhough such action would be highly unwelcome to the interests concerned. It was unlikely that the Opposition would challenge the government&apos;s policy.The Cabinet Approved the recommendations in CP. (55) 163.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary and the Colonial Secretary (CP. (55) 143) on theadministration of the New Hebrides.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that, the questionof future constitutional arrangements for the New Hebrides had beenunder consideration for some years. At one point it appeared that australia might be prepared to take over our responsibilities in the islands, but in recent years. the Australian Government had not shown any further active interest in the matter. The Islands wereadministered by an Anglo/French Condominium under a protocol of 1914. Following the Cabinefs decision of August, 1953, that anattempt should be made, in consultation with the French, to bring this Protocol up to date, agreement had been reached in discussions
between the British and French Resident Commissioners on the draftof a revised instrument of administration. This draft provided foran Advisory Council (to include representatives of the native population) and a Joint Secretariat, and there were proposals for economic development and for raising the revenue yield. On thebasis of the progress which had been made locally, it was nowproposed that the improvement of the administration of the new hebrides should be discussed further with the French Governmentand that negotiations should be opened for the revision of the protocol. In view of their geographical interest in the matter, theGovernments of Australia and New Zealand would be kept informed and consulted as necessary.The Cabinet were in general agreement with these proposals.The Prime Minister said that the proposals raised a point ofmore general importance, in that we might now have a changinginterest in retaining direct control over some of the more isolated and unpopulated islands which might be required for purposes of scientific or military experiment. This should be taken into account in the future in considering whether remote dependencies of thiskind should be transferred to Commonwealth Governments willingto assume responsibility for them. Commonwealth governments were inclined to be apprehensive about the use of territory under their jurisdiction, even if unpopulated, for the conduct of experimentsof the kind which might be necessary, and it would therefore be unwise to divest ourselves of direct control of all these remote andpotentially useful places.j The Cabinet- s^/ Approved the proposals in CP. (55) 143 for entering into/% negotiations with the French Government for the revisionof the 1914 Protocol which governed the administration ofthe New Hebrides.Canals.(previous reference :CM. (55) 37thConclusions,Minute 6.)6. , The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the composition of the proposed Committee of Enquiry into the system of inland waterways, and had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Transport (CP. (55) 165) containing proposals for the membership of this Committee.It was the general opinion of the Cabinet that, in view of thenature of the enquiry to be undertaken by the proposed Committee,Mr. Leslie Bowes would probably be the more suitable of thealternative nominations as Chairman of the Committee. It was felt,however, that the Committee was still too large to be effective andthat its members should be reduced to about six. One of these should, if possible, be a Welshman able to represent Welsh affairs.The Cabinet were informed that the British transport commission would prefer not to be represented on the committee but to give evidence before it. This would make it easier to avoidproviding for any representation of such groups as the inland waterways Association.It was agreed that the Minister of Transport should ascertain whether Mr. Bowes would be prepared to act as Chairman of theCommittee and that, if so, it would be appropriate to seek his views as Chairman Designate on the composition of the Committee.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Transport to ascertain whether mr. Leslie Bowes would be prepared to accept appointment as Chairman of the proposed Committee and, in that event,to discuss further with him the composition of theCommittee in the light of the views expressed by theCabinet.
Education.Teachers&apos;Superannuation.(previous reference :CM. (55) 34thConclusions,Minute 2.)7.  The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the&apos;Secretary of State for Scotland and the Minister of Education(CP. (55) 164) seeking authority for legislation to be prepared for anew teachers&apos; superannuation scheme.The Minister of Education recalled that the Cabinet had previously approved the general lines of a new teachers&apos; super-annuation scheme (set out in CP. (55) 138). These proposals had now been discussed with representatives of the teachers and localauthorities. The local authorities had in general accepted theproposals, although in some cases this was on the understandingthat the new scheme would represent an agreed settlement with the teachers. The teachers&apos; representatives would not commit themselveswithout further consultation, for which purpose a delegate conferenceof teachers was to be held in London on 19th November. the teachers&apos; leaders had recognised that the proposals as a whole were a considerable improvement, in that the Exchequer would meet theliability under the revised scheme to 31st March, 1956, and any future deficiency would be borne by the local authorities. although there would be continued opposition from teachers generally to theincrease in their rate of contribution to 6 per cent, he was reasonablyconfident that this opposition would not now be carried to a lengthwhich would jeopardise further progress with the legislation proposed.It would help to secure acceptance of the proposals if, before19th November, the Government could indicate that they wereprepared to make some increase in the pensions of retired teachers.One of the difficulties in satisfying the teachers&apos; claim was that negotiations on salaries had to be dealt with separately fromnegotiations on pensions.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was in full agreement with the proposals for a new superannuation schemev/hich, at considerable cost to the Exchequer, were a substantialadvance on the earlier proposals. As regards an increase in thepensions of retired teachers, it was likely that the proposal tointroduce a Pensions Increase Bill to improve the pensions of retiredmembers of the public services, including teachers, would be announced before the forthcoming teachers&apos; conference.The Cabinet Agreed that legislation for a new teachers&apos; superannuationscheme should now be prepared.technological education.(previous reference:CM. (55) 23rdConclusions,Minute 2.)Assistance by industry toIndependentSchools.8. The Minister of Education said that negotiations had beenin progress for several months for a scheme under which industry would provide capital grants for science laboratories for publis schools. Industry had shown itself most encouragingly responsive to this scheme, which would be of great value in furthering scienceeducation in the independent schools. A total sum of  1,400,000 forthis purpose had already been promised and further contributionscould be expected. The fund would be administered by a suitablyconstituted Committee and public statements would probably bemade about the scheme in the course of the coming week.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement by the Ministerof Education.
Pensions.(previous reference :CM. (55) 25thConclusions,Minute 9.)9. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it might be wiseif the Government were to make an early announcement that theywere considering the question of a Pensions Increase Bill to improve the pensions of retired members of the public services, both civil andmilitary. He had previously given the Cabinet (in CP. (55) 80) ageneral outline of such a measure, which would provide the majorityof such pensioners with an increase of 10 per cent, in their basicpension, subject to a maximum of  100, and would also abolish the requirement for a means test. Such a measure would, at present,involve additional expenditure of about  10 millions in the first year,of which 75 per cent, would have to be found by the Exchequer. the longer any such measure was postponed, the greater would be theincrease in pensions which would eventually have to be conceded.It was the general view of the Cabinet that the government ought to take an early opportunity of promising a Pensions IncreaseBill on these lines. It would, however, be injudicious to do so withinthe next few days when measures of retrenchment to deal with theeconomic situation were under discussion. The reply to a Questionwhich had to be answered in Parliament that day should thereforebe confined to the statement that the Government were undertaking a review of pensions. It would then be possible for the Governmentto announce shortly afterwards that they had decided to introduce a Pensions Increase Bill. It should be borne in mind that such anannouncement would need to be made before 19th November if itwere to be of help in securing acceptance by the teachers of theproposed new superannuation scheme.It was recognised that, although the scheme outlined by theChancellor of the Exchequer would give some increase to service officers retired under the 1919 Code, it would not fully satisfy their claim, and they might again assert that the Government had brokenfaith with them. The Minister of Defence asked whether service officers retired under the present (1950) Code would benefit if their pension exceeded  1,200. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that most officers retired under the present Code would benefit, but hewould examine this point further.The Cabinet Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to be guided bytheir discussion in any statement of the Governments policy on this subject.Cabinet Office,  S.W.1,27th October, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
