<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/60/0 images: 55-56</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF  HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1953.SECRET Copy No.     71C. (53) 11931st March, 1953.CABINETITALY AND PERSIAN OILMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs since the war Italy has built up a surplus of refining capacity. She can there-fore make good use of Persian crude oil, particularly at the discount of 50 per cent,below the world price which the Persians are offering to certain Italian companies,and as part of barter transactions which will give an outlet for Italy&apos;s industrialpotential.2. There has therefore been considerable pressure on the Italian government from certain Italian industrialists and businessmen to permit deals in oil from persia. The Fiat group have been playing a prominent part and are known to haveplans to provide machinery and textile goods in exchange for Persian oil. Therehave already been the Rose Mary attempt (which was frustrated in the Aden Court)and the Miriella venture (oh which Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (A.I.O.C.) lost thefirst round recently in the Venice Court); and now the Miriella and a larger tanker?the Alba, are loading oil at Abadan, and there are reports that others will follow.These deals are in the hands of an Italian firm, &quot; SUPOR,&quot; which may not havelarge financial resources.3. In the last 15 months the Italian Government have repeatedly assuredus that they would not permit the import into Italy for internal use of crude oiland products from Persia. (They have apparently no legal powers to prevent oil imports into free port areas for subsequent re-export.) More recently, however,under pressure from their industrialists and no doubt with an eye on the comingelections, the Italian Government have been wavering. Following the VeniceCourt&apos;s decision in the Miriella case, Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Rome strongly urged the Italian Government to refuse the issue of import licences for Persian oiland to make a clear statement of public policy, disapproving of such trade in&quot; stolen &quot; Persian oil. This would discourage Italian speculation and improve theA.I.O.C.&apos;s chances of winning their case in the Rome Court regarding ownership ofthe Miriella&apos;s cargo. The Italian Government^ response has hitherto beenequivocal.4. It is therefore satisfactory to note from the annexed telegram from her majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Rome that two of the leading Italian industrialists haveassured Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador that none of the large Italian industrial firmswere interested in purchasing Persian oil, and that similar assurances have beengiven to the Italian Government.5. We should not, however, place too much reliance on these assurances noron the Italian Government now issuing a firm statement to discourage Italian speculation-lators, since we are not in a position to offset, by, for example, offering cheapersterling oil to Italy, the undoubted economic attractions for Italy of trade in persian oil. But in view of this latest report, I am pressing the Italian Government again,to adopt a firmer attitude, to issue a clear statement disapproving of all deals in&quot; stolen &quot; oil, and to give us a categorical assurance that no import licences will beissued. /A. E.Foreign Office, S.W.1,31st March, 1953.43986
ANNEXSir V. Mallet(No. 184)26th March, 1953Persian Oil.Pirelli (the rubber magnate) and Valetta (head of Fiat) have called on meseparately in connexion with reports published in the British and French press.They both assured me emphatically that neither of these firms, nor any of the largeindustrial interests mentioned in the press reports, was interested in the purchaseof Persian Oil. They had given similar assurances to the Ministry of ForeignAffairs.2. Corrias confirmed to Minister Commercial that these important indus-industrialists had visited him and had spoken in similar terms. Minister Commercialpointed out that this indicated withdrawal of pressure from industrialists, to which both Zoppi and Corrias had previously referred. It should therefore be possiblefor the Italian Government to take a less compromising line, refuse the issue of import permits and make a statement to discourage Italian speculators. Corriasreplied that no permits had yet been applied for, but the present improbability ofSupor getting substantial financial backing might well have the undesirable resultof forcing Supor to try and sell their oil wherever they could as quickly as possible.The question of an. announcement of policy was a highly political one, and hethought that no decision had yet been taken with regard to it.3. It is clear that these responsible firms do not wish Anglo-Italian relations to be endangered merely for the possibility of. doing business with Persia. Theyboth naturally expressed hope that an early solution of the Anglo-Persian disputewould permit them to develop exports to Persia. Their influence with the ItalianGovernment may help to persuade the latter not to take any action which mightadversely affect our interests.

</content>
</cab>
