<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/60/0 images: 68-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET .  ,C. (53) 124 copy NO,   Ui U1 Oth APRIL, 1953.CABINETATOMIC ENERGY organisation note by the Prime minister circulate for the consideration of my colleagues an interimreport by the Committee on the future of the Atomic Energy organisation under the Chairmanship of Lord Waverley, which was established inaccordance with the decision taken by the Cabinet on 14th January(C.C,(53) 2nd Conclusions, Minute 9).W ,o. C,10, Downing Street, S.W.T.10th April, 1953.COMMITTEE ON ATOMIC ENERGY ORGANISATIONINTERIM report we were appointed by the Prime Minister -&quot;To devise a plan for transferring responsibilityfor Atomic Energy from the Ministry of Supply toa non^Departmental Organisation and to work outthe most suitable form for the new Organisation,due regard being paid to any constitutional andfinancial implications. &quot;2. We have had a preliminary exchange of views with representativesof the Treasury (Sir Edward Bridges, Sir Bernard Gilbert, Sir Thomas Padmoreand Mr. G. P. Humphreys-Davies);  of the Ministry of Defence (Mr. R, R, Powell,Deputy Secretary, and Sir Frederick Brundrett, Deputy Scientific Adviser);and of the Ministry of Supply (Sir James Helmore, Permanent Secretary).MW.W-tw^e have also had. oral evidence from the following officers v/ho are responsiblefunder the Minister of Supply for various aspects of atomic energy;General Sir Frederick Morgan, Controller of Atomic Energy;^Sir John Cockcroft,Director, Atomic Energy Research Establishment; Sir Christopher Hinton,Deputy Controller, Atomic Energy, Production; Sir William Penney, Chiefr      Superintendent, High Explosives Research.3. We have carried our discussions to the point at which it is clearthat the main problems with which we shall have to deal are:-
(a) The position of Ministers in relation to the new Organisationand, in that connection, the determination of the best methods of reconciling the practical efficiency of the various plants and establishments with the ultimate responsibility of Ministers toParliament,(b) The procedure for providing the new Organisation with thenecessary finance and the system of financial control.(c) The devising of means which will ensure that the standards of security observed in the new Organisation are not less effective than those at present in force.(d) The provision of suitable safeguards for the interests ofexisting staff who are to be asked to transfer to the new organisation.(e) The relations of the various Atomic Energy establishments and Plants to each other and to the Headquarters of the new organisation.(f) The status of the Establishments which are engaged on atomicweapon research and on the production of parts of such weapons;and the relation of those Establishments so far as they may bebrought within the new Organisation to the Defence departments and the Ministry of Supply.(g) The special difficulties of the interim period during which legislation is being prepared and passed and administrativepreparations are being made for the building up of the new or ganisation.4. None of the departmental representatives with whom we have discussed these problems has suggested to us that any of them are insoluble.And indeed we are now satisfied that it is completely practicable to devise a plan which will include reasonable solutions to all these issues.   Many ofthe problems, however, call for further close and detailed investigation,much of which can only be carried out effectively at the various plants and establishments.   We are not therefore in a position to commit ourselves inrespect to the most suitable form for the new Organisation, or for thetransfer of responsibility to it, until we have been freed to carry oninvestigations on the spot.   Such examination will inevitably lead to somepublicity and possibly to embarrassing questions which we understand that theGovernment may wish to forestall.   We therefore hope that the Government will now be prepared to take such steps as they think fit to set us free to make all such enquiries as appear necessary to us, including visits to any of the establishments.5. In the event of the Governments deciding, in the light of this report,to announce publicly at this stage a decision in principle to transfer responsibility for atomic energy to a non-Departmental Organisation, wewould urge that such an announcement should include a general undertaking that the interests of the existing staff will be fully safeguarded.WaverleyJ, H, WoodsW, A, Akers.9th April, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
