<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/60/0 images: 89-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET( iC.(53) 132 COPY NO.      j17th APRIL, 1953.CABINETATOMIC ENERGY organisation memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer was sorry to have to ask my colleagues to postpone a decision on theWaverley   Committee,s interim proposal (C. (53) 124),2. We want, I agree, to make some announcement -(a) to enable the Committee to continue its investigations withoutembarrassment; and(b) to allay the speculations and apprehensions likely to follow on theleakage which has already taken place.3. Should this announcement take the form suggested, i. e. the announcementof a decision in principle to transfer atomic energy to a non-departmental organisation?4. If we were to do this we should, I suggest, put ourselves in an awkwardposition.   It is, I think, evident that a non-departmental organisation to runatomic energy could not be on the same lines as, say, the Coal, Gas orElectricity Boards.   There must be provision for much closer ministerial responsibility.   Again, special arrangements will be needed owing to the factthat almost the whole of the cost for many years has got to be found from public funds.5. If we were to announce transfer tc?    non-departmental organisation weshould at once be asked what arrangements we contemplated to deal with these andother issues involved in such a transfer.   Would it not be better to make theannouncement on the main principle when our ideas are more clear-cut as to how these issues are to be settled?6. As the Cabinet know, the Waverley Committee was set up to provideanswers to these questions.   The Waverley Committee want first to pay personalvisits to the establishments in question.   Meanwhile I suggest that it would bebetter for us not to commit ourselves publicly to the setting up of a non-departmental organisation which would involve legislation before we have seenan outline of the proposed Bill.7. I would therefore suggest that the announcement should be in more general terms, on the following lines:-The Government have set on foot a review of the organisation for supervising atomic research and production in this country.   Tohelp them in this task the Government have appointed a committee under the Chairmanship of Lord Waverley.   This Committee has
already made a preliminary examination and will shortly carryout a more detailed investigation, including visits to the variousplants and establishments.The Government think it right to state that, whatever changesmay be decided upon, the rights and interests of the existing staff will be fully respected.   Consultation with the staff representatives will take place at the appropriate time.R.A.B.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.17th April, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
