<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/60/0 images: 153-154</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)confidential.(53) 146 COPY NO. //4th MAY, 1953.CABINETREVISION OF THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE ACTS:  MUTINYMemorandum by the Minister of DefenceLast February I circulated a paper (C. (53) 60) to the Cabinetinviting them to agree that certain proposals should be placed, beforethe Select Committee on the Army and Air Force Acts with regard to the penalty for the offence of mutiny, which the Select Committee had been discussing.2. Briefly, the Select Committee considered that the death penalty for mutiny should only apply to the most serious offences of this kind inpeace and war, in particular to mutiny accompanied by violence or to avoidservice against an enemy, and that the less serious forms of the offenceshould be punished with imprisonment.   At present death is the maximumpunishment for all offences of this kind under Section 7 of the Army and AirForce Acts, varying from violent mutiny in arms to the collective refusal of two or three men to obey orders or the failure of someone present to use his best efforts to suppress or prevent a mutiny.   In practice, the death sentence is rarely passed or carried out,3. The Service Departments agree in principle with the SelectCommittee&apos;s views, and would propose to confine the death penalty (as amaximum) to:(1) Taking part in(a) a mutiny involving violence or the threat of use of violence,  or(b) a mutiny with the object of avoiding or refusing some duty or service against or in connection with operations against anenemy, or impeding the performance of any such duty or service,(2)       Inciting to take part in such a mutiny or an intended such mutiny.(3)       With intent to assist the enemy, failing to use utmost endeavours to suppress or prevent a mutiny or to report it.For other offences of mutiny the maximum penalty would be imprisonment for life.4. When the Cabinet considered my paper the Solicitor-Generalexpressed some doubts about the difficulties of proving certain of the offencesunder paragraph 3 above, and the Cabinet invited me and the Service ministers to reconsider the proposals in consultation with the Law Officers, and tosubmit the matter again to the Cabinet (C. (53) 12th Conclusions, Minute 3).
5. We have now had a full discussion with the Law Officers.   while there are differences of opinion about the proposals of the Service Departments,the main concern of the Law Officers is to ensure that the difficulties whichthey see in them are fully appreciated by all concerned.   The Service Ministers,the Law Officers, and 1 are therefore now agreed to seek the Cabinetsauthority to place the proposals of the Service Departments before the SelectCommittee without attempting to resolve the points of difference, but bringingout clearly the difficulties and the implications of those aspects of them towhich the Law Officers have drawn attention.   In presenting the proposals to the Select Committee they will not be described as being sponsored formallyby the Army and Air Councils, and still less as being the considereddecisions of the Government.   The latter course would mean that the cabinet would be doing some of the work for which the Select Committee was appointedby the House of Commons;  and I feel that the Government might be subjectto considerable criticism if it became known that they had committed themselves to a particular view before the matter had been considered by theSelect Committee.   Moreover, it might be embarrassing for the government&apos;s supporters on the Committee (including the Chairman, Sir Patrick Spens)if they found that the views presented to them had already been approved bythe Cabinet.6. The course we recommend would enable these proposals to bethoroughly discussed by the Select Committee, who would includerecommendations on them in their report to the House of Commons,   Itwould then be open to the Government, after the Report had been presented, toreach a final decision on the measures which should be recommended toParliament.7. The Select Committee have been awaiting the proposals of theService Departments on this matter for many months past, and I should beglad if the Cabinet will authorise me now to present the proposals to theCommittee.A.Ministry of Defence, S.W.1.4th May, 1953.

</content>
</cab>
