<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/127/0 images: 87-89</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C(66) 150 COPY NO.     677th November, 1966CABINET vFURTHER SOUNDINGS OF THE SIX;  consultations with COMMONWEALTH GOVERNMENTSMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth affairs at the Cabinet Meeting on 3rd November (CC(66) 54thConclusions, Minute 4) it was recognised that it would be necessaryto decide the nature and timing of consultations with the Governmentsof the Commonwealth in regard to our further moves tov/ards Europe.2.       The position as it was left after the Commonwealth PrimeMinisters&apos; Meeting in September was that we had promisedCommonwealth Governments information on the progress ofexploratory discussions and consultation at all stages of any negotiations.    Other Commonwealth Governments continued to press for consultation even at the exploratory stage.     The relevant extractfrom the final communique (Cmnd. 3115) is annexed.3.       If a special meeting of the European Free Trade Association(EFTA) Heads of Government is convened at short notice a few weeks after the Lisbon meeting, Commonwealth Governments may suspectthat there has been a significant change in our attitude towardsjoining the European Economic Community, however much we assurethem that our position is unchanged.    Some may urge that a commonwealth Ministerial Meeting should be held.    My colleaguesv/ill probably feel that this would not suit us.    In short, whatever theadvantages in other directions of the proposed special EFTA meeting,it is likely to sharpen our difficulties with the Commonwealth, and toencourage them to press that essential Commonwealth interests shouldbe given as prominent a place in the proposed approach as those of efta.4.       Whether or not the EFTA meeting is held, we must eitherbeforehand or at the same time take Commonwealth Governments into our confidence and assure them that we shall seek to safeguard their essential interests,5,       As regards the line to be taken with, the Six, we shall need tosay to Commonwealth Governments that it is proposed to ascertain what terms are likely to be obtainable for safeguarding commonwealth as well as British interests.    I think that it will be desirable to mentionto the Six in general terms that we shall need to know whether terms atleast as good as those negotiated by the Conservative Government in 1962can be assumed for Commonwealth countries in Asia, Africa and the carribbean, as well as special safeguards for New Zealand,    If these arenot mentioned, there will be a risk that an alleged account of what hasbeen said will leak from one or other of the six capitals in terms thatmay embarrass us in relation to Commonwealth Governments and theOpposition at Westminster.H. W.B.Commonwealth Office, S. v7*l.7th November, 1966 SECRETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)
ANNEXCOMMONWEALTH PRIME MINISTERS&apos; MEETING,LONDON, 1966Extract from final communique (Cmnd, 3115)&quot;They observed that the British Government had indicated atthe Trade ministers Meeting its readiness to seek membership inthe European Economic Community provided that the essential interestsof Britain and other Commonwealth countries were safeguarded.    TheBritish Government stated that they would make available the maximuminformation possible to other Commonwealth Governments on theprogress of exploratory discussions and would at all stages of any negotiations consult closely with other Commonwealth Governments,The other Heads of Government noted this assurance and stressed theimportance of consultations at all stages of exploratory talks,discussions and negotiations.    The hope was expressed that theinterests of developing countries would receive special attention during these talks&quot;.


</content>
</cab>
