<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/127/0 images: 155-158</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
FAMILY endowment memorandum by the Minister without portfolio the Ministerial Committee on Social Services recentlydiscussed the problem of poverty among families with children and Iundertook as Chairman to report to the Cabinet the views of theCommittee on the need for early action to help the poorest familiesso that those views might be taken into consideration when public expenditure allocations for 1967-63 are settled.Extent of family poverty2.      The preliminary results of a survey recently undertaken by theMinistry of Social Security show that about 160,000 families containingabout 500, 000 children have incomes below the new supplementary benefit (formerly national assistance) level and are unable to bringthemselves up to that level because the father is in full time work or,being unemployed, cannot receive the full supplementary benefitbecause of the &quot;wage stop&quot;.    The figures show that the problem isnot c onfined to the lowest wage earners, nor to the larger families.The results of the survey will have to be published some time nextyear.    The level of income set by the new supplementary benefitsmay be represented as the minimum acceptable standard set by thecommunity for its members.Possible remedies3.       The Social Services Committee were generally agreed,because of the pressing need for the limitation of public expenditure,that any additional expenditure on families with children must be concentrated as far as possible on the families with smaller incomes.This cannot be achieved by an increase of family allowances on itsown even if the increase were confined to the larger families.    two alternative methods were therefore considered, one involving anincrease of family allowances associated with a reduction of incometax child allowances; the other involving the introduction of a new form of income-tested allowance.An increase in family allowances associated with a reduction of incometax child allowances4.       The most satisfactory type of scheme of this sort appeared tothe majority of the Committee to be one which concentrated the benefitof the increased family allowances on families paying no tax or tax at less than the standard rate.    This could be achieved by an all-roundincrease in the amount of family allowances accompanied at the sameCOPY NO.CGM FIDE INITIALHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S GOVERNMENT)C(66) 15911th. November, 1966CABINET
time by a reduction in income tax child allowances.    By this means the benefit of the family allowance would be scaled down or completelyextinguished or more than extinguished according to taxable income.The effect would be broadly similar to that of a specific income test,but without the political and administrative objections attaching to sucha test.    Those paying tax at the standard rate would gain nothing or would lose a little.    One possible example is a scheme costing (on thelatest revised estimates)  49 million net in the first year and  33million net subsequently.    These figures represent a net increase in expenditure on family allowances of  160 million and increased taxation of  111 million and  127 million respectively;  it would be anotherinstance of substituting Government expenditure for tax reliefs of the type referred to in paragraph 54 of the YtThite Paper on public expenditure:  Planning and Control (Cmnd. 2915),    Such a scheme would bring about 57 per cent of deficient families and 65 per cent ofthe children in such families up to or above the supplementary benefitlevel, and give material help to many of the remainder.    Schemes ofthis sort could be tailored to any given expenditure ceiling (althoughthe lower the expenditure the less help would be given to the deficientfamilies and the more the cost would fall on those with families in otherincome groups).Income tested allowance5.       This could give the greatest help to the highest proportion of the poorest families at the lowest cost, but would require a form of means test having familiar practical and political difficulties.    If this typeof scheme were adopted, the Committee would prefer one involving a form of &quot;housing allowance&quot; related to family incomes and rent whichmight cost  17 million in a full year.    This would entail a test of needon the lines of supplementary benefits or an income test on the linesof the rate-rebate scheme.    Before a final decision could be taken tointroduce such a scheme, further detailed consideration would be needed,particularly of its interaction with local authority schemes for the rebateof rents and rates.Views of the Social Services committee.       The majority of the Committee were opposed to any &quot;means-tested&quot; scheme for families in this field of social provision (wherein the great majority of cases the wage-earner would be in full-timework) and favoured the introduction of the type of scheme which com-bined an increase of family allowances with a reduction of income taxchild allowances to take effect if possible from the beginning of the tax year 1967-68,7.       Treasury Ministers, however, see objections on grounds ofboth policy and practice to schemes of this sort.    They feel that such schemes would involve a big disturbance of the tax and family allowanceposition of millions of families to meet the difficulties of a small minority;  and would concentrate the necessarily limited extra expenditure insufficiently on the poorest families and would be unpopular with husbands who would have to pay more tax in order tobring a higher family allowance to the wife.    Further, in their view,the Inland Revenue with all its present difficulties should not be calledupon to operate such a scheme in 1967-68 even if it were acceptable inprinciple.    Incidentally, such a scheme would make the tax system biteconfboential
more deeply into the wage packet and so lessen its taxable capacity.Treasury Ministers therefore think that the only possible means of helping the poorest families next year would be through a means-testedscheme, preferably of the &quot;housing allowance&quot; type, analogous to theschemes of rate rebates and rent relief, which also involve incometests and have been generally accepted.8.      If on policy or practical grounds it is decided that an increaseof family allowances associated with a reduction of income tax child allowances is impossible next year, some members of the Committeewould reluctantly acquiesce in a means tested housing allowance whichmight come into operation in September, 1967 (at the earliest), as theonly available means of helping quickly and sufficiently the 160, 000families in greatest need, pending the conclusion of a comprehensive review of family endowment in cash, services and kind.    Othermembers of the Committee, however, feared that if we adopted a meanstested scheme, even as an interim measure, we should be stuck with it and this would inevitably prejudice any reform of the present systemof family allowances and income tax child allowances to which they attach major importance.     They would in consequence be prepared to defer any improvement in provision, even for the poorest families, fora few months until April, 1968, if there was a firm prospect of a more radical reform by then.For decision9.       If the Committee^s first preference (for a combined scheme of increased family allowances and reduced tax allowances) is eitherunacceptable or could not be fulfilled in 1967-68:-(i)  does the Cabinet favour a means-tested scheme to begin aboutSeptember, 1967, or(ii)  would the Cabinet prefer to do nothing for 1967-68 and direct afurther and urgent study to be made of the whole problem, and(iii)  if the Cabinet adopt (ii) should additional charges for school meals and welfare milk be similarly deferred?D.H.70, Whitehall, S.W.I.11th November, 1966


</content>
</cab>
