<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/127/0 images: 182-185</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)EDUCATIONAL EXPENDITURE IN GREAT BRITAIN 1967-68Memorandum by the Secretary of State for education and science naturally find the Chancellor of the Exchequer&apos;s proposals for education (C(66) 15 8) unpalatable.    If accepted, they would leavespending on education in Great Britain next year only 4 per cent above this year&apos;s figure.     This compares with an increase of about 6 per cent for all public expenditure - 8 per cent excluding defence - and10 per cent both for roads and public housing investment.    In theNational Plan we said that educational spending would increase ratherfaster than the average for all services.    Although the link betweeneducation and long-term economic growth is generally acknowledge, theChancellor now proposes to reverse the priorities.2,     Between this year and next, the school population will increase by 3 per cent and the number of students in higher and further educationby at least 5 per cent.    If   educational expenditure increases only by4 per cent, it will barely be possible to maintain the present level of spending per pupil or student,3.     Nevertheless, I realise that education must make its contribu-tion, and I can reluctantly accept the Chancellor&apos;s proposals with one exception mentioned below.School Meals ( 12 million)4.     I believe that this can be justified, and that with suitableremission scales (already allowed for in the estimated savings) v/ecan protect the position of large families.    No doubt in the long runwe shall alter the whole system of meals subsidies as part of a major new policy for family support; but in the short run I agree that v/emust face an increase from 1/- to l/6d.    There will, however, be aconsiderable outcry both in the Party and amongst the parents affected.Miscellaneous ( 7, 0 million, including  3. 2 million from increasesfees)5.     I can again reluctantly accept these cuts, although I must pointout that half of them will fall on local authority spending and that they come on top of the cut in Miscellaneous Environmental Services, about10 per cent of which ( 3 million) will affect public libraries etc. ,regarded by many as part of the education service.C(66) 166COPY NO.14th November, 1966CABINET-1-
Direct Grant Schools ( 1.0 million)6.     A cut in the grant at this stage would look like a vindictiveattack on the direct grant schools and might damage the prospect o persuading them to play their part in our plans for comprehensiveeducation.    I would therefore prefer, and can promise, to save  1 million by other means.Student support (  8. 6 million)7. These cuts, unlike the others, I find great difficulty in accepting,I must ask that they be re-considered on three groundsi-(i)    The Chancellor^ proposed cuts in educational spendingneed to be scaled down at some point in order to redressthe imbalance described in paragraph 1 above, L e* inorder to bring education back to the priority which itheld in the National Plan,    For reasons described below,this is where I should prefer the scaling-down to occur,(ii)    We shall, even without these cuts, have major rows next spring over school meals and also teachers1 salaries;this would add a third (and monumental) row with the students.    The whole educational world, which hithertohas been comparatively quiet, would be simultaneously in uproar.    I am prepared to face the rows, but would prefer to space them out a bit.(iii)   The proposed cuts are extremely severe on the students.(The Annex gives details).    In a full year they would amount to a cut of   13 million in the present total figure of student support of  100 million - a cut of13 per cent.    Half the proposed cut (in the vacation grant)is a reduction of the order of  25 in the grant of everyBritish student.    The other half comes from an increasein the parental contribution which, on the contrary, notonly the Anderson Committee in I960 but also our ownTaylor Study Group proposed to abolish; to raisecontributions, and so increase the dependence of studentson their parents, would provoke a severe and well-justifiedreaction.    Moreover, following the report of the inter-departmental Working Party on Student Support, I amplanning to introduce major changes in the system from september, 1968, and hope then to be able to offer the firm prospect of substantial long-term savings.    Theoutcry caused by cuts now wmld make these long-termsavings almost impossible to achieve,C. A. R. C,Department of Education and Science, W. 1,11th November, 1966-2-
ANNEXReducations in the Value of Student AwardsThe amounts by which the value of awards would be reducedunder the two proposals in paragraph 25 of the Report annexed toC(66) 158 vary according to parental income and are shown for atypical student in column (2) of the table below.If the parent of the student wanted to compensate his childfor the reduction, the amount he would have to pay from his grossincome, before deduction of income tax, would be as shown in column (3).Parental Income Reduction   in Value Equivalent of (2)(  p. a, ) of Award in Taxable Income( . p. a. ) ( . p. a. )(1) (2) (3)Under 85025 251,000                             25 322,000                             48 693,000                              73 1064,000                             98 1545,000                             25 39-3-


</content>
</cab>
