<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/185/3 images: 16-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JESTY&apos;S government(75) 103 Q,COPY NO     0 i7 October 1975CABINETTHE LAW ON PICKETINGMemorandum by the Lord ChancellorPICKETING1. While I appreciate the political considerations which haveprompted them, the Secretary of State for Employments proposals for legislation on picketing in C(75) 101 are, in my opinion, open to serious objections.    I share the Home Secretary&apos;s view (C(75) 102) that it wouldbe a mistake to introduce them into the House of Lords at the present stage of the Employment Protection Bill, when they would almost certainly be defeated.2. Paragraphs 4 and 5 of C(75) 101 paint, I fear, too optimistic a picture of the way in which these proposals would work in practice.    Toreintroduce the old Clause 99, omitting the reference to obstruction of the highway, would, in my opinion, inevitably cause confusion since theclause would be differently interpreted by the police and the pickets.The likely effect would be to worsen relations between them, to antagonisea wide range of public opinion and to increase the risk of personal injury to the pickets themselves.3.        I am convinced that the best way to enable peaceful but effectivepicketing td take place within the law is to continue the dialogue betweenthe police and the Trades Union Congress TUC) which we initiated beforethe General Election of February 1974.    That there was so little troubleduring the miners&apos; strike at that time was, I believe, largely due to theco-operation achieved in that way.conspiracy4. It would also be a mistake, in my opinion, to introduce a small but contentious proposal to amend the law of conspiracy in advance of theLaw Commission^ general proposals on this subject.    In the context ofthe Employment Protection Bill this clause would inevitably seem to be related only to the Shrewsbury case and would for that reason receive a hostile reception.    The same proposal, considered against the widerbackground of a Law Commission Report, would on the other hand have agood chance of being accepted.     But if it were introduced, and defeated,now its proepect of success at a later stage would be much diminished.1
conclusion. I would add that tactical considerations also tell strongly againstthe Secretary of State&apos;s proposals.    The over-spill period is going to bea difficult one in the Lords, with the remaining stages of the EmploymentProtection Bill and the Community Land Bill to be negotiated in additionto the outstanding problems connected with the Trade Union and labour relations and Clay Cross Bills.    To pursue these proposals on picketingand conspiracy would, in my judgment, adversely affect relations withthe Opposition and increase our difficulties in getting the essentiallegislation through.    These considerations outweigh to my mind any possible credit which we might gain with the TUC for having triedunsuccessfully to meet their wishes.E-JHouse of Lords6 October 19752


</content>
</cab>
