<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 90-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN REPORT No.  XXXI.The Independent Labour Party&apos;s Pro-Turk Manifesto.ATTENTION is specially called to the pe&amp;ce programme of the I.L.P. urging the integrity of the Turkish Empire. Nothing is said against the German &quot; financial and commercial exploitation,&quot; which is not &quot; new.&quot; Apparently the I.L.P. have no objection to Berlin-Baghdad, Berlin-Mecca, or Berlin-Cairo. Even more extraordinary is the assertion that the disruption of the Young Turk Empire [i.e., the freeing of Arabs, Armenians, and Zionist Jews from Turanian yoke) &quot; would do injustice to the Moslem population.&quot; This is truly an amazing statement, such as we might expect from Mr. Marmaduke Pickthall and similar anti-Semitic pro-Turks. The I.L.P. are evidently ignorant of the Arab movement and of King Hussein&apos;s proclamations.The Labour party show more sympathy with the ideals of freedom and self-determination and a more just appraisement of the recent characteristics of Young Turk misrule.The Independent Labour party profess to accept the principle of &quot; the liberation of people held by conquest against their will under the domination of an alien power, and the submission to them of the opportunity to decide their own future government.&quot; But this is not to apply to Armenians, Arabs, or Jews.Southern Arabia.Attention is specially called to paragraphs 3 and 4 of the note by the political department of the India Office on the political situation in the Aden Hinterland.In regard to the telegram from Sir Reginald Wingate concerning Said MustafiVs version of the present proposals of Said Idrisi, it is well to remember that the latter is the head of a parvenu dynasty when compared with the prestige of the Hasbimites of Sana&apos;a. He has never hitherto contemplated making himself master of anything but the Tihamah or low-lying coastal belt of Yemen and Asir. The more populous and productive highlands will sooner or later rally to an Imam of the Zeidi sect rather than to the leader of the Idrisi sect. Nevertheless, the present Idrisi has shown himself a capable organiser of government in his hitherto limited sphere of action. He is fighting for his own hand and would be ready to turn to other anti-Turk Powers should we fail to support him, and, within his limitations, he is a power whom we cannot ignore. Any idea of a satisfactory compromise between him and the present holder of the Imamate is probably out of the question. *Russia.The telegrams regarding the crisis arising out of the Soviets&apos; unwillingness to allow Korniloff the necessary powers to enforce discipline throughout the Russian armies do[898-58]
not throw much further light upon the situation. The press reports of the proceedings of the Moscow Conference have been full and have revealed the singular difficulty of M. Kerensky&apos;s position at this moment.   The Soviets are veering &quot;left.&quot;It is most earnestly hoped that nothing will come of the idea of an exchange of able-bodied prisoners of war befweeu Austria and Russia.The telegram regarding the Petrograd police is significant and important. Unless order can be secured in the capital, when famine - begins to threaten, the result may prove disastrous in the extreme.W. 0.-G.August 29, 1917.
[This Docuriient is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ .Gow.rnment.jTOtaJBSUET.&apos; S*SBW.:iiPrinted for the War Cabinet.&apos; SflCKET.For Reference only.EASTERN   REPORT.No. XXXI.   August 29, 1917. (Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LYIII.)Contents.War Aims in the East.Russia.The Army. -   The Military Situation.Exchange of Prisoners of War.General Korniloff.The Minister of War.Military Supplies.The Cossacks.The Petrograd Police.The Sovyets.The Pope&apos;s Letter,Finland.The General Situation.Roumania.Evacuation.Message from Mr. Lloyd George. General de Oandolle. Arabia. Aden.The Political Situation in the hinterland. Asir.Idrisi. Yemen. The Imam. Persia.v    Internal Conditions.South Persian Rifles. India.Xnshki-Dalbandin Railway.WAR AIMS IN THE EAST.The Independent Labour Party has issued a declaration on war aims which takes the form of a note on the declaration of the Executive of the Labour Party, which was published on the 11th August. In regard to the problems of the Turkish Empire the latter said : &quot; The Conference realises that the whole civilised world condemns the handing back to the universally execrated rule of the Turkish Government any subject people which has once been freed from it. Thus, whatever may be proposed with regard to Armenia, Mesopotamia, and Arabia, they cannot be restored to the tyranny of the Sultan and his pashas. The Conference disclaims any sympathy with the imperialist aims of Governments and capitalists, who would make of these and other territories now dominated by the Turkish hordes merely instruments either of exploitation or militarism. If in these territories it is impracticable to leave it to the peoples to settle their own destinies, the Conference suggests that they should be dealfwith in the same way as the colonies of tropical Africa, and placed for administration in the hands of a commission, acting under the supernational authority or league of nations. The Conference further suggests that the peace of the world requires that Constantinople should be made a free port, permanently neutralised and placed (together with both shores of the Dardanelles and possibly some or all of Asia Minor) under the same impartial administration.&quot;The note of the Independent Labour Party on this was: &quot; We agree with the suggestion as. to internationalisation of Constantinople and ft   ; the Straits, but in regard to the proposals for the disruption and practicallythe abolition of the Turkish Empire in Europe and Asia, we would utter a [898-58] * B
warning as to the clanger of allowing a natural abhorrence of the misdeeds of the Turkish Government to lead us into a policy which would create new international problems of the gravest character, and would do injustice to the Moslem population. We would strongly oppose any attempt by the allied or central Powers to establish new spheres of sovereignty in Armenia, Mesopotamia, ancl Arabia for financial and commercial exploitation.&quot;EUSSIA.The Army. On the 22nd August Sir G. Buchanan transmitted a telegram&quot; [No. 1309] from the acting military attache, who said that the Chief of the General Staff had told him that no measures had as yet been introduced for restoring the disciplinary powers of officers, or for inflicting the death penalty in the rear. The Government commissar at General Headquarters and the Minister for War were pressing for the introduction of the death penalty in the rear, but M. Kerensky was frightened by the Soviet, though he recognised the necessity of the measure.On the following day Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed [No. 1314] that M. Tevestchenko had told him that the morale of the troops had improved on the southern and south-west fronts. Telegraphing again on the 24th August [No. 13^6], the acting military attache said that he had asked the Chief of the Staff of the Petrograd military district whether anything was being done to stop the troops in the garrison being got at by agitators, and had been told that the number of desertions was gradually diminishing in consequence of the arrest, daily, of some hundreds of undesirables of all sorts.The Military Situation. In the telegram sent by the acting military attache on the 22nd August [No. 1309], he said that the Chief of the General Staff considered the situation on the north front to be very serious; he was sure that Biga would be attacked, but he did not think that the Germans could advance on Petrograd on account of the lateness of the season. vExchange of Prisoners of War. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir G. Buchanan on the 28th August [No. 1800] in regard to the proposal that an agreement should be concluded between Russia and Austria for the exchange of able-bodied prisoners of war. The matter, Mr. Balfour said, was serious, and Sir G. Buchanan should make every effort to dissuade the Russian Government from concluding such an agreement.General Korniloff. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 23rd August [No. 1314] that he had heard that the Government was divided as to the necessity of properly supporting General Korniloff, against whom an agitation had been steadily growing.Telegraphing on the 25th August [No. 1333], the acting military attache said that General Korniloff, though in complete accord with M. Savinkoff, had not resigned with him, as he was apparently determined to push his policy through. His policy was to restore proper military discipline in spite of all opposition, and to unite front and rear under the commander-in-chief in the held. He wished, too, eventually to get rid of the committees and the Government commissars. The military attache had been informed that he relied for support not only on the Cossacks, but on the Moscow Conference.The Minister of War. Sir G. Buchanan on the 25th August transmitted a telegram [No. 1333] from the acting military attache in regard to the resignation of M. Savinkofr. He said that he had been informed that the question of the death penalty in the rear was the cause of his resignation : he was in complete accord with the commander-in-chief. His place had been taken temporarily by the Assistant Minister, General Yaku(? to)vitch.Military Supplies.---Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 24th August [No. 1325] that M. Terest-chenko had informed him that M. Kerensky had been very much pleased by Mr. Balfour&apos;s message of the 16th August [Eastern Report XXX, p. 3], and wished him (Sir G. Buchanan) to express his grateful thanks for the promised despatch of guns.The Cossacks. General Barter telegraphed on the 21st August that the greatest importance was attached to a declaration which had been published by the Committee of Cossacks to the following effect: (1) That General Korniloii&apos; was, in the opinion ot the majority of the people, the only general capable of restoring efficiency in the army, and lie could not be replaced by anyone else.   The Council of the Union of Cossacks
was entirely opposed to the opinions expressed by the Soviet organs condemning the measures proposed by the general for the restoration of discipline. (2) The Council, as the representative of all the Cossacks in Russia, declared that should General Korniloff be superseded, it would no longer be incumbent on the Cossacks to make further sacrifices for the country ; and the Council made known to the Government and the people that, in that event, it would decline all further responsibility in regard to the attitude of the Cossack troops at the front. (3.) The Council expressed its full and &quot;devoted subordination to its hero chief, General Korniloff.General Barter said that he had been informed that a similar declaration had been made at Petrograd by the Council of the Knights of St. George, which, though not of the same importance as the Cossack Council, represented the opinion of a large section of the best elements in the army.The Petrograd Police. In his telegram of the 24th August [No. 1326] the acting military attache said that the chief of the staff of the Petrograd district had told him that a force of police was the pressing need in Petrograd ; the present militia was absolutely useless. Unless something was done, he said, to organise the police force it would be impossible to maintain order during the winter.The Soviets. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 23rd August [No. 1314] that the Soviets seemed to have lost much of their authority, though the)7 were still strong enough to block almost any drastic measures.   They were veering to the Left.The Pope&apos;s Letter. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 24th August [No. 1324] that M. Terestchenko had told him that he regarded the Pope&apos;s effort as one to bring about peace at the expense of Russia ; and provided Russia&apos;s allies were prepared to adopt this standpoint, he thought the reply to the letter should take the form of a collective note.Finland.The General Situation. The acting military attache at Petrograd telegraphed [No. 1309] on the 22nd August that, though it was very serious, he thought that, provided the Germans did not attempt a landing in Finland, the Government could deal with the situation. The chief of the staff thought that Finland would not be secure from such a landing for another month.On the following day Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed [No. 1314] that the situation was critical and there was no Finnish Government. The Prussian Government had decided to dissolve the Diet, by force if necessary, if it should meet on the 29th August, as it had resolved to do. Votes in favour of supporting the Government in this had been passed by the local Russian garrison, but no reliance could be placed in either the garrison or the fleet.ROUMANIA.Evacuation. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 21st August [No. 1299] that whilst the Roumanian Minister in Petrograci was quite satisfied with the arrangements proposed for evacuation into Russia, he said that it was no good hiding the fact that he was much disturbed by the propaganda among the Roumanian troops and workmen, which was encouraged by Russians on the spot. The Roumanian Minister considered it essential that in the event of the army being evacuated, its victualling and equipment should be guaranteed by the other four great Powers in some public manner; otherwise he feared that the discouragement would be so great that the army would be lost to the allies as a fighting power. Sir G. Buchanan added that the Minister was thoroughly loyal and a man of sound judgment.He telegraphed on the 24th August [No. 1329] that the Roumanian Minister had spoken to him again on this question, saying that unless some such moral and material guarantee were given the troops might refuse to leave Roumania, so profound was the distrust of Russia. Sir G. Buchanan thought that the representatives of the allies at Jassy might give some such collective assurance without offending the Russian Government.Message from Mr. Lloyd George. On the 26th August Mr. Lloyd George sent the following message to the Prime Minister of Roumania : CD OOn the anniversary of Roumania&apos;s entry into the war, I wish to express on behalf of the British Government our heartfelt admiration for the heroic courage and endurance[898-58] B 2
displayed by the Roumanian people during a yeai- &apos;6f UlmoWt hnp^r^feled trial. In declaring against the central Powers, HoUihahia . took, her stand for the cause Of freedom against autocracy and of &quot;right against might.&quot; This cause can never fail, how-ever long delayed its triumph may seem. The re-creation of their army and the stubborn and invaluable resistance which it is now making against the enemy under ( conditions of exceptional difficulty is a magnificent example of the strength which freedohi inspires in a free people. , It is not less a proof of the resolution which animates^ -all the allied armies to prosecute the war until victory is won, a victory which I have never doubted tfiey will ultimately achieve.General te &apos;Gandolle.-:M.r&apos;. Balfour telegraphed to Sir G. Barclay 6&apos;h the 27th August [No. 323] that, by the wish of the C.I.G.S., General de Candolle was to leave hie mission m roumania,. under. Colonel Jack, and proceed to Petrograd early in September. At P,petrograd fhe Minister of Ways and Communications would discuss wifb him how best his services could be utilised.ARABIA.Aden.The Political Situation in tlie Hinterlandpolitical department of the India Office issued the following memorandum on the 25 th August :-1. The military history of the Aden Protectorate since the outbreak of war with Turkey may he very briefly related. News reached the Aden authorities on the 12th June, 1915, that Turkish forces were being concentrated at Ma via, which lies just beyond the border of our protectorate, with a view to advancing, via Ad-dareja, upon Lahej, the headquarters of the principal British protected, chief of the Hinterland (the Abdali Sultan), and situated only about 20 miles from Aden as the crow flies. On the 3rd July news was received that Lahej was actually threatened by the Turks, who had routed the Sultan&apos;s levies, and the military authorities at Aden decided to send up the local movable column for the protection of the town. The force reached Lahej but was unable to -maintain its position there in the face of superior enemy strength, and was compelled to retire upon Aden and to leave Lahej to its fate. Two 1.0.-pounder guns, several machine guns, and a considerable amount of ammu nit-ion and equipment were abandoned during the retreat. The Turks followed up their success, and the British troops found it necessary to retire behin-! the defences of Aden itself, leaving Sheikh Othman whence Aden obtains its water supply-in the enemy&apos;s hands. General Younghusband was promptly despatched to Aden with reinforcements, and had little difficulty in driving the Turks out of Sheikh Othman and regaining control over the water supply; but he made no attempt -nor has any attempt since been made to advance upon Lahej or to clear our protectorate of the enemy..2. The situation in which we have had to acquiesce during the past two years is anything but a satisfact. &apos;ty one. Indeed one of the main reasons which prompted the India Office in suggesting the transference of military control was the hope that it might lead to more effective measures. It is true that our position at Aden itself has never been seriously threatened ; but we have had the humiliation of looking idly on, month after month, at the occupation of our territory by the enemy, and of presenting to the world a spectacle of inability to help either ourselves or our friends. There may have been excellent reasons for this inactivity. But, locally, its political results have been deplorable ; and there is little hope that the political situation will improve until we are in a position to take effective military action. So far we have confined ourselves to attempting to induce the local Arabs (Saiyid Idrisi, &amp;&apos;c.) to do for us what wre-&apos;have not found it convenient to do for ourselvcs-a -policy which, naturally, has not been very fruitful in results. The Arabs have little love for the Turk, but so long as they are doubtful how far we really mean business they will hesitate to commit themselves irretrievably. They are moreover torn by internal rivalries and dissensions. Little effective help can be expected from them until we &quot;take the. field ourselves. It seems indeed hardly reasonable to expect them to declare themselves effectively against the Turks and on our side while we to all appearances are too weak to do anything substantial ourselves.
3. There is one point on which it is desired to lay great emphasis. It is all-important, from the point of view of our future relations with the Arabs, that we should, before the war ends, ourselves expel the Turks by force of arms from Lahej and the remainder of our protectorate. Victory elsewhere, followed by a diplomatic withdrawal on the part of the Turks, will not suffice for local purposes, and will not serve to re-establish our prestige or the belief . in our ability to protect our own interests and those of our friends.   TheArab, as has frequently been remarked, is impressed only by what passes before his eyes.4. It should be added that, according to the Indian military authorities, there are only about three, or at least four, months in the year (November to February) suitable, for climatic reasons, for military operations in the Aden area.Asm.Idrisi. Sir R. Wingate telegraphed on the 23rd August [No. 890] that Said Mustafa had given information&apos; to the effect that most of the chiefs of the Hashid Bakil were negotiating with Idrisi, a number of their prominent men being present with him. Tribesmen were arriving daily at Jaizan, 1,500 being already collected there. Nasir Mabkhut was on his w&amp;y. ,Sir R. Wingate went on to say that Idrisi proposed to raise a force of 10,000 men, and already had 3,000 tribesmen beyond his own Asir levies. He proposed to use half in watching the passes through the hills, and half in clearing the Tihamah of the Turks ; and directly he received the necessary food and money he would be prepared to act. It was evident, he said, that an anti-Turkish feeling existed in Yemen, and under present circumstances the best way to stimulate it seemed to be by means of Idrisi, though this involved the risk that his success, if pushed too far, might alarm all parties in Yemen. Major Reilly was about to proceed to Jaizan to study the local situation, and Sir R.-Wingate recommended that Major Reilly should be authorised to communicate the formula in his telegram of the 9th August [Eastern Report, XXVIII, p. 7]. If Idrisi should satisfy Major Reilly that ho realiy accepted, and would practise this and employ his levie? solely against raiders, Sir R. Wingate recommended that he should be offered such foodstuffs as might be required, together with the sum of 25,000Z.Yemen.The Imam. Sir R. Wingate telegraphed on the 27th August [No. 902] that a reply was being sent to the Imam by the Resident at Aden in the sense of the recom-mendations of the Government of India, amplified on the lines of the formula in his telegram of the 9th August. The Resident would add that any further hesitation would imply enmity to the cause of Arabian independence, the success of which depended on the suppression of territorial disputes and personal animosities till after the war.PERSIA.Internal Conditions. Sir G. Marling telegraphed on the 23rd August [No. 285] that it appeared that the taking of any further steps against the terrorists had been prevented by the democrat section of the Cabinet ; virulent attacks were published against us daily in the press, and the chief of police was accused of having exceeded his powers, the Government taking no steps to publicly approve his action. Teheran was filled with rumours of revolution and the worst characters in Persian politics were returning there. It was certain that nothing would be clone so long as the Cabinet remained constituted as at present. Sir C. Marling had warned the Prime Minister that he was inviting anarchy by not reconstructing his Cabinet in such a way as to allow energetic steps being taken against the terrorists and the press, but he feared that the warning would be useless, as the Prime Minister was quite senile and the other moderate ministers timid and weak. He (Sir C. Marling) thought that a complete change of Cabinet would be the best thing, and the Russian Minister agreed with him.South Persian Rifles. Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 23rd August [No. 28b&quot;] that he had informed the Prime Minister that His Majesty&apos;s Government wished to know what length of time must elapse before the projects contained in the Persian note [Eastern Report, XXVII, p. 8 ; XXX, p. 6] could be realised, and further the proposals of the Persian Government in regard to the South Persian Rifles.   Sir C. Marling
added that he had told the Prime Minister that this did not mean that those projects, had been accepted in principle by His Majesty&apos;s Government.   Mr. Balfour telegraphed^ on 27th August approving his language.INDIA.Nushki-Dalbandin Railway. Mr. Montagu telegraphed to the Viceroy on th^ 22nd August approving the extension of this railway to the Persian frontier, on the understanding that the extension would not interfere with any foreseeable railway requirements for the active theatres of war.PBIHTED AT THE TOKEIGK OFFICB BT C. K. HABBISOK 31/8/1S17.

</content>
</cab>
