<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 407-413</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret.Zionist Movement.THE meeting at the London Opera House should be noted as an event of political importance. The actual speeches made are of little consequence. What counts in this natter is that the Zionist movement has now taken a definite turn and enters into the ealm of world politics. That is to say that the world force of Jewry has been suddenly ttuned to one key, and that a movement of idealism has started on a course the lersistence, duration, and influence of which will be far-reaching. A new factor has aken its place in world politics which will make itself felt in the political, military, and international events winch henceforth take place.Russia.The Russian situation has in the last week developed somewhat on the lines indicated in the Appreciation of the last Report. It is evident that the Germans are in omething of a quandary in discussing terms with Anarchists who are avowedly out for le overthrow of all. organised government. They are also confronted with the unpleasant problem of having to part with their millions of docile, hard-working Russian irisoners, who are all engaged in war work, in return for masses of war-weary, revolution-infected Austrians of various races, ancl, in addition, risking disorganising their industry and railway machinery in the process. The Bolsheviks pass from folly and villainy to villainy and folly ; the murder of General Dukhonin, the appeal to Indian Moslems to rise, and the announcement that if the constituent assembly does not fall in with their views it will be suppressed all go to show that we are dealing with a band of persons who are not going to be bound by any very close adherence to the obvious meaning of the words proletariat, democracy, or humanity.As against this, the report of the pro-British demonstration in Odessa, the escape of General Korniloff, ancl the election returns go to show that the Bolsheviks are not by any means all-powerful.Persia.Attention is drawn to the suggestion of Sir C. Marling.Appendix.The article reproduced from the &quot; Cologne Gazette&quot; is interesting. It shows that the German expansionists are beginning to take a rather gloomy view of the Eastern situation and do not seem able to revise their vocabulary in accordance with the spirit of the age.M. S,December 7, 1917.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN REPORT No. XLV.
Sir ul HanKey.USMs Bscraneat is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]EASTERN REPORT.No. XLV.   December 6, 1917.64(Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LXXII.)Contents.The Zionist Movement.*Russia.Statement made by the British Ambassador. Note from M. Troteky. . Refusal to allow British Subjects to leave Russia.Murder of General Dukhonin.Trans-Caucasia :Formation of a Provisional Government. Deputation to British Minister at Teheran.* See Latest Intelligence.Poland.Poles in the Russian Army.The Senussi. Said Idrisi.Abyssinia.Expulsion of Germans.Persia.Cossack Division.THE  ZIONIST  MOVEMENT.A Jewish demonstration was held on Sunday, the 2nd December, at the London Opera House, Kingsway, to thank the British Government for their declaration in favour of the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people. It was announced that messages of sympathy and approval had been received from Lord Grey of Fallodon, Lord Hugh Cecil, Lord Emmott, Lord Tennyson, Lord Crewe, Mr. John Redmond. Mr. Arthur Henderson, Lord Selborne, Lord Balfour, Mr. Hodge,. Mr. Long, the president of the Roumanian National Delegation, and from New York. Petrograd, Canada, South Africa, Holland, Christiania, Salonica, Switzerland, and Belgium. Lord Rothschild presided, and the meeting was addressed by him, Lord Robert Cecil, M.P., Mr. Herbert Samuel, M.P., Colonel Sir Mark Sykes, Bart., M.P., Dr. Hertz (Chief Rabbi), Dr. Gaster (founder of the Zionist movement), Shaykh Ismail Abdul-al-akki (who, it was stated, has been sentenced to death by the Turkish Govern-ment for having joined the Arab national movement), Mr. Israel Zangwill (president of the Jewish Territorial Organisation), M. Yussnf Sakagan (a Syrian Christian), Mr. IT. U. Mostditchian (member of the Armenian National Delegation), M. Nahum Sokolow (leader of the Zionist forces in the West during the war), Captain the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore,. M.P., and Dr. Weizmann (president of the English Zionist Federation), and the following resolution was agreed to by acclamation  &quot;That this mass meeting, representing all sections of the Jewish community in the United Kingdom, conveys to His Majesty&apos;s Government an expression of heartfelt gratitude for their declaration in favour of the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people. It assures His Majesty&apos;s Government that their historic action in support of the national aspirations of the Jewish people has evoked among Jews the most profound sentiments of joy. This meeting further pledges its utmost endeavours to give its whole-hearted support to the. Zionist cause.&quot;[898-72]Bq Printed for the War Cabinet.&apos;&apos;i   SECRET. For Reference onlt.
RUSSIA.. - .....- ........-......-......-...... - -Statement made by the British Ambassador. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 29th November [No. 1902] that, in view of the manner in which our attitude in regard to the armistice was being misrepresented, and of the attacks being made on himself by M. Trotzky for not replying to ins note, he had thought it advisable to publish the following statement: So man)&apos; reports have been circulated regarding the attitude of the allied embassies that, while awaiting the final instructions of his Government, the British ambassador desires to make the following statement : In the interview accorded to Reuter&apos;s correspondent Lord R. Cecil is reported to have said that His Majesty&apos;s Government could not recognise the present Russian Government, and the ambassador has further been instructed to abstain from any action that could be taken as implying recognition. The note addressed to him by M. Trotzky proposing a general armistice was delivered at the embassy nineteen hours after the commander-in-chief at headquarters had received orders to open immediate pourparlers with the enemy for an armistice. The allies were thus confronted with an accomplished fact, on which they had not been consulted. Though M. Trotzky said that the notes had been telegraphed to London, it is impossible for the ambassador to reply to notes addressed to him by a Government which his own Government has not recognised. Governments, moreover, which, like His Majesty&apos;s Government, derive their powers direct from the people cannoo take a decision on a matter of such supreme importance without first assuring themselves that that decision will meet with the approval and sanction of the people.   They cannot therefore return an answer offhand.On the 1st December lie telegraphed [No. 1 925] that the following reply to this statement had appeared that day in the official organ of the Council of People&apos;s Commissioners : With reference to the British Embassy&apos;s communique, we, on the basis of information given us at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, consider it necessary to make the following statementAn open proposal to both allied and enemy peoples was made by the second All-Russian Congress of &quot;Workmen and Soldiers&apos; Deputies on the 26th October (8th November). Thus three days previous to the despatch of the note of the Minister of Foreign Affairs the allied Governments and embassies were fully and accurately informed of the proposed steps of the Council. It should be clear, therefore, that the Minister could have had no interest whatever in acquainting the German authorities before the allied embassies.The note addressed to the allies and the radio-telegraphic order to General Dukhonin were drawn up and despatched simultaneously. If (it is) true that the embassies received the note later than General Dukhonin it was due entirely aud exclusively to secondary causes of a technical character having no connection whatever with the policy of the Council.No doubt, however, the Council was not guided by or dependent on the assent or -dissent of the allied Governments in making their appeal- to the German military authorities. In this sense the policy of the Council is absolutely clear. The Council does not consider itself bound to the formal obligations of the old Governments, and in its struggle for peace is guided solely by the principles of democracy and the interests of the proletariat of the whole world. And precisely for this reason the Council is seeking to obtain a universal and not a separate peace. The Council with the vigorous efforts of the people against imperialist Governments [words omitted], universal peace will be&apos; secured.Note jrom M. Trotzky. Sir G. Buchanan on the 29th November telegraphed [No. 1906] the following translation of a note, dated the 29th November, received from M. Trotzky :-To the notice of the diplomatic representatives of the allied Powers in Russia.In reply to the formal proposal of the Council of Peoples Commissaries to open negotiations for an immediate truce on all fronts with a view to concluding a democratic peace, without annexations or indemnities, witii the right of every nation to decide its own destiny .... has answered by assent. All documents and definite communications i-e;adngto the above have been published by me tin the &quot; News Central Executive Committee.&quot;
Military operations on the Russian front have ceased ; preliminary discussions will be begun on the 2nd December, new style. The Council of People&apos;s Commissaries now, as always, considers it indispensable that all the allies should-begin discussions simultaneously with a view to bringing about as soon as possible a truce on all fronts, and assuring a general democratic peace.The allied Governments and their diplomatic representatives in Russia will be pleased to answer whether they are prepared to take part in the discussions opening on the 2nd December at 5 o&apos;clock in the afternoon.Refusal to alloiv British Subjects to leave Russia.  Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 29th November [No. 1898] that M. Trotzki had decided that unless Chichirin and Impliroff [Eastern Report XLIV, 5] were released no British subjects should be allowed to leave Russia, and further, that certain of them should be interned in camps with German prisoners. More than this, M. Trotzki said that if Chichirin and Impliroff were not let out he would not answer for the consequences, as feeling ran high among the soldiers, though, he remar-ked, so far there had been no demonstration against the British Embassy. He added that he wished to appoint Chichirin (or Tchicherine) one of his foreign representatives.Telegraphing again on the same day [No. 1908] he said that he had learnt from a neutral friend that M. Trotzki had told a Frenchman, who had relations with him, that he might have to go so far as to arrest him (Sir G. Buchanan) on the ground that he had been in touch with General Kaledin. and the Committee of Public Safety and had supplied them with funds ; and further, that he should keep a certain number of the allied subjects in Russia as hostages in the event of a complete rupture with the Government. Sir G. Buchanan, however, thought that, unless urged to do so by Germany, M. Trotzki would be unlikely to carry out the threat in regard to himself.Telegraphing again on the 30th November [No. 1910] he said that an official notice-had appeared in the papers intimating that, till the question of the two interned Russians had been satisfactorily settled, no British subjects would be allowed to go. And on the 1st December he telegraphed [No. 1927] that on the previous evening M. Trotzki had announced at a meeting of the Petrograd Soviet that he should send to internment camps those British subjects conducting war propaganda who were in sympathy with the counter-revolutionary movement. The time, he said, had come for everyone to understand that every Russian was under the direct protection of the revolutionary authorities ; a statement which was loudly applauded.Murder of General Duhhonin. Ensign Krylenko, the Bolshevik commander-in-chief, after capturing the headquarters staff issued a manifesto containing a reference to the murder of General Dukhonin.   The manifesto was as follows : To the Press.In the name of the x-evolution ; to all soldiers of the revolutionary army and navy r Comrades !  To-day I entered into Mohilefl at the head of revolutionary troops. the headquarters were entirely surrounded, without fighting.   The last obstacle to the causeof peace has fallen.I cannot be silent on the sad act of lynch law practised upon former highest commander-in-chief Dukhoniu. Popular hatred surpassed the limits of reason. In spite of all attempts to save him, he was thrown out of the railway train at Mohileff station, and killed. The flight of General Korniloff the day before the fall of the head-quarters was the ca se of this excess.Comrades ! I cannot allow the banner of the revolution to be stained, and it is necessary to condemn strongly such acts. Be worthy of the secured freedom ! Do not stain the people&apos;s authority ! The revolutionary people are fearful in struggle, but must be soft after victory.Comrades ! Following the fall of the headquarters, the struggle for peace receives a new strength. In the name of the revolution and of freedom, I call on you for revolutionary unity and for revolutionary discipline.Long live the authority of the Council of Workmen, Soldiers, and Peasants&apos; Deputies.(Signed) Kbyl,enko, Highest C commander-in-Chief.Trans-Caucasia .Formation of a Provisional Government. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 30th November [No. 1916] that the consul at Tiflis had reported that it had been[898-72] B 2
4-4 Jalmost unanimously,resolved, at.a meeting of all.parties and. factions, to form a. pmv-isi.on.al democratic Government in Trans-Caucasia in consequence of the anarchy $ sivihwar, and want of proper authority and.services..in Russia. When the members of the constituent assembly shall have been elected, they are to take over the Government until a responsible democratic Government shall have been established in Russia; in the meanwhile (before, that is, the election), the Government is to consist of a repre-sentative from each of the various committees.Deputation to British Minister in Teheran. Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 30th November [No. 413] news of the arrival of a deputation from the Caucasus to represent that that country could be secured as a stronghold against Maximalist influences if money were forthcoming, but if it were not then the Caucasian troops (which the members of the deputation asserted to lie the best disciplined and most loyal) would probably leave the front, and might be followed by General Baratov&apos;s forces, which would leave open the whole range of the Persian and Caucasian fronts. The deputation &quot;wished to ascertain whether the requisite credits would be provided in London by the British Government, and whether the Imperial Bank of Persia could facilitate the speedy conversion of part of such credits into rouble currency; in regard to the latter point Sir C. Marling added that he had been informed that, the bank could not do much, but it thought that such credits could be negotiated locally by the Caucasian authorities. J&quot;^hPOLAND.Poles in the Russian Army. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 25th November [No. 1886] that the Poles were anxious to summon all their fellow-countrymen serving in the Russian army to join together to carry on hostilities irrespective of the attitude assumed by the Russian army at the instigation of the Bolsheviks. His Roumanian colleague had suggested the possibility of Poles, Ukrainians, and Roumaiuans working together; Sir G. Buchanans own opinion was that the Ukraine was as desirous of peace as northern Russia, but still be said it might be advisable to sound the Rada. So far as the Poles were concerned, the suggested combined action would necessitate a preliminary grant of, say, l,250,O00LTHE  SENUSSI.Said Idrisi.-Sir R. Wingate telegraphed on the 3rd December j No. 1301] saying that Said Idrisi (according to the report of Major Royle, who had returned on the 2nd) was very much pleased on hearing of the promised Italian assistance. He was in difficulties, in regard to his food supply, and asked that the Italians should make a more liberal one with regularity. The growing hostility ancl power of the Turkish faction in the west aj)appeared to make him genuinely apprehensive. There had been reason to believe in the existence of serious difficulties between. Said Ahmed and the Turkish faction ; on the 8th November Idrisi sent him an ultimatum demanding that, if he would not join him (Idrisi) he should remove himself to either Jalu or Kufra with not more than 400 followers. A strong attack was expected to be made on Jedabia by Ramazan-el-Sawahili, and Idris was concentrating his forces at that place. idrisis treaties with Christians had injured his religious prestige, and he would find it impossible to maintain his position. Major Royle had received the impression that for the over-coming of hostile native elements Idrisi relied on British and Italian support ancl money.ABYSSINIA.Expulsion of Germans [see Eastern Beport XXVIII, 7 ; XL, 5]. Mr. Balfour telegraphed on the 1st December to Mr. Thesiger [No. 74] saying that the acceptance of the Abyssinian conditions, excluding 2 and 4, had now been agreed upon by the British, Italian, and French Governments, and he should join with his colleagues in informing the Abyssinian Government to that effect, unless he should prefer to defer the communication until the settlement of the question of allowing Taffari to import rifles as he (Mr. Thesiger) had suggested; efforts were being made to induce the Italian Government to agree to this.PERSIA.Cossacks Division.   Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 30th November [No. 414] urging that it would be politic to finance the Persian Cossacks division, which, was cut off from monetary supplies on account of its dependence On Tiflis. In the not improh-able event, he said, of the Russian anarchy spreading to Northern Persia, the knowledge that they were to be regularly paid would.tend to steady the men.
LATEST  INTELLIGENCE.RUSSIA..Zionists. The special correspondent of the Daily Telegraph at Petrograd, tele-graphing on the 5th December, said : The Zionists now are the strongest party among the Russian Jews, and they are overjoyed at the British promise of Palestine. At Odessa last Friday there was a huge Zionist demonstration, with a procession, twenty blocks long. Mr. Grusenberg, the newly-elected member for Odessa, made a speech of triumph and gratitude, to which the British consul, Mr. Pictoa Bagge, replied. Towards the close of the demonstration members of the Bund, or Jewish Socialist party, began - agitating against the Zionists and England.   There was a scuffle, and a shot was fired, but no harm clone.FINLAND.Finland a Republic. &apos;Mr. Grove telegraphed from Helsingfors on the 4th December 1917, that he had learnt that Germans and Swedes were urging the immediate recognition of FinlancVs independence by the German Government. He had been asked by the President of the Finnish Senate (who had that d&amp;y read a declaration in the Diet proposing Finland as a free independent republic) to ascertain wdiether the British Government would recognise Finland as an independent State.APPENDIX.The &quot; Kolnische Zeitung &quot; on British A inis.Sir W. Townley transmitted the following summary of an article entitled &quot; The Way to India &quot; in the &quot; Kdlnische Zeitung &quot; of the 24th November :  * The article begins by recapitulating the old arguments as to how the fear of a young, rising, and successful Germany, whose natural desire to stretch its limits would eventually compel it to demand from us freedom of the seas, first made us go to war in order that we might by timely action check her expansion, destroy her fleet, and seize her colonies. The chief motive governing our action in this was the necessity of securing the road to India.Germany&apos;s eastern policy of to-day, says the &quot; Kolnische,&quot; is based upon historical necessity. Its political ambition to hold Bagdad dates back to Charles the Great. It never came to anything because, on the one hand, Germany did not possess the means to force her way there and, on the other hand, because it is only in the last few decades that the necessity has become imperative enough to make it a leading plank in our foreign policy, That our policy in this respect is purely defensive, depending as it does upon friendship of Turkey, and is prompted solely by the need we have of obtaining access to the world&apos;s markets, unhindered by England, a glance at the map will prove. For on the day when Germany succeeds in obtaining an independent outlet upon the Persian Gulf a great step will already have been made towards achieving that equality upon the sea which we demand : England&apos;^ unhampered command of the Indian Ocean would therebj&apos; be menaced. This she would never tolerate ; here, therefore, the life interests of the two empires meet and clash. For Germany must gain independent access to the Persian Gulf if she does not wdsh to see herself cut off from the world&apos;s markets and the feeding of her population to depend upon England&apos;s goodwill; whilst England could not permit our access to it except at the price of diminished sovereignty on the sea, that sovereignty upon which the safety of her island kingdom in the first place depends. England recognised these facts long since : her attitude on the question of war with us was therefore long since fixed.The fact has even been admitted in writing by English authors that almost all England&apos;s Asiatic and most of her A african conquests were made solely in order to erect a glacis round India, the most precious star of the British Empire, in pursuance of this idea England conceived the purpose of acquiring a land route to India ; this
idea not being new, as some suppose, but dating back to shortly after the occupation of Egypt. The special significance of England&apos;s action in Egypt in this war &quot;has already been frequently discussed and heed not therefore be emphasised anew. It suffices to point out once again that its conquest became imperative if England after the opening of the Suez Canal was to remain undisputed master of the sea roufce India.The article then goes on to point out how systematically England has worked out her plan for the acquirement of a land route to India, how the first step was to buy the friendship of the heads of the Moslem world, to incite the Arabs to revolt against the Turks, to start the idea of an Arab caliph, a Turkish one being historically impossible. The second step, of course, was the occupation of Mesopotamia. The third, the military forcing of a passage from Egypt into the Arabian desert. The last step was the acquiring by diplomacy, or other methods, of those parts of Persia through which the land route would eventually pass.How far have the English attained these aims % The first tangible result of the British propaganda in the Arabian world was the exit of the Sherif of Mecca to reappear as King by the grace of England ; the military occupation of Mesopotamia has succeeded in so far as was necessary for English plans; and the well-known Anglo-Russian agreement of 1907 settled the Persian question.Some day we shall arrive at a settlement with Britain in regard to Belgium and the purely European questions between us ; but never shall we reach an agreement with her on a question which in any way touches her colonial possessions, least of all if thereby the connection between India and the mother-country were to be jeopardised. Let innocents wdno still believe the contrary be once more assured that England does not care one jot for her proclaimed principle of nationalities : it has no significance for her once it ceases to serve her interests. If, therefore, we fail to settle the Eastern issue on a basis of military success we shall never compel her to abandon her Mesopo-mesopotamian and Arabian plans even if we get her on her knees. She would stick to these to the bitter end.For us, of course, the German work of decades is at stake in Mesopotamia. The future will show whether Germany was ripe at the time for a policy which involved such expansion, or whether her political evolution failed to keep pace with it. Success in such undertakings attends the country whose masses are convinced of the national necessity for embarking on them. The greater part of the English working classes know what the British colonies mean to them. May the day soon dawn when Germanics foreign policy^ will find itself reposing on an equally solid basis of popular opinion.      J44PRINTED AT THB FOREIGN&quot; OFFICE Br C. R, HARBISON.-8/12/1917

</content>
</cab>
