<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 414-426</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.;.......... v,:   ZZSAPPRECIATION QE THE . ATTACHED EASTERN  REPORT No, X LVl.The Retaking oe Jerusalem.THE surrender of the Holy City is politically speaking the most important military event that has yet been recorded in the Eastern Report. It is, in certain aspects, a decisive action, since, whatever else may happen, unless we are evicted by force from Jerusalem during hostilities, it would appear hardly possible for Jerusalem to be handed back to Turkish control, as the sense.of the whole world would be against such an action.It is worth considering what are the various factors which have to be considered in regard to Jerusalem.The Islamic World.The Dome of the rock, which was the point of prayer to which Mohammed himself turned, before he established Mecca, gives Jerusalem a special sanctity to Moslems of all sects. The various Christian shrines of Calvary, the Holy Sepulchre, and Bethlehem are also regarded by the Moslems with great reverence. The effect of the fall of Jerusalem will therefore be considerable among Moslems as a whole, and have a tendency to produce Anglophil sentiments, and to lessen the malignant power of political Pan-Islamists.Christendom.Jerusalem is so profoundly impressed as a name and an idea on all who have been reared in a Christian environment that it is difficult to calculate what an effect it may have on /the world.The Bible-reading Christians in the English-speaking world will all hail with delight the idea that Bible lands will at last be under a decent and orderly Govern-ment, and our success will have a considerable moral effect in America.The Roman Catholic Church is undoubtedly profoundly moved by the event, and the satisfaction expressed in Vatican circles will be reflected throughout the Church. Indeed, this event puts Austria and South Germany in a somewhat difficult position, since it must be the outward policy of the Central Powers to have to pretend that they desire Turkey to be given Jerusalem on the conclusion of hostilities, a policy which will certainly run counter to the inner feelings of great numbers of Germans and Austrians.The Greek Orthodox Church, especially in Bussia, is very strongly attached to Jerusalem and to the places of pilgrimage. There is a possibility that the news of the taking of Jerusalem may have some effect in Russia, since it is the only place outside their own districts that the peasantry connect with any. historical event. The,--reason for.this is that there must be at this moment close on a million peasants of both sexes who have actually performed the pilgrimage, and another million who at some tiine or another intend to make it....................     Jewry.     . ..;.....So much has been said about Zionism lately that it is unnecessary to expand on the effect of the capture of Jerusalem on world Jewry.    However, it is important to note J898-731
that wherever there are Jews there are Zionists, in theory at least, and that, no matter what views these may have held about the war up till now, henceforth the goal of their ambitions rests in Entente hands.   . , ; , . -The above are the main considerations; lesser, but important, matters are as follows : Effect on Turkey,&quot;The loss of Jerusalem will certainly result in an access of unpopularity to the C.U.P. and the Germans in Turkey. The CUT. itself will be furious at having lost a great asset and a hold over the Zionists, the Germans will know that they have to take the blame for the loss. Anti-Germanism and anti-Enverism will from now on be a growing force in Turkey, and it is well to remember that the loss of Jerusalem will be a constant source of irritation, and will not pass away with a few weeks.Effect on the Arab Movement.It is less satisfactory to consider that our adoption of Zionism and our capture of Jerusalem will tend to a certain extent to somewhat abate. Arab enthusiasm. As matters stand the King of Hejaz will feel that Jerusalem has passed from al Islam Owing perhaps to his co-operation, and that the only definite result lias been a declaration in favour of the Jews. This, however, may only be of transient effect if we take an early opportunity of showing that we are behind the Arabs, appreciate their assistance, and desire their liberation. There is no doubt, however, that this aspect of the situation requires careful consideration and attention, otherwise the enemy will not be slow to profit by the event.General.The steps taken on the occupation of the city of Jerusalem should ensure tranquillity and good feeling.Me. M arm ad uk e Pickthall.Mr. Pickthall has written a letter to the &quot; Saturday Review &quot; (reproduced inl Appendix III) which is in its way a masterpiece of enemy propaganda.   He (a.) Insinuates that our ally King Hussein is a venal traitor. (6.) Does his best to set the Arabs at variance, (c.) Suggests that we have violated the holy territory by introducing police into! Mecca.(d.) Goes in for pure Turcophilism.The editor of the &quot; Saturday Review,&quot; Mr. Bauman, might be informed of thel ill-effects of such letters ; when they reach Egypt and India they are used by ourj enemies for all they are worth.M. S.December 14, 1917, .    .
EASTERLY REPORT. 64No. NLYI.   December 13, 1917. (Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LXXIII.)Contents.&quot;Russia. Palestine.The Armistice Negotiations. Jerusalem.Patriarch of all Russia. The Future from a French Point of View.Finland. Pilgrimages a Suggestion.Declaration of Independence. j    *Persia.Trans-Oaucasia. Proposed Future Policy in regard to Persiti.j    *Zionism.Roumania. I     &quot;Armenia.The Armistice. Appendices.* See Latest Intelligence.RUSSIA.The Armistice Negotiations. On the 6th December Sir G. Buchanan transmitted a telegram from the military attache, who said that the Russian delegation had been met at Brest Litovsk by General Hofman, chief of the staff to Prince Leopold, representing Germany, and by the military representatives of Austria, Bulgaria, and Turkey. The Russians commenced with a declaration on the conditions of peace, but were interrupted by the enemy delegates, who said they were not diplomatists and had nothing to add on this subject to the statements of Kuhlmann and Czernin, and this reply had particularly annoyed M. Trotzki. The Russians then proposed that the enemy Powers should invite all the Powers, not represented at the conference, to take part in its deliberations, and the enemy delegates replied that tbeywere not empowered to do so. The Russians proposed an armistice on all fronts, laying clown as conditions that all transfer of troops from Russia to other fronts should be forbidden, and that the enemy should evacuate the islands of the Mund Sound. The Germans then proposed a twenty-eight days&apos; armistice from the Baltic to the Black Sea, and the Russian delegates were on their way back to Petrograd for further instructions.On the same clay he telegraphed again [No. 1973] that a note had been received from M. Trotzki setting forth the course of armistice negotiations. It confirmed in substance the information given above, but added, that the German, delegates when asked to invite all the allies to participate in negotiations for a general armistice replied that, though they were not themselves empowered to do so, they would submit the proposal to their respective Governments. The note further stated in view of the refusal of the Russian delegates to conclude a formal armistice at the present stage of negotiations, it was agreed to suspend all military operations for the period of one week. The note concluded by pointing out that more than a month will have elapsed between the publication of the first. Russian peace decree, and the resumption, of peace negotiations, a period sufficient to have enabled the allied Governments, even in the present disorganised state of international communications, to have determined their attitude towards the question of peace negotiations.On the following clay Sir G. Buchanan transmitted [No. 1976] a message from the military attache, who said that the next meeting would take place at Brest Litovsk on[898-73] &quot;       , B[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Go-y4ament.]Printed for the War Cabinet. SECRET. For Reference only.
the 12th December. The enemy had refused for &quot; technical reasons&quot; the Russian proposal to meet at Pskov.Meanwhile a preliminary armistice had been arranged from the noon of that day until noon on the 17th December on the front from the Baltic to the Black Sea and on the Russo-Turkish front. In this period only such transfers of troops, of the strength of a division and over, as had been arranged previous to the oth December would be carried out.There was a general feeling that the Germans had postponed the negotiations as they wished to treat for a real armistice after the assembly of the Constituent Assembly.On the 8th December Sir G. Buchanan transmitted [Nos. 1984 and 1985], other messages from the military attache, who said that there were some points of interest in the armistice negotiations. The great idea of the Russian political delegates (who were honestly desirous of forcing a general armistice and not a separate one) was to make use of every opportunity of demoralising the (? wavering army). They fought unsuccessfully for half an hour to induce the enemy to allow fraternisation during the preliminary armistice. They asked if they could send political literature inlo Germany. Hofman said that Germany had enough of her own, and suggested that the Russians should feed France and England. Yoffe replied that they intended to do so. A political member of ^Russian delegation really expected to be joined by the allies before the next meeting. The Germans were evidently afraid of their troops being infected by pacific propaganda. They probably simply wanted the armistice to enable them to transfer troops to other fronts.The Russian proposals for the armistice had been published. The delegates had asked that there should be a six months&apos; armistice which was to apply to all armed forces on all fronts and on the seathat no enemy units should be transferred to other fronts; that the Riga Gulf islands should be evacuated by the Germans but not reoccupied by the Russians ; and that in the event of the breaking off of negotiations military operations should not be renewed for 72 hours. The military attache added that Lenin had made a speech to the representatives of the fleet in which he had said that the Russian army might yet have to fight for socialism and freedom should the German working classes support their Government. He said, too, that in that day&apos;s official press there was a remarkable change in regard to the allies, who were not attacked, the first time for several weeks.On the yth December Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed I No. 1988] that an official proclamation &quot; to the whole nation &quot; had been published by the Council of Beople&apos;s Commissioners, stating that the imperialist and propertied classes, helped by Cossack generals, were making a last desperate attempt to break up peace negotiations, and wrest the newly-won power from the hands of the people. The standard of rebellion had been raised in the Urals, the Don&apos; province, and elsewhere. General Kaledin, joined by General Kornilov, was preventing the despatch of grain to the front and threatening Moscow, Kharkow, and other big towns. In Orenburg General Dutov had arrested the revolutionary authorities, had disarmed soldiers, and was marching ou Cheliabinsk to cut off the grain supplies from Siberia for European Russia. General Karaulof was similarly engaged in the Caucasus. The Central Rada of the Ukraine was assisting Kaledin to concentrate his troops in the Don province, and impeding the despatch of revolutionary troops to suppress the rebellion. The Cadets were acting as political agents and providing the necessary funds. In view of this the Council of Peoples Commissioners appealed-to the people to rally to the defence of their newly-gained liberty ; declared the leaders of the above-meutioned movements to be outlaws; placed all districts where counter-revolutionary troops were located in a state of siege; gave full power to the local authorities to act on their own initiative ; prohibited all communication with counter-revolutionaries under pain of the severest penalties of the law ; and finally offered its full support to all Cossacks remaining loyal to the Bolsheviks&apos; authority.Patriarch of All Russia. Sir G. Buchanan, on the 8th December, transmitted [No. 1979] a telegram from the consul at Moscow saying that after a lapse of 250 years the patriarchate of all Russia had been revived, and the metropolitan of Moscow enthroned as patriarch on the 4th December in the cathedral of the Assumption. The consular body was present.Finland.Declaration of Independence [Eastern Report XLV, p. 5]. Mr. Balfour telegraphed [No. 2452] to Sir G. Buchanan on the 10th December instructing him to inform the
consul at Helsingfors that when the Russian constitutional assembly had sanctioned the independence of Finland, the British Government would be ready to recognise it. The Finnish authorities were to be so informed.Trans-Catjcasja.The Armistice, and the Troops. -Mr. Stevens telegraphed from Tiflis on the 6th December [No. 3 j that the Trans-Caucasian Government had communicated a-note to the consuls of the allied nations informing them that negotiations for an armistice had been begun by the Turks. The note stated that there was a clause providing that belligerents should remain in their present position and that no movements should take place, which would fully safeguard the interests of the British army in Mesopotamia. The consuls had protested against negotiations having been entered into without the knowledge of their Governments.ROUMANIA,The Armistice. Sir W. Townley telegraphed [No. 4156] from The Hague on the 9th December that a Vienna telegram, dated the 7th December, from the military correspondent of the &quot;Grazer Tagespost &quot; said that, thanks to Roumania s decision to join in the Russian demand for a truce, a lull had fallen upon the whole eastern front. The Roumanian Government had been compelled to take this decision by the ultimatum of the Petrograd Government, which threatened, in the event of a refusal, to with-draw all Russian troops from the Moldavia front and to close the frontier against the export of food and war materials.Sir G. Barclay on the 5th December transmitted [No. 738] a telegram from the military attache saying that the King had formally given up the command of the Roumanian army, doubtless to free him from any participation in the armistice.PALESTINE.Jerusalem. The city was surrendered to General Allenby on Saturday, the 8th December.The Future from a French Point of View. Lord Bertie telegraphed [No. 1455] the following on- the 11th December: The &quot; Temps&quot; awaits with the deepest interest the congratulatory message which the Pope will assuredly send to the King on the couquest of Jerusalem. It declares that England is not following a selfish object in Palestine. The Holy Places will be under international authority. The aspirations of,the Israelites will be respected. France applauds these results all the more cordially because she also has an important and disinterested mission in the East. It is impossible that the inhabitants of the Lebanon, Syrian Arabs, or Armenians of Cilicia and the neighbouring regions can remain subject to the Turkish regime, which has starved, persecuted, or massacred them. A western people, loved in and loving the East, must act as their arbiter and educator. That is the part which public opinion desires for France. It is in harmony with the wishes, of the populations and is free from all imperialism.Pilgrimages- A Suggestion. It has been suggested that it would be well to make known to the Russian peasantry that the capture of Jerusalem will make their pilgrimages to the Holy Land easier. If properly worked this would be most useful propaganda, as the revolutionary party will doubtless persuade the ignorant peasants that our taking of Jerusalem will hinder the pilgrimages, for which they save up their kopecks for years.PERSIA.Proposed Future Policii in regard to Persia.-On the 15th November Mr. Balfour telegraphed [No. 320] to Sir C. Marling saying that His Majesty&apos;s Government wished to arrive at some clear understanding as to future policy and asking his views as to the main objects of that policy as set out in this telegram.   These were three in number : 1. The recognition of the South Persian Rifles in their present organisation and form till the end of the , war without further protest or question, His Majesty&apos;s Government being prepared to discuss the matter with a friendly Government when the war is over. In regard to this Sir C. Marling in a telegram [No. 398] sent oil the 22nd November said that it would be difficult to find a satisfactory non-committal
answer to the suggestion of a single uniform force with neutral officers which the Persian Government was sure to renew ; he presumed too that concessions to Persian sentiment were not precluded, as, for example, the appointment of a Persian officer to a high post in the force. The Viceroy in a telegram dated the 3rd December said that the Indian Government agreed with Sir C. Marling that it would be difficult for the Persian Government to give the desired recognition in the absence^ of concessions of some kind.2. The appointment of a friendly Government, i.e., one which will have due regard to British representations and be actuated by general friendliness to British interests ; there seemed to be no sufficient reason for making large concessions till such a Government was assured. Sir C. Marling concurred generally. The Viceroy said that his Government thought that, so long as Persia itself remained anti-British, a Persian Government purchased as proposed (for suggested terms see below) could not be either genuinely friendly or effective in our interests.3. The security of Persia against the intrigues of Germans and Turks, and more particularly against the entry into the country of roving bands either from Afghanistan or from the west. In regard to this, Sir C. Marling only emphasised the danger of such bands, and suggested that it might be prudent to employ part of the large sum now paid to General Baratoff to finance the Cossack division. But the Viceroy said that the friendly Government contemplated doubtless would not guarantee the safety of the Ispahan-Caspian line, and indeed coufcl not do so. But there should be ungrudging expenditure in securing the support of chiefs and notables and in the intelligence department.Mr. Balfour said that His Majesty&apos;s Government would be prepared to pay a reasonable price for the attainment of these objects, and that this price might take two forms : (I) The payment of a monthly subsidy, to be continued not longer than a month after the end of the war, but subject to this for so long as the Persian Government fulfilled the conditions satisfactorily. (2; The payment, on the same conditions, of the British share of the moratorium at the revised rate of exchange. Should Sir C. Marling concur in these proposals, Mr. Balfour asked what he considered a sufficient minimum monthly subsidy? Sir C. Marling said that he considered the proposed inducements sufficient, and suggested an offer of a subsidy of 50,000 tomans as a start in negotiation. He further advised the payment of the moratorium instalments being made on a sterling basis.Mr. Balfour said further that rather than pay blackmail to notorious ruffians who deserved condign punishment it would be better that the Bushire-Shiraz road should be officially closed, and His Majesty&apos;s Government was therefore not in favour of&quot; subsidising the rebel khans on that road. Sir C. Marling, in a telegram sent on the 23rd November, presumed that Mr. Balfours decision did not preclude subventions to Souiet and Kavam, which had secured a fair security to trade, and which he thought should be renewed. The Viceroy, in his telegram of the 3rd December, said that till such time as His Majesty&apos;s Government could come to a final decision on the question of the Bushire-Shiraz road, it seemed distinctly desirable to encourage its unofficial use, and his Government trusted that Sir C. Marling was right in his assumption that the subventions to Kavam and Souiet would be continued.In regard to the views of the Indian Government generally, Sir C. Marling, telegraphing on the 5th December [No. 419], said that the policy still advocated by it had been advocated by himself in the early summer, and might then have been successful hut now it would be harmful. Already the Persian Government was putting out feelers for assistance in its financial embarrassments on the basis of a recognition of the South Persian Rifles. Whilst the purchase of the support of local chiefs in North Persia, if any large expenditure were involved, would require a considerably larger number of agents, he still thought the policy outlined in Mr. Balfour&apos;s telegram and his reply the best iri the circumstances.
LATEST INTELLIGENCE.ZIONISM.The Odessa Demonstration. [Eastern Report XLV, p. 5] ,Further details of the demonstration in Odessa have come to hand. The British Consul in that place telegraphed on the 30th November j^No. L56] that the Zionists m Odessa (in which place more than half the population is J wish) had, on the previous day, organised a great demonstration in consequence of the receipt of a telegram announcing that Great Britain had made known her willingness to allow the Jews to occupy Palestine. In the broad street outside the British consulate there was a crowd estimated at 150,000, and the procession which marched past it, playing the British ancl the Jewish national&apos;anthems, was some 2 miles in length. The consul was asked to convey to the King an address of thanks signed, on behalf of the Jews of Odessa, by the chief of the Zionist movement. When the consul appeared on the balcony there were repeated cheers for King George, for the British Government, and the British people. The consul made a short speech in which he told them that Britain was determined to fight till a complete victory had been gained, and that she was fighting in defence of small nations and to secure a lasting peace, with the freedom of the whole world; he also impressed upon them that Britain never backed out of any promise she had made. This done, he remained on the balcony for two hours whilst the procession passed by. After leaving the British consulate the procession passed on to the American, where similar scenes were enacted. The day following, 30th November, a deputation of rabbis, representing fifty-eight synagogues in Odessa, was received by the consul and presented him with an address to the British people, similar to the one already received.Movement in Germany. To lessen the effect of the British declaration, a strenuous effort is being made by the German Jews to induce their Government to approach that of Turkey, and try to persuade it to agree to a settlement of Jews in Palestine under the rule of Turkey. As a result of this, or for some other reason, the German Govern-ment is interesting itself in the movement, and will try to obtain concessions for the Jews from the Turkish Government. In the meantime the German Jews were repre-sented in Zurich by Dr. Adolph Friedmann, of Berlin, who (presumably in connexion with Zionist matters) was in close touch with the German legation.RUSSIA.Detention of British Subjects in Russia. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 6th December [No. 1971] that Captain Smith had had an interview with M. Trotsky, who had authorized him to report that &quot; on the publication in the local press of a communique to the effect that the British Government would reconsider the cases of all Russian subjects interned in Great Britain, and would give facilities for the return to Russia of all Russians innocent of any offence punishable by the laws of Great Britain, he would on the same day restore full liberty of movement to all British subjects in Russia. Mr. Balfour telegraphed on the 10th December [No. 2456] accepting this proposal.The Cossacks and Ukraine Movements. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 11th December [No. 2006] that it was important that it should be understood that both these movements were concerned with the internal political situation and not with the continuation of the war. In his opinion there was no chance of their rendering-active military support: the most that could be looked for would be their taking steps to prevent supplies reaching the enemy, and their delaying the conclusion of a separate peace by a refusal to recognise it.ARMENIA.Turkey and Autonomy.&apos; -An agent reports that Turkey is prepared (in event of pourparlers being opened with Russia), if Russia will gran: autonomy to the Caucasus, on her own part to guarantee some form of autonomy to Armenia.   Information received from other sources suggests that there is good reason for supposing that rumours to this effect are current in the Turkish axmy.England and Armenia. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to the British consul in ; iflis on the 13th December [No. 5] telling him that he might assure the Armenian military defence committee that, to the best of our ability, we were prepared to assist the Armenians in their efforts to remain free from the yoke of Turkey.[898-73]C
APPENDIX I.The Influence on the Zionists in the Central Empires of the Conquest of Palestine and the British Declaration concerning a Jewish State.[The writer from his own personal experience thoroughly understands the situation in Palestine, and is well up in the events of the Zionist movement. This paper has been furnished by the War Office.]Although at the beginning of the war the Zionists in the central empires, and even more those in Palestine, were for some time dazzled by the great &quot; victories&quot; of the German military command, and even supported German colonial policy in their political demonstrations, the situation has changed more and more during the war, giving place to a purely Jewish policy, and one therefore hostile to German interests. The persecutions of the Jews, which began in Palestine in 1915, and the almost indifferent attitude of the Government towards these persecutions, caused such uneasiness even at that time in Jewish governing circles, and especially among the Zionists of the central empires, that the Turkish ambassador at Berlin was forced to contradict the reports of these persecutions and to declare that under the Ottoman protection the Jews enjoyed absolute equality of rights.The &quot;;Frankfurter Zeitung&quot; of the 8th November, 1915, which published the denial of the Turkish ambassador, added that the German Government had manifested, and still manifested, the sincerest goodwill towards the Jews of Palestine. Since that time the German press has not ceased its efforts to appease the growing discontent of the German Zionists by soft words and flattery addressed to the, Jews and Zionists.Following the lead of the numerous articles in the press of the entente countries which discussed Palestine and the Zionists with sympathy, a discussion arose in the G-erman press on the aims and possibilities of the realisation of the Zionist ideas. All this press campaign, however, was only an effort to regain the vanishing sympathies of the Jews and German Zionists. It was at this time that articles and discussions began to appear in the most important German and Austrian newspapers and reviews on the practical and political importance of Zionism for Turkey and the central empires. They took care to point out that not only ought the central powers to support Zionism on its own account, but above all in order to gain the sympathies of the Jews in the central empires and abroad for the cause of central Europe. We need only mention here the articles of Professor Ballod in No. 10 of the &quot; Europaische Staats- und Wirtscbaftszeitung,&quot; 1916 ; the endless series of articles by Major Franz Karl Endress, which appeared in this Review (January 1917, under the heading &quot; The Aims of Zionism and of Turkey &quot;), as well as in the daily papers, notably the &quot; munich Neueste Nachrichten &quot; and the &quot; Frankfurter Zeitung.&quot; This man displays matchless eloquence in order to persuade Jews that Germany and Turkey are disposed to support Zionism, and on the other band to commend to these Powers the loyalty of the Zionist aspirations.On account of the numerous declarations of the different official organs of the allied Governments, a still stronger campaign was started last year by the governing circles of the German press, especially in the liberal and social-democratic press, and in a lesser degree in the pan-German papers, and those belonging to the great metallurgic industry. On the theme of &quot; The Future of Palestine &quot; and &quot; The Zionist Aspirations,&quot; they have done their best to compete with the press and public opinion of the Allies, in order to win over the German and Austrian Zionists to the German cause.We will only mention here the titles of a few of these articles, such as &apos;: England&apos;s Struggle for the Empire of Israel &quot; (&quot; Englands Kampf um das Reich Israel,&quot; &quot; Volks-freund&quot; of the 25th May, 1917), &quot;The Zionist Movement&quot; (&quot;Die Zionistische Bewegung &quot;), &quot; Yossische Zeitung &quot; of the 18th October, 1.917, of which the following extract is of the greatest importance : &quot; We consider it important on account of the aspirations of the entente Powers to draw the attention of those directing our foreign policy to the Zionist projects,&quot; &amp;c, &amp;c.The order of Jemal Pasha in the spring of 1917 to evacuate the Jews from Jaffa and some neighbouring Jewish colonies for so-called military reasons was very preju-
dicial to the German propaganda in the German-Austrian press. The irritation oi the German and Austrian Jews showed itself in a great number of articles, especially in the &quot; Oesterreichische Wochenschrift&quot; (Vienna, 25th May, 1917), which laid stress on the fact that this measure is an irresponsible and unnecessary atrocity which ought to be designated &quot; The Third Devastation of the Holy Land.&quot; It is known that a question was asked in the Reichstag on this head, during which the deputy Cohn publicly declared that this measure was not necessary from a militaxy point of view, and occasioned great irritation among the Jewish population in Germany. All the efforts of the German official organs to appease the growing discontent of the German Zionists were ineffectual. In spite of certain Jewish organisations, notably the &quot; Hilfsverein der Deutschen Juden,&quot; which placed itself entirely at the disposal of the pan-German eastern political party, who have done their best to support this propaganda of appease-ment, a spirit of discontent and irritation has prevailed since this time in Austrian-German Zionism, and still alienates the Zionists from the government policy.We are able to affirm, in consequence of certain information from high official sources of German Zionism, that many months before the British declaration the German-Austrian Zionists were of the opinion that a Jewish state could be formed in Palestine only with the goodwill and assistance of the allied Governments. Those now living in neutral countries have not hesitated to give their opinion that the foundation of a national Jewish home in Palestine will only become possible when Palestine is under British control.It is interesting to note in this connection that an Austrian subject, a talented journalist named Ben Mose Zvvi Landau, has founded at the Hague a Jewdsh press bureau which supplies the worlds press with Jewish turd Zionist xiews, and which strongly upholds the point of view that Zionism can only be realised by the help of the allied Governments.The famous declaration of the British Government published the 9th November in the British press, which announced that Great Britain favoured and upheld the foundation of a national home for the Jewish people in Palestine, spread like wildfire among the German and Austrian Zionists, and appeared to them to be the word of deliverance. The official organ of the German Zionists the &quot; Judische Rundschau&quot;  wrote on the 16th November. 1917 : &quot;The declaration of the British Government is an event of the greatest importance. It is the first time that a great Power has officially x-ecognised Zionism. For the first time the pretensions of the Jewish people to the renewal of their national existence in Palestine have been placed on a level with the present great political problems, and it must be said that the recognition of our pretensions by the English Government is an event of historic importance. To us Zionists it is evident that such a recognition of our movement as a political element is of the greatest importance, independently of the policy which the Govexmments may pursue with regard to Zionism. It is to be hoped that the central Powers, and especially Turkey, will adopt the same attitude.The influence exercised by the British Governments declaration on the Jews in Germany and Austria has been so great that already the big German papers are beginning to warn the Jewish population not to put too&apos;much faith in the British Government. In the &quot; munich Neueste Nachrichten &quot; of the 18th November, 1917, the above-named Fx*anz Karl Endress writes as follows : &quot; The English, cleverly making use of the Zionist hopes, promise the Jews of the world the kingdom of Judah. No German Jew is likely to fall into the trap of this masquerade of an imperial policy.&quot;The same man gave a lecture in the Zionist section of Munich on &quot; Zionism and World Policy,&quot; in which he praised Zionism to the skies and affirmed that the German Government certainly ought to interest itself in Zionism, if only from the German national point of view. &quot; When Turkey has regained Palestine,&quot; he said, &quot; she will have to take Zionism into account. The domination of pan-Turkism would be most unwise, but the Zionist movement itself should be warned against too great an impatience.&quot;The speaker further promised that anti-Semitism would in future be excluded from the German policy of government, and that the Government would soon support Zionism unreservedly.    &quot; That is why,&quot; the speaker concluded, &quot; Germany expects that
her Jewish fellow-citizens will support German policy with their usual loyalty, and will not allow themselves to be seduced by the enticements of England.&quot;Not only do Zionists in Austria and Germany hold the point of view described above, but Jewish organisations generally now seek to hide their real opinion with regard to the re-establishment of a Jewish state in Palestine by exaggerated declarations of their loyalty to the central empires. The &quot; Oesterreichische Wochenschrift &quot; of the 16th November does its best to prove, in a long article, that the Jews are not perse-cuted in the central empires, and that they, as good citizens, do not hesitate to make any sacrifice for their country, but that nevertheless they rejoice with all their heart in the efforts of Wilson and the other allied Governments with regard to the future of Palestine, and that they are grateful to them for their noble sentiments. The following sentence taken from this article is extremely characteristic : &quot; We Jews in Austria and Germany must at all costs take care not to be led by these influences to expect the salvation and deliverance of Judaism at the hands of the entente Powers.&quot;The result of all these articles and all this evidence is that a great part of the Jews and nearly all the Zionists in the central empires are influenced in the highest degree by the policy of Great Britain and the allies with regard to the future of Palestine, so that it has already been found necessary to explain this away to the Governments of these States, and to publish assurances of their loyalty. It must also be mentioned that many other influences are now at work to gain the sympathies of the Jews of central Europe for Great Britain and the allies on account of their policy in Palestine.The fact that the most important financiers among the Jews in Great Britain and America Lord Bothschild and Jacob Schiff have openly declared themselves in favour of a national Jewish home in Palestine, and that all the Jewish communities and largest organisations in Great Britain have lately expressed their wishes in &quot;favour of a Jewish state in Palestine, has not failed to influence very decisively Jewish circles in Germany and Austria.Although the great Jewish financiers and &quot; Commercial Advisers &quot; in Germany and Austria are careful not to express their opinion on this subject, it is nevertheless certain that on the conclusion of peace ali these powerful and influential elements of German and Austrian Judaism will declare unanimously for the cause of a national Jewish home in Palestine, and will be grateful to that Power which will contribute most to the realisation of this idea.APPENDIX II.An Important Document concerning the Holy War.* [This paper also has been supplied by the War Office.]IN the contributions to the philology, land lore, and knowledge of nations, Professor Dr. C. Snouck Hurgronje transcribes &quot;an important document concerning the Holy War of Islam and an official correction.&quot; aThe document, itself, communicated in translation, was printed at Constantinople after the outbreak of war in 1914.&quot; On more than one occasion,&quot; says the writer, &quot; I v/as conscious of the significance of the half-official explanation regarding the holy war, but at the time its tenor/contents were only fragmentarily known to me. Since I came into possession of a printed copy of the pamphlet in question, I determined that it must be brought to notice in a translation for European interests.&quot;The document was issued by a committee to which may be ascribed a semi-official character, it is composed in the form of a &apos; General Announcement to Moslems only, especially to Moslems outside Turkey.&apos;&quot; Here we make acquaintance with the intellectual/spiritual aspiration of Turkey as a Moslem power (as some of Turkey&apos;s allies have called it). This weapon, which Moslems of more recent date had long since kept out &quot;of view, and of which they* Pages 1359-62 of Vol. XXXIX, No. 10, &quot;De Indische Gids,&quot; October 1, 1917.
spoke with reluctance, is here brought to the light of day, disrobed of all modernising gauds, adapted for daily use by assassins and gang-robbers. The domestic group in Turkey of the C.U.P. here invites in the name of what it calls the &apos; Caliphate of Islam &apos; ail Mohammedans to work together to exterminate, by each and every method which Satan has taught mankind, all non-Mohammedans who have not in one way or another worked for the Turkish sultanate; yes, it declares them bound to co-operate in that work, under penalty of being ranked as infidels or at least as impious.&quot; From the detailed document we borrow a few passages : &quot; They (the Moslems) ought to know that the sanctified war is a duty and that the blood of infidels under Moslem jurisdiction may freely be spilt (always excepting the Jews and Christians subject to Moslem authority, that is to say, those to whom temporary immunity from danger is granted ; and also the allies.)&quot;&quot; They (the Moslems) ought to know that the slaughter of infidels dominant over Moslem territory/jurisdiction is the duty of every individual, be it secretly, be it openly, as the grand Koran preaches in the words, &apos; seize and slay where&apos;er you meet them. We give you clear power over them.&apos; &quot;   (&quot;Koran,&quot; 4, 93.)&quot; Indeed, he who, in secret or openly, kills be it only a single individual of those who bear sway over M.oslem territory assures himself a heavenly recompense comparable to that of him who wakes the whole Islamic world to new life. There every individual Mohammedan, wherever lie may find himself, must undertake the slaughter of at least three or four of these dominant infidels, foes of Allah and of (the true) religion. He must take this duty upon himself before God, expecting his recompense therefore from God alone. Thus may the Mohammedan be fully convinced that, even &apos;if he has done no single other good work than this, he will be saved on the resurrection day. May Allah strengthen the faithful by His glorious guidance.&quot;For the Mohammedans &quot; who live in India, Java (Netherlands East Indies), Egypt, Fez, Tunisia, Algiers, Caucasia, China, Bokhara, Turkestan, and Iran &quot; the state of affairs is set out as the most favourable possible for expelling the infidels now ruling in their territory,&quot; and &quot;for freeing themselves from slavery.&quot; The position of the Governments in those lands is pictured as &quot;most infirm.&quot;A pretty passage is the following, which occurs in the explanation of the three forms in which the holy war can take place : &apos;: The individual holy war is an individual personal act which may consist in the use of a cutting, or killing instrument; as, for example, the holy war of blessed al-Wardini, who slew with his revolver (the Egyptian Minister) the infidel Boetroes Chali Pacha who sided with the English ; or the assassination of an English police commissioner in India by one of our Indian brothers ; or the murder by Aboe Bazir (in whom may Allah be well pleased) of an official who came from Mecca in the time of the prophet. A parallel case occurred when the prophet charged Abdullah ibn Atik to kill Aboe Rafi and four of his comrades (Rah, whose hostility towards Islam made him the acknowledged head of the Jews at Chaibar).&quot; To the same category belongs the killing of another leading Jew, Asir ibn Razim, by Abdullah ibn Rawahah and his comrades.&quot; &quot; 0 God 1 what possible argument can be used now against Moslems if there were found in the world of Islam, men who carried on such a holy war ? How glorious it would be if among the Moslems there were some  self-devotees to death who came forth to kill even one infidel upholder of the Triple Entente, who was known as a foe to Islam, and clean the surface of the world of his presence.&quot;&quot; O Allah ! O our King ! help us and quicken in our souls the spirit of the Holy Wax!&quot;Professor Snouck Hurgronje adds : &quot; About six months after the appearance of the &apos; General Announcement&apos; the passages concerning the Nederlands-Indies and also the attention of the Turkish authorities began to circulate, and then the latter deemed it expedient to make, by means of a double insertion in certain Turkish and Arab newspapers, an explanation which would reach everywhere. The wording of these insertions in all the intended publications is not wholly true to the original.&quot; In the official &apos; Tanin,&apos; for example, it was intimated that the Turkish Government did not approve the summons in so far as it was directed against Holland, a government [898-73]  - D
on good terms with the Ottoman Government, and it forbade its publication and dissemination so long as the sentences referring to Holland were not removed. In an explanation in the Arabic paper &apos; al-Adl,&apos; printed/appearing at Constantinople, the following words occur : &apos; Holland&apos;s attachment to andgood relations with the Sublime (Turkish) Government.&apos; &quot;These, and similar expressions, writes Professor Snouck Hurgrondje, may perhaps be so understood by Mohammedan readers as implying the correct proportion of dependence of a non-Mohammedan state towards the Caliphate.The Leiden professor writes, in conclusion : &quot; They who in the last three years have been eager to rediscover for Islam the almost forgotten paths of fanaticism so as to tread them again will have a heavy reckoning to settle with Islam, for even in the Moslem world healthy intelligence holds the upper hand, and is the guiding superiority ultimately wise enough to perceive that they are not the genuine friends of a community wdio try to develop to their own advantage the present various germs of sickness which she contains. Still, the attempts merit attention, for the mischief which can be caused by instigators, who preach the doctrine of assassination and the formation of robber-gangs as means of attaining to a sacred martyrdom, while of its very nature exceedingly limited both as regards place and duration, may yet spell destruction for many unlucky Moslems, and it necessarily delays that harmonious connection with the rest of the world which it so desired for all Moslems. And that recommendation has remained incorporated in the &apos; General Announcement&apos; to all the votaries of Islam, even after the &apos; Correction of an Error.&apos; &quot;APPENDIX III.The following letter appeared in the &quot; Saturday Review&quot; for the 8th December : The Revolt of the Arabs. (To the Editor of the &quot; Saturday Review.&quot;)Sir,Your fearless attitude upon the subject of our eastern policy makes me hope that you will give publicity to the following comments on an article which appeared in the &quot; Times&quot; of the 26th ultimo, &quot; From an Arab correspondent.&quot;   In it I read : &quot; There has always been foremost in the minds of the Turks a long-standing desire for the total extinction of the Arab race, and hatred and scorn of the Arabs.&quot;In the interests of historical accuracy (at the risk of being thought old-fashioned) I must say that this is twaddle.The Turks never had the slightest desire for the extinction of the Arab race. The Arabs of the Hejaz, retaining their own tribal and feudal systems, were for the greater part of the period of Turkish suzerainty under a loose, and often merely nominal, not a despotic rule. The inconceivable brutality and ruthless cruelty (mediaeval methods of warfare) overtook them as reprisals for similar cruelties upon occasions when their lawlessness transgressed all bounds, and became a menace to the whole Islamic world which goes to Mecca. As for the taxes, they cannot have been so very exorbitant, since they were &quot; levied upon rich and poor alike,&quot; and the difficulty of collecting them became proverbial. &quot; The people &quot; were always &quot; more or less reckless and savage,&quot; and they robbed and murdered pilgrims in the period before the Turkish hegemony more ruthlessly than they were able to do afterwards, at any rate when the Turk&apos;s hand was strong in their country. As for &quot; all the money of the Plejaz &quot; being &quot; drained into the coffers of the Sultan of Turkey,&quot; the Sherif of Mecca was a wealthy man before the war, as wealth is counted in the Turkish Empire, and the position then secured to him and his forbears in the Hejaz would have enabled them to benefit their country greatly had they wished to do so. They ranked as high Ottoman officials, and one can fancy that his present Highness must occasionally see in dreams his&apos; pleasant palace on the Bosphorus and the old comfortable days.&quot; The devotion of Moslems to their religion is well known,&quot; and from the second century of the Fleprah it has been the reproach of the Arabs of the Hejaz and the Yemen that they placed their tribal jealousies and tribal pride before the interests of the
Islamic realm. They lost their heads and ran amok upon some local grievance or affront without regard for Moslem interests. For that reason they have been described by Moslem writers of the Arabic tradition as untrustworthy, It is the fashion for the moment to confuse the Arabs of Arabia and the desert with the vast Arabic-speaking populations outside Arabia, in whom the mixture of Arabian blood is very small, who acquired the Arab speech when they embraced Islam. These (Moslems) were the people who produced the splendid civilisations of Cordova, Cairo, Baghdad, and Damascus. The noble followers of the prophet became one with them, merging their nationality in their religion, as became true Moslems. The Arabs who remained behind in Arabia soon resumed their ancient habits, their tribal raids and jealousies. All the civilisations which arose to any height in the peninsula were the work of mixed Moslem populations in the plains and cities, protected by the Caliphate against, the highland Arabs.The Arab correspondent of the &quot; Times &quot; goes on to speak of the improvement which has taken place since the country was freed from the yoke of the Turks. We are told, among other things, &quot; that the luggage of pilgrims is well looked after.&quot; I can well imagine that the Governments at present in alliance with his Highness the Sherif would stipulate for such reforms as that! Under the Turkish regime, we are told, there were only three primary . schools in all the Hejaz. Six. others and one military school were opened a year ago. What will the Arab officers who for ten years and more have been educated free of charge in the military school at Constantinople, and now are fighting in the Turkish army, think of that ? &quot; Three courses of religious instruction are given daily in the Haram, on the lines of that given at the El Azhar university in Cairo.&quot; Ma shadlah ! Religious instruction on the lines of El Azhar was always easily to be obtained throughout the Moslem Empire. What was till lately unobtainable in the provinces was secular instruction on the lines of the Galata Serai lycee at Constantinople, and the Young Turk plan of a Medina university was to provide that and a more enlightened teaching of religion. &quot; The Public Works Department is rapidly widening the narrow streets of Mecca, and steps are also being-taken to improve the Customs Service.&quot;Now what I would impress upon your readers and, if I could, upon the British Government, is, that no one in the Moslem world outside Arabia cares a rap for all this, however favourably it may strike the English reader. It does not even touch the Arab &quot; nationalist,&apos;&quot; who wishes to restore the ancient Moslem sway from India to the Atlantic, and hurl out the infidels, though if our present aim of&apos;cutting off the Arab provinces from Turkey is pursued, he will soon get his chance. As a Turcophil in spite of everything, I find myself regarded almost as a traitor to my country by some people at the present time. It is possibly because I care so much about the British Empire in the East, and from the circumstances of my life can see things from the Moslem point of view. Having had good reason to suspect, as long ago as 1913, that the entente Powers contemplated a partition of the Turkish Empire, and having seen the means by which the same suspicion, near to certainty, was forced upon the Turkish Government before this war, I realised the terrible effect which such a policy, executed at a moment when the Turks sincerely aimed at progress, would have upon my oriental fellow-subjects. And in my small way I have been trying to make England realise it. Orientals, and Moslems in particular, judge politics on moral grounds, as history judges. They still regard national honour as more sacred than personal honour. I am amazed that the recent Russian revelations should have been allowed to be so widely published in our press, for they show the Allies to have been quite conscienceless in their designs upon an Asiatic Empire, and will rouse the utmost horror in the East. I am amazed, too, that the one thing in our favour, from a Moslem point of view our refusal (as asserted by Lord Robert Cecil) to remove the caliphate at the behest of Russia, with the declaration that it was an affair for Moslems only to decide should not have been proclaimed with flaring headlines. It ought to be made known at once throughout the Moslem East. Our anti-Turkish plans were formed to please the Russian Government. Now that Russia has dropped out, we, by retaining them, step into her position as the foremost enemy of El Islam. I wish a change could be announced immediately, for no one knows what course the war may take.I am, Sir,your obedient Servant,Makmadxjice Ptckthall.11, Bedford Place, W.G. 1.FXIHTED  AT THE FORKIftX OFFICE  BT C. B. HARKISOJf.-15/12/1917.

</content>
</cab>
