<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 440-450</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN REPORT, No. XLIX.Jerusalem and Palestine.THERE is nothing in this report on the situation in Palestine because, although it is now some six weeks since General Allenby attacked and defeated the Turks at Gaza, we have had practically no information of any kind as to political affairs in Palestine, as to what the enemy did in Jerusalem before he left, how we stand in regard to the population, or what the attitude of the various elements of the population is towards us, our allies, or the Entente as a whole. This is regrettable, since we are obliged to depend for our information on such reports as M. Picot and Captain St. Quentin send to the Quai dOrsay and are subsequently forwarded to us. It is difficult to appreciate a situation or base a policy on one which is kept in such obscurity.The problems in Palestine are many; none of them are particularly difficult to handle, but they one and all require firmness and breadth of vision. Unless the people on the spot have a clear view of the situation, and the centre of control here in London is in hourly touch with every changing symptom, we shall drift into very difficult and dangerous situations.Russia.The Russian situation is undergoing a very interesting and subtle change. Although the anarchy and chaos is superficially what it was before, certain quite encouraging symptoms are beginning to appear.The Bolsheviks are breaking from the Germans.The Ukrainian forces are apparently consolidating.The general tendency among Georgians and Armenians is towards organisation and resistance.The sum of all these developments has a tendency to produce a pro-Entente and anti-Central Power atmosphere.It may be asked to what this curious change may be attributed, and the answer perhaps is that the Jewish element is silently working for us as a result of our Zionist declaration.Especial attention is drawn to &quot;the alleged propaganda of the &quot;Daily News&quot; correspondent in Petrograd.Zionism.Tala&apos;at&apos;s speech and the Copenhagen telegram are to be noted. It is not likely that the Germans and Turks can make good now on this subject. We made our&apos; declaration when we took Jerusalem; they can only make theirs after they have lost it. The Turks have had thirty and the Germans ten years in which to take the step.   The inference is too obvious.If the Turks commit themselves to Jewish autonomy they will, without gaining the support of the Jews, restore our position with the Arabs, for the latter will perceive [898-76]
that an Arabophil-Entente form of Zionism will be preferable to a Zionist-Turanian alliance.Arabia.The account of the friction between Ibn Saud and King Hussein should be read with care. It is unnecessary to repeat that both of these men are past masters in I he art of exhibiting themselves as the real friend of England. A great deal is said of the Wahabi revival, but this does not appear to be based on anything more than a small tribal scrap.It may be possible that the Turks are using agents to promote dissension among the Arabs ; in any case it would be useful to suggest this idea simultaneously to the King and Ibn Saud.* The fact that Mr. Philby has now traversed Arabia and has probably reached Jeddah should help to clear matters up.The news in regard to the Anazeh siding with us in Mesopotamia is distinctly encouraging.^  L M. S.January 4, 1918.* Since the above -was written the activities of Shaykh Salih at Beyrut (see latest intelligence) have been reported.   It is quite clear that the Turks are endeavouring to foment discord.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.!Printed for the War Cabuiet.SECBET.For Referevcf, onlyEASTERN REPORT.No. XLIX.   January 3, 1918. (Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LXXVT.)Contents.&quot;Russia in Europe.Germm Kepiy to Peace Proposals. Nationalisation of Banks. Message to Allied Countries. The &quot;Daily Mail&quot;  Correspondent  on English morale.&quot;Finland.Turkey.The Ex-Khedive. &quot;Zionism.The Jews of Corfu and the taking of Jerusalem.*Arabia.Ilejaz.Increase of Subsidy. The King and the Wahabis.* See LatestArabia (continued)  Nejd.Ibn Saud and the King of Hejaz. Relations with certain other Tribes. The Kedawi.The Anazeh and the Turks.Russia in Asia.The Caucasus.A nti- British Propaganda. &quot;Siberia.Bombardment of Irkutsk.&quot;Armenia.Persia.The Question of the Cabinet. Russian Troops in Kliorassan.Intelligence.RUSSIA IN EUROPE.rwp German Reply to Peace Proposals. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed [No. 2135] on the 27th December that the text, of the German reply to the six points put forward by the Russian delegation [Eastern Report XLVI1I, p. 1] had been published in the official press.Count Czernin had expressed the quadruple alliance&apos;s readiness to accept the Russian proposals as the basis of the immediate conclusion of a general peace without annexations or contributions, provided that Russia&apos;s allies would also accept without reservation the principles therein embodied. He then made the following statement in reply to the above-mentioned b&apos;ix points : 1. The quadruple alliance disclaimed any intention to forcibly annex any territory captured during the war. The question of troops holding occupied territory must be determined in the peace treaty in so far as their withdrawal had not been previously arranged.2. The quadruple alliance did not intend to deprive of their political independence any of those peoples who had lost such independence during the war.3. The question of the future of nationalities not enjoying political independence could not be regarded as an international question, but was a matter for decision in accordance with the constitution of each state directly concerned.4. The protection of the rights of minorities was also a matter for each Government directly interested.   Where possible this principle would be given effect.5. The quadruple alliance had repeatedly expressed itself in favour of the renounce-ment of claims for compensation for military expenditure and losses incurred through the war. Each belligerent should pay only for the maintenance of its own subjects who were prisoners of war and for losses caused on its own territory to enemy^ civilian subjects by the violation of the principles of international law. The creation of a special fund for the above purposes was only possible if the other belligerents joined in the peace negotiations within the specified period.[898-7.6] B
6. Of the quadruple alliance only Germany had colonies, and the return of such as had been captured during the war constituted one of the essential conditions of peace which Germany could not, in any circumstances, forgo. Germany agreed with the Russian proposal for the immediate evacuation of these colonies by the enemy; arid in view of local conditions considered the determination of their own future by the natives to be practically impossible of realisation. Moreover, the loyal and determined manner in which those natives had fought for Germany against over-whelming odds in face of exceptional difficulties was proof of their determination to remain under her rule at all costs. The quadruple alliance was in full accord with the Russian proposals respecting economic restrictions, and considered the establishment of such commercial relations as would satisfy the interests of all the peoples concerned as one of the most important conditions for the re-establishment of friendly relations between the present belligerents.Nationalisation of Banks. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 28th December [No. 2144] that the two following decrees relating to banks had been published in the official press: 1. Nationalisation of banks.In the interests of the proper organisation of national economy, the definite eradication of speculation by banks, and the release of the proletariat peasantry and of the whole labouring population from exploitation by bank capital, and with a view to the formation of one national bank of the Bussian Republic, which should genuinely serve the interests of the people of the poorest classes, the Central Executive Committee hereby enacts : (i.) Banking operations are to be a State monopoly.(ii.) All existing private banks or banking institutions are to be incorporated in the State bank.(iii.) Assets and liabilities of liquidated banks are to be taken over by the State bank.(iv.) The procedure of the incorporation of private banks with the State bank to be determined by a special decree.(v.) The administration of private banks is to be taken over by the council of the State bank.(vi.) The interests of small depositors will be fully guaranteed. 2. Revision of safe deposits banks.(i.) All moneys deposited in safe banks must be transferred to the current account of the client in the State bank.(ii.) All owners of safes must appear at the bank when summoned with their keys to be present during the examination of the safes.(iii.) All owners failing to appear within a period of three days from the date of summons will be regarded as wilfully avoiding examination.(iv.) The safes of those wilfully avoiding attendance will be opened by a revisory committee appointed by the commissioners of the State bank, and all property contained in such safes will be confiscated to the State bank and become the property of the people.Message to Allied Countries. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed [No. 2158] on the 30th December that M. Trotsky had, on the previous day, issued a message to the peoples and Governments of the allied countries, in which the following were the most important passages :  Two programmes had been submitted at Brest Litovsk, the German and the Russian ; the latter set forth as its task the creation of such conditions as would enable every nationality to have complete freedom of national development, and to unite all nations in economic and cultural co-operation.The former indicated that the countries at war with us did not intend forcibly to annex any territories captured during the war. This meant that the hostile countries were ready, after the signature of peace, to evacuate the occupied territories. By renouncing new forcible annexations the enemy Governments had departed from the principle of old annexations, that domination of the strong over the weak sanctioned by historical precedent. This meant that the destiny of Alsace-Lorraine, Transylvania, Bosnia, &amp;c, on the one hand, and Ireland, Egypt, India, &amp;c, on the other, were not subject to revision.   Such a programme was decidedly inconsistent, and appeared to he
a compromise between imperialism and labour democracy. Nevertheless the fact that such a programme had been submitted was a great forward step.It was impossible now for the allies to state that the war was being conducted for the liberation of Belgium and other conquered territories ; impossible, too, for the allies to brush everything aside by complacent phrases, such as the necessity to fight to a victorious conclusion. It was necessary for them clearly and accurately to state what the peace programme of the Entente Powers and America was. Did they, together with Russia, demand the granting of the right of self-determination to the peoples of Alsace-Lorraine, Galicia, Posen, Bohemia, and South Slavonic countries? If so, are they willing to grant similar rights to the peoples of Ireland, India, Madagascar, Indo-China, &amp;c, in the same way that the Russian revolution granted the right to the peoples of Finland, the Ukraine, &amp;c. For it was clear that to demand the right of self-determination for the peoples of hostile States and to refuse it to our own would mean standing by the j^rogramme of the most obvious imperialism.Up to the present the allied Governments had not shown a readiness to join in a genuine democratic peace.Ten days separated us from the renewal of peace negotiations. If the allied Governments continued to block the cause of a liberal peace the Russian delegation would continue the negotiations. A separate peace with Russia would no doubt be a hard blow to the allied countries ; but to foresee results is the task not only of Russia, but also of the allied countries.The Russian revolution had opened the door for an immediate general peace. If the allied Governments were willing to use this last opportunity general negotiations might be started immediately in a neutral country. If, on the other hand, the allied Governments au&apos;ain refuse to participate in the. negotiations, the labouring classes would be forced to seize the power from those who could not, or would not, give peace to the people. The message concluded with the following words : &quot; Addressing Govern-ments with this last opportunity of participating in the peace negotiations, we at the same time promise our complete support to the labouring class of any country which would raise, against their national imperialists, Chauvinists,&apos; and militarists, the banner of peace for the brotherhood of mankind and the socialistic reconstruction of society.&quot;The &quot; Daily Neios &quot; Correspondent on English Morale. Lord Granville telegraphed from Athens on the 27th December [No. 2191] that the Minister of Foreign Affairs had told him that, though he himself attached no importance to them, he feared that much harm might be done by the most undesirable stories of bad morale in England which were being spread in Petrograd by the correspondent of the &quot;Daily News.&quot; This person also said that Lord Lansdowne&apos;s letter had the full support of the King, of the majority of the Conservative party, and of many Liberals, and that he, Lord Lansdowne, would join a new Government under Mr. Asquith on the fall of Mr. Lloyd George, which was imminent.TURKEY.The Ex-Khedive. An agent reports that a couple of million of francs has been placed at the disposal of the Ex-Khedive for preliminary expenses in connection with his effort to organise anti-British feeling in Arabia and Egypt. . He says too that the Ex-Khedive was working very actively among the Arab chiefs.ZIONISM.The Jeios of Corfu and the Taking of Jerusalem. The British Consul at Corfu telegraphed the following message on the 1st January, at the request of the local Jewish community, headed by its Rabbi: The Zionist Jews of Corfu, on the occasion of the liberation of Jerusalem by the brave army of the alliance, have celebrated a Te Deum (sic) in the synagogue ; at the same time they express to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government, worthy representative of the English liberal and chivalrous people, their profound thankfulness for the promise of the national restoration of the Israelites in Palestine. They now express their fervid wishes for the triumph of the humane idealism which Great Britain so vigorously supports. We beg His Britannic Majesty&apos;s consul to be so kind as to transmit our present decree to the Foreign Office, and permit to us to sign.(Signed by Chief Rabbi and Committee.)
ARABIA.Hejaz.Increase of Subsidy. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir R. Wingate on the 1st January [No. 3] that King Hussein might be informed in regard to his subsidy that, for a maximum period of five months, His Majesty&apos;s Government was prepared to increase it by 25,000Z a month.The King and the Wahabis.S\r R. Wingate telegraphed on the 23rd December [No. 1388] that an attack by Wahahis on friendly Ateihah tribesmen had been reported by some shaykhs who had recently arrived in Mecca ; i he attack, they said, had been made at a place a day and a-balf&apos;s march to the north-west of Riad. The King regarded the incident as significant, and seemed to be seriously alarmed at the Wahabi revival in Nejd, which he believed Ibn Saud to have encouraged.Nejd.Ibn Sdud and the King of Ilejaz. Sir P. Cox telegraphed to Cairo on the loth December [No. 6070] that after two days&apos; discussion with Ibn Saud, Mr. Philby had written that he had shown great jealousy of the King of Hejaz and that he was extremely irritated by the latter&apos;s assumption of the title &quot; King of the Arab Countries,&quot; and suspected that King HussehVs attitude was based on some secret understanding with us. Mr. Philby had declared that this latter idea was entirely without foundation, and the subject had then dropped. He said that theiuler of Nejd undoubtedly sought more definite assurance as to tribal spheres and post-war delimitations as well as greater equality of treatment, both financially and politically.Telegraphing again [No. 6283] on the 23rd December, Sir P. Cox said that his personal impression was that King Hussein was striving to do his utmost to weaken Ibn Saud both by discrediting him with us and by achieving now for himself a position so prominent that Ibn Saud would never be able to challenge it, the King realising that never again would he be so strong as he is now, either financially or tribally. Any permanent peace or understanding between them was out of the question, and having in view the readjustment of the Arabian principalities which would be inevitable after the war, it seemed to him (Sir P. Cox) that it. would be a great advantage to have a ruler in Nejd who would counterbalance the ruler of the Hejaz. This would auto-matically correct any undue pre-eminence wdiich had been accorded to King Hussein because of war policy, and would certainly simplify our work in Iraq. He tully agreed that tin such assurances should be given to Ibn Saud even if he could capture Hail; he could Only be assured that our treaty stood good, and that there was every inten-tion to safeguard the independence which had been guaranteed him.In regard to one point touched upon in the earlier telegram, the Secretary of State for India telegraphed to the Viceroy on the 20th December that the title &quot; King of Arab Countries&quot; was quite unauthorised. &quot; King of Hejaz&quot; was the title which had been recognised. Sir P. Cox himself was wrong in speaking of &quot;His Majesty.&quot; Sisada, the style allowed, merely corresponded to &quot;lordship.&quot; The titles should be strictly adhered to ; they were chosen after Very Careful consideration.Sir R. Wingate telegraphed [No. 1390, 1406] on the 23rd and 28th December that if future collision was to be prevented a careful co-ordination of policy appeared to be necessary, as the internal situation in Arabia presented disquieting features. Ibn Saud and other chiefs had been alarmed by the aggrandisement of the Sherif of Mecca and the extension of his influence with the Anaz-h and the Ateibah. Till Faisal had made good in the north and the Turkish menace had been removed, the policy of King Hussein appeared to be to defer cultivating relations with his neighbours ; the develop-ment of this policy might place Ibn Saud at a disadvantage and was dreaded by him. The Wahibi revival was probably encouraged by him as affording a counterpoise. This movement might develop into a menace to Hejaz, and King Hussein appeared to be genuinely anxious.It was difficult to appreciate the relative force of Wahabi fanaticism and that of King Husseiu&apos;s influence; Sir R. Wingate thought that the iconoclastic tendencies of the former made it a greater possible danger and one less easy to restrain than the King&apos;s secular ambitions, and the latters dependence on our subsidies should be sufficient to enable us to restrain him. We could not, however, object, having regard to the spirit of our earlier negotiations, to the placing of a nominee of the King in the place of Ibn Rashid if Faisal should be successful against him Ibn Rashid&apos;s personal influence might disappear, he was already discredited in Arab eyes.   Sir R. Wingate
fully realised the necessity for keeping Ibn Saud on our side, giving him such assistance as the position in Mesopotamia made necessary, but he did not think that Ibn Saud&apos;s objectives were of sufficient importance to justify the giving to him of a blank cheque. He further said that he had no reason for doubting his good intentions, but he feared lest his knowledge of Idrisbs covert hostility to King Hussein and pressure from his Wahabite supporters might decide him to settle his differences with King Hussein by force of arms. The latter fully understood that our policy was not to set up Arab against Arab and that we should resent military action by him against our allies.Relations with certain other Tribes. Sir P. Cox telegraphed [Nos. 6184 and 6185] on the 20th December to the-Indian Government in regard to the recent conversations with Ibn saud, saying that among the main topics were the respective rights of himself and the Shaykh of Koweit in regard to the levying of tribute from the Azawin tribe, and the relations with the Ajman tribe of the same shaykh and ourselves. In regard to the former it had been arranged that an endeavour should be made by us to induce the shaykh to write a friendly letter to Ibn Saud, reaffirming brotherly love, deprecating any continuance of friction, and suggesting a friendly reversion to the old arrangement by which that tribe paid tribute to the shaykh ; Ibn Saud had agreed to accept this solution with reserve if he should receive such a letter.In regard to the Ajman, he resented their being allowed to reside in British territory or Koweit from which they could not be excluded without the employment of troops. Owing to the loss of his brother at their hands, his animosity is implacable, and it appears i though he does not admit it) that his failure to make a big move against Ibn Rashid has been partly due to the fear that the Ajman might threaten his rear. It-was agreed that the Ajman should be called upon, tmough Shaykh Salem, of Koweit, to join our friend Fadal Beg Ibn Hadhdhal, and if they refused this, then that their leaders should go to Ibn Saud and make their submission, and arrange to live under his control where he should direct. Should they refuse both alternatives, they were to be regarded as hostile and forbidden to enter British territory or Koweit.Messrs. Philby and Watillton were agreed that there would be no forward action on the part of Ibn Saud till these questions had been settled.The Bedawi.The Anazeh and the Turks. Sir P. Cox telegraphed on the 23rd December [No. 6283] recalling that a large concourse of Bedawin of the Amarat, Fidaan, and Sba divisions of the Anazeh had (on account of the oppression and scarcity f om which they had suffered in Syria) migrated to the eastern side of the desert, and were assertiu-j- that, having done with the Turks, they wanted to serve under Fahad Beg Ibn Hadhdhal. He added that, as good rain had at length fallen in the desert, it was their intention to celebrate this unusual gathering of the Anazeh, when their animals had had two or three weeks&apos; grazing, by a move in force against their hereditary enemies the Shammar, and en route they would shift the Ajaimi.RUSSIA IN ASIA.The Caucasus.Anti-British Propaganda. General Shore, telegraphing from Tiflis a week ago, said that a very serious propaganda, which was at once Turcophile and anti-British, had been started at that jdace and at Baku by the Tartars.Siberia.Bombardment of Irkutsk. Sir J. Jordan telegraphed from Peking on the 27th December [No. 626] that, according to a telegram from Irkutsk which had just been received, that town was being bombarded by the Bolsheviks, and had been under fire for seven days. The property of British and French was being plundered, and they themselves were being exterminated. Help was implored. There was apparentlv no date to this telegram, which had been forwarded by the consular officer at Harbin on the 26th December. SirJ. Jordan added that the latest news was to the effect that the Bolsheviks were being worsted by the White Guards.[898-76] &apos; &apos; C
PEESIA.The Question of the Cabinet. Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 27th December [No, 481] that he feared that the Shah would refuse to make Vossuk-ed-Dowleh president of the council; his courage was failing him, and he thought that by trying a Vossuk-ed-Dowleh combination (which according to his expectations would fail&quot;) he would change the mere contempt of the Germans and the Democrats into active enmity. In these circumstances, Sir C. Marling proposed Cas an attempt to take the wind out of the sails of the extremists and to conciliate the moderates) to try for a cabinet under Amin-ul-Mulk and Vossuk-ed-Dovvleh. Mr. Balfour telegraphed on the 29th December [No. 369] approving this suggestion.Russian Troops in Khorassan. Sir C. Marling transmitted [No. 479] a message, dated the 23rd December, from the consular officer at Meshed saying that an order for the withdrawal of the Bussian troops in Khorassan had been received from the Cossack organisation. Had it come from the Maximalists, the officer in command would in all probability have disregarded it; as it is, he had replied that he must be supplied with sufficient funds before he could move. The sender of the message expressed the opinion that it was necessary to have one regiment at least in that province to assist in ensuring the safety of the roads, to secure and escort escaped prisoners, and to check democrats.LATEST INTELLIGENCE.RUSSIA.Statement by M. Trotsky. Sir G. Buchanan telegraphed on the 2nd January that M. Trotsky had published through the official Press Bureau a statement made with the view of establishing the truth regarding certain .questions of international policy. He referred first to the Austro-German delegation now in Petrograd He stated it numbered about sixty, more than half of whom were clerks, servants, &amp;c. Its aim was precisely specified in the published statement respecting the armistice, and the delegation had no connection with peace negotiations. No official announcement had yet been made on the delegation^ work, as it only began its sittings on Monday evening.The telegraphic facilities given to the delegation by the Eussian Government were the same as those granted to the Russian delegation at Brest Litovsk. Regarding peace negotiations, M. Trotsky said they had been suspended for ten days, and he doubted whether, when renewed, the sittings would continue at Brest Litovsk, as at the present stage the Bussiair Government considered it more expedient to carry on negotiations in a neutral country. He stated that the Eussian Government now possessed the Austro-German peace proposals. The document was not a draft respecting a separate peace but a detailed German view as to the future relations to be established between Eussia and the Central Powers. M. Trotsky declared the inacceptability of the proposals; a self-evident point of difference was in regard to peoples&apos; rights to determine their own future. The Germans, while accepting this right in principle, refused to apply it to Poland, Latvia, Courland, parts of Livonia, and Esthonia. M. Trotsky said: &quot;Just as yesterday the Government formally recognised Finland as an independent republic,* so it is prepared to recognise as republics Poland, Litovsk, and independence of Courland or voluntary incorporation with other countries.&quot; Eegarding Poland, the Eussian Government demanded that Polish workmen and peasants should be free to decide the future not only of Eussian but ofa 11 parts of Poland.M. Trotsky said that if German diplomacy imagined that Eussia regarded the prin-ciple involved merely as an empty formality it was profoundly mistaken. He complained bitterly of the attitude of the German press in keeping silence. He also mentioned the attitude of the allies towards peace negotiations, describing it as one of embarrassed perplexity, prompted by a desire to postpone the day of reckoning, apparently under the impression that a change of a few kilometres one way or the other on the western front, and the loss of several additional&apos; hundred thousands of French and German lives, created a more favourable basis for the opening of peace pourparlers. Concluding, he said : &quot; Our task is clear ; we continue negotiations on the basis put forward by the* This is the first intimation which has been received of this fact.
Russian revolution. We are taking every step to inform the masses of all European countries as to the result of these negotiations, notwithstanding the censorship established by European Governments, and do not doubt that negotiations will render us stronger and imperialistic Governments weaker in all countries.&quot;Hitch in the Peace Negotiations. Sir G. Buchanan on the 1st January transmitted [No. 4] a telegram from the Military Attache saying that a difference of opinion was said to have arisen in connection with the no annexation clause ; whether for this reason or another, there was a hitch in the peace negotiations another rumour attributed this to a German demand to import goods into Russia free of duty. M. Trotsky spoke of breaking off relations. Sir G. Buchanan, telegraphing on the same day [No. 5] said that the correspondent of a London newspaper, in close touch with the Bolsheviks, had told him that, the latter had at last realised that the Germans intended to annex the Baltic provinces, under the &quot;self-determination &quot; formula. The Germans claimed that the necessary pronouncement had already been made by those provinces; the Bolsheviks that they were not in a position to make it so long as the Germans were in occupation.SIBERIA.The Situation at Irkutsk. Sir J. Jordan telegraphed from Peking on the 2nd January [No. 5] that a telegram giving news of Irkutsk had been received by the railway officials. It said that much damage had been done, but the Bolsheviks had been defeated, and incendiaries and looters shot.ZIONISM.The Turks and Zionism. The Copenhagen correspondent of the Exchange Telegraph Company sent the following telegram on the 1 st January : The Grand Vizier, in an interview with the Constantinople correspondent of the &quot; Vossische Zeitung,&quot; declared that the Turkish Government was always favourably disposed to the Jews in Palestine. Turkey was the sole country winch never had an anti-Semitic movement. The Grand JVizier also declared that Mr. Balfour&apos;s promise that Great Britain would aid in establishing a national home for the Jews in Palestine was humbug and not seriously meant. The Turkish Parliament, added the Grand Vizier, is discussing a Bill which would open the possibility of a strongly developed Jewish autonomy. [&quot; The Times,&quot; 2nd January.]German Intentions in regard to Zionism. Sir R. Paget telegraphed from Copen-hagen on the 2nd January [No 16] in regard to the interview reported above that the secretary of the Danish Zionist Society had stated that it was given at Count Bernstorff&apos;s urgent request, as he was alarmed at the effect of Mr. Baifour&apos;s declaration on the Jews all over Europe; the secretary, referred to above, was, Sir R. Paget said, in close touch with continental Zionists. The interview would pave the way for an official declaration of German intentions in regard to Zionists iu Palestine, which would shortly be issued by the German Minister for Foreign Affairs. That this would undo much of the effect of Mr. Balfours declaration was feared by the secretary, who urged that it should be anticipated by the despatch of a Jewish d- legation to form the provisional Government of the new Jewish state in Palestine being at once announced through Reuter.ARABIA.Hejaz.Meeting at Jeddah. Sir R. Wingate telegraphed on the 30th December [No. 1417] that Mr. Philby was expected to reach Jeddah on the 31st December or the 1st January ; he left Taif on the 28th December. At Jeddah he would meet Commander Hogarth on the 4th or 5th January, and it was understood that King Hussein was also proceeding to Jeddah.MESOPOTAMIA  AND  PERSIA.Attempt to foment Discord among the Moslems. An agent reports, under date the 21st November, that a certain Shaykh Salih had been paid to write articles for the purpose of raising the Shiites of Persia against the English, and of raising the Sunnis of[898-76] D
Baghdad against the Shiites, who were denounced as infidels on account of their attachment to the English. This was done at the instigation of the German consul at Beirut. Shaykh Salih, who though outwardly pro-German (he has worked for them for some months) is really pro-British, avers that the Germans are paying Turkey to induce her to take Bersia under her protection.BALESTTNE.Alleged Pillage of Relics in Jerusalem. In reply to an enquiry, Sir B. Wingate telegraphed [No. 16] that he had learnt that when the patriarchs were deported from Jerusalem, they were ordered by the Turkish Governor to take all sacred relics with them. They took a few unimportant ones, but left those of importance in charge of their representatives. No case of pillage of the relics had been reported, but Turkish troops who had been billeted in convents had looted and sold vestments.ARMENIA.The Armenian National Committee at Tiflis. This committee on the 26th December sent a telegram to Boghos Nubar Pasha (President of the National Armenian Delegation), of which the following is a translation : Unfortunately your fears were well founded; there has been an almost complete abandonment of the Caucasus front. The Council, though without means, is taking urgent measures for the defence of the three provinces and the Caucasus ; it is rapidly pushing forward the formation of a national army corps under Nazarbecow, and the Armenian refugees will form a special battalion and a militia. Agreement with the Georgians is certain, though not definitive. Financial and military help are more than indispensable. The annulment of the secret diplomatic agreement to hand Armenia over to Russia would be another valuable help, and it would seem to be necessary that the immediate autonomy of Turkish Armenia should be formally recognised by the allied Powers, Russia having already recognised the right of peoples to decide their own fate. Please be good enough to keep me au courant with the negotiations.The following is a transaction of the reply sent to this on the 29th December : Your telegram has been received. The national delegation is pleased to hear that you are taking urgent measures for the defence of the three provinces and the Caucasus, and that a good understanding with the Georgians is certain. We sincerely congratulate you, but recommend that in the measures taken for the defence of the three provinces there should be no distinction drawn between the Armenians of R,ussia and those of Turkey. Intermediate union and co-operation are indispensable. I confirm my telegram of the 24th December informing you as to the military and financial help of the allies and the immediate despatch of funds needed for the organisation of defence.The national delegation is of opinion that in the actual circumstances a proclamation of autonomy by the allies would be impolitic, on the ground that it would compromise your understanding with the Georgians and provoke oj^osition on the part of the Moslem population; and this the more that Messrs. Balfour and Lloyd George, for the English Government, and M. Bichon, for the French, have recently declared officially in their Parliaments that the war aims of the allies include the liberation of iVraienia and the freeing of it from the Turkish yoke. When Armenian military forces occupy the freed Armenian vilayets in sufficient numbers to ensure their defence, the national delegation will see no difficulty in the proclamation of their independence by the Armenian masters of the territory.Copies of these telegrams were sent to Sir Mark Sykes with a covering letter from Boghos Nubar Pasha, of which the following is a translation : Herewith I send, for your information, a copy of the telegram which I have received in reply I sent, on the 6th December last, to the permanent national Armenian committee at Tiflis ; my telegram and the reply were both sent through the French consulate.The Quai d&apos;Orsay received with this telegram another from the chief of the French military mission, Colonel Chardigny, who, when he saw the last paragraph
of the enclosed telegram from the permanent Armenian committee, said that he agreed with his English colleague that the proclamation of Armenian autonomy, by a diplomatic act, would be impolitic at the present moment, as it would both excite discontent among the Georgians and the Russians and create difficulties with the Moslems.I entirely agree with this and have just sent the enclosed reply to the Quai d&apos;Orsay, which has undertaken to transmit it through its consulate at Tiflis. I am also sending copies of these two telegrams to Captain Amery for the information of the Supreme War Council.As you will see, the delegation did not approve the suggestion that the diplomatic act should be annulled and the autonomy of Turkish Armenia proclaimed by the allies. I hope that you will agree with the solution which we have suggested, that the Armenians should themselves proclaim the autonomy of the provinces when, having freed them, they hold them with a force sufficient for their defence.As to the request of the Armenian Coinrhittee for financial help, I know that the two allied Governments have already done what is necessary, but I think that it would be well to telegraph to your representatives in Tiflis to at once inform the National Armenian Council, so as to encourage our compatriots, and to convince them that they may confidently count upon military and financial help from the Allies, and so may organise themselves upon a large scale. May I venture to hope that you will be good enough to see that this is done as soon as possible ?FII1RIS AT THE TOItEIGK OyJTICK BT C. B. HXRRISOK.-4/1/1918.

</content>
</cab>
