<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 529-536</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN REPORT, No. LIU.Russia.INTEREST attaches to the first telegram given in the report regarding the i&quot; Congress of Sovyets.&quot; The reason given for the closing of the Constituent Assembly fits in with the Bolshevik doctrine that the proletariat alone have political rights. The Bolshevik aim is to replace Parliamentary institutions by a Congress of Sovyets on a Syndicalist basis not only in Russia, but in all countries.Bulgaria.Attention is drawn to the extract regarding the conclusion of peace between Bulgaria and Russia.Palestine.British policy in regard to Palestine is now clearly set forth in Mr. Balfour&apos;s telegram No. 113 to Sir R. Wingate, dated the 24th January.General Clavton&apos;s telegram concerning .VI. Picofs representations against the Italians being allowed to mount guards over the churches of the Holy Sepulchre and of the Nativity reveals the jealousy with which the French &quot; Commissioner &quot; is animated in his attempts to press French claims to an exclusive right to protect Latin Christians in the East. Now that Turkish rule has. disappeared M. Picofs claim has no solid foundation, and is inconsistent with our policy of &quot; equality of treatment in regard to our allies.&quot;W. 0.-G.January 31, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of Eis Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government] ^2sePrinted for the War Cabinet.SECRET.For Reference onxy.EASTERN REPORT.N0.LHI.   January 31,,1918. (Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LXXX.)Contents.Russia.Congress of Sovyets.Russia and Routnania.Demon strati&apos;m at Moscow commemora-tive of Red Sunday 1905. Treatment of Prisoners of War. Interchange   of    Postal   Matter   forPi isoners.Ukraine:Relations with the Allies after the cou-clusion of a Separate Peace. Poland.The Bolshevists and the Polish Army  a Suggi-stion.Roumania.Increasing Difficulties of the Situation.Serbia.The British and American Declarations.Greece&apos;.Untrue Report in regard to M. Venezelos and Cyprus.Bulgaria.Conclusion of Peace with Russia.Palestine.Administration. Outline of Policy.Representations of the Italian Govern-inent.Arabia.Hejaz.King Hussein&apos;s Title. Armenia.Decree of the Russian Bolshevik Govern-ment.See Latest Intelligence.RUSSIA.Congress of Sovyets. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 26th January [No. 235] that the third &quot; all-Russia n&quot; congress of Sovyets had opened on the 23rd Jauuaryat the Tauride palace; there were about 700 delegates, almost all Bolsheviks or Left Social Revolu-tionaries, the opposition consisting of Centre and Right Social Revolutionaries and a certain number of Internationalists not exceeding sixty. Socialist representatives from Switzerland, Roumania, Ukraine, Norway, Sweden, Denmark, Poland, United States were also present. The president in his opening speech defended the closing of the constituent assembly by the Sovyet Government, and declared that the congress, as the supreme and sole organ truly representative of the proletariat and of peasant interests, would have to decide the character of the future form of the administration of Russia and the questions of peace and the future status of nationalities living in Russia. The remainder of the sitting, which was marked by much enthusiasm, was occupied by the speeches of foreign Socialists and of Chicherin and Petroff, who received an ovation, and declared, amid loud applause, that Great Britain was on the eve of a revolution. Trotsky also spoke, but merely welcomed the foreign delegates, and expressed his conviction in the ultimate success abroad of the present revolutionary movement.The second sitting on the 24th January was marked by a lengthy speech by Lenin, whose appearance was the signal for prolonged applause. He dwelt on the history of the Bolshevik movement, detailed the work of Council of People&apos;s Commissaries, and explained the necessity and aims of its decrees.The sitting of the 25th January was chiefly noticeable for the impassioned speech of the Internationalist Martov, who severely criticised that of Lenin, and particularly the administrative methods of the Sovyet Government.[898-80] B
Russia and Roumania. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 26th January [No. 237] that the Roumanian Minister, as soon as he had permission, would leave for Sweden it would not be safe for him to attempt to reach Roumania. He had intimated to the authorities that he wished to leave on account of the difficulty of his position since his imprisonment, and the decree ordering the arrest of the King of Roumania., This he did to avoid a rupture, as he had heard that the Bolsheviks intended to break off relations with Roumania. Mr. Lindley said that a state of war with Roumania seemed to exist, though there had been no declaration.On the following day he telegraphed  [No. 235] that  the  official press bad &quot;that day published the following communique on the &quot; treachery of the Roumanian bourgeosie and the treason of General Scherbatov &quot; : The Roumanian oligarchy, steeped in crime, has opened military operations against the Russian Republic. Accustomed to maintain its authority on the poverty, enslavement and blood of the Roumanian peasantry and proletaiiat, the Roumanian monarchy has attempted to save itself, its estate owners and bankers, by the seizure of Bessarabia and its conversion into a bulwark against the tremendous current of the Russian revolution. The crimes committed by the Roumanian military and civil authorities are without number. The commissioners and repre-sentatives of the Russian revolutionary troops are being arrested and shot, and the revolutionary troops are being disarmed and starved to death and subjected to artillery fire whilst retiring to the rear. Scherbatov, the commander-in-chief on the Roumanian front, is taking a very prominent part in these bloody outrages.As a protest and warning the Council of Commissaries arrested the Roumanian Minister for a short time, but this step was without effect, and crime follows crime. The Council of Beople&apos;s Commissaries decrees the breaking off of all diplomatic relations with Roumania, and the deportation of Roumanian Legation and all agents of the Roumanian authorities across the frontier by the shortest possible route. It declares the Roumanian gold fund at Moscow inviolable as regards the Roumanian oligarchy. The Sovyet Government will be responsible for its safe custody, and will hand it over to the Roumanian people. It also declares Scherbatov, ex-commander-in-chief on the Roumanian front, who has risen against revolution, an enemy of the people and an outlaw..0n the 28th January Mr. Lindley transmitted [No. 255] a message from the military attache, who said that a formal note of declaration of war would be sent, that day, to the Roumanian Minister. That Roumania was on the eve of revolution and that the overthrow of the monarchy was inevitable was the belief of the Bolsheviks, who were working with Roumanian socialists to bring about both.Demonstration at Moscow commemorative of Red Sunday 1905. Mr. Wardrop telegraphed from Moscow on 23rd January [No. 12] that there had been a Bolshevik demonstration on the previous day in which soldiers, the Bed Guard, and roughs had taken part and had marched through the city, all being armed. There was some firing, but probably not more than a couple of score were killed. The object of the demon-stration, was to commemorate Red Sunday; incidentally to oppose the constituent assembly. The opponents of the Bolsheviks took no part in it, but they held some small open-air meetings. &apos;Mr. Wardrop telegraphed again on the 25th January [No. 15] giving some particulars of a proclamation issued on the 24th by a &quot; presidium &quot; of the Councils of Workmen and Soldiers and Peasant Deputies of Moscow and its district in regard to the firing on a demonstration, presumably that in commemoration of Bed Sunday. The proclamation stated that this had been fired upon by the followers of the Social Revolutionary mayor of Moscow, who on his election had been congratulated by Sir George Buchanan and other bourgeois. The proclamation asked whether the working classes were to be much longer menaced by the armed bourgeois. The revolutionary soldiers and workmen were, it said, boiling with rage and a desire for vengeance. The bourgeois desired civil war in its most acute form, and the rest would carry it through in such a way as to beat out for ever the desire to attack workmen. The working class should be ready to come out as one man against the bourgeois at any moment, but the moment must be decided by the supreme revolutionary authorities.Treatment of Prisoners of War [see Eastern Report LII, p. 3].- Mr. Lindley tele-graphed on 27th January [No. 242] that in regard to prisoners of war the Russians had agreed to consider the Hague conventions as binding, but no soldiers were to be forced
to act as officers&apos; servants against their will. They reserved, however, the right to denounce any clauses of the conventions which involved humiliation to any category of prisoners.Interchange of Postal Matter for Prisoners. In the same telegram [No. 242] Mr. Lindley said that he had reason to believe that a direct interchange of postal matter for prisoners began ou 25th January, via Dunaburg.All-Russian Anarchist Congress. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 28th January [No. 253] that the All-Russian Anarchist Congress had been opened in Petrograd that day. It had not yet been decided whether the public was to be admitted. One question to be discussed was that of the public openly taking possession by force of anything they might desire.Volunteer Socialist Army. On the 28th January Mr. Lindley transmitted [No. 255 i a message from the military attache, who said that an order had been sent by Krylenko instructing all committees at the front to help in the formation of a new volunteer socialist army, to be known as the &quot; Red Army.&quot;The Cossacks.- The military attache also said that ten Cossack regiments at the front had declared Kaledin to be a traitor, and had passed a resolution to support the Bolshevists against him.Ukraine.Declaration of Complete Independence. Mr. Bagge telegraphed from Kieff on the 25th January [No. 16] that on the previous day a proclamation of complete independence had been passed by the Ptada. The nationalisation of banks and the immediate conclusion of peace were also included in the proclamation.Relations loith the Allies after Conclusion of a Separate Peace.- Sir G. Barclay-telegraphed on the 23rd January [No. 67] that the chief of the Ukraine mission had called on the French Minister on the previous day and spoken of the peace nego-tiations ; and then went on to say that after the conclusion of peace the Ukraine would endeavour to entertain good relations with the Allies, to organise itself with their assistance, and to restrict to the minimum supplies furnished to our enemies, its object being to safeguard its future. He also declared that the Ukraine would facilitate the pro vision ing of Roumania.In regard to the supply of food or other necessaries to the Central Powers Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Mr. Bagge at Kieff on the 28th January [No. 5] instructing him to make it clear to the Rada that it could not look to Great Britain for financial assistance if it arranged or threatened to arrange for the supply of food or other necessaries to the Central Powers.POLAND.The Bolsheviks and the Polish Army : a Suggestion. Mr. Bagge telegraphed from Kieff on the 24th January [No. 15] that the recent Bolshevik attempt to disarm the Polish army might be explained by an agreement which was said to have been concluded between Germany and Austria giving the former a free hand in Poland and Austria similar freedom in regard to Ukraine. He had heard of this agreement from two good and, he believed, independent sources.ROUMANIA.Increasing Difficulties of the Situation. Sir G. Barclay telegraphed on the 28th January [No. 85] that on the previous day the ministers of the four allied countries had been called together by the prime minister, who had emphasised the ever-increasing difficulties of Roumania. With the exception of such as could be obtained from Bessarabia, all supplies might be cut off from Ptoumania as a consequence of the imminent conclusion of peace by Ukraine.,  SERBIA.The British and American Declarations. Sir C. des Graz telegraphed from Corfu on the 24th January [Mo. 13] that he had been informed by the French minister that intense depression in all Serbians, iron) the Crown Prince downwards, had been caused
by the British and American declarations, and the exclusion from them of a reference to a Jugo-Slav union with Serbia. The French minister had been to Salonica and had returned with the prime minister.Sir C. des Graz had telegraphed on the previous day that the prime minister had telegraphed at length, in regard to these declarations, to the assistant minister for foreign affairs, who had communicated the telegram to him and the United States minister.The prime minister said that these declarations had been a surprise and disdlusion and had caused anxiety for the future liberty of the Serbian people, for the principle of each peoples right to dispose of its future appear to have been given up.No mention had been made of the desire of the Serbian race to unite with Serbia nor of the struggle which had been waged throughout the centuries for that object.There was no mention of Jugoslavia, which, owing to its geographical position, could offer the only strong barrier to German spread eastward. The annexation of Bosnia and Herzegovina and the attack on the independence of Serbia proved the direction of German pressure; Germany and Austria risked this world war to crush the Serbian nation, which was the one obstacle in their path, by Constantinople and Asia Minor, to the Persian Gulf. And yet the Serbian nation was not treated on the same footing as the Italians and the Poles.Only the restoration of Serbia and Montenegro was spoken of, but not repatriation as in the case of Belgium.   And yet Serbia had suffered more and had lost more men.Mention was made of the national aspirations of the Italians and the Roumanians but not of the Serbians, though, both before and during the war, tens of thousands of&quot; Serbs had been condemned and killed in Austria-Hungary for manifesting national Serbian feeling and solidarity. Neither the Italians of the Trentino nor the Roumanians of Translyvania had ever shown the same determination for union or equalled the sacrifices in life and property made by the Serbians under the Turkish-Austrian yoke. And yet promises were made to both Italians and Roumanians, while the aspirations of Serbians, Croatians, and Slovenes were passed by.The violation of Belgian neutrality was quoted, but not the violation of the treaty of Berlin in time of peace and against every wish of Bosnia and Herzegovina, whose inhabitants had been ill-used and tyrannically ueed and had been made the pretext of this war.GREECE.Untrue Report in regard to M. Venezelos and Cyprus. Lord Granville telegraphed on the 24th January [No. 80], that as the Greek papers had that day published an alleged telegram from London to the French papers alleging that M. Venezelos had received assurances in London that Cyprus would be ceded to Greece at the end of the war, he had prepared to issue an oificial statement that no such assurances had been given by His Majesty&apos;s Government; but M. Venezelos, whom he had informed of his intention, had asked him to let him do it himself, and his renewed denial had appeared in the evening&apos;s paper.BULGARIA.Conclusion of Peace with Russia. Reviewing the Bulgarian press for the last ten days of December, the War Office &quot; Daily Review of the Foreign Press&quot; for the 24th January says that &quot; the most important event discussed for the period under review isthe conclusion of peace between Russia and Rulgaiia.....   Although press commentleaves little doubt as to peace having been signed, nevertheless, a remark by M. Gueshov imparts a certain mystery to it.&quot; The &quot; Mir &quot; of the 28th December made the following-announcement : To-day Radoslavov communicated to the Sobranye the terms on which peace was concluded yesterday at Brest-Litovsk between Bulgaria and Russia; the following treaty of peace was signed : 1. The war between Bulgaria and Russia is ended.2. The relations existing prior to the declaration of war between Bulgaria and Russia are resumed, and all consular, commercial, and other treaties come again into force, in other words, friendly relations are re-established.3. The right of Bulgaria to have a delegate at the International Danube Com-mission is acknowledged. This question will be finally decided on the conclusion of general peace.
In conclusion Radoslavov stated that peace had been concluded in full agreement withall the allied delegates.&apos; The announcement caused great joy and was followed by loud applause.But three days later M. Gueshov in an article contributed to the same paper speaks of &quot; the understanding with Russia &quot; as &quot; the forerunner of peace between us [Bulgarians] and those [Russians] with whom we were the least disposed to fight.&quot;In this regard a telegram [No. 36] despatched from Berne by Sir H. Rumbold on the loth January is of interest. He said that Bulgarian delegates returning from Brest-Litovsk were reported to have said that they considered a separate peace between Bulgaria and Russian to be assured. He had been informed as to this by a person who had spoken with the delegates.PALESTINE.Administration.-Sir R. Wingate telegraphed on the 27th January [No. 184 J in reply to Mr. BalfouFs telegram of the 23rd January [E.R. LII, p. 7]. He expressed his approval of the division proposed to be made between the administrations of Egypt and Palestine, and of the proposed line of demarcation. As to the Arab Bureau, he said that a nucleus already existed in Palestine and could be strengthened : Major Cornwrallis would continue to act as director in Cairo.Outline of Policy. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir R. Wingate on the 24th January [No. 113] suggesting for his guidance a general outline of the policy which should be pursued in order to reap the full benefit of our position in Palestine, such policy tending to secure 1. The establishment of a regime of justice, fair play, and religious equality for all.2. The reduction of the European personnel to a minimum and the employment of local functionaries and officials wherever possible without favouring any special community.3. The removal of German influence.4. Equality of treatment in regard to our allies..5. The return in the near future to Jerusalem of the religious heads of the various denominations, but not of the political or consular representatives.6. The settlement of all matters relating to the holy places, not through inter-mediaries, but directly with the religious chiefs, and the maintenance of order therein by a civilian police, under British control, recruited from the various denominations having a religious interest in their custodianship.7. The maintenance of Zionism on right lines without prejudice to the safety of the Christian and Moslem holy places, and with full facilities for the reconstruction and establishment of colonies and institutions.Representations of the Italian Government. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir R. Wingate on i:4th January [No. 106] telling him that he had been requested by the Italian Government to allow its consul in Cairo to proceed to Palestine; he should, Mr. Balfour said, be permitted to make a tour of inspection for a definitely limited period. In reply to this Sir R. Wingate on 27th January transmitted [No. 192] a message from General Clayton saying that if the Italian consul were allowed to go to Palestine it would be difficult to refuse similar applications, and that therefore it was undesirable that he should go there.In the same telegram Mr. Balfour also said that attention had been drawn by the Italian Government to the fact that a guard at the Church of the Holy Sepulchre was mounted by the French. The Italian Government thought that this was counter to the spirit of our agreement, and Mr. Balfour suggested that, as a temporary concession and until the abolition of military guards, the Italians should be allowed to mount, in the course of the week, the same number of guards as were mounted by the French.In regard to this General Clayton telegraphed that it had been arranged that we should mount guard on the churches of the Holy Sepulchre and the Nativity and on the mosque of Omar four days a week, the French on two days, and the Italians on one. As the French detachment numbered over 2,000 and Italians under 1,000 the arrange-ment appeared equitable.The arrangement arrived at was in consequence of the representations made by M. Picot that the French should mount guard on the two churches and the mosque. M. Picot. however, objected to the Italians mounting guard on the churches. General Clayton did not recommend any chanp-e being- made.[896-80] * * C
ARABIA.Hejaz.King liusseirfs Title. Six R. Wingate telegraphed on the 28th January [No. 199] that he had been approached by the King of Hejaz on the question of his title through the Hejaz agency in Cairo. King Hussein wanted to be recognised as &quot; King of the Arabs,&quot; and represented that this would not only help his cause, but would tend to refute enemy propaganda in regard to the Entente aims in Arab countries being annexationist.    Sir R. Wingate asked for instructions.ARMENIA.Decree of the Russian Bolshevik Government. On the 13th January the following decree was published at Petrograd : The Council of the People&apos;s Commissaries declares to the Armenian nation that the Government of the workmen and peasants of Russia maintains the right of the Armenians of Turkish Armenia to freely settle their national conditions (etat) comprising therein their independence. The Council of Commissaries admits that the realisation of this right can only be made possible by the establishment of a series of preliminary guarantees absolutely necessary for the security of the referendum to the Armenian people. The Council recognises the following as partial guarantees : (1) the evacuation of Turkish Armenia by the Russian troops ancl the immediate creation of an Armenian national militia with the object of guaranteeing the personal security of the inhabitants of Armenia and their property; (2) the unfettered return of Armenian emigrants and Armenian fugitives to Armenia; (3) the unfettered return of those who have been.driven by the Turks during the war to the interior of Turkey. The commissaries will insist upon this last point with the Turkish delegates during the peace pourparlers ; (4) the formation of a provisional Armenian Government in Turkish Armenia, in the form of a council of deputies of the Armenian people elected on a democratic basis. Stepan Chahpumian, who has been appointed commissary extra-ordinary for the affairs of the Caucasus, [? has been instructed] to assist in every way the inhabitants of Turkish Armenia to realise the provisions of articles (2) and (3) above and to form a mixed commission for the determining of the date and mode of evacuation of the Russian troops. The geographical frontiers of Turkish Armenia will be fixed by democratically elected representatives of the Armenian people in accord with the Moslem inhabitants and others of the disputed adjoining provinces together with the Commissary Chahoumian.A copy of this telegram was sent to Sir Mark Sykes by Bogos Nubar Pasha, who, in a covering letter, remarked that though it was needless to say that he did not attribute too much importance to this decree of an ephemeral Government, he thought that what should be remembered was that the Bolsheviks were not hostile to Armenian autonomy, and that it appeared that they did not wish to withdraw Russian troops from the conquered vilayets till Armenian forces had been organised to defend them.PERSIA.Recall of Russian Military Mission.   Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 23rd January [No. 53] that the Persian Government had been informed by M. Trotsky that the Prussian military mission had been recalled. Colonel Clerget, the newly-arrived commander of the Persian Cossacks, about whom the Persian Government seemed disposed to make difficulties, was prepared to disregard the order.Recall of all Russian Troops. Sir C. Marling telegraphed on the 29th January [No. 72] that he had been informed by a Russian officer who had just returned from Tiflis that orders had been issued by the Caucasus Government for the withdrawal of all Russian troops from Persia.
LATEST INTELLIGENCE.RUSSIA-IN-EUROPE.esthonia  and LlVONIA.Proclamation of Independence. Sir E. Howard telegraphed from Stockholm on. the 29th January [No. 241*] that the papers of that date had published a proclamation submitted to Mr. Vorowski, the official Bolshevik representative in Stockholm, by a deputation from the Esthonian and Livonian Ritterschaft and Landschaft declaring the independence of Esthonia and Livonia, and asserting their right to conclude agreements with other countries. They still desired to maintain friendly relations with Russia, but as the latter&apos;s aggressions, now and in the past, had reduced the provinces to a desperate condition, in which they were unable legally to establish their own indepen-dence, the Livonian and Esthonian Ritterschaft bad resolved to apply for protection to the German Empire. The proclamation was handed to the representatives of the Russian and German Governments. The proclamation justified the Ritterschaft&apos;s action on the ground that it constitutionally represented the population of the provinces, and referred to treaties of the 18th century concluded by the Ritterschaft on their behalf. It further stated that it voiced the general desire of the common people. Various agricultural and other organisations were said to have expressed the same wish, but these could not be named for fear of Bolshevik reprisals.Mr. Lindley had already telegraphed on the 23rd January [No. 207] that he had received a visit from the Esthonian members of the constituent assembly, and had been told by them of an official offer made by the German Government, some weeks previously, that, if Esthonia would accept its protectorship, the independence of the province should be guaranteed. Private hints were given that a refusal of this offer would involve the occupation of Esthonia by Germany. Mr. Lindley&apos;s visitors explained that, much as they dislike the idea of a German protectorate, they preferred it to being again under a Russian monarch, and they were convinced that monarchy would be restored in Russia.RUSSIA-IN-ASIA.The Caucasus.Increase of Disorder. Mr. Stevens telegraphed from Tifiis on the 28th January [No. 14] saying that: (l) Collisions between Moslems and Armenians were reported from various places. (2) Moslem activity, fanned by Turco-German propaganda, was on the increase. (3) There was a report from Vladikavkas of grave trouble at that place, during which private houses were pillaged and a&apos; number of public and Government buildings destroyed by fire, events which had been attended by considerable lossTurkestan.Autonomy [see E.R., LI, p. 6]. Sir J. Jordan telegraphed from Peking on the 29th January [No. 80] tbat the Bolsheviks appeared to have been helped by German prisoners of war in the recent fights at Tashkend, and that he saw nothing to prevent those prisoners from invading Kashgar if the Bolshevik regiment should remain in Turkestan.

</content>
</cab>
