<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/144/0 images: 545-553</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED EASTERN  REPORT. No. LV.Russia.THE news from Russia is bulky, but not susceptible of general appreciation. The Esthonian question is important, as it appears to be one of those areas over which the Russian Bolsheviks might once again come into conflict with Germany.Zionism.The official statement that France is in agreement with the policy of Zionism should be noted.   The French Government have long delayed making this view public.Arabia.The King of Hejaz&apos;s messages show a, growing confidence both in himself and our support. tTurkey.The war-weariness of the Turks should be noted, but it is to be observed that the pan-Turanian idea continues, and that the Turks are quite immovable about Armenia.M. S.February 14, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]296Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET.Fob. Reference only.EASTERN REPORT.No. LV.   February 14, 1918. (Incorporating Arabian Report N.S. LXXXII.)Contents.Declaration of non-existence of a State of War.Proclamations regarding Peace and De-mobilisation. M. Petrov.MM. Karrieneft&apos; and Saalkind. Consulate-General at Glasgow. Russians in the British Army. Confiscation of Bank Shares, &amp;c. Confiscation of Roumanian Funds. Change of Calendar. Ukraiuia.Peace with the Central Powers.Situation in Odessa.Suggested Advance of Gold by the Central Powers.Ukiainia and Roumania. Esthonia.Attitude of the Allies. Eastern Siberia.Bolsheviks in Krasnoyarsk.*Ronmania.The German Command, Peace Negotia-tions, and the Cabinet. General Averescu.&quot;Turkey. Palestine.The Military Administration of Palestine. General Situation.Zionism.The French Government and Zionism.&quot;Arabia.Hojaz.Message from   the  King  to  King&quot; Hussein, and reply.Armenia.Turkish View.Persia.Activities of the Jangali. Enemy Propaganda in Reslit Turks at Kasma.* See Latest Intelligence.RUSSIA.Declaration of Non-existence of a State of War. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 11th February [No. 417J that be had just heard that M. Trotsky had, on the previous day, informed the enemy at Brest that the Russians had refused to sign the imperialist peace terms proposed by the Germans, but that a state of war no longer existed between Russia and the enemy countries ; that orders for a complete demobilisation would be given at once.Proclamations regarding Peace and Demobilisation. The following Russian wireless message, addressed &quot; to all whom it may concern,&quot; was received in London yesterday : Comrades,The peace negotiations are at an end.    German capitalists, hankers, and landlords &apos; supported by the silent co-operation of the English and French bourgeoisie, submitted to our comrades, the members of the peace delegation at Brest-Litovsk, conditions such as could not be subscribed to by the Russian revolution.The Governments of Germany and Austria desire to possess countries and peoples vanquished by the force of arms. To this the .authority of the Russian peoples of workmen ancl peasants could not give its acquiescence. We could not sign a peace which would bring with it sadness, oppression, and suffering to millions of workmen and peasants. But we also cannot, will not, and must not continue a war which was begun by Tsars and capitalists in alliance with Tsars and capitalists.   We will not, and we[898-82] B
must not, continue to be at war with Germans and Austrians workmen and peasants like ourselves.We are not signing the peace of landlords and capitalists. Let German and Austrian soldiers know who are placing them in the field of battie, and let them know for what they are struggling. Let them know also that we refuse to fight against them.Our delegation, fully conscious of its responsibility before the Russian people and /the oppressed workers and peasants of other countries, declared on the 10th February, in the name of the Council of the People&apos;s Commissioners of the Governments of the Federal Russian Republic, to the Governments of the peoples involved in war with us and of neutral countries, thai&quot;, it refuses to sign an annexationist treatv.Russia, for her part, declares the present war with Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey, and Bulgaria at an end. Simultaneously the Russian troops receive the order for complete demobilisation on all fronts.(Signed) L. Trotsky, President of the Russian Peace Delegation andCommissioner for Foreign Affairs ; A. Bicenico, Coui-missioner for State Properties; W. Karelin, A. Ioitfe, M. Pokrovsky, Members of the Peace Delegation ; W. Medvkdiofp, President of the All-Ukrainian Executive Committee of the Sovyets; Shakhrai, Secretary for War of the Ukrainian Republic ; L. Karahan.Brest-Litovsk, February 10, 1918.In connection with the above, I order that the necessary steps be immediately taken for declaring to the troops that the war with Germany, Austria, Turkey, and Bulgaria is regarded from the present moment as being at an end. No military operations must again take place. With the present order the beginning of a general demobilisation on all fronts is decreed.I order the staffs mi the front to issue instructions for the withdrawal of troops from the first lines and for their concentration in the rear, and further for their being sent to the interior of Russia, in accordance with the general plan for demobilisation.For the defence of the frontier some detachments of the younger soldiers must be left.I beg our soldier comrades to remain calm, and to await with patience the moment for the return of each detachment to its home and in its turn.I beg that no effort be spared in bringing into stores all artillery and other military equipment, which has cost milliards of the people&apos;s money.Remember that only systematic demobilisation can be carried out in the shortest time, and that systematic demobilisation alone can prevent interference with the sending of food supplies to those detachments which remain for a certain period at the front.[Unsigned.]&apos;    February II, 19 IS.M. Petroc. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 5th February [Nos. 3.35 and 344] that a passport enabling M. Petrov to visit England had been sent to him for visa, but he had refused to give one pending instructions.M. Chicherin had, he said, spoken to Captain Smith on the subject and had requested that tire attention of His Majesty&apos;s Government might be drawn to the following points :  &apos; M. Petrov was originally arrested at the beginning of 1916, under paragraph 4(6)-of the Defence of the Realm Act, by order of the Home Office. He appealed against the order for internment before Lord Dewar who upheld (? appeal). He was, however, sentenced to be provisionally detained though he was never actually interned. When ordered to be deported lie again protested, and it was then explained to him that he was not being deported but repatriated. His passport was not therefore marked &quot; not to return &quot; as would otherwise have been the case, so that even from the point of view of British war legislation there could not be any legal impediment to his return to England.In reply to Mr. Lindley&apos;s request for instructions, Mr. Balfour telegraphed [No. 228] on the 11th February that M. Petrov could not be allowed to come to England ; he was released from internment and returned to Russia at the request of the Bolsheviks,
and there was no apparent reason for his being permitted to come here again with all the new prestige he would derive from being a Bolshevist agent. Before ins internment he had been actively engaged in fomenting strikes on the Clyde, and if he got the chance he would doubtless renew his activities.On the same day Mr. Lindley transmitted [No. 4L9] a, message from- Mr. Lockhart to the effect that M. Chicherin had again raised the Question of M. Petrov&apos;s visit to London. Mr. Lockhart said that it seemed clear that the whole of our future in Bussia depended on the manner of settlement, of this question, and he urged that permission should he given for the visit. MM. Petrov and Chicherin had given solemn assurances that the former had no intention of creating dissension in England.In another telegram of the same date J No. 420] Mr. Lindley said that M. Chicherin had told Captain Smith that Smolny attached the greatest importance to M. Petrov&apos;s visit. He was going to England to explain the policy and aims of the Bolshevik Government together with the situation in Bussia, and not to make trouble for His Majesty&apos;s Government. They thought the present the most suitable moment and -M. Petrov the.best man for the purpose. Mr. Lindley thought that it would be best to accept M. Petrov before friction had arisen, if there were any likelihood of the Government being obliged to accept him by external pressure.MM. Kameneff and Saalkind, [see E. R. LIV, p. 3]. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 6th February [No. 353] that he had received a note from the commissary informing him that M. Kameneff had been appointed representative plenipotentiary on a special mission to Sweden, Norway, Denmark, Franco, and England.Sir Esme Howard telegraphed from Stockholm on the 12th February [No. 399a] that he had been informed that M. Kameneff was going with the declared intention of; stirring up revolution in the allied countries ; he was a most dangerous man. And on the same day Sir M. Findlay telegraphed from Christiauia [No. 547] that Major Borne, the chief staff officer of General Poolers mission, had been told by Bolsheviks, with whom he had travelled, that both M. Kameneff and M. Saalkind intended to carry on a revolutionary propaganda in the United Kingdom.Consulate-General at glasgow. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Mr. Lindley [No. 230] on the 12th February in regard-to the wish of the Bolsheviks to nominate a British subject named Maclean to this post. His Majesty&apos;s Government was unable to comply with the wish, as Maclean was a convict on licence : he had been condemned in 1916 to three years&apos; penal servitude for seditious speeches.Russians in the British Army. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 5th February [No. 337] that the following communique had been published by the official organ : To all, to all, to all and to England.Considering inadmissible the application of compulsory enrolment in the British army to Bussian citizens in England, as also the delegation to any foreign State of the right to compulsorily enrol Russian citizens for military service, the People&apos;s Commissary for Foreign Affairs has instructed his representative in London, M. Litvinov, to enquire of the British Government what steps it intended to take in regard to the convention concluded on this question with M. Kerenski&apos;s Government, and has expressed the hope that no misunderstanding would arise between- England and Bussia therefrom, and that England would desist from all measures which might lead to such a result.Telegraphing again on the same day [No. 338], Mr. Lindley said that we should be forced in the end to yield to the agitation against the service of russians in the British army, as it was fairly clear it would grow. He therefore advised an early-concession.Confiscation of Bank Shares, ccc.--Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 8th February [No. 386] that a decree, styled Froject of Decree, signed by M. Lenin, had been officially published that day. It entirely confiscated all stock, reserve, and special capitals of the late private banks and transferred them to the Bopular Bank of the Russian Republic; it annulled all bank shares and ordered the discontinuance of the payment of all bank dividends. It was further ordered that ail bank shares should be immediately delivered by their present owners to the local-branches of the State bank, and if they were not in the owners&apos; hands that the latter should present lists pointing out the exact where-abouts of the shares. The penalty for non-delivery of shares or lists within a fortnight was the complete confiscation of all property. All bank share transactions and transfers were absolutely prohibited.
Confiscation of Roumanian Funds. Mr. Balfonr telegraphed to Mr. Lindley on the 11th February [No. 221] instructing him to make, in conjunction with his French colleague, a declaration that the Allied Powers bad a claim on the Roumanian funds at Moscow, seized by the Bolsheviks, which funds constituted a guarantee for money advanced to Roumania.Change of Calendar.-Mv. Lindley telegraphed on the 8th February [No. 380] that on the previous day a decree had been issued instituting the Gregorian calendar in - Russia from the 31st January old style.ukrainia.Peace with the Centred Powers. -Sir W. Townley telegraphed from the Hague on the 10th February [No. 630] that the quadruple alliance had signed peace with Ukrainia.On the 11th February Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Mr. Bagge at Kieff instructing him o associate himself with his French colleague and to make, on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, a declaration similar to the one which the latter was to make on behalf of his Government to the effect that it did not recognise the separate peace which had been concluded.Situation in Odessa.- Mr. Lowdon telegraphed on the 11th February [No. 51] that in consequence of their followers fearing the imminent arrival of Roumanian and Ukrainian troops, though the Bolsheviks were still in power they were losing ground. They had failed in their effort to raise au army to fight Roumania. It was believed that an attack on them was being prepared by the anarchists.Suggested Advance of Gold by Central Powers.  Sir H. Rumbold telegraphed from Berne [No.  190] on the 8th February that he had heard that the Germans and Austriaus had under consideration the question of advancing (on the security of mines and forests) gold to the Ukrainian Government immediately after the conclusion of&quot; peace.Okrainia and Roumania. In the telegram [No. 190] quoted above Sir IT. Rumbold, after saying that Roumania would probably make peace once Ukrainia had done so, went on to say that the Government of the latter country was willing that the former should have Bessarabia in return for her ceding Dobrudja to Bulgaria.Esthonia.Attitude of the Allies. Mr. Balfour, telegraphing on the 26th January to the British representatives in allied countries, said that His Majesty&apos;s Government considered that the reply to the Esthonians suggested by Mr. Lindley would be the most suitable; that is to say, that they should be assured that at the peace conference everything possible would be done to prevent their being, against their will, annexed by Germany, and further to secure some form of international guarantee for the independence of any States which, as a result of the war, might &quot;come into existence.Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 7th February [No. 371] that the Esthonian delegates seemed to be satisfied with the above reply. They desired to lay their case in person before His Majesty&apos;s Government, and Mr. Lindley had authorised their being granted a passage. In conversation they had told him that the Germans were intriguing to obtain an expression of opinion in their favour, and might bo successful in so doing on account of the outrages of the Bolsheviks and the Russian troops.Eastern Siberia.The Bolsheviks in, Krasnoyarsk. Mr. Lindley transmitted on the 9th February [No. 394] a message, dated the 5th February, which bad been sent via Moscow by the consul at Krasnoyarsk. He said that the Cossacks had left, without any notice to the inhabitants, when the town had been summoned to surrender hy the Bolsheviks, who were then masters of it. They bad seized the banks, and commerce was paralysed. The Cossacks of that region were arming, but they were said to be without a sufficiency of either ammunition or money, and therefore were unlikely to be successful in the fighting which was anticipated.
ROUMANIA.The German Command, Peace Negotiations, and the Cabinet. Sir G. Barclay telegraphed on the 6th February [No. 120] that the German command had fixed an imperative term of four days for the opening of peace negotiations. Consequent thereupon a cabinet crisis was expected. Telegraphing again on the following day [No. 123], be said that at the cabinet council held on the 6th the Conservative section wished to break off pourparlers, but the Prime Minister, with a view to gaining time, was in favour of opening peace negotiations. There had been a second cabinet council at which the Conservatives had made it quite clear they would not assume responsibility for the intensely unpopular policy of continued resistance unless there was some participation of the Liberals who were in the cabinet, and no Liberal minister would join them. On the 9th February Sir G. Barclay telegraphed that he had learnt that the German command would be informed that peace negotiations could not be opened for some days as a new cabinet was being formed for the purpose.General Averescu. Sir G. Barclay telegraphed on the 10th February [No. 141] that General Averescu had been charged with the formation of a cabinet.PALESTINE.The Military Administration of Palestine. Mr. Balfour telegraphed on the 8th February [Nos. 9 and 10], in regard to the position of the French commissioner, setting out what, under existing circumstances, appeared to him to be the proper and most convenient procedure, subject to the G.O.C.-in-C. finding no objection.In regard to all administrative affairs, the military administration was not only soleby responsible but supreme. French officials were accorded certain ceremonial honours by the Catholic ecclesiastical authorities, but no deduction should be made therefrom as to the French commissioner having any right to exercise executive authority or being entitled to make representations on behalf of any element, not French, of the Palestinian population or of any supra-national religious body; and M. Picot should be so informed. No claim based on consular status under the Turkish regime could be admitted by the military administration; pending a final settlement, all consular rights must remain in abeyance.As, however, France had considerable interests in the country, its commissioner was empowered to advise the military administration on any question relating to such interests, whether it concerned institutions, concessions, or persons, in so far as such matter had no supra-national character and was purely French. To enable this to be done, an office of petitions might be established, which should forward any petitions received, relating to such purely French persons or matters, to the French commissioner for his advice, on which the military administration should act, in so far as military exigencies might allow.General Situation. General Clayton telegraphed on the 6th February [LB. 472] that there was nothing special to report. As confidence increased and transport became easier the economic and currency situation was gradually improving.The general feeling throughout Palestine was pro-British; and the Arabs east of Dead Sea were strongly pro-Sherif and anti-Turk.Telegraphing again on the 11th February, he said that the Bedouins of the Beersheba district had been alarmed by enemy statements that they would receive severe treatment at our hands. These fears had been dissipated, and their attitude was more satisfactory. Conditions, in general, might be said to be steadily improving. The inhabitants were appreciating more and more the change from Turkish rule; and the Arabs were, generally speaking, very favourably disposed towards King Hussein.ZIONISM.The French, Government and Zionism. Lord Bertie telegraphed on the 9th February [No. 184] that the following communique had appeared in the &quot; Temps&quot; : M. Sokolow, representing the Zionist organisations, was received this morning at the Ministry for Foreign Affairs by M. Pichon, who was glad to confirm to him that the understanding between the French and British Governments was complete con-cerning the question of the establishment of Jews in Palestine..   &apos; [898-82] C
- ARABIA.Hejaz.Message from the King to King Hussein. The following message was sent by His Majesty the King to the King of Hejaz :  I hasten to express my great joy at the successes which your gallant son the Emir Feisal has obtained over the enemy in the Ard-ed-Sowan. As the leader of the noble movement of liberation of the Arab race and as father of a victorious son your Highness has double cause for satisfaction and pride. Equally with your Highness I rejoice in the constant progress of the Arab armies and the increasing area of Arab emancipation.In reply to this his Highness sent a message of thanks to His Majesty through Sir R. Wingate, who telegraphed on the 7th February [No. 268] that King Hussein had requested him &quot; to communicate his congratulations to His Gracious Majesty the King-Emperor &quot; for the victory gained by the Emirs Feisal and Zeid at Tafile. This was intended as a further grateful acknowdedgment of His Majesty&apos;s last message to King Hussein, and evidence of the latters loyalty to his alliance with Great Britain.ARMENIA.Turkish View. An agent reports that in regard to Armenia the Turkish attitude is that the country should be evacuated by the Russians and occupied by the Turks. Their contention is that there is no reason whatsoever for granting autonomy to. this part of the Turkish empire as the population was overwhelmingly Moslem.   From their-point of view any grant of independence should be confined to Russian Armenia..PERSIA.Activities of the Jangali. Mr. Balfour telegraphed to Sir C. Marling on the 8th February [No. 80] that he should point out to the Persian Government that its attitude in regard to the Jangalis would enable us to forecast the outcome of the negotiations on other subjects now in progress ; it should be urged to take such action or preventive measure as might be possible. In reply, Sir C. Marling said [No. 96] that the authority of the Government was of no account at Resht, so that the representa-tions which he had several times made, in the sense indicated, had been fruitless. The Cabinet was even too timid to take any action in the case of Obeidulla, whom its predecessor had wished to deport.Enemy Propaganda in Besht. In the telegram quoted above [No. 96] Sir C. Marling said that it had been reported to him that a German officer was then at Resht for propaganda purposes, and that there was also an Austrian officer at that place.Turks at Kasma. Sir C. Marling further said [No. 96] that he had been informed that thirty Turkish prisoners had arrived at Kasma from Baku.LATEST INTELLIGENCE.RUSSIA.Bolshevik Government and the Peace Delegates. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 12th February [No. 428] that the official organ of the Sovyet Government stated that at an extraordinary sitting of the Central Executive Committee of the Councils of&quot; Soldiers, &amp;c, Deputies the statement made by the Russian peace delegation at Brest bad been read out, after which the Executive Committee passed the following resolution with only one dissentient and twenty-three abstentions : The Petrograd Sovyet entirely approves the statement made by the Russian peace delegation at Brest on the 10th February. Further, the Petrograd Sovyet expresses the conviction that the workmen and soldiers of Germany, Austria, Bulgaria, and Turkey, at the present historical moment, will. perform their duty and not allow imperialistic Governments to carry out the proposed violence against the peoples of Poland, Latvia, and Courland.At the same sitting the Sovyet drew up and approved an appeal to the Russian soldiers in the trenches respecting the order for demobilisation which had already been issued by the Sovyet Government.   This appeal emphasised the necessity for preserving
perfect order during the demobilisation. In conclusion, the appeal referred to the formation of the new red socialist army, which it stated was the only army which could ensure law and order in the country and guarantee the retention of all ihat had been won by the revolution. This appeal practically invited all who were willing to join this new army.-Russia and Roumania. Mr. Lindley telegraphed on the 11th February [No. 413] that Mr. Lockhart had, at his request, spoken with M. Chicherin about Roumania. The latter had stated that a state of war existed though there had been no declaration. The Roumanians were not only trying to cut off the Bolshevik troops in Ukrainia from their supplies, but were also advancing on Kisheneff with the purpose of capturing Bessarabia. He acknowledged that the Russians were supporting the Bolshevik movement in Roumania, where he said a class Avar was going on as in Russia. An embargo had been laid on Roumanian gold in Russia, but there was no intention to confiscate it; no payment would, however, be made to anyone in Roumania till matters had been cleared up. There seemed to be no hope of any modification of the Russian policy in regard to Roumania ; the Bolsheviks regarded it as an essential part of their class war.ESTHONIA.Esthonia and Germany. Sir Esme Howard telegraphed [No. 395] on the 12th February that a member of the Esthonian Diet named Tonnisson, who stated that he was its authorised representative, had called on him and his allied colleagues and handed in a written protest against the petition of the Esthonian nobility to the German Govern-ment for armed protection. His written statement declared that until the Esthonian constituent assembly met, which would be on the 28th February, the Diet was the only legal representative or the Esthonian people, it having been properly elected in accordance with the Russian decree of the 12th April, new style, 1917, granting autonomy to Esthonia. It was this Diet which had declared the independence of Esthonia on the 28th November, new style, 1917, at the same time declaring itself the only legitimate authority in the country until the meeting of the Esthonian constituent assembly. This resolution was taken by the Diet in order to save Esthonia from the anarchy prevailing in Russia, and from the dangers of possible operations of war on Esthonian territory. According to M. Tonnisson&apos;s statement the nobility represented only 5 per cent, of the population, Le., the German element, while those who desired independence in accordance with the resolution of the Diet numbered 70 to 75 per cent., the remainder being Maximalists who wished for union with Russia. M. Tonnisson explained verbally that the representatives of the Diet particularly hoped for the support of Great Britain at the peace conference in order to maintain their indepeud-ence either of Russia or Germany. He explained the future policy of Esthonia as follows : The country was almost entirely engaged in dairy farming; before the war its products were mainly exported to Great Britain, and they looked to the United Kingdom as their principal market in the future. They expected to receive most of their requirements from the United Kingdom and America. In order to develop their country they wished to make all their ports free. Besides Riga and Baltischport they have a first-rate port in the island of Osel, which was always ice-free, and if connected with the mainland by ferry boats should become the great emporium for goods to be imported into Russia. This would be an advantage to French, British, and American trade. The higher culture of Esthonia would permit of more orderly administration than was likely to be the case in Russia for many years to come.ROUMANIA.General Averescu. Sir G. Barclay telegraphed on the 11th February [No. 142] that he had had a conversation with General Averescu. He found that the General was definitely opposed to retreat into Russia but that he was not prepared to deliberately accept peace at any price. He proposed to open negotiations to gain time and to ascertain the intentions of the enemy. Sir G. Barclay&apos;s impression was that General Averescu thoroughly believed that he was acting in the interests of the Allies, from whom he was quite willing to accept advice ; he was very anxious to i-remain on good terms with England.
Assurances given to Roumania. Mr. Balfour telegraphed [No. 110] on the 13th February to Sir G. Barclay instructing him to assure the Roumanian Government that this country would maintain energetic action on the battle fronts, and would do her best to settle the conflict between Roumania and the Bolsheviks ; also that all that might be done in the occupied territory should be considered as null and void.TURKEY.Feeling in Regard to the Continuance of the War. An agent has reported that information received from a variety of sources left but little doubt that the economic and military situation in Turkey was engaging the serious attention of the authorities. He had learnt from a Turkish diplomat that the attitude of the Turks in regard to the Brest-Litovsk negotiations had been that if Germany could not secure a general peace Turkey would not continue to fight for such questions as Alsace-Lorraine. Another official had said that if the Germans could not help the Turks to settle their troubles af Brest, the Turks would make their own bargain with Ukrainia and then settle the questions of Palestine, Arabia, &amp;c, with the Entente. From yet another quarter he had heard that the attitude of a party of some weight was that, as the Turkish army had had enough of fighting, if the Germans wished to continue the war, they should do it with their own troops.&quot;Jelal-ed-Din. An agent reports that Jelal-ed-Din, son-indaw of the ex-Khedive, left Switzerland on the 5th February for Constantinople, whither he had been summoned by a telegram sent by Talaat Pasha to the Turkish minister at Berne. It was believed that his journey was connected with the Egyptian nationalist movement.Mission to the Caucasus and Turkestan. The same agent reported that he had been informed that another Turkish mission had been sent recently to the Caucasus and Turkestan ; a suggested explanation was that the Turks were beginning to get accustomed to the idea of the possibility of one or two provinces being lost, and therefore were turning their eyes in other directions.ARABIA.Hejaz.Message from King Hussein. On the 11th February Sir R. Wingate telegraphed [No. 281] that King Hussein had begged him to convey his profound thanks for the expression of the sentiments and policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government towards Arab cause contained in Mr. Balfour&apos;s message of the 4th February [E.R. LIV, p. 5].o

</content>
</cab>
