<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/191/9 images: 97-99</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cp(76) 59COPY NO 5127 July 1976CABINETTHE   140 MILLION CIVIL SERVICE CUTS ANDTHE VEHICLE EXCISE DUTYMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer.        When we discussed the  140 million civil service reductions andthe Vehicle Excise Duty (VED) on 8 July, the Prime Minister said insumming up that, while the majority of the Cabinet favoured abolition,there should be no announcement of any kind about VED for the present.I v/as asked to consider further the question of timing and the possibilityof any alternative proposals for dealing with the   140 million.    Havingconsidered this further it is still my view that it would be wrong to announce an intention to abolish VED, even from a forward date like1979-80.THE PROBLEMS OF ABOLITION2. The arguments which have led me to resist abolition of VED can bebriefly restated as follows.3.        First, abolition means an important narrowing of the fiscal base.The tax this year yields  675 million.   It is likely that, in practice, mostof that would be lost within 2 or 3 years if the petrol duty had to carry itspresent fiscal burden and the VED burden as well.    The need for anincrease of 15p-20p a gallon in the petrol price would prevent us from raising the petrol duty on other grounds for at least 2 or 3 years before and afterVED abolition.    Our problems would be compounded because the british public would regard such a dramatic increase in the petrol price asparticularly odd at the very time we were reaching self-sufficiency on oil production.   And as my colleagues know, all the other European economic community (e.c.) countries have VED as well as petrol taxation.4.        We have been grappling in recent weekB with a need to reduce thePublic Sector Borrowing Requirement (PSBR), and to convince externalobservers that we had a plan for doing so progressively; while at the sametime doing as little damage as possible to employment.    Abolition of VED isa measure to make it more difficult to reduce the PSBR while reducingemployment in a development area (Swansea.) where we have no wish to giveammunition to nationalist supporters.1
5.        Secondly, there are important industrial arguments.    There are twoaspects of this.    The first is the sectoral impact on the car industry.   Anannouncement of an intention to abolish VED, even if after a delay of several years, would encourage the purchase of more small cars where the Britishindustry is not fully competitive.    Because of the delay and the room forargument that would provide it would also introduce uncertainty.    From the papers about the industrial strategy and the medium term development of the economy which we are putting to NEDC for their meeting on 4 August, irisclear that the success of the British car industry is crucial to success in theindustrial strategy as a  whole.6.        The second aspect is the impact which an announcement would have on our efforts on the industrial strategy as a whole.    The plan to increasethe employers1 national insurance contribution has inevitably put a strain onour relations with industry and has thus introduced a new factor since thelast Cabinet discussion of VED.   In two Budget statements I have rejected the proposal to abolish VED an industrial grounds.    If now the Governmentchanges its polity on tikis,    we must expect industry to argue that it canput no faith in the Governments commitment to the industrial strategy.And we can expect no support from the trade union side.    The trade union representatives, including Jack Jones, on the Secretary of State for Industry&apos;stripartite group on the motor industry have declared their opposition to theabolition of VED.7.        These fiscal and industrial considerations are not matters which concern only the Secretary of State for Industry and myself.    They will affect the scale of public expenditure which we can support over the yearsand are therefore of concern to us all.8.        VED abolition could of itself yield only  12 million towards ourshortfall of  45 million on the  140 million target.    Securing a further 22 million for a  2 registration fee to be substituted for VED could notfairly be presented as a manpower saving and would risk severe criticismnot only that the Government had failed to carry out its intention to find thefull  140 million but was attempting to conceal its failure.   Even so, weshould still be short of the target by  11 million.    This does not thereforeappear to be a worthwhile way through.9.        X recognise that our chances of reaching the  140 million target in thenext few months are not good.   Nevertheless, I mink we should not give up our efforts to reduce the  45 million gap at this stage.   The remainingpossibilities may be modest.    They may include some limited savings in1978-79 arising from the 1977-78 exercise, which officials are now engagedin identifying; and some results from a study of the scope for simplificationof the tax and social security systems being undertaken by the recentlyretired Chairman of the Board of Inland Revenue.    These could make a contribution to closing the gap. I2 I
CONCLUSION10.       I do not believe that this is the right time to make a new statement about the  140 million, whether to reaffirm or to modify the target.    ThePress has already reported that we have found  95 million of economies and that the search for the balance continues,    I realise that it would be helpful in relation to the Staff Side to reach finality on the exercise, but theright time to give a further account of it would be in the Public expenditure white Paper in the autumn.   Since the  140 million relates to 1978-79, itwould be better not to link it with the recently announced reductions for1977-78.D WHTreasury Chambers27 July 19763

</content>
</cab>
