<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 3-3</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 3 (47) 7th January 1947

1. Coal and Electricity.

E.Sh. Reason for this new review. Consumption estimates falsified by events.

We estimated in summer tht. electricity wd. use 415.000 p. wk. in summer period.

They used 446.000. For winter : estimate (CEB) 557.000. In 1945, actual was 514.000. 1946 actual was 607.000.

Christmas week 1946. 573.000 t. = 33% in excess of 1945 Xmas week.

Industry : winter ’45 837.000 actual. 901.000 in ’46.

Other factors. Production : apart fr. seasonal trends steady increase since October. From 3.6 m. to 3.9 in wk. before Xmas and wd. have bn. over 4 m. had it not bn. for wagon shortage. In Xmas and N. Year weeks we produced 500.000 + and 400.000 t more than in corresp. weeks of ’45. Good resumption after holidays. Man power 6 or 7.000 down on ’45.

Consumption is therefore cause of crisis – we are using more than we can produce.

Transport. Many wks. ago called attentn. to coal on ground – up to 400.000 t.

And cessation at pits because of transport diffies. That was cause of shortfall before Xmas. Lorries, slow in coming, arriving now when weather prevents use.

Reliance on 10 m. of open-cast. Frustrated by flooding. Dropped fr. 230.000 t. a week to round 100.000.

Electricity now says tht. w’out another 50.000 t. a week (rising poss. to 70.000) they can’t carry on.

Plant will be a diffy. for electricity even if they get the coal.

Nature of revision. Worked out with B/T. details can be settled by officials.

Want decision on principles.

Prodn. over next 6 wks. 3.6 m. a week (deep). May exceed that. Can’t risk it.

120.000 a week (open cast).

Allows for weather, sickness etc.

Deliveries over 6 wks. (P.U.U. and steel rlways. domestic etc. up to full allocations) 3.27 m. [incldg. 600.000 house coal]

Leaving for general industry 450.000 t

Consumptn. of industry : High priority (bricks etc). 250.000} Others. 510.000} 760.000

Normal estimate over 800.000 t. p. wk.

If iron and steel is to be exempt. g.i. will have only 50% of requirements.

If iron and steel is to be cut to 80%, g.i. will have only 58% of requirements.

17

Papers by R.S.C and H.M. First is in line with ideas.

Comment on 2nd. Importing coal. We have E.C.O. to allocate for Europe. If we imported they wd. complain – for Europe is worse off than we are. Also doubtful if we cd. get it fr. U.S. who are already short on deliveries to Europe.

Foreign labour. Been trying for months. N.U.M. haven’t agreed. In genl. have brght. N.U.M. round from hostility and if I’d forced the pace over Poles I wd. have undone this. Finally they rejected my Pole plan by 11 votes to 10.

Electrical Plant. We are short, suffering fr. war-time diversion of effort to munitions. Much done for exports – might have used the capacity for ourselves.

May have to review this policy because increasg. electrical consumptn. here.

Control of Appliances. Pity we didn’t prohibit manuf. or divert to export. Higher purchase tax now wd. differentiate v. the poor – as wd. increase in electricity charges.

L.P. discussions on greyhound racing, football etc. I have always entered a caveat – as on school-leaving age. Need to match production – e.g. houses w’out grates etc. Need for more “planning”.

H.D. Coal Cttee met last night to consider a) M.F. &amp; P. memo. b) M/T. memo.

We recommend –

Para. 8 of memo. Not true alternatives. Both must be adopted. The Power Stations must be kept going. But somethg. also required of electricity on cuts to industry. Officials shd. consider.

R.S.C. Can’t make selective cuts between firms because no switches.

H.D. M/L. proposed 5 day wk. as a relief.

Transport: Para 12. Over-riding priority. Cttee favoured principle : but cdn’t recommend clean-cut priority which might do more harm than good. We shd. however delay iron ore, wh. competes for wagons, when firms have reasonable stocks to cover next month.

We shd. also stop movemt. of surplus Govt. stores (road and rail) for a month.

Clearing coal on ground. V. special effort needed to move open-cast and other and all road haulage requd. to be supplied for this – from general reserve of transport.

We shd. also shorten hauls. Nearby consumers shd. be requd. to take it.

Sea-Transport. To use vessels from frozen Baltic. I will try to meet any diffy. of extra cost.

Austerity locos. 28 now in France. Can M/S. bring them at once to the ports?

18

Switch of loco. capacity fr. export to home use – to be considered.

No special trains for sporting events until further notice.

Coal in transit – increase of ¾ m. This shd. be reduced. Try to get rlway workers to do more, esp. at week-ends to get this moved.

Electricity Appliances. Para 13. No good fiddling with purchase tax – which I took off in first Budget. We recommend stopping supply to home market and diverting it all to export – possibly with a saving for new houses.

P.M. Hardship v. great – what wd. it save.

E.Sh. Increase in domestic consumption is almost 60%.

H.D. Industrial electrical equipment : stop temporarily all conversion to electricity in an existing factory.

Rationing electrical consumption. V. diff. E.Sh. to study it.

P.M. What is domestic stock position?

E.Sh. Increased in summer in London. satisfy. there. We deprived areas nearer to coalfields to bring Ldn. up. Total in Ldn. 2 m. tons in yards.

P.M. Statistics on electrical consumptn. – break-down for lighting, heating etc.

E.Sh. Street-lighting – forced to accept 50% cut, tho’ I wanted to revert to war.

Window lighting – all requests refused.

Hotels – are cutting down.

Street-lighting at 100% means only 900.000 t. p. annum.

A. What is total domestic consumption of electricity.

E.Sh. About 50%.

A.B. Ques of peak load. Thing is to let people know at what hours they shdn’t use electricity. That’s the way to avoid shedding.

E.Sh. Much propaganda being used already.

E.B. Is the real shortage coal or plant. If the former it wd. be madness to stop factories converting to direct electrical drive. That is the way to save coal.

What do you say to public. Save coal or electricity? And if the latter because of coal or plant? Must put this on plant, and say reason is failure to create generating plant during the war.

We must decide what priority requd. to get more plant built for next year.

R.S.C. Electricity a) Generating power + increased consumption. Agree with

19

E.B.

b) Short term. Need to avoid area cuts.

c) Short term. Need to avoid more than extra 50.000 +

coal.

With this degree of shortage – 300.000 t. a week – must have flexible means of ensuring to essential industries and firms more than average.

At present inequality is indefensible, from one area to another.

All trouble now in Lancs and Midlands.

Propose therefore drastic cut for all to yield pool in Regions for urgent cases.

Can’t do it by industries. Northwich Chem. e.g. wd. be in low category but only producer of caustic soda wh. is essential to e.g. glass. Can’t give high priority to all chemical industry.

A 37½% cut on all but coke ovens and steel (17½% cut) wd. give pool of 210.000 t. p. wk. Cd. be allocated to Regions acc. to need.

This wd. enable maximum no. of firms going. Those not given more cd. make a plan on basis of 40% reduction over next 6 wks.

This on basis of allocns. and deliveries over last 4 months have not averaged more than 60%.

G.A.I. Wd. it be useful to encourage industry to adopt 5 day wk. w’out reducing weekly hours. Wd. it mean non consumptn. on balance because working late on 5 days.

R.S.C. Electricity. Firms told to reduce by 2½%. We suggest now a cut similar to that of coal. And sanctions : cut them off for corresponding period in following months.

You shd. cut steel if these cuts are to go on industry because their steel consumptn. will fall.

Conversion to electricity in factories. Can’t do that because all machinery (modern) is electricity dependent.

J.W. Sc. Hydro. Electric. Its “export” will be 9 months late unless priorities given.

U.S. tunnelling machinery : bldg. materials for camps : steel and timber

A.B. Believe this is all based on pessimistic estimate of production.

B/T. plan takes the rap at cost of 1 m. unemployed.

R.S.C. No. Believe output will be much larger. Prodn. is elastic because dependent on manual exertion.

Problem then becomes transport. Concentrate on that.

Must be no shortage of wagons – or extra exertion will mean idleness.

Generating plant. Is most being made of what we have.

Propaganda to avoid domestic use at peak load.

B.B.C. shd. be used for this – daily.

Any idle generating plant in Germany we cd. pinch? 20

H.M. Not only unemployment. But grave effects on production drive.

Manufacturers can’t plan ahead.

Vital therefore to look at long-term as well as short.

Best to work w’in scheme appd. by N.P.A.C.I.

R.S.C. They wd. like a diff. scheme – they didn’t like the last.

H.M. Must maintain iron and steel because of repercussions.

Domestic consumptn. of electricity. 2-part tariff is designed to encourage use. Consider revising it so as to provide for higher rate for consumption above a basic date and period.

Long-term. Must try and get straight over this, certainly before 1950 (because that is year of next election).

Need also to get back to exporting coal.

Wage-structure shd. be overhauled to provide more incentive.

E.B. Spoke in favour of avoiding cuts. Preferred fresh allocations.

E.Sh. But I need 50.000 t a week more for Power stations.

Someone must give it up.

A.V.A. We supplied towns in France from submarines. Cdn’t we make some use of them. We supplied Naples for weeks.

P.M. This shd. be considered.

J.S. Shd. we not revert to daylight saving?

P.M. At this time of year you lose as much in mornings.

J.W. Supported B/Trade plan because more selective : effect on emplt. – amount of coal p. man employed : enables industry to plan.

P.M. Coal: shd. we adopt B/Trade plan, even tho’ expd. in terms of fresh allocations via percentage cuts?

Agreed : in terms of fresh allocations and a pool.

Will be reviewed as we go along. No equivalent cut in industrial user of gas and electricity.

G.T. Will essential firms be kept going.

R.S.C. That is the purpose : para 5.

Electricity: Para 8(1) of E.Sh. memo. approved.

Transport: Coal Cttee proposals appd. in principle.

21

Official Coal Cttee to work out details as above : consider points raised in discussion.

General feeling is against restn on appliances.

Ministerial Coal Cttee to consider : report on long-term fuel problem as a whole.

</content>
</cab>
