<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 6-6</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 6(47). 15th January 1947

1. Road Transport Strike.

G.A.I. Strike Cttee mtg. Prospects good.

Extension in docks : but not v. serious.

P.M. Threat of no newspp. if it continues. If one stops, all will.

G.A.I. Min. Cttee to meet, not before this p.m.

P.M. Let is consider newsprint first – they are mtg. at 3 p.m.

They can run until Saturday.

Home Secretary to preside over Cttee.

Palestine : Long Term Problems.

E.B. Preliminary discussions – exchanges of views – sorry cdn’t consult C.J.

P.M. Take Army memo first.

2. Palestine : Use of Troops.

C.J. Terrorist outrages continue.

Felt tht. military not properly used. Co-opn. of popn. not obtained.

High Commr. thought essentially Police job – cdn’t be done w’out co-opn. of popn.

Military have felt inhibited to some extent.

Police organn. in Pal. has bn. inadequate. Has bn. improved lately. But pro tem. mil. assistance is essential.

Lawlessness (includg. Hagana) diffies. from terrorism (denounced by Hagana).

Mil. shd. not be so used as to alienate popn. – e.g. not for reprisals.

I have impressed on J. leaders gravity of situation if no more co-opn. in handling terrorism.

C.I.G.S. My views completely at variance with H.C.

Proper use of Pol. &amp; mil. cd. bring situation under control.

Robust and effective measures requd.

Co-opn. by popn. cd. be secured by restoring confidence.

Continuous search will produce increasg. results.

Army shd. keep initiatives - then can control.

Agency statement has not produced results : since 4 killed. 64 wounded.

Policy of appeasement twds. condemned terrorists. None such has yet bn. put to death. They say – “you don’t dare”.

32

New directive is based on my draft. Will be effective info interpreted by H.C. in right way.

E.Sh. Meaning of “robust”?

C.I.G.S. Freedom to search at will : retain initiative.

Search needn’t involve hardship.

Restore confidence among law-abiding people.

A.B. That means universal search for persons, documents and arms.

P.M. Universal right to search. Directions to military.

J. Necessary if troops are not to take law into own hands.

H.D. Support Annex as interpreted by C.I.G.S.

But intolerable situation to allow to continue.

A.B. Attitude of Agency.

C.J. Trying : effective with some sections of popn. but not with terrorism.

Directive - agreed with C.O. But wd. be worked in consultn. with H.C. He knows more rigorous mil. action requd. ad interim. But hastening organn. of Police because he believes you can’t root out terrorism finally w’out co-opn. of popn.

P.M. Intention of terrorists is to wreck. Leniency twds. terrorists won’t therefore strengthen Agency. Law abiding popn. is itself being terrorised now.

E.Sh. x/ Wd. you search similarly for Arabs, if Mufti copied these methods?

N.B. Will this policy clear up the arms?

A.V.A. No : because big caches are held by Hagana not terrorists.

C.J. Unlikely we shall clear up all the arms.

P.M. Keep to catching the terrorists.

H.D. Re x/ directive doesn’t distinguish between Arab &amp; Jews.

A.B. More robust action but under directive of H.C.

Directive approved.

3. Palestine : Long-term Policy.

P.M. Preserving order – from mil. angle.

33

C.I.G.S. We cd. handle opposn. from either side alone.

If from both, we shd. have to reinforce. Cd be done from Germany w’out slowing up release scheme.

P.M. Importance of Pal. to our defence.

C.A.S. 3 factors in defence : U.K. sea commns. M/East.

These 3 are inter-dependent, in peace and war : if one goes all are affected.

Not ques. of keeping large forces : but facilities on wh. to expand at a threat.

In peace, presence of troops useful to prevent aggression.

Despatch of force to Basra was v. effective. Can’t in future draw such from India.

Egypt is key posn. in war : Pal. essential to its defence. We go out of E. now : must have posn. in Pal.

These are fundamental principles – unaffected by changes in weapons and constant whatever enemy we have in mind.

H.D. You think it important to retain existg. rights in Transjordan?

C.A.S. T. alone won’t be adequate. But we wd. want to keep it even if we had P.

J. Wd. it be enough if we held mandate (under Partns.) for Holy Places?

C.A.S. No.

H.D. But with Treaty arrangemts. with 2 States.

C.A.S. Yes : if airfield and ports available to us. Not unless.

H.D. Leave out enclave. Nec. that either State shd. ques. Treaty rights. C.A.S. Both.

C.A.S. So long as we cd. the facilities, wdn’t matter wthr. it was 2 States or more.

H.D. And end of tension wd. be advantage.

A.B. What use wd. base be against continuing hostility of Jews?

C.A.S. That cd. be handled. Worse if solution adopted wh. antagonised Arab world – for our trouble wdn’t then be confined to Pal.

From mil. angle, hostility of Arab wd. be worse than that of Jews.

E.Sh. Doesn’t it depend on the enemy? 34

C.A.S. No : wd. be the same if it were Germany.

We have considered problem of security v. any enemy. Our principles are constant. We are thinking long-term, not short.

A. Cd. you develop yr. facilities in Arab Zone alone?

C.A.S. No : neither airfield, commns. or ports.

C.E. What importce. has Med. got for commns. if countries bordering it are hostile.

To make Pal. effective, you must have friendly Spain, Italy and Greece.

C.A.S. Not essential if countries on S. Med. are friendly.

[Exit C.A.S.]

E.B. Repeated apologies for no consultn. Need to get issues focused. Need for discn. w’out heat.

My memo. looks at problem as it affects F.O. – outside.

First, legal issues on U.N. And practical issues too. U.N. is difft. from L/N.

If Arabs and Jews agreed on Partitn. and U.N. faced with it, we cd. get ⅔. tho’ Slavs. wd. prob. vote v. it. But in default of agreement then a) if we favoured Partn. At end war intentn. of Coaln Govt. was to apply partn, before U.N. establd: cd. Have bn. done twds. End of war. But went by default. At outset of this Govt. we tried to get away from 1939 W. Paper. Asked Arabs to allow continuance of 1.500 a month : and then get issue raised as contn to new problem of European Jewry. Jews wd. then have bn. glad to take 4.000 a month. Held conference on M/E. Told my repves. to work on Arab States, w’out raising constitl. issue. Making progress when Truman made his demand for 100.000. Sitn. then became acute. To reduce pressure and involve U.S. we apptd. Anglo. U.S. Commn. Never tried to influence them. Promised to do my best to implement their recommns. But U.S. Govt. did keep in touch with their repves. on Commn. – caused trouble. Was ready when they reported to carry out Rpt. as a whole. Cdn’t accept one in isolation esp. as known tht. money for terrorism is found from U.S.

Further complicn. B. Decln. for Nat. Home never envisaged Jewish State. But B’pool Confce. of Labour Party endorsed J. State.

If we decide for Partn. must get assent of Assembly. If we don’t go to U.N. one or more Arab State will take us there. My impn of temper of Assembly indicates we shdn’t get a majority for it. We wd. be worse off than in our support of Smuts. U.S. and we wd. be alone. Whole temper is v. creatg. religious states : and feeling that Jewry is a

35

religion. U.S. individuals Jews assert J. nationals of U.S. Apart from Hitler persecutn. no kinship betwn. Polish and Fr. Jew.

Against Partn. Arabs wd. put fwd. their plan. Wdn’t be accepted in that form. But Pal. State with equal rights for A. and J. – save tht. J. shdn’t have uncontrolled right of immigration. But they agree to use of Hebrew schools municipal autonomy. But insist they shall preserve majority because it is natural Arab State – Balfour decln. was unilateral.

Can’t trace tht. B. decln. was ever adopted by L/N. All L/N. adopted was mandate, with its condns.

Arabs. wd. also claim early independence – as Syria etc.

That claim in U.N. wd. in my view, …….

Prov. Autonomy turned down w’out much thought.

Arabs rejected it because wd. lead to Partn.

Believe this Plan cd. get ⅔ majority in U.N. if adapted to meet some of strong views on either side.

We haven’t had Jews Plan in full.

Partn. wd. put many Arabs permanently under Jews.

Tried another line – by mtg. Syria : Saudi Arabia etc. So tht. everyone cd. get somethg. But thing has become too rigid.

On horns of dilemma. W’out U.N. cd. go ahead.

Finally, if we impose a solution as mandatory – suppose we have to do it by force. Incident endangering peace : wd. come to Security Council.

Pressed U.S. to admit Jews. T. has put this in his message to Congress.

Have now asked how soon Congress may pass the legn.

For if only some countries (includg. Doms.) wd. do something, it wd. remove the pressure on Palestine.

Had thought a soln. might be found on “transitions arrangement” with a right of secession (to Partitions) in x years. M’while a unitary State (bi national) with a central Govt. Believe then they might never want to separate. For cross-voting shd. develop.

But am told that this approach wdn’t do because of continuing uncertainty wd. produce continued disorder. Wd. still like to try this out in Confce. Wd. avoid refce. to U.N.

Had the idea that U.K. shd. confess incompetence to handle a communal problem.

Ask for colleagues’ views.

C.J. No time to consider this memo. in C.O.

Disturbed by result of Basle Conference.

At end of it asked Ben Gurion what was meaning of that decision. They are confused : but clearly want to negotiate with H.M.G. They

36

sought acceptce. of condns. – e.g. change of policy on immigration. I refused. Pressed him to say if Executives met in Ldn. they wd. be available to discuss with H.M.G. He assented. Consultns. must not be in public. They have promised these talks w’out condns. They will be here on that basis.

Tried similarly to get Pal. Arabs in. They have agreed to attend Conference.

H.C. has been here. Deep sense of urgency for solution. Strain on Forces and adminn. almost intolerable. Threat of break-down. Need for finality.

He himself feels that Partition is the solution.

Diffies. with U.N. These exist whatever solution goes to U.N. The U.N. must come in to this – can’t dodge it. Diffies. there will be similar, whatever solution advanced w’out agreement.

H.L.’s objns. to P.A. Plan. Memo. – wd. like to circulate.

Unitary State with right to recede. Attractive to Jews : but awkward for adminn. Shd. try to get Unitary State if we cd : but wdn’t be accepted by J. unless time-limit v. short.

My own mind moving twds. Partition. Discussed with H.L. and C.I.G.S. who seemed to like it. So do Press and Party.

Agree with E.B. it wd. be difficult because essential to go to U.N. Is the situation there as dangerous as E.B. suggests. If we fail, it wd. be responsibility of U.N.

Ask for opportunity to examine this memo. in C.O.

P.M. What wd. be your next move if U.N. rejected Partn. You wd. have estranged Arab world. What wd. you do?

C.J. U.N. shd. take it on. Alternatively we shd. impose solution ourselves.

N.B. a) Our legal oblign. : Mandate not B. Declaration.

That is all the League adopted – tho’ it includes substance of Decln.

b)Believe P.A. Plan is best. Sitn. in Pal. no worse than was in Canada, S. Africa etc.

But if certain tht. its impracticable and we put Partn. to U.N. there is a chance it might go thro! Can persuade people in U.N.

P.M. Who will be for and against.

Arabs, India against. Probably Slavs too.

E.B. My analysis is : Slavs will oppose Partn. (not because of A. or J.) but because they want to support Arabs (oil) : can’t be any doubt of that.

Doubt if U.S. cd. control Philippines or China.

W’out these States you can’t get ⅔ majority. Someone wd. claim need for ⅔ qua important issue.

N.B. But that decision is taken by majority decision.

37

E.B. But if demanded, cdn’t be refused.

If you are rejected, C.J. says we go on and impose it. But we can’t do that against a ⅔ vote of U.N.

P.M. Is Slav Vote good enough to prevent ⅔ vote v. P.A. Plan?

E.B. Cd. get a combination there, in favour of principle of unitary State with independce.

Arabs might : but cd. get Slavs in favour of principle.

P.M. But if their motions are different, they will find a way of turning you down.

H.D. Discuss a) best solution on merits b) ques. wthr. we can get that solution thro’.

Stress urgency of early decision.

On merits, my view now = Partition is best solution. A. and J. won’t and can’t co-operate. Test : right of J. to immigrate at discretion of J. authy. into some J. area, however small. On that rock all other solutions founder.

On a) I believe there are ways and means, if U.K. and U.S. both back it.

A.B. Support H.D. re early conclusion : and mixing strategy and tactics.

Friendly J. State in Pal. is preferable to Arab base. Permanent and friendly because J. under continuing influence of our friends. If we impose anti J. solution we shall have continuing J. hostility. Initial A. resistance, but once over diffies. at an end.

If India and other Muslim countries are under R. influence, how long wd. they tolerate B. base in A. Palestine.

Alternatives to early solution – disorder, anti Semitism etc. – they can’t be contemplated by Labour Govt.

Our informn. is that there is Arab support for Partition. No unity in Arab world.

Suppose Partn. is rejected by U.N. – authoritative decision and wd. induce change of heart in A. and J.

But will it be rejected if supported by U.S. all Commonwealth and some W. Countries.

Partition for Jews is compromise solution. J. leadership passing to more extreme groups because of delay. W. has given place to Ben Gurion and if he gets no concessn. someone worse. As in S. Ireland.

A.V.A. If you cd. get Partn. by agreement, I favour it.

But differ from A.B. on ques. which is most dangerous side to antagonise.

38

Arabs will be solid : and R. will support them – in order to get behind the U.S. and U.K. position in Persian Gulf etc.

If it is to strategic advantage of R. to win over Arabs : then, after doing our best to settle and failing, we shd. look after B. interests. And as it is vital to retain Arab goodwill, then go for unitary State.

E.Sh. Can’t separate merits from appln. But tht. applies to other alternatives too.

Find it difficult to follow A.V.A. He says R. wd. support A : but on strategic grds. antagonistic to us. If so, we can get no help from R. support of A.

A.V.A. Ques. of substituting our influence for R. in M/E.

E.Sh. What is fair : And will seem to be fair?

Arabs and Slavs. wd. oppose Partn. But full support of U.S. – important because of getting them interested in M/E.

Haven’t accepted Zionism – hoped for assimilation. But no co-opn. achieved.

What is clear, however, is tht. J. want statehood, however small the State.

How are they to get it? Not fr. unitary State.

That will produce only disorder – for years.

Go for Partition. May get thro’ U.N. Must try it.

I can understand terrorists. Remember M. Collins was once “scum” of Ireland.

</content>
</cab>
