<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 14-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 14(47) 30th January 1947

1. Parliament.

W.W. Business for next week.

2. Civic Restaurants Bill.

J.S. I wd. prefer to put back the local option clause. Scottish group wish Scotland to be excluded.

E.B. Try to get it in. Restaurant licence is preferable to vertical drinking.

H.D. Main weight of the Party favours putting this clause back.

Agreed : exempt Scotland.

3. International Trade Organisation.

R.S.C. C.P.44. Don’t want debate until after Econ. Debate. If demand made for debate cd. it be promised at a later date.

P.M. No commitment.

[Exit W.W. Enter H. &amp; F.J.B.

Exit E.Sh. Returned.

4. Greece and Turkey.

E.B. As in memo.

Want to be able to take this up with U.S. They will prob. be ready to take over direct respons. for no. of roads and rlways and do it by direct contract.

Essential, however, to remove our troops : make Greece stand on own feet.

Turkey difft. Has gold.

H.D. Troubled – anxious to help and cd. meet E.B.’s verbal statement.

Re Turkey – no diffy. Anything over outstanding credit they shd. pay for in gold and goods.

F.J.B. Mission costs £110.000.

H.D. Not concerned over that – only supplies.

E.B. Wd. rather pay for mission to train Turks vice using B. man-power in Turkey.

84

A.V.A. Estimates : have bn. trying to shed cost of f. commitments. Cd. un-carry current cost of mission but ask Turks to pay for any expansion.

? Agreed.

H.D. Greece. Gk. Army of 150.000 cd. never be paid for by Gk. economy. Will mean £24½ m. for us in 1947/48 – half our savings on Estimates. Want out subsidy to end with this financial year : originally thought end ’46 wd. suffice.

Wdn’t mind having B. equipment there. But no more cash after 46/47. Why shdn’t then get a loan thro’ Fund – they are members – for development in their own country. We shd. use these organns.

A.V.A. What is extent of burden? The £2 m. cd. be met fr. blocked sterling.

The additional cost of C.I.G.S. enlargemt. wd. I am told, be £14 m. Thought E.B. meant us to get U.S. help with this.

H.D. Don’t think we shd. pay any part of it.

P.M. We shdn’t encourage Greece to keep larger Forces thn. they can afford. What point in raising nos. now beyond what they can keep thereafter.

N.B. Internal econ. posn. has improved. Non work and trade. Except in big cities.

Internatl. loan for reconstn. wd. be right means to assist and v. valuable.

Bank to make long-term scheme for improving roads, ports and supplying small ships – wd. have mil., pol., social effects as well as economic.

Support para. 4. of memo. B. troops and arms have helped to hold situation.

Cd. we approve subject to this – while Intern. Commn. is there, guerrillas and monarchists unlikely to fight : hope they leave observers behind : whole sitn. may therefore change.

E.B. Cd. Cabinet approve in principle w’out committing H.D.

And cd. there be official Cttee to scrutinise Gk. claims – to separate economic fr. mil. expenditure. Much cd. be justified as first which wd. help second. F.O., M/D. and Ty.

H.D. So long as no commitment to any expenditure on Gk. Army after end of this financial year.

E.B. Well : don’t throw away money already spent.

A.B. Must have mopping up opns. in spring. But long-term Army is ques.

General agreement : long-term Greece can’t afford more than

75.000 or so Army.

Agreed: short-term (no precise date : but over the “spring”)

85

approve E.B.’s proposals. But no commitment to spend any money on long-term size of Gk. Forces.

H. What about Gk. Navy.

E.B. It is a supplement to ours. Saves our man-power. Must remember that.

A.V.A. M/D. must look into costs and ways and means. Agreed.

Short-term problem is L.S.T.’s – which cd. be used here for trade. It’s not the Italian cruiser wh. E.B. mentioned.

Agreed also: Gks. to be reminded to go to the Bank.

E.B. Yes: and see its voted for specific purposes.

5. Employment of Women.

G.A.I. Summarised memo.

R.S.C. Same oblign. as young men. Cd. limit range for directive away from home.

Cd. get some of the 25.000 empld. on f’ball pools.

P.M. Wd. you reduce attraction of that emplt.

R.S.C. Once they went into e.g. cotton they wd. stay. And if they knew they were going to be directed into cotton at 20 they wd. go in younger.

E.B. Must have a sanction. Must be ready to prosecute. In way, not too much opposn. because climate of opinion among the women was favourable.

Won’t be now.

Also in way, was universal and comprehensive geographically. Not it’s bound to be localised to some extent.

Politically imposs. now. Bad enough during war – razor edge.

What of the courts. our enforces : storm breaks : you have to let the court down. First serious case of disobedience you are done.

T.W. Hard cases – when do they end?

E.B. In war, also, Man Power Bds. and appeal Tribunals.

Assheton resigned over putting this in, even for war.

R.S.C. Total brkdown of economy if we shirk diff. courses.

E.Sh. If we shirk direction, we must make condns. more attractive.

e.g. C.S. typists who will leave because pay and condns. not good enough.

86

Why do they work in pools – because high wages, bonuses etc.

Needn’t mean increasg. wages all round.

It’s conditions as much as wages. Condns. in cotton are not good. Mining : have resisted suggn. tht. need is for another 50/100.000. There are too many men in the pits. Want better organisation to make fewer men produce more.

This is clue: more attractive condns. and better organn.

Highest pay = millinery and dress-making. Because of diffy. of recruiting the labour.

R.S.C. That means – spiralling up with bigger wages and shorter hours.

Hours in cotton have bn. cut, with reduced prodn.

On seller’s market, no inducement to industry to avoid it.

A.B. That is exaggerated picture.

E.Sh. and I have always said must have wages policy in full emplt.

It is, however, status of industry that counts. Men are going into mining because its status is rising. Labour not so mobile as R.S.C. suggests.

Support E.Sh. general thesis. It’s long term working we must do.

R.S.C. line wd. kill cotton by denigrating its status.

P.M. Not to be supposed something is wrong because people won’t go into cotton.

Look at its history.

Recognise danger of spiral. But why shd. other industries move to preserve relativity with cotton, if cotton’s status is raised.

H.D. I regretfully agree we can’t conscript women.

Was part of a bold scheme. Defended this as part of it. Might have carried this as part of a bold p’mme. But if we aren’t to have that, agree we can’t go on with this item.

Warning re drifting to rapids.

G.A.I. a) Foreign labour. Progress being made –

1.000 in place : 1.000 on way : 5.000 waiting to come.

b) Amenities in factories. Insprs. are not at work on this. And B/T Prodn. Cttee on lay-out etc.

c) Sanctions : war-time reluctance of courts to enforce.

On balance, I don’t recommend Cab. to take this course.

C.E. Cause of present posn. = attitude of schools twds. manual labour.

The attitude of teaching profession must be radically altered.

Hope M/E. will insist on acquaintanceship with machines : processes of skilled industries.

G.A.I. Being done for textiles, mining etc. Shd. be extended.

87

C.E. Surprised at statistics. Wholly unoccupied only 16.000. Wd have thought from personal observn. it was much larger.

J.S. Cd. we explore thro’ Cttees – i) Foreign labour.

P.M. Is a Cttee on that.

y/ ii) restn. of less essential occupns. eg. by sumptuary measures.

A.B. Disappointed at progress with f. labour. Only 1/2.000 in a year since we decided to recruit for dom. service in hospitals.

G.A.I. Delay due to restg. recruitment to that – on grd. tht. they wdn’t come for that if other emplt. available. Over 7.000 have come for private dom. service.

P.M. Beware of cutting off nose to spite face.

N.B. Many sources of female labour abroad. Have a larger pool – the hosp. dom. service will benefit from it.

UNRAA empowered to move, at their cost, people from d.p. camps. Accommn. (para. 11) may be difficult.

G.A.I. Yes : even lodgings.

A.V.A. Are they landed conditionally for a period only.

G.A.I. D.p.’s. : understanding is that they will stay : but work where we send them.

P.M. Reject scheme for compulsion.

( F. Labour Cttee. to explore recruitment of foreign ( labour, esp. single women, the priority for hosp. ( dom. service being w’drawn.

C.E. Warning. This will add to existing surplus of women. Must be ready to admit no. of skilled men. I’m glad to do so.

P.M. We shd. absorb men too. It was our traditional policy: and it shd. be reinstated.

E.Sh. Use industrial psychologists to devise means of employing labour more efficiently.

A.B. Endorsed y/.

T.W. Start thinking of pools.

88

E.Sh. And week-day football. Stopped in Scotland. Cup re-plays lose more prodn. than any compulsion of women wd. add.

E.B. Cd. link that with 5 day week. Trouble will be racing and cricket.

P.M. Let us have a report on this general ques. includg. sports. M.E.P. Cttee. to make report to Cabinet.

H.D. Redn. of distribution costs. Study shows tht. w’out destroying small shops altogether can’t do much. If we limited distn. to big stores and co-ops it wd. force out labour and force down costs.

J.S. Sport etc. = short-term. Distribn. etc. is long-term but more profitable in the end.

A. Don’t lose sight of value of well-constructed factual campaign.

Surely many thousands of women doing nothing.

E.B. We have highest no. of m. women working in world!

[Exit H : F.J.B. N.B.

6. Economic Survey. White Paper.

P.M. Draft to be considered by a few Ministers.

7. Women’s Land Army.

T.W. As in memo.

A. Confession of failure. L.P. 21. envisages increased prodn. in 1948. Some of the sectors for expansion eg. poultry are obvious openings for emplt. of women. Can’t do it if W.L.A. disintegrates. Must ask why it was unpopular. My view : because scheme of opn was wrong. Ladies Cttees – whose condns. were resented by the girls. My personal experience. Can’t run this on existg. basis. But want entirely new basis considered with uniforms etc. to make it attractive to girls.

People i/c weren’t alive to human reactions of young girls.

G.A.I. Spoke in favour of T.W.’s memo.

C.E. Discontent in the Service is main deterrent to recruitment now – e.g. over “terminal” treatment.

Women in control over wrong type.

Favour re-constructing Service.

P.M. Was it a Service at all? Private employment for farmers.

T.W. Was an alternative to Forces.

89

Tried to get some “terminal” recognn. but failed.

No compulsion now as opting v. another form of conscription.

8.000 W.L.A. But 59.000 other agric. workers. Can you give W.L.A. v. much better condns. than the others?

Agreed : (T.W., J.W., A., and G.A.I. to examine report

on means of promoting women’s labour in agriculture.

90

</content>
</cab>
