<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 16-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 16(47) 4th February 1947

1. Fuel Situation : Austin Motor Works.

E.Sh. Not for me to decide allocations of coal.

Posn. worse because weather and transport. 400.000 + open-cast on ground which we can’t move.

This is now producing trouble at the pits.

Lorries now available, but haven’t made goods across more than 10.000 t.

H.D. Had understood they were getting now all the lorries they need.

E.Sh. Yes.

Backlog is being worked off at 10/12.000 t. a week. of v. large in relation to total output – 360.000 t. open-cast on ground.

Recent trouble : weather.

Allocations : worked out by officials. Provided for a pool, disposable by Reg. Cttee.

That shd. help Austins if there is worst case. But are they playing politics.

E.Sh. London area : only one complaint. Shedding of electric load is not due to coal shortage – nor is low gas pressure.

Man-power : increased by 4.000 since beginning of year.

Arranged today to discuss with N.C. Bd. means of getting more coal this year even at expense of long-term reconstn.

P.M. Concentrate on getting men into most profitable posns. this year.

E.Sh. Trouble is with men, not employers (!)

A. Public Opinion. Irritatn. at cutting electricity eg. at meal times. They believe it due to coal shortage. Let it be known that it isn’t.

Announcement of 25% cut in coal for textile industries. If true, deplorable.

Mtg. y’day with Doms. to announce cut in exports to Doms. of textiles.

E.Sh. The cut was on allocation, which they never received.

B/T. operate the scheme.

P.M. They shd. have managed publicity better.

E.Sh. Can’t get this over : electricity eg. facts made plain time and again.

Am collecting the facts re factories out and nos out of work; and will submit memo. to Cabinet colleagues.

Generating plant wd. break down if there were not shedding of load. Let A. go to control room of C.E.B.

Subs. arranged at P’mouth – v. useful. lookg. for mobile generating plant.

96

Considering means of easing domestic load – which is 70% up. Shall submit scheme to L.P. Cttee shortly.

T.W. Absolute priority needed for mining machinery and generating plan. In order to avoid repetition of this next winter.

E.B. Are we not crowding Lancs. too much with light industries? From Manchester. &amp; N. Cheshire to Preston. Creates 2 troubles a) coal is short in Lancs. b) Can’t get the labour in textiles.

Suggest H.D. (DI. Cttee) and G.A.I. shd. consider. May be another Gt. West Road.

H.D. Not a development area – save small area round St. Helen’s. No special pressure therefore. Diffy. is Merseyside, where much unemplt. and a Council wh. is both Conservative and corrupt.

Real trouble = in war too much munitions put into Lancs. Women like those condns. better than cotton. But no attempt to push new ind. development in Lancs apart fr. Merseyside.

2. Socialisation of Ruhr Industries.

E.B. Diff. problem. But I mustn’t before Moscow do anything implying central control of these industries. Originally proposed bigger Land for Rhine/Westphalia on this a/c.

Have now French plan. And R. criticising us for not socialising.

If the Länder Govts. not in this at all, will cause gt. suspicion.

Anxious tht. custodians be divided as all Länder Govts.

This is ques. of high policy qua Moscow.

Powers of custodians will be small : won’t prejudice eventual ownership and control. Want it so arranged as to imply tht. policy of H.M.G. is to attach the industries to the Land Govts concerned.

European neighbours of G. all opposed to any central G. control.

Shan’t concede internatl. control of indies. in this area unless I get it for all G. industries.

J.B.H. Posn. now (coal and steel). We have taken them into control of C.-in-C. and we have said we shall socialise. Agreed they shall be G., not international. Method : suggn. was appointmt. of custodians. I have proceeded on assumptn. this was all we intended – until we knew wthr. ownership wd. go eventually to Land or central Govt. Assumed custodians wd. be on Zone basis : nominees not drawn a single Land.

I proposed 3 for each industry (S.PD., D.U., T.U.) for whole Zone.

E.B.’s plan wd. give one Land Govt. control over industries throughout Zone. And this a reactionary Govt. Wd. antagonise all sections of G. opinion.

97

Purpose of proposal. To reduce efficiency of these industries – eg. Annex A. We have reduced G. industrial efficiency, artificially, by our reparations policy.

P.M. This is misreading of the para. Not intended to reduce efficiency of the industry, but reduce strength of a central G. govt.

E.B. We shd. consult B. coal and steel indies. at an early stage.

J.B.H. Also passage re avoiding competn. with B. export trade. B/in copy. No.55. This surely is inconsistent with our main policy of putting G. on her feet. We shall antagonise G. opinion and drive left into hands of Communists. Wd. prefer to wait until we know into what Govt. we can safely entrust these industries. Thus propose custodian be on a Zonal basis – as the existing control by C-in-C. is.

Proposed in memo. tht. Advisory Council be on Zonal basis. They will be more closely in touch than the 3 custodians. If that can be admitted, can’t we do the same for custodians.

E.B. Exports. U.K. Dpts., tho’ willing G. shd. have some export trade, want to be careful lest by B. capital we create a G. export trade damaging to our own. Must avoid recreating a Germany which will fight another war. Still greatest potential danger is G. Not sure our adminn. there is sufficiently alive to this risk.

Apptmt. of custodians won’t prejudice eventual decision merely because they are drawn fr. area in wh. industries are mainly concentrated. Advisory Cttees provide for wider contact. But custodians imply ownership : don’t want implication tht. this goes wider than Land Govt.

E.Sh. J.B.H. assumes our policy to be to help reconstitun. of G. industry for benefit of Germans. That wd. be unwise approach. Must have some restoration: but mustn’t put in hands of central G. Govt. However to use Ruhr industry for aggression or for export policy on Shacht lines.

T.W. Dilemma. H.D. wants to escape cost. Our mil. adminn. needs improvement in social and economic condns.

E.B. This looked after by limits set under Fusion agreement.

J.B.H. We have smashed much of G. industry by repns. policy. Had assumed that what remained was to be allowed to be efficient and to export.

E.B. Fusion agreement covers that. Custodians don’t affect it.

J. Ques. is : are we to adopt a course which antagonises G. or one which antagonises French and other Allies.

98

J.S. Don’t try to restrict G. exports too much to protect interests of F.B.I. Some G. competn. is inevitable a) to escape financial burden of G. b) to ruin world economy.

One of greatest diffies. is restoring world food supplies in loss of manufactd. goods fr. G. and central Europe. Our long-term interest is in expanding trade.

H.D. Ques of balance. But don’t accept a F.B.I. view.

eg. pre-war Cartels. no healthy competn. there.

For near future, E.B.’s line is obviously right. Don’t do anything now to imply we are committed to central control of G. industries.

E.B. Don’t put me in a posn. to have it said at Moscow we are seeking to integrate G. economy with our own.

I haven’t dropped intern. control. It broke down because Fr. wanted to detach Ruhr. Fr. plan now coming round to our original plan. R. may favour that too. If it came to intern. control, it wd. have to last for years.

P.M. Least prejudice to future decision is to keep to Land Govts – because these are only Govts. we now have : there is no Zone Govt.

Agreed.

J.B.H. Advisory Cttees. Iron and steel control already functioning – wh. operates the industry under our own guidance. Will we have to abolish this.

I intended the Cttees to have something more than advisory functions.

E.B. Willing on this to meet views of Control Office. Will discuss.

H.D. Custodians shd. be appointed at once.

E.B. I’m responsible for delay. needn’t be longer delayed.

J.B.H. Names to be finally settled.

3. Russia : Anglo Soviet Treaty.

E.B. Read message from Marshall.

P.M. Not v. definite.

A.V.A. Means tht. U.S. wants to adhere to 4 Power basis. If we try for that, we shall have U.S. support.

P.M. Anyway, I can release my telegram.

</content>
</cab>
