<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 27-27</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 27(47) 11th March 1947

1. South Persia.

Mc.N. As in memo.

P.M. Try to persuade them v. it.

Agreed : no statement if G/India persuaded not to have one.

Elections going v. well.

P.L. India’s consent to be secured?

McN . Yes.

H.D. Approach them : but hope they won’t dissent.

P.L. No reason to suppose they will.

C.A.S. Force already in operation.

But hope announcement won’t suggest w’drawal because mil. weakness.

Alternative : asked C. in. C. work somethg. out. Can’t be as quick or efficient or precise as before – also more limited in deal.

Mc.N. We wd. base w’drawal on fact no longer any pol. unrest.

We shall watch timing : consult all Dpts.

A.V.A. Remember there is a risk eg oil.

Remember it will be larger strain on air provn.

N.B. Lift from Palestine : pretty quick.

Doubt wisdom of public announcement.

Mc.N. Not commd. to announcement – only ask for authy. to make it if need be.

Genl. view = against announcement.

P.L. Prob . Govt/India will think it necessary.

[Exit C.O.S. &amp; Serv Ministers

2. Reform of Legal Procedure.

J. Type of ques : double appeals : separate Admy. and Divorce Divn. : leave to A.G. to bring up ques. : reduce costs of litigation.

Denning Cttee shows lawyers must do this because laymen don’t know details.

149

Hence propose technical w. parties under wider Cttee. – under both Cttees.

R.S.C. Govt. role - eg. Ty. Solr. shd be on first Cttee.

J. Agreed.

[Enter Nathan.

Suggd. I shd. select personnel of Cttees.

Shall encourage interim Rpts for quick action.

G.A.I. First Cttee. 13 : Second 12. Keep it the same (TUC) in both cases. Agreed.

J. will consult G.A.I. on names.

Agreed.

3. Air Navigation Bill.

N. Crown Procdgs. Bill left gap qua. civil aviation. There is protn. v. action for nuisance in respect of aircraft in the air, but not on the ground. No doubt because airports were Govt. property : so protected hitherto.

Awkward if prevented by injunction : nuisance. [Enter E.Sh.

Must go in this Bill, however. Must support it.

J. O. in. C. not liable to be laid.

Govt. under internatl. oblign. to provide airports – designated internationally.

J. Agrees tht. law shd. be altered if at all by Air Nav. Bill not Crown Procdgs. Bill.

Mil. aircraft protected because C.P. Bill doesn’t apply to them.

We have to provide for internatl. aircraft.

Regs. wd. cover times of day : extent of running engines.

Don’t want to go beyond minimum regun. for safe opern.

J. Critics will say : you will give leave w’out enquiry : and leaving residents etc.

But in view of Stevenage I’m ready to back this Clause.

A.G. May be some trouble in H/C.

[Exit N.

[Enter Barnes

150

4. Electricity Bill : Compensation to Local Authorities.

P.M. A.M.C. deputn. made little enough fuss over this. But we decided last time we wd. do somethg.

E.Sh. Cd. get away with a smaller sum (£5 m.) based on severance. Distribute on basis of units consumed – more equitable than capital expenditure.

This wdn’t prevent M/T. adoptg. latter method.

B. Willing to come into line on this: if confined to severance.

[Exit Barnes.

5. Coal : Five Day Week : Imports of Coal.

G.A.I. Has E.Sh. said this was accepted “by the Govt”

E.Sh. Yes : in principle, subject to satisfy. condns.

A.V.A. This means tentative statement only by Govt.

H.D. Opposn. know there is disagreement on Bd. on ques. wthr. 5 day wk.

will secure required output.

But trouble on N.C.B. over this.

Our fact-finding enquiry in Miny. showed effect as loss of output, but took no a/c of psychol. effect on effort by the men.

Now N.C.B. are negotiating with the men. Have agreed on certain condns. eg longer stints. Outstanding ques. a) appln. to surface workers N.C.B. against this. b) Wthr. 6 days pay on basis of arbitrary figure or average rate for district.

Some members of Bd. now say, irresp. of condns. can’t effect the output on 5 day wk. For no guarantee the condns. will be observed.

Reid and Gridley both resigning mood : persuaded both to hold their hands. They won’t accept the response for 5 day wk. But they both say tht. if Govt. say publicly its essential Bd. will accept that and try to apply it.

Arguments other way - a) men may take 6th day off w’out pay.

b) 6 day wk. deterrent to recruiting.

R.S.C. No : we are asked to say will there be increased output if 5 day wk.

E.Sh. Say – “last year we said no objn. in princ. provided satisfy. condns.

x/ under negotns. with N.C.B. no final result reached”.

R.S.C. Doesn’t answer ques. do we think output can be secured with 5 day wk.

151

P.M. Only real chance is to get miners to offer to delay its appln.

G.A.I. Full 5 days wd. get us more than theoretical 6 days.

Saty. not a profitable day because chasing up.

Can I use these arguments?

E.Sh. No : because even with 50% absenteeism they do produce some coal on Sat.

Condns. = no 6 day pay unless 5 full shifts worked. And if 5 full shifts effectively worked we can get the output. The condns. are the essential point.

P.M. shd. put it to N.U.M. tht. its up to them if they get 5 day week.

H.D. G.A.I. shd. stall and let Tories shout. P.M. is about to see N.U.M.

x/ is the right line.

R.S.C. Last year’s statement qualified by W. Paper since no redn. of hours w’out miners prodn. Now under discussion.

P.M. Yes : but don’t imply we’re running away fr. what we’ve said.

Imports for stock piling.

R.S.C. Say no theoretical objns. Shall do it if we can when we see how summer output goes.

E.Sh. U.S. have export surplus. And U.S. shipping to bring it. Might get 200.000 tons p. month. V. poor stuff.

Will submit report to Fuel Cttee.

H.D. Wd. mean cuts on rest of import p’mme.

P.M. Must balance pros and cons.

Agreed : E.Sh. to provide A.V.A. with formula.

</content>
</cab>
