<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/5/0 images: 69-69</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 91 (47) 27th November, 1947

1. Parliament

Business for next week.

Budget

R.S.C. Advertising. Propose to drop this proposal – on basis that newspp. will offer much of their space for Govt. advertisements.

Parliament

H.M. Query arises over Ullswater’s memoirs re position if H/L. merely fail to pass. We are examining this. J. Cd. provide tht. Bill shall be deemed to have bn injected by H/L. if not

passed by them 3 days before end of Session. But wd. draw attentn to

defect in Parlt. Act &amp; might cook this Bill.

Cabinet Meetings

Can cab. meet otherwise sometimes?

P.M. Mondays at 11.0 &amp; Thursdays – as from week after next.

A.B. Cttee Tues. Wed. Thurs. on my 2 Bills.

Leakage of Information.

H.M. To-day’s D. Worker. Will take this up with Liaison Cttee &amp; Party –

say we are determined to find out who it is &amp; shall w’draw the

Whip.

2. Parliament: Motion about Journalists.

A.V.A. E.B.’s speech – to be revealed during C.F.M. is v. serious. Treason rather than privilege.

E.B. All statements at Party mtgs. go to Soviet Embassy.

H.M. Issue: this isn’t privilege &amp; action must therefore be w’in courtesy

invitns by Parlt. to journalists.

R.S.C. Prefer 2nd formula. “Proceed against” suggests procgs.

T.W. Is it “offered” payment? Better “made”.

369

P.M. Then you exclude offering: would apply only to agent who paid.

Enter C.K.

3. Requisitional Land &amp; War Works Bill

H.M. Anyway, 2nd part doesn’t arise unless M.P. has bn. found guilty.

Approved. 2nd formula.

A. What is area of privilege? (Para. 6)

P.M. This is ungentlemanly conduct short of privilege.

[Exit W.W. R.S.C. As in memo.

R.S.C. Doesn’t arise: ques only of amount payable on dilapidations at end of

lease. Wasn’t entitled to anything at beginning.

Otherwise, we open door to endless claims re

A. Terminal. Wd. ceiling be added to compensn entitled to at beginning.

G.T. Diffy. tht. lease is coming to end.

R.S.C. That wd. affect, not amount of compensn, but division between tenant &amp; ground l’lord.

G.T. E.g. house with 15 yrs. to run: requisitioned for 7 yrs. Benefit if its restored goes not to tenant.

R.S.C. You’ve paid rent for the 7yrs.

A.V.A. Wd. also save them expense on dilapidatn.

C.K. Diffies: Houses requd &amp; turned into flats. Owner might want re-instatmt.

R.S.C. That wd. be a waste: &amp; compn is not on basis of re-instatement.

Compn must be based on values lost.

A.B. Land?

R.S.C. Not covered at all.

Must be done – to continue Service requisitioning.

A.B. Don’t say compensn for lack of access to keep land in good condn. foreshore.

A.W. Betterment of land requisitioned. Will this prejudice our rights to

recover betterment?

370

R.S.C. No.

A.V.A. No service diff. over rent. Argument over terminal compn.

But Service oppn w’drawn.

Memo. approved. [Exit C.K. Enter J.S.

4. Food Prices.

T.W. Ag. rents up by only 10% - as v. this 60%

J.S. No strong views. All methods will hurt. All give us some margin re

price increases.

Tea: v. unpopular, but wd. de-subsidise entirely - &amp; we have bn.

subject to blackmail by export taxes in India &amp; Ceylon.

H.M. 2oz. a week ration: money involved for family isn’t large.

N.B. Pakistan may impose additional tax.

A.B. Wasn’t here at Budget Cab. But don’t like this middle course

Sentimental speeches re o.a. pensioners.

T.W. £70/75m. must be found. Shdn’t we spread it over wide area than this.

Butter is below pre-war price. Bacon price increase on top of

reduced ration. Put bacon up a little &amp; put the rest on butter &amp;

milk.

G.A.I. Effect on c/living index: 101 to 107. Increased 3.27. Sugar price

increase = beer = purchase tax = will involve some increase

anyway. At least 106. [Food section alone from 101 to 112].

Then coal, gas, etc., next month.

Four wage rates still linked to index – boot/shoes=coopering:

waterproofs. Not important in themselves = but will provoke

demands fr. others.

R.S.C. Cab. authd H.D. to fix &amp; announce ceiling of £392m.

To do this, there must be some increase in food prices.

Food = 3.27 rise in index. About 3 points wherever you do it.

I wd. prefer a spread. Table B seems better to me.

Tea is politically sensitive.

Must mean 5½d p. wk. &amp; about 3 points on index, however you vary it.

N.B. Import taxes on tea shdn’t be met from subsidy. But we shd. tackle

that in financial negotns.

T.W. Table B. But more on eggs &amp; less on bacon.

P.M. When?

371

J.S. V. soon, if we are to keep under 392 this fin. year.

R.S.C. Don’t care – for a week or so.

E.B. Understood we were at 392: not, as now, over 400.

Cdn’t R.S.C. accept 400 as a ceiling.

If we increase tea prices, wd. like to increase ration.

What about the subsidies on agric. prodn? Shd. prefer to see these

increases spread over all subsidies.

x/ viz. 400m and spread evenly over all.

R.S.C. a) 392 = rate for an annual total.

Commd to sticking to that rate. Bef. end/year paymts. made will exceed 392.

b) Ag. subsidies. 26m out of 390. To reduce those wd. merely increase price demanded by farmers.

Any redn of subsidies will have to go back on price.

Timing – fatal to do this at Xmas. Right time is approachg. spring.

Much easier to do it then.

Further: negotiating now with Canada: may be able (if we Micawber

for another four months) by the spring to do better. Hope for

some increase in tea ration by then, also. Sugar stocks also a sore

point. Some little adjustment: so that when prices rise we give

more in quantity.

T.W. Prices fixed in Aug. on 4yr. p’mme. Took a/c of subsidies.

Wd. mean re-opening the 21/8 announcements.

E.B. T.U. leader: makes agreemt. re wages = 2 mos. later value of that money is changed. This memo. seeks to save £70m: &amp; will cost £4/500m in wages. Is that good business?

And 1/- on wages comes to 2/- or more by time it reaches consumers.

Appeal to R.S.C. to consider again – on basis of x/.

A.B. Sugar – Party is v. angry.

Ready to agree to sacrifices if really necessary.

But price increases will cause disturbances in industry after industry.

These increases are bound to provoke a series of wages demands.

Maximum friction – unofficial strikes.

Timing = support E.B. Psychol. effect of winter.

Strikes are in the air because France.

Increases, if any, shd. be in spring Budget.

R.S.C. Wasn’t supposing these wd. all go on at once, with full publicity.

But before next Budget we must stabilise expendre on food subsidies.

Have told Ty. to think of stabilisation at round figure of 400.

Ready to re-consider list on Basis B.

May M/F. and I re-consider, in light of discussion with a view to getting these on gradually over next month? 372

J.S. Bound to make some increases. But want to link announcemt. with improvemt. in quantity. At this level. cuts are worse than price increases. Want therefore to press for Canadian bacon &amp; eggs &amp; sugar: &amp; let price increases accompany that.

{ Discussion adjourned: M/F &amp; R.S.C. to produce a wider

{ table B.

{ Some to be filtered in.

{ Jam with the powder – increased ration.

G.T. Calories. Don’t mean anything to most people. Stop talking about it.

A.V.A. How much relates to dollar expenditure.

R.S.C. None.

373

</content>
</cab>
