<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/165/11 images: 169-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;5 government cp(72) 111 COPY NO23 October 1972CABINETHOUSING FINANCE ACT - DEFAULT PROCEDUREMemorandum by the Secretary of State for wales, I was invited to set in train the initial default procedure against thefive local authorities in Wales who are refusing to implement the housing finance Act, and to make a further report on the situation towards the endof October (CM(72) 43rd Conclusions, Minute 5).2. Letters were sent to the five local authorities on 5 October tellingthem that I was considering making default orders and would have regardto any representations they made within the next month.3. The only reply I have yet received is from Bedwas and MachenUrban District Council (UDC) setting out their reasons for refusing to implement the Act, and inviting me to appoint a Housing Commissioner.4. Merthyr Tydfil County Borough and Cwmbran UDC will have heldmeetings to consider my letter before we discuss this memorandum, andI hope to be in a position to let the Cabinet know their reactions during our discussion,    Vaynor and Penderyn Rural District Council (RDC) are meeting on 26 October,5. Ystradgynlais RDC have asked me to receive a deputation to discussmy direction that they should make a 90p increase instead of the 65pincrease they had sought.    I have agreed to see them and hope they may decide to implement the Act.DEFAULT ORDERS6,        I propose after 5 November to make default orders against those authorities who have still not taken steps to implement the Act,    In these orders I will give them 14 days in which to remedy their default.
SUBSEQUENT ACTION7.        I propose that if, after the time limit in the default order hasexpired, there are still recalcitrant authorities (as I would expect), Ishould proceed to the appointment of Housing Commissioners.    I amat the moment considering the availability of possible appointees.G.        I remain convinced that, as far as Wales is concerned, therewill be no advantage in my directing an extraordinary audit.    The moststubborn authority is likely to be Merthyr Tydfil and, I am sure, from rexperience of the school milk issue, that it would simply expose us toridicule if an extraordinary audit were ordered on this occasion.    TheCouncil will court the penalties which might follow, and will in any casewelcome the chance of procrastination and the possibility of legal proceedings, which they would be given.    My main purpose mustbe to make sure that the benefits of the Act are enjoyed by tenantsas soon as possible, and I believe I can best achieve this by appointingCommissioners.    The recalcitrant authorities have all asked forCommissioners to be appointed and have expressed willingness toco-operate with them,9.        I seek my colleagues&apos; agreement to the action proposed inparagraphs 6 and 7 of this memorandum.P J M TWelsh Office23 October 1972


</content>
</cab>
