<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 83-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1957SECRET Copy No.C.G. (57)10th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 11th February, 1957, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. The Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P.,  Secretary  of  State  for  theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 1-8).The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
contents minute no.                                       Subject page 1 Farm Price Review    .................. 32 Local Government Finance   ...      ...      ...      ...... 43 Anglo-American Relations    ............... 4Bermuda Meeting.4 Israel     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 55 Suez Canal      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 56 Jordan   ...      ...      ......      ...      ...      ... 57 Northern Ireland        ...      ............... 6Terrorist Activities.8 Parliament       ..................... 69 Oxford Roads..................... 6
Farm price review.(previous reference:Conclusions,CM. (56) 23rdMinute 6.)1. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Ministerof Agriculture (C. (57) 28) and the Chancellor of the Exchequer(C. (57) 29) about the forthcoming annual review of farm prices.The Minister of Agriculture said that the Governmenfs originalobjective of a total volume of production, which was 160 per cent,of the pre-war level, had been achieved and it was now increasingly important, in the context of a total agricultural output which amounted in value to some  1,200 millions a year, to determineindividual price guarantees on a basis which would discourage theproduction of some commodities and encourage the production of others. The farmers&apos; confidence in the Government, which the new system of long-term assurances had done much to restore, would again be shaken if the first settlement to be made under the new system was restricted to the minimum permissible award and if theannual review of prices was not conducted in such a way as to providethe opportunity for the farmers to recoup increased costs to areasonable extent. Moreover, the net income of the farmers, thoughadequate in the aggregate, concealed a decline in the income of thesmall farmer which a satisfactory settlement must take into account.The rise in farmers&apos; costs which was relevant to the determination of the level of guarantees for 1957-58 amounted to some  38 millions.This figure was broadly in line with cost increases in the twoimmediately preceding years which had attracted settlements of 28 millions and  25 millions respectively; and, while the forth-coming review must have full regard to the needs of the exchequer at the present time, the farmers might reasonably expect to recoversome  15 to  16 millions. As regards the higher cost of petrol and oil, the Government would be exposed to a charge of breach of faith if this item was not taken into account, unless it could be statedcategorically that the increased tax would be discontinued at somespecified early date.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that two-thirds of thenet income of the farmers was drawn from public funds. The costof Exchequer assistance, amounting now to  225 millions, would rise to  233 millions in the forthcoming year on the basis of thepresent guarantees. At a time of acute financial difficulty there wasno justification for giving still further assistance to farmers. the excessive production of milk and eggs was already embarrassing, andthe farming industry was not alone in being required to meet rising costs by a corresponding increase in efficiency. There was evidencethat, of the increased costs which would arise for consideration in the forthcoming review, the farming industry had already beenable to absorb between  12 and  15 millions; and the new systemof capital grants represented a further measure of Exchequerassistance which must be taken into account. In present circum-stances the settlement should be based on the minimum permissibleaward. Provided that this principle was accepted, the increased costof petrol and oil might be taken into account in the calculation, onthe understanding that a compensating adjustment would be madeat the next annual review if the increase in the tax on petrol and oil had by then been withdrawn. On this basis a figure of  8 millions would represent the minimum permissible award, and the government&apos;s intention to impose a settlement at this figure shouldbe made plain to the farmers at the outset of the negotiations.The Home Secretary said that farmers in Great Britain werehoping to achieve a settlement based on a figure in the region of 10 to  12 millions, and farmers in Northern Ireland were expectingslightly more. While the minimum award of  8 millions should go some way towards satisfying them and retaining their confidence inthe Government, it would be regarded as a breach of faith if no account was taken of the increased cost of petrol and oil.The Secretary of State for Scotland said that a settlement at 8 millions,&apos;while it would entail no breach of faith, would fail to51159-10 B 2
satisfy farmers in Scotland. They had suffered disproportionate lossas a result of the poor weather in the previous summer and, althoughthe Agriculture Acts imposed no obligation on the Government inthis respect, it was difficult to convince the farmers that lossesresulting from poor weather were not a factor to be taken intoaccount.It was the general view of the Cabinet that, in view of the gravity of the financial situation, a settlement should be sought, and ifnecessary imposed, on the basis of the minimum permissible awardunder the system of long-term assurances after taking into account the increased price of petrol and oil. The Minister of Agricultureundertook to consider how the Governments policy could best be presented in the forthcoming negotiations and to submit for the cabinets consideration a schedule of guarantees relating to an award of  8 millions.In further discussion The Commonwealth Secretary said thai-there was a danger that unduly high support prices for milk and wheat would jeopardise our trading relations with New zealand and the favourable trade agreement we had recently concluded with australia. The Cabinet were, however, informed that, althoughcosts had risen, there was no intention of increasing the guaranteed price for milk, and it was hoped that the production of milk wouldbe correspondingly discouraged. It would be necessary, for technical reasons, to raise the guaranteed price for wheat by Ad., but costs hadalready risen by more than that amount.The Cabinet  (1) Agreed that in the forthcoming review of agriculturalguarantees for 1957-58 the objective should, in principle,be the minimum permissible award under the system of long-term assurances.(2) Invited the Minister of Agriculture to give further considera-tion to the presentation of the Governments policy inthe forthcoming negotiations and to circulate to theCabinet a schedule of guarantees relating to an award of  8 millions.LocalGovernmentFinance.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 9thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Local Government (C. (57) 30) covering a revised draft announcement of the conclusions emerging from the Governmentsreview of local government finance.In discussion the draft announcement was approved subject tocertain textual amendments.The Cabinet- Authorised the Minister of Local Government to make astatement in the House of Commons in the terms approved in their discussion.Anglo-american relations.BermudaMeeting.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 4thConclusions,Minute 8.)3. The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that it had nowbeen finally agreed that President Eisenhower and he should meet in Bermuda for discussions from 21st to 24th March. The PrimeMinister of Canada had suggested that he might thereafter visitOttawa; but, as this would involve flying over United States territory,he had thought it better that this meeting should also be held in bermuda. It had now been arranged that Mr. St. Laurent would come to Bermuda for discussions immediately after the talks with president Eisenhower were over. These arrangements would be announced in the House of Commons that afternoon.The Cabinet-Took note of the Prime Ministers statement.
Israel. 4.   The Foreign Secretary said that he had been considering, in(Previous consultation with the Prime Minister, how best to avoid a vote in reference: the United Nations on the application of sanctions against Israel.C.C. (57) 8th It now seemed less likely that this situation would arise. For in conclusions, official circles in Washington there was a growing recognition that minute 3.) the application of sanctions against Israel would be a dangerous precedent; and the Canadian Government were considering thepossibility of framing a more constructive resolution.The Prime Minister said that the realistic solution was for Israelto withdraw her troops from the Gaza Strip and from the Gulf ofAqaba simultaneously with the arrival of United Nations forcescharged with responsibility for securing those areas from attack by either side. If we could make it plain that we favoured a constructivesolution on these lines, either by bringing forward a resolution ofour own or by sponsoring a Canadian resolution, the Arab states would be more likely to accept without reprisal our refusal to support a resolution imposing sanctions against Israel. In that event, if asanctions resolution were moved, it should be possible for us to abstain from voting on it.In discussion there was general agreement with the views expressed by the Prime Minister.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to ascertain the views of theUnited Kingdom Representative at the United Nations onthe question whether it would be tactically advantageous forus to sponsor a constructive resolution on the lines contemplated by the Canadian Government.Suez Canal. 5.   The Foreign Secretary said that it now seemed possible that(Previous        the Suez Canal might be opened for the passage of small ships by reference:       the beginning of March.   It was therefore becoming increasinglyC.C. (57) 8th     urgent that a satisfactory arrangement should be made for theConclusions,     payment of dues.   It now seemed clear that the United StatesMinute 3.)       Government would oppose any interim system for the payment ofdues which would prejudge the question of ownership of the Canal.This was reassuring; and the responsibility for pressing for an early settlement of this question could be left, for the present, with theUnited States Government and the Secretary-General of the united nations.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Jordan. 6.   The Foreign Secretary said that, in pursuance of the(Previous        Cabinefs decision of 7th February, H.M. Ambassador at AmmanReference:      had been instructed to press our claims for over-flying and air-stagingC.C. (57) 9th     rights in Jordan. It now appeared that the Jordan Government were conclusions,     ready to concede these rights, which were at least as much in their minute 1.)       interests as in our own; but they were reluctant, for political reasons,that any public announcement should be made.   We for our partwere anxious to get an early agreement on the other questions a tissue, so as to avoid a unilateral denunciation of the Treaty byJordan.   Would our needs be sufficiently met if the agreement onover-flying and air-staging rights were handled separately from thegeneral Heads of Agreement on the Treaty and covered by a separateexchange of letters which, for the time being, would remain secret?
The Minister of Defence said that, so long as a firm and bindingagreement was reached, it was not essential that it should immediately be made public. He doubted however whether it would be possibleto avoid publication for any length of time; for we should certainly be asked, as soon as the negotiation of the main Agreement had beencompleted, what arrangements we had made for the continuance ofour over-flying and air-staging rights.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange for the ForeignOffice to consider, in consultation with the Ministry ofDefence, whether means could be devised of securing our essential requirements for over-flying and air-staging rights in Jordan consistently with the desire of the jordan government that these concessions should be kept secret forthe time being; and took note that the results of this furtherconsideration would be reported to the Prime Minister forhis approval.NorthernIreland.TerroristActivities.(previous reference:CC. (57) 6thConclusions,Minute 6.)7. The Commonwealth Secretary recalled that on 1st february the Cabinet had agreed that further representations should be madeto the Dublin Government about the organisation of terroristactivities in Northern Ireland. A General Election was now howeverproceeding in the Irish Republic; and he and the Home Secretarywere agreed that these representations should be delayed until theresults of the Election were known.The Cabinet-Agreed that the question of making further representationsin Dublin about terrorist activities in Northern ireland should be reviewed again when the results of the election in the Irish Republic were known.Parliament. 8.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Oxford Roads. 9. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Minister of Local Government (C. (57) 25) about a motion tabled by reference: Lord Beveridge, for discussion in the House of Lords on. (56) 52nd 13th February, proposing the appointment of a Royal Commission to conclusions, consider the best means of preserving the amenities of Oxford whileMinute 5.) satisfying the community&apos;s need for adequate communications and services.The Lord President said that the terms in which this motion wasframed would permit discussion not merely of the proposed roadacross Christ Church Meadow, but also of the whole problem ofOxford as a major centre of communications. Government spokes-men would probably have little support if they attempted to resist the appointment of a Royal Commission or were reluctant toundertake that the Government would in the meantime suspend any action which might prejudice the Royal Commission^ Report. Itwas unfortunate that, when this subject was last considered by theCabinet, other possible solutions of the traffic problem in Oxfordapart from the road across Christ Church Meadow e.g., the
construction of a new shopping centre at Cowley and the completionof the outer ring road had not been brought to the attention ofMinisters. Nor had they been made aware that the Road research laboratory had not been consulted about the road across theMeadow and that Sir Patrick Abercrombie had expressed the view, in opposition to Dr. Thomas Sharp, that the completion of the outerring road would provide a more satisfactory solution to the problemthan would the proposed road across the Meadow. The earlier decision taken by the Cabinet in favour of the road should not,therefore, be regarded as final; and Government spokesmen in the debate in the House of Lords should, if possible, be free to make itclear that, even if the City Council submitted detailed proposals forthe construction of such a road, the Government were not bound toaccept these proposals, but would be at liberty to consider any alternative solution which might, on an objective and fully informedjudgment, appear to be preferable.The Minister of Defence said that the Government could not be accused of having failed to give adequate consideration to the other possible solutions which the Lord President had mentioned. Boththe completion of the outer ring road and the construction of a supplementary shopping centre at Cowley were specifically mentioned, in the letter which he had sent to the Oxford City Councilwhile he was Minister of Housing and Local Government, asmeasures which could offer a useful contribution to the easing oftraffic congestion in Oxford. Nor were the Government finallycommitted to the construction of a road across Christ ChurchMeadow as the only remedy for this congestion. Parliament andpublic opinion should realise that the Government were committed to no more than the rejection of the inner ring road across thenorthern half of the City and to requesting the City Council toprepare a detailed plan for a road across the Meadow, which wouldthereafter be the subject of a further public enquiry. No finaldecision could be given until the report of that enquiry was available.The Minister of Local Government said that the construction ofa shopping centre at Cowley had already been in hand for some years.The completion of the outer ring road was included in the roads programme which had now been made public. The proposed roadacross Christ Church Meadow would, in any case, have to be thesubject of a public enquiry in accordance with normal procedure, anda public enquiry would present the advantage over a Royal Corn-mission that it would give the opposing interests the fullestopportunity to expose, in detailed cross-examination, both the merits and the defects of the solutions favoured by the different bodies ofopinion. If there was any risk that an enquiry of this kind would bethought to be liable to be prejudiced by the fact that an Inspectorfrom his own Department would preside, he would be prepared toappoint an independent person to hold the enquiry and to arrange forhis report to be published, as had been done in the public enquiry onGatwick Airport.In discussion it was suggested that it might well be impossible to demonstrate, by factual evidence, that a road across Christ ChurchMeadow was essential until the Government could assess the fullmeasure of the relief offered by the new shopping centre at Cowleyand the completion of the outer ring road. It would be some time before these projects were complete; but it would be important thata public enquiry should be able to recognise the potential relief to traffic congestion in Oxford which they might provide, in order thatthe Government, in reaching a final decision, might give due weight tothis aspect of the question. The Minister of Housing confirmed that,if a public enquiry showed that the construction of a road acrossChrist Church Meadow was open to serious objection, the Govern-ment were in no sense bound to allow such a road to be put in hand.They would then be compelled to adopt some fresh approach to the
problem, in which they could take advantage of any conclusions which had emerged from the public enquiry about the degree of relieflikely to be afforded by the new shopping centre at Cowley and bythe outer ring road when both these projects had been completed.The Cabinet Invited the Lord President to arrange that government spokesmen in the debate in the House of Lords on LordBeveridge&apos;s motion on 13th February should be guided bythe views expressed during their discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,11th February, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
