<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 99-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  February 1957SECRETC.C. (57)12th conclusions copy No. 4 2CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Tuesday, 19th February, 1957, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. The Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir.Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. D. Ormsby-Gore,M.P., Minister of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat;The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper. i51159-12b
contents minute no.1234567SubjectSir Anthony EdenParliamentGhana    ...Cyprus   ...Foreign Affairs ...Israel.Suez Canal.British Forces in Europe.Oil Supplies     ......Industrial Disputes     ...Electricity Industry.Motor Industry.Page3333346
Parliament. 2,   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in theHouse of Commons in the following week.Ghana.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 8thConclusions,Minute 5.)3. The Commonwealth Secretary said that it would be inaccordance with practice for the United Kingdom Government tomake a suitable presentation to the Gold Coast on its attainment of independence within the Commonwealth. This might be mentionedin the statement on Ghana which the Prime Minister was to makein Parliament on 21st February.In discussion it was agreed that an appropriate gift would be asculptured plaque for the Parliament building at Accra. It was also suggested that the House of Commons or the CommonwealthParliamentary Association might wish to make a presentation of somearticle of furniture for use inside the Parliament building.The Cabinet -Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with theCommonwealth Secretary and the President of the Boardof Trade, to consider (i) what form the gift of the UnitedKingdom Government to the new State of Ghana shouldtake; and (ii) what presentation should be made to the parliament of Ghana from the House of Commons or theCommonwealth Parliamentary Association.Cyprus.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 6thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that,in the debate on Cyprus which had just begun in the united nations, the Greek Government had tabled a resolutionproposing that a United Nations body should be constituted to investigate our allegation that the Greeks were inciting terrorism in cyprus. It was, however, unlikely that they would press this resolution very far. The best outcome of the debate for which wecould hope would be the endorsement of a compromise resolutioninviting the Governments concerned to continue their efforts to reach a peaceful solution.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.ForeignAffairs.Israel.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 10thConclusions,Minute 4.) .5. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that the UnitedStates Government were evidently unwilling to endorse the specificguarantees about Gaza and the Straits of Tiran for which Israel wasasking as the price of withdrawal of her troops. There was indeedsome risk that the United States Government might feel compelledto vote in favour of a resolution invoking sanctions against Israel, ifsuch a resolution was eventually introduced. On the other hand,public opinion in the United States seemed to be hardening againstthe employment of sanctions against Israel; and it was still possiblethat the Canadian resolution, which would, in effect, give Israel the guarantees on which she was insisting, might be reintroduced ifsufficient support for it could be mustered.&quot;1159-12b 2Sir Anthony 1.   The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet would be grievedEden. to learn that Sir Anthony Eden had suffered two attacks of feverin the course of his voyage to New Zealand. A brief announcement to this effect would be made, at Sir Anthony&apos;s request, later in theday. He proposed to send to Sir Anthony, on the Cabinefs behalf,a message of their sympathy and good wishes.
Suez Canal. The Prime Minister said that it now seemed likely that we should(Previous        secure the agreement of the United States, France and other PowersReference:      to the proposed terms of an interim administration of the Suez CanalC.C. (57) 10th   whereby the dues payable by ships using it would be paid initiallyConclusions,    to a neutral agent who would transfer 50 per cent, to the EgyptianMinute 5.)      Government and would retain the balance for disposal as part ofthe eventual final settlement.  The agent might be the international bank or the United Nations itself: it was proposed that Egypt shouldbe allowed to exercise the choice between these alternatives.  Therewas admittedly some risk in conceding this right of choice to Egypt,since it might establish a precedent which could operate to our disadvantage in later negotiations.   But Egypt was, in any case,unlikely to accept the proposed interim settlement; and the advantageof securing the co-operation of the United States and other maritimePowers in a reasonable proposal outweighed any tactical risk whichmight be involved. In the negotiation of a final settlement we shouldnot necessarily be bound to accept the procedure of the interimadministration as a precedent, and we should adhere strictly to the six principles prescribed by the resolution of the Security Councilon 13th October, 1956.British Forces The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that both thein Europe. French and German Governments had been disturbed by our state-ment of the reductions which we proposed to make in the strengthof our forces stationed in Europe. The German Government were concerned mainly with the difficulty of justifying to their Parliamenttheir acceptance of the agreement about support costs. But the criticism of the French Government was directed, morefundamentally, to any contraction of British strength in Europe;and it was possible that they would formally oppose our proposals at the next meeting of the Western European Union (W.E.U.).The Prime Minister said that the reaction of W.E.U. was unlikely to be clear at the first meeting, since it would depend upon the reception given by the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation to our proposals. We should, therefore, be prepared for the main debate in W.E.U. to emerge at the second meeting. Our case would thenneed to be developed with skill and firmness; and in the meantimewe should do nothing to imply that we had any doubt that it wouldbe accepted.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.Oil Supplies. 6.   The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister(Previous of Power (C. (57) 37) covering a draft of a Parliamentary statementReference - on the extent to which the current restrictions on the use of oil mightC.C. (57) 3rd now be relaxed.  They also had before them a memorandum by theConclusions, Minister of Transport (C. (57) 39) on oil supplies for goods and publicMinute 3.) service vehicles.The Minister of Power said that supplies would not equaldemand until the flow of oil through the Suez Canal and the Syrianpipeline had been fully restored, and it was therefore necessary tomake preparations for a further rationing period after 17th April.Nevertheless, the situation had so far improved that it was nowpossible to relax the existing restrictions to some extent. The petrolration had not been fully taken up and, although consumption was now slightly increasing, the improvement in stocks would justifyextending over the Easter holidays the validity of coupons saved fromthe first rationing period. Stocks of petrol were relatively high andsome criticism of the Governments refusal to distribute them mustbe expected. In the case of fuel oil, it would be prudent to makethe rebuilding of stocks in anticipation of the following winter the
5CC. 12 (57)first charge on the improvement which had taken place in supplies.He therefore proposed to announce at this stage that the distributionof supplies of fuel oil to industry would be maintained at present levels, without any further cut, until the end of April. A substantialrelaxation could now, however, be made in the cuts imposed on theuse of gas/diesel oil by industry and for agriculture, fishing and central heating.The Minister of Transport said that the motor transportorganisations had expressed satisfaction at the manner in which the rationing arrangements had been carried out. He was now in aposition to bring in a simplified rationing scheme for goods and publicservice vehicles for the second period, and he was anxious to be ableto do so in order to release driving examiners to return to their normalwork of conducting driving tests.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The rationing of oil and petrol had not resulted in any significant unemployment.(b) The validity of the large volume of unused coupons now inthe possession of motorists could not safely be extended beyond theend of April, as the existence of such an unknown demand would impair the prospects of increasing the value of the rationing unit inthe second period. Nevertheless, the refusal to allow these couponsany longer period of validity at a time when petrol stocks might wellbe in excess of commercial storage capacity would provoke public criticism. It would be desirable, therefore, to include in theproposed Parliamentary announcement a statement to the effect that,if rationing continued to be necessary beyond 17th April, theGovernment expected to be able to maintain the ration at least at its present level.(c) A separate announcement should be made, on the authorityof the Minister of Power, of the facilities which would be availableto oversea visitors to this country.(d) Large numbers of motorists resident in this country were planning to take their cars to Europe for the summer holiday. Therewere also growing complaints from the remoter holiday areas in thiscountry that the outlook for petrol had seriously affected holidaybookings. The knowledge that additional supplies of petrol and dervwould be made available for the motor-coach trade during the summer would do something to allay the fears which were entertainedin these areas; but it was important that an announcement shouldbe made as soon as possible of the supplies of petrol which would beavailable to ordinary residents during the holiday period. No suchannouncement could safely be made until March.(e) Depending on the outcome of the further deliberations of theTexas Railroad Commission, which were due to be announced that day, it would be courteous if the proposed Parliamentary statement were to contain an appreciative reference to the exertions which theUnited States Government and oil industry had made to provideemergency supplies of oil for Europe.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Minister of Power, in consultation with theMinister of Transport and the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster, to revise in the light of the points made intheir discussion the draft Parliamentary statement annexed to C. (57) 37.(2) Authorised the Minister of Power to make the proposed statement, as revised, in the House of Lords during that week, and to arrange for the Paymaster-General to makea corresponding statement in the House of Commons.(3) Invited the Minister of Power, in consultation with theMinister of Transport and the Chancellor of the Duchy
of Lancaster, to arrange for a separate statement to beissued on his authority regarding the availability of petrolfor visitors from overseas.industrial disputes.electricity industry.motor industry.7. The Minister of Labour said that both sides in the dispute in the electrical power industry, which was concerned with paydifferentials for skilled and professional workers/were fundamentallyanxious to avoid a breakdown in the negotiations and there were grounds for hoping that a settlement would be reached.In the motor industry, however, the dispute at Briggs MotorBodies Limited gave cause for more serious concern. TheAmalgamated Engineering Union (A.E.U.) were embarrassed by theresult of a secret ballot favouring recourse to a strike; the questionof the re-employment of the individual involved in the dispute wasbeing elevated into an issue of &quot; trade union principle &quot;; there was little apparent scope for compromise; and it might well provedifficult to avoid a strike which, because of the supposed issue ofprinciple, might spread beyond the firm immediately involved. his department were in touch with both sides to the dispute, and theA.E.U. had been pressed to defer calling a strike until all methodsof conciliation had been explored.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,19th February, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
