<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 123-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;SjGOVJP&amp;NMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  March 1957SECRET Copy No. 5 0CC. (57)15th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street. S.W. I,on Monday, 4th March, 1957, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. The Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and Local Gov-ernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.Also present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
contents minute no.                                     Subject page 1      Western European Union    ......      ...      ...... 32     Israel     ...     ...      ...     .........     ...     .., 33      Singapore        ................      ...      ... 34      Christmas Island...............      ... 55     Somaliland..................... 66     Cyprus   ...      ...      ............      ...      ... 77      Suez Canal Users&apos; Association        ............ 7Privileges and Immunities.8     Rent Restriction        .................. 8
Israel. 2.   The Foreign Secretary said that, although the settlement(Previous        about the withdrawal of Israeli forces which appeared to have been reference:      reached between the United States Government and the IsraeliC.C. (57) 14th   Government would have been broadly acceptable to us, the latestConclusions,    speech by the United States representative at the United NationsMinute 2.)       had been unduly sympathetic towards the Arab States and there was now some danger that the Government of Israel would withdraw their agreement.  If the prospect of a reasonable settlement recededagain, we should have to reconsider our policy; but we might hopethat the risk of a resolution merely invoking sanctions against Israelhad now been finally averted.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.Singapore.(previous reference:CM. (56) 104thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theColonial Secretary about the proposed new constitution for singapore (C. (57) 48).The Colonial Secretary said that he hoped to resume discussions with the Chief Minister of Singapore in the near future on the basisof the proposals outlined in his memorandum. The new constitution would be a form of dyarchy, in which defence and foreign affairs would be reserved to the United Kingdom Government, whosespokesman would be the Resident Commissioner, while localMinisters would discharge the remaining functions of government.The Governor would be a Malayan-born personage, who would beappointed by The Queen on the advice of the Secretary of State,would hold office during Her Majesty&apos;s pleasure, and would be boundto act in accordance with the advice of Ministers. The iltimate authority to suspend the constitution would, however, vest in the resident Commissioner, who would in that eventuality supplantlocal Ministers as the adviser to the Governor.These proposals were acceptable to the Governments ofAustralia and New Zealand and were supported by the Governor of singapore, the Commissioner-General in South-East Asia, and theChiefs of Staff. They did little more than formalise the existing situation in which, for some time, we had been unable to use ourreserve powers and had been compelled to rely, in the last resort,on the power to suspend the constitution. This power would remain with the Resident Commissioner and, together with the fact that hewould preside over both the Defence and External Affairs Counciland the Internal Security Council, should suffice to retain in ourown hands an effective degree of authority in Singapore. At themoment the body of opinion in Singapore which was friendly tothis country was growing, and it would be advisable to seize thepresent opportunity to establish a constitution which would be popular with liberal opinion in the Colony and would, at the sametime, safeguard our essential interests.Western 1.   The Foreign Secretary said that the discussion in the NorthEuropean Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) of the proposed reduction inUnion. our forces in Europe was developing on not wholly favourable lines.(Previous But our agreement to prolong this process over two financial years,Reference: subject to a satisfactory settlement with the German government.C. (57) 14th about their contribution to the cost of our forces in Germany, had conclusions, been welcomed by the Supreme Allied Commander, Europe; and minute 1.) there was a reasonable prospect that the discussions in N.A.T.O.would end satisfactorily.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.
In discussion doubts were expressed about the precedent whichmight be constituted by the unique arrangements proposed for singapore. The Government of Malta, for example, might feel obliged to press for similar arrangements. But a constitution on the model proposed for Singapore would represent a regressive step formaltality, which already possessed most of the powers which, underthe new constitution for Singapore, would be transferred to localMinisters. There appeared to be no other Colonial territory wherethe present stage of constitutional development would provide abasis for a claim to treatment comparable with that proposed for singapore.Doubts were also expressed about the extent to which the suggested constitution would provide a lasting solution of theproblems of the Colony. It was proposed that local Ministers,although being consulted before the appointment of the Governor,should not advise The Queen on this appointment. Nevertheless,the Governor, once appointed, would exercise considerable power in such matters as the selection of a Chief Minister and the dissolution of the Legislative Assembly. On the other hand, the resident commissioner would be empowered, without necessarily consultinglocal Ministers, to advise the Governor to reserve for The Queen&apos;assent any measure affecting the responsibilities of the UnitedKingdom Government. The balance of authority between localMinisters and the Resident Commissioner would, therefore, be adelicate one; and although such an arrangement might prove feasiblewhile the present Chief Minister held office, it was doubtful whetherit would endure if he was replaced by a Chief Minister less welldisposed towards this country. It was open to question whether a constitution of the kind proposed was likely, for all its ingenuity,to be compatible with either stability of administration or themaintenance of our own essential strategic interests.It was, however, argued that, so long as defence and external affairs were reserved to the United Kingdom Government, our interest in Singapore as a major base should be adequatelysafeguarded. Moreover, the fact that the interests of the Federationof Malaya in Singapore were substantially the same as our ownshould ensure that, in most cases, our view would prevail in theInternal Security Council as well; and this, coupled with thearrangement whereby senior appointments to the Police Force wouldbe subject to the approval of the Council, should secure our continued control over public order. We should enjoy a further and valuable safeguard in the stipulation, which had still to be negotiated with Singapore Ministers, that if any Bill passed by thelocal Legislature affected matters within the sphere of responsibilityof the United Kingdom Government, the Resident Commissioner,would be empowered so to inform the Governor, who would thenbe obliged by the constitution to reserve the Bill for The Queen&apos;assent. With these safeguards the proposed constitution should enable us to maintain our essential interests in Singapore, withoutappearing to attempt to arrest the increasing tendency towardsMalayanisation. It might not provide a permanent solution; but itshould make possible a period of political stability in Singapore until it became practicable to advance towards the ultimate objective ofunification of the Colony and the Federation of Malaya. At thattime an essential condition of such unification would be our retentionof the right to maintain a major military base at Singapore.The status and powers of the future Governor were a concession to local opinion which was in no way derogatory to the Crown and,provided that the ultimate right of suspending the constitutionremained in the hands of the Resident Commissioner, should prove a useful precedent for maintaining our interests in other cases whereit was essential that we should retain a military base within a community which was  advancing towards  independence.   The
4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theCommonwealth Secretary and the Colonial Secretary (C. (57) 51)recommending that responsibility for Christmas Island should betransferred to Australia.The Colonial Secretary said that the Governor of singapore and the Commissioner-General in South-East Asia, with the supportof the other Colonial Governors in the Far East, had advised that,if the Government of Singapore continued to receive a net annualrevenue from Christmas Island for so long as its phosphate depositswere being worked, the resultant presumption that Singapore had an interest in the ultimate future of the Island would defeat the objective of clearly separating the two territories. The Australian Governmenthad now proposed  that the Island should be transferred toChristmasIsland.(previous reference:CM. (56) 68thConclusions,Minute 7.)constitution would not itself specify that the Governor must beMalayan born; and if an emergency developed or if, in the eventof the constitution having to be suspended, a Malayan-born Governorproved recalcitrant, there would be no impediment to theappointment as Governor, in his place, of any person whom theUnited Kingdom Government wished to recommend to The Queen.Nor were there grounds for supposing that the fact that the governor would normally be Malayan born would provide Singapore with ajuridical basis for seceding from the Commonwealth and appealingto the United Nations for recognition as a wholly independentcommunity. Opinion within the Commonwealth, and probablyelsewhere, would not endorse a claim by any nation to be whollyself-governing unless it controlled its own defence and external relations; and these subjects would, in the case of Singapore, remainreserved to the United Kingdom Government.The Cabinet Authorised the Colonial Secretary to open discussions withthe Chief Minister of Singapore about the future constitutionof the Colony on the basis described in his memorandum,on the understanding that, inter alia (i) the constitution would not itself prescribe that theGovernor should be a Malayan-born person or debar the United Kingdom Government fromrecommending any person to The Queen for appointment as Governor;(ii) the Governor would hold office during The Queen&apos;pleasure and the constitution would not preclude the United Kingdom Government from advisingHer Majesty to terminate the Governorsappointment and to appoint another person in his place;(hi) the Royal Instructions, in conjunction with theprovisions of the constitution, would oblige theGovernor to act in accordance with the advice oflocal Ministers or, if the constitution was suspended,in accordance with the advice of the resident commissioner;(iv) the constitution would expressly provide that if, in theview of the Resident Commissioner, any Bill passedby the Singapore Legislature affected matters withinthe sphere of responsibility of the United KingdomGovernment, the Resident Commissioner would havethe right so to inform the Governor, who would thenbe obliged to reserve the Bill for The Queen&apos;s assent;and in such cases the United Kingdom Governmentwould tender advice to Her Majesty.
Australia under an arrangement whereby they would finance thecompounding of the revenue which Singapore had hitherto receivedfrom the phosphate deposits. They had also agreed that the fewinhabitants on Christmas Island would be given the same rights and privileges in relation to Australian law as had been extended to theinhabitants of the Cocos Islands when these Islands had beentransferred earlier.This proposal was acceptable to the New Zealand Government,and was supported by the Governor of Singapore and theCommissioner-General in the Far East. It might now becommunicated to the Chief Minister of Singapore in the course ofthe forthcoming constitutional discussions, the figure for thecompounding of the revenue being initially fixed at  1 million. Itwould, however, be undesirable that we should attempt to obtainourselves any compensation from the Australian Government forthe transfer of Christmas Island.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in agreement with theseproposals.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals in C. (57) 51 relating to the futureof Christmas Island.(2) Invited the Lord President to arrange for the Australian andNew Zealand Governments to be informed accordingly.Somalil and.(previous reference:CM. (56) 70thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Cabinet had before them a report by officials (C. (57) 38)about the Somaliland Protectorate and the Horn of Africa.The Colonial Secretary said that the approaching independence of Somalia made it urgent to evolve a firm policy for the Horn of africa. Our efforts to maintain our position in the Aden Protectoratewould be frustrated if the Somali peoples united under influenceshostile to us. He therefore endorsed the recommendation inparagraph 39 (a) of the report that we should make a sustainedattempt to induce the Ethiopians and Somalis to work together, andthat we should seek to persuade other Western Powers to join with us in promoting this objective. The prospect that a Greater Somalia,if it came into being with our encouragement, would have expansionistdesigns on the Ogaden could be used as a means of persuading the ethiopian Government to carry out more satisfactorily their obligations in respect of the Haud under the Agreement of 1954.Although elements in British Somaliland would doubtless continueto press, on racial grounds, for the union of all Somali peoples, thestrength of this agitation would be reduced if the grievances relatingto the administration of the Haud by Ethiopia were removed. Asregards other possible courses of action, the support of the french would not be forthcoming for the union of the Somali peoples, andthe Italians would not be prepared to retain responsibility for Somaliawhen their trusteeship came to an end in 1960.The Foreign Secretary said that it would not be to our advantage to foster the creation of a Greater Somalia which would need to be supported by a substantial subsidy if it was not to come under Arabdomination. . Our interest lay, therefore, in building up Ethiopia asa counterpoise to Arab expansionism in the Horn of Africa. the ethiopian Government were themselves anxious to restore friendly relations, which had deteriorated solely because of the local difficultieswhich had arisen in connection with the administration of the Haud.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in agreement with theviews which had been expressed. If, however, the course proposed was to be followed, some further consideration might need to begiven to modifying the guardedly encouraging statement which
Cyprus. 6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Foreign Secretary (C. (57) 49) about a proposal by the Secretary-Reference: General of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (N.A.T.O.) that.C. (57) 13th he should use his good offices to promote a settlement of the problemConclusions, of Cyprus by conciliation between the three countries concerned.minute 4.) jfe foreign Secretary said that the Secretary-General apparentlyintended to entrust the responsibility for seeking a settlement to asmall Committee of representatives of three member countries ofN.A.T.O. which had no direct interest in Cyprus. Our motives mightbe misconstrued if we refused to take advantage of a proposal which did not commit us to do more than seek a settlement by conciliation.The Colonial Secretary said that we should take no action atthis juncture which might undermine the favourable position whichwe had now established in Cyprus against the terrorist forces. Therewas some risk that, if the conciliators failed to bring the three parties together, they would feel impelled to put forward recommendations which might be embarrassing to us. It would, for example, be unfortunate if we were confronted at present with any recommenda-tion relating to partition. On the understanding, however, that no more was involved than an attempt to seek a solution by conciliation,there should be no great risk in accepting the Secretary-GeneraFsoffer.The Prime Minister said that he was reluctant to approve aproposal of this nature except on the basis of the precise terms inwhich our reply would be conveyed to the Secretary-General,including the statement of any conditions to which our agreement would be subject. The matter might be considered by the Cabineton this basis later in the week, and the Foreign Secretary and hewould then discuss it with the Secretary-General in Paris on10th March.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theColonial Secretary, to circulate for their consideration a draft reply to the proposal of the Secretary-General ofN.A.T.O.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion at their next meeting.Suez CanalUsers&apos;Association.(previous reference:CM. (56) 74thConclusions,Minute 5.)Privileges and immunities.7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (C. (57) 54) about diplomatic privileges and immunitiesfor members of the staff of the Suez Canal Users&apos; Association(S.C.U.A.).The Cabinet were informed that S.C.U.A. might decide not tomake their permanent headquarters in this country. Because of this and of the public criticism to which each successive extension of diplomatic privilege and immunity gave rise, it might be premature to make an Order in Council under the International Organisations(Immunities and Privileges) Act, 1950, to deal with the three membersLord Lloyd had been authorised to make in the previous year abouta possible association between the Somaliland Protectorate andSomalia after 1960.The Cabinet Approved, subject to the points made in their discussion,the recommendation in paragraph 39 (a) of C. (57) 38, and authorised the consequential action outlined in that paragraph.
rent restriction.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 11thConclusions,Minute I)8. The Minister of Housing said that he proposed, subject tothe Cabinefs approval, to accept in principle two amendments to the rent Bill which had been tabled by Government supporters. Thefirst would provide, for the tenants of houses which would becomedecontrolled as a result of the Bill, a minimum statutory security of tenure of four weeks. The second would enable the tenants ofhouses decontrolled under Clause 9 of the Bill to claim, subject to suitable safeguards, compensation for improvements which they had made to these properties, with the consent of the landlords, duringthe period of their rent-controlled tenancies.The Lord Chancellor said that he was in favour of both these amendments. Allowing compensation for improveinents made bytenants presented difficulty, since such improvements were frequentlymade for aesthetic reasons without proportionately enhancing thevalue of the property. Nevertheless, it was reasonable that, in thecircumstances of the present Bill, compensation for improvementsshould be conceded in suitable cases.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Housing to accept in principle the two amendments to the Rent Bill which he had outlined.Cabinet Office, S.W, 1,4th March, 1957.of the staff of this organisation if the matter could be dealt with byother means. The relation between S.C.U.A. and the United nations organisation might be relevant for this purpose.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary and the Chancellor of theExchequer, in consultation, to consider whether some alternative approach to the problem of the tax liability of the members of the staff of S.C.U.A. could be devised which would not involve a fresh Order in Council underthe International Organisations (Immunities and Privileges)Act, 1950.

</content>
</cab>
