<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 168-174</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENT&apos;Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1957SECRET Copy No.C.C. (57)22nd conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Friday, 22nd March, 1957, at 10-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home department and Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair)The Most Hon. The Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The.Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Allan Noble, M.P.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Minister of State for Foreign Affairs. I    Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
contents minute no.                                      subject      Industrial Disputes     ......2      Cyprus   .........3      Bermuda Meeting       ......4      Suez Canal      ...      ...      ...British Evacuees.5      Shops&apos; Bill       .........
1. The Home Secretary said that he had informed the PrimeMinister of the present situation and that, in reply, the Prime minister had expressed the view that, since it would become publicly known that the British Transport Commission had already offered a wage increase of 4-J per cent, it would be unwise to expose the economy tothe dislocation of a railway strike for the sake of the extra \ per cent,which would probably make this offer acceptable to the railway unions. It would however, be easier to justify an increase of 5 percent, if it was coupled with some offer by the unions to increase productivity and to reduce the scope of restrictive practices.The Minister of Transport said that while an increase of A\ percent, could be defended, an increase of 5 per cent, was far lessjustifiable and might be represented as a surrender to pressure by theunions in return for no more than a few indefinite undertakings about future increases in productivity. There was some reason to think,however, that the general body of employers might not condemn a5 per cent, increase if it were accompanied by some genuine andconcrete evidence that the unions would make a fresh effort toincrease productivity. There could be no question of the Govern-ment&apos;s dissociating themselves from a 5 per cent, award, if that wasthe outcome; and it would be necessary for the Government at least to endorse such an award even if they did not positively commend it.The Minister of Labour said that an agreement on the basis of a wage increase of 5 per cent., reached only a few days after an arbitration award of 3 per cent., would be widely regarded as an act of appeasement which would endanger the whole principle ofarbitration, would undermine the morale of employers in industry generally and would be strongly criticised by the Governments own supporters. It was impossible to predict how a settlement of therailway dispute on the basis of a wage increase of 5 per cent, would affect the disputes in the shipbuilding and engineering industries. Inso far as the employers in those disputes were restrained by theprospect of the damage which the economy would suffer in the eventof industrial disturbances on the scale of a general strike, theirattitude might harden if this risk was reduced as the result of asettlement of the railways dispute. He had now succeeded In response-establishing contact between the employers and the unions in the shipbuilding industry and there was some prospect that the partiesmight reach agreement on the amount of a wage increase if the unions were prepared to give adequate assurances on certain issues of productivity which the employers had specified. If such a settlement was reached, it should not be impossible to prevail on the engineeringunions to abstain from strike action.In discussion there was support for the view that, while asettlement of the railways dispute on the basis of a % per cent, wage increase could be marginally justified on cost-of-living grounds, asettlement based on a 5 per cent, increase would be stronglycondemned by public opinion and would undermine the future ability and willingness of employers to resist excessive wage claims. Suchclaims were now pending in agriculture and coalmining, and theirsettlement would be bound to be affected by the terms finally agreed with the railway unions. The difference between A\ per cent, and5 per cent, represented a margin of principle which it would be dangerous to compromise.On the other hand, arguments which had had considerable forcein relation to the arbitration award of a 3 per cent, increase, or even to the Transport Commission^ original offer of a Z\ per cent, increase,lost much of their validity when the Commission, on their own initiative, had already increased their offer to A\ per cent. Publicopinion was not likely to be convinced that, for the sake of a mere\ per cent, the Transport Commission would be justified in-2 b 2
acquiescing in a railway strike which would cost them  1^ millions a day and would cause serious and widespread dislocation in industry.Moreover, the Transport Commission themselves held than anincrease of 5 per cent, could properly be conceded in return for improvements in productivity, some of which had already accruedwhile others were in prospect. Considerations of productivity hadbeen expressly excluded from the recent arbitration award and asettlement which purported to include some recognition of improvements in productivity should therefore be defensible.It was also suggested that it might be expedient for the transport commission to adhere, for the moment, to their existing offer ofan increase of 4i per cent, and to allow the railway unions to invokestrike action if they wished. The unions would be obliged to givea week&apos;s notice of such action, and in that week the normal procedure of conciliation could be brought into action. The advantage of thiscourse would lie in the firm front which the employers would therebyapear to present to the unions. Its disadvantage lay in the possibility that, in the end, the Transport Commission would still have to concedean increase of 5 per cent., if not more, while sterling would probably have been exposed in the interval to fresh pressure. It was agreedthat the disadvantages of this course outweighed its advantages.In the light of all the considerations involved, it was the balanceof view in the Cabinet that it would be unwise to aggravate thepolitical and economic problems which confronted the government by unnecessary obduracy in a situation where the margin betweenagreement and a damaging strike was so narrow. On the otherhand it would be desirable, if a settlement based on an increase of5 per cent, was to be justified, that it should be represented aswarranted mainly by definite assurances of increased productivity onthe railways in the future and only to a small extent by the rise inthe cost of living.It was finally agreed that the Transport Commission should beinformed that, in the view of the Government, they should seek to confine their offer to an increase of A\ per cent, for as long as possible;that they should concede an increase of 5 per cent, in the last resort,but only if the unions undertook to accept it and gave some concreteassurances about improved productivity; and that they should in no circumstances offer an increase of more than 5 per cent.In further discussion it was suggested that, nevertheless, theoccasion would eventually occur when it would be necessary to acceptthe challenge of a strike on a wage claim for which there was no adequate justification. The Minister of Transport said that, while he did not dissent, his own view was that it was an anachronismin modern circumstances to think in terms of defeating strike action by attempting to invoke the sanctions which existed in earlier periodsunless Governments were prepared to strengthen the powers of resistance of the employers by withdrawing from strikers the support which they at present derived from their income tax refunds, thepayment of national assistance while they were on strike and similar concessions.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that, if necessary, the settlement of the current wagedispute in the railway industry on the basis of an increaseof 5 per cent, should be accepted, subject to the railway unions giving adequate assurances about an increase in productivity.(2) Invited the Minister of Transport to be guided in his furtherhandling of this question by the views expressed during their discussion.
5 CC. 22 (57)Cyprus. 2.   The Colonial Secretary said that the Governor of Seychelles(Previous had reported that Archbishop Makarios had indicated that he was reference: now prepared to make an appeal to the people of Cyprus to renounceCC. (57) 2lst violence and that, while this appeal would include an expression of conclusions, some of his views, these would not be in the nature of reservations.Minute 1.) The Archbishop&apos;s capitulation would contribute more than any othersingle factor to securing an end of the violence in Cyprus, and theGovernor of Cyprus would consider forthwith how far the security measures in the island might be relaxed. The Archbishop&apos;s decision should be announced as soon as possible after the full text of his statement was available. The President of the United States had informed the Prime Minister in Bermuda that the United StatesGovernment would be willing to consider making an approach tothe Greek Government about Cyprus; and the Prime Minister wastherefore anxious to keep the United States Government informed of our intentions and of the terms of our announcement. It was also important that, provided that the text of the Archbishop&apos;s statementgave rise to no further question, his decision should be announcedquickly in order to forestall any unauthorised disclosure which mightprompt the Greek Government to try to bring pressure to bear on him to withdraw his declaration. The Turkish Government, who might not wholly welcome the Archbishop&apos;s change of attitude,should be informed of our announcement shortly before it was made;but there would be no advantage in communicating it to the GreekGovernment.The Cabinet expressed satisfaction at this statement. They were informed that, although Archbishop Makarios had satisfied theconditions for release from detention, he would be obliged to remainin the Seychelles for a further three weeks when the next ship was dueto call. Special air transport would be unjustified. He had expressed the wish to proceed, on release, either to London or to greece. The Cabinet would therefore need to consider as soon aspossible what further steps might now be taken to promote a solution to the problem of Cyprus. It would be necessary, however, to allow the Governor of Cyprus a sufficient interval in which to assess thelocal situation and to determine, in the light of the response in the island to the Archbishop&apos;s declaration, how far the existing security measures could be relaxed. In the meantime it would be desirable tomaintain our support for the proposed procedure of conciliation inthe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation and to resist any suggestionthat the declaration by Archbishop Makarios reduced the need forthat procedure.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Colonial Secretary to circulate, as rapidly aspossible, the full text of the statement in whichArchbishop Makarios would appeal to the people of cyprus to renounce violence.(2) Invited the Colonial Secretary to consider, in the light of thistext and in consultation with the Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster, the terms in which the Archbishop *s decision should be announced and to keep the Prime minister informed of further developments.(3) Agreed to resume their discussion of Cyprus at an early meeting.Bermuda 3.   The Home Secretary informed the Cabinet that a messageMeeting. had been received from the Prime Minister in Bermuda reporting that(Previous satisfactory initial progress had been made in the discussions withReference: President Eisenhower and Mr. Dulles, and that the PresidentCC. (57) 10th appeared to be genuinely anxious fully to restore the traditionalConclusions, relationship between the two  countries.   Although  Mr. DullesMinute 3.) remained rather cautious and legalistic in his approach to the problem
of the Suez Canal, it had been made clear to the United StatesGovernment that a major responsibility now rested on them topromote a satisfactory settlement of this problem and, if this failed,to join with us in condemning the Egyptian Government.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.Suez Canal. 4.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Home SecretaryBritish (C. (57) 74) covering a report by officials classifying the various typesEvacuees. of financial and commercial claims against Egypt and examining(Previous tne possibility of making advances against established claims by reference:      private individuals in this category.C.C. (57) 18th The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in the light of this conclusions, report and of all previous practice in comparable circumstances, thereMinute 2.) were clearly formidable objections to any system of paying advancesagainst assets. He had, however, seen Lord Killearn, who was aspokesman for this group of evacuees, and had satisfied him that theGovernment would deal generously, through the Anglo-egyptian resettlement Board, with cases of hardship. He had also agreed,at Lord Killearn&apos;s request, that a member of the British Chamberof Commerce in Egypt should be brought into consultation torepresent the interests for whom Lord Killearn spoke. A statementof the Governmenfs intentions in this matter would help to allayany disquiet which might be expressed in the debate in the Houseof Lords in the following week; but it would also be desirable toemphasise in the debate the considerations which prevented themaking of advances against assets.The Lord President agreed that a statement on these lines would help in reassuring public opinion. Nevertheless the arguments inC. (57) 74 against making advances to private individuals in respectof their sequestrated assets rested, in his view, on an unsoundpremise. On other occasions, notably in the two world wars, Britishsubjects resident abroad had been deprived of their property as aresult of political and military action which the Government in theUnited Kingdom had not initiated. The individuals now in question,however, had lost their assets as a direct result of action which her majesty&apos;s Government had themselves put in hand. In thesecircumstances the moral responsibility of the Government amountedto a debt of honour, and the difficulties set out in the memorandum,although important, could not be regarded as conclusive against thiswider consideration.Discussion showed that this view commanded sympathy. On theother hand, it had already been calculated provisionally that theclaims of private individuals and commercial organisations in Egyptmight amount to as much as  25 millions and  75 millionsrespectively, while the Sudanese Government had entered a claim of  20 millions against the Egyptian sterling balances. In face of claims of this order the question of making advances against assetswould need careful examination. It was agreed that a decision shouldbe deferred until the Foreign Office had completed their tabulationof claims, and that it would then have to be considered in the context of the general policy which we intended to follow in dealing with claims against the Egyptian Government.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to arrange for officials of the Treasury, Foreign Office and Board ofTrade to submit at the earliest opportunity, when thetotal of claims had been ascertained and classified,proposals for pursuing claims against the Egyptian
Government and for taking any interim action whichmight be practicable to meet the needs of individualclaimants.(2) Agreed that some 160 former officials of the Governmentof Egypt dismissed in 1951, whose compensation was thesubject of negotiation when diplomatic relations with egypt had been broken off, and pensioners, other thanpensioners of the Government of Egypt, should beregarded as coming within the responsibility of the Anglo-Egyptian Resettlement Board.(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to give furtherconsideration to the possibility of arranging to accept atpar Egyptian currency brought to this country by certain of the evacuees.Shops Bill.(previous reference:c.C. (57) 20thConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The Home Secretary said that he had agreed to acceptamendments to this Bill which should satisfy the criticism that itwas an unduly restrictive measure. The Bill would now containmore flexible provisions about the hours of confectioneryestablishments, and would include a measure of local option forother shops. The former Prime Minister had given an undertaking to the Trade Union Congress that one or other of the remainingBills arising out of the reports of the Gowers Committee would been acted in the current session, and if the Government failed to carryout this undertaking they would be pressed to do so later when theymight find it even more difficult to accommodate such a lengthyBill. It would therefore be necessary to consider, when the ShopsBill had made further progress in the House of Lords, whether theGovernment should press forward with it in the House of commons in the current Session; and he would submit further proposals onthis in due course.The Cabinet Took note of this statement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1.22nd March, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
