<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 242-247</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1957SECRET Copy No. 4C.C. (57)35th CosnclesnomsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Wednesday, 17th April, 1957, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold MaThe Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.iillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Dennis Vosper, M.P.,Minister of Health (Item 4).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
contents minute no.                                     Subject page 1      Suez Canal      ..................... 32     Jordan...................... 43      Parliament    ....................... 44      Local Government Organisation      ............ 45      Shops Bill............      ......... 56     Malta    ........................ 57      Medals and Awards    .................. 6Cyprus and Port Said.
Suez Canal.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 34thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (57) 99) on the method of paymentof Canal dues by United Kingdom shipping, together with telegrams nos. 911 and 920 from H.M. Ambassador at Washington andtelegrams Nos. 962 and 964 from the United Kingdom representative at the United Nations.The Foreign Secretary said that, although the United StatesGovernment appeared willing to ask for a meeting of the security council if we so wished, they were increasingly reluctant to do so onthe ground that the negotiations between themselves and theEgyptian Government might secure further improvements in theEgyptian proposals for the operation of the Suez Canal, whereas a premature debate in the Security Council might provoke theEgyptian Government to break off the negotiations and to publishtheir proposals without even the amendments which had alreadybeen secured. Moreover the Secretary-General of the United&quot;Nations, on his own initiative, had now made a fresh approach tothe Egyptian Government in which he had not only advised themhow they might give their draft declaration sufficient international character to justify its registration under Article 102 of the united nations Charter, but had also asked them to improve the substance of the declaration in several respects, in particular by stating that theywould welcome co-operation with the main shipping interests. Astatement of this kind, if the Egyptian Government could be persuaded to adopt it, would be valuable to us.In discussion it was agreed that, while we should continue to seek to secure that the Government of Egypt would publishunilaterally a declaration of their intentions which would, in substance, approach as nearly as possible to the six principlesapproved by the Security Council on 13th October, 1956, the balanceof advantage lay in accepting the wish of the United StatesGovernment to defer a debate in the Security Council for the timebeing, in the hope that resumed negotiations between the UnitedStates and Egypt would secure additional improvements in theEgyptian proposals which would bring them more nearlyinto conformity with the six principles. In that event it should bepossible for the Security Council to be convened immediately after easter to receive a report on these negotiations. There were grounds for believing that it would be possible to persuade British shipping companies to refrain for this further brief interval from committing themselves to resume transit of the Canal. On the other hand, the shipowners could not be restrained for more than a very short period;and, the longer the existing indeterminate situation was allowed tocontinue, the more the Egyptian Government would gain fromprolonging their evasive tactics. It would therefore be desirable toreach a firm understanding with the United States Government thatthe meeting of the Security Council would not be delayed beyond a date early in the following week; and that, when the debate tookplace, they would ensure that they would have carried their negotiations with the Egyptian Government to a point at which theywould be in a position to make a full report to the Council.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to instruct H.M. ambassador at Washington and the United Kingdom representative atthe United Nations in the sense of their discussion.(2) Agreed to defer discussion of C. (57) 99 until a subsequent meeting.
Jordan.(previous reference:CC. (57) 34thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The Foreign Secretary said that the armoured squadron atMa&apos;an was under orders to return to Aqaba on the following day.It was probably well known locally that this movement was due to takeplace; but it was for consideration whether, in present circumstances,it should be delayed until it was possible to see more clearly whether we should need to reinforce King Hussein in Amman.In discussion there was general agreement that the King shouldcontinue to be encouraged to look primarily to Iraq and Saudi Arabiafor military support and that it might be premature for the UnitedKingdom to appear to be proffering assistance at the presentmoment.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Defence to arrange for thewithdrawal of the armoured squadron at Ma&apos;an to takeplace in accordance with existing arrangements.Parliament. 3.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the first week after the end of the easter recess.LocalGovernmentOrganisation.(previous references :CM. (56) 52ndConclusions,Minute 6, and cc (57) 10thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Housing and Local Government (C. (57) 94) covering adraft White Paper on the redistribution of functions between countycouncils and county district councils.The Minister of Housing said that the preparation of the white paper on Areas and Status of Local Authorities had made it clearthat some reallocation of functions between local authorities was desirable. The draft White Paper appended to C. (57) 94incorporated the result of a comprehensive review of the functionsinvolved and had been approved by the Home Affairs Committee.There was, however, no agreement between local authority associations on the extent of the changes which they would approve;and it would be wise for the Government to admit that thisdisagreement existed and to publish their proposals, not as constituting a firm decision of policy, but as providing a basis onwhich further discussions with the local authority associations could proceed. It would be desirable that a debate on these proposals should be arranged in the House of Commons before the summer recess; and the consequential legislation should be introduced in thefollowing session.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Paragraph 19 of the draft White Paper should be amended,particularly by the omission of its second sentence, to reflect the cabinet&apos;s decision about the Shops Bill.(b) A population figure which might be a reasonable criterion bywhich to determine the delegation of other functions would notnecessarily be suitable in the case of higher technological education.It would be necessary, in the discussions with the local authorities, tomake it clear that, although responsibility for the minor institutions of technical education might be delegated to district councils, themain technical colleges would remain the responsibility of the countycouncils, who would also retain oversight of the general planning ofthis service.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Housing and Local Govern-ment, subject to the points made in their discussion, to
publish the draft White Paper annexed to C. (57) 94 as soonas possible after the Easter recess, as a basis for discussionwith local authority associations.Shops Bill. 5.   The Cabinet had before them a further memorandum by(Previous        the Home Secretary (C. (57) 95) on the proposed government reference:      amendments to the Shops Bill.CC. (57) 34thConclusions, The Home Secretary said that he had discussed with the MinisterMinute 7.) &apos; of Labour and the Minister of Education the suggestion that theBill should include a provision giving local authorities in holidayresorts power to fix later closing hours during the season than thenormal ones. This proposal would, however, give rise both todrafting complications and to anomalies. It would therefore be wiser to table an amendment on the lines originally proposed inC. (57) 93 enabling local authorities in holiday resorts to dispense with closing hours during the season.In discussion there was general agreement with this proposal.The Cabinet Authorised the Home Secretary to arrange for amendments to the Shops Bill to be tabled in the House of Lords, giving effect to the proposals summarised in C. (57) 93.Malta. 6.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the(Previous Colonial Secretary (C. (57) 98) reporting that the negotiationsReference: with the Prime Minister of Malta had reached a deadlock on theCC. (57) 23rd subject   of   economic   equivalence   and   recommending   that conclusions, consideration should now be given to the possibility of accomplishingMinute 5.) by stages the integration of Malta with the United Kingdom.The Colonial Secretary said that the negotiations had reachedan impasse despite the substantial measure of financial help whichwe had offered to the Government of Malta over the next five years.The Prime Minister, Mr. Mintoff, had refused to enter into a bindingarrangement for the permanent constitutional integration of Maltawith the United Kingdom if the parallel financial proposals were limited in the first instance to a five-year trial period and containedno definite guarantee that Malta would be assured of achievingeconomic parity with the United Kingdom within ten or fifteen years.Since such an unlimited commitment was out of the question, it was for consideration whether, in order to provide an alternativeapproach to the problem, we should suggest that both the politicaland the economic aspects of integration should be explored by successive steps. If this course was approved, the offer of financialassistance would be reaffirmed, together with an offer of constitutional advance on the lines discussed in the recent negotiations, but without representation in the United kingdom parliament for the time being. At the end of five years progress would be reviewed by an independent Commission, and in the lightof its findings the two Governments would jointly consider thepossibility of proceeding to the final stage of integration, comprisingMaltese representation in the United Kingdom Parliament andultimate comparable living standards. There was some reason tobelieve that Mr. Mintoff might prove responsive to proposals onthese lines.The Lord Chancellor said that, while Mr. Mintoffs attitude wasdisappointing, it would be unwise to reject any opportunity of encouraging a dependent territory to seek to develop a closer
relationship with the United Kingdom. He therefore favoured afresh approach to the problem, on the lines which the colonial secretary had suggested.The Prime Minister said that the situation which had now arisenrequired careful consideration. It should be sufficient, for themoment, to acknowledge Mr. Mintoffs latest communication.Thereafter the proposals in C. (57) 98 should be examined in greater detail, initially by officials and subsequently by the ministerial committee on Malta. This examination should take account ofthe possible adjustment of our strategic interests in Malta as wellas the constitutional and economic development of the Island. Itwould also be for consideration whether, in any resumption of negotiations with Mr. Mintoff on the lines which the colonial secretary proposed, it would be wise to make a limited offer initiallyand to hold in reserve the further concessions which we might need to make.The Cabinet-(1) Authorised the Colonial Secretary formally to acknowledge the communication from the Prime Minister of Maltarejecting our latest offer of financial assistance.(2) Invited the Colonial Secretary to arrange that the proposals in C. (57) 98 should be further examined, initially by officials and subsequently by the Ministerial Committeeon Malta, in the light of the points made in their discussion.Medals and 7.   The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that he proposedAwards. to recommend to The Queen that, following the precedents whichCyprus and     had been established in respect of operations in Palestine, KenyaPort Said.       and Malaya, General Service Medals with clasp &quot;Cyprus&quot; shouldbe awarded for service in Cyprus.  It would be appropriate that thesame General Service Medals, with clasp &quot; Near East,&quot; should be awarded for service in the recent operations in Port Said.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of this statement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,17th April, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
