<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 300-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1957SECRETCC. (57)43rd conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Wednesday, 29th May, 1957, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. George Ward, M.P.,Secretary of State for Air (Item 1).The Right Hon. The Earl of Perth,Minister of State for Colonial Affairs(Item 9).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.51760-1Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.&quot;Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.Mr. J. M. Wilson.
contents minute no. subject      H.M. The Queen       ......Flight in Comet Aircraft.2      Parliament       ...      ...      ...&quot;3      East/West Trade4      Commercial PolicyUnited States Tariff on Wool Goods.5      Jordan6      International Labour OrganisationVocational Training in Agriculture.7      Wages and Prices8      Europe   ......Free Trade Area.9     Malta10      Civil Aviation  ...Independent Airlines.
Parliament. 2.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.It was proposed that Parliament should be adjourned on 7th June for the Whitsun Recess until Tuesday, 25th June.The statement on business to be made on the following day would include an announcement that the Government did not intend to proceed with the Shops Bill in the House of Commons in thecurrent session.3. The Cabinet had before them a draft, circulated at themeeting, of a Parliamentary statement which the Foreign secretary proposed to make on the following day on further relaxations in thecontrol over trade with China.The Foreign Secretary said that the United States Governmenthad continued to maintain their opposition to our proposal tomodify our existing restrictions on this trade. As a result, certain other countries, which had hitherto endorsed our view that therestrictions governing trade with China and the Soviet blocrespectively should be brought into conformity with each other, were beginning to withdraw their support. Nevertheless, we had informed the United States Government, both in 1956 and more recently duringthe Bermuda discussions, that we should not be able to continue indefinitely to impose disproportionate restrictions on trade with china; and in view of the increasing public concern on this matterthere seemed no alternative but to announce publicly our intentionto apply the same restrictions to trade with China as to trade withthe Soviet bloc.Although there would be some support in the United states for our attitude, this decision could be expected to provoke adversecomment in Congress, and the announcement of our intention should therefore be framed in as conciliatory a manner as possible. he proposed to make it clear in his statement that we intended tocontinue our established policy of co-operating with our friends andallies in a system of controls on trade with both the Soviet bloc and china in the mutual security interest.In discussion there was general agreement with this proposal.Even if our decision provoked an unfavourable reaction in theUnited States, it was unlikely to do any lasting damage to therelations between the two countries. On the other hand, the perpetuation of separate control lists for China and the Soviet blocwould give rise to increasing difficulty in Parliament and with industry, and the risk of repeated disagreement with the UnitedStates over the treatment of particular cases was likely in the longer term to prove more damaging to the relations between the twocountries.East/west trade.(previous reference:CC. (57) 13thConclusions,Minute 7.)51760-1H.M. The 1.   The Prime  Minister  said  that  it  was  proposed  thatQueen. H.M. The Queen should travel in a Comet aircraft of the RoyalFlight in Comet Air Force Transport Command when paying her forthcoming visitAircraft. to Fighter Command in Scotland on 4th June. In view of the unfortunate history of the earlier types of this aircraft he had thoughtit right to bring this proposal to the notice of the Cabinet. He didnot, however, suggest that any objection should be raised. TheComet was in fact the most exhaustively tested aircraft now in use by the Royal Air Force.The Cabinet agreed that no objection should be raised to theproposal that The Queen should travel to Scotland in a Cometaircraft of Transport Command.
The Cabinet Authorised the Foreign Secretary to make a statement inthe House of Commons on the following day, in the termsof the draft which he had circulated, defining our future policy in regard to control over trade with China.Commercial 4.   The   Cabinet  were  informed  that  the  United  states policy. Government had decided to double the ad valorem rate of duty(Previous (while leaving the additional specific duty unchanged) on importsReference: of wool goods into the United States in excess of 5 per cent, of theC.C. (57) 4lst domestic production of these goods.   It was agreed that a protestConclusions, should be lodged against this action.Minute 4.)The Cabinet United States Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with theTariff on President of the Board of Trade, to arrange for a protestWool Goods. to be addressed to the United States Government against their recent decision to raise the tariff on imported woolgoods.Jordan. 5.   The Cabinet were informed that the prospects of securing(Previous        from the Government of Jordan the over-flying and staging rightsReference:      which we were seeking now appeared to be more favourable. It had .C, (57) 40th   also been possible to devise a procedure for the ceremonial transferConclusions,    of the Royal Air Force base at Mafraq on 31st May which should minute 1.)      minimise the embarrassment implicit in the fact that we were not atpresent in diplomatic relationship with Egypt, Saudi Arabia or Syria.It was agreed that it would be appropriate if arrangements weremade for the Commanding Officer of the R.A.F. units stationed inthe Middle East to be present at this ceremony.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Defence, in consultation with theForeign Secretary, to arrange for the Commanding Officerof the Royal Air Force units in the Middle East to attend the ceremony at which the base at Mafraq would betransferred to the Jordanian Air Force on 31st May.international labour organisation.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 13thConclusions,Minute 9.)vocational training inAgriculture.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofLabour (C. (57) 125) proposing that Recommendation No. 101 onvocational training in agriculture, which the International LabourConference had adopted in 1956, should be accepted, and should be announced in a White Paper which would state that the law and practice of the United Kingdom were generally in conformity withthe provisions of the recommendation.The Cabinet-Approved the proposal in C. (57) 125.Wages and prices.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 41stConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Minister of Labour (C. (57) 126) covering a reportby the Joint Permanent Secretary to the Treasury and the permanent secretary of the Ministry of Labour on the results of their discussions with representatives of industry about the proposal to constitute a body to report on prices, production and incomes.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the proposals in thisreport regarding the terms of reference and the title of the new bodyseemed likely to be generally acceptable to the interests concerned.
On the size and composition of the body, however, divergent views had been expressed by the representatives of industry, and it wouldbe necessary to consider further whether the body should be a smallone, composed of three independent persons with no industrialaffiliations or a larger one, consisting of perhaps five members, ofwhom at least two would be able to speak with knowledge on industrial matters, or an even larger one, providing for adequate representation of all the main interests involved. These possibilitiesmight be further explored in the more formal approach to industry which should now be made. This approach should be based on amemorandum outlining the Governments proposals; and thediscussions should be conducted, on the Government side, by ministers.The Prime Minister said that, although there was much to besaid for constituting some kind of independent body to report on prices, production and incomes, the Cabinet should recognise the dangers inherent in the proposals as they had now taken shape. Asmall body, consisting of three independent persons of goodwill andsound judgment, could perhaps fulfil a useful function. But ifthe membership was extended to provide representation for bothsides of industry, it was unlikely that the Councils findings would be wholly uninfluenced by sectional considerations. This fact was themore important in that it was apparently envisaged by all therepresentatives of industry who had been consulted that the council should be free to criticise the actions of the Government. If thisimplied that the Council would be at liberty to suggest that, forexample, the objective of stable prices could be more easily realisedif the Government would adopt a policy of subsidy or price controls,the potential embarrassment to the Government could be serious.In discussion it was agreed that, while the proposals before theCabinet clearly involved risks of the kind to which the Prime minister had drawn attention, these must be weighed against the advantages which might result from the establishment of a body empowered toprovide authoritative guidance on the questions comprised in theterms of reference. It would, however, be desirable to ensure, in subsequent discussions with industry, that the composition of theCouncil, as finally established, reflected the Governments originalconception of a small body of independent persons who would notbe representative of particular interests or points of view. It wouldalso be necessary to make it clear, either in the terms of reference orin the exploratory statement which would accompany the publicationof the proposals, that the Council would be expected to adhereclosely to their remit and would not be authorised to make pro-nouncements or recommendations on broader issues of economic policy.In further discussion of the terms of reference the followingpoints were made:  -(a) It was for consideration whether the words &quot; full employment &quot; should not be replaced by the words &quot; a high and stable level of employment.&quot; If, however, the conception of &quot; full employment&quot; was more likely to command the assent of the tradeunions, the point need not be pressed.(b) The reference to &quot; stable prices&quot; should perhaps be expanded, in order to guard against any implication that stable prices could always be ensured, regardless of changes in world economicconditions. The phrase &quot; reasonable stability of prices &quot; might be preferable.(c) There was some risk of ambiguity in requiring the Council toreport from time to time on the &quot; significance&quot; of changes in productivity, prices and incomes. It might therefore be wiser todelete the reference to &quot; the significance of such changes &quot; and to
Europe. g   jne Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, as a result of theFree Trade recent discussions between the Prime Minister and the FederalArea. German Chancellor and his own talks with French Ministers, we now(Previous        had some assurance that, as soon as the signatories of the Treaty ofReference:      Rome had ratified that Treaty, they would be willing to renew theirCC. (57) 38th   discussions with us about the constitution of a Free Trade Area.   for conclusions,    the time being, however, progress towards the Free Trade Area would minute 5.)      inevitably be rather slower than we had originally hoped.   Themeeting of the Council of the Organisation for European economic co-operation (O.E.E.C.) on this subject would need to be deferred until September; and we should employ the interval to explore more fully the implications of the Free Trade Area, and to discuss our proposals with officials from Commonwealth countries at a meetingimmediately after the forthcoming Conference of commonwealth prime Ministers.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) There was some risk that Denmark, and perhaps the otherScandinavian countries, would feel obliged in self-protection to join the Common Market to be established under the Treaty of Rome.It would be to our advantage to discourage them from doing so, andit would therefore be desirable to give them as much reassurance aspossible about the treatment of agricultural products within the framework of our proposals. The precise terms of any assurance ofthis kind would, however, need careful consideration, since it would remain uncertain, until after the forthcoming discussions with othermembers of the Commonwealth, how far we should be able to modifyour own attitude on this issue, and it would in any event be wise, asa matter of tactics, to defer until the latest possible stage in the resumed discussions in O.E.E.C. the announcement of any change inour policy in respect of agriculture products.(b) There were indications of a growing sympathy in Europe fora federal approach to the problems of capital development and an increasing conviction that, if these problems were tackled on a sufficiently large and imaginative scale, it would be possible for europe to achieve, relatively rapidly, a standard of living comparable with that of the United States. We could not afford to dissociateourselves from a movement of this kind; and we must press on withour own preparations for the constitution of a Free Trade area without allowing ourselves to be distracted or impeded by theobstruction of the French Government. It was becoming increasingly clear, however, that the political and technical problems involved were extremely complex; and it might become necessary tomake special arrangements for the handling of these problems.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Foreign Secretary, the President of the Board of Tradeand the Minister of Agriculture, to consider the possibilityof giving the Danish Government some reassurance aboutthe treatment of agricultural products in the context ofrequire the Council merely &quot; to keep under review changes in productivity, prices and the level of incomes (including wages, salaries and profits) and to report thereon from time to time.&quot;The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Ministerof Labour to initiate further discussions with representativesof industry, on the basis of a memorandum outlining the government&apos;s proposals as amended in their discussion.
7 CC. 43 (57)our proposals for a Free Trade Area, which might encourage them to resist pressure to join the EuropeanCommon Market.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion at a subsequent meeting.9. The Cabinet were informed of recent developments in thenegotiations with the Maltese Government about the future constitutional and economic development of Malta.The Minister of State for Colonial Affairs said that the maltese government had again rejected the proposals for integration and had described the suggested alternative of interim arrangements covering the next five years as such a radical departure from previous policy that they would need to consult the Maltese people about them.They proposed therefore to publish, on 4th June, a White Paper onthe recent negotiations. The Malta Committee had recommendedthat an immediate reply should be sent to the Maltese Government,expressing regret at their continued rejection of the proposals forintegration, denying that the alternative arrangements representedany change in policy, and asking that publication of the MalteseWhite Paper should be deferred in order that the United KingdomGovernment could prepare a White Paper for simultaneouspublication in this country. The Governor of Malta considered thatthe Prime Minister of Malta might now demand independence for the island, and that, in this event, he might obtain the support of theother local political Parties.In discussion it was agreed that, if the Maltese Government werenot prepared to postpone the publication of their White Paper, itwould be necessary that the United Kingdom White Paper shouldalso be published on 4th June. It would therefore be desirable tobring forward, to the following day, the meeting between the PrimeMinister and the Labour Party members of the former Round table conference on Malta, in order to avoid any impression that theGovernment had reached a final decision before these members hadbeen consulted.In further discussion it was suggested that the alternative offer which we had made to the Maltese Government, involving substantial assistance from the United Kingdom Exchequer during an interim period of five years, might be more readily accepted by public opinon as a reasonable response to the Maltese demand for &quot; economicequivalence &quot; if it was coupled with some definite action on our part to foster the development of the Island and to increase the productivity of its industries. We might therefore offer to appoint an eminentindustrialist or a small expert committee to encourage theestablishment of new industries in Malta and to advise and assist the maltese Government in the economic expansion of Malta during the interim period. This individual, or committee, could be asked toreport on the progress achieved at the end of the five years, so thatthe two Governments could consider whether a reasonable degree of&quot; economic equivalence &quot; was practicable in the event of integration.The terms of reference for this task would need, however, to be carefully defined in order to preclude the Maltese Government from using the enquiry merely to assess the amount of subsidy requiredby Malta in order to achieve &quot; equivalence&quot; with the UnitedKingdom. An offer 5on these lines should be made forthwith to the maltese Government, and the proposal should either be mentioned,if possible, in the forthcoming United Kingdom White Paper, or be announced as rapidly as possible thereafter.Strategically, Malta was no longer essential as a naval base, andthe implications of this fact could be made plain to the maltese government if they eventually declared a policy of independence of malta.(previous reference:CC. (57) 38thConclusions,Minute 7.)
the United Kingdom. It would be important, however, that we shouldnot allow the discussions with the Maltese Government to reach thispoint until we had clearly demonstrated that we had taken everyreasonable step to satisfy their demands.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Colonial Secretary to arrange for a proposal onthe lines agreed in discussion to be put to the maltese government.(2) Invited the Lord Chancellor, in consultation with the colonial secretary, to take account of the points raised in discussion in the preparation of the White Paper to bepublished in this country on the recent negotiations withthe Maltese Government.CivilAviation.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 42ndConclusions,Minute 6.)IndependentAirlines.10. The Minister of Civil Aviation said that the negotiations between the Central African Airways Corporation and the british overseas Airways Corporation (B.O.A.C.) had brought to a head thedifficulties which arose in connection with the limitations at presentimposed on the independent airline companies. The Air transport advisory Council (A.T.A.C.) had recently recommended that therestriction whereby the independent airlines were limited to the use of sub-standard aircraft on &quot; Colonial coach&quot; services should beremoved. He considered that this recommendation should beaccepted. The removal of this restriction was likely to be opposed by the B.O.A.C., but it would be in keeping with the Governmenfsrepeated undertakings to provide more scope for the independent air transport companies. As a further measure to help these independentcompanies, he was examining with the other Ministers concerned the possibility of giving them longer term contracts for trooping.He hoped to be able to make a statement in Parliament in the nearfuture about future policy towards the independent airlines. In themeantime it would be helpful if Government supporters in the Houseof Commons who were interested in civil aviation could be toldinformally about the Governmenfs intention to implement therecommendation of the AT.A.C.The Cabinet-Authorised the Minister of Civil Aviation to informGovernment supporters in the House of Commons of the government&apos;s intention to implement the recommendationof the Air Transport Advisory Council in favour of theremoval of the restriction limiting the independent airlinesto the use of sub-standard aircraft.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29th May, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
