<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 409-412</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC M,UE.STY&apos;S governmentPrinted for the Cabinet. July 1957SECRET    ICC. (57)58(h CotsclussoasCopy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held a: 10 Downing Street, S.W. /on Monday, 29th July, 1957, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P.. Prime minister the Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycrofi,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President :of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService, :f &apos;The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The -Right Hon. Viscount Kjlmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. D. Hbathcoat Amory.M.P., Minister of Agriculture, Fish-eries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Mousing and Local Oov-ernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Minisieiof Power.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present :The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance.The Right Hon. Ernest Marples, Ml&apos;.Postmasier-General.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
ContentsPensions.
PmAwm. :7...The Cabinet had before them memoranda, by the Homem&amp;nom      &quot;Secretary, the Minister of Pensions and the Chancellor of thec.c ^7?56th, P^W? (C (57) 177, 180 and 181) about pensions.. Conclusions,-,-if.1&apos;. -- ^-  -Minute 5.) r,The Prime Minister said that it was clear that an increase in the.. .. /National Insurance, pension should be. brought into effect as soon aspossible  and &apos; that, if  the  Cabinet  approved in  principle  a-supplementary pensions scheme, its introduction must form the&quot;.. subject of separate and subsequent legislation.  On this assumptionIt was necessary to decide the date on which the increase in then a^ionai Insurance pension should take effect and the amount by&apos;&apos;; which both benefits &apos;and contributions under the National Insurance/scheme should be raised...     In discussion^ there was general agreement that any attempt toensure that an increase in the National Insurance pension would be&apos; ; operative by Christmas would be open to considerable objection. In.  &quot;partibular, ;t would imply that the Government would be preventediromacceptm the passageof the necessary legislation through Parliament and that pension order books providing for payment of benefit at the new rate would be in. Uthe hands of the public before any statutory authority for the payment.fbf that rate had been! obtained.  Moreover, any interruption of theiParhamentary. time-table would involve the risk that extra-statutory: i payments on an unprecedented scale would have to be made.   It&apos; &apos;would,&apos;therefore, be desirable that the legislation should be introduced;either after the reassembly of Parliament at the end of October (inwhich case it would have to be reintroduced at the beginning of the,1957-58 session) or at the outset of the new session, and that itshould thereafter take its normal course, receiving the Royal Assentshortly after the middle of November.The Cabinet were informed, however, that on this hypothesis itwould remain necessary that the order for the printing of newcontribution stamps should be given to the Stationery Office in mid-August and that the administrative preparations for the consequential adjustments of war pensions should begin about thesame date. In each case there was some risk of a premature disclosure of the Governmenfs intentions. It was suggested that this risk mightbe reduced by confining the initial authority to the engraving of thenecessary dies for the stamps with adequate security precautions and: by deferring until mid-October the administrative preparations for the/increase in war pensions, even if, as a result, the new pensions couldnot become payable until the end of January or early in February and war pensioners did not, as hitherto, receive their increases materiallyin advance of other pensioners. It would also be necessary to ensure,as far as possible, that any increase in National Assistance rates shouldbe deferred until the increase in National Insurance pensions hadtaken effect or was clearly in prospect.Discussion then turned to the amount of the increase in theNational Insurance pension. It was generally agreed that an additionof 10*., provided that it was accompanied by a withdrawal of thetobacco concession, would be preferable to an addition of 55. or75. 6d. which left the concession intact. It would, however, bedesirable to ensure that the increase was presented as part of a comprehensive attempt to put the finances of the National Insurancescheme on a sound basis by the introduction of a supplementary pensions scheme on a graduated basis. On this hypothesis theNational-Insurance contribution would need to be increased to \ls.6d.,an increase of about 45. over the rate at which it would stand at thebeginning of September. On an actuarial basis, however, the contribution which could be justified by an increase of 105. in the rateof benefit would be only i65. 5d. The margin between this figure andthe proposed contribution of 17s 6d. represented the additional sumwhich would need to be obtained from contributions if the increasingdeficit which the National Insurance scheme would otherwise incur
during the period before any supplementary pensions scheme couldbecome operative was to be held in check. Nevertheless, an increaseof nearly 4s. in the rate of contribution, of which approximately halfwould have to be paid by the employee, represented a sharp rise incpntribution liability which might constitute a further stimulus toinflationary pressure; and it was for consideration whether, in viewof the relief to the Exchequer which a supplementary pensions scheme would provide in due course, the increase in the National insurance contribution should be limited, in the interim, to the lower figure of16s. 5d. Alternatively, it might be preferable to increase the contribution to 18j. Id. and at the same time to increase the rate ofbenefit by 12.y. rather than by \Os., thereby ensuring to all pensioners,whether they took advantage of the tobacco concession or not, anincrease of a clear 10s. in their pension. On this basis, the contribution liability would be no more than Id. higher than the11s. 6d. which would be payable, on the more conservative hypothesis,in respect of an increase of 10.$. in the rate of pension; and an increaseof 12s. was more likely than an increase of 10.?. to avoid the necessityfor any further improvement in the rate of pension during theremainder of the life-time of the present Parliament.As regards a supplementary pensions scheme, there was generalagreement in principle that there would be considerable advantage in introducing a scheme of this kind. It was urged, however, that itshould incorporate a provision whereby individuals alreadyparticipating in approved occupational pensions schemes should beentitled to contract out of the graduated element in the benefits ofthe new scheme. In the absence of any provision of this kind thenecessary legislation would not contribute to the greater mobility oflabour or carry a clear indication of the Governmenfs approval of occupational schemes in general. Moreover, the scheme wouldappear to be more inflexible than the proposals published by theOpposition which, at least in theory, envisaged provision for contracting out. On the other hand, the principle of contracting out,if accepted, might adversely affect the finances of the new scheme toa serious degree. Nor had the insurance companies, who had been consulted confidentially, attached any great importance to the&quot;  inclusion of a provision for this purpose.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that itappeared to be generally accepted that the tobacco concession shouldbe withdrawn as part of an operation whereby the basic rate ofNational Insurance pension would be increased by either 10.v. or \2s.and a supplementary pensions scheme would be introduced. Thepreparatory work for the increase in the basic pension should be sotimed as to involve no substantial risk of anticipation of Parliamentaryauthority or premature disclosure of the Governmenfs intentions, butalso to secure, if possiole, that the increased rate of pension wouldbecome payable by the end of January or very early in February.Any adjustment in National Assistance rates should be related as closely as possible to this time-table.It would be desirable that the National Insurance Committeeshould give further consideration to these issues, which would need to be finally settled by the Cabinet at a meeting later in the week.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Home Secretary to arrange for the national insurance Committee to undertake a more detailed examination of the issues which had been raised during their discussion.(2) Agreed to resume consideration of pensions policy at a subsequent meeting.

</content>
</cab>
