<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 427-432</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1957SECRET Copy No.C.C. (57)61st conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W.1, on Friday, 2nd August, 1957, at 2-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations and Lord Presidentof the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President  of the Board  of. Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and National.Service.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance.The  Right  Hon.  Ernest  Marples,M.P., Postmaster-General.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.
contents minute no. Subject page 1      Cabinet ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       3Procedure during Recess2      Europe   ......      ...      ...      ...      .........       3Free trade area      Export of Aircraft      ...      ...      ...      ...      ......       3Proposed sale of Viscount aircraft to EgyptProposed sale of Britannia aircraft to the U.S.A.4      Pensions.........      ...      ...      ......     ...       4Timing of increasesRate of increase in basic pensionSupplementary pension scheme
Cabinet.ProcedureduringRecess.1, The Prime Minister said that it should not be necessary forany of the main Standing Committees of the Cabinet to meet during august and September, and that the Cabinet would dispose of anyurgent business which would ordinarily be submitted to thoseCommittees during that period. He hoped that it would not benecessary to summon the Cabinet during the first half of August.Thereafter meetings would be arranged as business required andshould be attended by those Ministers who were within easy reach of London.Europe.Free trade area.(previous reference :CC. (57) 43rdConclusions,Minute 8.)2. The Prime Minister said that he had reached the conclusionthat there would be advantage in arranging for a single Ministerto be responsible for co-ordinating the preparations for theforthcoming negotiations in connection with the European free trade Area and for supervising the conduct of those discussions.He had decided, with the agreement of the Minister of Power, thatthe Paymaster-General should be entrusted with this responsibility,and he proposed to make an announcement to that effect during theforthcoming week.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers statement.Export of aircraft.Proposed saleof Viscountaircraft to egypt.Proposedsale ofBritanniaaircraft tothe U.S.A.3. The President of the Board of Trade said that a proposedsale of two Viscount aircraft to Egypt had attracted attention in thePress. No application, however, had yet been made for an export licence for these aircraft; and it was doubtful whether it would be justifiable to permit this transaction to be completed while Britishclaims against Egypt remained unsatisfied.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was open to theEgyptian authorities to employ such free resources as theycommanded in making purchases in this country, and we had agreedthat the purposes for which the new Special Account might be usedshould be subject to no limitations. It had already been decidedthat an embargo on trade would be an ineffective means of bringing pressure to bear on the Egyptian Government.The Prime Minister said that authority for this transactionshould be withheld until he had had an opportunity to considerit in greater detail.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Minister of Defence and the President of the Boardof Trade, to arrange for details of the proposed sale oftwo Viscount aircraft to Egypt to be reported to thePrime Minister.(2) Agreed that authority for the sale of the two Viscountaircraft should be withheld, pending further considerationby the Prime Minister.The Minister of Civil Aviation said that a United Statescompany, Trans-World Airlines, was negotiating for the purchaseof fifteen long-range Britannia aircraft, to be delivered in 1958. Ifthis transaction was completed, the delivery of Britannia aircraft to Transport Command and the British Overseas airways corporation, as well as to other customers, would have to be deferred. It would be premature, however, to attempt to reach adecision on this proposal at the present stage, since the time-table for the delivery of these aircraft had fallen into arrear and certain
mtechnical difficulties had hitherto prevented him from issuing thenecessary certificate of airworthiness. He would keep the PrimeMinister informed of any further developments during the recess.The Cabinet- (3) Took note of this statement.Pensions.(previous reference :CC. (57) 58thConclusions.)Timing of increases.Rate of increase in basic pension.4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (57) 186) about pensions.The Home Secretary said that, on the basis of the arrangementsoutlined in the Annex to C. (57) 186, increases in National insurance and war pensions could be put into operation in the week beginning27th January, 1958.The Minister of Pensions said that these arrangements were based on the assumption that the Royal Assent to the national insurance Bill would be obtained by 23rd November, If that bill was also to provide for the withdrawal of the tobacco concession,it might need to be preceded by a Ways and Means Resolution whichmight delay its enactment by about a week. Nevertheless, theannouncement calling in National Insurance pension books wouldhave to be made in the week beginning 25th November.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the timing of the increases in pensions shouldbe as proposed in the Annex to C. (57) .186.The Home Secretary said that the balance of advantage appearedto lie in increasing the basic rate of National Insurance pension byIQs. and that, on the assumption that a supplementary pension scheme on a graduated basis would be introduced in due course,the contribution under the National Insurance scheme should beraised to 11 s. 6d. To increase the basic rate of pension to 125. wouldinvolve an increase in the contribution to at least I85. Id. and aconsiderable revision of the supplementary scheme. It would alsoimply that the Government foresaw an indefinite continuance of inflation.In discussion it was pointed out that, if the basic rate of pensionwas increased by io5. but the tobacco concession was withdrawnat the same time, the real benefit to those pensioners who had takenadvantage of that concession would be no more than Is. Sd. Ofthis figure 45. 2d. had already been absorbed by the rise in pricessince the last increase in National Insurance benefits. If, therefore,the Government were to adhere to their intention to make no further improvement in National Insurance benefits during the remainder of the lifetime of the present Parliament, there would remain only35. 6d. as the effective margin to protect pensioners against anyfurther price increases in that period. In these circumstances it was for consideration whether it would be wiser to increase the basic rate of pension by 125. On the other hand, an increase of this order would have a more inflationary impact on the economy than anincrease of lOs. Moreover, the lower figure should suffice for some considerable time ahead; and if, in the event, it was overtaken to a significant extent by an increase of prices towards the end of thepresent Parliament, the Government would be compelled to concedesome further improvement, however inopportune it might be to do so.The Cabinet (2) Agreed that-the basic rate of National Insurance pension should be increased by 105.; that the tobacco concession should be withdrawn; and that the contribution shouldbe increased to 175. 6d.
Supplementary The Home Secretary said that, after further consideration of apension supplementary pension scheme on a graduated basis, the national scheme. Insurance Committee reaffirmed their view that the Governmentshould approve in principle the introduction of such a scheme. Itmight not be welcomed by the more highly paid section of thepopulation, whose contribution liability would be greater than undera flat-rate scheme. On the other hand, it would reduce the liability of the lower-paid workers; and it would provide, in addition, a significant relief to the Exchequer. This relief would, however,be diminished by any provision enabling individuals alreadyparticipating in private occupational pensions schemes to contract out of the graduated element in the benefits of the new scheme;and all the possible modifications in the scheme designed to enable it to incorporate a provision of this kind were open to objectioneither from the potential contributors or from the private insurance companies. The National Insurance Committee recommended,therefore, that the practicability of a provision permitting contracting-out should be further examined and that, if such a provision proved to be irreconcilable with a satisfactory scheme of graduated pensions,the development of occupational pension schemes should be encouraged by other means.The Minister of Pensions said that he was strongly in favourof the inclusion of the principle of contracting-out in any scheme of graduated pensions. Any consequential diminution in the additional revenue which the Exchequer would derive from such a scheme would be offset by a corresponding reduction in the ultimate liability of the scheme to the contributors. Moreover, contracting-out wasa feature of the supplementary pension scheme recently published by the Opposition, and Government proposals which implied thatcontributors to the new scheme would pay a higher proportionatecontribution and receive a smaller pension than under the Socialistscheme but would not enjoy any corresponding option to contract out would be inconsistent with the Governmenfs political principles and fail to command the support of the Conservative Party. his acceptance of a supplementary scheme in principle was, therefore,dependent on its incorporating some provision for contracting-out;and he proposed that a more detailed examination of this provision should be put in hand as a matter of urgency.In discussion this view received some support. It was urged,in particular, that the pension schemes in the nationalised industriesmight be adversely affected by the introduction of a government scheme of supplementary pensions which did not permit contracting-out. On the other hand, the insurance companies themselves had indicated a preference for a scheme which did not incorporate theprinciple of contracting-out. And it would only be possible to limit to Ms. 6d. the increased contribution appropriate to an increase of10s. in the basic rate of National Insurance pension if it could beassumed that a graduated pension scheme would be introduced ona financially sound basis.In further discussion it was agreed that officials should be instructed to prepare, as a matter of urgency, a detailed scheme of graduated pensions on two alternative hypotheses, the first including,the second excluding, a provision for contracting-out. On theformer hypothesis a distinction should also be drawn betweencontracting-out by individuals who were already, at the date of introduction of the scheme, participating in approved occupational pensions schemes and those who might decide thereafter to becomecontributors to schemes of this kind, whether such schemes were already in existence or were to be newly established.The Cabinet (3) Invited the Minister of Pensions to arrange, as a niatter of urgency, for officials to prepare detailed proposals for
Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,2nd August, 1957.a supplementary pension scheme on a graduated basis on the two alternative hypotheses that such a scheme ;*would include, or exclude, a provision entitlingindividuals already participating in approvedoccupational pension schemes to contract out of the graduated element in the benefits of the new scheme.

</content>
</cab>
