<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 473-480</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1957SECRET .        Copy No. 42CC. (57)69th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 19th September, 1957, at 10-30 a.mtPresent:&apos;The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Davtd Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right  Hon.  Geoffrey  Lloyd.M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Pensions and national Insurance (Items 1 and 2).The following were also present:The Right Hon. D. Ormsby-Gore,M.P., Minister of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. J. M. Wilson.Mr. I. P. Bancroft.52360-43
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1      Economic Situation    .........      ......... 32     Pensions.........      ...      ......... 33     Sudan......................      ... 54      Commonwealth Affairs        ................       6Meeting of Commonwealth Finance MinistersAnglo-Canadian Trade
The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of this statement.EconomicSituation(previous reference:CC. (57) 68thConclusions,Minute 3)Pensions(previous reference:CC. (57) 61stConclusions,Minute 4)2. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Ministerof Pensions and the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C. (57) 205 and 214)about pensions.The Minister of Pensions said that, in accordance with the wishes of the Cabinet at their last discussion of this subject, he had attempted to evolve a scheme of supplementary pensions whichwould include a contracting-out provision but would be at least as advantageous to the Exchequer as the proposals which the cabinet had considered in August. This new scheme was not likely to be politically popular or to appear to offer an attractive alternative tothe proposals recently published by the Socialist Party. Nevertheless,it had several advantages by comparison with the earlier scheme. Itdispensed with the conception that graduation should be appliedbelow, as well as above, the &quot; cross-bar,&quot; and substituted the concept of a fiat-rate contribution up to the &quot; cross-bar &quot; with graduationonly above that level. As a result the whole of the contributionabove the flat-rate base would be applied, on an actuarial basis, tothe supplementary pension, and the maximum entitlement of acontributor would be significantly greater than under the earlierscheme. Moreover, under the new scheme it would no longer benecessary, as it would have been under the earlier proposals, to collect from low-paid workers a lump sum to bring the pensionelement in their contributions up to the rate applicable in the caseof Class 3 contributors, a measure which would&apos; press very heavily on workers who normally lived from week to week. Finally, thenew scheme avoided the difficulty, inherent in the earlier proposals,of introducing simultaneously in the forthcoming Session a Bill whichwould increase the level of contributions under the existing national insurance scheme and a second Bill which would foreshadow areduction of some contributions in 1960. This procedure would inevitably provoke strong pressure against the initial increase; andhis own proposals would remove this danger by maintaining, upto the &quot; cross-bar,&quot; a fiat-rate contribution at the level to be indicated by the forthcoming National Insurance Bill.The interests concerned in the private sector, i.e., the Life offices and the Association of Superannuation and Pension Funds, had expressed a preference for the earlier proposals on the ground thattheir scope was small and would not be likely to embarrass theinsurance companies. They had been more divided on the questionof including a contracting-out provision in the scheme which he himself now recommended; but the Association had tended to favour the inclusion of such a provision if the contribution liability was likely to exceed 2s. 6d.*1. The Prime Minister said that, after further consultation withthe Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Governor of the Bank ofEngland, he had reached the conclusion that the Government should accept the view of the Bank that Bank Rate should be increasedto 7 per cent. The Rate had not stood at this level since 1920 orrisen so sharply except on the outbreak of a major war.Nevertheless, an increase of this order appeared to be inevitable.In present circumstances, the Government should not hesitate toadopt any measure, however drastic, which might assist in maintaining the parity of sterling. Moreover, the advice of the Bankwas unanimous and had been strongly represented by the Governor.The Government would carry a very heavy responsibility if theyrejected this advice and subsequently found that they had failed to deploy an essential reinforcement of their other economic measures.
He remained unconvinced of the desirability of introducing any government scheme of graduated supplementary pensions. If,however, the Cabinet were, in principle, in favour of the introductionof such a scheme, he believed that, for the reasons which he had given, the proposals outlined in C. (57) 205 were preferable to theearlier scheme.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he did not share thisview. The proposals in C. (57) 205 did not constitute a graduated scheme of the kind which the Cabinet had contemplated in earlier discussions. They merely superimposed a separate element ofgraduation on the existing flat-rate scheme. Nor did they allowgenuine contracting-out. The self-employed man could not choose to be included in the graduated scheme; the employed man couldnot choose to be excluded unless his employer so proposed.Moreover, the employer could do so only if his own scheme complied with certain conditions and he was willing to submit to certaincontrols. According to his decision, all his employees would either be compulsorily excluded (including those who might wish to beincluded) or compulsorily included (including those who might wishto be excluded).The interests concerned in the private sector had indicated thatthey would oppose a scheme on the lines indicated in C. (57) 205,whether it included a contracting-out provision or not. Moreover,the Minister of Pensions had admitted that this scheme had littlepolitical attraction. In the light of these facts, the effective choicelay between either abandoning the whole project of a supplementary pensions scheme and resting simply on the forthcoming increase in national Insurance benefits or adopting a graduated scheme of thekind envisaged in the Cabinet&apos;s earlier discussions in the knowledge that it would be acceptable to the private sector and would not be inconsistent with Conservative principles.In discussion, it was emphasised that the exclusion of a contracting-out provision from any Government scheme would be politically unwelcome to the Governmenfs supporters and wouldalso be resented by the workers, who attached considerable value to their existing occupational pension schemes. In so far as thescheme outlined in C. (57) 205 incorporated a contracting-outprovision, it might be preferable to the earlier proposals. Neitherthose proposals nor the new scheme, however, would compare favourably with the proposals recently published by the SocialistParty. It might be wiser, therefore, to confine legislative action inthe forthcoming Session to the Bill to improve National insurance benefits and to defer until the following Session any legislation on amore comprehensive scheme. In the interval a fresh attempt couldbe made to devise a scheme which would be likely to be more acceptable politically and would include the type of contracting-outprovision which would be genuinely in accordance with Conservativeprinciples. It could not be assumed that, by 1960, the earliest date on which any new scheme could take effect, the conception of compulsory saving, on which a graduated pensions scheme wasultimately founded, would necessarily be politically attractive. Ifthe economic measures which the Government were now takingsucceeded in their purpose, the general public might be more likelyto resume the habit of voluntary saving, and it might prove more advantageous in the long-term to adopt measures which wouldenable the Life Offices to attract these savings through occupational schemes or otherwise.On the other hand it had already been established by exhaustivediscussion in the Ministerial Committee on National Insurance thatthere were serious objections to any scheme, such as that which the life Offices themselves had originally devised, whereby contributors
Sudan(previous reference:C.C. (57) 28thConclusions,Minute 6)He had therefore suggested to the Sudanese Prime Minister thatthe Sudanese Government should agree to an auction withoutany reserve price, on the understanding that the United KingdomGovernment would endeavour to persuade the Lancashire industryto make a reasonable offer. The Sudanese Prime Minister, however,had rejected this proposal also. Meanwhile, Sudanese stocks were continuing to increase and the export prospects were becoming less favourable since the United States had now started to exportlong-staple cotton.The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs said that the SudaneseGovernment were seeking to negotiate a loan of  2 millions in local currency and  3-5 millions in sterling. The failure of the cottonnegotiations, together with the importance of maintaining friendlypolitical relations with the Sudan in present circumstances, made itdesirable to allow Barclays Bank to meet the Sudanese request. TheSudan was already being subjected to considerable pressure from. The President of the Board of Trade said that in recent discussions about the disposal of the Sudan&apos;s stocks of cotton theLancashire industry had refused to make any purchases unless theSudan Government agreed to auction a substantial proportion ofthe stocks and to reduce the present reserve price by 20 per cent.The Sudanese Prime Minister had rejected this suggestion.Subsequently, the French industry had indicated that, while they themselves could acquire Sudanese cotton only on the basis of barterarrangements, they did not regard the present reserve price asunreasonable. As a result, the Sudanese Prime Minister had been strengthened in his determination not to accept any reduction inthe reserve price which would involve him in domestic political embarrassment.would first be given the opportunity to take advantage of facilities provided by the private sector and the scope of any supplementaryGovernment scheme would be confined to those individuals whowere unable or unwilling, for various reasons, to take advantage ofthose facilities. The Life Offices themselves had abandoned thisconception.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet faced a two-fold decision. It was necessary to decide, onthe assumption that a Government scheme of supplementary pensions on a graduated basis would be instituted, whether theproposals in C. (57) 205 offered significant advantages by comparisonwith those which the Cabinet had considered in August. But it wasalso necessary to reach a prior decision on a more fundamentalissue, namely whether a Government scheme of this nature should beintroduced at all or whether the Government should seek primarily to take their stand on the facilities provided by the private sector and should confine their own efforts to supplementing those facilitieswhere necessary. If, on this latter issue, the Cabinet decided to revert in principle to a scheme similar to that devised by the LifeOffices, it might be necessary to defer the necessary legislative action until the 1958-59 Session in order that the details of such a scheme could be thoroughly worked out. On the other hand there were certain risks in postponing the introduction of this legislation for another year, not least the danger that the original impetus of the project might flag and the Government might appear to have nopolicy to match the Socialist proposals. The Cabinet would need to consider more carefully the various possible courses of action inthe light of these considerations.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion at a subsequent meeting.
r. . 6Egypt to sever her links with the West, and the Soviet Union were offering to purchase the whole of the Sudanese cotton surplus.In discussion it was agreed that it would be incompatible withthe stringent measures which the Government were taking tomaintain the value of sterling to agree at this juncture to a substantialloan to the Sudanese Government. The Sudan might be allowed,however, to draw up to  1 million of the Sudanese sterling balances;and Barclays Bank might be permitted to advance  2 millions in local currency, together with a small sterling loan of the order of 500,000. This loan could be defended as a normal commercialtransaction in the event of any criticism by the Indian government who had recently been refused a much larger sterling loan by theUnited Kingdom Government. In return for these concessions,however, the Sudanese Government should agree to auction asubstantial part of their present cotton stocks without any reserveprice, on the understanding that the Lancashire industry would, ifpossible, be persuaded to make a reasonable offer.The Cabinet Invited the President of the Board of Trade, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to explore with theFinancial Adviser to the Sudanese Government anarrangement on the lines proposed in their discussion andto report the outcome to the Prime Minister.Common-wealthAffairs(previous reference:CC. (57) 62ndConclusions,Minute 2)Meeting ofCommon-wealthFinanceMinisters4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (C. (57) 213) covering briefs by officialsfor the use of the United Kingdom representatives at the forthcoming meeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers and the subsequentAnglo-Canadian discussions on trade matters.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the brief for themeeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers (Annex A to C. (57)213) had been framed in accordance with the Cabinet&apos;s earlier decision that, while our attitude towards the Canadian proposal fora Commonwealth Economic Conference should be reasonablyconstructive, we should be guided by the reactions of the other commonwealth Ministers. If there was a general disposition infavour of a Conference, it would be necessary to decide its site, itstiming, and the level of Governmental representation.The President of the Board of Trade said that it might beimpossible for our representatives to wait upon the reactions of theother Commonwealth Governments, since the representatives ofthose Governments would tend to look to the United Kingdom totake the initiative. It might be to our advantage to support theproposed Economic Conference from the outset, and to provide it with a theme which would be intelligible and politically attractive.It would be embarrassing if the Conference decided to concentratediscussion on such possible subjects as the European Free trade area, the agricultural policy of the United Kingdom, and thepossibility of increased discrimination in trade between Common-wealth countries against the rest of the world. All members of theCommonwealth had, however, a common interest in the conflict between the responsibility of the United Kingdom to fortify thecentral reserves of gold and dollars and the needs of the under-developed Commonwealth countries to secure additional investmentfinance. A rational discussion of this problem, in a spirit of mutualco-operation, might do much to remove misunderstandings and toeducate other Commonwealth countries in economic realities.
In discussion there was general agreement that we should support the proposal for a Commonwealth Economic Conferencein view of the political importance of demonstrating the vitality ofthe Commonwealth conception and its ability to adapt itself, as asystem of individual relationships rather than a closed community,to changes in world economic conditions. It was doubtful, however,whether investment and development should constitute the dominanttheme of such a Conference, since our own contribution to thediscussion would inevitably be limited to a request to other membersof the Commonwealth to rephase their development projects overrather longer periods of time. It might be wiser that the forthcoming meeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers should seek to identifya number of issues which were of substantial Commonwealth interest,such as agricultural policy, investment and the disposals policy ofthe United States, and should remit these for further study by officials in preparation for a subsequent Economic Conference. Such aConference would preferably be held in Canada, the Canadian PrimeMinister presiding and other members of the Commonwealth beingrepresented by their Ministers of Finance or Trade.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, in the light of the unfavourable Canadian reaction to the proposal for an Anglo-Canadian Free Trade Area which the Minister of Agriculture had discussed with Canadian Ministers, it would not be advisable to press this proposal further at the present stage. It would, however, benecessary to discuss with the Canadian Government what public reference should be made to this proposal and to their attitudetowards it. It might also be wise to refrain, in present circumstances,from putting forward the further proposal that we should undertaketo remove discrimination on Canadian imports by a fixed date inreturn for a Canadian undertaking to make a substantial contributionto the central reserves of gold and dollars. Our representatives should, however, be given discretion to explore this possibility withthe Canadian Government if the course of the bilateral discussionsmade it appropriate to do so.The President of the Board of Trade said that the canadian minister of Commerce, who was at present visiting this country,had told him that neither he nor the Canadian Minister for ForeignAffairs agreed with their colleagues in rejecting the United Kingdomproposal for an Anglo-Canadian Free Trade Area. There was some prospect, therefore, that the Canadian decision was not final.,In discussion it was emphasised that the Government shouldnot allow themselves to be placed in a position in which they were unable to reply to public criticism in this country, based on themistaken belief that they had failed to respond constructively to theoffer by the Canadian Prime Minister to divert a substantial proportion of Canadian imports from the United States to the UnitedKingdom. There might be some advantage, therefore, in allowing the proposed Anglo-Canadian Free Trade Area to be further explored in the discussions with Canadian Ministers, if a suitable opportunity arose. We should also seek to ensure that this proposalreceived sufficient publicity to illustrate our readiness, in principle,to engage in a continuous and long-term effort to foster Anglo-Canadian trade.In further discussion support was expressed for the proposal that there should be some limited transfer from United States to canadian securities in the Exchange Equalisation Account, in orderto increase United Kingdom investment in Canada. Such an adjustment appeared to be practicable, provided that it was noteffected too rapidly.
The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Presidentof the Board of Trade to be guided, during the forthcoming meeting of Commonwealth Finance Ministers and the subsequent discussions on Anglo-Canadian trade, by thebriefs annexed to C. (57) 213 and the points made in the cabinet&apos;s discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,19th September, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
