<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 511-517</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1957CC. (57)74th conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 21st October, 1957, at 3-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of the State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The  Right Hon.  Geoffrey Lloyd,M.P., Minister of Education.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The following were also present:The Right Hon. D. Walker-Smith,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Health(Item 3).The Right Hon. D. Ormsby-Gore,M.P., Minister of State for ForeignAffairs (Items 2-5).The Right Hon. Ernest Marples, M.P.,Postmaster-General (Items 3-5).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
contents minute no. Subject page 1      Economic Situation    ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...        3Alleged Leakage of Information2      Washington Talks      ...      ...   ....      ...      ...      ...       33      Wages    ...      .....................       national Health ServicePost Office Engineers4      Compulsory Acquisition of Land: Compensation...      ...        65      Opening of Parliament ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       7Facilities for Television
EconomicSituation.(previous reference :CC. (57) 72ndConclusions,Minute 6.)AllegedLeakage ofInformation.Washington 2.   The Prime Minister said that the United States GovernmentTalks. appeared to be convinced that, in order to counter the Soviet threat,of which the earth satellite was the most recent and most spectacularwarning, the whole structure of Western collaboration needed to bere-examined. They were anxious, in particular, to review the pattern of their relations with the United Kingdom and to develop a closer relationship with this country. He had decided, therefore,to accept an invitation from President Eisenhower to pay animmediate visit to Washington in order to discuss the methods bywhich the collective strength of the free world could be more effectively mobilised. Russia was a formidable antagonist, and its resources, its technical efficiency and its system of government might enable it to maintain its pressure on the democracies for avery considerable time before the Communist ideology finally spentitself. The free world, however, possessed vast resources with which to meet this challenge, provided that they were not dissipated andmisapplied.    His objective  in  the  forthcoming  discussions  in.1. The Prime Minister said that, after the Cabinefs discussion on 8th October, the Opposition Leaders had communicated to theLord Chancellor, in confidence, the information which they hadregarded as constituting prima facie evidence that there had been some premature leakage, of information, from a political source,about the intention to increase the Bank Rate on 19th September.The Lord Chancellor had sifted this information, in an enquiry whichhad involved the questioning of twenty-six persons; and as a resulthe had reached the conclusion that it afforded no prima facie ground for supposing that there had in fact been any leakage of information about the intention to increase the Bank Rate. He had reported this conclusion to the Prime Minister, with the recommendation that therewere not sufficient grounds for holding any further enquiry, whetherby a Select Committee or under the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence)Act, 1921, or otherwise.The Prime Minister said that he had considered very carefullywhether the Lord Chancellor&apos;s report should be published. He had however come to the conclusion that it would be inexpedient to take that course. It would be contrary to precedent. It would also be unfair to the persons, named in the report, who had been examined by the Lord Chancellor without the knowledge that what they saidwould be made public and without the opportunity of being legallyrepresented. Moreover, the report would give scope for debate on matters not directly related to the allegation of a leakage ofinformation about the change in the Bank Rate in particular, therelations between a Government in office and its Party organisation,and the extent to which information about forthcoming announce-ments of Government policy was given in advance to the Press. Inthese circumstances he had come to the conclusion that the best course would be for him to write a letter to the Leader of theOpposition in which, after indicating briefly the nature of the allegations made and of the reasons why they had proved to beill-founded, he would say that the Lord Chancellor had come to theconclusion that there were no grounds for holding any further enquiry and that he proposed to take no further action in the matter.After discussion the Cabinet Agreed that no further enquiry should be held into the allegation that there had been a premature leakage ofinformation about the increase in the Bank Rate on19th September; and took note, with approval, of the terms in which the Prime Minister proposed to communicate thisdecision to the Leader of the Opposition.
Washington would, therefore, be twofold. He would seek, first, towork towards the repeal of the McMahon Act, in order that thetechnical resources of both countries might be organised to giveeffect to a genuine policy of collective defence and that the demands on our own economy might be reduced. Thereafter he would endeavour to establish, unobtrusively and without provoking the suspicion of existing international organisations, a basis on whichjoint Anglo-American machinery might be created for the implementation of an agreed policy towards the political, militaryand economic issues which confronted both Governments,particularly in the Middle East. For these purposes he would be concerned to impress on the United States Government that it was essential to the effective defence of the free world that each country should concentrate on the contribution which it was best equipped to make, that the resources of the Western Powers should not be wasted through lack of co-ordination, and that the democracieswould not be able successfully to withstand the Soviet menace unless they developed a greater integration of policy and purpose. Thenew approach to these issues which the United States government now appeared to be adopting provided grounds for hope that we might succeed in re-establishing the close association with them whichhad been so fruitful in earlier years.The Cabinet Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers statement and wished him all success in his forthcoming consultationsin Washington.3.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer and the Minister of Labour (C. (57) 237)on wages policy in the public sector, together with memoranda byC.C. (57) 73rd the Secretary of State for Scotland and the Minister of HealthConclusions,     (C. (57) 238) and the Postmaster-General (C. (57) 243) on wages policyMinute 4.)      in relation to the National Health Service and the Post Officeengineers respectively.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, although theGovernment should not attempt to interfere with the operation ofthe established processes of free collective bargaining and arbitration,the economic policy on which they had now embarked required that,both in their own capacity as a direct employer and in terms of the indirect influence which they could exert over the nationalised industries, they should seek to secure that the initial offers made in response to claims for increased remuneration would be low, thatthe issues would then be referred to arbitration, and that the awards of the arbitrators would be implemented by compensating savings.It would also be necessary to resist so far as possible any attempt bythe nationalised industries to meet increased wage costs by increases in prices rather than by economies in the scale of the servicesinvolved.The Minister of Labour said that, while he entirely endorsed the general principles proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,the application of those principles to the circumstances of eachnationalised industry would need careful examination. In the caseof an industry, e.g., coal, which already had insufficient manpowerto achieve full economic production, it might well be unrealistic to seek to offset increases in wages by a reduction in the scale of activity.The Minister of Transport said that, subject to the cabinet&apos;s approval, he proposed to inform the British Transport commission that the finance available for their modernisation plans in the next financial year would be no greater than in the current year, with theWages.(previous reference :
result that the cost of any wage increases granted to theCommission^ employees would have to be met by the discharge oflabour or by a reduction in the scope of the Commissions services.The Government would have to exercise their influence with theCommission to dissuade them from seeking an alternative remedy inan increase of fares. Even though fares were determined ultimatelyby the Transport Tribunal, the Tribunal itself was enjoined to haveregard to the public interest.In discussion there was general agreement with these views.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the general policy outlined inC. (57)237.(2) Authorised the Minister of Transport to inform the british transport Commission that no additional funds would bemade available by the Exchequer to meet any increases in wages and that, in so far as these increases were notmatched by commensurate increases in productivity, theywould have to be offset by a reduction in the scope of the commissions services.National Health The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the success of theService. policy which the Cabinet had now approved would depend to aconsiderable extent on the firmness with which the Government dealtwith wage claims by their own employees. In the case of the clericalgrades in the National Health Service it would be consistent with thispolicy that the Minister of Health should disallow the increase of3 per cent, which had been agreed by the Whitley Council concernedbut should offer to allow the issue to be submitted to arbitration andto accept the award of the arbitrator, on the understanding that thecost of any award would be offset by retrenchment in the service.The Minister of Health said that it would be extremely difficultto meet the cost of a wage increase in the National Health service by economies in the scale of the service. The Guillebaud report had only recently demonstrated that there was no scope for generalsavings, while a reduction in the numbers of hospital staffs wouldinvolve a contraction of the scope of the service, e,g., by the closure of hospital beds, which would be wholly unacceptable. The leastdamaging course, therefore, would be to inform the Whitley council that, while the Government could not approve the proposed wage increase at the present time, they would be prepared to give it their approval at some future date, to be determined in the light of circumstances, and would be ready to review the question in sixmonths&apos; time.In discussion there was general agreement that the Governmentwould be unwise to commit themselves now to giving definiteapproval to the proposed wage increase at the end of a specified period or to accepting any obligation on retrospection in connectionwith any increase which might ultimately be approved. It would bemore appropriate that they should merely undertake to review thewhole position after six months. If, as a result, the Staff Siderequested that the issue should now be submitted to arbitration, theCabinet would need to reconsider the question.The Cabinet-(3) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to concert with theSecretary of State for Scotland, the Minister of Labourand the Minister of Health, the form of words whereby the Whitley Council for the clerical grades in the national health Service would be informed  that, while  the
Compulsory 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theAcquisition of Minister of Housing (C. (57) 239) examining the possibility ofLand: introducing legislation in the forthcoming session to amend the basisCompensation. 0f the assessment of compensation for the compulsory acquisitionof land.The Minister of Housing said that, in view of the growingdissatisfaction about the disparity between the sum paid for land on compulsory acquisition and the amount which that land would havecommanded in the open market, it would be necessary to review thebasis on which compensation was assessed in such cases. The problem was, however, extremely complex, and a great deal of further work would be necessary before sound proposals could be put forward.He had it in mind to propose amending legislation for the 1958-59session. It would be quite impracticable to introduce it in the sessionimmediately ahead.Government were obliged to withhold for the time beingapproval of the recent agreement of the Council to grant a 3 per cent, wage increase to officers of the Service onsalaries up to  1,200 per annum, they would be preparedto review the question again after a reasonable interval.Post Office The Postmaster-General said that the wage claim of the PostEngineers. Office engineers had its origin in the recommendations of the RoyalCommission on the Civil Service, 1953. The greater part of these recommendations, in so far as they affected the Post Office, had been implemented, and the only outstanding claim was that of theengineering grades in question. These grades had been given an assurance that they would be treated no less favourably than theother Post Office grades; and the recent increases in Post Office tariffshad been assessed on the assumption that their wage claim wouldbe met. The case was, therefore, an exception to the general principles propounded by the Chancellor of the Exchequer; and anyattempt to force it into conformity with those principles would expose the Government to the charge that they had dishonoured one of the commitments by reference to which the increases in tariffs had been justified and would involve the Post Office in the loss of the goodwill of the staff whose co-operation was essential to the progressivemodernisation of Post Office services.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he could not accept that these were adequate reasons for creating a dangerous precedentby departing, at the very outset of the Governmenfs new economic policy, from the basic principle that the initial offers in wage negotiations should be sufficiently low to ensure that claims would besubmitted to arbitration.In discussion it was agreed that, while the Government should seek to avoid appearing to be founding their new policy on an act of bad faith in the first case in which that policy came to be applied,it would be appropriate in present circumstances that they should confine their initial offer to a range of figures which, though not unreasonable, would be calculated to secure that the issue would bereferred to arbitration. The timing of the arbitration should bedecided in the light of the progress of other wage claims now pending.The Cabinet (4) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to agree with theMinister of Labour and the Postmaster-General thedetails of an offer which might be made to the Post office engineering grades, with a view to securing that theclaim of those grades for a wage increase would bereferred to arbitration.
Opening ofParliament.Facilities for television.(previous reference:CC. (53) 38thConclusions,Minute 7.)5. The Prime Minister said that the Director-General of theBritish Broadcasting Corporation (B.B.C.) had again suggested thatthe Opening of Parliament should be televised. The arguments forand against this course had been fully considered by the Cabinet in1953, and no succeeding Administration had seen fit to modify thedecision which was then taken that facilities for televising thisceremony should not be afforded. The fact, however, that theOpening of a new session of the Canadian Parliament by The Queenhad been televised in full, including the reading of The GraciousSpeech from the Throne, might possibly be held to put a differentcomplexion on the matter. While he proposed to inform theDirector-General of the B.B.C. that it was not now practicable toconsider affording television facilities for the Opening of parliament on 5th November, he felt that, subject to The Queen&apos;s approval, thematter might perhaps be reviewed afresh before the Opening ofParliament in 1958.The Cabinet were in general agreement with this proposal,although it was pointed out that, if permission was granted for television of the State Opening of Parliament, it might proveincreasingly difficult to deny facilities for television and sound broadcasting of Parliamentary debates.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for furtherconsideration to be given to the possibility of providingtelevision facilities for the State Opening of Parliament.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,21st October, 1957.Discussion showed that the Cabinet were in agreement with thisview. Legislation on this subject would be liable to be very controversial, and its scope should be examined with great carebefore the Government were committed to a new policy. It wouldbe necessary, in particular, to seek to ensure that the law was notamended in such a way that property owners whose land was notpurchased compulsorily would suffer adversely from any new basisof valuation. Consideration should also be given to a revision of theexisting statutory provisions governing the treatment of land whichwas sterilised for possible future development.The Cabinet Invited the Minister of Housing to submit, in due course,proposals for the amendment of the basis of compensationfor the compulsory acquisition of land, with a view to theintroduction of legislation for this purpose in the 1958-59session.

</content>
</cab>
