<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/31/0 images: 563-570</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1957CC. (57) Copy No.  81st Conclusions &quot;&quot;&quot;cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Thursday, 21st November, 1957, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. The Earl of Home,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. John Maclay, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.The Right Hon. Henry Brooke, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment and Minister for welsh affairs.The Right Hon. Harold Watkinson,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation.Dr. The Right Hon. Charles Hill,M.P., Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Alan Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Hailsham,Q.C., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Iain Macleod, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Mills, Ministerof Power.The Right Hon, Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Reginald Maudling,M.P., Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. The Earl of Selkirk,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 8).The Right Hon. Hugh Molson, M.P.,Minister of Works (Item 9).The Right Hon. Derek Walker-Smith,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Health(Item 1).The Right Hon. Edward Heath, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. B. St. J. Trend.Mr. H. O. Hooper.THIS DOCTUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT
contents minute no.                                     Subject page 1      Her Majesty The Queen      ...............       32      Wages Policy   ............... ......       3 national Health Service.3      Economic Situation    ...      ...      ...... ...      ...       3Alleged Leakage of Information.4      Local Government Elections ...      ...      ... ...      ...       45      Minister^ Visits Abroad      ...      ...      .........       46      Parliament       ............... ......       47      Foreign Affairs ...      ...      ...      ...... ...      ...       5The Yemen.Tunisia.8      House of Lords Reform......... ...      ...       59      regent&apos;s  Park Terraces ......... ...      ...       610     British Honduras.........      ... ......       611      Cyprus.................. ...      ...       7
Wages Policy.National health service.(previous references:CC. (57) 78thConclusions,Minute 2, and cc. (57) 74thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Cabinet were informed that the Prime Minister hadbeen asked by the General Council of the Whitley Councils for theNational Health Service to receive a deputation to discuss theGovernment^ refusal to authorise a wage increase for the clericalgrades in the Service.In discussion it was agreed that representations from a bodyconcerned with wage negotiation in the National Health service should be considered in the first instance by the Ministers responsiblefor that Service.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister would inform theGeneral Council of the Whitley Councils for the national health Service that the Secretary of State for Scotland andthe Minister of Health would be prepared to receive adeputation from them in due course.EconomicSituation.AllegedLeakage ofInformation.(previous reference:CC. (57) 80thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Prime Minister said that The Queen&apos;s consent would berequired for any disclosure of Cabinet proceedings to the tribunal which had been appointed to enquire whether there had been a premature disclosure of information about the increase in Bank rate on 19th September. There were precedents for such disclosure; andon this occasion it should not be necessary to say more than that thepossibility of an increase in Bank Rate was mentioned in the courseof the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on 17th September. It would be made clear that the decision was left to be taken by the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Prime Minister, after further consultation withthe Governor of the Bank of England.In discussion it was suggested that it might be brought out, inevidence before the tribunal, that the purport of the cabinets discussion on 17th September was whether the other economic measures which the Chancellor was proposing to take would alonesuffice to meet the situation or whether they needed to be reinforced by an increase in Bank Rate. It should also be made clear that responsibility for varying Bank Rate rested formally with the Courtof the Bank of England; that the Courts decision was taken afterconsultation with the Chancellor of the Exchequer and with his approval; and that by tradition this was not a matter which wasdecided by the Cabinet itself. It might also be stated that at their next meeting on the morning of 19th September the Cabinet had beeninformed that the Prime Minister had accepted the recommendationof the Bank of England that Bank Rate should be increased to 7 percent.; and that the Cabinet had remained in session that morning until after the time when the increase in Bank Rate was publicly announced.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a statement on these lines should be made inevidence to the tribunal which had been appointed to enquire whether there had been a premature disclosure of information about the increase in Bank Rate on19th September.52720-3b 2Her Majesty 1.   The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet of the terms ofThe Queen. the message of congratulation which he had sent on their behalfto The Queen and the Duke of Edinburgh on the tenth anniversary of their marriage and of the gracious reply which he had receivedfrom Her Majesty.
SECRET 561(2) Invited the Prime Minister to seek The Queen&apos;s consent forthis limited disclosure of information regarding theproceedings of the Cabinet.iocaI 4-   The Prime Minister said that it would be in accordance with government precedent that the Minister of Housing and Local Government andfciechons. his Parliamentary Secretary should refrain from making public(Previous speeches in connection with the forthcoming local government reference: elections.   Other Ministers should, however, feel free to acceptCC. (52) 3lst engagements of this kind, although they should seek, as far as conclusions, possible, to avoid creating the impression that they were interveningMinute 1.) in particular elections.                                                           &amp;Ministers&apos; 5.   The Prime Minister said that he was concerned that the visits Abroad, number of Ministerial visits overseas might make excessive demands on the hospitality of the countries visited, particularly in theCommonwealth, and might also create the impression that membersof the Government were neglecting their primary responsibilities inthis country. It was important that such visits should be so timedand arranged as to achieve the maximum of effect abroad without interference with the efficient discharge of the Governmenfsbusiness at home.In discussion attention was drawn to the value of these visits.It was specially necessary that Ministers of Defence Departments and ministers responsible for overseas affairs should continue to makevisits overseas to obtain first-hand knowledge of the problems withwhich they were dealing. It was also desirable that the Governmentshould not neglect this means of strengthening the political and commercial links between the United Kingdom and other countries.At the same time it was recognised that there was need for closer -ordination of the timing and frequency of these visits.The Cabinet Took note that the Prime Minister would consider what further arrangements could be made to secure improvedco-ordination of plans for Ministerial visits overseas.Parliament. 6.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Cabinet were also informed that the Committee of privileges had submitted their report on the question whether theLondon Electricity Board had committed a breach of privilege inthreatening to take proceedings for libel against Mr. G. R. Strauss,M.P., in respect of statements made in a letter which he had sent tothe Paymaster-General. This report could not, however, beconsidered until the opinion of the Judicial Committee of the privy council had been obtained on a point of interpretation of theParliamentary Privilege Act, 1770. It was hoped that the motionseeking that opinion might be passed by the House of Commonswithout debate. The substance of the point of privilege could thenbe debated at a later stage when, after the opinion of the JudicialCommittee had been given, the report of the Committee of Privilegescame to be considered.
Foreign Affairs.The Yemen.(previous reference:CC. (57) 80thConclusions,Minute 3.)Tunisia.(previous reference:CC. (57) 80thConclusions,Minute 3.)7. The Foreign Secretary said that the discussions with theCrown Prince of the Yemen had now been concluded. These had ledto no new agreements or understandings, but some progress had beenmade towards establishing more friendly relations between thiscountry and the Yemen.Arrangements had now been made for tripartite talks to be heldin Washington, between the Americans, the French and ourselves,about the future supply of arms to Tunisia. The French might askfor assurances that no further supplies would be made without their consent, but we could not promise more than full consultation.Public opinion in France was highly sensitive at the present time.It was therefore advantageous, from the point of view of Anglo-French relations, that arrangements had now been made for the PrimeMinister and the Foreign Secretary to make a short visit to Parison 25th November.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.8. The Cabinet had before them a joint memorandum by theLord Chancellor and the Commonwealth Secretary (C. (57) 263) anda memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty (C. (57) 281) onthe reform of the House of Lords.The Commonwealth Secretary said that the exploratory debatewhich had been held on 30th and 31st October had shown that theproposal to create life Peerages was acceptable to all shades ofopinion in the House of Lords and had confirmed the wisdom of theCabinet&apos;s decision not to embark upon a more far-reaching schemeof reform. There was little doubt that, if the Government had putforward a more ambitious plan, the Labour Party would have been more likely to pledge themselves to abolish the Second Chamber.As it was, their counsels were divided and it was possible that, ifthe Government did no more than take power to create life Peers,the resulting position might be tacitly accepted by the Labour Party.In these circumstances he recommended that the Government should for the present confine themselves to taking power to create lifePeerages for men and women, and he sought authority for theintroduction of legislation in the terms of the Bill annexed toC. (57) 263.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The Bill had been so drafted as to exclude amendmentsdesigned to enable hereditary Peeresses to sit in the House of Lordsor to enable hereditary Peers to renounce their right to sit.(b) The First Lord of the Admiralty said that, while he recognised the force of the arguments for proceeding with the limitedlegislation proposed in C. (57) 263, he hoped that the Governmentwould look favourably on any amendments designed to enable theHouse of Lords, through its rules of procedure, to limit the attendance of hereditary Peers.The Commonwealth Secretary said that, if the scope of themeasure were enlarged in that way, it might well meet with opposition from a section of Conservative Peers who were jealous of anyencroachment on the hereditary principle. He would greatly prefer that the Bill should continue to be limited to the single purpose ofempowering the creation of life Peerages.House of lords reform.(previous reference:CC. (57) 73rdConclusions,Minute 6.)
RegenfsPark 9.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the LordTerraces.        Privy Seal (C. (57) 270) covering a draft statement which the CrownEstate Commissioners proposed to make on the future of the Regent&apos;sPark Terraces.The Lord Privy Seal said that the Commissioners had reachedthe conclusion that, apart from the demolition of a few buildings ofno architectural merit, it would be practicable to make a further effort to preserve these Terraces. Their proposals, which would notnecessarily involve substantial Exchequer assistance, had beenapproved by the Royal Fine Arts Commission and would be welcomed by public opinion in general. It would therefore be reasonable toinform the Commissioners that the Government had no objection tothe issue of the proposed statement.The Minister of Works said that the Terraces were in poorstructural condition; but the present proposals, by enabling theCommissioners to gain experience of the problems of converting themto contemporary use, would demonstrate whether it was possible to preserve them at reasonable cost.In discussion there was general agreement that the proposals weresoundly conceived. It might, however, be necessary to consider, ata later stage, whether despite the present views of the planning authority some of the accommodation should be used as offices ratherthan residences.The Cabinet-(1) Approved the proposals in C. (57) 270.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to arrange for the proposed statement by the Crown Estate Commissioners to be circulated in the Official Report simultaneously with its publication by the Commissioners.british honduras.(previous reference:CC. (54) 24thConclusions,Minute 4.)10. The Colonial Secretary said that the leader of a delegation from British Honduras, which was now in London, had been discussing with the Guatemalan Minister the possibility of severingthe British connection and transferring British Honduras ^ toGuatemala for an experimental period of seven years during whichthe Guatemalans would assume financial responsibility for its development. In these circumstances he saw no alternative but tobreak off his negotiations with the delegation and to intimate that hewould be willing to resume negotiations in due course with a fresh(c) It was recognised that there was no sufficient measure ofagreement, in either House of Parliament, on the reform of the hereditary element in the House of Lords. Proposals designed to confirm the right of a limited number of hereditary Peers to sit inParliament would excite opposition both from those who resentedany encroachment on the hereditary principle and from those who desired its abolition. Therefore, at present, the only practical course was to limit legislation to the creation of life Peerages, which all sections of opinion were prepared to support.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that legislation for the reform of the House of lords in the current session should be limited to taking powerto create life Peerages for men and women.(2) Authorised the Commonwealth Secretary to arrange for legislation to be introduced in the House of Lords in theterms of the Bill annexed to C. (57) 263.
Cyprus.(previous reference:C.C. (57) 78thConclusions,Minute 9.)11.   The Cabinet had before them:  (i) a memorandum by the Foreign Secretary (C. (57) 276)summarising the diplomatic action which had been takento further a solution of the Cyprus problem;(ii) a memorandum by the Minister of Defence (C. (57) 265)examining the basis on which certain enclaves of territory in Cyprus should be retained under United kingdom control;(hi) a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet (C. (57) 275) covering a report by officials on the problems of economicand commercial policy which would arise under a condominium in Cyprus.The Foreign Secretary said that, although no positive results hadaccrued from the recent discussions between the Secretary-Generalof the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) and the GreekForeign Minister, our own diplomatic action in recent months should enable us to demonstrate in the forthcoming debate on Cyprus inthe United Nations that we were still actively seeking a solution ofthis problem. On this basis we might hope that the debate would pass off without too much embarrassment and that we should notbe pressed to agree that the Secretary-General should be investedwith any new function or authority in relation to Cyprus.The situation was liable to be complicated by the fact that itwould shortly be necessary to seek Parliamentary approval for theextension to the European Commission on Human Rights of the diplomatic privileges and immunities which had already been accorded to the other organs of the Council of Europe. It was unfortunate that this would have to be done at a time when we werenegotiating with a Sub-Commission of the European Commission onthe scope of the investigations which they wished to carry out in cyprus in connection with Greek allegations that our actions in the island were in breach of the European Human Rights Convention.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The recent suggestion by the Greek Government that Cyprusshould be granted Dominion status, on the understanding that thisstatus might be changed after a defined period, envisaged an unprecedented arrangement which would be embarrassing in relationto the other members of the Commonwealth. We could not support this proposal, and the Secretary-General of NATO should be discouraged from endorsing it in any further discussions with theGreek or Turkish Governments.(b) The Order according diplomatic privileges and immunitiesto the European Commission on Human Rights could be presented as little more than a consolidation of the rights already granted in this respect to the Council of Europe and its other organs. Thenecessary Parliamentary authority should, if possible, be obtained inadvance of any public announcement that a Sub-Commission of theEuropean Commission would be visiting Cyprus.C.C. 81 (57)delegation constituted on a more satisfactory basis. This decision might provoke some unrest in British Honduras, but troops wereavailable to assist the Governor in maintaining order.The Foreign Secretary said that there was no evidence on whichthe Guatemalan Minister could be charged with impropriety andit was doubtful whether we should gain by asking for his recall..The Cabinet Took note of these statements.
The Cabinet -(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to arrange that the Secretary-General of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation shouldbe discouraged from lending any support to the suggestionthat Cyprus might be granted Dominion status on thebasis that this status might be changed after a definedperiod.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary, in consultation with the HomeSecretary, to seek Parliamentary approval for the grant to the European Commission on Human Rights of the diplomatic privileges and immunities already accorded tothe other organs of the Council of Europe.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,21st November, 1957.

</content>
</cab>
