<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/22/0 images: 5-5</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.(63)5. 22 January 1963. 11.30 a.m.

1. Parly. Business. (oral). [Enter Ch. Whip.

Ch.Duchy. Rearrangement of business.

2. Common Market. (oral).

P.M. Resumé of recent developments and present position.

L.P.S. Returned to Paris on Friday, 11th. Discussn. with C. de M. He denied any intention on part of de G. to impose political veto, provided agreement reached on technical difficulties.

Moved to Brussels. Mansholt report settled after long discussion on Fr. amdts. Spaak saw settlement on ag if we would accept 31.12.69 as end of trans period. Reasonable – apart from horticulture.

Our concessions on tariffs also welcomed, and progress made.

Discussn. on H. Kong proceeding when C. de M. arrived and insisted on discussing with Five future of negotns., wh. were now inconsistent with de G.‟s Press Confce.

We tried to strengthen Five, particularly Germans : Adenauer angry with de G. Hallstein??? confirmed no economic ???? to agreement. Difference therefore purely political, particularly Nassau and alledged secret U.K./U.S. protocols on assocn. of Canada and Atlantic F.TA. to alow U.S. to dominate Europe.

Report by Colombo proposed on progress : French wd. agree only if negotns. were ended. Five then threatened to make concessions (Algeria etc.) wh. Fr. wanted. Fr. finally agreed that confce. shd. remain in being and resume on 28 Jan.

Legally, therefore, confce. is intact : and meetings are being continued to demonstrate this – even tho‟ Fr. are abstaining.

We have sought more publicity for our stand and are mobilising pressure, including message from U.S. Prest. to Adenauer.

Dutch and Belgians will now refuse to ratify agreemt. on association of African countries : this will hurt French.

No informn. about current discussions between A. and de G.

But no sign of weakening among Five : but also no belief that A. will persuade de G. to change his mind. If so, onus of break must rest wholly un Fr. : our relations with Five must be preserved.

Courses of action : a) Continuous discussions between U.K. and Five. But unproductive : ultimate stagnation. But Five anxious to keep channels open.

b) Association. Earlier refces. part of war of nerves, designed to show U.K. not sincere. Five still believe this : and Fr. Premier admits little value because of it. Economic advantages doubtful – C‟wealth

arrangements tolerable as price of political agreement : not without it. Also agr wd. be excluded : therefore nothing in it for Fr. Also wd. have to apply to E.F.T.A. and Fr. wd. not agree. No real intention to use association : and we shd. be able only to express views – not to have part in management.

We must stand firm and reject assocn. But Fr. may now withdraw from negotns.

M.A.F.F. Mansholt enquiry appreciated our real difficulties and our desire to resolve them. Atmosphere good – apart from Fr.

Even they agreed that our agric. was no longer as serious an obstacle as our position as a world trading Power.

Now difficult for us to continue negotiating with Five. at risk of being rejected by Fr. on having to renegotiate with them when they return to confce.

Com.Sec. Assocn. without any real control, valueless. But negotns. in absence of Fr. may be useful. Agreement, if rapid, wd. demonstrate isolation of Gr. and precipitate crisis inside E.E.C., leading to revolt of Five against Fr.

Ch.Exch. But this means concessions by us to Five – unjustifiable : or by them to us – wh. Fr. wd. veto : or deadlock – wh. wd. justify Fr. stand.

Ch.Duchy. Also a dummy agreement wd. lack political force wh. wd. overcome detailed objections by domestic lobbies.

P.B.T. I agree. Failure will be disappointt to industry. Therefore, don‟t risk a dummy agreement, wh. may look like a political gimmick.

L.P.S. Two courses. Dummy agreement, to be re-negotiated with Fr.

Or Breakaway by Five and new negotns.

Latter not v. probable. Fr. will surmount 6 months‟ tension.

Five not yet ready to scrap Ty. of Rome and start again. And if Adenaur‟s Govt. survives, they will probably prefer to wait until some new opportunity comes – preserving relations with us meanwhile. Multilateral N.A.T.O. deterrent, they think, may further isolate de G.

M.Health. Sham negotns. with empty chair wrong unless Five are prepared, in last resort, to break with Fr.

L.P.S. Fr. really want a protectionist community while voting system gives them a veto. This is bad for long term future of Five. They shd. break and deal with us.

F.Sec. Yes. de G. becoming increasingly isolationist.

Home Sec. But isolation of Fr. cd. have disastrous effects on her stability.

P.B.T. And don‟t underestimate cohesive strength of E.E.C. We must try for

quick settlement, in or out. If out, we can make other arrangements.

Home Sec. I agree. If out, take new line quickly.

M.Lab. But if A. cannot over persuade de G. will he fall : and will there then be fresh incentive to Five to agree with us?

L.Ch. If A. fails, nothing will persuade de G. If so, settle quickly whether we are in or out : and avoid even short sham negotns.

M. Def. I agree. But end of negotns end of policy. No real altve. to Common Market. If negotns. end, onus must be on Fr. : and we must mobilise all our influence to keep Five in play and isolate Fr.

Ch.Exch. I agree. Avoid appearance of crisis and take measures to strengthen our position without abandoning objective.

F.Sec. Even so, we must make our posn. clear. We have failed and we are isolated. We must do something to attract investment on same terms as E.E.C. : to develop E.F.T.A. : to gain advantage from Kennedy round etc.

Germans v. concerned to maintain Fr. connection. Must avoid compelling them to choose between us and Fr.

M.H.L.G. Support Ch. Exch. Will Five be really tough with Fr.? And is it to our long term advantage if they are?

L.P.S. Doubtful if they will be tough – eg. on assocn. of African territories and Algerian agreement – if they think we are out. But they won‟t be keen to help Fr. on these issues.

Fr. farmers want us in and see no advantage to assocn. But they haven‟t been quick enough to press this.

Ch.Duchy. de G. will be seen to be historically wrong. But this will take time. Meanwhile we shall be seen to have failed. We must avoid any impression of a brave new policy, wh. wd. make nonsense of our efforts in last 18 months. Therefore support Ch. Exch.

Best to end negotns. otherwise Parliament will press for end.

Not so damaging electorally as might be, given intransigence of de G. - and death of Gaitskell.

P.M. In short term, must encourage Five to make trouble for Fr.

But avoid making concessions to them wh. will gain us no credit. Avoid any deliberate attempt to destroy E.E.C. Leave that to events and to development of de G.‟s now apparent design to create a non N.A.T.O. Europe, independent of Anglo Saxon influence and to reach agreement with S. Union. This will alarm Germany.

For this reason de G. had to destroy negotns. – not because they were failing but because they were succeeding! This gives us a short term

tactical advantage. In longer term a v. severe blow to this Govt. and to Br. industry. Our policy has failed.

But don‟t be caught on the rebound : a C‟wealth arrangement wd. be no real substitute for E.E.C. either economically or politically.

Fr. - G. reconciliation is a sham : it is merely another phase in the battle, in wh. Fr. has won. In another and wider context, it wd. have been safe. In isolation, it will break down. We must adopt such policies as our own interests now require, with minimum of inconsistency with genuine E.E.C. ideal. Avoid any fake altve. C‟wealth or other (including E.F.T.A.) Smaller countries may go to wall.

Difficult to hold public to European concept – tho‟ N.A.T.O. concept may survive. We may have to reconsider W.E.U. obligations.

But our hands are clean : and we have no responsy. for break.

L.P.S. Probable Fr. obstruction to Kennedy round may help us.

M.A.F.F. Five may want to continue negotns. with us, to demonstrate independence of de G. Do we agree or not? If we do, we can‟t draw back.

P.M. If so, we must temporise and ask what it means. Will it be subject to Fr. veto : or will they jettison Fr.? Or will it be merely to decide how to live with de G.? Or will it be a short term accommodation on individual tariffs – wh. if we refuse it, wd. put onus of break on us but might be attractive to Br. industry?

Home Sec. Discuss with P.M. Not a disaster : and we shdn‟t present it as such. It will bring together those in our Party who opposed E.E.C. and those who favoured it. Present it as a new 1940 – a challenge wh. we can turn to advantage if we take right measures.

L.P.S. Disagree. Public already anti U.S. : will now be anti-Europe. We must have some new sense of purpose.

P.M. I agree. We must not revert to autarkic concept (as Socialists would).

F.Sec. Then we must create new sense of purpose v. quickly.

Ch.Exch. Use N.E.D.C. to greater effect.

</content>
</cab>
