<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/22/0 images: 8-8</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.(63)8. 29 January 1963. 12.15 p.m.

1. Common Market. (oral). [Enter Ch,.Whip., M/S. C.R.O.

(Devonshire)

P.M. Brussels tels. 90, 91, 97 and 98.

Position constantly shifting. If de M. leaves at 8 p.m. world will know break caused by French.

Discussed with F.Sec. Agreed not to run after E.E.C. or to try to form some new body (unless Six breaks up). Have therefore sent tel (with embargo) to L.P.S.

L.Ch. “In good faith” questionable.

P.M. Dispense with this if necy.

Ch.Duchy. Agree in general. But is break certain, today?

P.M. Probably. Five will want to meet L.P.S. tonight after de M. leaves : but they too will leave tonight.

Ch.Duchy. Then L.P.S. must make statement in Parlt. tomorrow. But de M. must walk out first : and Five and we must then agree a joint statement.

F.Sec. Any point in having a later meeting with Five, as in last para of draft statement?

L.P. Not until we have consulted E.F.T.A. etc.

Ch.Exch. But get max. of support from Five also.

P.M. Avoid suggestion of any real altve. in sense of another club.

Otherwise, we shd. have joined it.

L.P. Agree. But still concert action with E.F.T.A., old C‟wealth etc.

Ch.Duchy. Last para of draft useful as propaganda : but dangerous as potential commitment – too vague.

F.Sec. Specify that contact will be maintained in existing Em. orgns. of wh. we and Five are members – eg. N.A.T.O.

M.Edn. Agree. U.S. can do good work in N.A.T.O.

M.H. Avoid a joint statement : and make our own?

Ch.Exch. Can‟t avoid it, for sake of Five. Don‟t exclude possy. of further economic collabn.

Ch.Duchy. Statements in both Houses tomorrow. Promise debate in due course –

not till we have our measures ready!

M/S C.R.O. Tels to rest of C‟wealth as soon as negotns. end. Tell them to wait for considered views from us.

[P.M. Gave details of POLARIS financial settlement.]

P.M. Grave sitn.. Reveals de G.‟s long term intentions. Reversion to pre-war Europe, except that de G. hasn‟t Hitler‟s strength. In the end the Five will rebel : but de G. may just try to extrude U.S. and U.K. from Europe and to do a deal with Soviet Union. Therefore we must keep in touch with our friends in Europe and with U.S.

L.P. Berlin? Result shd. be not a Br. soldier shd. die for Berlin.

Or else, if we want Germany to revolt against de G. we must give them 110% support.

F.Sec. Public presentn here? Not as a tragedy but as an opportunity missed. Our purpose consistent with Nassau agreement; and latter still valid if Fr. are reasonable in N.A.T.O. (i.e. unless de G. tries to negotiate direct with K. for denuclearisation of Europe, withdrawal of all foreign troops and reunification of Germany).

M.Def. If de G. really moves, he will do so v. quickly. If N.A.T.O. dissolves, the condition of Nassau agreement falls : and we may not get POLARIS unless we negotiate an Anglo American agreement.

M. w‟out P. Stress two visions of Europe in conflict : emphasise ours.

</content>
</cab>
