<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/22/0 images: 10-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C.(63)10 7 February 1963. 10.30 a.m.

[Enter Ch. Whip

1. Parly. Business. (oral).

Ch.Duchy. Statement.

Motion for C. Market debate.

2. Economic Policy : post Brussels. (oral).

Com.Sec. Let C‟wealth Economic Consultative Council meet before C.‟w. Finance Ministers on G.A.T.T.

L.P.S. Yes : but don‟t exaggerate into new C‟w. orientation.

P.B.T And G.A.T.T. meeting may be delayed or collapse.

Also revive discussion of Australian Trade Agt. renewal – without hurry.

P.M. Adopt Com. Sec‟s proposal : despatch telegrams : announce in debate.

3. Foreign Affairs. (oral).

a) Congo.

F.Sec. Tshombe has left Katanga for eye operation : may now settle down.

b) Indonesia.

F.Sec. Subandrio has denied any ?legve claim on Malaya or intention of starting a war. No risk of imminent trouble in Borneo.

4. Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland. (oral).

First Secy. Initial phase of talks mere recrimination by Welensky. By end of talks W. produced a plan, based on M.Cmn. Defence, taxation, European Educn. reserved to central Govt. (and he wd. privately surrender Em. Educn.) W. wd. accept conference on future assocn. on this basis.

N. Rhodesia : wd. accept confce. on economic links provided right of secession conceded first. Field will soon declare publicly for only economic links. Economic assocn. therefore only common ground : will W attend a confce. on this basis? He threatens an election or a referendum or a European revolt or an invasion of N.Rh. Field discounts this – especially military threat since he wd. oppose it and ⅔ of Fed. Forces are S.Rh.

Must aim at confce. in London, with parties in separate rooms! Then resume in Africa, if promise of success. I shall announce this in Parliament.

S.Rh. is key. Field selected on an anti African mandate wh. he won‟t change. This means renewed pressure from Africans and U.N.

Recent anti terrorist legn. v. repressive. This makes assocn. with N.Rh. problematical now and increasingly doubtful as S. Rh. policy develops. Therefore no time to lose.

Leave Fed Govt. in being : policy of attrition W secretly proposed to disappear.

Nyasaland refuse to contribute to Fed. Tsy. after this summer. Therefore transfer of Services under secession must start earlier.

No alternative to pledges : and no pressure in Commons. But Lords agitation persists.

L.Ch. P.Q. by Alexander on Tuesday : and Motion (Oppn.) down for 18th.

Swinton concurs in, and will support, our W.P. Hope to persuade Chandos tomorrow. Salisbury likely to be obdurate. Therefore publicn. desirable from Lords point of view.

P.M. Salisbury a member of Cabinet at time. No record of pledges in Cab. minutes.

L.Ch. Wait to see whether Chandos endorses W.P. If so, publish it before debate.

First Secy. A pity qua Commons. No steam behind it in Fedn. : and we shd. concentrate on future, not past.

Ch.Whip. Oppn. agreed to defer considn. till First Secy. returned. Must ascertain their attitude today.

L.Ch. A bad Lords debate (without W.P.) wd. be more likely to stir up Commons.

F.Sec. But an unconvincing document.

Home Sec. Yes : but if Swinton and Chandos endorse it, we are safe.

P.M. I will decide – with First Secy. and L.Ch. – in light of Chandos‟s reaction.

Try to square Boyd also. But leave Salisbury alone.

F.Sec. We shall also be asked whether we mean to maintain Fed. Govt. : and what we intend as regards defence.

First Secy. It depends on whether Field will stand up to W. and whether Forces can be shared between N. &amp; S. Rh. on basis that they will combine against external threat.

F.Sec. That implies some central political direction.

First Secy. But this cd. be arranged without W. or a central Govt.

5. Malta : Dockyard. (oral). [Enter. FLA &amp; Sol. Gen

Com. Sec. Statement on Malta on Monday. See text : improprieties in financial relations between two companies, favouring the parent.

Litigation will be long and complicated. But Law Officers endorse our case. If we win, company must repay our £3 m. : if they can‟t, lease reverts to us.

But things can‟t stop meanwhile. We don‟t want to nationalise Baileys. Therefore appoint temporary administration. Govt. of Malta agree to legislate for this provided we guarantee no discharge of labour for some years. We can‟t agree (since more efficient adminn. may lead to discharge of labour) : we must therefore proceed ourselves by O.-in-C. and will do so on Monday.

Charges to Admy. have been excessive, since Baileys have not attracted enough civil work. This wd. prohibit Admy. from placing further orders there : but we must try to continue some orders there, altho‟ prices may be excessive for some time.

P.M. Announce Tuesday – to spoil Brown‟s speech, not mine.

Ch.Secy. One refit is £¼ m. more expensive under Baileys. V. difficult to justify when U.K. shipyards are idle.

M.Trans. Baileys are crooks : and inefficient.

Essential that new council of admn. shd. include somebody who knows about ship repairing. Nobody on proposed list.

Com.Sec. I will consult M. Trans.

Ch. Sec. Let new management have a chance to reconsider tender for refit.

If margin over U.K. figure slight, might accept.

P.M. Or insist on realistic price : and give Malta an extra subsidy.

F.L.A. Much better for me.

Com.Sec. Then announce frigate refit in my statement. V. important to Malta.

M.Trans. But accurate est. for repair work impossible.

F.L.A. But similar job just completed in Baileys did cost 25% more than in U.K.

Sol.Gen. O.-in-C. technique doubtful : implies one party to dispute has an

advantage. Legn. in Malta or U.K. wd. be preferable.

But args??? of public interest must prob. prevail against risk of challenge to validity of O.-in-C. or ruling of contempt. If accountant‟s report is accurate, we shall probably win. But it may take v. long time.

P.M. Cd. we settle out of court?

Com.Sec. Bailey &amp; Son have now commented on report and wd. compromise – eg by mediation by political parties in Malta! When I said that they must sever connection with Malta dockyard, they seemed willing.

But later their written offer of terms of severence were unrealistic.

They may settle after we have acted.

L.Ch. Our action is doubtful, while case pending How will council of admn. work?

P.M. Any further dealings with B. shd. be handled by Law Officers, not Com. Secy.

Sol.Gen. I agree – if it is clear that they won‟t settle out of court.

L.Ch. Investgn. under Companies Act preferable?

P.B.T. Depends on place of legisln. and local law. We cd. probably only investigate parent.

M.Trans. L.Ch. is right. Bailey, if frightened, will settle.

L.Ch. Better to appoint a “receiver” for Malta company, i.e. somebody who will run the company.

Com.Sec. In effect we are doing this, by leaving company power only to prosecute litigation.

M.H. Don‟t let Malta blackmail us. Force them to legislate.

P.M. But don‟t drive them to Russia.

L.Ch. But Malta shd. be willing to press the company if alternative is collapse of dockyard.

P.M. Can‟t wash our hands of a plan of our making.

Can they challenge O.-in-C.

Sol.Gen. Yes, on validity : and we conduct act while this was settled.

Challenge on propriety wd. be separate and additional.

L.Ch. B. will dislike publicity. Use this to persuade them to accept somebody to manage company (leaving ownership intact) – or else we employ O.-in.-C. TSol shd. now handle negotns. – we shd. be directed

to keeping dockyard going, pending settlement of litign.

P.M. Either wait for litign., taking no action. Or take some action to keep dockyard going pending litign. If latter, let Com.Sec. L.Ch. and Law Officers consider best form of action, directed to agreement if possible. Future negotns. by Tsy. Sol. under threat of some form of legve. action.

[Exeunt Com. Sec., F.L.A., Sol. Gen.

6. Commercial Policy : Imports of Russian Oil C(63)12 &amp; 14).

[Enter M. Power.

Ch.Exch. £10m. tenders in sight : bigger tender possible. No specific quantities of oil mentioned : but clearly intended.

Ship orders wd. be welcome : but oil inconsistent with our policy on R. oil; damaging to coal : damaging to N.A.T.O. and new M.E. interests; risks diverting tanker order elsewhere.

If we can get a definite order, with limited amount of oil, balance of advantage is in favour of deal.

F.Sec. U.S. will object – more trade with S.U. makes them more dangerous.

Collapse of E. German economy shows this. We take opposite view; but something in U.S. point. Impact on M.E. problematical.

But, if employment arg. is paramount, do the deal on “hardest” terms.

M.Power. If M.E. supplies interrupted we depend on U.S. Therefore don‟t offend them.

Increase of pit closures wd. be damaging to coal industry and to future investment in oil refining and tanker building by foreign oil companies in U.K. – particularly since this will be thin end of wedge and further quotas will have to be accepted.

Ch.Exch. Use it as an addl. reserve?

M.Power. Only if we financed it : and storage v. expensive.

M.Trans. We are only ship bldg. country wh. does not take Russian oil. Therefore no risk here.

U.S. subsidise their shipbuilding : also Canada. Our yards have lost heavily as a result. U.S. have no cause to complain.

Politically, therefore, we shd. close deal for sake of our own shipbuilders, who wd. benefit at once. No altve. in sight. Further Russian orders may follow.

PBT Scope of deal is still obscure : all I need is authority to negotiate. Useful to show M.E. suppliers they have no monopoly; and impossible to disappoint our own shipbuilders.

M.Lab. Impact depends on size of quota : if reasonable, not too damaging.

Agree with P.B.T.

Home Sec. If we start negotn., we may fail. Then have worst of both worlds.

Ch.Exch. I agree. Russian purpose is to create domestic political trouble for us.

Russians must therefore make a firm proposal.

Ch.Duchy. Do the deal, for sake of empt.

P.M. I agree. But watch terms of announcement – agree in principle to consider offer to buy ships as part of arrangement comprising some oil.

L.P.S. Only justifiable in short term.

P.B.T. No : in long term, as means of increasing E.W. trade. We can limit arrangement to period of present trade Agreement.

P.M. In answer to P.Q.‟s or Press enquiries say no proposal yet made by Russians : but, if and when it is made, we wd. not rule out a bargain including some oil.

M.Power. Don‟t over-stress oil aspect. They may be merely leading us up garden path.

P.M. Very well : leave it as vague as possible. [Exit M. Power.

7. Broadcasting Policy : Television Bill : Duties &amp; Levies

C.(63)10.

[Enter P.M.G.

Ch.Exch. As in memo. But some of proposed rates are penal.

P.M.G. I will reconsider them.

P.M. Accept in principle : reconsider rates.

Home Sec. Discriminatory taxn. by Order v. dangerous precedent.

P.M.G. Less discrimy. than present Cl.7.

[Exit P.M.G.

8. Education : Teachers‟ Salaries. C.(63)11.

Ch.Exch. As in memo. Burnham proposals bad : dangerous qua nurses

Therefore press for better scale, conceding some total amount if necessary but trying for less.

M.Edn. Second row in one Parlt. on amount wd. be unwise. Even to refer back

on distribn. is tricky : if no agreement, I may have to enforce by legn. But I must try. £1½ m. from lower to upper half and transference of some assimilative quantum to responsy. allce will suffice. But I must say at once that £20.7m. starts as total.

Ch.Exch. I agree – so long as it does not appear to be merely redistribution of £20.7m.

P.M. Agree : base it on Educn., not financial, grounds.

M. Lab. Must also endorse para 7.

M.Edn. I will make proposals : but legn. will not be easy.

If N.U.T. consider ratification at confce next week, I must defer intervention till after then.

Ch.Duchy. Don‟t spoil 2 year settlement by early legn. to alter Burnham.

M.Edn. Agree : but will consider among ourselves.

P.M. Unwise to let N.U.T. ratify on a false basis.

M.Edn. Altve. is to intervene before confce. – wh. turns confc e. into demonstration against us. Formal ratificn. comes after confce. and I will intervene in between.

S.&amp;S.Sect. Watch Scots complicet.

First Secy. Tactics as M. Edn. proposes.

P.M. Agree.

</content>
</cab>
