<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/22/0 images: 18-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (63) 18. 25 March 1963, 11 a.m.

1. Pay of Members of Parliament. C(63) 50 &amp; 54

[Enter Ch.Whip.

Com. Sec. Don‟t discard link with C. Service.

M.Def. Agree. Definite link essential.

Ch.Exch. Any increase dubious qua incomes policy, - unless it cd. be referred to N.I.C. (wh. it can‟t).

Ch.Secy Agree. What wd. N.I.C.‟s criterion be – e.g. is membership a full time job?

M.W.P. If so, must have convincing reason against action.

P.M. If a change, must be substantial – e.g. £3000.

L.Ch. If so, means a change in M.P.‟s status: you earn your living by being an M.P.

L.P. Ministers‟ pay (note relativity with advisers) more urgent than M.P.s.

F.S. Action needed and justified on merits: but timing v. awkward.

M.A.F.F. ? Nothing now: but promise of action in election manifesto.

Com.Sec, ? Remit to joint committee of both Houses.

Ch.Duchy. Make intentions clear as soon as possible after meeting with Oppn tomorrow.

P.M. Can‟t increase own salaries by say 50% immediately after Budget designed to expand economy provided that country is reasonable about incomes. Therefore make our Statement after Budget – no action in this Parlt.

M.H.L.G. linked with whole question of method of Parliament‟s working.

P.M. That, too, is best dealt with at beginning of a Parlt.

L.P.S. But get our own ideas straight – at least for Election manifesto.

P.M. I will arrange this.

Ch.Sec. Have asked Tsy. to examine concessions to M.P‟s wives etc.

P.M. This shd. be brought within scope of enquiry.

2. Export of Large Diameter Steel Pipe. C(63)55.

Ch.Sy As in memm.

F.S. Pipes outside COCOM list. Our N.A.T.O. delegate made it clear that he would‟t play: so German claim of unanimous Council decision is wrong. But reaction in Germany (who have banned existing contracts) more serious than reaction in U.S.A. But can‟t help that.

P.B.T. Procedure wd. involve Parlty action on Orders.

P.M. Get facts straight: what happened on Indonesia? How are arms treated? How COCOM items? What wd. be procedure if we were dealing with non-COCOM item?

S.U. may move to dumping, at later stage of economic devt. Hence importance of pipe – to convey oil for dumping. Good if we could prevent it: but if we don‟t supply, Sweden or Japan will. Therefore only real point is whether, if we supply, we impose new strain on N.A.T.O.

F.S. But if we try to carry N.A.T.O. policy in Parlt, we may fail. We then have odium and no orders.

P.B.T. Odium a good thing: underlines our policy on E.-W. trade, on wh. we have agreed to differ with U.S.

L.P. But if we give way here, it is a slippery slope.

F.S. ? Try to arrange new debate on policy, in N.A.T.O. council as means of gaining time. Might demonstrate lack of unity and so let Germans out.

P.M. U.S. agree COCOM not strictly applicable: but wd. like to retard oil devt.

Ch.Exch. But U.S. have substituted imports of S.U. chrome for Rhodesian chrome. They don‟t hesitate to damage us!

P.B.T. Risky to renew debate in COCOM.

F.S. Not if restricted to this item.

L.P. Leave it alone: we must get order for N.E. if we can. Real German view is in favour of export and was only stifled by Parly manoeuvre.

P.M. We haven‟t yet got an order: if we do, try to initiate N.A.T.O. discussion to reveal position of countries on basic issue of enabling S.U. to export oil more easily.

? But first say no order received: defer our view until question is real.

L.P.S. Watch our long term interest in preventing oil sales as against short term interest of getting order for N.E.

P.M. Yes – if boycott cd. be effective.

L.P.S. See Wash. tel. No 856, worth exploring even with implication of no order from S.U.

L.P. But our policy is not to deprive S.U. of means of economic life. That is way to increase, not reduce, risk of war: particularly if boycott can‟t be effective.

F.S. But we must try to prevent S.U. from increasing her ability to help satellites with oil.

P.M. Keep Ball in play: but defer decision until issue is real.

Ball will be like McCloy: talk but no orders.

Must watch Russian oil penetration.

Resume discussion when order appears imninent.

3. The Atlantic Community (oral).

F.S. Statement in Parlt to-morrow. This will say that I went to Paris to tell N.A.T.O. what I had already told Parlt.

But wide political consdns. involved. Get terminology clear.

Can U.K. afford indept dett? Shd. N.A.T.O. have strategic (as distinct from semi-tactical) nuclear weapons? If objective is to prevent proliferation, what system of command? What change (if any) in order to fire procedure, if credibility to be prserved - ? a majority vote.

These are some of questions troubling N.A.T.O.

Own deterrent: we must keep it while future of test ban &amp; disarmt is uncertain. Also unanimity principle under joint command destroys credibility – unless one finger is on main triggers. Therefore don‟t discard while pattern of arms unclear.

N.A.T.O.‟s weapons: something must replace bombers and distinction between tactical &amp; strategic breaks down. therefore military arguement sound. Proliferation: recent U.S. action has forced nuclear weapons on Europe and has therefore created the problem. Therefore shared force is now only means of preventing proliferation. Nuclear Cttee of N.A.T.O. (our Athens proposal) no longer sufficient. Hence multinational force of NASSAU. U.S. accepted this and did not mention multilateral force. N.A.T.O. Council (excl France) approved multinational force and associated system of command:- i.e. five permanent (incl. Germans) and two rotating members, under oblign to report to Nuclear Cttee. Will be elaborated at Ottawa in May.

Credibility maintained by national character of multinational force – i.e. we can fire if we want to.

But U.S. regard multinational force as insufficient to satisfy Germany. Only a “non-withdrawable” force will suffice. Hence multilateral force, which I found at N.A.T.O. attracted many countries. 25 ships with 200 missiles v. expensive: but G. &amp; Italy prepared to pay. But doubts about vulnerability (and “second class” status) of surface vessels. If G &amp; I. insist on submarines, U.S. in trouble – administratively because of mixture of nationalities, politically because of Congress, technically because only U.S. or U.K. can work vital parts – and others will be relegated to second class jobs.

Nobody (except perhaps G. &amp; I.) yet committed on multilateral force. If we contributed, we cd. do so in kind – warheads, crews, dock facilities etc. Worth it, if it buys off Germans. And bad if force takes shape and we are left out.

Cost difficult. Stikker wants debate in N.A.T.O. on this, in relation to national resources.

M.Def. Don‟t excite Parlt about multilateral force: wd. only touch off debate about Nassau &amp; the bombers!

Mixed manned force is 200 m. Our share (5-10%) is £100 m. over the years. For this we cd. make our own weapon.

Conventional increase also being pressed by U.S. Our share might be increase of £300-400m over 1963-66.

Replacement of bombers by M.R.B.M.‟s is a third U.S. concept. Also very expensive.

We must not be rushed into backing all three horses. Our contribn under para. 6 and commitment on Polaris is enough.

Ch.Exch. Agree.

Ch.Duchy. Debate may be sprung on us to-morrow.

? Publish F. Sec.‟s N.A.T.O. statement as W.P.

F.S. Can‟t publish N.A.T.O. speech.

P.M. And it did (unwisely) mention possible U.K. contribn to multinational force.

Com.Sec. U.S. deterrent already adequate – and will remain so. European force not a military, but political (i.e. anti-proliferation) device. Control therefore decisive. If to be American, we have merely increased U.S. power and have not increased deterrent to S.U., wh. depends on there being a separate force. (Hence value of our own deterrent.) Surface ships adequate for this purpose – only a “fire first” capability is needed. Hence limit cost to ourselves.

L.P. Even so, it will ruin us, if additional to existing commitments.

P.M. Our commitment, as at Nassau, is defined in paras. 5-9. See first sentence of para. 9 – i.e. our contribn to bombers and submarines (when built). We are under no further oblign. But since Nassau agt not yet signed, we mustn‟t be too rigid about any further contribn. And v. important to contain Germans. Hence my new initiative with U.S. President on test ban and non-proliferation agreements.

Parly Statement shd. therefore concentrate on multinational force and stress no commitment on multilateral force, altho‟ we wish it well. See N.A.T.O. tel. 98, para. iv.

M.A.F.F. It won‟t deter G: it will merely whet their appetites.

L.P. But G. cd. make the weapons!

P.M. Therefore only way to hold them is by agreement freely negotiated, not under duress at end of war.

L.P.S. But, if multilateral force goes ahead, we can‟t afford not to be in it. How are para. 6 and paras. 8/9 forces related? Two forces or one?

M.Def. “Multilateral” has changed its meaning since Nassau. Bombers and submarines are our contribn to what was meant at Nassau by “multilateral”. Multinational force is a new addition.

F.S. Because when new style multilateral force is available there will then be no need for any other type of force. That is basis of U.S. thinking, wh. is designed to prevent any withdrawal of national components.

Therefore while stressing no commitment, leave door open for possible contribn.

</content>
</cab>
