<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/22/0 images: 26-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. (63) 26 25th April 1963. 10.30 a.m.

1. Parliament (oral). [Enter Ch. Whip.

Ch. Duchy. As in Statement.

2. Report of the Radcliffe tribunal. C(63) 67.

P.M. Amended version (for security reasons) to be published to-day.

I shall refrain from comment except on fact of amendment.

Home Sec. On payment of expenses of representation, Radcliffe is considering. I have refused permission for D. Mail to visit one of imprisoned journalists.

P.M. He is entitled to see his legal repve. Therefore handle carefully and get it in writing.

3. Foreign Affairs (oral).

a) Laos.

F. Sec. Gromyko has refused to co-operate with me, as co-chairman, to get I.C.C. operating over whole country. But we may get local Soviet co-opn in extending it to Plain of Jars. Chances of Geneva Agt surviving are now small: partition may be unavoidable, even though Royalist forces now united. Partition wd. lead to intervention by both Sino-Soviets &amp; U.S. Russians v. reluctant to quarrel with China on this issue. Harriman visiting Moscow to impress on Gromyko U.S. attitude if no Soviet co-opn – i.e. U.S. strengthening of Thailand (and U.K. air squadron as well?). We are almost back to where we were two years ago.

b) U.A.R.

F. Sec. New union to be created over two years. Both Syria &amp; Iraq less keen than Egypt. I.P.C. may be affected – tho‟, if commerce reserved to regions, may still deal direct with Iraqi Govt.

Jordan badly shaken internally. New Govt. v. ineffective. May be revolution to depose King: and Israel wd. then move.

Our arms sales to Iraq had better go ahead: but wait till I have seen Shah, since Iran v. nervous of new union. (But ordinary supplies of spares and replacements can continue.) I will try to persuade Shah better that we should arm Iraq than that S. Union shd.

P.M. We have more at stake than the Shah! We must not appear to be trying to oppose or destroy new union. It may destroy itself.

F. Sec. But remember Kuwait. Shd. we arm Iraq against K?

M. Def. Unless Shah reacts violently, we shd. let Iraq have arms.

c) Greece.

F. Sec. Gk. Govt. are protesting against attack (by Gks.) on Queen of Greece in London. V. embarrassing, with Royal Visit in prospect.

d) S. Union.

P.M. K.‟s reaction to U.K.-U.S. letter rather non-committal. Suggests internal posn not v. secure. Harriman‟s visit, under cover of Laos, may help. Partial leakage in Press also helpful.

e) India: Military Aid.

Com. Sec. Macnamara does not want to give aid: Harriman does. We must continue to dangle carrot for sake of Kashmir. Air Defence of cities: addn general aid: some v. vague and large Programme for future – all there are at large.

P.M. Air Defence of cities v. dangerous. It means war with China. There must be no commitment on this – not even discussion.

Com. Sec. I agree. But we must prevent U.S. from going too far: F. Sec. &amp; I will try to hold Rusk on this at C.E.N.T.O. meeting. U.S. want to do it because it is something they can do without Congressional approval.

Ch. Sec. Even test flight of Javelins has implications.

P.M. We can advise Indians on defence: and we (or U.S.) can supply such equipment as we see fit. But active participation v. different. If India wants this, she must join one of regional defence pacts. Then China will know where she stands.

Com. Sec. I agree. But tho‟ we can‟t go all way with U.S., we mustn‟t contract out of aid altogether, for sake of Kashmir talks.

P.M. Ascertain details of Javelin flight, wh. is not to be undertaken without my approval.

f) Germany: Royal Visit.

P.M. Cabinet shd. consider – for discussion on F. Sec.‟s return – pros and cons of Visit to Germany by Queen next spring.

4.

CLOSED UNDER THE

FREEDOM OF INFORMATION

ACT 2000

5. Law of Sea. (oral)

L.P.S. Canadian P.M. has asked us to defer action until his visit next week. We planned to initiate consultns to-morrow. If we delay a week, interval before notice will be cut to a fortnight.

F. Sec. He doesn‟t understand that giving notice doesn‟t prejudice confce.

P.M. Explain this to him.

M.A.F.F. Important to stress confce, to appease our deep sea fishermen.

6. Federation of Rhodesia &amp; Nyasaland. (oral)

First Secy I will circulate Field‟s latest letter: we must discuss reply next week.

7. Future Agricultural Policy. C(63) 65 &amp; 68.

[Enter Parly. Sec.B.of Trade.

M.A.F.F. Report by Officials shows prodn outstripping consumption throughout the developed world. Countries react in various ways: effects heaviest on exporting countries, but now extending to importing countries – hence rise in Exchequer bill. But our farmers reluctant to shift from increasing prodn to increasing productivity and reducing costs without increasing prodn. We have dealt with this by ad hoc measures – e.g. butter quotas, “voluntary” restriction of Argentine meat imports. We must now contemplate international commodity agreements – as we shd. have had to do if we had entered E.E.C.

We must also restrict our prodn, by limiting amount of guarantees; and we must establish some control over imports.

Direct grants are £120 m. We can adjust this as we like.

Deficiency payments are £240 m. Of this £210 m. is for cereals &amp; meat, £30 m. for other commodities. Problem is therefore cereals &amp; meat: and these are particularly suitable for intl commodity agreements.

Report proposes min. import prices about £2 a ton above basic price for Intl Wheat Agreement: other cereals pro rata. Wheat offered below this price on import wd. be subject to levy. Same technique not applicable to meat. Here quantitative control is needed: and foreign suppliers must be regulated by country quotas. This freezes pattern of trade – but not as much as B/T. think.

These measures merely maintain present posn: they don‟t shift any of the financial burden from Exch. to Consumer, (altho‟ they close open ended nature of commitment). To shift burden on cereals, a levy subsidy scheme (= ½d on loaf) wd. be required.

Agr Depts. want action on imports in parallel with action on domestic prodn. Tsy. &amp; B/T. want only latter. But part of open ended commitment then remains open ended, since market price remains uncontrolled as result of our market remaining a dumping ground for anybody prepared to sell produce regardless of price. Secondly, discrimn between imports &amp; domestic prodn politically indefensible. Thirdly, G.A.T.T. thinking favours combined approach. Fourthly, it gives other countries advantage of knowing where they stand: and wh. can bargain for some return in terms of our own exports of manufactures.

This policy leads to stabilisation, or fall, in farm incomes: this is not consistent with N.E.D.C. doctrine of growth. Therefore we must look to amalgamation of holdings and reduction in number of farms. We must also cooperate in disposal of world surpluses to needy countries.

First need is to decide on control of imports, in order to be ready for talks with Danes, with Commonwealth &amp; with G.A.T.T.

Ch. Exch. Our support is higher than in other countries: and return on capital is v. small. We are investing more in agric. than in industry: but subsidies more than cover incomes. This is rubbish. Also system subsidises efficient &amp; inefficient. Therefore we must control output and promote efficiency. Concept of global farm income misleading. But control of imports v. arguable, particularly in so far as it wd. increase price of food. Also quotas impose strain on b. of payments. Also reaction on our own exports must be watched. To restrict dumping is one thing: to increase food prices – with all its implications for incomes policy etc. – as a permanent measure is v. different. Quotas are worst method of protection; they freeze pattern of trade. Tariffs are better, but adjustment probably impossible. Variable levy on imports needs further examn: it is best from b/p. point of view. Min. import price also deserves thought: probably easiest to operate, provided impact on b/p. and prices is reasonable.

If we help foreign producer, we must bargain for our own exports.

Levy subsidy arrangement, wh. wd. increase prices, welcome to Exchequer: but politically v. arguable. We ought to produce here what we produce cheapest: and sell abroad what we sell cheapest.

First Secy Watch political implicns. I agree with M.A.F.F. that we shan‟t hold farmers unless we control imports. We propose in fact to reduce farm incomes: we can‟t do this alone. Control of imports must be done in least harmful way to b/p.; and we must bargain for our own exports. But we must control imports, both to carry farmers and to close both ends of commitment.

We shd. back levy: effect on price of loaf negligible, and wd. be consistent with Conservative policy in 30‟s.

L.P.S. Economically, it wd. be better to stop a lot of prodn altogether. But this is politically impracticable. Therefore go for levy and bargain for our own exports.

Both Eur. &amp; Americans will examine our price support system closely in G.A.T.T.: and we must bargain hard. Considerable impact on E.F.T.A. negotns on May 9-10.

Proposals not an obstacle if we renew E.E.C. applicn.

Parly Sec. I endorse Ch. Exch. But don‟t over rate bargaining advantages of

B/T quotas. Unless Danish &amp; Denmark incomes are increased, our exports

will fall. To increase them, we must increase foreign share of our

markets.

M.A.F.F. Can‟t have it both ways. Cost to b/p. of quotas is measure of scope for increase in our exports.

Parly Sec. Not where country is not “viable” itself – e.g. Argentine has no money

B/T. anyway.

L. Ch. I agree with First Secy. And, even if we control imports, farmers will still react against cut in a prodn wh. we have been trying to increase for sake of b/p. To stop open ended commitment is desirable: but look for some other way of doing it.

Ch. Exch. We want greater net output: not greater gross output.

M. Edn And we must stress present inefficient use of capital. This is our main justification for measures wh. will be politically v. difficult, in light of N.E.D.C. doctrine of growth.

Ch. Duchy I agree with First Secy. But provided we control imports, we can put new policy across.

M.W.P. Must reconsider amount of land under prodn. Defence interest?

M. Def. No longer any defence interest in keeping marginal land in prodn.

P.M. Not sure: fashions in war change! Use up land for New Towns?

M.H.L.G. That involves location of industry considns. We must try to foster amalgamations of farms – not to increase prodn, but to reduce costs.

M.A.F.F. Proposals – won‟t put up prices – apart from levy subsidy (if we do it). Even ½d on loaf might be swamped by ordinary rise in costs.

P.M. Let Cttee of Ministers settle questions to be settled and report to Cab. I will arrange.

F. Sec. I share L. Ch.‟s misgivings: there must be some element of growth, to match industry‟s N.E.D.C. rate of growth.

M.A.F.F. I agree. My proposals won‟t win votes. [Exit M. Education.

Ch. Exch. We are not limiting growth – only uneconomic growth.

M.A.F.F. Given no rise in consumpn, we can only get growth by limiting imports (and cooperating in intl agreements for disposal of surpluses).

P.M. Two problems: a) import controls or not: b) how introduce concept of growth.

Cttee shd. give Cabinet two lists of questions:-

i) those which we must answer – for G.A.T.T. etc.

ii) .. .. affect political problem of presentation – growth etc.

[Exit M.A.F.F.

8. Reform of the Exchequer Accounts. C(63) 66.

Ch. Sec. Fulfils our promise &amp; modernises procedure.

P.M. Approve.

</content>
</cab>
