<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/83/33 images: 350-359</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   CABINET

/&gt;\\&gt; CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street on THURSDAY 16 OCTOBER 1986   Jy at 10.30 am PRESENT ^ The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP Prime Minister he Rt Hon Viscount Whitelaw/A^\ The Rt Hon Lord Hailsham of St Marylebone ,ord President of the Counci ^Lord Chancellor [he Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP V   Mon Douglas Hurd MP Chancellor of the Exchequer Secretary of State for the Home Department [he Rt Hon Peter Walker MP The Rt H  n George YounSer MP Secretary of State for Energy Secretary of State for Defence The Rt Hon Nicholas Edwards MP Rt Hon John Biffen MP Secretary of State for Wales /xv^ord Privy Seal Ihe Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP M  n ^orman Tebbit MP Secretary of State for Social Services ^piiancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster The Rt Hon Tom King MP Th^^JJon Michael Jopling MP Secretary of State for Northern Ireland Minxgi$y of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food The Rt Hon Nicholas Ridley MP The Rt&lt;6on Lord Young of Graffham Secretary of State for the Environment Secretar^ of State for Employment The Rt Hon Kenneth Baker MP The Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP Secretary of State for Education and Science Paymaster Gene^v\ The Rt Hon John MacGregor MP The Rt Hon Malca&apos;idPR^.fkind QC MP Chief Secretary, Treasury Secretary of Stc^^^p^is Scotland The Rt Hon Paul Channon MP The Rt Hon John Moor%&gt;\ Secretary of State for Trade and Industry Secretary of State f^v^ransport THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT

The Rt Hon John Wakeham MP The Rt Hon Baroness Young Parliamentary Secretary Treasury Minister of State, Fore ignN^)  xfommonwea 1th

Office


   		SECRETARIAT			

Q		Sir Robert Armstrong			

		Mr D F Williamson	(Items	3 and 4)	

(t		Mr C L G Mallaby	(items	3 and 4)	

&lt;		Mr A J Langdon	(it ems	il 2 and 5)	

		Mr M J Eland	(It ems	1, 2 and 5)	

	%	\ CONTENTS			

Item	\	y Subject			Page

1.	PARL	affairs			1

2.	HOME	AFF^^T)			

		\V			

		Immigi^.^n Control: Visa Regimes			1

		Social Security			1

		Interest Rates^   N			1

		Changes in Sto  Ji  s&amp;hange Rules			2

		Deregulation of B  ts^i  fcvices			2

		Unemployment Figures/v^^\			2

3.	FOREIGN AFFAIRS &lt;/x\				

		Meeting between the Unit  ^gi^^es and Soviet Leaders in Iceland			3

		El Salvador			4

		The People&apos;s Republic of China y\			5

		Immigration Control: Visa Regimes			5

					

4.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS Y/y		?		

		Agriculture v			6

		Export of Lamb: Incidents in France		n	6

		Liberalisation of Air Traffic	c	  	6

		Finance	(	stti	6

		International Monetary Fund: Managing Director			7

5.	THE	QUEEN&apos;S SPEECHES ON THE PROROGATION AND OPENING OF PARLIAMENT			7

				m	


   /    zOTARY 1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House of Commons in the following week.

FFAIR5 &apos;   yO

THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL said that the House of Lords had a v^X^ery heavy load of business, but he remained reasonably confident that &lt;V\^twey would keep abreast of it without major problems.

^TIWE^ORD PRIVY SEAL said that the House of Commons, too, would be under S&apos;miS&apos;iwerable pressure for the remainder of the Session as major Bills re&lt;  &lt;irn&amp;i from the Lords. He still hoped, however, that Prorogation coul^^t-*ke place on 7 November.

m

I0ME AFFAIRS 2. THE HOME SECRETARY said that, thanks to the co-operation of the

Foreign and ComjnAnwealth Office, it had been possible to introduce visa Immigration	requirements	Ftff~Yiationa Is of	India, Pakistan and Bangladesh on the

ontrol:	previous day.	\^Th^e had been	a last minute rush to beat the

/isa Regimes requirement, mos/f/   o^Vhis influx consisting of single young men from Previous	Bangladesh who	to be acting on the advice of travel agents.

Reference:	Co-operation	with &lt;hW^rline	operators in India and Pakistan had been

CC(86) 31.3	good, but it	was thcMg^tNthat	there might be some trouble with a flight

from Bangladesh on ttfe^pv! owing day. At present there was a backlog of some 400 cases, 100 peorrf^lvad been sent back on the previous day and more were awaiting remc^^^T^nThere had been a good deal of media interest in the accommoda^-rpy^Sf would-be entrants at hotels, pending their examination. In the/  a^\&gt;of those who were refused admission and returned, however, this acc^toer^ltion cost fell on the carrier and not on the taxpayer. He would b^m^ps^^g a statement in the House of Commons the following week.

in

%&gt;

Social	THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIAL SERVICES said that he would be making

Security	a statement the following week on the   ^  rating of social security

benefits. The uprating would be in line with the change in the retail price index for the relevant period. The phasing in of the new April uprating date meant that this would be the tl^T^S uprating in the past sixteen months and he would stress in his pr\^ei    stion that the increases needed to be viewed together.	if Vt

% .

Interest	THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that base rates h^tf&gt;  isen by

Rates	i per cent earlier in the week. This had followed a VjMg&apos;Veriod of

turbulence in the markets and pressure on sterling. Tft^te^vad been pressure to raise base rates in the previous week but in circumstances then prevailing a 2 per cent rise would havA^\bl|^ needed to satisfy the markets. As it was, he believed that a 1 pe^&amp;y  brise would now suffice. He was encouraged in this view by the tac(yt\ptthe


   \vlLo	half-yearly figures for the Public Sector Borrowing Requirement which

would be published later that day would show that borrowing was in line with the forecasts made at the time of the Budget. It remained to be seen, however, what would be the outcome and implications of the forthcoming meeting of the Oil Producing and Exporting Countries.

Ik

es in TMX^RETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY said that on 27 October tlre    ^k Exchange would abolish minimum commissions and the single nj&quot; e	cap^&gt;    &gt;ystem of jobbers and brokers (the so-called &quot;Big Bang&quot;). The

&lt;chan8	StoctFlfcthapge were confident that the change would pass off smoothly.

rleS	He wou^Kdike every effort to ensure that in the publicity surrounding

the chSke it was made clear that this was a further consequence of the Government&apos;s drive to promote competition and remove restrictive practices, and an integral part of its policy to strengthen the City of London&apos;s international position. The Chancellor of the Exchequer would be referring (cttt change in his speech that night at the Mansion House.

%

^regulation THE SECRETARY OF STATCED&amp;TRANSPORT said that final deregulation of bus f Bus	services would take eti  r0Xom Sunday 26 October. He and the Minister

ervices	of State, Department of dtfar^port (Mr Mitchell) had planned extensive

publicity to accompany tnvs^^^nt. There would also be a series of frevious	advertisements highlightin^V^p^rtunities for small businesses in the

Reference:	new deregulated industry. T^^would be accompanied by a guidance

;c(86) 31.4	leaflet and booklet for potent  M/Ww operators. He would send written

briefing to Cabinet col league sM&gt;n/p^ background to the change and the Minister of State would be writi&amp;g&apos;t^all Members of Parliament. The Opposition Parties would no doubt&lt;^  k  to exploit any initial problems in the period immediately after th  ^S3#nee but he was confident that these would be confined to isolated &lt;UW  rents and would be only short-lived.	\\

The Cabinet -

Took note.	((

%

Unemployment THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that, c^p^r^v to alleged Figures	leaks in the newspapers and speculation by the Oppo&amp;irts^^ the

unemployment figures being released later that day Previous	encouraging. Although the unadjusted headline total w^^JjOOO higher

Reference:	than in the previous month, this was a low increase for\S^^s^er and,

CC(86) 31.4	when seasonally adjusted, showed a fall of 22,000, which

greatest monthly fall since April 1979. The seasonally	average

for the previous six months was now flat, while vacancies


   [yx\ higher figure than at any time since December 1979. Although the full underlying reasons were not yet apparent, it was satisfactory to note that the number of school-leavers on the count was the lowest since 1980. The Restart programme, aimed at the long term unemployed, was having an effect, and it was helpful that a Manpower Services &lt;^V?8^mmission survey of the pilot programme showed 60 per cent of those

ponding stating that they were leaving the register because they had

&quot;tjyfolA jobs.

TK^PjiiME MINISTER summing up a short discussion, said that these figg^^^were very encouraging. While it would be right to show quiet sati^-raj^cion, the Government should not depart from their practice of refusi^a^u forecast future employment trends. An important point to stress was the sustained rise in vacancies.

The Cabinet -

Took not*V|\

  Eg

OREIGN	3. THE MINISTER OF	FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE (BARONESS

ffFAIRS	YOUNG) said that theO^^ttil public reaction to the meeting the previous

L__	weekend in Reykjavik betw^v the United States President, Mr Ronald

eet.ing	Reagan, and the Genera l^^Tmtary of the Communist Party of the Soviet

jetween the	Union, Mr Mikhail Gorbach^vO&apos;tad been one of disappointment. Both sides

Inited States were now, however, emphasitf  n&amp;^he possibility of building on the md Soviet	progress that had been made\$jfo$ykjavik on various aspects of nuclear

Leaders in	arms control. The members of^^orth Atlantic Treaty Organisation had

Iceland	rallied to the support of the	of the Reykjavik meeting by the

United States.

The surprisingly wide areas of pot^H^^. agreement at the meeting had included the elements that there sho^Jic^^Ste 50 per cent cuts in the strategic nuclear forces of both powe^&apos;over five years and that over ten years all their ballistic missiles&apos;Oiin the United States view) or all their offensive nuclear weapons (in the Soviet view) should be eliminated. In the category of intermediate nuclear forces (INF), there had been agreement on the complete removal f^pm^Europe of missiles of the longer ranges, while each side would reqaj^n^iOO warheads, those of the Soviet Union being held in Asia and thosey^&apos;Ty&apos;e United States in the United States. There would be a freeze on\^fi/^eveIs in Europe of shorter range INF, with negotiations being held ^&gt;#wently to reduce the levels. According to the Soviet side, there	virtual

agreement on a phased approach to constraints on nOT^Vi^weapons tests, probably starting with steps to improve the measures oj^^^rification that had been foreseen in two United States/Soviet tri^i^is\which had not yet been ratified by the United States - the Thresn^Ld^^e^st Ban Treaty and the Peaceful Nuclear Explosions Treaty. This e^ft^is on verification would be helpful to the Government&apos;s public	on

nuclear test constraints. Mr Gorbachev&apos;s explicit confirma^^V^^o Mr Reagan that the modernisatin of the British nuclear detert^jK^y^s not


   tnt? vindicated the firm

relevant to a United   ates/Sovret ^agreement^n INFjtn^	^

position	United Kingdom about the Government s

useful in the debate in   t      	The failure to achieve

kri  Sag&quot;re  eantqUonr:ny of the .attet. discussed in tb.	^

should be confined to

a t or i e s.

V/y\	a ar Revkiavik would have accorded with the

W&amp;K the ideas di|eu|s  d at y J	or of the United Kingdom. But

ife^  f the 8orth i -rh accoidtd fully with British policy, namely on %&apos;S   the Mtt&quot;S	and constraints on short range INF, the

reducrtvnp^m longer ra g	t from the position it had taken in

M|     b$i.E*  &amp; a-ould continue to press for progress in this field.

in discussion ^following points were made -

\i-vi4s&apos;* in Reykiavik had been prepared as a meeting which a. The teefe&lt;iSS. f	le United States-Soviet Summit m the

m  ghta11	fact the meeting had gone much further than

United 5tath^    tn     ior to a full-scale Summit. The position preparatory	Qn INF had acCorded fully with prior

taken by the Un&lt;*^C\L&gt; Anies The proposal to reduce the

consultations a^ng^Aliie .	   states an(J the Soviet Union

strategic nuclea^	s was aiso welcome. The United

by 50 per cent wlth^^2^.^dent Reagan   s refusal to renounce the Kingdom should	against nuclear weapons, not

possibility	  ad a shield of

least because the S  vie^w/A

anti-ballistic missiles Y$  ^oscow.

t-he* United States and the Soviet b. Detailed   g0^11  08 se    4&amp;&gt;progress could now be made.

Union would be needed, to	ention to the importance of

Those negotiations shou pay	^ piaCe against the

background  of tS*    t  egf*   

-=   :rirco^tao::norcas in Europe and in chemical weapons.	ul)

o.	The points which th^Gov  rn   ,e&quot;i0f^5Si  rSdefeScesl  lready

included ?he Soviet Onion&apos;s possess^of	Onio   .s

and its continued research	lead by^fesraining research

consequent interest in maintai g	agreement in

by the United States;^strategic defencef^  ^ not take

a   I Sweats   -

^eSnf   ^^! agreement, in	well

as in the nuclear field.


   ^ vyy&apos;K	d. The history of the negotiations between the United States, the

^vvTv	Soviet Union and the United Kingdom which had led to the conclusion

of the Partial Nuclear Test Ban Treaty in 1963 provided a good v//y\	example of the need for thorough and private preparation of arms

control agreements.

%

L gaivador THg/mHikSTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE said that almost l,O(10^eAPle bad been killed, 10,000 injured and 150,000 rendered homeCSff^an the earthquake in El Salvador on 10 October. The United Kingdoreacted rapidly with the provision of assistance. This had includew&apos;a helicopter of the Royal Air Force, which had reached El Salvadorvfrom Belize on 12 October, bringing medical supplies, water purification kits and generators as well as army doctors. Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington would that day be visiting El Salvador as representative^tf?\the British Presidency of the European Community together withUheVyiuted States Secretary of State and others, and would see the situationV6m\the ground.

%

The People&apos;s THE MINISTER OF STATE, F$RMGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE drew attention to Republic of	the great success of th^&apos;jatfrtent visit by Her Majesty The Queen (with

China	the Foreign and Commonwea^thr^eeretary in attendance) to the People&apos;s

Republic of China.

Previous	V	&apos;X S/l

Reference:

CC(86) 23.2

mt

Immigration THE MINISTER OF STATE, FOREIGN AND COiffl^fSwEALTH OFFICE said that the Control:	Prime Minister of India, Mr Rajiv Ghana  , had said in Australia that the

Visa Regimes introduction of United Kingdom visas for citizens of India was a racialist move which accorded with the Government&apos;s racist policy towards South Africa. These unjustified and x  ?eto.ocative remarks by the Previous	Indian Prime Minister would be raised with th4 Indian High Commissioner

Reference:	when he called at the Foreign and Commonwealtn-^^fibe that afternoon.

CC(86) 31.3

The Cabinet -Took note.


   4.	THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that the Agriculture Council on 13-14 October had examined the Commission&apos;s FAIRS	posals to deal with the critical situation in the milk sector. The

[T i	milk quota system was not working as efficiently as it should: some

nCU xr&gt;^$armers had concluded that it was still worthwhile to raise their

(&lt;\vptoduction above the quota levels. It was clear that only a part of the ^/  jMtanission&apos;s proposals had any chance of acceptance. The United Kingdom ^V^^dency had therefore sought to explore other methods of tackling the in particular a further reduction in quotas and an increase in tHe^le^ to be paid on milk produced above the quota. He hoped that this  ^o  i? enable the Commission to adjust its package and to facii^^te^progress at the next meeting. The Council had reached with difficv^tj^an agreement on the treatment in the immediate future of raonetaryReompensatory amounts for eggs and poultry.

Lrts of THE MINISTER A^^RULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD said that he had spoken rb.	again that day t^?Moh)sieur Guillaume, the French Minister of

[cidents in Agriculture, aboSt  k)dents in which lamb from the United Kingdom had Lance	been blocked or dedtfD&amp;&gt;  d by French farmers. He had received a clear

assurance that new ito^uktions to protect these vehicles and their loads had been given	French police and that compensation would be

H m

iberalisa- THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TR^WR said thaC he bad held an informal ion of Air	meeting of Community Ministers Wf T^Xnsport on 3 October. At the

Traffic	Transport Council in June it had&lt;&gt;   eppapparent that a substantial

majority of member states were aga&lt;ro  t-^any significant liberalisation of air traffic and fares. Since then ^^United Kingdom had been successful in detaching France, the ^4e  al Republic of Germany and Italy from this opposition. The chants of some modest progress towards our objectives on air transport liberalisation at the Council on 10-11 November had improved.

CL

Finance	THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that the ENWaJp and Finance

Council on 13 October, in the presence of the Pre^Vp^ of the Commission, Monsieur Delors, and of Vice-President^jid^essen and Christophersen, discussed the serious problem of poft^fl^j}^ overspending on agriculture. The forecasts for 1987 were alarming i^^elation to the 1.4 per cent value added tax ceiling. He had been abl^to^each Presidency conclusions which should be helpful to the	of

Agriculture, Fisheries and Food in pressing for the neces^^ction in the Agriculture Council. On greater liberalisation of capNi^^^  yem  ntS within the Community some further progress had been made ancP&apos;h^^ped that agreement could be reached at the next Council. On loanV^&gt;X^


   for small and medium enterprises there were disagreements but the Presidency would be continuing its efforts to resolve them.

% -etary	/  ^Tffagues in the Community the appointment of a new Managing Director

)(j.	  fiytjve^lnternational Monetary Fund which had been held by someone of

iaging	Frviicb^ationality for 18 of the last 23 years. Mr Ruding, the

rector	NetK^  igtfi)4s&apos; Minister of Finance and Monsieur Camdessus, Governor of the

Bank of/TMice, were candidates and neither was likely to withdraw. It

seemedv  $fely, therefore, that for the first time there would be two

candidates from Community member states in the field right through to

the finaT decisions. Within the Community there was probably a small

majority for Mr Ruding but it was uncertain whether, taking account of

the views of third countries, he would be successful.

The Cabin&amp;2D.j^ZX

Took note. &apos;v~   -xw

% .

IE QUEEN   S 5. The Cabinet considered hu memorandum by the Lord President of the

   EECHES ON Council (C(86) 20) to whib^iri^s attached drafts of The Queen&apos;s Speeches

IE PR0R0GA- on the Prorogation and Opetfi^^Vf Parliament.

ION AND

fENlNG OF	THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUfiQjfe^eid that the draft Speeches attached

IrlIAMENT	to his memorandum had been	The Queen&apos;s Speeches and Future

Legislation Committee (QL) on th^ba^s of suggestions put forward by colleagues and were in their con-ve^^xa&amp;l form. The only issue to which he needed to draw the Cabinet&apos;s atSirf^on was the importance of keeping the legislative programme in the nextJ^Sie&apos;Ssion within manageable bounds and the consequent need, explained in\Ku.s memorandum, to find compensating reductions in the programme for any additions that might prove necessary. The possibility of legislation being needed on teachers&apos; pay and conditions of service now seemed sufficiently real for him to take soundings of his colleagues on QX/anm they were in no doubt that the Intellectual Property Bill was the ii^lv^aa^sure whose removal would release the necessary drafting and Pariiamenoary time to accommodate the new measure.

THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE AND INDUSTRY said	was grateful

to the Lord President for giving him notice of his	He was

bound to register that the Intellectual Property Bill	long overdue

measure of real assistance to British industry and had ^iready been the subject of five Green and White Papers. The Governmentputting pressure on other countries to improve their copyright re  lli^&apos;  nd such improvement was much needed in the United Kingdom. In part^cuir, undertakings had been given to the pharmaceutical industry.

Consumer Protection Bill was of yet higher priority.


   THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said that the Cabinet accepted the Lord President&apos;s assessment that a Bill would have to be deleted from the programme to make room for legislation on teachers&apos; pay and conditions of service, if that proved necessary. The Cabinet also ..noted that the Bill to be deleted might need to be the Intellectual (YSroperty Bill in the absence of any realistic alternative. The Lord    VjMsesident would consult further with QL and with the Secretary of State Trade and Industry, and report his conclusions to the Cabinet. The /Hp^iCing Speech would then need amendment accordingly. The Cabinet an^&lt;3ved the draft Speeches attached to C(86) 20, subject to the incln^on in the Opening Speech of a reference to the Coal Bill, which wa^iwr^^nown to be free of any risk of hybridity; to some amendments to the pa!y5ag  s dealing with defence and foreign affairs; and to some misceri^eous drafting points. Other changes might be necessitated by later developments, including those already described. The Secretary of the Cabinet should now prepare revised versions of the Speeches for her to submit to The Queen for approval.

The Cabi^^^

1.	Subjec^Tjythe changes agreed in discussion, approved thV-d^dwi Speeches attached to C(86) 20.

2.	Ins true te&lt;Cd  n&lt;ivtecretary of the Cabinet to prepare a finalVewL    3n of the draft Speeches, taking account of ^^a^\changes, for the Prime Minister to submit Thjfe Queen.

3.	Invited the Lord ^ti^Kient of the Council to proceed as indicated invM^MyPrime Minister&apos;s summing up.

   

I . u&gt;

16 October 1986



</content>
</cab>
