<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/221/13 images: 476-482</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
   CABINET

&lt;  &gt; ----------------

&lt;X^  AH00L TEACHERS&apos; PAY, DUTIES AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE

VS/	Note by the Secretary of the Cabinet

% ----------------

I attach a paper prepared by the Ministerial Group on Teachers&apos; Pay (MISC 122).

s

BH

ROBERT ARMSTRONG

   

Cabinet Office 29 October 1986

CL


   ^O^^CHOOL TEACHERS&apos; PAY, DOTIES AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE

Report by the MI SC 122 Group

%

The CabirtefQi&amp;reed in the spring that industrial action by teachers iiv%  c^land and Wales and in Scotland should be defused respectively^^yyendorsement of negotiations under the auspices of the Advisor^ Conciliation and Arbitration Service (ACAS) and by the appointment of the Committee of Inquiry chaired by Sir Peter Main. An inter  3in agreement for England and Wales was reached at Coventr^K^iup^July by the local authority employers and unions representing aum^jjarity of teachers, covering pay and pay structure and certain a&lt;  p&amp;p  s of conditions of service; that agreement envisaged a fii    jX^reement being reached by the end of the year which would conf^^rK the understandings reached and settle major outstanding is^^^on duties and conditions of service. The Main Report, wit^V&apos;re&amp;ommendations on teachers&apos; pay, duties and conditions of s^ral/ce, was published on 2 October as Cmnd 9 893.	y\

Coventry

2.	The Coventry agreement did not me6t^the conditions laid down by the then Secretary of State for&apos;  ducation and Science when he announced the Government&apos;s offer of additional provision for teachers&apos; pay of   1 ,250 million (for Engl    et\and Wales, with a further   125 million for Scotland) over foui^y^rs in return for a satisfactory agreement covering pay, pay	s

structure, duties and conditions of service. It	put all

unpromoted teachers, regardless of merit, on a basr^^^le running up to   14,500, i.e. 40 per cent higher than t^^^tesent scale; and it left for further negotiation the length teachers&apos; working week, the amount of class contact time^/^j&amp;dts on class size, and the circumstances under which teachers &lt;c required to cover for absent colleagues - all of them points^ojyy^ which concessions by the employers would prove very expensively^


   itWcl include, however, a broadly satisfactory list of *|L,. duties, and it accepted the principle a^O^l- Most participants at Coventry envisaged that

lSS&gt;katutory Burnham Committee, whose remit is restnc e to P^&amp;ithe voluntary Council of Local Education Authorities SchoiSAers, Co-ittee. which covers conditions of service,

Id be Wiked by new voluntary joint negotiating machinery covering bI|L and conditions; the Government would have no locus in thes^new arrangements.

The Main Repoi/^commendations on duties and conditions of

service are generalizes is tent with the Government so Dec

c    	the auality of education and

fives in terms of xwpbe^m tne qnaix y

providing for the smocking of the schools. The scope for teachers to take disruPti&lt;    5ki  n without being clear y breach of their contracts W^)be drastically reduced. On pay

i ohe^mekt the Government   s wish to &lt;=fmcture. the recommendations^  ^:

structure,	responsibility and proven

provide greater rewar	recommends increases of

good performance. On pay,	these are greater than

worth 16.4 per cen	thf^K of Coventry would

^nvisacred at Coventry, although the

eventually exceed those of Main as united teachers moved up towards the maximum of a basic pay sca&lt;nearly 20 per cent above that recommended for Scotland. The	|g

would set pay scales to operate until March	^

would be no &apos;normal&apos; annual settlement in piky^\	present

negotiating machinery, Main envisages replacem^t^f	P

statutory Joint Negotiating Committee (which	^

conditions) by a Standing Advisory Committee with

April 1988.

gnhfisguent developments	, ^^yia^les

\---Practically no ki  ss has been made for England a5^

has been made since Coventry; a further negotiating sessionC^)\

. is scheduled at Nottingham on 8 November under ACAS auspices is scneauie


      OThe English unions, seeing the larger immediate pay increases &apos;/^^commended by Main, are seeking &apos;faster assimilation&apos; to the &lt;/C^vwitry pay scales; the National Association of Schoolmasters/ USr^flXof Women Teachers, which was not a party to the Coventry agrSjajJt^nt, is seeking a further increase in the basic scale maxiSnunL/)and has called for further industrial action beginning next	In Scotland there seems to be a good prospect that

the union  /^d local authority employers will accept the Main package an^/jiagotiate it into place through the existing machinery, prpvipded that the Government makes full public expenditure provision for it.

The Government&apos;s Response

5.	The Ministers(air^ctly concerned, meeting under the Prime Minister&apos;s chairmansnpln MISC 122, have considered how the Government should respomy/to the Main Report, and to the situation developing in ^  rad^and and Wales. The Group&apos;s recommendations to the C^ima^are as follows:

(i)	the Government sntprvKaccept the Main recommendations on pay, duties and conditions of service.

(ii)	The Government should	an immediate initiative

to bring the &apos;Coventry process&apos;	end, so as to preclude

further expensive concessions by t^Jre/^ocal authority employers and prevent the implementation of the Coventry pay structure.

(iii)	Accordingly the Government shoulq^nisite the parties to agree at Nottingham to a &apos;Main-equivalerfr^Osettlement for England and Wales on lines which the Educatiq^^epretary would lay down.

(iv)	The Main and Main equivalent salary scale^X^nould be introduced in two stages, providing for average incresislgs of

Wk


   2 oer cent on 1 January 1987, and for the remaining 8.2 cent increases on 1 October 1987.

Failing agreement following Nottingham (or in the ScoW^^} Joint Negotiating Committee), the Government should 1	to impose the settlement. For England and Wales

they w^^jd-act in the light of recommendations made by an interimAovi^ory Committee, which would work within a cost envelope sfcnsistent with their response to the Main recommendations; given that the Main report already exists, there would be no-rieed for such a Committee in respect of Scotland until Q98$-89.

(vi)	No additiorr^J^payments should be made to teachers until they have eith^^a&amp;cepted the new specification of their duties and condxtrp^te of service in negotiation, or these have been put int&apos;^mect

by means of regulations mcG^  &apos;wider the new legislation imposing the Government1 s

(vii)	Provision should be ma^e^^jp the full additional

costs of   118 million and   14	in 1986-87, and   490

million and   60 million in 1987-88^f^: England and Wales and for Scotland respectively. Thi^additional provision reoresents the whole of the additional costs of the proposed settlement beyond the 3.75 per cent allowe^^for in next year&apos;s Rate Support Grant settlements foik^n&amp;Keased costs.

In recognition of the fact that local authqri  a/es will have been planning on an increase for teachers gra^wij?&gt;than 3.75 per cent, and in order to give them some incent^K^\  o find offsetting savings, especially in the education additional Exchequer grant for 1987-88 should be j^jjVj^ted to   200 million for England and Wales and   30 millio(f  ^ur Scotland; the effect would be a small reduction in tnq^]/^^ overall Exchequer grant percentage for England from 46.


   y 46.3, with corresponding reductions in the Scottish and (/X Welsh percentages.

The Government&apos; s decisions should be announced on 30 &quot;OLber in statements to be made by the Secretaries of ^I^Wation and Science and for Scotland.

more than   0.5 billion to public

6.	and more than   0.8 billion in 1988-89

eXp rUr%iCars Treasury Ministers have only accepted and subsequen^yea	and on the strict condition

them with the g^3   *her incr  ases. They threaten very that there can	ssi  kn $J| sector pay settlements,

awkward repercuss	resist. They will also mean some

which it will be essg	increases are already

further increase   authorities will be about 2 per in the pipeline, which	therefore be

cent, in presenting the	^ ^

essential to emphasise:

JvTiVx&apos;iVf f er represents an excep    i I \	that the Governments^   er rep

U)	M^  bense to the situation m

tional - and very generous - ^nse

the teaching profession;

H that it is quite differeSfl^ other pay settle-

    that it requires acceptan^ of much more tightly ments, in that it requir	. in return for the

specified duties and conditions of service

new pay deal;

(iii) that it represents the Government&apos;word, and that no further concessions could be made;

(iv)	that it inevitably imposes substantial t^costs,

    Edition to increases in expenditure (much o education) which local authorities are already plan^0^ which have to he met by the ratepayer and taxpayer


   &quot;0 improvements in the quantity and quality of public services have to be paid for.

Tire^Csbinet will have before them drafts of the statements to be madfe^$i\the Secretaries of State for Education and Science and for S&amp;OT^nd.

Leqislat:jg#r^.

7.	Legis^^^SNi will in any event be required in due course to repeal the Remuneration of Teachers Act and so abolish the Burnham Committee; that Committee has proved ineffective, deals only with pay and not with duties, and gives the Secretary of State no influence over the negotiations. This will be made clear in the annoui/rnn^nt of the Government&apos;s offer. It would not be appropriate to/pt&amp;te at this stage precisely how the Government would impos^^/settlement on the lines set out above, if the local authority e^wers and teachers&apos; unions failed to negotiate it into place tnrmidK the existing machinery.

However, the Government will^iee)d to make their intentions clear as soon as it emerges that ne^^s^ions are failing; thus there may well be a need for a furthe^a^nouncement about the content of legislation in the second half^pfj^ext month. The precise timing and content of legislation wc^Tlxjaeed to take account of the behaviour of the teachers, their~  arc  9ns, and the local authority employers in the developing qA}&amp;kt\on; it will be essential to ensure that there can be nc^question of the existing Statutory Committees awarding further pay increases before 1988 once a settlement on the Governments terms has been accepted. The Education Ministers, in consulv^t^en with the Environment Secretary, the Chief Secretary, Treaspi^. the Attorney-General and the Government&apos;s Business Ma^agp^s, will be carrying forward work in preparation for legislatio^AV^

&lt;#$)

Conclusion

8.	The Group seeks the endorsement of the Cabinet of t^^M. recommendations in paragraph 5 above.

Cabinet Office

29 October, 1986	6	&lt;^&lt;7/



</content>
</cab>
