<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/37/7 images: 88-101</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS BOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT) !TO BF i^coT n..---- 4MOST SECRET.Jt is-^IINDERLOOKANJDKEVensure me s,faul.tt0u 0&apos;,   &apos; 8 may hg :;t:-QG)py NO.J  1 1,1,6 document.-&quot;&quot;*-&quot;W.M,(43) 18TH CONCLUSIONS . MINUTE 1.Confidential Annex.(27til January, 1943   -   12.15 p.m.)CASABLANCACONFERENCE.(Proposed-meeting between the&quot;Prime Ministerand Representa-tives of Turkey.(previous reference:W*M.(43)15th &quot;Conclusions,Minuto l).The War Cabinet had before them copies ofthree telegrams from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador inAngora (Nos^ 165, 166 and 167)t   The first of these telegrams contained the reply from the President ofthe Turkish Republic to the message from the PrimeMinister.    The ^resident said that., hewould be glad to meet the Prime Minister at any timeand any place in Turkey, but that he could not leaveTurkey without appointing a remplacant, and this legalrequirement would not permit of his keeping the projected meeting secret.If a meeting in Turkey could not take place,the President of the Council, M. Saracogluj would beready to meet the Prime Minister in CyprusiIn a covering telegram, our Ambassadorexplained that the&apos; President of the Turkish Republicwas willing either to receive the Prime Ministerofficially and publicly in iingora or elsewhere, or tohave a secret meeting in the Presidential train.These telegrams had already been repeated tothe Prime Minister at Cairo*The War Cabinet discussed the matter, andcame to the following Conclusions:-(l) They took the strongest view that Angorashould not be contemplated, for securityreasons.(.2)   They would not take the same serious view ofthe security problem if a meeting were heldon the Presidential train at some isolatedpoint on the frontiers(3)    Though there would be advantages in ameeting with President Inonu, from thesecurity point of view the War cabinet would definitely prefer that a insistingshould be held in Cyprus.(A telegram embodying these conclusions&apos;- was approved by the War Cabinet, and despatched to the Prime Minister asTELESCOPE NO. 303..)&apos;.*Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.I.

Unparaphrased version of a Most Secret &quot;Cypher &quot;Telegramnot One lime.Table,TELESCOPE No. 298.TOO 0050Z/27.TOD 0125Z/27.MOST SECRET CYPHER TELEGRAM.MOST IMMEDIATE.From: -     Air Ministry.To:-       MideastrTELESCOPE No. 298.      27th January, 1943.Following is a repetition of Telegram No. 165 from.M. Ambassador, Angora, despatched 6,35 p.m. 26tffs^oTaryreceived by Foreign Office 8.40 p.m. 26th January.Begins.President of the Council asks me to transmit the.following message from the President of the Republic to thePrime Minister/Quote.I have received with great satisfaction yourreauest to have with me,in the name of GreatBritain and the United States,a conversation onthe equipment of the Turkish Army with the mostmodern arms now in production and also on questions concerning the general defensivesecurity of Turkey. &apos;   This meeting can take&apos; pla.ce according to your wish at any time and atany place in Turkey^ and I should be particularlyhappy to-have this meeting with you.    Neverthe-less the Constitution of the Republic obliges theHead of the State to appoint a remplacant when-ever he goes out of the country and this legalreauirement would not admit of my keeping the projected meeting secret.    If a meeting inTurkey cannot take place it is of course under-stood that President of the Council Saracogluwould be at your disposal at any meeting you would desire to arrange for him in Cyprus.- / For Ills p&amp;t&apos;t
MOST SECRET-NOT TO BE QUOTED
For his part Marshal Chakmac could accompanyhim or meet the British C.I.G.S. at any timeand place.    With all friendship.See my immediately following telegram.Circulation.ueputy prime Minister.Foreign Secretary.Mr. Peck.Sir Edward Bridges.UnquoteaPresident of the Republic is replying in the same sense to Mr. Roosevelt through my United States colleague.Ends.T.0.0. 0050Z/27,

Unparaphrased. version, of a Most Secret, Cypher Telegramnot......One Time TableTELESCOPE 299TOO   0055Z/27MOST IMMEDIATE TOD   0130Z/27MOST SECRET CY/-rKR TELEGRAMFrom:-     Air ministry to:-        MideastTELESCOPE No. 299     27th. Jan., 1943.Following is a repetition of Telegram No. 166from H.M. Ambassador Angora despatched 4.35 p.m.m^orTt^&apos;January received by Foreign Office 11.20 p.m. 26th.January.Begins.My immediately preceding telegram.President of the Republic is entirely preparedto receive the Prime Minister officially and publiclyeither in Angora or aaywhere else in Turkey.    Presidentof the Council told me Ismet would very greatly appreciatemeeting Churchill.   -2. If this cannot be done he would be ready forsecret meeting e*g. Presidential train could go to any point desired.    Turkish Government would do everything possible to safeguard secrecy.    This would be far fromeasy.     Incidentally the German Embassy have for somedays been asking questions as to the Prime Ministerswhereabouts though latter have no suspicion of present plan.3. If the Prime Minister prefers meeting Saracogluin Cyprus the latter could leave Angora by train late on the night of January 31st:   he is engaged to dinewith German Ambassador that night.    I understand he isotherwise free till February 6th when he dines at the embassy.4. If Cyprus is decided upon I would propose,subject to the Prime Minister&apos;s wishes,to travel withM. Saracoglu and would bring Mr. Helm with me.See my immediately following telegram.Ends.T.0.0. 0055Z/27Circulation.Deputy &quot;Prime Minister     Mr. Peck.Foreign Secretary. Sir Edward Bridges.

Unparaphrased version of a.Most Secret Cypher*  &apos;        Telegram not One Time TabletTELESCOPE No. 300.TOO,    0100Z/27.TOD    0150Z/27.MOST SECRET CYPHER TELEGRAM,MOST IMMEDIATE. &apos; &quot;From:-       Air Ministry,To: - Mideast.. TELESCOPE No. 500,.      27th Jan. 1943.Following is a repetition of TelegramNo. 167 from H.M. Ambassador, Angora, despatched7.47 pm. 26th January received by Foreign Office9.0.p*m* 26th January.Begins..My telegrams No. 165 and No. 166.I need hardly stress the advantage ofvisit to Angora if it is thought consistent with security.Ends.T.0.0. 0100Z/27.Circulation-Deputy Prime Minister.Foreign Secretary.Mir. Peck.Sir E. Bridges.
MOST SEC&quot; - 1 -Me &apos;    -   1 CD
UnparaphrasGd Version of a most secret Cypher Telegram not One Time TableTELESCOPE NO.303TOO. 1210Z/27TOD. 1230Z/27MOST SECRET CYPHER TELEGRAMMOST MEDIATEFrom:- Air ministry to:-    MideastTELESCOPE No.303 27th January 1943,For Prime Minister personal from Deputy PrimeMinister and Foreign Secretary.War Cabinet have considered Angora telegrams165, 166, and 167.    We take the strongest view thatAngora should not be contemplated for security reason it is full of German agents and we could not accept responsibility of acquiescing in your running suchrisk.   Remember the von Papeh incident.We should not take same serious view of security problem if meeting were on train at someisolated point on frontier.&apos;Though there would be advantages in meeting with Ismet., we should from security point of viewdefinitely prefer Cyprus,T.0,0. 1210Z/27Circulation -Deputy Prime minister foreign secretary mr.PecKCapt. Clifford




</content>
</cab>
