<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/91/0 images: 51-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A QTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of........-.....--------------TOP SECRET Copy No-i?-.^C,(53) 13Zlst January, 1958CABINETRELATIONS WITH THE SOVIET union memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues a draft reply to Mr. Bulganin&apos;s letter of 9th January, 1958.o  tForeign Office, S.W.1.21st January, 195S
TOP secret draft Reply to Bulg8nin&apos;s Second LetterMy colleagues and I have now considered yourfurther letter of January 9 to which I promisedyou -an answer when replying to your earlier letterof. December 11.2.     What vou now say is that you would like ameeting of Heads of Government to be arranged quitesoon in order to discuss various proposals.    Iwelcome the idea of such a meeting as soon as appropriate arrangements for it can be made.    I will therefore deal in this letter with the topics whichmight be discussed at the meeting and the arrange-ments which need to be made.Topics for Discussion3-     You make a list of the proposals which you think might be or:, the agenda of such a meeting.    Weare of course willing to discuss all these proposalsprovided that you for your own part are willing todiscuss the proposals which we have already madeon our side.    Ihey are as follows:h.   Disarmament(a)   We propose a balanced, practical andenforceable plan for partial measures of disarma-ment such as could be carried out in the next two of three years without political conditions ofany kind.    There would be the immediate suspension of nuclear test explosions.    This suspension could continue indefinitely if within two years partiesto the agreement brought into force its second measure/whichTOP SECRET
which is to stop using any new production of fissionablematerial for the manufacture of nuclear weapons.    once this second measure had taken effect,&apos;we&apos; should be&quot;ready to begin transferring existing military stocks offissionable material to peaceful uses,    From the out-set, steps would be taken to set on fooc the controlledreduction -of conventional armaments and military manpower.We also propose a system of ground and air inspection tosafeguard against surprise 8ttack, and we offer a widechoice of areas in which this inspection might operate;we, for our part, as- part of a reciprocal arrangement are ready to op^i the whole of the United Kingdom to inspection.Besides these measures, we envisage a joint effort to preventuse of outer space for military purposes, and we offer adefinite undertaking that nuclear weapons would never beused except in self-defence.(b) We regard this programme as both realistic and practicable in the world today.    We believe it would at least be a fruitful basis for further negotiation, and the greatmajority of the United Nations have recognised it as suchat the recent session of the General Assembly.    Fifty-sevenStates supported our plan.(c) Yoiir letter suggests including only two of themeasures in our plan in the agenda you propose for a conferencethere are the suspension of tests and inspection againstsurprise attack.    You relegate other matters, including the cessation of production of fissionable material for weapons aswell as all conventional disarmament, to an indefinite future.But a ban on tests by-itself will not eliminate or stop pro-,duction of a single nuclear weapon. What the world is looking for is an assurance that the nuclear powers will not go onpiling up stocks of weapons indefinitely, and that is the/assurance
TOP SECRETTOP SECRETassurance which our proposals would give.   Again,effective disarmament must include steps toreduce the menace of huge conventional forces.All these are vital points, and they cannot be resolved simply by pushing them out of sight intothe future.(d) We have always pointed out theimportance of effective verification and control.Our proposals provide for this, but judging from thepassage of control in your letter you appear to envisage little or no control for the measures youpropose;    you still seem to be demanding definitecommitments to specific measures of disarmamentbefore there has been any agreement on control.Moreover you have not accepted our oft^repeatedproposals for expert working parties to study thepractical and detailed measures required for effective control.5.    These are all matters which in my view mustbe considered in any realistic discussion of disarmament.6*    German Beunification.We believe that until Germany is reunifiedthere will be no secure and lasting settlement inEurope.    The German people themselves long to bereunified and neither, the Soviet Government nor theBritish Government have any right to shed their responsibility to do everything in their power togive effect to this natural and legitimate German aspi-ration. You ask mo in your lottor to admit that German/reunification
reunification can only be secured by the germans themselves.   This is precisely my own point of view.But whereas you maintain that agreement betweenGermans can only be &quot;reached by means of agreementbetween the Federal German Republic and the so-calledGerman democratic Republic, we take the view thatthe natural and logical method of obtaining agreementbetween the Germans themselves is to provide for free elections throughout Germany,     By refusing toconsider this method you are in effect saying thatyou do not wish the Germans to have a Government oftheir own choice.    Our proposal, which I now repeat,is that there should be free elections throughoutGermany and that the German Government which would beset up as a consequence of these elections shouldbe free to determine the future of Germany.7.   European SecurityAt the meeting of Foreign Ministers in1955 the Soviet Representative expressed concern that the reunified Germany which was free to choose its associates in collective defence mightconstitute a threat to the Security of the soviet union.     Our proposal is that in order to meet this concern there should be concluded.a treaty which   would   provide   among   other.  - /things
TOP SECRET/things for a zone comprising areas of comparable size and depth and importance on both sides of the line of demarcationbetween the retinif ied Germany and theEast European countries in whxch levelsfor armed forces would he specified so asto establish a military balance which would contribute to European security and help to relieve the burden of all armaments.There would be appropriate provisions forthe maintenance of this balance.    In partsof the zone which lay closest to the lineof demarcation special measures might beprovided relating to the disposition ofmilitary forces and installations.    Theparties to the treaty would provide informstion on an agreed progressive basis ontheir armed forces in the zone. &apos; Therewould be agreement on progressiveprocedures of mutual inspection to verifysuch data and to warn against anypreparation for surprise attaclc.8.     East European CountriesYour objection to discussing theproblem of East European countries isbased on the theory, according to your letter, that we wish to see differentregimes come to power in those countries.We do not mind what regimes are in power in those countries provided that they are/freelyTOP SECRET
freely chosen hy the people.    But you and we and our American allies agreed in1945 that we had a responsibility for ensuring that the peoples of thosecountries were able to exercise the rightto choose the regimes under which they/ould live.    It seems obvious to us thatour commitments in this respect have notyet been&apos;discharged and it is for thisreason that I proposed that the subject should be discussed.9.     Non-Aggression PactsAs I explained in my earlier letterI think it might in certain circumstances be useful to re-enforce the provisions ofthe United Nations Charter by the negotiation of a bilateral or multilateral declarationof non-aggression.    The utility of such adeclaration would depend in my view on what practical agreements had been reached in other fields.    By itself it would   not.add to our common security.    The.form ofsuch a declaration and the circumstances inwhich it would be useful to make one shouldbe one of the points to be discussed./-!0.
TOP SECRET10.   Promotion of exchanges and contactsI am convinced that a lasting improvementin Anglo-Soviet relations must depend to a largeextent on enabling the British and Soviet peoplesto become better acquainted ,vith one another.    Iam glad that we have already made some progress inthis direction by arranging exchanges of peopledrawn from different walks of life in our twocountries.      In particular, we are looking forward to welcoming an increased number of Soviet students and young people who have been invited to this country by our youth organisations under the auspices ofthe Soviet Relations Committee of the british council.   But this is only a small beginning and much remains to be done if our peoples are reallyto learn about each otherfs views, achievements andways of life.   For this purpose, there must be complete freedom to exchange ideas and information.    While there are no barriers to thison the British side, the Soviet Government stillimpose various restrictions which are not calculated to promote a closer Anglo- Soviet understanding.   Ihave in mind particularly the jamming of the Russianservice of the British Broadcasting Corporation, thefact that British newspapers and books are not on/freeTOP SECRET
free sale in the Soviet Union and theobstructions placed by current Sovietregulations in the way of Soviet citizenswishing to visit the United Kingdom and other western countries.   All these matters should bdiscussed.11.   Expansion of tradeI should very much welcome a further expansion of Anglo-Soviet trade.   There isi large area where there ere no securityrestrictions and where progress can easily be made if there is the will.    This subject should also be on the agenda of any meeting.^uery e paragraph on theMiddle Easfj712*   Arrangements for a meeting as I have already said, I welcome theidea of a summit meeting,  provided that appropriate arrangements can be made.     these arrangements include decisions about: -(a) the date for the meeting;(b) the place for the meeting;(c) the participation in the meeting;(d) the way in which the subjects to bediscussed are prepared for us.The decisions as to time and place should/not be
TOP SECRETnot &quot;be difficult once agreement has beenreached about the other two matters.13.     With regard to the participation inthe conference, I have noted yoursuggestions.    That seems to me to be amatter for further private discussion,lh.     With regard to the method of preparing the work of the conference, I believe that more must be done than was done before themeeting at Geneva in July 1955 if theconference is to have concrete andsensible results and not be just an exchange of amiable platitudes.    You will remember that at the Geneva meeting, therewas a meeting of Foreign Ministers eachmorning followed by a meeting of -Heads of governments in the afternoon.    In thetime available and working by that methodwe did not achieve much.    I thereforethink that it would be righlydesirable that this time there should bea thorough preparation by a meeting atForeign Minister level, to determine theareas where there is the best chance of reconciling our divergent views.    the heads of Governments would then be ableto concentrate upon those matters and somake real progress.15.      If you still oppose the ides of a/preparatoryTOP SECRET
preparatory meeting of Foreign Ministers,then perhaps you will indicate how in yourview the preparatory work should be done.One possible solution is that we should begin by preparing for the meeting by private, and confidential diplomaticexchanges.   Should you wish to pursue this method we should be ready to accept it and so 1 believe would our allies.    Ican guarantee that if you wish further negotiations to be of this kind we wouldobserve all due discretion and furtherexchanges between us would not bepublished except by mutual agreement.16.      In all this we must remember that ourpeoples are anxious that something concretein the way of agreement should beachieved.    My anxiety is that their hopesshould not be raised in vain and that theyshould not be disappointed.    In spite of ourdifferent approaches to the various questions discussed earlier in this letter, we undoubtedly ha-ve one thing in common, namely a very strong interest inthe preservation of peace.    I believe that each side recognises that the other hasthis same interest and on this basis it oughtto be possible for us to have a useful meeting.

</content>
</cab>
