<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/91/0 images: 90-92</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   J unitary 1958C. (58) 25 Copy No.28th January, 1958CABINETWAGES POLICY:   NATIONAL HEALTH service memorandum by the Minister of health i am seeking the agreement of my colleagues to proceed at once with negotiations on a revised grading structure and associated pay scales for the clericaland lower administrative staff (up to about  1,200 a year) in the National health service.2. At the end of October I withheld my approval to a Whitley agreement fora three per cent, increase for these grades and undertook to review the questionafter an appropriate interval of time. Earlier this month the Staff Side of the whitley Council submitted a new claim, for five per cent., apparently with theobject of securing arbitration. They were persuaded to defer this claim for a short time, on condition that progress could be made with discussions on the new gradingstructure recommended by Sir Noel Hall and new pay scales appropriate to it.This recommendation is contained in the report and grading structures prepared bySir Noel Hall, the principal of the Administrative Staff College, following a detailedenquiry undertaken at the request of the Health Minister.3. Discussions on the Management Side are already in progress. Myrepresentatives have explored with the non-Departmental members (who representthe hospital and other employing authorities) possible new scales, on the expressunderstanding that they are still subject to Ministerial concurrence.4. For my own part, I am satisfied that the new grading structure proposedis a real improvement on that now existing and that the scales which have been provisionally put forward represent reasonable levels of pay for the officers concerned. Details are given in the appendix. In brief, the existing nine scalesrange from  206 to  1,092: I propose that, for the new grades (telescoped, inaccordance with Sir Noel Hall&apos;s recommendation, to five) the range should bre from  230 to  1,200 (or, at most,  1,240). Straightforward comparisons are not easy, but these figures represent increases, at the maxima of the scales, of the orderof ten per cent. The National Health Service has dropped rather seriously behindlocal government and other comparable, and competing, fields of employment andI regard these proposals as a fully justifiable measure of revaluation to bring it back into line. The cost, in a full year, of full implementation of my proposals would be of the order of  2 millions (but see paragraph 7).5. The difficulty is one of presentation. Can we agree to increases of this order without undermining our whole anti-inflationary policy? I believe that wecan and that the answer lies in:  (1) the nature of the increases proposed;(2) the method of assimilating existing staff to the new scales;(3) the date of operation.6. This is not a straightforward pay claim or one based simply on the costof living.  The operation is essentially the introduction of an improved grading52911
structure, with a consequent improvement in career prospects (which the guillebaud committee, the Select Committee on Estimates and Sir Noel Hall have allconsidered to be urgently needed). The pay increases associated with it could be presented as doing no more than bring the National Health Service back into line with other comparable employment in the public sector, as unrelated to the cost ofliving, and, therefore, as essentially non-inflationary.7. The assimilation terms, which would determine the immediate cash benefitto the staff concerned, would form part of whatever agreement was negotiated. Ifthe new scales had to be announced while the present economic climate continues,we could and should reduce their impact on pay policy generally by making their terms very stiff and stressing in our publicity the small immediate benefit. If theannouncement took place in more propitious circumstances we could perhaps afford to be more generous.8. Clearly the slower the negotiations can properly proceed, the better. if my colleagues agree that they may proceed on the figures I have proposed, I shouldnot in any case agree to a date of operation without further discussion amongourselves.9. While we are not actually committed to agreeing to the introduction ofa new grading structure and pay scales for the hospital service at any particulardate, the Cabinet will wish to recall that I have, with their concurrence, made anumber of statements on the subject which at any rate were not discouraging. On18th November (and on other occasions) I told the House that I would considerthe Whitley CounciPs recommendations on the Noel Hall report on their merits and in the light of all the circumstances at the time they were received. And on 4th December I told the Staff Side of the General Whitley Council for the health services that in this case it would be possible to base revaluation on a careful review of structure and grading and it would therefore be wrong to assume thatthe Government would feel themselves precluded by their present policy from giving effect to such a revaluation and to any associated adjustments in salary scales.10. Both sides of the Administrative and Clerical Staffs Council are pressingvery hard to begin negotiating. Delay at this stage would unquestionably revivethe claim for five per cent, on the existing scales, which is due to be discussed at ameeting on 12th February unless some progress is seen to be being made on the&quot; Noel Hall &quot; proposals. The five per cent, claim, if revived, is almost certain to goto arbitration, which at the present stage would, I think, generally be regardedas unfortunate.11. An urgent decision is therefore needed. I ask the Cabinet to agree thatI should allow the Management Side to make.an immediate start on discussions with the Staff Side, on the understanding that (1) They make no offer higher than the figures Ihave proposed in this paper.(2) I will do everything legitimately possible to prolong the negotiations.(Certain technical features should make this not too difficult.)(3) I will not agree to a date for the introduction of the new grades and scaleswithout again consulting the Cabinet.12.   The Secretary of State for Scotland agrees.D. W-S.Ministry of Health, W. 1:27th January, 1958.
SECRET3APPENDIXNational Health Service Administrative and Clerical Staff New salary structure : General GradesNew Grade	Proposed Salary Scale  	Existing Grade	Salary Scale  *Clerical        ......	230 (age 16) to 345 (age 20)   ......	Al	206 (age 16)-453 (attainable at age 27)	375 x 25(9)-600 (attainable at age 30)	A2	206 (age 16)-515 (attainable at age 28)	t	B	299 (age 18)-546 (attainable at age 28)Higher Clerical	560 X 25 (7)-735   ......	C D (part)	515-597 556-659Junior   Administrative (Training)	575 X 30 (5)-725      .........		Admini strati ve	750 X 35 (6)-960      .........	D (part) E F (part)	556-659 623-753 693-862Senior   Administrative	960 X 40(7)-1,240   .........	F (part) G S.A.O.	693-862 802-983 890-1,092* These salaries would have been 3 per cent, higher under the recent Whitley agreement whichwas not approved by Ministers.f Staff employed wholly on simple repetitive routine work not to advance beyond a certain pointin the scale.

</content>
</cab>
