<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/91/0 images: 93-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
l CONP-HHAt 89(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)O C.(58) 2S COPY NO.   $T^29th January, 1958CABINETPOLIOMYELITIS VACCINEMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotlandand Minister of health the Cabinet gave approval last September to a proposal that upto 5,000 litres of Salk poliomyelitis vaccine should be imported from canada and the United States (C.C.(57) 6th Conclusions, Minute l).This was intended as a temporary supplement to the available suppliesof British vaccine so that vaccination could be offered before the summer of this year when the seasonal increase in poliomyelitis might be expectedto begin, to all children up to age fifteen and to expectant mothers.This offer was made by the Government, and the necessary action wastaken to import 4,000 litres of vaccine from Canada and 1,000 litres fromthe United States.    The first supplies have been distributed to local health authorities and most of the rest is undergoing its tests in this country.2. At the end of 1957 sufficient vaccine had been issued for thevaccination with two injections of abduttwo million children.   The current programme has been based on obtaining by the end of June this yearenough vaccine, either British or Salk, for 50 per cent of the presentpriority groups (children over age six months and under fifteen years,expectant mothers, and some small miscellaneous groups includinggeneral practitioners and ambulance staff and their families), i. e. ,about six-and-a-half million persons.   This programme has howevernow been upset.   There has been a production failure at Glaxo, whichis likely to mean that there will be no further supplies from this firmbefore the end of June, apart from the quantities now under test.Burroughs Wellcome have failed to produce the amount of vaccinepreviously estimated and there can be no guarantee that they will havebetter success in the early future.   The effect of these failures so faris that by the end of June vaccine will be available for only about five-and-a-quarter million of the six-and-a-half million persons in the programme.3. The only way in which the gap can be filled is by furtherimport of Salk vaccine.   The quantity required to make good the presentknown shortfall of British vaccine is about 2,500 litres and the approximate cost is  500,000.    This assumes that we shall receive800-900 litres from Burroughs Wellcome before the end of June;  butthere can be no guarantee that this will be delivered and some or all of this further quantity is therefore at risk.   Most of the cost of theadditional Salk vaccine would be payable in the early part of thefinancial year 1958-59, and subject to any extension of the vaccinationprogramme that may later be decided on, there would a correspondingsaving on the purchase of British vaccine.   If this further quantity is available in Canada or the United States, and is subjected to its Britishtests straight away, it will be ready for use in this country before the summer.-1-CONFIDENTIAL
4. We are advised on the vaccination programme by a committee set up by the Central and Scottish Health Services Councils with lord Cohen as Chairman.    This Committee   have advised us that forthe most effective control of poliomyelitis our first objective shouldbe to achieve as high an acceptance rate as possible among the presentpriority groups.   We do not feel that we can safely provide for a rateof less than 50 per cent by the end of June, and if the Government are to ful-fil their offer the purchase of an additional Z,500 litres of Salk vaccineseems inescapable together with any further quantity which may benecessary to replace expected supplies from Burroughs Wellcome.5. We also consider that in the light of the Cohen Committee&apos;recommendation we ought at some appropriate point in the coming months to embark on much more positive action to raise the acceptancerate than has been possible while vaccine has been so short.    If thisis done we do not think that, on the experience of other countries, wewould be justified in basing our plans for the rest of 1958-59 on anacceptance rate of less than 60 per cent in the present priority groups(including hospital staff and their families, whose inclusion hasalready been recommended by the Cohen Committee because of thespecial risks to which they are exposed).    For such a programmecovering in total nearly eight-and-a-half million persons about 9,000litres of vaccine (including the extra Salk) will be required during1958-59, at an approximate cost of  2 millions for Great Britain.This is about  j million less than the figure provisionally assumedso far in the Estimates for 1958-59 and compares with about 1. 6 millions estimated expenditure on vaccine during the current year.6. We expect to receive soon further advice from theCohen Committee on the priority which should be given to an extensionof the age groups at present eligible for vaccination and to thirdinjections as a means of maintaining or improving the protection givenby vaccination.   This means that, although, because of the physical work involved, it will not be possible to undertake more vaccination before theend of June than is already planned, we must reserve the right to proposeextensions of our programme after that date in the light of any advice from the Cohen Committee.    A similar extension would be required should the acceptance rate rise above 60 per. cent.7. Accordingly we seek the Cabinefs agreement to -(i) the purchase of a further 2,500 litres of Salk vaccine,together with any additional quantity needed to make good any further loss of British vaccine, to tide us over until the summer;(ii)  a provisional purchasing programme sufficient to allow for the vaccination before the end of 1958-59 of60 per cent of the present priority groups, at an approximate cost of  2 millions for vaccine, appropriate measures being taken to raise the acceptance rate toat least this level;  and(iii)  our reserving the right to propose extensions of this programme in the light of further developments and advice.J.S.M.D.W.-S.29th January, 1958- -2-

</content>
</cab>
