<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/1/6 images: 108-117</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THI3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;.3GOVERNMENT)secret.p.(G)(39)6. R Copy no.   ^war cabim;-:tassistance mi&apos; india memorandum by the Secretary of State&apos;for India.With reference to telegram No.288 from theGovernment of India communicated to the War Cabinet by theChief of the Imperial General Staff on September 8th, itwill be desirable to give the Government of India an indication of His Majesty&apos;s Governments requirements inthe matter.The points for consideration appear to be as under:(I) I assume that the War Cabinet will wishto approve forthwith the Government ofIndia&apos;s proposal to extend the outputof munition factories in India.(II) It is proposed to form two additionalBrigade Groups for possible employmentoverseas.Though Burma and Iran are mentioned by the Government of India aspossible venues for these reinforce--ments, the War Cabinet will probablywish to consider the matter on more general lines.    It would greatly helpif they could, could say whether theywould welcome two Brigade Groupssuitable for employment in a Near orMiddle East theatre being held in readiness in India,

India Office.12th September 1939.T7(III) It will be seen that if His Majesty&apos;sGovernment wish these troops to be earmarked for service overseas in thenear future, the Government of india would propose to start replacing themby raising new units and this would beundertaken at once.(IV) As the Government of India note inparagraph 2 of their telegram, theseproposals are outside the terms andconditions of the Ghatfieldsettlement.    It, therefore, appearsirrelevant to refer to such troops as are now under consideration as&quot;External Defence Troops&quot; on thelines of the Chatfield committee report.(V) It is suggested that the financial aspect of these proposals can best be dealt with in discussion.

SECRETTELEGRAM from Government of India, Defence Departmentto Secretary of State for India, dated6th September 1939.288.    6/9Now that we are at war, we are anxious to taketimely steps to render further aid to His Majesty&apos;sGovernment to meet certain eventualities which, in our judgement, may well have to be met by India from time totime during the course of the war.   As a first step inthis direction, we have already arranged to increase output of our munitions factories to maximum extent .possible in order not only to meet our own probableneeds but, if possible, all outside demands which,judging from our recent experiences, are likely to beconsidered (sic ? considerable).   V/e now propose to take immediate action, with such material resources as wehave at our disposal, to carry out the following:-(a) to form two additional Brigade groups for external defence purposes.   The first suitable for reinforcing Burma, and second for employment to protection of Anglo-Iran oil fields or elsewhere whereconditions of role are similar.(b) to simultaneously replace such troops as arerequired for (a) above by forming equivalent number ofnew units for our own needs.2.        Though we are extremely reluctant to raise a financial issue in a time of crisis such as this,nevertheless, it will be realised that the above proposals go outside the terms and conditions recently arrived at as a result of the Chatfield settlement andwill necessarily involve financial commitmentsadditional thereto.   But we are anxious and prepared to

implement these measures immediately, provided that wemay he assured that some equitable financial arrangements will be arrived at where under-charges,which are clearly outside the terms of the Chatfieldsettlement, will be met by His Majesty&apos;s Government,3.       We should be grateful for the very early approvalof His Majesty&apos;s Government on broad lines to theseproposals.4,       We propose hereafter from time to time, and asthe general situation develops, to inform you offurther efforts we might be able to make in similar orother directions to help His Majesty&apos;s Government,apart from the measures which we would in any case takeourselves, solely in the interests of India itself.




</content>
</cab>
