<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/51/8 images: 81-92</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cm (73)7th conclusions printed for the Cabinet.  February 1975 _Copy No. 02CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 15 February, 1973,at 10.30 am.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, mp, Prime Minister&apos;The Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Secretary of State for the environment the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Anthony Barber, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph, m p,Secretary of State for Social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for Trade and industry the Right Hon. The Earl JelLicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Joseph Godber, m p,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food (Items 5-7)The Right Hon. Sir Geoffrey Howe,qc, mp, Minister for Trade and consumer AffairsThe following were also present;Mr. Paul Channon, mp, Minister for housing and Construction (Item 1)The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Julian Amery, mp,Minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs (Items 1-4)Mr. Robert Chichester-Clark, mp,Minister of State, Department ofEmployment (Item 5)
Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. J. B. hunt mr. H. F. T. smith mr. P. benner mr. K. T. barnett mr. I. T. lawman mr. H. F. Ellis-rees mr. D. evans contents item Subject page 1     Parliamentary Affairs        ...     ......     ......      3Counter-Inflation BillEconomic Affairs: Inflationary PoliciesInternational Monetary situation     Oversea Affairs ...     ............     ......      4MaltaVietnam3     Northern Ireland     ......     ............      54     European Community Affairs       ............      55     Industrial Affairs     ..................      6Supplementary Benefits for StrikersIndustrial Action in the Gas IndustryMeeting with the General Council of the Trades UnionCouncil6     Report of the Layfield Panel of inquiry into the greater london Development Plan       ...     .........     107     Members&apos; Outside Financial Interests    ......     ...     12
ParliamentaryAffairsCounter-Inflation bill previous reference:CM (72) 53rdConclusions,Minute 2CONFIDENTIAL1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.It was reported that, if the Counter-Inflation Bill completedall its stages in the House of Commons by the end of February, itwas reasonable to hope that the House of Lords would complete their consideration of it by about 22 March, although it was unlikelythat they would do so earlier.The Cabinet were informed that the Ministers directly concerned had considered what attitude the Government should adopt towards an amendment to the Counter-Inflation Bill which had been tabled for consideration in Committee by Mr. Tugendhat m p. Hehad subsequently agreed to withdraw this amendment on the basis that the Government required time to examine the policy consider-ations involved; but he would be free, if he wished, to pursue thematter again at Report Stage. The purpose of the amendment hadbeen to extend the provisions of the Rent Acts to some 20,000unfurnished tenancies which were at present unregulated. Thetenancies concerned were those with rateable values of more than 400 in London and  200 elsewhere. The result, in many cases, was likely to be a very substantial increase in rent, which many of the tenants involved could not afford to pay, particularly at a time whenincreases in incomes were subject to strict limitation. They thereforehad a claim for a measure of relief; and the Governmenfs sup-porters, especially those representing constituencies in London, couldbe expected to favour the principle underlying Mr. Tugendhafsamendment. On the other hand the Government would be exposed to a charge of inequity if they offered protection to this group of tenants in isolation, since it would be argued that they were helpinga relatively wealthy group while denying assistance to other largergroups of tenants who needed it more urgently in particular theoccupants of rented furnished accommodation. It would notnecessarily be a complete answer in political terms to point out thatthe Government had already helped the less well-off by substantiallyincreasing the needs allowance for calculating the rent rebatespayable to both local authority and private tenants and that, sincethe proposal involved an extension of the existing fair rent pro-visions, any tenants of more expensive rented accommodation whowere at present paying less than a fair rent would in fact be liable to increases. In any event it would be undesirable in principle to extend the scope of rent control in the way proposed, since it would hasten the present contraction in the availability of more expensive rented accommodation. Moreover, although it might be initially intended that unfurnished accommodation which was at present unregulatedshould be subject to control only for a limited period (e.g. duringthe currency of the Counter-Inflation Bill), it was in practice likely that control would have to be made permanent.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thesubject was complex and required careful consideration. A memo-randum describing the courses which might be adopted and thearguments for and against each of these should be circulated forconsideration by the Cabinet at their next meeting.
economic affairs:Counter-InflationaryPoliciesPreviousReference:CM (73) 5thConclusions,Minute 2InternationalMonetarySituationPreviousReference:CM (73) 6thConclusions,Minute 1OverseaAffairsMaltaPreviousReference:CM (72) 39thConclusions,Minute 2VietnamPreviousReference:CM (73) 4thConclusions,Minute 2The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Home Secretary, in consultation with theMinister for Housing and Construction, to arrange forthe preparation of a memorandum on the lines indicatedin the Prime Ministers summing up.The Cabinet were reminded of the importance of avoiding any relaxation of the Governments efforts to secure maximum publicity for the presentation of their counter-inflationary policies. ministers should take every opportunity of explaining and justifying these policies in their public speeches and in interviews on local radio and television.The Cabinet were also reminded of the importance ofemphasising both in the forthcoming adjournment debate on theinternational monetary situation and more generally that the recentchanges in exchange rates did not imply any significant devaluationof sterling.secret. The Minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs said that the Prime Minister of Malta, Mr. Mintoff, had now agreed to receive the payment of  3^ million in respect of the use for the current quarter by the North Atlantic Treaty Organisationof the base facilities on the Island. We had also agreed that thenegotiations on a number of outstanding bilateral issues should be resumed.The Minister of State for Foreign and Commonwealth affairs said that he hoped that it would be agreed that the Secretary-Generalof the United Nations, Dr. Waldheim, should be the Chairman ofthe International Conference on Vietnam which would open on26 February. But there was some opposition to this proposal; inparticular, the Chinese Government would probably urge that theChairmanship should alternate between the United States and north vietnam.The Cabinet-Took note of the statements by the Minister of State forForeign and Commonwealth Affairs.
secret. The Secretary of State for Northern Ireland said that theviolence in the Province committed by Protestant extremists on7 February had resulted in a strong reaction of fear and disgustamong the Protestant community, which had been illustrated by thefact that Mr. Faulkner, Mr. Paisley and Mr. Phelim 0&apos;Neill of the alliance Party, and Mr. Vivian Simpson of the Northern IrelandLabour Party had visited him together, at their own request, on9 February in order to urge him to take the strongest possible measures to contain violence. On 14 February the Mayors of all the boroughs in Northern Ireland had made similar representations tohim. For the present, therefore, he had strong backing from aconsiderable section of the Protestant community in his actionsagainst Protestant extremists; and he had been able, as a result, tomake detention orders against seven of them and to charge severalothers. It had also been possible to establish that it was an offencein law to carry a cudgel; and the law would henceforward be appliedfirmly in this respect. At the same time the Security Forces had continued, with marked success, to arrest active members of theProvisional Irish Republican Army (IRA). Thirty had been arrestedin the past week; and the Provisional IRA now depended very largely on youths and women for carrying out their operations. Mr. WilliamCraig&apos;s recent speech, in which he had advocated an independentDominion of Ulster in the government of which both Protestantsand Catholics could take part, had received some support from certain Roman Catholics; but it should not be endorsed by anyresponsible person. It was no more than an attempt by Mr. Craigto recover the ground which he had lost through his association with the events of 7 February,The Cabinet-Took note of the statement by the Secretary of State forTWfF  Northern Ireland.^ &apos;i2Z-lJf        _____I confidential. The Cabinet considered certain current questions arisingfrom United Kingdom membership of the European Communities.In discussion the following main points were made-(a) Commonwealth Developing Countries. There was some evidence that the developing Commonwealth countries were reactingunfavourably to the option of negotiating association with the communities on the lines of the present Yaounde Agreement. Ifthis were to develop into a general rejection of the Yaounde-typearrangements, it could be embarrassing for the United Kingdom aswell as contrary to the interests of the Commonwealth countries concerned.(b) Tariff Treatment for East Germany. Concern had been expressed lest the proposal by the Federal German Government toextend the benefits of the common external tariff to the German
Democratic Republic might lead to unfair competition for UnitedKingdom manufacturers. The detailed operation of the originalrules was still under consideration in Brussels.(c) Community Procedures. The meeting of the finance ministers of the Communities on 14 February had provided further evidence of the organisational weakness of Council meetings. Inparticular it was regrettable that Ministers should allow permanent representatives to substitute for them at meetings where matters ofpolitical substance were being discussed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that we should take suitable opportunities to secureimprovements in Community procedures. In the discussions in brussels on the application of tariff arrangements to the german democratic Republic the United Kingdom representatives shouldtake account of the posssibility of unfair competition; and ininformal contacts with developing Commonwealth countries theyshould draw attention to the positive advantages of Yaounde-typeassociation arrangements.The Cabinet-Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.IndustrialAffairsSupplementaryBenefits forStrikersPreviousReference:CM (72) 16thConclusions,Minute 7SECRET5. The Secretary of State for Social Services said that, in thelight of growing public criticism of the payment of supplementary benefit to strikers&apos; dependants, the Industrial Relations PolicyCommittee had considered three proposals for possible modificationof the existing arrangements for the payment of such benefits,all of which would require new legislation. The first course wouldbe to provide that all such payments would be recoverable afterthe strike. Alternatively, in cases where no strike pay was paid bythe union an amount of &quot; deemed &quot; strike pay should be deducted from the payments. Third, it would be possible to adopt a com-bination of these two courses, whereby a fixed amount of &quot; deemed &quot;strike pay, say  5, would be made recoverable after the strike. TheCommittee had agreed that it would not be opportune to introduceany such measures at the present time. But they had concluded that legislation should be drafted to give effect to each of the threehypotheses, on the basis that the choice between them need be takenby the Cabinet only at the point when circumstances require actionin this context.The Committee had also considered a proposal that supple-mentary benefit should be withheld from those who took part instrikes which were unlawful under the Counter-Inflationary Bill.They had agreed, however, that the difficulties which would be likelyto arise in establishing that particular strikes were illegal under theBill, together with the consequent delay in applying this sanction,would be liable to render the proposal ineffective in practice.  For
the purposes of public presentation, however, it would be desirable for the time being to say no more than that the Governments study of supplementary benefit in relation to strikers was continuing.In discussion it was suggested that payments to those taking partin a strike which was considered to be unlawful under the Counter-Inflation Bill might be withheld until the question whether thestrike was illegal or not, which was not entirely a matter of fact and could not therefore be left to the Supplementary Benefit Commissionto decide, was resolved. In any case, in view of the pressure fromthe Governments supporters and from the public for some actionto withhold supplementary benefit from strikers, it woud be par-ticularly desirable to give further consideration to finding some wayof achieving this objective in cases where the strike was illegal underthe Bill.industrial action in the gas IndustryPreviousReference:CM (73) 5thConclusions,Minute 8The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that itwould be helpful if the Secretary of State for Social Services couldexplain to the Governments supporters in Parliament the difficultiesof taking action in this context at the present time. Further con-sideration should be given to the possibility of finding some basis fordenying supplementary benefits to those who took part in strikeswhich were illegal under the Counter-Inflation Bill.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister^ summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for Social Services to give further consideration to the proposal to withhold supple-mentary benefit from strikers and their dependants in thecase of strikes which were made unlawful by the Counter-Inflation Bill.The Secretary of State for Trade and Industry said that thereports on industrial action by the gas manual workers which hadbeen received from Regions that morning indicated that there hadbeen little change in the position during the previous 24 hours. Butit was clear that industry in the Midlands would be progressivelydisrupted if the present situation continued for several days more.There was also a report that a one-day strike was to be called inScotland, which could create substantial problems.In discussion the following main points were made (a) An arrangement had been negotiated between the unions and the Area Gas Board in the militant Northern Region wherebya complete cessation of the manufacture of town gas had been averted at the cost of cutting off supplies of natural gas to industrialusers and reducing pressure for domestic users. This arrangementhad disturbing implications, particularly if it created a precedent forother Regions, since its widespread adoption would enable the unions to concentrate the inconvenience on industry instead of on the domestic consumer and so avoid being accused of endangering safety.The bargain in the Northern Region had been made by the Area
Gas Board without the authority of the British Gas Corporation(BGC); and instructions had now been issued to other Area Boardsthat they should not contemplate similar arrangements. It wouldbe necessary, however, to be alert to the development of a generaltendency in industrial disputes for agreements to be reached at locallevels between the managements and the unions concerned, whichthe Government would have no statutory power to prevent and theunions could use as a means of maintaining industrial actionindefinitely without incurring public criticism.(b) It was arguable that the repeal of Section 4 of the Conspiracyand Protection of Property Act, 1875, which had provided for criminal penalties against workers in the gas and water industrieswho created a hazard to life, had contributed to the present situation.It was unlikely, however, that this provision would have had anydeterrent value in present circumstances. On the other hand theIndustrial Relations Act could prove very relevant to the currentindustrial situation. It should be considered, for example, whetherthe gas workers in working to rule were in breach of their contract orengaged in an unfair industrial practice. The unions, however, hadcomplied with the requirement to give 7 days&apos; notice of theirintended action and it was therefore doubtful whether they couldbe accused of resorting to an unfair industrial practice, as defined in the Act. If the &quot; work-to-rule &quot; was challenged as a breach of contract, the effect might well be to cause the unions to declare afull strike. Consideration might be given, however, to remindingemployers and the public of their right to take civil action againstthe unions for breach of contract, loss of business or injuries or damage caused.(c) The possibility of using the &quot; cooling-off&quot; provisions of theIndustrial Relations Act should also be examined in view of the factthat the BGC were now contemplating varying the form of their payoffer within the provisions of the Stage 2 pay policy. This adjust-ment might suffice to meet the requirements that there should bea prospect of settlement by negotiation before a &quot; cooling-off &quot; order was made.(d) It was being suggested that the Government ought to give evidence of their good intentions by an early announcement of the membership of the Pay Board and of the manner in which the board would deal with problems of differentials and anomalies underStage 2 of the pay policy. This suggestion should be consideredpromptly; and in the meantime publicity should be given to the factthat the Minister for Industry had already made it clear in writing tothe General Secretary of the General and Municipal Workers Unionthat the gas unions would be able to make representations to theBoard during Stage 2 about the treatment of their pay under theprovisions of paragraph 33 of the Stage 2 White Paper (Cmnd. 5205).(e) In the light of their latest assessment of the implications ofindustrial action the BGC were not now suggesting that the Govern-ment should take Emergency Powers; and there were obvious objections to taking such powers if there was no occasion for usingthem forthwith.   On the other hand, there was a psychological
advantage in proclaiming a State of Emergency; and emergency powers could well be needed at short notice in order to ensure public safety.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that acc-urate and up-to-date information about the number of workers whowere laid off work as a result of the gas workers&apos; dispute should bemade available on a continuing basis in order that tendentious andconflicting reports in the Press might be corrected without delay.The Minister of State, Department of Employment, should arrangefor urgent consideration to be given to the possible use of the powers in the Industrial Relations Act in the gas workers&apos; dispute. Inparticular, the desirability of applying for a &quot; cooling-off&quot; order and the question whether the gas workers were engaged in an unfairindustrial practice or in breach of contract should be examined. Hewould arrange for further consideration to be given by the ministers most closely concerned to the possible need for the declaration of aState of Emergency.The Cabinet-(3) Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their discussion by the Prime Minister.(4) Invited the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry toarrange for information about the number of workerslaid off by industrial action to be made continuouslyavailable.(5) Invited the Minister of State, Department of Employment,to arrange for urgent consideration to be given to thepossible use of the powers in the Industrial Relations Actin the present situation.The Prime Minister said that he had on the previous day net the  Trades Union Congress (TUC) General Council in order todiscuss the economic and industrial situation. He had appealed forthe co-operation of the TUC in implementing the second stage of the government&apos;s pay and prices policy and in referring the problemsof differentials and anomalies to the Pay Board. But, while the TUCrepresentatives had disclaimed any intention of seeking a confron-tation with the Government, they had not responded to his appeal.Indeed, they had made it clear that they supported the gas workers intheir industrial action against the pay policy. They had alsoannounced their intention to convene a special Congress on 5 Marchand had formulated proposals for an alternative policy, involving an additional  600 million of Government expenditure on such measures as food subsidies and the limitation of rents. There seemedlittle prospect of any constructive discussion on economic andindustrial affairs with the TUC in the near future.The Cabinet-(6) Took note of the Prime Ministers statement.SECRET146897-26 bMeeting withthe general council of theTrades UnionCongress
Report ofthe LayfieldPanel of inquiry intothe GreaterLondonDevelopmentPlanCONFIDENTIAL6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for the Environment (CP (73) 14) about the Report of the panel of Inquiry into the Greater London Development Plan (theLayfield Report), to which were annexed the PaneFs chapter of recommendations and a draft statement by the Government.The Secretary of State for the Environment said that thestatutory development plan which the Greater London Council(GLC) had submitted in 1969 had been subjected to an unusuallylong and thorough examination. The previous Administration had appointed a Panel of Inquiry with very wide terms of reference; andits Report was lengthy and wide-ranging. It would take many months to prepare amendments to the development plan; meanwhile,there would be constant risk of ill-informed speculation and criticism,reinforced by the imminence of the GLC elections. There were therefore strong arguments for publishing the Report without delay;and there would be advantage in issuing at the same time theGovernments preliminary observations on its main recommen-dations, without commitment on some of the wider issues, whichwould need further consideration, and without prejudice to his ownstatutory responsibilities.Although the Report was often critical of the GLCs policies,many of its recommendations on specific matters were consistent with the Governments own approach. On population and employ-ment the Panel had concluded that the development plan was undulypessimistic about the effects of a continuing decline in London&apos;spopulation. On housing they had accepted the emphasis placed bythe development plan on improvement and had made recommen-dations on the private rented sector and on the new house building programmes which were broadly acceptable. On the improvementof public transport and the restraint of traffic their detailed recommendations could be endorsed in general terms. On thecontroversial road proposals they had held that Ringway 1 was needed in order to relieve pressure on the environment in central london; that a substantial part of the southern arm of Ringway should be abandoned; and that most of Ringway 3 should be deleted.It would be right to accept in principle the PaneFs views on Ringways1 and 2, while making it clear that the precise alignment of all theroads was still to be settled. But it would be imprudent at this stage to endorse their recommendation about Ringway 3; and on this issue the Governments position should be reserved. The ministerial committee on Regional Policy and the Environment at their meetingon 1 February had agreed that a statement on these lines should bemade simultaneously with publication of the Report, which might best be arranged for 19 February, the day before the GLC budgetwas presented.In discussion there was general support for the view thatthe Report should be published without delay. But its trenchantcriticisms of the GLCs policies would attract considerable attention and on wider grounds might be seen as an indictment of the wholeprocess of development planning, which after years of inquiry had
still produced no definitive solution to London&apos;s problems. Indeed,the effort to produce a comprehensive development plan for so largean area and to articulate so wide a range of policies, which hadstifled planning initiative in London for years, might have been more profitably devoted to measures to deal with particular areas oraspects of planning policy. Meanwhile, public opinion was becoming increasingly exasperated by the whole planning process. Althoughit was important to protect the rights of those affected by planningproposals, almost any development encountered opposition whichat present enjoyed undue scope for obstruction; and there appearedto be no end to planning uncertainties which in some cases hadpersisted for more than 20 years. Although any substantial changesin planning procedures would require legislation, there would none the less be advantage in commissioning a thorough study with a viewto simplifying and curtailing them.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the PaneFs Report should be published as soonas possible. But the statement which was to accompany it, as atpresent drafted, might well be criticised as failing to do justice to therobust attempt which the Panel had made to deal with the complexissues involved on a genuinely organic and comprehensive basis.It should therefore be redrafted in such a way as to emphasise the government&apos;s appreciation of the wider problems of planning for large cities and their awareness of the human implications. In the longer term the Ministerial Committee on Regional Policy and the environment should consider what measures could be taken to makeplanning procedures shorter, simpler and more effective.The Cabinet-(1) Took note, with approval, of the summing up of their dis-cussion by the Prime Minister.(2) Invited the Secretary of State for the Environment (i) in consultation with the Home Secretary and theLord President of the Council, to arrange for publication of the Report of the Panel of inquiry into the Greater London Development Plan on19 February, together with a statement of the government&apos;s views as these had emerged fromtheir discussion;(ii) to circulate to the Ministerial Committee on regional policy and the Environment proposals for the reform of planning procedures.(3) Took note that the Secretary of State for the Environmentwould circulate proposals on further aspects of thePaneFs recommendations to the Ministerial Committeeon Regional Policy and the Environment.
pulsory registration of interests or, indeed, for a system under which members would be debarred from having any outside financial interests whatsoever. If the Government did not initiate action now,they would probably be forced to do so by circumstances; and theymight then be compelled to adopt more extreme arrangements.The moderate proposals which he had put forward, however, would afford recognised means of protection for Members; would reassurepublic opinion; and would confirm that the House of Commons was concerned with maintaining its reputation for integrity.In discussion, some concern was expressed that the proposed change in present practice would be ineffective in reassuring publicopinion and would be unsuccessful in safeguarding Members againstunjustified imputations. It would be wrong to proceed on the basis that the rules about declaration and registration would lessen therisk of corruption; corruption was by its nature concealed. More-over, the registration of only certain types of interests would be criticised as being inadequate; and there would undoubtedly be pressure for the disclosure of further information, leading to whollyindefensible intrusions into the private financial affairs of Members.In some quarters the existence of the interests disclosed in the registerwould be subjected to misleading and unjustified publicity and mis-representation, while the incompleteness of the disclosures wouldbecome a source of unwarranted suspicion. The extent of one member&apos;s interests would be compared with that of others; it mightwell come to be expected that similar disclosures of interests shouldbe made by public servants; and the final result would be a cumu-lative disincentive to individuals to engage in public activities or toenter public service of any kind.On the other hand, if the Government did not themselves take action, the Opposition would bring forward their own proposals. Itwould therefore be desirable to seek to devise some arrangements which could be defended as being reasonable and sufficient. Thereal problem was presented by those Members who acted on behalfof outside interests without disclosing this fact to their colleagues;and particular concern surrounded those who undertook public relations activities, even if they were not paid to do so. Any registerestablished should comprehend fees paid by way of retainer or fordirectorships; but the amounts involved should not be stated. Itwould be wholly inappropriate, however, to provide for the regis-tration of assets held by Members. On the other hand, providedthat the register was a voluntary one, Members should be free toenter particular interests in assets (e.g. by way of ownership) if theywere engaged in activities touching on such interests but did not intend to speak in the House and would therefore not have theopportunity to make the customary declaration of interest. If theregister were made compulsory, the inevitable criticisms of thosewho did not voluntarily register their interests, or all of them, wouldbe averted. On the other hand a compulsory register would beunacceptably rigid and might, indeed, create the impression that members could regard themselves as absolved from the responsibilityof making their own personal judgments about the financial interests which the House of Commons might regard as relevant.

</content>
</cab>
