<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/45/49 images: 574-581</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the. War Cabinet.   January 1-944. /SECRET. . Copy No.W.P. (44) 49.24th January, 1944. //f, /WAR CABINET. !/PUBLICATION OF DOCUMENTS ON BRITISH FOREIGN POLICY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.ON the 7th September, 1942 (W.P. (42) 121st conclusions, minute 4), theWar Cabinet decided that a collection of documents illustrating the course of anglo-German relations between 1925 and March 1939 should be got ready for publication, but that neither the full edition of these documents nor the proposedabridged edition should be published without further authority from the WarCabinet.2. In two papers circulated to the War Cabinet on the 26th November, 1941(W.P. (G) (41) 139) and the 17th August, 1942 (W.P. (42) 364) I had set out thearguments which, to my mind, made the publication of such a collection desirable.In my view those arguments remain valid to-day. However, it has been represented to me from various quarters that publication of this collection, whichis now ready, would be inopportune at present. I have accordingly reconsideredthe whole question and in the circumstances I do not wish again to press theWar Cabinet to authorise publication of this Anglo-German collection.3. On the other hand, I am impressed by the necessity of making availableto the general public both here and abroad, and more particularly to historiansand publicists, material on which to form sound judgments regarding theprinciples and mode of execution of British foreign policy during the inter-war years. There is no doubt that at present there is a tendency for the British case to go by default &quot;and for judgments to crystallise Avhich are based on inadequate-knowledge of the facts and are, in consequence, unfavourable to British policy..The longer the time that is allowed to pass, the harder it becomes to remove andcorrect such false judgments. In recent months letters to the press and questions in Parliament have indicated that there is a growing demand for the publicationof an authoritative collection of documents illustrating the course of foreignaffairs before the outbreak of war. Questions in Parliament on this subject havebeen answered to the effect that the matter is under consideration.. 4. The case for publication of such a collection of British documents isstrengthened by the fact that documents illustrating American foreign policyin the inter-war years are already being published. The United States Depart-ment of State has for more than a century past published a continuous series ofvolumes of diplomatic correspondence covering the main features of Americanforeign policy. This series has now reached the year 1928 and the volumes for1929 are about to be published. The publication is thus entering a period ofimportant and controversial issues, such as the Disarmament Conference, in whichFlis Majesty&apos;s Government were closely interested and about which it will be-particularly desirable that our own version of events should be made known. Inthis same series the State Department proposes shortly to publish the completerecords of the Paris Peace Conference of 1919, although, at our request, they haveagreed to &quot;exclude the minutes of the Council of Four (W.P. (43) 290 of the2nd July, 1943, dealt with this proposal). In addition, the United States Govern-ment published last year a book entitled &quot; Peace and War : United States foreignpolicy 1939-41.&quot; This work, which has been issued in this country undor - theif the Miiiisti^ of Information, constitutes an apologia for United states policy in the face of increasing threats of aggression by the Axis Powers duringthe decade between the Mukden Incident and Pearl Harbour.12259   [26784]
&apos; 5. It is undesirable that on the Allied side the only authoritative records of international relations during the pre-war period should be those from american sources and that compilers of textbooks should have to rely on theAmerican view of events. With the above considerations in mind I wish to seek the approval of my colleagues for the preparation and publication of a generalcollection of documents illustrating British foreign policy from 1919 to 1939.The collection would be on roughly the same scale as the State Departmentcollection (probably two or at most three volumes for each year) and should asfar as possible keep pace with-it. I am advised that a delay of about two years would be bound to occur before even the first volume of this collection would beready and a much longer time must inevitably elapse before volumes dealing withthe more controversial events of the years immediately preceding the war hadbeen completed. I would propose that the publication of the collection should begin with the volumes for 1930. These volumes would be ready for publicationabout the end of 1945. This would mean that our series would be near to butjust behind the American series. Volumes for successive years following 1930would thereafter be published annually. At the same time work would be carriedout upon the volumes covering the period between 1919-29 and these would becompleted and published as rapidly as our resources permitted. I would proposethat the collection should be entitled &quot; Documents on British Foreign Policy,&quot;and that the preparation and publication, as in the case of the volumes of&quot; British and Foreign State Papers,&quot; should be carried out, with expertiassistance when required, under the direction of the Foreign Office.6. I might add that there is already a precedent for the proposed collectionin the series of volumes of documents on the origins of the last war. Similarcollections have appeared in other countries, and are likely to be followed, afterthe present war, by collections dealing with the period between 1919 and 1939.,7. I have already authorised Mr. E. L. Woodward, who prepared theAnglo-German collection, to undertake some preliminary work in connexion withthe preparation of a collection of documents on the lines set out above. but before the work proceeds any further, I should be glad to know that my colleaguesapprove my proposal.A. E.Foreign Office, 2iih January, 1944.







</content>
</cab>
