<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/46/3 images: 30-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
11 ^(THIS DOCUMENT IS,THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret*P.(44)  5585th January, 1944 COPY NO. ^WAR CABINETAGRICULTURE policy note by the Secretary.I circulate, by direction of the Prime Minister, forconsideration at this evening&apos;s meeting of the War Cabinet, a minute addressed to the Prime Minister by the Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.,E.E.BRIDGES.Offices of the War Cabinet,S.W.19,25th January,  1944,PRIME MINISTERYou were good enough to say that when you had read myspeech on agricultural prices you might be able to strengthen theGovernment assurances to agriculture for the- future.     There isin my view a   strong case for some extension of the presentpledge in point of time-2.      In November 1940 the Government announced that it had decided &quot;to guarantee that the present system of fixed prices andan assured market for agricultural products will bo maintained forthe duration of hostilities and for at least one year thereafter*&quot;3.     Recently the War Cabinet decided that this pledge could ifnecessary be redefined as a guarantee that the present system would.bo maintained for two years after the end of hostilities withGermany.      This is more definite but not necessarily longer in point of time.4.     Since agricultural production (especially livestock production)has to be planned for three or four years ahead, we are now working on a Pour Year Plan,  i.e. up to 1947.      Farmers are being directed under the sanction of heavy penalties to incur considerablecapital expenditure which can only be recouped if they start-now to increase their livestock and if prices for meat and milkare satisfactory three and four years hence (the calf produced asthe result of the mating of bull and cow today cannot begin toproduce milk until 1946J.5*     Farmer&apos;s confidence would be largely restored if the WarCabinet would agree to an extension of the present guarantee tothe following extent:-(i) That the present system of fixed prices and an assuredmarket would be maintained until 1947 i.e. covering the harvest of 1947; , and(ii) That actual minimum prices for livestock should befixed now for the period up to 1947.6.      This extension of the guarantee need not cost the Governmentanything and could be safely given.     Though we may have to reduce

the production, and therefore prices, of crops like wheat and potatoes before 1947, wo shall need to expand milk and meat in view of the world shortage of m^at and fats - ashortage which will almost certainly extend beyond 194707.     The Lord President&apos;s Committee have authorised theMinister of Pood to opon negotiations for long term bulkcontracts for-meat, milk products, fats and bacon to theend of 1947, both with the Southern Dominions and with south Americai countries.     Home producers will feel that/hoy arc entitled to assured markets and prices for t-hoooproducts covering at least the same periods     The lord presidents Committee, while they were unwilling toauthorise a similar guarantee to home producers,recognised that if the Agricultural Ministers were strongly pressed the matter would have to be further considered as a general issue,8e     If this extension were agreed in principle theactual form in which the announcement should be made would need to bo further consideredo     It is probablethat a definite guarantee of this kind up to 1947 would do more to restore confidence at this moment than widerand vaguer announcements about long-term post-war policy.RsS tlioMinistry of Agriculture and Fisheries,S.W.lo35th January, 19440






</content>
</cab>
