<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/43/45 images: 384-392</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   September 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (44)129th Conclusions.WAR CABINET 129 (44).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Prime ministers room, House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Friday, 29th September, 1944, at11-45 a.m.Present: .The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs (Item 6).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton,Minister of Reconstruction.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of -State for Burma(Item 7).The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War(Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., Minister of Information.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Lord Privy Seal.Colonel the Right Hon. oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Colonies (Item 7).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport (Item 7),Captain the Right Hon. H.F. Crook-shank, M.P., Postmaster-General(Item 7).Miss Ellen Wilkinson, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of home security (Item 1).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[28376-2]
WAR CABINET 129 (44).Contents.M minute no. Subject. page 1      Home Guard and Civil Defence      ....      .....      ....      ....     97Retention of uniforms after release from service .2      Munitions Production ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     97Assumption as to the end of the war with Germany.3      Release of Capacity from Munitions to Civilian Production     984      Parliament      ....       ....      ....      ....       ....      ....      ....     99Prolongation of the life of United Kingdom Parliament and ofthe House of Commons, Northern Ireland.5      Prisoners of War       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     99Employment of German and Italian prisoners of war.6      Civil Air Transport    ........................     99Position  of   Eire vis-avis the   International Conference and preliminary Empire talks.7      Civil Air Transport    ....      ....................   100Ownership of civil air lines.
Home Guardand civil defence.Retention ofUniforms after-Release from service.1. The War Cabinet discussed the question whether the home guard and Civil Defence workers should retain their uniformsafter they had been released from service.The Secretary of State for War said that it had already beenagreed that members of the Home Guard should retain their boots,and that he proposed that they should retain their battle dress andwaterproof capes. There were, however, difficulties in agreeing totheir retaining their great-coats, since the production of great-coatsmade considerable demands on materials and the available stocksmight prove insufficient for the needs of the Army. Men on demobilisation from the Army would not retain their great-coats,though each man would be given a civilian macintosh.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Home Security,urged that members of the Civil Defence Services should be allowedto retain their great-coats. There would be strong opposition to anyproposal that the great-coats should be surrendered, and a distinctionin favour of the Civil Defence Services could be justified on theground that many Civil Defence workers had not been given fulluniforms.It was pointed out in discussion that the productive capacity inthe clothing industry was greatly strained, and that an additional burden had been placed on it by the demand for suits and macintoshesfor men demobilised from the armed Forces.The general feeling of the War Cabinet, however, was that if itwas at ail possible, the Flome Guard and members of the civil defence Services should retain their great-coats.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Home Guard should retain their boots,battle-dress and waterproof capes.(2) Invited the Minister Of Production, the Home secretary and Minister of Home Security, the Secretary of Statefor War, the Minister of Supply, and the President ofthe Board of Trade to consider whether the available resources would allow the Home Guard and membersof the Civil Defence Services to retain their gx&apos;eat-coats.munitions production.Assumption asto the end ofthe war withGermany.(previous reference: .W.M. (44) 124thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. At their meeting on the 4th September (W.M. (44) 116thConclusions, Minute 8), the War Cabinet had decided that, for thepurpose of estimating man-power requirements in the second halfof 1944, it could be assumed that the war with Germany would not continue after the 31st December, 1944.On the 19th September, the War Cabinet had considered amemorandum by the Minister of Production (W.P. (44) 517) setting-out the effect of this assumption oh the man-power situation and onthe production of munitions. The Prime Minister, when in Quebec,had telegraphed that he thought that the war would straggle over ina reduced condition into 1945, but that he, nevertheless; approved the steps which the Minister of Production proposed to take, subjectto the agreement ,of the War Cabinet and the Defence Committee.The War Cabinet had reaffirmed their view as to the assumed date,and had agreed that this conclusion should be translated into action as outlined in the Minister of Production^ memorandum.The Prime Minister said that he now thought that, with enemy resistance stiffening, the war might continue until, say, the end ofFebruary 1945. It was for consideration whether any of the cutsin production decided upon were too drastic.The Minister of Production said that, broadly speaking, owingto the amount of stores accumulated and in transit, the reductions which he had proposed and the War Cabinet had approved would suffice to enable our Forces to. continue to fight with the samestriking power, and with the same intensity, until the end of March[28376-2] b 2.
WAR CABINET 129 (44).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Home Guard and Civil Defence      ....      .....      ....      ....     97Retention of uniforms after release from service .2      Munitions Production ....      ....      ....      ....      ..... 97Assumption as to the end of the war with Germany.3      Release of Capacity from Munitions to Civilian Production    984      Parliament      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     99Prolongation of the life of United Kingdom Parliament and ofthe House of Commons, Northern Ireland.5      Prisoners of War       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     99Employment of German and Italian prisoners of war.6      Civil Air Transport........................     99Position of  Eire vis-avis the   International Conference and preliminary Empire talks.7      Civil Air Transport    ....      ....      ................   100Ownership of civil air lines.
Home Guardand civil defence.Retention ofUniforms afterRelease from service.1. The War Cabinet discussed the question whether the home guard and Civil Defence workers should retain their uniformsafter they had been released from service.The Secretary of State for War said that it had already beenagreed that members of the Home Guard should retain their boots,and that he proposed that they should retain their battle dress andwaterproof capes. There were, however, difficulties in agreeing totheir retaining their great-coats, since the production of great-coatsmade considerable demands on materials and the available stocksmight prove insufficient for the needs of the Army. Men on demobilisation from the Army would not retain their great-coats,though each man would be given a civilian macintosh.The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Home Security,urged that members of the Civil Defence Services should be allowedto retain their great-coats. There would be strong opposition to anyproposal that the great-coats should be surrendered, and a distinctionin favour of the Civil Defence Services could be justified on theground that many Civil Defence workers had not been given fulluniforms.It was pointed out in discussion that the productive capacity inthe clothing industry was greatly strained, and that an additional burden had been placed on it by the demand for suits and macintoshesfor men demobilised from the armed Forces.The general feeling of the War Cabinet, however, was that if itwas at &quot;all possible, the Home Guard and members of the civil defence Services should retain their great-coats.The War Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Home Guard should retain their boots,battle-dress and waterproof capes.(2) Invited the Minister of Production, the Home secretary and Minister of Home Security, the Secretary of Statefor War, the Minister of Supply, and the President ofthe Board of Trade to consider whether the available resources would allow the Home Guard and membersof the Civil Defence Services to retain their great-coats.2. At their meeting on the 4th September (W.M. (44) 116thConclusions, Minute 8), the War Cabinet had decided that, for thepurpose of estimating man-power requirements in the second halfof 1944, it could be assumed that the war with Germany would not continue after the 31st December, 1944.On the 19th September, the War Cabinet had considered amemorandum by the Minister of Production (W.P. (44) 517) setting-out the effect of this assumption oh the man-power situation and onthe production of munitions. The Prime Minister, when in Quebec,had telegraphed that he thought that the war would straggle over ina reduced condition into 1945, but that he, nevertheless, approved the steps which the Minister of Production proposed to take, subjectto the agreement of the War Cabinet and the Defence Committee.The War Cabinet had reaffirmed their view as to the assumed date,and had agreed that this conclusion should be translated into action as outlined in the Minister of Production^ memorandum.The Prime Minister said that he now thought that, with enemy resistance stiffening, the war might continue until, say, the end ofFebruary 1945. It was for consideration whether any of the cutsin production decided upon were too drastic.The Minister of Production said that, broadly speaking, owingto the amount of stores accumulated and in transit, the reductions which he had proposed and the War Cabinet had approved would suffice to enable our Forces to continue to fight with the samestriking power, and with the same intensity, until the end of March[28376-2] b 2.munitions production.Assumption asto the end ofthe war withGermany.(previous reference: .W.M. (44) 124thConclusions,Minute 2.)
1945. If the war in Europe were to continue at the same intensity-after that date, a difficult situation would certainly arise. Hethought that more risk could be taken with capital equipment than with expendable stores. The tank programme was being cut from350 to 170 tanks a month, but the effect of this would not be felt untilthe second quarter of 1945.The Prime Minister thought that we might take more risks overproduction of aircraft than over tanks and that the tank positionrequired further enquiry.The War Cabinet agreed as follows : 1(1) The Minister of Production undertook to submit a memo-randum on the tank position in the course of the nextfew days, setting out the stocks on hand and the rates ofproduction.(2) As it was clear that a decision on this matter should bereached in the very near future, there was no need forthe Minister of Labour and National Service and theMinister of Supply to slow down any of the action nowin progress for the release of labour.Release of capacity from munitions toCivilianProduction.(previous reference:W.M.(44)126tlConclusions,Minute 9.)3. The War Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Production (W.P. (44) 545) dealing with the release of capacity from war production.The Minister of Production explained that there was considerable pressure for a statement on the Government&apos;s plans forthe release of capacity from war production and the reconversionof industry to civil use at the end of the European war. he accordingly proposed, if the War Cabinet agreed, to make thestatement annexed to W.P. (44) 545 in Parliament on the followingTuesday. The statement included an offer of a debate on the subject,which might conveniently take place after the debate onRe-allocation of Man-power. In drafting the statement great carehad been taken to avoid anything which would prejudice thenegotiations with the United States Government on Lend-Lease in stage II.In discussion, stress was laid on the danger that, with the presidential Election pending in the United States, any statementof the kind proposed might be liable to misinterpretation. It wassuggested that the line which the Minister of Production should take in Parliament should rather be that, while the Government were doing everything possible to ensure that when the proper time camethere would be a smooth change-over from war-time to peace-time production, the stiffening of German resistance made it impossibleto give any definite promise of immediate action to divert resources from war work. At the same time the Ministers concerned should,of course, press on with action in consultation with individual industries but without any general publicity.It was also pointed out that the statement annexed toW.P. (44) 545 had necessarily had to be drafted in such cautiousterms that it gave very little useful information to industrialists.The Minister of Production said that it might be possible to redraft the statement in such a way as to relate it entirely to theaction which would be taken at some future unspecified date, and soget over the objections which had been raised in discussion.The War Cabinet-Invited the Minister of Production, in the light of thediscussion, to prepare a revised statement on the release of capacity from war production.
ParliamentProlongation ofthe Life ofUnitedKingdomParliament aridof the House ;of Commons,NorthernIreland.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 128thConclusions,Minute 2.)Prisonersof War.Employmentof German andItalianPrisonersof War.(previous reference:W.M. (44) 101stConclusions,Minute 3.)4. The Prime Minister said that he had it in mind to move the second reading of the Prolongation of Parliament Bill. in doing so he would make a general statement regarding the con-tinuance of the present Government which would, he hoped, do something to counter the agitation in certain quarters for an earlyGeneral Election.The War Cabinet-Took  note,   with  approval,  of  the  Prime  Minister&apos;intention.5. The Secretary of State for War said that the german prisoners of war for whom we were responsible were being kept in France under extremely unsatisfactory conditions. It wasimpossible to get the French authorities to construct better accom-modation and the presence of these prisoners was an embarrassment to our Forces. He had therefore come to the conclusion that theonly solution was to transfer a considerable number to this country.To enable this to be done the transfer to this country from SouthAfrica of a further 13,000 Italian prisoners of war would haveto be stopped. In particular, he asked for authority to cancel thesailing of a ship which was on the point of leaving South Africafor this country with about 3,000 Italian prisoners.In discussion, the view was expressed that we ought not to add to our own accommodation difficulties by bringing to thiscountry German prisoners of war whom it ought to be possibleto house in France, having regard to the vacant accommodation which was bound to be available in that country. It was alsourged that if the German prisoners of war were kept in Francethey could be usefully employed on the destruction of flying bomblaunching sites and submarine pens.The War Cabinet agreed as follows :  (1) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for War, was invited topress the French authorities to agree to the retentionof German prisoners of war in France and to their employment on the destruction of flying bomb launchingsites, submarine pens and similar installations.(2) Any proposal for stopping the transfer of Italian prisonersof war, in accordance with the agreed programme, shouldbe submitted to the Prime Minister, after consultationwith the other Ministers concerned.Civil Air 6. The War Cabinet resumed discussion of the position whichTransport. resulted from the invitation given by the United States, withoutPosition of consultation with us, to the Government of Eire to attend the Inter-Eire &apos; vis-a-vis national Conference on Civil Air Transport to be held in the Unitedthe States on the 1st November.International jt wag agreecj that this invitation should not have been issuedConference and without prior consultation with us. In any event, it was difficult topreliminary gee what justification would be adduced for the United States actionEmpire Talks. jn inviting Eire but not issuing an invitation to the Argentine.(Previous They could have proceeded on the basis of inviting all nations on,reference: as it were, a geographical basis.   But if they intended to discrimination -W.M. (44) 127th nate, we were surely entitled to be consulted before Eire was conclusions, invited.   This was a point which should be taken up with the minute 10.) United States Government.
The invitation to the Eire Government having been issued,nothing could now be done to prevent their attending the Inter-. national Conference. It remained to consider whether the eire government should be invited to the preliminary Empire talks at ottawa. The War Cabinet was informed that the DominionGovernments were in favour of the Eire Governments being invited.On the other hand, it was urged that to invite the Governmentof Eire to send representatives to an Empire Conference might wellprejudge the whole of our relations with Southern Ireland after thewar. We wished to see these relations re-established on a friendlyfooting. But the right way to go about this was surely not to inviterepresentatives of Eire to attend this Empire Conference, as thoughnothing had happened and without regard to the other and underissues involved. It was all the more difficult to do so during thewar, while German and Japanese Ambassadors were still in Dublin.As against this it was urged that the Empire Conference wasto be an official one to deal with technical matters, and that if Eirewent to the International Conference without first going to theEmpire Conference, there was a risk that she might be driven intothe American camp.In reply to this, it was pointed out that the increasing range of aircraft lessened the importance of Irish bases for Trans-Atlanticflights.After some further discussion, the War Cabinet agreed asfollows (1) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs undertook totake up with the State Department their action ininviting Eire to attend the Conference without prior consulation with us, notwithstanding the fact that noinvitation had been issued to the Argentine.(2) The arrangements for the Empire Conference at Ottawain October should stand, but no representative of Eireshould be invited to attend.(3) The Prime Minister undertook to send personal telegrams to the Dominion Prime Ministers, explaining the reasons why we felt that the Government of Eire should not beinviteddo the Ottawa meeting in present circumstances.Civil air transport.Ownership of,&quot;Civil Air Lines.(previous reference erence:W.M. (44) 114thConclusions,Minute 4.)7.   The War Cabinet had before them the following memo-randa on the future of B.O.A.C.  -(i) two memoranda  by  the Secretary of State  for  Air(W.P. (44) 268 and 529);(ii) a  memorandum by the Secretary of State for India(W.P. (44) 498);(iii) a memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production(W.P. (44) 508).They also had before them the following memoranda on theprivate ownership of British airlines (iv) a memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal, W.P. (44)&apos;263(Revise);(v) a memorandum by  the  Secretary of  State  for Air,W.P. (44) 279.A record of the discussion and conclusions reached is contained iin the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of- War Cabinet Conclusions.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,29th September, 1944.


</content>
</cab>
