<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/57/26 images: 346-356</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tklS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S government cc(75) 56thConclusionsCOPY no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 1 0 Downing Street onFRIDAY 12 DECEMBER 1975at 9. 30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short MPlLord President of the Councilin the Chair for Part of Items 1 and 2)The Rt Hon Lord Elwyn- jones lord Chancellor  (Item 1)The Rt Hon Roy Jenkins MP The Rt Hon Denis Healey mp secretary of State for the Home Department Chancellor of the Exchequer(in the Chair for Part of Item 2)The Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the Environment(Item 1)The Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon John Morris QC mp secretary of State for Wales   (Item 1)The Rt Hon Fred Peart mp minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food (Item 1)The Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy Seal(Item 1)The Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection (Item 1)The Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon William Ross mp secretary of State for scotland the Rt Hon Merlyn Rees mp secretary of State for Northern Ireland (Item 1)The Rt Hon Harold Lever mp chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Item 1)The Rt Hon Fred Mulley mp secretary of State for Education and Science(Item 1)
The Rt Hon Reginald Prentice MP The Rt Hon Robert Mellish mp minister for Overseas Development Parliamentary Secretary, TreasThe Rt Hon John Silkin mp minister for Planning and Local GovernmentTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Edmund Dell mp attorney General  (Item 1) Paymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon David Ennals mp minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsSECRETARIATSir John Hunt      (Item 1)Mr J A hamilton mr C J FarrowCONTENTSItem subject.       CHRYSLER (UK) LTD2.      IMPORT CONTROLS ON CARS
cCHRYSLER 1. The Cabinet resumed their discussion of Chrysler.     The(UK) LTD discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.previous reference:CC(75) 53rdConclusions,Minutes 1 and 2IMPORT 2. The Cabinet considered ,import controls on cars.    the controls discussion and the conclusions reached are recorded separately.ON CARSPreviousReference:CC(75) 53rdConclusions,Minute 3Cabinet Office12 December 1975
UMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S government copy NO45CABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION annex cc(75) 56th Conclusions, Minute IFriday 12 December 1975 at 9. 30 am the Cabinet had before them two memoranda by the Secretary of Statefor Industry (C(75) 144 and 145) on negotiations which had taken place with the Chrysler Corporation about the future of Chrysler (UK)Ltd.THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Ministerial Group on theAutomobile Industry had considered the previous evening proposalsfor the support of Chrysler (UK) Ltd which had resulted from further negotiations with the Chrysler Corporation.    There had been a clear majority, but not unanimity, among the Group for acceptance of theproposals.    It was now for the Cabinet to decide whether or not to endorse that recommendation.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that at their meetingon 5 December (CC(75) 53rd Conclusions) the Cabinet had agreed thatthe Government should not participate in the arrangements known asscheme B.    They had concluded however that there would be an advantage in making a positive offer to the Chrysler Corporation setting out alternative financial arrangements under which the Governmentwould be prepared to support a scheme based on the physical planscontained in scheme B.    It had been agreed that the proposal should include an offer by the Government to finance the losses incurred byChrysler (UK) in 1976-77 based on Chrysler&apos;s own estimate that the losses would amount to  40 million.    When negotiations had resumedthe Chairman of the Chrysler Corporation, Mr Riccardo, had made clear that more financial assistance than this would be needed.Following further discussions by the Ministerial Group the Governmenthad offered to contribute up to  72^- million towards losses by Chrysler(UK)Ltd in the next four years including  50 million in 1976 if losses were  60 million or more, to guarantee a borrowing of  35 million byChrysler (UK) Ltd from Finance for Industry (FFI) provided that the chrysler Corporation gave a counter-guarantee to the Government, andto finance by a loan a requirement for capital and model development of 55 million in the years 1976 to 1979:  the first two years1 expenditure,amounting to  28 million, to be subject to a guarantee by the chrysler corporation.    Chrysler for their part had offered to produce the
C6 (Alpine) model at Ryton, and to meet the cost of  10-12 millioninvolved in setting up a preduction line to assemble imported parts.If full production were to be undertaken this would cost a further 23-25 million.    He considered these arrangements thoroughlyunsatisfactory.    Although the Governments financial commitmentsappeared to be limited they would in practice be open-ended.    the assurances which the Government would have of continuity of operation in this country by Chrysler would be no more dependable than the assurances given in 1967 and 1972 which had now been totally set aside.The Industrial Development Advisory Board (IDAB) had concluded thatthe scheme was not viable although a majority had considered that support could nevertheless be justified on social and industrial and balance of payments grounds provided that certain difficult- pre-conditions could be met.    The arrangements would certainly be severelyhandled by the Trade and Industry Sub-Committee of the SelectCommittee on Expenditure, who had already been critical of theGovernments support for the motor industry.    Coopers and Lybrandhad expressed doubts about the arrangements.    There was likely to becriticism from the Public Accounts Committee.    Assistance wouldappear wholly unjustified when considered against the background ofthe report by the Central Policy Review Staff (CPRS).    Support of thiskind would be unpopular with the Governments supporters because it involved the provision of public funds without obtaining a public stake in the ownership of the company.    It would be presented as surrender to a multi-national company.    It would destroy the Governmentsindustrial strategy and weaken their policy of controlHng public expenditure.    It would create a precedent which it would be difficult to escape when faced by other companies, not only those in the carindustry, asking for Government support.    The decisions already taken on Norton Villiers Triumph would be hard to justify, and damage wouldbe done to the Governments policy for British Leyland because the clear impression would have been created that the Government was always willing to rescue firms in the motor industry how a-ver poor the performance of the workforce.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SCOTLAND said that any decisionon Chrysler was bound to be difficult.    The alternative to acceptanceof the arrangements was to accept a closure which would cause the lossof 55, 000 jobs.    There would have been no support in the Labour partyfor that course.    A number of improvements had been made to thescheme since it had previously been considered by the Cabinet.    their principal concern had been a lack of commitment on the part of chrysler corporation, but the Corporation would now be heavily committed by the guarantees that they would give and by the integration of the UnitedKingdom company with the rest of their Group.    Assurances must beobtained on the way that this integration would be carried out.    A further improvement was that the C6 was to be produced at Ryton, which wouldmean the preservation of another 3, 000 jobs directly: moreover thescheme would keep in operation the factories at Linwood, Dun stable andStoke.    The success of the reorganised company would be heavily2
dependent on an improvement in labour relations and it would benecessary to obtain agreements from the unions concerned.    It wasonly by improved productivity that the motor industry would prosper:retrenchment of itself did not achieve anything.    Neverthelesssubstantial retrenchment was involved in the arrangements proposed.They would result in a reduction of almost one third in employment byChrysler (UK) Ltd and a reduction of their motor vehicle production byone half. ;THE CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that he agreed with much that the Secretary of State for Industry ha.d said.    In particularsupport for Chrysler under the arrangements proposed could be verydamaging to the Governments industrial policy though ministers would have to work to minimise that damage.    Nevertheless he considered that the Government were committed by the offer which theCabinet had agreed should be made to the Chrysler Corporation.    Hehad not expected that offer to be accepted, but in the event the chrysler corporation had put forward alternative proposals which were in factmore advantageous to us, both financially and in terms of providingcontinuing employment at Ryton.    The result was a substantial improvement on scheme B which the Cabinet had earlier rejected.The Government would meet no part of past losses, and after 1976would make only a small and diminishing contribution to future losses;the Chrysler Corporation would be guaranteeing  63 million for theUnited Kingdom company and providing  10 to 12 million to financeproduction of the C6.    The scheme would save 37, 000 jobs.    The bigdrawbacks were the potential liability for  50 million in 1976, and the risks of the amount to be underwritten by the Chrysler Corporation.On the assumption that those who would have been redundant but forthis scheme would not have obtained further employment for two yearsand that the Chrysler Corporation did not itself collapse the cost to theGovernment of giving assistance was less than the cost of theunemployment benefits, tax losses and the proposed redundancy schemewhich would be associated with a closure.    On balance he consideredthat the benefits of the scheme outweighed the drawbacks.    He was particularly influenced by the damage which the collapse of the iranian contract would do to the country&apos;s standing in the Middle East,the likelihood that it would not be possible to obtain agreement to theimposition of import restrictions on cars even if the closure wentahead, and the damaging precedent which would be created if the supplementary redundancy scheme were introduced.    Nevertheless,if the support proposals were adopted the Cabinet should do all thatthey could to prevent its becoming a precedent.    They must also seek to obtain the co-operation of the trades unions on the same lines ashad been done at the time of the support of British Leyland.    If this were not forthcoming a further crisis could arise very rapidly.In discussion it was argued on the one hand that an agreement on these terms would be a body-blow to the Government&apos;3 industrial strategy andto its wider economic policies.    Whatever the Government said thesettlement would be taken as a precedent which would make it hard torefuse requests for assistance not only from other firms in the motor3
industry but from other industries also.    Whatever commitmentChrysler might give for the future they could not be forced to continueoperation in Britain if they were resolved not to do so.    On the otherhand it was argued strongly that the new arrangements made much moresense than the original scheme B which the Cabinet had rejected.    Thenew arrangements ensured that the Government would bear no part ofthe responsibility for past losses, there was a rmxch greater degree ofcommitment by the Chrysler Corporation both through the provisionof guarantees and through the financing of the introduction of theproduction of the C6.    It was also now envisaged that the UnitedKingdom company would be closely integrated into the rest of the chrysler group.    It was also argued strongly that the disadvantage of accepting the arrangements had to be set against the consequences of allowing closure to go ahead.    This would result in 55, 000 jobs beinglost at a time when the prospects of alternative employment was very bad, and this applied with particular force in West Scotland.    Thepolitical consequences of such a course would be extremely,damaging.    As against this it was argued that it was naive to thinkonly in terms of jobs saved at Chrysler:  if there were overcapacity inthe industry, preservation of Chrysler would simply lead to loss injobs elsewhere in the car industry, including British Leyland.Attention was also drawn to the balance of payments and benefits whichwould result from the Iranian contract continuing to be met from thiscountry.    It was clear that this could not have been preserved in theevent of a closure.    The Finance Minister of Iran had indicated withinthe past day or so that if the Iran contract fell through there might be serious repercussions on United Kingdom/Iranian industrial relations whichmight spread throughout the Middle East.    On the other hand it waspointed out that the Chrysler Corporation would continue the Iraniancontract even if Chrysler (UK) collapsed and the reputation of british firms in the Middle East or anywhere else depended primarily on their individual performance.    The special redundancy scheme which hadbeen envisaged in the event of the closure would also have damaging consequences as a precedent for other industries which would be avoided if these arrangements were accepted.    It was also argued,however, that while the preservation of employment secured by these arrangements was to be welcomed they amounted to an unprecedentedsubsidy for a foreign-owned company.    It would be preferable torequire Chrysler to meet all their liabilities and for the Governmentto acquire the company on a basis which took account of those liabilities.In further discussion there was general agreement that the co-operationof the trades unions was essential if there were to be any prospect ofsuccess for the new arrangements.    It would be necessary to obtain their clear agreement both to the principle of the arrangement, to theredundancies involved, to the transfer of work, and also to measuresto increase productivity on the lines suggested by IDAB.   Productionof the C6 model was unlikely to be successful in the long run unlessproductivity were raised by 25 per cent to the levels already achieved in France.    It should be made clear to Chrysler that the government
support was conditional on an agreement with the unions.    further negotiations with Chrysler would also be necessary to reach agreement on suitable arrangements for sharing the future profits, to obtainsatisfactory binding undertakings on the future integration of the UnitedKingdom company with the rest of the Chrysler Group, and tc secure asuitable degree of Government control over the operation of the companyIt should also be made clear that provision of assistance would be conditional on the approval of Parliament.The Cabinet were advised that the support arrangements would need tobe notified to the European Commission before they were announced.A.lthough it was not likely that they would refuse to accept the arrange -ments this could not be taken for granted.In further discussion it was argued that the presentation of theGovernment&apos;s decision would be made more difficult if it were accompanied by the publication of the GPRS report.    On the otherhand it was argued strongly that a clear commitment had already beengiven that the report would be published and the consequences of seeking to avoid publication would be more damaging than going ahead.    Itcould be argued that the action proposed was compatible with the reportin that the production of cars by Chrysler would be reduced by50 per cent as a consequence of the reorganisation.THE LORD PRESIDENT OF THE COUNCIL, summing up the Cabinet&apos;discussion, said that a large majority of the Cabinet considered,albeit with great reluctance, that the proposals for support of Chryslershould be accepted.    Considerations which had weighed with themparticularly were the saving of 37, 000 jobs out of the 55, 000 that wouldhave been lost in a total closure, the avoidance of the need for aspecial redundancy scheme which would have been a difficult precedentand the consequences of closure for the country&apos;s relations with iran and the rest of the Middle East.    The Cabinet considered, however,that a clear agreement would be needed with the trades unions concerned both over the principles of the scheme and over futureproductivity.    The Chrysler Corporation should be informed that theGovernment accepted the arrangements in principle, but that this was conditional on -a. a satisfactory agreement with the trades unions concerned;b. satisfactory binding assurances on the integration of the United Kingdom company with the rest of the chrysler Group;c. an agreement on profit sharing arrangements;d. arrangements for Government control over theoperations of the company, such as the right of theGovernment to nominate directors;
ande. Parliamentary approval of the provision of assistance.The Cabinet1 s decision should be announced to Parliament on Tuesday16 December.    The announcement should make clear that theGovernment&apos;s support was not open-ended and that creditors shouldnot assume that the Government stood behind the company.    Thereport by the CPRS should be published at the same time as theannouncement.    An approach should be made to the european commission under Article 93 of the Treaty of Rome on Monday,15 December.The Cabinet -1.      Took note, with approval, of the Lord PresidentJssumming up of their discussion.2.      Agreed to the proposals for the support of Chryslerset out in C(75) 144 and 145, and that there shoxdd be no special redundancy scheme.3.      Invited the Secretary of State for Industry to make an announcement to Parliament on Tuesday, 16 December,and to agree the terms of his statement with the secretaries of State for Trade, Employment and Scotland,the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Foreign and commonwealth Secretary and the Lord President.4.      Invited the Secretary of State for Industry, inconsultation with the Secretaries of Stg-state for employment and Scotland, to seek an agreement with the trades unionsbefore the announcement on the lines indicated in theLord Presidents summing up.5.      Invited the Secretary of State for Industry, inconsultation with the Secretary of State for Scotland, the paymaster General and the Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster to reach an agreement with-the chrysler corporation on the matters indicated in the Lord Presidentssumming up.6.      Invited the Minister of State for Foreign and commonwealth Affairs to arrange for a formal approach to be made to the Commission on Monday, 15 Decemberabout the proposal for assistance.7.      Invited the Head of the Central Policy Review staff to arrange for the publication of his report to coincide with the announcement in Parliament.Cabinet Office12 December 1975 6
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTIMPORTCONTROLSON CARSPreviousReference:CC(75) 53rdConclusions,Minute copy NO     /I IX1 dCABINETLIMITED CIRCULATION annex cc(75) 56th Conclusions, Minute 2Friday 12 December 1975 at 9.30 am the SECRETARY OF STATE FOR TRADE said that the Governmentwere making very large investments in the motor industry.    It was essential that they should protect those investments by imposingtemporary restrictions on imports of motor cars.    The balance oftrade in motor cars which had formerly been positive was now in largedeficit and import penetration this year was likely to be around35 per cent.    These developments could easily result in the collapse of the motor car industry in this country.    He recognised that theGovernment&apos;s freedom of action was limited by its treaty obligationsbut in his view the introduction of restrictions was entirelycompatible with the relevant obligations - Article XIX of the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade and Article 135 of the Treaty of accession to the European Economic Communities.    The Cabinet had previously agreed to seek approval for the imposition of restrictionsif Chrysler (UK)closed.    He had always argued that they should also doso in the event of a substantial contraction by Chrysler.    Under thearrangements which the Cabinet had just agreed, Chrysler&apos;s carproduction would fall by 50 per cent and there would be a very severeinterruption in their production in 1976.    The production of Imps would cease at the end of the year, the transfer of Avenger production toLinwood would take at least 6 months as would the start of the assemblyof the Alpine.    There would thus be no production, except to meet the iranian contract, for 6 months.    The circumstances were accordinglybasically the same as they would have been in the event of a closure.In discussion it was argued that the difficulties facing the British industry were their inability to produce cs-rs rather than their inabiHty to sell in competition with imports.    Temporary restrictions would make no difference to this situation.    There were stocks of 150, 000 importedcars already in the country but no stocks of British cars.    Article XIXrequired that if restrictions were imposed there should be compensatoryaction in some other areas.   The Prime Minister had reached the view,following his discussions in the European Council, that there was no prospect whatever of agreement by the European Commission to anapplication for approval for import controls on cars.    Indeed thePresident of the Commission had said that approval would not be grantedeven in the event of complete closure of Chrysler (UK) Ltd.
THE HOME SECRETARY, summing up the discussion, said that itwas necessary that the Cabinet reached a decision about import restrictions on cars even though many members had been obliged toleave to fulfil other engagements.    The Cabinet had clearly envisagedearlier that a decision would be reached about import restrictions oncars at the same time as the decision on the principle of support forChrysler, and a majority had then been against import controls ifChrysler (UK) Ltd did not collapse.     A majority of the members nowpresent were also agreed that there should be no import restrictionson cars.    Of the members who had already left sufficient had indicated to him that they remained opposed to import restrictions oncars to make it clear that a majority of the full Cabinet shared thisview.    This should therefore be taken as the decision of the Cabinet.If any of those who were in a minority wished to have the matterdiscussed further when the whole Cabinet was present they should put this request to the Prime Minister.    It would not be- right for the limited number of members now present to reach decisions on import controls on the other items.    A further meeting of Ministers shouldbe held on Monday 15 December so that decisions could be taken intime to allow the approval of the European Commission to be obtained before an announcement during the economic debate on 17 December.The Cabinet -1.       Took note, with approval, of the Home Secretary&apos;summing up of their discussion.2.      Agreed that the proposal for the imposition of import restrictions on cars should not be pursued.3.      Instructed the Secretary of the Cabinet toarrange for a further meeting of Ministers on Monday15 December to reach decisions on proposals forimport restrictions on other items.Cabinet Office12 December 1975

</content>
</cab>
