<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/1/46 images: 423-432</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOYERNMENT

Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1989.

SECRET.

W.M. (39)

46th Conclusions.

Copy No-

TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.

It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.

WAR CABINET 46 (39).

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, on Friday, October 13, 1939, at 11-30 a.m.

Present:

The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).

The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.

Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon. Lord Chatfield, Minister for Coordination of Defence.

The Right Hon. L. Hore-Belisha, M.P., Secretary of State for War.

The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.

The Right Hon. Secretary of Affairs.

Viscount Halifax, State   for Foreign

Hon. Winston S. M.P., First Lord of the

The Right

Churchill

Admiralty. The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,

M.P., Secretary of State for Air. The   Right   Hon.   Lord Hankey,

Minister without Portfolio.

The following were also present:

The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson, M.P., Secretary of State for the Home Department and Minister of

  Home Security.

The Right Hon. Malcolm MacDonald, M.P., Secretary of State for the Colonies (Item 13).

The Right Hon. E. L. Burgin, M.P., Minister of Supply (Items 9 and 10).

Admiral of the Fleet Sir Dudley Pound, First Sea Lord and Chief of Naval Staff (Items 1-13).

The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.

The  Right  Hon.   Oliver Stanley,

M.P., President of the Board of

Trade (Items 14 and 15). Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.

Newall,  Chief of the Air Staff

(Items 1-13). General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,

Chief of the Imperial General Staff

(Items 1-13).

Secretariat. Sir Edward Bridges. Major-General H. L. Ismay. Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N. Mr. F. Hemming. Mr. W. D. Wilkinson. Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, R.E. Mr. A. Bevir. Mr. G. N. Flemming.

[20141]


WAR CABINET 46 (39).

Contents.

Minute

No. Subject. Page.

1 Air Situation ... .................. 375

2 Air Policy ......... ............ 375

3 The Government Statement in reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s

Speech to the Reichstag ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 375

Its conveyance to Germany by leaflets, and its treatment in Germany.

4	The Naval Situation ... Capture of the Cap Norte.	375

5	The Military Situation	376

6	Belgium	376

7	Air Operations in the event of invasion of the Low Countries by Germany  ...      ... ... ......	376

8	Withdrawal of the British Garrison from Tientsin	377

9	Provision for Chemical Warfare ...	377

10	Possible use by the Germans of an unexpected form of Poison Gas        ...      ...      ... ... ......	378

11.	Turkey ...	378

12	Italy ......... ............... Proposals for the mutual withdrawal of troops from North Africa and for a Mediterranean ditente.	379

13	The Problem of Polish Refugees ............	379

14	Compensation for War Damage to Fixed Property	380

15	Proposal for the Chartering and Insurance of all available Neutral Tonnage ...      ...      ...^ &lt;~ ...	381

16	The Government Statement in reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s Speech to the Reichstag ... Attitude of the Dominion High Commissioners. Question of Broadcast by the Prime Minister.	381


375

W.M. 46 (39).

Air Situation. 1.   The Secretary of State for Air. said that there were no

(Previous        special operations to report.

Reference: W.M. (39) 45th

Conclusions, -

Minute 1.)

Air Polioy. 2.   The Secretary of State for Air said that consideration was

(Previous being given at the Air Ministry to the employment of our Air Force

Reference: in the event of certain courses of action being taken by the German

W.M. (39) 12th Air Force.  He suggested that, before referring the matter to the

Conclusions, War Cabinet, a preliminary discussion might take place between the

Minute 6.) Ministers concerned.   This might conveniently follow the meeting of Service Ministers already arranged for that afternoon.

The War Cabinet agreed 

That the question raised by the Secretary of State for Air should be discussed by : 

the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence, the three Service Ministers, the Minister without Portfolio, and the three Chiefs of Staff.

The Government Statement in reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s Speech to the Reichstag.

Its conveyance to Germany by leaflets, and its treatment in Germany.

(Previous References: W.M. (39) 45th Conclusions, Minute 7, and 44th Conclusions, Minute 15.)

3. The Secretary of State for Air said that he had discussed with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs the question of dropping leaflets over as wide an area of Germany as possible, in connection with the Government statement in reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s speech to the Reichstag.

The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed, and said that he had arranged to obtain the earliest possible news of the treatment accorded in Germany to the Prime Minister&apos;s speech.

The War Cabinet agreed 

That the action proposed in this matter accorded with the approved policy in regard to the dropping of leaflets.

The Naval Situation.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 45th Conclusions, Minute 2.) Capture of the Cap Norte. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 44th Conclusions, Minute 2.)

4. The First Lord of the A dmiralty said that there appeared to be an increase in U-boat activity.

A German submarine had been blown up by a mine in the Dover Barrage and 9 survivors had been picked up. Two of our colliers appeared to have been torpedoed and sunk at the tail end of an out-going convoy, the survivors being picked up by an American ship.  The report, however, had not yet been confirmed.

The Cap Norte had now been brought safely into Kirkwall and the German reservists on board taken prisoner.

An early attack on our shipping, ports and East Coast convoys must now be anticipated. Particulars were given of the vessels now operating with the East Coast convoys.

The War Cabinet took note of these statements.

[20141]


376

The Military Situation.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 45th Conclusions, Minute 3.)

5. The Secretary of State for War said that there now appeared to be between 59 and 80 divisions on the Western Front. New elements had been reported from the Aachen and Saarbrucken areas. There appeared to be 25 divisions opposite Belgium and 12 opposite Luxembourg.

The Chief of the Air Staff informed the War Cabinet that both the French and Germany ends of the Rhine bridges south of Strasbourg had been blown up.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.

Belgium. 6.   The War Cabinet were given certain further information

(Previous on the subject of the attitude of Belgium to her neutrality, in

Reference: supplement of that communicated to the War Cabinet at their

W.M. (39) 44th Meeting noted in the margin.   The information so furnished is

Conclusions, recorded on the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War Cabinet

Minute io.) Conclusions.

The War Cabinet took note of this information.

Air Operations 7.   The War Cabinet had under consideration a Memorandum

in the event of   by the Chiefs of Staff Committee (Paper W.P. (39) 87). invasion of the

Low Countries The Chief of the Air Staff said that, when the question of air

by Germany.     operations in the event of a German invasion of the Low Countries (Previous        had been previously considered by the War Cabinet, a decision had Reference:       been deferred in the hope that it would be possible to arrange staff W.M. (39) 24th conversations with the Belgians.  This hope had proved false, and Conclusions,      a, German attack now seemed to be impending on the Western Front. Minute 11).       Detailed plans had been worked out with the French, but it would be vital to put these plans into operation without a moment&apos;s delay should an attack through the Low Countries eventuate.   For this reason the Chiefs of Staff renewed their request for authority to be given to them in advance.  Every care would be taken to confine air attacks to the enemy, but some damage and casualties to civilians in the countries concerned was almost inevitable.

In the discussion which ensued, it was generally agreed that, though the dilemma was an unpleasant one, there was no escape from it. The situation envisaged was a military one, which would have to be treated from the military point of view. The action contemplated did not differ from that of bombarding towns which were of military importance but contained civilians. There would probably be an immediate call for assistance from the countries invaded, which would afford some justification.

The question was raised whether we should attack an invader in Holland, if the neutrality of Belgium was not infringed. It was decided, however, that any advance into Holland must be considered as a threat to the Allies on the Western Front and therefore treated

hostile act.

The Prime Minister undertook to leave the Belgian Ambassador, whom he was shortly to see, under no illusions as to what action we should take in the event of a German invasion of Belgium. We should attack the enemy wherever we might find him.


251

377 W.M. 46 (39).

The War Cabinet agreed 

(1) to authorise the Chiefs of Staff to put into operation,

without further reference to the War Cabinet, the pre-arranged plans for checking by air action any German advance into Holland, Belgium or Luxembourg, immediately certain information was received of the enemy&apos;s advance into any of those countries :

(2) that the French should be informed of this decision through

the normal military liaison channels.

Withdrawal of the British Garrison from Tientsin.

(Previous Bi;levence: W.M. (39) 30th Conclusions, Minute 9.)

8. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for War (Paper W.P. (39) 75) proposing the withdrawal of the Tientsin Garrison as early as possible on the grounds that the recent floods had rendered the barracks uninhabitable. There was no pressure now from the Japanese to withdraw the garrison, and the withdrawal could therefore be undertaken without any loss of prestige and with a very good excuse.

It was recalled that the removal of the garrison from Tientsin had been contemplated ever since 1931, but for various reasons a suitable opportunity had not occurred. When the matter was last discussed by the War Cabinet, it had been agreed that we should keep in step in this matter with the U.S.A. and France. The French were withdrawing 1,600 out of their total garrison at Tientsin of 2,000. The U.S.A. were not in favour of withdrawal in principle, but recognised that Tientsin was in a different category from Shanghai. It was suggested that it might be bettei* to wait two or three weeks for a favourable settlement of the U.S.A. neutrality legislation question before announcing the withdrawal; but it was doubtful whether the delay was really worth while, and the view generally taken was that this matter would not affect U.S.A. opinion on the neutrality issue.

The suggestion was made that we might withdraw the whole of the garrison except for a token force of, say, one company. On the other hand, it was felt that a token force, while being of no military value, would still remain a military commitment.

It was also pointed out that at the present time a detachment of the battalion at Tientsin was stationed at Peking. The view generally taken was that this detachment should be withdrawn at the same time as the main garrison at Tientsin, but the Foreign Secretary asked for a further opportunity to consider this aspect of the question.

The War Cabinet agreed 

Subject to any further representations that the Foreign Office might wish to make on the subject of the Peking detachment, to authorise the withdrawal of the garrisons at Tientsin and Peking as early as possible; it being left to the discretion of the Foreign Office to decide the most opportune moment for the announcement of the proposed withdrawal.

Provision for 9.   The War Cabinet had before them a joint Memorandum by

Chemical the Secretaries of State for War and Air on Chemical Warfare

Warfare. (Paper W.P. (39) 58), setting out proposals for increasing the plant

for producing gas of various types.

The Secretary of State for War said that, though limited quantities of gas were already being produced, as set out in the Memorandum, there was no doubt that on the present basis our supplies would be inadequate if gas warfare were to begin, in view of the increased size of the Army and Air Force for which we now [20141] b 3


378

had to plan. He and the Secretary of State for Air therefore asked authority for the factory programme set out in their Memorandum.

The Minister of Supply said that a good deal of preparatory work had already been carried out in regard to these proposals, which he regarded as a practicable scheme. His Department was ready to proceed as soon as authority could be given. The need for providing the greatest possible safety for the civil population would be kept well in view in planning the location of the factories, and the factories would be in relatively safe and isolated districts. It was, however, impossible to avoid all risks in storing large quantities of dangerous gas. It would be of assistance to his Department if the War Office could expedite release of the design of the shell to be used for gas projection.

In view of the information given by the Minister of Supply, the Chancellor of the Exchequer expressed his concurrence with these proposals.

The War Cabinet 

Approved the proposals for the provision of plant for the increased production of gas for chemical warfare as recommended in the joint Memorandum by the Secretaries of State for War and Air.

Possible Use by 10. Arising out of the previous discussion, the Secretary of the Germans of State for War and the Chief of the Imperial General Staff an unexpected mentioned that the French had recently captured prisoners wearing form of Poison gas masks fitted for protection against arsenical poison gas, against Gas. which our existing gas masks would not provide adequate protec-

tion. This might indicate that the Germans intended to use this form of gas. Our experts were in consultation with the French and were confident that they would be able to devise a pad which could be used in conjunction with the existing masks so as to afford adequate protection. This temporary provision could be made very quickly; later on, means would be found of incorporating adequate protection in the permanent design of the service gas masks. It was believed that the projection of arsenical gas, which was a difficult task, was likely to be attempted only in connection with military operations. Nevertheless, as soon as fuller information became available, the other Departments concerned would be kept fully informed.

The War Cabinet 

Invited the Secretary of State for War to arrange for a report to be submitted to the War Cabinet at the earliest opportunity setting out (i) the results of the enquiries now proceeding in regard to arsenical gas, and (ii) the steps that were being taken to guard against this danger.

Turkey. \\    The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he

(Previous        had at present nothing further to report regarding the discussions Reference:       jn Moscow between M. Stalin and M. Sarajoglu, the Turkish W.M. (39) 44th Minister for Foreign Affairs, on the subject of the proposed Turco-Conclusions,      Soviet pact, or in regard to the reaction of those discussions on the Minute 6.)       Anglo-Turkish Treaty.  It appeared from telegram No. 391, dated the 12th October, 1939, from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Moscow, that it was doubtful whether M. Sarajoglu would be received that evening by M.  Stalin, since the Finnish special envoy was apparently due to undergo his ordeal at that time.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.


252

379

W.M. m (39).

Italy 12.   The Chief of the Air Staff referred to the discussion

Proposals for which had taken place at the meeting mentioned in the margin,

the mutual One of the suggestions made during that discussion had been that

withdrawal of it might be possible to approach the Italian Government with a

troops from view to a mutual withdrawal of troops from North Africa, and the

North Africa establishment of a detente in the Mediterranean,

and for a The Chief of the Air Staff said that his attention had been

Mediterranean called to a draft telegram which had been prepared in the Foreign

detente. Office asking Sir Percy Loraine to broach this proposal to the

(Previous Italian Government.   The telegram had not yet been despatched.

Reference: He ventured to suggest that it should not be despatched, until the

W.M. (39) 39th War Cabinet had had an opportunity of considering the matter

Conclusions, further on the basis of a Report by the Chiefs of Staff.  There were

Minute 8.) certain obvious objections to our participating in a scheme of the character suggested, e.g.: 

(i) Once we had withdrawn British forces from the Mediterranean area it would take a considerable time to get them back there. On the other hand, it was a very easy matter for the Italians to replace any forces which they might withdraw from North Africa, (ii) Such a withdrawal would cut across the conception of a Middle East Reserve, which had become fundamental to our strategy.

(iii) The withdrawal of our forces from Egypt might have serious internal repercussions in that country.

The Secretary of State for War considered that we must be very careful how we proceeded in this matter. For example, we must do nothing which would preclude the possibility of Australian or New Zealand forces being stationed in the Mediterranean area, or being temporarily detained in that area on their way to the Western Front.

In regard to the Fleet, the First Lord of the Admiralty said that, when this matter had previously been discussed, he had not contemplated that we should be called upon to make any reduction in the strength of our Mediterranean Fleet. He had, however, contemplated an agreement which provided for the closing of the Mediterranean to submarines of belligerent Powers.

The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence pointed out that the Italian Government appeared to be apprehensive of the increase in the number of French troops in North Africa. It seemed possible that an arrangement in regard to a mutual withdrawal of forces might be arranged between Italy and France.

The War Cabinet 

(i) invited the Chiefs of Staff to submit a Report on the suggestion for a mutual withdrawal of troops from North Africa, and for a Mediterranean detente: (ii) agreed, pending a decision on this Report, to suspend the issue of instructions to our Ambassador at Rome on this matter.

The Problem of Polish Refugees.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 36th Conclusions, Minute 9.)

13. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Paper W.P. (G.) (39) 31) regarding the problem of Polish refugees.

The Home Secretary said that a letter had been received in the Home Office from the Foreign Office asking that a liberal line should be taken in regard to the admission of Polish refugees to this country. He was somewhat alarmed at this request, and hoped that no pressure would be brought for any relaxation of the existing practice.


The War Cabinet took note 

(a) that voluntary French associations and the Polish authorities in France were tackling the problem of Polish refugees without official assistance :

(6) that the Foreign Secretary was arranging for the appointment of Sir Francis Humphrys to deal with the Polish refugee problem generally, and, in particular, to co-ordinate the work of public and private bodies in this sphere in consultation, where necessary, with the Service and other Departments concerned.

14. The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (Paper W.P. (39) 84), covering a draft of the proposed White Paper on War Damage to Fixed Property. The draft contained the Report of the Committee presided over by Lord Weir, together with a draft statement on Government policy thereon.

The House of Commons had been promised the publication of the Report at a very early date, and the Chancellor&apos;s proposal was that the White Paper should be issued on Tuesday, the 17th October.

In the course of an explanatory statement, the Chancellor of the Exchequer drew particular attention to the summary of conclusions and recommendations contained in paragraph 16 of Lord Weir&apos;s Report. He (the Chancellor) was clear in his view that there was no course open to the Government but to announce their acceptance of these conclusions and recommendations. The broad effect of them was that the Government had been right in their previous decision not to introduce a scheme for mutual protection against the risk of war damage to fixed property in private ownership.

, Among subsidiary matters to which the Chancellor drew attention was the problem (discussed in paragraph 14 of the Weir Report) presented by the private organisations which were purporting to give protection against war risks to property on land. There had been large-scale advertising on behalf of these private schemes. It was now intended to introduce Government legislation forthwith to curtail the public activities of the sponsors of such schemes.

The Prime Minister said that, the following sentence in paragraph 6 of the Weir Report struck him as being one of its key passages: 

&quot; Any mutuality scheme either independent of, or complementary to, the Government scheme, also involving either premiums paid by property owners during the war, or annual levies after the war, appears to constitute an unjustifiable earmarking both during and after the war of one section of national resources for one particular objective.&quot;

After further discussion, the First Lord of the Admiralty said that he would not press, the views which he had indicated at the earlier meeting referred to in the margin.

The War Cabinet 

(1) approved the statement of Government policy;

(2) agreed that the Report and White Paper should be issued

on Tuesday, the 17th October.

Compensation (or War Damage to Fixed Property.

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 44th Conclusions, Minute 14.)


381

W.M. 46 (39).

Proposal for the Chartering and Insurance of all available Neutral Tonnage. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 38th Conclusions, Minute 9.)

(Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 35th Conclusions, Minute 11.)

15. The First Lord of the Admiralty informed his colleagues that, as invited at the meeting of the War Cabinet referred to in the margin, he had held an inter-Departmental Conference for the examination of the suggested policy of securing the control of all available neutral tonnage. This Conference had been attended by representatives of the Treasury, the Foreign Office, the Admiralty, the Board of Trade and the Ministry of Economic Warfare. He was about to circulate a Memorandum to the War Cabinet reporting the results of this examination. His paper would raise some fundamental questions; for example : 

(i) If German air attacks on our shipping were to materialise, the need of charterings from neutral countries might be greatly increased, (ii) The question would then arise in an acute form what was a fair rate to pay per ton for chartering neutral shipping, and what was to be rejected as blackmail? How long would the President of the Board of Trade be able to take a stiff line in negotiation with the representatives of foreign shipowners, as he had been instructed to do at the meeting referred to in the margin ?

(iii) If high rates were conceded to foreign owners, what line

should we take when British owners asked that their own rates should be increased to the same level?

(iv) The answers to the above questions would have important

consequences for the Ministry of Food, since certain of the difficulties which had already arisen in connection with the food rationing scheme had their origin in the anticipated shortage of shipping.

No decision was taken pending consideration of the Memorandum to be circulated by the First Lord of the Admiralty.

The Government Statement In Reply to Herr Hitler&apos;s Speech to the Reichstag.

Attitude of the Dominion High Commissioners. (Previous Reference: W.M. (39) 45th Conclusions, Minute 7.)

Question of Broadcast by the Prime Minister.

16. The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the Prime Minister and the Foreign Secretary, at their interview with the Dominion High Commissioners on the conclusion of the previous day&apos;s Meeting of the War Cabinet, had, he thought, succeeded in allaying some of the apprehensions expressed by the High Commissioners in&apos; respect of our reply to Herr Hitler. The meeting had undoubtedly been most successful. He had seen the High Commissioners again later in the day, and they had been most impressed with the good reception accorded to the Prime Minister&apos;s statement.

The Prime Minister reminded his colleagues that his original intention had been to broadcast a speech on the wireless on the evening of the same day as his statement in the House of Commons. He had given up this idea for the reason that a broadcast speech would either have had to reproduce the ipsissima verba of the House of Commons speech, which would have been pointless, or to depart from the language of that speech, which would have been dangerous. He had given consideration to the question whether he should broadcast on the evening of Saturday, the 14th October. In view of the favourable reception which had been accorded to his statement in the House on the previous day, he had reached the conclusion that it would be preferable to postpone his broadcast for a few days, say, until the middle of the following week.

The War Cabinet took note of the above statements and approved the Prime Minister&apos;s intentions regarding his forthcoming broadcast.

Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1, October 13, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
