<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/4/0 images: 42-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT20Printed for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET.CP. (45) 255.26th October, 1945.CABINET.NATURALISATION POLICY.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.1. It is my duty as soon as possible to resume the work of dealing with applications for naturalisation. During the last five years this work has been suspended except as regards applications for readmission to British nationality(mostly by women) and certain other limited categories. The law contemplatesthat certificates of naturalisation shall be issued to aliens of good character whohave assimilated themselves to this country, and there ought to be no long interval between the end of hostilities and the restoration of the normal practice ofdealing with applications within such limits as is practicable.2. Subject to the consideration of the views of my colleagues, / propose to announce in the House of Commons that as soon as the necessary staff is availablenaturalisation will be re-opened, that consideration will be given first to thoseapplications which were submitted before the policy of suspension ivas announced in November 1940, that it will take not less than two years to deal with theseapplications, and that when they have been disposed of, applications receivedafter November 1940 will be dealt with nOt in the order of their submission butaccording to the length of time the applicants have resided in this country.3. The number of applications which were awaiting consideration whenthe announcement of November 1940 was made is about 6,500. As there is a statutory requirement of five years&apos; residence, none of these 6,500 applicantshad less than five years&apos; residence in 1940 and will now7 have had at least tenyears&apos; residence. But for the war-time decision to suspend the work these 6,500applications would have been dealt with in the order of their submission and it-seems clearly right to give priority to these applicants.4. It is essential to maintain a proper standard of care in examining eachapplication and in making all necessary enquiries about the applicant, and I doubt whether it will be practicable to dispose of these 6,500 cases in less than two years. Any expansion of the staff of the naturalisation department must be gradual newcomers must be trained and the pace of the work is also limited by the rate at which enquiries can be made by experienced police officers.5. Despite the announcement in November 1940 of suspension, over 6,000applications have been submitted to the Home Office since that date, and thereare many more potential applicants waiting to submit their applications. To dealwith applications made after November 1940 in the order of their submissionwould be unfair, because it would differentiate against those who have beenconsiderate enough not to trouble the Home Office during the war, and in favourof those who, despite the public announcement, have persisted in putting in theirapplications. For this reason it is proposed that when it becomes practicable to deal with applications submitted after November 1940, these applications shallbe dealt with not in the order of submission but according to the length of the applicants residence in this country.6. The existing policy will be continued of dealing with applications forreadmission to British nationality (most of these are from British-born women who have lost British nationality on marriage to aliens),, with special cases ofpersons who by upbringing and associations are clearly British but are not Britishsubjects in law (for example, illegitimate children born abroad of a British mother,and brought up in this country), and with special cases where there is some specificreason in the public interest for the immediate conferment of British nationality.[30765]Copy No.r-i rf
7.   The adoption of the scheme set out in paragraph 2 (above) will mean   :that most of the applications1 dealt; with during the next two years will be   Iapplications from persons who came to this country not later than 1935, and that   j iit will be some years before applications can be dealt with from foreigners who   r;came here in 1936, 1937, 1938 and 1939.  Amongst these later comers are many   Ipersons who have rendered valuable service to the war effort, both in the Armed   1Forces and in civil occupations, and pressure will no doubt be put upon me to   take out of their turn many applicants whose wartime services can be represented as being of special value.   If the policy which I recommend is adopted, it willbe necessary to resist these representations unless in quite exceptional oases itcan be clearly shown that immediate conferment of British nationality is needed for some purpose of national importance. .. .8. : Representations are being made, and will continue to be made, for the .early naturalisation of aliens who have served in the Armed Forces, most of iwhom will by now have the statutory qualification either of five years&apos; residence jor of five years&apos; service with the Crown.   Sympathy must be felt with the view Ithat there is a special case for naturalising applicants of good character who Ihave served with the Forces, but the question now to be settled is not whether Iin the future such applicants shall be naturalised, but whether some special measures should be taken to naturalise them without delay.   The objections tosuch a course may be summarised as follows : .: 9. First, there is no sound ground of equity or logic for distinguishing between aliens who have served in the Forces and others who have done important and sometimes dangerous work in civilian occupations. Strong representations,for example, have been made in favour of the early naturalisation of scientistswhose contributions to the war effort have in many cases been of great value.If it were decided to treat service with the Forces as a ground for preferential treatment, it would be almost impossible to refuse to take up applications fromcivilians who have made useful contributions not only in the field of science butin other fields.: 10. Although service with the British forces makes a strong sentimentalappeal, and many who have so served have done fine work and would be welcomeas citizens of this country, service in the British army does not necessarily mean that an alien has become assimilated to the British way of life. Some such alienshave naturally felt themselves to be fighting not so much positively for thiscountry as negatively against Nazism and Fascism. Some joined the pioneer corps as an alternative to internment. Of these some were discharged on medical grounds after short service.11. To devise any workable scheme of distinguishing between the applicantsaccording to the nature or length of their service in the Forces would, I am convinced, be impracticable. Amongst the men, for example, with short service,will be some who were engaged in active fighting and were disabled at an earlydate by wounds. If service with the Forces were to be a ground for preferential treatment, such treatment would have to be accorded to all who were dischargedwith a good character.12. There is a further difficulty that many aliens who have served withthe Forces have never set foot in this country. They were recruited in the middle east in 1940 and 1941 and have served with the Forces in the Mediterranean.13. Secondly, it is in my view important that, for the present, nothingshall be done to prejudice a decision as to the ultimate disposal of the aliensadmitted to this country in 1938 and 1939 on the express understanding that they came here for temporary asylum as trans-migrants and in the expectation thatthey would shortly go overseas. It may well be that in the changed circumstancesmany of them will ultimately have to be allowed to remain here, but no guaranteeon this subject ought to be given at present. As stated by the Prime minister in a recent reply to a Parliamentary Question (Official Report, the 10th October,cols. 225 and 226) : &quot;It is the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to createconditions in Europe which will enable and encourage foreigners who are hereon a temporary basis to return to their own country.&quot; It is not proposed inpresent circumstances to compel any refugees of good character to leave this \country but, on the other hand, the United Kingdom ought not to be committedat the present date to guaranteeing permanent settlement here to all such refugeesas prefer, to remain here. ,14. Of the aliens who have served in the Forces a large number wereadmitted to the United Kingdom as trans-migrants for temporary asylum in
1938 and 1939. To naturalise such; persons, thereby conferring the right to permanent settlement, and at the same time to avoid holding out the prospectof permanent settlement here to refugees who have contributed as civilians to thewar effort, would be a most difficult course. If it be agreed that for the presentnothing should be done to prejudice future decisions about aliens admitted here,for temporary asylum,, it is essential that the question of naturalising such aliens:should be postponed. The proposed plan of dealing first with the: applicationsfor naturalisation submitted before November 1940 (i.e., applications frompersons who came to the United Kingdom before 1935) will mean that considera^tion will be postponed of applications from persons who were admitted in 1938;and 1939 for temporary refuge as transmigrants.15. If at a future date it is decided that many of these refugees may beallowed to stop here, then-and not before then -their applications should beconsidered and full weight given to service in the Forces and to other forms ofassistance to the war effort. I fully appreciate the force of the considerations which can be urged on behalf of those aliens who have served with His Majesty&apos;forces, but I am forced to the conclusion that it would be undesirable to placesuch applicants at the head of the queue and naturalise them at this stage.16. I shall no doubt be asked what the Government intend to do to giveeffect to the hope expressed on the 27th February last by the then Prime minister that it may be possible &quot; to offer the citizenship and freedom of the BritishEmpire, if they so desire,&quot; to members of the Polish Forces who fought under british command, if means are not found of enabling them &quot; to return in due course to Poland of their own free will, and under every safeguard, to play their part in the future life of their country.&quot;17. In replies to all such questions it is, I think, important to adhere to theline taken by the Prime Minister in replying to a Parliamentary Question on the9th October. (A copy of the Question and reply is attached.) It is not possibleto formulate proposals on this subject until more is known about the number of poles who will refuse to go back to Poland, and whether there will be amongstthem any considerable number of men who served in Italy but have never beenin the United Kingdom. Moreover, any Ministerial statement showing that special measures are in preparation for enabling members of the Polish forces to be naturalised would be inconsistent with the efforts which are being made toencourage members of the Polish Armed Forces who are in this country and in italy to volunteer for repatriation.J. C. E.Home Office, S.W. 1,26th October, 1945.Question and Answer.(House of Commons, 9th October, 1945.)(Hansard, column 24.)Polish Armed Forces (British Citizenship).53. Captain Gammans asked the Prime Minister how far he proposes to implement the pledge given by the Coalition Government to grant British citizen-ship to those members of the Polish armed Forces who are unwilling, or unable,to return to the new conditions in Poland.The Prime Minister: It is clearly of primary importance and in the best interests of the Polish nationals concerned, that as many as possible should be encouraged to return to Poland and should have time freely to decide to do soin the light of the information available as to the conditions which they are likelyto find on their return; and it is on this aspect of the matter that the Governmentsconcerned are concentrating. It is too soon to form any opinion as to the numbersof those who may eventually decide not to return to their homes, and the questionof the steps to be taken to give effect to the hope expressed by my predecessor thatit may be possible to offer British nationality to Polish troops who have servedunder our command is being borne in mind, but cannot be given further considera-tion until the nature and the size of the problem have been ascertained.


</content>
</cab>
