<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/4/0 images: 66-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY5 SGOVERNMENT)SECRETCP, (45) 25829th October, 1945 COPY NO.  cabinet&apos;    POLITICAL SITUATION IN BjURMAMemorandum by the Secretary of State for BurmaAs my colleagues are aware, Sir Reginald Dorman-Smiththe Governor of Burma, returned to Rangoon, on the 16thOctober.     The Civil Government, under his control has now taken over from the Military Government under the supreme allied Commander in the whole of Burma save the Southerndistricts, which still contain substantial&apos; armed Japaneseelements v/hich are in process of being cleared up.2o     The Governor, under instructions approved by Ho Mo Goon return to Rangoon initiated negotiations with political leaders with a view to forming a broad-based and representa-tive Executive Council, democratic in character.     He hasbeen confronted by a situation in which the body known asthe AFPIL (Anti-Fascist People5s Independence League) underthe leadership of &quot;Major general&apos;&apos;. Aung San, the leader ofthe Patriotic Burma Force, v/hich it will be remembered, cameover to us from the Japanese in the course of the spring,has established itself in a dominating position and claims to be accepted as speaking on behalf of Burmao     There is,however, clear evidence to suggest that it has acquiredthis dominating position in the countryside by the menaceof the armed force of the Patriotic Burma Force and becausemore moderate political elements in Burma have hesitated to oppose it openly.3b     I now circulate for the information of my colleaguesa copy.of a telegram No. 5 from the Governor reviewing theposition and describing the demands which have been putforward to him on behalf of the AFPIL, and the reply whichhe has given to them.   Those demands would give them a,clear majority of the Executive Council0     In addition,the AFPIL desire that the Governor shall accept without question the persons whom they nominate to be ExecutiveCouncillors: &apos; they demand the right to object to an executive Councillor proposed by the Governor:   they wishthe Governor to agree that he will assign portfolios to themembers whom they nominate to the Executive Councilaccording to the wishes of AFPIL:   and they appear to have it in view that any members chosen from their ranks shouldbe instructed by them to communicate the proceedings oi theExecutive Council to the AFPIL and to receive-politicalguidance from that body.     They furtrier claim the right to nominate/

hominate the members of the Legislative Council whichIs to he set up later in the year.\,    The AFPIL is unquestionably an important and well-brganised body which represents a body of opinion of whichhe shall have to take full account.     It has -all along&quot;een the intention,of the Governor to invite it to take a.Hue share in his Executive Council and his negotiations have in fact been directed to securing this.    But I am assuredtoy the Governor that its claim to be able to speak for all parties greatly overstates the position and that we shouldfaake a great mistake to allow ourselves to be manoeuvredginto accepting it as the voice of Burma and as adequatelyIrepresenting all political opinion in that country.   Demandsso extensive as   those advanced by AFPIL could not in any event be accepted consistently with the discharge of our obligations to the people of Burma as a whole.     Nor wouldtheir acceptance be consistent with the policy we have followed in Europe.     What is in dispute is not anyquestion of principle as to the constitutional developmentof Burma but whether AFPIL are to be placed without any.electoral mandate in decisive and exclusive control of thei Government.5.    I feel no doubt in these circumstances that theGovernor has taken the right course in declining to acceptthe demands of AFPIL and in making independent approaches to individuals, some of them in the AFPIL list, and in my telegram No.1235 of 28th October also annexed, I haveassured him of my full support,     A telegram since receivedfrom him states that -the omens are pretty favourable11and that two at any rate of the members of AFPIL whom hehad approached to serve on his Executive Council areprepared to do so even if (as he understands is likely)this may involve severing their connection with AFPILo     a third, he writes, &quot;is frightened but may join&quot;.     TheGovernor concludes:   &quot;Moderates are beginning to raise theirvoices&quot;.     The informative despatch in to-day&apos;s TIMES fromthe experienced Correspondent of that paper in Rangoon, ;also suggests that the&apos;true position is-fully appreciatedon the spot.     I may be in a position to give my colleaguesfurther information at the Cabinet to-morrow.P.-L.Burma Office,29th October, 1945

Allotted to Prlyate Secretary..Copies toy Sir Dv Monteath and Sir G. Laithwalte.Cypher (u.T,?-) telegram from governor of Burma to Secretary of State for burma, dated Rangoon, 20.40 hours,  27thOctobers 1945,I have come to the parting of the ways with the&quot;Big Three&quot; of AFPPL (Ba Pe, Than Tun, Aung San) much tothe relief of many people and to fear of numerous others,2,      1 have naturally insisted on my constitutional duty to reserve to myself allotment of portfolios,.    Ostensiblereasons for failure of negotiations are1.     That I insist on Paw Tun being Home Counsellor,2.      That I find myself unable to agree that apart from&quot;my&quot; four portfolios the AFPFL should have right to allocate other available offices.3..     That I refuse to accept Thakin (now &quot;Kg&quot;) Thein PeCounsellor,APPFL are also claiming right to nominate members of legislative Council when formed and obviously I cannotcontemplate this,5,      In ether words &quot;Big Three&quot; reckon that they should be in command and refuse to lose face by agreeing to my&quot;dictation&quot;.    They &quot;reckon they have gone a long way to meetme-    They have agreed to &quot;my&quot; having four members,    Theyhave also shown disposition to agree that in. existingcircumstances 15 members are too many and that my advice that 11 (v would be) enough should be accepted.:,    They sayAPPFL have been most reasonable.    How far have I gone tomeet them&apos;&apos;:&apos;   Their answer will be that 1 have beenintransigent from word go     that 1 have not tried to reachaccommodation en question of Home Member and. that I have not accepted fact that they and they alone represent publiccpinion,.    i&apos;t is no credit to me that I should have been disposed to aocopt their nominations to 7 seats on theCouncil since their supreme Council embraces ail political parties.    This is ostensibly true but  there are bothwilling and unwilling adherents to the League which in fact 1dominated by &quot;Big Three&quot;.4, .   The names they submitted to me were as  under :--Aung San U Mya Py in anticipation..U R&amp;zak-Th(?an) Mya,U Aye.,U Ba Pe.

2U Nyo Tun.TJ Thein Pe.U Be. Oh.Mxxn Ba Khin.Saw Ba U Gyl.5.      You will note that Than Tun1s name has been omitted andthat Thein Pe has been included.    Season for this is obvious,Thar). Tun reckons that he can do more for the League outsidethe Council than he can possibly do inside.    Monetaryconsiderations do not count, if my information is correct, asdecision is that, of their 4,000 Rupees.,  every AFPFL membershould accept for his own. personal use only 1,000 Rupees and putother 3,000&quot;back into AFPFL election fund,    4,000 Rupees under present income tax regulations boils down to less than they thinkpossible but it is disquieting and sadly revealing fact thatin not one of my talks with representative of AFPFL leaders hasquestion of finance been raised,    They mast think that money likebabies grows on AFPFL gooseberry bushes,    Aung San and Companyappear to hold the simple view that so outstanding have been theservices of PBF to the cause of United Nations that all thosenations are falling over themselves to provide money and goods to reconstruct Burma.    If they are not doing so then it onlyshows that Great Britain is determined to keep Burma down,this being one of the reasons why UHRRA is not admitted intoBurma.    The arrogance of Aung Sans knows no bounds.5,      This country is now governed by two fears.,    First fearis that I may not give way to Aung San and so may precipitatetrouble which. Burma naturally, after her long years of trouble,wishes to avoids    Second fear is that I will give way and sosurrender that government to extremists,,7.      I cannot fail to be impressed by the fact that many Burmanshave said to me that if we fail them they will have to make themselves voluntary exiles from their own country.    The wordu fail1&apos;means that.If we give way to AFPFL and thus face their ultimate control of the country, not through the real wishes of ordinary moderate opinion (in &quot;moderate&quot; I include socialistopinion, as I understand it) but by methods of force andfear, there will be no hope for Burma.    Whereas in Britainsome of us may have had fears for our purses If a left winggovernment came into power, we never- had any physical fears.Here physical fear is predominant.    This is bad.8.      Struggle now Is not for independence but for power.Aung San argues that no &quot;stranger&quot; to Burma (? which has) arisensince 194-2, Is competent to hold Borne portfolio.    Such a manwould never &quot;know (2 groups corrupt) or where arms are concealed.B0th. he and Than Tun warned me that there are a tremendousnumber of such arms and said quite firmly that only they coulddeal with this situation.    On ray suggesting that Home member in all important questions of policy would be carrying out policy as laid down by me after full discussion with Council theyshifted their ground to old point that it is the Home Memberwho will have most of the important postings In his hands and that unless he -knows conditions he will not be able toget/

get these right.    The &quot;new Burma&quot; does not seem to have theincorrect idea that civil servants can he used to assistpolitical parties,,9,      .4s far as Their). Pe is concerned it is not withoutsignificance that he was nominated on the grounds thathe is now leader of the Coramunist Party..    Not so long agoboth. Aung San and Than Tud called themselves communists,.Thein Pe is clearly not one whom j could accept,.    He isactively anti-British, his communism is crude to a degreeand of a kind which would make even Lenin blush and hiscontacts with. Indian communists bode ill for Burma.  (Youmight like to check up with information from India onthis point).    His Inclusion would certainly antagonisePhongyis which would, be most unfortunate,    (Swithinbankto whom I should like you to shew this telegram will beable to tell you about Tot Phongyi).10.      t suspect that truth really is all the &quot;chief three&quot;&apos;are nervous of their position should the;/&apos; appear to loseface by giving way to me and they feel they could only joinCouncil if they can say&apos;their power is such that they havemade me give way to them,.11c      If I were to give way undoubtedly whatever 1 or mysenior colleagues could  do Burma would come undercomplete sway of totalitarian system.    If, on the other hand.I stand by my guns, though trouble may repeat may occur in some places   model     elements will be encouraged endthere should be same hope for the future.    I am fortified by your view that emergence of single party government would be fatal development in Burma as in any other country,    .! havealso seen, but have not been officially confronted with,document which Is in. fact instrument of instructions to allelectors of APPPL who may accept invitation to serve onCouncil that they must report all proceedings of ExecutiveCouncil and must be guided in their actions by (? League)Council.    This is last proof, if proof were needed? that Iam faced with attempt to -set up completely totalitarianregime.    Copy of document follows by air mail.,12,      It seems clear therefore that whatever may beconsequences I can go no further than I have gone to meetthe wishes of APPPL,    1 reckon 1 have met such wishes asmay be deemed legitimate,      I cannot however meetunr ea sonab1e deraand s.13,      Therefore in reply to your telegram No,,  64 dated23rd October the names which .1  suggest for Council are asfollows:(l) Defence - H.C.    2.(2) Frontier areas -- Pearce.(5) Home     Paw Tun,,(4) Finance - Htoon Aung Qyaw.(&amp;) Commerce and Supplies - U Ayew,(8) Agri evil tore and Rural Economy     U T?u,(?) Education - Thakin Yen Aung.(3) Labour and Industry - U Ba On,(9) Social Services -- Caw Ba u Gya.(10) Transport and Communications - \i 3a Win.(II? Public Works and Rehabilitation - Thakin Mya,,Ob lection/

- 4Objection may be made that aome of these collaboratedwith the Japanese, but I am satisfied that willingcollaboration like that of Aung San was short lived ifit existed at all.    Brief biographical notes will followon names which may be new to you.14.,      Under this arrangement I would propose to includeHonourable Counsellor I (Sir John wise) as deputy chairman without portfolio.    You will appreciate thatthis does not mean without work.15.      At the same time I intend to make it known thatif at any time either Aung San or Than Tun or Ba Pewishes to - join Executive Council they can approach me and if I agree to their inclusion portfolios can bere-shuffled accordingly.16.      I have Instructed Pa?/ Tun as senior Bunnan Counsellordesignate to approach entirely without prejudice to thoseBurmans whom I intend to invite to serve and to report to me by Monday.    I hope this indication that I am determined to back him may have heartening effect and that show of readiness to turn down APPFL may do something to bring themto their senses although I am not too sanguine about this.It might possibly have opposite effect and provoke disorderbut I am advised this is not likely in immediate future.    1am naturally keeping General Stopford fully informed,1?&apos;.      I am firmly of opinion that only Burman leader who could get real grit; of situation is Saw provided he is fit and would welcome his return.    He would dispel present fears.    Nodoubt he might cause others but unless I have completelymisread his character he could be used, with most salutary effect in the present situation.18.      May I close on a note which Is not as Irrelevant asit might appear.      A country as devoid as Burma is of all supplies and of transport and means of communication is a ready forcing bed for alarms and disorder,   Bothing would have such sobering and reassuring effect as immediate and steadyflow of supplies.

Burma.0  iceFrom Secretary, of State for Burma.,To &quot; -        Governor of Burma-;Despatched 3.3*00 hou-rsj-, ,28th October;. 1945-,MOST^IEDIATE1 o .      Your t el sgr am N o.-- 5 &quot; of 2It h C e t oher.2, I would not have regarded appointment of Paw Tun as HomeCounsellor as by itself a matter on which to breaks    But right&apos; of selection must rest: wholly with Governor? and to give way on tbi snow would mean a. olimbdown on the Governor1 s part &quot;&quot;which 1 agreecould not be contemplated^, particularly as yob are, I understand *committed to him as Member designate and have employed him as suchas your go-between.    And 1 agree in any event that we could notconsider giving APP1L right to distribute portfolios ana nominateLegislative Councils nor (sea-our paragraph 11) could bs aoouiessein breach.of oath of secrecy or in guidance of Council 1 era b*yinstructions of an outside &apos;authority1.    Nor again can yon surrenderyour right of choice and rejection;; and 1 accept your rejection of D The in Pe.   Finally, list offered to you, while in formall-party and broadbased.  is., as I understand it, in fact asingle party list,, dominated by AFP XL * and cannot bo regarded assatisfying requirements of a democratic administration.3c 1 noto also, views expressed in your paragraph 7 .and your&apos;judgment that while firm stand and break with AFPIL now mayrepeat may mean trouble, you do not repeat rot think that likelyfat any rate* at present (your paragraphs 11 and. IS) a4* -       I agree in those circumstances that we cannot let our;selves either be bounced by AFPIL into placing thorn in exclusive  -authoritarian control of the/country or bo blackmailed by them,,and that a firm stand is necessary;  and I approve your action.reported in paragraph. 16. - . \,b-.       . As regards personnel proposed by yon In paragraph. 13.-  I agree as to wisdom of making only 11 appointments plus Wise now and keeping remainder in&apos; reserve against contingencies such as these mentioned in paragraph 15c -  I accept Wise as  deputy chairman without portfolio?  (I assume incidentally that he wouldcount against total of 15, but please confirm this).    As regardsyour remaining choices 1 note that Nos.5.? 8,  9 and 11 were included in the AFPIL list described in your paragraph 4.-    1.presume that your Inclusion of them in your list Is by way of helping AFPIL to save face.    But are you satisfied that If howappointed bp. your Council they can be relied on not to breaksecreoy (compare your paragraph .11) to APRIL?   1 rote also thatBa Win (though not.apparently on the AFPIL list) was 3a Maw&apos;sLaudation Hinister, while Thakin Mya was his Deputy PrimsMinister,  and so, one would have supposed,    deeply tainted.But subject to these comments, J await result of Paw Tun&apos;ssoundings,5.        As regards U Saw, you will now have had my telegram 120?/October

OUTWARD   TELEGRAMS -       38October- 26th.    In view of his record, we could place no confidence in him and could not contemplate his being employed in any circumstances.   We await your comments onproposal that he and Ba Maw should be permanently excludedfrom political life.7. I appreciate point taken in your final paragraph,-though you X know also appreciate the sharp practicaldifficulties.that confront us-    We will continue to do our best *3. We fully sympathise with you in the difficult positionyou are dealing with.    You may be certain of our- understandingsupport and swift consideration of any proposals you wishexamined.    Please continue to keep us in closest touch,? .andalso to maintain close touch with military&apos;..9. If things go badly, and indeed in any event if we break with APPIL. publicity will be of utmost, importance.    IfIlolburn is still in Rangoon. I understand that he is a wiseand experienced correspondent, whose despatches to the Timescarry, great weight, - and you may think It well to give himbackground.    1 will prepared the ground here.    Our case is avery strong one? but it is vital to get it across, properly;,and I know I can rely on you.to spare no pains to secure :hatfrom your end in Burma.Copy to:-.-   Mr. Joyce      -..(of Governor2 s telegram No. 5 and. of this reply,to go by hand this evening,)Mr. Turhbull.Sir D.T* Mont eath-.Sir G, Laithwaite*


</content>
</cab>
