<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/4/0 images: 246-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
V    115(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRET20TH November. copy no. faINVESTMENT  (CONTROL GUARANTEES)  bill memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.1.      I ask the approval of the Cabinet for the early introduction of the attached Bill, the Investment(Control and Guarantees) Bill, together with theaccompanying memorandum.The Bill has been considered by the lord president&apos;s Committee and I have incorporated somesuggestions there made to me,  including (a)  thesubstitution of &quot;regulation&quot; for &quot;prohibition&quot; in clause 1, and (b) an increase in the maximumguarantees permitted under Clause 2 from  25 millions to  50 millions a year.2.     The Bill is a vital part of our mechanism for regulating and,  if need De,    stimulating investment in the years immediately ahead,  so as to assumepriority, and proper timing, for those projects ofcapital development which are of the greatest importance in the national interest.3.      It is quite a simple Bill, giving power in thefirst Clause to regulate investment, and in the secondClause to provide guarantees for loans for industrialdevelopment and reconstruction.    But it is ml essentialinstrument of effective economic planning.H.D.Treasury Chamber, S.W.1.2OTH NOVEMBER,  191+5.

DRA F Tof atoProvide  for  the imprtsitinu nf   rpstrictffiins en   the   A.D. 1945borrowing   and   raising   of   money,   the   issue  of      -securities, and the circulation of offers of securitiesfor subscription, sale or exchange, to enable theTreasury to guarantee loans in certain circum-stances, and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid.&apos;E it enacted by the King&apos;s Most Excellent Majesty, by andwith the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled,and by the authority of the same, ast^lpw^:       ^^tt^a^^^15 The Treasury may make regulations for prohibiting. Treasurysubject to such exemptions as may be specified in the reguladoua, ,coptrol ofall or any of the following transactions, that is to say-^-^^ borrowing,etc.(a) the borrowing of money in Great Britain ;(b) the raising of money in Great Britain by the issue,) whether in Great Britain or elsewhere, by any body corporate, of any shares in that body corporate;(c) the issue for any purposes-^(i) by any body corporate of any shares in ordebentures or other securities of that body corporate,j ii either the body corporate is incorporated under thelaw of England or Scotland or the shares, debenturesor other securities are or are to be registered inEngland or Scotland ; or61-3 A9 Geo. 6. Investment (Control and IGuarantees).
A.D. i945.Power of theTreasury toguaranteeloans.(ii) by any Government, other than His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom, of any securities ofthat Government which are or are to be registered inEngland or Scotland ;(d) the circulation in Great Britain of any offer for sub-scription, sale or exchange of (i) any shares in or debentures or other securities of any body corporate not incorporated under the law of England or Scotland ; or(ii) any securities of any Government other than I0His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom :Provided that the provisions of this subsection authorising theprohibition of the borrowing of money shall not apply to the borrowing of money by any person (other than a local authority)in the ordinary course of his business from a person carrying 15on a banking undertaking.(2) The provisions of this section shall apply in relation to unitsunder a unit trust scheme as they apply in relation to shares ina body corporate, but as if (a) any reference to the issue of shares in a body corporate 20by that body corporate were a reference to an issue of units for the purposes of the scheme; and(b) any reference to shares in a body corporate incorporated,or not incorporated, under the law of England or scotland were a reference to units issued under a scheme 25governed, or not governed, by the law of England orScotland.(3) The provisions of the Schedule to this Act (which relate toenforcement and penalties) shall have effect in relation to regula-tions made under this section but the rights of the persons con- 30cerned in any transaction shall not be affected by the fact that the transaction was in contravention of any such regulations.2.-(1) The Treasury may, if satisfied that it is expedient inthe public interest so to do for the purpose of facilitating thereconstruction or development of an industry or part of an 35industry in Great Britain, guarantee any loan :Provided that the aggregate capital amount of the loansguaranteed under this section in any financial year (excluding anypart of that amount which is guaranteed neither as to principalnor as to interest) shall not exceed twenty-fiVfe million pounds. 40(2) Any guarantee given under this section may be given insuch form and manner and on such terms and subject to suchconditions as the Treasury think fit.
(3) Any moneys required for fulfilling a guarantee given under   a.d. 1945.this section shall be charged on and issued out of the Consolidated       -Fund or the growing produce thereof, and any moneys paid in ortowards repayment of any sum issued out of the Consolidated5 Fund under this section shall be paid into the Exchequer.(4) The Treasury shall lay before both Houses of Parliament -(a) a statement of any guarantee given under this sectionas soon as may be after it is given ; and(b) once in each year, an account of any sums issued out ofthe Consolidated Fund for the purposes of any suchguarantee.(5) In this section, references to the guaranteeing of a loanshall be construed as references to guaranteeing, whether whollyor in part and whether solely or jointly with other guarantors,the payment either of the interest, or of both the interest and theprincipal, of the loan, and the expression &quot; guaranteed &quot; shall beconstrued accordingly.3. (1) Regulations made under this Act shall be laid before ProvisionsParliament as soon as may be after they are made, and if either as toFlouse of Parliament within the period of forty days beginning reSulatlons-with the day on which any such regulations are laid before it,resolves that the regulations be annulled, the regulations shall cease to have effect, but without prejudice to anything previouslydone thereunder or to the making of any new regulations.(2) In reckoning any such period of forty days, no account shall be taken of any time during which Parliament is dissolvedor prorogued, or during which both Houses are adjourned for more than four days.(3) Section one of the Rules Publication Act, 1893, shall notapply to any regulations made under this Act.4. (1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, the Interpreta-following expressions have the meanings hereby assigned to them.tlon-that is to say : &quot; local authority &quot; means any authority being within themeaning of the Local Loans Act, 1875, or the LocalAuthorities Loans (Scotland) Act, 1891, an authorityhaving power to levy a rate ;&quot; registered &quot;, in relation to any security, includes inscribed,&quot; registered in England or Scotland &quot; means, in relationto securities, registered in a register in England orScotland, and &quot; register&quot;, in relation to securities,includes any book in which securities are registered ;&quot; security&quot; includes shares, bonds, notes, debentures,debenture stock and units under a unit trust scheme ;A z
A.D. 1945.Expenses,Short title and extent.&quot; share &quot; includes stock and any perpetual debenture orperpetual debenture stock ;&quot; unit trust scheme &quot; means any arrangements made for thepurpose, or having the effect, of providing facilities forthe participation by persons, as beneficiaries under a 5trust, in profits or income arising from the acquisition,holding, management or disposal of securities or anyother property whatsoever ;&quot; unit &quot; means, in relation to a unit trust, any right or interest,(described whether as a unit or otherwise) which may 10be acquired under the scheme, being a right or interestcreated or issued for the purpose of raising money for thepurposes of the scheme.(2) Any reference in this Act to the borrowing of moneyincludes a reference to the making of any arrangement by which 15a sum which would otherwise be payable at any date is payableat a later date, and includes in particular the making of any arrangement by which the whole or any part of the price of any property is allowed to remain unpaid either for a fixed period orindefinitely. 20(3&apos;) A person shall be deemed for the purposes of this Act to borrow of raise money in Great Britain if the money is madeavailable in Great Britain, or, in any such case as is mentionedin subsection (2) of this section, if the money would, but for thearrangement in question, have been payable in Great Britain, 25and, without prejudice to the preceding provisions of this sub-section, a person shall also be deemed for the purposes of thisAct to borrow money in Great Britain if the money is borrowedon the security of property in Great Britain.5. Any expenses incurred by the Treasury in the administration 30of this Act shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament.6. (1) This Act may be cited as the Investment (Control and guarantees) Act, 1945.(2) This Act shall not extend to Northern Ireland.
Investment (Control and guarantees).A.D.SCHEDULE.SectionProvisions as to Enforcement and Penalties.i. Any person who contravenes any provision of any regulationmade under this Act shall be liable on summary conviction toj imprisonment for not more than three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or the amount of the money or the value of the securities in question, whichever is the greatest, or to both such imprisonment and such fine.2. (i) The Treasury may give to any person directions requiringto him, within such time and in such manner as may be specified in the directions, to furnish to them, or to any person designated in the directions as a person authorised to require it, any information in his possession or control which the Treasury or the person so authorised,as the case may be, may require for the purpose of securing compliance15 with, or detecting evasion of, any regulations made under this Act.(2) A person required by any such directions as aforesaid to furnishinformation shall produce such books, accounts or other documents(hereinafter referred to as &quot; documents &quot;) in his possession or control as may be required by the Treasury or by the person authorised to20 require the information, as the case may be, and for the purpose ofinspecting any such documents any person so authorised as aforesaid^or any person authorised to act on behalf of the Treasury under this sub-paragraph, may enter any premises (using such force as is reason-ably necessary for the purpose) and may take possession of any of the25 documents or take in relation thereto any other steps which appear&apos; to him necessary for preserving them and preventing interferencetherewith.(3) Any information given by a person in compliance with thisparagraph may be given in evidence against him notwithstanding30 that it may tend to incriminate him.The provisions of this sub-paragraph shall be without prejudice toany question as to the admissibility as evidence of information obtainedunder statutory powers in the absence of any such express provision.(4) Any person who-35      (a) fails or refuses to comply with any requirement to furnishinformation or produce documents imposed on him by orunder this paragraph ; or(6) with intent to evade the provisions of this paragraph or of any regulations made under this Act destroys, mutilates, defaces,10 secretes or removes any documents ; or(c) obstructs any person exercising any powers conferred on himby or under this paragraph,shall be liable, on summary conviction, to imprisonment for not morethan three months or to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds15 or to both such imprisonment and such fine.
A.D. 1945.      3- (1) No proceedings for an offence under this Act shall be-       instituted in England except by or with the consent of the Director ofPublic Prosecutions.(2) Any proceedings under the Summary Jurisdiction Acts whichmay be taken against any person under this Act may, notwith- 5standing anything to the contrary in those Acts, be taken at anytime not later than twelve months from the date on which evidencesufficient in the opinion of the Treasury to justify the proceedingscomes to the knowledge of the Treasury, or, where the person inquestion was outside Great Britain at that date, within twelve months 10from the date on which he first lands in Great Britain thereafter.For the purposes of this sub-paragraph, a certificate of the treasury as to the date on which such evidence as aforesaid came to the know-ledge of the Treasury shall be conclusive evidence thereof.This sub-paragraph shall, in its application to Scotland, have effect 151as if for the references to evidence sufficient to justify a prosecution Ithere were substituted references to evidence sufficient to justify a report to the Lord Advocate with a view to consideration of the Iquestion of prosecution.(3) Proceedings against any person in respect of an offence under 20Ithis Act may be taken before the appropriate court in Great Britain Ihaving jurisdiction in the place where that person is for the time being.   I(4) Where a person convicted of an offence under this Act is Ia body corporate, every person who, at the time of the commissionof the offence, was a director or officer of the body corporate or was 251purporting to act in any such capacity, shall be deemed to be guilty iof that offence unless he proves that the offence was committedwithout his knowledge, or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent Ithe commission of the offence.(5) Where a person has been sentenced in England on summary 30Iconviction for an offence under this Act to a fine which exceedsfive hundred pounds, any moneys recovered in respect of the sumadjudged to be paid by the conviction shall be applied as follows : (a) first in payment to the person entitled thereto of any costsadjudged to be paid by the conviction the amount of which 35is ascertained by the conviction ;(b) if the balance remaining after payment of the said costs doesnot exceed five hundred pounds, it shall be applied inaccordance with the provisions of section five of the criminla justice Administration Act, 1914 ; 40(c) if the balance so remaining exceeds five hundred pounds, somuch thereof as is equal to five hundred pounds shall beapplied in accordance with the provisions of the said section five and the remainder shall be paid into the Exchequer ;and so much of the sum adjudged to be paid as falls, when recovered, 45to be paid into the Exchequer, shall, if not otherwise recovered, berecoverable as a debt due to the Crown.In this sub-paragraph, the expression &quot; the sum adjudged to bepaid by the conviction &quot; includes any costs adjudged to be paid bythe conviction, of which the amount is ascertained by the conviction. 50I

Investment (Control and guarantees).DRAFTof aBILLTo provide for the imposition of restric-tions on the borrowing and raising ofmoney, the issue of securities, and the circulation of offers of securities forsubscription, sale or exchange, toenable the Treasury to guaranteeloans in certain circumstances, and forpurposes connected with the matters aforesaid.CCLXXVII F. (5)i^tk November, 1945.6i-3(p. 34+2)
government /ICILANlJjJM. ON THE INVESTMENT (CONTROL AMD GU;ihjNTEES)  BILL.1.      This Bill has two purposes,  to regulate the borrowingof money and the  raising of money by the issue of securities,and to make provision for the guarantee of loans inappropriate cases for the reconstruction or development of   *an industry or part of an industry in Great Britain.Clause 1  deals with the first purpose and Clause 2 withthe second.    Clause 3 provides for the orders to be modeunder the Bill.2.      It is the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government to establish and maintain a proper balance between the economic  resourcesof the  community and the demands upon them.    This moans thatpriority must always be assured for those projects of capital development which are of the greatest importance in thenational interest.    Moreover,  it will sometimes bo necessaryto stimulate economic activity ao as to prevent our national resources, both human and material, being wasted in idleness.3.      It will,  thereforej be essential to plan both public and private investment, not merely in the narrow financial sense of controlling borrowing, but also in the wider sense of planning real capital development of all kinds.    But investment,even in this wider meaning,  represents only a part of thetotal claims on the national resources.    In addition, provision must be nr.de for the  current needs of the Central Governmentand other public authorities, for the export trade, and for personal consumption.    The planning of the investment programme as a whole must,  therefore, bo continuously glided by theGovernment and must he related to other Government plans forthe use of the country&apos;s economic resources.h.      Within the limits of such guidance, however, there  shouldbe the fullest co-operation between the Government, the public and private undertakings responsible for capital development,and the agencies providing the finance.    His Majesty&apos;s Govern-rnent are anxious to make this co-operation more close and effective than hitherto.5.      The Capital Issues Committee will be continued.    Subject todirections from the Treasury,  it will deal with individualapplications for permission to borrow.    The Public Works LoanBoard will also be continued.    But the important duties of these authorities in controlling and assisting the flow of new invest-ment, and of the Finance Corporation for Industry and theIndustrial and Commercial Finance Corporation, in providingfinancial assistance to industry, must be effectively linked with the operations of the Bank of England and with the planningby His Majesty&apos;s Government of the investment programme as awhole.6.      With this end in view His Majesty&apos;s Government have decidedto sot up a National Investment Council.    The Chairman will bethe Chancellor of the Exchequer,    The members of the council will include the Governor of the Bank of England,  the chairmen of the Capital Issues Committee,  and the Public Works Loan Boardand a number of other persons chosen for their wide knowledge and experience  of financial, economic end industrial questions.This Council will assist the Government in so organising and,when necessary,  stimulating investment as to promote full employment.

7.      Attached to this memorandum is the draft of theOrder which the Treasury would propose to make under clause 1  of the Investment (Control and Guarantees)Bill after it has passed into law, dealing with thecontrol of borrowing, etc.    Under this Order,  thescope of the control and of the exemptions therefromwill be substantially the same as at present.    Inparticular the general exemption in favour of borrow-ings not exceeding  50,000 in twelve months will becontinued.-2-


</content>
</cab>
