<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/202/0 images: 367-367</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government. Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1929.SECRET. Copy No.     28CP. 58 (29).CABINET.BELLIGERENT RIGHTS.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.WITH reference to the First Report of the Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence on Belligerent Rights dealing with Arbitration Treaties which was discussed by the Cabinet on the 15th February [Cabinet 7 (29)], I think that my colleagues may like to read the appended extract from the &quot;Times&quot; report of a speech made by Lord Grey of Fallodon. The speech was originally delivered on the 11 th November, 1927, at a meeting of the League of Nations Union at Plymouth, and last March was republished in French by the &quot;Journal de Geneve&quot; on the eve of a Council Meeting, when I believe that it attracted a good deal of attention.L. S. A.Dominions Office, February 25, 1929.Extract from Lord Grey&apos;s Speech.There were two reservations to be made as regarded both the Optional Clause and the &quot; All-in&quot; arbitration treaties. One was that they must not refer to internal affairs. And acts committed when a nation was at war, especially measures taken on the sea, were not suitable for arbitration. Before the United States came into the war they took a very narrow view of what might be done in the way of blockade. After they came into the war they joined with the Allies in carrying the rights of blockade and interference with neutral commerce to a point that had never been reached before. Thus, in one war one country had taken very opposite views of what was right and wrong with regard to blockade. That meant that on such a matter there was no agreed law, and precedents were valueless because they could be invoked on every side. There was, therefore, no standard by which any tribunal could decide such cases. Nor could they expect a country which was fighting for its life to hold up for arbitration the acts which it considered essential to bring pressure to bear on an enemy. Arbitration there might be on such things, but it must come after the war and&quot; not while the war was actually in progress. Having made these reservations, he would urge that the Government, by taking the two steps which he had suggested [viz., by signing the Optional Clause and declaring our readiness to conclude &quot; All-in &quot; arbitration treaties], would be making a contribu-tion to the feeling of security in the world and setting an example which other nations might follow7.[18910]

</content>
</cab>
