<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/202/0 images: 829-830</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1929.SECRET.Copy No.    23CP. 95 (29).CABINET.TAXATION OF NAVAL ALLOWANCES.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.WHILE I have every sympathy with the First LoroVs representations regarding the taxation inequalities which now exist as between Navy and Marine Officers on the one hand and Army and Air Force Officers on the other, * I should be reluctant to throw into the melting-pot on this account the whole question of the taxation of service emoluments. This would raise a very big issue, while the actual anomalies complained of are not of great significance. They could be remedied at a cost of  13,000 per annum, as the First Lord states, if it were possible to free from liability of taxation the lodging and servants&apos; allowances of the relatively few Naval Officers and men employed ashore. Unfortunately, this is not possible. It is one thing to administer the law so that taxation is not levied on emoluments which have been traditionally exempt. It is another to forgo tax where there is at least a strong presumption of legal liability and payment has been habitually made.If, then, Naval Officers cannot be granted exemption from taxation on the allowances in question, no advantage can accrue to them from tightening up the taxation of Army and Air Force allowances. Very considerable sums are here at stake. The following cash allowances, now for the most part untaxed, are provided in the Army Estimates for the year 1929 :  A general enquiry into the subject could not be restricted to an examination of these allowances alone. It would inevitably extend to the possible liability to taxation of the value of all quarters and other services provided in kind and of every kind of emolument, e.g., rations and allowances issued in lieu thereof.The grievance represented by the First Lord is not, in my opinion, of sufficient importance or urgency to necessitate the opening up of so wide an issue. If the enquiry is pressed and formal reference made to the Law Officers, the Government must be bound by the results. If, as is probable, the Law Officers were to find that a strict interpretation of the law requires that the present basis of taxation of service officers&apos; emoluments should be substantially widened, it is clear that a difficult problem of administration would arise. A revision of the allowance system would certainly be demanded by the service departments, and it is not beyond the bounds of possibility that the situation might call for legislative action which could hardly fail to be acutely controversial.Nothing would cause more ill-feeling among the military and Air Force Officers than for it to be said that the Government and Somerset House had together managedLodging FurnitureFuel and light ... Servants 354,500 163,000 191,000 81,000789,500[19039]* See CP. 76 (29).
to fecdnstrue the law so as to make all their allowances subject for the first time to Income Tax.   It would be represented as an act of voracious officialism.Already the Inland Revenue suffer in the public eye, because it is thought they are always looking for new and hard constructions of the law, and browsing on from point to point.For the sake of amending this petty anomaly of  13,000 a year to the Naval Officers, whose conditions of employment, taken as a whole, cannot be said to compare unfavourably with those of Army Officers, I do not desire to expose myself in the closing days of a Parliament to this kind of reproach, or let loose this new wave of prejudice against His Majesty&apos;s Government.w. s. c.Treasury Chambers, March 25, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
