<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/207/12 images: 177-192</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTC(79) 42 COPY NO   8 112 October 1979CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE 1981-82 TO 1983-84:OUTSTANDING ISSUESMemorandum by the Chief Secretary, Treasury1. On 13 September (CC(79) 15th Conclusions, Minute 6) Cabinetendorsed the proposals in C(79) 35 for the aggregate of public expenditurein 1981-82 to 1983-84, and the broad order of priority between programmes.I now report on my bilateral discussions with the spending Ministers, andmake proposals to resolve the outstanding issues.2. Some Ministers have accepted programme totals equal to, or littlehigher than, the proposals in C(79) 35.    Others have so far accepted onlysome of the suggestions of that paper, and have reserved certain majorissues for discussion in full Cabinet.    Annex A summarises the presentposition.3. The aim we endorsed is to stabilise public expenditure over thenext four years.    We must not pre-empt for public expenditure economicgrowth which has yet to be achieved.    The last three years, on whichdecisions are now sought, bring us to the end of the present Parliament.The reductions in plans now proposed are the least that would be necessaryso that we can reach the next election with a sound record of lower taxes,lower inflation and lower interest rates.4. The issues remaining to be settled amount to over  1^ billion by1983-84: (all expenditure figures in this paper are at 1979 survey prices).Provided that we remove this excess, the total expenditure plans in thelast three years of the survey period would be in the range of 682- 69 billion a year (line 10 of Annex D).    We shall not have got backto the 1977-78 level of  67  billion, but shall not be far off. Theseplanning figures are subject to the risk that unemployment (and henceexpenditure on unemployment benefit) may turn out larger than so farassumed.1SECRET
SECRET5. If we do not remove the remaining excess, not only should we beshowing no reduction from the level of the current year, but by the end ofthe period the total would be evidently taking off again.    This would beintolerable.    We run the risk of having the worst of both worlds. Weshall be criticised for making cuts but will not have reduced taxes enoughfor people to think that we delivered what we promised.    The electoratewill not believe what we say in the next general election campaign. Evenwith the totals now proposed, which are slightly higher than the target of 68- 68^- billion recommended in C(79) 35 and endorsed by the Cabinet, itwill be difficult to make any overall reduction in taxation.6. We have the objective, publicly stated, to reduce the basic rate ofincome tax to 25 pence over the lifetime of the Parliament.    The excessof over ilj billion in 1983-84, represented by the outstanding issues, isthe equivalent of nearly 4 pence on the basic rate.7. If the programmes where these unresolved issues remain are notcut as proposed, we shall need to consider whether to reduce otherprogrammes further.    All the provisional agreements which I have reachedwith spending Ministers have been subject to this possibility.OUTSTANDING ISSUESDEFENCE8. I maintain the Treasury proposal that the further increases indefence spending after 1980-81 should be limited to what is needed to fulfilthe North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) annual 3 per cent targetincrease in cost terms (for explanation, see Annex E), in line with thepractice of other NATO countries.    The Secretary of State for Defenceis suggesting on top of this a further addition, rising to  160 million by1983-84, to produce a 3 per cent increase in volume terms every year.AGRICULTURE, ETC.9. The Agriculture Ministers accepted the proposals for forestry andcertain minor items but their general view, particularly in relation to theproposals on capital grants, was that reductions would be inappropriate inthis sector.    We cannot in my view exempt agriculture from the need tofind the outstanding savings, amounting to  90 million in 1983-84. Theissues are being discussed in the wider studies of agricultural policycommissioned on 4 October (CC(79) 16th Conclusions, Minute 3).DEPARTMENT OF THE ENVIRONMENT (HOUSING)The Secretary of State for the Environment has accepted a reductionof only  500 million in 1983-84 compared with 1978-79, leaving a gap ofsome  750 million on rents ( 560 million) and public sector housebuilding2SECRET
SECRET(nearly  200 million).    Our wider economic strategy, as well as ourpublic expenditure plans, requires that we grasp the nettle of indiscriminaterent subsidies (on which the Secretary of State for the Environment hasundertaken to submit a separate memorandum).    See Annex F.EDUCATION11. The Secretary of State for Education and Science and I have agreedon many of the reductions proposed, and I have agreed not to press others.But there is still a difference on current expenditure on schools, on non-advanced further education and on higher education, amounting in total tosome  300 million by 1983-84.    Without significant contributions fromthese areas we cannot achieve the total savings required of this programme.Pupil numbers in schools are falling.    Our predecessors&apos; plans allowed foran increase in their unit costs that we cannot afford.    See Annex G.DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND SOCIAL SECURITY (SOCIAL SECURITY)12. The Secretary of State for Social Services and I have agreed on all theproposals in C(79) 35, except the proposed abolition of the Earnings RelatedSupplement, which would save some  200 million in 1983-84.    This needsto be settled by Cabinet.    See Annex H.CONSEQUENTIAL REDUCTIONS IN SCOTLAND, WALES AND NORTHERNIRELAND13. If we fail to make the reductions in agriculture, housing, educationand social security as originally proposed, then we lose also theconsequential reductions in the Scottish, Welsh and Northern Irishprogrammes, shown in item 4 of Annex A.OTHER MATTERS14. The following matters should be mentioned but do not needdiscussion in Cabinet now.EMPLOYMENT15.       The programme totals here proposed would not cover an extensionof temporary employment measures to new applications after March 1980.It is the view of the Secretary of State for Employment that it will benecessary to extend these measures, but he will not be ready to bringspecific proposals before Cabinet until the end of the year.    If Cabinetdecide to continue measures of this kind, the cost will have to be found fromthe Contingency Reserve.    If the present measures were continued lor onemore year, the net cost could be  50 million in both 1980-81 and 1981-82,and smaller amounts in the following two years.SECRET
SECRETNATIONALISED INDUSTRIES16. Most of the reductions have now been agreed, but there are largequestions outstanding on the energy industries and the Post Office. Thebiggest problem is on 1981-82 where the excess could be about  -1 billion.It is to be hoped that the bulk of the excess can be eliminated.    This is theaim of the discussions in the Ministerial Committee on Economic Strategyon 17 October (coal and gas) and of the Secretary of State for Industry&apos;sdiscussions with the Post Office.STAFF SAVINGS17. There are some overlaps between the Lord President&apos;s exerciseon staff savings and the reductions in Annex B.    The Departmentsconcerned are aware of these overlaps.    But the Lord President&apos;s reviewis also expected to produce staff savings additional to those in Annex B,and broad allowance is made for this in line 8 of Annex D.CONCLUSION18. I invite the Cabinet to consider the issues remaining in dispute, andto agree that no further increase should be made in the defence programmeand that the other four programmes listed in paragraphs 9-12 above shouldbe reduced by the full amounts shown in item 4 of Annex A (withconsequential reductions as shown for Scotland, Wales and NorthernIreland).J Btreasury Chambers12 October 1979SECRET
CONFIDENTIALANNEX A m 1979 Survey prices1981-82      1982-85 1983-84Inherited plans (line 5 ofAnnex D)759777722077200Sales of assets, reductions innationalised industries&apos;borrowing and extra staffsavings, and reductions incontingency reserve (lines 7 +8 t 9 of Annex D)-1822-2050-1900Reductions in major spendingDepartments provisionallyagreed (see Annex B)-4337-5453-5048Reductions to be discussedin Cabinet:maff	-70	-93	-90DOE (housing)	-418	-587	-746Education	-125	-210	-295DHSS (social security)	-260	-195	-195Consequential for Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland	-110	-150	-200-983-1235-1526fanning totals if alloutstanding reductionsagreed (lines 1+2 + 3 + 4)fttrthtn x er increase in DefenceDe discussed in Cabinet688556848268726+54+103+160CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALANNEX BReductionsand increases provisionally agreed m 1979 survey prices1981-82     1982-85 1985-84,(2)fence programme (1)0 (ODA)0 (other)ic Budget (incl IBAP)FF/DAFS/WOAD (excl IBAP)iirestry CommissionIlndustryTradeECGDpploymenttergyfcnsport(housing)ie (PSA))e (other))me Office)rd Chancellor&apos;s Deptmcation &amp; Science ^)pts &amp; Libraries(health)bss (personal social services)IDHSS (social security) -SOlD (civil superannuation)COIlottish Office (excl DAFS)1 Office (excl WOAD)Jorthern Ireland (inc NIO)l^er (local authorities&apos; VAT)TOTAL+31	+223	h-423-200	-292	-292-29	-35	-35+335	h-478	h-722-1	-3	-39-5	-6	-5-293	-408	-431-18	-22	-22+111	*27	-28-645	&apos; -686	-716-6	-13	-28-3I0	-367	-367-1125	-1424	-1600-70	-91	-91-293	-361	-361+41	4-58	+93-1	0	*7-529	-623	-703-43	-58	-58-156	-154	-154-127	-147	-125-412	-826	-519-4	-10	-15-3	-2	^2-5	-6	-6-312	-371	-390-123	-149	-155-121	-154	-153-24	-31	-32-4337	-5453	-5048V  Increases proposed in C(79)35(3) Partly subJect to British Council reviewNet, after allowing for maximum cost of assisted places scheme.CONFIDENTIAL
zu-  item  lA-  OTP ahhix&quot;a: ageeed&quot;CO&quot;&quot; C25 m 1979 Survey priceswoDepartmentDefence ProgrammePCO (ODA)J&quot;CO (other)EEC Budget (incl IBAP)MAFF/DAFS/WOAD (excl IBAP)Forestry CommissionIndustryTradeECGDEmploymentEnergyTransportDOE (housing)DOE (PSA)DOE (other)Home OfficeLord Chancellor&apos;s DeptEducation &amp; ScienceArts &amp; LibrariesDHSS (health)DHSS (personal social services)DHSS (social security)HMSOCSD (civil superannuation)CO IScottish Office (excl DAFS)Welsh Office (excl WOAD)Northern Ireland (inc NIO)1977-78	1978-79	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-84-7550	7509	8062	8250	8450	8650774	839	840	810	775	775270	293	290	276	272	271958	1164	1481	1549	1784	2028748	567	586	495	436	40352	54	57	58	58	591050	1016	995	812	644	610184	170	183	158	148	148-173	432	134	57	17	-381039	1111	1139	1045	999	968309	406	312	314	306	2912513	2507	2421	2360	2300	23004617	4376	4296	3842	3472	3137370	357	327	324	303	3032562	2588	2481	2444	2395	23951959	2049	2150	2212	2269	2304117	124	151	161	169	1768048	8232	7958	7798	7616	7453342	352	348	335	330	3306246	6421	6586	6b42	6769	67691076	1112	1066	1087	1110	113216595	18212	19289	18774	18668	1897490	99	100	95	90	85385	407	465	494	524	55824	28	25	23	22	223665	3729	3685	3650	3594	35461044	1104	1067	1048	1031	10152054	2239	2148	2114	2092	209064468	67497	68642	67227	66643	6675467670	70294	69604	68835	68482	68726Total of major spending Departments aboveTotal of all Depts, NIs, contingencyreserve etc.1. These figures take into account the reductions and increases in Annex B, and als? those in item 4of Annex A.2. Pigures for 1977-78 and 1978-79 are estimated outturns,; figures for 1980-81 are as agreed.
enwowCOJZ^e Changes1.     Total programmes   (excl NIs)*2. NIs&apos;   total borrowing (newdefinition)*3. Contingency reserve4. Shortfall5. TOTAL BEFORE CHANGES (lines 1-4)Changes6.7.8.10.11.Changes proposed in Annex A(lines 3+4)Sales of assetsReductions in NIs1 total borrowingand from extra staff savingsassumed in C(79)35Reductions in contingency reserveassumed in C(79)35TOTAL AFTER CHANGES (lines 5-9)Total if Cabinet accepted out-standing Departmental bids (inclDefence)665746657466899 0 771	78-79 69162 0 -1132	79-80 69863 277 -750	SO-ST 73335 750 1527 -1000	-82 7^4-080 700 2197 -1000	74770 700 2750 -1000	7A-750 700 2750 -100067670	70294	70340	74612	75977	77220	77200			-3431x	-5320	-6688	-6574-	-	-1000	-500	-200	-100	-100-	-	-	-300	-925	-1200	-1550-	-	-	-777 x	-697	-750	-25067670	70294	69340	69604	68835	68482	. 6872669872     69820 70412*   Outturn for 1973-74, 1977-78 and 1978-79; estimated outturn for 1979-80; Cmnd 7439 revalued for1980-81 to 1983-84.0   (a)   BP share sale proceeds of  697m are added back in 1977-78.(b)   To make the figures comparable with later years, the cost of that part of family support whichin 1973-74, 1977-78 and 1978-79 was provided through child tax allowances rather than throughchild benefit has been added into the social security figures./ Excluding short-term borrowing and leasing,x   Agreed in July.
CONFIDENTIALANNEX&apos;E&apos;reasury proposal ia that from 1980-81 onwards the increase inefence programme should he 3% per annum in cost terms, which onat calculations produces the following figures in volume terms,igures ia brackets show the increases over the previous Government &apos;spublished plans: n at 1979 Survey prices1981-828250(+3D1982-838450C+223)1983-848650C+423)je extent that later forecasts of price movements may modify the;ioa between cost and volume figures, the volume figures would beted in either direction so as to maintain the 3% per annum growthist terms in these three years.   Some adjustment may be necessarye publication of our plans this year.jo iaterpret the NATO commitment in cost terms is. in line withiractice of other NATO countries where Budget plans are expressed inIt enables us to take credit for our necessary and proper, butpive, provision for armed forces pay      and      : provides a betterre of the financial resources being devoted to defence.hese proposals still provide for defence spending to rise by 16%ier annum) in volume terms over the five years from 1978-79- Thewe share of total public expenditure would rise from 11% to 13%, and)f from some 4.9% to over 5-5%, a figure which no major Ally couldie Defence Secretary&quot; wishes to add a further  50m in 1981-82,  100mp-83, and  160m in 1983-84, so as to show 3% per annum increases)lua&apos; terms in each of those, years.   Over the five years from?9 this would make the increase in volume terms nearly 18%, and in* cost terms figures would appear in the White Paper in the defence&apos;      the Defence Secretary is concerned about the presentationalshowing less than 3% per annum over the last 3 years int** tablepntics cLes which are in volume terms.
CONFIDENTIAL6.   It is true that in most of our forward expenditure planning theemphasis is on volume figures, and the NATO target has hitherto beenconsidered in those terms.   But NATO countries, few of which publisaDefence figures at all for future years, can hardly criticise us formoving to an interpretation, in line - for the most part - with their iown, especially when we have substantially exceeded the target thisyear and are planning for next year an increase which will neet thetarget on either interpretation.7. This and the increasing share of total public expenditure shouldialso be a sufficient answer to any domestic criticism.
ANNEX FBOUSINGIfe can and should make real reductions in housing expenditure,by leaving more to $he private sector and cutting back on subsi-dies.   The original Treasury proposals entailed spending about 1250 million less in &quot;1983-84 than in 1978-79.   The EnvironmentSecretary has accepted a reduction of only  500 million, leavinga gap of  750 million.    (The gaps in 1981-82 and 1982-83 are  420million and  590 million respectively.)Subsidies2.  560 million of the gap in 1983-84 is accounted for bysubsidies, on which the Environment Secretary has undertaken toprovide a memorandum.    This part of the gap comprises two elements.On management and maintenance the Environment Secretary has notaccepted the Treasury proposal to stop financing a 2% p.a. realgrowth in management and maintenance (saving  45m,  70m,  100m).On rents I believe we must secure from 1981-82 onwards annualincreases of  1.50 a week larger than those planned by our pre-decessors (saving  250m,  450m and  550m).3. The Treasury proposal would entail an average rent in 1983-84of just over  11 a week in today&apos;s terms, and considerably less,after rebates, for the less well off.    Our wider economic strategy,as well as our global public expenditure plans, requires that weB^asp the nettle of indiscriminate rent subsidies.    If colleaguesdecided not to accept the Treasury proposal in full we shouldinevitably have to make larger reductions elsewhere, including, Isuggest, greater reductions in housing capital than the TreasuryProposal mentioned below. ublic sector housebuildingThe remaining gap of around  200 million p.a. reflects theEnvironment Secretary&apos;s wish to provide for 70,000 new publicsector dwellings a year.   But this year approvals are unlikely toexceed 65,000, and the trend is sharply downwards.   The TreasuryProposals allow for 55,000 approvals a year from 1980.   Even on afatherpessimistic view of the private sector1s capacity, the
Treasury proposal is consistent with a total housebuilding pro-gramme (England) of 175,000 to 200,000 p.a., against the expectednet household formation of 130-160,000 p.a. of which all but40,000 p.a. will be people living alone.    The Treasury proposalis justified both on realism and on merits.
ANNEX GEDUCATIONThe position on this programme is: m 1979 Survey prices80-81   81-82   82-83 83-841.	Gmnd 7439 revalued	8395	8452	8449	84512.	Reductions agreed	-437	-569	-678	-7583.	Assisted Places Scheme* (up to)	-	+40	+55	-h554.	Proposed expenditure (DES)	7958	7923	7826	7748%	Further reductions proposed	-	-125	-210	-2956.	Proposed expenditure (BUT)	7958	7798	7616	7453* This is a contingency provision and a maximum.    Figures to matchthe scheme actually adopted will have to be substituted in due course.Issues for discussion2.    The gap between the Education Secretary and the Treasury (line5 above) is wide.    It concerns current expenditure on the three mainareas of education - schools, non-advanced further education andhigher education.    But without the full contribution from theseareas which the Treasury is proposing, we cannot achieve the totalsavings required of this programme.3.    The Education Secretary considers that our Manifesto commitmentto &quot;maintain standards of achievement in basic skills&quot; ought tobe interpreted widely enough to allow a continuing increase in unitcosts in schools and that the level of expenditure in further andhigher education should keep up with the growth in the number ofyoung people aged 16-21.   My view is that our predecessors1 plansfailed to face up to the implications of falling school rolls andfalling demand for voluntary education.    The commitments in ourManifesto (and Queen&apos;s Speech) were about the quality of educationrather than the quantity of resources devoted to it - and the twodo not necessarily go together.   It should be possible to find theSquired savings from these three programmes.The implications of the specific Treasury proposals are asfollows.(a)  School teachers and non-teaching costs
5.     Unit costs would be held to their 1978-79 level with anaddition of about  130m pa. to allow for the practical problemsinvolved in reducing expenditure exactly in line with the expectedfall in pupil numbers over the period.6o     Between 1973-74 and 1978-79 unit costs increased, in realterms, by 17% in primary schools (while numbers were falling by10%).    In secondary schools unit costs rose by 7% (while numbersrose by 10%).    That is the background against which the implicationsfor &quot;standards&quot; should be judged.80-81    81-82   82-85 85-84Proposed expenditure:HMT 3746     5641      3546 5446DES 5746     5706     5656 5621Difference - 65        90 175(b)   Non-advanced further education7.     This activity would be scaled down first to its 1978-79 levelin 1981-82 and then to its 1977-78 level in 1982-83.   That wouldinvolve a 5% reduction on 1978-79 in the number of places and/orin unit costs; although the demand for EE is rising, those 16-18year olds wanting full-time courses would have the option of stayingon in school where they could be accommodated at low marginal cost.80-81    81-82   82-85 85-84Proposed expenditure:HMT	577	550	530	530DES	?77	590	600	605Difference	-	40	70	75(c)   Higher Education8.     The present rate of student intake could be continued, bearingin mind that total student numbers have been practically constantover the last four years, despite an increase in the relevant agegroup.   There is anyway scope for reducing unit  costs in the poly-technics and EE colleges which could, alternatively, offset anyrise in student numbers.80-81   81-82   82-85 85j^tProposed expenditure:HMT 1608     1604     1600 1626DES 1608     1 624     1 650 16/J.Difference - 20        50 ^
ANNEX HEARNINGS RELATED SUPPLEMENT TO SHORT TEEM BENEFITSBackgroundThe Earnings Related Supplement (ERS) provides an addition to flat-rate sickness and unemployment benefit (also widows&apos;, maternityand industrial injury benefit).    It is a contributory benefitpayable from the National Insurance Fund.   When it was introducedin 1966, the Labour Government said the purpose was to encourageskilled workers to search thoroughly for suitable employment ratherthan being tempted, by the sharp fall in their weekly income, totake the first available vacancy.    Similar provision was made forthe sick.   ERS thus cushions the fall in income.2.    The supplement is paid after two weeks&apos; unemployment orsickness and runs for six months.    It is calculated as one-thirdof weekly earnings between  15 and  30, plus 15% of weekly earningsbetween  30 and  105-    The maximum payment is  16.25 a week andthe average amount in payment in November 1978 was  9-34.    At anytime some 300,000 sick and 200,000 unemployed are in receipt ofthe benefit.The difficulties in abolishing ERS3*    (a)   The (first) actual cut in benefit entitlement.    The manon average earnings with a wife and two children who becomessick or unemployed now gets  13.37 ERS added to his flat-ratebenefit of  27-20.    This is 48% of his net earnings. Hisbenefit would drop to 32% of net earnings if his ERS went.(b) An increase in dependence on   supplementary benefitduring shorter term illness and unemployment, and in the loadon supplementary benefit offices.    The cost of this is howevertaken into account in the  200 million in 4(a) below.(c) The effect on the Government&apos;s relationship with theTrades Unions overall; and specifically on the proposal toMake employers responsible for the first six weeks of sickPay (worth  350 million p.a. in expenditure savings and 5,000in staff savings).(d) The need for contentious principal legislation,
particularly as regards widows and the industrially injured.Since EES is contributory, abolition would create an expect-ation of a reductionin employees&apos; earnings-related contribution.    However, ifthis were conceded it would be equivalent to a reduction intaxation, in accordance with the Government1 s general policy.The case for abolition4.      (a)   Public expenditure.    If not ended the scheme will havecontinuing costs of about  200 million p.a., even allowingfor the introduction of the sick pay scheme mentioned in paragraph 3(c) above.(b) Simplification.   Ending this scheme would also simplifythe contributory benefit system and Inland Revenue considerit should make it easier to bring short-term benefits intotax.(c) Incentives.   It is the Government*s policy as far aspossible to ensure an adequate gap between in-work and out-of-work incomes.   People who get ERS are those with good worrecords and substantial previous earnings; nevertheless ERSdoes - indeed is intended to - narrow this gap.(d) Erosion of purpose.   Successive Administrations haveallowed the value of benefit to diminish in real terms (themaximum rate is now worth roughly half its 1966 value) and,given present unemployment levels, it no longer serves itsoriginal purpose.

</content>
</cab>
