<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/108/0 images: 60-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;     46(This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty1^ Government.)CONFIDENTIAL, CABINETO.P. 1516.NOTES OP THE CONVERSATIONS AT LOT? HE, Iff THE, ON SUNDAY&quot;, JUNE 20, and of the CONFERENCE AT BOULOGNE on MONDAY, JUNE 21, and TUESDAY, JUNE 22, 19 20. ,;,(Note hy the Secretary to the Cabinet)The Conversations at Sythe and the Conference at Boulogne may conveniently be summarised together since the first was the preliminary to the second.The Conversations at Hythe were attended by. the Prime Minister and Mr.Chamberlain on behalf of the British Government and; by M..Mill,erand and li.Mars.al on behalf of the French Government. Financial representatives accompanied the Heads of Governments and Field-Marshal Wilson- an  Marshal Foch, accompanied by General weygand, were present to advise on military questions.The Boulogne Conference was attended by the Prime Minister, Lord Curzon and- Mr.Chamberlain on behalf of the British Govem-ment, M.Millerand and ,M.,Marsal, and, at the last meeting, M. Le Troquer, French Minister of Public Works, on behalf of France, Count Sforza on behalf of Italy, Viscount Chinda on behalf of Japan, M.Hymans and M.Jaspar on behalf of Belgium.Financial Experts accompanied the representatives of all the Governments and Field-Marshal Wilson and Marshal Foch accompanied by General Weygand, advised the Conference on mili-tary questions.^REPARATIONS.        The principal object both of the Eythe conversations and of the Boulogne Conference was to deal with Reparations and good progress was made.     Several questions were -   remitted to Experts and it will be more convenient to deal jj,     . with the question in a separate note which the Treasuryrepresentatives have been asked to prepare.-1- . 2. DISARMAMENT
Z+ DISARMAMENT        Prolonged, discussions on this question took piece of Qwmn.r ;, both at Hythe and et Boulogne.At Hythe it Was&apos; felt both by Mr.Lloyd George and.M.M&apos;illerand that it was desirable to moke some imoressionupon the Germans before the Allies went to Spa in order.to demonstrate to them that the Allies,were absolutelyunited oh the necessity for disarmament.    The followingPress Coiamunique was accordingly issued from Hythe :-&quot;The French Government has accepted the sug-gestion of the British Government that the rote at which the German Government is carrying into execution the clauses of the Treaty of Versailles which relate to dis-ermament is profoundly unsatisfactory.   The two Governments have therefore agreed to recommend to the Inter-Allied Conference at Boulogne that their military advisers should, be instructed to concert at once proposals for the acceleration of the execution of the clauses of the Treaty of Peace dealing with . German armaments both in men and material.&quot;After several discussions at Boulogne, the follow-ing Conclusions were reaohed ;-(a) To approve the despatch prepared by Marshal Foch and Field-Marshal Wilson on the subject of the disarmament of Germany:.  (b) That M.Millerand, as President of theBoulogne Council, should at once transmit the despatch to the&apos; German Government.(Hote.   The text of the despatch as finally approved is given in Appendix I.)It had transpired at Hytha that serious delay in the disarmament of Germany was being caused by technical difficulties which bad arisen   .      in the disposal of the scrap materiel realised after the destruction of war material.In order to surmount this difficulty the following decisions were taken(a) To accept the Report of Marshal Poch and Field-Marshal Wilson on the subject of the measures to be taken to ensure the rapid disarmament of Germany. (Appendix II).(b) That the Reparations Commission should be instructed to act with; the least possible delay.(H.B. The method of instructing tvhe Reparations Commission is that each Government instructs its-2-
own representative1&apos;and the responsibility1for1 this in the case&apos; of the British Government.will presumably rest with the Treasury).The following Conclusion   was reached in regard tothe&apos;destruction of aircraft the manufacture and importation of aeronautical material referred to in Article &quot;2C1&apos; in ihe Treaty of peace shall be prohibited in&apos; all German territory during the three months following the date on -which Germany shell have handed over all her aeronautical, military and naval material;-  delivery to be certified by the Inter-Allied&quot;Aeronautical Commission of Control.It was further agreed  That&apos; the above resolution should be communicated to the German Governmont by M.Millerand, as President of the Conference. &apos;A question arose at Eythe as to the precise date at which the ownership of war material to be surrendered by the Germans passed to the Allies.    Uncertainty existed as together this dated from the signature, the ratification, or the coming into force of the Treaty of Yersailles.   It was stated that this question was also delaying disarmament.Sir Cecil Hurst and M.Fromageot, the French legal&apos; -YAdviser were telegraphed for to come to Boulogne.   Unfortun-ately, M.Promagoot was in Strsssburg end only arrived towards the end of the Conference.    A legal opinion was given to the Conference, but there was no time to discuss the matter and no decision was taken.Finally it was stated at Hythe that the technical means at the disposal of the Allied Military Commission of Control were insufficient to secure a more rapid rate of destruction than 600 guns a week.     It was understood that Field-Marshal Wilson would telegraph to General Binghsm , inviting his opinion as to what technical mesns of destruc-tion he would require to increase this figure to, say, 2,000 guns a week.The Boulogne Conference agreed -That the Conference of Ambassadors should despetch a ftote which they had prepared in respect of the request of the German Govern-ment to be allowed to. maintain a standing army of. 00,000 men. (Appendix III)*S* 3-. COST
[n49COST OP At the Hythe Conversations a question arose as toPY OP&apos; UPATION.   the great cost of the,Allied Armies of Occupation inGermany.    At present this is reckoned on the basis of actual cost, with the result that the small jiraerican. Force is alleged to cost nearly as much as the largetFrench Army.    It was realised that this amount -would eatsomewhat deeply into the amount available for reparation.It was accordingly agreed -That Mr.Chamberlain and M.Marshal should instruct their .  - rorpoctifrv Financial Experts to work out together a scale for the armies of occupation.beginning on the basis of the French scale of cost.APPOINTMENT       The following decision was reaohod at Boulogne on AMBASSADORS BERLIN.      , June 21st(a) &quot;That the Charges dTAffaires of the principal Allied and Associated Powers at Berlin should be instructed by their respective Governments to meet together on Thursday, June 24, 1920 and present to the German Government an identic note announcing the intention of these Governments to appoint Ambassadors to represent them at Berlin at an early date.(b) That M.Millerend, as President of the Boulogne Conference should communicate this decision to President Wilson.TURKEY. Discussions took place both at Hythe and Boulogneon the present situation in Turkey and/the following  -decision was reached at Boulogne on June 22 :-*&quot;To approve the arrangements made with M.Veniselos for&apos;reinforcing by a Greek Division the Allied Forces, in the area of Constantinople and the Straits, and &apos; for concerted action by the Greek Forces in the Syrama area.The following Conclusions were reached in regard toan application by the Turkish Delegation for a further extension of the time allowed to reply to the Treaty ofPeaceI (a)   That the application of the Turkish&quot;(P Delegation for a second extensionof the time allowed for their reply to the Turkish Peace Treaty should . not be gran-4-&apos; (b) That
. f;       50(&quot;b) That M.Milleran&amp;, as President of the Boulogne Conference should telegraph&apos; 11 this decision to Darned For id Pasha:(o) That if the Turkish Delegation defers its reply for two or three days, no objection will be raised.5. SPA. As regards the representation of certain powers atthe Spa Conference, it was agreed   -    \ -    * &apos; &quot;(a)   To reply to the Serbo-Croat-Slovene V*       - -application tc be represented at the Spa Conference in the sense that they can send representatives to Spa, not to take part in the Conference with the Germans, but in order to attend any Allied Conference held in connection with the main Conference to consider questions such as Reparations or Disarmament in which the Serb-Croat-Slovene State is concerned.(b) That Portugal and Roumania and any ether; - - . Power similarly situated should be invited::;to send representatives to Spa on the same footing as the Serb-Croat-Slovene State:(c) That if any question arises affecting Poland, such as Dantzig, the Poles should be entitledto be heard but not as Members of the Conference.6. BRUSSELS   &apos; It was agreed - -C0H2BRSHC3.   . .That if July 5 remains as the date of the Spa Conference, the Brussels Conference shall take place on July 2 and 3.I?. RUSSIA. The Prime Minister&apos;had a long conversation withILMillerand at Hythe on the subject of his negotiations with M.Krassin and there was also a discussion on the subject at Boulogne.     The question was left in statu quo and M.Mlllerend was not vailing to send political repres-entstives. to attend the negotiations.(sgd) M.P.A. HAHKEY.s!, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.125rd June , 19 20.
DESPATCH TO THE GERMAN GOVERNMENT ON THE SUBJECT OF DISARMAMENT AS APPROVED AT THE INTER&apos;-ALLIED CONFERENCE AT BOULOGNE, 22.6.20.-The Allied Governments have noted with the greatest regret, the slowness and lack of good-will shown by the German Government in the execution of&quot; the military, naval and air clauses of the Peace Treaty.On June 22nd, after a period of almost six months since the final ratification of the Treaty,, the most important of these clauses have either not been carried out or have only been executed incompletely. For example, the Regular Army has only just been re?   &apos; duced to 200,000 men,, an effective which it should have reached on April 10th,; whilst its organisation is not in accordance with that fixed by the Treaty; no law has been promulgated establishing in Germany a military state of affairs in conformity with the Treaty;:: the military formations forbidden by the Treaty, i.e.; Sicherheitspolizei. and Eimwohnerwehr, still exist in spite of repeated demands for abolition; the destruct-ion of.war material, which should have been completed by March 10th, is not yet half finished;&apos; export of arms continues. i;,The Allied Governments,- after having carefully examined the situation, have unanimously decided to ad-here completely to the clauses of the Treaty signed by--Germany,, both as regards her disarmament in, effectivestheand in war material,., and in insisting upon/immediate and
complete execution of, these clauses) which hr::; already been far too long delayed;  ,T&apos;he Allied Governments further wish to&apos; to be understood that the German Government must make no further demand for modification in the Military clauses bf the Treaty; such demands can only receive a negative reply and conse-quently can only result in fresh delays.The. Allied Governments are to-day addressing to -the President. .of the German Gornmis-sion of Peace in Paris their&apos;&apos; reply to . the request of - the&apos; German Government to be allowed, to keep an Army of 200,000 men.- This reply informs the&apos; German Government that the military forces of Germany&apos;will be maintained at the figure of 100,000 men, as fixed by the Treaty, and with the organisation laid down b^ this Treaty; that the&apos; Sicherheitspolizei must be completely dis-banded within a period of three months; and that on the other hand the strength of the German police forces*is raised to 150,000 men, i.e. an increase of 70,000on the figure of 19.13.-   ;  -   .....The Allied &quot;Governments further request the German- Government (a&apos;) to set up without any delay the legislation required by.Article 211 of the Peace Treaty&apos;, :(b) To pass the necessary laws to forbid the export of war .material &quot;to foreign countries in accordance,with Article 170, -(e) To disband effectively the formations of Einwohnerwehren&apos;which still.&apos;exist in spite of the Resolution of April 8th to carry out the surrender- of
A       5the arms belonging to these formations.The Allied Governments wish it to be under-stood that no fresh delay must occur in the destruct-ion of the war material, and that the execution of all the Clauses regarding disarmament, both in effects ives and in material, should be completely carried out, without further postponement: failing this, the Allied Governments would see themselves compelled to s tudy the means required to ensure the complete execution of the terms of the Treaty.22.6 .20.
&apos; &apos; 54t f. .APPENDIX II.REPORT OF MARSHAL POOH AND FIELD-MARSHAL WILSON OH THF SUBJECT OF THE DESTRUCTION ^, AND DISPOSAL OF GERMAN WAR MATERIAL.1.        .  While waiting for the Various interpretations of the attribution of the value of materials of all kinds transferred by Germany tinder the terms of articles 169, 192 and 262, to be reconciled, it is essential that&apos;the disarmament of Germany should be proceeded with as rapidly as possible.2. Accordingly the Reparations Commission is requestedto proceed with the liquidation of all the material referred to in articles 169, 192 and 202, with the ex-ception of those reserved by the Allied and Associated Powers under the terms of the Treaty.3. The Military, Naval and Air Commissions of Control-will hand over to the duly accredited agents of the Reparations, Commission complete lists of all this material, the duty of fixing the technical conditions and rendering material unserviceable resting solely with these Commissions.4. The agents of the Reparations Commission shall beempowered to receive all sums, the proceeds of the sale of this material.   A special account shall be opened for these sums, the. distribution of which shall be settled later after a final decision has been reached on the question of the attribution now under discussion.
, .     V 11 &apos; &quot; [   55konsiour JUr &quot;Prosi o.nt,Pur una noto dix.t^o--d.u--&apos;4-w.juln) lo Gpuvornomont :d 1 sraand nlioguant quo Ida Puissancea allioos. n&apos;.ont pas ropondu do &apos;^maalo-re-dxjJ^liiitiYS a la. domando prosontoo par1 lui Is  .0 t3vril , dfin d-otrs autorisa.. a-donso-rvor - uno arms/3 portoandftto do  00,000 hornmoa, 3&apos;ast ad^rosSa a la Conforanoo; pour qua soitprolongo nrovisoire-&apos; mont do delai oxpifant Id 10 -julllat qui a to impart! a\L&apos;Ulomagno pour ramonor 1&apos;a    ptif do sos troupes uu1 chiffro de &apos;100,000 hommss.A 11 appui ds sa do mind 0, lo Q-ouvorn-Jm-ani allomand fait valoir on particulier qus^ d1 aproa co quo los Gouvornornonta. allios lui ont fait connaitro sur la Conforonco&apos;do San Romo, il faut a- at ton dr 3 a oa quo la1&apos; Conforonce do 3pa statuo dofinitivomant sur cot to roqueto.Los Puiasancos allioos no sauraiont accoptor cot to intorprot-ation do la note qu&apos;olios ont a&amp;rsssse ie Sari Homo au.Gouvornom3nt allomand.     Biles ont alors not to merit declare qu&apos;olios no poavaisnt memo pas examiner&apos;la domands pr3S.ontoa dr,ns lo memorandum nllomand du  0 avril tant quo 1&apos;Allemagno manquait uux plus impcrtantes obligations du traite de paix ot qu&apos;ello no procodait pas au de3-armsmont do son armoo.   Hion dans lour ro^ponse no permsttait au Gouvornomorit allomand do so croiro a at or is 0 a-auspendre 1&apos; application -dos imosuros &quot;qui dovaiont otra on courc1 d&apos;execution dapuia lo 10 avril pour ramonor a 100,000 hommos lo cMffro do son armoo.D&apos;ail lours, on pro long 3 ant jus.qu&apos;au 10 juillot lo dolai -accords pour cot to oneration, los Allies avalont pleinemont tonu compts dos difficultos quo 1&apos;Allemagno etait logitimomont autoiiaoo a invoqu3r.Dans cos conditions, los Gouvernomon-ts allies no voiont -aUcuno raison pour corns.on tir aujoara;hui a aoo nouvslla prolongation do - co dolai. Ils oonfirmont done.................&apos;.....&apos;.....(Do
I56prureme2rt-^-^ les Glausesmilitaires du traite de Versailles conoernant lrajii.eV-^llemajQde tant au point do vue des effectifs qu&apos;au point de s on * organisation&apos; et de son armement, sont inrtegriilemant^maini^nues: tiles Solventi*&amp;tre strictoment executees.Si olies sont resolues a pdursuivre le desarment de l1 allelmagtie confermement aux stipulations du traite&apos;, lee Puissances ne meconn-aissent cependant pas la necessity de laieaer a la disposition du Grouvernement allemand des forces interieur.   A cet egard, elles reconnaissent volontiers que les forces normales de police, si elles Staient maintenues a leur effeotif de 1913 ne seraient pas assez nombreuses pour faire face a tous les besoins.   Les Gouvernements allies sont prets a en auteriser 1&apos;augmentation; mais ils-.no pourraient admettre sous aucun pretexte que cette augmentation ait lieu par le maintien de la Sichersheitpolizei, police de caractere et dTorganisation   essentiellement militaire et que PAllemagne a ete invitee a dissoudre des le mois de decembre 1919..   Cette dis-solution devra etre acheve*e dans un dolai de 3 mois a compter de 1&quot;envoi de la presente notetPar contre, les Allies acoeptent le reinforcement de 1&apos;ancienne police dits Ordnungspalizei.    LrOrdungspalizei compte a 1&apos;heure actuelle 92,000 hommes.    Les Puissances consentent a ce api&apos;elle soit portee au chiffre de 150,000 hommes, mais elles mettent a cette concession les conditions suivantes qui devront etre striote-merit remplies*LTOrdnungspolizei oonservera son caractere dTorganfcsme region-al et municipal.   Elle ne reoeura a aucun degre et d&apos;aucune maniere une organisationcentralisee.   Elle sera detes dlun armement correspondant a son role et qui sera determine par le Commission inter-alli^e de controls. 11
d-oit --crtrc d1 out :c o por g&quot;&quot;&apos;^ jalromont - ontvgmVii quo dans 1r o   f oo-tifdo 150/000-liOiireic^ to Or umri^^oliaoi scat oon^cis loa10,000 hommoo autoriso? par la Commission intwrallies do c,ontrolo pour lo polico do la rJ^6*nqu&apos;i;ro-augmentation do 1&apos;Or&amp;nungspolizol no: portora dUiillours isi stir ios torritoiros do la rive gaucho du Rhin, oii la Haut Commission dos torritoires -rhon&amp;ns a seulo qualito &apos; pour  ixor les offootifs nocossairos, ni sur, los regions Boumisos au plebiscite .a moins qfdft-los Commission intoral1 lioos da oontrolo ot do plobiscito no lo demandant expresso-n&amp;ntaEnfin lf augmentation dos offoctifs do 1&apos;Ordnungstolizei so poursuivro au fur ot a closure do la dissolution do la Bioharhaitpolizod.Astaoun moment, 1T onsomble dos offoctifs do la Sicliornoitspolizoig1j do 1* JrdnungspoliSsi no pourra $epasoor 150,COO hommcs.Par contra, les Puissanoes ont domando dSautorisor1 lo Gourornorartallomanil commodities il on a adrosfio la aemando a la Commission doControle do portor de 12,000 a 17,00* los affootifs io la gondarmorleGcuvtrneaientlas Allies tionnont a cttiror lrattention du Gcurromcnt allem&amp;nd sur lefait quo durant los trois mois qui s^ecouler-cnt a partir do 1T-*nvoi de la presento note avant la dissolution-ticn dofinitivo      -a -.:diitair.M de la iiichorhoitspolizoi, ils na poursaient afimettre quo dc?fe militaires- proveant do la Reichswhor-; puissant- cntso incorporos a la Sichorhoitspolizei;   los offoctifs aotuols de collo-oi constituent un maximum qui doit otre progrossivement roduit. -La Commission militairo Interalliao do controle a qualito pour survoillor 1Tapplication do oos Sivorsos mqsuroS. Collos-ci sont de nature a dennor ontioro satisfaction aux  . domaridos lagitimos du Gcuvornonont alletaand.Agrees, Monsiour lo President, les assurances de ma .hanto censideration. .June 21 1920.

</content>
</cab>
