<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/108/0 images: 111-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
39(1p p 1 5 5^^OWERS   OF   THE   MINISTRY .0F JoHIPPING.1. The main powers *f the Ministry of Shipping expire onAugust 31st of this year, and tho Ministry itself ntust, under -        v Section 13 of the New Ministries and Secretaries Act, 1916, cease to exist twelve months after the conclusion of the war. or at such earlier date as may be fixed by Order in Council,2, The Shipping Controller had anticipated that no reason wouldexist for which he would require to recommend that Parliament bo asked to continue the powers of the Ministry but under conditions as they are today he hesitates, and desires to state a few facts, for the consideration of the Cabinet, and their decision (A)        The Government still continues to have theresponsibility for supplying the principal food requirements of the country, viz,, wheat and sugar. (3) &apos;      The Country is still at war with Turkey, and it appears probable that movement of troops, transport, etc,, may require to continue for some time in connection therewith.(C) (      Following on tho War there still continues considerable movements of troops to carry f,utA specially in the Eastern Mediterranean, Mesopotamia, etc,(D) Repatriation of ex-Enemy and Allied personnel, Poles ,   Czecho-Slovaks, etc,, mainly from India, Mesopotamia,the Black Sea, Far East and Baltic. (S)        While at the moment congestion at ports is not serious, the summer is the time when traffic is always easier, but as winter approaches the position may become difficult.    It is estimated in a general way that port working hours of labour have been reduced about 30$.and there seems no prospect at present of getting back to conditions which, existed pre-war. To secure equal labour results in port, would mean increased shifts of men,to compensate for shorterhours/
2. ,     9ihours (even if labour Unions were agreeable)., but in many ports men are not available.Coal control still continues and shipping has been called on to&apos; supply much more tonnage to meet the country&apos;s requirements in connection with United Kingdom coasting needs than before the -war.    Since the Armistice freight on all such coal carried hasbeen limited,.Dangers exist of -labour troubles and strikes, and after 31st August the Government will have no power under which any control can be exercised on shipping. General unrest world-wide.Under normal conditions there is no doubt that ample tonnage is available in a general way for the requirements of the c ountry. There-is more shipping afloat today than ever in the world&apos;s history and our shipbuilding yards are daily increasing the supply.    Further, although the great bulk of the German tonnage ultimately to be allocated to us is now at our disposal,, there is still a considerable quantity not yet, delivered,,  If tho Cabinet decide to ask Parliament to continue the necessary powers, a new Bill is required,, which could be so expressed that the powers could be exercised either under the Ministry of Shipping Gr by the Board of Trade, on whom any work remaining after the expiration of the Ministry of Shipping.will no doubt devolve.The form   of Bill required is annexed hereto, in case the Cabinet&apos; decide that the extended powers be asked for.The Shipping Controller takes this opportunity of bringing before the Cabinet the position of the Ministry in regard to ex - 3NEMY TOMAGS. It is anticipated that about 350&apos; vessels of varying sise will come to Britain but up to now the Reparation Commission have not made final decision or intimation.
JSo far as possible particulars of the expected tonnage have on collected by the Ministry of Shipping to prepare for prompt sales * Meantime there has been a heavy fall in values, which becomes eater day by day.     Sales have almost stopped and there will be serious ffficulty in disposing of so much tonnage and very considerable credit 11 require to be givon to effect sale3.It is further to be borne in mind that considerable new tonnage s now going into the water and there is very much more shipping afloat 3-day than ever in the world1 s history, while trade is enormously res-rlcted.Nothing has kept back a debacle in the freight market except ongestion delays and other difficulties following the war, and to some &apos; xtent those difficulties are promising to disappearsRailway Companies and Port Authorities are gradually improving heir position in which they are helped by the greatly reduced imports d exports, but supposing this country was able shortly to get bask o pre-war conditions in the way of quantity of imports and exports, the osition would be most serious, as it would be quite impossible to overtake he work in consequence of shortened hours of labour, lack of port accommodation, and in many ports, a shortage of men to increase the limber of working shifts.It is unfortunate that the decision relative to the flstribution of these ships has been so long withheld.The Shipping Controller has previously stated to the Cabinet, the osition, and specially his views relative to prices.    In a former emorandum (CP. 1269) dated 12th May, he called special attention to the ecossity that this country should have it clearly established that the [rices to be paid to the Reparation Commission should be the sale prices ctually realised in this country, and if this is departed from.it may be j ticipated that there will be a very heavy loss to the country.The Shipping Controller, in view of the situation, considers the only sound course is to attempt to bring in the British shipj^ing
- joirmiuiiity as a whole as purchasers and with this in view he has approached Lord Inchcape. who has express-ed, Jaly Trt 1.11 nffl^e^^&quot;^md^rtake*lie sale, (and the management ponding the sale) of the ex-enemy vessels, .for the &quot;benefit of the Government. / 1Lord Inchcape would accept no personal remuneration or profitin sales, bat his Lines would continue to., receive, as at present, the ordinary management remuneration for any of. the vessels, which they maylontinue to manage *The Treasury has approved of this course being adopted and theShipping Controller hopes shortly to have matters finally adjusted withtord Inchcape*The previous transactions arranged through. Lord Inchcape have -been of the most satisfactory character and all are finally concluded,Every ship in which the Shipping Controller was interested has low been sold, and the Ministry has also during the recent months sold iany small craft built for the Admiralty during the wan, adaptable for mercantile purposes, and which alone have realised about 4 millions of roney.It is very imperative   before a further decline takes place that all pressure be put on the British representatives&quot;by the Cabinet to put us in a position to sell.-A number of large German Passenger ships: are already lying up at considerable expense waiting disposal.Pending authority&apos;the Shipping Controller cannot make headway.(Sgd) J.P. MACLAY.4. 6.1920.
[10 &amp; 11 Geo. 5.]   Ministry of Shipping (Qontinucmoe). 1DEAE Top a bill to continue temporarily the  office and powers  of the a.d. 1920. Shipping Controller and to make further provision with respect to his powers and for purposes in connection therewith.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same., as follows: 5       1. (1) Subject to the provisions of this Act, the provisions Continuance of the New Ministries and Secretaries Act, 19.16, so far as they gy^J^ relate to the Shipping Controller or the Ministry of Shipping ConBer. shall, notwithstanding anything in  that or any  other Act, 6 *7 Geo.5-continue in force until the day of nineteen10 hundred and provided that-(a) the purposes of the Ministry of Shipping shall, in lieu of the purposes specified in section five of the New Ministries and Secretaries Act, 1916, or any15 other provision relating to the purposes for or inrelation to which any of the powers of the Shipping Controller may be exercised, be the organisation and maintenance of the supply of shipping in the national interest, and the control20 and regulation of any shipping available for theneeds of the country in such manner as to make the best use thereof having regard to the circum-stances of the time; and 198-1
2 Ministry of Shipping (Contimianoe).   [10 &amp; 11 Geo. 5.](b) nothing in this section shall be deemed to continue any power of making regulations under (the Defence of the Realm (Consolidation) Act, ;&quot;1914.(2) The Shipping Controller shall, during the continuance of his office, have and exercise all the powers possessed by him 5 at the time of the passing of this Act under Eegulations 39bbb, 39cc, 39dd, [and 39jt] of the Defence of the Realm Regula-tions, which regulations shall have effect as though set out in this Act; and the provisions of the War Emergency Laws (Continnance) Act, 1920, so far as they provide for the con- 10 tinuance of or relate to those regulations shall cease to have effect.Any orders made by the Shipping Controller under any of the said regulations and in force at the date of the passing of this Act shall unless and until varied or revoked continue in 15 force and have effect as though  made under  the  powers conferred by this Act.(3) His Majesty may by Order in Council provide (a) for the transfer of all or any of the powers of theShipping Controller under this Act to some other 20 Government Department or  Departments  if  it appears to him that those powers could be more satisfactorily exercised  by that  Department  or those Departments if so transferred ; and(b) for the discontinuance of all or any of the powers 25of the Shipping Controller before the date fixed by this Act if it appears to him that the exercise of those powers is no longer necessary.2. If after the passing of this Act any person is guilty of an offence or a summary offence under any of the regulations 30 specified in the last preceding section of this Act, or against any order continued by this Act or that may be made under any of the said regulations he shall be liable on conviction under the Summary Jurisdiction Acts, to imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term not exceeding three months or 35 to a fine not exceeding one hundred pounds or to both such imprisonment and fine:Provided that a prosecution for any such offence shall not in England or Ireland be instituted except by or with the
[10 &amp; 11 Geo. 5.]  Ministry of Slapping [Continuance). 3consent of the Attorney General for England or Ireland as the A.D. 1920. case may be, or by an officer of the police or by a person-acting under the authority of the Shipping Controller.3. This Act may be cited as the Ministry of Shipping Short title. 5 (Continuance) Act, 1920.
Ministry of Shipping (Continuance);DRAFTOF A15   I   L   LTo continue temnorarily the office and poweis of the Shipping Controller and to make further provision with respect to his powers and for pur-poses in connection therewith.CLXXV.   (1.)2-1 f/i June 1920.198-1

</content>
</cab>
