<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/108/0 images: 554-599</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^flAUd^flDENTIAL.New Series, Vol. II, No. 2.     10.7.20.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government.!MINISTRY OF LABOUR.WEEKLY REPORT.10th July, 1920.PART I.-THE LABOUR SITUATION. PART II.-THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY.Prepared by Intelligence Division.CONTENTS.Part I.-The Labour Situation. Week ending the 7th July, 1920.The General Situation General Survey of the Week Unemployment Position ...Features op the Week-General TopicsIndustrial and Other Organisationspage42 4242 44Features of the Week continued.Trade Union Topics......International Relations of LabourNegotiations and Disputes-Demands and Negotiations Strikes and Lock-Outs Settlements and Agreementspage48 4849-5052Part II.-The Work oe the Ministry. Week ending the 3rd July, 1920.Employment Department  - pageEmployment Exchanges......... 53Local Employment Committees...... 56Out-of-Work Donation and Unemploy-ment Insurance Benefit        ...... 57Discharged and Disabled Sailors andSoldiers   .........     ...     ... 57Juvenile Branch   .........     ... 58Appointments Department Appointments and Training      ...... 60Training Department-Ex-Service Men   ......     ...... 61Women&apos;s Training.........     ... 66Apprentices and Boys    ......     ... 68Finance Department-Out-of-Work Donation    ......... 70Unemployment Insurance        ..,     ... 70 (b 16259)  12  U75 7/20 H&amp;SIndustries Department  Industrial Councils Division  Joint Standing Industrial Councils-Negotiations     ............Reports   ...     ...     ...     ...     ...Works Committees     .........Interim Industrial Reconstruction Com-mittees Reports...............Trade Boards Division Proceedings of Trade Boards    ......Fixing and Variation of Minimum Rates Establishment and Amendment of Trade BoardsWages and Arbitration Department Awards     ......     ......     ...Agreements and Settlements     ......Committees, Conferences and Deputations Questions Pending and Miscellaneous   ...Appendix Questions in Parliament  ......Debates in Parliament    ,,,page70 70 737374 76767677-77.78
PART L-THE LABOUR SITUATION.THE GENERAL SITUATION.General Survey of the Week.The most&apos; important disputes which began during the week are the strikes of building operatives and electricians employed at the London Bocks. The strikes which were threatened a fortnight ago, affecting gasworkers, provincial compositors, Scottish bank clerks and Essex farm labourers, may be said now to have been averted. Considerable discontent exists among engineering workers, both skilled and unskilled. This lends particular signi-significance to the periodical hearing held by the Industrial Court on the 29th June. The position in the building trades remains difficult: the strikes in Sheffield and Scotland continue. Sir David Shackleton has been dealing with the latter strike in the course of the week. The advances which have been recently granted in some areas to building trades workers are having a disturbing effect on other trades.The annual delegate meeting of the National Union of Railwaymen opened at Belfast on the 5th July and the annual conference of the miners Federation of Great Britain at Leamington on the 6th July, and are still in session. These are among the most important trade union conferences of the year. Both conferences have to make wages decisions with which the Government are directly concerned, and both have before them the Government schemes for the permanent post-war organisation of their respective industries. The most important event in the near future is the holding of the special Trades Union Congress on the 13th July.The Royal Assent to the Increase of Rent and Mortgage Interest (Restrictions) Act, on the 2nd July, and the coming into operation of the new National Health Insurance Act on the 5th July, are both of considerable importance from the Labour point of view. The House of Commons entered upon the Report Stage of the Unemployment Insurance Bill on the 2nd July.*The Unemployment Position.The number of H.M. Forces and Merchant Seamen out-of-work donation policies current for the week ending the 25th June was 174,224, made up of 173,243 lodged by men, and 981 by women. On the 18th June there were 181.872 policies current, 180,801 by men and 1,071 by women.On the 25th June, 67,410 unemployment books, 46,609 for males and 20,801 for females, remained lodged by workers under the Unemployment Insurance Acts. Corn-pared with the previous week when there were 45,027 books lodged by males and 20,822 by females, the total increase is 1,561.The total live register for all Employment Exchanges on the 25th June was 242,002 men, 47,138 women and 20,409 juveniles, compared with 248,773 men, 47,362 women and 20,894 juveniles a week ago, and 264,199 men, 43,749 women and 20,196 juveniles a month ago.  A detailed analysis of the unemployment position will be found on page 53.FEATURES OF THE WEEK.General Topics.. Ireland, Russia and Hungary. Of the problems connected with these three countries, which are closely connected because the issue of &quot; direct action &quot; has arisen on each of them, the Irish question continues to be the one of greatest current interest to the British Labour movement.* See page 84 below.
4310.7.20,(B 16259)Such officers are, however, employed in other Exchanges.It is reported that both the National Union of Railwaymen and the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain have prepared resolutions for submission to the special Trades Union Congress which is to meet on the 13th July. The resolution of the first-named body expresses the opinion that the present situation in Ireland, for which the Government is blamed, demands the immediate consideration of the whole trade union movement and &quot; does not warrant any section of the workers being allowed to fight alone a&apos;battle for freedom.&quot; The resolution concludes by calling for an Irish truce, the Government to withdraw the &quot;Army of Occupation&quot; and the Irish people to stop&apos;all murder and outrage, whereupon the Government should open an Irish Parliament, with full Dominion powers in all Irish affairs, and with adequate provision for protecting minorities. The resolution of the Miners&apos; Federation, as reported, makes many protests against the policy of the Government but offers no definite suggestions.In Ireland itself the movements reported illustrate the serious effects which the present situation may have upon the Irish and British trade union movement. In Ulster, an Ulster Workers&apos; Union is being strengthened by Protestant secessions from the Irish. Transport and General Workers&apos; Union. In Dublin a meeting on the 4th July was attended by representatives of 18 trade unions, and. a scheme was approved for the establishment of an Irish Federation of Trade Unions. The purpose of this proposed federation is to encourage the breaking away of those Irish trade unionists who are members of British trade unions. A central fund based upon a general levy on Irish trade unions is contem-plated, which will be used for organising purposes and to compensate those who may suffer financially from secession. It is not possible to judge the strength of this movement. The lead is being taken by engineers. The Irish members of the National Union of Railwaymen took no official part in this meeting.The remaining members of the British Labour Delegation to Russia returned to this country on the 30th June. The special Trades Union Congress will deal with a second interim report of the delegation, not with the final report.The boycott of Hungary ordered by the International Federation of Trade Unions has had no direct effect upon the Labour situation in this country.. Its indirect effects, in enhancing the prestige of the International Federation, in testing the double basis, industrial and national, of their organisation, and in providing a further example of direct action, are important.  The position of the Federation is dealt with in greater detail below.A small deputation representative of the Labour Party and the Trades Union Congress waited upon the Prime Minister on the 30th June, and discussed with him the Russian and Hungarian questions.Employment Exchanges.-The Committee of Inquiry into the working and adminis-tration of the Employment Exchanges heard further public evidence on the 29th June and the 6th July. On the 29th June, Mr. H. Wolfe, C.B.E., dealt chiefly with the difficulties in the formation and working of Joint Industrial Councils as illustrating the problems of demarcation and co-ordination which would be involved in the industrial control and administration of the Exchanges and unemployment insurance. Professor A. R. Wright, chairman of the Gateshead Employment Committee, referred to the growing complexity of the Employment Exchange system, which he thought had forced the essential point of finding employment rather into the background. If all trades were organised they could very well deal with unemployment and unemployment benefits, and the Employment Exchanges might stay for statistical purposes. Sir James Urquhart, ex-chairman of the Dundee Employment Committee, expressed the view that there was sufficient work to justify the existence of the Exchanges but that the essential factor of their success, the co-operation of employers and employees, had been missed. They must be entirely reconstituted with a view to securing &quot;this necessary co-operation. Local Employment Committees ought either to be abolished, or to be given real charge and supervision of the Exchanges.On the 6th July evidence was given by Mr. G Mowlem Burt, of Messrs. J. Mowlem &amp; Co., Ltd., Viscount Burnham, Mr. Ben Turner, and Mr. P. Rockliffe. Mr. Burt criticised the staffing of Exchanges with officials of purely clerical experience and described by way of contrast and appreciation the organisation of the Central Building Trades Exchange, Tavistock Street, London, which was, so far as his. knowledge went, the only one where technical officers were emplo)Ted.* Viscount Burnham agreed with the former witness on the point of employing technical officials but declared that he knew of no machinery which would deal so effectively with unemployment as the Exchanges, and considered it
The National Union of Clerks are not affiliated to this body.would be disastrous if there were any diminution in their activities. He objected to employment being placed almost entirely in the hands of the trade unions, as was the case in the printing trade. Mr. Ben Turner, president of the General Union of Textile Workers, suggested that trade unions should be given executive powers for dealing with unemployment through the Exchanges and the staff placed under their control. Mr. P. Kockliffe, secretary of the Joint Committee of Friendly Societies, also gave evidence.The Cost of Living. The sub-committee of the Joint Committee of the Labour Party, the Traeles Union Congress and the co-operative movement, who are inquiring into the causes of high prices, met on the 30th June and decided to begin their work by an inquiry into international finance and the operation of foreign exchanges. The sub-committee hope that several experts on international finance will be willing to give evidence.A meeting organised by the National Alliance of Employers and Employed at Wigan on the 2nd July is reported, at which a local inquiry into the causes of high prices and the means available for their reduction to a reasonable level was determined upon, if trade unions were willing to appoint representatives for this purpose to work with the employers.The decision of the General Federation of Trade Unions to appoint a body to conduct an inquiry into high prices is noted below.Cornish Tin Mines. The refusal of the Board of Trade to give financial assistance to the Cornish tin mining industry was communicated to the secretary of the Joint Industrial Council for the industry on the 30th June. The Dolcoath Mine Company discharged 135 men on the 26th, partially carrying out the notices to their 680 employees, and other discharges will follow. The position at the Grenville and the Tincroft Mines is similar. Pumping machinery is being withdrawn from the lower levels. At Dolcoath the &quot; tributers &quot; or piece-workers will be allowed to work their pitches, but will no longer . be financed by the mine. A special meeting of the Industrial Council was held at Cam-borne on the 5th July, but nothing has yet transpired as to its proceedings.Trade Unionism in Wales. Trade unionism in Wales, and especially in South Wales, has in recent months been characterised by two general tendencies one to take unofficial strike action, and the other to break away from unions with English headquarters.The second tendency has been noticeable among miners and clerks. There is nothing further to report with regard to the South Wales miners&apos; ballot on the question of con-tinued affiliation to the Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain. The Welsh branches of the National Union of Clerks, on breaking away from the parent organisation, have endeavoured to form a federation of semi-independent guilds catering for Welsh, clerical workers. The most important of these proposed guilds-the Mining, Clerical and Administrative Workers&apos; Guild has been formally constituted, and Mr. Ben Griffiths, who led the Welsh defection, has been appointed general secretary. The Guild are endeavouring to secure the estab-lishment of a Joint Conciliation Wages Board for colliery clerks, and affiliation to the National Federation of Professional, Technical, Administrative and Supervisory Workers.^ Difficulties have, however, been experienced owing to the National Union of Clerks taking legal action to protect their property in Wales, and it is reported that trade union and labour influences have been at work to bring about a rapprochement.Writh regard to unofficial strike action the officials of the South Wales Miners&apos; Federation, have recently been conducting an informal campaign throughout the coalfield against indiscipline. It is also reported that the trade union officials controlling general workers have formed an unofficial committee for mutual assistance. On previous- occasions when disciplinary action has been taken against any group of workers the result has often been a transference of their allegiance from one general workers&apos; union to another. It is understood that the new committee have reached an agreement whereby expelled members, as a rule, will not be accepted by any other union. The committee are also dealing with other questions such as conflict of jurisdiction.between unions, and co-ordinated action on wages questions. The position of the committee is informal and they have no official status.Industrial and Other Organisations.Trades Union Congress. The Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress adopted, on the 29th June, an interim report of the Trade Union Co-ordination Committee, dealing with the reorganisation of the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress.
It will be recalled that as a result of the railway strike last autumn the question of the reorganisation of the Parliamentary Committee, which had been in the air for some time, became a matter of urgent importance. As a result of preliminary investigations by a sub-committee of the Parliamentary Committee, who consulted representatives of the so-called Mediation Committee, which the railway strike brought into existence, and the trade union side of the Provisional Joint Committee of the National Industrial - Con-ference, a resolution was submitted to the special Trades Union Congress on the 9th and 10th December, 1919, instructing the Parliamentary Committee to revise the standing orders of the Congress so as to substitute for the Parliamentary Committee a Trades Union Congress General Council.The Parliamentary Committee were instructed to prepare a scheme for the compo-sition and election of this General Council and to make arrangements for the development of the administrative departments in the offices of the Council. Further, they were instructed to consult with, the Labour Party and the co-operative movement, with a view to devising a scheme for setting up departments of research, legal advice, and publicity, under joint control, for the service of the whole trade union and Labour movement.This resolution was adopted by the special Congress by a substantial majority, although it is of interest to note that it was opposed by Mr. J. Bramley and Mr. F. Hodges, the latter arguing that all the effective steps which the scheme included were already within the power of. the Parliamentary Committee to carry out without any constitutional change.In the present interim report the Co-ordination Committee deal with the first half of the terms of reference, namely, the reorganisation of the Parliamentary Committee. The primary recommendation of the Committee is the deletion of the words &quot; Parliamentary Committee &quot; wherever they occur in the standing orders of the Congress, and the substitution therefor of the words &quot; General Council.&quot; This change is something more than a mere change in title. It is proposed to give the new Council many more duties than those performed by the old Parliamentary Committee.As defined in the standing orders the duties of the Parliamentary Committee are to give assistance when it is desired to take a legal action of general interest to trade unionism as a whole to the House of Lords ; and to watch Parliamentary elections.In addition to these two duties the following are now suggested : (1) The General Council shall keep a watch on all industrial movements and shall attempt, where possible, to co-ordinate industrial action.(2) It shall promote common action by the trade union movement on general questions, such as wages and hours of labour, and shall have power to assist any union which is attacked on any vital question of trade union principle.(3) Where disputes arise, or threaten to arise, between trade unions it shall use its influence to promote a settlement.(4) It shall assist trade unions in the work of organising and shall carry on propaganda with a view to strengthening the industrial side of the movement.(5) Tt shall enter into relations with the trade union and Labour movements in other countries with a view to promoting common action and international activity.The method of election of the new General Council is to be radically different from the method of election to the old Parliamentary Committee. The constituent members of the Congress will be distributed into seventeen trade groups and the thirty members of the Council will be allotted to the various groups in proportion to their size. For example, there will be four representatives of general workers, three representatives of mining and quarrying, unions, railway unions, and the engineering, ironfounding and vehicle building unions. The nominations will be. made by the unions within each group, but the election will be made by the Congress as a whole.A more important change, however, is the sub-division of the Council into five groups or sub-committees, each of which will deal with a group of trades. Each group will elect their own chairman for sub-committee purposes, and it is recommended that a full-time official shall be appointed to specialise in the work of each group. It is hoped that the groups when formed will promote the closest possible contact with the Federations and other bodies representing the same interests outside the General Council, and the official attached to each group will be responsible for collecting and filing special information regarding the activities of the unions represented by the group. It is hoped ultimately that each of the sub-committees will develop into special departments in the offices of the General Council.
  It is recognised that these alterations and reforms, if they are to be efficient, will need the expenditure of more money on the part of the headquarters of the Trades Union Congress. The Committee suggest an affiliation fee of Id. per member per annum as the appropriate sum.National Union of Railwaymen. The annual delegate meeting of the National Union of Railwaymen opened in Belfast on the 5th July. Except for Mr. W. Abraham&apos;s. presi-dential address, and the discussion of the National Wages Board Award the proceedings of the conference have been held in private.Mr. Abraham condemned the action of the Government during the railway strike last year, but declared that the promise of assistance by the co-operative societies to the railwaymen was a fact of the greatest importance. He showed that the beneficial results of the strike were not confined to railwaymen-alone. Mr. Abraham defended the National Wages Board Award and declared that the time had now arrived for them to &quot; cease chasing each other round the vicious circle.&quot; They should reserve their power and prepare themselves, along with the other great industrial organisations, &quot; for the next movement in economic emancipation, namely, freedom from wage slavery.&quot; He expressed a hope that the constitution of the Triple Alliance would be so altered as to allow of prompt and definite action being taken when necessity arose. When a Government refused to carry out its pledges and deliberately did things it was pledged not to do, he was in favour of direct action, even should the Government concerned be a Labour Government. Mr. Abraham referred with pleasure to the more friendly relations which had recently subsisted between the National Union of Railwaymen and the Associated Society of Locomotive Engineers and Firemen, and expressed regret that similar relations did not exist between the Union, and the craft unions catering for railway shopmen.On the 6th July the conference discussed in open session the National Wages Board Award. Mr. J. H. Thomas made a statement on the situation. He pointed out two difficulties in the way of rejection. Representatives of the union had signed the report and could not repudiate their signatures. For the first time, representatives of railway users had taken part in framing an award determining railwaymen&apos;s wages and the award therefore must be treated with much greater respect than if it had been an agreement between the men and the companies. He didnpt like the differentiation between industrial and agricultural areas, but on the evidence submitted they had been forced to agree that it was right to differentiate. The only alternative to signing the report was a strike. He did not think they could have carried a strike. In the discussion resolutions were moved accepting the report, rejecting it, and accepting it with reservations. In his reply on the discussion Mr. Thomas referred to the recent French railwav strike, and stated that 20,000 men were still unemployed in consequence of that strike. It was ultimately decided to accept the award and to instruct the executive to secure its extension to the grades not covered.   In the critical division 42 votes were in favour of, and 18 against, the award.Miners&apos; Federation of Great Britain. The annual conference of the Miners&apos; Federation opened at Leamington on the 6th July. Except for Mr. Smillie&apos;s presidential address the proceedings were conducted in private. Mr. Smillie gave a brief review of the history of the Federation since the last annual conference, at Keswick. They had not succeeded in securing nationalisation of the mines because organised Labour did not see its way to take strike action on the issue. He was, however, fully convinced that the rank and file of the organised Labour movement, and the delegates who gave the decision of the special Trades Union Congress, were unanimously in favour of nationalisation. The miners were desirous of carrying Labour as a whole, and, if possible, the nation with them on this question, but on one point they claimed that their decision should be accepted without discussion, or opposition, namely that public ownership of the mining industry was in the interests of the safety of the mining community. With reference to the special Trades Union Congress which is to meet on the 13th July to discuss the Irish and Russian questions, Mr. Smillie hoped that the Congress would ask the Government to withdraw the military from Ireland and to let the people of Ireland settle their own affairs.Mr. Smillie then dealt with two matters of more domestic interest. The executive of the Federation had agreed that there was no necessity to increase the price of household coal by 14s. 2d. per ton. The Conference would be asked to put a demand to the Govern-ment for the removal of this increase and for an advance in wages to mine workers. If the Government refused to reduce the price of coal the miners would claim the whole profits of the industry in wages. Mr. Smillie also dealt with the Ministry of Mines Bill. He declared that the Bill was an attack upon the Miners&apos; Federation, who would not exist for
more than two years if this Bill passed into law. They could not again return to area, as opposed to national, wage negotiations. He warned the members of the con-ference that before they settled the matter of coal prices and wages there would probably be a very serious crisis. The conference&apos;then proceeded to discuss this question in camera, and it was announced that the discussion had not been completed when the conference adjourned until the 7th July.General Federation of Trade Unions. The annual conference of the General Federation of Trade Unions was held at Leamington on the 1st and 2nd July. Mr. J. Cross, of Accrington, presided and in his opening address protested strongly against the proposal to allow friendly societies to administer the unemployment insurance scheme. Jle regarded this proposal as an attempt to undermine the trade unions. He also criticised the scale of benefits proposed under the scheme. A resolution embodying this protest was carried unanimously and a deputation was appointed to interview the Minister of Labour on the subject.-Mr. John Hill, representing the boilermakers, proposed a resolution in favour of a 44-hour, week, and regretting the delay which had taken place in negotiating proper remuneration and conditions for overtime and night shifts in the engineering and ship-building trades, due to the employers&apos; insistence that these questions could only he settled in conjunction with the general acceptance of payment by results. Mr. J. Crinion, representing the card and bloving-room operatives, also opposed the reso-lution and stated that a reduction in hours would mean a reduced output and an inability to supply the world&apos;s requirements. Mr. H. Boothman, secretary of the Amalgamated Association of Operative Cotton Spinners and Twiners, declared that Mr. Crinion could not speak for the cotton trade in opposing the resolution. The resolution was carried with two dissentients.On the 3rd July the principal business transacted was the passing of a resolution on food supplies and the cost of living. Mr. Ben Tillett, M.P., opened the discussion and declared. that trade unionists, as a party, must appreciate the position and undertake some definite scientific investigation towards helping to. solve the problems. Higher wages supplied no solution and could not prevent higher prices. They were faced with the blackest outlook in the history of civilisation. Mr. Tilletfs resolution was that the Management Committee of the Federation be empowered to obtain the facts as to food and food supplies, examine them and report to the affiliated societies. His resolution was carried unanimously. Mr. Tillett replied to the argument that the Labour Party, the Trades Union Congress and the co-operative movement had already set up a joint commit-tee for this purpose, by stating that they would co-operate with this committee if invited, but as a federation they had a distinctive duty to do something in the matter.Details of the annual report of the Management Committee were given in this report last week. The new Management Committee elected at this conference was as follows :-J. Asquith (Amalgamated Machine, Engine and Iron Grinders&apos; and Glaziers&apos; Society), W. Bell (National Amalagamated Union of Labour), F. Birchenoughf (Amalgamated Association of Cotton Spinners and Twiners), J. Cross (Amalgamated Weavers&apos; Associa-tion), I. H. Gwynne (Tin and Sheet Millmen&apos;s Association), T. Mallalieu (Amalgamated Society of Journeymen Felt Hatters), T. Richards (National Union of Boot and Shoe Operatives), A. Shaw (National Society of Dyers, Finishers and Textile Workers), A. Short (Amalgamated Union of Shipbuilding, Engineering and Constructional Workers), Ben Tillett, M.P. (Dock, Wharf, Riverside and General Workers&apos; Union), and J. Young (United Garment Workers&apos; Trade^Union).National Federation of Blastfurnacemen, Ore-Miners and Kindred Trades. The annual conference of this body, meeting at Scarborough during the past week,funanimously decided to press for the][raising of compensation payable for fatal accidents from  300 to  600. After an address by Mr. John Hodge, it was unanimously resolved to protest against the amendment in the Unemployment Insurance Bill making all societies approved under the Health Insurance Acts eligible for participation in the administration of the unemployment insurance scheme. The chairman, Mr. H. Nixon, in moving a resolution urging the Government to bring forward schemes for the nationalisation of land, railways, mines, transport, shipping and banking, laid special emphasis on the need for the national-isation of finance.
United Vehicle Workers. The annual conference of the United Vehicle &quot;Workers opened at Nottingham on the 29th June.. The progress of business at the conference has been considerably impeded by discussions over the question of salaries paid to the union staff, and representatives of two newspapers were excluded from the conference on the 1st July on the ground of alleged incomplete and misleading reports of the pro-ceedings on this point. On the next day it was decided to appoint a committee of seven to deal with the revision of rules, a delegate assembly to consider and decide matters involving principles or policy for the guidance of the committee. The committee will chiefly consider the matter of increased contributions.Trade Union Topics.National Union of Police and Prison Officers.--The annual conference of this union has been held recently. Mr. J. Marston has resigned the presidency. Mr. J. Hayes continues to be general secretary of the union. The union are inviting trade unionists to send information which may be useful to them in. securing employment for their members. This last action is a considerable step towards an open acknowledgment of defeat.Trade Union Staffs Guild. A meeting of trade union clerical workers held under the auspices of this Guild of the National Union of Clerks is reported. The meeting demanded that the Parliamentary Committee of the Trades Union Congress should hold an inquiry into trade union office rates of pay and conditions of work, and that the union should convene a national conference of trade union clerks. A programme was adopted involving a salary scale for general clerks ranging from  250 to  400 per annum, a 35-hour week and 18 working days&apos; holiday per annum.Society of Post Office Engineers. The annual conference, of this association has recently been held at Shrewsbury, and the feeling of the conference as reported was in favour of the adoption of a policy of militant trade unionism, and of securing the widest possible working agreements or amalgamations with other Civil Service employees.International Relations of Labour.International Labour Conference. The International Labour Conference at Genoa, who are examining seamen&apos;s working hours and conditions of labour, are approaching the end of their labours. A report of their work will be given when accurate accounts of the proceedings are available.International Labour Office. The paragraph under this heading which appeared in this Report No. 21, 19th June, p. 7.13, giving an account of the meeting of the Governing Body of the International Labour Office on the 8th and 9th June at Genoa, requires correction. The request for an inquiry concerning the position in Hungary did not come from a Hungarian,labour representative, but from the Hungarian Government, and the Governing Body did not consent but declined to institute an inquiry into the alleged &quot; White Terror.&quot; The only thing the Governing Body had power to do was to make an inquiry into industrial conditions in Hungary, and they,instructed the Director of the Office to make this if the Hungarian. Government desired it. Further, it was, on the motion of the British representative on the Governing Body, which was supported by M. Thomas, that the question of the weekly day of rest was inserted in the agenda for next year&apos;s International Labour Conference.It was also decided at this meeting that a scientific inquiry should be undertaken by the Office into the question of production. The proposal came from the employers&apos; group, who wished the relations of production to the conditions of employment to be investigated. The proposal was supported by the&apos; workers&apos; group, on the condition, which was accepted, that all the factors affecting production should be considered.International Federation of Trade Unions. The proclamation of a boycott of Hungary by the International Federation of Trade Unions from the 20th June has led to significant developments with regard to the status of the International Federation. The Hungarian Government have entered into direct communication with the International Federation. Further, the attempt to operate the boycott through the international trade federations, rather than through the national constituent bodies of the International Federation,
NEGOTIATIONS AND DISPUTES.Demands and Negotiations.Mining and Quarrying.Coal Mines Rescue Brigade Men (Scotland). The Scottish coalowners and the National Union of Scottish Mine Workers have been invited to attend a conference under the chairmanship of Sir David Shackleton on the 15th July in connection with the dispute concerning the right of the miners&apos; unions to negotiate on behalf of rescue brigade men.(B 16259) Gillustrates the character of the organisation of the International Federation. The boycott has been made effective through the co-operation of the International Federation of Transport Workers and the International Union of Postal, Telegraphic and Telephonic Workers, but this co-operation has depended on the active support of the workers in the countries surrounding Hungary. Before the enforcing of the boycott, the Inter-national Federation of Trade Unions addressed, on the 18th June, an appeal to the Hun-, garian Prime Minister for adequate guarantees for the immediate cessation of all terrorist action, and for the free development of the Labour movement in Hungary.Since the boycott has been put into operation passenger traffic across the Hungarian frontier has been suspended, and only charitable food supplies have been allowed to pass through on condition that they were destined for Hungarian children. The Christian Socialist unions of Austria, however, have strongly opposed the boycott, and so acute has been the resulting friction that the Austrian Government, in the interest of the safety of passengers, goods and rolling stock, decided on the 1st July to suspend the entire railway traffic from Vienna to the Hungarian frontier.On the 22nd June the Hungarian Government requested the International Federation of Trade Unions to send a delegation to Vienna in order to discuss the situation. Accord-ingly, M. Edo Fimmen, joint secretary of the International Federation of Trade Unions and secretary of the International Transport Workers&apos; Federation, accompanied by Mr. W. Appleton, general secretary of the General Federation of Trade Unions, Herr Hiiber, president of the Austrian Trades Union Commission, together with Czecho-Slovak and Yugo-Slav representatives, opened negotiations in. Vienna on the 27th with the Hungarian Government, who were represented by Dr. Gratz, the Hungarian Charge d&apos;Affaires in Austria. The negotiations lasted for three days and were presided over by Dr. Renner, the Austrian Chancellor. In the course of the discussions M. Fimmen stated that his Federation did not wish to interfere in internal Hungarian politics, but maintained that the blockade could not be removed until political and economic freedom had been secured for Hungarian workmen and the &quot; White Terror &quot; stopped. The substance of the final reply of the Hungarian Government has not yet been reported. It was conveyed by Dr. Gratz on the 30th. M. Fimmen expressed the hope that&apos; all the principles to which the Hungarian. Government had declared that they would adhere would be put into practice, and stated that he would report the course of negotiations to the Bureau of the International Federation of Trade Unions meeting on the 3rd and 4th July. It is reported that M. Fimmen considers the result of the negotiations unsatisfactory owing to the absence of a regular Government in Hungary. The Hungarian Cabinet resigned soon, after the starting of the boycott. In the meantime, however, Dr. Renner, the Austrian Chancellor, is attempting to secure from the new Cabinet in process of formation in Buda Pesth a declaration upon which to base further discussions with the International Federation of Trade Unions. Dr. Gratz insists that there have been no real negotiations with the International Federation, but that an explanatory meeting was arranged, as the Hungarian Government wished to persuade the Federation that their reasons for the boycott were based on wrong information. The whole incident is an illustration from the international sphere of the increasing complexity of the relationship between industrial and political affairs.
Metal, Engineering and Shipbuilding.Ironmoulders (National). The members of the unions catering for ironmoulders, core-makers and metal dressers have rejected the provisional agreement, which included clauses dealing with payment by results, by a majority of 11,490 to 8,216 votes. Systems of payment by results are at present in operation in some cases and these will not he affected by this decision. It was proposed in the rejected agreement that the unions and em-ployers should draw up a schedule of national conditions to which all existing or future systems of payment by results must conform. It was provided that such recognised systems could only become operative after consideration by the local trade union branch and with the consent of the union executive committee : an employer would not be allowed to introduce payment by results merely with the consent of his own employees.Unskilled Engineering Workers (National). At a meeting of the executive of the local branches of the National Union of General Workers, the National Amalgamated Union of Labour and the Workers&apos; Union, held at Sheffield on the 2nd July, it was decided to recommend the executive of the National Federation of General Workers to put forward a claim for a mjnimum rate of 2s. Id. per hour for all the lower paid workers in the industry.Iron and Steel Trade Workers. A divisional Council of the Iron and Steel Trades Confederation, meeting at Newcastle on the 3rd July, decided to instruct the executive council to claim a minimum of  1 per day for all workers employed in the industry, and full pay for all recognised holidays.Shipwrights (Clyde). Shipwrights on the Clyde are urging the executive of the Amalgamated Union of Shipbuilding, Engineering and Constructional Workers to call a national strike to enforce their claim for an increase of 3s. a day and an allowance for tools. Resolutions have been passed by practically all the Clyde branches of the union to cease working overtime meanwhile.Printing and Allied Trades. , .Printers (Lancashire). Members of the Manchester and Liverpool branches of the Typographical Association have decided to apply for a bonus of 10s. a week in addition to the national increase of 10s. which the employers have conceded.Transport.Tramwaymen (South Wales). The District Council for the Tramways Industry met on the 5th July to discuss the men&apos;s demand for a revision in the standardisation of wages. A deadlock was reached and it is possible that the threatened strike will take place shortly.Food, Brink and Tobacco.Brewery Workers (National). A conference of the unions concerned in the brewery trade, convened by the National Federation of General Workers, was held on the 1st July, in London, to consider a wages programme. It was decided to put forward a national claim for an all-round advance of 10s. a week with a minimum of  4 for men, and  2 for women workers ; time-and-a-third for night workers ; time-and-a-half for overtime ; and double time for week-end work; also for a fortnight&apos;s consecutive holiday each year. It was decided to include within the scope of the brewing industry all brewery workers, bottlers and those engaged in malting. Agreements which exist at present will be allowed to expire, but no new agreements are to extend beyond the 31st December. The conference also passed a resolution protesting against the employment of girls under 16 years of age in the industry.Miscellaneous Trades.Funeral Workers (London). Meetings are being held between representatives of the British Funeral Workers&apos; Association and the Workers&apos; Union in connection with the threatened strike of funeral workers and gravediggers in London. It is stated that the Workers&apos; Union are promising financial support.Strikes and Lock-Outs.Building and Allied Trades.Building Trade Operatives (Port of London). A strike of building trade operatives employed on construction in the London docks occurred on the 30th June owing to the
failure of the Port of London Authority to put into operation the award of the National Conciliation Board, dating from the 29th May, which granted further increases in wages and a 44-hour week.  Over 3,000 workers are involved.Carpenters and Joiners (Scotland). A conference convened by Sir David Shackleton was held at Glasgow on the 3rd July to endeavour to reach a settlement of the joiners&apos;&apos; strike. There were present representatives of the Scottish National Building Trades Federation (Employers); of the Scottish Committee of the Amalgamated Society of Car-penters, Cabinetmakers and Joiners ; and of the Scottish Building Trade Operatives&apos; Wages and Conditions of Service Board. Some progress was made towards a settlement and a further conference will be held.Metal, Engineering and Shipbuilding.Electricians (Port of London). Electrical workers employed by members of the River Thames Dry Dock Proprietors&apos; and Ship Repairers&apos; Association, in the Port of London, struck on the 1st July in support of their demand for the payment of the district rate of 2s. 3d. per hour. The association have refused to pay this rate. Between 600 and 700 are involved.Textile Trades.Lace Workers: Plain Net Section (Nottingham). Representatives of employers and workers from Nottingham, Derby and the West of England met at Taunton on the 6th and 7th July to discuss a national wages claim. It is expected that the workers who have been on strike at Nottingham since the 12th June will return to work pending the result of this conference. The Nottingham employers had refused to consider the local employees&apos; original claim for increased wages on the ground that it had not been made on a national basis. *Cotton Operatives (Stockport).-T!h.e employers in the fine cotton spinning industry have offered to pay a rate of l\d. per hour for night shift workers and an increase of 70 per cent, on piece-price lists, and this offer is being placed, before the doublers who have been on strike since the 12th May. The strikers demand an increase of 80 per cent, on piece-price lists. The employers originally offered to pay the 70 per cent, increase which was accepted by the other sections of the industry in May, but the doublers contended that they were the lowest rated class of workers in the industry and should receive a larger percentage increase.fClothing Trades.Tailors (London). The strike of tailors employed by Messrs. Thexton &amp; Wright, Ltd., London, which began on the 14th June against the introduction of a piece-work system, still continues.JWoodworking.Sawmillers and Woodcutting Machinists (Scotland). A conference was held on the 28th June between the executive of the Scottish Timber Merchants and Saw Millers&apos; Association and the Amalgamated Society of Woodcutting Machinists.^ As an alternative to arbitration on the original demand the employers made an offer of an increase of 2\d. per hour on existing wages to journeymen, with a minimum wage of Is. 10c?. per hour and an increase of l\d. per hour for apprentices, on condition that no further demands for wages be made for six months. The operatives&apos; executive were unable to agree to these terms, but promised to lay them before their members.Furniture Workers (Leeds District). The strike in the furniture trade in this district continues.  The employers renewed their offer of 2s. 2d. per hour, but this was again refused, 1 The men demand the building trade rate of 2s. 4d. per hour for skilled workers.  It is stated that most of the strikers in Bradford have obtained work in other trades.Food, Drink and Tobacco.Margarine Workers (Fulham). The threatened strike of employees of Messrs. Van den Berghs, Ltd., at Fulham, occurred on the 5th July in support of their demand for an increase of  1 per week. The firm state that if the workers insist on higher wages the works will have to be closed down.* See this Report No. 21,19th June, p. 718. f See this Report No. 17, 22nd May, page 568.I See this Report, No. 22, 26th June, p. 762.       $ See this Report No. 18, 29th May, p. 607.(b 16259) G 2
* See this Report, No. 21,19th June, p. 718.Agriculture.Agricultural Labourers (Cheshire). A strike of agricultural labourers began in Cheshire on the 5th July in support of a demand for a minimum of  3 a week ; a week of 54 hours in summer and 50 in winter; time-and-a-quarter for overtime, and time-and-a-half for Sunday work.Settlements and Agreements.Metal, Engineering and Shipbuilding.Wire-Workers (Birmingham). The wire-workers who struck in the Birmingham district on the 5th June* returned to work on the 5th July. An agreement has been reached whereby the employers guarantee a rate of Is Sd. per hour to male adult workers, and riddle makers will receive an increase of 25 per cent, on present piece-work prices. Separate committees of employers and employed are to negotiate for the adjustment of the wire-workers&apos; piece-work prices.Wire-Workers (Prescot). The workers employed by the British Insulated and Helsby Cables, Ltd., Prescot, who struck on the 23rd June, resumed work on the 5th July. The two men whose dismissal caused the strike have been reinstated.Public and Public Utility Services.Gas Workers (National). At a conference held on the 6th July of representatives of the workers&apos; section of the National Joint Industrial Council for the Gas Industry, members of the Regional Councils and the executives of the trade unions concerned, a resolution was passed accepting the employers&apos; offer of an increase in wages of Is. per day or shift; a week&apos;s holiday with pay, subject to certain conditions ; and improved overtime rates. Strike notices were withdrawn and executives of the unions were recommended not to sanction a strike which aims at repudiating the agreement. It was also decided that the Negotiating Committee should continue in session in order to settle any differences that might arise out of the interpretation of the agreement.Instructions had been issued to suspend strike notices until after the conference on the 6th July. These orders were disregarded at Bradford, Margam and Briton Ferry, and strikes took place. At Bradford and Margam the men were persuaded to resume work almost immediately.Agriculture.Agricultural Labourers (Essex). The threatened strike of agricultural labourers in Essex who are members of the Workers&apos; Union will not take place.Miscellaneous Trades.Piano Workers (London). After prolonged negotiations a settlement has been reached in the piano workers&apos; dispute which led to a strike on the 11th April, the workers protesting against the application of a bonus system. Work was resumed on the 7th July, on the conditions existing when the strike began, and a ballot is to be taken within three months as to whether wages in the industry shall be paid on a time-work or a bonus system.[Other disputes, negotiations and settlements, are referred to in the Wages and Arbitration Departments section of the Report, pages 76 to 79.]
PART IL-THE WORK OF THE MINISTRY.EMPLOYMENT DEPARTMENT.EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES.The Unemployment Position.The following table shows the work of the Exchanges in respect of registrations vacancies and placings during the week ending the 25th June&apos;: *	Men.	Women.	Boys.	Girls.	Total.Registrations 		4?,362			On live register at beginning of week   ...	248,773		10,259	10,635	317,029Fresh applications      ......     ......	34,204	15,808	4,130	4,289	58,431On live register at end of week.........	242,002	47,138	10,085	10,324	309,549Vacancies 					Brought forward from previous week   ......	38,170	43,166	6,704	10,297	98,337Fresh notifications        ............	12,182	9,460	2,745	2,425	26,812Carried forward at end of week.........	38,432	42,272	6,695	10,205	.97,604Placings       ............     ......	8,927	5,789	1,953	1,729	18,398The following notes summarise the reports and returns received for the week ending the 25th June.Statistical. During the week the men&apos;s live register,has decreased by 6,771, and the women&apos;s live register by 224. The vacancies carried forward, exclusive of vacancies in suspense, show an increase of 67 as regards men and a decrease of 1,224 in respect of women. All the divisions show decreases in the men&apos;s register. The Exchanges showing the largest decreases are Bermondsey, Hackney, Reading, Bristol, Lincoln, Rotherham, Sheffield, Attereliffe, Blackburn, Middlesbrough, West Hartlepool and Edinburgh. The occupations chiefly affected by the decreases are those of engineering and steel trade workers, motor drivers, clerks, shop assistants, carmen, dock labourers, fishermen and general labourers. Increases in the register are reported from Tottenham, Leicester, Wolverhampton, Darling-ton and Elswick, the occupations chiefly affected being those of painters, platers and shipyard labourers.As regards the women&apos;s register, all the divisions show decreases in the live register, except the South-Western, the West Midlands, the Scotland and the Wales Divisions. The Exchanges showing the greatest decreases are Kings Lynn, Luton, Rotherham, Barrow, Middleton, Darlington and Newcastle. The occupations chiefly affected by the decreases in the women&apos;s register are those of clerks and domestic servants.Men&apos;s Employment.Industrial Developments. At Stourbridge&apos;Messrs. Jones &amp; Attwood, Ltd., have commenced the construction of an additional foundry which on completion will employ 40 moulders. Newark report that the building of the Kelham sugar beet factory is proceeding rapidly. At Ashton-under-Lyne the Twin Bobbin Machine Co., who have been experimenting with a new machine, are now about to commence its manufacture for trade purposes. The corn elevator at Eleetwood has been acquired by Messrs: Lever Bros., Ltd., by whom it is being converted for use as a fish curing and canning factory. A new match factory at Garston which is being erected for Messrs. Maguire, Paterson and Palmer, Ltd., is approaching completion. At Thornaby-on-Tees, Messrs. Whitwell &amp; Co., Ltd., ironmasters, have commenced the construction of new plant for the manufacture of artificial stonework. Llanelly report that a start has been made on the erection of a large foundry and engineering works.
Labour Reductions. Canning Town report that discharges are still taking place in most of the local factories, and that there is little prospect at present of an improvement in the labour situation. Lewisham report that the Royal Air Force Stores, at Kidbrook, discharged 100 men at the end of June. Bedford report that Messrs. Hinde &amp; Mann, Olney, boot manufacturers, are standing off a number of workpeople owing to slackness of trade, due in the main to the stagnant condition of foreign markets. At Kettering there is no improvement in the condition of the boot and shoe industry, but local manufacturers are doing all that is possible to avoid closing down entirely. The depression in this trade is also felt at Northampton, where Messrs. White &amp; Co. are closing down, the third firm to do so since the beginning of the year. Messrs. Miller Bros., Barnstaple, anticipate the discharge of about 25 per cent, of their workers, owing to a depression in the lace trade. The discharges from the tin mines in the Redruth district still continue, a further 200 men being due for discharge on the 2nd July. Blackburn report that the situation in the cotton trade is still unsatisfactory. Eight local mills remain closed. This report reflects the position of the Lancashire cotton trade generally.Shortage of Labour. The manager of the Central London Exchange for the Building Trades reports that there have been no new developments during the week. The difficulty of obtaining skilled operatives in the trades with which this Exchange is concerned is still as acute as formerly, with the exception of painters and plumbers, whose numbers on the live registers have increased somewhat during the week. This position is general through-out the country. The only other trade in which there is some degree of unemployment is that of electricians, a number of whom are drawing benefit.Reports still make mention of the shortage of moulders and core-makers. At Bolton sheet-metal workers, brass moulders, spindle-forgers and core-makers are in great demand. Glossop report that there is still a considerable shortage of calico weavers, and that very little can be done to improve matters. Two large local employers are willing, however, to take on disabled ex-Service men for training as calico weavers if a satisfactory scheme can be arranged. A number of ex-Service men have indicated their willingness to enter on a period of training, and representations have been made to the Training Department. At Coatbridge there is still a shortage of iron and steel moulders and puddlers. At Greenock there is an unsatisfied demand for coopers, shipwrights and moulders.Shortage of Materials. From Brentford it is reported that Messrs. Gwynnes, Ltd., Chiswick, engineers, have had to discharge 250 men owing to a shortage of materials, and work is delayed on the new Great Western Road owing to the same cause. At Cowes, Messrs. Gilbert, Campling and Co., Ltd., makers of motor scooters, have issued discharge notices to their workpeople, assigning as a reason the shortage of materials. At Earles-town, the Vulcan Foundry, Ltd., and Messrs. T. &amp; T. Vicars, have had to suspend a number of fitters and turners owing to their inability to obtain materials, chiefly steel castings from Sheffield. At Redditch the scarcity of castings continues to retard work in certain branches of the engineering trade. From Aberdeen it is reported that a large number of skilled and unskilled men could be absorbed in the shipbuilding industry if regular supplies of material were obtainable. Nearly all local firms have large contracts on hand which are being delayed owing to insufficient supplies. At Leith, where arrangements were recently made for an increased supply of materials from abroad, it is reported that ship construction is practically at a standstill owing to the shortage of material, especially steel plates. One leading shipyard require 600 tons per month, but are able to obtain only about 80 tons.   The firm complain that there is a large export of these plates.Miscellaneous. At Bristol, there is still an unusually large number of ex-Service men unemployed. On the 25th June the Divisional Controller received a deputation from 80 ex-Service men who had that day received final payments under their out-of-work dona-tion policies. The deputation demanded that payments should be continued pending further discussion on the subject. These demands were communicated to the Central Office, but as a continuance of donation can only be made with Parliamentary sanction, the department were unable to take any action. The position at Bristol has been serious for many months, and with the prospective stoppage of donation the situation is becoming critical.The manager at Boston has submitted a report on his efforts to recruit labour in connection with the agricultural May hirings. The hirings this year have, as usual, brought many employers to the Exchange. The farmers were., not at all eager to hire men owing to the high wages prevailing. Many seem disposed to carry on with the fewest number of workers possible, endeavouring to balance matters by a fuller use of machinery and labour-
saving implements. The supply of domestics has fallen off considerably owing to the superior attractions of work on the land, which is better paid and more popular than domestic work.Women&apos;s Employment.General Industrial Situation. The general position regarding women&apos;s industries &quot;has not changed during the week. Slackness is still reported by the. London Exchanges in connection with all factory work, and there appears to have been no recovery in the rubber, boot and shoe, and straw hat trades in the Midland, Northern and North-Western areas. There appears to be still alack of orders in the hosiery trades in the districts of Leicester, Ilkeston, Greenock and Kilmarnock, but Coalville report that although the demand for women workers in the elastic web and hosiery industry is considerably less, the trades are steady in that area.In the North-Western areas there is still a general demand for skilled weavers. Although there is less activity in the cotton trade in the areas of Chorley, Blackburn, Burnley, Darwen and Dewsbury, the towns of Royton and Stalybridge report that trade is good and that short time is in no case necessary.A general quietness in industry is being experienced in Scotland owing to the proximity of the Fair Holidays and it is expected that very few vacancies will be notified to the Exchanges until the holidays are over. It is noted, however, that the fishing industry at Inverness and Aberdeen is again in full swing.Domestic Service. During the last few weeks there has been no material change in the position with regard to the placing of women in resident private domestic service. In nearly all divisions Exchanges are making efforts to fill the large demands notified at seaside and other holiday resorts for seasonal domestic workers.In the London and South-Eastern Division there continues to be a large demand for resident domestic servants, and the supply is quite inadequate. There is, on the other hand, a good supply of daily domestic workers. Seasonal vacancies are being notified to the Exchanges and efforts are made to induce employers to accept applicants from a distance. The Great Marlborough Street Exchange have been successful in supplying seasonal workers for Herne Bay, Margate, Great Yarmouth, Skegness, Maidenhead and Southend.Posters of coast towns received from the South Midlands and Eastern Division are being exhibited in areas where there is a possibility of obtaining suitable applicants for seasonal work. At Folkestone the Exchange manager has circularised hotel and boarding-house proprietors urging them to accept inexperienced women, and it is hoped to arrange for a member of the Folkestone Chamber, of Commerce to select women at one of the London Exchanges.The South Midlands and Eastern Division report difficulty in filling ordinary resident domestic service vacancies, though vacancies for companion-helps are comparatively easy to fill. Difficulty is often experienced in persuading employers to consider applicants for seasonal workers from a distance. It is, however, sometimes possible to persuade the seaside employer to travel to supply areas to engage seasonal applicants. This plan has been successfully carried out in the case of Clacton and Lowestoft employers, who have personally engaged maids from the Colchester Exchange and others.In the South-Western Division consideration has been given to propaganda work in connection with domestic service. A scheme of co-operation has been instituted between the Barnstaple Exchange and certain Welsh Exchanges for supplying women for seasonal work. Bristol have submitted 12 inexperienced girls to Weston-super-Mare for seasonal work, and have been so successful in staffing the local Young Women&apos;s Christian Association hostel that all future vacancies occurring at the hostel will be notified to the Exchange. The Gloucester Exchange have sent out about 500,letters to the principal residents in the district drawing their attention to the large number of women requiring daily work, and a number of fresh orders have been notified as a result.Efforts are being made in the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division to stimulate the supply of domestic servants in the area of the Branch Offices, and as a result of these effort an increase both of registrations and of vacancies notified is reported from several Branch Offices.   In the West Midlands Division there are indications that women are showing less reluctance to take up domestic work, although there is still a large unsatisfied demand.The North-Western Division report satisfactory progress in recruiting for seasonal
work. Blackpool have placed 120 applicants from other districts ; unfortunately, however * 49 applicants failed to come forward after acceptance.In the Northern Division wages offered for domestic workers are considerably higher than they were a year ago. A scheme for the decasualisation of charwomen has been inaugurated by the Newcastle Women&apos;s Sub-Committee. A Daily Domestic Workers&apos; Brigade has been formed, and a panel of the sub-committee interview the workers and impress upon them the necessity for fulfilling the engagements which they undertake. Efforts are made by the Exchange to secure that members of the Brigade obtain employ-ment for each day of the week.In Scotland an acute shortage of domestic workers of all kinds still continues. Large numbers of seasonal hotel vacancies are being notified, and the Exchanges are achieving a fair measure of success in filling them.Wales also report many vacancies for seasonal workers. Colwyn Bay report that various employers who engaged applicants from the Midlands last year have approached the Exchange again with a view to re-engaging the same girls. Good placings in private residential domestic service are reported from Cardiff and Llandudno.LOCAL EMPLOYMENT COMMITTEES.Activities of Committees.. Employment and Resettlement. The Letchworth Committee report that owing to the local shortage of houses some 200 vacancies for skilled and unskilled engineering workmen cannot be filled. *The Deptford and Greenwich Committee recently held- a conference with the local Mayors and employers of labour to consider the local unemployment situation. The conference recommended, as one means of diminishing the existing unemployment in the area, that the Ministry of Transport should be requested to open the railway stations at present closed in the south-eastern area of London, to provide a much-needed improvement in travelling facilities.A short while ago the Gloucester Committee called attention to a supply of timber destined for Messrs. Morelands&apos; match factory which was being detained by the Belgian Government in Antwerp harbour, and requested the department to approach the Foreign Office with a view to the early deli very, of the timber. The Foreign Office have been in negotiation with the Belgian Government for the release of the material, and as the negotiations are now assuming a favourable turn it is hoped that the timber will.shortly be delivered.Training. The Cheltenham Committee recently made a special appeal to local nurserymen, seedsmen and florists, to co-operate with them in connection with training in horticulture. A ready response has been made, and four firms have undertaken to take men for training. - Sanction has been obtained from the Ministry of Agriculture for the proposed training schemes, and four men have commenced work. Others have been selected, medically examined and referred to the County Agricultural Executive Committee for approval.The Barnstaple, Exeter and Plymouth Committees are holding a meeting at Exeter to discuss the extent to which men can reasonably be absorbed in the tailoring trade in Devonshire and Cornwall, and the desirability of setting up other training centres.Ex-Service Men. A very satisfactory report has been received from Hull in regard to the state of the live register of ex-Service men. During the past four weeks no payments of out-of-work donation have been made, and only one payment during the four previous weeks. The committee recommended that this information should be published locally. The Ilkeston Town Council have notified the local committee that they propose limiting the placing of Council contracts to those persons or firms who have adopted the National Scheme. This decision may be varied, however, in special circumstances by resolution of the Council.The Ramsgate Committee are taking up with the general manager of the South-Eastern and Chatham Railway the case-of a disabled ex-Service man, recently employed as flagman to platelayers at Richborough, who had been dismissed to make way for an able-bodied man.Inverness are meeting with difficulty in placing ex-Service men in employment, owing chiefly to the non-industrial character of the district. Most of the men are unskilled. The committee suggest that the Admiralty, rather than dismantling a local base with good sheds and equipment, should advertise it for sale, as in the committee&apos;s opinion the buildings are suitable for industrial purposes.
Women. The attention of the Hull Committee has been drawn to the difficulty in filling vacancies &quot;for scrubbers, notified by the local Board of Guardians, owing to the low wages paid, namely, 4s. per day with food. The committee decided to draw the Board&apos;s attention to the difficulty and to suggest that the wages be increased to 6s. per day.Clapham Junction recommend that the training centres for women be carried on as continuation schools for girls requiring training in any special capacity, according to recommendation by the school mistress. Oxford are proposing to establish a recreation club for domestic workers.Miscellaneous. In connection with the adverse criticisms of Employment Exchanges which have recently appeared in a portion of the Press, Woolwich have appointed a deputa-tion to lay before the present Government Committee of Inquiry evidence in regard to the usefulness of Employment Exchanges, and more particularly in regard to the effective work accomplished by the Woolwich Exchange. Braintree and Chelmsford have also protested against these criticisms.OUT-OF-WORK DONATION AND UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BENEFIT. Payments Made.For returns of the amounts paid upon out-of-work donation policies and in unemploy-ment insurance benefit during the last week see the report of the Finance Department under this heading on p. 70 below.Work of the Courts of Referees.Out-of-Worh Donation Appeal Cases (Great Britain). During the week ending the 24th June, 1,783 cases were referred to appeals officers, 1,742 were heard by Courts of &apos; Referees, and 1,737 cases were outstanding.The total number of cases heard by appeals officers up to the 24tli June was 446,571. The total number of cases heard by the Courts was 418,374. An analysis of 405,699 cases heard shows that 107,889 claims were allowed, 297,266 disallowed, and in 544 cases a compromise was arranged. The proportion of disallowances to total claims heard was 73*3 per cent. Of the number disallowed 43&apos;1 per cent, were cases of refusal to accept suitable employment.Out-of-Worh Donation Appeal Cases (Ireland). During the week ending the 24th June, 58 cases were heard by the Courts, and five dealt with by the Appeals Officers, making a total of 63 cases disposed of at 18 sittings.The total number of cases heard by the Courts up to the 24th June was 25,597. An analysis of 24,421 cases heard shows that 7,411 claims were allowed, 16,910 disallowed, and in 100 cases a compromise was arranged. The proportion of disallowances to total claims heard was 69&apos;2 per cent. Of the number disallowed, 4T4 per cent, were cases of refusal to accept suitable employment.Unemployment Insurance Benefit Appeal Cases (Great Britain). During the week ending the 24th June, 131 cases were heard by the Courts of Referees and 125 cases were outstanding.The total number of cases heard since the 14th July, 1919, up to the 24th June, was 4,051. An analysis of 3,833 cases heard shows that 1,173 were allowed and 2,659 disallowed. In the remaining case a compromise was effected. The proportion of disallowances to total claims heard was 69&apos;4 per cent. Of the number disallowed, 30&apos;2 per cent, were cases of refusal to accept suitable employment.Unemployment Insurance Benefit Appeal Cases (Ireland). During the week ending the 24th June, 7 cases were heard by the Courts of Referees.The total number of cases heard up to the 24th June was 233. An analysis of 211 cases shows that 44 were allowed and 167 disallowed. The proportion of disallowances to total claims heard was 79T per cent. Of the number disallowed 65*3 per cent, were cases of the incidence of the trade disputes proviso.DISCHARGED AND DISABLED SAILORS AND SOLDIERS.National Scheme.Certificates have been issued to 18,123 employers enrolled under the scheme up to the 29th June. These employers have total establishments of 2,961,652 workpeople, and the undertakings cover 173,145 disabled ex-Service men. The figures show a large increase on those given last week, due mainly to the inclusion of figures relative to Governmentdepart-ments, the Treasury having now been added to the King&apos;s National Roll on their behalf.(b 16259) H
Further visits are still being made, generally with good results, to firms whose replies after the first visit in connection with the intensive canvass were not satisfactory.In the South-Western Division 167 firms have been enrolled as a direct result of the canvass. The record from the Plymouth area, however, is not satisfactory. In this district 300 firms were visited, but only 10 signed undertakings. Many firms have, however, promised to give the scheme every consideration, and such cases will be taken up again later.In the South Midlands and Eastern Division the work has been pressed forward, and a substantial increase in the number of undertakings signed and accepted is recorded.Platings.South Western. The figures for the month ending the 4th June show that 219 men were placed, an increase of 68 on the total for the previous month. The number of disabled men on the live register at the end of the two periods were approximately the same, 1,506 as against 1,510. It has been suggested that the placing of disabled men is becoming more difficult on account of firms already having their full quota, and also because of the high wages being paid to all classes of workers. Employers are very chary of taking on men who are not able to do a full day&apos;s work.South Midlands and Eastern. The special officer reports that the number of placings is by no means commensurate with the efforts made in the canvassing campaign. Many firms have been visited and undertakings obtained, but few fresh openings for employment of disabled men have resulted as the majority of the firms already have the agreed quota on their staffs. The Lowestoft Exchange, however, report the placing of a man suffering with heart trouble as a supervisor of the canvassing staff of a large firm of stationery manufacturers at  5 per week and all expenses. Bedford report the placing of a man with an arm paralysed through wounds, as a watchman at  3 per week, and another, suffering from chronic rheumatism, as an institution porter at  55 per annum with board and lodging. Ipswich report the placing at Ghimsby of a naval shipwright, with two figures amputated and an injured thumb, in his trade at the full local rate.JUVENILE BRANCH.Juvenile Employment Committees.Visits to Factories and Workshops. Under the direction of the Kilmarnock Juvenile Advisory Committee a successful round of visits has been paid by children leaving school to local factories and workshops. They were accompanied by their teachers, the Exchange manager, and the secretary of the committee.In all, 24 visits were paid, and practical information was given about employment in such industries as engineering, ironfounding, the manufacture of pottery and woollen goods, shirt making, printing, the supply of gas and electricity, and drapery warehousing. The West of Scotland Agricultural College was also visited.School-leaving Children (London). The London Juvenile Advisory Committee have been giving further attention to the difficulty of placing children quickly and suitably at school-leaving periods, particularly in such areas as Deptford and Woolwich, which are unfavour-ably situated for employment in Central London, and are still affected by the stoppage of war industries. The committee felt that the difficulty would best be met by further organising efforts in advance both on the part of local committees and employers. It was decided to ask the education authority to supply a list of school-leaving dates for next year, and then to approach employers by letter, through trade organisations and through the Press, urging them to engage their juvenile staff at school-leaving periods.Domestic Service. The Altrincham Committee make the following recommendations for domestic service. The employer to pay fares of girls sent for interview ; wages to be from 5s. per week at 14 years of age to 10s. at 17, in addition to board and washing ; girls not to work after 10 p.m.; at least nine hours&apos; rest to be allowed each night; one half-day to be allowed during the week; a half-day to be allowed on Sunday; a free period of two hours to be allowed each day ; two weeks&apos; holiday to be given each year; and a separate bed to be provided.The Edgware Road Committee have laid down the following conditions as their standard for girls placed in domestic service and also for boys placed in private houses :  Uninterrupted meal-times to be arranged; two half-holidays to be given each week, or, if preferred, one half-holiday and six hours in addition to be taken at suitable times;
(b 16259)H2opportunity to be given for girls to attend a place of worship every Sunday and in addition a half-day to be given on Sunday at least once a fortnight; a fortnight&apos;s holiday, with pay and board wages, to be allowed each year if twelve months&apos; service has been completed, and in other cases one week with pay and board wages ; a separate bed to be provided, the bedroom to be well ventilated and not in the basement, unless exceptional reasons exist; only light household duties, as a rule, to be performed after 5 p.m., and no service ordinarily to be expected after 9.30 p.m.; no girl to do heavy washing or to clean windows outside ; reasonable facilities to be given for girls to have visitors; and wages to be in accordance with the current rate in other occupations in the district.The Kings Lynn Committee consider that  12 per annum, or  15 if the uniform be not supplied, should be the minimum wage for girls, and the St. Helens Committee have scheduled rates from 6s. 6d. per week at 14 years of age, to 9s. 6d. per week at 17, as the minimum.Apprenticeship. Reports on the question of apprenticeship have been received from the Chester, Greenock and Worcester Juvenile Employment Committees. The use of indentures in Scotland is at present not usual, and the Greenock Committee are not prepared to express an opinion on this point. The Chester and Worcester Committees, however, recommend their use. They consider that five years should be the maximum period for an apprenticeship and favour a probationary period. An examination by the school medical officer at the termination of the school period would, the Greenock Committee consider, be of value. The Chester Committee suggest that, as most apprentices are engaged in establishments to which the Factory and Workshop Acts apply, the require-ments of those Acts regarding examinations by certifying factory surgeons might be made more effective. The Worcester Committee recommend that a schedule of processes to be taught should, where practicable, be prepared by employers to ensure a full training of apprentices, but the Chester Committee do not consider it desirable to make out a schedule showing what time is to be spent on each of the various processes.Difference of opinion is shown as regards periodical trade examination. While the Greenock Committee consider such examinations should be recommended, the Chester Com-mittee feel that the difference in the tests applied by the various employers would render examinations of little value for comparative purposes, and the Worcester Committee suggest instead that periodical reports on the progress made should be obtained from employers. Overtime, the Worcester Committee consider, should only be worked in definite cases of sudden emergency, but it is the view of the Chester Committee that, during the last two or three years of apprenticeship, a reasonable amount of overtime might be worked. Endorsement of the indenture on completion of the apprenticeship is recommended in both the Chester and Worcester reports, but, in the former, objection is taken to any statement of competence in such endorsement. Premiums are not considered necessary or desirable by any of the three committees, except in the case of pupilage where facilities are given to go through all the different departments and subsequently the offices. The provision of bonuses for the best apprentices is favoured by all three committees. Holidays are mentioned only in the Worcester report, which recommends payment for an annual holiday, in addition to the usual Bank holidays. The need for a local committee to deal with apprenticeship problems and disputes is recognised in all three reports. The Worcester Committee consider that the Juvenile Advisory Committees should deal with these matters, but the Chester Committee consider that their function in this direction should be consultative only.[Reference to matters of interest to the Employment Department will also be found on pages 42, 43, 47, 48, 64 to 66; 69, 71, 73 to 75, 77, 81, 82, 84 and 85.]
APPOINTMENTS DEPARTMENT.APPOINTMENTS AND TRAINING.Appointments.The figures relating to appointments are shown below : 	&quot;Week Ending 18th June.	Week Ending 25th June.	Total at 25th June.Candidates available for appointments 			Ex-Service men       ..................	874	736	14,897Civilians        .....................	52	27	2,551Vacancies 			Vacancies registered..................	644	699	66,324&quot; Live &quot; vacancies    ..................	1,800	1,822	 Candidates submitted to employers............	4,310	4,236	239,568Candidates known to have been placed       .........	558	526	34,821Of the candidates known to have been placed, 4,495 were placed through the agency of Interviewing Boards.Maintenance and Training Grants Scheme.Applications. The following summary shows the number of applications received in this department for training under various authorities : ; Applications for Training.Week Ending ] 8th June. &apos;Week Ending 25th June.Total at 25th June.Cancellationsand Withdrawals.Balance.Board of Education, England Scottish Education Department ..Irish Office...........Board of Agriculture, England .. Board of Agriculture, Scotland .. Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction, Ireland.. Appointments Department162 28 78 13 104225154 15514 2423137,099 8,262 1,330 7,488 1,580668 45,3442,754 1,475134 1,19861951 17,72534,345 6,787 1,196 6,290 96161727,619The total number of cases dealt with to date by Interviewing Boards in the United Kingdom is 25,598.   Of these, 21,533 have been recommended and 4,065 rejected.Grants Committee. The work of the Grants Committee in dealing with applications sent forward after recommendation is summarised in the following table: Applications.	Week Ending 18th June.	Week Ending 25th June.	Total at 25th June.Received........................	169	110	20,7 0Sanctioned        .........     ...	165	184	16,945Refused   ......     ..................	16	34	2,087Transferred to other Departments     ...     .........	 	14	524Cancelled after being received by Grants Committee	2	23	612Pending   ............     ......      ......			612
Appointments Department-continued.Training of Disabled Officers under Pensions Warrant. The total number of oases dealt with to date is 736, as shown in the following table : 	Sanctioned.	Abandoned Training.	Completed Training.	In Training.	Awaiting Training.Education Departments       ...... Agricultural Departments     ...... Ministry of Labour     .........	70 306 360	30	35 46 143	31 209 162	4 51 25Total     .........     ...	736	30	224	402	80Reports from Directorates. In the Perth Directorate a large percentage of the candi-dates now registering are asking for appointments as travellers or representatives. It is with difficulty that many of these candidates can be placed, as firms almost always require men with previous experience, who have a connection in the district in which they are to work.The Director at Cardiff reports that there are no vacancies or training vacancies available in shipping and coal export, and there are indications that many firms are about to reduce their staffs, as there is not sufficient work.In the Leeds Directorate the feeling of apprehension which exists in commercial and industrial circles has not abated, and the position in the textile industry is becoming par-ticularly serious. Many cancellations of orders and contracts are reported, and it is said that many of the smaller firms are already badly hit.A general depression in most trades is reported in the Birmingham and Midland district, but the engineering and allied trades are brisk, and conditions generally are favourable, although there is still a marked lack of skilled workmen. A number of firms report that until more skilled labour is available vacancies of an administrative and executive nature will not arise. Firms state that owing to the high prices at present prevailing, business in furniture and household goods is practically at a standstill. There has been a falling off in the number of vacancies notified during the week, and difficulty is being experienced in maintaining the recent high level of placings.The Director at Bristol reports that, in approaching training firms with regard to salaries for trainees, it is found that in many cases the firms are willing to pay, or to increase present salaries. General satisfaction is expressed at the progress which has been made by the candidates.In the London Directorate there seems to be a very distinct depression in trade generally, and employers are very unwilling to open out in any new ventures, or create new departments, and in consequence there is a great falling off in the number of vacancies obtained.TRAINING DEPARTMENT.EX-SERVICE MEN.General.Statistical-Oil the 30th June, 24,310 men were in training, as against 24,285 on the 23rd June and 23,388 on the 2nd June. On the 30th June there were 23,098 men awaiting training, the corresponding totals for the 23rd June and the 2nd June being 23,626 and 24,310, respectively.On the 30th June the number of men whose training had been completed since the 1st August, 1919, was 12,255, the totals for the 23rd June and the 2nd June being 11,78? and 10,740, respectively.
The net addition to the total number of men in training is 25 only, and both the Northern and Wales Divisions show somewhat considerable and unfortunate reductions. In the former case, however, these are to be accounted for by the fact that the present is a time of general holiday in the Newcastle district. Hence while there have been quite a number of terminations of training there have been no fresh, admissions. In the London, North-Western and Middlesex Divisions, among others, the numbers of men in training have again risen, and had it not been for the falling off in the Northern Division and Wales the week&apos;s record would have been at least up to the average.The waiting list shows a very substantial decrease of over 500 names, and this figure would have been still more satisfactory had it not been for an increase of 165 in the waiting list for Essex and East Anglia, due mainly to the discovery of additional names in the records of certain of the original secretaries to local committees in Essex. It may be mentioned that the waiting lists for the London and South-Eastern Divisions were reduced during the week by 328 and 157 names, respectively.A return of the men in training on the 31st May shows that of 23,191 men under-going training, 4,080 were in Government Instructional Factories, 8,950 in employers&apos; workshops, and 10,161 in other centres.Building Trades. The proposal to employ men in training in the building trades on house construction under the Brighton housing scheme has been further discussed, and it is hoped that a concrete proposal will be put forward for sanction at an early date.The possibility of undertaking the building of some of the houses under the New-castle Corporation housing scheme, on lines similar to those of the scheme already in existence in connection with the Garrison Lane Factory at Birmingham, is being investigated. The authorities are adopting a sympathetic attitude, and it is hoped that the scheme will shortly take concrete shape.Shifts Cooks. From East Anglia an interesting proposal has recently been received for training disabled men as cooks on board drifters, and the matter is being investigated in detail.Hostels. At the beginning of June, 18 new schemes for hostels, canteens and mess rooms and for accommodating residents in Government Instructional Factories were being dealt with. During the month the hostel at Wrexham has been opened ; that known as Hill Crest, at Birmingham, lias passed under the control of the Ministry; and a number of men have come into residence at Sarisbury Court. Of the remaining schemes two have been abandoned and two combined into a single scheme. On the other hand five fresh proposals have been submitted for consideration and action. .There remained, on the 30th June, 17 new schemes in hand. On the same date the Ministry were responsible for carrying on 10 individual hostels, including the hostel at Wrexham, for the management of which Mr. Oppenheimer is primarily responsible, the group of hostels at Birtley, and seven canteens, including that at Forbesfield, for the management of which the British Red Cross Society are responsible. At two factories of the residential type, Sarisbury Court and Barham House, Claydon, some part of the living accommodation is already occupied.Government Instructional Factories. The monthly statistical return shows that the number of factories on the active list, which increased from nine in October last to 13 in January, and 24 in April, had risen to 28 by the beginning of June, and the number of men under factory instruction had increased by over 3,000 in eight months. Eleven out of the 16 divisions now have men in training in Government Instructional Factories, the numbers ranging from 58 in the South Central Division to 669 in&apos; London. The five divisions which, as yet, have no training facilities of the Instructional Factory order, are the Ireland, East Anglian, South-Eastern, South Midlands, and Devon and Cornwall Divisions.At the Bristol Factory it appears that a large number of men are working 33 hours a week only. Up to the present men have presented certificates from private medical practitioners, which, would seem to be obtained with little difficulty. In future the Ministry of Pensions medical referee&apos;s certificate of fitness to undergo training -will be required, and, if during training the men are unable to work a normal week they will be further examined by the medical referee. If then certified as unfit to continue training in normal conditions their instruction will cease.Communications have been sent to all Divisional Directors calling their attention to the fact that the United Services Fund are prepared, in certain circumstances, to provide supplementary grants for recreative purposes at training centres,
0310.7$).409Progress can be reported with regard to the factory at Preston. The architect is arranging the work in such a way as to give occupation of the premises floor by floor in order that training may be started at the earliest possible date. It is understood that the second floor will be completed in about five weeks.&apos;A start on a very small scale has now been made at the Rochdale Factory.Treasury Sanctions.The following are among the most important of a number of proposals which have received Treasury sanction since the issue of the last Report.The purchase of watch and clock tools in Switzerland at a cost not exceeding  2,500, and authority to establish a credit at a Swiss bank to pay therefor, and payment of 5 per cent, agentfs commission on the invoice price of tools.The transfer from the Ministry of Munitions, at a price to be agreed, as between a willing buyer and a willing seller, of the premises known as Gormanstown Aerodrome, near Dublin.Schemes Sanctioned.During the week 13 schemes providing 156 places have been sanctioned. Included in this number are 30 places for training in engineering.Local Technical Advisory Committees.Building Trade. The inaugural meeting of the Workington Local Technical Advisory Committee, which also covers Whitehaven and Maryport, was held on the 30th June.The inaugural meeting of the Maidstone Local Technical Advisory Committee was held on the 1st July.\ The chairman and the secretary of the National Trade Advisory Committee attended a meeting of the Birmingham Local Technical Advisory Committee held on the 20th June, to obtain a settlement of the dispute which had arisen on the question of the area covered by the Local Technical Advisory Committee. The chairman of the National Trade Advisory Committee confirmed the fact that the National Committee has not at any time agreed that the Birmingham Local Technical Advisory Committee should cover the whole of the West Midland area, and drew attention to the letter sent to the committee by the secretary to the National Trade Advisory Committee in December last, pointing out&apos; that it was not desirable to enlarge the constitution of the committee as previously suggested by the Divisional Director. The committee, however, insisted that they had always been led to believe that they covered the larger area and had based their estimates of the number of trainees for Garrison Lane on that assumption. In view of the very strong views expressed by the Local Technical Advisory Committee, the chairman of the National Trade Advisory Committee decided that no good purpose would be served by pressing the matter at that meeting. The whole position will be reviewed again at the next meeting of the National Trade Advisory Committee.Printing and Kindred Trades. A meeting of the Joint Industrial Committee for the printing trade is to be held at Norwich on the 7th July, when it is expected to transform this committee into a Local Technical Advisory Committee for the district.Shipbuilding and Engineering. On the 25th June a meeting of the Coventry engineer-ing panel was held, and it was decided to recognise this committee, with further additions to its membership, as a Local Technical Advisory Committee. This meeting was attended by the secretary of the National Trade Advisory Committee, who fully explained the situation.On the 28th June a meeting of the Manchester Local Technical Advisory Committee was held. As this committee had ceased to meet for some time, it was considered advisable to revive its activities, and for this purpose the secretary of the National Trade Advisory Committee attended the meeting.Reports from Divisions.North-Eastem. The factories are taking a prominent part in the equipment of the Carlisle Watch and Clock Training Centre. The benches, which have been made at the Walker Factory, have been executed very satisfactorily, and the job is said to compare quite favourably with similar work executed by skilled journeymen for other contracts. All the benches have now been delivered and the cupboards are in hand. Stools are being made at Birtley, and the order is now nearly completed.
Yorkshire. The delays in the provision of the new factories so urgently required in this area have checked the progress which was so conspicuous in the earlier stages. As, however, two new factories have started this month and a beginning was made in the brick-laying, carpentry and joinery and cabinet-making courses at the Whitehall Road Factory, Leeds, during May, the immediate prospect is now much more promising than it has been for some time past. The Whitehall Road Factory have already had an offer of a large contract for furniture and house building, but they have been unable so - far to give any definite reply, as the constructional work on the factory has not yet been com-pleted.North-Western. The division are still handicapped by the slow progress of the factory schemes and consequent comparative paucity of training facilities. Possession has, however, at last been obtained of the Derby Street Factory at Manchester, where training is expected to start in July.Arrangements are nearly completed locally for taking over the training of men partially trained by the Ministry of Pensions at their Convalescent Centre at Blackpool. Several Local Technical Advisory Committees have agreed to accept these-cases on condition that they have a right to assess the degree of proficiency which has been attained before leaving the convalescent centre, and to decide how long a period of training will be required under the Ministry&apos;s scheme.East Midlands. This division, with under 300 names, shares with its neighbour, the West Midlands, the distinction of having the shortest waiting list. It is, however, considered that there are still large numbers of men eligible for training who are as yet unaware of the advantages offered by the Ministry, and proposals for a publicity campaign have been made. Arrangements for the formation of Special Interviewing Committees have been made at all Exchanges in the division which are included in the Yorkshire and East Midlands Division of the Employment Department.At a recent meeting of the Engineering Sub-Committee of the Leicester Employment Committee the workpeople&apos;s representatives, who were in the majority, resolved that an Engineering Local Technical Advisory Committee be formed. Such a committee is urgently required in view of vacancies in the engineering departments of the Loughborough Government Instructional Factory. The matter has been taken up with the secretary of the National Trade Advisory Committee, and it is hoped that everything possible will be done to expedite and facilitate the formation of a committee.West Midlands. The bulk of training work is still concentrated in the City of Birmingham, which is particularly fortunate in the possession of adequate facilities, with two large Instructional Factories and several Technical Schools which, having been used for training work under the Ministry of Munitions, are particularly well equipped.No less than 1,144 terminations of training have already been recorded in the division since the 1st August, 1919, a figure which indicates that there was practically no breach in the continuity of training work when the transfer from the Ministry of Pensions to the Ministry of Labour took place. Moreover, the waiting list with 269 names only is still the shortest recorded in any division, which shows that all applications for admission are sifted with special care.Men who have completed their training as motor mechanics and works chemists at the Aston Technical School are giving a very good account of themselves with local firms, who, in many cases, are anxious to take on additional workers from this centre on the completion of their training.Good progress is being made by the men in training at the Garrison Lane Factory in connection with the building of houses to the order of the Birmingham Housing Committee. So far the only delay has been due to the fact that on certain occasions the men in training have kept ahead of their supply of material.Members of the Birmingham Training Committee are keenly interested in the welfare and progress of the men under instruction in the City, and have given most generous assistance in the formation of social and sports clubs attached to the centres.South-Western. The placing of men in workshop training after the preliminary period continues to be one of the most difficult tasks of the staff, and the Divisional Director remarks that the difficulties are accentuated by the shortage of living accommodation. Local Technical Advisory Committees are rendering most valuable assistance, but it is of great importance that further steps to enlist the interest of employers should be adopted.
(b 16259)south Midlands. It has been suggested that the projected Garden City, near Welwyn, might serve as a training ground for a certain number of disabled soldiers, particularly in carpentry and joinery. The Local Technical Advisory Committee for the building trade at Luton are prepared to include Welwyn in-their sphere of operations and it is expected that no objection will be raised.Wales. One of the most satisfactory features during the month has been the progress of training in Government Instructional Factories. There are now over 250 men under instruction at the Cardiff Factory, and three similar factories at Bangor, Newtown and Wrexham are now fairly established.For some time past there has been a good deal of criticism of training work in Wales in the local Press by members of various discharged soldiers&apos; associations. This has been met by a practical reply in the form of descriptions of the work at the Government Instructional Factory, Cardiff, as a result of visits to the factory made by local journalists. The articles appear to have aroused a good deal of interest and were well illustrated by photographs of the men at work in the shoe-making and tailoring departments. It seems probable that the opening of this large factory may prove one of the most effective means of propaganda.Scotland. At a meeting of the General Training Committee the whole question of allowances now paid to men in training was discussed and a series of practical recom-mendations made. A sub-committee was appointed to approach the Land Resettlement Department of the Board of Agriculture to raise the question of capital for men trained for agriculture who wish to acquire small holdings.The South-Eastern District Training Committee have been investigating the possi-bilities of the absorption of disabled men in the scientific and fancy glass trades, and openings for a limited number have already been found with individual firms. In the opinion of this committee the chemical glass industry is particularly suitable for seriously disabled men. Firms which have been visited are sympathetic, but.it is stated that the ques-tion of German competition in the near future cannot he disregarded.. Middlesex-The staff have been for many months engaged on the work of securing additional training facilities. Within the last few weeks the Ailsa Craig, Willesden and Harlesden Factories have been brought upon the active list, while the Tottenham and Hornsey Factories are on the point of opening. Two other factories, Hayes and Ponders End, have also been acquired, and before many months are over this division will stand second to none in adequate training facilities.During the first four months in the year under 50 men a month, on an average, were placed in training within the division. In the first two weeks of June the number was 156. The very long waiting list, which at the beginning of the year was estimated at 2,000, has been reduced by well over 50 per cent., and at the present rate it is hoped that it will be cleared before the end of the summer.London. Since the beginning of the year, on an average, nearly 500 men have been placed in training each month, and after allowing for terminations the number in training increased in the first five months by over 1,700. During the same period the waiting list was reduced by over 2,000 names but still stands at the high figure of over 3,000. This figure is now less than the number of men in training, but at the beginning of the year it was more than twice as large., South-Eastern. There has been no real improvement in the situation which has, if anything, rather changed for the worse. The Erith factory scheme is still in abeyance, and though good progress is being made with the establishment of an Instructional Factory at Wimbledon there are still regrettable delays in connection with the proposed factory at Guildford. The majority of the existing classes are held in premises under the control of various education authorities and must shortly either he removed or closed as the rooms are required for immediate educational purposes. Special efforts have, however, been made throughout the division to induce employers to grant training facilities in their workshops.South Central. Arrangements have now been made with the Divisional Controller whereby all men desiring training apply through the Exchanges, and in the absence of Local Technical Advisory Committees are interviewed by Local Employment Committees, the members of which will keep in touch with the men throughout their courses.
WOMEN&apos;S TRAINING.General.Work of the Central Committee.-J h.e work of giving grants from the sum allocated by the committee of the National Relief Fund, to enable unemployed women whose earning capacity or opportunities have been affected by conditions arising out of the war to enter or to continue a course of training, was first undertaken by the Central Committee on Women&apos;s Training and Employment, at the instance of the Minister of Labour, in January, 1920. With the object of dealing with applications expeditiously, the committee decided that some local machinery was necessary and accordingly took steps to set up, in areas co-terminous with the divisional areas of the Employment Department, one or more Local Interviewing Boards to interview candidates and to forward to the Central Committee their recommendations on each application.These Local Interviewing Boards consist of a representative of the Central Committee on Women&apos;s Training and Employment who acts as chairman ;* a representative of the local education authority, in addition to whom a University representative or other expert is asked to attend when necessary; a representative of the Women&apos;s Training Branch, and a representative of the Employment Department, fLocal Interviewing Boards are now active in every division. In London, the Board meet three times a week, and in other areas as the number of candidates renders it necessary.The types of training selected by candidates range over a great variety of occupations, including all forms of agriculture, horticulture and poultry keeping, clerical work, domestic science, eurhythmies, music, law, journalism, medicine, dentistry, X-ray treatment and massage, analytical chemistry, physical culture, health visiting, sanitary work, art teaching, architecture and the stage. It is significant, however, that about a quarter of the total number of applications have been for some form of clerical or secretarial work.Among the trainees who have already completed their courses are maternity nurses and teachers of the blind. One of the teachers has the promise of a post under the Ministry of Health, and another has been engaged as a substitute teacher in a training institution during the holidays.Extension of Schemes. It has been decided that, in certain cases, the training in Institutional Centres which on the 30th June had not reached the limit of the standard course for the particular form of training, may he continued for the number of weeks necessary to enable the pupils to complete their course. The standard course extends to six months for training as nursemaids and industrial courses such as dressmaking and tailoring, and three months for domestic courses. This decision will apply to 54 classes and approximately 1,500 trainees.Upholstery Class (East Ham). This class has been inspected by a member of the headquarters staff, who was very favourably impressed by the results achieved. The trainees have had experience in making tea-cosies, gauged curtains, bordered curtains, welted scrolls, and loose covers, and were able to show very satisfactory specimens. In seeking employment the girls will be handicapped by the lack of speed inevitable after a course of only 10 weeks&apos; training. At the time of the visit one of the staff of Messrs. Heal &amp; Son, Ltd., called to inspect the work, and was pleased with the progress made. Every -thing points to a certainty that the girls would obtain employment in first-class houses, if their training could be made longer. The West Ham Education Committee, under whose auspices the class is run, have passed a resolution expressing great pleasure at the progress of the trainees and regret that the duration of the course is not sufficient to enable them to obtain a livelihood immediately. They strongly recommend continuing the course for three months.Exhibition (Ponders End). The Ponders End Centre held an exhibition of work on the 24th June. The canteen, kitchen and administrative offices of the National Shell Factory have provided excellent accommodation for the laundry, cookery, tailoring and dressma-king classes, which were each represented by a very good display of work. The laundry class showed specimens of hand-ironing of embroidery, fine lace, intricate garments and delicate materials, and had a very large and varied assortment of work completed arid in course of handling. Judging by the standard attained no difficulty appears likely to arise in placing them in employment. Two of these girls have accepted posts in the laundry of the London Hospital and a third in another institution. The cookery class had a very representative show of dishes and confectionery.  Almost all the exhibits were sold.* In practice it has been found that the amount of time taken up by the Boards makes it difficult or impossible for one chairman to preside at every meeting, and additional chairmen have accordingly been appointed in respect of practically every Board.  .f See this Report No. 18, 3rd April, p. 340.
Women&apos;s Training-continued.Eleven of the cooks, who are married women and wish to have employment by the day within reach of their homes, are going to work in restaurants in the locality.The tailoring class had specialised in trouser making, and all their work was done to order. Each trainee was sufficiently skilled, to make a pair of trousers throughout, but seemed a little anxious as to whether she had attained the speed necessary to earn a living wage in a trade workroom.The dressmaking class, though represented by a good display of finished garments, seemed more than any of the other classes to have suffered through the shortness of the course, which had only been running three months and a half instead of the usual six montl. s. In spite of. this handicap, however, the work accomplished gained the approval of several experts representing West End firms. These representatives regretted that owing to the slack period in the dressmaking trade during the next two months they were unable to -consider employing any of the trainees immediately after June, but promised to remember them when engaging new hands in September. The trainees are all anxious to get employ-ment with West End firms, though it is possible thatsome may be placed in. clothing factories in Tottenham, Hackney or Walthamstow.Great appreciation was shown of the Minister&apos;s visit to the exhibition with Mrs. Macnamara.Tailoring Scheme (lalkirfy. The local Woman Training Officer has reported very satisfactorily on a visit to the works of Messrs. A. Anderson &amp; Sons, where 20 women are in training. She stated that four fully trained men have been specially engaged by the firm to instruct, and to help in. the work. One of them is a disabled soldier, trained under the men&apos;s training scheme in Messrs. Anderson&apos;s other workshop. The work done by the girls consists of men&apos;s ready-made suits and overcoats. A very good class of work is turned out. The foreman is pleased with the girls&apos; progress, and he is confident that they should be able to earn Trade Board rates at the end of their training. .Football Stitching (Walsall). As a result of a time-test given to the trainees in football stitching it would appear that only two of the girls would not earn their money on piece-rates. The firm are anxious to keep all the trainees as they have worked well. The two referred to will be given a month&apos;s trial at 6c?. per hour, and the rest will be put on piece-rates on the 1st July.Domestic Training (Dublin). On the termination of the domestic economy course at the Dublin Technical Schools good posts were available immediately through the Dublin Employment Exchange and 50 per cent, of the girls were at once placed in employment, living in, at wages ranging from 10s. to  1 per week. The remainder of the girls were more difficult to place, as they wished to be able to sleep at home.Disabled Nurses.During the past week five new applications for training have been received from disabled nurses, for whom it is hoped to arrange courses, if they prove eligible and physically fit. To ensure that these two conditions are satisfied involves a considerable amount of correspondence, interviewing, medical examination, and negotiations with the Ministry of Pensions, which unfortunately delays the commencement of training. A disabled nurse on the expiry of her temporary pension is often granted a gratuity instead of a renewal of the pension. In these circumstances she is not eligible for training ; she may however, decide to appeal against the decision, and if it is reversed and her pension renewed she again becomes eligible and her physical fitness for the particular form of employment chosen has to be certified. Arrangements for her medical examination are accordingly made through the Ministry of Pensions.While the eligibility of the nurse is thus being determined the department have to select a suitable place of training, to arrange terms for the course, and to have the candidate interviewed by the principal of the Training Institute or whoever may be responsible for her training.In institutional training it frequently happens that a case may be finally sanctioned just too late for the nurse to join in the current term, and she may have to wait several months for the next.War Widows and Dependants.During the week ending the 26th June, the number of fresh applications was again below the average, 10 having been received, bringing the total to 2,390. In 11 further cases train-ing was authorised, bringing the total of sanctions to 1,317. Ten applications were rejected or withdrawn; there were two withdrawals from training. At, the end of the week there were 366 war widows in training, and 605 had completed their training.(b 10259) I 2
10,7.20.- 68Women &apos;s Training-continued,*Since the transfer of the training powers to the Ministry on 1st September, 1919,1,154 applications from war widows have been, received. During this period 600 have been sanctioned, and 689 have been rejected or withdrawn.APPRENTICES AND BOYS. INTERRUPTED APPRENTICESHIPS.Negotiation, of Schemes.Schemes Approved. On the 29th June the scheme for the cutlery industry was approved on behalf of the Minister. It is to take effect as from the 1st January, 1919. This brings the number of approved schemes up to 41.Questions Affecting the Scheme.Wages. The chief engineer of the municipal electricity works at Bridlington has been under-paying the apprentices who have been accepted under the scheme, on the ground that they are being trained as professional men. Local headquarters, however, hope to secure the payment of arrears of wages.At Brierfield, a firm of cotton mill proprietors object to paying the rates required by the engineering scheme to apprentice mechanics in their repair shops. Such mechanics normally receive wages much below those prevailing in ^engineering shops, and to pay the apprentices on the latter basis would lead to their receiving higher rates than the journeymen.Messrs. Burton &amp; Sons, Kettering, builders, have four apprentices for training. One of them, however, after four years&apos; absence in the Army, had a renewed apprenticeship of one year only which has now terminated. This proved insufficient to make him a fully skilled man. The firm, therefore, find themselves unable to pay him the full rate. As, however, they desire to avoid dismissing him, they arranged to retain him for a further year at a slightly lower rate than that payable under the scheme, and so to complete his training. To this the man, who is a non-unionist, has consented. Local headquarters report that the firm are giving the apprentice every assistance.The Scheme in Operation.Statistics. Up to the 30th June, 41 schemes had been approved and applications had been received in respect of 40 schemes. The number of applications received at Exchanges from employers for apprentices, for the week ending the 24th June, was 260, making a total of 41,236. The number of applications received from apprentices was 293, making a total of 46,273.Up to the 30th June agreements had been received at headquarters in respect of 39,562 apprentices. Grants had been sanctioned in respect of 38,017 apprentices, employed by 15,101 employers. Of these, 13,653 were under the engineering scheme and 6,354 under the building scheme. The total number of agreements lapsed on the expiration of the appropriate period of training, or by mutual agreement between the parties, is now 6,972.Applications. The misunderstanding to the effect that the scheme is limited to indentured apprentices appears still to exist in some&quot; districts, even in large concerns. At Kettering, the Northamptonshire Printing and Publishing Co., Ltd., had brought one indentured apprentice under the scheme, but not two others who were serving under unwritten agreements.  They have now agreed to&apos;&quot;make application in respect of them.Acceptance or No?i-Accepta,nce.-Iji South Wales considerable difficulty is being experienced in bringing apprentice plumbers under the scheme, and a number of them are out of employment, especially at Cardiff, and others are completing their apprentice-ships upon much less favourable terms. Moreover, the district committee of the plumbers&apos; union prefer, where possible, to negotiate separate arrangements with the employer concerned, rather than have binding agreements for definite periods under the scheme. They consider that, as soon as an apprentice can earn the full rates, he should be free to do so and to seek employment in any firm, without waiting for the conclusion of his renewed training. The position may be compared with that which has prevailed in this industry in Scotland.
Messrs. Alley &amp; MacLellan, Ltd., Glasgow, engineers, have continued to delay their adoption of the scheme. The matter has been taken up with them by the local branch of the employers&apos; federation, and the firm&apos;s main objection now is that the department in which the apprentices are employed is about to be closed down, and that they will not make themselves responsible for finding further employment. The negotiations on. this matter have been proceeding for nearly a year. It has been finally suggested, how-ever, that the apprentices should be brought under the scheme, with a view to a course of institutional training in the autumn. The firm are now reported to have decided to accept them on this basis.In the Northern area local headquarters appear to have solved, a problem of some difficulty and hardship. An apprentice, a joiner, was before the War working with, his father, who is now working as a journeyman and cannot take him back. Owing to severe shell-shock the apprentice could get no other firm to engage him. He did not wish to change his trade, as he was convinced that, with a fair chance, he could make himself efficient. Eventually local headquarters obtained him employment at half the local journeyman&apos;s rate with a firm of joiners and builders, who have promised that on his showing reasonable progress they will bring him under the scheme.Non-Observance of Conditions. In two recent cases, those of the Shields Motor Co., Ltd., Perth, and the Buist Spinning Co., Ltd., Dundee, a reference to the Local. Employ-ment Committee concerned has had excellent results. In each instance the firm agreed to carry out their obligations and pay all arrears, without waiting for the hearing of their case.Training in Operation: Progress. In the London and South-Eastern area recent reports show the training to be on the whole satisfactory, and in the West Hiding of Yorkshire, the representative of the Amalgamated Society of Engineers describes the scheme as most satisfactory, and as working well, except for one or two trivial matters. At Nottingham, the apprentices of Messrs. Boots, Ltd., are making good progress. At Banbury, Messrs. S. Kilby &amp; Sons, coopers, have found that their apprentices are doing well. Messrs. Strachan &amp; Henshaw, Ltd., Bristol, engineers, who have not in the past been altogether favourable to the scheme, are showing very considerable interest in the apprentices and have given every facility to local headquarters to inspect their training.Institutional Training. In the North-Western area several apprentices have now been placed for institutional training in the Central Technical School, Liverpool. Local head-quarters have recommended the extension of the plumbers&apos; class at Salford for a further three months. The Blackburn class is to be closed shortly, as most of the students still in attendance come from other towns, and some or all of them will be transferred to Salford. &apos;GENERAL TRAINING.Boy Superintendence.Appointment of Superintendents. During the week ending the 25th June one firm appointed two boy superintendents, another firm appointed one, and two others com-bined to appoint a single superintendent to act for both.Apprentices: Conditions and Training.Sujjervision of Training : Changes in Methods of Manufacture. The Liverpool district secretaries of the engineering trade unions urge that the constant changes in methods of manufacture, render increasingly important the provision of adequate supervision of training. Such changes make obsolete previous forms of training, and lead to a surplus of workers in the displaced processes, and a shortage in those which are displacing them. As an instance, they refer to experiments now being made in shipbuilding in welding plates, which, if successful, may mean a considerable displacement of riveters. They feel that such conditions render more urgent the supervision and organisation of industrial training througlr a Government department, which would take account of impending changes, modify training accordingly, and arrange to train the displaced workers for other crafts.General.Voluntary Continuation Classes (Northampton). For some time past most Northampton employers have allowed their boys under 16 time off to attend the Technical School for one morning in each week, without deduction of wages.  The classes are arranged toApprentices and Boys-continued,
FINANCE DEPARTMENT.OUT-OF-WORK DONATION.Payments Made. Returns showing payments made, according to information received at the Claims and Record Office, Kew : 	Civilian Workers.		H.M. Forces.		Total.		No.	Amount.	No.	Amount.	No.	Amount.Total to 17th June    ... Week ending 24th June	20,377,217 979	  22,395&apos;,599 896	21,972,439 180,127	  30,813,160 207,790	42,349,656 181,106	  53,208,759 - 208,686Total to 24th June ...	20,378,196	22,396,495	22,152,566	. 31,020,950	42,530,762	53,417,445UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE.Payments Made-Th.% number of payments of unemployment insurance benefit at local offices during the week ending the 18th June, 1920, was 25,198, involving an amount of  12,566 12s. lid.INDUSTRIES DEPARTMENT.INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS DIVISION. JOINT STANDING INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS : NEGOTIATIONS.Government Industrial: Trade Joint Councils. Sir Malcolm Ramsay, K.C.B., presided at a meeting of the Provisional Joint Committee (Inter-Departmental) held on the 29th June to consider proposals for setting up Trade Joint Councils to deal with wages and trade questions among Government industrial employees. The principle was approved that Councils should be set up for engineering, for shipbuilding, and for building, and also a Council to cover the classes of general labour which may be unattached to these three industries. A committee was appointed consisting of eight representative^ from the departments and two representatives from each of the four groups of trade unions concerned.   This committee will meet on the 15th July.JOINT STANDING INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS: REPORTS.Industrial.Coir Mat and Matting. The Council met on the 1st July. The report of the sub-committee appointed to consider the piece-rates in the industry was discussed, and con-firmation was given to a previous decision of the Council, that piece-rates should be adjusted to enable the normal male worker to earn Is. 5\d. per hour and the normal female worker %\d. per hour,Apprentices and Boys-continued.suit the various trades or occupations. Thus for those in engineering a two years&apos; course is arranged, comprising English, drawing, elementary mathematics, and science. The boys, however, are reported not to have availed themselves to any extent of these opportunities. One reason given is that time-rates only are paid for the hours spent at school.   At work, they earn much larger sums on piece-rates.[Reference to matters of interest to the Training Department will also be found on pages 56, 59, 71, and 82.]
Industrial Councils Division-continued.Electricity Supply.--The District Council for the Eastern Counties met on the 1st July. An application from the trade union side for the rates of wages agreed upon by the Home Counties District Council, plus 3s. per week to each grade, was referred to a special sub-committee, who will report to the Council at an early date.Glass. As a result of representations made to the Home Secretary by the Council an amendment has been introduced into the Women, Young Persons and Children (Employment) Bill giving the&quot; Secretary of State power to postpone the date of the operation of the Act, so far as any branch of the glass industry is concerned, on being satisfied that, although a bonafide effort at reorganisation had been made, reorganisation is not complete.Hosiery. A representative of the department interviewed trade union leaders and members of the operatives&apos; side of the Council on the 28th June on the subject of the attitude of the Council towards claims for representation on the joint body from craft unions which are not affiliated to the Federation of Hosiery Unions, and from general labour unions.Local Authorities&apos;&apos; Non-Trading Services, Manual Workers (England and Wales). The National Council met on the 2nd July. The report of the sub-committee appointed to consider the question of payment of wages during sickness was considered. The report was in favour of the principle, and it was decided that the recommendations contained in the report be placed before the District Councils for their consideration.The North Wales District Council met on the 18th June. Decisions were arrived at on an average working week of 48 hours, overtime-rates and holidays.The South Wales and Monmouthshire District Council met on the 29th June. The application from the trade union side for Is. 8d. per hour for labourers permanently employed by local authorities, and Is. 9d. for those casually employed, was further considered. Agreement was reached as to the Is. 9d. per hour for casual labourers, but as no agreement could be reached on the other category it was decided to ask the Ministry to appoint an independent chairman to preside at the next meeting.The District Council for the West Riding of Yorkshire met at Leeds on the 1st July. Complaint was made as to the failure of many local authorities to honour the recommenda-tions of the Council, and a resolution was passed urging the National Council to convene a conference of representatives of District Councils for the purpose of considering if statutory powers should be asked for. A sub-committee was appointed to collect data with a view to classifying every type of worker employed in non-trading departments in the area, and the fixing of appropriate scales of pay.Needle, Fish-hook, Fishing Tackle and Allied Trades. The annual meeting of the Council was held on the 29th June. The constitution was amended to allow for the appointment of an independent chairman if desired. The Executive and Wages Com-mittees were re-elected en bloc, and Mr. Hill was elected chairman pro tern. The draft report of the Wages Committee was taken as read and submitted to the association and trade union concerned for approval. An interesting discussion took place on home-work and out-work. The former practice was unanimously condemned/ but no agreement-was reached on the latter.Pottery. The Wages and Conditions Committee on the 28th June dealt with some points of difficulty which have arisen in the operation of the Interrupted Apprenticeships Scheme. Apparently the number of agreements entered into is comparatively small, but this was accounted for to some extent by the fact that in many cases returned apprentices have been placed upon full journeymen&apos;s wages; there was, however, some feeling that employers were not receiving the financial aid from the State to which they felt themselves entitled, and after discussion a sub-committee was appointed to reconsider the provisions of the scheme. The suggested rules governing apprentices upon which the committee have been engaged for some time past were again considered. The workers wish to submit some minor points to the manufacturers, and if agreement can be reached upon these, the rules may be approved by the Council at their next meeting on the 8th July.The committee dealt also with a draft Order relating to the particulars clause of the Factory Act which it is proposed to submit to the Home Office with a recommendation that it be adopted as a Statutory Order. The committee approved the draft and recommended it to the Council for adoption.Quarrying. Representatives of the Freestone Section met on the 29th June to consider a draft constitution for District Councils. The National Federation of Freestone Quarry Owners, the National Union of General Workers, the Workers&apos; Union, and the
Operative Society of Stone Masons, Quarrymen, and Allied Trades were represented. After discussion the two general labour unions concluded an arrangement with the operative stone masons, which should bring to an end the difficulties between these unions which have hindered the formation of Sectional Councils and District Councils. The arrangement has to be ratified by the executive of the stone masons&apos; union, but it is believed that it will become effective. The draft constitution was accepted. District Councils have already been set up in Yorkshire and negotiations are proceeding in the Derbyshire, Lanca-shire and Bath areas.Waterworks Undertakings. The second annual meeting of the Council was held at Nottingham on the 30th June. The officers and the Executive Committee were elected. It was reported that active steps were being taken to form the three District Councils which had not yet been set up. The Metropolitan District Council had referred for settle-ment to the National Council applications submitted by the trade union side to the effect that throughout the Metropolitan District wages and bonus shall be consolidated for the purpose of determining pension; and that engineers&apos; labourers be paid according to engineers&apos; awards, other labourers according to building trade awards; that other grades shall receive a minimum of 80s. per week, with pro rata increases to those who are at present receiving more than the existing minimum; these rates to operate from the 1st April. It was agreed that the first item be referred to the Sub-Committee on Super-annuation for consideration and report. The employers&apos; side could not agree that the awards referred to were applicable in the district, and it was resolved that the Council should urge the Metropolitan Water Board to agree to go to arbitration on the application for an 80s. minimum.The provisional Executive Committee appointed to draft a constitution for the District Council for North Wales met on the 28th June. A draft constitution was adopted, and will be submitted to a conference of the undertakings and the trade unions concerned on the 12th July.Wool (and Allied) Textiles. The adjourned meeting of the Council for the Northern Counties District was held on the 30th June, to consider the offer of the employers&apos; side in response to an application for a 40 per cent, advance on current wages, with a minimum of  5 for men and  3 for women, together with payment for all statutory holidays and one week&apos;s annual holiday. The unions further claimed that all war wages should be merged in new basic rates. Subject to acceptance of these proposals the unions were prepared to accept a new form of sliding scale, based on the cost of living, which should not fall below a minimum of  4 for men and  2 8s. for women. The employers&apos; offer included an addition of 5 per cent, to basic rates, the payment of cost-of-living wage on the 10 per cent, advance on basic rates conceded in 1919, and the further 5 per cent, now offered, making a total increase in terms of basic rates for time-workers of 26&apos;f per cent, when the cost-of-living figure stands at 145, with corresponding increases to piece-workers. The sliding scale under the operation of which two advances of 3s. each have been paid in June and July, respectively, will continue at present. The proposals are contingent upon the acceptance of a settlement for twelve months. After a discussion, in the course of which the employers stated that they were not empowered to increase their offer, and had experienced considerable difficulty, in view of the present condition of the industry, in persuading certain sections to fall into line with the proposals now submitted, the operatives expressed their inability to accept the offer. They regretted the refusal of the employers to concede the principle of payment for holidays and to merge a proportion of war wages into basic rates, and decided to refer the proposals to their constituents for further instructions. A further meeting of the Council will be convened when the counter-proposals are ready.  The employers are not at present disposed to amend their offer.Government Industrial.H.M. Stationery Office. The first meeting of the Council was held on the 28th June. Mr. W. R. Codling, C.B., M.V.O., chairman of the Council, presided. It was announced that Mr. W. Broadbent would be the secretary on the official side. The employees&apos; side appointed, as vice-chairman, Mr. T. E. Naylor, of the London Society of Compositors, - and as secretary, Mr. A. E. Holmes, of the Printing and Kindred Trades Federation. A sub-committee of three from each side was appointed to prepare a scheme for works committees.Industrial Councils Division-continued.
Industrial Councils Division-continued.War Office. On the 1st July the Council held a joint session with the Ministry of Munitions Council to discuss what adjustments in the representation on the War Office Council would be necessary to cover the productive establishments transferred from the Ministry of Munitions. At a subsequent meeting of the trade union side it was agreed to recommend that the employees&apos; side of the War Office Council should be increased to 15, which, in view of the similarity in the composition of the two Councils, would provide for the representation on the War Office Council of all the unions at present represented on either of the two Councils.JOINT STANDING INDUSTRIAL COUNCILS: WORKS COMMITTEES.Brewing. The investigation of the conditions of the industry in the London and South-Eastern District has been continued, and the formation of works committees is now under consideration by Messrs. Smith, Garrett &amp; Co., Ltd., Bow Brewery, E., and Messrs. Steward &amp; Patterson, Ltd., Pockthorpe Brewery, Norwich.. Flour Milling.-Tlie Council having adopted a constitution for works committees, negotiations have been opened with a view to their formation. The secretaries of the District Councils for Scotland, North-Eastern, Birmingham and West Midlands, Lincoln-shire, Gloucester, Liverpool and Manchester and district, have been interviewed and have arranged for an officer of the Ministry to address their Councils at their next meetings. The Gloucester divisional organising secretary of the Workers&apos; Union, when approached on the subject, showed himself strongly in favour of works committees in view of the great success of the committees set up in the rubber industry in his district by the Ministry.Gold, Silver, Horological and Allied Trades. The formation of works committees is being considered by Messrs. Bernard &amp; Sons, Hatton Garden, E.C., Messrs. C. S. Harris &amp; Sons, Ltd., Hatton Garden, Messrs. C. T. &amp; G. Fox, Berwick Street, W., Mr. J. E. Sutton, President Street, E.C., Messrs. Jourdan &amp; Hickson, Soho Square, W., Mr. C. J. Vander, Drury Lane, W.C., Messrs. Saunders, Shepherd &amp; Co., Ltd., Fleet Street, E.C., and Messrs. C. Boynton &amp; Son, Ltd., Upper Charles Street, B.C.Needle, Fish-hook, Fishing Tackle and Allied Trades. At the works of Messrs. H. Milward &amp; Son the election of the members of the works committee evoked considerable interest among the employees. The provisional committee at the works of Messrs. Bartleet &amp; Sons, Ltd., have adopted the constitution suggested by the Council. Messrs. F. &amp;.S. English &amp; Co., Messrs. Morris &amp; Yeoman, and Messrs. Perkins &amp; Co., all of Redditch, have the formation of works committees under consideration.Pottery. At the works of Messrs. Dudson, Wilcox &amp; Till, Ltd., Hanley, members have been elected to the Avorks committee and the draft constitution has been adopted. The formation of works committees is being considered by Messrs. G. Jones &amp; Son, Ltd., Stoke, Messrs. Wilson &amp; Son, Stoke, the Rubian Art Pottery, Ltd., Fenton, the Canning Pottery Co., Fenton, and the Crown Staffordshire Porcelain Co., Ltd., Fenton.. It has been decided by the management to proceed with the formation of a works committee at the works of Messrs. Biltons (1912), Ltd.Rubber. The formation of works committees is now being considered by Messrs. G. W. Laughton &amp; Co., and Messrs. Mandleberg &amp; Co., Ltd., Manchester.INTERIM INDUSTRIAL RECONSTRUCTION COMMITTEES: REPORTS.Clay. The Negotiating Committee met on the 30th June to discuss the question of payment for overtime. It was agreed to recommend to the Committee that time-and-a-quarter should be paid for the first two hours, time-and-a-half after this, and.double time on Saturday afternoon and Sunday.Non-Ferrous Mining. The second annual meeting of the Committee was held on the. 30th June. It was decided to send a deputation to the President of the Board of Trade to ask that certain recommendations of the Departmental Committee appointed to inquire into the non-ferrous mining industry should be carried out immediately.Packing of Textiles for Export.-The London District Council met on the 1st July, The business was mainly formal and consisted of a discussion on unemployment insurance, sickness benefit and overtime.[Reference to matters of interest in connection with Industrial Councils will also be found on pages 44, 52, 78, 83 and 84.] .(b 16259) K
TRADE BOARDS DIVISION.PROCEEDINGS OF TRADE BOARDS.Chain Trade Board (Great Britain). The Board have considered the position which will arise as the result of the minimum rates now in force having been fixed for a limited period expiring on the 30th September. They resolved with regard to the hand-hammered chain-making section to vary the general minimum time-rates and general. minimum piece-rates to amounts equivalent to 15 per cent, increase on the present rates, and with regard to the dollied or tommied chain-making section to continue in operation for a further six months the minimum rates now in force.The Board also considered a letter from the Employment Department on the subject of co-operation of the Board with Juvenile Advisory Committees and agreed to invite a representative of the Juvenile Branch to attend the next meeting of the Board and discuss the matter.Rope, Twine and Net Trade Board (Great Britain). The Board considered the objections to their proposal to va^ minimum rates of wages for certain classes of male workers in Great Britain, excluding Dorset and Somerset, and to fix general minimum piece-rates and to vary overtime rates as set out in the Notice issued on the 12th April, * and to vary and fix minimum rates for certain classes of male and female workers in Dorset and Somerset as set out in the same Notice. They agreed to vary and to fix such minimum rates of wages with, a slight modification in the general minimum piece-rate. The Board agreed to suggest to the Minister that the minimum rates of wages as varied and fixed should become effective as from the 16th July.The Board considered a report from the Administrative Committee to the effect that they could not adopt the suggestion to utilise Local Employment Committees for the examination of applications for permits of exemption as they were of the opinion that the members of the Board were the most fit by reason of their technical knowledge of the trade to investigate such applications.  This view was endorsed by the Board.The Board agreed that a representative of the Juvenile/Branch should be invited to attend the next meeting of the Board to discuss the question of co-operation between the Board and Juvenile Advisory Committees.Sugar Confectionery and Food Preserving Trade Board (Great Britain). The Adminis-trative Committee considered the suggestion that Local Employment Committees should be utilised for examination for permits of exemption and agreed to recommend the Board to reply that, while cases might arise in which the assistance of Local Employment Com-mittees might be helpful, the Board asked that investigating officers might be at their disposal for investigating all cases in which the Board thought that this course was necessary.   This suggestion was endorsed by the Board.The Board considered the question of the usefulness of District Trade Committees and agreed to request the Minister to amend the regulations of the Board in order that the existing District Trade Committees might be disestablished or, alternatively, to request that the size of the existing District Trade Committees should be limited to two local representatives, two Trade Board members, and one appointed member.The Board agreed unanimously to. vary the general minimum time-rates, piece-work basis time-rates and overtime rates on the basis of their Notice of Proposal dated the 21st April,f it being understood that a proposal to vary the minimum rates should be con-sidered at the next meeting of the Board, to be held in October, or earlier in the event of a general advance in wages taking place before that date.Tobacco Trade Board (Great Britain). At a meeting of the Administrative Committee a letter was considered on the subject of the minimum rates applicable to apprentices engaged in learning the work of bundling and sorting cigars, and the committee concurred in the opinion expressed by the Ministry that such workers were not exempted under the Board&apos;s determinations of the 19th April.The Board considered the objections lodged against their proposal to vary minimum rates of wages for male and female workers as set out in the Notice dated the 13th April,* and agreed to vary such minimum rates in accordance with their proposal, and to suggest that they should become effective as from the 16th July. The minimum rates as varied for male and female workers, 21 years of age and over, are 61s. Qd., and 38s. Qd., respectively, for a week of 48 hours.* See this Report, No. 13, 24th April, p. 442. f See this Report, No. 14,1st May, p. 478.
Trade Boards Division-continued.The Board considered a letter on the subject of the examination for permits of exemp-tion, and agreed, to inform the Minister that they desire that the examination of applications should be undertaken by the Administrative Committee, and that investigations should be conducted either by members of the committee or by investigating officers.Stamped or Pressed Metal Wares Trade Board (Great Britain). At a meeting of the special committee it was agreed to recommend to the Board the following minimum rates of wages for special classes of female workers : General minimum time-rates for female workers, 18 years of age and over, employed as polishers or as drop stampers, lid. per hour during the first 18 months of employment, and Is. per hour thereafter, with lower rates for younger workers, according to age ; for female workers, 18 years of age and over, who are employed as japanners, hand brush lacquerers, and blow-pipe braziers or solderers using ordinary hand-iron or blow-pipe with bar-solder, Wd. per hour during the first twelve months of employment, and lid. per hour thereafter, with lower rates for younger workers according to age.It is recommended that female workers commencing employment in the above-mentioned branches of the trade for the first time at or over the age of 18 years shall be employed during the first two months at Id. per hour less than the general minimum time-rate applicable to workers during the first twelve months of employment after the age of 18 in that branch of the trade.Piece-work basis time-rates for female workers, who are employed as polishers or as [drop stampers, Is. Id. per hour, and for female workers of the remaining special classes referred to above, Is, per hour.A further meeting is to be held to discuss special rates for male workers under 21 years of age, and to define grades for special classes of male workers, 21 years of age and over.Corset Trade Board (Great Britain). A representative of the Employment Department attended a meeting of the Board and gave an explanation of the Unemployment Insurance Bill.The representatives of workers on the Board submitted an amended motion to vary the general minimum time-rates and piece-work basis time-rates, for male and female workers. The Board resolved to propose to vary the general minimum time-rate for female workers, other than learners, from S^d. to 9fci per hour, with proportionate increases for female learners, and a piece-work basis time-rate for all female workers from %\d. to 10fd. per hour. The Board also resolved to issue a Notice of Proposal to vary general minimum time-rates and piece-work basis time-rates for male workers.The Board&apos;agreed to suggest to the Insurance Department of the Ministry of Health that the special unit of work, for the purpose of the National Insurance (Health) Acts, for female out-workers in the corset trade should be fixed as that for which the remuneration is 24s. A letter on the subject of co-operation between the Board and Juvenile Advisory Committees was considered, and it was agreed that a representative of the Juvenile Branch should be invited to attend the meeting of the Administrative Committee for the purpose of discussing the question. They also considered a letter from the Minister suggesting that applications for permits of exemption should be referred to the Local Employment Committees, and agreed to inform the Minister that they considered it essential that the work of reporting on all such cases should continue to be done by the investigating officers.The Board considered a letter from the Minister intimating that be proposed to publish a Notice of Intention to amend the Trade Boards (Corset) and the Trade Boards (Dress-making and Women&apos;s Light Clothing) Orders, 1919, together with a draft amendment of the definition of the corset trade, and the Board agreed that the proposed amendment met with their approval.Paper Bag Trade Board (Great Britain). The Administrative Committee considered the subject of the examination for permits of exemption and were of opinion that the work should be performed either by members of the committee or the Board or by investigating officers.At a meeting of the Board it was resolved to issue a Notice of Proposal to vary theminimum rates for male and female workers on the following basis : General minimum time-rates for female workers, 18 years of age and over, from 8d. to %\d. per hour, with proportionate increases for younger female workers ; for male workers, 21 years of age and over, the minimum rates at present fixed to be increased by 10s. per week, and the rates for younger male workers to be proportionately increased. Piece-work basis time-rate for all female workers from %\d. to 9fper hour.  It was also agreed to vary the overtime rates.    IThe Board agreed to invite a representative of the Juvenile Branch to attend the next meeting of the Board to discuss the question of co-operation with the Juvenile Advisory Committees.(b 16259) K 2
Trade Boards Division-continued.FIXING AND VARIATION OF MINIMUM RATES OF WAGES.Retail Bespoke Tailoring Trade Board (Great Britain). The Minister has made an Order dated the 16th June, confirming general minimum time-rates as varied and fixed for certain classes of male workers, and has specified the 21st June as the date from which these rates shall become effective.The general minimum time-rates fixed are, for all male workers, 22 years of age and over, exclud-ing cutters and trimmers, learners, workers specified in Part I of the Schedule to the Order of the Minister of Labour, dated the 31st May, and certain apprentices, Is. 2d. per hour, with correspondingly lower rates for younger workers; and for male learners under 15 years to 21 years of age, 3c/. to lOfdl. per hour.ESTABLISHMENT AND AMENDMENT  OF TRADE BOARDS.New Boards.-Regulations have been made with respect to the constitution and pro-ceedings of the Milk Distributive Trade Board (Scotland).The Minister has given Notice of Intention to apply the Trade Board Acts to the fruit, flower and vegetable distributive trade; the fish, poultry, game and. rabbits distributive trade ; and the manufacture of boot and floor polish.[References to mutters of interest in connection with Trade Boards will be found also on page 82.]WAGES AND ARBITRATION DEPARTMENTAWARDS.The number of awards issued during the week was twelve, nine under the Industrial Courts Act, one under the Wages (Temporary Regulation) Acts, as modified by the Industrial Courts Act, and two by single arbitrators.Industrial Court.Women Workers (London). The Court found that the women engaged in working on sheet rubber and waterproofed cloth at the works of Messrs. F. Schutze &amp; Co., Ltd., were not employed in a rubber manufacturing establishment, and that Award No. 71 of the Court of Arbitration as extended by Statutory Rules and Orders, No. 635, of 1919, is not applicable to the workpeople now concerned. The Court further found that none of the said workpeople are employed in the making of rubber or waterproof garments under such conditions as would entitle them to rates for munition workers under. Statutory Rules and Orders, Nos. 546 and 1073, of 1918.  (Award No. 367.)Tramway Reconstruction (Bournemouth). The Court decided that the work in connec-tion with the reconstruction of the Bournemouth tramways, on which the men concerned are employed by Messrs. William Griffiths &amp; Co., Ltd., is not such as to bring them under the decision and agreements applicable to local building trade operatives.   (Award No. 366.)Machine and Hand File-Workers (Sheffield). Hand file-cutters were granted a bonus of 150 per cent, all round in lieu of the sliding scale bonus at present in operation. With regard to hand and machine grinders, the average percentage war bonus of 25 per cent, on the earnings on the new piece-price list, and in the case of male time-workers 21 years and over, on the new day-work rate of Is. lOd. per hour, was increased to 32^ per cent. The bonuses to time-workers and piece-workers, 21 years of age and over, engaged in file forging, machine cutting, hardening and subsidiary work, were increased to 47s. per week, and by 100 per cent., respectively. The bonus to piece-workers under 21 years of age was advanced to 90 per cent.   (Awards Nos. 363, 364 and 365.)Instrument Makers. In the application of Award No. 180 the advance of 15 per cent, granted is to be added to the prices in the old list only, and not to the prices as augmented under the agreement dated the 9th October, 1914.  (Award No. 360.)
AGREEMENTS AND SETTLEMENTS.Woodcutting Machinists (North-East Coast).-&apos;At a recent conference between representatives of the Tyne, Hartlepools and Tees-side, and the Hull Sawmilling Owners&apos; Associations and the Amalgamated Society of Woodcutting Machinists, with the Chief Conciliation Officer, Newcastle, acting as chairman, it was agreed that a rate of 2s. 2d. per hour should be paid as from the 3rd July, and 2s. Ad. per hour as from the 2nd August, and it was also agreed that the rate of 2s. id. per hour should operate for three months. A vote on the agreement was taken by the union, and was accepted by a majority of one vote only. The men on strike in the Hartlepools and Tees-side district returned to work on the 25th June.Painters (Kings Lynn). Up till now the rates of painters have usually been \d. to Id. per hour less than those of other building trade mechanics, but during the last few months in many parts of the country the painters&apos; rate has been levelled up to that of the other classes of mechanics. The latest instance in which this has occurred is in. the Eastern Counties under a decision of the South-Eastern Centre Conciliation Board for the Building Trades. In many cases this levelling up of the painters&apos; rate has led to difficulties. At Kings Lynn, the local master decorators&apos; association withdrew from the master builders&apos; association after the coming into operation of the new Eastern Counties rates, and refused to pay the same rate to painters as to other building trade mechanics on the ground that few of the painters were fully skilled men. The matter was taken up by the whole of the building trade operatives in the district and a strike appeared inevitable. The Chief Conciliation Officer for the South-Eastern area, however, succeeded in arranging a conference of the parties and a settlement was effected on the basis of paying the rate claimed, but from a date subsequent to that on which the area scheme came into operation. The rate is to be paid from the .19th June, or from whatever date constitutes the week current at the date of the settlement, instead of from the 1st May, which, is the date fixed under the area scheme.Demarcation: Plumbers and Pipe Fitters (Crystal Palace).--k strike involving four plumbers occurred at the Crystal Palace on the 14th June, over a question of demarcation. The plumbers&apos; union claimed that all work on cast-iron soil-pipes and screwed barrel pipes was theirs, and not that of pipe-fitters, who were doing it. The heating and domestic engineers&apos; union contended that the work had always been done by their members, and that various arbitration cases and agreements throughout the country had been in their favour. A continuation of the strike would probably, on sanitary grounds, have caused the closing of the Crystal Palace to the public. A conference was held in the department on the 23rd June, pending the question of demarcation being referred to the National Board for settlement. It was pointed out to the men&apos;s representatives that the meeting was convened, not to discuss the merits of the plumbers&apos; general claim, but to effect a working arrangement in the particular case. A suggestion was made that the plumbers should do all work from tees in existing mains to sanitary and domestic fitments, it being understood that all work on waste pipes and soil-pipes in screwed barrel is plumbers&apos; work. After some discussion the suggested.wording was qualified by the insertion of &quot;and future &quot; before &quot; mains.&quot;In discussing the term &quot; mains &quot; it was pointed out that it would be better if no definition were formulated, in order that the national position might not be prejudiced. It was agreed that if in future any difficulty arose regarding demarcation, the Crystal Palace engineer would call the two parties together to discuss the particular job in dispute.An agreement between the United Operative Plumbers&apos; and Domestic Engineers&apos; Association, the National Union of Operative Heating and Domestic Engineers and General Metal Workers, and the Crystal Palace authorities was reached on these lines, without prejudice to any other local or national settlement.COMMITTEES, CONFERENCES AND DEPUTATIONS.Hours of Employment Bill. The Provisional Joint Committee of the National Industrial Conference met at Montagu. House on the 28th June, and after the Minister had explained that in framing the Hours of Employment Bill the Government had to consider the recommendations of the International. Labour Conference, held at Washington, as well as those of the Provisional Joint Committee, the meeting was adjourned to enable the trade union members to consider their position with regard to the new proposals.
QUESTIONS PENDING AND MISCELLANEOUS.^]Brass Moulders and Dressers (Clyde). The claim for an advance of Id. per hour for which the brass moulders and brass dressers on the Clyde struck on the 7th June was further discussed at a conference which was held on the 16th June. No settlement was reached, but a special conference has been arranged between the parties at which repre-sentatives of the Scottish Employers&apos; Federation of Iron and Steel Founders and the Associated Iron Moulders of Scotland will also be present. The men resumed work on the 18th June.Cable and Asbestos Workers (Bradford). The Amalgamated Society of India Rubber, Cable and Asbestos Workers, apparently under pressure from the employers&apos; side of the Asbestos Joint Industrial Council, have now decided to press Messrs. CresswelFs, Ltd., to put all wage increases in the asbestos trade into operation, and to consider the arrange-ments entered into on the 3rd May as null and void. The firm&apos;s attitude towards this application has not yet been defined, but they contend that only about two-ninths of their workers are really covered by it, whereas the agreement referred to applied to all their employees.Building Trade Operatives (Bury St. Edmunds). Although some 20 non-union men have remained at work, about 80 building trade operatives have come out at Bury St. Edmunds owing to the refusal of the master builders&apos; association to pay Grade B rates under the Eastern Counties Area scheme. During the previous week the men concerned had refused to work more than a 44-hour week. The masters&apos; association are not affiliated to the Eastern Counties Federation. The contention of the employers is that the conditions prevailing in this town render it impossible to concede B rates, mainly because the proposed housing scheme for 300 houses has not yet been started, and the builders are confined to work for private individuals and firms who would not pay more than the present rates. It is understood that the Bury St. Edmunds Council have conceded Grade B rates to the men employed by them, but, in the case of carpenters and bricklayers lately employed by the master builders, a large proportion have obtained work in other districts, and it is reported that some of the men have gone back at the old rates of pay. The strike is being watched by the Chief Conciliation Officer.Lighting Engineers (London). Following the withdrawal of Messrs. Falk, Stadelmann &amp; Co. from the proposed arbitration proceedings on a claim by the National Warehouse and General Workers&apos; Union, the other firms concerned, Messrs. B. Cars, Ltd., and the Welsbach Light Co., Ltd., have now adopted a similar course. The attitude of the union is not vet known.Local Authorities&apos; Clerical Staff (Colne and Brixham). Two cases have recently occurred in which local authorities have granted increased bonuses to the technical and clerical staffs, and in order to reduce expenditure on salaries have proposed a re-organisation of staff involving the dismissal of officers. In the case of the Colne Corporation the inter-vention of this department and of the Ministry of Health, and in the case of the Brixham Urban District Council the intervention of the Ministry of Health only, has been requested. In both cases the Ministry of Health have informed the officers&apos; association that they have no jurisdiction in regard to staffing arrangements.Sack Workers (Bristol). It is reported by the Chief Conciliation Officer that a difference exists between Messrs. A. T. James &amp; Co., sack merchants, and the Workers&apos; Union, arising out of a claim made on behalf of the women employees of the firm for an increase of wages from 27s. to 33s. per week of 50 hours. Negotiations are proceeding, and strike notices have been suspended pending a further conference.Holidays: Paper Tube Workers (Rochdale).-The Chief&apos; Conciliation Officer, Man-chester, has endeavoured to arrange a meeting between the employers and the workpeople&apos;s delegates, but the employers&apos; association refuse to alter their decision not to meet any representatives of the men while they are on strike ; the position, therefore, remains unaltered.Biscuit Bakers (Dundee).-A. strike of biscuit bakers has occurred in Dundee for the rates and conditions accorded by the Scottish Bakers&apos; Joint Industrial Council to the bread-baking industry. The workpeople are represented on the Council by the Operative Bakers and Confectioners of Scotland National Federal Union, to which body they have lately been admitted, but the employers are not represented at all, and accordingly take the view that the Councils decisions do not cover the biscuit bakers. The Chief Conciliation Officer, Glasgow, is in touch with the matter.
[Reference to matters of interest in connection with Wages and Arbitration will be found also on pages 42 to 53, 70 to 76 and 83.]Engineers (Croydon). The National Federation of Women Workers recently summoned Messrs. E. Deane &amp; Beal, Ltd., before the Munitions Tribunal for non-payment of the prescribed rate. Before.the hearing the manager called at Montagu House for advice. The firm are non-federated and contend that they are paying the district rate of wages for the class of work on which they are engaged. Arrangements were made for representa-tives of the parties to meet and discuss the position with an officer of the department-. At this meeting the National Federation of Women Workers offered to withdraw the case. if the firm would attend a conference at the Ministry. The firm agreed to this proposal and a conference will shortly take place. Failing agreement at this conference the point at issue will be referred to the Industrial Court for determination.
APPENDIX.QUESTIONS  IN PARLIAMENT.The following extracts from the Official Report of the proceedings of the House of Commons relate to questions in which the Ministry is interested.Civil Liabilities Department.Mr. Neville Chamberlain asked the Minister of Labour (1) whether, in the Staffordshire district of the Civil Liabilities Department, there were only four new applications last week ; and whether these could have been dealt with by the War Pensions Committees at Stafford and Stoke as easily and promptly as by the Civil Liabilities Department.(2) Whether his attention has been called to a statement made publicly by the late Civil Liabilities Commissioner for the Midland district that the continued existence of the Civil Liabilities Department is nothing short of a public scandal; whether three districts which were recently managed with a staff of one male and three female clerks, with one office only, are nowr worked by two men at  500 a year each, with six assistants at  250 a year each; and whether it is intended to open new offices in various towns, such as Coventry, Stafford, and Worcester, presumably with clerical staffs in attendance.Dr. Macnamara : As the answer is necessarily a long one, I shall be much obliged if my hon. friend will allow me to publish it in the Official Report.In view of the detailed, criticism of the administration of the Civil Liabilities Depart-ment which has been contributed to the Press by the late Commissioner for the Birmingham and surrounding areas, I think it is desirable to deal not merely with the points raised in the questions which have been put down by my hon. friend, but with the charges in general.It is alleged by the late Commissioner in question, Mr. Marshall. Freeman, that the department ought to have come to an end last Christmas, as the work had practically ceased. As to this, it is sufficient to say that at the 20th December, after the headquarters of the department had been re-organised, there were 32,947 cases in hand, of which. 11,900 were with Commissioners in the country awaiting settlement, and, in addition, cases were coming in at the rate of, approximately, 5,000 per week. It is true that this number was very much less than the number when the re-organisation took place.  But it must beremembered that in the cases then in hand in the neighbourhood of 70,000-.....at least 50per cent, were in the nature of accumulated arrears. It is accordingly true to say that at the date mentioned the work was not declining, and indeed showed, if anything, a tendency to increase.It is further suggested that when the decentralisation scheme came into force on the 1st June the work was at an end. As to this, the facts are that at the date in question the number of cases in hand was 17,309.The facts with regard to the Birmingham area are as follows: Cases in hand, 27th December        .........\   659Cases in hand, 1st June        ............316of which 98 cases were transferred to the Staffordshire and Cheshire area.It may be noticed in passing that when an. inspection was made of the Birmingham office on the 21st February it was found that there were 710 cases in hand, of which 334 had been in the office for over two months.As regards the statement made in the second part of the question, it is true that for the week ending the 19th June there were only four new applications in the Staffordshire sub-district, but there were also 33 other cases forwarded from headquarters for further con-sideration during that week and the preceding week. There were also 98 other cases in hand when the work was transferred to the new Examining Commissioner. Of these 98, I may fairly assume that at least half were still outstanding at the close of the week in question. As regards the suggestion in the first question that the four cases there men-tioned representing as they do, and as I have just shown, a comparatively small part of the work of the sub-district could have been dealt with by the War Pensions Committees at Stafford and Stoke, that is not so. The four cases in question were those of able-bodied ex-Service men, a class of case with which the Wrar Pensions Committee have never dealt. The same is true of all the cases wnich I have dealt with as coming under the Staffordshire sub-district.
418Appendix--continued.These facts, I think, dispose of the allegation that the work is at an end, and that the continued existence of the department is a public scandal.I come now to the suggestion that the rerorganisation was unnecessary, ineffective, and extravagant. With regard to the necessity of the re-organisation, it is stated by Mr. Marshall Freeman that the department was satisfactory till August, 1919, but thereafter, owing to change in the control, it became unsatisfactory. The fact, however, is that the change in control did not take place till November, 1919, and that at the date of the change arrears had accumulated which were in the neighbourhood of 70,000. The reasons for this state of affairs have been explained to the House of Commons at other times, and it is not necessary again to traverse the ground.As to the suggestion that the re-organisation was ineffective, the facts are that the department are now dealing with current applications and are keeping up to date. In order to achieve this end, it was necessary to substitute for the part-time Commissioners whole-time officers, whose services would be at the complete disposal of the department. The original Commissioners, of whom Mr. Marshall Freeman was one, were on a part-time basis. The full-time newly-appointed men were all ex-Service men, and were appointed solely on merits. These men had had several months of practical experience in the depart-ment as examining officers. By sending them into the country time and expense were saved in dealing with applications, and the unnecessary duplication of examination of applications by Commissioners in the provinces and examining officers at headquarters, which had obtained, was avoided.As to the suggestion that the new scheme is extravagant, the facts are that for the month of October the salary bill was  9,07618s. Id. ; for the month of April,  10,368 11s. 9d. The increase is, to a large extent, accounted for by the substantial recent war increases granted by the Treasury to the clerical staff.So far as Mr. Marshall Freeman&apos;s own office is concerned, the facts are that Mr. Freeman was treated as in charge of the areas of Birmingham, Warwickshire, Worcestershire, and Staffordshire. So far from its being the fact that he was only assisted by a staff of one male and three female clerks, he was assisted during 1919 by two Commissioners at  350 per annum, plus subsistence, and had the part-time assistance at various periods of 13 Assistant Commissioners, the expense of the office for the year being, roughly,  2,130. On the other hand, the statements with regard to the new organisation are equally mis-leading. The new area, consisting of Birmingham, Worcester, and Warwick, has one Commissioner at  500 per annum, and three investigating officers at  250 per annum. The investigators are stationed at Birmingham, and no branch offices are being opened. This disposes of the final suggestion in the second question.The Staffordshire district has been incorporated with Chester, and has a Commissioner and two investigating officers, corresponding to a Commissioner helped by Assistant Commissioners under the old scheme. The total expenditure on the scheme is roughly  2,000, representing a small saving.I have dealt with this matter at length because of the publicity which has been given to the charges. I am confident that my hon. friend will realise that so far from the attack being justified, it helps to throw into relief the great advance which has been made as a result of re-organisation. And whilst I am most anxious in every direction to secure prudent economies in the administration of the department for which I am responsible, I hope my hon. friend and the House generally will support me in the appeal I make that the last thing in which we should be niggardly is the machinery which enables us to deal promptly and effectively with the needs of the ex-Service men. My hon. friend does not need to be told by me that great hardship is bound to be inflicted upon persons to whom we are all under a deep obligation if departmental administration in respect of their needs is not thoroughly efficient. (30$ June.)Mechanic and Torpedo Ratings.Commander Bellairs asked the Minister of Labour whether naval electricians on leaving the Navy are able to join a trade union.Dr. Macnamara: It is presumed that my hon. and gallant friend refers to electrical artificers. I understand that according to the regulations laid down by the Admiralty such men on entering the Navy must be thoroughly efficient fitters and turners or instru-ment makers with at least five years&apos; practical experience. So far as I am aware, such men on discharge are accepted for membership by the appropriate trade union.  If,(b 16259)L
however, my hon. and gallant friend has in mind the case of certain seamen ratings, such as torpedo gunners&apos; mates, leading torpedo men, and seamen torpedo men, I understand that these men are not in general freely admitted to full membership of craft unions on leaving the Service, not having been employed in mechanic ratings. (28th June.)Fruit Pickers, Scotland: Railway Fares.Captain W. Benn asked the Minister of Transport what course he proposes to take in reference to the special railway fares for women and girls in Scotland engaged in fruit picking.Mr. Neal: This question has been under consideration by me in consultation with the parties concerned and the railway companies, and in the result it has been agreed to grant a concession for this year by authorising the issue of special tickets at a fare and one-third of the present single fare for the double journey. I can hold out no hope of a similar concession being continued next year. I have asked my right hon. friend the Minister of Labour to be good enough to undertake the detailed arrangements with the railway companies, and it will be necessary to impose some geographical limitation within which the facilities can be granted.-(28$ June.)Ex-Service Men: Training and Employment.Mr. C. Palmer asked the Minister of Labour what progress has been made in the negotiation with trade unions concerning the facilities to be given for the training and employment of disabled ex-soldiers.Dr. macnamara: We are at work upon the matters referred to by my hon. friend, and we have the great advantage of a standing committee on the re-employment of ex-Service men, which is representative of employers, trade unions, and ex-Service men&apos;s associations. We have 23,500 disabled men unemployed, and are pressing in a number of directions for an extension of the application amongst public bodies and private firms of the National Scheme. We have 23,600 disabled men awaiting training some of them, I am sorry to say, have been waiting for a long time. But fairly good progress is being made in both respects.Mr. Lawson asked the Minister of Labour whether he will issue a White Paper showing the details of the scheme for training ex-soldiers and setting forth the allowances received by the men at each stage of training.Dr. macnamara: Yes, Sir; I think the suggestion a good one, and will forthwith prepare and lay a paper as my hon. friend asks.Mr. Lawson asked the Minister of Labour whether he is aware of the extreme dis-satisfaction prevailing among the ex-soldiers now being trained under his scheme on account of the allowances being insufficient to meet their needs; and whether he will reconsider such allowances with a view to increasing the same.Dr. macnamara: Yes, Sir; many representations have been made to me on the point. Their purport has been placed before my colleagues. I am not in a position to give any undertaking in the matter. (30$ June.)Cookery Training Centre, Erith.Mr. Mills asked the Minister of Labour why the cookery training centre at Erith, Kent, is being closed after 10 weeks&apos; training has been given ; whether the training period was fixed at six months ; and, in view of the progress of the pupils, will he reconsider the decision to close down the- centre in this manner.Dr. macnamara: I am glad to be able to inform my hon. friend that the cookery training centre at Erith is to be continued in order to complete the full three months&apos; course, which is the time fixed for training in domestic subjects. (30$ June.)Trade Boards (Jewellery and Watchmaking).Mr. W. Graham asked the Minister of Labour whether his attention has been called to the low rates of remuneration paid to the various classes of men engaged in the jewellery and watchmaking trade in Scotland ; whether he is aware that fully one-third of the men
engaged are earning only  2 10s. to  3 per week ; &apos; whether representations have been made to the employers by the National Union of Gold, Silver, and Allied Trades for an advance on such rates or for arbitration, and that both requests have been refused, with no offer by the employers ; and whether, having regard to the conditions prevailing in this trade in Scotland, he will consider the establishment of a Trade Board in order to bring .these workers approximately into line with the English conditions.*Dr. Macnamara : I have received no representations as to the payment of low wages to workers in the jewellery and watchmaking trade in Scotland, and I have no information with regard to the application for an advance on present rates referred to in the question. I will, however, inquire into the matter. With reference to the last part of my horn friend&apos;s question, I propose to have an investigation made, as soon as practicable, into the conditions prevailing in the trade throughout Great Britain, with a view to ascertaining whether the establishment of a Trade Board for the trade or any branch of the trade is desirable. (1st July.)Glass Works, Alloa: Trade Dispute.Mr. Myers asked the Minister of Labour if he is aware that a dispute at the glass works at Alloa has been in operation for 27 weeks, involving the stoppage of more than 100 workmen ; that the employers concerned refuse to meet representatives of the workmen in negotiation, decline to be parties to any method of arbitration, and have rejected strong representations made by a joint committee from the employers&apos; association and workmen&apos;s union in the trade to discuss the matters in dispute ; and whether his department are taking any steps with a view to bringing the parties together and effecting a settlement of the dispute.Dr. Macnamara : I am advised that the facts are as stated in my hon. friend&apos;s ques-tion. My department has been in constant communication with the parties to the dispute, but I regret to state that up to the present it has not been possible to effect a settlement. -(28$ June.)DEBATES IN  PARLIAMENT.Ministry of Mines Bill.Sir Robert Home, in moving the second reading, explained the necessity for con-tinuing to control coal exports, which involved carrying on a system of arranging the amount of profit, and made it necessary to fix pithead prices and to regulate wages. The Bill gave these necessary powers to the Minister of Mines, for a year from the 31st August. On the question of the nationalisation of minerals, the Government meant to carry out their pledge, but in view of the urgent need of legislation before the 30th August, it was desired not to complicate the present Bill. He referred to the experience of the Yorkshire coalminers&apos; strike and the railway strike as discountenancing the idea that nationalisation would bring industrial peace, and quoted Mr. F. Hodges&apos; pamphlet to show that the miners&apos; demand was a form of nationalisation which would give the State all financial risk without control. The Government were content to base the working of the industry upon private initiative and enterprise, but recognised the miners&apos; claims for greater amenities of life, for greater knowledge of the industry, and for the workers to become more directly interested in profits. The overlapping of Government departments dealing&apos;with the industry rendered necessary a single department for mines, and the size of the coal industry alone warranted a separate department.Sir Robert Home proceeded to explain the provisions of the Bill as regards the Advisory Committee to the Minister, the pit committees, district committees, Area Boards and the National Board, laying special emphasis on the powers of the Area Board to formulate schemes for adjusting workmen&apos;s pay on the basis of the profits of the industry in the area, in accordance with general principles laid down by the National Board. The Minister would be able to require compliance with any recommendations of any of these committees. The levy of Id. per ton on coal raised during the next four years for welfare improvements was also explained.Mr. Brace, moving the rejection of the Bill, said that it did very little to restore the confidence of the Miners&apos; Federation in the Government. The real basis of the Bill was the proposal to adjust remuneration according to &quot; profits within the area.&quot;  The White(B 16259) L 2
Appendix-continued.Paper on the industry for the three months ending the 31st March showed that several areas made a loss and others a profit. The industry had settled that it must be treated as a national unit. The prosperity of the prosperous coalfields should be used to balance the losses elsewhere. The alternative was to advance the selling price of coal in the areas losing money to a standard giving a wage equal to that in Wales, which meant an enormous increase. %The miners could not work the Bill.Sir Clifford Cory complained that the Bill was too near nationalisation, insisted that the Minister for Mines should be compelled to regulate prices when he altered wages, and criticised the composition of the Advisory Committee as including members with no direct interest in the industry.Mr. Stephen Walsh said that the real effect of the Bill was to throw the industry back into the hands of private owners. It was utterly impossible to go back to private enterprise. Within twelve months all effective control would disappear; the establishment of pit committees was pure dressing, and not very good at that. Under control a great deal of the passion and the friction among miners was allayed. He repeated Mr. Brace&apos;s argument as to the effect of regulating wages according to the profits in the area, when some areas were worked at a profit and others at a loss.Mr. Hartshorn condemned the Bill because it would add enormously to the cost of inland coal. Statistics showed that the recent increase was quite unnecessary; and if the miners accepted their leaders&apos; advice they would fight to compel the Government to take it off, even if it involved a strike. The Bill virtually established compulsory arbitration by setting over the various committees an independent chairman with a casting vote.Mr. T. A. Lewis argued that the Bill was an attempt to incorporate all the substance of the agreed Reports of the Royal Commission. The Bill made a stride in the direction of more closely associating the miners with the control of their daily life.Mr. N. Chamberlain welcomed the welfare provisions of the Bill. He suggested that as the profit-sharing scheme had been rejected by the miners&apos; representatives it would be well to drop the clauses dealing with this plan and with the various committees.Sir Robert Home, in reply, said it was obvious that the measure would be far more acceptable to Labour members if the profit-sharing part of the Bill were dropped, and undertook that before the Committee stage the Government would &quot; look, with perhaps a different eye,&quot; at these provisions of the Bill. The scheme for a series of committees, however, represented one of the fundamental ideas on which the Government^ Labour policy was based. An arrangement by which recommendations of representatives of employers and employed might receive the Ministers sanction, and become law, reached an entirely different stage in Labour legislation from that previously attained.Mr. Brace&apos;s argument that under the Bill wages must be reduced in several districts was based on statistics referring to a period when coal was sold to the inland consumer at a loss. That was no longer the case. Moreover, the Bill provided that so long as the export of coal was controlled, no order would be operative which allowed the Area Committees to begin fixing^wages. As long as the shortage continued which compelled the control of exports, the profits of the industry would continue to be distributed throughout the whole of the coalfields.The second reading was carried by 217 votes against 91. (30$ June.)Unemployment Insurance Bill.The Bill was considered on Report, on the 2nd July.Mr. Sexton moved an amendment exempting employed persons from any contribution under the scheme. In a well ordered State there should be no unemployment; where private enterprise failed to secure this end and the State did not provide work, the industry and the State together should bear the burden. In the case of dockers and other casual workers the waiting period had the effect of permanent disqualification from benefit. The working classes were being burdened with contributions and documents in a way which would produce very vigorous opposition.Lieut-Commander Kenworthy, who seconded the amendment, said that the whole scheme of unemployment insurance was wrong and could not last much longer.  The
problem would never be solved until each industry was responsible for its own unemploy-ment and each casual industry was decasualised. In certain industries output was re-restricted and men thrown out of employment to create an artificial scarcity, and such cases would be more numerous in the future.Dr. Macnamara opposed the amendment. This amendment, together with others introduced in Committee, which increased the benefit to 20s. a week and abolished the waiting period, would raise the cost per head to Is. id. per week. The State contribution could not be increased, and the employer would have to pay Is. 2d. a week instead of 8d. The workers would be left with no claim to a share in the administration of the scheme. The Government proposed to meet the case of the casual worker by reducing the waiting period from six days to three.Mr. Clynes supported the amendment, urging the analogy of the Workmen&apos;s Com-pensation Act in support of throwing the burden on the industry. The industry could bear the charge, as it already did in the case of those in the higher branches of service.Mr. Spencer quoted the case of the mining industry, where for four years benefit had been paid at 18s. a week, starting from the first day of unemployment, and charged entirely on the industry.  The miners would be worse off under the Bill than before.The amendment was rejected by 168 votes to 46. *Dr. Macnamara moved an amendment providing that if a workman was not employed for three days consecutively, then obtained employment for a period not exceeding six weeks, and then was again unemployed for three consecutive days, the two periods of three days might be linked together for purposes of benefit, without a further waiting period.  The amendment was agreed to.Mr. T. Thomson moved an amendment restricting disqualification in case of unemploy-ment due to a trade dispute to those who withdrew their labour to participate in the dispute.  The amendment was seconded by Mr. Clynes.Dr. Macnamara agreed that the problem was very difficult; but failing the production of a workable proposal acceptable to the employers and the employed alike, the best thing was what the Bill proposed. In reply to Mr. Clynes, he repeated that if such a proposal was produced, he would do what he could to secure its embodiment in the Bill.After further discussion the amendment was rejected.Dr. Macnamara moved an amendment providing that the period of disqualification where employment was lost through misconduct or by voluntarily leaving employment. should be six weeks, or such shorter period, not less than one week, as might be determined under the provisions of the Act.  The amendment was accepted.Mr. Clynes moved an amendment excluding societies approved under the National Health Insurance Act from administering the scheme. He pointed out that the friendly societies had hitherto no facilities, as the trade unions had, for providing for workmen in relation to unemployment. They had no position within the workshop, no direct contact with employers as employers, and no touch with the State in its functions in respect of this problem. There was no need for any extension of their scope ; the trade unions and the State could do all that was necessary. The clause would be the cause of a very unhappy quarrel.Lieut.-Colonel Sir A. Warren stated that there was no quarrel on the part of the friendly societies. The Unemployment Insurance Act of 1911 dealt only with, industries where all employees were organised in trade unions. The position to-day was widely different. The friendly societies believed that four or five million persons insurable under the Bill were not members of trade unions. The case had been prejudged when it was said that the friendly societies could not do the work. Many trade unions had not yet administered unemployment insurance benefit. The friendly societies were willing to do all they reasonably could to see that a unionist was insured through his union, and that new union members should be transferred to their union for this purpose.
Dr. Macnamara pointed out that it was vital that machinery should exist, not merely for administering benefit, but for putting men in touch with suitable employment. If the friendly societies sought this work, they must have efficient machinery for this purpose, and he proposed to introduce further amendments to secure that object. The friendly societies could not use their health funds for this purpose. The Government proposed to leave the amendment to the House. He believed that in six months most members would look back with surprise at the storm which had arisen over this matter.Mr. G. Roberts held that members representing the trade unions were not serving the interests of these bodies by forcing the matter to an acute issue, but the friendly societies would do well to withdraw their claim. Their machinery would have to be re-organised completely. The organised workers saw in the proposal a desire to undermine their organisation.The debate was adjourned.

</content>
</cab>
