<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/42/41 images: 418-427</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1943.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 491.1st November, 1943.WAR CABINET.SUEZ CANAL.   .Memorandum by the Minister of State.I circulate herewith a memorandum prepared by the Foreign Office in con-sultation with the Treasury and Ministry of War Transport, and approved bythose Departments, in regard to the future of the Suez Canal and of the SuezCanal Company&apos;s concession.The point on which an immediate decision is required is set forth in para-graph 4. If the general consensus of opinion among the Departments concernedthat it is essential to ensure a &quot; stand still &quot; arrangement after the liberation ofParis from German occupation is endorsed, it is for consideration whether thisshould be arranged in concert primarily with the Egyptian Government or withthe French National Committee.Whichever alternative is adopted it may be anticipated that the party con-cerned is likely to seek further elucidation of the future policy of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment towards the Company. The extent to which this information can begiven must depend on the degree to which Ministers may at present feel themselvesable to decide as between the alternative policies outlined in paragraph 8.Finally, the Departments concerned would welcome the War Cabinefsapproval of their joint recommendation that the future defence (as opposed to theoperation) of the Canal shall be assured by the negotiation of a revised Suez CanalConvention, to take the place of the out-of-date Convention of 1888, the respon-sibility to devolve, under the new Convention, on His Majesty&apos;s Government andthe Egyptian Government. A copy of the Convention in question is annexed tothe memorandum.R. K. L.Foreign Office, 1st Novem-ber, 1943.Suez Canal.(Secret.) . . . ,THE object of this paper is to state the present position as regards theseparate, but closely connected, questions of (1) the defence of the Suez UanalZone and (2) the administration of the Suez Canal. The second question, thoughof great importance, is really subordinate to the first. This paper has beenwritten at the present time because a certain situation (see paragraph 4) will arisewith regard to the Company now administering the Canal when France has beenfreed of enemy control; and we have explored the broad lines of policy whichmight be pursued as regards the second question in, or in anticipation of, thatevent, since recent interdepartmental discussions have shown that there are, infact, various courses open, each of which claims its adherents. Furthermore, thisexamination has made it clear that it is essential to be sure of our policy withregard to the first question.2.   The right to secure the military defence of the Suez Canal is in turnconnected with the observance of the international provisions with regard tonavigation on the Canal.   The right of military defence necessarily falls to someGovernment or Governments and not to a Company.   The present position is as;12188   [26336[ B
follows : The Suez Canal Convention of 1888 provides that the Canal shall befree and open in time of war as well as in time of peace to every vessel of com-merce or of war without distinction of flag. The Canal shall never be blockadedand though belligerent warships may use the Canal, no act of war may be com&apos;mitted in the Canal area. No Power may embark or disembark troops or materialsof war in the Canal area. Under the Convention the Egyptian Government is totake measures for the execution of the Suez Canal Convention, but if the EgyptianGovernment does not possess sufficient resources it is to call upon the OttomanGovernment to assist it. It is then provided that the provisions about committingacts of hostility, warships stopping there more than 24 hours, embarking or dis-embarking troops, &amp;e, shall not interfere with the measures taken by the Egyptianor Ottoman Governments to safeguard the Canal and to ensure the fulfilment ofthe provisions of the Convention, or for the defence of Egypt. It followed fromthis that under the Convention Egypt and the Ottoman Empire could stationtroops and warships there. When Turkey came into the war of 1914-18 GreatBritain declared a protectorate over Egypt and claimed to succeed to all therights of the Ottoman Government with regard to the protection of the Canal, aclaim which was recognised in the Peace Treaties (Article 152 of the Treaty ofVersailles). In 1922 when, by unilateral declaration of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment, Egypt became independent, His Majesty&apos;s Government made reservationsintended to cover inter alia the right to defend Egypt and the Canal. Under theTreaty of Alliance of 1936 with Egypt, this right of His Majesty&apos;s Government,together with the Egyptian Government, to defend the Canal is preserved. Theposition therefore has been up to now that, while the actual operation of theCanal is conducted by a company which is predominantly French, the Govern-ments which have the right to defend the Canal are the Egyptian Government andHis Majesty&apos;s Government. Up to the present time the fact that the operationof the Canal has been in predominantly French hands, whereas the right todefend the Canal is predominantly in British hands, has not given rise to seriousdifficulties, but this may not always be so in the future.3. The Suez Canal Company is an Egyptian company, holding a concessionfrom the Egyptian Government which expires in 1968. But at the same timethe administrative centre of the Company is (under the statutes) in Paris, thestaff of the Company in Egypt are predominantly of French nationality, thereis a large majority of French Directors on the Board (19 against 10 British) andby a special arrangement French law is applicable to &quot; sa constitution commeSociete et les rapports des associes entre eux.&quot; It is, moreover, an undertakingof which the French are exceedingly proud, and to which they will cling withgreat tenacity. Again, His Majesty&apos;s Government hold some 44 per cent, of theshare capital, and there are some though probably inconsiderable privateBritish holdings. The Canal is a vital Imperial communication, and before thewar roughly 6 out of every 10 ships using the Canal were British. And. sinceJanuary 1942, the British Directors have directly administered the Companyunder emergency powers conferred on them by the French Directors, while Britisharms have ensured the safety of the Canal itself. [In practice the BritishDirectors have exercised control since the collapse of France, but up toJanuary 1942 the French Directors were still nominally in charge, and indeedactually issued instructions (which were not, however, acted upon except withthe London Directors&apos; approval), though to a steadily diminishing degree.] TheEgyptian Government have taken powers to provide for the administration ofcompanies operating in Egypt which were controlled by persons in enemyor enemy-occupied territory. In the proclamation granting these powers, it wasexpressly stated that the Suez Canal Company (which would otherwise havecome under the proclamation) should be the subject of a later special proclama-tion. The Egyptian Government at one moment proposed to pass measuresestablishing an Egyptian &quot;Delegation&quot; of the Board of the Company withexecutive powers and composed of the Egyptian Directors, but, on being toldquite firmly that His Majesty&apos;s Government would not countenance such a step,they did not proceed with the proposal. On the other hand, the legal positionof the Company is at present insecure because there is some doubt as to thevalidity of the powers conferred on the London Directors by the Board in France,and the power of the London Directors to administer the Company can onlybe put on a secure legal basis by means of an Egyptian proclamation.4. Should it become possible for the French Directors again to exercisetheir functions, as they would certainly claim to be able to do once the enemyhad been driven out of Paris, the powers conferred on the London Directors
would lapse, Paris would again become the administrative centre and regularBoard Meetings could be convened as formerly. It is regarded by some Depart-ments as essential that there should be a breathing space during which the controlof the Company should remain, at any rate de facto, in London. This require-ment might be met in one of two ways. It would be possible to devise a decreeto be passed by the Egyptian Government which would so validate the existingpowers of the London Directors that those powers would remain in the hands ofthe London Directors until such time, after the liberation of Paris, as it mightbe appropriate to allow the French Directors to resume their position. It wouldnot be unreasonable to maintain that the &quot; normal &quot; working of the Company&apos;sadministration could not be restored until there had been an opportunity toexamine what changes have taken place during the enemy occupation in, e.g., theFrench holdings. To achieve our object by means of an Egyptian decree would,however, be liable to upset French susceptibilities; and would form an undesirableprecedent for future interference by the Egyptian Government in the Company&apos;saffairs. In view of our earlier pressure on the Egyptian Government to refrainfrom passing a decree it might be difficult to get them to pass one to meet ourconvenience without inserting provisions to assert Egyptian requirements. Inother words, we might seem to be joining hands with the Egyptian Governmentao-ainst the French interests. An alternative method of approach would beto reach agreement with the French Committee of National Liberation, who havebeen recognised by His Majesty&apos;s Government as in principle the body qualifiedto defend French interests abroad, before the liberation of Paris if possible. Theobject of such agreement would be to ensure either the maintenance of thestatus quo, even after the liberation of Paris, or at least that the French Directors,if they were allowed to resume their position in the administration of theCompany, would not embark on any policy or course of action concerning thepresent or future status of the Canal except within the framewrork of a generalpolicy which would first be agreed between His Majesty&apos;s Government and theFrench Government and any other interested Governments when the circumstancespermit. It would also be necessary to get the future French Government toratify the promises made by the French Committee of National Liberation, asindeed may also be necessary in connexion with other arrangements made by thesame committee. The Suez Canal Company is not a French Company; but theGovernment of France should be in a position to impose such a ruling&quot; upon theFrench Directors. Alternatively it might be thought better to delay the approachto any French authority until there are clearer indications as to the futureGovernment of France; but it is important to bear in mind that the liberationof Paris would automatically readmit the French Directors to their preponderantposition and the delay may be prejudicial to the object in view. On the otherband, the view is also held that it would not be worth while to attempt to securea longer delay in the resumption of administration by Paris than is necessaryfor administrative reasons and in order to ensure that enemy influence iseliminated. The danger of antagonising the French and so jeopardising theirco-operation in a long-term solution outweighs, in this view, any advantageaccruing from the temporary prolongation of exclusive British control.5. In whatever sense this immediate question may be decided, it will alsope desirable to define, before Paris is liberated, the main lines of the policy ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government towards the future of the Company so that theDirectors may know where they stand. And any policy must take into considera-tion the facts (a) that in 1968. if the concession is not prolonged by agreement,the undertaking falls, almost literally lock, stock and barrel, into the handsof the Egyptian Government, and (b) that some uncommonly solid inducement,or threat, or.argument is accordingly required to induce the Egyptians to forgothis advantage (the Company only obtain an indemnity for &apos;1&apos;abandon de sonmateriel et des objets mobiliers &quot;) and. what is perhaps even more relevant, toovercome their nationalistic ambitions, which asserted themselves with incon-venient violence in this, connexion as long ago as 1910. The following is anextract from a Foreign Office memorandum recording the incident:  &quot; The proposal [for the prolongation of the concession] was undoubtedlyprofitable to Egypt.....Nevertheless, nationalist passions were arousedboth among the public and the General Assembly; the Prime Minister.-tSoutros Ghali, was assassinated, and although the draft agreement wassponsored by the Khedive and Zaghlul Pasha, then Minister of Justice theGeneral Assembly turned it down with contumely.&quot;[26336] jj 2
During the abortive treaty discussions between Lord Curzon and Adly Pasha in1921 the question again came under discussion, but the.Egyptian Governmentrejected the proposals put forward on that occasion by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment largely on the ground that &quot; and mention of the subject in the treaty wouldbe fatal to its reception in Egypt.&quot;6. The vital interest of the United Kingdom is that the responsibility forthe defence of the Canal zone should be vested in His Majesty&apos;s Government; andthat the undertaking should be so administered as to facilitate the exercise of thisresponsibility. It is further a major British interest that the canal dues shouldbe fixed at the lowest rate compatible with efficient administration and with areasonable return to the shareholders, including the Treasury. It is, finally,desirable (if not a major British interest) that the British Empire should havea share in the management and control of the undertaking consistent with itspredominant position in the area and as the greatest user of the Canal.7. There is agreement that to safeguard the first, and vital, interest theInternational Convention of 1888, which is in any case out of date, should hereplaced by a new International Convention. The existing Convention is out cfdate because (a) In existing circumstances &quot; The Government of the United Kingdom&quot;must be read for &quot; the Ottoman Government &quot;;(L) There is great unreality in many of its provisions; and(c) Article 8 has never been in force.The new Convention should contain a provision that His Majesty&apos;s Government,as trustee for the United Nations, should, together with the Egyptian Govern-ment, be responsible for the defence of the Canal and guarantors for the enforce-ment of the terms of the Convention. Such a provision would be of greatimportance as a long-term safeguard of the British position, since under thetreaty of alliance with Egypt the right of His Majesty&apos;s Government to.protectthe Canal comes under review in 1957 at the latest, and the question may, if noagreement with Egypt results, be taken to arbitration. Moreover, the provisionsof the present convention which govern the use of the Canal by merchant shippingshould be clarified and extended. The provision that the Canal shall always befree and open, in peace and war. for merchant vessels and warships withoutdistinction of flag should remain; but additional provisions should ensure(1) the efficient maintenance of the Canal, and (2) direct protection for theusers of the Canal as regards the level of dues (cf., the Panama Canal Treaty withthe United States of America, and the provisions of the Versailles Treatyregarding the Kiel Canal).8.   The following policies have been suggested : (i) To permit the restoration of the status quo ante June 1940, to clear theCompany of enemy influence, and then to combine with the French inendeavouring to negotiate with the Egyptian Government a prolongation ofthe concession to the Company as at present constituted. The disadvantages ofthis policy are that it offers little hope of success so far as the negotiation isconcerned (short, that is to say, of forcible methods) : that, if France were anenemy in any future hostilities, the French personnel could sabotage the Canal;and that it does not secure to British interests the consideration to which theirpredominant use of the Canal entitles them.(ii) The cancellation of the concession to the existing Company and the grantof a concession for a more extended period to a Company differently constitutedand technically Egyptian, in which French participation would be diminishedand British and Egyptian participation increased, the. increase of Britishparticipation being sufficient to bring the Canal under British operational j&apos;control. This solution could only be brought about either with the agreement ofthe existing French-controlled Company or by the absolute confiscation of theirrights.   It seems unlikely that the existing Company could be brought to agree toit, and to confiscate their rights would (apart from the question of the generaldesirability of encouraging confiscatory measures) rouse violent and &quot;lastingresentment in France, and be contrary to our assurances regarding the restorationof France. Moreover, so far as the Egyptian Government are concerned, theywould be unlikely to agree save in response to a mixture of inducement andthreats; the inducement of (a) the material advantages which would accrue toEgypt as the result of the transference of the Company&apos;s central offices fromFrance to Egypt: and of possible increases in the number of Egyptian directors
and of Egyptian royalties combined with the threat (b) that if they refused theywould open the way to a demand for international control which they could notresist; or by bringing the status of the Canal into a possible bargain overCyrenaica. Even if the other difficulties in the way of this course could be over-come, there would remain the practical difficulty of replacing French staff byBritish, and the friction and possibly dangerous inefficiency of a mixed staffduring the transition period.(iii) The conversion of the present Canal Company into a public utilityservice on the general grounds that an undertaking of this magnitude and inter-national importance should no longer continue to be in the hands of a profit-making concern. If this policy were adopted, the revised convention referred toin paragraph 6 might provide that the operation of the Canal should be entrustedto a public utility service. And, assuming that His Majesty&apos;s Government hadsecured in the convention the responsibility for the defence of the Canal, therewould be an argument for trying to obtain that the public utility service should beunder predominantly British, or at any rate Anglo-Egyptian control. Alterna-tively the concession could be regrantecl to an international body representative ofthe maritime United Nations, who would confirm the present French Company asManagers in order to reduce their natural hostility to any interference with theirprospects. This solution falls short of the full attainment of British preponder-ance, at any rate in peace time, but it would be reasonable that when the UnitedKingdom was made responsible for defence, His Majesty&apos;s Government should begiven power to insist on the Canal&apos;s offices and workshops being so staffed as notto jeopardise the safety of the Canal in war. It, perhaps, offers the best hope ofovercoming (a) French insistence on something very like the status quo ante, and(6) Egyptian nationalistic ambition Egypt &quot;could scarcely hold out against asolution imposed by the United Nations, on which she would, of course, beconsulted. There would remain the financial difficulty of providing &apos; thecompensation that could fairly be claimed by the shareholders, &amp;c., in respect ofthe period up to 1968. The present value, as in 1946. of net profits for theremainder of the concession period on the basis of those earned during the last fiveyears before 1939 would be in the neighbourhood of  80,000,000. A claim wouldno doubt also be made by the Egyptian Government for compensation for loss ofthe d ues which could be charged after 1968. It is not possible to estimate whatthe Egyptians might ask for, but on the assumption that they might charge asdues the utmost that the traffic would bear, this claim too would be likely to besubstantial. It might, however, be possible to settle the Egyptian claim by othermeans, e.g., as part of a bargain over Cyrenaica. It may be noted that thissolution need not create an awkward precedent for the United States as regardsthe Panama Canal, since they took the precaution of obtaining the cession of thecanal zone, and are therefore in an entirely different position. 0But the case for itwould be greatly strengthened if internationalisation were adopted as a generalpolicy for such waterways as the Kiel (and maybe the Corinth) Canal.13th October, 1943.Annex.CONVENTION BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN. GERMANY, AUSTRIA-HUNGARY, SPAIN, FRANCE, ITALY, THE NETHERLANDS.RUSSIA. AND TURKEY, RESPECTING THE FREE NAVIGATIONOF THE SUEZ MARITIME CANAL.Signed at Constantinople, 29th October, 1888.(Translation.)Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland,Empress of India; His Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of 1 russia; MisMajesty the Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia, &amp;c and Apostolic King ofHungary; His Majesty the King of Spain, and in his name the Queen Regent oithe Kingdom; the President of the French Republic; His Majesty the King ofItaly; His Maiestv the King of the Netherlands, Grand Duke of Luxembourg, &amp;c;His Majesty the Emperor of All the Russias; and His Majesty the Emperor ofthe Ottomans; wishing to establish, bv a Conventional Act, a definite system
destined to guarantee at all times, and for all the Powers, the free use of the SuezMaritime Canal, and thus to complete the system under which the navigationof this Canal has been placed by the Firman of His Imperial Majesty the Sultan,dated the 22nd February, 1866 (2 Zilkade, 1282), and sanctioning the Concessionsof His Highness the Khedive, have named as their Plenipotentiaries, that isto say : Her Majesty the Queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain andIreland, Empress of India, the Right, Honourable Sir WilliamArthur White, her Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary;His Majesty the Emperor of Germany, King of Prussia, M. Joseph deRadowitz, his Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary;His Majesty the Emperor of Austria, King of Bohemia, &amp;c, andApostolic King of Hungary, M. Henri, Baron de Calice, hisAmbassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary;His Majesty the King of Spain, and in his name the Queen Regent ofthe Kingdom, Don Miguel Florez y Garcia, his Charge d&apos;Affaires;The President of the French Republic. M. Gustave Louis Lannes, Countde Montebello. Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary ofFrance;His Majesty the King of Italy, M. Albert, Baron Blanc, his AmbassadorExtraordinary and Plenipotentiary;His Majesty the King of the Netherlands, Grand Duke of Luxembourg,&amp;c, M. Gustave Keun, his Charge d&apos;Affaires;His Majesty the Emperor of All the Russias, M. Alexandre de Nelidow,his Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary;His Majesty the Emperor of the Ottomans, Mehemmed Said Pasha, hisMinister for Foreign Affairs;Who, having communicated to each other their respective full powers, foundin good and due form, have agreed upon the following Articles : Article I.The Suez Maritime Canal shall always be free and open, in time of war as intime of peace, to every vessel of commerce or of war, without distinction of flag.Consequently, the High Contracting Parties agree not in any way to interferewith the free use of the Canal, in time of wrar as in time of peace.The Canal shall never be subjected to the exercise of the right of blockade.Article II.The High Contracting Parties, recognising that the Fresh-Water Canalis indispensable to the Maritime Canal, take note of the engagements of HisHighness the Khedive towards the Universal Suez Canal Company as regardsthe Fresh-Water Canal; which engagements are stipulated in a Conventionbearing date the 18th March. 1863, containing an expose and four Articles.They undertake not to interfere in any way with the security of that Canaland its branches, the working of which shall not be exposed to any attempt atobstruction.Article III.The High Contracting Parties likewise undertake to respect the plant,establishments, buildings and works of the Maritime Canal and of the Fresh-Water Canal.Article IV.The Maritime Canal remaining open in time of war as a free passage, evento the ships of war of belligerents, according to the terms of Article I of thepresent Treaty, the High Contracting Parties agree that no right of war, no actof hostility, nor any act having for its object to obstruct the free navigation ofthe Canal, shall be committed in the Canal and its ports of access, as well aswithin a radius of 3 marine miles from those ports, even though the OttomanEmpire should be one of the belligerent Powers.Vessels of war of belligerents shall not revictual or take in stores in the Canaland its ports of access, except in so far as may be strictly necessary. The transitof the aforesaid vessels through the Canal shall be effected with the least possibledelay, in accordance with the Regulations in force, and without any other inter-mission than that resulting from the necessities of the service.
Their stay at Port Said and in the roadstead of Suez shall not exceed twentyfour hours, except in case of distress.   In such case they shall be bound to leaveas soon as possible   An interval of twenty-four hours shall always elapse betweenthe sailing of a belligerent ship from one of the ports of access and the departureof a ship belonging to the hostile Power.Article V.In time of war belligerent Powers shall not disembark nor embark withinthe Canal and its ports of access either troops, munitions, or materials of warBut m case of an accidental hindrance in the Canal, men may be embarked ordisembarked at the ports of access by detachments not exceeding 1 000 men witha corresponding amount of war material. &apos;Article VI.Prizes shall be subjected, in all respects, to the same rules as the vessels ofwar of belligerents.Article VII.The Powers shall not keep any vessel of war in the waters of the Canal(including Lake Timsah and the Bitter Lakes).Nevertheless, they may station vessels of war in the ports of access ofPort Said and Suez, the number of which shall not exceed two for each PowerThis right shall not be exercised by belligerents.Article VIII.The Agents in Egypt of the Signatory Powers of the present Treaty shall becharged to watch over its execution. In case of any event threatening the securityor the free passage of the Canal, they shall meet on the summons of three of theirnumber under the presidency of their Doyen, in order to proceed to the necessaryverifications. They shall inform the Khedivial Government of the clanger whichthey may have perceived, in order that that Government may take proper stepsto insure the protection and the free use of the Canal. Under any circumstances,they shall meet once a year to take note of the due execution of the Treaty.The last-mentioned meetings shall take place under the presidency of aSpecial Commissioner nominated for that purpose by the Imperial OttomanGovernment. A Commissioner of the Khedive may also take part in the meeting,and may preside over it in case of the absence of the Ottoman Commissioner.They shall especially demand the suppression of any work or the dispersionof any assemblage on either bank of the Canal, the object or effect of which mightbe to interfere with the liberty and the entire security of the navigation.Article IX.The Egyptian Government shall, within the limits of its powers resultingfrom the Firmans, and under the conditions provided for in the present Treaty,take the necessary measures for insuring the execution of the said Treaty.In case-the Egyptian Government should not have sufficient means at itsdisposal, it shall call upon the Imperial Ottoman Government, which shall takethe necessary measures to respond to such appeal; shall give notice thereof tothe Signatory Powers of the Declaration of London of the 17th March, 1885;and shall, if necessary, concert with them on the subject. .The provisions of Articles IV, V, VII and VIII shall not interfere withthe measures which shall be taken in virtue of the present Article.Article X.Similarly, the provisions of Article IV, V, VII and VIII shall not interferewith the measures which His Majesty the Sultan and His Highness the Khedive,in the name of His Imperial Majesty, and within the limits of the Firmansgranted, might find it necessary to take for securing by their own forces thedefence of Egypt and the maintenance of public order.In case His Imperial Majesty the Sultan, or His Highness the Khedive,should find it necessary to avail themselves of the exceptions for which thisArticle provides, the Signatory Powers of the Declaration of London shall benotified thereof by the Imperial Ottoman Government.
It is likewise understood that the provisions of the four Articlesaforesaid shall in no case occasion any obstacle to the measures which theImperial Ottoman Government may think it necessary to take in order to insureby its own forces the defence of its other possessions situated on the easterncoast of the Red Sea.Article XT.The measures which shall be taken in the cases provided for by Articles TXand X of the present Treaty shall not interfere with the free use of the Canal.In the same cases, the erection of permanent fortifications contrary to theprovisions of Article VIII is prohibited.   .Article XII.The High Contracting Parties, by application of the principle of equalityas regards the free use of the Canal, a principle which forms one of the bases ofthe present Treaty, agree that none of them shall endeavour to obtain withrespect to the Canal territorial or commercial advantages or privileges in anyinternational arrangements which may be concluded. Moreover, the rights ofTurkey as the territorial Power are reserved.Article XIII.With the exception of the obligations expressly provided by the clauses ofthe present Treaty, the sovereign rights of His Imperial Majesty the Sultan,and the rights and immunities of His Highness the Khedive, resulting from theFirmans, are in no way affected.Article XIV.The High Contracting Parties agree that the engagements resulting fromthe present Treaty shall not be limited by the duration of the Acts of Concessionof the Universal Suez Canal Company.Article XV.The stipulations of the present Treaty shall not interfere with thesanitary measures in force in Egypt.Article XVI.The High Contracting Parties undertake to bring the present Treaty to theknowledge of the States which have not signed it, inviting them to accede to it.Article XVII.The present Treaty shall be ratified, and the ratifications shall be exchangedat Constantinople, within the space of one month, or sooner if possible.In faith of which the respective Plenipotentiaries have signed the presentTreaty, and have affixed to it the seal of their arms.Done at Constantinople, the 29th day of the month of October, in theyear 1888.(L.S.) W. A. WHITE.(L.S.) RADOWITZ.(L.S.) C ALICE.(L.S.) MIGUEL FLOREZ Y GARCIA.(L.S.) G DE MONTEBELLO.(L.S.) A. BLANC.(L.S.) GUS. KEUN.(L.S.) NELIDOW.(L.S.) M. SAID.



</content>
</cab>
