<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/19/51 images: 562-564</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1941.W.P. (41) 278.November 20, 1941.SECRET.Copy No.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET.MINISTRY OF SUPPLY LABOUR REQUIREMENTS.Memorandum by the Minister of Supply.THE unsatisfied demand for labour is the most crippling influence on munitions production in this country.Short-term demands for labour for Ministry of Supply work amount to83,425. These demands are set out in detail in the annexed table. They havebeen submitted to the Ministry of Labour.The need for a supply of labour in the ball-bearing industry is especiallyurgent.   There are dangerous shortages.But tlhe outstanding weakness and over-riding anxiety in the man-power position is the shortage of female labour, especially in the Filling Factories.In the Ministry of Supply&apos;s total labour demand of 83,425 the filling factories&apos; (Royal Ordnance Factories) requirements account for 35,000 women,to make up the continued and accumulating deficiency of labour intake as againstdemand and wastage.At Swynnerton the small intake in the last three weeks has been offset bya rate of wastage so high that over two-thirds of the new recruits were needed to balance actual loss.&quot;Week after week, this failure of intake into the Filling Factories goes on.Week after week, the total shortage mounts.This is tlhe largest and the most urgent need.Female labour is available.  It awaits direction from the Ministry of Labour.Ministry of Supply.November 20, 1941.[23173][P.T.O.
ANNEX.Filling Factories (R.O.F.)     ..Explosives Factories (R.O.F.)Engineering Factories (R.O.F.)Small-Arms AmmunitionDrop Forgings ...Agency Filling FactoriesBall Bearings   ...Tank. Track and other FoundersCartridge CasesIron-Ore MiningNon-Ferrous MetalsTimberDolomite ...AbrasivesMachine ToolsNuts and BoltsScrap MetalTanks (Assemblers)Tanks (Components)GunsTotalSkilledMen.4001001,20030015019035075700900500OtherMen.3,5005002,0008008501,0003502,0001504001,6501,7001001004,0001,5002,000100250100Females.35,0003,5004,0002,0001,2503001,3605501501503,0001,6005501,1001,0004,86523,05055,510


</content>
</cab>
