<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/89/0 images: 148-150</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Vm-TW.a...Roo^ment iq the Pronely of - ^u3;?.il;Wa esty&apos;8 GovernmentIV-AuRTouLTim.^ Ann ^critical instruction fcp. irislawd.POOD PRODUCTION SOfflflCIS,   IRELAND.Memorandum prepared in compliance with Chief Secretary1sMinute of 17th Jlaroh, 1917.The following is a &quot;brief statement on the work of the Department during the past week in furtheranoe of Inereased Food Production in ireland-L0A1IS FOR agricultural MACHINERY.The nunber of applications for loans for the purchase cf agricultural machinery received during tho past -reek was 15, and the total value of the machinery ordered to datq is  56,454.tillage   SECTION,The work of checking the declarations of growers of cereals,. in connection with the Government^ guaranteed priioes, is being proceeded with, as well as the work of making the General Tillage Crop Survey..PRPQRiSSS j)F FARM V70RK.The weather during the week 6ontinued generally       1     K*. favourable for the securing of the harvest, although at timed it was showery in some parts of the country.   There was a considerable fall in temperature in the last three days.Except in a few of the later districts, the cutting of the grain crops has now been completed.   The greater portion has been stacked and threshing is generally in full swing.4The returns in most counties are said to be from fair to good, hut in many Instances, especially In the case of barley, exoellent yields are spoken of*notwithstanding the recent rains, grass is very scaroe, in a nunber of districts where it is feared that the &quot;hand&quot; feeding of Bfefcnfe stock will need to be resorted to earlier than usual In winter.Satisfactory reports continue to be received regarding the quality of the potato crop and its freedom from disease.-- As , previously reported, the yield will be below the average, chiofly24/9/19.
16./an-aafacunt of the largo propcrticn of undersized tubers.Root orops arc still making ^ood gr^wt^, but in some parte the rain arrived too late to enable the mangel crop to recover to any great extent.Reports still speak of the extra areas basing put under catch crops this season notwithstanding the high prices of seede.From one large tillage county it is reported that  armors are makitfjg preparations en a larger scale than usual for sowing winter wheat ana oats,FLAX.In a few districts the retting of seme late sown flax has not yet been completed, and in such cases the process is taking an unduly long tine owing to the advanced stage of the season and the recent cold weather.Only a tfery few l$ts of flax of the 1910 crop have been scutched up to tho present, and the reports received indicate that in proportion to tho yield of straw there is a good yield of fibre.In connection with the complaints nade)f by growers that Canadian seed supplied by the Government this season has proved in some oases to be ofl a non-fibre Variety, the Department have taken steps which will enable them to ascertain the average less incurred by growers who received unsatisfactory seed.Extreme disappointment and dissatisfaction is being expressed all over the country at the recent action of the Flax Control Board in deciding not to recommend that the fixed prioes for Irish flax should be advanced so as to place them on a par with ; the prices being paid for imported fibre of a similar quality, i Hotioes have appeared in the press calling protest meetings in the flax growing districts.FOOD CONTROL   SECTION.Baocn,    Under a licence issued by the food Controller, a small quantity of Imported Baowi has been allocated to Ireland,Butter.   A large number of paroels addressed te destinations outside Ireland and containing Butter are being confiscated weekly.   This number is on the increase.Bread.    The price of bread is now 9jd. per 4 lb. leaf in praotioally all parts of Ireland,
-   117Barley. Since the withdrawal of the restrictions on the export of barley the price has increased by 60^.Hilk.   Tho price of milk has been fixed in Londonderry,   It shows an increase over last year of Id, per quart.HAIJTTJ3TAITCE OP LIVE STOCK,During tho period from the 16th to R2nd instant, inclusive4. applications for licences were received as follows to slaughter or export heifers To slaughter bulls er bullocks To slaughter veal calves......300S3

</content>
</cab>
