<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/89/0 images: 206-286</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
,S.&apos;fig36..Thitrsday25th september /1919.BBPUT A T I 0 N toThe Rt. Hon, DAVID LLOYD GEORGE (The Prime Minister).fromThe Executive Committee of the National Union of Railwsymen.it&apos;&quot;?88$THE PRIMS MINISTER: Well, Mr. Thomas and dentlemen, this is something  \ ich, as far as the Cabinet is concerned, is quite an unexpected compile-ion.   We have only quite recently made ourselves acquainted with at. any&apos; te one view of the question in dispute. We have sesn the Railway Exe-tive; and I thought it very desirable that we should also hear the dnt of view of the Railway Union in order to be able to form a judgment )on the circumstances and the.merits of the dispute, with a view to taking: le necessary decision. Perhaps, ,.h\ Thomas, you will just put the case fefore us?MR J.R..-.THOMAS: I am afraid, Mr. Prime Minister, that I must recapitulate he statement I made this morning to Sir xLrio. I quite understand that a 1313 such as this and at this stage, may come as a surprise to. the Cab-net; but I cannot understand why they should have been ignorant of what as taken pla.ee, because, -whilst it is true that the negotiations, long,, difficult and protracted .as they have been, have been conducted nominally dth the nailway Executive, the Railway Executive from the onset made it perfectly clear, to us, and for their own reasons desired to emphasise, hat they were acting for Government: and we were assuming, as we had a  t f\l^ht to assume, that so far as the Government were concerned, they were-onversant with all that has taicen place. In the second place, yir, I have nothing but commendation for your action as the Prime minister in seeingbo;.h sides; because whatever the merits of any dispute may be, whilst you have an obligation to both sides of a dispute, you have a greater obliga-fc&amp;wi, to &apos;che public as a whole; and therefore in this matter the public awe a fac-oor that is not only involved, but has a .right not to be ig-norea: and I presume you are meeting us this afternoon as the -Prime Liinis ter,notnecessarily 1-&amp; 2partial
&apos;bo Mio hallway It:ooutivo or ourselves, but as tho .&apos;?rimohinister oi the Country responsible to allow   it is&apos; in that spirit that I want to pat tho situation before you.   In tho&apos; first place, I had better tell you what is the situation, so far as the crisis is concerned.   At this moment the men have received instructions to cease work at 1*3 o&apos;clock to-morrow nidit.   lou would be the first to admit that to keep that fact from you would be some thing that would bo criminal on the part of any man: and therefore, you will quite understand I am not using it in the way of a threat, or anything of that kind; but merely that you should know exactly what is tailing place.THS ITRJM IIIEISYJR: That is what I m.aant0   I did not mean to convey the impression that I did not know that there were ne-negotiations going on with the Railway Union, that has boon brou to my notioo once or twice, I. think once or twico oven at a Deputation,,   I meant that the fact- that they had reached an acute stage&apos;, which would involve the possibility of - a strike, uncl a strike at such short notice, which would&apos; throw the -whole Gountry into confusion, was certainly new to us*i.IR JpHo THOIvlaS: That being sofi that is the situation; and the roason why such an unusual stop as that was taken was, that if a strike was - inevitable in the opinion of the Lt-ecutive Committee, they contemplated that it may be difficult to let the members know viiat were their instructions; and in order to get over that possibility, they issued instruc-tions that in the absence of receiving any other message-, thea/ are to cease work,,   That is the situation,How1;, I am not going to waste your time or mino as to tho gravity ox that, e::cept to say two things.   In the first place, there has beon occasion when you yourself and other members; of the Government have expressed doubts as to
whether the i-uilwaymon thensolves would strike-.   You haveexpressed those doubts because you have taken this ground:(1) Tho circumstances of tho war; and (2)t, because you havebelieved that the offer cf tho Government Was One that wasa fair basis and ought to be accepted,.   Shortly, i thinkthat has always been your groun&amp;0   On this occasion,, I canonly state my own opinion; and in.my opinion, as distinct from the Llxeoutive Committeei whieii incidentally theyshare3 there is not a railwayman but will stop work at 13o1 clock to-morrow night, unless they hear to tho contrarycwhatflow, you are entitled to say: ,TDo fou know/that - -     ^ , &apos; / .  &quot;involves:- i do know0   Every member of this Executive knowsand i have no hesitation, in saying that, difficult as havebeen crises from tiiac to ttoo* the -possibility of a com-plete cessation, at i&amp;is stage of -ulio nation s difficulty,,of the railways, is something that no-one can calculatewhere it will lead toc   Now you might say-, fIf you know thatthe situation is so serious as that-, what justificationis there for taking that action?1&apos; Therefore it will bonecessary for mo to briefly give you the facts.   You will remember that last Liar oh 9 when we wore in a difficulty,you did on that occasion what you have done to-day, namely,netBa Deputation of the menbut on that occasion it was.your deputy2 because you were in Prance; but acting inaccordance with your own wish, llr Sonar Lav/, who was thenleading tho House ^ took your responsibility, and met whatwas can,cd the Triple alliance0   row in a very brief 31 s-cussion cf the case, l.r Bonar Lav/ then pointed out what he felt to be a very strong case on your behalf, and he saidto us in short $&quot;Do you really understand what the Govorn-menVs offer is?&apos;r Ho supplemented what  Sir -albert Stanleyhad said , which in short was this extent   He saidrTbo first give
you a guarantor that the wages will be stabilised until the 21st December, but we recognise the anomalies existing as between one grade and another; and in order to get over that difficulty in the interval the Committee shall go into standardisation, Sir Albert Stanley said; "They shall commence at once"; and in order to impress upon us the advantages of that proposal, he said, you will get the benefit of two things: (1) No man will be reduced but if the standardisation results in a man receiving more than the the combined basic rate and the war wage, he shall immediately receive it. That in short was the offer; and it was followed up by Mr Bonar law saying that the Cabinet had themselves discussed the ? of what he called equalisation, and which we call standardisation -- it is the same thing really -- and everybody agreed that it was to be standardisation ?.

Mr BONAR LAW: Perhaps I had better interrupt you there. Have you looked at the shorthand Notes since that meeting Mr J. H. THOMAS: I have them in front of me.

MR BONAR LAW: I have them, too. Those remarks referred entirely, as the Shorthand Notes shaw, to the arrangement we were making until the end of December.

Mr J. H. THOMAS: I accept that. That is not in dispute.

THE PRIME MINISTER: That is very important, I was going to ask that.

Mr J. H. THOMAS: It meant standardisation.

Mr BONAR LAW: But only as applying to the conditions up to the 31st December.

Mr J. H. THOMAS: It could not be that.

THE PRIME MINISTER. That is the first thing I want to have cleared up.

Mr BONAR LAW: Will you allow me to make it plain, as I think it is? I was asked about abort this question of the difference in rates; and the illustration you gave was a man working


in Liverpool for one railway at one rate, and for another railway at another rate; and i said in regard to that: "I hope I have made that plain". You gave an illustratin of men in Liverpool getting different rates for doing the same work.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: Which page are you on now?

MR. BONAR LAW: Page 25. The standardisation which we agreed to is, that that sort of thing should be put an end to; and that in a district the wages should be the same, irrespective of the railway for which the man is working. Is that clear?

MR. J. H. THOMAS: Then I followed on and said; "Yes, I understand that".

MR. BONAR LAW: Then Mr Cramp on the next page said to me

MR. J. H. THOMAS: One moment please. It is important to go on so that we may have a complete continuation of the story. Then I said: "Yes, I understand that"; and Mr. Robert Williams said: "Sir Albert Stanley has put the point that standardisation may add to the basic wage, and that something may be taken off from the war wage". I suggest that that hypothetical consideration should be left out, because that would raise the whole bone of contention which was raised so strongly last night. Any discussion of decrease in the war wage would do that. "(Sir Albert Stanley) But it does not decrease the total amount. (Mr. Thomas) It is not that at all; that is not the point involved, because there is no transference in any case. That was agreed before, namely, that we merely engaged to find a standard rate; and then I understand when negotiations in December took place, instead of negotiating on the 128 different rates, we shall negotiate on the one standard rate".

MR. BONAR LAW: It would be better to complete your reference to what I said, irrespective of what is said by anyone else, because that is the point you were dealing with.


MR Tf-IOWvS: Yes.MR BQIMIi LA&quot;.Y: You will see ray reference was not to a universal standard on the railways, but to the rate in a particular dis-trict.   tfhat I said about j/lvornool, for ins fcanoe, was that if a man was getting one rate fro-a one railway and another rate from another railway, tnat chat must be equalised.   I am only dealing with my remarks, I1 hen on the neat peg a        Cramp pointed out: &quot;11&apos;.-.y I say that there Id a great fear among the men on the most hignly raced railways that standardion might mean bringing them down./- and so on.   I said: &quot;That is not in-volved in anything we are doing now&apos;. Then Mr. Cramp said: &quot;I understand that standardisation doss not raise every one to the highest maximum now existing&quot;. My next answer shews plainly I was dealing only with the conditions up to the rilst December, for I said: &quot;It does this: in this agreement, that nobody would be worse off during the period than he is today, Dome will be bet-ter off&quot;      showing clearly I was referring to the period until the 31st December.MR J.H. THOMAS: Yes, but in fairness to you, you must read on your own words,.Ivffi BOUAK LAW: They have no bearing on this; but I will read them,if you like. THS PRIME MINISTER: Mr, Thomas wants them,MR BOIJAR LAW: &quot;If the time comes to fight about wages and you have the principle of standardisation, it may have the reso.lt of bringing&apos;everyone1s wages down, whereas in other conditions it would not,&quot; That surely is to the advantage of the trade; but that has no bearing on the particular point we are dealing with,MR J.H.THOMAS: I think it has.,MR 30HAR LAi: Then the maf:er is raised again, and I said: &quot;when we were discussing in the Cabinet the question of equalisation somebody said, and everybody agreed, of course, that it meant there must&apos;be equalisation upwards,&quot; I quite admit
that. Then Mr. Thomas said: What they were thinking of ? happened in the Cabinet. If you attempt to equalise, it has been in an ? and never ill a ? direction." Now look at what I say next, which shows it clearly applied only to the period we wer then discussing: "When I say that happened in the Cabinet it does not mean I agree with it in all circumstances, but it does mean that we at once recognise that if we accepted that principle at all on the present conditions" that is to say, during this perios -- "It would mean more money." That is all I said, so that it is quite obvious that what I was referring to was, the conditions in the period up up till the olst December.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: Now, Sir, I have asked for those additional words to be read, and I now emphasise them. I am deciding with your own words: "If the time comes" -- these are year ? -- "so fight about wages, and you have the principle of standardisation, it may have the result of bringing ? whereas in other conditions it would ?. Now I put it to you that no one could suggest that when you wre talking about standardisation the only object of standardisation when was something up till the end of December.

MR BONAR LAW: No, I think you are forgetting, Mr. Thomas, the conditions unders we were then discussing. We were discussing it with a view of avoiding an ?. I was dealing, in everything I said, with one order which I was making you up to the 31st December; and that is perfectly plain from what I said there. I was not ? after the 31st December; and that is quite evident surely, from my answer to Mr. Cramp.

MR J. H. THOMAS: Then Sir Robert Horse pass on: "We are not likely to fix standard rates which was ? "enouth experience to know." Whom I am ? to you there is,


that this is the first time      and there are many things which have transpired in this unfortunate crisis for thefirst time, as I will endeavour to shew -- &quot;but this is thefirst time I have heard it suggested that the record ofthe shorthand ; otes, now covering 40 days perhaps will shew Enand neither the railway Companies nor yourselves, so far as we know will now say for the first cime, Sir Herbert talker dare not say it now; I go so far as to say that oir Auckland Ceddes dare not say it now   that when we in all these negotiations have been discussing standardisation, we have been discussing on the basis that they were discussing stand-ardisation up to the end of the year.
luH.BOMR.li/iV/:.   You are going entirely ofi the point that I am discussing.   You , re dealing with negotiations winch h.: ve taken piece since.   The meeting to which ^ou relwr when you quote my words was a meeting called by me as this is, with the idea oi preventing,. if I could, an immediate strike.    I was dealing with the conditions whioh we wore then offering end remember it was quite natural I ::hould refer to standardization within that period ior this reason, that wo gave the promise, end it, was one of the inducements I held out to ?ou,. that if the :result of the standardization within this period was to give a ,...an a higher wage than his present war wage, he would get it; so I think it is quite obvious that in everything I saia I. was referring only to the conditions up to the 5Islecher.   01 course I can say nothing about what has happened in negotiations since.luR. J.H.TE0LA5:    I content myself on that point by sayingthat I leave you to judge as I Ijave the public to judp as to v/hether a body of icen meeting you or meeting theGovernment and prat establishing the case,, that to ha-ve the same  oflrss of men working under one condition in one place for one $rice and at another price ih.anotle r place   having established that and you lmving agreed   ----I did not deal at all with the question of the general standard of a particular grade all over the country;   I was do a.ling with men working in the sane ^lace under the same conditions getting different rates, HE. J.H.TEOki 3:      I agree, but it is the same principle.   let me substitute your words so that there may be no ambiguity I will take jour own words and I \*ill say that if you meantLE.BOUAR VSH:But you are wrong as a matter of fact..
then that you were going to remove that anomaly only up to Deoenber, aa ia now implied   well then I am entitled to aay that air months have elapsed since then rn&quot; now ia the first attempt to remove that anomaly.O.B0H/.R IkM;     This is tho first time I have heard it0MR. J.4VJ!HOi:/.S:   Very well.   The. first sis months have elapsed, probably forty meetings have taken place and what earthly value uould it be to say that now it is tho end of September and we are doing something that is only operative until December.hi! BOivAR LAY/;    But you are. not dealing, if ;ou will arousemo saying so, with .the point.   I only interrupted becauae they were ay.own statements; they have no reference to the merits of this dispute at all; they have no reference to whet I then said as to the conditions the Government then expected and surely my answer to jur.Gremt) itself makes it plain that I was referrin. only up to 31st Docom-ber because he aakec a question and&apos;l said what the promts means ia that no men will be worse off and some will be better off in this period.&amp;R..J.H.T.30MAS:       I do not see the relevancy of it yet, if it ia not what 1 say.   Do you moan by what you have now said that when you made that statement you only meant it c3 being a p., llosble up to December? LB.B0HAR IAT7:       Certainly; I think that ia quite plain fromthe Shorthand Notes * liR.J.H.KI01IAS:      Very well, I will leave it at that.   1 donot think it requires a v,ord from mo and it certainly does not help much.   I leave the records of that aid the records of your other colleagues which aro in tho minutes aa well aa the subsequent records      the Railway executive to a peak for themselves on thrt ^:oint, and I will oome to
one other statement that you made, namely, that you said, and you have just repeated it now, that one of the inducements that you offered then was that the men should be no worse off but that they may be better off. Those were your own words.

MR. BONAR LAW: Yes, but you have left out the vital thing -- during this period.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: I am accepting for the purpose of my ?ment

"During this period". I suppose there will be no difference that "during this period" mean to-day.

MR. BONAR LAW: Yes, up to the 31st. December.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: Very well, to-day -- during this period.

Then all I have to comment on is that if you had that in your mind, if the President of the Board of Trade had that in his mind and repeatedly said to this side of the table: "See that you are gaining. You are sure not to lose but you may even benefit." I put it to you that you resume someone would benefit. I put it no higher than that, but my comment on the figures as presented to us is that it is not true.

MR. BONAR LAW: That anybody benefits?

MR. J. H. THOMAS: That anybody benefits.

MR. BONAR LAW: Surely that is not so.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: I am making a definite statement.

THE PRIME MINISTER: If I may say so I think you had better state your case and whilst you are stating your case will you please assume that even if we do not contradict we only reserve our observations until you have finished.

MR. J. H. THOMAS: Of course, but equally on the assumption that if I am interrupted I may deal with the interruption.


either I have to go on with my caso or I hive to-doal iirlt&amp;rt&amp;a, interruption.   I do not care which way it is. /THE PRIME MISTER:   You are quite right.MR. BOKAR LAW;   I thought It was right that I should intorvono.MR, J.H.TH0]yLA$: I :;m not complaining &quot;but I am going to deal with it vory specifically because wo are at too grave a moment to allow the case from our side to bo prejudiced ormisunderstood.THE PRIME MINISTER;   That is vory very important, certainly, because tho public will finally ,1u&amp;go.112. J.H..TH0MAS:   Absolutely, ond I only want them to judge correctly.THE PRIME MINISTER:   Quito right.MR, J0HvTHOMAS:   I will continueTHE PRIME MINISTER:   And if I may say so I should like to judgo myself bofore it goos to tho public.   Mr. Bonar law and I will hoar what you have to say and wo will judgo by what you say f.-nd if you c?not accept our view then the public will hate to judge.MR.-J.H.THOMAS:   I merely say again that this is tho first time I have over heard that when wo talked of standardisation it mount standardisation only up to the 31st December.     Thisis the first timo I have hoard of it and if it is so then wo have wasted all our timo;   the.Railway Executive havo boon under a misapprehension;   wo havo boon under a misapprohon-sion and tho statement that Sir Albert Stanley made, namely, that when we got standardisation wo will havo then paved tho way for negotiations which remove all anomalios, I am at least entitled to eay that we understood it to moan something else than hero stated to-day.
Now, Sir, that being so you ask us what are the circumstances that led to tho immediabo,..crisis,     From March we were negotiating; offers of different ^hare-civers were made to us for some grades; and uli.ima.tely we reached   &apos; a stage where the Associated Society sent an ultimatum to the Government that unless a settlement was made with them for locomotive men, certain consequences would follow. Up to this stage we had been negotiating and tryinr to find a basis of settlement,     The result of that ultimatum was that we met at once and the Government made proposals.. Those proposals. Wore debated and ultimately agreed.THE PRIME MINISTER.     These are the proposals by the locomotive men?MR. J.H&apos;. THOMAS.   3y the Government,THE PRI1E MINISTER.     Were there any other classes there? MR; J.H,THOMAS.   No, only 1ocomotive men. THI PRIME &quot;MINISTER I&quot;    That meansMR. J,H.THOMAS-.     Drivers, firemen and cleaners; there is one else in this particular negotiation.TH1. PRIME MINISTER:   So I understood.     When was that particular negotiation concluded?MR. J.-H. THOMAS.   August 20th.A MEMBER OF THE DEPUTATION,   It came into operation as from 18th August. .MR.. J.H.THOMAS.   The daV. being made retrospective because of the negotiations.     It was negotiated on tho 20th August.     Now, when that offer was made the first offer of-the Government was not accepted, negotiations took place   -and ultimately, as I say, an agreement was arrived at. That agreement did this:    it   nobled the highest paid driver to have added to his wages 55/- or more, and that belaud the standard rate.     In other words, although there may have only been 5 per Cent of the drivers  I think it would be less, I think I am well within the mark when I say
3 per cent   a]though there may have only been 3 per cent of the Irl^Mediterranean who were roc ex zing 9/5 per day, the average tor toe whole of the dri/ers was 6/9 j but the agreement enabled * every man to recede at leas&apos;: 5/6 per day- that Is a sixth of 33/- over and above the top rate of 9/6,   That was in short standardising upwards.&apos; That was the position of the driver,-and no driver of any sort.or kind on any railway received a standard basic rate of less than the original basic rate plus 33/-.   then T,je come to the firemen precisely the same thing operated.   There were firrroon whose minimum rate was 3/6; not 2 per cent would -be 5/- but here again there was not a fireman whose new standard rate was as much or more than the previous standard rate plus the war wa^e of 33/-, which 1 very hujiDly submit to you meant standardisation upwards; because ;you ^ould be the first tc see you can get standard: sation bymerely dropping everybody down.   However, you see the point If ycu were getting 24/** and I 20/- at the same work  the PRIMS MINISTER;   There are three classes here; Ihave the agreement in front of government  drivers,motormen and firemen..MK. J.H.THOMAS:   Nf, there are no classes, do not niijj it*THE PRIMS MINISTER:   Well, cleaners.MR. J.H.THOMAS: No, that Is age limit.   I beg of you keep this point clearly before you.THE PRIMP; MINISTER:   I have the actual document here and I havfe drivers and motcrmen^ I have firemen and I have cleaners.   New you have de&amp;l. with the drivers, motormen and the firemen.   Tell me *rhat was done with the cleaners.MR.J.H.THOMAS:   But I want to clearly emphasise the poinV as long as you are satisfied, that in this agreement no man&apos;3 standard rate was less than his basic then existing wage plus 33/-.   That ia all I have to say on the first
tv&apos;o.     Now I Gome to the cleanera-  Then ,;e came to the cleaners may I say we were dealing ^ith in the main an overwhelming majority of juniors, boys. The overwhelming majority was boys.A MEMBER rF THE CABINET:-.   But the agreement simply refers to seniors,.MR. J.,HvTHOMAS;-   Ho, excuse me, it refers tc both; the agreement says sixteen years of age and under, that is juniors; seventeen years of age,, that is juniors.   It dealt with them all   and not ene*THE PRIME MINISTER:-   18, 19, 20, and wer, MR, JiH-THOMAS.-   Exactly.,   As I was saying., we were dealing with both..   The overwhelming&apos;majority employed was beys,   fen we came to them we Lad made proposals similar to the drivers and firemen, to merge the lot, but the answer of the Government was that every one of these, whether they be juniors or adults &quot;;ere only men who did a very short period as cleaners and automatically become drivers and firemen.   There they urged; and it was pointed out with very strong force that in their oases probably even before this agreement could be made, many of them would come under the category, of either of the first two; drivers or firemen and in their case the 7/-was made the maximum, the remainder living on with the war wage.     So I have there dealt with the three *
THE PRIhE MINISTER:- What doer, tho ts. mean?: tiwt, p-erc^ta^ What vn$ tho &quot;basic rate there?Mr, J.H. THOMAS: - There waa a difficulty bet-noon both sides, and, to be quite fair. Sir Herbert Walker on his sido: was in as much a difficulty as we   were because of the over-whelming majority being lads and boys..   On some railways adults were employed,but not on many*THE PRIME MINISTER:- I want to know whether any of these cleaners were adults, and received less than: their basic rate, plus the 33s. ? Mr. THOMAS: - Undoubtedly; there need&apos; be no dispute about that, because?, we do not want to bother about technicali-ties.   That is perfectly true for the reason I havo rivonj and It is equally true, what I have said, in the case of firemen or drivers,.    Wow we come to the proposals affecting tho other grades, and I want to put the situation.; but first let me observe what happened when th; t settlement was made.   It was difficult, having regard to the period, March to August, that had elapsed, and the men. always asking when this thing was goin: to be settled.   We made all manner of excuees, and tried to justify it, but Immediately the locomotive settlement was made, as we all knew would happen, the whole of the other grades at once wanted to know why it was they had not been dealt with, and so on, and so on, and difficulty arose there.   But:it beeemc so   acute that a&apos; week ago last Tuesday tho* Exe-cutlve Committee, my own Executive Committee, felt that. It was getting out of hand, and they waited upon the President of tho Board of Trade, Sir Auckland Geddes, and 1 there stated the whole situation to him, and I pointed out the dangers rmd difficulties.   After consultation with the Railway Executive he stated thfft he hope$ to M in. a  .IT, &apos; -
position to send m the proposals in the coarse of a few days.   Having regard to the delay 1 stated quite clearly, to him that I hoped that when the proposals came they would be final proposals.   We had had proposals before on the same point thct were rejected; and we had negotiated, as I say, for days.        and weeks, and months,.and it had become so serious that I said, quite clearly and definitely, that I hoped&apos; it would be understood&apos; that we did not want any further prop-a nr. is *b a mere jumping off ground, but as a final offer.   That request was submitted.to, him, nnd ho accented it, saying that he fully understood, and appro-ciated the situation.   Then we waited a few days, and on the 19th the proposals came along,   $hey were accompanied by this letter.   I need net read the whole of the letter, I only want to draw attentions to certain words? &quot;I trust your Executive; will realise, that this will be a veryr heavy burden for the railways of this country to stand, and I therefore wish you to understand that the proposals con-t ined in the attached memoranda are not put forward as-, a V&apos;S-ls of negotiation, hut as a definitive offer of the: Government.&quot;THE PRIME MINISTER:- Th-t is what you asked for.Mr, J*H. THOFAS: Exactly; that, as you rightly say, is exactly what wo asked f or,- - That- was on the 10th. . They were&apos; Immediately submitted to the Executive Committee, and I wrote this reply on the same day, and sent it by hand.THE PRIME MINISTER: ** What day is that ?Mr. J.H. THOMAS:- The 19th.   This ia the reply; &quot; I       am in receipt of your letter of the 18th inst,, together with the proposed rates of pay for men employed In the Goods Section, and bo on.   My Executive-Committee considered the.   -proposals immediately they arrived, and it would be unfair
to you if I&apos;dad npt at onoo say   that they were unanimous in their declaration thatthe proposals are not such as to Justify the hope of their   being the basis of a satisfactory settlement; but so that the matter may not be prejudiced and tho case considered as a whole, they have decided to defer their final decision until   wo are in receipt of tho proposals : covering the other grades, whioh I understand from your letter will arrive In tho courso of a day or so.   The only point I want to make there is this.    Let there bo no misunder-standing about this.     I make no complaint whatever against Sir Auckland Goddos clearly intimating that this was a final offer, but C.P&amp;lly I am entitled to   say that no one olsc has a right to complain of my side so Interpreting that.     That is the point I mako.     That is a very fair statement from both sides.THE PRI,E MINISTER    I have road   that letter, and there is some-thing   there to    tho effect that details will bo discussed.MR J.H*THOMASs     I till read its &quot;Xou will hoar from the Railway . Executive in. the course of the m%% day or two suggesting dates for tho S^b-Goimnibtees to meet, to sottlo any details of tho scheme outlined in the enclosed schedules and to discuss any anomalies   that may bo found to exist&quot;.lh/. PRIME MIHISTEiJ Tes.MR .7*1-1 iTHOMAS.   How the answer to that is this, that wo had agreed tow Committees, and we haijo had at least a dozen, In fact . more than a dozen sitting -TEE HU E MINISTER    I only want to point out that it 3s not-quite- the same thing as a final offer.     It is an offe*where you arc Invited to discuss the details, and tho removalof any anomalies.     I only want just to   call attention tothat. ...MR J.H.THOMAS:   Then It is   well you should know what themoaning of it is, bocauoo you do not.   I had better explain i
at once. From March even up to Monday of this week, the very afternoon of the final decision of the Executive, a Sub-Committee composed of three of my side with three of the Railway Executive, were meeting in order to consider what we call the details. Details in these matters mean this. There is a long list here. We do not want the Board of trade to argue whether Station A. should be in one category, or Station B. The Railway Executive have said through Sir Herbert Walker: Let the Goods Managers, or the Traffic Managers, or the Local Superintendents, settle these details. They are not principles and the result is that we have a dozen such committees. Simultaneously with this letter, I have read dated the 18th inst-incidentally both letters are dated the same day - Sir Auckland Geddes&apos; letter is dated the 18th - a letter dated the 18th, again comes from Sir Herbert, saying: "Will you please arrange for your Engineering Sub-Committee to meet the Sub-Committee of this Committee on Tuesday next to settle any details of the scheme outlined in the offer submitted to you today by the President of the Board of Trade, and to discuss any anomalies that may be found to exist" - Not the negotiating Committee, because it is clearly obvious from what you said that you assumed that meant: "Come and discuss the differences". But the Engineering Sub-Committee is one. The same day this letter came from Sir Herbert saying "Will you please arrange for your goods Sub-Committee" - in other words, arrange for one or for two of these particular Sub-Committees to discuss what? - to discuss the details of this. Now on seeing the danger of that I at once knew where we were travelling, and I immediately sent this reply to Sir Herbert on the 19th by hand: " I have received your letters with regard to the proposed meetings of the Sub-Committee,/
and I herewith enclose a copy of a letter addressed to Sir Auckland Geddes which will erplain the inability of my Sub-Committee to meet as suggested on Tuesday ne::t&quot;; and I sent Sir Herbert a copy of the letter that I sent to Sir Auckland Go tides, and which I have just read.   Now you have interrupted, Sir, with a view of saying j   But surely a wron-r Interpretation is put on that ?   This letter, as I told you, was dated the 18th september,  my reply is the 19th September, and my reply says; &quot;The Executive Committee considers it does not prov-.de the basis of an agreement&quot;.Slxl AUCIILA;dG.&quot;.&apos;.!v  S:   Excuse me one moment.   Go on with therest of your letter - &quot;but&quot;,Mr.. J.E. TrK-dAS:   &quot;But so that the matter may not be prejudiced, and the case considered as a whole, they have decide&apos;/, to -efer their final decision until we are in receipt of the proposals, covering the other grass&quot;.SIR ATOCL^lfctf a-S :   Thank- you,Mr, J.K, THCMA3:   Now that was the 19th September.   The other proposals are sent on tha 23rd,TH&apos;d PAT   MI-T T-&quot;R:   That is on Tuesday, two days ago ?Mr, J.H. THOMAS:   Yes; and so that there may be no misunderstanding I may say theyere sent up on the Monday.   Your letter die not come until the Tuesday.SIR AUCKLaIT Gd-T&apos;.&quot;.&apos;!&apos;-::   You got them, on the afternoon of the 22nd.Mr. J.H. THO&apos;A3:   Yes, on the Tuesday: ,rI an &amp; sired by Sir Auckland C-cddes to acknowledge the receipt cf your letter of to-day&apos;s date enclosing cor?y of a Sesolution o-osed by the Executive Committee of the National Union of Railway-en on the subject of Standard, Rates of Vdages, and. to scy that your letter has been transferred to the Minister of Transport, by whom it will bo considered.&quot;.. Here ia another letter,   I need not go into the whole
of the natter except to say this offer was made on the same conditions as those referred to in the penultimate paragraph of his communication of Thursday last,   Again do not let us have any bothering about misunderstanching or blaming anybody; all I say is that having clearly asked that the offer bg final, and having been clearly told that tho offer was final, the Executive Committee had no other alternative than to&apos; assume that it wan final, and take their course accordingly.   How what course r10. they take ? They looked at those proposals, and they first found them--elves up against this proposition.   How were they going to hopo to explain to a Guard of 50 years service that whilst hi3 son, who may be a fireman with 4 years experi-ence was standardised upwards, and received the whole of the war wage added to his basic rate - what reason, or justification was there for that principle, whether it is good or ba &apos;, not applying to him ?   That sane statement can&apos;be made with regard to tho Shunter, the Passenger-Guard, tho Ticket-Collector, and ovary grado in the service; and Incidentally, when I toll you that in the whole of these proposals, although you heard a moment ago Mr. Bonar Law saying that he assumed that there would be some benefit to somebody or other, I: ha^e only to tell you tho bald statement that the only people who receive a copper, the only people whose wages are - -orgod, are the drivers and firemen; and every one of those others, without a solitary exception to my kncwleO- e, often having examined the figures - wo will hear to the contrary in a moment * we know of no grace where t c present existing wage and the war wage is merged on the standard basis of tho highest. Veil, Sir, you may say; &quot;that about the cost ?&quot;; but you will be the first to recognise that to make a more settle-went round this table is valueless to you.   It is no goou
my saying to you: &quot;I will accept this&quot;; it Is no good this Executive saving: &quot;I rill accept this&quot;; the only value Of an- agreement is that those making it arc in a position to see that it is given effect to, and the Executive Committee, in considering all the circumstances of these proposals, were unanimously of opinion that tc submit them to the men themselves, and ask fcr their judgment, *ould result in an immediate strike.Now we come to ^hat I have always conceived to be the difficulty of your side of the case.   It.is perfectly true that the flat rate bonus, or war wage, in proportion.,&apos;does net give the same relative ^vantage to the higher paid men as it does to the lower paid men; that is obvious.   I make two observations on it, though.   The first- is that if you were in receipt of  1 a &apos;&apos;&apos;eek      and-there are 100,000 railway men &quot;hose basic rate was  1 a week, or less ---- if you ^ere in reciept of  1 a week in 1914, and the cost of living went up as it did go up   it may be that to me in receipt of  2 with a 10s. advance, it would hot mean so much proportionately as it would to the man with  1 a week but you v,ould know perfectly veil from your o^n experience that the man existing on  1 a week has not that reserve to bear the increased strain as the man upwards.THE PRIME MINISTER.: - Do-you mind my asking a question at this stage?- You have taken the case of a man with  1 a week,   rhat is the lowest rate of standard wage which is proposed by the Board of Trade?MR. J.Hv THOMAS:- 4Oa.   It, is proposed 42/- 44/- and46/-THE PRIME MINISTER:-   That *.-as the lowest rate before the war paid to railway men?MR. J.H..TH0MAS:-   The lowest rate, I am ashamed to say, on some railways **e have discovered was as low as 18/-. I leave you to draw your oim picture as to the conditions .
of those-yTHE PRIME MINISTER:-   I know them.MR. J*HtTHOMAS:-   To keep this clearly In m&apos;nd, this proposal of 40s. and 44s. for plate-layers, means this, that in South Tales, take either the Rhondda Valley, and the Taff, the Rhymney Valley) or the Eastern or Western Valleys in Monmouthshire, there you have, and we have, this difficulty, that the plate-layer who works in the colliery as a plate-layer receives 70s. odd minimum and we have got to go and try and persuade these plate-layers that 4C.Sr or 44s. in .?ndustrial districts is equivalent for them.MR. BONAR LAV.:-   You are leaving out, though, the additional war wage,MR.Jr.H.THOMAS:-   Yes, I am coming to that, because^ I want to say something about the war wage,   we are assuming a standard basis.   These men have no war wage.   Do keep that- point in mind.   That appears to me to be the diffin culty.SIR ROBERT HORNE:-   $hi ah men?MR.J.Hi.THOMAS:- The miners.&apos;   In the colliery districts there is no ^rar wage.MR. BONAR LAW:-   In comparing the present condition, which is what ycu are doing, of the two men you must compare., them, though It Is still unfavourable to you.MR.J.H.THOMAS:- 52 SMR. BONAR LAY-&apos;:-   Yes,MR.J.H.THOMAS:-   I agree, but here Is the difficulty, Sir.   If that Is so, then there can be no difference in having one amount on a balance-sheet, one side or the other, because there Is no difference in amount   but there Is a difference in principle, as I will show you in a moment. I do not want to be bothered with that now.   I merely
aphasiso that fact.    r&apos;hon I come to the Shunters, hero again arc Shunters employed.-in. collieries nhr ro there is a difference of 25s., oven in tlv top figure, that is to say, tho combined figure.    Then when you come to the Labourers, there is the Cardiff Corporation with its  3 minimum for labourers,     TTve point, shortly put, is that we havo to hoop in consideration, and vc cannot --lind ourselves to the conditions outside.     You cannot expect the Carman, merely because he works for the lJonth-&apos;&quot;&quot;estern or the --rent-&apos;restern, to drive about London with Hacnamara&apos;s carman without comparing what they get.    The offer either of tho standard rate, or tho combined rate, for the outside carriers, for either ono or two teams, or for tho motor man, is nothing comparable to ibn  other.     Now I want to come to what I believe to be tho thing that is upper:-ost in our minds, and I merely say this:   How can you crpect us to go to the men and attempt to say that if a driver and foreman having been standardised on an upward basis can be justi-fiod, from ono point of view, and tho rest of the gradea excluded?    T&quot;&quot;e do not beliove it is possible, with all the desire in the rorld to carry tho men with us, and all I can say in conclusion is this,     r*c thank you for the oppcr-tunity of stating tho case.     Incidentally, I may say that you would havo been wanting in your duty if you had not avail-ed yourself of this opportunity, that we would havo been making a profound mistake had we not accepted it.     But tho fact of us being here, the fact of us arguing this morning, is in itself the best evidence of our negotiating to avoid what wo believe will bo a torriblo business, whatever the result is, if it results In a fight.    Therefore I believe, Mr. Prime Minister, just as I havo said publicly in the House, and have said to you, that in a fight of the State versus a section of the State, tho State has to do all-it
&quot;   18Scan to win,-and in this matter no are undr-r no apprehen-sions that you trill not do all you can;,  we quite recognise that.     But tho State, whilst It must protect the interests of the State, ought itself to be sure that It Is just before it precipitates a crisis.,    In this matter I do not believe justice is done.)    In these proposals I do not believe that I would be justified, with all my anxiety for peace., . I know I would not have it on my conscience that I had tried to persuade tho men to do something I did not boliove wan right, and I know, in spite of their regard for me, they will reject it, because I believe the Government is in a bad position, because I believe they are wrong, because I believe they ought to put themselves right at this opportunity,     I hope, whatever else may result from this interview this afternoon, you will realise, as I realise, that none of us   whatever the mistakes may have been, whatevor language may havo becrj used or construed - ought to allow anytt&amp;ng of that to prevent us doing the right thing,, and the right thing is In this matter not to ask us to accept the proposals that have been submitted to us.THE PRIMP minister&quot;^:-   I want, at any rate, before I come to a decision in the matter to be fully informed of the circum-stances, and I should like to ask a few questions.MR. J. H. THOMAS.-   Certainly.THE PRILF MINISTER:-   I should also like not to have to ,. answer without having some time to think it over.    &apos;r: Whatever your plans are, I Co not want to Interfere with them, and therefore I should see you certainly to-morrow morning, if that would meet your convenience.MR. J. H. THOMASi-  Do I undorstand that you are going to put a series of questions to the Executive Committee, and that you do not want an answer now?
THE PRIME MINISTER.   Ho, I should Ilka to hcvd thoanswor now, but boforo consulting ray oolloaguos as totho lino which tho Government ought to toko, I wont tobo fully informed &apos;of tho foots, ,nd therefore I shouldsolike to ask a few questions now/as to inform mysolfof tho f--cts from your point of view;   end I should liko then not to give on answor, but to trdco a little tlma to think it: ovor,. and if it would meet tho convenience of tho Executive I will sec thorn vny time they like to-morrow morning.     I will put off everything olso.   I was going down to a meeting rt Carnarvon, but I will put it off because I consider this is a very urgent-mattor, end thoreforo I do not want in the least to delay it. It is obvious that one3 n dispute lixu this begins, and tho public are excited, noturally, about it, It must be brought to a concision one way or the other.MR* J*HoTH0MAS*   I only mcko this reservation, Mr. Pritfo Minister.   In -&apos;11 tires:) nottors you know I act in the main, whether it is advantageous or not, as tho single spokesman;   we do not believe in throe or four speakers to put our case.   I will answer up to the point of giving you whatever information I can, but if there is ony question that you want an answor to, which requires my Executive Ooarnfttoe to answer  -THE PRIME MINISTER.   You con remain hero, and we will go outside.MR., JoEoTHOMAS.   I only moke that reservation.
THE PRMJO^ I gWlike to -,sk is thiSi      I went to know o. r^tly-^oTir-Yiow of whet this proposal is.   As I understand It moons th.it taking    railway portor or a platolcyor who is in rooolpt of 18/-9 ho will now roooiva as a minimum 40/-,     That is correct I understand.MB. J.HoTH0UAS.     Yos,THE.PRIME MINISTER,   As I understand, that has no reference at all to any fluctuation thero may to in tho cost of living.HR. JoH.THOMAS0   Up to   -THE5 PEIM3 MINISTER.   Up to 40/-.ME. .7.H.THOMAS.   Yes, that Is quite right.THE PRIME MINISTER.   So if the cost of living goes down - suppose it was 125 per cent and it goes down to 75 por cont - and I do not anticipate th?t it will immediately, I do not mind telling.you thrt - that will make no differenoe so for as tho 40/- is concerned.MR. .7.H.THOMAS,     No.THE PRIME MINISTER,   As a matter Of fact it has come down from 125 to 115 and I think It is coming dtfwn bolow that.   Therefore he will bo receiving his 40/- in any event.MR. J.H,THOMAS,   exactly;   that is quite clear, THE PRIME MINISTER,   Then I should like to know from you what your counter proposal is to tho pro-posal which is put forward by tho Railway E. ooutivo and I want to understand fully, you see what the effect of it is,MB. J.H.THOMAS.   Exactly,   Now, our proposal is this.;   that/
you shall apply to tho other grades precisely the sane principle that you applied to the engine drivers and the firemen, namely, that you will take the highest maximum paid and add to that the 33/-.   Wow so that you may know exactly also my vieva on the further point, let no say this. You have put to mo;   But what is the position if the cost of living ^oes donna THi&apos; PRIME I-IiTISTSR:   Yes, I want that.MR, J,H, THOMAS:   I will face it cults as frankly as I want to face It now.   My answor to that is, as is the answer of my Executive Committee, that there may be differences as to -whether it is going ton or not; there may be differences as to how far it has gone down;-but let ,U3 both, for the purposes of accuracy, assume that it does go down some tine or other,   one ther it be six months or six years we can leave out of tho question.   Lot us assume that there was a substantial reduction in the cost of living anyway - I do not think it will ever como back to 1914 - approaching that or any other lovol or anything you like.   Commonsense must dictate to you as to us that just as you have put in a clause in the last agreement which Mr,, Bonar Law&apos; has emphasised, that at the end of December, ]9J9, the whole question of this war wage must be reviewed, so equally you should have a clause in that the whole question of any wage standard should be reviewed according to the circumstances then.   I see no earthly reason accept doing considerable harm outside to merely having a clause that savs you must review the war wage,, because if the men w ere going to strike what is the difference between them striking on a war wage than on a standard wage; there will be nothing in it; so far as the money is concerned there will be nothing in it from
&quot;your point of view and all 1 nay is that if the cost of living \TCTG-&apos;^ub^taitl^ally&apos;&quot;hoinuLfrom your side, which I frankly admit, toask us to review the circumstances In the light of tho then existing conditions, just as we agreed to review the posi-tion in the light of the conditions on December Slot, 1919*&apos;asHow I hope I havo been quite as .frank ami/fair In answer-ing the questions. Till&apos; PRE&apos;.V MINI .TS.i:   Yos, that Is an answer to my question. Do you mind now just pursuing the 18/- men.   Under your proposals now what would bo the standard wage of the 18/-men ?MR. BONAR LAY/:   51/-.   That is right, is it not ?MR. J-.H. THOMAS:   No, it would be more.   Me ask for a minimum of 60/- but here I want to say somethin&apos; now because ofmisunderstandings that are likely to arise.   This morningI was asked specifically whether I was proposing on behalfof this Side that every man should receive the highestmaximum and nothing less.   Now, what I wanted to put toyou before, Sir, was this.   Last- March our proposals were submitted.     They havo boon considered, thoy have boon debated, they have been reviewed.   As evidence of ouranxiety for a settlement we hove debated every &quot;ounterproposal that the Companies have put forward, or the Government, and incidentally I may say that these are not thefirst proposals; these are substantially in advance of thefirst proposals, which Is the clearest evidence that wehave not taken up the attitude of saying that unless yougive exactly what wo ask there is nothing more to befield&quot;,-&quot;   On the contrary, we have do no in this as we have in all previous negotiations, made an effort to find
accommodation from, both sides, and it was in that spiritabsolutely that I opened tlu. negotiations in ray speech last li a roh.     lo show, you that I anticipated the diillcuity-,- V . this ic the verbatim report oi the Conference held on March lvth, 1919.    nov/, that is a fairly long time ago, on this very point, which incidentally shows how long they have been going on.    But Sir Herbert &quot;Jalkor anticipated then this very point you now raise and he put this cuestion. He said:   &quot;The general principle underlying our offer&quot;  that W3S the offor they then made  - &quot;which you say your people hove rejected is that part oi the&apos;existing war wage shall be put on to the baoio standard rates, and that the remainder shall remain on as a war wage to fluctuate in accordance with the cost oi living.     Having turned down that principle, does that mean that your people will not accept anything less than the whole of the existing war wege being converted into permanent Wages?&quot;THiii P2Bhi) hlHIOThH:   I wanted to ask that.     How, what is your answer?L? J HoTHGLUiS:     This is what I said in La roh.THai PI-ULa] LOT ST Jib     That in the next thing I was going to put.J.K.THOhiS:   &quot;(hr. Thomas )   That is the decision they have arrived at.     (Sir Herbert i/aikor)    You are noi empowered to negotiate on anything less than that?   (l/ir.Thomas) That oi course is rather a delicate question, and you know me sufficiently well to know that 1 takj risks.    I would not interpret their decision as meaning that we were not empower-ed to continue negotiations, but I coiuld not interpret their decision as meaning that tluy would accept the principle that we havo already acted upon which is turned down. If you have any offer or counter arftpoaal of any sort or
kind to submit bo thorn&quot;       now need 1 road another word?TEj) PKILj lit   31.33:    &apos;io on, please.     This is really very dexterous I must say.lir.J.H.THOU.3: &apos; &quot;Ii you have any other offer or counter proposal oi any sort or land to submit to them, well then it would be done by us, and no would arrange a meeting to hear it   in last I am anxious to arrange a meeting   but you are quite right in intorprosing their decision as meaning absolutely that they would art yoowt anything less than the full war wage being out imos wm^s, and oi course plus the other items in the programme as well-&quot;. That was in Larch.     Then what hau,;.,noe.     The Company made counter offers and we went on negotiating and the iisftcutive Committee accepted the answer I gave and we have been negotiating ever since up to this moment.SIS ROBERT UGBMli:   key I interrupt to say that there followed upon that discussion which you have just been quot-? ing the agreement which was made and you rather went further in the agreement than you did in what you said because the agreement specifically provides after talking about the fixing of the standard wage &quot;This would involve a transfer of a part oi the war wage to the permanent wagen-Not the full war wage.MR. J.H.TIIOLiiS:     Yea.SIR ROBjRT HORHiS:     So you really accepted what Sir Herbert talker put to you on that occasion.THj PKIhli; MINISTER:   You mean that you would not negotiate.SIR ROBgRT HORNj:   No, that tlu negotiations were to go on, but the standard wage ohoaId&quot;involve the original wage plus a pert of the war wage;   and so clear is it that it was not intended that the whole war wage should go onthat
109X nJ (Jthat&quot;,clie-&quot;fv3,roouont^sooa further and says &quot;it the ,;niUo  tho year tho ..holo a i &quot;nut innrwill be re/lowed^tha-v/ar wage will bo looko * a b In thc:.rccuat.oncos of tho ti,..o yen,, rally.&quot;     That meant of course that thei\; was a till a war-wage enistin;-; v,hich hod nob boon put into the standard.     Therefore I en afraid lr. Thomas cannot now maintain that ha stuck religiously to tho principle which evidently lio was finding it bard to keep his foot on, when Sir Herbert halker asked him the question.LB J.II.THCE.h3:    I am quite sure, Sir Robert, you, as a lawyer know how difficult it very often is to keep on your feet, but, you would also know what within 20 hoars of the crises at any time is the time for a ui.an to show that he ia snsioua to find one way to avoid it and if I have made the mistake in not giving a blunt yea or no when I find some other way oi escape to continue negotiating it may be a crime but circumstances hove always justified .it and if either you or the prime Minister finds himself in a position tc merely say to a man &quot;yea&quot; cr &quot;NO&quot;, then I merely say that it will be a bad day for this country when the man on the workman?s side haa not sufficient brains and courage to try and find a way out instead of saying a plain yea or no.    I.y answer is that then we were in e crisis and for me to have given a straight yes to that question might have burst the negotiations and I at least was sufficiently courageous to say &quot;Ho, if there is a way of escaping I will find it&quot;,     My only comment on it today is that if it waa a mistake then made perhaps I will make the other mistake today in saying no and give a plain answer yea or no.     That ic tho only comment I makeTH.J PRIM j LIBSTj;.:    V/hat we really want ia this. Mr.Thomas may bo ssaured and the whole of his ^ecntive
that I a.&apos;.i not asking &quot;questions in order to lay trapo.Ir. J.K.THOSiiS:    I know that.:B;i Kittli) Uitt^a.    I eia anxious ii 1 oan toget peaoe on terms which era fair to the community asa whole.    Lr.Thomas put tks case very very fairly from my point of view that hr.Boner Iiaw and I are herespecially representing the community as a Whole.    Vieknow that even our proposals will involve e considerableaddition to tho lo3a at which the railways of thecountry have been running at the present moment andthat the new minister of Transport will have to &quot;make proposals within the nest few weeks for increasingthe railway rate3 all round       Passengers probably,certainly goods.
Thereforej wc arc here in the position of having to do justice, not as between share-ho.ldoi&apos;s and worknonn but gs botwr.cn tho cownm^ nity as a v/hole and the worhcrs on the rail-uaysci     I Imoii what Is due to tho Lorlrorsj and you nay depend that i &quot;ill taho that into accounto     I an one of those who have always believed that the Railway worhers before the war, certainly very larrje numbers of thorn, were disgracefully paicl0- . . .MR, BOri AH LAr:   Hear, hoar**nm PRIM? r.Ii-!ISr;:^H:   I say. so without any hosi-tatlon.     I also believe that their hours of - labour wcro such as no men ought to have been called upon to engage inj   but that is no reason for imposing burdens beyond vhat the community can pay, in order to pay wages which arc beyond the capacity of the community to require labour 101%     what that figure is I shall have to ro into very, very carefully, I shall consider with ray colleagues what Ire Thomas has said as to the counter proposal which he is putting forwardo     If there is an-r basis for negotiation.; I shall certainly seek it out-   but I could not give an answer straight away;   it would be unreasonable to ask that I should;   it is much too grave an is sue 0    It is a very grave issue for the railway worhers*    The-&apos; will have to face,-,
if they cannot sec theIn nay to accept the proposals of the Government, a very serious conflict;   am&quot;.1, everybody knows what a strike may moan.    -The whole of the community rill have to suffer.     It will bring the trade of the Country to a dead standstill;   millions of workmen will be thrown out of work;   It will be very difficult to distribute food to the community;   and that in a very serious responsibility for the hallway work-man and for tho Government to undertake5 but there is a limit beyond which wo should not bo justified in asking the community to incur further expenditure.    There is wo question of profiteering here.     This is a direct issue between the State and a class of workmen.     For all practical purposes the position is exactly the some as if the rail-ways of tho Country had been nationalised; and the issue hero is not tho sort of issue which has boon raised so often, where it is stated that big profits are made by employers of labour, and that tho workers ought to get their fair share of it.     The question is to what extent the burdens of the community as a whole, including workers, should he increased in the way of increased costs of commodities, in the way of increased cost of travel, in order to pay an increased wage to the Railway workerse     That I will consider. I hope I will get a Shorthand Note of what Mr. Thomas has said;   because I should like
to consider very carefully what ho has said. He has spoken with his usual lucidity and force;   and he has made vory clear v/hat tho case of the Railway wor1 ers is,     I think I now know vory thoroughly what the point of view of the Railway workers Is, as well as tho point of view of the Board cf Trado and the Railway &quot;xccutive;   and I shall he very much obliged if the railway Union could moot myself and my colleagues to-morrow.     It has just been put to rne that this leaves us ,vvcry little time for negotiation, If the wen go out to-morrow night;    and I was going to suggest, if you ultimately come to the conclu-sion that you cannot accept our offer, wo shall not use any powers we have as a Government to prevent your sending whatever notification you can send now to your men;   wc should not ask you to put It off, and put you in a worse position than you are;   but it leaves very little time for negotiation, to say: &quot;Unless you are able &apos;to give us an answer by 12 b1clock to-morrow, or whatever It is, then the men come out&quot;.-57*
MR. J.H.THOMAS: Let me put this position to you, Sir, that you have said about the public we recognize, because the public are to be considered, but with regard to all this talk of railway rates and passenger fares, so far as we are concerned, why should not the trading community pay to the Railway Companies in the same way as they would pay to somebody else, or themselves charge. If the worker in a private industry rota an increase, whether it is mines or anything else, the consumer or those trading in the commodity have to pay for it and we simply say it is no answer to the argument to unrest that the railway men should work under any unfair conditions.

THE PRIME MINISTER: Certainly not; I have not said that.

Do not put that into my mouth. On the contrary what I said was you must pay what is fair, but I have always to bear in mind that we are here adjudicating between the general public and the worker on the railway and one must be fair to both.

MR.J.H.THOMAS: I agree. Then that being so, there is no difference between us. May I revert once again to the situation. To be quite frank, I was upset this morning as I was upset just now by the suggestion that when one endeavours to find a bridge it must be used as an argument  
against him,   I want to put this question to you, Mr. Prime Minister,   suppose this afternoon, within a few hours of the crisis I hand o/er these terms to you and say &quot;Are you prepared to give us this or nothing else?&quot; If you wanted a rupture you would say &quot;No&quot;, hut if you wanted to find a bridge you would say &quot;Well, let us see&quot;. THE PRIME MINISTER:     Quite.MR. JJL THOMAS:   I make no more comment on that.   All my actions(- this letter that I cent to Sir Auckland God&amp;es,-were deliberately done with a view to finding a briftgw.   As to the letter that Sir Brio Geddes sent last night, my Executive know that the first thing I aid was not to seise on the points of contention because it could bo construed by those who wanted a row as not an invitation.   The wording of the lotter itself causes dlffioulty.   1 do not say It was intendedk but I want to m-ke this olear outside as well as now that if we are going to find a basis, for Grod!s sake let us do it, both 3idos giving oredit to eaoh othor to find a bridge, because my difficulty up to now the PRIME MINISTER:   I am oonoerned now for the next twenty-four hourB not so muoh with a bridge aa with a pontoon.
THE PRIME Mj:;;:iS9&apos;ER:   It is quite impossible if you really insist upon coming out tomorrow, quite   in fact I think it is hopeless, to endeavour to have a discussion, Therefore I would ask you to put. it off at any rate for two or three days so. as to give us a real chance cf talking the matter over.   &quot;&apos;e have no desire to take any unfair advantage.   Te should not stop your notices or anything of that sort.   There is no desire ,to do anything of that kin^ or to take advantage of whatever powers the Government may have in order to prevent you declaring your strike.   That is certainly not cur intention.MR.J..H.THOMAS:-   The difficulty is, as you, Mr. Prime Minister, will appreciate, at a glance, that it was necessary tr take unusual steps If there was going to be a strike and, as Mr. B^-nar La-- says, the point.is net so much sending out a notice tc step work, as the position is now that w:ork will cease unless there is a notice sent out not to cease, which is an entirely different and far m^re serious situa-tion.   Obsricusly you know that I could not, whatever my views were,&quot; give you an answer tp the question which you have put Without consultation with my colleagues, and I am gring tc, so that they will know what it is &apos;they propose.    I will just put a couple of questions to you and ask you to retire for us to consider the matter, bScause it is no good my giving an answer abmit something which they will have to be consulted upin.THE PRIME MINISTER.:-   That is perfectly natural.. MR,J,Ho THOMAS r-   I want to know exactly &quot;hat is ycur request.   Do I understand that you, having heard our &apos; side, ef the case,   propose&apos;considering the whole matter to-night and meeting,
us in the morning at 10 o1 clock ?THE PRIME MIWI.JE-.R:   Yes, to-morrow morning.IE, J.H. THOMAS: To-morrow morning to give your answer to the case we havo presented, but in the interval, correct me If I am wrong, you make a request that we shall take what steps we think necessary to prevent the men giving effect to tho ultimatum that they have received at least until the result of our negotiations are completed one way or the other, and you on the other hand undertake that if the worse comes to the worst and the strike is to become operative, the Government will not use their machinery to prevent at least the members in all parts of the country receiving the instructions from this side. Is that what I understand, is the request ?THE PR HE HIHIrTT R:   Yes, on this strike, receiving the same communication as they have already received to come out to-night,MR. J.H. THOIiAS t   I only want to know what the request is.-MR. BOKAR LAV:   I do not quite understand one point you put.   You do not expect do you that wo will be prepared, to-morrow morning without further dis-cussion with you to present to you an ultimatum ? It is a case for a few days&apos; negotiations. THE PR HE MINISTER:   I will give you an answer to-morrow morninge   You will certainly get your answor then.and, if you regard that answer as . unsatisfactory then you      take your own action.
If you rego.nl it as at any rate sufficiently satisfactory to go on, very veil, it will be for you to decide, but I must, you sco, consider very carefully your.statementj I shall consider it to-night, in fact I shall go on considering it immediately now with my colleagues,   1 think we shall have to adjourn now until to-morrow morning until we get the Notes,   But there are two or three tilings you have said which one has to consider more carefully than othersi   for instance, the answers to the questions I put.   If you came here at 12 o1clock to-morrow I should give you the-   answer which my colleagues and 1 have determined to give after considering carefully the statements which have been made by the Railway Executive and by you on behalf of tho Union,   Uith regard to the second, I have given you the answer, so therefore I think you had bettor go on.MR, SONAR LAw:   Ac to any decision you are taking as to whether or not you would stop the notices, surely it is vital to remember that this is not a case where you can bo injured immediately, because there are three months at any rato before any evil can happen to you.   That is something to bear In mind in regard to the Prime Minister&apos;s request that yo u w ill no t p r e c i p i t at e ma 11 e r s.MR, J.K. THOMAS:   he have also to consider what the position is in the country   but at all events X do not want to say a word about that now.TE.: PRI)-&quot; UIHI .T.;R.   he will not discuss that point.[Th: Cabinet \m :;hd-ew and tin Pcpnta&apos;:ien diseus sod the matter be two en themselves,.)
or,., their very strong regret that words bearing the meaning that these words boro/Mr..Bonar Law, when last we met in March have been construed to-day in b way. that we believe is foreign both to ourTHS.fRmS-JirMIS.T3S...   Now,. w^...shculd: like to hour what lc thresult of&apos; your Confer onoe...MRo THOMAS...     Tillength of this aj\eurnment will be th^best evidence shut there was very serious oonjSideration bivvn to your proposal, and I have to inform you th;;t th-j Bxeoutive Oomciiitae felt I.had better, inform ^ou tt once that a profound mistake hat; been rn-do by your side in not keeping you very fully acquainted with all the circumstances of the negotiations that have been taking place since March, Thay have,., however, noted and appreciated the fact, .and I may as   ell say, that th-y believe th..t you yourself did not understand-what I should, shortly,. call &quot;our. side&quot; of the oaso, until thiw after noon,i j^ut they., also expressed, to put it no high-
-dl-o ono opt ion - wo know foreign to tha t of tho roon&apos;o acceptance of tho:-50 words - aid could not possibly havo boon aceupted by no with any such moaning,in thorn.   I had bettor infer a you also that when that, coupled with, again, a clear difference of opinion on your side as to the moaning of tha last tlhtt.r which wo took as final, and which, apparently, you did not intend as final, judging by what was said booh this morning and this afternoon, has left them in a vary delicate and dlffijulty position of knowing what language they can understand.   They have, however, given serious consideration to tho proposal that you made to them, namely, what steps arc they prepared to take to make it possible for yea to give further coneideration to tho matter and give some answer - I thine I cm using your own words &quot;come answer&quot; - to tho position at a meeting at 12 ol clock to-morrow.   The y have dee rod, and instructed mo
to inform you, that, if your answer tomorrow holds out any hape irhasever of any settlement, they will be delighted to comply with your request and issue instructions at once.      The Idecision to strike does not operate until 12 o&apos;clock to-morrow night, and, in order to give you that fair chance that they think you are entitled to, notwithstanding the delay and [difficulties, they will be prepared to join in any arrange-ent tomorrow to cancel those notices immediately we meet, if the answer of the Cabinet is such that would warrant them aklng that step.     I have endeavoured, as briefly and as oncisely as I can, to interpret to you a decision which, gain, I would repeat, has caused very serious differences f opinion; because they felt that, after this morningfs nd this afternoonfs negotiations, we ought to be in a posi-ion even tonight to have said something to the members of different character, but they appreciate your difficulty, do not want to aggravate it, except to express the per-nal hope, and the hope of all these gentlemen,, regardlesstheir opinion, that between now and when we meet tomorrow u will see whether you cannot appreciate our difficulty d also understand cur anxiety to avoid, what I believe may suit in losing everything that this nation fought for for ve years, and for which hundreds qf thousands gave their ves.   The responsibility of destroying that and destroying js country, as we believe it would if carried to an extreme, Id be such that must compel us, regardless of any feel-s of dignity or anything else, or misrepresentation, to our best at this eleventh hour to avert the crisis,   m in that spirit that I will bring my Executive here to-jrow; I hope and believe it will be in that spirit youmeet us tomorrow
That is the only decision I have, to convoy to ^ou,THT: PRIjC UIHXSiTR:    There were so many nontrovcrsial matters raised in your statement that I hope if I do not controvert them it will not be assumed that, therefore, I accept them,MB THOMAS: Ycu may take it there will he great anxiety to reach a decision.TEE PR Ilia iIIKl3&apos;F.Il:   I oannot accept tho criticism that 11137 colleagues have not informed me.     After allM there arf a thousand and one things in all Departments which happens and they can only bring them to the notice of the Ho ad of the Government at certain stages in the proceedings.     They have brought this to my notice when it reached an acute stage when it required decision. I am not going to enter into the c-ncstion of who is responsible of precipitating the crisis.        That would be folly whorl we all admit the mosu important thing of all is tc put an end tc the crisis, and the only question I should like to ask is this- supposing we meet tomorrow at IE noon; I assume we shall have a talk, at any rate for about an hour, and I also assume that whatever I say will call for some deliberation en the part of your . Executive.    hill it be possible for yeu at that time, supposing ycu came to the conclusion that what I said was sufficiently hopeful, at any rate, to induce you to prolong negotiations   I do not mean to say it would be sufficiently hopeful that you could accept   but sufficiently hopeful to induce you tc prolong negotiations with a view to trying to arrivo at a satisfactory arrange-ment, will it not then bo too late for you?.MR THOMAS:   Ho, we will meet you on that point, because,
ftftiov ftS-?.,   rfiCftgy^BC tb.M., ftftajr .9.0.3. tho mont^w        2 we have been negotiating:;, no sar.o man weald accept the Head cf the Gcve^rmeat to come to a decision on what I might call all the details.     Ocmmcnscnse tolls mc it is impossible to expect, but you have hoard what I \ uuld call very fundamental differences of or.iuei.plc this aftemccn,THO MINISTER;   That is, if you have any hope&quot; of settling tomorrow.MR THOMAS;   Which I rhimitcd myself to, and if the indication from your side, which will be very scon grasped by me, I hope, is such that would warrant-that I would say, without hesitation, we should immediately take the necessary stops to do it   without hesitation, and we could do it,TJ.jT-1 3mlCLIP. MINISTER*   Yen could do it? &apos;-M THOMAS:   We could and world.     Our machinery,with the greatest respectis. in tlris connection^tc put it no higher) as good as that cf the Government,and you knew wo arc net a small organisaticn,I knew seme people .may say that it is not sayingmuch, but I will not put it higher,.     At all events,I have sufficient confidence in my own machinery and the organisation.     As you knew, it is not a minor organisation.      Vie have staff, we havemachinery, wo have everything, so that&apos;if at any timel$Lp to two o1 clock tomorrow&apos;there is any hope,judging bj the answer you.will give us of accommodationen the principle, then I . ill give you the guaranteehere and now.that there will be no difficultywhatever...       It is only fair tc say, also, -I think,that in this crisis you can rely upon the loyaltyand ooepcration of our men.TIE PBlMT- MINISTER: I -ie not think there is any more to&apos;say.    T&apos; olyo oTclock tomorrow we ^hall meet. MR. THOMAS:   H*re? THE PRI1F MIHISTT.R:   Yes.    .(Thr Meeting then adjourned) 47&apos;.
E&amp;cJM^Jjeptginber 26. 1919.FRO.&apos;&apos;-&apos;THE EXtfCUTTTS OGMITTEEJOF THE. 1I0^\L UKICN Off ffiL:7Ai^3H.5THE PRIME MINISTER:   Gentlemen, as one wants to avoid every possibility of any misunderstanding about words or phraseswhich are used, I have reduced to writing most of what Ihave to say,   If we finally are unable to come to an understanding we.are confronted with the mosi serious Laboutrouble which this country has ever seen;   and therefore make no apology for doing my best, and for my colleaguesdoing their best, to arrive at a possible solution,&apos; if it
- oan be done.   But, as I pointed out yest&quot;:*day, we. have a variety of great interests in our charge.   vVe have got to see fair-play to the workmen engaged on the railway^ but we have also rot to see that fair-play is done to the general public,   and I again emphasize the fact that here there is no conflict between capitalists and workmen, because whatever increases are made will be passed on to the gen-eral public.     Owing to the very substantial increases in the actual payments which lave been made up to the present and the cost which is involved in a substantial reduction in the hours of labour, the whole of the railway rates of. this country must necessarily be revised and very substantial increases &quot;must be made either in the costs of the travelling pudlic or in the costs of the transport of goods, or probably in both,   Whatever deci-sion we come to.in ^hese negotiations, nothing can avert that., and I want not merely you, gentlemen, because I am sure you will understand it, out I want the men whom you represent, and I want the whole public thoroughly to realise that this is not in the ordinary sense, of the term a difference cf opinion between employer and   or&amp;nan   it is a question - of what burdens you oueht fairly to impose upon the general public of all classes- in orde 1 to do -what is fair and right to the railway workers,   dven the proposals which have been put forward by the Government involve an increase in the deficiency and a substantial increase in the deficiency which had been created by oth.?-cone as si ons ..Mr J.H.THOMAS:   One moment.   Do I now. understand that younow make the statement that there is a deficit on the rail-ways through the improved conditions of the men?THE PRIME MINISTER:   An enormous deficit.
J jr/raoi&amp;St,- Do- you.nonfirm that a tat-eTnerrt, Sir1 Hric Geddes?SIR ERIC GEDDES!   Put your question again.Mr J.H.THOMAS:   I refer to the statement that J.he Prime Minister has just made, namely, that the proposals ,already submitted by the Government will add to the deficit on the railways brought about by the increases to the men .proposed.   The Prime Minister turned to you, Sir Erie, apparently for confirmation, and before we:go another yard I want to know whether Sir Eric Geddes confirms that state-ment of fact.SIR ERIC GEDDES:   The answer to that is that when you bring in the war-wage today it is not clear.   If you will let me work out the figures I will answer the point as you go along.Mr J.H.THOMAS:   It is of vital importance,   I understood you, Lir Priuie Minister, in your opening remarks wanted to be so careful in the event of disagreement because you are goIn? to issue a statement to the public;   and I am going to say that it is equally important that my statement must also, in fairness, be issued to the public the PRIME MINISTER.   Certainly.Mr J*H.THOMAS:   And therefore it is doubly important to have the facts issued to the public and to agree with us what-ever statement you issue to the public, and I take it that you will arrange for the same facilities with regard to the answers which I shall give.THE PRIME MINISTER:   Cf course the Press will publish any statement you put forward on behalf of the railway men, and I have no doubt at all but that they will publish any statement which I or anyone else put   forward on behalf of the Government..  We shall actually give the figures if
&quot; i t nhoul d* &quot;&apos;b c no c es s a r y ,Have you the figures yet, Sir Eric1? SIR P.RI0- GF.RDSS:   No-    I will five them later on, TEE PRJLE LlINIbTER.    Mow, this is a differeneo,xrf-e-wlnlonnot about any wages which are to be paid during the current-year:   it in a difference of opinion with regard to the wages which.a.re to be paid after the 31st December.   How, how has this dispute arisen?   The present difficulty with\
regard to railwayman7a wages has its origin in the facts that, before the IVar, each Company had its own grades of worxmen, its own rates of remuneration^ and its own general conditions of service.   During the &apos;-7ar, to meet the increased cost of living, a flat war-wage was granted to the railwaymen, and this, when the coat of living reached its maximum4 say 1&amp;5 per cent, above the pre-war rate, amounted to 33/- per man per week, regardless of his grade of service or rate of wages.   The agreement which governed the grant of the war-wae.e stipulated that,as the cost of living fell, the war-wage would be reduced   I draw special attention to that clause in the agreement, Mr JJi, THOMAS:   Do you mean by that that the agreement we arenow dealing with stipulates that? Mr BOMB LAW:   No, it is the sliding-scale agreement, THE PRIME MINISTER:   I am referring to the agreement withregard to the war-wage.   The agreement which covers the grant of thew^ar-wage stipulated that,as the cost of living fell, the war-wage would be reduced., After the Armistice the rail-way men put forward a request that their future wages should be based upon, the amounts which they were then receiving in wage and war-wage, and that, in addition, the pay of every man who did similar work under similar conditions should be .standard-ised.   In addition, they asked for improved general conditions of service, namely, an eight-hours day, extra pay for Sunday duty, overtime, night duty, special arrangements with regard to holidays, and fp&quot;* a large number of minor adjustments in the conditions of service of the various grades.   The. request for the eicrht-hours day was granted, and, in order to give time for. the very complicated re-adjustments required, an agreement was entered into by the Government, on the one hand, and the Railway Unions on the other, to the general effect that until the 31st December, 1919, the sliding scale affecting the war-wage would
not onorate, and that &quot;a11waymen&apos;s wages should -remain at the same figure aa prevailed at the Armistice.   In this respect the railwaymen obtained an advantage over the other workmen of the country whose wap;e3 were only stabilised until gist November, 1919.;   The agreement also provided that negotiations should proceed to adjust the conditions of wasea and to fix future minimum wages.   At the time it was clearly contemplated that, in general, the full pre-war wage would not be consolidated with the,old basic rate, although in some instances the new standard wage might be more than the old wage plus the war-wage. Prom the date of the,agreement until now, the negotiations have proceeded and agreement has been reached upon all points affecting the general conditions of employment;   and the effect of that settlement has been to improve enormously the general conditions under which railwaymen carry on their most important industry, and we all rejoice in that, These negotiations were necessarily protracted, as they covered the ^moloyment of hundreds of thousands of men wo.rK.ini?, in every part of the country under all sorts of differing.conditions, whose rates of wages had pre-viouslv been determined according to the system of the particular railway on which they worked.   It would not be&apos; quite accurate to say there were almost as many systems as there were railways, but it would not be far wvohfj, to say there was almost a different system on every railway;   and the &apos;efore the time it took to examine the question over the whole ground was necessarily one which occupied a.good many weeks.   Accordingly, the necessity of reducing all these different grades on the different railway lines to a uniform system- T,,as a matt :-r &quot;of infinite detail and-54-
requiring a moat elaborate investigation by numerous sub-committees of experts before decisions could be arrived at.   The result has been that,by the alterations which have been made in the conditions of service, the men have been enabled to obtain considerably increased earn-ings* firstj because the hours of work were reduced from 10, and in some cases from 12, to R;   second, through the increased rate allowed for Sundav duty, night duty and ordinary overtime,   It is estimated that the increase of earnings thus effected amounts, in the case of ordinary men, to an average of SO per cent.   That is  0 per cent, upon the ordinary wage, is it not? SIR ERIC GKDDES:   Yes,Mr JJ-LTHOIvIAS:   The statement of the Prime Minister was that the amount already granted was equivalent to SO per cent,, but vou mean it is 20 per cent, on this offer,SIR ERIC G-IDDES:   &quot;hen applied to the new standard rates.Mr J,Ti.THOMAS:   Then you are wrong there,THE PRIME MINISTER:   An increase of earnings on the proposals made by the Government,   In accordance with the previous agreement, negotiations have been going on for some time for the purpose of fixing the&apos;standard minimum rates to be applicable in the fu*u?e to all classes of railway services.   The classes first dealt with were the locomotive drivers,- fire, en and cleaners.   These were satisfactorily arranged, and the present trouble has arisen out of the
fixinr? the standard for other branches of railway service,   I shall have something to say late0 with regard to the rates fixed for 4 he drivers, firemen and cleaners.   In the meantime, we ought to be clear as to what the standard rate which we are attempt into fix is, because if there in a dispute do not let us hive a dispute about a misunderstanding as to what the actual proposals are.   It is not a rate to come into operation at once, because the agreement still prevails which stabilises the railwayman&apos;s wages to the 31st of December.   It does not even come into operation then, because the agreement provides that at that date the whole situation is to be again reviewed, and I shall have something further to say about that later on.   The fixing of the standard is really only an attempt to establish a minimum below which wages will not in future drop-, in the case of the railway services, however much the&apos; cost of living diminishes.   I want to draw especial attention to that,Mr J.H.THOMAS:   That i* to say, that no matter what ultimate standard basis was agreed upon, the cost of living would not affect it in the least?THE PRIME MINISTER:   hot. in the least.SIR ERIC CkDDBS:    It. would not affect it in the way of reducing it-.Mr BONAP LAW:   Of course no. Government can guarantee a minimum for ever.
V.r J.F,Tr&quot;&apos;Ol&apos;.AS:    No,THE PPUffi L&apos;.inTSTTR:   7?e-are-dealing *ith th.o facts of today J.H.&quot;KCIIAS:    Let us oe quite clear,   That,, jou want to emphasize to ray side is: &quot;Do no- let us mix o\^agenda^iLaartiorr--v/if,h cost of livings&quot;,   that is what you want to emphasize.? THb PRIME iuIUIST;..R:   ho.    I will deal with the cost of living late:1 on.   The cost of livine;, let us say., was 1?,$ per cent. when the &apos;r&apos;ar-wa&quot;e was fixed at 3-3/-.   Sup-nosing the cost of living goes down, if you lime,&apos; until-----iir JJLTHOLAS:   Until it is normal.TIP&apos;;-; PRILile ,J&quot;JIST.-&quot;,R: ; &quot;Jell, until it is 50 pea cent,kr J .K.TiiOiiAS:    It does not matter what the figure is.Tim&apos; Pell^ KIJJISTER:   That dees not affect the standard, the standard remains;   and even if it comes down to normal it does not affect the standard -uVge.   Tame a plate-layer who is earning 18/- to 20/- a week, you were paying him less, I re...e.her, near my hoe.   Suppose, the standard which is fixed is 40/-, and suppose the cost of living coe.es d.o&quot;&apos;n to r.orwal, he gets 40/- instead of 18/-.   That is what the standard means.   Then you &apos;dll say:   Suppose the cost of living still remains at 115   well, that I will deal with later;   that in a different question, and I will deal with it presently.mr J,H,TH0mmS:    &quot;That you -ant clearly to put before us, as I pather, is this,   let us have no ambiguity about it.mm? ppT?-s rwwTSTep:    i -think it is very tersest ant there should not be any ambiguity.mr J.H.Ti:0mA3:    There were., to the disgrace- of all of us, plate-layers, as you rightly say, get ine near your hone 17/- and IB/-.
LXPRiM MINI3TEH:   Yes.Ct. J.F.&apos;&quot; fC&quot;.- )3, N ;w tie cost of living to-day; lot Us take it at anyffigure you like * J2l PRIMJ MINISTER;   115 I think you may tak.-* as the final figure , ft J...H4&apos;E0k S:   New 33/- ard 1?&apos;/- with the uoGt   f livnug an it is to-day is 50, and that is an entirely aiff^r^nt thing to 40 with the cost ef living as it te;^*Vl^l.4fl 3D PRIME MINISTER: Yos, but supposing the cost cf living&apos;6omes dowri to that of 1914, he will get   his 40/*4 That is not affew led Try tho fluctuation In the cost of living? r. J*H.THOMAS:   You are quite entiled end it is your duty to put that; and I am equally anxious there should be no mistake in exactly what you mean. !HE PRIME MINISTER: I want you to know, and I want the public to know exactly what it means, that it represents a permanent xw-iroase in the lower wages.   For instance, those who were receiving 17/- to SO/- a week*   It establishes a minimum wage for them of 40/- whatever the cost of living is? r. j.H.THOMAS:   Yes9UHE PRIME MINISTER:   The fixing of the standard is really only an aattempt to establish a minimum below which wages will not in future drop in the case of the railway service however much the oost ef living diminished . An effective contrast will he soon whon it le rooollocted that whereas tho minimum wage for any railway servant whioh has boon suggested by the Govern-ment at the present timo is 40/-.&apos;; the same men were, previous to the war;&apos; working for a sum varying from 18/- to  0/- per woek.   I ropoat it because I think it is important to repeat it, that this 40/- will remain fixed th ough tho oost   cf living should go back to the pre war figure.   The present complaint put forward by the railwayman is that this standard is not being fixed as high as the present aggregate wageThe terms of the agreement cf March, however, make It
clear that the parties did not contemplate that the standard should be fixed at such a figure. I refer, in particular, to the phrascology dealing with the fixing of the standard, which is thus stated:-

"This will involve the transfer of a part of the war wage to the permanent wage", Further, the Agreeement goes on to say that at the end of the year, the whole situation will be reviewed. The war wage will have to be looked at in the light of the circumtances of the time generally".

This clearly contemplates that there will still remain some part of the war wage which has not been incorporated in the standard. And it is further provided that it will be open to the men to ask for a revision of the now standard rates if they think a case can be made for it. This seems to make it clear that it was foreseen that the conditions of living at the end of the year might not have improved to the extent that was hoped and if that should turn out to be so the men would have an opportunity of making representations against the reduction of the present earnings of the standard wage which had been fixed in the interval. It is contended, however, that the rates already fixed for drivers, firemen and cleaners embody the principle that no reflection is to be made on the present earnings in fixing the new standard.

That was one of the points made very powerfully by Mr. Thomas yesterday, and I should like to deal with it. Two points fall to be made upon this contention. In the first place, the standard fixed for the cleaners - whatever may be said with regard to it - does not embody this principle because the rate fixed for this class of railway servant works out at a less sum than the present aggregate rates. Further, in putting forward the case for the drivers and fireman, both the railway unions made a special plea on their behalf to the effect that they had been unfairly dealt....
with when the war wage was fixed. The argument presented was that a flat rate gave a much higher percentage increase to the low paid men than to the highly paid men - that is obvious - and that in as much as the drivers and fireman were better paid than the ordinary railway servants they had received, less in proportion than the lower paid servants. It is obvious that if the lowest paid servants were to be dealt with now in the same way as the higher paid servants, this would be only repeating the anomaly which the unions previously protested against. As a matter of fact this is a difficulty we came up against in granting a war bonus to civil servants. The question was whether you were going to give an increase all round say of 50 or 60 a year, or whether you were going to give a percentage increase. That question was examined very carefully by an impartial body, and they came to the conclusion there that ? mere fixed amount added on to the wage of every member of the Civil Service, whether he was of the first rank, the second ?, or the third rank, would not be fair, and that therefore the best method of dealing with the matter was a combination of percentage, and a fixed grant. But in the main I think the increase there ia a percentage increases. That was the contention of the drivers and the firemen.

-THOMAS: No, not the firemen.

ADMINISTER: Not the firemen, but the drivers. That was the contention of the drivers, and there is a good deal to be said for it; and we were acting upon a principle which we had already applied in the case of civil servant as the result of the recommendation of the thoroughly impartial investigators. Further it was argued by both Unions that the pro-war rates for
drivers and fireman v/ere dispropo rtionately low considering the skill these men must necessarily possess ana the responsibility which rests upon their shoulders.iThe Government took this view into consideration in -fixing the standards for these grades, and it was on this ground and not - ae is alleged - in accordance with the principle of combining the old wage with the presentewar wage that their new standards were arrived at. Indeed, at the disoussion which took place with regard to the rates to be given to the drivers and firemar it wqs specifically stated by thG representatives of the men that the other grades of service still to be considered would be dealt with cn their own merits; and that is what we have attempted t.o do.
?1. Now let me summarise first of all what I consider the present proposals of the Railway Executive to mean.  (1) The new standard wage proposed is equal to an average of at least one hundred per cent over the pre-war wage and guarantees to every adult railway worker, irrespective of any fall in the cost of living, a permanent minimum of 40/- per week. This figure of 40/- compares with the minimum of 18/- to 20/- per week before the war. (2) In addition the extra payments for Sunday duty, night duty and overtime recently conceded and now in operation are equal on the average to another twenty per cent on the pre-war wage. (3) In addition to these, advantages in money the hours of labour have boon reduced to eight. (4) These increases are put forward as the permanent railway wage to remain irrespective of any possible fall in the cost of living. (5) In any event the issue does not arise until the 31st December, as until then no man will receive less than his present aggregate earnings, and during that time there is time for negotiations which the Governmen are willing to continue,   (6) In addition tc this standard increase there is no question of reducing the present total wage at the 31st, December if the cost of living should be the same as at present.

MR J. H. THOMAS: ? do you mean by that?

THE PRIME MINISER: To cost of living new is 115.

MR BONAR LAW: The war wage will continue.

THE PRIME MINISTER:  To war wage will continue.

MR J. H. THOMAS: This is something new. Is there is anything new I want tc know what it is.

MR BONAR LAW: This is not new.

MR J. H. THOMAS: At any rate this is the first I have heard.
of it,THE PRIME MINISTER.     I think this last is new.MRBJ.H,THOMAS. It has certainly novor teen convoyed to mo &quot;before*idoBONA3 LA1:.     It is not new to me though.THE PRIME MIHIST3H. Before you mako any comment let me put the three things to you;   I have something beyend this,MHoJoHcTHCMaS.     I want to be quito clear whet it meansfirst.THE PRIME MINISTER.    Ask me on the three;   this is only the be ginning 8    In addition to this standard Increaso there-is no question of reducing tho present standard wage at tho 31st December if tho cost of living should be tho same as at present.    In dealing with any portion of the war wage   this is new.MR.J*H.THOMAS.    So is tho other.THE PRIME MINISTER.    Yes, but this goes further.     In dealing with any portion of the war wage whioh may remain when the new standard rates come into operation, tho Government &quot;undertake that Buch residue will not be reduced until the cost of living has fa lon and remained for three months at not more than 110 por cent. -- it is now 115 per cent;   it was 125 when the war wage of 33/- was fixed.    110 por cont addition to the pro war cost of livingo    It must be borne in mind that the present war wago of 33/- was fixed under the sliding scale when the cost of living was 125 per cent above tho pro-war cost,    You can ask mo a question upon those two together now because the other is a different point.MR.J.H.THOMAS. Let rae see if I understand it first, because it is doubly necessary to understand it.THE PRIMS MINISTER.     Indeed it is.     Do not let us have strife about any misiuiderstanding,
MR. J.H, THOiaS:     In tho first place, why 1 interjected that it was some thing new was this,    Mr. Donor Law said ho thought it was not.MR, dOdAA La..:      I am sorry;   I understood it to be so.mii. J.H. THC AS:   .;hat I want to make clear is that so far as wo are concerned on this sido of the table this is the first Intimation of any sort or kind of what tho Government1s intention is after the 31st December.SIR ERIC GEDDESi     I thought we had it yesterday, !\r. Thomas. I remember distinctly conferring about the matter with Sir David Shaokioton.THE PRIME MINISTER:     d-hat matter   is the proposal, if you do not mind.     Do not begin to discuss that, otherwise we shall have to begin looking at the Shorthand Notes and I really do not want to do that because this you will get in writing.MR. J,H, THOMAS:     But I want to know what it is first, before I met it in writing.     ddhat I understand you are now saying is that if agreement is reached on the question of standard-isation whatever the margin of difference between standard-isation and war wage may bo      -THE PRIME MINISTER:   &apos; And. tho existing&apos;wago.MR. J.H. THO; AS:     The war wage.THE PRIME MINISTERj     It is the residue of the war wage. MR. J.H. THOMAS:     That is to say whatever the difference may be,THE PRIME MINISTER:     Yes, whatever the difference in theresidue of the war wage may be. MR. DONAA LAW:     Because some of the war wage will be absorbed in the standard. MR. J.H. THOMAS:   -1 will give you a simple &quot;illustration.I will come back to the minimum.     Suppose 40/- was the
standard for man &quot;A&quot; and he is in receipt of a found a week;   there is there a difference of 13/.-&apos; war wage, is not there?MR. BONAR LAhi     Quite true.SIR ROBERT HORNE:     Yes.MR. J.I1. THO. AS:     His basic rate is a Pound.     You have nowoffered a minimum of  2, THE PRIME MINISTER:     Yes.MR. J.H. THOMAS:     The difference between the  2 and what he now receives is lo/-. THE PRi: E MINISTER:     Yes.MR, J,H, THOMAS:     Very well;   &quot;,&apos;hat you say is that after the 31st December this agreement that nominally expires then will continue to be in operation and he -rill draw the 13/-as he does to-day until at least three months after the cost of living comes below 110 per cent,?THE PKIiiE MINISTER:     You, that is it.MR. J,H, THOMAS:     That is only part.THE PRIME MINISTER:     Hot merely docs it come under 110 but it must have been for throe months,, because you see it may flop up and down.     It must bo down for throe months-sMR. J,H. THOiAS:     I clearly understand that the drop mustbe a drop for three months and remain bolow 110, THE PRIME MINISTER:     Yes, MR, J.H, THOMAS:     Very well, what then.THE PRIME MINISTER:     be do not went to take advantage of a temporary drop which may be due to a great importation of something or other into the counary,MR, J.H. TH0.M/.S;     I follow that exactly, but that is only or stage.     Hoi: a drop takes place for three months and lot us assume by way of illustration that it droppod and
hi hi Oremained for three months at 105  that is below 110&apos;     Now again coming back to this man with 13/-what do you propose is to happen then; or, in other words, vhat Is to be the margin, 5 per cent of 13/-THE PRIME MINISTER:    I will tell you&apos;at once what the difficulty is there...     That ever we lay down with regard to the railway men you may depend upon It ia going to be claimed throughout the country; and therefore we have to consider not merely your case,., but we have to consider the cases of all other trades in the Kingdom,MR. Jf,H. THOMAS.:   Of course as you know.,, that equally applies to our side and we feel that; we feel equally in coming down that v,e are doing some-thing for the -rest of the workers.THE PRIME MINISTER:   But there are two ways in which that can be dealt with.   Undoubtedly the best way of dealing wIth it would be to deal with it in conjunction with all the trades of bhe country, because you must remember that the same problem is going to arise with every trade.   The war wage has been fixed in all trades with refer-nee to an increase of 125.     When it comes down it was thoroughly understood that there should be a reduction in the war bonus in every trade.     &quot;hat we are stipulating here is that it should not come down until it is something substantial.     At this figure it   is down 10 per cent at present.     we are stipulating that there should be no alteration until it comes down 15 per cent and remains at that figure\
When it comes - dom belowthut- you^have...to consider the &quot;hole of the trades of the country ^nd what the Labour&apos;Depart iii out suggests is that the Tribunal which Is dealing with that matter should consider it in reference tr. all the trades of the country., And the same thing would apply to you.     The second method of dealing with it is under the sliding scale agreement,     New these are two ways by which it can be dealt with.     V.re are q&amp;ite open to discuss which of the two ways would be the right way of dealing with it.     It does not mean;mind you; that no allow-ances will be made under 110; but what-the allowance Is must be a subject for discussion at the time, either in conjunction with the general trades   of the country, because   what applies to you applies to every trade throughout the country, or under your own special agreement.     That we are open to discussion   upon-. MR. THOMAS.     Yes, all I am anting and enquiring at this stage is, whether the proposal that you now submit to us even if the cost of living is below 110 and remains below no for three months, does not necessarily mean that the residue of the -war-wage will all come off. THE PRIME MINISTER.     Oh, no. -.   MR. THOMAS.     I want to be quite clear on that.-6V-
9 97THE PRIME MINISTER.   Certainly not.MR. THOMAS.   rhat you do propose ia that that residue whatever it is shall be reduced in some ether agreed v.&apos;ay applicable to the whole of the Country,, or alternatively, in accordance vith the sliding scale hitherto in existence vith us.     Is that what I understand?THE PRIME MINISTER.     I say at once tc you that those who are concerned with the settlement of labour throughout the Country, employers and v,crk-men, are pleading that it should be dealt with as a general issue..   &apos;They say it is very difficult to Settle it for one trade and not for the others, and they would infinitely prefer that the ^hole of the trades of the Country should come into a dis-&apos; cussion of the principles upon which you are going to adjust the war bonus ijhich is attributable to the increased cost of living-     We are prepared to discuss with you which of the two methodswill be the better one to adjust the differences when;you come under 110,   hut we do not want to raiae it at all if the cost of living does not come under 11^.. MR. ,THOMAS. .   All I am cencerned with at the present moment in considering the new proposal is to know exactly &quot;hat the new proposal means and how it affects everybody.     That is whet 1 want to get at.THE PRIME MINISTER. .  There is one other word I want to say because there has been a great deal of discussion about/&apos;,
tho meaning of word is&quot; and aa to what anomalies and details mean.m THOMAS.   And a groat deal of differenceTH&amp; /RIME MIlliaTJSR.   Hore ;i0yin do not lot us havo strife or a fight about words,   -That I want to say is that in fixing the now standard rates.tho basis hes b on roughljtan average addition of 100 per cent over the pre-war wago. and that the Government will not act on rigid linesj but will in the future as in the past, be ready to consider and discuss anoma-lies and c ses of hardship to any particular grades in the application of the percentage of increase to bo made,MR. THOMAS.     I will deal generally with your statement in a moment, but again now for the purooso of definition I want to know what that means,    let me put it in my own way to see if I know what it means..     Suppose I a-.-&apos;, in o position to show that the proposal offered by.the Government for standard rates say to a guard or a goods worker or any other grade, it does not matter what, is not so advantagoous evon on percentage as another grade,SIR BRIO GEDDES   (in a whispered aside to the Prime Minister) - We could not do   that.MR, THOMAS.   Then I need not say anything further.THE PRIME MINISTER. Ploaso continue Mr. Thomas, s-Mr Eric Geddes&apos; remark was addressed to mo privately, and you ought not to havo heard itu . *MR. THOMAS.   Hero wo are within a few hours of the strike and I sm doinfo all I   can to help you.THE PRIME MINISTER,     V/hen wo are consulting together you are not supposed to hear,MR. THOMAS. But it is no good when he says, I cannpt agree to that,   I h*d not made the suggestion,THE PRIME MINISTER.    Thot ia something which is sal&amp; to me,MR,, THOMAS.   Let me try to make the suggestion.   I am;and ]doing all I can to find some way out/if I can leave this&apos;&apos;
room finding a way out I will do it, but I do know it is difficult to find a. way out I moan it is difficult to do it   and no one knows that hotter than I do.As I understand your proposal, it is this, that you say in addition to tho other offers you have given, whon I use -the figure 100 per cent, whatever the figure is, that thore may ho anomalies as applying to certain grades, and that this 100 per oent is not applicable to them.   Well, what I want to know is what does that mean, end to give you a simpleillustration I will take the cq30 of the goods guaid or they/jupassenger guard.     If I am able to show/that the general maximum over the country is 65/-* now with the war-wage, tho combined maximum, whieh means in other words an average of 32/- before making it 65/-, and if I m able to show you that responsible as tho position Is for guards, goods workers or whatever they may bo under tho category, this offer of 60/-is not oven in conformity with the principle of your proposal -is that what you mean by removing an anomaly.     In other words if I am able to say, No, your 100 per oent is not true, to putU i iit very bluntly, -that Is tho very figure you have mentioned.THE prime MINISTER.   Here again I am going to say exactly tho same thing as Mr. Thomas 3     It is very important that I should know exactly what it is ho is asking before I givo an answer in ,die affirmative or tho negative,   You see the 100 por cent is an average^MR. THOMAS.    Yes.THE PRIME MINISTER.   That means that some people aro getting more than 100 per cent, but that also means that seme will be getting loss than 100 per cent.   If Mr. Thomas says: Well, if I could show to you that somebody is getting less than 100 per cent will you put it up to 100 per cent -MR. THOMAS.   Lot me givo you a simple illustration.   I
want to bo quite fair and that there should be no misapprehension-haiisionu     I will give you two illustrations in this room. &quot;ra will take two men in this room to illustrate tho point Here is Anderson at Bristol, a mo u who is a guard, a men with lDng eaoerionce.   Jow his present rato is 31/- o. we eh plus 33/-.-.THE PRIME IlIILTSTERo   64/-.Iffio THOMAS..   64/-,   This is shortly his ease.,   He says the fireman who was not even a fireman when ho was a guard, but a oleaner, end who wos aotting 24/-, has rot 33/- added to his, which io much more than 100 por cent, but he is limited to a mamimuii if ho goes on to it of 60/-.   His maximum is 60/r under the pro -osal, -aid therefore he is 4/- less than either hie present combined or his 100 per cent-,    That is or.o illustration,,     lot mo give you another,THE PRIME MI1MI3TER.   Do you mean under the standv-rd&apos; wage ho gets 60/-?MR, THOMAS.     Yes,,THE PRIilE his.3T3R.     He- is now gotfihg 64/-, MR, THOMAS.   Exactly.THE -cRDvffi MINISTER,,   And he will got 60/- plus whatever allowance is made fo- the cost of living?MR. THOMAS,    Yes, but I em dealing with the now present point for the moment,     nor  I will give you another illustra-tion of v/ilson.     Wilson comes from li owe as tie.   He is a goods worker on the Worth Eastern,   He is under this proposal getting ll/- less than tho 100 per cent,,   Do mot mix now merging 33/-wlth the standard wage, because I am doalin, with your actual statement of 100 per cent;   I am limiting it to that exclusively.   Wilson io getting exactly ll/- loss per week toon 100 per cent.SIR ERIC CEEDS3*   dive mo his pay,MR, THOMAS.       23/^c
THE PRIME MINISTER,     28/.- pro-war?MR, THOMAS,    100 per cent would bo 55/- and your propo-sals ore 45/-.SIR ERIC GEDDES,   &quot;What ore you?MR. WILSONc   A drayman or trolley-man.the, THOMAS-   In order that you may have/   full foots   &apos; before you I will take another mano     I will take Robson and see how he comes out.     Robson comes under the other agree-ment.     He was a driver.   His pre-war v.tgo was 6/6 a day.   He now gets 15/- per day, so that he gets an increase of 8/6 per day.     I do not want to get into anomalies, but what I am trying to beg of you to keep in mind is that we have got to go outside and explain these anomalies and try to get them understood.     There you have three illustrations of exactly how it operates in the different ways0THE PRIME MINISTER. I think I will go out and have a talk about this. Is there anything else you want to men-tion before I go out.MR, THOMAS.     I will reply to some of your statements presently.     I now understand that is the amended proposal. I will put it In this way; that is the position.   The Cabinet wants us to understand how those proposals operate *. THE PRIME MINISTER. There are two or three definite con-cessions which are not In the original thing.MR. THOMAS.   No, but I would ask you to remember this in considering it, and I had better say it now so that you have the full facts before you. : All these what Sir Herbert Wal-ker calls side-shows which wore mentioned to you, such as overtime, Sunday duty, night duty, and which we call side-shows, amount to 20 p .r cent.   Then I w nt you to clearly keep this in mind.     It is because we are continuing,; at the request of the Companies to allow the man, although thoy
aa*er kicking about working the excessivo hours, and. we ere saying to them: (So on working then.     That is the first point i made.   The second pcie&apos;1 Is this.   I ask Sir Robert Home, vuio is v/ith you, to coco up any agreement for any trade; or industry in the Country and show me one where for night work they do not yet double what we are retting - in the main treble - for night work.   Turn up any agreement for ahy out-side trade or Industry where they do not get at least 5&quot;0 per cent more for Sunday work than we get;&apos;turn&apos; up any ireland.de or industry where tire overtime or sis is not more than 50 per cent whrt we are getting.   31 merely ask you in keeping these things in mind not to talk about outside conditions without having those facts in your mind..   You have hecrd what I say.THE PRIME MINISTER.   Are there any further questions you want to ask about this, because. I should rather like to re-tiro with my colleagues for a little whilecMr. THOMAS.   I suggest you should retire because: 1 may wa: to      put some new proposals, so that you? may be able to give ua an answer on this,.The Prime Mini st e   and Jail s coll e agues wi thdrew and after a short intorvr.1 returnefl.THE PRIME MINISTER.     You put &quot;a series of questions to me which I understood to mean not were we prepared&apos; to make the -concessions which you are asking, but were we prepared to discuss and to negotiate with regard to them:.     You put two or three typical illustrations.
oare kicking about working the excessive hours, and. we ore sayitir&apos; to then: (So on working then.     That is the first point ; made.   The second p-oiodl Is this,   1 ask Sir Robert Home, vnio is with you, to euro up any agreement for any trade, or incHistry In the country  and show me one where for night work they do not get double what we are retting - in the main treble - for night work,   Turn up any agreement for any out-side trade or Industry where they do not get at least 5&quot;0 per cent more for Sunday work than we get;&apos;.turn up any trade or industry where the overtime basis is not more- than 50 per cent what we are getting.   I merely ask you in keeping these things in mind not to talk about outside- conditions without having those facts in your mind.   You have heard what I say.THE PRIME MINISTER.   Are there any further questions you want to ask about this, because I should rather&apos;like to re-tire with my colleagues for a little whilesMr. THOMAS.   I suggest you should retire because: I may want to      put some new proposals, sb that you? may be able to give ua an answer1 on this,.The PrimeJJinisteand Jhis-co11earues withdrew &apos;and after a short interval returned.THE PRIME MINISTER.     You put&quot;a series of questions to me which I understood to mean not wore we prepared to make the -concessions which vou are asking, but wore we prepared to discuss and to nerotiatc with regard to them.     You put two or three typical illustrations.
MR J. H. THOMAS;    Do nut lot us havo any misunderstanding ;   about that.     I put it to you! Has that the Mind of thingyou meant as an anomaly and would you agree to that beingmet.-THE PRIME MINISTER:   Yfe will agree to yo; putting your case in reference to it.    That might bo an individual anomaly and when you are standardising you-; must deal vdth tho so things in grados.    If a particular grade is suffering f 10 m an anomaly,I do not mi&quot; d taking the guards as a wholo, sup ose $ou were able to prove that they wore suffering as a whole   and that thora is an anomaly  ran which they aro suffering, then wo oertainly are prepared to look into that and to consider ft and, if a case is made out, to redress it.    You simply gaveindividual oases.      You oannct deal with individual cases.When you are settling a standardisation on a railway you must deal   with   tho group as a wholo.    Individual casesmust ho dealt with in another way.MR .T.H.raOMAS:      I merely mentioned those as illustrating whatyourI bolievod to be tho difficulty you had In/mind, namely, the sts^ment about the 100 por cent. THE PRIME MINISTER:   Toe, but then I go at once you see to tho answer to that in the individual cases, that there may bo special circumstances in tho individual cases - for -instanco that the goods man on a particular railway may bo bettor or worso treatodthan on other railways. MR J.H.TH0MAS:   That is the real explanation.    Vlhen I gavo you a typical case of an individual, do not lot that bo hold, in your mind that It is only that individual.    Vfhat I wait   you to clearly understand is that what aprlied in Wilson&apos;s caso ap liod to other mon in his    particular  grade in Newcastle; what ap lied in Andersons case
applied to the whole of the Great &quot;western system; what applied in RobsonJs case again applied to the whole. Do not be deceived into asswning that I was dealing with an individual.   I was dealing with merely typical cases of the whole ana net individual cases. THi; PRIhh : THIbTah:   If you mean by that tho levelling up on every railway to the very highest in every district, you are raising a very big question, but if you want to have the grievances of any particular group considered we are perfectly prepared to discuss that,   I only want you to clearly understand that we do not say to you : How with regard to the&apos; guardst if you have anything further to say with regard to the grievances of the guards (I am taking them as an example) we have said the last word, . That is all I want you to understand, &apos; Have you anything further to say in discussion about individual grades of that kind ?   If you say that particular grade is not well treated or any particular grade is not well treated, or that it is treated unfairly in our standardisation, that we are willing tc consider.   I do not want to go away, nor do I want any of you to go away, with the idea that we have said the last word in respect of the treatment of any particular grade, but that we have always been willing tc consider anything that can be said in the course of discussion or negotiation with regard, to any anomalies in the treatment of any particular grade under the scheme of standardisation we have submitted to you.   How, here are the words and I shall give you a copy of this so that you can take it away with you.   In the absence of Shorthand Notes I must say what I understood Mr, Thomas to ask. Hill the Government be prepared to discuss ana consider
--^^&quot;VOT^ssfttitatlonB       that In youa* w^i^m-*i*Ui*4M!..i wuw...that there aro ajaotiaxiltea--ac &quot;&quot;between grades which. Should-......be removed in standardising a 0 also to consider orad.es as a whole which we not been advanced, by the 100 per cent ?   Ily reply is that we are certainly prepared, to discuss and. consider such matters, but of course it will be incumbent upon you to demonstrate in the case of these trades- that such anomalies would arise in the proposals put forward.   You will make your case in respect of each trade,Mr. J.II. THC;!&apos;AS:   That is to say in addition to the other proposal that you have made to us, which I will deal with in a moment, you say &quot;How, whatever you havo to say on standardisation notwithstanding any letter that has been sent to you or any interpretation of that letter, the Government are free to go on considering the matter and to see what can be done&quot;.   Bo I correctly interpret that ?TKl PRIM&apos; IddoISTdlh:   I will not say &quot;Uhatever has been said in any letter&quot;, but &quot;&apos;whatever interpretation has been put on any letter&quot;,   I say that if you feel that there are any particular orudes that are unfairly treated in the standardisation proposals in comparison with others, we are quite willing to consider it in connection with that. For instance, as I pointed out to, you, some are getting over 100 per cent, and there are some who are getting less than 100 per cent.   I am putting this merely as an illus-tration.   If you are able to say: dell, why should you give these less than ICO per cent ?   This is an anomaly and for such and such reasons these people certainly ought to get their 100 per cent.   Very too 11, there we are quite willing to discuss that with you.   If you make tho case in respect of any particular grade    -&apos;---&apos; -----
Mr. J,H, THO&apos; AS:   That is to say we are free to make a case on these proposals in the same way as we were compelled to make a case on previous proposals on this same subject sent to us, and it is for us to prove our case and to establish our case, but the door is not shut so far as you are concerned to any representations or arguments that we can adduce.   That shortly, as I understand it, is the situation.TEE Pi:I&apos; E !XiI;:T: :m   Yes,   If you ca   prove that anyparticular grade has been anomalously treated in compari-son with the rest. - which is the sort of case you made -Mr. J,II. THo: AS:   Exactly; in other words the sort of anomalies which I presented to you this morning,THE Pol 1 MIHI TJ.il!   Yes r if in comparison with the rest you say that they are unfairly treated, in the distribution of the percentages,Mr.  JJ1. THOMAS:   To that, Mr, Prime Minister, 1 could, reply at some length, but you are like me in this &quot;utterj it is not a question of debatej it is not a question of scoring points; It Is a question of seeing whether there is any accommodation likely and In this matter, as you know, unless accommodation is arrived at and we can send some telegrams even to the north of Scotland. - to use the illustration of distance - early, there will certainly be a stoppage at 12 o!clock to-night.   Having regard to those facts I think I had better reserve anything I have to say ami rather ask you to retire and. let my colleagues and mo at once consider your proposals and. rive you an answer to them. I thin1.: on the grounds of time and urgency that will be the best course.Till PRIME MIHI^maximum:   Very well.(The Prime Minister and his colleagues retired, and after a short Interval returned).
fjMH. THOMASs   &quot;Toll, Mr, Prime Minister, tho Executive Com-mitteo have debated and considered everything that took place hero this mornings     I myself have put to them what 1 believe to be the most generous incorprocation of all that you have said, and they havo come oc the conclusion that, in their judgment, nothing has been said or offered that Wjould warrant thorn departing from the&apos; decision they arrived at two days ago, which   moans that tho members rill be asked to strike at 12 to-night.    The resolution that they unanimously carried was:-That this Executive, having carefully considered the offer of the Government for a basis of negotiations to effect a settlement in tho railway dispute, regrets thatTthe Government will not apply tho principle which brought about tho settlement of locomotive drivers and firemen and tho other grades in the conciliation scheme.     It is, therefore, with regret we fool we cannot effect a settle-mcnt which would bo acceptable to our members.    Consa-quontly, wo arc forced to put into operation our deci-aionu of 23r&amp; and 81th and now confirm the instructions already Issued to tho branches,I have been compelled on many occasions to submit to you, as to your predecessor, decisions af various kinds,    I am not unmindful of the fact that I am now conveying to you a dcci-sion not only grave In itself, but probably tho most import-ant and perhaps terrible decision that has over boon conveyed. No words noed bo said as to what this moans, because I am not unmindful, and have not failed to point out what you yourself emphasized, namely, that this was not a dispute between thorailway companies and ourselves, but that it was a disputeSirbetween tho railway men and the Government,     But/serious
as it is, terrible as it may be in its consequences, I beg of you to believe that every effort has been mado to seo whether a bridge could be found,     I would also not be doing you or your colleagues justice if I did not tell you quite frankly and plainly that the - incidents in connection with tho negotia-tlons have not tended to help my position,    when I say &quot;my&quot; position, it is no secret to anybody, certainly not to my Executive, that, in tho main, on all matters, they look upon me as rathoir$ conservative leader, and it has often boon said that I have gone too far in effecting a compromise,    &quot;hat has distressed them, certainly what has not helped my task or theirs has boon that they have felt that even you yourself, in giving decisions, or making suggestions, have at least found yourself, as we have had to observe, In a difficulty, that, if it was left to someone else to give effect to those decisions, they may, at least, to put it no higher, not have put the same interpretation that you yourself may havo Indicated, &apos;   I put it no higher than that, but it is fair to you and your colleagues that I should tell you exactly what has happened,    Therefore, I have only to say in conclusion that no one regrets having to convoy this decision more than mo, because I am not unmindful of tho conse-quences.     I bog of you to believe mo when I say that If you attach any importance whatever to any fooling or suggestion that tho men will not loyally respond, let ro beg of you, in this last minute, to attach no importance whatever to it, Whatever else may bo said in criticism of me, I may, at this stage, say that my conduct has at least inspired confidence in men who would hesitate to strike   who would hesitate to strike   and I toll you now that, in my solemn judgment, at 12 o&apos;clock to-night, tho railways of this country will be paralysed.     In convoying that decision I can only toll you that nothing will bo venting on my part to ensure that,
even with all the danger Involved., property and life shall be protected^     I do not want the fight to develop into- riot--&apos; ingj-  I do not- w-nt. the men to do other than coase work;   and I hope you equally well recognise the situation that I make in saying that    Therefore..,, hr. Prime kinister.. I have only one other word to oay4, and it is thist   that you are faced irith a responsibility as tho Head of the Government.    I am faced with a responsibility as tho Road of a Union,,,    Just as I hone and believe you will not forget your obligations as a citizen, terrible as is the decision I am conveying, I hope that what-ever the result, It will not be said that I forgot that I was a citizen as well as a leader,,    That is the decision I have to convey.    You youself must interpret it for vhat it is worth.TIF&apos; PRIIF HIFISTrR:   r&apos;CII, Mr.. Thorns and gentlemen, there is no Interpretation that needs to be placed on that decision. It Is a plain clear statement that the loaders of tho railway-men reject tho terms pronoscd by the Government, including the. concessions which I annoimced this morning.    Thoy decline, not merely the terms which I proposed, but they decline fur-ther to negotiate for an amelioration of those terms in res-pectedf Individual groups, where a case could be made out that they were harshly or anomalously treated.    There is no dif-ficulty in Interpreting that0    None.    The leaders of the men have chosen to throw the whole country, at tho time when it is struggling forward to recover Its lost trade, into this frightful conflict..    That Is their responsibility entirely., I can only regret it3     It is in respect of conditions which, could not come into operation until the 1st of January.    That, seems to me to be not merely anticipating a conflict, but rushing to meet a conflict, when, considering the time be-&apos;S3wecn now and then, with further discussion there would havo been a possibility of averting the conflict,,    By, that timo we-shall know very much better what the conditions will ho in regard to cost of living and other things,,    But the mon have
decided, and, therefore; it is idle for me to advance any further arguments,   j rc Thomas said the men would no doubt be absolutely loyal to their decision.,   I have no doubt about that for a moment.   I was under no delusion,   i.^ appeal must be to the public of Great Britain.   The.decision I have taken has been, as I conceive it, in their interests    I am here as their trustee.   The burden will have to be passed on to them I have no right; especially at a time when there is a great demand   and a perfectly legitimate demand   for economy, merely in order to avert a confct in this country, however serious it might be,, to im&apos;/ooe upon tho country burdens which, in my heart, I foe I wpuld not be justified..   I watched very carefully all the observations made by * r.Thomas to see whether there was a gleam of hope that might be a possibility of avert-ing the conflict.   I know him sufficiently well to understand that-, as he has now come to this conclusion, there Is none. Under thoso circumstances I can only say I deeply regret it. He says that he has been denounced by his own friends for the conservatism of his action^   The criticism always directed against me is that I am too ready to consider the demands onion are put forward by the men; and I invariably lean to their side more than I do in the case of employers.   I have tried to do my best and to judge impartially,but in this case I could not honestly advise Parliament and advise the country to carry any further burdens.   I cannot accept the Interpretation which is put in that resolution upon our action.   T.e have not departed from any of the principles that guided us in settling the terms of the enginemen and the firemen and the cleaners. i-R THOMAS:     Oh,yes.SEVERAL :Ei.HERS:    &quot;Oh, yes, you have, . r.Prime   inister, with all respect.&quot;
-82- and S3-THE ,JPhIU^-lOTSTER^fcell, I fawr-yxwriKdnt of view,-im&amp;--T^-ii^vc stated It v^ry.....clearly &quot;and very f  rciblyy -and i am sure you v,ill alloy, mo,.&apos; at this very last hour when vie are-parting-on the eve of a very terrible conflict;, quietly, and with deep distress, to tell you what my feeling is.A iE:BERJ Ye so the PEL; E MINISTER:     i went into that very carefully, and I was convinced that there was no departure in principle as I indicated this morning.   However, I &amp;-  not think there is anything to be gained b^r further interchange of views or of arguments.   I deeply regret it..R. THO, AS:   I have conveyed the decision, but I should be ^anting if I did not say to you that, in a resolution that was submitted during, your absence * the Executive recorded their appreciation of the fair and impartial way in which you endeavoured to conduct the case from your  ide, and also the fair and frank way in which you endeavoured to meet it.   That at least must not prevent us from saying,.much as we regret it, that dis-agreement should not prevent any man accepting a tribute to a genuine effort which we believe was made by -*ou to avert what unfortunately is the decision.(The proceedings then terminated).

</content>
</cab>
