<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/89/0 images: 424-430</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tit \Tnfs Document is the Property oTHis Britannic majesty  &apos;s Goveniment.ttmtAL QMicxmQY (minmm) bill.(circulated by trc Home Secretary)This is a Bill to amend the Mental Deficiency Act. 1913, and the Cental Deficiency and Lunacy (Scotland) navy, 1913, by removing the limit placed on the amount of the Treasury contribution towards the expenses incurred by local authorities in providing for the suitable treatment of mental defectivesc     The enclosed memorandum which has been prepared for the use of the House of Commons explains the financial effeot of the Bill. The Bill is an urgent one because until more money is provided it is impossible for the local authorities to make adequate progress with the task of providing for. the defectives within their area.    I nsed not dwell on the need of providing for this unfortunate class of the population as       &apos; speedily as possible - a need which was sufficiently emphasised by the Royal Commission^ Report on which the Act was based.      The work of the local authorities has been much hampered by the war, but I hope that good progress may be vade in the next few years and I have urged the Board of Control to bring more pressure to bear on the local authorities in order to carry on the valuable work which has been begum    The ultimate annual expenditure is considerable ( 700,000) but this will be largely if not altogether counterbalanced by the reduction which may be confidently expected in the charges on public funds resulting from orimo and other social evils for which the mental defective class are largely responsible.The Treasury have agreed to the Bill.     I should be glad to be authorised to proceed with it as soon as possible after the House re-assemblesr
tfffi.Or.AMHft: OTi EXPaiJIXUiiE LIKiSLY TO BE IKCU.uU3l) VMDKii THIS MENTAL OEvXCILivOY Si WViAM (mMpOSXt)   lilLL.ENGLAND   AMD &apos; WALES.Under the iaental Deficiency Act, 1913, the duty of making provision for defectives who require care and control (except defectives of dangerous or violent propensities sent to State Institutions) rests with the Local Authorities.    Section 47 provides for contributions from the Exchequer to the expenses of Local Authorities and Section 30 enatg-s that there shall be no obligation on a Looal Authority to provide for the supervision, guardianship or maintenance in an institution of defectives, or to appoint officers to assist the Authority in the performance of the duties under the Aot, where the Exchequer contribution is less than oee half of the expenditure (as approved by the Board of Oontrol) incurred in performing such duties.By  the proviso to Section 47 the aggregate amount of the annual Exchequer fontribution payable for all cases other than &quot;criminal&quot; cases, (i.e. cases of defectives transferred from prisons, etc..t or defectives committed to Institutions on criminal oharges) is limited to  160,000.Accordingly (except as regards &quot;criminal&quot; oases) the Act,&apos; as it now stands, does not make provision for the oare and control of all the defectives&apos; who are included within the scope of the Act as being in need of *are (arid control (see Section 2):   it only requires, in effect, that provision shall be made so far as oan be done by a total expenditure of  300,000.The sum of  300,000 lias proved to be quite inadequate, and the object of this Bill, which repeals the limit on the Treasury Contribution, is to enable provision to be made for all defectives belonging to the classes brought within the s*ope of the Aot, and to empower the Treasury to refund half the expenditure so incurred, provided such expenditure ia approved by the Board of Oontrol.An estimate of the charge that will ultimately fall on the Treasury is necessarily conjectural, since there in uncertainty both as to prices and as to the precise number of defectives who are liable to be dealt with under Seotion 2 of the Act.Returns have been collected by the Board of Control from typical areaB and from the figures so obtained it appears   probable that, if full use were made of the Aot during the next five years, provision should be made for the maintenance in institutions or under guardianship of about 21700 defectives.It is estimated that the average annual oogt of maintaining defectives in Institutions (including the annual cost on income aooount of land and buildings) will be about  60 a head.    The oost of &quot;guardianship&quot; cases will be less, but these oases are very few, and the total sum required for the
81700 defectives will be about  1.300,000.In addition administrative expenses will be incurred in ascertaining the defectives to be dealt with, in taking the necessary steps for obtaining orders under the Act, and in supervising those defectives for whom institutional treatment or guardianship is not necessary,    It is estimated that these expenses nay amount to about  100,000*Accordingly the total annual expenditure may be estimated in round figures at about  1,400,000 ef which half -  700,000 - will be refunded tt the Local Authorities from the Exchequer.The whole of this own will not be required at once, but it is anticipated that the expenditure will rapidly increase during the next few 1 years as the necessary additional  accommodation for defectives is provided, and may reaoh the estimated figure in about five years time..SCOTLAND.The Mental, Deficiency and Lunacy Act (Scotland,) is framed *n similar lines to the English Act and the general considerations set out ab*ve apply to the proposal to repeal the proviso in Section 37 *f the Scottish Aot which limits the annual Treasury contribution to  20,000,It is estimated that in Scotland provision should be made for.the maintenance of about 4*000 defectives, ,and if the cost of providing accommodation and maintenance is taken at  60 a head, the expenditure will be  240,000 &apos;9T including other items cf expense! an aggregate sum of about  260,000 **f which half., viz.  130,000 will be repayable frow the Exchequer.
[9 &amp; 10 (J-eo. 5.]  Mental Deficiency and Lunacy [Amendment).  1DRAFT03? aB I L LRemove the limit imposed by section forty-seven of the a.d. 1919. Mental Deficiency Act, 1913, and by section thirty-seven of the Mental Deficiency and Lunacy (Scotland) -Act, 1913, on the contributions which may be made 1  by the Treasury under those sections, and to extend the powers of district boards of control in Scotland -    to borrow money.BE it enacted by the Kmg&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5       1. The limit imposed by section forty-seven of the Mental Removal of Deficiency Act, 1913, and section thirty-seven of the Mental Jj,miton, ireasuryDeficiency and Lunacy (Scotland) Act, 1913, on the amounts contribution, which may be paid in any financial year out of money provided 3 &amp;^ Ge0,5* by Parliament towards the expenses referred to in those sections 3 &amp; 4 Geo. 5. 10 shall not apply to the amount to be so paid in the financial year c- 38-commencing on the first day of April nineteen hundred and nineteen, or in any subsequent financial year, and accordingly in each of those sections the proviso is hereby repealed.2. So much of section sixty-one of the Lunacy (Scotland) Abolition of 15 Act, 1857, as limits the rate of interest at which district limit on rate, -. , pp   .        -, ,   of interest atboards may borrow shall cease to have effect, and the words which dis-therein occurring &quot;and such money may be so borrowed at tric^boards&quot; any rate of interest not exceeding five pounds per centum may borrow.&quot; per annum&quot; are hereby repealed. 20&amp;21 Viet.75-3 &apos; c&apos;7L
2  Mental Deficiency and Lunacy (Amendment).   [9 &amp; 10 Geo, 6.]A.D. 1919.Power of district board in Scotland to borrow for current ex-penditure.Short title.3. If in any year a district board of control shall find it necessary to make payments in connection with the current annual expenditure for the purposes of the Lunacy (Scotland) Acts, 1857 to 1913, and the Mental Deficiency and Lunacy (Scotland) Act, 1913, in anticipation of the assessment authorised 5 under the said Acts, it shall be lawful for such district board to borrow by way of temporary loan or overdraft on the security of the aforesaid assessment such amount as may be necessary to meet such expenditure, but when any sum has been so borrowed on the security of the assessment of any financial year, it shall 10 not be competent to borrow on the security of the assessment of any other year until the money borrowed as aforesaid shall have been paid off.4. (1) This Act may be cited as the Mental Deficiency and Lunacy (Amendment) Act, 1910. 15(2) The Mental Deficiency Act, 1913, and this Act, so far as it amends that Act, may be cited together as the Mental Deficiency Acts, 1913 to 1919, and the Lunacy (Scotland) Acts, 1857 to 1913, and this Act, so far as it amends those Acts may be cited together as the Lunacy (Scotland) Acts, 1857 to 20 1919,

Lmnacy (Amendment).DB/AE T or aBILLTo remove the limit imposed by section forty-seven of the Mental Deficiency Act, 1913, and by sec-tion thirty-seven of the Mental Deficiency and Lunacy (Scotland) Act, 1913, on the contributions which may be made by the Treasury under those sections, and to extend the powers of district boards of control in Scotland to borrow money.LXVII.   (3.)11th June 1919.75-3

</content>
</cab>
