<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/89/0 images: 515-515</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Military Secret.    This D       1W0,the Property ofHiB rGovernmentJVotji Viceroy, Army Department, to Secretary of State for India,Ast October 1919.1st October.Afghanistan.   Fromeverywhere published most misleading versions of Peace Treaty. The generally received versions of Afghan case is as follows : (a) Afghans were victorious in actual fighting, and penetrated far into India; (b) Government of India, in vie*w of defeat in field, desertions and mutiny of Indian troops, and unrest and even risings in internal India, sued for peace ; (c) Afghans agreed to six months&apos; armistice on condition of recognition of complete independence of all control, doubling of subsidy, large gifts of money and arms, recognition of Afghan suzerainty over frontier tribes, and large territorial concessions in India, together with freeing Indian Mahometans from alleged British oppression.   All these conditions to be carried out within six months.&quot; 2. it is obvious that these persistent misleading reports have had bad effect.&quot;3. I gather from many enquiries that should Bolshevic assistance be on sufficiently large scale, Afghans may after some months make impossible demands on us, and, on our refusal, make another attempt at Jihad, based on the grounds that we have refused to honour the alleged conditions of the armistice, as outlined in&apos;para. 1 above.&quot;4. I have persistent reports of Afghan propaganda in Eastern Persia, and in Russian territory during the last few weeks. This seems undoubtedly to be due to recent orders from Kabul,- as during past summer very little was done by Afghans in this direction. The result of this Afghan agitation is to strengthen local opinion regarding the probable purely temporary character of peace.&quot;5. I am, of course, taking all possible steps to counteract Afghan and Bol-shevic propaganda, but gist of above as reasons for the strongly held opinion in these parts that peace will not last.&quot;(Received 3rd.)On 30th September Malleson wires :  all quarters&apos; make it clear that Afghan officials have

</content>
</cab>
