<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/89/0 images: 517-519</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.&apos; ViAR CABINET,* G.T. C267.^ * ..THE 33REaL SUBSIDY.Copy of a letter from tho Food Controller to thd Secretary, V/ar Cabinet.Palace Chnmbars, Westminster, S.W.1. 3rd October, 1919.Tear Hankcy,On the 23rd September you wrote on bohalf of tho Cabinet Committee on Finance to ascertain our views as to tho advisability of a complete or gradual withdrawal of the Bread Subsidy.     I accordingly forward herewith a memorandum dealing as concisely as possible with the question in all its aspects. It seemed best that the Iforsorandum should as far as possible merely sot forth tho facts, but it may bo convenient if tho Finance Committee are in possession of my personal views on the. general question.1,      While I take the view that the principle of subsidies of this character is undor normal conditions vicious, it scorns to mo that as the Bread Subsidy was introduced as a war expedient, and that as the conditions which justified it originally largely remain, it would not bo wise to abandon it at the present timo.2.      The removal of the Subsidy now would involve - an increase in the price of the quartern loaf from 9id to l/l (or even possibly l/l-g-d.). Such an advance in the cost of the first necessity would almost certainly be a signal for another       *&quot; cycle of wage demands. 03*   - Wages negotiated on a basis of standardisation-tion in a period of fluctuating prices and uncer-tainty cannot be properly related to the real economics of industry.     Advances conceded to moot a rise in prices cannot in practice bo taken off when prices fall, without danger of industrial strife.   The Bread Subsidy involves a heavy demand iti the freas^ry, but further wage demands inspired by its removal might be even more costly to national industry.Yours sincerely,(Signed)   GEORGE H. ROBERTSLieut.-Col. Sir Maurice Hankey,G.C.B.(THIS DOCUMENT 13 THS PROPERTY OP HI8 BRITAFITIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVE1MCTT.L
THE BREAD SUBSIDY.&apos;1.     The cost of the Bread Subsidy during the current financial year is estimated at  50,000,000.     fbia figure is reached after taking into account (a)    the 1919 crop of home grown wheat at the guaranteed minimum prioe to the producer, and (b) an import for the cereal year ending August &apos;3lbt, 1920 of 5 million tons;, of this it is estimated that; shipments frorn^Australia and the Argentine will amount, to at least 1q milliononsacks, and the subsidy arises through the sale of about 40 million sacks at an uneconomic price.     The present rate of the subsidy is accordingly approximately 25/-per sack (280 lbs.) or 1,07Id. per lb.2.  he subsidized selling prices of the prices without the subsidy are as figures are approximate.flour and follows.bread and The latterFLOUR.Subsidized Selling PriceUnsubftidized Selling Price.sack (280 lbs) Wholesale &quot; &quot;        RetailStone (14 lbs) Quartern (3l lbs) Half Quartern lb. MM It44/-50/-2/8ef2*69/-75/-3/11V-6d3*BREAD,4-lb-loaf 2-lb   &quot; 1-lb   &quot;Retail ntt4I2i1AI3l3.     If the subsidy is continued, it is estimated that in the early winter (November) of this year the weekly expenditure on foodstuffs of the average working class family, on the basis of the Summer Budget, will be 49/11 as against 50/6J in November 1918. &apos; According&apos;to this Budget the average family consumes 25 lbs. of bread and 8 lbs of flour per week, so that the removal of the subsidy would bring this figure up to 52/9 per week, an increase of 2/10.   The effect of this increase on wages requires the most serious consideration.It
It may be added that a small rise in the prices of certain commodities will probably occur after Chriitmas for the remainder of the winter.   The Profiteering Act may occasion a decline in the price of certain minor commodities, but this will not substantially affect the total expenditure figures04.     It is not possible to estimate future movements of markets, but there is no reason to anticipate any appreciable advance in the world1s prioa of wheat.   The lj millions tons of Australian wheat and the larger proportion of the 1 million tons of Argentine wheat, referred to above; have already been secured at prices which, after due allowance is made for the difference in rates of freight, are considerably below the present parity price of wheat is North America; and further purchases will be made in the Argentine as finance becomes available.   Although the^iarket in the Argentine, which is a free market, will probably fluctuate, it is not anticipated that the average price to be paid will vary widely from the present cost.   The possibility of any material reduction in the rate of the subsidy, therefore, depends on the possibility of a break in North American prices, and some people think that this may happen in the early Spring.   Canadian prices will be governed largely by prices in the United Spates.   The possibility of the United States being able to market its exportable surplus at the present price, which is based upon the price guaranteed to the American farmer, will be determination-ed mainly by the economio conditions in importing countries. Against the possibility of a break in price must be set, to some extenti the possibility of a further break in the rate of exchange.5.     There is one further peint vhich must he mentioned. Imported wheat is attpresent sold to millers below cost price and at such prices, according to quality, as enable the loaf to be sold at 9jd.   If the bread subsidy is abolished, these prices must be raised.   On the other hand, under the present arrangement, farmers sell their wheat at prices far below Its intrinsic value, compared with the average cost of imported wheat.   When the selling prices of imported wheat are advanced tc cover its average cost, it will be evident to the farmer that at the prices which he is at present able to obtain, he &apos;5-       has been contributing (at the rate of about. per quarter)i t* the reduction of the Bread Subsidy.   It will then be ex-extremely difficult to resist the demand for a free market in heme-grown wheat,   If this were done, it would mean the addition of a further ^d to the quartern loaf, making It l/li, instead of the present price of 9jds6.     If it is decided to abolish the Bread Subsidy, it is con-sidered that prices should be advanced in one step rather than by a series of smaller sdvancesj in the latter case all the objections to a total withdrawal of the subsidy would be raised at each step.   If any material reduction is to be made in the amount Of the subsidy by a general advance in the selling price of flour, it is ccnsidered that this should be done either at once or not before the end of the financial year, when the -worst of the winter ^ill be over.MINISTRY OP POOD,Ootober, 3rd, 1919.

</content>
</cab>
