<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/105/0 images: 91-92</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1961C.(61)66 Copy No.   512nd June, 1961.CABINETEXCHEQUER ASSISTANCE FOR THE BUILDING AND EXPANSIONOF HOTELSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer on 4th May the Cabinet invited me:&quot; to give further consideration to the proposal for some form of Exchequerassistance for the building and expansion of hotels&quot;. (C.C. (61) 26thConclusions, Minute 7.)The two kinds of assistance suggested by the Committee on Tourism were exchequer loans for selected hotel projects, and a tax concession such as the extension to hotelsof the existing industrial building allowance.2. Suggestions of this kind have been given exhaustive examination over theyears. They were considered in detail by the official Working Parties of 1954 and1958 which studied hotels in relation to the tourist trade, and former Chancellors ofthe Exchequer gave particularly close attention to them when the reports of theseWorking Parties were considered. It was decided that discriminatory financialassistance or fiscal concessions in favour of the hotel trade would be expensive and could not be defended.Direct Exchequer Assistance3. I have again examined carefully all the arguments put forward in favourof direct Exchequer assistance to hotels. There is room for argument as to theextent to which it would effect a genuine improvement in the balance of payments.4. But the overriding consideration is a broader one. I cannot advise mycolleagues to embark on direct Government assistance to yet another private industry after the difficulties experienced over support for Colvilles and Cunardand private industry generally. And it would be particularly inappropriate to be doing so just at the time when the nationalised industries are being required tobecome less dependent on Exchequer finance.Tax Concessions5. Industrial buildings attract on their capital cost a 10 per cent, investmentallowance, a 5 per cent, initial allowance and 2 per cent, annual allowances. Ihave re-examined the proposal that either these allowances or simply the investmentallowance of 10 per cent, should be extended to capital expenditure on new hotelsor on extensions and improvements to existing hotels. This proposal would represent tax discrimination at its worst as it would pick out a selected class ofcommercial buildings used by one section of a particular industry for relief, whencommercial buildings generally are given no tax allowances on grounds of principle and cost. The competitors of hotels hoarding-houses and holiday camps,restaurants and public houses would seek similar relief on the grounds that they59098
would otherwise be subject to unfair competition; and if those claims wereconceded there could be little justification for not extending the relief to allcommercial -buildings, at an annual cost to the Exchequer of  28 millions ifcommercial buildings were given the same allowances as industrial buildings.6. Moreover, an investment allowance would foe a wasteful method of seeking to stimulate the provision of new and improved hotels to cater for tourists from overseas. When this possibility was considered -by the Committee on Tourism itwas agreed that, for practical reasons, the allowance would have to be given toall establishments within the qualifying definition, whether or not they cateredsubstantially for overseas visitors.7. Hotels do however receive substantial help through other tax allowances.Plant and machinery qualify for the investment allowance at 20 per cent, and initialand annual allowances totalling 100 per cent, on a wear-and-tear basis. (Thepractical result is that 120 per cent, of the cost of new plant and machinery can be written off for tax purposes.) It has for a considerable period been the practice to treat the following as plant and machinery in the case of hotels: lifts; baths, &amp;c.;central-heating apparatus; fixtures and fittings; furniture of a permanent anddurable nature; carpets and other floor coverings and curtains; and also alterationsto existing buildings so far as they are incidental to the installation of machinery orplant (e.g., the building work incidental to the installation of additional baths).8. Moreover hotels have quite recently qualified for substantial additionalhelp. Expenditure on renewals of such things as plate, glass, crockery, linen,bedding, and kitchen utensils is allowed as a deduction in computing the taxableprofits, but until recently no investment allowance used to be given. As a result ofa case that went to the House of Lords the meaning to be put on the word &quot; plant &quot;was intended to mean &quot; whatever apparatus or instruments are used by a businessman in carrying on bis business&quot;. It was therefore agreed in April withrepresentatives of the hotel and restaurant trades that all equipment qualified forthe 20 per cent, investment allowance whether the expenditure was on the firstoutlay or on renewals and whether the equipment was otherwise dealt with for tax purposes on a wear-and-tear or on a renewals basis. The only conditions are thatthe equipment must be new and not second-hand and that it has an average working life in the taxpayers own trade of not less than two years.9. The result of the case is that now practically all assets and equipment used by a hotel-keeper in his trade qualify for the tax bonus of the 20 per cent, investmentallowance except the site and structure of the building itself.10. I, therefore, consider that the tax treatment of hotels is generous. Evenif it were desirable to extend the industrial buildings allowance to hotels (qualifiedby reference to size and regardless of their earnings from overseas visitors), it wouldbe quite impossible to hold the line there. In these circumstances I cannot recommend any further tax change.S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,1st June, 1961.

</content>
</cab>
