<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/105/0 images: 108-114</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C (61)73 Copy No.    381st June, 1961CABINETCIVIL SERVICE: RECKONING OF UNESTABLISHED SERVICE FORPENSIONMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer should like to consult my colleagues about the latest developments in a claim by the Staff Side of the Civil Service National Whitley Council for animprovement in Civil Service pension arrangements. The claim has a long history:it was revived by the Staff Side in 1956 and since then it has been strongly pressed by them on a number of occasions. It has been rejected by each of my threepredecessors. On the last occasion, in 1959, the then Chancellor of the Exchequerwrote -to the Staff Side in categorical terms. His letter is reproduced at Annex A.The Claim2. Unestablished civil service is temporary, unpensionafole service. As thelaw stands, an unestablished civil servant who&apos; [becomes established that is whoobtains a permanent pensionable appointment may count towards hissuperannuation benefits half of any unestablished service rendered between 1st January, 1919 and 14th July, 1949 (when the Superannuation Act, 1949 waspassed) and (under that Act) the whole of &apos;any unestablished service renderedthereafter. The Staff Side claim is that all unestablished service, whenever rendered,should count in full if it has been followed by establishment, and that it should doso not only for future retirements but for past retirements.The Motion3. In November last, a Motion appeared on the Order Paper calling on theGovernment &quot; to authorise discussions to take place On the Civil Service national whitley Council with a view to arriving at a reasonable settlement of this long-standing problem &quot;. The Motion has all-party sponsors, led by Sir Lionel Heald,Mr. Douglas Houghton and Mr. Jo Grimond. It has now attracted 387signatories, of whom 157 are Conservative, 6 are Liberal and 224 are Labour. Inorder to hold the position I met an all-party deputation in March, and told themthat, while I would consider their representations, I could not give them any decision until May or June. There is now clear evidence that I shall have toinform the sponsors of the Motion very shortly whether or not I am prepared toauthorise Whitley Council discussions. If I authorise such discussions, it willbe assumed that I am conceding the case in principle, and treating it rather asequal pay was treated in the later stages. Presumably there will be noParliamentary Debate. If I decide not to authorise the discussions, a parliamentary Debate seems inevitable.4. In the paragraphs which follow I have summarised the main arguments for and against acceptance of the claim. It is a complex and technical problem;but I feel bound to trouble my colleagues with it because of its political implications.Arguments for Accepting the Claim5. The Staff Side and their supporters argue that the principle of fullreckoning was established by the Superannuation Act, 1949; that there is no difference in principle between service before 1949 and service since then; thatto make a distinction is unfair; and that to make any distinction between existing59064bPrinted for the Cabinet. June 1961
and future pensioners is wrong, as was recognised when the Superannuation act of 1946 made the reckoning of unestablished service as to one-half retrospectiveto 1919. Moreover, the argument runs, the staff affected are mainly on smallpensions, and many of them entered the Service after the 1914-18 War when theyhad to serve Jong periods in an unestablished capacity before they were ableto secure establishment: in short, common justice supports the claim.6&amp; 6. The Conservative Party backed the principle of the claim when theywere in opposition in 1949; this support was reaffirmed in the conservative party&apos;s 1950 Campaign Guide.7. When the claim was referred by the Government to the RoyalCommission on the Civil Service, 1953-55, the Commission formed the view thatthe events of 1946 and 1949 respectively had established the principle thatretrospection and full reckoning were acceptable. The Commission went on tosay &quot;... there is no question of merit or principle outstanding. It is in factnow common ground that unestablished service should reckon in full. ... It is our view that the sole consideration is that of cost&quot;.8. The Staff Side are said to be prepared to be accommodating in the detailsof a settlement. In particular, they are ready to endorse an arrangement underwhich full reckoning is introduced gradually over a period of four or five years;they are also prepared to agree that there should be no revision of the lump sums of those who have already retired or died at the time of introduction. It is also said that they would not press for the inclusion of unestablished service renderedbefore 1st January, 1919.9. The effect of these modifications would be to make a short-term reductionin the cost. For example, the first year cost might be brought down from amaximum of  26 millions to a figure of  1^ millions.10. The large amount of Parliamentary support which the claim has attracted is potentially embarrassing.Arguments against accepting the Claim11. Talk of justice or injustice is misconceived. At the time the service inquestion was rendered there was never any expectation that it would be allowed to count at more than half its length or in some cases even at all on subsequentestablishment. The justice of the situation is that these civil servants entered ontheir service on certain conditions which have been fully honoured and in somecases improyed. Nor is it a question of &quot; the principle of full reckoning &quot; or &quot; theprinciple of restrospection &quot;. Concessions have been made in the past, but theywere specific and limited. They gave uncovenanted benefits, and outside theirlimits did nothing to invalidate the conditions of service previously accepted byunestablished officers. The question is therefore whether it is right to go back andalter, at the public expense, the conditions of service which then ruled. Nor is itthe case that the main beneficiaries of the claim will be retired civil servants livingon small pensions. Of the half million staff affected by the claim, only some 140,000are pensioners; the rest (370,000) are civil servants who have not yet retired.12. Retrospection is rarely expedient in changes affecting superannuation orother conditions of service; partly because it invariably adds so much to the costof what is to be done as to put desirable reforms in jeopardy for the future; andpartly because it usually produces a crop of difficulties and anomalies. The mainprecedent for retrospection which the staff quote-namely the Superannuation Act,3946 is outfaced by the numerous other precedents against retrospection: forexample, the 1949 Act provided for service to count in excess of 40 years, but only for officers still serving on 3rd December, 1948: the 1957 Act introduced improvedgratuities for temporary staff, but only for staff leaving after 15th May, 1957. Similarprecedents exist in respect of other major changes in conditions of service. Forexample, when the marriage bar was removed in 1946 it applied only to thosewomen still in the Service: and the introduction of equal pay was not made retrospective.13. In 1956, the then Chancellor of the Exchequer answered the point aboutthe change in the Conservative attitude towards full reckoning when he wrote inthe following terms to the Staff Side-&quot; I do not accept, and I should be surprised if any party would accept, thatin this connexion [the significance of views expressed in opposition] viewsCONFIDENTIAL
expressed on Civil Service matters are in a class apart. It is the Opposition^duty to criticise and oppose. It must of course oppose in a responsible manner.This applies on all subjects, and the Staff Side&apos;s suggestion that there is some special obligation attached to discussion of Civil Service matters that does notattach to discussion of other matters seems to me not only a quite unacceptablethesis, but one whose acceptance would not be in the best interests of theService.&quot;If this was true in 1956 it is even truer five years later. Less than a quarter of thepresent Conservative majority sat in the 1945 Parliament, and there is no constitutional rule or convention which ties the present Government for ever towhat was said by their predecessors when they were in opposition in 1949.14. In expressing the view that the only relevant consideration was that of cost the Royal Commission on the Civil Service ignored the fact that Treasurywitnesses had argued the case against extension of full reckoning on grounds ofprinciple as well as cost. In any event the Royal Commission stopped short of a recommendation in sharp distinction to those parts of their Report dealing withother matters before them. The question whether the cost can be afforded is clearlyone for the Government to decide, having regard to the many other competing claims on public funds. It is not irrelevant to note that the annual Civil Servicesalary bill (non-industrials only) nearly doubled between 1950-51 and 1960-61 rising from  284 millions to  555 millions; and the total superannuation bill nearlytrebled in the same period rising from  25 millions to  69 millions.15. On any basis the cost of the claim is large. Even assuming that the staff side concessions referred to in paragraph 8 above were offered to, and accepted by,the Government in the course of the Whitley negotiations, the overall saving wouldnot be significant. Detailed figures are shown in the table and notes at Annex B.It will be seen that  300 millions is the estimated cost of full implementation overthe years: this is bound to be an underestimate since it makes no allowance forany future pay increases. Gradual introduction saves only about 3 per cent, ofthis sum and the exclusion of past lump sums a further 6^ per cent.; in other wordsless than 10 per cent, of the total cost, despite the considerable reduction in expenditure in the first year. No less than  24^ millions of the overall saving of 29 millions accrues in the first year: in part this is merely a postponement ofexpenditure until the mid-1960s.16. It is in any case a matter of opinion whether it would be either justifiableor practicable to accept the Staff Side offer to exclude from any settlement the revision of past lump sums. My predecessor felt bound to reject this offer, for thereasons set out in his letter at Annex A. To accept it would inevitably attractcriticism in Parliament when the necessary Bill was under debate, on the grounds that it would be inequitable and would discriminate against the retired publicservant precisely the point where full reckoning^ strongest sentimental appeal lies.17. Acceptance of the claim, particularly if it were modified in the waysuggested by the Staff Side&apos;s supporters, would throw up a considerable numberof anomalies. For example, there is the sensitive topic of war service. Iftemporary service in the Civil Service were to count in full from 1919 onwards,then the war service from 1939 to 1945 of those who afterwards became civilservants (which now counts as to one half) would also count in full. But 1914-18war service would continue not to count at all. This would accentuate the differencebetween 1914-18 war service (not counting at all) and 1939-45 war service (countingat twice the rate it counts now). Again, the effect on those who served during the1939-45 War and entered the Civil Service afterwards would be quite unnecessarilygenerous. It would be an extraordinary uncovenanted benefit if they now receivedfull pension benefit in respect of years before many of them had even thought of coming into the Service, let alone entered upon established service. adjustments in widows&apos; pensions, and in the gratuities awarded to staff who had originallyretired with insufficient established service to qualify them for a pension, would be two of the other matters which would produce difficulties and, probably,controversy. The administrative effort entailed in reopening and recalculatingpast cases would of course be formidable.18. There will inevitably be direct repercussions on other public employmentsif this claim is accepted for the Civil Service; the extent of these is difficult to predict, but even if limited they will cost money.  Apart from the direct effects,59064CONFIDENTIAL
however, acceptance of the claim could have a number of damaging indirectrepercussions. It will not be easy in future ever to withhold full retrospection for improvements in public service pensions; or to withstand skilfully organisedParliamentary pressure for alterations in Civil Service and public service pensionarrangements. There are already signs of pressure blowing up in Parliament,stimulated by the Public Service Pensioners&apos; Council, for the early introductionof another Pensions (Increase) measure. There is evidence that this might welldevelop into a campaign to bring all public service pensions, whenever awarded,up to the level of those awarded to staff now retiring, i.e., the doctrine of &quot; parity &quot;.It has a strong emotional appeal because it covers, e.g., servicemen and theirwidows: and concession of retrospection for full reckoning will lend additionalforce to any campaign for parity, which is essentially a retrospective concept.The Parliamentary supporters of full reckoning are also zealous adherents of parity.Its first year cost is estimated at  70 millions. Another effect of conceding theclaim would be that it might seriously prejudice any attempt to contain and control the future growth of public expenditure. It would be a demonstration of the factthat, because of a campaign of pressure, the Government had reversed their previous decisions and committed themselves to unproductive expenditureamounting to some  300 millions over the years.19. I should like to know whether my colleagues would wish me to adhere to the position taken up by my predecessors.S. L.Treasury Chambers, S.W. 1,29 th May, 1961.
Annex ACOPY OF A LETTER FROM THE CHANCELLOR OF THE exchequer to THE STAFF SIDETreasury Chambers, Great George Street, London, S.W.1,25th June, 1959.When I had the pleasure of meeting you and your colleagues of the national staff Side on 24th April I undertook to consider fully your representations aboutthe way in which unestablished service reckons under the Superannuation Acts.May I first acknowledge that the view that all unestablished service shouldreckon in full is one which is strongly and sincerely held by the National Staff side and those whom you represent. As I see the position, it has been fostered by the concession which was made in 1949 (to allow all service from 14th July of thatyear to reckon in full); and by the fact that, although the Royal Commission on theCivil Service 1953-55 made no recommendation, they gave as their view that &quot; it isin fact now common ground that it is right that unestablished service should reckonin full&quot;. I recognise, too, the natural desire of the many civil servants affectedby this claim to enjoy larger pensions than they now expect to receive.There is room for more than one opinion on whether, as a result of the first of these factors, the principle that unestablished service whenever rendered shouldreckon in full has been accepted or should be accepted. For example, my predecessor, Sir Stafford Cripps, emphasised during the debate on the superannuation Bill 1949 that he did not regard the question as one of justice orinjustice, as is sometimes suggested, but of whether it is right and expedient to go back and, at the expense of the community, to alter the conditions of serviceaccepted by unestablished officers. I see great force in this view. Whether it wasgiven sufficient weight by the Royal Commission is another debatable point. Butit is one which has to some extent been relegated to the background by the emphasiswhich they put on the aspect of cost.Perhaps I may remind you what the cost would be of allowing unestablishedservice before 14th July, 1949, to reckon in full. If a change were made to take effect during the current financial year the additional cost of Civil Servicesuperannuation (which is already rising fast) would be  6 millions. This annualfigure would rise to  7^ millions by the seventies. Although it might have fallen to about  4 millions a year by the turn of the century the effects of the concession would not disappear until some way through the next century.These figures are substantial enough; but I should point out that they relateonly to the pensions of those who have already retired and to the pensions andlump sums of those who will retire in the future. They do not allow for the revision of lump sums awarded to those who have already retired. I understandthat the National Staff Side would be prepared to forgo the revision of such lumpsums, but I cannot believe that it would be possible to proceed on this basis. If itwere expedient to concede full reckoning for the years before 1949 and still moreif it became generally accepted that it was right in principle to concede it therewould be no logical ground for not revising lump sums paid to those who havealready retired, or even in respect of those who have retired and since died.Assuming that it could be regarded as right to exclude the last category, the costof revising lump sums would still add about  14^ millions to the first year cost ofa change in the law. If it were not excluded the corresponding figure would be 17^ millions.I am therefore bound to consider this as a proposal which might call for expenditure of not less than  20^ millions in the first year and would certainly involve a smaller but continuing annual sum for more than half a century. In so faras I stand for the Government as an employer I may be tempted, as I am suremy predecessors have been tempted, to make this retrospective improvement in conditions of service. But I need not remind you that as Chancellor of theExchequer I have another obligation: to consider whether I can justify to taxpayersgenerally what would be regarded in many quarters an uncovenanted benefit toR. A. Hayward, Esq.
one section of the community. I must keep in mind also that more than half the male working population (and a much larger proportion of women) still gain no benefit from occupational pension arrangements. Such people would be among those who would have to find the money for this retrospective improvement inCivil Service pensions. If they were to say, as well they might, that they were just as entitled to an extra share of the national wealth, I do not think that I would find it easy to answer them.I am afraid that for these reasons I am unable to agree that proposals shouldbe put to Parliament for the legislation which would be required to meet theNational Staff Side&apos;s claim. And, having regard to the increasingly heavy burden which will fall on the economy in years to come, as a result of the rising proportionwhich old people will bear to the rest of the community, I think it unlikely thatI or my successors will be able to- take a different view.May I say in conclusion that I appreciate the offer which you made to take part in a joint committee of the National Whitley Council to examine thepossibilities of introducing full reckoning by stages. But the gradual introductionof full reckoning would make very little difference to the total cost over the years.For this reason I do not consider that such an enquiry would help.(Signed)     D. HEATHCOAT AMORY.
-   Annex BCOST OF CONCEDING FULL RECKONINGAssuming that the claim were conceded only on future retirements and on future instalments of pension in respect of past retirements, it is estimated thatthe annual cost in 1961-62 would be about  7 millions rising to about  8 millions in the ensuing 10 years and then slowly declining until it finally disappeared sometime in the first quarter of the next century. If the concession were extended tolump sum benefits granted to civil servants now in retirement or deceased 19 millions would be added to the first year cost, raising it to  26 millions in all.The total cumulative burden which all this would involve over the years isestimated at about  300 millions.2. The effects, in the first decade, of gradual introduction and of excluding the revision of past lump sums are shown in the table below.1	2	3	4Year	Cost of immediate total full reckoning	Cost of gradual total full reckoning (7 stages over 6 years)	Cost of gradual modified full reckoning (7 stages over 6 years)1961-62        ......	  millions 26	  millions	  millions n1962-63        ......	7	74	31963-64        ......	7	7*	41964-65        ......	n	9	71965-66        ......	n	9	81966-67		101	9i1967-68        ......	8	H	811968-69.......	8	8	81969-70        ......	8	8	81970-71        ......	8	8	notes(a) The figures in columns 2 and 3 include the revision of lump sums already awarded.(b) The figures in column 4 exclude the revision of lump sums paid on retirement or on deathbefore 1st April, 1961.(c) The figures in both columns 3 and 4 assume that full reckoning will apply immediately inrespect of death and ill-health retirement.(d) The total cost over the years of the three schemes (not taking account of the uplifting effects of future pay increases or pensions increase measures) is estimated roughly as follows:Column 2.........     300 millions.Column 3   .........     300 millions minus  10 millions (for gradualintroduction^  290 millions.Column 4.........     300 millions minus  10 millions (as above) and afurther  19 millions (for exclusion of past lumpsums^  271 millions.May 1961.

</content>
</cab>
