<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/105/0 images: 133-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. June 1961C. (61) 80 Copy No.   5 315th June, 1961CABINETTOURISM: THE GARNET SYSTEM FOR MOTOR CARSMemorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer as requested by my colleagues at the Cabinet meeting on 4th May(C.C. (61) 26th Conclusions, Minute 7), I have given further consideration, inconsultation with the Minister of Transport so far as mention is made of the vehicleregistration and licensing system only (see paragraph 8 below), to the possibility of abolishing the carnet system for tourists&apos; motor cars. In the result, I am satisfiedthat there is no sufficient ground for changing the views I expressed on 4th May.The main considerations which I have taken into account in reaching this conclusionare summarised in the following paragraphs of this memorandum.2. In general terms, the problem, as I see it, is one of weighing the possible advantages to be derived from the suggested abolition against the consequentialrisks to the revenue.3. It has been argued that the main advantage to be gained from the abolitionof the carnet system is the removal of a deterrent to increased tourist traffic to thiscountry, from Western Europe in particular, where the system has now been generally abandoned. But I find, it difficult to accept that the need for the touristto obtain, as a rule with the help of a motoring club abroad, a simple formof triptyque, costing no more than ,6s. for a single visit, can be regarded as a deterrentof any substance to visiting this country, as compared with other factors, such as thedifficulty for a visitor of obtaining transport bookings at reasonably short notice,the high cost of transporting a car to and fro across the Channel (which in itself would, instead, cover the cost of some 2,000 miles of continental motoring), and ouruncertain climate. The main benefit said to have been derived from the abolitionof this system by our Western European neighbours has been by way of increases in so-called &quot; impulse travel &quot;, particularly at weekends, across their land frontiers.But our insular situation rules out any significant increase in this form of trafficfor us.4. It has also been argued that our failure to fall in line with the rest of western Europe in this matter is liable to create the impression that we are unwilling to co-operate with our neighbours in getting rid of outmoded controls.But I consider that this suggestion rests on a misunderstanding of the motiveswhich have prompted the Western European countries to dispense with carnetsand triptyques for motor cars. They have not done this by mutual agreement,in order to substitute a less cumbersome but equally efficient system for one whichhas ceased to serve the purposes for which it was designed and introduced withthe authority of a United Nations convention, but have, one by one, abandoned the carnet system, unilaterally, simply because the vast volume of traffic passingacross their land frontiers had made it unmanageable for them. In western germany and Austria, for instance, I understand that something over 12 millionarid 6 million cars respectively pass annually&apos;to and fro across their frontiers, ascompared with some 60,000 visiting this country from the Continent. The fact thatthe continental countries have been motivated by necessity, rather than by a mutualdesire to simplify their controls, is to some extent evidenced by the fact that, contraryto the suggestion made at the Cabinet meeting on 4th May, they have not in general59175
abandoned the carnet system for aircraft, for which it continues to be manageable.Our special position so far as car traffic is concerned is, in fact, well understood, ifnot envied, at least so far as other Customs administrations are concerned.5. As to the risks to the revenue involved, it has been suggested that these have been exaggerated and that they are in fact almost negligible; but I cannot accept this contention. The report of the Committee on Tourism referred to information submitted by the Joint Committee of the British motoring organisations,to the effect that the abolition of the carnet system had led to no actual decline inthe total revenue derived from imported cars in certain of the continental countrieswhich have abolished the carnet system for cars. This may well be true, so faras it goes. But, apart from the fact that the information covers only four countries,none of which levy import dues on cars on a scale comparable with our import duty and Purchase Tax (which together amount to 95 per cent, of the value of the car),this proves very little in itself, since, for a number of reasons, such as the constantlyincreasing volume of traffic on the roads, the fact that there is no actual decline inthe total revenue derived from commercially and privately imported cars togetherby no means proves that there has been no substantial evasion in respect of thoseimported by tourists.6. So far as most of the continental countries are concerned, the risks entailedin abolishing the carnet system were relatively insignificant, as there is plainly no incentive to smuggle cars from countries in which they bear high duties (and aretherefore relatively expensive to buy) into countries in which they are less highlytaxed, and therefore cheaper. It is, for all practical purposes, only the countries with the highest tariff barriers which have much to fear from this form of evasion.Of the Western European countries which have abandoned the carnet system onlyDenmark and Spain levy Customs charges comparable with ours on imported cars.Spain has abandoned the carnet system in the last few weeks only, and it is thereforetoo early to expect their Customs authorities to be able to gauge the results. Sofar as Denmark is concerned, however, our Customs have ascertained, on a confidential basis, that the Danish Customs have reason to believe that abuse ona substantial scale has resulted from the abolition. The Danes frankly avow thatthis step was in effect unavoidable for them, because the volume of traffic had made the carnet system unmanageable in Denmark, but that they take comfort inthe fact that they have gained an increase in tourist traffic, particularly in the formof week-end &quot; impulse travel &quot;; but this benefit would not be open to us.7. Duty and tax amounting to some  135,000 are at present collected annuallyunder the carnet system, in respect of motor cars which, having been imported ona temporary footing, are not duly re-exported, for one reason or another. Mostof this sum is paid voluntarily by the owners, without its being necessary to invokethe guarantee given by the sponsoring motoring organisation; but it is impossibleto estimate how much of this potential loss of revenue might still be collected ifit were not generally known that the guarantee would be invoked in the last resort.Nor is this figure of  135,000 in any sense a measure of the annual loss of revenuewhich might be sustained, as a result of deliberate evasion, which the existing system prevents, if the cainet system were abolished. This risk cannot, in fact,be quantified, because, apart from other factors, it is impossible to forecast how many people would be tempted to take advantage of the easy and lucrative, thoughdishonest, gains which would then be open to them. It has been suggested that theprofits from this form of evasion, after allowing for incidental expenses, would notbe attractive; but when it is borne in mind that a Mercedes-Benz 190 Saloon canbe bought in Germany for about  850 (or in many cases less, as substantial discountscan be obtained), against its United Kingdom list price of  1,838 and that aVolkswagen can be bought in Germany for about  391, against its UnitedKingdom list price of  739, it is apparent that the potential illicit gain could bevery attractive. Perhaps the best example is the fact that popular cars, such as theFord Anglia and the Morris Oxford, can be bought in Dublin for some  100 to 150 less than their price in Belfast. This means that the risks to the revenue areexceptionally high in Northern Ireland, because of the ease with which people living there could obtain and import cars from the Republic, with only trivialincidental expenses. It is indeed probable that, in the event of the abolition of thecarnet system there, honest car dealers in Northern Ireland would before long find it very difficult indeed to compete with dealers in the Republic. Although it isimpossible to estimate the extent of the evasion which might develop, the total
revenue at risk in Northern Ireland alone is estimated at $2\ millions annually,to say nothing of the equally unpredictable proportion of the remaining  12 millionsor so of duty and tax chargeable on the 60,000 or so cars at present imported bytourists from the Continent, which might be lost.8. Every possible effort has been made to devise an effective alternativesystem for limiting these revenue risks, e.g., by a link-up with the registration andlicensing system. But, although it might be possible by these means for the Customsto discover the whereabouts of cars imported by tourists but irregularly disposedof or retained in this country, assuming that the offender made no effort to coverhis tracks, this would at the best as a rule merely enable the Customs to confiscatethe car, probably from an innocent purchaser, the real offender meanwhile havingleft the country undetected. Moreover, the registration and licensing systemprovides no defence against the deliberate evasion which would almost certainlydevelop, as it is admittedly all too easy for those who wish to do so to make detectiondifficult by using false names or addresses for registration purposes, or by usingsuitable bogus registration books, which would be bought on the black market,as is already done for stolen cars.9. The real danger is not that normally honest casual tourists would be tempted to dispose of their cars while here, but that a highly organised &quot; racket&quot;in uncustomed cars would be developed by the kind of &quot; racketeers&quot; who wouldbe all too well aware of the need to cover their traces and of the ease with whichthis could be done. After carefully considering the question in all its aspects,the Cabinet Committee came to the conclusion that the risks entailed could onlybe measured by means of an experimental abolition. As it would be virtually impossible to re-introduce the carnet system at the end of the proposed experimental period of two years, I can only regard this recommendation as a proposal that weshould gamble on the chance that, contrary to the indications of the facts summarised above, there would be little or no serious evasion. I cannot agree that a gambleof this kind in a fiscal matter of this importance would be justified. I should,therefore, much prefer only to adopt a simpler form of document and review thematter again after a period, in the light of experience gained with it.S. L.Treasury Chambers, SWA,15th June, 1961.

</content>
</cab>
