<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/105/0 images: 251-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1961C. (61) 96 Copy No. g g11th July, 1961CABINETVISIT TO COMMONWEALTH CAPITALS IN AFRICA, JUNE-JULY, 1961Memorandum by the Minister of LabourGeneralI found all the Governments with whom I had discussions warmly appreciativeof the decision that members of the British Cabinet should visit Commonwealthcapitals in this way. The Commonwealth Governments were pleased that theBritish Government were taking considerable trouble to make the process of consultation a reality and that this was being done at so early a stage. I did,however, find on my arrival at each capital a pretty strong belief that we had infact decided to seek negotiations with the Six. One of my first tasks was to convinceeach Government in turn that this was not so. Coupled with this belief went somesurprise that we were not yet in a position to put more precise proposals forward for discussion.2. All the discussions I had with Commonwealth Ministers, and those myadvisers had with Commonwealth officials, were friendly and frank. This did not,however, mean that the issues were not regarded as potentially capable of creatingserious difficulties between our countries. In Ghana particularly as PresidentNkrumah&apos;s public statements before and since have shown these issues were verydelicate.Publicity3. During my tour I adhered to the procedure, agreed to before I set out,for keeping communiques, Press interviews and so on as formal as possible and asempty of details about the talks I had had with Commonwealth Ministers.Commonwealth Governments accepted the argument that the discussions shouldbe regarded as confidential between our two Governments. This was satisfactory as far as it went, but it did leave a vacuum which some reporters were inclined to fill with their own inventions, such as the utterly groundless Reuters canard fromLagos that I had had a &quot; rude shock &quot; from my reception by Nigerian Ministers.Results4. The aims of my visits were summarised in paragraph 16 of the agreedDirective (C. (61) 87). Broadly, these aims were attained in all four capitals. I attach copies of documents setting out the general course of the discussions (aletter I wrote to President Nkrumah, which he told me was entirely acceptable tohim, and notes of my discussions with the other three Governments which were agreed with them before I left their capitals). All four Governments:(a) showed understanding of the reasons that might lead us to decide to startnegotiations with the European Economic Community (E.E.C.);(b) recognised that the British Government had the right to take their owndecisions;SECRET59285 B
(c) agreed that it would be pointless to hold a Prime Ministers&apos; Meeting until there was something concrete to discuss; and(d) agreed that there must be close consultation between the United Kingdomand the rest of the Commonwealth at all stages.I was also able to ascertain the interests, political and economic, which these four countries would wish us to have in mind. They varied between countries, and Ioutline them below.Ghana5. Far and away the most important thing in the Ghanaians&apos; eyes is their political objection to the whole Common Market set-up and especially to the associated Overseas Territory (A.O.T.) relationship as it now exists. AdmittedlyPresident Nkrumah recognised that commercial discrimination against Ghana was undesirable. But he made it clear that political considerations meant more tohim than the avoidance of this discrimination. He accepted that the present shape of A.O.T. status was evolved before the French-speaking African countries wereindependent and that it was now being reviewed. He acknowledged that therewere pressures from the A.O.T. countries, from among the Six themselves, andfrom outside (especially the United States), for changes both in the A.O.T.arrangements under the Treaty of Rome and in the quite separate French financialand currency tie-up with the ex-French territories. But he clearly doubted whether anything that he would regard as tolerable would emerge from the process ofreview. Accordingly he is not in fact keeping an open mind while that processgoes on, although he told me he would do so.6. We have to remember that his whole approach is bedevilled by hisaspirations to be the African leader. However reasonable the revised A.O.T.status might turn out to be he would not hesitate to use our joining the E.E.C. asa pretext for leaving the Commonwealth if at the time this furthered his pan-Africanambitions. Meanwhile, he seems to regard attacks upon the Common Market, andhis African rivals&apos; relationships to it, partly as a means of forwarding theseambitions.7. He has greatly increased the authoritarian element in Ghanaian political life, as exampled by his recent action in taking over the Treasury in addition to the armed Services and police. I do not think that his Ministers really count for anything now. During our talks he was throughout full of his usual charm, butas ever he was not so reliable the moment one&apos;s back was turned.Nigeria8. Unfortunately neither the Finance Minister nor the Minister of commerce and Industry was in Nigeria at the time of my visit, so that the Ministers I met inLagos were rather a scratch lot. This gave especial value to my private talks withthe Prime Minister at his home in Bauchi, which confirmed some of the impressionsI had received in Lagos and put others in a better perspective.9. The Nigerians attach more weight to the economic factors than theGhanaians do, but the political factors are nevertheless very important to them also. These political factors are not quite the same as those which motivatePresident Nkrumah. But like him the Nigerians are anxious that there shouldbe nothing in the relationship of African countries to Europe which involves any kind or appearance of subordination or colonialism, or which might impede political or economic co-operation between the African countries. The Nigerians, are,however, ready and indeed anxious, to join the French-speaking African countriesin a purified form of A.O.T. States. Thus at one and the same time they would avoid economic discrimination against Nigerian exports and advance their aim ofpolitical as well as economic co-operation between the Monrovia Powers. WhereGhana, because of the doubts which I have mentioned, might be prepared to smashthe relationship between the Associated Overseas Territories and Europe, I thinkNigeria wants to see it reformed and extended.10. This strongly &quot; African&quot; attitude is perhaps still rather a recentdevelopment in Nigeria. I am sure that it would be a serious mistake tounderestimate it, and I think it is likely to become an increasingly important factor
in Nigerian thinking. I would add that the Nigerians told us that they would beconsulting Ghana and Sierra Leone, and their Monrovia associates, about my discussions with them.Sierra Leone11. The Sierra Leone Government take much the same line as the nigerian government. Their views are not so deeply-considered, nor perhaps sostrongly-held, as those of the Nigerians, but they had evidently given the wholequestion more thought than I had expected. They clearly look to Nigeria for a lead. I was rather amused to be assured privately by the Prime Minister of sierra leone, Sir Milton Margai, that the account of my talks in Nigeria which I had given to him and his Ministers tallied closely with the account the Nigerians had provided themselves.12. The Sierra Leone Government were clearly very favourably impressed by the evidence of the reality of Commonwealth consultation which my visit,coming so soon after independence, afforded them. In return they welcomed mysuggestion that they should keep us informed of the progress of the MonroviaPowers&apos; discussions of these matters. These discussions will begin with a meetingof experts in Dakar this month.Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland13. Federal Ministers started in a rather suspicious frame of mind. they believed our decision had already been taken. Our discouraging response inMarch to their proposal that they should seek some kind of A.O.T. relationship with the Six inclined them to doubt whether we would seriously try to secure thatstatus for them. The constitutional controversies of the last year or so had alsoleft in their minds some resentment and doubt of our good faith. I think I was able in our discussions to do something to dispel the doubts expressed to me.14. Federal Ministers were throughout resolutely insistent that if we joined the Six the only adequate safeguard for the Federation lay in obtaining A.O.T.status. I assured them that we would do our level best to obtain this for them,though I could clearly make no promise that we would succeed. They were reluctant to agree to consider any fall-back position, and even when persuaded to do so they continued to insist that only A.O.T. status could meet their needs.They have considerable justification for this view if as they must they are to expand and diversify their economy. For their main existing exports some formof protection might be manageable short of A.O.T. status.Conclusion15. I have already said that the aims of my visits were broadly achieved.So far as concerns the four Governments with whom I had discussions, I seenothing that need stop us seeking negotiations with the Six in order to ascertainon what terms and conditions we could join the E.E.C.16. We must, however, recognise that we should have serious trouble onour hands if we eventually joined the E.E.C. without having secured arrangementssuch as these Governments regard as essential. These are:(a) a relationship between Europe and the African countries which does notdiscriminate against the trade of the formerly British countries in west Africa, or impede their political and economic co-operation withtheir neighbours, and which cannot be described as &quot; neo-Colonial &quot;;(b) A.O.T. status for the Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland.J. H.Ministry of Labour, S.W. 1,10th July, 1961.59285
ANNEX AGHANAText of Letter dated 29th June, 1961 from Mr. John Hare to Dr. Kwama Nkrumah,President of the Republic of GhanaI am most grateful to you for giving me the opportunity to discuss with you and your Ministers the problem of the European Common Market.I explained to you the strong arguments which have led us to think that weshould consider entering into formal negotiations with the Six.As I emphasised to you, the British Government themselves have not yet reached a decision on this question, and we shall not do so until we have completedour consultations with all Commonwealth Governments, and have consideredtheir views. Should we decide to negotiate, I know you will appreciate the reasons why.You explained very clearly to me the points that are of special importanceto you. As I explained, it would only be through the process of negotiationthat we would be able to discover ways in which we could endeavour to safeguard the points to which we both attach importance. If these negotiations take placewe shall certainly bear your points in mind.Meanwhile I can, of course, assure you that in any such negotiations we wouldthroughout keep in the closest touch with you, and that before any final decision was taken there would be the fullest consultation between us.ANNEX BNIGERIAAgreed Note of Meetings between Ministers of the Federal Government of Nigeriaand Mr. John Hare, on behalf of the British Government, held in Lagos on30th June, 19611. The United Kingdom delegation explained the reasons why the BritishGovernment were considering seeking negotiations for membership of theEuropean Economic Community.2. The Nigerian delegation took note of this explanation. While recognising that it was for the British Government to decide whether to seek such negotiationsthey set out certain relevant objectives of their own policies as follows:(a) Economic Considerations(1) Discrimination against Nigerian trade with the European economic community should be abolished.(2) As stated in the speech from the Throne on 29th March. 1961,the Nigerian Government would &quot; examine the possibility of closereconomic co-operation with African States and association betweenNigeria and the European Economic Community&quot;; the nigerian government would discuss this whole matter with the otherMonrovia Powers beginning with the meeting of officials to be heldat Dakar in July 1961.(3) The Nigerian Government considered that if the British Governmentjoined the e.c. Nigeria should be fully eligible for assistance fromthe Development Fund. They noted the British delegation^ viewthat nothing in the Treaty of Rome precluded the giving of bilateralaid in addition to that given by the Development Fund.
ANNEX CSIERRA LEONEAgreed Summary Record of Discussions between Ministers of the Sierra LeoneGovernment and Mr. John Hare on behalf of the British Government,held at Freetown on 3rd June, 19611. On behalf of the British Government Mr. Hare explained that, both because of the desirability of achieving greater unity in Europe and because ofthe opportunity for increased economic growth and activity which membership of the E.E.C. would offer, the British Government were considering the implications of seeking negotiations for membership of the community. Thequestion at present before them was whether to seek such negotiations, in orderto ascertain whether suitable arrangements could be secured to safeguard theessential interests of the Commonwealth, the other E.F.T.A. countries and Britishhome agriculture. No decision had yet been reached on this question. Theywere anxious to acquaint themselves more fully with the views of the other commonwealth Governments before reaching a decision.2. Sierra Leone Ministers recognised that the decision whether to seeknegotiations was one for the British Government to take. In response to theUnited Kingdom request for information on the Sierra Leone Governmenfs views,they said that they hoped that the British Government would bear the followingpoints in mind while considering whether to seek negotiations and during any negotiations which might be entered into:(i) The   importance   attached   by   Sierra   Leone   to   maintaining   theCommonwealth connexion, and at the same time to ensuring that anyeventual form of association between African countries and theEuropean Economic Community would be consistent with the aim of closer co-operation among the countries of Africa, and with the advancement of their political and economic development.(ii) The need to avoid discrimination by the European Economic Communityagainst the exports (actual or potential) of Sierra Leone. Sierra LeoneMinisters also expressed interest in the operation of the Community&apos;sDevelopment Fund, and in the possibility of access to it by sierra leone.3. Mr. Hare said that the British Government would keep these considerationswell in mind both while considering whether to negotiate with the Six and during any such negotiations. He also undertook that the British Government would continue to keep in close consultation with the Sierra Leone Government. Hesaid that the British Government would be grateful if they could be kept informed of any views expressed on these questions at the forthcoming meeting at Dakar.(b) Political Considerations(1) The Nigerian Government regard it as being of equal importance thatat all stages careful consideration should be given to the effect ofany closer association with the E.E.C. upon the Commonwealthrelationship as a whole.(2) They likewise attached great importance to ensuring that the relationship between the various African States should be bornefully in mind throughout.(3) Similarly they considered that relations with countries other than thosein Africa or the Commonwealth must be given full weight.3. The United Kingdom delegation said that these considerations would bekept well in mind both while a decision was being considered on whether to negotiate with the Six and during any such negotiations. They also undertook that the nigerian Government would be kept closely in touch throughout the course of any negotiations. In addition they noted the views of the Nigerian Government on thesubject of Commonwealth preferences on individual commodities of importance toNigeria.
ANNEX DFEDERATION OF RHODESIA AND NY AS ALANDAgreed Summary of Points Discussed at Meetings of Federal Ministers andMr. John Hare on behalf of the British Government at Salisbury on 4th and 5th July, 19611. Mr. Hare explained that both because of the desirability of achievinggreater political and economic unity in Europe and because of the opportunity forincreased economic growth and activity which British entry to the european economic Community would offer the United Kingdom, the British Governmentwere at present considering the implications of seeking negotiations for membership of the Community. The question at present before them was whether or not to seek such negotiations in order to ascertain whether suitable arrangements couldbe secured to safeguard the essential interests of the Commonwealth, the other  .F.T.A. countries and British home agriculture. No decision had yet been reached on this question. They were anxious to acquaint themselves more fully with theviews of the other Commonwealth Governments before coming to a decision.2. The Federal Ministers expressed the view that the entry of the UnitedKingdom into the European Economic Community would be damaging to theFederation. They recognised, however, that there were wider considerations whichmight lead the United Kingdom Government to decide to seek negotiations. they hoped that while considering this question and throughout the course of any negotiations the British Government would give full weight to the following points in addition to the Federal Government^ fear that damage would be done to theFederation:(i) The Federal Government were much concerned about the possible effectof United Kingdom entry into the E.E.C. upon the Commonwealthconnexion as a whole.(ii) The Federal Government considered that if the United Kingdom entered the E.E.C. it was essential, in the interests of the Federation, thatAssociated Overseas Territory status should be secured for theFederation.3. Mr. Hare said that the British Government would certainly have the viewsof the Federal Government, as expressed above, fully in mind and that in particular the British Government would do everything they Could to secure A.O.T. statusfor the Federation if they decided to enter into negotiations with the Six.4. Mr. Hare went on to explain that it could not be regarded as certain thatA.O.T. status would be obtainable. He asked, therefore, if he could be informed of the specific products of importance to the Federation^ economy in respect ofwhich special arrangements to protect the Federation^ exports would have to besought if A.O.T. status did not, in the end, turn out to be obtainable. In response to this request, but without retracting any of their emphasis on the essentiality ofobtaining A.O.T. status, the Federal officials discussed this aspect of the matter with United Kingdom officials and gave them the attached list of individualproducts of this nature. The Federal officials emphasised that, in addition to maintaining access to the British Market for existing exports like tobacco and tea,there was also a need for free or preferential entry into that market for increased exports of agricultural and industrial products so as to make possible thedevelopment of the Federation^ economy. These discussions were subsequentlyreported to the Ministers and Mr. Hare took note of the views that had been expressed.5. Mr. Hare said that the British Government would give full weight to allthe views expressed by the Federal Ministers both while considering whether tonegotiate with the Six and during any such negotiations. He undertook that theBritish Government would continue to keep in close consultation with the federal government. The Federal Ministers raised the question of a commonwealth meeting to consider all aspects of this whole question. Mr. Hare said that hethought it likely that the United Kingdom Prime Minister and the Prime Ministers
AppendixAGREED LIST OF ITEMS REFERRED TO IN PARAGRAPH 4TobaccoMaizeBeef and products of beefGroundnutsTeaCitrus and products of citrusIron and Steel (especially Pig Iron and High Grade Steels)Ferro-chrome and other Ferro-alloysLead and ZincWrought CopperWattle ExtractLeather.of other Commonwealth countries would wish to arrange for collectiveconsideration of the whole matter at a Commonwealth meeting before any final decisions were taken by the British Government on whether to join the Community.6. Mr. Hare undertook to inform the Ministers concerned that sir Donald Macintyre would wish to discuss with them, during his forthcoming visit to London, and subsequently, if necessary, the question whether the BritishGovernment would support the Federal Government in an application for separatemembership of the International Monetary Fund and the International Bank.

</content>
</cab>
