<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/161/9 images: 190-193</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(72) 924 January 1972CABINETRESTRICTIVE PRACTICES IN THE SUPPLY of professional services memorandum by the Secretary of State for Trade and industry. At their meeting on 13 December 1971 the Ministerial Committee onEconomic Policy agreed that our Bill on competition policy should enablerestrictions in the supply of commercial services to be dealt with by the restrictive Practices Court, instead of (as now) by the monopolies commission.    But the Committee were divided on whether professionalservices should be similarly treated.    A decision on this is now urgently needed.2.        I am quite clear that it would be right to take power now to enablecertain restrictions in professional services to be examined by the Court,rather than by the Monopolies Commission.    The problems to be dealt withare not those of monopoly or oligopoly as commonly understood, but ofconcerted restrictive practices by many suppliers.    The professionalbodies are unlikely to modify their practices voluntarily in the light offurther recommendations by the Commission,    Their restrictive agreementscould then be dealt with only by Order, which would be more controversialthan invoking a judicial procedure.    Moreover, it would be necessary torefer each profession to the Commission in turn, whereas one or twodecisions of the Court would clearly indicate to other professions wherethey stood.    Finally, to exclude all the professions explicitly from theproposed extension to services of the restrictive practices legislation wouldgive rise to problems of definition and provoke adverse comment,SCOPE OF THE NEW POWERS3. The restrictions under the 1956 Act relevant to the professions wouldbe those relating to fees and charges, to advertising, to the terms or conditions on which services are supplied, and to the persons by or to whomservices are provided,  * The quality of a professional service andrestrictions on entry into a profession, on forms of entity (eg. a&quot;partnerships only&quot; rule) and on the carrying on of other business would notbe covered.    Nor would agreements authorised under statute.    But the new legislation would cover the restrictions criticised by the monopolies commission that have attracted most public attention - including the scalefees charged by accountants, architects and auctioneers (for example),copy NO       g  
4. The existing &quot;gateways&quot; (i. e. grounds on which restrictions can bejustified to the Court) would allow restrictions imposed in the interests ofthe public as purchasers or users of services to be defended.    But in orderto meet a further point raised by the Lord Chancellor, I propose to include an additional gateway under which the professions might seek to justifyrestrictions imposed to serve some (probably few) interests of the public at large.PROCEDURE UNDER THE EXTENDED legislation. There would be no question of requiring the wholesale registration of restrictive agreements in the other professions.    The Director-Generalof Fair Trading and Competition would first discuss with a profession^representatives the public interest in relation to its restrictive practices.Only if they proved unwilling to change or abandon practices that he considered detrimental would he advise me to make an Order (subject to affirmative resolution) requiring the profession to register its restrictiveagreements so that the Court could examine them.    The Director-general would keep in close contact with Departments, and I would of courseconsult those colleagues with a direct interest before making an Order.6.        I recognise that some professions - the law and medicine are theprime examples - have special obligations in terms of maintenance of standards and a fiduciary relationship with clients which differentiatethem from other suppliers of services.    My proposals are designed totake these obligations into account - being directed at the economic aspectsof professional practice, where the relationships are similar.    We cannotignore these aspects in putting forward comprehensive proposals topromote competition generally.7. There is no reason in principle to suppose that a judicial procedure would be any less successful in dealing with restrictive agreements in services than in goods.    But there is a special problem in the case of thelegal profession.    The Lord Chancellor considers it unacceptable thatsolicitors (many of whose restrictive practices are authorised by statuteand would thus be exempt) and barristers (whose practices would becaught) should be treated differently under the proposed extension of thelegislation.    He has also pointed out that the legal profession, unlikeothers, have a duty to the Courts and to the administration of justice whichmay override their duty to clients; to enable them to discharge it they accept restrictions which would be registrable but very difficult to defendin terms of the legislation.    We have not been able to reach agreement on changes that would meet these objections, and since they have much forceI propose to exclude legal services altogether from the extension of the restrictive practices legislation.    They will however still be within thescope of the monopoly provisions.    The question of extending the restrictive practices legislation to include them could also be consideredlater in the light of changes in the Solicitors Act (or rules made under it).2
PRESENTATION8.        I accept that these proposals may be unwelcome to manyprofessional bodies.    But they will find it difficult openly to oppose them if carefully presented as part of our comprehensive policy for enhancingcompetition in every sector of the economy, with emphasis upon the selective approach and safeguards referred to above.9.        I seek my colleagues agreement to arrange for the necessary powers to be included in the Bill now in a late stage of preparation.J d department of Trade and Industry24 January 1972


</content>
</cab>
