<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/53/11 images: 102-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s goyernmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CM. (45)11th Conclusions.CABINET 11 (45),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.1, on Friday, 6th July, 1945, at 3 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.Colonel   The   Right   Hon.   oliver stanley, M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir James Grigg,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. The Earl of Roseeery,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade and Minister of Production.The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma.The Right Hon. Brendan Bracken,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Works.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell, Pay-master-General.Sir Alexander Maxwell, permanent under-Secretary of State for HomeAffairs (Item 5).The Right Hon. H. U. Willink, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Health.Major the Right Hon. G. LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Fuel and power.The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.Field-Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff (items-2).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Mr. Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.[30421-1]b
CABINET 11 (45).minute no.1Contents.Subject.Canadian Army........Disturbances in Aldershot.2      British Armies of OccupationAttitude towards Ex-enemy Nationals.3      Cabinet Arrangements4      Man-powerRe-distribution of Man-power in Second5      Housing....      ....      ....      ....      ...Occupation of Empty Houses.Half of 1945.Page6969707172
CanadianArmy.disturbances in Aldershot.1. The Prime Minister asked for the latest information aboutthe disorders among Canadian troops in Aldershot on the 4th and 5th July.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that thesedisorders had broken out among Canadian troops who had beenbrought from overseas to await repatriation to Canada. Accordingto the latest reports received from the Canadian Military Head-quarters (who were wholly responsible for maintaining disciplineamong Canadian troops in this country) the grievances which had given rise to these disturbances were : (i) that, owing to shortage ofshipping, the troops were finding greater delay than they had expected in being sent forward for repatriation to Canada; (iij that,after a period of paid leave, they had received no pay since their return to Aldershot; and (iii) that their scale of rations atAldershot was lower than they had enjoyed overseas. the demonstration on the 4th July had taken the local military authori-ties by surprise; but on the 5th July both the civilian police andthe Canadian military police in the area had been reinforced.100 men had been arrested and those against whom sufficient evidence was forthcoming would be court-martialled.There was some reason to believe that the Canadian militaryauthorities had not taken sufficiently firm action at the outset, butthey were now alive to the seriousness of the situation. The troopsin transit to Canada were being distributed among camps outsidethe built-up area of Aldershot; and some 2,500 were being sent out of the area that day to embarkation points.The Prime Minister referred to the disorders among Britishtroops at the end of the last war, and stressed the need for promp action to prevent the spread of these disorders. It was speciallyimportant that prompt and exemplary punishment should be visitedupon the ringleaders, so as to make it clear that nothing was gained by those who sought to take the law into their own hands in thesematters. Full restitution must also be made for the damage suffered by the owners of property in the area.The Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for War to see that allpossible steps were taken by the Canadian military authori-ties to prevent any further disorders by Canadian troopsin the Aldershot area.british armies ofOccupation.Attitudetowardsex-enemynationals.2. The Prime Minister said that he was concerned about theconsequences of continuing to enforce strict compliance with the&quot; non-fraternisation &quot; order, which required the British Armies ofOccupation to refrain from all intercourse with German and austrian nationals. He had caused a message on this subject to besent to Field-Marshal Montgomery earlier that day; and the Field-Marshal had replied that in his view the time had now come tomodify the &quot; non-fraternisation &quot; order, but that his recommenda-tions on this subject had not hitherto been accepted by higher authority.The Secretary of State for War recalled that, more than amonth ago, he had forwarded to Field-Marshal Montgomery a message from the Prime Minister suggesting that this order shouldbe gradually relaxed. He had added that, if possible, it would be preferable to secure that a common policy was followed by the fourArmies of Occupation in introducing relaxations of the order.In discussion it was pointed out that, strictly speaking, thepolicy in this matter should be prescribed by the Control Commis-sion. As, however, the Commission was not yet fully functioning,it was agreed that it would be proper for His Majesty&apos;s Governmentto give instructions to the British. Commander-in-Chief regardingthe policy to be followed within the British zone of occupation.[30421-1] B 2
After further discussion, the Cabinet reached the following conclusions : :(1) The Secretary of State for War should send to Field-Marshal Montgomery a broad general directive whichwould permit of gradual relaxation of the present rulesregarding &quot;non-fraternisation,&quot; while not directlyencouraging fraternisation and leaving to theCommander-in-Chief the precise methods by whichrelaxation was to be achieved.(2) The Secretary of State for War should inform Field-Marshal Alexander that he had similar authority to relax the &quot; non-fraternisation &quot; order so far as it affectedBritish troops in Austria, and that it was the policy ofHis Majesty&apos;s Government that the attitude of theBritish occupying troops should be less severe in Austriathan in Germany.(3) The Secretary of State for War should arrange for theUnited States Government to be informed of the instruc-tions given on this subject to Field-Marshals Alexanderand Montgomery.(4) On all matters affecting the control of Germany and austria, instructions could be given on behalf of HisMajesty&apos;s Government to the British Commanders-in-i Chief in respect of the British zones of occupation, untilthe machinery of the Control Commissions was fully inoperation, provided that appropriate steps were takento notify the other occupying Powers of the instructionsso given.Cabinet 3.   The Cabinet had before them two memoranda by the PrimeArrangements.  Minister CP. (45) 58 : outlining the arrangements proposed for holdingmeetings of the Cabinet during the current month andannexing a list of the main subjects on which he wishedto see substantial progress made during the month.CP. (45) 59 : giving particulars of the standing ministerial committees of the Cabinet which had been reconstitutedsince the formation of the new Government.The Prime Minister said that, since the formation of the new government, Ministers had necessarily&apos; been preoccupied with thebusiness of the General Election; and it was necessary that theCabinet and its standing Committees, which had now been recon-stituted, should take special measures during the next few weeks to dispose of outstanding business and carry forward the prepara-tions for dealing with the urgent problems of reconstruction.The Secretary of State for the Colonies recalled that in thepast it had been found convenient to bring before the lord presidents Committee questions affecting the Colonies, which werenot of sufficient importance to be submitted to the Cabinet. he hoped that he would be able in future to bring such questions beforethe Home Affairs Committee, which had taken the place of the lord presidents Committee.This was agreed to.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the proposals for the transaction-tion of Cabinet business put forward by the Prime minister in CP. (45) 58, and of the arrangements described in cp. (45) 59 for the reconstitution of the standingMinisterial Committees of the Cabinet.
Man-Power.redistribution of Man-power in second half of 1945.(previous reference:W.M.(45)42ndConclusions,Minute 1.)4.   The Cabinet had before them (i) a Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (CP.(45) 53) on the man-power position in the second halfof 1945; and(ii) two Memoranda by the Prime Minister (CP. (45) 61 and cp. (45) 62) regarding the release of women from theServices.The Prime Minister said that, in view of the serious shortageof man-power for the restoration of civilian industry and for housing, it was essential that the maximum releases should be madeboth from the Armed Forces and from the munitions industriesduring the remainder of 1945. In the uncertainties of the weeksimmediately following the end of hostilities in Europe, he had felt it undesirable that releases should proceed at the maximum rate;and he had, in particular, asked that a standstill should be imposed on the reduction of the Metropolitan Air Force. The international situation had, however, improved to some extent and, subject to amore definitive review in the light of his forthcoming discussions with President Truman and Marshal Stalin, he now thought weshould aim at securing the highest possible rate of release from theServices during the remaining months of 1945.One of the most effective means of meeting the shortage ofman-power would be to increase the releases of women from theServices. There seemed to be large numbers of redundant women in the Services at the present time, and it should be possible to allowall women who desired to leave the Services to do so withoutaffecting the rate of release of men in Class &quot;A.&quot;In discussion, there was general agreement that it was important to secure the largest possible increase in the man-power available for civilian industries and for housing. On the otherhand, the view was expressed that, although some acceleration inthe rate of release should be possible, no substantial increase couldbe secured in the man-power available for the civil sector without some modification of the approved plans for our participation inthe war in the Far East. So far as concerned the release of women,the Service Ministers pointed out that, while every effort must bemade to avoid retaining women who were redundant, it would notbe possible to make redundancy an automatic ground for dischargewithout encroaching on the principle of release by age and lengthof service. Moreover, many Units which were still required werestaffed by women to the extent of 50 per cent. For these reasons it did not seem possible to make it an absolute rule that any womanwho wished to leave the Services should be allowed to do so.The Secretary of State for Air said that, since the Man-power committee had reported on the redistribution of man-power in thesecond half of 1945, authority had been given by the Prime Ministerfor certain relaxations of the standstill order on the MetropolitanAir Force and it had been agreed that the 1st August could be taken as the latest date for the revocation of this order. There had alsobeen a reduction from 116 to 87 in the number of squadrons requiredfor the South-East Asia Command; and it seemed probable thatthe number of airfields which would be made available for ourV.L.R. Force would reduce to 10 the number of Squadrons whichcould be,deployed. The Air Staff had also agreed that a saving of about 20,000 could be made in the man-power required forsquadrons in the less active theatres. The combined results of these factors should be to make possible a considerable increase in thereleases from the R.A.F. An estimate was being made of the savings which would result from these changes of plan.The reduction in the V.L.R. Force should also result in a saving of man-power in the aircraft industry.Other points in discussion were (a) If the rate of releases- from the Forces were speededup substantially, there would be an increased amount of local
unemployment before those released could all be reabsorbed into civilindustry.(5) Particular difficulty was being experienced in securingman-power for textile industries because of the relatively low wages paid in these industries compared with wages in the munition industries. It might be necessary to use the power to direct labourinto the textile industry, though this would be done only in very exceptional circumstances. Steps were being taken by the Presidentof the Board of Trade to improve the conditions of employment inthe cotton industry.(c) The Minister of Works drew attention to the shortage oflabour in the building materials industry. At present the shortageamounted to about 10,000 and in the next three months it was likelyto rise to 25,000.Summing up the discussion, the Prime Minister said that itwas clear that over the next few months every effort must be madeto release the maximum amount of man-power from the armed forces and the munitions industries. Pending the result of hismeeting with President Truman and Marshal Stalin, no final decisions should be taken which would affect our strategy in theFar Eastern war; but, subject to that, the present situationwarranted a considerable speeding up of the rate of release. Inparticular, the Secretary of State for Air might treat the 15th Julyinstead of the 1st August as the date for the removal of the stand-still order on the Metropolitan Air Force and might provisionallyassume that the V.L.R. Force would not exceed 10 squadrons.The Cabinet Agreed that the Man-Power Committee should review thesituation further in the light of the directions given bythe Prime Minister and the points raised in the discussion and should submit revised proposals for consideration bythe Cabinet at an early date.Housing. 5.   The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to news reportsOccupation about the illegal occupation of empty houses in Brighton by home-of empty        less families.houses. It was explained that the Home Office had been in touch withthe local police on the matter. So far, only two empty houses hadbeen entered and since no damage had been done there were no grounds for criminal proceedings. It was understood that civilactions for trespass would be brought against the families who werein occupation of the houses.There was general agreement that the Home Office and theMinistry of Health should act quickly in order to prevent anyfurther lawless action. It should be possible for the local police to shadow the person who had broken into the houses and so make sure that he did not break into any further houses. At the sametime, every effort should be made to ensure that the families were removed at the earliest possible date from the two houses which hadbeen illegally occupied, and the Ministry of Health should see thatalternative accommodation to which these families could move was provided. Moreover, in order to prevent further illegal occupationof houses, whether in Brighton or elsewhere, the Minister of health and the Secretary of State for Scotland should take whatever steps were necessary to bring into use for&apos; the accommodation of homelessfamilies any available empty houses.The Minister of Health said that he was satisfied that thenecessary action could be taken under the requisitioning powers con-ferred by Defence Regulation 51. Hitherto it had been the practice,when it was proposed to requisition a house for a family which had- not been bombed out, to give the owner an opportunity of sellingthe house or reoccupying the house himself or of selling or letting, it. This, however, was apt to lead to delay and it would probablybe desirable that in all cases the house should be requisitionedwithout giving the owner a prior right to sell or let it.
The Cabinet (1) Invited the Home Secretary and the Minister of Health todeal with the situation in Brighton on the   lines indicated above.(2) Agreed that the Secretary of State for Scotland and thenecessary to ensure that, both in Brighton and in otherparts of the country, the maximum use was made of anyempty houses for the accommodation of inadequatelyhoused families.Minister of Healthany further actionCabinet Office, S.W. 1,6th July, 1945.




</content>
</cab>
