<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/6/21 images: 236-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  March 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)76th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 76 ( 40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, March 27, 1940, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare,Bt., M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.Viscount Halifax,State   for   foreign the Right hon secretary   ofAffairs.Admiral of the Fleet the Right Hon.Lord Chatfield, Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Stanley,M.P., Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. Lord Hankey,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Mr. R. H. Cross, M.P., Minister ofEconomic Warfare (Item 8).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office.Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.Sir Horace J. Wilson, permanent secretary to the Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff.General Sir W. Edmund Ironside,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General H. L. Ismay.Captain A. D. Nicholl, R.N.Captain A. W. Clark, R.N.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Wing Commander W. Elliot.Mr. L. F. Burgis.Major C. R. Price, R.E.[21057]b
WAR CABINET 76 ( 40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Supreme War Council ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     1672      General Strategical Situation ...      ...      ...      ...     167German oil position.3      Western Front.....................     170Action in the event of a German invasion of Holland and/or belgium.4      Royal Marine Operation      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     1725      Scandinavia     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     173Proposed  communications   to  the   Norwegian  and   swedish governments.6      The Balkans : General situation in South-Eastern Europe     174Attitude of Turkey: proposed visit of Foreign Secretary.Possible action against Russia.Italy; suggested visit of Foreign Secretary to Rome.7      France   ........................    177Anglo-French   Declaration  regarding  no  separate  peace and post-war co-operation.8      Contraband Control   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     177Control of supplies to Germany from the Far East.Soviet ship Selenga.9      The Air Situation     ..................     178R.A.F. activity on the Western Front.10      The Naval Situation..................     178S.S. AUmark.U-boat activity.
Supreme Was 1.   The Prime Minister said that arrangements had now beenCouncil. made for the Meeting of the Supreme War Council to take place(Previous on the following day.   In view of the importance of the mattersReference: to be discussed at the Meeting, he had thought it right that theW.M. (40) 75th full War Cabinet should meet and consider the matters which were conclusions,      to be discussed with the French.Minute 4.) M. Reynaud was bringing with him the three Service ministers and the three Chiefs of Staff. He (the Prime Minister) proposedthat the British representatives at the Council should likewiseinclude the three Service Ministers, in addition to the foreign secretary and himself.The French Chiefs of Staff were arriving in advance of theFrench Ministers, and a meeting was to be held that afternoonbetween the French and British Chiefs of Staff. The PrimeMinister thought it would be of value if the British Ministers could have a short report of this Meeting before the Supreme WarCouncil met.The Chief of the Air Staff undertook to supply this report.The Prime Minister said that the French asked that their official entertainment should be confined to a luncheon, which wouldtake place on the following day, and which he hoped that all members of the War Cabinet would be able to attend.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.GeneralStrategicalSituation.2. The War Cabinet had under consideration the following papers dealing with the general strategical situation : (1) a Report by the Chiefs of Staff on Certain Aspects of thePresent Position (WP. (40) 111);(2) a Note by the Minister without Portfolio, on the GrandStrategy of the Allies (WP. (40) 103);&quot; (3) a Note by the French Prime Minister on the French Govern-menfs views on the Future Conduct of the War,forwarded under a covering Note by the foreign secretary (WP. (40) 109).The War Cabinet first considered the Report by the Chiefs ofStaff (WP. (40) 111).The Chief of the Air Staff said that the Chiefs of Staff hadbeen preparing a full-scale appreciation of the whole situation.The shorter paper now before the War Cabinet was intended toserve as a background for the questions to be discussed at theMeeting of the Supreme War Council on the following day.The Chief of the Air Staff then recapitulated the main points in the paper, touching in particular on the following paragraphs :  (i) Paragraph 7 dealt with the grave danger which wouldresult from an intensification of enemy air attack on our shipping in Home Waters, and the consequent needwhich might arise for diversion of shipping to&apos; WestCoast ports.(ii) Paragraphs 10-15 showed that our air policy was basedon the progressive development of a large Air Forcedesigned to reach its full strength in three years.(iii) Paragraph 16 pointed out the strategic advantage which germany enjoyed in holding a much shorter line thanthat which the Allies were called upon to defend.(iv) Paragraphs 20 and 21 dealt with the attitude of Italy, towhich the Chiefs of Staff attached the greatest impor-tance. We could either maintain our present conciliatory attitude or arrange a show of force against Italy.  The[210571 b 2
Chiefs of Staff had prepared a paper showing themeasures which could be taken to deter Italy from entering the war against the Allies.[It was pointed out that the specific reference to&quot; a show of force in the Middle East &quot; in paragraph 21was a mistake, and that the proposals of the Chiefsof Staff included the adoption of measures wherever they would be likely to intimidate the Italians.](v) Paragraphs 23-25 contained the conclusions of the Chiefsof Staff. Paragraph 25 included a caveat against our being stampeded into undertaking unprofitable militaryprojects offering little prospect of decisive success,merely for the sake of doing something.German oil The Secretary of State for Air suggested that a Report,* whichposition. had just been prepared by the Committee on :the German Oil(Previous Position under the Chairmanship of the Secretary for Mines, had reference:        an important bearing on the discussion of the present strategicW.M. (40) 22nd position of Germany.  This report stated that, if the German forcesConclusions,      remained more or less inactive for the next six months, and a fairlyMinute 10.)       high rate of importation of oil from Roumania and Russia were maintained, it was considered that Germany would be able to keepher stocks above danger point; and that by the end of the year herrate of supply might begin to exceed her rate of consumption.   If,on the other hand, Germany elected or was compelled to undertake a high degree of activity during the coming months, she wouldprobably find herself in a serious situation before next winter.  TheReport suggested, by way of corollary, that Germany&apos;s petroleumdifficulties would be increased if we could induce her to undertakemore active operations.In discussion it was explained that the figures quoted from thisReport had been considered by the Committee on Preventing oil from reaching Germany, under the Chairmanship of the Minister-without Portfolio. The latter informed the War Cabinet thathe had drafted a commentary on the Report, which dealt, inparticular, with the conclusions from the Report quoted by theSecretary of State for Air and put a somewhat different inter-pretation on the figures of Germany&apos;s oil position. Generally, itwas thought that lubricating oils represented Germany&apos;s ihostserious problem. Normally, Germany obtained two-thirds to three-quarters of her supplies of lubricating oils from across the atlantic, and only a very small proportion from Russia and roumania. In present circumstances her best source for augmentingsupplies of lubricating oils was Russia, and deprivation of this source might prove very serious for her. He agreed that theconclusion to be drawn from these arguments was that we shouldtake all possible steps to prevent Germany from importing oilproducts.The War Cabinet then considered the Note by the minister without Portfolio (W.P. (40) 103).The Minister without Portfolio pointed out that the Chiefs ofStaff had independently come to much the same conclusions ashimself on the present strategic position in their Memorandum(W.P. (40) 111). Broadly speaking, his own view was that weshould continue our present general policy, which he would nowprefer to describe as an offensive-defensive policy. By means of operations such as the raid on Sylt and the proposed Royal marine operation we should constantly endeavour to harass the enemy asmuch as might be in our power, while at the same time building up our resources. The action which should be taken in the event ofan invasion of Holland had already been carefully considered bythe War Cabinet.   Outside the Western theatre he advocated our* Paper No. P.O.G. (40) 38.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 74thConclusions,Minute 7.)
taking a more active line in the Near East and against Eussia, andfor this purpose he was in favour of a marshalling of our forcesin the Near East.Discussion then turned on the Note submitted bv the french prime Minister (W.P. (40) 109). &quot; .The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs felt that the French note took no account of jjractical difficulties, and, in particular, itwas remarkable that in paragraphs 7, 8 and 9, referring to thepossibility of action in the Black Sea, no mention whatever wasmade of Turkey. He suggested that in discussing the Paper withthe French, while not actively opposing any of the suggestions made,we should endeavour to find out how it was proposed to achieve the projects for example, how it was contemplated sending Frenchand British submarines into the Black Sea.As regards Scandinavia, he felt that the Foreign Office plansuggested in the draft A ide-Memoire, which was before the Cabinet(W.P. (40) 107), was preferable to, and more practical than, theFrench plan of taking control of Norwegian ports.The Secretary of State for War was unable to accept theassumption in paragraph 6 of the French Note that a German attackon Norwegian ports, following on their occupation by the Allies,would bring Norway in on our side.The Prime Minister found little of value in the French note which, while proposing certain ostentatious actions, gave no details and deduced no arguments for carrying them out.The.First Lord of the Admiralty thought that some allowance should perhaps be made for M. Reynaud&apos;s previous lack of contact with the conduct of the war.The Prime Minister&apos;s general comments on the situation were as follows : The shock of the Finnish collapse had faded and theset-back to the Allied cause was not so great as it had at firstappeared, partly as a result of our stating our case, partly as aresult of the attack on Sylt, which had received even greater importance in the eyes of the world than it had merited. But theappetite of the public for spectacular operations remained, andthis psychological factor could not be ignored. Any blow whichwe could deliver at Germany would encourage our own people andwould be admirable for propaganda purposes. It was of the utmost importance that we should make the best use, for propaganda purposes, of our exploits.In considering what action we should take, it was important,first that any blow which we delivered should be directed againstGermany; secondly, that it should be regarded in the eyes of theworld as legitimate and as one which did no injury to innocentparties. The projects put forward by the French Prime Ministerfailed in both these respects. The Royal Marine Operation, on theother hand, fulfilled them both and it was difficult to understand why the French hesitated to agree to its execution. He felt thatthe psychological effect would be tremendous; it would give us the initiative and encourage our own people and the neutrals.With regard to the interruption of Germany&apos;s ore trade from narvik, he felt that the laying of the mine-field was an operation which could be carried out at any time, and it was only a questionof choosing the best moment.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence thought that theFrench were inclined to think of land operations to the exclusion of the broader issues, and emphasised the necessity of impressingupon the French that economic pressure still remained the strategicbasis of this war. This strategy had always meant a long war, butto-day there was surely some hope of a short war because the-enemy had started in a weak state.   It was, therefore, all the more
important to do everything that was possible to make Germanyexhaust herself. She would be subjected to economic shocks, and steps must be taken to prevent her conducting the war in her ownmanner. We should not be hurried by the pressure of publicopinion and feeling.Continuing, the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence said he believed that Germany would make an attack and that her offensivemight very well employ some new means. He thought it was possiblethat the Germans might be developing a method of using the torpedofrom aircraft, and that they might employ this weapon against our merchant shipping and even against docks and harbourfacilities.He agreed with the opinions already expressed that now wasthe time to put the Royal Marine Operation into effect, and he feltalso that the time was equally ripe for blocking the Norwegiancorridor. Further, he suggested that consideration should be givento the desirability of bringing diplomatic pressure to bear uponRussia. She was potentially a large supplier of oil to Germany.We knew Russia&apos;s weaknesses and had cards which we could playagainst her. While Germany would be inconvenienced if we cutoff her supplies of ore, she had undoubtedly accumulated stocks,and had already manufactured large quantities of armaments. Onthe other hand, Germany must obtain oil.The Foreign Secretary said that the Soviet Ambassador had asked to see him that afternoon. He suspected that the approach was in connection with the action which had been taken againstRussian shipping. In this connection he proposed to take a stiffline on any matter of contraband complaints.The First Lord of the A dmiralty agreed that there was always the danger that Germany might turn her attention to aircraftattack with torpedoes upon shipping. At the same time, to datethey had been able to sink ships by bomb a cheaper method.Therefore, they might not be willing to contemplate the employmentof a far more expensive weapon.The Minister for Co-ordination of Defence pointed out thatthe submarine menace had already largely been defeated. Thetorpedo was an extremely effective weapon and Germany might wellemploy it from the.air, in default of its satisfactory employmentfrom the submarine. It was also to be remembered that a torpedoattack from the air on harbour facilities would not subject civilians,to danger to the same degree as the bomb.The War Cabinet Took note of the Report by the Chiefs of Staff (W.P. (40)111) and of the Memorandum by the Minister without Portfolio(WP. (40) 103).(The conclusions reached on specific issues are recorded inthe ensuing Minutes.)Western Front.Action in theevent of aGerman invasion of holland and/or Belgium.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 74thConclusions,Minute 7.)3. The War Cabinet had under consideration a memorandum circulated by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on theProtection of the Low Countries (W.P. (40) 106).The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that he wasnot clear how the matter of assistance to Holland stood. We had made approaches to the Belgians, but was there anything morewhich we could do to meet the contingency of a German invasion of Holland?The Chief of the Air Staff said that the Chiefs of Staff, whenthey had examined this question, had come to the conclusion thatthere was very little which we could do to prevent Holland beingsoverrun.
The Secretary of State for Air said that we could impose some delay by air action, but the effect would be very limited.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that a new and important point had arisen in this connexion during his recent visit to General Gamelin. General Gamelin had said that theFrench would not be prepared to move into Belgium, if Hollandwere attacked, except at the invitation of the Belgians. His reasons(with which he (the Chief of the Imperial General Staff), general george and Lord Gort were in agreement) were that the AlliedArmy could not render effective assistance to Holland until it had moved some 100 miles across Belgium. It would have to maintainitself by Belgian roads and railways; and in the course of itsadvance it would have to establish itself on successive defensivepositions, in order to provide against the possibility of subsequentwithdrawal. Unless this advance were carried out at the invitation of the Belgians, it would be made through a potentially hostilecountry, and at best would be slow. Moreover, if the Alliesoccupied a line having on each flank fortress areas in the occupationof Belgian troops, they would be in an insecure position, if the belgians refused to co-operate. It was clear, therefore, that it was of the utmost importance that the Belgians should invite us into their country without a momenfs delay, immediately the Germanscrossed the Dutch frontier. Any time lost would prevent the Alliesfrom doing more than occupy the line of the Scheldt, which would afford no assistance to Holland.The Prime Minister said that Dr. Colijn had told him that theposition in Holland was now very much stronger than it had beenin September 1939.The Secretary of State for War suggested, that we must tell the Belgians that, if the Germans succeeded in reaching the Belgian-Dutch border before they gave us the opportunity to move into belgium, we should then be powerless to save all but a very smallportion of their country.The Prime Minister appreciated that it was of capitalimportance that the Belgians should invite us to enter their country at the earliest possible moment if Holland were invaded. general gamelin&apos;s hesitation was probably due to the fact that, whileBelgian acquiescence would certainly be forthcoming in the eventof Belgium being invaded, it might be withheld if Holland alonewas invaded. He suggested that the Chiefs of Staff at their meeting with their French colleagues that afternoon should say that thispoint had been put to the War Cabinet that morning; and that theWar Cabinet had wondered why General Gamelin believed thatthe Belgians would discriminate between the case of an invasion of Holland and one of Belgium, in the matter of inviting allied assistance.The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs referred to part &quot; C &quot; of his Memorandum (WP. (40) 106). He pointed outthat in the Note to paragraph I, sub-paragraph (a) 2, it was statedthat, in the event of a German invasion of Belgium, the French high command had confirmed that the French Forces would enterBelgium without waiting for an invitation from the BelgianGovernment. It had been assumed that this was also the attitudeof the French Government, but the point had not yet been confirmed by them, and he would like to raise it at the Supreme War Council.The War Cabinet agreed (i) That the Chiefs of Staff should confirm, at their meeting with the French Chiefs of Staff, that General Gamelin&apos;views as to the action which the Allies should take in
the event of a German attack on Holland are asfollows :  &quot;It is of paramount importance for the Allied forces to move into Belgium the moment the german invasion of Holland commences, but it is militarilyimpossible to do so unless the Belgians co-operate with us.&quot;(ii) That the above question should be raised at the meetingof the Supreme War Council on the 28th March, with aview to considering what pressure could be put uponthe Belgian Government to extend an immediateinvitation to the Allies to enter their countryimmediately the Germans entered Holland.(iii) With reference to W.P. (40) 106, paragraph (C) I (2), thatthe French Delegates at the forthcoming meeting of theSupreme War Council should be asked to confirm thatthe French Government shared the view of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment that, if Germany invaded Belgium, allied forces should immediately move into Belgium without waiting for an invitation, but that this intention shouldnot be made known to the Belgian Government, lest itshould give them the impression that it was a matterof indifference to us whether they invited us into theircountry.Royal marine operation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 72ndConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The following were the main points made in the courseof discussion in regard to the Royal Marine Operation : The Secretary of State for Air emphasised the desirability fromthe air point of view of carrying out the Royal Marine Operation inApril or May and hoped that any suggestion from the Frenchof postponing it until June would be strongly resisted.The Minister without Portfolio said that it was important to start the Royal Marine Operation as soon as possible, in view ofthe intention to carry out a similar operation elsewhere at a later date.The Prime Minister observed that the initiation of the royal marine Operation provided the kind of action that M. Reynaudwanted. If the meeting of the Supreme War Council were immediately followed by an offensive stroke, the effect upon publicopinion would be considerable and it would greatly strengthenM. Reynaud&apos;s position.The Secretary of State for War thought that it was a strong arguement in favour of the Royal Marine Operation that it might provoke Germany to taking offensive action on the Western Front.It was entirely in our interest that she should do so. He contrasted with this the underlying thought in M. Reynaud&apos;s paper, which wasthat our energies should be directed to provoking action on the partof other countries, which did not lend themselves to the achievement of our main object.The Chancellor of the exchequer thought that it was important to ascertain the real reasons why the French had insisted upon the postponement of the Royal Marine Operation, so that we shouldbe prepared to meet their arguments.The Secretary of State for Air said that the French obection had lain in their anxiety regarding the security of a number of aircraft which they had assembled in vulnerable areas.The Secretary of State for the Dominions thought that theFrench feared that a German retaliation might come exclusivelvupon their country.   It was important that the French should be
Scandinavia.Proposedcommunicationsto the norwegian and swedish governments.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 78rdConclusions,Minute 7.)5. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs covering a draft Aide-memoire, prepared for communication to the French Ambassador,as to the policy to be adopted towards Norway and Sweden (W.P.(40) 107).The Prime Minister said that he thoroughly endorsed theForeign Secretary&apos;s plan to give formal notice to the scandinavian government that we could not allow the course of the war to be influenced against us by the advantages derived by Germany from norway and Sweden; thus preparing the ground for action whenit suited us. He felt that there was no immediate urgency forcarrying out the Narvik plan, which might be deferred until afterthe Royal Marine Operation had been carried out.The First Lord of the Admiralty strongly supported theproposed communication to the Scandinavian Governments. Hesuggested that in discussion with the French we should first obtain their agreement to carry out the Royal Marine Operation, but he hoped that we could also get them to agree to the stoppage oftraffic in Norwegian Territorial Waters. The neutrals could hardlymake stronger protests than they had already made in connectionwith the firing of a shell on to Norwegian territory and theoperations of our surface forces over the previous week-end on thefringe of the 3-mile limit. These operations had resulted in an appreciable check to the ore supplies, and the crews of the german ships had shown an extremely nervous state of mind. Even afterLulea was ice-free, the Narvik route would continue to be of greatimportance to Germany. He was, however, strongly opposed to theFrench suggestion of occupying Norwegian soil.The First Lord described, in general terms, a further projectwhich was in course of preparation for interfering with Germany&apos;sore supplies from Lulea.The Prime Minister said that he did not propose to mentionthis project to the French.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that para-graph 7 of his Note covered two points. First, it defined action onthe part of the Norwegian and Swedish Governments which weshould regard as un-neutral. Secondly, in paragraph 7 (e) the line was taken that the Allies could not allow the course of the war tobe influenced against them by advantages derived by Germany from norway and Sweden. This line was justified on two grounds; first,,by the character of the war; and, secondly, by the attitude whichNorway and Sweden had taken in regard to Finland. He agreedthat, if we made this communication to the Norwegian and swedish governments, we must expect protests, and that the protests wouldnot be much stronger if we went further and took steps to stoptraffic in Norwegian Territorial Waters by laying a minefield. Hewas, therefore, prepared to agree in principle that we should take this action, subject to the proviso that it was of great importance[21057] cconvinced that they were wrong in this respect. It would be ofgreat value if the Royal Marine Operation could synchronise with air action directed to the same general objective, and perhaps also with some other exploit on the lines of the attack on Sylt.The War Cabinet agreed : That it was of the utmost importance to press the french representatives to agree to the Royal Marine Operation beingstarted as soon as possible; and that this proposal should be linked, in discussion with the French, with the suggested actionin Norwegian Territorial Waters (see Minute 5 below).
that the minefield should be laid at the right moment. This involvedconsideration of the best moment from the point of view of ensuring that the maximum number of German ships had already passednorthward to load at Narvik.It was also important that the War Cabinet should keep in the forefront of their minds the balance sheet of arguments for and against the action proposed. It was not impossible that, if westopped this traffic from proceeding through Norwegian territorial waters, the Norwegians might in turn refuse to supply any furtheriron ore to the Allies.The Prime Minister said that the President of the Board ofTrade had informed him the previous day that our position inregard to supplies of iron ore was now a good deal better. Therewas every hope of bringing more blast furnaces into operation, andour arrangements to obtain Spanish iron ore had improved. Onthe other hand, any interference with the chartering of Scandinavianshipping would be serious.The First Lord of the Admiralty said that, if Norwaythreatened to cut off supplies of iron ore, she could be reminded that the Allies held command of the sea and that, if circumstancesforced them, they might very well come to Narvik and fetch their requirements if they were not willingly offered. There were alsoother possible counter-strokes.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he favoured actingquickly, once the formal protest had been made. He demurred fromthe suggestion that the timing of the operation should necessarily depend upon the number of German merchant ships which should first have passed northwards.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thought action might be taken within a week of the presentation of the Note to norway and Sweden. He was attracted by the First Lord&apos;suggestion that in discussion with the French the British attitudemight initially be one of reluctance to consider forward actionagainst the Scandinavian countries, while pressing for theimmediate initiation of the Royal Marine Operation.The Foreign Secretary said that he would like to hand a copyof the Aide-Memoire to the French Ambassador that afternoon,subject to a few verbal amendments suggested by the Prime Minister,as a basis for discussion at the Supreme War Council on the ensuing day.The War Cabinet agreed : (1) That a copy of the draft Aide-memoire as to the policy to be adopted towards Norway and Sweden, should be handed to the French Ambassador.(2) That discussion at the Supreme War Council on the ensuing day should follow the lines indicated above.The Balkans: 6-   The War Cabinet had under consideration a MemorandumGeneral Situa- Dv tne Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on South-Easterntion in South-    Europe (W.P. (40) 110).Eastern Europe. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that his(Previous Memorandum presented only one side of a complex problem.   the reference: conclusion reached was that, both from the strategical and politicalW.M. (40) 72nd angles, it was not to our interest to intervene as yet in South-Conclusions, Eastern Europe. The overriding consideration must be ourMinutes 2 strength and the effectiveness of our intervention, once decidedand 3.) upon.   To be effective, allied intervention would require a neutralItaly and the co-operation of Turkey. A joint guarantee of the balkan States by Germany, Russia and Italy, given in return for
Attitude ofTurkey :proposed visit of foreign secretary.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 72ndConclusions,Minute 3.)(previous reference erence:W.M. (40) 71stConclusions,Minute 2.)Possible actionagainst Eussia.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 66thConclusions,Minute 1.)economic considerations, would be tantamount to a diplomaticdefeat for us. Further, if Roumania accepted the virtual status ofa German province, it would go a long way towards defeating our blockade. The only real card in our hands at the moment wasTurkey.The Memorandum dealt with the position on the basis of&quot;power politics.&quot; We were not yet in a position to offer the balkan peoples an effective assurance that in the event of an invasionby Russia or Germany the Allies could prevent them from beingoverrun. But, as in the case of Norway and Sweden, there was probably some &apos;&apos; slack &apos;&apos; in the political situation that could be&apos;&apos; taken up &apos;&apos; before reaching the brink of war. He proposed, there-fore, to give instructions that our Missions in this part of europe should &apos;&apos; show the flag &apos;&apos; as much as possible and should be vigorousin their attempts to counteract the effects of German propaganda.It seemed to him increasingly important that he should payan early visit to Ankara or Istanbul, in order to give the balkan countries some evidence of our activities in that direction. Thedifficulty was to be certain of any concrete result which he wouldbe able to show on his return.The Prime Minister felt that there were several very good reasons for such a visit. The present point of pressure wasRoumania, and if she were threatened, she would look to us for help. The attitude of Turkey in such circumstances would be of paramount importance, since without Turkish assistance, there was little that could be done to help Roumania. One object of a visit to Turkey would be discussions of joint action in such circumstances.It should be pointed out to the Turks that their lack of adequateair bases, naval bases and roads, would make it difficult for theAllies to render them effective assistance. The Turks should be pressed to improve their bases and communications. No doubt theywould ask for financial assistance.The First Lord of the A dmiralty referred to the importanceof Italian neutrality in connection with Allied action in the balkans. At some point it might be desirable to stage a navaldemonstration in the Mediterranean with a view to influencing theItalian attitude. At 9-10 days&apos; notice a superior Allied fleet couldbe concentrated at Gibraltar, but rather longer was requiredto concentrate the British section thereof in the eastern mediterranean.The First Lord compared the oilfields at Baku with the ironmines at Galivare as regards their economic importance to Germany.Baku could not be bombarded without the goodwill if not theco-operation of the Turks. This project was another reason infavour of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs paying a visit to Turkey. It was just possible that such action might not involve us in war with Russia, but the Turkish Government would realise the danger only too well. With this in view, it was more than ever desirable to get Turkish consent to the passage of submarinesinto the Black Sea. Two or three submarines would not onlyinterrupt the Russian oil traffic in that sea, but would have aterrifying moral effect on Russia, and would give some protection to Turkey against any combined operation aimed at her northerncoast.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs agreed that we could do little to save Roumania against combined German and Russianaction without active assistance from Turkey. But a differentsituation would arise if the Turks were to go to the assistance of roumania. They might be prepared to&quot; do this in the face ofunprovoked aggression by Russia, but they would be very suspicious of any Allied activity likely to provoke Russia.[21057] c 2
Air action against the Baku oilfields would, however, seem likely to result in reprisals from Germany. They would probablyreinforce the air defences of Baku with fighter aircraft, and theymight send bombers to attack the Iraq and Anglo-Persian oilfieldswhich appeared vulnerable to this form of action.The Minister without Portfolio suggested that the Turks might possibly be prepared to agree to our sending submarines into the black Sea, under the terms of the contraband control.The Prime Minister said that if we became involved in warwith Russia, the way in which this came about Avould have animportant effect, not only on Turkish opinion, but also on a certainsection of opinion in this country. The full implications, such asthe bombardment of the oilfields at Baku, should be very carefully considered.Discussion then followed on the suggested visit of the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs to Turkey. It would be undesirable for him to return from such a mission without some proof of success.It was suggested that the discussions with Turkey should befollowed by discussions at Bucharest or Athens.The Lord Privy Seal hoped that the visit would take place soon.Fie felt that a visit to Rome at the same time would ensure that theobject of the Turkish discussions was not misconstrued in Italy.Such a visit would be a rallying-point for the large pro-ally sectionof Italian public. The signing of the trade agreement now underdiscussion could well form the pretext for such a visit. We had not made enough of the agreements which we had reached with otherGovernments.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs welcomed these suggestions. At the same time, the proposed visit to Ankara mightembarrass the Turkish Government, who were very suspicious ofany activity likely to provoke the Russians. He was, therefore,unwilling to reach a definite decision before he had had time to consult our Heads of Missions in Balkan countries, whom he hadsummoned back to London for a conference on the 8th April. Hewould also wish to ascertain the probable Italian reaction to theproposed visit.The War Cabinet (1) Took note of the Memorandum by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (W.P. (40) 110).(2) Expressed general approval of the proposed visit of theForeign Secretary to Ankara (and possibly also to othercapitals in South-East Europe, and to Rome); butdeferred a decision pending the receipt of reports fromthe Heads of Missions accredited to the States concerned.(3) Agreed that at the forthcoming meeting of the supreme war Council our general attitude to the french proposals for action in the Black Sea and in theCaucasus should be to ascertain how it was proposed thatthese projects should be carried out. In particular, asregards the suggested air attack on the Baku oilfields,we should indicate that we were willing to preparedetailed plans without, however, committing ourselves to this operation.
Prance.Anglo-FrenchDeclarationregarding no separate peace and post-warco-operation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 74thConclusions,Minute 8.)7. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (WP. (G.) (40) 89), covering a revised draft of the proposed Anglo-French Declaration not to conclude a separate peace and concerning post-war co-operation.The Foreign Secretary said that the principal point on whichhe now wished to consult his colleagues was as regards the inclusionof the word &quot; foreign &quot; in the second paragraph of the draft. that paragraph read :  :(2) The two Governments further declare their intention tocontinue the closest co-operation  in their financial,economic, defence and foreign policy after the conclusion, of peace.On the whole, his preference was for the omission of the word&quot; foreign.&quot; It had not appeared in the draft which the DominionGovernments ha,d seen, and it seemed to him that its inclusion might give rise to a good deal of criticism. Neither here nor in theDominions had it been forgotten how divergent the British andFrench conceptions of foreign . policy had been in the years immediately following the last war. More harm than good waslikety to be done by reviving memories of, for example, the Frenchoccupation of the Ruhr in 1923. The French Government need not know that we had ever contemplated the inclusion of the word&quot; foreign &quot; in the Declaration. Even without it, the present draftseemed to strike the desired note of complete mutual confidence forthe future.The War Cabinet Gave a general approval to the draft of the proposed anglo-French Declaration appended to W.P. (G.) (40) 89,subject to the omission of the word &quot; foreign &quot; in paragraph 2.8. The War Cabinet had before them an Aide-Memoire,circulated by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(W.P. (G.) (40) 88), on the subject of Contraband Control in theFar East, which had been communicated semi-officially to the FrenchEmbassy in London with a view to serving as a basis for discussion at the Meeting of the Supreme War Council on the 28th March.(Previous The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs said that the reference:        proposals for dealing with this question were summed up in para-W.M. (40) 68th graphs 9 and 10 of the Memorandum.  The general plan for dealingConclusions,      with the leakage of goods into Germany through Russia was to minute l.)        restrict the export to Russia of goods from our own and the FrenchEmpires.   Any Russian complaints would be answered by sayingthat we could not spare such goods.  The second and more importantstage would be to endeavour to get Japan to agree to a strictlimitation of goods carried in Japanese ships or on Japanese-controlled railways and destined for Russia, and at the same timeto induce the United States Government to take parallel action.The Foreign Secretary did not anticipate that the latter would bean easy task, as the attitude of the United States Government inthis matter had recently been unhelpful.The Minister for Economic Warfare said he had nothing to add to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Aide-Memoire. If we succeeded indiverting a large number of ships to Saigon for examination, theFrench Prize Courts (which were prepared to condemn on lessevidence than our Prize Courts) would probably condemn a largenumber of cargoes. This might mean trouble with Russia. he understood, however, that it was unlikely that we should be ableto divert more than a few ships.contraband control.Control ofsupplies toGermany fromthe Far Bast.
Soviet shipSelenga.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 68thConclusions,Minute 1.)The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said he was notdisturbed by the thought of taking a strong line with Russia inthis respect; his principal preoccupation would be to keep out of trouble with Japan.The Minister for Economic Warfare said, in reply to a question,that the Soviet ship Selenga had now been seized and sent to a french Prize Court at Saigon. The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs said that M. Maisky maintained that the 1.200 tons of wolfram on board was intended for Russian use. Nevertheless, it seemed likely that the cargo would be condemned.The War Cabinet agreed : That the Aide-Memoire submitted by the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs should serve as a basis for discussion at the meeting of the Supreme War Council on the following day.The air situation.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 75thConclusions,Minute 1.)R.A.F. activity on the western front.9. The Secretary of State for Air said that on the 26th Marchthere had been considerable German air activity in the area betweenMetz and the Luxemburg frontier, more enemy formations than hitherto being seen by British fighter patrols. These formationshad generally consisted of five or seven Dornier 17 aircraft, escorted by three Messerschmitt 110&apos;s, but formations of nine or twelveMesserschmitt 109&apos;s had also been encountered. Several combatshad taken place, with satisfactory results. In one combat a formation of five Dornier 17&apos;s, escorted by three Messerschmitt 110&apos;s,had been observed by a patrol of two Hurricanes at 23,000 feet.The Hurricanes had immediately attacked. The enemy fighters had left the reconnaissance aircraft in order to engage the Hurricanes.The Hurricanes had attacked the Dornier 17&apos;s, closely followed bythe enemy fighters. The enemy aircraft by this time bad turnedand were flying towards the front line, and the result of the combathad been inconclusive. The third Hurricane of this section, whichhad previously left the formation to engage an enemy aircraftreported by the intelligence system, had intercepted the Dornierson their return and had inflicted damage on one enemy aircraft.This aircraft had been seen to lose height with engines runningslowly and emitting smoke. Our fighter had then been attacked byone of the Messerschmitt 110&apos;s but had been able to make good itsescape in clouds.In a second combat three Hurricanes of the same Squadron hadintercepted a formation of nine Messerschmitt 109&apos;s over Bouzonvilleat 24,000 feet. One enemy fighter was claimed to have been destroyed, and one of our Hurricanes had been shot down by theenemy fighters; the pilot had escaped by parachute.Finally, ten minutes after this last combat, a second sectionof Hurricanes had intercepted twelve Messerschmitt 109&apos;s overBriey. The section leader had immediately attacked the enemy fighters, two of which he had shot down in flames.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.The Naval 10.   The First Lord of the Admiralty informed the war situation. Cabinet of the latest movements of the Home Fleet.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 75thConclusions,Minute 2.)
S.S. Altmark. Our Naval Attache at Olso had reported that the Altmark(Previous had sailed from Sandef jord, with a German tug, on the 21st March.Reference:W.M. (40) 64thConclusions,Minute 2.)U-boat activity. On the 25th March H.M. Anti-submarine Trawlers Kirkellaand Bandolero had carried out an attack on an enemy submarinein Barnstaple Bay, with hopeful results.In the early hours of the 26th March the Norwegian S.S. Cometa(3,794 tons) had been torpedoed and sunk 80 miles west of the shetlands, while being taken into Kirkwall for examination. her crew, as well as the armed guard, had been rescued.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,March 27, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
