<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 38-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT      JgPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1945.SECRET.--- Copy No. A (.CP. (45) 155.9th September, 1945.CABINET.REPORT BY THE PRIME MINISTER, CHAIRMAN OF THE INDIA and burma COMMITTEE,AT their meeting on the 2.0th August (CM. (45) 24th Conclusions, Minute 1)the Cabinet agreed that the Viceroy should be invited to return here immediatelyfor discussion of general policy in India. Lord Wavell arrived in this country on the 26th August. Since then he has attended meetings of the India and BurmaCommittee and the whole field of policy has been fully explored.2. I need not trouble my colleagues with the detail of the discussions. Theyhave centred round the desirability of making it clear without further delay thatit is our intention to convene a constitution-making body as envisaged in theCripps offer of 1942 as soon as possible once the results of the forthcoming Indianelections are known.3. The Viceroy at first was doubtful of the wisdom of any public under-taking in this sense. He pointed out that there were many points of detail to be examined and resolved before a constitution-making body could come into being.There was the risk of inflaming communal feeling, particularly during the electionperiod, and in Lord Wavell&apos;s view the major political parties, for different andmutually destructive reasons, might well decline to take part in any constituentassembly. The Congress might decline to particijDate if the principle of the partition of India appeared to be conceded, and the Muslim League unless it was conceded.4. The Committee have made it clear, on the other hand, to the Viceroythat in our view it is quite essential to face whatever risks there may be in thismatter, and to give India and the world a clear indication without further delay of our intentions.   If, when the time comes, it is impossible to persuade
the Indian parties to take part in whatever constitution-making body may beset up, a new situation will arise which we shall have to consider in the light ofthe circumstances. But at least we shall have done our part in giving effect tothe Cripps offer, to the principles of which this Government and its predecessorshave repeatedly asserted their adherence, and if there is a failure it will notbe possible to place the responsibility for it on the shoulders of His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.5. In the : result, and after further discussion with Lord Wavell, werecommend that he should be authorised on his return to India to broadcast anannouncement in the terms of the Annex to this Report, which has been drafted inconsultation with us. The Viceroy would accompany this announcement witha personal message of his own, emphasising its significance, and appealing forco-operation. The feeling of the Committee, which the Viceroy shared, was thatthere would be advantage if I were to make a very brief broadcast in the nameof His Majesty&apos;s Government on the occasion of the Viceroy&apos;s announcement which would affirm in general terms the policy of this Government towards India,and this, if my colleagues so desire, I shall be very willing to do.6. Opportunity will be taken before Lord Wavell leaves this country inthe middle of next week to discuss with him in a general and exploratory waycertain of the difficult issues of detail that will have to be considered in connectionwith the establishment of any constitution-making body.7. On behalf of the Committee I invite the Cabinet to approve the makingby the Viceroy of an announcement in the terms appended hereto,^&apos; and to agreethat this should be accompanied by a short broadcast by myself as Prime Minister.C. R. A.10 downing  Street,9th September, 1945.* Annex.
ANNEX.As stated in the gracious Speech from the Throne at the Opening ofParliament, His Majesty&apos;s Government are determined to do their utmost topromote, in conjunction with the leaders of Indian opinion, the early realisation of full self-government in India. During my visit to London they have discussed with me the steps to be taken.An announcement has already been made that elections to the Central and provincial legislatures, so long postponed owing to the war, are to be held duringthe coming cold weather. Thereafter His Majesty&apos;s Government earnestly hopethat ministerial responsibility will be accepted by political leaders in allProvinces.It is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to convene as soon aspossible a constitution-making body and as a preliminary step they have authorised me to undertake, immediately after the elections, discussions withrepresentatives of the Legislative Assemblies in the Provinces, to ascertain whether the proposals contained in the 1942 declaration are acceptable or whether some alternative or modified scheme is preferable. Discussions will also beundertaken with the representatives of the Indian States wdth a view to ascer-taining in what way they can best take their part in the constitution-makingbody.His Majesty&apos;s Government are proceeding to the consideration of the content of the treaty which will require to be concluded between Great Britainand India.During these preparatory stages, the government of India must be carriedon, and urgent economic and social problems must be dealt with. Furthermore,India has to play her full part in working out the new World Order. HisMajesty&apos;s Government have therefore further authorised me, as soon as the resultsof the Provincial elections are published, to take steps to bring into being an executive Council which will have the support of the main Indian parties.

VIATHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1945.TOP SECRET.CABINET.MEMORANDUM BY- THE LORD  PRESIDENT; OF  THE  COUNCIL,CHAIRMAN OF THE PALESTINE COMMITTEE.I attach the recommendations of the Palestine Committee on the short-term policy to be adopted in that country.2. I would like to put on record the importance of maintaining the utmostsecrecy, both as regards these recommendations and indeed as regards the factthat a Palestine Committee of the Cabinet has been constituted. As my colleagues will appreciate, we may be placed in a very embarrassing position if it becomesknown that there is such a body, and for obvious reasons it is most undesirable that any inkling should get out of the line on which our minds are moving asregards Palestine policy generally.H. M.Privy Council Of/ice, S.W. 1,8th September, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
