<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 70-83</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1945.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of............................v........................&apos;.........Copy No.CABINET.TOP SECRETCP. (45) 159.&amp;h September, 1945.SUMMARY OF NAVAL AIR OPERATIONS-1st MAY to 1st AUGUST, 1945.Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty.Section I. Aircraft Carriers Disposition and Movements.1. Fleet Carriers.H.M.S. Indomitable On the 1st May H.M. Ships Indomitable, Victorious,H.M.S. Victorious Indefatigable and Formidable, forming part of TaskH.M.S. Force 57, sailed from Leyte to open Phase II of Opera-Indefatigable   tion &quot; Iceberg &quot; which, as in Phase I, consisted of the.M.S. Formidable   continuous neutralisation of the Sakishima Gunto insupport of the Okinawa landings.Dawn of the 4th May saw the Task Force in the operating area, and our fighters were soon active indestroying two of a group of enemy aircraft passing wellNorth of the Force. Battleships and cruisers were thendetached to bombard the BZirari and Nobara airfields,which were also subjected to bombing attacks, and considerable damage was caused. During the absenceof the bombarding force, the carriers were attacked byabout 20 aircraft, 8 of which were shot down. Only onemade a successful suicide attack, diving steeply from agreat height on to H.M.S. Formidable. Eight men were killed and forty-seven wounded, but the ship remainedoperational. An evening attack by 5 aircraft was also&apos;thwarted, 3 of them being shot down without loss.Again, the next day, Hirari and Nobara airfields were bombed and an enemy aircraft was shot down. Duringthe two days, the Japanese had lost 18 aircraft destroyed and 4 damaged. We lost 5 aircraft in combat and 11 asa result of the suicide crash.After three days spent on passage and replenishing,the Force returned to the attack on the 9th with strikesat the Miyako and Ishigaki airfields. At noon a largegroup of suicide aircraft attacked the Force. One was destroyed by ships&apos; gunfire and another by fighters, but three made successful crash dives, two on the Victorious,and one on the Formidable. Both ships stood up well tothis punishment and in an hour or so were operationalagain. Ten aircraft were destroyed on the flight decks. and eight badly damaged.[30452] b
Two days were spent in replenishing before the nextstrikes on&quot; the 12th May, when 78 tons of bombs were dropped on the only four airfields found serviceable inthe islands.70 tons dropped on Hirara town and airfield the next day started many fires, including a large oil fire and caused great destruction.After the usual replenishing period, the attack was resumed on the 16th May with 90 tons of bombs on the airfields, which the enemy had been trying hard to repair. The town of Ohama was bombed inadvertentlyand a huge explosion resulted. In addition, ten small ships were destroyed or damaged, and an oil dump andlorries laden with troops were set on fire. Ohama was bombed again the next day, as were all the islands&apos;airfields, and several more small craft were set on fire.In these two days, the enemy lost 4 new aircraft and 2Baka suicide aircraft destroyed and 3 damaged, all onthe ground. We lost 2 Corsairs to flak and 6 aircraft ina bad crash on deck.,While the Force was retiring to the replenishmentarea, a serious fire broke out in the hangar of H.M.S.Formidable. Seven Avengers and twenty-five Corsairswere made unserviceable, but the ship remained in action and took part in the next series of strikes on the 20thand 21st.Fog on the 20th prevented all activity except for onebombing raid on Hirara, which was attacked again thenext day when 60 tons of bombs were dropped on thistown and the airfields. Buildings in the town and portarea suffered considerable damage and several fires were started. One enemy aircraft, a Myrt, was shot down. Our losses were one Corsair in combat and aCorsair and a Hellcat from other causes.The Force then retired to refuel, and on the 22ndHATS. Formidable was detached to proceed to Sydney.The three remaining carriers continued the attack onthe 24th May. 36 tons of&apos; bombs were dropped on that day and 44 the next. Nobara was bombed andstrafed, the town of Sukama was left in flames and allthe airfields were effectively cratered.This ended phase II of operation &quot;Iceberg,&quot; andTask Force 57 withdrew to Sydney for major replenish-nients and to repair action damage. The enemy had lost 12 aircraft in the air and 13 on the ground,bringing his latest assessed losses for the whole operation&quot;Iceberg&quot; so far to 96. Many more aircraft were damaged. We lost 11 aircraft in combat, which broughtour total combat losses up to 30.The success of this operation effectively removedany doubt which may have existed in the American mind of the ability of a British Carrier Task Force to operate in the Pacific. Indeed, the toll taken by the suicidebomber of the more lightly armoured American Carriersled to an increase in the proportionate effort provided by our Carriers, none of which was out of action for morethan a couple of hours, despite the efforts of theKamikaze Corps.By this operation. Task Force 57 made British Navalhistory in that it operated continuously off the enemycoast for nearly thirty days. It can be said that theBritish Task Force effectively carried out its under-taking to neutralise the Sa.kis.him a Gunto.H.M.S. Illustrious      After    completing    temporary    repairs.    H.M.S.Ttttistrlom left Sydney on the 24th May for the UnitedKingdom, where she arrived on the 27th June. She isundergoing a major refit at Rosyth.
H.M.S. Implacable      Completed her working up in the East Indies and early in May joined the British Pacific Fleet. On the14th and 15th June she took part in her first operation against the Japanese, when she and other units of theBritish Pacific Fleet carried out continuous day and night air strikes and bombardments on the oncegreat air and naval base at Truk. H.M.S. Implacable&apos;&amp;aircraft dropped 40 tons of bombs, inflicting damage on shipping, a floating dock, town and harbour facilities,airfields and radio and radar installations. Two enemy aircraft were destroyed on the ground and threedamaged. In all these attacks we lost one Seafire.H.M.S. Implacable returned to Manus from this operation.HM.S. Indomitable On arrival at Sydney from operation &quot; Iceberg,&quot;H.M.S. Formidable ELM. Ships Formidable, Victorious and indefatigableH.M.S. Victorious were taken in hand for repairs to action damage, and h.M.S. H.M.S. Indomitable underwent a short refit. ELM. ShipsIndefatigable Formidable and Victorious had completed repairs by the.M.S. Implacable   22nd June and on the 29th sailed for Manus, whereH.M.S. Implacable already was, followed soon after byH.M.S. Indefatigable. ELM.S. Indomitable did not complete her refit until the 20th July.On the 6th July, ELM. Ships Formidable, Victorious,Indefatigable and Implacable sailed from Manus asTask Force 37 to join the American 3rd Fleet forPhase III of Operation &quot;Iceberg.&quot; On the 17th july the first strikes by British aircraft on the Japanesehomeland were made, with the Northern Tokyo area asthe target. 13 enemy aircraft were destroyed and3 damaged on their airfields. Railways were subjected to many attacks which resulted in the destruction of 3locomotives and damage to installations. Shipping also was attacked, one junk being sunk and 11 other shipsdamaged.51 combat sorties were flown against similar targetsthe following day when 13 more grounded aircraft were destroyed and 25 damaged. Anti-shipping strikesdamaged 24 junks. Further strafing and rocket attacks were made on railways and ground installations.During these two days the enemy lost 26 aircraft destroyed and 28 damaged, while our losses were 5 in combat and 2 from other causes. All the aircrews were saved.A further series of air strikes against Kyusho tookplace at daAvn on the 24th July and during this successfulday we destroyed 21 aircraft and damaged 57 on theground, sank 5 ships and 5 small craft, totalling6.000 tons, probably sank an escort carrier, damaged a destroyer, 11 ships of 30,500 tons and 41 small craft. Welost 8 aircraft to accurate flak but many of the crews were saved.Bad weather limited the effort on the 25th to175 sorties, but still the toll of damage to the enemy rose.5.000 tons of shipping were sunk, and 38,100 tons plus11 small craft were possibly sunk or damaged. Groundinstallations and communications were destroyed and7 enemy aircraft seen on the ground were damaged.Eight enemy aircraft made an ineffective dusk attackon the combined Fleets and lost 3 to Task Force 37 and1 to the American Task Force 38. Our losses for theday were 2 aircraft.The attack was resumed on the Kure-Kobe area onthe 28th and in the face of weakening opposition our aircraft created havoc amongst shipping, airfields andindustrial targets.   The enemy lost 8 aircraft on the[30452] b 2
2. Light Fleet Carriers.H.M.S. ColossusH.M.S. VenerableH.M.S. VengeanceH.M.S. GloryH.M.S. Oceanground and 26 damaged. A destroyer, 12 merchant ships and 17 junks were sunk, 3 merchant ships and 2 luggersprobably sunk, and 3 destroyers, 12 merchant vessels andmany small craft were damaged. In attacks on indus-trial targets, a large warehouse, an oil tank and 4 work-shops were destroyed, while among targets which suffered damage were the Kawasaki aircraft plant, the ports ofFude and secretary, shipyards at Harima and a factory,hangar and radar installations at Nishi Shima. Eight ofour aircraft were lost in combat, but, except for two men,all the crews were saved.H.M.S. King George V and cruisers carried out a successful bombardment of Hamamatsu at midnight onthe 29th.Bad weather on the 30th decreased the air effort whichwas directed against Eastern Honshu, but from the onestrike flown highly satisfactory results were achieved.The enemy lost 5 more aircraft of his fast-dwindling airforce on the ground and 5 were damaged. A lugger was sunk, many small craft probably sunk and 3 destroyers,4 destroyer escorts, an armed trawler and many small ships were damaged.  Our losses are not yet known.The attacks continue.After working up in the Mediterranean, these carrierswere attached early in June to the East Indies Stationfor a further period of training and acclimatisation.They left Trincomalee on the 7th July to join the BritishPacific Fleet arriving at Fremantle on the 16th July.On the 14th May H.M.S. Glory left the UnitedKingdom for the Mediterranean to start working-up.She left Alexandria on the 24th May for the East Indies,where she will complete working up.This ship will be the first British carrier to specialisein the operation of aircraft exclusively at night. Shecommissioned on the 30th June and starts sea trials onthe 1st August.3. Aircraft Maintenance Ships.H.M.S. UnicornThis ship has, throughout the period under review,supported the operations carried out by the BritishPacific Fleet.Joining the British Pacific Fleet in June, this ship is taking part in the support of the third phase of operation &quot; Iceberg.&quot;Similar to H.M.S. Pioneer, HM.S. Perseus corn-missions in August as an aircraft maintenance ship.H.M.S. PioneerH.M.S. Perseus4. Escort Carriers.(i) H.M. Ships Y index and Premier, escorted R.A. 66 from the 27th Aprilwhen it left Kola until the 8th May when it reached the United Kingdom.J.W. 67 left the United Kingdom on the 14th May protected by H.M.S. Queen,and it arrived safely at Kola on the 20th. The return convoy R.A. 67, againprotected by H.M.S. Queen, arrived in the United Kingdom on the 30th May,having left Kola on the 23rd. In contrast to the determined enemy air. attacks in February and U-boat attacks in March and early April, these convoys, the lastRussian convoys of the war, had safe and unmolested passages. In all, 75 shipsreached their destinations without loss.(ii) On the 4th May a notable attack was made by aircraft from HM. ShipsSearcher, Trumpter and Queen on U-boat depot ships at Kilbotn in the LofotenIslands. In the face of heavy flak, a striking force of 16 Avengers, escorted by 28 Wildcats dived on their targets, released their bombs and broke awayout to sea. Hit by 8 bombs and near-missed by at least 5 more, the Black Watch,the large U-boat depot ship, exploded violently and sank. A 250-ton U-boatseen alongside the Black Watch at the start of the attack was not seen again.A supply ship was left burning. furiously and sinking. A flak cruiser, theHarold Haarfagre, which had sent up intense light and heavy A.A. fire
throughout the attack, was silenced and set on fire. The complete success ofthis operation was a fitting ending to the Home Fleet offensive operations in theEuropean War and the result may well have helped to persuade the german naval High Command that the continuation of U-boat warfare from Norwaywas not worth while.On their return from this operation these carriers covered the passage of units of the Home Fleet to Copenhagen.(iii) Six operations against the Japanese have been mounted by escortcarriers of the East Indies Fleet.Two operations, &apos;,&apos; Dracula &quot; and &quot; Bishop,&quot; formed part of the amphibiousassault on Rangoon on the 2nd May, 1945.H.M. Ships Empress and Shah in company with battleships and cruisers of the East Indies Fleet left Trincomalee on the 27th April for Operation&quot; Bishop.&quot; The main object was to maintain a position near the AndamanIslands and prevent any enemy surface interference with the assault convoys and landings, but the Force Commander was given a free hand to plan andexecute minor operations calculated to confuse and discomfort the enemy. Itwas therefore decided to interfere with any possible Japanese attempt to baseaircraft on the Andamans and Nicobars, and also to destroy all shipping foundin that area. Between the 30th April and the 7th May continuous air strikes and bombardments were launched against the Andamans, Nicobars and theTenasserim coast. Airfields were the chief targets and were severely damaged,though several successful attacks were also made on port and harbour facilities,radar stations and other installations. The only two enemy aircraft seen were damaged. Little shipping was encountered, but five small ships were sunk and twelve other small craft damaged. In the 154 sorties flown we lost only one aircraft.While these minor operations were in progress the assault convoys had sailed from Kyauk Pyu on the 30th April, covered by H.M. Ships Hunter, Stalker,Khedive and Emperor, to effect the landings at Rangoon operation &quot; Dracula.&quot;No opposition was met on passage and the landings took place as planned on the2nd May. On that day Naval aircraft flew 110 sorties giving fighter cover and close support to the troops on the beaches. Due to the lack of enemy air oppo-sition, our carriers were released on the 4th May, so the opportunity was taken toattack the Tenasserim coast. Successful air strikes were made in the Merguiarea on the 5th and were continued in the Victoria Point area until noon on the6th when bad weather prevented any further flying. Damage was inflicted ondock and warehouse areas, jetties were destroyed and radar stations and barrackswere bombed and strafed. Seven small ships, including an oil-carrying junk, were sunk and several barges and lighters were damaged. 282 sorties were flown andnot one of our aircraft was lost in combat.A Japanese Nachi Class cruiser having been sighted at sea by a submarine,H.M. Ships Emperor, Hunter, Khedive and Shah were ordered to carry out asearch. On the 15th May the target was sighted by an aircraft of 851 squadron and was attacked shortly afterwards by 3 Avengers with 500-lb. bombs. Oneprobable hit and one near miss are claimed. The cruiser was sunk the next day by our destroyers.In preparation for forthcoming operations, aircraft from H.M. Ships Stalker,Khedive and Ameer carried out a photographic reconnaissance of areas in southern Malaya on the 18th, 19th and 20th June. All the priority targets were completely covered and excellent results were obtained. The operation was com-pleted on the 20th with strikes by 21 Hellcats on Medan and by 8 sea fires onLhoksemawi. Three enemy aircraft were destroyed, seven probably destroyed and nine damaged, all on the ground. In addition, runways, airfield buildings,locomotives and wagons were bombed and strafed and two junks were set on fire.One Hellcat was lost.From the 5th to the 11th July, H.M. Ships Ameer and Emperor gave fighterprotection to a minesweeping operation off Car Nicobar and the Force took theopportunity to carry out air strikes and bombardments on neighbouring targets.AH small craft seen were rendered unseaworthy, buildings were set on fire andradar and D/F stations were put out of action. Four aircraft were lost to flakbut all the pilots were recovered. Despite heavy rain squalls, an air strike andbombardment were made on Nancowry on the 7th July. Fires and explosionswere caused and two coasters were left on fire. Two Hellcats were shot down butthe pilot of one was saved. The airfields at Kotaraja and Ldonga were bombed[30452] e 3
and strafed by 24 Hellcats on the 11th. No aircraft were seen on the ground buta Dinah was destroyed in combat. The pilot of the only aircraft lost wasrecovered. -. H.M. Ships Ameer and Empress protected a.similar minesweeping operationoff the West coast of Malaya between the 19th and 27th July. One of the mine-sweepers was sunk after striking a mine on the 24th, and on the morning of the26th suicide aircraft attacked the force. One was shot down by H.M.S. Ameer&apos;sgunfire. H.M.S. Sussex and the minesweeper H.M.S. Vestal were both hit.H.M.S. Sussex was holed above the waterline and H.M.S. Vestal was sunk. Onlya few casualties were caused.During the day our aircraft carried out widespread attacks in theKra Isthmus, destroying or damaging-15 locomotives, damaging 14 small ships and 4 harbour craft and disorganising railway communications. In an attackon Songei Patani airfield, 6 enemy aircraft were destroyed, 3 set on fire and2 damaged.   We lost one Hellcat.(iv) The Escort Carrier Eorce of the East Indies Fleet has been furtherconsiderably strengthened during this period by the addition of the assaultcarriers Attacker, Pursuer and Searcher and the ferry carrier Activity.H.M. Ships Smiter and Trumpeter arrived on the East Indies Station on the26th July, where they will take part in forthcoming operations before joining theBritish Pacific Fleet. There are now nine assault carriers, three general purposecarriers and two ferry carriers in the East Indies Fleet.(v) The six replenishment carriers of the British Pacific Fleet, H.M. ShipsArbiter, Speaker, Slinger, Striker, Chaser and Ruler have been actively employedin maintaining supplies of aircraft, aircrews and material to the Fleet carriers intheir attacks on the Sakishima Gunto and the main Japanese islands. H.M.S.Fencer has been refitting at Simonstown since mid-June.(vi) Of the escort carriers ferrying under United States command, onlyH.M.S. Atheling is now so employed, H.M.S. Ranee having been released in June,followed by H.M. Ships Rajah and Tracker in July.. (vii) Training duties during this period have been shared between HM.Ships Ravager, Battler, Premier and Puncher, and they have qualified 452 pupilsand&quot; given refresher courses to 26 others. H.M.S. Puncher, the Canadian-mannedtraining carrier, visited Canada in July to give leave, and returns to the UnitedKingdom in August to continue deck-landing training.(viii) H.M.S. Pretoria Castle continues in active employment as the trialscarrier.5. M.A.C. Ships.Fifteen ships, two sailing under the Dutch flag, were operating at thebeginning of this period in defence of Atlantic Convoys. With the end of the warin Germany and the final surrender of the U-Boats, these Merchant aircraft carriers were enabled to return to normal trading, the last one, Empire Mackay,being released on the 28th June. It is interesting to note that the flight of aSwordfish from that ship on the 27th June was the last operational flight of abiplane of the Naval Air Arm.Section II.-Detached Naval Squadrons Operating from Shore Bases.6. 810 and 822 Squadrons, which had been left under the orders of coastal command on the release of the other Naval Air Squadrons in order to combat themenace of enemy small battle units in the Channel, operated for the first fortnightof the period under review. Despite the 141 sorties flown, these squadrons wereunfortunate in not securing any sightings.A. V. A.Admiralty, &amp;th, September, 1945.




APPENDIX I.Wastage February, March, April, 1945.Losses of Naval Aircraft incurred during period February, March, April, 1945.Reports received up to and including 31st July 1945.Type.Operational Squadrons.Squadrons working up.Training and Ancillary.IT.B.R.5.S.F.iS.F.;:A B.K.Total Operational.   Types   ......Non-operationalTypes   ...Total......Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-eentage of strength.	i Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.	Total Wastage.	Strength.	Average monthly wastage as per-centage of strength.100 158 13	375 622 35 6	8-9 8-5 12-4	10 17 2 1	59   ;     5-7 145   1     3-9 13        3-5 5        6-7		120        427 75   ;     306 22          92 4   1      22		9-4 8-2 8-0 6-1271	1,038	8-7         30		228	4-4	!                1 221   i     847   j     8-7				...			481		1,851   j     8-7	271	1,038	8-7	30	228   j    4-4		702     2,698 i		8-7m
APPENDIX II.Wastage February, March, Apeil, 1945.Losses of Naval Aircraft incurred during period February, March, April, 1945.   Reports received up to and including 2,1st July,Aircraft.	First Line.					Training and Ancillary.						Operational Types.					Operational Types.				Non-Opera-tional Types.	Total.	T.B.R.	S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R. and L.R.	Total.	T.B.R.	S.S.F.	2 S.F.	A.B.R. and L.R.	Miscellaneous.	(a) Lost or missing in operational flying (b) Destroyed on  ground or on H.M. Ships by enemy action (c) Lost in ships whilst in transit (d) Written off charge owing to accident       ... (e) Written off charge owing to age, reduction to spares, &amp;c.        ...      ...      ... (/) Unclassified     ......      ...... Totals        ...      ...	38 60 11 1	46 1 117 11	4 9 1 1	... 1	88 1 187 23 2	65 55	i i ! 1 1 i     &quot; 53            18 . 22     j       4 i		4	122 357 2	262 438 2	no	175	15              1		301	120     1     75 i		22	4	481	702note.-Written reports have not yet been received in respect of 97 of the items included in above tables. These have been included in the appropriate groupswhere possible.   Certain cases included in group (d) may belong to group (a), since some accidents are subsequently shown to be attributed to enemy action.APPENDIX III.Casualties to Naval Flying Personnel, 1st May-Z\st July, 1945.Operational. Killed.     Missing.    Prisoner of War.Officers.........      13 3 2Ratings.........       3 3 ...16 6 2A ccidental.Officers......      ... .    90Ratings.........      21



</content>
</cab>
