<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 116-127</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).SECRETCP. (45) 1671QTH SEPTEMBER.  19^5.BANK OP ENGLAND bill memorandum, by the Chancellor of the exchequer attach a draft of a Bill to &quot;bring the Bank, of Englandunder- public ownership.    Normally this Bill would have &quot;been examined &quot;by the Lord Presidentrs Committee before submission tothe Cabinet, hut, in view of the need for an early decision,having regard to the Parliamentary time-table and the hybridnature of the Bill, I have consulted the Lord President, whohas agreed that this memorandum should come direct to theCabinet.2.      Clause 1 provides that the existing capital stock of theBank, amounting to  1 L\,553*000, shall be acquired &quot;by the Treasuryfrom the stockholders in return for&apos; 39b Government Stock of suchamount that &quot;the sum payable annually &quot;by way of interest thereonis equal to the average annual gross dividend declared duringthe period of twenty years immediately preceding the31st, March, 19^5.&quot;Sub-clause (L)  gives the Treasury the right to redeem thestock at any time after 31st March, 1966:    subject to that, thestock will be perpetual.    Thus, the stockholders will, at anyrate for 20 years, receive the same income, neither more norless,  than they have received in recent years. As regards&apos;capitalvalues, it is thought that the market value of the Government Stockto he issued to owners of existing Bank Stock will he roughlythe same as the present price of Bank Stock.    (The average priceof Bank Stock over the six months to 30th June last was 383)*I;   3*      Clause 2 provides that on the appointed day the presentCourt of Directors,  consisting of a Governor, a Deputy GovernorI   and twenty-four Directors, shall give place to a new Court of a governor, two Deputy Governors and sixteen Directors, allI   appointed &quot;by His Majesty.    Detailed provisions ahout terms ofI   office, etc. are in the Second Schedule to the Bill.COPY NO.hrtCABINET

3*      Clause k   suh-clause (1)  confers on the Treasury the widest possible powers to give directions to the Bank ofEngland, if such directions are. necessary. - We may hope, andexpect, that resort to such formal directions will he very exceptional,,    It is intended that this power&apos; should he usedin relation to issues of policy and that (as is indicated &quot;by sub--clause (2))  the day-to-day management of the Hank by theCourt of Directors will not he interfered, with.Sub-clause (3) is designed to give the Bank of England,with the support of the Treasury, power of control over thecommercial hanks...    Here again it may he hoped that the powers will not have to he formally used, hut, if necessary, theywill give control over such matters as the credit policies of the .hanks..(intld)    H.D.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1.10TH SEPTEMBER,   1945.

SECRETA I&apos;T N E XDRAFT.OF    ABILLTOBring the Bank of England under public control,to make provision for regulating bankingoperations: and for purposes connected with, thepurposes aforesaid.Be it enacted, etc.Transfer of 1.-     (1) On the appointed, day -Bank stockTo Treasury.(a) the whole of the existing capitalstock of the Bank of England (here-herein after  referred to as &quot;Bank Stock1&apos;)shall, by virtue of this section,be transferred to such person asthe Treasury may nominate, andshall bo held by that person onbehalf of the Treasury free of alltrusts, liabilities and incurobrances;(b) the Treasury -shall issue, to every person who immediately before theappointed day is registered in the books of the said Bank as the holderof any Bank stock,  the equivalentamount of stock created by them forthe purpose (hereinafter referred toas the &quot;government stock&quot;).(2) The government stock shall bear interest at the rate of three per cent per annum;    and the equivalent amount of the government stock shall, inrelation to any person, be taken to be such thatthe sum payable annually 037- way of interest thereonis equal to the average annual gross dividenddeclared during the period of twenty years immediately preceding the thirty-first day of March,nineteen hundred and forty-five upon the amount of bank stock of which that person was the registeredholder immediately before the appointed day.(3)    The interest upon the government stockshall be charged on and issued out of the consolidated Fund of the United Kingdom or the growing produce thereof.

(4)    The government stock may he redeemed atpar by the Treasury at any time after the thirty-first day of March, nineteen hundred and sixty-sixafter giving not less than three months&apos;&apos; notice inthe London Gazette of their intention to do so.(5)    -he Treasury may, for the purpose ofproviding any sums required by them in order to redeem the government stock, raise money in anymanner in which they are authorised to raisemoney under the National Loans Act,  1939, and anysecurities created and issued to raise money underthif.subsection shall he deemed to have been created and issued under this Act.(6)   No dividends shall he paid on the Bankstock in respect of any period after it has beentransferred under subsection (1) of this section:but in lieu of any such dividends the Bank shall pay to the Treasury,  in respect of the yearbeginning with the&apos; appointed day and each sub-sequent year,  the sum   of    1,746,360or such less or greater stun as may from  -time to time be agreed upon between the treasury and the Bank,Any sum paid to the Treasury under this subsection shall be paid into the Exchecuer.Oourt ofdirectorsof Bank ofEngland.(7)    The incidental and supplementalprovisions set out in the First Schedule to thisAct shall have effect with respect to thegovernment stock.2.-. i-vi) On the appointed day, all persons who are,immediately before that day, members of the courtof directors of the Bank of England shall vacatetheir office,  and on. and after that day the court shall consist of a Governor, two Deputy governors and sixteen directors.(2) The Governor, Deputy Governors anddirectors shall be appointed by His Majesty.(3)   A quorum of the court shall consistof not less than eight directors, together withthe Govei-nor or one Deputy Governor, and when a quorum is present the court may act notwithstanding that a vacancy exists among the members of thecourt.(a) The provisions of the Second Schedule tothis Act shall have effect as respects the tenure of office and qualifications of members of thecourt of directors.-(5) hotemployed, toaoreivcone irn four of the directors may beexclusive services to the

C o nae quenti a1provisionsas to consti-tution of bank ofEngland.3..-      ,--(1 ) On the appointed day the chartersof the Bank of England&apos; and any byelaws inforce thereunder shall, Toy virtue of this sup-section, be revoked, but the revocation there-of shall not affect the existence of theGovernor and Company of the Bank of Englandas a corporation incorporated by Royal Charter,and the members of the corporation shall be themembers of the court of directors for the time&quot;being together with, the person who holds thecapital stock of the Bank on behalf of theTreasury.(2) Subject to the provisions of thisAct, the Bank of England shall be constitutedand regulated in accordance with such chartersas&quot; may from time to time be granted by HisMajesty arid accepted on behalf of the Bank bythe court of directors.Treasurydirectionsto Bank ofEngland andrelations of bank ofEnglandwith otherBanks.li.- . -(1) The Treasury may from time to timegive such, directions to the Bank of England as,after consultation with the Governor of theBank, they think necessary in the publicinterest.(2) Subject to any such directions,  the affairs of the Bank shall be managed by thecourt of. directors in accordance with suchruleif any.as ma?be laid down by the charter of the Bank and any byelaws made there under.(3) The Bank of England may,  either in-fur the ranee of such directions or otherwise,request information from, and make recommendations to, banks in regard to banking-operations, and the Treasury may, if theythink it expedient in the public interest,make such regulations and give such directions as they think, necessary for the purpose ofsecuring that any such request or recommendation is carried out.(h)    In this section the expression &quot;bank&quot;means any person carrying on an undertaking which the Treasury by order declare to be abanking undertaking for the purposes of thissection.appointed day.puz;e of this Act the aooointed5.     For theday shall beorder determine, not being later than / threesuch day as the Treasury may bymonths from the day of^/ the thirty-firsthundred and forty-sispa ssiiarch,rig of this Act/nineteenShorttitle.6,Act,This Act1945.dcthe Bank of Englant

FIRST SCHEDULE/&quot;&quot;Ancillary provisions as to registration, trgjisfen?etc^_of Government secur 1 tics. J&quot;^SEOOHD SCHEDULESupplementary P^rovisiqns as to Court of Directors1.     The term-of office of the Governor shall befive years,  and the terra of office of the DeputyGovernors shall be four years.2.      The term of office of the directors shall be four years, and. four of them shall, retire each year on the anniversary of the appointed, day:Provided, that,  of the directors appointed to takeoffice.on the appointed day, four shall be appointedto hold office until, the first anniversary of that day and shall then retire, four shall be appointed to hold office until the second, anniversary of that day andshallthen retire, and four shall be appointed to hold office until the third anniversary of that day andshall then retire,3*     A person who has held office as Governor, deputy governor or cVirector shall be eligible for re-appointment.I+.     A person shall be disqualified for holding theoffice of Governor, Deputy Governor or director if -(a) he is a Member of the Commons House ofParliament or a person holding an officeof profit under the Crown;    or(b) he is subject to any disqualificationwhich may be imposed by the charter ofthe Bank,and a person shall vacate any such office if hobecomes subject to any such disqualification.5. Where the office of a director is vacated underthe foregoing paragraph, or by death or resignation, aperson appointed to fill the vacancy shall hold, officeuntil the time when the person in whose place he wasappointed would, regularly have retired, and shall thenretire.


</content>
</cab>
