<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 214-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovernmentPrinted for the Cabinet, September, 1945TOP secret copy No. 81CP. (45) 17518th September, 19451:The circulation  of this  paper  has  been strictly   limited.    It   is  issued   for   the personal use ofCABINETARMY RELEASES AND MANPOWER IN 1946NOTE BY THE PARLIAMENTARY UNDER-SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR1. I attach a Memorandum containing (a) a Review of the Release Programmebased on the Chiefs of Staff revised assessment of military commitments at 30th June,1940, and (6) a note on intakes needed in January to June, 1946.2. Briefly, the conclusions are that by next June the Army can release a total ofabout 1,895,000 men and 163,000 women, i.e., approximately 455,000 more men and52,000 more A.T.S. than was estimated before the defeat of Japan, an increase of over half a million. Thus within a year of Releases starting the Army will have been reducedby nearly f of its strength at the end of hostilities in Europe.3. While retaining the Age and Service principles of Release, the limiting factor in the rate of release is the transport available with which to bring back personnel from overseas theatres. The most recent survey of the transport situation shows that in addi-tion to the acceleration in releases of 110,000 men and 28,000 women in 1945, to whichI have already agreed it will now be possible (subject to the provision in time of theadditional transport recommended by the Defence Committee on 14th September) tocomplete the release of Group 23 (men) this year; this will mean the release of a further88,000 men in Class &quot; A     in 1945.4. If the principle of equality between those at home and overseas is abandoned, therate of release at home could be increased in 1945, although at the expense of disorgani-zation in the form of delay in the issue of pay, allowances, and civilian clothing. Themilitary view is that such a course, however, would be regarded by the Army as acomplete breach of faith. Moreover, a telegram had just been received from the Secre-tary of State for War&apos;s Private Secretary which reads &quot; S. of S. spoken to troops in cairo. Pledged Government would maintain Bevin scheme and not release men athome before equivalent men from overseas &quot;. (This statement was made before themeeting of the Defence Committee on 14th September.)5. In order to fulfil the estimated operational commitments as at 1st January,1947, and on the assumption that releases must continue after June, 1946, the intake of men required in January to June, 1946 is 235,900.The reason for such a large demand is that I regard it of the greatest importance for the reasons set out in Part II of the Memorandum that the tour of conscribed service should be reduced as quickly as possible to a maximum of 5 years.6. The intakes for women, N.A.A.F.I., civilians and doctors needed in january to June, 1946, are set out in paras. 18-21 of the Memorandum. A separate memorandum is also being submitted to the Ministerial Committee on the subject of Medical Officers.7. I ask that the process of dereservation in industry should be carried to thefurthest possible extent so that the intake required by the Army is provided and therelease of. long service men may be facilitated; this was the policy set out clearly in para. 8 of the White Paper, Cmd. 6548, of September, 1944.N. of C.The War Office,18th September, 1945.
ARMY RELEASES AND REVIEW OF MANPOWER IN 19461. The size of the Forces required at 30th June, 1946; for Stage HI, has now beenreassessed as a result of the defeat of Japan, and approved by the Chiefs of Staff.In the light of its revised commitments,: a review has been made of the manpowerposition of the Army which is dealt with in this Paper under two headings:  Part I Programme of Releases from June, 1945 to June, 1946.Part II Survey of Manpower Problems in the Period July to December, 1946,with special reference to the intake required in January to June, 1946.part   IProgramme of Releases from June, 1945 to 30TH June, 1946Introduction.2. For convenience the release programme is divided into the two periods:  (a) 18th June, 1945 (6 weeks after V.E., when releases started) to 31st December,1945-(6) 1st January to 30th June, 1946.Prior to the defeat of Japan, the Army planned to release under Class &quot; A &quot;:  Men.      A.T.S.June to December, 1945............      468,000      47,000January to June, 1946............      972,000      58,000Total      ...............    1,440,000    105,000This would have left the required numbers available for commitments then assessedfor Stage II at 30th June, 1946, at:-Men...............      .........      1,360,000A.T.S. ..................... 90,000Total ............      ......      1,450,000Revised Estimate of Releases from June, 1945 to June, 1946.3. (a) The revised commitments of the Army at 30th June, 1946, will require thefollowing trained personnel:  (thousands)Men..................      ......      1,029-9A.T.S..........      ............... 47-oNurses   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... 4-25Total.....................      1,081-15The above figures exclude those under training at 30th June, 1946, as the intake tothe Forces during January to June, 1946, has not yet been decided.In the case of men, the commitment includes some 17,000 British personnel requiredfor the Indian Army.(&amp;) The strength of the Army at 18th June, 1945, when release started, was asfollows:  (thousands)Men      ........................      2,962-4A.T.S.........................        197-7Nurses........................ 10-5Total ...      ...      ...............      3,170-6(c) The gross surpluses are arrived at by deducting the commitments at 30th June,1946, from the strength at i8th June, 1945; certain adjustments must, however, bemade to these figures for the following factors:  (i) Intakes in July to December, 1945.(ii) Taking on strength of P.O.W. from the Far East.(hi) Wastage during July, 1945 to June, 1946, in so far as it occurs among those not due for release by 30th June, 1946.
(iv) Class &quot; B &quot; releases again in so far as they are found from those not due forClass &quot; A &quot; release by 30th June, 1946. It has been assumed that of thetotal of 77,000 Class &quot; B &quot; releases which the Army is expected to find,53,000 will come from men in Groups 1-31 and 24,000 from men in Groups32 and later. No reasonable estimate can yet be made of the result of futureClass &quot; B &quot; offers-since there is no guide to the effect of the improved termsnow to be given.(v) The gross releases represent a bulk surplus and it would not be possible to achieve the release of the exact totals for the following reasons:  (a) The incidence of release falls unevenly on the various Arms resulting ina surplus in some and a deficit in others.(&amp;) Surpluses and deficiencies between Arms can only be adjusted wheremen are fit and suitable for retraining and remustering; large numbersof men are not fit or suitable to be so transferred.(c) The Army is dispersed in five major areas and many smaller ones, andreleases do not fall on them in such a way as to reduce them by 30thJune, 1946, to their several commitments at that date.It is therefore necessary, in the case of men, to retain a marginout of the bulk surplus to ensure that the commitments at 30th June,1946, are filled with efficient men. This is assessed at 80,000. Nosuch margin is needed in the case of A.T.S.4. The application of the above adjustments is shown in the following table:  	Gross Surplus	Intakes July to December, 1945	Wastage in Strength NOT due ; for Release	Estimated Class &quot;B&quot; Releases from those remaining after June, 1946	Margin for Deficiencies between Arms and Theatres	Available for ReleasesMen A.T.S.     ... Nurses	1,932,500 150,700 6,250	4-io6,8oo(a) +   7.5oo +420	-40,000 - 1,200 -430	-24,000 Nil Nil	-80,000 Nil Nil	1,895,300 157,000 6,2405. The tables at Appendix &quot; A &quot; for men and A.T.S. and Appendix &quot; B &quot; forNurses, show the plan for releases proposed up to 30th June, 1946, to achieve the netreleases in para. 4 above.  This is based on:  (a) Adherence to the Age and Service Group principle of priority for release.(6) Release in U.K. within the periods shown of personnel of all ranks and tradesfrom all theatres in each Age and Service Group.The increase in releases by 30th June, 1946, made possible as a result of the revisedassessment of commitments is as follows:  Releases from 18th June, 1945 to 30th June, 1946	Previous Estimate	Revised Estimate	Increase	Percentage of IncreaseMen     ...... A.T.S....... Total Nurses......	1,440,000 105,000	1,895,300 157,000	455,300 52,000	31.6 49-5	1,545,000	2,052,300	507.300	32-8	No estimate made	6,240	not applicable	not applicable(a) Includes 38,800 ex-P.O.W. (Far East).(23753) a 2
Plan of Release in 1945.6. Immediately after the defeat of Japan and without awaiting a reassessment; of commitments or of gross releases by June) 1946, it was agreed that Class A &apos;.&apos; releasesup to December, 1945, should be increased by 110,000 men and 28,000 A.T.S. this involved the release of Groups 1-22 (plus one-quarter of Group 23) men, and Groups1-34 A.T.S., which programme, with dates, has been announced to the public.The additional transport capacity for releases as recommended by the DefenceCommittee on 14th September, if obtained in time, should make possible the release ofthe whole of male Group 23 this year, i.e., an additional 88,706 men.The release plan in Appendix &quot; A &quot; assumes that this transport will be so available.Groups 1-23 (men) total 706,100, but these will not all materialize as Class &quot; A &quot;releases some will be discharged to civil life (wastage), and others will have left theService under Class &quot; B &quot;.Possibility of Further Acceleration in Release.7. When the release of a Group is ordered, all men ready for release in that Groupgo as soon as possible. Men at home do not wait until those in the same Group from overseas arrive in U.K. This in itself may constitute, in the large Groups, a substantialadvantage for men at home. Consideration has been given to the possibility of extendingthis process by bracketing together two or more release groups over a period of 4 to 8weeks, and thus accelerating the release of those in the Groups who were ready to go,that is, those at home. It would not, however, be possible to bring all men home from overseas to participate in this acceleration, unless further transport is made available.Any such combining of release groups would certainly be regarded by those over-seas as a device to accelerate out of their turn the release of those who. happen to be athome, and would be a breach of the principle of equality in release between those athome and overseas both in spirit and in fact.Position in U.K.8. Every effort is being made to reduce commitments in U.K. as quickly aspossible As a result of this, considerable numbers of men will become surplus without reference to and before the due date of their release group, and it will not be practicable to post them overseas.In addition, the effect of the Python Scheme and compassionate postings to U.K.is to bring home large numbers of men who have served long periods overseas but arenot yet due for release.Such a position is inevitable in U.K. which is the Army&apos;s Base, and the centre forthe dispersal of personnel under the Release Scheme.The accumulation of men nearly due for release is inherent in any orderly schemeof release which is not directly related to a reduction of commitments.While the Age and Service principle is retained there is no way of releasing thesurplus in U.K. without breaking faith with men overseas.Position in Overseas Commands.9. The commitments of all theatres at 30th June, 1946, with the exception of middle East, show considerable reductions from their present strength, but the rundowncan only be made gradually owing to the tasks with which the Armies are faced in theearly stages of occupation necessitating the temporary employment of large numbers ofmen.  Such tasks are:  (a) Withdrawal of Allied Prisoners of War.(6) Protection of Displaced Persons.(c) Guarding of military equipment, captured enemy equipment and civil instal-lations.(d) Distribution of food, fuel and clothing, and rehabilitation of transport andpublic utility services.If further transport beyond that recommended by the Defence Committee becomes available any acceleration of releases would have to take these factors into account; theyhave been taken into account in the programme of releases now planned.
Consideration has been given to the question whether, within the existing transportcapacity, more men for release could be brought home if other claims were reduced; this,however, would entail the postponement of men coming home after long service overseas(Pvthon) and leave personnel. In view of the important effect on morale which both these factors exert, it is unacceptable to increase releases at their expense.Officers.10. No difference between officers and other ranks has been made in the applicationof the Release Scheme.There was, however, a shortage of officers before releases began, and the incidence of Age and Service falls more heavily on officers than other ranks in the release groupsdue during the first year of operating the scheme.The situation is, therefore, arising where there are insufficient officers to fill the establishments required for the strength of other ranks. Every possible economy inofficers is being made, but it will be inevitable that officers in certain Arms will be heldback temporarily after they are due for release, under the clause in the Army ReleaseRegulations which confers the power on Commanders to take such action.Administration.n. If circumstances arise which make an acceleration of release possible, a warning of 9 weeks is essential for overseas theatres to effect a change in the numbers withdrawnfrom units and assembled at ports for embarkation. Disorganization in the form of delay in the issue of pay, allowances and civilian clothing would also have to be accepted,12. Conclusions.i. Quantity of Reduction.(a) The present release plan provides for the reduction of the Army by the middleof 1946 to the size which the Chiefs of Staff have determined for that date.This is a reduction of over 63 per cent.(&amp;) The reduction planned is over 500,000 more (men and women) than it was planned to be before the end of the Japanese war an increase of 33 percent, over the earlier plan. Of this total increase, over 220,000 will be released this year.2. Rate of Reduction. The average weekly rate of Army releases planned for thelast quarter of 1945 is now 43,500, and for the first six months of 1946 is 49,200.The only factor which prevents a faster rate of release this year is lack of transport to bring men home in time to be released witii their groups. If more transport beyond that recommended by the Defence Committee is found this year, and adequate notice ofthis given, the rate can be increased. If not, it can only &quot;be increased by introducingdifferent rates of release for those at home and abroad.3. Publicity. It is considered that the publication of the above facts and figures,as well as of the figures mentioned below, if no security or other objection to this exists,would do much to allay anxiety in the Army and the country on the question of release.The further information which it is suggested should be given is:  (i) Total size of the Army at 1st July, 1946.(ii) Full programme of release by groups and dates up to 1st July, 1946.(23753)B
PART IISurvey of Manpower Problems in the period July to December, 1946, withspecial reference to the Intake Required in January to June, 1946Introduction.13. Only a small reduction is envisaged in the Army&apos;s commitments at 1st January, 1947,compared with 30th June, 1946; for the purpose of this Memorandum this reduction is assumed to be 130,000 men. In addition, we should in this period be able to dispense withthe margin of 80,000 men referred to in paragraph 3.The reduction above will permit freleases to continue only to a limited extent and additional intakes are therefore necessary: -(a) To offset normal wastage, and a small loss which may be expected from casualties in local operations the total wastage for July to December, 1946, is assessed at24,000.(5) To ensure that there is a reasonable limit to the total length of service of those menwho will not have been released by 30th June, 1946.This problem is examined in detail below.Position at the End of the Emergency.14. With the end of hostilities it is most desirable that there should be some limit onthe tour of conscribed service.Such a limit would be legally imposed if the end of the Emergency was declared, thusterminating all duration engagements.There is, as yet, no indication as to when this may take place, but as it doubtless dependsnot only on purely service considerations, it may well happen at a time when military commitments are greatly in excess of the projected size of the Post-War Army. legislation in the form of a new National Service Act would, therefore, be required to retain in the Armyon some form of new engagement enough men to cover commitments.As the Post-War Army will take some years to build up, it is intended shortly to publish the terms of service. If we are to attract the necessary number of recruits it is desirable, ifnot, indeed, essential that the period of colour service should not exceed 5 years.15. Now that hostilities have ceased it would be unreasonable to hold the war-timeconscript for a period longer than the new Regular engagement; his tour of duty oughtreally to be shorter.It is, therefore, essential that the tour of service of duration engagements should bereduced as quickly as possible to a maximum of 5 years. When a new National service act is introduced, as few men as possible then still serving on duration engagements shouldbe retained; certainly those who will then have more than 5 years conscribed service willhave a very strong claim to be released.Composition in Length of Service of the Army, July to December, 1946.16. The strength of the Army at 1st July, 1946 (1,110,000, consisting of men in Groups32 and later and Regular Soldiers) will include a considerable number of men who by thattime will have had over 5 years&apos; service, some having over 6 years. Large numbers of theseare men who joined the Army under 19 years of age, who will virtually have to make a freshstart in civil life.By 31st December, 1946, with no further releases after July, 1946, there would be inthe Army no less than 197,100 men with more than 5 years service ; 56,600 of these wouldhave had more than 6 years.Without departure from the &quot;Age and Service&quot; basis, which should be maintained, itis not possible to release men merely on length of service. In order to ensure that those with long service are not retained, it is necessary to release the whole of the groups in whichthey are serving.The Groups containing the 197,100 men with over 5 years service are 32-43 inclusive.It will, therefore, be seen that to release all those with more than 5 years service,without departing from the Age and Service principle, it would be necessary to release inthe period July to December, 1946, the whole of these Groups.   They total 421,900
Assessment of Intake Required.17. The intake required in January to June, 1946 (i.e., becoming trained in July toDecember, 1946), to reduce the maximum tour of service by December, 1946, to 5 years is: Total numbers in Groups 32-43 inclusive covering all men with morethan 5 years service at 31st December, 1946     ... 421,900Add Wastage (para. 13(a))     ...:     ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       24,000Total    ...      ...      ......      ......      ...      ...     445,900.Deduct reduction in commitments (para.-13)        ...      ...      ...      ...      130,000Deduct margin of 80,000 retained at 30th June, 1946, no longer required       80,000Total   ...      ...      ...      ...      ......      ...      ...     210,000Intake required...       ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     235,900Intakes of A.T.S.18. It is desirable that A.T.S. releases should continue after June, ^46, and wastagewill also have to be met. Against this there will be some reduction in A.T.S. commitments,but this has not yet been determined.Voluntary recruiting should not be stopped, and a tentative estimate of the requiredintake during January to June, 1946, is 7,500.Intakes of Nurses.19. In order to bring home the large numbers of nurses who have completed long toursof overseas service, for whom there are no replacements available in U.K., an intake of 600is required.in January to June, 1946. This will also facilitate the continuation of releasesafter June, 1946.Intakes of Doctors.20. A separate review of the position of medical officers is being submitted to the ministerial Committee on Manpower: this will show that an intake of 600 is required during January to June, 1946.Intakes of Civilians.21. The estimated requirement during January to June, 1946, of Industrial and non-Industrial civilians other than for N.A.A.F.I. is being examined.N.A.A.F.I. have stated their needs in January to June, 1946, at: Non-IndustrialIndustrialMale.10,625Female.80 \ plus 13,0006,900 J   wastageTotal30,605Summary of Intakes required January-June, ig46.22. (a) War Dept.(b) N.A.A.F.I.Men ...A.T.S.NursesDoctorsCivilians235,9007.50060060030,605
APPENDIX &quot;A&quot;PROPOSED PLAN FOR RELEASES FOR THE PERIOD i8th JUNE, 1945 TO 3oth JUNE, 1946 (All figures in thousands)Serial               /	Detail	MEN							A.T.S.						Releases			Wastage (Group 32 and later)	Class &quot;B&quot; Release (Group 32 and later)	Total Loss per month	Residual Strength	Releases		Wastage (Group 50 and later)	Total Loss per month	Residual Strength		Equivalent A. &amp; S. Groups	Numbers released or to be released (including British in Indian Army)						Equiva-lent A. &amp; S. Groups	Numbers released or to be released				W	(2)	(3)		(4)	(5)	(6)	(7)	(8)	(9)	(10)	(11)	(12)I 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13	Strength at 18th June, 1945 (a) ... June, 1945       ......... ex-P.W. (Europe)     ...... July     .........    -August    ............ September        ......... October............ November............ December        ......... Estimate of expired deferments ... Total Release and Wastage 18th June to 31st December, 1945   ... Strength at 31st December, 1945, after adding ex-P.W. (Japan) 38-8  and intake men 68-o, A.T.S. 7-5       ......... January, 1946         ...... ex-P.W. (Japan)   ...... February       ......... ex-P.W. (Japan)   ...... March............ ex-P.W. (Japan)   ......	i-3 4-9 io-i3(Pt.) i3(Pt.)-i6(Pt.) l6(Pt.)-20(Pt.) 20(Pt.)-22(Pt.) 22(Pt.)-23 24-25(Pt.) 25(Pt.) 25(Pt.)-26(Pt.)	i5-i&quot; (b) 7-1 45-6 54-6J 62-9 I5I-7 185-7 179-1 4-3	Actual * Releases	3-7 3-3 3-3 3-3 3-3 3-3	8-o 8-o 8-o	22-2 49-3 57-9 66-2 163-0 197-0 190-4 4-3	(01)2,962-4 2,318-9	Married and i-i4(Pt.) 14-21 22-26 27-30 31-34 35-37 38-40 41-42	r 7-5i J        L Actual [24-2 1 Releases I 6-4J 5-8 6-3 8-i 9-5	-i -i -1 -I -i -i	7-5 24-3 6-5 5-9 6-4 8-2 9-6	197-7 136-8			706-1		20-2	(d) 24-0	750-3			(0)67-8	-6	68-4				189-8! (c)!3-o 189-81 (c)i3-o. 189-8 1 (c)i2-8^		3-3 3-3 3-3	-	206-i 206-i 205-9			10-4 I3-I 12-7	-i -I -i &apos;&quot;-	10-5 13-2 12-8	
1415i6171819April   ...........May    ............June    ...........Estimate of expired deferments ..Total Release and Wastage January-June, 1946     .....Strength at 30th June, 1946Less margin for unmusterables ..Army commitment at 1st July,1946, less trainees26(Pt.)-27(Pt.)27(Pt.)-28(Pt.)28(Pt.)-3i189-9189-8189-8n-51,189-21,109-98o-o1,029-943-4445-4647-4920-216-814-6i-420-316-914-7i-489-847-0It also includes(a) This figure is based on the figure as at 31st May, 1945, in the Statistical Digest, adjusted to include personnel taken on strength in June, less wastage.17,000 British personnel of the Indian Army.(b) Ex-P.W. from Germany in Groups 1-17 who were eligible for release in June and were at, or awaiting acceptance for, Civil Resettlement Courses amounted to 7-1thousand.(c) It has been assumed that ex-P.W. (Japan), amounting to 38-8 thousand, will be released during the period January-March, 1946.(d) The balance of 53,000 Class &quot; B &quot; releases to complete the total of 77,000 are included in Class &quot; A &quot; total in column 3, vide para. 4(c) (iv).(e) The shortfall of 7,200 compared with the target of 75,000 in para. 3 is due to a recent reassessment of the numbers in the groups concerned.vO
PROPOSED PLAN FOR RELEASES OF NURSES, i8th JUNE, 1945 TO 30TH JUNE, 19463 w w tn	Detail	Equivalent A. &amp;S. Groups Married and Single	Numbers released or to be released, Married and Single	Wastage (Group 43 and later)	Total Loss per month	Residual Strength	(1)	(2)	(3)	(4)	(5)	(6)1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18	Strength at 18th June, 1945... June, 1945   ......... July............ August September    ...      ;.. October November December Total Release and Wastage 18th June-3ist Decem-ber, 1945......... Strength at 31st December after adding intake (421) January, 1946 February March............ April............ May   ............ June............ Total Release and Wastage January-June, 1946 Commitment at 1st July, 1946, less Trainees	i-3 4-9 io-i3(Pt.) i3(Pt.)-i6(Pt.) l6(Pt.)-20(Pt.) 20(Pt.)-2l(Pt.) 2l(Pt.)-23 24-28 (Pt.) 28(Pt.)-32(Pt.) 32(Pt.)-35(Pt.) 35(Pt.)-38(Pt.) 38(Pt.)-4o(Pt.) 4o(Pt.)-43(Pt.)	2ll\ Actual ,2  l Releases 410J 316 610 323 349 2,813 572 57i 571 571 571 571 3.427	42 42 42 42 42 42 252 30 30 30 30 30 30 180	215 632 452 358 652 365 391 3.065 602 601 601 601 601 601 3.607	10,501 7.857 4.250Note : No allowance has been made for married Nurses in Groups later than 42 who may claimrelease before June, 1946.B45/67)   no   9/45   W.O.P.   23753APPENDIX &quot; B &quot;



</content>
</cab>
