<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 254-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  September 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (45) 181.18th September, 1945.CABINET.ORGANISATION OF GOVERNMENT SUPPLY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.1. I am in full agreement with the proposal in Annex II of CP. (45) 178,that a combined Ministry of Supplies should be formed to carry :--(i) Responsibility for the supply (and in many cases the design) of a largerange of stores used by the Government for which concentration of-purchasing arrangements seems advantageous,(ii) The primary Government responsibility in the field of engineering.2. I also agree that (ii) might usefully be extended to cover the development and maintenance of an adequate industrial potential for the fighting Services.Centralised or pooled arrangements would also be appropriate for certain formsof basic research, e.g., nuclear energy, metallurgy and explosives.3. It would, however, be most unwise to attempt to extend the wide field ofresponsibility embraced under (i) and (ii) by including within it responsibilityfor research, development and procurement in connection with the specialisedwarlike equipment of the fighting Services. This responsibility is one whichshould be reserved to the Ministers responsible to Parliament for those Services.The point here involved is one of critical importance to national security.4. It is the duty of the fighting Service to specify the technical equipmentit wants. This definition, on which so much depends, is, or should be, the resultof a fusion of military, scientific and engineering thought. Between the issueof the complete specification and the moment when the finished equipment is placed in the hands of the Service there lies a continuous series of processes,through design, prototype and trial to final production. At no stage in these processes can we afford to dispense with that fusion of thought which gave riseto the original specification.5. This is the fundamental argument underlying the proposition that responsibility for research, development and procurement of specialised warlike stores should be restored to the fighting Services themselves. To break the chain of connected processes by a change of departmental responsibility is bound to damage efficiency.6. The Ministry of Aircraft Production was formed in 1940 by taking thedepartment of the Member of the Air Council responsible for research, develop-ment and procurement, together with ancillary finance and contract elements,and placing it in charge of a separate Minister. The team which the newMinister took over was thus an integrated civilian/service team. It was also an efficient team. At the beginning of the war our aircraft, designed and developedunder the control of the Air Ministry, were superior in nearly all respects to thoseof, the enemy. The entirely new device of Radar had been developed into a successful defensive organisation with remarkable speed. Heavy aircraft werefitted with gun turrets again produced under the direction of the Air Ministry which were in advance of any installation used by any other nation.7. As the result of this start, of the pressure of war and of the strongpersonal ties which united the two Departments, contact between user andproducer was- on the whole maintained during the five years of Avar which[30540]
followed. There were also good contacts between the firms on the one hand andthe Air Ministry staffs and the United Kingdom-based squadrons on the other.Even so, there have been signs that user and producer have already lost a little of their original intimacy of thought on needs and possibilities. Whether this is so or not, it is scarcely open to doubt that the result of placing research, develop-ment and procurement of warlike equipment in the hands of a Ministry ofSupplies with a wide and expanding range of non-service responsibilities wouldbe a growing separation of military and technical thought.8. The Committee under Sir Henry Tizard which recently reported to theChiefs of Staff Committee on modern technical possibilities and their effects on methods of war drew attention to the need for the closest integration of user andproducer interest. Since that report was written the release of nuclear energy-has become an accomplished fact. We are face to face not with the rapid develop-ments of military equipment which seemed probable a few months ago, but withthe necessity for a complete revolution in all existing ideas of military equip-ment. The effect of continued severance between user and producer would havebeen grave in any circumstances. At the present time, a decision in this sensemight be disastrous. Some mistakes of organisation can be rectified when shownup by experience. A fundamental error in the organisation of defence supplymight well have consequences beyond our power to recall.9. For all these reasons I ask the -Cabinet to agree that responsibility for research, development and procurement for aircraft and associated equipmentshould be reunited with the Air Ministry as soon as possible.10. I believe that the advantages in maintaining the high quality of british air equipment, which could be secured by the reabsorption of the Ministry of aircraft Production into the Air Ministry, would also be enjoyed by the otherDepartments mainly interested the Admiralty and the Ministry of - CivilAviation. I recognise that they must be satisfied that a proper balance would be struck between their needs and those of the Air Ministry. A scheme has beenprepared to give effect to this principle. I am ready to discuss this scheme withthe First Lord and the Minister of Civil Aviation at any time. It will afford theAdmiralty and the Ministry of Civil Aviation the fullest safeguards, and indeed amore direct voice in the control of development and procurement than they enjoy-in the Ministry of Aircraft Production to-day.11.   I hope, therefore, that the Cabinet will agree to (a) the creation of a combined Ministry of Supplies, with the main Govern-ment responsibility in the field of engineering, and responsibility for developing and maintaining war potential;(b) the assumption by all three Service Departments of responsibility for research, development and procurement of specialised warlike stores;with pooling of functions and resources in all appropriate cases.S.Air Ministry, 18th September, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
