<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/2/0 images: 282-291</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   September 1945.The circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.   It is issued for the personal use of................................................................;TOP SECRET Copy No.CP. (45) 189.25th September, 1945sCABINET.THE ITALIAN COLONIES, AND BRITISH INTERESTS IN THEMEDITERRANEAN-RED SEA ROUTE.Views of the South African Government.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I circulate for the information of my colleagues a copy of a memorandum from the High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa. In view of itslength, I also annex a summary of the main points.A.Dominions Office, S.W. 1,25th September, 1945.

ANNEX I.Summary o\f Memorandum of 20th September from the High ^Commissionerfor the Union of South Africa to the Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.IN the view of the South African. Government, the chief issue in the disposalof the Italian colonies is whether or not the protection of the strategic Empireroute through the Mediterranean and Red Sea is to be maintained or abandoned.2. The future control of strategic bases in Cyrenaica and Italian Somalilandshould contain an effective guarantee to the British commonwealth that thedanger it had to fight against in the last two wars shall not occur again.3. The future of the route has already become hazardous as a result of the changing character of the Arab world.4. Russia is expanding, and the Near East is already becoming Sovietised.To place the Italian colonies under international control will expose the Arabsto Soviet influence.5. This would be of little concern to the United States. The Mediterraneanis not their lifeline and the maintenance of British strategic interests in theMiddle East forms no part of United States policy.6. The United States proposal for international trusteeship for the italian colonies rests on the assumption that the principle of single Power trusteeshiphas failed either because mandatory Powers have abused their trust or becausethey have failed to put first the interests of the native populations. This assump-tion is unjustified, at least in respect of British mandatory Governments.7. If the mandate system has failed, it is only in the case of Japan, but ithas not been suggested that international control should be applied to ex-Japanesemandated islands.8. Neither the establishment of a United Nations Organisation with a security Council nor the discovery of the atomic bomb justifies us in failing toguard the sea routes of the future.9. The debate on the United States proposal for international trusteeshiphas probably advanced too far to revert to the idea of trusteeship by a singlenation.10. To reconcile British strategic interests with the United States proposal,Cyrenaica should be. retained under British control either (i) as a British strategic base under the Security Council, or(ii) by granting independence to the Senussi and making a treaty with them under agreement with the Security Council, or(iii) by putting it under Egyptian administration on condition that themilitary clauses in the Egyptian treaty apply to Cyrenaica.11. Tripolitania should either be returned to Italy with guarantees as todemilitarisation and native interests or it could come under internationaltrusteeship.12. Eritrea could be given to Abyssinia with special arrangements for thedevelopment of Massawa; in exchange Abyssinia should give up Ogaden and the reserved Area to Somaliland.13. If Italian Somaliland cannot be formed with these areas and british somali land into a Greater Somalia under British mandate, French, British andItalian Somaliland might all be administered as a single territory by a Franco-British-Italian international body.Dominions Office, &apos;22nd September, 1945.
ANNEX II.Memorandum from the High Commissioner for the Union of South africa to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, 20th September, 1945.THE ITALIAN COLONIES AND BRITISH INTERESTS in mediterranean-RED SEA ROUTE.(1) The Dominions and India have hitherto consistently supported themaintenance of British power and prestige in the Middle East, in order to safe-guard the communication lifeline to India, Australia and New Zealand. Inthe protection of this route Britain originally went to Egypt. The thanklessand costly trusteeships of Iraq, Palestine and Trans Jordan were accepted forthe same purpose. The Commonwealth has collectively always considered thatprotection of the Mediterranean-Red; Sea route was vital to its trade and security, and many thousands of men from all parts of the Empire in two greatwars have fought and died to protect these Empire communications.(2) In the view of South Africa, the chief issue raised by the disposition of the Italian Colonies, apart from the humanitarian aspect, is whether ornot the old Commonwealth policy is to be maintained or abandoned. If it isto be maintained, then, in view of the lessons of the war, Britain&apos;s strategic position must be strengthened by giving her use of those areas from which theenemy so nearly wrought our destruction. If the policy is to be abandonedin favour of internationalism, then there should be some measurable degree ofcertainty that the new order will be at least as favourable to Commonwealthsecurity as the policy which is being abandoned.(3) Apart from the question of security for the Mediterranean-Red Sea-Commonwealth route, South Africa as the only non-Colonial belligerent nationin Africa, has vital continental interests at stake, both economic and ethical.Since, however, these do not affect the other Dominions they need not now beconsidered. For the purpose of this argument the question can be confinedsolely to the interests which the countries of the Commonwealth have in common that of Empire communications in the security of which bothAustralia and New Zealand are equally interested. Unless they can be satisfiedthat in all future circumstances the contemplated international trusteeshipover the lands of the Mediterranean Littoral will guarantee to them the samesafety of the Mediterranean-Red Sea route that they have enjoyed in thepast, then under no circumstances should the strength of the British strategic position along the line of route be impaired.(4) The strategic plan of the Axis Powers was to seize Egypt between thetwin jaws of its military power in Libya and Eritrea. The plan very nearlysucceeded. It was finally defeated by a Commonwealth army at El Alamein.The lesson, it would appear, remains still to be learned. It is the purpose ofthis Memorandum to suggest that the future control of both strategic bases in cyrenaica and Italian Somaliland should contain an effective guarantee to theCommonwealth that the danger it had to fight against, in 1914 and 1939 shallnot occur again.(5) The future of the Mediterranean route has become very hazardous as aresult of the changing character of the Arab world. Arab nationalism is growingwith the appearance of a vocal middle class. Egypt is getting ready to ask fora new Treaty with Britain which will require the complete withdrawal of all british troops : and the indications are that the current international sentimentto which appeal will be made, will support the claims of Egypt. Trans Jordanmay be expected to make a similar request. French and British troops are on the point of leaving Syria. To-day the Arab League is pro-British, not only because it looks to Britain for support but because it admires the British liberalsystem. It may be expected, however, that within an appreciable measure oftime this organisation will become the recognised authority of the whole arab world, and its influence will stretch from Bagdad to Tripoli. The question whichnaturally arises is whether or not the Arab world will continue to accept theBritish connection, which, by permitting British Military establishments toremain on Arab soil, acts as a valuable aid in the defence of Empirecommunications.
(6) It is known from the reports arriving from many sources that Russian,influence is growing in the Middle East. In Persia the struggle is even now taking place between the Persian Government and Russia regarding the physicalpossession of the Northern Province and the political control of its people.A military campaign is already under way in the northern area of Iraq. Thesatellite Balkan States have all &quot;ganged up&quot; behind Moscow, and Greeceis struggling at this moment against sharing the same-fate. Turkey is being reduced to a nervous wreck as a result of the sedulously conducted Soviet press campaing against her. In Palestine the immigrant Jews are largely Communistand the next trouble which will occur there will be a reflection of the anti-British policy fomented in the Balkans by Russians. These are facts. Therecan be little doubt that Russia will get all she wants in regard to strategic bases in the Straits. The day of appeasement has come again. The Near East isalready half way to becoming Sovietised. The only influence which wouldcounteract that of the Soviet, which is well understood in Moscow, is that ofthe British.(7) The American proposal to place the Italian Colonies under international control will result in joining up the Arab sentiment in those areas with theSovietised Near East, to the complete destruction of British influence.Mr. Byrnes, in arguing for the adopting of his proposal and in reply toM. Molotov&apos;s statement that Russiar-had much experience in the handling ofdifferent peoples, gave promise that Soviet administrative methods might be tried out in the Italian Colonies. There can be little doubt that this will happen,and the young effendi Communists, anxious to break away from their islamicrestraints, will do all that is politically required to obtain control. The techniquewhich has been applied throughout the satellite Russian States will be appliedunder international control, aided by the Russian representative. Proof of thisis surely to be found in all the countries of Central Europe, in which AlliedCouncils have operated. The Americans, of course, would not be much concerned to prevent this happening. The Mediterranean is not their life-line, and themaintenance of British strategic interests in the Middle East forms no part ofUnited States policy.       &apos;-(8) The United States proposal to establish an international trusteeship forthe Italian Colonies rests on both or one of two assumptions. First that theprinciple of Single-Power trusteeship adopted after the last war has failedeither because the Mandatory Powers have abused their trust both militarilyand economically, or secondly, because they have failed to make the cause oftheir subject populations their primary consideration.   .(9) Is either of these two assumptions justified on the facts ? It is true thatthey both apply in the case of the Japanese Mandates. The Japanese did abusetheir trust both militarily and economically, and they did not make the interestof their subject populations paramount. But to whom else does this indictmentapply? To Australia in her mandate over New Guinea, or to New Zealand in her mandate of Western Samoa? These two countries would be the first to repudiate such an allegation. Certainly the charge cannot be laid against theBritish, whose record of trust is beyond reproach. The Mandated territory ofIraq was granted independence in 1927, and became a member of the League ofNations in 1932. Under the Declaration of 1923, Transjordan was accorded anindependent government under its own Amir; and to-day it is practically an autonomous country. Palestine, the greatest liability of all the Mandates, is held to maintain the balance between the conflicting forces of world Jewry andthe Arab people, at the request of the whole western world. Tanganyika isregarded by all unbiassed observers as a model of advanced native administration in which the native authority is encouraged and directed to the uplift of thepeople. South-West Africa under the Mandate held by the Union shows a material political and social advance of a truly commendable character. It has itsown Executive Committee, elected by the Legislative Assembly, which governsits own concerns. Its population of all races has increased by 40 per cent, sincethe Mandate was granted. Its trade and industry have prospered exceedingly,and it has ministered to the needs of its native population in a manner comparable with any other country in Africa.(10) Nor can it be said that any British Mandatory Power has used itsMandates to benefit itself, either militarily or economically. Neither Australianor New Zealand nor South Africa attempted in any of their territories to arm
and train its subject population, and the need for a change of form in the Mandate,which brought about the reconsideration of the whole Mandatory system arose inpart from the inability of Mandatory Administrations, e.g., in Tanganyika, toestablish any defences for the security of the territories administered.(11) Similarly none of the Mandated Territories has been of any economic advantage to the Commonwealth Power which held it. The urgent need hasalways been for greater money grants from the parent country to enable them todevelop their natural resources, and the economic burden entailed has from timeto time led to suggestions for admitting private enterprise, which has had to be refused because of the fear of exploiting the Native population.(12) The change of system therefore from Single-Power Mandate to international control cannot be due to the failure on the part of those BritishPowers holding Mandate in the past. In so far as the change may be ascribed topast failures, such failures lie solely with Japan. It is not, however, proposed toapply international control to the Japanese Mandated Islands of the Pacific nowin possession of the United States. So far as can be ascertained they are not tobe regarded as colonies at all, but as strategic bases. Internationalism is toapply only to the Italian Colonies. This American proposal has been made morewith a view to placating American opinion than from any regard for the welfare of the Colonial people and without any consideration for British interests. Theethical arguments in favour of international control, which are all based on abelief that the nations of the world will have no sectional interest to serve, andwill be collectively imbued with liberal sentiments, have so impressed the western world, that it is probably too late to reverse the decision in favour of Single-Nation Mandates; and the fact that Russia, which has had no previous interestsin Africa, should now be eager to obtain a Single-Nation Mandate, shows clearly that her objective is both strategic and political.(13) It is not sufficient to assume that because there is a United nations organisation with a Security Council, that therefore their is no need for guardingthe sea routes in future. That the United States makes no such assumption isshown by its declaration regarding the Pacific bases; and the whole Russianpan-Slav policy is aimed at securing the defence of Russia, despite its member-ship of the United Nations, and its insistence on the vote in the Security Council.Nor will wisdom accept the atomic bomb as a substitute for taking newprecautions to guard against assault upon the Empire lines of communication.It is admitted that its secret cannot be indefinitely maintained, and its verydeadliness may rule it out as a weapon of war. If Washington suspected thatMoscow could as easily drop an atomic bomb on New York as she could on Moscow,would America dare to use it ? And in such a case would not the final test of power lie with that country which was prepared to use the bomb and pay the leastregard for human life and the destruction which it would create? Again, is notthe menace of the bomb greatest to the densely populated countries, where liberalideals prevail, while being of lesser concern to those more sparsely populatedcountries of great area, where authoritarianism is in force ?(14) There is as yet no indication that the nations are anywhere, outside theDominions, remotely considering the abandonment of military power for bothattack and defence, or that Power-Woes will not continue to form the basis ofinternational relationhood for years to come. Yet, before sufficient time has elapsed to form any sound judgment on the probabilities of future worldco-operation, the Commonwealth is being asked by the United States, on the scoreof international goodwill and understanding, to accept the first sacrifice of thesecurity it won on the battlefields of Northern Africa before America entered the war.(15) The debate on the American proposal for international trusteeship has probably advanced too far to permit a reversion to the Single-Nation Mandate.If a reversion were now attempted it might be difficult to refuse to allotTripolibania to Russia, in view of the refusal of the United States to accept any obligation. It may, therefore, be necessary to reconcile British strategic interestswith the American proposal. This can best be done by securing Cyrenaica as aBritish strategic base.(16) Cyrenaica was developed as a strategic base for the attack on Egyptby the Italians. For this purpose roads and railways were built, harboursdeveloped and airways constructed. As events showed, it was admirably suitedfor the purpose, and the Italian plans for aggression would assuredly have
succeeded had their troops been better soldiers. With the recent air develop-nients, and particularly with a few atom bombs stored away in the vast regions of the uninhabited desert, it can truly be said that Cyrenaica is the key to allthe Near Eastern defences. It provides, moreover, the only real answer to anyattempted raids by a future rapacious European Power, heedless of consequences;for if the fear of reprisals by densely populated Western European countries should operate against the use of the atomic bomb to their detriment, and ifWashington and New York should fear their fate too much to come to the rescue,no such fear would prevent its use from the deserts of Cyrenaica. It has been pointed out by a military authority that, in the new world, the existence of aninternational air force provides no answer to the sudden seizure of London bythe air-borne forces of a determined aggressor who wished to benefit by itshelplessness. There could be no striking back, for the bombing of the invasionforces would destroy the unfortunate inhabitants of London. Only the fear ofcertain punishment inflicted in the capital and towns of his own country wouldrestrain the aggressor. The remote desert would offer that threat without fearof reprisal and act as a safety valve for the world.(17) From this base all the likely danger spots in Eastern and SouthernEurope could easily be reached. Knowledge that such a potential striking forceexisted on the doorstep of any wishful European aggressor would, in itself, exerta most sobering influence on all its external relations while, in the Near East,the same knowledge would materially strengthen and maintain British influenceeven although all British troops were. withdrawn from Egypt and other arab countries, an influence which would not be without its effect on the new India.(18) Since Alamein, Cyrenaica has been administered by a British military government which, as the attached Memorandum* on Cyrenaica shows, has thegood will of the Arabs, Bedouin and townsmen alike. The Italian colonistshave all gone, and the Arab population, which was reduced by half in the cruelwar of repression by the Italians, now number only 200,000. They are BritishAllies and threw in their lot with the British in the darkest days of the war.This small population, inhabiting an immense area of desert, removes the country from the category of a colony into that of a strategic base; and the undertaking given to the Senussi by the British Parliament who understand that there willbe no more colonisation, places it under British protection.(19) There are several ways in which Cyrenaica could remain under british control&apos; -(a) It could be claimed as a British strategic base under the security council on the same grounds as those put forward by the Americansfor the Pacific islands. Its small population and its immense areaof desert, and its unsuitability for any colonisation, put it out ofthe category of mandates, and its past history, and the graves ofthe dead clearly define it to be a. strategic base.(&amp;) Independence could be granted to the Senussi who would accept it and ask for British technical assistance in administration. A treatygranting rights to Britain to maintain military establishments mightbe entered into under agreement with the Security Council.(c) It could be mandated to Egypt on the condition that the military clauses relating to Egypt in the existing treaty should apply &apos;toCyrenaica.(20) Tripolitania is not nearly so important for British interests asCyrenaica, and could very well come under international trusteeship, if returnto Italy is impossible. If it were returned to Italy under certain positiveguarantees as to de-militarisation and paramountcy of Native interests, it wouldbe quite safe for British interests. In case of internationalisation, the Sovietisa-tion of Tripolitania would not affect the position in Cyrenaica which wouldcushion the effect upon Egypt from the West.(21) If Eritrea is given to Abyssinia little harm would be done to theBritish strategic position. It will be many years before Abyssinia attains acivilised standard. The port of Massawa should be the hands of some expertbody able to administer it in the economic interests of the whole region, and ifthe United States will not undertake the task, and Britain, because of the veiled* Not printed.
hostility to any further extension of its &quot;Empire&quot; by the international frontis inhibited, then it might be possible to place it under the Egyptian Sudancondominium, and join up the railway line from Agordat to Kassala so as toserve the economic interests of the Lower Sudan. In exchange for Eritrea,Abyssinia should be willing to give up the desert provinces of Ogaden and the reserved Area which belong to the Somali.(22) In the case of Italian Somaliland, if it is found impossible to create a Greater Somalia by joining this Italian Colony with British Somalilandunder a British Mandate, then a solution, having as its aim the maintenanceof British security, might be obtained by bringing in French Somaliland andcreating a single territory out of the three colonies, administered by an inter-national body drawn from Britain, France and Italy. Italian feelings might receive some solace from this manifestation of goodwill.South A frica House, London, W-C. 2,20th September, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
