<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/23/40 images: 378-385</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PriPP-ow/ ^........... Sn?! HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 SSj&amp;RET w BE kept&quot;uMDERTdtf*&quot; we- -----f.P, (42j 160 It J8 requested that special, ew6 may be taken to ensureEVACUATION OP .DTOIANS FROM,BUf?MA.Memorandum by the Secretary ot. State XOil BumaA serious problem lias arisen in Burma in connexion- withthe refugees who are trying to get to India,   The Indianpopulation in Burma in normal times is rather more than,000,000,   Many of these as well as European, women andchildren left Burma before the sea route was closed, and since then up to the end of March 35,000 Indians and 700Europeans have passed over the route of the new road nowunder construction.   But large numbers of Indians remain inthe areas which we hold (e.g. some 70,000 in the Mandalaydistrict alone) and, should these be occupied by the enemy,have strong grounds for fears as&apos;to their treatment not somuch by the Japanese as by the Burmese population owing tothe strong Burmese antipathy for the Indian; thus one danger is-that as the enemy advances there may be a stampede,falling adequate facilities for orderly evacuation.2,     It is particularly desirable to move 15,000 dependants of essential workers on the railways, oilfields, etc., assoon as possible, since anxiety aboiro them is threatening to load to strikes and desertions,3,     The Governor has throughout been making every endeavourto cope with the whole problem.   The presence of masses of refugees would hinder urgent constructional work on the landroute to India,   Congestion at places along the approaches to the route has already led to an outbreak of cholera.   Itwas originally intended to limit the number of refugees onthe line of the new road to 500 a day.   At present it is taking 1,500 a day and this number may be somewhat increasedbut two -important limiting factors are that the water in the chindwin River by which part o-f the journey is made, is now and for the next four or five weeks .at its lowest level, andthat the provision of food and shelter for large numbers inthe inhospitable country to be traversed presents greatproblems.,   In any case there are many women and children andaged and infirm who cannot make the arduous land journey.In order to supplement the facilities for evacuation byland and to provide for those who cannot face the&apos;rigoursof the land journey, the only possible transport is by air and it is a matter of urgency to see whether some means can-not be found of making additional transport aircraft avail-able.   There was previously a limited amount of evacuation by air but this has now been reduced to little or nothing.The Governor reports that if adequate aircraft can besupplied and operated he may be able to break the back ofthe problem&apos;but that otherwise he anticipates 11 a very tragicsituation,&quot;2. The problem has an important political aspect in India.The Governor has reported that he is trying hard to avoid

racial or class distinct ion, and that at - Magwe aerodrome(from which, while it was in&apos;use, evacuation was effected)all civilian aircraft were being used almost entirely forIndians quite irrespective of their ability to pay; but thatthe problem of Europeans, Anglo-Indians, and high-classIndians is so different from that of the coolies that he feared the Government could not hope to avoid all criticism.But, however   successful the authorities may be in avoidingdiscrimination, failure to evacuate a large number of -Indiansis bound to arouse an outcry in India coupled    howeverunjustifiably - with charges of discriminatory treatment;and this is exactly the type of issue most likely to causeIll-feeling against the British authorities on the part of indians of all political parties.   The refugee question isalready becoming a first-class political issue in India(and according to one press correspondent has beeninfluencing the attitude of the Congress Party towards theconstitutional proposals),5.     A request by the Governor made on the advice of ArmyHeadquarters in Burma for transport aircraft was referredto the -Chiefs of Staff.   Their reply states that there are10 in India and three were arriving shortly from the middle east while six more destined for India had been delivered to us in the U.S.A.; but that all these aircraft would beused for vital Service requirements and that it is extremely unlikely that General Wavell will be able to divert them forthe purpose of evacuating civilians.6,     Apart from the British allocations of aircraft from theU.S.A, we heard a month ago that the United States Govern-ment have decided to allocate 100 freight-carrying aircraft from American civil air lines for operation between Indiaand China and that 35 of these are to be sent in the firstinstance.   It is most desirable fronv every aspect, and fortheir primary purpose of supplying China, that they should reach India at the earliest possible moment.    If they werein service it seems probable that some space on these air-craft could be provided for&apos; refugees on the return journeyfrom China to India via Burma.   The Governor    of Burmatelegraphed on 4th April direct to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador,Washington, asking very urgently for information as to thenumber and expected arrivals of these aircraft and whetherthe Americans would, be willing to allow these machines tocarry refugees back to India.    In reply to this telegramLord Halifax referred the Governor to General Brereton,Commander of the UvS, Army Air Forces in India.7.     I consider that the issues involved are so important that a special effort should be made to get the Americans to push on with their deliveries of aircraft, and feel thatthey would respond if the whole case in its military,political and humanitarian aspects were put before them.   i suggest therefore that His Majesty&apos;s Government should instruct His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador, Washington, to make aspecial approach to the United States Government putting tothem the facts given above and urging them to make available at the earliest possible moment some transport aircraft which could be used and to give their consent to their being used, while the need, subsists, for the evacuation of refugees from Burma to India even to the exclusion of exports from China.8.     Apart from this suggestion, it seems desirable toconsider urgently whether any further steps could be takento assist in solving this refugee problem, the proportions

and possible consequences of which I have thought it rightto bring to the attention of the War Cabinet.L.S. A.WYMk OFFICE.11th April 1942.




</content>
</cab>
