<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/190/21 images: 512-515</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cp(76)46 COPY NO    SiS July 1976CABINETDIRECT ELECTIONS TO THE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth affairs.        At its meeting on 11 June Cabinet agreed that the Report of the SelectCommittee on direct elections should be considered by Parliament ariddiscussed by Cabinet itself before the European Council on 12-13 July.The Committee published its first report covering the Community aspectsof the problem on 15 June.    I attach at annex to this paper the summary ofits recommendations.   Arrangements have been made for the report to be debated by the Commons on 9 July.    Mr Hattersley will open for theGovernment in my absence in the United States.2.        Thia memorandum sets out the line that I propose we should takeboth in the debate and at the European Council at which there will be great pressure to settle the main outstanding issues in the Community,    Ingeneral the Select Committee&apos;s recommendations are close to the lineproposed in the Government&apos;e Green Paper Cmnd 6399 which has been taken as the guideline for our negotiations in the Community so far.    The situation under the four main headings considered by the Committee itself is asfollows:SIZE AND COMPOSITION OF THE ASSEMBLY3.        Within the Community the negotiating options have become a gooddeal clearer since the last Cabinet discuBaion,    Community foreign ministers had a useful exchange at their informal meeting on 12 June andthe Prime Minister and I were able to pursue the matter further bilaterallyduring President Giscard&apos;s State Visit,   As we had hoped the Presidentproved to be more flexible than his Foreign Minister or officials,    since he had formal difficulties with the Belgian compromise proposal which wewere inclined to favour (outlined in paragraph 4 of my memorandum cp(76) 25 of 7 June), we floated with him another variant devised to meetMs objections, which would give an Assembly of 390 of which 78 seats would go to the United Kingdom.    President Giscard was careful not to commit himself but indicated that he would not take a lead in opposing a solution onthese Hubs.1
4.        In the debate I believe we should accept the Select Committee1?recommendations as to our broad negotiating aims while making it clearthat the result we obtain will have to be within the limits of what isnegotiable.    It would not be right to reveal the confidential exchanges with president Giscard and we should not tie our hands too tightly before thefinal negotiations in the Community.   In the European Council we shouldcontinue to seek the best possible solution for the United Kingdom in comparison with the smaller Member States.    I believe that a solution in the range of the Belgian proposal or the variant floated with Giscardshould be acceptable,DATE FOR ELECTIONS5.        The Committee recommend In favour of elections being held inMay or June 1978.    They believe that it should be possible for the necessarylegislative and preparatory work to be completed in time for this date to be adhered to but add that they will be in a better position to make a firmassessment on this point when they have considered the matters raised inPart 3 of the Green Paper (ie the electoral arrangements includingconstituencies, franchise etc which are to be decided nationally).    Theseare matters which the Government will itself wish to consider carefully inthe light of the Select Committee&apos;s future report.    In concluding thenegotiations in the Qommimity I believe we should keep open the possibilityof nominating United Kingdom members In 1978 in case this should prove necessary.,    But we should emphasise our intention to proceed to electionsat the same time ae the other Member States if possible.    We should alsoindicate these intentions in the debate.6.        The European Council may also set the precise dates for the firstelections in 1978 which it has already been decided should take place withina period of a Thursday to Sunday inclusive in May or June,    hi the green paper we suggested there might be advantage in holding the european assembly elections in May at the same time as local authority electionsif this can conveniently be arranged.    The Select Committee in the lightof the views put to them recommend that elections should take place on a date on which no other elections are statutorily held.    The Labour Party,however, recently inclined toward a different view on this point.   It is forconsideration whether we should accept the Committee *s recommendation on this and say so in the debate.    Since the prospect of altering dates ofthe local elections due in England in 1978 is in any case under considerationbecause of the coincidence with Ascension Day, there would in practice beno problem in accepting any date in May or June 1978 which avoidsUnited Kingdom public holidays.THE PERIOD FOR WHICH THE ASSEMBLY SHOULD BE ELECTED7.        The Select Committee came out in favour of a fixed term but with aslight bias in favour of four rather than five years.   As explained in the green Paper there is already a broad consensus in the Community in favour2
of a five-year period.    I think we should go along with the Communityview rather than reopen the point at this stage.    The Committee advancesno substantive arguments in favour of four rather than five years.STATUS OF MEMBERS OF THE ASSEMBLY8.        The Committee recommends clearly in favour of an optional dualmandate.    This is also the view put forward by the Government in the green Paper.    We should stick to this.conclusions .        The negotiations in the Community are now within sight of a conclusion.    The main outstanding points are likely to be settled at theEuropean Council on 12-13 July and the final details will be settled as soonas possible thereafter.    In the negotiations so far we have played a full part in order to make sure that British interests should not go by default,but under the general reservation mat the Government would wish to look at the agreement as a whole in the light of the results of their politicalconsultations within the United Kingdom.   As far as the Communityaspects of the problem are concerned (ie those covered in Part 2 of the green Paper) the debate on 9 July will be the conclusion of a process of consultation in which we have sought a full spectrum of political views.I believe that an agreement on the lines outlined above will be acceptable to the broad majority of opinion in Parliament.    I therefore recommendthat Cabinet should agree that the Prime Minister and I should seek to conclude the Community negotiations on this basis.A foreign and Commonwealth office July 19763
ANNEXFIRST REPORT FROM THE SELECT COMMITTEE ON DIRECT ELECTION3 TOTHE EUROPEAN ASSEMBLY.SUMMARY OF recommendations-   The Government should press for an agreement under which the^size of the Assembly should fall between 350 and 425 seats.2.   In reaching a decision on the final number and allocation of seats, the following considerations in particular should be borne in mind:-(i) that population should be the chief factor in anycomputation of seats as between different Member States;(ii) that any formulation should be such as to make it possiblefor the United kingdom&apos;s allocation of seats to be large enough to provide representation for its component partsnot significantly out of proportion to those of thesmaller Member States (with the proviso that Luxembourgshould be treated a3 a special case).5.   The Government should a^ree in the Council that electionsshould be held in May or June 1978.4.   Elections 3hould take place on a date on which no other electionsare statutorily held.5.   Elections in the different Member States should be held on thesame date or within a few days of each other (but not on a Sundayin the United Kingdom), and the results in each Member State shouldbe declared at the same time.6.   To allow for the fact that some Member States may use an electoral3ystem requiring more than one ballot, in such cases the first ballotshould be held at the same time aa the single ballot in single ballotcountries, and the result of the first ballot should be declaredat the same time as the final results are declared in single ballotcountries.7.   The directly elected Assembly should be elected for a fixed termof four or five years (with a slight bias in favour of four).8.   An optional dual mandate should be adopted so far as the UnitedKingdom is concerned.

</content>
</cab>
