<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/54/15 images: 175-189</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT0 9CC(74) 15th COPY NO     0 0ConclusionsCABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the cabinet held at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 9 MAY 1974at 10. 30 am present the Rt Hon Harold Wilson mp prime minister the Rt Hon Edward Short mp lord President of the council the Rt Hon Lord Elwyn-jones lord chancellor the Rt Hon Denis Healey mp chancellor of the exchequer the Rt Hon Michael Foot mp secretary of State for employment the Rt Hon Shirley Williams mp secretary of State for Prices and consumer protection the Rt Hon Anthony Wedgwood Benn mp secretary of State for industry the Rt Hon Roy Mason mp secretary of State for defence the Rt Hon James Callaghan mp secretary of State for Foreign and commonwealth AffairsThe Rt Kon Roy Jenkins mp secretary of State for the home department the Rt Hon Anthony Crosland mp secretary of State for the environment the Rt Hon Eric Varley mp secretary of State for energy the Rt Hon Barbara Castle mp secretary of State for Social services the Rt Hon Peter Shore mp secretary of State for trade the Rt Hon Reginald Prentice mp secretary of State for Education and science
The Rt Hon Merlyn Rees MP The Rt Hon Fred Peart mp secretary of State for Northern Ireland Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Rt Hon Lord shepherd lord Privy seal the FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTThe Rt Hon Samuel Silkin QC MP The Rt Hon Robert Mellish mp attorney General (Items 1-3) Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat sir John hunt mr P D Nairne (Item 4)Mr H F T Smith (Item 3)Mr P Benner (Items 1, 2 and 5)Mr J An son (Items 6 and 7)Mr K R Stowe (Items 1 and 2)Mr H F Ellis-Rees (Item 4)Mr D Evans (Item 3)Mr R L Baxter (Item 6 and 7)contents item Subject page 1 PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSLegislative Programme 12 MEMBERS1 OUTSIDE FINANCIAL INTERESTS 13 FOREIGN AFFAIRS iiMiddle East - european Community 34 EUROPEAN ECONOMIC COMMUNITY ENERGY POLICY 55 HEALTH AND SAFETY AT WORK ETC BILL 66 ROAD TANKER DRIVERS 9? POST OFFICE PAY 10
PARLIAMENTARY   1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the affairs House of Commons during the following week.    It was not intendedduring that week to make any announcement about the dates of the whitsun Recess; but it was in fact envisaged that it should last for slightly over two weeks.LegislativeProgrammeThe Cabinet were informed that parliamentary draftsmen would shortly have completed work on virtually all the major legislation for which they had received Instructions.    It was therefore important that all Ministers with responsibility for Bills - and inparticular major Bills - -with a place in the legislative programme should ensure that urgent steps were taken to secure any necessarypolicy clearance and to complete the preparation of Instructions,so as to ensure that the services of parliamentary draftsmen were used to the best effect and that congestion was avoided in the later stages of the programme.ffiMBERS1OUTSIDEFINANCIALINTERESTSPreviousReference:CC(74) 13thConclusions,Minute 22. THE LORD PRESIDENT said that, as agreed by the cabinet at its last meeting, he had consulted the Liaison Committee of theParliamentary Labour Party about the Governments proposal totable Resolutions requiring Members to declare their financial andother interests in debate and in dealings with Ministers and government Departments, and setting up a compulsory and publicregister of such interests.    He had put before the Committee the cabinets provisional definition of what might constitute aregistrable interest, together with the definitions arrived at in theall-Party discussions, and in the Labour Party&apos;s own discussions in 1973.    The Chairman of the Committee had also produced hisown definition.    The outcome of the discussions was agreement that there should be a compulsory and public register but that a select Committee should be appointed to consider the definition of interests to be included in it, the arrangements for maintaining it,and the methods by which registration should be made compulsoryand enforceable, including the question whether this should be by legislation or by Standing Orders of the House.    He commendedthis proposal to his colleagues.    The Cabinets own discussion theprevious week and the further discussion in the Liaison Committeehad shown how difficult it was to define a registrable interest and it seemed desirable to remit this aspect to a Select Committee of theHouse for detailed consideration.    If the Cabinet agreed he would now put this proposal to the Opposition Parties forthwith, discuss it with the Parliamentary Labour Party next week, and then tablethe necessary Resolution in time for it to be debated, and theSelect Committee set up, before the Whitsun Recess.
THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said theCabinet agreed that the recommendation of the Liaison Committeewas attractive in that it would give a firm lead in the setting up ofa compulsory public register of Members1 interests while assisting the House to reach a sound judgment on the definition of the interests to be included and on the best method of enforcement.    There wasa risk that the proposal to set up a Select Committee might giverise to charges of delayj but these could be dealt with byemphasising the complexity of the matter and by requiring theCommittee to work to a strict timetable.    It would be desirable for Parliamentary business to be arranged, if practicable, so thatthe debate could take place early enough for the Select Committeeto have its first meeting before the Whitsun Recess.    TheResolution should empower the Committee to sit during the recess and the aim should be to have the Committee :s report completed,and the consequent Resolutions debated, before the Summer Recess.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister*summing up of their discussion and invited theLord President of the Council and the Chief whip to proceed accordingly.2
si?&apos;. :L:;r;FOREIGNiFFAIRSijiddle East3. THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN and commonwealth AFFAIRS said that he had received a message from the American Secretary of State, Dr Kissinger, saying thathis current talks in the Middle East were proving very difficult.He felt however that there was still a slightly better than evenchance of securing a disengagement of the Syrian and Israeliforces which was the immediate objective.    If this was not obtained there could well be a resumption of full scale fighting inthe Golan Heights;  and the position of President Sadat of Egyptcould be undermined and the threat of interference with oil supplies to the West might be revived.    Dr Kissinger had held a meeting in Cyprus with the Soviet Foreign Minister, Mr Gromyko, andtheymight have a further meeting before Dr Kissinger returned to america.The Cabinet -1. Took note of the statement by theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary.EuropeanCommunityTHE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the meetings of the Council of Ministers in Brussels on 6 May hadbeen overshadowed by the decision of the Italian Government, inthe light of prolonged and severe balance of payments difficulties,to introduce an import   deposit scheme.    As a result, and becauseof the inefficiency of Council proceedings, there had been no timeto discuss some other important matters.    The Italian importdeposit scheme had encountered strong criticism because it causeddifficulties for other member states who could argue that theapplication of import controls to intra-Community trade conflictedwith the Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) and with the principlesof the Community&apos;s customs union.    Both the Council of Ministers(Foreign Affairs) and the Council of Ministers (Agriculture) had therefore spent considerable time discussing the scheme and possible modifications aimed at making it more acceptable to other member states and more compatible with Community rules.    Butit had been recognised at the end of the day that the ItalianGovernment had no option but to take strong measures in the face of a critical economic situation and that the Community must acceptthe situation.More generally the meetings underlined the current doubts withinthe Community as to its future objectives.    It had been suggestedthat there was widespread pessimism at present in Western Europeabout the future of democratic institutions.    This was perhapsreflected in the Italian situation; many Italians regarded the
Cornmunity as essential since it imposed from outside a disciplinewhich Italy&apos;s own political institutions had failed to maintain.The Community was now entering a period of reappraisal quite apart from our own aims for renegotiation.    The recent changesin leadership in the three major member states together with theeconomic and monetary difficulties which all members currentlyfaced could lead to a major transformation by the autumn.    T)ierenegotiation of the United Kingdom terms of membership might then take place against a changed background of Community thinkingboth on internal matters and on relationships with other countries.This could be to our advantage in renegotiation and in the shapingof the future of Europe.The Cabinet -2. Took note.
EUROPEAN 4. The Cabinet considered a note by the Secretary of StateECONOMIC for Energy (C(74) 38) to which was attached a paper about theCOMMUNITY formation of a common energy policy within the EuropeanENERGY POLICY Economic Community (e.c.),,THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY said that the ministerial Committee on Energy had recently approved proposals about the line which the United Kingdom should adopt towards thedevelopment of a Community energy policy, and had invited him,in view of the importance of the issues involved, to report them tothe Cabinet.    The Summit meetings of October 1972 in Paris and december 1973 in Copenhagen had agreed general expressions of intent to work towards such a policy, but Httle progress had yetbeen made.    During the coming months there would be various international discussions of these matters, and he himself was dueto see the Vice President of the Commission concerned(M. Simonet) later that day.    A Community policy however was likely to confer little advantage on the United Kingdom, since bythe late 1970s we could expect to be more or less self-sufficient inthe supply of energy;  and it was arguable that the main aim of theproposals which the Commission had now tabled for discussion wasto secure control over our supplies of North Sea oil and gas.Although it would not be in our wider interests to block all progress towards a Community energy policy, we should take care not toenter on commitments which we might later regret,,    We couldsupport some of the Commission^ proposals, and collaborate in research on longer term developments like the use of solar energy and tidal barriers; but proposals for Community control of the oilmarket which would undermine our own control of our indigenoussupplies should be firmly resisted.In a brief discussion there was general support for this view.    Inparticular any attempt to establish Community control over north sea oil would be particularly unwelcome to Scottish opinion, andany concession in this area would be turned to advantage by theGovernments political opponents in Scotland.    It was further suggested that if, as proposed in paragraph 9(b) of C(74) 38, weshould not refuse to participate in work directed towardsincreasing coal and nuclear supplies, we should make it clear thatour agreement to engage in studies of this kind stopped some wayshort of collaboration: we should not allow the Commission orother members of the Community to suppose that they had an invitation to interfere in our own coal industry, or that we wereprepared to underwrite the grandiose French investment in nucleardiffusion plant.The Cabinet -Approved C(74) 38 subject to the amendmentof paragraph 9(b).5   &apos;
5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Employment about the position of the Alkali Inspectorateunder the Health and Safety at Work Etc Bill (C(74) 37)THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR EMPLOYMENT said that at a recent meeting of the Home! Affairs Committee it had been agreedthat the clauses in the Health and Safety at Work Etc Bill affectingthe inclusion of the Alkali Inspectorate should be deleted, and that instead there should be a power by Order to apply the Bill&apos;sprovisions at some future date to the field covered by the Alkali Actand Inspectorate.    He had been unable to attend the meetingpersonally but his position had been reserved.    The courseapproved by the Committee was in his view a,mistake and might even in the end lead to the withdrawal of the Bill.    It would makeit necessary to support an amendment for the exclusion of theAlkali Inspectorate which had been put down by a Conservativebackbench member of the Standing Committee; but the amendmentwas unlikely to commend itself to most Opposition Members, bearing that mind that the Bill as introduced by the previous administration had applied to the Alkali Inspectorate.    Exclusion would be contraryto the recommendations of the Robens Committee and would beobjected to by many Government supporters.    It would in particularbe highly unwelcome to the Trades Union Congress, who wouldsuspect that an amendment at so late a stage could have been made only in response to the representations which had been made by the confederation of British Industry.    Moreover, the exclusion of theAlkali Inspectorate would renew the disquiet, which he had withsome success been working to allay, which the National Union of mineworkers felt about the inclusion of the Mines and QuarriesInspectorate in the Bill, and would lead to renewed pressure, whichit would be difficult to resist, for the latter Inspectorate to be excluded also.    In that event one of the major principles underlying the Bill - the establishment of unified machinery for dealing withhazards to the health of workers and of the general public arisingat places of work - would be imperilled.    There was no doubt acase for reviewing the functions of the Alkali Inspectorate; but theBill as it stood would help in the immediate future to provide more effective control over unhealthy emissions to the air from industry,while at the same time presenting no obstacle to a review of theAlkali Inspectorate.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE ENVIRONMENT said that,in response to mounting criticism of the Alkali Inspectorate, he wasabout to propose the establishment of an authoritative working partyto report on the administration of air pollution policies,,    It was undesirable to pre-empt any decisions which this body might reach,and in particular to risk two changes in rapid succession in thearrangements for managing the Alkali Inspectorate, which would6
have a damaging effect on the morale of the Inspectorate as wellas being presentationaily embarrassing.    The Labour Party,when in opposition, had not reached a firm view about the futureof the Alkali Inspectorate; and the Inspector ate1 s present criticswere not advocating its transfer to the Health and SafetyCommission but rather its unification with the local authorities1Clean Air Inspectorates, which carried out the major volume ofwork in this field.    It would therefore be unwise, pending the !outcome of the inquiry, to separate the Alkali Inspectorate fromthe relevant local authority inspectorates and also from the CleanAir Advisory Council and the Royal Commission on EnvironmentalPollution.    There seemed no good reason to fear serious political consequences from excluding the Alkali Inspectorate from the Bill,pending the working party  s report; nor should there be any increased difficulty in preventing the exclusion of the Mines andQuarries Inspectorate, which had completely different functions.In discussion, it was argued that this was not a matter which appeared to be giving rise to strong political feelings and that inany event opinion amongst Government supporters was divided.There was a growing feeling that the organisation and functions ofthe Alkali Inspectorate should be subjected to a rigorous review;but such a review would not be helped and might even be hinderedif the Inspectorate were at this stage transferred to the Health and safety Commission, even though the inquiry might in the end showthat this was in fact the best course.    On the other hand, it was argued that the Labour Party had given a good deal of thought tothis matter when in opposition and had broadly supported therecommendations of the Robens Report,    Recent incidents at lead and other factories had shown the importance, from the point ofview of ensuring the safety of employees and the public alike, of placing the relevant inspectorates under unified management.This would be provided by the Health and Safety Commission, andone of its further merits was that a major part would be played inits affairs by the trade unions, who were very sensitive toenvironmental considerations generally, as well as to matters affecting health and safety at work.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said thatthere were strong arguments in favour of not disturbing the presentposition of the Alkali Inspectorate, and in particular for notseparating it from the parallel local authority inspectorates.    on balance, however, the Cabinet accepted the view of the Secretaryof State for Employment that the Bill should not be amended soas to exclude the Alkali Inspectorate.    The Inspectorate, and responsibility for the Alkali Act, should therefore be transferredunder the new legislation to the Health and Safety Commission.&quot;      -...7   ,
The Alkali Inspectorate should remain an identifiable group andthe Commission should be responsible to the Secretary of State forthe Environment for their work.    It should, however, be made clear that a general study of arrangements concerning air pollutionwas to be carried out and that this might in due course makenecessary some adjustments in the Commission^ responsibilities.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;summing up of their discussion.8
ROAD TANKERDRIVERS6.        The Cabinet had before them a minute, dated 8 May 1974,from the Secretary of State for Energy to the Prime Minister, abouta possible wage dispute involving the drivers of road tankers.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR ENERGY said that the two major oil companies, Shell Mex &amp; BP and the Esso petroleum company, which together accounted for about three-quarters ofthe oil that was moved by road, were having difficulty in thecurrent wage negotiations with their road tanker drivers.    Theyhad made an offer which was at the Stage 3 limit.    The transport and General Workers Union (TGWU) Delegates1 Conference wouldbe held on 13 May, and it was possible that they would vote in favourof the offer.    If not there was a danger of industrial action.    he understood that the Secretary of State forpEmployment did not regard the danger as imminent; but he thought it right to warn the Cabinetthat if a strike did take place it would cause considerable disruption.Motorists would rush to fill up their tanks, and filling stations would run out of stock quickly.    The only way to safeguard vitalservices and food distribution would be to use troops to get somesupplies through and to provide by Order that those supplies shouldbe available only to priority users.    This would require a proclamation of a State of Emergency as well as the making of orders under the Fuel and Electricity (Control) Act 1973.     The plans were tobe reviewed by the Civil Contingencies Unit on 10 May.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said thatthe Cabinet took note of the situation and agreed that if a strikeoccurred itwould be necessary to take prompt emergency action.Meanwhile it was essential to avoid making any public statementsthat might cause a run on the filling stations or panic buying of food.The Civil Contingencies Unit should keep the- situation closely underreview.The Cabinet -1. Took note, with approval, of the summing upby the Prime Minister.2. Invited the Home Secretary to arrange forthe Civil Contingencies Unit to keep a close watchon the situation and report urgently to the cabinet if emergency action was required.
7.        The Cabinet had before them a letter dated 8 May 1974 fromthe Private Secretary to the Secretary of State for Industry to thePrivate Secretary to the Prime Minister, to which was attached adraft letter for the Secretary of State to send to the Chairman of thePost Office.THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that the staffsituation in the Post Office was serious.    Members of the civil and Public Services Association and the Society of Civil Servantswere already taking industrial action, and there was a risk thatthis would spread since the Union of Post Office Workers (UPW)had been disappointed with the limited pay offer that had been madeto them.    The Chairman of the Post Office, Sir William Ryland,thought it essential to offer talks with the unions before the UPWbegan their annual conference.   Sir William Ryland accepted thatthe talks would have to be without commitment on either side, andthat any wage settlement would have to be in the context of thepolicy which was adopted to follow the statutory pay policy.    BeforeSir William Ryland met the unions the following afternoon it wouldbe necessary to make the Governments views on the question oftalks available to the Board in writing.    One course would be toagree to talks being opened with a view to reaching a fresh pay settlement; but this -would cost at least  110 million and he did not recommend it.    On the other hand the Government could not preventtalks taking place, especially as the UPW had a good case for along term review of their pay.    Accordingly, after consultingSir William Ryland and the trade unions, he thought it right toencourage the Board and the unions to open the talks, but at thesame time to make it clear that the Government could not at thisstage enter into any commitment.    In his letter he would proposeto indicate that, although the Government had concluded that therewas not sufficient ground for the issue of a general consent on the pay of the Post Office workers, they recognised that it was desirable for the Board and the unions to begin talks; that the government considered that besides pay the talks should cover the tariff and the investment implications of whatever was concluded; and that the talks would be without commitment on either side or by government, and their outcome would have to be examined in the context of the social contract and of developments in prices policy.Sir William Ryland disliked the suggestion that the talks should take account of tariffs and investment, but he himself thought it right that any pay proposal should be considered in the light of its implications for tariffs, and there would be advantage in includinginvestment also as the unions were anxious to see the recentinvestment cuts restored.    The inclusion of these subjects would lead to a wider discussion, perhaps on the same lines as the currentexamination of the coal industry; he hoped that the system of planning agreements would encourage the wider use of discussions10
of this sort, leading to a system of free wage bargaining withinprice constraints,    A letter on the lines that he had proposedmight help to forestall militant resolutions at the UPW conference which the Prime Minister was to attend.In discussion it was argued that although the Government had no power to prevent the Post Office and the unions from entering intowage negotiations, it would be dangerous to encourage them to doso.    The teachers and nurses, who, like the Post Office workers,had a strong case for a general increase in pay, would be encouraged to reopen their Stage 3 settlements.    Pay increases for these three categories could cost the Exchequer some 400 million a year, which would be equivalent to 1 per cent of thenational wage bill.    Moreover, it would then become impossiblefor the General Secretary of the Trades Union Congress to hold tohis policy of helping the Government to maintain the Stage 3 limitsuntil a voluntary policy could be introduced.    The RetailConsortium and the food manufacturers would also become lessinclined to co-operate in a voluntary agreement on food prices,on which the negotiations were at a crucial stage.   If, on the ptherhand, the Secretary of State were to write in terms which avoidedencouraging the opening of talks, the UPW might still resolve to open negotiations, but there would then be no need for theGovernment to express any opinion or for the Prime Minister to say anything of substance at the UPW conference.    The Governmentwould still be faced, at the end of the negotiations, with the problemof deciding whether to issue a consent, but at least there would by then have been time to take proper account of the repercussionsfor other groups.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that the draft letter circulated by the private secretary to the Secretary of State for Industry should be amended so as not to offer any Government encouragement for talks betweenthe Post Office Board and the unions.    It might still be possible,however, to include the suggestion that if the talks did take placethey should cover the tariff and investment implications of whateverwas concluded for pay.    For his speech at the UPW conference hewould need to have available a form of words that would reserve theGovernments position without provoking an unnecessarily hostile reaction.11
Cabinet Office9 May 197412Invited the Secretary of State for Industry,in consultation with the Secretary of Statefor Employment -i. To revise the draft letteron the lines indicated in the summing up.ii. To arrange for the drafting of an appropriate passage for use if necessary by the Prime Minister at the Union of post Office Workers conference.


</content>
</cab>
