<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/18/0 images: 10-11</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                  Intelligence Bureau,                       Department of Information.                              B\W/007.Weekly Report on Poland. -VII.      (27th June, 1917.)     The answer given    the Central Powers to the Council ofState on June 8 has had the reception and effects foreshadowedin our report of June 13..   It was found unsatisfactory hutyet it rendered it difficult for the Council of State to carry.out their threat of resigning in a body.   The extreme Lefturged once more that they should do so and thus throw the burdenof further action and initiative on the occupying Powers.   Butthe opinion of those who favour a policy of &quot;conciliation11towards the Central Powers has been finally accepted, and thetask of preparing proposals for the future organisation of thePolish government on the basis offered by the Central Powers hasbeen assigned to a Joint Comnittce consisting of ten membersof the Council of State and (so far) of ten members invited fromoutside.   The success of the &quot;moderates&quot; is no doubt due to someextent to the support wla&amp;ch they now receive from the aristocraticbranch of the late pro-Russians.   Among the ten members of theJoint Committee invited from outside are Prince Z. Lubomirski,President of the City of Warsaw, Count Julius Tarnowski andM. Jan de Stecki, who in December 1916 had refused to join theCouncil of State; further Prince E. Sapieha, President of theCentral Committee of the Boards of Guardians, and Count AdamTamowski, late Austro-Hungarian ambassador at Sofia andWashington.   So far not a single Jew is on the Joint Committeeand it is unlikely that any representative of the Jews, who form
tone-sixth of the population of Russian Poland,  will be invited.     The moving spirits of the reconciliation of the&apos;pro-Austrianand a branch of the pro*Rusaian conservatives which is nowevidently taking place in Russian Poland  on the basis of co-operation vrith the Central Powers, seem to be Prince Z. Lubomirski,hitherto the most prominent statesman in  the pro-Russian camp,and the notorious Count Adam Tarnowski, with whom the former isconnected by marriage;  their endeavours seem to have also the supportof Archbishop Kakowski.     The students1 strike at,  and the closing of,  the WarsawUniversity and Technical High School - the only events in Polanddealt with by the British Press during the past week - are ofsmall importance.   The conflict was caused by some high-hahdednesson the part of the German authorities, but in its  further develop-ment the Polish students have  shown a certain amount of pre-sumption and lack of judgment  and have acted contrary to theadvice of more responsible people.   This is an incident whichis not likely to have any far-reaching consequences.                                       LBH.

</content>
</cab>
