<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/18/0 images: 101-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Telegram from Viceroy,  Home Department,  dated.         .      ISth June 1917*   .     Following Comunique issued by Government of Madrasrepeated for your information &quot;In the exercise of the powerconferred on him by Bule three of Defence of IndiaConsolidation Rules 1915 His Ixcelleney the Governor inCouncil lias directed service of Orders on Mrs. AnnieBesant, Mr. CS. Arundale and Mr. B.P. Kadla prohibitingthem from attending or taking any part in any meeting, fromdelivering any lecture, from making any speech and frompublishing or procuring publication of any writing orspeech composed by them, placing&apos; their correspondence undercensorship and directing further that after the expiry ofa brief prescribed period they shall cease to reside incity of Madras or district of Chingleput,  and shall takeup their residence and remain within any one of the followingsix areas, Kilgiri district, Coimbatore district,  Bellarydistrict, Palni Hills, Shevaroy Hills, and the Municipal townof Yizagapatam/V
        Telegram from President, Bombay Association        to.Secretary of State for India dated 27th                       June 191?.     By direction of Council Bombay Presidency AssociationSir Binsha Idulji Wacha President Association lias honourto send following telegram to Prime Minister Secretary ofState for India Mr. Asquith after requesting Viceroy tocable it officially to Secretary of-State Council BombayPresidency Association draw earnest attention of PrimeMinister and Cabinet United lingdom and Secretary of Statefor India to grave situation which has arisen all overIndia owing to internment of Mrs. Besant and Messrs.Arundale and fadia by arbitrary and unjustifiableapplication of Defence of India Act by Madras Governmentthe step taken by that Government has produced unprecedentedferment tlircughout country which is bound to increase in .volume and intensity unless it is immediately retracedCouncil regret that policy of repression never successfulanywhere in suppressing national aspirations for politicalfreedom should have been resorted to by authorities inIndia at this juncture when India having- spontaneouslyrallied, to help of England in cause of lapire was pouringforth money and shedding blood on various battlefieldsalong with rest of Sapire in cause of liberty justice andrighteousness for which England and her great Allies werecarrying on present war at such heavy sacrifice of lifeand wealth statesmanship would dictate for India policy fardifferent from this at such time Council therefore deeplydeplore entire lack of imagination and of political foresightand judgment which is responsible for this policy ofrepression and earnestly appeal that Imperial Government may
  lose no time in ordering its reversal Council trust that.  consideration of upholding official  prestige will not&apos;he  allowed by Imperial authorities to influence their decision  and embitter situation Council feel  constrained  to point  out that this policy of repression is being construed  as an  attempt on part of authorities in India to  force Indian  public to accept without demur such  postwar reforms of minor  character as Government of India are believed to have  formulated without giving effect to  essential features of-  scheme of reforms which Indian national Congress and all  India Muslim League have conjointly framed  and adopted as a  definite step towards self-government for India  within.  Ifepire which, they desire (roverosent.  to take at close of &apos;  War Council pray that in order to  allay acuteness of present  situation and prevent its becoming still more critical  Imperial Government  will be  pleased besides directing  forthwith rectification of blunder which Madras  Government  has committed in interning Mrs. Besant  and.  her two co-workers  to  announce authoritatively  and unequivocally that it  is..  the aim and object  of British  policy  to confer self-  government on India  at  an  early date and to  direct Government  of  India to jmblish immediately for public  discussion postwar  reforms  which they may  propose as  a substantial and  immediate step in furtherance  of this policy publication of  such proposed reforms for public criticism before they are  finally  shaped and promulgated would be in consonance with  precedent  established - in herd Mintos regime ^en Lord  Morley was Secretary of State  for  India Council fully  appreciate great. strain which exigencies of war impose  on  time  and  energies of Imperial authorities but having  regard,  to gravity.of&apos; situation at present moment in. India  and  need for  immediate consideration and prompt action with  a view  to  assuage intense public feeling which has been                                                 aroused
aroused Council pray that imperial Government will bopleased to deal without&apos;delay with situation is India inspirit of courageous and true statesraanship.

</content>
</cab>
