<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/18/0 images: 278-286</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Intelligence Bureau,    Department of Informat ion.           BWA/007.              Weekly Report on Au atria-hung ;.ry.   VII. .                        (30th June.)     It is now possible to summarise the course of the latestAustrian crisis.    Count Clam-Martinic,&apos;fair was due -not somuch to his lack of statesmanship as to the gradual culminationof the situation in which he ha;&apos; tried to square, the circle.V/hen he first  took office he allowe;:V it to he supposed that histendency would be in a more Slav direction; but no positive actionof his can be  adduced .to justify such a theory.    For nearlysix months, he  consistently hedged and avoided any concrete steps,but even before Parliament met it was notorious th\t he stoodcommitted to a definitely German solution of internal problemsin Austria.   his speech in the Reichsrat on June 14 - foilov/ingupon the Speech from the Throne - definitely alienated the Slave,without really satisfying the Germans by a no-compronise policy.The weakness lay in the government rather than in Parliament.&quot;Lack of leadership&quot; is the Socialist Aftbeiter Zeitung&apos;g summaryof its faults, and never wa? that lack - it &apos;io inherent, in theracial divisions of the State - so much in evidence.   irvon oneof the leading German-Bohemian papers openly complained that thePremier &quot;seems to have no official knowledge of-the living, forcesin the State and in Parliament&quot;.     In order  to secure a Parliamentary majority, Clam-Martinichad.two possible alternatives - (1)  to rely upon  the&apos;German blockwhile buying Polish oupport--&quot;by special cone ess ion s; or (2) tothrow himself  on the support of a Slav block (Polesy Czechs,Jugo-Slavs and Ruthenes) and risk German opposition.   The latterwas only conceivable as a policy if the Emperor was prepared to
break with the Dual System and defy the Magyars;  and of thisthere is absolutely no sign.    The continual emphasis laid byClam-Mart in ic  on  the word &apos;Austria&apos; and &apos;Austrian&apos;  only servedto bring  out  the fact that every one in Austria, except: a fewbureaucrats and federalists,  thinks not of Austria but merely ofhie own racial group.     Attitude  of  the Poles.   What rendered Clam-Hartinic*sposition finally  untenable was the attitude of the Polish Club.In it there are two main  tendencies - (a)  the conservatives whoalways tend to welcome co-operation with &quot;the powers that be&quot; and(b) the radical &quot;maximalists&quot;, of whom the largest group is thepeasants Party.    Though  the  driving force of the latter tendencyand indeed of  the whole Club  has been more and more the socialistleader, Mr.  Daszynski, the Club selected as its new president Mr.Lazarski, a democrat not without conservative leanings.    Under  hisleadership the Polish&apos;Club has been in close touch with the otherSlavs, but has given no sign  of anything which could fairly bedescribed as Slav solidarity.   The attitude of the Poles towardsCount Clam may be described as personal.   They resente:&quot;! the v;ayin which he continued to  play with the question of Galician autonomy;but their decisive grievances were the maintenance of militaryadministration, the insistence on the German language on therailways, the  use of German in Courts Martial for civilians,  andabove all the  continuance of economic exploitation and the refusalto concede their  wery extensive claims for financial compensation.Their resentment  turned also  against the Ministers of nationalDefence and Railways,  General Georgi and Dr,  Porster.    Pinally,though Mr. Lazarski made  a conciliatory speech in the Reichsrat,the more extreme  elements insisted upon a  breach, and the polishClub unanimously  accepted a motion of Mr.  Daszynski to the effect(1) that it will  not support  the present Premier, but  is readyto negotiate with a new government, and (2)  that  it will vote
the necessary state credits, &quot;in so far as the new governmenthas its confidence.     Count Qlam-ilartinic resigned rather than be defeated on theBudgeti   The Emperor showed reluctance to part with him andcommissioned him to attempt a reconstruction of the Cabinet.   Por /two days the inspired press of Vienna propounded a scheme fora &quot;Ministry of the Peoples&quot;, in which the Ministries of Interior,finance, Railways, Education, Defence and Pood would be in thehands of high officials; while there would be seven specialministers e?ach representing a racial group.   The fleue greie Pressewith clumsy openness described this as a necessary answer to&quot;the slanders of the Entente and their Ifote to President Wilson&quot;,and also as necessary &quot;in order that Austria should have therespect of Europe and be listened to at the Peace Congress&quot;.   Theclerical Christian Socialists were the first to hold aloof, formallydeclaring that they did not regard the present time as suited forParliamentary Cabinets.    The Poles maintained their hostilityto Clam; the other races refused to accept the shadow for thesubstance.   A meeting of the Southern Slav, Czech and Rut hen edeputies decided upon joint opposition.   The President of theSouthern Slav Club, Pather Korosec, was summoned in audience bythe Emperor and received authority from the three Slav groups tospeak to him in their name.   T/hat took place is of course notknown, but the issue has shown that the Crown^s intervention hasagain been as unsuccessful as it was last month, -when the Czechleaders were summoned to the Palace of Laxenburg (21st May) butpersisted in putting forward their extreme claims at the openingof the Reichsrat.     Count Clam&apos;s last despairing effort was to invite the Germansocialist leader, Dr. Renner (who holds in Austria a special positionowing to his important books advocating racial autonomy but who
 during the war.has takSn a definitely German line)  to accept office.    Renner  declined,- ostensibly because no socialist can share in  the  government  of a State  at war.    On 21st June Count Clam definitely abandoned his efforts,  and  has since been appointed Governor  of Montenegro.      ^*J8^-*x^xl.m^Q3fo^ftSfrHis successor as Austrian Premier,        Z  &apos;       is Sr.  von Seidisr,/a not very prominent departmental  head in the Ministry  of -Agriculture&apos;  and with  one exception all his&apos; colleagues are  equally colourless permanent officials.    Politically they represent  nothing,  and it is practically  certain that they liave been selected  with a view to  providing no clue whatever  to their attitude towards parties and groups.    During the  past twenty years there have been several cases  in Austria  of Cabinets formed of bureaucrats; but  even  in the weakest  of these there have  always  been a few men of mark.    The Sei&amp;ler, Cabinet represents the low water lino. The  solitary  politician  which it contains is Kerr Hattaja, a fairly prominent  member,  of the Christian  Socialist  party,  which is singularly lac kin e, in leaders.   It  is worth noting that during the&quot;recent debate he  laid stress on Britain&apos;s responsibility for the war  and invited the government to placard extracts  from the Entente press at  every street corner,  as an  incentive to resistance.    He also^laid great stress on the peace  efforts  of the  Pope and of the Catholic  Congress in Zurich last February.    Iierr IAattaja, who Was  present at this Congress,  is in  close touchywith Kerr Srzberger and  with  the  South German Catholics:  his  selection  may posaibly have some connection with the latter&apos;s efforts to organise an inter- national  peace campaign  of a clerical kind.      Dr.  von  Seidler at  once announced openly the provisional character of  his  Cabinet,  and it is  therefore too soon to expect any  definite  policy from him.   On 27th June,  however,  he made an important  statement in the Reichsrat in answer to an interpolation
determine their  own fate as a hasis for peace and informed theHouse that he  did so after consultation with the Foreign Minister,Count Czernin.    Th^. Ane1;r-o*Enn^                  he declared,took its stand on the constitution which specially-reservedto the Emperor the right to conclude peace: the interests andrequirements of  the Austrian peoples were therefore in thaEmperorhands,  and tiie^goromment firmly^^iliJae4--any otherbasis for peace  negotiations.     The full  reports of recent debates in the Austrian Parliamenta fortnight ago  are now to hand, and throw startling light uponAustrian conditions during the war.   Various Czech deputies maderevelations as to the treatment of the thousands of innocentcivilians in internment camps in Bohemia and Lower Austria.   TheThe Dalmatian  Croat poet Tresic-Pavicic declared that all suchaccounts were  mere trifles compared with what had been done amongthe Southern Slavs, but that &amp;e dared not tell the truth, as hispre-war speeches in Parliament had been used by the PublicProsecutor as  the basis of a 2 years1 detention, ending in histrial for high treason, and he did not wish the same to happenagain.   The Austrophil Ruthene teacher Petruszewycz describedthe ill-treatment of the Ruthene population and said that Germans,Poles and Magyars had all played the executioner towards them.The Polish Socialist Daszyn3ki declared that the return to Galiciabrought with it  &quot;gallows and murder&quot;, and that 30,000 persons,and possibly twice that number, had been executed.   Other Czechdeputies interpellated regarding the brutal military suppressionof food riots  in a Czech county town last April.   The CzechSocialist Stribmy, after giving further details as to the reignof terror in Bohemia, openly greeted the advent of a new era inwhich the democratic republic is recognised as the highest form ofhuman government.   &quot;Austrian patriotism,&quot; he declared in answer
to Count  Clam,   is  only  an  artificially cultivated plant,  butan extremely  rare one.    It has  been  Austria^ fate to be  ruledby a reactionary bureaucracy which identifies the interests ofGermanism with  those  of  the State.&quot;   The Young Czech deputyDr.  Stransky, though  in  his speech he paid compliments to  theyoung Emperor as guiltless for the  war,  roundly declared that theState and the dynasty had trampled under foot the rights andliberties of  the Csech nation, and warned the Premier that thetime is near  at  hand  when Austria&apos;s Peter and Paul fortress willrelease its prisoners.    It is significant that the CzechParliamentary Club  as a  whole sent affectionate greetings  toDr.  Kramarz in  his  prison,     Hungary.    The Hew  Cabinet.   Now that Count Esterhazy&apos;s listis complete,  further  details may be given regarding the rathercontradictory elements which compose  it.    In it the extreme leftwing is represented by M. Vazecnyi, a clever and very eloquentJewish lawyer who has long  enjoyed great vogue with the lowermiddle class  in  Budapest.    A moderate Jewish organ in Austria&quot;places&quot;  him  in  outlook  as  &quot;halfway between Jaures and Clemeneeau&quot;.It is certainly  a sign of the times that this very typicaldemagogue should be Minister of  Justice in-a semi-feudal Government.     Count Batthyany&apos;s appointment as Minister a latcre (i.e.  tothe Court) is also  remarkable.   \7idely known as &quot;Storn-Batthyany&quot;(a pun on his Christian  name in  Magyar),  he did more than  any oneto break  down the Coalition Cabinet in 1909 and to form a  new&quot;forward&quot; wing  of the Independente party.    It was he too  whopushed his leader Count  Karolyi  a  year ago into active opposition.He is slightly  less illiberal than other Magyar politicians inthe question  of the non-ka&amp;yar nationalities.    His new positionis a guarantee  that the  reformers  will retain the ear of the King.     M. Gratz/  the  Minister of finance,  began his career as anadvocate  of reform  12 or 15 years  ago:  but early this year had
received through. Tisza a post in the Joint Foreign Office, whichseemed to suggest a turn -&quot;towards the official attitude.     M. Ugron,  a son of a former prominent Independence leader ofnot too savoury reputation,  represents above all Magyar landedinterests in Transylvania.    Neither he nor Count Stephen Bethlen,a Transylvanian magnate, are likely to show undue leniency towardsthe Roumanians.     M. MezBssy (Agriculture) is an ultra-Agrarian.    Count Sichy,leader of the Clerical party, and Count Serenyi (who only recentlyleft Tisza*s party) hold a middle position, and may be regardedas buffers between majority  and minority,  between a radical and acurtailed form of Electoral  Reform - being neither very friendlynot very hostile to either view.   The Socialists are quitejustified in regarding Count Apponyi as &quot;the real fly in theointment&quot;.    He is the typical representative of the old oligarchicsystem, with his insistence  upon constitutional claims and hisdevotion to obsolete mediaeval traditions.    His position as aforemost champion of Magyarisation has been alluded to in previousreports.     The best proof of the conflicting and patchwork characterof the new Government is the fact that Count Apponyi,  in manyways its most prominent member,  has formally announced that hedoes not regard himself as committed to the new Premier&apos;s attitudein accepting the Ausgleich concluded by Count Tisza,  but reservesa free hand *for himself v/hen it  shall come up for Parliamentaryratification.     Count Esterhazy met Parliament on 21  June and made a lengthystatement of aims.    He proclaimed Electoral Reform  as the newGovernment1s whole raison dTetre, and whi^e avoiding  details.committed himself to reducing the age of the electors  from 30(as under the Act of 1913, which is on the  statute book but  hasnever taken effect) to 24, and to giving the vote without  any
qualification to all holders of the military Charles Cross.He also promised automatic registration, stricter measures againstbribery and corruption, and redistribution.   He accepts theballet (hitherto unknown in Hungary), but with the proviso thatit would only be applied, in constituencies where there are enoughvoters who &quot;read and write, to be able to &quot;exercise it seriously&apos;5.This would seem to be a device for maintaining open voting.bydeclaration in n on-Magyar constituencies, where it is one of thechief weapons- of the present regime of electoral comption.   Healso promised that the reform would be carried out &apos;fwith dueregard for the life interests of the Hungarian State&quot;.   In afurther phrase aimed at the non-Magyars he promised that &quot;inparts of the country where symptoms of a breakdown of loyalty tothe State have.- occurred, /the necessary steps will be taken tomaintain the principle of the military Magyar political nation&quot;.     The speech promises many social reforms - especially inhousing,  hygiene,  harvest, pensions, reconstruction, tradeinspection, etc..    He speaks of an extension of the ownershipof land,  but in terms of studied vagueness.   It describes thefinancial position as quite satisfactory; tut here-the latePremier Count Tisza at once sounded a strong note of alarm andWarning,  alluding to the vital need of self-denial and even hsreishunless the victory of HungaryJs gallant troops was to.be followedby her economic ruin.     Count Esterhazy closed  -,^ith the hope that an appeal to thecountry might be avoided in war time, but wa-rned the House thatif Electoral Reform should be delayed he would appeal from afictitious majority resting upon an unduly extended mandate,  tothe real majority in the elect or ate   Save for this firm note atthe end,  his speech had a, mild tone compared with that of CountTisza who followed with all his old vigour.   He not merelj&apos;-polemised against Andrassy for dragging the King&apos;s name  into the
 question of reform, but denounced the projected reform, expressing the hope that as God had defended Hungary for 1,000 years, He would do so in the future and that such a reform would never be realised.   He also strongly denounced the Czech pronouncements in the Austrian Parliament in fawour of the Slovaks, flung a &quot;Hands off&quot; at all who dare to assail Hungary*-s territorial integrity or the Dual System, and found fault with the AustrianPremier for not taking a stiffer line in the matter and for actuallynegotiating with the authors of such a pronouncement (i.e. the Czech  Club).    Count Esterhasybriefly endorsed Tisza&apos;s attitude &quot;as the confession of faith of the whole Hungarian (i.e. Magyar)nation&quot;.

</content>
</cab>
