<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/18/0 images: 321-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                           WAR CABfo&amp;T.SECRGv1                       SITUAfflOH . IiST  IKELAIfl).G.  g.  1361,                      &apos;:               Memorandum by the Chief &quot;Seoretary, for: Ireland.            (Circulated with reference  to War Cabinet 173,  Minute 24),1,       I proceed as desired by the .Jar Cabinet to. deai with theletter of Sir Bryan Mahon dated 25th June 1917* on the  question ofpublic order in Ireland, and the covering letter.of Lord Frenchdated 29th June 1917.2.       There is beyond doubt reason for great vigilance  in dealingwith the Irish situation,  That any definite  change of-method is re-quired is not apparent to me.  ITor has anyone yet suggested  any changeof method which1 would in my opinion be prudent or effective.   I wo;jwill state my view of the recent facts and present, position..,  v  .3.       The assembling of multitudes of people to welcome or to seethe released prisoners was: in inevitable result of the  release and ofcourse produced political excitement.  The decision not to attempt&quot;to prevent these assemblies&quot; was deliberately taken. Looking back  Ithink it was a right decision.  The occasion.was avowedly  one of-amnesty.  To.have attempteti: to suppress demonstrations  such  as tookplace in Dublin would have resulted in violence and probably in blood-shod. . ITo responsible person has yet suggested to me that  it wouldhave been a wise Course, either ih Dublin or  elsewhere..4.       Sir Bryan Mahon is right in saying there were  in  places dis-plays of disloyalty and of a spirit of insurrection. Certain incidentsof molestation of small parties of troops in  Dublin and of tho march-ing of bodies of men and display Of Irish Volunteer uniforms alsospiling up at the same time, and they gave cause for careful  policearrangements which I discussed with the I-olice authorities when theincidents were reported,5.      .1 assume that Dublin and Cork.are particularly referred to  inthe reference to disloyalty, and. a spirit of, insurrection.  The incidentsin question in Dublin occurred about a fortnight ago and in  Cork nineor ten days ago;  The Chief Commissioner of the Dublin  Police/reportedto me this morning &quot;there, was no disturbance  of public  order in Dublinlast week&quot;.  From Cork I was informed yesterday that at the  end ofthe week in which disorders occurred the extra police who  had beenbrought to the City were returned to their homes.6.The         The molestation of soldiers in Dublin has,  I think, ceased.    Chief Commissioner reported to-day that there had been no com-plaints in the past week.7*   .    She risks involved in open-air meetings and in the systematicmarching about of men, whether in regular formations or otherwise, Idiscussed with Sir Bryan Hahon, the Deputy Inspector-General RoyalSi?7 b0nsto&apos;&quot;bulary, and the Chief Commissioner,  when I was last inJ^blin and the matter was fresh,  and in view of-possible eventualities,i had drafts prepared on my return to London of amended Defence of                                                                  the
theHe-aim Regulations: to enable the Executive to deal with suchdemonstrations.  These were adopted,  and  are  in operation.   In caseof neec.-De teat the things in Question can now.be prohibited by the  oom-military authority.        :.-  Two illustrations occur to. me of the difficulty of1 deciding as to-, regressive action as to the prisoners.  One of the. [ablest and most trusted of the Irish. Roman Catholic Bishops said  to [nie to-day with regard to- the. released-prisoners .&quot;They would; .do., the.-. Government much more hafm in prison than they can now they are  at liberty&quot; i   .1s to meetings - on Sunday evening last an immense open-                                the&apos; Convention and&apos;the &quot;Partition  of                                     So far as I know no one thought11V.air meeting-to protest  againsxIreland&quot; was held  in Phoenix Paof prohibiting it  and there  was  no  disturbance of the peace.  Ibelieve that a prohibition of this  meeting would have produced scenesof disorder far worse than any which  have occurred in Dublin since&apos;the Rebellion.                                         *9.Outside of Dublin and Cork the releaseofI believenot                                    the prisoners has,been the occasion of Serious &apos; disturbances *   She  report:of the Royal  Irish  Constabulary which I have carefully read showed&apos; inthe rural  districts  a general&apos;absence  of violence or of-disorderwhich needed  severe  means of repression-o-  There was of: courseexcitement  and  there were In places rebel cries and -songs.  Thisno novelty.Is-lOe        Before  considering the ruestion of&apos;somethods  I  must refer to the statement in Sir&apos;Boae  possible  change&apos;/ of -MahohXs letter that&quot;the chief  factors  in the    mrestricSir Bryan nor  I was I thin)organization ofthe  unrestricted meetings  that were  allowed&apos;to take place&quot;                                          the last rebellion were     \                                                            : Heitlier .                            in Ireland during the-rebellions  Butall the evidence I have eeen convinces me that the-true cause of therebellion was the tolerated existence in Ireland&apos;for: many months ofarmed and disciplined forces of Volunteers whose leaders were able tolaunch them into,belligerent action against the Government wheneverthey thought fit to do so*  These forces no&apos;longer exist and unlessthey are permitted to revive I cannot see what serious insurrectionarymovement is possible in face of an armed Constabulary of nearly 10,000men and a military force such as that which is now in occupation of  thcountry.11*   ^ -  The question for immediate consideration at this time seemsto me to be whether the Executive should issue a-general prohibitionOf        - . (a) Meetings, and.          (b) Processions,as well as a prohibition of such things as          (c) The marching of men carrying hurley clubs - a dangerous                 practice, and of -          (d) The wearing of the Irish Volunteer uniform.          I think (c)  and (d) should be prohibited.&apos;  I framed the newRegulations
Reflations in order that they might &quot;be.   And being&quot; prohibited j.thev must at all costs be prevented.  A &quot;general prohibition.ofmeetings and -orocessions would I think be mischievous and probablyimpossible of&quot;enforcement,  At this moment, the Orange Lodges ofUlster are claiming to hold their usual processions, and the pro-valent opinion of the County Inspectors of Royal Irish Constabulary  .is as I gather that it would be unwise to forbid them.12c       Heretofore tho course pursued since I became Chief -Secretary has been to dec! with acts of lawlessness -when theyoccurred and only to prohibit by general prohibition things whichmust be and can be prevented, as for.example, drilling.  I am opposedto any coercive action except that of which experience from day today shows the necessity and affords the justification.  An attemptto suppress the mere vexatious incidents of disaffection among apopulation.of which a considerable section is notoriously disaffectedwill produce no good and would exasperate moderate Irish opinion.13.       Lord Frenches letter takes in my view a rather alarmist vie\:of the situation.  &quot;Disturbances&quot; we must face in Ireland and dealwith.  &quot;Disturbance&quot; in the insurrectionary sense which calls for mil? -tary action is no doubt talked of a great deal but in rny judgment isno more likely as a serious happening th;n it was a year ago0  Thereis at this time in Ireland as I believe a large measure of activesupport for the Government among the nationalist population.  Thissupport I desire to justify and Increase.  It would certainly be alienJated hy any general scheme of coercion which was not plainly calledfor by previous dangerous action of the malcontents,14,       I observe in Lord French1s letter a suggestion that &quot;thehands of the G.0.C in Ireland require strengthening&quot;.  I shall beglad to know what is this reinforcement which is desired *  She exist-ing powers of the Defence&apos;of tho Realm Regulations are enormous and Ithink ample,  She only restraint is that the competent militaryauthority must necessarily be subject to some control of the civilExecutive - that is of His Majesty1s Government.  Under our constitu-tion that seems.to me inevitable,15.&apos;       I ought to add perhaps that I. cannot recall any case at the &apos;moment in which a recommendation of the. Commander-in-Chlef In Irelandas to specific action which ought in his judgment to be taken has-beenover-ruled by civil authority.3rd July 1917:..(Intd.)   HoEoD,

</content>
</cab>
