<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/90/0 images: 375-377</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
BpAED OP AGrBICUlTTJKS j?OR SCOTUJTO. ^^Jpm for the Week. /16th October 1919;I. [ AgBIGtJL&apos;J?IJRB: ,&apos;1&apos;   Defopoe of the Boa to ft eolation 2M.In March 1917 tho Board took poocession of the Drumchapel Golf Course,- Bearoden, (Jlacgow, and arranged for its cultivation by the tenants of the farms from which the land was taken when the Golf Course was formed,      The land has been cropped by these farmers as agents of the Board during seasons 1917, 1913, and 1919, and the Board have now british.rated that they&apos;will withdraw from possession at the forthcoming term of Martinmas,2.   Sictormination of Rate,Grants amounting to  46:9/- and  100 respectively have been paid by the Board in aid of sohemes for tho destruction of rats organised in Oupar District and in the Eastern District of Haddingtonshiro;, in accordance with the conditions laid down in the offer made to looal Authorities in the Board1 a circular letter of 25th September 1917.    In Cupar District &quot;Liverpool Virus11 was supplied free of charge to applicants approved of by the Sanitary Inspector; 367 warrants in all being issued, and very good results were obtained.    The scheme in the Eastern District of Ka&amp;iingtonehire, which was adopted by the Board in 1917 ao a &quot;model&quot; soheme, was carried cut on the. usual lines, three skilled, rat-catchers being, engaged.-      Dogs, ferrets and traps were employed, and it was estimated that during the year ended 15th May last over 14,000 rats weic destroyed in this district.3,   Wart Disease of Potatoes (Scottish Seed Potatoes) Orderorm-------;-------------......&quot;........................ The provisions of this OrdeT, which waa roa.de by the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries in March last, require that any person in England or Wales who imports seed potatoes of a non-immune, variety from Scotland must previously obtain a declaration from the grower that his farm is free from V/art Disease and a certificate from this Department to the effect that no V/art Disease has been found on or within one mile of the farm on which the potatoes were grown.     During the Spring 1783 farms were certified by the Board in the terms of the Order.The despatch of seed potatoes of the early non-immune varieties for planting in England next year is now in progress, and the issue of certificates has recommenced.      Enquiries have been received from merchants and growers as to the possibility of obtaining certificates in the event of arrange-:ments being made for the export of their seed potatoes, to England.Owing to the difficulty experienced by consigning merchants and growers in furnishing their oustoners with copies of the required declaration and certificate in cases where several consignmenta of potatoes grown on the same farm are /O t
z..aro forwarded to different destinations in England, a eon-: cession was granted in the Spring1 by the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries whereby for the remainder of the season they accepted as a sufficient compliance with the requirements of the Order a declaration from the consignor to the effect that tho potatoes were $rown on a farm on which there was no Wart Disease and which had been certified in accordance with the terms of the Order.     Prior to. tho grant of this conoeesion as many an 50 copies of the Board1s.certificate were issued in respect of one farm, and already this-abason one merchant applied for the issue of 75 copies of a certificate.As a result of representations made to tho&apos; Board of Agriculture and fisheries it&quot;has been arranged that the conces. :sion. granted in tho Spring will be continued,this season, and an intimation to this effect is being -communicated to the merchants in Scotland who carry on an export trade in seed potatoes, with Englandrs.4.   Goat Keeping.Messrs John Swan and. Scno, Auctioneers, Edinburgh, havo arranged to hold a sale of goats on 5th November under the auspices of the Board.    A large number of breeders have indicai red their willingness to send goats to the sale, which,* it is hoped, will provide an opportunity to those desirous of taking up goat-keeping of securing good utility, and pedigree animals. The Board have offered prizes amounting to  12 to be awarded in competition in the various classes of animals exposed at the sale.5*   Scheme for Higher Agricultural draining.During the four weo&amp;s ended 14th October, 101 appli-:cations for Agricultural Scholarships, and 43 applications &quot;for Practical Agricultural Training Allowances havo been received by tho Board.Particulars of the disposal of all applications received to date are as followsAgricultural Scholarsniffa, .Recommended to the Board by the Ministry of 3Jabour   .. 372Granted by the Board     ............................... . 8*15Refused   &quot;     ,T    &apos;r        ......... .&apos;.v,..........,.......,. 105Withdrawn.&apos;.............,...................... 29j,r an s fe r r e d .....                           .......... *..... ...*......,.*.. i *. d 1Under consideration            ..................... 2Praotioal (Draining AllowancesRecommended to the Board by the Ministry of labour   .. 242Granted by the Board............................ e.... T5*S&quot;Refused   &quot;    iT      &quot;............ 41Withdrawn............................................ 20(Transferred   .........,,a.......,,,,.................. 5Under consideration................................. 19ifi!
I i 16*   yjainin^ of Disabled Officers.On let October, in accordance with an agreement come to at a conference hold in london In August, the responsibility for the agricultural training of effioors under the provisions of Article 7 of the Ifcoyal (Pensions) Warrant was transferred to the Board.The Article referred to provides for the payment of officers during training at the rate applicable to maximum die-:ablement (i.e. 100$ disability) whatever the degree of disable-:ment at which they may be assessed by Me&amp;ical Board, provided (1) the officer in in receipt of Disability Retired pay which is estimated to continue for a considerable portion of the period of proposed training;   ( ) that ho is through his disability medically unfit to return to his pre-war occupation;   and (3) that he has a reasonable chance of employment on the conclusion of his training.II.   EOBILI8A7I0P Of A&amp;RICPLTOAL JgggS,Of the total number of 10127 men applied for by the Board for demobilisation, reports show that 9302 men have been released to date.III.   LAMP SETTTOffl?,l.The total number of applications received from service men up to the 11th instant is 2,334.   Of these 603 have boen reported on.2.   Small Holding colonies Aots 1916-1918.^art^Tstjate,        &quot; &quot; &apos;A schema of sub-division lias been prepared and is under the Board&apos;s consideration for the constitution of 25 small holdings at tho term of Martinmas 1919.    These holdings will absorb an area of approximately 320 acres.   Of the remainder of the property suitable for sub-division, 2C9 aeras will be available at Fartin-:mas 1921 and 102 acres at Martinmas 1923.&amp; Small Landholders (Scotland) Act 1911.Arrangements have bean made for the constitution at Martinmas 1919 of one small holding at Humbie, Aberdour, Fife, (area - 6 acres, 0 roods, 23 poles:   rent -  11),    The holder will be an ex-service roan.

</content>
</cab>
