<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/90/0 images: 476-480</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
vmmmim of ?wm&amp; (exhibition) bill,1*    3?he. object of the Bill is to afford a measure of protection to rare wild birds by restricting tho trade in their plumagcu     India and car tain of tho Dominions have already passed measures restricting the oxport of plumage , wd. a prohibition of importation into the United Kingdom is desirable in order to assist in the prevention of smugglings The Bill is substantially in tho form in which it was passed by standing Committee B in 1914,8*    Tha Bill prohibits tha importation into the United Kingdom of the plumage of any wild bird  with tho exceptions mentioned below; and tho having in possession or sale of artyplumage imported in contravention of the Bill. 3,     others  it excepted from the general prohibition the plujaage. of birds inclu&amp;sd in the Schedule (at present only ostriches.and tider ducks) which may;&apos; however, be varied by the Board of Trade t of birds Imported alive; and of birdsordinarily used as articles of diit aid imported for that purposes     Power is given to tht Board of &apos;Iraae to grant licences, under such conditions and. regulations as they think fit; for the importation of specimens for museums or for the purpose of scientific research, or for any other special purpose should be glad to receive sanction for the introduction of this Bill into Parliament at an early date.4, o, mm17, 10. 19.
[9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.]  Importation of Plumage (Prohibition),DRAFTof aBILLtoProhibit the importation of the plumage of wild birds and A.D. 1919. the sale or possession of plumage illegally imported.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5 1. (1) Subject to the exceptions contained in this Act a Prohibition . person shall not import into the United Kingdom the plumage on imP0lta-n *ij i *  i tion ofof any wild bird. plumage.(2) Goods prohibited to be imported by virtue of this Act shall he deemed to be included among the goods enumerated 10 and described in the table of prohibitions and restrictions inwardscontained in section forty-two of the Customs Consolidation 39 &amp; 40 Viet. Act, 1876, and the provisions of  that Act and of any Act c- 36* amending or extending that Act shall apply accordingly.2. (1) The plumage of the following birds, namely        Exceptions 15 (a) birds for the time being included in the Schedule ^0701urohibi&quot;to this Act : .-.  importation.(b) birds imported alive:(c) birds asthorised to be imported by licence granted underthis Act: -20 (d) birds ordinarily used as articles of diet and importedfor the purpose of being so used: is excepted from the prohibition on importation imposed by this Act-(2) The Board of Trade may by order add to or remove from 25 the Schedule to this Act the name of any bird.. 204-2
2 Importation of Plumaye (Prohibition).   [9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1919. A.n order made under this provision shall specify the name of the species and of the order, if any, to which the bird mentioned in the order belongs.(3) The Board of Trade may grant to any person a licence under such conditions and regulations as they may think fit 5 authorizing the importation of specimens of birds for any natural history or other museum, or for the purpose of scientific research, or for any other special purpose.(4) Any importer claiming that the plumage of any bird is excepted from prohibition on importation under this Act on 10 the ground that the bird is being imported for any such purpose as aforesaid, shall on importation deliver to an officer of Customs and Excise, if required by any such officer, a written declara-tion of the purpose for which the bird is imported.Prohibition on possession or sale of plumage illegally imported.Interpreta tion.3.-(1) A person shall not have in his possession or be 15 concerned in selling any plumage which has been imported in contravention of this Act, or the plumage of any bird which having been allowed to be imported on the ground that it was to be used for a certain purpose has been or is being used for some other purpose. . r ,    20(2) If any person has in his possession or is concerned in selling any such plumage as aforesaid, he shall be liable on conviction under the Summary Jurisdiction Acts to a fine not exceeding five pounds in respect of the first offence, and to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds for the second or subsequent 25 offence, and the court before whom he is convicted may order the forfeiture or destruction of the plumage in respect of which the offence has been committed.(3) The  expression  &quot; person&quot; in this section shall not include a woman other than a woman engaged in the business 30 of importing, buying, or selling plumage.4. In this Act-The expression &quot; plumage &quot; includes the skin% or body of a bird with the plumage on it:The expression &quot;sell&quot; includes exchanging and letting 35 out on hire:The expression &quot; importer&quot; means the owner of or any person for the time being in possession of or benefi-
[9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5.]  Importation of Plumage (Prohibition). 3cially interested in the goods at and from the time of A-D-1919-importation until they are duly delivered out of the charge of the officers of Customs and Excise.b Short title.5. This Act may be cited as the Importation of Plumage 5 (Prohibition) Act, 1919.SCHEDULE.Ostriches, Eider d ticks.
Importation of Plumage (Prohibition).D HAFTof aBILLTo prohibit the importation of the plumage of wild birds and the sale or possession of plumage illegally imported.CLXVI.   (2.)lQth October 1919.204-2

</content>
</cab>
