<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/90/0 images: 535-535</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
14238.  20th October.  No. 111.Part I. 1. All quiet north of Kuram.2. Reported that Hakim of Khost, told Wazir and Mahsud Maliks in Matun, Maliks of all frontier tribes were going to &quot;Kabul to meet envoys from Germany, Russia, Turkey and Persia, to discuss their frontier relations with the British and Afghan Governments and advised them to continue to harass the British, as nothing more than a six months&apos; armistice had been arranged between the British and Afghans. Shah Daula, who lias returned to Wana from Khost,&apos;is spreading similar propaganda.3. Report of departure of Kabul troops from Matun definitely confirmed.4. Mahsuds are saying deaths among their party in Khost were clue to poison given, them by subordinate of Nadir Khan at the instigation of Tochi Wazirs.5. Pro-peace Mahsud gangs failed to raise representative jirga at Kaniguram on 15th October, and jirga postponed pending return of Maliks from Kabul.6. Some Ahmad zai and Mohamad Khel Waziris have arrived (corrupt group) to take up their winter quarters.7. Annual migration of Wana Waziris with flocks to Gomal plain has been hastened by bombing on 9th October, which had considerable moral effect.8. Seven miles of telegraph wire removed from Tochi road night of 14th-15th October by Waziris. Party from a large Waziri gang near Murtaza cut water supply on 17th October. 150 (corrupt group) looted from Tank district by Mahsuds on 14th October.9. Suliman Khel are coming down to Zarmelan to escape from a. disease resembling cholera, which lias broken out amongst Powinclahs.10. Larglia Sherannis reported collecting at Domandi (? near) Chaudwan in anticipation of punitive column.11. Reported from Meshed that the-Shrine custodians from Herat, travelling via JJala Murghab have entered Russian territory and proceeded to Panjdeh. At Muharram, Governor of Herat displayed special courtesy to Shiahs.   ...Part II.-Nil.Paras. 2, 10 and 11 have not been communicated to Press.

</content>
</cab>
