<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/90/0 images: 584-586</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AIll&apos;s Document is the94?liiNT OF AGRICULTURE AND TECHNICAL INSTRUCTION FOR IRELAND.POOD PRODUCTION SOHKMKS, IRELAND,Memorandum prepared in compliance with Chief Secretary&apos;sMinute of 17th March, 1917.Week ended 22nd October, 1919.The following is a &quot;brief statement on the work of the Department during the past woek in furtherance of inoroased Food Production in Ireland:-LOANS FOR AGRICULTURAL MACHINERY *The number of applications for loans for the purchase of Agricultural machinery received during the past week was 17, and the total value of maohinery ordered to dato Is  58,649.TILLAGE   SECTION.Satisfactory progress was made during the week with the w6rk of oomploting the orop survey of the country.PROGRESS OF FARM   WORK.Farmers were generally engaged during the week in the threshing of grain, tho lifting of potatoes^ and In early districts, in tho autumn cultivation of land.   On somo. farms a commencement was made with the pulling of the raangot crop.A large proportion of the potato crop is1 now lifted and stored, although in certain northern counties late varietjese on some farms aro keeping remarkably greerij and are not yet fit for lifting.   The yield of late varieties displays Considerably more variation than usual, but roports on this head beOtme moro encouraging as the season advances. *Turnips oontinuod to make good growth, and fair yields are now oxpeoted.A reduction in the pricey of oats and barley took placo during the past two weeks, in many farkets^ and farmers are^ already lodging with the Department claims for the amounts by which the prices guaranteed by the Government exceeded the prices realised by the farmers.   A memorandum explanatory of the scheme *?f guaranteed prices was preparod during the week for Issue to inquirers and to the Department^ agricultural staff.22/10/19,
FLAX.The-returns of yields of Boutched flax from the Department&apos;8 variety trials are now available,*111 series 1, trials, the following were the varieties tested, shown in the order *5 merit:-of dutch (White Floworinfe/ Department^ Selected No.5 Russian, 1917. Co. AntrimDepartment&apos;s Selected No.Si JapaneseCanadian (Ontario) Dutch (Blue Flowering) Co. CorkCanadian Western Fibre (Wayland).In series H, trials, English flaxseed from Peterborough, i*3.hy, and Yoovil, and Scottish flaxseed, were tested against Dutch at fii&amp;o centres.  ,The returns from these centres show that English seed from all districts has proved superior to Dutch, and Scottish slightly inferior.The relatively poor results obtained from Dutch seed are to be largely attributed to tho fact that the crop grown from this seed had been seriously affected by a fungus disease known as &quot;Browning&quot;.In the districts of South Armagh and South Monaghan the scutchers are threatening to strike unless their wages are increased from ls.9d. per stone of scutched flax to 2s. por stone,Tho returns of yields of scutched flax obtained by the Department from a number of mills show that tho yields are considerably larger than those obtained last year, but are still under the average,MAINTENANCE OF LIVE STOCK%During the period from 14th to 80th instant, inclusive, applications for licences were received as follows:-To slaughter or export heifers..........,..280To slaughter bulls or bullocks............. 69To slaughter veal .jj&amp;ves................. 82,
Llvo stock for &amp;ovastatod(Aro,aB.     The Department announced some time ago that it had been arranged to permit the export from Ireland on licence of a limited number of flattie and horses, via. British Parts, for the devastated areas of Belgium and Franco.    For the remainder of the year the number of cattle at present allotted to Belgium is 1,500 (in lots not excooding 50), and to France 5,000 (in xBdEfca lots not exceeding 200).   There is he restriction as to ttee class of cattle, except that they &quot;be not Mloh cows or springers, but it has been announced that the shipments - as was originally intondod - should consist of heifers for breeding.In no case will a licence be granted for more than one lot of animals to the same exporter in the first lnstanoo, and a licence for a   further let wiil not be granted him until the previous let has been exported.Export of   Store Heifers to Great Britain.    The Department having decided to permit the export to Great Britain of a limited number of young heifers (not in calf) announced that they wore prepared to receive applications for licences under the Maintenance of Live Stouk (Ireland) Order, in respeot of *ka animals of this class for one week ending 10th instant.   As on previous occasions the only applications consldored were those from regular shippers or from persons desiring to export direct to British farms.During tho period mentioned abovo the number of applications for licences under these heads were-i To export store heifers to Great Britain........600To export oattle to devastated areas.............60To export horses to devastated areas............ 10.

</content>
</cab>
