<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 140-145</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (46) 66.14th February, 1946.CABINET.THE ACCOMMODATION OF  STUDENTS AND  TOURISTS  FROMTHE UNITED STATES DURING 1946.Report by the Chairman of the Tourist Accommodation Committee.At their meeting on the 20th November (CM. (45) 54th Conclusions,Minute 5), the Cabinet agreed that it would be advantageous to encourageAmerican visitors to come to this country during the summer of 1946, if it provedpracticable to provide the necessary facilities without prejudice to other impor-tant Government programmes, and invited the Secretary for Overseas Trade toconsider, with the assistance of a Committee composed of junior Ministers fromthe Departments primarily concerned, whether a practicable scheme could be devised. It was recognised that the main difficulty would lie in the provision of accommodation; and it was contemplated that special arrangements might bemade to use for this purpose spare accommodation in Universities, schools andhostels. It was intended that the scheme should cater primarily for students and persons in the middle and lower income groups.2. In accordance with the decision of the Cabinet the Prime Ministerappointed the Tourist Accommodation Committee with the following terms ofreference :  &quot; To advise and report to the Cabinet on the practicability of usingGovernment hostels, Universities and Public Schools for the accommodation of tourists, particularly from the United States of America, during 1946,&quot;and with the following composition : Secretary for Overseas Trade (Chairman), the Parliamentary Under-Secretaries of State of the Foreign Office, Home Office and Scottish Office, theParliamentary Secretaries of the Ministry of Labour and National Service,the Ministry of Education, the Ministry of Health, the Ministry of war transport, and the Ministry of Works.3. The Committee has held two meetings (at the second of which, in theabsence through illness of the Secretary for Overseas Trade, the parliamentary secretary to the Ministry of War Transport presided). It also arranged fornumerous enquiries to be made on its behalf. After very careful considerationof the evidence put before it (which is summarised in the Appendix) the Com-mittee recommends :  (1) That it is inadvisible that there should be any Government sponsorshipof tourist traffic in 1946, in view of the lack of suitable accommodation and other facilities.(2) That as far as possible Government assistance should be given, where necessary, in an unobtrusive way to those organisations that havealready planned to accommodate overseas visitors in 1946.H. A. MARQUAND.Board of Trade, Millbank, S.W. 1,14th February, 1946.[31311]
APPENDIX.1. In order to carry out their instructions under their Terms of reference the Committee made a number of enquiries in order to ascertain (a) What arrangements were already being planned by existing student andtourist organisations to bring American visitors to this country during 1946.(b) What accommodation was likely to be available during the summer of1946 in schools and universities, in hotels, hostels, &amp;c, for furthervisitors.(c) What were the views of educational, tourist and catering interests on thedesirabilitv of Government action to encourage visits from Americain 1946.The results of these enquiries are summarised in the following paragraphs,together with some general considerations which impressed the Committee.2. Existing Arrangements for Visits by American Students and Tourists.(i) The Travel Association of Great Britain have initiated a scheme toprovide American Forces in Europe with tours of this country of a week&apos;sduration at the rate of 20 or more a day for the next six months. This schemeis in effect a continuation of a scheme operated previously by the AmericanRed Cross, from whom the Travel Association are in process of taking over.The new scheme has not yet begun to operate, but it is hoped that it will start inthe near future. At the rate of 20 a day the number of visitors over the next six months would be about 3,560.It had been hoped that the rate of visits would be nearer 100 a day, butvarious circumstances have prevented this : the accelerated demobilisation of american Forces; the fact that the French Government is offering a week&apos;s tripentirely free of cost as against a charge of $25 for the United Kingdom visit;and the difficulties of transport on the Continent.(ii) The British Council are planning to accommodate in Universities and elsewhere a fairly large number of students, teachers and technicians from foreign countries during the coming summer, and although there is as yet nofirm estimate of the numbers involved, the present indications are that there willscarcely be sufficient University accommodation to meet the Council&apos;s needs underthese plans.(iii) In addition, the Universities themselves will, under their own arrange-ments, be catering for a number of American students in the coming year. Atpresent there are over 3,000 American students at Universities in the UnitedKingdom; but, mainly owing to the demobilisation of the American Forces, allbut 400 of these will have left by the summer. A further number of Americanstudents are likely to be enrolled for the 1946-47 season to the extent thataccommodation is available.(iv) The Workers&apos; Travel Association is planning to arrange visits to thiscountry for small parties of tourists from Scandinavia, France and Belgium.(v) In addition, it may be expected that a number of American tourists, aswell as tourists from other countries, will visit this country during the comingsummer under individual arrangements.3. The Availability of Accommodation for Further students and Tourists in 1946.(i) University Accommodation. As will be seen from the previous para-graph University accommodation already appears likely to be insufficient to meetthe British Council&apos;s own needs under their existing plans; and a sample checkof University accommodation in July and August 1946, which was made speciallyfor the Committee, showed that all their available college and hostel space wouldbe fully taken up during those two months.(ii) School Accommodation.-The Ministry of Education, at the request ofthe Committee, made an approach to the Governing Bodies Association for Boysand Girls Schools, the Headmasters Conference and the Association of independent and Direct Grant Girls Schools. They were asked as a matter of urgency to consider the possibility of accommodating tourists from America and elsewhere during the summer holidays.
So far a reply has been received only from the Governing Bodies Associationfor Boys Public Schools. On the other hand, this is bv far the most importantBody, and its views are likely to be representative of the&apos; other organisations also.The letter containing the views of the Committee of this Association is signed by the Archbishop of Canterbury, as Chairman of the Association, and theconclusion reached is that schools will not be able to co-operate under presentconditions. The letter points out that the domestic problem in most schools isvery acute, that stocks of linen and crockery are depleted, and that there aregreat arrears of repairs and decorations which can only be carried out in holidaytime. The Archbishop has promised to bring the matter before the GeneralMeeting of the Association on the 1st March; but expresses the view that it isvery unlikely that they will reach a different conclusion, and that enquiries to individual^ schools are unlikely to be profitable.(iii) Hotel Accommodati6n.-Th.e number of hotels under requisition at the1st January, 1946, was about 4,000, and the Ministry of Works intend to reducethis number to about 1,500 by next July. The Committee considered, however,that the very considerable domestic demand for more holiday accommodationshould be given the first claim on the freed hotel space, and that this demand will be more than sufficient to absorb the increased space available.(iv) Hostels and Camps. The Committee was informed by the Ministry ofWorks that it is most unlikely that any Government hostels can be made availableto American tourists. The hostels will all be required to meet other important national needs, such as those of agriculture and emergency housing. Since theCabinet discussion made it clear that any arrangements for tourists were to be&quot; without prejudice to other important Government programmes,&quot; the committee did not feel justified in pursuing this line of enquiry further.(v) Reconstructed Nissen Huts. The Committee considered that Americanvisitors would expect a higher standard of comfort than can be provided by aNissen hut, however thoughtfully adapted.(vi) Private Homes. A further suggestion was that by advertising and bycareful selection it might be possible to billet some tourists on private families.But, in the Committee&apos;s view, any Government appeal to householders to accom-accommodate tourists for short periods would run grave risk of being misunderstoodby the general public, who might resent the occupation of private houses *bytourists at a time when many families are without homes of their own.4. The Views of Educational, Tourist and Catering Interests.A number of interviews were arranged with representatives of educational,tourist and catering interests in order to obtain their views on the desirabilityand practicability of Government sponsorship or encouragement of tourist traffic form abroad in 1946.   The following interests were consulted : The University Grants Committee, the Incorporated Society of Head-masters, Messrs. Thomas Cook and Sons, the Travel Association of GreatBritain and Ireland, the Hotels and Restaurants Association, the Workers&apos;Travel Association and the American Express Company.With the exception of Messrs. Thomas Cook and Sons the representativesof all the above interests expressed the view that no large scale tourist traffic would be practicable in 1946, and that any Government action contemplated wouldbe more fruitful if directed to the 1947 season. The Chairman of the hotel sand Restaurants Association expressed the view that to encourage civilian touristsfrom America until such time as we could give them a reception at all comparable with that to which they were accustomed would, in the long run, do positiveharm to the tourist trade, and that any preparatory explanations to touristsabout conditions in this country would be out-weighed in the minds of average-Americans of the middle and lower income classes by their actual experience ofdiscomfort.The Managing Director of Messrs. Thomas Cook and Sons realised that thevery great difficulties in the way of tourist traffic in 1946 would be shipping spaceto and accommodation in this country. But, he considered that there were a great number of people in the United States of America who would welcome theopportunity of coming to this country in 1946, and who would not expect to live in luxury hotels. On the other hand, representatives of the American ExpressCompany, who were interviewed, were definitely of the opinion that presentconditions for tourists in this country would not be attractive to Americanvisitors, although there was plenty of money in the United States of America to
be spent on travel. The representatives of the American Express company were nevertheless very anxious that the country should be ready to receive visitorsin 1947.5. General Considerations.The Committee considered that the poor living conditions in the UnitedKingdom would have a bad effect on the future of the tourist trade if tourists wereofficially encouraged to visit this country in 1946.It was felt, furthermore, that the encouragement of foreign visitors in 1946,with the general accommodation situation being so difficult and the standard ofliving so low, would give rise to public criticism. If any assistance is to be givento those organisations who are planning tours for foreign visitors in 1946, itshould therefore be given unobtrusively.6. Plans for 1947.The Committee was of the opinion that every possible effort should be madeto stimulate and encourage visits by foreign tourists in 1947. The Cabinet willbe aware that a committee of officials has been appointed by the Lord Presidentof the Council to review Departmental responsibility for the Tourist trade.Pending any further decision on this point, the Department of Overseas Trade,which is at present responsible for the relations of the Government with the travel Association, is actively laying plans in conjunction with that associationfor the opening of the Tourist traffic in 1947, the year in which the BritishIndustries Fair is to be revived. The Committee was assured that the TravelAssociation was staffed with personnel well experienced in the Tourist trade andwas investigating in detail all the requirements that would be needed to make the tourist trade a success.



</content>
</cab>
