<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 158-171</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1940.75SECRET. Copy No.   ^ C.P. (46) 69.18*A February, 1946.CABINET.SECOND REPORT FROM THE SELECT COMMITTEE on procedure, PARLIAMENTARY QUESTIONS AND REPLIES TOM.P. S LETTERS.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.I circulate herewith a copy of the Second Report from the Select Committeeon Procedure.   As will be seen, the Committee recommend that:- (1) The period of notice for oral Questions handed in during the sittingof the House should be increased from one to two days, not countingSundays; Questions received at the Table Office before the hour of sitting of the House should be deemed to have been received the day before (paragraphs 8 and 10).(2) Questions not for oral answer should be answered within seven days after their appearance on the notice paper (paragraph 11).Oral Questions.2. The Financial Secretary to the Treasury in his evidence before theSelect Committee suggested that the period of notice for oral Questions shouldbe extended to two clear days (excluding Sundays). The Committee have accepted this in principle, subject to the important proviso that Questionsreceived at the Table Office before the hour of sitting of the House should bedeemed to have been received the day before.3. While this is not all that might have been desired, the concession is substantial; and it is to be borne in mind that without the proviso there would only be one day Monday on which a Member would be able to put down aQuestion, otherwise than by Private Notice, for answer the same week.4. I think, therefore, that the Committee&apos;s proposal should be adopted,but I should point out that it is not Avithout its practical difficulties. A con-siderable proportion of the Questions handed in by Members are out of orderin some respect or otherwise require amendment before the Table will passthem. A smaller but far from negligible proportion say, 10 per cent., at a rough guess, I am told are out of order altogether and are refused by the Table.5. Especially since it is not likely that there will tend to be a last minuterush to hand in Questions just before the Flouse sits, this means that when thehour of the commencement of the sitting has passed the Table Office are boundto have a number of Questions which will either not appear on the order paper at all or will appear in an amended form; and it may not be possible to clear them all up with the Members concerned until late in the evening.6. Short of throwing over the Committee&apos;s recommendation, three coursesseem to be open :  (a) Departments can collect from the Table Office (say, an hour after theHouse meets) only the Questions which have been passed, and wait for the rest either until later in the afternoon or until the next day&apos;sOrder Paper. This would mean, however, that as regards a fairproportion of Questions they would be no better off than at present.[31327]
(6) It could be made the rule that if a Question appeared to the Table Officeto be out of order or to require amendment and it had not been passedby the hour of sitting of the House, it should not have the benefit ofthe expedited procedure but should be dealt with as if it had been handed in after the appointed time. The Clerk of the House thinks and I agree with him that this would place the Table Office inan invidious position. There are borderline cases in which the Clerkshave to exercise their discretion; often the necessary amendments areof a purely drafting character; the decision of the Clerk might makethe difference not only between a Question being answered in one week or the next but also, owing to the operation of the roster system,to the chances of it getting an oral answer for several weeks. Thiswould place on the Clerks a responsibility which they ought not tocarry, and would make for friction between Members and them.(c) Departments could be supplied by the Table Office with all Questionsregardless of the likelihood or otherwise of amendment. The draw-back of this is that Departments would be caused unnecessary workon those questions which are, in fact, out of order or require sub-stantial amendment. But the amount of extra work should not be great, the problem only arises on Questions handed in on Mondays,Tuesdays and Fridays, since it will not be possible to put downQuestions for the same week on Wednesdays and Thursday, and thedifficulty is less in the case of Fridays because of the earlier risingof the House; and the Clerk of the House will be prepared to arrangefor the doubtful Questions to be marked with some indication thatthey are being queried, and for Departments to be informed of thedoubtful Questions which are cleared, in time for Departmental actionto be taken the same day.7.   On balance, therefore, I think that course (c) is the most satisfactory.Written Questions.8. The proposal that written Questions should be answered within seven days seems to me to be reasonable, and I recommend its adoption. This is not amatter for the Standing Orders of the House but for a Government instruction to Departments, and I suggest that Departments should.be instructed accordingly.At the same time, I should like it impressed upon all concerned that seven daysshould be regarded as a maximum and not a minimum, and that every effort should be made to get in replies quickly. If written Questions are answeredwithout delay, Members will be likely to make more use of them, and the numberof oral Questions may correspondingly fall off.Replies to letters from Members of Parliament.9. In paragraph 12 of their Report, the Select Committee say that it would help to reduce the number of Questions, oral and written, if Departments made ita rule to answer letters from Members within a fortnight. The parliamentary labour Party has also recently made representations to the Prime Minister onthe same subject.10. In view of the dissatisfaction which has been expressed, the PrimeMinister has asked the Secretary of the Treasury to examine the question of improving the procedure in Government Departments for dealing with letters from Members of Parliament. I welcome this action, because as Leader of theHouse I am much concerned about the present position and the effect on theGovernment^ reputation. There is no doubt that the feeling is strong. To someextent it is misinformed, but on the other hand while I fully appreciate thedifficulties and recognise that circumstances vary considerably as between departments, I am satisfied that there are some grounds for legitimate complaint,and it is the case, I am afraid, that many Members tend to judge the efficiency ofthe Government by the promptitude with which their letters are answered. i hope, therefore, that as a result of the review which the Prime Minister hasinstituted substantial improvements will be found possible, and I would like tosuggest to my colleagues that as far as they personally are concerned they should give this matter special attention, at any rate for the time being.
Conclusions.11.   I recommend, therefore, that (a) We should accept the recommendation of the Select Committee that theperiod of notice for oral Questions should be increased to two days,Questions received before the hour of sitting of the House being deemedto have been received the day before.(b) Departments should be instructed that written Questions should be answered within seven days, and at the same time urged to deal withthem more quickly where possible.(c) Subject to the views of Mr. Speaker, whom I should propose to consultas a matter of courtesy, I should arrange for the necessary action tobe taken in the House as regards the amendment of Standing orders to give effect to the Select Committee&apos;s recommendation on oralQuestions. It would, I think, be useful to draw attention to thedifficulties which may be involved by the proposal to allow Questionsput down before the hour of sitting to be treated as if they had been putdown the day before, and to ask Members to avoid taking advantageof the expedited procedure except in the case of urgent Questions.* Especially in view of the burden which may fall on the Table Office,Mr. Speaker might also be prepared to invite the co-operation ofMembers in this way and in putting their Questions down as early as possible.H. M.Office of the Lord President of the Council, S.W. 1,18th February, 1946.

SECOND   REPORTFROM THESELECT  COMMITTEEONPROCEDURETOGETHER WITH THEPROCEEDINGS OF THE COMMITTEEOrdered by The House of Commons to be Printed24/i January  1946LONDONHIS MAJESTY&apos;S STATIONERY OFFICETWOPENCE    NET
ORDERS OF REFERENCEFriday, -z^th August, 1945.Procedure, Select Committee appointed to consider the Procedure in thePublic Business of this House and to report what alterations, if any, are desirable for the more efficient despatch of such business: Committee to consist of Seventeen Members: Mr. W. J. Brown, Mr. Seymour Cocks, Mr.Cove, Captain Crookshank, Mr. Crossman, Mr. Clement Davies, Mr. Gaitskell,Viscount Hinchingbrooke, Mr. Messer, Mr. Pickthorn, Mr. James Reid, Mr.Sydney Silverman, Mr. Viant, Mr. Maurice Webb, Mr. Octavius Willey, EarlWinterton and Sir Robert Young: Power to send for persons, papers and records; to sit notwithstanding any Adjournment of the House; and to reportfrom time to time: -Five to be the Quorum: -Power to appoint Sub-Committees for any purpose within the Order of Reference to the Committee: (Mr. Herbert Morrison:) Motion made and Question proposed, &quot; That it be an Instruction to theCommittee that they do report as soon as possible upon any scheme for the acceleration of proceedings on Public Bills which may be submitted to them on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government:&quot; (Mr. Herbert Morrison:) Question amended by adding, at the end thereof, the words &quot; and thatduring the consideration of any such scheme they do report from day to day the Minutes of the Evidence taken before them and such other records relatingto any such scheme as -they may think fit and that if the House be not sitting,they do send such Minutes and records to the Clerk of the House, who shall thereupon give directions for the printing and circulation thereof, and shalllay the same upon the Table of the House at its next meeting.&quot;: (Captain Crowder:) and, as amended, agreed to.Tuesday, gth October, 1945.Procedure, Minutes of Evidence taken before the Select Committee on procedure on Public Business in Session 1930-31 and the Select Committeeon Procedure in Session 1931-32 referred to the Select Committee on procedure. (Sir Robert Young).The cost of printing and publishing this Volume is estimated by H.M.Stationery Office at  13 10s. od.
SECOND REPORTThe Select Committee appointed to consider the Procedure in the public business of this House and to report what alterations, if any, are desirable for the more efficient despatch of such business, have made further progressin the matters to them referred and have agreed to the following second report.QUESTIONS AND DIVISIONSi. In the course of Your Committee&apos;s inquiry into the Government&apos;^proposals for accelerating legislation, the Clerk of the House undertook toprepare for their consideration a comprehensive scheme for the reform ofparliamentary procedure. They employed the interval while this scheme, wasbeing prepared in the examination of two parts of parliamentary procedure which could conveniently be considered separately from the rest, viz.,Questions to Ministers and Divisions.QUESTIONS2. Evidence was taken on the subject of Questions from the Speaker of theHouse, the Rt. Hon. Douglas Clifton Brown, and the following members ofthe House: Mr. W. Glenvil Hall, Financial Secretary to the Treasury, andWing-Commander John Strachey, Under-Secretary of State for Air, repre-senting the Government, and the Rt. Hon. Anthony Eden, M.C., representingthe Conservative Opposition; also from Mr. E. A. Fellowes, C.B., M.C.,the Second Clerk Assistant.3. Before dealing with specific points Your Committee desire to make certain observations of a general nature. They regard the right to putQuestions to Ministers as one of the most important possessed by Members.The exercise of this right is perhaps the readiest and most effective methodof parliamentary control over the action of the executive. They would therefore deprecate anything which tended to diminish the effectiveness ofthis right. On the other hand the very powerfulness of the right imposesupon Members a proportionate responsibility in its use. The Departments veryproperly accord a high degree of priority to the answering of parliamentary questions. It is important therefore that Questions, especially oral Questions,should only be put down when other and less formal methods have failed toproduce a satisfactory result, or when some information or action is urgentlydesired. Similarly, in deciding the date for which a Question is put down,regard should be had to the time which may be needed for the preparationof the answer and to the real urgency of the case. In fine, the smoothworking of this form of parliamentary procedure (as indeed of all parliamentary procedure) depends to a great extent upon the individual Member. your committee venture to suggest that at the beginning of each Session ofParliament an appeal by Mr. Speaker to Members for discretion in the useof oral Questions would be opportune.4. The points to which Your Committee&apos;s attention were particularlydirected were (a) whether the number of oral Questions which a Member may put downshould be further restricted;(&amp;) whether the period of notice for oral Questions should be lengthened;(c) whether the practice in regard to supplementary Questions should be altered;(d) whether a time limit should be set for the answering of Questions not for oral answer.
(a) Number of Questions per Member per Day.5. The rule is that not more than three Questions for oral answer may beplaced on the notice paper by the same Member for the same day (Manualof Procedure, 1941, para. 57). In the present Session an average of about150 Questions for oral answer appears on the paper each day, of which onan average rather more than 70 actually get oral answers within the allottedhour, so that about half the Questions put down for oral answer are not reached and the Members asking them have to be content with a writtenanswer. This situation has suggested the desirability of reducing the rationfrom three to two Questions a Member a day. The average number ofMembers asking three Questions in the present Session is 17, so that, if the ration were reduced as suggested from three to&apos; two, more Members mightbe enabled to get an oral answer to a Question each day.6. Your Committee are reluctant to restrict a right which has already been severely curtailed. Originally the number of, and time for, Questions wasunlimited: the time was fixed at one hour in 1902, and the number perMember per day was first limited to 8 in 1909 and reduced to three in1920. It is recognised that there are many occasions when a Member mayfairly require oral answers to at least three Questions. He may wish to aska number of Questions concerned with his constituency, or he may be par-ticulariy interested in the work of one Department and on such occasions itmay seem an unwarranted restriction of his rights further to limit the numberof Questions he may ask. It may well be that, as in other Sessions, thenumber of Questions put down for oral answer will decline as the Sessionproceeds.(b) Period of Notice for Oral Questions.7. The period of notice for oral Questions is prescribed by Standing order no. 7 (4) which says that &quot; such question must appear at latest on thenotice paper circulated on the day before that on which an answer is desired.&quot;That is to say, the shortest time which a Department may have to prepare the answer to a Question is a little more than 24 hours. It was urged by representatives of the Government that in some cases this period of notice is insufficient, in particular where consultation is necessary between different departments or between widely separated branches of the same Department,or where information has to be obtained from some distant part of the world.It was therefore suggested that the minimum period of notice should beincreased by one day.8. As the representatives of the Government pointed out, many Questionswhich are put down at the minimum period of notice do not appear to meritsuch urgent treatment, and Departments would be relieved of unnecessarypressure if Members refrained from putting down Questions with the shortestperiod of notice, and so far, as suggested in an earlier paragraph, the remedj&apos;lies with Members themselves. Since, however, the effect of putting off aQuestion from the earliest day is usually to defer the answer for a whole week,your Committee recommend that the rule as to period of notice should be amended so as normally to give the Departments a full two days&apos; notice.Questions received at the Table Office before the hour of sitting of the house should be deemed to have been received the day before. arrangements should be made for copies of such Questions to be sent by hand to theappropriate Department as soon as they have been examined by the Clerk incharge of Questions. In this way the Departments would have the advantageof several valuable working hours to initiate such inquiries as may be necessaryfor the preparation of an answer, and the right of Members to a quickanswer to a really urgent Question would be preserved.
Q jt was also pointed out by the -representatives of the Government thatin the case of Questions first appearing on the notice paper issued on saturday for answer on Monday the position is more difficult than during theiveek, as they have to be dealt with by the Departments during the week-end.It was therefore suggested that Questions first appearing on Saturday shouldnot require an answer before Tuesday. Your Committee accept this suggestion and recommend that oral Questions handed in during a Friday sitting shouldnot require an answer earlier than the following Tuesday.jo. To carry out these recommendations Your Committee propose thatStanding Order No. 7 (4) should be amended to read as follows:  &quot; Any member who desires an oral answer to his question may distinguishit by an asterisk, but notice of any such question must appear on thenotice paper at least two days (not counting Sundays) before that onwhich an answer is desired. Provided that questions received at the TableOffice before the hour of sitting of the House shall be deemed to have beenreceived the day before.&quot;(c) Supplementary Questions.11. Your Committee consider the rules and practice in regard to supple-mentary Questions as a matter which should remain entirely within the speaker&apos;s discretion.(d) Questions not for Oral Answer.12. Undoubtedly the volume of Questions put down for oral answer is tosome extent attributable to the uncertainty of written answers. If members could be assured that they would get a written answer within a reasonable time, they would be encouraged to make more use of the Question forwritten answer and so relieve the pressure of oral Questions. Your Com-mittee therefore recommend that a written answer should be given withinseven days after the appearance of the Question on tire paper. It would alsohelp to reduce the number of Questions, oral and written, if Departments made it a rule to answer letters from Members within a fortnight.DIVISIONS13. Your Committee inquired into the possibility of reducing the amount oftime spent on Divisions. They considered various suggestions, including a mechanical method, put forward by the Public Bill Office, and heardevidence from representatives of the Government and Opposition Whips.Your Committee found, however, that none of these suggestions would savemuch, time and that a mechanical method such as the one suggested wouldbe neither so convenient nor so accurate a means of counting votes andrecording names as the present method. Some saving of time is, however, tobe expected when the new Chamber is built.SUMMARY   OF   RECOMMENDATIONS.14. Your Committee recommend that, (1) The period of notice for oral Questions handed in during the sittingof the House should be increased from one to two days, not countingSundays; Questions received at the Table Office before the hour of sittingof the House should be deemed to have been received the day before(paragraphs 8 and 10).(2) Questions not for oral answer should be answered within seven days after their appearance on the notice paper (paragraph 12).
PROCEEDINGS OF THE COMMITTEE.THURSDAY, ist NOVEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. W. J. Brown.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Mr.  Cove.Captain Crookshank.Mr. Crossman.Mr. Clement Davies.Mr. Gaitskell.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. Pickthorn.Mr. James Reid.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Mr. Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Mr. Octavius Willey.Earl Winterton.The Committee deliberated.[Adjourned till Thursday, 15th November, at Eleven o&apos;clock.THURSDAY, 15TH NOVEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. W. J. Brown.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Captain Crookshank.Mr.  Crossman.Mr. Clement Davies.Mr.  Gaitskell.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. Pickthorn.Mr.  Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Mr. Octavius Willey.Earl Winterton.Mr. E. A. Fellowes, C.B., M.C., Second Clerk Assistant, was examined.[Adjourned till Thursday naxt at Eleven o&apos;clock.THURSDAY, 22nd NOVEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. Cove.Captain Crookshank.Mr. Crossman.Mr. Clement Davies.Mr. Gaitskell.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. Pickthorn.Mr. James Reid.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Mr. Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Mr. Octavius Willey.Earl Winterton.Mr. W. Glenvil Hall, a Member of the House and Financial Secretary to theTreasury; Wing-Commander John Strachey-, a Member of the House and Under-Secretary of State for Air; and&quot; the Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M.C., a Memberof the House, were examined.[Adjourned till Thursday next at Eleven o&apos;clock.
THURSDAY, 29TH NOVEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Mr.  Cove.Captain Crookshank.Mr. Clement Davies.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. Pickthorn.Mr. James Reid.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Mr. Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Mr. Octavius Willey.Earl Winterton.Colonel the Right Honourable douglas clifton brown, Speaker of the House, was further examined.[Adjourned till Thursday next at Eleven o&apos;clock.THURSDAY, 6th DECEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. Seymour Cocks. Mr. Pickthorn.Captain Crookshank. Mr. Viant.Mr. Grossman. Mr. Octavius Willey.Mr. Gaitskell. Earl Winterton.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. B. H. coode, Clerk of Public Bills; Mr. S. gordon, a Senior Clerk in thePublic Bill Office; the Right Honourable william whiteley, a Member of the Housead Parliamentary Secretary to the Treasury; and Mr. P. g. T. buchan-hepburn,1 Member of the House, were examined.[Adjourned till Thursday next at Eleven o&apos;clock.THURSDAY, 13TH DECEMBER, 1945.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. W. J. Brown.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Mr. Cove.Captain Crookshank.Mr. Grossman.Mr. Clement Davies.Mr. Gaitskell.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Mr. Viant.&apos;Mr. Maurice Webb.Mr. Octavius Willey.Earl Winterton.The Committee deliberated.[Adjourned till Thursday, 24th January, 1946, at Eleven o&apos;clock.THURSDAY, 24TH JANUARY, 1946.Members present:Sir ROBERT YOUNG in the Chair.Mr. W. J. Brown.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Captain Crookshank.Mr. Clement Davies.Mr. Gaitskell.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. James Reid.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Mr. Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Earl Winterton.
Draft Second Report, proposed by the Chairman, brought up and read the first time.Ordered. That the Draft Report be read a second time, paragraph by paragraph.Paragraphs i and 2, agreed to.Paragraph 3, amended, and agreed to.Paragraph 4, agreed to.Paragraph 5, amended, and agreed to.Paragraph 6:  &quot; Your Committee are reluctant to restrict a right which has already been]severely curtailed. Originally the number of, and time for, Questions was unlimited:the time was fixed at one hour in 1902, and the number per Member per day!was first limited to 8 in 1909 and reduced to three in 1920. They recognise thatthere are many occasions when a Member may fairly require oral answers to atleast three Questions. He may wish to ask a number of Questions concerned withhis constituency, or he may be particularly interested in the work of one Department,;and on such occasions it may seem an unwarranted restriction of his rights further-to limit the number of Questions he may ask. It may well be that, as in other-Sessions, the number of Questions put down for oral answer will decline as the session proceeds. Nevertheless, in view of the present quite unusual number ofjoral Questions on the paper, it seems to Your Committee fair that as many member as possible should have the opportunity of getting oral answers. They therefore&apos;recommend no Standing Order is involved that Members should be restricted to two oral Questions a day until the volume of Questions declines to normal.&quot;;Amendment proposed, in line 11, to leave out from &quot; proceeds &quot; to the end of!the paragraph.Question put &apos;&apos; That the words proposed to be left out stand part of the paragraph the Committee divided:  Ayes, 4; Noes, 8.Ayes.Mr. Clement Da vies..Mr. Gaitskell.Mr. Viant.Mr. Maurice Webb.Noes.Mr.  W. J.  Brown.Mr. Seymour Cocks.Captain Crookshank.Viscount Hinchingbrooke.Mr. Messer.Mr. James Reid.Mr. Sydney Silverman.Earl Winterton.Paragraph,  as amended, agreed to.Paragraph 7, agreed to.Paragraphs 8 to 10, amended, and agreed to.Paragraph n, agreed to.Paragraph 12, amended, and agreed to.Paragraph 13, agreed to.Paragraph 14, amended, and agreed to.Resolved, That the Draft Report, as amended, be the Second Report of thejCommittee to the House.[Adjourned  till  Thursday  next,  at   Eleven  o&apos;clock.(48105)   Wt. 4667-744   1/46   d.L.   G. 335



</content>
</cab>
