<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 222-229</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of his britannic majestvs governmentPrinted for the Cabinet,   February 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (46) 77.21st February, 1946.CABINET.VISIT TO CANADA AND THE UNITED STATES, JANUARY 1946.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.MY colleagues may be interested in some of the impressions I formed duringmy recent visit to Canada and the United States. They are necessarily superficial,but perhaps they may not be without value if they are taken for what they are so to speak, a snapshot of the two countries at a crucial stage in their post-wardevelopment and at an important point in their relations with the UnitedKingdom.Canada.In Canada, where I spent ten days, I visited Ottawa, Quebec, Montreal andToronto. In the course of my tour, I had several talks with the Prime Ministerof Canada, met a number of the Dominion Ministers and officials, talked to both national and provincial leaders of the C.C.F., met the Progressive Conservativeleader, Mr. Bracken, and was entertained by the Progressive Conservative Govern-ment of Ontario, under whose auspices I visited Niagara Falls and the OntarioHydro electric power plants in the area. I also met the press on several occasions,and saw a considerable number of prominent business men, industrialists andtrade unionists. In Quebec I had a short talk with Cardinal Villeneuve, andmet the Episcopalian Archbishop, who, as I was interested to find, is a Socialist;his wife also. I made three public speeches, to the Canadian Club at Ottawa,the Canadian Club at Montreal, and the annual dinner of the Toronto Board ofTrade; each of them was broadcast. I also spoke off the record to the TorontoBranch of the Canadian Institute of International Affairs. It may be of interestto add that, at the invitation of the O.C. Troops on board ship, I spoke over theship&apos;s broadcasting system on New Year&apos;s Eve to the passengers, including5-6,000 returning Canadian service men and women. I also visited the troopswho were sick in hospital.Everywhere I went I was most cordially received. A naturally hospitablepeople, Canadians were particularly pleased to have the opportunity ofentertaining a member of the United Kingdom Cabinet, and they were interestedin me as a representative of the Labour Government. The keynote was struckby Mr. Mackenzie King himself. Though we arrived in Ottawa late in the evening and much later than planned, he went to the trouble of meeting me atthe Station, he personally conducted me over the Parliamentary buildings and attended my press conference with the Parliamentary Gallery, he invited me totea at his house, he presided at a Government dinner in my honour, and he took a close personal interest in the arrangements for my stay. Throughout, the PrimeMinister was very kind and friendly.And so it was at every level. No courtesy was overlooked, no pains werespared, while it was touching to find at every hand a lively interest in the UnitedKingdom, sympathy and concern about the privations we are still experiencing,universal admiration of our fighting men, and an obvious affection for the &quot; oldcountry,&quot; the expression used even by some who were not of British descent.This applied amongst all classes, from the coloured steward- an immigrant fromLouisiana (who looked after us most efficiently on the private carriage or&quot;business car&quot; which Canadian National Railways allocated to me) and the domestic staff at the hotels, to Ministers and business leaders. I was constantlybeing told with pride of connections with the United Kingdom; many of the[31343] &quot;
people I met Mr. Coldwell was one had been born or brought up here them-selves; and it almost seemed as though there was nobody who could not claimsome connection. Often, of course, the most recent connection was the service in this country of a son or other relative.An aspect of this warm sentiment towards the United Kingdom is the evidentloyalty to the Crown. Again and again 1 was given reminiscences of the visit by the King and Queen, which seemed almost as fresh in the memory as if ithad taken place last year, and was told how much it had meant to Canada. AndI was asked if I could say what were the prospects of Their, Majesties comingagain or of a visit from Princess Elizabeth, who could be assured&apos; of a no lessenthusiastic welcome. It was a striking reminder of the significance of the Crownas a unifying factor in the Commonwealth. -&apos;:.No visitor to Canada oan, I think, fail on the other hand to be struck bythe distinctive national characteristics which the Canadians have developed. Notonly are they conscious of their own separate national identity and, even whenthey proudly relate their British antecedents, they.leave you in no doubt thatthey are first and foremost Canadians but in&apos; their outlook and in the tempo oftheir lives they are as different from us as from the Americans, to whom super-ficially they bear so close a resemblance. I found this the more noteworthybecause, with few exceptions, the Canadians I met were English-speakingand of British origin, and I saw little of the French Canadians and nothing ofthe new Canadians of the Prairie Provinces, who derive from Central and Eastern;Europe.But I was told much by English-speaking Canadians of all types of theiranxieties about the French-Canadian Catholic problem-the problem which is presented by the continued existence of an almost entirely distinctive French-Canadian culture and by the growth spurred on by open propaganda in theFrench-Canadian population relatively to Canadians of Anglo-Saxon descent,with the prospect that in the not very distant future the French Canadians willpredominate numerically. (The French-Canadian outlook is nearer to that ofthe Louis XIV period than that of modern republican France.) I cannot, ofcourse, claim to have studied this difficult problem, but. making all allowances for natural prejudices, I must confess that at first sight I have some sympathy with the point of view of the English-speaking Canadians. I cannot look forward with equanimity to a future in which Canada is controlled by a French-Canadianmajority, with all that, as things are, this implies.; &apos;&quot; &apos; At any rate at present there seems to be no Canadian politician who panhold a candle to Mr. Mackenzie King in the art of politics. As a statesmanand as a political tactician he is in a class apart, and, whoever succeeds him;the Liberal Party will miss him sorely when he retires, as he has announced his intention of doing before the next General Election. On the other hand, from what I was told and from what I saw of his chief opponent, Mr. Bracken, the leader of the Progressive Conservatives, and his party, I did not feel that the liberals under Mackenzie King had much to fear from the Conservatives.However, I noted Colonel Drewe, the Premier of Ontario, as a considerablepersonality, though it was said that as a tactician in the wider Dominion fieldhe was likely to be somewhat clumsy. But the Conservatives seem to have nopersonalities equal to the Prime Minister, and it is difficult for the outsiderto distinguish between their policy and that of the Liberals on fundamentals.Both are fifhdamentally what we should call Conservative, though owing to the size of the Dominion and to the Federal system both, like the American political parties, represent rather a grouping of interests than a united body of opinion.In these circumstances the natural course of events might seem to be thefusion of the Liberals and the Conservatives, especially as the C.C.F. increasein power as a Left-wing opposition. I was told that such a union has, in fact,been mooted, but that while the Conservatives would be prepared to unite,Mr. King is firmly opposed to the idea. On the other hand, he would be ready fora coalition with the C.C.F.; but.the C.C.F. do not favour it. However, thepossibility of a Liberal-Conservative coalition is a likelihood, when Mr. mackenzie king gives up the Liberal leadership, especially if the C.C.F. show signs ofsecuring a majority in the Dominion Parliament. This might cause the CiCF;a temporary set-back, but, jn the long run, open up the road to power. ;;.&apos; As my colleagues may have read, my informal talks with C.C.F. leadersled to criticism in certain sections of the Canadian press. It was alleged that I had come to advise and to ginger up the C.C.F., and it was said thatI had no business to interfere in Canadian, politics. This foolish misunder-standing of the purpose of the talks was partly due to somewhat clumsy publicity.
I had made it clear to the C.C.F. that while I should naturally want to meetC.C.F. and trade union leaders informally it would be wrong for me as a UnitedKingdom Minister to enter the Canadian political arena. However, the trouble--which was far more a rumpus between the Canadians than a dead-set at me blew over when I explained my attitude and pointed out that I was also meetingthe leaders of the other parties; and Mr. King throughout dismissed the matter as a triviality.It is significant, on the other hand, as showing the extent to which theC.C.F. count in Canadian politics to-day, that it should have been worth thewhile of their political opponents to exploit the incident. It is recognised, Ithink, that potentially they represent the most powerful threat to the Govern-ment and that it may not be long before they are the largest party in the State.They are promising, though in some respects a bit raw; for example, some ofthem are infected by the North American &quot;British Imperialism&quot; bug, whichdoes them no good with the Canadian public as a whole. I did my best to warnthem off this line.I found, as I have said, great interest in the political situation here and inthe programme and prospects of the Labour Government, but I had expected,I must confess, that except on the part of the C.C.F., there would be a fairlyuncompromising hostility to our socialisation proposals and our general attitude to economic policy. It came as an agreeable surprise, therefore, that while, ofcourse, the Liberal and Conservative politicians and business men took it com-pletely for granted that our remedies were unsuitable for Canada, as a rulethey went further than I would have expected towards recognising that thedifferent circumstances in which we found ourselves might necessitate very different methods from those appropriate for Canada, even including a much stronger dose of State control and experiments in nationalisation. I pointedout that we were embarking on these not on doctrinaire grounds but because wewere convinced as practical men that they provided practical solutions for theproblems which faced us, and I reminded them to some effect of their ownventures in nationalisation including Canadian National Railways, Trans-Canada Air Lines, the Ontario Hydro Electric Scheme, municipal transport, andeven a small railway owned by the Conservative Province of Ontario. At thesame time I was at pains to make it clear that I had not come to Canada to winconverts to socialisation or to tell Canadians how to manage their own affairs.I was naturally asked many questions about trade and the prospects for Anglo-Canadian trade in the future. I found that there was some misunder-standing about our import restrictions, which were suspected of being protectivein character and designed to induce Canadian manufacturers to set up factories in the United Kingdom, but my explanation that this was not so and that thedifficulty was the dollar situation was readily accepted. There were healthysigns, too, that the illusion that exports need not be offset by imports is vanishing.I was told that the point that exports must be balanced by imports is now generally accepted and understood, and indeed, I was assured that there was akeen desire to have our goods.I may mention incidentally that Mr. J. S. Duncan, the head of the Massey-Harris Company Ltd., in a very friendly speech at the annual dinner of theToronto Board of Trade, said that his firm had a factory in Manchester but theyhad found that it was difficult to produce as cheaply there as in Canada, eventaking into account the cost of transporting their goods from Canada to theUnited Kingdom. The reason was not the quality or cost of labour, but the high cost of, firstly, British iron and steel, and, secondly, British coal.Altogether, I came home with the firm impression that there is great scope for developing our trade with Canada, and that this presents a fine opportunityfor our economic Departments.   The wish to trade with us is there.An account of my tour in Canada would not be complete without a referenceto the great contribution which, as I was told on many occasions, Mr. Malcolm Macdonald has made to good relations between the two countries during hisperiod of office as our High Commissioner. I heard many tributes, endorsed byMr. MacKenzie King himself, to the understanding which Mr. MacDonald had shown of the Canadian point of view and the ability and persuasiveness withwhich at the same time he discharged his duties as the spokesman of the UnitedKingdom.The United States.My stay in the United States was even briefer than my tour in Canada.   Iarrived in New York by plane from Toronto in the early hours of a Friday[31343] . b 2
4.morning, left New York for Washington on Saturday afternoon, and set off from washington on the first stage of my homeward journey on the Monday night.Like the Canadian tour, it was a case of truly Transatlantic hustle, but, shortthough my stay was, it was well worth while and I crowded a great deal in. in new York I took the opportunity of going round the British information services office and discussing their work with the chief officials; I also sawsomething of the work of British Information Services in Washington. I lunchedwith the Association of Radio News Analysts, a select group of high-poweredand highly remunerated radio commentators of the type which is soinfluential in the United States but, in my opinion fortunately, does not exist here : as to their earnings, I was told that the dozen or fifteen per-sons round the table almost certainly earned between one and two million dollars a year between them. I dined with the Council on Foreign Rela-tions, a body which is in some respects the New York counterpart of ChathamHouse, and spoke to them on the situation here. On the following day I lunchedwith an ad hoc gathering which was representative of the New York press andradio men of all shades of opinion from the Nation and New Republic to theHearst group. I also took the opportunity of my visit to New York to renew(through my friend, Mr. George Field, of Freedom House) my acquaintance withold Socialist and Left-wing friends.In Washington I did a national broadcast on &quot; Britain Faces Peace,&quot; inwhich I laid stress on our determination and capacity to surmount our present economic difficulties, and I spoke in public answering questions afterwards, bothon and off the record to the National Press Club. I also went to other and offthe record functions for both British and American press and radio men.But much more interesting than these formal engagements were the&apos;variousinformal contacts which I had. Chief amongst these was a short interview with president Truman at the White House.I also met Senator McKellar, the Acting President of the Senate, and withhim a number of other Senators, including Senator Barkley, the Majority Leader,and Senator White, the Minority Leader. Being determined on both sides to keepoff controversial topics, notably the Loan, which must have been in the forefrontof all our thoughts, and perhaps because Republican as well as DemocraticSenators were represented, the talk we had was amiable rather than stimulating,and for the most part consisted of a not very penetrating exchange of information about methods and procedure in our respective Legislatures. It was, however,livened for a moment when a sensitive Senator took offence at my mild advocacy ofthe small Chamber in which there was no attempt to provide places for allthe members all the time, because, as I thought, it was an advantage that thedrama of great occasions was heightened by the crowded benches. He obviouslytook this as an affront to the American system!Indeed it was perhaps fortunate that in the case of the House ofRepresentatives it proved impracticable to get together a number of Congressmento see me; and the interview which I had with Mr. McCormaek. the FloorMajority-Leader, alone, was much more profitable. I was greatly impressed byhis ability, lively personality, and sincerity, and we had a long talk mainly on questions of Parliamentary procedure and Parliamentary management, in whichwe both, T think, learned a good deal.Organised inter-changes of visits between our Parliament and the UnitedStates Congress would be all to the good. There is all too little understandingin the United States of the virtues and vigour of British Parliamentarydemocracy.Lastly, thanks to the kindness of Lord and Lady Halifax (Lord Halifaxhimself was, unfortunately, ill during my stay in Washington), I had the oppor-tunity of meeting a number of representative American leaders at lunch anddinner at the Embassy. These included Chief Justice Frankfurter (at whoseinvitation I attended the opening of the Supreme Court on the following day)..Mr. Ickes, Mr. Vinson, Mr. Dean Acheson, General Omar Bradley, and variousimportant industrialists, business men and trade unionists. At the largest ofthese parties, at which the guests included Mr. L. B. Schwellenbach, the Secretaryfor Labour, Mr. Robert R. Wason, President of the National Association of manufacturers, Mr. Eric Johnston, President of the American Chamber of Com-merce, and Mr. John L. Lewis, there was a discussion which was, I think, sosignificant and for that matter so American that it seems to me to be worth: * His opposite numbers, Mr. William Green and Mr. Phil Murray, had been invited, but,much to my.regret at missing the chance of seeing the three great rivals of American tradeunionism together on neutral soil, they were too preoccupied with the current strikes to come.
recording. The question of controls was raised, and it might have been expected in view of the occasion that the conversation would have centred mainly on theBritish position. Not so. It was clear that the interest of the. industrialistsand the trade unionists alike in events outside the United States was lukewarm,and I was able as an almost silent spectator to enjoy an animated three-cornereddiscussion in which capital and labour, as equally fervent exponents of an almostclean sweep of controls, united in a combined operation against Government inthe person of Mr. Schwellenbach, the Secretary for Labour. It was the moreremarkable because it was initiated by a really eloquent and competent expositionby Mr. Lewis (who was much more mellow than when I had met him before) ofthe case for the removal of controls. These were the main obstacle to recon-version; the danger of inflation was not serious, some inflation might be good,and he denied that the lesson of the post-1918 period was that controls were removed too early; indeed he went very near to denying that the post-war boomwas followed by a post-inflationary slump, and he argued that the best antidoteto inflation being increased production all that was necessary in present circum-stances was to let the controls go and allow industry to do its job. Therepresentatives of capitalism, Mr. Wason and Mr. Johnston, naturally endorsedMr. Lewis&apos;s views, though Mr. Johnston was a little more cautious and thoughtthat rent control was an exception, and that price controls should perhaps beretained for six months but no longer. Mr. Lewis and Mr. Wason. I think,accepted these reservations; and Mr. Schwellenbach, no doubt unwilling to enterinto violent controversy especially within the precincts of the British Embassy,confined himself to a few mild expressions of- dissent and one or two examples of commodities where the removal of the present ceilings would lead to price increases. Altogether it seemed to me a disquieting illustration of the short-sighted way in which some of the leaders of American capital and labour, regard-less in large measure of the lessons of the past and of foreign experience, are approaching the problem of reconversion.I heard much of the Loan from &apos;&apos; Ministers &apos;&apos; and others. The general impression at the time seemed to be that in the end it would go through after a rough passage. But it would take a long time, we could not expect it probablyuntil April, and we must be prepared for much to be said of an anti-Britishcharacter. We should just have to put up with this as philosophically as wecould. Eor our part the more we can create the impression that we are stillalive and kicking, forward-looking, and stimulated rather than dismayed by our temporary difficulties, the better the effect on American opinion is likelyto be. There is a tendency to look upon Britain as a chronic invalid in theeconomic sense: the picture we want to get over is of a brave and energeticconvalescence from the wounds inflicted by the war. This I sought on all occa-sions to do.Criticisms of Britain and British Policy.Both in Canada and in the United States I met in the nature of things people who were on the whole likely to be sympathetic to Britain. But, makingevery allowance for this, my impression in both countries was of a fundamentalfriendliness, and it is necessary to recognise that, as I told the Press Club in washington I mention the remark because I think it is significant that it wentdown extremely well the periodical baiting of Britain is a national pastimein the United States which should not be taken too seriously. But, of course, Icame across a number of criticisms, and it may be of interest to record thosewhich recurred fairly often. There was little difference between Canada andthe United States as far as these criticisms are concerned.(i) Indonesia.Even amongst the otherwise well-informed, there were frequent examples of suspicion of British policy in Indonesia, combined with an ignorance of-thefacts which it is really rather difficult to excuse, notwithstanding that manyof the critics, Americans as well as Canadians, were in general friendly to Britainand were genuinely puzzled at what seemed to them an instance of our inveterateimperialism. Yet the most obvious rejoinders came almost as a surprise to them.They did not appear to have grasped that we went into Java not of our own soleinitiative, but in the discharge of our share of the Allied responsibilities in theFar East (incidentally the point was made by some that it was a pity that therewas not at least a token American contingent with our troops); or to haverealised that withdrawal at this juncture would expose Europeans to the risk
of death and torture, and be a breach of trust to the Dutch, not to mention theAmerican Government itself. And some had taken it for granted that once we were there we intended to stay.(ii) Palestine.The prevalent misunderstandings on this subject are so well known after all, they have their counterparts here that it seems unnecessary to do more than to mention them. On the whole, however, I heard less about Palestine than Iexpected.(iii) Professor Laski.I am afraid that I found the inevitable questions about Professor Laskiincreasingly irritating, because of the disproportionate importance attached tohis various utterances, but they are no doubt revealing of that curious sensitive-ness to criticism which is characteristic of some Americans.As I pointed out, we are after all a free country, we accept philosophicallyAmerican criticisms of Britain, Professor Laski, although a distinguishedpublicist, is a private individual who will at Whitsun cease to be Chairman ofthe National Executive Committee of the Labour Party, and it was all a stormin a teacup. Yet, while I do not take the matter too seriously, there is no doubtthat considerable resentment was caused by Professor Laski&apos;s criticisms of theUnited States. The same is true to a lesser extent of the Dean of Canterbury&apos;scriticisms. It was extraordinary to find that the Dean is taken seriouslysomewhere!(iv) Mosley.It was odd, almost like old times, to hear from Left Wing quarters the familiar variations on this hoary theme, from the question of his release by meto the alleged revival of Fascism now with the connivance, through default, ofthe British Government. And it was no less difficult to persuade these &quot; liberal &quot;critics that penal action by a Minister against a person who had committed no legal offence was inconsistent with the laws and traditions of a free society.(v) The General Election.I came across a few traces of the view that the British people had showningratitude to their great war leader by their verdict at the Election, but onthe whole it was recognised that gratitude for past achievements was irrelevant,and that the future, not the past, was in issue. The enormous prestige andpopularity of Mr. Churchill in both Canada and the United States were, however,everywhere apparent; the tributes which I paid to his wartime services were always enthusiastically applauded.I found, too, less evidence than I had expected of the belief which is saidto exist that Britain had gone &quot; Red &quot; and revolutionary. The attitude was rather that what the British did at the General Election was a matter for themselves,and keen interest was shown in the whys and wherefores of the Government&apos;ssocialisation programme as I expounded it. Some of my listeners were obviouslyand agreeably surprised that it was less radical and comprehensive than theyhad supposed; most of them did not hide their distrust of State control and the threat which, in their opinion, it involved to individual initiative and enterprise;but they did not seem to fear British Socialism as a commodity for export.British Information Services.I naturally took a keen interest in the activities of the United KingdomInformation Office in Ottawa and British Information Services in New Yorkand Washington. As far as I could judge it, I was impressed by the generalefficiency of the existing services and the excellent relations which seem to havebeen established with the Canadian and American press and radio; and, further,I was impressed with the importance of keeping this work going on a sufficiently large scale and at a high level of quality, not closely tied up withEmbassy or High Commissioner^ Office. The opportunities of misunder-standing, accidental and non-accidental, are so numerous, and the dividends fromgood relations are so great that we cannot afford to neglect the machinery whichis necessary to keep the British point of view adequately and accurately beforethe public in these two great countries. I found this was the firm view of the embassy in Washington and the High Commissioner in Canada as well as ofthe officials actually engaged on information work.
7108The Tourist Traffic.My trip enhanced my already strong conviction that the potentialities ofthe tourist traffic from Canada and the United States to this country are immense,as are the prospective advantages to us in terms both of dollars and good will.The number of persons I met who had personal associations with the UnitedKingdom was impressive, and many of them, including some who had been bornhere, said with obvious sincerity that they had long hoped to be able to come over on a visit but had never had the opportunity of doing so. There are many thousands of returning Service men and women who would like to renewtheir acquaintance with Britain and her people in peacetime conditions, and thereis a widespread interest in British culture and institutions which in itself would afford an excellent basis for the development of the tourist traffic on a larger scale than ever before.We cannot, of course, look forward to the resumption of this traffic on anyscale until the shipping situation has improved, the shortages of food and otherstaple commodities have passed, and our hotels are in a position to give satis-factory service to the visitors, but any plans we make now for their reception whenthe time comes will be richly rewarded. And I hope that those plans will take full account of the needs not only of the wealthy, who can probably be safely left to ordinary private enterprise, but also of the many thousands of Canadians and americans of the middle and better-off working classes who could not afford to stay in first-class hotels and for whom special facilities, in the shape, for example, of organised &quot; all in &quot; tours, would be useful. One difficulty for which it is not easy to see a satisfactory solution is that, unless Transatlantic air travel becomes aproposition for the masses, a quite disproportionate amount of the average summervacation would be taken up by the sea voyages, but a partial answer might be -as was done to some extent before the war to set out to make the voyages holidays in themselves, so that the visit to Britain would be combined with a pleasure cruise.I would hope too, I may add, that there would be an increase (not necessarily on acorresponding scale) in the number of British visitors to Canada and the UnitedStates. This would be a most valuable method of promoting mutual under-standing.H. M.Office of the Lord President of the Council, S.W. 1.21st February, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
