<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 396-399</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ft/  &amp;,      t^^Ji^Ccoi (V&quot;0THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1946.SECRET.CP. (46) 89.1st March, 1946.CABINET.% R Copy No. J uNATIONAL HEALTH SERVICE IN SCOTLAND.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland.Scottish Consultations.THE Minister of Health has reported in his paper CP. (46) 86 on thoseconsultations about our National Health Service proposals that have been con-ducted on a United Kingdom basis. The Scottish Local Authority Associationshave not taken part in the United Kingdom discussions, but I have consulted!them separately and I do not think that we need expect serious opposition inprinciple from the Scottish local authorities to the transfer of their hospitalsto the State.2. My consultations with the local authorities, the medical profession,and other interests in Scotland on the special Scottish aspects of the proposals have shown general support for the points of difference from England andWales described in my paper CP. (45) 345 of the 13th December last theadministration of ambulance services by the hospital organisation instead of by local health authorities; the establishment of Executive Councils for the family practitioner services on the basis of geographical counties instead of foreach local health authority; and the provision and maintenance of health centresby the Secretary of State in the first place, instead of by local health authorities.Teaching Hospitals.3. One other special Scottish point has been raised. The hospital facilities-used for clinical teaching in Scotland include a much larger proportion of thetotal hospital resources than in England and Wales. Thus the adoption in its-present form of the proposal to establish separate Boards of Governors forteaching hospitals would exclude from the direct concern of the Regional Boardsthe operation of a very substantial and most important part of the hospital service. In some quarters the view has been expressed, particularly by the localauthorities, that in Scotland the Regional Boards should be more directly concerned with the teaching hospitals than the powers to be exercised by the boards of Governors would permit. In considering modifications to meet thispoint of view, which I am inclined to share, I will, of course, take care to safe-guard the necessary independence of medical education. When the EnglishBill has been published I propose to discuss the matter further with the ScottishUniversities and other interests.4.   I should like briefly to mention two further points : (a) Payment for Loss of Remunerative Time.There is a case for providing, for members of both central and local bodies-set up under the National Health Service, not only out-of-pocket expenses and subsistence but also payment for loss of remunerative time. There is a recentprecedent in this sense in the Disabled Persons (Employment) Act, 1944.Indeed, if Ave make no such provision for Executive Councils, we are takingaway a power which at present exists for Insurance Committees in the national health Insurance Act. As regards local authorities, there is already inScotland provision for payment for loss of remunerative time to members of[31393]
County Councils, although not of other authorities. Some persons who have been concerned with hospital management as members uf County Councils will beincluded&apos; in the membership of -Regional Hospital Boards and Hospital Manage-ment Committees. I feel that, in all these circumstances, I must make provision in the Scottish Bill to apply to the various National Health Service bodies therelative provision of the Local Government Act.(b) Capital Value of Dental Practices.The Scottish dental representatives have pressed for compensation for theloss of capital values of dental practices, particularly those affected by theestablishment of a health centre in the neighbourhood. While dental practicesmay not be bought and sold to the same extent as medical practices, the practicesof better-class dentists have substantial capital values. There is a danger thatwe shall not be able to attract these dentists into health centres if we db notcompensate them for the loss of capital assets involved in this step, so that weshould be driven back on the less successful members of the profession, and thoserecently qualified. This might postpone the effective operation of the general dental service for many years. While I recognise that we must be careful to limit compensation to losses resulting directly, and not merely indirectly, fromthe operation of the new legislation, I am not clear that on balance it is desirableto treat dentists in so different a way from doctors as our present proposals seek to do.Scottish Bill.5. Subject to these observations. I fully support the proposals embodied in the Ministers draft Bill. Preparation of the Scottish Bill is under way,but I propose to defer its submission to my colleagues with any revised proposals about teaching hospitals in Scotland at least until the English bill has had its Second Reading.J. W.Scottish Office, S.W.1,1st March, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
