<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 400-405</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
5 3. v (, I Cjsfo -o a^-^-I3 DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC [MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT)Elfljg C R E To.P.(46) 901ST MARCH,   1946 COPY NO.CABINETWORLD FOOD SUPPLIES &apos;PROPOSED POLITICAL DISCUSSIONS 7/ITH UNITED STATESAND CANADIAN GOVERNMENTSMemorandum by the Lord president of the CouncilSince the Cabinet discussed my previous memorandum(CP. (1+6) 30) the problems then raised in discussion havebeen further considered by officials. I am now able toput forward the following revised appreciation.2. The short run gap between demand and supply continuesto widen.      Latest advice from the United States is thatduring February/March alone their exports will fall short&apos;of the target,  agreed in January and reaffirmed by thePresident on 6th February, by more than \ million tons.The measures so far decided on are recognised by authoritiesin Washington as inadequate,:  but even these inadequatemeasures are not being carried out.      In fact few countries are&apos; yet pretending to take steps proportionate to the gravity of the situation and of these fewer still arebacking their promises by action-3- For 1946/7 prospects are  even worse owing to the exhaustion not only of abnormal surpluses,  but of normalcarryover stocks and to the cumulative effects of lackof manpower,  lack of fertiliser,  and in some cases evenlack of seed to sow.      Therefore, after at least 2 yearsof famine or near famine, huge harvests in 1947 will be needed to restore any sort of reasonable security to theworld&apos;s bread.      If we are not to be blamed for doing too little too late we would be wise to plan on the basis ofat least two .dangerously lean years and one more year after that to restore normal conditions,4. It is true that on paper our own United Kingdomsupplies are assured.      We are, however, responsible,even within the Empire,  for tens of millions of people who are faced with starvation, headed by India,  SouthAfrica and our Far Eastern colonies.      Does any Ministerimagine that we can either maintain U.K.  food consumptionor sustain our policies in the Empire and foreigncountries against a background of two years&apos;  famine?Could we hope to defend the Government in that eventagainst the criticism that we  should have acted while there was   yet time?-1

5. The Minister of Pood has his vital and oneroustask to perform of procuring and distributing available supplies and of coping with the many related problems.In this unprecedented crisis, however, we have to consider how to bring all our power and influence to bear throug hall possible channels to reinforce his efforts.      We arenot directly responsible for the greater part of either the excessive demands or the deficient supplies which are-creating this crisis;    we can however, as the greatestimporting country and as the natural political&quot;leader ofthe importing countries,  play a.decisive part in mobilisinglong-term demand and mailing it effective in terms of increased supply.6. For this purpose I suggest that:-(a) The Minister of Food should invited the combined food Board to take account,  in consideringbids for wheat,  of the  extent to which theclaimant countries are doing all  in their powerto increase supplies at home by growing morecereals and making them available for human consumption, and abroad by translating theirunstable panic demands into reliable long-termbuying programmes which will justify exporting countries in making the necessary sweepingchanges in their crop policies;(b) In this connection I suggest that the ministers concerned should follow up the lead which&apos;theMinister of Food has already given in hisassurances to Canada by inviting India, France,China and other main claimants to  join with usin assurances that we will not buy wheat duringsay the next 3 or h years at a price of be lewone Canadian dollar or the equivalent in othercountries.    I do not suggest that we shouldcommit ourselves to any quantities as oardemand is already fairly stable and well-known,but there would be great advantage in the indians, French, etc.  giving assurances of atleast some minimum amount that they will buyand a minimum price at which they will buy it.We might complete this business at the EuropeanEmergency Economic Committee Food Conferenceof Ministers on hth April, meanwhile assuringthe Americans of our support and openingdiscussions with the governments concerned.In effect, we are ashing American farmers whohave a highly remunerative assured domestic market for other cereals,   to give it up infavour of growing wheat for a world market which is hopelessly uncertain at this momentas regards prices,  quantities,  and duration.The United States Government may be so impressed by the political dangers of world famine thatthey are ready to take the whole risk, and if so we should let them, but it would be imprudent not to be prepared if they insist that other countries (on whose behalf this effort is to be made) should share as much ofthe risk as their resources permit.      Also,even if the United States Government is readyto take a risk, American farmers may not do their part unless they can see a reasonablyassured, market in front of them.

(c)  The other essential is that the Overseas and service Departments should consider fully the implications in terms of civil disorder/ lossof production,  and otherwise of a famine -ridden world and that a statement of theseimplications should be conveyed to theUnited States Government by a personalapproach at the highest level.7. -Some day, perhaps not far distant, Parliament andthe Electorate will be impelled by events to place asearching scrutiny on what we have done and what we have failed to do in fighting the threat of famine.      if that threat should eventuate the nasty rocicing whichthe Government received In the weeic ending 9th Februarywill    appear a mere breeze compared with a cyclone.I cannot feel that, when that day comes, what we have sofar achieved will appear a very convincing answer tocritics.H.M.Office of the nord President,1 st March,   1 91+6.S.W.1.,


</content>
</cab>
