<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/7/0 images: 442-455</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY^ GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (46) 97.7th March, 1946.CABINET.PARLIAMENTARY PROCEDURE.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.1. The Select Committee on Parliamentary Procedure have asked for the comments of the Government on a memorandum which they have received fromSir Gilbert Campion, putting forward a number of drastic proposals for the reform of Parliamentary procedure. The proposals, which are summarised in annex I below, have been examined by the Machinery of Government (Parlia-mentary Procedure) Sub-Committee (under the Chairmanship of the Attorney-General), which was already reviewing the whole field of parliamentary procedure with a view to considering what further evidence might be laid beforethe Select Committee on behalf of the Government. The Report* of the Sub-Committee has been considered by a group of Ministers appointed by the PrimeMinister for the purpose, under my Chairmanship. We are agreed in recom-mending to the Cabinet that the memorandum at Annex II below, which contains,in Part I, comments on Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals and, in Part II, alternative proposals by the Government, should be presented to the Select Committee.2. This Memorandum rejects all Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals except one Supply procedure which is accepted with important modifications. The positivesuggestions for changes in Parliamentary procedure which are favoured in it areas follows : (a) Supply Day arrangements should be reorganised to provide greater flexibility throughout the Session and opportunities, at the discretion of the Government, for discussion on such days of matters involvinglegislation (paragraphs 4-6).(b) At the Report Stage of the Budget Resolutions the question should beput without amendment or debate (paragraph 14; but see (c) below).(c) At the Report Stages of Bills (other than the Finance Bill) kept on the floor of the House debate should be restricted, by Order, to Govern-ment amendments, points left over -from the Committee Stage and newpoints arising after the completion of the Committee Stage. (If theSelect Committee prefer to apply this also to&apos; the Finance Bill, theproposal at (6) may be dropped).   (Paragraphs 15 and 16).(d) The procedure on motions for the limited recommittal of any Bill towhich the proposal at (c) above applies should be equated to theprocedure on motions to recommit a Bill generally, when moved at thebeginning of the Report Stage (paragraph 17).(e) The Chairman and Deputy Chairman of Ways and Means should havepower to accept closure motions whenever sitting as Deputy Speaker(paragraph 18).(/) There should be established a &quot; Business Committee,&quot; nominated by the speaker, with the function of allocating, between various parts ofa Bill, the time allowed for any particular stage of a Bill, whetherby guillotine resolution or voluntary agreement (paragraph 19).(a) There should be a restriction on debate in Standing Committee on thequestion that &quot; the clause stand part&quot; (paragraph 20).(A) A minor point regarding financial resolutions, on which the SelectCommittee deferred a decision, should again be brought to their notice (paragraph 21).M.G. (P.) (46) 4.

THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJE8TVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1946.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (46) 97.7th March, 1946.CABINET.PARLIAMENTARY PROCEDURE.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council.1. The Select Committee on Parliamentary Procedure have asked for the comments of the Government on a memorandum which they have received fromSir Gilbert Campion, putting forward a number of drastic proposals for the reform of Parliamentary procedure. The proposals, which are summarised in annex I below, have been examined by the Machinery of Government (Parlia-mentary Procedure) Sub-Committee (under the Chairmanship of the Attorney-General), which was already reviewing the whole field of parliamentary procedure with a view to considering what further evidence might be laid beforethe Select Committee on behalf of the Government. The Report* of the Sub-Committee has been considered by a group of Ministers appointed by the PrimeMinister for the purpose, under my Chairmanship. We are agreed in recom-mending to the Cabinet that the memorandum at Annex II below, which contains,in Part I, comments on Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals and, in Part II, alternative proposals by the Government, should be presented to the Select Committee.2. This Memorandum rejects all Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals except one Supply procedure which is accepted with important modifications. The positivesuggestions for changes in Parliamentary procedure which are favoured in it areas follows : (a) Supply Day arrangements should be reorganised to provide greater flexibility throughout the Session and opportunities, at the discretion of the Government, for discussion on such days of matters involvinglegislation (paragraphs 4-6).(b) At the Report Stage of the Budget Resolutions the question should beput without amendment or debate (paragraph 14; but see (c) below).(c) At the Report Stages of Bills (other than the Finance Bill) kept on the floor of the House debate should be restricted, by Order, to Govern-ment amendments, points left over -from the Committee Stage and newpoints arising after the completion of the Committee Stage. (If theSelect Committee prefer to apply this also to the Finance Bill, theproposal at (b) may be dropped).  (Paragraphs 15 and 16).(d) The procedure on motions for the limited recommittal of any Bill towhich the proposal at (c) above applies should be equated to theprocedure on motions to recommit a Bill generally, when moved at thebeginning of the Report Stage (paragraph 17).(e) The Chairman and Deputy Chairman of Ways and Means should havepower to accept closure motions Avhenever sitting as Deputy Speaker(paragraph 18).(/) There should be established a &quot; Business Committee,&quot; nominated by the speaker, with the function of allocating, between various parts ofa Bill, the time allowed for any particular stage of a Bill, whetherby guillotine resolution or voluntary agreement (paragraph 19).(g) There should be a restriction on debate in Standing Committee on thequestion that 1&apos; the clause stand part&apos;&apos; (paragraph 20).(h) A minor point regarding financial resolutions, on which the SelectCommittee deferred a decision, shoidd again be brought to their notice (paragraph 21).M.G. (P.) (46) 4.
3. The arguments which have weighed with us in adopting this attitudeare embodied in the memorandum itself. There are, however, a number ofadditional points, not altogether suitable for inclusion in the memorandum, towhich I would draw the Cabinet&apos;s attention :Comments on Sir G. Campion&apos;s Proposals.(a) Public Expenclittire Committee. dt is clear that Sir G. Campion&apos;intention in this proposal is that the war-time National expenditure committee should in effect be reconstituted, with terms of referenceenlarged to cover the whole field of Government expenditure.Nominally that Committee was precluded (as are the Public accounts committee and the Estimates Committee) from considering questionsof policy; but it constantly strayed outside its proper scope and fre-quently caused embarrassment to Ministers by ranging over widequestions of policy which should properly be dealt with on the floor ofthe House, where the responsible Minister can reply. Some Ministersthought at the time that an improper degree of power was in practiceacquired by the clerks of the Committee and its sub-committees. in deciding not to reconstitute the National Expenditure Committee theGovernment have in effect already decided against this proposal.(b) Reform of Supply Procedure. We have accepted, with importantmodifications, Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals on this matter, in the hopethat they will save time by making Allotted Days more readily avail-able throughout the session for debates which would otherwise occupyGovernment time. I must warn my colleagues, however, that the saving may not be so great as we hope, because the disposition of the days through the Session will be largely in the hands of the Opposition;they could hinder the progress of the Governments programme either by using up the Allotted Days quickly, so that Government time wouldhave to be found for similar debates later in the session, or byrefraining from using them in the earlier part of the Session, so thatthere would be a large number to be worked off, to the detriment ofother business, before the Summer recess.(c) Reorganisation of Standing Committees. An additional reason against taking the Report Stage of Bills upstairs is that it would give theGovernment considerably less control over legislation. Under thepresent system the Report is essentially the stage where the Govern-ment can insist on getting their way and are enabled by their majorityto set right, if necessary, anything which has been carried against them in Committee and to carry half-way concessions on pointsreserved in Committee for further consideration. Since the Whips donot fully function in Standing Committee and under Sir G. Campion&apos;sproposals the decision on points of detail would be removed from the floor of the House altogether, the whole advantage of the present report Stage would be lost.(d) Second Reading of Scottish Bills. An additional reason against theproposal to refer to the Scottish Standing Committee the SecondReading of Scottish Bills is that it might well prove an embarrassingprecedent, if adduced in support of similar devolution for othersectional Bills. Further, if it so happened that the majority of scottish Members were in opposition to the Government, special measures would be necessary to ensure that the Government retainedcontrol over the proceedings of the Standing Committee.(e) Select Committee on Statutory Rules and Orders. The proposal that theSelect Committee should have power to enquire into the merits ofcertain Statutory Instruments was considered and deliberatelyrejected by the Coalition Government, when the institution of theSelect Committee was first under consideration.Alternative Proposals by the Government.(f) Budget and Finance Bill. This is the most important of the Govern-menfs own proposals. Although arguments can be found againstalmost any change in the present Budget and Finance Bill procedure,the fact remains that year after year the Committee Stage of theBudget Resolutions is repeated in the Second Reading of the finance bill and the Report Stage of the Resolutions in the Committee Stage
of the Finance Bill. The proposal put forward to formalise theReport Stage of the Budget Resolut ions is the one which does leastviolence to the present pixtcedure and should nevertheless produce a material saving.(g) Restriction in Delate on Report. We should have liked to propose that,where the Committee Stage of a Bill has been taken on the floor ofthe House, debate on Report should be restricted to Governmentamendments. There is, however, considerable force in the argument that such a restriction would in fact deprive Ministers of thepossibility of offering on the Committee Stage to consider furthersome point which had been raised, since, if their considerationdid not result in a Government amendment, there would be no oppor-tunity for further discussion of the matter. Moreover, where aguillotine has been in operation in Committee it may have excludedcertain clauses from discussion altogether and the Report Stage maythen be the only occasion for the Opposition to press their amendments.Finally, it is always possible that new points may arise after thecompletion of a Committee Stage upon which there is legitimate desire for debate but which are not covered by Government amendments.4. In the course of our examination of this matter we have been impressed by the likelihood that, although on the whole the use of delegated legislationsaves time, it must be expected that in the future considerably more time will be spent by the House in discussing delegated legislation. It seems to us that theincrease might be mitigated to some extent if there were a more clearly definedpractice regarding the use of the Affirmative Resolution procedure. On thewhole this involves greater calls on the time of the House than does the negative resolution procedure. Important or controversial delegated legislation will be debated in any event and, if instruments are made sub j ect to Affirmative resolution which would not provoke a Prayer if subject to the other procedure, there is clearloss of time. Affirmative Resolution procedure is regularly pressed for duringthe Committee Stages of Bills, but the cumulative effect of making concessions in particular cases may be serious. There are certain classes of case and importance is not necessarily the criterion where Affirmative Resolutions are appropriate. I suggest that &quot;it would be worth while for the Cabinet to arrangefor this area to be defined and adhered to in future Government legislation.5.   I ask the Cabinet (a) To approve the submission of Annex II to the Select Committee.(6) To arrange for an examination to be made of the principles which should govern the use of the Affirmative Resolution procedure.H. M.Office of the Lord President of the Council,7th March, 1946.
ANNEX I.Summary of Sir G. Campion&apos;s Proposals.I. Public Expenditure Committee.THERE should be established by Standing Order a Select Committee on public Expenditure of at least thirty members, replacing the Public accounts committee and the Estimates Committee and working through seven Sub-Com-mittees, of which four would deal with both the accounts and the estimates of all Departments (grouped under four heads), the fifth with &quot; major enquiries,&quot;the sixth with &quot; special short-term enquiries into current complaints,&quot; while the seventh would be a co-ordinating Sub-Committee of the Chairmen of the otherSub-Committees. The organisation would be similar to that developed by theNational Expenditure Committee. The services of the Comptroller and Auditor-General and his deputies would be available as required and there would also be&quot; need of a sufficient body of trained clerks who would perform similar services to those recently rendered to the National Expenditure Committee.&quot;II. Procedure in Committee of Supply.(a) There should be a minimum of 28 Allotted Days, including the four days at present devoted to moving the Speaker out of the Chair on first going into Committee of Supply, and also days for the Spring Supplementary Estimates.(b) These days should be spread evenly over the session, so that one allottedday would fall in practically every week. It might be advisable to set aparta particular day Thursday for this purpose, subject to an easy method of changing the day, when the House wishes.(c) There should be two guillotines, one in July to cover the main estimates and any others to be included in the Appropriation Act, and the other in march to cover the Spring Supplementary Estimates, the Vote on Account and anyother supply normally financed by the March Consolidated Fund Bill.(d) At periods of the year when there is no business to transact in Committeeof Supply, debate on an Allotted Day should be on an amendment to the motionthat Mr. Speaker do leave the Chair, and at other times debate should, at the option of the Opposition, be either on such an amendment or on a selected Voteor Votes in Committee of Supply.(e) The rule excluding from debate matters involving legislation should beretained in Committee of Supply, but abolished for debates on moving the speaker out.(/) On two Allotted Days reports from the Public Expenditure Committeeshould have precedence.III. Adjournment Motion under Standing Order No. 8.An attempt should be made to reduce the inconvenience caused when aMember succeeds in raising a &quot; definite matter of urgent public importance&quot;by (i) limiting the period of the debate on such a motion to two hours, as opposedto hours as at present, and (ii) providing that business superseded by the motion should automatically become exempted business for a length of time equalto the time lost.Further, it might be advantageous to return to the earlier practice wherebyit was for the Speaker to decide whether the matter raised was &quot; definite,&quot; whileits &apos;&apos; urgency and public importance &apos;&apos; was a matter for the Member raising thesubject and his supporters.IV. Reorganisation of Standing Committees.(a) There should be established two large standing committees, consistingof 75 to 100 members each, to be divided into at least three sub-committees ofabout 25 members each;(6) Bills sent upstairs should be committed to one of the sub-committees,15 additional members being added in respect of each Bill;(c) Seven members of each sub-committee should be nominated to makedrafting and consequential amendments between the committee stage and thereport stage;
(d) The report stage of such Bills should be taken not by the House but byone of the two main standing committees;(e) Bills so dealt with should be reported to the House, which could re-commit the Bill to the Standing Committee, but could not amend it, though it mightdebate the Bill as a whole on the motion for its consideration;(/) Any member who had given notice of an amendment to a Bill committed to a standing committee should have the right, although not a member of theCommittee, to attend, move his amendment and take part in the debate upon it,without the right to vote.V. Application of Scheme to Scottish Bills.The constitution of the Standing Committee for Scottish Bills should remain as at present, but it should be empowered, if it saw fit, to divide itself into sub-committees. Whether it did so or not, the Report Stage of Scottish Bills wouldbe taken by the Standing Committee and the procedure for further stages wouldbe the same as for Bills reported from other Standing Committees. In addition,provision might be made whereby the Second Reading of Scottish Bills could betransferred from the House to the Scottish Standing Committee.VI. Uncontentious Bills Committee.Small select committees, drawn from a panel appointed for the purpose,should be constituted for the consideration of uncontentious bills.VII. Private Members&apos; Bills and Motions.(a) Private Members&apos; Bills should be given precedence according to theamount of support they obtain, not according to a ballot;(b) The ballot for Private Members&apos; motions should be retained, but shouldbe between notices of motions instead of between members.(c) The time for Private Members&apos; motions should be spread over a longer period by allotting one half-day a week (possibly on Mondays) forsuch motions, instead of as at present, a whole day.VIII. Statutory Instruments.The Select Committee on Statutory Rules and Orders should be given theadditional functions of (a) Enquiring into the merits of statutory instruments brought before it, ifsubject to Negative Resolution procedure only, and(b) Enquiring into and reporting on any grievances arising out of instru-ments already in operation. Complaints would be laid either bypetition to the House or direct to the Committee by Members or bythe actual complainants.IX. Time Limit to Speeches.An experiment might be made, if desired, in a suitable field of proceedings,in the application of a time limit to speeches.
ANNEX II.Draft Memorandum for Presentation to the Select Committee on parliamentary Procedure.1. The Government have given to Sir Gilbert Campion&apos;s memorandum thecareful consideration due to a document so boldly conceived and ably presented.The result of their examination is set out in Part I below; Part II containscertain alternative proposals which are submitted for the consideration of theSelect Committee. If it is thought that Part I is unduly destructive, and part II disappointingly meagre, two points should be borne in mind : (a) The Government inevitably approach this matter from a point of viewdifferent from that of the Clerk of the House. He is concerned with&apos;&apos; the general improvement of the machinery and forms of proceedingof the House so as to provide suitable instruments for the dischargeof its various functions &quot;; the Government, on the other hand, mustbe constantly mindful of their legislative requirements, and proceedwith the main objective of facilitating the passage through Parlia-ment of legislation which the Government regard as necessary forthe well-being of the nation.(b) The memorandum previously submitted by the Government to the SelectCommittee, on which the Committee have already reported, covers a great deal of the ground which, from the Government point ofview, it is profitable to explore.Part I. Comments on Sir G. Campion&apos;s Proposals.Public Expenditure Committee.2. The Government agree that the control of expenditure is a properfunction of the House, and that debates in Committee of Supply no longereffectively serve that purpose. They consider, however, that the present public accounts and Estimates Committees can meet the requirements of Parliament far more effectively that Sir G. Campion allows.   Thus (a) Inconsistency and overlapping between the Committees are very rare,and can be avoided by providing an element of common membership.(b) The Estimates Committee consists of twenty-eight members only twoless than the proposed Public Expenditure Committee and has powerto appoint Sub-Committees.(c) It is somewhat unreal to argue that the three-year period spanned bythe Accounts and Estimates is the natural unit, that therefore the accounts and Estimates must be considered by a single body, andthat under the present system the middle year of the three is leftuncovered. In normal times that year will have been considered bythe Estimates Committee of the previous year; and it has alwaysbeen the practice for the Estimates Committee to receive full informa-tion about expenditure in any previous years.3.   The Government consider that Sir G. Campion&apos;s own proposal is opento the following objections :  (a) The Comptroller and Auditor-General and his staff could not possiblyrender advice and criticism over the whole of the field proposed,much of which is quite alien to their statutory function of conductinga continuous audit directed to the regularity of expenditure.(&amp;) To institute some parallel organisation for the Estimates would faceMinisters and Departments with the necessity for securing approval to projected expenditure not only from the Chancellor of the Exchequerand the Treasury, but also from another set of officials independent of the executive.(c) A system which subjected every item of departmental expenditure overa three-year period to the close and searching scrutiny of a small bodyof Members would place a very heavy burden on senior officers and inevitably hamper the efficiency of executive action by importingdelays and cramping initiative.The Government accordingly feel unable to agree with Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals under this head.
Procedure in Committee of Supply.4. The Government are on the whole attracted by this part ofSir G. Campion&apos;s proposals which recognises that debates in Committee of Supplyhave come to be occasions for the criticism of Government policy and adminis-tration and that their incidence throughout the Session should not be governed bythe accidents of the financial calendar. They would therefore be disposed to welcome proposals on these general lines, subject to the following : (a) The Government think that 28 Allotted Days would be too many.   Theynotice that on two days it is suggested that reports from the public expenditure Committee should have precedence. If, as the Govern-ment suggest, the proposal for this Committee is not proceeded with,it may perhaps be agreed that 26 days would be enough.(b) To arrange the days as suggested by Sir G. Campion, so that one fallson nearly every Thursday, would import an element of inflexibility inthe plan which would rob it of much of its attraction. It may oftenhappen that both the Government and Opposition desire to take twoAllotted Days together for the purpose of a single debate. It seemsbetter, therefore, to make no provision for the precise manner in whichthe allotted days are spread through the Session.(c) The Government agree that two guillotines, one in July and one in March,will be necessary. They will have to be timed by reference to acalendar date rather than to a specified number of Allotted Days.(d) The most difficult features of the proposals are : (i) that debate may arise on any Allotted Day on amendments to the motion that the speaker do leave the Chair; and (ii) which must be considered with (i) that in such debates the rule against raising matters requiringlegislation should be abolished. In the Government view, these pro-posals go too far. The almost inevitable result would be that debates on moving the Speaker out, with their greater freedom, would becomemuch more frequent than debates in Committee of Supply; this wouldchange the whole character of the debates and the estimates themselvesmight never be considered at all. Further, while the abolition incertain circumstances of the present rules of debate would often be convenient both for the Government [and] the Opposition, too exten-sive a relaxation would greatly increase the burden on Ministers andtheir Departments in preparing for these debates and frequentlygive rise to pressure for statements on matters which were still underconsideration by the Government and might well be at the moment the subject of delicate negotiations.5. The Government would, however, agree that on the four days when the speaker is moved out of the Chair on first going into Committee of Supply(when debate arises on amendments put down by members successful in the ballot),the rule against raising matters involving legislation should not apply. But,for the reasons given above, they could not agree to any automatic relaxation of the rule on other Supply Days. They agree that it might at times be con-venient to have debates on Supply Days on the motion that the Speaker doleave the Chair, rather than in Committee of Supply itself both in order tostage wide debates for which no particular Vote or batch of Votes is quiteappropriate, and in order to stage debates on Supply Days at periods of theyear when there is no business to transact in Committee of Supply; but theyconsider that debates should take place on this motion only if the government agreed and not at the sole option of the Opposition. They further considerthat the rule against discussing legislation should not be relaxed automaticallyon all such occasions, but only when (after discussion through the usual channels)it had been specifically suspended. As in the case of motions to suspend theStanding Order (Sittings of the House), only the Government should be ableto move a suspension motion and it would be put without amendment or debate.6.   The Governments suggestions therefore are :  (i) There should be a minimum of 26 Supply Days spread (but on no rigidsystem) throughout the Session. These would include the four daysnow spent on first moving the Speaker out of the Chair, and daysfor Supplementary Estimates,(ii) There should be two Guillotines, fixed by reference to calendar dates, one in the Summer and one in the Spring.
(iii) On the four days when the Speaker is first moved out the rule againstdiscussing matters involving legislation should be relaxed.(iv) On any of the other 22 days debate could, if the Government agreed,be on the motion that the Speaker do leave the Chair, instead of in committee of Supply; and on any such occasion it would be opento the Government to move to suspend the rule restricting debate,the motion to suspend being put without amendment or debate.Adjournment Motion under Standing Order No. 8.7. The Government see no reason to alter the present procedure or to take any steps which would have the effect of making such motions more frequent.In particular, they would not feel it right to accept the proposal that the urgency and public importance of such motions should be decided by the member raising the matter and his supporters. The Government time-table cannot be at themercy of any forty members who have thought of a motion which would go forwardsolely on the ground that it was sufficiently definite to be accepted by the Speaker.Reorganisation of Standing Committees.8. This is, perhaps, the boldest part of Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals, and isattractive at first sight, since it would appear to save time on the Floor of theHouse by transferring the Report Stage upstairs. On examination, however, theproposals expose themselves to the following objections :(a) Additional stages would be introduced into the legislative procedure,making six instead of four, and involving a corresponding extra burden on Ministers.(&amp;) The debate in the House on the question that the Bill be considered, onreport from the main standing committee, would very largely duplicatethe debate on the third reading. The only power of the House wouldbe to recommit (which is already open to them on Third Reading) andmotions for recommittal would certainly be more frequent.(c) There is a serious possibility that the bottleneck might arise in standingcommittee when Bills were coming forward for consideration by themain committee on report at the same time as its members were, intheir respective sub-committees, occupied with the Committee stages of other Bills. Under the present system a Coal Bill can be taken in committee upstairs in the morning and an Industrial Injuries Bill canbe taken in the House on Report in the evening. Under Sir G.Campion&apos;s proposals these two processes could be taken on the same day only if the time of the House were used under Standing order no. 49a for Committee work.(d) The proposal for a drafting sub-sub-committee is wrong both in principle and in practice; drafting must be the responsibility of the Governmentand must be clone by an experienced draftsman.(e) The whole basis of the work of Standing Committees would be altered;if any member had the right to attend and speak they would lose their corporate identity, and their proceedings would almost certainlytake longer than under the existing system.(/) Members not members of the standing committee would be able to avoidhaving to declare themselves either for or against a particular pointin a Bill.(g) Nevertheless, the removal of the report stage from the House might wellbe unpopular with members generally, who would thus have no oppor-tunity to speak on particular points in the Bill on the Floor of theHouse. The right to speak in the Standing Committee would probably not be regarded as sufficient compensation.For these reasons the Government are opposed to these proposals; in particular,for the reasons given at (a), (c) and (e) above, they believe that they would notfacilitate the passage of legislation.Application of scheme to Scottish Bills.9. In so far as the proposals repeat features of those for English Bills,they are open to the objections given in the preceding paragraph and the attitudeof the Government towards them is the same. The proposal to transfer theSecond Reading of Scottish Bills to the Scottish Standing Committee wouldprobably not be generally popular.  It would appear to put Scottish Bills into an
inferior class inappropriate for the full attention of the Mother of Parliaments,and Scottish Members would be deprived of the opportunity to speak to them on the Floor of the House. Even if, nevertheless, the proposal were popular withScottish Members because of the tendency it would indicate towards greaterdevolution of Scottish affairs, it would probably be unwelcome to Members for english constituencies (some of whom are Scots), since they would, even morecompletely than at present, be debarred from debate on purely Scottish Bills. TheGovernment, therefore, oppose these proposals also.Committee for Uncontentious Bills.10. In the opinion of the Government very little would be gained by thisproposal, since really uncontentious Bills occupy very little time on the Floor ofthe House. The proposal would add another stage to the procedure. Moreover,it would be necessary to arrange some time-limit, after which, if no amendments to the Motion for Second Reading were put down, a Bill might be regarded asuncontentious. The period allowed would have to be of reasonable length andit might therefore become more difficult to get uncontentious Bills throughquickly.   The Government are, therefore, unable to support this proposal.Private Members&apos; Bills and Motions.11. The Government are disposed to agree that plans might well be devised for increasing the usefulness of Private Members&apos; time. The whole matter,however, is academic at present, since the Government continue to find it neces-sary to take all Private Members&apos; time. No detailed comments are thereforeoffered on Sir G. Campion&apos;s proposals under this head; the Government would welcome an opportunity of considering the matter further.Statutory Instruments.12. The Government cannot recommend either of the additional functionsproposed for the Select Committee on Statutory Rules and Orders. The first would mean that Ministers would have to attend before the Select Committee todefend the policy embodied in subordinate legislation; the second would havethe effect of enabling the Select Committee to enquire into all phases of Govern-ment administration within the very wide field now covered by delegated legislation.Time-Limit on Speeches.13. The Government would regret the introduction of a time-limit tospeeches, in any field of proceedings; they believe that the object of the proposalscan best be attained through the influence of public opinion in the House and theexercise of the powers already possessed by the Chair.Part II. Alternative Proposals.Budget and Finance Bill.14. It is clear that the shortening of procedure on the Budget and finance bill could only make a relatively modest contribution to the total time availablefor Government legislation. The case, for a change must rest rather on thecharacter of that procedure itself, with the opportunities it offers for repetitivedebate; and, of course, any reasonable saving of time would be welcome. Thepresent procedure involves duplication of Debate at two points : the committee stage of the Budget Resolutions is duplicated in the Second Reading of theFinance Bill, and the Report Stage of the Resolutions in the Committee stage of the Finance Bill. It would, therefore, seem logical to formalise one or other part of each pair of stages. There are formidable difficulties in the way offormalising either the Committee Stage of the Budget Resolutions or the SecondReading of the Finance Bill; in the view of the Government the least difficultchange would be to provide that at the Report Stage of the Budget Resolutionsthe question should be put without amendment or debate, any points of detailAvhich members desire to raise being left over for the Committee Stage of theFinance Bill. If this proposal were accepted, it would ^probably be necessaryto provide that on the Committee Stage all the Resolutions except one shall betaken immediately after the Chancellors Budget Speech, the Committee dividingif necessary.  (The immediate passing of these Resolutions is essential to preserve
the machinery of the Provisional Collection of Taxes Act; and presumably theOpposition would not be so ready to accept them without a division if they couldnot be further discussed on Report.)Report Stage of Bills kept on the Floor of the House.15. Before reaching a decision on the proposal in the previous paragraph,the Government suggest that the Select Committee might consider the followingproposal in connection with it. It seems likely that one of the results of the recentchanges in Standing Committee arrangements will be the lengthening of theReport Stages of Bills sent upstairs : conversely, therefore, it would seem appro-priate that means should be found to shorten the Report Stages of Bills kept onthe Floor of the House. The Government therefore propose that at the report stage of such Bills, debate should be restricted, by Order, to Government amend-ments, points left over at the Committee Stage for further consideration and newpoints arising after the completion of the Committee Stage.16. The connection of this proposal with the previous one rs as follows.It would apply to the Finance Bill, inasmuch as that Bill is normally kept on the floor of the House. The Government, however, do not wish the procedure of theBudget and Finance Bill to be truncated in two places : if, therefore, the SelectCommittee accept the proposal for the formalising of the Budget Resolutions theGovernment would agree to except the Finance Bill from the scope of the present proposal: on the other hand, they would be prepared to drop the proposal forformalising the Budget resolutions if the Committee accepted, for the finance bill, and all other Bills kept on the Floor of the House, the restriction on debateindicated in the preceding paragraph.Recommittal Procedure.17. The adoption of the proposed restriction on debate on Report wouldmake it necessary as a corollary to limit the freedom of members to move the limited recommittal of a Bill, whether on the Report Stage or on the third reading. It would be sufficient for this purpose if the procedure on motions for limited recommittal, whenever moved, were equated to the procedure on motionsto recommit a Bill generally when moved at the beginning of the Report Stage.The effect of this would be that the Speaker would permit only a brief explanatorystatement of the reasons for the proposed recommittal from the mover of the motion, and a similar statement by one Member opposed to it; the question wouldthen be put without further debate.Powers of the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of Ways and Means.18. In the view of the Government, the Chairman and Deputy Chairman of ways and Means should have the power to accept closure motions whenever theyare sitting as Deputy Speaker (instead of only when the Speaker&apos;s unavoidableabsence has been previously announced). This change would of course apply toall proceedings of the House.Business Committee.19. The memorandum previously presented to the Select Committee by theGovernment contained a proposal (paragraph 12) for the establishment of aspecial Committee of the House, consisting of the members of the Chairmen&apos;sPanel with five additional members nominated by the Speaker. This Committeewas to have the function, where a guillotine resolution had been carried in respectof a Bill, of allocating, as between various parts of the Bill, the time allowed bythe guillotine resolution for any particular stage. The Select Committee con-sidered this proposal chiefly in relation to the Committee stages of Bills takenupstairs, and for this purpose produced an alternative proposal (First Report,paragraph 17) which the Government accepted as an improvement on their own.As the Select Committee recognised, however, their proposal makes no provisionfor sub-dividing the time allotted to the Committee Stage of Bills taken on the floor of the House, or the Report Stage of any Bill. For such cases the Govern-ment consider that a Committee of the kind originally suggested would be of value, and they accordingly ask the Select Committee to reconsider it for thislimited purpose only. Apart, however, from the natural difference of scope,they would suggest two further modifications of the original proposal:(a) The name might be &quot;Business Committee&quot; rather than &quot;EmergencyBusiness Committee.&quot;
(b) The terms of reference should be so drawn as to enable the Committeeto function not only in cases where a guillotine resolution has beencarried in respect of a Bill, but also where the length of time tobe devoted to a particular stage has been fixed by voluntary agreement.Procedure in Standing Committee.20. The former Government memorandum contained a proposal (para-graph 11) for the amendment of procedure in Standing Committee, to the effectthat, if a clause has been amended, debate should not be permitted on the question that &quot; the clause stand part.&quot; unless the Chairman is of opinion that the principleof the clause, cr any substantial point arising thereon, has not been adequatelydiscussed. The Government agree with the first comment of the Select Com-mittee (First Report, paragraph 19) that the principle upon which the proposals is based applies with equal force where the clause, although not amended, hasbeen fully discussed on amendments proposed. They do not. however, agree either that the onus which would rest on the Chair is an improper one, or that the powersalready possessed by the Chair are sufficient in practice; they therefore ask theSelect Committee to reconsider the matter and see whether they could not agreethat the proposal, modified to meet their first comment, should be adopted atany rate on a trial basis.Financial Resolutions.21. The Government would remind the Select Committee that they havedeferred consideration (First Report, paragraph 23) of a proposal in the formerGovernment memorandum that the rule under which a Financial Resolution is needed to cover provisions of a Bill requiring money to be paid into theExechequer should be abolished. They trust that the Committee will find it possible to accept this proposal.


</content>
</cab>
