<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/50/50 images: 491-498</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. January 1975CM (72) Copy No.49th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Friday, 3 November, 1972at 3 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Edward Heath, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Lord Hailsham of st. Marylebone, Lord chancellor the Right Hon. William Whitelaw,mp, Secretary of State for northern ireland the Right Hon. Robert Carr, mp,Secretary of State for the home department and Lord President ofthe council the Right Hon. Geoffrey Rippon,qc, mp, Chancellor of the duchy of lancaster the Right Hon. Gordon Campbell,mp, Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Peter Walker, mp,Secretary of State for the Environ-ment the Right Hon. James Prior, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Anthony Barber,mp, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Lord Carrington,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Sir Keith Joseph,mp, Secretary of State for social services the Right Hon. Margaret Thatcher,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl Jellicoe,Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Peter Thomas, qc,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. John Davies, mp,Secretary of State for Trade and industry the Right Hon. Maurice Macmillan,m p, Secretary of State for employment the following were also present:The Right Hon. Francis Pym, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir/Peter Rawlinson,qc, mp, Attorney-general secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Burke trend . J. J. B. hunt mr. K. T. barnett mr. J. anson mr. I. T. LawmanSECRET146897-9 A
SubjectIndustrial AffairsDiscussions between the Government, the Confederation of British Industry andthe Trades Union Congress/
IndustrialAffairsDiscussionsbetween theGovernment,theConfederationof BritishIndustry andthe TradesUnionCongressPreviousReference:CM (72) 48thConclusions,Minute 4*The Prime Minister informed the Cabinet that at the final meet-ing with the Confederation of British Industry (CBI) and the TradesUnion Congress (TUC) on the previous afternoon the Governmenfscomprehensive proposals for bringing inflation under control hadbeen tabled in full. The CBI had been prepared to discuss them itemby item. But the TUC had dismissed them in total, maintaining thatthey provided no basis for negotiation. Their spokesmen had under-taken to convene a meeting of their General Council on the following monday; but they had indicated that they would not be prepared torecommend the Governmenfs proposals to the Council and had expressed complete conviction that the Council would reject them.The tuc&apos;s motives in breaking off the discussions so abruptlymust remain a matter of speculation. Some of the union leadersmight have been determined from the outset to thwart any attemptto reach agreement with the Government; others might have misin-terpreted the situation and, assuming that the government&apos;s proposals were no more than the basis of subsequent bargaining inthe conventional sense, might have been disconcerted by the Govern-ment s insistence that they constituted an integrated programme fordealing with inflation, which must be judged as a whole. But,whatever the reasons, the negotiations had now broken down andit was a matter for great regret that it had not proved possible tobring the enterprise on which the Government had embarked earlier in the year to a successful conclusion.In discussion there was unanimous agreement that nobody could have done more than the Prime Minister to seek to reach a reason-able settlement with both sides of industry. In particular, he hadconducted the discussions in such a way that the final breakdownhad occurred not on some specific issue on which the Governmenfsposition might not have been easily defensible but as a result of the tuc&apos;s rejection of the proposals as a whole. The Government were therefore in a strong position; and it was important that they shouldextract the maximum of advantage from it in terms of the public presentation of the issues involved. They should not indulge inrecrimination or attempt to apportion blame for the failure of thediscussions. Their attitude should rather be one of regret that the tuc had failed to seize a major opportunity to deal rationally with inflation. But, although they should endeavour by these means notto lose contact with the more moderate union leaders and to leave theway open for a resumption of the discussions at some point in thefuture, they should also ensure that the public presentation of theirown case did no go by default. The measures which they had tabledhad included many proposals which should command the supportof public opinion; and it would be important to demonstrate how much had been lost possibly not even excluding an increase in thefigure of  2 per week which they had prescribed as the maximum permissible increase in wages as a result of the folly and intransi-gence of the TUC.
It would now be necessary to introduce legislation, togetherwith an explanatory White Paper, empowering the Government to institute a 90 day &quot; freeze &quot; of prices and incomes as the prelude tothe enactment of more permanent methods of statutory control.The Cabinet turned to consider drafts of these documents, whichhad been circulated under cover of a Note by the Home Secretary(CP (72)116) and had been discussed at a meeting earlier that dayunder the chairmanship of the Chancellor of the Exchequer. In thelight of the results of that preliminary discussion, the cabinet considered the following main issues:  (a) Scope of the legislation. The draft Bill empowered theGovernment to apply a standstill in prices and incomes by prohibitingany increase above the level prevailing before 6 November. the standstill would end 90 days after the enactment of the Bill but couldbe extended by Order for a further period not exceeding 60 days.It would be enforced, where necessary, by Order or notice, anycontravention of which would be punishable by fine. An offencewould arise, however, only if an Order was disobeyed; and the government&apos;s power to make Orders would not be effective until theBill became law. To attempt to create offences as from the date of introduction of the Bill would involve retrospective legislation on a scale for which there was. no precedent. It followed that during thepassage of the Bill the Government would be relying essentially onthe voluntary co-operation of those responsible for price and wagefixing; and it was therefore important that the Bill should be not onlyequitable but also simple. It had accordingly been drafted incomprehensive terms; and the Order-making powers prescribed by itsschedule were very wide. Its practical implementation, however,should be by way of notice rather than Order so far as possible.(b) Date of effect. The &quot; freeze &quot; should apply to all increases in pay, provided that, where a settlement was reached before the standstill and its operative date was on or before 6 November, theincrease could be implemented.(c) Occupational pensions. It was agreed that these should be exempt from the &quot; freeze &quot;.(d) Wages Councils and Boards. Since the workers involved were among some of the lowest-paid in industry, there was some justification for the suggestion that proposals from Wages councils and Boards made on or before the introduction of the Bill should be implemented if the operative date of the previous Order was atleast 12 months before the standstill. It was agreed, however, thatthe Chancellor of the Exchequer should discuss further, in consult-ation with the Ministers concerned, whether,/ if the intervalwas less than 12 months, an increase should be deferred until theend of the standstill.(e) Arbitration Awards. It was agreed that these might be implemented during the &quot; freeze&quot; if the relevant hearings were completed on or before 6 November and their operative date was not later than that date. But, if negotiations or arbitrations took place during the &quot; freeze &quot;, any resultant increase should not take effect
before the end of the standstill period and should in any case besubject to the policy which was in operation after that period.(/) Breaches of Agreements. Clause 4 of the draft Billauthorised employers to disregard pay increases in existing contracts and exempted them from liability in respect of a breach of contractin this respect during the period of the &quot; freeze &quot;. This provision was particularly relevant to pay increases deriving from contractsmade before the &quot; freeze &quot; but providing for specified increases to take effect during it, including &quot; staged &quot; agreements. If such increases were permitted, those whose pay was governed by agreements ofthis kind would benefit unfairly by comparison with others whoseclaim for an increase in the normal course would be precluded bythe &quot; freeze &quot;. Their operative date should therefore be deferred until the standstill came to an end. In the absence of Clause 4,however, employers would be unprotected against actions for breach of contract in such cases; and if, as a result, the increases wereconceded and were such as to require subsequent reversal, it wouldbe necessary for the Government, as soon as the Bill became law, tomake Orders for this purpose. Even if these could take the form of comprehensive &quot; blanket&quot; Orders, prohibiting various types of increase, difficult problems of definition would arise and everyexception would require a Ministerial decision involving a separateOrder: whereas if Clause 4 were included in the Bill, the need forOrders should arise only in a relatively small number of cases. Onthe other hand, many of the Governments supporters would be strongly opposed in principle to a Clause encouraging employers tobreak agreements; and it would be preferable that the Governmentshould themselves assume the responsibility in this matter by being prepared to issue Orders or notices in cases where this proved necessary. Moreover, the Clause would be liable to be interpreted as implying that the Government wished to encourage the type ofemployer who would seize any opportunity to withhold a pay increase; and, if this impression took root, the concept of voluntary-operation on which the Bill was essentially based would been dangered and the psychological climate in which the Govern-menfs longer-term measures for regulating prices and incomes wouldbe introduced would be soured from the outset.The Cabinet concluded that on a balance of these considerationsClause 4 should be omitted from the Bill. Normal increments shouldcontinue to be paid during the period of the &quot; freeze &quot;, since theydiffered essentially from pay increases in the conventional sense and,if they were withheld, legislation would in some cases be required.For the rest the Government must rely on the voluntary co-operationof employers in seeking to ensure that the implementation of increases arising under &quot; staged &quot; agreements during the period ofthe &quot; freeze &quot; would be deferred until the end of that period.(g) Penalties. The Cabinet approved the relevant provisions in the Bill, subject to an increase in the penalty for non-disclosure ofinformation from  50 to  100. Since the offences created by the bill would be punishable only by fine and the existing law restricted thepowers of a Court to commit an offender to prison for non-payment
of a fine imposed for an offence which was not itself punishable withimprisonment, it would not be necessary to include in the Bill aprovision that a warrant should not be issued for imprisonmentunless the Court was satisfied that no other means of enforcing a finewas available. The law in Scotland and Northern Ireland in this context was perhaps more severe than in England and Wales; butdiscrepancies must be accepted for the relatively brief period of the&quot;freeze&quot;.(h) Rents. It was agreed that the Bill should empower theappropriate Minister to provide by Order for preventing increases of rent over rent payable before the standstill. This would not inhibitthe Ministers concerned from continuing to deal resolutely with thoselocal authorities who were still refusing to implement the rent increases which had been due on 1 October under the recent housing finance legislation. But it would be necessary to give further con-sideration to the position which might arise if the Bill had to beextended by an additional 60 days, since its provisions would thenextend beyond 1 April 1973 when the first of the rent increases in1973 would become due. It would also be desirable to give furtherconsideration to the application of the Bill to furnished tenancies inthe private sector in order to ensure that it did not result in wholesaleevictions of tenants.(/) Steel. It was proposed that the principles of the &quot; freeze &quot;should apply to the prices charged by the nationalised industriesexcept in so far as the steel industry might find it necessary to adjustits prices under its obligations to the European Coal and steel community. It was agreed, however, that this exception was undesir-able and that we should seek to agree with the Community that theincrease in the price of steel which was to become operative on1 January 1973, should be deferred for the period of the &quot; freeze &quot;subsequent to that date. The approach to the Community shouldbe undertaken as a matter of urgency in view of the importance of informing the steel industry of its position during the &quot; freeze &quot; as rapidly as possible.The Cabinet then considered the timing of the introduction ofthe Bill. The Governmenfs intentions would be announced in astatement by the Prime Minister in the House of Commons onMonday, 6 November; and it was desirable that there should be noprior indication that the Government proposed to introduce legislation on the lines which the Cabinet had been considering. It would therefore be necessary to depart from the normal practice wherebynotice of introduction would be given that afternoon, immediatelyafter the Cabinet&apos;s meeting, and to arrange for the publication of thedraft Bill in the form of a White Paper on 6 November, concurrently with the Prime Ministefs statement and the White Paper explaining the policy to be pursued during the &quot; freeze &quot;.&apos; Thereafter, the Billshould probably receive its Second Reading on Wednesday,8 November.During their discussion the Cabinet were informed of progressin dealing with several current wage claims which were clearly being pressed forward in the light of the current expectation that some
form of wages &quot; freeze &quot; would shortly be imposed. It was agreedthat, since the increases which were now being claimed were lessextravagant than had appeared likely at an earlier stage, it would be advisable to settle them without delay, provided that the Govern-inent were seen to be still trying to enforce moderation so far aspossible. Authority might therefore be given to try to reach agreement in the case of local authority manual workers on the basisof an increase of  2-25. This would be broadly in line with the expected arbitration award of  2-30 in the case of the industrial civil Service; but the possible repercussion on the claim by corn-parable grades in the National Health Service constituted powerfulargument for disposing of the local authority claim as economicallyas possible. The offer of an additional  12 increase in the LondonAllowance for teachers might be increased to  15.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theGovernment faced a troubled prospect ahead, not excluding furtherperiods of industrial unrest. Nevertheless they must pressresolutely forward on the basis which the Cabinet had approved.The Cabinet Approved the publication, on Monday, 6 November, of adraft Inflation (Temporary Provisions) Bill and anaccompanying White Paper in the form agreed in their discussions.Cabinet Office,5 November, 1972.


</content>
</cab>
