<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/8/10 images: 148-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY-S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1940.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (40)198th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 198 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Tuesday, July 9, 1940, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister(in the Chair).The Right Hon. Neville Chamberlain,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The following were also present:The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security (Items 1-6).The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air (Items 1-6).Air Chief Marshal Sir Cyril L. N.Newall, Chief of the Air Staff(Items 1-6).Admiral of the Fleet Sir dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff (Items 1-6).&apos;Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.[21523]
WAR CABINET 198 (40).Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Air Operations...       ...       ...             ...       ...       ...      692      Naval Operations     ..........      ......      ...      69The French fleet.3      Home Defence.........      .........      ...      69Measures against possible invasion.4      Northern Barrage     ...       ...       ...      ...       ...       ...       695      Gibraltar        .....................      69Evacuated civilians.6      Air Raid Warnings..................      707      Trance........................      70Members of French civil and military missions in London.
Air Operations. 1.   The Secretary of State for Air said that the Commander-(Previous in-Chief, Fighter Command, had informed him that, although the reference:        number of German aircraft brought down in recent encounters offW.M. (40) 197th the coast might not appear very large, yet the figures were reallyConclusions,      better than they claimed to be.   There had been a good deal of minute 1.)        fighting in cloud, which made the observation of results difficult. air marshal Dowding had no doubt that our fighters were still on top of the enemy.   It was believed that the Germans were now usingHurricane machines obtained from Belgium, France and othercountries.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.naval operations.The french fleet.(previous references:W.M. (40) 197thConclusions,Minutes 3and 4.)Home Defence.measures against possibleinvasion.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 191stConclusions,Minute 9.)NorthernBarrage.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 99thConclusions,Minute 6.)2. The War Cabinet were given the latest information inregard to the French Fleet, and in regard to naval dispositions and movements. This is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File ofWar Cabinet Conclusions.3. The War Cabinet were given particulars of the progressof various measures to strengthen our defences against invasion.This information is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard file of War Cabinet Conclusions.4. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty (W.P. (40) 253), in which it was explained that the project formerly discussed (which was for a submarine barrage) was no longer practicable, in view of theGerman occupation of Norway. It was now proposed to re-site theNorthern Barrage in a new area. Work would start about themiddle of July.It was proposed that the whole of the Northern Barrage area should be declared forthwith, in view of the deterrent effect whichthis declaration was likely to have.The War Cabinet Approved the First Lord&apos;s proposals as summarised inparagraphs 11 and 12 of his Memorandum.Gibraltar.Evacuatedcivilians.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 197thConclusions,Minute 11.)5. The Prime Minister said that a message had been receivedfrom the French authorities to the effect that they would not allow the British ships which were approaching Casablanca harbour,with French troops on board, to be victualled or to take in waterunless we agreed that the ships should take away the refugeeGibraltarians. After consulting with the Ministers concerned, hehad agreed that an undertaking should be given that these refugeeswould be removed from Morocco. The Colonial Secretary was taking all possible steps with a view to arranging for the refugeesto be received in various parts of the Empire, or in Portugueseterritory.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.
Air raid warnings.(previous references:W.M. (40) 191stConclusions,Minute 6,and 195thConclusions,Minute o.)6. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theMinister of Home Security (W.P. (G.) (40) 174), proposing a modifi-cation of the air raid warning system. The main modificationproposed was the abolition of the green message and the introduc-tion of a new purple message, to be known as a &quot; Lights Warning,&quot;on receipt of which all exempted external lighting would beextinguished.In discussion, the following points were made:  (1) The Minister of Home Security said that the Air OfficerCommanding-in-Chief, Fighter Command, was under-stood to be anxious as to how he should exercise the very wide discretion given to him to limit the red warning,so far as possible, to places where severe or sustainedattack was expected. The Minister of Home Security saidthat he would be glad of an opportunity of examiningwith the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief, fighter command, the best method of restricting the issue of thered warning, without undermining public confidence.(2) The Minister without Portfolio said that a plan had beenagreed between the British Employers&apos; Federation andthe Trade Union Congress with a view to maintainingjDroduction during air raids. This plan had now beenapproved.(3) The Prime Minister said that our system of air raid warnings must be modified from time to time in thelight of experience. He thought the scheme now-suggested should be authorised.The War Cabinet-(i) Approved the proposals made by the Minister of home security for the modification of the air raid warning system.(ii) Took note that the Minister of Home Security wouldre-examine, in conjunction with the Air OfficerCommanding-in-Chief, Fighter Command, the best method of restricting the issue of the red warningwithout undermining public confidence.France.Members ofFrench civil and militarymissions inLondon.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 197thConclusions,Minute 10.)7. The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theCharge d&apos;Affaires at the French Embassy had been informed of theaction which it was proposed to take in regard to segregatingvarious members of the French Naval, Military, Air and CivilMissions. The Charge d&apos;Affaires had stated that he wished to protest in the most formal way against what he regarded as anirregular and unnecessary act, which in his view was contrary toall diplomatic etiquette.The Foreign Secretary said that Sir Robert Vansittart had suggested that, in view of the War Cabinefs decision that weshould endeavour to continue diplomatic relations with France andshould consider the possibility of re-establishing bilateral represen-tation, it would be for consideration whether the measures ofsegregation proposed, which were due to take effect that afternoon,should not be suspended, pending consideration of the reply of theFrench Government to the communication which it was proposedto make in regard to Anglo-French relations.The view generally expressed was that the case for putting intoeffect measures of segregation (which was largely based on the factthat some of those concerned were attempting to undermine general de Gaulle&apos;s position) was not greatly affected by the discussion inregard to Anglo-French relations.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the right course was to proceed with themeasures of segregation already approved.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,July 9, 1940.



</content>
</cab>
