<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 6-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ument is the  Property of His  Britannic Majesty s Government.]CONFIDENTIAL.POLITICAL INTELLIGENCE  DEPARTMENT,           FOREIGN  OFFICE.Germany/026     (December 6, 1918.)u..l.*7&quot;   J^^TERANCESBY GERMAN SOCIALIST  LEADERS DURING THE WARTABLE OF PERSONS QUOTED.Otto BraunHeinrich CunowEduard DavidFritz EbertEmmel (Alsatian)Conrad HaenischWolfgang HeineGustav Hoch--KatzensteinOtto LandsbergPaul LensehHermann Miiller  ...Gustav NoskePhilipp ScheidemannFriedrich StampferHermann Wendel (Alsatian). 1.-MAJORITY  SOCIALISTS.Treasurer of the party; Minister for Agriculture in the new Prussian    Government.Editor of &quot;Die Neue Zeit&quot; since October 1917.Member of the Reichstag ; in the new Government, Under-Secretary    for Foreign Affairs.Member of the  Reichstag; Chairman of the Social Democrat party;    appointed  Imperial Chancellor on November  9, 1918 ; since    November  12, one of the six Peopled Commissaries  (&quot; Volks-    beauftragte &quot;); at the head of the German  Government.Member of the Reichstag for Mulhausen.Member of  the Prussian Diet;  editor of &quot;Die Glocke&quot;; one of the    two Ministers for Public Worship and Education in the new    Prussian Government.                                   \Member of the Reichstag; Minister of Justice in the new Prussian    Government.Member of the Reichstag.Deputy to the Social Democrat Party Congress  in October 1917.Member of the Reichstag; one of the six People&apos;s  Commissaries since    November 12.Member of the Reichstag; formerly editor of the &quot; Leipziger Volks-    Zeitung&quot;; &quot; regular collaborator &quot; in &quot; Die-Glocke.&quot;Secretary of the Social Democrat party.Member of the Reichstag; Commandant of Kiel since the revolution.Member  of  the  Reichstag;  Joint Chairman of  the  party since    October 1917 ;  one of the six  Peopled Commissaries since    November 12.Editor of &quot;Vohvarts.&quot;Member of the Reichstag.            II. MINORITY (INDEPENDENT SOCIAL DEMOCRAT PARTY).Eduard Bernstein  ...      ...  Member of the Reichstag; f ormerly cor respondent of the &quot;Nation &quot;;                                Assistant Secretary of State for the Treasury in the new German                                Government.Kurt Eisner      ...      ...  Writer on social questions: formerly editor of &quot; Vorwarts&quot;; Minister                                President of Bavaria since the revolution.Hugo Haase      ...      ...  Member of the Reichstag:  Chairman of the party till the beginning                                of 1916;  later, Chairman of the  Independent Social Democrat                                party; one of the six Peoples Commissaries since November 12,                                1918.Karl Kautsky    ...      ...  Editor of &quot;Die Neue Ziet&quot; till  October 1917; Assistant Secretary                                for Foreign Affairs in the new German Government.Georg Ledebour   ...      ...  Member of the Reichstag.Heinrich Strobel  ...      ...  Member of the Prussian Diet; formerly editor of &quot;Vorwarts&quot;;  one                                of the two Minister-Presidents of Prussia since the revolution.Oswald Vogtherr  ...      ...  members of the Reichstag; Assistant  Secretary for the State Labour                                Department in the new German Government.                          .   III.-&apos; SPARTACUS &quot;  GROUP.Xarl Liebknecht  ...      ...  Member of the Reichstag till his imprisonment in June 1916.[367-54]B
     THE  following  is a  selection  of  utterances by  the  principal GermanSocialist leaders since the 4th August,  in which  their attitude to the war isexhibited.   They make clear that the crucial question by which the GermanMajority Socialists  must be acquitted or condemned is whether the status quoof July  1914 was of such a kind that Germany  was justified in fighting tomaintain or restore it.  When the German Socialists  say, as they do over andover again, that Germany&apos;s enemies  aim at  &quot; conquests &quot; from Germany and her Allies, this is perfectly true, if by &quot;conquests&quot; is meant  the detachmentfrom Germany, Austria-Hungary  or  Turkey of territory of which they stoodpossessed in July 1914.  The German Social Democrat Majority seem to havestood quite consistently for a peace &quot; without annexation,&quot; understanding  by&quot;annexations&quot;  any change of the territorial status  quo of July  1914, to theadvantage of either side.  They condemned the desire of the Pan-Germans to annex Belgium as  much as  the desire of the  French to re-annex Alsace-Lorraine, or the purpose of the English to take away the African Colonies fromGermany, or Mesopotamia from the Turks.  They admitted that the status quoof 1914 could not be restored in every particular, but any change  of boundary-stones must be made (they said) by mutual agreement as a quid pro quo, so thatthe equivalent at any rate of the status quo would be restored.   If they  werejustified in regarding a fight to maintain the territorial integrity  of Germany,Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria and Turkey, as they  were in  1914,  as a fight in self-defence,  then  all the rest of their policy logically follows.   They  wereprepared to go  on voting war-credits  so long as the enemy Powers manifesteda purpose to  take  away from Germany or her Allies any part  of what  hadbelonged to them in 1914;  they  declared-and we have no reason to doubtthat they meant it that if ever  the enemies of Germany expressed a willing-ness to accept the status quo of 1914, and the German Government still wishedto go on fighting for &quot; annexations,&quot; they would oppose the Government, refuseto vote any  more war-credits, and even try to create a  revolution.   Theydisapproved of  the peace of Brest-Litovsk and the peace of Bucharest, whichmanifestly involved &quot;annexations,&quot;  but argued that they could not even  thenrefuse to vote  war-credits, so long as the enemies purposed to annex german territory   It was,  they said, now a  choice of evils either  by  voting  war-credits they must  acquiesce in German annexations,  or, by refusing to  votewar-credits, permit annexations to be made at Germany&apos;s expense, and of thetwo evils the second appeared to  them the greater.     If, contrary to the view of the German Socialists, the status  quo of  July1914  was really evil, if the  detachment  of Alsace-Lorraine from Germany, of countries inhabited by Czechs, Southern Slavs, Italians, and Rumanians  from austria and  Hungary, of Armenians and Arabs from Turkey and her Allieswas a measure  of justice, without which there could be no secure peace, then the Allies were justified in  making  it part  of their war aims to  effect  this change of the  status quo of 1914 to Germany&apos;s  disadvantage, and germany was fighting to perpetuate an unjust state of things.     It  is upon the character ol  the status quo of July 1914 that the moralestimate of the behaviour of the German Social Democrat Majority during thewar must turn.     What has just been said does not indeed apply to the Right  wing of theparty the groups of &quot;Imperialist Socialists&quot; some of whom frankly desiredannexations on the part of Germany.  These groups, however, although  theyincluded a  number of the ablest writers of the party, were a minority, and cannot  be  taken  as  representative of its official  attitude.   Since   this&quot; Imperialist Socialism &quot; has  now, with  Germany&apos;s prostration, obviously lostall outlook,  it  has  not  seemed worth while to give many quotations from itsexponents in the selection which  follows.  Only one quotation, for instance, isgiven  from  Paul Lensch:   Some are given from Conrad Haenisch, the editor-of &quot; Die Glocke,,&quot; in which  Lensch  writes, and  the statement  by Haenischunder No  21  is practically a  summing up  of the  gospel  common to  the&apos;&quot; Glocke&quot;  group,  of which  Lensch  is  (or was)  the most vigorous preacher.Winnig, the prominent trade unionist  leader  (Builders&apos;  Union),  is also amember of this group, and Wolfgang, Heine, and  Noske are more towards the eight than Ebert and Scheidemann.
                      I.-MAJORITY SOCIALISTS.     1.  For our people and  its peaceful future much, if not everything;,  would declaration of the party     i,i    I   i i  A   -    i  1  .      i .  ,  i    ,     i  .      &apos; .,,  r  i ,   i Oroup in the Reichstag.be at stake should  Russian  despotism, which  has stained  itself with the bloodof the best among its own people, triumph.   It is a question of warding  offthis danger, placing the civilisation (&quot; Kultur &quot;) and independence of our ownland in  security.   Hereby we make good what we  have always affirmed wedo mot leave our own fatherland in the  lurch in the  hour of danger.                                                       (August 4, 1914.)     2.  The Social Democrat  Group still  holds  the  same ground as  in  its Declaration by the Sooialdeclaration of the  4th August.   We opposed, up  to the last moment, the war JjjJJJJar0UP inwhich has been brought about by a clash  of economic interests.   The frontiers of our  country are still menaced  by  hostile forces.   For  this  reason  theGerman people is still to-day bound to put forth its  whole strength for  thedefence  of  the country.   Therefore Social  Democracy  grants  the  &quot;creditsasked for ... .     We  stand fast  by what we said  on the 4th August: We demand that so soon as  ever the  aim of the war, security,  has  been  attained  and  our opponents are disposed for peace, the war shall be concluded by a peace which makes friendship with neighbouring nations possible.     (December 1.914.)     3.  In peace-time it is our task to work for peace.   But  if, in spite of our Wolfgau  Heine-efforts, war comes, then the people, with  its frontiers, its possessions, its security and  its freedom menaced, could not tolerate  our embarking on elaborate con-sideratlons and arguing backwards and forwards as to who bore the miilt forthe war.                   (&quot; Siiddeutsche Monatshefte&quot; for March 1915.)     4.  In this  hour  of  increased  danger^ we express  our  unhesitating ^&apos;eitK^staMeinbe1&apos; **adherence to that which we  affirmed on  the 4th of August and  on lateroccasions  in  this place.   We  stand  by  our  people!   With one heart  theGerman people will concentrate its whole  strength to master this new clangerand  protect our country.....We Social  Democrats  never  allowed any doubt to exist as to our intention to spare no  effort  or sacrifice,  in union withour people, in order that we might hold our own, economically and politically.That is  true in an especial sense to-day, when, by the last great  Power joining the coalition of our enemies, this war has become a  gigantic struggle for thefree  existence and  independence of the  German people.                                              (Reichstag, May 28,  1915.)     5.  The people want no annexations ;  the people want peace.              Manifesto of the Party                                            (&quot; Vorwarts,&quot; June 22,  1915.)    DlMclorftte- .     6.  (1.)  No cession of German territory ;  this  applies to  the re-unitino&apos; of Resolution 6f Party Com-. v   TV  &apos;  .    i  in         l        /.      l  i                              mittee and ReichstagAlsace-Lorraine to -trance under any form whatsoever.                        Group sitting together.     (2.) Security for the economic development of Germany, implying :      (a.) The open door in all colonial dependencies. &apos;     (o.) The  inclusion of the most-favoured-nation clause  in  the treaty of           peace concluded between all the belligerent Powers.     (c.) Free trade, so far as possible.     id.) Levelling up of social-political arrangements in all countries in the           sense desired by the international labour movements.     (e.) Freedom  of the seas, viz., abolition  of the right  of  capture  at sea           and the internationalisation  of all straits important  for world-           commerce.     (3.) Integrity of  Austria-Hungary and of the Turkish Empire.   -  (4.) No annexations on the part of Germany.     (5.) A perpetual International Court of Arbitration.                                        (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; August 24, 1915.) -     7. These three considerations, (l) import of food-stuffs, (2) supply of raw August Winnig.materials, (3) facilities for export  of products of industry, prescribe  impera-i   &apos;  &apos;  &apos;         &quot;-.&apos;,&quot;,&apos;/--&apos;             * The danger had been increased by Italy&apos;s entering the war.
tively the line which  German policy must take.   To unite the economic life of the Central Powers as closely  as possible with the Balkans and Asia Minor,rich as those countries are in agricultural products and receptive as they are for the products of industry, to  knit together  in  one indissoluble whole theeconomic interests of Germany,  Austria-Hungary, the Balkan  countries and turkey this, in the nistorical  situation  as it is to-day must be the aimtowards which the world-policy (&quot; Weltpolitik &quot;) of the German working-class iedirected.  (&quot; Die Glocke &quot; for 1915,  p. 478 ; Berger, &quot; Fraktionsspaltung undParteikrisis,&quot; p.  98.)August Winnig.     8. The commonplace facts that the economic life of Germany means thepurchase of 5,000,000,000 marks&apos; worth of raw materials and  3,000,000,000marks&apos; worth of  foodstuffs and  commodities from abroad annuallv. andthat Germany  is  thereby compelled to turn out manufactured  articles forsale  abroad, if  Germany  is not to  starve or  send masses  of  its  working-men overseas as /culture  manure&apos;  for others these facts,  commonplaceenough  hut  true  and  vital,  have  gradually  penetrated  the minds  of theworking-class and, together with  the tremendous change of attitude towardsthe State and the nation as a whole, have prepared the  way for a wholly newconception  of our economic needs and our relations to the world market.   Letno one suppose  that  the working-class does not recognise the economic back-ground  to  this war !   Perhaps it was not understood at first, but as soon as england&apos;s designs  became plain, our working-class quickly grasped the signifi-cance of  the war for the economic interests of the German  people.  To-day it stands, open-eyed and resolute, on the side of the country because its political life and  its economic  interests constrain it to  take up this station.  That is what these facts really mean.                    (Braun&apos;s &quot; Annalen&quot; for 1915, p. 146  ; Berger,  p. 97.)Frits Ebert.     9. No attempts  to  conclude  peace  have yet led to the desired result,The leading men in the States opposed to us still hold fast to their  attitudeof refusing  every suggestion of peace till the  German Empire is  broken up and  their  plans of  conquest  ha ve  been  realised  against  Germany andGermany&apos;s allies.   [N.B.  Any detachment of what was Austrian  or  Turkishterritory in 1914 is  included in &quot; plans of conquest.&quot;]  In view of  these factsit is the absolute duty of the  whole German people to maintain its defensivefirm and united, and to keep all  means required for defence in  readiness. TheSocial  Democrat&apos; Parliamentary Group  still protests against any plans ofconquest on the German side.  The  Chancellor on the 9th December madeGermany&apos;s readiness for peace plain.       (Reichstag, December 21, 1915.)Declaration by the PartyDirectorate.     10. The vote  of  credits  by  the Parliamentary  Group on  the  21stDecember,  1915, was justified.   It was the consistent following out of thepolicy  initiated  on  the 4th 1 August,  1914.    The  circumstances whichdetermined that policy are the  same to-day.  Our enemies  do not yet showany disposition  for peace, but persist in their purpose to bring Germany  and her allies to the ground, both in a military and economic sense.                           (&quot; Vorwarts,&quot; January 9, 1916 ; Berger, p. 13.)Directorate,Directorate.     11. The Governments of the Eritente, which  have hitherto rebuffed everyoffer of peace negotiations, set their hope^I upon a protraction of the war.  Theycalculate, not  only upon our economic difficulties, but upon the outbreak ofinternal discord in the German people.  The Socialist group in France, no lessthan the Labour party in England, share this view,  and have backed up thepolicy of their Governments in  every possible way.....They demand the continuation of the war till Germany  is brought to the ground.                                                      (March 27, 1916.)     12. &quot;A  Social  Democrat  party  which  recognises  the  necessity of defending its country ought not to  act in any other way than  the  SocialDemocrat Group in the  Reichstag has acted during the war.&quot;                                         (&quot; Vorwarts,&quot; March 31, 1916.)
     13. Foreign  countries no  longer  believe that a  military overthrow of phU,PP Soheidemran.  ermany is possible.  All. hope is therefore set  upon  economic need, hunger, ivisions in the people, discord  in the parties.  Every  sign of disunion  raises he hopes of our enemies, prolongs the  war, and costs the health and the lives IF thousands of our comrades.   We want peace !   But we do not want to bej* it IN our knees.   We want it by the way of understanding [i.e., on  the  status \uo basis].   If our enemies  refuse, if they want to go on with the  war, we aust go on standing by our  country.                              (&quot;Torwarts,&quot; April 5, 1916.  Berger, p. 53.)     14. One must be a child in politics to imagine that a whole continent can Phiiipp Soh*idemann. )e wrapped in flames, millions and millions of people killed, and at  the end oi t  all no single frontier pillar shifted, no frontier pillar set up by some old liplomat long ago dust.                        (Reichstag, April 6, 1916.)    15. We have witnessed the German Kaiser&apos;s love of peace, worth a good Wolfgang Heine. leal more than the  pacifism  of the Tsar and of English  humanitarians, because it really did  on two occasions avert the world conflagration.  We have seen the almost excessive love which has  animated the  German towards otherpeoples and their forms of culture especially towards England, France, andItaly. ....   Quite apart, however, from the question what the intentions of lermanys  enemies may be, the effect of a defeat of our fatherland would be anything but a weakening of militarist tendencies.   It would have the veryopposite effect.   What would remain to a mangled Germany and Austria butIhe thought how they could gather new force for a new attack (sic).                             .   (&quot;Frankfurter Zeitung,&quot; April 20, 1916.)    16. Even if the present Government bore the sole guilt for the war, even Wolfgang Hebe. f-as our enemies assert it had let slip the  dogs of war with the purpose of ubjugating Europe, even so we could not have acted in a&apos;manner different from that in which we have  acted.                               (&quot; Bremer Biirger-Zeitung,&quot; May 1, 1916.)ana.     17.  The Social Democrat party has done its best to bring the war to an  Pbiiipp Scheidem snd by co-operation with  the Socialist parties  abroad.....  The French iSocialists assert for themselves the duty of voting credits  &quot;according  to  our principles, as a means of victory,&quot;  and they ask their&apos; German comrades to letray their country.  German  Social Democracy will continue to do its duty IN working for peace.  It will not allow itself to be  put off by the unfraternal onduct of Socialists in other countries.  But it appears  to me no less a matter f course  that it will stand by its country and vote  the means for carrying on he defensive war so long as the enemies are not disposed to peace.         (&quot; Internationale Korrespondenz,&quot;  May 12, 1916.   Berger, p.  52.)     18.  Germany will not, cannot,  collapse.   Germany  must not collapse,  philiPP Scheidemaun. lince a collapse would mean that we  should exchange the present  temporary distress for lasting misery.,  Under the ruins  of Germany, the working class would lie deepest  buried.   Two things we   must demand bread, and no shaking of our conviction that we.are waging a war of defence.                                      (Speech at Dresden, Summer, 1916.)     19.  The situation in  August 1914 was, in point of  danger to  Germany,  PMiPPScheid.roa.uu  mere bagatelle compared with the situation to-day ....     We fight against all annexations though that does not mean  that not a      &apos;        , pngle  boundary-stone would  be shifted but that in all  changes of frontier [the wishes of all concerned must be consulted.                                  (Reichskonferenz, September 21, 1916.)     20.  The French  do not know .... that they could have the freeing of  PWiipp Scheidemanu$heir country, and of Belgium too, from German troops without having to shedtnother drop of blood and without  losing an inch  of ground.  We say that rhat is  French shall  remain French ; what is Belgian shall remain Belgian; .nd what is German, German.              (Reichstag, October 11, 1916.)       [367-54]                                                 C
(Conrad Haenisoh.     21.  Just as the war has revolutionised our economic system at home, just as it has been an immense force for concentrating capital and thus preparing the  way for Socialism, so it has revolutionised the  economic system of theworld.   The most  important fact in  this  connection  is the transfer of theeconomic centre of gravity across the Atlantic, the  substitution of New Yorfor London  as  the &quot;world&apos;s banker&quot;-in  one  word,  the  dethronement oEngland, whom Karl Marx nearly seventy years ago termed &quot;the despot ofthe  world market.&quot;   However  the war may end, Great Britain&apos;s positionin the world lias  suffered a blow from which the island kingdom will neverrecover.....     More than sixty-seven years ago Karl Marx prophesied : &quot; England, as inthe  days of Napoleon, -will stand  at the head of the counter-revolutionaryarmies, but will be thrown by the war  itself to the head of.the revolutionarjmovement, and so  pay the debt incurred by its opposition to the revolution ofthe 18th century.&quot;     What we  see to-day is the fulfilment of Marx&apos;s prophecy.....Thegrand dialectic of history  has brought it about that Germany, decried all theworld  over as  reactionary, in this war champions the cause of  historicaprogress, whereas  England, universally praised as the  freest State in thwrorld, champions,  just  as she did in the days of Napoleon, the cause of retro-progression.   It is England who in this war represents the reactionary principle,and  Germany who  represents the revolutionary principle.  Over  against thebackward forms of capitalism which prevail in England, stands in Germany,and  on  the  side of Germany,  the more highly  developed form of modernorganised, capitalism.   Over against England, whose  labouring masses  havebeen hardly stirred  by  the faintest  breath of the Socialist idea, standsGermany with  the most  powerful Social Democrat  Labour Movement in theworld.  The victory of the  English Coalition would  thus be the victoryolantiquated forms  of capitalism  over capitalism of the most up-to-date type,and at the same time the victory&apos;of proletarian backwardness over proletarianSocialism.   The hour of England&apos;s defeat in this war will be the birth-hour olan up-to-date labour movement  in England, and thus make the way clear faEngland  to arrive at higher forms of economic life.....     The future interests  of international Socialism imperatively require the victory of Germany. ....     To endanger  the future of  German capitalism  is to endanger the futureof the German labour  movement, and  to endanger the future of the Germanlabour movement is to endanger the future of international Socialism.           (&quot;Die deutsche Sozialdemokratie  in und nach dem Weltkriege&quot;           .   .                  (1916) pp. 129-131.)Philipp Seheidemnnn.     22. When the  enemy in their  notorious  answer to Wilson reckless!exposed their policy of conquest [i.e., a policy which arrived at altering &apos;&apos;status quo of July i914 by liberating subject nationalities] they arousedmore in our country the firm ,will to defend ourselves.....In view of texpression of their will, what could  we (Socialists) do ?                                         (Reichstag, February 27, 1917.Eduard David.Philipp Scheidemann.     23. David denied Haase&apos;s statement  that Germany could  have peaceshe  renounced annexations.  The French  Socialists  refused  to  renounAlsace-Lorraine:                             (Reichstag, March 29, 1917.]     24. The  Socialists retain the point  of view  they  expressed  in 1^namely, the territorial integrity of Germany and guarantees for German]development  and  independence.    They  do  not want to  enslave  foreipeoples .... A  speedy  peace   by  mutual agreement would  be a grshappiness for  all Europe .... If France and  Britain renounce  annexatw]and Germany insists on them, we  shall see a revolution in the land.  (Tuffli1in the House.)  We have not reached that stage.   France and  England h]not renounced annexations.  Let  us  stop  making demands  on oneanc&apos;&apos;let reason prevail  in  favour  of a peace that does justice to all sides. Iconvinced  that no peace can be arranged without altering the  frontier po*but that must be done by  mutual  consent.       (Reichstag, May  15, 1917&apos;
79      25.  We must abandon all Pan-German talk of annexations.....Now, EduM-d D*yid. as in 1915, we put the national interest at the head of our programme.   We do  not want to subject our people  to a process  of decay.   We demand the most-favoured-nation clause in  all  peace  treaties, freedom  of  the  seas, internationalisation  of   sea  routes,  &amp;c.....Our  economic  freedom  of development must be guaranteed to us.   [This  phrase probably refers  to colonies.]  Only peace by agreement will give us freedom in our economic life. The method  advocated  by the  Right \ic, the Pan-Germans] would leave us blockaded by the hatred of the world.          (Reichstag, May  15, 1917.)      26.  The Entente [before the war] was really nothing else but an economic BdttardD*Tld- World Partition Syndicate on a huge scale.  Its three great partition schemes were  responsible for the growing military tension in Europe.  The  first concerned North Africa.  .... The secret  treaty between England and France -with  regard to Morocco was   the  flagrant  breach  of  an  international treaty.....Germany&apos;s protest  was well justified.....The  second scheme had to do with  the remainder of Turkey VEuropean territories  and the whole of its Asiatic territories.   ....  Russia was to get Constantinople, the southern sea-board of the  Bl ick Sea,  and North Persia;  England,  South  Persia, Mesopotamia, and Egypt, with the  country between them; France,  Syria; Italy (which already had seized  Tripoli),  counted on getting  islands  in the iEgean.  The third  scheme had  to do with  the  Danubian  Monarchy; Italy was to get South Tyrol and Trieste; Serbia was to get Bosnia and Herzegovina; Rumania the Bukovina ;  and Russia, Galicia.     (The answer of the  Entente  Powers to Wilson  at the  beginning of this year (1917) proved that they really had in mind these great projects.  The war  aims which they then specified  coincided with the plans&apos;just described, .and contained also France&apos;s older aim the reconquest of Alsace-Lorraine.)     On the other hand  the policy of the Central  Powers  was essentially a&apos; defensive one.....     Austria, like Turkey, was fighting for its existence.....Some blame, no doubt, rested upon the rulers  in Vienna and Budapest for the strained relations with Serbia, in consequence of Austria&apos;s  economic policy.   Hence, Serbia became a vassal of Russia, and the Great  Serb movement threatened the integrity of Austria.  It is thus true  that Austria&apos;s policy was, on the whole, defensive.  Gennany was interested in the maintenance  of Austria, as  - a  flank protection against the Russian peril.     Where was  the &quot;menace to the  world&quot;  of which  Germany is held guilty ? . .  .  .  There is not a single fact to show that  Germany abused her military power to threaten her neighbours.  . .  .     Germany had  for years been isolated  by the Entente, under England&apos;s leadership,  and  threatened with a  coalition war.     Even therefore if it were possible to show a diplomatic fault  ori Germany&apos;s side in the critical  days  before the outbreak  of war  (which, according  to my conviction,  is not the case) the German people would have no other choice but to defend its  present and future existence  against a coalition which for years had aimed at holding Germany down. ....     The Russian general mobilisation in the night between 30th and 31st July was the formal act which clinched the military measures that had been taken against Germany during the preceding days,  Thereby war was  begun.....     It is clear that a portion of the guilt for the  war rests upon the Govern- ments in Paris and  London.....England&apos;s share  in  the  responsibility for the victory  of the war party in St.  Petersburgh is  proved by  the report  of the Belgian Minister, M. de L&apos;Escaille.....     Just as I fail to see the guilt for the  war on the German  side, but am compelled, on the basis of the documentary material  accessible to me, to put it upon the  statesmen of the enemy Powers ... . so I must &quot;charge the same men with the no less heavy guilt for the  prolongation of the war.   The peace offer made by the Central Powers  on the 12th December, 1916,  was seriously meant, and  we German Social Democrats take to ourselves a  part of the credit for it. ...  .     So long as  the other side persists in its plans of conquest,  so long as it refuses to conclude a peace which assures political  independence, territorial integrity, and freedom for economic development,  to our country and  to our
Philipp Soheidemann.Eduard Darid.Hoeh (Section of Majoritynearest to the Minority).Otto Landsberg.Eduard David.Philipp Scheidemawa,allies, so long we shall stand with closed ranks and  unshakable fidelity&apos;by our country.  . .  .  . We hold fast by our people, so long as the  other  side ianot ready for a  peace  such as,we could accept, a  peace  which respects andsafeguards our own vital interests just  as it recognises the right ol  all otherpeoples to live.          (Speech before the Dutch-Scandinavian Committee at Stockholm,                                 June 6, 1917.)     27. We will concede  the  new credits in the spirit of our accompanyingresolution not  as a vote of confidence in the Imperial Chancellor.   We have always conceded the  credits&apos; to the  country alone ; we concede them to  theGerman people, of whom  we know that nine-tenths take their stand on theground of our peace programme.              (Reichstag, July 19, 1917.)     28. The voting of the  credits on the 4th August, 1914, was an &quot;historicalact.&quot;  That act was in  complete consonance with the attitude taken up by theInternational before the war with regard to national defence.  If the GermanSocialists had voted differently they would have had the whole German peopleagainst them.   It was not a vote of confidence in the German Government,but a vote of confidence in the  nation.  The Government might have been theiworst in the  world, but when  the house is on fire it is no good criticising the defects of the fire appliances.   It is not true that Germany was the aggressor,and  the Entente Socialists  are quite wrong in  demanding  a  &quot;peace  OFrepentance.&quot;  . .  . . At no time during the war has  Germany gone beyond thepure necessities  of self-defence.       (Wurzburg Congress, October, 1917.)     29. The war was prepared for systematically by the ruling classes of allcountries, and was designed by them as  a  war of conquest.   If it has not proved  a war of conquest, that is  not the fault of the ruling classes.  TheSocialists, who are opposed to the oppression of any people, are, of course, infavour of national defence,  but they must test the war at every stage to mak!esure what its underlying motives really are.   So long as German  Socialistshad reason to fear that their nation was in danger, they were bound to helpin averting it. But that stage has long past. The war has proved conclusivelythat there is  no danger of any nation being crushed and suppressed.  Henceit is  not true that the war  is now being carried on for defensive purposes   ITis continued  in  the interest  of the capitalist classes,  who  are still hopingagainst hope that  something  may  happen  to enable  them  to crush their opponents.                          (Wurzburg Congress, October, 1917.)     30.  Socialists ought not to vote war-credits in any and all circumstances.Supposing  the  German nation  had been  driven into the war, as Italy andRumania have been [by their rulers], then German Socialists would have flatlyrefused  to vote the war-credits.  As it is, the war for Germany is one of pure.defence.                            (Wurzburg Congress, October, 1917.)     31. Since when has Germany ceased to be in danger ?  When  have  herenemies  been  ready to make  peace ? [ie.,  a peace  which.left the german empire the full extent, continental and colonial, which it had in July, 1914.]                                   (Wurzburg Congress. October, 1917.)     32.  The Chancellor [Hertling] has done well, to emphasise so clearly theright of nations to determine their own destiny.  We don&apos;t want to curtailany  people&apos;s freedom.  We  want  nothing but our own  preservation and a lasting peace.  Germany has been forced to fight for her own existence.   Thisis proved by the secret treaties.  The nations can now  see who it  was whodrove them to death.   We have no choice but to fight in order to  secure that what is German may remain  German  [i.e.&apos;, that  territory attached  TO  THEGerman Empire in July  1914 be  not taken away from Germany].  THEsituation is clear for all the world.   France and England  want  TO  determineGermany&apos;s frontiers on the West, and the Tsar wanted to determine Germany&apos;sfrontiers on the  East.  Every one wanted to cut out of Germany&apos;s skin what he liked.   We ARE ready to remove all obstacles TO peace and  .... WE look forward WITH LONGING  TO  THE DAY  WHEN  THE WORKING MEN OF  ENGLAND AND
France will fight for peace [i.e., a peace which  preserves the integrity of theGerman  Empire as  it was in  1914],  together  with  the working  men ofGermany and Russia.                     (Reichstag, November 29, 1917.)     33.  A strong and free Empire, in which our children are to dwell safely, People^ Umon. consisting         . ,.    &amp;.        .    J         ,     .      f. ,   r.                J  of the Committee ofhas been indicated  to  us  in  many proclamations  of the Government  as  our German (Christian Social)German future ....   In detail we need :-                                SniSf^fiST^                                                                           Trade Unions, General!                                                                           Association of Christian                                                                           Trade Uriions, Association(1)  In view of our enemies&apos; still unbroken will for our destruction, an       absolute union of all our forces until that will is broken.           for the interests of German                                                                      Officials, Association of                                                                      German Workers&apos; Unions     (2) Immediate political reform.....     (3) A clear foreign policy, carried on by people  and Government, which (Hirsch huncker), Associa-            aims at a lasting peace, secures our requirements in the matter of WorkL^anTLibourlrs7            imports and facilities for export, and  bases  the  honour  and free Association of German            development of nations on the principles of morality and law.       Q^^^?SS^                                        (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; December 19, 1917.)        -     34. Speaking at Cologne,  Haenisch declared that Germany needed new Conrad Haenisch. territories for colonisation in the  East (Russia), though in view of  the advan- tages  to be derived from a separate peace with Russia, Haenisch was prepared to forego  annexations at. her expense.  He  concluded his  speech:  &quot;Prussia first in Germany, and Germany first in  the world ! &quot;     In another speech at Dortmund, he declared that it was  Germany&apos;s duty to support the Flemish cause in Belgium, and &quot;bring the Flemish  part under          .....il intense German influence.&quot;                               (January 1918.)     35. (With regard to a proposed International Socialist Conference).       Heinrich Cunow.     We must demand that no  discussion of the so-called &quot; question of guilt &quot; [question who is responsible for the war] should take place at all.                                     (&quot; Die Neue Zeit,&quot; January  7, 1918.)     36. Ebert and I are already described  as traitors,  who must be shot on Phiiipp Soheidemanr; the sand-heap [by the Conservative &quot; Kreuz-zeitung &quot;] ....  The calculations of the victors by the sword are based, firstly, on the U-boat warfare ;  secondly,. on  the  offensive power  of the  enemy.  As regards  the  U-boat warfare, according  to a memorandum of the year 1916, it  was to have  an absolutely smashing  success  in  six months.  That  time-limit has  been  long  over- past ....   The most visible result of  the U-boat warfare  is  the  entrance of America into the war ....   I come now to the second factor the offensive power of the army ....  Suppose  we took Calais  and Paris ....  would that mean peace?   I say, No.  ....   Both sides ought to have  seen clearly long ago that this war cannot be  ended by  a great military decision  .... I cannot see the day in the furthest distance on which we should  say :  &quot; We are vanquished, we accept your conditions.&quot;    But just as little do I see the day when  the  French,   the English,  and  the  Americans  say:  &quot; We  are defenceless against Germany, we  will accept her peace conditions.  .  . .  .&quot;                                           (Reichstag,  Januaiy 24, 1918.)     37. No one should  be blind and  deaf to the indications of a growing Phiiipp Scheidemam. desire for peace in  Wilson&apos;s  and  Lloyd  George&apos;s  speeches.  .... In my opinion, a plain understanding could  be very quickly  reached on eleven of Wilson&apos;s fourteen points.  .... If something  definite is said about Belgium, there will  be an end of the Jingo agitation in England  \ i.e., England will  be      .       .  - :y ready to accept the status quo of  July 1914].                                            (Reichstag, January 24; 1918.)     38. As regards victory and  faith in victory, the question is  not whether Phiiipp Scheidemann. we believe in our ability to win battles-anyone who is  to fight  at all must have faith of that kind but whether one group of &quot;Powers  can so  crush the other that it can dictate peace.   I said before, &quot; he is a fool who thinks so,&quot; and I  say it again.   Arms alone cannot decide the war.   Of course  those will       ,  .   ,; come off best in  the negotiations who have done best in arms                                               (Reichstag, June 26, 1918.)  &apos; -   [367-54]                                                  D
Philipp Soheideuiann.     39. We have been launched into this war- I can  find no other expressionfor it- without  aim.   Surrounded  by enemies, encompassed by the furioushate of the  whole world, Germany could pursue  no other policy than this out of  the corpses of her sons to erect firm barriers on which  the  storm of hostile rage broke till it  ebbed back  again.  Her war aims  policy had to bedirected not on grounds of principle, but solely from  practical  considerations mainly  to the maintenance of the  status quo ante.  ....  Germany was bound  to wage a national war of defence, which she was ready to conclude themoment her possessions were no longer attacked by the enemy.  To get this idea adopted by  German official policy, German  Social Democracy has strivenfor nearly four years.   And there has been no Government in Germany duringthe war which has not almost completely subscribed to this opinion of ours.                                               (Reichstag, July 3,  1918.)Philipp Scheidemaon,     40. We have  always exerted ourselves to bring about peace finally inthe peace resolution of the 19th July, 1917.  No other Government has goneso tar as the German, which has said that it is prepared to make peace.....We must do our best to get out of the war as soon as possible.  But we mustnot allow  our  country to be overthrown  in  this war, for it is precisely  theGerman working-man who would suffer most  by  that.                                       (Speech at Essen,  July 22, 1918.)Vritz Ebert.Philipp Scheidemann.Conrad Haeniich.Otto Landsberg,     41.  We declared to Troelstra that we would  be prepared to  agree thatthe  memorandum  of the  Dutch-Scandinavian  Committee  (the  &quot; NeutralMemorandum&quot;)  should be  made  the  basis  of  the  discussions  at  theInternationa] Conference..  En this connection, however, we  were  obliged tomake two  reservations : (1) We declared ourselves, as we have always done before, in favour of the restoration, of an independent Belgium, but emphasised that with  regard  to the demands over and above that \%.e. demands thatGermany should indemnify Belgium for the damage done there], there was as yet no agreement between the Neutral Memorandum  and our own attitude;(2) we  further declared that  on the  question  of Alsace-Lorraine  we are obliged  to adhere to  our own Stockholm declarations.     [It  was just on   these  two questions  that  the Neutral Memorandumdiffered  from the German Majority Socialist Memorandum.  In accepting theNeutral Memorandum with the exception of these two questions, the GermanSocialists were  therefore making an apparent concession which was none at all.]                                      (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; September 6, 1918.)     42.  We Socialists will go to the conference table with confidence, because we have not lost our  belief in humanity.....The world has no  interest inpunishing  Germany  with unemployment.....President  Wilson&apos;s  pro-gramme culminates in  the  acknowledgment  of the freedom  and equality of rights  of all peoples, and  that .... is also the  programme of  GermanSocialism.....I need nut  tell you that the  coming peace  will makedemands upon us which  we  shall feel as sacrifices.   We are penetrated by thebitter feeling which this idea arouses;  but we  must be brave  enough to draw the necessary conclusions from the actual situation, for which neither we northe German people are guilty.           &apos;.  (&quot; Vorwarts,&quot; October 15, 1918.)     43.  German Social Democracy will come out of this world-war somethingquite different from   what   it  was  when  it went in.  (&quot;Die deutscbeSozialdemokratie  wird  aus diesem Weltkriege ganz anders herausgehen,:sie in ihn  hinein ging.&quot;)                    (Haenisch,  &quot;Die deutsche Sozialdemokratie,&quot; p.  149.i     The following have special reference to Alsace-Lorraine :      44.  He who lifts the knife to cut pieces  out of the body of the German.people  will  find,  wherever he  goes  to work, that he has to meet a peopleunited in defence,  who will strike the knife out of his hand.                            (Reichstag, December 21, 191,5, Berger, p. 9.)
     45. As for A.lsace-Lorraine, the Jena Conference demanded full republican  Frite Ebert-. autonomy for the country within the framework of the German Empire .... We hold  unshakably fast  to this  standpoint to-day, and therein we have behind us the German working class to the last man.                                     (Wurzburg Congress, October 1917.)     46. If the  party  declared  at  Stockholm for the  right  of peoples  to  Katzenstein (representing j .    -    ,i   &apos;        , i   i -     ,i     ,i-    -i,      ,   A    -   1 ,          the lection of the Maiority determine  their  own  destiny,  then  this  right must  be given  to every  noaTeBt t0 the Minority). nationality as soon as it  asks for it.   There are no difficulties in the case of Alsace-Lorraine in the way of carrying it into practice.  Even if   one  is personally in  favour of Alsace-Lorraine&apos;s belonging  to Germany, the decision must be left to the people itself.       (Wurzburg Congress, October 1917.)     47. A comrade spoke of Alsace-Lorraine in connection with the right of  Phiiipp Soheidemann, people to determine their own destinies.  But the people of  Alsace-Lorraine are not a separate nation.  Alsace-Lorraine is German land.  We demand for Alsace-Lorraine complete autonomy within the Empire.  The integrity of the Empire that is our condition of peace.                                      (Wurzburg Congress, October 1917.)     48. Alsace-Lorraine  can only be torn away from a completely conquered  Hermann Mulier. Germany.....A concession  from our side would  not  satisfy the  French demands.   According to the  French  idea of a  plebiscite  the Germans who have immigrated since 1871 would be excluded from the vote.   Tactically also nothing could be a greater mistake than a  plebiscite two or three years after the conclusion of peace [as the German  Minority and the  Neutral Socialists desire].   That would only kindle the embers of hatred over again.                                      (Wurzburg Congress. October 1917.)           *                                               *     49. He was not in favour of a  plebiscite  in  Alsace-Lorraine, because he  Emmel (Leader of the could  not&apos;see why Alsace-Lorraine should  be treated  differently from   Hesse,  Alsatian Socialists, Member 1t  , ,   j        J      ,                     .                 J        11   of the Reichstag for Mecklenburg, or any other part of  the Empire.   Alsace-Lorraine was  closely  Mulhausen). bound up with the Empire economically, and  its  separation would&apos; inflict incalculable damage&apos;upon the country.                                    (Wurzburg Conference, October 1917.)     50. Wilson says, with regard to Alsace-Lorraine, that the wrong  should  Phiiipp Scheidemann. be repaired.  Here it must be made clear to Mr. Wilson  that there is nothing               ... to repair.   Alsace-Lorraine is German territory and remains so.  That what is German remains in German possession is a matter of course,   f Status quo of July 1914.]                             (Reichstag, January 24, 1918.)     The following passages refer to the U-Boat War :      51. We  must  defend ourselves with the U-boat also, in  order that our  Phiiipp Scheidemann. -women and children be not starved to death.    (Reichstag, April 6, 1916.)     52. Gentlemen, the  U-boat war cannot be  carried  on in such a  way as  EduardDayid. to  be more  reckless  than  the  construction put by my  honourable  friend Ledebour  upon the  U-boat  resolution.   It is  said  in the resolution that respect  is to  be paid  to the just interests of neutral States.  If, in  spite of that, one arrives at the idea of the resolution which has  been  maintained by Ledebour, that  is  certainly to  torpedo, recklessly and  without warning, all sound logic !   (Loud laughter.)                 (Reichstag, April 6, 1916.)     53. Haenisch, Lensch, and Mulier attack Scheidemanns peace policy, all  ConradHaenisoh. advocating annexations and unrestricted U-boat war.       (&quot; Die  Glocke&quot; quoted in &quot;Deutsche Kurier&quot; for January  25, 1917.)     54. Our  policy did  not prevail.   Much as  we lament it, yet we realise  Phiiipp Scheidemaau. the fact none the less ....  But now that the course has been adopted, we too  only hope with all our hearts that it  may bring  us peace as soon  as^possible.  ,                                (Reichstag, February 27, 1917.)
Gustav Noske,Otto Landsberg.Philipp Scheidemann.Gustav Noske.Philipp Scheidemann.Friedrich Stampfer.Otto Brauu.Eduard David.(Reichstag Main Committee, January 22,1918     58.  Should the  peace negotiations  be broken  off and should politicalreform be delayed or abandoned, the hour will strike for action.                                    (Speech at Chemnitz, January 1918.)     59.  The feeling among the masses is  very  serious.  The food difficulties are certainly not less great here than in England and France.  If you let  thenegotiations in the  East break  down,  and  the hopes  in the West  aredisappointed, what  then?  I. will not dwell  on these ideas any further, but i will say this : We Socialists  want  to do  everything for our people and  our country.   But we will never think of taking risks for a Government, of whichwe may perhaps come to be  convinced that it is not fulfilling its duty to  thepeople.                                   (Reichstag, January 24, 1918.)     The attitude of her party leaders to  Russian Bolshevism  is illustrated by the following quotations :      60.  In  Germany, in accordance with  her own  economic   and politicalstage of development, the relations between  democracy and revolution mustbe totally different  from  what it is to-day in Russia.   We in Germany can nolonger conceive the dictatorship of the proletariat as the forcible rule of one class,  but only as  a  democratic position  of power, based  upon the strongconviction of.the majority of the  people.   If  in  Russia the watchword  is:First the entire power  and  then  Democracy,  with us it  is different :  FirstDemocracy and then the entire power.           (&quot; Vorwarts, January 20.)     61.  They must  be  told with  all plainness  that  their hopes of an earlyviolent revolution  in Germany  is  sheer  madness.    They wrongly applyRussia&apos;s standards to German circumstances, which in political, economic and cultural respects are  at  le^st a hundred years ahead of Russia.   There  is noroom in  Germany  for  Bolshevik  methods of revolution.   We,  as  social democrats,  utterly  condemn the Bolshevik  methods of violence.   ....  Whatthe Bolsheviks have established in Russia  is neither Socialism nor Democracy,but simpl\T a reign of violence and anarchy.                                       (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; February 15, 1918.)     62.  What has  the policy  of the  Bolsheviks been?  It is true  that theirtheories aimed at bringing about an International revolution.  But it is alsowell known that in the Socialist International as a whole the Bolsheviks who held their theory were a small desperate minority, and that they attacked usGerman. Social Democrats particularly sharply because we were not prepared toagree to these tactics, which  we regarded as preposterous and hopeless.   Wehave therefore no reason to defend the Bolsheviks.  They are not our people;they have always attacked us bitterly and ruthlessly.  Neither do we approve     55. We consider it necessary to employ all  fighting means and do  not think of any restriction in the U-boat war.  Whilst it has been shown  that we can confidently expect a favourable issue of the war, the Reichstag  has nevertheless ground  for  adhering  to its idea of ending the  war by a peace of understanding.                               (Reichstag, April 7, 1918.)     In addition to the  allusions to a  possible  revolution contained in the quotations already given (Nos.  25 and 30), the following utterances seem worth  noting in this Connection :      56.  There can be no  revolution.  No one desires it.  No one  advocates revolution, who has the prospect of serving his own interests and the interests of his  class, by peaceful  development  ....  Democracy  must  help us to bring about peace.  It must break  up  the  hostile coalitions  against us, and make impossible to repair  by hard work all that has been destroyed.                              (&quot; Hamburger Echo,&quot; November 18, 1917.)     57.  See to it that the prohibition of &quot; Vorwarts &quot; is removed immediately,in order that the German workers  may not have  the idea that they mustuse other means before justice can be helped to its own.                                                                       )
of their political practices,&apos; their breaking up of the Constituent Assembly.But ....  the  Bolsheviks were the only party in Russia who put forward  a programme  of immediate peace,  if not with, then against, the Entente ....The Bolsheviks wanted an immediate peace,  but of course a democratic peace..... Hence their tough light at Brest-Litpvsk.     The way will  now be open to arrange things amicably.   Undoubtedlycertain mistakes on our side must be avoided.....  We owe it to the menin the trenches and to the women at home to bring about peace at the earliest  -possible moment.                         (Reichstag, February 20, 1918.)     On the question of Belgium the official attitude of the party was that thestatus quo of 1914 must be restored in the sense that Belgium was given  backits complete independence.  On the other hand, the majority did not admittill recently.(after the publication of Erzberger&apos;s book)  that wrong had  beendone to Belgium by the German invasion.  How the matter was regarded onthe Plight wing of the party is shown by the following  quotations from  PaulLensch and Winnig :      63.  It  was a symbolical act that the world-revolution was begun on the  Paul Lensch.German  side with  a  deliberate  insurrection the tearing  up of  Belgianneutrality.   It is open to question whether this  act was good policy.   but what  did   our  pure-doctrine   Socialists  (Radikalen)  do?   They  startedwhimpering about  the breach of law!  No  State-attorney  in the Moabitquarter could have talked in that strain more impressively.   What kind of a&quot; law &quot; was it which  the German  Government was reproached for breaking ?Had Socialists any interest in its preservation ?  That is not even suggested.The simple  fact  is that the money-bag interests  of world-dominating England,together with the Belgian bourgeoisie&apos;s craving for profits, had here rigged upthe  caricature of an  up-to-date State which you can  ask the professors of constitutional law, if you like, to regard with  reverence,  but  revolutionarySocial Democrats never!  This  &quot; law &quot; has already a thousand holes knockedin it; it had been cynically prostituted by the Belgian  Government  itself, asthe documents since discovered have clearly shown and here you find pure-doctrine  Socialists  treating this  worm-eaten relic of the  age  of absolutismbefore &apos;48 as if  it were the resolution  of a  Congress of the German SocialDemocrat party, whose breach  is  visited with excommunication.  (Lensch inthe  &quot; Hamburger Echo&quot;  (1915)  quoted with approval by  Haenisch,  &quot;Diedeutsche Sozialdemokratie,&quot; p. 138).     64.  It is incomprehensible  how  the statement  can still go  about that  Eduwrd David.England entered upon the war to rescue poor Belgium.   England was boundto France.   To preserve Belgium safe from all harm England had only to declare that  she herself would not enter  into  the  war.   That Grey refused to do.It is upon England, therefore,  that the guilt, for Belgium&apos;s misfortunes  reallyrests.  Belgium is the victim of England&apos;s policy of encirclement.         (Speech before the Dutch-Scandinavian Committee, June  6, 1917.)     65.  We cannot demand the restoration of the status quo ante in Belgium Auguit winoig.without some security against  English aspirations.                                             (&quot;Die Glocke,&quot; April 1918.)     The following quotations show the  attitude of the party leaders to the specific  question of  peace ill the  East after the Bolsheviks had  openednegotiations : -     66.  The German working class will look upon it as a matter in which    Ebwrt.they are  bound,  on pain of forfeiting their honour, to strengthen the fight ofthe Russian revolution.         (In a speech quoted &quot; Frankfurter Zeitung,&quot; November 21, 1917.)     67. We resist all plans of annexation  in  the  most decided way, those  Philipp Scheidemann.which look Eastward no less than those which look toward the West.   we want to come to an understanding with the Russian  people as to .the form inwhich liberty  is to , be given  to the populations of the occupied districts aliberty which no one wants to withhold from them.  We demand an adjustment       [367-54]                                                 E
Social-Democrat PartyResolution.jPhilipp Scheidemann.Fritz Ebert.JPbilipp Scheidemann.Friedrich Stampfer.JTriedrich Stampfer.Phiiipp Scheidemann.of interests, in which there is no disregarding of the vital  interests  of Russia.by an appeal to the right of the victor of  the moment.   So to disregard them would be to sow lasting enmity between Germany and Russia and to perpetuatethe war in Europe.   Many things divide  us from  the Bolsheviks.   We shall never believe that the methods which they consider right--and which may be right for Russia can be adopted as workable schemes in all countries  of  theworld.   But what unites us to them is that we share their ultimate Socialist                            (&quot;Frankfurter Zeitung,&quot; November 21, 1917.)AIMS.     68.  With reference to the proceedings at Brest-Litovsk and the onslaughtof  the annexationists upon the  right of peoples  to self-determination,  theSocial Democrat party of the Reichstag again declares that a  neighbourlyrelation and a permanent peace is possible only if the democratic  principle ofthe right of peoples to  self-determination is carried through.  The Socialistparty therefore demands that a free and absolutely independent declaration oftheir will should be guaranteed to the people concerned.                                          (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; January 7, 1918.)     69.  It is clear that, like us Social Democrats, wide circles of the people will see  a contradiction  between  the  declarations  made by  the Germannegotiators on the 25th December and on the 28th December......I willnot allow any doubt to be* possible for  a moment  as to the attitude of theSocialist  party.   From  the beginning of the war till to-day our policy hasbeen absolutely consistent.   We stand for the defence of our country, and wereject every  intention of annexations.  We  support  the unrestricted self-determination of peoples.   Just  as decisively as we defend ourselves againstthe annexationist politicians  of  the  Entente,  we oppose  the aimexationist&quot;politicians in our own country  [i.e., status quo of July 1914].  I say that once more plainly before all the world to-day.                                            (Reichstag, January 5, 1918.)     70.  It is significant that the attitude of our negotiators in Brest-Litovsk produced this immense excitement in Austria. &apos; I protested here on Wednesday against  General  Hofiman&apos;s procedure, and  left no doubt  that  his methods must imperil  peace.              (Reichstag Main Committee, January 22.)     71.  A month has passed since the  diplomatic  catastrophe  of the 27th December, 1917, without our  having made any progress at Brest-Litovsk. What devil  took possession of our diplomats  that two days after the 25thDecember they should have executed  such a volte-face ?                                           (Reichstag, January 24, 1918.)                 *     72.  It is simply horrible  to  think with what levity the Bolsheviks have renounced Russian territory and have pushed aside one part  of  the  country after another with the good-humoured remark that they could even separate themselves from Russia !  German Socialists would never have acted so. . .. If  the  Bolsheviks  and  the German  annexationists are so agreed with  one another, what can we Social Democrats do ?                                        (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; February 24, 1918.)     73. Why if all the Government  promises  and  pledges with regard to a peace by understanding have broken down, dd I not advise my political friends to  break  away  from the  Reichstag majority bloc,  pass into  opposition and refuse further war credits ?  THE official  party would alter  its attitude only if thereby some advantage could be  gained  for the German people and the world at  large.   A great party cannot go into a  corner and sulk.  Opposition without action is nonsense, but action would be possible only outside Parliament, and for that  there  is  no room.  The Socialists can only act within  the limits of parliamentary procedure and with constant regard for the  needs of nationa defence.                             (&quot;Vorwarts,&quot; end of February 1918.)     74.  It was  not our  intention,  not the intention of German  Social Democracy, that Russia&apos;s fate should  be  what it is now. ... .   WE consider it necessary to proclaim to all the  world that the policy which has been pursued
                                    15                        ,                         13is not our policy.....   Meanwhile  there is nothing to be gained by makingempty protests against things which  we endeavoured, but were  not strong enough, to prevent.     A fair share  of the  responsibility rests  upon Russian  Bolshevism.   Itcompletely disarmed Russia.....It played  into the hands of all separatistdesigns.   If it now asks us to make a revolution in order to repair the mischief,it asks too much of  us.....We are still at war in  the West.    ...  Wedo  not wish to attain power under conditions which  would  compel  us to conclude  a peace with the Entente like the peace Trotsky and  Lenin are nowconcluding with us.....     The  conclusion  of peace  in  the  East creates accomplished facts.    WeSocial Democrats  adopt the  view that the  arrangements made in  the Eastneed not be an  insurmountable obstacle to a general peace.                                        (Reichstag, February 26, 1918.)     75. We rejoice that all  along the Eastern front  fighting has  come to an Eduard David.end.   Still we regret that the peace of Brest-Litovsk is not the outcome of amutual agreement, but is obviously imposed  by  force.....We  have made our chiel  task the breaking-up  of  the  hostile coalition not  easier  butharder.                                         (Reichstag, March, 1918.)     76. The aim  of the  Social Democrat party is to end the war by a true Philipp Soheidemann.peace of  peoples, after the fatherland  has been successfully defended, a peacebased on understanding which will  exclude the use of armed force  in  thefuture. This aim has not been furthered by the treaty submitted.....But asthe state of war   has actually ended  in the East  by  this  treaty  we do not propose to reject it.  We abstain from voting.  (Reichstag, March 22, 1918.)     77. Little  as the Russian treaty pleases us,  we are  glad such a treaty has Eduard David.not been imposed on Germany,               (Reichstag, March 22, 1918.)     78. After  this  peace with  Russia ....  what  remains of  all  those Hermann Wendeln        i.        I   .     i   .   j-      in I I    -   i -     T               (a Member of the Majorityflowery  phrases about understanding, self-determination,   disarmament, a but with an unusuallyLeague of Nations?  .... The party must not agree.to such a peace.   The independent standpoint).party must not sanction any more  war-credits.                                (Frankfurt &quot; Volkstimme,&quot; March, 1918.)     79. My/friends  have great objection to  many provisions of  the treaty. ^SSpllTwhh.... All the same, the treaty does bring to an end the state of war between Rumania).Rumania and the Central Powers.                (Reichstag,  July  o, 1918.)                     II.-MINORITY  SOCIALISTS.     The attitude of the Minority Socialists contrasts favourably with that ofthe  Majority  in its honest facing of certain facts, yet  it is harder to give alogical account of it.  They differed  from the Majority  by refusing to regard the war as defensive for Germany.  The Majority, as has been  shown, argued that it was defensive (1) because in the origins of the war Germany was notthe  aggressor;  (2)  because the  status quo  of July 1914  was now  being attacked  by the  enemy. . As  against  this, the  Minority Socialists 1:3LD adifferent view  of the  origins  of the  war; they  believed that the gi saterportion of guilt rested upon Germany and Austria, and, secondly, they wereprepared, if Alsace-Lorraine and the  Polish districts of Prussia  expressed their desire by a plebiscite to sever their connection with the  German Empire,to see a modification of the status quo of July 1914.    So far, the view of the minority generally coincided with the view taken on our side, and they  votedsteadily  against  war-credits from December  1915 onwards.   The logicalweakness of their attitude is their attempt  to make out that, although theyvoted against war-credits, they did not wish to see Germany defeated.  when their opponents pressed them to  say what could be done to bring about a justpeace which had  not  been  done, they  habitually replied  that, if  a genuinepeace offer  were  made by Germany,  the  proletariat  in the  enemy countries would  rise against  their own governments and compel  them to make peace.
It was not difficult for the Majority Socialists to show that this assertion wajrefuted by all experience, if by a genuine  peace offer was meant an offer opeace on the status quo basis.  Perhaps if the Minority had felt able to speakout their mind,  they would have said definitely that Germany should makepeace  offer which  included a change in  the status  quo to Germany&apos;s disadvantage.  Because they either themselves  could not face this conclusion, ordid not think it politic to say it plainly (though in their Stockholm Memorandumthey indicated such change in the  status quo as agreeable to Socialist principles),the logical  weakness in their attitude remained.    Some utterances of Minority leaders follow : Eduard Bernstein.Kurt Eisner, his attitudedescribed by a MajoritySooialist.Hugo Haase.Georg Ledebour.     80. [Eduard David wrote (&quot; Niederrheinische Arbeiterzeitung,&quot; April 18 1916) :-          &quot;The same  Bernstein, who in the  days  before  the 4TH  August     adduced Marx and  Engels as witnesses  to  prove that we must vote for     war-credits;  the  same  Bernstein,  who  co-operated  zealously  in our     declaration and enthusiastically supported it the declaration in which it     was  stated that  Social Democracy would  not leave its own  fatherland in     the  lurch, in the  hour  of danger ;  the same Bernstein who emphasised     that in doing this we felt ourselves still at one  with the International-     this  same man  talks to-day  about the  fatal  vote of the 4th August,     1914!&quot;]     Haase  had passionately opposed the granting of the credits ; I had both spoken and  voted  in  their  favour.   The  reasons  which  moved me.. . proceeded from the views I at that time  held as to the origin and occasion  of the  war.....The first weeks of war were enough to shake me, and after two months it was  clear  to me that on this, as on other  important questions, THE assumptions which had determined my attitude in the first days of August were mistaken,                        * (&quot;Die Zukunft,&quot; April 21, 1917.)     81. Some part is  played  in  the opposition by honorable ideologues, like the  highly-gifted  Kurt  Eisner, formerly  editor-in-chief of vorwarts, whol incessantly  rack  their  brains trying to make out  on which  side in this war &quot;the rio-ht &quot; arid &quot;the  truth&quot; are.  And since they find much to  object to[ (who  can take  that  amiss?)  in  the  manner  in   which  Austria-Hungary addressed its ultimation to Serbia in July 1914, and. since further in their un- remitting study of all the innumerable Orange, Yellow and  Pted Books, they begin to see all,green and blue,  and thenceforth are  no longer able to regard the Central  Powers as only clothed in  the snow-white robe of innocence and the Powers of the Entente as only pitch-raven black devils,  they withdraw in despair into the contemplative attitude of a pure ethical condemnation of thii wicked world.        (Haenisch. &quot; Die deutsche Sozialdemokratie,&quot; p.  143.)     82. Everything points to the conclusion that our army, in spite of great military sucesses, will  not be able to bring the  enemy  to  his knees.  Two mighty coalitions stand face  to  face, and at the  end of  the terrible  conflict there will probably  be neither victors nor vanquished.   [Tumult in the House.] In  reality there  will be  only  vanquished peoples bleeding  from millions of wounds.                                    (&quot;Reichstag, March 24, 1916.)     83.   He  who votes for the credits gives a blank cheque for the use at the Governments pleasure of the means thus  granted.  A party which by votingthis  credit gives the  Government  the strongest possible vote  of confidence, thereby takes on itself a share in  the responsibility FOR  the war-aims of the Government  and the measures  which the Government thinks  good  for the realisation of its war-aims.  We are unable  to give the Government THIS vote of confidence . .  .  The fact  that  the  ten  [Powers of  the Entente] haveintimated in their Notes their adherence to  extravagant schemes of conquest cannot weaken our  judgment  on the attitude  of  our own Government . .  . We Socialists must wage THE same, FIGHT IN. all countries AGAINST THE imperialist efforts of capitalism.                      (Reichstag, FEBRUARY 23, 1917.)KtJJ
     84. We  demand the cessation of the  ruthless  U-boat  war.   It is as GeorgMcbour. inconsistent with the laws of humanity as the English starvation scheme.                                         (Reichstag, February 23, 1917.)     85. The Entente sees our real annexationist temper  .  . .  The old swindle Oswald Vogtherr. is continued of telling the workers  that we are  engaged  on a war of defence.                                          (Reichstag, February 26,  1917.)     86. We  do not forget the Austrian ultimatum to Serbia,  nor the Austrian HugoHaase. preparations for war against Russia,nor  the conferences which took place in Berlin on the 5th July,  1914, nor  the activity of Tirpitz and Falkenhayn in those  critical days.                            (Reichstag, July 19,  1917.)     87. When  I stated in  this House  eighteen  months  ago that  the war HugoHaase. would end without  victors  or vanquished, I was shouted down,  but now we&apos; hear the same thing from all sides.             (Reichstag, July 19,  1917.)     88. Any one  who  tries  to prevent  the examination of the question of Eduard Bernstein. responsibility for the war does poor service to the Socialist  work for peace, for that work can only be successfully  accomplished if it is based on the foundation of an  honest recognition of facts.                       (&quot; Sozialistische Auslandspolitik,&quot; August 15,  1917.)     89. The working  men  want freedom and peace.  The proceedings of to- HugoHaase. day must strengthen the conviction in the masses of the people of all countries that  diplomacy  cannot  bring about a democratic peace, and that the people must  bleed to death unless they help themselves.....There is only one road to salvation. -.... International class-war alone can help.                                         (Reichstag, INovember 29,  1917.)     90. What  is  the  attitude of our Government to the peace programme of HugoHa&amp;se. the Russian Proletarian. Government?  .... The &quot; Tagliche  Rundschau&quot; reported as  the  result  of a Grown Council in Berlin ... . an enormous annexationist programme, stamped with the seal of the darkest Cabinet policy. Even  the dullest  person can no longer assert that the war is to be continued purely for defence  against the enemies&apos; schemes of dismemberment. .  .  .     If the gate of peace which is slowly opening is not to be shut immediately, the Government must  relinquish  once for all, without condition and without, reservation, the  schemes as tp Poland, Courland, and Lithuania.....(To the Majority Socialists.)  Your &quot;  deed,&quot; your &quot; solidarity &quot; with the Russian proletariat, your &quot;powerful support of the Bolsheviks&quot; these last few days have  shown  in all its  magnificence what that means    It  means your still voting war-credits [interruption] after  this programme  of annexation  has been published.                        .  (Reichstag, November 29,  1917.)     91. Any one  inspired  by Socialist views cannot do anything to harm his HugoHaaae.. own people for  the advantage of  another people.  A Socialist of the German Empire can  do nothing to deliver up Germany to the enemy.  The German Socialist workers do not want to promote either the English, the French,  the Italian, or  the  German  imperialism.   We  are  firm  opponents of .every imperialism.  . . .  But the  German Socialists will not allow  themselves to be deterred from fighting  for  peace with all the power at their disposal or from using  those  methods  which  constitute  the  strength  of  the   modern proletariat. . . .     The publication of  the secret documents of the Entente has confirmed what  in the main we already^ knew, and have always said that the Entente is carrying on the war for imperialistic ends.  But not the Entente only.  No, on that side as on this.                   (Reichstag, November 29,  1917.)     92. Peace  would soon be  achieved if Prussia-Germany were so reformed Heinrich strobei. that it could  be regarded as one of the civilised nations of the  world. .  .  . The reactionary  Prussian system is the strongest support of our militarism and       - imperialism which we have to  thank for this hideous war.  . . .  It was  the        [367-54]          .                                        F
GusteT Strdbel.Karl Kautsky.Heinrich 81 rob el. .Georg Ledebonr.Hugo Haaso.Georg Ledebour. thoughtlessness  of  the  Government and of the parties which encouraged the Government to support that unbelievable ultimatum to Serbia. .  . .     Foreign,  countries have a right to demand democratic guarantees from Germany.  Foreign countries  can have no faith in the German Government so long as  it finds  its support in the present ruling classes.  The German people  certainly  did not want  war, and the vast majority of the army would vote for peace by agreement and without annexations.  The German  people cannot be content to go on being a pariah among the nations.  It wants to make its peace with mankind     free people.                                       (Prussian Diet, December 6, 1917.)     93. I don&apos;t  demand a revolution, but I say it  will come when conditions favourable to  it show themselves.        (Prussian Diet, December 6, 1917.)     94. We  have  reached a decisive-perhaps the decisive moment of the&apos;,war.  The  peace negotiations with  the  representatives  of  the  Russian Government are  beginning.....Were the  negotiations to end  in a, peace which even one  of  the  nationalities concerned the Russian, the Polish, the Lithuanians,  or  the Letts merely endured  with  gnashing of teeth, that would make a profound  impression on  the nations still in arms against the German Empire.....The greatest  obstacle to peace amongst the Entente nations  is  still  their deep-rooted  distrust of the  German regime,  which continues in. its  essence the same as when the war broke out.....If the1 fact of a peace without annexations proves that Germany is not animated by the desire of conquest,  if the fact of parliamentary control  of  the peace negotiations proves  that Germany is not an  autocracy, then we may expect that the conclusion of  peace with Russia will lead to an early general lasting democratic peace, which  will leave no  sting behind.....That is  the peace we want.                 (&quot;Leipziger Volkszeitung,&quot; December 10,  1917.)     95.  We must  not tuy to  exploit Russians need  of peace for imperialist aims, otherwise  we run the risk of  seeing  Russia  reorganise  herself,  and having  to fight  next  summer, not only with the Americans, but  with  the Russians as well.  The German Independent Socialists have now been refused passports to  Stockholm, where they  wished  to come into touch  with  the Bolsheviks.   If the  Central Powers do not  make  an honourable peace with Russia now, at the eleventh hour,  we shall be swallowed up by the war.                                     (Prussian Diet, December 11, 1917.)     96.  We wish for a general peace on a democratic basis.  In so far as the Bolsheviks too desire such  a peace we aoree with them.                                          (Reichstag, January 24, 1918.) -     97.  If  the  separation  of Alsace-Lorraine  from  France  in   1871 is described as a &quot;  disannexation&quot; [i.e.,  if Germany  is  stated merely  to have resumed its   own in  1871] we   must  remember  that the deputies from Alsace-Lorraine in  the French Chamber voted against the severance.  The French  and German Social  Democrats  before the war were united on  one point-that Alsace-Lorraine  should become a free German Federal State.   If it is possible to end  the  war by conceding a referendum to the population of these provinces, the concession should be made.                                          (Reichstag, January 25,  1918.)     98.  The reason why  the negotiations at Brest Litovsk have broken down is that  the  German  Government refused to give  the  principle   of  self- determination the meaning  given  it by the Socialists of every country.  The Independent Socialists had no objection to a separate peace if certain of the con- tracting parties refused to enter upon a general peace.   The question was, What were the conditions of peace to  be?.....(Reichstag, February 20,  1918.)Georg Ledebour.    99. We have no hope of the Governments being able  to bring us  a  repeace the German as little as any other.   One  and all they look at  every-thing from the standpoint of the extension of power, of profiteering  interests,
of the capitalists.  We expect a world peace only from the  spreading light of knowledge which is  shining everywhere, and  from the proletariat gatheringfor a  mass strike, till the final victory of the proletariat is won.                                         (Reichstag, February 20, 1918.)     100. The old treaty should  have been enough to secure the  complete Oswald Vogthew.independence of&quot; Belgium.  But that was  thrown over the  housetops  by the wrong done  to  Belgium.  What force have international declarations when&quot; necessity knows no law ? &quot;               (Reichstag, February 26, 1918.)     101. A vote for  this budget would imply a vote of confidence for the Hugo Haase.Government, for the capitalist State, for the military dictatorship, for theenrichment  of the  big  capitalists,  for the peace of violence with Russia, forthe fight against the Russian revolution, for the oppression  of national groups in favour of a small  privileged dominant caste.   We therefore reject  thebudget.                                     (Reichstag, March IS, 1918.)     102. My party holds that the U-boat war  on merchant shipping is Q-eorg Ledebour.justified  in  view of the right  of  capture  at  sea  (asserted  by England) and england&apos;s plan  of starvation,  but  not a  ruthless  U-boat  war.  The  terrortheory rests on a false psychology.   It prolongs the war, and it increases thenumber of our enemies.                        (Reichstag, April 17, 191.8.)                                                                           * - -     103. The suggestion of Luxburg that ships should  be  sunk  without Georg Ledebour.leaving a trace (&quot;spurlos versenkt &quot;) is the most infamous thing I have everread in any  State document.                 (Reichstag, October 9, 1917.)     104. The question   of national defence must  be considered, not in the Karl Kautsky.abstract, but  in connection with the particular  political  background ....Here we see  the hidden root of the conception which obtains among theGovernment Socialists as  to  national defence confidence in  the  existing government, in  the existing system.  Here lies the  fundamental ground ofthe divergence  of views of the Independent  and the Deoendent Socialists.No Independent Socialist wants  to surrender his country to the foreignenemy, to  commit  what is^ called  &quot; high treason,&quot; but he sees the greatestdangers  which threaten  the  people in  another  quarter  than that  wherethe Dependent Socialists see them, and his  method of protecting the countryand the people differs essentially7 from theirs.                              (&apos;&quot; Leipziger Volkszeitung,&quot; April 20, 1918.)     105. The German  Government broke ks  treaty with  Belgium,  but the Gteorg Ledebour.demand that Germany should  be punished  for this has not been given up.The demand made by   Wilson, Lloyd George,  and  Clemenceau  that theGerman  people  should  be punished is as unjust  as  the  demand  that theRoumanian people should be punished for the crime of their Government.                                             (Reichstag,  June 21, 1918.)     106. As regards guilt for the  war,  our view has been  confirmed by KariHaase.everything that  has become known.  Austria-Hungary, by her ultimatum toSerbia, forced on war, and Germany had previously bound herself to approvethis step.                      ......         ,  (Reichstag,  June 25, 1918.)     107. We have often enough heard that military victory is impending, but Hueo Haase.it has always been seen that peace is unattainable by military victories.   the masses must understand  that it is their task to end the war.                                             (Reichstag, June 25, 1918.)                 III.-THE &quot; SPARTACUS &quot; GROUP.    Some phrases  characteristic  of  Karl Liebknecht may be  noticed  inconclusion.   The &quot;Spartacus&quot; group, of which Liebknecht was one of thefounders in 1915, is not to be confounded with the Minority.  It is one of theextreme  groups  which  together make  up what we  now call the Bolshevistelement in Germany.
     108.  &quot;The leading principles  of the  new  party,  of which  Dr. KarlLiebknecht  is  the nucleus, are  shown in  their chief maxims.  The principalone is      &quot; &apos; The  proletarian  has  no fatherland except  the  Socialist International.&apos;The talk  about &apos; the duty of defence of the fatherland &apos; used by Socialistpatriots they describe as  nothing but a &apos; fallacious phrase&apos; (&quot; Verwirrungsphrase&quot;)intended  to harness  the working-class to the imperialist  car.   Their  ownwatchword  is &apos; International  class-war against the war  in  order to force onpeace through the will  of  the masses.&apos;  &apos; The centre of gravity of  the class-organisation of the proletariat  rests  upon the International.&apos;  &apos; The duty  ofcarrying out the resolutions of the  International  takes the precedence of allthe other  duties which attach to membership in Socialist  organisations.&apos;&quot;                                                         (Berger, p.  81.)     109.  &quot; The most  consistent group (of  the opposition  groups), that led byLiebknecht,  declares roundly that the  proletarian has no fatherland, which itcould be  his duty to defend.  This  war  is  an  imperialist war of robberybetween  the ruling classes in the several States.   On  the other  hand, theproletarians of all countries have to preserve their international solidarity, and,by united concerted  action, compel their war-frenzied bourgeoisies  to makepeace.   One. must give Liebknecht the credit that  he  has never  made anyconcealment of these views.  They recur in all his declarations.&quot;                                        (E. David, quoted Berger, p.  18.)     110.  Gentlemen, if this is treason to the country, if it is treason to thecountry to  champion  the  cause  of  peace,  and   the proclamation of  theInternational  proletarian class-war  against war, if the systematic rupture ofthe party truce is treason to the country, then,  indeed, gentlemen, I  repeatwhat has  been  said in another place, it is an  honour to be  called a  traitor tothe country!          (Liebknecht in the Prussian  Diet, March&apos; 3,  1916; Berger, p.  45.)     111.  It is  our business to call at such  a juncture  to  the working-class ofall  countries :  &quot; Get  to work  !  Those in the trenches, no  less  than  those  inthe country, ought to down arms  and  turn against the common enemy, whodeprives them of light and air.&quot;                     (Prussian Diet,  March 16, 1916; Berger, pp.  45-46.)o

</content>
</cab>
