<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 40-45</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&quot;HIS DOCUMENT h\ &apos;&amp;a PROPERTY OF ;HIS BRITANNIO I-.; .J^S-Y&apos;S  GOVERNMENT&apos; *f1 W&apos; &apos;-wtrri IWWHWm Ml/SECRET.(1)The Board of Admiralty have no doubt that the War    Cabinet are fully aware cf the seriousness of this question.    They are probably aware that a special Committee appointed by    the Board and presided over by Admiral Sir &quot;artyn Jerram is now    taking evidence at Portsmouth on this question.   It had been in    contemplation to wait for a day or two pending Admiral Jerram&apos;s    preliminary survey and then have come to the War Cabinet with a    proposal to grant an immediate ad interim increase in substantive    Wy of all ratings *   This course will indicate to the War    Cabinet how important the matter is in the view of the Board of    Admiralty.   The Board would thereafter have awaited Admiral    Jerram&apos;s final recommendations and have come to tba War Cabinet    with its complete proposals..(2)           The Board understand, however, that as part of a scheme    for setting up Armies of Occupation and Home and Oversea    Garrisons, the War ^Office will be Bound to make recommendations    at once in favour of substantial increases in pay in the Army    for those who would be held to continued&apos; service under that    scheme and for- those who - otherwise about to be demobilised -Office will take the form of a weekly bonus to the officers andmen - including the permanent Army - who may-join the Armies ofOccupation, to be introduced at the date when the units of thoseArmies are formed and established apart from units about to be demobilised.   It is understood that the date suggested forthe introduction of this bonus to these officers and men willmight volunteer for service in these Armies of Occupation.The Board understand that the proposals of the Warbe ^ebruarjr 1st.
         It is&apos; understood that the amount of the weekly-bonusto be proposed will be as followsPrivate SoldierPaid Lanoe-Corporal .CorporalsSergeants ......*..Colour-Sergeants, 0 a,Q.,1.3*3,  and Q.MWarrant Officers ..2nd Lieu t lieutenant sLieutenants.......Captains ..........Majors *.....*.....Li ou t lieutenant 0 o1 one1sHigher Ranks ......Having had these natterT T1Js s. d,10  6 per week12  3    &quot;12  3    &quot;14  0    &quot;S,17  621  024  628  031  635  038  642  0s before them,  the Board ofAdmiralty are anxious as far as possible to adapt their proposals to those of the War Office, because they recognise the extremeinexpediency of initiating a scheme of this sort side by side with&apos;the set of proposals differing in any substantial degree putforv/ard on behalf of the Sister Service.         There are, however, two points upon which their proposals must as they think necessarily differ from those of the V/ar Office.They call particular&apos; attention to t^ese hereafter.         As regards the date o^ the introduction of this scheme,the Board of Admiralty have no alternative, as they think, but to fall in with the &quot;:Var Office date:  though thev warn the WarCabinet in advance that there can be no doubt that the volume ofevidence before the Jerram Committee &quot;111 ask that whateverconcessions are now and ultimately to be made shall be antedated.to October 1st, 1916.    The Board will deal with that matterwhen it arises and make whatever recommendations to the WarCabinet may seem necessary.         The War Office scheme would apparently propose to grant                                                          the /
increased Day only to the Regular Army:   the  men hold  to service for the purpose of occupation,  etc;  and to such officers and men who might otherwise ho demobilised but who volunteer for continued service.  In other words,  fromthe date of the introduction of the War Office scheme  noofficer or man in the Army thereafter to be  demobilisedwould get the benefit of these concessions.   The Board ofAdmiralty find it quite impossible not  to apply the proposedconcessions to all its officers and men, Active Serviceand &quot;Hostilities only&quot;.  It would point out  that part  ofthe Army sohone is the separation into  different units ofthq men who join&apos; the, Army of Occupation and  those who  willbe set asido for demobilisation.  This  is a  vitally necessary thing to do, because of the grave  difficultieswhich -would, arise if two men of the same rank serving in the same unit wore one on one rate of pay and the otheron another.  It will at once be obvious that the Admiraltycannot make this separation.   It cannot have a ship manned by officers and men to be demobilised.   Therefore, unless  i,heconcession is given to all alike in the Navy, the board will be confronted with a situation under which two menof the same rating in the same ship  will be gettingdifferent rates of pay.  This would be  quite intolerableand v/ uld lead to a situation for which the  Board ofAdmiralty could not be responsible.  Further, directlythe discrimination is made in the Amy, the  men not inreceipt of these, concessions could at once secure them byvolunteering for the new.force.  There  can be no suchincentive to the Navy &quot;Hostilities&quot; men, because it is notdesired that they should volunteer.  Further, finally,directly the Army is able to get together its force tobe demobilised, all the officers and men in  that force would               &apos;                      ,         -  . . .        be /
&quot;be simply awaiting the completion of-tha-administrativeprocess of demobilisation and the means of transportationhomo.  That is very far from being true as regards thevast majority of the Navy &quot;Hostilities only&quot; men, who,whilst wore it merely a matter of administrative procedurecould be demobilised forthwith, are held to service forthe  time being, because of the necessities of the Fleet.(9)      The War Office scheme provides that the concessionshall take the form of a bonus.  The Board of Admiraltyview is that whatever it may be called it is quite incon-coivablo that it will ever be reduced, and that the proper course is not to treat it as a bonus but frankly to announceit as an ad interim permanent increase-in substantive pay.The  Board of Admiralty with respect would point outthat precisely the same proposition was adopted in regardto Separation Allowances.  They were to be withdrawn atthe  close of the war.  The same policy was adopted asregards the abolition of Hospital  Stoppages and the abrogationof the necessity of a man in the Navy to replace his kit.The  Board of Admiralty are very much aware of the  seriousmisgivings in the Fleet which those decisions called forth.-And  they must point out that it has now been decided tocontinue the Separation Allowances until the revision  of pay  to be proposed by Admiral  Jerram&apos;s Committee isannounced;  and that, so far as they are aware, no oneproposes to reimpose Hospital  Stoppages or to revert tothe  old system under                                                 which /
     which the sailor had to replace his kit  after  its first     free issue on joining.  They would therefore with respeot     suggest thcit no good purpose would he  served by  playing     ivith words in these matters, and that  to oall  it a  bonus     would create the same misgiving, rob the concession of     much of its graciousness, and undermine  the confidence     of the men in the bona fides of the Govern:ient&apos; s     intentions.  They therefore very strongly urge that the     concession now  proposed both for Army  and navy should     frankly be announced as an ad interim  and permanent     increase in substantive pay, rending further consider-     atioh of the problems of the conditions of service and     emoluments of the Army aid navy.(10)      Confronted, therefore, with the Army proposals,     the Board of admiralty suggest the following,  to be     introduced at the same  date as the Army proposals  are     introduced, and as ad interim permanent  increases in     substantive dailv pay, viz:-                                 s d               Boy.............    *G per day               Ordinary Seaman.  1 0    11               A.B..............  1 6               Leading Seaman;.  19    &quot;               P.O.............  2 0               C.P.O...........  2 6               (The increased rates for men of the                hoyal ; arines ;dll be the same as                for the army.)          iis regards officers, the following,  are proposed:-                                         s  d               Warrant Officers, It.J...  3  6 per dayfui O-JLL*AJI    I CoiDTQd- W.0&apos;s and Mates..  4  0   &quot;u  ^^MZ^kI &quot;Su^IiTeffEelrant s&quot;7^......  2  6 .  &quot;  &quot;           * Lieutenants.............  4  6   &quot;               Lieut, -Commanders........  5  0   &quot;               Commanders..............  5  6   &quot;               Captains &amp; above........  6  0   &quot;          The Board of Admiralty would wish it to be  under-     stood that these also are proposed ad  interim  permanent     increases; and that tfte reference to further increases in
permanent pay hereafter, already mentioned aa regardsmen, applies also to the officers.     The annual charge for the ratings of the permanentUavy is estimated at  3,500,060\   To this mayt be added the cost of the concession to &quot;Hostilities only&quot; men.This may be estimated at a lump sum of  1,300.000.     The. annual cost for officers of the permanent itfavyis estimated at  900,000,  To this must be added the costof the concession to temporary officers, estimated at a lump sum of  200,000.     Therefore the annual charge of these concessions tothe permanent foroe  will be roughly  4,500,000 on presentfigures.  During the period of demobilisation, anadditional oharge of about ll millions will be involvedas the ooet of the concession to the officers&apos;and. mento be demobilised.

</content>
</cab>
