<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 52-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
L II ii H I  S E R V I C..EvL.G.4.  Memorandum by the President of the Local Government Board on mr. Winston Churchill&apos;a Memorandum of the 17th January (0.T.6S74)     1.   I a..; strongly of opinion that the surest ion to renewobjection.   It seems to me that the pledges whioh have beengiven by members of the Government ;uake this course impossible at the present time.   It would ral^e a storm of protest inthe Country.   It would! be urged by the Labour Party and othersthat It was the thin end of the wedge to conscription after thewar, and oreate profound diotrust which no asauranoe or denialswould allay.   It would be held to be in flagrant contradictionto the announced policy of the Government to PREA3 for a Leagueof Nations) and the end of compulsory military service.A number of other difficult questions would arise -Whether recruiting is to be limited to the youths of18 years of age;Whether men, especially young men,  formerly exemptedbeoause of their importance &quot;for munition work are tobe recruited,&quot;Whether, and if so, what other fcr^s of exemptions  -there were to be.   Should we, for instance,  have theConscientious Objector over again?Whether we should recreate Military Servioe tribunals and many other thorny questions&apos;.The present time, when industrial unrest prevails soacutely, would be a most unfortunate time at which to throw intothe arena new causes of distrust and trouble, which would certain-ly be represent?! by not a few Labour leaders as adopted partly because of industrial troubles.recruiting under the Military Service  Acts  ia  open  to  the gravest     3.   For these reasons, I ^ould strongly depreoate atpresent any attempt to resume ooapuleory reoruiting,  or indeed,
 to resume it at all unless it is shown to be inevitable.      3.   The statement moreover does not reveal on what baois of policy it is suggested that 1,150,000 men,  1th a margin of 300,000 are required for the Armies of Occupation, Overseas and Home Garrisons.           It is not olstar further why the men required for the Armies of Occupation, Overseas and Home Oarria^na, should be exclusive of the ppet be Hum Army.    Surely this Army, or a large part  of it,  could be uaad, and trained during use, in the Armies of Occupation,  Overseas, or in the Home Garrisons.           In addition to these considerations, any possible alternative  method of obtaining the number of men &quot;THE may be required merits the closest scrutiny.           Aooerdina; t:  the etatsment. (G.T.6331) circulated On the 7th instant, there  were 5,911,000 Officers and Men in the,Army  on the  11th November.    The number of men required for the Armies  of Occupation, Overseas and Home Garrisons, is estimated in the  Adjutant-General&apos;3 report at 1,100,000, lee  than a fifth of the  total Officers and Men in th*j Army on the 11th November. Is not  the  firrt otep to ascertain .7H-3TH*?r,  by offering proper inducement a-&apos; (a  course euRested in  the report itself for higher warrant and  non-commissioned : ranks&apos;) the necsaoary number of men Oanhot  be obtained for  th-* required period of time,  on a voluntary basie?   I  do not  think  that the Country would shrink from  a.considerable increase  of pay if this  should be required.      4,   ..J?f0BIT,l3ATI0S?.&quot;   With respect  to  Sir Auokland geddes Note  &quot;oii demobilisation-,  hie  conclusion &quot;appears  to be that he ifl prepared to  scrap  the present  scheme of demobilisation and sub-&quot;etitute fjar  it  sowe other.    This,  ooncluaion is somewhat startlf What  ia,important  is  a  statement of the . reasons on which,it is            -&apos;.t, ... ,                          - founded.   The  present-scheme  of - demobilisation was- drawn-up by a  Comxittee  -preside:-/over by  the Secretary of State for India,
      and by the War Office and Ministry of Labour with the assistance      of representative employers and workpeople.   After the moat      prolonged and detailed.discussion of it at every stage with      leaders of industry, its principles were heartily approved.      It was agreed to by the Cabinet nearly tr/o years ago, so far      a3 the general scheme is concerned.   I am certain myself that      unless vre preserve the industrial basis which has b*en agreed      upon and for which the whole machinery and organisation has      been designed, we shall throw the o-country into hopeless con-      fusion.   There has only been, up tc the present, so far as I      know, one considerable attempt to depart from the arrangements      previously agr^d upon and it has been attended with  most      unfortunate consequences.    By all means, let us remedy the      manifest defects a- they arise, but frequent  changes only      irritate both soldiers and employers, and I think it vould  be a      grave mistake to altsr its principles tmleae  an overwhelming oaee      can be shorn for doixvj soe                By Tay of one single illustration tfe may consider what      the abandonment of the pivotal system would mean to our Housing      soheme.   Men neoeaaary to re-etart brickyards, men necessary      for Local Authorities, surveyors, architects, inspsotors, etc.      havn b**n asked for in connection rcith the Housing scheme.   We&apos;      ars constantly confronted with the sxcuse cf  lack of ataff,  and      unl^sa th*? essential men are got back to the  brickyards a      serious lack cf materials  would certainly arise before long.                Any wholesale  scrapping of the industrial system  of      demobilisation already arranged for vould,  I  am oertain,  play      havoo with cur Housing schema, as it  certainly -?ould with a      host  of other important  undertakings.                                                 C  ADDISON.Local Government board,    Whitehall,  S.W.I.       37th January,  1919.

</content>
</cab>
