<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 313-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
K&amp;KJUT relating to the. y/orjc of the&apos;&apos; loarCeT^grioulture for       Scotland for: the week ending 5th February 1919,&apos;F00D FKOBUOTIOH.   1.  Defence of the&quot; Realm Iteffulation Z1L          -,  ,^Y.*     The Asriculturai&apos;fc&apos;e:outive&apos; Committee for Kincardine shire have reported 234 oases to the Board, qf.farmers who had failed to &quot;return the&apos; Schedule- of cropping:; particulars within the specif- ,led time.   &apos;The Board are at &quot;Present i:a.e.omimmi cation with the parties concerned;..   ;    &apos;\  \\ ,/; v&apos;         .   8. &apos;The Rats Order 1918.  &apos;  v\ /i.&quot;&apos;&quot;&quot;&apos;  &quot;  .           Under the Rats Order&apos;-&apos;i*918,&apos; owners or occupiers of land or buildings are required to take  reasonable and proper precautions. to prevent sueh land or buildings,. from becoming infested by rat3,&quot;.and&quot; the local Authorities^ (fiats&quot;&apos;)-&apos; Scotland&quot;TOder&quot; 1918-imposes on Local Authorities the powers, and&apos; duties necessary  for the effect- :ive discharge of the functions&quot;assigned to them under the Rats- Order. 1913.   The Board,have,., accepted the, responsibility of administration of&apos;the&apos; latter&apos;,5r.de-r \n Scotland, and they have accordingly communicatecL.with&apos;;thevarious. Town Councils and County Councils offering for&quot;their-consideration&apos;-suggestions as to tho measures to be adopted, and asking -particulars of  the steps which they propose to &quot;take &apos;.with a view&apos;to the  effective. administration of  the Order.&quot;.&apos;The.Board have also communicated with the District Agricultural Executive Committees  asking them to calf the attsn- :tion cf Local Authorities to.any  bad cases that may  oome under their notice.  &apos;   .3,  Horses and Horse implements.           In several dfstricts where. Committees were  provided with horses and ploughs for hire tC farmers there  is  now little or  no demand for the use of these, and  accordingly the Committees in  these oases have been authorised to  sell the horses and artie- :les to the best advantage.-  The  Committees for Inverness, Perth, Kinross, Mid ArgyllMel.rose, Peebles,  Kirkcudbright&apos; and Wigtown have already disposed of a number  cf horses and ploughs along with, the harness which was also supplied, and, on  ths whole, satisfactory prices have boon received  for these.    It is propos-.&apos;: ed to retain, meantime only those  horses and implements which- will, be required to undertake worlc.,during the&apos;-Spring;months for&apos;.which the Committees have entered  into  contracts with farmers.: &quot;Where&quot;such.work has not already commenced it has been arranged in  most eases to&quot;give out the horses to farmers on &quot;meat for work&quot; terms.   4.  Labour^   Agricultural Oompanies.          The Board have drawn the attention of the ScottishCommand to the receipt of many complaints from farmers as to theperemptory withdrawal of soldiers from agriculture for demobilise:tion, without notice being given to their employers, and as aresult of the board&apos;s representations, stringent orders have beenissued by the War Office that this practice is to cease, and the convenience of the farming community is to be consulted beforesoldiers are withdrawn for demobilisation in future.Many /
i       Many complaints continue to bo received as to the practiof demobilised pivotal and ollp mon not reporting for work to tfarmers who have applied for them.  5.  Seed Oats for France.          The Royal Commission on Wheat Supplies acting In con;)uncj   with the Food Production Department and this Board are making  I   arrangements for the purchase of seed oats for Franco, &apos;o  &quot;whiofc   about 20,000 quarters aro to be purohaeed in Scotland.   Tho tg   of purchase were, explained at-a meeting of Scottish Merchants \   last Wednesday and ten&amp;era for the supply of the  oats were  invt           From the replies reoeived a list of 17 merchants was dr,   up and sent to tho feheat Commission who are, to place the ordere  - with, the merchant!?.:   Before the oats are finally accepted  tfcej   to &quot;be inspected and passed by a representative of this Departs     6*  Wart Disease of Potatoes (Scotland),Order 1919,           By means of a certificate issued under Article    (1) ol   above Order certain areas in Lanarkshire and Perthshire have te   added to the list of &quot;Infected Areas&quot;.          \arrangements have been made, with the three.Potato Trade   Associations for the supply of seed potatoes of the immune  vari   :ies to retail merchants in infected areas.   The  sscoi&amp;tions   have furnished the.Board with a list of whole sale.merchants wh   have expressed &quot;their willingness to supply&apos;seed potatoes of the   immune varieties,, and this list will be circulated tc all retail   merchants in the infected areas.         &apos; -II.  COLLECTION OF STATISTICS AND RETURNS RELATING  TO  AfllttOULOTS.     Annual Agricultural Returns.            The Board of, Agriculture and Fisheries  having obtained    Treasury sanction for tho collection of the Annual Returns  by 1    officers of their own Instead of the officers of Customs  and Is   .. the Board have&apos; considered the advisability of proposing a eimil    scheme for Scotland.  As&apos;however, the&apos;; Board of  Customs and  Exoi  /are willing to maintain the present arrangement&apos; for the ourrent  -&apos;  year, no change will be made.   The arrangements necessary  for    dealing with claims under the Corn Production Act  are however    under consideration, in conjunction with  the English;and  Irish    Department 5UIII,  IMS SETTLEMENT FOR SOLDIERS AND SAILORS.mm m h ***********m*-*m*m*m*mmm*i&apos;*mm^             ******* *m*nw**mmm**-*w*mm ******************      Castlo Huiitly Estate,. Perthshire.            Under the Small Holding Colonies  Acts,  the Board  have, &apos;    the approval of the Treasury, effected the purchase of part of t    Estate of Castle Huntly for a colony settlement for ex-services    The part of the Estate which the. Board have acquired is peculiai    suitable for the purposes which they have in view.  The area cos    :prises 690.acres, and consists of. land of high  quality.   ExcelHI    markets and transport facilities are conveniently  available.  - busy industrial- and market centres, of Dundee and lochee are lesj    than 4;miles distant,, while to the we:st is Perth,  &apos;an important    market town and&apos;railway junction.   The leases  of  the farms takt    over expire in 1919 and 1920.             .   - -; IV.  DMOBILISATIOII /
3.204PTOBILISAJPIOIT of ASBICULTURAL TOJJSRS.        Tho Board are informed that the  demobilisation ofagricultural workers?continues to proceed more  rapidly,  and&apos;they hops to be in a position to report  the actual rate  ofdemobilisation by means of &amp; system which has been institute:ed whereby employers ere requested to acquaint tho Board ofthe arrival of every demobilised man.   The Board have conplst-;ad their second quota of pivotal men for consideration by theMinistry of Labour.   IS is estimated that tho  number of name3forwardsd to date is 11,000pr

</content>
</cab>
