<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 459-463</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This  Document Is the Prope iiHis  Britannia  IV) majesty&apos;s  Govern     .t (?()       MINISTRY  OF  FOOD.OF  THE   SUBCOMMITTEE  ON   REFORMS.  1. The terms of the reference to the Sub-Committee appointed by the Consumers Council were :       &quot;To consider the measures  taken,  by  the  Ministry  of Food for the .control of prices  and        a distribution of food and  for other purposes during the war period, and to advise whether          any, and, if so, which of these measures should be continued in peace time.&quot;  Upon the matters falling within that reference the  Sab-Committee present the following report:                      I.-IMPROVEMENTS  IN METHOD OF TRADING-.                                     A. NETT WEIGHT.  2. The question of  short  weight was discussed by a Select  Committee appointed by the House ofiinmons,  which presented a  report  on  15th July 1914 [Od.  359].  No steps  have been taken  bydiament to give effect to the recommendations made by that report.  3. The Food Controller in regulating dealings in articles of food has had to consider the questionnett weight, and in certain cases has made express  provision that articles shall be sold nett weight.  nature of the provisions made by the Food Controller, together with references to the Orders in whichase provisions are contained, are set forth in Appendix A.  4. Apart entirely from express provisions to  the effect that sales shall be made nett weight, it is to beerved that the effect of the  Food Controllers  orders in fixing maximum prices  by reference to weight; necessarily put upon the dealer  the obligation of supplying full nett  weight for articles sold wherehas charged the maximum price.   The  practice  of charging the maximum  price is  almost  universal.effect, therefore, the regulations of the Food  Controller (which have covered about 90 per cent, of thelicles of food commonly consumed) have resulted in dealers becoming accustomed to sell nett weight.  5. Resolution I. On this head the following resolution was passed by the Sub-Committee :       We strongly request that the Food Controller impress upon the Government and Parliament the          necessity of continuing, in the form of permanent legislation, the regulations made by  him          relating to the sale by nett weight of the articles mentioned in Appendix A., viz.:               Tea, bread, jam, beans, peas  and pulse, wheat, rye, oats and barley, potatoes, canned                   meat,  horse mixtures and poultry mixtures and cattle  feeding  stuffs (other  than                   wet brewers&apos; and distillers&apos; grains).                     B. COMPULSORY SPECIFICATION  FOR CERTAIN  ARTICLES.  6. In  regard  to certain foods the Food Controller  has required  certain articles  to  conform  withscified standards of quality with the  object of securing to the general consumer that a proper articlesupplied.  The reasons for such action and the nature of such action are stated in Appendix (B).  7. Resolution II. On this head the following resolution was passed by the  Sub-Committee :                                       *                               -      (a)  The Sub-Committee approves of the regulations laid down by the Food Controller prescribing             certain standards of quality for the following articles :                  Compound lard, vegetable butter,  vegetable lard, shredded  suet, dripping, jam, cocoa-                   powder, and margarine.               The Sub-Committee  are of opinion that such regulations be maintained  in  the  form             of permanent legislation.      (b)  With regard to margarine, the Sub-Committee  suggest that the first and  second standard of             margarine should be  certified  by  Government  analysis  and  imprimatur,  and no  other             margarine should he allowed to he sold.      (e)  With regard to sausages, the  existing standards are                               $                (i)  ,Sausages containing not less than 67 per cent of meat or  pork;  and               (ii)  Sausages containing not less than 50 per cent, meat or pork;             and the Sub-Committee suggest  that no other sausages should be allowed to be sold.                                           C-MILK.   8. In our opinion, the question of  the conditions under which liquid milk is produced and distributed one of  the greatest urgency and importance.  By  the Milk and Dairies (Consolidation) Act,  1915, wideiwers were given to the Local Government Board  to  make Orders regulating  the conditions under whichilk should be sold  and distributed, the  object being  to  secure the observance of proper sanitaryeditions  in relation  to the  keeping of cows,  the prevention of  the sale of  tuberculous  milk, thestribution of milk under proper sanitary conditions,  and other kindred matters.   9. By an order of the  Food Controller  (see Appendix C.) and  under arrangements made with the )asury,  milk  may be provided at  less than cost price to nursing and expectant mothers, and to children der the age of five  years.   Under arrangements made  with  the Treasury, half of the loss falls on the easury and half upon  the local rates.   10. By the Maternity and Child Welfare Act of 1918, a local authority  is empowed  to  make ch arrangements  as the Local Government Board may  sanction for attending to  the health of expectantothers and nursing mothers, and of children who  have not attained the age of five years, and who are not   m  (37)7410  Wt 42726-1938 575 2/19  E &amp; S                                                     A
educated in schools recognised by the Board  of  Education.  The expenses of any such &quot;arrangements mupon the Local Authority.     11, In our opinion it would conduce to more effective provision being made for expectant and nursinomothers and young children  if the cost under permanent legislation fell, at any rate as  to part, upon tiTreasury, rather than that the whole cost should fall upon the Local Authority.     12. The activities of the Food Controller&apos;have also assumed another form.  We refer to the contJof the wholesale milk trade by the Food Controller.   The activities of the Food Controller in such conyhave necessarily been hampered and confined within narrow limits by the absence of any declared policy oJthe part of the Government relating to the permanent control of the milk trade.                        I     13. RESOLUTION III. On this head the following resolution was passed by the Sub-Committee :    J          We  approve of the work being  done by the Food Controller, and are of  opinion that it jj               absolutely necessary  to  exercise  national and municipal control  over  the supply anl               distribution of milk.                                                                 J                                        D.-TESTING OF  SEEDS.     14. The Food Controller has  made an Order (SEE Appendix C.) requiring certain farms and gardeJseeds to comply with specified requirements as to purity and  germination.   A statement by Mr. Weave]Controller of Supplies in the Food Production  Department  of Board of  Agriculture, is included j]Appendix 0.     15. RESOLUTION IV. On this head the following resolution was passed by the Sub-Committee: -  (          In the opinion of this Sub-Committee  it is desirable that the testing process embodied  in til               Order be made part of the permanent legislation of the country, and.  if possible, extended I                                     E. EXHIBITION OF NOTICES.                                  J     16. Many  of  the  Orders of the Food  Controller provide for  the  exhibition  by a retailer of  tilmaximum price and, in some cases, of the actual prices applicable to goods sold by him.     In  the opinion  of the  Sub-Committee this is an  elementary  and  a proper  safeguard  to  tJconsumer. .    17. RESOLUTION V. On this head the following, resolution was passed by the Sub-Committee:    !        . This Sub-Committee  is of opinion that, so far as  is reasonably  possible, the price of staji              articles of food sold  in any shop shall  be exhibited in a place where  it is easily visible til              customer.                                    II.-NATIONAL KITCHENS.     18. The facts relating to the establishment of National Kitchens and their work are well known totibody of the Customers&apos;  Council, and it is not thought necessary to restate any of such facts.     19. RESOLUTION VI. On this head the following resolution was passed by the Sub-Committee : ,          This Sub-Committee approves  of the establishment of  National Distributing  Kitchens an!              National Restaurants, and is of opinion that the system should be continued and extended,                    III-DEMOBILISATION  OF  THE MINISTRY  OF  FOOD.     20. The Sub-Committee have taken into consideration the questions arising out of the possible cessatiof the activities of the Ministry of Food in relation to  the control of food.     In  their fullest form those activities have  embraced the importation  of foodstuffs, the control oidistribution - among traders,  the  limitation of  consumption  by individuals, the  fixing of  prices, andrestriction upon use for specified purposes.                                , IY.-IMPORTS BY  THE  STATE.     21. The general question, of the State retaining  the sole right to import essential foodstuffs presentsroomfpr considerable differences of opinion.   The question  is one of national organisation and ultimatelyof international organisation.  It does not stand as a  question  by itself  and  is  intimately linked with thequestion of the State control of shipping, the  possibility of effectively controlling food trusts,  and the limits of co-operative action.   Obviously., in the event of the food trusts extending their operations to all markets,the only possible means of meeting this combination is by the actfion of the State.     22. The Sub-Committee  do not profess to  have examined this subject in  all its bearings.  Up01certain  aspects of  the  subject they  have, however, come to definite conclusions.   First A monopoly^State purchase of imported  foodstuffs would in  their opinion be a powerful weapon not only against aforeign trust but also  against a shipping ring.  Second In times of  fluctuating  prices, State purchasewould secure the importation of articles when a private  trader would be loth to incur the risks invol^Third-When the article is scarce or  there is even a small excess of  demand over supply or  there ISMfor any reason, effective competition between dealers,  prices are apt to rise  to  an inordinately high leyeHa level out of all proportion to the amount of the deficiency.  Our experience is that where there is $1shortage, control of prices without control of  distribution is of little, if of any, use,  and that the best waytojachieve effective distribution is for the State to have the right to exercise control by reason of its owners&apos;Jof the articles controlled.                                                                       -  *     23. RESOLUTION VII. Upon this head the Sub-Committee have passed the following resolution:-&apos;        That the Government  should continue  to purchase and import essential foodstuffs  from overseas,             and should  take all necessary  steps through the control of  imported foodstuffs to maW8!11!             supplies and control prices.
oo;srsiaitedV.-INTERNAL CONTROL,   24. The problem of the removal of internal control presents for solution matters in respect of whichhere is no past experience to act as a guide.   25.  It is obvious that until there is  a  reasonable  certainty that an adequate supply of food is assurednd that freedom from  control will not  impair equitable distribution at a reasonable price, control should,I the opinion of the Sub-Committee, remain.   Further, so long as the State acts as the sole  or mainnporter of any article, control of prices and distribution should remain.   26.  Eesolution VIII. Upon the matters  now under consideration the Sub-Committee have passed thoallowing resolutions:    (a)  That coupon restrictions and other restrictions limiting consumption should not be retained after          it becomes reasonably certain, having regard to the state of supplies, that such restrictions can          be abolished without  fear of having to re-impose them.   (6) That registration  of customers should  continue for the present under arrangements whereby, at          short intervals,  the public have  the  unrestricted right  to change  their  registration either          generally or as to any particular rationed article.   (e) That registration of customers should  not be abandoned until supplies are fully sufficient.   (d) It is desirable  that the retail prices of all essential foodstuffs should be fixed so long as there is          any risk of  scarcity and while  present conditions exist, and that prices should  also he  fixed for          such food stuffs as are from time to time being imported by the State.GENERAL.t!iin   27. In an interim  report the Sub-Committee  expressed  two general conclusions at which they had unanimously arrived, which were as follows:    (a) Resolution IX. The effectiveness and beneficial results of control (including control of  transport)          have been manifest in keeping the price of commodities at a reasonable level  to the  consumer,          and  the Sub-Committee will accordingly go more  fully into the whole matter with a view to          bringing definite proposals before the Consumers&apos; Council for the co-ordination of the different          departments affecting the well-being of the people.   (6) That this Sub-Committee, while strongly in favour of  abrogating forthwith all the measures which      ,    have been  enacted under the Defence of the Realm Act in restriction of  personal freedom of          every kind, expresses its opinion that it would be a great misfortune to the country if the          admirable service rendered by the Ministry of Food and its various committees were put an end          to, the Sub-Committee being firmly convinced that co-ordination in production and distribution          under central control  has proved exceedingly advantageous to the whole community during the          war, and will prove equally to their advantage in time of peace.   This policy should therefore          he continued and developed as part of the national interest.   28. The Sub-Committee regret  that time has not permitted of their following up the question, of the -ordination of the activities of the different Government Departments as proposed in Resolution IX. (a).   29. The Sub-Committee reiterate the view expressed in  Resolution IX.(6).   Apart from  this,  they desire to express their strong view that  the time has not yet come  for the wholesale removal of control.Before an  adequate  supply of foodstuffs can  be said to be assured the exact position of the belligerentsremains to be settled and known ; before  direct  State action in importation and distribution of  foodstuffsan be dropped, it is necessary to have  ready an effective weapon with which to deal with food trusts.The Sub-Committee cannot predict the  course  of future events,  but  in  their opinion it would be a grave danger to  the community if in the circumstances now obtaining,  the powers and activities of the Ministryof Food were lessened, or if the efficiency of the Ministry was in any way diminished.m  7410                                                                                  A 2
APPENDICES.                     APPENDIX  A.                     NETT WEIGHT..    (i) The Tea&quot;(Nett Weight) Older No. 318  of 1917.-TEA.It  was provided (1st July 1917)  that tea  sold by  retail inquantities of 2 ozs. and over shall he sold nett weight  andin multiples of ozs. or lbs.  This Order  is still in force.    (ii) The Breai Order No. 547 of  1918.-BREAD.   It  was provided  by the Bread Order, 1917,  that from and after the12th March 1917 all bread should  be  sold  by weight  andnot otherwise, and that no loaf  of bread should be sold oroffered for sale  unless  its weight  were  1 lb.  or an evennumber of pounds.  Both these provisions  are continued inthe Bread Order, 1918, and are now in force.    (iii) Jam (Prices)  Order No. 2, 1918, No. 930 as amended by  No. 1070 of 1918. JAM.  Prices  have been fixed for jamto  be sold  by weight in the usual, one pound and othercontainers since the 20th August 1917.  In the  schedule tothe latest Order it is made clear  that  these prices, bothwholesale and retail, are for nett weights of jam.   The Orderfixed the price for sale by wholesale &quot; where the  containerholds &quot; 1  lb.,  2 lb., 3 lb., 7 lb. and over  7 lb., per lb., ami  byretail &quot;where the  container holds &quot; 1  lb., 2 lb., 3 lb., 7  lb.,with  a provision in each case  that if  sold  in  a  containerholding  a  quantity  not  specified  in the  schedule  themaximum price is to be at the rate per lb. applicable to sales in a  container holding the next higher  quantity specified,and further, in the case of a retail sale, that the rate  per lb.when the container holds more than 7 lbs.,  is to be at  the,1b.  rate.  For sales by retail without a container  prices are fixed  for  weights of  1 lb., ij lb., h  lb. and ^ lb. of jam,and when the quantity sold is  not  an  even    lb., -J lb., or  lb., the price is  to be at the rate  provided  on the  sale offib.    (iv) Beans, Peas and Pulse (Retail Prices) Order No. 511of 1917. BEANS,  PEAS  AND  PULSE.   Certain beans, peasand pulse.set out in the schedule to the Beans, Peas  andPulse (Retail Prices) Order shall be sold only by weight.    (v) Grain  (Prices)  Order No. 1090  of 1918-WHEAT,RYE, OATS,  AND  BARLEY.  Whether  imported  or homegrown since 31st August 1917 shall be sold only by weight.This  is re-enacted in the Grain  (Prices) Order No. 1030,clause 10.    (vi) Potatoes  (Consolidation)  Order No. 1428 of 1918. POTATOES (since 15th September 1917), except where a groweris selling potatoes in  the  ground,  shall  be sold  only  by.weight.  This is re-enacted  in the Potatoes (Consolidation)Order, clause 4.    (vii) Canned Meat (Nett Weight)  Order No. 598 of 1918. CANNED  MEAT.  The  Order  provides  that  after 31stAugust 1918 canned meats are not to  be sold except in  acontainer  labelled with the nett weight of the meat therein.    (viii) Horse and Poultry Mixtures  Order No. ,1173   of1917. Horse  mixtures  and  poultry mixtures  since 22ndNovember 1917 shall  be sold only  by weight.  Horse   and poultry Mixtures Order, clause 2.    (ix)  Cattle  Feeding   Stuffs  (Maximum  Prices)  order no. 173  of 1918. Cattle feeding   stuffs  (other  than   wetbrewers&apos;  and  distillers&apos;  grains)  since  9th  February 1918shall be sold only by weight.                    APPENDIX B.   (i) Fats. Full particulars of what has been done will befound in the report of the Director of Oils and Fats Section,Mr. Mansfield, together with his views on permanence.                       Margarine.   In  order  to  arrange a freight programme it  has  been necessary to insist  on a standard  specification for  eachmanufacture.  It is not, however, advisable to continue thisspecification  as  a post-war measure.   Each manufacturerprefers to choose his own materials according to quality and price.  Apart from the provisions of the Pood  and DrugsAct stipulating that margai&apos;ine  shall  not contain  more  than16 per cent,  of water there  is  no standard  of quality.Unfortunately,  the standards  depend on taste  and smell,for which  there  are no tests other than an expert  tester.My branch has upheld the quality of margarine by  submittingsamples each week to experts, and communicating  the results to each manufacturer.  I suggest that the quantity of water should be limited to 16 per cent., as at present, and  preser. vatives  limited  to 0&apos;5  per  cent.,  the remainder  beino pure fat.                     Compound Lard.    We have had a  standard  specification of  compound larj consisting  of 50  per  ceiit.  animal fats and  50  per cent, deodorised cottonseed oil.   In tins case also the test of quality depends  on taste and smell.  I  suggest that tlij quantity of water should be limited to 015 per  cent, and free fatty acids to 0&apos;5 per cent.                Vegetable  Butters and Lard.    Although  we  fixed a  standard specification  for these articles, this was arranged  in order that we could fix a price to  the consumer.   It will  not be possible to  continue this after control  is  relaxed.   There should, however,  be a limitation  of  moisture  and  free fatty  acids: Vegetal) butters,  1*5 per cent.,  vegetable lard,  0&apos;25 per cent,, ol moisture and free fatty acids not  to exceed 0 - 5 per cent, in either case.                      Shredded Suet.    This is  a proprietary article manufactured at present three firms.  It consists of animal fat and  rice  flour.  Is order to  protect the consumer I suggest that  clause 7 of tie Shredded Suet Maximum  Prices  Order, No. 1030,  should be continued.  This stipulates that  shredded suet shall consist of 80 per cent, of beef premier jus or beef stearine or both, not more than 1  per cent, of  moisture, and the remaining ingredients to consist of  rice flour or  some  other cereal oi cereal product.  The object of this would  be  to prevent tie consumer being supplied with an undue quantity of rice flow at the price of animal fat.                        Dripping.    This  is an article where legislation  is  most  desirable. Dripping as  commonly understood  is  the fat  which drop from a roast of beef.  When  the Oils and Fats Branch tool control  we discovered that  the  vilest  tallow, which wl suitable  only  for  greasing axles,  was  being mixed witll inferior cottonseed  oil and  being sold extensively as drippiiiJ at 3s. Qd. per lb.  I consider it  to be  most  important tluA the great improvement we  have made in dripping should : 1 perpetuated by perpetuating clause 10 of the Home-Iell Tallow and Grease (Maximum Price) Order,  No. 636, WLIKLL stipulates that it shall be manufactured from raw beef factoil raw mutton  or beef  or mutton  hones, it shall have beeiH manufactured by a  process Other than the acid process, ail it should not  contain more than  1. per cent. of. water ail impurities taken together or  more than 2 per  cent, of felfatty acids.                                            J    When this order was made the trade protested that TFJ standard could not  be reached.  I  found samples of drippkB containing  as much as  10 to 12 per cent, of free fatty aciH It is rank  poison.  The whole trade  has now been able m produce  a  quality in accordance with  the specification \M down.    These articles are the finished. products.  I  have a hafi more ambitious scheme in  hand which  regulates qualities m raw materials, such as  seeds, crude oils and  refined oils :B fixed on standard tests.  I  do not know whether this  COBB within the  scope of your present  inquiry, but  I attach RE sample   contracts  which  are  now  being  considered m scientific and commercial committees connected  with B trades concerned.                      (Signed)    ALFRED  MANSFIEIAB    M. 6,30/11/18.                             -       I    (ii) The Jam Prices Order  No. 30  of  1918.-JAM. *B Order provides  a  standard of  quality  below  which jamgfl not be sold, and requires the labelling  of  jam so that c-m ponent parts of the mixture are stated  in the description!&apos;! the information of the consumer.                       I&apos;    Clause 7. In addition the Order requires  every contaiiB to bear the name and address  of  the manufacturer, and t-B guaranteed nett weight of the contents  when the containsB. not of the usual nett content size of 1 lb., 2 lb., &amp;c.     FB    The Report from the Director of Fruit Supplies and J*B (Mr. Martin) is as follows:                            ?    It is extremely desirable that  some  form of cowJM         should be  maintained as to the quality of jaffl^B         marmalade after the Orders now in force have t^B         withdrawn.                                 B
 The chief difficulty arises from  the fact that we have no       good definition of  the  word  &quot;jam.&quot;  Under the       Order it is stated that             &quot; Water Boluble extract  of jam shall not be         less than G3 per cent, of the total weight of such         jam.&quot; In  order to comply with this condition it would be       necessary that the jam shall  contain  a high  per-       centage of  sugar, which is not  necessary in a cheap       jam packed in hermetically sealed bottles  or  cans. I am  discussing  this matter with our technical advisers,       and will let you know if any better definition can       be suggested.                                   * It  is  greatly to be desired that the  weight  of  packages       should be  guaranteed, and  that every receptacle       should indicate the name of the manufacturer .and       the material from which the jam is made.  There is no doubt that regulations now in the Jam Order       have produced good ef ect on the quality of the jam       now in the market.                    (Signed)     CHARLES S. MARTIN.  (iii) Cocoa Powder ,No. 2) Order, 1302, of 1918.-OOCOAPOWDER, A standard  of  quality below which cocoa powdernay not be sold  is established by the Oocoa Powder (No. 2)Order, 1918, and provision also made for  the sale of a powdertontaining a still lower percentage of cocoa bean shell at  asmall increase in price.  (iv) Meat Retail Prices  (England   and Wales)  Order,Jfo. 2,1188, of 1918.-SAUSAGES AND SAUSAGE MEAT. Thenecessity for pxwiding an equivalent value  in meat contentwhen  fixing the price of sausages and sausage  meat  hasresulted in a grading being set up in this class  of foodstuffsivliich has  been  of advantage to  the consumer, and for the irst  time afforded  the public some guarantee of food value in these foods.   Sausages  and,  sausage meat  have  beengraded    (i) To contain not less  than 67  per cent, of meat or                                                pork.  (ii)       ,,                    50      ,,      meat or                                                pork.  (iii)       ,,     less than 50 per cent, of  meat or pork.  (iv)            no meat, except coupon-free edible offals.  Mr.  F. T. Boys, Director, Meat Supplies  Branch, has reported that they have endeavoured to maintain the grading set up in  the Order, and generally, no doubt, manufacturers kve  carried the Order  out, possibly  from  fear of being letected in some way if  they failed.  There is no difficulty so far as the trade is concerned  in putting the required meat into  sausages except that the manufacturer,  though pro- riding the correct percentages of meat, may sometimes be prejudiced by the  action of the  machinery not maintaining throughout all the sausages a uniform mixture.  In a few eases taken before the courts for breach of the percentage provisions, the Enforcement Branch have met with difficulties of proof of contravention.  The analysts employed  have not been able  satisfactorily. to determine by analysis the meat content, at  any rate with a confidence sufficient to secure conviction.  This point of expert evidence is a serious one.   The Meat Section are taking further advice from the Society of Analysts on the matter, as the advantage to the consumers  in haying i guaranteed meat  content in  the  sausages sold  is  so manifest.                   APPENDIX  0.  Mill (Mothers  and Children) Order, No. 189, of  .1918,-MILK.  This Order empowers local authorities to arrange,ind when required by the Local Government Board compelsthem to arrange, for the  supply of food  and  milk forexpectant mothers  and nursing mothers, and  of  milk for children  under five  years of age  under certain conditionswhich are laid down.                    APPENDIX D.   The  Touting of Seeds Order, No. 1156, of 1917 (revolted).j.he Testing  of Seeds Order, No. 648, of 1918. TESTING OFSEEDS, Before the war there was no State guarantee inGreat Britain with reference either to the purity of germi-nation of farm or garden seeds, and the matter was left tothe trade.  Only a few of the largest houses carried out ina scientific manner the cleaning  and testing of seeds.   Inother cases the methods employed (if any)  did not justifythe advertised claims of the trader.   So far as Great Britain is concerned we were behind someother countries  (including  some  of the Dominions) in thematter of the protection of the  public against the sale ofimpure seeds.   The report of Mr. Weaver, Controller of  Supplies, PoodProduction Department, is  as follows:                   Testing of Seeds Order.   In reply  to your inquiry I am  authorised by the Presi-deut of the Board  to say that  he is most  anxious  that theTesting of Seeds Order shall be confirmed by legislation.   The operation of the Order during the present year hasbeen  of the  utmost benefit to (a) the farmer, \b) the allot-ment holder, (c) the honest seedsman.  We have evidence onall sides from farmers that the certainty which they have  of getting good seed, which is given them  by the declaration with seedsmen have to make as  to purity and germination,is preventing what often happened in times past, namely,the partial or total failure of crops  resulting  from the use ofunguaranteed seed. -    The allotment holders  and cultivators of small gardenshave been specially at the mercy of the seed trade, becausethey  did not  ordinarily  obtain  their supplies from  theimportant houses, who have for many years sold their seedsunder a guarantee, but from  small retailers who, howeverhonest they may have been in intention,  had no knowledge of the goods that they were&apos;  handling, and, moreover,  con-stantly carried forward from year to year unsold stocks whichnaturally deteriorated very seriously.  I  may say that the Agricultural Wholesale  Society,  which has  undertaken thetask of supplying so many of the allotment holders associa-tions, have given an especial welcome to the Order.    The  feeling  of the  seed  trade  may be judged by the following extract from the annual.report of the Agricultural Seed Trade Association of  the  United  Kingdom, dated November 12th :-&quot; The new  &apos; Testing of Seeds Order, 1918 &apos; &quot; is  generally acknowledged to be  a fair  order  in  every &quot; respect, but it will also go far in raising the general status &quot; of the trade.&quot;    I might  add that  as  a result of  the  operation of the Order  a large quantity of clover seeds wore,  on  the Order coming into force, sold for feeding  cattle,  root seeds  were crushed for the same purpose, and grass  seed  was sold for poultry food, in all cases  because the holders of the seed would  not  have effected  a  sale  if  they had  declared the germination.  In days past such seed would have been mixed in with new and good seed to the  great disadvantage of the purchaser.    If I  can give  you any further information I shall be happy to do so.                        Yours sincerely,                    (Signed)     LAWRENCE WEAVER,                                  Controller of Supplies. A. Andrewes TJthwatt, Esq.,      Ministry of Pood.

</content>
</cab>
