<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 471-473</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
A3           MEAT SITUATION.Note by the President of the Board of Trade,          I circulate a memorandum whioh has been prepared     for me by sir Thomas Robinson on the above subject, and     I should be glad if it could have the early consideration     of the War Cabinet,                                  A, H. STANE33Y,3oaJ?d of Trade,     11th February, 1919,                             ...                 Memorandum by Sir Thomas Robinson,     ;  ,                Meat Situation.     *e-*wa*rWW          The high prices of food is beyond doubt one of the     principal causes of the existing Industrial unrest,          The hardship of dear food will he felt more&apos;severely     as the out-of-work payments cease and demobilisation pro-     ceeds, and as regards meat especially so by returned soldiers     hitherto accustomed to the Army ration of ff IK of meat     ger day  and suddenly reduced to the civilian ration of     19&apos; o&quot;zs per week.     IWIII, i, II mm i in ........n          The Ministry of Pood can well afford to increase the     civilians meat ration and reduce the price of meat, end     in the public interest this should he done promptly,          INCRBASSjO? R&amp;TION.  If Army consumption were main-     talnecTaS pre-moTSZaaETon figures, and ^civilian ration     maintained et present figures the reserve stocks of     imported meat in store (which now stand at afrout 96.000     tons) while falling as the year advances, would at the     end of  June next be over 59,000 tons.          Between January anil June, as the result of demobilisa-     tion, Army consumption will decroase by about 90,000 tons.     This, added to the 59,000 tons above referred to, shows a     total surplus supply of 140/150,000 tons, or more than our     total refrigerated meet warehouse accommodation.          3?rora  July onwards increasing quantities of meat will     be arriving from Australasia, and homegrown fat stock     will then also &quot;become available.          Consequently ronless the public are allowed to eat more     meat our stores will again beoorae so congested that meat     steamers will he unable to discharge their cargoes.
      IF IT should&amp;E -FOUND  THAT HERE MEAT IS REQUIRED THIS OOULD BO PROVIDED BY POSTPONING INTENDED SHIPMENTS OF RABBITS,      PRICJJ. &apos; ANY AUSTRALASIAN MEAT FOUND TO BE IN EXCEED OF ARMY REQUIREMENTS,  IS TRANSFERRED BY THE BOARD OF TRADE TO  THE  MINISTRY OF POOD AT COST PRICE, VIZ. JLOD, PER LB. FOR LAMB AND 8ID PER LBI FOR MUTTON.  THE MINISTRY OF FOOD SELL THIS  TO WHOLESALERS AT IS 3D PER LB 4 AND SO MAKE A PROFIT  OF  OD PER LBI (OR SAY ABOUT 50$) ON ALL SUCH MEAT.      OVERFEEDS GOVERNMENTS AND PRODUCERS HAVE ALWAYS PROTESTED AGAINST THE MAKING OF SUCH PROFITS BY THE MINISTRY OF POOD, AND THEY STRONGLY URGE THAT THE CONSUMER SHOULD BENEFIT BY THE MODERATE PRICE AT WHICH THOY i SELL THE MEAT TO THE IMPORIAL GOVERNMENT,      THE TRADE MEAT IMPORTED FROM THE BIVER PLATE IS COMMANDEERED ON ARRIVAL; THE MINISTRY OF POOD PAY IMPORTERS 10-GD AND RE-SELL (WHOLESALE) AT 14JD PER LB. MAKING A PROFIT THEREON OF ABOUT 35J&amp;     AS THE DEMOBILISATION PROCEEDS, THE POOD CONTROLLERS. PROFITS ON MEAT WILL BE MATERIALLY INCREASED, BECAUSE A CONSIDERABLE PROPORTION OF THE 90,000 TONS OF ARMY MEAT NOW BECOMING AVAILABLE FOR CIVILIAN CONSUMPTION WILL BE THE BOARD OF TRADE CONTRACT BEEF FROM THE RIVER  LATE, WHICH COSTS 8D PER LB. LANDED IN THIS COUNTRY.  IF PRICES ARE NOT REDUCED AND THIS MEAT IS TAKEN OVER BY THE POOD CONTROLLER AND SOLD TO WHOLESALERS AT THE SAME PRICE AS THE LATTER NOW PAY FOR SIMILAR RIVER PLATE (TRADE) MEAT THE POOD CONTROLLERS PROFIT WILL BO 6D PER LB. OR ABOUT 80/J,   THE POORER CLASSES WOULD NATURALLY REGARD THIS AS PROFITEERING AND APART FROM ALL OTHER CONSIDERATIONS, A  PROPER REGARD FOR PHYSICAL CONDITIONS OF OUR PEOPLE SHOULD PROMPT A BETTER RATION AND A REDUCTION IN THE PRICE OF MEAT AT THE EARLIEST POSSIBLE MOMENT.     THE LARGE PROFITS MADE BY THE MINISTRY OF POOD ONAUSTRALASIAN ANA SOUTH AMERICAN IMPORTED MEAT ARE NOW BECOMING KNOWN TO THO PUBLIC, AND HOSTILE CRITICISM HAS APPEARED IN THE PRESS.     AS, THE PURCHASE OF NORTH AMERICAN MEAT HAS NOW CEASED AND INCREASING QUANTITIES OF CHEAPER AND BETTER MEAT FROM OUR OTHER SOURCES OF SUPPLY ARO  NOW AVAILABLE;.FOR CIVILIAN CONSUMPTION IT APPEARS TO ME THAT THE TIME HAS COME FOR A DRASTIC REVISION OF THE PRICES CHARGED TO THE TRADE, AS WELL AS  OF THE MAXIMUM RETAIL PRICES.(2)
     A REDUCTION IN THE PRICE OF IMPORTED MEAT will of COURSE AFFECT THE PRICE OF HOME-KILLED MEAT,  ANDIT APPEARS TO ME THAT AS A MATERIAL REDUCTION in price OF MEAT SEEMS TO BE INEVITABLE IN THE AUTUMN.IF NOT BEFORE.   A COMMENCEMENT SHOULD BE MADE SOONAS A GRADUAL REDUCTION WOULD BE LESS DISTURBING TOTHE BRITISH PRODUCERS THAN A SUDDEN FALL, SUCH as might TAKE PLACE SHOULD GOOD SUPPLIES OF GRASS-FEDHOMEGROWN CATTLE COME TO market SIMULTANEOUSLY with increased QUANTITIES OF FROZEN MEAT ACCUMULATED INAUSTRALASIA DURING THE WAR.   THIS IS A MATTER WHICHCONCERNS THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES,(SIGNED)  T.B.  R03INS0N.

</content>
</cab>
