<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 484-485</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

SECRET.

G.T.6784

WAR CABINET.

PEACE CELEBRATIONS.

Official Secretary, Commonwealth of Australia to Colonial Office.

Australia House.

20th. December, 1918.

Sc. 410/5/1.

Sir,

    I am directed by the High Commissioner to ask whether you will be good enough to supply me with full particulars regarding any arrangements that may be made for holding services etc., in connection with the celebration of Peace, in order that advice may be furnished to the authorities in Australia, who are anxious to know what is being done here.

For your information I have to inform you that arrangements are being made to hold in Australia, a three days&apos; programme on the official declaration of Peace, as follows:-

On the first day, thanksgiving services in all churches and chapels throughout Australia, uniform as far as possible, and special undenominational services in the parks and gardens with naval and military bands, and philharmonic and choral societies.

Second day; salutes, naval and military marches, processions, pageants, exhibitions of war trophies, decorated buildings, triumphal arches, bands and street chairs, led by philharmonic and choral and theatrical societies; in the evening, illuminations, carnival processions in masquerade and charade costumes.

Third day; children&apos;s exhibitions in sports grounds and parks, tableaux, aquatic reviews, rogattas, aeronautical displays; in the evening, illuminations, street carnivals and fireworks displays. A souvenir medal is to be issued to every child,

I am, etc.

(Sd.) E.A. BOX.



Colonila Office to Official Secretary,

Commonwealth of Australia.

Downing Street,

30th. December, 1918.

Sir,

    I am directed by Mr. Walter Leng to acknowledge the receipt of your letter Sc.410/5/1 of the 20th. December, requesting information with regard to the arrangements that may be made in the United Kingdom for the celebration of Peace, and to request you to inform the High Commissioner that no arrangements have yet been made, but that his wishes will be borne in mind.

I am, etc.

(Sd.) HENRY LAMBERT.

P.T.O.

 
Official Secretary, Commonwealth of Australia to Colonial Office.

Australia House,

20th. January, 1919.

410/5/1 Mil.

Sir,

     I have the honour, by direction of the High Commissioner, to refer to my letter dated 20th. December No.410/5/1 and to your reply of the 30th. December, No. 61941/1918, regarding arrangements which are to be made in connection with the celebration of Peace. A notice has appeared in the public press in issues dated 17th January, notifying that a rough programme has been drawn up which will be the basis of the celebrations, and it is further stated that the Royal approval has been given to certain of the proposals which have been made. From the newspaper reports to which I have referred, it appears that the celebrations are to be grouped under three headings, viz. Military Processional, Civil Processional and Regilious Ceremonies. It is possible that the reports appearing in the press will reach Australia, and in order that the Government may be in full possession of all arrangements which may be approved, the High Commissioner will be very much obliged if he can be kept in close touch with developments.

I have, etc.

(Sd.) E.A. BOX.

2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.

12th, February, 1919.



 

</content>
</cab>
