<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/74/0 images: 498-501</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
      Document is the Property of                353His Britannic tV&amp;jeety-o Government,VA.fr, IWLI  *.BIOOKAEB RESTRICTIONS ON EXPORTS.Koto by the President of ths  Board ef  Trade.     With reference to  my memorandum of January 18th(GrtT.6682) regarding export restrictions  to blood&amp;adedcountries, I circulate^ h^a with  a memorandum on thesubject by Lord Bmmott.   I should be glad if thismemorandum sould be considered by ifoe War Cabinettogether with    memorandum of January 18th.                                 A. H. MMIM.Board of Trade,     11th February,  1919.(0
   .  The following observations apply to the memorandumrespecting the continuance.of  Uie Blockade issued by theForeign Of ii ce [;\0. 11214/1/1150) and the memorandum on export restrictions to blockaded countries by Sir albert stanley [War Cabinet G.T. 6682).  The Foreign Office da-si ras the continuance of  the ijlockade as  tie most efiec-tive weapon left to the Associated Powers for t speedilythreat of a cohtinuod Blockade (a threat which it is agreed must be modified in order to prevent the spread  .oi Bolshevism) is the convincing weapon that it is sup-posad to be?  i,Jould it not be ah equally efficientweapon to allow Germany to have some of&quot;her urgent needssupplied., with the continued threat hanging over her ofall ef tiie supplies to which she ;&apos;/as becoming accustomedbeing stopped in case she did net accede to our terms?Judging by the ineffectiveness of the threat of shortagecombined with actual shortage in neutrals adjacent tothe threat of complete stoppage would be as effieiont a weapon as absolute shortage to which people have becomeaccustomed.  In any ease^ the world its so short of goods and the vacuum in the Central Powers is so groat that itwould takj a long time to supply them with goods otherthan food, ra* materials and ammunition reouisites in3uch quantities as would materially break down the effectof the Blockade.  It should also be borne in mind thatGermany&apos;s purchasing power at the present moment is graat-ly restricted, owing to the undertaking given  by her tothe Entente not to part with securities etc.. until theIndemnities are settled.  The scheme of the foreign Office,seems to be one for supplying the neutral countries withgoods nearly.to the point of saturation an&amp; to importdirect to the Central Powers such commodities as seeni ne-cessary to restart their trade again^  I am not sure til atthe diifareacG between their scheme and that of -Sir Albert3tanley would turn out in practice to be so great as they-imagine, but it must be admitted that if woollen and cottongood3/ for instance, were to be put on the free lists forScandinavia, Holland and Switzerland, a ?$od deal wouldpercolate to the Central B&amp;tfers.  On the &quot;other hand, thescheme proposed of supplying Germany with food, raw mater-ials and certain manufactured commodities would probablyresult in most of the ^oods sent being food and raw mat-erials, and that British trade would relatively suffer byvery few manufactured goods being allowed to be sent. Inregard to manufactured&quot; goods, it is extraordinarily dif-difficult for the Allied Powers to arrange for the supply.They are liable to Quarrel amongst themselves as to vmois to sunply and what is to be su-oplied, and so causeendless delay.  The tendency of all Government buying isto insist on standardised commodities which perhaps arenot in existence.
The tendency of trade left to itself is for buyer andseller to agree to business on the basis of produitssimilaires, in case the actual thing which the buyerwants in not in exi3tenco at the moment.  Governmentbuying and provision is a clumsy method compared tothe actual process of buying am selling on the partof individual traders who are accustomsa to dealingwith each other on an individualistic basis.     It is important to remember the difference that shipping difficulties at the present time make asbetween&apos; Ansrica and Japan on the one ham and ourselves on the otiBr,  We are near the  iSuropoan markets,theyare near many of the mariots that wo supplied beforethe war.  Shipping difficulties  therefore, mean that america and Japan aro bettor able to supply our more distant markets aud tot we ought to be^better ableto supply the European markets *  This means that theEuropean markets aro for the  time being relativelymore important to us than they were belora fee war,and that if our export trade to them in manufacturedgoods is to be still greatly crippled for Blockadereasons, it is very difficult for us.to find the ne-cossary outlet for our oxportable surplus in rrarse&amp;smarkets further afield.     For these reasons it is apparent that the obser-vation on page 5 of the Foreign Office memorandum that ou&amp;.*trade with Northern neutrals forms at thepresent &quot;time only a snail part of our total exporttrade does not hold good.     In rofere nee to paragraph 4 of the   reign office memorandum, the iBefulness ot Allied tocuiivesand3?rogram Oenmitteec may haw Deen considerable during the war, &quot;but 30 far as purely British trade interestsin contrast with Allied interests are concerned theyhave been a crippling faotor, and the s&amp;onsr they can be  got rid of the better from the point of view oiBritish trade alone *     A good deal of stress is laid in the foreignOffice memorandum on the harmful results of rapidly increasing prices*  The danger seems to me to oequite in the other direction.  There ia a completehold up of trade at present in Ibis country in manytrays,  Thercondition of the cotton trade is absaluw-ly alarming.  All the factors of the case must be weighed together,  lack of orders and consequentunemployment is a very serious danger in this oountryat the present time, far more serious than that oxa probable increase in prices.  Personally I belieTethere is a much greater danger of a serious slump inprices and of trade becoming unprofitable than cimy dangerous increase of price and consequ^atdeleterious results.
     In. regard to another observation on the same page thatall the Associated Powers are on an equal footing since theBlockade restrictions apply equally all round, that is truein theory, hut in practice these Blockade Restrictions sofar as menufeotured gootf.s are concerned are undoubtedly a more serious obstacle to British trade than they are tothe trade of any of our Allies,   This is because the exigencies of the war. have for the present reduced Britishmanufacturing capacity of peaceful  articles while american and Japanese capacity for the production of such articlesis largely undirainished.   The consequence is that our competitors are in a much better position to promise neutral*immediate delivery and that they frequently secure the lion1..share of the ration for manufactured goods..   Prior to thewar our superior manufacturing capacity for export trade as compared with franee, America and   Japan ali!:e, andalso the distance of America and J&amp;pan from the NorthernNeutrals had enabled us to secure a predominant position.     On page 6 it is stated &quot;incidentally the Board ofTrade policy will have the dangerous result of building up an enteepfct trade in neutral countries to the lasting de-triment of British trade in particular71.   Seeing that before the war much of the trade with the Central Powerswas done through Holland and Belgium I do not think thatthis is a very vital consideration,   It really depends on shipping and London being the financial centre of the world.     In the memorandum by the General Staff, appendix B.,it is stated &quot;at the same time, in order to avoid the dangerof complete Bolshevism in Germany,,  food end raw material to start industries and prevent unemployment should be dis-tributed under the control of the Associated Powers&quot;,  Thatis true, but, at the same time, the food and raw materialdo not come from Great Britain to any considerable extentend manufactured goods do, and to supply them only withfood and raw material would prevent our selling.our surplusof manufactured goods and so lead directly to the slump in trade which I,so much dread.   This memorandum is writtenfrom the point of view of stimulating British export trade.Unless if $oods are to go at all manufactured goods are tobe sent to the Central Powers directly or indirectly, our trade rivals will benefit and we shell obtain little or no advantage.     There is one matter urgently requiring settlement.We seem to be at an impasse with the Americans in referenceto free goods versus controlled goods    not subject to ration,   I do hope the $ar Trade Board may be persuaded to accept  our suggestions as to expanding the free list,but if not do let us get abea  with the other arrangement and increse the number of unrationed prohibited goods,I think we might facilitate the machinery of export inthese floods by a plan which I am having enquired into.                                    E.                                       25/1/1919,

</content>
</cab>
