<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 6-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel I. Dallj Ism,(MIS gggJBag IS TOE J20EGS2T 03 HIS SKHUiHIC ix..Jj,oTl&quot;&apos;i OOTLEHlJiiaj)&apos;.&apos;BE 0 B E I.W A. P;0    3 I IT ii I.POOLIiiG-Oj? bUPPLIES jlOIi THE klLIES.See1,4668.Copy of correspondence between Lord I-ilner and Gen. Porshinff.(Circulated with reference to G,!1, 4668, and War Cabinet 426, Limite 5).(i)Copy of letter dated 29th Liay, 1918 from Lord miner to Sen , Pe rshin^Iliy dear General,Oolonol Dawes had&apos; handed me the memorandum of Hay 22nd, 1918,, signed by L, Clemonccau and yourself ,r    We have all been in hearty accord with your aim to co-ordinate, as far as possible, the use of facilities and the distribution of supplies among the allied Armies in France.    Doubts, however, have been expressed by our supply departments as to the extent to which a unification of supplies and facilities would be practicable,     I am glad to find, however, that these doubts have apparently arisen from a misunderstanding of the purpose and scope of your proposal.I now understand from your memorandum and Colonel Dawcs* explanations &quot;:-1,     rfhat your plan is intended to apply only to supplies and facilities of the armies in France,2.     1&apos;hat the avoidance of duplicate facilities in cloclps,warehouses end railroads, and the proper distribution of labour supplies, are among the things of immediate importance.     It is not intended that the proposed Board shall interfere with the rations or with the distribut-ing machinery of the respective armies, nor, indeed, with any other matters relating to their internal administra-tion.3eThat the requirement that the decision of the proposed Board shall bo unanimous has been introduced in order to leave each army free to determine whether the principle of co-ordination is or is not applicable in any given ease.     For instance, your army might have what scorned like a surplus of foodstuffs on hand, but which was not a real surplus because of your distance from&apos; your base and the period that must elapse before further supplies arrive,     (The same might be true in the case of our army, The representative of each army on the proposed 3oard is therefore left free to exercise his own judgment in voting on such questions.
4. That the decisions of the Board, when unanimous, are to be communicated, through proper Military channels, to the chiefs of the appropriate departments of the respective armies, and shall be given effect to Only through them.

If I am right in the above interpretation of your a views, I shall be happy to give the proposed system an immediate? trial and to nominate a representative on the Board. I assume that the Italians and Belgians will also be invited to be represented on it.

Yours sincerely,

(Signed). MILLER.

GENERAL J.J. Pershing.

(ii).

Copy of letter from Gen. Pershing to Lord Milner.

American Expeditionary Forces, Office of the Commander-in-Chief, France.

June 2, 1918.

Rt. Hon. Viscount Milner, G.C.B., Secretary of State for War, London, England.

My dear Lord Milner,

I was very glad to receive your letter of May 29th, Stati? your agreement to the proposed plan to co-ordinate, as far as possible, the use of facilities and the distriubtion of suppli? among the Allied Armies in France. The interpretation of my views, as set forth in your letter, is correct, and I hope th? you will be able to nominate a representative on the Board as soon as possible.

I have informed M. Clémenceau of your agreement to the pl? and have suggested to him that he invite the Italian and Belg? Governments to be represented on the Board.

Sincerely yours,

(signed). JOHN J. PERSHING.







</content>
</cab>
