<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 88-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
J-fQtyctc on effect of British projector gas prepared in______--- &amp;oeor dance with Jflinute 5 of VTar Cabinet 425of 4th June, 1S18.Twenty-four gas operations were carried out during the month of March, several of which were on a very extensive scale,Projector drums were fired into $ueant on the 12th Harch,   After this operation it was reported that streams ef ambulances were seen all day long leaving this sector,   $here has &quot;been no artillery activity on our part during the night of the Hth/l8th,   Our infantry also reported that large numbers of rats came over from the German lines and died in our tr entities *On the night of the 19th Haroh a projector attacic was carried out against 3t,Q,uentin,   A prisoner stated that 100 men were killed outright and 3Q0 more were seriously gassed, many of whom ver&amp; not expected to live.   The nhola staff of a regiment was killed,further information has been obtained regarding the results of earlier operations,   A gas attack was carried out with projectors and Stokes mortars in the  ens sector on the 27th July, 1917,   The 2nd Bn., 15&amp;th X,B*, had 00 men killed and many gaasedj the 3rd 3n,,&apos; of the same regiment had 76 casualties evacuated to hospital, of whom 30 died, besides a number of mm killed immediately   in the trendies,   2his confirms the statement made in a captured letter of a man of the x5otn $*Eest that one company had only 24 men left after this gas attach,A prisoner of the 85th R,X*8* stated that his regiment lost 50 men killed in a gas operation in the Qulant sector early in October, 1917,  We projected drums into this sector on the 7th October, I9l7,   The same prisoner had heard that hie regiment had suffered severely from cylinder gas attacks in the Angree sector in the summer of 1016.   Shis confirms the state-merit of another prisoner regarding the effect of our cylinder operations at Andres in June and July, 1C16,   (Gee &quot;Monthly Summary of Svidence of 35ffect of our G-aew September, 1617, in which it was mentioned that the 34th SUX,B,, belonging to the same division, had become a byword on account of their ^as losses),A projector and Stokes mortar operation carried out in the Lens sector onfthe 3rd December* 1917, caused 30 fatal casualties in each of the four companies of the 3rd Bn,, 1st ad, Res, Re^t,   !The supporting battalion had many gassed in&apos; addition,A report has been received that in November, 1S17, 3,500 Germans, who had died from gag poisoning, were buried at Bourses Cemetery,   (Dourges is seven miles 3, of  ens, and many gas operations have taken place in this sector,)A British signaller, who had been captured and escaped, had been told in English by his captor that the one thing the Germans feared fro:: the British was tlieir gas, because the Germans realized that their mask was not proof against it.On the night of the 16th July, I9l7, and on two previous occasions, projector drums were fired against trenoh positions in the Hooge sector held by the 46th R, X,R,, the 46th I.R. and the 53th  .I,R&apos;,, all regiments belonging to the 119thDivision,
Division.   The 2nd Company, 46th I.R., had 30  as casualties, anc^, the 1st Company a larger number, about oO ;?er cent, being fatal.  ^ (previous reports mention 200 dead in the 1st Battalion.)   A pioneer company, 230 strong, had come to work in the front line without their gas masks.   Only one man came out alive,   (See the &quot;Third Report on the Effects of our Gas,&quot; page 19; the 46th I.R, lost 100 dead from gas in June, 1917, and a further 100 in July, 1917.   Previous information shows that the 119th Division suffered 400 fatal -casualties from gas on the Ypres ffront in 1C17.)   Recently captured N,CrO&apos;s, who had been employed at the depots of these regiments in the summer of 1917, stated that 250 men left the reoruit   depot of the 53th I,R. in June, 400 men in August, and 600 left the depot of the 46th I.R. in July.    (See the &quot; Third Report&quot;, page 20J draft of 400 to replace gas losses in the 46th I.R.)A Stokes mortar operation on the 8th November, 1917, .  -against the 77th R, I.R. and the 91st R.I.R., in the Armentieres sector, killed 25 men in the 2nd Company of the former regiment; the 91st R, Z.R, had over 200 men gassed, of whom 10 - 15 per cent, died.   One prisoner of the 77th R, I,R, stated that he would much rather go through an artillery bombardment than a gas-mine attack.The 470th IeR0 &quot;was subjected to a projector attaok on the 20th November, 1917, in the Riencourt sector.   One company oame out 3 strong; other companies suffered similarly,In the sector S.U. of Queant, 40 men of the 14th Bav. I.R, were killed and 100 gassed by our projector operations of the 12th March, 1918.   As an example of the constant attempts made by prisoners to minimize the effects of British gas, it may be mentioned that other prisoners of the same unit examined on the same day admitted that they had been through tills gas attack, and maintained that practical^- no casualties were caused.    (See &quot;Gas &quot;Tarfare&quot;, Ho. 9, March, 1918, page 3; streams of ambulances were seen leaving this sector.)A British prisoner of war, who escaped back to our lines on the 14th April, 1918, reported that he had been employed by the enemy in burying German dead in the neighbourhood of Lagnicourt on the 10th April, 1918,   He buried about 50 corpses himself and saw altogether about 200 bodies in this locality. The appearance of this batch of dead was quite different from that of the dead in other places.   He and all other men employed with him were convinced that these Were bodies of men who had been killed by gas.   It is possible that these were the corpses of men killed by our projector operations on the 12th March or the 17th March, 1918, in the Lagnicourt - Moeuvres - Queant sector.Confirmation has been received of the heavy losses suffered by German troops in St,Quentin in our projector attack of the 19th March, 1918.   (See &quot; Gas Warfare&quot;, No, 9; 100 dead, whole regimental staff killed,)On the 21st March, 1918, the 55th R.I.R, in Lens had 53 men killed besides a larger number of more or less serious casualties, as the result of our gas operation on tint date. Further evidence shows that this regiment alone, of. the 220th Division holding the Lens sector, suffered 400 gas casualties during its stay in the line,A very small operation with projectors was carried out against Duriez Farm, S/.7, of Warneton, at 11 p,m. on the 30th March, 1918,   On the following morning, the numerous stretcher cases were observed being taken away from this position.Stretcher bearers were also seen continuously at work during a period of three hours, along a road to a house,&apos; on themorning
morning succeeding a further projector and Stoke a mortar operation., on the 31st March, 1918, in the sswie sector,A prisoner of the 29th Reserve Infantry Raiment (l6th Reserve Division), captured on the 25th Kay near Serre, had the following entry in his diary:*wl2th March, 1918,* 400 gaff casualties in our regiment, Masks worn for over 2 hours, &quot;&quot;tn^li^h barrage accompanied by gas mines,wThis probably refers to our projector attack south of Moeuvres on the 12th March,The prisoner   states that the majority of oases occurred in the 1st Battalion, that none of the gas cases had reappeared by the 25th Kay, and that the strength of most of the companies in the 1st Battalion was reduced to 30 men.The prisoner, further states that they had had a considerable number of casualties from the effects of their yellow cross gas blowing back over their lines,   Host of these were eye cases,A prisoner of the 8?th Reserve Infantry Regiment (2lst Reserve Division) states that, in the Cambrai sector about the middle of Maroh, 1918, his regiment suffered 300 gas casualties, including a percentage of dead, and that only one man had returned from hospital.These casualties were probably caused by our projector attackB south of Moeuvres on the 12th and 17th Maroh,General Staff, \?ar Office.12th June, 1918,

</content>
</cab>
