<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 207-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Ihis Document Is-the Property tf(cvC*.tt Jw*His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government)Victoria 82d0. &quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;................&quot;&apos;&quot; ............     TitynmUmV&apos;^^^ Sowkst, Londox.156BOARD OF AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.To avoid delay, address all communications toFOOD  PRODUCTION   DEPARTMENT.The Director General.72, Victoria Street,London, S.W. (.1)12th June, 1918, Sir.,I beg to submit the following Report on the work of the Food Production Department for the week ended Juno 11th,1913The weather,The weather has continued fine and by tho end of the week rain was badly wanted throughout most of the country.All crops except fruit are, however, still looking well for. the time of year.     Potatoes promise excellently, and tho root outlook is generally good,     Allotment crops are reported as most promising.LOCAL 0RGAin.SATT.0K DIVISION. Agricultural Executive Committees, Essex. The Committee have been authorised to take possession of a farm of 77 acres&apos; at Bradwell which had recently been purchased by a private in an Agricultural Company who has no capital and insufficient experience to work the farm.     It contains 21 acres of arable and 10 more acres are to be broken up. Prosecutions.   The results of a number of prosecutions which ,were undertaken at the -expiry of the period for ploughing for the 1918 harvest have been reported this week.      Justices in various parts of the country appear to consider that a fine of  20 or  25 and costs is sufficient punishment for negligent or
wilful non-compliance with an order to plough up grass land in cases in which there are neither aggravating nor mitigating circumstances.    Penalties of this nature have been inflicted in five cases in Somerset, one of which was for non-compliance with order to clean and crop with potatoes 2 acres of potato land, thj rest being for failure to plough up grass land,, Determinationiof Tenancies. - During the week 2 Orders have beenl made by the Department determining tenancies on account of bad farming in respect of 239 acres.HORTIOWORAL DIVISION. Provislqn^of Land for Allotments - Reports received from 1,168 districts show that 306,058 applications have been made for plots under the Cultivation of &amp;ands Order, 1917 (No.2), and that 279,495 plots containing 20,104 acres have been provided.During the week seven Local Authorities have undertaken to acquire in all 32 acres (39*i allotments), in addition to the d mentioned above.At the Park Royal Munition Works 50 acres are under cultivation and very satisfactory results are being achieved. Repo: from other Munition Works indicate that good progress is being madi in the cultivation of allotments, and tfctat the crops are looking well.,&apos;.Fruit Section - Basket making centres have been established in Ken; and at Hull disabled soldiers are being trained in this work.   At the Belgian workshops at Sur-biton and Hammersmith good progress is being made, 800 baskets for the Ministry of Food having already been turned out from the latter Factory.During the week 137 demonstrations in bottling, canning and drying have been given.   At Norwood a very successful exhibition was held, which was attended by 2,250 people.   The numbe of orders received for jars by the Glassware Supply Department of the Ministry of Munitions now totals 6-J millions.-2-
Arrangements have been made for the Midland and Great Northern Joint Railway to run a special train daily between Peter-borough and Wisbech during the fruit-picking season, while the Great Northern and the Great -Eastern Railways have agreed to take 50 and 175 pickers per day respectively to this district. Small Live Stock * The National Utility Rabbit Association has now been organised with Lord Lambourne as President.   Temporary offices have been taken and arrangements are being made -for the establish-ment of a Central Rabbit Station at Neasden.The Departments scheme for the increase of rabbit keeping is arousing great.interest.   The Inspector in Yorkshire.reports that several of the principal rabbit breeders are very favourably &apos; disposed to the scheme, and that the Local Authorities can be of great assistance in rearing, as in many cases they have already suitable buildings and efficient staff to undertake the work.A Leaflet on &quot;Rabbit keeping In War time&quot; will beavailable for circulation in.the course of a few days.Marketing - The following statement shows the present position asregards the formation of Marketing Organisations in the Counties1)   Counties which have registered Societies   ...    .... 62)   Counties in which Societies are in course of formation 18 (3)   Counties which have made arrangements for Marketing,but not as yet by registered Societies          ... 7(4)   Counties which have arranged for local Markets   ..... 3(5)   Counties considering preliminary organisation    ... 4 (6)   Counties which have decided with other counties ona federated scheme.........     .....    &apos;... 6Complete information as to the remaining counties is notavailable at present.Vegetable Marrows for Jam.- The Department has issued a notice urging the cultivation of vegetable marrows for jam making to supplement the short supplies of soft fruit.   Copies of cultural notes on the growing o  this vegetable have also been issued.   As an immediate result one firm which had put- out 4 acres under marrows immediately ordered 6 further acres to be planted and is raising 10,000 plants: in pots under glass. -
TECHNICAL DIVISION. Crimson Clover for Silage. A visit has been paid to a farm n Bishopfs Stortford where a silo 30 ft. x 20 ft. was being fllle^ with crimson clover by means of a stack-elevator fitted with horse-gearing. The clover, cut in the morning, was being carted and elevated in the long condition in the afternoon. Crimson clover is not generally grown for conversion into silage, but it the South of England it possesses many advantages for this purpc It is easily and cheaply grown, being merely broadcasted on the stubbles in autumn and harrowed in. It is fit for cutting earl] in June, thus giving time for a following crop of roots or a bastard fallow. Moreover, it is&apos;probable that it is a safer anc more satisfactory feed in the form of silage than In the form of Collection of Indigenous Grass Seeds. Arrangements are being ma for the harvesting of substantial quantities of certain varietiei of indigenous grass seeds this year for the purpose of testing their value in plot trials compared with ordinary commercial see There are reasons for supposing that the indigenous seeds will t more valuable than commercial varieties in the preparation of short leys. It is proposed to confine the scheme this year to I the collection of cocksfoot, timothy, meadow foxtail, tall oat I grass, rough-stalked meadow grass, and the fine-leaved fescues. I An endeavour will be made to secure supplies from Devon, North Wales, Hampshire,/Yorkshire, Cambridge and Hertfordshire. Plant Diseases. During the week 75 cases of attack by insect 50 by fungus pests have been investigated and remedial, measures advised. Special attention is being paid to the fungus disease of the onion crop. There has been an outbreak of caterpillars o the Antler Moth in the moorland pastures of Yorkshire, and reporg have been received of a similar outbreak in South Wales. The I districts are being visited by an Inspector of the Department anjr
by honorary correspondents of the Technical Committee in order that any necessary measures may be taken to prevent the caterpillars from spreading to cultivated land.LABOUR DIVISION. Recruiting;;, The Ministry of National Service are preparing, In consultation with this Department, an Instruction which will consolidate all the existing Instructions with regard to agriculture and recruiting.     After the 11th inst. exemption on occupational grounds of men in agriculture and allied industries will be dealt with entirely by the County Agricultural Executive Committees in consultation with the Regional Representative of the Ministry of National Service.     The Tribunals will in future have no powers in these cases.Soldier Labour. An additional 514 soldiers were sent out to farmers during the week, making the total number of such men now out on farms 58,466.War Agricultural Volunteers.   Press notices have been Issued by the Ministry of National Service calling the attention of the public to the scheme for the enrolment of War Agricultural Volunteers for work on the land.Prisoners of War.   Twelve additional agricultural prisoner campshave-been opened during the week.     The number of prisoners nowemployed on farm or drainage work is as follows:-Prom 201 agricultural camps -&apos;-       11,284Employed from other camps 1,008Combatant prisoners lodged on farms 134, - , r,.,, .,..,g \ . pg 1 ; 12,426   -       . 1Released aliens employed in.\ .  - agriculture 1,912Total      14,358,        153 schemes, providing for. the employment of 8,858additional prisoners in agriculture are now with the War Office.Schemes have also been prepared for employing a further 3,000prisoners, but these are held in abeyance owing to no prisonersbeing available for them at present.
Women4,s Branch,Recruiting,   Recruiting has been progressing..favourably durinj the weeli.   Evening meetings have been held at West Ham and V/altham Abbey as well as in London, and a procession was held Saturday through Walthamstow and Leyton, which roused great enthusiasm.   It is hoped shortly to organise in the industrial! areas of England an open air recruiting campaign on similar 11 to the one conducted in London.A Women&apos;s Camp has been established at Romney Marsh t centre from which women are supplied to meet the needs of the farmers in the district.   Other camps are being started on similar lines.   Large parties of fruit pickers are being sent Wisbech.Training, During the week 79 fresh training centres have been arranged.   Gang hostels have been started in Glamorgan and Bed: shire to accommodate 40 women *;ach, and another In Wiltshire f 50 women.   A new t?&apos;aining centre has also been opened in Susse to accommodate 20 women.At Sparsholt, Hampshire, 12 women are being trained in thatching, and other training centres for this branch of work ai being started, The rneed for thatchers in the future is likely to be greater than the available supply, and it is intended to train as many women thatchers as possible.11,3.64 women are accounted for In the Land Army asfollowsOn Farm Work............................ 8,056Employed by Forage Department     ......... &apos;   188&quot;    &quot;   Timber Department s..........     151In Instruction Centres .................. 2,115Waiting for references to be placed intraining centres t...................     624Waiting in Depots e,,.,,6................      47Waiting in their own homes ..............     18511,564Women1s&apos; iInstitutes. 22 new Institutes have been started during the week.
CULTIVATION blVISIOM.Charges for Ploughing^ Harvesting and other Operations, In viewof the increased cost of labour, fuel and forage, the Departmenthave decided to revise the charges made to farmers for the use ofthe Government tractors and horses.   Hitherto, a minimum of20/- per acre has been fixed by the Department for ploughing;in future the minimum charges for tractor ploughing will varyfrom 22/6 per acre for light land to 57/6 for heavy 4-horseland.   The minima for horse ploughing wj.ll be 2/6 per acre morethan for tractor ploughing.   Minimum charges have also beenfixed for all other operations, including harvesting and threshingTractor Scheme. It has been decided to restrict the tractors andploughs to be operated under the Department&apos;s scheme to thefollowing types :-Tractors. Ploughs.Titan                                  Ransome 3 &amp; 2-furrow.Fordson                               Cockshutt 3- &quot;Clayton &amp; Shuttleworth         Davey Sleep 2- v25 H.P.Mogul -                       Emerson 2- &quot;Saunderson                            Howard 3 &amp; 2- &quot;Oliver 2-Saunderson 2- &quot;Arrangements have been made with the Surplus GovernmentProperty Disposal Board to sell the other makes of tractors andploughs owned by the Department with the exception of about 300&apos;Emerson, Overtime, and Parrett tractors, which will be handed overas required to the Forage Committee for baling work..   Thetractors that are withdrawn from the counties will be replacedprincipally by Fordsone, but a certain number of Clayton andShuttleworth and Saunderson ti-actcrc will also be available for &apos;the purpose.The tractors, machinery and implements consigned during the week ending 8th June are as follows
Consign?d to Countieaduring week. Total Consigned to Date.Tractors                 &quot; &apos;   &quot;64 4/OTlPloughs                         35 5,161Cultivators 9/11 tine    81 1,432Cultivators disc jjpattern       16 687Pressers,3-ring               - 202Trailers                          - . 910In addition, 254 Pordson tractors have been dispatched from the M.O.M. Factory to farmers, having been sold by Messrs. Henry Ford &amp; Son, while 200 tractors have been released to Messrj Henry Ford &amp; Son to be sold to agents for demonstration to farms: Deliveries from the factory during the past week have been retarded by the shortage of railway trucks, but matters in this respect are improving.The total acreage dealt with during the week ended 31u( May is as follows:-   ploughed 8,428, cross-ploughed 4,111 and cultivated 33,095 acres.    Very satisfactory, results have been received from Surrey, Kesteven, Wiltshire and Hereford.The results of the Gordon Selfridge prize competitions as follows:-   Fuel Consumption.   The first prize for the three months ending May 3rd has been won by a team in Norfolk, tho consumption being 2,49 gallons per acrej   the 2nd prize by a teal Wiltshire, the consumption being 2.6 gallons,4   for the two month! ending 3rd May, both 1st and 2nd prizes,by teams in Holland, the consumption being 2.13 gallons^ and 2.26 gallons respectively; for the month ending 3rd May, 1st prize, a team in Cumberland, 1.49 gallons;   2nd prize, a team in Norfolk, 1.82 gallons. Acreage.   Three months ending 3rd May, 1st prize, a team in Holland, 354 acres, 2nd prise a team in Oxford 265 acres.   Two months ending 3rd May, 1st, Prize, a team in Hereford, 257 acres, 2nd prize a team in Worcester, 191 acres.     Months ending 3rd Maj 1st prize, a team in Somerset, 94 acres, 2nd prize, a team in Yorks (W.R.) 87 acres.Fuel, At a meeting of the Petroleum Executive Committee it was - decided that, in view of the report furnished by the Department, would be inadvisable to have paraffin-using tractors adapted to
use petrol.    As It is clear, however, that all tractors designed to run on petrol will not run,..satisfactorily on paraffin, the Petroleum Executive is willing to license additional quantities of petrol to such private users of agricultural machinery a3 make application.    The Department are issuing a circular (approved., by the Petroleum Jbcecutiye) to Agricultural Committees explaining the new position with regard to the use and issue of paraffin and petrol for agricultural&apos;purposes. .Tractor Ploughs.   The experiments conducted with a view to making j&amp;e Oliver plough convertible at will to turn a 12 or 10 inch furrow have now been satisfactorily completed.    Arrangements have been made&quot;for the parts&apos;required for this conversion to be made in quantities * &apos;Successful experiments have also been carried out whichwiXI jenable the Cockshutt plough to be altered in such a way as tomake It entirely suitable to meet the most difficult conditionsunder which it occasionally has to work In this country.Horse Scheme.   The horse-drawn implements consigned to the countiesduring the past week are as followst-&apos;    Consigned to counties Total consignedduring week,   ! -   to date&quot;.Carts &amp; Lorries 50 1,746Cultivators                     - 1,454Disc Harrows 1 785Drills 4                             -1,456Harrows &amp;. Pra^s.. .16               , 3,179. Ploughs 19 6,240Rollers &amp; Presses 11- 2,562Farmers claim that horse teams should plough an asre a.day.    This acreage is, however, seldom maintained for more than aday or two except on light land, and on heavy land three-quarters ofan acre is generally regarded as a good dayfs work.      It issatisfactory, therefore, to learn fr*m a report Just received that,in East Suffolk in February a team of F0P. horses lh charge of a
soldier ploughman ploughed 13 acres of heavy land in 12 consecu days - a remarkable performance for the short days at that timli the year.Steam Tackle. During the week ending 8th June 46,000 acres were dealt with by steam ploughs.     The work done was principally preparing land for rootsj stirring fallows and breaking up gras land and stubble which had not been previously ploughed. Preparation for the Harvest,   135 binders were consigned to the counties during the week, making a total to date of 2,269;   also 18 threshing machines making a total of 146.   There have besides been released from the Departments contracts for sale to thresh contractors and farmers 48 threshing machines.   Negotiations are proceeding with the Forage Committee for the release of 150 trac engines to threshing-contractors during the coming threshing season.    To enable the Forage Committee to continue baling, the Department are offering, as mentioned above, to place about 300 tractors at their disposal.Steps are being taken to increase the number of horses in each county preparatory to harvest operations.SUPPLIES DIVISION. Fertilisers,   The makers of basic slag have collected orders fronf their customers covering their requirements for the year up to 31st May next, and these represent In the aggregate 562,000 tons j for England and Wales, while in addition very considerable applications&apos; have been received from individual dealers.   The maximum quantity available for distribution, after providing for the needs of Scotland and Ireland, will be .450,000 tons, so it wi not be possible to meet the requirements already put forward. Applications have also been received for sulphate of ammonia amounting to over 100,000 tons for the year, of which 35,000 tons are for-the first three months.   This again is in excess of the \&apos; amount which it will be possible to allocate.
A provisional alloeatioh has been made in respect of the majority of the applications so far received, and licences have been issued authorising the sale of some 15.000 tons of sulphate of ammonia and 150,000 tons of basic slag.   These quantities are sufficient to enable the works to deliver their output as produced pending detailed consideration of the balances to be allocated.Applications have been received from 988 firms to be appointed as Approved Agents.   1?hese are being referred to the Agricultural Executive,Committees in order that they may consider the suitability of the firms in question and the sufficiency of the storage proposed to meet the requirements of the local small growers and allotment holders.Arsenate of Lead, Some months ago the Department obtained from the Ministry,of Munitions an allotment of 28 tons ,of,litharge, from which arsenate of lead is manufactured, and this has been distributed among the manufacturers in order to meet the requirement of the spraying season.   In View of the prevalence of caterpillars in certain parts of England it is satisfactory to know that, so far as can be ascertained, this supply will be ample to meet all requirements. *Potato Spraying. Potato blight has already appeared in the Penzance district of Cornwall on the foliage      the following early varieties:-   Sharpes1 Express, Midlothian Early, May Queen and Royal Jersey,   Spraying demonstrations are being given throughout the county and the actual spraying of main crop potatoes has in some districts already commenced.Revision of the Testing of Seeds Order,   The revision of the &apos; Testing of Seeds Order has now been completed, and it is hoped that the new Order will be issued in the course of the next few day3.It has been found that there were insuperable difficulties in providing that a statement as to germination should appear on all small packets of vegetable seeds, but the new Order will
require that a declaration shall be madej either on the pack in some other form,- in cases where the seeds fall below a standard of germination Specified in the Order,   The effect oj this will be that all seedsmen will be more or less forced to supply packets of seeds which germinate above the standard, a required declaration, in cases where.the seeds fall below this] standard, would to a very large extent check their sale. Exemption of Seed Experts *   The Ministry of National Service I now agreed thaf all the principal agricultural and horticultur seed firms in England and Wales shall be included under the description &quot;Wholesale Food &apos;Seed Industry&quot; used in the Order recently issued withdrawing exemptions from agricultural labou and its accessory industries.   In future,, therefore, all Heads Departments and seed experts employed by the principal seed fi1 will be dealt with&apos;by the Agricultural Executive Committees.I am. Sir,Your obedient Servant,^Blrector-General.The-Rt. Hon.. Rowland E. Prothero, [viVP.President of the Board of Agriculture and Fisheries.

</content>
</cab>
