<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 309-309</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/ml hi U-(This gp^Hnent..1.8 theproperty of Hie Britannic Majesty&apos;s government). Icrot.IT .4865*&quot;* War Cabinet.&quot;Wholesale Milk trade - control or purchase&quot;.-- n-ntw...........---- --r-iri&apos; --(---i &apos;v n i rrn-rrr-n-itfin r innr mmt mat.......mmmtn i Mi wrn.fi m an l J)jm. iimr in niir; ijimijiriiMemorandum by the President of the Board of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries.........-................11......if      -i n  iV--iii-iiTif.iinnl.iiMiinin-iniii.iiiiIt is proposed by the Ministry of flood to assume control of the wholesale milk trade in order to ensure hotter distribution under the conditions set up by the imposition of a flat rate of prioes and to prevent waste of labour by competition and of transport by overlapping.The question has been examined by a Sub-Committee of the Committee on the Production and Distribution of Milk, /presided over &quot;by Major Astor,   Shis Sub-Committee   recommended that the Ministry of Pood should assume control of the wholesale milk trade and it further passed a resolution reooramending the Ministry of Pood to take options for the purchase of the chief firms involved in order that they might be able, at the close of tho war, to deal equitably with competing firms whose business connections would have been disturbed hy the operation of control.   This latter recommendation was not endorsed by Major Astorls main Committee, However, press notices emanating from the Ministry of Pood seem to indicate that the Ministry are proposing to take up such options and even to purchase outright and take over the wholesale milk trade as a Government enterprise, at any rate for the period of the war,I am unable to concur in the proposal to purchase or even in the policy of taking options, which will almost inevitably commit the State to subsequent purchased   I would submit that this proposal, which involves certain fundamental questions of policy from the point of view of the relation of the State to industries after the war, has not received sufficient oonsidera-tion on the financial and administrative sides,   I ask, therefore, for a Cabinet decision and suggest that the following questions should bo submitted to a small oommittee of men of financial and administrative experience(1)     Is the weight of evidence, as regards unequal&apos; distributionspa waste of labour and transport, sufficient to justify State control?(2)     Is such control practicable without purchase? *(3)     Is purchase now possible except at inflated prices.What are the probable requirements of capital?(4)    Would control and purchase for the period of the war compel the State to remain the sole wholesale dealer in milk after the war?R.-E. PRQTHJ3R0.7th June, 1918

</content>
</cab>
