<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 311-314</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS JttCUteM? IS THB PROPERTY OF HIS BKITATOO HAJ8SJY13 fiSSSffiSS)Is S C R B T. j ^S.T.-4867.Supreme War Council, Versailles *TAR   CABIN F, T. RE P 0 R,Ton thePOLITICAL SITUATION IK PRANCE for the month of May.prom a purely political point of view the month of May may he divided into two distinct periodB.   It &quot;began in an atmosphere of quiet, which lasted as long as relative quiet reigned on the Front, but very quickly became disturbed when the German offensive took place and imposed upon the Allies a withdrawal on a considerable scale.    When this occurred many ambitions, which had hitherto remained hidden, suddenly revealed themselves and the covert opposition in certain quarters took an active and open form.      It was considered, in certain circles, that if France&apos;s military misfortunes gave the opportunity for the Cabinet to be overthrown or, at any rate,&quot; its preBtige diminished and its position in the country shaken, they would not be an unmixed evil.The month began, however, quietly.     There were no full dress debates in the Ohamber, no sensational interpellations were made, and no virulent attacks launched.   There was little animation in the lobbies, and no intrigues. .The manifestoes of the General Councils, which were issued just before the re-assembly of the Chamber, were bearing fruit.    The departmental assemblies were nearly unanimous in assuring M. Clemenceau of their devotion and confidence. Even in those departments in w^ich the unified element pre-dominates, and in the Councils in which the Opposition Radioal Socialists have seats, the prevailing current carried all before it; and in the face of this general sentiment the Opposition Members satisfied themselves with showing their hostility by abstaining from voting on the order of the day, expressing admiration of, and sympathy for, the Government. It should be observed that there was no doubt the idea that this restraint should be confined to the departmental assembly and that the Opposition should take the earliest opportunity in the Chamber to take up its old line once more, and again accuse the Government of having forfeited the confidence placed in it.For a just appreciation of the Political Situation it must be realised that, generally speaking, the Clemenceau Ministry was imposed on the Chamber by the country, in opposi-tion to the private and personal wishes of many Members of the Chamber,      Parliament did not dare to take an open stand against the will of the people.    The French nation, sick and tired of a policy full of  *ttfLtaa*38tu, short-sightedness and mistakes, demanded a Government that should govern.      The Painleve Cabinet had lamentably tumbled to pieces - M. Clemenceau was the man called for by public opinion.     His first acts, on assuming power, had a re-assuring effect; themorale
w O xmoral ft of the nation rose., and the national sentiment was strengthened.     On the; other hand, a considerable party in the Chamber toeoame anxious and was much troubled by thenee-*ome acta.    These are the two points which really characterise the situation.    After six months the Government1 a.,majority has, &apos; so to speak, crystallised.    Each successive vote. shOwe re-eults practically identical with the one before&apos; it.    The Opposition comprises the Socialist Party, plus about 20 Radicals of socialist tendencies or convictions, who are on terms bf more or less personal friendship with H. Caillaux and more or less compromised or anxious about their own position-The Opposition can muster, in all, 110 or 120 votes.- a maxi-mum of 125, which figure is hitherto the highest attained.There are divisions in the Socialist Party itBelf, About 40 Socialists, lead by M. Varenne, vote against the Government, while at the same time in private conversation they express their confidence in It.    These represent the Right of the Party.    It is only the Socialist Centre, lead by M. Renaudel and M. Sembat, who appear to be absolutely irreconcilable, even the Minority Socialists, who follow M* Jean Longuet, adopt, generally speaking, an attitude of reserve and distinguish sharply between their public attitude and. their personal convictions.The most unswerving and bitterest enemies of the Government are to be found among the friends of E. Cajllaux and M. Malvy.    These gentlemen^ adherents are the last to hold to a policy which has, so to speak, survived its own extinction - the ex-Minister of the Interior, being at once its symbol and its ghost.     A haggard shadow he tirelessly prowls the corridors of the Palais Bourbon in quest of the greetings and interviews which become fewer for him every day. He broke down altogether when he heard of the verdict which condemned his ex-Chof  de Cabinet (whom he had not had the oourage to defend) exclaiming &quot;it is barbarousi&quot;- and M. Halvy gave the impression that his pity was chiefly for himself.None the less the Loyal Malvyiete are still keeping their eyes open, they still hope that they will be title to win over a certain number of votes, a number sufficient to. embarrass the Government if military events should tafce an unfortunate turn.    In a move directed against a War Govern-ment they might find Allies among those who are openly or&apos; secretly pacificists, among the Conservatives who fear for their own interests, and among the Clericals, who take their orders from Rome.     This explains why the German offensive was bound to be the signal for an Opposition offensive in the Chamber, the opportunity -was bound to be seized for a series of tortuous intrigues ultimately leading up to a noisy and dis-orderly sitting, at the end of which the Government found itself in its usual majority.The drama was preceded by a curtain raiser.     On May 30th the Chamber wafl asked to assign a date for the discussion of the interpellations put down in the names of -W,r Cachin, Jobert and Brunet on the military situation..    The Socialists asked that this question should be taken immediately; it was proposed troir. t?:iO other side that it should be put down for June 4th,     I lZ memcers vox-cd with the Minority, on this pro-posal, a certain numoer ci Socialist Radicals uniting with the usual opposition - some of them claimed after to have been misled.On
9 9 s)hi i)  j &apos;On Tuesday June 4th the debate opened at  ever heat.The agitation rose to a paroxysm,.    The united Socialist group had decided to ask for a secret Crmmittee, &quot;but It subsequently revised this decision and announced that it left to the Government to elect what procedure should be followed in the discussion of the interpellations.      The Radical Socialist group under the Presidency- of ft* Rene&apos; Renault (in spite of the opposition of some of its members, notably MM. Dalbiez, Jugy,. Angles,. Maurice Long and Franklin Bouillon) decided to vote&apos;for the adjournment of the debate, and instructed its leader to intervene for the purpose of making a statement in this sense-As soon as the sitting:began M, Clemenceau ascended the tribune.   He began by expressing his appreciation of the feelings which ,h&amp;.d led to the interpellations being put., down, but he sal-d --hat he could not agree to their being dis-cussed in view of the present, situation,    This was the signal for an oi.t:..a^eous series of obstructive interruptions by M. Deguise, who had also put down an interpellation; and stood up in front of the Government bench cutting into the Prime Minister&apos;s a^oon with one interruption after another. K.. Clemenceau refused to continue his explanations under euch conditions., and returned to the Government bench, and demon-strati ons of various kinds took place in various parts of the House,.M. Marcel Cachin having averred the patriotic view which lead him to leave the question of tho date for the disoussion of the interpellations to the Government, M, Clemenceau continued his speech.   He spoke amidst a noise which speedily rose to a hubbub.     He had considerable diffi-culty in making himself heard, and th$ Opposition was de-lighted to see the Leader of the Government expending his energies in a physical effort which appeared somewhat to diminish his usual clearness of expositionsThe Chamber had broken- loose altogether.   When the Prime Minister had finished,- M. Renaudel and H, Lenoir, the member for Rheims, found it as difficult to make themselves heard as- he had done, and when L Forgoet (Marne), who is generally a highly appreciated speaker, wished to express his vi evm y.   he found a di stracted.assembly.The Socialists proposed that the debate should be. adjourned for a fortnight.      The&apos; Government replied by pro-posing an adjournment sine die&apos;, and making it a question of confidence..   The quostion was put and there voted: for the . Government&apos; 377, against&apos;110. -   A dozen or so Radioal members abstained,-The sitting had been tumultuous, and it was generally-thought, that appart&apos; from the actual voting, M, Cl&amp;oenoeau had not had his usual success&apos;.-  At the time it appealed as if the day * s proceedings had in some degree diminished the Government&apos;s prestige, but this impression had subsequently to be revised; it was found that the country showed extreme resentment of the Parliamentary&apos; habits which ean prevent a Prime Minister,; who is popular and respected, from getting, a fair hearing at a particularly serious crisis.     This view had its effect on the gentlemen at the Palais Bourbon, and
fa *j a48 hours aftor the debate, it was generally recognised that the Government1e position was as solid as ever, while the Opposition on the other hand was so placed as to make it Impossible for it at once to embark again on a manoeujrm oo universally condemned.    In the circumstances, naturally nobody wag anxious to appear as having participated in the organisation of the attack,    M. A. Briand, who was not un-reasonably suspected of having had a hand in it, protested indignantly that Me intentions were of the purest, and observed in the strongest terms, that such a proceeding would have been unworthy of him.There was one certain criterion of the effect of the sitting: the Chamber at its next meeting adjourned for a week, and a large number of members, were inclined to make it a fort-night; they felt themselves cheapened, and their prestige re- &apos; duced by the acandai, and realised that 3uch a scene could not. be often repeated without considerably increasing the Parliaments already considerable, unpopularity,    It must be admitted that the position of the Deputies is a difficult one. They vaguely feel that they no longer altogether, represent tjie spirit of the Preach people in the way that that spirit ought to be represented after four years1 of war.    In fact their mandates have run out.    But for the fact that hostilities are still in progress, they would no longer have the right to sit, and they have been obliged to prolong their own political existence.    It is very clear that this factor will play a   ; more and more considerable part as time goes on, and there are already discussions in the Press questioning the validity of -the Assembly&apos;s powers.(Signed)     ARTHUR CAPEL,Captain,Secretary.War Cabinet.I forward the attached Report on the Political Situation In France for the Month of May, prepared by Captain Capel&apos;.It is particularly interesting as it represents MM. Clemenceauffl arvd Mahdel&apos;3 views of the Political Situation.(Sgd.) C. SACKVTLLE WEST&apos;.MajorsGeneral, Acting British Military Representative, 1 . - Supreme War Council,Versailles.12th June, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
