<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/54/0 images: 423-424</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MEMORANDUM B TIII  KINISfRT   0?   IABOU,PRIORITY AND ALLOCATION OP MATERIALS IN THE 20ST   WAR   PERIOD,
PRIORITY AND ALLOCATION OF MATERIALS IN THE POST WAR PERIOD.

The report of the Advisory Council on Post-war allocation of ? materials submitted by the Minister of Reconstruction on G.T.481? refers to the "allocation of labour".

It is clear that the rapid restoration of pivotal industries which receive priority of material by direction of the State will be impossible unless an adequate supply of labour for those industries is immediately available after the war, but the words "allocation of labour" have a meaning which is so important that I wish to draw attention to the questions involved.

Normally the removal of the existing restrictions upon the freedom of labour would result in wages being determined largely by collective bargaining, the ordinary economic action. Owing to the absence of effective foreign competition due to the position of other countries in respect of materials etc., and the vast demands for all classes of goods and works, it is probable that wages and prices would, if left to themselves, rise to great heights in those? priority industries, at the general expense of the Community, as they have done in the Building Trade during the war. It appears necessary therefore to consider what shall be done to safeguard the consumer, when the present restrictions are withdrawn and they must be withdrawn in accordance with the pledges of the Government.

It may be suggested that the present restrictions on labour shall be continued during the Reconstruction period, but I think it safe to predict that the Trade Unions would not consent to this unloss a more effectual limitation of profits and of interest on capital invested industrially were secured than is actually in operation now. It is not the function of the Ministry of Labour to comment on the Excess Profits tax, as the difficulties of its administration are not known, but enough has been learned in frequent conferences with workpeople to know that they believe that it does not operate with undue harshness against employers, and this impression right or wrong, makes it essential that any control of labour during the Reconstruction period should be accompanied by a clear and intellgible control of profits.

A suggestion that the total volume of available labour trained during the war has materially increased is not altogether accurate; it has largely been a matter of ?tion for labour drained off in other ways. In any event, any attempt by industries receiving favoured treatment in the way of materials to use the loss-organished but comparatively skilled supply of women&apos;s labour in preference to the ordinary male labour would raise such a protest from the Trade Unions that no Government could face the situation without interference.

Allocation of materials with labour following the requirements of the market may be a satisfactory proposition, provided the community is guarded against the dangers outlined above, but the allocation of labour raises very serious problems - all connected with the idea of industrial compulsion.

These arguments lead me to the conclusion, that the Committees who are the? deal with this allocation should have upon them a stronger representation of Trade Unions than appears to be contemplated, and which I support the proposals. I would suggest that this po? deserves care? consideration.

(Signed) GEO.H. ROBERTS.

21.6.1918.

</content>
</cab>
