<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/135/0 images: 235-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C(68) 2415th January, 1968CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE;  POST-DEVALUATION MEASURESDRAFT PARLIAMENTARY STATEMENTNote by the Secretary of the CabinetThe attached draft of tomorrow^ Parliamentary statement willconstitute the agenda for this afternoon^ meeting of the Cabinet, to beheld at 3.30 p. m.    Various sections of it, including the passage on defence, are still under discussion between the Ministers concerned interms of presentation;  and further amendments may have to be proposed at Cabinet.    But all Departments are asked to ensure that their ministers are briefed on the factual accuracy of the passages whichare their departmental responsibility.    The timetable for printing thestatement as a White Paper will make it impossible for the text co befurther amended after Cabinet.(Signed)    BURKE trend cabinet Office^ S.W.1.15th January, 1968 . sJTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER  BRITANNIC MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.     .. $rrr^y. T^Tr1TOP secret copy No.
Tuesday  Statementlt   On December 18 I informed the House that the Governmentwas engaged in a major review of every field of public expenditure as one of the measures necessary to achieve- a progressive, orderly and massive swing of resources from..home consumption, public and private, to the requirements of exports,import replacement and productive investment,2.    The objective first is to release resources from homeuse, in order to reinforce the balance of trade, and to do this in a way which realises every practicable opportunity toreduce Government expenditure overseas.    Second, it is toensure that, as the economy swings into expansion, led by the priority areas I have mentioned - exports, import replacement,;ani investment - the total level of demand, public and private,I is kept in line with what the productive machine can make[available without lurching into inflation and excessive strainm our national resources.    Third, and immediately, at a timenen unemployment, contrary to widespread expectation six monthsgo, is falling - seasonal factors apart - and demand forabour increasing, it is to ensure that the growing consumer-expansion now under way, gives way to an export-led expansion.Our aim is not deflation, but expansion, based on therowing use of our resources at an ordered pace so that theouild-up of exports and. &quot;She other priority categories, doesnot lead to undue pressure on those resources.    A higher proportion oi our growing national production must be shiftedfeelsively for the benefit oi&apos; the balance of payments and
- 2 - M o 2,investment and a smaller proportion will be left thereforetor rising consumer demand and government expenditure.H;   The measures which I shall announce this afternoon,relate to r^public expenditure.    These will be progressivelyreinforced, as I indicated on December 18, by all appropriatefurther measures budgetary and. non-budgetary to hold backprivate consiimpti on.5,   in order to secure the required swing in our balance ofpayments, starting this year, to achieve it next year and tomaintain it &quot;thereafter we have to hold back home demand inrelation to the growth of production by getting on tor 1000 m. by the time the measures we are taking have workedtiirough the economy.    From every point of view it would be wrong to seek to achieve this solely by restraining the growth of personal consumption.    Public expenditure also must make its full contribution;   indeed if the rate of increase of public expenditure were not severely restrained in the years immediatelylaheaci, insufferable burdens on the standard of living of the(ordinary family, would be required.The measures I shall armounce follow a detailed anddeep review of policy in every major field of expenditure, with[io exceptions, on the basis that no spending programme could3 sacrosanct.    All these are in addition to the measuresnnounced by my Pet. Hon. Friend the Home Secretary on November.   The House will be aware, from long experience, that the&quot;penditure of any given year is to a very large extentQuitted by decisions taken two and three years before,
TOP SECRET M.-3-ticularly where major works such as roads, hospitals and schools, and marry items of defence production are involved,ecause of this time-lag, and the difficulty of making animpact on many continuing projects, we have concentrated onxpenditure in the financial year 1969-70, though in somecases the full saving resulting from our decisions will not heseen until 1970-71 and subsequent years.    At the same time,substantial reductions in expenditure in 1968-69 will heachieved.    I must however tell the House that so great is theproportion of expenditure governed by programme decisionslaken two, three and more years ago, that &quot;there will still hea considerable rise in public expenditure in 1968-69 comparedkith 1967-68, and a further small rise in 1969-70.:8.   1 begin with defence expenditure, the whole of which[has teen reviewed against the background of our commitmentsana alliances.     Our decisions have been based on two main principles.    First, while we intend to make an appropriatecontribution, related to our economic capability, to thealliances of which we are members, the overriding need, notonly in our own interests but in those of our friends andallies, is for this country to strengthen its eoonomic basequickly and decisively.    There is no military strength,whether for Britain or our alliances, except on the basisof economic strength,    Second, reductions in capability,whether in terms of manpower or equipment must follow and bebased on a review of the commitments the Services are required^undertake.    Defence must be related to the requirements
TOP SECRET- 4 -of foreign policy, but it must not be asked in thename of foreign policy to undertake commitments beyondits capability.   Major foreign policy decisions thereforeare a prior requirement, of economies in defence expenditure.   And in taking these decisions we haveto come to terms with our role in the world.   It isnot only at home that, these past years, we have beenliving beyond our means,   Given the right decisions,above all given the full assertion of our economic strength, our real influence and power for peacewill be strengthened by realistic priorities.9,    We have accordingly decided to accelerate thewithdrawal of our forces from their stations in theMiddle Last and Far East which was announced in the supplementary Statement on Defence Policy of July1967 (Cmnd. 3357).   The broad effect is that, apartfrom our remaining dependencies and certain other necessary exceptions, we shall not be maintainingmilitary bases outside Europe and the Mediterraneanby the end of the financial year /&quot;&quot;1970/71J7.
10.    By that date we shall have withdrawn completelyfrom Malaysia and Simapore,   &quot;7e have told both governments that we do not thereafter plan to retain a special military capability for use in the area.   But we have assured themboth, and our other Commonwealth partners and allies concerned,?jt(iat our general capability based in Europe will be availableffor deployment overseas,   y/e shall thus retain the abilityfto lend assistance if circumstances in our judgment wereIto demand it.   [We shall come to a new understanding aboutthe Anglo/Malaysian Treaty,]   Wo have also informed thej Governments of Malaysia and Singapore that we will discusswitii them the aid implications of this accelerated withdrawal.life shall amend our force declarations to SEATO as our forcesj in the area are run down.IlL    We shall make an early reduction,,in the number of aircraft based in Cyprus while maintaining our membership of CENTO.12.    On the Persian Gulf we have indicated to theGovernments concerned that our basic interest .in thej prosperity and security in. the Gulf is not lessened [and,.,,repeated that..-the general military capability based,.on Europe --111 be-available, for deployment overseas-if circumstances:in our judgment-.were to.....deraand.it..-  But It is not realistic-g-to--maintain a military presence in the ..Gulf after -our&quot;&quot;&quot; &quot;&quot; &quot;&apos;&apos;--1 withdrawal., from -the Far. East, and - we-have- therefore-decided.. -I to -withdraw our military forces from the.Gulf as part of. ..the   -same-operation.-        - - . . .....
TOP SECRETM.- 6 -13.    As the House already know my r.h.f. the foreign secretary has visited Washington to discuss our intentions with the U.S. Administration.   And my r,ti0f.the Commonwealth Secretary has paid special visits to thefour Commonwealth countries concerned with Far east defence so as to acquaint their Prime Ministers of the changes in our [political commitments and consequent]military dispositions and to discuss the consequenceswith them,   My right horn Friend the Minister of State,Foreign Office, has paid a special visit to the Statesof the Gulf for a similar purpose.   Other governments and Organisations concerned have already been made fully aware of our decisions,14.    V/e recognise the deep feelings and anxieties of our allies and Commonwealth partners.   We recognise too thatthese changes involve risks, but measuring our resourcesagainst our priorities we believe they are risks that mustbe accepted.   One risk we are not prepared to take is toshoulder burdens and commitments beyond the capacity ofthe forces we can afford.15.    These decisions will entail, major changes in the rolcnsize and shape of the forces, in the nature and scale ofthe equipment which they will require and in the supportingfacilities which are necessary.   Time will be needed towork out the precise implications:   these will be embodied in a White Paper to be published and, if the House so
pTOP SECRET- 7wishes, debated later in the year.   Nevertheless, I can nowgive some specific illustrations of the effects of our decisions in advance of the further detailed work.16.    Manpower,.   Command 3357 envisaged withdrawal from certain East of Suez stations by the mid-seventies,   andplanned for a reduction by roughly the same date in theestablishment of the Services of 75,000 uniformed manpower,and 80,000 civilians.   The House will understand that withthe much earlier withdrawal from the Far East which I have announced and our decision to withdraw from the Gulf, itwill not in these altered, circumstances be possible to achieve the run-down in numbers at the same pace aswithdrawal.   Because of considerations affecting the orderly run-down of the forces including such matters as their restructuring, resettlement and. the need to maintainrecruitment for volunteer forces a further short time willbe needed.   As a result of our decisions, and of others thatwill result from the further planning which is now starting,the active strength of the forces will be reduced by[April, 1971] well below the levels forecast last July inCiiid.3357.   We would expect that, within about 5 years or sofrom now, we shall have reduced the total size of the force;below the long term strengths we had previously planned.   Thithe eventual saving in Service manpower will be greater thanthe total reduction of about 75,000 forecast previously forthe mid-1970s and we shall achieve it earlier.   We shall alsc
&apos; Mo- 8 -be reducing civilian manpower at a faster rate over thesame period, and our aim will be to increase the forecastreduction of 80,000 civilians, and to achieve thissignificantly earlier than previously planned.17,    The Navy.   The aircraft carrier force will be phasedout during [1971] after our withdrawal from Malaysia,Singapore and tirr- Persian Gulf has been completed.   [? Wehave decided to stop the refit of the Ark Royal and not toproceed with the plans for refitting Fagle. ]   There will alsbe r eductions nit no rate of new naval construction, forexample in the nuniear-powered Hunter/Killer submarines,13- There will be a considerable increase inthe rate of rundown of the Army and in the disbandment orniaigamati.cn of major units.,   As a result of our acceleratecwithdrawal from Singapore and Malaysia, the rundown of the brigade of Gurkhas to 10,000 by the end of 1969 will continuat the same rate until [1971] bringing the total strength ofthe Brigade to 6,000,   The future of the Brigade after [1971will depend on developments obtaining at that time;   thereis no question of inducing the strength or effectiveness ofthe Hong Kong Garrison,   There will also be substantial savings on Army equipment and stocks and many of these willoe achieved between 1969/70 and [1972/73.]19.    The Royal Air Force.   We have decided to cancel theorder for 50 F.111 aircraft.   Further study is being given tothe consequences of this decision on the future equipment of
^0 TOP SECRET Mo- 9 -the Royal Air Force.   Leaving out of account the results ofthis study, the cancellation of the F.T11 is estimated to yield total savings on the Defence Budget of about  392 m.over the period of 1977/78.   This figure allows for likelycancellation charges.   The saving in dollar expenditure over the period,again allowing for likely cancellationcharges, will be in the region of 3[74Q]mc   Because of the credit arrangements, these savings will mature over a period,of years   [The U.S. Government have agreed to maintain boththe existing credit arrangements for the Phantom and Herculesaircraft and all the offset orders already firmly placed.   Weare grateful to the U.3. Government for their action, andrecognise that we cannot expect further offset orders inrespeot of our reduced U.S. aircraft purchases.:]   Thereduction in our overseas commitments will make it possibleto cut down the transport force.20.    Support Facilities.   The more rapid withdrawal of our forces from outside Europe and the changes we intend to makein their role and equipment will impose a massive task on those responsible for providing the most efficient and economical logistic support for the three Services.   very substantial savings in base facilities staff overseas will follow as a consequence of withdrawal.   The rundown in theforces will be increasingly reflected in reduced supportfacilities, such as training establishments in this country,but it is too early yet to indicate the extent of the total
- 10 -reduction of trie u .K. base as a whole.   In spite of the extra planning load placed upon it, we shall energeticallycontinue the process of cutting the size of the Ministry of21.    Financial effects.   The financial effects of policy changes on this scale will inevitably take time to workthemselves through.   The immediate effect will not bo toreduce the level of defence expenditure:   indeed, in 1968/69the level will be increased through cancellation payments and other transitional costs.   These are expected to be relatively modest thereafter.   From 1969/70 onwards,accordingly, leaving transitional cost on one side, therewill bo an increasing relief to the Budget, accompanied bya release of valuable resources for civil production.   Thescale of what is involved for the economy earn be measured by my expectation that in 1969/70 the Defence Budget which was planned to be about  1950m. at 1964 prices will be reducedby about  150m.   By [1972/73] the Defence Budget is expectedto be between  1,6C0m.- l,65Cm., at 1964 prices.defence.
TOP SECRET M.

-11-

22. The Government are very conscious of the effect that these further cuts will have on the Services and of the upheavals they will cause. Nevertheless, they are necessary of our economy. The accelerated rate of rundown in the Services, and in the civilians associated with them, is bound to cut short the careers of some who would otherwise have expected to have served for some years to come. There will inevitably be a considerable amount of disruption in all three Services and one of the major problems will be to arrange this very large reorganisation so that hardship to individuals is minimised and at the same time efficiency is maintained. The Government intends to ensure that the changes I have indicated are worked out as carefully as possible and implemented in as humane a way as possible so as to ensure that at the end of them the Services remain cohesive and viable and still offer a good career to those who serve in them.

23. So far I have been dealing with the redeployment of our defence effort in terms of Europe rather than the more far flung battle line of a century ago. [But we still face the problem of the heavy continuing cost in foreign exchange of stationing our troops in Germany. As the House knows there have already been informal preliminary talks in Bonn about ways and means of meeting this after the current Anglo-German Offset Agreement expires on 31st March next. We are now ready for formal negotiations and have proposed to the Federal German Government that the talks should start early in February.]


?4.   Now I turn to civil public expenditure.    /While in thecurrent year the Estimates for Defence provided for an expend!ture of  ... .mns., the Civil Estimates amounted to  ... .rans.,and this of course excludes Consolidated Fund expenditure./&apos;m0 review of planned expenditure programmes would be realisticor adequate for the task we have set ourselves as a nation,which failed to go deeply into every aspect of home expenditufTnis we have done.     Nothing was sacred.    Our decisions reflethe national priorities we have applied and which we commendto hie House.     In almost every major area of expenditureeconomies have been made in the rising programmes which wehad before us.    Within each major area we have of course beenIextremely selective in the cuts we have made.     Our objective,jas I stated a month ago, is to produce a total of economies which is coherent, credible - and fair.25.  Social Security.    I begin with Social Security.Expenditure this year, 1967-8, is  2909m., an increase at current prices of 48$ since 1963-64.     Last year &quot;the Houseapproved a general uprating of National Insurance and other(Benefits, which took effect last autumn.    In our forward planning we do not envisage that a further general up-ratingj;can be undertaken before at least the autumn of 1969.28.  Sir, in the statement made by my Right hon. Friend thenone Secretary on November SO, an assurance was given thatnie most vulnerable classes of the community will be protectedi&amp;gainst hardship resulting from those price increases whichpusr result from the effect of devaluation on import costs.
TOP SECRET- 13 -&apos;jje shall be watching price-rises very carefully and we intendin the light of this to raise Supplementary Benefits in theautumn of this year.    But more is needed to cover the needsof less well-off families and we therefore intend also toraise the income limits for the Rate Rebate Scheme. the qualifying limit for the full rebate will be raised from  8per week to  9 per week, and the rate for each child fromSOsin to  2.   The effect will be to extend, the coverage ofHate Rebates from the present figure of just over 1 millionhouseholders to between li and 2 million householders.27.  It has already been decided that Family Allowances will go up by 7 shillings in April.   But it is essential that this increase should be confined to families most in need and myRight Hon. Friend the Chancellor of the Exchequer intends to recover the full amount of the increase from taxpayers at thestandard rate and above through the tax machinery, taking backlesser amounts from those who will pay tax only at reducedrates,    I should add that my Right hon. Friend is examining the possibility at a later stage of extending this principleof selectivity based on tax adjustments more generally throughthe family allowance system, not just the 7 shillings increase.28.  Education.    Next Education, one of the biggest, and mostrapiclly expanding expenditure programmes.   Total expenditure is estimated this year at  1,989m., an increase at current prices of since 1963-4.    Here again it is a questionof priorities.   We have decided, we have no alternative todeferring from 1971 to 1973 the raising of the school leaving-    246M.2
TOP SECRET -       247age a postponement of two years.    I need not tell the Househow difficult, indeed repugnant, this decision has &quot;been tn myRight lion. Friends and myself.    It means that two annualgenerations of school children, up to ....... hundred thousandin all, will, and lor all time, be deprived of the benefits ofan extra year at school.    The fact that our action affectsonly the mandatory school leaving age, and that many - indeedan increasing number - are voluntarily staying on an extra year&apos;s , of course, relevant but we have to put on record the factthat there is still a severe /and growing?/ regionaldifferentiation in the proportion who decide and are allowedto stay on, as between North and South.29.  This decision will mean a saving of about  33m in 1968-S9,and  48m. in 1969-70 principally in the school building;programme.    But the basic school-building programmes will beincreased by extra starts of  8 mills on both in 1968-69 and in1969-70 to ensure that comprehensive reorganisation is not heldip, and to provide that additional resources beyond the extraIS m. starts in each of these years announced by my Eight lion,riend the Secretary of State to the House last year, for improving conditions in educational priority areas.30. We propose to cease the provision of free milk in secondary schools from September of this year.    This will require-egislation.31,  /The capitation grants to direct grant schools will beEduced/.32.  Some new capital projects in the universities, colleges
of further education and elsewhere will he held hack during1968-69.    At the next review of students&apos; awards nextSeptember, the increase will only cover half the rise in theeost-of-living since the last review.i% The combined effect of all these measures in the field ofeducation will be to make a net saving of  43millions in 1968-69 and  64 millions in 1969-70.54. Health and Welfare.    I turn next to health and welfare,with a 1967-68 expenditure of  1619millions, an increase att current prices of 45^ over the past 4 years.35, We are proposing no reductions in the hospital building programme which will go ahead as planned.o60 The Government have, however, decided, after the mostserious consideration and with the utmost reluctance, to re-Introduce a system of charges for prescriptions issued underthe National Health Service, at the rate of 2s. 6cl. per item.Regulations will be made to bring these charges into operation in the spring which is the earliest that arrangements can bemade to introduce simultaneously refund of charges to thosejin need on the pre-1965 basis, namely ...........L37. This would, if no further mitigations or exemptions weremoposed, save about  50 millions in a full year.    But mylight hen. Friend will immediately enter into discussions withjhe medical profession with a view to introducing as soon aspossible a system oi&apos; exemption for particular categories ofatients.    Those we have in mind are the elderly, over 65,IJnlclren up to 15, /war pensioners; 7, expectant mothers and theponic sick.    Exemptions on this scale, and we regard them
TOP SECRET -249- 16 - M. 2.Is fair and necessary, will reduce the saving from  50 millionlo about  25 millions, and we propose to make this good by increasing the NhiLS.. enroloyees&apos; contribution by 6d0 as soon asJiossible.18.   The maximum charge for dental treatment which has noteen changed since 1952 will be increased from  1 to 30s0 andmis will yield a further  li mi11ion.    As the House knowsjoung people up to 21 and expectant mothers receive freetreatment and. will continue to do so.     In addition someInductions in local health and welfare capital expenditure are being made averaging rather less than / 5 millions/ agear over the three years 1968 to 19717.p.    I have referred to the M.H.S. stamp.     The House oughtId know that quite apart from the expenditure review, and forlite other reasons, a further shilling, 6d. for employees,n. for employers will be needed to prevent the national insurance Fund from going into deficit.    This will be done at the same time as the 6d. increase in the N.H.S. contributionhich is collected on the same stampAf).   Home Department Services,     Now I turn to Home Departmentervices, including Home Defence.    We have decided to reducePie Defence to a care and maintenance basis, with a saving oflout  14 millions in 1968-69, and  20 millions in 1969-70 and in subsequent years.    /This will involve the disbanctaent ofeCivil Defence Corps, the Auxiliary Fire Service and therltorial and Auxiliary Volunteer Reserve/-     The Governmentpose to restrain the grants of expenditure on other Homef part merit services by  6 millions in 1968-69 and  12 millions1969-70.
fi TOP SECRET M.2- -- 17 -ll. Housing expenditure this year Is  1018m.    The Governmentlave decided to reduce planned approvals of new houses by15,-000 in England and Wales and 1,500 in Scotland in both1968 and 1969, saving in terms of Government expenditure27 inns, in 1968-69 and  55 inns, in 1969-70.    But even withiiese withholdings, we shall be able to maintain the momentumif the programmes for- slum clearance and for the relief oflerious local housing shortages.    These will be no cut inIlie 141 housing priority areas.12. Transport,     Next, Roads,     The estimated expenditure in1967-68 is  560 m., an increase of 52. per cent at current prices, compared with 1963-64.     Of the present programmep500 el. is on the major road programme of my Right Hon.Friends, and the remainder, nearly all local authority^expenditure, includes some  200 m. on road maintenance.The Government have decided that, overall, the programme should be. reduced so as; to produce Savings of  55 m. in968-69 and  69 m. in 1969-70.     Of this, local authoritiesill be asked to find  75 m. over the two years- out of their expenditure on the maintenance and improvement of their roads;and the planned growth of expenditure, Including maintenancepel minor improvements, on major roads will be cut by  18m.i,m the first year and  29 m. in the second.fff At the same time expenditure, on the new forms ofssistance to public passenger transport, provided for inpe Transport Bill, is being limited to  10 m. in 1.968-69f-nd  20 ni. in 1969-70, a reduction against the planned[programme of   ... and   ... m. respectively.
0- 1844  Industry.    There will he no reduction in the programmesproviding how at the rate of ... m., a year for Industrialaxpansion and regeneration in the Development Areas.45.  In the Ministry of Technology&apos;s programme for speedingthe modernisation of industry there will he a careful selection of priorities.    The reorganisation of the shipbuilding industry will continue, the work of the N.R.D.C. will bemaintained at the higher level which it has reached and programmes will go ahead for other industries includingcomputers, electronics and machine tools.    The plainedexpansion on industrial research in the Ministry of Technology&apos;sjown /&quot;ex-DSIR7 stations will be held back, and there will beIeconomies in the research and development programme of the atomic Energy Authority.    There will be a further cut In theMinistry&apos;s defence research programme in 1968-69.    The savingj on planned expenditure from all these measures will be 10 nr. a year both un 1968-69 and in 1969-70.    This is inhdition to savings by the A.E.A. which were foreshadowed byprevious: announcements and which involve  3 m. in 1968-69 andl 5 m. in 1969-70.jnh  On investment grants, where in the current year the BoardIjofTrade have accelerated their programme so as to pay grants[on five quarters of investment, the Government consider that(further shortening of the period between &quot;the making of[investment and the payment of grant must be postponed for thepiffle being.    It -therefore intends that in 1968-69 grants willN paid only in respect of four quarters&apos; past investment, so
TOP SECRET M.2.

19

that the average time between investment and payment will remain at the twelve months which it has already reached. This will reduce planned payments in 1968-69 by £?0 m. Decisions about 1969-70 will be taken in the light of circumstances nearer the time.

47. Local Authorities. The House will be well aware that a substantial area of public expenditure lies within the control of local authorities, whose expenditure has risen by £... m., or ... per cent at current prices over the past ?five years. A considerable part, though by no means the whole of local authority expenditure, is in response to national programmes endorsed by this House by statutory or other provision. Much of it is, however, subject by various means, indirect and direct to a measure of Government control or influence, and some of it will be affected by the measures I have announced. But it is vital that local authorities, no less than Government expenditure, make their full contribution to restraint in their programmes, the release of resources for the reinforcement of our trade balance and the avoidance of inflation.

48. Taking local authority expenditure as a whole, the Government hopes that in 1969-70 local authorities as a whole will restrain the level of their expenditure so that it does not in total exceed a figure in the region of 3 per cent in real terms above that has already been agreed for purposes of the Exchequer contribution in 1968-69: and the Government will propose rate


-    25TOP SECRET - M,lipport grant for 1969-70 on this basis when the time comes,As regards 1968-69, the Government will expect local authoritiesS) absorb any increases in cost which they cannot avoid byliking savings elsewhere, and it does not contemplate anyjirther increase of Exchequer grant in respect of them.g9.  Finally, Public Service manpower.     Special measuresfill be taken to arrest the growth in the number of peopletiployed in public service.    Despite the ever-growing demandlor the services provided by Government Departments, thesefcpartments will, under the guidance of the Treasury, sollan &apos;their complementing that over the year 1968/69 there isjo further nett increase in the number of civil servants in post.    This is estimated to save  15 m.    The economiesIhich we are asking Local Authorities to make should producelirnilar results in &quot;that area. 7
TOP SE,EmM50.    Sir, to avoid unduly wearying the House I have giventhe facts only about the main expenditure programmes of anysize.   In addition there are other reductions totalling[ 26m. 1 in 1968-69 and [ 37m, ] in 1969-70,   These come fromenvironmental services in 1968-69 and from those Services andcertain other expenditure in 1969-70.   There may well be other savings as the consequences of these major decisionswork through the whole field of public expenditure.51,   Summary.    The results of all the changes I have announced will be to reduce planned expenditure in 1968-69 by[ 302Million and 1969-70 by [...Jmillion.   This implies anaverage annual rise in public expenditure in the period1967-68 to 1969-70 of [... ] per cent.   [I am circulatingin the Official Report a table      showing public expenditurein 1968-69 and 1969-70 as forecast before the reductions,and the details of the reductions themselves.152.    I must again remind the House of the severe limitationswithin which any expenditure review must operate, particularlyso far as the period immediately ahead of the review isconcerned.   In many of the continuing programmes, particularly where major and lengthy capital projects are concerned, the basic decisions were taken 2 or 3 or 4 or more years ago, andcuts which act quickly can be achieved only with greatdisruption and great dis-econoray.   Some of the Government5sdecisions will have an immediate and major impact on
TOP SECRET II,f - 22 -: -expenditure in 1968-69 and subsequently, others will havela more limited effect in 1968-69, a growing impact on\ 1969-70 when a decisive switch of resources will be needed,In defence large-scale savings will be achieved only in! 1970-71 and later years.   But in this case, if the decisions are not taken now, they will not nuke any impact until wellinto the seventies, and Parliament in 1970, 1971 and later years will be impotent to secure major savings in thoseprogramme Sc53.   Finally, Mr. Speaker, I repeat that the review whoseconclusions I have announced today is only part of a continuing process which will dominate national financialand economic management for the next two years.   other measures including budgetary decisions will be required.54.    But in a wider sense, no measures of a purelyfinancial character, however necessary, can by themselvessolve our problems, and ensure that &quot;the opportunitiespresented to us by the decision to devalue are fully realised.55.    I must again emphasise the paramount importance ofprices and incomes policy.   The measures we have decided on and those which will be announced in succeeding months will be adequate if and only if the advantages we have gained are not dissipated in increased incomes over and above the very austere levels the country can afford, onthe basis not of what it - or individual sectional interests would like or would seek to extract, but on. the basis of*at we are earning.
M.- 23 -56,    But, sire, success in securing the massive shift we need to get from home consumption to the priority requestsof exports and import saving depends above all on the responseof industry, at all levels, to the challenge of winnableexport markets, import replacement and productive investment.The House will feel that a mood, of determination that thesechallenges must be met, is growing in the country,characterised by the thousands, soon millions, each of whomis asking himself what, in his own individual circumstances he can do to back the national effort, a mood which will Ibelieve give short shrift to individuals in industry - and organisations too - which for selfish reasons or forceof ingrained and irrelevant habits of thought, seek to resist what the country as a whole needs to be done.57,    To the efforts of those who in industry are responding to the challenge and opportunity which the new situation has created, the measures I have announced, cutting deep,comprehensive, but the Government believes balanced and fair, provide essential help and backing.   What these measurescan ngpt do is to provide a substitute for the efforts that now have to be made by all in. industry, indeed by the wholenation.


</content>
</cab>
