<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/135/0 images: 267-276</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C(68) 2629th January,. 1968HOUSE OF LORDS REFORM; REPORT ON THE PROGRESSOF THE INTER-PARTY^conference memorandum by the Lord ChancellorFollowing the Cabinet&apos;s conclusions on 12th October(CC(67) 59th Conclusions, Minute l)P discussions have taken place between representatives of the Government and the Conservative and liberal Leaders on the composition and powers of a reformed Houseof Lords.    These discussions have now identified the main points ofwhat might become an agreed scheme for the reform of the House ofLords, and although some of them need to be worked oat in greater detail, both sides think the issues have now become clear enough forus to report back to our colleagues the progress we have made.2.      The Government^ principal objectives in opening these negotiations, as set out in paragraph 2 of my earlier memorandum(C(67) 157), were;(a) that the hereditary basis of the Lords should be eliminated,thereby avoiding an in-built majority for any party!(b) that the Government of the day should be able to secure areasonable working majority over both Opposition Parties;(c) that the power of the Lords to delay legislation should be restricted and their power be abolished to withhold consent to subordinate legislation against the will of the Commons;(d) that the reformed House of Lords should develop as a partof a modern Parliamentary structure complementing, butsubordinate to, the will of the Commons and with its functions and services more closely and efficiently integrated with thoseof the Commons.3.     At the beginning of the discussions we suggested that the simplestscheme would be a single-tier chamber, consisting only of nominatedpeers - i. e. life peers and hereditary peers of first creation, but excluding all the present peers by succession, except those few whov/ould have been given life peerages.     We also proposed the&quot;separate session&quot; procedure that had previously been endorsed bythe Cabinet (i. e. a scheme by which the present requirement for oneCOPY NO.    &quot; &apos;JCABINETDOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY!S GOVERNMENT)
year!s delay between second reading in the Commons in the first session and the repassing of the Bill in the Commons in the second session would be abolished so that the requirement would in effect becomeProrogation, followed by just over a month in the new session,, coupled with re-passage of the Bill in the Commons).    The Oppositions openingposition was that they wished to keep the hereditary principle, withhereditary peers remaining permanently at least as speaking membersof the House, and that, with a reformed composition, the powers of theHouse of Lords to delay measures should be increased rather thandecreased,.4.       We found in discussion with the Leaders of the Opposition Partiesthat we were able to move together on the basis of a two-tier schemewhich distinguished between -voting&quot; and 3speaking: members of the reformed house, essentially as described, in Annex II to C(67) 157(reproduced as an Annex to this paper).    The main features of thescheme as they emerged from the discussion are set out in thefollowing paragraphs.Composition5.       The reformed House would be based or. a two-tier structurecomprising voting peers with a right both to speak and vote, andspeaking peers with a right to speak but not vote.    The voting peers would constitute the working House and would consist of existing peersof first creation, supplemented by additional life peers created as necessary to give an appropriate size and balance between the political parties,,    On the Conservative side the addition would be made from existing peers by succession.    There would be upwards of 200 members;the precise number needs further consideration, but would depend partly on how many members were necessary for the efficient conduct ofbusiness.    They would be expected to give a substantial part of their time to the business of the House and would be paid provided that theyattended an appropriate proportion of sittings.    The relative strengths of the Parties would ensure the Government of the day an adequatemajority over other Parties^ but not of the House as a whole includingCross Benchers.6.       In addition to these working members there would be a numberof other members who would be entitled to speak but not vote.    These^speaking2 members would be those peers of first creation who becauseof other commitments preferred not to accept the obligations of fullworking and voting membership but would be able to make a valuable contribution to discussion from time to time.    In order to meet theOpposition^ point of view, they would also include existing peers bysuccession^, but only a.s a transitional measure and these would not beable to transmit their rights to their descendants.    Membership of the!speakingJ House would not be restricted to any particular number.7.       There would be likely to be a place in the reformed House for law Lords and Bishops, but the detailed arrangements require futher consideration.
8.       The negotiating Ministers were attracted by these proposals for two reasons,    First, peers by succession would be eliminated fromthe exercise of Parliamentary power in the Lords, wholly and immediately, subject only to the qua.Lifica.tion that a number ofprominent existing peers by succession would be created life peers and as such would in future sit in their own right as ordinary membersof the reformed House.    Secondly, the in^ built Conservative majority in the Lords would at one stroke by totally eliminated.    These are substantial gains from the Governments point of view.    the conservatives were attracted because existing peers by successionwould be able to retain their speaking rights in the House, though not to transmit these rights to their successors.    One aim of the two-tierstructure of the reformed House is indeed to meet the Conservativeson this point? and it can be argued that tho two-tier structure is complicated.    But the scheme nevertheless stands on its merits as thebest way of combining the two functions of a working legislative chamberand a debating chamber of distinction.    The speaking House would include a substantial number of life peers whose contributions to debate lend distinction to the House, and there would remain a place forthe cross-bench and expert element which forms a valuable part of itspresent membership.Powers9.       The scheme which emerged from discussion provides for a specified, period to be available to the House of Lords for considering a public Bill and for a further period of delay which the House couldimpose on the enactment of a Bill from the time when disagreement between the two Houses became apparent.    The period of delay would be capable of running over into the next session of a Parliament, and at theend of the period of delay the Bill could be presented for Royal Assentfollowing a simple resolution of the House of Commons.    The period would also be capable of running into the opening session of a new parliament, when the Bill could similarly be presented for Royal Assentfollowing a resolution of the new House of Commons.    The period forconsideration of the Bill would be two Parliamentary months!  theperiod of delay would be six calendar months.10.      The negotiating Ministers had offered first the ^separate session1proposals already described.    This proposal did not, however, commend itself since it v/as pointed out that any disagreement might be likely to occur in the summer when the Government vvould be able to hold aseparate session during the Long Recess,    There would thus be nodisturbance of the Parliamentary programme or any significant delay in the passage of legislation, and the Administration would not be compelled to give serious consideration to the Lords2 amendments.11.      The Opposition Leaders then argued that the scheme should provide for a period of delay after disagreement had becomeestablished, partly to give the Lords a genuine sanction which wouldforce the Government to consider their amendments, and partly to allowpublic opinion to express itself on the matter in dispute.    They proposed a period of nine months.    The negotiating Ministers at first proposedthat if there were to be a period of delay at all it should be related notto disagreement but to third reading in the Commons and should belimited to three months.    The Opposition could not accept this proposal
on the grounds that it would in effect mean in the case of a major bill delay of only some two or three weeks (the Lords take up to nine orten Parliamentary weeks to pa.ss major legislation at present).    TheOpposition thought that a delay of six months from disagreement mightbe acceptable, but the negotiating Ministers felt that it v/ould still be unreasonable until the Opposition proposed the very important concessionthat the period of delay should be capable of being carried over into thenext session or even the next Parliament.    This provision would havethe very important practical advantage of allowing the Government tosend a Bill to the Lords comparatively late in the session and3 even ifit were disagreed, to present it for Royal Assent without much loss ofParliamentary time in the second session.    It commended itself to the negotiating Ministers as achieving in practice the objective of protecting the Parliamentary timetable and as representing if anything animprovement on their original proposal from the point of view of flexibility and business management.     The objection that thisarrangement would constitute a precedent for extending the period forconsideration of legislation generally was considered and rejected, onthe grounds that the proceedings in the second session, would be limitedto a resolution of the House of Commons and v/ould in effect ha similarto the present Parliament Act procedure, but in a more modern form.12.      As regards subordinate legislation, the negotiating Ministerspropoeed that the Lords should be deprived of their existing light ineffect to veto any subordinate legislation, and that instead the House ofCommons should be able to override, by subsequent direction, the rejection by the House of Lords of a motion for any order requiringaffirmative resolution,    The operation of any negative resolution passed by the Lords would also be suspended for a period, and provision made for it to become ineffective if subsequently a correspondingresolution were rejected by the Commons or the instrument were approved by resolution of the Commons overriding the Lords resolution.These proposals were accepted in their entirety.Functions13.       In all the discussions with the Opposition Leaders, there hasbeen growing appreciation that all sides have been considering in a positive and constructive way the part which the House of Lords should play, both as a deliberative and as a scrutinising chamber, and thedirection in which it should develop as part of a modern Parliamentarystructure complementing the elected chamber but subordinate to itswill.    It has also been generally accepted, on all sides, that the reformed house as it develops will not seek to obstruct the Governmentslegislative programme but rather to identify issues on which it would be right to require the Administration to think again.    These issues are most likely to arise on subjects which are not in dispute between theParties as such, and none of those taking part in the discussionsenvisaged the reformed House rejecting a measure which formed animportant part of any Party:s political programme.    Finally, it hasbecome evident that the Opposition Leaders are anxious to find an agreedscheme for the reform of the House of Lords and that an extremelyfavourable climate now exists for completing the discussions as rapidly as possible,
Conclusions14. To sum up, the scheme achieves in full the Governmentsobjectives of abolishing;(a)the hereditary principle j(b) the built-in Conservative majority?  and(c) the power of the Lords to withhold consent to subordinate legislation.Although it retains power for the Lords to impose some delay in thepassage of a public Bill, an important &apos;carry-over&apos; provision is introduced which represents an effective safeguard for the crucialrequirement - the protection of the Parliamentary timetable - and it isparticularly attractive to the managers of Parliamentary business.    Thescheme also provides a basis for developing the House of Lords in a waycomplementary but subordinate to the House of Commons and for enablingit to take a full and valuable part in modern Parliamentary business.Finally, it is a scheme to which the Opposition might be expected toagree, and it might therefore be carried into law without the need to invoke the Parliament Act procedure, thus avoiding a disturbance ofthe present working relations with the Opposition in the Lords whichmight threaten or cause delay to the Government1^ legislative programmeover a period of a year or more.15.      For these reasons, the Cabinet is invited to approve the schemedescribed in this paper as a basis for further discussions with theOpposition Leaders.    If it is approved, and if the Opposition Leadersalso agree, it would seem right to publish, perhaps after the Budget,,a White Paper describing the scheme and the extent of the agreementbetween the Parties which it has been possible to achieve.    The cabinet is also invited to agree that the discussions with the Opposition Leadersshould have an agreed White Paper in view.G.Lord Chancellors Office, S.W.1.26th January, 1968
ANNEXA Plan for Reform of the LordsIntroductionIn their report last August (C(67) 145) the Ministerial Committeesaid that there appeared no satisfactory way of dealing in isolation withthe Lords&apos; powers j  and that if consideration of composition and functions were to be excluded, it would be better to leave well alone.    Theirreasons were, briefly, as followss(a) In the present situation (in which the House of Lords is effectivelydeterred from using its powers by the magnitude of the powers themselves)an alteration of powers alone might lead the Lords to abandon the restraintwith which they treat controversial commons legislation.(b) The introduction of legislation dealing only with powers would almost certainly lead the Opposition to propose amendments as tocomposition.(c) So limited ?, measure might inhibit the development of the Lordsas a revising and scrutinising chamber working as an integral part of abicameral legislature.Case for Reforms2.       The Ministerial Committee have further considered whether itwould be expedient to allow the House of Lords to continue as it is.They are against this for the following reasons?(a) The Government are committed in their Election Manifesto to the reform and modernisation of Parliament.    They cannot fulfilthis promise unless the composition and function of the Lordsare so changed as &quot;to reinforce the democratic element in modern Government&quot;.(b) Notwithstanding the view expressed in paragraph 1 there remainssome risk to a Labour Government from a FIou.se of Lords in itspresent form, both as regards Bills (particularly in the last year of a Parliament) and as regards subordinate legislation to whichthe Parliament Acts do not apply? and the Manifesto categori-cally states that there will be legislation to deal with the Lords1powers of delay.(c.)    There is strong evidence that both the Conservatives and the liberals are working on proposals for the reform of the composition and functions of the Lords.    If the government do not take the initiative at present available to them to reform the Lords, the other Parties will take the initiative from them.The Ministerial Committee have therefore concluded that there would bemuch to be gained, and nothing to be lost, by the Governments takingthe initiative in the coming Session.-6-
Desirability of a Consensus3.       It is clearly desirable that a constitutional reform of such weightas is now proposed should proceed by consensus;  or at any rate that theproposals should command some degree of acquiescence by the opposition parties, if not their active support.    There is reason to believe that aconsiderable measure of agreement cOuld be reached on a &quot;two-tier&quot;system as described in the following paragraphs.4.       These proposals are therefore expressly designed to describe the result which might emerge from negotiation, without necessarilyruling out other kinds of relorm0     The statement proposed for TheOueen&apos;s Speech in the covering memorandum would leave us free, if negotiations broke down, either to proceed unilaterally with the schemewe now propose or adopt some other solution.Proposals for Reform5.       In outline, the scheme would at once deprive the hereditarypeerage of effective power in the House of Lords.    The exclusionwould be total as regards future recruitment from the hereditarypeerage.    Existing hereditary members would be excluded from voting, but permitted to attend and speak.    Effective power v/ould be concentrated in a newly appointed voting House.     This voting House,composed essentially of Peers of first creations would be so arranged as to give the Government a working majority over the tv/o mainOpposition Parties.    But the House would still include in iis membershipthose independent-minded individuals of distinction whose contributionsrthough occasional, are of undoubted excellence? for example, scientists and similar specialists.6.       The scheme that the Committee now recommend is as follows.All Peers of first creation (whether they have been created Life Peersor Hereditary Peers) would be offered the voting writ.    An examinationof the individual circumstances of Peers of first creation has suggestedthat a considerable number would not be prepared to accept theobligations of a voting Peer.    Many of therm especially amongst the conservatives, are elderly and scarcely ever attend, while otherscan find time to do so only on occasion.    Jt would be open to them torefuse the voting writ and to opt instead for a speaking writ.    Thosewho undertook the obligations of a voting writ would be expected toattend frequently and play a full part in the increased work of are formed House more closely integrated with, and complementary to,the House of Commons.    There v/ould be a retirement age (probablyaround 75) for voting Peers.7.      For the reasons given in paragraph 6 it is likely that it will benecessary to supplement the number of voting Peers of first creation,both to enable them to fulfil the functions required of them and to ensurethe retention as voting Peers of a number of the better hereditary Peers,mostly Conservatives, who attend regularly.    All hereditary Peers thuschosen would be made Life Peers so that they could, sit and vote by virtueof appointment and not by hereditary right.    It would be for the party leaders on the invitation of the Prime Minister to make recommendations to him for these appointments.-7-
8.       Though these additions from the ranks of the hereditaries wouldbe likely to include a number of the more valuable and assiduousmembers of the Lords, they v/ould still be only a small minority of present Peers by succession,,    The question then remains whether togrant a speaking writ to the remaining hereditary Peers for theirlifetime only.    Though it can be argued that the inclusion of hereditary peers is not an essential part of a two-tier scheme it is a means bywhich &quot;power&quot; could be more painlessly removed from hereditary Peers.The right to speak would also keep, as members of the House, a numberof distinguished individuals who v/ould be unlikely to attend regularly.It could greatly help to ensure a speedier and easier passage of the reform, without a major political battle and the consequent waste ofParliamentary time.9.      A number of points of detail arise in connection with a majorreform of the Lords.    For example, there is the representation ofBishops and Law Lords,    It is possible to accommodate them (perhapson a reduced scale) within the scheme.     Other questions includeadministrative arrangements, pay, procedure and of course the foimof the necessary legislation.    These are under study by Ministers and officials.Functions of Procedure10.      It is impossible to consider a meaningful reform of compositionwithout also considering changes in functions and procedure.    Theobject is to improve the efficiency of Parliament and to relieve the commons of some of its routine work by enabling the Lords to carry a heavier Parliamentary load, particularly in the less controversialfields of legislation.    More Bills of secondary importance might startin the Lords and it might even be possible to devise a system wherebyall stages of certain Bills need not be taken in both Houses; for example^Law Commission Bills might be taken first in the Lords and only brieflyin the Commons, with very limited debate there (cf. Consolidation Bills).Possibly the Lords could also shoulder more routine work on subordinate legislation and private legislation.    Some of these suggestions mayhowever have to wait upon negotiation between the two Houses afterthe reformed Lords has been constituted.Powers11,       If functions are to be so transferred, the Government will need to be reasonably sure of getting its business through, and therefore tohave a small working majority over the Opposition Parties.    But sincethe Cross Benchers in practice rarely vote (and when a few do, theyeither break even or tend to support the Government of the day) it isconsidered unnecessary to have an automatic majority of the wholeHouse, which could be difficult to defend and less conducive to a responsible attitude in the House,
12.       In theory, however, the Opposition Parties, together with CrossBenchers and perhaps even a few Party rebels, might combine to reject Government proposals.    It is therefore necessary to furthersecure the position of the Government, particularly in the last year of a Parliament.    While the Government could in the last instanceenforce its v/ili by &quot;swamping&quot; (with the new composition It is unlikelythat many new creations of Peers would be required), the years delayenjoined by the present Parliament Act should still be removed.    the commons could then pass the Bill again over the heads of the Lords ina new Session which could follow immediately.    Similarly, the commons should have the power to over-ride the Lords on subordinate legislation.These sanctions should give the Government sufficient control to ignore the theoretical capacity of a reformed House of Lords to thwart the will of the Commons.Conclusion13.       There is an opportunity for reform and the words in the manifesto enjoin it on us.    The Opposition are undoubtedly consideringreform and could produce proposals of a much less attractive kind thanthese.    On the other hand they will rightly fear that they would loseheavily if they did not enter into negotiation.    Whatever chey might hope to save, it would be only the shadow, for we should not give wayon any major issue of substance.14.      The effect of our proposals would be that the hereditary peers would immediately and totally lose their legislative power and wouldbe eliminated from Parliament altogether after a transitional period.At the same time the powers of the Lords would be so reduced thatthe elected majority in the Commons could always prevail.    TheHouse of Lords, thus reduced, could play a fuller and more usefulcomplementary role to the Commons, while in no sense being a rivalin power or authority.-9-


</content>
</cab>
