<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/73/0 images: 89-90</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
)secret(55) 612th January,1955COPY NO.&quot;70CABINETMUSCAT AND OMAN; ASSISTANCE TO THE SULTANMemorandum by the Secrete-ry of State for Foreign AffairsThe independent Sultanate of Muscat and Oman has a long historyof friendship with Britain.    We afforded the Sultan military assistance against the inland tribes in 1913;  we have on occasion lent him money andsupplied him with arms;  and we obtained for the Royal Air Force, duringthe last war, staging facilities (which we still possess) at Masirah andSalalah in th2 Sultan!s dominions.     We are also acting on his behalf inthe Buraimi affair, on which arbitration is about to begin,,2.     Recent developments in Central Oman, a region which the Sultanhas always claimed but over which his authority has never been clearlyasserted, seem likely to make the Sultanate much more important in thenear future.    Prospectors of the Iraq Petroleum Company, guarded by a unit of the Sultan&apos;s forces, have found such promising oil prospects in central Oman that the Company is preparing to spend something like If millions in order to get drilling operations started there by the endof the year.    The economic and strategic advantages to this country ofa major oil strike by a British Company, in an area outside the persian gulf and well removed from the vulnerable northern fringe of the middle east, need no emphasis.3.      The tribes in the vicinity of these oil operations are friendly tothe Sultan.     But just beyond their tribal lands are pro-Saudi factions anda religious dignitary, known as the Imam, who disputes the Sultanssclaim to Central Oman and who is being encouraged by the Saudis to maketrouble.4.      Further to the west, in the Sultan&apos;s province of Dhofar, there is alsolikelihood of trouble from the Saudis, who have protested against theoperations there of a United States Oil Company, named City Services,which holds a concession from the Sultan for that part of his dominions.Here the Saudis are even better placed to intervene than they are in central Oman.    In neither case is the Sultan&apos;s (or Saudi) frontierdefined, still less demarcated.    But whereas in Central Oman, accordingto the Saudis, the tribes are independent and Saudi intervention there islikely to be only at secondhand, in Dhofar the Saudis have territorialclaims of their own.    Those claims were last discussed seriously in1935, King Ibn Saud claiming one line of frontier and we, on the Sultan&apos;behalf, offering another.    The negotiations broke down;  and the regionin which the City Services Company is now operating lies between thetwo lines.
5.     A recent report from Muscat,apparently well authenticated, saidthat Turki bin Ataishan was gathering a force together in the desert north of Dhofar, apparently with intent to enter the region of oil operations,,It will be recalled that it was Turki who established himself at BuraimiOasis and held it, against our blockade, for so long.    This report mayor may not be well founded;  but we should be prudent to assume thatthe Saudis will make trouble for us in that area.6.      The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on my instructions, has gone to Salalah to discuss the situation with the Sultan and to ascertain hisplans.    The Resident will also suggest to the Sulian that we should tell the Saudis forthwith, on his behalf, that the area of the City ServiceCompany&apos;s oil operations is within the Sultan&apos;s province of Dhofar, andthat he is prepared to resist any incursion into it.7.      I am sure that we must help the Sultan, by all means at our disposal, to strengthen his forces both in Central Oman and in Dhofarjand speed is essential.    After securing the assent of the Treasury atdepartmental level, I have -(a) authorised the Political Resident to tell the Sultan thatwe shall be ready to make available to him arms andequipment for the further 400 soldiers we know he isthinking of raising;  and(b) arranged with the Air Ministry that the Air OfficerCommanding, Aden, shall if possible provide (i) air transport between ivlasirah and Salalah (see paragraph 1above) for a detachment to reinforce the Sultan&apos;s posts in Northern Dhofar;  and (ii) wireless sets and Araboperators for inter-communication between those posts and Salalah.8.      The cost of the material at (a) above will be in the region of 150,000.    We are suggesting to the Sultan that this should be treated asa loan, to be repaid on conditions to be discussed at leisure.    But i hope that the Iraq Petroleum Company, operating in Central Oman, willbe ready to assist in discharging any debt the Sultan may incur, andthis question is being taken up with the Managing Director of the Company.The War Office have the material ready for despatch as soon as we hearthat the Sultan accepts our offer,9.      The Colonial Office and the Air Ministry have been good enough to instruct the appropriate authorities in Aden to consult together with aview to reporting on the further assistance, by air and on the ground,that might if necessary be provided for the Sultan.    It is not easy to fore-cast what aid or intervention might be needed but we must know, as soonas possible, what we may dispose of in the event of an emergency,10o    I ask the Cabinet -(i) to approve the preliminary measures that I have taken;and(ii)  to agree in principle that Her Majesty&apos;s Governmentshould support the Sultan in resisting Saudi incursionor pressure.AJ5 0Foreign Office, S, Wc 1011th January, 1955.

</content>
</cab>
