<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/73/0 images: 370-374</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-  THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY^  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1955CONFIDENTIAL Copy No. 71C. (55) 4823rd February, 1955CABINETINTERNATIONAL LABOUR organisation memorandum by the Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Labourand National service in accordance with the Constitution of the International Labour Organisationit is our practice to inform Parliament of the Government&apos;s proposals on reccomendatons and Conventions adopted at sessions of the InternationalLabour Conference. This Memorandum contains proposals on two Recommenda-tions adopted by the Conference in 1953 and two Conventions adopted in 1948.It is proposed to inform Parliament at the same time that a correction has been necessary to a declaration made on behalf of Southern Rhodesia in respect of an earlier Convention.2. The Annex to this paper contains a summary of these recommendations and Conventions and sets out the considerations that have led to the present proposals, which are as follows:  (i) that partial effect should be given to Recommendation No. 96 (concerningthe Minimum Age of Admission to Work Underground in Coal Mines)to the extent of existing legislation and by appointing 1st July, 1957,the date after which no boy under 16 may be employed undergroundexcept for specified training;(ii) that Recommendation No. 97 (concerning the Protection of the Health ofWorkers in Places of Employment) should be declared acceptablesubject to three detailed reservations and a general reservation on non-\.   industrial employment;(iii) that owing to the continued need in present circumstances for theemployment of a limited number of women and young persons in industrial establishments at night, the Government must defer a finaldecision on Conventions Nos. 89 and 90 concerning the Night Work ofWomen and Young Persons employed in Industry.3. The Minister of Fuel and Power is in agreement with these proposals sofar as they relate to mines and quarries, and the concurrence of other Departmentsconcerned has been obtained. The Ministry of Labour and National Insurance ofNorthern Ireland have been consulted and concur in the action proposed exceptfor Recommendation No. 96 with which Northern Ireland is not concerned ascoal production there is negligible.4. If these proposals are approved, authority is sought for the presentation to Parliament of a White Paper which will be based on the Annex and which Ishall circulate to the Cabinet for information in due course.H. W.Ministry of Labour and National Service, S.W. 1,17th February, 1955.47677
Recommendation (No. 96) Concerning the Minimum Age of Admission to WorkUnderground in Coal Mines1. This Recommendation, the text of which was presented to Parliament in cmd 9023, contains two provisions. First it prohibits the underground employ-ment in coal mines of young persons under 16 years of age. Secondly it providesthat young persons between the ages of 16 and 18 should not be employedunderground in coal mining except for certain purposes or under certain conditions.2. As regards the first provision, the existing law does not prohibit theemployment of boys under 16 below ground in coal mining, and the presentmanpower situation in the mines makes it undesirable to do so. Any suchprohibition before the school-leaving age is raised to 16 (when compliance withthis provision of the Recommendation will become automatic) would make itdifficult to recruit and retain the boys on whom the future of coal productiondepends. The coal industry must be able to compete with other industries in the recruitment of school leavers, for experience has shown that boys who have taken up other employment on leaving school are less inclined to change later to employment in the mines. In theory, the industry could recruit school leaversand employ them on the surface until they are 16, but many boys would leavethe industry if they were kept for nearly a year on uninteresting surface work andnot allowed to go underground even for training.3. In order to secure a measure of conformity with this provision of theRecommendation before the school-leaving age is raised, however, the Ministerof Fuel and Power proposes to avail himself of a provision in the Mines andQuarries Act, 1954, which empowers him to appoint a date after which no boyunder 16 may be employed underground in any mine except for purposes oftraining. After consultation with the Chairman of the National Coal Board theMinister of Fuel and Power proposes that the appointed date should be fixed as1st July, 1957, to allow sufficient time for the Coal Board to make the necessary preparations. After this date no boy under 16 would be employed undergroundexcept for training purposes. The type of training for which boys would beallowed to go underground would be prescribed by regulations made afterconsultation with both sides of industry. The proposal will not enable full effectto be given in 1957 to this provision of the Recommendation, which precludesemployment underground even for training purposes, but it is not thought desirableto go further, for the reasons given above. The intention to make an Order underthe Mines and Quarries Act, 1954. for this purpose would be stated in the white paper announcing the Government^ proposals for action on the Recommendation.4. With regard to the second provision of the Recommendation, under whichyoung persons between the ages of 16 and 18 may not be employed undergroundin coal mining except:  (a) for purposes of apprenticeship or other systematic vocational training under adequate supervision by competent and experienced persons, or(b) under conditions determined by the competent authority after consultationwith the employers&apos; and workers&apos; organisations concerned relating tothe places of work and the occupations permitted and the measuresof systematic medical and safety supervision to be applied,the law and practice in the United Kingdom are in general in conformity with alternative (b) except that the places of work underground which may be permittedfor male young persons between 16 and 18 years of age are not directly prescribed by the Government. The object of this provision is, however, secured by a systemof statutory medical examinations under which young persons are not passed fit for underground work unless they are considered able to undertake any work whichthey may be called upon to perform during the early years of their employment.This system provides, in effect, all the necessary safeguards in relation to the places of work in which such persons are employed. It is not proposed in thecircumstances to take action to secure greater conformity with this provision.Recommendation (No. 97) Concerning the Protection of the Health of Workers in places of employment. The substantive provisions of the Recommendation are in four parts. Thefirst of these deals with technical measures for the control of health risks.   The47677
second calls for medical examinations for workers employed in occupationsinvolving special risks to their health. The third makes provision for the notification of cases and suspected cases of occupational disease, and the fourthfor first aid facilities. The text of the Recommendation was presented toParliament in Cmd. 9023.6. In the field of industrial employment, in which the majority of health risksare encountered, the law and practice in the United Kingdom are, in general, inconformity with the provisions of the Recommendation. There are, however,certain of the detailed requirements of the Recommendation which are not atpresent covered by legislation and in regard to which it is considered unnecessaryor impracticable for the Government to introduce legislation or to take other actionto secure compliance. While these points need not prevent the acceptance of theRecommendation as a whole it will be necessary to make reservations in regard tothem. Paragraph 8 below contains particulars of the provisions in question, thereasons why reservations are necessary, and where appropriate the nature of the comments which it is proposed to make in the White Paper announcing theGovernment^ proposals for action on the Recommendation.7. In addition to the reservations on particular points it is also necessary tomake a general reservation in regard to the field of non-industrial employment,including agriculture and transport. The scope of the Recommendation is not confined to industrial establishments but covers all places of work, though many ofits stipulations are obviously inappropriate outside the industrial field. while there are legislative provisions concerning or affecting the protection of the health of workers in certain types of non-industrial employment, these are limited both in character and in scope. The possibility of introducing more comprehensivelegislation for the protection of the health of workers in a wide field of non-industrial employments in Great Britain is under consideration by the government but it is not, at this stage, possible to foresee how far such legislation will conform with the Recommendation, the provisions of which will be taken into account, orto predict the date of its introduction. It will be necessary to make this clear inthe White Paper.8. The provisions of the Recommendation on which particular reservationsare necessary are as follows: -(a) Paragraph 2 (h) calls for measures to eliminate or reduce harmful noiseor vibrations. The principle is entirely acceptable but it is consideredimpracticable to legislate in the present state of knowledge on thesubject.(b) Paragraph 13 says:  (i) That   medical  examinations   made   in   accordance   with   theJ Recommendation should not involve the worker in any expense.(ii) That deductions should not be made from wages where time is lost through attending a medical examination in cases where the matter is dealt with in laws or regulations, and where the matter is dealtwith by collective agreement, the position should be as determinedby the relevant agreement.So far as fees are concerned, the employer is required to pay the feesfor medical examinations carried out under the provisions of the factories Acts and under Regulations made under the Coal Mines Act.As regards out-of-pocket expenses and loss of earnings, existing legislation is designed to ensure that as far as reasonably practicablestatutory medical examinations are carried out at or near to the placeof work so as to avoid any loss to the worker. It is not considered that legislation should go further than this and it is proposed to say in theWhite Paper that this is the Governments view.(c) Paragraphs 14-17 deal with the notification of cases and suspected cases of occupational disease. While the paragraphs are generally acceptablethere are three points of difficulty:-(i) The Recommendation requires notification to the Labourinspectorate or other authority concerned with the protection ofworkers&apos; health. In the case of mines and quarries existing legisla-tion does not provide for direct notification; reliance is placed upon
information made available by the Ministry of Pensions and national Insurance, and this method of obtaining information is working satisfactorily.(ii) The Recommendation stipulates that a time limit should be set fornotification in cases where immediate notification is required.To implement this would weaken existing factory legislation in theUnited Kingdom, which requires immediate notification withoutany period of grace.(iii) The Recommendation lays down in detail the information whichshould be contained in notifications. The information specified,even if it could be obtained, might be misleading and it isconsidered preferable to maintain the practice in the UnitedKingdom of obtaining detailed information through aninvestigating officer.It is proposed to cover these points by a general reservation on thefollowing lines: the Government agree that the authorities concernedwith the protection of the health of workers should have adequateinformation about the occurrence of cases of occupational disease;arrangements to this end already exist in respect of factory workers and workers in mines and quarries; these arrangements do not correspond in all respects to the very detailed provisions of theRecommendation but they are well tried and work satisfactorily inpractice; the Government do not therefore propose to alter them.Convention (No. 89) Concerning Night Work of Women employed in Industry(Revised) 1948.Convention (No. 90) Concerning the Night Work of Young Persons employed in industry (Revised) 19489. These two Conventions were adopted by the International LabourConference in 1948 and their texts were presented to Parliament in Cmd. 7638 inFebruary, 1949. It has not so far been possible to make any statement about the conventions but it is proposed to do this in the White Paper now envisaged. the conventions restrict night work for women and young persons respectively in industrial establishments. Permanent legislation in the United Kingdom is in accord with Convention 89 and except in the case of coal mining is largely in accord with Convention 90.* Under emergency legislation, however, a limited amount of night work for women and male young persons is authorised in caseswhere the work cannot be performed by other means and where it is essential inthe national interest for it to be done. In present circumstances it is necessaryto retain this more flexible approach to night work and to defer reaching a finaldecision on the ratification of these two Conventions. This would be explained inthe White Paper.Convention No. 83.   Southern Rhodesia10. It is also proposed to make use of the present opportunity to inform parliament of a correction which it has been necessary to make to a declarationof acceptance of Convention No. 83 on behalf of Southern Rhodesia. ThisConvention, which was ratified by the United Kingdom in March, 1950, but has not yet come into force, provides for the application to non-metropolitan territories of a number of earlier Conventions adopted by the InternationalLabour Conference. The Convention was accepted on behalf of SouthernRhodesia; owing to an error, however, the declaration omitted to state a modification which would be made in the application to the territory of one of theearlier Conventions. The declaration of acceptance has now been rectified andthe Director-General of the International Labour Office has formally recorded therectified text. The matter is being reported to Parliament because the originaldeclaration was laid before Parliament in Cmd. 7865.* In the case of coal mines the new Mines and Quarries Act will bring the law into conformitywith Convention 90 but it will not come into operation until a day to be appointed by the Ministerof Fuel and Power. Even then night work for young persons between 16 and 18 will be permitted in three counties under a special exception which must, however, terminate not later than five yearsafter the coming into force of the Act.


</content>
</cab>
