<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/38/41 images: 406-415</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1943.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.W.P. (43) 291.2nd July, 1943!&apos; WAR CABINET.THE FRENCH COMMITTEE OF NATIONAL LIBERATION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,TFIE French Committee of. National Liberation was constituted at Algierson the 3rd June. It was composed of General de Gaulle and General Giraudas Presidents, General Catroux, General Georges, M. Massigli, M. Jean Monnetand M. Andre Philip. It was stated in the declaration which was published that the Committee would be completed later by the addition of other members.2. On the 7th June I received a communication on behalf of the newlyformed Committee informing me of its formation and expressing the Committee&apos;confidence that His Majesty&apos;s Government would recognise it as &quot; the bodyqualified to ensure the conduct of the French effort in the war within the frame-work of inter-Allied co-operation as well as the administration and the defenceof ail French interests.&quot;3. A translation of this communication and of the declaration which accompanied it is annexed to this memorandum.4. In a telegram, dated the 8th June, the Resident-Minister at Algiersreported that the French Committee of National Liberation had published anannouncement stating that it had decided to create Commissariats- for thedischarge of public business and that the Committee had allotted the followingCommissariats: Foreign Affairs, M. Massigli; Co-ordination of MussulmanAffairs, General Catfoux; Rearmament, Supply and Reconstruction, M. Monnet;Colonies, M. Pleven; Communications and Merchant Navy, M. Mayer; Informa-tion, M. Henri Bonnet; Interior, M. Philip; Justice, Education and PublicHealth, M. Abadie; Finance, M. Couve de Murville; Production and Commerce,M. Diethelm; Labour and Social Security, M. Tixier. At the same time, all those who were nominated Commissioners were appointed to be members of theCommittee of Liberation, which was thus composed of 14 members. The relevantdecrees were no  published until some days later.5. I was on the point of instructing His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador atWashington to put certain suggestions regarding the recognition of theCommittee to the United States Government, since it seemed to me essentialthat both Governments should adopt the same line, when a developmentoccurred at Algiers which rendered it necessary for this action to be postponed.This development concerned the question of the command and the control of theFrench fighting forces. The details of the dispute between General de gaulle and General Giraud over this question did not fall within the scope of thismemorandum. It looked, however, at one moment as if the discussions amongthe French might drag on in such a way that the security of the Allied base and lines of communications in North Africa might be threatened. In view ofthis danger, His Majesty&apos;s Government and the United States government decided that the Allied Commander-imChief should tell General Giraud andGeneral de Gaulle what his minimum requirements were in North Africa asregards control of the French forces. On the 19th June General Eisenhowerreceived the two Generals and made it clear to them that in view of his responsibilities and impending operations he must insist on effective control ofthe French, forces being in the hands of General Giraud, with whom he had worked during recent months.   He appealed to both Generals, ias a soldier to[25673]
soldiers, to accept this view. He did not intend to interfere with any internalorganisation that the French Committee might decide upon; his sole require-ment was that there should be a Commander-in-Chief, that General Giraudshould be that Commander-in-Chief and that he (General Eisenhower) shouldbe satisfied that the organisation was such that the Commander-in-Chief had.effective and proper control of the army in its widest sense.6. This intervention was reported by Mr. Macmillan to have aroused con-siderable resentment among all Frenchmen in Algiers whatever their politicalcomplexion. Yet it no doubt hastened the solution of the crisis which was finallyreached by the Committee on the 22nd June. The solution was that the Com-mittee controlled the French land, naval and air forces; a permanent military committee was constituted, composed of General Giraud and General de Gaulle,with their respective military, naval and air Chiefs of Staff; General Giraud wasCommander-in-Chief in French North and West Africa; and General de GaulleCommander-in-Chief of the French forces in the remainder of the Empire. BothGeneral Eisenhower and Mr. Macmillan recommended acceptance of this arrange-ment. His Majesty&apos;s Government and the United States Government, however,decided that the moment had not yet arrived to accord any degree of recognitionand that we should wait and see how the Committee behaved.7. Mr. Macmillan has since reported that the civilian members of the french committee claim credit for the solution reached, which they apparently forced inthe face of considerable opposition from both General Giraud and General de gaulle. This development is important. The civilian members had becomeimpatient of the seemingly endless wrangle between the two Generals on thesubject of command and genuinely wanted to get- down to their variousdepartmental duties, which needed urgent attention. Mr. Macmillan also pointedout that this awakened sense of responsibility was all to the good, that neitherGeneral, was used to the system of collective responsibility, and that the effectivefunctioning of the Committee would be dependent upon the strength, and ability of the civilian element.8. There has been a further development which affects our study of this question. The United States Government are strongly opposed toGeneral de Gaulle and his followers, and would prefer that he should not be amember of the French Committee. Indeed, they would have preferred, had itbeen possible, to deal with General Giraud alone and to relegate any committeeto a purely subordinate role. They have inspired comment in the United Statespress to the effect that His Majesty&apos;s Government have dropped General de gaulle and have come round to the American view that General Giraud is the man who should be supported. This attitude of the United States Government hasled to some outspoken comment in the United States press. Mr. Walter Lippman,for example, has declared : r&apos; The situation we have now produced will not remain as it is now. Whatever chance General Giraud ever had of leading french national resistance has been profoundly prejudiced because our denial of theauthority of the French Committee for National Liberation in Algiers has placedGeneral Giraud in the unhappy position of deriving his authority solely from washington and London, and this is no way to make him popular in France.&quot;This comment is pertinent. The more the Americans single out Giraud for their favour, the more harm they do him in French eyes, with corresponding advantage to, de Gaulle.9. The War Cabinet agreed on the 28th June that it was very desirablethat we should take action which would build up the authority of the civilianmembers of the Committee of National Liberation but that, bearing in mind the American attitude, it would probably be undesirable to accord formal recognition at this stage.10. The most effective means of building up the authority.of the Committee,however, lies in our granting it some form of recognition. Until such recognitionis given by the British and United States Governments, we shall find it difficultto persuade the press and public opinion that our policy is to build up theCommittee itself on the basis of collective responsibility, and that it is not our policy to back one French General or another. We must make it clear that ourrelations henceforth are with the Committee as a whole and not with individualGenerals.11. Moreover, the Soviet Government are anxious to recognise theCommittee and have only delayed their recognition at our request.. It may be
difficult to persuade them to delay action much longer. Of lesser countries, theBelgian, Luxemburg and Uruguayan Governments have already recognised theCommittee. -     &apos;12. I would therefore ask my. colleagues to authorise me to take . up thequestion of recognition with the United States and Soviet Governments. I would suggest recognition on the following lines : &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government are happy to recognise the french committee of National Liberation as administering those parts of the Frenchoverseas empire which acknowledge their authority, and as having assumed the functions of the former French National Committee in respect of territories in the Levant. They also recognise -it as the body qualified toensure the conduct of the French effort in the war within the framework of inter-Allied co-operation as well as, in principle, the administration and defence of French interests. The practical application of this principle to thedifferent categories of French interests must be reserved for consideration in each case as it arises.&quot; His Majesty&apos;s Government have taken note of the Committee&apos;determination to continue the common struggle, in close co-operation withall the Allies, until French and Allied territories are completely liberatedand until victory is complete over all the enemy powers. They count on theCommittee to afford such facilities in the military and economic sphere inthe territories under their administration as may be required by theGovernments of the United Nations for the prosecution of the war. Inrespect of certain of these territories, agreements already exist between theFrench authorities and the British or United States authorities. Thecreation of the French Committee of National Liberation may make itnecessary to revise these agreements, and pending their revision all such agreements concluded since June 1940, except in so far as these have beenautomatically made inapplicable by.the formation of the French Committeeof National Liberation, will remain in force.&quot; .A. E.Foreign Office, 2nd July 1943.ANNEX.M. Vienot to Mr.. Eden.(Translation.) i-l -   &apos;M. le Ministre, 4 Carlton Gardens, S.W. 1.I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the French Committeeof National Liberation was constituted at Algiers on the 3rd June, 1943.I enclose herein the text of the Declaration of the same date, in which theCommittee announces its creation, states its attributions and sets forth its aims.In instructing me to inform you of its formation, the French Committee ofNational Liberation has asked me to transmit to you the expression of its confidenthope that His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government will recognise it as the Bpdyqualified to ensure the conduct of the French effort in the war within the frame-work of inter-Allied co-operation as well as the administration and defence of all french interests.Please accept, M. le Ministre, the assurances of my high consideration.(Signed) P. VIENOT.Declaration of the French Committee for National Liberation of the3rd June, 1943.(Translation.)Generals de Gaulle and Giraud as Presidents, General Catroux, general george, Messrs. Rene Massigli, Jean Monnet and Andre Philip as members,constitute the French Committee for National Liberation. This committee willlater be completed by addition of other members.The Committee thus constituted is the central French power.The Committee direct the French war effort in all its forms and in all places.Consequently, it exercises French sovereignty on all territories not subject to thepower of the enemy. It undertakes the administration and the defence of all french interests in the world.   It assumes authority over the territories and the
land, sea and air forces which up to the present have been under the authority ofthe French National Committee and of the Civil and Military Commander-in-Chief.All necessary steps to bring about the fusion of the administrationsdependent on these two bodies will be taken without delay by the Committee. Inaccordance with the letters exchanged between Generals Giraud and de Gaulle,the Committee will relinquish its., powers to the provisional Government whichwill be constituted in conformity with the laws of the Republic as soon as the liberation of, metropolitan territory permits, and at latest upon completion of the liberation of France. The Committee, in close co-operation with all the Allies,will continue the common struggle with a view to the complete liberation of Frenchand Allied territories until -victory is complete over all the enemy Powers.The Committee solemnly undertakes to re-establish all French liberties, the laws of Republic and the Republican regime through the complete destructionof the regime of arbitrary authority and of personal power which is to-dayimposed upon the country. The Committee is at the service of the French people,whose war effort, whose resistance and whose trials,, as well as the necessary workof renovation, requires the union of all National forces.The Committee calls upon all Frenchmen to follow it in order that, throughstruggle and victory, France may regain her liberty, her greatness and hertraditional place amongst the great Allied Powers, and that in peace negotiationsFrance may be able to make its contribution to the Council of the.United nations which will settle the state of Europe and of the world after the war.







</content>
</cab>
