<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/90/7 images: 75-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT



COPY NO

CABINET

CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet

held at 10 Downing Street on

THURSDAY 28 JULY 1988

at 10.30 am

PRESENT

The Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MP

Prime Minister

[he Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey HowerOC

Secretary of State for Foreig&lt;D^fEC\

Commonwealth Affairs \(^s)

The Rt Hon Lord Mackay of ClashfeVfy^X

Lord Chancellor Vy/\

Lie Rt Hon Peter Walker MP

lecretary of State for Wales \S

The Rt Hon Tom King MP i

Secretary of State for Northern Ireland

pe Rt Hon Lord Young of Graffham

Secretary of State for Trade and

Industry

ffhe Rt Hon Kenneth Clarke QC MP

Secretary of State for Health

The Rt Hon Malcolm Rifkind QC MP

Secretary of State for Scotland

the Rt Hon John Moore MP

Secretary of State for Social Security

The Rt Hon The Lord Belstead

Lord Privy Seal

Ihe Rt Hon John Major MP

Chief Secretary, Treasury

The Rt Hon Nigel Lawson MP

Chancellor of the Exchequer

The Rt Hon Douglas Hurd MP

Secretary of State for the Home Department

&apos;^Os.he Rt Hon Norman Fowler MP

iilbcretary of State for Employment

whV^St Hon Nicholas Ridley MP

s^^Efertary of State for the Environment

Thi^RL^^Q Kenneth Baker MP

Secre^tarv^f State for Education and

Sc ienc^^S-&lt;\

The Rt HcfeO^mn MacGregor MP

Minister o\\Agriculture, Fisheries

and Food

The Rt Hon Paul Cha*H*on MP

Secretary of Statra^rcra Transport

The Rt Hon John Wak&lt;/ftain)liP

Lord President of twetfxmcil

The Rt Hon Cecil Parkin^pjKttK

Secretary of State for Ener^^

The Rt Hon Antony Newton MP &lt;X^/)

Chancellor of the Duchy of LaB*^^^

THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT

pe Rt Hon David Waddington QC MP

parliamentary Secretary, Treasury

The Rt Hon Peter Brooke MP

Paymaster General


SECRETARIAT

Sir Robin Butler

Mr R G Lavelle    (Items 5 and 6)

Mr P J Weston      (Items 5 and 6)

Mr A J Langdon    (Items 1-4)

Mr S S Mundy       (Items 1-4)

CONTENTS

tern		Subject	Page

1.	CABINET ^^WflCS		1

2.	PARLlAMENTAH^fFFAIRS		1

3.	HOME AFFAIRS		

	Police Pay		1

4.	NORTHERN IRELAND AFK 		1

5.	FOREIGN AFFAIRS		

	Iran/Iraq War		2

	Thailand		3

	Soviet Armenia		3

	Burma		3

	United States		3

6.	COMMUNITY AFFAIRS		

	Foreign Affairs	Council,  25 July	4

	Budget Council,	26 July ^	4




1.      THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Cabinet welcomed the Chancellor of

the Duchy of Lancaster as a new member following the recent Ministerial

changes.

i

 \       The Cabinet -

^1      Warmly endorsed the Prime Minister&apos;s comments.

 parliamentary

Iffairs

2. ^^KjpXabinet were informed of the business to be taken in the House

of ComqjO^^in the first week after the Summer Adjournment.

10ME AFFAIRS

&apos;olice Pay

&gt;revious

(eference:

;C(88) 17.2

3.      THE HOME/S CMTARY said that on the previous day agreement had been

reached at a m^^iftgvof the Police Negotiating Board (PNB) to a pay

increase of 8.5 Mrjtnt with effect from 1 September 1988 for police

officers in Englaxfcd^alJ Wales.    This was in line with the recommendation

of the 1978 Edmund-^&gt;a1?Ajrt report that police pay should be increased

annually in line witlfijn^Jfements in the index of average earnings over

the previous 12 monthsV*^[K had also been agreed that there should be a

one-year freeze on startirfg/Salaries for new recruits.    Contrary to the

impression which the medi^&apos;fiadj given,  the pay agreement did not

represent a full settlemen^jS^kplice pay and allowances issues and

there would now need to be dvfSowjlt further negotiations on allowances,

on which there had so far beeifo^rfa/real progress.    As had been agreed in

exhaustive discussions in the Tflra^&amp;erial Steering Committee on Economic

Strategy, Sub-Committee on Publl^S^tor Pay (E(PSP)) it would be

necessary to stand firm on those ^BueA and it seemed likely that the

staff side of the PNB would in due ^/&amp;$a take the matter to

arbitration.    At the end of the day,^^^&lt;ad the power to impose a

settlement if the importance of the cig^japstances justified it.

The Cabinet - V

Took note.

northern

IRELAND

affairs

Previous

Reference:

CC(88) 16.4

4.      THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR NORTHERN IRELAND ssrfohxpt there had

been a meeting the previous day of the Anglo-Irish Ipw^^pvernmental

Conference. As he had indicated publicly, the meeting&lt;^fa^^ een the most

encouraging which had taken place since the signing of th-^/Jflyglo-Irish

Agreement in terms of the atmosphere of co-operation ovev^efegurity which

had developed both between Ministers and between the Chiei^gjaraXable of

the Royal Ulster Constabulary (RUC) and the Commissioner of^i^varda

Siochana.    Despite poor health, the presence of the Tanaiste\\M^Brian

Lenihan, had been a helpful factor in contributing towards the^ywp^wed

relations.    The RUC and the Garda Siochana had agreed a number &apos;w )\


operational improvements,  including the establishment of a secure

telephone link between their two chief officers, which were useful steps

forward,  though it was perhaps surprising that they had not been put in

1   place earlier.    The Garda Siochana had recently made a number of

xvdiscoveries of weapons,  including a heavy machine gun and eight mortar

V^P^s, which were welcome in themselves and might also shed light on the

^Syoyisional Irish Republican Army&apos;s arrangements for obtaining weapons,

ftkpr &lt;&amp;hey were exchanging any information on these discoveries with the

i^yvro^ress remained slow, however, on reaching agreement on

e*cra#fr:ion matters.    It was clear that a good deal more work would be

req&lt;j&amp; e&lt;CNon that issue, though this would now take place in the improved

atmospJv6re^.which had been generated by the Prime Minister&apos;s exchange

with t4^/?aoiseach at the Hanover European Council and by the previous

day&apos;s mating.

The Cabinet -

Took not^^^

foreign

affairs

Iran/Iraq

War

Previous

Reference:

CC(88) 26.3

5.      THE FOREIGN ANj/j^tfobftWEALTH SECRETARY said that the Secretary

General of the Unitedvffa^rpcs, Mr Perez de Cuellar, had begun talks

separately in New York wOJ^Xhe Foreign Minister of Iran, Mr Ali Akbar

Velayati, and the Foreigrf^Mialster of Iraq, Mr Tariq Aziz, with a view

to securing a ceasefire.  vS^d^^sct meeting between the two Foreign

Ministers might be poss ibleyl^Nungs went well.    The Secretary General

had also sent a technical teraj^Q/ the region to prepare the ground for

United Nations observers to m^nLp^^a ceasefire.    But Iraq was proving

difficult and seemed determined^co/cress home her tactical advantage.

Iran was being more flexible.    Thj^Sartetary General had said that he

was discouraged but not despairing^# fc-^an early ceasefire could be

achieved.    Both Foreign Ministers wo^riWT^fxay on in New York for the time

being.    The United Kingdom would sust^^j^fressure on Iraq and hoped that

other members of the United Nations SeVurity Council would do likewise.

The outcome was not assured.    It seemedVsensible on a contingency basis

to look at the prospects in the Gulf and surrounding countries if a

ceasefire should be realised.    There would,  for^_example, be implications

for oil prices and for British trade with botyfpTnkn and Iraq.    He was

sending an official from the Foreign and Comm^owrt&amp;iih Office to Tehran

for a short visit during the second half of Aug f/t7)Yhus filling

temporarily the vacancy in British diplomatic re^*^^fktation since May

1987.    The objectives were to obtain better advico^fnMAe spot of what

was going on in Iran, to press for the release of tlhK^^h British

citizens in prison there, to assess the prospects fof^rA-^establishing a

permanent British diplomatic presence and to maintain rjjj^a^oxe over

British hostages in Lebanon, about whom there was no fr^&amp;Jrunformation.




THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that in Thailand, which the

Prime Minister would be visiting during August, the outgoing Thai Prime

V   Minister, Mr Prem Tinsulanonda, had declined to accept renomination.

)j   Instead, Mr Chatichai Choonhavan,  the leader of the Thai Nation Party

^^ofhich had emerged with the most votes from the general election on

&apos;&quot;^ZA. July, had accepted nomination as Prime Minister by the coalition

o^*a &quot;ties but the President of the National Assembly had not yet put his

pfime\to the King.    It was not clear to what extent the apparent

VitbAnawal of Mr Prem Tinsulanonda was tactical and whether he would

cd[jrcujxpe to exert real political influence.

Soviet

Armenia

Previous

Reference:

CC(88) 12.3

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the continuing troubles

in Soviet Armenia had met with tough response from the General Secretary

of the Communis^ J?arty of the Soviet Union, Mr Mikhail Gorbachev, who

appeared to beys&apos;Tgyalling that the limits of the political possibilities

had been reached*. remained to be seen whether the idea of upgrading

the enclave of Na^gonip-Karabakh to the status of autonomous republic

would be pur sued l^wje the strikes in cities such as Erevan and

Stepankert now app&lt;^era^fo be over, there was still much Armenian

frustration below th^^wUce.

I Burma

THE FOREIGN AND COMMON WEAL TJfl^E^ETARY said that following disturbances

in Rangoon on 21 July,  the CmUMn of the Burmese Socialist Programme

Party, U Ne Win, had resignedVy^fe^jad been replaced by a hard-liner,

U Sein Lwin, who had previously\^^njfce\d fourth in the Party hierarchy.

It was not clear whether U Ne Wit^JfacHdefinitely relinquished power.

But the underlying prospect was the^^mjj.iar pattern of pressure for

economic change and reform away froflCJrtS&amp;&apos;socialist model; the

reconfiguration of political forces w^^^reflection of this.

United States

Previous

Reference:

CC(88) 26.3

THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said ttfaT&gt;vit would be prudent

if Ministers in charge of Departments would myie^_Dlans for British

Ministerial visits to the United States dur ingyfre&apos;~Vter iod before the

United States Presidential Election in November \kod^A*v the period

between the Election and the Inauguration and lim]^/Oem to what was

strictly necessary for the pursuit of pressing Govevm^k\ business. The

Prime Minister would of course be visiting Washingto^yiflL vid-November

but there would then be a period during which the Reagan^^wpoinistration

was phased out and changes in Government posts would be^^da\by the

incoming Administration. x^^v^X

The Cabinet - V^f?

Took note. 1 ^/^^


FFA^^

&lt;^

oreign &lt;V

ffairs ^

louncil,

5 July

6.      THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that the meeting of the

Foreign Affairs Council on 25 July had had a light agenda.    The Greek

Presidency had given some publicity to what in reality had been an

i   uncontroversial discussion of relations between the Community and CMEA

^o^COMECON) member states.    It had been agreed that priority should be

^IjpLven to development of links with individual member states in cases

yyfdere the progress of economic reform justified it and a closer

yge^tionship would be mutually beneficial.    Agreement had also been

Veacm^d on the jurisdiction of the Court of First Instance which would

b^fiapx^l ing second order business such as staff issues,

udget

ouncil,

6 July

THE ^e^^CELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER said that at its meeting on 26 July the

Budgefl^^ncil had had a first reading of the 1989 budget. A

satisfactory agreement had been reached on a basis consistent with the

conclusions of the Brussels European Council.

The Cabinejt-^-

Took notkV^j^-x

Cabinet Office

28 July 1988



</content>
</cab>
