<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/17/0 images: 72-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  March 1950SECRETCM. (50)15th conclusions copy No. -&apos;isCABINET 15 (50)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 27th March, 1950, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.PThe Right Hon. Herbert MqrrisonM.P., Lord President of the council I The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Lord Chancellor.Viscount Jowitt,The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence,The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dai/ton, M.P.,Minister of Town and country planning.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborouc-h, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of State for economic affairs (Item 5).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 6-7).Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.The Right Hon. Maurice Webb, M.P.,Minister of Food (Item 5).
CABINET 15 (50.)contentsN0.12618SubjectEconomic Development in South a/nd /South-East A-siaBechuaualand ProtectorateChieftainship of the Bamangwato Tribe.Korth Atlantic PactIndiaIndo-PaMetan Relations.FoodRetail Price Increases.Local Government Boundary ExtensionsCouncil of EuropeGermany .Socialisation of Basic Industries.Page8181818182838484Minute346
EconomicDevelopmentla South andSouth-BastAsia.(previous reference:CM. (50) 13thConclusions,Minute 4.) 1BechuanalandProtectorateChieftainshipof the-  ,7..BamangwatoTribe.(Previous    1Beference:CM. (50) 131th fConclusions, -Minute 6.)north atlantic Pact.(previous reference:CM. (49) 31stConclusions,Minute 5.),, 1. The Prime Minister- informed the Cabinet that the Pay-?master-General had agreed to lead the United Kingdom delegation to the first meeting of the Consultative Committee on economic development in South and South-East Asia. The Paymaster--General&apos;s appointment as leader of this Delegation would be announced in the debate On foreign affairs which was to be held inthe House of Commons on the following day.i 2l The Lord President said that the leader of the liberal party in the House of Commons had given him notice that he would seek an opportunity, in the forthcoming debate on foreign affairs,to express nis views about the Governments handling of the claim of Seretse Khama to the chieftainship of the Bamangwato Tribe.This would not afford the House a convenient opportunity to discuss this matter; and the Chief Whip was ascertaining whether it wouldbe possible to arrange for two hours to be given to this subject inthe debate on the Motion to adjourn for the Easter Recess.3. The Foreign Secretary said that he had been hoping tobe able to arrange for a meeting of the Council of Atlantic PactPowers to be held in London in May, during the course of the visit of the United States Secretary of State. The French Governmenthad at first been reluctant to agree to this plan since they feared that the Soviet Government might regard such a meeting as pro-vocative. They had now, however, withdrawn their objections, and preparations for,the meeting were going forward.India- 4.   The Cabinet were informed that a very dangerous state ofIndo-Pakistan tension was developing between India and Pakistan. SubstantialRelations. numbers of Indian troops had been moved to positions very close to(Previous the Pakistan border. Knowledge of these troop movements had reference: reached the Government of Pakistan, who had urged the Govern-CM. (50) 13th ments of the United Kingdom, Australia, Canada and the united conclusions,. States to call upon the Government of India to state what inten-Minute 5). tions lay behind them. Before those representations were receivedfrom Pakistan, the United Kingdom High Commissioner in Delhihad already made enquiries at the highest official level and hadreceived a disquieting reply suggesting that, if any further riotingoccurred in Pakistan, the Government of India were prepared tosend their troops across the frontier to protect Hindu minorities.. The Cabinet agreed that this increasing tension made it evenmore important that the Security Council should proceed withoutfurther delay terthe appointment of a mediator in the Kashmirdispute. The best course would be for the United States and UnitedKingdom Governments to agree upon the most suitable choice andto join in pressing the other members of the Security Council to put this name forward without further consultation with the two partiesto the dispute. After some preliminary discussion of various indi-viduals who might be asked to undertake this duty The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister would discuss thismatter further with the Foreign Secretary and the Secre-tary of State for Commonwealth Relations later in the day,so that the Foreign Secretary might be put in a positionto urge the United States Government to join in pressing the Security Council to proceed at once to the appoint-ment of a mediator in the Kashmir dispute.
FqocL &amp;hRetail Price   &apos;.Increases, i(Previous-Reference:&apos;1   &apos;CM. (50) 14thConclusions,Minute 5.)5, The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Minister ofFood (CP; (50) 46 and 50) recommending that the retail prices of butter and bacon should be increased by 4rf. and 2d. a poundrespectively. *&apos;The Minister of Food said ,that, if expenditure on food subsidiesin 1950-51 was,to be limited to  410 million, and farmers were toreceive  18^ million towards their increased costs as agreed by theCabinet on 23rd March, the retail prices of food would have to beincreased by amounts which would produce some  18 million in afull year. It would not be practicable to spread these price increasesover a large number of commodities, and he had, therefore reachedthe conclusion that the savings heeded could best he secured by in-creasing the price of butter and bacon. The adjustments which he proposed would yield  17-5 million in a full year, and would in-volve an increase of -66 in the cost-?of-living index. If necessary,the announcement of these price increases could be deferred until19fch April, but it would be preferable to announce them at once.He ;COjuld announce at the same time his intention to increase the butter ration from 4 ito 5 ounces- He was not at present in a posi-tion to make any further ration concessions, but he was considering whether it would be possible to discontinue the points rationing scheme and he proposed to circulate a paper on this subject shortly.In, discussion, the following points wore made(a) As far as could be foreseen, the cost-of-living index was not likely to rise above 114 by the end of June; beyond that, accurateforecasts could not be made.(6) Ministers had hitherto been reluctant to sanction increases in the price of butter on account of their disproportionate effect onthe cost-of-living index. In consequence, butter was more heavily subsided than any other commodity and its present price was quite inconsistent with the general level of prices.(c) Would it be possible to compensate the consumer for thehigher price of butter by increasing, or even abolishing, themargarine ration, I The Minuter of fofld said that, it would notbe possible to discontinue the rationing of margarine; he would, how-ever, consider whether supplies would permit any increase in the ration.(d) It was suggested that the quality of margarine for cookingpurposes had deteriorated as the result of treatment to make it morepalatable, and that this might account for the fact that many people were not taking up  heir ration in full. The Minister of Food saidthat,, if people were making less use of margarine for cooking, thiswas more likely to be due to improvements in other forms of cookingfat, but he undertook to look into this question.(e) The general view of the Cabinet was that it would not be advisable to announce an increase in the butter ration at the sametime as the increase in price.(/) Some anxiety was expressed about the political effects ofan announcement that expenditure on food subsidies in 1950-51would be limited to  410 million as compared with  465 million in1949-50. Might it not be assumed that the level of food subsidieswas being drastically reduced at a time when there was great public anxiety about the high cost of living ? It was pointed out that this figure involved no alteration of policy. It had already been announced that certain subsidies, such as that on feeding-stuffs,would be discontinued, and  410 million merely represented themaximum limit on the existing basis after allowing for thosechanges. This had been fully explained by Ministers to the SpecialEconomic Committee of the Trades Union Congress in November.(g) Many people were unaware of the benefits derived fromthe system of food subsidies because they did not know the economicprice of subsidised commodities, it was suggested that, in announc-mg changes in the prices of subsidised commodities, ministers should normally indicate both the subsidised and the economic price.And could not shopkeepers be required to show clearly the coin-parative figures in their shops ?
The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the retail prices of butter and bacon should beincreased by 4d. and 2d. a pound respectively.(2) Authorised the Minister of Food to announce these changesas soon as possible, and invited him to consult with theChancellor of the Exchequer regarding the terms of theannouncement.(3) Agreed that the proposed increase in the butter ration: should not be announced for the present.(4) Invited the Minister of Food to consider the suggestionrecorded in paragraph (g) above.6. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofHealth (CP. (50) 44) on the attitude which the Government shouldadopts in present Parliamentary circumstances, towards PrivateBills providing for alterations in the areas or status of localauthorities.The Minister of Health recalled that, during the debates on theLocal Government Boundary Commission (Dissolution) Bill inNovember 1949, he had indicated that the Government were examin-ing the structure of local government and that, meanwhile, it was undesirable for county boroughs to seek extensions of boundary by private Bill, save where such changes were urgently necessary.Nevertheless, sixteen county borough councils and one borough council had promoted Bills for substantial extensions of boundaries,and two borough councils (Luton and Ilford) were seeking countyborough status. It seemed iundesirable that major changes in the structure of local government should be effected in this way under existing circumstances, and he therefore proposed to take steps to block all Private Bills of this type on Second Reading, on the groundthat only urgent changes should be made piece-meal, pending theresult oi &quot;the Governments consideration of the general question.It should, however, be recognised that the delay in reaching decisions on the reform of local government was likely to be much more pro-longed than had been contemplated in November. In the meantime,his intention was to refuse to agree to any extensions of local govern-ment boundaries except for the limited purpose of securing sites for housing purposes.In discussion there was general agreement that it would not be right to allow widespread adjustments in the present structure oflocal government to be made piece-meal by Local Acts while a comprehensive review was pending. The Cabinet also agreed that,an absolute rule could be maintained against allowing the creationof any new county boroughs pending the general review. ministers were doubtful, however, whether the need for housing sites shouldbe the sole reason for allowing changes iim local ^authority boundaries:There might be special cases in which an adjustment of boundarieswas urgently required on other grounds.; and the Minister wouldbe well-advised to leave himself with a rather wider discretion tomake exceptions from his general rule against allowing changes tobe made in existing local authority boundaries. The general formulaused in paragraph 5 of CP. (50.) 44 was not in itself open toobjec-tion; but, if the Minister were called upon ito define what was meantby &quot; urgent changes &quot;it would fee inexpedient to iclaim that theywere confined entirely to changes required for the purpose of facilitating housing programmes.The Cabinet Approved the policy summarised in paragraph ;5 of cp. (50) 44; but invited the Minister of Health, in apply-ing it, to leave himself discretion in an exceptional case to acquiesce in the adjustment of a local authority&apos;sboundaries for reasons other than its housing needs.
Council ofEurope.(previous reference:CM: (50) 11thConclusions,Minute 4.)7. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (50) 40) on the relations between the two organs ofthe Council of Europe, viz.; the Committee of Ministers and the consultative Assembly.The Foreign secretary said that, although the existing position was unsatisfactory, the&apos; proposals put forward by the Secretary-General of the Council were neither sound in principle nor workablein practice. He had no doubt that those proposals must be rejected;but at the same time he was anxious to be able to propose some con-structive alternative. He therefore sought authority to put forward the plan outlined in paragraph 6 of his memorandum, by whichthe Committee of Ministers would offer to discuss their decisionsat an informal meeting with representatives of the StandingCommittee of the Assembly. It might also be useful if the LabourParty could be persuaded to make a declaration supporting theview, which underlay the Governments policy in this matter, thatthe future development of the Council of Europe must be such as to involve no transfer of national sovereignty.The Minister of Town and Country Planning said that he supported the general approach to this problem which was outlined in the Foreign SecretaryV memorandum. He was satisfied, fromenquiries which he had made during his recent visit to Strasbourg,that there should be little difficulty in securing the rejection of theplan put forward by the Secretary-General. He was also satisfiedthat there would be no difficulty in obtaining from the Labour Partya declaration on the general lines suggested by the foreign secretary.In further discussion the following points were made : (a) We should be slow to make further concessions beyond that proposed in paragraph 6 of CP. (50) 40. We should be fully justified in arguing that the Committee of Ministers must have time to assess the value of this experiment before they embarkedupon others.(b) It must continue to be a primary aim of our policy toprevent the Assembly from encroaching upon the jurisdiction of theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation in economic affairs. .   -(c) the Lord President said that, despite the arguments usedin paragraph 5 of CP. (50) 40, he was still inclined to favour theinclusion of some Ministers in the national delegations to theAssembly: At the first meeting of the Assembly the United King-dom delegation would certainly have been at a disadvantage if ithad not included some Ministers; and he believed that other nationaldelegations might have shown a greater sense of responsibility ifthey had included a Ministerial element.The Cabinet-Approved the recommendations made in paragraphs 9 and10 of CP. (50) 40.Germany.socialisation of basic industries.(previous reference:C.M.(48)68thConclusions,Minute 7.)8. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (50) 43) on the reorganisation of the coal industryand the iron and steel industry in Germany.The Cabinet agreed that consideration of this memorandum should be deferred until a later meeting, when they would have more time to discuss the far-reaching issues which were involved.Cabinet Office, S. W, 1,27th March, 1950.

</content>
</cab>
