<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/17/0 images: 95-100</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1950SECRETCM. (50)18th conclusions copy No. 4 6CABINET 18 (50)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 4th April, 1950, at 11-30 aw.PresentThe Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, MThe Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council!The Right, Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Minister   of   Town   and   Country; Planning. 1&apos;        &apos;The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Ghuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon.MinisterFisheries.ofT. Williams, M.P.,Agriculture    andThe Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,   M.P.,   Chancellor   of   theExchequer.The Right. Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of State for economic affairs.The Right Hon. Edith Summerskill,M.P., Minister of National Insurance.The Right Hon. H. A. Marquand, M.P..Minister of Pensions.Secretariat.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.38573-3ContentsNational Health ServiceB
National The Cabinet resumed their discussion of memoranda by the health Chancellor * of the Exchequer, the Minister of Health and theSendee. Secretary of State for Scotland (CP. (50) 53, 56 and 57) on the cost(Previous      of the National Health Service.Reference: There was general agreement that the Government could notCM. (50) 17th   contemplate an increase in the level of expenditure at which this conclusions,    Service was at present running.   Even if it proved impossible to minute 5.)      reduce the net cost to  350 million, as the Chancellor of - theExchequer desired, it was necessary to decide how money could befound to finance any necessary expansions of the Service whichmight from time to time become necessary, for example, increases in the number of beds available for tubercular cases.  The cabinets discussion mainly turned on the extent to which savings could besecured by economies in administration or by reorganising orcurtailing existing services, or whether it would be necessary, in, addition, to resort to a scheme of charges for,some or all of theservices provided. . &apos;The following is a summary of the main points made in dis-cussion of the administration of the Service and of the directions inwhich economies or reorganisations might be made : (a) The Minister of Health suggested that a Cabinet Committeeshould be appointed, under the chairmanship of the Prime Minister,to which the Health Ministers would report monthly how expendi-ture on the National Health Service was running and what steps were being taken to effect any necessary economies. This suggestionmet with general approval.    ,   .(b) Attention was drawn to the steps which were being takento set up under the National Insurance Act Advisory Committeesincluding representatives of workers,  employers and friendly&apos; societies, with a view to bringing enlightened local opinion to bearon the administration of the National Insurance Act. The sameCommittees, or similar committees, might be given the task ofsupervising the local administration of the National Health Service.These committees could investigate complaints of extravagance orabuse in the working of the Scheme.(c) When the National Health Service was being devised, theGovernment had rejected a suggestion that the local authoritiesshould assume responsibility for the hospital service. What waslacking, however, in the present administration of hospitals wasprecisely the kind of control which had previously been exercised by the chairman of the Finance Committee of the local authority.Steps should now be taken to place in this position an officer of the health Ministry who would have, to be satisfied about items of pro-posed expenditure. The doctors had secured too great a degree ofcontrol over the hospital management committees, and were pursuing a perfectionist policy without regard to the financial limits whichhad necessarily to be imposed on this Service as on other public services. The experience of the Ministry of Pensions in adminis-tering fourteen hospitals might be found to be of value in securingmore economical administration in the hospital service.(d) The Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Health ministers were considering in detail what action would have to be taken (underthe authority of regulations to be made under the National HealthAct) to secure stricter, central control over hospital expenditure.The Minister of Health had that morning met the chairmen of regional Hospital Boards and had informed them of the need foreconomies in the current financial year. Hospitals would be requiredto furnish monthly statements of expenditure incurred and com-commitments entered into, and in this way it was hoped to get to gripsat once with any excess of expenditure over estimates. Althoughone or two of the chairmen of Regional Hospital Boards had com-plained that this proposed supervision was &quot;bureaucratic,&quot; the chairmen had been told that they must assume that it would continue for the next year or so.  The chairmen had also been told that some
or all of any-, savings- which- they made. on their estimates would be- available for other urgent requirements, such as provision of bedsfor tubercular cases.(e) Although capital expenditure did not at present amount toan appreciable proportion of the total cost of the Health Service,there was support lor the view of the Minister, of Health that this expenditure should in the ordinary way be met by loan rather than from current revenue. ., &apos;  !(/) The remuneration Of specialists appeared in some cases to-    be excessive, notably that of the part-time consultants on the staffs of teaching hospitals, who were now receiving substantial salaries and, in addition, were able to carry on almost as much private work;    as they did before.   The system of merit awards should also be reviewed since, in the opinion of many of the more responsiblemembers of the medical profession, these awards, with the basic;     salaries, yielded higher remuneration than was justifiable.   TheMinister of Health said that he had been in touch with the chairmanof the committee responsible; for making merit awards and had asked him not to make&apos; awards to the full extent that the scheme permitted.; He reminded the Cabinet, however, that the total cost of specialists&apos;remuneration , in England and Wales was not more than about 13 million.(g) No material reduction could be made in the cost of thegeneral practitioner service.: The Health Ministers had informedV    the British Medical Association on the previous day that they could not accede to the proposal; for an increase in the capitation fee.(h) The cost of the ophthalmic service was unduly high. the health Ministers were already proposing to reduce the choice ofspectacle frames provided free of charge and to increase the changes made for special frames. These economies, might yield about 1 million. It was suggested that much greater savings could bemade if eye-testing, and possibly dentistry, were carried out in small clinics where the substantial overheads of the present practi-practitioners would not be incurred. In some areas maternity and child-welfare clinics had spare accommodation which could be used forthis purpose. Admittedly, it might be difficult to find opticians to staff such clinics.(?) Serious concern was expressed about the cost of the dentalservices. The sums involved appeared to be quite out of proportion to the benefit to the public. The high scale of remuneration fordentists under the National Health Service had attracted dentistsfrom the School Dentistry Service, and had done that service seriousharm. There was some support for the suggestion made by theSecretary of State for Scotland that the scope of the public provision should be limited to persons under twenty-one and other special classes, such as pregnant women. It might also be considered whether there was scope for the development of a dental nursing services on lines which had been successfully adopted in NewZealand. Although this would doubtless be opposed very strongly by, the dentists, New Zealand&apos;s experience suggested that women nurseswith an elementary training in dentistry could carry out a great dealof the work now performed in this country by fully-qualified dentists,particularly for young children. The Health Ministers were em-barking on further negotiations with a view to reducing the remuneration of dentists, and some abuses might be detected anderadicated if the Health Ministers were allowed to appoint a numberof supervising officers with professional qualifications to examinedentists&apos; claims and undertake investigations. This supervisionmight yield savings totalling  1 million.(j) The cost of the pharmaceutical services also appeared to be excessive.   This was in part due to the prescribing of high-pricedproprietary drugs.   It was hoped that the report of the Cohen38573-3 B 2
Committee would make it possible to require doctors to prescribenon-prOprietarydrugs where, these were available; and the health ministers had also invited the British Medical Association toco-operate ih takingi disciplinary action against doctors who wereguilty of extravagance in prescribing. ; The general view of Ministerswas that the Health Ministers would be justified in taking strongmeasures to prevent high-priced proprietary drugs being prescribed Iwhere other equally efficacious drugs were available.(&amp;) There was general agreement that every effort must be madeto eliminate all unnecessary expenditure in the administration of the health Service, not only on financial grounds, but also to ensure thatthe Service retained its high place in the public esteem. It was widely recognised that there were limits to the amount which couldbe spent on this Service, and the common sense of the ordinary mantold him that the Government must enforce a proper measure of economy. Some Ministers were, however, doubtful whether thefinancial savings to be achieved by economies would yield amounts which would effect any appreciable reductions in the costs of theService. Where figures of savings had been mentioned, they were ofthe order of  1 million on individual items. There appeared, there-fore, to be little prospect that these savings would appreciably reducethe cost of the Service from the current total of  392 million to thelong-term figure of  350 million which the Chancellor desired toreach. From this angle there was some support for the view expressedby the Secretary of State for Scotland in CP. (50) 57 that asubstantial proportion of the money required must be found either by a reduction of less essential services or by a system of charges.Thefollowing: were themain points raised in discussion of the impact of any general system of charges on the various branches ofthe National Health Service.(I) In various forms,; schemes of charges for maintenance of hospital beds had been common in the past in the voluntary andlocal authority hospitals. Moreover, a person receiving sickness benefit or national assistance had a deduction made after eight weeks in hospital which yielded in the aggregate between  2 and 3 million a year. The principle of making a charge for maintenance in hospital was, therefore, already accepted for the poorest class of patient and it was in some Ways surprising that this anomaly had not caused some public comment. The general view ofMinisters was, however, against imposing charges for maintenance in hospital, if this course could be avoided. As much as 64 percent, of the hospital beds were occupied by mental patients and bymentally defective, tubercular or chronic sick people from whomlittle or no charge could be recovered. As regards the remainderit would be argued that it was unreasonable to penalise those whowere most in need of medical attention. Moreover, there was noquestion of abuse of the hospital service, since people were notadmitted to hospital unless they were in serious need of medical orsurgical treatment. Most patients were not in hospital for more thana week or fourteen days and it would be a matter of some difficulty to recover charges from them after they had left. Under thearrangements in force before the National Health Service came into existence, there was free hospital attention over a wide field and itwould be a retrograde step to introduce charges at this stage.(m) Under the National Insurance Scheme of 1911 insuredoersons had received free medical attention and free medicine. Alee of Is. for a medical prescription would make the National health service appear less favourable than the earlier scheme had been.There would also be a strong demand that the amount of the charge should be met from the National Insurance Fund, and there wouldbe a revival of earlier arrangements under which working peoplecontributed to local funds out of which those in need were recoupedfor charges of this kind. Moreover, there was a real danger tha*in others might fail to take young children for medical attention at
an earlier stage of ailments if they knew that a fee would have tobe paid for any prescription. &apos;;(h) There was support for charges for the more expensive formsof appliance, and possibly for spectacles and dentures.  These werethe services where people felt mat some abuses had occurred, andthere would probably be a considerable measure of public support, for,charges designed fto curtail the extent of the abuse. The Ministerof Pensions was hoping to provide, a useful yardstick for testing: the; - cost of appliances, by the manufacture. of plastic teeth andspectacles in factories administered by, his Department.; The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, while he welcomed the suggestions which had been made for securing economies in the\ administration of the Health Service, he considered it essential thatthe Government should also take such steps as were necessary toenable&apos; them to ensure that expenditure  on this&apos; Service was kept within whatever ceiling they might decide to fix for it. The currentcost was more than the country could afford to spend on this Service,and was already out of relation to the sums spent on other social services. Yet some parts of the Service must be expected to expand :there would, for example, be irresistible pressure for the opening ofmore hospital beds. He himself believed that, if no changes ofpolicy were made, it would become clear by the end of the summer- that expenditure in the current financial year was likely to exceed 392 million. The Government would then be faced with a choice between (i) seeking appropriations-in-aid through the imposition of charges; (ii) curtailing services, by closing hospital beds; or(iii) facing the necessity for a Supplementary Estimate. He wasnot prepared to contemplate the third course. The Cabinet were likely to raise objections;to the second. He therefore desired that the health Ministers should be empowered, if need arose, to adopt thefirst course; and he- urged that amending legislation should be intro-duced which would give the Health Ministers power to impose, by regulation, such charges as they might, deeni necessary. If, as aresult of further efforts to achieve administrative economies, it became clear that the original Estimate for 1950-51 would not be exceeded, there would be ho need to invoke those powers, but their existence would be a stimulus to economy throughout the wholeadministration of the scheme. He would also like to be able to announce in his Budget Speech that: it was the intention of theGovernment to seek these powers and that they would not hesitate to use them if it became necessary to do so for the purpose of keepingexpenditure in the current year within the ceiling already announced.Iii further discussion the view was expressed that the chancellor was entitled to receive a firm assurance that expenditure in thecurrent year would not exceed the ceiling of  392 million. For thispurpose it was not enough to rely on attempts to secure miscellaneouseconomies in the administration of the scheme : the Governmentshould be in a position to enforce compliance with that ceiling, andthe Chancellor ought to be enabled to satisfy Parliament that theGovernment had effective control over expenditure on this Service.On the other hand doubts were expressed about the wisdom ofthe Governments making an early announcement of their intentionto take power to impose charges, before they had been able to decide for what services charges should be imposed, what the scale of thecharges would be and what classes of persons might be exempted.Ministers were bound to be questioned at once on these and similardetails; and they would give an impression of weakness if they couldnot answer them. A general announcement on these lines would expose the Government to political difficulties; and it was suggestedthat it would be unwise for the Government to expose themselves tothese before they were certain that the future course of expenditureon this Service would make the imposition of charges inevitable
Finally, it was suggested that it might be found, on further investi-gation, that economies could be more effectively secured by curtailingsome of the services rather than by any general imposition of charges; and this might be a further reason for not giving undueprominence, in any early statement, to the general principle of imposing charges.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were clearly concerned at the progressive rise in the cost ofthe Health Service, and there seemed to be general agreement that definite limits must be set for future expenditure on this Service andthat there must be effective means of ensuring that those limits wouldnot be exceeded. On the other hand, the Cabinet were evidently notprepared to; support the general application of the principle of charges throughout this Service, though it might be possible and desirable to make charges for some of the appliances which weremade available? under the scheme, There was general support fori; the proposal that a special Cabinet Committee should be appointedto watch the progress of expenditure on this Service, to assist theWo Ministers in initiating and carrying through a vigorous drivefor economy and to follow up some of the specific suggestions whichhad been thrown out in the course of the Cabinet&apos;s discussion. Someof those suggestions merited careful consideration, e.g., those for strengthening local control over expenditure on the hospital service,and for the appointment of local advisory committees to focus publicopinion on the need for economy, as well as efficiency, throughout all branches of the Service. Further action was evidently required toreduce expenditure on the dental service; and the possibilities of closer inspection of dental work and the establishment of dental and ophthalmic clinics should be specially examined. The Cabinet Com-mittee should also consider what the total permissible cost of this service should be in the next few years after 1950-51, and howexpenditure could be reduced by the end of 1950-51 to the annual rate appropriate to the hew ceiling.These points on which there now seemed to be general agreement were not, however, sufficient in themselves to give the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer the full assurance which he sought that the net cost6f this Service would be kept within  392 million in the current financial year and within whatever lower ceiling might be prescribedfor future years. The Prime Minister therefore undertook to dis-euss with the Chancellor of the Exchequer what further assurancescould be given him and to report to the Cabinet at their next meeting.The Cabinet-Agreed to resume their discussion of this question at their meeting on 6th April.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,Uh April, 1950.

</content>
</cab>
