<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/17/0 images: 207-210</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1950SECRETCM. (50)34th conclusions copy. No.CABINET 34 (50)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 2nd June, 1950^ at 2-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, M.P., Lord President of the Council (inthe Chair)The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Horn G; A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Comfhon-weaith Relations.The following were also present:The  Hon.  K.  G. Younger,  M.P..Minister of State.Sir Edward Bridges^ Treasury.Mr.  Douglas Jay, M.P., FinancialSecretary, Treasury.Sm William Strang, Foreign Office.Sir Edwin Plowden, Treasury.Sir Norman Brook ...... SecretaryContentsSubject PageIntegration of French and German Coal and Steel IndustriesIndustries...............      ......      2438833-1 B
Integration of The Minister of State said that, in spite of the numerousFrench and diplomatic exchanges which had taken place during the past fewGerman Coal days, it had proved impossible to reach agreement with the Frenchand Steel Government about the terms on which the United Kingdom couldIndustries. join in the examination of the French proposal for the integration of the coal and steel industries of Western Europe. The FrenchGovernment were insisting that all Governments participating in theproposed examination of this proposal should commit themselves inadvance to accepting the principle of the scheme before it was discussed in detail. Since the matter had last been mentioned at themeeting of the Economic Policy Committee on 25th May, a further attempt had been made to overcome the French scruples bysuggesting that the position of the United Kingdom Governmentshould be explained in a final paragraph to be added to the proposedcommunique announcing the initiation of the discussions. This para-graph (reproduced in Foreign Office telegram No. 491 to Paris of31st May) would have stated that the United Kingdom Governmentwould participate in the proposed conversations in a constructivespirit in the hope that, as a result of the discussions, there would emerge a scheme in which they would be able to join; but it wouldhave made it clear that the United Kingdom Government could notat this stage enter into any more precise commitment. This sugges-tion had, however, been rejected by the French Government, who had now invited us to accept the revised form of communique set out inParis telegram No. 141 of 1st June (Annex I of CP. (50) 120). Thiswould involve the participating Governments in a public declaration that they &quot; set to themselves as an immediate aim the pooling of theircoal and steel production and the institution of a new high authority &quot;whose decisions would be binding upon them. The proposedcommunique also foreshadowed the preparation of a treaty; and itwas known that the French Government desired that a treatyembodying the general principles of their plan should be concludedand ratified before the participating countries proceeded to the detailed examination of a practical scheme. The French Governmenthad stated that, if we were unable to assure them by 8 p.m. that day that we would join in the discussions on the basis which they nowproposed, they would feel compelled to go forward without UnitedKingdom participation.Officials of the Departments directly concerned had met that morning to consider the position, and their recommendations were setout in CP. (50) 120. It was their view that there was a real difference of approach between the United Kingdom Government and theFrench Government which could not be glossed over by mere verbalingenuity in the drafting of a communique, and that it was better that this should be faced at the present stage rather than later. they therefore recommended that the latest French proposal should be rejected; and that, if the French Government decided to hold their proposed discussions without United Kingdom participation, our attitude should at once be made clear in a public announcement onthe lines of the draft in Annex II of CP. (50) 120.The Lord President said that he and the Minister of State hadbeen able that morning to discuss the position with the foreign secretary, who also felt that this latest French proposal must be rejected. The Foreign Secretary considered that a communication should at once be sent to the French Government on the following lines. It should make the point that the United Kingdom Govern-ment were unable to accept the French proposal by 8 p.m. that evening, since they were still without any information about thepractical details of the scheme and were therefore unable to estimateits possible effects on their programmes for economic development and defence. They were acting in good faith in this matter, and were anxious to do their best to see whether a workable scheme could be devised which would be fair to all concerned and likely to promotepeace, European solidarity and economic and social progress.  They
felt, however, that the best way of achieving this was, not by thecontinued exchange of notes, which had led only to misunderstandingand delay, but by a meeting of Ministers of the countries concerned,which could consider by what means the examination of the french proposal could best be handled. If, however, the French Govern-ment rejected this offer of a meeting of Ministers and went ahead with their plan without our participation, we should certainly loseno time in making a public announcement which would make ourposition Clear.In discussion there was general agreement that the UnitedKingdom could not participate in the proposed discussion of theFrench proposal on the basis of the communique suggested by theFrench Government in the telegram reproduced in Annex I of cp. (50) 120. This would commit us to accepting the principle ofthe French proposal before any of its details had been made knownto us. No British Government could be expected to accept such a commitment without having had any opportunity to assess theconsequences which it might involve for our key industries, our export trade and our level of employment. There was, therefore,general support for the proposals which the Lord President had putforward in the light of his conversation with the Foreign Secretary.Other points made in the discussion were:  (a) The bulk of public opinion in this country, as reflected inParliament and in the Press, was likely to support the view that theGovernment could not be expected to commit themselves in advance to accepting the principle of this proposal before they knew whatpractical shape it would take and what it was likely to involve. Therewould doubtless be some criticism from groups which were disposed to favour almost any scheme for European integration; but most people would think that the course now proposed was not undulycautious.(b) There was some risk that our attitude might be regarded by public opinion in the United States as a further sign of our reluctance to promote European union; and it was specially important fromthis point of view that, if the French decided to hold their conversa-tions without our participation, the reasons for our attitude should bemade clear without delay.(c) It was important that, as proposed by the Foreign Secretary,a further attempt should be made to dissuade the French from goingforward on the basis proposed without our participation. It was unreasonable that we should have been presented with an ultimatumthat, if we did not concur in their proposal within 24 hours, the french would proceed without us; and it should be made clear to the FrenchGovernment that we were surprised to receive such summary treat-ment in a matter of this importance.In this connection it was suggested that use might be made ofthe argument that the German Government were not free to engage inthese discussions without the permission of ail the uccupying Powers.It was pointed out, however, that this argument could hardly be used at the present stage, since the Prime Minister, in his statement in theHouse of Commons on 11th May, had already welcomed the project for Franco-German discussion of this proposal. At a later stage itmight be appropriate to make it clear that German adherence to atreaty entrusting control of her basic industries to an international authority would require the concurrence of the Occupying Powers.(d) Some Ministers thought that the French Government musthave some underlying political motive for urging this precipitateacceptance of the principle of integrating the coal and steel industries of Western Europe. They might perhaps envisage this plan as a means of avoiding the additional commitments for the defence of western Europe which had been foreshadowed in the recent meetingof the North Atlantic Council.    Alternatively, they might be
strengthened by knowledge that the United States Government would support their efforts to secure an early agreement on the principle oftheir plan.(e) Although the other European Governments invited to partici-pate in the discussions had accepted the latest French formula, someof them had done so with reservations. It would; however, be undesirable for the United Kingdom Government to take this course;for nothing Would be more likely to exacerbate Anglo-French rela-tions than for us to join in the discussions with mental reservationsand withdraw from participation at a later stage.(p Our position was different from that of the other european countries by reason of Our Commonwealth connections; and weshould be slow to accept the principle of the French proposal without consultation with Other members of the Commonwealth, especially as it appeared to involve some surrender of sovereignty.The Cabinet agreed that if* despite the further representations which were to be made to them, the French Government decided tohold their proposed discussions without United Kingdom participa-tion, an announcement should be made without delay explaining theattitude of the United Kingdom Government towards the french proposal. This should follow the general lines of the draft set outin Annex II of CP. (50) .120. It was, however, agreed that the reference to the Atlantic Pact at the end of that draft should be omitted; and that the whole Of paragraph 5 of the draft might with advantage be recast on the lines that the United Kingdom Govern-ment would have Wished to be associated with the examination ofthis proposal and regretted that French insistence on a prior commit-ment in principle had made it impossible for them to do so, havingregard to their obligations to Parliament and to the public.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the United Kingdom Government should not participate in the examination of the French proposal fort^he mtegfation of the cOaf and steel industries of western europe on the basis set out in the telegram reproduced in annex I of CP. (50) 120.(2) Irivited the Minister Of State to arrange for a communication to be sent forthwith to the Fferieh Government, on thelines approved by the Cabinet, suggesting that they shouldconvene iri Paris a meeting of Ministers of the countries concerned to consider by what means the examination ofthe French proposal could best be handled.(3) Agreed that if, in spite of these representations, the FrenchGovernment decided to discuss their plan with the other western European countries concerned without UnitedKingdom participation, a public announcement should bemade without delay explaining the attitude of the UnitedKingdom Government on the general lines of the draft in annex II of CP. (50) 120; and authorised the lord president to settle the final text of that communique inconsultation with the Minister of State.Cabinet Office, SWA,2nd June, 1950.

</content>
</cab>
