<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/17/0 images: 228-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1950SECRET Copy No. 4 6CM. (50)38th conclusions cabinet 38 (50)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.1,on Thursday, 22nd June, 1950, at 10 a.m.Present:f ....The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lof d Privy Seal.The Right hon. Viscount Jowitt; LordChancellor.The Right Hon. E. shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. James Griffiths, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford cripps,K.C., M.P., Chancellor of theExchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount alexander of Hillsborough, Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. P. C. Gordon-Walker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The following were also present:The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 5).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of State for economic affairs (Items 4-5).The Hon. K. G. Younger, M.P., Minis-ter of State (Items 4-5).The Right Hon. Sir Hartley Shaw-cross, K.C., M.P., Attorney-General(Items 1-3).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 5).The Right Hon. Edith Summerskill,M.P., Minister of National Insurance(Item 3).Lord Macdonald of Gwaenysgor,Paymaster-General (Item 4).The Right Hon. John Wheatley, K.C.,M.P. Lord Advocate (Item 3).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 1-2).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. A. Johnston.
CABINET 38 (50)ContentsMinuteNoSubject p*f1     Parliament        ......     -Business in the House of Commons.Memorial to Keir Hardie.Kitchen Committee.81822     Parliament        ...     ..,......     ...     .....iDisqualification of a Member.3     Pensions for Judges&apos; Widows.........     ......4     Economic Development in South-East Asia.........     835     Integration of French and German Coal and Steel Industries     84
parliamentary inthe Houseof Commons.Memorial toKeir Hardie.KitchenCommittee.1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.The Lord President said that the third of the Private Members&apos;Motions for discussion on 23rd June was one by Dr. H. M. King, M.P.,proposing that a memorial to Keir Hardie should be erected withinthe precincts of the Palace of Westminster. What attitude shouldthe Government spokesman take towards this proposal, if the motion should be reached? A similar proposal had been rejected by Mr.George Lansbury when he was Minister of Works in the labour government of 1929. It had then been felt that Keir Hardie hadhot been a sufficiently prominent Parliamentary figure to warrant the erection of a monument in his memory at Westminster.In discussion if was pointed out that, although Keir Hardie hadnot himself been prominent in Parliament, he had been the founderof a Party which had subsequently established itself as one of the great political Parties in the country and had commanded a majority at two General Elections. It was the general view of the Cabinet thatthe Government should adopt a sympathetic attitude towards theproposal that a suitable memorial should be erected to him at West-minstcr. It was, however, recognised that a final decision could notbe taken on the basis of a Private Member&apos;s Motion: it would require a formal Address to the Crown.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the Kitchen Com-mittee had now presented a second report, which raised the questionwhether the Exchequer subsidy towards the restaurant facilities in theHouse of Commons should be further increased. Some public anxiety might be expressed about this subsidy, and he suggested that ministers should now consider the question of principle involved.The Cabinet-Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultation withthe Lord President, the Minister of Works and the chief whip, to submit to the Cabinet a memorandum on thequestion of principle involved in making an Exchequer con-tribution towards the provision of restaurant facilities in theHouse of Commons. VParliamentDisqualifi-cation ofa Member.(previous reference:CM. (50) 36thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Lord President said that the Government had not so far been asked in the House of Commons what action they proposed totake on the report of the Select Committee on the election of the Rev.J. G. MacManaway, and it seemed possible that no further questionsmight be raised about this unless the Government took the initiative in reopening the matter. There were precedents for not taking action on a report of this kind. Mr. MacManaway was now ill andwould be unable to attend Westminster for about two months: there-after he might perhaps be left to attend, or not to attend, as he thought fit. A Government Motion to refer the case to the Judicial Com-mittee of the Privy Council would involve a debate occupying half aday, and much other business had to be carried through in the few remaining weeks of the Session. Moreover, the Government couldnot be sure that the Motion would be carried, since on a matter of thiskind there would be a free vote.The general view of Ministers was, however, that the Governmentshould take the initiative and propose to the House of Commons thatthe case should be referred to the Judicial Committee. The Govern-ment had proposed the appointment of the Select Committee and theywould be expected to indicate at some stage what action they proposedto take on the Committee&apos;s recommendation for legislation.Although the Opposition had not yet raised the matter, they might still do so at a time more inconvenient to the Government. While theOpposition might oppose reference to the Judicial Committee, on theb 2
ground that this was a delaying device, their argument would now beless effective since Mr. MacManaway&apos;s illness would in any eventprevent him from attending at Westminster. If the Judicial Com-mittee were to deal with the matter in the present Term it wasimpori-ant that an early decision should be taken so that the LordChancellor could constitute a court and counsel could have time toprepare their case.The Cabinet-Invited the Lord President to arrange, after the necessary consultations with the Opposition, for a Motion to be putdown for discussion at an early date proposing thatMr. MacManaway&apos;s case should be referred to the JudicialCommittee of the Privy Council for an advisory opinion.Pensions 3.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Lord Chancellorfor Judges&apos; (CP. (50) 131) covering a memorandum which he had submitted to widows. the Lord Presidents Committee proposing the adoption of a schemeof pensions for the widows of judges and certain other judicial officers on the lines of the scheme already in force for the widows of civilservants. This proposal had been referred to the Cabinet because ithad been impossible to reach agreement upon it in the lord presidents Committee.The Lord Chancellor said that he was concerned about thedifficulty of finding barristers of the right calibre who were willingto accept judicial appointments, particularly appointments as county court judges. He accepted the fact that in present circumstances itwas impracticable to increase judges&apos; salaries, but he believed thatthese appointments cooki be made somewhat more attractive if pro-vision were made for a widow&apos;s pension. Under his scheme a judge&apos;pension would be reduced from the present basis of two-thirds of salary to the basis applicable to civil servants, namely, half salarytogether with a gratuity, part of which would be surrendered by a married man to provide part of the cost of a widow&apos;s pension. he realised that it would be impracticable to introduce legislation on thissubject in the present Session, but he sought authority to try to securethe judges&apos; agreement to the proposal with a view to the introductionof legislation in the following Session. If he found that there wasno substantial agreement among the judges, he would discuss theposition further with the Chancellor of the Exchequer.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) It was most important that the high standards of the JudicialBench should be maintained. The Law Officers and the ministers concerned with judicial appointments had in recent years been djs-disturbed to find that barristers of the necessary calibre could not easily be found for appointment as county court judges and as Metropolitanpolice magistrates. There was too great a tendency for barristers to delay an application for the less important judicial offices until theyhad ceased to be fit for work at the Bar.(b) The jurisdiction of county court judges had been substantially increased in recent years. They had originally been empowered to try only cases involving  20 or less; but the limit was now  200 andit was contemplated that it might be raised to  300. This extensionof their jurisdiction had increased the volume, as well as theimportance, of their work.(c) The Government had discouraged applications by tradeunions for pensions schemes for manual workers in socialised industries on the ground that the country could not afford these schemes in present economic circumstances and that their relation tothe general provision made under the National Insurance Actrequired further examination.   The scheme put forward by the Lord
EconomicDevelopmentin South-east asia.(previous reference:CM. (50) 15thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Cabinet had before them (i) a report by the Paymaster-General (CP. (50) 123) on the meeting, held in Sydney in May, of theCommonwealth Consultative Committee on Economic development in South and South-East Asia; and (ii) a memorandum by the Chan-cellor of the Exchequer, the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations and the Minister of State (CP. (50) 127) commenting on theconclusions reached at that meeting.The Prime Minister expressed the Cabinefs appreciation of the satisfactory results achieved at the meeting by the Paymaster-Generaland the Delegation which he had led.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it was important thatthe recommendations submitted to Governments as a result of themeeting should be adopted without delay and followed up energeti-cally by the steps summarised in paragraph 4 of CP. (50) 127. he hoped that an experienced official of the Commonwealth relations office would be made available to attend the meeting which was tobe held in Colombo in the following month: it was important thatthe United Kingdom should be well represented at this meeting.In discussion several Ministers expressed the hope that publi-cation of the recommendations of the Sydney meeting would not belong delayed.The Cabinet (1) Approved the report and recommendations of the Sydneymeeting of the Commonwealth Consultative Committeeon Economic Development in South and South-East Asia;and authorised the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations to inform other Commonwealth Governmentsaccordingly.(2) Invited the Minister of State to arrange for the results of themeeting to be communicated informally to the Govern-ments of the United States, France and the Netherlands.(3) Approved the action proposed in paragraph 4 of CP. (50) 127for following up the results of the meeting.Chancellor could be differentiated in a number of ways from the pro-posals which Ministers had opposed in the case of nationalised industries: but there remained some doubt whether the differencescould be made apparent to the workers in these industries.id) The legislation providing for pensions for civil servants&apos;widows had been passed without adverse comment, probably becauseof the contributory element, and the scheme for judges&apos; widows,which covered a much smaller field, might also prove to be non-con*controversial. The grant of pensions to judges&apos; widows might, however,increase the pressure for similar provision in other pension schemesadministered by the State, notably for teachers and members of the armed Forces though, in point of numbers, the precedent of theCivil Service was likely to be more important from this point of viewthan that of the judges.The Cabinet-(1) Approved in principle the proposals in CP. (50) 131 for pensions for the widows of judges and certain otherjudicial officers.(2) Authorised the Lord Chancellor to initiate discussions withthe judges, with a view to ascertaining whether there wouldbe general support among them for this scheme and, inthe event of a favourable response, to proceed with thepreparation of the necessary legislation.
5. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Secretary of theCabinet (CP. (50) 128) covering a report by a Committee of officialsappointed to advise on the French Foreign Minister^ proposal forintegrating the coal and steel industries of Western Europe. Thisreport had been considered by the Economic Planning Board, whose views on it were annexed.In&apos;a preliminary discussion of the report the following points were raised:-(a) Some concern was expressed about the attitude which tradeunions might take towards this proposal. The Cabinet were informedthat in the preparation of their report officials had held, some informal discussions with individual leaders of the trade unions most directly concerned, and the report had been seen by the trade union represen-tatives on the Economic Planning Board. All these discussions had,however, been confidential and the individuals consulted had not been at liberty to discuss these matters with their colleagues in the tradeunion movement. The Cabinet agreed that more formal consultationwith the trade union movement must be deferred until the Govern-menfs attitude towards the proposal had been more clearly defined.(b) If any scheme of this kind was to prove acceptable to theworkers in these and related industries in the United Kingdom, itmust be accompanied by detailed and satisfactory financial plans forthe expansion of the coal and steel industries. It would be impossiblefor the Government to accept such a scheme if it was based on theassumption that coal and steel production would shortly be surplus to requirements and was designed primarily to restrict production inthe interests of the producers. It followed, therefore, that anyinfluence which the United Kingdom Government could bring on theinternational discussions now proceeding should be directed to securing early consideration of measures for expanding the productionand consumption of coal and steel and of detailed financial plans for future capital investment in these industries. The Government1should lose no opportunity of giving prominence to their aim ofsecuring a progressive expansion of the coal and steel industries.(c) The Government had already given ample proof that theywere prepared in principle to, support all reasonable plans for pro-promoting closer economic co-ordination in Europe. They were not therefore opposed in. principle to some integration of the coal andsteel industries of Western Europe. They must, however, reject anyproposal for placing these industries under the control of a supra-national authority whose decisions would be binding on Governments.Equally, they could not accept proposals for placing these industries under the control of an industrial cartel on the pre-war restrictionistmodel.(d) The proposal raised three main questions requiring urgent examination. First, what form of administrative organisation wouldbe appropriate to control and manage these industries? Secondly,what form of political organisation should be established to supervisethat control? Thirdly, what financial arrangements were proposed for securing the expansion of these industries?(e) The issues raised by this proposal were complex and far-reaching, and it was essential that Ministers should have full oppor-tunity to consider them in detail. There was no reason to suppose that this opportunity would be lacking; for it was likely to be sometime before any detailed scheme emerged from the international discussions now proceeding in Paris. The greater risk was perhapsthat a deadlock would be reached in those discussions and the UnitedKingdom Government would be asked to assist in resolving it. Itshould also be borne in mind that the French Government had under-taken to keep us informed of the progress of the discussions, and theywould doubtless expect us to offer constructive comments.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion saidthat the issues raised by the report annexed to CP. (50) 128 should
integration of Frenchand German.Coal and steel industries.(previous reference:  sCM. (50) 34thConclusions:)5. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Secretary of theCabinet (CP. (50) 128) covering a report by a Committee of officialsappointed to advise on the French Foreign Minister^ proposal forintegrating the coal and steel industries of Western Europe. Thisreport had been considered by the Economic Planning Board, whose views on it were annexed.In a preliminary discussion of the report the following points were raised:  (a) Some concern was expressed about the attitude which tradeunions might take towards this proposal. The Cabinet were informedthat in the preparation of their report officials had held, some informal discussions with individual leaders of the trade unions most directly concerned, and the report had been seen by the trade union represen-tatives on the Economic Planning Board. All these discussions had,however, been confidential and the individuals consulted had not been at liberty to discuss these matters with their colleagues in the tradeunion movement. The Cabinet agreed that more formal consultationwith the trade union movement must be deferred until the Govern-menfs attitude towards the proposal had been more clearly defined.(b) If any scheme of this kind was to prove acceptable to theworkers in these and related industries in the United Kingdom, itmust be accompanied by detailed and satisfactory financial plans forthe expansion of the coal and steel industries. It would be impossiblefor the Government to accept such a scheme if it was based on theassumption that coal and steel production would shortly be surplus to requirements and was designed primarily to restrict production inthe interests of the producers. It followed, therefore, that anyinfluence which the United Kingdom Government could bring on theinternational discussions now proceeding should be directed to securing early consideration of measures for expanding the productionand consumption of coal and steel and of detailed financial plans for future capital investment in these industries. The Government!should lose no opportunity of giving prominence to their aim ofsecuring a progressive expansion of the coal and steel industries.(c) The Government had already given ample proof that theywere prepared in principle to, support all reasonable plans for pro-promoting closer economic co-ordination in Europe. They were not therefore opposed in principle to some integration of the coal andsteel industries of Western Europe. They must, however, reject anyproposal for placing these industries under the control of a supra-national authority whose decisions would be binding on Governments.Equally, they could not accept proposals for placing these industries under the control of an industrial cartel on the pre-war restrictionistmodel.(d) The proposal raised three main questions requiring urgent examination. First, what form of administrative organisation wouldbe appropriate to control and manage these industries? Secondly,what form of political organisation should be established to supervisethat control? Thirdly, what financial arrangements were proposed for securing the expansion of these industries?(e) The issues raised by this proposal were complex and far-reaching, and it was essential that Ministers should have full oppor-tunity to cbnsider them in detail. There was no reason to suppose that this opportunity would be lacking; for it was likely to be sometime before any detailed scheme emerged from the international discussions now proceeding in Paris. The greater risk was perhapsthat a deadlock would be reached in those discussions and the UnitedKingdom Government would be asked to assist in resolving it. Itshould also be borne in mind that the French Government had under-taken to keep us informed of the progress of the discussions, and theywould doubtless expect us to offer constructive comments.The Prime Minister, summing up this part of the discussion saidthat the issues raised by the report annexed to CP, (50) 128 should
85CM. 38 (SO)be examined by a small group of Ministers including the Chancellorof the Exchequer, the Minister of Fuel and Power, the Minister ofSupply and the Minister of State. This group of Ministers could afjokeep in touch with the progress of the international discussions. Theywould be concerned primarily with the economic aspects of the pi o-posals. Concurrently, the Minister of Defence and the Secretary )state for Commonwealth Relations should respectively examine the strategic and Commonwealth implications of the proposal and preparememoranda on those aspects of it. At a later stage the Econor:icPolicy Committee should review the results of these enquiries andfocus the main issues for final decision by the Cabinet.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Prime Minister to arrange for a small group ofMinisters to examine the issue arising from the report annexed to CP. (50) 128 and to keep in touch with theprogress of the international discussions now proceedi.gin Paris on the proposed integration of the coal and steel industries of Western Europe.(2) Invited the Minister of Defence and the Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations to consider, and prepare memo-i anda upon, the strategic and Commonwealth implications of that proposal.The Cabinet next discussed the line to be taken by the Govern-ment spokesmen in the debate on this proposal which was to take placein the House of Commons on 26th and 27th June. They had beforethem a note by the Secretary of the Cabinet (CP. (50) 133) covering the draft of a Government amendment to the motion tabled on behalfof the Opposition.The Cabinet agreed that the Chancellor of the Exchequer shouldbe the first Government spokesman in this debate and that the PrimeMinister should speak on the second day. Various suggestions weremade regarding the points which might be stressed by the government spokesmen in the course of the debate.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that notice should be given of a Government amend-ment, in the terms set out in CP. (50) 133, to the Motiontabled by the Opposition.(4) Agreed that a meeting of the Cabinet should be held on27th June to review the course taken by the debate on thefirst day and to discuss the general line of the reply to bemade by the Prime Minister in winding up the debate.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,22nd June, 1950.

</content>
</cab>
