<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/31/3 images: 44-51</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1942.MOST SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (42) 523.November 14, 1942.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.REBUILDING OE THE HOUSE OE COMMONS.Note by the Secretary.BY direction of the Prime Minister the attached report by the Minister ofWorks and Planning is circulated for consideration by the War Cabinet.(Signed)      E. E. BRIDGES.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.1.[24618]
REBUILDING OF THE HOUSE OF COMMONS.Description of Work.I. Chamber and Division Lobbies.A. Carcase.(i) It is estimated that two months would be required for decisions to be arrived at as to any minor alterations to be made to the seating, accommodation,lighting, heating, ventilation, acoustics, &amp;c, to the Chamber, as this is a good opportunity to carry out all the modifications that have shown themselvesnecessary and which can now easily be embodied without altering the appearance of the Chamber.Meanwhile, the demolition of the remaining unsound walls of the Chambercould proceed, leaving as much of the sound portions of the Division Lobbiesas possible; the upper portions of the Commons&apos; Lobby walls would also have,to be demolished down to the ceiling level of the Lobby, and an accurate surveymade of the whole work so that the preparation of the working drawings couldbe proceeded with directly the above decisions have been reached. Four monthsmore will be required to complete the drawings.Thus, after six months, it should be possible to start building.and to giveactual occupation of the Chamber and Lobbies in another twelve months. Thiswould only include temporary or &apos;&apos; austerity &apos;&apos; panelling of plywood and soft-wood joinery throughout, but would include the up-to-date heating andventilating scheme and much of the permanent seating and furnishings.The structural work would include the reinstatement of all the stoneworkinside and out, the only variation proposed being the omission of the upperportions of the old Chamber windows, which are now redundant and which wouldinvolve a lot of unnecessary labour to reinstate. This space can either be leftblank on the outside or a series of fourteen statues introduced, if suitable subjectscan be suggested.(ii) Heating and Ventilation (see attached notes on Engineering Services).The opportunity has been taken to introduce entirely new and up-to-dateheating, ventilating, and lighting systems, which embody the results of the1931 House of Commons (Ventilation) Memorandum, but with still further improvements, such as the installation of floor heating to the Chamber, seatingand lobbies, &amp;c.(iii) Electrical Services.No fundamental change in the method of lighting the Chamber is suggested,except that the possibility of flood lighting the sloping portions of the ceilingfrom chandeliers instead of from the window sills has been investigated owingto the blaok-out curtains interfering with the window-sill lighting.(iv) Finishings of a temporary nature.The temporary joinery and panelling would be of simple natural-colouredplywood, which could be replaced gradually by the permanent oak panelling,which, being of an elaborate nature, would take some eighteen months to complete and fix after occupation of the Chamber has been given.(v) Supplies Services.For the time being most of the carpets and curtains may have to be of atemporary nature, to be replaced after the war.B. Permanent Finishings.(i) It is proposed to omit temporarily the elaborate stone screens to theLadies&apos; and Strangers&apos; Galleries, but these will be replaced with any modificationsdesired when the permanent oak panelling is being installed. The present schemeincludes the reinstatement of all the elaborate oak linen fold panelling to eventhe small and subsidiary rooms and lobbies as previously existing; unless it is decided to modify this in any way.(ii) Commons&apos; Looby.It is proposed to replace the damaged stonework and to reinstate the ceilingas before m soft wood painted and gilt.
(iii) Whips&apos; Rooms and Corridors.These rooms will be restored with their original panelling.Notes on the war-time supply of the necessary stone and oak are attachedherewith.ESTIMATE OF COST.I Chamber and Division Lobbies.A. Carcase.(i) Demolition of damaged work.Erection of steelwork, walls, concrete floors and roofs(resistant to incendiary bombs).Reconstruction of Lavatories.Sundry building works in attendance on Engineers(ii) Heating and Ventilating (a) Floor panel warming installation (Low Temperature) forChamber and Lobbies      ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 3,500(b) Air  conditioning with  Refrigeration for  Chamber  andLobbies.Plenum Heating and Extraction system for specialrooms, galleries, &amp;c.         ...      ...      ...      ...       ... 24,000(c) Extensions and renewals to Sundry Services     ...       ... 2,500(iii) Electrical Services (a) Lighting of Chamber, Lobbies and adjacent rooms      ... 4,000(b) Power supplies .to switch gear (including conversion fromD.C. to A.C.) ...    &apos;............... 5,000. (c) Sound Amplification, to Press only, with provision forextension later      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...       ... 1,000(d) Extensions and renewals of Sundry Services, includingBells, Signals, Telephones, Annunciators   -     ...       ... 4:000(iv) Finishings of a temporary nature to Chamber, including dealbenching      ...       ...      ...       ...      ...       ...       ...       ... ...(v) Supplies   Services,   including   carpets,   curtains   and   benchupholstery of a permanent nature        ...      ...       ...(vi) Contingencies  ...90,00030,000Total to make Chamber habitable14,00016,00010,000160,00010,000170,000-Permanent Finishings. -Erection of stone screens and provision of carved oak panelling towalls and ceiling of Chamber and Lobbies with eresting and metal work as previously; also panelling to adjoining rooms,including Press Room, and to staircases ...Contingencies        ...      .-- ---Total for Chamber    ...      ...      ..-      ...150,00010,000160,000330,000II. Commons Lobby.Reinstatement of Commons Lobby, including ventilating shaftsadjoining        ...      ... ...      ...      ...    .25,000ReinstatementIII.-Whips&apos; Rooms and Corridors.total,000361,000[24618]B 2
REBUILDING OF HOUSE OF COMMONS.Scheme of Operations and Estimate of Labour Requirements.Time.Discussion (2 months).Drawings (4 months) .Demolition,  reconstruction  of  CommonsLobby, Whips&apos; Boom, &amp;c.....&apos;..Carcase   of   Chamber   and   EngineeringServices...............Temporary Finishings..Permanent Finishings...6 months.12 months.17 months.		-25 men for- 4 months 	-87 men for . --6 months-	- Building 150 men for 12 months--j- Engineering (site) 60 men for-9 months-(Shops) 100 men for 5 months--60 men --for----i 4 months-125 men for 24 months (shop and site)-Total36 months.B
NOTES ON ENGINEERING SERVICES.(Subject to-re-examination, modification and experiment.)Heating and Ventilating.The air-conditioning plant will be capable. of providing ten changes ofconditioned air per hour (equivalent to 20,000 cubic feet per minute. The 1931,House of Commons (Ventilation) Memorandum recommendation is 16/20,000cubic feet per minute).The general distribution and extraction will follow the recommendations asset out in the 1931 Memorandum.Temperature and humidity conditions will be under control, irrespective of outside conditions. A refrigeration plant will be installed for the control ofhumidity and for cooling during the summer.The warming of occupants&apos; feet will be effected by the installation of mildtemperature heating coils embedded in the Chamber floor.Electrical Services:Lighting of Main Chamber by central lay light augumented over backbenches and ceiling panels, all as previously. If desired, flood lighting would be examined as an alternative.Lighting of Lobbies by more modern fittings, combining direct and indirectillumination.Sound Amplification.Generally similar to equipment in use in present Chamber, but capable of extension to other galleries and floor of House.Sundry Electrical Services.Signals from Speaker&apos;s Chair to engineers for lighting, heating andventilation control. .Bells from clerks on floor of House and adjoining lobbies and rooms.Annunciators, renewing four instruments and necessary wiring.Telephones as required.EXPLANATORY NOTES.Labour.I. -Building Labour.It may.be accepted that, with the exception of joiners and wood carvers,building labour will be available from men not essential to the War effort.Masons and Labourers. 20 masons are still employed, on the repair of stone-work at the Houses of Parliament and can be transferred to this work. Similargroups of men are attached to large contracting firms.Joiners and Wood Carvers are normally engaged on such work as aircraft production.Requirements (a) Temporary finish : 60 men for 12 months.(b) Permanent decorations : 125 men for 18 months.Steel Erectors would probably have to be withdrawn from War work.Requirements 15 men for 10 weeks.II. Engineering Labour.Practically the whole of the labour required for engineering services is atpresent engaged on War work.Requirements -Shops : 100 men for 5 months. &apos;Site : 60 men for 9 months.
Materials.Stone.The Clipsham Quarry from which stone for the restoration work now in handwas obtained is closed. It is worked right up to the over-burden. It would take20 men and 2 mechanical excavators 3 months to remove.this. About 15;000 cubicfeet of stone is required, and it would take 30 men 9 months to quarry this amount.Some margin would have to be allowed for selective quarrying. The full quantityof stone would not be available for at least 12 months. The quarry would, there-fore, have to be reopened for this work and suitable labour released from other work, immediately a decision to proceed is arrived at.Oak.The quantity of English oak required is approximately 13,000 cubic feet.Messrs. James Latham, Ltd., have in stock 8.000-10,000 cubic feet of oak of3 years&apos; fell, not fully seasoned.Messrs. Rattee and Kett have in stock approximately 3,000 cubic feet ofseasoned oak.Messrs. Mallinson and Sons also have stocks of which details are hot available.Engineering Equipment.All materials and manufacturing capacity required for this are used forWar purposes and the necessary priorities would have to be accorded.Furnishings.Carpets, fabrics, &amp;c, would require the release of material, labour and machinery.



</content>
</cab>
