<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 69-72</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His-Britamric Majestys Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1922.SECRET.C.P.-3905.CABINET.WEEKLY SURVEY OF THE STATE OF IRELAND.Memorandum by the Chief Secretary for Ireland.I SUBMIT, for the consideration of the Cabinet, my survey for the period from the 21st to the 31st ultimo.General State of the Country.The most important event of the past week in Southern Ireland has been the definite breaking-away of the two sections of the Irish Republican Army as a result of the Convention held in Dublin on Sunday, the 26th ultimo, in open defiance of Mr. Griffiths prohibition. It is not yet possible to form an estimate of the respec-tive numbers of the two sections, but it is probable that the anti-Treaty party is in the minority. Two prominent political leaders, Mr. Cathal Brugha and Mr. Boland, are reported to have attended the Convention as delegates, and Mr. de Valera&apos;s official organ, &quot; The Republic of Ireland,&quot; makes no secret of its support to the new policy of substituting physical force for constitutional methods as the most effective means of defeating the Treaty. From a statement issued to the press by Mr. Mnlcahy, the Minister of Defence in Mr. Griffiths Dail Eireann Cabinet, it appears that the following far-reaching decisions were arrived at by the Convention : (1.) That an Executive Council should be appointed at once to take over from the Minister of Defence (Mr. Mulcahy) and the Chief of Staff (Mr. 0&apos;Duffy) the whole control of the Army.(2.) That the Executive Council should be authorised to suppress the Parlia-mentary Elections if it should think fit.(3.) That the Executive Council should consider and report to a further meeting of the Convention, to be held on the 9th April, a recommendation for setting up a Dictatorship for the purpose of overthrowing the four Governments at present functioning, viz., Dail Eireann, the Provisional Government, the British Government and the Northern Government.(4.) That the Belfast boycott should be re-imposed forthwith.An announcement issued on the 29th ultimo by the newly-appointed Executive Council declared that Mr. Mulcahy and Mr. 0&apos;Duffy should no longer exercise any control over the Army, and required all officers and men recruited by the Provisional Government for the new Regular Army and the Civic Guard to return at once to their respective units. A counter-blast to this proclamation was promptly forth-coming from Mr. 0&apos;Duffy in the shape of a public intimation that any superior&apos; officer who attended the Convention had, by so doing, severed his connection with, the I.R.A., and it now remains for events to decide which party are the secessionists and which the main body of the Organisation.That this new departure of policy on the part of the Republican extremists was intended to be more than a mere political gesture was soon made clear. On the night of the 29th instant the offices of the &quot; Freeman&apos;s Journal,&quot; which in its issue of that day had boldly charged Mr. de Valera and his associates with attempting to gain their ends by reducing the country to a state of chaos and anarchy, were raided by a [8157J ^ -
band of armed men, who demolished the machinery and set fire to the building. In a letter to the Editor, the Commandant of the First Dublin Brigade of the I.R.A. accepted responsibility for this outrage, and stated that it had been deemed neces-sary to take measures to suspend the publication of the paper on account of its opposition to the Republican policy. A series of other acts of violence in different parts of the country marked the first steps in the new revolutionary campaign. The Royal Irish Constabulary Barrack at Belcoo on the Fermanagh side of the Northern border was raided by a large body of men on the night of the 28th instant, and the garrison, who were taken by surprise, were overpowered before they could offer any attempt at resistance. Seventeen of their number, including eight Special Constables, were made prisoners and carried away by the raiders, who also took possession of the whole stock of arms and ammunition in the Barrack. On the same day the military Barrack at Kenmore, Co. Galway, which had been handed over to the Provisional Government, was seized by a body of Republican troops, who expelled the Free State garrison, numbering about 200. Further evidence of disaffection in the Provisional Government&apos;s Forces was seen in the desertion of a number of men of the Regular Army, stationed at Beggars Bush Barracks, Dublin, who withdrew from the Barrack in accordance with the orders issued by the Convention, but there has been no indica-tion, so far, that these orders for desertion are being generally obeyed by the I.R.A. throughout the country.The most serious of the many outrages committed in pursuance of the new Republican policy was an ambush of a party of Northern Government Police, which occurred on the 29th ultimo near Crossmaglen, Co. Armagh, and resulted in the death of a Sergeant of the Regular R.I.C. and a Special Constable, and the wounding of another Special Constable. This outrage was committed by a party of Republican troops armed with machine guns, who crossed the border from Co. Monaghan, and was without doubt a deliberately premeditated act of aggression. On the same day a patrol of Special Constables from Newry in a Crossley Tender, who appear to have crossed the Louth border near Omeath through inadvertence, were immediately fired upon by a patrol of I.R.A., and one of their number was slightly wounded. Another ambush of police in Northern territory was committed near Aughnacloy, Co. Tyrone, on the 30th instant, but no casualties resulted on either side.The attempt at reimposition of the Belfast boycott has already given rise to numerous acts of violence, of which the most serious was tbe derailing of a goods train near Adavoyle about 9-.30 p.m. on the 29th ultimo, and the burning of nine waggons containing Belfast merchandise. Other boycott outrages included the seizure of a large quantity of goods from a train at Sligo on the evening of the 29th ultimo, the seizure of a quantity of foodstuffs at Carrick-on-Shannon Station, and the destruction of a quantity of whiskey and flax seed at Drogheda Railway Station, both also on the 29th ultimo.Three attacks on British Forces were committed during the week, viz., the firing at a Sergeant of the Royal Irish Constabulary in Rathmines, Dublin, on the 26th ultimo; the ambush of a party of four military officers, none of whom was injured, at Clondalkin, Dublin, on the 29th ultimo; and the kidnapping of six soldiers from a train at Limerick Junction on the same date. To these breaches of the Truce must be added the murder of an ex-Sergeant of the Royal Irish Constabulary, who was shot dead in Cork City by a party of assjissins about mid-day of the 25th ultimo. In recording this murder, however, I ought to mention that a very prominent leader of the anti-Treaty section of the I.R.A. attended the inquest, and not only condemned the crime, but promised to do everything in his power to trace the assassins and to bring them to justice.State of the Police Forces.Disbandment of the Regular Royal Irish Constabulary in Southern Ireland commenced on the 29th ultimo, and will be carried through as rapidly as possible. In view of the present bitterness of political feeling, it is to be hoped that the Government&apos;s offer to pay the removal expenses of men who cannot return to their homes in Ireland without danger, and also those of their families and dependants, will be fully taken advantage of, but I am afraid that in many cases the men will elect to face the risk of assassination rather than to emigrate. The following are the latest figures of the strength of the Irish Police Forces ; &apos;
Royal Irish ConstabularyStrength on the 19th March, 1922 ... ...         ...      8,630Deaths during week        ... ... ... NilRetirements        ...         ... ... ... 141Resignations      ...         ... ... .... NilDismissals or discharges ... ... ...           1Total wastage ...       142Recruits ... ... ... ...        NilNet decrease       ... ... ... ...       142        142Strength on the 26th March, 1922       ...         ... ...      8,488Dublin Metropolitan Police.Strength.on the 18th March, 1922       ...         ... ...      1,128Retirements        ...         ...          ...         ... recruits ...         ...         ...          ...         ... 1Wastage ...        Nil        NilStrength on the 28th March, 1922        ... ... ...      1,128Present Political Situation in Ireland.The new Peace Agreement between the representatives of the Northern and Southern Governments has met with a very favourable reception in the press both of Dublin and Belfast. It is recognised, however, that both Governments will have considerable difficulties to overcome in order to give effect to their undertakings, and that some degree of forbearance will be required on both sides if further misunder-standings are to be avoided. The recent record of Mr. de Valera and his advisers does not justify the hope that they will show themselves ready to co-operate in this latest effort to promote the cause of Irish peace, but with the cessation of strife in Belfast and on the border, their opportunities of mischief will be greatly curtailed. The Belfast atrocities of the past two months have undoubtedly had the effect of diminishing the prestige of the Provisional Government, and the Agreement should strengthen its hand in dealing with the fomenters of discord and anarchy at home.H. G.-Irish Office, Old Queen Street, S.W.1, April 4, 1922.
Statement showing Total Number of Serious Outrages from January 1, 1919, toFebruary 11, 1922.Weekly Totals to Week ended March 25, 1922, and Totals at that date.		Week ended 						Nature of Outrage.	Totals from Jan. 1, 1919, to Feb. 11,1922.	Feb. 18, 1922.	Feb. 25, 1922.	Mar. 4, 1922.	Mar. 11, 1922.	Mar. 18,1922.	Mar. 25, 1922.	Totals to Mar. 25, 1922.Courthouses destroyed        ..	89							89R.I.C vacated barracks destroyed	524							52411.1.0. vacated barracks damaged	125							125R.I.C. occupied barracks destroyed	25							25Ji.1.0. occupied barracks damaged or captured	270			* *				270Raids on mails      ..          .. ,	2,568	1	* *	1	* *			2,570Kaids on coastguard stations and light-houses ..         ..         ..	100		* *					100Kaids for arms      ..	3,245		3	1	1			3,250Raids on offices of rate collectors and Petty Sessions clerks	122							122Policemen killed	.   416	1		3		2	* *	422*Policemen wounded           ..	720			3	1	2		726tPolicemen fired at, &amp;c.       ..	Not recorded	5	1	5		..		Soldiers killed      ..         ..	150	1	2					153Soldiers wounded   .	352	..	* *				* *	352Soldiers fired at, &amp;c.	Not recorded	2	1	..		..		Civilians killed j    ..         ..	198	1	2	1		2	1	205Civilians wounded	187	&apos;A.	*-		2	1		190Totals	9,112	11	9	14	4	7	1	9,123* This figure includes ten Special Constables. it This figure includes twenty-three Special Constables.$ These figures do not, include casualties in Ulster riots during period from June 1920 to the 52nd November, 1921, the date on which Executive Authority was transferred by IIis Majesty&apos;s Govern-meut to the Government of Northern Ireland; twenty civilian deaths occurred in the Londonderry riots and 146 deaths in the Belfast riots.N.B. The above particulars do not include outrages of a kind which are not now being&apos; committed, e.g\, 119 raids on revenue offices, which occurred during the months of April and May 1920, and resulted in the destruction of many official documents and much other public property. They also do not include minor forms of outrages (e.,?., intimidation, cattle-driving, &amp;c.) or any outrages committed in Northern Ireland since the 22nd November, 1921.

</content>
</cab>
