<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 73-74</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.j    D 1Printed for the Cabinet   March 1922.^5SECRET.CP. 3906.THE CABINET.LORD   PLUMER  AND  THE  MALTESE LOCAL FORCE.Memorandum hy the Secretary oe State eor the Colonies.SOON after the termination of the war the conclusion was reached that the two battalions of Malta Militia (paid from War Office funds1) were of little or no military value in their present shape of a force under Maltese officers embodied only in time of war.This was the opinion not only of the Army Council but also of Lord Plumer, the. Governor and Commander-in-chief of Malta.*After a more ambitious scheme for an improved force had been submitted by the Governor and rejected by the War Office on the ground of expense, Lord Plumer put forward on the 14th August, 1920, a proposal for a machine gun and infantry force of 250 privates under British officers, to serve (me year with the Colours and seven years with the Reserve the total estimated cost for the cadre being 27,8591. per annum and for the Reserve ^,2807., rising to a maximum of 15,968f.This proposal was accepted generally by the Army Council in their letters of the 22nd and 24th June, 1921.They stated, however, that the cost for the first year must not exceed 25,000/,.At the same time the Army Council ordered the disbandment of the existing Militia to be completed hy the 31st December, 1921.On the 7th December Lord Plumer telegraphed to War Office asking leave to publish the conditions of service in the new force at the same time that he announced the disbandment of the existing Militia.The War Office replied that such an announcement would be premature, as owing to the prospective reduction of Army Establishments it was not certain that they would be able to maintain a local force.Lord Plumer replied on the 29th December : &quot; I have repeatedly announced publicly on authority of Army Council that when Malta Militia is disbanded a new local force will be raised. If such a force is not raised I am guilty of a breach of faith and my position as Governor and Commander-in-chief becomes untenable.&quot;Lord Plumer amplified his view in a private letter to me on the 30th December. He said : &quot;I have been quietly letting the Militia disappear during the last six months, &quot;always promising them a new local force which though small would be a real one and something they would eventually be proud of.&quot; If my undertaking is not fulfilled, neither the Ministers nor the people of Malta can ever have the slightest confidence in anything I say. That is a position 1 am not prepared to occupy, aud I submit it is not right I should be placed in it.&quot;He added that from the military point of view there was no immediate importance in the addition of 200 or 300 Maltese; &quot;but,&quot; he continued, &quot;from an Imperial pointj of view it is important. If the little force is started and allowed to grow year by year, it will leaven the whole community, and in ten or fifteen years&apos; time it may make all the difference whether we have in the Mediterranean an actively loyal community or aIsmail and discontented one.   But the immediate point is the breach of faith, and thatll cannot be a party to.&quot;f8143]
On the 3rd January the Array Council said they would do all in their power to avoid departure from this project for a local force, and that if they had to do so they would publicly take full responsibility for it.On the 28th February, however, the War Otfice wrote to the Colonial Office saying-there was no justification for the expenditure from Army Funds on a local force in Malta, and suggested that, as the question was political, the Colonial Office might find the money; otherwise in all probability the Army Council would have to inform Lord Plumer that the project for a local force must be abandoned.As regards the suggestion that the Colonial Office should pay the expense, I have no objection myself to asking Parliament for the money, but it would of course be Unusual to include such an item in the Colonial Services Vote.If it is meant that Malta funds should supply the money, the idea is impracticable; firstly, because. Malta has the utmost difficulty in meeting the existing calls on its finances; secondly, because Malta naturally would not vote the money unless the force were officered and controlled by Maltese; and thirdly, because such a force would not have the political effect desired by Lord Plumer.I am in favour of Lord Plumer&apos;s proposal that a force should be raised and paid by the War Office at a cost for the first year not exceeding 25,000/., both because of the advantages to the Empire entailed, and also because the rejection of the scheme will clearly involve the resignation of Lord Plumer. which would have the worst possible effect, both generally, and especially in Malta, where his wisdom and strength are needed to guide the first steps of the Constitutional Government recently inaugurated under his auspices.The resignation of Lord Plumer would be a serious misfortune.w. s. c.Colonial Office, March 29, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
