<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 188-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^aNr..is cub pjjtDP&amp;ir-Y og hia shitamhio hajhisty&apos;s aofigiuifogffr.Cabinet. Epidemic Disease in Russia.L1.H.46Note by the Minister of Health.I new circulate for the information of my colleagues the full test of the report cf Lieutenant Cclcnel S.P. James, I.iioS.. tc which I referred in my letter to the Prime Minister of the 4th April.      Copies cf this letter have already been circulated as CP.3927aA. iiONDoministry of Health;C?   Vf   1
Report by the official Delegate representing-  GREAT BR1TA3HLt-C ol. Li,P o James, M. D. k edio a 1 Officer,.Ministry of Health.to which ia annexed tho text of theRESOLUTIONS passed by the Conference in plenary-session.HELD AT WARSAW from 20th to 28th March, 1622.
ne.WARSAW I hi SRlS ATI OK AL HEALTH QGftFgivEKGK.LISTS DES DilLEGUESKomg des Deleguea.Le Dr. r&apos;rey.Le Prof. Otto.Le Prof. kuehlens.Titre.Directeur au Service d&apos;hygiene publique.e.Le Dr. Hermann Schroetter.Le Dr. van Bcookel.e.Le Charge d&apos;Affairea Daniel Batchvarcff.Le Dr. Dime . 1&apos;ianeff.isiinistre a Varsovie.Un delegue.Le Dr.:Lossmann. Le Dr. Rommul. Le Dr. iiottus.M. le Oharge d&apos;AffaireB Gonzalo del RioM. Gustaf Greenland.Le Oolonel Conrad Ernst,Secretaire a la Legation de Finlande, Varscvle.tagne,Le Dr. Cruveilher, Le Dr. Baron.Le Colonel d.P.James, M.D., D.P.H.Lied;? o in Major de la Mission francaioe a Varsovie.du Linistere Brit. d&apos;Hygiene.- p. -
lavsngrie. alie.Le Prof, Hugo Pre is s..Le Dr. Alesaand.ro Lessea.Le Dr. Arnaldo fciaggiora. Dr. Aide Castellani.Vice-Dir. Gen. de 1 &quot;Hygiene&apos; publique.Prof, d&quot;Hygiene.Prefesseur de 1&apos;cicole de iledeoine tropicale de Lcndres-.[pen.Le Dr.Kcnuosuke aiyajina, i... Kuaame,Ittonie.Le Dr. Earena. Le Dr. Reinhard. Le Dr. Feb.ma.ns.Ithuanie.        M. le Dr. Eokas Slinpaa. M. Jules Abrai te s.days-Baa..Le Baron van Asbeok.Le Dr. Terburgh.Hinistre des Pays-Baa a VaraoviecInspecteur principal, Service d&apos;Hygiene publique-Ilcgne.uraanie.Le Dr. (Jhodzkc.Le Dr. Trenkner:Le Dr. Sztolonan.Le Dr. I. Gwietochcwaki.Le Dr. Jean Gantaousene.epublique Huaoe federative socialiste fa Societs et la Republique socialiste des Viets de la Ruasie blanche.M. Leonidao L. GbolenskyJSi.. I.L. Loreno.tiiniatre de Gante publique.Profeaseur a 1 ^Jniversite&quot; de Bukar.es t;.ivi. Le Rep. de la R.S.F.S.R. en Polcgne.Premier Secretaire a la Legation de la R.S.F.S.R,, Varsovie.
pays..Koms des delegues,k. I. Siak.Le Dr. J.P. Kalina.Le Dr. A.h. Syosin.Le Dr. K.G. Kreyberg.Ti tre.Premier Secretaire a la Legation U.3.S.R., Varsovie.Chef du oureau de 1 information. Etrangere du Commissariat du Peuple,Ghef de la Section epideniclogique du Commissariat d:Hygiene du Peuple.Expert technique: Chef du Ccnmiissariat d&apos;Hygiene du Peuple.Republique social 3ste des Soviets d:Uhraine, Le Dr. en drcit Jean Biak, M. le Dra Jules Ehclcdnytt Gerbe-oate-,slovne(lede.lisse.Le Dr,, Andrea, Btamper.Le Di\ Bcrysaw Bcrcik-B.E. Jiloid&apos; Ackarsvard,Le Dr. Dec. Carl Laclund.S.E. m. de Pfyffer.heco-Slavaquie. Le Dr0 kaxa.Le Dr, Bamarak.&apos;quie,Le Dr. Antcnin Kolinsky.Le Dr. iioi^diozka.k. le Dre Bekkl Bey. Deux adjpints.Direoteur du Service d!Hygiena publiquenMinistre a Varsovie.Professeur a 1&apos;Univeroite d !Upsala.toinistre a Varscvie.Ministre a Varsovie-,Vice-ministre de l&apos;Hygiene publique.Chef de Section au liinistre d &quot;Hygiene-Lliriistere d&apos;Hygiene.
WARSAW INTERNATIONAL CONFERENCE.PRESIDENTIAL-BUREAU.President- Le Dr. Chodsko,     Minlstre de la Sante-Publiqueen Polo^ne,Vice-presidents       - Le Dr. Tcrburgh,    Delegue des payable-Bas.Le Dr. Cuvelhier, Delegue de la France. Le Dr. Groenlund, Delegue de la Finlande.Les Presidents des trois OcmissicnsPresident de la lere Commission,,President de la Seme Commission.President de la 3erne Commission,Le Colonel  ames,. de la Granae Bj/etagre.Le Directeur Prey, de la Delegation&apos; Allemande.Le Dr0 Lassee, de la Delegation Itallenne,,Lestoe-Prenidenbp des 0oma1..39ions.lere Commission.     Le Prof. J. Gantacuzene, de la Delegationroumaine!, &apos;Le Dr, Kulhav-y, de la Delegation toheco-slovaque.,Seme -Commlssioon     Le Dr. Stampar, de la Delegationyugo-slav.Le Dr. van Boeckel, de la Delegation beige.3erne Commission.     Le Dr. Kalina, de la Delegation rus.se.Le Dr. Naealund, de la Delegation suedoise, &quot; .
REPORT.Towards the end of 1921 destitution and epidemic diseases in Russia increased greatly, and large numbers of the inhabitants of affected areas and cf people who wished to be repatriated to Poland began tc cove in masses towards the North and West.    This migration under distressing climatic and economic conditions resulted&quot;in a sudden and violent recrudescence of typhus and relapsing fever.    The frontier system of sanitary defence proved insufficient to deal with the situation and its breakdown in January this year was followed by a widespread extension and increased prevalence of infectious diseases in towns and villages of Poland.     A severe epidemic of cholera in the Ukraine added to the gravity cf the outlook.    In these circumstances the Polish Government sought the advice of the Council cf the League of Nations and en their recommendation decided to convene a technical medical conference to enquire into the epidemic situation in Eastern -Europe and to devise measures to deal with it. All European States were invited to send expert delegates, and the United States, China, Japan and Brazil were informed of the intention tc hold the Conference and were invited to participate if they so desired.2,      The Governments cf 27 countries accepted the invitation cf the Polish Government and were represented at the Conference by the delegates named on page 1 of this report-      The Secretariat for the Conference was provided by the Health Section cf the League cf Nations, Dr. Raj oilman, the nedioal Director cf that Section, acting
as Secretary-General, Dr. Chcdsko, Minister cf Public Health in Poland, was President of the Conference.3,     The first plenary technical meeting; was held at Warsaw on 20th March.    Dr. Rajchman gave at this meeting a lucid exposition of the epidemic situation in Eastei^n Europe based upon statistical and other information collected by the Health Section of the League cf Eatjens, The Conference then appointed three Commissions for the following work:-(l)    To study the Incidence and extension of epidemicdiseases in Eastern Europe ana to appraise the risk oftheir spread towards the West.&apos;2) To study what local inter--state conventions and other agreements might he made between neighbouring countries in order to keep one another informed cf the progress of epidemic diseases and the measures taken to prevent their spread,(3)   To study the general principles upon which anti-epidemic action ahould be baser?; to decide the policy to be recommended; and bo draw up programmes and estimates cf the work to be done.The Presidents and Vice-Preeidentd cf these Gomniiasions and certain other delegates named on page 2 were also appointed to constitute a &quot;Presidential Bureau&quot; in whioh proposals and draft resolutions were examined before submission to the Conference in plenary session.4.     At meetings in Warsaw from the 20th to 23rd0 March; the delegations from each country represented at the
Conference reported to the three Commissions the 6pidemlological sitriation in their countries and the action which they considered should be taken..    The Commissions also had before them all the information collected by the Health Section of the League of Nations;    and Dr. Normal White, Chief Commissioner&apos; of the League&apos;1 s Epidemic Commission, placed his services at their disposal.     First-hand information of the situation In the interior of Russia was also given by Professor Muhleris of the German Red Cross Mission, who had just returned from a tour of inspect.) on in the Volga region, and by Dr.. W..E. Haigh, of the British Relief Organisation for Russia., who had just returned from a tour in the Ukraine.     The official delegations from tho Russian Socialist Soviet Federation and from thp Ukraine also furnished detailed reports and personal assistance,5.     Meetings and inspections at Warsaw continued until the evening.of the 23rd March, when all delegates who were able to do so proceeded on a four days&apos;1 tour organised by the Polish Health Ministry.     During this tour we visited the following localities:Stopee, on the frontier between Russia and Poland,where&apos; refugees and repatries from Russia change trains andare  .od by voluntary workers, Baranowicge, 40 miles west of the frontier, the PolishQuarantine establishment which is the first receivingstation for immigrants to Poland and the chief post ofthe frontier sanitary defence cordon. Vilna and surrounding areas within a radius of aboutS miles.Smorgon, north-east of Vilna, a town formerly of 40,000 inhabitants but entirely devastated during the war and still in the same condition.- 8 ^
A line of underground dugouts in a forest about 5 mile-s fror. Smorgon, abandoned by the German army in 191S and now the dwelling place of the destitute people of that town. Wolywosk and other reserve posts to which the sick from the first line of sanitary defence are evacuated. Bialystok, a large town in which there are hospitals and other arrangements forming the first line of sanitary defence on the river Bug.,6,     Work in committee and sub-comriittes was continued in the train during this tour and the draft resolutions cf the 3rd Commission were prepared in collaboration with the delegates of Great Britain and Italy.     We returned to Warsaw on the 26th March and the Resolutions after being fully discussed and modified in the Presidential Bureau were submitted at plenary sessions of the Conference on the 27th and 23th,     The text of the Resolutions which were finally passed by the Conference is annexed to this Report.7.     As the Resolutions constitute a sufficient account of the work and conclusions of the Conference I think it is not necessary fOr me to do more than supplement them with the following personal notes:First in regard to the epidemic situation in Russia.(a)    It was unfortunately not possible to obtain permission for members cf the Conference to proceed beyond the Polish frontier;    but reports from Professor Muhlens and Dr. Raigh, and information communicated by the Russian delegates seemed to show that the situation, is much graver than available statistics indicate.     The Ukranian delegate stated that the statistics of typhus and cholera in the Ukraine for 1921 (540,000 cases) should at least be doubled, and that in view of the access of cholera in January he anticipated at least 2,000,000 cases of epidemic disease during the present year.     Owing to transport difficulties
only a proportion of those casea can be brought to hoanitaln, but even for those tho existing hospital accommodation is deficient by about 75,000 beds.(b) The following are some notes abstracted from recent medical reports of Black Sea ports and other localities in the Ukraine famine zone:    in the city of Odessa tho births in 1914 averaged over 1,100 per month, but in January 1922 they were only 180 and in February 147.     The deaths during those months were 2,028 and 2,716 respectively as compared with, a-monthly average of about 900 in 1914.     During, the first week of March this year between 15-20 deaths were occurring daily and the dead wore seen lying in the streets of tho suburbs and heaped in the churchyards.     The canalization system and the city waterworks were out of action and water had to be bought from street vendors&apos;.     Shipping was at a standstill.Typhus fever was increasing and outbreaks of plague and cholera were expected during the present year,      Some of tho hospital personnel had already died from starvation. In Yekaterynoo1av conditions were found to be such that the dead lay unburiod for two weeks and wero then buried many together in shallow graves where the dog3 got at them. Most of the hospitals had been obliged to close owing chiefly to lack of food and fuel.     Malaria was prevalent and three fatal cases of cholera (confirmed bacteriologically) occurred in Inarch this year.     ffioholayev, and Oh era on were found to be very gravely smitten by famine and epidemic diseases and the death rate among famine victims was reported to be 50 per cent.     It was said that theIscondition of children collected in houses was terrible.(c) Both Dr. Kaigh. and Professor Muhlehs have placed on record in their reports the occurrence of instances
of oannabilism among the faraine-etrieken in districts which they have visited.Secondly as regards the sanitary cordon of defence between Russia and neighbouring countries.(a)    Our tour of inspection made plain to us that the existing sanitary defence between Russia and Poland had failed to prevent the westward spread of the epidemic diseases prevailing in Ruesia.     Typhus and relapsing fever were present in every town and village which we visited in Poland and in many Instances we ascertained that refugeS3 or repatries from Russia were the source of infection and the agents of spread.      Some of the factors concerned in tho breakdown are stated in medical reports on Minsk and other localities as follows:-(l)    In Russia no moans has yet been found to prevent or control the movement of refugees from famine districts. It is said that all responsible officials have a real fear of infringing tho &quot;liberty&quot; of individuals to do as they like, and that (as Russia is virtually a country without a legal code) no sanitary regulations with penalties for infringement can be enforced.(2)   Refugees who have money to buy a railway ticket move by train in any direction without hindrance other than the difficulty of obtaining room in the trains.     But owing to. absence of coal and shortage of wood, railway traffic is carried on.only with the greatest difficulty.     There are frequent long delays at wayside stations and when this occurs the passengers invade the nearest towns and villages and barter some of their clothes for food and accommodation. In this way the local inhabitants become infected and a serious local epidemic begins.(3.)   Refugees passing in large groups through disinfecting stations in Russia are not satisfactorily de-loused, chiefly from lack of adequate means and supplies such as wood, sulphur,
soap and clothing.     Owing to the shortage of wood (in a country of forests) the water &quot;boilers at some stations..had. not boon used for a month and poo pie travelling in snail parties could not be de-loused.(4)   Between the Volga area and IT in sic there is no barrierto deal with refugees who do not pass through Moscow,(5)   A numerous crowd of people have taken refuge in thewoods extending along the whole frontier of White Russia.They hope to reach the Polish frontier by road, but theyare in no one&apos;a charge, are existing without inspection ovmedical help, practically as savages, and no information asto numbers, diseases or mortality among thorn can be obtained.(b)   The arrangements at tho Polish Quarantine stationof Baranoviese are pood and thoroughly carried out, butthe arrangements at some of the hospitals which we inspectedin Polish towns and villages left much to be desired.Nevertheless I believe that the Polish authorities havedone all that was possible with the.moans and materialavailable, and that they well deserve further financialand other material assistance.Thirdly as regards tho action to bo taken.(a)    The above notes are additional to the official information on which, and on tho results of our tour of inspection, the Conference arrived at the conclusion that action limited to extending and supplementing the existing frontier sanitary cordon would bo ineffectual.     People fleeing westward from Russia start from known famine and disease affected centres, but the lines along which they travel multiply and spread out fanwlse, and the meshes of the defensive net got larger, as the frontier is approached. It seemed clear that defence on the frontiers and action at the sources of infection In Russia must be simultaneously carried out.     Action in the interior of Russia would, of course, lesson greatly the coat of the elaborate arrangements
ffor defence which the delegations from neighbouring countries laid before the Conference.     Moreover it seers cle?r that in Russia while there is so much suffering, mortality, incapacity to work, and panic-stricken flight hither and thither, no economic reconstruction can be possible.     The existing conditions of famine and epidemic disease paralyse all activity except the attempt to escape death.     On a much more severe scale the position is analagous to the position during the earlier years of effort to construct the Panama Canal when it was not possible to get or to retain any labour until the prevailing epidemics had been overcome. For those reasons, as woll as for those which are stated in tho Resolution on this subject passed by the Conference; I consider that the problem of reconstruction in Russia is at present primarily a Public health and Medical problem; and that, unless this aspect has precedence,  any endeavour toward industrial and commercial reconstruction will fail.O * A  *     J ill&apos;:.; ,iO *i3rd April,  1012,istry of Health, Whitehall,a m
EUROPEAN HEALTH CONFERENCE HELD AT WARSAW PROM 20th to 23th MARCH,  1222. .   RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED AT PLENARY SESSIONS OF THE CONFERENCE.1. Resolutions relating to the proeont epidetnic^ &apos;situation in Eastern Europe and the risk of Wg s tward spra ad..,Tho following resolutions were unanimously adopted by tho Conference in plenary session:-(l)    The conditions. which arose, in Eastern Europe during and after the great war woro very favourable to tho development of dangerous epidemics especially of the insect-borne diseases typhus and relapsing favor, of food and water-borne.diseases such as cholera,  typhoid fever and dysentery and of other communicable diseases such as smallpox. For example, in Russia before the war the overage incidence of typhus fever was about 90,000 oa.ses por annum and of relapsing fever about 30,000:   but in 1920 the typhus cases officially notified numbered 3,000,000 and tho relapsing fever cases 1,000,000.&apos;      Poland and other countries of Eastern Europe suffered on a similar scale.(2)    The countries attacked by those epidemics organised and carried out thoroughly all the measures of control and defence that were possible in circumstances of great social and economic - difficulty and their efforts were followed during the first 9 months of 1921 by a marked improvement:.,     For example, cases of typhus fever fell in Poland from 157,000 during 1920 to 48,000 during 1921;
in Russia from 3,000,000 to 800,000;    in Roumania from 45,855 to 4,334.(3)   But unfortunately towards the end of 1931 a new and intense access of adverse conditions associated with famine, migration and repatriation severely overtaxed the....................... anti-epidemic arrangements andled to a sudden and violent recrudescence of typhus and relapsing fever accompanied by an epidemic of cholerae After hearing the reports of the responsible officers who have Just returned from afflicted areas in the Volga district, the Ukraine and the Black Sea littoral, the Conference ia convinced that the increasing prevalence and extension of cholera in the Ukraine and the mass-migration towards the North West of populations from these and other famine-stricken areas combine to constitute an immediate danger to the rest of Europe,,     The adverse conditions, the migration from stricken areas, and the associated epidemic diseases are at present increasing rapidly and the situation a3 a whole is becoming more menacingu(4)   Having regard to this information and to the knowledge that the causes of the development and extension of cholera ana ether dangerous epidemic diseases in Eastern Europe are continuing in an aggravated degree * tho Conference is convinced that unless much, greater efforts than have hitherto been possible are made - and that without delay - the present epidemiological situation will cause much more serious suffering end death among the populations of the infected areas, will impede reconstruction will hamper trade and will constitute a real and imminent danger to the whole continent of Europe.
II. Resolutions rolntinr to the action whjch should be taken. A.     Tho genor al poli cy which the Confer one e reo grim ends .The following resolution was adopted unanimously in plenary session.1.- -      - &apos;    In regard to the principles upon which action should be based, the Conference has carefully considered that following policies, namely(l)    A defensivo policy of strengthening and supplementing the existing anti-epidemic arrangements.within the frontior zone of Russia, White Russia and the Ukraine, and the countries bordering, them on the west,In the opinion, of tho Conference, the minimum requirements of this policy are:-(a) To improve and supplement existing arrangements at Seba.3, Polock- Minsk, Gomel and Sheptcwka.(b) Ditto at South Russian, ports, chiefly Odessa,Nlcolaya, Kherson and Rostov.(c) Ditto in Finland, Esthonia, Latvia, Lithuania,.Poland and RoUmania. (2),   A policy which, combines the strengthening of thedefence within tho frontier zone with comprehensive measures in Russia and the Ukraine.     The measures would comprisej-(a) Within the frontier zone.     All the arrangements enumerated In the first policy outlined above.(b) In the interior of Russia and the Ukraine.    Tho
reinforcing of health organisation  at railway junctions and at various other places of importance from- the point of vie;; of epidemics in the interior of Russia particularly at Smolensk, Kiev, Kharkov, Odessa and also at places in the cholera area of the Ukraine, (c) Strengthening of the public health service in Russia and the Ukraine essential for the prosecution of the epidemic campaign. In coming to a decision as to which policy to recommend, the Conference has fully realised the magnitude and cost of the arrangement proposed merely for countries bordering on Russia, but, it is convinced that a campaign confined, to those countries or to tho frontier area would be ineffective.     The Conference is convinced not only that the reconstruction of Russia is impossible so long as tho present epidemics continue, but alee that the continual menace of those diseases is seriously impeding reconstruction in neighbouring countries.In view of the fact that an epidemic of cholera has recently begun to spread rapidly in the Ukraine and in Russia in addition to the epidemics of typhus and relapsing fever, no scheme for the economic reconstruction of these countries can be carried out until there is an improvement in health conditions.      Should these deplorable conditions continue they will seriously hinder anj  attempt . to resume commercial relations and will paralyse any real
economic activity.     The Conference fully appreciates the great work done by the Health Services of the Soviets under the most difficult conditions but it is deeply impressed by the amount of suffering and mortality in Russia.      It considers that the health defence,of adjoining countries, and particularly that of Poland,  is now organised on a sound basis and that their health services have proved their competence *In view of these facts the Conference has decided to adopt tho plan of a combined campaign against epidemics hy defence on the frontiers and by simultaneous action in the interior of Russia.B.     Financial and other Administnative arrang.em.entafor oarryirr* the policy J-nto effect, II OS.  (I) to (7) of the following resolutions were adopted unanimously.   No.(8) was adopted by 35 votes . as against 3 votes.     The dissentient votes were of Russia and-the Ukraine.     The Conference took: note of the reservations presented by these two delegations and agreed that the alternative resolution which they had drawn up should be presented as a minority resolution.     It is placed below under the number (8a) .(l)   Whereas the health, situation in Europe is in grave danger, the Conference is of opinion that the campaign against epidemics requires very serious efforts, which cannot be made solely by the countries chiefly concerned.
&apos;(2) All European countries should agree to take an active part in the cmpaign against the epidemics prevalent in Eastern Europe.(3) The allocation of expenses in the case of States who are Heribers of the League should be made in accordance with the scale cadopted by the Second Assembly,(4) /ill other States should be asked to -contribute their share of the expenses on a similar basic0(5) States conducting the campaign in their own country at their own expense shoipLd be allowed to deduct from their quota tho expenditure incurred for that purpose in their own territory..(6) Contributions nay bo made in money, in supplies or in Tjersonnsl.(7) The execution of work or of the measures adopted should bo exclusively directed by the health service of the G0v3rumen1s cone erncd,(0) The health Organisation of the League of Nations should be entrusted with the execution of the decisions of tho European Health Conference at Warsaw.Should European States furnish financial or other assistance to one of the States&apos; concerned, through the intermediary of the Spidenies Commission of the League of ITations, the Health Organisation of the League shall have the right to control the use to which money.or supplies arc put *The Conference desires to lay stress upon the necessity that States not h-e ibers of the League of Nations should have representatives on this,Organisation.i(6a) The execution of the decisions arrived at by the International Health Conference at. Warsaw, together19,
with such measure? as nay, in future,  appear necessary, shall be handed ever to a special International Committee, All countries shall be represented on this Committee and enjoy equal rights,.The International Committee shall have the right to control the use of funds and material provided through-its agency.
C. Loc?il sanitary^ cox^yentione, and othor, e^reeyaont^ between, neighbouring states, to, facilitate, carrying the,, policy into, effect.The following resolutions were adopted unanimously.(l) International regulations dealing with infectious diseases should &quot;be extended to covor other diseases besides those named in the Paris Convention.(2) Compulsory notification &quot;by Governments of infectious diseases should be extended to cover other diseases not named in the Paris Convention, and tho machinery of notification should bo orgainised in a more apprcpriate manner.(3) Comprehensive measures should be introduced to deal with infectious diseases, especially the diseases now raging in the East.     These meaetires should, in addition to general provisions, contain special provisions dealing with:(a) frontier traffic (including local frontiertraffic);(b) traffic by water.(4) For the execution of 1,, 2 and 3 the States concerned and directly threatened should,  as soon as possible, take steps to conclude special health agreements, the clauses of which will naturally differ according to the special conditions in the various -States, but which will conform to the principles enunciated in the attached report.(5) llutual recognition of certificates for protective vaccination,-disinfection and deloueing, given by medical men authorised by the State, would
greatly facilitate traffic &quot;between the Contracting IStates. ((6) The Conference expresses tho hope that other health questions, such as social hygienic (tuberculosis, sexual diseases   diseases due -to seme&apos; particular&apos;, imployment others) exchange of medical men, etc. will bo included in the agenda of one of the next International Health Conferences in order to produce close co-op.oration tetwcai all states in matters of public health.      The Conference believes, hoy/ever, that without the sujjport of public opinion, efforts to improve public health will not attain their.object and that, therefore, systematic instruction and education of the people is absolutely necessary.I.i Resolution ^r^err^d^b;/ gi^ojfe^eejr Otto,;.janjd^a^lopJ^The European Health Conference at Warsaw lays special stress on the necessity of supporting health measures, to be undertaken in Russia end the Ukraine, by a campaign against the famine, which is one of the chief causes of the epidemics, and invites all nations to take part in this campaign, without which efficient measures against tho epidemics are impossible.2.  ocioj^hd^tie^It appears that several Health Conventions will be concluded betwoon different States.      It seems advisable therefore that if an organ of conciliation or mediation has to ho constituted to settle in a friendly manner questions in dispute, the Health Section of the lefigue of nations, or possibly a special
Co:mission of the Section&apos;, should ho entrusted with this duty, without prejudice to the right of eny State to have recourse to a different procedure.3 * KeepJ.ijt,ijori proposed by Pro fees or ^Castel^-anl Qnf the^ Itelij?^Delegatipn j.ind adopted, by^the^ confereneg, on March 27th., 19,22 eHaving regard to the necessity of refilling the ranks of the medical and sanitary personnel engaged in the campaign against epidemics in Eastern Europe and believing that the fight can be waged successfully only by the personnel of the interested Public Health Services, the Conference recommends that training courses for all grades of medical and sanitary personnel should be organised at two or three centres, for example, Warsaw, Eharkoff and Moscow.     Experts drawn from Public Health Services of all nations should be invited to join the teaching staffnAt tho acme centres permanent museums should be established consisting of the most appropriate apparatus etc., for the fight against infection, as well as all other useful means of combating epidemic diseases.The Conference requests that the technical organisation, which is entrusted with the execution of these resolutions should take early steps to realise this recomraendation.4. Xlesolution--presented &apos;by-Lthe 3 st: Commission. and, ad. on ted,, Try&quot; the Confer on per in. p2.ena.ry_ session.The Conference desires to put on record that the difficulties of dealing with the present situation are accentuated by the lack of medical men and trained personnel caused in part by disease and death among those who have so honourably and selflessly devoted their lives t o this c amp campaign.

</content>
</cab>
