<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 229-235</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.&apos;]Printed for the Cabinet.   April 1922.CONFIDENTIAL.CP. 3931.CABINET.CONSTABULARY (IRELAND) BILL.Memorandum by the Chief Secretary fob Ireland. (Circulated to the Committee of Home Affairs.)I CIRCULATE herewith the draft of a Bill which has been prepared to make provision for the disbandment of the Royal Irish Constabulary and with respect to magistrates appointed under the Acts relating to that force, and for the validation of things done or omitted in the execution or purported execution of those Acts, and for other purposes incidental thereto.The sole object of this Bill is to give legal effect, so far as is necessary, to the terms on which the Government have undertaken to disband the Royal Irish Constabulary. Disbandment is, in fact, taking place on these terms at the present time, but it is most important that this Bill should be passed into law as soon as possible, as until this is done there will be great difficulty in administering that part of the disbandment scheme which has reference to the commutation of compensation allowance in cases where a man desires to emigrate.The Bill has been drafted in close consultation and agreement with the Treasury. 1 hope, therefore, that I. may be given permission to introduce the Bill forthwith.H. G.Irish Office, Old Queen Street, S.W. 1, April 5, 1922.[82063
[12 Geo. 5.]      Constabulary [Ireland). 1DRAFTof aB I L LTOMake provision for the disbandment of the Royal a.d. 1922. Irish Constabulary and with respect to magis-trates appointed under the Acts relating to that Force, and for the validation of things done or omitted in the execution or purported execution of those Acts and for other purposes incidental thereto.BE it enacted hy the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, hy and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, arid by the authority of the same, 6 as follows : 1. (1) The Royal Irish Constabulary shall be dis- Disband-banded on such day, not being later than the thirty-first ^&quot;I^jj.;^ day of May nineteen hundred and twenty-two, as may Constabn-be fixed by the Lord Lieutenant, and on or before that lary, and10 date every officer and constable of that force shall retire provision from the force as and when required by the Lord Lieu- as t0 milg&apos;8-tenant, and shall on his retirement be entitled to receive pr0a^,etse^p&quot; such compensation as may be awarded to him hy the under the Treasury in accordance with the rules contained in the Acts relating15 Ninth Schedule to the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, thereto, as amended and modified by the provisions set out in the Schedule to this Act.(2) The provisions of Article 15 (which relates to assignment and regulations as to payment of pensions, &amp;c), 20 Article 16 (which relates to forfeiture of pension or allow-ance), and Article 17 (which relates to suspension of pension in case of service in another force, &amp;c.) of the Royal Irish Constabulary Pensions Order, 1922, shall86-3 A/
2Constabulary [Ireland).      [12 Geo. 5.]A.d. 1922. apply as respects compensation allowances awarded in pursuance of this section in like manner as they apply as respects pensions under that:Order, with the substitution of references to the Treasury for references to the Inspector-General. 5(3) Sections eight and ten of the Police Pensions Act, 1921, shall not apply to the service in the Uoyal Irish Constabulary of any officer or constable to whom a compensation allowance has been awarded in pursuance of this section, but if any such officer or constable takes 10 service in any police force, or is appointed to any office remunerated out of moneys provided by Parliament, or to any office which is a public office within the meaning of the Superannuation Act, 1892, and on his ultimate retirement therefrom is awarded a pension, then, if the 15 amount of the compensation allowance when added to the amount of his pension exceeds the higher of the two following sums, (a) two-thirds of the salary on which his compensa-tion allowance was calculated; or 20(b) two-thirds of the salary of which he was in receipt at the time of his ultimate retirement;or should those sums be equal, exceeds either of those sums, his compensation allowance may be suspended to the extent of the excess : 25Provided that where the officer or constable on his ultimate retirement is awarded a lump sum instead of or in addition to a pension, the annual amount which would represent that sum, if converted into a life annuity, shall be determined by the Treasury, and the amount so deter- 30 mined shall, for the purpose of the foregoing provision, be deemed to be or to form part of his pension.Ibr the purposes of this subsection the expression &quot; Parliament&quot; shall include any Parliament which is or may be established in Ireland. &apos; 35(4) The Pensions Commutation Acts, 1871 to 1882, shall apply to any officer or constable to whom a com-pensation allowance is awarded in pursuance of the provisions of this section in like manner as if he had retired from the permanent civil service of the Crown on 40 the abolition of his office, and any terminable annuity payable to the National Debt Commissioners in respect
1[12 Geo. 5.]       Constabulary (Ireland). 3of the commutation of a compensation allowance shall he A.D. 1922. paid out of the same funds as the allowance:Provided that in such cases and on such terms as the Treasury may hy regulation prescribe, the Treasury may, 5 on the application of any such officer or constable, commute a portion of the compensation allowance so awarded to him as aforesaid for an annuity for a term of two years but ceasing on his death if he dies within that term, and in such ease the following provisions shall have 10 effect:-(a) the capital sum representing the portion of the compensation allowance to be commuted shall be ascertained in accordance with the tables and the rule for determining age for the time being in15 force under the Pensions Commutation Acts,1871 to 1882 ;(b) the capital sum so ascertained shall be applied bythe National Debt Commissioners in providing an annuity for such term as aforesaid, and the20 National Debt Commissioners shall have powerto grant such an annuity; (c?) in calculating the amount of the annuity, the same rate of interest shall be assumed as is assumed in calculating such  capital  sum as-25 aforesaid;(d) Subject as aforesaid the annuity shall be calcu-lated in such manner and in accordance with such tables, and shall be payable in such manner and at such times as the Treasury may by regu-30 lations prescribe.(5) Section nine of the Constabulary and Police (Ireland) Act, 1888 (which relates to the punishment of persons obtaining pensions, &amp;c, by fraud), shall apply in the case of compensation allowances and commutation 35 annuities awarded or payable in pursuance of this section in like manner as it applies in the case of pensions under that Act.(6) &quot;Where, for the purpose of expediting the dis-bandment of the Royal Irish Constabulary, any member 40 of that force has, since the tAventy-fifth day of January nineteen hundred and twenty-two and before the passing of this Act, been discharged with compensation, his discharge and the grant of compensation to him shall86 A 2
4Constabulary (Ireland).      [12 Geo. 5.]A.D. 1922. be as valid and effectual as if they had been expressly authorised by this Act, and the compensation shall be treated as compensation payable under this Act, and the provisions of this Act with respect to a cominpensation allowance awarded in pursuance of this section shall apply 5 to any annual allowance so granted.(7) All compensation payable under this Act (in-cluding any compensation which is to he treated as so payable) shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament. 10(8) For the purposes of section fifty-seven of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, so far as it relates to pensions of officers and constables, of the Royal Irish Constabulary payable at the date of transfer, the day fixed for the disbandment of the Royal Irish Constabulary 15 shall, so far as respects Northern Ireland, be treated as the date of transfer.Transfer of 2. On the day fixed for the disbandment of thepublic Royal Irish Constabulary the public services in connec-cooneeti&quot;1 ^on w^ mag&apos;ish&apos;ates appointed under the Acts relating 20 with resident that ^01*ce shall, as respects Northern Ireland, be trans-magistatcrs. ferred from the Government of the United Kingdom to the Government of Northern Ireland, and the provisions of the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, in their applica-tion to Northern Ireland, shall have effect accordingly in 25 like manner as if the said day had been duly determined by His Majesty in Council under section nine of the said Act to be the date for the purpose aforesaid.3. Anything done or omitted after the first day of January nineteen hundred and nineteen in relation to the 30 appointment or distribution of officers or constables of the Royal Irish Constabulary, including the appointment or purported appointment of officers or constables in excess of the numbers authorised to be appointed by the Acts relating to that force, or otherwise in the execution 35 or purported execution of those Acts, shall be deemed to have been lawfully done or omitted if the act or omission was authorised by the Lord Lieutenant or Chief Secretary or is certified by a Secretary of State to have heen necessary or expedient with a view to the restoration or 40 maintenance of order in Ireland.Short title. 4. This Act may be cited as the Constabulary(Ireland) Act, 1922.Validation of things done or omitted in the execution of the Acts relating to the Royal Irish Con-stabulary.
[12 Geo. 5]       Constabulary (Ireland).schedule.-  The rules in the Ninth Schedule to the Government of Ireland Act, 1920, shall apply for the purposes of the award of compensation under section one of this Act, subject to the 5 following modifications : (1) Any reference to the Lord Lieutenant shall he construed as a reference to the Treasury, and the expression &quot; existing enactments &quot; shall be construed as meaning enactments in force at the time of the passing of 10 this Act and any orders made under those enact-ments and in force at that time.(2) The following proviso shall he added at the end of rule 2 :-Provided that in the case of the surgeon of the 15 Royal Irish Constabulary his compensation allow-ance may, should he so desire, be calculated in like manner a s the pension which he would have been entitled to receive on retirement under the existing enactments applicable to him if the years to be 20 added as aforesaid were added to his years of ageinstead of to his completed years of actual service.(3) Rule 3 shall not apply.(4) The following rule shall be substituted for rule 4 : &quot; (4) The allowance awarded to an officer or constable 25 shall in no case exceed two-thirds of the salaryon which the allowance is calculated.&quot;
Constabulary (Ireland).BEAETof aBILLTo make proAdsion for the disbandment of the Royal Irish Constabulary and with respect to magistrates appointed under the Acts relating to that Force, and for the &quot;validation of things done or omitted in the execution or pur-ported execution of those Acts and for other purposes incidental thereto.ith April 1022.86-3

</content>
</cab>
