<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 444-454</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Mades^s^Government.]Printed for the Cabinet,   June 1922.SECRET.CP. 3953.CABINET.IRAQ TREATY.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I circulate telegrams which have passed between the High Commissioner for Iraq and myself since this question was last discussed by the Cabinet.Colonial Office, June 8, 1922.(1.).SJ    / Mr. Churchill to Sir P. Cox.(Personal and Private.) April 6, 1922.Clftu1 the line.Caafjnet to-day fully considered Treaty Mandate question and were unanimously of opinion that it would be impossible for us to escape from the Mandate position imposed upon us by League of Nations except by abandoning Mandate altogether and consequently quitting Iraq. I shall telegraph next week a formal statement of our views for communication to Feisal and also a personal message from myself. 1 shall be glad to hear from you forthwith whether it is not possible to leave the whole matter in suspense for one, two or three months and carry on as we are doing without either ratified Mandate or a Treaty. Cabinet would be willing to concede point about foreign representation, i.e., to accept Colonial Office version of Article 5, referred to in your secret and personal telegram of the 19th March, if other matters were satisfactorily adjusted. You had better make no formal communication to Peisal on this message until you hear further at length from me. This is sent purely for your personal information.Secondly, I am astonished that Feisal should have dismissed four Ministers without consulting you. Such action was surely not in accordance with the spirit of his personal undertakings about taking your advice in important matters. I should be very sorry if Sassoon Effendi insists on going. You may, if you like, tell him I have telegraphed personally about him. It seems doubly important to temporise over the Treaty, as departure of Naqib would be very bad when so many others are going for different reasons. Please advise me at once whether (a) either a formal communication should not be made by you to Peisal on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government about his precipitate action, or (&amp;) whether I should not refer to it in personal message I am going to send. Churchill.[8464]b
(3-).Telegram from High Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State for the Colonies.(No. 294.   Secret.) April 15, 1922.My telegram No. 175 of 3rd March (not printed).I had a long personal talk with Feisal yesterday on the situation in general, the occasion being the fortunate outcome of the Kerbala conference, regarding which see my immediately preceding telegram. After discussing the above and observing in conclusion that, at any rate, he hoped that His Majesty&apos;s Government would appreciate the advantage of his having secured a formal resolution of loyalty and support from the Shia hierarchy, he turned to the question of Treaty negotiations, and asked if there was no news yet from London. I replied that I had not yet received an answer to my last communication, owing, no doubt, to your other great pre-occupations at this juncture; but, I continued, from the tenor of a private letter which I received by the last air mail, I very much feared that the chances of His Majesty&apos;s Government being internationally able to abandon the mandatory relation were very remote, and that, in case a final reply should come in an unfavourable sense, it would be well for us to contemplate what our position would then be here and what would be our best course of action.Feisal replied promptly that he had intended to tell me at this interview that the situation would not admit of the matter remaining in suspense much longer, and that, if I had not received or did not expect to receive a reply within the next two or three days, he proposed to address me officially, pointing out the difficulty of his position after ten months in Iraq and the danger and impossibility of carrying on much longer on the present indeterminate lines.Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq, to Secretary of State for the Colonies.(Secret.   Private and Personal.) April 7, 1922.Your private and personal telegram of 6th.As regards the Mandate question, I propose to defer communicating conclusions of Cabinet to Feisal until Kerbala gathering is over. The unfavourable news would only provide agitators with fresh stimulus.The alternative in the last resort to carry on for a few months longer as we are has been envisaged in discussion between Feisal and myself, but not recently, and only with misgiving.There is, first, the consideration that we oannot indefinitely postpone the elections for the Constituent Assembly, and, secondly, the probability that the patience of the British personnel in regard to the settlement of their terms of service would be exhausted, and that a number of resignations would follow announcement of fresh postponement of negotiations. But I would wish to defer my final views on this suggestion until we have seen the result of the Kerbala gathering and matter has been discussed with Feisal and Naqib; that is, supposing that your present telegram is the last word on the question of the Mandate.I recommend that you also defer your personal communication to Feisal until after the Kerbala meeting for reasons above indicated.As regards the Ministers, Feisal seems now to realise that he was too hasty, and -inclined to seek means to make it possible for one or two to return after a short interval if he can do so without loss of dignity. I think your communication to him on that point had better be a personal one, expressing disappointment that he had taken such a disturbing course without consultation with me or his own natural advisers. Message had perhaps better await conclusion of Kerbala episode, so that if necessary both can be dealt with together. .My &quot;point of view is that it is not the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government nor my personal inclination to destroy his prestige as King and oblige him to abdicate by compelling him to undo hasty or ill-advised acts which he has taken without consultation, but that, if he shows an undue tendency in that direction, my remedy is to ask to be relieved and to make known the reason.As regards Sassoon, he is coming to see me this evening. I will give&apos;him your message and hope we may be able to find a solution which will satisfy him.
You are aware of the great risk from a British point of view involved in the postponement of Treaty negotiations, namely, its effect upon the British personnel and upon the Constituent Assembly when it meets. The public are aware that the negotiations have come to a halt over the Mandate question, and I agree with Feisal that delay is dangerous and that the position would deteriorate quickly if the matter were left in the air.The people of Iraq no doubt are mainly inarticulate, and whether a majority of them at all appreciate the portent of the mandatory relation or actively wish the termination of it I am not prepared to say. But I am certain that the young Iraqis, the newspapers and the articulate elements in the towns are out against it, and I am convinced that Feisal personally cannot now make good under the mandatory relation, and that a Treaty on that basis will not go through on its merits.But what I feel is that our difficulty in this connection are in a great measure questions of terminology and international technicality, and that, as regards the wishes and intentions of the parties concerned, there is not really much divergence. Consequently I earnestly recommend that every possible avenue for solution be explored before a final unfavourable answer is sent to Feisal, which it might be difficult for His Majesty&apos;s Government to recede from.To this end I respectfully offer the suggestion that Feisal and I should pay a short visit to London by air in the hope of reaching a solution by personal discussion. I do not think the purpose would be served by either of us coming alone. His going alone would be interpreted to mean that he was not coming back. My going alone would suggest that I had been called home to be squared. On the other hand, if we go together and the public are frankly informed that one or two difficulties have arisen in connection with the Treaty negotiations which it is considered could be best adjusted by personal discussion, I am sure we could come without risk of complica-tions, especially after the clearing o  the atmosphere resulting from the Kerbala meeting.I beg that this suggestion be deliberately considered before final conclusions are taken.(4-)Telegram from Secretary of State for the Colonies to Sir P. Cox.(No. 244.) April 20, 1922.We see serious difficulties in you and Feisal leaving the country at the present time. We do not exclude this at a later stage if you are convinced that it offers a real prospect of a solution. Meanwhile, our position must be taken as fully defined by our previous communications. We thought we were meeting Feisal&apos;s wish in placing our relations with Iraq upon a Treaty basis. But if the King does not like the form which the Treaty has now reached after these long negotiations, it is out of our power to depart from the attitude adopted, and the Treaty must remain in suspense.We should be very glad to receive from him in the course of the next few weeks any counter-suggestions which he may care to make, and you are fully entitled to aid him in any way. It is no use repeating the same arguments over and over again. We have taken up the only position possible to us, having regard to international obligations by which we are bound.I am quite ready to send him a direct message from the Cabinet explaining the situation. I send you a draft of the sort of thing that may finally have to be said, on which you should let me have your observations at leisure. But, for the present, I think it better to temporise. Please inform me what course you think events will follow in the next few months if Treaty deadlock is prolonged, and what inconveniences are we to face. I am sure that if trouble arises in Iraq involving the prospect of additional expense, the Cabinet will order immediate and complete evacuation. Feisal should be under no delusions in this matter. He will be a long time looking for a third throne.Draft follows (begins) : The British Government have no power to abrogate or terminate the Mandate for1 Iraq which they hold from the League of Nations, except by resigning once and for all their special&quot; position in the country.  The other Great Powers on the Council [8464] B 2
of the League of Nations would not agree to &quot;Britain having a special position in Iraq unless controlled by the Mandate. America, though not a member of the League, would also refuse consent. There is no possibility, therefore, of Britain freeing herself from the Mandate otherwise than by washing her hands altogether ot responsibilities towards Iraq.The meaning of the Mandate and its whole purpose was to restrain Britain and not to restrain Iraq. The Mandate regulates and restricts the action of the mandatory Power, and is intended solely to safeguard the interests of Iraq. The other great Powers would never allow Britain to have special treaty relations with Iraq while escaping from the Mandate. If we were to ask the League of Nations to release us from the Mandate, they would refuse; and the only course open to us would be either to bow to their decision or to quit the country altogether.Of course, when Iraq becomes strong enough in our opinion to stand alone, we shall be in a position to state that our task has been fulfilled, and that Iraq is in fact as well as in status an independent sovereign State. But this cannot be said with any respect for truth and fact while we are forced year after year to spend very large sums of money on helping the Iraq Government to defend itself and to maintain order.&quot;We therefore are unable at the present time to alter the position which has been reached in the negotiations for the Treaty. If there is to be a Treaty it must be on this basis and no other. If the King or his Cabinet or the Assembly cannot agree to a Treaty on this basis, then it will be impossible to frame a form of agreement regulating the relations of Britain and Iraq. These are facts which do not depend upon the wish of the British Government, but on powers and laws to which they must bow.The King will therefore see that if the Treaty, which was his idea and not ours, cannot be agreed, there is nothing for us but to go forward on the present indeterminate basis until Iraq is strong enough to stand alone. There really is no use searching for vain formulas which disguise the fact that Britain has to obey the League of Nations, and that Iraq must accept our guidance whilst it requires our aid.The question which the King should now address, himself to is the following : Does he desire us to quit Iraq forthwith ? We have installed him and his Govern-ment in power, and the country is at present in an orderly state. We could begin the evacuation immediately after the hot weather, and all British troops and civilians could be out of the country before the end of the Christian year. If this is the King&apos;s wish, he should say so, with the knowledge that the responsibility for what follows will rest upon him. I will then bring his wish to the notice of the Cabinet, who alone can take the final decision. The British nation would rejoice to be relieved from a burdensome charge devoid of the slightest advantage to them, but which they have carried thus far from a sense of duty to the people of Iraq, whose Turkish Government they overturned in the war, and out of loyalty to the King, who they believed wished to continue for himself and the Shereefian family the friendly relationships established in the Great War. Churchill.  Ends.(5.)    :Telegram from High Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State for the Colonies.(No. 312.  Secret.) April 22, 1922.Your telegram No. 244, received 21st April.As regards proposed message to Feisal. The position of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment internationally being what you describe, the sooner we clear the air by stating it authoritatively the better for all parties. The text of your message as a whole seems to meet the case, but I would advocate allusion to the alternative of retirement to Basra as well as to that of complete evacuation. Closer scrutiny of draft may suggest observations in regard to some other detail; meanwhile, please consider following suggestions, and, if possible, let me know immediately whether the course proposed is prima facie feasible.My telegram No. 299 of 18th April suggesting a possible interpolation in the Treaty, and my telegram No. 302 regarding effect of Kerbela episode, probably reached you after despatch of your telegram under reply.Feisal&apos;s undoubted personal association, if not his direct initiative in encouraging Ulema to interfere in matters which.concern the Government, and the
evident disposition of himself and his extremist adherents to exaggerate the Akhwan incident and use it for their own ends, is now evoking much unfavourable comment among the best people, especially among the tribal Sheikhs; and a considerable body of the latter have spontaneously gathered in Baghdad with the intention of presenting a written memorial or of going in a body to Feisai to remonstrate at recent happenings, and to remind him of the condition of their oath of allegiance. Feisal&apos;s stock is consequently somewhat low at this juncture, and the moment is a psychological one for an announcement from His Majesty&apos;s Government. It would, however, have very much greater value and effect if it could be made in a form which can be given prompt publicity throughout Iraq, instead of being communicated to Feisal personally. Could it not be arranged that someone should ask a question in the House of Commons saying that he understood that there was a hitch in the Treaty negotiations with Iraq over the question of the duration or continuance of the mandatory relation, and asking that the House should be informed what the position was, and, if possible, of the purport of the Treaty under negotiation ?In reply you would explain the situation as far as possible in the terms of your proposed message to Feisal, and if it is not considered feasible to insert in the Treaty some clause on the lines suggested in my telegram No. 299, perhaps you could include an authoritative observation to an equivalent effect in your reply. If you could also communicate to the House the text of our final draft of the Treaty, and authorise me to make it known here, it would be more advantageous. It would then be arranged with Reuter to telegraph your reply in- extenso, and if received in this form it would furnish valuable propaganda at the present moment. It will no doubt arouse controversy, but the position of His Majesty&apos;s Government being what you state, we had better face it frankly now. The announcement will, I think, be well received by the Sheikhs in their present temper, and by the people of Basra, while the Extremists will lose the opportunity that they now enjoy of discrediting a Treaty of which the generous terms are not known to the public.My suggestion that allusion should be specifically made to the alternative of retiring to the Basra Vilayet is made with two objects. It will help to ensure and strengthen the staunch adherence of Basra to the British connection, and will remind the Extremists of Baghdad of the risk they run of losing Basra if they push things too far.Anything in your draft message to Feisal which could not be included in your replying to the House could be telegraphed to Feisal simultaneously with the despatch of Reuter.I do not fully understand the reasons for which you favour a temporising course. I will think the matter out, but I have explained the effect which such an expedient will have on the Constituent Assembly, and on the British personnel, and it seems to me full of dangerous possibilities.(6.)Telegram from High Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State for the Colonies.(No. 318.  Secret.) April 25, 1922.My telegram No. 312 of 22nd April.Impressed, I think, of the trend of public opinion since the Kerbela Conference, and by the attitude of the number of Sheikhs who have assembled here, Feisal sent for me to-day urgently to discuss the general situation, Cornwallis being present.Speaking at considerable length, he said he felt that for the past month his relations with us have been clouded, and that the resulting situation was unsatisfactory and disquieting, and he felt it was urgent to clear the air. He emphasised his irrevocable attachment to the British connection, and continued that he realised that he had perhaps made mistakes, but that anything that he had done, had been done in the belief that he was promoting the success of the policy, of which his coming out at our invitation was the essential feature. He had to bear always in mind that we had expressed our inability to help him with money and troops outside the reduction programme, and he had to depend on his own exertions as far as possible.I replied that as far as he and His Majesty&apos;s Government were concerned, the question of the abrogation of the Mandate was the essential question at issue.   As regards him and myself, he was aware that I thought his judgment had been wrong [8464] B 3
in the matter of the dismissal of the Ministers and the encouragement of the Kerbela Conference. That, in my opinion, what was needed to clear the air was an announce-ment of the final decision of His Majesty&apos;s Government on the Mandate question, and a full exposition of policy in that connection which could be imparted to the public. I had expressed that view to you and hoped for a reply at any moment. Having got it, I thought we should give time to see what impression it made on the public mind, and that he and I and the Naqib should then take stock of the position and decide what course of action to recommend or to follow.He was in general agreement, and entirely agreed as tc the great need for a public announcement of policy.(7.)Cypher Telegram from, Secretary of Slate for the Colonies to Sir P. Cox.(Secret and Personal.) April 27, 1922.I am carefully considering both the proposed question and answer in Parlia-ment, and at the same time, as an alternative, the new words suggested by you, and I will telegraph to you again in a day or two. Meanwhile, please clear up this point about Basra. We have always been told that it would take more troops to hold Basra without holding the interior of the country than to hold Baghdad as we are doing now. I have frequently used this argument, and I must be careful not to stultify myself in regard to it. What do you think you could hold Basra with ? You might discuss this with the General. I agree with you in seeing great advantages in threatening to withdraw to Basra rather than retiring from the whole country, but it is necessary that there should be a practical military scheme behind it, even though we do not happen to expect to give effect to the threat.I am really very much obliged to you for the great assistance you are giving me in every aspect of these difficulties. I am far from giving up hope of getting through successfully, but I think Peisal must be brought to reason, and I never like to make a threat which one has not the power in a practical way to carry out if forced. If you think the psychological moment for bringing matters to a head has come, I will certainly not delay you beyond the middle of next week. Churchill.(8.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received April 28, 1922, 11-35 p.m.)Clear the line.There is no doubt that recent events have had an excellent effect both in strengthening moderates and chastening Feisal.He came to see me to-day to beg me not to let His Majesty&apos;s Government get impression that he would under any circumstances work against them or oppose their policy. If he found that he Had undertaken a task which he could not bring to a successful issue he would retire into private-life in England, but he would never forfeit our friendship.We then got down to business. He had now come to recognise strength and importance of moderate elements, and agreed that, when final announcement of His Majesty&apos;s Government came, if it made clear the j-eal portent of Mandate and real inability of Great Britain to divest herself of it, we (that is, he, myself and % Naqib) should not throw up the sponge, but should labour to influence electorate to accept Treaty without abrogation of Mandate, provided that apart from that clauses of Treaty were generously fair.This is a great advance, and I think it well to inform you without delay.
7 (9-)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq.(Received May 1, 1922, 3 15 p.m.) (Secret and Personal.) &apos; April 30, 1922.Your Personal and Secret, 29th April, which crossed my official telegram No. 324.General Officer Commanding is at Basra to-day, 30th April, considering on the spot question of defence of Basra, and I will submit our views in a day or two.As regards Treaty, owing to salutary effect caused by recent episodes, I feel pretty confident that omission of mention of Mandate in preamble and an interpola-tion on lines suggested in my telegram No. 299 would now satisfy Feisal and Naqib as far as Mandate question is concerned, and that they would sign Treaty if we can compose differences of view still prevailing regarding one or two articles. I still advocate dictation of proposed question and answer in House of Commons and publication of Treaty before we resume Treaty negotiations. We must consider, therefore, precisely what draft Treaty to publish. In this connection please see my telegram No. 175 of 3rd March. Apart from Mandate question, which has been separately dealt with, the present position is as follows : Article 1. Feisal has so far adhered to his request for insertion of words &quot; at the request of,&quot; which your draft omits. Can you not concede this? It does not seem crucial, and it certainly seems that position can be safeguarded by his obliga-tion to be guided by our advice in important matters.Article 3. Your draft adds words &quot; which shall be in conformity with present Treaty,&quot; which they have hitherto objected to. I suggest they might be given choice either of saying &quot; shall be drafted in consultation with High Commissioner (or with His Majesty&apos;s Government),&quot; or, &quot; shall be in conformity (or harmony) with present Treaty.&apos;&apos;A rticle 4. This is the one remaining article in regard to which I anticipate serious difficulty. They regard your wording as very severe. Can it not be eased a little?Article 5. I understand Colonial Office draft has been accepted by Cabinet. It will be accepted here.The other articles need no comment.With these remarks I respectfully leave to you precise text of Treaty for publication-. Perhaps you could say Article 4 and question of Mlahdate were only important points on which final agreement had not been reached, and explain in what way it was hoped to adjust them.In referring to Feisal in your reply in House, I hope you will allude sympathe-tically to difficulty of his task in endeavouring to satisfy extremes of opinion rather than express annoyance or impatience at his recent excursion [one corrupt group]s. I am sure you will agree that it is important not to let it appear that there has been any rift between us and him. Cox.(10.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 5, 1922, 7-30 a.m.)May 4, 1922.Reference to current correspondence. First: Feisal to-day invited me to resume Treaty negotiations, leaving the question of Mandate alone, and endeavouring to come to an agreement regarding other clauses. I replied that apart from the Mandate question financial clauses were only ones in regard to which much difference of view still existed, and I would be prepared, if he wished, to discuss any possible modifications.Secondly : It is clear that result of Kerbela meeting has been to bring people into open and divide them into pro-British or property -Mandate, and converse. Divisional advisers are being importuned for advice or a [ ? inkling] as to how cat is likely to jump, and ask urgently for an announcement of policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government which should not be delayed longer.
(Personal and Private.) May 5, 1922.I do not like plan of making announcement in Parliament. Any indication that negotiations were breaking down would revive strong public opposition to our spending money on Iraq. Your telegram No. 324 of the 28th April and private telegrams of 30th April and 1st May give impression that all that is necessary now is an official statement of our views to Feisal on lines already indicated to you. I see no objection to your informing him at the same time that ir he cannot see his way to sign Treaty, public statement will have to be made, but that, in present temper of British public result will almost certainly be demand for reduction of British commitments in Iraq.With regard to specific points raised in your telegram of the 30th April, I am prepared to give way on Article I; to accept either of alternatives now suggested by you for Article III; to accept Colonial Office draft for Article V; and to include interpolation on lines suggested in your telegram No. 299. All mention of Mandate may also be omitted from Preamble. I am not quite clear what is wanted as regards Article IV. If our draft is too severe, Feisal&apos;s original draft is not sufficiently precise.  Can you and he not arrive at alternative wording ?(12.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 12, 1922, 9 30 a.m.) Your telegram of 5th May.I addressed Feisal in the terms prescribed on 7th May, sending at the same time fresh draft of the Treaty brought up to date. Copies by air mail.Feisal sent copies to the Prime Minister for discussion in Council one day this week. Meanwhile, he has sent me the ad interim reply in which he asks me to inform you that he vehemently disclaims any idea, much less any wish, that the British should abandon Iraq, and that it is very painful to him to think that His Majesty&apos;s Government should have thought for a moment that he could entertain such feelings. If we went he would go, and his attitude in regard to the Mandate had been based on the sincere belief that a free Treaty was the surest way of cementing the British and Arab friendship.I saw him yesterday. He is highly strung as you know, and appeared genuinely upset in above connection. I replied that I did not suppose that you really thought that he personally wished us to go any more than I did, but that it was very real and lively contingency, and matters had come to a pass at which it was necessary to put the case plainly to him and have a plain answer.I think that it would be good thing if you could send him short personal message, saying you could hardly doubt what his personal feelings would be, but it was necessary to speak plainly, and you are glad to have his personal disclaimer.(13.)May 13, 1922.Your telegram No. 342 of 11th May.Before considering despatch of personal message to Feisal I should be glad to learn exact terms of your communication to him.  Please report by telegraph.,    (14.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 18, 1922, 5-4 p.m.) Your telegram No. 281.My communication to Feisal; copies by air mail have gone to you, was practically transcription of draft communicated in your telegram No. 244 of 20th April.
(15.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 25, 1922, 12-5 p.m.)Clear the line.My telegram No. 357.  Last sentence.No further progress yet. Council have had several meetings but without specific result. It appeared that members of the Council hesitated to express their individual views without some definite indication of policy from Naqib, and latter hesitated to give any because he could get none from the King, whom he still understands to demand abrogation of the Mandate. On my pointing this out to the King and suggesting that he should now come into the open and give the Cabinet a line, he says that he cannot until he has secured the Treaty draft which he can produce, and says (begins) : &quot;We must accept Great Britain&apos;s assurance that she cannot abrogate the Mandate; but our own relations with her are on the basis of this Treaty, which is the best we can expect in the circumstances, and safeguards our interests as well as hers.&quot;   (Ends.)Accordingly, we resume discussion of the draft on 26th May. Meanwhile, there is great deal of mischievous anti-Mandate propaganda going on, based in great measure on ignorance of what Mandate portends. In view of the decision in your telegram of 5th May, that any publicity at home would be imprudent at this juncture, I am doing what I can in way of counter-propaganda here, otherwise extremists who shout loudest will have it all their own way and queer pitch in advance.(16.)Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 29, 1922, 11-45 a.m.)        ,(Confidential.)Treaty negotiations have reached following stage. King asks for following modifications on following lines, and expresses confidence that if conceded he can count on NaqhVs signature. Modifications are subject to confirmation in one or two details, but as Bairan Festival is at hand, I think it advisable communicate present position with reference to draft sent with my endorsement of the 11th May.Particular passage which upset the King was (begins): &quot;The question which the King should now address to himself,&quot; &amp;c, to end of telegram.Since the despatch of my telegram No. 342 of 11th May, I have had further lengthy discussions with the King and with the Naqib, and text of the Treaty has been discussed in principle.Feisal is now personally ready to come in over the Mandate question provided that we agree to one or two consequent adjustments in the wording of the other articles.   This I have little doubt we shall be able to do.Result of very intimate talk with the Naqib is that he admits as an Iraq land-owner prospect of some measure of Mandate is by no means unwelcome to him. On the other hand, he points out that by signing the Treaty placing Muslim State under the Mandate of a Christian State he stands to gain nothing from the worldly point of view, while he thereby incurs great risk of damaging his spiritual prestige and influence in Islam. Fie has, however, given me his personal assurance that he is most anxious not to fail His Majesty&apos;s Government, and that if it should prove convenient, as an alternative to his resignation (which he is quite ready to place in our hands), he would agree to remain in office and accept situation loyally if another Minister were selected to act as plenipotentiary for the signing of the Treaty.This may provide a solution in last resort, but it will make FeisaFs position more difficult. I would much prefer, if possible, to get the Treaty into a form which the Naqib will sign himself.Council have not finished the examination of the Treaty. I do not anticipate much trouble from them. It is a little difficult to prevent new hares being started and to get them to leave well alone, but I hope to telegraph recommendations at end of week.
(17.).Decypher of a Telegram from High Commissioner, Iraq. (Received May 29, 1922, 8-45 a.m.)(Confidential.)My immediately preceding telegram. T submit following comment: Preamble. Object of general curtailment of clauses referring to responsibility of King desired by Council of Ministers on the ground^ that they are incompatible with ^he position of the constitutional monarch.Article 1. Additional words are intended to disarm criticism of the Extremists. As an alternative wording I suggested that after words &quot; subject to provisions of this Treaty,&quot; we should insert words &quot; and with due respect to the rights inseparable from national independence.&quot;  They prefer their own wording, however.Article 3. Reason given for alteration proposed is that contents of organic law had no bearing on the greater part of the Treaty, and consequently it would be more logical to refer to the specific Articles rather than the Treaty as a whole. If you do not see reason to object in principle, please consider whether reference to four Articles mentioned suffices or not.   I am also considering this point.Article 4. Reason given for omission of reference to the last sentence of Article 3. is that new wording provides for due consideration of our advice &quot; in all important matters,&quot; &amp;c, and this covers among other important matters those mentioned in Article 3.Preamble.Retain clause 1, omit clauses 2, 3 and 4. Retain clause 5; but delete from it words &quot; and responsible for Government of the country.&quot; Retain clause 6. Clause 7 to run as follows : &quot;Whereas His Britannic Majesty is satisfied that the relations between himself and His Majesty the King of Iraq can now better be defined by such a Treaty than any other means.&quot;Clause 8 to end preamble remains.Article 1. Omit the word &quot;independent&quot; before word &quot;State,&quot; and in place thereof insert at end of sentence words &quot;without prejudice to right of national sovereign.&quot; (Arabic expression used for latter is &quot;Siyadat al Wataniyeh.&quot;) Remainder of article stands.Article 3 runs : &quot;His Majesty the King of Iraq agrees to frame an organic law for presentation to Constitutional Assembly of Iraq and to give effect to said law, which must not contain provisions inconsistent with the terms of this article and those of Article 9, Article 11 and Article 12 of the present Treaty, and shall take account,&quot; &amp;c.  Remainder of article stands as it is.Article 4 runs as follows: &quot;Without prejudice to provisions of Article 17 of this Treaty His Majesty the King of Iraq agrees to accord all due consideration to advice given to him by His Britannic Majesty through High Commissioner in all important matters affecting international and financial obligations of His Britannic Majesty for whole period of this Treaty. His Majesty the King of Iraq will consult High Commissioned in what is conducive to a sound financial and fiscal policy and ensure the permanence and good organisation of finances of Iraq Government so long as that Government is under financial obligation to Government of His Britannic Majesty.&quot;Article 5 : for &apos;&apos; in London and other places&apos;&apos; read &apos;&apos; in London and other capitals and places.&quot;Article 17 runs as follows : &quot; This Treaty shall come into force as soon as it has been ratified by high contracting parties, and it shall remain in force for twenty years, and nothing shall prevent high contracting parties from reviewing from time to time provisions of this Treaty and those of separate agreements arising out of Articles 7, 10 and 15 with a view to any revision which may seem desirable in circum-stances then existing; and any modification which may be agreed upon by high contracting parties shall be communicated to League of Nations.&quot;Other articles stand as they are.
The King&apos;s draft refers &quot;His Britannic Majesty&quot; instead of &quot;His Majesty&apos;s Government,&quot; and omits reference to our &quot;interests.&quot; King supports recom-mendation on the ground that extremist elements will criticise word and suggest we may have predominant interests, and that it is not right that Iraq should be required to accept guidance or advice which may be &quot;interested.&quot; If you find difficulty in agreeing to its omission, I suggest qualification by prefix of adjective &quot;legitimate&quot; or &quot;recognised.&quot;It will be noted that second part of Article 4 has been recast and provides for consultation with the High Commissioner instead of with His Britannic Majesty. Motive for this is to safeguard Iraq Government against interference or criticism by His Majesty&apos;s Government in regard to detailed expenditure in estimates. It is contended that in this respect His Majesty&apos;s Government must rely on vigilance and cohesion of their men on the spot. Sassoon has strong convictions on this point, Slater Smallwood and I entirely support him in that attitude. Feisal asks for specific assurances on this point.The King&apos;s wording only provides, for consultation with High Commissioner. I think we must either have &quot; fully consult &quot; or &quot; pay due regard to the advice of.&quot;Article 5 also explains grievance.Article 17. They do not like the idea of being at the mercy of the League of Nations on completion of the twentieth year. I have explained difficulty of allowing no discretion to the League to insist on continuance of Great Britain&apos;s responsibility in the event of Iraq being unfit for complete freedom from supervision. I suggest purpose would be served if last sentence of Article ran &quot;the termination and any modification which may be agreed upon,&quot; &amp;c.Earliest possible indication of your views of use of modifications would be very convenient.o

</content>
</cab>
