<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 462-465</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
miS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MiLSSTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)3 5 OH H T.CABINET.CP. 5955. --REPORT BY GENERAL OEPICBR COM^commanding-IN-CHIBP ON TH3 SITUATION IN IRSLAlflTfOR YfBEK 8ND3D  9th&quot;aprIl^ISSe.^3i22&apos;^li lS^^YAl2t-Seoretarv.-of .StateMf orjy/ar)1.     The past week in Ireland has heen noticeable for a series of dastardly murders of Protestants in S.W. Cork, for a recrudesoenoe of thefts ef motor oars, and for the breakdown of the Conferences held in Dublin in the hope of restoring peace between the rival factions in the South.   Belfast and the whole of Northern Ireland have been unusually quiet, but the situation on tho Border is obscure, as owing to the seizure by force of their motor cars, the British personnel of the Southern Liaison Commission has been withdrawn.   There has been no apparent result from the action ef the Labour Party in calling a general strike on Monday 24th April as a protest against &quot;Militarism&quot;.   The Roman Catholic Bishops accompanied their* declaration in favour of the Treaty by an exaggerated statement as to the coercion and intimidation of their co-religionists in the 6 Northern Counties and this has Gravm a reply from the leading representatives of ether denominations in the North.2,       On Saturdey, 29th, the last cf a series of peace conferences organised by the R.C Bishop of Lublin and the Lord Mayor of Dublin, resulted in complete failure to come to any agreement.    In -addition to the representatives of the pro-treaty party (Messrs Griffiths and Collins) and the opposition (Messrs De Valera and Brugha) this conference was attended by three members of the Labour Party.   After the failure to come to any agreement, Messrs Griffiths and Collins issued a statement to the&quot; press, according to which they made the opposition three offers, covering between them every possible method for obtaining the views and wishes of the Irish people as to acceptance or rejection of the treaty, and on the question of the proposed free State Cpnstitution.   The refusal of the De Valera party to consider any one of the three proposals places the Provisional Gov srnment in a stronger position in the eyes of all law abiding persons, and will tell in favour of the treaty at the elections, if, and wherever, these are held without intimidation and threats.iiOcording to press reports Mr. Griffithsfs pro-treaty meeting at Ennis, Co,Glare, on Sunday, 30th, was a success; but so were De Valerars meetings at Mullingar and Longford.3-. The situation in the South of Ireland, ajjart from therecent murder of Protestants, is said to be gradually improving and to be now more favourable to the Provisional governments on 26th Anril, 3 officers and one private soldier (M.T. driver, R,A.S.C.) were kidnapped when travelling in Co. Cork. Details regarding this outrage are still lacking,    Every effort Is being made both through the Provisional Government&apos;s officials and through the Roman Catholic Clergy to obtain some clue as to the whereabouts of those officers.    Search parties have so far mat with no success.4., Prom a. statement by Liam Lynch (late Commanding 1stSouthern Division I..R.A. ) who is acting as Chief of Staff/to
6. The BELFAST boycott is still being strictly enforced andis bein?? used as an excuse for general plundering ^f goods trains.    Appendix &quot;A&quot; shows the outrages which occurred on the railways in Southern Ireland on two consecutive days (21st-22nd April).7. The following moves have taken pla.ee recently 419th April - Personnel of nYn Coast Battery B.G.A. arrived as a reinforcement to tho LOUGH SWILLY Defenceso21st April - Personnel of &quot;V&quot;, &quot;S&quot;, nX&quot; Coast Batteries R.G.A. arrived as a reinforcement to the Southern Ireland Coast Defences.25th April - 24th (H.T.) Company, R.A.S.C. left for Great Britain on disbandment.89th April - Headquarters 5th Brigade B.G.A, left for DABKHILL Im^land e18th and 20th Batteries B.S.A. left for LABKHILL, England,19th Battery R.G.A. from Baldonnel to MARLB030UGH Barracks, DUBLINoThis is attributed by General Oamarcn to the withdrawal of the T0X Specials at his request from duty in the streets of BELFAST.to Bory 0&apos;Connor (the leader of the mutineers) it appears that a considerable quantity of armstand ammunition (30 Thompson Ksohine guns Vvith 8,000 rounds (.45), 75 rifles and 10,000 rounds ,,303 ammunition) were despatched at the request of the Pro-visional Government from North County Jork area for use in the North of Ireland;    these arms however v -cpe^r to tu.ve been retained by the authorities at BEGGAR&apos;S BUSHi.   Two points are significant in this - (a) that at some time recently the Provisional Govern-ment were responsible for ordering the despatch of arms te the North or at any rate Northern 3ordsr,  though this order may have boen subsequently cancelled, and (b) that from one Divisional area it was passible for the 1.3.A. to spare, apparently without demur, no less than 30 Thompson machine guns.   This to some extent confirms the reports that large numbers of these weapons hsrve been smuggled into.the country since the &quot;Truce&quot; of July 11th.5.. The situation in BELFAST has been quieter&quot; - the casualtiesfor week (23rd-29th April) beingKilled.     Wounded.Protestants 2 2Roman Catholics 2 4Jews - 1Police - military - -Total 4 0
The evacuation of heavy baggage and stores continues.8.     The R.A.F. Aerodrome at BALDONNEE is being handed-over to the Provisional Government authorities on 4th May, the military g\iard and R.A.F. Plight (4 machines) and personn el being transferred to DUBLIN and COLLINSTOWN respectively.9.     As already reported ^ORTOBELLO Barracks, DUBLIN, were to have been handed over to the Provisional Government on 1st May.     This has not been carried out as the Provisional Government have not been able to move their stationery office from some military huts near Royal Hospital-. KILMAINHAM,- which are required for the accommodation of one of the battalions from PORTOSELLO Barracks.     As soon as these huts are handed over the evacuation of PORTOBELLO Barracks will be carried out.10.    The evacuation of the troops at YOUGHAL snd BALLINGOLLIG on QJJEEN3T0W via CORK has been further postponed owing to the inability of the Provisional Government to relieve our Garrisons.(Signed) Ce p.N. MACREAPY, General,Co11&apos;-landing-in-Chief, Ireland,G, H--Q-* Ireland, F arkgate, Dublin,2nd May,  1922,
RAILWAY SITUATION.On  1st. ins tant at Inniskeen,&apos;Co. Monoghan, the C830 hours gtiods train ex clones for Dundalk and the 1255 hours goods train ox Dundalk for Clones wore held up hy armed men and searched for Bel-fast goods.   One box, of confectionery ex London for Oarrickmacross was removed from the former train&quot;.   The 0530 hours goods train rrundalk to Inniskeen was also searched at the same place-   Bo thing was removed.OPi-glst. Instant at Templemore, Co. Tipperary, the 2100 and 2200 hours goods trains ex Kingsbridga for the South were held up by armed raiders and c quantity of goods removed from both trains.On 21st* instant at Killarney, Go. Kerry, armed men seized 2 trunks of B.IoC. luggage, consigned to Courtney, Killarney and Donnelly, Oahirciveea.On 21st. instant at $l$astlaniaisae,Co*- Kerry, armed men raided the goods store and removed a quantity of cycle parts and other goods consigned from Limerick to Csstlemaine.Qn 21st. instant at Kenmare, Oo. Kerry, armed men removed 2 boxes of grass seed,&quot;&quot;from the gocds store.&quot;On 21st. instant at iParranfore, Co. Kerry, the 0400 hours goods ex Cork for Tralee wa3 stopped and searched by armed men. nothing was removed,,foa 21 st. instant at Listowel, Co. Kerry, armed men seized 1 motor&quot; cycilo cthsJigned by ?. Oolohan. Listowel to J. iiorton, Sheffield by unofficial (Republican; troops.Cn, 21 St.. instant at Eeadford Junction, Co. Kerry, armed men held up and searched the luggage of an ex R.I.C. man.   Nothing was taken frem him.jj,P..jlst:.-instgnt;&apos;-at- Rathmore, Oo. Kerry, armed men seized the luggage of an ex B.I.C. man who arrived at Bathmore on the 1435 hours train ex MallowwOn 22nd., -instant &apos;at -Urogheda, Co. Louth, the 0900 hours goods ex -Adelaide for Dublin was stopped and searched by armed men. Nothing was taken.   The same party also held up and searched the 1430 hours passenger train ex Belfast for Dublin and removed 4 parcels and 13 pieces of commercial luggage from the guardrs van.ga 22nd, instant at Lixnaw, Oo. Kerry, the 1125 hours passenger train ex Limerick for 2ralee was stopped by armsd men who refused to allow the train to proceed until a party of 62 BeG9 troops, left the train.On 22nd. instant at Killorglin, Co. Kerry, the goods store was entered by Republican Troops who seized a quantity of furniture and 2 boxes of goods which were waiting despatch to ^ at erf ord .On 22nd.. instant at Gahirciveen, Co. Kerry, the goods store was raided by armed &quot;men who removed one case of. gramophones ex Belfast for ?JatervilIe, Co. Kerry.

</content>
</cab>
