<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 555-555</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1922.CONFIDENTIAL.CP 3969. %CABINET.CANADIAN CATTLE EMBARGO.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.I CIRCULATE a letter which I have received from the Chairman of the Norfolk Executive Committee for Diseases of Animals.w. s. c.Colonial Office, June 7, 1922.Sankence, Aylsham, Norfolk, Sir, June 5, 1922.I am writing to you, at the request of and on behalf of Norfolk arable farmers, as to the removal of the embargo on Canadian store cattle.At a meeting recently at Norwich of about 1,000 farmers, only four hands were held up against the removal of the embargo, and the Central Chamber of Agriculture was asked by that meeting to allow me to attend with the deputation that was about to see Mr. Chamberlain and Sir Arthur Griffith Boscawen. At a meeting of some 300 farmers convened by the Norfolk Chamber of Agriculture, only ten voted against the removal of the embargo, and again the Central Chamber was asked to allow me to attend and speak on behalf of Norfolk farmers.And the Norfolk branch of the National Farmers&apos; Union, by a large majority, also asked the London Committee of the Union to allow me to attend and advocate the cause of Norfolk arable farmers, but in all these cases our request has been ignored, and when deputations have gone to high members of the Government, only the views of those in favour of the retention of the embargo have been explained to those gentlemen. A public debate, challenged by Mr. German, Vice-President of the National Farmers&apos; Union, was arranged to be held at Norwich on Saturday last, the 3rd June, and Mr. Hill-Forster and I were appointed to put the case of Norfolk arable farmers, but at the last moment Mr. German called off.It is said that you are about to receive a deputation upon the subject of the embargo. I am asked by Norfolk farmers, who are angry that the Government does not give them a chance of expressing their opinion on the matter, to beg you, if you do receive such a deputation, to allow Mr. Hill-Forster and me, or if only one speaker can be allowed, that one should be Mr. Hill-Forster, to attend the deputation and inform you as to what a serious matter the retention of the embargo is for Norfolk arable farmers.I have, &amp;c.B. B. SAP WELL, Colonel, V.D.,J.P., Chairman, Norfolk Executive Committee for Diseases of Animals.The Right Hon. Winston Churchill, M.P.[8476]

</content>
</cab>
