<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 614-617</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
d 3 2S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.CABINET.INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION.Proposal with regard to tho Chairmanship of the Governing Body of the International Labour Organisation.NOTE BY THE MINISTER OP LABOUR.3TA I circulate for tho consideration of the Cabinet aMemorandum by the Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour with regard to the Chairmanship of the Governing Body of the International Labour Organisation.I propose, unless any dissent is expressed by my colleagues, to support tho proposal made in the last para-graph of the Memorandum.(Intld.) T.J.M.Ministry.of Labour. 15th May, 3 9S8.
Memorandum by the Parliamentary Seorotary to the Ministry of Labour.Chairmanship of the Governing Body of tho International Labour Organisation.1.     At the next meeting of the International Labour conference in October the Governing Body of 24 will complete th9 present throe yoars of office: and the Conference will eleot (so far as the IS employers&apos; and workers&apos; representatives are ooncernod) a new Governing Body.     This will raise -(a) tho question of tho Chairman for tho next three years;(b) the method of his election.Under the present standing orders the Chairman ia elected for a period of three yoars.2.     The presont Chairman is M. Arthur Fontaine, tho French Govornmont representative on the Governing Body.     It is possible that an attempt may bo mado to re-olect M. Fontaino as Ohalrman. Great Britain pays jointly with France the largost contribution to tho League Budget, and on this and on general grounds has claims to the Chairmanship for tho next period of three years; hut it is by no means euro that these claims would result in the appointment by tho new Governing Body of a British Chairman; and as certain other countries, e.g. Italy, havo also claims, it is not Impossible that the conflict of interests might result in the re-election of M. Fontaine.3. M. Fontaine has been a not ineffective Chairman during tho past three years; but his position Is opon to criticism, on the grounds --  INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION.
(a) that he has not time to do the continuous work of Chairman of the Governing Body, and also of soveral of its Sub-Committees - and has to appoint substitutes for the latter:(b) that both he and the Director (M. Thomas) are Frenchmen.4.     Tho Government representation on the Governing Body roquiros to be strengthened: and the smaller States in particular do not send representatives of position and foroo sufficient to resist the domands of some of the moro extreme Labour men.5.     I suggest, therefore, in order to obviate difficulties which have arisen with regard to the three years Chairmanship, and with a view to securing stronger and more responsible Government representation, that in future the Chair should be taken by oach Government Member of the Governing Body in rotation andvthat each Member should bo Chairman for one meeting only. This method has beon adopted in the caso of the Council of tho Loague of Nations, and I understand that it works well in practice.6.     The Chairmanship of the Governing Body is by tacit con-son t of the employers and workers groups confined to the Govern-ment representatives; and this system of rotation, if adopted, would moan that with four meetings a yoar and a three years duration of office- oach of the 12 Government representatives would occupy the Chair at ono meeting during the three years.This should promote greater interest on the part of the 12 Governments ropresontod and tend to secure moro effective representation.Th9 proposal will require amondmont of the Standing Orders of the Governing Body, and should be considered with other proposed amendments at the next meeting in July.I anticipate that the proposal will meet with considerable and possibly genoral support in th9 Governing Body.If no objection is taken by any member of the Cabinet may I-  o .   -
assume that I am authorised to put forward on behalf of the British Government the proposal that from October onwards tho Chairmanship be held by each of the Government repre-sentativos in rotation, and that the Standing Orders be modified accordingly?(Sgd).    0.A, MONTAGUE BARLOW. 14th May, .1988..

</content>
</cab>
