<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 805-813</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
tjjg Britannic Majestv&apos;s GovernmeTrtT22 H2ient is the Property ofmmFOREIGN OFFICE.May 24th. 1922.Drift Despatch to Lord Hardinge.Submitted to the primo Minister and Cabinet by direction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.My Lord:-I have received and laid before the cabinet your despatch of the 20th. instant forwarding copy of a note addressed to Sir M. Cheetham by M. poincare under date of the preceding day in which he seeks to give a most unexpected interpretation to the solemn pledge given to His Majesty&apos;s Govern&apos; merit by M. Millerand in April 1920 on be-half of the French government that &quot;in all &quot;inter-allied questions raised by the exe-&quot;cution of the treaty it has no intention &quot;of acting otherwise than in accord with &quot;its allies&quot;.2.    M. poincare  now contends that this pledge has no application to the case of any coercive measures which the French government may wish to take if and when the Reparation Commission declare Germany to have voluntarily defaulted in the manner contemplated, as a contingency, in paragraphs 17 and 18 of Annex II to Part VIII of the treaty of Versailles.
3.    To support this contention M. Poincare* enters upon an elaborate legal argument as to the precise meaning of the paragraphs quoted, endeavouring to establish that, in any case falling under these clauses, each one of the allied Pov/ers has the right, separately, to take isolated action, without agreement with the other allies, and if necessary in op-position to their opinion.4.    I do not propose to follow M. poincare into these legal disquisitions&apos;. I would only say that His Majesty&apos;s Gov-ernment do not agree with them, and con-sider that it would be easy to traverse them by cogent &quot;counter-argument.    But they refrain from embarking upon such a legal controversy, in which neither they nor M. Poincare* are really competent to pronounce a decisive opinion.     In accord-ance with paragraph 12 of the same Annex to Part VIII, authority to interpret the provisions of that part of the treaty is expressly conferred on the Reparation Commission, whose decision, under para-graph 13 (f) must be unanimous.     I need only add that His Majesty.&apos;s Government would be much surprised if it were found that the interpretation on which IvI. poincare unauthoritatively relies, represented the unanimous
unanimous view of the Reparation Commission 5.    His Majesty&apos;s Government must ex-press their sincere regret that M. poincare should have thought it necessary thus to expound in an official form his view -which he can hardly have expected, after Mr. Chamberlain^ statement in the House, of commons, to he shared by His Majesty&apos;s \ Government    on a hypothetical situationwhich might conceivably arise if the Re-paratiori Commission were to report Germany involuntary default, and if, thereupon, no agreement were to he arrived at between the British and French governments as to the action to be taken in that situation.- But whatever view M... poincare&amp; may take of the technical aspect of the point of interpre-tation of the treaty, His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment cannot admit that this has any genuine bearing on the undertaking given by Millerand in 1920, which they continue to regard as dominating the whole field of allied policy touching German infractions of the treaty of peace.-   M. Poincard in his note gives a summary account of the situation out of which the pledge arose. In the concise form In which he states the case, the real facts do not, however,&quot; clearly emerge.     It may therefore be well to recapitulate a little more fully whatactually
actually passed in April 1920 between our two governments.6.   The occasion was the occupation by French troops on April 6th of Prank-fort and four other German towns in pursuance of orders issued by the French government without the knowledge of their allies, and in spite of reiterated and explicit declarations made by the French ambassador in London, by the Director General of the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs e-nd by M.Millerand him-self, that the French government would not in any circumstances take independent action, but would only act in concert with their allies who, as a matter of fact, had consistently opposed the despatch of French or allied troops.7.   In these circumstances, His Majesty&apos;6 Ambassador at Paris was in-structed to refrain from any further participation in the Ambassadors&apos; Con-ference, in so far as it dealt with the execution of the German treaty, until an adequate assurance had been given that in no circumstances would one of the allies act on such important matters except with the knowledge and concurrence of the remainder.
8.   In answer to a communication to the above effect, M.Milierand wrote on April 9th a note to Lord Derby, claiming that he had acted strictly in accordance with the assurance given by him to Lord Derby of April 1st:   that he would do nothing without having warned and consult-ed the allies, seeing that he had notified them on April 3rd that &quot;Marshal Foch was &quot;studying the military measures which &quot;can now no longer be avoided or pust-&quot;poned&quot;.     The note, however, concluded with the assurance that &quot;the French &quot;government do not hesitate to declare &quot;that in all inter-allied questions which &quot;are raised by the execution of the treaty, &quot;they do not contemplate any case in &quot;which they will not be happy, before &quot;acting, to assure themselves of the &quot;assjent of their allies&quot;.9,     This assurance was not considered satisfactory by His Majesty&apos;s Government, for the reason clearly atated in the following passage of a conmunication made to M.Millerand by Lord Derby on April lotln&quot;The
(s)&quot;The French government appearto think that it is sufficient, before&quot;taking isolated action, to have warned&quot;and consulted their allies, and that, &quot;if, after such consultation, they &quot;have failed to convince the latter &quot;of the wisdom of the proposed course, &quot;they are nevertheless free themselves &quot;to follow it.     His Majesty1 s Govern-&quot;ment mast say definitely that they. &quot;carnot accept this view, which is &quot;incompatible with the entire spirit &quot;upon which the alliance has hitherto&quot;been maintained, and that until&quot;there is a complete understanding&quot;on this point, the British Ambassadors-&quot;dor in paris cannot attend meetings&quot;of a conference which exists to&quot;concert allied measures for the&quot;enforcement of the treaty&quot;.
in10.     M. Millerand replied in a further note dated April 11th. which finally closed the incident hy recording that:&quot;As regards the future, the govern-&quot;ment of the Republic repeat that in all &quot;inter-allied questions raised by the exe-&quot;cution of the treaty, it has no intention &quot;of acting otherwise than in accordance &quot;with their allies&quot;.11. This is the assurance to which the Lord Privy Seal referred in his reply given in the House of Commons on May 18th to a parliamentary question, and which M. Poincare&apos; now endeavours to represent as having a restricted meaning tending to de-prive it of all practical importance.12.     It will be clearly seen from the above narrative of events, that the whole end and object pursued by His Majesty&apos;s Government in pressing for an unequivocal understanding on the entire question of coercive measures for the execution of the treaty, was to prevent any recurrence of such incidents as the occupation by one of the allies against the wishes of the others of German territory beyond the area authorised hy the treaty, or similar one-sided military acts.     They accepted M.Millerand1s
Millerand&apos;s assurance in its final form under the impression that it gave them complete satisfaction on this all-im-portant point.    It is not too much to say that, had His Majesty&apos;s Government, at the time they received the assurance,, been made aware that it was liable to be ex-plained away under cover of the legal subtleties now advanced in M. Poincare&quot;&apos;1 s note, they would never have agreed to ac-cept it as a settlement of the acute dif-ference which had so unhappily arisen between them and the French government.13.    An assurance of such attenuated scope as M, Poincare- would now have it assume, would not have had then, and would not have now, any value for His Majesty*s Government.     If the French gov-ernment really consider themselves definition-itely committed to this restrictive in-terpretation, His Majesty&apos;s Government feel constrained to enter their emphatic pro-test against what they cannot but regard as a deliberate breach of the honourable understanding on which they have hitherto confidently relied;   and if the French government should proceed to act on the view of their pledge as presented in M. Poincare:&apos;s note, His Majesty&apos;s government must
must warn them that they would be as sum-ing a heavy responsibility in entering on a path which can have no other issue but to break the hitherto happily main-tained harmony between the allies in their task of defending by common effort the sanctity of the treaties.14.    Your Excellency is authorized to read this despatch to the French Minister for Foreign Affairs and to hand him a copy.I am &amp;c.,

</content>
</cab>
