<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/136/0 images: 839-842</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ocument ia the property of his Britannic &apos;..;ajesty&apos;s Government).S E C R E T-t C ,f ,5997.p..A BINE copy Ho. 3&quot;memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Iri my Budget speech I made with the approval of the Cabinet a declaration of the intention of R.ri. Government to continue to make reductions in national expenditure.   I repeated those declarations in the City at the Bankers&apos; Association Dinner on the 11th May, and there is no doubt that they have attracted widespread attention and given rise to -public expectation of further reductions.Unquestionably the Government Is fully committed to a policy of continuous economy;   it remains to be considered how best to carry it into effect.I think that the task fif effecting the necessary reductions ought to be undertaken by Ministers themselves, but the result of the Cabinet Committees which were set up in the beginning of this year shows that muoh assistancecan be obtained by bringing common experience to bea* uponfparticular votes.Accordingly I propose that two Cabinet Committees should be appointed one to consider the Fighting Services Estimates for 1922^,the other to consider that year&apos;s Civil Estimates.     I further propose that a general circular should be issued by the Treasury in terms of the annexed
annexed draft addressed to all departments and calling for provisional estimates for 1923/24 by the 15th September, but as the great bulk of the national expenditure is confined to a few large Departments, a special request should be addressed by me to the heads of those departments to submit provisional estimates for 1923/24 by 30th June next.   These provisional estimates would be examined by the Treasury, arid submitted &apos;to the respective Cabinet Committees in time for substantial progress with the task of examination to be made before the autumn recessiThe provisional estimates of the other departments would be examined by tbe Treasury,and I do not anticipate that Iii the majority of cases It would be necessary to bring these estimates before the Cabinet Committee, but in special cases it might be desirable to do so.I propose to detach one or more Treasury officers as Secretary and Assistant Secretaries to the Committees.R.S.H.TREASURY, S.V*.l. 26th Kay,  1922.
I am&amp;c*to acquaint you that H .M Government have had under review the financial situation of the country.In his Financial Statement on the 1st May the Chancellor of the Exchequer declared the intention of the Government to continue to effect reductions in the national expenditure.      He stated -&quot;I wish also to make it plain that even upon these figures&quot; (i.e. the total anticipated Supply Expenditure of  546,500,000 including an allowahde of  25,000,000 for possible Supplementary Estimates)   &quot;ifcie Government is in no wise desisting in its efforts to effect reductions.    Indeed, I am confident that in the course of the present year, as we did in the course of last year, we shall succeed in making very appreciable reductions and still more in the year following;&quot;The financial prbspects for the current and ensuing years are such as to permit no relaxation in the endeavour to reduce expenditure, but on the contrary call for a continuous and progressive effort for economy by all Departments of State.        The unfavourable industrial and commercial situation of the past yearNwill be reflected In next year&apos;s Revenue Receipts;     the full effect of this year&apos;s remission of taxation will not be felt till next year;   and on the expenditure side of the national balance sheet it will be necessary to make provision of an additional sam of net less than  25s000,000 to meet this country&apos;s obligations to the U.S.A.The Government feel that it is not necessary to enlarge further on the vital necessity for economyor
or to justify in greater detail Their demand from all Departments that they should do their utmost to secure it *Bxsenait^-re in. I,9g5r24*I am to request that all Departments will supply Them with a provisional forecast of their expenditure for 1923/24 on or before the 15th September next unless specially requested to do so by an earlier date.     My Lords advisedly do not at present ask for a reduction of any girven proportion In the expenditure of your Department relying, as They do, on the greatest possible reductions being made.     The provisional Estimates will be examined in this Department and if it is deemed advisable will be referred to a special Committee of the Cabinet under the Chancellor of the Exchequer.     In framing these estimates for 1923/24 Departments may provisionally take cost of living bonus for that year at trie rate fixed at the revision as on 1st September 1922.Expenditure in 1922/25.In the Financial Statement already quoted the Chancellor of the Exchequer referred to further reductions of expenditure within the current financial year.     It must not be assumed that because an estimate for 1922/23 has been approved and voted no further effort is needed.      On the contrary My Lords attach the utmost importance to substantial savings on the current year&apos;s provision being made^ and I am to request that concurrently with the Provisional Estimate for 1923/24 They may be supplied with a Separate statement showing what savings, are anticipated j on the Vote for 1922/23.

</content>
</cab>
