<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/151/0 images: 13-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED WESTERN AND GENERALREPORT, No. 51. PART I-BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.The Freedom of the Seas.The reference by President Wilson to international control of the high seas in time of war is of special interest to the British and to nations in the Dominions. This subject is referred to in Part II., and will be dealt with more fully in an Appendix to next week&apos;s Report.Canada.The Dominion Ministers have telegraphed their agreement with the principles outlined in Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s speech.The possibility of Sir Wilfrid Laurier relinquishing the leadership of the Opposition in favour of Mr. Mackenzie King is referred to in this Report.Austral tan Com mos wealth.The course taken by the-Governor-General in requesting Mr. Hughes again to take office bears out the estimate given in the Appreciation to Report No. 10 that an administration of any stability could hardly be formed outside the National Party. An adverse Referendum vote has not hitherto been considered to involve the resignation of a Government, and it would not necessarily have brought about Mr. Hughes&apos; resignation if he had not pledged himself on the subject.New Zealand.Attention is drawn to the comments of the Dominion Ministers upon &quot;self-determination&quot; in.relation to Samoa.South Africa.Interesting references appear this week regarding the captured territory in Africa.It is satisfactory to note that the wool question may now be considered settled.African Colonisation. The views of Dr. Solf on this subject are given in the Appendix.January 17th, 1918.G. G. A
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET.For Reference only. -WESTERN   AND  GENERAL  REPORT.No. 51.    Week ending l(jth, January 2918 (niglit).PART I. BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.Contents.Imperial Affairs.Reductions of imports into United Kingdom.Canada. - - .Return of Prime Minister. Ministers and W;ji r Aims. Conscription of labour. Leadership of Opposition. Military Service Act: registrations and exemptions. Quebec^ and Privy Council appeals.   Military Service Convention.   Vessels on Canadian-African service.Australian Commonwealth.Formation of new Ministry. Reception by Official Labour Party. Reasons for Govemor-GeneraPs action. Motion of want of confidence. Offer by Mr. Hughes to stand aside. Conscription Referendum figures.   War expenditure for half year.   Copper output.   Manufacture, of paper.Row Zealand.Samoan natives and British rule.South Africa.General Botha on success of Allied arms.   Natives of German South-West Africa and British rule,-Petition against return of German colonies.   Sir T. Smartt on return of captured territory, WooL purchases.    Mr. Merriman on recruiting. German East Africa.Position of enemy.   Strength of German troops.The Pacific.Appointment of German Governor of New Guinea.   Dr. Solf on German South Sea possessions.Appendix : A German View on African Colonisation.(33)4761-3n   Pk100   1/18   e &amp; sa
PART   I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE  AND   AFRICA.IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.The Dominion Governments have been informed that the estimated reductions of imports into the United Kingdom, rendered necessary by the tonnage situation for the year 1918 as compared with 1917, will be as follows : Tons.Foodstuffs - - - -   2,500,000Munitions - - - -   1,550,000Timber, including pit-prous   - - -   1,000,000Paper and pulp *    - &apos; *  - - -     150,000Oilseed cake       - - . - -     200,000Iron ore - - - -     200,000Stones and slates - - - -      100,000Wool    - - - - -       50,000Miscellaneous articles ...     100,000As to the actual reductions in relation to the Dominions, it appears probable that shipping will not be available for further imports of dried, canned and preserved fruits, canned fish and wines and spirits, amongst other articles. It is not anticipated that the imports from Canada will be materially affected by the restriction of timber imports.CANADA.The Prime Minister (Sir Robert Borden) has returned to Ottawa after his brief rest, and presided at a meeting of the Cabinet immediately upon his return.The Dominion Ministers have telegraphed their agreement with the principles outlined by Mr. Lloyd George&apos; in his speech upon War Aims as being those best calculated to restore and maintain security and peace, and they reaffirm their deter-mination to continue their whole-hearted support.The Prime Minister has issued a statement that the Government do not intend to introduce conscription for any class of labour.With regard to the possibility of Sir Wilfrid Laurier retiring from the Leadership of the Opposition, it has been freely rumoured that Sir Wilfrid is desirous of relinquishing his post in favour of Mr. Mackenzie King, who occupied the position of Minister of Labour under him, and it was stated that Mr. Rodolphe Lemieux was prepared to resign his seat at Maisonneuve to enable Mr. King to enter the House. Mr. Lemieux, however, has declared that Sir Wilfrid will retain the Leadership, and the Premier of Quebec (Sir Lomer Gouin), wiio attended the Opposition Conference at Montreal, has stated that Sir Wilfrid &quot; certainly&apos;would not think of retiring to-day when he has the majority of the Party behind him.&quot;The number of registrations under the Military Service&apos; Act total 400,395, while the exemption claims amount to 380,510. Of the latter, 278,779 have been allowed, those disallowed numbering 47,868.The following figures show the total exemption claims, and their distribution amongst the Provinces : 	Claims.	Allowed.	Disallowed.	JSTot dealt with.	Appeals.Out.  -       -.;	118,128	94,176	19.148	4,783	21,276Que.	115,707	89,575	3.711	22,421	27.683N.S.   -	23.831	16.158	2,774	4.899	2.8152f.B.	15,629	10,181	2,524	2,924	2.034.P.E.I. -	4.176	3.648	332	196	34SMan.	20.858	14,241	5,221	1.396	3,982Sask.	44^203	26,13S	5,783	13,282	2,359Alta:	25,069	18,093	4,560	2.416	4,503B.C.   -	12.824	7,548	3.S15	1.478	2,122
Regarding the position of the. Province of Quebec in relation to the Dominion and the Empire, Mr. J. N. Francoeur, who recently, tabled a motion in the Quebec Legislature relating to the separation of Quebec from the Dominion Confederation (vide Report No. 48), has proposed a 33111 in the Provincial Legislature to abolish appeals to. the Privy Council in respect of civil cases arising in Quebec.As the British Government were being pressed by the United States to sign the Military Service Convention without further delay, the Dominion Government were asked by the British authorities whether they would agree to the Convention being-signed with the inclusion of Article 4-, which leaves the Canadian Government free to define the class of British, subjects to be,dealt with by separate agreement. In reply, the Dominion Government stated by telegram of the 11th January that the Deputy Minister of Justice and the Assistant Adjutant-General were proceeding to Washington to confer with the British Ambassador and the United States authorities, as it was very important that Canada should be included in the arrangements from the commencement. On the same date, however, the British Government informed the Dominion Government that it had been found necessary to offer to sign the Agreement without the proposed Article 4, though it had been explained that it would not be possible to ratify the Agreement until the proposed Canadian Convention had also been ratified, in order that the two Conventions would come into force at the same time.With regard to the proposed requisitioning of the ships employed on the Canadian-South African Service, the Dominion Government have pointed out that the vessels indicated are essential to the continuation of the Canadian-South African export trade, and that unless the Elder. Dempster Company can replace them, the proposal would have the effect.of terminating the trade in question.AUSTRALIAN COMMONWEALTH.The Prime Minister (Mr. Hughes) on the completion of his new Ministry announced their names to the House of Representatives on January 10th. All Mr. Hughes&apos; previous colleagues were re-nominated, and the disposition of portfolios is the same as in the case of the last Administration. It was indicated, however, that there would be certain changes in the Government in the near future with a view to strengthening it.The announcement of Mr. Hughes having been recommissioned to form a Govern-ment, following upon his resignation, met with a somewhat hostile reception from members of the Official Labour Party in the House of Representatives, whereupon Mr. Hughes read a memorandum, from the Governor-General. This stated that Mr. Hughes tendered his resignation on January 8th, and offered no advice as to who should be asked to form an administration. The Governor-General then considered it his duty (1) to make provision for carrying on the business of the country in accordance with the principles of parliamentary government ; (2) to avoid a situation arising which would involve a further appeal to the country within 12 months of an election Avhich had resulted in the return of two Houses of a similar political complexion. In choosing a successor to Mr. Hughes, the Governor-General felt that his judgment must be determined solely by the parliamentary situation, as any other course would be a departure from constitutional practice. In the absence of the defeat of the Government in Parliament, the Governor-General sought information from repre-sentatives of all sections of the House in order to determine where the majority lay and the prospects of forming an alternative Government. It appears that amongst those consulted, besides Mr. Hughes and Mr. Tudor, were the Commonwealth Treasurer (Sir J. Forrest), the Minister of the Navy (Mr. Cook, who was Leader of the Liberal Party before the formation of the National Government), Mr. Watt and Mr. Higgs  the last named being Mr. Tudor&apos;s most prominent supporter in the House. In the result the Governor-General came to the conclusion that the majority of the National Party was likely to retain cohesion, and that therefore a Government having a promise of stability could only be formed from that section of the House. It also became clear that the Leader in the National Party who had the best prospect of securing unity amongst his followers was Mr. Hughes, whom the Governor-General therefore corn-missioned to form an administration. -Before accepting the commission Mr. Hughes -consulted the Ministerialist caucus who decided by 60 votes to 11 that he should be asked to accept.
At the meeting of the House of-Representatives on January 11th the. Leader of the Opposition (Mr. Tudor) moved a motion of want of confidence in the new Government. After criticising Mr. Tudor for omitting to refer in his speech to the &quot;magnificent declarations&quot; of Mr. Lloyd George and President Wilson &quot;which a-oiced the opinion of all the Allied Nations,&quot; Mr. Hughes declared that when the Nationalist Party was formed, Mr. Tudor and the Opposition were asked to join the Party and thus endeavour to create a truly national Government by including all sections of the House, but the offer was declined. Mr. Hughes then proceeded to&apos; suggest a coalition, and stated that if Mr. Tudor was prepared to work with the National Party he (Mr. Hughes) would be prepared to help him. He added &quot;if I &quot; am the man who stands in the way, and he will work with the Party if I am out of &quot;it, 1 will go out of it.&quot; It appears, however, that though some individual members of the Official Labour Party might favour combination with Mr. Hughes, the Labour caucus is still hostile to Mr. Tudor and his colleagues entering a Coalition Government.The Conscription Referendum figures of the Commonwealth votes have now been, given by the returning officer as followsAgainst   - -- - - -   1,173,256. For - - - - -   1,013,361Majority against - - -      159,895&apos; The latest information regarding the distribution of votes amongst the States is given as follows :  	For.	1      Against.	Majority for.	Majority against.New South Wales	309,225	1      452,821		143.596Victoria           -           -           -           -	304,173	!    .308.026	y -	3,S53Queensland	119,217	i      154.631		35,414Sontli Australia          -	77.871	98,497	:  	20,626.Western Australia	74,924	38,055	36,869	-Tasmania	35,728	35,184	544	-      -Federal Territories	1.700	1,220	480	Referring to the war expenditure of the Commonwealth for the half-year ended December 31st, 19.17, the Treasurer (Sir J. Forrest) states that this amounted to 27,326,000Z. being an increase of 6,387,669Z. over the amount spent in the corresjxmd-ing period of 1916. The increase included the payment to the British Government for the upkeep of the Australian troops, amounting to 3,500,000L, and also 1.940,686L which was advanced in respect of the purchase of foodstuffs for the British and Indian Governments.In continuation of the previous communication on the subject of the Australian copper output (vide Report No. 47), the Commonwealth Government intimated to the British authorities, in a telegram dated January 9th, that they would be prepared in a fortnights time to commence negotiations with a view to the sale of the output (less Australian requirements) for a period of 10 years. The basis will be similar to that suggested for lead and zinc.The Government of New South Wales have recently been conducting scientific experiments with a view to the manufacture of paper from local timber. It is stated that the experiments have given satisfactory results.NEW ZEALAND.In reply to the telegram from the British Government asking for a statement concerning the wishes of the natives of Samoa to live under British rule and for suggestions from the Dominion Ministers, the New Zealand Cabinet have telegraphed giving references to their despatches on the subject and stating that they consider it essential to retain the German Colonies. The Dominion Ministers state that if further efforts should be made to ascertain native opinion, these should be conducted through the Native Chiefs, but the Ministers express their belief that the same desire to remain under British rule that has been previously indicated would be manifested at the present time. But a vote of the natives themselves, it is pointed out, would not be practicable, as they are not
sufficiently educated., and such a measure would be contrary to Samoan custom:; moreover, any attempts at a plebiscite would no doubt enable the Germans at present in Samoa to use both money and influence to turn the population from their attitude of loyalty to British rule. In reply the British Government point out that they did not intend to suggest taking a plebiscite, but they wotdd be glad if the Dominion Ministers would consider the steps necessary to be taken in order to consult the Native Chiefs, if this should prove desirable. Meanwhile, a more detailed report on the attitude of the natives would be welcomed.SOUTH AFRICA.The Prime Minister (General- Botha) has telegraphed his thanks to the War Cabinet for the New Year message and the belief is expressed in the &quot; ultimate success of our arms.&quot;In reply to the telegram from the British Government as to the wishes of the natives of German South -West Africa to live under British rule, the Prime Minister of the Union has expressed the view that a good case regarding the attitude of the natives can be made, and that a Memorandum is being prepared on the subject.A petition containing 5,000 signatures, collected in two and a half days, protesting against the return of the German Colonies was presented on January loth to the Mayor of Johannesburg, who has called a public meeting for January 21st to discuss the subject.The Leader of the Opposition in the Union Parliament (Sir Thomas Smartt) has referred in an interview to the question of the return of the German Colonies in South-West and East Africa, in the course of which he states : It is xmthinkable that the &quot; Allies would agree to these countries being handed back to the Power which has &quot; shown its incompetency to govern them in the interests of their native populations ; &quot;and, as the British Dominion which has been so closely associated with, their &quot; conquest, and has such paramount interest in their proper government, we feel &quot; convinced that the voice of the loyal inhabitants of South Africa will receive that &quot; due consideration to winch it is entitled.&quot;The difficulties that have attended the matter of wool purchases appear now to be solved satisfactorily. It will be recalled that about one-third of the clip had been offered to the British Government, but it appeared that the remainder might secure higher prices from buyers in the united States and Japan. As a result of careful consideration by the British Government, the Union Government have been informed that while the British authorities would be glad of all the wool the)&quot; can obtain, they realise that during the period of difficulty regarding the provision of freight to England, it has been possible to obtain freight more easily for Japan and the United States, and that a greater demand for South African wool has arisen in those countries than was originally anticqDated. While considering that the original offer was a fair one, the British Government agree that those Avho came into the purchasing scheme should now be allowed to withdraw from it if they so desire. The Union Ministers, in reply, have exjDressed their deep appreciation to the British Government for their action. Prior to the publication of the correspondence between the British and Union Governments in the South African Press, in Avhich the above solution was suggested, De Volkstem, the leading organ of the Dutch in the Transvaal (which generally supports General Botha) published an article urging that representations should be made to the British Government in favour of cancellation of the wool contracts^ The Cape Times, however, denounced this suggestion, and pointed out that the Union Government asked the British Government to make the offer, which was freely accepted by the farmers concerned after months of public discussion.Mr. J. X. Merriman has made a strong appeal to the Union Government to^ commence a recruiting campaign in order to maintain the South African Contingent in. Europe (vide, however, Report No. 49). Mr. Merriman, basing his attitude on the fact that the call for men was pre-eminently a national matter, stated : &quot; It is unfor-&quot; unfortunate that, we in South Africa are, for our sins, riven into two factors of almost-&quot; equal strength. Almost one-half of the European population is coldly neutral &quot; towards the issue, which we look upon as vital, if indeed they are not positively &quot;hostile to the cause of the Allies, with the result that nearly all the burden of &quot; recruiting has fallen upon the other half.&quot;   Regarding the South Africans serving4-761 -3a B
in Europe, Mr. Merriman adds : &quot; The sacrifices of these men, and of those who have &quot; sent them forth, have done more to lay the true foundations of the South African &quot; nation than all the Avindy oratory to which is due much of the dangerous dissension now threatening this unhappy country.&quot;GERMAN EAST AFRICA.General Nor they reports that the main enemy forces, consisting of six or seven companies, appear to be near Mtarika on the Lujenda river, with detachments of three or four companies each in the Mwembe and Medo districts. He states that while the transport difficulties are being surmounted, he fears that the rounding-up of the enemy in this large area will necessitate operations of a protracted character.The German Wireless has issued a statement regarding the strength of the German troops in East Africa, in which the assertion is made that these troops have been alleged to be much greater than is really the case. According to reports from the German Commands of January 1st, 1915, it is stated that there were 1,697 Europeans and 0,250 Askaris employed, and on April 2nd, 1915, 2,000 Europeans and 7,500 Askaris, plus 2,000 auxiliary forces under arms.THE PACIFIC.The Union of South Sea Firms at present sitting in Berlin have addressed a manifesto to the German Colonial Secretary (Dr. Solf) thanking him for the appoint-inent of a new Governor of New Guinea, and observing that they recognise the will of the All Highest in proclaiming a strong Colonial policy of &quot; holding firmly to our richly blessed possessions in the South Sea Colonies now in enemy hands.&quot; In reply, Dr. Solf expressed the hope that the German flag would soon be flying again &quot; over &apos;&quot; our fine South Sea Colonies, so that German spirit and enterprise will be given an &quot; opportunity to continue opening up the promising South Sea possessions as &quot; energetically and successfully as hitherto.&quot;
APPENDIXtoWestern and General Report No. 51.  Part I.A GERMAN VIEW7&quot; OF AFRICAN COLONISATION.An important speech was delivered in Berlin last month by Dr. Solf, the German. Colonial Secretary, on various aspects of African colonisation. Referring to the doctrine of &quot;self-determination,&apos;&apos; he said: &quot;Is the right of peoples to self-determina-&quot; tion to be seriously acted on, even in Africa? Do we want to leave it to the natives &quot; to organise themselves &apos;? That is absolutely impossible, and will not be advocated &quot; hy any serious politician. ... I should like to make a certain change in the words &quot; &apos; right of self-determination.&apos; I should like to say: The natives have a right to be &quot; an end in themselves, a claim to be regarded by the moie highly developed races at &quot; all times as an end, and not merely as a means to an end.&quot;As to the militarisation of the natives, Dr. Solf said : &quot; The problem of the &quot; militarisation of the native races of Africa requires special consideration; the far-&quot; reaching and frightful importance of this problem which France has presented to &quot; the/world has been demonstrated by the war . . . There is no doubt that the &quot; possibility of arming immense native armies will constitute a fresh menace to &quot; European peace in future. There is also no doubt that the militarisation of the &quot; natives must seriously prejudice the development of the African colonies. It is &quot;therefore in the joint interest of the European Powers to remove the fresh &quot;danger which has so suddenly arisen.&quot; The best method, Dr. Solf says, of obviating militarisation is the redistribution of the continent. He continues : &quot; By &quot; striking a balance in place of the former unequal distribution it will be made &quot; impossible for individual Colonial Powers to transport coloured forces to Europe &quot; without having to fear a danger to the colours from its equally powerful &quot; neighbour, through denuding it of these forces. Interest in setting up native army &quot; corps will be very much diminished if they cannot be counted on for service in &quot; Europe or any other foreign country. Over and above this, however, our &quot; fundamental attitude to the whole question will make us promote restriction of &quot; military armament in Africa by treaty.Dr. Solf asserts that Africa will remain, even after the world war, in the hands of a number of European colonial Powers, but he states : &quot; The rearrangement of owner-&quot; ship, which we demand, will, however, provide that the share of individual Powers &quot; shall be adapted to their economic interests and their economic and cultural &quot; capabilities. The treaty system, the foundations of which were laid at the com-&quot; mencement of the newer colonial era, must be expanded and developed for the &quot; whole continent, or, at least, for the tropical districts. These treaties should &quot; guarantee the participation of white men in the work of.opening up of the African 41 colonies, under equal conditions, and draw up fundamental guiding lines for the &quot; joint solution of the great problems of colonial administration. Every care must &quot; be taken to prevent militarisation of the natives of Africa.&quot;The relation of Germany to the above programme is given by Dr. Solf in these words : &quot; If these demands are successfully realised, we shall have the conditions &quot; necessary for a happy development of Africa and its inhabitants in the coming &quot; decades. Then the best talents in Europe can and will proceed to the great task &quot; imposed on civilisation, with the guarantee of success. Then the individual African &quot; races, which have vegetated for centuries in the shadow of history, will be led by &quot; the patient work of education to the light of our civilisation and of our material &quot; Eultur. Then the still slumbering economic treasures of the very rich countries &apos;&quot; will be raised by the methods of European science, learning, and organisation to be &quot; a blessing to the native population, and a blessing to the rest of the world. Then, &quot; and onlv then, Africa will take her true place as one of the worhTs continents. We .&apos;&quot; Ge rmaus, however, feel ourselves called on to take on ourselves a good share of this immense task.&quot;
sAddressing a later meeting of the German Colonial Society on January 8thr Dr. Solf referred to German missions in the German Protectorates, and said that,, unlike England, Germany must consider mission work from the international point of view. He sketched the good. Avork done by both denominations, Avhich aimed at inculcating a sound native policy, based on the improvement of commercial, moral, and spiritual life, as also on education, scientific research, and other literary work. The check to these inflicted by the frivolous breach of the Congo Act Avas, h&amp; said, lamentable. .... He concluded : &quot; WhoeArer supports missions in the German &quot; Protectorates confers a double blessing, for he not only serves his faith, but also &quot; advances Germany&apos;s OA-overseas position.&quot;

</content>
</cab>
