<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/151/0 images: 22-34</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION, OF - THE ATTACHED WESTERN AND GENERAL).REPORT No. 52.PART I. BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.Imperial Affairs.The &quot; Freedom of the Seas.&quot; This subject is dealt with in an Appendix to this Report.Canada.The suggestion of the Dominion War Cabinet regarding the supply of authoritative war information to the Press indicates the desire of Ministers to stimulate a sound public opinion.The motion in the Quebec Legislature seems to have been proposed more with the idea of protesting against the criticism passed upon Quebec by the other Provinces than with any belief that separation from the Dominion woidd be seriously con-templated by responsible people.Australian Commonwealth.The attitude of the Official Labour Party towards the war and proposals for coalition is worth noting.The comments of the Administrator of Rabaul upon the application of the policy of &quot; Self-determination &quot; to the inhabitants of German New Guinea are particularly interesting.      -The German view as to the manner in which Australians ought to regard their position in the Pacific is quoted in this Report.New Zealand.The question of the supply of labour for the plantations in the Samoan Islands appears likely to reach an acute stage during 1918.
South Africa.The references made in the Governor-General&apos;s speech at the opening&apos; of Parliament indicate the intention of the Union Government to recruit as many men as possible for service in Europe from the troops returning from East Africa.South African comments appear in this week&apos;s report upon war aims, the return of captured territory, the production of gold, and&apos;native recruiting.  &apos; - ;; 1 ; &apos; - french  West Africa.The system and methods to be adopted in the fresh campaign for native recruits merit careful attention.January 24th, 1918.G.rGk A
[This Document is the Property-of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.SECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND  GENERAL  REPORT.No. 52.    Week ending 23rd January 1918 (niglit). &apos;PART I, BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA. Contents.Imperial Affairs. *Re-exportation of goods to Russia. Canada.War information for Press.   Quebec and separation.   Unionist Major of Sherbrooke.   French scutcheon:  Admiralty gift.   Military Service Act:  special police measures.    Military Service Convention.   Labour questions.   Shipbuilding.   Steel production.  Wood and engines for aeroplanes. Ontario election and soldiers&apos; votes. - War expenditure and revenue.   Wheat for export. Australian Commonwealth.Imperial War Cabinet meetings. Political parties and reinforcements. Labour opposition to Coalition. New Guinea and self-determination : position of population. A German view of Australia and the Pacific.   Loan arrangements.New Zealand. &apos;        - --Imperial War Cabinet meetings: attendance of Dominion Ministers. Labour question in Samoa. Returning- soldiers and employment of officers.   New Minister of Lauds.South Africa.Opening of Parliament: statement as to assistance in war and contemplated legislative measures. Ministers on War Aims, and return of South-West Africa. Gold production. Nationalists and wool question.   Native labour.French West Africa.Recruiting&apos; of natives : French policy.Appendix : The Freedom of the Seas.(33)4761-ia   Pk       100   1/18   e &amp; sa
PART I.-BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.Re-exportation of Goods to Russia. The Dominion Governments have been informed that guarantees are being required from Japan against re-exportation of goods to Russia in the case of imports which are licensed from British countries. The hope of the British Government is expressed that ineantime the Dominions will not grant licences for the export of goods to Japan. It is added that the Japanese Government have been requested to stop all exports to Russia, but the above step is considered necessary until a decision on this matter is arrived at.CANADA.&quot;War Information for Press. -The Dominion War Cabinet have suggested to the British War Cabinet that, with a view to encouraging interest and sustaining the spirit of the Canadian people in relation to the vigorous prosecution of the war, a weekly&quot;survey of the military, shipping, and economic situations should be issued by the War Cabinet and cabled to the Dominion GoA-ernment for communication to the Press. The Canadian GoA^ernment point out that the weekly statement issued to the Press by the United States Secretary for War is considered of utility.Quebec and Separation. The motion in the Quebec Legislature last Aveek relating to the possible separation of the Province from the Dominion Confederation led to an interesting discussion. In proposing the motion, Mr. Francoeur stated that the time had arriA&apos;ed to stop the statements which had been made in other provinces regarding Quebec, or to accept the logicarconsequences. He described his motion as a protest against the campaign of falsehoods Avhich had been carried on during the election. He continued, &quot; Quebec&apos;s only crime is-that she interpreted the Constitution in a&quot; manner different from her co-citizens of different origin.....Quebec&apos;s only crime&quot; was that its citizens were, above all, Canadians.....We only asked that the&quot; people&quot; should be consulted before conscription was applied.&quot; The Leader of the Opposition- (Mr. Satrve) stated that separation was against the interests of the French Canadians, and that all the social disputes since the Confederation had groAvn out of the school question in the English provinces. He remarked that the rights guaranteed to Quebec by the constitution had never been attacked, and ended by proposing an amendment to the motion calling upon the House to petition the King to disallow the Military Service Act. Lieut.-Colonel Gault pointed out that the inevitable result of separation would be annexation by the United States, and Quebec would then lose its language as well as its educational system. There were only three members avIio spoke in favour of Mr. Francoeur&apos;s motion.In the above connection it is Avorth noting that a prominent Unionist (Mr. C. D. White), who took an active part in support of Sir R. Borden in the recent election, has been elected Mayor of Sherbrooke.(Que.), Avhere the great majority of the population consists of French-Canadians.French Scutcheon : Admiralty Gift. With reference to the presentation by the Admiralty of the old French Scutcheon of the City of Quebec (which Avas taken on 18th September 1759) to the Canadian War Museum (vide Report No. 41) the Dominion Ministers have telegraphed their regret that an acknowledgment of this thoughtful action has been delayed through, the absence of Ministers in connection with the recent election.   The warm appreciation of the Dominion GoA-ernment is conveyed
to the Admiralty for this historic gift, which, it is mentioned, was once prized as a trophy of a chivalrous rivalry and &quot;has now become more happily a token of the &quot;striking significance of that enduring friendship . which has united France, &quot; Great Britain and Canada in a splendid comradeship in arms.&quot;Military Service Act. The Dominion Government have decided to take special -measures for deserters under the.Military Service Act, and have established for this purpose a special constabulary. This force will be given all necessary authority and will work in co-operation with local police forces and the military police over the whole of the Dominion. It is anticipated that this action will make it practically impossible for anyone coming-under the Act xo escape service.Military Service Convention. With regard to the signing of the Military Service Convention (vide Deport No. 51), the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs will take no further action pending the receipt of information as to the.actual proposals of Canadian Ministers, and the Dominion Government have been so informed. * -Labour Questions:- Two important Conferences on the Labour Situation are being&apos;held in the Dominion. One of these, which is presided over by the Minister of Agriculture (Mr. Crerar), is considering, in conjunction with representatives from all the provinces, the question of the supply of sufficient, labour, more particularly in. connection with agriculture and. mining. At the other Conference, the President of the Privy Council (Mr. Rowell) is consulting with Labour Representatives. While conscription of labour is not contemplated, it is understood that Federal and Provincial labour bureaus will probably be established by means of which all the necessary labour will be secured. The view of the representatives of organised- labour appears to be that sufficient help for agricultural and other purposes will be available if properly organised efforts are made by the Dominion and Provincial Governments.Shipbuilding. -The Dominion Government, have decided to use the shipbuilding yards to their full capacity for the construction of steel ships which will be owned by the Government and registered in Canada. The vessels will be used during the war for the purpose considered to be most essential. As the Dominion Government do not intend-to construct wooden ships, they have enquired from the British Govern-ment whether the yards which are at present engaged in the construction of such vessels might not accept orders from allied and neutral countries. Otherwise, it is pointed out, these yards, which are well equipped and supplied with skilled labour, would remain idle.Steel Production. As the result cf a conference between the War Committee of the Cabinet and Dominion Steel Manufacturers, it is announced that there will be an increase of 20 per cent, this year over last year&apos;s production of steel.Wood and Engines for A eroplanes. The British Columbian Government have passed an Order-in-Council enabling them to arrange with the Imperial Munitions Board for the immediate logging of aeroplane spruce \\-pon all vacant areas and Crown lands. In case of failure to comply with the order the Government may make its own arrangements and fix compensation for the timber cut.The first of 1,000 aeroplane engines, which are being constructed under the authority of the Imperial Munitions Board at Toronto, has been completed and has given satisfaction.Ontario Election. It is anticipated that the provincial election in Ontario will take j)lace about June next, and legislation is being introduced during the coming session which will enable Ontario soldiers and nurses on active service to exercise the franchise.War Expenditure and Revenue. The Dominion war expenditure for the nine months ending December 31st, 1917, amounted to $171,748,839, as compared witlr .$170,229,748 during the same period of the previous year. The revenue for the same period in 1917 was $190,658,370, as against $166,856,349 in 1916.Wheat for Export. The total quantity of wheat in store in Canada now amounts to 100,000,000 bushels, and, after the requirements for home consumption and for seed -are met, 40,000,000 bushels will be available for immediate export.
AUSTRALIAN COMMONWEALTH.Imperial War cabinet. The. British- Government have informed the Prime Minister of the Commonwealth that General Botha anticipates being able to leave for the meetings of the Imperial War Cabinet by the middle of April or a little later, while Sir Robert Borden cannot come before the middle of May or the beginnino- of June. The views of the Commonwealth Prime Minister are therefore sought as to the-&apos; date which would be convenient to him for holding the Sessions; and attention is called to the conflicting reports appearing in the Press regarding his intentions, to visit England.Political Parties and Reinforcements. During the continuance of the debate on the-want of confidence motion of the Leader of the Opposition (Mr. Tudor), Sir William Irvine threw out the suggestion that four members on each side of the House should confer regarding the ways   and  means  of  obtaining reinforcements.    Speakers, representing the Official Labour Party, while declaring their opposition to conscription,, stated that their attitude towards the war was the same as in 1914, namely, to assist in attaining the declared objects for which Great Britain entered the war.   The Minister for the Navy (Mr. Joseph Cook) stated that if co-operation between all political parties for the establishment of a new national Government could be-brought about, he would gladly resign  if  that  would   assist  in the   direction-indicated.   He emphasised, however, that urgent&quot; action was necessary in order to-secure the necessary reinforcements for the Australian Imperial Forces.     On the vote being taken, the &quot; No Confidence &quot; motion was negatived by 43 votes to 19.   A. two months&apos; supply bill was then passed.Labour Opposition to Coalition. The Official Labour Party have not indicated any desire to accept Mr. Hughes&apos; offer to stand aside in order to enable the Opposition, to work with the National Party. The Federal Parliamentary Labour Caucus discussed the question at a recent meeting, and Mr. Tudor afterwards announced that there was no possibility of agreement between the parties. It appears, how-ever. that prominent Labour representatives are in favour of conferences taking: place in order that measures to stimulate recruiting may be considered and joint action by the parties agreed upon.New  Guinea  and  Self-determination. With  regard  to &quot;Mr. Lloyd  Georges-acceptance of the general principle of self-determination in relation to the inhabitants of captured territories, the Administrator of Rabaul lias pointed out that while such a policy would   be  applicable  to  countries  settled by civilised or white populations, it would be difficult to apply it to German New Guinea.   ]\&apos;ot only do the islands lie at varying distances from each other, but the native inhabitants, numbering between 500,000 and 800,000, consist of different races speaking different languages, and the tribes are constantly at war with each other.   These facts show, it is submitted, that little cohesion could be expected from the natives and that they would  be  unable   to express  their  wishes   regarding   future   government   with, any   reliability.     Indeed, it  is  doubted   whether the  natives  understand   that they are   now under   the   British,  as they see  German  planters  still carrying-on  their businesses.    Moreover,  the  idea of   conquest  is  generally   associated in  the   native  mind  either  with  slavery  or  with  a  human  feast.     Though-labour conditions have been improved during the Australian occupation, it is not thought that the natives would trace this to British rule.   Under the terms of the-capitulation, British settlement in the Colony has not been practicable, and it is estimated that two-thirds of the white population..-are Germans.   This circumstance, combined with the indifference of the natives as to their future government, would, it is suggested, enable an estimate to be formed of the result of the application of&quot; Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s policy.   The strategic and commercial value of the Colony is. given as the reason for calling attention to the subject in the above manner.A German view of Australia and the Pacific. A. striking article upon &quot; Conscription in Australia &quot; has been published in the Vossiselie Zcitung by Professor-Alfred Manet. The author states that the Referendum result was a triumph of Australian Nationalism over British Imperialism, and after asserting that there have been voices raised against the war in Australia, he also says that there have been voices declaring how absurd it is that a people of less than five millions should own territory fonr-fifths the extent of Europe and yet further endeavour to take over-the South Sea Colonies.   In interpreting the view of the Australians to whom he--
refers, tlie Professor says that they consider it much more important for Australia to have a peojole schooled in culture as a neighbour. Also besides Australia, he continues, Japan and America are candidates for the South Seas, and it must not be forgotten that the fate of the South Seas may yet be decided on the Franco-Belgian front.Loan Arrangements. It has been decided to extend the maturity date of the Commonwealth loan for 18,OO0,000Z. until five years after the war. The State Treasurers have agreed to reduce their loan requirements to an absolute minimum, and the Commonwealth Government are advancing the reduced amount of 3,000,000Z. to Queensland, South Australia, Western Australia, and Tasmania during the current year. In addition, these States and the State of Victoria will raise money locally. New South Wales will obtain loans independently.-   NEW ZEALAND.Imperial War Cabinet. In reply to the encpury of the British Government, the Prime Minister (Mr. Massey) has telegraphed saying that as it does not appear likely that the Imperial War Cabinet and Conference will meet before the beginning of June, the matter will come up for consideration by the Dominion Cabinet. He adds that the New Zealand Government will endeavour to arrange for the attendance of two Ministers.Labour in Samoa. The Dominion Government have pointed out the difficulties -connected with the supply of labour for plantations in the Samoan Islands. At the time of the occupation there were 2,18-1 Chinese labourers, whereas there are now 1,525. Of the latter 125 are about to be repatriated, while the indentures of the remainder expire during 1918. It is suggested that labour from the Solomon Islands would meet the difficulty if it were available. Further, the Administrator raised no objection to the proposed employment of labour from Java in October 1916, but the Dominion Ministers understand that this was vetoed by the Colonial Office. The New Zealand Government therefore express their anxiety to obtain the views of the British Government as to the policy to be pursued with regard to the provision of labour for the maintenance of Samoan industries.Returning Soldiers. More than 14,000 New Zealand soldiers have now returned to the Dominion. The arrangement by which the British Authorities are taking over a number of experienced officers from the New Zealand Division, in order to relieve the difficulty caused by the great number of officers available for service, has been publicL announced.    (Vide Deport No. 40.)Minister of Lands. It is announced that Mr. D. H. Guthrie, M.P., will become the new Minister of Lands.SOUTH AFRICA.Opening of Parliament. The Third Session of the Second Union Parliament was opened by the Governor-General on January T8th, 1918. In the course of his opening Address, the Governor-General referred to the satisfactoiy progress of the campaign in East Africa, Avhich had made possible the release of the bulk of the European forces. He continued: &quot; It is the earnest hope and desire of my Ministers that the strength of the Overseas Contingent may not only be maintained, but &quot; substantially increased during the remaining stages of the war. Certain proposals &quot; will be laid before you in furtherance of the policy of Ministers to render His Majesty&apos;s &quot; Government all possible assistance in the prosecution of the war.&quot; The Legislation foreshadowed in the speech included the provision of a census of the European population, the institution of a Commission to investigate complaints connected with the public service, industrial legislation, &amp;c.4761-4a B
&apos; - War Aims. Various statements have been made regarding Mr. Lloyd Georges-speech upon Avar aims.&apos; The Minister of Railways (Mr. Burton) has observed that it-will be an immense service to the cause of the Allies, and not least because it will &quot; go far to remove suspicion and misapprehension lis to our good faith.&quot; The-Minister of Mines and Education (Mr. Malan) &apos; said that Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s. re-statement of the Avar aims of the Allies is generally approved in the Union.Return of Souih-West Africa. In welcoming the reference to the German Colonies-contained in Mr. Lloyd George&apos;s recent speech, the Union Minister of Raifwa3&apos;s has stated : - - It is difficult to exaggerate the feeling of South Africa against any prospect of &quot; a return of  the South-West Protectorate to Germany;  if any  concessions are &quot; eA-entual])&apos; made to German colonisation, Ave can never tolerate her as a neighbour &quot; again, especially after the revelations of the war as to her purpose and methods.&quot;Gold Production. Owing to the-difficulties connected with working certain of the mines, through shortage of stores, labour and explosives (vide Report No. 47), the-Minister ot Mines (Mr. Malan) has given notice in the Union LToti.se of Assembly that, he Avill move for the appointment of a Select Committee to consider the situation. Meantime, an interesting statement on the Imperial aspect of gold production has been made by the President of the Chamber of Mines (Mr. Wallers), lie ascribed the difficulties of maintaining- the gold output to three main causes--firstly, the heavy increase in the cost of mining material and the general working expenses, Avhich eliminate the margin of profit ; secondly, the native labour &quot;shortage ; and, thirdly, the reduction in glycerine supplies. If neither native labour nor explosive supply can be maintained, Mr. Wallers states that the problem of maintaining the gold output for Imperial purposes Avill be most difficult to solve. lie estimates, however, that the native labour supply will neither appreciably improve nor become much Avorse, and that the explosive shortage will be somewhat relieved by the use of substitutes. In that case he- believes that, with Government assistance and the rearrangement of the-operations of the industry as a whole, the difficulties will be surmountable.Wool Question. The Leader of the Nationalists (General Hertzog) has given notice in the Union Parliament of a motion deprecating the conduct of the Union Govern-ment in their negotiations Avith the British Government upon the wool question. The terms of the motion practically amount to one of &quot; no confidence,&quot; and there is little doubt, therefore, that it will be defeated, as the Unionists will not be likely to support any action which is calculated to embarrass the Government.Native Labour. In pursuance of the views expressed by the Army Council (vide Report No. 45), the Prime Minister (General Botha) has announced to the native Chiefs, headmen and people that, for purely military reasons, recruiting for the South African Native Labour Contingent will cease, and that no further contingents of&quot; labour will be sent oversea. General Botha expressed appreciation of the natives&apos; loyal response to the call for men, and stated that the reinforcements that had been provided not only made good the wastage, but had actually increased the strength of the contingents.FRENCH WEST AFRICA.Recruiting of Natives. The French Government have decided to resume-recruiting for the Army in the French West African Colonies, and some interesting, particulars of the measures to be taken are given in the Journal Ojjiciel. From this it appears that Monsieur Blaise Diagn-e, the representative of Senegal in the Chamber of Deputies, has been appointed, with the title of &quot; Commissioner of the Republic in West. Africa,&quot; which carries with it the rank of Governor-General of the Colonies, at the head of a Mission charged with increasing the recruiting of natives in Western and Equatorial Africa. Monsieur Pierre Alype, the principal assistant in the French Colonial Office, who was formerly head of the Secretariat of the Governors of Dahomey and Senegal, has. been appointed assistant to Monsieur Diagne, with the rank of Governor of the Colonies. It will thus be seen that the head of the Mission Avill be himself an African native ; and the Mission Avill haA*e power to recruit, on the voluntary system, by special appeals and offers of bounties, amongst the natives of
West Africa between the ages of 18 and 35. Apart from the inducements offered to the natives who enlist, various advantages will be given to the families of the native soldiers. For example, at least half of the amount payable to the soldier on enlistment will be hauded over to the family in the&quot; cases of those undertaking oversea service, and if the family should be in necessitous circumstances other sums will be allotted in addition. At the same.time, the wives, children, and other connections of the soldier will be exempted from hut tax and other taxation. In order to provide a reward for-those serving, places will be reserved for them on their return in the branches of the Civil Service where natives are at present employed.The spirit underlying the measures that are being taken is indicated in a note addressed by the Colonial Minister to the. Governors-General, of French West and Equatorial Africa. In the course of this, Monsieur Henri Simon says: &quot;Our&apos; &quot; populations of West Africa should understand that by the appeal which France is &quot; addressing to them, the country has raised them-to the position of citizens.&quot; He points out that in France it is an honour as much as a duty to be a soldier, and that the laws have hitherto excluded natives from the National Army. He adds : &quot; To &quot; fight in the ranks of the French Army is for our African subjects to range &quot; themselves for ever on the side of civilisation, which is menaced by our enemies.&quot;
APPENDIXtoWestern and General Report No. 52.  Part I.THE FREEDOM OF THE SEAS.The Prime Minister. &quot; I want to linow ichat &apos; freedom of the seas &apos; means. Does it mean freedom from submarines, and does it mean starvation for this country ? After all, ice are in a very different position from America, or Germany, or France, or any other continental country. We are an island, and we must, scrutinize with the very greatest care any proposal which might impair our ability to protect our lines of communication across^the seas. &apos; Freedom of the seas &apos; is a very, elastic term. There is a sense in which we would rejoice to accept it, but ice must guard very, carefully against any attempt to interfere with the capacity to protect our shores and our shipping that has alone enabled us even to exist up to the present moment.&quot;  (Mr. Lloyd George, January 18th, 1918.)GERMAN PEACE OFFENSIVE.In their urgent wish to make peace while they still hold the territories captured by their armies, the Germans accepted the Bolshevist formula, &quot; without annexations or indemnities.&quot; The insincerity of this acceptance was proved at once when it was definitely applied to Lithuania, Couriand, and Poland, and the meaning of another formula, &quot;self-determination,&quot; is now the subject of acute debate.   *Another catch-phrase, the &quot; Freedom of the Seas,&quot; has been used freely by the Germans, and this reepiires very careful consideration from the point of view of the United Kingdom, the nations in the Dominions, and India. We have so far been unable to elicit from our enemies any clear official definition of the meaning which they attach to the expression. Herr Dernberg told an American audience three years ago that the freedom of the seas was the first requirement for the w-orld&apos;s peace, but, in making this demand, he added somewhat unwisely that what he referred to was the &quot; traditional &quot; mare liberum.The &quot; traditional&quot; demand for a free sea was formulated about three centuries ago as a protest against those who claimed the exclusive right to trade in certain seas in time of peace. Examples have at various times been afforded by such claims, as those by Venice to the Adriatic, by France and by Genoa to parts of the Mediterranean, by Sweden and by Denmark to the Baltic, by Spain to the Gulf of Mexico and- to parts of the Pacific, and by Portugal to the East Indies and to part of the Eastern Atlantic. The British traditional policy has been to combat all such demands, whenever and wherever they have been put forward, and the &quot;traditional&quot; free sea, advocated by Fferr Dernberg to enlist the sympathy of Americans, has already been established for centuries. It has been guaranteed by the supremacy of the British Navy.4761-4(i - C
&quot; British sea-power, so far from limiting that freedom, has extended it, first by-repressing piracy, secondly by improving navigation, and thirdly by making it more safe through charting various imperfectly surveyed waters, all of which activities-have been for the common benefit of all seafaring nations. It follows that no-greater freedom of the seas can be conceived than that which existed during&quot; peace. 1A FREE SEA IN WAR.. The real point at issue between the Germans and ourselves is not the &apos;1 traditional &quot;&apos; freedom of the seas, which we ourselves established and thereby enabled the Germans to build up their immense mercantile marine, containing great fleets of steamers like those of the Nord-Deutsche Lloyd and Hamburg-Amerika lines. &quot;The real question is whether we or they shall be free to use the sea in time of tear.   This has been made quite clear by admissions of men like Grand Admiral von Tirpitz, Count Bernstorff,. Count Reventlow, and others.   The undefined phrase; &quot;freedom of the seas,&quot; has attracted sympathy in several neutral countries, and even in countries at war with Germany.  Amongst those who have been attracted may be mentioned President Wilson (while still a neutral), the Pope, Lord Lansdowne,the official representatives of some Labour and Socialist organisations in France, England, and neutral countries, and the-Bolshevists in Russia.   In these circumstances there is an urgent need for clear-thinking and precise definition- in a matter of so &quot;vital an interest to ourselves. Speaking in the House of Commons last December, Mr. Asquith said that he had sought in vain for any exact, or even approximate, definition of the meaning of the phrase, and asked what stipulation Great Britain, for instance, would be 7asked to-embody- in the terms of peace which would curtail and fetter the immemorial right of the maritime marine of all nations of the world to use the seas in time of peace, or what limitations it was proposed to impose upon belligerents in time of war.   He-expressed his opinion that &quot; we are not likely to hear much more from enemy lips, of the freedom of the seas.&quot;   This prediction has not been fulfilled.   There is still a constant clamour in Germany for an undefined &quot; freedom cf the seas,&quot; the nearest approach to a definition  being given in Ueberall, a semi-official naval monthly, published last month &quot;For Germany there is only one Freedom of the Seas, which &quot; is the liberation of the sea from the tyranny of England ;   Englanchs outrageous &quot; power must be broken for ever&quot; which can be read in conjunction with Grand Admiral von Tirpitz-s statement &quot;I know of only one way, and that is that we (sic)-do away with England&apos;s policing of the sea.&quot;Before proceeding further with this investigation it is interesting to note an historical precedent. -The polic.y of Great Britain for centuries has been to maintain the balance of power in Europe, and to throw her sea-power in war time into the-scales against absolute rulers who endeavour to use their armies to dominate the-whole Continent. Napoleon constantly raised the cry for the freedom of the seas in time of war which has now been taken up by the Hohenzollerns.Continental military emqhres claim the freedom of the seas in time of war for two reasons (1) in order to use their armies to devastate countries beyond the sea, as they use them to devastate countries accessible by land, and (2) to prevent a strong Sea Power from exerting economic pressure.PRESIDENT WILSON&apos;S ANNOUNCEMENT.In the circumstances set forth above, President Wilson&apos;s announcement of the-8th of January requires special attention.   He advocated : &quot;Absolute freedom of navigation upon-the seas outside territorial waters alike in peace and in war,   except as the seas may be closed in  whole-or in part   by   international action for the enforcement  of  international covenants.&quot;1 Professor Scott, &quot; Jevons &quot; Lecture, Mare Idberivm Aer clausus at Glasgow University.
BRITISH VIEW OF THE FREEDOM OF THE SEAS.The British idea of the freedom of the seas is free and unfettered access in time, of peace to all the seas by all who wish to cross them &quot;upon, their lawful occasions &quot; : but that in time of war this privilege must be fought for by belligerent navies, causing as little inconvenience as possible to neutrals, but maintaining the right of searching neutral merchant ships in order to verify their nationality and prevent their aiding a belligerent.The reasons why Great Britain adopts this attitude are the following : (1) To secure the population of the United Kingdom, the Dominions, India, British Colonies, and Protectorates from attacks by continental armies more especially the German, after the cruel and super-bestial horrors they perpetrated amongst the civilian population of Belgium.(2) To maintain mercantile traffic, without which the population of the United Kingdom would perish for want of food and raw materials for industries.(3) To maintain sea communication between the nations and territories grouped under the British Grown.(4) To enable troops to cross the sea for defence of territory and to maintain treaty obligations.(5) To hold in reserve an economic weapon for use in extreme emergencies against predatory continental Emperors, like the Kaiser, who try to dominate the whole of Europe.From the point of view of Great Britain, then, the most obvious comment on President WilsoiTs pronouncement is that Belgium was closed to the German armies in 1914 by an &quot; international covenant,&quot; and that, if We accepted the formula, the North Sea would be in a similar position. German armies could cross it to attack us, as they crossed Belgium to attack the French. Transports are identical in appearance with merchant ships, aud it is impossible at present to conceive any form of &quot;&quot;inter-national action&quot; that could operate quickly enough to save us from invasion by the armies of an unscrupulous Continental Power.At this stage it is unnecessary to follow up the subject through the other headings, as tiiis one consideration amply suffices to indicate our vital interest in the problem. It is necessary, however, to take account of some further statements which have been attributed to President Wilson on the very best authority (Sir C. Spring-Rice). He has since (January 10th) laid great stress upon the point that his views must depend upon the nations agreeing formally to the restrictive action that must be taken to limit the freedom of the seas. He thinks that the rules of blockade must be amended to meet the new conditions disclosed in this war, and no single nation should be permitted to place its own arbitrary interpretation upon them. He recognises that Great Britain is obliged to maintain a strong fleet in order to safe-guard the means of livelihood of the population of the British Islands, and also for employment on police duties.It will be seen from this paper that, broadly speaking, there are three principal views of the freedom of the seas : (l).The British view, that supremacy must be established over the sea forces of airy prospective enemies.It is clear that the provision of sea forces of sufficient strength to maintain such supremacy will require the co-operation of all the Nations under the British Crown.(2) The German view, that German sea forces should wrest the supremacy from the British.(3) President Wilsons view, that the freedom of the seas both in peace and in war shall be subject to the control of an international organisation, now generally known as a &quot; League of Nations.&quot;From the British point of view, the position is so exceptional, that it seems impossible to contemplate any alteration of policy. A League of Nations has not yet materialised, and in order to realise President vYilson&apos;s ideal such a League would require to have at its disposal naval, economic, and moral forces of such overwhelming-strength that no continental governments, however strong, would dare to disobey its dictates. In the meanwhile, free national development in the British Isles and in the Dominions will dex^end upon the supremacy of the British Navy over the sea
forces of continental military Powers. Without that supremacy, neither we nor other nations can be free from Prussian dominance, and we cannot gain our principal object in this and in all war security.G. G. A.January 23rd, 1918.[Articles of some weight and interest on the Freedom of the Seas have appeared in the Nineteenth Century Magazine for November 1917 and January 1918, and in the Cornhill Magazine for December 1917. Some of the points in this paper have been extracted from those articles. In a recent lecture at Glasgow University, Professor Scott dealt at some length with the Freedom of the Seas and of the Air, in connection with the question of a League of Nations. The following is an extract: &quot; Any type &quot; of thinking which would limit the use of the Navy in war, save under considerations &quot; of humanity, would be a great wrong, not only to the people of this country and &quot; of the Dominions, but to our Allies as well. To fail in making the most efficient &quot; use of an instrument bequeathed to us by our fathers, and improved by the &quot; sacrifices of the present generation in preparation for the possibilities of defence, &quot; which, have now become actual necessities, would be a fatal error for wnich there &quot; Would be neither excuse nor forgiveness.&quot;]

</content>
</cab>
