<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/151/0 images: 44-55</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED WESTERN AND GENERAL -&quot;  &apos;&apos; &apos; ;   &quot;REPORT No.&apos; 54.PART I. -BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA.Imperial Cabinet.The beginning of June seems to be indicated as the period that is most likely to suit the convenience of the Prime Ministers of Canada, New Zealand, and South Africa, for the next Sessions of the Imperial Cabinet. Though the Prime Minister of the Australian Commonwealth would prefer the date to be in July, on account of Parliamentary business, the telegram that lias been sent to him may result in arrangements being made which will facilitate his attendance at the time suitable to the other Members of the Cabinet. It is interesting to note that the New Zealand representation is expected to be the same as last year.Canada.The appointment of a Dominion War Mission to the United States, to act in close touch with the British Ambassador at Washington will, it is to be hoped, entirely satisfy the feeling in the Dominion that Canadian interests should receive individual and special attention in the United States.AUSTKALlan C0mm0nvvEALTH.It appears that the Government policy for the organisation of industry is to receive the full support of the Opposition. Attention is drawn to the serious position of wheat stocks.New Zealand.The experiment relating to the provision of a camp for unfit men is interesting.South Africa.Further political difficulties connected with wool exports seem to have been narrowly avoided. In this, and other matters appearing in this week&apos;s report, the Nationalists appear determined to cause trouble to the Government. General Botha&apos;s statement regarding the maintenance of the South African Brigade is encouraging. The proposal made at the recruiting conference in favour of conscription for Oversea service has been recognised as impracticable.
GermanyandCentralAfrica.I attach an important Appendix by Mr. Howard d&apos;Egville on this question.Now that it is known that Dr. von Kiihlmann was the author- of the important .work &quot;Deutsche Weltpolitik&apos; und kein Kreig,&quot; special interest m attaches: to a the quotations in the Appendix and the connection which is made apparent between them and the. more recent official pronouncements regarding German aims in Central Africa. The Foreign Office has received additional information from a reliable source that this book has occupied the KaiseFs attention a good deal, and that he has recommended its perusal to various partv leaders.G. G. A.February 7th, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet. k ^SECRET. - ^       For Reference only.WESTERN   AND  GENERAL  REPORT.No. 54.    Week ending 6th February 2918 (night).PART I. BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA. . Contents..Canada.Dominion War. Mission. Quebec and Separation. Labour and the War. Military Service Con-Vention. Military Service exemptions in Quebec. - Militia Department and the use of influence. Soldiers&apos; votes.   Shipping- on the Pacific.   Steel ships for United States.   Civil Service reform.Australian Commonwealth.Meeting- of Imperial Cabinet. Common-wealth shipbuilding-. Organisation of industry. Germany and New Guinea. - Serious position of &quot;wheat industry. Australians and English -wives. Damage to Mack ay district.   Loans to States.   Vote of Censure on New South Wales Government.New7 Zealand.Meeting of Imperial Cabinet.   Dabour difficulties.   Camp for unfit men.   Supply of coal.   Tin supplies after the war. South Africa.Question of conscription. Exports to Japan: the wool question. Return of Soxith African soldiers. Difficulties of gold mines.   Repairing facilities at ports.British East Africa.Development of war resources.German East Africa.Progress of military forces.Portuguese Africa.Proposal for internationalisation.Appendix : The Foundations of German Policy in Central Africa.(33)49S5-la    Pk100   2/18   E &amp; S
PART   I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE   AND  AFRICA.CANADA.. Dominion War Mission. The Dominion Government have appointed a War Mission to look after Canadian affairs in the United States, the Chairman of which is Mr. Lloyd Harris, a former Member of Parliament, who will be directly responsible to the Dominion Cabinet. The Mission will work in touch with the British Ambassador at Washington, will keep him informed upon the main lines of a.etion, and will rely upon his assistance when required (oi.de Reports Nos. 38 and 42).Quebec and Separation. The Premier of Quebec (Sir Lomer Gouin), in a letter to Sir -Tames Grant, who is one of the few surviving&quot; JxL embers of the First Confederation Parliament of the Dominion, has stated that, &quot; though our Province has deeply felt &quot; the injustice of the attacks which have been recently directed on its population, it &quot; remains, and will continue to remain, faithful to the ideals that inspired the fathers &quot; of Confederation.&quot; -Labour and the War. A statement has been issued by the Labour representatives who have recently been in conference with the Dominion Government (wide Report No. 52). This indicates that those appointed to represent labour demanded the nationalisation of all railways, or failing that, their control by a Central Board for the period of the war. Thej- denied that there was any shortage of labour for railway maintenance, and blamed the railway companies for the low rate of w^ages. The proposal for compulsion in relation to farm labour, put forward by the Provincial Governments, met with the strong opposition of the labour representatives. The latter, however, approved of a vigorous campaign to assist in food production, and asked for free transportation for farm labourers. While opposing the employment of alien labour, on the ground that &quot;any man who is not entitled to the full industrial freedom of a citizen should be interned and employed by the Government, the labour representatives agreed to the desirability of a census in order to ascertain the man-power of Canada. At the same time they asked for the registration of wealth as well as of man-power.Military Service Convention. The agreement with the United States regarding conscription has been submitted for signature. The proposals give to Canadians in the United States, who are between the ages of 20 and 40 years, and to citizens of the United States in Canada, between 2.1 and 30 years, the -option of returning to their own country for military service before the expiration of 60 clays after the convention comes into force. At the expiration of this period,, they will be subject to military duty under the laws and regulations of the country in which they reside, unless meantime they should be exempted, in the case of United States citizens by the Consul-General at Ottawa, and, in the case of Canadian citizens by the British Ambassador at &quot;Washington.Military Service exemptions in Quebec. Appeals have been lodged by the military authorities against 10,718 exemptions granted by the tribunals in Quebec Province.Militia Department and the Use oj Influence.--The Department of Militia has issued a memorandum dealing with the attempts to use influence in connection /with soldiers serving in the Canadian Forces. The memorandum states that requests for leave of absence, furlough,, and transfers should be made by the soldier himself, and that requests by friends or relatives of officers employed in France or England for return to Canada are not likely to be effective and may easily prejudice the position
of the officer concerned. The hope is expressed that the Members of the Senate and House of Commons and persons holding official positions will refrain from making-requests which are at variance with the policy which.is announced.Soldiers&apos; Votes.-lX has been decided that the votes of soldiers which were cast in. the recent General Election for candidates in any constituency other than that in which the voter last resided, will be disallowed. Many soldiers apparently cast votes for candidates in constituencies where thej7 neither lived, nor enlisted, and it is estimated that 10,000 votes will be annulled through illegality.Shipping on the Pacific. -The Shipping Controller has informed the Dominion GoArernment that it would be in Imperial interests to requisition the Empress of Asia and the Empress of Russia, now on the Pacific service. It is pointed out that these vessels can be fitted to carry 2,000 to 2,500 men each, and it is considered that as regards the transport of Chinese, the vessels still remaining in the Pacific service will be sufficient for the purpose, more especially as it is possible-, that the further recruiting of labourers from Manchuria may be obviated. The hope is expressed that the Dominion Ministers may therefore requisition the vessels in question.It has been decided to augment the shipping for Pacific Coast req\iiremlmts by the construction of 10 wooden ships, having an aggregate tonnage of 140,000 gross. Twenty of these vessels will be built at Victoria, B.C.Steel Ships for United States. A contract has been placed with the Canadian Car and Foundry Company for the construction of steel ships for the United States at Fort William: The cost of the vessels will be $10,500,000 and the work will employ 1,000 men.Civil Service Reform. The Dominion Government have issued a statement to the effect that the reform of the Civil Service, which was outlined in the programme of the Unionist Party at the recent elections, will be now undertaken. The Civil Service Commission has been instructed to prepare the necessary legislation which the Government intend to introduce in the coming session of Parliament.AUSTRALIAN COMMONWEALTH.Meeting of Imperial Cabinet. The Prime Minister (Mr. Hughes) has informed the British Government that it would not be practicable for him to attend the coming-Sessions of the Imperial Cabinet before July next, owing to the necessity of his being-present during the sittings of the Commonwealth Parliament, which will be dealing with urgent business. In reply, it has been pointed out that the Prime Ministers of all other Dominions are prepared to attend the meetings of the Imperial Cabinet early in June, and that it is desirable to hold the meetings as early as possible for various reasons. It is&quot;mentioned that if, for instance, the great offensive in the West fails, the German Governmexit may propose peace terms suddenly ; and the hope is therefore expressed that the Prime Minister will agree to attend the meetings at the beginning of June.Commonwealth Shipbuilding. The Minister for the Navy (Mr. Joseph Cook) has stated that 12 snips will probably&quot; be building shortly in various parts of the Commonwealth. The Governor-General, when speaking at the Australian Natives Association Foundation Day Luncheon in Melbourne, devoted the greater portion of his speech to advocating Australian shipbuilding.As the result of a conference of the shipbuilding trades unions, the Prime Minister has stated that a scheme covering industrial conditions had been ratified, and a formal contract would be signed. When this has been done, tribunals will be appointed to regulate matters connected with the various trades.Organisation of Industry. -With reference to the arrangements in contemplation by the Commonwealth Government for the organisation of industry, which were
outlined in Report No. 41, the Leader of the Opposition in the Federal Parliament (Mr. Tudor) has declared that in organising industry there could be no partv, and that all are united in the determination to make Australia self-contained.Germany and New Guinea. An interesting statement has been made by the Chief &apos; Justice and Lieutenant-Governor of New South Wales (Sir William Cullen) regarding the possibility of Australia having to consider the guarding of a land frontier in New Guinea and the presence of Germans in that country. He stated, &quot; Australia is &quot;&apos; threatened with the curse of a land frontier from such a nation as Germany, quite &quot; apart from the creation of submarine bases on the New Guinea coasts and other &quot; him savagery. Germany covdd raise a quarrel at any time over mines, oilfields, or &quot;&apos; anything else which might suit her purpose. Germans are still occupying and &quot; developing New Guinea. No Australian can contemplate such a situation with &quot; equanimity.&quot;Serious position of Wheat Industry. The Prime Minister has stated that present stocks of wheat now in the Commonwealth cannot be shipped overseas for at least five years. It is estimated that at least 100,000,000 bushels from the last two seasons are still unsold, while the incoming crop is expected to yield 120,000,000 bushels, of which only one-third is required for Australian consumption. The New South Wales Government is considering the advisability of assisting wheat growers to transfer their efforts to raising stock.Australians and English Wives: Owing to the fact that 2,000 Australians have married women in the United Kingdom, the marriages recently averaging 800 per month. the Premier of New South Wales has agreed to the suggestion of the Agent-General of that State that soldiers should have the right of nomiuatins; their wives for assisted passages to Australia.Damage to Mackay District. Owing to the submerging of the district by the Fitzroy River, it is estimated that 1,500,000?. worth of damage has been done within a 20 mile radius in the Mackay district, and that 500,000Z. worth of sugar ha6 been damaged.Loams to States. During 1914-15 the Commonwealth Government advanced to the various States, excepting Queensland, the sum of 18,000,000L, and repayment was agreed within three years. By an agreement of 1915 with all States except New South Wales, the Commonwealth Government arranged to borrow for the States from overseas 8,0OO,00OZ. up to the end of 1916 and subsecprently 7,450,000Z. per annum until one year after the war. In January last, the Commonwealth Government were obliged to submit a fresh agreement reducing the annual amount for 1917 to 5,400,000L, while at the conference with the State Treasurers which has just concluded, the Commonwealth have agreed to provide 3,000,000Z. for 1918 and to extend the period for repayment of loans made in 1914-15 (totalling 18.000,000Z.) to five years after the war, provided this is not later than 1925. The 3,000,000Z. for the current year is divided between Queensland, South Australia, Western Australia and Tasmania, Victoria having agreed to borrow locally and New South Wales standing out altogether.1Censure of New South Wales Ministry. The Vote of Censure upon the Ministry of Mr. Holman in the New South Wales Legislative Assembly for statements made in connection with conscription (vide Report No. 53) was moved by the leader of the Opposition (Mr: Storey) but was defeated by 50 Votes to 28.NEW ZEALAND.Meeting of Imperial Cabinet. It has been announced in New Zealand that the Prime Minister (Mr. Massey) and Sir Joseph Ward will represent the Dominion at the meetings of the Imperial Cabinet and Conference this year. They will be able to leave after the special session of Parliament in April.1 lSfe\v South Wales received 7,400,000Z. of the original 18,000,000/. loaa, but stood out of the agreement of 1915 as well as the present arrangement.
Labour Difficulties. There is a serious shortage of labour in the Dominion, except in the supply of farm labourers.   Arrangements have been made to utilise schoolboys . in assisting with the harvest during their holidays.Camp for Unfit Men. The Dominion Government established some time ago a special training camp f or C 1 men, whom it was considered might be ultimately made fit for active service OA^ersea. This experiment has proved a great success, and the figures show that 60 per cent, of the men are thoroughly rehabilitated. The Minister for Defence (Sir James Allen) has expressed the opinion that the results of this important experiment should not be, lost sight of after the war.Supply of Coal. The Prime Minister (Mr. Massey) has informed the British Government of the great difficulty experienced in maintaining the supply of coal to the Dominion. This arises from the fact that the Admiralty require considerable quantities from Westport, and.it is practically impossible to obtain the tonnage necessary tojbring corresponding amounts from Newcastle (New South Wales) for the use of railways and coasting steamers. It is therefore suggested that the British Government might assist the Dominion in arranging that some of the vessels trading to Australia and New Zealand should carry coal from Newcastle to the Dominion.Tin Supplies after the War.-The Dominion Government have informed the British Government that the quantity of tin ore likely to be produced during three years after the war in New Zealand would be under 5 tons, and that this would probably be smelted in Australia. There is no tin ore smelted in New Zealand, and no tin plate produced. Requirements in New Zealand for the period mentioned above are estimated at 250 ton,s: of block tin a year, and 6,000 tons of tin plate.SOUTH AFRICA.Question, of Conscription. At a Conference of Delegates called together from various parts of the Union to discuss recruiting for the South African Brigade, the Prime Minister (General Botha) stated that the prevailing idea was to help the British Empire, and he asked those present not to allow tire shame of the South African unit being incorporated with other units.Referring to the suggestion of conscription. General Botha asked, &quot;Have we not-enough trouble in the country that people want to create more ? &quot; Events in Australia, he declared, had been a shock to men like himself who wanted to assist in the war and they had provided an argument for the opponents of the Empire. &quot; No,&quot; he continued, &quot; I cannot, and will not do this. If you introduce conscription you will not get the men to send to Flanders, but will be obliged to recall men from Flanders to put down trouble in South Africa.&quot; Referring to the proposal to conscript British-born subjects in South Africa, he said that this class of legislation could not be introduced. As to the allegation that men were fleeing to South Africa to escape conscription in England, General Botha promised, if supplied with particulars, to make representations to the British Government.In the result, the Resolution urging the Government to introduce conscription was negatived. The amendment of the Mayor of Cape Town, &quot; regretfully recognising &quot; that conscription was impracticable for South Africa, but pledging the Conference to redouble their efforts to obtain recruits under the voluntary sj^stem, was adopted.Exports to Japan : The Wool Question. With reference to the telegram from the British Government relating to the re-exportation of goods from Japan to Russia (vide Reports Nos. 52 and 53 under &quot;Imperial Affairs&quot;), the Union Government have telegraphed that they have cancelled all export licences to Japan until they receive the approved list of firms from the British Ambassador. The first approved list of firms who are to be permitted to import wool has now been received.In the announcement concerning the temporary suspension of export licences to Japan which appeared in the local Press, no reason was given for the suspension, and reports thereupon appeared that there had been a sudden drop in the price of wool. The Minister of Mines and Industries therefore found it advisable to make a statement in the House of Assembly upon the matter and to read the telegrams from the British Government. On the motion for the adjournment of the House, the Leader of the Nationalist Party (General Hertzog) accused the Government of betraying the interests4985-la B
of South Africa, more particularly the wool farmers, for the purposes of the Empire. In replying, the Minister of Mines and Industries reaffirmed the Governments determi-nation to &quot;ensure that no exports should go from South Africa to countries from which there was a risk of their being re-exported to the enemy. The debate concluded automatically without a division.L Return of South African Soldiers. The motion of the Leader of the Opposition (Sir Thomas Smartt) to appoint a&quot; Select Committee to inquire into arrangements to-facilitate the return of South African soldiers, and into the measures for assisting them in taking up civilian work, was adopted^ without a division, notwithstanding the-oppositiou of the Nationalists, who argued that the sufferers of the Boer War should first be considered. The Acting Minister of Defence (Colonel Mentz) stated that 6,589 men were in various hospitals, &apos;of whom 70 per cent- were suffering from malaria and only 2- 7 per cent, from wounds. He quoted statistics to demonstrate-that the Government were working in the direction of placing returned soldiers onthe-land.Difficulties of Gold Mines. The amendment to the motion of the Minister of Mines, proposed by the Leader of the Labour Party (Colonel Creswell), in which it was suggested that the Government should administer any mine which closed down during the war and should take direct&quot;control of the gold mining industry (vide Report No. 53), was &quot;negatived in the House of Assembly by-40 votes to 20. The House subsequently adopted the amendment of Mr. Merriman that a Select Committee should consider the whole subject of the economic and labour conditions in the mines.Repairing Facilities at Ports.- Owing to information having been received that A^essels have been held up in South African ports through absence of repairing-facilities, the Admiralty have appointed a representative to proceed to South Africa to look into the matter with the object of helping forward the work of carrying out repairs and also of increasing&quot; the local facilities in connection with South African trade.BRITISH EAST AFRICA.Development of War Resources. A meeting at Nairobi has unanimously passed a resolution requesting the British Government to appoint Sir Percy Girouard (ex-Governor of the Protectorate) as Military Governor of British East Africa during the Avar, with power to organise &quot;the country in the direction of &quot; utilising such &quot; portion of its population as may not be aA-available militarily, to develop its mines,. &quot; potential energies and.resources in the immediate production of commodities which &quot; are urgently required.&quot; It Avas emphasised that the entire resources of the Protectorate should be utilised to provide for. the immediate requirements of Mesopotamia and Palestine, and thereby save shipping. It aaras stated that there were millions of acres of the finest land available in East Africa for British soldiers.GERMAN EAST AFRICA.Progress of Military Forces. General Northey has reported that Mwembe was; occupied by a detachment of the 2nd Cape-Corps on. January 21st, without opposition,, and that ffve companies of the enemy forces under Wahle are retiring east wan i towards Mtarika ; one company of the 2nd Cape Corps and 50 Portuguese rifles, are in pursuit.PORTUGUESE AFRICA.Proposal for Internalionalisation. The fear of the Portuguese wjth regard to the proposed internationalisation of Tropical Africa, as outlined in the Manifesto of the British Labour party *has been indicated in the course of a communication sent by the Geographical Society of Lisbon to the R.oATal Geographical Society. The letter-from the Portuguese Society stated that the Portuguese nation Avas most alarmed at the proposal to found a sort of international State in Africa, the chief reason for the-apprehension being that Mr. Henderson, avIio was associated with the idea, was an. ex-Cabinet Minister.
APPENDIX* ....TO -     .   - -Western and General Report No. 54.  Part I.THE FOUNDATIONS OF GERMAN POLICY IN CENTRAL AFRICA.It is difficult to apprehend the full significance of the recent observations of Dr. Solf, the German Colonial Secretary, and other official spokesmen of German Colonial policy in Central Africa, without reference to the views which have been promulgated from time to time, during recent years, by those who may be termed the more moderate leaders of political thought in the Fatherland. The treatise which has perhaps exercised more direct influence upon authoritative German opinion than any-other publication of the last few years is Deutsche Weltpolitik mid Icein Krieg, which appeared anonymously just before the war, but the author of which was, in fact, none other than Dr. von Kuhlmann, the present German Foreign Secretary. This book, as pointed out in the Memorandum on &quot; The situation in Germany,&quot; issued by the Intelligence Bureau on the 28th January, has, since the entry of America into the war, occupied the mind of the Kaiser, who upon frequent occasions has recom-mended its perusal to the leaders of the political parties. Some extracts from this work are, therefore, given below, and also some quotations from the productions of those writers on Colonial policy who may be considered to have directly influenced the more moderate party in Germany. This party is at present associated with Dr. Solf, and is now believed to be pressing forward the scheme of establishing a great German Empire in Africa by means of negotiation. The bearing of this upon proposals for the intei nationalisation of tropical Africa will not be difficult to appreciate.GERMAN POLICY BEFORE TEE  WAR.1Economic Development : not Colonisation. The truth of the statement recently made by General Smuts that the German aim in Central Africa is not colonisation in the ordinary sense of settlement by white people, but the provision of strategic positions and openings for trade is abundantly shown in German writings. On the economic aspect of the matter Dr. von Kuhlmann writes : &quot; AATe have no need of &quot; colonies for purposes of settlement, but on the other hand we have great need &quot; of a colonising policy in those territories which are able to provide our industries &quot; with a large portion of raw materials ; where our countrymen can carry on, not the &quot; lower forms of labour, but the organisation of the work of directing economic &quot; development.&quot;German Interests in Central Africa. In showing the project of a German Colonial Empire in Central Africa, Dr. von Euhlinann observes : &quot; In that which concerns our &quot; political world interests, which are naturally before ail of an economic nature, the &quot; vast territory of Central Africa, bordering upon our Eastern and Western African &quot; Colonies, and separating them to-day, offers the best, and it is necessaiy to add, the &quot; only avenue of advancement.&quot;English disinterest in Central Africa. Relying upon the speech of Viscount (then Sir Edward) Grey in the House of Commons of November 27th, 1911, as indicating that England was in effect disinterested in Central Africa, the author asks if Germany can hope that England may make her a present of part of her own possessions. &quot; Until, now,&quot; he says, &quot;our complaint against England has been that she has thwarted1 All the quotations given under this Leading are from Deutsche Weltpolitik and Icein Krieg. 49S5-In C
s&quot; our Colonial aspirations, and now that England is disposed to leave us a free hand &quot; in Central Africa and not to create difficulties for us there, we must be on our &quot; guard against delusive presents from England. One of two courses is necessary : &quot; either we wish for a policy of expansion, and in that case we have every reason to be &quot; satisfied that the obstruction offered up to the present by England is about to &quot; disappear, or we do not wish for a policy of expansion, and in that case, we have &quot; not any reason to complain that England wishes to prevent us carrying it out.&quot;Comparison with France. In proceeding to justify the idea of German Colonial expansion, Herr von Iviihlmann calls attentioii to the French Colonial Empire in these words : &quot; But if we consider how France, notwithstanding her grave defeats &quot;of 1870, has created for herself a vast Colonial Empire;&apos; we have, without doubt, &quot; the right to believe that we are capable of the same achievements. Naturally, &quot; everything depends upon the choice of the sphere of our Colonial activities. We &quot; ought never to forget that we are, in the first instance, a territorial and continental &quot; Power, and that we shall never become a maritime Power and an oversea Power &quot; in the same sense as England. It is precisely for this reason that a geographical &quot; concentration of our Colonies, such as should be carried out in Central Africa, is &quot; forced upon us ; whereas an empire spread about all parts of the world and in all &quot; seas, such as the British Empire, can onfy be controlled by a Power which is, &quot; before ail, a maritime Power.&quot;Security of Central Africa--In contrasting the advantages of a Central African Empire as against German penetration of Asiatic Turkey, Herr von Kuhlmann says:  &quot; From the strategic point of view, as well as from the political standpoint, our &quot; situation in Central Africa would be incomparably more favourable than in Asiatic &quot;Turkey. In the latter case, we should have to consider the territorial frontiers &quot; of Russia, we should ourselves be at a great distance [from our base, and our &quot; communications woidd be seriously menaced. On the contrary, one does not find &quot; in Central Africa any strong military power, and, in short, any territorial power &quot; which is able to become a menace to us . . . The Militia of the South African &quot; Union provides, it is true, an excellent army for the defence of its own country, &quot; but it lends itself in a very much less degree to a policy of attack or conquest. We &quot; should be in complete security against the attacks of European powers by land. &quot; Moreover, as to attacks by sea, the strongest enemy fleets would be as little able to &quot; concjuer an African Colony as to defeat a defending army. On the other hand, the &quot; conditions oE a naval war in an open sea are, for us, infinitely more favourable than &quot; in a closed sea.&quot;Methods of Penetration : A Central African Block. Dr. von Kuhlmann, in the work which is quoted above, proceeds to point out that a pacific German policy would have the best chance of success in Central Africa, and in discussing the methods, indicates that the Belgian Congo needs capital, that Mozambique is insecure - on account of the lack of railway development, that Angola, which lias excellent ports, cannot profit by them through absence of capital, whereas the ports would be particularly useful to Germany, and that German finance and German industry could provide the railways, develop the agriculture, &amp;c, and undertake the economic penetration of the Colonies of other Powers. This will lead to the realisation, in the words of the author, &quot; of the sole and fundamental idea that, from the political and &quot; commercial point of view, it is necessary that all Central Africa shall be treated &quot; as a sphere forming a single block, and that all commercial projects shall conform &quot; to this principle.&quot;1THE CENTRAL AFRICAN EMPIRE AFTER THE WAR.The above extracts indicate the line of policy which influenced German thought before the war, and which, without doubt, is exercising its influence over present-day thought.    The view of Dr. Solf that the world-war has shown that the german In the event of any Power hesitating to conform to the German plan, the method of procedure to be adopted was outlined by Herr Zimmei-mannin Was ist tins Central Afrika as follows : &quot; If on the Belgian &quot; side there is a disinclination to make a compact with our Central African Railway, our cargoes mast be &quot; shipped according to a sjjecial tariff from Hamburg and Antwerp to the mouth of the Lukuga more &quot; cheaply than Belgium can bring hers to Stanley Pool/&apos;
Colonial Empire was not a proper &quot;Empire&quot; at all but &quot;merely a number of &quot; possessions without geographical and political connection, and without established &quot; communications,&quot; has caused him to declare that the aim of German Colonial policy must be connected with all. other aims &quot;which we are determined to attain bv the world-war.&quot;In the event of German Victory.  In the event of the German victory being sufficiehtly considerable, the German attitude is shown by Professor Delbruck, who is closely associated with Dr. Solf, and who has declared : &quot;If our victory is great enough, Yve &quot; can hope to unite under our hand the whole of Central Africa with our old Colony &quot; South-West Africa ; Senegambia, Sierra Leone, the Gold Coast, Dahomey, well-populated Nigeria with the port of Lagos, Cameroon, the rich islands of San Thome and &quot; Principe, with their splendid ports, the Katanga ore &quot;district, Northern Khodesia, &quot; Nyassaland,Mozambique and Delagoa Bay,Madagascar, German East Africa, Zanzibar, *&apos; and Uganda ; and in addition the great port of Ponta Delgaclo in the Azores, one of the &quot; most important and most frequented coaling stations, and Horta, one of the most &quot; important centres of the Transatlantic cable s\-stem. At present the Azores belong to Portugal, which is at war with Germany. Portugal also owns the Cape Verde &quot; Islands, with the port of Porto Grande, one of the most frequented coaling stations &quot; in the Eastern Atlantic. All these territories together have over 100.000,000 inhabitants. United in a single ownership, and with their various characteristics &quot; supplementing one another, they offer simply immeasurable prospects. They are &quot; rich in natural treasures, rich in possibilities of settlement and trade, and rich in &quot; men who can work and also be used in war. To demand them is not unjust, and does not offend against the principle of equilibrium, since Germany would thus only &quot; be obtaining a Colonial Empire such as England and Russia, France and America, &quot; have long possessed.&quot;This view is officially emphasised in the Kaiserzeitung des Ostheeres, published by the Press Administration of the German Commandantur of Lodz on the occasion of the KaiseFs birthday on January 27th, 1915 : &quot; A victorious war. . , . would give us the Belgian Congo, the French Congo, and if Portugal continues to translate her &quot; hostile intentions towards us into actions, would also give us the Portuguese colonies &quot; on the East and a test coasts of Africa. We should then have a Colonial Empire &quot; of which our fathers, who used to smile slily at our first essays in colonisation, &quot; could never have dreamt. But the most important factor in this probable partition &quot; of the African world is, that we should thereby have put an end to the English &quot; attempts at domination from the Cape to Cairo. Between Egypt, loliicli is still &quot; English., and Anglo-Boer South Africa would stretch the immense band of our vast &quot; colonial possessions, extending from the Indian Ocean to the Atlantic. Still V- English, we say advisedly of North-East and South Africa. For who can tell &quot; what may happen when the words of the poet are realised : &apos; One day Germanism *&apos; &apos; will be the salvation of the world.&apos; &quot;Strategic Importance of Africa. If the above policy should be rendered possible by a German victory, it has been pointed out in the Deutsche Politik by Herr Franz Kolbe that considerable strategic assistance could be given to Germany by her African possessions, and he says: &quot;The whole coast of West Africa from &quot; the mouth of the Cross River to the mouth of the Orange River would be in &quot; German possession. When one only remembers what 1 0111161136 il chievements were &quot; performed by the Emden in the Indian Ocean, and by the Karlsruhe in the Atlantic, &quot; without any naval base, without any possibility of replenishing in port their supplies &apos;&quot; of munitions, food, &amp;c, it will be realised what the fortification of half the West &quot; Coast of Africa would signify for Germany and for England ! As soon as, in a new &quot; war, the Suez Canal is closed against England by the Turks, all traffic between 41 England and India, Australia, and South Africa must go round the Cape of Good &quot; Hope. But then all the shipping must pass the Coast of German Central Africa ! &quot; It would be impossible for England any longer to concentrate her whole fleet in the &quot; North Sea and to menace Germany.&quot;Again, Herr Emil Zimmermann (the author of such works as Was ist uns Central Afrika, &amp;c.) states : &quot; German Africa which will find allies at once in Abyssinia &quot; and in Mahomedan freedom movements, will make the employment of black troops ;&quot; against our European frontiers impossible. German Africa alone will give us a &apos;&quot; balance of power in the East and in Africa   ....   German Africa will make
&quot;jus a tvoriel-power by enabling us to exert decisive influence upon the world-political &quot;decisions of our enemies, and of other Powers, and to exercise pressure on all &quot; shapings of polic3&quot; in Africa, Asia Minor and southern Europe.&quot; sRedistribution and the Maintenance of the Balance of Power. The idea referred-to in the last quoted extract concerning the employment of black troops in Europe-has been recently discussed by Dr. Solf, who sees in the redistribution of the African Continent &quot; the best method of obviating militarisation of the coloured races.&quot; His idea of militarisation, however, apparently applies only to the einployment of natives in a military capacity in Europe, as the following quotation indicates that when Africa is equally divided, the Powers, according to Herr Solf, will confine the natives to their respective African territories through fear of attack from other territories. He says : &quot; By striking a balance in place of the former unequal distribution, it. &quot; will be made impossible for individual Colonial Powers to transport coloured forces &quot; to Europe without having to fear a danger to the Colony from its ecpially powerful &quot; neighbour, through denuding it of those forces.&quot;Present German Colonial Aims.-The most recent expressions of the German Colonial Secretary (Dr. Solf) are apparently based upon the assumption of a less complete German victory than that which the writers of some of the above quoted observations appear to contemplate. The standard which Dr. Solf sets up is, however, the same economic one as that outlined in Deutsche Weltpolitik und kein Krieg. He asserts1 that it is in relation to economic activity that &quot; the Colonial territories of the earth should be divided amongst the Powers who wish.for a share.&quot; He continues : &quot; What individual States are capable of in the sphere of culture must serve as the &quot; standard by which to measure their right to co-operate in the education and &quot; advancement of the native races.&quot; He then makes the following significant-declaration : &quot; It is sufficient to point to the far too large possessions of France, Portugal,, and Belgium to make it evident that the present distribution does not correspond to these standards. We demand that, on the conclusion of peace, a more suitable division of the Colonies should be taken in hand, and are convinced that a position of equality in the colonial sphere could be created in this way, which will remove the possibilities of future conflict.&quot;International Control. The official German view, as expressed by Dr. Solf, regarding the internationalisation of&quot; tropical Africa, must be considered in relation to the above extracts, and in any case Dr. Solf has clearly indicated that his view of the policy of international control is limited to such matters as &quot; the creation of great &quot; joint traffic routes through the possessions of different Powers, and of the combating &quot; of dangerous epidemics.&quot; While recognising that by this means &quot; the owners of individual territory become guardians of the joint organisation,&quot; he asserts that the-prospect of such a development could not move Germany front the attitude which, he sets forth as the basis of her policy. That this attitude involves the economic penetration of the whole of Central Africa by Germanx, may be understood from the quotations that are given above, and these provide a real meaning to Dr. solf&apos;s statement that &quot;the treaty system, the foundations of which were laid at the com-&quot; mencement of the newer colonial era, miist be expanded and developed for the &quot; whole continent, or, at least, for the tropical districts. These treaties should &quot; guarantee the participation of white men in the work of opening up of the African &quot; colonies under equal conditions.&quot;II. b&apos;E.1 Sjjeecli delivered in January 1918.

</content>
</cab>
