<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/151/0 images: 65-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION OF THE ATTACHED WESTERN&apos; AND GENERALREPORT. No. 5(3.PART L -BRITISH i EMPIRE AND; AFRICA.,Imperial. Affairs.It is now clear that the Prime Ministers of Canada, Australia, New Zealand, and South Africa-will&quot;be able to attend the-Meetings of the Imperial Cabinet at the beginning of June, and it is hoped that- the Prime Minister of-Newfoundland will find the arranged date equally convenient.Canada.The Report of the Military Service Council on the operations of the Military Service Act-is of interest, and the manner in which the Government, are dealing, with claims for exemption and with those who endeavour to evade the law shows a determination to administer the Act with both.firmness and uniformity as affecting the various Provinces,The intention of the Government to abolish any vestige of favouritism in appoint-ments to the Civil Service is being carried into effect by an Orderdn-Oounc.il. Presumably the arrangements will find their- way into the Statute- Book in due course.The decision, to grant the Parliamentary franchise to women will extend to the Elections for the Dominion Parliament the rights already possessed ; by women in. several Provinces in relation to Provincial Elections.Au ST akali AN  0 0 M it 0 N W EALTH.It is particularly satisfactory to note that Mr. Hughes has made arrangements to enable him to attend the Meetings of the Imperial Cabinet in J line, and owing to the substantial majority which the Prime Minister now has behind him in the Federal Parliament there is no reason to anticipate any event such as that which unfortunately prevented the representation of the Commonwealth at the Session of last year.It is to be noted with satisfaction that in the State of New South Wales, where a certain amount of - personal hostility has been shown to the Prime Minister by those who were formerly his colleagues in the Labour Party, a Resolution, proposed at a meeting of the State National Party, which asked for the retirement of Mr. Hughes from his position of leadership, was defeated by an overwhelming majority.
. The important speech of Mr. Hughes &apos;upon the organisation of industry should be noted ; it was reported last week that the policy outlined is to receive the support of the Opposition in Parliament.Certain events which occurred recently in Queensland and arc referred to in this Report, seem to point to the necessity of some clear understanding as to the rights of the Commonwealth and the States in the administration of the law respecting riotous assemblies.It is interesting that the number of marriages between Australian soldiers and Englishwomen have rendered special arrangements necessary to enable the women to reach Australia.New Zealand.The new Session of the Dominion Parliament at the beginning of April will be a particularly short one in order to enable Mr. Massey and Sir Joseph Ward to attend the meetings of the Imperial Cabinet.South Africa.The first Budget speech of the new Minister of Finance shows a revenue in excess of that estimated, and an increase of expenditure due to war conditions.The South African Parliament has decided against extending the Parliamentary franchise to women.The attitude of the Nationalists towards the settlement of returned soldiers on the land is characteristic of their general efforts to discourage the participation of South Africa in the war.The Ekefhxi-m of the Sfas.An Appendix is attached to indicate the extent to which our exercise of sea power is affecting the issue of the war, by economic pressure.G. G. A.February 21st, 1918.
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty ?s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet. f 0&apos; _ 4bSECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL  REPORT.No. 56.    Week ending 20th February 1918 (night).PART I.-BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA. Contents.] mperial Affairs.Meetings of Imperial Cabinet: Dominion Ministers attending.Canada.Operation of Military Service Act.   Woman suffrage for Dominion, elections.   Compulsory reg-is-tration for men and women.   Alien, labour.   Quebec tax on bachelors.   Production of maple sugar.   Production of paper.   Military Service Convention.   Patronage in the Civil Service.. Australian Commonwealth..Imperial Cabinet : attendance of Mr. Hughes. National Party and Mr. Hughes. The Government and economic problems : organisation of industry, &amp;c. Australians and English wives. Settle-inenf. of soldiers on land. Soldiers and effect of intoxicating liquor. Commonwealth and Queensland : conflict of laws.    Queensland elections.   Arrival of Governor of New South Wales.New Zealand. jCNext session of Parliament, Revenue returns. Use of aeroplanes in peace. Soldiers and award of Gallipoli Star.    Clubs for returned soldiers.South Africa. &apos;Introduction of Budget. Woman Franchise. Nationalists and returned soldiers. Amount of wool available under purchasing scheme.   Production of glycerine.   Natives as hospital orderlies.German East Africa.Civil control of central and southern areas.   Progress of military forces.Portuguese East Africa.Recruitment of carriers.Appendix : The Blockade and the Freedom of the Seas.(33)-A9i-5-^3a   Fk        100   2/18   E &amp; S A
PART   I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE  AND   AFRICA.IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.Meetings of Imperial Cabinet. -The Dominion Governments have been informed that the Sessions of the Imperial War Cabinet and Imperial War Conference will be arranged to commence as early asjDOSsible in the month of June next. Canada will be represented by the Prime Minister -(Sir Robert Borden) and possibly one other Minister; Australia will be represented by the Prime Minister (Mr. Hughes) and possibly one colleague ; New Zealand will be represented by the Prime Minister (Mr. Massey) and the Minister of Finance (Sir Joseph Ward); while South Africa will be represented by the Prime Minister (General Botha). No decision has yet been reached as to the representation of Newfoundland and India.CANADA. \Operation of Military Service Act. The Prime Minister has presented a report from the Military Service Council upon the operation of the Military Service Act. From this it appears that the number of volunteers who enlisted in the Dominion between September 1st, .1917, and January 31st, 1918, was 8,795. Volunteers from the United States during this period amounted to 7,653.The number of men who were called up \mcler the Proclamation was 22,234, about a fourth of whom reported before being ordered to do so. The total number of men called up for reinforcements up to the present amounts to 46,696.As to the claims for exemption, there are 52,165 now pending before the tribunals, and of these, about two-thirds are from the Province of Quebec. The large number of cases in Quebec is due to the fact that the military authorities have been obliged to appeal against the widespread exemptions in the Province in order to secure uniformity in the administration of the Act.With regard to persons endeavouring to evade the operations of the Military Service Act, the Government have adopted stringent police measures. In the city of Ottawa, nearly 100 deserters were rounded, up in the first two days of the campaign, and these men were immediately despatched to the 1st or 2nd depot battalions. A number of those arrested on Saturday of last week appeared in uniform as soldiers at Church Parade on the following day.Woman Suffrage. -The Dominion Government have decided to introduce a measure granting the Parliamentary franchise to women in respect of elections to the Dominion Parliament. . It is estimated that between one and two million women will be placed on the register, but it is not 3ret certain whether the proposed legislation will be submitted to the forthcoming session of Parliament.In this connection it should be noted that the women of Ontario and the four Western Provinces already possess the franchise in respect of provincial elections.Compulsory Registration. Following upon the. recent conferences held between the Dominion Government and the Labour representatives (vide Report No. 52), the Government have decided to enforce the compulsory registration of all males and females over the age of 16 years. The intention is to secure by voluntary means the necessary labour to increase the food production and the industrial output of the Dominion.Alien Labour. In view of the attitude of Labour to the matter, the Dominion Government will not at present import coolie labour, but the subject may receive further consideration later on, &quot;No decision has been arrived at regarding the conscription of alien labour.
Quebec Tax on. Bachelors. Amongst the new taxes which have been authorised by the Quebec Legislature are those involving an additional tax on unmarried men.Production of Maple Sugar. During the year 1917, 20,000,000 lbs. of maple sugar were made in the Province of Quebec, and it is announced that the supply can be materially increased.Production of Paper. During the year ended March 31st, 1917, the exports of pulp and paper from Canada amounted to the value of 40,000,000. A third of the paper used, in the United States for newspaper purposes, is provided for by Canaclian manufacturers.Military Service Convention. The Dominion Government called the attention of the British Government on February 14th to the negotiations which took place recently between Canada and the United States, in order to prevent further inconvenience, and to define the relations between the two Governments, in respect of the Military Service Convention. The Dominion Ministers wished to know whether the draft Convention should be signed in Washington or in London, and having regard to the wish of the United States to avoid further delay, the Dominion Ministers submitted that the ratification of the Convention was a matter of urgency.On February 18th Lord Reading reported that both the Canadian and British Military Service Conventions had been signed at Washington that day.Patronage in the Civil Service. An Order-in-council has been passed by the Dominion Government abolishing patronage in all Civil Service appointments. The&apos; effect of this will be that future appointments can only be made with the approval and on the recommendation of the Civil Service Commission, who will :make their selections from those who have been successful at competitive examinations. The new arrangements will subsequently be embodied in an Acfr-o  Parliament.AUSTRALIAN COMMONWEALTH.Imperial Cabinet. The Prime Minister (Mr. Hughes) has informed the British Government that he is making arrangements to enable him to be present at the meetings of the Imperial War Cabinet early in June, and he has asked whether there is any objection to his being accompanied by one of his colleagues. The British Government have agreed to the last-named suggestion.    (Vide also under &quot;Imperial Affairs.&quot;)The National Party and Mr. Hughes. At a meeting of the Grand Council of the National Party of New South Wales, a Resolution declaring that the interests of the Commonwealth and of the National Party required the retirement of Mr. Hughes from his position of leadership was considered, and on being put to the vote was defeated by 80 votes to 6.The Government and Economic Problems. The Prime Minister has made an important pronouncement upon the economic problems affecting Australia as arising out. of the war. . He stated that the welfare of Australia was dependent upon the solution of post-war economic problems, for which effective organisation was essential. He stated that the Ministry had approved the scheme which he had already&quot; outlined (vide Report No. 41), and they were prepared to put it into operation at once. Mr. Hughes stated that the Commonwealth war expenditure was 80,0l)0,000Z. per annum of borrowed money, and in discussing the effect of the war upon local industry, he said two things were necessary to meet the reversion to peace con-ditions : (1) that the Commonwealth must economise by organisation, and (2) that the Commonwealth must secure home markets and develop oArersea trade. He added that no scheme could succeed without the co-operation of labour, and that the effective organisation of industry was as essential to the welfare of labour as of capital. Referring to the Associations which would represent the industries and would elect a Council having a permanent Secretary, with branch secretaries in the various States, to advise on the circumstances of particular industries [vide Report No. 41), he stated that the Council would also deal with export trade and consider the best markets, &amp;c, for Australian products. It would act through the Department of Commerce and Industry, which would have trade representatives in foreign countries. The Department of  Commerce and Industry  would  be  the  link  between the
Associations and the Government, and in conjunction with the general Council of the Associations, would shape the policy for expanding trade, improving methods, and establishing new industries.With   regard to finance, the Prime  Minister stated that something  approxi-&apos;mating to German methods of financing industry must be achieved, and he again declared that the credit of the Commonwealth would he behind approved enterprises. A conference of Associations interested will be held immediately to discuss details.Australians and English Wives.- With reference to the statement appearing in a recent Report (No. 54) as to the marriages between members of the Australian Imperial Force and English women, the Commonwealth Government have now in operation a scheme providing for free passages to Australia, not only for the relatives of soldiers who are discharged in Australia and who cannot afford to pay the necessary passage money, But also for women to whom such/soldiers have become engaged in England.The repatriation passages are provided in the following order: (a) Widows and orphans of discharged members of the Australian Imperial Forces.(o) Wives and children  of returned  members   of   the Australian Imperial Forces.(c) Fiancees of returned members of the Australian Imperial Forces.The above regulations were brought into force by reason of the fact that numerous marriages and arrangements for marriage had taken place between Australian soldiers and English women, and there was no provision, in cases where the persons were impecunious, for enabling the women to reach their husbands, or prospective husbands, in Australia. The latest arrangements made by the Commonwealth have superseded those which were in force under the State of New South Wales. . The latter provided only for reduced rates for the relatives of discharged soldiers.Settlement of Soldiers on the Land. The Minister of Repatriation (Senator Milieu), in reply to recent criticisms, has stated that a Board of Control, composed of men of commercial and military experience, is already working as a Repatriation Commission, and that the training in agricultural schools of returned soldiers who are desirous of settling on the laud has been arranged.The Minister for Lands in Victoria has stated that the Government policy is to form model villages in various, parts of Victoria, and to place there 12 or 10 soldiers. Those who are in possession of a considerable amount of land are being asked by the Government to take returned soldiers as share-farmers.Soldiers and. Intoxicants. Giving evidence before a Select Committee of the Senate regarding the sale of intoxicating liquors to soldiers, the Acting Commandant stated that while drink had something to do with desertions, there was not much loss of efficiency even amongst those given to immoderate drinking. He stated that the drink ha bit was declining among the younger men.The Commonwealth and Queensland. During the recent visit of the Prime Minister to Brisbane considerable disorder took place, as a result of which some questions of constitutional significance arose between the Commonwealth and the State. Mr. Hughes accused the State authorities of endeavouring to prevent the voice of the Government being heard, and he asserted V ao far from assisting to preserve order, the police actually connived at the assault on me and lent their aid to it.&quot; As a result of this, the Prime Minister pointed out to the Premier of the State of Queensland that the laws of the Commonwealth override those of the State, and he observed that the officer in charge of the police had refused to accept his direction to prosecute the men creating the disturbance under the Commonwealth law, on the ground that he recognised the laws of Queensland only. Mr. Hughes therefore called upon the Queensland Premier to suspend this officer from dul/v, and he added &quot; unless &quot; this is done forthwith the Commonwealth Government Avill take steps to enforce its &quot; own laws and will hold you responsible for any breaches of such laws.&quot;Elections in Queensland. The Governor dissolved the State Parliament of Queens-land owing to effluxion of.time.   The General Election will be held on March 16th.New Governor of Neiv South Wales. The new Governor of New South Wales (Sir V7. Davidson) has reported that on February 1.8th he assumed office and received a cordial welcome.
NEW ZEALAND.Next Session of Parliament. The - next Session oil Parliament -will be opened on the 9th April, and will be a short one in order to allow Mr. Massey and Sir Joseph Ward to leave in such time as to enable them to arrive in England for- the Session of the Imperial Cabinet. There will be no Budget presented in this short Session of the Dominion Parliament.Revenue Returns. The Revenue returns of the Dominion for the last 10 months show a promise of a sidjstantial surplus being realised. The Land and Income Taxes already collected amount to nearly 6,000,000/,, but the revenues from Customs and Railway Departments, as anticipated, show a considerable decrease.Aeroplanes in. Peace. The Minister of Finance (Sir Joseph Ward) in the course of a recent speech stated- that after the war aeroplanes will be very largely used for carrying mails in New Zealand, and that motor lorries will be employed to link up the small settlements with the railways.Returned Soldiers and Gallipoli Star.-The dissatisfaction amongst returned soldiers in the Dominion with regard to the award of the Gallipoli Star is apparently based on the belief that the conditions of the award are unfair, and it is stated on their behalf that it would be impossible to make conditions which would not be unfair unless the Star were to be given to everybody who ever bore arms in Gallipoli. It is pointed out that the present arrangements reserve the decoration for the main ho&amp;y and the first and second reinforcements, excluding some who landed on April 25th and very many who served lor mouths oh Gallipoli, and excluding also those who went to Samoa, and then on to Gallipoli, without going out of uniform. Steps have been taken to inform the authorities in New Zealand of the strong feeling in the New Zealand Expeditionary Force in support of the views of the Returned Soldiers&apos; Association in New Zealand.Glubs for Returned Soldiers. lire Dominion Cabinet have given their approval to a scheme for the erection of clubs for returned soldiers at Auckland and Dunedin.SOUTH AFRICA.introduction of Budget. The Minister of Finance (Mr. Orr) introduced the Budget into the House of Assembly on February 15th. From this it appeared that the estimated revenue for the financial year 1917-18 amounted to 19,-109,000^., which exceeded the original estimate. The revised expenditure is estimated at 18,945,000/. Both Customs and Inland Revenue exceeded the estimate by substantial amounts, and the Minister stated that the increased expenditure was almost entirely due to war conditions.Woman Prauchise.-A. motion in favour of incorporating in the Electoral Bill a clause extending the franchise to women was proposed in the House of Assembly on February 12th, but was rejected by 54 votes to 39.Nationalists and Returned Soldiers. The question of settling returned soldiers on the land was again discussed in the House of Assembly on the additional estimates for 1917-18. The position adopted by the Nationalists was that no preference should be given to returned soldiers over others, and especially that no discrimination in their favour should be made over ex-Republicans who fought in the Boer .War. The Acting Minister of Defence (Colonel Mentz) declined to withdraw the arrangement giving preference to returned soldiers.over other applicants, and it was pointed out in the course of the discussion that the matter was in the hands of the Land Boards. The proposals of the Government were agreed to by 59 votes to .19.Amount of Wool Available. The Governor-General has informed the British Government that it is now found that 133,013 bales of wool will be available under the scheme for sale by the farmers to the British Government, the number of bales withdrawn being 57,65b (vide Report No. 55).-1-9S5-3a 3
Production of Glycerine. The Union Ministers have informed the British Government that the utilisation of ilihihbriia sulphate for the production of glycerine by the present known process would involve.a delay of about six months in erecting the&apos; necessary plant. The Ministers have asked, therefore, whether aii alternative process; which they understand is nOw employed by Messrs. Brhniier, Monti &amp; Co... can be cotumunicated to the Moderfoitteiii Factory by telegraph, as it is of the utmost -importance to relieve the difficulties connected with thc\glyeerihe position by an. early production of ammonium nitrate.Natives- as Hospital &apos;0i:dtiHhs.-Th% Uiiioii Govgrhrneht have informed the British Government that, owing to the decision to stop recruiting lor the Native .Labour Cbntingent in South Africa, all the/natives who were in training as hospital orderlies have been discharged; It is therefore suggested that the Army Council should select men for these duties from those who are now serving in &quot;France, and should train tfieiri at the native base lidsjhtal, instead of recruiting and training mote men in the I iiioihLGERMAN EAST AFRICA.Civil Control: The Administrator df German East Africa has telegraphed that lie received on the 13th February a proclamation by the Ooimuander-iii-Chief promulgated on January 31st applying the present civil administration as from the 1st March to the central and southern areas.- The Administrator points out that lie had not been consulted as to the terms of this Proclamation, and he has been obliged to inform the Coniniamler-iii-(Jhicf that his consent at the Nairobi Conference to the extension of civil control was dependent on the transfer of the civil headquarters to Dar-es-Salaain, as experience showed the impracticability of administering a largely extended area from the present situation.- As it has been found impossible to find accommodation at Dar-es-Salaam, the Administrator lias been obliged to withdraw the Proclamation and to postpone the transfer of the extended area to civil control.Progress of Military Forces. General Northey reported on the&apos; 1.3th February that Mtarika had&quot; been occupied by the Second Cape Corps who dislodged the enemy after some opposition. The whole area west of the Lujenda river is now clear of the enemy, who. have retired east and south-east out of the reach of the British, who have now reached the limit at which, for the present, they can receive supplies.PORTUGUESE  EAST  AFRICA.   .Biiiirtntmenl of Garfiefi. The Governor of Nyassaland has telegraphed I hat the fe^urtrhent of carriers-, iii Portuguese Angonilaud has proved unsuccessful through the local officials advising the natives that service was optional. Apart from their unwillingness to help, the local officials, it is reported, are afraid to use pressure on the ground&quot; that the. natives, who are in fact assisting, the Germans, may revolt. The British Minister in Lisbon has been instructed to take action in the matter.
APPENDIXTOWestern and General Report No. 58.  Part I.THE BLOCKADE AND THE &quot; FREEDOM OF THE SEAS.&quot;In the paper on the &quot; Freedom of the Seas &quot; attached as an Appendix to the Western and General Report No. 52, Part I., one of the reasons for Great Britain s -attitude towards this question in time of war is given in the following&apos;words : &quot; To hold in reserve an economic weapon for tise in extreme emergencies against predatory continental Emperors, like the Kaiser, who try to dominate the whole of Europe.&quot;The attached extracts from a report prepared in the War Trade Intelligence Department are of interest in this connection. The question is of course a relative one ; it is a question not only of putting economic pressure upon the enemy, but also -of avoiding measures likely to react more- strongly upon our own economic position.February 20th, 1918. G. G. A.1. Until recently the enemy&apos;s insistence on the &quot;freedom of  the seas&quot;  was regarded in this country with mingled perplexity and amusement.   But high-sounding generalities are dangerous ; and, as the full significance of the phrase is being slowly dragged to light, it is apparent that a doctrine -which seemed at first to be a mere truism has developed into a potential menace to the maritime supremacy of this country and to all the advantages, political, strategic and economic, which flow from that supremacy. ......president Wilson has defined the &quot; freedom of the seas &quot; as absolute freedom of navigation in peace and war outside territorial waters, subject, nevertheless, to closure of the seas for police purposes by international action. He meant, presumably, that in time of war neutral vessels should be immune from search &quot;So long as they remained outside the zone of an effective physical blockade ; though whether this immunity is to extend to enemy vessels is not clear. Count Czernin gave his full support to the -doctrine, and seems especially to have welcomed the words &quot; outside territorial waters &quot; as constituting a pledge of non-interference with Turkey&apos;s sovereign rights OA-er the Dardanelles. Count Hertling accepted the doctrine of free navigation, but rejected the &quot; police &quot; c[ualification, which he characterised as &quot;not quite intelligible and apparently superfluous,&quot; adding that it would be &quot;highly important for the&quot; freedom of shipping in the future &quot; if Great Britain renounced her outlying naval-bases. Probably both Count Hertling and Count Czernin were deliberately taking the &quot; freedom of the seas &quot; in its widest rjossible significance as conferring upon a belligerent the unrestricted right of maintaining his vessels and his commerce upon the high seas.At present, neither the enemy nor the neutral Press appears to throw much further light upon the question. But it is worth noting that the Danish Social-demokralen a paper closely connected -with the German Government Socialists  welcomes President Wilson&apos;s enunciation of the freedom of the seas in peace and war as being just the claim which Germany herself has declared to be her principal object in the way, and regards England&apos;s waiver (sic) of her right to make prizes, which is the main pillar of her superiority in war and the basis of her world dominion in peace, as one of the most important events iir the war. &quot;Germany,&quot; says the writer, &quot;has at last burst the fetters which her geographical position has imposed on her enterprise and her desire of expansion and -activity &quot; (Socialdemokraten, 10th January 1918).4985-3a C
Thus, while much is obscure, it is at least plain that the question is far from being academic.2. The right in time of peace to navigate freely the seas outside territorial waters is fully recognised. Probably there are: few who would challenge the corollary that in time of peace, subject to compliance with the municipal laws of the visited country, and subject to any limitations imposed as a condition of peace, vessels of any.nationality have the right morally, if not legally, of resorting to the ports of another country for the purpose of loading and discharging cargo, undergoing repairs, and receiving bunkers and supplies. But Count Her fling goes bevond . this, and throws, out a hint that every nation should be compelled to internationalise its outlying coaling stations. In other words, one of the mainstays of the British command of the sea is to be cut away ; the possibility of economic retaliation or pressure by control of bunker supplies is to be denied us; and in the race for&apos; oversea commercial expansion which peace will inevitably bring Germany is to start level with Great Britain. What can the enemy offer us by way of compensation for this surrender&apos;?o. In time of war a belligerent in seeking to deprive his enemy of the &quot;freedom of the seas &quot; has two objects in view : (a) the direct strategic or tactical object of destrov-ing or impeding the enemy&apos;s combatant vessels and of cutting his military communications ; and (b) the indirect strategic object of depleting the enemy&apos;s resources by seizure of his non-combatant vessels, by curtailment of his supplies and by general disorganisation of his trade. The distinction between the two objects is not hard and fast (for instance, the seizure of a cargo of copper bound for an eiiemy port may have military consequences as direct as the destruction of a munition factory by aircraft), but for the purpose of a wide survey it will suffice.4. The relation of the new doctrine of the &quot; freedom of the seas &quot; to the direct strategic or tactical aims of naval warfare is a matter upon which experts on naval strategy in its widest aspect are alone competent to express an opinion. There appear to be three main questions involved, viz. : (a) the strategic effect of the permanent neutralisation of outlying naval bases ; (b) the effect of submarine development upon sea-power; and (c) the right to proclaim barred zones in the open sea?!5. The relation of the doctrine to the indirect strategic aims of naval warfare cannot be determined without an amplified statement of the doctrine itself. President Wilsoids saving clause that in time of war the seas might be policed by international action depends both for its efficacy and its deterrent force upon the. powers entrusted to the &quot; police &quot;x; and it is probable that an attempt to define these powers would prove as fruitful of controversy as anything contained in the Declaration of Paris or the Declaration of London. Nevertheless the prospect of this controversy must be faced : and it is therefore pertinent to examine briefly the scope and effect in the present, war of the group of operations&apos; popularly known as &quot;the Blockade.&quot; Our concessions can only be formulated in the light of our achievements.G. The blockade and its ancillary operations, regarded not merely as a means of preventing supplies from reaching the enemy- but in their wider aspect of a retaliatory attack upon enemy trade and enemy resources wherever found, may be classified roughly as follows : (a) Seizure or sequestration of enemy vessels lying in Allied harbours or inter-cepted on the high seas.(b) Seizure or sequestration of enemy-owned goods lying in Allied harbours orintercepted on the high seas.(c) Seizure of neutral vessels carrying contraband or conditional contraband to theenemy.(d) Seizure of contraband or conditional contraband, and sequestration of non-contraband goods, destined for the enemy without regard to the nationality of the carrying vessel. -(e) Sequestration of all enemy, exports without regard to the nationality of the carrying vessel.(/) By economic barter, purchase, or otherwise, preventing the &quot; border neutrals &apos;&apos; from supplying their native products to the enemy.1 Also upon the nature and upon the nationality of such :i police &quot; forces. Or. Gr. A.
(g) Stoppage of the enemyks commercial and financial activities in every part of the world by means of (i) Censorship of cables and letters.(ii) Black-listing of enemy firms or neutral firms  acting in enemy interests.(hi) Conditions against carrying enemy goods imposed upon neutral vessels as a term of the grant of British-controlled bunkers.7. With these weapons what has been achieved? Difficult as it is to pierce the veil which shrouds the real economic conditions in enemy countries and to draw true inferences from facts which are often isolated and sometimes contradictory, the following conclusions may be stated with some confidence :  (a) For the past two years the populations of Germany, Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria,and Turkey (aggregating about 135,000,000) have suffered from insufficient sustenance. Naturally, conditions have varied in different countries and even in different districts of the same country. But on the whole there has been acute hardship, in many cases approaching and in some cases even reaching actual starvation; the death-rate rises while the birth-rate falls ; tuberculosis is increasing; diseases of malnutrition such as typhus and dysentery have taken a heavy toll ; serious food riots have occurred. It seems clear that the German and Austrian troops in the depots and reserve stations are underfed, and there have been severakindications that the rations for the troops in the trenches are inadequate. Moreover, that Germany has at last been driven to elect between the provisiomuent of her armies and the maintenance of her civil population is indicated by two reports received quite recently from independent sources each stating that German doctors, officially prompted, had refused certiiicates for extra food to men over 50 on the ground that they were &quot; functi offlcio.&quot;(b) The civil populations of enemy territories are experiencing an acute shortageof clothing and the necessaries of life other than foodstuffs. The equipment of the troops is noticeably inferior in quality. For the present it appears adequate in quantity, though both the German and the Austrian commands have more than, once issued orders emphasising the imminent prospect of shortage.(c) In Germany (and presumably in Austria as well) the efficiency and output ofthe workers in coal mines, munition works and other factories is substantially reduced by bad food conditions. This reacts in turn upon the man-power question.(d) There is evidence that shortage of raw material is affecting both the quantity and quality of the German munition output. Unfortunately the evidence is not conclusive. That there is a serious shortage of certain rare metals, and a wholly inadequate supply of such materials as leather, is indisputable ; but the Germans have displaj^ed great ingenuity in the use of substitutes.  .(e) The enemy can no longer rely upon the Border Neutrals as bases of supply.The re-export by those neutrals to the enemy of goods imported through the blockade has been completely stopped for close upon, two years. Their export of native products to the enemy has been considerably curtailed in 1917, and with the aid of the United States strenuous efforts are being made to effect a still greater reduction. (/) Germany&apos;s foreign trade has virtually ceased to exist ; her commercial houses in every corner of the world are slowly but surely atrophising ; her financial resources for the prosecution of the war are depleted accordingly ; and her stocks of raw material for post-bellum recuperation are steadily shrinking. The feeling in German trade circles is indicated by the following-extract from a speech delivered in December 1917 by Dr. Otto Brandt, the Secretary of the Dusseldorf Chamber of Commerce1 : &quot; The most serious injury which w7e have suffered owing to the war is the destruction of our foreign trade a strong expression, but we may employ it to-day. After the Avar we shall find the world s market in a totally different position from pre-war days. Not only have we almost entirely lost the political and commercial props of our foreign trade, and with them a large proportion of our customers ; not only will hate and a1 See Keports from Foreign Press.   Reconstruction. Supplement, 1st January 1918.
secret economic war block tbe roads for us in peace times and the scarcity of cargo space impede transport ; but, above all else, tlie receptivity of many countries has suffered owing to the war, many new competitors in industry have made their appearance, and the United States and Japan have attained a far more important position as competitors in the world&apos;s markets than heretofore.&quot; (g) Of Germany&apos;s mercantile marine, about 50 per cent, has been destroyed or has passed into the service of the Allies.   The remaining 50 per cent, (with the exception of a few vessels employed in the Baltic) is immobilised in neutral or German harbours.(//) Thanks to the blockade and its ancillary measures (including especiallv control of bunker supply) the Allies have secured already a large proportion of neutral tonnage, and it is hoped shortly to secure all the Norwegian, Swedish, Danish and Dutch tonnage which remains after providing feu- the minimum import requirements of these countries. This accpusition of tonnage at a critical juncture will be invaluable.( ) The value of ships and cargoes seized by Great Britain is over 30,000,000?,, though it does not follow that all these will be condemned.8. Broadly stated, these are the principal results of the blockade in its widest aspect, AVhether it could have been made more effective ; whether it would have -ended the war but for military setbacks (it is well known, for instance, that from May 1917 till the new&apos; harvest Vienna lived from hand to mouth on imported Rumanian grain, and that without the Galician and Rumanian oil-fields the enemy&apos;s position as to oil and lubricants was almost desperate) ; whether termination of the war by the blockade alone would have been politically prudent; whether (as some think) the blockade is now our only means of victory ; whether the Russian debacle has deprived us of that means also all these are speculative questions capable of a diversity of answers. But the essential fact remains that the blockade with its kindred operations has sapped the vigour of the enemy peoples, has weakened their financial resources, has killed their hope of speedy economic recuperation, and has to some extent impaired the efficacy of their fighting machine. These results are prone to be over-looked just because thej^ are incalculable. But they are all results which might, and probably would, have been sacrificed if our sea power had been hampered by any doctrine of the &quot;freedom of the seas &quot; and if we had not acted on the knowledge that &quot;in time of Avar, betwixt kings, it is lawful for the one party to intercept the assistance &quot; and succours sent to the other, and to take care that no damage may grow thereby &quot; to himself.&quot;9. Moreover, is there not a fallacy underlying President Wilsoids statement of the doctrine of the &quot; freedom of the seas&quot;? If the League of Nations with its inter-national police is to be an effective guardian of the world&apos;s peace, is it not a work of supererogation to formulate rules of icar as conducted under the auspices of the League ? Inability to prevent war implies a breakdown of the League with a consecpient reversion to individual belligerent methods. This being so, the rules of warfare for the future (if their definition be worth the trouble) should represent, as they have done in tbe past, a compromise between the powers and needs of competing states rather than an attempt to conform with the ideal standard of a League which ex hypotliesi will have failed of its purpose if war breaks out. And we should on no account be ensnared by the lofty concept of the&apos;League of Nations into concessions which we are not prepared to stand by in the capacity of independent belligerents.10. In conclusion, it should be borne in mind that any abstract enunciation of the &quot;freedom of the seas&quot; will give rise in turn to a kindred and perhaps more difficult question &quot; the freedom of the air.&quot; An air base will become as vital strategically and economically as a sea base ; the problems of air traffic and sea traffic present many common features and should be considered pari passu for times both of peace and war.War Trade Intelligence Department, February 14th, 1918.0. R, A. S.

</content>
</cab>
