<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/151/0 images: 122-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.APPRECIATION Ob&quot; THE ATTACHED WESTERN AND GENERALREPORT No. 61.PAST I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE AND AFRICA.Canada.The statement made in Parliament on behalf of the French-Canadians about the success of British arms indicates that, as in the past, the realisation of a common danger does more than anything else to weld together the diverse elements in the British Empire.The appointment of a Minister for External Affairs is one more proof of the growing magnitude of Canadian interests outside her own shores.The Government has taken prompt measures to avert Labour troubles in the shipbuilding world.The terms upon which the franchise is to be extended to women in the Dominion, and the attitude adopted by various sections of the community towards the bestowal of hereditary honours, merit attention.Australian Common wealth.The Commonwealth Government has decided to raise the Pacific question at the forthcoming gathering of the Empire Statesmen in London. This Avill furnish an opportunity for the presentation and discussion of the Dominion point of view.The decision of the Prime Minister to reconstruct his Cabinet and add fresh blood to it should serve to strengthen the Administration.The general attitude of Official Labour towards the visit of Mr. Hughes to England should be noted. The fear of any surrender of Australians self-governing powers was no doubt one of the reasons for the suggestion that Mr. Tudor- should accompany Mr. Hughes to London.Other matters deserving attention under this heading include the suggestion to extend the powers of the Commonwealth, the statement by the new Treasurer, the progress made towards the organisation of industry, and the action taken in relation to Irish disloyalists in the Commonwealth.New Zealand.The figure relating to the amount spent on the war is of interest and importance;
when it is remembered that the Dominion community consists of only a little over one-million inhabitants.The statement about the operations of the Wolf in the Pacific contains some points &quot;which deserve attention.South Africa.As &quot;might be expected, the Nationalists have made the most of the Allied decision to requisition Dutch shipping. The Prime mini steps reply was singularly effective ; Mr. Burton&apos;s challenge to the Nationalists as to German South-West Africa was particularly appropriate.The telegram from the Union Ministers about facilities in South Africa for the production of glycerine is important.German Africa.The report on the desire of the natives of Togoland for British rule furnishes valuable additional evidence of the superiority of British methods of native administration.G. G. A.March 28th, 1918.
&apos;xs?     is[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestv&apos;s Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet. ggSECRET. For Reference only.WESTERN   AND   GENERAL  REPORT.No. 61.   Week ending 21th March 1918 (night).PART I. BRITISH EMPIRE AND AFRICA. Contents.Imperial Affairs.Naval co-operation with United States.Canada.Canada and operations at the Front. Quebec and British victory. Prayers for victorj-. Minister for External Affairs. The work of the new Parliament. Woman Suffrage Bill.. Women and seats in Parliament. Opposition and Deputy Speaker. Estimates for the year. Staff of Army headquarters. Shipbuilding Conference. Military Service Convention. Hereditary honours. Quebec and farm labour.Australian Commonwealth.Imperial War Cabinet and Conference.   Reconstruction of the Cabinet.   Labour organisations and -  Mr. Hughes.   German Pacific Colonies.   Financial arrangements.   Sinn Peinism in the Common-wealth.   Australian Natives&apos; Association and conscription.   Extension of Commonwealth Powers. Prisoners of war.  Organisation of industry.   New Victorian Ministry.   Australian administration of the Pacific Islands.New Zealand.Amount spent on the War.   The Wolf in the Pacific.    German Colonies in the Pacific. South Africa.The Nationalists and Dutch shipping-, &amp;c.: attack on General Botha. Glycerine production. Government and mining leases.Portuguese East Africa.Recruiting of carriers.Togoland.Natives and British rule.(33)5257-4a   Pic100   3/18   B &amp; S
PART   I.-BRITISH  EMPIRE   AND   AFRICA.IMPERIAL AFFAIRS.Naval Co-operation with United States. The Governments of Canada and Newfoundland have been informed of an arrangement made with the United States for the co-ordination of plans and operations between the British and United States Naval Services on the Western side of the Atlantic, particularly in connection with convoys. Under the system arranged, the Naval Oommander-in-Chief will be stationed at Washington, but he will probably visit Ottawa from time to time.CANADA.Canada and Operations at the Front. The Prime Minister (Sir R. Borderi) announced in Parliament that he had received a cable from the Minister of Overseas Military Forces to the effect that the Canadians were not at present involved in the operations, which were taking place south of the line held by them.Quebec and British, Victory. Following on the statement by the Prime Minister in the Dominion House of Commons as to the course of events at the front in France, a statement was made by Mr. Lucien Cannon, on behalf of the French-Canadian Members, which is all the more remarkable when the controversy at the Dorchester by-election at the beginning of last year is remembered concerning Mr. Cannons observation as to ruining Canada &quot; from the point of view of men and wealth and everything else, for England.&quot; Speaking in the House of Commons this week, Mr. Cannon said : &quot; We are just as much in favour of the triumph of the Allies as &quot; are those on the other side of the House. The war causes us as much anxiety as it &quot; does our friends opposite. Every day prayers go up from the heart of Quebec &quot; for the victory of the British flag the flag which gave Quebec its liberty.&quot;Prayers for Victory. Special intercessory services have been held in nearly all the churches throughout the Dominion, the congregations praying for the success of the Allied arms. In Quebec, all the Roman Catholic churches, under the direction of Cardinal Begin, held special services, his Eminence asking the priests to exhort the parishioners to prayer and penitence in order that the Allies might attain victory and peace.     -Minister for External Affairs. The Dominion Government have given notice in Parliament of their intention to make provision for a new department to deal with external affairs, the head of which will be entitled Secretary of State for External Affairs.    The Minister will receive a salary of $5,000.The Work of the New IJarliament. The Dominion House of Commons concluded the Debate on the Address unexpectedly the day after the opening of Parliament. Amongst the Bills alreadv introduced have been those relating to Woman Franchise and Daylight Saving. Both of these measures have been accorded a first reading, but the latter is meeting with opposition from those representing farming interests, on the ground that it will hamper product ion.Woman Suffrage Bill. The provisions of the Woman Suffrage Bill introduced into Parliament will extend the vote to every female person who is a British subject of 21 years and upwards, who has resided in the constituency concerned for at least three months, and who is not disqualified b)r race or original nationality to vote for members of the Provincial Parliaments. The franchise is not extended to the wives of alien enemies. When moving the Second Reading of the Bill, the Prime Minister said that the Government felt that women were entitled to the vote on their merits, and in granting the privilege the intention was to cany out the same principles as those which now prevailed regarding votes for men.
Women and Seats in Parliament. A proposal to extend to women the right to sit in the Ontario Legislature has been introduced into the Legislature, and having been ojuposed by the Government, has been rejected.Opposition and Deputy Speaker. In accordance with the traditional practice of the Dominion House of Commons that the Speaker and his Deputy must respectively represent the French and English sections of the&apos;House, a member of the. Oj)position (Mr. Boivin) has been elected Deputy Speaker,.on the proposal of the Prime Minister, seconded by the Minister of Trade and Commerce (Sir George Foster), and supported by the Leader of the Opposition. The only French-Canadian member in the Government ranks (Dr. Chabot) had previously declined to accept the position, and the Government were, therefore, obliged to select a representative from the Opposition.Estimates for the Year. The Acting Minister of Finauce (Mr. A. K. Maclean) has declared in the House of Commons that the main estimates for the fiscal year commencing April 1st next amount to a total of 8252,795,097. This shows a decrease of about two million dollars compared with the estimates of the year about to close.Staff of Army Headquarters. The Minister of Overseas Military Forces has reported to the Dominion Cabinet as to the composition of the Staff of Officers and men employed at the Canadian Army Headquarters in London. This shows that of 76 officers and 209 other ranks employed. 55 officers and 128 other ranks have seen service in the field.Shipbuilding Conference. A. conference has been called by the Minister of Labour (Mr. T. W. Crothers) which will, be attended by representatives of shipbuilding companies, who are controlling yards situated between Port Arthur and the Atlantic Coast, and also by representatives of all trades engaged in ship construction, in order that an arrangement may be reached with the men as to wages and working conditions. The object of the Minister is to prevent the Government^ programme of construction being interfered with later on by labour disputes.Military Service Convention. The British, Canadian and American draft treaties regarding military service (vide Reports Nos. 51, 52, 54, 56, 57) have been returned to the State Department by the United States Senate for certain changes to be made before ratification. Amendments have been made which have the effect of exempting Irishmen and Australians in the United States from the Convention, by providing that the treaties shall not apply to men who are not subject to conscription in their own countries.Hereditary Honours. Notice of a motion in the House of Commons has been given by Mr. Fielding (who was formerly Minister of Finance under Sir Wilfrid Laurier, and who is now a supporter of the Union Government) to the effect that hereditary titles should not be granted in Canada. A resolution on the same subject is also to be proposed by Mr. W. F. Nickle, and this states that hereditary titles should be prohibited, and that if any further titles are granted, the wb-es of the recipients should not be recognised.The British Columbian Legislature has unanimously agreed to. a motion, without debate, which declares against the grant of hereditary titles in Canada.Quebec and Farm Labour. The Quebec Provincial Agricultural Board have recommended that, in order to release students for farm work, all colleges and schools should close from Mav to October.AUSTRALIAN COMMONWEALTH.Imperial War Cabinet and Conference. The Commonwealth Government were recently informed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies that the Imperial War Cabinet at the forthcoming meetings would presumably deal with cptestions relating to the conduct of the war and terms of peace, and that the Imperial War Conference would deal with questions which mainly affected policy after the war, especially of an
economic nature. The Commonwealth were therefore invited to notify the British Government as to any desires they might have with regard to raising any special economic questions. In reply, the Prime Minister of the Commonwealth has telegraphed that the Commonwealth Government desire to raise the Pacific question; post-war problems, including Imperial trade and tariffs ; the constitution of the. Privy Council and the representation of the Dominions upon it. It is intimated that information as to any further subjects that the Commonwealth Government may desire to raise will be telegraphed later.Reconstruction of the Cabinet. Owing to the resignation of Lord Forrest from the post of Commonwealth Treasurer on the ground of ill-health, the Cabinet is under-going some reconstruction. The new Treasurer will be Mr. Watt, who has hitherto been Minister for Works and Railways, and the last-named office will be filled by Mr. Littleton Groom. Amongst, the new Ministers who have already been sworn in as Members of the Commonwealth Government are Mr. G. If. Wise, Mr. Massy Greene and Mr. Poynton. It is probable that these gentlemen will not all receive permanent appointments, but positions of a temporary character during Mr. Hughes&apos; absence in England. It is anticipated that the Minister of Customs (Mr. Jensen) will be transferred, to another office and that the Minister of Defence (Mr. Pearce) will retire. Many Australian Press organs are demanding Mr. Pearce&apos;s retirement on account of the recent strictures by the Royal Commission upon the efficiency of the Defence Department (vide Report No. 57); the second Report of the Commission commented severely on the chaotic condition of the accounts. Meantime four business men have been appointed as the Business Board to deal with the working of the Defence Department on economical and efficient lines.Labour Organisations and Mr. Hughes. Some of the Labour organisations in several of the States of Australia have passed resolutions declaring that Mr. Hughes in not an appropriate representative of the Commonwealth at the forthcoming meetings of the Imperial War Cabinet in London. This action on the part of Official Labour should be considered in connection with the demand that the Leader of the Opposition (Mr. Tudor) should accompany Mr. Hughes to London (vide Report No. 59). The attitude of the&apos; Official Labour Party in connection with the representation of Australia at meetings in London was shown in Appendix to Report No. 59 to be based on the fear that some curtailment of Australian self-governing powers might take place ; and therefore that &quot; decisions affecting the Commonwealth should be submitted to the .Federal Parliament for ratification.&quot;German Pacific Colonies. The Australian Associated Chambers of Commerce, at a meeting in Melbourne, have jessed a Resolution in favour of retaining the captured territory in the Pacific,Financial Arrangements. The new Treasurer (Mr. W att) in a speech last week, declared that Australia had muddled her man-power, but that she must not muddle her financial propositions. He pointed out that the bank deposits from September 1914 to September 1917 had increased by 61,000,000?. and that the Banks were relatively stronger by 56,000,000/. In calling attention to the fact that Great Britain had lent the Dominions 180,000,000/., Mr. Watt said this was unexampled generosity. &quot; Australia,&quot; he announced, &quot; must now have 40,000,000/., if not voluntarily from the people, then taxation must be heavier.&quot; He mentioned that the women of Australia were spending far too much money, which ought to be invested in War Bonds.Sinn Feinism in the Commonwealth: A deputation of over 3,000 persons waited upon the Lord Mayor of Melbourne last week to protest against a display of disloyal flags at the St. Patrick&apos;s Day procession, and the general   attitude of Mgr. Mannix, who was described as an arch-traitor. After carrying a motion asking the Federal Government to prevent the display of enemy flags, the deputation proceeded to the Prime Minister, where a leading Roman Catholic, presented the Resolution and stated that the meeting desired that Dr. Mannix should be prosecuted under the War Pre-cautions Act. In reply, Mr. Hughes said that &quot; one flag only can float in Australia as emblematic of the country, viz. : the Union Jack.&quot; He agreed, that the matter was of the first importance and could not be evaded, and declared &quot; it shall be settled.&quot; He added, &quot; I have always been in favour of Home Rule for Ireland, but am a determined &quot; enemy of any attempt at settlement on the fantastic futile lines set up by Sinn Fein *&apos; adherents.&quot;
NEW ZEALAND.Amount spent on the War. The amount spent by the Dominion upon the war, inclusive of amounts allocated to relief purposes connected with the war, up to the present time totals 38,500,000L Additional liabilities have been incurred amounting to six and half millions. The loans raised by the Dominion during the Avar reach a total of nearly 28,0OO,O00Z.The Wolf in the Pacific. In a personal report which has recently been made by the Chief Officer of the Wairuna. to the High Commissioner for New Zealand with regard to the capture of this aTessel by the German Wolf, it is stated that the German ship Avas challenged by the Avenger when coming out from GermanAr via the Baltic, but that word was not sent to the Pacific that the German vessel was at large. It is alleged that the Wolf went to the coast of NeAv Zealand and laid some mines betAveen the Three Kings and the North Cape and others in Cook Straits. As to her taking the Wairuna, the Chief Officer stated that his a*essel happened to go close to the Ivermadec Islands AAdiere the Germans were cleaning up their engines, and they immediately sent up a seaplane after her which sAvept doAvn close to the deck and dropped a paper to say that if they did not stop they would! be bombed. They stopped, and then the Germans Avho were down almost to their last lb. of coal and had very little precisions left, unwed 1,200 tons of the finest New Zealand coal from the Wairuna as well as large quantities of stores. The Second Officer of the Wairuna stated that there ought to be definite instructions given to the Captain of each ship regarding his line of action when falling into enemy hands. In this case the Germans chaffed the British for not having scuttled their ship.5257 4a. BAustralian Natives&apos; Association and Conscription. At the Annual Conference of the Australian Natives&apos; Association last week a proposal that the Association should&apos; not support conscription was defeated.Extension of Commonwealth Powers. At the Australian Natives&apos; Association Conference, a Resolution was carried stating that the time has arrived tor the extension of the powers of the Commonwealth on lines similar to those adopted in Canada and South Africa.Prisoners of War. The Commonwealth Government have informed the British authorities that letters received from Australian prisoners of war which have been sent to Switzerland from Germany show that the correspondence of prisoners in Germany is destroyed, and that the contents of parcels are frequently appropriated by the guards,   it is stated that further details can be furnished to the War Office.Organisation of Industry. The Australian Associated Chamber of Commerce at their Fifteenth Annual Conference have approved the Prime MiuistsPs scheme for the organisation of industry, and have appointed five representatives to serve on the temporary General Council (vide Reports Nos. 58 and 60).New Victorian Ministry. The new Premier (Mr. Lawson) has succeeded in uniting the two wings of the Liberal Part)&apos; in Victoria (vide Report No. 60), and has formed a Ministry which is representative of the.consolidated Liberal Part)&quot;.Australian Administration of the Pacific Islands. In a recent article ou the Pacific and its political settlement, Sir William McGregor (ex-Governor of Queensland) makes the following interesting observations : &quot; Assuming that it is proposed that &quot; Eastern New Guinea, the Bismarck Archipelago and the Solomon Islands, with the &quot; smaller groups connected with them south of the equator, should be administered &quot; by the Commonwealth, this would mean an area of some 200,000 square miles, and &quot; probably 800,000 natives ; and then the veiy pertinent question arises : Can these &quot; territories, with due regard to the interests of the aboriginal inhabitants, be safely &quot; entrusted to Australia? I confess frankly that SO or more years ago I should have &quot; answered unhesitatingly and emphatically, &apos; No.&apos; Circumstances have greatly &quot; changed, and so has my deliberate opinion. That the Commonwealth knows how &quot; to govern the islands is demonstrated by the case of Papua . . . The Papuan &quot; is to-day as secure in his land, as safe in his freedom, as well protected from &quot; alcohol as he was under the Colonial Office regime.&quot;
;; As to the capture of the Mabangci, it is stated in this report that the Sydney people had sent wireless messages to their agents as to everything that the Matunga contained, as to the time of her departure, and where she was to he at certain times, and the Germans waited until she came up and quickly seized her.It is further stated that twice the Germans were nearly in the hands of British cruisers, but that thejenemy were able to pick up wireless messages and to send up seaplanes to find out the location of the ships and act accordingly. They laid mines about Australia and also off Ceylon, and went right up to Singapore. They did not send wireless messages from their own ship but relied upon picking up the wireless messages from British vessels.German Colonies in the Pacific. At a recent meeting of the Royal Geographical Society in Edinburgh when a lecture was delivered on &quot; The Settlement of the Pacific,&quot; the High Commissioner for New Zealand (Sir Thomas Mackenzie) wrote : &quot; We in New Zealand are keenly interested in the proper settlement of affairs in the Pacific, and I know I am expressing the views of my Prime Minister and of Sir Joseph Ward, as well as of the people of the Dominion generally, when I say that if these islands which have been secured bv Australia and New Zealand during the course of the war are parted with, a feeling of disappointment, and perhaps something more, will be aroused which will be greatly regretted by all those who wish to see the union and stability&apos; of our Imperial fabric strengthened and maintained.&quot;SOUTH AFRICA.The Nationalists and Dutch Slapping, die. : attack on General Botha. In the House of Assembly on March 21st on the vote for the Prime Ministers salary, the Nationalist Leader (General Hertzog) welcomed the discontinuance of the recruiting of natives for Europe and attacked the Government in connection with its refusal of coaling.facilities to neutral ships in South African ports. Referring to the requisitioning of Dutch ships by the Allies, General Hertzog said he hoped for the sake of those who said the war had been undertaken for the protection of small nations, that this was untrue,-as otherwise it was one of the gravest violations of the rights of nations which could be imagined. General Mertzog asked whether General Botha had taken steps to see that South Africa should not be a partner to such great injustice.The Prime Minister (General Botha) replying, denied General Hertzog&apos;s allegations as to the refusal of facilities to neutrals who he said had to wait their turn, and he pointed out that as part of the Empire, South Africa had to do her duty iu helping to see the war through. Referring to the Dutch shipping question, the Premier declared that South Africa was not an Ally of the Entente but an integral part of the Empire and therefore the Union had not been consulted and was not responsible for the decision of the Central War-Executive. He declined to express views which might lead to further trouble and he certainly would not do anything to help Germany.The Premier added that he had the greatest respect and the greatest love for Holland and none prayed more fervently than he that that noble little country- might keep out of the war. They must avoid anything which might create a false impression among the Dutch people. Personally&apos; he was convinced that the good sense of the Dutch would enable them to keep out of the war.General Hertzog speaking later on the same subject, quoted newspaper articles including one in the Nieuice Rotterdamsehe Co-want to the effect that efforts to facilitate the coaling of Dutch ships in South African ports ended in nothing owing to the Admiralty&apos;s unwillingness to cede anything. Another Nationalist (Mr. Charles Fichardt) moved a resolution to expunge the Premier&apos;s salary in a violent speech in which he accused General Botha of untrustworthiness and untruth fulness. The Minister of Railways (Mr. Burton) referred to this speech as containing prepared slanders and calumnies, and he challenged the Nationalists to say whether they desired that German South West Africa should be returned to Germany. He asserted that nothing the Government did would satisfy the Nationalists unless it foreswore fealty to the British Empire.Glycerine Production. As a result of further consideration by the Union Ministers of the subject, of glycerine production, the British Government have been informed that the South African Government are of opinion that the Union is in an excellent position to secure raw materials for this purpose, being within easy steaming distance
of ports in East and West Africa. It is estimated that if the supplies of oil seed in British and Portuguese East Africa and Madagascar alone were used, about 150 tons per month of-additional refined glycerine could be produced. It is submitted that much saving would be effected in freight by the concentration of the manufacture of the tropical raw products required at a central destination south of the equator.The Union Ministers therefore ask to be informed whether the scheme of the British Government will involve the provision of the necessary plant and the purchase of glycerine at a price which will cover the amount .of capital sunk. It is also asked if the British Government would consider it desirable to arrange some control by the Government over the operations of those firms who are able to produce glycerine in the country or whether it would be preferable to erect a new factory. The question of providing for the transport of the raw material is also raised.Government and Mining Leases. The House of Assembly by 60 votes to 20 has read for the first time the Bill dealing with mining leases (vide Report No. 60). The Labour Leader (Colonel Creswell), announced his intention of opposing the Bill at every stage, and he protested against giving the Board of Control responsibility, which the Government, he considered, ought -to retain in its own hands.PORTUGUESE EAST  AFRICA.Recruiting of Carriers. The British Minister at Lisbon has been informed that as the adequate supply of carriers is essential to the quick termination of the campaign in East Africa, and that as representations to Portugal have not influenced the conduct of the local officials, the British military representatives have been instructed to exercise their own judgment as to obtaining the carriers either with or without the authorisation-tion of the Portuguese. This decision will be explained as necessary in both Portuguese and British interests, and as having been forced upon Great Britain by the apathy of Portuguese officials.TOGOLAND.Natives and British Ride. As a result of an official tour which has been conducted throughout the British sphere in Togoland, it is reported that the desire was universally expressed by the natives to remain under British rule. The complaints made against German rule included charges of compulsory labour without payment ; of forcing the people to borrow money to enable them to pay head tax; and of general ill-treatment and floggings. Amongst the reasons given by the natives for the desire to remain under British rule were that they are treated well, that they are relieved of head tax and of frequent calls on labour and that every man is free to work for himself and earn money.It is further stated in the report that frequent reference is made by the natives in the west and especially Krepi to the former connection with the British, and the fact that it was the British who freed them from the Ashanti oppression and troubles with the Germans in the past. There has been no instance of any wish to return to German rule, and no wish is expressed to serve under the French. Any boundary line which would again sever the Krespi country as a whole is opposed by the Chiefs concerned. It is also announced that the educated classes favour British rule as affording greater opportunities for individual trading enterprise which was dis-couraged under the Germans.

</content>
</cab>
