<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/62/0 images: 2-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fjlHlS DOCUMENT IS TEE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M^ESTY^S QQV3RNMENS E C R E T. COPY NO.* CAB I NET   36  (29).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No* 10 downing street, S.S.I., on MONDAY, October 7th,  1929,at 12 Noon.Note.        The Acting Prime Minister thinks that the Meeting willhave to be continued in the afternoon and he suggeststhat the discussion on Item 6 - Dominion Legislation -should be taken at 2.30 p,m.AGENDA.1.  FOREIGN AFFAIRS.Russia, Conversations with Soviet representatives and Protocol.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.CP. 267 (29)    -    circulated herewith.2.  GOVERNKENT LEGISLATION 1929 - 1930 SESSION.Conclusions of the Committee of Home Affairs.(Reference E.A.C. 7th Conclusions  (29)    -    already circulated).3.   THE v IDOWS&apos;,   ORPHANS1  AND OLD AGE CONTRIBUTORY pensions bill memorandum by the Ministry of Health  covering draft Bill.CP. 265 (29)    -    to be circulated.4.  THE UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE BILL.(Reference Cabinet 34 (29),  Conclusion 6).Second Report of Cabinet Committee,CP. 262 (29)    -    already circulated.Note.    The question of the extension of theTerms of Reference of the Committeeis raised in this Paper.
5*   :IHS COAL II! JUS TRY - DISTKICT AlVD IN TER-DIS TRICT SCHEMESFOR  THE REGULATION OF GOAL 0UuT&quot;ANfTPRICES.Interim Report of the Committee on the british coal Industry covering a Memorandum circulatedto the Committee by the President of the Boardof Trade.CP. 268 (29)    -    circulated herewith.6&apos;  &apos;JHH. FORTHCOMING COKP^RIiffCS OH &quot;TH-&apos;-S OPERATION OF dominion legislation AND MERCHANT SHIPPING LEGISLATION&quot;!Questions to be raised by the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs.7&apos;   S INDIAN POLITICAL SITUATION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.CP. 26G (29)    -    circulated herewith.8.  TO TAKE NOTE OF  :-THE HAGUE CONFERENCE,   1929.(a) The Political Commission.Note by the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,  covering his despatches to SirRonald Lindsay dated August 50th,  1929.CP. 263 (29)    -    already circulated.The Proposed Bank for International Affairs.Memorandum by the-Chancellor of the Exchequer.CP. 261 (29)   -   already circulated.(Signed) M.P.A.  HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.October 4th,  1929.*&quot;      *&quot;
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY [ S GOVERNMENT) .SECRET. Gooy No.CABINET    56  (29) .CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at.10, Downing Street,  S.W.1.,  on MONDAY,  7thOctober,  1929, at 12 noon.PRESENT:The Right Hon.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.(Acting Prime Minister).The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.:.p.,The Right Hon.Lord Passfield, Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey,  G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Benn, D. S. 0. ,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, Bt.,M.P., President of the- Board of Education,The Right Hon,A.V. Alexander, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of Frieth,K.C.V.O.,K.C., lord president of theCouncil.The Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P,, Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood^ M,Minister cf Health.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P/,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.William Graham, M.P.,President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon.William Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.Sir M.P.A. Hankey,  G. C.B. , G. CM. G.................  Secretary.
RUSSIA.(previous reference:Cabinet 34(29), Con-elusion 1. )1. The. Cabir^t^had Jbeior-e them a Memorandum(Paper CP.-267 (29)) by the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs containing a report of his conversations   ith representatives of the SovietGovernment, together with the Protocol which hadbeen signed as the result of those conversations,which provided for negotiations between HisMajesty&apos;s Government in the Halted Kingdom andthe Government of the Union of Soviet socialist republics with a view to the settlement of an agreed List of Questions immediately on the resumption of full diplomatic relations, includingthe exchange of Ambassadors.    It was furtherprovided that the steps to be taken as set outin the Protocol, including the decision concerningthe re-establishment of diplomatic relations,should be brought for approval before Parliamentearly at the beginning of the next Session.After considerable discussion the Cabinet agreed-(a) That the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs, before the meetingof Parliament, should ascertain whether the Protocol (CP.-267 (29),Enclosure No07) was acceptable tothe Russian Soviet Government, andthat he should also have authorityto inform that Government, if andwhen he deemed appropriate, thatthe said Protocol was acceptable toHis Majesty&apos;s Government:(b) That in taking the action referredto in (a) it was unnecessary for theSecretary of State to insist on anexplicit statement by the russian soviet Government that they regardedClause 7 of the Protocol, relatingto propaganda, as applicable toabstention from propaganda by, theThird International, since theSecretary of State had made it plain to M. Dovgalevsky on October1st. that His Majesty1 s Government
regarded the wording as coveringpropaganda &quot;by the Third Inter-national and had asked M. Doygalevskyto make this quite clear to hisGovernment (CP.-267 (29), EnclosureNo.6).   Moreover, the Cabinet took the viow that the wording of Article16 of the General Treaty &quot;of 1924,which Yiras reaffirmed by the termsof Article 7 of the Protocol, was drawn in such a way as to debarpropaganda by the Third International,and they considered that a statement to this effect by the Foreign Secre-tary of the British Governmentsinterpretation, combined with theaction proposed in (a), would carryout the undertakings given by thePrime Minister and the Secretary ofState in Parliament last July:(c) That the only document it was deemedessential to communicate to Parlia-ment was the Protocol (CP.-267 (29)Enclosure No. 7), the text of whichhad already been published in the newspapers.    The Cabinet inclined to the view that it was unnecessary and inadvisable to publish theremainder of the documents attachedto CP.-267&apos; (29) unless this was pressed for in Parliament, but left the decision to the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs, who wishedto confer with other Departmentsconcerned(d) That the question of the appointmentof a British Ambassador at Moscow,on which the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs had asked for an expression of the views of hiscolleagues9 should be left to theSecretary of State to settle;   butas a matter of principle the cabinet felt that if the appointment of a:Member of Parliament was considered to be the most suitable in the publicinterest, the necessity for a by-eleotion should not &quot;be regarded asan insuperable obstacle.
government business.2. The Cabinet had before them the recommenda-tions of the Committee of Home Affairs (H.A. C*7th Conclusions (29)) regarding the elassifioatioand relative degree of urgency of the variousBills submitted for introduction in the present session of Parliament (Appendix).In approving the proposals of the Committee ofHome Affairs the Cabinet agreed(a) That as regards the essential Billsmentioned in the King&apos;s Speech,List (B), the order of introdue-tion should be as follows1. WIDOWS&apos;, ORPHANS&apos; AND OLD AGECONTRIBUTORY PENSIONS.2.  COAL.3^ UNEMPLOYMENT INSURANCE,the order of the remaining Billsbeing left for later decisionaccording as the parliamentary situation night develop:(b) To take note that the First Commis-sioner of Works might find it necessaryto ask, as a matter of urgency * forthe introduction of a Bill for thedevelopment of the Montagu Housesite:(o) To take note that it would beindispensable to introduce an indemnity Bill,, owing to theappointment through mlsunderstand-ing of an additional Under-Seoretaryin &quot;the House of Commons.    The cabinet were informed that there was a precedent for such a Bill in 1864, and that thenecessary legislation was in draft.(previous reference:Cabinet 30(29)? Con-elusion 7. )
THE WIDOWS&apos;, 3.The Cabinet had before them a MemorandumORPHANS1  and old AGS CON- (Paper CP.-265 (29)) by the Minister of HealthTRIBUTORYPENSIONS covering the draft of the Widows1, Orphans&apos; andBILL-Old Age Contributory Pensions Bill.    In this;(Previous Memorandum the Minister of Health explained in[jReference:jCabinet 54 detail the considerable extensions to the proposals(29), Con- *   * ;:elusion 5). made in his earlier Memorandum (Paper CP.-232 (29))now introduoed as the result of further discussionwith tin Chancellor of the Exchequer, e.g*:-(i) Provision is now made for pensions for all pre-Act widows of men in theinsurabie date gory who have attained the age of 55 or at the date whenthey shall attain that age.(ii) Pre-Aot Widows&apos; Pension will continue until the youngest child attains theage of 16 and not of 10   this isreadily defensible, as the widowherself will now receive pension atthe age of 55.(iii) A minor Clause arranged as the resultof a Conference with the service departments (which was to be draftedfor consideration by the Home AffairsCommittee on the 9th October) reducingthe contributions of Service men by^d. a week, to meet a grievancearising out of the provision inthe original Act that Widows1 Pensionswere not payable under the Act to persons in receipt of a ServiceDependant1s Pension.(iv) A Clause hasten added at the requestof the Lord Erivy Seal providing for payment of pensions and continuanceof insurance in the event of migrationto other parts of His Majesty&apos;sDominions.(v) At the instance of the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer the Bill will containprovisions fixing the annual charges for the Pensions Fund on an increasingscale sufficient to provide for thenew liabilities and to smooth overthe heavy increase in the exchequer contribution which would otherwiserequire to be ma.de at the end of thefirst decennial period.(vi) In view of the very large number of widows who will now be brought underthe scheme it will be impossible,as a matter of administration, to
commence payments of pensions to allbeneficiaries on the 1st January, 1930.Consequently it is proposed to pay -(a) As from the 1st January, 1930,pensions to wives aged 65 to70 of men over 70 on the 1stJanuary, 1928, and all other minor classes brought intobenefit by the Bill (over 70,000-):(hO As from the 1st July, 1930,pensions to the pre-Act widowsover the age of 60 (about 210,000):(c) As from the 1st January, 1931,pensions to the pre-Act widowsbetween 55 and 60 (about 85,000).In his Memorandum the Minister of Health set1out certain difficulties which it has not beenHpossible to deal with in this Bill, and indicated that the answer to criticisms would be that whatIthe Government had set out to do was to deal withanomalies within the purview of the Act of 1925,and that other matters must wait for the widermsurvey of the social insurance systems which theyHwere under obligation to undertake.The Cabinet agreed  I(a; To approve the proposals of theMinister of Health as set forth in Paper CP.-265 (29) and summarised above, subject toexamination in detail of theBill by the Committee of HomeAffairs:(b) That after approval of the- Billby the Committee of Home Affairs,the Minister of Health should have authority to circulate it to Membersbefore the meeting of Parliament, in fulfilment of the pledge given tothis effect:H(c) That, as regards the proposalaffecting the Service Departmentsreferred to on page 2 of paper cp.-265 (29), instead of areduction of ^d. being made inthe contribution by the men, ..provision should be made for theamount collected from this sourceto be transferred to a&quot;fund toprovide some payment additional to the pension of post-war service widows.  ;.Details were left for the Minister erf Health toarrange with the Service Departments.[2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W. 1,October 7.
Secret.ILa.C. 7th Cons. (29).I - APPENDIX.CABINET.committee of. home affairs 7 (29).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Committee held in the &quot; Moses &quot; Room,House of Lords, S.W. 1, on Wednesday, September 25, 1929, at 4-30 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Lord Sankey, G.B.E., Lord Chancellor (in the Chair).the Right Hon. J. R. Clynes, M.P., The Right Hon. W. Adamson, M.P.,&apos; I  Secretary of State for Home Affairs. Secretary of State for Scotland.Mr. F. W. Pethick-Lawrence,  M.P.,   Sir   William   Jowitt,   K.C.,  M.P.,Financial Secretary to the Treasury. Attorney-General.Sir  James   Melville,   K,C,   M.P.,Solicitor-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,    The Right Hon. Noel Buxton, M.P.,M.P., Minister of Health. Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.Mr. Herbert Morrison, M.P., Minister   The Right Hon. F. O. Roberts, M.P.,of Transport. Minister of Pensions:Mr. C. G. Ammon, M.P., Parliamentaryi    and Financial Secretary, Admiralty.Mr. Thomas Kennedy, M.P., Parlia-I    mentary Secretary to the Treasury.I -Sir Arthur Robinson, G.C.B., C.B.E.,Secretary, Ministry of Health.i;Sir W. M. Graham-Harrison, K.C.B.,First Parliamentary Counsel.Sir Edward Crowe, C.M.G., Comp-troller-General, Department of Over-seas Trade., Mr. A. E. Widdows, C.B., assistant under-Secretary of State, War Office.[19955]Mr. W. R. Smith, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,G.C.B., Permanent Under-Secretaryof State, Home Office.Sir Charles Ho well Thomas, K.C.B.,C.M.G., Permanent Secretary, Minis-try of Agriculture and Fisheries.Sir Cyril Hurcomb, K.B.E., C.B., Per-manent Secretary, Ministry of Trans-port.Mr. T. W. Phillips, C.B., C.B.E.,Deputy-Secretary, Ministry of Labour.Mr. P. J. G. Rose, C.B., assistant under-Secretary of State, scottish office.        -    .
The following were also present-(continued) :Mr. G. A. Mounsey, C.M.G., O.B.E.,Assistant Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office.Sir Adair Hore, K.B.E., C.B., Princi-pal Assistant Secretary, Ministry ofPensions.Mr. E. G. Howarth, C.B.E., Account-ant-General, Board of Education.The lion. A. E. A. Napier, C.B.,Assistant Secretary and Deputy clerk of the Crown, Lord Chancellors Office.Mr. L. A. J. Granville Ram, SecondParliamentary Counsel.Mr. H. H. Piggott, C.B., C.B.E.,Principal Assistant Secretary, Minis-try of Transport.Mr. J. M. Spaight, C.B.E., assistant secretary, Air Ministry.Mr. G. R. Hill, Parliamentary CounselOffice.Mr. I. M. Forsyth, Mines Department.Mr. A. F. Hemming, C.B.E., Acting Secretary to the Committee.Government 1,   The Committee agreed-Legislation,1929-30 Session. (a.) To adopt  the  following classification in submittingtheir recommendations to the Cabinet regarding therelative degree of urgency of the Bills enumerated in committee Paper H.A. 20 (29) :-List (A). Usual Compulsory or Annual Bills.List (B). Essential   Bills,   mentioned   in    the   King&apos;sSpeech.List (C). Other Essential Bills.List (D). Important Bills.List (E). Useful Bills, mainly non-controversial.List (P). Bills which are not ready and which can standover for consideration at a later date.List (G). Consolidation Bills.(&amp;.) To recommend the Cabinet to approve the classification of the Bills as set out in the Annex to these Minutes,on the understanding that the insertion of Bills in list (P) was without prejudice to their ultimateclassification.Next meeting. 2.   The Committee agreed- r   . f(a.) That their next meeting should be held in the&quot; Moses &quot; Room, House of Lords, on &quot;Wednesday, the9th October. 1929, at 4&apos;30 p.m. ;(o.) That at their next meeting they would consider (i.) The i Widows, Orphans and Old Age Con-tributory Pensions Bill,(ii.) The Factories Bill.(hi.) Any Bills included in List (B) that may beready for circulation by the 4th October,&quot;: &apos;     1929.    , :,&quot; .(iv.) Any other Bills that may be ready.2, Whitehall Gardens, 8.W. 1,September 25, 1929.
AnnexLIST (A).Usual Compulsory or Annual Bills.No.	Bills.	Department.	Departmental Remarks, &amp;c.1 2 I   3 -; 4 5 6 7 8	Consolidated Fund Bill Expiring   Laws   Continuance Bill Consolidated Fund Bill (March) Appropriation Bill (July) Finance Bill  ... Isle of Man Customs Bill Public Works Loan Bill Army and Air Force Annual Bill                 - :	Treasury          ...       ... ...           ... ti                                   &quot;    * * * V                              ...             ... ...         ... It                   ... ***          * War Office       ...      ...	This Bill is essential and must be passed before Christmas to pro-vide   Ways   and   Means   for increased Government cbntribu-tion to Unemployment Insurance Fund.   It will also include any other smaller supplementaries. Essential.    Must   be passed by December   31  next.    :It  has already been introduced. Essential.   Must be passed between Christmas and the end&apos; of the financial year. Essential.   Must be passed between Christmas and the end of the Session in July or August 1930. Ditto. Ditto. Ditto. f.      . Essential and must  receive the Eoyal Assent by April 30,1930.[19955]
LIST (B).Essential Bills, mentioned in the King&apos;s Speech.No.Departmental remarks, &amp;e.Widows, Orphans and Old Age ; Ministry of HealthContributory Pensions&apos; iiSlum  Clearance  and   town planning of Built-up Areas4S6Factories Bill.....Hours of Employment Bill  ...Unemployment Insurance BillBill to amend the Trades Dis-putes and Trade Unions Act.: 1927 ; hGoal    ...      ...      ...      ..Home office ministry of Labour.Law OfficersBoard of Trade ...If payment of the new pensions isto have effect as from January 1,it will be necessary to press this bill through all stages&apos;^-im-mediately after the meeting ofParliament, so that the claimforms, which cannot be issuedtill the Bill is law, may be in thePost Offices by the end ofNovember.It may be convenient to divide thisinto two Bills. It is hoped tohave the Slum Clearance Billready for introduction early inDecember, and its passage there-after as quickly as possible isrequisite in view of the holding up of slum clearance schemes by recent legal decisions, the effectof which will be dealt with in theBill.Will be ready for submission to home Affairs Committee at its next meeting.Notice of Introduction given by the attorney-General on July 3,1929.It is desired by the Board of Tradeto obtain the Boyal Assent forthis Bill by December 20, 1929.
No.12345671011121314151617LIST (C).Other Essential Bills.Bills.Department.Lunacy BillLand Drainage BillUnemployment Insurance forAgricultural WorkersRaising of School - leavingAgeRailway Rating Bill ...London SquaresCollecting Charities (Regula-tion) BillChildren (Employment Abroad)BillBill to amend the silicosisprovisions of the Workmen&apos;compensation Act, 1925Third Parties (Rights AgainstInsurers) BillCrown Proceedings BillWar Pensions Act, 1921(Amendment) BillLand Drainage (Scotland) BillArbitration (Foreign Awards)BillCoast Protection Bill.Admiralty.Ministry of Agricultureand Fisheries.Ditto.Board of Education.Ministry of Health.Home OfficeLaw OfficersLord Chancellor.Ministry of PensionsScottish Office.Board of TradeLondon TrafficRoad Traffic BillMinistry of Transport.Departmental Remarks; &amp;c.Introduced on July 2&apos;5, 1929.Ditto.Notice of Introduction given bythe Home Secretary on July 25.1929.If it proves impossible by admini-strative action to fulfil the PartyPledge in favour of a removal of- the time limit on fresh claims,this Bill will be required toamend Section 5 of the WarPensions Act, 1921.This Bill has passed.the House ofLords, has received SecondBeading in the House .. ofCommons, and has been referredto Standing Committee A.This Bill was introduced in theHouse of Commons in July, andits Second Reading will be taken on the first day that the Housemeets.   &apos;&apos;
LIST (D). Important Bills.			No.	Bills.	Department.	Departmental Bern arks, &amp;c.1 2 3 4	Lunacy Bill to amend the Overseas Trade Act, 1920-1929 Development (Scotland) Bill.. Safety of Life at Sea ...	Ministry of Health. Department of Overseas Trade. Scottish Office. Board of Trade.	LIST (E). Useful Bills, mainly Non-Coxtkoversial.			No. 1 2 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11	Bills.	Department.	Departmental Remarks, &amp;c.	Colonial Naval Defence Bill... Seamen&apos;s Wills Bill  ... Naval Pay Bill         ...... African Air Service (Subsidy) Bill to amend the Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1922 Bill to  deal  with  the  un-authorised   use ( of motor vehicles belonging to others Preventive Detention Bill Highlands      and      Islands (Medical   Service)   Addi-tibnal Grant Bill Acquisition of Land, &amp;c. Standing     Committee     on Mineral Transport Bill to permit the Solemnisa-tion of Marriages in Mili-tary Chapels	Admiralty. Air Miiiistiy. Home Office. ...       ... Scottish Office. Ministry of Transport. Tt                               IT War Office.	If it is found possible to pass the Road Traffic Bill this session, it might be found possible to insert in it a clause dealing with this subject, and thus to dispense with the necessity of a separate Bill. .. *. if
LIST (F).Bills which are not ready and which can stand over for Consideration at aLater Date.1   No.	Bills,	Department.	Departmental remarks, &amp;c.. 1     1 2 3 If.  , 8 l/.(sit) 1.0. 9	Bill to amend the China In-demnity (Application) Act, 1925 Childrens Bill Bill to amend Section 9 (4) of the Workmen&apos;s Coinpensa-tion Act, 1925 Sti&apos;eet Offences Reservoirs (Safety Provisions) Bill Criminal   Appeal   (Northern Ireland) Bill Bank Notes in Ireland Bill to amend the law relating to Savings Banks Bill  to amend  the  Official Secrets Act	Foreign Office. Home Office ... M J J )J Treasury War Office. ^	See CP. 234 (29). If this Bill is found necessary, it will have to be passed into law early in November.LIST (G). Consolidation Bills.			No.	Bills.	Department.	Departmental Remarks, &amp;c.1 2	Unemployment      Insurance Consolidation Bill Solicitors Consolidation Bill ...	Ministry of Labour. Lord Chancellor.	

</content>
</cab>
