<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/62/0 images: 59-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S C RET.?opy No.CABINET   40 (29).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1., on TUESDAY, 22ndOctober,  1929, at 2.50 p.m.PRESENT;-The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M,P. ,chancellor of the Exchequer.(Acting Prime Minister).e Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.e Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of Frieth,K.C.V.O. ,K.C. , Lord Presidentof the Council.e Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P., Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.:&amp;g.-Gen.  The Right Hon.Lord Thomson, G.B.E.,D.S.0.,Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.,lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.he Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P.,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.he Right Hon.William   Graham, M.P.,President of the Boardof Trade.he Right Hon.William Adamson, M.P.,S&amp;cretary of State for, Scotland.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, Bt.,M.P., President of theBoard of Education.The Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First commissioner of Works.Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B, G.C.M.secretary.
MPLOYMENTIfeURANCS.reviousfeference:--cabinet 36(29), Con-elusion 2 and appendix. )l.The Cabinet had before them the following documents relating to Unemployment Insurance:-(i) A Memorandum (Paper CP.-279 (29))by the Minister of Labour on the .subject of the UnemploymentInsurance Bill:(ii) A Memorandum by the Minister ofLabour (Paper CP.-282 (29))oovering the Report,of Sir HaroldMorris1s Committee on procedure and Evidence for the determination of Claims for Unemployment insurance benefit,The Minister&apos;s proposals on the whole subjectcovered by the above Memoranda    are summed up in paper CP.-279 (29)) as follows:-(l)  To abolish the &quot;genuinely seeking work&quot; condition and to make other provisions as indicated in para-graph 3 above.(2) To abolish the practice of suspend-ing benefit pending a decision ofthe Statutory Authorities in oasesin which the question at issue isthe general one whether the applicantis making reasonable efforts toobtain work, and in certain other cases of a similar kind.(3) Subject to the Reports of the ISationalJuvenile Advisory Councils, to lower the age of entry into insurance tothe new school-leaving age as from april 1931, when the higherschool-leaving age takes effect.The contributions and benefits to be the same as those now applying to boys and girls aged 16.(4) Not to include the insurance ofagricultural workers in the present bill.(5)    To provide increased rates of benefit for persons of both sexes aged 17, 18and 19, but otherwise to make nochanges in the rates of benefit.(6) To make certain minor extensions inthe olasses of dependants eligiblefor allowances.(7) To make no change in the present&quot;waiting period&quot; &quot;of six days-(8) To extend the transitional period for one year as already decided bythe Cabinet, the cost of theextension to be met by the Exchequer.
(9) To consider the Inclusion of a clause giving general authorityto provide training and removalexpenses.The general approval of the Cabinet to theMinister of Labour&apos;s proposals was subject tothe following conclusions:-(a) In regard to the &quot;genuinely seeking work&quot; oondition  (i) In order to define what is&quot;a specific job of a suitablekind&quot;  (CP.-379 O^T,&apos; para.-TT&quot;Ta)), refusal of--whiohwould disqualify a claimantfor benefit, words based onthe existing Government PairWages Clause should be intro-duced into the appropriateclause in the UnemploymentInsurance Bill.(ii) The utmost oare should bo takento ensure that it is madeunmistakably clear in the Bill- that the onus of proof istransferred from the claimantto the Court of Referees, as suggested in CP.-279 (29),para. 3 (b).The Lord Chancellor, as chairman of the Committeeof Home Affairs, undertook to keep this point undercareful observation.(b) Acceptance of the Minister of Labour&apos;sproposals on the subject of suspension of benefit (cp.-279 (29), para.4).(c) The question of the lowering of ageof entry into insurance to the newschool-leaving age to be reserved until the Report of the NationalJuvenile Advisory Committee hasbeen received.(d) That the Ministers concerned, namely,The Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Secretary of State for Scotland,The Minister of Agriculture andFisheries,- The Minister of Labour,should further examine whether itwould be possible to includeAgricultural Workers within theUnemployment Insurance Scheme, and,if so, on what conditions (cp.-279(29), para.6).(e) That as regards Rates of benefit the Chancellor of the Exchequer and
the Minister of Labour should examine whether means could &quot;befound to make some reduction in(f) That the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Minister ofLabour should confer in regardto improving the benefit scales of persons aged 17, 18 and 19(CP.-279 (29), para. 13).(g) That the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Minister ofLabour should confer in regardto the inclusion in the Unemplov-ment Insurance Bill of a clause the waiting period (CP.-279para. 12).giving1 general authority to
^EMPLOYMENT[policy.previous reference:Cabinet 23(20), Con-conclusion 4.)2.    In the course of the previous discussion the Lord Privy Seal informed the Cabinet that hewas about to circulate a Memorandum on unemployment policy.The Cabinet agreed  To hold a Special Meeting onFRIDAY next, OCTOBER 25th, at-30 p.m. , for the.purpose of discussing Unemployment Policy.The Secretary was instructed toplace no other question on theAgenda Paper.
-THE factories bill.(previous reference:Cabinet 38(29), Cpnolu-sion 4. )3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum(Paper H.A.-22 (29)) by the Home secretary covering tho draft Factories Bill, togetherwith the Minutes of the Committee of Pome affairs thereon (H.A.C.  8th Conclusions (29) Para.2).The latter Committee had reserved for theconsideration of the Cabinet the following ques-tions of policy set out on pages 2 to 7 of theHome secretary Memorandum, viz.:-Cubic space of work-rooms(clause 3).Washing facilities (clause 38).Accommodation for clothing(clause 39).Weekly rest day (clause 44).Humid factories (clause 5l).Prohibition of night-work inbakehouses (clause 54).Prohibition of employment ofpersons in lifting excessiveweights (clause 57).General provision as to hoursof employment of women and youngpersons (clause 72).Overtime (clause 73).Exceptions as to employment ofwomen and young persons inshifts (clause 80).ment of young persons (clause 95).Provisions regarding the use of lead paint..Provisions regarding holidayswith pay.
GiHaving regard to the congestion of theParliamentary time-table (see Cabinet 30 (29),Conclusion 4), which, to the great regret ofthe Cabinet, made it extremely unlikely thata Second Beading of the Factories Bill couldbe obtained before Christmas, the cabinet agreed  That a Cabinet Committee, composed as follows -The Home Secretary (in the Chair),.The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The Lord Privy Seal,The Secretary of State for DominionAffairs and the Colonies,The Secretary of State for War -Jive.    tfuK-KiKi-   Sj-   Ltdrrrvtsfshould meet to examine the various points on which the Home Secretarydesires a decision, and report tothe Cabinet.
THE EXPIRING laws continuance BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 36(29), Con-clusion 2 and appendix).4. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum(Paper H.A.-23 (29)) by the Financial Secretaryto the Treasury covering the draft Expiring laws continuance Bill, which must be passed into lawby the 25th December next, and the SecondReading of which it is proposed to take early inNovember;   together with a Letter from theLord President of the Council (Paper H.A.-26 (29)urging that the proposal.to continue to keep inforce the Aliens Restriction (Amendment) Act,1919, Section I, which figures in Part I of theSchedule, should be deleted.    In addition, theCabinet had before them the Conclusion of theCommittee of Home Affairs (H.A.C.  9th Conclusions(29), Paragraph l) recommending the sirculationof the Bill as soon as possible, subject to thedecision in regard to the point raised by theLord President.In view of a report by the parliamentary secretary to the Treasury to the chancellor ofthe Exchequer that the withdrawal of the AliensRestriction (Amendment) Act from the expiring laws Continuance Bill would prove highly contro-versial, and having regard more especially tothe congestion of the Parliamentary time-table,the Lord President of the Council said he wouldnot press his suggestion.In accordance with the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs., the Cabinet agreed  ,   To approve the circulation to Parliament ofthe Expiring Laws Continuance Bill,1929, in the form of the draft annexed to H.A.-S3 (29), subject toany drafting or other minor altera-tions, with &quot;a view*to the passageof the Bill into law before the 25thDecember next.
RESERVOIRSPRO-ONS) BILL.evlouserence:cabinet 36&apos;g), con-conclusion 2 andpendix).5. The..^cabinet .had. before them a Memorandum(Paper H.A.-24 (29)) by the Home Secretary covering the draft Reservoirs (Safety Provisions) Bill asintrodueed by the late Government in the House ofCommons in June, 1928.    The Bill is based on theReport of an Inter-Departmental Conference which,after the Dolgarrog Dam disaster four years ago,reviewed the legal position as tc the protectioncf the public from danger due to failure ofreservoirs, and its provisions are underst&amp;od tobe generally acceptable t&amp; the interests concerned.In accordance with the recommendations sf theCommittee of home Affairs (H.A. C. 9th Conclusions(29) Paragraph 2), the Cabinet agreed  Tc approve the introduction in theHouse of Commons as seon as possible after Parliament reassemblesof theReservoirs (Safety Provisions) Billin the form of the draft annexed with.A.-24 (29) subject to the modifi-indications indicated by theCommittee of Home Affairs and toany other drafting ar other minor alterations that may be necessary or desirable.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,Oct&amp;ber 22, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
