<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/62/0 images: 102-110</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SB(JHT3 DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVJRNM^NT)sliiil&apos;Copy No.CABINET   AA (29).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No. 10,Downing Street, S.W.1., on FRIDAY,November 1st, 1929, at 2.^0 p.ra.AGENDA.1.      STATEMENT BY THE PRIME MINISTER2.      FOREIGN AFFAIRS.3.      INDIA.(Report to the Prime Minister).(Signed)    M.P.A. HANKEY,Secretary to the Cabinet,2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.51st October,  1929.
The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister.    (in the Chair).fe Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.-P. ,Chancellor of theExchequer.fe Right Hon.J.H. Thomas , M.P. ,Lord Privy Seal.-le Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of Frieth,K.C.V.O. ,K.-G. , Lord Presidentof the Council.fe Right Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P. , Secretaryof State for Home Affairs.le Right Hon.-Tom Shaw, C.B.E.,M.P.,Secretary of State forWar.fie Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.fie Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, M.P.,President of the Boardof Education.he Right Eon.A.V. Alexander, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield, Secretary ofState for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.Ther Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C. ,M.?.&apos;, Secretary ofState for India.Brig.-General The Right Hon.Lord Thomson, C.B.E.,D.S.O.,Secretary of State forAir.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P.,Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries.The Right Hon.William Graham, M.P.,President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner ofWorks.Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B. ,G. CM. G............. . Secretary.RE. T. Copy No._CABINS T    44 (29).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street,&apos; S.W.1.,  on FRIDAY,November 1st,  1929, at 2.^0 p.m.
PRIME 1. The Prime Minister,, who was warmly greetedSISTER1 S-tt TO THE by his colleagues, made a very full statement in&apos;rpED STATES$ERICA regard to his visit to the United States ofCANADA.America and Canada and his conversations with president Hoover and Mr Mackenzie King.-1-
BXJSSIA,previous reference:Cabinet 39(29), Con-conclusion 5. )2.    The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs consulted the Cabinet as to the general character of the Ambassador to be sent to moscow in accordance with the Anglo-Soviet Agreement,and a short discussion took place.The matter was left to the Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs to deal with according tothe usual procedure in the light of the cabinet discussion.
too&apos;3 LEAGUE OFHONS.oposedinancialssistaixethe Victiman Ageres-on.previous reference:Cabinet 33(29), Con-clusion 3. )3.    The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs informed the Cabinet that a Question had been putdown for answer in the House of Commons as towhether the Government was committed to givefinancial support to a nation which, accordingto the judgment of the Council of the League ofNations, was the victim of an aggression.    TheCabinet agreed  That the general nature of the reply should be to the effectthat the subject had not yetbeen settled at the League ofNations and would be discussed at a future Session:    that theSecretary of State&apos;s statement at Geneva had been in generalaccord with, though rather lesscommittal than, the statement made by Lord Cushendun at theprevious meeting of the League:and that the subject would befurther examined before it was again brought up at the Leagueof Nations.
% POLITICALJT0ATION INPreviousReference:Cabinet 43(29), Con-elusion 5. )4. The Prime Minister stated that the Chanoellorof the Exchequer and the Secretary of State forIndia had already informed him fully of what hadoocurred in regard to the Viceroy&apos;s statementimmediately before the Cabinet Meeting.    Thematter, therefore, was not pursued.
THE UNEMPLOYMENT 5. The Cabinet agreed -INSURANCE BILL. BThat the Unemployment Insurancet-n^^ma 5111 Snou1^ be considered by the(Previous Home Affairs Committee.Reference:Cabinet 43(29), Con-clusion 8.)
THE electricity board.The BatterseaPower Station.(previous reference?Cabinet 42(29), Oon-conclusion 8. )6. The First Commissioner of Works informed the Cabinet that, having now had an opportunityto make himself familiar with the Memorandum bythe Minister of Transport in regard to theBattersea Power Station (Paper CP.-293 (29)),he was in accord with the proposal to publish the experts&apos;1 Report.The Cabinet agreed  That the Report of the Company1sexperts (together with the Reportof the Government Chemists&apos; Com-mittee) should be publishedwithout delay so that it mightbe available for general informa-tion and the consideration of thepublic bodies concerned.-6-
-NEXT MEETING 7.    The Cabinet agreed  OF CABINET.That their next Meeting should beheld on WEDNESDAY IBXT, NOVEMBER-6th, 1929, at 5-30 p.m.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,November 1, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
