<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/155/25 images: 400-408</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYrS government cp(71) 25 COPY NO26 February 1971CABINETINTERIM AGRICULTURAL IMPORT LEVIESMemorandum by the Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food. At our meeting on 16 February (GM(7l) ICth Conclusions, Minute 5)I was invited, in consultation with the Foreign and Commonwealth secretary and the Secretary of State for Trade and Industry, to make a further effort to secure agreement with the Americans on our cereals levy policy withoutthe need to go to the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT) tounbind our cereals tariffs.2. I have already reported to the Prime Minister and to other ministers immediately concerned the results of the further discussions which havetaken place within the past few days with the United States Embassy hiLondon and with Canadian and Australian officials,,    A copy of my minuteis at Annex 1.    In spite of the further modification to our original priceproposals which the Cabinet authorised - and a further concession which,on my authority officials Indicated to the Americans that they would beprepared to recommend as part of a final settlement whereby the increaseof  4 per ton would cover not simply the rest of the calendar year 1971 butthe whole crop year 1971-72 which ends in June 1972 - the reactions both from Washington and from Canadian officials have been unfavourable.    Itseems likely that, even on the terms now on offer to them, they will judgethat for domestic political reasons they cannot come to an agreement with us.3.        I am sure we were right to have made this last effort with the americans and it is most disappointing that It has not succeeded.    It iscertainly not for lack of trying or willingness to compromise.    We need the cereals scheme not only because it is the key commodity but because without it we should have difficulty in holding the considerable measure of agreementwe have with other countries Including New Zealand and Australia to bring inthe other Interim levy schemes,    *K*e-i* (failure to proceed with cereals now would undermine our whole agricultural policy.    In my view therefore weshould now, as recommended by the majority of the Ministerial Committeeon Agricultural Policy (CP(7I) 21), proceed to set in hand the necessaryprocedures for withdrawing our GATT tariff bindings on cereals.    This,1
and the necessary notice of termination of our bilateral agreements withminor cereals supplierst must be done forthwith if we are to be able tointroduce our new cereals scheme on 1 July and to give the trade sufficientadvance notice of how It will operate.    We must stick to 1 July since that isthe date on which the arrangements which give us our existing GATTwaiver expire, end it is unthinkable that there should be a hiatus duringwhich we have no minimum import prices arrangements for cereals at all.5. If my colleagues agree that we now have no alternative but to proceed in the GATT. I am sure It would be right for us to give advance warning toour major cereals suppliers and Annex 2 contains a draft message from thePrime Minister to President Nixon which has been discussed between departments.    I suggest that comparable messages should be sent to canada and Australia,    K there is any last minute inclination on the partof the Americans to reach agreement with us, this formal communication should reveal it.    Moreover the message makes it clear that, even after we have made an approach to the GATTS we would still be willing to continueefforts to reach agreement with the major suppliers.conclusion, I invite my colleagues to agree that we must now Institute thenecessary procedures in the GATT to unbind our cereals tariffs and thatwe should give notice of termination of our agreements with minor cerealssuppliers.    I further propose that the Prime Minister should be invited togive the United States President advance notice of this decision In the termsof Annex 2 and that similar communications should be made to theGovernments of Canada, Australia and the Argentine.J ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food SW125 February 19712
PRIME MINISTERINTERIM AGRICULTURAL IMPORT LEVIESAt Cabinet on 16 February, (CM(7l) 10th Conclusion) I was authorised to make a further attempt to secure American agreement to our cereals levy proposals on the basis of limiting the increasein mips to an average of  4 per ton in 1971 and  6 per ton in1972.   My officials, in consultation with FCO and DTI, have now had discussions with the US Embassy in order to prepare such an offer in a form which would give it the best chance of accept-ance in Washington.   I attach to this minute the draft of an ex-change of letters and a schedule of prices which was drawn up and agreed on that basis.   The schedule of prices represents anaverage increase on all cereals of  4 and  6 but, when expressedin terms of a seasonal scale applied to individual types ofcereals involves increases below the average on maize, the pro-duct of greatest trade interest to the US.    I have also authorisedofficials to tell the US Embassy that we would be willing, for the sake of agreement, to apply the increase of  4 to the whole of the crop year, ie from July 1971 to June 1972 and the increase of  6only to the last six months of 1972.   This was a point to whichUS officials at the recent meetings attached importance and there appears to have been a genuine misunderstanding on the point withthe Embassy here.   It will put us at slightly greater risk duringthe first half of 1972 but since this is the period when themarket is normally strong. I think it is a risk we should be willing to take.2.     In discussing these proposals with the US Embassy it soonbecame clear that any chance they had of success was dependent upon their believing that we were determined to proceed with our policy, and in accordance with the authority given to me by cabinet, I authorised officials to make it clear that british ministers were unable to accept the counter-proposals recently put to us by US officials and that, in the absence of agreement, they saw no alternative but to institute the necessary GATT procedures.Officials explained that because of the timetable, it would be1.
necessary to put in hand this action (as well as corresponding action in relation to our agreements with the minor cerealsuppliers) by the end of this month.Finally, they indicated that they would only be willing torecommend that you should put this offer formally to the USPresident if there was a good sporting chance that it would be acceptable to the Americans.    Following a meeting which theForeign and Commonwealth Secretary had with the US Ambassador on22 February to confirm this approach, the proposals have been formally put to the Americans on the same basis, namely that UKofficials will recommend them if US officials are willing to dothe same.3.     The proposals have also been conveyed to the Canadians andthe Australians.   The Australians have indicated that they wouldprobably agree to anything that was acceptable to the US and canada; but the Canadians&apos; preliminary reaction was that theproposed price levels would cause damage to their trade in wheat and flour and that the offers of consultation procedures do not give them sufficient guarantee that we will take effective remedial action should their trade suffer either directly from the scheme or because it will stimulate domestic production.4.   The US were asked for a definite reaction in time for actionto be taken by the end of this week.   The US Ambassador has indicated his readiness to recommend acceptance of these pro-posals but the initial reaction from Washington is that the USSecretary of State is not likely to be ready to advise the USPresident to accept them against the expected opposition from theUS Secretary for Agriculture.   The US are likely in any event to wish to consult Canada and the other exporters which is bound toharden their attitudes as well as cause further delay.   On theevidence of their reaction so far. and that of the Canadians. Ido not believe that it would be right to advise you to pursue the proposal in a personal message to the US President.   It wouldnot secure agreement, and in the event that negotiations continue2.
even after we have gone to the GATT, would only weaken ourposition.   We have already shown sufficient willingness to try to meet them.5.     I think we shall have to allow the Americans and the canadians a day or two to reflect further on our proposals, butwe shall need to take the final decision about going to GATT as early as possible next week.    I propose to circulate a paper to cabinet for that purpose.   Even then we shall have barely enoughtime to complete the GATT procedures by 1 July as well as bringus a few days over the period of notice required under ourbilateral agreements with minor suppliers.   I think therefore that officials should now be instructed to make all the necessary pre-reparations to go to the GATT, including the drafting of a suitablemessage for you to send to President Nixon, and possibly also toMr Trudeau and Mr Gorton so that action can be taken withoutfurther delay if we have no more favourable reaction from the US.6.   To sum up, I recommend:-(a) that you should not send a message to president Nixon offering further concessionsat this stage;(b) that officials should be instructed to make all the necessary contingency arrangements to go to the GATT;(c) that we invite Cabinet next week to take a finaldecision about going to the GATT.7.   I am copying this minute to the Chancellor of the Exchequer,the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary, the Secretary of Statefor Trade, the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster,Sir Burke Trend and Sir William Nield,J.P.24 February 1971Minister of Agriculture,Fisheries and Food.3.
PROPOSED AGREEMENT ON HM GOVERNMENT1S INTERIM CEREALSLEVY scheme.     The US Government has noted the decision of the BritishGovernment to move over to levies as the main means of agri-cultural support, and that it is the intention to introduce a variable general levy scheme for cereals from 1 July 1971.Having regard to the existence of GATT trade rights on certaingrains, it is the objective of both Governments that thispolicy should be implemented without disrupting establishedpatterns of trade between the two countries.2.      To this end, the British Government has agreed to implement the arrangements in close consultation with theUS Government and other major suppliers.    In particular, theBritish Government agrees to keep under review the operationof the schemes and to consult with the US Government and other major suppliers in good time before making any significant change.    Either Government shall be free to require consulta-tions at any time on the operation of the scheme having regardto the objective set out in paragraph 1 in particular in theevent of a relevant change or prospective change in circumstances.3.     In accordance with these procedures, consultations aboutinitial price levels have taken place as a result of which ithas been agreed that, for the remainder of 1971 and during1972 (and subject to any agreed variations on individual items)threshold prices under the scheme shall not exceed the levelsset out in the attached schedule.4.     In consideration of the above, the US Government agreesduring the currency of this agreement not to exercise therights it has by virtue of the tariff bindings in Schedule XIXannexed to the GATT, it being understood that these rightsremain unimpaired.    Either Government shall be free to terminatethis agreement by giving not less than four months&apos; notice inwriting to the other.
PROPOSED MINIMUM IMPORT PRICES FOR CERTAIN CEREALS  	WHEAT				MAIZE	GRAIN SORGHUM	Group 3	Group 5	Group 6	Group 7		1971						JULY   ) AUGUST)	29.15	31.45	32.30	33.15	25.05	24.50SEPTEMBER	29.45	31.75	32.60	33.45	25.35	24.80OCTOBER	29.75	32.05	32.90	33.75	25.65	25.10NOVEMBER	30.05	32.35	33.20	34.05	25.95	25.40DECEMBER	30.35	32.65	33.50	34.35	26.25	25.701972						JANUARY	32.55	35.00	35.90	36.80	28.25	27.60FEBRUARY	32.85	35.30	36.20	37.10	28.55	27.90MARCH	33.15	35.60	36.50	37.40	28.85	28.20APRIL	33.45	35.90	36.80	37.70	29.15	28.50MAY	33.75	36.20	37.10	38.00	29.45	28.80JUNE	34.05	36.50	37.40	38.30	29.75	29.10JULY	34.35	36.80	37.70	38.60	30.05	29.40AUGUST	31.05	33.50	34.40	35.30	26.75	26.10SEPTEMBER	31.35	33.80	34.70	35.60	27.05	26.40OCTOBER	31.65	34.10	35.00	35.90	27.35	26.70NOVEMBER	31.95	34.40	35.30	36.20	27.65	27.00DECEMBER	32.25	34.70	35.60	36.50	27.95	27.30
DRAFT MESSAGE FROM THE PRIME MINISTER TO PRESIDENT NIXONCEREALS LEVIESDuring our discussions at the White House on 17 December Ireferred to our policy of changing the system of support for agriculture and we agreed that our two Governments should continue their efforts to reach some understanding and agreement on our proposals bearing in mind the wider implications discussed between us.    There have since been meetings between officials but afterthe most thorough exchange of views they have been unable toreach any agreement.    As you know it is our objective in the context of our economic policy as a whole, to reduce government expenditure on agricultural support by transferring some of it tothe food consumer.    As I emphasised when we met, we do not believethat our proposals, even as originally put forward, would havebeen damaging to US trade interests.    However, in an attempt tomeet the doubts expressed on this latter point, we offered to modifyour ideas on price and on some aspects of the scheme in theproposals which were put forward during Secretary Hardin1s visit to London.    More recently we have explored the possibility ofmaking further modifications to our proposals in an endeavour tomake them more acceptable to you and our latest position was discussed by the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary with yourAmbassador on 22 February but we have so far had no reaction tothis.    We now feel that we have gone as far as we can in modifyingour original proposals, if we are to achieve the objectives whichI have explained to you and to which we are publicly pledged,without imposing constraints on our domestic agriculture which itwould be politically impossible for us to accept.My colleagues and I greatly regret that it has so far proved impossible to reach any solution acceptable to both our countries.We are anxious to continue to explore the possibility of reaching a solution acceptable to both our countries and to our othersuppliers and I hope and believe that a basis for agreement canstill be reached.    However we can no longer delay taking theaction in GATT which is necessary to enable us to introduce our new
policy on 1 July when the present agreement between us and our major suppliers of cereals comes to an end.    In order to allow the fullest possible time for consultations with you and our other suppliers, and in the hope that we could proceed byagreement, we have already accepted delays in pursuing the policies which we first put to you last October.   We now see no alternative but to proceedings by way of unbinding our cerealstariffs in the GATT and we shall therefore be making a formalapplication to the Contracting Parties of the GATT later thisweek under Article XXVIII (4).I need hardly say that I have authorised this action withgreat reluctance and we still remain ready to seek an alternativesolution consistently with our objectives.    If, as I hope,agreement can still be reached with you and our other supplierson a basis which will not prejudice the implementation of our policy we would of course be ready to withdraw immediately fromthe proceedings in the GATT.March 1971

</content>
</cab>
