<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/63/51 images: 562-567</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
March 1945.SECRET.I Copy No.W.P. (45) 196.26th March, 1945.WAR CABINET.QUESTION OF BRITISH NATIONALITY FOR POLISH SOLDIERSSAILORS AND AIRMEN.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I circulate to the War Cabinet a copy of the telegram sent to dominion prime Ministers as a result of the discussion at the War Cabinet on the21st February W.M. (45) 23rd Conclusions, Minute 2 together with copies ofthe replies which have now been received.2. It will be seen that Canada, New Zealand and the Union of South Africahave expressed the view generally that there would be no objection to the grantof naturalisation to members of the Polish Forces by the &quot;United Kingdom, butthat this would not give them any right of entry into the Dominions since the immigration Legislation of the Dominions gives power to refuse admission toBritish subjects. Australia has taken the line that the adoption of the proposal would confer on the Poles concerned very wide rights, including, in effect,automatic admission to Australia. The position as to entry of British subjectsinto Australia is generally similar to that in the other Dominions as described above and, although the Commonwealth Government have agreed to accept Britishmigrants and, in particular, ex-servicemen, they have stipulated that the individuals must all first be approved as settlers. Probably, all that the Common-wealth Government have in mind is that, if these Poles were naturalised as Britishsubjects, it would be very difficult, if not impossible, in practice to apply differentcriteria to them as regards either entry into Australia or treatment after arrivalfrom those applied to British-born migrants possessing similar qualifications.Australia, however, holds out some hope of accepting Polish ex-Servicemen assettlers without their being naturalised as British subjects.3. It will also be seen that the Canadian Government have asked that nofurther publicity may be given to this matter until after further consultation withthe British Commonwealth Governments concerned.C.Dominions Office, 26th March, 1945.[29515]
ANNEX.Telegram to Dominion Governments.(Sent 2- 30 p.m., 26th February, 1945.)(D. No. 348.   Top Secret.)My.telegram of 21st February, D. No. 320.   Following for Prime Minister.Begins:General Anders has informed us that he is much concerned as to future position of his troops in the light of decisions of Crimea Conference relating to poland. He pointed out that he and they have sworn allegiance to PolishGovernment in London who might refuse to release them from their oath.Situation might therefore arise in future in which Polish forces who have foughtunder our command or elements of these forces might be unwilling or might indeed not be permitted to return to Poland. He asked what, reassurances couldbe given them as to their future. This was important if their morale was to bemaintained.2. We have been considering what could be done to meet his difficulties. ThePoles can, of course, be assured that they will have a part in occupation ofGermany in the British zone and this should safeguard their position for a periodof some years. It is, however, necessary to envisage the possibility that such an assurance will not wholly satisfy them. Poles may feel that possibility of difficulties arising later cannot be wholly excluded, and some assurance of a more permanent character may therefore prove to be necessary.3. One possibility which has been suggested is that we might give an under-taking that any of the Polish troops who have fought on our side in western europe or any elements of them who might be unwilling or might find itimpossible eventually to return to Poland under the new conditions, should been abled to become British subjects and thus to receive treatment accorded to members of the United Kingdom forces who have rendered equal service. Thereis some precedent for this in the provision made in Section 4 of the british nationality and Status of Aliens Act, 1943, as to special naturalisation of Frenchnationals who have served in His Majesty&apos;s forces, though the position in the two cases is, of course, not identical. Any such course, if it were decided upon, wouldinvolve amendment of nationality law and would accordingly require generalagreement of all British Commonwealth Governments. It is not possible to give an estimate of number of persons who might be affected by any such arrangementbut Polish Ambassador informed us not long ago that the total number of Polishcitizens of all kinds who might be unwilling or unable to return to Poland was approximately 60,000 and number might in fact prove to be of the nature of100,000.4. We should be grateful for general views of Dominion Governments onthis question. It will be appreciated that no definite decision is at presentrequired since whole matter is still under consideration. It would, however, bevery helpful if we could know how the idea mentioned above strikes you.   Ends.Letter from the High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa of 1st March,1945.Grant of British Citizenship to Members of the Polish Armed Forces.My dear Secretary of State,In reply to your Circular telegram D. No. 348, my Government have asked me to inform you that the position as affecting amendment of the NationalityLaw is being examined and a reply in this connection will be sent later. In theUnion Governments view, however, the Polish troops under General Anders&apos;Command, though under British Army control, are fighting for all the allied nations, and their future is therefore a concern for all and not the British Govern-ment only. Provision for their future, if necessary, should accordingly be a jointaffair for all the major Allies (U.S.A., France, the U.S.S.R., &amp;c).
Large areas of Germany are going to be incorporated into Poland, and Poleswho have fought for the Allies should have a claim to occupation of such areas.The Russians should be asked to agree. Moreover, the new Provisional PolishGovernment should agree to recognise the rights of these Polish soldiers and their families and the Allied Command dealing with the new Polish set-up should insist on such recognition from them. It is wholly unfair to saddle the british authorities with a responsibility which belongs to all.The Polish question bristles with enormous potentialities of future trouble, .and my Government consider that the United Kingdom Government would bewell advised to keep in close touch with the Allies and share responsibility tothe full with them.I have sent copies of this letter to the other Dominion High commissioners in case they should wish to inform their Governments of the Union&apos;s views.Yours sincerely,G. HEATON NICHOLLS.Letter from the High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa of13th March, 1945.My dear Secretary of State,Further to your circular telegram D. No. 348 and my letter of the 1st March,regarding naturalisation of Polish troops, the legal position as we see it, is that ifthe persons in question were naturalised under Part II of the British nationality and Status of Aliens Act 1914 (which is &quot; agreed &quot; legislation) they would alsobe British subjects under the Union&apos;s Naturalisation Law. Naturalisation under special legislation, however, would not enable them to claim British status in theUnion, nor would they be British subjects in the Union if Part II of the BritishAct were similarly amended or legislative provision made for recognition of suchnaturalisation. As naturalised British subjects none of those persons couldenter the Union for permanent residence except under authority of an Immigra-tion Permit issued in terms of our Aliens Act of 1937.I have sent copies of this letter to the other High Commissioners.Yours sincerely,G. HEATON NICHOLLS.Telegram from Government of the Commonicealth of Australia.(No. 69.)Dominions Office telegram D. No. 348 of 26th February.We see no objection to proposal in paragraph 2 provided that Polish forces are carefully disposed to avoid risk of difficulties with Soviet Union.2. The adoption of proposal in paragraph 3 would apparently confer onthe Poles concerned very wide rights, including in effect automatic admission to Australia and possibly equal rights with British ex-servicemen in employment,&amp;c. As the numbers may be.large, we cannot support the proposal without furtherinformation.3. We therefore suggest that, if necessary, the Poles be reassured by anundertaking on the lines of that given by Mr. Churchill in The House of commons on 27th February when he offered &quot; the freedom and citizenship of the BritishEmpire to all who fought if they desire it.&quot; We might be prepared to allow asubstantial number of Polish ex-servicemen to migrate to Australia after thewar, but, as at present informed, we think this could be arranged without a priorgrant of British nationalities.
Telegram from the Government of Canada.(No. 69.   Top Secret.)1. Your telegram D. No. 348 of the 26th February, 1945, concerningnaturalisation of members of Polish armed forces.2. The Canadian Government would have no objection to any action whichmight be taken by the United Kingdom Government or Parliament with a viewto naturalising the members of the Polish armed forces along the lines suggestedin paragraph 3 of your telegram. In the event of action being taken, legislativemeasures would be prepared to the extent that it might be necessary to providefor recognition of the position of such persons as British subjects in the eventthat they were at any time in Canada.3. It will, of course, be understood that the recognition thus accorded inCanada, would not go beyond&apos; that which is accorded to British subjects. Inother words, they would not by naturalisation under an amended United Kingdomstatute become Canadian citizens or Canadian nationals. Any question of settlement within this country would depend upon compliance with the Immigra-tion Act and Regulations.4. I assume no further publicity will be given to the possibility of action being taken on the lines contemplated in your telegram until after further consultation with the Commonwealth Governments concerned.Telegram from the Government of New Zealand.(No. 68.   Secret.)Your telegram D. No. 348.The unfortunate plight of a large number of the Poles who have fought onthe side of the United Nations is clearly recognised and the New Zealand Govern-ment is most sympathetic towards the idea that the offer of British nationalityshould be made to them.There has not been sufficient time to study all the implications of the proposal,and in the absence of any estimate of the numbers involved it is difficult to give any firm undertaking as to the practical assistance which New Zealand Govern-ment might be able to offer. As you know, we are concerned with our own capacity to deal expeditiously with the rehabilitation and housing of our own ex-servicemen.We would have to take this compelling factor into consideration in deciding to what extent we could accord similar facilities to people of nationalities otherthan our own. Subject to this qualification, the New Zealand Government willprovide all possible assistance.



</content>
</cab>
