<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/16/0 images: 1-1</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 2(57). 8th January, 1957.

1. Egypt – Suez Canal. [Enter R.T., B.C., Str., E.H.
S.Ll. Dr. Summerskell is going to E. to satisfy herself about casualties. No
opportunity to stop her.
2. Economic Situation.
H.M. Suez hasn’t changed situation – but it has revealed it.
Debt : £27.000 M, external and internal.
Defence p’mme launched at Korea wd. now be costing, if we hadn’t
cut it back, well over £2000 M.
Social services – on a vast scale.
Nationalisation – damage to our finances. Natd. indies. make no profits
: or if they did wd. lose them in higher wages: have no profits to
plough back. But also can’t borrow on market. They have in fact
bn. financed by Exchequer for years past because their loans
were not taken up in market. We have now taken them on
“below the line”. As quid pro quo, we have forced larger l.a.’s
on to market. –£400M for former : +£200 M for latter.
Theology. Extreme orthodox view = Budget shd. balance over-all.
That view is now being pressed by City because recent run on
reserves due to lack of confidence and our recent borrowing (once
for all) to check it. Unless Budget is balanced, confidence will
weaken again. O.F. support this High Church view.
The latitudinarians (Economist etc.,) hold tht. all that is needed is that
the economy as a whole shd. be in balance: and that expenditure
below the line can be regarded as borrowing. But you can’t tell,
until year is ended, wtr economy is in equilibrium.
Middle view : declines excessive taxation to achieve High Ch.
objective.
My judgment : shd. seek to cut £300 M. off Estimates. This will give
us spirit in which to survive crises – economic and political – of
coming months. Wd. enable us to give £50 M. or so of tax
concession designed to encourage prodn. and efficiency.
Must find some way of dealing with borrowing by natd. industries. Ty.
haven’t expert knowledge to test validity of their claims. Look at
the size of the bids. And this has to be supplied by Ty. w’out the
test of the market. Alternatives : i) a Ministry of Production,
staffed by people who cd. scrutinise these demands. The parent
Dpts. can’t do it any better than Ty. cf. plan for modernising
rlways which, even now, you can’t drive goods traffic from road
to rail.
Need also determination to enforce economies wh. are politically
difficult, e.g. abolition of R.A.F. Vol. Squadrons.
3
P.M. Natd/ industry borrowg. is a formidable problem. Don’t think we can
carry whole of this investment w’in a balanced Budget.
Agree we must try to aim at redn. of order of £300 M.
Defence. Hope for run-down of 65.000 in this financial year. Diff. to
get larger redn. this year.
A.H. Defence – prodn. and equipmt./man-power. About equal proportions.
“Commitments” have led us into m’taining larger forces than we
can equip with modern weapons.
I plan to run down from 750.000 to 450,000 – with civilianisation.
How soon can it be done? Army 385.000 to 200,000. The faster
the better. But 50% = Regulars, whom you want to keep. Rundown
must therefore be in N.S. element. Dangerous to do it by
reducg. length of service. Can’t cut intake too far, or you wd.
have to re-instate it later. Nonetheless we shall run down all
Services by 70.000 this year.
P’mme of 18 mos. ago wd. be costing now £2.000 M. Has bn. pruned
down, by successive efforts, to £1550 M. Also £50 M twds £100
M. saving. German costs : U.S. aid – will both mean more on
Exchequer.
In long-term, marked reduction in expenditure is assured. But shortterm
savings are v. hard to find – no fat left now in these
Estimates.
P.T. Research scientists : 50% are on defence : and ?rds of expenditure is
on defence research.
A.H. Agree we are using too much. But don’t accept these figures.
D.S. Hope Cab. will have full opportunity to judge method of reducing def.
expenditure. Need for long-term policy. We have always lived
from hand to mouth, on proportionate cuts.
L.P.S. Estimates are already late. Quick decisions on defence cuts are
essential to support sterling.
P.T. Can’t publish Estimates foreshadowg. Budget deficit of £580. M. But
agree Cab. shd. have memo. – e.g. on implications of a Defence
cut of £200 M. this year.
A.H. If you proceed by implications of cuts, Service Dpts will always show
they can’t do with less. Only way of securing redns. in cost is to
cut back on man-power. I am satisfied we shall be able to meet
our commitments. Make a long-term plan, based on man-power,
and stick to it. P.R. Cttee. have endorsed my plan : Service
Ministers and C.O.S. have accepted it.
H.M. C.D. is a wash-out. Abolish it. But at least save £8-10 M.
Block grant principle shd. be applied.
4
N.H.S. £540 M. Must save £15-20 M. Racket in drugs. Must make
people pay something – £50 M. e.g. by 1/= on stamp.
H.A. What of separate stamp for N.H.S. – wholly payable by individual.
Education : £10 M. on school meals.
Agriculture : Subsidies will be £285 M.
Defence : reduce to £1350 – a £200 M cut. Balanced by £80-100 M.
off the Civil Estimates.
Ll.G. Can’t get cuts of order required w’out changes of policy. Drastic
changes are necessary.
Investment in natd. industries. Coal. Report on reconstruction. With
no gt. drop in man-power, but vast increase in mechanisn., still no
increase in output. How much money has bn. sunk in coal, since
war ended?
D.S. Must balance retrenchment by practical prospect of future prosperity.
There must be a positive side, with a strong Tory appeal.
L.P.S. Real gap is nearer to £250 M. than £560 M.
On confidence – we shall have to consider some changes in structure
of our exp’re. : balance betwn. defence/social services/agriculture
and redn. of valueless commitments overseas (e.g. Jordan). If it is
seen that we are correcting this, confidence will be strengthened
– even tho’ results don’t accrue this year.
R.T. A forward policy on N.H.S. wd. secure savings. E.g. too many people
are being treated in hospitals.
B.C. N.H.S. – suggn. of more of cost on stamp. We shall need the increase
for Pensions side.
P.M. We have to seek a cut of order of £300 M.
To-morrow : we shd. look at Def. Exp’re. for next year. we shd.
consider future of C. Defence.
More contribn. twds N.H.S. by “contributor”.
Fashion a “positive” framework – equal opportunity for all to increase
our wealth, vice equal shares for all.
5


</content>
</cab>
