<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/16/0 images: 16-16</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 16(57). 7th March, 1957.

1. Parliament. [Enter Str., E.H.
E.H. Business for next week.
Budget : Tues. 9/4.
M/East debate : spokesmen S.Ll. and O. Gore.
2. India.
P.M. Attack on H.M. Queen in newspaper wh. was Party organ of Congress
Party. Am ascertaining facts.
CLOSED UNDER THE
FREEDOM OF INFORMATION
ACT 2000
Mr. Nehru is publishing a statement. May also be delivering a note to
H.M.G.
3. Congress for Rights in Russia.
S.Ll. Congress for Rights in Russia want to hold mtg. in U.K. Propose to
agree subject to scrutiny of individuals. Organised by R.
emigrés. Somewhat provocative on our part. But R. do similar
things.
Hail. How reputable?
S.Ll. Not disreputable. No Br. sponsors yet in evidence. Speakers all have
R. names.
K. We have always taken firm and correct line about attacks on “friendly”
x| Govts. Worth asking L.O.’s to consider wtr this cd. be regarded
as breach of comity of nations.
Agreed : F.O. to consult L.O.’s on x/.
4. Farm Price Review.
64
H.A. Course (a) wd. be disastrous. Wd. be represented as contrary to spirit
of long-term assurances qua disregard of current factors : also as
damaging smaller farmers.
Course (b) mght get us into same trouble – with farmers and our Party in
H/C. Not sufficiently clear of minimum.
Course (c) is defensible. I wd. accept imposed settlement at £13 M., if
imposed settlement is essential.
But I guess we cd. get agreemt at £15 M., includg ½d. a gallon on
milk. Our supporters wd. think we were mad to miss chance of it
for sake of £2 M.
Addl. points i) Milk. The £4 M. cd. be recovered by m’taining price
at 8d. through year. This wd. reduce cost to Exchequer from £15
to £11 M.
ii) Legn. on long-term assurances, now due, wd. go thro’
much more easily after an imposed settlement.
Str. Our main concern is with small farmer – and as our herds are larger the
milk price is less important. This is a ques for pol. judgment.
P.T. In a year when many demands made on other sections, I thght it wrong
to go above minimum. This, at £8 M., is generous interpretn. of
minimum.
Asked if we cd. get agreemt. by gesture on pigs (small farmer) – their
answer is “No”. Therefore, to get agreed settlement, we are asked
to give more on eggs and milk. Eggs : we are now exporting :
subsidy will rise : can’t defend that. Milk : no economic case at all
for encouraging prodn. of milk. If price is m’tained at 8d., we
shan’t be able to sell output.
Ready to agree to £8 M. plus no change on pigs = £9.6 M. – rounded
up to £10 M. = 25% above minimum.
L.P. Unwise politically to antagonise rural voters for sake of a few million.
But C.R.O. concerned at further encouragemt. of milk prodn. –
which damages N.Z. exports of butter and cheese, who are
increasingly concerned.
H.A. The cost of milk prodn. has risen by 1½d. : we shd. only be meeting
⅓rd. of it.
H.B. Generosity to farmers will have to be defended to taxpayer. Our main
objective shd. be tax production. Public think tht. farm subsidies
are too high. We must consider more than farmers’ votes.
E.H. Party are showing signs of anxiety. i) They don’t like defending
imposed settlements. ii) Not a good time to antagonise further
sections.
Hail. Advantage in imposed settlement. How justify stern-ness to urban
popn. if we appear soft to rural.
65
But, to hold posn., must be fairly generous. Agree we are producg. too
much milk and encouraging inefficient prodn.
Think right figure is about £11 or £12 M.
M. What about taking tax off petrol before settlement is made.
Ch.H. No answer to P.T.’s case on eggs and milk. The only ques : how much
need we pay to retain farmers’ good will. Imposed settlement
wd. be healthy : but £10 M. is too low to keep good will. My
feeling is in favour of imposed settlement at about £12 M.
Gt. mistake to increase subsidy on milk – and even worse to m’tain retail
price in flush period.
I.M. Real choice is between imposed at £10 M. and agreed at over £15 M in
all probability. I prefer lower figure.
P.M. To get agreed settlement, we shd. have to give total of at least £15 M.
and increase on milk which we know to be wrong.
We must therefore have imposed settlement. If so, what are right
decisions on eggs and milk? Surely, to hold fast. But I wdn’t
mind total at £12 M. if it didn’t include concessions on milk or
eggs. Put the extra on oats/barley or fertilisers. Get schedule
which can be justified individually, on econ. grounds.
P.T. Wd. settle for £12 M. imposed, with no concession on eggs or milk.
P.M. ⅓rd. more than minimum.
Agreed : H.A. to speak to Turner on range of £8 – 12 M.
And present to Cab. an agreed (with Ty.) schedule
for £12 M.
5. Public Service Salaries. [Enter B.C.
P.T. As in memo.
E.H. i) Doubt if we can get agreemt. with Oppn. at £1500 – cd. at £1750.
ii) Fear Party will re-act violently v. this, esp. before Budget. Party is
now steady in H/C., but unsettled in country. This wd. cause
disquiet in country to be transferred to H/C.
P.T. Must be reasonably soon. But wd. be ready to do it after Budget vice
before.
I.M. Low award to rlwayman is likely in 10 days’ time. Engineering is
dead-locked.
Hail. In light of action we are takg. elsewhere, we shd. delay this (just)
action.
66
H.W. V. unfair to Parly. Secs. if this is put off indefinitely. In natd. indies. we
are paying more to managers than to Bd. members.
L.P. Average reward of g.p. is larger than that of Parly. Secretary. These
proposals go hardly far enough.
D.S. We shdn’t p’pone this yet again. [Enter D.V.
I wd. much prefer that the whole range (M.P.’s and Ministers) shd.
be linked with C. Service. A more generous and lasting settlement.
Hail. That wd. be sensible, but wd. arouse v. gt. controversy.
H.B. Do somethg. more generous in June. E.g. £1600 for M.P.’s and
somethg. more for Junior Ministers in H/L.
P.M. We can’t make a permanent settlement at this time. We under-estimate
our pol. diffies. in the country. Re-actions of Suez are beginning
only now to be felt. Rough water ahead over Canal settlement.
Believe we must hold this up until July. (Agreed.)
6. Remuneration of Doctors and Dentists.
P.M. We must tell them to accept R. Commn. We can’t accept their
interpretn. of Spens.
We must give 10% at once to the junior hospital grades. Had intended
to give interim award of 5% at once to others. If general increases
in p. service salaries are p’poned, it may be better to w’hold it for a
time – tho’ makg. it clear we shall not negotiate it. Ques of
judgment : do we, by immediate concession, appear too weak.
P.T. If not dependent on R. Commn. or on negotn., we have no reason to
delay it for long.
D.V. Doctors will expect somethg. fairly early. But interim increase from
1/7 shd. suffice.
I.M. Wd. not exacerbate wage demands. They are annual events. These are
events of five year interval or longer.
Ch.H. Only objn. to new course : pressures will build up m’while and
concession will appear to be wrung from us.
Wd. be good if somethg. cd. be announced before mass rally of doctors
in 3rd. week of Apl. A promise to give them decision before
Easter recess. (Agreed.)
7. Germany.
67
[Not heard.]
8. Cyprus. [Enter D.E.
S.Ll. Preference for B. – tht., if it leads to diffies., it’s harder to object.
A.L.B. But, for presentn., better to offer than to appear to be co-erced.
P.M. We cd. await suggn.; and then take some time to consider it.
A.L.B. In Parlt. it will be represented tht. it has bn. taken out of our hands.
P.M. Then let us take initiative, but write more generally – rehearsing our
earlier offer, Gk. reluctance, U.N. discn. : if you think it useful to
revive this idea we wd. in principle be ready to consider
proposals if made.
L.P. Prefer to leave initiative with Ismay. If we take it, we seem to accept
defeat.
D.S. After hearing discn., I have come round to view expd. by L.P.
P.T. So have I.
K. And I. Play it slow.
Agreed : don’t offer.
9. S.W. Africa Company.
P.T. They don’t now intend to apply for change of domicile. We cd. make
it a condn. tht. they don’t.
x/ A good way of shifting some of investment in Comm. fr. U.K.
M. I agree. Mistake to discourage it.
P.M. Likely to be controversial.
P.T. Growing knowledge of x/.
68


</content>
</cab>
