<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/16/0 images: 62-62</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.C. 80(57). 14th November, 1957.

1. Parliament. [Enter E.H.
R.A.B. Business for next week.
Need for Bills to be completed.
2. Bank Rate Leakage.
R.A.B. P.M.’s regret that time did not allow for consultn. with Cabinet.
P.T. Sure decision was inevitable – no other way of clearing imputations.
Hail. Abuse of absolute Parly. privilege : growing scandal. Monstrous
injustice.
E.H. Opposn. amendment : Spker unlikely to call it – out of order.
R.A.B. Argument will be used in debate anyway.
P.T. Stand firm on Bank rate leak : that was their case and complaint.
Hail. Also : this is proper for judicial enquiry : the other is at most a matter
for political discussion.
R.A.B. Appointment : formally by S of S. In accordance with precedent.
K. Parker L.J. – Chairman : Holland (Chancery) : Roskill (Common law)
If they consent to serve.
K. In light of discussion, agreed to substitute Veale for [Enter Att.G.
Roskill. Subject to checking that none is Conservative candidate.
T. of r. on Order Paper p. 217.
3. Foreign Affairs.
a) Aden and Yemen.
b) Arms for Tunisia. Fr. wdn’t supply : B. (P.M. of Tunisia)
threatened to go to E. or R. Despite pressures on Fr. Govt., they
have offered only if B. promises not to transfer them to anyone –
or only if he promises to look to west and refuses E. gift of arms.
Risk tht. B. will decline undertakg. If he does, U.S. and we feel we
must supply : about £40.000 worth in all. Will be bitter
accusations v. us from France. Even so, we can’t afford to drive
these Arab countries one by one into R. arms.
Encouraging unity with U.S. – heartening message from Dulles.
c) Egypt. “On account”: not “on account of Egyptianised property”.
227
Bring out i) we preserve our rights ii) it is on account. N.B. to arrange
for amendment to be sent.
[Enter Selkirk.
4. Malta.
A.L.B. P.’s discussions have bn. v. successful. Esp. on money, we have
averted trouble and secured reasonable solution.
Status of Malta. Can’t change R. Title. Alternatives in Annex C. wd.
avoid this. First wd. be more acceptable to Malta.
Att.G. L.O.’s not consulted. Must have chance to consider if I am to advise.
J.M. And Sc. L.O.’s too.
K. II wd. be neat and effective, but I better for Malta.
H. No gt. objn. to I.
R.A.B. Wd. be diff. to get this thro’ H/C., save with Opposition votes. Need
therefore for caution re titles. I wd. prefer II – easier in H/C. and
wiser, constitutionally.
Agreed : L.O.’s (all of them) to consider Alternatives.
Affirmations. To be reviewed also by L.O.’s ….
H.B. First affirmation – wd. bind up in perpetuity : more than qua Scotland
even.
Hail. Unless faith is pledged, I wd. be v. much concerned over this.
R.A.B. Qua N. Ireland, the right is reserved to Parlt. at W’minster.
Agreed : Cab. shd. have memo. on repercussions for Sc.
Wales and N. Ireland.
L.O.’s also to consider legal aspects.
Agreed. H.O. to co-ordinate and present a single memo. for
Cabinet.
R.A.B. Dockyard. Can’t settle all this now. But how wd. decision on
dockyard affect general solution?
S. I cd. guarantee level of work for 3 years, if Vickers took it over.
During that time they cd. build up commercial work. Naval work
is tapering off : it is urgently necessary to get Vickers in.
228
A.L.B. They wd. employ only ⅓rd. of those now. We shd. have 7,000
unemployed and U.K. wd. have to carry them. Tho’ I am anxious
to see commercial vice naval work there.
D.S. No strategic justifn. for keeping dockyard in Malta. If we keep it on,
we shall be doing to merely to keep up emplt. there – and we shd.
have to close Chatham. Also wd. cost us £6 M., by reason of
sending ships out for repair there. Serious to ask R.N. to do a
military nonsense merely to help Malta.
R.A.B. Def. Cttee. must review this first. Then come to Cab. (on Malta) with
other Malta pp.
P.T. Dockyard is only natural asset Malta has. Must exploit it. Wd. wish to
see Vickers going on.
D.S. Then go ahead with approach to Vickers.
Agreed : Go ahead with that – to get agreement ad ref. to
Cabinet.
Def. Cttee. can look at main genl. ques m’while.
5. Access to Cabinet Records.
No note taken.
6. Kenya.
Approved – subject to submission to C.P. Cttee. of matters under Concln. (2).
229


</content>
</cab>
