<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/9/0 images: 30-30</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 53(51).				19th July, 1951.



	1.	Parliament.



C.E.	Business for next week.



W.W.	Opposn won’t agree to 3 day debates on defence &amp; economics.

		May not even want a one-day debate.



H.M.	V. tiresome, when I have a big speech to make.



H.G.	Tiresome also because my speech on economic affairs.





C.E.	Forestry Bill.   No. of Oppn amendmts.  What if we are defeated on	

		one – this is Rpt. Stage:  no opportunity later to put things right.



T.W.	Defeat on Monday p.m. was organised – not on merits of amendment.

		But another (on public enquiries) they (Tories) didn’t press to

		Divn. tho’ Liberals voted v. us.  This was Cttee.  It’s down again

		on Rept.  If it’s called, we must resist it.



C.E.	But do we abandon Bill if we are beaten.



T.W.	If on that amendmt., yes.



H.D.	Yes:  but not necessarily on other amendmts.  Depends on wh. we are

		defeated.





	John Lewis, M.P.



C.E.	Motion by Paget tht. Lewis’ case be considered by Sel. Cttee.  Shall be

		asked to find time for it.  Propose to decline.  Not much support.

		But Silverman will then put Motion saying Spker’s ruling was

		wrong.



P.M.	Better to give time &amp; get Motion rejected, as it will be, after debate.



C.E.	Various names w’drawn from Motion:  we haven’t much time.

	How cd. Cttee of Privileges consider &amp; report before summonses

		heard on 12/9.  Wd you recall H/C. to consider report.



H.M.	i)  Too much claim to privilege.

	ii) This claim = snobbery.  Won’t do us any good to have this pressed.

	Support C.E.’s inclination to refuse time.

	But Silverman cd. then force our hand by challenging Spker’s ruling.



P.M.	Why not give time at 10 p.m.?



C.E.	Dangerous w’out a whip.



P.M.	Not a matter for whipping – ques. for the House.



C.E.	Not on Order Paper for to-day.  Next week, there are Prayers.



P.M.	The Sel. Cttee motion.



			Agreed:  At 10 p.m. one day next week:  C.E. &amp; W.W. to

			               discuss which.



	Forestry:  Dedication of Woodlands.



A.V.A.	Ty. have raised ques. of dedication by King.



P.M.	Must get L.O. view.



J.	Add declaratory clause to Bill tht. King is a person for this purpose.



T.W.	Crown Lands have never asked for grants.



P.M.	Get L.O. opinion to-day.





	2.	Broadcasting:  Beveridge Report.



G.W.	Much criticism on 2 points – a) 85%  b) Regionalism.

	Shall I say these are only provisional Govt. views.  Or stand firm.



H.G.	Stand firm.

	Shd. B.B.C. give their views on fiscal ques.



H.M.	I told them they cd. make views known after Govt. had put out

		proposals.  Less objn to other than financial.



P.M.	Moderate line:  don’t throw anything away:  but don’t be too firm.

		Let everyone express their views.



H.M.	Special objn to l.a. nomination to Reg. bodies.  Cd. adopt Govt.

		nomination in lieu.



G.W.	That wd. expose us to severe nationalist lobbying.



P.M.	Listen to debate, be ready to be influenced by views

		expressed.



G.T.	And we shd. consider again, after debate.		[Exit  W.W.

					[Enter  N.B. &amp; B.





	3.	Supplementary Pensions.

	

A.V.A.	As in memo.



A.R.	Agree with A.V.A.  But final para. of draft lr. shd. be re-considered.

		Say, instead, “…. &amp; wd. be very glad to receive views of 

		T.U.C. ….”  Don’t let T.U.C. hold us up on this point.



E.S.	Agree, with both.



A.V.A.	Also, want amendment of t. of r.



			Agreed.		[Exit  E.S.

					[Enter  Bottomley.



	4.	Persia.



B.	i)   Delay.  Applies to other commodities.  Can’t continue to delay 

		w’out publicity.  Want to be able also to promise compensn.

	ii)  Stopping.  We shd. have to requisition.

	This gets us near to econ. sanctions.



H.M.	We are criticised for weakness.  Don’t like this stuff going.

	Somethg. in Harriman point.  Prs. avoid public disclosure until he is

		finished.



P.M.	Favour requisitioning.



E.Sh.	This = econ. sanctions.  Isn’t it premature?  Harriman still talking.

		Cargoes cd. be diverted at e.g. Gib. w’in next week or so.

	Aren’t we anxious to avoid creating Comm. unrest in Persia?  May

		not these econ. sanctions create that.



P.M.	P.Q.’s make us look v. silly.



H.M.	Are we to do nothing at all?



R.R.S.	Cdn’t we say:  steps taken to divert cargoes if things don’t go well at

		Tehran.



E.Sh.	Why not link this with our mil. time-table.  These ships won’t get

		there before then.



P.M.	What of loading?



B.	Why stop that?  Stronger action, if needed, can be taken before ships

		arrive.  Otherwise, we muck up our shipping interests.



P.M.	Don’t mind letting this loading etc. go on, so long as we can keep

		posn under control.

H.G.	Defer decision to make it public – until Monday.

	Finance.  Propose order prohibitg. dealings in sterling by Persia w’out

		our permn:  as soon as P. Bill goes thro’ empowerg. them to use

		their currency reserve.  Avoids breach/contract betwn. 2 Banks.



N.B.	Para. 10.  No publicity is inevitable before Monday.

					[Exit  B. &amp; Bott.



H.M.	Saw Opposn.  Told them of w’drawal plan.  W.S.C. didn’t object to

		that.  But urged us to hold on to Abadan.  If no staff left there,

		no excuse to send military in.

	Explained w’drawal fr. fields.  Inform P. Govt. to-morrow &amp; announce

		in H/C. same day.

	Inclined to add (as W.S.C. wants) no intentn to bring remaining

		nucleus out of Abadan.



P.M.	W’draw from fields.  If we delayed telling P., &amp; there was trouble, 

		they cd. say they had no time to prevent disorder.  Therefore,

		tell them first.

	But may be trouble at Abadan.  We have enough troops to hold Ab.

		Cdn’t come in w’out overt act.  If we went in, we mght. stay

		there.  Mght. say it’s consistent Hague decision.  But it’s tricky:

		can’t forecast P. re-action.  Must watch position:  be ready to

		come in:  but not on basis wh. mght. rally P. opinion round M.



H.D.	Cab. ruled out use of major force.



P.M.	If we went in to protect life, circs. mght. arise in which we mght. wish

		to stay on.



H.D.	Don’t want protn of installations.



P.M.	Oh, no!  It’s only for protn of life.



H.D.	Cab. shd. have chance to consider that point.

				[Exit  N.B.

				[Enter  M.W. &amp; T.P.

	5.	Slaughtering Policy.



H.D.	Core of this is in para. 12:  250/400 houses as an aim.

	Must be natl siting plan.  Want authority to go ahead with that.

	Issue:  para. 14(3).  Shd. that be done, w’out legn, by existg. authies

		under M/F;  or by special slaughtering authy under M/Ag.

		I favour M/F. proposal.

	Occupn &amp; ownership:  avoid prejudging ultimate future of meat 

		trade – natn ques. can be left open.

	But (14(5) para.) we want interim bldg. p’mme of 24 houses and 

		7 in 1952, subject to investment p’mme.

	Compensation only in exceptional cases.

	Legn in following Session.

	Minister wd. be strengthened by recommn of independent siting

		authority.

	As on White Fish, we cd. appoint shadow authy to plan, in advance of

		legn.



H.M.	Paid?



T.W.	Two or 3 part-time.  Needn’t be paid.



A.V.A.	Livestock Commn under 1937 Act?



T.W.	Same sort of body – with wider scope.



A.V.A.	Why not get M/F. &amp; L. Commn to have a Joint Cttee to get on with 

		this instead of expense of new body.

	Don’t want Govt. to build 24.  There are Co-op. houses wh. were

		closed wh. cd. be used on interim basis.

	Reasonable compensn if we do nationalise later.



H.M.	Use existg. managerial agencies – l.a.’s, Co-ops etc., - to maximum.

		With minimum natl co-ordinn.  No case for expensive new 

		authority.  Why not M/F. and M/Ag., with advisory Cttee.



H.D.	That is view of majority of Cttee.



M.W.	We can handle this w’out new organn.  M/F. have knowledge &amp;

		contacts with other agencies.



H.M.	Yes:  we aren’t going to build.  This is only a planning function.

		Surely Dpts. can handle that.



T.W.	Defer to view of Cab.



H.D.	Then we shall need less legn &amp; none immediately.



J.	Stress this as proper subject for l.a. management.

				[Exit  M.W. &amp; T.W.

				[Enter 3 Serv. Ministers

	6.	Service Pensions.



E.Sh.	V. small differences between by proposals &amp; H.G.’s.

	Pensions not linked with pay, as in Civil Service.

	War Office.  P.U.S. on retirement will have £2.000 p.a. pension

			   C.I.G.S.  ..        ..        ..       ..    £2.000 on my plan.

		I think this too sharp a distinctn (?)       £1.900 on H.G.’s

	On diffces as small as £25, surely I shd. have benefit of doubt.

	Agree, wdn’t affect recruitment.  But mght. affect views of senior

		officers on ques. wtr. he shd. go on.



P.	Support this case.

J.S.	Comparison is with Chorley.  This is embarrassing to P.U.S.  Much 

		feeling over v. little money.



H.G.	Are the pensions to rise disproportionately to pay increases?  That’s

		the point.

	Comparison with P.U.S.  C.S. pensions depend on length of service.

		Not strictly comparable.



A.H.	P.U.S. also get gratuity.



E.Sh.	Can’t base Service pensions on length of service because many have 

		to retire early.



H.G.	They are not therefore comparable to C.S. pensions.



A.R.	Percentage basis is important.



P.M.	Settled (by casting vote) in favour of Services.





	1.	Parliament  (resumed).	[Enter &amp; Exit  W.W.



C.E.	Read out revised Business announcement.



H.D.	This is much more satisfactory.



H.M.	F.A. debate.  K.Y. to speak as well as H.M.





	7.	Information Policy.



G.W.	Need to educate public re re-armament.  Discourage anti-U.S. feelings.

	This means more Min. speeches.

	B. Group.  Will Ministers ask for their help.



H.M.	Importce of Min. speeches.

	Urgency of public educn on defence.

	Ministers must be ready to take their share in this.

	Co-ordination?  Ty. &amp; F.O. will help with material.

	Ministers shd. take trouble.  Hand-outs in advance.

	Duty of Ministers.

	Encourage G.W. to co-ordinate &amp; develop all this.



E.Sh.	Indoctrination of Forces.  Have now got a pamphlet for offrs. takg.

		discn groups.

	Also, thro’ P.R.O., several requests for informn on R. re-armament.

		Think time is ripe for authve &amp; factual statement on this.  Have

		this in prepn.  Press confce proposed.  Justificn for our defence 			policy.



H.G.	Warm support for G.W. memo.  Case for re-armament must be made.

		i)	R. record must be stated:  nature of threat.

		ii)	informn re R. strength.

		iii)	a little more informn about our own strengths.  We must 

			      be able to use some figures in order to rebut Bevan.

			      U.S. give a lot of detail.

		iv)	Publicise U.S. effort in propn to their national income.



E.Sh.	I favour doing more on iii) if security objns can be overcome.



J.G.	Stress 36/47 point.  We must put content into this, as cpd. with

		“numbers”.



H.D.            i)	Form of statements.  Min. speeches are ephemeral.  More useful

		if we cd. have some pamphlets.  Prs. by Labour Party.

		Re-print speeches?

                    ii)	B. Group.  What material will this be?



H.M.	Possibly on model of Econ. Bulletin.



G.T.	Ministers must talk about other things too.  Esp. the good things we

		want to do.  And the money we are still spending on social

		services, despite this.



</content>
</cab>
