<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/15/0 images: 176-183</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CUMENT IS THE . PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAImNIC MaJESTY!S GOVERNMENT,*J*-P R E T-0^^46^441TH DECEMBER,  1946COPY NO.CABINETIMPENDING FOOD DIFFICULTIESNote by thgxA.dclition.Q.1 Secretary- of the CabinetBy instructions of the Prime Minister, I circulate herewith for oonsicleration at Cabinet at 11=30 a.m.minute by the Minister of Food covering a draft statement to be made in the House on Thursday,5th December.(Signed) NORMAN BROOK.cabinet Office, S.W. 1 *both DECEMBER,   1946.

F.M. 46/11PRIME MINISTER1.      Attached-is a draft text for my statement inthe House, warning the country of impending fooddifficulties;, and explaining their causes.2.     This text has been cabled to Mr. Maurice Hutton,head of the British Pood Mission in Washington.Mr. Hutton has discussed it with the Ambassador and made several amendments which I have incorporated inthe light of his talks with Mr. Clinton Anderson,the American Secretary for Agriculture.3.      I am anxious to make the statement after questions on Thursday.(Intld.) J.S.4th December, 1946-1-

88 draft Statement by the Minister off food.     The Government considers that the   House should be warned that repent events in the Americas may seriously affect thesupply of certain foodstuffs to this country during the coming months.2.      It is necessary to speak of these  events, and theirrepercussions upon us,  since the House, and the Nation, has aright to know the reasons for the continued difficulties ofour food supply.    But in doing so, I wish at the outset to saythat no criticism of any kind is implied or intended of thegreat transatlantic exporting countjbbes.    I know they are fully conscious of the difficulties which may be experiencedabroad as a result of their own domestic troubles,3.     The main events affecting our overseas supplies havebeen a series of labour disputes.    Unfortunately,, the largestof them is still in progress, namely, the strike in the softcoal industry in the U.S.A.    This strike if continued willprofoundly disturb the entire American economy including the transportation system.    A really protracted strike might intime affect the movement of supplies in Canada.    Thus we are faced with the possibility of developments in North Americawhich may have the gravest consequences for this  country andfor all other countries which must rely upon North Americansupplies.4.     What I have to tell the House, however,  is that theseevents have gravely impeded the flow of certain staple foodstuffs to this country.    I have already described the serious consequences to our stocks of wheat, which are today littlemore that half what they were this time last year.    It isnecessary for us to obtain the actual delivery to this country of additional supplies of wheat in the next three or four months,  over and ahove those which we have already purchased.I have therefore asked the United States Government to sellus certain quantities of wheat and flour for shipment in thenear future.    I must tell the House that if the United StatesGovernment should find itself unable to agree to our request,or if circumstances should develop which made it impossiblefor these quantities to be moved to the American seaboard for loading on ships in the first few months of the new year, thenfar from it being possible to de-ration bread, it would almost certainly be necessary to reduce the present ration.    TheUnited States Government is today making great  efforts to ensurethat the flow of grain for export will not in fact be impeded.They are fully alive to their great and serious responsibilities,for&apos;they know that the U.S.A.  in this crop year has largersupplies of grain available for export than exist in any other country.5.     Another strike has affected our meat supplies.    The greatmeat packing plants of the Argentine f rigor if icos have been held up by a strike which lasted for seven weeks.    That dispute,  I amthankful to say,  has just been settled.    But we have lost nearly7 weeks&apos;  shipments of meat, a loss which it is almost impossibleto make up completely.    The most immediately threatened of our supplies is,  however, bacon.    Canadian shipments are running belowexpectations. . Supplies from Denmark are only rising slowly.    Wecannot hope to increase our own supplies till we can increase our imports of... animal feeding stuffs.    It may well not prove possible to maintain the present bacon ration.    We should knowdefinitely in the immediate future.

6,     Altogether it is clear that a very d ifficult periodlies immediately ahead of us.    This is not because the realworld food position has worsened.    Indeed, at the risk of seeing ou^ hopes blighted in the  event, I would say thatlooking many months ahead a gleam of light on the food supplyprospects of this country is discernable.7,     The Secretary of Agriculture of the U.S.A.  drew attention in a public statement the other day to the large supplies of grain which would have accumulated for export at 30th June, 1947in the U.S.A.    Insofar as the United States Government canimprove upon the very large export target which,  despite theirmeasures of internal decontrol they have set for themselves,not only will importing countries have been helped at a vitalperiod but a United States carry-over of potentiallyembarrassing dimensions will have been reduced.    If on theether hand transport difficulties prevent the United Statesfrom exceeding their export target,  there will remain large supplies of grain available for export at a later date.There is therefore some promise that the supply situation mayease.    This encourages the substantial hope that one day,and perhaps ifr may be sooner rather than later, the UnitedIngdom, which is by far the greatest continuing market inthe world for exportable surpluses of foodstuffs, may againe importing in full measure the supplies of which today wetand in such great need.    When that time comes we shall not &apos;forget those exporting countries which,  despite their presenttiff difficulties, have stood by us during the period of scarcity.


</content>
</cab>
