<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/15/0 images: 248-251</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
s DOCUMENT  IS  THE  PROPERTY OP  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT   ^:   119Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1946SECRETCP. (46) 449Mh December, 1946Copy No.cabinet internation LABOUR conference memorandum by the Minister of Labour and National Service &apos;       1THE International Labour Convention (No. 63) concerning statistics ofwages and hours of work, adopted by the International Labour Conference in1938, provides for the regular collection and publication of statistics of wagesand working hours, on uniform lines, in countries which: ratify the Convention.It was designed to facilitate international comparisons of wages and working hours by introducing uniformity in the bases of existing statistics and the methods by which they are compiled. 12. His Majesty&apos;s Government voted for the Conjlvention in 1938 as did the United Kingdom employers and workers&apos; representatives, and I have nodoubt that this vote would have been followed by ratification of the Conventionbut for the outbreak of war., , ,3. Ratification of the Convention would, I am advised, involve only avery small extension of the work which is at present being regularly undertaken in connection with the compilation of statistics, and no great extension of whatin the past has been done as regards the publication of such statistics. Theeffect of the Convention is, in fact, that countries which ratify the convention in its entirety will be following as nearly as possible tJhe same lines as thosewhich we have already adopted in this country with regard to the compilationand publication of statistics on this subject.4. There has been inter-departmental consultation on this question andthere is general agreement that the Convention should now be ratified. I propose,therefore, that this should be done and I seek authority for the issue of a white paper in terms of the attached draft.G. A. LMinistry of Labour and National -Service, S.W.1,9th December, 1946[32838]
2ANNEXDraft White PaperINTERNATIONAL LABOUR conference proposed action by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom of GreatBritain and Northern Ireland on the Convention concerning Statistics otWages and Hours of Work in the Principal Mining and manufacturing industries including Building and Construction and in AgriculturePresented by the Minister of Labour and National Service to Parliament byCommand of His MajestyINTERNATIONAL LABOUR conference convention (No. 63) concerning Statistics of Wages and Hours of Work inthe Principal Mining and Manufacturing Industries including building and Construction and in AgricultureTHIS Convention was adopted by the International Labour Conference at its 22nd Session in 1938, and the English and French texts were presented toParliament in Command Paper No. 5875., The; Convention provides for the regular collection and publication onuniform lines of statistics relating to wages and hours of work in all countriesratifying the Convention. It is accordingly designed, to facilitate internationalcomparisons of wages and working hours by introducing a greater degree ofuniformity in the bases of existing statistics and the methods by which they arecompiled.His Majesty&apos;s Government supported the Convention in 1938, but further action had to be suspended on the outbreak of war. It is now proposed to ratify the Convention forthwith. ,



</content>
</cab>
