<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/15/0 images: 438-441</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
-    210(THIS DOCUMENT  IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SECRETCP. (46)  46217TH DECEMBER,   1946CABINETELECTRICITY bill note by the Minister of National Insurance onthe    proposed Area Boards covering wales. I would remind my colleagues that the Government, hasmade it known in the recent &quot;White Paper on Wales that as faras is practicable Wales shall be treated as a single unitfor the purposes of Government Administration.2. I note that the proposal in the Electricity Bill Isto provide a separate Area Board for South Wales, whilstcentral and North Wales are to be included under the Merseysideand North Wales Electricity Board.    In so far as Wales isconcerned,  the boundaries fixed for this latter Board arepurely arbitrary.      For example,  the Board will include partof Cardiganshire which has no connection with the Merseyside.Moreover,  the proposal will cut across possible rearrangement of Local Authority boundaries.      The Commission on LocalGovernment boundaries  (under the Chairmanship ofMr. R. Moelwyn Hughes, K.C ) has put forward a proposal to unite Cardiganshire, Pembrokeshire and Carmarthenshire intoa single &quot;County Council&quot; area, and if the proposals in theElectricity Bill are approved.,  this area would be divided.3. The proposals to divide Wales in the Electricity bill will be criticised both on grounds of National sentiment andon the grounds that the-y provide an arbitrary division of areas which, for other administrative purposes,  are treatedas a single unit..4. For the above reasons I strongly urge- that the matterbe reconsidered and,   unless there are overwhelming technical reasons for the proposals in the Bill, that Wales and monmouthshire should Toe constituted under a single Area Board.J. G.Ministry of National Insurance, S.W.   1. ,17th December,  1946.COPY NO.

The attached note by Lord Chancellor isrculated for consideration the Cabinet at theireting on Thursday,th December, 1946.


</content>
</cab>
