<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/61/0 images: 148-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Colonel Jones.I circulate the following notes which have been prepared in the Intelligence and Statistics Section of the Ministry of Munitions on the labour position in munition industries.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.i.-strikes.statistics of strikes in july.The following table shows for the month of July the number of persons involved in strikes in each district, the total number of days lost, and the average duration of the strike :-District-	Number of Work people involved.	&quot;Number of Days Lost.	Average Duration of Strike in Days.London and South Eastern      -         -South Western -         -         -         -         -         -YVestivlkllands -         -         -         -Yorkshire and East Midlands   -NorthWestern           -   s    -Northern        -Wales Scotland	23,186 1,128 33,270 5,070 2,915 7,379 1,381 439	134,165 1,716 109,870 26,027 13,069 40,411 9,996 649	5-8 -   1-5 &quot;&apos; 3-3   &apos; 5-1 4-5 5-5 7-2 1-5   &apos;	74,768	335,903	4-5The average duration of strikes has been slightly less in July than in June, when 26,156 workers lost 121,642-days-^-an average of 4&quot; 7 days per head. The reduction in time worked during July owing to strikes was 0&apos;48 per cent. 1 day in 208 as compared with 0*19 per cent. 1 day in 526-in June.causes of strikes in july.The most important strike during the month was that which took place against the &quot;embargo.&quot; Out of 38 other stoppages occurring during the month, 19 were occasioned by disputes as to wages-including demands for an advance, questions of piece-work, the terms of arbitration awards, and methods of payment. Six stoppages were due to dismissals, one to a grievance against a foreman, and three to the employment of non-unionists or diluted labour. Other stoppages occurred from various causes such as demarcation, recruiting, hours of labour, clocking-in, and conditions of work.week ending 7th august .1918.During the week ending the 7th August 1918, 13,992 working days-or one-eleventh of 1 per cent, of the. possible working time were lost through strikes. The most important stoppage was that of the. moulders at Sheffield,, whioh still continues.the london aircraft strike.The recent dispute at the Alliance Aeroplane Company&apos;s factory has issued in a final settlement between the conflicting parties which fully justifies the action taken by the Ministry of Munitions in the affair. It was at the beginning of July that the aircraft workers in the London district struck because of the refusal of Messrs. Waring &amp; Gillow, Limited, to recognise a shop committee at their Alliance Aeroplane Works, and they refused to resume work unless Mr. Rock (chairman of the shop committee) were reinstated pending the result of an arbitration.   The attitude of theA  (33)6382  Pk 50  125  8/18  E &amp; SConfidential, (this document-;    His yntannio fv ii m t.)labour position in munition industries.(14th august 1918.)
firm indicated a certain opposition to interference by the shop steward even in domestic negotiation. On the other hand, as subsequent inquiries show, the dismissal of Mr. Rock was justified on the merits. As the deadlock between the parties was seriously obstructing aeroplane production, the Ministry announced its intention of taking over the factory. This measure was not an end in itself, but it has achieved its object in a very satisfactory way. The firm has not only agreed to recognise for purposes of negotiation a committee composed of shop stewards, hut has afforded further proof of the restoration of amicable relations by reinstating Rock. It is part of the settlement that questions not solved&apos; through the shop stewards shall be referred on the one side either to the trade union executives-or to the London District Aircraft Committee, and on .the other to the Engineering &apos; Employers&apos; Federation. An important precedent is thus provided for the aircraft industry. In view of the amoris integratio between employers and employed, the reason for taking over the factory has ceased to exist and the Ministry accordingly has withdrawn its decision.ii.-welfare and health conference.During the comparative tranquillity of the Bank Holiday week^ the Welfare, and Health section assembled its officers from all parts of the kingdom to&apos;hold a conference, at Oxford, where they were offered the hospitality of Lady Margaret Hall. The subjects discussed in the course of the week included the ethics of labour, the feeding of operatives, maternity problems in industrial life, recreation, the relative views of capital and labour, billeting, workers&apos; hostels, the health of young persons, the necessity for (and the results obtained and to be anticipated from) industrial research, the training of. welfare supervisors, the problem of the boy. casually employed, and the education of juvenile workers.Experts gave addresses on their own subjects, and the ensuing discussions showed that the officers present were equally eager to learn and to make their own contributions to the commoastock of knowledge. Much light was thrown, by the citation of concrete. instances, on the opportunities, hitherto neglected, which factory life affords for social progress and industrial conciliation. Moreover, apart from the formal sessions of the conference, much useful work was achieved by the informal interchange of ideas and comparison of difficulties between the officers attached to the several centres, who, at last; felt themselves a corporate whole, inspired with.a novel sense of esprit de. corps. and collective enthusiasm.It may be said that the conference was an unqualified success;. and the hope was freely expressed that it would become an annual fixture.

</content>
</cab>
