<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/61/0 images: 199-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL.-MJ ugust 12, 1918.]Political Intelligence Department, Foreign Office.United States /005.memorandumon-.....-----&quot;War labour organisation in the united states.the following report on war labour organisation in the United States has been furnished by Lord Reading as the second instalment of a series of reports on the internal war policy of the United States Government. It raises an interesting question on which a few introductory notes may not be out of place :From the beginning of the war the internal policy of the United States Government has been controlled by fear of labour unrest perhaps more than by any other single consideration. The possibility of any unrest arising out of the question of war-aims has indeed been much diminished by the consistent attitude of the American Federation of Labour against any inter-belligerent conference (see note below), and by the effect of the Brest-Litovsk treaties on the sentiment of the immigrant socialist labour elements outside the Federation. The &quot; disloyal&quot; labour elements may be safely ignored for the moment. The majority of the old Socialist Party, though they persist in their opposition to war, are not a real danger. Mr. Gompeis&apos; Federation has added to its membership largely during the past year, and its strength is probably steadily on the increase. But labour, while in accord with the Government on the broad question of war and peace, is by no means quiescent in regard to its own immediate interests, and, curiously enough, while the radical and socialist sections of the Federation have recently been forced&quot; more and more into a back seat by Mr. Gompers and his conservative followers, various factors are tending to turn the policy of labour in the direction of a Government control over business not far removed from the best programmes of socialism.The public ownership of all public utilities has long been one of the main planks in the Federations &quot;platform.&quot; Recently the New Jersey State Federation of Labour seems to have gone even so far as to advocate Government ownership of all natural resources. Meanwhile, the traditional hostility of the farmers to &quot;big business &quot;is * coming to a head in such new movements as the N on-Partisan League. In the North-Western States, as in Western Canada, the farmers have been pressing for public ownership of grain elevators and the like. Recently a distinct tendency has been discernable in these States and on the Pacific Coast towards an alliance between labour organisations and the farmers. The Non-Partisan League in the North-West has been concerned in such a movement, and in California a programme of political action has been announced by a &quot;triple alliance&quot; representing organised labour and two farmers&apos; associations which, among other things, advocates &quot; the public ownership of public utilities including terminal warehouses and packing plants.&quot; There are rumours, probably largely unfounded, that party politicians are attempting to exploit these movements. These tendencies are enormously reinforced by the bad relations which have long existed between employers and organised labour in the United States ; by the-violent accusations of profiteering levelled against capitalists since the outbreak of war ; by the somewhat indiscriminate hunt after profiteers recently indulged in by the Federal Trade Commission-an unfortunately ignorant and sell&apos;-advertising body; and by the long-standing agitation for the improvement of labour standards in industry and for its regulation in the interests of the public.This is a rough sketch of the general atmosphere in which the relations between the Government and industry are now being carried, on in the United States under the pressure of war. It will be seen that the direct intervention of the Government is more and more being appealed to as the solution of all abuses and difficulties. Lord Readings report and Mr. Frankfurters memorandum show that attention is now being directed at Washington to the evolution of a definite labour policy, but there are signs that the very administrative organs set up for this purpose may precipitate the general tendencies mentioned above.Of the two central bodies set up at Washington, the War Labour Board, though supposedly an impartial body charged with the function of mediation, has shown *some[367-38] *       b
tendency to split, the representatives of labour and of the employers voting against each other in a body, and a majority being given to the former by the votes of the two chairmen. This may tend to make the Board an instrument for creating, rather than for solving, deadlocks, and in one instance already, that of the threatened telegraph strike, the Government has had to take over the industry in order to end a deadlock thus created. Moreover, one of the joint chairmen--Mr. Walsh, a lawyer who ha* gained his position by a deliberately indiscriminate championship of labour is suspected in some quarters of being more anxious to secure opportunities of ruling in favour of labour demands than to prevent disputes arising. This danger may be the more serious in view of the fact that the relations between the War Labour Board and the War Labour Policies Board have not yet been properly worked out, though, in theory, if the latter lays down standard rates of pay the former should in no particular controversy award rates higher than these standards.The War Labour Policies Board is open to no such charge of weakness, hut its policy may tend in the same direction. That policy is to establish broad standards of wages, hours, and conditions over the whole country, as a basis for regular periodical increases of wages to meet the rise in the cost of living. Such broad standards can easily be interpreted and applied in detail in the case of labour directly controlled by the Government itself, through the Conciliation Boards and administrative agencies already set up by various Government Departments, e.g., the Shipbuilding Labour Adjustment Board, instituted by the Shipping Board in August 1917, which has recently -established a uniform rate of pay for all ship workers on the Atlantic and Gulf seaboard ; the Cantonment Adjustment Committee, the Board of Control of Labour Standards in Army Clothing and the National Harness and Saddlery Adjustment Committee, set up in 1917 by the Quartermaster-General&apos;s Department; the Industrial Service Section of the Army Ordnance Department, which has already laid down its own standards in arsenals by the well-known Order No. 13 of the 15th November; and the two Boards recently established by the Railroad Administration, viz., the Board of Railroad Wages and Working Conditions, and the Railway Board of Adjustment No. 2. But the means of enforcing these standards on privately-owned industries, viz., by provisions in Government contracts, and by the pressure which the War Industries Board and the Railroad and Fuel Administrations can exert upon recalcitrant employers through the refusal of raw materials, transportation facilities, and coal seem to be too drastic for actual use unless the Government is prepared to meet a deadlock by taking over recalcitrant industries.Moreover, so far as the Policies Board has evolved any principle of action, it is that no.decision regarding.the regulation of labour shall be arrived at between employer and employed, but shall be imposed by the Government as the supreme party to every dispute.&apos; Indeed, the report of the Executive Council of the Federation to the St. Paul Con-vention lays it down that &quot; in war production the Government clearly occupies the relationship of employer, and hence does not constitute a third party in interest.&quot; In other words, employers and labour are both to be encouraged to deal direct with the Government rather than with each other.Again, while the attitude of labour has on the whole been extremely satisfactory in practice, the Federation has declined to abandon union conditions in principle during the war, on the ground that any promises to restore such conditions after the war must be illusory. . If, therefore, official concessions are to be secured from the unions, some constructive post-bellum policy must be offered to them, and a representative of the Board is already conducting enquiries in England with this idea in view.It would be a mistake to attempt to deduce too much from vague indications of this kind, but there is some ground for believing that the Administration at Washington is considering the adoption of a new Labour policy on a bigger scale and on more radical lines than any yet contemplated in other countries. The development of any such policy must be tentative and slow, but American public opinion is perhaps not wholly unready for it. The Government operation of the railroads, telegraphs, and telephones has made a great impression on the public mind. The creation of a Merchant Marine by direct Government action has in a way caught American imagination. Government intervention in industries where labour conditions were previously chaotic, as in the lumber industry of the north-west, has been marked by considerable success. The Government has, through the new War Finance Corporation, entered upon a rather startling course of direct assistance to industry which cannot fail in the long run to carry with it some corresponding control. If Californian working men and farmers demand the public ownership of packing plants, Mr. Hoover has actually established close Government control over the Chicago packers, and he has done it with a definite eye to the
welfare and satisfaction of labour both in the United States and in Allied countries through increase of production and control of prices. Mr. Hoover has also by the organisation of Government controlled corporations, brought the whole grain and sugar business under his direct control. Besides the impression produced by such concrete instances of Government action, the British Labour Party&apos;s programme of reconstrction has had a marked effect on public opinion in the United States, though the Federation of Labour definitely rejected it at its recent convention as being alien to the non-political spirit of the American trade union movement; while the President^ allusion in March to the &quot; economic serfdom &quot; of the working classes seemed to startle no one, and even employers may be found discussing in vague terms the &quot; abolition of the wage system.&quot;One thing seems almost certain -the jusqiiau boutisme of Americandabour in the war, strong though it at present is, is based upon patriotism and upon confidence in the President, not in any way upon cordial relations with capital or upon abandonment of the old bitter feuds with &quot; big business.&quot; In these circumstances, the authorities at Washington will find it necessary to maintain the war spirit of labour as time goes on by an increasingly radical internal labour policy.All that can be said at present is that these tendencies are well worth watching. In view of the present influence of labour in Allied countries, the labour policy of the United States may have a very marked effect on the future stages of the war, and on President Wilsons eventual views as to the international peace settlement. Already, as regards the peace settlement, the report of the Executive Council of the Federation quoted above indicates a desire to give very definite functions in the sphere of labour policy to a future league of nations. It proposes international action to maintain labour standards in regard to child labour and the basic eight-hour working day, and suggests, apparently in connection with economic questions,] that &quot; an administrative body composed of representatives of the principal groups constituting national interests should be established [by a league of nations] to deal with practical problems in a constructive way.&quot; The President may be led into a policy of Government maintenance of labour standards and Govern-ment control over the processes of production and marketing which may in a measure enable him to steal the thunder of British and Continental labour in regard to national reconstruction, as he has already stolen much of its thunder in regard to the international settlement. In that event a close understanding between the Governments of Great Britain and the United States in regard to labour policy7&quot; in the two countries may become as important as the understanding which we are now trying to reach in regard to the economic and political aspects of the peace settlement. And in the sphere of labour policy, as in these other spheres, such an understanding between the Governments might well supersede the far less natural and logical union which the British Labour party is now attempting to establish with the Socialist parties of the European Allies.Note on the Attitude or American Labour towards an Inter-belligerentConference.This attitude of the American Federation of Labour and the American Alliance for Labour and Democracy was reaffirmed at the League to enforce Peace Convention at Philadelphia in May, as also at the recent Convention of the American Federation of Labour at St. Paul.   The &quot; platform&quot; contained the following pronouncement:-&quot;International Labour Conferences in War Time.&quot;American labour favours, and has always favoured conferences with the organised labour of all other countries in times of peace. In times of war we oppose conferences with the subjects of enemy countries for any purpose connected, with war or peace. In America, as in all other, democracies at war, the Government speaks for the entire nation in all negotiations or conferences with enemy subjects or Governments in relation to foreign affairs ; this function furthermore belongs exclusively to each democratic Government; private conferences cannot speak for the nation. All persons or groups of persons who in open or private collusion with persons in enemy countries attempt to cause to be initiated, or to influence, peace negotiations or the conduct of the war independently of the Government are guilty of violating the fundamental principles of democratic Government, based upon the consent of the people.&quot;[367-33] B 2
The proceedings at St. Paul, however, though almost unanimous, were hot entirely so, as the president of the International Ladies Garment Workers&apos; Union protested against the report of the mission which has just returned from Europe.An indication of the grounds on which many radicals in the Federation support Mr. Gompers and the conservatives in this matter is furnished by the following private report of a conversation with John Walker, president of the Illinois Federation of Labour and a leader of the Liberal Socialists in the Federation.&quot; He is bitterly opposed not only to an inter-belligerent conference until the Germans have been driven back from France to German soil, but equally opposed to the consideration of any programme of reconstruction such as that of the British Labour Party. He defends this&apos; opposition on the ground that the temper of American labour with its large foreign admixture is so uncertain that to debate any question not immediately concerned with winning the war might breed dissension among the workers and so disrupt the unity of our industrial army. Theoreti-cally, he is a political actionist in sympathy with the British Labour Party&apos;s programme, but he feels that it must be ignored by the leaders of organised labour until the war is won.&quot;Before leaving the United States, the American Socialist Mission, at present in England under the leadership of Mr. A. M. Simons, announced their complete opposition to an inter-belligerent conference at the present moment, but did admit that some such conference might conceivably be of value at some future date provided that the representatives from the Central Empires were not only in agreement with the aims announced by President Wilson and by the Inter-Allied Labour Conference, but were also actively engaged in attempting to bring about the revolutionary overthrow of their Governments. Mr. Simons appears to be discussing matters with British Labour leaders quietly and with good sense. He understands the situation far better than Mr. Gompers&apos; representatives did, and his influence may not perhaps be without good results here and in Paris.*    LORD READINGS REPORT.(1.) LABOUit.The following memorandum deals with the question of the means hitherto taken by the United States Goverment to forestall and remedy labour difficulties and unrest.In order to understand the trend of recent reorganisation in the Department of Labour it is necessary to go back to the report of the Presidents Mediation Commission on Industrial Unrest in the West. Most of the subsequent changes in the Department of Labour have arisen from the recommendations of this report. The pertinent recom-mendations were as follows : 1. Continuous administrative machinery for the disposition of industrial issues.2. Unified direction of labour policy.3. Recognition of the principle of the eight-hour day.4. An educative campaign to give labour a fuller understanding of the war.Shortly after the report of the Mediation Commission President Wilson appointed the War Labour Conference Beard, composed of representatives of employers and employees, under the joint chairmanship of ex-President Taft and Mr. Frank Walsh, to -lay down a complete labour programme for the period of the Avar. This body made its report on March 29th of this year and recommended the formation of a National War Labour Board for the settlement of industrial disputes and laid down at the same time an outline of policy to be pursued generally by the Department of Labour. Possessing thus the rough outlines to be followed in the treatment of labour problems, the Administration has since been gradually putting them into effect.So far the following changes have taken place. In January 1918 the entire control of Labour Administration was handed over to the Secretary of Labour. On April 10th the National War Labour Board was created. It is composed of the same personnel as the War Labour Conference Board and was constituted on the advice of that body and on recommendation 1 of the Mediation Commission. Its object is to adjudicate on industrial disputes when all other machinery has failed. In this respect it is a Court of Appeal, but at the same time it can extend its functions to those of a Court of First
(2.) Memorandum by Mr. Frankfurter.The. War Labour Policies Board was created early in May 1918, to unify the industrial polity of the war agencies of the United States. It is composed of repre-sentatives of the ten national departments and agencies concerned with producing and distributing the necessities of war, to wit: Department of Labour, Department of Agriculture, Emergency Fleet Corporation, Fuel Administration, Navy Department, Railroad Administration, Shipping Board, War Department, War Industries Board, Food Administration.Until the Board was established each separate governmental agency formulated its own labour policies without any necessary reference to the needs or to the practices of other branches of the national service. The result was that Army and Navy and Fleet Corporation and private war industries found themselves in unhealthy competition for workers. The waste was indicated by the enormous turnover of. labour. j At certain plants this was said to have reached the appalling figure of 3,000 per cent. The productivity of labour naturally was greatly impaired.To relieve this confusion the President appointed Secretary of Labour Wilson, War -Labour Administrator for the country. Secretary Wilson appointed Mr. Felix Frank-furter to exercise the authority committed to him as War Labour Administrator. To carry out these duties Mr. Frankfurter was made chairman of the War Labour Policies Board. The Board meets weekly and acts upon reports prepared at its direction by committees of specialists from the various governmental branches.The essential task which awaited it, was the concentration of the full energies of the workers of America upon the duty of doing the utmost towards the winning of theInstance by means of sections and permanent sub-committees. A pplications for assist-ance are referred by the Board to a section or a sub-committee composed of two members of the Board appointed ad hoc, or to a permanent local sub-committee appointed from employees and employers in the district. Failing the settlement of the dispute by these bodies, the case is referred to the whole Board, sitting as a Court of Arbitration.The duties of the Labour Policies Board, which was created on the 19th May by the Department of Labour, are purely administrative. Presided over by Mr. Frankfurter it is composed of representatives of the principal Government Departments employing labour, together with Messrs. Taft and Walsh who are also members of the National War Labour Board. Its function is to co-ordinate the demands for labour with the available supply so as to prevent wasteful competition between Government Departments and works and to abolish the present excessive migration of labour.Industrial sections have been attached to many Government Departments to consider labour problems as they arise. These sections are represented on the Policies Board.On the 13th June the problem of housing labour was turned over to the Secretary of Labour by the President in virtue of his powers under the Overman Act. Sixty million dollars have already been appropriated by Congress for this purpose and Mr. Otto Eidlitz has been put in charge of the Bureau.On the recommendation of the War Labour Policies Board the recruiting of labour is to be brought as far as possible under the Federal Employment Service, which forms a part tof the Department of Labour. On the 1st August this programme will be applied to all unskilled workers. It will he gradually extended to skilled workers. A committee of priorities is to be appointed by the Policies Board to assist the Employment Service in the allocation of labour. Though the obligation to obtain labour through the Federal Employment Service is purely voluntary much pressure can be brought to bear on recalcitrant firms by the refusal of other Government bodies such as the Railway and Fuel Administration to grant facilities without which work cannot be carried on.In the case of the Shipping Board I understand that the recent arbitration is considered to have remedied the labour difficulties which have hitherto existed and that no further trouble is anticipated. It is interesting to note in this connection that both the chairman of the Shipping Board and the vice-chairman recently appeared before a Committee of Congress and vigorously opposed the application of measures which would deprive the ship-workers of their beer.Annexed is a memorandum by Mr. Felix Frankfurter setting out the constitution and aims of the War Labour Policies Board of which he is the chairman.
owar. The Board accordingly sought to eliminate all those factors which at the time were reducing the productivity of the workers. To achieve this end the Board deter-mined quickly upon a few important policies. All of these focussed upon the single object of an increasing output of ships, munitions, and food, the material conditions of victory. In these matters maximum productivity for the war emergency is the end kept in sight.The procedure of the Board is to arrive at tentative rulings through the work of committees and the officials composing its membership, and then to consult with industrial management and organised labour, and any other interest affected. Only after the constructive criticisms of such conferences is had are policies adopted. The Board itself has three advisers. One represents industrial management, one organised labour, and a third is termed the economic counsellor.The first effect was to secure recruiting of labour. In effect this meant that the Government itself, through the United States Employment Service (the analogue of the English Labour Exchange System) would assume exclusive charge of the recruiting of unskilled labour after the 1st August. This, policy was announced in a presidential statement, and the war industry of the country was called on to co-operate for its fulfilment. Virtually a monopoly of the placement of unskilled labour was planned. This was done because in no other way did it seem possible to escape: the tremendous w7aste due to &quot; the stealing &quot; of labour from one industry to another. Central recruiting through the United States Employment Service was planned to establish intelligent order where only the anarchy of particularistic competition has been found.After beginning this voluntary mobilisation of the nation&apos;s workers through the central recruiting plan, the War Labour Policies Board turned its attention to the standardisation of wages, of hours, and of the conditions of labour on governmental work. Upon these problems it is now at work. Each one of the related departments and agencies enforces the policies formulated by the Board, which acts as a clearing house for all. Thus, for example, the War Department would both itself in Govern-ment plants observe the regulations laid down, and at the same time use its powers of contract with privately-owned plants to assure a general compliance with them. Again, the War Industries Board through its economic leverage, will furnish the means of enforcing the rulings of the Policies Board.July 1,1918.

</content>
</cab>
