<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/61/0 images: 225-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I Lh? ^Q ^ent is the Property of. j-^11    -Majestyfs Covernmerit.) At  , JkI4 SgOJLg &quot; - /CMP. 5455.--       .       TT ,DISCUSSION Og VSNSHKAI. DISSASB AH) THE QggRIAL WAR COMKEKCB. 1917-1918.(Note prepared in the Colonial Office).This question was discussed at tho Imperial Wat Confer-enoe, 1917, and some,very strong opinions were expressed including the following by. Sir R. Borden:-   &quot; I do not think Canada will over again send men overseas to any war unless we are assured that such conditions, as .have,:met our soldiers will not meet them again.   I say unhesitatingly: hat if I should be Prime Minister in Canada at the outbreak of another war, I would not send one man overseas if the conditions were such as.have prevailed during the progress of the present war. ; I think it is a horrible outrage that Jhey should be so exposed as they, have been.&quot; -;The Conference passed the following Resolution &quot;That the attention of the authorities concerned be called to the temptations to which our soldiere when oh leave are sub-jftoted-, and that such authorities bb: empowered by legislation or otherwise fl) to protect &apos; otafc men&apos; by (having the streets, the neigh-hourhood of camps, and ether $laCeS of public resort, kept clear, so far as practicable of women of the &quot;prostitute class, and (2) to take any other stejps that may be necessary to remedy the serious evil that exists.&quot;It was in consequence of this that Regulation 40 D was passed in March last after prolonged discussion between the Depart-&apos; ments eonoerned and with the approval of the War Cabinet.The question was again raised at the Conference this year, and Mr. Rowell, speaking on behalf of Canada, said that they had been unable to see that any Very adequate steps had been taken to carry out the Resolution. .He said, however, that Regulation 40 D would be of some real benefit, and the opinion of the Canadian military authorities was that the convictions which had taken place lad been useful even if they had not wholly met the situation.Mr. Massey supported Mr. Rowell in the view that more should be done.Sir George Cave referred to two other regulations, 13(a) and 35(c) which he thought had been useful, and Mr. Rowell, reply-Ing to him, said that he d&amp;ecussed the matter with some of the Canadian officers, who thought that the regulation 40 D would be more effectivo if it covered both sexes.   Sr. Macpherson said that our American allies had asked to be covered by 40 D.There was a Considerable discussion with regard to the difficulties and to statistics, and the discussion closed without \   any formal resolution being taken.The general effect of the discussion was, however, undoubt*; edly that the Dominion representatives were anxious to see more effective action taken, and they did not,press for a further Reso-lution because they understood that further efforts were to be made by Eis Maje.sty&apos;s Government to deal effectively with the question.A print of the discussion is arailable if required.Colonial Office, S.W.,&apos; 20th August, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
