<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/61/0 images: 252-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUIaENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS ERITANNIO MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.IgpT&apos;, &quot; WAR CABINET *,T,5463.ATTENDANCE OP SIR EDWARD KBI.jp AND SIR GEORGE PERLEY &apos; W SIR HOBI^RT BORDBN.(Copies of letters from Sir Robert Bor&amp;en to the .Prime Uinister.)ItConfidential.15th August, 1918.Dear J r. Lloyd George,At present I do not propose to appoint a resident minister empowered to act as a regular member of the Imperial V/ar Cabinet.    In a lotter of even date, copy of whioh is being sent t$ Sir Edward ICemp, I am suggesting that in case his presence should be desired at any meeting of the Imperial War Cabinet for ctnsulta-tion in matters relating to the war, he will be glad to attend.Faithfully yours,(Sgd.)   R.L.BOKDEII.The Right Hon.David Lloyd George, M.P.II.15th August, 1918.Dear Hr. Lloyd George,As you are doubtless aware, Sir Edward Kemp, the Minister of the Canadian Overseas iiilitary Forces, resides in London and devotes his entire time to the very responsible duties that oon-tinually accupy him.    Notwithstanding the insistent claim of tho?e duties he is prepared at any time to attend a meeting of the Imperial r/ar Cabinet in oase his presence should be required for consultation or otherwise.Faithfully yours, (Sgd.)   H.L.BORDENThe Eight Eon.David Lloyd George, II.P.
ir5 a t15th August, 1918.Dear Mr. Lloyd George,Sir George Perley, High Commissioner for Canada, who was a Liember of the late Government and is. a Ilamber of the i:ingrs Privy Council for Canada, upon the formation of the Union Government in October last ceased to be a liember of the Administration and was appointed to the position of High Commissioner, the duties of which he had already boon discharging as Minister without Portfolio- from June 1914.    He has my complete confidence in all matters relating . to the administration of public affairs in Canada, and all our business in the United Kingdom with reference to such affairs (except matters directly connected with war activities) centres in his office. If at any time his presence should be desired at a meeting of the Imperial T7ar- Cabinet for purposes of consultation or information in respeot to the matters which he thiis directs, he would be prepared to attend.Believe me,Yours faithfully,(Sgd.) R.L.B0BDEH.The Bight Hon.Havifl Tiloyd George, Li.P.Whitehall Gardens, S.&apos;7. 21st August, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
