<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/61/0 images: 255-257</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
34 &amp; 35, New Bond Street London, V/.1.14th August, 1918.Dear Mr. prime Minister,I enclose herewith on &quot;behalf of Colonel   McCalmant, Colonel Leslie Wilson and myself a Memorandum to the War Cabinet to which we secured very extensive signatures just before the House rose.The announced decision of the approval of the Government of an issue by the War Office of a decoration for the operations in Gallipoli to Dominion troops only has o^me as a great surprise to most Members of the-House of Commons. It is felt very keenly that our troops which participated in those operations should certainly receive at the same time similar recognition for their gallant services.The number of signatories to the Memorandum enclosed is evidence that this feeling is shared by all sections in the House, and many more names could be added should you wish for further proof,VJhether the recognition should take the form of the issue of the &quot;1914 star&quot; with a Gallipoli bar, or of a decoration similar to that to be issued to the Dominion troops is, of course, not for us to say, but we do submit, most respectfully, but most earnestly, that the Royal Navy and our troops who actually landed in the Peninsular and who took part in the operations at Suvla, Anzac and Htdles should not be forgotten in this award.Yours sincerely,( Sgd.)    C . A.&apos; MONTAGUE BARL017.&apos;The Rt,Hon, David Lloyd George, M.P., 10, Downing Street,s. EC r g t,     *-% 207    -V  V 1 LI   c A B. I IT. 3S, t.g.t.-5465.     I     /gallipoli     df.cqrat IONS.Copy of, a letter from Sir ic.a. Kontajguo Boglov^ k. 13.3*, H. pW&quot; Vo the prime Mi His tor&quot; f or^IFding a memorandum signed by 142 -Mgabors^of^aTlimenu&quot;.  &apos; &quot;(See alse g.t.1344, g.t.2676, g.t.5348, g.t.5386, g.t.5394, and g.t.5413).   -
ENCLOSURE O^O G. 10,5465,House of Commons.. August, 1918;.To      The War Cabinet.In view of the fact&quot;that the issue of a Decoration to ,jixLStxalian, J&amp;ovr Zealand and Newfoundland Troops, who served in Gallipoli, has, to the great satisfaction of us all, been approved by His Llajesty and will be issued by the War Office; and in view of the fact that the war Office has stated that it is not proposed to issue this or a similar Decoration to the Imperial forces who also served in Gallipoli, including amongst othersH*Hi Royal Navy.29th Division, comprising Lancashire Troops, Minsters,etc 42nd Territorial Sast Lancashire, Division. Royal Naval Division.52nd Territorial Lowland       Scottish Division. 10th Irish Division.11th Division, including Yorks and Che shires.Welsh Division.-East Anglian Division, andYeomanry Division,we, the undersigned members of Parliament, desire to urge the War Cabinet to reconsider the question so that tho gallantry of all the Imperial forces may at the same time receive similar recognition.( C.A.MONTAGUE BARLOW. (Signed). ( R, HcCALMCHT. -( LESLIE WILSON.The following Members of Parliament have also appended their signatures :-Allen, AiAiAllan, Henry Haveloch, Baker, Randolf, S. Brunner, J.P.L. Butcher, J,G* Bathurst, Charles. Boles, Denman F, Burn, C.R, Barnett, R.W. &apos; Beckett, Gervase. Boyton, James. Berosfordi Blair, Reginald. Bonn. I.Hamilton. Banner, J.Harmood. Barratt,Franc1bLayland. Broke,Wi1loughby de. Beauchamp, Edward. Bentinck, H. Benn, A.Shirley, Bryce, Annan,Cholmondeley. Coates, E.F, Cooper, RiAi Cooke,ClementXinloch. Craig, James, Craig, Norman. Cat or,&apos; John, Cosgrave, Jas. Cantley, Hi 3; Craik, H, Cecil, Evelyn, Davies, David. Dougherty, J,B* Denniss, &amp;.R,Bartley. Devlin, Joseph. Denman, R.D. Dalziel, Henry. Davios, William. Digin, Essex, KiWiFarlngdon, Foster, Philip S. forester. Pox, H,&apos;.ilson. IPlanne ry, i?orte scue, Greenwood, Hamar, Gretton, John. Gardner, J.TiAgg, Goddard, Daniel, f, Goldstone,&apos; IvWi Home, W*^dgar, Henderson, J,licDi Hall, I^red. HamiIt on, C. Go 0 rge. Hodge, Robert Hermon, Henry, Charles 8, Harris, Percy Ai Hill, James. Hughes, Spencer Leigh. Henry, Denis S, Haslam, Lewis, Haekott, John.
Hill, -Staveley,H.S. Jones, lie if.. Jacob sen, rI&apos;.0wen. Jones, E.Pryce. Jones, Kennedy, Jonas, liidgar Kenyon Lincolnshire Lowthor, Claude Lloyd, George Levy, Maurice MayoMorgan, G, Hay Mount, &apos;/?.A, McNeille, J.G, Swift Monsell, B. liyres Marriott, J.A.R. McNeill, Ronald Mason, D.M. Marshall, ..:rthur E. Malcolm, Ian Norman,&quot;Henry Neville, Reginald, J, Nicholson, CN. Outhwaite, R.L.Erice, Chas.L. Pontypridd Priestley, A. Peel, George Pollock, jiirnost Li. Price, Robert J... Pringlo, \%U.R.. Ponne father, De 1?, Poarce, vta. Perkins, &quot;7* irrank Pearce, R. Robertson, J.H. Roundway Rees, J.D. RotherhamRutherford,     jatson Rees, G.Caradoc Roberts, oaml. Roch, Walter Raffan, P.   ilson -Robinson, Sidney Sydenhaffi&apos; . Strauss, ^rthur StairSheehan, D.L,Sheehy, David Stewart, G. Salisbury Scanlan, T.N. Stanier, Beville Socly, Charles button, G.E. iypear, John \\. btuart of Wortley Tryon, CO, Tickler, u,G. .:&apos;ittenham 7/right, ILPitzherber 7/ilson, A. Stanley Tfeigall, A.tl. Walker, V/. Hall \7hite, J, Dundas V/e dge wo o d, Jo s iah, C. Weston,. J.W; 7/iles, Thomas Hinge T.V:hiteley, Herbert H, Yeo, Alfred 17. Younger. George 0.  &apos; Yate, Charles.I

</content>
</cab>
