<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/39/36 images: 394-401</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July, 1943./W.P. (43) 336.23rd July, 1943.WAR CABINET.SELECT COMMITTEE ON NATIONAL EXPENDITURE.Note by the Lord President of the Council and the Chancellor of theExchequer.AT their meeting on the 19th April the War Cabinet invited us to speak tothe Chairman of the Select Committee on National Expenditure on the lines indicated in W.P. (43) 160 (W.P. (43) 56th Conclusions, Minute 11).2. We have had considerable discussion and correspondence with Sir JohnWardlaw Milne and, in his absence, Sir Adam Maitland., and have also had an informal meeting with the Co-ordinating Sub-Committee of the Select Committee.The outcome of these negotiations is summarised in the attached memorandum.3. Before bringing our discussion with the Select Committee to a conclusion,we sought the views of those of our colleagues who are most directly concerned.It was at their instance that we pressed some of the points to which reference ismade in the memorandum.4. Our discussions have throughout been carried on in a friendlyatmosphere; and in his final letter of the 11th July Sir Adam Maitland has saidthat the Select Committee fully recognise the particular difficulties which war conditions impose. Whilst we have not on every point received from theCommittee the precise assurances for which we asked,. I think that we can be reasonably satisfied with what has been achieved and can in general look forward to a period of better relations with the Committee. We accordingly recommendthat we should take no further action for the time being except to keep a carefulwatch on the Committee&apos;s activities. Departments might, we suggest, be asked toreport to the Treasury any cases in which they consider that the Committee havebeen guilty of practices such as those against which we have recently had to protest.J. A.K. W.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,23rd July, 1943.SECRET. V Copy No.   33ANNEXSummary of Results of Consultation with Select Committee.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council and the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer.1. General Basis of Relations between Select Committee and GovernmentDepartments-.THE representatives of the Select Committee cordially agreed that theoperations of the Committee should be such that, whilst the Committee mustcriticise freely where criticism is called for, their relations with GovernmentDepartments must be, and must be seen to be, relations of trust and confidence.[25809]
2. Departmental Evidence.(a) Selection of Witnesses.The Select Committee agreed that Departments should normally be permitted to nominate their own witnesses.(b) Treatment of Witnesses.We raised objection to the procedure whereby the Select Committee havesometimes intimated to Departmental witnesses that they should not disclose their evidence to anyone, even their superior officers a procedure which clearly tendstowards the undermining of official loyalties. We were informed that this wasnot the intention of the Committee : some difficulty had arisen owing to the wording of certain instructions drawn up by officers of the House with a view tostressing the confidential nature of the proceedings of Committees of the House;but a recent ruling by the Speaker recognised the unity of Departments and therewould, in future, be no doubt but that officials would be in a position to be quitefrank with their superior officers with regard to the evidence which they had given.(c) Disclosure of Documents.We told the Select Committee that we felt that it should be recognisedexplicitly that Ministers had discretion not to disclose to the Select Committeereports which they did not consider it in the public interest to disclose and that,in the exercise of this discretion, Ministers would not, in fact, disclose Depart-mental advice tendered by their officials. It was suggested to us in reply that thisproposal rested upon a misconception of the normal procedure and practice of theHouse regarding the powers given to Select Committees. A Select Committee isnot, however, at liberty to send for papers which, according to the rules and practice of&quot;the House, it is not usual for the House itself to order; and it is made clear in Erskine May (p. 623) that, however ample the power of the House toenforce the production of papers may be, sufficient cause must be shown for theexercise of that power, and that, if considerations of public policy can be urgedagainst a Motion for papers, it is either withdrawn or otherwise dealt withaccording to the judgment of the House. We have pointed out to the SelectCommittee that this gives clear support to the attitude which Ministers havetaken up and that there is, therefore, no need to carry the point further.3. Non-Departmental Witnesses.(a) Procedure.We asked that Departmental liaison officers should be informed whenever theSelect Committee proposed to call non-Departmental witnesses and that theyshould, in general, be kept in touch with the proceedings of the Committee. TheCommittee were not willing to commit themselves on this point and evinced some anxiety lest any arrangements of the kind proposed might lead to the withhold-ing of evidence by non-Departmental witnesses. We pointed out, however, thatthe further the Committee could go in keeping liaison officers in touch with their work the less danger there would be of misunderstandings arising between theCommittee and Departments; and we believe that the Committee will, withoutentering into any commitments, tend more frequently in the future to inviteDepartmental liaison officers to be present when non-Departmental witnesses are called.(b) Use of Evidence.The Committee have assured us that it has been their practice to bring to thenotice of the Department any criticisms derived from the evidence of outsidewitnesses upon which a Department ought in fairness to have the opportunity ofeommenting before any conclusions are reported to the House. They have under-taken to adhere to this course and always to be careful to give Departments anopportunity of checking any factual statement about the correctness of which theCommittee may have been in doubt.4. Secrecy.Under the instructions hitherto in force witnesses have been told that theymay ask that their replies on any matters which they regard as secret should notbe recorded.   At our suggestion the Committee have now agreed that, whenever
a witness is doubtful as to the propriety of disclosing information for which hehas been asked, he should be given time to consider the matter and should notmeanwhile be further pressed..5. Outside Establishments e.g., Outstations, Regional Organisations or government Contractors.(a) Visits.We pressed the Committee to agree to make it a regular practice to consult the Departments concerned before deciding to visit an outside establishment and,as a general rule, to give Departmental liaison officers an opportunity of being present on the occasion of such visits. The Committee have replied that in manycases in the past visits to outsbations, and even to contracting firms, have beenarranged through the Departmental liaison officer concerned, and that on such occasions he has frequently been invited to attend. They add, however, that inother oases arrangements have been made direct and have reserved their right inall cases to decide in this connection how they can best discharge their duty to theHouse.(b) Questionnaires.The Committee have assured us that they recognise the general desirability,both from their own and the Departments&apos; point of view, of consulting with theDepartments before issuing Questionnaires, and that it is their intention to followthis course when Questionnaires are addressed to Government-controlled estab-lishments. They have added, however, that where requests for information areaddressed to private firms, different considerations apply, and that they cannotbind themselves to consult Departments on every occasion.After our Meeting with the Co-ordinating Sub-Committee of the SelectCommittee we were left with the distinct impression that the Committee as awhole would not have approved of the wording of some of the more leadingquestions which have in the past been put in these Questionnaires to firms.6. Attendance at Weapon Trials.At the request of the Service Ministers we informed the Select Committeethat we considered that members of the Committee or of its Sub-committees should not seek to attend trials of weapons not fully developed, and that when they wished to attend trials of a fully developed weapon this would be arranged oh thefirst suitable occasion. The Committee have taken the line that there may be caseswhere large sums of money are involved, and that it is not within their competenceto limit beforehand the methods by which they conduct their enquiries. We have,however, riiade it plain that this is a matter over which the Service Ministers feelthat they must, in the public interest, retain control.7. Business Interests of Members of the Select Committee.In our discussions with the Chairman of the Committee we referred to the complaint that members of Sub-Committees sometimes had business interestsinconsistent with those of the firms whose establishments they visited. Sir JohnWardlaw Milne said that this was a matter which the Committee had always kept in mind, and that he could not think of any instance where such a criticism wouldhave been justified.






</content>
</cab>
