<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/9/69 images: 390-407</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  Jidy 1941.SECRET Copy No.W.P. (G) (41) 69.July 16, 1941.WAR CABINET.INDIA AND THE AVAR.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.THE War Cabinet approved on the 9th June (W.M. (41) 58th Conclusions,Minute 6) the proposal to expand the Viceroy&apos;s Executive Council and to create a War Advisory Council (of which the title has since been changed to &quot; NationalDefence Council &quot;). The Viceroy has since secured eminently suitable individualsto complete both bodies and was about to issue an announcement in the formannexed.He has, however, met with an unexpected obstacle in the shape of a threatby the Punjab Government to resign if no Punjabi is added to the ExecutiveCouncil. Telegrams dealing with this problem, which requires most urgentsolution, are also annexed.L. S. A.India Office,Jidy 16, 1941.(1)Text of Announcement to be issued by the Governor-General of India.As a result of the increased pressure of work in connexion with the war ithas been decided to enlarge the Executive Council of the Governor-General ofIndia in order to permit the separation of the portfolios of Law and Supply andalso the creation of portfolios of Information and of Civil Defence and Man-Power. His Majesty The King has approved the following appointments to thethree new seats on the Council :  Member for Supply :Sir Hormusji Peroshaw Mody, K.B.E., M.L.A. (Central).Member for Information :The Rt. Hon. Sir Akbar Hydari, Privy Councillor.Member for Civil Defence and Man-Power :E. Raghavendra Rao, Esq.2. For the vacancies which will occur when Sir Muhammad Zafrullah Khanand Sir Girja Shankar Bajpai take up the posts to which they have recently beenappointed, His Majesty has approved the following appointments :  Law Member :Sir Syed Sultan Ahmed.Member for Education, Health and Lands :Madhao Shrihari Aney, Esq.[22723] b
(2)Telegram from Governor-General of India to Secretary of State, dated july 14, 1941.(Immediate.)1622-S. Punjab Ministry, on the strength of rumour that Defence portfoliois to be transferred to a non-Punjabi, have tendered contingent resignation, totake effect if this proves to be the case, coupling with this a complaint thatexpanded Executive Council will not contain any Punjabi.2. I have discussed with Glancy and will see Sikendar to-morrow, and makeit clear to him that there is no foundation for rumour regarding the Defenceportfolio, though Civil Defence and Man-power portfolios will deal with certainpurely civil aspects, such as A.R.P., which have hitherto been handled by theHome Department, but with which Defence portfolio has never had anything todo. I have always given him to understand that, in the event of a change in defence portfolio arrangements, I would take him into confidence, and I will makeit clear that that remains the case.3. As regards Punjabi member, I should doubt Sikendar and his colleaguesbeing wise to resign on that limited issue, though one&apos;s confidence is shaken bytheir readiness to resign on a mere rumour, which they made no effort to sub-stantiate, about the Defence portfolio. As you know, I would have been glad tohave had Firoz or another Punjab member, but it has not been easy to fit one in.3. In pursuance of the desire of His Majesty&apos;s Government to associateIndian non-official opinion as fully as possible with the prosecution of the war,approval on the recommendation of the Viceroy has also been given to theestablishment of a National Defence Council, the first meeting of which will takeplace next month. The Council, the strength of which will be about thirtymembers, will include representatives of the Indian States as well as of theProvinces and of other elements in the national life of British India in its relation to the war effort. The following will be members from British India :  Ambedkar, Dr. B. R., M.L.A.Assam, Chief Minister of (the Hon&apos;ble Maulvi Saiyid Sir MuhammadSaadulla, M.L.A.).Bengal,  Chief Minister of  (the Hon&apos;ble Mr.  A. K. Fazlul Huq.M.L.A.).Chhatari, Sir Muhammad Ahmad Said Khan, Nawab of, K.C.S.I.,K.C.I.E., M.B.E.Chettiyar, Kumararajah Sir Mutia, of Chettinad, M.L.A.Darbhanga, the Hon&apos;ble Maharajadhiraja of, K.C.I.E.Deshmukh, Mr. Ramrao Madhavrao, M.L.A.Gidney, Lieut.-Col. Sir Henry, M.L.A.Jehangir, Sir Cowasjee, Bart, K.C.I.E., O.B.E., M.L.A.Khallikote, Raja Bahadur of, M.L.A.Khuda Bakhsh Khan, the Hon&apos;ble Malik, M.L.A.Mehta, M. Jamnadas M., M.L.A.Morton, Mr. G. B., O.B.E,Naunihal Singh Man, Lieut, Sardar, M.B.E., M.L.A.Nawaz, Begum Shah, M.L.A.Punjab, Premier of (the Hon&apos;ble Khan Bahadur Major Sirdar SirSikander Hyat Khan, K.B.E., M.L.A.).Rajah, Rao Bahadur M.C., M.L.A.Sarker, Mr. Nalini Ranjan, ML.A.Shah, Professor E. Ahmad.Sind, Chief Minister of (the Hon&apos;ble Khan Bahadur Allah BakhshMuhammad Umar Soomro, O.B.E., M.L.A.).Srivastava, Sir Jwala Prasad, M.L.A.Usman, Khan Bahadur Sir Muhammad, K.C.I.E.The names of the Indian States members will be announced separately.
(3)Telegram from Governor-General of India to Secretary of State.dated July 14, 1941.(Immediate.)1627-S. My telegram No. 1622-S of 14th July. I have now seenSikendar and discussed position with him in great detail.2. I made it quite clear at the outset that the action of his Governmentraised very serious issues. It was not possible for His Majesty&apos;s Government orfor Governor-General to admit of interference of Provincial Governments in amatter such as composition of the Governor-General&apos;s Council or to be faced with,or negotiate under, contingent threat of resignation in certain events. I drew his attention also to practical difficulties arising out of attitude of Moslem league and Congress; and commented on light-hearted manner in which he and hiscolleagues had, without enquiry, been prepared to accept a rumour for whichthere was no foundation whatever. I developed dangerous and damaging effecton future working of any constitution in India based on broad principle of anAll-India Central Government wuth self-governing Provinces of action of this order. I touched on grave injury which would unquestionably be caused in field of enemy propaganda by resignation, and hinted at view likely to be takenby public opinion of sufficiency of grounds to be alleged; and put it to himfinally that no constitution in the world would, or could, possibly work if states-men at head of affairs were to behave in this volatile and impossible manner.3. Sikendar&apos;s points bore a different shape from those he urged in hisrepresentation of last night. They were substantially as follows : There oughtto have been no expansion. We should get no thanks if we were endeavouring toplease the malcontents; we could not hope for support of Congress or moslem league; and we should have done much better to have left things as they were,possibly taking opportunity of vacancies as they occur to make new appoint-ments. He agreed that expansion was justifiable on administrative grounds,and gradually, and claimed to have suggested this to me some months ago.Reminded that present expansion claimed to be justified only on administrativegrounds, and asked where that argument broke down, he admitted at once thatthere was a good case for the bifurcation of Law and Supply, and accepted thata successor must be appointed to Bajpai. Mody and Sultan Ahmed he thoughtwere good choices. Assured that on administrative grounds there was a decisivecase for separation of Civil Defence and Manpower, he left the impression ofbeing prepared somewhat reluctantly to agree. (This is a point that will haveto be emphasised at Press Conference.) He strongly urged that words &quot;and manpower&quot; should be removed from title of portfolio, since that would giveimpression in Punjab that recruitment, &amp;c, was likely to be dealt with by anon-Punjabi Hindu Minister. I said I was quite prepared to meet him on that,subject to your approval. As regards information, he suggested that wre coulahave got on without such a portfolio. I admitted that information was on administrative grounds probably the weakest case, but took the point (Sikendarhaving suggested that Moslems would now have no one to look after them in theCentral Government, since their two portfolios, Law and Information, neither of them carried patronage, &amp;c.) that I had had it in mind that Hydari. whowould not be heavily burdened, would be able to act as general, watchdog onbehalf of his community.[22723] b 2I do not propose to commit myself in any way. He seems entirely to ignoredifficulty, arising out of attitude of Moslem League, in our picking men fromMoslems in &quot; Parliamentary &quot; provinces.4. I hope we shall get round this most awkward and wholly unexpectedcorner. But I fear we must play for safety and postpone to-morrow&apos;s announce-ment for a day or two uncertainty about Bajpai&apos;s post can be used as pretext. i will telegraph further, and would meanwhile welcome any comment, I amcancelling to-morrow&apos;s press conference and arrangements for announcement on tuesday, and suggest you do the same.
Sikendar finally took the point that both Hydari and Sultan Ahmed wereShias and that we ought to have had at least one Sunni. I suggested that therewas a limit to the extent to which we could represent all sub-divisions of opinions,particularly given our extreme difficulty in getting men in face of hostility ofMoslem League.I made perfectly clear to him. position as regards Defence portfolio, and he expressed appreciation. I said in communication that I would see that steps were taken with Press to put beyond any question that Civil Defence representedwork hitherto done by Home Department, and that new portfolio, as to administrative justification for which I repeated that I was satisfied, would notimpinge on work hitherto done by Defence Member, which would continue as hitherto under C-in-C.4. Sikendar then urged that we ought to have had with expanded Councilsome representative of co-operating Provinces. Pressed on this, he agreed thatthere was no one who could be considered from Sind and Assam. He further agreed that Moslem League position created a difficulty in respect of Punjaband Bengal. He repeated that he himself did not wish to be considered, butsuggested that I might have considered Nazimuddin. He was informed thatwhen I had sounded Nazimuddin 6 weeks or so ago he was solid for moslem league, and that, while he might have misunderstood me, I did not believe thathe did. I urged on Sikendar that we were not endeavouring to make politicalcapital out of expansion of Council; that was purely administrative and justifiedin my judgment on administrative grounds. That being so, it was clearly wisein our selections for the new portfolio to concentrate on persons who, while veryprominent in Indian life and highly respected, were not too closely identifiedwith political parties. That had been my object in the selection I had made.He would appreciate, too, impossibility of discussing in detail with large numbersof persons interested precise composition of Executive Council, and he wouldremember that there had been a great deal of criticism of the pains I had taken18 months ago to consult all sections of opinion regarding my proposals for political advance.He accepted the force of that argument. What it boiled down to was thathe was exceedingly keen to have Punjab represented, since he felt that otherwisesuggestion might be made that really co-operative provinces were getting nothanks for what they had done, and that such plums as these were being givenaway in a vain attempt to placate the implacable. I declined to Gommit myselfin any way as regards inclusion of Rajput Punjabi when occasion offers (though,as you know, I have all along been anxious to see one in my Council if possible).Difficulty of this position is not lessened by the fact that I have learned fromGlancy that Sikendar would probably take very strong exception to selection ofE. K. Noon, who is to some extent, it appears^ his political rival.5. I told Sikendar that we must ,now consider how to deal with this matter as a practical issue. Members of New Council had been approved by the King,the individuals concerned had been offered and had accepted portfolio and I couldnot see any way of going back from what had been done. Equally I would regard it as a calamity and the greatest possible encouragement to German propaganda and our enemies in this country were Punjab Ministry to resign in presentcircumstances. I hinted also that they would not find themselves on too goodgrounds were they to resign on any of pretensions which he had suggestedpossible. I said that I should of course be concerned to help him as much aspossible with (sic) any time in any way and on any point he could suggest, onceour conference here took place. I suggested also that he would do well to concentrate on extremely representative and substantially National defence council rather than on expansion in Executive Council. He told me that hewas wholly in agreement with Defence Council idea and only wished that it had come into being without any expansion of the Executive Council, to which Ireplied that such expansion was inevitable administratively. I urged the pointfurther that Defence Council had in it the germs of very important growth,and incidentally that it was the first time since the shelving of Federation thatwe had been able to get the Princes afrd British India together.6. Sikendar promised to see his colleagues and let me know the result. Iconfess that I have been disappointed by his general reaction on this business.Reduced to its essence it is that as Punjab is quite content with things as theyare, that any change in general political make-up of the Centre is liable to reduce
(4)Telegram from Governor-General of India to Secretary of State,dated Jidy 15, 1941.(Immediate.)1633-S. My telegram No. 1627-S of 14th July. Punjab and Expansion of council. Matter was, I understand, further discussed at great length by PunjabGovernment this afternoon, first by members themselves and subsequently withGovernor present. Their conclusion was that they would be exposed to so much criticism and ridicule from enemies from Punjab that, unless they could getone seat in expanded Executive Council, a request which they are, I understand,asking me to put to His Majesty&apos;s Government, they saw nothing for it but to resign. Glancy says he used all possible arguments with violence, but without success. I am seeing Glancy to-morrow and will then telegraph further. Mean-time we shall have to mark time regarding publication of our announcement.(5)Telegram from Governor-General of India to Secretary of State,dated Jidy 15, 1941.(Immediate.)1634-S. Personal. My telegram dated to-day. Punjab attitude. I think this is ia lamentable business, which reflects no credit on Punjab Government.Glancy, of course, is at some disadvantage, since he has not the influence withthese people which Craik had, but I am sure he has done his best to make themsee sense. For the moment I am taking line that I am not prepared to consider this proposition, in the hope thus of bringing some further pressure on them, andI am seeing Glancy to-morrow. There would, of course, be no difficulty in finding a further portfolio if we wanted one by splitting Labour (or with Aney&apos;concurrence by splitting Education, Health and Lands), but principle involved is a very serious one; and if we are to be held to ransom by a Provincial Govern-ment (admittedly with an excellent war record) in this way it will be a veryexpensive precedent; though admittedly in one&apos;s assessment of the arguments on both sides the most unfortunate propaganda use to which this business could be turned has to be given full weight. My own general conclusion at this stage,much as I dislike being blackmailed, is that the importance of keeping Sikendarand his Government, of avoiding propaganda damage that resignation wouldmean, and of avoiding also probable partial disintegration of Defence council which might result were Sikendar to withdraw, tilt the balance in favour ofgiving way.   But I shall still wish (corrupt group) to protect the principle, e.g.,special position enjoyed by Punjab, and that, as they are quite content, everyoneelse ought to be also. I did not fail to impress on him that we were under strong pressure from various quarters for some sort of move in the Centre and for closer association of Indian opinion with the conduct of the war. I hope I producedsome impression, though I would not like to be sure as yet. The Punjabis are clearly very touchy over necessity for Punjabi representation. I will report further. Meantime I assume that you would see no objection to deletion of words&quot;and man-power&quot; from title of Civil Defence portfolio. Man-power aspect(largely European) is not of great importance and might well be covered bygeneral label &quot; Civil Defence.&quot;7. We may have to mark time for another day or two. For the moment Iam using as pretext for delay in announcing the delay in securing american agreement to Bajpai&apos;s appointment. Jinnah is still ill, and I have asked Lumleyto refrain from communicating with him till to-morrow. When he does so hewill not disclose any knowledge of difficulties which have arisen with the Punjab,as to which I have taken Lumley only among Governors into confidence.
(6)Telegram from Secretary of State for India to Governor-General, dated july 15, 1941.(Most Immediate.)8214. Personal. Your personal telegram of 15th July, 1634-S. I entirelyagree with your handling of Sikandar, but, while sharing your dislike of beingblackmailed, I fulhy appreciate the risks which you suggest of allowing hisGovernment to resign. We cannot afford a breakdown or even serious delay now and, having in mind the Punjab&apos;s natural grievance in the matter on the strengthof their war record as well as their psychological case of Izzat as against other provinces, I am strongly in favour of your closing with Sikandar forthwith.I should be disposed to make a virtue of necessity, give way wholeheartedly and find room for some Punjabi Sunni now. The best choice might be Sikandarhimself on the ground of his war record if he is willing and prepared to facepossible trouble with Jinnah and provided that Glancy can find an alternativePrime Minister. Failing him, I should be disposed to select Firoz. I was not previously aware of rivalry between them, but Sikandar would be in a very weakposition to complain if he had not only got his Punjab representative in yourCouncil but also had himself received the first offer.2. Effect of adding another Muslim to your Executive Council would beto produce equal number of Muslims and Hindus, whereas we have previously been proceeding on the basis of giving Hindus a slight predominance.Alternatives seem to be to accede to Punjab by adding one Punjabi Sunni Muslimat risk of invoking considerable Hindu criticism or to maintain slight Hindupredominance by adding another Hindu member at the same time. You mentionpossibility of splitting Education, Health and Lands as well as of separatingLabour from Commerce. The former would enable you to create separate portfolioof &quot; Indians Overseas.&quot; In the event of your adopting this suggestion, it mightbe a good thing to select a Hindu from United Provinces 13. I see no objection whatever to dropping sub-title &quot; Man Power &quot; fromportfolio of Civil Defence.4. I have discussed issue with Anderson and Attlee. Both consider moral,as apart from constitutional, case of Punjab a strong one, and would give waywholeheartedly at once. Both also think that, in view of addition of extraMuslim, you would be well advised to add another Hindu. Meantime, I agreethat delay can be ascribed to BajpaFs U.S.A. appointment.5. Foregoing has been composed in the light of your 1627-S, 1633-S and1634-S, and I note that you will be telegraphing further after seeing Glancy.by issuing our announcement in its original form and letting it be known at thesame time that a further appointment was understood to be imminent, leavingthat appointment to be made, say, a fortnight or a month later. I should be grateful for your comments as early as possible.
Telegram from Governor-General to Secretary of Statefor India, dated 16th July, 194-1&apos;l6k9S.   MOST MEDIATE.Your personal telegram of July 16th.     Punjab position.    I am glad that we cannot have a breakdown over this business.     Only questionnow is tactics.2.      There is no change in attitude of Punjab Government but Glancy isdiscussing with them again today.     I have continued to give no indication that I am prepared to compromise, though you of course know my mind onthat matter.3.      I agree with you that, whether they climb down or not, we should maketwo extra portfolios.     If they do climb down then we can meet them withall the better grace.    If they remain obstinate thoy will at any rate havemade their point and we shall avoid the appearance of having capitulatedto one province.     In the light of your viows I would drop for the presentmy suggestion to drop Clow, and would make the new portfolios (a) Labour(b) Indians Overseas.k*      I agree also that one should go to a Moslem and one to a Hindu.    one must of course go to the Punjab.      I have carefully considered youromission of United Provinces for the other, but I do not favour it.     Theonly prominent Hindu there is Kunzru.     He has declined National defence council and would be likely to decline Executive.      I think wise course isto give it to Bengal.     That also has advantage of securing representation for other major co-operating province.5*     As regards personnel, Sikandar has been quite positive both inwriting and orally that he does not want to be considered for ExecutiveCouncil or to leave Punjab.      I would myself welcome Piroz as Punjabrepresentative if our decision was to give Moslem seat to Punjab.      Inthat event I would favour Nalini   Sarker subject to Herbert&apos;s reaction.I anticipate however that Bengal will be anxious to get Moslemrepresentation for themselves, and alternative which I see is to take in Nazimuddin plus a Punjab Hindu if Nazimuddin is willing to serve and prepared to take his chance with Jinnah.     I cannot guarantee that.     Ifhe is not willing to serve that strengthens case for Piroz - Sarkar com-bination, but at the moment, after discussion with Aney (who will bedelighted to take an Indian overseas portfolio, together with leadership of House) and Maxwell, I definitely incline to Piroz - Sarkar combination.6.     As regards time-table, Halifax has just telegraphed State Department&apos;concurrence in Bajpai.     But this is such useful cover for us that Ipropose to reply suggesting that announcement should be made on MondayJuly 21st.     As Parliament does not sit after tomorrow till Tuesday wecannot in any circumstances get out constitutional announcement beforeTuesday.     But if we were to reach agreement on personnel for the2 extra seats by then I would work for a Press conference on Monday afternoon.7.     D.I.B. has just heard from a source in close touch with Jiunah that&quot;if any scheme regarding expansion of Executive Council is given effect in the near future Jinnah is almost certain to withdraw Moslem Leagueparty from the Central Legislature&quot;.      I rather anticipated this as apossibility but am not much worried about it though effectiveness of theCentral Legislature without either Congress or Moslem League will be negligible.     I had previously arranged with Lumley to give Jinnah warningon the day before announcement of our intentions but for obvious reasonshave asked him to hold his hand until we know where we stand.

Telegram from Secretary of State for India to Governor-General, dated 16th July, 1941 *8257.   MOST  MEDIATE.Your telegram 16th July 16A9S.I am glad there seems some way out of this difficulty. I agree thatcombination of Piroz with Nalini Sarker or alternatively Nazimuddin withPunjabi Hindu would be solution, not only as securing Bengal representationbut also on basis that it is desirable to preserve slight Hindu preponder-ence in numbers and not to advertise surrender to Punjab by takingadditional member from that Province only.    If in light of your conversationwith Aney we are comrnitte   to that course either of above combinationswould serve and possibly Chhotu Ram would be suitable Hindu from Punjab.He is I believe well though of by Sikandar.But on further consideration I feel that at present stage whenexpansion is to be justified on score of administrative conveniencethere may be more advantage in limiting that expansion than in aiming at communal balance and with this in mind you might, if position is stillopen, consider whether it would not suffice to take in Chhotu Ram alone ifhe is willing.2.      Khuzar Hayat Tiwana has been suggested to me as a just possible alternative to Piroz for Punjabi Muslim if we proceed on basis of two additional portfolios.      If, on that basis, you secure Punjabi Muslimbut cannot get Bengali Hindu, there are possibly Ambedkar (who wouldover-weight Bombay but would fit Labour portfolio) or Krishnamachari, whowould represent Madras.3.      Cabinet are to consider this troublesome matter and possible solutionstomorrow, Thursday, and I should be grateful for your final proposals as early as possible.A.     As to time-table I understand your proposal is that I should laywhite Paper next Tuesday,  22nd July and answer private notice question as contemplated for last Tuesday and that it is only announcement asto Bajpai that is contemplated for Monday 21st.     Please confirm.

199itINDIA OFFICE,17th July, 1941.Telegram from Governor-General to Secretary of State forIndia, dated 16th July, 1941.IMMEDIATE. -1--&quot;-1655*S.        My telegram of today 1649-S.     There are signs that the Punjabposition is easing.   Glancy (on whom I continue to maintain the strongest possible pressure) reports today that two of the Punjab Cabinet realise that this business is not so feasible as it looks.     In the light of thathe has again discussed with Sikandar who after explaining again in great detail the difficulties which his party and he himself anticipated in theevent of expansion without a Punjab representative, suggested that thedifficulties might be overcome if we could work gradually on the followingtime-table:   Announcement now only of National Defence Council of which he thinks most highly and on which the greatest stress should be laid coupled with announcement of separation of Law and Supply and appointments of SultanAhmed and Mody which he thinks impeccable, coupled with the announcementof Raghavendra Rao to succeed Bajpai when he goes;     this to be followedafter interval of 2 months by announcement of appointment of Aney; Aney&apos;appointment to be followed a fortnight later by announcement of Hydari anda Punjabi appointment to be announced say 2 months later.     His attitudeseems to be that if 5 new members are announced at once, the whole world willsay this is definite expansion and it must include a Punab;     If it is donein.driblets as suggested above and a Punjabi comes in in 4 or 5 months timedifficulties will not be the same.2.     I am refraining from giving Glancy or Sikandar any indication ofmy view.     For the moment it is of course impossible for us, now that the appointments have been approved by the King and that all concerned have accepted, to agree to this time-tnble.     But it is all to the good that Punjabis coming off its perch.     I am telegraphing in terras of my immediatelysucceeding telegram to Herbert and will let you know result.     Tactics I have in view with Punjab would be that I am very glad that they realiseimpossibility of bargaining on this sort of issue;   that it would not be possibleto work to gradual timetable of this nature since appointments have beenapproved by the-King and accepted by individuals;   at the same time Irecognised their anxiety to assist and appreciate on reflection their difficulties;   that I had always intended to make with your approval afurther expansion later in the year which would not be confined to Punjab;that I was now going ahead with it at once and that the result would be thatthey would obtain a Punjabi seat as part of extended expansion.3.     The other matter of much importance which has emerged from Glancy&apos;sconversations with Sikandar is that Sikandar will be quite content were ourchoice to fall on Noon.   That in some ways much eases our difficulties.4.     We have still two or three days in which to move.     I have deliberatelynot given Herbert much choice as to suggesting a Moslem.     I am certainthat on merits Noon would be better and less communal than Nazimuddin.   Hisselection also is more in line with our policy of choosing for expandedCouncil, which we are explicitly expanding for administrative reasons,individuals relatively colourless politically (Nazimuddin is of course a quite definite Moslem Leaguer).     I am emphasising also as you will seeto Herbert that selection will continue to be made on personal and noton party merits and basis.5.     We can consider separately successor to Firoz if that goes through -I think probably Mirza, though Mudaliar might be worth considering.Circulated by the Secretary of State for indian continuation of W.P.(g)(41)69.

IMMEDIATE.1656.     Personal and most secret.     I am still held up in announcingexpansion of council in absence of American agreement to Bajpai which ought to arrive any day now.     Delay has enabled me to ponder as toarguments for and against making at once further expansion which I have always had in view for a later date of two extra seats one for Labourone for Education Health and Lands less Indians overseas which would becomeseparate portfolios.      I am pretty clear now that we may as well go ahead straight away and avoid doing this business in driblets and I should like for E.H. and L. vacancy to appoint a Hindu from Bengal (it has gotto be a Hindu because of communal balance in my new council).     further expansion will of course be justified solely on administrative grounds andwould not purport to be political in character and selection as in caseof other Executive Council vacancies would be entering on personal merits and not party in character.     The best man that I can think of is NaliniSarker (we would replace him on the National Defence Council).     Gratefulif you would telegraph your reactions as urgently as possible so that Ican go to the Secretary of State.     Please also treat this as most secret and for yourself and your secretary alone.     If anything is to be done it would have to be done very quickly.Addressed to Governor of Bengal repeated to Secretary of State.Telegram from Governor-General to Secretary ofState for India, dated 17th July, 1941.MOST IMMEDIATE.1662-S.     Your telegram of June 16th No.8257*     Many thanks.     Youwill by now hp.ve had my telegram 1655-S of July 16th giving result offurther discussions between Glancy and his Ministers and text of myreference to Herbert about Sarker.2.      I would prefer to hold to (a)  two additional portfolios.    (b) ThePiroz - Sarker combination.3*     As regards (a) it would not be easy to resile after my talks withAney.      But apart from that I attach great importance to avoiding sofar as possible appearance of surrender to Punjab pressure, and aBengal appointment would help to avoid that.      I doubt too a singleadditional Hindu appointment even though from Punjab giving realsatisfaction to that Province.    Given existing communal tension I attachvery considerable importance to maintenance of present communalproportions.     So far as administrative argument goes there is a clearcase for a separate Labour portfolio.    Indians Overseas is lees strong.But it will relieve what is at present a very heavy charge, and I thinkthat (the general respect in which Aney is held apart) it will be popular politically and will not attract any undue criticism.    Aneywill also of course be Leader of Assembly.4-*     As regards (b) position is eased by the fact of Sikandar&apos;s readiness to accept Piroz and he would, I would judge, clearly prefer a Moslem.Khiznr Hayat is very light stuff.     Chotu Ram does net compare withSarker.     Madras is already represented by Mudaliar and Krishnmachariwould be regarded as a second States representative.     I want AmbedkarTelegrara from Governor-General of India to governor of Bengal, dated 15th July, 1941.

but will probably try to fit him in if and when Clow goes to Assam.Unless Herbert raises some deeisive objection therefore still reccmmendthe Firoz-Sarker solution.5.     Your paragraph No.A&apos;     That is not quite right .    Bajpai&apos;sAmerican post to be announced in morning papers of Monday July 21st:our main announcement of expansion etc.  (with any necessary draftingchanges) to be announced in morning papers of Tuesday July 22nd here,White Paper giving text to be presented to Parliament by you on tuesday afternoon and censorship to prevent any comment or quotationfrom being transmitted Home by air or before the White Paper hasbeen laid.




</content>
</cab>
