<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/33/39 images: 326-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT J g f)Printed for the War Cabinet.   January 1943.secret. / Copy No.     24W.p. (43) 39. , /January 25, 1943. to BE KEPT  UNDER  LOCK  AND  key it is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document war CABINET.THE UNITED NATIONS&apos; PLAN.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for India.THE plan for the preservation of world peace produced by the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, in consultation with the Minister of aircraft production (W.P. (43) 31). is based on the assumption (Paragraphs 5, 7 and 23)that the three Great Powers, viz., the British Commonwealth, the United States,and Russia, will in future, pending the establishment of some effective world council, continue to be &quot; equally interested in maintaining the peace everywherein the world and will speak with one voice and act together whenever andwherever it may be threatened.&quot; It is further assumed that the rest of the27 United Nations will continue to support, or at least acquiesce in, this plan.What warrant, either in history or in present probabilities, is there for these assumptions ?They are, in fact, substantially the same assumptions as those upon which theLeague of Nations was based, with the exception that the exclusion of the defeatedenemy Powers is somewhat more strongly emphasised, that nothing is said aboutneutrals, and that the military responsibility of the three principal Powers ismore definitely stressed. We have the same doctrine of the &quot; indivisibility ofpeace &apos;&apos;; the same assumption that nations are more concerned with themaintenance of peace everywhere than with their own immediate interests; thesame belief that the particular nations, whom circumstances have brought together on the same side in a particular struggle, will continue to see eye to eye, to takethe same view as to what constitutes aggression or the danger of aggression and act upon it. and at the very least, not to turn aggressors themselves.All these assumptions and hopes were falsified after the last Avar. Americaran out of the League of Nations at the start, in obedience to that instinct forisolation and avoidance of commitment which is as deep-seated in Americandemocracy as its readiness to ventilate plans for world regeneration. It Avas thesame instinct which made her run out of the guarantee to France. In our case,too, the instinct against definite commitments was strong enough to make us go back on our guarantee on a technicalitjr the subsequent Locarno guarantee, givento both sides, never committed us in the same way. The araguer obligations of theLeague we accepted, though never quite clear in our minds whether there were, infact, any obligations beyond those of conference and conciliation, or, at most, ofeconomic sanctions if everybody else agreed to impose them. While France looked upon the League, a^ery much as the Foreign Secretary iioav looks upon the united nations, as an instrument for the definite and prolonged disarmament of thedefeated enemy, Ave, in accordance with our traditional incapacity to remember,began to swing toAvards a pro-German and anti-French outlook almost from the start, and subsequently pressed forward disarmament schemes Avhich could onlyweaken the relative strength of the victors of 1918. Meanwhile, tAvo of thePowers who made &quot; the Avorld safe for democracy and peace &quot; in 1918, began a career of local aggression in Asia and Africa, to which avc replied by futilegestures which had no real will behind them, and Avhich only drove them into thatcoalition of aggression which has all but overwhelmed the world.   It may well be[24942]
said that nothing contributed more to the grim reality of this universal war thanthe fiction of &quot; indivisible peace &quot; with no indivisible will to enforce peacebehind it.All this was the result, not of abnormal wickedness nor of abnormal feeble-ness on the part of statesmen, but of natural tendencies which are bound toreassert themselves. Let me begin by drawing the picture of what, in fact, islikely to happen when Germany collapses, not the blue print of what ought to happen. Those of our Allies who are on the spot Prussians, Poles, Czechs,Yugoslavs. Greeks will seize what they can and, by massacre and expulsion,effectively fortify their case. Neither we nor the Americans will be in time to stop them or be prepared to reverse the accomplished fact. With our men andtheir families clamouring for demobilization we shall certainly not be prepared touse military force for that purpose. Nor are we likely to agree as to withholdingfood from starving populations because boundaries are still unsettled. We shalldo as the Big Three did in 1919 : look important and pretend to settle a Europeanmap already settled by those immediately concerned.By the time the accomplished fact has been thus regularised the new BigThree will be far more concerned with their own affairs than with the affairs ofEurope. The United States have, ordinary politics apart, been accumulatinginternal economic and social problems which will require all their attention, andwdiich will enormously reinforce the inevitable swing of the pendulum towards their traditional isolationism. The Soviet Government, as Mr. Baggallay haspointed out in a very revealing despatch (U. 67/67/70), will &quot; occupy themselvesfirst and foremost with the reconstruction of their own devastated areas.&apos;&quot; Weshall have to face immensely difficult problems of reconstruction at home and inthe Empire. India alone may dominate all our thoughts for years. In all ourcountries these urgent and inescapable problems will bulk far larger than theconfused tangle of rights and wrongs in Europe.Even to the extent that the Big Three do continue to intervene we must face the prospect that their intervention is no more likely to be united or whole-hearted than last time. The Russian outlook and that of the two Anglo-SaxonPowers are fundamentally different. The latter will at any rate be anxious topromote European peace for its own sake. Russia will be primarily concernedwith the extension of her territory and influence and, secondarily, with the spread of Communism. If mutual antagonisms among the European nations are calculated to promote those ends she is not likely to refrain from encouragingthem. As between ourselves and the Americans our general objects may be thesame, as they were in the case of France and ourselves after 1919. But differences of temperament and outlook will only too often create divergences of policy. TheDarlan affair is only a foretaste of the disagreements which are bound to arise.In Paragraph 23 of the memorandum it is suggested that, while a certain measure of &quot; regionalism &quot; should be encouraged, anything in the nature of a&quot;limited liability&quot; under which each Great Power were regarded as solely responsible for the peace of a given area would lead to group rivalries and &quot; hencesow the seeds of future war &quot;; the conclusion being that in principle all the BigThree should be equally interested in maintaining the peace everywhere. Is itsuggested that the Monroe Doctrine is to be regarded henceforth as a menace tothe peace of the world, and that we, Russia (and China ?) should in future showourselves &quot; equally interested &quot; with the United States in maintaining the peace of Central and South America? If, on the other hand, there is much to be said on the other side of the Atlantic for the regional principle and for the monroe doctrine, is there not also something to be said for considering that the peace ofEurope may be best maintained by the European nations themselves and by theirmore directly interested neighbours, viz., Russia and ourselves, and not by adistant and essentially irresponsible democracy on the other side of the Atlantic?The question is perhaps more theoretical than practical, for the United States willprobably &quot; pull out &quot; of Europe whatever we, or the present american administration, may say.After all, there is this to be said for regionalism on the American plan, thatthere is, on the part of the major Power concerned, a definite sense ofresponsibility and a direct instinct of resistance to any form of externalintervention that could lead to aggression. On the other hand, the lesser Statesnot only know whom to look to for protection, but have no temptation to play offone protector against another. A corresponding Monroe Doctrine in our case would cover the territories of the British Empire, together with the effective control of the Mediterranean and of the Middle Eastern countries lying athwart
the sea and air route to India, Malaya and Australasia. We did, in substance,assert that doctrine in 1927 in our reservation to the Kellogg Pact against war as a instrument of policy.The cases of Europe and the Far East are not so simple. In the Far East thesituation is still essentially fluid. It is still far too early to say whether Chinawill emerge as an active self-dependent factor or once again go to pieces in civil war. In the former eventuality she will, in fact, become the centre of her ownregion. In the latter, the United States, Russia and ourselves will.have the choice of either agreeing upon measures which will restore order in the Far East, orof leaving it to anarchy, or, lastly, of intervening against each other at the riskof major war.The essence of the European situation is that its nations are too strong, both&apos;in fact and in national self-consciousness, to be subject for long to any externaldomination. In the first stage, immediately after victory we may hope that thekind of Armistice and Reconstruction Commission envisaged by the foreign secretary&apos;s memorandum will be able, under the supervision of the Big Three,, toset the Continent on its feet politically and economically. But the european nations will very soon want to determine their own destinies. The real questionthen will be whether they are capable of coming together and forming some sort of unity among themselves, or whether we and Russia the United States almost certainly by then having withdrawn from active intervention are to be drawn into the conflicts of a divided Europe and find ourselves in opposite camps. Theformer is clearly the one solution calculated to lead to a stable and peacefulsituation, and we should, in my view, make it the definite and publicly proclaimedgoal of our European policy.It will be said that any European polity in which the Big Three, or at leastwe and Russia, do not actively and permanently participate will, sooner or later,fall under German control and become a mere instrument of German ambitions.The answer to that is not, I believe, to be found in attempting for an indefinitetime to police Europe from without. Nothing, indeed, would be more calculated to rally Europe round Germany as the defender of European independence. Itlies, first and foremost, in a defeat of Germany so complete, and an immediatepunishment of Germany so drastic, as to deprive her of the power, and cure herof the desire, to reverse the verdict of this war before her neighbours have, bytheir own growth and by union among themselves, become capable of holding theirown against her and dealing with her as equals. The expulsion of the germans from East Prussia, Upper Silesia, and the Sudetenland, as weli as the surrender of Alsace-Lorraine and the Saar to France, are instances of the type of reductionof the material and economic base for aggression which is likely to be far more effective than schemes of control which are almost certain to break down withina very few years. A Germany so cut down and chastened may become a goodEuropean and settle down into equal partnership with her neighbours.What is true in the political field is no less true in the economic field. Theidea that the nations are prepared to hand over their economic independence tosuch bodies as a World Economic Council, to an International Investment board or a Commodity Control, or that there will be any agreement among the major powers to establish such institutions on a permanent basis, as apart frommeasures of immediate post-war relief, is just sheer illusionism. The wholetrend of the world is. rightly or wrongly, towards economic nationalism. Bythat is meant not necessarily a policy of rigid protectionism. Economicnationalism may be liberal as well as exclusive. But it treats trade as a matterof national, not of individual, concern, and as an integral part of social and defence policy, and not as a sphere apart. It is a trend that cannot be directlyreversed by trying to set the Humpty-Dumpty of the individualist laisser-faireinternationalism of the 19th century on his wall again under Anglo-Americanauspices. The easiest way to modify and mitigate it is on the same regionalistlines as are most likely to afford a solution of the political problem. Mutualeconomic arrangements within a &quot; region &quot; are the natural concomitants of mutualpolitical support, and afford the best means of strengthening the sense of acommon peaceful interest.The criticisms I have ventured to put forward are in no sense intended as an objection to the general conception of keeping the United Nations together aslong a,s possible over the immediate post-war period or to our proclaiming that asan object. What I do regard as dangerous and likely to lead to disaster, for our-selves and for the world, is to delude ourselves once again by publicly proclaimedannouncements of a new world structure of permanent peace based on ignoring
all the stubborn realities in the varying outlook and behaviour of those intenselyindividualistic entities which we call nations, and in doing so neglect the more practical measures for promoting the peace and prosperity of the world whichcan be achieved by recognising those realities. Let us be content to build, on amore limited scale but more securely, on the lines of the natural evolution towardslarger group entities as the immediately feasible step in advance towards theultimate goal of a world system.      &apos; -In other words, I would urge that, so far as we have a definite conception ofthe line which we wish the immediate future organisation of the world to take,we should favour development on regional rather than on world lines. At thesame time we should never lose out of sight the fact that it is those immediately concerned who will decide these matters, and that we can at best only exert alimited influence on the course of other peoples. What we can do. and be sure of doing effectively, is to concentrate on furthering the unity, prosperity and security of our own particular &quot; region,&quot; namely, the British Commonwealth andthe territories and peoples that come within its orbit. Our success in that taskwill not only secure our own peace and protect our own heritage of freedomagainst the incalculably fluctuating course of future events outside, but will prove a far greater influence on others to imitate our example than anything else thatwe can do. Frankly to proclaim that as our goal will give a new life and newstrength to all our peoples, and give to the world outside a new sense of England&apos;power of vision and leadership.L. S. A.India Office. January 25, 1943.



</content>
</cab>
