<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/36/20 images: 212-221</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 4943SECRET.W.M. (43)152nd Conclusions.Copy No.fgWAR   CABINET 152 (43).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Wednesday, 10th November, 1943,-at 6 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.p lord President of the Council,The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Minister of Production.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,.Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs (Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Secretary of State for theHome Department and Minister ofHome Security.Field-Marshal the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, Prime Minister of the Unionof South Africa.The following were also present:The  Right  Hon.   Viscount   Simon,Lord Chancellor (Items 5-7).The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary   of    State    for   Burma(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Thomas Johnston,.  M.P./Secretary of State for Scotland(Items 4-6).The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,President of the Board of Education(Items 5-6).The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Leathers,Minister of War Transport (items-2).The Right Hon. Sir William Jowitt,K.C., M.P., Minister without Port-folio (Item 4).The Right Hon. Richard Law, M.P.,Minister of State.The Right Hon. Sir Donald Somer-vell, K.C.. M.P., Attorney-General(Item 7).The Right Hon. -Lord Beaverbrook,- Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M:P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,  M.P.,  Minister  of aircraft production.The Right Hon. R. S. Hudson, M.P..Minister     of     Agriculture     andFisheries (Items 4-6).The   Right   Hon.   Lord   Woolton.Minister of Food (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. W. S. Morrison, K.C.,M.P., Minister of Town and country planning (Item 4).    rThe Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. Harcourt Johnstone,M.P.^ Secretary, Department of overseas Trade (Items 1-2).The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (Item 7).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.[26422]B
WAR   CABINET 152 (43).Contents.Minute. No. Subject. page 1      Return of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs fromthe Moscow Conference    ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     1512      Shipping ......... ................     151Indian Grain Requirements.Canadian Offer of Wheat for India.3      Ireland ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      .....      ....       ....     152Application of Members of Parliament for Leave to Travel to eire.4      Land Utilisation in Rural Areas    ....       ....      ....       ....     1525      Parliament      ....      ....      ....      ....       ....      ....      ....     153King&apos;s Speeches on Brorogation and Opening of Parliament.6      Conscientious Objectors employed as Teachers of Youth     1537      War Criminals ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     154
1. - The Prime Minister, on behalf of the War Cabinet gaveSecretary of a warm welcome to Mr. Eden on his return from his memorable and state for successful visit to Moscow.Foreign Affairsfrom theMoscowConference.Shipping. 2.   On the 24th September the War Cabinet had authorisedIndian Grain the shipment of up to 200,000 tons of food grains to India by therequirements. end of 1943 and had agreed that the position should be reviewed(Previous again at the end of the year in the light of the Indian harvests.Reference- The War Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by theW.M. (43) 131st Secretary of State for India (W.P. (43) 504) suggesting that further conclusions, review could not be postponed until the end of the year.Minute 1.) The Secretary of State for India said that the food situation-in India gave cause for grave anxiety. The Indian rice harvestwould not reach the market until January; and, to support theefforts which were being made to draw a substantial proportion ofit into Government hands, it was important that in the meantimeimports of food grains should continue steadily. If a decision regarding further imports were delayed until the end of the year,there would be a dangerous interruption in the flow of supplies.The Government of. India took the view that the minimum requiredto give them a fighting chance of extracting supplies fromcultivators and restoring confidence was an assurance that an import of 50,000 tons of food grains per month would be maintained for a year. In view of the shipping difficulties, the Secretary ofState was not prepared to press the War Cabinet to commit them-selves to a long-term programme of this kind; but he did think it essential that arrangements should be made to ship to India from australia (i) a further 50,000 tons of wheat before the end of 1943,in addition to the shipments already authorised; and (ii) another100,000 tons of wheat in January/February 1944.The Minister of War Transport said that it would be. impracticable to provide shipping for any additional shipments ofwheat from Australia to India in the remaining months of 1943.In the first two months of 1944, however, it should be possible to ship up to 100,000 tons, though this would be at the expense ofreplenishing the stocks in the Middle East.The view of the War Cabinet was that an assurance might nowbe given to the Government of India that arrangements would bemade to ship up to 100,000 tons of wheat from Australia to India&quot; X &quot; during the first two months of 1944. It should, however, be made clear that this did not imply any promise to undertake a long-term programme of shipping food grains to India at the rate of50,000 tons a month.The Secretary of State for India said that he had received that day a telegram indicating that the Canadian Government could make available one 10,000-ton Canadian ship for carrying to Indiapart of the Canadian offer of 100,000 tons of wheat.The War Cabinet were informed that, if this Canadian shipwere made available for this purpose, it would be withdrawn fromthe pool of shipping available for Anglo-American war purposes.In these circumstances the War Cabinet decided that, in view oftheir decision of the 2nd. November regarding the Canadian offer of wheat for India, they must press the Canadian Government notto use this ship for a purpose which they regarded as whollyuneconomic from the shipping point of view.The War Cabinet-(1) Invited the Minister of War Transport to arrange for the shipment of up to 100,000 tons of wheat from australia to India in the first two months of 1944.[26422] b 2Canadian offer of wheat forIndia.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 149thConclusions,Minute 3.)
(2) Authorised the Secretary of State for India to communicate this decision to the Government of India in the termsindicated at &quot; X &quot; above.(3) Invited the Prime Minister to send a personal message tothe Prime Minister of Canada deprecating the proposed allocation of a Canadian ship to carry to India part ofthe Canadian offer of 100,000 tons of wheat. TheMinister of War Transport undertook to furnish a draft which might serve as a basis for the Prime Minister&apos;message.(4) Took note, with approval, of the terms of the reply whichthe Secretary of State for India proposed to give to a parliamentary Question on the following day, asking whether shipping would be made available to convey toIndia the wheat and milk which had been offered by theCanadian and South African Governments respectively.Ireland.Application ofMembers ofParliament forLeave to travel to. Eire.(previous reference:W.M. (43) 92ndConclusions,Minute 1.)3. The Home Secretary and Minister of Home Security saidthat he had received applications from three Members of parliament for&apos;permission to travel to Eire.On the 2nd July the War Cabinet had decided.(i) that applica-tions for leave to travel to Eire should be dealt with on.the same basis as applications in respect of any other neutral country;(ii) that facilities for travel to any neutral country should be withheld unless the Government were satisfied that a definite publicadvantage would be served by the journey, or that the applicanthad bona fide domestic business to transact in that country whichwas urgent and important and could not be transacted without a personal visit; and (iii) that these rules should, apply to Membersof Parliament in the same way as they applied to other persons.Under these rules the present applicants could not make out acase to warrant the grant of permission to travel to Eire. On theother hand, one of them had visited Eire previously for similarpolitical purposes, and no harm had come of his visit. It seemed unlikely that there would be any positive disadvantage, from thepoint of view of the public interest, in allowing any of these threeapplicants to visit Eire. This view was shared by the Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and our High Commissioner in Dublin.The question thus arose whether it was worth while to risk Parlia-mentary controversy by refusing these applications.The War Cabinet saw no reason to modify the rules which theyhad laid down on the 2nd July and considered that these applica-tions should be refused if they could not be brought within thoserules.The War Cabinet-Invited the Home Secretary and Minister of Home security to deal with these applications on the basis of the ruleslaid down at their Meeting on the 2nd July.LandUtilisation in rural Areas,4. The War Cabinet considered a Memorandum by theMinister without Portfolio (W.P. (43) 485) covering the draft of a proposed statement on the recommendations made in the Report ofthe Committee on Land Utilisation in Rural Areas presided overby Lord Justice Scott.The Minister without Portfolio said that this Report had been presented to Parliament in August 1942; and it was desirable thatthe Government should now indicate their general attitude towardsits recommendations. The draft statement which was appended tohis Memorandum had been drawn up in consultation with theDepartments primarily concerned. It was designed to be made byway of Written Answer to Parliamentary Questions. Para-graphs 1-12 would form the answer to a Question addressed to theMinister of Town and Country Planning; and the answer in the
153W.M. 152(43),: remaining paragraphs, which related to Scotland, would be givenby the Secretary of State for Scotland.There might be some desire to debate the Committee&apos;s recom-mendations in the House of Commons; but it would be preferable,if a Debate was to take place, that it should be held after this statement had been made.It was proposed that the statement should not be made untilthe new Session; it would follow conveniently upon the reference in The King&apos;s Speech to the Reports recommending further controlover the use of land in Great Britain.The War Cabinet-Agreed that a statement on the Report of the Committeeon Land Utilisation in Rural Areas should be made, earlyin the new Session, in the terms of the draft annexed toW.P. (43) 485.Parliament. 5.   The War Cabinet had before them a Note by the LordKing&apos;s Speeches President of the Council (W.P. (43) 509) covering drafts for Theon Prorogation King&apos;s Speeches on the Prorogation and Opening of Parliament,and Opening which had been prepared by the Committee appointed by the war of Parliament.    Cabinet on the 5th October.(Previous The War Cabinet-Reference :W.M. (43) 135th Approved the drafts of The King&apos;s Speeches subject to a conclusions, number of verbal amendments adopted in the course of the minute 3.) discussion.   (The amended drafts are being circulated tothe War Cabinet as W.P. (43) 513.)6. The Prime Minister said that he had been surprised to learn that a number of conscientious objectors were runningauthorised youth organisations subsidised by the Board of Educa-tion, or were employed as teachers by local authorities. While he did not suggest that anything should be done to impair the statutoryrights of conscientious objectors, he thought&apos; that they might dogreat harm when employed as teachers of youth.The War Cabinet were reminded that the appointment of teachers or of paid youth workers rested not with the Board ofEducation, but with the local education authority or the voluntarybody concerned. A large number of local education authoritiesdeclined to employ as teachers men registered as conscientious objectors. Others took a different view. If, however, in any casea teacher who was a conscientious objector was found to be abusinghis position and propagating his views among his pupils, this wouldbe regarded as a grave professional default. No such case had so fararisen.Discussion showed that the general opinion of the War cabinet was that, if an attempt were now made to debar all conscientious objectors from being employed as teachers of youth, controversywould be aroused and considerable difficulties would result.The President of the Board of Education said that he proposedto give instructions to the Board&apos;s Inspectorate to keep this matter under review, so as to ensure that any cases in which an undesirableinfluence might be exercised were at once brought to light.The War Cabinet-Agreed that the matter should be left on this basis.ConscientiousObjectorsEmployed asTeachers ofYouth.
Offices of the War Cabinet, S. W. 1,10th November,. 1943.War Criminals. 7. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous Prime Minister and Minister of Defence (W.P. (43) 496).   In thisEeference:        Memorandum the Prime Minister pointed out that the JointW.M. (43) 103rd Declaration on Atrocities signed in Moscow would result in a largeConclusions,      number of lesser war criminals being handed over to the SovereignMinute 2.)        States against whom  their outrages had been committed.   it remained, however, to deal with the major criminals, and hesuggested that the United Nations should take steps to prepare asingle list of such major war criminals, who would be declaredoutlaws and might be put to death Avithout trial on falling into thehands of the Armed Forces.The Prime Minister said that he thought that the process of preparing and publishing a relatively short list of the major war criminals would be calculated on the whole to shorten the War, since it would isolate these named war criminals from the other leadingpersonages in enemy countries.In discussion, it was suggested that the procedure proposed should not be applied to Quislings, who should be handed over tothe country whose nationals they were, to be tried for treachery.The proposal that major war criminals on the suggested list shouldbe shot as outlaws, without reference to higher authority, was felt by some Ministers to be open to grave objection. To shoot menwithout trial in this way would be to set a very dangerous precedent, however fully it might be justified in the cases of menwho had undoubtedly committed what might be called a capitaloffence against civilisation.On the other hand, it was pointed out that an impossible position would result if minor criminals were to be tried and in somecases sentenced to death, while no provision was made for the punishment of the major war criminals. The process of legal trialwas clearly inappropriate for the major war criminals. In their case, what was called for was a political decision, or an Act of State,on behalf of the United Nations,The War Cabinet-(1) Decided to record no formal decision.(2) Invited the Lord Chancellor, the Attorney-General and theMinister of Aircraft Production to redraft the PrimeMinister&apos;s Memorandum on the basis that (a) Quislings were excluded from the scope of theproposal.(5) Any person in the suggested list of major war criminals coming into the hands of the Armed- Forces of the United Nations should be seized and held pending a decision by the United Nations asto their fate.

Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W. 1,10th November,. 1943.War Criminals. 7. The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the(Previous Prime Minister and Minister of Defence (W.P. (43) 496).   In this reference:        Memorandum the Prime Minister pointed out that the JointW.M. (43) 103rd Declaration on Atrocities signed in Moscow would result in a largeConclusions,      number of lesser war criminals being handed over to the SovereignMinute 2.)        States against whom their outrages had been committed.   it remained, however, to deal with the major criminals, and hesuggested that the United Nations should take steps to prepare asingle list of such major war criminals, who would be declaredoutlaws and might be put to death without trial on falling into thehands of the Armed Forces.The Prime Minister said that he thought that the process of preparing and publishing a relatively short list of the major war criminals would be calculated on the whole to shorten the War, since it would isolate these named war criminals from the other leadingpersonages in enemy countries.In discussion, it was suggested that the procedure proposed should not be applied to Quislings, who should be handed over tothe country whose nationals they were, to be tried for treachery.The proposal that major war criminals on the suggested list shouldbe shot as outlaws, without reference to higher authority, was felt by some Ministers to be open to grave objection. To shoot menwithout trial in this way would be to set a very dangerous precedent, however fully it might be justified in the cases of menwho had undoubtedly committed what might be called a capitaloffence against civilisation.On the other hand, it was pointed out that an impossible position would result if minor criminals were to be tried and in somecases sentenced to death, while no provision was made for the punishment of the major war criminals. The process of legal trialwas clearly ina/ppropriate for the major war criminals. In their case, what was called for was a political decision, or an Act of State,on behalf of the United Nations.The War Cabinet-(1) Decided to record no formal decision.(2) Invited the Lord Chancellor, the Attorney-General and theMinister of Aircraft Production to redraft the PrimeMinister&apos;s Memorandum on the basis that (a) Quislings were excluded from the scope of theproposal.(b) Any person in the suggested list of major war criminals coming into the hands of the Armed&apos;  Forces of the United Nations should be seized and held pending a decision by the United Nations asto their fate.



</content>
</cab>
