<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/40/10 images: 98-115</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC KAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENTSECRET. Copy No.W.P. (43) 360(Also C.O.S. (43) 228)5th August, 1943WAR cabinet weekly RESUME(No. 205)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 0700 29th July, to0700 5th August,1943[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]Cabinet War Room.
COMBINED OPERATIONS COMMAND.1.   Raids by the S.S. Brigade have taken place during the week : Night 31st/1st.Two small reconnaissance raids near Eletot (between Fecamp and St. Valery-en-Caux) and at Onival (south of the R. Somme) were abandoned owing to weather.The M.T.B. carrying the latter raiding party encountered enemy R-boats on thereturn passage and suffered some damage and one casualty.Night 3rd I Uh.Three small reconnaissance raids were made during the night.Near Eletot, eight all ranks were landed, and having gained useful intelhgence were re-embarked by M.T.B. 344 on the night of the 4th/5th.   The M.T.B.was attacked by E-boats whilst awaiting to re-embark the patrol, but successfullyevaded them.Weather conditions prevented an attempt to land by ten all ranks nearQuendplage (north of R. Somme).Four all ranks reconnoitred, from canoes, the East Pier, Dunkirk. Activityashore prevented landing. During the absence of the canoes the two M.T.Bs.which had brought them were attacked by three enemy small craft and lost touchwith the canoes, which proceeded back to England and were sighted by our aircraft and subsequently picked up.naval SITUATION.General Review.2. Allied ships have carried out a number of bombardments off Sicily and southern Italy.Eleven U-boats, including three supply U-boats, have been sunk, five probably sunk and two probably damaged.It is estimated that 31 U-boats have been sunk during July.Shipping casualties, principally caused by U-boat attacks off the east african Coast, have been moderately light.Home Waters.3. On the night of the 29th/30th, M.G.Bs. damaged three enemy trawlers inan engagement with a trawler patrol off the Dutch coast. Early on the 1st,coastal forces attacked a sperrbrecher with four trawlers off Ijmuiden and disabled the sperrbrecher.Mediterranean.4. H.M. and Allied ships have continued to bombard coastal targets in sicily and Southern Italy in support of military operations.On the night of the 27th/28th, M.G.Bs. shelled railway targets at Giardini(N.E. Sicily) at close range. On the 29th, H.M. Cruisers, Aurora and Penelope,with six destroyers, bombarded bridges south of Locri (toe of Italy). On the night of the 31st/1st, Euryalus (cruiser), with a destroyer, bombardedVibo Valentia (west coast of Calabria). Sirius and Dido (cruisers), with three destroyers, shelled the bridge at the mouth of the River Oliva (north side of theGulf of Eufemia). Aurora and Penelope, with six destroyers, bombardedCotrone; fires were started in the harbour area and two patrol craft were sunk.On the following night, Wheatland and Quantock (destroyers) shelled the Coastroad near Taormina without opposition. On the 2nd, the U.S. Cruiser Savannahbombarded roads and gun positions near Agata (north coast of Sicily). Onthe 4th, H.M. Monitor Roberts bombarded the coastal road and railway atTaormina.5. Three M.T.Bs. on the night of the 31st/1st, engaged three E-boats southof Reggio and severely damaged one of them; two M.T.Bs. were slightly damaged.
H.M. Monitor Erebus was slightly damaged by air attack on the night of the23rd/24th at Augusta; five of her crew were killed and 25 wounded. In an air attack at Palermo on the night of the 31st/lst the U.S. Minesweepers Striveand Skill were damaged. The U.S. Destroyer Shubrick was damaged in an air raid on the night of the 3rd/4th at Palermo : two of the crew were killed and16 wounded.On the 1st, 8,692 tons of cargo were discharged at Augusta and 4,187 tons at Syracuse.6. H.M. S/M Safari, on patrol off Corsica between the 18th and the 25th,sank two motor minesweepers, an anti-submarine steam yacht, a minelayer anda trawler. H.M. S/M Trooper damaged a 2,000-ton ship northbound off theAlbanian coast.7. The French naval authorities took over control of Philippeville harbour and approaches on the 1st.Black Sea,8. Russian cutters in the Sea of Azov sank two barges and two other lightcraft in engagements on the 19th and 21st.Pacific.9. U.S. submarines operating in the Pacific and Far Eastern waters have sunk two large transports, six cargo ships and two medium-sized tankers, andhave damaged four cargo ships.A leutians.10. On the 30th, U.S. light craft shelled the main camp on Kiska island and also Gertrude Cove.New Guinea.11. Allied M.T.B.&apos;s, early on the 29th, attacked 30 barges in Vitiaz Strait(N.E. New Guinea) and sank seven of them.Solomons.12. Allied M.T.B.&apos;s sank two out of four barges attacked in the BlackettStrait (S.W. of Kolombangara Island).Anti-Submarine Operations.13. Forty attacks on U-boats have been reported during the week : 29 by aircraft and 11 by ships.On the 30th, in the Bay of Biscay, Sunderland and Halifax aircraft andsloops of a support group sank three U-boats, two of which were supply U-boats.On the 1st, a Sunderland sank a U-boat in the Bay of Biscay. On the 2nd, alsoin the Biscay area, Halifax and Sunderland aircraft sank two others and, onthe 4th, a Sunderland destroyed a supply U-boat, from which 59 prisoners were captured.On the 30th a U.S. aircraft sank a U-boat off Recife and, on the following day, U.S. and Brazilian aircraft sank another south of Rio de Janeiro. On the3rd a large U-boat was sunk E.S.E. of Recife by U.S. aircraft and the U.S.Destroyer Moffett. An Italian U-boat was sunk of Pantelleria on the 3rd by theU.S. Destroyer Buck. Five U-boats were probably sunk by British and U.S.aircraft in the Biscay area on the 28th and 29th, off the heel of Italy byH.M. S/M Trooper on the 29th, in the Caribbean by U.S. aircraft on the 28th andsouth of Recife by U.S. aircraft on the 30th. Two attacked by British and U.S.aircraft in the Bay of Biscay were probably damaged.14. It is provisionally estimated that during July, in addition to an ItalianU-boat captured, 31 U-boats were sunk, seven were probably and 11 possibly sunk.Three of those sunk were Italian.Enemy Intelligence.German.15.   Photographic reconnaissance on the 31st showed the Koln at Kiel.[25886] b 2
Three Elbing class destroyers, which are believed to have been engaged inescorting U-boats, were sighted by aircraft west of the Bay of Biscay on the 2nd.There have been signs of increased activity among the Far Eastern blockaderunners in Biscay ports during the past fortnight.Italian.16. Reconnaissance of Taranto showed that a Regolo class cruiser had arrived on the 3rd.Japanese.17. No Japanese heavy ships have been sighted in the South or South-west pacific.It is believed that, in addition to barges, Japanese U-boats are being usedto carry supplies and reinforcements both to New Georgia and to Lae (new guinea) at night.U-boats.18.   About 85 U-boats are at sea in the Atlantic and Indian Oceans.It is estimated that the recent sinkings of supply boats will cause U-boatsnow operating in the Caribbean and off the South American coast to cut shorttheir cruises by at least a fortnight.Enemy Attack on Shipping.19. During the week U-boats are reported to have attacked five ships, ofwhich four are known to have sunk.Two ships, one of which was in a northbound convoy, were sunk in theMozambique Channel. One ship was sunk south-east of Madagascar and anothertorpedoed off Durban, but reached port.  One ship was sunk off the coast of Brazil.A ship was sunk by air attack in Palermo Harbour.Three ships were damaged by underwater explosions in Gibraltar Bay.20. The provisional figure of tonnage lost by enemy action during July,including losses during the Sicilian operations, is about 348,000 tons, amongwhich were five tankers totalling 40,000 tons.Protection of Seaborne Trade.21. During the week ending the 1st, 913 ships were convoyed. Of these,234 were in ocean convoys and 679 in British coastal convoys.Sixty-seven destroyers (including ten U.S. destroyers), 89 sloops, frigates,cutters and corvettes (including four U.S. cutters), one merchant aircraft-carrier,two escort carriers, one anti-aircraft ship, one ocean boarding vessel, one Frencharmed merchant cruiser and two cruisers were employed on escort duties.Two ocean convoys, consisting of 97 ships, arrived in Home waters without loss.22. During the week ending the 31st imports into the United Kingdom by ships in convoy totalled 754,000 tons, compared with 1,552,000 tons during theprevious seven days and an average of 1,050,700 tons during the past ten weeks.Of the week&apos;s imports, 339,000 tons were mineral oil of various grades.British Minelaying.23. During the week surface craft laid mines off the Dutch and Belgiancoasts. Aircraft laid mines off the German North Sea coast and off the biscay ports.Enemy Minelaying, British Mines weeping.24. There have been no reports of minelaying my enemy surface craft or aircraft during the week. ,Nine mines have been destroyed off the East Coast and one in Lyme Bay.The mine totals are : 4.446 ground and 3,017 moored.Enemy Merchant Shipping.25. All the French and German-owned ships previously engaged in the oretraffic from Bayonne are now laid up at Bayonne. Two small Spanish ships under
German control are, however, - engaged in the ore traffic between Bayonneand Gijon.Air reconnaissance of southern French ports shows that, during the sixmonths from December 1942 to June 1943, work on all merchant ships of anysize had been suspended, and that a programme of tank-landing-craft had beenput in hand at all the building yards.The ex-Vichy tanker Firuz (7,327 tons) is expected shortly at Istanbul fromConstanza with a cargo of oil for the ^Fgean.   Two ex-Vichy ships have recently;left Istanbul for Bulgarian ports with cargoes of chrome ore.French Intelligence.26. Rear-Admiral Lemonnier has been appointed Chief of the Naval Staffof the Combined French Navies, with Rear-Admiral Auboyneau as assistant chief of Naval Staff.Spanish Intelligence.27. Two of four German M.T.Bs. which are being bought by Spain arrivedat Pasajes on the 2nd.MILITARY SITUATION.Sicily.28. The assault against the Axis positions in the north-east corner of Sicilystarted on the 1st. On the Eighth Army front fighting in the coastal sector was limited, during the early part of the week, to offensive patrolling and considerableexchanges of artillery and mortar fire, but, by the 4th, British patrols were inthe outskirts of Catania and close to Misterbianco. Catania itself was capturedat 0830 hours on the 5th. Further inland the fighting has been extremely fierce,the Germans resisting to the last man; nevertheless, on the 29th, British and canadian troops captured Catenanuovo, thereby securing a vital bridgeheadover the River Dittaino. Further north, on the 2nd, Regalbuto fell to the canadians. These advances have been exploited to the high ground east of Mugliaoverlooking the River Simeto, and along the road towards Adrano. Thus theenemy has been forced to yield considerable ground in the central sector, and his forces in the Catania area were in danger of being cut off. This threat probablyhastened the fall of the town.The Seventh Army has now encountered German troops and the fighting hasbecome increasingly severe. Demolitions have hampered progress on the coastalroad, but the U.S. troops have continued to advance. On their right they captured.Cerami on the 31st, whilst on the same day French Moroccan Goums seizedCapizzi. Troina is now surrounded. In the coastal sector San Stefano fell onthe 31st, and U.S. and French troops are now close to San Fratello.The Russo-German Campaign.Leningrad Sector.29.   Local Russian attacks south of Lake Ladoga have continued.Orel Sector.30. After further advances from the north, east and south throughout theweek, and especially along the Kursk-Orel railway, the Russian communique ofthe 4th reported that Russian troops had broken into Orel, where street fighting was taking place. Railway stations approximately four miles north and two anda half miles south of the city were captured. The German News Agency early on the 5th admitted the evacuation of Orel.Donets Sector.31. The Russians appear to be attacking in the Byelgorod and Izyum areas.Mius Sector.32. The Germans have counter-attacked heavily and claim to haveeliminated the Russian penetration north of Kuibyshevo.
Taman Bridgehead.33. - There has been some slight Russian activity.Burma.A arakan.34. Japanese patrol activity north of Buthidaung has increased and a clashoccurred three miles west of Taung Bazaar. &apos;&apos;Chin Hills and Upper&apos; Burma.      **35. There has been patrol activity only. Levies claim to have inflicted 20casualties on an enemy party ten miles north of Sumprabum on the 28th.South-West Pacific Area.New Guinea.36. Further small advances have been made by Australian and U.S. forcesin the Komiatum area. In particular the Australians captured a track junctionnear Old Bobdubi, four and a half miles south-west of Salamaua, thus cuttingthe main track from Salamaua to Komiatum. The Japanese in the area southand south-west of Salamaua are now being enveloped from three directions, andthere are indications that they are becoming apprehensive about the defence ofSalamaua.About 300 Japanese reinforcements landed by barge on the 27th at Salamaua.Solomons.37. U.S. forces have continued their advance towards Munda airfield.According to a U.S. Navy Department communique of the 4th, U.S. land forcesadvancing along the coast have reached the east end of Munda airfield. Inland,to the north-east of the airfield, Allied troops have occupied the north-east slopesof a hill overlooking the airfield. Allied advance on other parts of the frontcontinues:AIR SITUATION.General Review.38. At night, two further attacks were made on Hamburg and one onRemschied. By day, Kiel, Warnemunde, Cassel and eleven enemy airfields were bombed.In Sicily, support was provided for the land forces. Airfields in Italy were successfully bombed.A strong force of Liberators (B. 24) attacked Rumanian oil installations atPloesti and Campina.United Kingdom.39. In daylight, nine enemy reconnaissance aircraft were reported over thesouth coast.At night, ten enemy aircraft penetrated inland. Four enemy aircraft were shot down.Coastal Operations.40. Coastal Command Beaufighters attacked a convoy off Texel, sinking one3,000-ton ship and damaging three escort vessels; escorting Spitfires destroyedfour enemy aircraft. Off the Norwegian coast, Hampdens torpedoed a ship of4,000 tons which, later, was seen to be aground with decks awash. Beaufighterson patrol in the Bay of Biscay destroyed a F.W. 200.Aircraft of Fighter Command damaged two small ships and seven E. or R.boats off the north coast of France.Bomber Command aircraft laid 135 sea-mines in enemy waters.Germany and Occupied Territory.Day.41. On the 29th, three formations of Fortresses (B. 17) of the U.S. VIHthBomber Command bombed, with good effect, the U-boat yards and naval dockyardsat Kiel and the Heinkel aircraft works at Warnemunde; a total of 283 tons of
bombs was dropped at Kiel and 116 at Warnemunde (vide Appendix VI). Thefollowing day, the Fieseler aircraft components and assembly factory at Casselwas attacked by 115 Fortresses (B. 17), for whom withdrawal cover was provided from just south of the German border by Thunderbolts (P. 47). Eighty tons were released over the target (vide Appendix VI).Escorted Marauders (B. 26) of the u.s.. with Air Support Commanddropped 185 tons of bombs during attacks on airfields at St. Omer, Merville (bothof which were raided twice), Woensdrecht, Poix, Abbeville and Tricqueville andon shipyards near Rouen.Casualties to U.S. aircraft in the above operations, which flew 729 sorties,were 19 heavy and two medium bombers and seven fighters. Enemy casulties are given provisionally as 91 destroyed, 33 probably destroyed, 24 damaged.Fighter Command and the Tactical Air Force carried out attacks by escortedTyphoon bombers, Bostons (A. 20), Mitchells (B. 25) and Venturas (B. 34) on airfields at Poix, Abbevile (both were attacked twice), Coxyde, Courtrai, Schipol,St. Omer, Brest / Guipavas, Amiens and Lille, also two raids on the power station at Yainville; a total of approximately 90 tons of bombs was dropped. On thesemissions and in sweeps and fighter-escorts, involving over 2,050 sorties, 12 aircraft were lost. In combat, 14 enemy fighters were shot down and 23 probably destroyed or damaged.Night.42. On the 29th/30th, 698 aircraft of Bomber Command dropped 2,277 tonsof bombs at Hamburg. A cloudless sky, marred only by smoke from fires still burning from the series of previous attacks, enabled excellent concentration to beachieved. (Vide Appendix VI.) Three nights later, a force of 740 aircraft wasdetailed to bomb the city but, on this occasion, cloud obscured the target and the399 aircraft which attacked, most of them independently, did so in a thunder-storm; 1,343 tons were dropped. Other objectives in North-West Germany were bombed by 124 aircraft which, owing to the prevailing conditions, were unable to locate their primary target; 402 tons were released.On the 30th/31st, Remschied was the objective; 693 tons were released by 228aircraft, in clear weather, and considerable damage was caused. (Vide Appen-dix VI.)Remschied, 16 miles east of Dusseldorf, has a number.of factories makingprecision tools and a works, employing 2,600 hands, which manufacturesmachinery for the chemical industry, components for motor transport and small-arms.A total of 1,711 aircraft was despatched on these operations, from which 72(i.e., 4^ per cent.) did not return; five enemy night-fighters were destroyed.Mosquitoes (one is missing) made small-scale attacks on Cologne, Duisburgand Husseldorf.Airfields in Germany, Holland and France were attacked by &apos;&apos; intruder &apos;&apos; air-craft : 62 sorties were flown.   An enemy fighter was shot down.Mediterranean.Sicily.43. Bombing on a big scale was carried out by medium and light bomberson targets of tactical importance in North-East Sicily.The main concentration was on Adrano; roads, buildings, enemy gun positions and troops were attacked at frequent intervals with fragmentation and h.E. bombs, and on the 3rd August at least 80 M.T. vehicles were destroyed.Other centres to be heavily bombed were Paterno, Ragalbuto, Randazzo, St. MariaDi Licordia, Centuripe and Cesaro. At least three attacks were made on the coastal town of Melazzo. Fighter bombers in strength participated in these operations and attacked enemy M.T. barges, and the docks at Messina andMilazzo.The enemy air reaction was almost negligible and our losses were light. Onthe night 31st July/1st August enemy bombers attacked Palermo and caused considerable damage to the docks where a ship was sunk, some petrol and oildumps were sent on fire, and an ammunition train was destroyed.Italy.44.   Successful attacks were made on enemy airfields.Naples/Capodichino was bombed by 47 Fortresses (B. 17) by day and21 Wellingtons at night; a hangar was damaged, a building was set on fire,
s35 aircraft on the ground were destroyed, including 17 Ju. 52, and the airfieldwas rendered temporarily unserviceable. Fifty-six Fortresses (B. 17) attacked the airfield at Viterbo (43 miles N.N.W. of Rome) and 36 enemy aircraft were burnt out and six others seriously damaged. Grottaglie airfield (12 miles E.N.E. ofTaranto) was also attacked by Fortresses (B. 17) and severe damage was caused to hangars, workshops and barracks and three grounded Ju. 88 were destroyed andothers damaged. Medium bombers attacked Prattica di Mare (15 miles S. of rome), where 14 aircraft were destroyed, Aquino (50 miles N.N.W. of Naples),which was rendered unserviceable, and Monte Corvino Rovello. In these operations Allied casualties were three bombers, and four enemy fighters were shot down.On the night 2nd/3rd August. 69 Wellingtons made a successful raid onthe marshalling yards at Naples. Heavy borribers made two effective attacks onReggio Di Calabria.Sardinia.45. war hawks (P. 40F) carried out offensive sweeps in force over Sardinia,in the course of which 23 enemy fighters were destroyed for the loss of twoWarhawks (P. 40F).Rumania.46. On 1st August, 177 U.S. Liberators (B. 24) were despatched to bomboil installations at Ploesti and Campina.A low-level attack was made by 135 aircraft at Ploesti and 158 tons of bombs were dropped. Direct hits and material damage was caused at the ColumbiaAquila Refinery, Astra Romana Refinery, Phoenix (Orion) Refinery, ConcordiaVega Refinery and Creditul Minier Refinery (Brazi).At Campina, 29 Liberators (B. 24) dropped over 30 tons of bombs and considerable damage was caused to the Steaua Romana Refinery (Compina).Intense light flak fire was experienced and at least 87 enemy aircraft were encountered, some of which were obsolete biplanes. Fifty-one of these were destroyed and 24 Liberators (B. 24) are missing and eight others came down inTurkey.Attacks on Shipping.47. U.S. Beaufighters torpedoed a ship of 8,000 tons in the TyrhennianSea, and left her sinking. A destroyer and a M.T.B. were set on fire by cannonstrikes.A ship of 2,500 tons was sunk at Alinnia Island (N.W. of Rhodes Island).A night attack was made by Wellingtons and two ships were probably damaged,from one of which a column of smoke was seen rising.In the ^aegean Sea and off the west coast of Greece a ship of 5,000 tons receiveda direct hit; a tug, a trawler, five schooners, nine caiques and six small motorboats were sunk or damaged.Battle Casualties and Sorties.48. During the week ended the 3rd August, 110 enemy aircraft were shot down; 79 Allied aircraft are missing.   A total of 7,876 sorties was flown.Russia.49. The Russian Air Force continued to give support to the land forcesadvancing on Orel. German counter-attacks have caused an increase in air activity in the Donetz Basin area, the Russians claiming 115 aircraft destroyed in the course of three days&apos; fighting.On the night of the 27th/28th July, the railway junctions of Orel andBryansk were heavily attacked and raids were also made on German airfields in the Orel area on the same night.There is still no indication of German reinforcements being brought up fromother fronts or from Germany, in spite of the decreasing strength of the G.A.F.in Russia, which is estimated to have fallen from some 2,000 aircraft at thebeginning of July to about 1.850 aircraft at the beginning of August.
Burma.50. Small-scale operations were continued over a wide area, but fewimportant results have been reported. It is believed that Mitchells (B. 25)demolished the centre span of a bridge over the Mu River, west of Mandalay.Hurricanes did heavy damage to cargo sampans on the Irrawaddy. medium bombers effectively raided the airfield at Meiktila, oil installations at Cbauk(140 miles E.N.E. of Akyab) and railway targets at Myingyan.No Japanese offensive activity has been reported.Pacific Zone.New Guinea.51. During the ten days ended the 4th August, nearly 200 enemy barges,many of which were used as troop-carriers, were destroyed or rendered useless.A total of 140 heavy, medium and light bombers attacked Salamaua airfield and adjacent villages. Escorted Mitchells (B. 25), during an attack on Dein Bay(40 miles S.E. of Ma-dang), destroyed six enemy fighters. Lightnings (P. 38),patrolling near Saidor, encountered 14 enemy fighters, destroying 11 and probablydestroying another.New Georgia.52. Enemy installations, Munda airfield and gun positions at Bairokoharbour were heavily attacked by a total of more than 300 Avengers (T.B.F. 1),Dauntless (S.B.D. 3), and Wildcats (F. 4 F. 3). Mitchells (B. 25) bombed WebsterCove, on the south coast of Kolombangara Island and, on the 31st, 116 bombers and fighters operated against the bivouac area near Vila airfield. EighteenJapanese fighters, attempting to attack Allied positions at Rendova, were dispersed by Allied fighters; 13 enemy aircraft were destroyed for the loss oftwo of ours.Bougainville.53. Escorted naval aircraft sank eight barges and scored hits on two ships in the Shortlands area. Escorted Liberators (B. 24) started fires on the airfield at Kahili. Allied fighters, in a surprise low-level raid on the seaplane base atShortlands Island, destroyed seven float planes, three barges and a small cargo ship.New Britain.54. Near Cape Gloucester Allied aircraft sank. two destroyers and a transport. Gasmata airfield was bombed and machine-gunned and three jettiesat Montagu harbour were damaged. A Catalina (P.B.Y.) claims to have hit a destroyer 60 miles S.E. of Gasmata.China Zone.55. Escorted Mitchells (B. 25) bombed Hankow airfield. Liberators (B. 24)attacked shipping in Samah Bay, Hainan Island; hits were made on two ships of 3,500 and 6,000 tons and the former was left listing and on fire. Enemy aircraftcasualties in combat during these operations were 20 destroyed and 17 probably destroyed for the loss of one Kittyhawk (P. 40).Hongkong was bombed on three occasions; a cargo ship was hit and damage in the deck area was extensive; one Allied fighter is missing and one bombercrashed. On the 29th and 30th, the Allied airfield at Hengyang (34Q miles N.N.W.of Hong Kong) was attacked by a total of 47 Japanese bombers with fighter escort; two enemy fighters and three bombers were shot down and eight other aircraft were damaged by Kittyhawks (P. 40), two of which are missing.HOME SECURITY SITUATION.General.56. On two nights in the early part of the week a few minor bombing-incidents occurred in Southern England; damage was negligible and no casualties have been reported.On the last night of the period (4th/5th) a few shells, fired from the french coast, fell in the Dover area causing slight damage to property and two fatalservice casualties.  &quot;[25886]c
APPENDIX Y.Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary Vessels and to Naval Personnel.27 th July. L.C.T. 335 sunk by bombing off Syracuse.kth/bth August. M/S Trawler Red Gauntlet sunk by E-boat off Harwich.The following casualties to naval personnel have been reported : ;Officers:  24 killed (16 previously reported missing);  10 wounded;2 missing; 4 prisoners of war (previously reported missing).Ratings: 53 killed; 51 wounded; 4 missing.APPENDIX YI.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports have been received during the week : Germany.Hamburg. It is not possible at present to give any accurate or detailedpicture of the damage caused in the attacks to the 29th/30th July. The smoke from the fires, which continued to burn during the whole of the period from thefirst attack, and cloud have hampered interpretation of photographs that havebeen obtained. It can, however, be seen that the damage caused has been on an enormous scale, and is particularly severe in the east and south-eastern parts ofthe city, the dock area and near the main station at Altona. The districts ofWandsbeck, Hammerbrook, Hamm, Horn, Borgfeld, St. Georg and BillwarderAusschlag have been virtually devastated. The districts of Barmbeck, Steilshoop,Uhlenhorst, Winterhude and Grasbrook have been very severely damaged.Industrial damage is widespread. Blohm and Voss shipbuilding yards, where,in addition, one dry dock has apparently been sunk and another damaged, andHowaldfs yards, have suffered heavily. The Ebano Asphaltwerke A.G. and theRhenania Ossag lubricating plant have been similarly affected. Apart from these four priority targets, numerous other factories have been damaged. The main station in Hamburg is almost completely destroyed and that in Altona heavily damaged.While attacks continue, and until detailed interpretation reports areavailable, it will not be possible to give any accurate picture of what has been the cumulative effect of this record weight of attack.Remsheid. Photographs taken after the attack on. the 30th/31st july show part of the town obscured by a heavy covering of smoke. It is possible tosay, however, that damage to residential, commercial and public property is wide-spread and very severe, especially in the central town area near the main station.Considerable industrial damage can also be seen, including the destruction ofmore than half of a very large factory in the Honsberg district.Further photographs show that the severe industrial damage causedincludes the following factories : Bergische Stahlindustrie (Special forgings for aircraft).Alexanderwerk A. von der Nahmer A G. (Main works, machinery forchemical industry).Mannesmann Bohren-Werke.Stahlwerke Lindenburg.In addition the Town Hall, the main post office and the main station have been severely damaged.Appendices I, II, III and IY will be published periodically.
Cassel. An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the28th July, one hour after the U.S.A.A.F. attacks, shows that the main building of the Spinnfaser A.G. received two direct hits and was on fire at both places.These works, which are priority 14-, manufacture textile yarns from staple fibreand are the largest of their kind in Europe. Several houses and huts in thevicinity have been partly demolished or damaged and many of them are burning., An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the 1st August showsthat, as a result of the IT.S.A.A.F. attack on the 30th July, two large buildings of the Fieseler A/C Components Factory at Bettenhausen have been severely damaged. Other damage in this district includes the Feka Factory (specialmachine tools), a large building of the Bahr Ludwig Paper &apos;Factory and a building of the Salzmaan &amp; Co. Factory (linen, sailcloth and cotton weaving).In the Waldau district one large assembly shop of the Fieseler A/CAssembly Works has been very severely damaged and another smaller buildinghas also suffered.&apos; Hanover. A further interpretation of photographs taken after theU.S.A.A.F. attack on the 26th July reveals a large area of damage by H.E. and fire extending over about 30 acres in the town. Besides considerable damage to business and residential property, many public buildings have suffered severely,and these include : ,a -Market Hall: Completely gutted.Royal Castle : Half gutted.Old Palace : Completely destroyed.Old Town Hall: Part destroyed.Opera House : Half destroyed by fire.Law Courts : Almost completely gutted.Police HQ. : Main building damaged.Police Station in Burg Strasse : Completely destroyed,Kaffee Kropche: A famous restaurant in Georg Strasse completely destroyed.A achen. A final interpretation of photographs taken on the 15th July showthat, as a result of the R.A.F. attack on the 13th/14th July, damage is severe to industrial, residential and business property. The heaviest industrial damage isin the N.E. districts, where there are many factories, and in the central part ofthe city, where many textile factories and small old-fashioned works stand amongbusiness and residential property. While there are no very large industries inAachen, the town is noted for the number of small textile and engineering firmsit contains, and out of some 140 works no fewer than 80 are damaged many ofthem more than half destroyed. Damage to communications is severe, and muchrailway property, including station buildings, sheds, stores and rolling-stock hasbeen destroyed or badly damaged, while there have also been direct hits on tracksin many places. Several Public and Municipal buildings are among the vastnumber of buildings destroyed or seriously damaged, and the Rathaus, the PoliceH.Q., the Stadt Festhalle^ the Courts of justice, the Reichsbank and three of theleading hotels are the chief of these.Destruction of residential and business property, chiefly by fire, amounts toabout 50 per cent, in the built-up town areas, and it is estimated that, as a resultof this attack, living accommodation for more than 16,000 families is no longeravailable.Huls. -A final interpretation of photographs taken on the 24th July afterthe U.S.A.A.F. daylight attack on the 22nd June shows that many of the mostimportant plants and buildings of the Synthetic Rubber Plant have been damaged, many of them severely. In addition, seve*ral miscellaneous buildings and sheds throughout the works have been destroyed or severely damaged.Kiel. An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the 26th July,after the U.S.A.A.F. daylight attack on the 25th July, shows damage in theKriegsmarine Werft and in the Deutsche Werke. In the former two coveredfloating docks have been badly burned, sheds and stores have been destroyed andthe engine shop has again been damaged. Other buildings, which include one ofthe carpenters&apos; shops, have been partly demolished or damaged. Damage in theDeutsche Werke includes three workshops on the east of the dockyard, the enginesmithery and the engineering workshop, which have all received direct hits.An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the 31st July showsthat in the attack by the TJ.S.A.A.F. on the 29th July further damage was caused to the Kriegsmarine Werft (naval dockyard).  The large engine shop at the south
end has been severely damaged. Other buildings, including the iron and steelfoundries and a floating dock, have been damaged. In the naval arsenal two main buildings have been hit and in the dockyard basin a depot ship is seen tobe partly submerged.Warnemunde. An immediate interpretation of photographs taken on the29th July shows that damage caused in the U.S.A.A.F. attack on the same day to the Heinkel factory and the Warnemunde airfield is severe. Buildings in theHeinkel factory severely damaged or destroyod include four assembly shops, office buildings, stores departments and a boiler house. Damage in the neighbourhoodincludes two passenger trains derailed, two goods trains hit, fuel storage tanksdamaged and a direct hit on a light flak position. There are at least 100 craters on the airfield.Italy.Cislago. Photographs taken after the attack on the 16th/17th July confirmground reports of damage to the transformer and switching station. The north-west corner of the plant is seen to have been damaged by a direct hit and an eight-bay building and three sheds have been partly destroyed. At least onegantry has been damaged. *Arquata Scrivia, Photographs taken after the attack on the 15th/16th july show roof damage over an area of 330 square yards to the building which housesthe 130 K.V. apparatus and transformers. A shed near the north-east end hasbeen destroyed by two direct hits.France.St. Omer I Fort Rouge. Photographs taken during the attack on the 31st july show eight bursts on the landing ground of the airfield, 48 on the dispersalarea, one On the perimeter track and about ten on canal barges and railway tracksin the neighbourhood.Belgium.Zeebrugge.-An immediate interpretation of photographs taken after theR.A.F. and U.S.A.A.F. attacks on^the 27th and 28th July shows at least onedirect hit on the new coke ovens. Three buildings of the benzol plant have been destroyed and another severely damaged. Two more have suffered roof damage.South of the benzol plant, the power station has been hit at both ends andadjoining buildings have been destroyed or severely damaged.Holland.Amsterdam ISchipol Airfield. Photographs taken during the attack on the25th July show a concentration of at least 80 bursts in the western dispersal area,including several hits on aircraft shelters and taxi tracks.







</content>
</cab>
