<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/2/12 images: 192-205</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
:..?. (R) (39) 52,Copy No:WAR   CABINET.SURVEY OF GERMAN PROPAGANDA.Third Fortnightly Report submitted by the Minister ofInformation covering the period October 1st to 15th.(Previous Report:   Paper No, W.P. (R) (39) 34.Initialled__M.18th October, 1939

1.   SOURCES:The chief sources used for this survey have been:-(l) Monitored Broadcasts from German   Stations.(2) Communications intercepted by the Postal and TelegraphCensor a(3) Summaries of the press in foreign capitals sent byH.M.Embassies, Legations or consulates.(4) Information received from a German Socialist Movementhostile to the Nazisn(5) The Weekly Summary of the Political IntelligenceDepartment has also been consulted.2.   THE BID FOR PEACE.Germand propaganda during this fortnight has been notless copious than before, but dullere     One truth shows plainlyon the surface of the rather muddy stream - that Germany wouldlike to stop the war     Of course this is not what NaziPropaganda says0     To us they say:    &quot;Why continue this war?Why not listen to your elder statesmen who tell you to makepeace while you may - Lloyd George, venerable and wise, andBernard Sha?\r, almost as wise and even more venerable?&quot;     Orthey try to convince our middle class that their presentdiscomforts will become disaster and ruin, and our workers thatthe war is being waged for armament profiteers and Jewishfinanciersc     The Empire, it is added, is doomed, there are riftsalready, and the strain of war will be too great.     And to theFrench - &quot;this is England&apos;s war, which she is trying to fightwith your soldiers&quot;.     There are sometimes added expressions ofrespect, almost of admiration,&apos; for France, in contrast Y\dthcertain well-known passages in Mein Kampf.

As regards neutral countries, there is absolute evidenceof active German propaganda in U.S.A. and the Argentine, but thereis evidence also that it is not very effectives     Elsewhere themost is made of - Germany1s strength and of our alleged weaknessesand, of course, of our detention &quot;of neutral ships.       In some countries, in Sweden and in Belgium, for example, Germany&apos;s directpropaganda has some effect,     It is vigorous and amply staffed.There are said to be 27 Gorman correspondents in Brussels, and in stockholm German newspapers are said to arrive punctually and in large quantities whilst ours are few and late0     Brussels hasEnglish papers only thrice weekly and at the price of a simplebreakfast.But German indirect propaganda may well be even more effective - propaganda suggesting that economically she is so littledisturbed by the war that she is ready to sell her goods as inpeace-time and at the same prices,, though thirsty Belgians are saidto be still waiting for several thousands of gallons of Pilsenerbeer ordered weeks agoD     Germany is selling commodities which sheis likely to want herself if the war should be prolonged and isusing some of her precious petrol for a daily air-line service toSofia, whence it is continued thrice a week to Instanbul.     Thereare trade delegations busy - one,  it is said, on doubtful authority,is bound for Afghanistan.Neutral peoples are told, of course,  that if the war inthe West has to be begun in earnest on land and in the air as wellas at sea, it will be because Britain must have it so, or, with aglance over the left shoulder to Moscow, because British capitalistsnust have it so.In general, it may be said that the German propagandama-chine, designed of necessity for mass production, is not very

ready to turn out new material;    repetition ad nauseum is a cardinalprinciple, and this no doubt accounts for old words being fitted,sometimes rather inharmoniously, into new songs;    abuse follows too soon upon wheedling and is itself followed or accompanied by threats.But the aim is clear - it is what the enemy calls &quot;peace&quot;, and weshould call a truce.There is,  of course, every reason to doubt the GermanGovernment&apos; s sincerity in their professed wish for peace, and tothink that all that they really want is &quot;half-time&quot;, very early inthe game.     But that the German people want peace genuinely is very likely, and this makes their reported reception of the broadcastarmistice-hoax last week quite credible03.HITLER&apos;S HAND,It is easy to understand that Germany would like to stop the war, after a short campaign which was an overwhelminglyeasy triumph, and that she sees that a truce would be useful tostrengthen her armed forces still firther, particularly, perhapsat sea.     It is not to be supposed, however,  that in a complicatedsituation her motives are quite simple and her policy clear-cut.Has she other reasons for wanting peace, even for preferring a genuine peace to the continuation of the war?     In other words,what, as the German Government may be supposed to see it, is thesituation to which her propaganda, as an instrument of policy, isaddressed?     To answer this question it is desirable to glance back* or a moment to the condition of Germaiy immediately before the war,especially the moral condition.,     Nearly all the evidence seems toagree that Germany !s young manhood, grown up under Nazi tutelage,could be regarded by the regime as completely reliable.     The pactU1th Russia must have seemed to them to remove the only serious danger that Germany had to fear.     On the other hand, the health

and morale of the workers, particularly of the older men, had beenundermined by long hours, low wages, poor food, inadequate medical care, bullying and spying, and the postponement of the pension age.There was some shortage of trained officers for the army.Then came the swift triumph over Poland, which.must have still further improved the excellent fighting spirit of the forces,and is known to have had an effect on the civil population whichwas immediately favourable., though unlikely to last long.     once more there have been crowds outside the Chancellor&apos;s Office inBerlin, waiting to cheer Hitler,, crowds which had disappeared duringthe first days of acute anxietyo     There are some signs that the anti-capitalist twist given to recent Nazi propaganda has beenwelcorned by German xvorkmen,.But the debit side of the account is a long one *     Thereis a scarcity of meat, butter and eggs0     Fish and fruit are notrationed, but are commonly sold out before noon.     Soldiers have enough to eat and money in their pockets, but workmen say thattheir wages will not even buy the poorish rations that they are allowed.     There is a serious shortage of clothing - not enoughwool for uniforms even, according to some accounts;    if the reportedclosing of all but three out of 82 textile factories near theBelgian frontier is true, the shortage is the less likely to bemade good.     There is not enough leather, and informed opinionthinks that oil cannot possible suffice for a year&apos;s full speedcampaigning;    perhaps this accounts in part for the inactivityhitnerto of the German Air Force since their necessarily expensivesuccesses in Poland0As to moral conditions, people!s nerves are on edge from-nsion and from fear of secret service spies.     There is muchgrumbling that so many of the latter are staying behind to look after the home front, instead.of being with the fighting forces.-4-

h there are some signs, as yet hardly unmistakeable, of strainedrelations between Party and Army;    an Aachen daily paper printedan article asserting rather too elaborately that the relations wereexcellent.There is a queer report that the sale of Mein Kampf was prohibited as from September 28th;    a Revised Version of this Bible,purged of all matter that might given offence to Uncle Joseph, wouldbe a tiresome task in war time, though the result would certainly be a saving of paper in future editions.In Bohemia and Moravia, though there was not in fact an open revolt in Prague last month,  there is evidence enough of thepeople&apos;s stubborn hostility to their masters, in spite of all thearrests of leaders.      In the factories, so reports say, theysabotage what work they can, and persistent &quot;whispering campaigns&quot;are facilitated by the Gestapo&apos;s ignorance of Czech, as similarcampaigns would be in this country if carried on in Welsh.It is reported, not for the first time , that defensiceprecautions are being taken on the Italian frontier, but no doubtwe should be wise not to attribute much importance to this story.These are some of the significant factors in the situationconfronting Hitler.     The most significant of all is the plain truththat the Drang nach Qsten has come to an abrupt halt, barred by russian forces from the Baltic, the Ukraine, the Balkans and the black Sea.      &quot;What is Hitler to do?     Remain on the defensive andface a long war in spite of a shortage of some essentials, a shortagelikely to increase?       In spite of the evident danger on the homefront?       In spite of the improbability of his being able to retainfor long his personal power?     Or try, by the immediate use of allflis strength, to smash the Allied Armies and Air Forces, and so heable to dictate a swift peace?     There is the risk of failure, whichsight well mean final disaster. .    There is the certainty that even-5-

success would leave him dangerously weak against his Easternneighbour.4. HITLER&apos;S GAME.How Hitler will solve this problem only a competentstrategist can guess.     There is, by the way. no evidence that hitler himself has any competence in strategy, once war has ceased to be &quot;white&apos;1.,   His   advisers, no doubt, will decide whatmust be done.     As to what is to be said,  it seems likely that german propaganda, unless given something to talk about by a greatoffensive effort, will appear for a time to flounder.       This maymean that German leadership is floundering, and wishes to keep usguessing whilst it makes up its own mind0


</content>
</cab>
