<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/20/25 images: 272-277</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  December 1941.SECRET. Copy NoW.M. (41)182nd Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 132 (41).134. 44CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Saturday, December 20, 1941, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Sir John Anderson,   The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,M.P., Lord President of the Council.      Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,   The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer. Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,Secretary  of  State  for  DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon. J. T. C. Moore-Brabazon, M.P., Minister of aircraft production.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton,Minister of Food.Captain the Right Hon. H. D.Margesson, M.P., Secretary of Statefor War.The Right Hon Sir Andrew Duncan,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers,Minister of War Transport.Sir Orme Sargent, Deputy Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office.Sir Edward Bridges, Secretary.Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Allied Co-operation ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....    2402      Military Situation    ....................      ....    241[23273]
1.   The War Cabinet had before them-(1) A factual Memorandum as to the stage reached in Inter-Allied Co-ordination at the time of the outbreak of warwith Japan (W.P. (41) 302).(2) A draft telegram to His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador atWashington, prepared at an Inter-DepartmentalMeeting (W.P. (41) 303).The War Cabinet approved the factual statement and gavedirections that copies of it should be forwarded to Washington.The War Cabinet went through the draft telegram to washington paragraph by paragraph, and made the following comments : Paragraph 2 : Higher Direction in Allied War Effort.The substance was approved, but this paragraph should be putmore shortly.Position of the Dominions.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that theDominions would almost certainly claim to be brought into the picture rather more fully in the future than in the past. He thoughtthat what they really required was some prior inner knowledge ofthe discussions which led to important decisions being taken. Hethought that the position might be met if the Dominions were to berepresented in London by military officers on a higher level than atpresent, who could, on occasion, be brought into direct consultationwith the Chiefs of Staff.The Lord Privy Seal, summing up the discussion, said that hethought a separate paragraph should be added to the draft dealingwith the relationship between the United Kingdom and theDominions. This paragraph should indicate that, so far as possible,co-ordination with the different countries of the Empire should beeffected here, and that this might involve some form of representa-tion at a higher level than at the present time. There might also beoccasions on which it would be appropriate that one or more of theDominions should have representation on bodies set up to deal withregional or specific questions.It was agreed that a new paragraph should be added on theselines.Reference was also made to the position of India.The Minister of Labour and National Service enquired whetherrepresentatives of India could not be brought more fully into consultation.In this connection it was suggested that consideration shouldbe given to the question of a representative of India being added tothe Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster&apos;s War Council in singapore.It was agreed that the Secretary of State for India should be consulted in regard to this point.Paragraph 3.The War Cabinet were informed that the Chiefs of Staffconsidered that the system of areas of strategic responsibility,arbitrarily laid down on a geographical basis, was dangerous andwrong. Thus, for example, the areas worked out in A.B.C. 1 would preclude a United States offensive against Japan. The strategy ofthe war must be looked at as a whole, and the predominant role ina series of operations allocated in accordance with the generalstrategic situation and the resources of the Allies.allied co-ordination.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 128thConclusions,Minute 6.)
Military 2.   The War Cabinet were given the latest information aboutSituation. the military situation. __aot-;afan(Previous The pursuit of the enemy in Libya was proceeding satisfac-WM^lSlst t0%e had received no report from Hong. Kong since early on theConclusions, preceding morning, and the Japanese claim to have captured the minute l.) island might well be true.Paragraph 4.The need was emphasised for all the American Missions inLondon and all the British Missions in Washington to be under thedirection of a single head who could speak with authority on behalfof his Government. The exact status of this individual wouldrequire careful examination, more particularly in his relationship to the Embassy. What was required was someone corresponding toan Agent-General, of Ministerial standing if not status, and responsible to his Government as a whole.It was agreed that a new paragraph on these lines should beinserted after paragraph 4.Paragraph 5.The Minister of War Transport said that the United states had recently set up a strategic Shipping Board, with representa-tives on a high level. This country could usefully be associated withthis Board. But we also required to have a United States represen-tative accredited to this country on a far higher level than at thepresent time.Paragraph 6.The Minister of Food referred to the supply of food to Russia.Hitherto he had not taken steps to make any arrangement toco-ordinate purchases and supplies of food between this country andthe U.S.S.R. He thought that, if we were to do so, we might find that we had assumed responsibility not only for the supply of food to Russia, but for payment for the purchases made. He thoughtthat, on the whole, the best plan was to leave matters as they stoodfor the present, without making any arrangements for co-ordinatingRussian food requirements from the British Empire.Agreement was expressed with this view.Paragraph 7.There was general agreement that the tendency would be forthe co-ordination of production programmes to be centred, in due course, in Washington. Some better phrase should be found for&quot; co-ordination of production programmes,&quot; the essential meaningbeing to settle what munitions should be made in which countries.The allocation of production was, however, a matter whichmust be determined on broad strategic grounds, and we should not commit ourselves to the view that this should take place in washington.   The paragraph should be redrafted accordingly.U.S.S.R.A new paragraph should be added dealing with the position ofthe U.S.S.R. in regard to inter-Allied co-operation.The War Cabinet Agreed that the telegram should be redrafted in the lightof the discussion and submitted to the Lord Privy Seal,who was authorised to despatch it without further reference to the War Cabinet.
Any public statements made, if and when the fall of HongKong was confirmed, would require careful handling, particularlyin the light of what had been said at the time when Canada&apos;s offer to send Canadian Battalions to the fortress had been accepted.Attention was drawn to the various rumours which werecirculating as to lack of equipment or defensive preparations at singapore.The&apos; War Cabinet agreed that steps should be taken to enquire into these allegations as quickly as possible.Timor.(previous reference:W.M. (41) 131stConclusions,Minute 5.)3. The Lord President of the Council said that the full text of Dr. Salazar&apos;s speech had not yet been received, but it seemed thathe had made a vigorous protest, which he had followed up with ademand that we should withdraw our forces. This, of course, weshould be ready to do if the Portuguese were, able to provide adequate defence themselves, which, unfortunately, was not the case.Altogether, the position did not appear to be too unfavourable.The War Cabinet took note of this statement.Great George Street, S.W. 1,December 20, 1941.



</content>
</cab>
