<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/193/15 images: 148-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cp(76) 125COPY NO    g30 November 1976CABINETINCOMES POLICY, LIVING STANDARDS ANDPUBLIC expenditure memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer. In our discussions on 25 November it was suggested that we might gofor a complete freeze on pay and prices as our main initiative to restoreexternal confidence on the economy.    With such a freeze, it would be possibleto avoid any uprating of social security benefits during 1977 and that would itself produce substantial public expenditure savings.    It was envisaged thatthe effect on confidence of this stop on incomes and prices would be sufficientwith little or no further cuts in public expenditure.    Given the price and incomes freeze there could be no increases in taxation.PRACTICABILITY OF A PRICE/INCOMES FREEZE2.        Pay.   The first question is whether such a price/incomes freezewould be practicable.    We have to start by considering how long the freezewould have to last.    In 1965-66 the Labour Government successfully operateda statutory pay policy with a nil norm but at a much lower level of inflation and at a time when there was no buildup of price increases in the pipelinefrom a major depreciation of sterling.    The Heath Government ran a statutory pay and price freeze from November 1972 until March 1973.   Theexperience cf successive incomes policies over the last 15 years stronglysuggests however that it is dangerous to apply different limits to pay increaseswithin a single pay round.    There is acute resentment if the same treatment is not applied to everybody.    For that reason the Heath freeze was no morethan a deferment of increases for those affected by it.3.        I conclude that if we went for a pay freeze it would have to apply atleast to the whole pay round up to August 1977 and very possibly until december 1977, so as to ensure that each group was hit once by it.    Thefreeze would be in substitution for the present A\ per cent agreement with theTrades Union Congress (TUC) (although over 2 million workers have alreadysettled uner that agreement).1
Prices.   A price freeze to match the pay freeze might take one of several forms:-i. A freeze for the period 1 January to 31 July on the ground thatthat would correspond to the period of the pay freeze.    The delayedprice increases would then come through in the following months, asthey did following the Heath price freeze of November 1972 to march 1973.    But the counterpart of that would be that pay alsoshould &quot;catch up&quot; after July 1977, or there 1b no real &quot;match&quot;.ii. A 12 months price freeze, but excluding import cost increases.But of the 16 per cent year on year rate of inflation we now expect by mid-1977 over 8 per cent will be attributable to increased importcosts (mainly from the depreciation of sterling).    In many cases it     /would be very difficult to trace the effect of import costs through toconsumer prices.    It would be still more difficult to convince people /that it was right to ask them to bear these costs in a pay freeze andthat price increases were genuinely being limited to this factor.iii.      A straight 12 months price freeze; though even then exceptionswould have to be made for seasonal foods.5.        Different forms of price freeze would have different effects on thedistribution of resources, as well as on unemployment and inflation.    Ourstrategy requires a switch of resources from consumption to the balance ofpayments and investment.   Assuming continuance of the present 4  per centpay policy, the latest inflation forecasts and the best assessment we have beenable to make of the increase in earnings during the pay round point to a fall inthe real take home pay of the average worker by the late summer of i977 of between 6 per cent and 7 per cent.    If the policy holds, this will mean a transfer of resources to the balance of payments and to investment as wellas a better inflation outlook from the last months of 1977 onwards.6.        Of course it would be better still if this transfer could be made at a lower level of pay and price increases.    That would however require a rateof pricft increaoe of something like 6 per cent cr 7 per cent during a payfreeze.    If it were necessary to have a 12 months price freeze consumerswould be substantially better off than under the present policy and therewould be extra burdens on the balance of payments and on industry.    industry would benefit from the pay freeze but they would have to carry the inflationarycost increases now in the pipeline (and any subsequent import cost increases)for up to an extra year before recouping them in prices.    In practice therewould have to be many exceptions to present firms going out of business, andthat would reduce the credibility of the price freeze.    But there would alsobe a major squeeze again on liquidity and profits, at a time when private sector bank lending has had to be limited.    There would be extra unemploy-ment, a contraction of industrial activity and a serious loss of industrialconfidence.    Notwithstanding the pay freeze it seems likely that as theeffects of the price freeze become apparent relations with industry would bedamaged to the point whore the industrial strategy would be Impaired if notdestroyed.    These damaging effects on confidence would offset theconfidence gain from a ;jay freeze.
7.        A price freeze would have to be applied at least as s trictly to public sector prices as to those of the private sector.    The total effect onthe public sector borrowing requirement (PSBR) would depend on the nature and duration of the price freese and on the balance between gains from lowerpublic sector pay, lower social security benefits and lower private sectorprices for goods and services purchased by the public sector; and losses from lower tax revenues, lower insurance contributions, lower public sectorprices and, presumably, a stop on rate increases.8.        In fact the obstacles to a lengthy and convincing price freeze, of a kind which we would be expected to impose to match a complete pay freeze,seem to me insuperable with the degree of inflation now in the pipeline. 1A STATUTORY PAY POLICY79.        I think we must assume that a pay freeze would have to be statutory,especially if it were not possible to accompany it by a fully effective pricefreeze.    It does not seem credible that the TUC would be in a position tonegotiate with us a pay freeze lasting 8 or 9 months in substitution for theexisting second round pay agreement, and sell the proposition to a specialTrade Union Conference.    But could we really contemplate enacting a statutory pay freeze to which the TUC were in no way committed and which many individual unions might at once refuse to accept?   Given its likelyimpact on living standards, we shall I think do very well if with TUC helpwe hold the present 4^ per cent pay round and succeed in negotiating asatisfactory successor agreement.THE THIRD PAY ROUND AND THE STANDARD OF LIVING10.       The Prime Minister said during the Debate on the Address that weneeded an agreement to limit pay in the year after July 1977.    Followingdiscussion in EY Committee we have agreed the broad basis on which weshould open negotiations with the TUC with a view to an agreement beforethe spring Budget, if possible.    I expect to begin the main negotiation withthe TUC National Economic Development Council (NEDC) Six in January.Before we can expect to make much progress on the third pay round howeverwe have to deal with the IMF loan, and see our way to finance the balance ofpayments deficit and establish external confidence.    We BbaU have to explainfuUy to the TUC whatever measures are necessary to achieve that and tosecure their understanding, if not their agreement.    When we get to negotiations for the third pay round we shall need to aim for a rate of pay increase not very different from the increase in the present 4j per cent roundif we are to resume the deceleration of inflation and help restore confidence in the economy.    That will leave no room for any increase in the standard ofliving during the third pay round.3
11,      My conclusions would be:-i. that a pay and price freeze is not at present a practicablemethod of establishing confidence in the economy,ii.       that the prospect for real take home pay described above and our support for a voluntary pay policy point firmly against any attempt at a pay freeze; and that both this prospect and therequirements of confidence point to achieving the necessaryPSBR reductions so far as possible through cuts in public expenditure rather than increases in tax.D W treasury Chambers30 November 19764

</content>
</cab>
