<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/42/0 images: 88-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Friday, 3rd February, 1967,at 9.30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. George Brown, mp,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Denis Healey, m p,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, m p, Minister without Port-folioThe Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes, m p,Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the Right Hon. James Callaghan, m p,Chancellor of the exchequer the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the following were also present:The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, m p,   Mrs. Judith Hart, m p, MinisterChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster      State for Commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon.  John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, TreasuryofSecretariat :Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. H. L. Lawrence-Wilson7875aPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1967CC (67) Copy No.     36th conclusions cabinet
contents item , Subject page 1     Defence Estimates 1967    ...............       draft White Paper2     Malta   ........................      5
contents item Subject page 1     Defence Estimates 1967    ...     ............      draft White Paper2     Malta   .............     ............      5
DefenceEstimates1967Draft white paper(previous reference:CC(66) 59thConclusions,Minute 2)SECRET*1. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Defence (C (67) 15) covering the draft White Paper on theDefence Estimates for 1967.The Defence Secretary said that the draft White Paper was essentially a progress report on the implementation of last year&apos;decisions on the Defence Review, and on the resulting redeploymentof our forces. It showed that a saving of  750 million had been achieved in three years on the plans of the previous Administration,that, at constant prices, the Defence Estimates for 1967-68 were  78million below the target of  2,000 million for 1969-70 and that,allowing for increases of pay and in prices, there was a fall of  45million between the Defence Estimates for 1966-67 and those for1967-68. As regards oversea expenditure on defence it was notpossible to say what savings would be made in the foreign exchangecosts of our forces in Germany, in view of the moratorium on reducing our combat capability there until the end of June which we had accepted as part of the United States agreement on an offset payment.Savings elsewhere in the world would reach a rate of  75 million by the end of 1967-68. Under the offset arrangements in respectof the F-lll, contracts worth  45 million would have been obtained in the first year of its operation: this was over one-third of the totalrequired. Troop withdrawals from outside Europe would total25,000 out of 100,000.The main problem in drafting the White Paper had been thatthe further defence studies now in hand and the moratorium onreducing our combat capability in Germany until the end of June,made it impossible for us at this stage to take and announce thedecisions on the shape and size of our forces which the Services andthe Press were expecting. A background had to be provided in theWhite Paper for the decisions to be taken later in the year following the further defence studies. It was clear&apos;that we could not expect to obtain from the Germans the full offset costs for our forces stationed there and that in any event a reduction of the defence budget well below  2,000 million would involve reducing our forceselsewhere, and particularly in the Far East, below the levels agreedafter the Defence Review. Paragraph 4 of the introduction to theWhite Paper sought to foreshadow the decisions that would haveto be taken, without alarming our allies unduly. As regards our forces stationed in Germany the section dealing with the revisionof the strategy of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO)was intended to provide a justification for reducing these by drawing attention to the reduced threat in Europe and to the period of politicalwarning that could be expected of any deterioration in the situation there. It also sought to justify our case for reducing the logisticbacking of our forces in Germany to match their fighting capability.The opportunity had been taken to narrow still further the range of hostilities in which we were prepared to engage outside Europe* Previously recorded as a Confidential Annex.SECRET7875a 2
so as to exclude our becoming involved, even in partnership withallies, in operations on the scale of those in the confrontation withIndonesia.In discussion the Cabinet first considered our position in relationto foreign exchange costs of our forces in Germany. In the current year we were, receiving  50 million in offset payments against costs of  85 million. It now seemed possible that against costs next year of  85 million we might receive no offset payments at all, and thiswould mean a deterioration of  50 million in our balance of payments.The assumption on which the White Paper was drafted, and onwhich work on further defence studies was proceeding, was basedon the Cabinefs view that the foreign exchange costs of our forcesin Germany should be fully covered. Preparations were beingmade, to enable us to withdraw forces from Germany but there wasa limit to the rate at which they could be withdrawn, and in any event withdrawals could not begin until after the end of June becauseof our agreement with the United States over their own offsetpayment to us. In the longer term it would be necessary to considerwhere the balance even of purely economic advantage lay, in acceptingexpenditure in foreign exchange on the one hand, and in incurringthe additional budgetary costs and expenditure of resources on theother in withdrawing forces.The Cabinet then considered the extent to which the white paper should make clear that a further stage of defence studies wasin hand. A careful course had to be steered between on the onehand alarming our allies prematurely, and thus risking attempts toinhibit our freedom of choice, and on the other failing to provide. a clear basis on which decisions to be taken later in the year couldbe shown to be deliberate acts of policy. On the whole it was agreedthat the draft achieved the right balance between these conflictingobjectives. In particular it did not inhibit major changes in the equipment programme so far as numbers of equipment were concerned, or even in types of equipment, for example aircraft, iflater decisions should show any of these to be unnecessary.In further discussion attention was drawn to the problems thatwould arise on the lines of those which we were now facing in Malta,when withdrawals of our forces from Aden and the withdrawals of forces and reduction of facilities in Singapore led to large-scaleunemployment there.A number of drafting amendments in the White Paper were also agreed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet approved the draft White Paper subject to certain amendments. It was unfortunate that the difficulties of presentation of the White Paper in present circumstances, coupled with the timetable which had been set for publication, had on this occasionleft members of the Cabinet insufficient time.to consider the draft white Paper. It was important that in future the timetable for thepreparation and circulation of important draft statements and White
secret. The Minister of State for Commonwealth Affairs (Mrs. Hart)said that the Prime Minister of Malta, Dr. Borg Olivier, had rejectedour offer to send out a small mission of prominent industrialists toconsider ways in which the economy of Malta could be more rapidlydeveloped to mitigate the consequences of the reduction of our forces.It appeared that Dr. Olivier took the view that such a mission would only be of some value in the longer term, since it would admittedlybe impracticable to increase industrialisation at a rate which wouldprovide any adequate substitute for the employment afforded by our forces. The proposal would, therefore, only be acceptable if we agreed to slow down the planned rate of their reduction. If thesituation so developed that we had to evacuate service families, there might well be unpleasant incidents. Nevertheless, it appeared that dr. Olivier might still be seeking negotiations. A proposal had beenput to the Acting British High Commissioner by Mr. Mintoff, the leader of the Opposition in Malta, that he might come to Londonsecretly to negotiate, but any such proposal would cause greatdifficulty.The Defence Secretary said that detailed plans were availablefor the evacuation of Malta if this became necessary. The maindanger was the possibility of a general strike the following weekand he had brought to a shorter period of notice the specialist service personnel who were already, under an existing contingency plan,earmarked to go to Malta to provide administrative support for theforces if local labour were withdrawn. If we had to evacuate our forces it would also then be necessary to send the battalion whichwas earmarked for reinforcement for internal security duties. A fullassessment was being made of the military, political and economic consequences of total withdrawal.As regards the payment of customs duties on imports for our forces which were being demanded by the Maltese Governmentcontrary to the provision of the Defence Agreement the Law officers had advised that we could pay such duties without serious legalimplications for our acceptance of the abrogation of the defence agreement. After discussion in the Defence and Oversea PolicyCommittee it had, however, been decided not to make use as yetof the authority which the Cabinet had given at their previous meetingfor these duties to be paid if the Law Officers advised in this sense.It had been reported since the Cabinet discussion that in any eventPapers should be settled in the light of the date of eventual publication in order that Ministers might have adequate time to consider and discuss them.The Cabinet Approved the draft White Paper attached to C (67) 15,subject to the amendments agreed in discussion.
the Maltese administration were refusing to admit other fuel suppliesimported outside the provisions of the Defence Agreement, on whichcustoms duty had lawfully been paid and in such circumstances theCommittee took the view that it would be preferable not to pay theduty on other imports under the Agreement until the situation as awhole was clearer.In discussion there was general agreement that, while we should in no way discourage any proposal by Dr. Olivier to come to thiscountry for discussions, whether with his governmental colleagues orleading an all-party delegation, it would not be appropriate for thereto be negotiations with the Leader of the Opposition in Malta by himself.The Cabinet-Took note of the statements by the Secretary of State for defence and the Minister of State for commonwealth affairs.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,3rd February, 1967.


</content>
</cab>
