<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/42/0 images: 208-218</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC (67)16th Conclusions33CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W.1, on Tuesday, 4th April, 1967, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the Right Hon. Michael Stewart, m p,First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic AffairsThe Right Hon. Lord Gardiner,Lord Chancellor (Items 2 and 3)The Right Hon. Richard Grossman,mp, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary of State for  the  home department the   Right  Hon.   Patrick   gordon walker,   mp.   Minister   without portfolio the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, Secretary of State for education and science the   Right   Hon.   The   Earl   of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon.  Fred Peart, mp,Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,mp, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. James Callaghan,mp, Chancellor of the exchequer the Right hon. Herbert Bowden,m p, Secretary of State for Common-wealth AffairsThe Right hon. Denis Healey. mp,Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Douglas Jay, mp,President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, m p,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Anthony Wedgwood Benn, m p,Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. Arthur Bottomley,mp. Minister of Overseas Develop-ment (Item 3)The Right Hon. Kenneth Robinson,mp, Minister of Health (Items 1and 2)The Right Hon. Lord Chalfont,Minister of State for Foreign Affairs(Item 3)The  Right Hon.The Right Hon. Frederick Lee, mp,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Items 1 and 2)The Right Hon. Reginald Prentice,m p, Minister of Public Building and works (Item 3)The Right Hon.  Sir Elwyn Jones,qc, mp, Attorney-General (Items 1and 2)John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat:Sir Burke trend . P. rogers mr. K. barnes mr. H. L. Lawrence-Wilson8125aTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1967Copy No.
contents item Subject page 1     Parliament     ............     .........       3The Torrey CanyonBristol Siddeley Engines Limited2     Prices and Incomes Policy...............       4Statutory Powers3     Defence Expenditure Studies     ............       8
CC 16 (67)confidential. The Prime Minister said that the draft of a White paper on the Torrey Canyon had been circulated by the Home Secretaryto the Cabinet under cover of C (67) 43. The timetable had however,exceptionally, made it impossible for the draft to be discussed in cabinet in accordance with normal practice for White Papers and members of the Cabinet had instead been asked to let the HomeSecretary have by the end of the previous day any amendments which they wished to suggest. The White Paper would be published that afternoon and it was for consideration whether it would be appropriate to put down a Government motion, on the issues which arose, for debate the following week.In discussion there was general agreement that the desirabilityof putting down a motion for debate could best be judged after thestatement which the Prime Minister was to make in the House ofCommons on the Torrey Canyon that afternoon.The Prime Minister recalled that the Minister of State, Ministryof Technology, had made a statement in the House of Commons on22nd March about the repayment by Bristol Siddeley EnginesLimited to the Ministry of Technology of  3,960,000 in respect of excessive profits which the firm had made between the years 1959to 1963 on a number of contracts for the overhaul of certain types of aero engines. Further investigations since the statement, and theParliamentary and public reactions to it, suggested that there wasneed for a formal inquiry into these transactions. It would not be wholly appropriate that the inquiry should be conducted by thePublic Accounts Committee and the balance of advantage lay ininstituting an independent inquiry on the lines of that which hadbeen carried out under the Chairmanship of Sir John Lang, a formerPermanent Secretary of the Admiralty, into the excessive profitwhich had been obtained by Ferranti Limited on the contract forthe BLOODHOUND guided missile. It might also prove desirablesubsequently for this or a comparable inquiry to cover transactions inrespect of contracts for certain other weapons systems. Initially,however, the inquiry could best be confined to the transactions ofBristol Siddeley Engines Limited which were immediately inquestion. The statement which would be made in the House ofCommons the following day would be in terms which would notprejudge the outcome of the inquiry or the attitude which the firmhad adopted towards these profits and their repayment.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the issues ofprinciple relating to Government contracts which arose in thisconnection were being discussed with the Confederation of BritishIndustry. Particular difficulties had arisen in respect of contracts with firms producing aircraft and electronic equipment. It wouldnot, however, be appropriate for these issues to be raised inParliament the following day.The Cabinet  *Took note of the statements by the Prime Minister on theTorrey Canyon and on Bristol Siddeley Engines Limited.8125
Prices andIncomesPolicyStatutoryPowers(previous reference :CC(67) 13thConclusions,Minute 6)The First Secretary of State said that it was now necessary toreach decisions on further statutory powers over prices and incomesfor the period after the expiry of Part IV of the Prices and incomes act in August 1967. The existing powers under Part IV werecomprehensive in character, though their exercise in practice hadbeen limited. We should face a difficult economic situation afterthe end of the period of severe restraint, with pent-up wage demands and a consequent threat of pressure for prices to rise. If movements of prices and wages were allowed to go unchecked, there would bea risk of a renewed crisis of confidence in sterling and the needfor further drastic economic measures. There were a number of policies which the Government could follow to prevent this, ofwhich the policy on prices and incomes was only one, though animportant one. The Governments long-term objective should bean effective policy in this field conducted on a voluntary basis, butthe present issue was the speed with which the Government couldmove from a situation of extensive statutory control to a completelyvoluntary system.The right course was for the Government, before the expiry ofPart IV of the Act, to activate Part II and to seek additional powers which would be valid for 12 months only. To seekpowers for a longer period than this would provoke hostilityunnecessarily; on the other hand, the Government might be placedin difficulties later if they undertook at this stage that they wouldnot seek further powers at the end of 12 months; there should therefore be no commitment either wfty. When the additional powers expired at the end of 12 months, it would be important to ensure that Parts I-III of the Act still remained on the statute book and were capable of being activated if necessary. The existing powers under Part II, when activated, provided for Orders imposing a standstill of up to one month on proposed increases of prices and wages pending a decision on whether to make a reference to theNational Board for Prices and Incomes (NBPI), and a furtherstandstill of up to three months if a reference to the Board weremade. A further power should now be sought extending themaximum period of standstill to cover one month pending a reference to the NBPI and an additional six months beyond that,making a total of seven months&apos; delay from the date of notification of the proposed increase. Provision should be made whereby Ordersimposing a standstill should remain in force for their appointedperiod, even though the parent legislation might have expired before then. This was a modification of the proposal previously consideredby the Cabinet whereby a maximum delay of 12 months couldbe imposed from the date of reference to the NBPI but the relevantOrders would be of no effect after the expiry of the parent legislation;2. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the first secretary of State and Secretary of State for Economic Affairs(C (67) 39) on the question of taking further statutory powers inpursuance of the Governments policy on prices and incomes.
CC 16 (67) *this would have meant that the maximum period of standstill wouldin practice progressively shorten as the date of expiry of the parentlegislation drew nearer. The present proposal was preferable since a maximum period of six months would be more acceptable to theTrades Union Congress (TUC) than one of 12 months and since it would be more equitable and administratively more practicable to maintain the same maximum period of standstill throughout the currency of the legislation. It would also be essential to take powers to prevent retrospective payment of wages in respect of a standstill period and to enforce reductions of prices. All these powers should be exercised only in pursuance of a recommendation by the NBPI, though the Government would not be obliged to make an Order whenever the NBPI so recommended. A provision,exercisable by the Government on their own initiative, would benecessary to enforce the temporary reversion of an increase of prices or wages which had been implemented before the issue could bereferred to the NBPI. Finally, it would be necessary to include aprovision protecting employers against actions for breach of contractwhere they had deferred increases of wages in accordance with a request by the Government during the periods of standstill andsevere restraint, but had not gone through the statutory procedures which were necessary if they were to be protected from such actionsby Section 30 of the Act.The Minister of Labour said that he was deeply concerned atthe present general deterioration in industrial relations. It was important to avoid taking decisions which would exacerbate thesituation. Many trade union leaders now felt that as a result ofthe conference of trade union executives on 2nd March they were committed to oppose the retention of any reserve powers by theGovernment. There was no longer any prospect of securing by further negotiations even the reluctant acquiescence of the TUC inthe taking of additional statutory powers. It was neverthelessnecessary for the Government to retain some reserve powers. Hewas prepared to accept the proposals put forward by the first secretary of State; he had, however, serious reservations aboutincluding the power to prevent retrospective payment of wage increases, which would provoke bitter opposition.In discussion, it was argued that the proposals put forward bythe First Secretary of State would mean only that increases of prices and wages could be delayed for up to seven months instead of upto four months in accordance with the provisions of Part II; thiswas only a marginal extension of statutory control and would nothave sufficient impact on the economic situation to justify incurringthe industrial and political difficulties attendant on further legislation. It was not necessary to take further powers from thepoint of view of the effect on overseas opinion, which was less concerned with the Governments policy on prices and incomes thanit had been a year earlier, but was influenced rather by the progress being made towards a continuing surplus in our balance of payments.It would therefore be preferable for the Government to confine8125a 3
themselves to the activation of Part II, which in itself represented a substantial measure of statutory control, but to make it clear that,if the policy on this basis were to prove inadequate, the Governmentwould be compelled to introduce more comprehensive legislation.On the other hand it was urged that the power to delayincreases by up to seven months would constitute a considerablebrake on price and wage movements. Without such a brake, itwas likely that increases of wages over the next 12 months would more than pre-empt the whole of the increased spending power which would be generated if we achieved the economic rate of growth now expected. If this happened, it would be necessaryeither to introduce substantial increases of taxation or to reduceprogrammes of public expenditure of great social importance. Ifthe Government were to confine themselves to the activation ofPart II, their powers over prices would be limited and this would help to stimulate further increases of wages. Moreover, it wouldbe impossible to avoid giving the impression that the Governmenthad retreated from their original position under pressure. Recentcontacts with Commonwealth Governments had shown that international opinion was still greatly concerned about the futureof the policy on prices and incomes in relation to the future of sterling.It was also suggested that the proposal that Orders imposing a standstill on increases of prices or wages should remain in forceeven after the parent legislation had expired would mean thatstatutory control would continue until virtually the end of 1968; thiswould provoke strong opposition. On the other hand, the TUCthemselves had stressed the inequity of the original proposal whereby the maximum period of standstill would in practice diminish towardsthe end of the period for which the legislation remained in force,and the present proposal was unlikely to increase materially the hostility of the TUC.In further discussion, it was argued that the proposal to take power to prevent retrospective increases of wages should be abandoned. If it were retained, the legislation would attract evenstronger opposition both industrially and among the governments supporters in Parliament. Retrospective increases of wages werenot likely to become widespread; retrospection was not a familiarconcept to those concerned with wage negotiations in the private sector and they would be unlikely to change their habits quickly.Moreover it should be possible to use the Governmenfs powers over prices to check any tendency on the part of employers to give way to demands for retrospective payments. In any case, it wouldnot be possible to prevent agreements for retrospective increasesbeing reached after the expiry of the proposed additional statutory powers; and in view of this it was at least questionable whether itwas worth while to seek to prevent them solely during the lifetime of the proposed new legislation. The Governmenfs primary objectshould be to do everything possible to ensure the success of the tuc&apos;s arrangements for controlling movements of wages and fromthis point of view it would be better to drop the power to prevent
retrospective payments, which would provoke a bitter reaction from the TUC and prejudice their own efforts to work out an effective policy. The Government could, however, make it clearthat, if retrospective increases of wages began to be made on sucha scale as to undermine the policy, they would be prepared to take powers to prevent them. Indeed there would be advantage in making it clear that, if the policy of relying primarily on voluntary controlscoupled with the activation of Part IT were not to be effective, theGovernment would take far more draconian powers in this field.On the other hand it was argued that the proposals for additional powers had already been considerably diminished and, if the powerto prevent retrospective increases were to be dropped, the proposals as a whole would no longer be worth pursuing. Retrospectiveincreases could be expected to become considerably more frequentif they represented the only way of circumventing statutory Ordersimposing a standstill, and it was necessary to have power to prevent them if minority groups who challenged the policy were to be dealtwith effectively. If this power were dropped, we should in effectbe reverting to the system obtaining before July 1966; and therewas no evidence that this would work any more effectively in thefuture than it had done in the past. The Government would thenbe relying on a policy which was virtually certain to result inincreases of wages on such a scale that in order to safeguard thebalance of payments it would be necessary to pursue policies whichwould inhibit economic growth, to maintain unemployment at ahigher level and to restrict public expenditure still further. If,concurrently with the increases of wages which such a policy would permit, the Government continued to restrain prices, there would bea consequential diminution of profits which would adversely affectinvestment, to the further detriment of economic growth.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said theCabinet on balance agreed that the Government should activatePart II before the expiry of Part IV and take further powers asproposed in the annex to C (67) 39, except for the power to preventretrospective payment of an increase of wages following theimposition of a standstill. The powers should be valid for 12 months and should enable a standstill to be imposed on proposed increases of prices or wages for up to one month pending a decision on a reference to the NBPI and for a maximum of a further six monthswhere this was recommended by the NBPI. Provision should bemade for the relevant Orders to continue in force for their appointedperiod, even where this extended beyond the date of expiry of the parent legislation. As regards the power to prevent retrospectiveincreases of wages, while strong arguments had been adduced for taking such a power, the Cabinets view on balance was that itwould be preferable not to do so, but to make it clear that theGovernment would be prepared to introduce further legislation onthis specific issue if it should prove that retrospective increases were undermining the policy. Indeed, when the Governmentintroduced their proposals for legislation, it would be necessary to
make it clear that they would bring forward more comprehensivelegislation providing for stronger and more comprehensive powersif the policy on the basis proposed were to prove ineffective. Itwould be important when the Governmenfs policy was announcedfor all Ministers to seek every possible opportunity for its publicexposition.The First Secretary of State said that a decision not to take powers to prevent retrospection would not only be regarded as aretreat by the Government but would also have serious implications for the practicability of the remaining powers which it was proposedto take. It would for example no longer be possible to obtain theagreement of the Confederation of British Industry to the powers which were proposed in respect of prices. In these circumstances hewould wish to consider the repercussions of the Cabinefs decisionon the Governmenfs policy on prices and incomes as a whole beforethe decision was implemented in its present form.In renewed discussion it was generally agreed that theFirst Secretary of State should accordingly circulate a further memorandum for consideration the following week.The Cabinet (1) Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministefs summing up of their discussion.(2) Invited the First Secretary of State to circulate to the cabinet for consideration in the following week a memorandumassessing the implications for the proposals for statutory powers as a whole of a decision to omit the power toprevent retrospective payment of an increase of wagesfollowing the imposition of a standstill.DefenceExpenditureStudies(previous reference :CC (66) 59thConclusions,Minute 2)CONFIDENTIAL*3. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the secretaries of State for Foreign Affairs and for Defence (C (67) 40) and by theSecretary of State for Commonwealth Affairs (C (67) 41) on thedefence expenditure studies.The Defence Secretary said that the series of defence expenditurestudies set in hand in the autumn had now progressed far enoughto show that there was no hope that, by making reductions in our forces but without major changes in our oversea policies, we could reduce planned defence expenditure in 1970-71 by  200-300 million in addition to the reduction achieved during the previous defence review of  400 million for that year. Subsequent consideration had emphasised the need for the maximum contribution on defenceaccount to a reduction in the cost of present planned programmes of public expenditure as a whole in 1970-71. On the basis of thedefence studies we could only look for savings of  100-125 million in 1970-71, although these would increase by up to  25 million in subsequent years.   Whereas in the defence review it had been* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.
CONFIDENTIAL9     113possible to make large economies in defence expenditure by obtainingbetter value for money and without large reductions in our military capability, it was now no longer possible to make further cuts in defence expenditure on the scale required without reducing the size of our forces and therefore their capability. This must carry with it reductions in their tasks and commitments which wouldinvolve major changes in our foreign policy.Our room for manoeuvre in the next few years was limitedmainly to our Far Eastern deployment and commitments, and to the consequential effects of changes in these on the forces, facilities and stocks which we maintained in the United Kingdom. So far, thedefence studies had taken as a main assumption the reduction of our forces in Singapore / Malaysia by about half by 1970-71. Largersavings would be possible if the rundown could be made part of a firm plan to withdraw all our forces from Singapore/Malaysia nolater than 1975-76 with, if necessary, a military presence in the far east consisting of small naval and air forces based on Australia.A very tentative estimate was that savings in the planned defence budget might on this, basis be  150-200 million by 1970-71,compared with the  100-125 million foreshadowed by the present defence studies, and up to  300 million in all by 1975-76.If we were to make savings of this order and in this time-scale,it was essential that decisions should be taken and announced inJuly so that the Services would have a firm plan on which to work.Before this would be possible, however, we must consult our Allieson the proposals, notably the United States, Australia, New Zealand,Singapore and Malaysia. Major renegotiations of our forcedeclarations to the South-East Asia Treaty Organisation (SEATO)and of our treaty obligations to Malaysia and Singapore would benecessary; we should have to renegotiate our agreement withBrunei and, soon after 1970-71, we would no longer be able tocontribute land forces to the Commonwealth Brigade although wecould contribute maritime and air forces to a CommonwealthStrategic Force. Apart from these wide-ranging changes in politicaland military commitments, and the very large problem ofdisbandment, reorganisation and retraining that would be involvedfor the Services, and for the army in particular, the economic consequences in the area as a whole would be considerable and in singapore would be grave, since expenditure by our forces thereprovided 20-25 per cent of the Gross National Product and since we employed some 10 per cent (33,000) of the local labour force which already had an unemployment rate of at least 10 per cent.It would be difficult for us to carry our partners with us in this new approach but it was essential for us to try to do so and to embark quickly on the necessary process of consultation. although he would be seeing the United States Secretary for Defence later that week he had agreed with the Foreign and CommonwealthSecretaries that this should not be the occasion on which to discuss with him even the general shape of our plans. This would be doneby the Foreign Secretary with the Americans and with the New
Zealand Prime Minister at the time of the SEATO Council meetingon 18th-20th April and, at the same time, the Prime Minister mightsend a message to the Australian Prime Minister, Mr. Holt. Hesuggested that he himself should visit Singapore and Malaysia todiscuss our plans with their Governments very soon thereafter.In discussion it was agreed that there was insufficient time onthis occasion to discuss the present proposals adequately and thata final decision on the future disposition of our forces must in any event be left until a fully considered plan had been worked out and presented in the context of the defence studies as a whole inJune-July. It would however be necessary for the Cabinet todecide before the Foreign Secretary went to the meeting of theSEATO Council whether we should plan a withdrawal from theFar East on the scale and timetable proposed by the Foreign and defence Secretaries. It was of particular importance that strictsecrecy should be maintained about our plans until the time came to discuss them with our Allies since we should otherwise face unitedopposition to them.The Cabinet Agreed to resume their discussion in the following week.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,4th April, 1967.


</content>
</cab>
