<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/42/0 images: 685-699</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CC (67)56th conclusions copy no cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10 Downing Street, S.W.1, on Thursday, 21st September, 1967at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Harold Wilson, m p, Prime minister the   Right   Hon.   Lord   Gardiner,Lord chancellor the Right Hon. Dents Healey, mp.Secretary of State for defence the Right Hon. William Ross, mp,Secretary of State for scotland the Right Hon. Michael Stewart,m p, First Secretary of state the Right Hon. Richard Crossman,m p, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Roy Jenkins, mp,Secretary of State for the home department (Items 3-7)The Right Hon. Patrick gordon walker, mp, Secretary of State for education and science the Right Hon. George Thomson,m p, Secretary of State for commonwealth AffairsThe Right Hon. Anthony Greenwood,m p, Minister of Housing and local government the Right Hon. R. J. Gunter, mp,Minister of labour the Right Hon. Barbara Castle, mp,Minister of transport the Right Hon. Richard Marsh, mp,Minister of power the Right Hon. Anthony Crosland,m p, President of the Board of trade the Right Hon. Peter Shore, mp.Secretary of State for economic affairs the Right Hon. The Earl of longford, Lord Privy seal the Right Hon. Fred Peart, m p,Minister of Agriculture, fisheries and food the Right Hon. Cledwyn Hughes,m p, Secretary of State for wales the Right Hon. Anthony wedgwood benn, m p, Minister of technology the following were also present:The Right Hon. John Diamond, mp,Chief Secretary, treasury the Right Hon. Sir Elwyn Jones, qc,mp, Attorney-General (Items 2-7)The Right Hon. Frederick Mulley,m p, Minister of State for foreign affairs the Right Hon. John Silkin, mp,Parliamentary Secretary, treasury secretariat :Mr. W. A. nield miss J. J. nunn mr. E. M. rose mr. L. errington mr. K. Barnes
ContentsSubjectItem page 1     Oversea Affairs     ............     ......       3The Tkachenko IncidentGibraltarNigeriaGuyana2     Cabinet........................       3Consultation of the Law Officers3     Cabinet.........     ...............       4Security of Ministerial Discussions4     Report of the Committee on Ministerial Publication       65     Industrial Disputes.........     ...     ......       9RailwaysDocks6     Aircraft Industry   ......     ............     11Beagle Aircraft Company7     Economic Situation.........     .........     12Unemployment Figures for September
OverseaAffairsTheTkachenkoIncidentGibraltar(previous reference :CC(67) 55thConclusions,Minute 1)Nigeria(previous reference :CC (67) 55thConclusions,Minute 1)GuyanaCC 56 (67)confidential. The Minister of State for Foreign Affairs (Mr. Mulley)referred to the recent incident in which a Soviet scientist, Dr. VladimirTkachenko, had been removed by the police from a Soviet aircraft at London Airport on suspicion that he was being taken out of thecountry against his will, but had been allowed to leave once it hadbeen established that he wished to do so. The criticism in the SovietPress on our handling of this question seemed to be merely attemptsby the Soviet security authorities to cover up their own incompetence;and there was no evidence to suggest that the incident would adversely affect our relations with the Soviet Union. A delegation of Soviet trade unionists had just arrived in this country as planned.The Foreign Secretary had informed the Spanish ambassador on 18th September that he was ready to meet the Spanish ForeignMinister for a discussion on Gibraltar, if a suitable place and timecould be found. It was satisfactory that Mr. Stuart Christie, who hadbeen serving a sentence of 20 years&apos; imprisonment for bringingexplosives into Spain, had now been released. We had been pressing for his release for some time.The Commonwealth Secretary said that the Federal Governmentwere now taking the initiative in Nigeria and had reoccupied Benin,the capital of the Mid-Western Region. But there was no indication that Biafra, the breakaway Eastern Region, was collapsing. the deputy High Commissioner^ Office in Enugu had recently been&apos;raided by the Biafran authorities who had removed some diplomaticwireless equipment. They had now been informed that, unless it wasreturned, we should withdraw our representatives from Biafra.A dispute had developed between the Prime Minister of Guyanaand the Minister of Finance (who belonged to a different political party) over the appointment of a Commissioner of Income Tax. Asa result there was a danger that the dispute might spread and theGovernment of Guyana break up.The Cabinet Took note of the statements by the Secretary of State for commonwealth Affairs and the Minister of State forForeign Affairs.CabinetConsultationof theLaw OfficersCONFIDENTIAL2. The Prime Minister recalled that he had previously circulated a memorandum (C (P) (67) 1) specifying certain types of case in whichthe Law Officers should be consulted by Departmens. In some recentinstances, however, there had been a failure so to consult. he therefore wished to remind Ministers of the importance of earlyconsultation with the Law Officers before action was taken whichmight give rise to difficulty in the Courts, especially where importantpolicy issues were involved. A recent case had also shown the need forsuch consultation where the actions of a department, or the advice it
gave to outside bodies about their actions, might later require adecision by the Law Officers or by the Director of Public Prosecutionson whether a prosecution should or should not be launched. failure to consult in such cases circumscribed the freedom of decision of theLaw Officers. He proposed, therefore, to issue a further memorandum, calling attention again to the importance of consultation with the Law Officers on.the categories of case previouslyspecified and adding the new category to which he had referred. Itwas important that Ministers should bring this memorandum to thenotice of their legal advisers and emphasise the importance ofcompliance with it.The Cabinet-Took note of the statement by the Prime Minister.CabinetSecurity ofMinisterialDiscussions(previous reference :CC(67) 1stConclusionsMinute 1)secret. The Lord Chancellor recalled that he had been invited bythe Prime Minister to investigate the sources of certain apparentleakages of information relating to Cabinet business. He was satisfied that there had been no deliberate leakage of such information.Apparent leaks frequently appeared to be no more than informedguesses by experienced journalists. Such journalists were, however,expert in acquiring separately and piecing together small items of intelligence, none of which might in themselves be important orexplicit, but which in total often provided an informed and experiencedman with sufficient material to make an accurate assessment of the government&apos;s intentions. The only safeguard lay in strict limitationof classified information to those who needed to know of it. It hadto be recognised, however, that guidance to the Press was necessary and there was no clear cut line between legitimate guidance andleakage of classified information. He suggested, however, that theextent of the circulation of Cabinet documents by the Cabinet Officeto Ministers and officials should be reviewed. Further, ministers should review the circulation within ^their Departments of cabinet documents including circulation to junior Ministers. Thirdly,Ministers should be on their guard against discussing Cabinet businesshowever fragmentarily with those who did not need to know, whetherjunior Ministers or officials. Practice on all these matters varied verywidely among Departments.In discussion it was pointed out that some apparent leakages of ministerial discussions related to the evolution of policy on mattersof controversy which did not carry the highest security classification.The proposed review should, therefore, extend to Confidentialmaterial as well as to Secret and Top Secret documents. In view ofrecent cases, the review should also cover the practice of civil servants in taking Top Secret and Secret documents home for work overnight.In further discussion, the following main points were made (a) In some instances, as in the case of the Defence Review, a relatively wide departmental circulation of Cabinet documents mightbe necessary in order to ensure both preparation for and the effectiveexecution of Cabinet decisions.
(b) Steps had been taken, in the light of a recent case, to preventunauthorised extra copies of documents being taken, and in regardto the notebooks of shorthand-typists and their security clearance.(c) Ministers should review the arrangements in their PrivateOffices for the handling of Top Secret documents; further it was desirable that Private Offices should keep an accurate record of themovement of classified documents taken by Ministers to their homes.(d) There might be a case for examining instances where the secrecy of controversial topics had successfully been maintained during prolonged Ministerial consideration.(e) While the nationalised industries could be relied on in mattersof national security, they were liable to use confidential informationaffecting their interests for the purpose of exerting political pressure.(/) While close relations between Departments and the Presswere desirable on general grounds, there was a risk to security whereofficials were entertained individually by specialist journalists. It was for consideration, therefore, whether officials should report the receiptof such invitations and should make a record of any discussion of official matters.(g) Where a matter under review was difficult or controversial,it was undesirable to announce that it was under discussion since thisaroused Press interest and led to continued speculation where anannouncement of policy decisions was delayed.(h) Where temporary Civil Servants had subsequently takenemployment as journalists, Departments should be warned againstdiscussion with them of matters in which they had previously been engaged.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that hewould arrange for the Secretary of the Cabinet to review the presentcirculation by the Cabinet Office of Cabinet documents to ministers and officials and in consultation with the Permanent Heads of theDepartments most concerned with sensitive material, the practice inrelation to the circulation of such documents within Departments. Itshould also be ascertained to what extent junior Ministers and parliamentary Private Secretaries were given access to cabinet documents, particularly where their own Department was not directly involved. These reviews should extend to Top Secret, secret and Confidential material. The practice of Civil Servants taking TopSecret and Secret documents home should also be reviewed. In thelight of these reviews and of the points made in their discussion, hewould subsequently circulate a memorandum making specific proposals for consideration by the Cabinet.The Cabinet-Took   note  with  approval  of  the  Prime   Minister^summing up.
Report of theCommittee onMinisterialPublication(previous reference :CC (67) 3rdConclusions,Minute 1)SECRET*4. The Cabinet had before them a note by the LordChancellor (C (67) 146) to which was appended the report of aCommittee of Ministers under his chairmanship on Ministerialpublication.The Lord Chancellor said that the Committee had agreed thatsome restriction on the publication by Ministers of material whichwas derived from their experience in office was necessary in orderto maintain the principle of collective responsibility, but there wasthe delicate problem of balancing, on the one hand, the requirement of collective responsibility and, on the other hand, the desirabilityof allowing the production of autobiographical work, which was the raw material of history and the basis of much of the country&apos;saccumulated political experience. The Committee found the presentsituation unsatisfactory: the Official Secrets Acts prohibited the disclosure without authority of any information received by ministers in their official capacity, and, while there were conventions governing the circumstances in which publication could be authorised for thepurpose of the Acts, these conventions were not generally known.The Committee had therefore drawn up a code of conventions whichthey recommended should be specifically brought to the attention ofMinisters.   The code would require Ministers, on taking office, to acknowledge that the Official Secrets Acts applied to them; and toundertake that they would not on leaving office remove official papersexcept, with the permission of the Secretary of the Cabinet, copies of papers (other than those classified Top Secret) with which they hada close personal association; and that they would submit to theSecretary of the Cabinet before publication the manuscript of workbased on their experience as Ministers. The security risks inherent1 in keeping diaries or diary material should be drawn to the attention ofMinisters, who should ensure that any typist transcribing the material was aware of the provisions of the Official Secrets Acts, and that such material was securely kept.   A Minister? should not while in officeenter into a contract with a publisher for any work based directly onhis Ministerial experience. These recommendations were unanimous,but the Committee were divided on the question whether ministers should undertake to be bound by suggestions made by the Secretaryof the Cabinet for the deletion or amendment of material submittedto him. Three members, who were themselves authors, had objected to this proposal; the other two members had thought that, since itwas generally agreed that in the event of legal proceedings a minister would accept the decision of a judge, it was not unreasonable to ask him to accept suggestions from the Secretary of the Cabinet who was better qualified to advise on whether particular passages would be detrimental to security or to the country&apos;s current relations withforeign Powers.The Home Secretary said that the majority of the Committeehad taken the view on broad grounds of principle that, while theSecretary of the Cabinet was best qualified to advise former Ministers* Previously recorded in a Confidential Annex.SECRET
on passages in their work which might be harmful to the national interest, it would be unreasonable to expect Ministers to undertake inadvance to accept what would amount to censorship at some timein the future in circumstances which could not be foreseen. In themajority of cases the advice would no doubt be accepted, but a formerMinister should be free, if he thought the advice oppressive, to publishand to accept the risk that there might be legal proceedings. It was doubtful whether any Minister could sign the undertaking proposedby the majority of the Committee without secret reservations, and itwas important to avoid a distinction growing up between the theoryof Ministerial conduct and the actual practice.In discussion it was pointed out that while an author might be willing to listen to advice from the Secretary of the Cabinet he wouldbe unlikely to agree to be bound by that advice, particularly inrelation to works on the machinery of government in which theSecretary of the Cabinet would inevitably have some professionalinterest. Moreover, the proposed scheme was vitiated by the factthat it would be impossible to control the publication of articles in the Press which could be both highly mischievous and highlyremunerative, whereas the author of a book would be required toobtain the assent of the Secretary of the Cabinet. There was no satisfactory alternative to relying on the integrity and good judgment of Ministers. It would be undesirable to seek a binding undertaking which could not be enforced; and a Minister who would be preparedto publish material harmful to the public interest or the reputationsof his colleagues might also be prepared to give and subsequentlyignore the undertaking.It was suggested that a distinction should be drawn betweenquestions of security and accuracy and the reticence necessary to preserve the doctrine of collective responsibility. The Secretary ofthe Cabinet would be a suitable person to handle the former construing security in the sense employed in the Defence notice system: in recent instances he had in fact secured the omission ofmaterial which would prejudice security. As the servant of successive Governments he was also concerned with the maintenanceof the doctrine of collective responsibility and might be able to give an author valuable advice on this aspect of his work. Thepublication by a former Minister of attacks on the integrity orcompetence of his former colleagues would, however, harm boththe political system and the reputation of the Party concerned, who might as a result be assumed by the public to be incapable ofgoverning under the existing system of collective responsibility. Itmight therefore be appropriate for the Secretary of the Cabinet tobe consulted on matters of security and accuracy, subject to appealto the Prime Minister of the day; and to refer matters affecting theprinciple of collective responsibility either to the Prime Minister ofthe Government in which the author had served, or, if he were notavailable, to the current leader of his Party If the author refusedin the last resort to accept advice, it might be possible to have
recourse to proceedings under the Official Secrets Acts or to anapplication for an injunction; but it was unlikely that a judge would consider the political harm that might be done by the publication ofthe material in question to be sufficient ground for issuing an injunction, and the ultimate sanction would lie in the fact that the author had disregarded the advice of the leader of his Party and inthe freedom of those concerned to reply to his criticisms, or tocontribute hostile reviews of the book to the Press.It was argued, however, that reference to the leader of the author&apos;s Party would have several disadvantages. It might bethought unfair to expect a former Minister who had disagreed withhis Party to submit his manuscript to its leader, or a senior Ministerto submit to the judgment of a man much his junior in politicalservice. It would be embarrassing for the leader of the Party to seek the excision of criticism of some of his colleagues but not of others, and an attempt to interfere with the publication of the bookwould show the Party concerned in an illiberal light. Nevertheless,consultation with the leader of the Party might result in some reduction of inaccurate or malicious comment in the book; and experience suggested that authors would themselves be willing to consult the leaders of their Party. It was suggested, however, thatit would be a mistake to attribute too much importance to thepublication of autobiographies which were critical of fellowMinisters. An author who wrote from malice served to condemnhimself rather than to damage the reputation of his victim; andthere was no evidence that malicious autobiographies had harmedthe Party concerned in the eyes of the public. Moreover, in viewof this growing public sophistication, it might be more important toallow the free publication of material which promoted greaterunderstanding of the operation of government than to protectindividual Ministers against the criticism of their former colleagues.In further discussion the following principal points were made:(a) The opinion stated in paragraph 14 of the report of the ministerial Committee that the possibility of publishing dissentingopinion should not be excluded was open to question. It was one thing for a Minister to explain immediately on resignation why hehad dissented from the views of his colleagues; but quite another fora Minister who had remained in the Cabinet to claim years later that he had in fact dissented from the policies of his colleagues,especially if they were named, though he had not thought itnecessary to resign. It was pointed out, however, that the propriety of disclosures of this kind depended largely on when theywere made. Once the official records were open to public scrutinysuch disclosures were not necessarily harmful; and to preventdisclosures which had been customary in the past would deprivehistorians of valuable material.(b) The keeping of diaries by Ministers involved risks to security,both because Ministers seldom had secure facilities for the custody of the diary itself and because typists employed to transcribe dictation
IndustrialDisputesRailways(previous reference:CC(67) 55thConclusions,Minute 5)&apos;secret. The Minister of Labour said that the situation in the currentdispute affecting railway guards had somewhat deteriorated and the-strike had spread during the last few days. A further meeting betweenthe British Railways Board (BRB) and the National Union of railwaymen (NUR) was taking place that day; if no progress wasmade at this meeting the situation might well become more serious,since a proposal for a national strike in support of the guards had only been narrowly defeated on the National Executive of the NUR.or tape recordings were unlikely, even if warned of the applicationof the Official Secrets Acts, to be as conscious of the significance ofthe warning as would be a civil servant. Moreover, a Minister whokept a diary would have an advantage over any colleagues whom hesubsequently chose to criticise. On the other hand, it would not be practicable to forbid Ministers to keep diaries; and the fact that theydid so should afford some protection against inadvertent inaccuracyin their autobiographies.(c) It might be desirable to make a rule that Ministers shouldnot attribute official advice to a named individual, since he could notdefend himself and his value to the public service and his ownprospects might also be prejudged. On the other hand, senior officersof the Armed Forces had enjoyed considerable freedom to criticise the policies of Ministers, and it was not clear why civil servantsshould be protected by a rule of anonymity. It was possible, however,that the recommendations of the current Committee on the CivilService might have a bearing on this problem.(d) It should not be assumed that the Official Secrets Acts couldbe invoked as an ultimate sanction if a former Minister provedunwilling to accept advice on the amendment of his manuscript. Itwould be unwise to rely on proceedings either under the Acts or byway of injunction, in view of the reluctance to proceed against a former Minister and the risk that such proceedings would be presented as an attempt to suppress unpalatable information. It wastherefore the more incumbent on Ministers who enjoyed this degreeof immunity from legal sanctions to accept moral sanctions on thelines which the Committee had proposed.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that it was clear that the Cabinet were unwilling to reach a conclusion on theCommittee&apos;s proposals. He would accordingly give furtherconsideration to the problem himself, in the light of their discussion and in consultation with members of the Cabinet as appropriate; andwould later put before the Cabinet an outline of the conventionswhich might be found acceptable.The Cabinet-Took   note   that   the   Prime   Minister,   after   furtherconsideration and consultation, would bring new proposals before them.
Docks(previous reference:CC (67) 35thConclusions,Minute 6)He would consider in the light of the outcome of the meeting betweenthe BRB and the NUR whether there was any initiative which hecould usefully take with either or both sides in the dispute.The Home Secretary said that the Official Committee on emergencies would be meeting to consider the situation that afternoon. The main problem was the mounting accumulation ofparcels traffic on the railways, and if this continued it would soon benecessary to consider either placing restrictions on the acceptance ofparcels or the use of Service aircraft to move them.In discussion it was pointed out that the attitude of the NURwas contrary to the long-term interests of their members, since theGovernments plans for diverting traffic from road to rail under theprovisions of the forthcoming Transport Bill depended on the railwaysdemonstrating their reliability: this point had been emphasised to theUnion.There was general agreement that it would be unwise at thepresent juncture to make use of Service aircraft for the movementof parcels, and a decision on this should be deferred at least until thebeginning of the following week.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the statements by the Minister of Labour andthe Home Secretary.(2) Invited the Home Secretary to be guided by their discussion in considering the use of Service aircraft to move parcels.The Minister of Labour said that the number of dockers on strike in protest against the conditions of decasualisation of dock labour fluctuated from day to day: the previous day&apos;s total had beenapproximately 17,000 out of a labour force of some 60,000. the trouble was largely confined to parts of the Port of London, wherenearly one-third of the labour force was on strike, and to liverpool and Manchester where the ports were&quot; completely stopped. It was unfortunate that the official leadership of the Transport and general works Union ( T &amp; GWU) had not been prepared to take a firmerstand in the dispute. There were, however, signs that there might bea general resumption of work by the beginning of the following week.A major advance had been secured by the decision of the NationalAmalgamated Stevedores and Dockers to abandon their oppositionto a common register for stevedores and dockers, which was a vitalfeature of the new decasualisation scheme. There was no initiativewhich the Government could usefully take at the present time to hasten a resumption of work.The Home Secretary said that the main effect so far on maintenance of essential services was the delay in unloadingAustralian mail.The Cabinet-(3) Took note of the statements by the Minister of Labour andthe Home Secretary.
9 &quot;711     &apos;J 1 *AircraftIndustryBeagle AircraftCompany(previous reference :CC(66) 65thConclusions,Minute 5)CC 56 (67)secret . The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Secretary ofState for Economic Affairs (C (67) 151) about the position of theBeagle Aircraft Company.The Secretary of State for Economic Affairs recalled that theGovernment had decided in July 1966 to acquire the Beagle AircraftCompany and had reaffirmed their decision in December 1966, atwhich time it was estimated that the Company&apos;s production programme would require subventions from public funds totalling 3-2 million in the five years to 1970-71. The Company had now,however, submitted a revised programme and new financial estimates which would increase the requirement for Exchequer assistance to 4-5 million up to 1970-71. This change in the situation was largely due to a short-fall in sales of the B-206 aircraft and to the inclusion in the programme of new variants of this aircraft and of the smallerB-121.In view of this deterioration in the Company&apos;s position, the ministerial Committee on Industrial Policy had considered whetherthe Government would be justified in going ahead with the project,but had not been able to reach a consensus. Some Ministers hadargued that the advantages of the Governmenfs acquisition of theCompany had always been marginal, that the deterioration in salesprospects which had now taken place tipped the balance againstproceeding, and that the Government should withdraw now before their commitment became too heavy. Other Ministers had felt thatshort-term fluctuations in cash flow in a project of this kind had tobe expected and that the situation had not changed sufficiently tojustify withdrawal. In his view, the change in the situation since the government&apos;s decision in the previous December was not sufficientlysignificant in itself to warrant abandoning the project, and the argument in favour of that course must rest mainly on the proposition that it had been wrong to decide on acquisition originally. the project was not significant from the point of view of its effects on employment or on technological innovation and should therefore be judged solely by commercial criteria. On that basis it was doubtfulwhether the Government should continue with the acquisition of theBeagle Aircraft Company and the support of its programme.In discussion it was argued that there had been markeddeterioration in the Company&apos;s prospects over the previous nine months. Estimates of sales had proved over-optimistic, and therewere now no outstanding orders for the Company&apos;s principal aircraft. &apos;The prospective rate of return on the Governmenfs investment overthe next 13 years was now likely to be a little more than half thereturn of 6-2 per cent which was expected when the original decision was taken, and the investment of Government funds at such a low rate of return would represent a misuse of resources. While there might be some embarrassment to the Government if they now decided to withdraw, they would risk even greater embarrassment if
they persisted in supporting a project which the commercial worlddid not regard as viable, as had been shown by the fact that a numberof other companies, after closely examining the prospects of theBeagle Company, had not been prepared to interest themselves in it.If the Government proceeded with acquisition, this would be the firstproject to be undertaken under the proposed Industrial ExpansionBill, and it would be difficult to defend such a choice during thepassage of the Bill through Parliament. The Government should therefore abandon the project. This need not mean that the UnitedKingdom would be forfeiting any share of the market for light aircraft.A number of other British companies produced such aircraft, and the better course might be to aim at the creation of large organisations for marketing light aircraft which would have a better chance ofestablishing a world reputation in this field.On the other hand there was wide support for the view that theGovernment should proceed with the acquisition of the Company.The change in the situation since the previous December had notbeen sufficient to warrant reversing the decision taken then andwriting off the sum of  2 million which would be involved. If theGovernment were to withdraw, this would mean the immediatedismissal of some 1,000 employees which would exacerbate theproblem of the emigration abroad of skilled men in the aircraft industry. The Company still had reasonable sales prospects in a world market for light aircraft which was expected to expand at separately of 10 per cent per annum over the next decade. All theCompany&apos;s sales would either be exported or would represent a saving of imports. Marketing arrangements had been made with a major concern in the United States and were being negotiated withorganisations in France and Germany. The quality of the Company&apos;smanagement should be improved by the appointment of a newManaging Director and a suitable candidate had now been found.If the Government were to change their mind about the project so soon after their original decision, the aircraft industry, which was already beset by many uncertainties, would have legitimate ground for complaint.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that on balance the Cabinet agreed that the situation had not changedsufficiently to warrant reversing their earlier decision. Arrangementsfor the acquisition of the Company and for support of its programme should therefore continue.The Cabinet Agreed that the Government should proceed with theacquisition of the Beagle Aircraft Company and withsupport for its programme.SECRETEconomic 7.   The Minister of Labour said that, despite some gloomySituation prognostications in the Press, the September unemployment figuresFigured for^11 to be published that day were encouraging. The total number ofSeptember      registered unemployed at 11th September was 555,000, a fall of some
500 from the August figure, representing a percentage rate of 2-4which was unchanged since August. The number of unfilledvacancies for adults, seasonally adjusted, showed an increase of about10,000 between August and September, and this was the first increasein any month since April 1966. While it would be unwise to place too much weight on the figures for a single month, these movementsmight well mark the beginning of a general recovery in the economy.There had also been a slight improvement in the areas of high unemployment where the unadjusted percentage rate of unemploy-ment had fallen between August and September from 4 - 3 to 4 - 2 inthe Northern Region, from 4 -1 to 4 - 0 in Wales and from 3 - 8 to 3 - 7in Scotland.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the seasonallyadjusted increase between August and September in the number ofadults wholly unemployed was only 4,000 compared with an average monthly increase of 16,000 over the period March to August. Theslight fall of 500 in the total registered unemployed comparedfavourably with a rise of 23,000 from August to September in 1966.There was still appreciable unemployment among school leavers, butthe total number unemployed was only some three-fifths of thecorresponding number at the time of the last recession in 1963. it seemed a reasonable inference from these figures that the economy was beginning to recover and further evidence was provided by theincrease in the production index in July, the signs of increased activity in the motor industry and in housing. Moreover, the effects of alarge amount of public expenditure would be increasingly felt overthe coming months. Developments on the Stock Exchange reinforcedthe view that business confidence had not suffered to the extent that had seemed possible some months earlier. If the signs of recoverywere borne out, it would become important to avoid action whichmight lead to the overloading of the economy in the following year,and the Governmenfs measures should continue to be concentratedmainly on correcting regional disparities in unemployment and onselective strengthening of the economy.In further discussion the following points were made (a) The Prime Minister, with the Secretary of State for economic affairs and the Minister of Power, had discussed with the Chairmanof the National Coal Board on the previous evening the possibilityof selective deferment of pit closures with a view to alleviatingunemployment during the coming winter. The fact that this discussion had taken place was public knowledge, but talks were continuing and no Government statement on their substance couldyet be made.(b) It would be preferable not to seek special publicity at thepresent time for the measures under consideration for assisting minersdisplaced by pit closures, including the scheme for protecting the earnings of those made redundant over the age of 55.  It would be
more appropriate for the announcement of these measures to becoupled with the statements which would have to be made later aboutfuel policy.The Cabinet (1) Took note of the statement by the Minister of Labour on the september unemployment figures.(2) Invited Ministers to be guided by the points made in discussion in any public reference to the rundown of the coalmining industry.Cabinet Office, S. W.1,22nd September, 1967.


</content>
</cab>
