<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/188/4 images: 62-64</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^CUMENT IS THE property OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(76) 29 O *COPT NO      0 A10 March 1976CABINETCOMMUNITY SUPPORT FOR AGRICULTURE IN 1976-77Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and food.        The Council of Ministers (Agriculture) agreed last week on community support for agriculture in 1976-77.    The major points for uswere the retention of the beef premium scheme; a package of measures on milk; cereals prices; and the retention of an unchanged green pound.    Theprice negotiation took place against the background of monetary proposals and volatile exchange rates.    The outcome has to be assessed as a packageas well as measured against our negotiating objectives in the maincommodity sectors,2*        Beat;.    The introduction of fully variable premiums for beef was a major breakthrough for us.    These premiums keep consumer prices downand relegate support buying to a strictly contingency role.    At the periodof peak marketings we shall have a 25 per cent FEOGA contribution.    Evenmore importantly, the Council has now agreed to consider a full report onthe merits of premium arrangements to determine whether they should beadopted throughout the Community.3* Milk.    On milk it was a prime objective to hold down the price increasand to insist on the need to avoid arrangements which build up surpluses.After four days of hard bargaining I had to agree to target price increases,averaging 6 per cent over the year, which were somewhat higher than theCommission^ first proposals.    But this increase is effectively reduced toabout 4^ per cent by the new decision to Bet a lower intervention price forPkimrned milk powder.    We succeeded in getting this brought forward from september to March, so as to cut the new level of support from the outset.*Q addition the monetary changes lower the milk price increase in France toabout 3 per cent and in Germany to about 2 par cent.    These decisionstherefore represent a cut in support in real terms for milk producers in thetwo major producing countries of the Community.    I would have liked to seethem cut even more.    But this was the sticking point for France, and we hadno effective support from Germany - or any other country - in fighting forhigger cuts in r**l returns to milk producers.1
4. We did however secure, for the first time, a firm commitment tothe principle of producer co-responsibility for milk product surpluses inthe Community.    The Council will decide this year on the introduction ofa financial contribution by milk producers to the cost of disposing of milksurpluses.    This contribution will be levied from the beginning of the nextniilk year,    This would have been woAhinkable a year ox two ago and couldprove to be of major importance in tackling the surplus problem at source.5.        Cereals.   In the cereals sector the lower intervention price forfeed wheat is a clear gain for us.    The Commission had already proposed a reduction.    In the event the price was reduced even further, so that itwill be about 8 per cent below the current year!s level.    As we expected,the Commission^ proposal for flexible intervention for breadmaking wheatwas too far reaching for the producing countries to accept.    But in agreeing to the retention of normal intervention for a further year we managed toget the price increase cut substantially to 4 per cent,    I regret that wecould not secure bigger reductions in the target prices for maize and wheat.    This was another case where the Germans were not on our side.They are persistent supporters of high grain prices.6*        Monetary changes.    The proposals for monetary changes greatlycomplicated the negotiation.    The Germane and Dutch, who might other-wise have supported us on milk, were concerned above all to reduce the cut in their own farm support levels resulting from the proposals for changes in their green currencies.    This left us virtually isolated in the battle on milk.    In the event the smaller changes agreed still reducedsupport levels significantly for Germany (by 2. 5 percentage points),France (by 1.4 points) and Belgium and the Netherlands (by 0. 6 points).I too came under great pressure on the monetary side.    As theBpot rate for the pound fell the Commission proposed to devalue the greenpound bytowo percentage points.    This would have been very welcome to ourfarmers, but I rejected it as unacceptable to us because of its effect on food prices.    The effect of retaining an unchanged rate is to provideincreased import subsidies on many of our foodstuffs, financed by theCommunity.    The decline in the pound to yesterday &apos;s spcrtrate implies an extra Community cost on our import subsidies of over  50 million in afull year.    But in winning this point I was less well placed to secure other objectives.8.        In Bum, the package adds about l  per cent to our food prices by theend of the year, in addition to the 1 per cent transitional step to which wea*e committed under the Act of Accession.    I had to decide at the end ofthe day whether to take the drastic step of withholding agreement to apackage agreed by all other members.    I was guided by three main considerations.    First, the Committee on European Questions had agreedthat this was not the time for us to make a general stand of principleagainst those elements of the policy we find distasteful.    Second, although2
the package was very far from ideal, particularly on milk, it containedsubstantial gains for us, particularly on beef and cereals.    Finally, anddecisively, I judged that a delay would offer no prospect of a better solutionat a later meeting, but rather a very considerable risk, in the light of thedeclining value of the pound, of much heavier pressure on us to devalue the green pound and no put up fao-i prices across the board.   I am certain that inthe circumstances the right course was to accept.T F ministry of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food10 March 19763

</content>
</cab>
