<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/46/32 images: 480-485</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOYERMMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  February 1944.SECRET.Copy No.W.P. (44) 82.4zth February, 1944.WAR CABINET.ARTICLE VII DISCUSSIONS WITH THE DOMINIONS AND INDIA.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.IN accordance with the decision of the War Cabinet of the 21st December(W.M. (43) 173rd Conclusions) invitations were addressed to the Governmentsof the Dominions and India with a view to their sendiilg officials to London inFebruary for further discussions with United Kingdom officials covering the wholefield of Article VII. These invitations were accepted by all the Governmentsconcerned, and arrangements are now in train for the discussions to open hereon the 21st February.2. I need not trouble my colleagues with the details of the arrangements forthe conference, but one point arises on which I should welcome their views, namely,the instructions to be given in regard to the avoidance of publicity.3. This will be the third meeting with Dominion and Indian officials on article VII topics. On the two previous occasions, October 1942 and June 1943,it was agreed with the Governments concerned that both the substance of thediscussions and the fact that discussions were taking place should be kept strictly confidential, and steps were accordingly taken throughout the commonwealth to ensure that there should be no publicity. In the same way, on the present&apos;occasion, the Governments concerned have been asked to keep the arrangementssecret.4. There have, of course, been numerous references in the press and inParliament to the fact that discussions have been proceeding with the UnitedStates on monetary matters, and it might be said that, if it became public thattalks on this aspect were proceeding with the Dominions and India, no greatharm would result. But the difficulty would be to confine any public referencesof this kind to the monetary field, and if it became known that talks were alsoproceeding on commercial policy, commodity policy, &amp;c, there might be serious embarrassment not only to the Dominions but also to the United States. DominionGovernments have impressed upon us in the past the importance they attach to secrecy at this exploratory stage, and recent telegrams from Washington havemade it clear that any public reference here, in particular to commercial policydiscussions, would be strongly deprecated by the State Department at the presenttime.5. In the circumstances I would propose, if my colleagues agree, to follow the same course as on the two previous occasions and to ask the Censorship toarrange with the Press for the avoidance of all reference to these discussions,whether on the monetary or other aspects.- -Q-:.Dominions Office,4-th February, 1944.26875






</content>
</cab>
