<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/8/20 images: 206-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO EE KEPT UNDER LOOK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.(this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;s GOVERNMENT)secret.P.40 (190)copy No. 2 to3rd June, 1%.0.WAR   CABINETCAMPAIGN TO PREPARE PUBLIC FOR INVASION.Memorandum by the Ministry of InfcarnationThe Committee presided over by the Lord President of the Councilrecently invited the Ministry of Information &quot;to warn and rouse thepublic&quot; against &quot;the imminent danger of invasion&quot;.   The necessaryprograms was prepared and was approved by the Lord President1 s Committeeon Friday May 31.   It is now ready to be put into operation but in viewof the fact that the situation has materially changed since May 31 theMinistry require further Cabinet authority before launching their/   programme.   A summary of the scheme proposed is attached to thismemorandum.The Mihistjry of - Information assume that in view of the present state of public uncertainly some reference to the possibility of invasion,and to our means of meeting it, will be made by the Prime Minister in his speech on Tuesday or- in his subsequent broadcast on Wednesday.   The pointupon which they ask for Cabinet guidance is whether the Prime Minister&apos;sspeech should be followed up by an immediate launching of the agreed programme for warning the public.(l) Although the Y/ar Office inform us that &quot;it is probable thatthe enemy v/ill attack in Prance before attempting anyinvasion of this country, yet there exists a possibility that he may strike at us first.   Should this happen thepublic will blame the Government for not having warned thornin advance,(2) The public have already observed the defensive preparationsbeing adopted and anxiety would be allayed if full warningand instructions were issued immediately.(3) It will take some time for the public to digest their instructions and it may be considered prudent to issue themnow, even if no early invasion ia expected.(4) The issue of warnings and instructions should have a toniceffect upon recruiting, and, if properly handled, uponproduction.The disadvantages of putting the scheme into immediateoperation would be the following(l) The danger of upsetting French opinion. It may berepresented in Prance that H.M.G. , having withdrawn theB.E.P., - from French soil are now preparing to render thisThewould seem toadvantages of putting the scheme into immediate operationbe the following:-
island a defended fortress and that no further Britishtroops will be sent across the seas. It should not howevejprove difficult to launch an anti-invasion campaign. athone while reassuring the French as to the further assistance v/e propose to give then.   Such reassurancenight &quot;be given in the Prine Minister^ speech.(2) If, as soons probable, no invasion of England will be threatened in the immediate future, it night seenpremature to issue the scheme at this moment.   The sohenecould he held ready in every detail.   But if launchedprematurely, it night expose the Government to the accusation of scarenongering, and such stimulus as it niggive to the publio night die down as the weeks passedwithout invasion taking place.The SiSsiistjry of Inf omatian would-be obliged if the WarCabinet would consider these arguments and give a decision whether thesanpa&amp;gn is to be - laraiohea immediately or&apos; helfl in readiness for operatiSwhen -the danger fceoenea dearly iociiAeat. ..
ANNEXE     A-The Prtoe,Minister&apos;s speech in the House of Conuons, and hissubsequent &quot;broadcast, will have warned the public of the danger of invasionand will have reused then to neet it when      $pnes.It will then be -necessary to tell the public how to preparethenselvea for the energency, and to issue to then precise instructions as to what they are to do.   It is suggested that- the following broadcasttalks should be the first steps in this canpaign.Tuesday, June 4thaPull report of the Friiae Ministers statenent in the Houseof Cannons,9 0&apos;clock Newse   Appeal for additional personnel required... for the Civil Defence Services,   . &apos;vThe Ministry of Hone Security have already&apos; instructed thelocal authorities to he prepared to reoeive volunteers whorespond to this appeal.   This will include a request totrained personnel to return to the Civil Defence Services,nostly as part-tine volunteers.   There will also be a reference to the needs of the Civil Nursing Reserve, andthe need for Stretcher Bearers and for additional PoliceWar Reservists and Special Constables,Wednesday, June 5th.9 o&apos; clock,   Broadcast by the Prine Minister, followed bythe News Bulletin, including a brief talk by the G. 0,C, inC,   Hone Forces, General Ironside, with the object ofareassuring the public regarding the preparedness of theHone Defences,Thursday, June 6th,Talk by the Minister of Information, bringing to theattention of the civil population the series of instructions which will be issued to then by the press, by broadcasting,and by panphlets.These instructions are now being prepared by the Ministryof Inf ornation on the basis of naterial prepared by theWar Office, in collaboration with G.H..Q,, Hone Forces, andTrf.ll include infomation on the following points:1. Action to be taken by the civil population if enenytroops land by sea or by air.2. Necessity of keeping the roads clear for our troops,3c Denying transport to the invader,4* Special instructions for those in charge of factories,,




</content>
</cab>
