<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/56/14 images: 132-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;8 GOVERNMENTINTERNATIONAL CIVIL AIR TRANSPORT : WHITE PAPEROUTLINING GOVERNMENT POLICY.ON the 25th September (127th Conclusions) the War Cabinet decided thatthe question whether a White Paper should be presented to Parliament in thenear future, outlining&apos; the policy which we advocate for the future ordering ofinternational air transport, should be further considered when a draft had beenprepared and circulated.2. I circulate a draft herewith. I trust that my colleagues will agree tovery early publication, seeing that Commonwealth discussions are due to start at montreal on the 23rd October and the International Conference in the UnitedStates on the 1st November.3. The Dominions and India are aware of and have endorsed these proposals.The Americans and other foreign countries with whom we have had conversa-tions are also aware of them. An accurate version of our plan has even appeared in an American journal. The Americans have recently published their own ideas;the Canadians have published theirs; the Australian, New Zealand and SouthAfiican Governments have also indicated where they stand. Parliament and ourown people, however, have not as yet had a full conspectus of our plan. It is only right that they should be given it now.Printed for the War Cabinet.  October 1944.SECRET.W.P. (44) 564.Qth October, 1944.WAR CABINET.Note by the Secretary of State for Air.A. H. M. S.Air Ministry, 9th October, 1944.&quot;283651

Draft White Paper.PROOFInternational Air TransportPresented by to Parliament by Command of His Majesty1944LONDONPRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICETo be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERV OFFICE at the following addresses:York House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2;   13a Castle Street, Edinburgh 2;39-41 King Street, Manchester 2;   1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;So Chichester Street, Belfast;or through any bookseller1944price      netCmd.
INTERNATIONAL AIR TRANSPORT.Fou some time past, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kin^i,,,,.in consultation with the Governments of other Commonwealth countries&apos;hus been giving close attention to the problems of international civil aittransport and to the general principles which should govern the post-wararrangements. It now seems appropriate to Mis Majesty&apos;s Governmentthat the plan which it favours for the ordering of post-war air transport should be communicated for the information of Parliament.2. Before the war, the international regulation of civil aviati.ni w,,concerned mainly with its technical aspects, eg., safety regulations, rulesthe air, air worthiness, radio and meteorological procedure, and the liceusiiof personnel and aircraft. Moreover, there was no single international convention which commanded universal support. At the outbreak pi warthe Convention for the Regulation of Air Navigation (the Paris convention of 1919) had been ratified by thirty-three States, but, among others, theUnited States, the U.S.S.R. and China were not parties to it. ;,.addition to providing for a high degree of uniformity in technical matters the Convention embodied the doctrine of the national sovereignty of the airEach party to the Convention, however, granted to private (non-cominercialjaircraft of other member States the right of innocent passage through iuair space prohibited ar-eas excepted provided that permission was sought for landings for re-fuelling and emergency purposes. The operation of regularcommercial air services was, in practice, subject to the consent of the Statesthrough whose territory the services passed.3. The United States of America, in conjunction with eight CentralAmerican Republics and Chile, concluded in 1928 the Havana Convention,which, though broadly comparable in scope with the Paris Convention,differed in certain important respects. In particular, its application was limited to the American Continent and it made no provision for internationaluniformity in technical matters.4. Neither of these Conventions made provision for international regulation in the economic, as opposed to the technical, field. In the result,the growth of air transport was conditioned by political rather than economic considerations and its development as an orderly system of world com-niunieations was impeded. Summed up, the major evils of the pre-war period were, first, that any country on an international air route could holdoperators of other countries to ransom even if those operators only wishedto fly over or refuel in its territory; secondly, that there was no means of controlling the heavy subsidisation of airlines which all too often were maintained at great cost for reasons mainly of national prestige or as a war potential; and thirdly, that the bargaining for transit and commercial rightsintroduced extraneous considerations and gave rise to international jealousiesand mistrust.General Principles which should Govern the Posi-War Arrangements.5. His Majesty&apos;s Government desires to see a radical change in this situation after the war. Recent technical advances have increasedenormously both the range and carrying-capacity of transport aircraft. the modern multiple-engined aircraft has made possible the development of anetwork of air routes which already span the world. The potentialities ofair transport are indeed great; so also will be its influence, for good or ill.on international relations.
qq   in other economic spheres, the importance of co-operation between e nations after the war has been recognised.   It is no less important thatIcvflopment of air transport should proceed under enlightened inter-ul direction.   Accordingly, the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government; asto Parliament on the 11th March, 194H, is that &quot; some form ofinternational collaboration will be essential if the air is to be developed inthe interests of mankind  as a whole, trade served, international under--t-mdings fostered and some measure of international security gained.&quot;rpbe main objectives of such collaboration would be:  (i) to meet the needs of the peoples of the world for plentiful, efficient and cheap air services;(ii) to maintain broad equilibrium between the world&apos;s air transportcapacity and the traffic offering;(iii) to ensure equitable participation by the various countries engagedin international air transport;(iv) to eliminate wasteful competitive practices and.  in particular, tocontrol subsidies;(y) to standardise practice on technical matters important to the safety of flying;(vi) in general, to contribute to world security.A New Air Convention to give Effect to These Principles.7. His Majesty&apos;s Government propose that a new Convention shouldbe drawn up to take the place both of the Paris Convention of 1919 andof the Havana Convention of 1928, and to make provision for the regulationof international air transport. This Convention, to which all States wouldbe invited to subscribe, would: -(i) reaffirm the principle of national sovereignty of the air and definewhat should, for this purpose, constitute the territory of a State;(ii) define the degree of freedom of the air to be enjoyed by the ratifyingStates.   It is j)proposed that this should&apos;extend to:  (a) the right of^passage through a States air space;(b) the right to land for non-traffic purposes (re-fuelling, emer-gency, &amp;c.);(c) the right to disembark passengers, mails and freight from thecountry of origin of the aircraft:((7) the right to embark passengers, mails and freight destined forthe country of origin of the aircraft.(Note: The right to pick up and set down traffic to andfrom destinations which are not. in the country of origin of the aircraft and the right to engage in thecabotage of another country would be a matter for negotiation.)(iii) define the international air routes which should be subject to inter-national control; these would be reviewed from time to time as necessary;(iv) provide for the elimination of uneconomic competition by the deter--n dilation of frequencies (total services of all countries operating on any international route), the distribution of those frequenciesbetween the countries concerned and the fixing of rates of carriagein relation to standards of speed and accommodation;(v) provide for the licensing of international air operators who under-took to observe the Convention and to abide by the rulings andfor the withdrawal of the licence from any operator who dis-regarded his obligations;
(vi) provide for the denial of facilities to any unlicensed operator;(vii) provide for the collection and review of information about servicescosts, subsidies, rates of carriage, landing fees, &amp;c.;(viii) provide for arbitration in matters of dispute](ix) secure the acceptance by the ratifying States of an obligation toprovide, in their respective territories, the ground facilities needed for international services or to allow such facilities to lie provided-(x) prescribe safety regulations, such as rules of the air, airworthiness&apos;licensing of personnel and aircraft, ground signals, meteorologicalprocedure. &amp;c. (The domestic airlines operating within the territories of the member States would not be governed by theConvention, hut it is hoped that States would voluntarily appfothe agreed standards to their internal services.)ixi) provide for the standardisation, so far as possible, of riiciioequipment, meteorological and ground facilities.The International Machinery.8. For the administration of the Convention, it is proposed that anInternational Air Authority should be established and under it (i) an Opera-tional Executive with subsidiary Regional Panels: and (ii) sub-commissions to deal with technical matters.9. The Authority would consist of representatives of the ratifying states with voting powers to be determined on an equitable basis.10. The composition of the Operational Executive and the procedure for selecting its members are matters for further examination. Possibilitiesare (a) that the members should be nominated in the Convention; (/;) thatthey should be elected by the Authority: and (c) that they should be nominated by the major Powers, with provision for representation of thesmaller Powers.11. Membership of a Regional Panel would be confined to States which,in the opinion of the Operational Executive, have an interest in international air transport in the areas for which each Panel is responsible.12. It would be the prime task of the Authority to give effect to theprovisions of the Convention for the determination and distribution of fie-quencies and for the fixing of rates of carriage in relation to standards of safety and accommodation. It would, for this purpose, work through the operational Executive which in turn would delegate its functions as appropriate to the Regional Panels, the decisions of the Panels being subjectto review by the Executive, and those of the Executive, as necessary, by theAuthority.13.   In addition, the Authority would :  (i) administer the provisions of the Convention governing such matters as safety standards and ground organisations; and(ii) prescribe standard requirements for international  aerodromes and ancillary facilities, the provision of which would be theresponsibility of the ratifying States; or arrange for the provisionof such aerodromes and facilities in cases where a State was unableor unwilling to do so.14. Such in broad outline are the proposals which His Majesty&apos;sGovernment favour for the ordering of post-war international civil air transport. The proposals are, of course, of a provisional nature and may be modified in the light of views expressed by other countries.8th October, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
