<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/48/18 images: 172-187</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT86TOP secret the circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.........\s &amp;QUZ&amp;bijt.......   ^-v.Copy No.       &apos;W.M.(UU)  169th conclusions confidential Annex(16th December, !9hA - 3.0 p.m.)FOREIGN AFFAIRSPoland(previous ReferenceW.M.(hh) 157thConclusions)The War Cabinet had a general discussion on foreign affairs.     The first matter dealtwith was the situation in Poland.THE PRIME MINISTER read to the WarCabinet a telegram (No. T.2366/h) from thePresident dated 15th December In which he asked whether it would be helpful if he wereto send a message to Premier Stalin suggesting the postponement of positive action on thePolish question until he (the President),Premier Stalin and the Prime Minister could get together.The President recalled the contents of aletter dated 17th November which he had sent tr*Mo Mikoiajczwk by Mr. Harriman, and of which a  .copy had been shown to the Prime Minister,outlining American policy in regard to Poland.He anticipated strong pressure for the positionof the United States Government to be made clear, and he might, therefore, have to make public in some form the four points containedin this letter.THE PRIME.MINISTER re called the substance of these four points which were as follows -(i) The United States Government standunequivocally for a strong, free and independentPolish state with the untrammelled right of thePolish people to order their internal existenceas they saw fit.(il) If mutual agreement was reached on the$WSss^L t future frontier of Poland between the Polish,/^.l&amp;ht&amp;iiMOifr^yfi       Soviet and British Governments, the United StatesOffW^h1^ fagt**atW Government would offer no objection.     TheI 0 United States Government could h*t give aguarantee of any specific frontiers, but was working for the establishment of a world security organisation.(iii) The United States Government would raise no objection, and so far as practicablewould facilitate transfers to and from Polishterritories of National minorities in connectionwith the new frontiers of the Polish state.

11 &apos;*. (iv) The United States Government was. prepared to assistas far as practicable in the post-war reconstruction of &apos;Poland. ^THE PRIME MINISTER read to the War -cabinet a draft interim reply to this telegram, inviting the&apos;President to carry out at once his proposal to send a message to Premier Stalin, suggesting that he postponed any positive action on the Polish question until the three ofthem could get together.The War Cabinet agreed with this course-,but felt that nothing but good could come from thepublication of the four points in the Presidents letter toM. Mikolajczwk and that the President should be urged to publish them.     It was agreed that an addition in this sense should be made in-the Prime Minister&apos;s telegram tothe President. .Some discussion ensued about the Easternfrontiers of Poland.     The view was expressed that provided it was definitely agreed that Lwow belonged to Russia,the Russians might of their own accord be willing tocede it to Poland as a gesture..    Such a gesture, however,was only likely to be made in a friendly atmosphere.The War Cabinet&apos;s conclusions were asfollows -(l) The despatch by the Prime Minister of atelegram to President Roosevelt on thelines at &quot;?7&quot; was ,approved.    (Despatched asT. 2369/4)(2) The Foreign Secretary undertook to consider,.   in the light of previous telegrams, whetherit would be wise for the Prime Minister alsoto despatch a telegram to Premier Stalin,urging him to take no positive action on thePolish question until the next meeting of fcinself. the President and the Prime Minister.(3) The Foreign Secretary undertook to supply thePrime Minister with material for a fullerreply to the President&apos;s telegram of the15th December - (T.2366/4)/ Sir Archibald Clark-Kerr withdrew at this point,JGreece(previous reference:W.M.(44)168thConclus ions,Minute 1)The War Cabinet then discussed the situation in greece, and had before them - - -(i) a memorandum from the King of Greece dated 13thDecember, and a telegram from the Foreign Officeto the Ambassador at a Athens- of the same date(w.P.(44) 740)(ii) a letter dated 14th December from the King of Greecevto the Prime Minister (W.P.(44) 741)   ,(iii) telegrams No. 1325 of 14th December and-1331 of15th December, to the Prime Minister from field marshal Smuts.\

(iv) telegram No. 239 of 15th%december to the Prime&apos;Minister from Mr. Mackenzie King.(v) a series of recent telegrams from Mr. Deeper andMr. Macmillan in Athens, Nos. 610-614, 61-6-620of 15th and 16th December.I.- The War Cabinet first considered the Attitude of theDominions a in the light of the telegrams referred to under (ill) and (iv) above.Field Marshal Smuts reported that he had spokenstrongly in favour of the policy of the United KingdomGovernment.     He added that his own view was that when theE.A.M-. revolt had been suppressed the Greek King should return to discharge his proper constitutional functions,and the United Kingdom Government should not be left with* the onus of practically running Greece.The telegram from the Prime Minister of Canada, onthe other hand, expressed uneasiness at the situation whichhad arisen, Mr. Mackenzie King said that he had given apublic assurance that Canadian troops would no.t serve in greece without the consent of the Canadian Government.After discussion -The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs was invited to prepare draft telegrams for thePrime Minister to send to Field Marshal Smutsand Mr. Mackenzie King.The reply to the latter would be on the linesthat he would do a great dis-service to the unity- of the. Empire if he were, as-he suggested, tomake any public statement dissociating the-Canadian Government from the action which wasbeing taken in Greece, and assuring him thatthere was no intention of using Canadian troopsin the Greek operations.IX.    The King of,Greece&apos;s letter of 14th.December.THE PRIME MINISTER drew the attention of the WarCabinet to the letter from the King of Greece dated 1hthDecember, circulated as W.P.(44) 741.      The King had made astrong and reasoned plea against the immediate establishmentof a Regency.     He questioned the degree of.support for theappointment Of the Archbishop as Regent, and he emphasised that a decision in that sense would be against the presentviews of.his own Prime Minister and of many other political leaders.The Prime Minister said that he had asked theForeign Secretary what action we could take if the Kingmaintained his opposition to a Regency,-and reached theconclusion that itwas essential, nevertheless, to appoint aRegent&quot;.  .. He      -.erstood the Foreign Secretary&apos;s view to bethat the only course open to us would be to inform HisMajesty that if he felt unable to accept our view, weshould be forced to recognise a Regent, howeverappointed, as the de facto lawful government of thatcountry, and to withdraw such recognition from His Majesty.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that this would be theonly course open to us.

The War&apos;Cabinet proceeded to consider the latest reports which had been received from Mr. Macmillanand   His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Athens.     VIt appeared that M. Papandreou (with the support ofof most of the members of the Present Government) had nowadvised the King to agree to a Council of Regency of threeconsisting of the Archbishop (President), General Plastiras,and M. Dragoumls (Athens,Tel. 613 of 15th December and619 of 16th December).      M. Sophoulis on 1hth December hadbeen opposed to the appointment of a Regent, but on the evening of 15th December he and the politicians collaboratingwith him had advised the King to appoint one, the Archbishopbeing indicated as suitable (Athens Tel.- 61U. of 15thDecember and 620 of 16th   December).     Three Ministers orex-Ministers consulted by the Ambassador had said that theappointment would be.welcome, and M..Svolos and M. Kaphand(a former Prime Minister) supported the appointment of the archbishop (Athens Tel.  611 of 15th December and 621 of 16thDecember). Field Marshal Alexander was strongly of Mr.Macmillans opinion that the Archbishop should take controland would fly over to Athens to interview him&apos; personally ifhe was appointed (Athens Tel. 618 of 15th December).Mr. Macmillan and Mr. Eeeper continued to urge thatthe King should be pressed to agree -without further delay to the appointment&apos;of the Archbishop as Regent;    it was important that the initiative should come from His majesty and not appear to be a concession made to the insurgents.To accept M. Papendreou&apos;s advice for a Council of RegencyWould in their view lead to nowhere, because in that event the Archbishop&apos;would not accept, and only the appointment of-. the Archbishop as a single Regent would have any influence on&apos;the Left (Athens- Tel.. 619 of 16th December).The following points were made in-discussion -(a) It was important to ascertain what advice had beentendered pd the King of Greece by his Ministers, who wereconstitutionally responsible.      If he was in a position to claim that in refusing to t.gree to a Regency., or to theappointment of the Archbishop as sole Regent, as distinct from a Council of Regency, he was following their advice,it would be very difficult to justify taking extreme stepsiith him..  (b) Was the evidence that the-appointment of a Regencywas necessarily the right solution really conclusive?     Itwould be unfortunate if we.were to commit ourselves to theprinciple of a Regency, and bring pressure on the King toaccept our view,  only to find that we had asked him to makethe sacrifice involved to no purpose, and that the position. in Athens was no better than before.(c) Were we completely satisfied that the Archbishop wasnecessarily the right man for the post?     While he was understood to have played a distinguished part against the axis during the occupation he was said to be a wordly andambitious prelate.     The King clearly entertained doubts asto his suitability,: .and it appeared that his appointment assole Regent would not be welcome to M. Papendreou.(d) It was not clear on what Mr. Macmillan based his view that a Regency of three would not. meet the case, andthat the Archbishop would only be prepared to act as 1Regenot if appointed, without colleagues.      It seemed desirable to test-the position further.

(e) It was suggested that the right course was that weshould first persuade the King to accept the principle of.aRegency, leaving the question of the person to he appointedto he worked out subsequently, yThe general sense of the war Cabinet was that havingregard to the conflicting nature of the evidence, itwould be desirable to invite our representatives on the,spo,t to let us have a fuller appreciation of the -position,-and in particular of the attitude of representativeopinion in Greece. ,The Prime.Minister and the Foreign Secretary should further, -discuss the position with the King of greece and ascertain what further information was availableto His Majesty, and in particular,  if possible,   whatadvice which had heen tended to him by his Ministers abouta Regency.      They should aim at securing his acceptanceof the principle of a Regency, and should warn him that whatever his decision, and even assuming therestoration of order now,   before very long events mightwell make it necessary for him to have a representative on the spot.IV..    The Military Position in Athens.A discussion followed on the military position.The following points were made -(a) THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF said thatre-inforcements were continuing to arrive.     *The presentestimate of the strength of E.L.A.S. in Athens and thePiraeus was believed to be about 12,000.      Although theposition was difficult, there was no danger in his judgment of our forces in Athens not being able to hold out.(b) The military position in Athens was by no meansclear.      In particular it was difficult to judge whether our troops were merely holding the position or whether&apos; an active -offensive was being taken against E.L.A.S.(c) There was nothing to show that Field Marshal    ^Alexander thought that resistance was dying.      On the otherhand it was urged that there seemed much to be said forawaiting to see the effect of the reinforcements now beinglanded, since a marked military success would greatlystrengthen our hands in dealing with the political situation..(d) Attention was drawn to the importance of protecting   .the lives of the King1s supporters, and-of those troops which had been loyal to him.      It was generally felt.-thatany terms of settlement approved by us should include ageneral amnesty.V.    The Time FactorThe War Cabinet felt that the situation had not reached a point at which immediate decisions were necessary.Nor was the evidence available to them, either on themilitary or on the political situation, sufficiently firmto make it possible with confidence to reach an immediate decision.      It might well be that a delay of two or three days  (during which further appreciations could.be .obtained from our political and military representatives in   Athens)    would   be    advantageous.

After such an interval wo should he hotter able to judge the&quot;effect of the fresh reinforcements that1were being sent in, and the state of opinion -in Greece.     ,The King, too, might modify his attitude, and:theresult.of the discussion between His Majesty and thePrime Minister and Foreign Secretary would be. available.Meantime our representatives in Athens should beinformed&apos; of the course of discussion and the reasonsfor which no immediate decision was felt to be possible-It v/ould be desirable also that a factual account ofthe course of events should be sent to Premier Stalin;and that President Roosevelt, from.whom the primeMinister informed the Y/ar Cabinet that he had receiveda sympathetic and co-operative message,  should receive a full appreciation of the position as we saw it.The conclusions of the discussion may besummarised as follows.(l) It was noted that,  if the King refusedto accept a Regency, the only course open to His Majesty&apos;s Government, ifthey decided- that a Regency was essential, - -would be to inform him that they&apos; would recognise the Regent, however appointed,as the do facto lawful head of the^State,and would withdraw such recognition fromHis Majesty.    This extreme step could,however, only be justified on very stronggrounds if the King claimed that, in refusing to agree to a Regency, he whsfollowing the advice &apos;of his Ministers, whowere constitutionally responsible;(2) Given the conflicting nature of the evidence as to the degree of stxpport on whichthe   Archbishop-  could rely, the attitudeof the Greek Ministers, and the advicetendered by them to His Majesty, and thepossibility of a favourable turn in themilitary situation, as a result of the arrival of reinforcements,  it would be inadvisable to force an immediate decisionon the Regency issue, against a continued refusalby the King.(3) The Prime Minister and Foreign Secretarywere invited to discuss the positionfurther with the King of Greece in thelight of. the information now available tothe War Cabinet, and to ascertain what further information His Majesty had on thesituation and in particular, if possible,the advice tendered by his Ministers onthe matter of a Regency.    They should aim at sercuring his acceptance of the principle ofa Regency and should warn him that,whatever his decision now, and evenassuming the restoration of order, events. might well before very long make it necessaryfor him to have a representative on thesnot:

(If) Our representatives in Athens should he informed of the reasons why the War cabinet had reached the conclusion that no immediate decision on the question of a Regency was,possible; ,(5) Fuller appreciations of the military andpolitical situations and as to the state ofopinion in Greece so far as that could be. ascertained, should be called for from themilitary commanders on the spot and from our ambassador in Athens.      The Prime minister unertook to be responsible for the necessary action.(6) The Foreign Secretary was invited toprepare a draft telegram to Premier Stalininforming him of the course of events, andthe Prime Minister undertoak to letPresident Roosevelt have an appreciation ,of the position.(7) The Secretary of State for the Dominions wasi nvited to prepare drafts of telegrams fromthe Prime Minister to Field Marshal Smutsand the Prime Minister of Canada in replyto the telegrams received from them;(8) The War Cabinet would resume considerationof this matter, in the light of the reportsnow asked for? and the King&apos;s attitude, in2 or 3 days time.Offices of the War Cabinet, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
