<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/3/8 images: 106-149</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
K&apos;9THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT,SE ORE T.W.P.(R) (39) (93) Copy No,W A R      C A B I N E T.ACTION TAKEN BY THE DOMINIONS*Third Report submitted by the Secretary of Statefor Dominion Affairs.(Previous Report:    Paper No, V/oPe(R).  (39) 50).27th November, 1939.

CANADAil Jl. Goner a.&quot;.,. Position.A General Election took place in Quebec on the25th October,  the Provincial Premier, Mr. Duplessis, havingappealed to the country on account of the alleged threat toProvincial autonomy involved in the putting into force by theCanadian Government of the War Measures Acte      The Electionresulted in the defeat of Mr0 Duplessis and a victory for theLiberal Party by 63    to 18.(2) Naval Military and Air Activities.The Canadian destroyers are engaged in patrol andconvoy duties in the North Atlantic,      H.M.So&quot;Kempenfeldtwhich had been purchased by the Canadian Government, has nowbeen transferred to the Royal Canadian Navy and re-namedH.M.C.S.&quot;Assiniboine&quot;.Discussion has taken ijlace with the Canadian military representatives in this country as to matters connected withthe despatch of the Canadian Expeditionary Force.      The 1stCanadian Division will be ready to leave Canada early inDecember and, if it sails then,  it will be possible for itto be assembled in this country early in January 1940 and tojoin the 4th Corps after the 1st May 1940.      A Canadian ArmyStaff is in process of formation at the Office of the HighCommissioner for Canada in London.As a result of discussion in Canada between theMissions from the United Kingdom, Australia and New Zealand,and Canadian Ministers,  with regard to the Air Training Scheme,it

u 0it is hoped that it will be possible within the next few daysfor an agrend scheme to be drawn up,  defining the contributions of the several participating Governments,,      The detailed provisions of the scheme are still under discussion,The suggestion was made to the Canadian Governmentthat they might be able to provide forthwith an Air Squadron for service overseas,      They have intimated that this would not be practicable but have put forward the alternative suggestion thata Squadron of the R.A.F. might be formed from Canadianpersonnel already serving, to be  subsequently absorbed in theRoyal Canadian Air Force.      Action to this end is being taken,(.5)    Legislative Action.__There have been no developments of importancesince the date of the last report.(Ai Seonomic Action.The United Kingdom Purchasing Mission underCaLGreenlyan association with the Canadian War Supply Board,have continued their work and a number of munition orders havebeen placed.      Arrangements for Aircraft contracts have alsobeen made in conjunction with the separate Mission headed byLord Riverdale sent to Canada to deal with the Air training scheme,Raw materials have remained on the whole a matter for negotiation in London, and advantage is being taken of thepresence of special Canadian representatives in connexion withthe visit of Dominion Ministers to hold discussions with theappropriate Departments.      Negotiations are also in progressregarding the purchase of certain Canadian food products.Details were given by the Minister of Pood in his recent reportto the Cabinet W,P.(R).  (30) (69),o  o  

it is hoped that it will be possible within the next few daysfor an agreed scheme to be drawn up, defining the contributions of the several participating Governments,      The detailed provisions of the scheme are still under discussion.The suggestion was made to the Canadian Governmentthat they might be able to provide forthwith an Air Squadron for service overseas.      They have intimated that this would not be practicable but have put forward the alternative suggestion thata Squadron of the R.A.F, might be formed from Canadianpersonnel already serving,  to be subsequently absorbed in theRoyal Canadian Air Force.      Action to this end is being taken,( 5)   Legislative Action._There have been no developments of importar.eesince the date of the last report.(Sconomlc Action.The United Kingdom Purchasing Mission underOaLGreenlypin association with the Canadian War Supply Beard,have continued their work and a number of munition orders havebeen placed.      Arrangements for Aircraft contracts have alsobeen made in conjunction with the separate Mission headed byLord Riverdale sent to Canada to deal with the Air training scheme.Raw materials have remained on the whole a matter for negotiation in London,  and advantage is being taken of thepresence of special Canadian representatives in connexion withthe visit of Dominion Ministers to hold discussions with theappropriate Departments.      Negotiations are also in progressregarding the purchase of certain Canadian food products.Details were given by the Minister of Food in his recent reportto the Cabinet W.P.(R).  (39) (69),

it is hoped, that it will be possible within the next few daysfor an agreed scheme to be drawn up, defining the contributions of the several participating government      The detailed provisions of the scheme are still under discussion.The suggestion was mace to the Canadian Governmentthat they might be able to provide forthwith an Air Squadron for service overseas.      They have intimated that this would not be practicable but have put forward the alternative suggestion thata Squadron of the R.A.F. might be formed from Canadianpersonnel already serving,  to be  subsequently absorbed in theRoyal Canadian Air Force.      Action to this end is being taken,(5)    Legislative Action.There have been no developments of importancesince the date of the last report.(4) Economic Action.The United Kingdom Purchasing Mission underCXGreenlyan association with the Canadian War Supply Board,have continued their work and a number of munition orders havebeen placed.      Arrangements for Aircraft contracts have alsobeen made in conjunction with the separate Mission headed byLord Riverdale sent  to Canada to deal with the Air training scheme.Raw materials have remained on the whole a matter for negotiation in London, and advantage is being taken of thepresence of special Canadian representatives in connexion withthe visit of Dominion Ministers to hold discussions with theappropriate Departments.      Negotiations are also in progressregarding the purchase of certain Canadian food products.Details were given by the Minister of Food in his recent reportto the Cabinet W,P.(R).  (39) (69).

Limited purchases of wheat have been made but no largelong-term contract has yet been placed as the difficulties referredto in the previous report are still being encountered.Active discussions have been taking place in Ottawabetween Mr. Osborne and Canadian representatives as regards the financing of United Kingdom purchases of Canadian products andother prospective expenditure in Canada in connexion with the air training Scheme.Trade discussions are being continued in London very shortly with Mr, Crerar,  the Canadian Minister of Mines and resources and Mr. GCF.  Towers,  the Governor of the Bank of Canada,who, it is hoped, will be arriving in England in a few days&apos;   time.It has been necessary to impose heavy restrictions on anumber of Canadian imports in the United Kingdom.    The principalitems are apples and tobacco.      The decision to cut these to about.0$ and 40$ of normal has been conveyed to Mr. Crerar by theChancellor of the Exchequer.      Mr*  Crerar appeared fully to appreciate the exigencies of the situation and aftersubsequent discussions between officials the Canadian Governmenthave agreed to take the necessary steps to limit the export ofapples on the above basis,  and detailed arrangements to restrict the import, of Canadian tobacco to an agreed figure are with their concurrence being made by the Board of Trade.

COMMOIPPSAITH OF AUSTRALIA.(I )   GnnereJ Position.:Public opinion continues firmly to support theGovernment&apos;s war-time policy and the measures which it has takento give effect to that policy.The Department of Defence has been abolished and replaced by the following four new Departments, namely,  theDepartment of Defence Co-ordination,  the Department of the Navy,the Department of the Army,  and the Department of Air.(2) Na^al,Military and Air Activities.Naval Activities.Five destroyers and a cruiser, H.M.A.S,&quot;Hobart&quot;,  were transferred to Singapore as part of a movement for the redistribution of naval forces and to enable ships&apos;  companies tosecure anti-submarine trainingsThe Commonwealbh Government have since agreed that the destroyers of the Royal Australian Navy should be available for service in the Mediterranean,  two C or D class cruisers being sent to Australia In replacement.The Commonwealth Government have placed orders inAustralia for three  &quot;Tribal&quot; class destroyers and theconstruction of four anti-submarine mine-sweeping-vessels hasbeen approved..      The motor ships &quot;Manoora&quot; (10,800 tons),  and&quot;Duntroon&quot; (10,540 tens) are being fitted out in Australia asarmed merchant cruisers for service with the Australian navy.The

The total of defensively armed merchant ships which have beenfitted out in Australia is now 63,Military Activities.Compulsory Military Training for all males in certain age groupshas been determined upon for home defensive purposes.      It will operate from 1st January, 1940, and at the outset will include all of 20 to 22 years of age.      The period of training will be three months.      Service requirements abroad will continue to bemet by voluntary effort.Sixth Division for Overseas Service:        This division will bedrawn from the various States thus:-New South Wales ... one BrigadeVictoria ... one BrigadeQueensland ) each contributingSouth Australia       ) one battalion to : .Western Australia    )    ... form a Brigade to bTasmania ) concentrated in NewSouth Wales by theend of 1939.Training commenced at the end of October.Air Force Activities.Air Expeditionary Force: In view of the agreed desirabilityto do everything possible to ensure the best results from thescheme for the training of airmen in Canada and to enable theultimate air contribution of Australia to be more effectivestill,  the proposal for the early dispatch of an AirExpeditionary Force from Australia has been abandoned.The Australian Sunderland Flying Boats in home watershave, however, been established as No.10 Squadron R.A.A.F.consisting of 6 Flying Boats with 3 in reserve.      The squadronis engaged on anti-submarine and trade protection convoy duties.It

GOIt serves in the Coastal Command R.A.F., but as an Australianunit, and is liable to be called to   Australia should emergency-make necessary such a course.(5)_Legislative Action.There have been no developments of importance.(4)   Eg9nomic Action.During the month the discussions between theCommonwealth and United Kingdom Governments concerning the selling to the latter of surplus products of the Commonwealthhave been carried substantially further.The United Kingdom Government has purchased the wholewool clip,  subject to the satisfaction of Australia/s ownr e quire men t s.Negotiations are in progress, and in some casesagreement has been reached,  regarding the purchase of foodstuffsby the United Kingdom from Australia.      Details have recentlybeen made available to the War Cabinet by the Minister of Poodin his second report of the 8th November (W.P.  (R) (39) 69).The Commonwealth Cabinet has approved of theestablishment of an Import Licensing System to accord priority to essential Australian requirements.      Control will beexercised by the Department of Trade and Customs.      Applicationsfor priority will require the endorsement of the Department ofSupply and Development.Sea transport continues to present difficulties,partly because of the requisitioning of ships for various purposes,andPartly because of almost continual loss of time on the differentroutes, due to the need for precautionary measures.

b 1NEW gjji ALAND.(1) GENERAL POSITION,Parliament was adjourned on the 7th October until the8th February, but it may be convened earlier if the situationso warrants.A Central Council, presided over by a Minister,consisting of one Employers1   and one Labour representative ofeach of the primary production, Factory production,  andIndustrial Emergency Councils.,   together with one Senior Officer-to represent the Armed Forces, has been established to enquire into and report upon all matters affecting the utilisation of man-power.    The Council will determine questions of reserved occupations and arrange the training of substitutes for thosedesiring to serve in the Armed Forces.(2) PAVAL, lhaITaw7  \ND at  ACTIVITIES.The maximum possible liaison is being maintained with theCommonwealth of Australia and with Fiji.NAVAL. Further Reserves of Naval personnel arc being called up as found necessary.      No enemy action againstNew Zealand shipping has been reported.      Six Merchant ships have been defensively equipped,  and three vessels have been commisioned for rninesweeping duties.      One vessel is being converted to an Armed Merchant Cruiser.      Assistance continuesto be rendered to  the Fiji Defence Force.ARMY. The training of the first Echelon of the Special force for service overseas, comprising 6,600 men, is continuing satisfactorily

a selected number are at present undergoing training forCommissioned rank.      The New Zealand Government have recently announced that this echelon will be ready to proceed overseas whenshipping can be made avail-able.      Arrangements are in train forcalling up and training the second Echelon,,      Recruiting for aMaori unit to serve with the Special Force is proceeding satisfactorily,,AIR. The training of the Air Force is being vigorously pushed forward.      Additional Ground and Flying Training Schools have beenestablished,  and civil aircraft to a total of 77 mixed types havebeen requisitioned by the Air Force for training and general purposes,,      Recruiting is most satisfactory.(3) LBGISLATIVE ACTION.A Marketing Act has been passed authorising the Crown topurchase and dispose of any specified product, whether in theDominion or elsewhere.Regulations have been brought into force:-(l)    Prohibiting strikes and lockouts and providing procedure for the settlement of disputes.(2) Controlling the collection and distribution of fundscollected for purposes of war by x^atriotic and otherorgani sations.(3)    Obliging employers to reinstate in employment allemployees discharged or on leave from the Armed Forces.(4)   Extending the period of service of Naval personnel forthe duration of the war.The Aliens Regulations have been amended to require enemy aliens to obtain a permit before absenting themselves from a registered place of abode for any continuous period exceeding24 hours.(4) ECONOMIC ACTION.Negotiations with the Government of the United kingdom for the sale and disposal of primary products are continuing,and,inthe case of Meat, prices are agreed.    Early finality is e:xpected forthe other products.    . Various controls to increase and regulatedominion production are functioning satisfactorily.UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA

n 9UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.(1)    General Position.General Hertsog seems now to have  thrown inhis let with Dr. Maian and the Nationalists, with theresult that a new political party,  an &quot;Afrikaner &quot;bloc&quot;,  isin process of formation.      General Smuts, on the otherhand,  has consolidated his position toy securing,  at ameeting held cn the 3rd November,  the endorsement of his policy by the Central lie ads of the United Party by 28votes to 18.In a speech on the following day General Smutsgave a restrained account of recent events, declared thaturgent problems of administration lay ahead,  stressed theimportance of the British connection, attacked Mr. Pirowby name,  and ended by saying &quot;When Britain is in vitaldanger, this country cannot remain neutral&quot;.General Hertzog countered with a bitter speech which showed increasingly anti-British feeling.      He ended withthe words &quot;The British Jingo can take it from me that either South Africa shall be governed as an indei^endentfree country,  or her participation in the BritishCommonwealth of Nations will not continue much longer&quot;.Earlier he said, however,  &quot;I do not wish for the timebeing to reckon myself among the persons......wishing to break the  ties of the Commonwealth&quot;.      The latterstatement has aroused considerable misgivings on thepart of the Republican wing of the Nationalist Party whofear that the Nationalist leader, Dr. Maian, may besurrendering

surrendering&apos; his republican principles in thenegotiations with the &quot;Hertzog group&quot; in which he is att he moment e ng ag e d.(2)    IJayjal^ Mill try,  and Air activities .Mine-sweepers are now operating.      arrangements have been made by the Union Government for the deepeningof the approach channel to the Durban graving dock tomeet Admiralty requirements;    the work on this projectis to be speeded up as much as possible.600 officers and other- ranks of the CitizenForce  attended qualifying and specialist courses atmilitary college branches during October and courses forNon-Gommissioned Officers of the Citizen Force  are being held at all command training depots.      The total strengthof the forces was increased by 200 officers and 3s000other ranks during October1.      A new command and one infantry battalion have been established in South WestAfrica.      Other new units which have been establishedinclude a heavy artillery brigade,  a corps of mechanics,a first special service reserve battalion and a battalion of the Pretoria Highlanders.      All artillery regimentsare in future to be trained at one  centre, where theultimate strength will be about 12,000 men.      Allcommands have been instructed to submit recommendations for the establishment of additional infantry battalions.Steps have been taken to undertake theab initio training of 1,000 volunteer pupil pilots todate at the rate of 160 every two months;    arrangements have been made to open a central flying school and theorganisation

organisation, of two advanced flying training schools isin hand.      The aim is to create a reserve which may ultimately reach a total of 1,500 trained pilots.      Thereare 2,100 volunteers for service as air gunners.      Thepresent strength of the Air Force is 250 officers, 1,700other ranks and 1+50 pupil pilots and cadets.      An AirForce radio signalling company has been established.The erection of fourteen new hangars is in hand.(3)    Legislative action.The Cape of Good Hope and Natal provincialdivisions of the Supreme Court of South Africa have beenappointed to act as Prize Courts.(U)    Economic Action.The organisation of the engineering industry is proceeding with a view to increasing the production ofmunitions, especially mortar and aircraft bombs and armoured cars.      T.N.T. plant has been delivered and a factory is now being erected.      Three-inch mortarpractice bombs and fuses are being delivered in quantity.The small arms ammunition factory is working additionalshifts and is now producing at the rate of thirty millionrounds per annum.      One million rounds have been delivered to Southern Rhodesia and a request for anadditional four million rounds in the next 3 months hasbeen approved.Negotiations are still in progress as regardsthe price at which the United Kingdom Governmentsagreement in principle to support the Union woolmarket is to come into operation but it is hoped thatthis

U 0)this matter will he settled in the near future.The Natal sugar crop has teen sold to theUnited Kingdom and negotiations are in progress in regardto several other foodstuffs.      Details of these will befound in the recent report by the Minister of Food   W.P.(K)(39)69.

The only major development has &quot;been thediscussion with the hire Government as to the possible use of Berehaven by the Royal Navy, with which the WarCabinet is familiar.The Royal Navy officer appointed, as NavalAttache1 on the staff of the United Kingdom representative in Dublin has taken Up duty.In view of the possibility of leakage ofinformation from this country to the enemy throughEire,  certain measures for preventing such leakage havebeen discussed informally with the Eire authorities, whoare prepared to assist to the best of their ability.

GSHE WFOU NDL AND.(1)    General Position.In order to take a share in the heavy warburdens assumed by the United Kingdom and all parts oP theEmpire,  the Commission of Government have offered to limit their request for grant-in-aid to the amount of their total sterling expenditure and to meet the deficit by increases in taxation and reduction of expenditure in newfoundland.      The offer has been gratefully accepted,but even so it is expected that a grant of  950,000 willbe required next year.( 2)    Naval, Military and Air Activities.The Royal Navy have agreed to take 625 men forpatrol duty in the North Sea.      The first batch of recruits is expected to sail early in December.Thereafter the Royal Navy are ready to take 1,000 men, inthe first place, for general service.The Army have agreed to take 1*375 recruits from newfoundland forthwith and more later.      They propose to enlist them in the Royal Artillery with a view todrafting them after training to one or more heavy mobilefield units which will eventually be wholly or mainlymanned by Newfoundlanders.      Details regarding rates of pay and allowances, etc.,  and the question of transport are still under consideration and it is understood thatrecruitment has not yet actually commenced in newfoundland.With regard to the Royal Air Force,-,, Lord Riverdale

Lord Riverdale was asked to explore the possibility of including Newfoundland in the Empire Air Training scheme on the &quot;basis that personnel selected for training would join the Royal Air Force with a view to the eventualformation of one or- more Newfoundland Squadrons.      TheCanadian Government have expressed their agreement.(5)    hopielative Action.Nothing to report.(h)    Economic  Action.Orders for three million pounds of frozen fishto be produced before the end of January have beenplaced, and it is expected that further orders to theextent of the refrigerating capacity of the local firmswill follow.      The special interests of the producers ofsalt fish of various kinds in Newfoundland are being kept in view in connection with the agreements contemplatedwith Iceland and Spain.With regard to iron ore, of which about 500,000tons were available up to the end of the year, shipping for lOOjOOO tons has been arranged for October and november and 52,h00 tons for December.With regard to timbers  a contract for 50?000fathoms of pitprops for delivery next summer has beenarranged, but the terms have not yet been finally settled by the Timber Controller.      The Government of new foundland have been asked if they can send over about,000 loggers forthwith for service under the TimberController in cutting pitprops in the United Kingdom forthe use of the coal mines to meet the shortage expectedbefore

before the suppplies ofpitprops from Canada andNe wfoundlandand become  available next summer.regard to rnewsprint, it is understood thatthe two local factories ore working to capacity, viz.,about 3 50,000 tons per year.      The Bowater Lloyd company are however experiencing difficulty in obtaining shipping for the purpose of taking raw pulp wood logs from newfoundland to their Kerns ley Mill for manufacture.      Asa considerable balance of pulp wood cut last winter forexport has not been shipped yet, it is understood thatthe Company will restrict their logging operations in newfoundland to that extent this winter.

SOUTHERN RHODESIA.(1)    Peneral position.Nothing to report.(2)    Mijlit.ary^and air activities .The personnel, comprising some 1+50 of all ranks, which were reported in W.P.(R)(39)50 as havingleft to join the Royal West African Frontier Force and the somali land Camel Corps have arrived in West Africa andSomaliland and have teen attached to their units.      Thedetachment,  50 strong, which,  as reported in W&quot;.P. (G)(39)5was sent to Nyasaland at the beginning of September, hasreturned to Southern Rhodesia.      Southern Rhodesia hasrelieved units of the Northern Rhodesia Regiment by taking over the protection of the Victoria Falls andKafue b ri dge s.There  are also at present 735 men in militarytraining in the Colony;    a further call-up of volunteersis now in progress,  end this will practically complete the establishments of the two training camps, which total1,100.      It is estimated that the first output of trained personnel will be ready for service at the end of January,191+0.      The Southern Rhodesia Government have offeredthese men for service on any front,  and have enquired howit is proposed that they should be employed.      This is atpresent under consideration.Discussions have taken place with the GeneralOfficer Commanding East Africa regarding the provision inLi7i East Africa

East Africa of personnel and. equipment from SouthernRhodesia.    Arrangements have teen made for the delivery of 670 motor lorries, 8 ambulances and certain other items of equipment0    a sufficient supply of motor vehicles has been obtained to enable a battalion of the rhodesia Regiment, a base - hospital and a base camp tomove by road to East Africa if this move should become necessary.The Officer Commanding, Southern Rhodesia AirForce,  is at present in this country and has been discussing the detailed arrangements arising out of theoffer of the Southern Rhodesia Government to bring up to full squadron strength the air Unit already in Kenya andto provide two further air squadrons in the field on anyfront.    Reinforcements for the air unit numbering 103of all ranks, left Salisbury for Kenya on the 17thNovember.    As a first step, it is proposed to giveadvanced training for the personnel for these squadrons in Iraq, and the first batch of pilots will report inIraq at the beginning of December,    A proposal is atpresent under discussion to establish two Royal Air Forceflying training schools in Southern Rhodesia, one forelementary and one for advanced training.The number of applications received since the recruiting campaign for the Southern Rhodesia Air Forcebegan on the 15th September is (up to the 14th October)961;    of the 354 so far medically examined, 47 have been rejected as unfit or temporarily unfit.

w 9(3)   Legislative action.A &quot;profiteering order&quot; and orders on the linesof the United Kingdom Trading with the Enemy(Specified Persons) Order, 1939, have been issued.(^-)    Eco nomic act ion.Discussions are taking place between theSouthern Rhodesia authorities and the Ministry of Poodregarding the purchase by the United Kingdom Governmentof meat supplies from Southern Rhodesia.Southern Rhodesia has taken steps to bring theexport licensing system of the Colony into line with therequirements of the contraband control system and isconsulting the United Kingdom authorities beforegranting licenses for the export of goods on the contraband list.      Provision has been made for theintroduction of petrol rationing if such action is deemed by the Fuel Controller to be advisable at a later date.


</content>
</cab>
