<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/10/7 images: 110-119</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS document IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.  November 1940.SECRET. Copy No.    43W.M. (40)287th Conclusions.mTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 287 (40).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held in the Cabinet war room, S.W. 1, on Tuesday, November 12, 1940, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill. M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Halifax,Secretary   of   State   for   ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Lord Beaverbrook,Minister of Aircraft Production.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.Minister of Labour and Minister ofNational Service.The Right Hon Sir John Anderson,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. A. Greenwood, M.P.,Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State for India and secretary of State for Burma(Item 5).The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The   Right   Hon.   Sir   archibald sinclair, Bt., M.P.,  Secretary  ofState for Air.The Hon.  Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.General Sir John Dill, Chief of theImperial General Staff.The Right Hon. Viscount Cranborne,M.P., Secretary of State forDominion Affairs.Lloyd, Secre-the   colonies the Right Hon. Lordtary of State for(Item 5).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. A. Duff Cooper, M.P.,Minister of Information.Admiral  of   the  Fleet  Sir  dudley pound, First Sea Lord and Chief ofNaval Staff.Air Chief Marshal Sir Charles F. A,Portal, Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Major-General Sir Hastings Ismay.Mr. W. D. Wilkinson.Mr. L. F. Burgis.
WAR CABINET 287 (40).contents minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ....      ........      51Air Operations Greece.Naval Operations Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.Shipping losses.Escort for convoy.Military Operations Italy-Greece.2      Baltic States   ............................      51Requisitioning of shipping.3      France   ................................      52Relations with the Vichy Government.The French Fleet.4      France   ................................      52Movements of General de Gaulle.5      Middle East     ............................      53Visit of the Secretary of State for War.6.     Parliament: Prorogation and opening of new session   ....      53King&apos;s Speeches.!
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 286thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Greece.naval operations.Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.Shipping Losses.Escort for convoy.MilitaryOperations.Italy-Greece.1. The Chief of the Air Staff reported that five Italian airmenhad been taken prisoner on the previous day. One Fiat bomber had landed with its engine still running, and the pilot had given as hisreason for landing that he thought his machine might have been hit in the petrol tank. A preliminary examination of these prisonersshowed that their morale was low. The fighter escort had turnedtail as soon as it had been intercepted.Enemy activity on the previous night had been on a small scale,only 50 machines having been employed, of which seven had been over London.  Therehad been no casualties.On the 11th November three Blenheims had attacked the harbour at Sarande on the Albanian coast and jetties at KonispolBay on the Greek-Albanian frontier. At Sarande one bomb had fallen near a 7,000-ton merchant ship.The Chief of Naval Staff said that according to the latest reports only 10, and possibly nine, ships were now missing from the halifax convoy which had been attacked by Admiral Scheer on the5th November.No reports had yet been received from the Commander-in-Chief,Mediterranean, regarding the attack on Taranto. An Italianofficial communique had stated, however, that one of their warshipshad been extensively damaged.The gun-boat Aphis, in co-operation with a flare-dropping air-craft, had successfully bombarded enemy positions at Sidi Barraniduring the night of the 9th-10th.A report had been received on the previous day of the presenceof an enemy raider south of Ceylon. A search was being made forthis vessel.There had been no shipping losses due to submarines on theprevious day. The Ravnanger (Norwegian, 3,371 tons) had been bombed and sunk off the Tees.Three other ships in ballast had been damaged by air attack.,and a fourth set on fire and beached.The question of escort for a certain convoy was discussed. Thedecision is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that there was nothing to report from the Sudan or Egypt.A report had been received that 11 Italian officers and 600 men had been captured by a cavalry regiment in the Koritza area.The Greeks were advancing again towards the Kalamas river.Reports had been received to the effect that the Italian troopsembarking for Albania were unenthusiastic and that the civilian population of Italy were terror-stricken by the bombing of Britishplanes.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Baltic States.requisitioning of Shipping.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 276thConclusions,Minute 7.)2. The Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs reminded theWar Cabinet that the ships belonging to the Baltic States had been formally requisitioned about 2 to 3 weeks ago. M. Maisky had made a protest, and as a result further action in regard to the ships had been suspended. Sir Stafford Cripps had been asked to enquire whether it was in order for us to use the ships, the question of thepayment being settled later. The Soviet answer had been obscure.Later, on the 3rd November, M. Vyshinski had objected to the requisitioning of these ships, and Sir Stafford had told him definitely that the ships had been requisitioned, and that this action couldnot be reversed.
WAR CABINET 287 (40).contents minute no. Subject. page 1      Naval, Military and Air Operations....      ....      ....      ....      51Air Operations Greece.Naval Operations Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.Shipping losses.Escort for convoy.Military Operations Italy-Greece.2      Baltic States   ............................      51Requisitioning of shipping.3      France   ....      ............................      52Relations with the Vichy Government.The French Fleet.4      France   ................................      52Movements of General de Gaulle.5      Middle East     ............................      53Visit of the Secretary of State for War.6.     Parliament: Prorogation and opening of new session   .... .    53King&apos;s Speeches.
Naval, Militaryand air operations.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 286thConclusions,Minute 1.)Air Operations.Greece.naval operations.Mediterranean.Indian Ocean.Shipping Losses.Escort for convoy.MilitaryOperations.Italy-Greece.1. The Chief of the Air Staff reported that five Italian airmenhad been taken prisoner on the previous day. One Fiat bomber had landed with its engine still running, and the pilot had given as hisreason for landing that he thought his machine might have been hit in the petrol tank. A preliminary examination of these prisonersshowed that their morale was low. The fighter escort had turnedtail as soon as it had been intercepted.Enemy activity on the previous night had been on a small scale,only 50 machines having been employed, of which seven had been over London.   There had been no casualties.On the 11th November three Blenheims had attacked the harbour at Sarande on the Albanian coast and jetties at KonispolBay on the Greek-Albanian frontier. At Sarande one bomb had fallen near a 7,000-ton merchant ship.The Chief of Naval Staff said that according to the latest reports only 10, and possibly nine, ships were now missing from the halifax convoy which had been attacked by Admiral Scheer on the5th November.No reports had yet been received from the Commander-in-Chief,Mediterranean, regarding the attack on Taranto. An Italianofficial communique had stated, however, that one of their warshipshad been extensively damaged.The gun-boat Aphis, in co-operation with a flare-dropping air-craft, had successfully bombarded enemy positions at Sidi Barraniduring the night of the 9th-10th.A report had been received on the previous day of the presenceof an enemy raider south of Ceylon. A search was being made forthis vessel.There had been no shipping losses due to submarines on theprevious day. The Ravnanger (Norwegian, 3,371 tons) had been bombed and sunk off the Tees.Three other ships in ballast had been damaged by air attack,and a fourth set on fire and beached.The question of escort for a certain convoy was discussed. Thedecision is recorded in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of War cabinet conclusions.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff- said that there was nothing to report from the Sudan or Egypt.A report had been received that 11 Italian officers and 600 men had been captured by a cavalry regiment in the Koritza area.The Greeks were advancing again towards the Kalamas river.Reports had been received to the effect that the Italian troopsembarking for Albania were unenthusiastic and that the civilian population of Italy were terror-stricken by the bombing of Britishplanes.The War Cabinet took note of these statements.Baltic States.requisitioning of Shipping.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 276thConclusions,Minute 7.)2. The Secretary of Stale for Foreign Affairs ,reminded theWar Cabinet that the ships belonging to the Baltic States had been formally requisitioned about 2 to 3 weeks ago. M. Maisky had made a protest, and as a result further action in regard to the shipsha,d been suspended. Sir Stafford Cripps had been asked to enquire whether it was in order for us to use the ships, the question of thepayment being settled later. The Soviet answer had been obscure.Later, on the 3rd November, M. Vyshinski had objected to the requisitioning of these ships, and Sir Stafford had told him definitely that the ships had been requisitioned, and that this action couldnot be reversed.
The Minister of Shipping was most anxious to use these ships.The Foreign Secretary suggested that he should instruct Sir Staffordto inform the Soviet Government that the ships had been formally&quot;A&quot; requisitioned and would be put into use, and that we would paythe usual charter rates into a blocked account, from which theowners could be recompensed when the question of ownership had been settled.It was generally agreed that Soviet policy was unlikely to be influenced by any action taken by us in regard to such a minormatter as the requisitioning of these ships.The Minister of Labour and National Service raised thequestion of the action to be taken in regard to the seamen in these ships, more than half of whom were Communists. There was a lotto be said for sending them all back. If, however, some of them were willing to serve in the Mercantile Marine, they should notbe left in the Baltic ships but should be distributed over other ships.He suggested that before anything was decided the Ministry ofShipping should consult the National Seamen&apos;s Union.The War Cabinet (a) Invited the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to tele-graph to Sir Stafford Cripps as at &quot; A &quot; above.(&amp;) Invited the Ministry of Shipping to consult the NationalSeamen&apos;s Union before reaching a decision as to thedisposal of the crews now on board the requisitionedships.France.Relations withthe vichy government:the french fleet.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 286thConclusions,Minutes 4and 6.)3. The Secretary of State for Foreign A ffairs said that he had had an interview with M. Dupuis, the Canadian Charge d&apos;Affaires,who was proceeding to Vichy on the following day. M. Dupuis had stated that he knew Admiral Darlan well and hoped to have a talk with him. In regard to the French Fleet he (M. Dupuis) proposedto tell the Admiral that his word of honour that it should not be handed over to the Germans was not doubted, only his physicalability to carry out the pledge. M. Dupuis had then asked what his reply should be if Admiral Darlan asked him where we should like the French Fleet to be.The War Cabinet took the view that there was no reason why we should give an answer to this question until it was put to us by the French; more especially since the Vichy Government hadnot responded to the various proposals which we had made to them.For the time being M. Dupuis should cultivate good relations withthe Vichy Government, and should report at once any promisingopenings.The War Cabinet invited the Foreign Secretary to speakin this sense to M. Dupuis.France.Movements ofGeneral de gaulle.(previous reference:&quot;W.M. (40) 286thConclusions,Minute 5.)4.   The War Cabinet-Invited the Secretary of State for Air to make the-necessary arrangements for bringing General de Gaulle to thiscountry as soon as possible.   The aim should be to bringhim back within, say, 8 to 10 days.
Middle East.Visit of theSecretary ofState for War.(previous reference:W.M. (40) 286thConclusions,Minute 9.)Parliament.Prorogation,and opening ofnew Session.King&apos;speeches.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 92ndConclusions,Minute 14.)5. The Secretary of State for War gave the War Cabinet an account of his visit to the Middle East.A record of the discussion is contained in the Secretary&apos;standard File of War Cabinet Conclusions.6. The Prime Minister informed the War Cabinet that thefollowing programme had been arranged : Tuesday, 19th November. Meeting of Parliament at theAnnexe.Wednesday, 20th November. Meeting of Parliament inthe Palace of Westminster, and prorogation.Thursday, 21st November.- Meeting of Parliament at theAnnexe. Opening of the new Session by His Majesty The King,the usual ceremony being curtailed.These arrangements had been approved by The King.Two King&apos;s Speeches would be necessary, on the prorogation and on the Opening of the new Session. The Prime minister thought that, on the analogy of what had been done last year, twoshort Speeches would suffice.The War Cabinet-Invited a Committee, comprising The Lord Privy Seal (in the Chair),The Lord President of the Council,The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,The Secretary of State for Air,to prepare drafts of the King&apos;s Speeches for submission tothe Prime Minister.Richmond Terrace, S. W. 1,November 12, 1940.




</content>
</cab>
