<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/63/0 images: 261-284</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
AGENDA.(1)    FOREIGN ; AFFAIRS.  (If required),.(2)    THE NEW TREATY WITH IRAQ,.(Reference Cabinet 12(30) Conclusion 3*)Memoranda by the Secretary of State for the Colonies *(CP.    45(30)    -    already circulated).(CP, 101(30)    -    already circulated),(3)    THE BAGHDAD HAIFA RAILWAY AND PIPELINE^(Reference Cabinet 55(21?) 6,)(4)    AGRICULTURAL POLICY.(Reference Cabinet 16(30) Conclusion 9.)Report of Cabinet Committee.(CP, 104(30)    -   to be circulated),(5)    UNEMPLOYMENT BISURMOE.(Question to be raised by the Prime Minister)*(6 )    THE ECONOMJC CONSEQUENCES OF DISARMAMENT ,(Reference Cabinet 12(30) Conclusion&apos; 4)departmental Report on Memorandum by TradeUnion Congress General Council.(CP. 55 (30)    -   already circulated) *(7)    THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE ANNUAL BILL.Memorandum by&quot; the Secretary of State for Warcovering draft Bill.(CP. 102(30)   -     already circulatedS SiJji&apos; COPY HO.   /OABPIBT 17(30).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at No.10,Downing Street, S.W.1. on Wednesday, March 26th,1930, at 10.30 a.m.
(8)    SALE OF APSIS AMD MUNITIONS TO FOREIGN 607MMM&amp;,(Question to be raised by the Secretary ofState for War,)(9)    THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES (MABLING) BILL.Memorandum by the Minister of Health.(CP. 103(30)    -    already circulated).(10)    THE COAL WEg BILIt     (If required).(11)    RECOMErEHDATIONS OF THE COMMITTEE OF HOME AFFAIRS .(Reference H*A.C. 5th Conclusions (30)).The Overseas Trade Bill.Note by the President of - the Board of Tradecovering&apos; draft Bill.(He/A. 9(30) already circulated).The, Housing Bill.Memorandum by the Minister of Healtbcovering draft Bill.(H.A. 10(30)    -    already circulated).The Agricultural Marketing Bill. .Report of Cabinet Committee covering draftBill.(CP- 79(30)    -    already circulated).(Signed)   K.P.A. HANKEY.Secretary, Cabinet.&apos;2, Whitehall Gardens, S.C124th March, 1930.
COPY NO,CABINET 17 (SO).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10,Downing Street, S.W.1, on Wednesday, March 6th, 1930at 10.30 a,m.PRESENT :The Right Hon. J. Ramsay MacDonald, M.P.,Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer,The Right Hon.J.H, Thomas, M.P.,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of Frieth, K.C.V.O.,K.C., Lord President of theCouncil.The Right. Hon.J.R. Clynes, M.P.,Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C.B.E.,M.?.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Arthur Greenwood, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon.William Graham, M*P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Kon.William Adamson, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M.P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield, Secretary ofState for Dominion affairs and Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W, Wedgwood Benn, D.S.O.,D.F.C.,M.P., Secretary ofState for India.Brig.-Gen. the Right Hon.Lord Thomson, C.B.E.,D.S&apos;.0.,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield, M.P.,Minister of Labour.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan,Bt.,M.P., President of the Boardof Education.The Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M.P.,First Commissioner of Y/orlcs.Colonel Sir M,P.A. Hanlcey, C-.C.B. ,G.C.M.&amp;.  (Secretary).DOCUMgNT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT).
RUSSIA.Anglo-RussIanCommercialRelations .Export CreditsCommittee.(previous reference:Cabinet 16(50), Con-Clusion 3.)1.    The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs reported that he had had a satisfactory interview with the Russian Ambassador and was getting togrips with the different points of the negotia-tions.   The Ambassador had made an encouragingstatement to the effect that orders to the valueof from  15,000,000 to  30,000,000 could bearranged expeditiously if a modus vivendi couldbe reached on satisfactory terms.   He read adraft Protocol (Appendix) in regard to the granting of export credits, for which he ashedthe approval of the Cabinet, since it involvedsome extension of previous Cabinet decisions(e.g., Cabinet 13 (30), Conclusion 3).&quot;The Cabinet approved the proposal of theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs and agreed to his suggestion that a Committee composed as follows  The Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,The Chancellor Of the Exchequer,The Lord Privy Seal,The President of the Board of Trade  should be set up to consider the attitude to be adoptedin regard to the question of Export Credits for Russia&quot;.Commit too v-
2. The Cabinet had before them, a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for the Colonies (paper cp.-101 (SO)) reporting to the Cabinet a modifi-cation that had been made in the instructions tothe High Commissioner for Iraq (Paper CP.-45(30)) as approved by the Cabinet.   This modifica-tion had been made at the request of the ForeignOffice in order to avoid embarrassing them inthe conversations which are about to be held withthe Egyptian Government on the subject of thedraft Anglo-Egyptian Treaty .The Cabinet were assured that the Iraq treaty was being considered on lines similar, Mutatis Mutandis. to the Egyptian Treaty.The Cabinet noted and acceptedthe alteration in the instruc-tions to the High Commissionerfor Iraq reported by theSecretary of State for the olonies.
IRAQ,.Baghdad-haifa railway and pipeline.(previous reference:Cabinet 35(29),  Con-elusion 6.)3.   The First Lord of the Admiralty notified to the Cabinet certain fresh evidence of a highlyconfidential character that the French are makingevery endeavour to secure that the pipeline to be built by the Iraq Petroleum Company shall follow the route emerging on the coast at Beirut, andthat they are likely to construct a railway onthis route with the object of attracting the pipeline.The Cabinet agreed  -(a) That a Cabinet Committee,  composed as follows  The Secretary of State forForeign Affairs,The Secretary of State forthe Colonies,The Secretary of State for War,The Secretary of State for Air  should consider the whole situationvery carefully and submit a Reportto the Cabinet at the earliestpossible moment:(b) That the Committee should set up an inter-Departmental Committee of officials,  on which the Treasuryamong other Departments should berepresented, to assist in theirinv es tig at ion.
agricultural policy.(previous reference:Cabinet 16(.30), Con-- elusion 9;.)4 .The Cabinet bad before them the following documents relating to Agricultural Policy:.-A Letter to the Prime Minister fromthe Chairman of the Committee onAgrieultural Policy (Paper C .P .-99(30)) which had been adjourned atthe previous Meeting and which contained the following recommend-ation:-That the organised marketing ofhome-grown produce by a co-operative method would be tothe advantage of arable farmers,as well as to the general advantageof the agricultural industry inGreat Britain.The Committee accordingly recommendedthat the Government should adopt theAgrieultural Marketing Bill:A Second and Final Report of theCommittee on Agricultural Policy(Paper C.P.-104 (30)) to the follow-ing effect:-(i) That by a substantial, majoritythey are in favour of somesteps being taken by theGovernment to secure to wheat-growers a price that will enablethem to grow wheat without loss:(ii) That, after prolonged considera-tion of the various schemes pro-posed to effect this object, they find themselves so divided inopinion that they are unable torecommend for the CabinetTsapproval any one of the schemesthat have been considered, viz.:-A State monopoly comprising the grain trade and flour-milling industry:An Import Board for wheat and flour:A Statutory quota of home-grown wheat in home milledflour, associated with aprovision for the blendingof a similar proportion ofall-English flour withimported flour.
In the course of the discussion some commentwas made on the fact that the Committee had adoptthe method of voting, and it was suggested thatit would be preferable that a Committee of thiskind, which included public servants, should actonly in a consultative capacity.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheriessuggested that a Cabinet Committee might be setup to assist him in drawing up a scheme for a quota of home-grown wheat in home-milled flour.After a long discussion the Cabinet agreed. -(a) That the President of the Board ofTrade should circulate.,  if possible before the next Meeting of theCabinet,, the draft of a very short bill, drawn with a view to provid-ing compulsory powers to the consumers&apos; Council.    The Billshould be drawn up on the under-standing that not more than aday would be available for SecondReading:(b) That the Prime Minister should discuss with the parliamentary secretary to the Treasury themeans by which time could be found for the consideration of such a Billin Committee, and should examine inparticular whether it would bepossible to set up Committee D.. withthis object:(c) That the Minister of Agricultureand Fisheries should place himself in touch with the Chancellor o^ theExchequer with a view to the produc-tion of a scheme for a Statutoryquota of home-grown wheat, whichshould not involve any appreciablecharge on public funds.
UNEMPLOYMENTIftoURANCE./previous reference erence:Cabinet  16t:W). Oon-conclusion ion 6 . )5. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandumby the.Minister of Labour on the subject ofUnemployment (C.P.105(30)   ) , prepared with a viewto the Parliamentary Debate on Friday next.In this Memorandum the figures for the increasein unemployment were analysed, and it was shownthat the exhaustion of the Unemployment Fund isdue to an abnormal and unforeseeable increasein unemployment, which is world-wide in character.Attention was drawn to the importance of settling upon a definite policy before the autumnin regard to the treatment of able-bodiedunemployed who do not possess the minimuminsurance qualification.In the course of the discussion much evidence was adduced as to both the world-wide character ofunemployment and the inaccurate picture which is presented by the figmres of unemployment in theform in which they are at p??esent published.    Itwas clear that the present register does not givea true reflex of the amount of unemployment.Attention was drawn to some of the known and opendepartures from the original intentions  of Unemploy-ment Insurance, and the hope was expressed that theCabinet Committee would,  in due course, be able torecommend means for correcting this.Some discussion took place as to whether it wouldbe in the public interest to invite the House ofCommons...to set up a Committee o^ all Parties to look into the meaning of the figures as at presentpublished .The Cabinet felt that &apos;or political reasons this plan would not be prudent at the present time, but
invited the Minister of Labour, in the debate on Friday, March 28th, to do her best to explain the true situation in regard to the UnemploymentRegister.
REDUCTION and limitation of armaments .The EconomicConsequencesof Disarmament(previous reference:Cabinet 12(30),  Oon-conclusion 4.)6, The Cabinet had before them a letter addressedto the Prime Minister by the Joint disarmament committee of the Trades Union Congress general council expressing dissatisfaction at the Reportof the Inter-Departmental Committee on the economic consequences of Disarmament (Paper CP.-55 (30)),the general tenor of which had been communicatedto them by the First Lord of the Admiralty.   Thevery strong opinion of the Disarmament Committeewas emphasised that trade facilities, under suitablesafeguards, are essential to the shipbuilding and engineering industries, and it was urged that, theAdvisory Committee on Export Credit Facilitiesneeds reconstruction and that provision should bemade for the representation thereon of industrial interests.    The letter further contained a request that if the P3?ime Minister, whose present preoccupa-tions were recognised,  could not receive them himselfhe would arrange that the Joint Disarmament committee might meet the Ministers concerned in this question.The Cabinet agreed  ThatThe Secretary of State for War,The First Lord of the Admiralty,The President of the Eoard of Trade -should form a Committee to meet theJoint Disarmament Committee of theTrades Union Congress General Council,in order to hear what they have to sayand to give them explanations as to&apos;the policy of the Government in thismatt er.
U ABMY ANDIjg FORCEpjUAL BILL.IpreviousI Reference:I Cabinet 8(30), Con-[elusion 19.)7. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for War (Paper CP.-102 (30))covering the Army and Air Force Annual Bill-    Inhis Memorandum the Secretary of State for War drew attention to his decision, which he had already communicate to the Cabinet, to introduce in theBill amendments which will abolish the death penalty for cowardice and certain specified offences alliedto it, viz-:-(i) Without orders from, his superiorofficer, leaves his guard, picket,patrol or post: or(ii) By discharging firearms,  drawingswords ,1 beating drums, makingsignals, using words,  or by any means whatever, intentionallyoccasions false alarms in action,on the march, in the field, or elsewhere?    or(iii) Being a soldier acting as sentinel,leaves his post before he is regularlyrelieved.While it was stated that the Secretary of State forAir concurred in these proposals and that the Boardof Admiralty are considering the introduction ofparallel provisions in the Naval Discipline A.ct,the Secretary of State for War warned the Cabinetthat he was acting against the expressed view- ofhis military advisers, and that he proposed to make this clear to the House of Commons.The Secretary of State for Air informed theCabinet that he also had received representations from his Air advisers to the same effect as theSecretary of State for War.The Secretary of State for War warned hiscolleagues that he expected opposition in Parlia-ment from those who desired still further to limit the application of the death penalty.
The Secretary of State for Dominion affairs said he had received objections from the IrishFree State to the use of the term &quot;Great Britainand Ireland&quot;.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve the Bill as submittedby the Secretary of State for Warwith. 0 .P.-102 (30) t(b) That the Secretary of State forDominion Affairs should confer with the Secretary of State forWar and the Secretary of Statefor Air with a view to a modi fie a-tion of the Bill to avoid theobjections of the Irish Free StateGovernment.
SALE OP ARMS ANDAMMUNITION .(previous references:Cabinet 13(30), Con-elus ion 9:Cabinet 10(30), Con-elusion 11:Cabinet 53(29), Con-conclusion 5.)8. The Secretary of State for War brought tothe notice of the Cabinet an application receivedby the War Office from the Portuguese delegation in London asking for the supply of a Livens Pro-jector, 6 drums for gas and smoke, and 12 capsulesof lachrymatory gas for use for instructionalpurposes in the Military School of Ergineers inLisbon,    The Secretary of State wished for adecision as to -whether this was prohibited by theCabinet decisions referred to in the margin.The Cabinet authorised the Secretaryof State for War to use his discretion to approve the application from thePortuguese Government,
THE LOCALAUTHORITIES(ENABLING)BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 8(30), Con-clusion IS.)9 . The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Minister of Health (Paper CP .-103 (30))  inregard to the Local Authorities (Enabling) Bill,which had received a Second Reading and was likelyshortly to come before the Standing Committee.Although the Bill had no chance of becoming law,the Minister had to be ready with amendments forthe Committee stage.    It was pointed out in theMemorandum that if it were proposed to pass theBill with its present wide scope, weeks of work would be required to bring it into proper form;and that, quite apart from: other considerations,there was no time for this work on a Bill with no prospect of becoming law.   He proposed, therefore,that the powers of the Bill should be applied tothe principal enterprises for which Local Authori-ties have sought power in recent years by LocalBills, such as the sale of milk and coal, and powerto manufacture and sell bricks, to develop surplusland by the erection of shops,  etc., and to provideentertainments&apos;,    to which he would add- the making and the sale of bread.    Some other small mattersfound in Local A^ets might be added, and it was pro-posed to provide that the Minister should have power by Order (the Order to be subject to confirmation&apos;by Parliament if opposed) to grant to a LocalAuthority any power which has been granted by Parlia-;ment in Local Acts, subject to any conditions whichmay have been imposed when the power was given.With regard to the acquisition and the use of land,the Minister proposed that a provision, now freelygiven to the larger towns by Local Act, should befollowed, under which the Local Authorities are
given wide powers to acquire land where this isdesirable for the development of their district.If powers to establish Municipal Savings Bankswere to be included in the Bill, the minister suggested they should be restricted to county boroughs with a population of not less than, say,200,000.   He also thought it prudent that a limit of 50,000 population (&quot;instead of 20,000, as inthe Bill) be provided for the general powers,except that places of less population might begranted the powers by Order, subject to theconfirmation of Parliament if the Order was opposed.   As regards borrowing powers the minister proposed that a limit of one-twentieth of therateable value should be inserted.The Cabinet agreed  (a) To approve generally the proposalsof the Minister of Health:(b) That as regards the provisionsof the Bill for the acquisitionof land by Local Authorities,the Minister of Health should refuse to commit himself at thepresent stage, on the ground thatthe whole subject was under con-si deration and that so large aquestion of principle ought notto be dealt with on a Bill ofthis kind.
THE GOALMINES BILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 16(SO), Con-clusxon 8.)10. The President of the Board of trade reported that the Liberal Leaders had asked tosee hire the same afternoon.The Cabinet agreed -That if the President of theBoard of Trade wanted adviceas the result of this interview,he should confer with the CabinetCommitt ee.-14-
OVERSEAS. TRADE/ 11 .The Cabinet bad before them the. draftBILL,  1930-     / , ,      ./ Overseas Trade Bill, 1930, (Paper No. H.A.-9 (jJO)),(Previous together with the Conclusions of the Committee ofReference:-Cabinet  36 Home Affairs thereon.     The Committee of Home(30), Con-clusion 2 Affairs had reserved for determination by the..and Appendix. )Cabinet the question of the retention of thefollowing Clause 1  (2) which had been agreed toky.the Treasury and the Department of OverseasTrade, in the following forrni-i(The provisions of the said Acts shall beextended so as to authorise the giving of guarantees in connection with theexport of goods whether-wholly or partly produced or manufactured in theUnited Kingdom or not, but excluding goodsmanufactured or mainly manufactured outsidethe United Kingdom, if they are of a class which compete with any class ofgoods manufactured in the United Kingdom.&quot;After this- agreement had been reached thePresident of the Board of Trade had proposed. the omission of &quot;Che last sentence beginning with the words &quot;but excluding goods&quot;,  on theground that such restrictions would be almost impossible to administer.The Chancellor of the Exchequer, however,did not accept the proposal of the President ofthe Board of Trade.The Cabinet, while agreeing on principle with the President ofthe Board of Trade, felt that froma political point  of view it wouldnot be possible at the present timeto defend a measure which could berepresented as giving British agentsspecial assistance to export foreigngoods.   The question of the form inwhich this decision should be imple-mented was left to the President ofthe Board of Trade in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequerand any other Ministers he might wish to consult.
The Cabinet approved the introduc-tion in the House of Commons of the overseas Trade Bill, 19 30, in theform of a draft annexed to paper.A.-9 (30), subject to thedecision taken as recommendedabove in regard to Clause 1 (2),and subject to any minor or otherdrafting alterations that mightbe found necessary or desirable.-15 a -
HOUSING -12The Cabinet had /before them a &apos;MemorandumBILL,  19 30.(Paper H.A.r-10 f 30.)) by the ;Minister of Health,(Previous covering the draft Housing Bill, 19 30, togetherReference:Cabinet -12        with .the -recommendations of the Committee of Home(30), Con-elusion l(a)..) Affairs thereon.   The Committee of Home affairs had reserved for determination by the Cabinet aquestion of principle relating to compensation,-which had been raised by the Secretary of Statefor Scotland.The Cabinet agreed..-(a) That, as regards the objectionraised by the Secretary of State-for Scotland,  the Bill should beintroduced -in its present form,but that if strong opposition was raised in Parliament .on this point the question of principle should be-re-considered-:(b) That -the Minister of -Health should give consideration to any amendments which might be desired by theSecretary of State for War, whoseDepartment had not yet had anopportunity to examine the Bill:(c) That the Housing Bill,  1930, shouldbe introduced in the House of commons in the -form of the draft annexed to paper HeA,.-10 (30), subject to theabove and to the modificationssuggested by the Committee of HomeAffairs, and to any other drafting or other minor amendments that mightbe -found necessary or desirable,
AGRICULTURALMARKETINGBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet- 16(30), Con-clusion 9 .)13. The Cabinet had before them a Report(Paper C.P.-79 (30)) by a Cabinet Committeecovering the draft Agricultural Marketing Bill,together with the recommendations of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon.The Bill was criticised on the ground ofits complexity and length.The Cabinet agreed  That the Bill should be referred back to the Committee of HomeAffairs with a view to simplification-t ion.
PARLIAMENTARY 14. The Cabinet agreed with the Prime MinisterPROGRAMME.  that, in the long run, Parliamentary time was notThe EasterVacation. likely to be saved by asking the House of commons to meet during Easter Week.   The question of whether the House of Commons should meet on theMonday or Tuesday following Easter, and of thebusiness to be taken, was left in the hands ofthe Prime Minister.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.1,March 26,  19 30.
PARLIAMENTARY 14. The Cabinet agreed with the Prime MinisterPROGRAMME.- that,  in the long run, Parliamentary time was notThe EasterVacation. likely to be saved by asking the House of commons to meet during Easter Week.    The question of whether the House of Commons should meet ora theMonday or Tuesday following Easter, and of thebusiness to be taken, was left in the hands ofthe Prime Minister.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,March 26,  19 30.
APPENDIX,.PROTOCOL.In concluding the present Agreement the ContractingParties are animated by the intention to eliminate fromtheir economic relations all forms of discrimination.They accordingly agree that, so far as relates to thetreatment accorded by each Party to the trade with theother, they will be guided in rega.rd to the purchase and sale of goods, in regard to the employment of shipping and in regard to all similar matters by coinnercial andfinancial considerations only and, subject to such considerations, will adopt no legislative or administra-tive action of such a nature as to place the goods,shipping and trading organisations of the other Partyin any respect in a position of inferiority as comparedwith the goods, shipping and trading organisations ofany other foreign country,,In accordance with the above principle, trade between the United Kingdom and the U.S.S.R. shall be eligible for consideration on.the sarae basis as trade between the United Kingdom and other foreign countriesin connection with any legislative or administrative measures which are or may be taken by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment in the United Kingdom for the granting ofcredits to facilitate such trade, that is to say thatregard shall be had to financial and corniercial con-siderations only.

</content>
</cab>
