<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/63/0 images: 311-319</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS .THE PROPERTY, OF. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;S GOVERNMENT)a E, C R..E..T-. COPY NO.ICABINET    18 (30).Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at   No.10,Downing Street, S.W.I., on Monday, April 7th,1930, at 12 noon.AGENDUM.THE LONDON NAVAL CONFERENCE AND CONNECTED POLITICALQUESTIONS,(Signed) M.F.A. HANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I.4th April, 1930.
/&quot;THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)CABINET 19 (50).SECRET.COPY NO.Conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at10, Downing Street, S.W.1, on Monday, April 7th,1930, at 12 noon.PRESENT:The Right Hon.J. Ramsay MacDonald, M. P. ,Prime Minister     (in the Chair).The Right Hon.Philip Snowden, M. P. ,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon.J.H. Thomas, M.P.Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon.Lord Parmoor of frieth, K.C.V.O.,K.C., Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon.J.R. Clynes , M. P. ,Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.The Right Hon.Tom Shaw, C.B.E. , M.P. ,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon.Ar thur Gr e enwo o d, M. P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon.Noel Buxton, M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon.William Graham, M. P. ,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.Arthur Henderson, M. P.,Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Right Hon.Lord Passfield,&quot; Secretary ofState for Dominion Affairs and secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon.Lord Sankey, G.B.E.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon.W. Wedgwood Berm, D.S.O. ,D.F.C., M.P., Secretary ofState for India.Brig.-Gen. the Right Hon.Lord Thomson, C.B.E. , D.S.O.Secretary of -State for Air.The Right Hon.Margaret Bondfield,Minister of Labour.M. P.The Right Hon.Sir Charles Trevelyan, Bt. ,M,P., President of the Boardof Education.The Right Hon.A.V. Alexander, M. P. ,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon.George Lansbury, M. P. ,First Commissioner of Works.Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B., G.C.M.G.(Secretary).
THE COVENANTOP TEE LEAGUEOP NATIONS.Propos edAmendmentsto ArticlesIS, IS and15.LONDON naval conference.The PoliticalNegotiationswith France.(previous reference:Cabinet IP(SO), Con-conclusion 3.)The Cabinet had before them a Note by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (paper cp,-117 (30)) circulating a Memorandum concerningthe amendments to the Covenant of the League ofNations proposed by the Committee which recentlymet at Geneva.At the outset of the Meeting the Secretaryhanded round a draft Declaration on the understandingby the Signatories of the position as regardssecurity as it now exists for members of the Leagueo&quot;^ Nations .The Prime Minister explained to the Cabinetthat this draft had been given to M. briand on thedistinct understanding that the Cabinet had not seen it *    that it would be brought before theCabinet before his return^    and he would then be told whether the Cabinet accepted it.   M. Eriandhad gone to Paris to consult the French Cabineton the Declaration.    The Italian Delegation atthe London Naval Conference had been kept informed in regard to the document tut had not been a partyto the negotiations.    The dra^t statement was intended to accompany a Five-Power Treaty and not a four-Powe- Treaty.   It represented the views ofthe negotiators, both of whom had undertaken tosubmit it to their respective Governments.   the document had not yet been shown to the delegates of the Dominions and India, but it had beendiscussed, that morning in its general lines withtherm, and the discussion ^as to be continued onthe -morrow.
The Oabinet then entered on a discussion o&quot;&apos; thedra&quot;rt Declaration (Appendix) paragraph by paragraph.PARAGRAPH 1.   This paragraph was criticised onthe grounds th.*t neither the London Naval Conferencenor two or three nations attending that conference are entitled to give a binding interpretation o&apos;r themeaning of the Covenant, and that only the Leagueitself could give such an interpretation.    It wassuggested that in the event of soime trouble arisingwhich necessitated an interpretation in regard tothe obligations and commitments of the States memberso&quot; the League it might be found that there was a conflict between the interpretation here suggested and the interpretation adopted at the time by theLeague,   If a particular State had agreed to sou.eme&apos;-sure of disarmament on the basis o&quot; this Peclara--tion and then found that the League did not supportthe understanding as set forth in the.draft Deolara-tion, a very serious situation -might arise.    It wassuggested that an understanding of this nature wascomparable to the Anglo-French understanding which preceded the British entry into the -Yar. in 1914.In this connection it was pointed out that anint erpretsion had already been given by one groupo-f nations In order to reassure the German government as to the extent  pf their commitments under Article 15of the Covenant of the League of Nations at the timewhen the Locarno Treaty was being drawn up, and was &apos;to be found in Annex F. to the Locarno Treaty, whichwas read to the Cabinet.PARAGRAPH 2 oailed&quot; for no comment .
PARAGRAPH 5.   Attention was drawn to the words&quot;further powers&quot; at the end of this paragraph, inregard to which it was explained that the further powers referred to were the amendments proposed tothe Covenant of the League for strengthening thehands of the Council in the prevention of war.PARAGRAPH 4.   Attention was called to the lastwords,  &quot;proposals having for their purpose the&quot;prevention of war by rapid and effective joint&quot;action in acoo-dance, with a, prearranged plan&quot;.Xt was explained that these words did not refer toa military plan, but only to the plans for safe-guarding peace and preventing the outbreak of war.The Cabinet agreed  That the words &quot;in accordance witha prearranged plan&quot;,  in paragraph 4,might be misunderstood and should bereplaced by some words to show t-hat-they do not refer to a military planbut- to plans for safeguarding peace or to prevent the outbreak ofrwar:^or ex?  pie,  &quot;joint action on thelines oJ the proposed amendments to Articles 13f 15 and 1-5 of theCov lieutenant&quot; .- PARAGRAPH. 5.   The remainder of the Meeting was occupied in the discussion pf Paragraph 5 of theAmpendix.    In this connection the Prime Ministerread, the following extract from an authoritativecommentary on the Covenant of the League of Nationsth&quot;t had been issued as a Parliamentary Paper inJune, 1919 fCmd.151/1919):-&quot;The sanctions of Article XVI,with the exception      the last paragraph,  apply only to breaches of the Covenant involving a resort to war.    In the first instance, itis leftto individual States to decide whether or not such a breach hasoccurred and an act of war againstthe League has been thereby committed.To wait for the pronounces)ent- of aCourt.of Justice o^ even of theCouncil would mean delay, and delayat this crisis might be fatal.   Any
State, there-fore, is justified in        29?such a ease&apos; in breaking off rela-tions with the offending  State onits own initiative, but it is probable,in fact, that the smaller States,unless directly attacked, will waitto see what decision is taken by theGreat Powers or by the Council, whichis bound to meet as soon as possible,and is csertain to do so within a few hours.    It  is the duty of the Council,with the help o^ its military, navaland air advisers, to recommend whateffective force esoh Member of theLeague sh?ll supply;    for this purpose,each november f:oom which a contribution is required has the right to attend the Council, with power of veto, duringthe consideration o&apos;&quot; its particular case.   The several contingents will therefore be settled by agreement,as is indeed necessary PF the spirit0-** the Covenant is to be preserved,and if joint action is to be effioa-cious.   Pu4- it is desirable at thispoint to meet the objection that under such conditions the League will always be late, and consequently offers nosafeguard againstisuddem aggression11.This interpretation, it was pointed out, tended tosupport the interpretation ^contained in Paragraph 5o&apos; the draft Declaration.In order to provide opportunity for further discussion on this question, the Cabinet agreed  (a)  To meet the same afternoon in thePrime minister&apos;s Room at the Rouseof Commons, at 5 p.m.lh) That the Meeting of the Baghdad-Haifa Sub-Committee, which had beanarranged for 5 p.m.., should takeplace a-^ter the Meeting of theCabinet.fc) That the Secretary of State rprForeign Affairs should, answer theQuestions addressed to the PrimeMinister in regard to the proposed declaration by referring to previousanswers on the same Question, byexpressing the hope that he wouldbe able to make a statement in twoo-&quot; three days. and by asking theHouse in the meanwhile to exercisepatienee.2, Whitehall Gardens,April 7, 19 30.&quot;o      o A
APPENDIX.DRAFT DECLARATION.The Undersigned, duly authorised to that effect, herebydeclare as follows:-1. Recognising as we do that a close connection exists between international security and the reduction and limitationof armaments, we desire on the occasion of the signature of thetreaty for the limitation of naval araament, to place on record the understanding of our respective Governments &amp;f the positionas regards security as it now exists for Members of theLeague of Nations.2.    Those Members of the League who are parties to the -Treaty for the Renunciation of War signed at Paris on August27th,  1928, have already agreed that the settlement or solutionof all disputes or conflicts of whatever nature or of whateverorigin they may be which may arise among them, shall never be sought except &quot;tey pacific means.      Among the methods which exist for giving effect to this obligation, in addition tothe Covenant itself, are the Optional Claus A,  the general act, and the conclusion of bilateral arbitration tr eat163,and it is  the intention of our Governments  to make the fullest use of such methods for the settlement of any dispute whichmay arise. &quot;between them.3*    In the event of a threat of war Article II providesthat the League is to take any action that may be deemed wiseand effectual  to safeguard the peace of nations, and thatany Member of the League may forthwith cause a meeting ofthe Council to be summoned.      The importance of the role ofthe Council under this aruicle in preventing an outbreak ofwar has been increasingly recognised in recent years, and our
Governments view with the greatest interest and sympathy theefforts which are &quot;being made to place further powers at thedisposal of the Council when carrying put its functions underv** -this article.2f.    They are resolved to encourage these efforts inorder that the competent organs of the League may as soon aspossible draw up proposals having for their purpose the pre-vention of war by rapid and effective joint action in accord-ance with a prearranged plan.5.    We recognise that each state Member of the League is bound to co-operate loyally and effectively in support of theCovenant and in resistance to any act of aggression to an extent which is compatible with its military situation and -takesits geographical position into account.      Since, before making recommendations under paragraph 2 of Article 16&quot; as to the effective military, na*al or air force which (in accordancewith the terms of the Covenant itself) &quot;the Members of the&quot;League shall severally contribute to the armed forces to be&quot;used to protect the covenants of the League&quot;, the Council will necessarily have taken into account the military situationand the geographical&apos; position of the states concerned, ourGovernments declare their intention of complying promptly withthe recommendations which the Council may make under thisparagraph, and mf fulfilling loyally and effectively their obligations under paragraph 1  of the said article.6.    At the present time the obligations resulting fromArtiele       for the Members of the League enter into force incase of violation of the engagements resulting from Articles12, 15 and 15 of the Covenant.      as they now stand these articles do not exclude the possibility of recourse to forcein circumstances where the Pact of Paris forbids it.
7*    Amendments are now under consideration for trie prorposaof rectifying this situation.8.    Our Governments undertake to do everything in their power, in co-operation with other Members of the League,  toensure that these amendments shall be incorporated in theCovenant with the least possible delay.9.    Our Governments are convinced that this declarationwill dissipate all uncertainty regarding their common intentionfully to carry out, should need arise,  the duty which theCovenant of the League of Lations lays upon then;    and that by so doing it will effectively help to prevent any situation arising in which, as the result of the failure of preventiveaction,  the question for the community of nations would be no .longer the maintenace but the re-establishment of peaje.-xn-

</content>
</cab>
