<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/8 images: 104-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   October 1942.SECRET. Copy No.  29W.P. (42) 478.October 22, 1942.WAR CABINET.UNITED NATIONS RELIEF AND rehabilitation administration.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, the Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs and the President of the Board of Trade.FOLLOWING the discussions at Washington, in which Sir Frederick Leith-Ross participated, a draft agreement for the creation of a United Nations relief and Rehabilitation Administration (attached) was worked out by the UnitedStates Departments concerned, and, with the knowledge and approval of thePresident, has been communicated informally to the Soviet and Chinese Govern-ments, as well as to His Majesty&apos;s Government, with a request for their views.Until agreement has been reached between the four Powers, the United StatesGovernment do not propose to communicate the draft to the other Allied Govern-ments or United Nations or to give any publicity to these proposals.2. This draft agreement has been considered by the Official Inter-Depart-mental Committee, and their recommendations, which have been accepted by allthe Departments represented on the Committee, were as follows :- That (after such consultation with the Dominions and India and with theSoviet Government as Ministers may deem appropriate) His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment should reply to the United States Government on the following lines : (1) His Majesty&apos;s Government agree with the broad lines of the scheme forthe creation of a Relief and Rehabilitation Administration as set outin draft No. 2, revised, of the 13th August, and they are prepared toco-operate in carrying it into effect, subject to the following points and to any observations that the Soviet Government may wish to make.(2) The preliminary view of the United Kingdom Government was that, for reasons of effective administration, the balance of advantage lay inconfining membership of the Policy Committee to the four great powers. On reflection, however, it is felt that limitation of member-ship of the Policy Committee in this way would not, in practice, beconducive to smooth working, since the scheme as a whole would thereby be rendered less acceptable to other important countries whosewhole-hearted co-operation it will be essential to secure. In particular,the United Kingdom Government consider that Canada, as one of the major potential suppliers of relief goods, has a very strong claim to membership of the Committee, a claim that, on merits, is regarded ascarrying greater weight than that of any other country apart fromthe four Great Powers. The United Kingdom Government recognisethat any enlargement of the Policy Committee should not be such as would be likely to impair the efficient working of the directingmachinery, but it is thought that a Committee not exceeding sevenmembers would fulfil this requirement, and this number would&quot; enablemembership to be accorded to two other countries in addition to canada. The United Kingdom Government accordingly wish torecommend that the Policy Committee be expanded to include rep re-sent atives of three countries in addition to the four Great Powers,and that Canada, as one of these three countries, should be accordedfull membership of the Committee.[24531] . this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT
(3) This is the only definite modification which the United KingdomGovernment would suggest in the draft. They note that provision ismade for the constitution of a Regional Committee to deal with european relief, and they would again emphasise the importance they attach to giving as much scope as possible to this Committee. they hope that a Regional Organisation for the Far East will also be constituted.(4) The United Kingdom Government take note that the Relief Administra-tion shall, wherever practicable, use the facilities made available by such agencies of the United Nations as shall at the time be inexistence, and they understand that il is not intended that theAo. ninistration shall set up its own agencies, either for planning orfor execution of plans regarding provision of supplies and shipping,except where no suitable agencies of the United Nations are available.(5) The United Kingdom Government would also reserve the right to moveamendments of detail when the stage is reached of submitting this draft agreement to a meeting of the United Nations for acceptance.(6) The United Kingdom Government feel it important, however, to obtainthe views of the other United Nations, and particularly of theEuropean Allied Governments, on these proposals at the earliestpossible date, and they would suggest that, if the draft is acceptable to the Soviet and Chinese Governments, it should be communicated tothe other Governments with a view to their giving it consideration and submitting their observations on it. So far as the EuropeanAllied Governments are concerned, the draft could, if the UnitedStates Government agreed, be communicated by Sir Frederick Leith-Ross to the Allied Committee in London.(7) In this way, the ground could be prepared so that when the United StatesGovernment feels it opportune to proceed further, a meeting could beheld of the representatives of the four Great Powers, to review thedraft in the light of the observations received, and subsequently ameeting could be arranged of the United Nations to obtain its general acceptance and to carry it into effect.3. It will be seen that the only point on which the Official Committeesuggests a modification of the draft agreement relates to the constitution of thePolicy Committee of the Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. The UnitedStates draft proposes to limit membership to the four Great Powers, viz., theUnited States, United Kingdom, Russia and China. In our view, it is important that the four Great Powers should retain control of post-war political arrange-ments, but this should not preclude the participation of other Governments inorganisations set up for particular purposes. In the present case, we considerit impossible to resist the claim of Canada to membership of the directing bodyof the proposed Relief organisation, and this will entail adding to the proposed policy Committee, in addition to the four Great Powers, not more than threeadditional members, one of which should be Canada. We regard it as essential,if the Committee is to work effectively, that its membership should not be extendedfurther.4. Accordingly, we endorse the recommendations of the Official Committeeon this and other points relating to the draft Agreement, and we ask the WarCabinet to agree, in principle, that a reply should be sent to the United StatesGovernment on the lines proposed.5. Before this reply can be despatched, however, consultation will benecessary both with the Dominions and India, and also, in virtue of the Anglo-Soviet Treaty of Alliance, with the Soviet Government. In order to avoid delay,the question of Canadian membership of the Policy Committee has been broachedwith the High Commissioners by the Dominions Secretary, and it is hoped toget agreement with the Dominion Governments and India before approaching theSoviet Government. As soon as possible, however, the Foreign Secretary would inform the Soviet Ambassador that we propose to reply on these lines to theUnited States Government in a fortnight&apos;s time, but that before doing so weshould welcome an expression of the views of the Soviet Government.6. One other point is raised in the Report of the Official Committee, viz.,whether the time has yet come for His Majesty&apos;s Government to reconsider thedecision taken by the War Cabinet on the 9th July (W.P. 42 (90th Conclusions),Minute 1) as to the issue of an announcement about the continuation of rationing
after the war. We do not feel that there is any immediate need for a decisionon this point, and we consider that its consideration can best be deferred untilthe constitution of a United Nations Relief Organisation is actually decided upon.C. R, A.A. E.H. D.October 22, 1942.ANNEX.Relief and Rehabilitation Administration.August 13, 1942.Draft No. 2 (Revised).THE Governments whose duly-authorised representatives have subscribedhereto,Having subscribed to a common programme of purposes and principlesembodied in the Declaration of January 1, 1942, known as the United NationsDeclaration and the Joint Declaration of the President of the United States ofAmerica and the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom of Great Britain andNorthern Ireland dated the 14th August. 1941, known as the Atlantic Charter,Being determined that immediately upon the liberation of any area by theirarmed forces the population thereof shall receive aid and relief from theirsufferings, food, clothing and shelter, aid in the prevention of pestilence and inthe recovery of the health of the people, and that preparation and arrangementsshall be made for the return of prisoners and exiles to their homes, for the resumption of agricultural and industrial production and the restoration of essential services, to the end that peoples once freed may be preserved andrestored to health and strength for the tasks and opportunities of building anew,Have agreed as follows :-Article I.There is hereby established, the United Nations Relief and rehabilitation administration.1. The Administration shall have power to acquire, hold and conveypropert)^, to enter into contracts and undertake obligations, to designate or createagencies and to review the activities of agencies so created, to manage under-takings and in general to perform any legal act appropriate to its objects and purposes.2. Subject to the provisions of Article VII, the purposes and functions ofthe Administration shall be as follows : (a) To plan, co-ordinate, administer or arrange for the administration of measures for the relief of victims of war in any ai^ea under the controlof any of the United Nations through the provision of food, fuel,clothing and other basic necessities, housing facilities, medical andother essential services; and to facilitate in areas receiving relief theproduction and transportation of these articles and the furnishingof these services so far as necessary to the adequate provision of relief.(&amp;) To formulate and recommend measures for individual or - joint action by any or all of the member governments for the co-ordination of purchasing, the chartering of ships and other procurement activities in the period following the cessation of hostilities, with a view tointegrating the plans and activities&apos; of the Administration with thetotal movement of supplies, and for the purpose of achieving an equitable distribution of available supplies. The Administration mayadminister such co-ordination measures as the member governmentsauthorise.[24531] - B 2.
(c) To formulate and recommend for individual or joint action by the united nations measures with respect to such related matters arising out ofits experience in planning and performing the work of relief and rehabilitation, as may be proposed by any of the member governments and approved by unanimous vote of the Policy Committee.Article II. Membership.The members of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Adminis-tration shall be the governments or authorities signatory hereto and. such othergovernments or authorities as may upon application for membership be admittedthereto by action of the Council or the Policy Committee thereof.Article III. The Council.1. Each member government shall name one representative, and suchalternates as may be necessary, upon the Council of the United Nations relief and Rehabilitation Administration, which shall be the policy-making body ofthe Administration. The Council shall, for each of its sessions, select one of its members to preside at the session.2. The Council shall be convened in normal session not less than twice ayear by the Policy Committee. It may be convened in special session whenever the Policy Committee shall deem necessary, and shall be convened within thirty days after request therefor by a majority of the members of the Council.3. The Policy Committee of the Council shall consist of the representativesof China, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, the United Kingdom and theUnited States of America, with the Director General presiding. Betweensessions of the Council it shall exercise all the powers and functions thereof. Itshall invite the participation of the representative of any member government atthose of its meetings at which action of special interest to such government is discussed.4. The Council may establish such standing committees as it considersdesirable to advise it, and, in intervals between sessions of the Council, to advise the Policy Committee. The members of such committees shall be appointed bythe Policy Committee, with the approval of the Council if it be in session, and otherwise subject to its ratification, from members of the Council or alternatesnominated for the purpose. Among these committees, the Council may establishregional committees to advise it on the making of plans and formulation of policy for the relief and rehabilitation of Europe, the Far East and of any other areas where such committees may be found desirable. The regional committees shallnormally meet within the area, and shall include members of the Council, or their alternates, representing the member governments directly concerned withthe problems of relief and rehabilitation in that area. The Regional Committeeon European Relief when so constituted shall take over and carry on the work ofthe Inter-Allied Committee on European Post-War Relief established in london on the 24th September. 1941. For such technical standing committees as maybe established, in respect of particular problems such as nutrition, health,agriculture, transport, materials and supplies, repatriation and finance, themembers may be members of the Council or alternates nominated because ofspecial competence in their respective fields of work. Should a regional committeeso desire, sub-committees of these technical standing committees shall be estab-lished to advise the regional committees.5. The travel and other expenses of members of the Council and its committees shall be borne by the governments which they represent.Article IV. The Director General.1. The executive authority of the United Nations Relief and rehabilitation administration shall be in the Director General, who shall be appointed by theCouncil on the nomination of the Policy Committee.2. The Director General shall have full power and authority for carrying-out relief operations contemplated by Article I, section 2 (a), within the limits of available resources and the broad policies determined by the Council or its policy Committee. Immediately upon taking office he shall,&apos; in conjunction withthe military and other appropriate authorities of the United Nations, prepare plans for the emergency relief of the civilian population in any area occupied by
the armed forces of any of the United Nations, arrange for the procurement and assembly of the necessary supplies and create or select the emergency organisationrequired for this purpose. In arranging for the procurement, transportation anddistribution of supplies and services, he and his representatives shall consult andcollaborate with the appropriate authorities of the United Nations, and shall,wherever practicable, use the facilities made available by such authorities.Foreign voluntary relief agencies may not engage in activity in any areareceiving relief from the Administration without the consent and unless subjectto the regulation of the Director General. The powers and duties of the director general are subject to the limitations of Article VII.3. The Director General shall also be responsible for the organisation and direction of the functions contemplated by Article I, sections 2 (b) and 2 (c).4. The Director General shall appoint such Deputy Directors, other officers,expert personnel, and staff, at his headquarters or elsewhere, including the staff offield missions and secretarial and other necessary staff for the Council and its committees, and may delegate to them such of his powers as he may deemappropriate.5. The Director General shall make periodic reports to the Council covering the progress of the Administration^ activities. These reports shall be made public except for such portions as the Director General may consider it necessary,in the interest of the United Nations, to keep confidential until the end ofthe war.Article V. Supplies and Resources.1. Each member government pledges its full support to the Administration,within the limits of its available resources and subject to the requirements ofits constitutional procedure, through contributions of funds, materials, equip-ment, supplies and services, for use in its own, adjacent or other areas in need,in order to accomplish the purposes of Article I, section 2 (a). All such contribu-tions received by the Administration shall be accounted for.2. The supplies and resources made available by the member governmentsshall be kept in review in relation to prospective requirements by the director general, who shall initiate action with the member governments with a view toassuring additional supplies and resources as may be required.3. All purchases by any of the member governments, made outside their ownterritories during the war for relief or rehabilitation purposes, shall be made only after consultation with the Director General, and shall, so far as practicable, becarried out through the appropriate United Nations agency.Article VI. Administrative Expenses.The general administrative expenses shall be borne by the member govern-ments in proportion to be determined by the Council. The governmentalauthority of any territory receiving aid from the Relief and rehabilitation administration shall in addition place at the disposal of the Administration any sums required in the currency of that territory for local expenditure in theadministration or distribution of such aid.Article VII.Notwithstanding any other provision herein contained, while hostilities orother military necessities exist in any area, the Administration and its director general shall not undertake activities therein without the consent of the military command of that area, and unless subject to such control as the command may find necessary. The determination that such hostilities or military necessitiesexist in any area shall be made by its military commander.Article VIII. Amendment.The provisions of this agreement may be amended by unanimous.vote of thePolicy Committee and two-thirds vote of the Council.




</content>
</cab>
