<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/66/39 images: 260-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CP. (45) 39. \flQth June, 1945.CABINET./BRABAZON I TYPE CIVIL AIRCRAFT : PROPOSED EXTENSION OFFELTON (BRISTOL) AIRFIELD.Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production.ON the 11th June, 1945 (CM. (45), 7th Conclusions, Minute 6) the cabinet considered my Memorandum, CP. (45) 25, regarding the provision of facilities atFilton Airfield, Bristol, for the construction of Brabazon I type Civil Aircraft.It was suggested that the construction of the assembly hangar might be put inhand if the expenditure to be incurred before the 1st August, 1945, would notexceed  50,000, and I was invited to submit a schedule of disbursements showingthe expenditure which would be incurred in each of the months over which theconstruction of the proposed assembly shed would be spread. I append theschedule. No commitments involving larger sums than  32,000 need be incurredbefore the 1st August.2. I hope that, in the light of this, my colleagues will feel able to authoriseme to put this work in hand.3. I am having discussions with the Secretary of State for Air regardingthe length proposed for the runway. Whatever the outcome of these discussions,this hangar will be necessary.4. This paper has been prepared in consultation and agreement with theSecretarv of State for Air.E. B.Ministry of Aircraft Production,&apos; IQth June, 1945.Schedule of anticipated disbursements in each of the months over whichthe construction of the proposed assembly shed would be spread.Month                                        Expenditure Cumulativeduring Month. Total.   It]......        12,0003rd.......        20,000 32,0004th                      .........        45&apos;000 77,0005th-                 80&apos;()00 157,000.........       ......      ^20,000 277,0007th                               -       - -      125&apos;000 402,0008h                      -                         100 502,0009th......        75-000 577,000loth:::   ........   -   gwg 627,000Hth ...      .          &quot;      -      -V        ?3,000 660,00015,000 675,000[30081]




</content>
</cab>
