<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/57/30 images: 226-233</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   November 1944.Gopy No.WAR CABINET.AUSTRALIA-NEW ZEALAND CONFERENCE AT WELLINGTON.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.I think the War Cabinet should see at once the annexed telegrams from our high Commissioner in New Zealand reporting on the conclusions of the recentAustralia-New Zealand Conference at Wellington.I propose to submit my comments on the position separately.C.Dominions Office, .8th November, 1944.ANNEX.Telegram No. 388 of A4h November from United Kingdom High Commissioner in new Ijealand.(No. 398.   Secret.)I understand that at meetings held outside Canberra Conference confidentialunderstanding was reached that the two Dominions would collaborate generally inall international economic matters, and especially in all policies making for.full employment. I have no more details, but I gather that the understanding islikely to be confirmed, and perhaps amplified, at present meeting. Final meetingof Conference, which I have been asked to attend, takes place on Monday,6th November, and after that I will telegraph further.Telegram No. 399 of 6th November.(No. 399.)AT the conclusion of the Australia-New Zealand Conference this afternoonI was asked by the Prime Minister to send you the following message. Begins: -&quot; The Australia-New Zealand Conference meeting in Wellington send a message of special regard and goodwill to the pe&amp;ple.of Great Britain, nowentering upon their sixth winter of the War. They rejoice--iruthe historicAllied victories which have driven the enemy back from Britain&apos;s gates andhave lightened the trials which have lain so heavily upon the British peoplethroughout the summer. They trust that in.the coming months the commoneffort of the United Nations will bring the final triumph of the cause forwhich they justly took up arms.&quot;.   Ends.SECRET.W.P. (44) 630.   .8th November, 1944.Telegram No. 400 of 7th November.(No. 400.)REFERENCE my telegram No. 399 of 6th November.Following are principal points from statement by Prime Minister at theconclusion of the Australian-New Zealand Conference, 6th November: 1. Agreed conclusions reached on number of important issues of externalpolicy arising from special position as neighbouring British Dominions in theSouth Pacific, as well as on those issues which are the common concern of theUnited Nations.[28559] B
2. The two Governments have already made known the supreme importance-attached to the establishment of a general international organisation as discussed at Dumbarton Oaks. Formulation of the considered views of the two Govern-mertts must be reserved for United Nations Conference, for which it is to be hoped Dumbarton Oaks proposals have prepared the way. For the organisation to fulfil its task, the condition underlying all others is that members should fullyhonour obligations which they assume. Power of Governments&apos; to perform what has been promised Will depend on people&apos;s support, and therefore on theirunderstanding of pledges given. Charter of the organisation should thereforemake clear. to peoples of the world the principles on which action of theorganisation is to be based. Members should pledge themselves to carry out by force, if need be, the decisions taken by the competent bodies of the organisation for the preservation of peace. It should be a positive principle of the organisa-tion, openly declared and binding on all members, that territorial integrity andpolitical independence of members should be preserved against change by force or threat of force. Provision should be made by the organisation for facilitatingorderly change of a situation continuation of which might endanger peace.Organisation will depend upon the leadership of the greater Powers. On theother hand, it is essential that all members should be enabled actively toparticipate in the general direction of its affairs. Powers of the assembly, onwhich all members will be represented, should therefore extend to the wholesphere of action of the organisation. Council should have special powers inregard to the settlement of disputes and the-prevention of aggression.3. Reference Clauses 28 to 31 of the Canberra Agreement^ the Govern-ments consider that there should be set up as part of the organisation aninternational body analogous to the Permanent Mandates Commission, to whichColonial Powers should undertake to make reports on the administration of colonial Territories. This body should be empowered to visit dependent territories and to publish reports of its deliberations. This is a naturalimplication of the spirit of &quot; trusteeship &quot; for dependent peoples. TheAustralian and New Zealand Governments are willing to subscribe to a generalundertaking to that effect as regards both Colonies and Mandated Territories.Considered that this system of international supervision should be binding ontrustee States. In addition, the Australian and New Zealand Governments are anxious to promote a Regional Commission as a means by which governments and Administrations of the South Seas area may pool their experience andcollaborate in furthering the welfare of dependent peoples. Repetition of proposal in the Canberra Agreement that representatives of the UnitedKingdom, United States and France should join the Commission.4. The Australian and New Zealand Governments regard international agreement to pursue domestic policies of full employment as fundamental to allinternational co-operation to promote human welfare. Agreements for the encouragement of trade are most necessary, and it is a matter of immediateconcern that international discussions about this should proceed. To be successful, latter must, however, operate in a world not afflicted by unemploy-ment. Most important first step towards attaining this would be for each government, recognising its obligations to its own people and to the people ofevery other country, to join in international agreement pledging itself to followan appropriate domesticjoolicy of full employment.5. The Conference also discussed other matters which cannot be announcedpublicly at this stage.6.&apos; In the Conference the two Governments were fully conscious that manyof the issues discussed are of concern to other United Nations. Examination ofthese questions has been carried out not in an exclusive spirit but with the broadobjective of making a contribution to world peace and welfare.Telegram No. 401 of 7th November, 1944.(No. 401.)REFERENCE my telegram No. 399 of 6th November and my immediately preceding telegram.Public statement at conclusion of Australian-New Zealand Conference also made by Forde. He stated that Fraser as Chairman of Conference had clearlypresented objectives and some of the immediate results of the Conference, and.* Annex I to W.P. (44) 70.
there was nothing he wished to add to Eraser&apos;s review of Conference^ work inWellington. Rest of the speech was concerned with general observations aboutinternational relations including complimentary references to the organisation ofthe Conference by Departments of Internal and External Affairs.Telegram No. 402 of 1th November. 1944.(No. 402.)MY telegrams Nos. 399, 400 and 401.Canadian High Commissioner and I were invited to concluding meeting of australian-New Zealand Conference and were given copies of (a) Fraser&apos;s andForde&apos;s statements which were to be given to the press and (b) secret conclusionsof the Conference. My telegrams Nos. 403 and 404 gave substance of conclusions.As regards Colonial Administration, I did my best to secure exclusion frompublished statement of details of recommendation contained in conclusions.Evatt was, however, insistent on publication of paragraph as it stood. I was,however, able to secure substitution of the word &quot; visit &quot; for the word &quot; inspect,&quot;though latter word remains in the conclusions. Texts of the two published state-ments and of secret conclusions of Conference follow by bag.Telegram No. 403 of 1th November, 1944.(No. 403.   Secret.)MY telegram No. 402.    Following is summary of secret conclusions of conference.   Begins:  I. General International Organisation.Main clauses are fully summarised in Fraser&apos;s public statement, my telegramNo. 400.   Additional clauses as follows :-(A) Organisation to be open to all sovereign States subject to approval of admission by Assembly.(B) There should be maximum employment of International Court of Justicefor ascertainment of facts in dispute.(C) Security Council should be limited in numbers but as representative aspossible.(D) International welfare bodies should be brought within framework of organisation. [Note : Last sentence of clause relating to organisa-tion analogous to Permanent Mandate Commission reads &apos;&apos; that body should be empowered to publish reports of its deliberations andto inspect dependent territories.&quot;]II. Armistice Arrangements.III. South Seas Regional Commission.For verbatim text of these sections see my telegram No. 404.IV. Welfare Relations.1. General Policy.Governments reaffirm understanding reached at Canberra (see my telegramNo. 398 of 4th November) in exchange of letters of 24th January (of which Ihave not previously heard) that following expresses their common point ofview : (i) It is agreed to press strongly for international agreement by which (A) countries will bind themselves to pursue policies aimed at full employ-ment, and(B) existing organisations such as I.L.O. or new organisations will be usedto facilitate exchange of information and consultation on employment policy. .(ii) It is agreed to support such international economic collaboration in immediate post-war period as will make unnecessary policies of aggressiveeconomic nationalism.(iii) Limited agreements between individual nations providing for regularconsultation of economic matters might lead to more comprehensive agreements.[28559] &quot; b 2
(iv) Countries which are not fully developed . or are highly dependent onnarrow range of exports should be able under any agreement (A) to use such measures as Import Selection, Exchange Control, States        Trading and British Commonwealth preferences as may from timeto time prove necessary. Need for these will decrease to extent that international collaboration succeeds, and(B) to develop and diversify their industries.(v) Agreements affecting Australia and New Zealand must take into specialaccount dislocations and developments necessitated by total war effort.2. Employment Agreements.Agreement by which signatories undertake to pursue internal policies of full employment and improved living standards is regarded as fundamental to all aspects of international collaboration for promoting human Welfare. Calling ofan employment conference should take precedence over all other international economic discussions. &quot;We propose therefore to approach the United StatesGovernment with the proposal that a conference be called by the United StatesGovernment in conjunction with the United Kingdom, Australia and NewZealand Governments.&quot;3. Discussions between officials.Arrangements to be made for early examination of (A) matters of international economic collaboration including employmentconference, commercial and commodity policy proposals, control of(B) matters of Australia-New Zealand relations including trade, industrialdevelopment, shipping, co-ordination of policies regarding export of primary products to United Kingdom, application of price stabilisation-tion policies to Australia-New Zealand trade, post-war trade in the-&quot;Pacific and post-war international planning.   Ends.Telegram No. 404 of 7th November, 1944.(No. 404.   Secret.)My telegram No. 403. Following is text of Parts II and&apos; III o/Conclusions.   Begins:  II. Armistice Arrangements.1. The Conference has noted communications which have been exchangedon the subject of the armistice arrangements in Europe. It considers that theDominions and other nations which have been actively engaged from thebeginning in the war against the Axis Powers, and have contributed and are con-tributing materially to their defeat, both on the European fronts and in other theatres of war, are entitled to an effective voice in the conclusion of theEuropean armistices, and the preparations for the peace settlements, and partici-pation in their own right in the control of the armistice machinery.2. In the interests of solidarity of the United Nations, both Australia andNew Zealand have felt obliged to acquiesce in their exclusion from those arrange-ments in the past, even though settlements of vital concern have been involved,but they cannot acquiesce in a similar situation in the Pacific and the Far East.3. Australia and New Zealand are agreed that they should take the strongest possible action to ensure that their Governments are consulted in regard todrafting armistices with Japan and Thailand, that they are represented directlyat the conclusion of the armistices and that they have the right of participating inthe armistice control arrangements.4. Noting Clauses 7 to 11 of the Australia-New Zealand Agreement and work already done, the two Governments agree that they will -proceed further with co-ordination of their armistice and post-hostilities planning.III. South Seas Regional Commission.1. Immediate steps should be taken to establish South Seas RegionalCommission at the earliest possible date.* Annex I to W P. (44) 70.
2. The general scheme for organisation of South Seas Regional commission should be as follows :&apos; (a) the Commission proper which should consist of representatives of governments and administrations in the region;b) a secretariat;c) research and functional bodies established by the United Nations Govern-ments on the advice of the Commission.3. Provision should be made for associating with the work of the Commis-sion existing research and functional bodies.4. There should be held regularly a South Seas Conference for discussion ofPacific Island problems.This Conference might comprise nominees of Governments represented onthe Commission (these nominees to represent administrations, scientific bodies,missionary bodies and native peoples) together with nominees of international organisations concerned with welfare problems (e.g., the I.L.O. and food and agricultural organisation).5. The native peoples shall, wherever practicable, be enabled to take part in work of Commission and its agencies.6. An immediate approach should be made by Australian and NewZealand Governments to the United Kingdom in regard to establishment of commission.. Ends.




</content>
</cab>
