<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/14/0 images: 20-25</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ittTiES DOCUMENT IS THE PjgOPERgY of HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT.WAR CABINET 381a.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, downing street    S.W. on WEDNESDAY, 3rd. April, 1918, at 12.30 a.m.present.The Rt. Hon. A. Bonar law, M.P.  (in the Chair)The Rt. Hon. the Earl Curzon of The Rt. Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Kedleston. K.G.,G.C.S.I..G.C.I.E.The Rt. Hon. The Viscount Milner, Lieutenant-General the Rt. Hon.G.C.B..G.C.M.G. J. c. Smuts, E.C.,THE following WERE ALSO PRESENT.The Rt. Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,Iff.P., Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.The Rt. Hon. Sir G. Cave, Z.C.,M.P., Secretary of State for HomeAffairs.Fhe Rt. Hon. the Earl of Derby,IPG.:, G.C.V.O., C.B., Secretarybf State for War.Che Rt. Hon. Sir A. C. Geddes,pCB., M.P., Minister of NationalService.The Rt. Hon. H. E. Duke, P.C., M.P.Chief Secretary for Ireland.The Rt. Hon. Lord Wimborne, lord lieutenant of Ireland.The Rt. Hon. Sir Henry Robinson,K.C.B., Vice-President, LocalGovernment Board for Ireland.Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones,  C.M.G., Acting secretary.
( xfcia Poovmetit is the. Property jjMIs BritannicMas 31 y1 a g&apos; v e r- use nt .&quot;)&quot;   war CABINET 381 A.DRAFT MINUTES of a Meeting held at IB, Downing Street, S ,W.,en WEDNESDAY, APRIL 3,  1918,  at &apos; 13.30 p.ia.With reference to War Cabinet 379 A, Minute S, MrBonar Lav.&apos; informed the Cabinet that he had seen the Lord.Lieutenant, with whom he had had a conversation on the policyof the Home Rile and Compulsory Military Service questions,and similarly Sir Henry Robins on.    Both these gentlemen wereavailable to be interviewed by the Cabinet.The War Cabinet also had before them a Memorandum bythe Chief Secretary (Paper G-.T.-4105), and a Memorandum bythe Lord Chief Justice for Ireland (Paper G.T.-4101).Lord Wiraborne then attended., and was invited to give his vie^s. which were to the effect that to issue the order for Compulsory Military Service to Ireland before the settle-ment of the Convention would be to uf*&amp;e-t&quot;Wie^-orw^nfci-m^-&quot;ii-t-&quot;Self-.- jTraZs&apos;-^^ .It was suggested that the promise of Home Rule mightbe held out as an inducement for acceptance of conscription.On the other hand,  it was pointed out that to put the settle-.iaent *f the -0ertvontj.on before Conscription would be to defer the latte &quot;* indefinitely . l&amp;ifo&apos;****A^-&apos;!f6*fe*7tA*H/^^&amp;*^*^77**t**(ZA**M!Sir George Cave^8^5^9^e4-tm Order in CounciltntaNB- application &amp;  conscription simultaneous with the Intro-duotion of Rome Rule.The Chief Secretary preferred a modification by whichpowers should be taken in Order of Council for extending themachinery of conscription in the case of failure of response to a call for voluntary enlistment., and a period of one month was proposed... ^ _
The situation was summed up as being that if the nationalists were promised Home Rule, to be^followed by con-soription, they would not accept.    If their opponents were asked to accept conscription which was to be followed by home Rule, they would equally object:   while if both home rule and Conscription were to be brought in together, opposi-tion would be general,-    In the minds of Unionists the greatpoint of Conscription was that it would imply the maintenanceof an United Kingdom,    It wag understood that, on the whole,.Lord Wimborne considered that the -s-drg-itt thing was to intro-duce the two projects simultaneously, -having in vlew^ the,-po-ifi^ that the strength of Sinn-Fein lay In&quot; its opposition to conscription.Lord Wimborne concurred in this statement.Mr Duke referred to the necessity of keeping anunruly minority in order, and read to the Cabinet a letterreceived from Archbishop L*Hpw*, which indicated that Conscriptlon oo^ld have been effected on two previous occasions.First, two years ago, before Sinn-Fein developed;    and,second, after the United States had declared war.   The worstthing that could happen would be to suggest the introductionof Conscription and not to carry it through.    If Conscriptionwas declared and enforced,  it would inevitably cause disturb-disturbances and imperil the settlement of the Convention, but,  oncestarted, it must be carried through,    Mr Duke expressed hisconfidence inja -&amp;a&amp;oIutQ- Government for Ireland^ provided Itwas well supported, and believed that, under those conditionssuch a Government might be trusted in the future even tooarrylng out Conscription.Mr Bonar Law thought that they roust have a Home RuleBill which included Conscription.Lord Gurzon understood that the view of the lord lieutenant and of the Chief Secretary was that it would bebetter to take both Home Rule and Conscription together-3-
than to take either separately and fail with regard to theother,  or to do nothing at all.Lord Milner deprecated the idea of playing torth Con-script ion .   Once entered on, they would have to see it through.Mr Bonar Law was in favour of taking the two projectstogether, hut for the danger of an explosion in Ulster.Lord Milne r thought that, however &quot;Btrar.g.e. i^financial&amp;biappear, an attack&apos; -qh- both aides would not be a bad thing.The Government would undoubtedly receive&quot;va-e-t support inthis country, a great deal in Ireland,  and the^ supp*rri---cnf -the.&quot;&quot; he^ppGsia^.-^4.ew3-H^^center a(Miing^inf-2^en^^^Lord vfimborne stated that there^exist e-d in Ireland aconsiderable body in favour of genaogiptionx ^^^^^ ^&apos;Lord Milner said that a settlement in Ireland would never be attained unless it was imposed;    it should be Imposed,therefore,  on both sides.    The two measures should be pa**e4conourrently, J&amp;x *v--2&amp;$-&apos;A&amp;^^-ti-^n-o-f-Co na c^iti^pt-ion^-mig-ht^he^po^pAne&apos;^General Smuts,  concurring with Lord Milner, said that now was the right  tiroe to carry both these things.Mr Duke added that this was the only time that therewould be a chance of setting up a Conservative Parliament,on account of the new enfranchlsementS^nd^he^^^ct-o^-^-case-ss^lord Ourzon agreed with Lord Milner and General Smuts,and thought that either both measures\ires 3hould be incorporated in one Bill,  or that,  if in two Bills, both should be intro-duced at the same time.Lord Milner considered the better course would be tobring in the two together, the Conscription Bill to contain a clause saying that Conscription would be applied when bothBills came into force.Mr Bonar Law pointed out that the Government would haveto stand or fall by both.
9 9c*Lord Milner called attention to the increasingdifficulties resulting from every postponement,and urgedthat),  if the outcome were disturbances in Ireland, it couldnot be helped, but that a further postponement would make matters worse.Mr Duke thought that a state of suppressed rebellionwould ensue.(Lord Wimbo .rne then withdrew.)Sir Henry Robinson, Vice-president of the LocalGovernment Board for Ireland, attended the Meeting, and,in reply to a question as to what would be the effect of conscription, gave his views that different cla3sen wouldbe differently affected.    The young shopmen in towns wouldgive trouble, while farmers&apos;  sons in the country wouldprobably try to escape service.    Prom the labour ranks he did not think that many men would be got, by reason of theincreased number employed on additional tillage.    On thewhole, he thought that they would not be disappointed in getting a fair supply of men.    Questioned as to the possi-bility of outrages and anarchy resulting, Sir Henry Robinsonsaid that that depended entirely on the way the matter was put to the people.    IS they were convinced that it was goingto be carried through, they would accept the position.    Itdepended on the administration; if this were faulty and weak,the people would fight to the death against it,  but if they saw that this administration was determined, they would accept.If Conscription was started and resolutely carried through,Sinn-Fein would die at once.    The farmers were not supporters of Sinn-Fein, but had to appear at markets as if they were,because otherwise no-one would deal with them.    The farmershated Sinn-Fein and wanted to be quit of it.    If Sinn-Feinwas defeated, opposition to conscription would certainlycollapse.    There would be a hard fight at first, but it wouldnot  last long, if it was thought the measure was meant. Theyhad to remember the great effect of the large amount ofmoney which was pouring into Ireland in respect of separation-4-
allowances and compensations, the question *f aimulta-neous application of the two Bills, Sir Henry feared thedanger of trouble in Ulster, which would tend to stop theWar by interfering with the output.Mr Balfour put the question whether, from a militaryil O point of view, we could afford to have shipyard labour outon strikes.   Although there was now no evidence of any impend-ing strike, employers and workmen were working, with extra-ordinary energy,  and it would be deplorable to have any inter-ruption to this state of affairs.Lord Milner asked if the Ulster workmen would strikeif they saw that we were fighting Sinn-Fein.    In his view the two things seemed to balance each other.Sir Henry Robinson said he would not be afraid atordinary times, but now great unrest would be occasioned,especially among the women&apos; linen-workers, who were employedon aeroplane work.    He was afraid of unrest and reduction of output.    Much depended on the leaders.Mr Balfour wished to revert to the fundamental point the War.   He asked the question whether we should be strongerif we got a few men from Ireland and ran the risk of disturb-ances,  or stronger if we did nothing.    He laid down that therewere only two policies - all, or none.    If we adopted the&quot;none&quot; policy, it would be difficult to persuade England.We should have to state the naked truth, that Ireland is asheer weakness,, but that it would be a greater weakness ifwe did something than it was if we did nothing.-Lord&quot;-&quot;M-i-lne^--a ee e-nt-e-d-mr Duke asked how long Sir Henry Robinson thought thatshipbuilders would be likely to hold out on strike at thist ims.Sir Henry Robinson did not anticipate a strike.   Hethought there would be much unrest and consequent reducedoutput, but did not think there would be an actual strike, asthe men were making so much money.    He did not think they would go so far a3 to down tools.Whit*v,*ii n    a       &apos; r.       &apos;^3ir Henry Robinson then withdrew),vmitehall Gardens, S.W..April 4,   1918.      * 5 &apos;   &apos; 151 &apos;  &apos;

</content>
</cab>
