<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/14/0 images: 106-109</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
pjS DOCUMBNT IB THE^RPOPBRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT) .mi-WAR CABINET 4ISA.secretary Notes of a meeting held at 10, Downing Street,S.W.,Monday, 27th. May 1918, at noon.PRESENT.    .The Prime Minister(in the Chair).je RtB Ron. the Earl Curzon of Lieutenant-General the Rt. Hon.;Hieston,K.G. ,G.C.S.I. ,G.C.I.E. , J.C.  Smuts,K.C..Ie Rt. Hon. G.N. Barnes, M.P. , The Rt. Hon. A. Chamberlain,M.P.&apos;eRt. Hon. A.  Bonar Law, M.P.The following were also present:-ineral Sir H.H. Wilson,K.C.B. , The Rt. Hon. Sir E. Geddes,Lo.,Chief of the Imperial G.B.E.,K.C.B.,M.P., First LordsIneral Staff. * of the Admiralty.Rear-Admiral G.P.W. Hope, C.B.Deputy First Sea Lord.eutenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey,K.C.B............Secretary.
ion(This DocumentMis the Property gf His britannic  A estv [ a Go-rernment.)G RET -to&apos;?AR CABINET 4X8 A.DRAFT MINUTES of a Meeting held at 10, Downing Street, S ,fMon MONDAY, MAY 87. 191s, at \% Noon.RUCTION With reference to ,?ar Cabinet 410, Minute 11, thercsiANIC FLKRT. Deputy First Sea Lord informed the War Cabinet that a somewhat corrupt telegram had been received from theNaval Attache&apos; at Petrograd, .dated May ZZ* 19X8, relative to the destruction of the Baltic Fleet.    It indicated thatCaptain Groaie had been approached by his agents and in-forced that, if the scheme for destruction is delayed too long, money already expended might be lost, several of themen who were to carry out the destruction having said thatthe danger mt&amp; no longer existed, and that therefore they desired to return to their villages.    The agents therefore proposed now to obtain men that could be relied on to pre-pare a scheme, and for a certain date to be fixed for thedestruction, although the present scheme would still exist in case of emergencies.   The Naval Attache asks whether heshould accept this greater responsibility.The First Lord stated that the existing orders to CaptainCroiaie were that the time of the destruction of the BalticFleet was left to his discretion, but that he was not to doit until there was imminent danger of a German advance onPetrograd.   This might be said to be the case, as theGermans were reported to be in a position to occupy Petrogradwithin &amp;4 hours of making an advance.   The situation,
therefore, was now such that, tf Captain Cromie did not carryoat the dastauction within a short time, he might, when theactual German advance began, not have the men wherewith tocarry out the destruction.The Naval Attache&apos; had added that, in the event of any ac-tion of the Allies in Murmansk, or Archangel, this destructionwould be used as a strong anti-Ally propaganda, on the same lines as the Japanese landing in Vladlvostock, and he furtherrequested that he might be kept informed of the conditions and Allied intentions in the North, to enable him to be in aposition to answer any quest ion concerning Murmansk and Arch-angel which might arise, and to aid him in forming an opinon as to the right moment to carry out any scheme in hand.It was pointed out that I*lr lockhart had stated that M.Trot-zki had agreed to the blowing up of the Russian Fleets in caseof necessity, and it was understood that M. Trotski was makinghis own ar rang amenta ^or &quot;t**i^s*Admiral Hope mentioned that the form of destruction pro-posed by us vas damage, beyond hope of repair, to the main,turbines of the Russian ships.The lap Cabinet were of opinion that it would fee unwise totrust to any less damage than that which entailed the actualsinking of the, ships, and that to do this might mean the folow-ing up of some of the Russian sailors on board, and oonse-quently, if this took place, it would involve a final break with Russia, and the question resolved itself into this,whether, by sinking the Fleet, we should gain or lose more.In this connection it was mentioned that the blowing upof the ships -might result in our losing the services of theCzeoho-Slovak force that was now in Russia, and attention was drawn to telegram 317, from Mr lockhart, in which it was indicated that M. Trotzki, although he had no objection tothe Gzeeho-Siovak forces being sent, to Archangel en route to-
Prance, demanded that they should be disarmed while in transit through Russia, and ^as holding the Vice-Presidentof the Czeoho-Slovak National Council as a hostage for suchdisarmament.As against this, it was pointed&apos; out that the risk of theRussian ships falling into German hands was a grave one.The War Cabinet decided that -The essential thing was to avoid the shipsfalling into German hands* and they there-fore authorised the First Lord of the Ad-jairalty to telegraph to Captain Croatie thathe was to take whatever steps he thought necessary for the purpose, deferring his action as long as possible, subject&apos;to theabove essential racquirement, and, so far aspossible, keeping in touch with Mr lockhart.*       w       *       *       V       *Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,May 37,  1918,

</content>
</cab>
