<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/14/0 images: 138-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
WAR CABINET 444a; Ilinutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing1 Street, S.W., on Thursday,  11th.  July, 1918, at 11.30 a.m.PRESENT.The Prime Minister fin the Chair)It. Hon. the Earl Curzon ofgont/OH9 n.G.,G.C.S.X.,G.C.X.E.It. Hon. A. Bonar law, M.P.It. Hon. G. II. Barnes, M. P.Lieutenant-General the Rt. Hon.J a Co Smut s, X.C.The Rt. Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.THiii FOLLOW IIJG WERE ALSO present. Hon. A. J. Balfour, CM., General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B.,Secretary of State for D-S-0., Chief of the Imperialm Affairs. Staff.^tenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, 1,.C.B............. Secretary.wain Clement Jones.........................     Assistant Secretary.pin I. ]?. Burgia,.........................     Assistant Secretary.
1( THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)S E C R E T .-1   &quot; 5 uffi western front.omoarisonf Alliedod Enemytrength.WAR   CABINET    444-^.DRAFT MINUTES of a Meeting held at 10 downing street, S.W.   , on THURSDAY, JULY 11th, 1918,at 11.30 a.m.With reference to War Cabinet 443, Minute 2, theChief of the Imperial General Staff stated that on March 21the Germans had 82 fresh Divisions, and that to-day they had63, but he calculated that during the last ten days of thismonth, provided no heavy fighting took place, the germans would have a total of 85 fresh Divisions available.    If thenumber of Divisions in the line on the front on wbteh theGermans intended to attack were added to this number, itwould give them a total of 100 to 110 Divisions availablefor an attack.     With this number they could attack on a front of 50 to 60 miles. This was based on the calculationthat allowing for two separate waves of attack they would use in the aggregate roughly two Divisions to a mile. Withregard to the British reserves, the number of Divisions was20, including 5 American Divisions which we could coxurt uponat the eftd of the month.     If we calculated that we had inthe line the same number of Divisions as the Germans on thefront of attack, i.e., 25, that would give us a total of 45Divisions including the Americans.     With regard to theFrench reserves, the Chief of the Imperial General staff stated   that they had about 29 Divisions available.   he added that the whole of the D.A.N. would be gone by the endFrench divisions of the month, and thatJ North of/Beauvaisii   Should the Germans attack on theBritish front, it would take some time for the Frenchreserves to reinforce us at a point as far North as, say,Bethune.     General Wilson said that the assumption thatthe whole weight of the German attack would fall on the
British, was an extreme hypothesis, hut there was no doubtthat the Germans could, if they wished, use all theirfresh Divisions against us.     Questioned as to the warningwe might receive of an attack, General Wilson said thatField-Marshal Sir Douglas Haig hoped to get ahout 48 hoursnotice.     It was pointed out, however, that only on oneprevioud occasion this year had we received warning of the exact front of any big attack.Attention was drawn to the danger that the French,for political reasons, might endeavour to safeguard Parisat grave risk to the British front.General Smuts said that he was very nervous of this possibility, and, in his opinion, the French reserves werebeing moved much too far South, bringing about a distrihu-tion of reserves, as far as the British front was concerned,not dissimilar to that existing before the attack of March21st.The War Cabinet decided that :-(a) The Chief of the Imperial General staff should send the calculations which hehad just given to the War Cabinet, toGeneral Foch, adding that the War Cabinetregarded the situation with anxiety;(b) The Prime Minister should write toM. Clemenceau, enclosing a copy ofGeneral Wilson1s letter to General Foch,pointing out that General Foch was an allied and not merely a French Commander--in-Chief, and that he must treat theAllied interests as a whole, making hisdispositions on this basis and not mainly from the point of view of French interests.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.WJuly 11th, 1918

</content>
</cab>
