<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/14/0 images: 300-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
fr^DOCTJMENl&apos; IS THE PROP BRTY OF HIS gRIMMIG MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT)SEORET-WAR CABINET 495 A.DRAFT MINUTES of a Meeting of file War Cabinet Held at10 Downing Street, S.W. on Friday, 1st November, 1918 ati 12 Noon.IsTRIA.SJaval TermsArmistice.[SSABY TOpilTlNOPLE.(1)    The assistant Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs read to the War Cabinet a telegram vffliieh he had just received from Versailles, giving the Naval terms of armistice with Austria as laid down by the Supreme WarCouncil.    He said that a further telegram indicating the Military terms was to follow.The Deputy Chief of the Haval Staff said that theterms were evidently framed so as to include the surrender of most of the more modem vessels of theAustrian fleet.     A particularly Significant point wasthe surrender by Austria of all German submarines.The Director of Military Intelligence said that,as regards the Military terms of armistice, GeneralDelme Hadcliffe, in a recent telegram, had said that oneof the Austrian parlementaires had stated that thesituation was so graw that Austria would have no altern-ative but to accept any terms the Allies might choose toimpose.The Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff stated thata telegram had been received from our Naval Commander-in chief at Mudros, asking that the attention of the ForeignQffice might be drawn to the extreme importance of sending at once to Constantinople a British statesmanof high standing.
o I-Em Admiral Freemantle then referred to various Austrianmessages \ivhihc had &quot;been intercepted in the Mediterraneanoat i anwhich were to the effect that one ship had hoisted theCroatian Flag, and another ship had made a general signalthat all ships in the Adriatic were to hoist the same Flagat once.RBUCBSIf (2)    Lord Curzon then read out to the Cabinet twoILLBS .telegrams which had been received from Sir Maurice Hanlceyby the Acting Secretary of the War Cabinet (Nos. 1348 &amp;1349, dated October 31, 1918), giving a brief account of thepreliminary Qonferences which had been held at Versaillesprecedent to a meeting of the Supreme War Council (Appendix)The Secretary of State for India referred to the omission in the telegrams of all reference to the german colonies.    The telegram stated that a Memo, of the observ-ations proposed by the Prime Minister had been agreed to on them previous day.    This Memo, said that,  subject to certainqualificationsl the Allied Governments declare their willing--ness to make peace with Germany on the lines proposed by president Wilson.    The first qualification concerned Clause 2lating to the Freedom of the Seas,  and the second referred to thelause which declared that invaded territories must be restored as wellevacuated and freed.    Should there not be some qualification in regarding German Colonies?Mr.  Chamberlain said that he would like to War Cabinet totite the Prime Minister&apos;s special attention to President Wilson&apos;s^rd- point, which dealt with the economic question.     He thought thatI should not bind ourselves to granting most-favoured treatment to^9my nations unless a proviso were added that this must be subject to* obligations to our present Allies in regard to the restoration of1*64 territory.
The Secretary of State for the Colonies saidthat he thought President Wilson&quot;s Third point was expressed in such vague terms as not to debar us from pursuing our proposed economic policy.   Any limitationswhich might be imposed upon us if \^e accepted that point would be greatly magnified in their applicationto the United States herself.    He agreed with Mr.Chamberlain that our representatives in Paris shouldbe warned of the dangers underlying this point.Mr. Chamberlain pointed out that the president had explained that he did not mean this paragraph toconnote any interferance with any other country7s inter-nal policy.   Mr. Chamberlain then read out a draft tele-gram which he suggested the War Cabinet might send toVersaille s.The  Secretary of State for the Colonies enquiredas to what was the exact position as regards t&amp;e german colonies.    The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs had more than once stated in public that in &apos;oe circum-stances could they be restored to Germany.    The DominionGovernments felt so strongly upon this question that hehad telegraphed to them to be prepared to return toEngland at a moment&apos;s notice, if necessary.     He thought the Cabinet were bound to warn our representatives at versailles that, if the captured Colonies were not tobe retained there was likely to be very serious trouble.In his opinion the Government should decide without fur-ther delay the line they really intended to take.    Inhis view it was not honest for us to go to the peaceConference with apparently an open mind in respect ofthe disposal of these captured territories but really
9 qintending to retain them.    It was essential, therefore,that there should be no misunderstanding.The  Secretary of State for India thought that thisformed another important qualification to president Wil-son&apos;s Points,, as there was nothing in those points to preclude the return of the Colonies to Germany.General Smuts said, in regard to the german colonies, our position undoubtedly was very strong, andthis fact had hitherto determined our attitude.    He him-self was opposed to adding another qualification to president Wilson&apos;s Points, but he was altogether infavour of suggesting to the prime Minister that he shouldseize the  opportunity of making our position quite clear.The Assistant Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs also  deprecated adding a further qualification.The more we made it appear that we differed from presi-dent Wilson the more we should play into the^ hands of thewhose interest vras  to sow dissension among one Allies.Germans./ As regards Mr. Chamberlain&apos;s point, he said thathe understood that the President,  in his conception of a league of nations, meant that each member should havean equal economic position in the War.Mr. Chamberlain thought that the French wouldcertainly insist on the most-favoured-nation treatment.After some discussion the War. Cabinet decided  
To approve the desptaeh to Versaillesof the following telegram, includingthe points raised by Mr chamberlain and the Secretary of State for India&quot;Following for Prime Minister.,   Begins.    two points in President Wilson1s declaration and inyour memorandum of observations upon it seem tocall for further notice.    If it is too late toinclude them in agreed Memorandum, War Cabinethope you will consider desirability of makingour views upon them perfectly clear to our Alliesand have them formally placed on record.    Thefirst is ecenomio point.   His Majesty&apos;s Gevern-ment ought not to be committed to grent of&quot;most-favoured nation&quot; treatment to enemy nations which would prevent fulfilment of our obligations to assist in restoration of Allied territories,and prejudice our own economic policy in future.Secondly it would be we&amp;l that our Allies should know that German Colonies will in no circumstances to restored to Germany, and that claims ef ourDominions to certain of them oannot possibly to waived.   Clear reservations on both these points now may prevent misunderstanding later on.Ends.&quot;ITISH EMISSARY 3.     At a later stage the War Cabinet had aR C ON S TAN TIN 0 -s6 short discussion in regard to the desirability of sending a British Emissary to Constantinople and agreed that a representative of weight and experienceshould be sent.The War Cab inet requested Lord Curzon and-Lord R.Cecil to confer as to the appointment of asuitable representative, and to suggest his namefor the approval of the Secretaiy of State forforeign Affairs.O        A *        S2, Whit ehall Ga gardens, S.W.\
CIRCULATE5D TO THE KING AND WAR CABINET.Dccypher.Lord Derby (Paris).October 3ist,  1918.D.4.20 p.rruOctober 31st,  1918.10.10 p.in.No.1348.Secret.Following from Hankey for&apos; Acting Secretary ofWar Cabinet.Begins.Conferences have hitherto been of a preliminary character precedent to meeting of Supreme War Councilto be held this afternoon.On Tuesday and Wednesday important preliminary discussions took place on the subject of President Wilscnfs14 points and on procedure to be adopted as regards Germanand Austrian armistice.As regards Germany it was agreed that proposition of supreme War Council that terms of armistice approved bySupreme War Council should in first instance besent to President Wilson who,  if he agrees, should beinvited not to communicate terms to Germany, but toinform German Government that next step is for them to send a flag of truce to Marshal Foch,  who would be empowered toact on behalf of the Associated Governments.     At the sametime it was agreed that ^resident Wilson should be invitedto communicate to German Government a memorandum ofobservations by Allied Governments on the 14 points.      A/short
short memorandum of observations proposed by Prime minister was yesterday agreed to.     Memorandum states that,  subject tocertain qualifications. Allied Governments declare their willingness to make peace with Government of Germany on termsof peace proposed by President Wilson.      First qualificationconcerns Clause 2 relating to Freedom of the Seas, which Isooen to various interpretations,  some of which AlliedGovernments could not accent.      They must therefore reserve to themselves complete freedom on this subject when they enterinto Peace Conference.      The second qualification relates to president Wilson&apos;s declaration that Invaded territoriesmust be restored, as well as evacuated and freed.      TheAllied Governments feel no doubt ought to he allowed to existas to what this provision, implies.      By   it they understand,compensation will be made by Germany, for all damage done to civilian population of Allies and. their property by land,by sea, and from the air.As regards Austria    It was agreed to submit to supreme war Council that terms of armistice should be communicated byGeneral Diaz on behalf of Associated Governments toproperly accredited Austrian Parlemertaires.      General Diazhas already received e flag of truce, but some doubt existsat present as to whether Austrian envoys are properlyaccredited and this point is being cleared up.Allied Naval Council has submitted terras of armistice with Germany and Austria.      Marshal Foch has submitted freshterms for an armistice with Germany, and Military Representa-tives at Versailles have just submitted terms of an armistice with Austria,  but none of these have as yet been finally approved.      It is generally agreed to be very desirable todeal at once with Austria, and more particularly to insist/in
in the Austrian armistice on right of allies to occupy strategic points in Austria and to use theirrailways,  so as to indicate to Germany the menace to her from Austrian side.
CIRCULATED TO THE KING AND  WAR CABINET.Decypher.Lord Derby (Paris),October 31st, 1918.D.4.15 cm.October 31st,  1918.R.9.30 cm.No.  1349.Secret.Following from Hankey for Acting Secretaryof War Cabinet.      Begins:-In continuation of my telegram No. 1348a somewhat heated discussion took place yesterdayafternoon on the subject of Admiral Calthrope (?s)negotiations for an armistice with Turkey.      Frenchprotested against exclusion of French Rear-Admiralfrom negotiations and insisted that he and ItalianAdmiral must also sign armistice.      Prime Ministerreplied that If this procedure adopted in this instance it must be decided formally at a fullsession of Supreme War Council and that the rulemust be of universal application in all theatresthat all the nations concerned were to sign armistices.On hearing this French agreed to accept the (group undecypherable).

</content>
</cab>
