<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/78/0 images: 25-26</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  October 1955SECRET Copy No. g 4CP. (55) 15718th October, 1955CABINETSPAINNote by the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the ColoniesWith reference to the Foreign Secretary&apos;s Memorandum CP. (55) 147 aboutSpain, I circulate a note setting out opinions on this subject expressed to theColonial Secretary during his recent visit to Gibraltar by the political leaders there.L.Colonial Office, S.W. 1,17th October, 1955.RELATIONS WITH SPAIN:  OPINIONS OF POLITICAL leaders in GIBRALTARPolitical leaders in Gibraltar spoke with strong feeling of the effect of Spanishrestrictions which are being maintained without relaxation and which seriously affect the economy of the Colony. In particular, the refusal to renew permitsinvolves progressive reduction of the essential Spanish labour force which, ifcontinued at present rate, will lead to complete disappearance of this labour forcein a very few years. Much dissatisfaction was expressed at the apparent impotenceof Her Majesty&apos;s Government in the face of these hostile measures. The allegedpolicy of drift has led, in their view, to a serious decline of confidence in Gibraltarin the City, and they maintain it has now become impossible to attract investment in the Colony from that source.2. On the other hand, there was unanimous agreement that any attempt to bargain with Spain over this question by offering support for admittance to theUnited Nations in exchange for removal of discriminations against Gibraltar wouldbe a psychological mistake and would only have a harmful effect. There wasemphatic general support for the view that in the long run the best hope forGibraltar lay in a re-establishment of friendly relations between the UnitedKingdom and Spain and support for Spain&apos;s admittance to United Nations wouldbe one way of fostering this. They emphasised, however, that it would be essentialto couple this with a clear-cut statement of Her Majesty&apos;s Government^ firmintention to maintain sovereignty over Gibraltar. They also considered it was essential to make plain to the Spaniards that there could be no differentiation between Gibraltar and the United Kingdom in any Anglo-Spanish treaties and thatcontinuation of the present discriminatory restrictions against Gibraltar would be inconsistent with any general improvement in Anglo-Spanish relations.48930THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT
PUBLIC RECORD OFFICEReferenceALL ODD  NUMBERS BETWEENFOLIOS   \ARE BLANK AND HAVENOT BEEN COPIED

</content>
</cab>
