<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/78/0 images: 70-75</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.,   November 1955.CONFIDENTIAL-P.P. (55) 1719th November, 1955Copy No. g ^CABINETCOLOMBO PLANNote by the Secretary of State for Foreign affairs circulate for the information of my colleagues a report by Lord Reading onthe recent meeting at Singapore of the Consultative Committee of the ColomboPlan.H. M.Foreign Office, S.W. 1.7th November, 1955.ANNEXCOLOMBO PLAN: MEETING OF THE CONSULTATIVE COMMITTEE,OCTOBER 1955The meeting of the Consultative Committee of the Colombo Plan was heldthis year at Singapore from 17th to 22nd October. It was again a successfulconference. In spite of the fact that there were many newcomers amongst bothMinisters and officials the usual atmosphere of cordiality and informality was fully retained.2. The most important decision was to extend the life of the Plan from june 1957, the end of the six-year period originally fixed, until June 1961, with the reservation that the position should be re-examined at the 1959 meeting of the consultative Committee with a view to considering whether it should be terminatedin 1961 or further prolonged after that date.3. A situation has never yet arisen in which it has become necessary to takea vote, and that admirable precedent was not broken this year.4. Whatever criticisms may sometimes be read in the Press of the scope and scale of the Plan, the basic gratifying fact remains that the Asian membersbelieve in it, are satisfied with its progress and only desire, it to continue, anyhowfor the time being, though they do not lose sight of their ultimate goal of economicself-sufficiency. A feature of this meeting was the entry on to the stage of the peaceful uses of atomic energy as a field in which donor countries were now prepared to help in respect of both capital and technical assistance. The UnitedStates offered in general terms to set up a reactor somewhere in the region for thebenefit of the Asian member countries as a whole; the Canadians confirmed theirgift of one to India; and the United Kingdom agreed to provide vacancies atHarwell for courses in the use of isotopes for medical and agricultural purposes.Though it will probably be some time before most of the countries concerned are49039
able to take practical advantage of the opportunities thus provided, the making ofthese various offers undoubtedly had a stimulating effect upon Asian &quot; morale.&quot;5. Our own announcement that we were substantially increasing our contribution towards technical assistance was very well received.6. One decision which I personally regret was that Ministers should be free to give their main speeches to the Press immediately after they had spoken. while this only slightly affected the tone of the speeches at Singapore, we must try to revert at subsequent meetings to the former rule of privacy if we are to preserve the free and friendly character of the debates.7. It was a happy coincidence for the newly-elected Singapore Governmentthat it had been decided to hold this year&apos;s meeting there. They certainly madeevery possible effort to ensure the efficiency of the arrangements and the comfortof the delegates. Their expenditure as hosts amounted to nearly  40,000, but theyseemed to regard it as money well spent. The Victoria Memorial Hall was an excellent setting for the conference, though the acoustics were poor and notimproved by the failure of many delegates to make proper use of their microphones.The preliminary stages proved a heavy tax upon the Singapore officials and theywould readily agree that the situation was only saved from a breakdown by the help that the very competent and experienced members of the United Kingdomofficial delegation were fortunately able to give.8. Mr. Marshall, the Chief Minister of Singapore, presided over theconference and had a great personal success. He is quite a newcomer to politicseven in Singapore and had certainly had no experience of so high-powered ameeting. He was in considerable trepidation at the prospect of occupying the chair at it, but he soon showed himself calm, tactful, courteous and decisive and thecompliments paid to him on the last day were thoroughly well earned. Hisperformance was all the more commendable as he was throughout the week of theconference beset by urgent and anxious problems arising out of the local politicalsituation and by threats to his own position as Chief Minister. Mr. Lim Yew Hock,the Minister of Labour, who only a few months ago was a clerk in Mr. Marshall&apos;slaw office, deputised one afternoon in Mr. Marshall&apos;s obligatory absence and roseequally to the occasion.9. The delegations of Singapore, the Federation of Malaya, North borneo and Sarawak were as usual attached to the United Kingdom delegation, but in viewof the altered status of the first two I insisted upon their acting in the conferenceitself as independent units, though I am glad to think that we were of veryconsiderable use to them behind the scenes. They came to us constantly for guidance and were very grateful for the ready response. They took a useful partin the discussions and I feel that it had a salutary effect on a number of other delegations, not excluding the Americans, to see such effective examples of&quot; colonialism &quot; in action.10. It was obviously very instructive too for the Asians to see Singapore;many of them in private conversation contrasted rather wistfully the conditions intheir own countries with Singapore&apos;s clean streets, lack of flies and absence ofbeggars.11. The diversity of interests embraced by the Colombo Plan was wellillustrated by the variety of offices held by heads of delegation in their respective governments. Eight were drawn from Foreign Ministries and there were othersfrom Finance, Economics, Industry and Commerce, Agriculture and Planning,whilst the United States delegation was led by Mr. Hollister, the Chief of theInternational Co-operation Administration.12. There were still far too many social functions, but perhaps fewer took theform of cocktail parties, a very welcome relief. Several delegations cheated, asafter agreeing with our initiative to cut out cocktail parties, they either promotedor connived at the giving of entertainments, not by the delegation itself but by theirConsuls-General or other permanent representatives in Singapore. TheCeylonese delegate blandly broke the agreement by giving a cocktail party on theopening day.13. The efficiency of the United Kingdom delegation did not suffer in any way from the fact that I was the only member of it who had ever attended a previous
November 4, 1955.meeting. The Economic Secretary to the Treasury introduced the United Kingdomcountry chapter in a lucid, concise and effective speech, which was obviously heardwith keen interest. Mr. William Armstrong of the Treasury led the officialdelegation with great skill and discretion and it was obvious to me on my arrivalthat he and his colleagues had established the most cordial relationship with allother delegations, which was maintained and even increased during the ministerial meeting. I received from many delegations expressions of gratitude for theirhelpfulness and understanding and I am personally most deeply obliged to themfor their co-operation and for the diligence and enthusiasm with which theyapplied themselves to their novel tasks. I hope that whoever may lead the UnitedKingdom delegation to the 1956 meeting in New Zealand may have the benefit ofthe experience gained this year by substantially the same team.READING.

November 4, 1955.meeting. The Economic Secretary to the Treasury introduced the United Kingdomcountry chapter in a lucid, concise and effective speech, which was obviously heardwith keen interest. Mr. William Armstrong of the Treasury led the officialdelegation with great skill and discretion and it was obvious to me on my arrivalthat he and his colleagues had established the most cordial relationship with allother delegations, which was maintained and even increased during the ministerial meeting. I received from many delegations expressions of gratitude for theirhelpfulness and understanding and I am personally most deeply obliged to themfor their co-operation and for the diligence and enthusiasm with which theyapplied themselves to their novel tasks. I hope that whoever may lead the UnitedKingdom delegation to the 1956 meeting in New Zealand may have the benefit ofthe experience gained this year by substantially the same team.READING.


</content>
</cab>
