<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/78/0 images: 127-132</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
document is the property of her britannic  majesty&apos;s   governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1955CONFIDENTIALCP. (55) 17617th November, 1955CABINETIMPRESSIONS OF MY COMMONWEALTH TOURMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Commonwealth relations my colleagues have so much to read that I hesitate to add to the quantity. Thisis a short sketch of my main impressions of the Commonwealth countries I visited.I begin with India and Pakistan because it is there that the situation is most fluidand challenging.. H.Commonwealth Relations Office, S.W. 1,15th November, 1955.India, Pakistan and CeylonBefore I left England representatives of British business operating in India and pakistan expressed real apprehensions as to their ability to carry on. I tried toestimate how far their fears were justified.2. All three countries are applying policies of nationalism which means,among other things, that they insist that an increasing number of the natives of thecountry must be employed in every business.3. This must be accepted. So far the restrictions are not being appliedonerously and I was assured by Ministers that all that they wanted was to besure that foreign firms would give the bright boy the chance to work through tothe highest posts.4. It is difficult to quarrel with that if the practice is not extended too far beyond its present limits.5. I could find no ill-will in Pakistan I am more doubtful about Ceylon towards British business and arrangements to accommodate their requirementsseem to be reasonable.6% In Pakistan there is an acute shortage of foreign exchange and that, coupled with widespread incompetence in administration, particularly in the issue of importlicences, is continually leading to situations which are exasperating and mean realloss and hardship to industries. The Government are now very wisely going slowon new industrialisation and are concentrating resources on improving the situation of those industries which earn wealth from overseas. This will strengthen thecountry&apos;s economy. They are also reviewing the import licensing system. Thereare, too, good prospects ahead in Pakistani development programme, but latelyour prices have compared adversely with Germany and others who are making a real effort to get a footing in the country. By and large I thought that the business community with the constant help of the High Commission in ironing out frustrationought to be able to carry on.49086 - B&quot;Copy No. go
7. I cannot feel so confident about India. All and sundry assured me they wanted British capital and skill but their financial policies carried out in the nameof Socialism may well make it impossible to recruit British people to live and make their careers in India. There is strong pressure throughout the Congress Partyto apply ceilings on salaries and to tax perquisites generally including passageallowances to Europe. All this is proposed in the name of equality and would apply to Indians but the result is sharp discrimination against foreigners whosecircumstances are so different. .    .8. The Finance Minister understands the adverse effect such measures willhave and with great courage has tempered the wind by including clauses in theFinance Bill and Companies Act which permit elasticity in administration. Butthe theoretical Socialists among Ministers continue to make headway and theyare the majority.9. The High Commissioner is considering the most effective ways of approaching the Indian Government so that they may clearly understand the damage they may do b) any further increases in personal taxation, but the Britishbusiness community, especially the smaller firms, have reason for their fears.10. This lack of confidence is a pity because there are great opportunitiesin the country&apos;s development. The best hope is that the Government will seethemselves falling so far short in the financing of the second Five-Year Plan thatthey will realise in time that they must mobilise and attract all the help they can get from abroad.11. There is one broad political tendency which is disquieting India is clearlycarrying on a flirtation with Russia. The papers are full of what Russian capital and technical skill can do to promote Indian expansion and development and theRussians are responding with some good work.12. The Prime Minister of Pakistan gave me a warning that people, even inhis country, were beginning to ask what there is for them in membership of theCommonwealth and alliance with the West. Might it not be better, like Nehruand Nasser and Daud to play off one against the other and pocket the gains from both sides?13. Of course, Chaudhri Mohamad Ali has an interest to declare. But ifthe United Kingdom can be seen to support Pakistan in her reasonable requests for diplomatic aid in Afghanistan and Gwadar, and if we can get down to thebusiness of practical planning with her and her Muslim associates in the BaghdadPact, we may correct a tendency which could be exceedingly dangerous and loseus our one reliable military ally in the Sub-Continent and in the East.14. Clearly impressions gained in a three weeks&apos; tour cannot be other thansuperficial. But my feeling is that Pakistan, despite the Prime Ministers warning,will be completely with us, but that India, while unlikely to leave theCommonwealth, has little positive enthusiasm for it and that we shall have towork very hard to keep her eyes turned towards the West.15 We have some good cards of entry: the goodwill of the Services, theleaning of the Indians towards the West which they have inherited from theBritish although there is a slow reversion to type; their genuine dislike of theSoviet political system; their need for financial and technical help in reaching their development targets. This indeed is the most promising opening. Nothing would do more to convince the Indian Government of our goodwill towards their development Plan than our agreement to build their new steel plant on reasonableterms. It is looked upon by them as a test case.16. If within the next year or so British businessmen can convince IndianMinisters that the private investor and the enterprising industrialist areindispensable to the fulfilment of their programmes, then we shall retain a small but vigorous British population in India which will have a beneficial influence and help to keep if not their affections at least their interest in the western world.17. America, with all her money and strength, makes no headway in winningtheir confidence. In so far as any country from the West can exercise influence thetask of holding them lies upon us.
18. Kashmir bedevils relations between India and Pakistan; and feeling inthe latter is rising. They have learnt the hunger strike and satyagraha tacticsfrom India; and will use them. The sequence of events is likely to be a(representative) meeting called by the Pakistan Prime Minister to decide thecountry&apos;s policy; a meeting with Nehru which Mohamad Ali thinks will fail; afresh appeal to the Security Council; and, if that renews the suggestion for a plebiscite, a possible appeal to the United Kingdom and Commonwealth to arrangeways and means of seeing it through.. 19. There is nothing to report about Ceylon. As long as the present government survives they will I believe retain their allegiance to the Crown.20. There is clear evidence that in all three countries the use of the english language is deteriorating. If the tendency continues our general influence and our commercial interest will suffer. The British Council &quot;is effective, and I wasimpressed by its efficiency particularly so in Karachi and Bombay.21. A few more men and women capable of instructing teachers of Englishwould pay a handsome dividend.New Zealand.22. I had not realised until I saw it the extraordinary richness of NewZealand&apos;s grass lands. Farming is at a high standard and increasingly scientific.Much use is made, for instance on the sheep pastures of top dressing from the airwith super-phosphates and any chemical elements in which the soil is deficient.The existing areas in cultivation and grazing will show a steadily increasing outputalthough shortage of labour on the land will be a limiting factor until there is arecession in secondary industry and unemployment in the towns.23. There is a large area of potential sheep land still under native bush andreclamation is proceeding fast. The trees and scrub are cleared and within threeyears the grass is sufficient to carry two or three sheep to the acre.24. From improvement of existing grassland and reclamation, New Zealandwill shortly have a larger exportable surplus of wool and mutton and, to a lesser extent, milk products and butter and cheese.25. Industrially, the island is not so well placed. There is coal, and powercan be generated from rivers and geo-thermal steam. One real asset is timber andits availability for conversion into paper and pulp, ft has been found that on the previously wasted acres of pumice land conifers will grow in profusion. As soonas the forest is cleared natural regeneration clothes it with thick woodland. Thefirst large processing plant is about to come into production and pulp, paper,plaster-board and the like will soon be a considerable dollar saver and will laterprovide an increasing income from overseas. There should be a good return on british capital invested in this enterprise.26. There is an attempt, particularly in Auckland which is a rapidly growingcity, to establish secondary industries. This is partly pride. The New Zealanderlikes to think that what others can do he can do as well, but it is also to try andsave foreign exchange and reduce the effect of isolation in a future war. some industries will establish themselves and will be permanent assets but those whichemploy a lot of labour cannot be really economic.27. On top of high wages ruling in war time, the wage structure was furtherdistorted by the boom in wool which accompanied American stockpiling in Korea.On top of that again, the Government has pursued an all-out programme ofbuilding under the broad heading of the &quot; Welfare State &quot; so that there has been an unrestrained scramble for labour and materials. Wages are very high and theoutput from industries, other than those with great natural advantages such aspaper and food processing, cannot be competitive in world markets. meanwhile the import bill rises.28.  If primary produce prices hold and markets can be extended intoIndonesia, Malaya and China, the balance of payments may not deteriorate too far or too fast but. it is doubtful if the people understand the precarious positionand the Government show little inclination to make them face up to realities.49086 - . ... B 2
)Years of &quot; Welfare State &quot; and prosperity have created an atmosphere of a giantspree which will last for ever. The saving factors in the situation are that thebalance of payment difficulties could easily be overcome if a little more work was done and a little less pressure put on the available labour and materials by publicworks activities of the &quot; State.&quot; I fear they may have to learn the hard way butthe country is so naturally rich and the New Zeaianders are fundamentally suchsteady prudent people that I feel they would not shirk the measures necessary tomeet the situation, if they were given a lead.; 29. Everyone is strongly pro-British. They want British immigrants and Iwas constantly assured that they only accepted American imports because of difficulty over delivery dates from British firms. The only point at whichenthusiasm stops short at all levels is at adequate payment towards defence. social welfare always wins.Australia30. The outlook in Australia is far more dynamic. Everyone thinks andtalks in terms of expansion and development while the need to populate Australiawith Europeans, preferably British, so as to be able to resist expansion from Asiais everywhere accepted as the only possible policy to pursue. Although the pressures on the economy from such a full-blooded programme are clear I did not meet a single Australian who questioned its necessity.31. The economy of the country rests, as the people say, &quot;on the sheep&apos;sback &quot; and the healthiness of balance of payments depends on wool maintainingits price in world markets.32. Within a comparatively short time it would be possible to double theoutput from existing farms so effective is the scientific treatment of pastures whichhave until now been largely left to nature. There is quite a lot of improvementtaking place but there is some hesitancy apparent, as unless new markets can be exploited a greatly increased wool crop would lower the price. There is someopening up of land but the pace of it is limited by the cost of land, the lackof communication and the need for irrigation. If present progress is slow the plans for future increase in land under cultivation are ambitious.33. Sugar, thanks to the Commonwealth Sugar Agreement, is profitable butwheat and fruit (fresh and canned) are running into difficulties because of surpluselsewhere and the cost of labour in cultivation and harvesting. Plentiful andreadily accessible supplies of coal and iron-ore of a high grade easily mined support a steel industry which can produce well below world prices. All the output (exceptfor a small export to New Zealand) is internally consumed and is well below whatis needed.   A rapidly expanding engineering industry is being created.34. The most spectacular expansion is in secondary industries which arespringing up everywhere like mushrooms. This is part of the deliberate policy towhich I referred of making Australia secure and increasingly self-supporting.The process is this: to reinforce a high birth rate with an immigration programme of125,000 Europeans a year, keeping the annual increase of population at 3 per cent,or more and then to attract new industries to supply the new demands. Thepolicy is meeting with phenomenal success. A great variety of firms areestablishing themselves and factories are being erected everywhere. Even withthe high rate of increase in population there is an acute shortage of labour andthe products seem to reach a reasonable standard of efficiency. Everything wouldseem to be set fair in the long run: they are probably right to invest in men andmachines and there are many projects which look very attractive for the foreigninvestor. But in the short run there are certain adverse factors to which one cannotturn a blind eye:  (i) The average earnings throughout manufacturing industry and the public services are about  20 a week. There is a 40-hour week which is notworked fully and the unions are irresponsible. So long as theseconditions persist it will be impossible for Australia to compete at allin export markets with manufactured goods except where they have great material advantages in accessible raw materials. They should,for example, be able to build up a good export trade in steel but jioattempt is made to do so.
(ii) The servicing of the public is already behindhand. One-third of the city of Sydney has no sewerage and half of Brisbane is in a similar position.On the top of that every immigrant family has to be catered for withhouse, school, hospital and the like so that pressure on labour and materials and consumer goods is all the time being intensified.35. So long as these conditions persist and until the people are willing to workharder or moderate their wage demands the country will balance precariously onthe edge of inflation and will be in perpetual trouble with its overseas account.The people have so clear an idea of the social and economic goal which they meanto reach that they may take the necessary action in time but it is probable thatthey will have to be taught a sharp lesson. The hope is that it will be short induration. If wool prices fall the general position would deteriorate quickly.Happily they seem to be firm and if they were to rise, which is by no meansimpossible, the position would be greatly eased.36. I was particularly on the watch to discover whether Australian dependence on American military support in the Pacific and the influx of American capital isadversely affecting the Australian outlook towards Great Britain.37. To-day the answer is that it is not. But with the increasing numberof immigrants from Europe, the strategic dependence on the United States and the growing interest of American business in Australian prospects there is a widespreadfear that our two countries may gradually drift apart.38. The Australian regards that possibility as nothing short of a tragedyand there is an insistent demand for more British immigrants (only 33 per cent,of the total come from the United Kingdom) and more British capital and the most effective British representation at all levels.39. In the particular field of security Government circles clearly set great value on A.N.Z.U.S. They would like to see the United Kingdom associatedwith it but they will do nothing which might conceivably upset the Americans.They are disappointed at the Americans&apos; recent refusal to discuss detailed plans for the defence of South-East Asia and think that they have been misled, but theirprotests, if any, will be gentle.40. My colleagues are aware of certain tentative proposals put to me byMr. Menzies for associating the Americans with A.N.Z.A.M. I found a generalreadiness to agree that A.N.Z.A.M. is valuable and a ready acceptance of ourassurances of the part we mean to play in the defence of Malaya among all ministers, with the unfortunate exception of Sir Philip McBride, the Minister ofDefence.41. Politically the country is unsettled because they are never free fromelections. Elections to the Federal Parliament and to both Houses of the StateParliaments mean that politics are always in the newspapers and always on theair. The State Parliaments, irrespective of which party is in power, spend their time roundly abusing the Federal Parliament and Federal Ministers who controltaxation.42. This situation makes it extremely difficult to govern effectively from thecentre especially as the State Governments have enough powers to baulk the objectives of Federal Legislation when they feel so inclined. The people musthave an acute political sense and an extraordinary balance to work the systemat all.43. Visits from British Ministers are very welcome; the more Ministers that can go, at well-spaced intervals, the more harmonious our relations will be. Thisis equally true of New Zealand.44. I shall hope to discuss in more detail matters involving Defence, UnitedKingdom representation in Australia, the prospects for British industry, deliverydates and the quality of British-exported goods and migration with those of mycolleagues most closely concerned.


</content>
</cab>
