<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/20/8 images: 58-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
wAR ; O^BiMETMINISTRY OF&apos; SUPPLY LABOUR PJQinREMEMTS,Memorandum ^1*     The agreed, statement of the facts as to the supply of women for the filling Factories (W.P..G. (4-1)136) shows that the immediate demand for womenis 3*700 a week,     I understand, that the corresponding agreed demands for* skilled men&apos; and 1 other.menT are 80 a week and 600 a week respectively.Expressed as   short-term&apos;1 demandsa which 1 gather are the accumulated demandsup to the end of the year, these amount to 400 skilled men, 3j000 other menand 18,500 women.2*     As accumulated demands up to the end of the year T accept the remainingfigures in the Annex to the Minister of Supply&apos;s paper (\7.P* (41 )278)*The total &quot;short term&quot; demands ccme to 4?865 skilled men, 23,050 other menand 39*000 women*3,   - The agreed statement of facts (lT.P6G4 (41 )13^) shows that as a percentage of average strength over the 8 weeks ending November 1stthere was a wastage rate for women of 0a75/i per week - about the same as fora large sample of Ministry of Supply coFrferjy&amp;tors in the Engineering and allied. Trades.     Having regard to the position of the Filling factories and the difficulties of travelling., this is in my view a low rate of wastageand represents a satisfactory position.     I understand that the agreed rateof wastage at Swynnerton is only 0,57/So     It is quite misleading to take the wastage as a percentage of intake - it must be taken as a percentage of totalstrength1 to get a correct picture;   also the wastage at Swynnerton duringthe weeks to which the Minister of Supply refers was, I understand, considerablyheavier.than usual there.4*     As regards the position generally, the intake of women into some of theR.0.Fs** e, go, Ghorley, Kirkby, Rislcy and Swynnerton, has been falling inrecent weeks;   for others the intake has been maintained and even increased.The falling;off at certain factories is a reflection of the increasingly difficult man-power situation.     On the other hand, last month theregistrations of women were speeded up to an age-group a fortnight and thenumber cf women being placed in the Yfomen* s Services and in industry as aresult of interviews under the Registration Order is increasing steadily andhas now reached 10,000 a week.5*    As to the suggestion that certain factories have not had their requirements fully met because I have not been ruthless enoughs I havedeliberately adopted a policy of trying to obtain the women required by voluntarymethods so far as possible, only &quot;issuing directions&quot; when necessary,     Xn my view any more ruthless use of   my powers in respect of women might have produced a revulsion of feeling and might not have been supported either bythe Appeal Boards (to whom persons &quot;directed&quot; can appeal) or by the Courts.I have been using my powers of direction increasingly and I think the time has now arrived when they oan be issued still more freely,     I am accordinglyproposing to issue an instruction to my Local Offices as in the Appendixannexed.     I would propose to announce this in the House in the course of theforthcoming man-power debate.This will make the position clear to all concerned, including the vromenthemselves, the employers from whom women will, have to be taken and theemployers to whom they will be sent.     Any consequent representations ororitioisms in the House will have to be sternly faoed, and in view of this I wish to call the special attention of my colleagues to the matter before Itako action.,24th November, 1941. E.B.SECRET. TO BE ifFPjUNDER LOOK AND K Y.^PJ41)28!5- .        nn^uwted that special care may be taken to -j q- tMUW the secrecy of this document. --Ic424th November, 1941.
APPENDjDC.PISTRUCTION ON TON POWER.1*    Notra-thstanding the progress made recently under the Registrationfor Employment Order the numbers of women required for the increasedprogramme of vital war work are not being obtained fast enoughs     Largenumbers of vacancies, for example, at aero-engine work and in the filling factories are not being filled.2*     The Minister has therefore decided that the time has come forintensifying (a) the pace at which women are moved to vital war work under the Registration for Employment Orler^ and (b) the firmness of decision ^in requiring women to transfers er*     He has accordingly instructed that thefollowing developments of present practice should be put into effect immediately a(i) Representations by employers against the removal of their workersmust be.rejected unless the Local Office is satisfied either thatthe woman has special qualifications which are being properlyutilised in the national effort or that she occupies a pivotal- position in the employees establishment,,    Hardship to the employer is not a ground for retention,f&apos;,&apos;/) (ii) The present practice of postponing cases for a second interview when , i the woman cannot make up-her mind at the first interview should not normally be followed,     wherever possible women must be informedwhen first interyiewed of. the specific employment or training into which it is proposed to place them if they are not prepared to 3oinone of the Women1s Services,    Where? howevers the InterviewingOfficer is satisfied that a more satisfactory conclusion is likelyto be reached by allowing the woman a few days for consideration ,this may be done (sec M,L,Cire*136/50, Appendix.I).(iii) Where at the first interview a woman who does not volunteer for oneof the Services is unwilling to go into the employment or training for which sho is considered to bo available and suitable, directionsshould be issued forthwith.    She.must be regarded as mobile unless-(a) Sho is the wife of a man s orvittg in the ikrmed Forces orthe Merchant Navy;(b) is a married women with household responsibilities!(c) there is doubt and the case needs to be referred to aWerners Panel,. .The fact that night work is involved should not prevent theissue of a direction,(iv) The rate of interviewing under the Registration for Employment Ordermust be increased to at least 50,000 a week and maintained at leastat that levels    To enable this to be done Headquarters will make arrangements under which Local Offices will call, for interview th.6remaining,categories of women, (including those in GovernmentDepartments) who are in the age groups 20-25 and not at present in.war industries^     Hjistructions on this development will follow as soonas arrangements have been made centrally.     Women with children under14- will remain exempt from interview,3*    Those developments in policy will be stated publicly and the Minister rashesoil officers to understand that in carrying out his instructions thoy will be fully supported by Headquarters,    While, therefore, all interviews, both withthe women and with their employers, should be conducted with scrupulouscourtesy, there should be absolute firmness of decisions and promptness in giving off ect to them,4*    Consequential amendments to existing instructions will follow,H.Q.805-75 K,K*.    -       , 2* .



</content>
</cab>
