<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/59/20 images: 218-221</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
( 3 &apos; OciTHIS DOCUMENT ISIS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   December 1944.   j103try r*TOP secret copy No.W.P. (44) 720.11th December, 1944.WAR CABINET.india the CONSTITUTIONAL POSITION.Report by the India Committee.WE have considered the Viceroy&apos;s proposals for a constitutional move set outin the enclosures to W.P. (44) 684.2. Those proposals contemplate the establishment in the near future, andin advance of any further steps towards a settlement of the constitutional issue,of a transitional government at the Centre, representative of the main political parties, and functioning within the framework of the present constitution. Asa preparatory step, a conference of leaders would be called together to frameagreed proposals for the composition of the transitional government, and toconsider how best to re-establish popular governments in the Section 93 provinces.3. The Viceroy attaches great importance to an early move and states that&quot;it is not my opinion alone, but that of the Commander-in-Chief, the HomeMember and the eleven governors that an early move is necessary.&quot; He asks that,if the War Cabinet are not prepared to accept his proposals, he should be allowedto visit this country to urge them personally.4. We note, in the first place, that these proposals are substantially identical with those put forward by the Viceroy, before he assumed office, in September 1943.These proposals were not at that time accepted by the War Cabinet, though itwas recorded that it was, of course, open to the Viceroy at any time to submit recommendations to the War Cabinet if he thought the moment was opportune for taking some further step which would assist a solution of the constitutional problem. We know of no change since then in the Indian situation which would render these proposals acceptable at the present time. Furthermore, the degree of support which the Viceroy&apos;s telegram at first reading seemed to suggest, on further examination, appears to us to be for some new initiative rather than theViceroy&apos;s specific proposals.5. The views of all the members of the Committee are wholly adverse to theViceroy&apos;s proposals, although the Minister of Aircraft Production and theSecretary of State for India are not prepared to come to a final decision until there has been an opportunity for the Viceroy to visit this country and explain the reason why he and his advisers consider that circumstances are nowpropitious for putting forward such proposals.6. The Viceroy, when he submitted these proposals to the Secretary ofState in September 1944, took the view that &apos;&apos; some positive move should be madeby His Majesty&apos;s Government as soon as possible.&quot; But he now agrees that thematter is much less urgent. Sir Tej Sapru has convoked a conference ofprominent political personages in India, and we are agreed that any action must await the outcome of the deliberations of that body. If, in fact, it produces ascheme which is sufficiently realistic to merit consideration, that will ease the[28796]
position. If, as we are inclined to anticipate, nothing constructive results fromits discussions, future policy can best be considered in the light of the resultingsituation.7. In these circumstances we are disposed to suggest that, while some replymust be sent to the Viceroy, all that need be said to him at this stage is that,while His Majesty&apos;s Government note the consensus of opinion to which he hasreferred, they are of opinion that, before any proposals on the lines which he has put forward gain currency, it is very desirable that there should be a discussionwith him here in London, and that the best time for such discussion would bewhen the outcome of Sir T. B. Sapru&apos;s discussions is known.8. We attach considerable importance to nothing being done which would lead to the Viceroy&apos;s proposals being discussed in a wide circle in India; andfor this reason, and for this reason only, we have rejected a suggestion that theviews of the eleven Provincial Governors on the Viceroy&apos;s proposals should becalled for in writing.9. In suggesting that the Viceroy might pay a visit to this country we areinfluenced by the great importance which he clearly attaches to the acceptance ofhis proposals, and by the misrepresentation to which a refusal to hear him personally, if followed by his resignation, might give rise; and by the injury whichthis might do to relations between Great Britain and India, as well as in the widerinternational sphere.10. Pending the report of Sir Tej Sapru&apos;s committee, we think there wouldbe advantage in a stocktaking by Ministers in London of the Indian position,designed to set out (i) The precise commitments which we have entered into (in particular werepudiate the view implicit in the Viceroy&apos;s correspondence that there. are pledges which we have failed so far to honour or contemplatedishonouring).(ii) The practicability of a different approach to the solution of the Indianproblem.Discussion disclosed that the opinion was generally held that the attempt toapply the British constitutional system to the Central Government in the entirely different circumstances of India was wrong, and that there would be considerable advantage if a technical and non-committal examination of possible alternativescould be made. The point was also taken that the application of democratic principles to countries with serious minority problems had never been reallyexamined. Some members of the Committee held that it would be advantageousif this problem could be considered in its general aspects, and without specific reference to India.(Signed) C. R. ATTLEE(On behalf of the Committee).11th December, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
