<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/4/41 images: 558-573</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C R E T.40)  11.COPY no war CABINETSTOPPAGE OF ALL SUPPLIES OF IRON ORE TO GERMANYPROM THE NORTHERN SWEDISH FIELDS,Memorandum by the Minister of Economic Warfare.&apos;1. Since the outbreak of war,  a number of papers havebeen circulated by other authorities as well as by theMinistry of Economic Warfare, dealing witn Germany&apos;s ironsituation in war under different hypotheses0      In some ofthem the calculations have been based merely on the weights Qf iron ore involved;    in others, upon the ironcontent of the ores,      Since the iron content differswidely between the 29% of the average Luxemburg ore, andthe 61^j of the northern Swedish ores,  figures based upon ironcontent present by far the more accurate picture.2. But in the metallurgy of iron, it is not only theiron content of the ore which is of importance.      Thepresence of other substances, or their absence, governs thequantity of iron which can be extracted from the ores aswell as the quality of steel which can be pro duced and alsothe processes required to produce it.      One of these othersubstances, of particular importance to Germany,  isphosphorus, since the Bessemer process upon which theGerman steel output largely depends,  demands an ore, oradmixture of ores, which contain an appropriate proportionof phosphorus to iron,  sulphur and other chemicalconstituents.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK  AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.

3. Most of the ores available to Germany^.fr-om domesticdeposits or from adjacent neutral countries,  are of lowphosphorus content.      Even the Luxemburg ores which containO0 6/0 phosphorus are usually mixed in Germany with thehigher quality ores from North Sweden which contain 1% or over, and the post-1919 German steel industry has largelybeen built up with the utilisation of these particularores in view04, Thus, the greater part of the northern Swedish oresare not only of high iron content, which is important initself, hut also of high phosphorus content, which makesthem far more important to Germany, so that the denial ofthem, failing an alternative supply,  rich in phosphorus aswell as in iron, would have a much more depressing effecton the output of the German steel industry than is apparently revealed by calculations based on the mere ironcontent of the ores concernedc50 It is not possible to estimate statistically theadditional loss bo German steel output which would beoccasioned by a serious shortage of ores rich in phosphorus.It is a matter of practice rather than theory,  and there isno precedent to go upon&amp;      There is, however, no doubt thata considerable effect would be produced, over and above that due to the mere loss of the iron content of the ores.Some authorities suggest that this effect might exceed allexpectationso      Among these is understood to be HerrFritz Thyssen,  the well-known German steel manufacturer.6. However,  even if it he impossible to take fully intoaccount the effect on German steel output of the loss of highphosphorus ores,  it is possible to consider statistically theloss in terms of iron Vn-i,ev Germany would suffer if deniedall imports from the northern Swedish fields, with the

assurance that the actual loss incurred by Germany would,in practice, be greater, failing an adequate alternativesupply of phosphoric ores.7o As a direct result of the war, Germany has lostsources of supply of iron ore which helped to supply her in1938, e0go France, Spain, Newfoundland and other countires overseas,.      On the other hand, she has somewhat increasedher domestic production,,      The position is shown in thefollowing table :-German Supplies of Iron Ore(in terms of iran content^1938. First year of war&quot;(estimates).Million tonsoDomestic resources:-Old JRsicn 000*00000   3o 15jri.    S &quot;fc 3? X cl    eoooooooooo o 8Chechoslovakia *o o *    06PoIgLXIcI 00000 oooooco    o S *i 4o 8 6e 0Xmj)oz*&quot;tS    O  O O O O O O O O o o o o o o o o o -L lp O (3p 3TO i** &amp; 1    ooooooooco 16 q  1 ISo 88. The 608 million tons of iron contained in theestimated German imports of iron ore in the first year ofwar are made up as under and take into account the actualrate of-supply to Germany since September 1st, 1939. and subsequent agreements   signed between the belligerents and neutral countries involved, as well as relevant factsconcerning the rate of output of ore at the mines.Million tons.From North Sweden 0 *.*.***. 4 402Rest of Sweden O**.oooooooco 1*no rway . o.... o ************** *&apos;.PLuxexaburg . o. * * * o *********** * 35Other sources 00...... .**ooo o 25Total .*..*********** &apos;&apos;,* 6* 8

9- It remains to be seen how Germany might increase hersupply of iron ore from sources other than North Sweden.She has a limited supply of scrap and at the start of thewar had a small stock of ore.      Once these are exhaustedher supplies will depend chiefly upon the strategic situation,and it  is first   of all assumed that the stoppage ofsupplies from North Sweden has been caused by the occu-pation of the mines there by an Allied Force, and that theAllied Navies are in control of Narvik and norwegian territorial waters in the vicinity.10;       Norway.In the above situation, Germany should get nosupplies or iron ore from Norway at all, since the mines aresituation north of Narvik, and shipments should be inter-cepted by the British Naval Forces.      Germany would there-fore lose the *5 million tons of iron content which she isalready credited with obtaining from Norwegian ore.11.       Rest of Sweden.The absolute maximum output from Sweden, less thenorthern fields, is estimated at ore with a 3 million tonsiron content.      Of this Germany is at present obtaining1.5 million tons and Swedish Industry consumes the remainder.If, therefore, Germany is materially to increase her intakefrom this source, she must apparently not only invadeSweden but force the Swedes to shut down their own ironand steel  industry and compel Swedish labour to workextremely hard in German interests.      It is therefore quite possible that in the assumed situation Germany would getless rather than more iron from the rest of Sweden.

12.    Luxemburg.Luxemburg iron ere is of low iron and inadequatephosphorus content.     The total iron content of theannual rcAse is about 1.5 million tons, of which Germanygets at present about 350-002 tons and which couldapparently only be increased by the German invasion of thecountry.     Even so, not only would Germany have to capture the iron workings intact. but would seemingly have to driveback the Allies from their present fortification lines,since the southern Luxemburg iron fields are withinartillery range.13-    Other Sources.The other sources from which Germany is at presentdrawing relatively small quantities of iron ore areSwitzerland, Greece and Yugoslavia.      There is no reasonto suppose that the quantities drawn from these sourceswould be, or in fact could be, greatly increased.There remains the possibility of Germany obtaining supplies from the U.S.S.R., where there are certain oresof high phosphoric content.     The limiting factor is thattho present Russian production barely suffices to coverdomestic demand, and the difficulty of transporting Russianores to Germany will be considerable.      It is reported thatGermany is now negotiating with the U.S-S.R. for anannual delivery of 2 million tons of ore, which would yield something under one million tons of iron.    The ore,of which samples have been recently analysed at theWitkowice Works, is described by the German analysts asbeing the poorest, apart from its phosphorus content, thatthey have ever seen.

Prom the foregoing, therefore,  it is concluded that:-(a) if Germany were denied all imports of iron ore from the northern Swedish field, Germaniron and steel output would,,  in practice,he reduced further than is indicated bystatistical calculations of the iron content of the ores concerned owing to the non-availability of substitute ores of highphosphorus content *(b) Assuming that  the stoppage included naval action in Norwegian Territorial waters,Germany should lose in addition all supplies from ITorway; since the mines are situatednorth of Narviku(c) By the invasion of Sweden, Germany would riskgetting less iron from the central mines than she is now getting,(d) By the invasion of Liixemburg, Germany mightget some additional supplies of low grade lowphosphorus ore3 but might get little more than she does at present, dependent upon the strategic situation.(e) Supplies from Russia,  the only remaining sourceadditional to those at present fully tapped,are problematical and are unlikely at best to exceed 750,000 tons in a year.(f) The position, is shown in the following tableGerman Supplies of Iron Ore.Present rate Rate of supply ifof supply.Northern Swedish orodenied.Theoreticmaximum.(In terms of iron content por annum -domestic Sources 6.0ImportsINorth Sweden 4.2Rest of Sweden 1.5NorwayLuxemburgRus siaOthers*5.35nil12.86,0nil3*0nil1.5-.1511:5s00Probable.million tons)6.0nil2.nil.75.75.257.0* - 9.75-.6r

(Intd.)    R.H.C.finis try of Economic Warfare,9th January, 19UO.h   Note,      It is, however, again emphasised that the actualamount of iron made available to Germany from importedas well as domestic ores will, in practice, fall below,and perhaps a long way below, the statistical estimate,in the absence of sufficient phosphoric ore from northern Sweden to mix with the other ores of lowphosphoric content.




</content>
</cab>
