<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/18/0 images: 2-10</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This hooument is......the .. Property .of His^ha:&apos; env&apos; i Gov eminent,.)L Britannic,cj. t?  P.   o T?  rpcab 171?;? 1  (19) .OOHGLUSIQSJS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, downing street, S.W.1,  on TUESDAY,  * JGVR&amp;BF.R 4, 1919, at 11-3c a.a. &apos;IfheThe Prime Minister (in the Chair).f    TheTheBight Hon. A. Bonar Law,Lord Privy Seal. tIRight TT0r?, a. J.Balfour, O.M.,M.P.,lord President of the Council,       8Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P., chancellor of the Exchequer. 5i&amp;ght Hon. Lord Birkerihead,Lord Chancellor.1hiip right RonSddisonfheTheMinister of Health.Disrht Hon. Sir Robert Horns,V o  b     8&quot; f:     1*   P ni of labour our *1Right Hon. Lord Lee of fareham,      gG.B.k.,k.c.B., President of theBoard of Agriculture &amp; Fisheries.Right Ron, Earl Curzon of kedleston, k,G.,0.C.S.I.,g.c.I.E., Secretary of Statefo r Fo peiKn Affairs.The Right hon. Viscount Milner,Q.0.E M G.G.M.:G.;, Secretaryof State for the Colonies.I   The Right Ron. R.S.Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.Right Hon. J.X. Ifiaopheraon, k.c., $ TheM.p-.- Chief Secretary for Ireland. f8Right Hon.       Long, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Ron. W. Z,Churchill,M.P., Secretary of State forWar and Air.The Right Hon. Sir A.C.Geddes,K.C.D.,k.?., President ofthe hoard of Trade.\    The Right Ron. H.A,L.Fisher, LL,D,LI.?., President of the Boardof Education.lieut..-Colonel Sir M.P.A.Hankey, &amp;.G.B., Secretary.
4 m  i    2(1) The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to the follow-in.^ Question in Parliament, out by Mr Butler Lloyd (Mo.6?,op. the Paper.for ^overnher 4, 1919):-&quot;To ask the Sfcp. Chancellor of the Exchequerif he will consider the question of itapos-ing an Import Duty on foreign flour, andalso an Export deputy on feedingstuffs, withthe object of inducing the foreigner togen-! us wheat instead of flour, and therebyenable the farmers in this country to secure a larger supply of aillers&apos; offal&quot;.The Cabinet took note of the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer&apos;n proposed reply, to theeffect that the Government would not beprepared to adopt the suggestion.(a) With reference to a recent suKanohs to Minister?, toattend at the railway station to meet the Shah of Persia,the Cabinet took note of an arrangement which Lord Curzonha4 Egade with Lord Stamfordhaa, that, in future, summonsesto Ministers to meet distinguished visitors on arrival inLondon should only be sent to those Ministers specially concerned;   that the summons should be in the sense that,acting on the King*8 commands, the Lord Chamberlain requestdthe attendance of suefc-and-sueh a Minister;    and that HisMajesty will indicate which Ministers should be summoned,on the understanding that their attendance is conditional upon the exigencies of their respective affairs of State.
M -      JSTRUCTIONS (5) The Cabinet considered a draft of Instructions toTHE SECRE-&amp; *&quot;he Secretary of the Cabinet on the subject of procedure.CARD TO &apos;BltiET which was read to them by the Prime Minister.OCBDURR.The draft was amended in the following sense(a) An addition should be made to the effectthat any member of the Cabinet should have access at any time to the Cabinet records.(b) The complete Draft Conclusions and final conclusions should be sent only to theKing, the Prime Minister, and the leader of the House of Lords.    The Ministers atthe head of Departments specially concernedin particular Conclusions, whether for action or otherwise, ahould receive copiesof these Conclusions, but they should notbe sent, in. addition, to Ministers who hadtaken a specially leading part in the die-cue si on.(e) Ministers at the head of Departments should themselves be responsible for notifyingConclusions to their Departments, as neces-sary, and the 3ec.reta.ry should not send the Conclusions to the Permanent secretaries of Departments, nor to the Chiefs of Staffof the Fighting Departments.(d) The following paragraph at the end of theoriginal draft was deletedt-&quot;Cabinet Minutes and Papers are not the personal property of me cube rs, and on a minister leaving office it is the dutyof the Secretary to recover from him,or, in the event of his death, from hisexecutors, all Cabinet Papers issued tohim from the Cabinet Offices&quot;.-Secrecy was considered to be-safeguarded by the&quot; rule that no-one is entitled tomake public use of Cabinet documentswithout the permission of the King.- The revised Instruction^ tct-he.Sec petarv. as approved PYtho.Cabippt. are attached in the.A^endijL.EHDAJJCE (4)     The Cabinet agreed that it was desirableMINISTERS for Ministers to be present in ParliamentPA PL IA iv. RUT. as often as possible during the Parliament-ary Session, and that,&apos;with this object in view, Ministers should at such times,whenever practicable, transact their official business in their rooms in theParliamentary buildings.
pocedure inating theverhmentit &amp;llitaryElioy.F^8^ pOLIGY&apos; (5) The Cabinet had a general discussion on the QuestionI: RU SS IA ,I   - of British policy in Russia, in view of the fact that theHouse of Commons would probably desire a statement on thesubject ^rore the Government in the course of the forthcoming debate on Military Expenditure.The Cabinet took note of the procedure proposed bythe Secretary of State for Tar, namely, that the Financialsecretary of the War Office should open with a statement or: the financial aide of the revised Army Estimates, andthat he himself should follow later with a general statement on Russian policy.The Cabinet took note of a short outline given themby the Secretary of State for War of the general lines ofhis proposed statement on military policy.   This justifiea-tion of cur policy was based on the original argument thatwe had endeavoured to re-create an Eastern Front in Russiaduring the 57ar, partly in order to prevent, Germany frombreaking the Blockade by supplying herself from Russia, andpartly to prevent German troops froffl beipg released fromthe Eastern to the Western Front, and that we had not, uptill now, been justified in abandoning a movement that had come into existence at cur instance, but the government recognised that their assistance could not be continuedmuch longer.    The statement also contained the followingsalient pointst-(a) The principal change in the situation isthat all British forces have been withdrawnfrom Russia with the exception of some 1,500volunteers with General Denikin.   The UnitedStates of America, France and Italy still haveforces in Russia, and Japan and Poland havelarge forces there.(b) The statement recently made by J5r Asquith andin the Press as to expenditure in Russia arevery greatly exaggerated, as would be shown by announcing the correct figures.
(c) Responsible anti-Bolshevist Russians allstate their /willingness to pay for thesupplies ami stores furnished to them bythe Allies as a first charge on theirrevenue in the event of success.(d) General Denikin has been notified thatafter March 31st. he must consider himself as self-supporting.   After that date hewill only he able to obtain supplies fromthis country by purchase.(e) The Bolshevists have alienated all sympathy of the Allies by smashing the ConstituentAssembly, and if General Denikin did thesame the hands of the British Governmentwould be tied as regards further aasist-anee to him.(f) Mr Asquithds description of General fenikinas an adventurer is unjustifiable.    He had remained loyal to th,e Allies all through,and at the moment of his greatest successhad placed himself under Admiral Koltchakat a time when the latter was losing.(g) By distributing the final &quot;packet&quot; ofsupplies gradually to General Denikinthe British Government were able toexercise a certain amount of influence with him in the orevention of pogromsand relations with the Germans.
GAs regards general policy in Russia, the Secretaryof State for &apos;*?ar was asked to make it clear that the BritishGovernment were not out to destroy a revolutionary Govern-raent in Russia, and had supported Admiral Koltchak andGeneral Denikiri because they had called their forces intobe in??, during the latter part of the Sfar, for the reasonsmentioned above, and could not honourably desert then.    TheGovernment had simply helped the people who had helped them.If -we were making war on the Bolsheviks, our policy wouldbe a thorough one, and in such a case the Government wouldnot have contented themselves with merely sending a last&quot;packet&quot; of stores to General Denikin.e Caucasus. There was general agreement that, if General Denikinhad designs on the independence of the newly-formed states in the Caucasus, the despatch of supplies to him should be stopped.   The information before the Cabinet, however, on .this point was not conclusive.The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs was asked to-instruct Mr H.J,Mackinder, M.P.,who has been selected as High Commissionerwith General Denikin, to use his best endeavours-ours to restrain General Denikin froru any action of the kind.The Secretary of State for War undertook to make enquiries as to a Proclamationalleged to have been issued in the Azerbaijanby Colonel Rowlandson, to the effect thatGreat Britain supports General Denikin in a unified, undiyided Russia, etc., which has caused great dismay in the TranscaucasianStates.   After ascertaining the ciretna-stances in which the Proclamation had beenissued, if* indeed, it had been issued atall, he would take such disciplinary action as the case might require.jneralsliov in,ts   a.
i Baltici-tsa.regard/ the British policy towards the Baltic Statesof Rasaid, th* Cabinet took note that ample material for astatement^&quot;&apos; available in the telegram addressed to HisMajesty^ Representatives at Reval (No.157), Riga (Wo.SB)and Ko&apos;no (Ho.l) on September 2-5th (Tar Cabinet 6S4, Appendix&apos;6) art in the following extract from the despatch addressed by jsa five Principal Allied and Associated Powers to AdmiralKpftc-haJs., froTS Paris, on Kay S6,  1919:-*Fifthly, that if a solution of the relationsbetween Esthonia, Latvia, Lithuania and the caucasian, and TransCaspian territories and russia is not speedily reached by agreement,the settlement will be made in consultation and. co-operation with the League of Rations,and that,until such settlement is made, theGovernment of Russia agrees to recognise these territories as autonomous and to confirm therelations which may exist between their de factoGovernments and the Allied and Associated Gov-ernaient ss,together with Admiral Koltohak&apos;s reply, dated. June 4, 1919, ofwhich the following is an extract:&quot;We are fully disposed at once to prepare forthe solution of the questions concerning the fate of the national groups in Fsthbnia, Latvia,Lithuania and of the Caucasian and TransCaspiancountries, and we have ever;/ reason to believe&apos; ,   that a prompt settlement will be made., seeing that the Government is assuring, as from thepresent time, the autonomy of the variousnationalities.    It goes without saying thatthe limits and conditions or these autonomousinstit contributions will be a ettled s e pa rat ely- asregards eu-oh of the nationalities concerned.And even in cage difficulties should arise, inregard to *the solution of these various ques-tions, the Government is ready to have recourse to the&apos; collaboration and good offices of theLeague of Nations, with a view to arriving ata sat is fact o ry a et 11ement &apos;*.
nland. As regards the British policy in Finland, the cabinet took note that the Secretary of State&quot;for fa? proposed to reply in the sense that the question of Finnish policy wasone for the Government, of Finland to decide, but that HisMajesty*s Government was not in a position to afford them any assistance.The Secretary of state for Foreign affairs undertook to enquire whether a denial hadbeen issued to General &quot;.!annerheim&apos;s recentstatements to the effect that the BritishGovernment would! welcome the intervention of Finland in favour of General Yudenitoh,and, if net, to take appropriate action.ival Opera- As regards the recent Naval operations in the Baltic,Ions in the title. the Cabinet took note that these had originally been under-taken in order to prevent the Bolshevist Fleet from dominat-ing the Baltic to the detriment of the Allies, and possiblyco-operating with the Germans.    The fact that the BritishHavy was in conflict in those waters with the same enemy asthe Baltic States had Inevitably led to a certain degree ofco-operation, but only a limited British force had been em-ployed, and it could not he said that the 13avy had been usedto its fullest extent to assist in the advance of GeneralYudenitch.vSSMIIIM BOMBS.      (6) In vie^ of the fact that a. Select Committee had ^already.examined the question of Premium Bonds and had not reactedthe principle but had only deemed that the moment wafe not at   ,that time opportune for their issue, the Cabinet decided  I (a) That the House of Commons should/hot be askedto aoooint a fresh Select Committee. &apos; j(b) That, if the House of Commons desired it, a /1                                   day should be given for a Debate on thesubject:i(c) That, if the House of Commons desired the jadoption of the system of Premium Bonds, ithe Government should not oppose it.* Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I,November 4, 1919.
DOCjTOIIT IS Tin PROPERTY op HIS ETITUiiilC MLJRSTY&apos; S GOvTJRHMRKT)C 0117? ID TNT IAL . APPPPDIX.INSTRUCTIONS TO TH^ SFCRFTAR^ OF THP CAB I HPT.(Approved by the Cabinet on 4th November. 1919.51. The Secretary will attend Meetings of the Cabinet to keep a record of the Cabinet proceedings.    These will be confined to&apos;conclusions similar te those circulated recently in connection withthe War cabinet discussions.    In addition,   a single copy of a fulJLernote will be kept by the Secretary in cases where   the Cabinetexplicitly desires it.2. The Secretary is to airculate complete copies of the draft conclusions and final conclusions to the King,  the Prime Ministerand the Leader of the House of  ,&apos;erds,.    As seon as possible after eaiSimeeting he i s to send oopies of the draft Minutes for^their remarks to the Ministers at the head of Departments which are particularly concerned in them whether for action or Otherwise.3. The Secretary Is responsible &quot;that copies of the final Con-conclusions of the cabinet are fcrwarded to Ministers, whether Membersof the cabinet or not,.whose Departments are affected by them.    TheMinisters are themselves responsible for communicating the oon-clusions to the Departments as necessary.    Any member of the cabinet has the right of actress at any time te the Cabinet Minutes.4. The Cabinet Secretariat will supply Secretaries for cabinet committees and such Conferences as the prime Minister may from time,te time summon fir the discussion of questions referred by theCabinet or dealing with matters which could mere conveniently bediscussed in this manner than in the Cabinet itself.    The records ofCabinet committees and Conferences shall as a rule be kept sn thesame principles as are&apos;laid down for Cabinet recorus.5. Subject to any special instructions the Prime Minister orChairman of the Committee may give in individual oases, theSeoretarv will circulate the Minutes sf the Cabinet Committees and conferences to all Members of the Cabinet.6. Subject to any instructions he may receive from the PrimeMinister in regard to any particular paper,  the Secretary willcirculate tc all Members of the Cabinet all Memoranda and ^therdocuments prepared for&quot;&quot; the use of the Cabinet.    Subject to referencet? the Prime Minister in doubtful cases,the Secretary will use his discretion in circulating Cabinet papers to Ministers outsidethe cabinet and to the Permanent Seeretaricsx of Departments affected.x    in the case cf the fighting Departments the Chief of Staff maybe substituted for the Permanent Secretary.2,  &quot;hitehall gardens,  S.&quot;&apos;.30th October,  1919.

</content>
</cab>
