<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/18/0 images: 153-202</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I If i1 i\l A I &quot; -148(?.M9. flcwr-,*,r.t in the Property pf Kiq IrltanniOOHCUTSIOHS of a Meeting held at 10, Downing Street, S.w.1,Oh JTBiaiBSISAy, tfKCRIBBfSB 10, 1919, at 11-30 at.-n.5rise Minister, (in thf Chair)X 6 rt!Hon. A. Ponar Iswr, M, P.,! The Right Hon. A. JhBalfour, O.M.,M.P.Priin&apos; Seal&quot;. I        Lord President of the Council.1\m Hi&apos;tot Hon. A. Chamberlain,       If Tho Ri&amp;ht Hon. Lord Birkenhead,Chancellor of the 1        The Lord Chancellor.Excheguex;, 5i The right Hen. the Karl Curaon of..e  ivi^ it Hon. g. Shorti,  K.G.,M.M  edleetSn, K.&amp;..,G.C.S.I.,&amp;.C,I,&quot;Secretary of State for Home     I Secretary of State for ForeignAffair a. \        hifatra.&apos;ifl Right v*cn. R.S.Mentanu, I The Bight Hon. Churchill, K.PtySecretary of State for India. $ Secretary of State for Par ri-v-s        Air.is night hon. 9f. Long, iii.P., iFir-it Lord of the Admiralty.   I The Ri^ht Hen, JVLMaopheraon, L.C.,i.P., Chief Secretary for[on. iCunrc, K.C.,M..P,J Ireland.*ry for Scotland. iion. Sir R, Ce&amp;des,&apos; 0,0.3,,The &quot;Bight hon. C, Addisen, P.P.,    *        G.B.h.,P.P., Minister of Trans-iinlater of health. $        port.The 8ij?ht Hon. Sir A,C.aeddes,       I The Sight Hon. Sir Robert Home,S.O.B&quot;. PV;:, * PreeiJent of the I         ,B.E.yK.G.,M,.P.-, Minister ofBoard or Tp&amp;de, I Labour.The Pioht Hon. Lord Lee of Pare-    \  The Bl$ht Hon. K . A. L. Fisher, LL.D.- hswa, President of the Board     1        M.P., President of the Boardof Agriculture- and Fisheries. I        of Education.The following were also present:-
The Right Hon. G.H. Roberts, M.P., Food Controller.

The Right Hon. Sir L. Worthington-Evans, Bart M.P, Minister of Pensions.

Sir Hamar Greenwood, Bart., M.F., Director of Overseas Trade.

Mr F.G. Kellaway. M.F., Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Munitions.

Mr Philip Kerr.

Lieut.-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B., Secretary.

THE KING&apos;S SPEECH FOR THE PROROGATION OF PARLIAMENT.

(1) The Cabinet was informed that the King had expressed to the Lord President of the Council a desire that the King&apos;s Speech for the Prorogation of Parliament should be ready for this Majesty&apos;s consideration not later than Saturday, December 30th.

Attention was drawn to the fact that the usual phraseology employed at the outlet of the King&apos;s Speech was "My Lords and Gentlemen"; and in the portion relating to the House of Commons, "Gentlemen of the House of Commons". The recent election of a lady Member of Parliament would necessitate some alteration in these terms.

The Cabinet agreed:

That in the draft submitted to the King the phrase "Members of the House of Commons" should be employed instead of "Gentlemen of the House of Commons".

THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA BILL.

(2) The Prime Minister expressed the congratulations of his colleagues and himself to the Secretary of State for India for his skilful and successful conduct of the Government of india Bill Through the House of Commons.

 
PROPOSED OPENING OF INDIAN LEGISLATURES BY THE PRINCE OF WALES.

(3) The Prime Minister stated that, in view of the fact that the Government of India Bill would probably become law before the Prorogation of Parliament, it was proposed that the King should be asked to send a message to the People of India in regard to the character of the Bill. The question had been raised as to the desirability at the Indian Legislatures being opened by the Prince of  Wales in person. The King had expreesed his approval of the proposal, and the Prince of Wales was willing to undertake the mission. If the Cabinet agreed, it had been proposed that the King should be asked to mention this in His Majesty&apos;s Message. The Prince of Wales proposed to make a tour of the British Self-governing Dominions during 1920, and the suggestion was that after his return to England he should, during the winter of 1920-21, visit India for the purpose of opening the Legislatures.

The Cabinet agreed:

(a) That the opening of the Indian Legislatures by the Prime of Wales in person was eminently desirable, and should have an admirable effect in India:

(b) That the Secretary of State for India should also include in the draft of the King&apos;s Message some expression of confidence that the People of India would await the measures for giving effect to the Government of India Act in tranquility and without any distburbance of the peace.

THE HOUSING BILL.

Housing Bonds to become Trustee Investments.

(4) With reference to Cabinet 8 (19). Conclusion 6, the attention of the Cabinet was drawn to a proposal that Housing Bonds should become Trustee Securities, which proposal was coming before the House of Commons, in Committee, the same afternoon.

 


Tp$ question had been referred to the Lord*Hi^h chancellor-oeller, who wan the constitutional authority for deciding what securities were to he reckoned as t ruatee securities,and the Lord Chancellor had referred it to a  seating of theChancery Judaea,   h letter which had been received by theLord Chancellor was read to the Cabinet, in which it was stated that *ha Chancery Judges were uuaniaouel*r against theproposal (Appendix I).    attention was drawn to the last p?4ra-ftraph of the letter, where it wae stated that the ChanceryJudges had no objection to sort.page loans, raised by author!-ties who already have power to la sue ateck ranking a? atrustee security, being constituted trustee securities.In this connection it was pointed out that the RousingPonds would practically have the guarantee of the Statebehind the/a, since, beyond the id. rate, the whole financial responsibility Per the Housing Scheme fell on the State.The Lord Chancellor explainsa that, in view of the statements which had been made to hiss by the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer and the Minister of Health, he did not feel justified in opposing the proposal.The Cabinet, agreed -That, while the greatest respect was due tothe opinion of the Chancery Judges, in viewof the fact that the Chancellor of the Rxche-   *.juer and the Minister of Health could see noother satisfactory. &apos;*ay of financing the housing policy, and that the Lord Chancellor did not offer objection, the Severn^ant should aeh theHouse -of Oomsohs to adopt the proposal that.Ifoueins Bonds, as well as Mortgage Loans,should be included aaonff Trustee Securities.IpHM SUPPLY (5) with reference to Cabinet 9 (19), Appendix, theBOMPXTTP^.      prime Minister drew the attention of his colleagues to theimportance of the work of the Supply and Transport Committee.At the present time the country wa* faced with the possibilities-itv of two -strikes.    If the negotiations in regard to the
railwaymen&apos;s wages should not be concluded by December 31st. there was the possibility of a railway strike. There was also the possibility of a strike on the question of nationalisation of the mines. There was considerable difference of opinion in the labour Party on this question. One section of the Party advocated Parliamentary action, but the other section favoured direct action, and in a recent speech Mr Smillie had clearly shown that he did not believe in Parliamentary action. There was some danger that a strike on the question of nationalisation might be precipitated in early Spring. He therefore earnestly requested the Ministers at the head of the Departments concerned to give their close attention to the work of this Committee.

The Minister of Transport asked the Cabinet to take note that if a strike occurred the Government were in an infinitely worse position than in the case of the recent Railway Strike. The Civilian Departments concerned had done their best to help the Committee, but the representatives of the Fighting Services had informed the Committee that they could give but little help. For example, the General Staff looked to the Minister of Transport to undertake the responsibility for moving troops, but if the railways were not available the Minister of Transport had no motor lorries or other means of transport available. The Chief of the Air Staff had informed him that he had not the means for maintaining wireless communication.

The Secretary of State for War stated that he had already given instructions to his Department to do their utmost to assist the Supply and Transport Committee, and the First Lord of the Admiralty said that the Admiralty could give the same assistance as before, but that this did not amount to very much.
After some further discussion:

(a) The Prime Minister, on behalf of the Cabinet, invited the Secretary of State for War and Air, and the First Lord of the Admiralty, to associate themselves personally in the work of the Supply and Transport Committee, with a view to a report, to be made on their joint responsibility, to the Cabinet as to the position in the event of a possible strike:

(b) The Secretary of State for War undertook to give the Prime Minister a Paper regarding the number of troops which would be in Great Britain and Ireland respectively in March and April, 1920.

UNAUTHORISED PUBLICATION OF A CABINET DOCUMENT.

(6) The attention of the Cabinet was called to a letter dated November 20, 1819, which had been addressed by Sir Maurice Hankey to all Departments, on the subject of the staffs of Government Departments, and which had appeared in full in "The Daily Mail" of December 8th.

It was pointed out that the version as published in "The Daily Mail" was not indentical with the original letter. There had been certain slight discrepancies, and one or two sentence or portions of sentences had been omitted, giving the impression that it had been hastily copied.

The suggestion was made that action might be taken, under the Defence of the Realm Act, to compel the Editor to divulge the source of his information, but some doubts were expressed as to whether this should be done unless it could be alleged that the safety of the Realm had been endangered.

The Cabinet agreed:

That the Secretary should obtain an opinion from the Law Officers of the Crown on the subject.

LEAKAGE IN REGARD TO THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE IRISH COMMITTEE.

(7) With reference to Cabinet 2 (19), Conclusion 2, attention was drawn to a further leakage of information regarding the proceedings of the Cabinet Committee on Ireland.


which had appeared in "The Daily Mail" of December 5th. The article referred to, which was furnished by the Political Correspondent of "The Daily Mail", had contained a good deal of detail and had actually stated the views expressed by certain named members of the Committee. No minutes had been kept of this meeting, and the information, if correct, could only have been obtained from persons present.

It was pointed out that "The Daily Mail" report was only partially accurate.

(8) Attention was called to a leakage, which had occured in the Irish "Freeman&apos;s Journal", of a very import decision taken by a Cabinet Conference on December 2nd, relating to the apprehension of certain malefactors and suspected persons. The carrying out of this decision required prompt action and secrecy, and, owing to this leakage, the Police had been unable to carry out their instructions.

THE GOVERNMENT OF IRELAND BILL.

(9) With reference to Cabinet 10 (19), Conclusion 14, the Cabinet had before them a draft of a Bill to amend the provision for the Government of Ireland (Paper C.P.-266).             

The Ultimate aim of the Government&apos;s Policy.                                                 

(10) With reference to Cabinet 10 (19), Conclusion 4, there was some further discussion as to the ultimate aim of the Government&apos;s policy. It was pointed out that the Bill appeared to have been drafted on the assumption that this ultimate aim was a united Ireland with a single Parliament of its own. Those who were life-long Unionists would naturally prefer that there should not be a single Parliament.

The Cabinet, were reminded, however, that one of the principal aims of the Government&apos;s policy was to produce a good effect in the self-governing Dominions, as well as in


the United States of America and other foreign countries. This object, it was maintained, could not he achieved by anything short of a measure which paved the way for a single Irish Parliament if and when both the North and South of Ireland were willing to accept it. The general trend, of opinion in the Cabinet was in favour of adhering to the lines on which the Bill is at present drafted.

(Mr Balfour asked that it might be placed on record that he was not in agreement with this view.)

The Representation of Ireland in the House of Commons. -- Clause 16.

(11) Attention was drawn to the provisions of Clause 16, whereby Ireland would be represented in the House of Commons by 63 Members who would not be entitled to vote on any Bill not affecting Ireland. It was explained that the Speaker would be the judge of what questions did or did not affect Ireland.

It was pointed out that the Irish Members would probably be allowed to vote on many questions, such as, for example. Nationalisation of Mines or Railways, which vitally affected the whole course of domestic policy in Great Britain. The practical effect of this might be to give Ireland a decisive voice in our domestic policy. It was suggested that this was a reason for cutting down the representation of Ireland in the House of Commons within the narrowest possible limits.

It was pointed out that Ulster claimed to remain for all purposes and integral part of the United Kingdom, and on this ground it was probable that Ulster would strongly ? either any proposal for reducing her representation in Imperial Parliament, or the :in-and_out" Provision for Irish Memebers.


The &quot;ii^and-out &quot;-proposal sr&amp;e also criticised on   *the ground that no Ceverragent would &quot;possess a stable ferityin the -House of Coisssone, since this majority would wary on each question,&quot;according as the Irish representatives were&quot;in&quot; or &quot;out&quot;.As regards Ulster&apos;s objection to the reduction inthe nua&amp;er of Irish. Members, it woe sur? nested that if theParliaisenta of the South of Ireland and the Worth of Irelandwere regarded as - part of an eventual federal system, theyMi^ht each be treated as a unit, and, in this case, Ulstermight be given an equal nvusber of representatives to theSouth of Ireland.   The Bill already treated the two Parlia-joents as units so far as concerned the Council of Ireland,in which each Parliament was to have s^u?jI representation.This soapiest ion, however,, was rejected on the ground that itwould furnish an undesirable precedent &quot;as regards the repre-sent at ion of Hnsland in any federal seheasie.After soue further discussion the Cabinet agreed -(a) That, subject to the result of an inter- .view which the Priiiie Minister intendedto have with the Irish Metsbers of theG-overrusent, Clause 1*5 of the Bill shouldhe amended so as to reduce the number of irish Hessibers provided for in the XssperlalParliaisent to 4P, the &quot;in-and-out&quot; portionof the Clause being retained!(b) That the  overrent should be prepared toj*e-ooneider the whole Clause when they had ascertained the general opinion of theHouse of OOKUiions on. the question,* -(it) with reference to Cabinet 10 (19), Conclusion 5,during the diseusnion referred to in the previous conclusion the questions were again raised either of leaving the six counties out of the seheae, or of Uniting the Parliamentof Northern Ulster to the Six Counties.It was stated that the trend of opinion amongresponsible Ulster politicians was in favour of limiting the
scheme to the Six Counties, since the idea of governing thethree Ulster Counties which had a Nationalist aajorityvasnot relished.The administrative and other reasons against theproposal either to exclude the Six Counties-or to Halt the parliament for Jferthern Ireland to thorn, were&apos; again mentionedand reinforced.It was further pointed out that the Bill in itspresent forrr possessed the advantage of fitting into anysellers for the establishment of- a federal eyeteai in theUnited Xingdca* should saeh a sehesve sv?r be. adopted.Subject tc possible further consideration in the light of anything that the UlsterS&amp;eiahera M.g.hi have to say when seen (asproposed) by ivej-sbers of the Oovemaent,the general vies? vas against any altera-tion of the Bill in this respect.Proposal to (13) It was suggested that the administrative difficultenable . worth-t Ireland    ties in regard to the exclusion of Ulster, which were at -tc discard-&apos; echeiae.     present regarded as almost insurmountable, might possibly be overcoat by proposals emanating fron Ulster itself.   Itwas suggested, therefore, that provision should be ;aade inthe Bill, to enable Ulster to propound such a echews and to five up its separate Parliament.It was generally felt, however, thatthis would contravene the principles- aliped at in the Bill. -rhraseoloey: (14) The suggestion was saa&amp;e that, in the draft Bill,&quot;Ulster&quot; of&quot;northern        the %bvm &quot;Ulster&quot;1 should be substituted for * NorthernIreland&quot;. . ^   ,   .Ireland&quot;.   In support of this it was pointed out that the constant reference to Parliaments for Northern Ireland and southern Ireland and a possible Parliament for the whole     .of Ireland were very confusing, while the change would &quot;be acceptable to the people, of Ulster.
It was explained, however, that the terms "Northern Ireland" and "Southern Ireland" had been adopted deliberately in order, if possible, to escape from the terms associated with the old and long-protracted controversies.

It was agreed --

To adhere to the phraseology employed in the draft Bill.                                     

Compulsory military service: Article 4(1)(3).                                                

(15) Attention was drawn to the last sentence of Article 4 (1) (3), which, it was explained, was intended to prevent the Imperial Parliament from imposing compulsory military service on Ireland without the consent of the local legislatures.

It was agreed --

That Clause 4 must be amended so as to remove the restrictions on the power of Imperial Parliament to legislate for compulsory military service in Ireland.

Reserved Services: Employment Exchanges and Unemployment: Clause 9.

(15) Attention was drawn to the fact that the Committee had originally included Employment Exchanges and Unemployment Insurance among the reserved services. The reservation of these services had, however, been dropped in the present bill. This would cause great difficulties, as there was very close association between certain parts of Ireland and certain parts of Great Britain in the question of employment. For example, the Belfast Employment Exchanges worked in very close association with the Clyde, and the same was true of Belfast and Dublin. Moreover, the Trades Unions were intimately connected.

Against this it was urged that one of the principal difficulties the Government had to meet in Labour questions was that rates of Unemployment Insurance, etc., had to be fixed on a British standard and were grossly extravagant when applied to Ireland.


The Cabinet agreed --

Not to alter the draft Bill in regard to Employment Exchanger and Unemployment Insurance.

The Cabinet Committee.

(17) The Cabinet invited the Cabinet Committee on Ireland to examine the B111 in the closest detail before its introduction in Parliament.

ANGLO-FRENCH AGREEMENT REGARDING OIL SUPPLIES.

(l8) With reference to Cabinet 10 (19), Conclusion 17, Appendix II (7), the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by Sir Hamar Greenwood on the subject of the Draft Agreement with the French Government on Petroleum matters (Paper C.P.-259).

It was stated that this Agreegment, which had been repudiated by the Prime Minister and M. Clemenceau when it was on the point of being concluded, was now considered as desirable by all the Government Departments concerned. The effect of it would he to give to the French a 20 per cent, holding in a Company to work the oil in Mesopotamia, while it would leave the whole control definitely in British hands. The urgency of the question lay in the fact that, unless it was concluded at once, there was a danger, owing to the activities of the Standard Oil Company, that the French might associate themselves with American oil interests instead of working, as it were, as a junior partner with British oil interests. By means of Agreements, of which this was a part, it was hoped to secure that British interests, instead of Dutch, should control the powerful Royal Dutch Shell Combine, and this was a matter of the utmost importance.

It was explained, however, that the moment was not very opportune for finally concluding this Agreement, which was closely connected with conversations about to be entered upon by the Prime Minister with M. Clemenceau. Further, as


the Agreement had been rejected by the Prime Minister and M. Clemenceau, it was only they who could restore it.

The Prime Minister undertook, in his conversations with M. Clemenceau, to bear in mind the view of the Departments concerned, that the Agreement was a favourable one to this country. If the conversations took a turn justifying him in resuscitating the Agreement, he would not neglect to do so.

EXPORT OF OIL FROM SOUTH RUSSIA

(19) With reference to Cabinet 10 (18), Conclusion 17. Appendix II (7), the Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by Sir Hamar Greenwood dealing with the export of oil from South Russia (Paper G.P.-259).

It was explained that the Shell Company were anxious to obtain the permission of the British Government to take steps to bring the oil from Baku and Grosny to this country.  The Shell Company owned all the oil-producing wells in these districts. A very large quantity of oil was available which was actually the property of the Shell Company.

A proposal that a British Major-General should be sent to Batum to negotiate on behalf of the Shell Company was not pressed. It was pointed out that for political reasons this proposal was undesirable.

It was further pointed out that the question was not merely one of securing oil for this country, which was admitted to be of great importance, but was also of great political significance. The oil pipeline from Baku to Batum ran through four States, namely, Azerbaijan, the Armenian State, Georgia and Batum, while the railway from Grosny to Novorossisk ran through General Denikin&apos;s territory.

It was agreed --

That, subject to further enquiry by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs into the political aspects of the question, Sir Hamar Greenwood should authorise the Shell Company to take steps to obtain the oil in South Russia and Trans-Caucasia.


C!&quot;amy introduction in the House cf Qoimmnactsj??.ft! of a Bill tc afoenft the 4hgio-l-erbiahGAliT.&apos;tL) -       Oil no,p;vy (Acquisition of Capital)(&amp;1) 1&apos;he Cabinet, too-h note of tee Gonelueione of- thfollowing Conferences cf Minlstere:-  -Conference of Ministers held on*rc-sir*sh*s* as, 1919 (Appendix n).Conference of Ministore held onlloveaiber S8, 1919 (Appendix XIX):Conference of Ministers hold-onDecoder 3, 19IP   (Appendix IV):Conference of Ministers held onDecoder &amp;, 1919   (Appendix V):Conference of tSlnlsters held on.Pecefflber S, 1919   (Appendix VI):Conference of Ministers held on-Decodej? -S, 1919   (Appendix VII),hall wardens, p-,a-*a.,
4f4. if  Icopy r  The Boyal Courts.of Justice, -Strand, London, W.C. :.4th December, 1919.My dear Schuster,We had a meeting of the Chancery Judges yesterdayafternoon whereat we fully considered your letter of the 28th ultand its enclosure,  supplemented by the memoranda which appeared in yesterday&apos;s Times.We are unanimously of opinion that the proposed LocalBonds should not be- constituted a trustee security.     It appears tombe contemplated that all local authorities - rural and urban andas well those whose mortgage loans would &quot;not be trustee securitiesas these whose loans are trustee securities - should be authorizedto issue these bonds.     We consider the security would in manycases fall below the standard properly required for trusteeinvestments.     Further, inasmuch as the supply is to be continuous,there would be no market for realization except   at a discount.Yvre find by experience that facility of realization for purposesof distribution is almost as important    for trustee securities assafety and you are no doubt aware that it was this realizability( if I may use so hideous a word) which in times past largelyinfluenced the Court of Chancery in its preference mi. for Consolsabove any other investment for funds in Court.We see no objection to mortgage loans raised byAuthorities who/have power to issue stock ranking as a trusteesecurity being constituted trustee securities.I remain,Yours sincerely,(sgd)    Harry T.Bve.
J6 /. ,, ,,i    *     71 163[THIS DOCpigKT 15 Tffi^ PROPZRPY OP His gIMIO PAJ..:.PysS government^hHEaiT).SECRET,C --CONCLUSIONS of a Conference? held at 10., $owning Street, S.Wol,,on Tuesday, Koveriber 25th,  1919,1   v&apos; at 12 POOH.The Eight Hon.A.Bonar Lav;, M.P.,  (in the Chair).The Bight &apos;H on,.A. Chamber la in, M.P.,    The Bight Hon.E.S.Kontagu,Chancellor of the Exchequer. M.P., Secretary of Statefor India (for Item 5).The Right Hon. If ,3. Churchill, M.P. t    The Bight Hon. W. Long, M.P.,Secretary of State for War &amp; Air.       First Lord of theAdmiralty.THE POLLOV/BKJ VfZSRE A IS 0 PRESENTThe Right Hon.Lord Inverforth, Air Marshal Sir H.M,Minister of Munitions  (for con- Trenchard, Bart,, LCB,,elusions 1 and 6). D.S.O..,   (for conclusions.  5 and 6)*Lienoenant-Colonel Sir M. P;,A.Hankey, G-..-C.B........ ,Seoretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L.3toi*r, C.B.. ............. . ,assistant secretary.IviHT o To 3 *t/ e G^&quot;lZjLlX*tj ijl   Hills o c o c t- c 9 * *.* e o a a a     m. m *.* * o * 4* -o o * e o JL SSX S foci IX &quot;fcSecretary.ll/hT* &amp;3?clfV!i.Oli,S.4V ts.o o*7-*-*,i.sj is o e a o e* .* o  * ffi * * o e &amp; ft o * a w ffi. 0* aa *o 6 a-jti. SSX S 0 Secretary.
development WISH     (1) With reference to h&apos;ai- Cabinet 2C9, Minute 1 (f), theA P FLEETCOMPANY. Conference had under consideration a Memorandum by bhe Min-&apos;&apos; &apos; iistcr of Munitions  (Paper C.P.-136) regarding the agreement which had been entered into with the Appleby Iron Company inSeptember, 1917,It was generally agreed that, while on.the face of It theGovernment could not legally refuse to pay the claims of the C cm-pa ny ,  they had every moral right to evade fulfilling the sontraciif possible, as such fulfilment would amount to the payment of 2,500,000 to the Company in return of nothing.   Doubts were expressed as to whether the legal position had been sufficientlyexplored, and it was suggested that further examination of the contract by the Law 0ffiGer3 was desirable..The Conference decideds-That the Law Officers  should be asked to considerafresh the whole question of the contract with theAppleby Iron Company, end to advise whether, in theiropinion,  it was so drawn that nothing short of the terms proposed, by the Minister of Munitions was possible *    Inparticular the Law Officers should be Invited to con-sider whether the Minister of Munitions was bound to award anything under the terms of paragraph 3 of theletter of September 21st, 1917, from the Ministry ofMunitions to the Appleby Iron Company,  if he thoughtthat the Company was otherwise sufficiently rewardedor compensated;.NCIAL (2)  The Conference had under consideration a Joint Memoran-dum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Financial Secre-tary to the Treasury (Paper F.C.-25)  regarding Financial Reso-resolutions tc Bills *It was explained that it was difficult, now that manyBills were discussed in a Standing Committee of the House ofCommons and not, as formerly, in a Committee of the Whole House,for the Government of the day to.provide against the insertion Ira Bill of amendments involving increased expenditure if theFinancial Resolution under consideration was wide enough to permi.a:.&apos;&apos; asuch amendments.The Conference decided(i)  That in future all Financial Resolutions, like allEstimates,  should be placed on the Paper In the name ofthe Financial Secretary to the Treasury, and that forthis purpose Departments should be&apos;required to submitb*i-the
the terms of their Resolutions to the Treasury forthe approval of the Financial Secretary be-forethey are placed on the Paper:(ii)  That the Secretary to the Cabinet should communicate the above decision to all government Departments.fjsTRIBUTION (3) With reference to War Cabinet 593, Minute 1, regardingIf far medals.the distribution of the British War Medal, the Lord privy seal stated that he had received a letter from Sir FrederickPonsonby referring to the divergence in procedure betweenthe Navy and the Army in the grant of the Medal.Some discussion ensued on the difficulties of uniform-ity of practice in the case cf the &quot;Navy and the Army, and itappeared that, so far as the Army v,rere consumed, distribu-tion of the British Y?ar Medal to soldiers she had servedabroad would not be completed before the expiration of fouryears.    So far as the War Office was concerned, therefore,the question of extending distribution to those men who hadnot served abroad did not arise as an immediate issue *The Conference decided(i)  That the question of the distribution ofthe British War Medal to the Army shouldbe kept distinct from that of Its distri-bution to the Royal Navy:(II)  That the First Lord of the Admiralty should go into the matter and see if it were notpossible to restrict the distribution ofthe Medal;(iii)  That the practise of the Royal Air force should follow that of trie Army,  exceptfor minor differences in such cases asthose of airmen who had ascended to attaokenemy aircraft raiding this country, but who had not actually gone abroad for service.DISCHARGE (4)  The Conference had under consideration the following3F CIVILIANSUBORDINATES   documents on the Question of the discharge of civilianW THE ROYALgjIR FORCE.        subordinates of the Royal Air Force:-A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air-  (Paper C.P.-141),&apos;A Minute from the Chancellor of the exchequer to the Secretary of State for Air(Paper C.P.-169).The Secretary of State for Air stated that he had
suggested the action outlined in his Memorandum of&quot;November17th, because he &quot;was under the  impression that the cabinet had decided that,  when the Out-of-work Donation ceased,there would be a slowing dovm of discharges from SdTemimsatemployment.     At the moment, the civilian subordinates em-ployed at Royal &amp;ir Force Depots wore giving a great dealof trouble and were appealing to the Prime Minister, who hadPTKSalsed to visit Woolwich on Priday nest.        He thought thatif these civilian employees we re discharged,   the result wouldbe a great deal of agitation ana trouble,,    As a set-off totheir retention at Royal Air force Depots,  a scheme had been evolved for the release of unfit ex-service men.      Thisscheme,  if adopted,  would result in a reduction of at leabthalf of tho extra cose incurred by the modification of theprogramme suggested in his Momorandun (Paper C,p -3.41).Moreover,  the retention of these men wax. desirable in itself as it would expedite the disposal of stores,,It was    pointed out that the scheme for slowing downdischarges from the Dockyards (Cabinet 4 (19).  Conclusion 1( )), was different from the proposals uf the Secretary ofState for Aii 7  in that It was a very special remedy for an acute evil.      It applied only to places such as the great.Dockyard towns, where there were large and simultaneousdischarges from the Havyp  the ^rmy and from other Governmentemployment,  and where no alternative employment existed.The  scheme was al  o conditional on men In Naval Dockyardsagreeing to work sh ort time and tuko less pay,,     As a matterof fact the scheme had been rejected by a majority of themen,  and the    uestion would have to come before the CabinetagaiUcThe conferencp decided :-(i) That the discharges of civilian subordinateswhich weie due to be carried out at RoyalAir Force Depots should be suspended forthe moment:(ii) That the question of c out ir.u-tsg such dis-charges in accordance with the standing pro-gramme should be  settled by  discussion between
IB?the Chancellor of the exchequer and theSecretary of State for Air, after thequestion of the Dockyard discharges hadbeen decided by the Cabinet and the PrimeMinister had: paid his visit to Woolwich.(Ill) That the Secretary of State for Air should as far as possible,  expedite- the  discharge-of military employees at Royal j ir ForceDepots, with a vi--.w to substitutung as-permanent employees the civilian subordlnr-ates- referred to in his MemorandumsROUTE      (5)      With reference to War Cabinet 629 Minute 5 the Confer-EGYPTINDIA       ence had before re them a Memorandums by the Secretary of Statefor Air (Paper C *P a S3) on the- question! of am Air Route- fronuEgypt to   India, covering a Minute by the Chief of the AirStaff to the Chief of the Imperial. General Staff askingr thatthe War Office should give ins true tiorx-s to investigate andthoroughly to explore the cues tioio of establishing posts- im.Asia Minor on the lines indicated in the Memorandum..It n is suggested-that, in view of the complications-which might arise in Syria consequent on the v&amp;hdrawal ofthe British troops, it would be desirable to postpone them at tear&quot;.    On the other hand^- -It     fas pointed out that all theSecretry of State for Air desired was  authority to make a survey.The Conference agreedThat it was desirable that the matter should-be settled. Is possible, and requested theSecretary of State for Air to confer with- theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and take such actiora as might be agreed on between)them.OSED -      St6;      l2he Conference had under- consideration a Memorandum! byOFRAFT TO the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs  Paper CP,, -it)KDregarding the gift of aircraft to Poland.. . It appeared that -the offer which had been&apos; made to the Polish Government ofcertain aeroplanes was contrary to. the&apos;-decisions of the War-Cabinet taken on October 16 and October 20* 1919 (War Cab-in eft. 63?:, Minute 4, ara.&amp; War- Cabinet 633, Minute 5&apos;),  which stated that the stores- to be given to Poland should be limited to
non-marketable munitions, and that any assistance from theWar Office-    should form a contribution to an allied effort and not be an independent contribution.   &apos; -Moreover, negotiations were now on the point of conclusion between the .ulnistry of Limit ions and a group of buyers for the sale of allaeroplanes and their engines which had been or would be declared surplus-,The Conference decided -(i) That it would be undesirable to withdraw theoffer madd to the lalish Government:offer(ii) That the Minister of Munitions should aseer-fair whether he could complete fba negctiations2?aierred to above,  with the omission^owing  of theaeroplanes mentioned in the foreign office memorandum (Paper CP-..179),  andih&amp;.t,  ifthis were not poesib2.e, he should refer thematter to the Cabins i.23  Whitehall Gardens,.   d.W*laNovember 25,  1919
f,THIS DOCUPhbT lo THE PKiIERTY Off HIo   :..IM.....10 MAJESTY&apos;S GOvERiPIEHT. )SECRET.    \   ,,.....IiCONCLUoIONo of a Conference hold atI 10, Downing street,  S.W.1*,. on Friday,1  8th November, 1919, at 5iS0 p*m*I-KooED T:-Tho Prime Minister fin the Chair0The Eta Hon, Aa Boner Law. M.P., The Rt, Hon* J.I. Macpherscn, K.0Lord Privy ocale M.P., Chief secretary forIrelandsThe At. hon A,  Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exohoquor.. The Rt, Hon. Sir AeC9 Geddes,E,C,B., M.P,,, President,.   -Board o f Trade*.   ,THE POLLCPING  .-EKE ALSO PPEoEHT.-The Rt. Hon* G.H. Roberta, M.P.,Eocd Ccntrollor,Mr, P.H* Coller,  O.B.,  permanent secretary, Ministry - of - Food,,Mr. C.A. Me Curdy, E.C., M,I .,Parliamentary secretary, Ministryof Pood.Sir fi.!h Vv&apos;arren Fisher, K.C.B.,Permanent Secretary9 Treasury,,Mr, &amp;*L. Barstow, CBo,Treasury.Sir A.D. Hall,  K.C.B,, F.R.S.,Permanent Secretary, Board -of agriculture and fisheries.Lieut, colonel  Sir M.P.A. Hen hoy, G.C.B.. Secretary.Mr. Pembroke Wicks,  ..........................^Assistant Secretary.
MOTOR OARS (l)    Tho attention of the Conference was drawn, as aIII IH15SLAKDquestion of urgency,  to ohSections raised by the labour Partyto an Order issued by the Irish Government for restricting the use of motor oars     in I:.eland. Tho object of this order was to prevent the use of by Sinn Feiners ox motor cars for, raids0The Conference agreed  That tho Order could not be revoked, but thePrime Minister stated that if tho labour Partyagreed to tako the responsibility for raising&quot; -the question, ho would not refuse to receive a Deputation..MB&amp;I (2) With reference to War Cabinet 635, Llinuto 6    the Con-SUPPLI3S.ference had before thorn a Memorandum by the Pood Controller(Paper C,P.- - 146)  on the financial effects of the trans-actions of the Ministry of Food,The Conference proceeded to consider the acute conges-tion of meat supplies owing to the heavy importation of fro-2en meat from Australia,, It was estimated that up to June of next year there would be 75,000 tons a month of imported meat for disposal,  of which.tho Army and lavy would consume 10,000tons, leaving 65,000 tons for distribution. All cold storagewas occupied.    It was suggested,,  on the one hand, that thoonly way of clearing the a em:., a flat ion. was to restore complete freedom of sale by putting an end to control, including there-in the system of compelling purchasers to buy only at the par-ticular butcher with whom they were registered. It.was pointedout, on the other hand., that the Ministry of Pood were com-mitted to the farmers to take home-grown meat at a guaranteedprioe, and that if large quantities of imported meat were re-leased the Government would incur a liability to the farmersamounting to several millions in fulfilment of the guarantee.On the other hand, it was suggested that the Government had only commuted themselves to take from farmers at a guaranteec.price as much meat as was required for consumption^    against this it was urged that, it would be impossible to ask the-1-
formers to submit to do-control at the present time after they had made their arrangements for  the season,  if at thesame time tho market was to ho hroken by a flood of imported meat.    It was pointed cut, however, that the present consump-tion of moat was  down to 25,000 tons a we ok as compared witha normal pro-war consumption of 50,000,  and that if consump-tion wore increased by 5,000 tons a week it would help to relieve tho congestion.    Objection was raised to tho completeremoval of restrictions and tho stimulation of consumptionto tho pro-war rate, on the ground,  that if the presentaccumulations were disposed of there would be a very seriousworld shortage in the following autumn, and it was consideredthat the crux of the problem was in fact a deficiency ofcold storage, which it  -Mediterranean impossible to build in time toprevent the neat from going ba.deIt was stat d that tho Board of Agriculture should boable to approach tho farmers with a suggestion, by  my of compromise,  that they should agree to do-control subject totho total amount of imported meat released not being morethan the pre-war normal consumption of 16,000 tons a &quot;eek.It was suggested that farmers would not be likely to entertainthis figure.    Some discussion took place as to tho applicabilityof this figure to current conditions of diminished consumption,but it   ras generally folt that if the farmers  &quot;mild ayree to therelease of 16,000 tons a week, or roughly 65,000 tons a calendarmonth, the problem of tho accumulations   .;ould be solved,The Conference decided -That the Pros id ht of the Board of trade should confer,  r t 3 p.m.  on the following day,  with the President of tho Board ofAgriculture and  representatives of thoPinistry of Food, and endeavour to arriveat a solution on the lines of the above6 iscuss ion.LIAMENTARY       (3)    Tho Chancellor of the Exchequer stated that theIS TOlOERS. opinion of tho Treasury Solicitor had boon received on aquestion which had be .;n r &apos;;f erred to him by the Finance
Committee., whether.the officers in the navy and Army towhom sums of money had been granted by Parliament for theirdistinguished services in the &quot;.&apos;av mere entitled to object tothe money being tied up in strict settlement for the benefitof their children, and were able to demand payment of a capital sum free from restrictions.    The Treasury Solicitor&quot;&apos;as of opinion that the recipients of the money granted byParliament had no legal right to enforce payment eitheragainst the Crown or against the treasury,  and it was there-fore open to the Crown to ask that tho sums in question should be made the subject of strict settlement on the ohild-ren of the beneficiaries.    It was explained that the operative part cf the Resolution in the House of Commons wasthe grant of a lump sum to the King,  and that while the termscf the Resolution named officers individually, it was merelyan empowering Resolution and did not confer any rights.The Conference agreed  That His Majesty&apos;s Government must insist onthe sums granted,being tied up in striotsettlement for the benefit of the recipients&apos;chil dr en.S, Whitehall Gardens, .3.Y/..1.November 28,  1919.
fclflS DOCPmEHT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITaHHIC MAJPSTY&apos; S GOVERN!rpHT):0Rr.T.COHCLUSIOHS of a Conference Held at 10 DonningStroot, S.rr.l., on Tuesday, December 2nd, 1919., at11.30 acm0The Primo Minister    (in the Chair),The Right Hon, A, Bonar LLord Privy Seal,9 j-   *   ,The Right Hon. A.J,Balfour, O.H., MLord President of the Council.The fight Hon.A.Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of tho Exchequer,The fight Hon, the Lord Birkonhcad,Lord Chancellor (for iiinute 1)p* j- *Tho Right Hon.rr.S.Churchill,H.P.,Secretary of Stato for Par &amp; Air., field-Marshal the Right Hon. theViscount French of Ypros, K.P.,0.Mo ) -&apos;&quot;odoB. , G 0 C . V&quot;. 0 . , K. C . M . G 0 ,Lord Lieutenant of Ireland.(for minute 1)The right Hon.P.!hortt, K.C.,M.P.,Tho Right Hon. J,I* Hacpherson,K.Cc EI.Pe, Chief Secretary for ireland (for Minute 1).Secretary of State for Home AffairsThe Light Hone the EaihL Curzon of kedleston, K.G.,G.C.S.1.,G.C.1.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsTho Right Hon.E.S.Montagu, E.P*,Secretary of Stato for India.The Light Hon. &quot;iLong, i .1.,First Lord of the Admiralty,Tho Ri ght Hon. R.munro, K.C.Secretary for Scotland (for minute 1).. The Right Hon. Sir A.C.Goddcs,K. C.B.,M.P., Presidont, Board ofTrade (for Minutes 3,4 &amp; 5).Tho Right Hon,H.A.LvFishcr,L&apos;.P,,Prooiclont&apos;, Board -*f Education.THE FOLLOWING: &quot;TIP: ALSO PRE SEPT : -colonel  Leslie PiIson, C.M.G,,D.S.0.,M e P . , P ar 1 i erne nt any S e c rc tcry,Ministry of Shinning,  (for Minute 2),&apos; Lieutenant-Colonel Sir H.P.A. Honlcey, G.C .B............. Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Storr, C .B.-.-...&apos;, *&apos;, ..... . Assistant Secretary.Captain L.F. Burgis. . Assistant Secretary.Mr. T.St .Q.uintin Hillt........................ Assistant Secretary3
-1-IMPRISONMENT    (1)    With reference to Par Cabinet 541, Minute 4, theOF SINN FEINPRISONERS IN   Conference had before then a Memorandum by the HomeENGLANDoSecretary (Paper C.Po-145) regarding the imprisonmentof Sinn ^ein prisoners in England^The proposals of the Home Secretary related to thefollowing questions(i) Hunger-striking:(ii) Military Guards. ill) Applying the Prison Regulations toSinn Fein prisonerss notwithstandingany legal difficulties that might arise oOn a review of the arguments for and againstthe proposals in regard to hunger-striking^ as statedin the Home Secretary&apos;s Memorandum and further develop-ed in the course of the discussion, the conference agreed:-(a) That, having regard to the fact that themen impriscned In this country had thealternative of deportation to a foreign country If they could find one to harbourthem (Cabinet 8(19). Appendix II, Conclu-sion 1 (8)  ),  it was essential,  in theinterests of law and order, that the Irishdeportees shnufld not be permitted, byhunger-striking, to obtain their release.As the men imprisoned In this country would,  in the majority of cases, be thosesuspected of conspiracy to murder, it was felt that the Medical Officers would not feel the same objection towards allowing a prisoner to starve, as they did in thecase of other persons:(b) That the Home Secretary should be author-ised to sanction the posting up of a notice In the prisons to the effect that prisoners would not, by hunger-striking,obtain their release:(c) That the . Irish Government should endeavour-not to send to Great Britain prisonersconvicted of piirely political offences:(d) That the War Office should arrange withthe Home Secretary to reinforce the prisonstafft as required, with military:(e) That the Prison Regulations should been forced, notwithstanding any legaldifficulty that might arise.The Conference agreed and took note of thefollowing facts:-(i) That Serjeant Brut on was being trans-ferred from the Secret Service Branchof the Police in Ireland to the secret service Department In this Country:
after(ii) That the families of police officers who had b&amp;^is.ittnLcrrod in Ireland wererecaivihg adequate oompensation underthe Malicious Injuries Act.The Conference approved -the statement of the Chancellor of the exchequer that he was prepared &quot;to consider favourably thequestion of giving assistance to servants of theState in Ireland who were being boycotted for hav-ing performed-their duty during the War, and author-iserl the thirst Lord of the Admiralty to deal withthe immediate needs of the coast watchers out ofAdmiralty Secret Service Funds.&apos;. RETURN OF ( ) The Conference had under consideration a MemorandumICE BREAKERS&apos;-A1R1 SEALING- by tne Shipping Controller (Paper CP.183) regarding theSTEAMERS TORUSSIA. return to the Northern Provincial Government of Russia of seven ice-breakers and four sealing steamers, and Memoran-dum by the First Lord of the Admiralty (Paper CP.216)&apos; sug-suggesting that two ice-breakers    -    the SVIATOGOR and ALEXANDERshould be retained until the British Naval forces are clearof the Baltic,  and that it might be desirable to hand over one of the remaining five ioe-breakers to the LatvianGovernment for use at Riga. --It was nointed out that the town of Riga had neverpossessed an ice-breaker before the War;&apos;   that&apos;very probably.it could not maintain the vessel;    and that there were twoice-free ports within a hundred miles of Riga.The Conference agreed  fa)    That the. four sealing steamers and five of the ice-breakers in question shouldbe returned to the Northern Provinoia.1Government of Ru.sp.ia at once . but &quot;chat thetwo remaining ? ce-breakers   the SVIATOGORand the ALEXANDER - should be retaineduntil the British Naval forces are clear ofthe Baltic:(b)    That the SVIATOGOR and the ALEXANDER shouldbe returned to the    Northern provincial government  of Russia as soon as the BritishHaval forces have left the Baltic.british policy IN: RUSSIA.Instruc-I tions tothe HighCommis-sioner.(3) With reference to Cabinet 1 (19), Conclusion 5, theConference had before them a draft of Instructions to Mr.Mackinder (Paper CP-.E25),who is being appointed as british high Commissioner and Political Representative at the he^dc- ,rt ore of -General DenxiLin.-&apos;- : -   :-&quot;-
&apos; Stress war. laid on the f      &apos; tha.t-lir* Jifsuckinder &apos; activities -were-isalxfLyr^politlj^al., and that,  although he-Trao to keep in the closest possible touch with the miXit-e-cyand economic Missions,  these would operate independently,.It was suggested that Mr. Kackinder1 a task would bea particularly difficult and uncongenial one  in view ofthe fact that,  after a few months;  no further supplierwould be cent to General Benxkxn from this country.  andMr.- Mackinder would therefore have nothing substantialwherewith to support his advice.After some discussion, the Conference expressed con-:currence in the Draft Instructions.      In view of the im-portance of further information to assist the Government infffasmlating their Russian policy, the Conference invited:-The Secretary of State for Foreign affairs to add a paragraph to the Instructionsdirecting Mr. Mackinder to send a full report on the situation in South Russia.It was also agreed :-On page 4, line 20, to omit the word&quot;British&quot; from the phrase &quot;for theestablishment of British trade andIndustry&quot;.(The Secretary of State for War asked thatit might be placed on record that,  in hisopinion, the value of the Mission was seriously impaired by the omission of any provision for placing the British political representative in the Caucasus under mr. Mackinder.    This, he pointed out, hadbeen an essential object of the Mission,and it was doubtful if it would now serveany useful purpose.)DESPATCH OF (4)    VIth reference to War Cabinet  ^33, Minute       theFOOD TOMtnPIAITSK. Secretary of State for War informed the Conference thatGeneral Denikin would be prepared to send 6,000 tons of flour to Egypt for feeding the troops in the Mediterraneanarea.      It was proposed that an equivalent amount of flour should be despatched by the British Government to murmansk.    Such an arrangement would economise tonnage.The Conference agreed to the proposal ofthe Secretary of State for War.n!- ^ -
llERlM (5) With reference to Conclusion 7 of a Conference ofpRANTEEI BELGIUM,    Ministers held on November 18th, 1919, the Conference had before them two Memoranda    by the Secretary of State forForeign Affairs  (Papers CP.-117 and CP.-228) regardingthe proposed provisional guarantee of the Independence andintegrity of Belgium,It was explained that the Belgian Government desiredto abolish the old dyf&amp;em which had been established by theTreaty of 1839 and to complete a new Treaty with the Dutchregarding Limburg, ,but, .pending the establishment of theLeague of Nations, they were anxious to obtein from France andGreat Britain a guarantee of Belgian integrity and independ-ence.    Holland showed the greatest reluctance to complete the negotiations with Belgium, and it was considered thata guarantee of Belgian int sgrity and independence by France.and Great Britain would facilitate the conclusion of theTreaty between Holland and Belgium...It was pointed out that the Belgians-Government had clearly changed their attitude..  During the earlier stages of the &apos;&quot;ar they had always maintained that, if the 1839Treaty could be abolished, Belgium would be able to make better arrangements for her own protection.    Their presentclaim was that Belgium should be relieved of her responeibil-ities under the 1839 Treaty to maintain her own neutrality^while at the same time her Integrity and Independence shouldcontinue to be guaranteed by France and Great Britain.    Shedesired t&quot; be a Sovereign State protected by France andGreat Britain without giving anything in return.      The limit of time in such a guarantee meant little, as, when the periodof three or five years expired, it would probably be found impossible for France or Great Britain to withdraw theguarantee.On the other hand, stress was laid on the fact thatthe integrity of Belgium had been a secular Interest to
3, Whitehall Gardens, 8.W./1Snd December.;, 1919.this country; that we shoiuld...have- to intervene if suchIntegrity were menaced., even if we had not guaranteed it;and that popular    $pinion,  as in 1914, would he solid insupport of a Government which intervened in Surope in orderto fulfil Its written pledges.      The existence of the Treatyof 1839 might &quot;be said to have Baved Europe, for the considera-tion that she had to fulfil her obligations! under theTreaty had be en an important If not a decisive factor inInducing Belgium to defend herself against Germany.A suggestion \?aa me.de that, in return for guaranteeingthe neutrality of Belgium, pending the oatablishment of theLeague of ffationB, the British Government should demand from the Belgian Government a guarantee of Belgian neutrality.The Conference invited :-The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,in the light of the above discussion, toooneider the possibility of making arrange-meute with the Belgian Government wherebyBelgian integrity and independence would&quot;be guaranteed for e. limited period byEranoe and Great Britain, provided that belgium undertook to maintain her neutrality.
POCUMSHT 13 THE PROPERTY Or HIS BR1TANPIC MAJESTY&quot;o IOvERNMEHT)C0:T0LPSI0u3 cf a Conference held in Mr, SonarJ&apos;,n&quot;v&apos;s Rorj; Ho-.ee of Coiom-cis, 3ci&quot;hl-., on Friday,5&apos;cli* Decernbar, 1919,, at 4 b.i*n.oPRESS? 9? vThe Rt. Hon., Ac Bonar Law. M:?-,    (in the Chair)he Rt, Hone A, Ball oar, Ot,M,, The Rt., Hen. E, So Montagu. M.PP, , Lord President ot the Secretary of State for India,,lounoil.ore &apos;j.aanceo:.;;. or Ja^&amp;ncu ifie Rt. Hon, Ac Charbbsilain, M,P.-; . The Ril Hon, Sir 1., C0 Geddes.iiancellor of tho Exchecpasr, K-C.-.B* ..M,PC, Prosid.ont of theBoard of Trade i(he Rtc Hon, &apos;.76 3, Chr.rohj.ll,I,P.:, Secretary of State The Rt - -Hon, Sir B; Geddes, G,Cor &quot;/ar &amp; Air. G - B -E0 ,M5?0 , Minister ofThe Rt, Hen. Sii Robert Homo:E;ourp-Hc Ar I.,, Fisher,President of the BoardLB,Ec,ZoO,5M,PS, MinisterjPhe following.were, a?jeo..;?regsent-s-fie Rt, Hon. Sir Jh Maelay, Barb. ,       Roar-Admiral Sir Osmond de B.upping Controller, Urocii Kb CAB  .X C ,Jw-,Gg ,11.0,7-0jibutonant-Colcnel H G. fh0-0.0 .,fsputy Controller   H * It * S t a ti c neyIflioo ,bopu-;y oniei 0:3utcnant -C03.ono 1 Sir k^P. A. Hanksy . G ;C t B.-.o. ft .,,.*, c0Assistant Secretarynontenant-Colonel EbYPPaniel, C. 3,E-,.Secrete 17 - Historical Section(Cabinet)
JV.T-: HGT.1.;/YTS        (1) The Chancellor of the Exchequer raised the question\i CPdhSffthiS,as to whether Saturday, Bece; ber 27th,  should be declared ageneral holiday in England.After a short discussion,  during which the Presidentof the Board of Trade,  in reply to a question by the lord privy Seal,   stated that ho was advised that no inconveniencewould be caused to manufacturers by such, a decision,  it &quot;wasagreed  (a) To declare December 27th, a general bank holiday in England and Ireland,  but tomake no reference to Scotland,  as it was understood that  there were objections tosuch a holiday being declared there:(b) To declare January 1,  1920,  a Bank Holidayfor banks  only.IP EPS REST RIO-    (2)   &quot;ith reference.ee to -Par Cabinet 633,  minute 4, the LordION (AMENDMENT)ILL. Chancellor raised the question of the Aliens Restriction(Amendment) Bill, which was before th? House of Lords,  and pointed out that there would be strong opposition to thepassing of Clause 9.    An amendment had been tabled putting the onus of proof on to the person who impeached the integrity of an alien,  and it was almost  certain that a Division wouldbe taken early  in the following ye els..    Clause 9 as wordedwan,  in his opinion,   open to considerable criticism,  and wouldbe very difficult to defend.    He had (consequently had anamending clause drafted,  which he would like to propose in substitution for the existing one,  if the Conference agreed.After a short discussion,   during which it was pointedout that tho prime Minister and Mr Bonar Law had made a defi-nite promise as regards the Bill in question,  and that itwould consequently be difficult for the Government to go backupon this undertaking,  it was agreed  That the Chancellor of.the -Exchequer should,as  soon as  possible,  discuss the proposed -amendment with Si&quot; John Butcher, Mr Bottomley,Hi Ernest Wild and Sir Herbert Nield, and decide on the best way of drafting an amend-ment, which the Chancellor.....of the.....exchequer should then arrange for someone outside theGovernment to propose as an amendment whenthe Bill came up for discussion.
7181PXHNS IN THE       (3) The Chancellor&apos; of the Exchequer- informed the Confer-ence that a further Question wan being asked in the Rouseof Commons in connection with the  Regulation that no-one could be employed in the Civil Service who was not the son of a British-bom subject5 and that he proposed, replying,as he had done before;, in the sense that the Government were at liberty to employ anyone they liked in the Civil Service,OBLIGATION (4)  The Conference had before them the following documentsp THE FIRSTpLOME CP in connection with the publication of the First Volume of[HE NAVALfTSTORY CP       the Naval History of the I7ar:-IfS EAR.A Note by the Secretary  (Paper 0.P.-9),A Memorandum by the  Secretary of the historical Section of the  Committeeof Imperial Defence (Paper 23B-B),A Letter from the Admiralty to theSecretary of the Cabinet, with covering Minute from the Secretaryof the Cabinet to the Prime Minister(Paper 0P.-2 03) .After a protracted discussion it was agreed.  (a) That the First Volume of the Naval Historyof the Ear should be published,  and thatthe question of publishing subsequentvolumes cf this Hist o &quot;7/ should be post-poned for further consideration after theYjubiicatiou of the First Volume:(b) That the First Volume  of the Military History,which is  complete.,  subject to final revision,should be proceeded with,  but it  should notbe set up in tyr^e 0    After this Volume has been passed by the War Office., the question of its publication should again be brought before theCabinet:(c) That work on the Air History should be continued,with a view to the publication of Volume I.There was a general desire that thisHistoryj  which was considered lesscont&quot;oversiai than the Naval andMilitary Histories,  should be pub-lished.(d) That the publication of the First Volume of theHist cries  on Sea-borne Trade and the Lie &quot;chantNavy should/be approved,   subject to the Depart-wentp eonce&quot;ned raising no objection:(e) The preparatory work of collecting and collat-ing material for the  Second Volumes of all theHistories  should continue,  but the actualwriting of those volumes in their final shapeshould not be taken up,  and nothing should beset up in type until the cabinet decide thatthey are to be proceeded wit lit
(f)  It should be made clear to the authorsconcerned that the Government  do not commit themselves in any way to under-taking that, the Histories will eventually be published..FFXNG- SITDA-    (5) With reference to war Cabinet 631,  Minute 7,  theN AN&apos;!) OOKGBS-ili AT THE      Conference had before them the  Report  of an Inter-Departmentaliio.Conference of November 7, 1919 (Paper C.P.-105) at which theDepartments concerned had agreed  -(1)&quot;That the Ministry of Shipping,  in consulta-tion with the Ministry of Transport,  shouldhave authority to block Government traffic at the port of shipment in cases where theyare satisfied, after consultation with theDepartments interested, that the import would add to or cause congestion due to lack of storage accommodation in this country.Departments importing goods on government account to be required to show to theMinistry of Transport how they Y^ropcce tostore the Roods in this country beforeshipping facilities are arranged.(ii) To appoint a Committee,  consisting of repre-sentatives of the Ministry of Pood, Ministryof Transport and Ministry of Shipping, toexamine the possibilities of diverting goodscontrolled by the Government,   such as wheat and timber,  from the railways tc the canalsor roads,  and,  if possible,  tc make arrange-merits for the purpose w *The Conference took note of and approvedthese decisions.It was explained that a further recommendation by the interdepartmental Conference had been withdrawn,  viz:-&quot;That the additional cost of inland transport by methods other than railways should beincluded in tho subsidy for coastal trafficuntil the  railways were placed upon aneconomic basis&quot;.It had been agreed that,  as a matter of accounting,  it wasnot desirable to follow this course.(6)  Seme discussion took place as to whether there was aatpossibility of obtaining.an early date results from the attempts being made by the Ministry of Transport to clear the congestion cf the docks.    It was explained that the Minis-try of Transport were working as hard as they could with thefacilities at their disposal.The question was rained whether sufficient orders hadbeen placed for railway wagons,  and it was suggested that
i[S3U^ opa;:d parlia-kSNTARYPAPERS TOPER PRESS..many firms who were able to construct railway wagons were unable to obtain orders.    On the other hand,  it was pointedout that no firm was in a position to deliver wagons.Owing to the iron-moulders  strike it would be impossible toobtain essential parts of the framework..(7)  The Conference had under consideration a Minute bythe Secretary (Paper CP.--163)  covering a letter from the vice--chairman of the Newspaper Proprietors&apos; Association,  inwhich it is stated that the practice of Government Depart-ments,during the War, of issuing to the Press documentsmarked for publication not  before a certain date,  causesunde^ peace conditions serious inconvenience and injustice;together with a further Mote by the  Secretary  (Paper C .P.-223) covering letters from the Secretary cf the newspaper proprietors&apos; Association in which attention is drawn to thefact that advance copies of certain Parliamentary reports have been furnished to three newspapers, and suggesting that public documents should be issued to the Press withoutpreference or priority,  and that an order to this effect should be Issued by the Cabinet..After a short discussion the Conference decided  That the  Secretary to the Cabinet should beauthorised to make with the Newspaper Pro-proprietors&apos; Association such arrangements regarding the points raised in the lettersreferred to as would be acceptable to theAssociation, the Government Departments,and the Stationery Office.a,  Whitehall Gardens,--.T   t.   CO.,Decembe1919 .
(This Document la the Property   f Hi a britannic  jest y&apos;. a Gey e government nlL.jS B 0 R E T -DRAFT 0GN0LUSI.CNS cf a Conference held at 10, Downing StreetS.7.M,. on SATURDAYv  DKO EMBER 6,  1919;  at 9-3C p,.mcfRESENTThe Primu. Minister (in the Chair),Right Hon, Ac Bonar law, Mt.P0        \ Tho Right Hon. the Earl CurzonLord Privy Seal.                                k cf, Ee&amp;lestcn, E,     ,G60,S,I,,j Gt.CeIcE0, Secretary of StateRight Hon. A,J.Balfour, Cr.Me,ample^J f--r Foreign affairs:lord President of the Ccuncil.Tho Right Eon. ^..S, Churchill, McpSecretary of State for Par,The foil:wine was sine present:-Mr Philip herr.Lieut,-Colonel Sir II ,. P., A, hankey, G.C.B.,  Secretary.
.TlO*MOF urgency to consider the situation.in regard to the rat if isF&quot;AC ...a-tion of peace with Germany, had the  following-documentsbefore it:-Lord Derby&apos;s very urgent telegram No.1211,dated D e c e. nb e r 5 :Sir gyre Crowe&apos;s private telegram ofDecember 5  (11-30 p.m.):. . A despatch from M&quot;,  C1 ernencecu to Baron vrnFF. 5^1^) &apos;^ Lersner, Chairman of the German Bele-station, Paris,  dated&quot; November 22,  1919(CCD. 1419) :A despatch from Baron von Lersner to M.Clemenceau on the subject of theScape Plow incident,  dated November27,   1919  (p77.e p. 1423):A despatch from Baron von Lersner to 11.Clemence.au dated November 27, 1919(v7.CP.142G) .The following documents were  received immediately before o&quot; during the meeting:-The first draft of Id.  Clemenceau&apos; s pro- ,posed despatch to the Ger .an G: verrv-ment on behalf of the  Supreme Council:A second draft of 1.1,  Clemervosaof s proposeddec oat oh.,  which  r -i c Doe- considered bythe Supreme Council that coy:Sir Eyre Crowe&apos;s tele &quot;ram. (Mo .1  62 )  contain-ing a fresh draft of the final paragraphof&quot;M. Clemenceau1 s despatch,, as agreedto at the meesmog of the Supreme council that day, but which had been reservedby Sir Eyre Crowe for reference to the3rit. is h Gove rnmeht *.A telegram from Lord Derby (No.1214 ) in&quot;Ofrard to that day? s proceedings att he Sup r erne C ou: ie 11:Net - The draft  despatch of the Supreme council as amended by Sir Eyre Crowe&apos;s tele-gram psattached in Appendix I.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs read asummary cf the events which had led up to the presentposit ionFrom a study of the various documents,  including those received during the meeting,  as well as a private letter from Lord Derby which Lord Curson read to the Gon-ference,  the position confronting the Conference may be summed up; as follows:-GERMANY AMD The.
As soon as the attitude of the United States of America towards the Peace Treaty had become clear, and it was known that the United States Plenipotentiaries were about to leave Paris, the German exports, who had been sent to Paris to conclude the final arrangements for giving effect to the Treaty of Peace, had withdrawn to Berlin.   Remonstrances had then been addressed to the German Government by the Supreme Council (W.C.P.-1416).

On December 1st. Baron von Lersner had replied by a verbal communication to the  Secretary-General of the Peace Conference, in the course of which he had drawn attention to the fact that the participation of America had been an important element in the ?tions of the Peace Treaty, and was regarded in the whole of Germany as an important guarantee. He had agreed, nevertheless, to give assent to the Treaty, but, as a compensation for this sacrifice on Germany&apos;s part, had asked for a relaxation of the Treaty in regard to the extradition of those accused of breaches of the laws of war, and for certain concessions in regard to the return of prisoners of war. He had refused to sign unconditionally a protocol dated November 1st., which had been sent by the Supreme Council to the German Delegation, and which contained a list of unfulfilled conditions of the Armistice, which Germany was asked to undertake to carry out as a preliminary to the final exchange of ratifications. The items in this protocol which Germany declined to agree to were :-

(1) The demands presented in consequence of the sinking of the ships at Scapa Flow:

(2) The reservation of the right by the Allied and Associated Powers to have recourse to all measures of military or other coercion which they might judge appropriate in the event of Germany not fulfilling her obligations within the period mentioned in the protocol.

Although Baron von Lersner&apos;s verbal communication had been followed by a despatch from the German Government, the latter was reported to be weaker. Further it was evident that the German Government had not altogether supported Baron von Lersner and their experts in their action, for they had offered to M. Clemenceau to replace Baron Von Lersner, if he was persona ingrata, to which M. Clemenceau had replied that he was persona ? Further. M. Clemenceau had stated he had secret evidence that the Germans intended to sign if the Allies maintained a firm attitude, and, although the precise nature of this information was not disclosed, the American Delegation, who had seen some of the Germans remaining in Paris in order to tell them that America was ? in this question with Great Britain, France, Italy and
and Japan,  had formed the sane Impression.These were the circumstances in whichthe Supreme Council had prepared the draft note(Appendix I) which constituted an ultimatum,threatening a rupture of the Armistice as a penalty for any further delay by Germany insigning tho Protocol.The Supreme Council was reported to be unanimous, and the urgency of the matter lay inthe fact that the American plenipotentiaries are due to leave Paris on Tuesday and the UnitedStates Go\rsrnmcnt have declined to consent totheir remaining- any longer.    Kir. :.Polk was pre-pared tc sign the note,  but if they did not signbefore Tuesday no American&quot;with authority to signwould be left in Paris.The actual, question for decision was as towhether Sir Pyre Crowe should be given authorityto sign this ultimatum..Phile recognising tho urgency of the question andthe importance of obtaining the signature of the UnitedStates plenipotentiary,  and while impressed with the factthat the Supremo Council was unanimous on the subject,  the conference felt thyt the circumstances wore not- such as tojustify or necessitate an ultimatum involving actual hostil-ities in tho event of non-compliance by the Germans,    It waspointed out that tho Germans,had not made the cancellation of the Article of the Treaty of. Peace in regard to breaches of the laws of war a condition, but had merely suggested thatthis concession should be made in order to ease their position.The same applied to their demand in regard to the return of their prisoners of war detained in Prance t- a matter inwhich the French had adopted a somewhat harsh&apos;attitudeT    Inregard to the German refusal to make qompenaation for theScapa Plow incident,  or to assent to eventual measures ofmilitary coercion,   the Conference took note that&apos; the supreme council had agreed &quot;to take&quot; them &quot;into -coneidaratlon&quot; . Asregards the former point it was generally felt that on meritsj
mr Polk&apos; s plan,- eoamunicaiea t rough the American ambassador in London, would have been preferable,  namely, to insist on the principle cf. compensation,  and to refer the amount tobe decided on by the  Reparations Co mission.    It was further pointed cut that the present German Government was a moderateGovernment, believed to have the intention -yf honestly giving effect to the Treaty.    If an ultimatum was presented in theterms now proposed,   the effect might be to bring about itsfall.    If this should occur,  its successor ay onId probably beeithe^ a Spartaoist or a military Government,  b-vth equallyundesirable.    In any event,  if the Germans declined to yield,military action of some kind would be necessary and wouldhave to take the&apos;form either of en advance into Germany orof a blockade..  The Chief of the Imperial General Staff had reported -from Paris to the Secretory of State for W&amp;r thatthe Allied Forces &quot;-&quot;ere not adequate to enforce a strong mill-tary oolicy.,  Considerable forces would,  the Conferencethought,  he  required,  as the Germans,  though probably incapa-ble at present cf serious offensive operations,   still hadmo re than a million armed and trained men in one formor another available,  and might be able  to oppose an obstin-ate resistance.    It was felt that re-mobilisation in orderto enforce  our policy would be highly unpopular and couldonly be  justified for very valid reasons.    The re-establish-inent of the blockade would be  only slightly less unpopular.On a review of all the circumstances,   the  conference agreed on the following action:--(a)  That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should telegraph to Sir  -&quot;yre Crowein the  sense that grave misgivings we&apos;uefelt as to the form of Pee final paragraph,which threatens Germany with a definiterupture of the Armistice,    The    ritish Cov-e.&quot;w:ment are uncertain as to  the wisdom ofsuch a threat,  and as to the effect thatmay be produced upon the Gemoan Government.They suggest the following amended version,which they earnestly trust that all SirEyre Crowe&apos;s colleagues will be able toaccept:-&quot;The Allies must insist,  therefore,that there should be no furtherdelav in the signature of the protocol and the  conclusion ofPo vme &quot; .--4-1
(b) That Mr Philip Ker- should leave london at once,  in -order to be in Paris on sunday, to rive full explanations:(c) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffair-  should notify Mr Philip Kerr&apos;departure to Sir Pyre Crowe:(d) That Mr Philip Kerr should in any eventendeavour to brina. about a visit by li.Clexnenoeau to London as early as possiblWhitehall Gardens,  S..7.1,December 5, 1919.
(1)  The Slip-erne Council has considered verbal communication .vhich&quot;on made on behalf of the German Government on December 1.(2)  Notes of November 1 and November 22 have defined respensibil-ity of German Government for delay of ratification, of Treaty and conclusion stated therein holds rood.(3) The suggestion concerning the alleged right of Germany to demand (as compensation for the absence of the American delegates from the Commissions until the ratification of the Treaty by theUnited States)  a modification of the clauses  of the Treaty dealingwith the  surrender of guilty persons and the  ^eturr. of prisonersof war, is not well founded.    According to the final clauses ofthe Treaty, the Treaty is to enter into force as soon as Ge&quot;manyand three of the principal Allied and Associated Powers  shall have ratified it;    it  is useless for Germany to attempt to  sake itsputting into force dependent on a new condition, the presence of american Delegates in the Commissions.(4)   It is not  correct to  say that the&apos; German point of view was accepted in this respect  on October 14.(5)  It is no less incorrect to state that Her&quot;en von Simson andvon Lersner were invited on the 20th November to oral and writtennegotiations on the subject of the Protocol of November 1st: theywe-8 siw.nl v informed that, havine received a note in waiting, theGerman Government must   -oplv in writing to those demands,  andthose alone, which were formulated in it,(6)  The Supreme Council considers that Article 221 of the Treatyof Peace (regarding the  return of prisoners of war)  is perfectlyexplicit and is in no need cf amplification.    prance has already declared on several occasions that  she would liberate the prison-ers as soon as the Treaty was put into force;    there is no reasonfor her to repeat it again.(7)  The Council  can only take into consideration the objections raised to the demand fc compensation for the destruction of theGerman fleet at  Scapa Flow,  and to the foreshadowing of eventualmeasures of military coercion described in the Allied note ofNovember 1st.(b) Before mailing their demand,  the Allied and Associated Powersexamined this question.    They do net share the fea-s of the Ge &apos;manGove -,nment as to the economic effects which might result therefromfor the German ports.They adhere to the Protocol in the form, in which it is d-awnuo.After having received a complete list  of all the  floatingdocks,  floating cranes,  tugs, and dredgers,   demanded by the Protc-col,  the Allied and Associated Powers will make known their choice,takin&apos;r into account the general economic situations of the Go-manports.If the German Government then considers it can show that oneof the said demands is of  such a nature as to affect  seriouslythe capacity of Germany to satisfy its legitimate needs in respectof the maintenance of its  river navigation c- other vital  economicDPAFT NOTE TJL-GJl&amp;i^JISLEGATION.Proposed by the Supreme Council,December 6,  1919.
interests of the sa..o class, the German Government can presentits claims to the Principal Allied and Associated Powers, who,  ontheir part, will be prepared to examine them in a spirit of equity after hearing the views of the Reparations Commission.(9) As regards the last paragraph of the Protocol of November 1,the Supreme Council hold what the signature of the said Protocol,and the deposit, of the ratification., decide the coming intooperation of the Treaty ahd consequently the state of Peace.    it follows that execution&quot; of the provisions of the Protocol,  onwhich the coming into operation of the Treaty of Peace is depend-ent, will be guaranteed by the general stipulations of that treaty as well as by application of the ordinary rules recog-nised by the law of nations.Draft proposed by, the.Sue; erne Council,.(10) Pntil the Treaty of Peace ooraeg into operation the dentineia-tion of the Armistice suffices to leave the Allied Armies everylatitude as cegarde such military measures as they might consider necessary.    If the German Government continues to defer signature of the Protocol and thereby definitely to ratify the Treaty, theSupreme Council are determined without further delay to placeGermany in face of a rupture cf the Armistice with all the con-sequences which would follow therefrom.pro,ft proposed, by, .theConference.*(10)  The Allies mast, insist, therefore, that there should be nofurthe^ delay in the signature of the Protocol and the conclusionof Peace.
(Thij3 Document in the property of : H-la. Drjtannio*&quot; Ma jo&quot; gpyjV Gc ye rr.:-. [nt,&apos;)Notes of a Conference held &amp;t 10-, Downing Street, S.PT.1on MONDAY,  DECEMBER -8,  1919,  at 11-15 a.&apos;m.PRKSFNT:-The Prime Minister (in the Chair),The Right  Hon. A. Bonar Law, H,p lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Pight Hon. Sari Curaon of kedleston, K. G-., G. C-.-S. I-,.,G.C.I.E.,  Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.S.Churchill, M.P.,The Right Hon.Seoretary of State for Tarand Air.The  Right Hon. (Ti-H, Long, M.F.,First Lord of the Admiralty.The following was also present:-Field Marshal Sir H,H.Wilson, G .G .B., B. S.0.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Lieut..-Colonel Sir M.P.A. hankey, G.O.B.,  Secretary.
j ., 193t&amp;f-KMANY AND (1) ^ith refe-er.ce to their meeting held on Saturday,Ujp PATXFTCA-.?ICN CP December 5th., at 0-30 p,:t, the Conference had be Fore themPSACE.a telegram dated December ?th.   ^No.1670)  from Sir Eyre Crowe,reporting the results of an interview which he and Mr PhilipXerr had had with Li.  Oiemenceau (Appendix) .M,  Glerneneeau had net  been able to agree to the draftof the final paragraph of the  despatch to Germany proposedby the Conference,  but had agreed to accept a $-resa-eh draft,which was  translated in the telegram as follows* Until the Treaty comes into, for oe we  remindGermany once more  (une der^iere fois)  thata denunciation of the Armistice suffices toleave the Allied Armies every latitude asregards  such military measures   as they  may consider necessary.    This being the situation(literal:    dans net esprit) we await the signature of the Protocol and the deoositof ratifications without further delay&quot;.The Conference took note that M.  Clemenceau hadreiterated his firm conviction that  even in this revised formthe note would undoubtedly lead to Germany&apos;s immediate acceptahoe of the demands of the Allies.    Their attention was drawnhowever,  to an interview,reported in &quot;The Daily Mail&quot;,withFerr Noske,  the  e -man ^a.&quot; Minister,  in which the latter had stated categorically  that he would recommend the GermanGovernment  not to sign the Protocol.The  Chief of the Lope rial General Staff also reportedthat Marshal Foch was yerj doubtful if the Germans would signPiile the  Conference felt that - the draft now proposed was less satisfactory than the draft they had themselvessuggested,   and that the evidence of its probable acceptance by the Germans was by no means satisfactory, nevertheless,having regard to the fact that the American plenipotentiarieswould be  leaving Paris on the following day,  the-&apos; felt thatno other  course was open to them than to accept the new draft,  which was,  at any rate,  a substantial improvement onthe original draft.      It was therefore agreed  That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs  should immediately inform Sir EyreCrowe that  the new draft was accepted byIthe British Government, and that he had authority to sign the despatch.
FUTURE OF THE PEACE CONFERENCE.

(2) It was generally agreed that the present constitution of the Supreme Council in Paris was not altogether satisfactory, and that sufficient safeguards were not provided against crises such as that now under consideration. Owing to the exigencies of political business at home, it is impossible to spare a Cabinet Minister, and Great Britain is only represented by an official of the Foreign Office. Great Britain is therefore at a disadvantage compared with France, which is represented by one of the greatest statesmen of the day. The withdrawal of the American representative was, therefore, held to provide a good opportunity for re-considering the future of the Peace Conference, and with this object in view it was considered desirable that, Sir Eyre Crowe should accompany M.  Clemenceau on his forthcoming visit to London.

It was agreed --

That the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should instruct Sir Eyre Crowe to accompany M. Clemenceau on his forth-coming visit to London.

ITALY AND THE ADRIATIC.

(3) The attention of the Conference was invited to the latest development in the attitude of the Allied and Associationed Powers towards Italy&apos;s claims in the Adriatic.

The British, French and American representatives on the Supreme Council had recently drawn up a statement of the present attitude of their respective Governments towards the Italian claims. They had proposed to communicate this statement to Signor Scialo ja, the new Italian Foreign Minister, before his departure for London. At the request, however, of the British Government, who had felt that it would embarrass them in their conversations with Signor Scialo ja if this memorandum had been presented, the matter had been postponed. Sir Eyre Crowe had now telegraphed pointing out that if there were any further delay in signing the memorandum it would be impossible to obtain the signature of an American plenipotentiary, since the American Delegation


was leaving Paris on December Oth.    He therefore asked for authority to sign,  with a view to the memorandum beingpresented to Signer Scialoja on his return from London.The Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs wished tohave tho -hews of the Conference both as to Sir Eyre Crowe&apos;request and as  to  the attitude he himself should adopt towardsSigner Scialoja,  whom he was expecting to meet at luncheon.Would he,  for example, be justified in showing signer Scialo^atine memorandum ?    Should he give any indication that thememorandum might be altered after his conversation withSigner scialoja ?    in this latter connection he drew atten-tion to the danger that signer Scialoja might make anattempt to divide the British,  French and American Govern-ments on the subject.The general opinion of the Conference was in thefollowing sense :-(a) That the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs would be justified in givingSigner Scialoja the gist of the memorandum,explaining to him that this was what theAllies proposed to present  to the ItalianGovernment,   and that he thought that assign or scialqjy. was in London it would be only right to talk to him about it:(b) That  the Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs should reserve his decision inregard, to Sir Ey^e Crowe&apos;s request for authority to sign the memorandum until after he had seen Signer scialoja:(c) In any case,   anything in the nature ofan ultimatum to Italy must be avoided.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.W.  1.8th December,  1919.
pb cypher;-   Sir-       Crowe (Astoria, Paris),No . 1670.-    ---&quot;  ------* -SUP&quot; COMMITTEE .If. aft No to to Gerraspy .. ...... iffr;Kerr and -1 saw II: 01 cm apeeau to^hight on his return&apos; from/country, .   He agrees tc- omission of second sentence of concluding paragraph of note;   . The first sentence of that paragraph roalhy^fsprms part ftf argument in preceding paragraph 9/ Which contains.withdrawal from posit ion we had taken u*p in protocol.     The protocolhad explicitly reserved, right of Allies in ease of non-fulfilment of its conditions to revert to such military measures as might be required to enforce their demands.   &apos; To this Germans objected that as signature(69411)  tf ProtCaol is to coincide with coming - into.forcewe. should at once come under conditions of.peace whichwould not admit of one party proceeding to reopenhostilities without a fresh declaratiOn o.f war.     We hayerecognised force of this argument and conceded Germanpoint by saying that once peace is re-^stabolished bycoming into forceof treaty- or deposit of ratification modifications ions,the treaty itself will afford necessary guarantees forenforcement of stipulations of Protocol and that ordinaryrules of law of nations i.o.     No hoekl-litles prior todecle.ratlon of war, will apply.      But we atfd. (group unde-oypherable)   in first sentence of concluding paragraph,until- treaty of peace does become operative,, the Alliesretain power to resort&quot;to military measures by simplytermltis&amp;tiing armistice. - -This is a statement. of fact.-      It is moreover merelya restatement of what was already said to Germans in note in whiah we invited thamptc sig;n Protocol. .    To withdrawthis warning altogether in face of Ge.rmjj.ny having re-galled her delegates in answer to request to sign.Protocol seemo to M,  Clemenceau to go top fav9     &quot;He is however Willing to attenuate sentence by making it &quot;quite clear that, whilst  conceding German view of true positionas regards resort to military measures, we recallwarning, already given that such resort though notcompatible with a stato. of peace would always remainop&amp;n to Allies under&apos; rSgimc of a. prolonged armistice.11/ Clamenceau would- accordingly accept following,wording for concluding paragraph   -   1 translate literallyfrem French:&apos;
Until treaty comes into force we remind Germany once more (une derniere fois) that a denunciation of the armistice suffices to leave Allied armies every latitude as regards such military measures as they may consider necessary. This being the situation (literally: dans cet esprit) we await signature of the Protocol and deposit of ratifications without further delay.

M. Clemenceau reiterates his firm conviction that even in this revised form the note would undoubtedly lead to Germany&apos;s prompt acceptance of our demands.                              

We said that of course we had no authority to accept this wording but we agreed to refer it to His Majesty&apos;s Government. He was emphatic as to his inability to go any further in his concessions to British view he had earnestly requested our acceptance. He repeated what he had already declared at Supreme Counci1 that French Government did not in any case contemplate military operations at present juncture.

M. Clemenceau cordially agreed to come over to London on Wednesday or Thursday provided that this question was decided and out of the way.

As regards Scapa Flow reparation Mr. Polk&apos;s message as described in my telegram No.1657 to which Prime Minister&apos;s message to Mr. Kerr refers was modified subsequently as reported in my telegram No. 1662 when he agreed to formula which I had altered to meet his objection. The sole difference between Mr. Polk&apos;s last proposal and that now adopted is that whilst he left ultimate decision entirely to Reparations Commission the version adopted retains authority of Allies and Associated Governments to decide after hearing Reparations Commission. In pressing more effectual provision which I got adapted I have throughout acted on (group undecypherable) representations of my Naval advisers who had their instructions from Admiralty. If in light of these observations you still think that we should revert to original American proposal I will raise question at tomorrow&apos;s meeting of Supreme Council on receiving your instructions to this effect.

May I remind you that Mr. Polk&apos;s departure on Tuesday December 9th makes it imperative to get note to Germans signed and despatched tomorrow. Could you therefore let me have decision as early as possible tomorrow?

</content>
</cab>
