<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 83-94</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).CONFIDENTIAL. CP. 4114.LEAGUE   OF   NATIONS. MANDATES FOR PALESTINE AND SYRIA.Provisional Minutes of a Private Meeting of the Council of the League of Nations held on 19th July, 1922 at St. James&apos; Palace.(Circulated for information).2, \&apos;whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. 20th July, 1922.
PRESENT:-       All the Members of the Council, and The Secretary-General.^A&apos;^^M A g If A T E S.M. VIVIANI asked that the Syrian Mandate should be dis-dussed by the Council box ore tho Palestine Mandate .     It would create an intolerable situation for Prance if the Palestine Mandate were to be awarded to Great Britain and discussion of the Syrian Mandate postponed.     This would cause administrative difficulties of the gravest nature for the French authorities in Syria.LORD BALFOUR recalled the fact that the present meeting was an exceptional meeting convened primarily for the purpose of dealing with the Palestine Mandate.     In May last, he had &quot;brought forward before the Council in Geneva the question ef the Palestine Mandate.     Certain of his Colleagues had then taken the view that insufficient notice of the question had been given to enable it to be adequately discussed.      On that occasion, he had pointed out the dangers of delay, to the territories concerned- mainly through the encouragement of vain and empty hopes among certain sections of the population. Be had pointed out also how unfair it was to the mandatory Power to compel it to carry out its difficult, and some Thanes thankless task under such a handicap.     He had, therefore, urgently pressed that the question of the Palestine Mandate should be then and there discussed.,      In deference, however, to his Colleagues- views,  he had reluctantly agreed to a short postponement of the discussion.     At the same time he had suggested the end of June as a. possible date.     &apos;M.Bourgeois had considered this period to be too. short, . .n&amp; had suggested July 10th.     It was now July 19th,  and he submitted., that itHwould/
would be tantamount to a breach of an understanding arrived at between the Members of the Council, If the Palestine Man-date were not immediately discussed.He felt great sympathy with M. Viviani&apos;s observations regarding the inconvenience which would be caused to the French administration in Syria if the Palestine Mandate were awarded to Great Britain at the present meeting, and the question of the Syrian Mandate were postponed.     M. Bourgeois had pointed out the same thing in May.    He himself earneistly hoped  that both the Mandates could be dealt with at the present session of the Council.     He was unable, however, to agree that in the actual discussion of the intrinsic merits of the Mandates the Syrian Mandate should take precedence of the Palestine Mandate. If M. Vivian! stated that it was impossible for France to accept the Palestine Mandate unless the Syrian Mandate was dealt with at the same session, M. Vivian! had his warmest support and sympathy.There were really two points involved -(1)     A question of procedure.     The question whether the Council should deal with the Palestine Mandate alone or with the Palestine Mandate and the Syrian Mandate during the present session.(2)      The question of the intrinsic merits of the two Mandates.If M. Vivian! meant that the question of procedure, whether-the two Mandates could be separately awarded or not, should be first discussed&apos;; ho agreed entirely.     When, however, the Council came to discuss the second point, he was obliged to request that the Palestine Mandate should ha&apos;e precedence.THE MaHQUIS IMPERIAL I recalled &quot;Che fact that when the question of. the Palestine Mandate had been brought forward by Lord Balfour at the last meeting, he had st;,fced the reasons why/
he was unable to agree that the question should be then and there discussed.     He had explained that at the titae an exchange of views was talcing place between the British and the Italian Governments on certain details arising out of the question of the Palestine Mandate which were of the.greatest importance to the Italian Government.     He had then stated that he expected shortly to be in a position to give the. consent of his Govern-ment to the Palestine Mandate,:     Since that date the discussions between the two Governments had been bi-ought to a satisfactory conclusion.He was now in a somewhat similar position as regards the Syrian. Mandate.     he had not. expected that the question of the Syrian Mandate would be discussed at this session.     The ques-tion of the Syrian Mandate was now the subject of an exchange of views between the French and Italian Governments.     He personally had no doubt that these conversations would be brought to a satisfactory conclusion, but they were not yet terminated, and pending such conclusion he was unable, in the absence of instructions from his Government? to agree that the Syrian Mandate should be finally disposed of at the otsrrent session.     He would now make to M. Viviani the same request which he had made in May to Lord Balfour, namely, to allow a brief period for the indispensable exchange of vie?/s.M. VJP7IAHI observed that the attitude taken up by the Marquis Inrperiali had altered the situation.      It would appear that the Marquis Imperiali was unable to agree to an immediate discussion of the Syrian Mandate.     If the Palestine Mandate were to be discussed and perhaps awarded to Great Britain, and if then the Marquis Imperiali were to maintain his objection to the discussion of the Syrian Mandate,the situation m would be/
intolerable for Prance.     He was not in a position to agree to any procedure which would make it possible for a situation of this nature to ariseiOn the general question of Italy&apos;s attitude to the mandates, he wished to point out that it was now nearly two and a half years since the French Government nad formally applied for the Syrian mandate *     During this period the Italian Government had raised no objections.    The objection now raised, couia, therefore, only refer to the modifications suggested by the Government of the United States.     These modifications were, moreover, unimportant and purely on points of detail.     The Continued delay involved by these last minute objections was having a most prejudicial effect upon the territories involved, and was wasting the time of the League.     If there were never to be any sacrifices of national feeling in order to secure agreement on important questions, the utility of the League of Nations would appear to be considerably diminished.He pointed out that the situation created by the attitude of the Marquis Imperial! amounted to an impasse.     The Marquis Imperial! could not agree to the discussion of the S?/rian mandate.      In this case he himself could not agree to the discussion of the Palestine mandate.As regards the present exchange of views between the French and Italian Governments, he was read:/ to give the Marquis Imperiall every possible information.The MARQUIS IMPERIAL! stated that for two years the view of the Italian Government on the Palestine and. Syrian mandates had been perfectly well known.     The main point of this view was that the fate of these mandates should be bound&apos; up with that of the Treaty of Sevres.     This point of view had also been approved by the last Assembly after a discussion in the Political CoTnmittee.
The reservations made by the Italian Government were not reservations of principle.     When Lord Balfour raised the question of the Palestine mandate in May, he had stated ttiat the Italian Government agreed in principle.     The Italian Government was ready to make the same Statement as regards the Syrian mandate.     It considered the question of principle .as definitively settled in both cases, and in the case of the Syrian mandate it was how only waiting for the conclusion of conversations with the French Government on certain points of detail affecting Italian interests in the mandated territory. In these circumstances it was perhaps a little exaggerated to lay formal responsibility upon the Italian Government for obstructing the passage of the mandates.LORD BALFOUR thought that the Marquis Imperial! would agree upon reflection that when this question oame to be dis-cussed in a public session - as- It would Inevitably have to be discussed - his defence of the Italian Governments attitude might seem somewhat inadequate.     The question of these mandates had now been delayed for more than two years.     There had been no new factors in the problem, no new proposals.     Indeed, if It had not been for the letter in February 1921 from the Govern-ment of the United States, all the mandates would then and therehave been awarded.     The intervention of the Government of theaUnited States had caused/delay In the granting of the mandates which was most regret &quot;cable from an administrative point of view, but this delay had afforded the Italian Government even greater opportunities than before to consider and make up its mind upon the question.It had come as a complete surprise to him that now, in the middle of July 1922, there suouid be an objection on the part of the Italian Government to the discussion of the Syrian mandate. It must have been clear to the&apos; Italian Government In May last that the French contention that it was impossible to give one of these mandates and to withhold the other - the historical,
national, and geographical connection of the two territories being so close - made it inevitable that the question of the Syrian mandate would bo raised by the French representative on the Council when the Palestine mandate was discussed...    Since the date of the. last meeting the Italian Government had boon per-perfectly aware that the British Government attached the utmost importance to the early award of -the Palestine mandate.   Every weekls delay in this matter was the cause of great inconvenience both to the mandatory power and to the mandated territory.   The Italian Government also knew that, at considerable inconvenience to everyone concerned, a special meeting of the Council had been convened with the precise object of avoiding delay in the settlement of the question.     The Italian Government also knew that it would be impossible without grave difficulties to secure the passing of the Palestine mandate, if the question of the Syrian mandate was postponed; and yet it was not until July 18th that he had been informed of the intention of the Italian Government to delay or postpone the discussion of the Syrian mandate.   It was evident that by this action the award of the Palestine mandate was endangered.   This would have the most serious results.     The delay would encourage every possible counter-influence and put fresh strength into those parties which were trying in this matter to thwart the intentions of the Allied and Associated Powers.     It would also cause the gravest administrative difficulties in the mandated territory.   He coulfi hardly believe that upon a dispassionate survey of the facts the Italian Government would, not feel that its responsibility in the matter was very great, above all, since he himself would be compel led within a few days to make in public the statement which he was now making in private.   He felt sure that the general effect upon public opinion would be to create the view that the machinery of the League of Hations had not been used to the best advantage, end thatthe//
the immensempowers ^he-wo-Aild,&quot;uo-fc-aay of --obstruction, hut of delay accorded to the members of thp Oouncil had b-een in this instance used in a manner &quot;which would bring, if not discredit, upon the working of the League,, at least a feeling of something approaching, despair to those who had to work the machinery.     How could these continual delays be justified?     The Oouncil would have to bear the onus of responsibility for them.     He would earnestly beg the Marquis Imperiali to consider most carefully whether r he could find it  in any way consistent with his instructions to withdraw from the position which he had taken up and to allow the Council to proceed now to do what shotild have been done two years ago, instead of causing further delays by an attitude which he believed was not supported by any of his colleagues .THE MARQUIS IMPERIAL! said that the Italian Government had made its declaration on the extent to which the fate of the Treaty of Sevres was bound tip with that of the    an dates, even before the disciission which arose out of the intervention of the united states.     If the question at present before the Council had been raised in &apos;, arch 1921, he would have had to make the same declarations as those he had just made. Italy had fully adhered to the granting of the mandates to prance and to the British Empire, but she had not,therefore, lost the right to watch over the interests of her nationals which, as he had already explained, were concerned only with points of detail.     As regards the exchange of views at Paris between M. roincare, .; ord Curzon, and LI, Schanzer, of which M. Viviani had spoken, he would only say that he had not been informed by his Government of the progress of these conversations.     He could not hind his Government beforethe/
the Council, especially in view of the fact that the question at Issue was one of high policy. It was above all necessary that he should await the instructions of his Government.VISCOUNT ISIiTI reminded the Council that a similar situation had arisen in regard to the &quot;C11 Mandate which had been approved in 1920,     The British and Japanese Governments had not been in agreement in regard to certain provisions of the Mandate, but public opinion had pressed strongly for immediate action.     The Council had agreed to deal with the difficulty by approving the Mandate subject to an exceptional provision to the effect that the Japanese Government reserved the right to discuss&apos;&quot;the -questions still outstanding with, -the British Government.     By this procedure the.Council was enabled to present the Mandate to the.Assembly without further delay.     Would it not be possible.for the Italian Government to assent in the same way to the Mandate for Syria, reserving the right to discuss outstanding details with the French Government?The MARQUIS IMP3RIALI was not acquainted with the detailed points upon which his Government desired, to come to an under-standing with the French Government.     The final terms of the Syrian Mandate had onl?/- been communicated to his Government on Thursday evening lastj    there had not, therefore, been sufficient time to examine them.     The Italian Government which had already come to an agreement with the British Government would certainly be able  to reach an agreement, with the French Government.     He could only, however, maintain his previous attitude and consult his Government.
VIVIANI said that the Mandates had been oommunic-ate-d to the Italian Government for the last two and a half years. The only new information which the Italian Government could have received on the subject on Thursday evening last,, was the information concerning the &quot;unimportant&quot; modifications proposed by the Government of the United States.    The reservations therefore, made by the Marquis Imperiali did not touch the principle of the Mandate but only related to the American modifications.He pointed out that if modifications were to be intro-duced the Mandate would have to be sent to America,The MARQUIS IMPERIALI protested that the objections formulated by his Government had no connection with the modifications proposed by the United States.    There was therefore no question of a fresh discussidn with the Government of the United States.M VIVIANI stated that he was forced logically to the conclusion that the objections of the Italian Government concerned the principle of the Mandate, with which Italy had been acquainted for two years and a half without having raised any objection,The MAB&amp;this IMPERIALI urged the absolute necessity of a preliminary conversation between the French and Italian Government just as there had been an exchange of views between the British and Italian Governments on the subject of the Palestine Mandate.LORD BALFOUR briefly resumed the pedttdnn.    The Italian Representative was bound by the instructions of his Government to oppose the discussion of the Mandate for Syria.    The French Representative was similarly bound to oppose the discussion of tho Mandate for Palestine, if the Mandate for Syria were net take at the same time.    It, followed that unless the Italian Government could be induced to modify its attitude,
tho Council would ho unable to make any progress, and a most deplorable delay would ensue.    The Council would thus be obliged publicly to confess its impotence, and would, cut a very poor -figure before the public -end before the Assembly.. He hoped that the Marquis Imperial! would be able to obtain the as-sent of the Italian -Government to an immediate dis-cuGolon and -that they would thus be able to avoid failure in a matter on which all the rest of the Council were: agreed. He proposed that,;pending a reply from the Italian Government to the representations of - the Italian Representative on the Council, the question of &apos;the&quot;&quot;A&quot;Mandates should be adjourned. It was understood that the two Mandates would be taken together, but he would suggest that it might perhaps&apos;be possible to have a preliminary discussion of some of the subsidiary questions- raised by the Mandate for Palestine.The MARQ.UI8 IMPERIAL! stated that he would inform his Government of the position an.&quot;, would ask for explanations on the subject of the conversation- which were takin- piece in Paris.   He added that between the present -meet in,-- and. tho next meeting of the Assembly, there would be another meeting of the Council.   He did not think that public opinion could blame his Government if it asked for a delay of one or two weeks in orde    to obtain certain informed,ion, in view of the fact that the vital interest of his country were at stake.2-T. H5fMAS&apos;S considered that there were two main points at issue:1.    The peace of the world. i,e. the necessity of settling the future of Asia Minor by a simultaneous grant of the Mandate-,2.    Tho interests of the League of Nations.public opinion should not be lost si;?ht&apos; of.    The real reason for the convocation of the present session *-&apos;as the question of the-e two mandates.   Any sc-Wback on the question woul;: rirhtly give rise to suspicion.
He thought that after the 3&apos;Iarquis Iraperiali had consulted his Government it would be possible to arrive at a solution. He also noted the declaration of the Marquis Ircperiali that no question of principle was involved in this matter.    The whole question turned therefore on points of detail, which would presumably be settled by an agreement between the French and Italian Governments.    He expressed his agreement -with Viscount Ishii&apos;s suggestion.M. TANG TSAI FOU and K. Da GAMA expressed their agreement with K. Hymans.THh PRESIDENT observed that the two mandates were Intimately connected and that one could not be discussed without the other.The MARMOTS IMP3RIALI saw no objection to a discussion of minor questions arising out of the Palestine Mandate&apos;.M, VIVIAN! agreed that there might be one or two points which could be discussed which did not touch questions of principlej but in view of the danger that secondary questions might become fundamental it would be perhaps better to discuss the Mandates as a whole&apos;.After discussion,  the Council decided to adjourn the discusnion on the question of&quot;A&quot;Mandates in order to give the Marquis Imperial! an opportunity of receiving instructions from his government 

</content>
</cab>
