<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 138-140</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.SECRET.CP. 4121.THE CABINET.REPORT ON THE SITUATION IN IRELAND FOR THE WEEKENDING 15th JULY, 1922.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.I circulate the report on the Irish situation by the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief. Ireland, for the week ending the 15th instant.L. W.-E.The War Office,  .24th July, 1922.Southern Ireland.(a) Dublin. The week has passed quietly in Dublin and the sniping at night has practically ceased.The life of the city is again normal.The Tailteann Games, which were to have taken place this month, will not now be held until August, 1923 ; but it is understood that the Dublin Horse Show will take place next month as arranged.Information is in our possession which goes to show that Rory 0&apos;Connor thought that British troops would be employed in forcing him to evacuate the Four Courts, and that, after consideration, it was decided that resistance to British troops would be good propaganda. The same source states that the ultimatum of the Provisional Government came as a surprise, and that the mines which destroyed the Four Courts had been laid previouslj&apos; with a view to resistance against a British attack only.The Republican prisoners in Mountjoy Gaol gave a good deal of trouble at the beginning of the week, and, after many warnings, the guard was obliged to fire on certain individuals who insisted on leaning out of the windows and signalling to their friends outside the prison walls. Two prisoners were slightly wounded as a result and matters are now quiet.About 7th July the Provisional Government gave the Press in Dublin to understand very clearly that, in the present state of -the country, they would not agree to any compromise between the forces of law and order and the Republicans. The Press was to take no part therefore in any attempt to come to an understanding. This shows that the leaders of the Provisional Government, at any rate, realise the futility of a policy of concession as a means of suppression of disorder and outrage.There is no doubt but that the Provisional Government mean business. On 13th July a War Council was formed, composed of Mr. Collins as Commander-in-Chief, Richard Mulcahy as Chief of Staff and Eoin 0&apos;Duffy. The first meeting of the new parliament has been postponed for a fortnight, and every effort is being made to enrol volunteers and to encourage the population by means of propaganda. In this latter connection small leaflets are being circulated throughout the city.(b) Outside Dublin. Except in Munster and Co. Mayo the situation is improving slowly.The towns of Galway, Wexford and Dundalk have been cleared of Republicans. Dundalk appears to have been occupied by surprise and most of the 300 rebels captured were taken in their beds at daybreak on Sunday, 16th July.(B22/208)   100   7/22   W.OP.   215
The Provisional Government troop? had a minor set-back near Sligo on 13th July. An armoured Lancia car and two Crossley loads of Provisional Government men were ambushed. The whole party was captured, with known casualties of 5 killed and 4 wounded. Information to the above effect was conveyed to the Officer Commanding British troops at Belleek by the Officer Commanding Provisional Government troops at Bally-shannon (Co. Donegal) ; the Provisional Government officer also stated that there were about 600 armed Republicans near Sligo, and as he himself had only about 70 men armed with rifles and very little ammunition, and as there were only 25 Provisional Government men with arms at Finner Camp close by, he was very anxious to borrow guns, armoured cars, rifles and ammunition from the&apos; British in case he should be attacked ! His exorbitant demands were met by the loan of 8,000 rounds of small-arm ammunition and some spare parts for a Lewis gun.The repeated calls for 18-pr. guns and armoured cars by their troops in other parts of Co/Donegal were met by the Provisional Government on 14th July, when the small steamer &quot; Helgar,&quot; loaded up at North Wall, Dublin, with one 18-pr. and two Rolls Royce armoured cars, reached Buncrana in Lough Swilly. With the help of this field gun the Republican stronghold on Inch Island, Lough Swilly, was taken with 21 prisoners.There was also fighting at Collooney, Co. Sligo, during the week-end, and over 70 Republicans were taken prisoners in this affair.On the whole the Press continues to exaggerate, out of all proportion, the severity, of the &quot; fighting.&quot;   Casualties on both sides are very few and far between.In no case, whatever may be said beforehand, do the Republicans stand and fight to a finish. An individual who has just lately reached Dublin from Waterford, which town is in the hands of the rebels, states that these irregulars are quite ready to leave &quot; by the back door &quot; as soon as the Provisional Government troops approach the town.Very little news is available regarding the situation in Munster generally. The newspapers report fighting during the week-end in Limerick City, and it is understood that the Provisional Government troops will first clear that town before moving south-westwards ; they have already cleared Thurles.Cork City is quiet, but is entirely in the hands of the Republicans.According to Naval reports from Haulbowline, the rebels have forced the Collector of Customs at Cork to write out a cheque for them for  10,000 ; and have occupied Roche&apos;s Point lighthouse at the eastern entrance to Cork Harbour.The railway situation varies from day to day. Trains have run normally on the main Dublin Belfast line during the week; but on the Great Southern and Western Railway there are no trains south of Thurles, and on the Midland, there are no trains west of Athlone or north-west of Ballymote. On the Dublin and South-Eastern Railway traffic is at present normal between Dublin and Wexford, and as far as New Ross on the branch line to Waterford.The national response to the call for volunteers is improving. It is interesting to note that the 1st, 2nd and 3rd Northern Divisions are not included in the new &quot; Command &quot; organization as published in An T&apos;Oglach. The two latter divisions would naturally be disregarded as they are entirely in Northern Government territory.In conclusion, all reports tend to confirm the impression that the vast majority of the population of Southern Ireland are with the Provisional Government in its attempts to restore the normal life of the country.Northern Ireland.The quietness within the six Ulster counties has been maintained, the attention of the general public being still directed to the events taking place in the Free State, where the offensive action of the Provisional Government troops is almost universally approved.Within the Six Counties the Irish Republican Army are still lying extremely low, though signs are not wanting that in at least one division the work of reorganization is going forward, and activity may be resumed within the near future.Police activity has been maintained with good results, and further successful raids have been carried out in Belfast and at Enniskillen, and a number of important and interesting documents have been brought to light. Amongst the papers found at Enniskillen were orders and pay rolls for the South Fermanagh Brigade. These show definitely that during April and May this year the South Fermanagh Brigade, though situated and operating within the Six County area, was administered by and took orders
from the 1st Midland Division, the Commandant of which was &quot; Major-General&quot; Sean McKeown, T.D., the principal military supporter of Collins and. the Provisional Govern-ment.The most important raid in Belfast was that on the headquarters of No. 2 Battalion, 1st Brigade, 3rd Northern Division, the second battalion headquarters to be raided by Crown forces within ten days. Documents seized during the course of this search show that two companies of executive Irish Republican Army exist in Belfast. Between these and the Provisional Government troops there appears to be little love lost, and an interesting account of a fight at the end of June between the two parties is given. From these documents it also appears that both sections of Irish Republican Army are impli-cated in the arson campaign, though the murder of members of the Crown forces is confined to the &quot; Executives.&quot;C. F. N. MACREADY, General,C ommanding-in-Chief, Ireland.General Headquarters,Dublin. *&apos;18th July, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
