<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 193-194</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
sfrU *^f)Hv** &apos;.    i5fiThis document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.SECRET.CP. 4130.THE CABINET.CROWN AND GOVERNMENT LANDS.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.The effect, so far as the War Office is concerned, of the recommendations of the Gen. No. 8 Committee on Crown and Government Lands, whose reports were recently circulated &quot; 1189 with a note by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, CP. 4037, dated 16th June, 1921, would be : (1) The entire Lands Branch of the War Office would be transferred to a Central Lands Department under a Board of Management responsible to the Treasury.(2) All professional work in connection with the valuation, purchase and sale ofland and buildings would be undertaken by the Central Lands Departmentacting as the agent for the War Office. (3) Command Land Agents would be absorbed in the Central Lands Department,and the Estate management of War Department Lands would be dealt.with bv officers &quot;seconded&quot; from the Central Lands Department to theWar Office.As regards (1), it seems to be unsound that there should be no permanent expert personnel in the War Office to deal with holdings of over 200,000 acres. The delays and difficulties involved through the necessity of reference to an outside department would be considerable. Further, the Committee do not seem to have considered Government lands abroad, on which the advice of the present Lands Branch of the War Office is of great value. It seems essential that the War Office should retain a small Headquarters Lands Branch.As regards (2), it will be essential in any event to adhere strictly to the recom-mendatios contained in paragraph 9 of the Final Report that, &quot; in conducting purchases and sales of property, the central body would not be concerned with any questions of policy, in regard to which the decision must obviously be taken by the department responsible to Parliament &quot;; and also that the surveyor in charge of War Department purchases should be placed at the disposal of the Department. This latter condition is indispensable if the annual purchase programme is to be carried through within the&apos; financial year, an achievement which is difficult enough even under existing conditions, and would be quite impossible, if formal correspondence with a separate department were necessary on all the points of detail that arise in the course of negotiations.It is not clear how the Committee propose that hirings should be dealt with, but in this case it is thought that the functions of the Central Department should be limited to giving technical advice, when required.As regards (3), the Committee say in paragraph 14 of their Final Report that the officers &quot; seconded &quot; to the War Department &quot; should feel that they have the full strength of the Central Lands Department behind them.&quot; If it is contemplated that these Land Agents will be in direct communication with the Central Department and will seek and receive instructions and guidance from that department, the use of the word &quot; second &quot; is misleading. A seconded officer does not communicate with his regiment about his duties, or feel that he has the full strength of his regiment behind him. The position would rather be that of an officer attached to a formation not his own, for the performance of certain technical duties.I understand, however, from the Director-General of Lands, who was Chairman of the Committee, that the Committee intended that these &quot; seconded &quot; Land Agents would
be left entirely to the War Office, so long as required, and be responsible to the War Office for discipline and instructions in just the same way as men lent by other Government Departments.I hope that this interpretation of the report may be accepted. Dual control does not make for satisfactory administration, and I am of opinion that the Command Land Agents should owe undivided allegiance to the War Office, by whom they should be paid and from whom alone they should receive their orders.The balance between &quot; military &quot; and &quot; estate&quot; claims is always difficult to adjust, and the task of getting the best residual value out of military land will certainly not be made easier if military officers feel that the weight of an outside department, with purely &quot; estate &quot; interests, is being brought to bear on them through their expert advisers. The latter should, however, have every opportunity of informal consultation with the Central Lands Department on professional questions, of course with the cognizance of their departmental (War Office) superiors, and the Central Department should be invited from time to time to inspect War Department estates and call attention to any points which seem to them to require consideration.The Committee&apos;s recommendation1 that the Central Lands Department should deal with the disposal of land surplus to requirements is agreed to, but the proceeds should be credited as an appropriation-in-aid to War Office Votes.On the more general aspects of the question, I am opposed to any measure of centralization, for centralization^ sake, which will impair the direct responsibility to the Crown and to Parliament of a Minister on whom the duty of administering a department is laid. I am not convinced, on the information before me, that the economies anticipated will compensate for the difficulties and delays inseparable from a system of dual control.Moreover, I do not gather what the position or the Treasury vis-a-vis the War Office will be. If the new Central Department is responsible to the Treasury, the latter department will have to he satisfied twice over, first on the policy as is now the case, and secondly on the administrative details to give effect to that policy. Treasury control of policy is, of course, perfectly legitimate, and I do not demur to its continuance ; but intervention in administration is, I contend, not the function of the Treasury, and I cannot contemplate with equanimity any infringement of my responsibility in this regard. Not only is a question of principle involved, but administration would become more complicated and less efficient. . I think a Cabinet Committee of all the Ministers concerned should consider the Report.L. W.-E.The War Office,24th July, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
