<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 252-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^ dormant. 1b- the-&apos;pTOpeirfcy- -ofDLLs -Brxttannio Maj9sty*s Governmont).0 A B I ME T.IBTBRIilA.T1 QiffAL LABO&apos;JD QGEWER&amp;W&amp;,  THIRD......SBSSION,. GENEVA,.  19S1Proposed action on Draft Conventions and Recommendations,Memorandum by the Home Secretary.Draft Convention covioar:r.t.ng Workmen&apos; s Compensation in Agriculture.In his Memorandum (C0P04117) the Minister of Labour suggests that the words in this Draft Convention, &quot;accidents arising out of or in the course of their employment&quot; ought to be amended by substituting -51 and&quot; for &quot;or&quot;&apos;  so as to correspond exactly with the words in our Workmen1 s Compensation Act of 1908,,I am unable to agree in this stiggestio.no      In ray opinion the words used in the Convention - whether intentional or not - are distinctly preferable from a British point of view to the words &quot;accidents arising out of and in the course of their employment&quot;. The Workmen^ Compensation laws of many other countries are not limited -to accidents arising out of and in the course of employment;, but apply (with or without qualification) to accidents arising during employment.,      The effect therefore of altering the word &quot;or&quot; to &quot;and&quot; in the Convention would tie to raise serious doubts whether      j or how far the Convention would apply to such legislation, and whether the countries concerned would be under any obligation to extend their laws to the agricultural worker^I would point out that the words In the Convention as it stands appeared in the Draft Convention prepared by the Interna-tional Labour Office before the meeting of the Conference- and that      ji this text was accepted by the Cabinet who approved.an Instruction        -i to the Government Delegates directing them to support, this toxty and.   \ that in accordance with this instruction the Delegates voted&apos; for the Convention in its oresent form,I&apos; If any amendment were made,  it should be to &quot;and / or&quot;, but in   1,iI, I
llndustrlal UndertakingsI agree that the Government oughtI to undertake to ratify this Convention at present3 but it appears line that the attitude proposed to be adopted Is unnecessarily a^i lagonistio and likely to expose the Government to attack on the fund of lack of sympathy.      It will be borne in mind that the teption of the Weekly Rest is one  of the. matters referred to in liole 427 (General Principles) of the Labour Section of the Treaty Peaoe as of special and urgent importance.      I would suggest that :fannouncing its decision not to ratify the Draft Convention atIfsent, the Government should be content to base its decision on 1 fsot that the legislation which weuld be necessary to give fleet to the Convention, would undoubtedly give rise to much  -loussion and possibly to serious controversy and must take up aW deal of parliamentary time whioh pressure of other businessHp*Kes it impossible to provide at present.WL . . E * S *Hp July,  1922.opinion-no-alteration.should he made or suggested.      The only&apos; fjigation proposed on the State by this Convention is to see [at its Workmen.&apos;s Compensation legislation embraces agrioul-iral as well as industrial wage earners.      Consequently in e case of Great Britain where no distinction is drawnjWeen the agricultural and the industrial workers as regardsIfrloneri^ s Compensation, no harm can in any oaso be caused by j9 ratification of the Convention.i;      I am of opinion that the Government should decide to ratify lis Convention as it stands and that all that is necessary or jsirable in announcing this intention to Parliament is to explain It the only obligation entailed on the State by the Convention is f extend its Workmen&apos;s Compensation Acts to agricultural wage yrners, and that as this condition is already, and has been ever .advance 1900; fulfilled in this country, no legislative or other lion to give effect to the Convention will be necessary on tho It of His Majesty5 s Government.aft Convention concerning the Application of the Weekly Rest Day

</content>
</cab>
