<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 282-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.FOURTH SESSION OF THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR CONFERENCE, GENEVA,  .18TH OCTOBER,  1922.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OF LABOUR.all Governments Questionnaires in connection with the items on tho Agenda of the next Session of the International Labour Conference, which will opon at Geneva on 18th October, 1922.     The items are as follows :-I.   Revision of Part XIII of the Treaty ofVersailles and tho corresponding Parts of the other Treaties of Peaoe;(a) With a view to the roform of theconstitution of the Governing Body;(b) With a view bo modification as regardsthe periodicity of the Sessions of the ConferenceII.   Communication to the International LabourOffice of statistical and other information rogarding emigration and immigration and the repatriation and transport of omigrants.Although a request was made for the Replies tothoso Questionnaires to be furnished to the InternationalLabour Office in the first week in August, the Questionnaireswere not received in this country until recently andinsufficient time was given for complying with the requestof the International Labour Organisation.     The examinationof the Questionnaires by the Departments concerned has accordingly had to be undertaken under conditions of great pressure.     It is hoped,, howover, that by the end of thoweek, the draft Replies prepared to the Questionnaires by/theCABINET.EC RET. .P.4145.The International Labour Offico has oiroulated to
the Departments concerned will havo &quot;been examined and approved by the Interdepartmental International. Labour Committee, and that the propossd Replies will be circulated to the Cabinet within a fow days.It does not appear to be necessary, in view of the fact that these Replios have been examined by an Inter-departmental Committee, that they should be submitted to the full Cabinet for consideration, and I therefore suggest that a Sub-Committee of the Cabinet, say two . members of the Cabinet jointly with myself, might be appointed to deal with them.If the Replies proposed by tho British Government aro to have any influence, as it is hoped that they may, on the policy of tho International Labour Conference, it is desirable that they should be transmitted to the International Labour Office at tho earliest possible date, in order that thoy may be circulated to othor Members of the International Labour Organisation prior to the opening of the Conference.(Sgd.) T.J. UAONAMARA.Ministry of Labour. 2nd August,  1922.

</content>
</cab>
