<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 289-291</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cabinet.SO RET. COPY NO.4143.       UNE&amp;3fLOYIvtENT RELIEF.    LAND DRAINUOE AND AFFORESTATION.Memorandum by The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.I have read the memorandum (C.P.4136) circulated by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.I understand that this Question is to be considered by the new Cabinet Committee set up under the Chairmanship of the Prime Minister to-morrow the 4th August and as I am not a member of that Committee 1 am anxious that the Committee should be in possession of such facts as will enable them to appreciate both sides of the question.The whole question of unemployment during the coming Autumn has been considered by a special Inter-Departmental Committee appointed by Sir Alfred Mond to advise&quot; the Cabinet Committee on Unemployment which has, I understand, now been dissolved.     The Inter-Departmental Committee reported against afforestation in view of the line taken with regard to that subject by the Geddes&apos;Committee, but as regards Land Drainap-e, which includes water supply, there was a difference of opinion among the members of the Committee, who therefore contented themselves with giving both sides of the question fully and leaving the Cabinet Committee on Unemployment zc :iecide the issue.The matter was brought before the Cabinet Committee on Unemployment early last week when it was decoded without a dissentient that schemes of land drainare and at foret l-consideration should be continued during the coming autumn and winter-- or the lines of last autumn and winter.     Owing, however, to the fact that a supplementary estimate had already been laid which was understood to represent the maximum that the Chancellor felt it possible to advance for unemployment works during the current financial year., j;-The findings of the Cabinet Committee as set out in C.F.4126, have been referred to the Cabinet for decision,I am, therefore, anxious that the new Committee, when it meets to-morrow, may appreciate the desirability of drainage &quot;rater supply schemes and afforestation being continued,In the following remarks I deal more especially with drainage and water supply, as being the most capable of resulting in immediate benefit, not only to those whose lands are affected, but to the nation.1.     The schemes recently carried out have proved an unqualified success both from the point of view of absorbing -unemployed, who have shown themselves anxious to work even &quot;If it meant travelling considerable distances on foot or by bicycle, but also from the point of view of public benefit in that waterways which have beenlnnapartially derelict condition for many years have been cleaned and flooding has thereby been prevented.
2.      I have been pressed on all sides to continue these schemes during the summer but it was decided that no works of this kind should be carried out during the months when any unemployed agricultural labourers could normally be absorbed by the harvest. It has nevertheless been represented to me that the large majority of those enraged on drainage works will, as a matter of fact, be unemployed during the summer mtsnths.3,     It Is represented that there should be no unemployment in agriculture in view of the fact that agricultural labourers did not wish to be included in the Unemployment Insurance Act.     I contend that agriculture Is suffering from unemployment of a temporary character.     The figures given by the Minister of Labour indicate that there are some 1,300,000 unemployed of all classes at present. I submit therefore that we are dealing with an exceptional situation as the result of the Great t?ar and that if any special measures of relief are necessary to deal with this situation, there is no justification for deliberately leaving out one class of the unemployed community, especially when the work which that class can do is probably of far greater benefit than many other forms of relief work, such as even the making of roads,4.     Unemployment in towns and rural districts are inter-related.     A considerable portion of the unemployed in rural districts consists of persons who have returned to their homes in the country owing to their inability to find work in the towns and this category will be reached by land drainage schemes, which also benefit miscellaneous unemployed labour when carried out in the vicinity of large towns.5.     I submit that my proposals as regards land drainage represent emergency measures.     If the Government decide not to proceed with the schemes, the unemployment at present existing may become so acute in rural districts that the Government may be&quot; forced later on to improvise hastily-prspared schemes which are bound to fall short of their object.     It Is sus/rested by the Chancellor that agricultural labourers could participitate in the St. Dav.Ld&apos;s Committee relief schemes, for the continuance of which provision is being made.      I submit that this could be done only to a limited degree.     No grant can be made in aid of schemes submitted to that Committee unless the Minister of Labour is prepared to certify the area as one of serious unemployment. It is difficult to do this in the case of rural areas.     It does not necessarily follow, however, that because the actual number of unemployed In such an area Is comparatively small that area may be regarded as free from serious unemployment,     A few unemploved in a village may be just as serious a matter as a large number of unemployed in a large industrial town and I submit that these men could be provided for under my drainage proposals and could be better employed on remunerative work rather than come down on the assistance provided by the Poor Law Authorities,     In other words, I am satisfied from the work that has already been done that the class of labour employed on drainap-e schemes have welcomed the chance of work in preference to Poor Law assistance or, where they are entitled to unemployed insurance, to doles.
The sum which has been mentioned as required for future drainage schemes is  600,000.   The sum granted last year was  650,000 and chiefly owing to the fact that the decision of the Cabinet Committee came at a very late stage, when schemes had to be prepared hurriedly, It was not possible to take advantage of the full amount of the grant placed at my disposal.The result is that, although my commitments, as the Chancellor mentions, amounted to nearly  400,000 I do not expect that the actual expenditure will exceed  355,000.     To meet this sum  130,000 will have been incurred before 31st March last.     The remainder,  225,000, will be provided out of the  1,500,000 contained In the Supplementary Estimate referred to in the Chancellor&apos;s first paragraph.     So far as my Department is concerned, this stun represents a re-vote. I understand actually that it includes  250,000 for land drainage schemes, but I do not think that more than  225,000 will be required.   The Chancellor contends that If the sum asked for land drainage and afforestation is to be granted, the budget will not balance.    I should be perfectly willing, if it would ease matters, to reduce my demand from  600,000 to  500,000, or even  250,000, if that could be arranged.If the present proposal that the schemes should go on until SLst May is accepted, It is quite possible that a certain amount of this would not fall to be paid this year.   On the other hand, I should be quite willing to restrict all drainage schemes to the period 1st October to 31st March, so as to secure that there is no carrying over of any expenditure into next year.A. G. B.rd August, 1922

</content>
</cab>
