<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/138/0 images: 354-354</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.-----&quot;    278C WSECRET.CP. 4160.THE CABINET.surplus stores.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.57In the last paragraph of the memorandum which I submitted to the Cabinet on 2nd -    ( August, 1921 (C.P. 3188), I suggested that generally, &quot;after the close of the present  financial year (i.e., after 31st March, 1922), all stores which have not then been actually declared surplus should be dealt with by the Army in accordance with normal peace time procedure.&quot;This question was remitted by the Cabinet to the Committee under Mr. ChurchuTs chairmanship which reviewed the proposals of the Geddes Committee on the Navy, Army and Air Force.   Mr. churchill&apos;s Committee recommended as follows : &quot; The Committee considered that apart from surplus war stores, which are being disposed of by the Disposals Board, the pre-war practice, under which the ordinary surplus stores of a Department were disposed of by the Department concerned, should be reverted to, and that the Department concerned should receive credit for the amount realized by the sale of its surplus stores. This arrangement should be without prejudice to the Departments making use of any sales organization that may be set up by the Disposals Board.&quot;The intention of the Government clearly was that this change should take place from 1st April, 1922.I have, however, received a letter from the Treasurj&apos;, dated loth May, 1922, -which postpones this change till 1st April, 1923.i desire to protest against this alteration in the clear intention of the Cabinet Committee. I am at one with the Treasury in desiring that all surpluses arising either from the war or from the Geddes reductions shall as far as possible be thrown up not later than 30th September next, and I can undertake that this will be carried out as far as the Army is concerned, but it is very desirable that we should return to the peace time procedure as early as possible, and I can see no reason why it should be delayed beyond that date.It will readily be seen that as personnel has been reduced to the minimum necessary to meet the requirements of the normal routine, the re-introduction of which was under-stood to be imminent, the responsible staffs of the Royal Army Ordnance Corps and Royal Army Service Corps have considerable difficulty in keeping abreast of their work owing to the continuance of the existing regime. It is essential that the final segregation of the stores declared for disposal to the Disposal and Liquidation Commission from those to be retained for the use of the Army should determine the intervention of the Commission in so far as War Department stocks are concerned, so as to admit of ledgers being adjusted and the military staff devoting themselves entirely to the discharge of their proper functions.I therefore ask the Cabinet to agree that any Army stores declared surplus from 1st October, 1922, should be disposed of by the Army (subject to the use, where desirable, of the Disposals Board machinery as long as it lasts), and the proceeds of sale credited to Army Funds. I may add that the quantities so thrown up for the rest of the current financial year will not be considerable. It will be observed that in this proposal I am trying to meet the Treasury by substituting the date 1st October, 1922, for 1st April, 1922.L. W.-E.the War Office,Uth August, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
