<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/2/44 images: 502-509</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property op his britannic majesty&apos;s governmentPrinted for the War Cabinet.  December 1939.SECRET. Copy No.W.M. (39)110th Conclusions.TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.WAR CABINET 110 (39).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street,S.W. 1, on Sunday, December 10, 1939, at 5 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. Sir John Simon, K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Winston S.Churchill, M.P., First Lord of theAdmiralty.The Right Hon. Sir Kingsley Wood,M.P., Secretary of State for Air.The following were also present:The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,Permanent Under-Secretary of State,Foreign Office.Rear-Admiral   T.   S.   V.   Phillips,Deputy Chief of Naval Staff.Air Marshal R. E. C. Peirse, deputy chief of the Air Staff.Major-General H. R. Massy, deputy chief of the Imperial General Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Colonel L. C. Hollis, R.M.Mr. F. Hemming.Lieutenant-Colonel V. Dykes, RE.Lieutenant-Colonel E. I. C. Jacob, R.E.!&apos; 20465]B
WAR CABINET 110 (39).Contents. &apos;minute no.                                       Subject. page 1      The Air Situation     ...............      ...     3752      The Naval Situation.........      .........     3753      Magnetic Mines ...       ...      ............     375Suggested retaliatory measures.4      The Military Situation        ...............     3765      Finland ...   &apos;.....................     376Invasion by U.S.S.R.Supply of munitions, &amp;c.6      Seizure of German exports   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...     376Case of the Japanese S.S. Sanyo Maru.
the air 1.   The Secretary of State for Air said that there had beenSituation. very little air activity on the 9th December.   Two German aircraft(Previous had been reported flying high over Kirkwall, but no furtherBeference: information of them had been received. One of our aircraft had.M. (89) 109th made a forced landing just inside the Belgian border, having lostConclusions, its way owing to darkness coming on. The pilot, however, had minute l.)        escaped.One aircraft had been plotted flying high over Peterboroughthat morning. Fighters had been sent up, but no interception hadbeen made. There had been some air activity off Newcastle duringthe afternoon.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.The naval situation.(previous reference erence:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. The First Lord of the Admiralty reported that thesubmarine Salmon had sunk an outward-bound U-boat on the4th December, 80 miles south of the Lister Light.Losses of British shipping were as follows : S.S. Middlesborough, 980 tons; struck a submerged objectoff Flamborough Head.Pacific Shipper, 6,290 tons; sunk by collision in convoy.A 7,000-ton tanker outward bound in ballast had been torpedoed and sunk off Land&apos;s End. H.M.S. Wolverine washunting the submarine which had carried out this attack, andhad made a good contact.The German ship Adolf Leonhardt, which had escaped fromLobito Bay, had been intercepted by two cruisers, but had scuttledherself.The approaches to Harwich had been swept for magnetic mineswithout result. The port was now open to traffic, but it was not certain whether there were, in fact, no mines in the fairway orwhether our sweeping methods had not been successful.The Chief of the Norwegian Naval Staff was reported to have said that neither the Deutschland nor the Emden had been sightedby the Norwegian Navy.Several reports had been received of Danish shipping beingstopped by the Germans, both inward and outward bound.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Magnetic Mines.SuggestedRetaliatoryMeasures.(previous reference:  .WM. (39) 93rdConclusions,Minute 3.)3. In the course of the discussion of the preceding item,reference was made to this project.The First Lord of the Admiralty emphasised the need for offensive action.The view was generally expressed that, bearing in mindGermany&apos;s complete disregard of international undertakings, thequestion whether, and, if so, what retaliatory measures we shouldtake against Germany, should be determined by the expediency ofthe measures open to us, rather than by reference to the nature and extent of the retaliation which we should be justified in exercisingon a strictly legal view of the position.[20465]
The MilitarySituation.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 3.)4. The Deputy Chief of the Imperial General Staff said thatone Brigade of the British Expeditionary Force was now on the saar front with the French. These troops had carried out patrolswithout incident. One more German Division had been definitelylocated on the Western Front, the total being between 94 and 97.There was no sign of the withdrawal of any German formationsfrom the front, though no doubt they were regularly relieving the divisions in the front line. It was very doubtful, however, whether any big operation could be mounted under present conditions, owingto the state of the country.The War Cabinet took note of the above statement.Finland.Invasion bj7TJ.S.S.R.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 109thConclusions,Minute 4.)Supply ofMunitions, &amp;c.(previous reference:5. The Deputy Chief of the Imperial General Staff said thatthe situation was unchanged. It was perhaps significant that theRussian wireless in the last 24 hours had contained no news inregard to the invasion of Finland.Reference was made to the report that Italian aircraft had beenflown to Finland.  No confirmation of this report had been obtained.The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsW M (39) 108th sa^ that up to the date of the Soviet attack the German Govern-ment had supplied arms to Finland and had allowed the transitof arms ordered in Italy, Hungary, &amp;c.    He had no definite information as to the position since that date.The First Lord of the Admiralty mentioned that on the3rd December a German warship had stopped a Swedish tankerin Swedish territorial waters and had stated that the German Navyhad orders to stop supplies of oil from reaching Finland.The War Cabinet took note of the above statements.Conclusions,Minute 5.)Seizure ofGermanExports.(previous reference:W.M. (39) 97thConclusions,Minute 11.)Case of theJapanese s.s.Sanyo Maru.6. The Permanent Under-Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs said that the previous evening the question of the treatment to be accorded to German exports to Japan had been rendered acuteby the prospect of the sailing of the Japanese steamship SanyoMaru from Rotterdam on the 10th December, 1939. The JapaneseEmbassy had pressed for the exemption of this ship from our contraband control. In order to prevent a serious dispute arisingat the outset of the operation of the Order-in-Council, the ForeignOffice had informed the Japanese Embassy that the ship must bebrought into the Downs for examination in accordance with ournotified decision, but that in conformity with our undertaking toimpose control &quot; gradually and with leniency &quot; she would be subjectto search only for a very limited category of goods, and that no sub-stantial delay would be involved. The Ramsgate Control Base hadbeen informed that the ship must not be delayed for more than24 hours, and that only formal action should be taken, e.g., to copythe ship&apos;s manifest. The &quot; limited category of goods &quot; which theForeign Office had had in mind were goods consigned from Germanyto German firms. Information from a secret source had, however,since been received which indicated that the Sanyo Maru wascarrying &quot; secret naval goods.&quot; In these circumstances, therefore,the Admiralty might wish to make a more careful examination ofher cargo.  The period of 24 hours would not expire till the evening
of the following day (Monday, the 11th December, 1939). Thequestion raised by this case had been submitted to the Secretaryof State for Foreign Affairs, who would no doubt raise it at themeeting of the War Cabinet to be held the following day.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the War cabinet would no doubt wish to consider the matter the following day, andhe asked Sir Alexander Cadogan to arrange for the circulationthat evening to the War Cabinet of a short note setting out thefacts.The War Cabinet :-took note that the above question would be raised by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs at the meeting ofthe War Cabinet to be held the following morning.Richmond Terrace, S.W. 1,December 10, 1939.




</content>
</cab>
