<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/24/5 images: 58-61</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
; &apos; &apos;THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   April 1942. 29SECRET. Copy No. 29W.P. (42) 175.April 23, 1942,WAR CABINET.MILK  FOR CHILDREN  IN  OCCUPIED  EUROPE.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.ON the 16th February the Cabinet gave general approval in principle to aproposal made by the Minister of Economic Warfare to allow regular shipments of wheat to Greece subject to certain conditions which have been submitted bythe Swedish Government to the Axis Powers, whose reply is awaited.2. This concession is fully justified by the exceptional situation in Greece,but there is suffering in many parts of Europe, less acute indeed than that in greece, but still ample to create a very urgent demand for help. The AlliedGovernments will be under particularly strong pressure from their nationals, whohave the example of Greece and the success of the Greek Government before theireyes. The concessions asked will probably not be large, but for this very reason,it will be difficult to give adequate reasons for refusing any one of them now thatthe arrangements for Greece can be claimed as a precedent. Nor will it for longcontinue to be possible to draw between one Allied country and another the sharpdistinction so far drawn between Greece and the rest.3. The Belgian Government have already urgently demanded the admissionthrough the blockade of small monthly amounts of special foods for children.The Yugoslav Government are pressing for permission to send relief goods toBelgrade.4. It will not for long be possible to refuse such requests unless analternative can be offered. I am, however, convinced that it would be disastrous to accede to such indiscriminate demands. The result would be an endless seriesof piecemeal and probably ill-conceived concessions growing continually in volumein response to an insatiable demand. The fabric of the blockade would be wornaway, and the Allied Governments would compete with one another and ourselvesfor the limited supplies available.5. In my opinion this danger can only be averted if it is possible to devise a form of relief which can be offered to Allied Governments, subject to suitableconditions, as the one variety which we are prepared to tolerate to the exclusion of all others. In order to avoid the disadvantages of Allied competition, anysuch action must, of course, be organised under joint Anglo-United Statesinitiative. In addition it must, so far as possible, (a) be easily controllable inthe occupied countries, (b) not require the allocation of shipping otherwiseavailable for Allied needs, (c) offer the least possible prospect of indirect benefit tothe enemy.6. After consideration of the various possibilities in conjunction with theMinistry of Economic Warfare, I have reached the conclusion that theseconditions can best be met by a concession allowing the supply of limited quantities of milk in concentrated form for the relief of children only, in someof the worst areas. In my view such a concession will be substantial enough to achieve its purpose if means can eventually be found to provide 2,000,000 children11700   [23743]
on the scale applied by the American Red Cross in France. This would requireabout 33,000 tons of powdered whole milk, or the equivalent, yearly. It would,however, be desirable to begin on a much smaller scale with experiments in afew selected areas. If such a plan were adopted, I should hope to secure the collaboration of the Swedish Government in providing shipping from the Balticand supervisory personnel, as they have offered to do in the case of Greece.7. Care would, of course, have to be taken to ensure that arrangements forthe supply of milk do not interfere with the United Kingdom import programmefrom the United States.8. I ask the approval of my colleagues to action on the lines proposed above.I suggest that I should concert the necessary measures with the Minister ofEconomic Warfare and should then seek the approval of the United StatesGovernment and their assistance in overcoming the inevitable difficulties ofsupply.A. E.Foreign Office, April 23, 1942.



</content>
</cab>
