<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/16/0 images: 74-81</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OP HIS  BRITANNIC, MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  August 1949SECRETCM. (49)52nd conclusions copy^NoI    4(CABINET 52 (49)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in Conference Room &quot; B,&quot;Cabinet Office, Great George Street, S.W. 1, on Friday, 12th August, 1949,at 10-30 a.m.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of,Food (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Hector McNeil, M.P.,Minister of State (Item 2).Mr. P. C.  Gordon-Walker,  M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Commonwealth Relations(Item 2).The Hon. Sir Alexander Clutter-buck, United Kingdom High Com-missioner in Canada (Item 2).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power(Items 1-2).Mr. Douglas Jay, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury (Items 1-2).Mr. John Edwards, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Board of Trade.Sir Edward Bridges, Treasury.Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.contents minute     &apos; Subject page 1      Wages Policy  ....      ....      ....  -  ........      ....      ....      146Retail Trade Wages2      The Economic Situation      ............      ....      ....      147. 3      International Labour Conference, 1947     ...      ....      ....      149Conditions of Labour in non-Metropolitan Territories37479 B
1. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Minister ofLabour (CP. (49) 173) on retail trade wages.The Minister of Labour said that the Wages Councils whichhad recently been set up for certain branches of the retail distribu-tive trades had either submitted wage regulation proposals orpublished proposals which they, intended to submit to him. Theseprovided for substantial increases over the minimum rates estab-lished under the current agreements. He could not say precisely how many workers were covered by the Wages Councils concerned, butin July 1948 there were some 1,500,000 workers in the distributive trades and, if comparable increases were granted to all these workers, the annual cost would be between  15 and  20 million.It was probable, however, that the actual total would fall substan-tially short of these figures since many employers were alreadypaying wages above the existing minimum scales.These proposals faced him with a dilemma. Acceptance wouldErobably provoke fresh claims in other industries, and might alsoave the effect of increasing the man-power engaged in retail distribution, contrary to the -Government&apos;s policy! The Presidentof the Board of Trade had represented very strongly to him theobjections to wage increases in any section of retail distribution atthe present time, and had specially stressed the anomaly ofsanctioning wage increases in clothing shops at a time when theGovernment were imposing a 5 per cent, cut in the controlled pricesof clothing. On the other hand, refusal to confirm the unanimousproposals of these Wages Councils would be regarded as a blow tothe authority of the statutory wage-regulating machinery.,HI&apos;t,might also put the Government in the embarrassing position of appearing to be settling wage rates, if they-were pressed by the Councils toindicate what rates would be acceptable. The revised rates proposedby the Councils were not in themselves unreasonable. He consideredthat the present level of wage rates in the industry was unduly low and that there was room for some improvement without prejudice to the policy laid down in the White Paper on. Personal &quot;Incomes,Costs and Prices. Finally, he had been informed&apos;. by the TradesUnion Congress that rejection of these proposals would make it moredifficult for them to give effective support to the White Paper policy.For these reasons, he thought that the right course was to confirm the proposals submitted to him by the Wages Councils.In discussion, Ministers expressed serious concern at theeconomic effects of a general increase in wage rates. in the retaildistributive trades. This would give further impetus to the inflationary pressure, of which there were already disturbing signs.In present circumstances the Government should exercise a restrain-ing influence over wage adjustments within the field which theycould directly control. Acceptance of these proposals would alsoprovoke a fresh cycle of wage claims, the limits of which could notbe foreseen. Claims for comparable wage increases would be putforward in a number of industries, but the consequential adjust-ments of prices might have even more far-reaching effects. For itwas unlikely that any substantial proportion of the increased costof these wage increases could be met out of existing profit margins,and the greater part of it would be passed on to the consumer. in food distribution the increased cost was estimated at  9 million ayear, which would have to be met by increased subsidies or higher prices. If it were decided to put into effect the revised wage ratesproposed for the drapery trade; it would hardly be possible to main-tain the recent cut of 5 per cent, in retail prices.It was suggested that the Government might find it difficult todefend a refusal to accept proposals for an adjustment of wage rates many of which were substantially below  5 a week. In viewof the existing cost of living, could it not be argued that these ratesfell within the range specifically excluded from the scope of theWhite Paper policy t  Against this, it was pointed out that manv
employers were already.paying wages substantially higher than theexisting &quot;minimum rates. Moreover, the distributive trades had nodifficulty in recruiting workers at the present rates : these tradeswere, in fact, employing an unduly large proportion of the nation&apos;sman-power, and it would be in accordance with the Government&apos;economic plans that labour should be drawn away from them. Itcould not therefore be maintained that acceptance of the wages councils&apos; proposals would be consistent with the principles of theWhite Paper, which the Chancellor of the Exchequer had stronglyreaffirmed in the recent debate in Parliament on the economicsituation.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that these proposals for wage adjustments putforward by the Wages Councils for certain branches ofthe retail distributive trades should not be confirmed.(2) Invited the Minister of Labour to communicate the decisionrecorded under Conclusion (1) above to the wages councils concerned, and to inform them in general termsv-   \   of the reasons why their proposals were considered to be!.j,,vi      , inconsistent with the principles set out in the white paper on Personal Incomes, Costs arid Prices, and with/.&apos; the requirements of the present economic situation.(3) Invited the Minister of Labour to bring before the Cabinetany revised proposals which might be submitted by theseWages Councils.The Economic 2. On 29th July the Cabinet had agreed that an approachSituation. should be made to the Canadian Government, before the forth-(Previous coming economic discussions in Washington, about the basis . ofEeference: Canada&apos;s long-term trade relations with the sterling area, and theC.M.(49)5ist United Kingdom High Commissioner in Canada had been recalledGonclusions, to London to advise on the manner in which this approach should minute 2.)      be made.The Cabinet now had before them (i) a note by the Secretary(CP. (49) 174) cohering a record of a discussion on this subject which the Prime Minister had held on 10th August with the UnitedKingdom High Commissioner in Canada; and (ii) a note by thePrime Minister (CP. (49) 172) recommending, in the light of that; discussion, that the long-term problem of Canada&apos;s future trade. relations with the sterling area should not be broached with theCanadian Government in advance of the Washington discussions.Fhe Prime Minister *said* that&apos;the; High Commissioner had advised against ooening this long-term problem with the Canadiani; Government in advance of the Washington talks.   The Canadiansregarded this as essentially a second stage in any discussions of theeconomic situation. They would be most reluctant to consider it until it was known what solution could be found for the immediate difficulties confronting the sterling Commonwealth, for the nature-  - of that solution would affect their attitude towards the long-term problem.   It was most important that we should have their full support in the Washington discussions, and we should be in dangerof forfeiting that support if we insisted on their discussing thelong-term problem separately and in advance of the Washingtonmeeting.   The High Commissioner therefore proposed that any immediate approach to the Canadian Government should be limitedto the short-term problem and should be directed mainly to enlistingtheir full support in persuading the United States Government toauthorise the Economic Co-operation Administration to resume their financing of Canada&apos;s wheat exports to the United Kingdom,i   It was proposed that, on his return to Ottawa, he should hand tov the Canadian Government a memorandum in the terms of the draft\ annexed to CP. (49) 172.B 2
In discussion there was general agreement that in the long runCanada would be forced to accept some adjustment in the pattern ofher trade : she ihust realise that we should, not be, able to continueto find means of paying in dollars for all the goods which she was anxious to sell tb its. And even in the short run some such adjust-meht would have to be faced unless further dollar assistance couldbe made available to us in one way or another. This, indeed, wasimplicit in the draft memorandum annexed tb CP. (49) 172. some ministers would have preferred that it should be made explicit atleast to the extent of making it clear that, unless we secured furtherdollar resources, we should not be able to contract for furtherimports from Canada, as existing contracts expired, except on thebasis that part at least of the payment would be accepted in sterling.Ministers recognised, however, that it was a matter of tactics at what stage this point could best be made explicitly to the canadian government; and the general opinion of the Cabinet was that, inview of the advice given by the High Commissioner, it would be unwise to put the point directly to the Canadians in advance of theWashington meeting.In further discussion the following points were also made: (a) Officials of the Ministry of Pood had held some informal discussion with a representative of the Economic Co-operation administration about the prospects of the Administration s beingauthorised to resume their financing of bur purchases of canadian wheat. He had given it as his.opinion that there would be greatdifficulty in securing this since the United States Government wouldbe reluctant to do anything which would imply that they were notintending to declare a surplus of United States wheat.(&amp;) The Treasury should prepare for the United Kingdom HighCommissioner, for his use in his forthcoming conversations with theCanadian Government, a factual memorandum (on the lines indi-cated in paragraph (c) of the. note attached to CP. (49) 174) oh theextent to which the dollar difficulties of the sterling area were diteto a drop in exports to dollar markets of primary products from therest of the sterling area rather than the high.cost of exports of manufactured goods from the United Kingdom;The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the United Kingdom High Commissioner inCankda, on Ins return tb Ottawa, should Communicate tothe Canadian Government a memorandum in the termsof the draft annexed to CP. (49) 172, and should alsoconvey to them a factual appreciation of the causes of thecurrent dollar difficulties of the sterling Commonwealthon the lines indicated in paragraph (c) of the noteannexed to CP. (49) 174.  ,     . . ,(2) Agreed that the long-term problem of CahacUVs future trade relations with the sterling area should not be broachedwith thie Canadian Government iri advance of the forth-coming economic discussions in Washington.(3) Agreed to resume their consideration of that long-term problem when they discussed with the Foreign secretary and the Chancellor of the Exchequer at a later meetingthe general conduct of their forthcoming negotiations in washington.
international labour conference,1947.(previous reference:C:M.(49)31stConclusions,Minute 6.)Conditions ofLabour in non-metropolitan territories.3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the SeeretaryofState for the Colonies and the Minister of Labour (CP. (49) 166)on five International Labour Conventions adopted at the Inter-national Labour Conference of 1947 regarding conditions of labour in non-metropolitan territories.This proposed that the United Kingdom Government shouldratify these five Conventions, and that their ratification should be accompanied, in each case by a declaration indicating the extent towhich the provisions of the Convention would be applied in thevarious Colonies.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that these Conventions should.be ratified and applied to the Colonies to the extent set out inAppendix II of CP. (49) 166.(2) Authorised the Minister of Labour to communicate to theDirector-General of the International Labour Office the declarations set out in Appendix II to CP. (49) 166.(3) Took note that the Government&apos;s intentions in respect ofthese Conventions would be communicated to parliament in the form of a White Paper.Cabinet Office. S.W. 1,12th August, 1949.




</content>
</cab>
