<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/142/0 images: 18-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[($HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT)C(69) 5213th May, 1969COPY NO.66CABINETGREECE AND THE COUNCIL OF europe note by the Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth affairs attach for your information copies of the recommendationpassed by the General Assembly of the Council of Europe on 30th Januaryon Greece, the resolution approved by the Committee of Ministers on 6th May and my statement in Parliament on 7th May.M,S.Foreign and Commonwealth Office, S.W. 1.13th May, 1969CONFIDENTIAL

-.CONSEIL 01U jcv*Provisional edition!v CONSULTATIVE ASSEMBLYRECOMMEIDATION 547 (196 9) ^on&apos; the situation in GreeceShe Assembly,lu &quot;Deploring the deprivation by the Greek regime of Greekcitizens&apos; rights of unfettered free expression,&apos; and of free elections to a representative parliament;2.     Condemning in the strongest terms the refusal of the GreekGovernment to admit the Assembly^ Rapporteur, in whom itexpresses full confidence;3* .  Concerned at the lack of any real progress in Greecetowards the restoration of constitutional democracy, as called for. in its previous resolutions and as promised by the Greek&apos;Government;4.: &apos; Recalling its Resolution 3*51 of 31 January 1968 on situations in Greece;theRecalling that in its Resolution 385 of 26 September 1968its session in January 1969, in thethe5.it decided &quot;to consider, atlight of a new report of its Rapporteur concerningprogress made towards the restoration of democracy in Greece,whether to recommend&apos;to t^e Committee of Ministers to suspend the Greek Government, from&quot; its right of representation inCouncil of&apos; Europe, in accordance with Article 8 of theStatute&quot;;&apos;.the1* &apos;&apos; : Assembly Debate on. 30 January 1969 (25th and 26thSittings).. See Doc. 2525, report of the PoliticalAffairs Committee.   Text adopted by the Assembly on30 January 1969 (26th Sitting).D 28.92701.33/1

(5...    Declares....that, the present Greek regime is at present in serious violation of the conditions for membership of theCouncil of Europe, as set out in Article 3 of the Statute;7,     Considers that in view, of the foregoing the Greek regimeought to draw the necessary, conclusions and to consider&apos; its position under Article ,7 of the Statute &apos;by virtue, of which any Ilember..of the Council of Europe may withdraw;3.     Decides not to recognise the credentials. ,of any Greekdelegate purporting to &quot;represent&apos; the Greek parliament until such tine as the Assembly; is./satisfied &apos; that freedom of expression is restored and a free and representative parliament is elected in Greece;9,     Recommends the Committee of llinisters to. draw these conclusions to the attention of the Greek Government&apos; andfurther, in: the overall best interests of the Greek people,recommends the Committee &apos; of&apos; Kinistors to take such action,.within .a specified period, as is appropriate, having regard&apos;to Articles 3, 7 and 8. of. the: Statute of the &apos;C6uncil ofEurope&apos; and. to the resolutions of the Assembly cited above.

fi^e,^(:,iv.n??csc4?;.t.i^jQgsRed by the6omnitt.ec of Kinistera on 6 tfriyf.The Committee of Ministers,, .Having considered Keco!make:hdati-oh 347 of the Consultative/tscembly, adopted on: 30th January 1963,Sharing the Consultative Assefcbly*a anxiety over thesituation in Greece,reaffirming the need for a speedy return to a democraticregime in that country,-(l)   Decides to. bring the conclusions of the said Hecommendationto the attention of the Greeh Government* in order that thelatter may draw the necessary conciuoionsj(2)   Declares itself ready to t; he a decision at the next meeting of the Committee of Ministers;(3)   Expresses the hope that the Deport of the Commissionof Human Righto will be made available as soon as possible;(h)   &quot;Decides in the meantime to keep Secomniendation 5h7 ofthe -Assembly on the agenda of the Committee of Ministers andon that of the Ministers&apos; Deputies.

Statement by the Secretary or? State for foreign and. Commonwealth Affairs, the Rx^ht^JaonqujabloMichaol Stewart. C.H. . M.P.... on Greece and, theCouncil of Europe, on Wednesdayvt^,7thMay 1969-With your permission, Mr. Speaker, and that of theHouse I wish to make a statement on the question of greece and the Council of Europe.As the House will be aware, on the 6th of May theCommittee of Ministers of the Council of Europe passedby 13 votes.to 2, with 3 abstentions, a resolution onthis question.    This resolution does four things.It identifies the Committee closely with Recommendation547, passed by the Consultative Assembly on the.30th of January;   it brings the conclusions of thatrecommendation to the Greek Government1s attention (as suggested by the Consultative Assembly), in order thatthe Greek Government may draw the necessary conclusionsit expresses the hope that the report of the Commissionof Human Rights will be made available as soon aspossible;   and it declares the Committee ready to takea decision at its next meeting, until which timeRecommendation 547,will remain on the agenda of theCommittee of Ministers and of their Deputies./There

There are several points about this resolution which I should like to emphasise.    First, tiio resolutiondoes not mean indefinite postponement, still less evasion,of this important issue.    On the contrary, its effect is to set a time limit for the Greek Government to convince European opinion that the evolutionary process/towards democracy, which in their view they have begun,has either been completed or is within striking distance of fulfilment.The reason why Ministers expressed the hope - andno more - that the Human Rights Commission would make available their report as soon as possible is thatconstitutionally it would be wrong for thu Committeeof Ministers to do anything that might suggest thatit was giving this distinguished judicial body any kind of directive.    A number of my colleagues urgedthat no decision should be taken on the Greek question by the,C ommi tte e unti1 tin s rep ort was avai1 ab 1 e. -There is no doubt that the report will have an important bearing on the Committee&apos;s final decision.    My own view, which I expressed in committee yesterday, isthat it is highly desirable that Ministers should havehad time to study,the report before taking their decision,but, that this is not essential./Finally,

Finally, the resolution speaks simply of the next meeting of the Committee, without specifying when thismeeting will be held.    This is deliberate.    Incertain circumstances my colleagues ana I would boprepared to hold an extraordinary meeting to considerthe Greek question.I believe, therefore, that the outcome of yesterday&apos;smeeting was satisfactory.    Much of the credit for thisis due to the Chairman, the German Foreign Minister,




</content>
</cab>
