<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/24/0 images: 13-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1952SECRET Copy No.     4C.C. (52)4th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, SWA,on Thursday, 12th January, 1952, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (inthe Chair).The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, K.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Ismay, Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.   vThe Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P., I The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.;Secretary of State for War (Item 1).    I    Minister of Supply (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Item 3).Mr. T. Padmore, Secretary.
contents minute no. subject      Korea. Winter Clothing.2      Washington and Ottawa Talks3      The Economic SituationGovernment Expenditure.4      Trade with Eastern Europe   ...Battle Act.5      The Sudan       ...      ...      ....-6      Town and Country Planning ...
rKorea.WinterClothing.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 3rdConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theSecretary of State for War (C. (52) 6) reporting on the provision of winter clothing for British troops in Korea.The Secretary of State for War informed the Cabinet that he had examined the position soon after his appointment and had made a parliamentary statement which had foreshadowed the presentposition. Current Press reports of inadequate provision of winterclothing were without real substance. The cause of the criticism wasthat, although the Finnish type of clothing in use last winter and stillin use for part of our Forces was adequate, it was being replaced byequipment of a much better type. It had been decided locally to begin the issue of improved equipment although full replacement ofthe Finnish type of clothing could not be completed for a few weeks.As the memorandum showed, the Government had a good case in answer to the criticisms which were being made.The Cabinet Invited the Secretary of State for War to hold a press conference at an early date with a view to removing currentmisapprehensions about the provision of winter clothing forthe troops in Korea.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 1stConclusions,Minute 3.)Washington and       2.   The Foreign Secretary and the Commonwealth SecretaryOttawa Talks.   gave to the Cabinet an account of the discussions with the UnitedStates and Canadian Administrations during the course of the recent visit of United Kingdom Ministers to North America.Before describing the course of talks on specific items, TheForeign Secretary made the following general observations:(a) He said that he had returned from North America with a renewed conviction of our need to do everything possible to re-estab-lish our economic and financial independence. We must do thiseven if, as a result, rearmament took longer than had been hoped.It was, indeed, in his view the first and most important task of thepresent Government. The United States Administration had beenfriendly and helpful, and they had not adopted a critical attitudewhen our Ministers had explained our balance of payments positionand our difficulties in increasing coal production; but there was nodoubt that their attitude was fundamentally affected by our dependentsituation and would be substantially changed once we were standingon our own feet.(b) Politicians in the United States were already deeply pre-occupied with the forthcoming Presidential Election, even more sothan usual because of the possible candidature of General Eisenhower.This made the Administration anxious to produce quick results anddisposed to take a short view of the problems before them and us.It was by no means certain that General Eisenhower would secure the republican nomination, since Senator Taft had wide support. Butif he did secure the nomination he seemed fairly certain of election.(c) The Foreign Secretary had met the Foreign Relations Com-mittees of both Houses, of Congress and had had useful and friendlydiscussions with them.      .On the particular topics included in the agenda of the talks, theForeign Secretary gave the following report:  (d) Reform of N.A.T.O.The United States views on the reform of N.A.T.O. appeared tobe closely in line with ours, except on the one subject of the futurelocation of the headquarters of the Organisation. For this theyfavoured Paris, while we favoured London; and the questionremained undecided.41803-4 b 2
(e) The Atlantic CommandDiscussions on this were still continuing. The Foreign Secretary&apos;simpression was that, while the United States Government felt thatthey were now deeply committed to their ideas, the present situation would not have developed if they had been fully aware much earlier ofthe nature of the arguments advanced on our side. He thought thatin the upshot the Prime Minister would be successful in obtainingmuch of the substance of what he desired.(/) EgyptClose agreement had been established between the two Govern-ments in the working out of ideas for settlement of the Egyptianproblem. The United States Government were entirely helpful to our point of view and were giving good support.(g) PersiaDiscussions on the Persian oil problem had not been altogethereasy, since both the United States Secretary of State and the Secretaryof Defence were critical of the manner in which the matter had beenhandled by us and by the International Bank. They were undulyanxious for quick results and had allowed the Persian Governmentto see that they were disturbed by such pin-pricks as the refusal ofthat Government to renew its military agreement with them. TheForeign Secretary had made plain to them the importance of playingour hand slowly and carefully.(h) KoreaGeneral Bradley had given a most impressive account of themilitary situation in Korea. The Communist forces had undoubtedly been strengthened during the period of the armistice talks, but GeneralBradley was nevertheless confident that the United Nations forces could hold any Communist offensive which might be launched. Thiswas subject to their view that, in the event of such an offensive, itwould be necessary to bomb targets beyond the Yalu River. Indeed,in the event of any breach of the armistice, the United States Govern-ment would wish to undertake fairly widespread bombing outsidethe frontiers of Korea, but would confine this to military targets, suchas air-fields. They would also wish to cut off all trade with China.In this connection the President had been very critical of what he understood to be the scale of the continued export of strategic materials to China, either by us or in British ships. Material sent from London had enabled United Kingdom Ministers to answer this criticism effectively.(/) South-East AsiaUseful discussions had taken place on policies in South-East asia and staff talks in which the French had taken part had been satis-factory to them. It was clear that the United States Administrationwere now much better aware of the danger that Communist pressuremight be switched from Korea to other parts of South-East Asia,though there were still some remaining signs of their old antj-Colonialprejudice.(/) The Foreign Secretary observed that Parliamentary difficulties might arise over the handling by the United States Government ofthe question of relations between the Government of Japan and theNational Government of China in Formosa. The United StatesGovernment took the view that the communication which theJapanese Government had sent to General Chiang Kai-shek wasnecessary if the United States Senate was to ratify the Japanese peace treaty; but we had not agreed with this action.The Commonwealth Secretary, in supplementing; the foreign secretary^ account, made a brief reference to discussions with theGovernment of Canada.
3. The Cabinet discussed the timing of the Parliamentaryannouncement on the measures contemplated for remedying thepresent economic situation. Parliament and the public had been ledto expect an announcement immediately on the re-assembly ofParliament and it would be politically undesirable to defer it untilthe second week of the sittings. It would, however, be necessary, ifa debate on economic affairs were to be opened by the Chancellorof the Exchequer on 30th and 31st January, for a firm decision inthis sense to be taken before 22nd January in order that theOpposition might be informed of the change in the parliamentary business agreed for the first week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer gave the Cabinet a general indication of the measures which he had in mind. While that partof them which related to Government expenditure had already beengiven preliminary examination by the Cabinet on 20th December,he would be recommending other measures following on the con-clusions of the Conference of Commonwealth Finance Ministers nowin progress.In view of the information which the Chancellor of theExchequer gave to the Cabinet on the steps necessary to remedy the deficit in the balance of payments, the Cabinet felt that every effort should be made to ensure that other demands did not adversely affectvital exports, particularly of the products of the metal-using industries.In this connection they were informed that the Prime Minister had under examination proposals for according priority to the productionof certain items of the defence programme. The Cabinet were ofopinion that priority should be accorded only to the extent recom-mended in a telegram which had been sent to the Prime Minister bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Cabinet (1) Provisionally decided to examine at their meeting on22nd January the economic and financial measures to be recommended to them by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,with a view to their announcement to Parliament at theopening of a debate on the economic situation on30th January.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary and the Chancellor of theExchequer to telegraph to the Prime Minister (i) seeking his assent to this time-table;(ii) recommending that priority for arms production should be accorded only within the limits recom-mended to him by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The EconomicSituation.(previous reference:C.C. (51) 19thConclusions,Minute 3.)(k) The Canadian Minister of National Defence, who had recently been in Korea, took a less sanguine view of the militarysituation there in the event of renewed hostilities than did GeneralBradley. He thought, in particular, that the South Korean divisionholding the line on the left flank of the Commonwealth Forces was of doubtful quality, while the United States division on their right flankwas not first-class. In the event of a renewed attack our forces mightsuffer heavy casualties.(/) The Government of Canada were in sympathy with the PrimeMinister^ views on the question of the Atlantic Command. Theywould support those views provided that arrangements could be made which, while being consistent with them, would avoid upsetting theother North Atlantic Powers.(m) The Commonwealth Secretary said that he had been impressed by the strongly pro-British attitude of the Canadians,though they were also ardent nationalists and deeply conscious oftheir status of equality with the United Kingdom within theCommonwealth.
National health service.The Minister of Health informed the Cabinet that the proposalsplaced before them at their meeting of 20th December for the im-position of certain charges in connection with the Health service would require legislation, which would be introduced soon after theannouncement on economic and financial policy shortly to be madeby the Chancellor of the Exchequer. It had been suggested that thelegislation might provide for the charges to come into effect (subjectto Parliamentary approval) within some two weeks of the introductionof the Bill. It would, however, in his view be unusual and inappropriate-priate to bring these charges into force at a date earlier than that onwhich they were actually authorised by the passage of legislation.The immediate imposition of new taxes in a Budget (to which the&quot;Provisional Collection of Taxes Act applied) was not, he thought, a true parallel. Nevertheless, deferment of the charges until royal assent might reduce revenue from them by as much as  500,000.The Cabinet-(3) Agreed that Health Service charges to be imposed byforthcoming legislation should not take effect until thelegislation received the Royal Assent.Trade with 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the ForeignEastern Europe. Secretary (C. (52) 7) summarising the issues arising from talks whichBattle Act.       had just taken place in Paris on the implications of the United States(Previous        Mutual Defense Assistance Control Act (Battle Act).  Following on reference:      the instructions given by the Cabinet at their meeting on 3rd January,C.C. (52) 1st     the United Kingdom Delegation to the Paris Group had securedConclusions,     substantial support for our views from the European Governments.Minute 1.)       In the Paris Group discussions the United States representative, while he had been unable because of the terms of the United States law togive an assurance that his Government would in all respectsadminister the Battle Act in a manner consistent with the principles and procedures already laid down by the Paris Group, had appearedgenuinely anxious to take all possible steps to meet the views of theEuropean Governments.  He had agreed on the importance of main-taining the Paris Group and had undertaken that the Administratorappointed under the Act would give maximum weight to the recom-mendations of the Group and would seek to change existing pro-procedures and policies as little as possible.   He had made threerecommendations for modifications in present procedures designed toassist the Administrator in using the machinery of the Group todischarge his obligations under the Act. These suggestions were--(i) that the present procedure relating to the export of itemssubject to embargo should be amended to ensure consulta-tion with the Paris Group in advance of export whenever possible;(ii) that the export under existing contracts of goods includedin the embargo list should be held up to give the UnitedStates Government time for consideration and for theobtaining of authority for the necessary exports under the battle Act;(iii) that we should consult the Paris Group before exportingsome six items which appeared on the American embargolist but not on ours.The Cabinet were of the opinion that, while the Battle Actremained objectionable in principle and while we should continueto make this clear, the proposals made by the United States Govern-ment might be accepted subject to some modification of that noted in paragraph (ii) above and to our retaining freedom to resistrestrictions on the export of rubber and tin which might be proposedlater but would adversely affect the price of those commodities andwould therefore reduce the dollar income of the sterling area.
The Sudan. 5.   The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that he had discussed relations with Egypt and the Sudan with the United StatesGovernment and had under examination a suggestion that we should give a fresh indication to the King of Egypt of the attitude which weshould adopt on the various outstanding problems if an egyptian government were formed with which we could negotiate. He wished the Cabinet to be aware that among the proposals made to him wasone relating to the question of the King&apos;s title: on this it wassuggested that we should indicate that, as part of a general settlement,we might agree that, although we did not recognise King Farouk&apos;claim to the title of King of the Sudan, he should not be asked to change the Egyptian law by which he enjoyed this additional title,provided that it was understood (i) that pending the establishmentof self-government in the Sudan the existing administration shouldcontinue unchanged, the additional title having no practical effect,and (ii) that after the establishment of self-government the positionof the King of Egypt in relation to the Sudan should be determinedby a plebiscite conducted by an international Commission under anagreement to be reached between the Egyptian and United kingdom governments.The Foreign Secretary said that he was not seeking an immediate decision from the Cabinet. But he would be glad of their authorityto open preliminary discussions on this proposal with the UnitedStates Government. If after such discussions it seemed desirable toproceed with the suggestion he would consult the Governor-Generalof the Sudan.The Cabinet (1) Invited the Foreign Secretary to circulate to them a memo-randum setting out the suggestion which he had mentioned.(2) Subject to any comments which members of the cabinet might wish to make to the Foreign Secretary on receipt ofthis memorandum, authorised the Foreign Secretary toascertain the views of the United States Government onthe suggestion made in it.Town and 6.   The Minister of Housing and Local Government informedCountry the Cabinet that he was preparing proposals for the amendment of planning.        the Town and Country Planning Act, 1947, and would be glad todiscuss these with a few of his colleagues.The Cabinet Invited the Foreign Secretary, on behalf of the PrimeMinister, to appoint a Cabinet Committee to examine theseproposals.Cabinet Office, SWA,\lth January, 1952.The Cabinet agreed (1) That the suggestion noted in paragraph (i) above might beaccepted.(2) That we should not accept any general hold-up of &quot;exports towhich we were committed, but should remind the UnitedStates Administration that they were already in possessionof a list of our contracts and should offer to examine withthem any individual items which they might wish todiscuss with us.(3) That the suggestion noted in paragraph (hi) above might beaccepted, but that we should maintain our freedom toexamine on their merits any additions to their embargolist which the United States Government might propose.

</content>
</cab>
