<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/24/0 images: 33-39</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   January 1952SECRETC.C. (52)7th conclusions copy No.40CABINETCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.I,on Friday, 25th January, 1952 at 11-.15 am.Present:The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs(in the Chair)The Right Hon. Lord, Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Most Hon. the Marquess &apos; of salisbury, Lord Privy SeakThe Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, K.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Ismay, Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,K.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster(Items 3-6).The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries (Item 4).The Right Hon. Gwilym LloydGeorge, M.P., Minister of Food(Item 4).The Right Hon. David Eccles, M.P..Minister of Works (Item 5).Commander T. D. Galbraith, M.P.,Parliamentary Under-Secretary ofState for Scotland (Item 5).4.1817-2The Right Hon. J. P. L. Thomas, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty (items-4).The Right Hon. Lord De l&apos;isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air(Items 1-4).The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 3-6).The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (items-4).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 4-6).Field-Marshal Sir William Slim, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff (Item 1).
Marshal of the Royal Air Force Sir i  Admiral Sir Rhoderick McGrigor,-John Slessor, Chief of the Air Staff !     First Sea Lord and Chief of Naval-&apos;(Itern 1). I     Staff (Item 1).Secretariat:Mr. T. Padmore.Lt.-General Sir K. McLean.Mr. O. C. Morland.contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1      Egypt    .........      ...      .........      ...     37Situation in Canal Zone.2      Military Expenditure   ...      ......      ...      ...      ....   37Transfer from Civil to Defence Vote.3      The Economic Situation        ...      ...      ... 38Air Force Man-power.Army Vehicles.Centurion Tanks.4      Balance of Payments   ..........      ...      ...      ...      395      Housing Programme   ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      ...      40Supply of Scarce Materials.6      The Kashmir Dispute ...      ...      .........      ...      41
.37C.G. 7 (52)Egypt- 1.   The Foreign Secretary informed the Cabinet that the situation(Previous       in the Canal Zone appeared to be deteriorating seriously.  ReuterReference:      reports which might be exaggerated spoke of considerable fightingC.C. (52) 2nd    in Ismailia that morning in the course of the operation undertakenConclusions,    to disarm the Egyptian police. Late on the previous evening he had minute 4.)       discussed with the Chiefs of Staff the situation which would arise ifSituation in      tne Egyptians were to take violent reprisals for this operation.  the canal Zone.     Chiefs of Staff subsequently instructed the Commanders-in-Chief tobring to a high degree of preparedness their measures to protect Britishand foreign lives and property in Egypt. The Foreign Secretary read to the Cabinet his telegram No. 164 to Cairo instructing the Ambas-ambassador in what circumstances he might recommend to His Majesty&apos;sGovernment that these measures should be put into force and asking&apos;that the recommendation should be made, if possible, in agreementwith his United States colleague. He had also instructed the Ambas-ambassador to deliver a suitable warning to the King of Egypt.  The PrimeMinister had been kept informed of events and was in agreement withthe action taken.   The Foreign Secretary proposed to inform the leader of the Opposition of the situation.   The Cabinet agreed thatthe Commonwealth Secretary should also inform the Governmentsof Canada, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa.  The Govern-ment of India might also be informed of the deterioration of thesituation, but not of the military preparations which were being, takento meet an emergency.   The question of economic- and financial measures against Egypt might be further considered by the Cabinet. .  in the following week.   These would be appropriate if the situation deteriorated still further.The Cabinet Took note of the situation.Military 2.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theExpenditure. Chancellor of the Exchequer (C. (52) 13) proposing that the excessTransfer from cost of United Kingdom forces acting in aid of the civil power inCivil to Defence Malaya over and above what the same forces would otherwise costVote. (estimated at  9 million for 1952-53) should be transferred from the vote for Colonial and Middle Eastern Services to Army and Air Votes.The main reasons for suggesting this change were that an essentiallycivil Vote was at present distorted by this large addition for military expenditure; that, as the Service Departments framed military policy,financial responsibility should also rest with them; and that thestruggle in Malaya was only one part of the world-wide imperialstruggle against Communism and should not, therefore, be represented as a purely local disturbance.While the Colonial Secretary supported the proposal, the Secre-taries of State for War and Air were reluctant to accept it. While they- agreed that financial responsibility should accompany responsibilityfor policy, in their view the main policy decisions in relation to the useof military forces in Malaya were taken by the civil power under theColonial Secretary. xThe general view of the Cabinet was that the balance of advan-tage and of financial propriety lay on the side of accepting the proposal made by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. It would, however, bedifficult to amend the Service Estimates at this late date.The Cabinet  , -Endorsed in principle the proposal made in C. (52) 13 for application, if circumstances remain unchanged, in the Votesfor the year 1953-54.
The Economic 3. The Cabinet resumed their examination of the memorandumSituation. by the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C. (52) 8) on the economic(Previous situation. They had also before them a memorandum by the minister reference: of Labour (C. (52) 14), to which was annexed the draft of an announce-C.C. (52) 5th ment on the reintroduction of a Regulation of Engagement Order and conclusions,     the revival of labour supply inspection.minute--) The Foreign Secretary said that the Cabinet would also wish to hear the views of the Secretaries of State for War and Air on sugges-tions made by the Prime Minister (in his telegram No. 4 of 23rdJanuary) about further possible reductions in Service estimates.Air Force The Secretary of State for Air said that the Prime Minister hadMan-power. suggested that a further 15,000 men should be struck off the man-power requirements of the Royal Air Force. It had been proposed toincrease the total man-power from 270,000 in December 1951 to297,000 in December 1952, but by under-manning in certain groundestablishments it might be possible.to make a rather smaller increasewithout impairing essential efficiency. The chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster was now examining the figures in consultation with him and in the light of the latest forecasts of aircraft deliveries, a decision could not well be reached until this examination had been completed.Army Vehicles. The Secretary of State for War said that the Prime Minister hadbeen mistaken in supposing that  100 million was to be spent onArmy lorries. The total had been reduced from the first proposal of  64 million to  48 million, and orders to that amount had alreadybeen placed. When the orders had been completed, in a few months&apos;time, the manufacturers would turn over to commercial manufacturefor export. New Army vehicles to replace obsolete and worn-outstock were urgently needed.It was pointed out that exports would benefit greatly from anyfurther reduction that could be made in the military demands forvehicles. The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that he proposed to examine once more the total requirements of the service departments for vehicles.Centurion The Secretary of State for War said, with reference to the pro-Tanks, duction of Centurion tanks (to which the Prime Minister had also referred in his telegram), that it had been agreed with the PrimeMinister before his departure that all available production shouldbe given to the Army. We were committed, however, to selling110 Centurion tanks to Canada in 1952, and he hoped that this under-taking would not be broken.In discussion it was agreed that, subject to the approval of theMinister of Defence, the undertaking to Canada should be honoured.The question of priorities for certain, types of arms production was still under discussion with the Prime Minister, who favoured theinclusion of Centurion tank production in any priority system intro-duced. The Minister of Supply said that, meanwhile, he would seek to ascertain whether the United States Government would be willingto buy Centurion tanks. If they would, they might very well agreeto contribute steel and components for their manufacture, and he hoped that priority would be given to it. Since such a priority wouldbe in part for manufacture for export, he did not expect that difficulty would be felt in according it.The Cabinet- .(1) Invited the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, in con-sultation with the Secretaries of State for Air and Warrespectively, to examine further the man-power require-ments of the Royal Air Force and the requirements forthe supply of military vehicles.(2) Invited the. Minister of Supply to. ascertain whether theUnited States Government would be willing to purchaseCenturion tanks.
The Chancellor of the Exchequer informed the Cabinet thathe did not now wish to ask his colleagues to reach a decision onthe question dealt with in Part II of the Confidential Annex toC. (52) 8. This could be deferred until his Budget proposals were under consideration. In this connection he informed the Cabinet ofcertain matters connected with the Budget on which he would beconsulting the Prime Minister.Balance ofPayments.(previous reference:C.G. (52) 6thConclusions,Minute 2.)4. The Cabinet resumed consideration of the memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer on the balance of payments situation(C. (52) 10).The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in the light of theCabinet&apos;s discussion on the previous day he had re-examined thewhole field of possible import economies. It had been his colleague&apos;view that reductions in food rations should not now be made, and itwas accordingly necessary to find new savings to replace thosetotalling  19 million in respect of imports of sugar and fats in para-graph 29 of his paper. He did not feel that the saving (of perhaps 4 million in 1952 rising to  8 million later) which would result fromthe reintroduction of petrol rationing would justify the administrative difficulties it would cause., and he would not favour further directrestrictions on imports of wine, which might better be dealt with inother ways. He considered, however, that an additional  5 millionmight be found from cuts in defence orders for textiles, and thatsome part of the saving on food mentioned at the end of paragraph 29of his memorandum should also be made. If the tourist ration were cut to  25, and it was agreed to secure an additional  10 million bylowering still further the quotas for &quot; deliberalised &quot; imports from europe, the necessary total of  150 million could be reached.In discussion concern was expressed about the effect which these additional measures would have on our relations with other european countries. The reduction of the tourist ration to  25 might well by itself provoke retaliatory action; and, if it were combined with further&quot; deliberalisation &quot; and additional cuts on miscellaneous food imports,the result might be the erection of barriers against our exports to europe. In reply The Chancellor of the Exchequer pointed out thatour deficit with the European Payments Union had already reached a stage in which&apos;80 per cent, of our European expenditure was in gold.In further discussion the following points were made:  (a) It would not be possible to cancel the orders for Japanesetextiles, which had been mentioned in the Cabinefs previous discus-sions. The. orders had been placed more than a year ago, and thecanvas and cloth were urgently needed for the defence programme.(h) The possibility of reducing actual consumption of tobaccoshould not be dismissed without further examination.. Any measuresto this end would have great psychological value, and would do noinjury to the public health or vitality.(c) The total burden of production for defence and exports was greater than the economy could bear. A reduction of  40 million inthe defence production programme would largely solve our problem by making possible an immediate increase in engineering exports. Itwas agreed, however, that decisions on this question could not bereached immediately. As things were, it must be borne in mind thatthe engineering industry had been so seriously affected by the shortageof steel that it would be unwise to assume that its exports in 1952could be greater that in 1951, particularly as the additional UnitedStates steel would reach us only in the middle and latter half of theycai. The view was expressed that, if it Were decided in due course to reduce production for defence, this should be done by means of adefinite reduction in the approved programme and not throughdiverting to export production the raw materials which the programmerequired.
housing programme.Supply of &apos;ScarceMaterials.(previous reference:C.C. (51) 20thConclusions,Minute 3.)5. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the Chancellorof the Duchy of Lancaster (C. (52) 12) reporting the results of an examination of the implications of the housing programme onrequirements of scarce materials.The Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster said that his paper was a factual one, showing as accurately, as was at present possible,the demands of the housing programme on scarce materials. Theposition might be rather better than indicated in the paper, owingto economies which he hoped would be made through technicalprogress and the adoption of improved methods of building.The Minister of Housing said that there was a good prospectof making an increasingly economic use of scarce materials. In thelast paragraph of the paper reference was made to his agreement that the labour force engaged on housing should not be increasedabove its present level. His colleagues would appreciate the closeinter-relation of labour engaged on housing with that employed on other building work, but he intended to keep broadly within the limitindicated. In consultation with the Minister of Works he had agreed. upon a procedure for regional consultation on starting dates whichwould ensure close co-ordination between housing and other building projects. The Minister of Labour and the President of the Boardof-Trade supported the arrangements for co-ordinated regionalcontrol.The Minister of Works said that a serious problem arose overthe requirements of steel for housing fitments referred to in para-graph 2 (e) of the paper. 20,000 tons of steel would be needed forthis purpose in 1952 (not 5,000 tons as stated in the paper) and thefull force of the cut in supplies of steel would fall on exports. if more steel could not be allocated for the production of housing fit-ments, he Would have to warn the industry that they must drasticallycut supplies for export.After further discussion of the measures necessary to reduceimports it was agreed:  (i) that the cuts proposed in paragraph 23 of C. (52) 10 shouldbe made (subject to an increase to  22 million of the saving on tobaccoand a decrease to  6 million of the saving on soft wood), giving atotal saving of  76 million;(ii) that the reduction proposed in paragraph 26 in quotas of&quot; deliberated &quot; imports should be made, yielding some  7^ million;(hi) that the reductions proposed in paragraph 29 should bemade in respect of wheat and flour, bacon and cheese, yielding a totalof  18 million;(iv) that the savings previously discussed should be made onlinseed oil ( 2 million), purchases by the United States of rubber&apos;( 8 million), imports of coal ( 2^- million), and overseas military expenditure ( 1.01 million), totalling  23 million.In addition to these savings, totalling  137 million, it was agreedthat a further reduction of about  5 million should be made inpurchases of textiles for defence, and that the Chancellor of theExchequer should discuss with the Lord President and the Ministerof Food possible savings on Government purchases of miscellaneousfood in order to reach a final total as close as possible to  150 million.It was agreed that no additional savings should be sought from further &quot; deliberalisation &quot; of imports from Europe.The Cabinet Approved the measures proposed in C. (52) 10, subject tothe modifications agreed in discussion.
In discussion attention was drawn to the burden on the balanceof payments resulting from the housing programme through its effects on both imports and exports. It might be necessary in due course to review the existing priorities between housing, exports and defence.The Cabinet Took note of C. (52) 12.The KashmirDispute.(previous reference:C.C. (51) 18thConclusions,Minute 5.)6. The Commonwealth Secretary informed the Cabinet thathe thought it desirable to depart in some degree from the policy inrelation to the Kashmir dispute which had been approved by theCabinet at their meeting on 19th December. There were some indica-tions that the Government of India might prove to be moreaccommodating in their attitude than had been previously believed,but this tendency would no doubt be reversed if we were to press onrapidly with the promotion of a resolution in the Security council as previously intended. The Commonwealth Secretary thought thatit might be preferable to give the parties a further opportunity for settling their differences within the next two months. He would beglad to have the assistance of a few colleagues in examining thematter further. ,The Cabinet Took note of the statement on the Kashmir dispute by theCommonwealth Secretary and of his intention to discuss further developments with some of his colleagues.Cabinet Office, S.W.I,25th January, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
