<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/24/0 images: 68-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   February 1952SECRET Copy No.    4C.C. (52)   .15th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Monday, Wth February, 1952, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister and Minister ofDefence (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Ismay, Secretaryof State for Commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right JHon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of. State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The  Right  Hon.   Lord   Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P., j The Right Hon. David Eccles, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 3).   j    Minister of Works (Items 1-2).
contents minute nNo.                                      Subject page 1      The Coronation.........      ......      ...... 772     The Stone of Scone    ...3      Dunkirk Memorial     ...      ......      -........ 774     Atomic Energy...... s
The&apos; Coronation.1. The Cabinet considered what advice should be offered toThe Queen regarding the date of Her Coronation. The precedentspointed to a date in the early summer of 1953. It was to be hopedthat by then conditions might be more settled than they seemed likelyto be in 1952. If the Coronation took place in 1953, it might bepossible for The Queen, if She so wished, to visit Australia and NewZealand in the winter of 1952-53. The Minister of Works said thatthere would be great difficulty in making the necessary buildingpreparations at Westminster Abbey for a Coronation in 1952.* The Cabinet (1) Asked the Lord Chancellor to verify that there would be no constitutional objection to a Royal Visit to other Com-commonwealth countries, if desired by Her Majesty, inadvance of the Coronation.(2) Invited the Prime Minister, in ascertaining Her Majesty&apos;swishes, to indicate their preference for holding the coronation in the early summer of 1953.The Stone ofScone.2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the LordChancellor and the Secretary of State for Scotland (C. (52) 26)suggesting that the Coronation Stone should be replaced in the coronation Chair in Westminster Abbey.The Cabinet favoured this proposal but thought that, before any announcement was made, it would be desirable to consult through their Leader certain prominent Scottish Members of the Opposition.Similar consultations had taken place previously on matters concerning the Stone.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the proposal to restore the Stone ofScone to Westminster Abbey.(2) Invited the Prime Minister to seek the comments of leadingScottish members of the Opposition on this proposal.DunkirkMemorial.(previous reference:C.C. (51) 16thConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secre-tary of State for War inviting them to decide whether the imperial war Graves Commission should proceed with their plans for a modest memorial at Dunkirk at a cost of some  23,000 or shoulderect there at more substantial cost a national memorial com-memorating the Dunkirk operation.The Secretary of State for War said that, as the site which hadbeen selected was on the sea front, any memorial which included agarden, as had been previously suggested by the Cabinet, must havea surrounding wall to retain the soil. A design had therefore beenprepared for a national memorial which took the form of a court-yard surrounded by cloisters and enclosing a Garden of Remem-brance. The cost to the public of erecting a memorial to this designwould be about  77,000.The Cabinet were disposed to favour the erection of a nationalmemorial in preference to the more limited project of a smallarchway designed to commemorate those soldiers who fell in the1939-40 Campaign and had no known graves. They did not,however, wish to authorise a grant for this purpose in the current economic circumstances.The Cabinet-Deferred their decision on the nature of the memorial to be erected at Dunkirk; and invited the Secretary of State forWar to bring this matter before them again in the summer of 1953.
Cabinet Office, S.W.1,11th February, 1952.Atomic Energy.       4.   The Cabinet were informed that an atomic bomb of Britishmanufacture was to be exploded in Australia, under test conditions.,- &quot;\during the summer. All the arrangements for this test had now beert- ./concluded with the Australian Government, and the party in chargeof it were shortly due to leave for Australia. Some information aboutthe experiment had already found its way to the Press, and it was desirable that an official announcement should be made at an early. date.The Prime Minister said that no time should now be lost in settling the terms of the announcement, in consultation with theAustralian Government, and arranging for its simultaneous release inthis country and in Australia. The Paymaster-General undertook tomake arrangements accordingly.

</content>
</cab>
