<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/66/8 images: 94-104</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRETUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO 79CABINET8thsionsCONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinetheld at 10 Downing Street onTHURSDAY 5 JULY 1979at 11. 00 amPRESENTThe Rt Hon Margaret Thatcher MPPrime MinisterThe Rt Hon Sir Geoffrey Howe QC MPChancellor of the Exchequerfcon Lord CarringtonHry of State for Foreign andBiwealth AffairsAt Hon Sir Keith Joseph MP[etary of State for Industrylit Hon Lord Soames[resident of the Council^Hon Sir Ian Gilmour MPBrivy SealKion Michael Heseltine MPf tary of State for the Environmentfton Nicholas Edwards MPBy of State for Walesfon Patrick Jenkin MPBy of State for Social Servicesfct Hon John Nott MPBy of State for TradelRtHon Mark Carlisle QC MPffcry of State for Education and Science   Chief Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Angus Maude MPPaymaster GeneralThe Rt Hon Francis Pym MPSecretary of State for DefenceThe Rt Hon James Prior MPSecretary of State for EmploymentThe Rt Hon Peter Walker MPMinister of Agriculture, Fisheries and FoodThe Rt Hon George Younger MPSecretary of State for ScotlandThe Rt Hon Humphrey Atkins MPSecretary of State for Northern IrelandThe Rt Hon Norman St   John-Stevas MPChancellor of the Duchy of LancasterThe Rt Hon David Howell MPSecretary of State for EnergyThe Rt Hon John Biffen MPSECRET84
SECRETTHE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENTHon Norman Fowler MPr of TransportThe Rt Hon Michael Jopling MPParliamentary Secretary, TreasuryThe Rt Hon Sir Michael Havers QC MPAttorney General   (Item 4)SECRETARIATSir John HuntMr M D M FranklinMr P Le CheminantMr P J HarropMr R L Wade-GeryMr P MountfieldMr D E-\R FtuifcafcrMr G D MilesDt N B W Thompson   (Item 4)(Items 2 and 3)(Items 4-6)(Item 1)(Items 2 and 3)(ftem 6)(Item 1)(Item 5)CONTENTSSubjectPARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRSFOREIGN AFFAIRSTokyo SummitAustraliaMiddle EastVietnamese RefugeesCOMMUNITY AFFAIRSRHODESIAN SANCTIONSFurther InquiryMPs1 AND MINISTERS1 PAYREGIONAL&quot;INDUSTRIAL POLICYPage111223457iiSECRET
CONFIDENTIAL1, The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.2. THE PRIME MINISTER said that the Economic Summitmeeting in Tokyo on 28-29 June had been dominated by energyquestions.    On the immediate need for reduced oil imports by thedeveloped world, the United States, Japan and Canada had beenunwilling to accept import targets unless the European EconomicCommunity (EEC) global target which had been agreed previouslyby the European Council in Strasbourg was broken down on anational basis.    This process was bound to present difficulty forsome members of the EEC and she had argued that commitmentsshould not be made until our EEC partners who were not at Tokyohad been consulted.    She had not received support, especially fromPresident Giscard, for this approach.    Since accepting a nationaltarget presented no difficulty for the United Kingdom, which withina few years would cease to be a net importer, she had gone alongwith the views of the other Summit participants so that an agreementon specific targets could be presented to the Organisation ofPetroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) countries as a reduction indemand by the developed countries.    The targets were somewhatdiverse but the result was better than no agreement on importrestraint.    The Summit had been concerned about the vulnerabilityof the West to continued pressure from the OPEC countries andaccepted the need for increased use of nuclear power tobecome less dependent on oil in the longer term.THE PRIME MINISTER said that, following the Tokyo meeting, shehad paid a short visit to Australia.    Her talks with Mr Fraser hadlargely concentrated on Rhodesia but one result of her visit had beento clear the way for the signing of a United Kingdom/AustraliaSafeguards Agreement for the supply of uranium.    This had beenblocked by the European Commission which was concerned,following rulings by the European Court, about the compatibility ofthe agreement with the EURATOM Treaty.    She had personallytaken this up with Mr Roy Jenkins who had now agreed to withdrawthe Commission&apos;s objections on the understanding that the UnitedKingdom/Australia Safeguards Agreement would be reconsideredbefore the end of 1982 if no EURATOM/Australia agreement hadbeen concluded in the meantime.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALTHE PRIME MINISTER said that she had talked to the PrimeMinister of Bahrain, Sheikh Khalifi, during a refuelling stop onher flight home from Australia.    He had emphasised the importancewhich Middle East oil countries attached to the safeguarding of therights of the Palestinian people; but also the desirability of morefrequent first-hand contacts between the Middle East oil countriesand the Western world.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that onhis way home from Japan he had visited Iraq, where the Governmenthad agreed with him that the boycott on British trade should be lifted,but had proved unwilling to release an unjustly imprisoned Britishsubject although they had agreed to improvements in his treatment.THE FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that hehad discussed the refugee problem in Hong Kong and Malaysia onhis way back from Japan.    We would now need to prepare our ownpolicy line for the international conference which the United NationsHigh Commission for Refugees was holding in Geneva on 20 July;this could be worked out between the Prime Minister, the HomeSecretary and himself,THE PRIME MINISTER added that while in Australia she had urgedthe Australian Prime Minister, Mr Fraser, to help Hong Kong&apos;sdifficulties by accepting refugees from there in addition toAustralia&apos;s normal yearly quota of Vietnamese immigrants.The Cabinet -Took note.2CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALkousjence:) 6thusions,fcand 43. THE PRIME MINISTER said that, at the European Councilin Strasbourg on 21-22 June, it had proved very difficult to get theother Member States to recognise that the United Kingdom had besnbadly treated over the Community Budget.    Nevertheless, theCouncil had agreed to instruct the Commission to present an analysis.,including the likely budget outcome in 1979 and 1980.    This wouldgo to the Council of Ministers (Finance) for comment and theCommission would then make proposals in time for the next meetingof the European Council in Dublin in November.    Progress had thusbeen made but we faced a real battle if we were to secure an adequateresponse from the rest of the Community.THE MINISTER OF AGRICULTURE, FISHERIES AND FOOD saidthat, if the United Kingdom had accepted the original Commissionproposals on Common Agricultural Policy (CAP) prices, it wouldhave involved a higher United Kingdom contribution to theCommunity budget.    As it was, the price increases agreed to bythe Council raised the Community budget by far less than the figureswhich had been given to the Press by the Commission. Ourcontribution to this increased cost was more than offset by thehigher subsidies to be paid to the United Kingdom on butter andschool milk so that we would in fact be better off by some  34 millionHe would circulate the details to the Cabinet.In a brief discussion, some concern was expressed about thecoming six months under the Irish Presidency.    The Irish PrimeMinister had been most unhelpful during the discussions about theUnited Kingdom budget problem at Strasbourg.    There were closelinks between the Irish and the French who took a similar line onmany issues of interest to us.    For example, there was evidencethat the French wanted to postpone a settlement of the fisheriesissue in the expectation that our legal position would be weakerafter 1 January 1982.    They would try to persuade the IrishPresidency to put off the Fisheries Council scheduled for theautumn, although Commissioner Gundelach had assured theMinister of Agriculture privately that the Commission would notstart proceedings in the European Court against the United Kingdom&apos;snational conservation measures before the Council had met.The Cabinet -Took note.CONFIDENTIAL2?0 0
CONFIDENTIAL4. THE PRIME MINISTER recalled the Cabinet&apos;s discussion on14 June on the undesirability of holding a further inquiry into breachesof Rhodesian sanctions (CC(79) 6th Meeting, Minute 8) when it hadbeen agreed to defer a final decision until Lord Harlech, theGovernments special representative in Africa, had returned fromNigeria.    In deciding to defer a decision the Cabinet had been influencedpartly by consideration of opinion in Africa and partly by the fact thatthe Director of Public Prosecutions (DPP) had still to reach hisdecision on whether any prosecutions should, follow from the BinghamReport.    Lord Harlech had now reported but &apos;the DPP had not yettaken a decision on prosecutions.    The question remained whetherthe time was yet right for the Cabinet to reach a decision and announceit.the FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH SECRETARY said that hefavoured further deferring a decision.    The Nigerian Governmenthad reacted adversely to the British Petrulftfcna (BP)- CONOCO oilexchange deal which would result in non-embargoed crude oil beingsupplied to South Africa.    Even though that decision was entirelydefensible, a decision now not to institute a further inquiry intoRhodesian sanctions would exacerbate relations with Nigeria in therun up to the Meeting of Commonwealth Heads of Government due tobe held in Lusaka in the following month.    There was moreoverlittle pressure in Parliament for a Government announcement and,even if the Government were pressed for a decision, such pressurecould easily be resisted.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up a brief discussion, said that theCabinet agreed that a final decision on whether there should be afurther inquiry should in any case be deferred until the intentions ofthe Director of Public Prosecutions were known on the question ofprosecutions arising from the Bingham Report.    To defer a decisionand an announcement would have the additional advantage of avoidingprejudicing the atmosphere at the forthcoming Meeting of theCommonwealth Heads of Government.    Any Parliamentary pressure foran announcement could continue to be met by saying that no decisionhad yet been reached.    The Cabinet would return to the issue in theautumn when the decision of the Director of Public Prosecutions wasknown.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Minister&apos;ssumming up of their discussion.CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster (C(79) 24) reporting on thesoundings which had been taken on proposals for dealing with the payof Members of Parliament and Ministers contained in the 12th Reportof the Review Body on Top Salaries (TSRB).THE CHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTER said that theCabinet&apos;s original proposals had proved very unpopular with theHouse and in his view unless some concession were made there wasa grave risk that the Motion to implement them would be defeated.The Chief Whip had discussed possible changes in the Governmentsproposals with the 1922 Committee and the Chairman of thatCommittee had subsequently written to make the specific proposalsset out in paragraph 2 of C(79) 24.    In his view the Governmentshould accept these proposals with one change designed to bring themmore closely into line with those recommended by the TSRB. Thiswould involve paying 50 per cent of the increase recommended byTSRB in the first stage.    This would be only slightly more generousthan the 1922 Committee proposal for the majority of Members, butwould avoid an anomaly by which certain Office-Holders would havebeen substantially worse off under the 1922 Committee proposals.It would also have the presentational advantage that the Cabinet wouldnot be seen to accede completely to an approach recommended by aCommittee of backbenchers.    He would propose that the remainderof the TSRB increase should be paid in two further equal instalmentsin June 1980, and June 1981, and that the June 1980 figure should beupdated to take account of inflation meanwhile, in a manner analogousto that adopted for other Review Body groups.    The TSRB should alsobe asked specifically to seek one or more professional analogues towhich the pay of MPs could be linked in the future.    The aim shouldbe to have these available for any updating that proved necessary in1981.In discussion it was agreed that the main principle to be preservedwas that the settlement should not be more generous than thetreatment that had been accorded to other Review Body groups.That implied three stages, spread over two years.    No commitmentcould be given to updating of the third stage.    Although there wereconsiderable problems with establishing &quot;linkage&quot;, opinion in theHouse was such that unless the Cabinet made some recommendation onthis, it seemed likely that amendments to provide for linkage wouldbe made to the Governments Motion and carried.    There were gravedisadvantages in the use of a general index of earnings or in linking,directly or in percentage terms, to hierarchical, and incremental,salary scales, such as that of the Assistant Secretary in the CivilService.    The suggestion from the 1922 Committee for a link withprofessional salaries therefore had attraction, and would result inperiodic reviews by an independent body outside the control of theHouse.5CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALFor Ministers1 salaries it was argued that the biennial reviewssuggested by the TSRB should be adopted, and that some form ofupdating between reviews was desirable for Minijt^nfial salaries,as for Parliamentary salaries.    However it was noted that with75 per cent of the TSRB increase now proposed for payment fromJune 1980, updating at that time could well take the Ministerialsalaries above the final level recommended by TSRB.    It was feltthat Cabinet Ministers should impose a ceiling on the uprating oftheir own salaries) to the final level recommended by the TSRBReport.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that theCabinet were agreed that the TSRB recommendations should beimplemented in three stages, spread over two years.    50 per centof the increases would be paid immediately, and the remainder intwo equal instalments in June 1980 and June 1981.    The June 1980increase would be further updated, in a manner analogous   to thatadopted for other Review Body groups.    These conclusions wouldapply to the salaries of Members of Parliament, Ministers andother Office-holders, but for Cabinet Ministers the amount payablein June 1980 for their Ministerial salary would be limited to thefigures recommended in the 12th Report of the TSRB. TheGovernment would invite the TSRB both to carry out the 1980 upratingand to make recommendations abont one or.more auaaloguea in theprofessions to which Members&apos; salaries could be related from 1981onwards.    Ministerial salaries would be subject to a biennial reviewby the TSRB beginning in 1981.    There had already been extensiveconsultation, and there was no need for a further Governmentannouncement.    Subject to further consultations during the courseof the day, through the usual channels, the Government should putdown Motions, on the line3 agreed, on Friday 6 July which wouldallow sufficient time for Members to prepare for a debate onWednesday 11 July.The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministers&apos;summing up of their discussion, and invited theChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, and otherMinisters concerned to be guided accordingly.6CONFIDENTIAL91
CONFIDENTIAL6.        The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Secretaryof State for Industry (C(79) 23) recommending substantial changes inthe level of Government support for regional industrial development,and reporting discussion in the Ministerial Committee on EconomicStrategy, Subcommittee on Economic Affairs (E(EA)).THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDUSTRY said that his proposalswere intended to make regional policy more effective, and at the sametime secure substantial reductions in public expenditure.    At present,40 per cent of the population lived in assisted areas, and theboundaries had not been substantially altered since 1972.    As aresult there were substantial anomalies in the present system. Anurgent decision was now needed, both to remove uncertainty on thepart of investors, and to secure the earliest possible savings. Adebate would be necessary on the Order to reduce the level of grant.His proposals had been discussed in E(EA) where there had beengeneral agreement on the need for a more cost-effective policy, butdisagreement on the speed and extent of change.    In subsequentdiscussion, he had modified his proposals to meet some of theseobjections.    There remained four areas of difficulty.    First, it wouldbe useful presentationally to link the announcement of changes inregional policy with some more positive measures to help industry.But it might not be possible to reach agreement on these in time for anannouncement before the summer recess.    Some of his colleaguesplaced considerable  emphasis on this.    Second, some Ministers feltthat the proposed reduction in the rate of grant in Development Areas(DAs) were too steep.    It might be sufficient to reduce it from 20 percent to 15 per cent, although this would slightly reduce the availablesavings.    Third, he was prepared to reconsider the proposed down-grading of the Rhondda Valley from Special Development Area (SDA) toDA status, although the precise boundaries of the SDA would need to beconsidered further.    Changes of this kind, however, risked creatinggrave anomolies and should be kept to a minimum.    Fourth, heproposed that all areas being downgraded should retain their presentrate of Regional Development Grant for one year.    Thereafter thepresent Intermediate Areas which it was proposed should lose theirAssisted Area status would retain the new style Intermediate Areabenefits for a further 2 years before losing their status. AssistedAreas which it was proposed to downgrade by more than one stepwould in any case retain Assisted Area status until the end of the3-year transitional period.    Before that period expired their futurestatus should be reviewed in the light of the developing situation.In discussion there was general support for the modified proposals,and welcome for the concessions which the Secretary of State forIndustry had suggested.    It was however argued that the politicalsituation in Scotland and Wales remained very delicate, and that eventhe modified proposals would expose the Government to much criticism.Some of the areas affected were those where the Government had onlyrecently made electoral gains, often by small margins, and some7CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALmembers might have difficulty in supporting them.    In presenting thechanges, it should therefore be made clear that the proposal to withdrawassistance at least in those cases where a double dov npfading wasinvolved would be reviewed before the end of the three year transitionalperiod and that no area should be downgraded by more than one step ayear.    Even with these changes, the sharp differentiation between SDAand DA status would make it more difficult to operate a sensible regionalpolicy in areas like South Wales, where the SDAs were geographicallyunattractive to internationally-mobile industry.    In addition, it wouldbe important to maintain the operations of the Welsh Development Agencyand analogous bodies in the rural areas which would lose assisted areastatus.In further discussion, it was argued that the proposed regional packagewould gain in presentation, if it were linked to an announcement of morepositive measures to help industry.    A number of so-called Accelerator&apos;schemes were under consideration.    But these would take time to workout in sufficient detail, and could not be announced before the summerrecess.    A simpler alternative might be to create &apos;pilot areas&apos; in placessuch as Shotton and Merseyside, where a five-year tax holiday might begiven, and where quick decisions could be promised on planningapplications for new industrial development.    It might be possible todevise a limited scheme on these lines in time for announcement beforethe recess.THE PRIME MINISTER, summing up the discussion, said that the Cabinetagreed upon the need for a major change in the direction of regionalassistance for industry, so to concentrate help on the areas of greatestneed.    The rates of Regional Development Grant payable in SDAs shouldremain at 22 per cent.    The rates in DAs should be reduced from20 per cent to 15 percent.    Regional Development Grant should beabolished in Intermediate Areas.    Minimum values for eligibility forgrants should be increased as proposed by the Secretary of State forIndustry.    The coverage of assisted areas should be modified in the wayproposed by the Secretary of State for Industry, and set out in Map 2annexed to his paper C(79) 23.    However, the Rhondda Valley shouldremain a SDA, and the exact boundaries of that area should be settledbetween the Secretary of State for Industry and the Secretary of Statefor Wales.    The areas to be downgraded should retain their presententitlement to Regional Development Grant for one year. Thereafterthe present Intermediate Areas which it was proposed should lose theirAsairted Area status should remain eligible for selective assistance andfor access to the European Development Fund for two more years.Assisted Areas which it was proposed to downgrade by more than onestep should not be downgraded by more than one step a year, nor shouldsuch areas lose their Assisted Area status before the end of the 3-yeartransitional period.    In addition the position of areas suffering morethan one downgrading should be reviewed before the end of the transitionalperiod to see whether they should continue to receive Assisted Area statusthereafter in the light of the developing situation.    The review should be8CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALgenuine and carry no presumption that the present decision wasirreversible.    The areas subject to review should be separatelydistinguished as review areas on any published maps.    The Welsh andScottish Development Agencies, the Development Board for RuralWales, and the Highlands and Islands Development Board should retaintheir present functions in the areas being downgraded, subject to areview during the transitional period.    Industrial DevelopmentCertificates (idc&apos;s) should no longer be required in Intermediate Areasand the exemption limits for idc&apos;s in the non-assisted areas should beraised to 50, 000 sq. feet.    The Secretary of State for Industry shouldannounce the Governments decisions on these matters in the week of16 July, and the necessary Order should be introduced and debatedthereafter.     Precise timing should be agreed between the Secretary ofState and the Leader of the House.    The exact terms of the announcementshould also be agreed between the Secretary of State for Industry, theSecretary of State for Scotland and the Secretary of State for Wales.The Governments decisions should be discussed with the EuropeanCommission as necessary.    The Secretary of State for Industry shouldinvite the British Steel Corporation to defer an announcement of theirintention to close steel making at Shotton until after the Governmentsannouncement on Regional Industrial policy.    The Chancellor of theExchequer should consider urgently, in consultation with the Secretaryof State for Industry and the Secretary of State for the Environment,what might be said at the same time as the announcement about theproposed &quot;pilot1 schemes.    A reference to the schemes should ifpossible be included in the announcement.-The Cabinet -Took note, with approval, of the Prime Ministerssumming up of their discussion, and invited theMinisters concerned to be guided accordingly.Cabinet Office5 July 19799CONFIDENTIAL94

</content>
</cab>
