<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/8/0 images: 64-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOYERNMENt3 printed for the Cabinet.   March 1946.SECRET. Copy No. 3 cp. (46) 106.m/i March, 1946.CABINET.POLISH ARMED FORCES UNDER BRITISH COMMAND.Note by the Prime Minister.SPECIAL efforts must be made to find an early and effective solution ofthe various problems connected with the dispersal of the Polish Armed forces under British Command, and with the future of their dependents and otherPolish civilians now under the control of the Interim Treasury Committee forPolish questions.2.   These problems fall into four groups : -(a) The need for the immediate removal of Polish troops from Italy and thedisbanding as soon as practicable of all Polish forces under british command.(b) The completion of arrangements for the repatriation to Poland of those members of the Polish Forces under British Command and their dependants who are willing to return.(c) The settlement in British or foreign countries overseas of some proportionof those Polish soldiei-s and civilians who are unwilling to return to poland.(d) The absorption of the remainder in the United Kingdom, whether incivil employment or in the British Aimed Forces.3. These various aspects of the problem concern different groups of Depart-ments; and I understand that they have already received a good deal of attention from inter-departmental Conferences of Officials convened by the Foreign Office.Moreover, the larger part of the residual problem under 2 (d) above falls withinthe scope of the Cabinet Committee on Foreign Labour which was recentlyappointed under the Chairmanship of the Lord Privy Seal.
I am satisfied, however, that further machinery is required to assure theForeign Secretary of the sustained and effective support of his colleagues in securing the early dispersal of these Polish Forces. We cannot tolerate very much longer either the grave political embarrassment, or the heavy financial commit-ment involved by our maintenance of these Forces under arms. The problemmust be vigorously tackled, and all Ministers concerned must be ready to make a contribution towards its solution.4. I have decided to appoint a small steering committee, composed asfollows : Chancellor of the Exchequer (Chairman).Lord Privy Seal.Home Secretary.Secretary of State for War.Minister of Labour.Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,to review the whole problem of the dispersal of the Polish Forces under british Command, to direct and stimulate the search for an early solution of thevarious parts of the problem, and to report to the Cabinet at the earliest possible date the measures which are being taken, or are recommended, to determine thepresent deadlock.This steering committee will call into consultation from time to timeMinisters who are not members of the committee but are directly concerned withparticular aspects of the problem. They will arrange for the component partsof the problem to be studied by groups of Ministers or officials of the departments directly affected. They will arrange, through the Lord Privy Seal, for the CabinetCommittee on Foreign Labour to give specialty early consideration to the questionof absorbing Polish troops into civil employment in the United Kingdom.5. I hope that, in general, the Secretary of State for War will speak on the steering committee for the other two Service Departments. The other service ministers will, however, be called into consultation on matters in which they havea special interest.The Chiefs of Staff will be in attendance at the steering committee, as required.6.   The whole of this work is to proceed with the utmost urgency.C. 11. A.10 Downing Street, S.W.1,11th March, 1946.



</content>
</cab>
