<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/49/0 images: 360-371</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
i.BMI. COPY HOOABIOf   15(25).Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at 10 Downing Street,S.W.I., on WEDNESDAY, MARCH 11th, 1925, at 11,30 A.M,AGENDA.1.     THE AHUCAL REGISTER OF ELECTORS.Memorandum by the Chance smaller of the Exchequer.(CP,100(25)   -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Home Secretary,(0.2.12.5(25)   -*   already circulated).e.     ARTILLERY FOR IHStAK STATES *(Reference Cabinet 66(24), Conclusion 6).Memorandum by the Chairman of theCommittee of Imperial Defence.(C,Pft 126(25)   -   already circulated).3.     gfCHOOL TEACHERS SUPERANNUATION.Re-port of Cabinet Committee.(CP. 73(25)   -   already circulated).Memorandum by the Secretary for Scotland.(CP. 141(25)   -   To he circulated).4.    the bbhguella railway aim thade facilitiesact guarait^e;Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.(J5.P. 137(25)   -   already circulated).Note by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.(CP. 140(25)   -   To be circulated).45.     ^IMPERIAL WAR GRAVES COMMISSION.Kote by the Secretary of State for War,(CP. 113(85)   -   already circuleted)rflOUMEHT IS the PROPERTY Off HIS BRITABflIC MAJBSTY&apos;3 government^RNMEM?) .
6.     m AWAIHS COmiTTKE.Consideration of Recommendations of Meetingheld on March 9th, 1925.(JI.A.O. 6th Conclusions (35) - To he circulated).ADDITIONAL HEM.Disinterested Management of Licensed Premises,Memo, by Lord Privy Seal,(CP. 147(25)    - circulated herewith). AJSfKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.9th    Maroh, 1985.4f-   -
6.     HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE,Consideration of Recommendations of Meetingheld on March 9th, 1905.(JI.A.O. 6th Conclusions (25) - 5?o fee circulated).(Signed)   M. P.. A. HAHKBY,secretar&apos;, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.9th     Maroh, 1985.
Secretary.,jB C RE I.COPY HO.CABINET   15.(85),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.1., on WEDNESDAY,MARCH 11th, 1985, at 11.30 A.M.PRESENT.-The Right Eon. Stanley Baldwin, M.E.,Prime Minister,jbe Eight Hon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.ie Right Hon.W.S. Churchill, C.E.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.ie Right Hon.L.S. Amery, M.P.,Secretary of State forthe Colonies.le Right Hon..The Earl of Birkenhead,Seoretary of State for India.Ilie Hight Eon.W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,first Lord of the Admiralty^jhe Right Hen.   sNeville Chamberlain, M.P.,Minister of Health.ihe Right Hon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President,of the Board ofEducation.mpe Right Hon. -I   Viscount Peel, G.B.E., first commissioner of Works.(In the Chair).The Most Hon.The Marquess of Salisbury,L.G.,G.G.V.O.;0o Bd,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Eon.Sir William Joynson-Hicks,Bart.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Home Affairs.The Right Hon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bart.,G.B.E.,M.P., Secretaryof State for War.The Right Hon.Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Eon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-Lister,K.BoB. ,M.C. ,E.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right; Eon.Sir John Gilmour, Bart.,D.S.O.,M.P., Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon.-Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland, Bart,M.P. , Minister of Labour..The Right Hon.Viscount Cecil of Chelwood,E.C.Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster.The Right Hon. Sir Douglas Hogg,E.C., M.P., Attorney-General,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO-PRESENTThe Right Hon. Walter Guinness, D.S.0..M.P.,Financial Secretary, Treasury.(For Item 8).ir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B..................................Seoretary.(jpIS.JDOClMEBT IS IHE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC majesty is GOVERNMENT).
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic-secret cabinet 15 (25).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cahinet,held at 10, Downing Street? S.W. 1, onWEDNESDAY, MARCH 11th, 1925, at 11-30 a.in,LEAKAGE OPINFORMATION.(previous reference:Cabinet 51(24), Con-conclusion 5. )1. The attention of the Cabinet was drawn to several recent instances of premature disclosure inthe Press of decisions taken by the Cabinet, including a reference in the Press to the Court of Inquiry tobe set up in connection with the &quot;Weir&quot; houses, whichhad added considerably to the difficulty of negotiationswith the Trades Unions concerned, as well as a para-graph which, though inaccurate in detail, mentioned the setting up of a Cabinet Committee under theChairmanship of the Secretary for Scotland on thesubjeot of naval, military and air pay.The Prime Minister made an appeal for the utmostreticence in referring outside to discussions which hadtaken place at the Cabinet.
t! 3 92. The Cabinet had before&apos; them a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer, covering a minute by the Financial Secretary to the Treasury in regardto a proposal for a single Annual Register of Electors(Paper CP.-100 (25)), and a Memorandum by the HomeSecretary raising objection tb the proposed ohange(Paper CP.-125 (25)).The Cabinet agreed (by a majority)  (a; That legislation should be introduced to authorise the preparation of asingle Annual Register of Electorsin place of the two half-yearlyRegisters:(b) That provision should be made in theBill for shortening the qualifyingperiod for a vote from six months to three months:(c) That the Home Secretary and any other minister concerned, in consultationwith the Chancellor of the Exchequer,should prepare a Bill to give effeotto these decisions, and should takeadvantage of this opportunity to remedy certain small defects of administrative machinery which have developed in the working of the representation of the People Act,1918.
INDIA.3.   After consideration of a Memorandum by theChairman of the Committee of Imperial Defence, reporting the Conclusions of the Committee on the subject of artillery for Indian States, which had been referred back to them by the Cabinet (Paper CP. -126(25)), the Cabinet agreed (by a majority)To approve the following re-affirmationby the Committee of Imperial Defence oftheir previous recommendation, viz:-&quot;&quot;That 15-pr. guns should be Issued toseleoted Indian States, subjebt tothe following provisos&apos; which are setforth more fully in C.I.D. PaperNo. 136-D:-(a) Only selected States should besupplied with 15-pr.  guns, andthe proportion of artillery toother arms in those States shouldnot be higher than in the british army, and&quot;the control of the supplyof ammunition should rest with theGovernment of India.(b) The implication should be avoidedthat the pattern of artillery whichhas last been rejected by the regular forces should successively be con-ceded to selected States.(c) The Government of India should beinformed of the reasons which haveinduced His Majesty&apos;s Government to sanction the issue of 15-pr. guns to Indian States, and that thearguments put forward by the Gov-ernment of&apos;India which might suggest the grant of field artillery of thelatest pattern are not endorsed.(At the Meeting of the Committee of ImperialDefence &apos;here &quot;this recoimiendation was made,the Chancellor of the Exchequer had asked that his dissent night be recorded.)
3H00LTEACHERS1SUPERANNUA-[ON.previous reference:cabinet 335) , Con-conclusion 5.)4.   After consideration of the Report of a CabinetCommittee on School Teachers&apos; Superannuation (paper cp.-73 (25)), and a Memorandum by the Secretary forSoot land urging that contributions paid by teachers and employers should be funded, as was recommendedby the Emmott Committee (Paper CP.-141 (25)), theCabinet agreed  (a) To approve the Report of the CabinetCommittee:(b) That contributions by teachers and employers should not be funded.(c) That provision should be made in theSchool Teachers1  (Superannuation) bill that alien school teachers should nolonger be excluded from the pension scheme:(d) That, subject to preliminary examina-tion of the School Teachers&apos;  (Super-annuation) Bill by the Committee.ofHome Affairs, the Minister of Educa-tion should have authority to intro-duce it in the House of Commons atthe earliest possible date.
5. After consideration of a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (Paper CP--137 (25))and a iSlote by the Secretary of State for the Colonies(Paper C.P.-140 (25)) In regard to an applicationfor a guarantee under the Trade Facilities Actsin respect of the completion of the Bengaella Railway.the Cabinet agreed  That j with a view to an early decision by the Cabinet, the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies should inform theGovernments of Southern Rhodesia andNorthern Rhodesia by telegram of thepresent situation in regard to theBenguella Railway, namely:   that his majesty s Government had information which leads them to believe that theextension of the Benguella Eailwuyto the Belgian frontier, where It willmeet the Belgian Government railway line from the Katanga Copper Mines,will be proceeded with at ones, andthat no difficulty is anticipated in raising the necessary capital:   thatan application has been made for aguarantee under the Trade FacilitiesActs;   that if this guarantee is granted, orders to the extent of between  1,500,000 and  2,000,000will be given in this country;   andthat if no guarantee is given, theorders for the railway material willbe placed in Belgium or elsewhere onthe Continent.    He should explain that, while His Majesty&quot;s Governmentare anxious to take no step whichwould result in injury to the -railway,interests of Southern or northern rhodesia, or which would tend to weakenImperial sentiinsnt in those Colonies,yet, in the present very serious stateof unemployment in this country, theyare most reluctant that manufacturersshould lose the orders of the BenguellaRailway, which wnni^ aan^^ .  -* -&quot;As in any event they cannot presentthe construction of the railway, the Governmentwould not wish to place any. obstacle in the       jum*uwoHte Trade Facilities Act Advisory ^Committee considering the question o   J -gjguarantee as an ordinary business Position,   -but that before communicating a decisionto this effect to the Committee they wishto learn what the local feeling would bewhen Si the circumstances of the case arerealised&quot;.
5. After consideration of a Memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (Paper.0. P.-137 (25))and a Note by the Secretary of State for the Colonies(Paper CP.-140 (25)) in regard to an applicationfor a guarantee under the Trade Facilities Actsin respect of ths completion of the Benguelia Railway?the Cabinet agreed  That, with a view to an early decision by the Cabinet, the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies should inform theGovernments of Southern Rhodesia andNorthern Rhodesia by telegram of thepresent situation in regard to theBenguella Railway, namely:    that HisMajesty&apos;s Government had information which leads them to believe that theextension of the Benguella Railwayto the Belgian frontier? where it willmeet the Belgian Government railway line from the Katanga Copper Mines,will be proceeded with at once, andthat no difficulty is anticipated in raising the necessary capital:   thatan application has been made for aguarantee under the Trade FacilitiesActs;   that If this guarantee is granted, orders to the extent of between  1,500,000 and  2,000,000will be given in this country;   andthat if no guarantee is given, theorders for the railway material willbe placed in Belgium or elsewhere onthe Continent.   He should explain that, while His Majesty&quot;s Governmentare anxious to take no step whichwould result in injury to the railway-interests of Southern or northern rhodesia, or which would tend to weakenImperial sentiment in those Colonies,yet, in the present very serious stateof unemployment in this country, theyare most reluctant that manufacturersshould lose the orders of the BenguellaRailway, which would secure employment .in the very trades in which it is most
ous-ence:Con- .2.)6. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Lord Privy Seal in which he referred to actionwhich he had taken..when in Opposition, to urge an inquiry into the  system of disinterested management of licensed premises, and suggested that the Governmentshould agree to an inquiry which was being urged byLord Lamington in the House of Lords (Paper CP.-147(25)).As Lord Lamington had agreed to postpone for a week, the question was reserved for consideration ata. later Meeting.er-mentoensedes.
g IMPERIAL 7. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bv the$, GRAVESOMMISSION. Secretary of State for War, enclosing a Memorandum by major-General Sir Fabian Ware, the Permanent Vioe-previous conference: Chairman of the Imperial War Graves Commission, inablnet 6722), Con- which he recommended that the present rate of annuallusion 1*)contribution of  1,222,800 be continued for 6^ yearsso that, with proportionate contributions by DominionGovernments, the cost of completing the memorialsand of maintenance during the period may be defrayedand a capital sum may be accumulated which will provide an annual Income of  210,000 to defray the cost ofmaintenance in perpetuity (Paper CP.-113 (25)).While the Cabinet were unanimous that adequate provision must be made for maintaining in perpetuitythe graves of those who had sacrificed their lives inthe War, there was considerable discussion as towhether this should be effected by means of an acoumu-lated sum the interest of which would defray the cost,or whether, as a matter of principle, the cost shouldnot be brought before Parliament in the Annual Esti-mates, thus providing a convenient opportunity fordiscussion.The Cabinet agreed (by a majority) (a) To approve the principle of accumulatinga capital sum which will provide the annual income required to defray&quot;the cost ofmaintenance in perpetuity:   .(b) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should make a proposal to the cabinet as to the number of years over whichthe instalments for accumulating themaintenance fund should be spread.2s Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1,March 11, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
