<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/49/0 images: 372-393</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
nOCPMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS, BRITANNICi majesty&apos;s GOVERNMENT,)COPY NO.    4    jC AiJvB J.KET    Ifl(25) *Meeting of the Cabinet to be held at 10 Downing Street,s.Vv. (1)., on Wednesday, the 18th March, 1925, at 11.30 a.ra.AGENDA.1. THE DOMINIONS AND THE COLONIAL OFFICE *Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies,(CP. 148(25)     -       already circulated).2. NAVAL POLICY.(Statement by the Chairman of the Naval programme committee).3. CONSTRUCTION OF EXTSNSIONAL SECTION OF FLOATING DOCK,Memorandum by the First Lord of the Admiralty,(CP. 156(25)     -     circulated herewith).4* TERMS OF REFERENCE OF COMMITTEE-ON MARRIAGE allowances for THE NAVY AND RATES OF&apos; PAY OF NEW ENTRANTS IN THE(Reference Cabinet 9(25) Conclusion 2).Note by the Chairman of the Committee,(CP. 130(25)     -     already circulated).5. liquor control * disinterested management of licensed&quot;&quot;Premises&quot;:(Reference Cabinet 15(25) Conclusion 6).Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal,(CP. 147(25)     -     already circulated).Memoranda   by the Home Secretary,(CP, 154(25)     -     already circulated).(CP.  158(25)      -     to be circulated).  &apos;q&apos; the RETAIL PRICES. IN HOUSEHOLD COAL.Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade,(CP. 155(25)     -     already circulated).
7. HOUSE OP LORDS REFORM.8. HOD/IE AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.Consideration of Recommendations on thefollowing subjectsfi) The Charitable Trusts Bill.H.A.C.  6l25T&quot;l.(ii) The Circuit Courts and Criminal ProcedureTScotland) Bill.H.A.C.  6T25T 4.(iii) The Sandwich Port and Haven Bill.H.A.C.  6(25)  5.(H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (25) - already circulated)(iv) The Greenwich Hospital (DisusedBurial Ground! BiJLl.H.A.C. 7(25&apos;Tl.&apos;ADDITIONAL ITM3 TO AGENDA.:,^ted).JUDICIAL PROCEEDINGS (REGULATION OF REPORTS) BILL.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.(CP. 163(25)    -   Circulated herewith).PUBLIC HEALTH BILL. 1925.Memorandum by the Minister of Health covering:Private member&apos;s Bill,(CP. 164(25)   -   Circulated herewith).2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.116th March, 1925.
7. HOUSE OF LORDS REFORM.8* HOME AFFAIRS COMMITTEE.Consideration of Recommendations on thefollowing subjects(i) The Charitable Trusts Bill.H.A.C.  61257 1.(ii) The Circuit Courts and Criminal ProcedureTScotland) Bill.H.A.C 6T257 4.(iii) The Sandwich Port and Haven Bill.H.A.C.  6(25)  5.(H.A.C. 6th Conclusions (25) - already circulated).(iv) The Greenwich Hospital (DisusedBurial GroundT, Bill.H.A.C,  7T55T&quot;1.&quot;(v) School Teachers Superannuation Bill.H.A.C.  7(25)  2.&quot;(H.A .C. 7th Conclusions (25) - to be circulated).(Signed) M.P.A. RANKEY,Secretary, Cabinet.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.116th March, 1925.
The Secretary.347k DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY 03? HIS BRITAINIC MAJESTY1 .jt GOVERHMSNT)aiCBE T. COPY no.c a bj net    16(25).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W.1., on WEDNESDAY,MARCH 18th, 1925, at 11.30 A.M.PRESENT.-The Right Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.,Prime Minister.Right Hon..aAusten Chamberlain, M.P.,secretary of State forIjJoreign Affairs.ae Right Eon.fSLS,. churchill, C,H.,M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.Right Hon.Ili,S. Amery, M.P.,iSeoretary of State forthe Colonies.I Right Hon.The Earl of Birkenhead,Secretary of State for India.Right Hon.1W.C. Bridgeman, M.P.,Hrst lord of the Admiralty,e Right Hon.I Seville Chamberlain, M.P.,^Minister of Health.p Right Eon.jSir John Gilmour, Bart.,D.S.0,jM,P., Secretary for Scotland.p Right Hon.(Sir Arthur Steel-Maitland, Bart.,Minister of Labour.f Right Hon.[Viscount Cecil of Chelwood, L.C.,Chancellor of the Duchy ofI&amp;n caster,.(In the Chair).The Right Eon.Viscount Cave, G.C.M.G.,Lord Chancellor.The Right Eon.Sir William Joynson-Eicks,Bart.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Eome Affairs.The Right Eon.Sir Laming Worthington-Evans,Bart.,G.B.E. ,M.P.,&quot;Secretaryof State for War.The Right Eon.Sir Samuel hoare, Bart.,C.M.G.,M.P., Secretary ofState for Air.The Right Hon.Sir Philip Cunliffe-LIster,E.B.E.,M.C.,M.P., Presidentof the Board of Trade.The Right Hon.E.F.L. Wood, Stop,, Ministerof Agriculture and Fisheries.The Right Eon.Lord Eustace Percy, M.P.,President of the Board ofEducation,The Right Eon.Yiscount Peel, G.3.E., first commissioner of Works.The Right Hon.Sir Douglas Hogg, K.C.,M.P.,Att orney-General.THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT: -Lt.-Col. 6.R. Lane-Fox, M.P.,Parliamentary Secretary,(Mines Department), Board of Trade.(For Item 6).M.P.A, Eankey, G.CB..................................Secretary.
lo The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the secretary of State for the Colonies containing proposals for the re-organisation of the ColonialOffice (Paper CP.-148 (25)), which may be summed upas follows(i) That, while the Dominion point of viewshould be fully accepted by the creationof a separate Secretaryship of State for. Dominion Affairs and of a Dominions Office,the practical aspects of the case shouldbe met by continuing the new Secretary-ship in the same person as the ColonialSecretaryship and by retaining the dominions office for internal administration purposes has a part of the Colonial Office:(ii) That an additional Parliamentary Under-Seoretary of State should be appointedto deal with Dominion affairs and to actas Chairman of the Oversea SettlementCommittee:(iii) That an additional Permanent Under-Seoretaxy should be appointed so as toenable each side of the work to be directly in charge of a man of first-class ability and of the right temperament:(Iv) The control of the Colonial Office as an office to be vested in. the Permanent Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies.After considerable discussion, the cabinet agreed  (a) That the Secretary of State for the colonies should see the High Commissioners of theDominions and should inform them that theGovernment approved in principle the follow -ing changes in the organisation of theColonial Office and would be glad if theHigh Commissioners would communicate theminformally to their respective governments and ascertain whether they would meet with approval:-(l) That a separate Secretaryship of Statefor Dominion or Imperial Aifairs shouldbe created and should be held by thesame person as the Secretaryship ofState for the Colonies:(2) That, having regard to the importanceof Oversea Settlement and to the desir-ability of rendering possible personalvisits to the various parts of theEmpire by the Secretary of State forthe Colonies and other representativesof the Colonial Office, an additionalTHS DOMINIONSAND THECOLONIALOFFICE.
Parliamentary Undersecretary ofState should &quot;be appointed to dealwith Dominion affairs and to aotas Chairman of tho Oversea Bettle-mont Committee:(3) That there should he only onePermanent Undersecretary for theColonial Office, but that Dominionaffairs should be dealt with by a. Deputy Undersecretary, who shouldbe only of slightly lower rank and status than the Undersecretaryand should have direct access tothe Secretary of State.(b) That the proposed re-or^.nisation shouldbe announced by the Secretary of Statefor the Colonies in the House of commons on his return from Iraq, and should not take effect until it had been approved in Parliament.-2-
--jaVALj POLICY. 2.  After hearing from the Secretary of State for.India, as Chairman of the Naval Programme Committee,previous reference:        a verbal report of the present position on that cabinet 8[(25), Con-        Committee, the Cabinet agreed  elusion 1.) in the first instancei* To approve the reference/    to theCommittee of Imperial Defence of the&quot;following questions:-(a) The policy of leaving to the admiralty the responsibility for the Naval defenceof the Empire on the basis of the one-Power standard was last reaffirmed bythe Committee of Lmoerial Defence in1923.Is it proposed to reverse or modifythis decision?If not, what does it in practiceinvolve?   In what waters are we to beas strong as any other Power?   Do wesatisfy the requirements of a one-Powerstandard if our fleet wherever situateis equal to the fleet of any other nationwherever situate?(b) Is aggressive action on the part of Japan,such as would tend to involve this countryin armed conflict in the Pacific duringthe next ten years, a contingency so seriously to be apprehended as to&apos;impose upon the Admiralty the responsibility ofmaking material preparations to meet it,upon the basis that we must in the Pacificbe able to confront and defeat their wholemaritime strength?(c) If the decision referred to in question (a)still stands, ought the British war plan to contemplate placing at Singapore fora decisive battle in the Pacific a Britishbattle fleet with cruisers, flotillas andall ancillary vessels&apos;superior in strength,or at least equal, to the sea-going Navyof Japan0     If so, on what date couldthis, or ought it to, be achieved having&apos; regard to the strength which must beretained in Home Waters&apos;&apos;&apos;(d) In the event of war occurring before the base at Singapore is capable&quot;of sustaininga British fleet superior to the -JapaneseNavy, what ought the interim British warplan to be?(e) If the answers to (b) and (c) are in the negative, what should be the guidingprinciples on which to form a&quot;war plan,with particular reference to the develop-ment of the base and the maintenance of fuel and other reserves in the Singaporearea?
(f) If, on the other hand, the answer to (b) is in the affirmative, andto (o) in the negative, on whatprinciples should&apos; the British Warplan be based?That the decision on the above questions should be reserved entirely for theCabinet, with whom the ultimate responsi-bility could alone lie, to whom shouldbe communicated not only the recommenda-tions but also the Minutes of the Com-mittee of Imperial Defence on the subject,and any other Papers necessary to setforth the views of the Chiefs of Staffof the three Services.
IlfJAPORE.struct iontjie Exten-Dal Seo-D Ofatingviousarence:inet, 12), Con-sion 2. j3. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty, enclosing a letter from tieAdmiralty to the Treasury on the subject of the arrange-ruents proposed for the construction of an extensionalsection of the floating dock at Singapore (Paper O.P.-156 (2,5)).The Cabinet -were reminded that when the questionof the extension of the l%val Base at Singapore hadbeen under consideration by a Sub-Committee of theCommittee of Imperial Defence, no mention had beenmade of the necessity for additional expenditure on theextension of the floating dock, and that the MarquessCurzon, who had been Chairman of the Sub-Committee, in announcing the total expenditure to be incurred on theNaval Base at Singapore during the next few years had not Included the cost of the extension of the floating dock.    To introduce a Supplementary Estimateinvolving additional expenditure over and above thatannounced by Lord Curzon,        but nevertheless requiredin connection with the Singapore base, would excitemuch adverse comment.    It was further pointed out thatthe question of the extension of the floating dock waspart of the general question of Ifeval construction which had been referred to the Cabinet Naval programme committee, and it was suggested that the Cabinet^decision in regard to the floating dock should be reserved until after they had received and dealt with gReport of the committee of Imperial Defence on the questionnaire referred to in the previous Conclusion.On the other hand, it was urged that theprogramme submitted by the Sub-Committee of theCommittee of Imperial Defence. and approved by theCabinet for placing a floating dook at Singapore
by the&apos; Spring of 1928 could not be carried out unlessthe oonstruction work on the extension of the dock wasbegan in July next, and that this would not be possible if the decision in the matter was delayed until afterthe large questions of Naval Policy referred to in theprevious Conclusion had been examined by the Committeeof Imperial Defence arid decided by the Cabinet.The Cabinet agreed - That the Naval Programme Committeeshould invest!gate &quot;whether in facta postponement for a few months ofa decision was likely seriously to delay the completion of the programme approved by the Cabinet for stationingthe floating dock at Singapore bythe end of the financial&quot;year 1927-28,and in the event of their finding thatserious delay must result from post-postponing the decision, but only in this event,&quot; they should make a separate report to the Cabinet as to the desir-ability of incurring the expenditureproposed by the Admiralty.
COMMITTEE ON 4. The cabinet.net had before them a Memorandum byMARRIAGEALLOWANCES        the Secretary fov Scotland, as Chairman of the cabinet for THE NAVYAr3D RATES Committee on Marriage Allowances for the Navy and RatesOP PAY for new ENTRANTS of Pay for new Entrants in the Fighting Services (paper in THE FIGHT-ING SERVICES.    CP.-150 (25)), proposing an extension of the Terms ofReference.previous reference: The Cabinet were reminded of the followingCabinet 9(25), Con-        Party pledge given at the General Election:-conclusion 2.)&quot;The attention of Unionist Party Head-quarters has been called to statements made on Socialist platforms that theUnionist Party, if returned to power,will reduce the pay of the FightingServices.    It would be a breach of&quot;&apos;contract to reduce the pay of men now serving in these Services, and it is absolutely untrue the Unionist party would make any attempt to do so.&quot;The Cabinet agreed  (a) That the attention of the CabinetCommittee should be drawn to theabove pledge, and that the Commit-tee should &quot;be asked to report on alternative bases:-(i) Excluding from their Termsof Reference all serving menand offioers:(ii) Including: in&apos; their Terms ofReference men re-engagingor otherwise entering on new contracts, and officers on promotion: , &quot;(b) That the Committee should also consider the p-ay-adad- s&amp;l&amp;frssettr&amp;sr jssiof cadets of the three Services.
3^* w JQ.COB CONTROL.isinterostedagement ofoehssd Pre-ses.-eviouseference:cabinet 1525), Con-conclusion 6. )5. The Cabinet had before them Memoranda by theLord Privy Seal (Paper CP.-147 (25)) and &quot;by the HomeSeoretary (Papers C.P.-145 (25)    and CP.-158 (25)), onthe subject, of the disinterested management of publichouses.The Cabinet agreed  That, in view of the Lord Privy Seal&apos;sindisposition, the Lord chancellor should ask Lord Lamington to postponehis Question for another week.-8-
IHB RETAIL 6. The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum byIRADE inHOUSEHOLD       .  the President of the Board of Trade, covering a coal.Memorandum by the Secretary for Mines on the questionPrevious of the Retail Tirade in Household Coal (Paper CP.-155Reference:Cabinet 4 (25)).(21) &apos; Oon-elusion Ita;.; There was general agreement in the desirabilityof announcing the intention of the Government to obtainpowers for the compulsory investigation of accounts of retail coal dealers, but it was felt that considerablereserve must be exercised at the present stage in announcing what powers the Government would, ask forin order to secure justice for the community If the accounts disclosed profiteering.The Cabinet agreed -That, In the light of the cabinet discussion, the&quot;President of theBoard of Trade should prepare, fortheir consideration at the usualMeeting next week, a form of wordsfor use by the Secretary for mines in the Debate on Wednesday, March25th.
1 HOUSE OP lords reform.(previous reference erence:gab inet 40(22) , Con-conclusion 4.)7. The Prime Minister read a letter from the lord privy Seal, who was absent through indisposition, Inwhich it was pointed out that there should be someintimation of the Governments attitude towards thequestion of House of Lords Reform before Wednesday,March 25th, when a Debate an the subject would begin in the House of Lords, and that some of the Government&apos;supporters in the House would like to know the sort ofanswer tho Government proposed to make.The Oabinet agreed  (a) That the Government representatives in the House of Lords should statethat the Government fully recognised the importance of, the subject, &quot;andthat they proposed to set up aCommittee to consider the question:(b) That the Lord Chancellor should inform Lord Lansdowne that thiswas the line the Government proposedto take.
THE CHARIT- 8.  After consideration of a Memorandum by theABLE TRUSTSBILL. Financial Secretary to the Treasury, covering thedraft Charitable Trusts Bill, 1925 (Paper CP.-114*(25)) , together with the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 6th. Cons*(25), Para.l), the Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction forth-with in the House of Commons of theCharitable Trusts Bill, 1925, inthe form of the draft annexed to cp.-114 (25).
9.  After consideration of a Memorandum by theSecretary for Scotland, covering the draft CircuitCourts and Criminal Procedure (Scotland) Bill (paper cp.-117 (25)), together with the recommendation ofthe Committee of Home Affairs thereon (H.A. C. 6th Cons(25), Para. 4), the Cabinet agreed  To authorise the introduction forth-with in the. House of Lords of theCircuit Courts and Criminal Prooedure(Scotland) Bill in the form of thedraft annexed to CP.-117 (25).-12-
THE SANDWICH 10. After consideration of a Memorandum by thePORT ANDgAVEN BILL.        Financial Seoretary to the Treasury, covering thedraft Sandwich Port and Haven Bill, 1925 (Paper C.P.-56 (25)), together with the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs thereon (H. A. C. 6th Cons.(25), Para.5), the Cabinet agreed  To authorise.the introduction forth-with in the House of Commons of theSandwioh Port and Haven Bill, 1925,in the form annexed to CP.-56 (25),sub^eot to drafting amendments, with aview to its passage into law, ifpossible, before the summer recess.-13-
H* After consideration of a Memorandum by theFirst Lord of the Admiralty, covering a Bill toauthorise buildings to be erected on a disused burialground forming part of Greenwich Hospital (paper c.P.-123 (25)), and of the proceedings of the Committeeof Home Affairs thereon (H.A.C. 6th Cons. (25), Para.2),and H.A. C. 7th. Cons.  (25), Para.l), the cabinet agreed - To authorise the introduction In theHouse of Commons of the GreenwichHospital (Disused Burial Ground)Bill.-14-
TEACHERS0UPER-annuationBILL.(previous reference:Cabinet 15(25), Con7elusion 4(d). )12. After considering a draft of the&apos; Teachers&apos;Superannuation Bill (Paper C.P. -152 (25)) and therecommendation of the Committee of Home affairs thereon (H. A.Q, 7th.Cons.  (25)., Para.2), theCabinet agreedTo approve the - Introduction of theBill, subject to minor and drafting amendments and to certain detailsbeing adjusted between the Presidentof the Board of Education and theTreasury.-15-
TBS PUBLIC 13.  After consideration of a Memorandum by the health BILL,1925, Minister of Health, covering the Public Health Billpresented by a Private Member, which is the second Orderin the House of Commons on Friday, March 20th, theCabinet agreed  That the Minister of Health shouldbe authorised to give the Bill his general support, without committing himself to the approval of anyparticular provision, and to under- 1take that the Government would affordsuch facilities as may be-necessary at later stages.-16-
JUDICIALPROCEEDINGS(REGULATIONOP REPORTS)BILL.14. The Cabinet agreed&apos;  That the Memorandum by the HomeSecretary on the Judicial Proceed-ings (&quot;Regulation of Reports) Bill(Paper CP.-163 (25)), should beconsidered at the next wsoKlyMeeting of the Cabinet.-17-
NSXT meeting of OABINET.15. The Oabinet agreedThat a Special Meeting of the cabinet should be held in the-Prime Minister&apos;sBoom at the House of 0cannons on FRIDAYnext, MARCH 20th, at 11 a.m. , for &quot;whichrhe^SeclFetar;/ was &quot;instructed to placeon the Agenda the following questions :.-FOREIGN AFFAIRS,    Statement by the Secretary2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1March 18, 1925.

</content>
</cab>
