<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/155/23 images: 389-391</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HJ.S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government cp(71) 23 COPY NO 0218 February 1971CABINETANNUAL REVIEW OF THE AGRICULTURAL INDUSTRY 1971Note by the Lord President of the Council\introduction. The Ministerial Committee on Agricultural Policy has consideredthe line to be taken in the discussions with the farmers1 unionr,9 be ginningon 24 February, about the determination to be made in the light of the 1971review of the agricultural industry,1970-712.        In 1970-71, agricultural production has moved ahead in reasonable balance after recovering in 1969-70 from a sharp fall in the previous year.The only important exception is sheep, where the breeding flock continuesto decline0    In real terms? total net income ie estimated to have declinedby 4-1 per cent hi 1970-7L, but net income per farm to have increasedslightly - less than the increase in real wages, although on the other handindustrial profits fell.    The farmers1 unions claim that spendable income(ie net income less increases In the valuation of stocks) fell from 505 million to  454 million.    Costs in respect of production covered bythe price guarantees increased by a record  140 million0    This figureexcludes  24 million for milk, pigs and eggs produced in excess of thestandard quantities to which the price guarantees apply; but includes 17 million of cost increases on eggs within the standard quantity.    Eggsare being phased out of subsidy, so any increased egg costs included in ouraward would not go to egg producers.ATTITUDE OF THE FARMERS&apos; UNIONS3. The farmers&apos; unions atseea $batcost increases and continuinginflation have adversely affected farmers1 liquidity and restricted their ability to invest: without a marked improvement in the resources availableto the industry, production would not expand.    They argue that we shouldtake account, not only of the  140 million cost increase on guaranteedproduction, but also of the  24 million on excess quantities - especially the  11 million of it which relates to milk.    This extra rnilk production isa side-effect of the expansion of beef: it goes for manufacture and so helpsto keep down our imports of dairy products.THE MAIN considerations , Our Manifesto said we would help agriculture to expand andcontribute to further import savings.    If we enter the e.c., we shall wantour production to be on a rising trend to reduce balance of payments costs,And under our proposed interim levy schemes for beef and cereals we
intend limiting deficiency payments to the gap between our guaranteed prices and target indicator prices if these are higher than our marketpricesi this will be a new discipline on home producers and a means offurther containing the Exchequerss liability0    A manifestly fair award inthe current review should maintain the industry&apos;s goodwill over these new arrangements,,5.        At the same time, we must not treat farmers (who will gain . 30 million per year as a result of increased efficiency this year) undulyfavourably, while other parts of the economy and small businesses inparticular are facing rising costs and falling profits,,    We must also haveregard to the public expenditure implications of our award and its possible effects on the consumer.    The minimum award permissible under the 1957Agriculture Act would be  106 million, entailing an estimated claim on the contingency reserve for 1971V72 of perhaps  22 million; an award of 140 million (which would fully recoup costs on guaranteed production)would entail a possible claim of  33 million.    But the actual public expenditure cost will depend on the course of prices and production duringthe year and the outcome of our interim levy negotiations.    And, whether we made a minimum award or one of  140 million, the retail price of milkwould have to go up from 5p to 5fp a pint on 1 July.VIEWS OF MINISTERIAL COMMITTEE ON AGRICULTURAL POLICY (AG)6. Weighing these conflicting considerations, AG recommend a totalaward of  135 million.    This would recoup the industry for all its cost increases on guaranteed production within the standard quantities otherthan the  17 million for eggs, plus rather over half the  11 million inrespect of milk above the standard quantity, and provide  5.8 million in increased incentives to encourage the eradication of brucellosis.(Further public expenditure of some  2 million outside the award isexpected on related measures for eradicating brucellosis).    &quot;We wouldcontemplate going at most to  138 million to secure an agreed settlement;the Minister of Agriculture will inform us beforehand if it should benecessary to use this latitude.    The Minister of Agriculture should have discretion, in consultation with the other agricultural Ministers and theChief Secretary, Treasury, to settle the detailed distribution of the award.CONCLUSIONS7, I Invite the Cabinet **a. To endorse AG&apos;s conclusions on the determination of theaward and to authorise the agricultural Ministers to proceed accordingly,b. To note the need to increase the retail price of milk from 5pto 5fp a pint from 1 July 1971.W w privy Council Office SW118 February 1971


</content>
</cab>
