<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/3/0 images: 5-7</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Qdhineb.   January 191.7SECRET. ^i 5 27G-101.BRITISH PROPAGANDA IN ALLIED AND NEUTRAL COUNTRIES.Admiralty Notes on the Use of the Press in the United States of America.For the Purpose of putting before the Public of America the Allied, and more especially the British, Attitude with regard to Actions and Policy of the present War.PROPAGANDA is either offensive or defensive in policy, and up to the present time offensive propaganda has been left entirely in our enemies&apos; hands with regard to the United States of America, and the agents of these countries have spent, and are spending, fabulous sums of money in an undertaking that is alluded to on all sides as enemy propaganda. The British methods of dealing with this must therefore be alluded to as defensive propaganda. Full details of the present system and organisation are naturally in the hands of the News Department of the Foreign Office, who are and were responsible for the inauguration of Wellington House. Defensive propaganda and the work necessarily attached to it should not be entirely passive. There are times when the action of His Majesty&apos;s Government, such as, for example, the publication of the black list, has proved that the system requires expansion&apos; and that explanations are necessary early in the movement to avoid the application of German principles to the lever that our action has given them. Points such as these the Germans take full advantage of, and a considerable amount of further explanations and assurances are necessary to alleviate the conditions that have arisen. The interest that the Admiralty have in this defensive propaganda lies in the activity and ability of the Naval Attache in New York. Through active work in New York, the Naval Attache is looked upon by men in the newspaper profession as the individual in authority to whom they should go. for advice and confirmation of reports and rumours. He has among his acquaintances the best men in the journalistic profession in America, and they are willing to do what they can to aid the Allies, provided the matter given out by him is of sufficiently good value to merit space in the columns of the papers. The Naval Attache is in a position to know exactly those papers that deserve attention and those which can give the best results to attain our ends.In America the thing that counts to newspaper editors is the news one gets from a man, be he official or otherwise, and if the individual concerned is given the credit for reliable and interesting news, he is considered a valuable man for the paper to cater to. If, on the other hand, he has nothing but routine articles or news that is stale or that has already received notice in the press, he may be dropped and soon deemed of no value.Under such conditions, editors are apt to be disinterested, and the leverage that is possible in the first instance is useless. On the-other hand, if occasionally the individual concerned is able to give the newspapers good value, the reporters will hover about the office and consider it as one of their important news sources in the city. The instances where the Naval Attache has been in this. position have, unfortunately, been few and far between, and, notwithstanding this fact, he has been able to be of immense value to the Government without in any way prejudicing his position. . In New York it is-looked upon as only natural for the Naval Attache, with an office in the Consulate, to be the dispenser of news, and it follows as a matter of course that the&quot;more valuable news he has the less, ike -Central Powers get into the papers. -
The present position of the Naval Attache entitles him to every consideration as the head of the British defensive propaganda in U.S.A.-with a suitable staff to enable the work to be efficiently carried out.   His requirements in this position will be :  (a.) A thorough knowledge of the policy adopted in Great Britain.(b.) A continual flow of articles dealing with the work of the Allies, especially the part that Great Britain is playing in the present war. Stories dealing with the human side, and detailed reports of actions and incidents.By these means he will always have at his control a sufficient accumulation of news, &amp;c., which would enable him to fill spaces in magazines and periodicals that otherwise might be and would be used by the German propaganda agents. With regard to the daily papers and evening papers, incidents and reports of immediate interest would enable him at any time to check any indiscretions and misunderstandings that might be made the subject of bitter comment by the public of America, or be worked up by our enemies.If the Naval Attache is in a position to hand out news that is of value, he gains more and more in the esteem of the newspaper profession, and carries a great deal of interest and influence with the leading newspaper men, which would enable him, as it has done before, with the small amount at his disposal, to object to articles which harm the cause of Great Britain and the Allies.The personal equation in America is everything.It stands to reason, therefore, that the more valuable news that is available,, the less the Central Powers can use the press to attain their ends. Last August and months prior to that, the Naval Attache had little or no news to give out that was really of value. The &quot;Times &quot; and &quot; Herald &quot; men, who were interested in the cause of the Allies, nevertheless visited his office daily, but there was a sad falling off in other newspaper representatives, such as the &quot;Tribune&quot; and &quot;World,&quot; &amp;c. During this period it was extremely difficult for Captain Gaunt to keep the papers concerned from being filled with German propaganda.In the above few remarks I have dealt purely with press work. Films and photo-graphs, however, are playing a strong part in bringing before the American public our side of this momentous struggle. It has been practically decided by Wellington House that pictures of value shall be forwarded to the Naval Attache as a further lever and hold on the leading papers. Until quite lately, the Germans have been able to place more and better pictures than the Allies, but this &quot;point is receiving the most careful attention of Wellington House, and arrangements are being made that should bear good fruit in the near future. The question of films is under consideration, having been through a phase during which excellent series of moving pictures were sent to the States and arrived there, supervision departed, with the natural consequence, that in some instances, instead of being used to the advantage of our cause, they fell into the hands of German Jews who used them to our disadvantage, or did not use them at all. Moving pictures are of great importance in any propaganda work, and this fact should never be lost sight of, and every care should be taken to see that full value is obtained for films shown in the States.It is strongly recommended that the Naval Attache should be in a position to supervise into whose hands these films are given.With regard to items of naval interest, there is certainly an opportunity to publish considerably more than has been used up to the present time. With the exception of popular articles by Rudyard Kipling and Alfred Noyes dealing with submarine warfare, destroyer work, and certain patrol work, very little has been given on the doings of the Royal Navy, and without in any way suggesting that a policy should be developed with regard to the publication of articles and news that might or might not in any way give information of value to the enemy, it is suggested hereon that a great deal more could be written and used to great advantage on the subject of naval doings.At the present moment this matter is receiving the careful consideration of the Admiralty, and there is reason to suppose that shortly the above implied deficiencies will be to some extent remedied.It is absolutely necessary to ensure an efficient defensive propaganda that press work, pictures, and films are worked together as far as is possible.Admiralty, December 20, 1916.
Admiralty Notes on Propaganda and News for the United States of America.- * -The News Department of the Foreign Office deals with administration of practically-all the defensive propaganda and all detail in connection with this work in the United States of America.Branches of the News Department are located at 82, Victoria Street (Mr. Mair), and Wellington House (pictures and films, Mr. Masterman).Articles, Sec, dealing with the nayal side of the war have been carried out by the News Department in conjunction with the Chief Censor, and special articles have been written by Mr. Rudyard Kipling and Mr. Alfred Noyes on the work of the small craft, whilst from time to time journalists have been given special facilities to visit certain fleets or establishments.During the past two months Mr. Frederick Mordaunt Hall, especially sent over at the instigation of Captain Gaunt, Naval Attache, Washington, has been working under the Foreign Office and assisting the Intelligence Division to deal with certain news of naval interest in an American way ; and during the past week Staff Paymaster Ricci, R.N., has been appointed to the staff of the Chief Censor for special work.Mr. Ricci, who writes naval stories under the title of &quot;Bartimasus,&quot; should be most useful, and it is hoped that this officer, assisted by Mr. Hall, should be able to write articles that will allay the continual demand for naval writings, and should also be -able to deal efficiently with actions and incidents that can be passed for circulation.One of the many difficulties that have been experienced in bringing naval matters before the public of the United States of America is that incidents and actions have only been dealt with either in too phlegmatical and mechanical a manner by merely issuing an official document or report (whereas if permission could be obtained the &quot; human &quot; side could be given with great advantage to the incident concerned), or are dealt with in a broader manner when this special action is of too ancient a character for use in current channels.It is a great asset to be able to keep touch with the American press on current affairs without the trouble vof many denials of enemy reports before our own story and incidents are written, which always gives the enemy an opportunity for damaging the moral of our statements, and this asset is catered for on this side at the Admiralty by the various representatives of the press associations visiting the Director&apos; of the Intelligence Division on Wednesdays at 4&quot;30, during which visit questions of immediate importance are broached and discussed.Admiralty, December 20, 1916.printed at the foreign office BY c. It. harrison.-5/1/1917.

</content>
</cab>
