<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/3/0 images: 309-315</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1917.SECRET. G.-131.ALLIED CONFERENCE AT PETROGRAD, JANUARY-FEBRUARY 1917. -Further Confidential Not,-; by Lord Milner dated March 13, 1917.(Previous Paper No. G.-130.)IT is certain that the official minutes of the Conference at Petrograd can only-give a very misleading impression of what actually happened there. All the real work was done either by committees or in private conversation. The proceedings of the plenary meetings of the Conference were of the most jejune and superficial character. There was, as a matter of fact, a very good reason for keeping them as formal and platitudinous as possible. The whole thing was exceedingly ill-arranged. All suggestions for keeping down the numbers of those present at these meetings proved futile, and it was obviously impossible to discuss anything of a confidential nature before more than forty persons, many of whom we did not know at all, and one or two of whom we had a certain amount of reason to suspect.The so-called political decisions of the Conference, which ooeupy the foremost place in the formal report of its proceedings, are, with one exception, of no importance at all. There was some disposition, especially on the part of the Russians, to extend the scope of the Conference to matters which seemed to me to lie altogether outside its real objects, though in the absence of any clear definition of those objects it was rather difficult to object to anything as positively out of order. Questions like that of Yolo, and other aspects of the Greek situation/for instance, were constantly cropping up, and I had some difficulty in getting them out of the road. The only means of doing so in one or two cases was to agree to some harmless, ,if unmeaning, Resolution. The four first Resolutions are in fact of this character. It would have been more annoying to waste energy in this way if one had not known that, while the civil chiefs of the Conference were engaged in these futilities, important and necessary work was being got through by the generals and other expert members of the Conference in committee, so that no time was actually being lost.The only political Resolution of&quot; the Conference calling for serious attention is the last (No. 5), which advocates the creation of a Central Council of the Allies to ensure the more prompt decision of questions affecting the supreme direction of the war. This is really nothing more than an.extension of the first Resolution of the Home Conference, which declared that &quot;in future more frequent Conferences of the Allies are necessary.&quot; But the Petrograd Resolution; and the conversations which led up to it, take the matter a step further by defining more clearly the kind of Conferences that are required, by giving them, under the name of a Central Council, a regular place in the war machinery of the Allies, and by committing Russia to participation in them. At the same time the Resolution, while indicating clearly enough the nature of the body which it was proposed to create, did not lay down hard-and-fast lines for its constitution, as I was particularly anxious to leave it to the Governments themselves, and especially to my own Government, from which the first suggestion for more frequent Conferences emanated, to determine its final shape.The discussion of this subject resulted in eliciting a real unanimity of opinion among all parties that the present method of deciding important questions connected with the war is hopelessly cumbrous and unsatisfactory, and that, in order to ensure promptitude and harmony of action, closer personal touch between the real directors of policy in the several Allied countries is essential. To this end it was felt that much more frequent Conferences between the several Governments not at fixed times, but whenever the course of the war seemed to call for it should be.arranged, but that these meetings should be as brief and as informal as possible, should preferably be held somewhere else than in a capital city, and should above all be attended by the heads of the several Governments.
When we came to drafting the Resolution, it was found impossible to provide that the Allied countries should always be represented by their Prime Ministers, because, as was pointed out, in one case, that of Italy, the nominal head of the Government was not in fact the real director of its policy ; while in another case, that of Russia, the only really authoritative person-the Czar-obviously could not attend. Moreover, even in the case of France and Great Britain, exceptional circumstances might on some occasion prevent the Prime Minister himself from being present. A certain latitude was therefore left to each country in the choice of its representative, but the Resolution was drafted in such a way as to leave no doubt of the intention that he should be a man capable of coming to a decision of his own authority, and not obliged in every case i to seek instructions from home. It was not, of course, intended to limit the number of persons present to these four principal figures. According to circumstances, military or other advisers, and even other Ministers, might, it was felt, be included. At the same time, it was certainly in our minds that future Conferences ought to be less unwieldly in their numbers than those held at Rome and Petrograd.The Resolution dealing with this subject, like all the important decisions of the Conference, was practically settled in private conversations outside. It was actually drafted at a meeting at M. Pokrovski&apos;s, at which only he, M. Doumergue, M. Scialoja, and I were present. When it came before the full Conference, an awkward incident occurred. M. Sazonow, who apparently had not been informed, as he ought to have been, by Pokrovski, of the contemplated proposal or of the reasons for it, took up a very hostile attitude. The cause of this, as I very soon discovered, was not that he disapproved of the idea itself he admitted to me in private conversation that some-thing of the kind was absolutely necessary, if the Allies were to co-operate more effectively in future-but that he had learned that, if the proposed &quot; Conseil central&quot; came into existence, it was intended to appoint Trepof, whom he detests, as the Russian representative upon it. As a matter of fact, I found out next day that Trepof had already been appointed by the Czar. This extraordinary proceeding is characteristic of the chaotic way in which-public business is at present conducted in Russia-where extreme slowness and infinite delays are diversified by occasional acts of great pre-cipitation. It was impossible to foresee that it would occur to anyone, least of all to people who, as a rule, stand s) much on formalities as the Russians do, to appoint a man of Trepofs standing he had only recently been Prime Minister to a position which as yet had, and might never have, any raison cVeire. So far, the idea of the Central Council of the Allies had got no further than a proposal to be made to the Conference. Even if the Conference accepted it, as subsequently happened, the proposal could still be nothing more than a recommendation to the several Governments, and the Central Council could not come into existence till that proposal had been approved by them all. Trepof was therefore being appointed, with much pomp and circumstance, as a special envoy to Western Europe to represent Russia at the meetings of a body which might never come into existence. Moreover, the appointment was in itself a bad one, doubly bad from my point of view, because it irritated Sazonow, who is the best Russian public man we came across at Petrograd and the most helpful to the cause of the Allies.The hasty appointment of Trepof was no doubt due to some domestic intrigue, which I had no means of fathoming. But, whatever its origin, it put me in a very difficult position. I could not support Sazonow in opposing a proposal which I had myself advocated, and in which I still thoroughly believe. Neither could I object to the appointment of Trepof even if I had had official cognisance of it as it would have been a most unwarrantable interference in a matter which Russia had every right to decide for herself. All I could do was to represent privately to Pokrovski, as I did with some emphasis, that it was going rather far to appoint a representative to the proposed Council before it was known whether the several Governments approved of its creation, and that in any case I hoped that no appointing nt would be announced before their decision was known. Pokrovski, who had evidently grounds of his own for wishing to hurry the matter, did not much like this, but he could not dispute the reasonableness of my contention, and, as a matter of fact, no public announcement of Trepofs nomination was made. So there the matter rests, and I can only hope that the delay may result, as is always possible in Russia, in some reshuffle which will get rid of Trepof, or that, even if this does not happen, it may at least give Sazonow time to get over his irritation, which at one moment threatened to lead to serious consequences.I now turn to the &quot; Decisions as to Military Operations,&quot; which form &quot;the second batch of Resolutions taken by the Conference. These illustrate perfectly the superficial character of the proceedings at the full sessions of that body. For they were based upon
a report of the conclusions reached by the military members of the Conference at their separate sittings, which was deliberately confined to generalities. These Resolutions, therefore, are a mere shell. All that was vital in the discussions of tbe Generals was, I think wisely, withheld from the full body of the Conference, with its crowd of secretaries and hangers-on, by which it could not in any case have been profitably discussed. General Wilson is making a full report on the proceedings of the Generals to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, so I need not dwell further upon the subject here. 1 will only say that on the main point, viz., the co-ordination of military efforts on the Kasteru and Western fronts in the campaign of the&quot;coming spring and summer, it seems to me that as good an understanding w7as arrived at-as could reasonably be expected. There are so many elements of uncertainty in the case (climatic conditions, the course which may be taken by the enemy, &amp;c.) that it was really quite impossible to devise a hard-and-fast plan by which the commanders on the different fronts should be bound. The most that could be obtained was an agreement on certain guiding principles of action. General Wilson is satisfied that such an agree-ment was in fact arrived at between the Generals who met at Petrograd, and that the Russians can be relied upon to do their best to carry it out. In this respect, therefore, I think the work of the Conference may be regarded as satisfactory. We seem to have reached something like unanimity between the military chiefs as to the best method of co-operation between the various Allied forces. The degree of strength which Russia may be able to exercise the probable momentum of her coming offensive on the East.  is another question, to which I shall refer presently. What I regard as certain is that she means to attack with all the strength she possesses.The third set of Resolutions of the Conference deal with the supply to Russia of material of war, and are based on the Report of the Munitions Committee, or &quot;Sub-Commission&quot; as it was generally called. This Committee, of which General Headlam and Mr. Lay ton were the British members, was appointed at the first meeting of the Conference. Its work was arduous and uninterrupted, continuing during the whole of our stay in Russia, so that its report was only brought up to the Conference at the last meeting of that body the day before we left. I attach very much greater importance to this work than to all the other Petrograd proceedings put together. Not only did it lead to definite practical results, but, m the course of the exhaustive examination made by the Committee of the reports and statistics furnished by the various Government Departments, we obtained for the first time tolerably accurate and complete information as to the real state of Russia&apos;s military equipment. We also had the opportunity of realising what Russia expects from her Allies in the way of help to make good the deficiencies in that equipment.I may say at once that the attitude of the Russian authorities on this subject was the biggest difficulty we had to encounter during the course of our negotiations. It was evident from the first.that they had formed very high expectations of what the Western Allies, especially England, might be induced to do for them in the way of supplying guns, aeroplanes, rolling-stock, and a score of other military and semi-military requirements, or money wherewith to procure them. In some cases their expectations were carried to a very unreasonable pitch. General Gourko, who was a very active figure throughout the Conference, and always a thorn in our side, seemed to think that all he had to do was to draw up an exhaustive list of all Puissia&apos;s wants, which could by any means be represented as of military importance, and ask us to foot the bill. But even the most reasonable and moderate of the Russian members of the Conference, like MM. Belayeff and Pokrovski, certainly expected a great deal, which we ourselves always knew that it would be quite impossible for us to give them. A considerable measure of disappointment on their part was therefore inevitable from the first, and it was one of my principal solicitudes throughout to soften this disappointment as much as I possibly could. So I spent a great deal of time, while the Munitions Committee was laboriously working out details, in trying to make them understand the great limita-tions which difficulties of transport alone, to say nothing of difficulties of finance, imposed upon our capacity to help Russia, however great our goodwill. It was hopeless to get Gourko to see reason about this or anything, but with the rest of the leading Russians I think I had a fair measure of success.While combating their illusions, I am bound to say that I felt a considerable degree of sympathy with their point of view. I am not speaking now merely of Ministers or members of the Conference, but of educated and thinking Russians generally, as far as I was able to gauge their opinions. 1 feel it to be necessary that my colleagues should realise as I certainly did not myself realise till I went to Petrograd the Russian attitude of mind with regard to the failures and losses of the war.   There can be no
doubt that there is just now a feeling of considerable discouragement. Reckless as the Russians are of human life, their enormous losses at least 6,000.000 men, up to date, killed, captured, or permanently disabled are beginning to prey upon their minds. More than this, they feel bitterly that these exceptional losses were not inevitable, but that the Russian soldiers, whose gallantry is undoubted, never have had in this war, and still have not, anything like a fair chance, owing to their lamentable deficiency in equipment. It is true that this is not quite a fair estimate of the case, for bad organisation has really had quite as much to do with their misfortunes as lack of guns and ammunition. But at any rate it is, not unnaturally, the Russian estimate. There is undoubtedly in their minds a sense of grievance, of resentment, at the unfair Handicap under which Russia labours. I do not say that they are unreasonable enough to make the Allies responsible for this. But they certainly do feel intensely that the Allies, in view of their much more fortunate position in regard to material of war, are bound to do everything that is humanly possible, and even at some sacrifice to themselves, to redress this great inequality. It is absolutely necessary, in my opinion, that we should take account of the strength of this feeling, and go as far as ever we can to allay it.   Our neglect to do so might have the gravest political consequences.In appealing to the Allies for substantial assistance towards making good then-weakness in respect of armament, the Prussians constantly referred to the second Resolution of the Rome Conference,^ as well as to the strong declarations made in the same sense at Paris by both English and French Ministers. The words &quot; mettre toutes leurs ressources en commun &quot; were never out of Gourko&apos;s mouth. It did not seem to me politic to dispute the principle, nor do I in fact disagree with it. The line which I consistently took throughout, and pressed home in conversation with all the leading-Russians individually was, that we were not only ready but anxious to give them of our best, but that (1) the amount we could give was inexorably limited by physical conditions, and (2) we were not justified in giving anything, unless we could reasonably hope that it would be turned to good account. Finally, weary of iteration and yet not satisfied that, when our backs were turned, these considerations would be sufficiently remembered, I put my views on this subject into the form of a confidential memorandum, which I gave to Pokrovski and subsequently to the Czar. A copy of it is annexed to this paper.The point of greatest practical importance is No. 2. The amount we can get in io Russia is governed mainly by circumstances out of our control. But whether she makes good use of anything she gets, depends to a large extent upon the amount:, of supervision we are able to exercise over the transportation of the various articles after they reach Russia, the assembling of their parts, and, in the case of the most modem and complicated engines of war, the training of the men who are to use them.To these points, therefore, we gave special attention during our stay. We found that, up till now, everything connected with the arrival and distribution of guns, aeroplanes, motors, and war material generally, was in a very chaotic condition. More skilled British supeivision and better organisation were absolutely necessary. General Wilson accordingly worked out, with the help of General Headlam and Mr. Lay ton, a scheme for the creation of a small British department- under General Poole, whom we left behind us in Russia, charged with, the control of all these matters. Upon the successful working ot this body, for the establishment of which the assent of the War Office had been obtained by telegram, the value of our future supply of war material to liussia largely depends. That the officers specially selected will do their work well I have no doubt whatever. Some of them, like Captain Valentine, who is in charge of our Aeroplane Depot at Moscow, have already done much excellent work under great difficulties. The whole question is, whether they will be given a free hand by the Russians, or regarded with jealousy and faced with veiled hostility and obstruc-tion at every turn ?I may say that the high Russian authorities, whom of course we consulted before making our proposals, were quite cordial about them. In addition to the consultations which were constantly taking place between the experts, I personally put the case to the Emperor, to the Grand Duke Serge (who is Inspector-General of Artillery), and to General Belayeff (Minister for War), and got from each of them severally an expression of approval and promise of support. It remains to be seen this is the crux of the whole matter whether this good-will at the top will filter down through the various* &quot; The Conference regard as essential to the successor the Allied cause that the Western Powers should take immediate steps to provide the Russian armies with the necessarv guns and ammunition, to enable them to make full use of their great resources in men, and to break through the German lines on the Eastern front.&quot;
disconnected offices to the numerous minor officials, civil and military, upon whose co-operation or, at least, non-resistance the success of our efforts depends. The course of events will need careful watching. If we find, as a matter of fact, that the promises made to us in high quarters are not being carried out, we shall be in a position to make a strong appeal to the.men who gave the promises. And, in the last resort, we always have the remedy in our own hands, for, unless we are assured that the war material which we are giving to &quot;the Russians is properly handled and made use of, I presume that we shall stop sending it. It will be all the easier to do this as the consignments of the most important of these supplies are echeloned over a considerablespace of time. , . &apos;.      .I think we are all agreed that, for carrying out the Russian side of the bargain with regard to munitions and giving the organisation which we are trying to set up a fair chance of working satisfactorily, we must rely largely on the personality of General Belayeff, the Minister for War. He is our sheet-anchor in the -matter. He is not, unfortunately, a very strong man. But he is intelligent, appreciative, hard-working, and to all appearance completely disinterested. He thoroughly realises the value of our help, not only in material, but in the advice and suggestions about the best use of the material supplied which our experienced officers are .able to give. He cordially welcomed the appointment of General Poole and his assistants, and expressed his complete agreement with the very important recommendations made by the represen-tatives of the Allies on the Munitions Committee in the concluding paragraphs of their report. Owing to technical objections raised by General Gourko, these recommenda-tions were not included in the &quot;Resolutions&quot; of the Conference, though they were recorded as an annexe to the minutes. But General Belayeff assured me personally at our parting interview, in the most emphatic terms, that he thoroughly approved of all these recommendations and that he meant to see them carried out. Moreover, he stated with equal emphasis that he had full authority from the Emperor to do so. I am quite convinced that he meant what he said, and as long as he remains Minister for War I think we are safe in this respect.Unfortunately Ministers in Russia are changed with disconcerting frequency. It would, in ray opinion, be a disaster if we lost General Belayeff at the Ministry of War. It is, of course, out of our power to prevent this, and I have no reason to suppose that a change is contemplated. But at an)&apos; rate I felt it right to do what little I could to strengthen his position. At my last interview with the Emperor I made a point of dwelling upon the great assistance we had received from General Belayeff, and the confidence we felt in him. I also wrote a letter to General Hanbury-Wiliiams, which he could show to the Emperor, if occasion arose, in which I said that, in view of the importance of good personal relations, I earnestly hoped that General Belayeff would remain Minister for War.To sum up this part of the subject, I think we have done two things : 1. We have worked out a practical scheme for the supply of war material, based on the principle of using the available tonnage to give the Russians the largest possible quantities of the types of which they stand most in need.2. We have done what lay in our power to ensure this material being turned to the best account.Of course, when all is said and done, the amount of assistance which&apos;we are offering to give to Russia, even if it all materialises, falls very far short of her undoubted requirements. Moreover, it must not be, forgotten that the French have for a long time past been giving substantial help to her, especially in respect of the output of ammunition, and that the Italians also keep on doing a little. But, in spite of all this, Russia will continue very weak, compared with the other great warring nations, in respect of her armament, though not certainly so weak as she has been. And this fact, of course, materially affects any estimate we may make of the strength of her military effort in the future.That the impact of any offensive she may undertake will be greatly heightened by the additional armament we are now proposing to send her, when it once gets into the held, cannot be doubted. Even in the operations of the coming spring she will be materially strengthened by the guns and aeroplanes already promised and now on their way. But whether, either now or later, tier offensive power can be so much increased as to justify our counting upon her to alter the character of the war oh the Eastern front, is another question. She will continue to contain a large proportion of the enemy&apos;s forces. We may reasonably hope that she will compel him to send further [403] &quot; &quot; C
reinforcements to the East. And it certainly is not impossible that she may break through his line at some point in such a fashion as to compel a general retreat. But, to be quite honest, I hardly hope for as much as this, and I am quite certain that we should be unwise to reckon on it.None the less do 1 feel convinced that it is absolutely necessary, in our own interest, to strain every nerve to clo whatever we can for Russia at the piesent time. And this for political quite as much as for military reasons. The Russians are in an unhappy frame of mind just now thoroughly disgruntled, from domestic causes quite as much as from war-weariness. So far from being the stolid, unmovable, irresistible &quot; steam roller&quot; of popular imagination, they are very sensitive, impressionable, and almost mercurial people. I am speaking, of course, of those with whom I have come in contact not of the bulk of the nation, which it would take years to know but then those whom we met were typical of the class which is politically influential. That class, as I say, is very much perturbed in mind at present, very restless, easily swayed. It is exposed, at every point of the compass, to German and pro-German influences, some open, many clandestine. I do not think it would be true to say that, apart from the Germanopmles, there are many of its members who are consciously losing hea;t about the war. One frequently hears this said of one or other conspicuous person  notably of the Empress, in whose case, I think, it is quite untrue. I am inclined to disbelieve all such stories, which are no doubt deliberately disseminated by the enemy. But what I do feel is, that the general discontent and vague unhappiness might easily turn into disgust with the war. In short, I think the Russians just now need to he very carefully bandied, especially by the English, about whose attitude- to themselves they are very sensitive. Anything we can do to help them, above all to make them feel that we are really eager to help them, that we are understanding, sympathetic, genuine friends,, will have a peculiar value in keeping up their morale.Such an attitude is all the more called for in view of Russia&apos;s internal troubles. These are indeed intimately connected with her ill-success in the war, but I am tint sure that Prussians themselves are always quite conscious of this. When we reached Petrograd we found people generally to all appearance much more interested in domes; ic affairs than they were in the fortunes of the campaign. When one comes to analyse these matters, it is soon apparent that the root cause, even of the domestic discontent, is dissatisfaction with the course of the war, and bitter resentment of the mismanage-ment -for which the Government is held responsible that has been the cause of so many failures.As far as the purely political aspect of the matter is concerned, I have formed the opinion that there is a great deal of exaggeration in the talk about revolution, and especially about the alleged disloyalty of the army. That the army should be very dissatisfied with the way in which the war has been conducted is only natural. But there is a long distance separating dissatisfaction in the army and the nation, and even the loud public expression of it (for astonishing freedom of speech is allowed in Russia), from a genuine revolutionary movement. And, assuming for a moment that a revolution were successful, I should regard with great apprehension its effect on the conduct of the war. For the autocracy alone holds Russia together, and though autocracy is a bad form of government, it will take something like a generation to organise anything in its place.But, short of anything that could be described as revolution, there may be very grave internal troubles aud much sporadic disorder. If this happens, it will be due to economic rather than political causes. Broadly speaking, the danger which threatens Russia is not so much deliberate revolution as chaos, resulting from the confusion into which a badly organised administrative system has been thrown by the strain of the war. It is, I am afraid, true that in many parts of Russia, especially some of the towns, there is to-day great shortage of food, although, taking the country as a whole, the food supplies are very far from exhausted. It is equally true that factories are shutting down every week for want of coal and labour, although the coal exists in the country if it could only be got to tbem, and there is any amount of labour if it was not so lamentably wasted.Ultimately two-thirds of the economic trouble resolves itself into a question of transportation. Russia is terribly short of means of communication, especially railways, and the climatic difficulties standing in the way of regular traffic, are, ot course, exceptionally great. Still it is certain that the existing railways could do a great deal more work with proper management. As my colleagues are aware, we have smt a very experienced railway manager, Mr. Bury, of the C.P.R., to examine into this question on the spot, and to help the Russian authorities to improve
their system of railway management, if they will let him. It is too early yet to say what amount of success he may be able to achieve, but I regard it as a hopeful symptom that General Sakharoff, commanding the Russian armies in Roumania, has hist asked for the assistance of an expert railway man from England. There is no doubt a general recognition in Russia that the railway system is very much at fault, and amoiiff the more progressive men a willingness to appeal for our assistance with a view to putting it right. But British railway managers, or even advisers, would cartainly meet with considerable obstruction on the part of the main body of the bureaucracy, and the question is this, as in other cases, is whether the prejudices or the dishonesty of a number of subordinate officials will be sufficient to defeat in practice the policy favoured by their chiefs.It is very interesting to speculate on the future political, economic and social of Russia, for she has the greatest undeveloped resources of any part of the globe. But it would require as many years as I have spent days in the country to form an estimate of the probable rate of her development, or of the lines which it is likely to follow. Confining myself to the immediate problem what is the degree of help we may exoect from Bussia in the war, and what we can ourselves do to help her I must repeat that I have no hope that she is likely to derive any additional strength for the purpose of this war from a great political upheaval. If such an upheaval were to take place I am afraid its effect on the course of the war might be disastrous. On the other hand, Russia would undoubtedly gain appreciably, even in military strength, if the Czar could only form a more or less homogeneous Ministry of decent people. At present the Ministry is composed of some good and some very bad men, of the most diverse tendencies. Each Minister is responsible only to the Czar. There is no cohesion, and nothing to prevent one departmant from pursuing a line directly in conflict with the line pursued by another department. A very strong Emperor might make such a system work, but the present Emperor is not such a man. It follows that the best we can hope for, at the moment, is some mitigation of the present situation. Any great improvement is unlikely. We have to reckon with Russia as she is, and must do what we can to strengthen her in her present condition. As far as our mission is concerned it was to this end that all our efforts were directed. The scheme we have worked out is based on taking account of what Russia actually is. If that scheme can he completely, or even to a large extent, executed, I am satisfied that the Russian military effort will be materially strengthened. But everything depends npon close attention to details, both over here? and in Russia. As far as the Russian end is concerned all we can do is to send out a few more competent experts (if the Prussian authorities are favourable, the number of these may be gradually increased), and to use whatever political influence we possess, through the Embassy, to see that these experts get a fair chance, and to try and save such Russian Ministers and other high officials as are capable and desirous of working heartily with us, from being hampered in their efforts to do so, or lightheartedly dismissed. What is required at this end is, firstly, the approval by the Cabinet of the scheme we have worked out; and, secondly, the appointmeut of a small Committee, representing the several departments War Office, Munitions, Navy, &amp;c. whose co-operation is necessary to watch over its execution.MILNER.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,March 13, 1917.FKISTKD AT THE FOREIGN OFlflCE j31&apos; C. k. HARRISON. 24/3/1917.

</content>
</cab>
