<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/3/0 images: 518-521</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.MACHINERY FOR COMPULSORY RATIONING.I STATED in the House of Lords on the 25th ultimo, with the concurrence of the Prime Minister, that it had been decided to set up forthwith the necessary machinery for a system of compulsory rations. During the past four months the whole subject has been fully considered by a Committee which I appointed for the purpose. They have collected and fully examined all the available information, including reports from Germany and all other countries which have attempted to limit food consumption by compulsory measures. The whole question has been exhaustively explored, and the general lines of the proposed scheme of administration have been carefully laid down.I propose that the municipal authorities and district councils in England and Wales, and the County Councils and municipal authorities in Scotland, should be charged with the duty of carrying out the scheme under the general coutrol and supervision of the Ministry of Food. I have conferred with the President of the Local Government Board and the Secretary for Scotland, and we have agreed, subject to the consent of the War Cabinet, to the letters and statement appended to this note, which explains the steps at present proposed. The application of the scheme to Ireland has not yet been decided, but I am conferring with the Chief Secretary and hope to arrange with him in the course of a few days for the necessary adaptation of the arrangements to meet Irish conditions.  This at his personal request.A provisional estimate of the cost involved has been made, and it is calculated that the expenditure will amount to about 760,000/. for the first year.If and when it is decided by the War Cabinet that compulsory rationing is necessary, I propose to make an order prohibiting the sale or distribution of bread, flour, or any other foodstuffs which it is decided to ration, except under such regulations as to presentation of tickets. &amp;c-as may be prescribed by the order, and to impose upon the specified local authorities the duty of carrying out the scheme.It is calculated that the necessary organisation can be completed, and forms, tickets, &amp;c, printed and distributed, within two and a half months after the date of the issue of the letter to local authorities.DEV02sPORT.Ministry of Food, May 2, 1917.1. Letter from the President of the Local Government Board to Lord Mayors, Mayors,and Chairmen of District Councils.Sir,AS Avill be seen from the accompanying letter which I have received from the Food Controller, the time has now come when a system for the rationing of food must be initiated in this countrv. In the view of the Government the local authorities who undertook the work of the Kationai Register and the constitution of the keal Tribunals should set up in their areas suitable organisations for the purpose. The nature of the organisations will be apparent from Lord Devonporfs letter and from the papers which accompany it. &apos;The initial step is to appoint suitable Food Commissioners, having an intimate knowledge of conditions locally prevailing, and possessing the confidence of the public within their districts, who will make themselves fully acquainted with the proposed scheme and arrange for its application to their areas.Any system of rationing must involve a great deal of administrative work, and I hope that the leading officials of local authorities, notwithstanding the many other [570]Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1917.
calls upon their time, will, be able to give to the Local Food Commissioners the benefit of their wide experience to ensure the success and smooth working of the arrangements.In view of the paramount importance of the work to be done, I have no hesitation in asking them to render all assistance in their power, even if this involves delegation of other duties which in normal circumstances are rightly regarded as of primary importance.Any acknowledgment of this letter and subsequent correspondence on the subject should be sent to the Ministry of Eood, Central Rationing Department, Grosvenor House, London, W..1.I am, &amp;c.RHONDDA.[A similar letter to be written by the Secretary for Scotland].2. Letter from the Food Controller to the President of the Local Government Board,Dear Lord Rhondda,The Government have, as you know, decided that it is necessary to take immediate steps to establish throughout the country a complete organisation which will bo available for carrying out when necessary a scheme of compulsory rationing&quot;, by tickets, of bread and flour. The organisation will be framed on lines which will enable it to be readily adapted for the rationing of other essential articles of food, and it must of necessity be local in character. The Government propose that the immediate responsibility for carrying out such a system should devolve in the first instance upon local authorities acting in co-operation with, and under the direction of, this Ministry, and I shall be obliged if you will communicate at once with the appro-priate local bodies in England and Wales, and secure their assistance for this purpose.I enclose herewith an outline of the scheme which has been adopted in so far as immediate action is required. You will see that under it the local authorities are required to appoint local Eood Commissioners, and to establish local Eood Offices. The Ministry of Eood should be notified on the enclosed form at the earliest possible date, and in any case not later than the 15th&apos; May, of the names, addresses, descriptions, and qualifications of the Eood Commissioners whom each Local Council proposes to appoint. The appointment of these Commissioners will be subject to appi oval by this Ministry, and will be for the period during which it may be found necessary to keep in force a system oC compulsory rationing.An examination of the outline of the scheme enclosed will indicate to the local authorities the importance and responsibility of the work to be entrusted to the Eood Commissioners, and will afford a guide in the selection of qualified persons. It will be remembered that the responsibilities of the Commissioners may be further increased by the extension of compulsory rationing to other foodstuffs. The Eood Commissioners need not necessarily be members of the Council, and local authorities should not hesitate to go outside their own body to secure the most suitable persons to act as Commissioners. They will, 1 am sure, realise the desirability of including among their number at least one woman.The Government confidently rely upon the co-operation of the local authorities throughout the country in setting up with the least possible delay the necessary machinery, so as to be fuily prepared to put it into force if and when it becomes imperative to do so.Yours verv trulv,DEVONPORT.[A similar letter to be addressed to the Secretary for Scotland.]
3. Preliminary Note for the Guidance of Local Food Commissioners.1. Full preparations will be made to bring into force, as from a date to be hereafter communicated, a scheme of compulsory flour and bread rationing. This scheme provides for the issue of bread and flour cards to the civil population and for the regulation of the amounts of flour and bread to be supplied to all catering establishments. Provision will also be made for the control of the supplies, of-flour issued to bakers and other flour distributors. The scheme is set out in the following paragraphs.2. The scheme will he administered in accordance with the instructions of the Ministry of Pood by Local Pood Commissioners (unpaid)., who, in Great Britain, will be appointed by the following Local Authorities : England and Wales. In London the City Corporation and Metropolitan Borough Councils; elsewhere the Municipal Borough Councils and Urban and Rural District Councils.Scotland. In counties (excluding Royal, Parliamentary, and police boroughs), the County Council, witli power to divide the county into such districts as they may determine. In Royal, Parliamentary, and police boroughs, the Town Council; provided that if the County Council and the Town Council of any borough so agree, the borough may be administered as part of the county.There will be at least three Local Pood Commissioners in each district, and the desirability of including a woman among their number should be borne in mind.If at any time the Pood Controller finds it necessary to ration other foodstuffs, the responsibilities of the Local Pood Commissioners will b3 correspondingly increased.3. The main duties of the Local Food Commissioners in each district will be (a.) To organise the work in their area, to obtain premises for the necessary staff,including an executive officer. (6.) To make the provisions of the scheme widely known in their area, to receiveapplications for bread cards, to form a register cf these, to classifyindividual applications, and to issue bread cards through the post to thepublic. . -(c.) To make registers of the retailers, caterers, and institutions in their districtand to receive returns from them. (d.) To fix the supplies of flour and bread allowed to caterers of all classes and byinstitutions, and to issue vouchers which will authorise them to buv theirnecessary supplies.(e.) To deal with complaints, enquiries, and local difficulties arising in connection with the scheme.4. The fh&apos;st duty of the Food Commissioners will he to secure suitable offices and a responsible executive officer. It is hoped that suitable offices may, as a rule, be placed at the disposal of the Commissioners, by the Local Authority, or otherwise obtained without payment. If this is impossible, offices may be rented. In some of the larger districts sub-offices will prove necessary. But it should be borne in mind that most of the work of the Pood Office will be carried out by correspondence, and it wall not be essential for members of the public to call at the offices except in cases of difficultv.VThe executive officer will, except in the smaller districts, need to give substantially the whole of his time to the work, and may be remunerated if necessary. It may, however, be found possible in some cases to obtain a volunteer for the post, or to take advantage of tbe services of an existing officer of the Local Authority. For much of the work of the Food Office, particularly the temporary work involved in the issue of bread cards, it should be possible to rely on voluntary assistance. It is important, however, that the clerical work should be efficiently performed, and paid assistance may be obtained if necessary. The size of the staff will, of course, vary with the population of the district to be served. It is impossible to make any exact estimate of the numbers that will be required, but for the guidance of the Food Commissioners it may be stated that the staff for a town of 100,000 is expected to be from ten to fifteen, employed regularly, with a large additional staff employed for about three weeks during the actual issue of bread cards.  Printed forms, posters, &amp;c.3
will be supplied by the Ministry, but the Food Commissioners will obtain their own stationery. The Commissioners are authorised to incur expenditure on premises, staff, and other necessary purposes up to a total, amount not exceeding in the six months from the 1st May to the 1st November 6Z per 1,000 bread cards issued. Any expenditure in excess of this can only be incurred with the sanction of the Ministry. It is believed that in practice most Commissioners will find it possible to effect considerable economies in the scale laid down. In particular, it is hoped that-voluntary help will be obtained to carry out a large part of the work involved in the scheme.Engagements of the staff should be subject to one month&apos;s notice at most, and the lease of any premises taken should also be terminable at not more than six months&apos;notice.5. On and after the date arranged, it will be an offence for any person to supply flour or bread retail unless he has in the meantime been registered bv the Local Food Commissioners for the district in which his business is situated. On and after the same date no member of the public will be able to obtain flour or bread for domestic consumption except on presentation of a bread card to a retaiJer, In order to obtain such cards the head of every household must secure a form of application through a post office. He will fill up particulars in regard to himself and his household on the form and then post it in the nearest letter-box for transmission to the Local Food Office. Institutions and caterers&apos; establishments will similarly be debarred from obtaining flour or bread in excess of amounts allowed them by the Local Food Commissioners.6. Assistance will be given to the Local Food Commissioners bv Divisional Food Officei-s. These will be responsible officials of high standard appointed by the Ministry of Food in twelve centres in England and Wales and in three centres in Scotland. These officers will be responsible generally for supervising and assisting in the administration of the scheme in their divisions.7. Detailed instructions for their guidance will be forwarded to Local Food Commissioners at an early date, together with copies of all necessary forms, leaflets, &amp;c. It is important that Local Food Commissioners should at once make preliminary arrangements for distributing forms and leaflets for the guidance of the public as soon as received and for giving, all necessary publicity to the scheme in their district. No doubt it will be possible to enlist the help of teachers, social workers, and others for this&apos; purpose.R. HENRY REW, Secretary.Ministry of Food, May 1, 1917.o

</content>
</cab>
