<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/209/0 images: 310-351</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)SJS^C RET. CP o 31  (30).COPY KG.CABINET.UNEMPLOYMENT POLICY.Copy of a letter from Sir Oswald Mosley to the &quot;Pr ime Minisi er aCHANCELLOR OF THE DUCHY OF LANCASTERTreasury Chambers,Whitehall, S.Yj.1.23rd January,  1930.My dear Prime Minister,I venture to forward to you my paper on the unemployment and general economic problem, and the organisation nacessary to meet it which I told you in a previous letter was in course of preparation.I have already sent a copy to Thomas, whom I have assured that the criticism of the present situation is in no way intended as a reflection upon him and that,  indeed,  the present limitations of policy and machinery in my view make his task impossible. I have also shown the document to Lahsbury and Johnston who,  I . understand,  are writing you to say that they agree with the substance of it,I hope very much that you will be able to  consider it before any announcement is made or white paper is issued relative to theproposed economic staff,  as the argument on Organisation materiallyaffects that body.      The policy suggested in the paper is notadvanced in any dogmatic spirit and certainly not as any cast ironformula.      I am more than open to any alternative suggestion whichcan be shown to be superior.      I have reached, however,  the very definite conclusion after mature consideration that it isimpossible   to continue as at present.Yours verv sincerely,(Signed) O.E. MOSLEY
The object of this paper Is to suggest:    (1) That for the purpose both of immediate unemployment plans and of long term economic reconstruction a far larger and more comprehensive organ-isation is required than has yet been employed,  or is even now contemplated.      (2) That measures can be taken within the existing resources of Government by which the unemployment problem can be materially reduced within a relatively short period of time. (3) That the real problem of permanent economic reconstruction requires not only a greater co-ordination of the Government   . activities, but a mobilisation of national resources on a larger scale than has yet been contemplated by measures I will attempt later to suggest.In the latter aspects these proposals will be largely a summary of suggestions which Mr. Lansbury,  Mr. Johnston,  and I have advanced at various times during the last six months, and which have largely been rejected or suspended,     On the subject of organisation I have already made representations, but now venture to advance a detailed structure which is set out in graph form In Appendix 1.      I am aware of the existing proposals to provide the Government with a small Research Staff,  and my argument on Organisation strives to suggest that these proposals are altogether inadequate to our purpose.     However, before approaching this question it will be appropriate first to deal with the difficulties of the existing organisation and the reasons which lead me to the conclusion that nothing short of the compre-hensive form of central organisation suggested In Appendix 1. can meet the problems with which v,.!e are confronted. Existing Organisation for Dealing with Unemployment.Under the late Government the whole problem of unemployment both in relation to the provision of work and the administration of Unemployment Insurance was   concentrated In the Ministry of Labour, with the exception of the Unemployment Grants Committee which has since been brought under the Ministry of Labour by the present
m    222Government.      Plans for the provision of vork were  surveyed from time to time by Cabinet Committees, but the staff work of such plans was carried out by the Ministry of Labour and the responsibility resided, in the Minister of that Department.      The only difference in organisation under the present Government is that another Minister,   the Lord Privy Seal&apos;, has been put in charge of work plans.      The machine by which he i-?. served remains in essence the same,      The only difference in form of organisation is that the principal officials who previously handled work plan3 have been divided formallv from the staff dealing with Unemploy-ment Ins\france-, have been reinforced, by two officials from the Inland Revenue,  plus an official from, the Board of Trade and one from the War Office,  and. have been moved to the Treasury at the disposal of the Lord Privy Seal.      It is quite clear that these very able and devoted Civil Servants with their intimate experience of the Unemployment problem should be absorbed in any economic organisation which is established by the present Government for meeting the Unemployment problem and the general task of economic reconstruction.      It is.not so clear that the matter should be left almost entirely in the hands of officials who have been exclusive!^ responsible for its conduct during the last five years.The present Government takes a very different vie1&quot; of the magnitude and urgency of this problem to the last Government. Above all it regards it as fundamental with widely diffused causes of origin requiring for its subjugation the participation of nearly all the major Departments of State.      If this view has any validity the Treasury,   the Overseas Trade Department, the Ministry of Health,  the I Ministry of Agriculture, and certainly the Ministry of Transport, are quite as much concerned with this problem as the Ministry of Labour.      But no officials from these Departments have any place on the present staff serving the Lord Privy Seal.      An attempt to meet this point and to co-ordinate the work of the relative Departments was made by the present Government in tho constitution of the Inter-Departmental Committee on Unemployment,
which consists of tho permanent heads of the various Departments mooting periodically under the Chairmanship cf the Lord Privy Seal. It would appear from tho fact alone that this Committee has only met twice in the last six months that it is scarcelv effective to achieve such purposes.      It is,  in fact, clear that sporadic meetings of permanent heads of Departments much immersed in their own work cannot provide the stead&quot;?- and co-ordinated drive which is essential to a successful issue.The absence of the political chiefs from regular meetings of the Inter-Departmental Committee on Unemployment constituted another difficulty.      If any decision be taken In that Committee it is a decision taken over their heads v^hich they are required to implement on the subsequent explanation of their Civil Servants; while all initiative from the Departments to that Committee in the absence of the political heads Is likely to come frcm the Civil Servants rather than from the responsible Ministers of a Government returned on an executive programme -      Such an organisation naturally tends to produce the maximum friction for the minimum results. The fact that no grave friction has arisen from Its activities is merely a comment upon the small degree of those activities.      In such circumstances the sole initiative in the advancement of unemployment pla.ns rests with the Lord Privy Seal, who alone possesses any executive capacity,,      He is assisted by a small staff drawn from the &quot;&quot;inistry of Labour and by three Ministers appointed in a purely advisory capacity,  without executive power of any kind, whose views have vemr often differed from those cf the Lord Privy Seal and r.ave been overruled by that Minister.      He certainlv can have no complaint against hi-&quot;&apos; on that score as the sole power to take decisions on policy was vested In him by the Cabinet.      The fact of disagreement upon police among Minis teis is, however, irrelevant to this section of this memorandum.
The point here advanced is  that neither the Lord Privy Seal,nor any other riinister,   can handle effectively a problem of this magnitude within the means at his disposal,  and in the conditionswithin which he is required to operate.      At present it is thebusiness of the Lord Privy Seal to produce Unemployment plans withthe assistance of a small staff which was responsible for theconduct of policy under the late Government.      It is the businessof the other Departmental heads to get on with the normal work oftheir Departments.      They are in no sense mobilised for an attack upon Unemployment as the primary obligation upon them.      The whole problem is to secure that mobilisation of the Government wachine,and ultimately of the resources of the Pation,  in a co-ordinatedand consistent effort of economic reconstruction.Suggested Organisation for dealing^with the Economic Problem.(See graph form Appendix 1).It is submitted that a mobilisation of the whole resources economic problem car. only be effective under the auspices of the of Government for an attack on tho/Prime Pinis ter himself, who should, bo armed with an adequate staff for such purposes..      Healone possesses  the power to secure co-ordination and. theauthority to enforce action when decisions are tfken.      Of course,much of the detail work can,  and. should be,  delegated to other ministers.      The wore precisely defined their allocated functionsare the better.        An organisation of any kind is only effectivewhen every man knows his duty,   is allotted certain functions,  andis then held responsible for their discharge.      Confusion and difficulty alwpvs arise --hen spheres of action are not preciselydefined    and responsibility cannot be charged upon any particularMinister.      The essence of efficient organisation is the preciseallocation of function.
It is only possible to reconcile this essential basis of organisation with the necessary amount of co-ordination between Departments and Ministers if the effective head of the Government is the controlling authority *      Any other Minis tor at. the head of such an organisation has no means of enforcing the execution of decisions except by the cumbersome method of appeal on every small point to the decision of the Cabinet.      If re accept the fact that unemployment must be the primary concern of several major Departments of State r:e are led inevitable to the conclusion that the Prime Minister alone can co-ordinate and direct their activities.      In the absence of such authority any organisation constituted to deal with Unemployment muat fall into one of two errors.      It becomes  (l) A stud.-&quot;- circle revolving ideas in the void,  or  (2) a &quot;Ministry of National Reconstruction&quot; with all the defects of the last attempt of that kind:    overlapping and interfering at every turn with the work of other Departments, who are inspired by ever- sort of friction to resist rather than to assist the economic push.The problem is in the first place to produce ideas from a central economic staff,  and in the second, place to secure their execution through the existing Departments &apos;:    otherwise we will either duplicate the existing mechineof Government,  or will fail tc secure the execution of Government policy.      It must be clear that mo can only avoid these dilemmas If the personal authority and supervision of the Prime minister bo at the head, of the machine.      It is further submitted that the head of the Civil Service must be actively associated with such an organisation. Just as all    inistors look to the  Pri^o Minister for author-itv and direction,  so the whole Civil Service looks to the permanent head, of that Service.      If the authority cf the Prime Minister and the head of the Civil Sorvice wer combined in such an organisation ve
I    226   IIcculd rel&quot; upon tho mobilisation of all the Departments to five effect to these decisions.iResearch and Action.Once that authority is secured we come to the problem of devising machinery whereby the process of thought and research can be related to and translated into action.      It is essential that seme body of experts employed on a full-time basis by the State should, be free from all dist met ion for the pure work of research.      The Prime iv-irister&apos;s statement when the Government first took office that the Government was going to &quot;think&quot; was received with the derision peculiar to Oppositions &quot;-hen any particularly s  pient observation is made from the  Treasury Bench. The proposal that the Government.should think was certainly novel, for officially no Government has ever done any thinking. Political parties have done some thinkin;  and have produced programmes-within the resources at their disposal, but without the advantage of official information and statistics.      Subsequently when parties reach power officials have to assist them to translate into practice programmes produced without any regard to facts which Government. Departments alone  possess.      Few things in our short experience have been more striking than the disparity between Party estimates of costs and effects,   and official estimates. Sometimes this process has weakened party proposals and made them more difficult of execution.,      Sometimes it has strengthened them and made them easier of execution and  1&quot;.:s  costlv than -as su;posed.      The point is  that the complicated machinery of modern Government appears  to have reached: a sta,e of development when estimates and. programme-m-.es  can only be framed, with any accuracy
and certainty if assisted by trie wealth of fact and. statistics which Departments alone possess.      That is why it has become so essential for Governments,  as well as Political parties, to &quot;think&quot;.      Thinking can no longer be left with anv confidence to the amateur,  as expert examination is liable ludicrously to falsify his conclusions.      In the complexity cf modern organisation the divorce between the informed and the uninformed mind, is becoming ever wider,   and indeed, more dangerous to the &quot;whole structu.ro cf the State.      For these reasons, apart from the necessity for more solid thinking: on the immediate economic problem than has yet been done,  it is essential that Governments should, be armed with a thinking staff entirely free from the distraction of detailed administration,  but with full access to the information which other Departments  possess.It is idle, ho?ever,  to employ for this purpose one or two economists thinking in vacuo without relation to executive Departments,  snd regarded by them with tolerant amusement.      A thinking staff must be large aud. representative enough to survey the whole economic problem, and above all, ^ist  have definite machinery whereby its ideas can be translated into action by executive  -ministers and Departments.      On the research side such a staff could be assisted, by Advisory Committees drawn from Finance. Commerce and. Industry.      It could, even be assisted,  if desired,  bv Political Committees on which all parties are represented.      The dangers to executive action of such participation are larcelv mitigated, if the advisory functions are completely divorced from the executive,  as a.&apos;.;own in Appendix I.      The essential liaison between advisory and executive functions is &apos; there provided by the
&quot;thinking&quot; or research staff, which at the same tine is afforded means to secure the flow of its  considered productions Into executive channels. The Executive Organisation.The Executive Or organisation would function under the direction of the Prime Minister himself, with the assistance of a rain Committee meeting weekly, which would be composed of the heads of the various Departments concerned with Unemployment problems, as shown in Appendix 1, plus the Unemployment Ministers. The latter Ministers would be concerned with the detailed work of the executive secretariat of the  Prime Minister&apos;s Department, which would consist of at least twelve permanent higher officials drawn from all Departments concerned with Unemployment and. assisted by appropriate subordinate staff.      The routine work of this Department should be apportioned, among the Unemployment Ministers as the Prime Minister th.ou.ht fit, so that each Minister should have execuGive authority over his own task and be held responsible for it.      The main economic problem, should then be divided into sections appropriate for the concentration of a Civil Service Committee having, at its head a minister drawn from, the main Executive Committee.      The list of problems thus handled can,  of course, be extended indefinitely,  and the subjects detailed, in Appendix 1 are by no means  suggested as final.      Each Committee would be provided, with a Secretary from the Executive Secretariat and an Adviser&quot;   from the Research Secretariat.      Thus liaison and contract between the Research and Executive Secretariats would not only be maintained by consultation between these two bodies, but the research side &quot;&apos;ould also be dovetailed Into the execution of the detailed work of Executive Committees. It would,  of course, be the duty of the Unemployment Ministers
attached to the  ?ri-&apos;e        ister&apos; s Department to ensure detailed liaison between the Imecirtive and Kosenrch Secretariats,   and to keep him informed of the whole great process of translating the &quot;thinking&quot;  of the Government.into executive action,Unemployment and.the-Gengrainsconomie Problem.Such an organisation would undoubtedly produce a more scientific approach to a solution of the Unemployment problem than can be expected from tho improvised organisation which has so far dealt with it,      Nevertheless,  after six months of this work I venture to suggest some of  the alternatives of Government polic^ which such a bodm would have to consider,  together with suggestions which I have from ti^c to time advanced, and along which lines I still have every  confidence the problem can be overcome.      The first essential is to divide the problem into its  two rrain features(1) Long term planning: of permanent economic recon s truc t i on.(2) Short term schemes for the immediate relief of unemployment.Con      ion between, these two really distinct problems is responsible for much .of , our present difficult-&apos;-.      Admittedly the problems frequently overlap and executive action to deal with them must also overlap.      Nevertheless,  in broad outline the- can be regarded separately,  and it is essential so to regard them if we arc  to arrive at any clear conclusion of G o v e rn mon t policy.The first problem of long term planning is,  of course, fundamentally of far greater importance,  and no Government can shirk it.   -   It is well, however,  to be clear that anything&apos; -9-
approaching permanent economic reconstruction involves at least a three year programme,  and that no results in terms of a reduction of the unemplo7/ment figures could be expected under such a period.      In fact,  the first effect of such an effort mast almost inevitable increase unemployment. National reconstruction involving tho modernisation of British industrial methods through such measures as Rationalisation in the first instance will generally mean an actual discharge of labour.      That condition of weakness must be expected before the benefits of the surgery end be realised.      It is        ,. idle,  therefore,  to believe that we can dispense with short term schemes for the immediate relief of unemployment unless we also believe that any Government can face steadily increasing unemployment figures for at least three years,  or would be normally or economically justified in facing with equanimity a prospect which involves such grave psychological and economic reactions.At present we appear to be tinkering with long period reconstruction in terms of short period schemes for the immediate relief of unemployment.      This is a confusion of terms from which we must free our minds before the problem can be faced scientif icall?/.      To do this it is necessary to divide in our minds and. organisation the long term, from the short term.      It is true that short term schemes for the immediate relief of unemployment-nrent can be made to contribute materially to the economic equipment of the country, but. they must differ in  their character from such long term schemes as the promotion of Rationalisation,  the only immediate effect of which is likely to be an increase In unomp1oyment.
At present wo are concentrating on  such Rationalisation schemes and holding out hope to the country that we are thereby reducing immediate unemployment.      We are,  in fact, doing immediately exactly the reverse and if our pledges to deal with present unemployment are to be implemented we must also devise a far larger immediate policy.      As that immediate programme presents the most difference of opinion it may be left to a later section of this document.      Long term reconstruction has hitherto not occasioned the same differences,  possibly because we have not yet in very many cases approached the precise and the concrete.Long Term ?Iannirug for Economic Reconstruction.The main principles of long term planning for the economic reconstruction of Britain are almost universally agreed.      The process is summarised in the word &quot;rationalisation-tion&quot; .      Differences of opinion as we approach individual problems may well arise regarding the degree of public con-trol to be secured in return for public assistance, and other questions of a similar character.      But the necessity for industrial reorganisation in the form of the big merger involving standardisation and the pooling of resources with a view to lowering the costs of production is agreed from the City of London to the advanced section of the Socialist Movement.      The question is, by what means the State can best assist this agreed necessity.      At present the tendenc;/-appears to be virtually to hand, over the whole process to the Banks,  and in particular to the Governor of the Bank of England, with the blessing of a Labour Government. Admittedly the co-operation of the Banks is essential to any: -11- .1
such programme, and any measure to secure that co-operation may justly be agreed as a considerable achievement.      But a big difference exists between co-operation between Government and Banks, and the abdication of the Government to the Banks. However,  apart from any question of principle a very practical point arises on the question whether the British Banks by tradition and present practice are competent to play am&apos; such part without at least the aid and general direction of a big State organisation.      The British banking tradition is,  for instance very dissimilar to that of the German banking institution.      In that countrv the Banks have been interwoven for a generation with industry.      They have played a big and consciously formative part in the industrial development of the country.      They have for years filled the big gap never filled by the  finance of this country between the short term credit on collateral security and the long term loan market.. TheY have been speculative partners.In Industry, appointing their own skilled industrial directors to the Boards of concerns they were assisting,  and in whose success they hoped to participate.      Such a tradition of industrial-political banking is very different- to the  tradition and. practice of British Banks, which in principle have rigidly rejected any such conception.      The British banks,  in fact,  approach the enterprise adumbrated in the ? anchester speech of the Lord Privy Seal without are of tho long tried, equipment which the German banks would, bring to such an organisation.More than that,  they approach tho situation with heavy existing commitments.      They have for long past supported certain British industries in methods of organisation which were scarcely worthy of their generosity, and. as a result have commitments to these Industries which there is little present prospect of recovering.      As Professor Henry Clay puts it  :-
&quot;The situation eight years after the depression began is much more serious  than it should have been, because the banks, with an ill-timed generosity, have kept in existence large numbers of Firms that were already insolvent .in the   changed commercial conditions.&quot;    (p. 146.   &quot;The Post Yiar Unemployment Problem.&apos;)The same point was referred to by tho Balfour Committee in their final report   :-&quot;It has been suggested, that In many cases their support  (the Joint Stock Banks) has been not too niggardly but too lavish,  and that injury has been done to the permanent interests of British Industry and trade by the nursing of weak undertakings by the banks in the vain hope of an early recovery.&quot; (Balfour Committee Final Report p.51).Is there not at least a danger that any effort of the Banks uncontrolled, and directed by the State will tend, to make its first objective the salvaging of existing commitments rather than the development of ne&quot;;,  more economic, but possibly competitive industries.At present we are hypnotised by the position of what arc known as our basic industries,  and tho ineffectual object of successive Government has been their restoration.      Is there really any hope of success in this direction,  at least to the point of absorbing our present unemployed?     Are we not faced,  apart from economic dislocation, with fundamental changes in world demand, which postulate new Industries and new production to satisfy new demands.      Various Committees, Commissions and Departments have studied this question,  but no co-ordinated, thought by Government surveying the vtiole economic position  and arriving at considered conclusions as to the industrial future of this country has yet been under-taken..     Are the Banks, within, the limits of their existing practices,  competent or likely to undertake such a survey before they give the promised, assistance to industry.      If no such survey is made before their resources are allocated are . we not liable to be faced with more bolstering of Inefficiency,
or at least with the support of industries catering for an ever diminishing and elusive demand.     If these considerations have any validity, and much detailed evidence exists to support them, we are driven back again to the prime necessity for an extensive economic organisation of Government co-ordinating and directing the whole national effort of reconstructions.     Under suoh auspices and direction the co-operation of the Banks would indeed be welcome for this great task, but without such direc-tion we run all the dangers cf improvised and unscientific organisation for which the State assumes responsibility, but over whioh it has no effective control.     No Government, and certainly not a Labour Government, has any right to leave these grave matters involving the whole future of industry to the sole activity of our present banking system, assisted by sporadic consultation with one Minister and a small staff from the Ministry of Labour.     As a Government we should arm ourselves with the strongest possible oconomlc staff, should systematically con-suit with every branoh of finance, Industry and Commerce, and 3hould then make up our minds upon the futuro industrial develop-ment of the country.     Then with close, detailed and systematic liaison between the Government and the financial authorities dispensing the necessary assistance we should proceed to the task of reconstruction.     Here is whole time employment for what may appear the rather hjoo olaborate organisation whioh I have attempted to describe, and certainly half a dozen rather than one Minister would be required for the task if it be thoroughly done.It is difficult to see, how short of such an organisa-tion the work can possibly bo accomplished.     la are embarking upon a long term programme for a great transition of our indus-trial life from a pre-War to a post-War basis.     It really verges on the frivolous to confront such a task with our present machinery, or indeed, without tne most powerful machine that we
can devise.      It can only be solved by scientific thought and the scientific method.     The improvised and the haphazard can-cmly land us in yet greater difficulties by the mis-direction of effort and tho dissipation of exiguous resources . Connectod with the problem of what industries should be assisted are fundamental questions suoh as tho relationship of the Home and the Export trade In our future economic equill-opprobrium.     We have novor yet scientifically examined the very doubtful question whether we can materially reduce unemployment by an Increase in our Export trade.     Ministerial spoeohes poin in this direction as a solution of our unemployment problem, but on what evidence are they based?     If wo achieve 30 large an increase in our Export trade as 50 million pounds worth of goods per annum we are only thereby employing^aan extra 225,000 per annum according to tho estimates of Professor Henry Clay-. Further, to have any hope of securing such an increase we shall have to rationaliso by the introduction of now mechanical processes to achieve oheaper costs of production to an extent which may well lead to an economy of labour nearly equivalent to the additional demand.     Have wo, In any case, such hope of securing such an increase as that just suggested through the medium of our basic industries, upon whioh we formerly relied for our command of foreign markets?     Can we rostoro at all our economic position by an increasing struggle for competitive ftorld markets, In which the developmen of other oountries has naturally robbed us of our initial advantage?     Is not the wholo fetish of Export trade the product of minds who have just sucoeedod in grasping the elementary eoonomio fact that to import our roquisite food-stuffs and raw material we must export sufficient to pay for them, and who build upon that 3imple and obvious premise the fantastic conclusion that tho sole criterion of British prosperity is the amount of goods we can send abroad for the consumption of foreigners?     Do these economics of the last
contury, whioh still find oxprossion in spoeohes omanating from all political parties in fact ooinoide with the economic facts and possibilities of the past war situation? Is the policy of all Governments still to be dominated by the belief that employment in our stoal trade to build a Bailway in Iraq or tho Argentine is of nooessity better for the people of this country than ompioymont for&apos; the building! of a road in Britain?     Those may seem just genoral questions, but an understanding and determination of such general principles in relation to the new situation is essential to a coherent national policy.     At present little or no thought beyond the work of Isolated politicians and economists has been davoted to them, and in all parties half a dozen inchoate opinions can be found upon suoh subjects.Surely we have roaohed the point in long term planning where a Government must indeed settle down to think upon such subjects, and they can arrive at no considered oonolusion with-out an adequate machine for the collection &quot;and oollaticn of facts.     I have myself advanced at various times in speeches prior to taking offloe oertain arguments, statistics, and oonolusiona on those subjects whioh differ materially from the policy of the Government as far as that policy can bo asoer-tainod.     It would, however, be effrontery on my part, or for that matter on tho part of any individual, to present such conclusions as being in any way tenable until all evidence on the subject had been thoroughly oxamined.     My argumont is that no suoh examination has ever taken placo,  and that before wp prooeed to long term reconstruction it should take place.       We have not, in a more immediate sphere,  even yet reached any considered conclusion upon suoh a pressing subject as the relation of the various forms of transport within the Stats of tho future.     Here is a subject which in nearly every branch involves the direct activity of the Government.     Vre have so far oonoerned ourselves with assistance for Bailway development as a short&quot; term scheme to give immediate
employment in certain trades,  but we have not yet even con-sidorod the balance between railways, roads,  and canals in cur economic equilibrium.      It has been argued that railway develop-men t in this country is almost anachronistic.     live have made no real inquiry into this subject,  but everything is subordinated to our promotion of railway development.     My constant demands for a big road programme involving employment on a large scale are countered by the objection that suoh a programme might damage thG railways.     The canal system of the country has already been largely suppressed by railway interests.     Yet it can be strongly argued that for short transit of light and perishable goods tho roads are more effective in this co cmtry than railways,  and that for long transit of heavy imperishable goods an adequate canal system is often preferable.      These are questions on which the amateur is clearly not qualified to form an opinion.      The Government may noxt summer be assisted to some extent by the findings of the Boyal Commission now sitting, but some real eoonomic thought covering a long period ahead is required before thG Government can arrive at any considered con-elusion upon the future transport system of the country and the forms of transport which it should immediately assist.Here arises again,  and acutely, tho danger of con-fusing short term unemployment -schemes with long term planning, which we arc undoubtedly doing at preeeu&quot;&apos;-:.      In all those spheres we should be assisted materially by an inteiisivo study of the methods of other countries.     Much material for this purpose exists in Government Departments,  but it is not collected *r collated.     More can bo gathered by tours and examinations of exports on the spot.      Just as other countries benefited by our oxporiences and mistakes because our industrial development came tho first, so now we can benefit by their experience and
mistakes because our industrial and national Rationalisation comes tho last.      It would bo possible to extend almost indef-initely the list of subjects incidental to national recon-struction on whioh no considered conclusion of Government exists.     Tho whole great question of Agriculture and the possibility of linking up Agricultural stabilisation with the Party policy of bulk purchase of Wheat,  etc. is a case in point.     We came near to drifting into this policy as a short term unemployment scheme arising from tho lord Privy Seal&apos;s visit to Canada;    yet it is a policy which if undertaken at all should bo attempted wholeheartedly and on a large soale, as a result of a considered decision based, -upon the best det -iled thought and planning.     In this sphere of long term recon-struction a great case exists for caution and for careful and considered action,    in this sphere it is essential to have a coherent and comprehensive policy.     Yet it is precisely in this sphere th it we have    improvisation verging on tho rockless as part of a short term unemployment policy, while in the real sphere of short torm unomoloyment schemes, where rapid improvised action is essential and desirable, we are confronted with the whole weight of the Government machine in favour of caution and delay.The confusion between long term planning and short term unemployment schemes arising from our failure to divide two quite distinct objectives in our minds is responsible for a policy whioh in one sphere is ill-considered and dangerous, and in the other sphere is hesitant and ineffective.      It will be my purpose in the next section on short term plans for the immediate relief of unemployment to suggest that in this sphere bold and executive action is above all required,  in tho reverse method to my suggestion of this section,  that in the region of long term planning a far more carefully considered policy is required than is being pursued at present.
Short Term Schemes for the gelief of Immediate Unemployment, whioh jai^ the&quot; Same Time can&apos; Make&quot;Effeetiye Contribution to the EcTonomic &quot;&quot;Equipment&apos; of the Country.If there bo any justification for the view advanced inthe preceding section, that few, if any, results in terms of areduotion of the unemployment figures can be expected under aperiod of at least three years as a result of long term recon-struction, and that indeed, the first effect of such measures will probably be to increase unemployment, the need for a shortterm programme to provide useful work in the immediate futurebecomes a yet more par-amount necessity.    In this region I havetaken the view throughout that far more can be done than atpresent is being done;    and that indeed, certain decisions of theGovernment are actively impeding tho execution of this work.     Onthis subject it is possible for me to be more precise than onthe preceding subject of long term planning for two reasons.(1)    Tho &quot;Advisory Unemployment Ministers&quot; have been almostentirely excluded from long term planning measures and discussion,and the information there available to mo is very little morethan that open to the ordinary private member.      (2) If my wholeview of the subject of long term planning has any validity it isan egregious error to bo dogmatic on that subject In the absenceof the collection and collation of far more evidence and statis-tics than are yet available,  and in default of far more thoughtby a Governmental mac nine than has yet been devoted to the subject,or is possible within the limits of present machinery.      However,on the subject of short term schemes for the relief of unemploy-ment I have long advanced very definite views,  and believe that by the measures shortly to be defined a material reduction in thefigures could be effected in a surprisingly short space of time.
To arrive at a proper understanding of this question it is necessary to be clear as to the working of the present machinery.      The Department of the Lord Privy Seal has no power by executive action to set a single man to work.      It can devise plane, but their execution depends on other Departments and Authorities.     For immediate work-giving plans we are broadly dependent on four Departments:-    (1) The Ministry of Health for Housing and Slum Clearance;    (2) The Ministry of Agriculture for Land Drainage;    (S) The Ministry of Labour under whose control the Unemployment Grants Committee operates since the Home Development Act of the present Government removed that body from tho control of the Ministry of Health, and (4) Tho Ministry of Transport for Road Construction and Reconstruction, Railway and Canal Development,  and speed-up of Electrification.      There are other bodies concerned suoh as the Forestry Commissioners and Development Commissioners, but for all major purposes it will bo found that every suggestion for - immediate provision of work coming from any quarter, Political or Economio,  falls within the administrative ambit of those Dcoartments, who are in their turn subject to Treasury control.le may set aside for the moment the first two Departments, together with the questions of Land Drainago and Slum Clearance   is falling; solely within the province of these Departments,  and so far outside tho Lord Privy Seal&apos;s activities except for occasional reqaents for a speed-up, which we have cert --inly no reason to suppose will not be implemented.      It is difficult for outsiders to comment with any authority upon such purely Departmental work:.     If I was permitted any comment it would find expression in tho hope that both  in Slum Clear, nee  jind Land Drainage,;, a more definitively St tte intervention will be considered
than at present appears to be contemplated, with a view-to short circuiting the local, machinery and delays which are at present incidental to thoso subjects.     It is rather in the interacting spheres of tho Ministry of Transport and the Unemployment Grants Committee that the major conflict between my views and those of some other Ministers have arisen, and it is in this region that I submit tho biggest results can be achieved by a change of method.Tho first important faot which fortunately has not yet been understood by the House of Commons is that the road programme of tho present Government shows little if any increase on the road programme of tho late Government.     We have contented ourselves with continuing the programme of tho Tory Government on a five year basis in place of a one year basis, subject to the proviso that if the work be accelerated and the revenue of tho Road j?und be therefore exceeded in any ono year, the Treasury will make arrangements (so. far undefined) to meet the situation.     This matter has been tho subject of protracted controversy between the Minister of Transport ;and mysqlf, but it now appears that wo have at least nearly reached agreement as to the facts.     Appendix 2 shows, a note to me by the Minister of Transport giving comparative figures between tho present and late Government1s road programmes, and the note in reply from my Department analysing these figures and asking for any correction of our analysis if it was challenged before tho Debate of December 20th, 1929.     While I understand tho Minister does not entirely accept the analysis   no correction has yet been received, and I believe it can bo shown that my estimate of their road building activities orred if anything on the side of the generous.     In any case,  it is perfectly dear from the Minister&apos;s own note that no increase over the late
Government &apos;s programme sufficient to afford, any material employment has yet been approved..Since tho inception of this Government I have pressed, for a large road programme and as a result chiefly of differences on this subjoct a Gonferenco to consider National Schemes was set up which hold its first meeting on November 8th 1929, and has since met once.     Tho only practical effect of this Gonferenco in the provision of work schemes was to produce the suggestion from the Minister of Transport to add fifteen million pounds worth of work to his programme spread over five yoars, and as a result only affording employment for another twelve thousand men per annum.     Even thi3 modest advance has not yet received Treasury sanction, and it appears at least doubtful that it will receive this authority.      If tho matter rests here it means that one of the main avenues to the immediate provision of work is definitely blocked.     But the whole gravity of the situation does not rest here because tho quostion of road schemes reacts vitally on other work plans of the Government through tho medium of the Unemployment Grants Committee.     Vve are confronted with the Cabinet decision to continue the trans fee policy of the lato Government.     There are two ways of transferring men from tho distressed areas to Stato assisted schemes cf employment in other areas:     (1) Through the medium of National schemes such as roads, etc., in which the Govornmont bears a portion of tho cost at least sufficiently substantial to enable it to enforce the employment of a high proportion of transferred labour.    (2)    Through the medium of local authorities under schemes approved by the Unemployment Grants Committee, and assisted by the Exchequer.with the difficulties and delays resulting from
attempts to maintain transfer conditions over a wide area of tho work of the Unemployment Grants Committee I will deal shortly.      It will anyhow be agreed that the work of that machinery in the provision and execution of work plans      - ; would be greatly facilitated if the transfer conditions were abrogated, but tho only way to free looal authorities from this obligation thoy strenuously resist and at the same time to maintain tho transfer policy is by carrying the necessary transferred labour on National road plans and in other National schemes that could be devised.     The State can possibly stand the racket and unpopularity of transfer in schemes under its own auspices.     Local authori-ties in areas with a substantial unemployment of their own simply cannot defend a large import of outside labour to their constituents, and often when they are induoed to accept it the inevitable bargaining and manoeuvring on each side leads to interminable delays.     So we ara faoed with the complex that in the absence of National road soheme s we have no means of continuing the transfer policy unless we throw loads of sand into our Unemployment Grants Committee procedure.     V*o thus lose employment, not only by our failure to increase our road programme, but also by the reaction of that failure on other works schemes.     The insistence upon that maintenance of transfer conditions under the Unemployment Grants Committee has had mors adverse reactions than are contained in tho unwillingness of local authorities subject to those conditions (i.e. with less than 10 per cont. local unemployment) to acoept transfer.     It has also created the extraordinary and indefensible anomalies in the financial treatment of the &quot;distressed areas&quot; and &quot;areas suffering from severe and prolonged unemployment&quot;.     Such areas with more than 10 per cent, of their male population
unemployed receive les3 favourable financial terms on all non-rovenue producing schemes than the more prosperous areas subject to transfer. :   If Brighton accepts transfer conditions it receives more favourable financial assistance than the most distressed mining village in b-uth Wales, which by the nature of its case and by official ruling is debarred from transfer conditions.     Tho official defence of this policy is that transfer conditions make necessary a premium to authorities liable to them, and if authorities not liable to those conditions are given tho same financial terms the premium disappears.     It is argued that transfer would then appaar as an obligation imposed, rather than as an obligation accepted, in return for the reward of moro favourable finanoial terms.It must be admitted that as long as we seek to carry the transfer policy through Local Authorities some forco rosts in these arguments, but how long can wo defend more favourable finanoial terms for prosperous seaside resorts than for tho distressed areas which returned our members in such large numbers pledged,, among other things, to&apos;give local employment to local men on.long overdue schemes of local reconstruction and economic improvement.     These conditions are only just beginning to be understood,  and whon they are fully grasped a sense of anomaly and grievance will undoubtedly arise whioh will make the work of tho Government very difficult.      In the distressed are-j.s with crushing local Bates work on the present financial basis oannot procood at all .     To this fact it is often replied that these areas are virtually dead and that it is in any case uneconomic to spend money on thorn.     This, view is surely a fallacy of overstatement.      It is probably true that tho economic life of these areas can never bo fully restored and that they will employ loss people than before, but that is a very different condition to economic death. Because fewer workers than before will bo employed in distressed areas is no reason to let these areas fall to pieoe
or to deny thorn assistance for sanitary conveniences or economic amenity on at least the same terms- afforded to tho large prosperous Boroughs.     Beoauso South Wales is suffering from an economic depression is no reason to maintain dangerous ccrnors in that area, or unclassified roads which are not repaired.     No modification in transfer conditions such as the Government has introduoed with very beneficial effects can effect the disparity in financial terms between the prosperous and the distressed areas whioh arises indirectly from tho maintenance of transfer conditions in any form.     The modifications that wo have introduoed after very con-siderable internal debts have greatly extended the operation of . the Unemployment   Grants Committee from some  6-4- millions in the last two years of the late Government to  14.832 millions approved in seven months by the present Government, and  18.776 millions under consideration, which represents a notable achievement. Nevertheless it is my confident bolief that we cran at least treble the amount of useful and economic work provided by looal authorities by the procedure I will suggest in the next section.     So long as we insist on transfer through local authorities instead of through National schemes, so long shall we have reluctance to embark on these schemes and delay in their exooution.     Innumerable troubles of detail arise oven after the schemes have been submitted and approved.     i&quot;or instance, it is the practice of the Ministry of Labour to roplaco transferred men on Unemployment Grants Committee schemes who obtain private employment in the neighbourhood not by local men, but by other transferees, e.g. an unemployment scheme gives four thousand men employment for a yoar and the agreed quota of transferred labour wo will say is 25 per cent.     This should mean that one thousand men   employed on the job are transferred from other areas.     But if tho local Ministry of Labour official chooses to push these transferred men for whatever local jobs are available they might all find looal omployment    onoe every three months, with the result that in the course of the year four-    * \ ----- -............................^    .............._________.......&quot;25-........................................^...................
thouoand transferred men, instead of the agreed one thousand, are absorbed into a locality.      This of course is a very exaggerated instance, as these powers are not exercised in fact to anything like that extent, but it serves to illustrate a principle and practice to which strong objection from local authorities has been brought to my notice.      As long as we maintain this system local authorities will not know where they are, and the maximum of friction will be created at every turn.      Tne present situation entails a long manoeuvre between local authority and Government,  each striving to beat tho other.    As the local authority staff is less skilful it usually is worsted and a reluctance follows to participate in all such efforts.This is really not the way to get business done quickly or on a large scale.     The same mentality dictates resistance to all more generous financial treatment of local authorities.    From the principles upon which we are now acting it would be deduced that we are really saving the Nation&apos;s money if we can save the taxpayer at the expense of the rate-payer.    Successive authoritative-tive inquiries culminating in the Golwyn Committee have informed us that we are doing nothing of the kind.    In this region we do not lack the fruits of inquiry, and it is now an accepted principle of the fiscal theory of all parties that rates are a more vicious burden on industry than taxation.,    why then this insensate struggle to push the burden of unemployment off the shoulders of the tax-payer and. on to those of the rate-payer which is holding up our unemployment policy at every turn, and is a flagrant violation of the declared principles on the subject for which our Party has always stood?      In economics it is fallacious and in politics it verges perilously on the actually dishonest.    To achieve quick results in this sphere of short term unemployment schemes we must give generous assistance and act decisively on clear and well understood, principles. In this sphere we can afford to take some small risks
in contra-distinction to the sphere in which we are at present taking: the risks of improvised policy, namely that of long term planning,  in which considerable forethought and caution is required Actual Measures Suggested for Short Term Schemes for Relief of Immediate Unemployment.It is submitted.--  (l)    That we should frame the maximum possible programme of road construction and reconstruction over a period of three or five years, without regard, to the present limiting factors of:-(a) Expense,  (b) Reaction on the Railways.This programme should, be carried out on the existing basis of operations through the local authorities,  or on well established precedent by the State doing the work itself and handing over the roads subsequently for the maintenance of the local authority.    Specially generous assistance to be given to all authorities co-operating with the Government in this short term programme, on the clear understanding that such assistance related only to the emergency programme and would form no part of the &quot; permanent relation between State and local authority.    The whole emergency short period scheme to be financed by a loan based on the revenue of the Road Fund.    This procedure would set aside fc the time being the whole great question of Nationalised road which I have advocated in regard at least to Trunk\Roads for considered deliberation and conclusion of the Government in relation to the general question of the long term planning r future transport system.    In the same way we should set as-5&apos; the purpose of this programme, the danger ox&quot; road develop damaging the railway.    A short term period, of intensive construction of this kind could scarcely within the narrow limits of time suggested derange our transport equilibrium.    The whole question has formed, the subject of discussion between the Minister of Transport and myself in papers which are available, and on which I am prepared to argue my view at any time or place.(2)    The Financial terms granted to local authorities under
Unemployment Grants Committee to &quot;be uniform throughout on the most favourable basis,  subject again to the clear understanding:(a) that the grant of these financial terms is to be limited to a definite period as part of an emergency scheme.    (b)    That all schemes requiring that assistance must be submitted within a short space of time (say six months) and that no schemes advanced after that period would be considered.    (c) that work must be begun immediately   after the schemes weK* approved and compressed within the shortest possible period.(S) That no transfer conditions would be required if the local unemployment of insured males is above 6 per cent., which is the Government Actuary&apos;s estimate of the normal.    Below that local percentage of unemployment authorities might reasonably be expected to accept a full quota of transferred labour in return for abnormal State assistance.(4)    The transferred labour lost to local authority schemes to be carried on the emergency road schemes, either under the direct auspices of the State or so generously assisted by the State that it could dictate terms.&apos;(5)   The State to make 100 per cent, grants for approved works in distressed areas carried out either by:  (a) The State,(b) The Local Authority acting as contractor for the State, (c)Actual Contractors; and to be financed by a loan raised by theState over the same period as Unemployment Grants Committee loans, otherUnder no/conditions can work be carried out in the heavily rated areas as the local authorities are not in the position to carry any portion of the cost.    The special treatment could be justified if again it was made clear that it wa3 part of an emergency unemployment scheme which would form no part of a permanent relation between State and local authority.(6)   When these clear principles for the assistance of work schemes were laid down an organisation comparable to that which explained the National Health Insurance Act to the country before the War should be organised to push these schemes in the localities. Nothing is more surprising than the ignorance of many Deputations and officials from local authorities, not only as toihe terms
afforded lay the Government, hut as to the possibilities of useful economic development in their own localities.By these measures alone it is my confident belief that work would be forthcoming which involved calls on the money market for very substantial loans, with which I will deal in a subsequent section,.      The essence of the plan is that such assistance should be emergency in character and limited in term.      Ve should present authorities with a &apos; now or never&apos; position.    It is probably true that many are now hanging back in the confident expectation that the Government will yield later, as all Governments have yielded,  to the demand for better terms. Let us grasp the nettle by declaring at once the best possible terms and making it clear that at tho end of a definite period all such emergency unemployment assistance will come finally to an end when we anticipate the fruition of our measures of long term planning.      By this means we could usefully bridge the gulf between the present situation and the first results of our long term planning.    It must, however, never be forgotten that from every aspect it is necessary to divide in our minds and in our policy the short term schemes from the long term reconstruction;    other-wise in muddle and confusion between two concepts we fail to achieve either purpose.(There are, of course, other possibilities of the large scale provision of work in the early future with which I am not so qualified to deal, but which are worthy of the attention of the Government and the economic organisation which is suggested.      Can we not carry out both slum clearance and land drainage to a larger extent by the direct action of the State?      Cannot
we even approximate to the idea of the mobile labour corps drawn largely from the distressed areas for the rough work?    These arc admittedly matters for the Department concerned, of which I am of necessity ignorant, but it is difficult to resist the feeling that big results night be secured if a new approach was adopted and these matters were linked to an emergency push against immediate unemployment by the direct intervention of&quot; the State.Expenditure.It cannot be denied that short term schemes for the immediate relief of unemployment/will involve some charges upon the Exchequer.    Our Party has never denied this, and at the Election we roundly denounced the Liberals for their pretence that no expense was involved in their unemployment proposals.      The question is, whether such an immediate programme involves expenditure beyond the capacity of the Nation to support.    If so it appears that the only course open to the Government is to inform the country that it cannot carry its Election programme, and in accordance with honourable precedent, to adopt the same course as Sir Robert Peel in an analogous situation.    But would the expenditure involved in the foregoing suggestions to implement our programme in fact exceed our capacity?Let us assume that we are sufficiently successful in these measures to secure  200 million pounds worth of work spread over the next three years and financed by loan, which is a programme in my view by no means impossible of achievement as it involves only the trebling of our present volume of Unemployment Grants Committee schemes, and a road expenditure
spread over three years at roughly half the rate ofMr. Lloyd G-eorge&apos;s proposals in the first two years. The Exchequer proportion of the interests on these loans, even on the most generous basis, could scarcely exceed the charges -e have recently incurred in respect of the Widows and Orphans Pension Bill, while the economic return to the country could scarcely be less. The effect of a  200 million programme averaged over three years would be the employment on current computation of nearly three hundred thousand men per annum.      If to this programme was added the Emergency Retirement Pensions plan and the raising of the school age, on the most conservative estimates we should reduce unemployment in the relatively near future to considerably below the Government Actuary&apos;s estimate of the normal.With the finance of the Retirement Pension plan and the great offsetting economies which can thereby be secured,  not only to the Nation, but to direct Exchequer expenditure, I have dealt elsewhere and will not here repeat.      However,  I believe it can be shown that the whole programme of constructive works, pensions, and raising the school age, can be carried out for a nett cost of little more than the usual estimate of the yield of even a sixpenny tax on unearned income, and I am pre-pared to argue this view in detail if required.    Do we believe that such expenditure, or anything approximating to such moderate figures, would involve a &quot;flight from the pound&quot;, especially if it be counteracted loy tho enormous psychological effect of such great reductions in the unemployment figures,  and be accompanied by a scientific and explicable long term programme for economic reconstruction?    If this indeed be our view we have travelled so far in these short months from our Election
programme- that normal political conduct appears to indicate that we should take the public into our confidence. If it is to be replied that such a programme has its merits, but that we have already mortgaged all resources available for such purposes, an argument of exceptional force supports the suggestion for more forethought and co-ordination in the planning  of the Government&apos;s programme which appears earlier in this paper.    For instance, if the question of expenditure dictated a deliberate choice between the Widows Pension Bill and constructive measures which would materially reduce unemployment who would choose the former?In another instance the increased Exchequer con-tribution under the U.I.Bill would be rendered unnecessary by savings arising from the Retirement Pensions scheme, but the Ministers charged with the preparation of the latter proposals knew nothing of the former measure until they read its terms in the newspapers. Any proper Government machine co-ordinating our activities would have   .obviated such a situation, and would at least have made possible considered and deliberate decisions between clear/but  alternatives.    In the absence of such machinery the first scheme that comes along is liable to be accepted,  irrespective of the rival merits of other schemes which by the very fact that they take longer to mature may possess more profundity.     Under the present system, not only of the present Government, but of all Governments, Departments are like a crowd of bookmakers jostling through a turnstile on the race-course.    The man who can push hardest and make the most nois gets through first and takes the money.    Unemployment -Ministers, without any Department, can never by
the nature of their case at present he in the fortunate position of getting through first.    For instance,  the Stafx which was engaged on our Retirement Pensions scheme belonged largely to Departments concerned with the Widows and Orphans pensions Bill, and. were taken off our work to push ahead the work in which their Departments were concerned.    So their schemes were ready first and later schemes, which at least on grounds of National economy had more justification, are now told that the cupboard is bare.    But it is useless to bemoan the past;    it is only fruitful to learn its lessons and the out-standing lesson of the last six months is the paramount necessity of a central economic organisation surveying the whole position and systematically planning ahead.In regard to the question &quot;of expenditure, I venture to repeat the suggestion I made in September last in a report to the Cabinet on the Iraq Raj.lv/ay project -that we should make up our minds what we can afford to spend on eunemployment policy, and should then allocate our resources deliberately to the most desirable objectives,    If little or no money is now available for unemployment policy let us frankly recognise that no immediate programme for the reduction of unemployment is possible,  that -we must rely entirely on a long term programme of economic reconstruction, and must be ready to face the possibility of steadily increasing unemployment figures for some years ahead, as the first effects of that large scale Rationalisation programme are tolerably certain to be adverse.    In that event the Government might have to review its relation to
its Election programme and the electors who voted for that programme.lionetary; Policy and the Home Market0Only one known factor may offset the tendencies of leng term reconstruction with the Rationalisation process which it involves, temporarily at least, to increase the unemployment iigures.    That factor resides in the sphere of monetary policy.    My views in favour of a more elastic monetary policy are well known, to the point of being regarded as an obsession, and have therefore not been included in this paper. However, I should, of course, be the first to recognise that cheaper money accompanied as required by an enlargement of the basis of credit would have an early and beneficial effect on the unemployment figures, although it is doubtful whether it -would do very much more than counteract the displacement of labour caused by any wide measures of Rationalisation. Suojh a monetary policy, however, would be incomplete unless accompanied by a large Home Development Policy. The raising of substantial loans for such a purpose has been made much easier by the recent American collapse, and the Government had good reason for delaying suoh a policy until the Exchange   position prior to that crash was relieved.    At the presont time the raising of such loans by the Government should even have a good effect in rallying the present financial situation.    But it is in the effect on labour conditions of such an employment giving policy in combination with an easier credit policy that the real hope of the future appears to me.It is quite possible that such immediate
unemployment measures on so large a scale might create conditions approximating to a shortage of labour in at   Xeaat some Trades.      This is the situation moat feared in some quarters because it leads inevitably to successful demands for higher wages.      It is precisely for this reason that those should earnestly desire this situation who believe that the real solution of unemployment rests in an expansion of our Home Market, and that a search for larger Export outlets will become increasingly difficult owing t** the intensification of world competition.     A certain shortage of labour giving the workers a sound bargaining position on a buoyant market situation occasioned by monetary measures is a situation most favourable to the development of the Home market through the increasing purchasing power of the people.    It is-precisely this situation whioh has created tho American boom of the last eight years.      The Immigration Laws cause artifically the shortage cf labour in relation to the demand. The measures of the federal Reserve Board maintained a continually buoyant market.    The result was a position in which the wages of the workers, and con-sequently tho Home Market, were almost constantly increased.      Every ernplcyer in America who counts is in agreement that the basis of American prosperity is the Home market, which is caused by high wages and high purchasing power.    It is not in the successful countries that suggestions for wage increase and high purchasing power are regarded as immoral.
In America, it is true, a temporary setback hasoccurred through the failure of the federal ReserveBoard of control ..&apos;all Street, but here again thecountry whose Rationalisation comes the last maybenefit from the mistakes of others and may avoid theerrors while imitating the suceesseo.      An easyin this countrv,  combined with a development policv Credit policy/vhich gave employment on a large scalemight well reproduce here conditions on which prolonged American prosperity has rested.    By natural and gradual preasure we might pass from a low wage oasis of production to a higher wage basis of production, the greater rate of which in response to a larger demand more than offset the increaso in labour costs.    Once that awkward transition is achieved our futuro employment can rest increasingly on the growing&apos; Rome Ilarket.These may seem to many the ideas of phantasy, but they are in fact based upon the experience of other-countries which have largely avoided our recent failures, and where they are regarded as coramonplace.    In any case, it is submitted that the ideas of this paper taken as a whole at least represent a coherent and comprehensive conception of national policy, both for tho purpose of economic reconstruction and for the purpose of the State organisation necessary for that great task.    It is for those who object to  show either that present policy is effective for this purpose, or to present a reasoned alternative which offers a greater prospect of success.January 16th 1930.
APPMDIX I. PPvTMJg MINISTER 1 s departPrime Minister Head, of Civil Service;Secretariat of IS Permanent Higher Officials. Secretariat draws from and centralises body of economic information at present dispersed in departments P and provides Secretaryfor each Standing Committee; Ministers without portfolio would be attached to this body.VEXECUTIVE COMMITTEES-Eairi Committee to consist of following members meeting weekly from whom will be drawn Chairman ,&apos;for Standing Committees.    Chairman P.11.Vice; Privy Seal, Ministers of Labour, Health, Agriculture, Chan, of Exchequer, President of Bd. of Trade. &quot;Unemployment Ministers&quot; (Minister of Transport and Parl.Secreta.ry of Dept. of Overseas Trade.)\rLong Term PlanningI-Indus. Prod. Doing work of present Cotton and Steel In-quiries Indus-try by Indus-try thus putting steady pressure on whole of Industry to Rationalise.Credit Policy. Keeping touch with present Finance In-quiry and con-tinuous watch to prevent finance and Industry get-fin g out of step.Agric Policy Considera-tion of Bulk Import Boards.0&apos; seas Ifktg. Correlate &amp; extend work of Commercial Attaches,etc. Dept.of Over-seas Trade &amp; Empire Mktg. Board become two main sections.Civil Reseaj Scientific Committee t( focus on theii more rapid application 1 of invention ani-d technical de-velopmsnt to Industry.Ministry of Labour. Factory Insp.De-Board of Trade.    Empire Marketing Bo(To this structure is attached a Finance House or Industrial Bank which Rationalisation and Reorganisation.      (b) Financing of Export Trade td
meht.Research Committee of Economists employed on a full time basis and producing considered views on:the economic development of the county.      Acts as liaison between Advisory and Executive Committees and provides at least one adviser for each of Executive Committees.JTADVISORY COMMITTEESAdvisory Economic Council of Economists, Business Men, Financiers,  etc. in which the participation of Members nominated by the other Political Parties might be sought. Meetings occasional jj only , say monthly.f ICOMMITTEES (Meeting say weekly)terra SchemesMisc.  RoadsIndus Prod..Overseas    CivilCredit    AgricI     ___ _____Policy. Policy. Marketing. Research.it. of Home Office. Department of Overseas Trade ird.Ill provide credit for (a) Large scale scheme of Countries which need extended credit.)
APPENDIX    llv In July last, the present Government authorised the Trunk Road programme up to a total of ....  9,500,000 (4-5 years)This is entirely new, and represents additional expenditure of approximately.................  E, 000,000per annumThe present Government has also stimulated specialexpenditure on Unclassified Roads,assisted bytho unemployment Grants Committee, which maybe estimated at approximately ................ 2,000,000per annumThe present Government has taken the further important step of enabling Local authorities to plan their expenditure for a period of 5 years ahead up to. a. stated amount, with the assurance of assistance from the Road Fund throughout the period.    This ,5 years1 pro-gramme, amounting to  27,500,000 is expected to have the effect of assuring the accelerated oxecution of work on a substantial scale. - There is no certainty that provisions at the same level would have been repeated in subsequent years in the annual Road Fund Budgets.The average annual expenditure under the 5 yearsprogramme amounts to...................5,500,000A provision of  1,500,000 has been retained in the Road Fund Budget for this year for improvements on classified roads, not included in the 5 year programme.    This would permit of saxictions to works costing in total about another  2-^ millions, but it is doubtful how far the commitments in the current year will absorb the whole of this provision and how far similar provision will be required in future.
The provision made by the late Government for  grants to improvements on classified roads amounted to  4,000,000 and if it had been continued would have represented an estimatedannual expenditure of....................... 6,500,000but it cannot be assumed that an annual provision of  4,000,000 would continue to have been made during the next five years.It will be seen that it is difficult to make a clear estimate of the annual increase in expenditure sanctioned by the present Government and it must be stressed that,although the expenditure is stated as an average per annum, the actual rate of expenditure will vary. It will be low at first, rise to a peak, and diminish at the end of the period.Provisions will continue to be made for grants towards the cost of reconstruction of&quot;weak bridges, abolition of level crossings and tolls, etc., and of improvement works on unclassified roads, in addition to those, already mentioned, which are assisted by the Unemployment Grants Committee.
1.        ROAD FUND BUDGET 19 9  (Lite Govt.)Improvements on :(1) Classified roads  4 in.(2) Rural roads  I-4-m. (3) Unclassified urbanroads  -^ m-Grants -    5 mm.2.     AUTHORISED PHOGRu^lii. (Present Covt. )Expenditure Trunk Roads programme %Lilm       u    (say)  2m. 4-55-Year ProgrammeTotal expend iture  7-gm.Grant ^ x^ of  7-gm-g-x ^ &apos;70HGrant - ^  5jmvAssuming that one half is spent of the amount (1-gm. ) retained from the original Road Fund BudgetTotal Grant -    6m. The figures  4m. and  6-gm0 on page   of your memorandum would suggest 60.

</content>
</cab>
