<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/209/0 images: 390-390</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1930.SECRET. Copy No. 3CP. 38 (30).CABINET.THE COLONIAL OFFICE CONFERENCE, 1930.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.A COLONIAL OFFICE Conference, attended by the Governors and Senior Officials of the non-self-governing Colonies, Protectorates and Mandated Territories, was held in the year 1927, and in 1928 my predecessor addressed a despatch to Colonial Governments enquiring whether they favoured the idea of holding a further Conference, and, if so, what form it should take. He suggested that the normal year for holding the next Conference would be 1930. The replies which were received were generally favourable to holding a further Conference, and I have accordingly had under consideration the question of holding one next June, to be attended by Governors and Senior Officials, as on the last occasion. The Conference would, in the main, work on the lines of the last Conference and would consolidate, or, where necessary, modify, the schemes or proposals then put in hand.I have informed Colonial Governments that it was not improbable that a Conference would be held next June, and asked them for any suggestions for discussion. After receiving their replies I propose to summon the Conference accordingly in that month. I anticipate that it will last for about three weeks, and I hope that it will be possible for nearly all the Colonies and Protectorates to be represented. I should perhaps explain that a Conference of this nature is of a different character to the Imperial Conference, as it is composed of permanent officials, and its discussions are confined largely to administrative matters. As on the last occasion, a summary of its proceedings will be presented to Parliament.I will communicate the Agenda when it is fixed to Departments for their consideration of any items in which they may be concerned.P.February 4, 1930.[20534 I

</content>
</cab>
