<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/209/0 images: 524-533</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
P. 42(30).--T CHARING CROSS BRIDGE SGHT-ME,.MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OP TRANSPORT.In view of the opposition which is being raised in certain quarters, and particularly by the Royal Institute of British Architects and other similar bodies,  to the Charing Cross Bridge Scheme, I think that the Cabinet may wish to be apprised of the position.     The necessary Bill, which is being promoted by the London County Council with my support, is to be read a second time on the 19th February and I annex a statement which will be circulated to Members of the House of Commons generally in connexion with the debate.     The first three pages of this document recite the history of the negotiations and pages 4 and 5 describe briefly the leading features and advantages of the Scheme.It will be remembered that the late Government appointed a Royal Commission to consider the whole problem of London Bridges and that the origin of their action was their desire to preserve Waterloo Bridge V7hich had showed signs of collapse.      It must, I think, be clear that if Waterloo Bridge is to be preserved, additional road facilities at Charing Cross are essential.     The proposal for a double-decker bridge, as recommended by the Royal Commission, was found to be open to serious constructional and other objections and, after much negotiation, the alternative proposal embodied In the present Bill was evolved.It has been criticised mainly on the ground that the height of the bridge and the level of the railway necessarily involve the construction of roads carried at a high level (the so-called &quot;viaducts&quot;) until they can connect up with appropriate traffic centres.      It is contended by the critics&apos;HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMy^NT. )CABINET.CRET. COPY NO, \^   .
- 2359that this will make satisfactory architectural treatment impossible and interfere with development on the south side of the river,      I am satisfied that a &quot;bank to bank&quot; bridge is not practicable as it would create an intolerable traffic situation.     We have to look not only to the existing volume of traffic but to the developments of the next generation. It is also obviously necessary to construct the bridge at a &quot;height which will not obstruct navigation,I agree, of course, that a scheme of this magnitude costing over  12 millions, of which the Road   Fund will find 75%, ought not merely to solve technical engineering and traffic problems but be a great addition   to the dignity and development of the Metropolis.     In this matter we have taken the advice of Sir Edwin Lutyens.     Ke has, of course, been bound to subordinate his ideas to the essential engineering and traffic considerations which must condition any scheme but he has stated that In his opinion he has no doubt &quot;that the bridge and its bridge heads, as we finally agreed upon, are capable of a distinguished expression in their architectural treatment&quot;.No doubt if endless millions were available we could town-plan to much greater advantage than will be possible under the present scheme, but this Is not the issue. The position we have to face is, in my opinion, that it is this scheme (subject to such minor modifications as may be found desirable) or nothing, and that If this scheme fails, Waterloo Bridge will in all likelihood come down and the present railway bridge at Charing Cross will continue to disfigure London for another generation.      It is interesting to &quot;note that the only detailed suggestion made since I received the deputation from the Royal Institute of British Architects is that put forward by Sir Reginald Blomfield. His plan briefly is to construct a bridge running from the
- 3 -380level of the Strand somewhat to the east of the present railway bridge (the line of which will be followed under the London County Council1s proposal) to the south side of the river.      I am advised that the proposal to construct a new bridge further down stream and, therefore, nearer to Waterloo Bridge, would give rise to grave difficulties from the point of view of navigation.     It would also go far to destroy the amenities of the Victoria Embankment Gardens and finally its author suggests that.the railway bridge should be left alone until It falls down.     I do not see how any responsible local authority of Government could go to Parliament with such a proposal.The crucial point Is the position of the railway station on the south side of the river.      If this could be pushed back to the site of the existing 7/aterloo Junction Station it would be possible to get down to road level more quickly on the south side with some advantage from the point of view of lay-out, but the Southern Railway throughout the negotiations took the strongest exception to any   proposal of this kind and if it had been persisted in might have fought the whole scheme  and would certainly have very greatly increased their claim for compensation.     The site on the river frontage possesses considerable advantages over the Waterloo junction site, in that it Is nearer to the existing Charing Cross Station and is In such a position that connection can be formed much more easily and conveniently with the underground railways at Waterloo.In all the circumstances and as at present advise I, I propose to give my unreserved stipport to the proposals of the London County Council and I hope that if any of my colleagues are approached in the matter the?/ will take an equally firm line in favour of what I believe will be the biggest improvement to London since the Victoria Emabnkment was constructed.flntld, ) h,M..181330
Revise-7.2.30IN THE HOUSE OF COMMONS. Session 1929-30.LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL (CHARING CROSSBRIDCE) BILL.statement on behalf of the London County Council in support of Second Reading.The main objects of the Bill are to obtain authority to construct a new bridge for vehicular and pedestrian traffic across the River Thames on the site of the existing Charing Cross-bridge of the Southern Railway Company and to carry out street works in connection therewith. The proposed bridge will involve the transfer of the terminal station of the Southern Railway at Charing Cross to a site on the Lambeth side of the River and the removal of the existing bridge, and the necessary powers in this connection are sought in the Bill. Provision is also made in the Bill for the construction of a subway to enable passengers to pass between the proposed new terminal station of the Southern Railway and the underground railway stations at Waterloo and of an underground booking hall (similar to that at Piccadilly Circus) for the London Electric Railway beneath the circus to be formed in the Strand, with an escalator subway connecting the booking hall with the Strand Station of that Company. Powers are also sought for the reconstruction of the Charing Cross (Embankment) Station of the Metropolitan District Railway Company within the structure of the proposed new bridge.A new bridge at Charing Cross has for many years been a subject of discussion but the present proposal arises out of the report of the Royal Commission on Cross-River Traffic in London (1926). This Royal Commission was appointed owing to the failure of certain of the arches of Waterloo-bridge and to the controversy which arose as to whether that bridge should be reconstructed or should be entirely demolished and a new bridge built. The Royal Commission recom-mended that the bridge should be reconstructed and widened to take four, lines of vehicular traffic. It had been suggested that the bridge should be widened to take six lines of traffic, but the Royal Commission stated that they did not think it either necessary or desirable that a bridge of such dimensions should be erected at this
spot and that the demand of through-London traffic could be far better satisfied by a new bridge at Charing Cross. In thus linking up their proposals for Waterloo and Charing Cross bridges, it is clear that the Royal Commission regarded their proposal for a restricted widening of the former bridge as practicable only if a road bridge were built at Charing Cross at a date much earlier than that hitherto contemplated.   On this latter point they remarked (paragraph 122) :&quot; Apart from the weighty evidence which we have received in its favour, we are ourselves convinced that, in the interests of traffic, a new road bridge at this point (Charing Cross) is essential. We regard its provision as of special importance as a means of affording relief to both Waterloo and Westminster bridges and we are of opinion that there should be no unnecessary delay in proceeding with this project.&quot;The Royal Commission considered many schemes for the suggested new bridge and their definite recommendations on this subject involved the removal of the railway station to another site slightly to the east of the present site, the demolition of the existing railway bridge and the construction of a new double-deck bridge to accommodate railway, vehicular and pedestrian traffic, with extensive approaches to the bridge from both sides of the River.The Council on 29th March, 1927, decided to give effect to the recommendations of the Royal Commission as to Waterloo Bridge provided that the necessary steps were taken to construct a bridge and approaches at Charing Cross in accordance with a scheme to be approved by H.M. Government and the Council, subject to certain questions as to the amount of grant to be received from the Government.The Ministry of Transport instituted an inquiry into the financial, engineering and other aspects of the scheme suggested by the Royal Commission, and Messrs. Mott, Hay and Anderson, Consulting Engineers, and the Council&apos;s Chief Engineer (Sir George Humphreys, K.B.E.) were appointed to investigate the matter and draw up a report. After close examination the engineers found that the carrying out in all its details of the recommendation of the Royal Commission presented serious constructional difficulties which, though not insuperable, led them to suggest a transference of the railway terminus to the Lambeth side of the River, thus obviating the necessity for providing accommodation for railway traffic across the River.The attitude of the Southern Railway Company throughout has been that in their opinion any scheme involving removal to the south side of the River would cause inconvenience to the travelling public using the existing station and possibly loss to the shareholders,
but if such removal was regarded as vital to a satisfactory improve-ment they would consider it if satisfactory terms could be arranged. They raised special and serious objections to the scheme of the engineers for the transfer of the station to the site at Waterloo junction to which they stated they would be compelled to offer strenuous opposition. As a result of further examination the con-clusion was reached by all parties that the present proposed site, which is the only practicable alternative, offered considerable advantages to all concerned. This site possesses considerable advantages over the Waterloo junction site, in that it is nearer to the existing Charing Cross Station and is in such a position that connections can much more easily and conveniently be formed with the underground railways at Waterloo. Moreover, it provides an opportunity for the immediate improvement of the river frontage by the construction of an embankment wall and public gardens. The utilisation of this site received the general approval of the Council on 31st July, 1928, subject to satisfactory terms being arranged with the Southern Railway Company.Further negotiations then took place with that Company, and these eventually resulted in the adoption by both the Council and the proprietors of the Company on 30th July, 1929, of the heads of agreement set out in the Seventh Schedule to the Bill.The principal features of these heads of agreement are : -(i.) The Council to acquire and convey to the Company the site of the new station, (ii.) The Company to proceed with the construction of the new station and complete the same with all reasonable despatch, (iii.) On the opening for traffic of the new station the Company to convey to the Council without payment the site of the existing station.(iv.) The Council to pay to the Company a sum equal to the estimated cost of reinstatement of the Company on the new site and of providing means of communication with adjacent stations.(v.) The Council to pay to the Company a sum of  325,000 in satisfaction of all claims by the Company for compensa-tion.(vi.) The Council to provide during the construction of the bridge a temporary road bridge between Charing Cross and the new station.As soon as agreement had been reached with the Southern Railway Company the Council approved the general lay-out of the improvement and formally resolved to promote the necessary legislation.
Negotiations have also been carried out with the London Electric Railway Company and the Metropolitan District Railway Company with a view to powers (which are included in the Bill) being obtained to enable those Companies to carry out works which will greatly increase the facilities for the travelling public.The Bill (if passed) will involve the demolition of the existing railway bridge, which the Royal Commission described as &quot;an eyesore and a blot on one of the finest vistas in Europe.&quot;The present scheme has been devised with full regard to the important traffic problems involved. Every scheme suggested during the last thirty years was most carefully examined before the present proposals were settled. The four primary considerations involved are traffic, engineering, valuation and architecture, and it is submitted that the best advice has been obtained under each of these heads.It is not practicable to construct a &quot; bank-to-bank&quot; bridge without materially raising the existing bank level, as, apart from other important considerations including traffic, the bridge has to be constructed at such a height as not unreasonably to restrict the use of the River for navigation purposes. The height of the bridge and the level of the new railway involve necessarily the construction of roads carried at a high level and such roads have to be continued until they can connect up with appropriate traffic centres. It might be pointed out that the present scheme does not involve nearly so much viaduct construction as was proposed in the scheme recom-mended by the Royal Commission.The scheme, which has been prepared in collaboration with the Ministry of Transport, deals in a comprehensive manner with the whole of the transport problem, and it is believed that, when completed, the improved facilities provided for an easy flow of traffic on to and off the bridge and for the interchange of passenger traffic as between railways, tubes, omnibuses and tramways and the removal of the present-unsightly bridge will more than justify the expenditure incurred. It should be remembered that the scheme is mainly one for the construction of the bridge over the River Thames, the siting of which has to be considered in relation to requirements of navigation of the river and to the presence of underground railways and for the road connections in the immediate neighbourhood. The scheme will not however interfere with the solution of other traffic difficulties, and has been designed in relation to other traffic schemes now in contemplation, e.g., at the Elephant and Castle and Vauxhall Cross. Consideration is also now being given to the question of the improve-ment of the traffic facilities north of the Nurse Cavell statue.
As regards cost, it should be borne in mind that there must be some limit to the expenditure to be incurred. The Council have heavy liabilities to face in connection with the re-conditioning of Waterloo Bridge and other important improvement schemes. It is true that 75 per cent, of the cost of the present scheme is to be borne by the Road Fund, but that Fund has many other calls on its re-sources. The net cost of the scheme for which authority is sought in the Bill is  12,500,000, and the Council feel that the limit of expendi-ture has been reached in adopting this scheme. It is submitted that nothing less than the improved traffic facilities provided by the scheme would adequately solve the existing difficulties, and that ifc would be impracticable to devise a less expensive scheme which would be equally effective in dealing with the many problems involved. Any suggestion as to placing the terminal stations of the Southern Railway underground is impracticable because the cost would be prohibitive.The lay-out of the present scheme has been drawn up in collaboration with Sir Edwin Lutyens, R.A., whose services were secured by the Minister of Transport.The Victoria Embankment gardens are not only not interfered with in connection with the scheme, but will be slightly extended. Ornamental gardens will be provided on the Lambeth side as part of the development of this area.Within the limits of the present proposals, the Council would willingly consider any suggestions for the best possible architectural treatment of the scheme, and, if the present Bill becomes law, the Council will be prepared to consider the advisability of throwing open to competition the designs of the main features of the scheme, in-cluding the new bridge and viaducts and the circuses in the Strand and in Waterloo Road.As has been stated above the question of a new bridge is linked up with that of the reconstruction and widening of Waterloo-bridge. The rejection of the scheme, after lengthy and difficult negotiations have been brought to a satisfactory conclusion, might cause the indefinite postponement of the proposal to construct a new bridge at Charing Cross, with the result that the problem of Waterloo-bridge might have to be reopened.It is submitted that the merits of the present scheme can only be decided after a close and exhaustive consideration of expert evidence on the many difficult considerations which arise. It is for this reason that the Council respectfully ask that the Bill may be read a second time in order that it may be examined by a Select Committee of the House who will be in a position to form a considered judgment upon the scheme after hearing the views of supporters and opponents.

LONDON COUNTY COUNCIL (CHARING CROSS BRIDGE) BILL.statement in support of Second Reading.[The Bill has been set down for Second Reading on Wednesday, 19th February, at 7.30 p.m.]H. MARTYN 4IOOKE,The County Hall,Westminster Bridge, S.E. 1, Parliamentary Officer to the Council. DYSON, BELL &amp; CO.,19, Abingdon Street,Westminster, S.W. 1.Parliamentary Agents.75   T.P. 29-2   6-2-30   .J.T.S.

</content>
</cab>
