<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/47/28 images: 256-263</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
rERNMENT       ^Q ^THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   February 1944.84secret.Copy No,W.P. (44) 128.22nd February, 1944.war cabinet;POLES IN THE UNITED STATES.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.MY colleagues may be interested to read the annexed secret paper from aBritish official source in the United States about Polish-American politicalgroups there, with particular reference to Polish-Soviet relations.THE question of the relative strength of the Polish-American groups whoare opposing the policy of the Polish Government-in-Exile is not an easy one to answer.If one takes the Polish press, it is quite clear that the overwhelming majorityof the Polish daily -papers and weeklies are aggressively nationalist in theirintransigent demand for a post-war Poland not merely restored to its pre-warborders, but extended at the expense of Germany. In so far as they were atthe time of Sikorsky critical of the Government, it was because of the Govern-menfs alleged weakness towa,rds Russia. To-day they all are solidly behind anuncompromising attitude to the U.S.S.R. and are bitterly hostile to Russia.On the other hand, the few &quot; pro-Soviet &quot; papers have been considerably-increasing in influence and circulation lately : The Communist Glos Ludowy andthe much more influential Left-wing, although non-Communist, Nasz Swiat ofDetroit, the Gwiazda Polarna, a Wisconsin weekly, and lately Trybune, a NewBedford (Mass.) weekly. Nasz Swiat counts amongst its contributors some of themost outstanding Polish intellectuals, including Professor Oscar Lange&quot; ofChicago and Professor Louis Karpinski of Michigan Universities. It is editedby a brilliant journalist, Waclaw Soyda, who is particularly hated by the advocates of the official view.Professor Lange stoutly denies that the overwhelmingly anti-Soviet Polishpress accurately reflects the sentiments of the Poles, as in his opinion it reaches-only 10 per cent, of Americans of Polish birth and extraction. The secondgeneration does not read it, and, in any case, does not follow its political lead;They follow the line of their party of labour affiliations.In the absence of any more definite evidence, or of any public opinion poll,it is, as stated before, very difficult to state in hard figures the respective strengthof the different Polish groups, but certain general conclusions can nevertheless be advanced. 1The growing cleavage between the American Poles follows the line of thePolish-Russian dispute. In their views the American Poles are influenced bytheir general political attitude. Thus, in so far as the Polish-Americans are irrclose touch with the profoundly reactionary Catholic hierarchy in the United&apos;States (with rare exceptions in the ranks of the lower clergy), they reflect theirbitterness towards the &quot; godless &quot; U.S.S.R. and corresponSingly repudiate any concessions towards Russia. At the same time, these groups are vociferously5anti-Roosevelt and equally anti-British. Britain&apos;s 20-year pact with russia is always in the forefront of the accusations levelled against us.A. E.Foreign Office, 22nd February, 1944.ANNEX.12285   [26976]
Similarly, the Right-wing trade unionists and; so-called Socialists of theP.S.P., who are closely connected with the anti-Communist leaders of theAmerican Federation of Labour, and whose paper is the Robotnik Polski, are equally uncompromising to any concession to Russia. --j All these groups fear Russia more than Germany and say this constantly in private talks and conversations. Just as the Green-Matthew-Woll clique of theA.F. of L. is anti-British because of the T.U.C.&apos;s insistence on the inclusion of theSoviet trade unions in an international organisation, so are the Polish Right-wingSocialists anti-British because of the supposed support by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment of Russia&apos;s claims.,. On the other hand, the tendency for a rapprochement with Russia has nowgone far beyond the Communists or &quot; fellow-travellers.&quot; The whole liberal press and most of the responsible commentators and columnists advocate this rapproche-ment, which is now the least criticised point of the Administration^ foreignpolicy. This has had obvious consequences in Polish circles. Polish organised labour and prominent Polish intellectuals rushed into action and the KosciuszkoLeague was formed in Detroit at the end of 1943, the first non-CommunistPolish-American association standing for friendship with the Soviet Union. Theleaders behind this movement are (1) Professor Lange, whose much-discussed declaration, &quot; Call to Reason,&quot;drafted by him and signed by thirty prominent Polish-Americans and polish citizens, started the movement.(2) Waclaw Soyda, referred to in the foregoing.(3) Reverend Stanislaus Orlemanski.(4) Bolislaw Gebert, chief of the Polish-American section of the I.W.O.,(5) Szymon Kaminski, formerly editor of Robotnik Polski, with which hebroke in protest against its anti-Soviet policy.(6) Dr. A. Penzik.(7) State Senator Nowak of Michigan.(8) Leo Krzycki, vice-president of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers ofAmerica (C.I.O.), the most influential Polish-American Labour leader.(9) Professor L. Karpinski of the University of Michigan.(10) Professor I. Zlotowsky of Vassar College. ,;(11) Dr. W. T. Ossowski, president of the Michigan Star Congress. -i(12) Dr. Joseph Wedda. president of the Detroit Civil Service Commission.^The aims of the Kosciuszko League may be gathered from the declaration ofpolicy adopted at its first meeting. This stated that collaboration of Poland withRussia was no less necessary than similar collaboration on the part of the UnitedStates and Great Britain. It laid the biame for the break in Polish-soviet relations upon the Polish Government-in-Exile and asserted that the Government-in-Exile was itself a &quot;prisoner of reaction.&quot; Concretely it proposed two forms of activity. One was support of the Kosciuszko Division of Poles fighting with theRussian Army, the other a campaign &apos;&apos; to unite Americans of Polish descent insupport of the policies of President Roosevelt as well as to&apos; combat the activitiesof the fifth columnists and appeasers on American and Polish-American fields.&quot;In conversation with a friend following the meetings, Lange said that theKosciuszko League was organised &apos;&apos; to give moral rather than material support to the Poles fighting in Russia.&quot; He spoke of the need for such support in thiscountry, and said that his group did not plan to send relief or men to Russia, but merely to provide a channel for liberal Poles in America to give their moral support to the Poles in Russia.The officers of the League appear to be Labour leftists of some prominencein the Detroit community of Poles; no men of Lange&apos;s type are included in the directorate.The National Council of American-Soviet Friendship in New York has been organised practically by the same people as the Kosciuszko League. This council,according to a pattern already taking shape in Detroit and Chicago, is rallyingbroad support for Soviet-Polish friendship and will drive ahead on three mainfronts simultaneously. The Kosciuszko League, intended to appeal to Polish-American liberals, now has branches at Springfield, Mass., and at Detroit.Orlemanski has just returned from a whirlwind campaign in Canada, where hedelivered eight lectures urging the formation of branches. One branch has been created in Mexico City. A campaign will be launched, said Orlemanski; toorganise a branch &quot; in every town and village of the United States and Canada.&quot;
A further group of organisations are the Polish-American Trade UnionCouncils for the cause of Polish-Soviet friendship. A number of StatewidePolish-American Trade Union Councils have recently expressed support forPolish-Soviet conciliation, notably those of. Chicago, Milwaukee, Detroit andNewark, New Jersey. A movement has been on foot to form a national organisa-tion of Polish-American Trade Union Committees.We must repeat that we are not in a position to give figures as to the relative &apos;strength of the various groups now working for an improvement of Polish-Russian relations. We are safe, however, in saying that these groups are on theincrease; that no anti-British feelings are ascertainable among them; that theintellectual leaders and Mr. L. Krzycki are strongly pro-British and that theyare denounced as traitors, Soviet agents, renegades, &amp;c, by the agents of thePolish Government and by the Matuszewski-Wegrzynek press. None of theleaders of these various movements is Communist.v In the American press the figure of 600,000 was once mentioned as the goalof the Trade Union Councils. Whereas the number of organised workmen of polish descent may approximate this figure, it would be exaggerated to assume that all of them adhere to the pro-Russian line. What can be said with areasonable degree of certainty is : (a) that the movement against the anti-Russianpolicies of the Government-in-Exile is gaining strength in the circles of theworkmen and the intellectuals; (&amp;) that the movement is generally in line withthe policy of the Administration; (c) that it is pro-British, viz., for an enduringunderstanding with Britain and the U.S.S.R.; (d) that the pro-Polish Govern-ment policies are strongly entrenched in the press, the clergy and the middleclass, and that they are actively assisted by the numerous agents of Polish officialpropaganda; (e) that the pro-Polish Government circles are increasingly anti-British and anti-Roosevelt.






</content>
</cab>
