<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/181/8 images: 108-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
EUROPEAN COMMUNITY REFERENDUM:INFORMATION policy memorandum by the Lord President of the council I. In my general memorandum (C(75) 7) proposing the announcementof a referendum on membership of the European Community, I mentioned that I was also circulating a paper about the handling of information and themedia.    This aspect has great political importance.    It is also urgent -the pro European Economic Community (e.c.) and anti e.c. organisationshave already started their campaigns.2. Chapter 4 of the report by a preliminary Working Party of officials(C(75) 6) outlined the questions for consideration,    I now invite mycolleagues to read the annexed note by officials, which takes the examinationof the main issues a stage further.GOVERNMENT INFORMATION (paragraphs 3-12 of Annex)3.        In my view the Government have a clear duty to see that the electorate have the necessary information on which to give their decision in the referendum.    We should make a start by making factual information available about the nature of the Community and about the impact of community policies in this country.    We should aim to begin this programme by the end of February.    We should be exposed to criticism if we postponed the start of the programme until after the completion ofthe renegotiation;, there would then be insufficient time for the programme to be effective before a June referendum.    The work should be handled bya special interdepartmental unit centrally located in the Cabinet Officeworking under the close supervision of Ministers.4. When the renegotiation is complete, the range of the informationprogramme will need to be widened.    We shall want to publicise the outcome of renegotiation and to put forward a comparison of the new terms of membership with the present terms.    We shall also need to be ready with information about the wider prospects of Community membership and the implications of withdrawal.1A 9C(75) 8 COPY NO  617 January 1975CABINET
5.        After consultation with the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary,who is Chairman of the Ministerial Committee on European Questions, i suggest that he should have the Ministerial responsibility for a programme on these lines.CONTROL OF OTHER INFORMATION ACTIVITIES (Paragraphs 13-22 of Annex)... &apos;     . -    .      .  . &apos;6.        There is some apprehension about the conduct of the referendumcampaign: will both pro and anti-marketeers have a fair crack of the whip?Public opinion will expect us to take any practicable measures that are needed to prevent manifest unfairness.7.        Nevertheless, we should hesitate before interfering with normalfreedom of expression in these matters.    The one statutory control onelection expenditure - limits on expenditure designed to promote theelection of an individual candidate - is not an available option in the caseof a referendum.    The main expenditure will be national or regional.8.        Any special control of expenditure for referendum purposes wouldnot be easy to formulate.    It could not catch the whole range ofprogapanda activities.   Although consideration could be given toimposing limits on specified activities such as national newspaperadvertising, provision for the control would need to be made in the referendum Bill and could operate only in the few weeks before royal assent and the referendum.&apos; . . . : &apos;   . &apos;...,.!&apos;.9.        We could consider what Government assistance could properly begiven to the outside organisations, eg by providing for the freedistribution of a document analogous to an Election Address.10.       Special attention will be focussed on radio and television programmes, including any allocation to pro and anti-market organisations of special time on the lines of the General Election broadcasts by thepolitical Parties.    We may find that the broadcasting authorities feel thattheir arrangements can be readily adapted to ensure the necessaryfairness and balance.    Nevertheless, in the novel situation of a referendumI do not think that the Government can dissociate itself entirely from thearrangements made and Parliament will expect to be told what is proposed.At the least, we shall want to have informal contact with the Chairmen ofthe two authorities.11, We do not need to take immediate decisions about these questions.I shall examine them further before I bring a draft of the Referendum bill before my colleagues.2
E S. v.Privy Council Office17 January 1975312.       I ask my colleague s:-a. To agree that the Government should take responsibility for providing the public with information needed for the referendumdecision by way of the factual information mentioned in paragraph 3and information about the renegotiation terms and the wider issuesmentioned in paragraph 4.b. To agree that the Foreign and Commonwealth Secretary should now put in hand arrangements for providing the factual informationmentioned in paragraph 3 and preparations for the wider programmeforeshadowed in paragraph 4 for the period after the renegotiationhas been completed.c. To note that I shall give further thought to the possiblecontrol of propaganda activities, on the basis of the considerations set out in paragraphs 6 to 10. . , i
ANNEXEUROPEAN COMMUNITY REFERENDUM:   INFORMATION policy note by Officials1o     If Ministers decide to hold a national referendum to fulfil theircommitment to give the British people &quot;the final say&quot; on British membership of the European Community, important issues of information policy ariae.The main issues were outlined in Chapter 4 of the report of the preliminaryworking party of officials (C(75) 6)0   This note takes the matter a stage further and concentrates on the key questions requiring ministerial decisions. -2.    The issues fall under 2 main headings -,V:&apos;&apos; - &apos; &apos; ji &apos; if/if;-?:/./ . - - .Is    The information programme which the Government might wish toarrange.II.   Control of the information and propaganda activities of othersoI.     A GOVERNMENT INFORMATION PROGRAMME&apos; j IScope3.     There is a widespread feeling, supported by survey data, that theBritish people do not have sufficient information on the subject for themto be able to give an informed decision at the referendum.   The Governmentare expected to see that this gap is filled.4s     The information which might be made available to the public mightfall into 4 broad categories -a. the nature of the Community as it now is and the role of theCommunity in world affairs;b. the impact of existing Community policies on the United Kingdom,both generally (eg in relation to Parliament) and in different sectors(eg agriculture, fisheries, transport, etc);.   4
c. the outcome of renegotiation - a comparison of the renegotiatedterms (if renegotiation is successful) with the terms of entry in 1973td. the implications of withdrawal and an assessment of the alternatives.5*    Information on the Community is always liable to he open to controversy,hut some aspects are less controversial than others*   It would be compara-tively easy to provide factual, relatively non-controversial information on a.; b. would be less easy, and do would be extremely controversial.Timing6.    Experience suggests that an information programme of the kind requiredwill need to start some months before the date of the referendum if it isto be effective.   If the referendum is to be held in June, it is suggestedthat the programme will need to start before the results of renegotiationare known at the end of March.   This conclusion is reinforced by the startwhich has already been made to the campaigns of the main outside organi-sations who are in favour of or opposed to membership.Y*      - .&apos; &apos; -   .&apos;7*     a. and b. (paragraph 4) can be tackled as soon as Ministers wish,though a little time will be needed to prepare a programme and the material.Information in these 2 categories will then form the backcloth for    ninformation on the outcome of the renegotiation c.   Probably d. oughtalso to wait until that stage.   The programme should continue until the holding of the referendum, and Ministers themselves will no doubt wishto put forward their views on all these matters during the referendumcampaign itself.8.    The Government will soon be pressed to say what arrangements they propose.   Ministers will presumably wish to include a passage on thesubject in any statement to Parliament announcing that a referendum isto be the method of consulting the British people05
Machinery9*    We considered whether the conduct of the programme should b? in thehands of an independent agency, headed by a respected senior figure ofmanifest impartiality.   Such an agency, when fully operational, mightbe able to move more quickly and more flexibly than the government machine, and the Government could claim that the information arrange-ments were on the most neutral basis possible.   But the agency would still depend on official sources for most of its material;   ministers would not be able in practice to avoid all responsibility for the workof the agency, which could arouse considerable controversy at awkwardtimes during the passage of the Referendum Bill; it would be more costly;and it would take some time to set up.   This last consideration seemsdecisive against setting up an agency.   The agency could not be fullyoperational until the period after the outcome of the renegotiation, whenthe Government would in any case be involved in explaining the new terms which had been secured.100   We therefore suggest that the information programme should be carriedout from within the Government and that the existing machinery shouldbe strengthened for the purpose.   It will be necessary to decide which Minister should have responsbility.I!11.   At official level, the Foreign and Commonwealth Office (FCO) as theDepartment responsible for the renegotiation, would have to play a leading part.   But the FCO might be regarded by public opinion as beingtoo partisan, and there could therefore be an argument for placing the responsible team in the Cabinet Office, presumably under the general supervision of the European Unit.   The team would need to be drawn fromother Government Departments, together with the necessary secretarialstaff.   A rough estimate of direct staffing,costs, based on previous experience and an operation extending over 5 months would be about  30,000(on the assumption that accommodation and support costs would be borne on existing votes).6
12.   The operational ,oo^ts would depend on the scale of the programmedPossible methods of distribution include posters^ distribution throughoutpost offices and direct advertisements inviting requests for material.The expenditure involved would be in the range of  1-3 million.   Theteam would use the technical facilities of the Central Office ofInformation, who would need to be specifically absolved, especiallyduring the campaign period, from their normal obligation to reduce their activities in an election period.II.   CONTROL OF OTHER INFORMATION ACTIVITIESGeneral considerations13.   Ministers will also be asked whether there is to be any control overthe information and propaganda activities of the other participants whoare engaged on both sides of the main issue. ; The electorate will have in mind the system which applies to General Elections and broadlyprovides -aa     strict control of the expenditure of individual candidatesduring this campaign period?b. an equitable allocation of time on radio and television forthe political parties.In addition -c. The Independent Broadcasting Authority (IBA) is under ageneral statutory requirement to maintain a proper balance inthe subject matter of programmes.   The British Broadcasting Corporation(BBC) is not under airy such statutory obligation, but has engagedto do so by exchange of letters with the Government.   Thisbalance is normally achieved by ordinary editorial policy.The existing system does not limit expenditure outside a campaign period or expenditure on nationwide campaigns by the parties, or by other organisations, which cannot be linked to individual candidates.7
14.   The Government will wish to bo able to say that they are takingwhat measures they can to ensure, so far as possible, a balancedpresentation of the issues which the electorate has to decide? and anational referendum will be different in some respects from a GeneralElection.   But any system of control which departed significantly fromthe General Election system would raise major questions of principleabout the freedom of expression.   Paid propaganda, if too insistent,may in the end be counter-productive.   Electors are just as likely tobe impressed by the arguments of leading political and other figures and official information disseminated under the Governments own informationprogramme (see Section I above).15*   There are also considerable practical limitations on what can bedone.   Special legal controls, which would need to be included in the referendum Bill, could apply only after Royal Assent and therefore probablyonly to a short campaign period.   There would be no way of controllingall forms of outside propaganda, even if the Government thought it rightto do so.   There would, moreover, be a major problem in defining the propaganda and organisations subject to control, since the EuropeanCommuntiy issues can be related to many political and other questions*16.   Against this background we consider the main possibilities forGovernment action.   In a novel area of this importance, all the implications will requiro close examination, and a further paper would be needed before Ministerial decisions could be taken.17* We assume that a Government information programme would not besubject to any additional controls instituted for other informationpropaganda activitieso18.   A ban on paid advertising on radio and television.   The IBA andthe commercial radio stations are debarred by statute from acceptingadvertising on political matters.   The Government will be able to assureParliament that this statutory prohibition will apply to advertisingrelating to the referendum issue (though  before a statement was made, itshould be mentioned informally to the broadcasting authorities)o   Butthere is nothing which can be done to stop Radio Luxembourg acceptingadverti sement s *8
19*   A &quot;ban on press advertisingi from any source, if directed towardsthe referendum issue would raise difficulties of principle and definitionmentioned in paragraphs 14 and 15.   It would require legislation.20.   Special provision about activities, &quot;by firms.   Any general control would run into much the same difficulties of principle and practice,and would require legislation.   Firms would have time to make their contributions before it came into force.   It might be feasible for theBill to require firms and other bodies to make public their contributions to specified categories of organisation involved in the referendum issue.But this requirement would not of itself limit the amount of moneyprovided.Radio and Television21 a   The BBC and IBA are obliged to ensure a proper balance in their programmes and Ministers will presumably wish to rest as far as possible on the view that the responsibility for discharging this obligation rests on the broadcasting authorities.   This obligation to ensure a properbalance will extend to ordinary news and discussion programmes and airyspecial programmes which are put on as the date of the referendum approachesIt is possible that the broadcasting authorities will also wish to institute&quot;referendum broadcasts&quot; analogous to Party Political and ElectionBroadcasts in the sense that an amount of time would be allocated to proand anti Community organisations to use as they wished to advance theirviews.22.   A separate problem may arise over the normal party political broadcasts insofar as these touch on the referendum issue.   If thesebroadcasts contained over a period a preponderance of opinion on one sideof the referendum issue, the broadcasting authorities might take theview that the balance should be redressed in other programmes.   Thealternative would be an understanding between the political parties notto use the broadcasts to deal with the referendum issue.9
23*   In addition, Ministers may wish to make Ministerial broadcasts, whichwould involve a right of reply for the opposition.24o   Against this background Ministers may wish to consider the followingspecial steps -io    As soon as it is announced that there is to be a referendumthe Government could inform the BBC and the IBA that they are confidentthey will observe strictly their obligations as regards balance andimpartiality through the whole period until the referendum takes place *ii. There could be informal consultations with the 2 Chairmenabout the detailed programme arrangements proposed, including any proposals for programmes analogous to Election Broadcasts, so that parliament could be informed at ait early stageeiii, The broadcasting authorities could be particularly asked how they proposed to select organisations to make any special &quot;referendumbroadcasts1-.   They might wish to consider setting up a specialadvisory body for the purpose*Financial Assistance25.   The Government might bo asked to provide assistance in cash or in kind for responsible activities by outside organisations.   While therewould he obvious objections to the expenditure of large sums of public money on advertising, it might be defensible to arrange for the freedistribution (and possibly also to assist in the production) of reasonablyshort documents analogous to election addresses.   It would he necessaryfor a single umbrella organisation on each side to be accepted as the spokesman for this purpose.   The facility could however raise thequestion of the political parties also wishing to send out statements.i i ;17 January 197510


</content>
</cab>
