<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/25/0 images: 40-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  government cabinet OFFICEPrinted for the Cabinet.   May 1952   q^qq^q COPYSECRETC.C. (52)57th conclusions copy No.cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 29th May, 1952, at 11 30 am.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.offorThe Right Hon.Chancellor.Lord Simonds, LordM.P.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Alexander of tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The  Right  Hon.The Most Hon. the MarquessSalisbury, Secretary of StateCommonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor   the   Home   Department   and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food(Items 3-6).The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of State (Items 3-6).The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 3-6).The Right Hon. the Earl De La Warr,Postmaster-General (Item 2).The Right Hon. Henry Hopkinson,M.P., Minister of State for colonial affairs (Items 3-6).Patrick   Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 1-2).The   Right  Hon.Secretariat:Mr. T. PaDmore.Mr. G. Mallaby.
contents minute no. Subject page 1     Parliament       .....................     139Business in the House of Commons.2     British Broadcasting Corporation    ............     139Renewal of the Charter.3      Food Prices     .........      .........      ... 1394     Meat Supplies..................... 1405     Wages    ...      ...      ......      ...     .......... 1406     Economic Policy        .................. 140
1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the week beginning Tuesday, 10thJune, when Parliament would reassemble after the Recess.The Lord Privy Seal said that he and the Chief Whip were con-cerned (as was the Speaker) that so small a number of Questions wasbeing answered orally in the House of Commons. He had discussed this with the Speaker, who intended to take steps to reduce the time taken by Supplementary Questions. It would be helpful if ministers would do their best to cut down the length of draft replies submittedto them.2. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Pbst-master-General (C. (52) 180) stating that there had been considerable criticism in the House of Lords of the proposal in the White Paper on broadcasting (Cmd. 8550) that Governors of the B.B.C. should infuture be appointed and removable by a Committee presided over bythe Speaker of the House of Commons, instead of, as at present, byOrder-in-Council; and suggesting that the proposal should now be dropped and that the Governors should continue to be appointed bythe Crown on the advice of the Prime Minister.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) There was general agreement that the Government would beill-advised to adhere to the proposal for a Committee of Appointmentif it encountered continued opposition. The proposal to include twoof Her Majesty&apos;s Judges in its membership might in any event requirereconsideration in view of the fact that the Committee^ powers relatednot only to appointment but to removal of Governors. The Judgesmight be in some embarrassment if a demand for the removal of a governor were made on political grounds.(b) It would, however, be premature to take or announce any decision to amend the proposal in advance of the debate in the Houseof Commons. The suggestion for a Committee of Appointment was known to be welcome to some Government supporters. The matter should therefore be reconsidered in the light of the balance of opinionexpressed in the House of Commons&apos; debate.(c) In the meantime, as it was urgent to proceed with the draft-ing of the Charter and the Licence, alternative drafts of the relevantpassage in the Charter should be prepared, so as to allow either forthe adoption of the White Paper proposal, or for a reversion to themaking of appointments by the Crown on the advice of the PrimeMinister.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Postmaster-General to proceed with the drafting of the Charter and Licence for the B.B.C. on the alternativebases agreed in discussion.(2) Agreed that the Debate in the House of Commons should takeplace on a Government Motion to approve the white paper on Broadcasting; and that, if in the course of this debate, opposition developed to the proposal for a Com-mittee of Appointment, that proposal should be withdrawn.^Parliament.Business in theHouse ofCommons.british broadcasting corporation.Renewal of the charter.(previous reference:CC. (52) 52ndConclusions,Minute 4.)Food Prices.(previous reference:CC. (52) 52ndConclusions,Minute 6.)3. The Minister of Food said that on the Prime Ministers sug-gestion he had circulated a memorandum (C. (52) 178) showingchanges which would shortly be made in the controlled prices ofcertain unsubsidised foods. These prices had to be increased to meetrises in costs. Similar variations in prices of unsubsidised foods were constantly occurring and attracted little public comment. No detailedpublic announcement would be required beyond notification to theappropriate trades.
4. The Minister of State said that in the current negotiationsv/ith the Argentine Government for the supply of meat to the UnitedKingdom the Argentine negotiators had not reacted strongly against our refusal of canned meat. They wished to discuss credit facilitiesfurther, and they had so far maintained their price of  192 per ton.It seemed doubtful whether they would be able to offer as much as200,000 tons. Their aim was to exchange meat to a value of  50million for  50 million worth of supplies from the United Kingdom,mainly in oil and coal.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Minister of State.5. The Minister of Labour said that there was no prospect thatthe trades unions would accept any general wages standstill, sinceexisting agreements provided for some automatic adjustments in sympathy with rises in the cost of living, and the lower-paid workers had benefited little by the remissions of taxation in the Budget. Butthere was evidence of some support from responsible trades union leaders for a policy of wage restraint. The reaction to theChancellor^ recent appeal had been good, but he doubted if the trades union would be willing openly to co-operate with the Governmentin the ways suggested to them.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Minister of Labour.6. The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the memorandumby the Chancellor of the Exchequer (C. (52) 166) on the economicsituation. They also had before them the following furthermemoranda:  C. (52) 171: reproducing a minute addressed by the Paymaster-General to the Prime Minister, commenting on C. (52) 166;C. (52) 172: by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the balanceof payments;In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The rises in the prices of unrationed meat included in theAppendix to C. (52) 178 were made in conformity with the rises inthe prices of rationed meat announced in the Budget Speech. Allthese increases in meat prices had been timed to coincide with thecoming into effect of the income tax reliefs allowed in the Budget andwith the rise in the meat ration. It would be desirable to handle theother rises in such a way as to cause the minimum comment and perhaps to defer some of the rises in prices of subsidised foodsresulting from the Budget so as to coincide with the increases in social service benefits.(b) In certain other ranges of consumer goods prices had begun to fall.   Public attention might be drawn to these reductions.(c) The Lord President said that people were not getting enoughmeat. The shortage of sugar, which would not allow full advantage to be taken of the expected heavy crop of fruit, would be muchresented. A reduction in the butter ration would have to be made inthe autumn and would cause further resentment and malnutritionunless it could be offset by an increase in the ration of margarine.The Cabinet Approved the increases in food prices set out in theAppendix to C. (52) 178; but invited the Minister of food to consult with the Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster ontheir timing and on the best methods of avoiding undesirablepublicity for them.
- C. (52) 175: by the President of the Board of Trade on the exportproblem;C. (52) 173: by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the need toincrease the export of products of the metal-using industries;C. (52) 177:   by the Minister of Labour on the man-powerimplications of reducing the defence production programme in the interests of the export trade;C. (52) 181:  by the Minister of Supply suggesting measures toassist the engineering industries to increase their exports.In the course of a general discussion of economic policy, directedprimarily towards the necessity of remedying the adverse balance ofpayments of the United Kingdom and of the sterling area as a whole,the following points were made: -(a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that the present government had, since they came into office, largely succeeded instopping the drain on the currency reserves of the sterling area. they now had to turn to the task of putting our economy on a sound basis for the future. The situation in which we found ourselves and the broad outline of our necessary objectives were summarised in theearly paragraphs of C. (52) 172. The over-riding duty which facedthe Government was the restoration of a long-term balance in pay-ments between the sterling area and the rest of the world. We mustnot only take all the measures, however disagreeable, which were necessary to achieve this state of balance, but we must re-establishpublic confidence in our determination to do so. Our ability to get through 1952-53 without an open sterling crisis was wholly unassured,but the problem was not one which affected the early future only.We must reach a position in which the United Kingdom had a con-tinuing surplus on overseas account of at least  300 million a year.This meant that our earnings from exports (both visible and invisible)must be increased or our overseas payments must be reduced by an aggregate sum of  600 million a year. We could only hope to achieve this by a combination of many measures; we should have (i) to endeavour to increase substantially the export of those goods which we could sell, viz., the products of the metal-using industries: in order to do this, home demands on metal goods for both civil and military purposes must be further restricted;(ii) to review the whole of our overseas commitments, a study of the greater part of which had already been put in hand by theForeign Secretary;(hi) to examine the import programme in order to achieve all practicable economies: that programme would be brought before theCabinet by the Chancellor of the Exchequer in a few weeks&apos; time;(iv) similarly to re-examine the investment programme, with aview particularly to increasing investment in those industries whichcould produce for export; and(v) to reconsider at an early date the possibility of increasingcoal exports.(b) The Minister of Defence said that he hoped within the nextfew weeks to be able, in the light of a new strategic appreciation whichwas being prepared for him, to propose to the Cabinet substantial savings in defence expenditure in relation both to overseas commit-ments and to the diversion of productive capacity from armamentwork to export. It would be necessary to take bold and far-reaching decisions and to recognise the necessity for spending on defence no more than we could afford. But he thought that he would be ableto offer substantial assistance towards achieving the objectives outlined by the Chancellor of the Exchequer without greatly weakening oureffective military strength. He would concentrate on the building upof forces which, though they might be smaller than those previouslycontemplated, would be of maximum efficiency and striking power.(c) The Minister of Supply said that, if the Cabinet were todecide to slow down rearmament in the interests of the export trade,he thought it would be possible materially to increase metal exports.But there was a limit to what could be done in this direction if the
defence production programme were not to be gravely dislocated&apos;In any event it would not be possible to find, by reducing defence production, the whole of the steel which could profitably be used forexport production., It would be desirable initially at any rate, in orderto achieve quick results and to avoid creating unemployment, to con-concentrate on the export of products which were already being manu-factured for the Service Departments.(d) The Minister of Labour agreed with this view. He hoped,for the reasons set out in C. (52) 177, that early decisions would betaken on the future size of the defence programme and that prepara-tpry measures for the production of goods for export would be well advanced before defence production was reduced. Otherwise therewas a serious risk of a substantial increase in unemployment in thelatter part of this year and of serious criticism if the measures whichthe Government had already taken to increase man-power in thedefence production industries were followed by unemployment and short-time in those industries.(e) The Minister of Supply said that, if the needs of exportproduction were to be regarded as over-riding, there seemed to him(as he had suggested in C. (52) 181) to be a strong case for measuresto defer the call-up of ex-apprentices from the industries concerned.The Minister of Labour said that he was under constant pressure from many quarters to make concessions in relation to national serviceand he was apprehensive lest any further measures of special defer-ment should bring the whole doctrine of the universality of nationalservice into serious question.(/) The President of the Board of Trade said that when everything possible had been done to increase metal exports by adjustment ofthe defence programme it would probably prove not to be enough.We should therefore need to look again at the other uses to whichsubstantial amounts of steel were being put. It might be necessaryto reduce the use of building steel for social purposes. The provisionof steel for school building in the current quarter was greater thanthe whole provision made for building by the industries for whichthe Board of Trade was responsible. It might be found that suchan allocation of our resources could not be justified in presentcircumstances.(g) The President of the Board of Trade said that, while it wasnecessary to press exports of manufactures from the sterling area to the fullest possible extent, it would be desirable also to re-examinewith the Commonwealth the extent to which the sterling area as awhole could reduce its imports from elsewhere. We should not abandon hope of returning to the old pattern of world trade in whichwe had a surplus with the Commonwealth, and the commonwealth countries other than the United Kingdom had a surplus with the dollar area. It might be that, when the Committee on commercial policy had reported and the Cabinet had reached their own con-elusions on our future commercial policy, it would be desirable tohold a high-level Commonwealth Conference on this subject; this might in turn lead to a Commonwealth approach to the United states administration.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Minister of Defence, in consultation with theChancellor of the Exchequer, to pursue his examinationof the defence programme in the light of the new strategicappreciation being prepared for him; and to report tothem on measures which, by reducing and deferring that programme, would reduce overseas military expenditure and increase production of metal goods for export., (2) Took note &quot;that the Foreign Secretary was reviewing the overseas commitments of the United Kingdom with aview to making any possible reductions; and invited himto report his conclusions to them.
143CC. 57 (52)(3) Agreed to consider further the memoranda before them inthe light of recommendations to be made by the Ministerof Defence and by the Foreign Secretary in accordancewith Conclusions (1) and (2) above; and of memorandato be submitted by the Chancellor of the Exchequer onthe import programme and the investment programme.(4) Invited the Minister of Supply to submit to the DefenceCommittee specific proposals for the sale outside the sterling area of articles of defence equipment of whichdelivery to the Services might be reduced or deferred.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,29th May, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
