<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/25/0 images: 61-71</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet,   June 1952SECRET &apos; Copy No. 45C.C. (52). .60th Conclusions&apos; &apos; &apos;&apos; 7,        &apos; cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 17th June, 1952, at 11 a.m.. Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Horn Anthony Eden, M.P.,-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,. M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,* Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The following were also present:The Right Hon. R. G. Menzies, Q.C.Prime Minister of Australia.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,. Minister of Supply (Item 8).The Right Hon. the Earl De La Warr,Postmaster-General (Item 11).The Right Hon. J. P. L. Thomas,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty(Items 1-2).The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Items 1-2).Mr. Nigel Birch, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry . of Defence(Item 8).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook. -Mr. A, S. Brown (Secretary of the Australian Cabinet).Mr. G. Mallaby.42454-1b
contents minute no.&apos; Subject.   .1    , Mr..Menzies    ...&apos;  -2     Royal Visit to Australia and New Zealand......3   &apos;&apos;. Germany ...      ....      ......      ......4.i   Korea.   ...     .A.............1 ;., - Armistice Talks. - -5 -   Persia    ...      .....&apos;.&apos;     ............*&apos;  6     Trade between the United Kingdom and Australia&apos;. &apos; 7     Meetings of Commonwealth Ministers      ......^8     Supply of Defence. Equipment to Australia......9 . -&apos;.Central African Federation   ......Page1611611.6116116216216316416^11 Recognition of Post Office Staff Associations12     Conclusion of Mr. Menzies&apos; Visit   ...16616740
Mr,Menzies. - ,.&apos; &apos;   1.   The Prime Minister said that he and his Cabinet colleagues were very glad to have, the Prime Minister of Australia with them at this meeting.   They would greatly value the benefit of his..&apos;   experienced counsel.       &apos;      .2. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Secretary of theCabinet (C. (52), 183) covering a minute by the Prime Minister ofAustralia on the proposed dates of the Royal Visit to Australia andNew Zealand and on the suggestion that The Queen and the duke of Edinburgh should make use of the s.s. Gothic during the courseof their Visit. -In discussion there was general agreement that it would be advantageous if Her,Majesty made use of the s.s. Gothic during thisVisit. The Chancellor of the Exchequer expressed his appreciation of Mr. Menzies&apos; offer of ah Australian contribution towards the costof using this vessel.It was also agreed that, subject to.the views of the New zealand government, it would be convenient that the Visit to New Zealandshould take place in January 1954 so that the Visit to Australiacould be completed by the end of March. .The Cabinet : (1) Took note that the Prime Minister would inform Her Majesty&apos; of the views which had been expressed in the discussion.(2) Invited the Chancellor of the: Exchequer to arrange for- official consultations to be held with the australian government regarding Australia^ contribution towardsthe cost of using the s.s. Gothic for the purpose of this-   /     , - Visit. - ....3. The Foreign Secretary said that there was good reason to hope that the German Federal Chancellor would be able to hold hisCoalition Government together and secure the ratification of theTreaty for the&quot; European Defence Community. Ratification wouldbe opposed by the&apos; Social Democratic Party, owing chiefly to the hostility of its Leader, Dr. Schumacher. More reasonable viewswould prevail in the Social Democratic Party if its leadership passed in course of time to Herr Reuter. The most serious riskwas that the German Supreme Court might find that theTreaty could not be ratified without a two-thirds majority in theWest German Parliament, for the Federal Government could notcommand such a majority. The French Government continued tovacillate, but it was unlikely that they would finally abandon theirown conception of a European Defence Community and he hopedthey would secure the ratification of the Treaty towards the end ofthe year. We must be prepared for a period of tension in ourrelations with the Soviet Government. Our sharp reaction to Sovietpressure in Berlin would make them cautious about further hostilemoves; but they would lose no opportunity of obstructing the final conclusion of the Treaty. .        ...\   The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Foreign Secretary.Royal Visit toAustralia andNew Zealand.&apos; (previous reference:C.C. (52) 54th:Conclusions,Minute 1.)Germany.(PreyiousReference:GC. (52) 58thConclusions,Minute 8.)Korea.Armistice Talks(previous reference: -GC. (52) 56thConclusions, ?:Minute, 6,)4. The Foreign Secretary said that the Indian Government hadbeen taking informal soundings in Peking with a view to breaking the deadlock in the negotiations for an armistice in Korea; and the IndianHigh Commissioner in London had communicated to him alternative proposals for the solution of the prisoners of war problem which theChinese Communist Government might be willing to accept. Thefirst alternative, which the Chinese would prefer; was that 110,000prisoners of war (20,000 Chinese and 90,000 North Koreans) should42454-1    &apos; v b2
Persia. 5. ,TheForeign Secretary said that economic conditions in Persia(Previous        were now worsening and it seemed likely that Dr. Musaddiq would reference: &apos;    fall within a few weeks.  He wished, therefore, to be ready with freshC.C. (52) 31st : proposals for a solution of the Persian oil problem, which could be conclusions,    put to a new Persian Government. He would submit these proposalsjvlinute 6.)     - to the Cabinet in the following week. It was unfortunate that in these. &apos;    more favourable circumstances the awkward problem of the RoseMary should have arisen. This ship had sailed from Bandar Mahsuri with a cargo of crude oil which the Persian Government were not, legally entitled to sell.  Arrangements had been made to take legal, - action to prevent its disposal, but the success of these arrangementsdepended to some-extent on the ship&apos;s first port of call.  It would be- much easier to take the.necessary action in Aden than in Egypt.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Foreign Secretary.Trade between     ,   6.   Mr. Menzies said that he had discussed at length with thethe United       President of the Board of Trade the difficulties which Australia^Kingdom and   import restrictions had caused to traders in the United Kingdom.Australia.       The area in which any accommodation could be extended to United(Previous        Kingdom traders was necessarily limited, since the purpose of the reference:      Australian import restrictions was to preserve Australia^ financialG.C. (52) 59th   reserves.  He had, however,&apos;agreed with the President of the BoardConclusions,    of Trade that the Australian import quotas must be first used for minute 8.)       existing contracts before they were applied to new orders from else-where. .He had further agreed that cases involving special hardship,particularly the exclusion, of goods made specially for the Australianmarket, should be dealt with sympathetically, though this might mean, , exceeding the target limit of Australian imports by a few millionpounds.   He had been unable to suggest any special regulations to ease the difficulties of the textile and pottery industries in the United&apos;. . -Kingdom: Australia herself had a textile industry which was at.   ; :&apos;   present, under-employed: He did not, however, wish to shut the door&apos; \ finally upon the possibility of finding some method of alleviation and... &apos;he would be prepared to discuss this further on his return to -... - : Canberra..&apos; ; .        The President of the Board of Trade said that both he and.Mr.Menzies were equally concerned that present circumstances made itimpossible,for them.to arrange more substantial measures of mutualbe returned and that the remaining prisoners in the hands of theUnited Nations Forces might go where they pleased. This we couldnot accept, since it would be inconsistent with the principle which wehad affirmed. Moreover, we only had about 20,000 Chinese prisoners in our hands, and many of them were reluctant to be repatriated. Thesecond alternative was that the United Nations High Command should accept the principle that all prisoners of war from both sides shouldbe repatriated; but that those prisoners who showed any disinclina-tion to go home should be brought to Panmanjom and screened by four neutral States and the National Red Cross organisations of the belligerent Powers on both sides. The Chinese Government wouldbe prepared to abide by the results of this screening. The four neutralStates concerned were Poland, Czechoslovakia, Sweden and Switzer-land. He thought that the second alternative merited further examina-tion and he proposed to report it to the United States Governmentand obtain their views.The Cabinet-..      &apos; - Took note with approval of the course which the Foreign. Secretary proposed to follow.
Meetings of 7.   In connection with the discussion recorded in the precedingCommonwealth Minute The, Commonwealth Secretary referred to the emphasis which ministers.       Mr. Menzies had laid during his visit, both in public speeches and(Previous        in his private talks with United Kingdom Ministers, on the need for reference:      a united Commonwealth policy on economic and commercial matters.CC. (52) 59th 1 He had been considering, with some of his colleagues, what arrange-Conclusions,     ments could be made for holding a Commonwealth Meeting on these minute 9.)       subjects.   Such a Meeting could not be successful unless full prepara--       &apos;      tion for it had been made in advance; and the first need was for all commonwealth Governments to define their own attitude towards this problem.  In the United-Kingdom preparations to this end hadalready been begun,, but these were not likely to be completed muchbefore the end of the year. He therefore proposed that all Common-wealth Governments should now be asked to agree that the Meetingof Commonwealth Finance Ministers which was to be held in london in January should be expanded to cover commercial and economic. policy and should be attended, not by Finance Ministers only, but.       . also by Ministers . responsible for commerce and industry.   Theprovisional conclusions reached at this Meeting could be reviewed by Governments immediately thereafter, so that any outstandingdifferences of view could be reconciled at the Meeting of Common-wealth Prime Ministers which was.tO&apos;be held in June at the timeof Her Majesty&apos;s Coronation.Mr. Menzies said that in his view it was of first importance thatthe Commonwealth countries should concert their economic and commercial policies.. For this purpose a Commonwealth meeting should be held at the earliest practicable moment. He fully agreedthat, if this was to be successful, an immense amount of preparatory work would have to be done by officials and experts; and he urgedthat this should be put in hand without delay.In discussion it was suggested that the time-table proposed bythe Commonwealth Secretary would not produce a sufficiently earlyresult. The Conservative Party had undertaken, at the time of the,. Election,&apos;that as one of their first acts in office they would convene a Commonwealth Economic Conference; and, as the economic situa-tion was now seen to be even more serious than it had then appeared,they would find it difficult to defend delaying effective decisions on42454-1benefit. He was specially glad to hear that Mr. Menzies was pre-pared to give further thought to the question of textiles on his returnto Australia; and he would not press him to say more on that subject at present. He.hoped that, when the. time came for Australia to relax the quota system, Mr. Menzies would consider giving the firstbenefits of this relaxation to the United Kingdom, especially as any goods bought outside the sterling area had to be paid for in dollarsor gold.     &apos;Mr. Menzies said that he would much prefer that no reference should be made in public statements to the possibility of discrimina-tioh or preference in favour of the United Kingdom. These termsgave rise to misapprehension and created difficulties with othercountries. Australia had large trade balances with european countries and he must take these into account in settling the pattern of Australian trade. He recognised the force of the argument thatgoods from the non-sterling area had to be paid for in dollars or goldbut he would prefer not to make any promises in advance aboutAustralian policy with regard to the release of quotas. He wouldcertainly deal sympathetically with United Kingdom claims when thetime came.The Cabinet-     ; &apos;Took note of these statements by Mr. Menzies and thePresident of the Board of Trade.
-V    \ v . 164these problems until the middle&apos; of 1953. It was also suggested thatthe matter was one of such importance that it ought to be discussed at a Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers. Would it bepossible to hold such a meeting in November 1952?Mr, Menzies said that, in his recent discussions with the Presidentof the Board of Trade, he had been impressed by the political difficulties which attended the making of relatively minor concessions in commercial transactions between one Commonwealth country andanother; and he believed that the only way to overcome theseobstacles was to lift the discussion to higher levels at which it would attract the attention of a wider public with more general interests.This strengthened his conviction that from the political point of view,both in Australia and in the United Kingdom, there was everythingto be said for initiating Commonwealth consultations on the widerissues of economic and commercial policy and for holding a meetingon these subjects at the earliest possible moment.   He shared the: view that it would be of special political importance to hold thismeeting before the end of 1952: If it could be held in the second part of November, he would undertake that Australia would be effectively represented^ At the same time he recognised the needfor proper preparation for the meeting; and he suggested that a body of senior officials should-be appointed, drawn from as many&quot; as possible of the. Commonwealth countries, and charged with theduty of undertaking all the necessary preparations and carrying dis-cussions to such a point that, when Ministers met in November, theywould have a reasonable opportunity of reaching fruitful decisions.If the United Kingdom Government were willing to put forward proposals on these lines, they could, count on his firm support; hewould.in particular commend them to the Prime Minister of NewZealand and to the Prime Minister of Canada, whom he would beseeing on his return journey to Australia.The Cabinet- .: (1) Agreed that every effort should be made.to arrange for aMeeting of Commonwealth Ministers to be held in london in the second half of November 1952, to discuss meansof concerting the economic, financial and commercialpolicies of Commonwealth countries; and that at this&apos;Meeting Commonwealth countries should be represented,wherever possible, by Prime Ministers.(2) Agreed that preparations for this Meeting should be under-taken by a body of senior officials drawn from as many.. - - of the Commonwealth countries as were willing to secondofficials for this purpose.(3) Invited the Commonwealth Secretary to commend these pro-, posals to the favourable attention of other commonwealth governments; and agreed that no announcement shouldbe made until the views of all the other commonwealth governments had been ascertained.Supply o    i 8.   The Minister of Supply said that Mr. Menzies had given himDefence a list of the defence equipment which Australia needed, divided intoEquipment to   mobilisation equipment and equipment for stockpiling.   He had con-Australia,        centrated his attention on the mobilisation equipment, which was themore urgent&apos;need: the stockpiling requirements could.be considered.      ./. later.   The Australian Army requirements amounted to a figure of; &apos;  A. 73 million spread over a period of about three years and included/ :   . 190Centurion tanks.   There might be some difficulty in supplying a: , . \  .....few of these requirements; but, generally speaking, the equipment. asked for could be made available from current production and the. ,   .    . Australian orders, could be phased in with the United Kingdom:   rearmament. programme.  The total requirements of the Royal
Australian Navy amounted to  A. 87 million spread over a ratherlonger period, and these were being examined by the Admiralty.   The1 total Air Force requirements amounted to  A. 89 million, likewisespread over a period of three years. Of the demand on the UnitedKingdom, the 89 Canberras required could be supplied, and it wouldbe much less expensive to obtain them from the United Kingdom than- ;&apos; to increase Canberra production in Australia. The 34 Prince trainerscould probably be supplied also; but there might be some difficultyr-not, he hoped, insurmountable in the supply of Gannets, which were much needed by the Royal Navy.   However, this was being examined.Turning to Australia^ proposed purchases of aircraft from theUnited States, the Minister of Supply said that Australia were askingi    for  170 Sabres, for half of which engines would be manu-, factured in Australia, at a cost of  A. 23, million. The Sabrewas &quot;already obsolescent. - He wondered if Mr. Menzies. would consider the possibility of substituting an order from the UnitedKingdom for Hunters and Swifts, if these could be made available.These were better aircraft and less expensive. Similarly, it might bepossible for Australia to substitute the Blackburn Freighter for theAmerican. transport aircraft Cl 19, and the Shackleton for theAmerican naval reconnaissance aircraft Neptune.&apos;. Mr. Menzies said that he would examine these suggestions on his return to Australia. The list of equipment which he had presentedcould be regarded as firm requirements. He had to consider the needfor retaining some industrial capacity for aircraft production in Aus-tralia and particularly for the production of aircraft engines.Mr. Menzies said that his discussions in London had resulted inagreement on two very important principles. The first.was that&apos; increased Australian food production was to be regarded as of a highorder of priority; both in peace and in war. To help in planningAustralia^ food production, the Minister of Food had agreed to lethim have a forecast of United Kingdom food requirements. Theacceptance of this principle would in no way limit Australian targets for the raising and training of armed forces in war; but it would limit the extent to which Australia committed resources to the manufactureof defence equipment. The second principle was that, in return,Australia should be able to look to the United Kingdom to meet herreasonable requirements for defence equipment; and that the UnitedKingdom, should incorporate these in their own defence production,.   programme, so that Australia would receive her due proportion of-equipment as it became available.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the statements by Mr. Menziesand the Minister of Supply.Central african federation.(previous reference erence:C.C. (52) 59thConclusions,Minute 2.)9. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Com-commonwealth.Secretary.and the Colonial Secretary (C. (52) 193) covering a draft White Paper on the Federal Scheme for Southern Rhodesia,Northern Rhodesia and Nyasaland, to be published on 18th June, anda draft of a statement to be made in both Houses of Parliament on thesame day. .    .The Colonial Secretary drew attention to three particular points in the Scheme. The proposal&quot; to include in the Federal Cabinet a specially appointed Minister for. African interests had been abandonedas constitutionally unsound, and in its place the African Affairs board had been strengthened. Provision ,had been made by which, if any objection was raised to any proposed constitutional amendment, either by the. African Affairs Board or by a Territorial Legislature, theamendment could only be made by Order in Council, and the draft order would be laid before the United Kingdom Parliament for fortydays before it was made.   In Part II of the White Paper the Federal
PUBLIC RECORD office group.Class ..CLOSEDUNTILDocument^ ^at the time of the transfer of the class to the P.R.O.: *delete as necessary.2017(h) 001767 11,800 6/72 a.g. 3640/4
n&apos; - :j  - .166    &apos;.   q,   . legislative powers had beer; defined in two lists-the first list being- confined to matters on which the Federal Legislature alone would be.    .    empowered to rriake ,laws, arid the second to matters on which.   ,    both the Federal Legislature and the Territorial Legislatures wouldbe empowered to make laws, with Federal law prevailing in cases of-inconsistency, Further investigations into the financial, administra-tive and* judicial problems of federation would be made during the summer and, when these investigations were completed, it was. intended to. hold a; further conference in Africa later in theyear to -give \ final  shape to the Scheme.   It would then be- submitted to a referendum of the Southern Rhodesian electorateand &apos; to the &quot;legislatures of Northern Rhodesia and  Nyasalandfor ratification.   The sacrifice of a certain measure of freedom&apos; which federation would impose upon Southern Rhodesia madeits acceptance by that country uncertain; but it was hoped that,.&apos;    - . - -.given the full support of the Southern Rhpdesian Prime Minister, the referendum would be favourable. -&quot;/The Cabinet-        --. 7  &apos;        Authorised the Colonial Secretary to arrange for the White&apos;.&apos; Paper annexed to C. (52) 193 to be presented to Parliament- on 18th June; and agreed that statements should be made&apos; on that day, in both Houses of Parliament, in the terms ofthe draft in Appendix II of C. (52) 193.Recognition of 11. The Postmaster-General said that he wished to make a state-Post Office ment in Parliament on the following day about the report of the Corn-Staff &apos; .mittee, under, the Chairmanship of Lord Terrington, which hadAssociations,&apos;! considered the question of recognition of the various staff associations- &apos;    in the Post Office,  The Committee&apos;s recommendations would have
Conclusion of 12.   Mr. Menzies said that, before he left London that afternoon,Mr. Menzies&apos; he proposed to issue, primarily for publication in the Australian Press,Visit two statements on the results of his. discussions in London.  One ofthese would be devoted to his discussions about the impact ofAustralia^ import restrictions upon United Kingdom industries:the other would be concerned with his more general talks on international affairs and supply questions including, particularly,Australia^ food production and the supply of defence equipment from the United Kingdom to Australia.The Prime Minister said that these statements would be published in the London newspapers on the following day. It would thereforebe necessary for him to make a corresponding, though shorter, state-ment on behalf of the United Kingdom Government, which couldbe published at the same time. He proposed to make this statement in the House of Commons that afternoon.. He read to. the cabinet a draft of the statement which he proposed to make. The Common-wealth Secretary would simultaneously make a corresponding state-ment in the House, of Lords.     - v:.    -      The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the terms of the statement to\ !;      be made on behalf of the United Kingdom Government&quot;      &apos;   i   regarding the discussions held during Mr. Menzies&apos; visit.The Prime Minister said that he and his colleagues were very glad to, have had the opportunity, during the past three weeks, of holdingpersonal consultations with Mr. Menzies.   They greatly appreciated&apos; ..   his wise counsel and the stimulating contributions which he had made.to their discussions. They looked forward with pleasure to his returni for further consultations at a relatively early date.the effect of requiring the Minister to satisfy himself about the com-competence of the various associations to represent staff interests: this he regarded as a matter to be settled by the staff, and not determinedby the employer, and he was not prepared to accept the Committee&apos;sreport. He therefore proposed to defer taking a final decision forsome months, and during that time he would do everything he could to induce the parties to settle the differences between them. TheParliamentary situation was difficult; for the Conservative Party^when in opposition, had strongly advocated the recognition of someof the smaller associations. He believed that his proposal was thebest way of overcoming the Parliamentary difficulty: it had thesupport of the Minister of Labour, and had been approved by theHome Affairs Committee on 16th May. At that time he had been-intending to announce that his final decision would be delayed fortwelve months, but he had since ascertained that a delay of six months would be more acceptable to Government supporters in the Houseof Commons.In discussion some preference was expressed for a longer periodof delay than six months; and The Prime Minister said that theCabinet should have an opportunity of discussing this question fur-ther when they had seen the draft of the Parliamentary statement which the Postmaster-General wished to make. If in the meantime the Postmaster-General were pressed for an early statement of his policy, he might promise that a statement would be made in Parlia-ment on 24th June.The Cabinet- &apos;Agreed to resume their discussion of this question at alater meeting; and invited the Postmaster-General to circu-late a draft of the statement which he wished to make in.  Parliament.
Mr. Menzies said that the discussions which he had held inLondon had been most valuable-more valuable perhaps in their con-firmation of a common, understanding on fundamental issues than intheir immediate results. He greatly appreciated the sympatheticunderstanding of Australia^ difficulties which United kingdom ministers had shown throughout his discussions.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,.    17th June, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
