<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/25/0 images: 104-108</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July 1952SECRETCopy No.C.C. (52)66th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W, 1,on Tuesday, 8th July, 1952, at 11 -30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Alexander of tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Most Hon. the Marquess of Salis-bury, Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The  Right   Hon.   lord paymaster-General.Cher well.The following were also present:The Right. Hon. Viscount Swinton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Minister of Transport and civil Aviation (Item 1).The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 1-2).Sir Reginald Manningham-Buller,Q.C., M.P., Solicitor-General (items-2).The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of State (Items 3-5).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.
contents minute no.                                      Subject page 1      Legislative Programme         ............... 132     Iron and Steel Industry      ............... 13Draft White Paper.3      Economic Policy............      ;..      ... 144     Employment    ..................... 145      Housing Policy         ...      ......      ...      ...      ... .14
Legislative 1.   The Prime Minister said that he had held further discussionsProgramme.     with some of his colleagues about the Parliamentary time-table, with(Previous        particular reference to the Transport Bill and the Iron and Steel Bill;Reference:      As a result he now proposed that the Transport Bill, although itCC. (52) 53rd   would be presented that day, should not be given a Second ReadingConclusions,     before the summer recess; and, similarly, that the Government should minute 4.)       not find time for a debate before the recess on the White Paper onthe Iron and Steel Industry.   This should make it possible to begin the summer recess on 1st August.   Parliament would then reassembleon 14th October and would be prorogued on 31st October.   Subjectto The Queen&apos;s pleasure a new Session would be opened on 4thNovember: both the Transport Bill and the Iron and Steel bill would be introduced early in the new Session and would proceed con-currently.   Allowing for a Christmas recess from 19th December to20th January, it was estimated that the Transport Bill could pass into law by the middle of March and the Iron and Steel Bill by theend of April.   This revised time-table would enable the Iron andSteel Bill to be passed into law more than two months earlier than had hitherto been contemplated, at the expense of delaying for onlya few weeks the enactment of the Transport Bill.The Minister of Transport said that he greatly preferred thisrevised time-table. If the Second Reading of the Transport Bill weredelayed, as now proposed, there was some prospect of narrowing the differences between the Government and the Opposition; and the disadvantages of a long interval between the Second Reading and theCommittee Stage would also be avoided. There was perhaps some risk that the Opposition might insist on debating the annual report ofthe British Transport Commission, which was to be published on11th July; but they might well be persuaded to defer dealing with that report until the general debate on the nationalised industries, whichwas to be held after the summer recess.The Minister of Supply said that he also favoured this, revisedplan, which would advance substantially the date by which the Ironand Steel Bill would become law. In the changed circumstances hewould prefer that his White Paper should not be debated before the summer recess: for, if it were debated immediately after publication,the Opposition were more likely to take up an attitude of uncom-promising hostility to its proposals. He recognised that a debate could not be prevented if the Opposition were willing to use a SupplyDay for the purpose, but this might be avoided by postponing publi-cation until nearer the date on which Parliament was to be adjourned for the recess.In further discussion the Cabinet were informed that two-daydebates were to be held in the House of Commons before the recesson Germany and on the economic situation. It was at present pro-posed that the first of these should be held on 28th and 29th July, andthe second on 30th and 31st July.The Cabinet Approved the revised Parliamentary time-table put forward by the Prime Minister; and authorised the Lord Privy Sealand the Chief Whip to discuss it in confidence with Oppo-sition leaders in the House of Commons.Iron and SteelIndustry.Draft white paper.(previous reference:CC. (52) 65thConclusions,Minute 3.)2. The Cabinet had before them a note by the Minister ofSupply (C. (52) 227) covering a revised draft of the White Paperembodying the Governments proposals-for the future of the iron andsteel industry.The Cabinet Authorised the Minister of Supply to present the white paper, in the terms of the draft annexed to C. (52) 227, on a date to be determined in consultation with the Lord privy seal.
Economic 3.   The Cabinet discussed the progress of the enquiries whichPolicy. they had set on foot at their meeting on 29th May with a view to(Previous        redressing the adverse balance of payments.   Progress had alreadyReference:       been made in assessing the adjustments which might be made in theC.C. (52) 57th   defence programme, in the light of a new strategic appreciation pre-Conclusions,     pared by the Chiefs of Staff; in devising means by which a largerMinute 6.)       proportion of the capital investment programme could be devoted toexpanding the capacity of productive industry; and in selectingpossible means of securing further reductions in imports and expan-sion of exports.   Further meetings of Ministers were being heldduring the course of the week in order that the studies initiatedunder these three heads might be carried to a point at which specific recommendations could be submitted for final decision by theCabinet in the following week.The. Prime Minister said that during the next two weeks theCabinet must be ready to devote to the consideration of these recom-mendations such time as was necessary in order to enable a statementof Government policy to be formulated for use in the debate on theeconomic situation which was to take place in the House of commons on 30th and 31st July.The Cabinet-Agreed to resume their discussion of the economic situation at meetings to be held in the following week.Employment. 4.   The Minister of Labour said that figures for the month(Previous ending 16th June showed a reduction of over 27,000 in the number ofReference: unemployed, including a small reduction in the textile industry.C.C. (52) 58th This seasonal improvement had come rather later than usual, but he conclusions, hoped that the next monthly figures would. show a furtherMinute 4.)       improvement.The Cabinet were also informed that recent discussions had resulted in the placing of substantial textile contracts which shouldalleviate the serious unemployment in Northern Ireland. Employ-ment prospects in the textile industry generally seemed to be slighty more favourable now that accumulated stocks were being reduced.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.Housing Policy.(previous reference:C.C.(52)20thConclusions,Minute 5.)5. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the lord president (C. (52) 207) and the Minister of Housing (C. (52) 216) onmeans of increasing the proportion of houses built for occupation byowner-occupiers.The Lord President said that the Government ought soon to make a start in applying the principle of &quot; a property-owningdemocracy.&quot; He did not ask for any increase of the total capital investment in housing; but he suggested that within that total fewerhouses should be built for letting by local authorities. Instead ofpersisting in the Socialist policy of herding people into heavily-,subsidised Council houses, could not the Government now remove the restriction on the building of private houses of up to, say,1,000 sq. ft. and pay a subsidy to a person buying a single house whichhe proposed to occupy himself, subject to control over resale or lettingfor a period of years?The Minister of Housing said that he would be glad to take partin a detailed examination Of the Lord Presidents proposal, with
which he was generally in sympathy. The deterrents to private house-building were certainly formidable. While the tenant of a council house continued to be subsidised to the extent of some  769,the recent rise in interest rates had loaded the dice still more heavilyagainst the prospective owner-occupier. There were various possible ways of assisting him, apart from direct subsidy, and by the time these had been examined the amount of timber and steel which would beavailable for next year&apos;s housing programme would be known.In discussion reference was made to the unfortunate effect of the rent Restrictions Acts on the maintenance of houses within their scope and of the increasing pressure by Government supporters forsome alteration of the existing law on this subject. The Minister of housing said that the marked discrepancy between the rents of council houses and of rent-restricted nouses was tending to create an atmosphere more favourable to a solution of this problem.The Cabinet Invited the Lord President to arrange for the Committee on development Charges and Compensation to consider theproposals in C. (52) 207 and 216.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,8th July, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
