<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/25/0 images: 219-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is the property of her britannic  MA jest ys   governmentPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1952SECRETCC. (52)83rd ConclusionsCABINETCopy No.42CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Wednesday, 1st October, 1952, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Winston S. Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. P.. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl Alexander of tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P,, Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Woolton, lord president of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Lord Leathers, Secre-tary of State for Co-ordination ofTransport, Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Lord Cherwell,Paymaster-General.The Right Hon. Viscount SwintonChancellor of the Duchy of lancaster the following were also present:The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.Minister of Supply (Items 3-5).The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 7).Sir   Reginald   Manningham-Buller,Q.C.,      M.P.,      Solicitor-General(Items 1-6).Secretariat :Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.43008-2b
contents minute no. subject      Public Expenditure2     War Criminals............Alfried Krupp.3      Town and Country Planning Act, 19474      Rent Restriction Acts..........5      Departmental Advisory CouncilsMembership of Communists.6     The Coronation ...      ..:      ...      ...7     Petrol
PobMc 1.   The Prime Minister drew attention to the large excess ofExpenditure. expenditure over revenue in the out-turn of the Exchequer accounts for the first half of the financial year. Was this an unexpectedmovement, and were there balancing factors which would come intooperation in the second half of the year?The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had been watchingthis development closely.  He was particularly disturbed at the large increase in expenditure by local authorities.  It was now clear thatit would be one of the Governments main preoccupations over the; coming months to restrict public expenditure.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Chancellor of theExchequer.War Criminals. 2. The Prime Minister said that considerable public interestAlfried Krupp. was being shown in the fact that Alfried Krupp von Bohlen undHalbach had not only been released from imprisonment as a warcriminal but was now to receive substantial compensation for theloss of his industrial interests. This seemed: likely to be the subjectof comment in Parliament after the recess.The Foreign Secretary said that Krupp had been tried by a united States military court, and it was the United States HighCommissioner in Germany who had decided, as an act of clemency,to remit the remainder of his sentence as a war criminal and to revoke(-.. the order for the confiscation of his property. His industrial interestshad been sequestrated by the Allies in pursuance of their policy of breaking up the largest industrial organisations in Western germany on which the power of the Nazis had been partly founded. he knew of no grounds on which compensation could have been with-held from Krupp.   Though the amount of the compensation wasi , &apos;  large, some of-it would probably go to pensioners of the Krupporganisation, and the remainder might be subject to Federal taxation.In any event no criticism could properly be directed on this accountv.:&apos;:&apos;;.;-. against the present Government of the United Kingdom.   ForKrupp&apos;s imprisonment had been terminated by the United states authorities; and the payment of compensation was due under a lawapproved by the United States and French Governments and theprevious Government Of the United Kingdom. He would take asuitable opportunity of making a public statement on this point.&apos; The Cabinet-\ .&quot;: &quot;   . Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Town andCountryPlanningAct, 1947.(previous reference:C.C. (52) 78thConclusions,Minute 8.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Housing and Local Government (C. (52) 304) covering a provisional draft of a White Paper . explaining his proposals for amending the financial provisions of the Town, and Country planning act, 1947, and a memorandum by the Commonwealth Secretary(C. (52) 312) outlining his objections to certain features of theseproposals.In discussion attention was directed mainly to two aspects ofthe problem: - \&apos;      &apos; - &apos; &apos; &apos; &apos; *,   (a) The Limited Compensation scheme the Commonwealth Secretary said that he would find itdifficult to defend a system under which owners of land who were,. refused planning permission for developing it or whose land wascompulsorily purchased by a local authority received for all time43008-2 b 2
compensation for &quot; development value &quot; at the 1947 rate while otherowners could obtain the current market value for their land. this seemed to him to be inequitable and inconsistent with conservative party principles. Many small land-owners were involved and the conception of a property-owning democracy would be underminedif justice were denied to them. With the passage of time and apossible further decline in the value of money the inequity of thisfeature of the scheme might well increase. He therefore favouredarrangements under which an owner who sold his land would receivefor it whatever might be a fair price at the time, whether the purchaser was a public authority or another private individual, andan owner who was refused planning permission to develop his land would receive fair compensation. It was an illusion to suppose that,in transactions for the sale of land, public authorities were alwaysreasonable and private individuals always extortionate. When an owner of land stood out for an unduly high price from a public bodythe matter could be referred to arbitration by an independent bodyof experts.The Minister of Housing said that he recognised that his proposals involved the differential treatment of owners of land towhich the Commonwealth Secretary took exception. It had to beremembered, however, that owners who were refused planning per-mission or whose land was compulsorily purchased would underthese proposals receive 100 per cent, of the 1947 &quot; development value &quot; of their land, as compared with the 80 per cent, which theywere at present expecting to receive. The Commonwealth Secre-tary&apos;s views did not, moreover, appear to take sufficient account ofthe fundamental change in the land-owner&apos;s position resulting fromthe passing of successive Town and Country Planning Acts the underlying assumption of which was that tin owner Was no longer free to do what he liked with his land without regard to the public interest.Nor was it reasonable that a public authority should have to pay forland which it might require for public purposes the current market value which might be due at least in part to public development and provision of services. His proposals must be considered as a whole.Many land-owners would benefit from the abolition of development charge: some would gain from the freedom to sell their land at thecurrent market value; others would receive compensation for&quot; development rights &quot; at 100 per cent, of their 1947 value.&apos; &apos;     &apos; &apos; . &apos;The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he shared the viewof the Commonwealth Secretary on the inequity of this feature ofthe limited compensation scheme but did not agree with him in thinking that the remedy lay in adopting current market value as thebasis for both compensation and compulsory purchase. That wouldbe likely to involve excessive charges on the Exchequer. He would prefer to preserve equity by retaining development charge at a reduced rate.(b) Development charge the Minister of Housing said that the scales were heavilyweighted against the private developer, particularly the house-builder.Thus, interest rates were high, there was a large programme ofsubsidised building and a large pool of houses available at frozenrents. If, in addition, the private developer had to pay development charge, there was little prospect that house-building by private enter-prise would be resumed on any substantial scale. Hence his anxiety to see the charge abolished.Considerable support was expressed for the view that developrment charge ought to be abolished. It was feared that a reductionof the charge would not act as a sufficient stimulus to development,and there would also be a risk that a later Government would restore the rate of charge to 100 per cent.
Rent 4.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theRestriction Minister of Housing and Local Government (C. (52) 299) outliningActs. a short-term policy of relaxing rent control for the purpose of(Previous encouraging the owners of house property to carry out essentialReference:       repairs.C.C. (52) 78th jne prfme Minister said that any legislation amending the RentConclusions, Restriction Acts must be so designed as to bring no financial benefitMmute 9.) tQ ianciiorcjs - ft must be made evident that the Government had noother purpose than to increase the number of habitable houses.The Labour Party, in a recent pamphlet, had admitted that the controlled rent of some houses did not provide an income sufficientto maintain the property in a proper state of repair, and that tenantswould benefit by some amendment of the Acts which would enable a proportion of the rent to be spent on the improvement and main-tenance of the dwelling. There might therefore be a . politicalopportunity in the coming session to pass amending legislation whichcould fairly be represented as designed to increase the national stock of habitable houses.The Minister of Housing said that the scheme outlined in his memorandum had been framed with this in view. It would not bringany additional profit to the owners of house property. It would,however, serve the national interest by helping to prevent existing houses from falling further into disrepair.In discussion there was general support for the scheme outlined in C. (52) 299. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he accepted the scheme in principle, and he undertook to communicate the Home Secretary^ said that he had for long held the view expressed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer that the right meansof preserving equity as between one owner of land and another wasto secure a contribution from the land-owner who made a profitrather than to enable all owners to obtain the current market value.He had been assured, however, that there was no satisfactory wayof achieving this object without seriously impeding development. Insupport of this view it was argued that development charge was paid in practice, not by the owner who sold his land at a profit, butby the developer, who in many cases had already paid for the landmore than its existing use value and therefore in effect paid for&quot; development right &quot; twice over. Could not a form of tax be devised which would be paid by the owner of land out of the unearnedincrement which he might obtain from its sale?The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that, while it might bepossible to devise a suitable tax for this purpose^ it would set a dangerous precedent for a capital gains tax in respect of transactions in securities. Some Ministers thought that there should be nodifficulty in preventing what might be done in respect of land inthe context of the Town and Country Planning Acts from being used as a precedent for action in respect of securities or other formsof property. A more serious objection to replacing development charge by some form of tax on land sales was that in practice thelatter would almost certainly act as no less an impediment to develop-ment than development charge, since any tax, wherever it was imposed, tended to be passed on to the ultimate consumer.The Cabinet Invited the Prime Minister to arrange for the issues raised inC. (52) 304 and 312 to be further considered by a smallerbody of Ministers in the light of the Cabinefs discussion andwith the object of formulating the broad principles on which any settlement should be based.
to.the Minister of Housing certain comments on technical aspects ofthe scheme connected with income tax and assessment for rates. he observed, however, in the final paragraph of the Minister&apos;s paper,a reference to slum-clearance: he could not agree that any new programme of slum-clearance should be added to the existinghousing programme.The Cabinet-(1) Approved in principle the scheme outlined in C. (52) 299 for amending the Rent Restriction Acts.(2) Invited the Minister of Housing to work out this scheme in further detail, in consultation with other Ministers con-cerned, and to proceed with the preparation of amending legislation.Departmental 5.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theAdvisory        Minister of Supply (C. (52) 311) drawing attention to a ParliamentaryCouncils.        Question about his action in appointing a Communist as a memberMembership of of one of the advisory bodies attached to his Department.   the communists.    Minister explained in his memorandum that the members of this(Previous        body were nominated, for appointment by him, by the appropriateReference:      employers&apos; associations and trade unions; and that, if he had rejectedCC. (52) 30th   this particular nomination, the union concerned would probablyConclusions,    nave declined to put forward any alternative.   The individual in minute 9.) &apos;    question had served on this and another advisory body for manyyears, and no secret information was made available to either of the bodies of Which he was a member. He proposed to defend his actionon these grounds in reply to the Parliamentary Question.The Minister of Labour said that the arguments which he had advanced, in the Cabinefs discussion on 13th March, 1952, againstthe appointment of a Communist to an arbitration board had no application to the appointment of Communists to DepartmentalAdvisory Councils. The Chancellor of the Exchequer endorsed thisview.The Cabinet-: Approved the substance of the reply which the Ministeijof Supply was proposing to give to a parliamentary question about the appointment of a Communist to one ofthe advisory bodies attached to his Department. ,the coronation.(previous reference:CC (52) 61stConclusions,Minute 3.)6. The Prime Minister recalled that on 1,9th June the cabinet had agreed that no Service Reviews should be held in connectionwith the Coronation in 1953. This decision had been taken on theassumption that heavy expenditure would be involved; but he had recently been informed that a Naval Review could be held withoutany additional cost beyond that of a firework display and the charter of a liner in which distinguished visitors could steam round the Fleet.He thought that the matter might be reconsidered on this basis:there need be no question of corresponding Coronation Reviews bythe other two Services.The Cabinet Invited the First Lord of the Admiralty to consider whetherarrangements could be made to hold a Naval Review at thetime of the Coronation without incurring special expendi-ture otherwise than on the two particular items mentioned by the Prime Minister.
Petrol. 7.   The Minister of Fuel and Power said that he and theChancellor of the Exchequer had agreed in principle that the war-time system of pooling all petrol supplies could now be discontinuedand that the oil companies could revert to the normal system of marketing their petrol under brand names. Although this changecould not be brought into operation until after Christmas, he had himself been anxious to announce the decision at once. TheChancellor of the Exchequer had, however, suggested that, in viewof the additional burden which this change would impose on our balance of payments, the announcement might be delayed until afterthe departure of the Commonwealth officials now meeting in london to prepare for the Commonwealth Economic Conference.After discussion the Cabinet agreed that the balance of advan-tage lay on the side of announcing this decision before the openingof the Conservative Party Conference in the following week.The Cabinet (1) Took note with approval of the decision to resume thepre-war system of marketing petrol in this country, and authorised the Minister of Fuel and Power to make anearly announcement of this decision.(2) Invited the Minister of Fuel and Power to arrange, in con-sultation with the Commonwealth Secretary, for other commonwealth Governments to be informed of thisdecision in advance of the public announcement.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,1st October, 1952.

</content>
</cab>
