<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/166/1 images: 5-14</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS government cp(72) 126 Copy No. Q6617 November, 1972CABINETREVIEW OF GOVERNMENT STRATEGYNote by the Prime minister attach a paper prepared by the Central Policy Review Staff as abasis for our discussion at No. 10 on 24 November.E. H.10 Downing Street,17 November, 1972.SECRET
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy No. 066MID-TERM STRATEGY: IS THE BALANCE RIGHT?By the Central Policy Review StaffI.   introduction.1 When the history of a Parliament comes to be written, hindsighttends to suggest three kinds of unfriendly questions about its record:First: &quot; How on earth did they manage not to see thata and b were going to be the next great problems, and leave usquite unprepared for them? &quot;Second: &quot; Granted they did c and d, but how could theyhave thought that was enough to get the results which they wanted? It should have been easy to see that things wouldn&apos;t &apos;tturn out like that.&quot;Third: &quot; Granted they did well on e and /, how did theyallow their programme to become so overbalanced that prettywell nothing was done about g and hi &quot;1.2 This paper attempts to guess the values of a to h in thesequestions. It makes suggestions for action which could be addedto the programme for this Parliament, and argues for a newmomentum to launch a programme for the next.1.3 The Government^ major achievement has been the passingof a programme of reforming legislation perhaps only equalled in two other Parliaments in this century. The framework of life in theUnited Kingdom has been radically altered in a number of fields.Britain has been taken into Europe and, with the help of the newflexible approach to exchange rates, committed firmly to a policyof growth; while the rules of the game are being rewritten in industrial relations, taxation, local government, rents, pensions and health administration. When to these is added the proposedrealignment of educational priorities, the fair trading reforms andthe increased resources directed to the social services and the arts,the record becomes a formidable one covering most of the areas ofgovernment.1.4 Some gaps remain. There are also areas where the business is clearly unfinished. We deal with these two categories later in thepaper. First, however, we suggest what could be the next big issues.
II.  ISSUES OF THE FUTUREFuture Issue 12.1 Tripartite Economic Management. The achievement oftripartite management remains of paramount importance; and everyeffort should be made to resume the Downing Street discussions,even during the Stage One freeze. We should therefore considernow the agenda for tripartite meetings of the future. The initialfocus will be the Stage Two prices and incomes controls, which willrequire some degree of consensus about how the national incomeshould be divided. To obtain this, it will be necessary to discusswider issues of economic management, including some aspects ofpublic expenditure, taxation and growth policy, as well as such nowfamiliar items as unemployment, redundancies and the lower paid.In the longer term an unavoidable agenda item will be the problemsof pay differentials and the relative position in society of differentoccupations.2.2 In addition, four background issues will be crucial to theGovernments tripartite strategy:(i) Parliaments prestige is low, and will fall further if majorpublic policy decisions are increasingly agreed inthe tripartite forum, as part of general economic bargains.There will be increasing concern about this processamong people who fear its implications for Parliamentarydemocracy.(ii) The TUC and CBI are not yet powerful enough to make itusual for their members to accept an undertaking madewith Government at the top level. Both CBI and TUCwill need higher calibre staff, more money, and betterorganisation. The Government should consider whatindirect pressure it can bring to bear to achieve this.(iii) Even if the CBI and TUC are strengthened, the Governmentwill still need to be adequately equipped to represent theinterests of those large sections of the country for whichneither the TUC nor the CBI can speak. The retailershave already been recognised as a case in point; and theinterests of other groups (consumers, professionals,farmers) must be given adequate consideration. TheDirector-General of Fair Trading may have a role toplay here.(iv) There is an increasing conflict between expectations and educational attainments on the one hand and the boringand disagreeable nature of so many industrial and clericaljobs on the other. Workers also increasingly resent their
lack of involvement in decisions about how their life is organised. A Government-led attack on these problems,which are underlying causes of much militancy, might bewell received at any rate by the non-militant Unions (or their members) and should therefore help in futuretripartite negotiations. The CPRS has begun an enquiry into this subject.Future Issue 22.3 Britain&apos;s role in the world. The long decline in British moralesince World War II has been associated with a series of shockdiscoveries that our power was less than we had thought or thatwe faced more retrenchment than we had expected. If confidence in our international role is now at last to be rebuilt, on Europeanfoundations, we must avoid classing ourselves too high and invitingdisillusion. Our national resources in the coming generation looklike being much the same size as, say, Italy&apos;s; and by the 1980s theymay not be much more than half those of France or FederalGermany.  This fact will bite in two main areas:(i) Defence. Retaining a major influence on European defence policy will increasingly mean spending more of our GNPon defence than our richer neighbours. Anti-militaristsentiment and strong demand for higher social expendi-ture will make this very difficult. But we must recognisethat, if we come down to the European average, we mayimpair the chance of securing an adequate level ofEuropean defence and in the longer term establishing a european defence identity.(ii) Prestige.  We are used to thinking of ourselves as one ofthe richest countries in the world. We have to shake offthe mental habits of great wealth, as we threw off the mental habits of empire. This need not mean the endof our influence, particularly on our near neighbours.But if we cling to prestige symbols which we cannot afford, such as apparent self-sufficiency in hightechnology fields, we could easily become a laughing-stock.Future Issue 32.4 Public Expenditure. Even without the latest commitmentsaccepted in the counter-inflation context, the average expected rateof increase in public expenditure in the coming 5-year PESC period is uncomfortably high. The rate of increase in the first half of theperiod is much higher than the average, and the slowing downthereafter is likely to require action to contain some very strong135917
pressures for more spending in the years immediately beyond thepresent PESC horizon. Local authorities&apos; expenditures, inparticular, are on a fast-rising trend. Any new claims on totalresources, e.g. for Nationalised Industry deficits or for defence, willmake an already dangerous situation worse. Once reasonably full employment is restored, spare resources will no longer be availableto finance large increases in public expenditure. Major objectives,such as progressive tax reduction and the Tax Credit scheme, will therefore be at risk. So should the objective of steadily lighteningthe tax burden remain valid?Future Issue 42.5 Pollution. The lesson of America and Japan is clear. the anti-pollution lobby must be expected to develop from a middle-classcoterie to a major national movement. The Royal Commission on environmental Pollution has pointed out that we are still withoutthe basis for a truly comprehensive policy, which would help us toavoid hastily devised crash programmes. This means settingpriorities for action and research; selecting appropriate methods ofcontrol; and deciding what should be done by national and what by international effort. If implementation is paid for by the polluter,large public expenditure need not be involved. But the call on national resources will be enormous; 2 per cent of GNP is suggestedin the United States.III.  UNFINISHED BUSINESSUnfinished business 13.1 Inflation. The fundamental approach represented by the tripartite talks offers the only reasonable hope of curbing inflation.Given present Union attitudes, the statutory policy is an inescapablepart of this. But there are no further fall-back positions if it fails.Serious breaches of the policy must therefore be resisted to theutmost by Government. For this resistance to be possible, theGovernment will need to retain the genuine public support which thepolicy now commands. Great care should be taken not to alienatesympathy by contradictory or confusing policies, or by unpopularpolicies which are not central. All new proposals for government action should be closely examined for their effects on the distributionof income.3.2 The controls over prices and incomes must be designed withclear knowledge of where the strengths and weaknesses of theGovernments position lie. If the weaknesses are so important as to endanger the programme, action should be urgently undertaken to
reduce the vulnerability of the economy to industrial disruption.Given that some major conflicts are almost certain, the crisismachinery which exists in Whitehall will need further improvementto ensure maximum strengthening of the Government^ hand. It willnot be enough if the Government is strong against weak opponentsbut weak against strong ones.Unfinished business 23.3 Industrial change. e.c. membership will speed up the existingdecline of weak industries as well as the growth of new ones. WithinEurope, individual countries will begin to specialise in particularfields and to make less attempt to maintain across-the-boardcapabilities. The eec&apos;s regional and industrial policies, if they getoff the ground, will help this process. Properly managed, changecan yield faster economic growth. But on the way, some big sectorswill hit crisis situations; we believe that the only hope for these willbe in Government leadership and joint planning with industry onthe French model.3.4 Integrated machinery will be needed to bring together thevarious organisations which are now available for this purposereferred to immediately above. The NEDO, the various NEDCs andthe Regional Planning Councils have been in existence for sometime. In addition, we now have the Industrial DevelopmentExecutive and a Manpower Services Commission is proposed. Sofar, help has been used mainly to ward off immediate unemploymentthreats. But in the longer term this policy of simply reacting toevents will be self-defeating and will easily absorb all the resources available. If we are to make real headway, more selectivity basedon an underlying strategy will be needed.3.5 A realistic estimate of the scale on which we can expect declinein the industries where decline is certain or highly probable mustbe made. The next step should be to calculate the effects of thesedeclines on different regions. Certain regions will suggest themselves as candidates for special selective aid as a result of these industrialchanges, and their needs will be on a scale only to be met by an integrated approach involving the direction of new growthinvestment via the Industrial Executive, the setting of geographicalpriorities for the work of the Manpower Commission and the drawing up of specific 5-year development plans by reorganised and strengthened Regional Planning Councils. This integrated approachwill need to use predictions about growth industries which, howeveruncertain, will be better than nothing, as well as predictions aboutdecline which are relatively easier to make.
3.6 Industrial change on this scale will alter patterns of employmentfundamentally. Government programmes for retraining andredundancy have been expanded; but do they yet match the scale of the problem? In addition to the demand for training derivedfrom structural change, one effect of improving the earnings of thelower paid will be to worsen the short-term situation by increasingshakeout in those lowest paid industries (such as textiles) which willnot gain much or quickly from increased growth. These industries should be identified now and given priority under the Secretary ofState for Employments plans for the expansion of retraining. TheSecretary of State&apos;s proposed co-ordination of the various specialredundancy schemes which now exist could be similarly directed.Unfinished business 33.7 Northern Ireland. Still the most dangerous issue of all. TheGovernments record since Direct Rule has commanded generalrespect; the Green Paper was well received. Despite the violenceof extremists on both wings, new constitutional arrangements can nowprobably be promulgated early in the New Year. If these arrangements get bi-partisan support at Westminster, and if it isclear that they are not meant to be the final answer, they mayhave a chance. But they will only get Catholic support if theydo genuinely break the old Protestant monopoly of power. If the protestant politicians reject this we may have to appeal over theirheads to their followers and make clear that membership of theUnited Kingdom means conforming to the instructions of theUnited Kingdom Parliament. The need for a fall-back position if our plans are rejected is heightened by the frail state of british public opinion. The urge to leave the Irish to their own violentdevices is already widespread and could easily become irresistible.Unfinished business 43.8 Europe. There is a real short-term danger in 1973-74 that public opinion will blame everything unpleasant on the e.c.. TheGovernment will need an explicit strategy to counter this backlash.Informed opinion may be partly appeased by devices to increase theanswerability at Westminster of our representatives in the Councilof Ministers, or by boosting the European Assembly. But thegeneral public is likely to appreciate positive British successes (e.g. on regional policy) and possibly a few well publicised British vetoes.
IV.   GAPSGap 14.1 Crimes of violence. Many ordinary people in the country feelthat the energy which has gone into some of the complex reformsof the last two years should now be matched by a similarlydetermined war on crime.  A three pronged attack is necessary:(i) Shortages   of   police   manpower   must   be   overcome,particularly in London. Differentials in pay and in conditions of service will be necessary.(ii) Changes in court procedures should also be considered. Themost promising might be:(a) abolition of the &quot; caution &quot; procedure on arrest;(b) removal of the present freedom of the accused torefuse to be questioned in court.Fears of too much police power should be allayed by improving the procedure for complaints against policemisconduct and arranging for serious cases to be investigated by civilian review boards.(iii) We continue to need more knowledge about the causes of crimes of violence.Gap 24.2 Devolution and the problem of the rates. The reform of the structure of local government leaves unanswered the fundamentalquestion: how much power should be devolved? The need for an answer is becoming acute, because without it there can be no lastingdecisions about local government finance. The proposed LocalGovernment Finance Bill commits us to rates as the main methodof local taxation for the time being. But Governments will inevitablycontinue to want to &quot; relieve the burden on the ratepayer &quot; with theresult that more and more central revenue will be administered bylocal authorities, who are not accountable directly to Parliament:Alternatives to this situation are:(a) another attempt to find a better local tax than rates whichimplies support for genuine local autonomy (implyingpower to vary standards and to obstruct centralgovernment);or(b) the removal from local government of responsibility forsome major programmes e.g. education or housing which implies abandonment of the commitment todevolution.The Report of the Crowther-Kilbrandon Commission on theConstitution is expected next year and is bound to stimulate public discussion of these issues.
Gap 34.3 Parliamentary Reform. The Governments ability to carry out its functions are constantly hindered by anachronistic and time-wasting procedures at Westminster which are not a necessaryconcomitant of democracy. No one can remember a time in whitehall when the log-jam in the legislative programme was not aserious obstacle to good government. Currently, serious damage to ministers&apos; programmes may result from the inescapable demands ofNorthern Ireland and the counter-inflation measures. The impetusfor reform will probably have to come from a formidable bodyindependent of Government. Thought should be given both togetting such a body established and to finding sufficiently ableleadership for it.Gap 44.4 Social policy. Ministers have agreed that they need to review the whole question of overall priorities and objectives. These willbe discussed by a Ministerial Strategy Group.V.   conclusion.1 The Government has so far given little thought to policyinitiatives beyond the present Parliament. This is now urgent; new policies requiring legislation or changes in expenditure prioritiesneed to be thought out now to be of any use in 1975-76.Generating this new momentum in the latter half of a parliament has been a task which has defeated most British Governments.Executive pressure on Ministers and officials is, of course, the reason.5.2 At the last Strategy meeting Ministers accepted a CPRSsuggestion that Ministerial Strategy Groups should be developed as one answer to this problem; and a start has since been made. we now suggest a way of facilitating strategic thought at official level;namely, the Task Force system, best known from Kennedy&apos;sWashington. The essence of a Task Force is that its members areassigned to it temporarily but full-time. They are detached from allnormal duties in their Departments. They are not formally requiredto clear their conclusions with their Departmental colleagues as theygo along. But they are chosen as being authoritative (which doesnot necessarily mean senior) members of their Departments, so thattheir results are likely to be realistic and practicable.5.3 Ministerial Strategy Groups and official Task Forces each offerways of developing the new momentum without which it will beimpossible to solve the problems we have identified (or others which ministers may think more important) and to launch the programme for the next Parliament.


</content>
</cab>
