<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/108/0 images: 84-88</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C. (62) 14 COPY NO.cabinet united NATIONS BOND ISSUEMemorandum by the Secretary of State jforForeign AffairsThe United Nations faces a deficit of more than $100 millioncaused by the refusal of the Soviet bloc and others to pay their shareof the costs of United Nations operations in the Middle East and inthe Congo.    Until now this deficit, which has been rising steadilyand is likely to reach $170 million by June this year, has beenpartially covered by borrowing within the United Nations system (fromvoluntary funds, etc.), by exhausting the $25 million cash float, andby postponing the payment of bills.    Of this $170 million, $80 million will represent unpaid bills and $90 million borrowing from otherfunds.    At the end of last year the Secretary-General, acting on united States inspiration, proposed to float a bond issue of$200 million to meet this emergency.     This was approved by theGeneral Assembly by 58 votes (including the United Kingdom) to13, with 24 abstentions.    Again on United States initiative, andwith United Kingdom support, the General Assembly also attempted to tackle the root problem - that of getting defaulters to pay up -by asking the International Court to give an advisory opinion whethera member Government was legally obliged to pay its share of theexpsnces of the operations in. the Middle East and the Congo.2.      The Bond issue is designed to raise sufficient cash to keepthe Organisation solvent in 1962 and at least part of 1963, and toenable its operations in the Congo and in the Middle East tocontinue.     Bonds can be purchased by member and non-member governments and by non-profit-making institutions;  they arere-payable over ten years out of the regular budget, which will beincreased by $10 million each year for this purpose, and they willbear interest of 2 per cent.3.      Ytfhen we decided to vote for the Bond issue we had reserva-tions, which we made clear to the United States at the time:-(i)       It would do nothing to solve the root problem ofmaking the large part of the membership, whichdefaults in payments for these United Nationsoperations, pay up.       In fact, it would tend toencourage financial irresponsibility;   since thecountries already in default would not subscribe to the Bonds, the countries which meet their obligations would in effect be paying twice overto cover the defaulters.-1-CONFIDENTIAL
r(ii)        In our view, $200 million is unnecessarily largeto meet the immediate uncovered deficit.    if all the Eonds are purchased, it may provide theUnited Nations with a surplus which couldencourage extravagance or irresponsible use bythe Afro-Asian majority (e. g. , the mounting of another peace and security operation in, say,Angola).     The United States authorities thern-selves have said that they regard any part ofthe $200 million not required to finance the deficit as a pool available for peace and securitypurposes.4. With regard to the second of these reservations it istrue that even if the issue were fully subscribed the funds providedcould be consumed by existing United Nations operations by themiddle of 1963.     In any case, the present indications are that thegreater risk is the opposite one of the Bond issue failing to provideenough to keep the Organisation solvent.5. If the Bond issue fails, the United Nations would facefinancial collapse.     This would require a drastic curtailment of its activities, and almost certainly mean that the operations in theMiddle East and the Congo would have to be rapidly brought to anend without any alternative arrangements to take their place.     Itmight precipitate the end of the Organisation altogether.     Despiteour misgivings about the United Nations, we believe that it is in thelong-term interests of the United Kingdom that it should be preservedin being.     It is essential for this purpose that the Bond issue should succeed.6. The United States Administration have announced thatthey propose to subscribe $100 million;  but this depends on approval by Congress, where the Administration is likely to face greatdifficulty especially if their close allies have not shown.that theyare willing to support the United States effort.    Congress may decide that the actual United States contribution should be related to thecontributions of other Governments.     If we refuse to buy any Bonds,there is a real danger that many other potential subscribers will follow our lead and that the whole scheme will collapse, becauseCongress will fail to approve adequate United States participation.For these reasons, the United States Government attach extreme importance to our response and are pressing us to let them knowour intentions within the next few days.     They have suggestedthat we should subscribe $25 million.     We have already told themthat we cannot hope to go as far as this, but there is no doubtthat a failure on our part to make an adequate response would have aserious effect on Anglo-American relations.     We could not expect the United States Administration to continue co-operating with usvery closely on United Nations questions generally, includingfinancial control, or helping us on matters like colonialism asthey are now doing and which are of special importance to us;-2-confidential 
and we should lose the ground we gained last week in the Anglo-American talks in Washington.    Furthermore, we should gravelydisappoint many of our friends among the smaller countries whoset great store by the United Nations.     We should be regarded bythem, and accused by unfriendly countries, of having given up theOrganisation as a bad job;   and our influence with other delegationsand with the Secretariat would be greatly reduced.7.        I therefore conclude that to preserve the United nations in being, for the sake of our relations with the United States, andthe maintenance of our influence more generally, it is essentialthat we should subscribe to the Bond issue.    At the same time,we should take into account our balance of payments difficulties and the need to avoid presenting the United Nations with a financial surplus.    This will require a certain flexibility in thepayment of our contribution and we should combine our payments with continued efforts to achieve better standards of political andfinancial responsibility within the Organisation.8*        There remains the question of the amount of our contribution.     The obvious standard of reference is the percentageassessment for contributions to the ordinary United Nationsbudget.     In our case this is 7k 58 per cent and for the UnitedStates 32 per cent.    In suggesting that we should contribute$25 million, therefore, the United States intention was to preserve the ratio betv^een our two assessments.     The only other Govern-ment which has so far announced a decision is the Canadian.     they propose to subscribe $6. 24 million which is in proportion to theirassessment of 3.12 per cent.     The Scandinavians and Dutch arealso likely to buy Bonds on the basis of their assessment of theregular budget.    On the same basis, our contribution would be$15.16 million.    If our resources could bear this,, a contribution of$15 million should induce other subscribers to follow,.suit andsatisfy Congress, even if we could not actually pay more thanone-half or two-thirds before 1963.9.        At the other end of the scale, a contribution of $10 million is the absolute minimum which could be represented as a reasonableor respectable share.    However, this would gain us little creditwhereas a somewhat larger offer, though still short of our regularassessment percentage, would bring us political benefits, at atimely moment from the political point of view, out of proportion to the extra cost.10.       The Chancellor of the Exchequer and I have talked this overand the two possibilities seem to us to be an offer to buy $5 millionworth of Bonds now with a promise that we would buy more later,or an undertaking now to buy $12 million worth.-3-CONFSDENTIAL
11.       My own preference is for the latter course and I recommend it to my colleagues.    I would also tell the United States Governmentthat we were taking this action in response to their request and inthe confidence that they will work jointly with us to do everything possible to achieve higher standards of political and financial responsibility v/ithin the Organisation.H.Foreign Office, S. W. 1.19th January, 1962.-A.CONFIDENTIAL


</content>
</cab>
