<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/108/0 images: 246-252</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
secret&apos;this DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. March 1962Copy No.     50CABINETSMOKING AND HEALTHMemorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home department and report by the Royal College of Physicians on &quot; Smoking and Health &quot; is tobe published on 7th March. It gives an authoritative appraisal of the damagingeffects of smoking, particularly in connection with lung cancer. At Annex A isa paper which I have discussed with the Health and Education Ministers and theMinister of Housing and Local Government.2. The Governmenfs policy hitherto has been limited to making the risks of smoking known and leaving the individual to make up his own mind in theknowledge thereof; and all publicity on smoking and lung cancer has been left tothe local authorities, who have received no financial or other assistance from theGovernment. I agree with the Ministers with whom I have discussed the matter that the Government will now have to move forward from this position and thatthey should be authorised to announce immediately after the publication of theReport a new Government initiative on health education. At Annex B are drafts of answers which might be given to questions in the House on 12th March. Thenew features are that the Government v/ill be giving advice or guidance to localauthorities that smoking should be discouraged, and supplying publicity material for their use.3. These answers, confined as they are to Government support for action bylocal authorities in the health education field, may suffice to meet immediatedemands for Government action. Meanwhile the Government will have time toconsider whether a more elaborate publicity campaign on a national basis shouldbe prepared and what attitude the Government are to take to the other suggestions made in the Report, some of which are highly controversial.4. These suggestions are quoted in paragraph 4 of Annex A. It is likely thatsome at least of them will be strongly pressed and the chances of any publicity campaign succeeding would be much diminished if the Government refrained from taking now such measures as are open to them.R. A. B.Home Office, S.W.1,2nd March, 1962.C. (62) 432nd March, 196260502a
ANNEX ASMOKING AND HEALTHMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Minister ofEducation and the Minister of health the Royal College of Physicians have prepared a Report, to be published on 7th March but already &quot; leaked &quot; in the Daily Express, on &quot; Smoking and health &quot;. It is an authoritative collection and appraisal of existing data ratherthan a new contribution to knowledge. Its main conclusions are set out inAppendix A.2. There can be no doubt about the serious effect on health of the great and growing consumption in this country of tobacco, particularly cigarettes.About 60 people die of lung cancer every day and most of these deaths wouldhave been avoided if the patient had not smoked. Indeed lung cancer is a largelypreventible disease.3. The question for us is whether it is our duty as a Government to setabout preventing it. We shall certainly be pressed to announce our attitude assoon as the Report is published.4. The Report suggests that &quot; general discouragement of smoking,particularly by young people, is necessary &quot;, and it makes the following specificsuggestions as to the action which the Government should take to this end:(i) more education of the public and especially school-children concerningthe hazards of smoking;(ii) more effective restrictions on the sale of tobacco to children;(iii) restriction of tobacco advertising;(iv) wider restriction of smoking in public places;(v) an increase of tax on cigarettes, perhaps with adjustment of the tax onpipe and cigar tobaccos;(vi) informing purchasers of the tar and nicotine content of the smoke ofcigarettes;(vii) investigating the value of anti-smoking clinics to help those who find difficulty in giving up smoking.We shall, as a minimum, be expected to say whether the Government agree thatsmoking should be discouraged and accept the specific suggestions.5. We asked officials to consider the possibilities of a Government publicity campaign, and we attach a note by them at Appendix B, which suggests (a) that aGovernment campaign could not be limited to &quot; giving the facts &quot; but must go onto give advice (b) that a campaign, to stand any chance of reducing smokingsubstantially would have to be novel, elaborate and sustained, and (c) that even so,that chance would be much diminished if the Government refrained from taking such other measures to discourage smoking as are open to them. We agree withthese conclusions.6. Most of the specific suggestions made by the Royal College are within thedepartmental sphere of other Ministers. Thus, of the suggestions in the Report, (ii)and (iv) are for the Home Secretary (iii) and (vi) for the President of the Board ofTrade, and (v) for the Chancellor of the Exchequer. The Postmaster-general would be also concerned in (iii) as respects television advertising.7. As regards what lies within our own responsibilities, we intend to intensifyhealth education on this subject, especially in schools and in teacher training colleges, and to endeavour to enlist the co-operation of teachers and parents. Thisis the least we should do, and we shall be able to mount such action fairly quickly and fairly cheaply say at the level suggested in paragraph 4 (i) of Appendix B.But we must say plainly that in our opinion no publicity campaign, however costlyor elaborate, would by itself have more than a strictly limited effect unless (in the
words of the Officials&apos; Note) &quot; the Government are seen to be taking in additionsuch other measures as lie to their hand to reduce the present level of consumptionof cigarettes &quot;.8. The matter is clearly one of great social, political and indeed industrialimportance, and our colleagues will wish to consider it on broad lines. As theMinisters responsible for the health and education services, we feel that we musturge strongly the case for the Government to use all the practical means in their power to discourage smoking, particularly of cigarettes.J.S.M.D.E.J.E.P.26th February, 1962.Appendix AEXTRACT FROM ROYAL COLLEGER SUMMARY OF THEIR REPORTConclusionsThe benefits of smoking are almost entirely psychological and social. It may help some people to avoid obesity. There is no reason to suppose that smokingprevents neurosis.2. Cigarette smoking is a cause of lung cancer and bronchitis and probablycontributes to the development of tuberculosis, coronary heart disease and various other less common diseases.   It delays healing of gastric and duodenal ulcers.3. The risks of smoking to the individual are calculated from the deathrates in relation to smoking habits among British doctors. The chance of dyingin the next 10 years for a man aged 35 who is a heavy cigarette smoker is 1 in 23whereas the risk for a non-smoker is only 1 in 90. Only 15 per cent, (one insix) of men of this age who are non-smokers but 33 per cent, (one in three) of heavy smokers will die before the age of 65. Not all this difference in expectation of life is attributable to smoking.4. The number of deaths caused by diseases associated with smoking islarge.5. Reduction in general air pollution should reduce the risks of cigarettesmoking but it is necessary for the health of the people in Britain that any measures that are practicable and likely to produce beneficial changes in smokinghabits shall be taken promptly.Preventive Measures6. Since it is not yet possible to identify those individuals who will be harmedby smoking, preventive measures must be generally applied.7. The harmful effects of cigarette smoking might be reduced by efficientfilters, by using modified tobaccos, by leaving longer cigarette stubs or bychanging from cigarette to pipe or cigar smoking.8. General discouragement of smoking, particularly by young people, isnecessary. More effort needs to be expended on discovering the most effective means of dissuading children from starting the smoking habit. There can be nodoubt of our responsibility for protecting future generations from developing the dependence on cigarette smoking that is so widespread to-day.9. Most adults have heard of the risks of cigarette smoking but remainunconvinced.  Doctors, who see the consequences of the habit, have reduced their60502
cigarette Consumption. Some evidence of concern by the Government is needed to convince the public. The Government have so far only asked local health authorities to carry out health education in respect of smoking, but little seemsto have been achieved. The Central Council for Health Education and localauthorities spent less than  5,000 on anti-smoking education in 1956-60, whilethe Tobacco Manufacturers spent  38 million on advertising their goods duringthis period.Possible Action by the Government10. Some decisive steps should be taken by the Government to curb thepresent rising consumption of tobacco, and especially of cigarettes. This action could be taken along the following lines:(i) more education of the public and especially school-children concerningthe hazards of smoking;(ii) more effective restrictions on the sale of tobacco to children;(iii) restriction of tobacco advertising;(iv) wider restriction of smoking in public places;(v) an increase of tax on cigarettes, perhaps with adjustment of the tax onpipe and cigar tobaccos;(vi) informing purchasers of the tar and nicotine content of the smoke ofcigarettes;(vii) investigating the value of anti-smoking clinics to help those who find difficulty in giving up smoking.Doctors and their Patients11. There are good medical grounds for advising patients with bronchitis,peptic ulcer or arterial diseases to stop smoking. Even a smoker&apos;s cough may bean indication that the habit should be given up. Doctors are better able to helptheir patients to stop smoking if they do not smoke themselves. They have aspecial responsibiliiv for public education about the dangers of smoking.February 1962.Appendix BSMOKING AND LUNG CANCER-PUBLICITYNote by officials the Government^ policy hitherto has been to encourage local health authorities to make the facts known, leaving individuals to choose their own courseof action. As a result, it appears that a large proportion of the population are aware that there is, or may well be, a causal connection between smoking and lungcancer; but few members of the general public take this seriously or regard the riskas serious in their own particular case, and few appear to have altered their habitsas a result. The connection between smoking and other diseases is not generallyrealised at all. There is no doubt that those local authorities who would themselves have liked to be most active have felt handicapped by the absence of any government participation in the publicity and of any Government expression ofview.2. The Royal College&apos;s Report contains little that is new in the way of scientific evidence. It pulls together the existing evidence and authoritativelyappraises it. It will attract publicity and have some effect on some people. But itwill not enable the health education efforts of local authorities to be much more effective than at present. If any real and lasting impression is to be made on thepublic mind, the Government will have to sponsor, and indeed conduct, a campaign.3. We were asked to consider whether it would be possible for a Governmentcampaign to be limited to &quot; giving the facts &quot; without also &quot; giving advice &quot;.  We
do not think it would. The &quot;facts&quot; are not in themselves sufficiently clear,striking and unqualified to make a telling impact without explanation, commentand derivative judgment (&quot; smoking is a cause . . .&quot; &quot; much higher chance of death . &quot;, etc.). And even if they were, it is not practicable for the Governmentmerely to stress facts without giving, or implying, an opinion that people should do something about them. Every Government publicity campaign diphtheria,road safety, service recruiting aims to guide the public towards a particular course of action or the acquisition of a particular habit.4. We have looked at the possible content of a Government publicity campaign on the conventional lines at three levels of cost:(i) Cost  20,000 covering posters, leaflets, filmlets  for use by localauthorities, schools and interested bodies, etc., addressed to a selectedpublic, especially the young.(ii) Cost  125,000 covering (i) plus Press and television advertising for alimited period (2-3 weeks), addressed to the general public,(hi) Cost  1 mijlion covering Press and television advertising extending overa year, plus posters on hired hoardings.5. To start one of these campaigns might provide the Government with a defensive position against those who urge that it is the Governmenfs duty to be up and doing. But we do not think that even the most expensive of them would initself make any large and lasting difference to smoking habits.6. If the Government regard it as their duty to induce such a difference that is, to put the authority of the State behind an attempt to reduce substantiallyand permanently the consumption of cigarettes then something more and differentwill be needed.7. First, the force of example must be recognised, and the Government mustaddress themselves to those categories who are specially well placed to influenceothers. Of these, perhaps the most important are doctors, teachers and parents.8. As the Report shows, doctors have markedly reduced their own smokingsince the scientific data first became convincing to those best able to understandthem. It should be possible to stimulate doctors, through their own organisations,both to alter their own habits and to advise their patients to do so. (Incidentally,posters and leaflets in doctors&apos; surgeries would be a cheap and effective mediumfor publicity.)9. It would clearly be desirable to persuade children not to take up smokingat all. To them the risk appears far off as well as slight, and smoking is an attractive sign of maturity. The task of persuasion is therefore difficult, particularly if parents and others with whom they are in daily contact not only smoke themselvesbut allow, and even encourage, the children to smoke too. The task would be quite impossible, without the whole-hearted co-operation of schools. It would therefore be necessary to attempt to persuade teachers that it was their duty notonly to plug anti-smoking propaganda in the schools but also to add example to precept.10. The campaign would therefore need careful preparation among&quot; influential&quot; classes and their professional organisations, and the above wouldbe only some of the steps needed. The campaign, once launched, would have tobe carried on, at considerable intensity and for a long period, through all publicitymedia of which television would perhaps be the most effective as well as themost expensive. And large numbers of people from many walks of life wouldhave to be recruited in order to play a part. The cost would be considerable notless than  1 million a year.11. It must be recognised that such a campaign would be attempting whatno national publicity campaign has ever attempted before a big change in astrongly ingrained social habit, with no recommended substitute. It seems morethan doubtful whether it would stand much chance of success unless theGovernment were seen to be taking in addition such other measures as lie totheir hand to reduce the present level of consumption of cigarettes.February 1962.
ANNEX draft ANSWER FOR USE BY THE MINISTER OF HEALTH ON12th march the Secretary of State for Scotland and I will shortly be asking the local health authorities to use all channels of health education to make the conclusionsof the Report known and to discourage smoking on health grounds, particularly of cigarettes. We shall be giving them guidance and providing them with publicitymaterial. We are also consulting with the Central and Scottish Councils for HealthEducation about ways in which they can help. As regards health education inthe schools, my Rt. Hon. Friend the Minister of Education is answering anotherQuestion on that subject to-day.DRAFT ANSWER FOR USE BY THE MINISTER OF EDUCATION ON12th march the Secretary of State for Scotland and I propose to draw the attention ofthe local education authorities to this Report and to seek their co-operation andthat of the teaching profession and of all those who work with school children and young people in making clear to them through all the means at their disposalthe dangers to their future health of smoking, particularly cigarettes, and to discourage the formation of the smoking habit. It is my intention to publishseparately a revised version of the section in the Ministry&apos;s pamphlet &quot; HealthEducation &quot; which deals with the dangers of smoking incorporating material fromthis Report and to consider with all those concerned what further assistance Ican usefully give.My Rt. Hon. Friend is taking corresponding steps in Scotland.


</content>
</cab>
