<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/118/0 images: 126-128</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1964CP. (64) 124 Copy No.    5 922nd June, 1964CABINETTHE CONCORDMemorandum by the Chief Secretary to the Treasury and paymaster GeneralThe proposal in the Minister of Aviation&apos;s paper (CP. (64) 123) that we should now decide to go full steam ahead on this project, in its revised form and at anenormously increased cost, raises some very large questions. In a number ofimportant respects particularly as regards cost the project has changed almostbeyond recognition since we originally approved it in 1962.2. One cannot at this stage, as the Minister says, be precise about the size of the research and development bill we shall have to pay. Even if it ultimatelyturns out to be no more than the half share of the  275 million which the Ministernow forecasts (and bearing in mind how the costs of other advanced projects, suchas the TSR-2, for which the British Aircraft Corporation (B.A.C.) and BristolSiddeley are responsible, have escalated, this seems unlikely), it would still be nearly as much as the cost of two Channel tunnels.3. Let us assume, however (and these are large assumptions) that the aircraft is successfully developed, that it costs no more for research and development thanthe Minister is now forecasting, and that it comes into service by the Minister^date of 1971. Even on this basis, the project does not look economic. If the Concordis sold at a unit price of  5 million its operating cost per seat mile will, I gather,be, on the most favourable assumptions, some 25 per cent to 35 per cent worse than the Boeing 707s which are now being flown by British Overseas airways corporation (B.O.A.C.). But  5 million is not in fact an economic selling price forthe Concord. The Minister hopes to sell 150 aircraft. Spreading the research anddevelopment expenditure of  275 million over this number of aircraft, the economicselling price would be not  5 million but  7 million. If the Concord is not competitivewith subsonic jets even at  5 million, can the airlines be expected to pay  7 million?Should we be able to sell 150 at this price? If we do not recover our investment,let alone get any return on it, we should in effect be paying heavily for technologicaldevelopments which would be surpassed in a year or two by the Americans. Howprofitable, moreover, is the Concord venture likely to be for the aircraft companies concerned? If it is a complete failure, will both the British Aircraft corporation and Bristol Siddeley be ruined? At what level of sales is it likely to be profitablefor them?4. There is also the impact of the Concord on B.O.A.C. If the aircraft isdeveloped and put on sale, will B.O.A.C. have any alternative but to buy it? Ifthey do, and losses result, these are bound to fall on the Exchequer.51. Not only are there these big questions of operating costs and economicreturn: there is also the problem of sonic bang. I am told that the Concord willmake louder bangs than those against which some of the residents of Oklahoma Cityhave been protesting. I should not have thought that the public could be expectedto stand for them. I am sure this is a problem which needs to be investigated more carefully. May we not find at the end of the day that our money has been spent onan aircraft that could only go supersonic over seas and deserts? On this basis,IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT4504
would the project have been worth doing? I think we should look into thesjgfequestions very closely while our rate of expenditure on the Concord is still relatively^low rather than later on, when we have sunk large sums in this project.6. Beyond this there is the relationship between the problem of the Concordand that of the VC-lOs of which B.O.A.C. are now seeking to disembarrassthemselves. These two aviation issues are connected in various ways. Large amounts of money are involved in both of them say  150 million for the Concord and between, say,  40 million and  70 million for the VC-10. The British aircraft corporation is concerned with the building of both aircraft. The operatingeconomics of B.O.A.C. are also involved in both. And finally, the view that onetakes about the operating economics of the VC-10 and sales prospects of theaircraft itself are substantially affected by one&apos;s assumptions about the date onwhich the Concord will be coming into service. And both these issues will call for decision and a public announcement in the course of the next few weeks. They are both, of course, profoundly complex but I think we ought to consider them together.J. A. B.-C.Treasury Chambers, S.W. I.22nd June, 1964.
SECRET4521aSECRETNOTEThe attached memorandum by theChancellor of the Exchequer (CP. (64) 125)is circulated for discussion at the meetingof the Cabinet which has been arranged for thursday, 2nd July.The contents of the memorandum areof a particularly confidential character.Ministers will no doubt ensure that it istreated accordingly.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,29th June, 1964.

</content>
</cab>
