<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/118/0 images: 138-139</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet. June 1964CP. (64) 128 Copy No.     6430th June, 1964CABINETEARNINGS-RELATED benefits memorandum by the Minister of Pensions and National insurance on 18th June the Cabinet considered papers by the Chancellor of theExchequer as Chairman of the Pensions and National Insurance Committee(CP. ,(64) 118) and by the Chancellor and the Chief Secretary (CP. (64) 121).The Cabinet decided that short-term benefits for unemployment, sickness andwidowhood should be related to earnings (CM. (64) 32nd Conclusions, Item 7,Conclusion (1)). It also decided against the publication of a White Paper outlining the proposals and felt that further consideration should be given to the best wayof presenting them publicly.2.  There are several ways in which this could be done:(i) to outline the proposals in the course of a speech in the House ofCommons, if the Opposition happen to choose to debate pensions and benefits on one of the remaining Supply Days;(ii) to make a statement in the House of Commons or announce in answer to a written Question that we have accepted the principle of wage-relation;(iii) to make a similar announcement in a speech outside Parliament;(iv) to postpone any declaration until the beginning of the election campaign.3. If the Opposition have a Supply Day on pensions, it would be difficultto refuse any indication of our views and then produce fairly detailed proposalsa few weeks later.4. Even if we avoid a debate, the arguments for some kind of parliamentary statement are that (i) there have been many questions asked already;(ii) we are known to have been considering the question for more than ayear;(iii) a statement could be confined to this subject;(iv) if no statement were made, the Government would appear to havedeliberately avoided one. This would become quite clear when the subsequent publication of our proposals showed that information could have been given to Parliament in July.5. If the proposals were announced in a speech in August or September, itwould underline the fact that we had by-passed Parliament. Moreover, if our otherpensions proposals were not announced in the speech, no impression could begiven of our general approach; but if the other proposals were announced, weshould be pressed for details and outbid by the Socialists.4529
6. The main question we have to decide is whether the announcement shouldbe made soon in Parliament or outside; or postponed for as long as possible. Thearguments for an early announcement are that:(i) the longer it is postponed, the harder it will be to recapture the initiative:we shall appear merely to be copying our opponents and be producing a less attractive scheme;(ii) as long as we postpone announcing even a decision in principle it will beimpossible to criticise our opponets for failing to disclose their hand;(iii) we ought to give some guidance soon to our supporters.On the other hand, the case for reserving the proposals for announcement in the manifesto is that:(i) they could be presented as a complete policy;(ii) they would be seen to represent the Governments intentions during thenext Parliament, and pressure for early legislation would be easier to resist;(iii) it would reduce the danger of destructive criticism and more attractivebids.7. On balance, I think it would be best to wait for the Manifesto; but if therewere to be a debate, I should like to consult my colleagues again, because I thinkit would be necessary to announce a decision in principle. I should be glad to knowif the Cabinet agrees with these conclusions.R. W.Ministry of Pensions and National Insurance,London, W.C. 2,29th June, 1964.

</content>
</cab>
