<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/3/3 images: 48-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY 03? HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;5 GOVERNME&quot;.SECRET.. COPY,. NO.WPP.(R.)(39)88.COAL__PjOSITCCNj.Fifth Fortnightly Report suhmitted by the -Secretary for mines covering the period 1st to 14th November,  1959.(Previous Report:    Paper No. W.P.(R.)(39)  62.)(Initialled)        G.  L.Richmond Terrace,SPY.  1.17th November,  1939.

FIFTH   REPORT    ON    COAL    POSITION.For Fortnight 1st to 14th November,  1939.Production and Supply.Output is at a slightly higher level than during thecorresponding period of 1938.    Shipping difficulties continue to restrict output for export and coastwise trade but inland supplieshave been satisfactorily maintained.ITEM	1939		1938	Week ending 28th October	Week ending 4th November	Week ending 5th NovemberEstimated Quantity of Saleable coal raised Total Quantity of     H coal shipped abroad Approximate Quantity of coal available for Koine consumption	Tons 4,747,000 823,000 3,924,000	Tons 4,728,000 1,002,000 3,726,000	. Tons 4,611,000 1,112,000 3,499,00056Including the coal equivalent of cokeand manufactured fuel.Employmant.On the 4th November, 1939, the number of wage-earners was758,300, an increase of 2,100 as compared with a fortnight ago andan increase of nearly 10,000 since the end of the first week of thewar.    As compared with the 5th November,  1938,  there was a decreaseof 15,200.    The average number of days worked during the week ended4th November,  1939, amounted to 5.40 as compared with 5.03 days inthe corresponding week of 1938.Taking into account the number of persons employed and timeworked the volume of employment as compared with the 5th November, 193 8,has increased by about 5 per cent.    During the same period outputhas increased by 2% per cent.Distribution.Rail deliveries are generally satisfactory but lack of wagonshas caused short time working at some pits in Northumberland, Durhamar-d Midland districts.    In the two former districts shipping delays

are mainly responsible for the hold up of wagons at the ports.The Department^ local officers and the Railway Companies are endeavouring to overcome the difficulties.    Delayed clearances hymerchants, particularly in the South of England are a part cause ofthe trouble.    The matter has been taken up by the Departmentsconcerned with the trade interests.Shortage of tonnage continues at all East Coast ports.    in durham the dislocation of coastwise shipping is the chief cause of reduced output.    Some essential supplies have had to he diverted torail.    To relieve the congestion at Humher ports the French Coalliission are considering a suggestion to ship Midland coal fromWest Coast ports.Rationing.In view of the improvement of stocks in merchants&apos; yards and ofthe foreign demand being at present restricted by shipping and other difficulties the rationing percentage of coal,  coke and manufacturedfuel has been raised from 75 to 100.    As mentioned in the last reportin connection with a similar increase for gas and electricity it isnecessary to maintain the machinery of rationing in order to preventexcessive consumption and to provide for re-imposing reductions at short notice if necessary.    It is hoped to complete the work of registration and the fixation of basic quantities in a few weekswhen, if the present circumstances still obtain, part of the LocalFuel Overseers&apos; organisation can probably be dispensed with.Prices.(i) Pithead.  - The Government agreed to an increase in thepithead price of all coal by 1/- per ton for collieries in Englandand Scotland and by l/4d.  per ton for collieries in Wales as from3rd November.    An Order of the same date advanced by l/- per ton&quot;the prices specified in existing contracts for inland supply.(ii) Coke.  - The price of furnace coke for metallurgical purposeshas advanced by 5/- per ton in accordance with the tripartite agreement by which the price is related to the price of steel.

0iLi IExports..Permission has been granted freely during the period underreview for the export of coal to practically all destinations.There has been some restriction in exports to one or two countries,although not below the level of Exports in 1938,  in order to bring pressure in connection with War Trade negotiations on the countries concerned.At a meeting held recently at the Ministry of Economic warfare the question of the quantities of coal to be made available for ourvarious foreign markets was considered.    On the basis that a globalquantity of some  6 million tons would be available for export anda provisional schedule of allocations was drawn up and agreed.A copy of the schedule, which is subject to revision in December,is attached.

Provisional allocation of coal exports agreed with the Ministry of Economic Warfare on thebasis of an estimated surplus of approximately46 million tons available for export.1938ExportsTon sPrance andFrench 7,407,000possessionsNorwaySwedenDenmarkIcelandFinland1,365,0002,655,0002,996,000124,0001,140,000Provisionalallocationnow agreed,subject to review atfrequentintervals.TonsIncreaseorDecrease  (-)comparedwith exports in 1938TonsRemarks20,000,000    + 12,595,0001,365,0002,655,0002,996,000124,000700,000) Exports to these countries) are being maintained as far) as possible at normal levels) (except to Finland, where) it is anticipated that) shipping difficulties will) bring about a reduction)) pending the conclusion of) War Trade Negotiations now) in progress.) Thereafter the provisional) allocations may have to be- 440,000) increased.LatviaLithuaniaEstoniaBelgiumHollandSwitzerlandEgyptItalyGreece431,000)237,000)52,000)658,000889,000257,0001,576,0002,260,000143,000500,000658,000730 , 000257,0001,576,0004,617,000356,000- 220,000&quot;159,000It is unlikelycountries will maintain their trade with the that thesebe able tonormalU.K.The redaction    represents he&apos;supply of British coalin transit to Germany andto ships bunkering atDutch ports in 1938.  Thisis being stopped in orderto prevent neutral vesselsevading our hold over them through our Bunker Control.2^357,000) These increases are) provisional pending the) conclusion&apos; of War Trade4- 213,000) Negotiations.Spain andCanaryIslands1,065,000500,000- 565,000Spain&apos;s imports of U.K.coalhave   practically ceasedsince the   Civil War, butit is anticipated that shemay require substantial quantities of U.K. coal infuture.

1938ExportsPortugalPortguese,ColoniesTon s713,OOO160,000Yugo Slavia 4,000Eire 2,447,000260,000.ChannelIslandsCanadaNewfoundland   157,000British India     7,000and BurmaAnglo-Egyptian   7,000SudanOther british territories   875,000U.S.A.BrazilUruguayArgent ineOthers(unalloc-ated)GermanyT^iALS135,000531,000285,0002,030,00032,024,000145,0003,687,000Provisionalallocationn ow a greed,subject to review   atfrequentin tervals.Tons1,000,0004,0002,477,000260,0001,128,000        1,200,00157,0007,0007,000875,000135,000531,000285,0002,500,000Increase  (h-)or decrease  (-)comparedwith exports in 1938Tons* 127,0004- 72,000+ 470,00046,472,000  * 14,448,000- 3,687,00035,856,000      46,472,000 + 10,761,000RemarksIf an increase is possiblein the face of competition from American coal it will help to pay for additionalU.K. purchases from CanadaArgentine has asked for anincrease and its supply will help to pay for the heavypurchases of grain to bemade by the U.K.


</content>
</cab>
