<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/1/0 images: 38-41</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CM. (45)22nd Conclusions.CABINET 22 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 14th August, 1945, at 10-45 f.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. F. W. Pethick-Lawrence, M.P., Secretary of Statefor India and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. E. Shin well, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.General Sir Hastings L. Ismay.Mr. Norman Brook.Contents:Subject: PageJapan ....       ....       ....       ... -----      ----      **6Surrender.[30692-2]
Japan.Surrender.(previous reference:CM. (45)21stConclusions,Minute 2.)The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that earlier inthe evening he had heard, by telephone from Mr. Byrnes, the UnitedStates Secretary of State, that the United States Government hadreceived a reply to the communication sent to the Japanese Govern-ment on the 11th August on behalf of the four Allied Governments,Mr. Byrnes had given him the substance of this reply and had saidthat the United States Government considered that it constituted asatisfactory acceptance of the terms of the Potsdam Declaration.They therefore proposed that the Japanese surrender should beaccepted by the Allied Governments, and that an announcement tothis effect should be made forthwith. It was proposed that theannouncement should be released at 7 p.m. in Washington, whichwould be the equivalent of midnight British Summer Time. Afurther message had since been received from Mr. Byrnes to theeffect that the Soviet and Chinese Governments had accepted his proposal for an announcement at 7 p.m. Washington time.The Foreign Secretary said that he had taken steps to obtainthrough the United States Embassy the text of the reply from theJapanese Government; and he suggested that the Cabinet should reserve their final decision until they had had an opportunity of examining the text. Meanwhile, it would be advisable to ask theB.B.C. to warn the public to stand by for an important announce-ment which might be made at midnight.This suggestion was agreed to, and the B.B.C. were askedat 11 p.m. to issue a warning notice in the terms suggested.Later in the meeting, the Foreign Secretary received from theUnited States Embassy the following text of the reply from theJapanese Government: &quot; With reference to the announcement of the 10th Augustregarding the acceptance of the provisions of the PotsdamDeclaration and the reply of the Governments of the UnitedStates, Great Britain, the Soviet Union and China sent by secretary of State Byrnes on the date of the 11th August, theJapanese Government has the honour to communicate to theGovernments of the four Powers as follows : &quot;(1) His Majesty the Emperor has issued an Imperialrescript regarding Japan&apos;s acceptance of the pro-visions of the Potsdam Declaration.&quot; (2) His Majesty the Emperor is prepared to authoriseand ensure the signature by his Government and theImperial General Headquarters of the necessaryterms for carrying out the provisions of the PotsdamDeclaration.&quot; (3) His Majesty is also prepared to issue his commandsto all the Military, Naval and Air Authorities of japan, and all the Forces under their control, where-ever located, to cease active operations, to surrenderarms and to issue such other orders as may berequired by the Supreme Commander of the allied forces for the execution of the above-mentionedterms.(Signed) TOGO.&quot;Some discussion ensued on the interpretation of the third para-graph of this reply. It was suggested that the demand of the AlliedGovernments had been that the Emperor should comply with direc-tions given to him by the Allied Commander; and that the proper con-struction of the reply was that the Emperor would command his military, Naval and Air Authorities to comply with directionsgiven to them by the Allied Commander. The language of the replymight have been deliberately chosen to avoid putting the Emperorin the position of having to accept the directions of the Allied Com-mander. After discussion, it was agreed that the terms of the replycould be regarded as satisfactory on this point, since they would ensure that the Military, Naval and Air Authorities of Japan would
be commanded by the Emperor to comply with such directions as might be given to them by the Allied Commander for the purposeof securing compliance with the provisions of the PotsdamDeclaration.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the reply from the Japanese Government couldbe regarded as a satisfactory acceptance of the condi-tions set out in the communication sent on behalf of. theAllied Governments on the 11th August; and agreed thatthe Prime Minister should announce at midnight the news of Japan&apos;s surrender.The Prime Minister read to the Cabinet the text of theannouncement which he proposed to make, and outlined the arrange-ments for celebrating the end of the war. Wednesday and Thursday,the 15th and 16th August, would be celebrated as holidays : HisMajesty The King would broadcast at 9 p.m. on the 15th August:the two Houses of Parliament would hold their Services of Thanks-giving at 4 p.m. on the 15th August; and thereafter both houses would move Addresses of Congratulation to His Majesty. the debate on the Address would be opened on Thursday, the16th August.The Cabinet (2) Took note with approval of the arrangements proposed bythe Prime Minister.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,14th August, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
