<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/1/0 images: 86-91</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1945.SECRET.CM. (45)28th Conclusions.Copy No.CABINET 28 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 4th September, 1945, at 11 am.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following was also present:The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply and aircraft production (Item 2).Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.Contents:minute no. Subject. page 1      Education       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      74Raising of School Leaving Age.2      Industrial Organisation and Efficiency     ....       ....       ....      743      Man-power      ............      ....      ....      ....      ....      764      Monetary Awards      ............ .... 77[30725-2] B
Education.Raising of school-leaving age.(previous reference:CM. (45)25thConclusions,Minute 3.)1. At their meeting on the 23rd August the Cabinet had invited the Lord President of the Council to arrange for a Com-mittee consisting of the Ministers primarily concerned to considerthe practical implications of a decision that the school leaving ageshould be raised to 15 on the 1st April, 1947.The Cabinet now had before them a Memorandum by the lord president of the Council (CP. (45) 140) reporting the conclusions reached by the Committee.The Lord President of the Council said that, after examining the difficulties involved, the Committee were satisfied that it was desirable to adhere to the proposal to raise the school leaving age to 15 on the 1st April, 1947. There would be difficulties in providing the necessary accommodation, but, given the standards of con-struction which the Education Departments were prepared toaccept, it should be possible to do so without undue strain on ourbuilding resources. It would, however, be essential that thereshould be no delay in releasing from the Forces the skilled technical staff required for the building programmes of local authorities.With regard to the supply of teaching staff, it now appeared thatthe original estimate of the abnormal wastage of teachers over thenext four years had been unduly pessimistic, and, although thestandard of education provided would not be as high as was desirable, the prospective shortage of teachers was not sufficient tojustify the Government in postponing further the date for raising the school leaving age. The Government should, however, take thepublic into their confidence with regard to the difficulties and warnthem that for a time it would be necessary to accept imperfectconditions.The Minister of Education said that active steps were beingtaken by the Ministry to increase the number of places in training-colleges for teachers, and it was hoped to have an additional 3,000places by the beginning of 1946.The Minister of Health said that while he did not dissent fromthe removal of the existing ban on building for educational purposes in London, he would have to press for the removal of the ban onhospital building in view of the large number of hospitals whichhad been damaged or destroyed.The Cabinet &apos;Endorsed the recommendation made in CP. (45) 140 thatthe school leaving age should be raised to 15 on the1st April, 1947.Industrial 2.   The Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by the Presi-Organisation    dent of the Board of Trade (CP. (45) 142) submitting proposals forand Efficiency, encouraging industrial efficiency in those industries which would continue to operate under private enterprise.The President of the Board of Trade explained that his pro-posals had already been discussed by the Lord Presidents Committee(L.P. (45) 30th Meeting, Minute 5) and that the scheme put forward in CP. (45) 142 took account of the points which had been raised in the discussion. The main feature of his scheme was that thereshould be an investigation into each industry with the primary object of ascertaining and agreeing with both sides of the industrywhat the industry needed in order to make it as efficient as possiblein the national interest. Each investigation would be conducted by a committee consisting as to one-third of employers&apos; representa-tives, one-third of Trade Unionists, and one-third of persons appointed by himself, including a chairman of high standing. Theindependent representatives would watch the consumers&apos; interests as well as being useful in the technical field in which they wereexperienced. He had provisionally selected for investigation thepottery, wool, boots and shoes, hosiery and furniture industries.Once the investigation into an industry had been completed it would
be for the Board of Trade to work out a scheme for the industryand to take such steps as were best calculated to bring it intooperation.Discussion centred primarily on the composition of the com-mittees of investigation. The proposals of the President of theBoard of Trade were criticised on the grounds that they gaveundue preponderance to the employers&apos; representatives and trade unionists, and the fear was expressed that this might lead eachcommittee to concentrate largely on promoting the sectional interestsof the two sides of the industry concerned without regard to theneeds of the consumer, and to shirk from recommending drastic changes in organisation even when such changes were necessary. Itwas suggested that it might be preferable that the committees should consist entirely of independent members with representatives ofboth sides of the industry as assessors, or that the number of independent members should be increased at least to the extentof not reckoning the chairman as part of the independent thirdof the Committee. The suggestion was also made that amongthe independent members there should be persons with thenecessary qualifications in accountancy to enable them to obtainaccurate information with regard to costs; and attention was drawn to the desirability that the representatives of employers andTrade Unionists should be appointed personally by the Presidentof the Board of Trade and not merely be nominated by the two sides of the industry.Further points in discussion were : (a) The Minister of Supply and Aircraft Production said thatit would be undesirable to give the impression to the public that theprocedure suggested by the President of the Board of. Trade wouldbe adopted as a model for all similar enquiries and that any public announcement should be so worded as not to imply that in all casesthe two sides of the industry would be represented on the investi-gating body.(b) The Minister of Education said that she hoped that arrange-ments could be made for the officials of the Ministry of Educationconcerned with technical education to be kept in close touch withthe work of the proposed committees.(c) The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs stressed theimportance of recruiting to the Board of Trade officials who hadthe necessary training to enable them to deal with problems ofproduction.(d) The Secretary of State for Scotland said that he hopedthat suitable representation would be given to Scottish interests onany committees which might be appointed.The President of the Board of Trade said that he attached great importance to obtaining the co-operation and goodwill of theindustries concerned. The protection of the interests of consumerscould best be done by the Board of Trade itself, and it would be forthe Board of Trade to reject the report of any committee whichfailed to put forward adequate proposals. The problem of obtainingaccurate costings could be dealt with by the appointment of a specialsub-committee on this particular problem, and it was his intentionto give the chairman of each committee a direction that the policyof the committee in making their recommendations should be oneof expansion rather than restriction. He would have preferred to adhere to the proposal that the independent members, including thechairman, should not represent more than one-third of the committee but he was prepared to agree that the chairman should be regardedas additional to the independent members who would constitute&quot; the&quot; one-third of each committee. So far as the EducationDepartments were concerned, he saw no difficulty in making arrange-ments, possibly through the appointment of a special sub-committeeon education, which would enable close contact to be maintained between the officials concerned with technical education and the-2] B 2
proposed committees. He would see that any announcement madewith regard to the committees took account of the point made by theMinister of Supply and Aircraft Production, and that suitablerepresentation was given to Scottish interests.The Cabinet Approved the proposals in CP. (45) 142, on the under-standing that in the composition of the committees of investigation the independent chairman would be additional to the independent members who would formone-third of each committee.Man-Power. 3.   At their meeting on the 30th August the Cabinet had(Previous invited the Man-Power Committee to submit an early report on reference: possible modifications in the demobilisation scheme designed toCM. (45)26th accelerate releases in Class A and increase the number of workersConclusions,     released in Class B.Minute 4.) The Qam&apos;net now before them a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs (CP. (45) 141) covering areport prepared by the Ministry of Labour and National Service andthe Service Departments, and a draft Press statement to be madeby the Minister of Labour and National Service.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that theproposals now put before the Cabinet, the main feature of whichwas the acceleration of Class B releases, were in the nature of an interim report and that the Man-Power Committee would submitfurther proposals as soon as information was available as to theForces required to meet our military commitments on the basis ofthe fresh appreciation which was being made by the Chiefs of Staff.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that in viewof the information given in the broadcast by the Prime Minister onthe previous day, it would be necessaiy to make a certain numberof changes in the draft statement appended to CP. (45) 141. he proposed to make the statement on the following day.In discussion attention was drawn to the importance of makingreductions in the administrative and clerical staffs of the Serviceand Supply Departments concurrently with the progress of the demobilisation scheme and the cutting down of the munitions programme, and the hope was expressed that Ministers would take every possible step to ensure that staffs were not retained unneces-sarily either at headquarters or in the regions. Experience afterthe last war showed that unless timely steps were taken to makeplanned reductions there was a danger that the Government wouldbe driven by public criticism to make drastic cuts which would dolasting harm to the efficiency of the civil&apos; service. Moreover, the civilian Departments who had heavy responsibilities in connectionwith reconstruction were urgently in need of additional staff, whichmight suitably be transferred from Departments whose responsi-bilities were contracting.The Secretary of State for War said that about 45,000 mendue. to go on leave or to be released were waiting at ports in theFar East for the necessary transport. It was most important thatsome announcement should be made with regard to the steps whichthe Government proposed to take to bring these men home as soonas possible, and he proposed that the Minister of War transport should take up with the United States authorities the question ofincreasing our share of the available shipping for trooping purposes.He also suggested that the First Lord of the Admiralty and theSecretary of State for Air should consider whether more assistance could not be provided by the use of aircraft and naval vessels. TheSecretary of State for Foreign Affairs said that it might be useful if any requests for a greater share of shipping for trooping purposeswere put in the first instance to Mr. Byrnes when he will be in thiscountry next week.
The Cabinet-(1) Approved the proposed modifications designed to speed upreleases in Class B&apos; set out in the Annex to CP. (45) 141and agreed that the Minister of Labour and NationalService should make a statement to the Press on thefollowing day.(2) Invited the Man-Power Committee to keep the demobilisa-tion scheme under continuous review and to submit afurther report when information was available withregard to the Forces required to meet our military commitments.(3) Took note that the Prime Minister would circulate a directive with regard to the reduction of staffs inGovernment Departments.(4) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for aspecial Meeting of the Ministers concerned to examinethe possibility of increasing the transport available for members of the Forces stationed in the Far East whowere now due for release or for leave.Monetary 4.   The Cabinet had before them a note by the Prime MinisterAwards. (CP. (45) 126) on the question whether any monetary awards shouldbe made to the principal Service leaders at the conclusion of thepresent war.A note of the discussion and of the conclusions reached is contained in the Secretary&apos;s Standard File of Cabinet Conclusions.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,4$h September, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
