<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/1/0 images: 146-153</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1945.SECRET.CM. (45)38th Conclusions.Copy No.CABINET 36 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 28th September, 1945, at 3 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:The Hon. Sir Alexander Cadogan,M.P., Permanent Under-Secretary ofState for Foreign Affairs.Mr. G. R. Strauss, M.P., Parliamen-tary Secretary, Ministry of war transport.Field-Marshal Sir Alan Brooke, Chiefof the Imperial General Staff.Lord Nathan, Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for War.Admiral of the Fleet Sir andrew cunningham, First Sea Lord and chief of Naval Staff.Air Marshal Sir Douglas C. S. Evill,Vice-Chief of the Air Staff.Secretariat.Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Major-General L. C. Hollis.Contents :Minute No. Subject.1      Man-Power2      United States Bases in Iceland3      Allied Control Machinery in Japan ....[30754-4]Page122125126b
1. At their meeting on the 4th September the Cabinet had invited the Man-Power Committee to submit a report on releases from the Forces and Supply Department work, based on the revisedappreciation by the Chiefs of Staff of the forces required to meet our military commitments.The Cabinet now had before them a report by the Chairmanof the Man-Power Committee (CP. (45) 191).The Cabinet considered first the proposals put forward by theMan-Power Committee for releases from the Forces and supply department work up to the 31st December, 1945.The Secretary of Slate for Foreign Affairs said that the pro-grammes of releases put forward by the Service Ministers had provided for an increase of only about 200,000 on the figureannounced by the Minister of Labour in his statement at the begin-ning of September. The Man-Power Committee had thought it essential to aim at releasing an extra 400,000, thus bringing the totalreleased during 1945 up to 1,500,000. The main limitation on therate of release was the availability of transport but the Committeehad felt that the right course was for the Service Ministers to assume that transport would not impose any limitation on the rate of releaseand had invited them to submit for consideration at a meeting onthe 1st October, revised estimates showing how far they could gotowards releasing a further 200,000 men and women in 1945 onthis assumption. It was clear that the Government must make available the necessary transport at all costs, and he felt that theproblem could be solved if it were tackled with the.same resourceand determination as had been displayed in meeting emergenciesduring the war. In order to avoid delays a single person shouldbe appointed by whom any questions of priority in connection withthe provision of transport could be settled.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that it wasimperative that there should be a release of 1% million men andwomen up to the end of 1945. Moreover, in view of the arrange-ments for the release of women which had been under consideration at the time of the change of Government, he felt that the Govern-ment would be placed in an impossible position if the number ofwomen included in the total was less than 250,000. He proposedto issue a statement of the Government&apos;s revised proposals to thePress on Tuesday for publioation on Wednesday morning and to broadcast on Wednesday evening. The statement would begin by giving an estimate of the numbers to be released up to mid-1946,and it was for consideration how far it should include separatefigures relating to the size of the armed forces and details of thetransport and shipping facilities available for bringing men from overseas.    ,The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of War Transport,.saidthat the Ministry of War Transport felt confident that, by imposingcuts in services and by various other emergency measures, they couldincrease substantially the shipping available for the repatriation of men due for release.If the United States Government were not willing to give us an equivalent lift in place of the loan of the &quot;Queens&quot; and theAquitania, we should consider withdrawing those vessels fromthe United States and employing them for the conveyance of pas-passengers from the Far East. The possibility of bringing men fromthe Far East home across North America was also worth consider-ing.In discussion the following points were made : (a) On the assumption that the Services were able to release1,500,000 men and. women by the end of 1945, to what extent would it still be necessary to retain men in the Services in this country who could not be fully employed 1It was explained that it was impossible to make any statisticalassessment of the extent to which men in the Services would be under-Man-Power.(previous reference:C.M.(45)28thConclusions,Minute 3.)
123CM. 36 (4S).employed while they were waiting for release, but that the services were doing what they could to reduce the extent to which men athome had to wait for release by spreading the release of any onegroup over a period of some weeks with the result that men at homecould be released at the beginning of the period. It was essential,however, to complete the release of any one group before the releaseof the next began.(b) The Chief of the Imperial General Staff pointed out thata review of the available shipping had already been made, and thatit was estimated that, even on the assumption that emergency measures were adopted and that we obtained an equivalent lift fromthe United States Government in return for the loan of the&quot;Queens&quot; and the Aquitania, it had seemed doubtful whetherthe original programme of releases of the Services could be carriedout. When this review had been made, the Ministry of War Trans-port had indicated that their resources were stretched to the utmost.(c) The Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for Warexplained that the War Office estimated that one way in which thereleases from the Army in 1945 might be increased by about 50,000would be if men who had been prisoners of war in the hands of theenemy were released forthwith, irrespective of their age and lengthof service group.It was explained that the proposal to release prisoners of war might raise considerable difficulties for the navy where prisoners ofwar who had been found to be fit were serving side by side with othermen. The suggestion was made, however, that the possibility mightbe explored of confining the release of prisoners of war to men whohad been in the hands of the enemy for a specified period, or to menwho were below a certain medical standard.(d) Every effort should be made to call up as many men aspossible for the Forces in order to increase the number of releasesand the Minister of Labour should explain in his statement whatwas being done in this respect. It was pointed out that the navyhad been unable to absorb the intake of 47,000 for which they had originally asked for the second half of 1945. The surplus intakewas, however being absorbed by the army.(e) The suggestion was made that some financial compensation should be given to men overseas whose release was delayed.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was prepared toconsider any such proposal sympathetically. The general feeling was, however, that it would be unwise to make any announcementwith regard to compensation at the present juncture. If, however, inthe event, the release of men overseas had to be delayed, some financial compensation should be provided.The First Lord of the Admiralty pointed out in this connectionthat consideration would have to be given to the question of reducingthe special rates of pay, which had been fixed for the Services in theFar East, on the assumption that the Japanese war would continue.Summing up the discussion on the main issue, the PrimeMinister said that it seemed essential that the target of 1,500,000should be accepted, and that all possible steps should be taken, short of infringing the principle of release of age and length of service to minimise the extent to which men and women who could not be fully employed were retained in the Forces in this country. The provisionof the necessary shipping for the repatriation of men due for releaseshould be treated like a warlike operation, and the Ministry of war transport should submit immediate recommendations for increasingthe available transport. He suggested that any question of priorities which might arise in connection with the provision ofadditional transport should be decided by the Foreign Secretary onbehalf of the Cabinet.Subject to the views of the Foreign Secretary the statement tobe made by the Minister of Labour should include overall figures of-4] b 2
the strengths of the three Services, and particulars of the shipping and transport difficulties. It would, however, be undesirable to give information regarding the disposition of our Forces by theatres.The Minister of Labour should submit a draft of his statement tothe Man-Power Committee for approval.The Cabinet then considered the proposals for releases from theForces and from Supply Department work up to the %Wh June, 1946.The Foreign Secretary said that the Man-Power Committee had felt that to retain upwards of 2\ millions men and women in the armed Forces at mid-1946 might be more than the country could afford, and that there was scope for substantial economies in theman-power which the Services proposed to retain in order to meetthe requirements laid down by the Chiefs of Staff in their apprecia-tion. The question also arose whether it would not be necessaryto make some reduction in the number of ships in commission,divisions and squadrons which the Chiefs of Staff had postulated as necessary to meet our commitments.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that the apprecia-tion made by the Chiefs of Staff of the Forces required at r,he30th June, 1946, was necessarily based on a number of extremelyuncertain factors, and that events might show that the Forcesactually required at that date were smaller or larger than had been estimated. The Chiefs of Staff would, however, keep the matter under review, and would submit a revised appreciation towards theend of the year.tThe Secretary of State for Air pointed out that, so far as theRoyal Air Force was concerned, a very large part of the man-power required was for Transport Command and Maintenance Command.The Royal Air Force were obliged to keep in being considerablestriking forces in order to support the armies of occupation.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was concernednot only at the numbers of men and women whom it was proposed toretain in the Forces at mid-1946, but also at the very large amountof war production which would still be going on at that date. Wehad hoped to reduce the total expenditure on the Forces in peacetime to something of the order of  500 millions a year, but heestimated, on the figures given in paragraph 9 of CP. (45) 191, thatthe expenditure on the production of munitions of war alone at mid-1946 would be at the rate of  600 millions a year. The estimates for the Service Departments during the current year would have tobe discussed with the Treasury, and thereafter submitted to theDefence Committee, but he was gravely disappointed to learn that notwithstanding the ending of hostilities the amount proposed to be spent on the Services during the remainder of 1945 was as high asthe estimate which had been prepared on the assumption that thewar would continue. He was particularly anxious that there shouldbe a reduction in the resources devoted to the production of Serviceaircraft in order to enable speedier progress to be made in thebuilding of new civil aircraft.The Prime Minister said that it was clearly desirable that thepossibility of securing economies in the man-power required by theServices in 1946 should be pursued further. With regard to theproduction of munitions and equipment for the Services, he would arrange for the matter to be fully reviewed by the DefenceCommittee at an early date.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that a figure of 1,500,000 should be accepted asthe target for releases from the Forces in 1945, and invited the Man-Power Committee at their meeting onthe 1st October to settle the allocation of the increasedfigure of releases between the three Services.
125 &apos;  C.M. 36 (45). &quot;jF g(2) Invited the Minister of War Transport, in consultationwith the Service Ministers, to prepare as a matter of extreme urgency, a list of all practicable measures(including the withdrawal of the Aquitania from theNorth Atlantic run) which could be adopted to increasethe transport available for the return to this country of men in the Services due for release. The foreign secretary was authorised to decide on behalf of theCabinet any questions of priority which might arise between the needs of the demobilisation scheme anidother competing claims on transport.(3) Took note that at their meeting on the 1st October theMan-Power Committee would consider (i) whether it&quot;would be possible to release in 1945, irrespective of theirage and length of service group, some or all of the prisoners of war who had been in enemy hands; and (ii)&apos;what additional number of nurses could be released bythe Services in 1945.(4) Took note that the Minister of Labour and National service would issue a statement for publication in the Press onWednesday morning and would broadcast on Wednesdaynight, and invited him to submit the draft of his state-ment to the Man-Power Committee for consideration at their meeting on the 1st October. Subject to consulta-tion with the Foreign Secretary, the Minister of labour should include in the statement information about the overall strengths of the Services and about transport facilities, but should not include particulars of thestrengths of the Services by theatres.(5) Took note that the Chiefs of Staff would keep under review the strength of the Forces estimated to be required tomeet our military commitments at the 30th June, 1946,and would submit a revised appreciation towards theend of the year to the Defence Committee.(6) Took note that the Joint War Production Staff had beenasked to prepare revised estimates of the numbers ofworkers required for Supply Department work with aview to effecting an additional cut of 300,000 in thenumber employed in Group I industries at the endof 1945.(7) Agreed that a determined effort should be made to effect asubstantial reduction in the resources devoted to pro-duction for the Services, and took note that the DefenceCommittee would review at an early date the presentand future scale of production of munitions, equipment,&amp;c, for the Services; and that account would be takenin this review of the needs of Civil Aviation.(8) Invited the Secretary of State for War to ascertain on whatauthority Field-Marshal Montgomery had made a public statement about the retention of officers in the british army of Occupation, in Germany.United StatesBases in iceland.(previous reference:CM. (45) 35thConclusions,Minute 2.)2. At their meeting on the 25th September the Cabinet had considered what attitude the Foreign Secretary should adopt towards a proposal made by the United States Government for theleasing of bases in Iceland.The Foreign Secretary explained that although on the25th September Mr. Byrnes had agreed to defer presenting a note on the matter to the Soviet Government, it had later been ascer-tained that the American Embassy in Moscow had actuallypresented the note. In these circumstances, he felt that, in orderto minimise any harmful effect arising from the action taken bythe United States Government, we should endeavour to persuade them to ask for the lease of the bases in question for a limited period
as a temporary measure pending the coming into force of thesecurity provisions of the Charter and the admission of Icelandto the United Nations Organisation. It would be understood thatwhen these two conditions had been fulfilled, the whole question ofmilitary facilities in Iceland for the maintenance of world securitywould come before the Security Council. The terms of the com-munication which he proposed to make to Mr. Byrnes had beenapproved by the Chiefs of Staff.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the viewof the Canadian Government had been obtained and that they hadno objection to the line proposed.The Cabinet-Approved the despatch of a letter to Mr. Brynes in theterms proposed by the Foreign Secretary.Allied Control 3.   The Foreign Secretary said that he had had a furtherMachinery       conversation with Mr. Byrnes about the machinery for the control in Japan.        of Japan, and had made it plain to him that if the United States(Previous        Government expected us to work in harmony with them, they mustReference:      consult us in advance before announcing major changes in policy.C.M.(45)35th   He had been given full assurance on this head by Mr. Byrnes, and conclusions,     had provisionally agreed with him that we should accept the minute 3.)      proposal of the United States Government for the constitution of-an Advisory Commission, to be located in the first instance atWashington, on the understanding that the constitution of theCommission would be open to amendment.   The Commission would include  a  representative  of  Australia and,  provided  certain technical difficulties could be got over, a representative of Indiamight also become a member.   If the Cabinet approved he wouldconfirm the agreement by writing to Mr. Brynes.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that he understood that the Foreign Secretary had discussed the matter with Dr. Evatt, who had indicated that he would be satisfied withan arrangement of this kind, provided that adequate provision wasmade for enabling the views of the Dominions with regard to thecontrol of Japan to be taken into account.The Cabinet-Took note with approval of the agreement which theForeign Secretary had reached with Mr. Byrnes withregard to Allied control machinery for Japan.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,28th September, 1945.



</content>
</cab>
