<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/1/0 images: 194-201</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET. Copy No.CM. (45)41st Conclusions.CABINET 44 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Minister s Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Monday, 15th October, 1945, at 5 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H. Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the BoardTrade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. T. Williams,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of War Transport.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Works (Item 1).Mr. Hector McNeil, M.P., Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State forForeign Affairs.Mr. George Buchanan, M.P., joint parliamentary  Under-Secretary  ofState for Scotland (Item 1).The Right Hon. Sir Ben Smith, M.P.,Minister of Food.The Right Hon. Lewis Silkin, M.P.,Minister of Town and country planning (Item 1).The Right Hon. W. Whiteley, M.P.,Joint Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Item 1).Mr. William Leonard, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary (Supply), Ministryof Supply and Aircraft Production(Item 1).General Sir Ronald F. Adam,Adjutant-General (Item 3).Secretariat :Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Bart.,[30777-3]b
CABINET 41 (45).Contents.minute no. Subject.1      Housing....      ....       ...       ...      ....      .--Labour Shortages.2      Dockers&apos; Strike....3      Man-Power: Release of Officers from the Army
1. The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda-relating to housing : (i) CP. (45) 224 : a memorandum by the Minister of Healthoutlining the general statement of housing policy whichhe proposed to make in the debate on the 17th Octoberon the motion by the Opposition on the subject of thehousing shortage,(ii) CP. (45) 226 : a note by the Minister of Works circulating a draft of a White Paper on the temporary housing programme.(iii) CP. (45) 225 and CP. (45) 230 : a joint Memorandum bythe Minister of Health and the Joint parliamentary under-Secretary of State for Scotland and a memo-randum by the Minister of Labour and National service on labour shortages in the building materials and building components industries.(iv) CP. (45) 229 :  a note by the Minister of Health on theprogress made with the programme of permanent houses to be built by local authorities in England and Wales.In the discussion on the proposed statement of housing policy the following points were made :  (a) In view of the difficulties which might often arise in sharingaccommodation in the smaller type of house, it should be made clearthat the appeal to householders who had spare accommodation tomake it available to persons with no home of their own appliedprimarily to those householders who were occupying the larger typeof house. The proposal that requisitioning powers should be usedshould be kept so far as possible in the background. These powers would be delegated to local authorities only in areas where theywere needed and guidance with regard to their exercise would begiven to local authorities by the Ministry of Health.(6) It was explained that it would be unrealistic to propose ahigher target figure of houses to be completed within two years ofthe end of the war than that given by the previous Government.Thus the only alternatives were either to give no target figure or tosay that the Government accepted the target set by the previous government and would do their best to achieve it despite thedifficulties which they had inherited.The Cabinet took the view that it would be preferable to avoid giving any target figure for England and Wales. This would not preclude the joint Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State forScotland from adhering to the figure for Scotland which he hadalready given.(c) The Minister of Health said that he would make it clear in the debate that it was not intended to exclude the use of otheragencies than local authorities in proper cases (e.g., where for special reasons the organisation of the local authority was not equal to meeting the housing needs in the area). At the same time, in orderto encourage the local authorities to the greatest possible efforts, he desired to stress that during the immediate future the Governmentwere relying primarily on them. The undesirability of leading localauthorities to believe that if building were carried out in their areas by some other agency they would be relieved of financial liabilitywould be kept in mind.(d) The Joint Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State forScotland said that he had put forward to the Housing Committeeproposals for reconstituting the Scottish Special Housing Associa-tion and giving it powers, to be used at the discretion of theSecretary of State for Scotland, to build in any area where the localauthority, whether because of lack of resources or for other reasons,was not meeting its housing problem.(e) It was explained that as soon as local authorities had indicated how many houses of the various permanent non-traditional-3] b 2
types they wished to order, the necessary arrangements would bemade for bulk orders and for the control of the price of thecomponents of such houses. The question of placing an order forthe mass production of 50,000 steel houses for England and wales was being pursued and orders had been placed or were being negotiated for Weir and Atholl steel houses in Scotland. Acommittee had now been appointed under the chairmanship of professor Bernal, to select from the numerous systems of non-traditional construction various elements which in combinationwould provide a system which could be recommended for adoption by local authorities.(/) The Minister of Health had arranged to meet representativeoperatives in the building industry on the 19th October in order to enlist their co-operation. He hoped that the addition to the buildingindustry of men returning from the Forces and the progressive reduction in the use of the cost-plus system of contracts for housingwork would help to bring about a better standard of performanceby building workers.(g) The revised arrangements for ensuring that building materials and components were produced in sufficient quantities andin due time were working well. Steps were being taken to lightenthe load on industries where there was now a bottleneck. Thus, toreduce demands on the iron foundry industry, orders were being placed for the supply of steel baths which would be manufactured in a Royal Ordnance Factory. The arrangements for the produc-tion of materials and components covered not only those requiredfor the temporary housing programme, but also those to be used inthe erection of permanent houses by local authorities.(h) The Minister of Health should not enumerate specificallyin the debate the Bills referred to in paragraph 4 of CP. (45) 224,but should merely state that the necessary legislation to confer onthe Government any powers required in the field of housing wouldbe introduced.(i) The statement in paragraph 11 of the draft White paper on the temporary housing programme that the Government proposedto bring forward a Bill to extend the amount of the financial provision made in the Housing (Temporary Accommodation) Actbeyond  150 million should also be omitted, pending furtherconsideration of the form in which authority for the necessaryadditional expenditure should be sought. In this connection it seemed desirable to make the required provision in a form whichwould not make it necessary for the Government to introduce afurther Bill should the total expenditure again have to be raised.(j) The Minister of Works drew attention to the importance of proceeding as a matter of urgency with the Miscellaneous housing bill, which would authorise the Treasury to finance purchases of building materials and components by the Ministry of Works.The Ministry had already incurred considerable expenditure withoutParliamentary sanction, and there would be criticism if the intro-duction of the Bill was delayed much longer.Labour The Cabinet then considered the memoranda by the MinisterShortages. of Health and the Joint Parliamentary Under-Secretary of Statefor Scotland (CP. (45) 225) and by the Minister of Labour and national Service (CP. (45) 230) about labour shortages in thebuilding materials and building components industry.The Minister of Health and the Joint Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State, for Scotland stressed the difficulties which theywere meeting in carrying out the housing programme owing to theshortage of labour, not only in the building materials and compon-ents industries, but also in the building industry itself. TheOpposition were aware of these difficulties and in the motion to be debated on the 17th October specific mention was made of theproblems of labour and materials. The scheme of Class B releaseswas not producing the necessary labour force and the allocations of
labour made were not being implemented. Moreover, even whenbuilding workers were sent to housing sites by the local labourexchange they drifted away to other work.It was pointed out in discussion that the proposal in para-graph 8 (a) of CP. (45) 225 to alter the call-up of men in the forces would require to be examined by the Man-Power Committee, andthat any scheme for recalling ex-employees of building materials and component firms now in the Forces to their old firms, would raise difficulties in administering the scheme of release underClass B. Sufficient time had not yet elapsed to enable the improvedconditions for releases under Class B to take effect, since many ofthe men involved had to be brought from overseas, and it wouldbe better to seek to meet the problem by increasing Class B releasesrather than by embarking on a proposal which would jeopardise the Class B scheme. The matter could best be examined by the Inter-Departmental Committee on Releases from the Forces. Withregard to the proposals for the direction of labour in order to obtainadditional workers in the building materials and componentsindustries, the matter was bound up with the general policy withregard to the future of labour controls which was under considera-tion by the Lord President&apos;^ Committee.In the debate on the 17th October the Minister of Health should state frankly that, while the necessary allocations of labour hadbeen made and the Government were doing everything in their power to ensure that they were implemented, some time must neces-sarily elapse before the progress of demobilisation would enable a really adequate labour force to be built up.The Cabinet    .(1) Authorised the Minister of Works to lay before Parlia-riient the White Paper on the Temporary housing programme annexed to CP. (45) 226, subject to the deletion of the words &apos;&apos; and the Government propose tobring forward a Bill to extend the amount&apos;&apos; inparagraph 11.(2) Subject to the points made in discussion, gave general approval to the statement which the Minister of Healthproposed to make in the debate on the 17th October onthe Opposition motion on the housing shortage.(3) Took note that the Minister of Health would speakimmediately after the mover and that the Joint Parlia-mentary Under-Secretary of State for Scotland wouldwind up the debate.(4) Agreed that the Opposition motion should be accepted, onthe understanding that the Government spokesmanwould reply to any criticisms of the Government&apos;s policymade by Opposition speakers in the course of the debate.(5) Agreed that the proposals made in sub-paragraphs (A),(B) and (C) of paragraph 8 of CP. (45) 225 with regardto labour for the building materials and componentsindustries should be considered by the Man-Power Com-mittee, the Inter-Departmental Committee on releases from the Forces and the Lord Presidents Committeerespectively.-(6) Invited the Minister of Labour and National Service, inconsultation with the President of the Board of Trade,the Minister of Supply ancl Aircraft Production and theMinister of Works, to consider the suggestions made inparagraph 8 (D) and (E) of CP. (45) 225.
2. [The Minister of Labour and National Service reported onthe circumstances which had led up to the strike in the docks, and discussion ensued as to the action which could properly be taken todeal with the. position.The Cabinet were informed that representatives of theemployers and of the Trade Union concerned were to meet onThursday, 18th October. A meeting of the delegates from the dock-yards had also been arranged for the 23rd October. As this was an unofficial strike it would be undesirable to offer to appoint aCommittee of Enquiry, since this would tend to weaken the normal procedure of negotiations between the duly accredited representa-tives of workers and employers. The position in this respect would,however, be different if the terms offered by the representatives ofthe employers were rejected. On the whole, he thought that theright plan would be to watch the position for the next two or three days.Reference was made to the action of the B.B.C. in refusing toallow Mr. Donovan, the Acting Secretary of the Transport andGeneral Workers&apos; Union, to broadcast. The Cabinet were informed of the reasons for this decision. The view was expressed that theposition of the B.B.C. in regard to withholding permission forbroadcasts on such occasions as this, should be the subject of consideration in due course.The Minister of Food gave the Cabinet a full report of thestrike situation particularly in regard to food supplies. Altogetherabout 71 ships were held up. While there was no danger of failure to honour the present week&apos;s ration of meat and bacon, some difficulty might be experienced in maintaining the ration in full inthe ensuing week unless the position improved. The strike wasalso resulting in some difficulties in regard to the sugar position.Furthermore the strike, by delaying the turn-round of ships, would lead to a deterioration in the long-term food position.The Minister of Food said that there was a move on behalf ofthe workers at the wholesale depots in London to refuse to handlemeat which had been delivered from ship or cold store by military labour; and that some road transport workers were inclined to be unwilling to take meat handled by military labour. This might make it necessary to call for more help in the form of military labour; but for the present the Minister of Food thought it wouldbe unwise to use military labour except in the ports.The Cabinet Took note of these statements and agreed that no further action could usefully be taken for the next few days.Dockers&apos;Strike.(previous reference:CM. (45) 39thConclusions,Minute 4.)Man-Power. 3.   The Cabinet were informed that difficulties were beingReleases of      experienced in the working of the release scheme owing to theOfficers from    shortage of Army officers, particularly in Germany and that to meetthe Army.       these difficulties the War Office proposed to delay the release of(Previous        officers in certain groups for periods amounting perhaps to threeReference:      months beyond the date of the release of the corresponding groupCM. (45)36th   of other ranks.   If this was done, Army officers from all theatresConclusions,     would be released at approximately the same dates, and some officersMinute l.)      could be sent from this country to Germany or to other theatresabroad to relieve officers in the earlier age groups who were beingretained owing to the shortage of officers, although men in the sameage groups had already been released.The Minister of Labour and National Service said that he feared that if this plan was adopted it might throw doubt on thestatement made on behalf of the Government that the principle of release by age and length of service would be maintained. Hesuggested, therefore, an alternative plan whereby the shortage of
officers in Germany would be met by retaining individual officers or groups of officers on grounds of military necessity, after the date when other officers in the group had been released. Apart from suchexceptional treatment officers generally would be released at thesame date as other ranks in the same age group. This plan would necessarily result in officers in this country obtaining release at an earlier date than many officers now serving in Germany and in other theatres abroad.After discussion the Cabinet Expressed a preference for the method proposed by theSecretary of State for War, and agreed that action shouldbe taken accordingly.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,15th October, 1945.


</content>
</cab>
