<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/1/0 images: 230-239</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   October 1945.SECRET.CM. (43).46th Conclusions.Copy No.CABINET 46 (45).CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 2Qth October, 1945, at 10 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.-The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C, M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Lord Jowitt, -LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. G. H.:, Hall, M.P.,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. Viscount Stansgate,Secretary of State for Air.The Right Hon. Ellen Wilkinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., First Lord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. Lord Pethick-Lawrence, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. J. J. Lawson, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of War Transport (items-3).The Right Hon. Lord Winster, Minis-ter of Civil Aviation.The Right Hon. Sir Ben Smith, M.P.,Ministry of Food (Item 3). -[30816-3]Mr. Ness Edwards, M.P., Parliamen-tary Secretary, Ministry of Labourand National Service (Item 3).Mr. A. Woodburn, M.P., Pariiamen-tary, Ministry of Supply and of aircraft Production (Items 1-3).Secretariat:Sir Edward Bridges.Mr. Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.
CABINET 48 (45).minute no.134Contents.Subject.ParliamentBank of England Bill.Civil Aviation ....Services to Europe and South America.Prestwick Airport.Dockers&apos; Strike....Ceylon   ....Page.195195197198
195CM. 46 (43).Parliament. 1.   The Prime Minister asked that all Members of the CabinetBank of should make a special point of being in attendance at the House of .England Bill.   Commons on Monday, the 29th October, 1945, to take part in a division which was expected at about 9-45 p.m. on the Bank ofEngland Bill.CivilAviation.(previous kef erence:CM. (45) 43rdConclusions,Minute 2.)Services to europe andSouth America,2. At their meeting on the 18th October the Cabinet, whileapproving in principle the remaining proposals on civil aviationpolicy outlined in CP. (45) 221 and 222, had reserved for furtherconsideration the question of the participation of private enterprisein the proposed European and South American Corporations andhad asked that this point should be further considered by the CivilAviation Committee in the light of the views held by the CivilAviation Group of the Parliamentary Labour Party.The Cabinet now had before them a report by the Secretaryof State for Dominion Affairs (CP. (45) 245) covering a memoran-dum by the Civil Aviation Group of the Parliamentary LabourParty and submitting the considered views of the Civil aviation committee on this point.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the CivilAviation Group pressed very strongly that the Governments plan should provide for fully socialised ownership, operation and controlof civil aviation, and they would be opposed to any provision forthe participation of private interests in the proposed European andSouth American Corporations. The Group were, however, preparedto leave to private enterprise charter services and feeder airlines.The Civil Aviation Committee were satisfied that this would give to private enterprise an undue opportunity of exploiting profitableservices. The real question was whether there should be any scopeat all for private capital in the field of civil aviation. After pro-longed consideration, the Committee had come to the conclusionthat, in spite of the political disadvantages, there were strongpractical grounds for allowing private enterprise to play a strictly limited part in the European and South American Corporations,subject to the stringent controls and safeguards set out in para-graph 7 of CP. (45) 245, and subject to the limits indicated inparagraph 8, viz., a maximum participation of 40 per cent, in theEuropean Corporation and 33^- per cent, in the South AmericanCorporation.In discussion, the following arguments were put forward infavour of excluding private enterprise from all participation incivil aviation :  (a) The programme of the Labour Party had provided for public ownership and control of civil aviation. This was the con-sidered policy of the Party; and it was advocated by the CivilAviation Group, which included many reliable and experiencedsupporters of the Government. There would be great political difficulty in carrying through a plan which was, in part, inconsistent with this policy ana with the views of this Group of government supporters.(b) An attempt to compromise between the principles of public ownership and private enterprise might result in a scheme whichhad the merits of neither. Under the proposals outlined in para-graphs 7-8 of CP. (45) 245, the private holding in the european and South American Corporations would be so limited there wouldbe no equity and no possibility of capital accretion-that therewould be no financial attraction to private enterprise, and it seemeddoubtful whether the railway and shipping companies would be anxious to come in on these terms. Even if they did, they wouldhave no incentive to play an efficient part in the organisation.(c) It would be difficult to negotiate an agreement with theprivate interests on the lines suggested in CP. (45) 245. TheGovernment would first have to admit in Parliament that they were[30816-3] B 2
not proposing full public ownership because they needed the co-operation of private interests over part of the field; and, having thusimplied that they could not do without that co-operation, they wouldhave to try to enlist the assistance of those private interests on theunattractive terms indicated in the memorandum.On the other side, the following considerations were putforward : (d) The main reason for allowing private interests to participate in the European and South American Corporations was to enablethese Corporations to use the facilities already provided by the surface transport interests, in particular, the ticket agencies andother ancillary organisation catering for the traveller. It was important that civil aviation should be enabled to use these existing facilities. To attempt to build up a separate organisation for civilaviation alone would involve substantial delay and disproportionateexpense. These overhead charges were very large : they could notbe carried by civil aviation alone : and the only practical solutionwas to arrange that these ancillary services were provided as acommon service for all forms of transport.(e) If the principle of public ownership was to apply through-out, the operation of new air services would be delayed until thenecessary legislation had been passed. If, on the other hand, thescheme permitted limited participation by the private interests which already had rights to operate airlines, a start could be madeon the basis of those rights without waiting for legislation. It was true that these rights were not exclusive, but the present shortageof civil aircraft would prevent other companies from beginning to operate for a time and legislation to regularise the position couldbe passed at a later stage.In this connection The Foreign Secretary said that, from thepoint of view of foreign policy, it was specially important that anearly start should be made with the establishment of British air services, particularly to South-Eastern Europe.(/) If British shipping companies were not given an oppor-tunity of participating in British civil aviation, there was some risk that they might enter into association with foreign companies for the purpose of civil aviation business.(g) The Minister of Civil Aviation said that, while the terms proposed in CP. (45) 245 might not be financially attractive to private interests, the railway and shipping companies had other reasons for desiring participation in the proposed European andSouth-American Corporations. The shipping companies, inparticular, were interested in seeing that shipping interests werenot unduly prejudiced by civil aviation. From the tentativeenquiries which he had been able to make he had reason to believethat the companies would be prepared to co-operate on the basisoutlined in CP. (45) 245.As regards the point recorded at (c) above, he believed that,if the Cabinet approved the scheme proposed in CP. (45) 245, itmight be possible for him to reach agreement with the companieson the main issues involved before the scheme was announced inParliament.Further discussion showed that it was the general view of theCabinet that the principle of public ownership should be appliedthroughout the whole field of civil aviation. At the same time, itwas recognised that arrangements must be made to enable civilaviation to use the existing facilities, established by the surface transport interests, for handling traffic. The Minister of CivilAviation should therefore say, in his forthcoming announcementof policy in the House of Lords, that, while the principle of public ownership and control would be applied throughout, he was proposing to discuss with surface transport interests the means by which they could best participate, possibly on an agency basis,in the provision of these common services, particularly in respect ofairlines to Europe and South America.
The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that the-Civil Aviation Committee had also given further consideration tothe future use of Prestwick Airport, and they proposed that apublic statement should be made to the effect that: (i) Prestwickwill be designated as an international airport; (ii) B.O.A.C. haveplanned for certain services to be operated via Prestwick, thenumber to be dependent on traffic demands; and (iii) Scotland willbe able to play its full part in civil aviation, both as regards services .and airports, by the opportunities provided for internal services,including services between Scotland and the rest of the UnitedKingdom and direct services between Scotland and the Continent.In discussion, it was pointed out that the concluding words of (iii) above might be taken to exclude Atlantic services; and itwas agreed that these concluding words should be amended so asto read &quot; direct services between Scotland and overseas countries.&quot;&apos;   The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the principle of public ownership should be-applied throughout the whole field of civil aviation, and-that no provision should be made for financial participa-tion by private interests in the proposed European andSouth American Corporations.(2) Invited the Minister of Civil Aviation to include, in his forthcoming statement of policy in the House of Lords,a declaration &quot;on the lines indicated at &quot; X &quot; above.(3) Asked the Minister of Civil Aviation to make a public statement regarding the future use of Prestwick Airportin the terms outlined in &quot; Y &quot; above.3. The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Labour and national Service, gave the Cabinet the latest information about the dockers&apos; strike. Meetings were being held that day and furthermeetings would, if necessary, be held during the coming week-end;but there was as yet no evidence to warrant the belief that the strike would collapse during the week-end.In view of the critical stage of the discussion, Mr. churchill had been asked to defer until Monday a Parliamentary Questionwhich he was to have asked that day. The Cabinet agreed that, ifthis Question were asked, the reply should be to the effect that thiswas an unofficial strike and the Government did not intend to intervene in any way which would jeopardise the working of theconstitutional machinery for the settlement of issues between employers and workers. At the same time, they could not allow the clearance of ships carrying essential cargoes to be held up byan unofficial strike.The Cabinet proceeded to consider a memorandum by theMinister of War Transport (CP. (45) 248) asking that authority should be given for the extended use of military labour for the clearance of ships from the ports. The memorandum stated the classes of ship on which military labour was already being used and asked that, if the strike continued beyond the week-end,military labour should also be used for handling (i) vessels loadingexport cargo; and (ii) irrespective of cargo, vessels whose clearancewould make available sterling tonnage for the import f^ogrammeand thus reduce the need for employing dollar tonnage for thispurpose.There was general support for the view that, in the present emergency, the extended use of military labour for the clearance ofships would be justified. The Secretary of State for War was asked-to consider what further military labour could be made availablefor this purpose.In discussion, it was suggested that arrangements should bemade to enable the Minister of Labour to obtain advice on the extent
to which it would be justifiable to employ military labour in the docks, without having to seek specific authority from the Cabineton each occasion. It was also suggested that there was need forsome standing machinery to review, on behalf of the Cabinet,questions of wages policy and other questions arising from indus-trial disputes. While it was desirable that statements in Parlia-ment about industrial disputes should be made by the Minister ofLabour, it would be helpful to the Minister if there were a smallstanding committee of the Cabinet to which he could refer on matters affecting his colleagues.The Cabinet-  ...(1) Agreed that, if the dockers&apos; strike continued beyond thecoming week-end, the use of military labour for the clearance of ships in United Kingdom ports might beextended to (i) vessels loading export cargo; and (ii)irrespective of cargo, vessels whose clearance would make available sterling tonnage for the import programme.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for theappointment of a Cabinet Committee, under the chair-manship of the Chancellor of the Exchequer, to keep under review questions of wages policy and other ques-tions of policy arising from industrial disputes, and toauthorise such emergency action as might be necessary,by reason of industrial disputes, to maintain supplies and services essential to the life of the community.4. The Cabinet had before them a report by the Chairman ofthe Colonial Affairs Committee (CP. (45) 244) on constitutional reform in Ceylon.The Lord Privy Seal recalled that at their meeting on the11th September the Cabinet had approved the publication of the Soulbury Report. The Report had been published on the9th October, and it was desirable that a statement defining theGovernments attitude towards its recommendations should be made without delay. The Colonial Affairs- Committee proposed that thedraft statement annexed to CP. (45) 244 should be published forth-with as a White Paper in this country and in Ceylon. In his conversations with the Colonial Secretary Mr. Senanayake had made it clear that, now the war was over, the Ceylon Ministers were nolonger willing to proceed on the basis of the 1943 declaration onthe reform of the Ceylon constitution and wished to press for thegrant of Dominion status; and it was doubtful whether, without some concession by His Majesty&apos;s Government which would demon-strate that his mission to London had not been fruitless,Mr. Senanayake would be willing to sponsor the Soulbury recom-mendations before the Ceylon State Council. The Colonial AffairsCommittee had accordingly felt that the proposed statement ofpolicy should include a promise that six years after the introductionof the new constitution the Government would initiate a further review of the constitutional issue in consultation with the ceylon government. The object of this review would be that Ceylonshould take her appropriate place in the Commonwealth with fullinternal self-government under a constitution on Dominion lines.In discussion the following points were raised : (a) Past experience had shown that a promise to take a furtherstep forward in constitutional reform after a fixed period of years was likely to create unwillingness to give a fair trial to the consti-tution in force in the interim period. The proper road towardsthe achievement of Dominion status was by the gradual developmentof new constitutional practice in the working of existinginstitutions.A promise of a review after a period of six years was alsoopen to the objection that the question of constitutional reformCeylon.(previous reference:CM. (45) 30thConclusions,&quot;Minute 3.)
would be a major issue in the general election which would be dueto be held five years after the present reforms were introduced.Paragraph 10 of the draft statement annexed to CP. (45) 244should be recast so as to make it clear that our objective was toenable Ceylon to attain Dominion status, but that this objectivecould be reached only through the evolution of the capacity for self-government based on the practical working of the reformedconstitution now&quot; offered. The statement should not imply that afurther instalment of constitutional reform would follow after a fixed period, irrespective of the progress made.The First Lord of the Admiralty asked that, iu recasting thispart of the statement, special attention should be given to theprobable need for reserved powers in respect of defence and foreignpolicy.(b) The last sentence of paragraph 12 of the draft statementof policy, which made it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government didnot regard themselves as bound by the provision in the 1943 declara-tion that there should be a three-quarters majority of the Council infavour of the reforms, seemed to be inconsistent with the earlier part of the paragraph. If His Majesty&apos;s Government did not intend to be bound by this condition there was no point in referring to it,and some other formula to secure the protection of the minoritiesshould be devised.The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he was willingto omit any reference to the three-quarters majority.(c) The Secretary of State for India drew attention to para-graph 6 of CP. (45) 244, which set out the views of the Govern-ment of India on the Soulbury Report. These views had been fully considered by the Colonial Affairs Committee and he did not feelthat he could press them further. At the same time, he was boundto point out that the proposals were looked upon in India with considerable misgiving.. The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he had goodhope that, now the war was over, some of.the points at issue betweenthe Government of India and the Government of Ceylon would besettled by direct negotiation.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the new constitution for Ceylon should follow the general lines proposed by the Soulbury Commission.(2) Invited the Prime Minister, in consultation with the lord privy Seal, the President of the Board of Trade, theSecretary of State for Dominion Affairs and the Secre-tary of State for the Colonies, to reconsider para-graphs 10 and 12 of the proposed statement of policy inthe light of the points made in discussion.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,26*7*. October, 1945.




</content>
</cab>
