<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/10/0 images: 48-57</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   June 1947SECRETCM. (47)52nd conclusions copy No.   a q^4   ! kCABINET 52 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 5th June, 1947, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attj.ee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison, \ The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,M P. ^Lord President of the Council. I    Secretary   of State   for   foreign     Affairs.&quot;The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood. j The Right Hon. Hugh Daxton, M.P.,M.P.. Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Crlpps,K.C., M.P.. President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for DominionAffairs.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.Tatm pThe Right Hon.Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.Chancellor of the Exchequer.&apos;The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P.. Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. J. Westwood^ M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. The Earl of listowel, Secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Lord Inman, lord privy Seal.The folknving were also presentThe Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.The Right Hon. William Whiteley,J.YJL.J-  .,ParliamentaryTreasury (Item 1).Sir Edward Bridges, Permanent Sec-retary, Treasury.Secretariat.Mr. W. S. MuRRiE.-    Mr. S. E. V. Luke.Secretary,[34108-3]b
CABINET 52 (47)Contents.minute no. Subject. page 1      Parliament     .. .      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....      ....        73Business in the House of Commons.2      Import Programme for 1947-48    ................        733      Double Summer Time        ....................        78
2873CM. 52 (47)Parliament.Business inthe House ofCommons.ImportProgrammefor 1947-48.(previous reference erence:CM. (47) 39thConclusions,Minute 5.)1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.On 9th June the Third Reading of the Agriculture Bill wouldbe taken, and it was hoped to obtain the Second Reading of thePenicillin Bill.10th and 11th June would be the first two days of the Com-mittee Stage of the Finance Bill.On 12th June the Report Stage and Third Reading of the fire Services Bill and the Committee and remaining Stages of the isle of Man (Harbours) Bill would be taken.The Second Reading of the Northern Ireland Bill and the Com-mittee Stage of the Financial Resolution would be taken on13th June. This occasion was likely to be used by government supporters for a demonstration against some of the activities ofthe Northern Ireland Government. The Home Secretary would,however, avoid entering into any discussion of matters for which that Government were alone responsible.2. The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda on the Import Programme for 1947-48 :- CP. (47) 167 : by the Chancellor of the Exchequer covering a memorandum by the Treasury setting out proposals for reductions in the Import Programme and for other measures designed to deal with the problem of the balance of payments;CP. (47) 170 : by the Minister of Food on the questionwhat cuts might be made in food imports;CP. (47) 109 : by the Minister of Fuel and Power on theneed for a positive balance of payments policy; and cp. (47) 169 : by the Lord President proposing certain measures to expand the supply of essential commodities.The Cabinet first discussed the recommendations made inThe Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he had for some time been gravely concerned at the deterioration in the balance of pay-ments position. This deterioration was continuing, and the latest figures were even more unfavourable than those given in cp. (47) 167. In eleven months we had drawn more than halfthe United States credit; and if the present rate of drawing con-tinued the credit would be exhausted as early as the end of 1947.Every effort must be made to stimulate exports, but no possibleincrease in exports could meet the situation, and we were faced withthe alternatives of reducing imports or seeking a further credit.He would be most reluctant to approach the United States Govern-ment for a further credit, and he hoped that it would be possible toavoid this course.The Treasury had originally proposed a cut of  200 million in the import programmes submitted by Departments, of which 150 million was in the food programme. A reduction in the food programme on this scale had, however, been thought too drastic,and the revised proposal now made was that this cut should be 80 million only. The original proposal for cuts of  50 million inthe other parts of the import programme remained unaffected. Theeffect of the proposed reduction of v 130 million in the full import programme could not be precisely estimated, but it might reasonably be assumed that it would postpone the exhaustion of the UnitedStates credit by four or five months. Agreement had been reached on all the proposed cuts except that on food. He had discussed with the President of the Board of Trade whether it would bepossible to secure a greater reduction in expenditure on importedfilms, and they were satisfied that it should be possible to devise ascheme which would save  8-1 million in a full year and about  3 or 4 million in the current year. If the Cabinet approved thisproposal, a new Clause would have to be added to the FinanceCP. (47) 167.[34108-3]B 2
Bill. The cut proposed for raw materials was very small but itwould involve a return to the four-page newspaper. He proposedthat the import of motor spirit should be reduced by 500,000 tons.The Treasury would afford the Ministry of Fuel and Power and theMinistry of Transport all possible help in making arrangements toenable this reduction to be effectively maintained for some years.As regards tobacco, the recent increase in duty had already resultedin a fair reduction of consumption, and he was discussing with thePresident of the Board of Trade the possibility of persuading the manufacturers to make greater use of Turkish tobacco. No dollarshad been refused for the purchase of machinery, though there hadsometimes been difficulty in obtaining deliveries. As regards privatetravel, a reduction of the personal allowance of  75 to  50 would produce a saving of only about  1 million and would add consider-ably to the difficulties of administration. He was therefore inclined to make no change.The proposed cut in the food import programme would involvea reduction, not below the level of consumption in 1946-47, butbelow the improved standard provided for in the programme for1947-48 put forward by the Ministry of Food. The value of our food imports in 1946 had been  555 million, whereas under theprogramme for 1947-48 it would be  790 million, even after theproposed cut of  80 million had been made. He recognised that thevalue of this comparison was affected by the steady rise in prices.Nevertheless, a comparison of the relative volumes of imports for thetwo periods showed that, for 1946, imports were 63 per cent, ofthe imports in 1938 and that, under the reduced programme proposed for 1947^18, the comparable figure would be 78 per cent, of 1938.In paragraph 12 of CP. (47) 167 he had shown the possible lay-outof food consumption after allowing for the proposed cut. Of theexisting rations, that for meat would alone have to be reduced. the suggested lay-out would provide a total calorie intake on approxi-mately the 1946 level.It would be impossible to carry out the programme adjustmentssuggested in CP. (47) 167 in a manner consistent with the strictterms of Article 9 of the Anglo-American Financial Agreement.It was therefore of great urgency that we should obtain the agree-ment of the United States Government to a less restrictive interpre-tation of the provisions of the Agreement. The better course wouldbe to approach the United States Government on a number of specific cases rather than to raise the issue in general terms.Finally, the Chancellor drew attention to certain items of over-seas Government expenditure. Gross military expenditure wouldbe about  140 million in 1947-48, of which some  30 million, mostlyon oil and food, was equivalent to hard currency expenditure. TheService Departments were examining the possibilty of securing some reduction in this expenditure. A further  80 million had to beprovided in 1947-48 for Germany; but he hoped that every effort would be made to reduce this expenditure. Could not the UnitedStates Government be persuaded to accept responsibility for theprovision of food required for the Anglo-American Zones ?The Lard President said that some cuts in the Departmentalimports programmes would be unavoidable. He was, however,opposed to such a drastic cut in the import food programme ashad been suggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. In parti-cular, he saw great difficulty about the proposal for a reduction inthe meat ration. The objections to a severe reduction in the food programme were indeed so great that every possibility of alternativeaction should first be considered. He thought, for instance, thatthe forecast contained in CP. (47) 167 of the likely expansion of exports was unduly conservative. He was, moreover, advised thatthe loss of exports due to the fuel crisis was not likely to be so great as suggested in paragraph 2 of the Treasury memorandum.Had not the export target been set at too low a level, and would it not be possible to attain a level of 140 per cent, of the 1938volume at an earlier date than the second quarter of 19481 Therewas considerable scope for increased textile exports, and he thought
that special efforts should be made to stimulate recruitment of labour for the industry. The whole question of the world shortage of dollars should be taken up with the United States Government assoon as possible. As regards discrimination, might they not agreeto the modification of the Anglo-American Financial agreement on the lines of the draft I.T.O. Charter?The Minister of Food said that the detailed implications of theproposed cut of  80 million in the food import programme hadbeen set out in paragraph 6 of CP. (47) 170. Since the war therehad been a substantial deterioration in our diet, which was nowphysiologically inadequate for those sections of the population whohad no access to canteens or differential rations. Food was itself a raw material; we might import less, but we might be faced witha corresponding, or even greater, fall in our output and exports.Moreover, the programme put forward by the Ministry of Food wasno more than a target, and under present conditions such targetscould never be fully achieved. If the target itself was reduced tothe extent proposed in CP. (47) 167, the final level of food imports would be substantially worse than appeared on paper. The mostserious aspect of the proposed cut was that it would involve twosuccessive reductions in the meat ration. This, coupled with reduc-tions in dried fruit, apples, canned fruit, coffee and poultry, wouldbe very badly received by the public. In any event, he was not clear what purpose the proposed cut would achieve. At the present rateof drawing it would merely serve to postpone the final exhaustion,of the United States credit for one month; and it would not gainany advantage for us in the eyes of the United States Governmentand people. His information (which had been fully confirmed bythe telegram No. 3189 from His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washing-ton) was that the way to impress American opinion was to showthat Britain was a vigorous and thriving concern. A cut of 25 million in food imports, which he was prepared to accept,would make the maximum contribution to redressing the balanceof payments.The President of the Board of T-rade said that it was impossibleto estimate accurately the future trend of exports. There were signsalready of a change from a sellers&apos; to a buyers&apos; market and wewere meeting fierce competition from United States exports in some areas. It was also impossible at this stage to gauge accurately thefull effect of the fuel crisis, as its secondary results were not yetapparent. The difficulty about an approach to the Americans onthe subject of discrimination lay in the fact that many articles onwhich we should wish to discriminate against hard currency areascould in fact be sold more cheaply by the United States. clearly the best course was to take up specific cases with the United StatesGovernment on the lines proposed. He had already circulated tothe Cabinet a paper on the question of textile exports (CP. (47) 172),the proposals in which had been made as part of the concertedprogramme put forward by the Chancellor of the Exchequer. Ifthe other cuts suggested in CP. (47) 167 were not to be made, hewould wish to reconsider the recommendations made in his paper.It should be possible to expand the textile exports to hard currencycountries, and everything possible was being done, by propaganda and other methods, to attract labour to the industry. The response,was, however, slow and no substantial increase in output could be looked for until new machinery had been installed and extensivereorganisation had taken place. As regards the import programmegenerally, he thought that it was essential to take action now whichwould postpone the exhaustion of the United States credit. Thearguments set out in CP. (47) 170 showed an optimism for whichthere were no grounds. He would not have agreed with any proposalfor reduction of the level of the diet below that of 1946, but nosuch proposal was made : what was at issue was the extent to whichfood supplies should be increased. At the present level of prices the proposed reduction of  80 million seemed unavoidable. If prices should fall substantially there would be a case for reconsidering thefood programme generally at a later stage.
The Minister of Health said that he believed that in 1945 itwould have been a feasible policy to call on the country to makeheroic sacrifices in order to avoid the need for asking for the originalUnited States credit. This opportunity had, however, been missedand it was now impossible to impose sufficiently drastic cuts to enable us to dispense with a further credit from the United States Govern-ment in 1948 or 1949 if dollar prices remained at their present level. If, on the other hand, dollar prices fell substantially, theexisting credit would last longer and we should find the UnitedStates Government much more willing to offer a further loan or commercial credits or to support an application for a loan from theInternational Bank. The cuts proposed in CP. (47) 167 would merely create despondency and impede the production drive; and, inparticular, a second cut in the meat ration would have a most disastrous-trous effect on output in such industries as coalmining, agricultureand iron and steel manufacture. Moreover, he did not see how thiscut in the meat ration could be justified if dollar expenditure onfilms was to continue virtually at the current rate for the greaterpart of 1947. We must use our dollar resources prudently and hewould not oppose a cut of as much as  25 million in the food import programme. Any further cut would, however, merely create con-ditions which would lead the United States to believe that anyfurther assistance to us would be wasted.The Lord Privy Seal said that the success of the productiondrive was largely dependent on an increase in the supply of food and other consumer goods. There was a great fund of goodwilltowards the United Kingdom in the United States and he believedthat if a suitable representative could be sent there to explain our difficulties there would be no lack of willingness to give us further help on reasonable terms.The Minister of Labour said that the proposed cut of 80 million in hard currency food imports would have a disaterous efect on production and would dishearten the housewives of thecountry, who had had to endure a great strain and were anxiouslylooking for some improvement in living conditions. In his view the right course was to encourage the Americans to believe that wehad the will and the capacity to overcome our difficulties and totake any risk involved in limiting the cut to  25 million.The Minister of Agriculture supported the view that a cut inthe food import programme of the order suggested in CP. (47) 167would have an adverse effect on output. The rate at which homefood production could be increased should not be exaggerated.Thus, the restoration of the livestock industry was necessarily aslow process and it should be realised that, though egg production was going up, poultry keepers were still receiving only about one-sixth of their pre-war supplies of feeding-stuffs. Again, therewere difficulties in providing dock and rail transport facilities forfish traffic which made it unwise to rely on any very great increasein the amount of fish which could be supplied.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that the Cabinet should keep in mind that there was a world-wide shortage of dollars which,in the long run, would compel the United States Government to take steps to redress their balance of payments. He had always stressed the importance of developing^ so far as possible, the home produc-tion of those commodities which had to be imported from hard currency areas and of guiding our exports to hard currency areas,and he hoped that these policies, which were now recognised inparagraph 33 (v) and (vii) of the Annex to CP. (47)&apos; 167, wouldbe pursued more actively than hitherto. It was also important thatour exports should be carefully scrutinised with a view to limiting the demands made by them on raw materials of which there wereacute shortages at home. He was opposed to the proposed cut of 80 million in food imports, and he suggested that more active steps should be taken to obtain food supplies from Russia and other
The Minister of Health said that he believed that in 1945 itwould have been a feasible policy to call on the country to makeheroic sacrifices in order to avoid the need for asking for the originalUnited States credit. This opportunity had, however, been missedand it was now impossible to impose sufficiently drastic cuts to enable us to dispense with a further credit from the United States Govern-ment in 1948 or 1949 if dollar prices remained at their present level. If, on the other hand, dollar prices fell substantially, theexisting credit would last longer and we should find the United \States Government much more willing to offer a further loan or commercial credits or to support an application for a loan from theInternational Bank. The cuts proposed in CP. (47) 167 would merely create despondency and impede the production drive; and, inparticular, a second cut in the meat ration would have a most disastrous-trous effect on output in such industries as coalmining, agricultureand iron and steel manufacture. Moreover, he did not see how thiscut in the meat ration could be justified if dollar expenditure onfilms was to continue virtually at the current rate for the greaterpart of 1947. We must use our dollar resources prudently and hewould not oppose a cut of as much as  25 million in the food import programme. Any further cut would, however, merely create con-ditions which would lead the United States to believe that anyfurther assistance to us would be wasted.The Lord Privy Seal said that the success of the productiondrive was largely dependent on an increase in the supply of food and other consumer goods. There was a great fund of goodwilltowards the United Kingdom in the United States and he believedthat if a suitable representative could be sent there to explain our difficulties there would be no lack of willingness to give us further help on reasonable terms.The Minister of Labour said that the proposed cut of 80 million in hard currency food imports would have a disaterous efect on production and would dishearten the housewives of thecountry, who had had to endure a great strain and were anxiouslylooking for some improvement in living conditions. In his view the right course was to encourage the Americans to believe that wehad the will and the capacity to overcome our difficulties and totake any risk involved in limiting the cut to  25 million.The Minister of Agriculture supported the view that a cut inthe food import programme of the order suggested in CP. (47) 167would have an adverse effect on output. The rate at which homefood production could be increased should not be exaggerated.Thus, the restoration of the livestock industry was necessarily aslow process and it should be realised that, though egg production was going up, poultry keepers were still receiving only about one-sixth of their pre-war supplies of feeding-stuffs. Again, therewere difficulties in providing dock and rail transport facilities forfish traffic which made it unwise to rely on any very great increasein the amount of fish which couJd be supplied.The Minister of Fuel and Power said that the Cabinet should keep in mind that there was a world-wide shortage of dollars which,in the long run, w-ould compel the United States Government to take steps to redress their balance of payments. He had always stressed the importance of developing^ so far as possible, the home produc-tion of those commodities which had to be imported from hard currency areas and of guiding our exports to hard currency areas,and he hoped that these policies, which were now recognised inparagraph 33 (v) and (vii) of the Annex to CP. (47)&apos;167, wouldbe pursued more actively than hitherto. It was also important thatour exports should be carefully scrutinised with a view to limiting the demands made by them on raw materials of which there wereacute shortages at home. He was opposed to the proposed cut of 80 million in food imports, and he suggested that more active steps should be taken to obtain food supplies from Russia and other
non-dollar sources. He also urged that the Cabinet should be furnished with the best available forecast of the likely trend of dollar prices over the next year or two.The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs said that it wouldbe unwise to reduce the food import programme to such an extent as to involve a second cut in the meat ration. The possibility ofobtaining additional food supplies from the Dominions should be actively pursued and every effort should be made to remove anyimpediment to our obtaining such supplies which might be con-tained in the non-discrimination provisions of the Anglo-AmericanFinancial Agreement. Discussions with a view to increasing theproduction of Southern Khodesian tobacco had already been under-taken and he believed that, if we were prepared to offer a firmcontract for, say, five to ten years, we should be able to get much larger supplies from this source. He hoped that it would be possibleto abolish bread rationing at a very early date and he supported the proposal that there should be an increase in the sugar ration.In general, he believed that the right course was to restrict the cutsin the food import programme to the  25 million suggested by theMinister of Food and to proceed on the assumption that within areasonable period there would be a break in dollar prices whichwould ease our difficulties.The Minister of Education said that, in his view, the cabinet should approve an expenditure of  790 million on food imports during 1947-48, on the understanding that any fall in food prices which took place during that period would be reflected in increased imports of food. At the same time, there should be a further reviewof the import programme in order to ensure that expenditure wasbeing concentrated on those foods which were of most importanceto the classes of the community on whom we mainly depended forincreased production.The Foreign Secretary said that he hoped that the cabinet would be provided with further information about the proposal toreduce expenditure on imported films in this country before theywere asked to take a final decision on it. He would wish to consider what effect a step of this kind would have on our relations withthe United States Government in other matters.The Cabinet then considered the memorandum by the lord president (CP. (47) 169) proposing certain measures to expandthe supply of essential commodities.The Lord President said that if it were possible to stimulateworld production of food-stuffs and other essential commodities ourown difficulties would be greatly eased. He hoped that the proposals in paragraph 10 of CP. (47) 169 would be generally approved.The following points were made in discussion : (a) The President of the Board of Trade pointed out that para-graph 10 (b) of CP. (47) 169 proposed that reports on the supplyprospects of such commodities as timber and steel should be madeto the Lord Presidents Committee. In fact, however, this hadalready been done and he doubted whether any useful purpose wouldbe served by further reports at the present time. The Departmentsconcerned would naturally keep the position under review.(b) The Secretary of State for the Colonies said that he pro-posed to circulate to the Cabinet a memorandum showing what steps were being taken to expand the production of essential commodities in the Colonies.(c) The Foreign Secretary said that careful consideration wouldhave to be given to the proposal in paragraph 10 (e) of CP. (47) 169for suitable publicity on the theme of expanding supplies of vitalcommodities, since the same approach would not be suitable for all foreign countries.
jjouDieSummer Time.(Previous^Reference:CM.(47)&apos;51stGoneluiSIinute 6.)3. At their meeting on 3rd June the Cabinet had agreed toconsider whether an assurance might be given to the national farmers&apos; Unions that the Government would not introduce double summer time in 1948.The Secretary of State for Scotland and The Minister ofA griculture urged that this assurance, which would go a long way towards obtaining the co-operation of farmers in the campaign forincreased food production, should be given.The Cabinet Agreed that the Prime Minister should give an assurance to the National Farmers&apos; Unions of England and Scotlandthat the Government would not introduce double summertime in 1948.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,5th June, 1947.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed to resume discussion of CP. (47) 167, CP. (47) 170and CP. (47) 109 at their meeting on 10th June;(2) Invited the President of the Board of Trade to circulate a memorandum on the proposal to reduce expenditureon imported films in the United Kingdom;(3) Subject to the points noted at (a) and (c) above, approved generally the proposals made in paragraph 10 of cp. (47) 169 and invited the Ministers concerned toconsider what steps should be taken to implement them.


</content>
</cab>
