<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/10/0 images: 180-186</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS  DOCUMENT IS THE   PROPERTY OF^HIS ^BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S ^GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   August 1947SECRETCM. (47)68th ConclusionsGopy Mo.    4 BCABINET 68 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W. 1, on Friday, 1st August, 1947, at 2-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Arthur Greenwood,M.P., Minister without Portfolio.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C., M.P., President of the Boardof Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. J. Westwood, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.TheTlfiTAWTTTRightHon. The Earl of secretary of State forIndia and Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. John Wilmot, M.P.,Minister of Supply.The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.Sir   edward the Right Hon. Alfred Barnes, M.P.,Minister of Transport.Lord  Pakenham,  Chancellor of the duchy of Lancaster.Bridges,    permanent secretary, Treasury.Secretariat :Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.[34134-1]b
CABINET 68 (47)Contents.SubjectBalance of Payments ....Transport of Goods.Capital Investment.Hours of Work.Redeployment of Labour.Production Committees.Efficiency of Management.Emergency Powers Bill.Convertibility of Sterling.
195CM. 68 (m)The Cabinet resumed their consideration of the memorandumby the Chancellor of the Exchequer on the balance of payments(CP. (47) 221), and also had betore them a memorandum by theMinister of Labour (CP. (47) 220) covering a scheme for securing an increase of production through lengthening the hours of workin certain industries.The Minister of Transport pointed out that, if the railways were to play a full part in the drive for increased production, itwould be necessary to give priority to all their demands for materials and equipment.It was pointed out that absolute priority could not be given,and that the Central Economic Planning Staff, in consultation withthe Departments concerned, were already considering what steps would have to be taken to enable the railways to meet the demands which would be made on them during the coming winter.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that it would be necessaryto curtail the use of steel for commercial building and that someslowing down of the housing programme would be inevitable.The Minister of Health said that, while he recognised thatthere must be some reduction in housing, he hoped that any cuts would be selective.There was general agreement that the application of theprinciple that capital investment should be curtailed should be worked out by the Central Economic Planning Staff in consultationwith the Departments concerned.Hours of The Lord President said that, with the Minister of Labour, heWork. had arranged to meet representatives of the Trades Union Congresslater in the day and that, if the Cabinet agreed, he would putforward suggestions for the working of longer hours on the lines indicated in the Annex to CP. (47) 220. He would also make itclear that it would be against the national interest for the workers to make excessive claims for higher rates of remuneration for anyovertime worked.There was general approval of the Lord Presidents suggestion and it was agreed that the appeal for longer working hours shouldbe based rather on the country&apos;s needs than on monetary incentives.The Minister of Transport said that the adoption of the five-day week in many industries had imposed a heavy strain on transport,and he hoped that so far as possible any extra hours of work wouldbe secured by reverting to a six-day week.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was considering whether any modifications could be made in the P.A.Y.E. scheme inorder to give workers a greater incentive to work for longer hours.He believed, however, that the discouraging effects of P.A.Y.E. were greatly exaggerated.The Minister of Labour pointed out that the building workers had now accepted a scheme of payment by results, and it was agreedthat some reference should be made to the desirability of extending the system of payment by results.Redeployment The Lord President said that he also proposed to suggest to of Labour. the representatives of the Trades Union Congress that in presentcircumstances some measure of negative or positive direction oflabour was desirable.The Minister of Labour agreed that this should be done. he also thought it would be desirable to take up with the Trades UnionCongress the question of facilitating the employment of Poles andother European volunteer workers in under-manned industries.In discussion there was general agreement that the Control of engagement Order should be re-enacted and that all employers should be required to engage workers through the employmentexchanges. Some doubts were expressed about the wisdom of attempting to use powers of positive direction under peace-time conditions, and it was suggested that the Minister of Labour might[34134-1] B 2Balance ofPayments.(previous reference erence:CM. (47) 67thConclusions,Minute 2.)Transport ofGoods.capital investment.
emergency powers Bill.explore further, in consultation with the Minister of Food, whetherit would be possible to devise means, short of the war-time directionof labour, to ensure that all the country&apos;s man-power was usefullyemployed. In particular, the possibility of reducing from four to two days the period for which persons might stay in hotels withoutsurrendering ration cards should be considered.Production The Minister of Labour said that some reference should be madeCommittees.    to the desirability of encouraging the establishment of productioncommittees.There was general support for this suggestion, on the under-standing that steps would be taken to ensure that such committeesdevoted themselves solely to matters connected with raising the levelof output.Efficiency of The President of the Board of Trade said that cases would ariseManagement,   in which it would be necessary in the interests of production toreplace inefficient managements.The Foreign Secretary suggested that in any public statementof the Governments intentions there should be recognition of thefact that the majority of managements were efficient and willing toco-operate with the Government.The Cabinet then discussed the proposal in paragraph 39 of cp. (47) 221 that an Emergency Powers Bill should be introduced.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that parliamentary counsel had advised that a Bill would be necessary in order toenable new regulations to be made, since the Supplies and Services(Transitional Powers) Act, 1945, and the Emergency Laws(Transitional Provisions) Act, 1946, merely continued in force regu-lations which had been made under the war-time emergency powerslegislation. This Bill would be a short measure and could, in his view, be passed before Parliament adjourned for the Recess.The Prime Minister said that a Bill on the lines suggested bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer seemed desirable. The cabinet might consider a draft of the Bill at their meeting on 5th august and the Opposition should be consulted before the Bill was intro-duced in order to ascertain whether they would facilitate its passage.The Lord President suggested that consideration might begiven to the possibility of providing in the Bill for the continuationafter 31st December, 1947, of the regulations covered by the Emer-gency Laws (Transitional Provisions) Act, 1946.The Lord, Chancellor said that the co-operation of the Oppo-sition would be more readily obtained if the duration of the newmeasure were limited to a year, with power to extend it for furtherperiods by resolution of both Houses of Parliament.Convertibility The Cabinet then discussed the effect on the United Kingdomof Sterling.      dollar resources of the obligations with regard to convertibility of sterling which had been entered into by His Majesty&apos;s Government.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that there was no evidenceof a marked increase in the drain on our dollar resources since15th July, when the obligation had come into force under the LoanAgreement to make freely convertible sterling receipts from currenttransactions of all sterling area countries. It should be borne inmind, however, that before 15th July wre had been obliged to agreethat some of the sterling receipts of individual sterling area countries should be convertible. Moreover, other countries such asCanada and the Argentine had also insisted on converting intodollars their sterling receipts for supplies sent to us, and this tendency had been aggravated by the increasing world shortage of dollars. In July 1947 there had been an exceptionally high with-drawal, amounting to 700 million dollars, from the United Statescredit, but he hoped it would not be necessary to draw more than about 300 million dollars in August. He recognised that we should now have to seek relief from our convertibility obligations under the
197CM. 68 (17)Loan Agreement, but be was convinced that it bad been worth while to accept these obligations in view of the advantages which theUnited States credit had given us in the period of reconversion.He had arranged for a special check to be kept on sterling trans-actions and though, so long as sterling was ^ an internationalcurrency, it&apos; was impossible to obtain an absolutely precise balance sheet at any given time, he was confident that the information available to the Treasury enabled them to keep a close watch onmovements of sterling.The Minister of Health said that he hoped the Chancellor ofthe Exchequer would circulate a memorandum to the Cabinetanalysing the effect on our dollar resources of our convertibilityobligations both under the Loan Agreement and under agreements with particular countries, such as the Argentine. The drain onour dollar resources resulting from our convertibility obligationsseemed to be greater by far than any savings which would beachieved by the reductions in expenditure proposed in CP. (47) 221.Further, the policy of allowing countries in the sterling area to convert sterling into dollars was directly contrary to the interestsof our export trade.The President of the Board of Trade said that the object ofthe convertibility provisions in the Loan Agreement had been to stimulate the revival of world trade and the drain on our dollar resources had arisen, not because of convertibility as such, but because we had been unable to supply foreign countries with thegoods they wanted and had therefore been obliged to allow themto use their sterling balances to buy goods from the United States.He had discussed our difficulties with regard to convertibility withthe United States Under-Secretary of State on the previous day,and had also pointed out to him that in our present situation wecould not contemplate being debarred by the non-discriminationprovisions of the Loan Agreement from buying food in softcurrency areas.The Lord, President said that it would be useful if the Chan-cellor of the Exchequer would give the Cabinet information aboutthe extent to which our dollar resources had been drawn on for therelease of the sterling balances held by countries such as Egypt.The Cabinet should also have an opportunity of considering theproposed settlement with regard to the Indian sterling balances.The Foreign Secretary said that he had considered further thesuggestion made at the previous meeting (CM. (47) 67th Con-clusions, Minute 2) that an approach should be made to the UnitedStates Government with a view to initiating discussions on thepossibility of reducing the drain on our dollar resources resultingfrom our obligations in regard to non-discrimination and con-vertibility and our financial responsibilities under the Agreementrelating to the Anglo-American Zone in Germany. He felt that itwould be undesirable to give formal notice under Article 12 of theLoan Agreement without some preliminary exchange of views withthe United States Government, and he hoped that the Cabinet would authorise him to take the matter up with the United States Secre-tary of State informally in the first instance.In further discussion it was pointed out that some statement would have to be made in the debate in Parliament on the subjectof convertibility and non-discrimination. Any such statement would have to be very carefully worded.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that the necessary resources should be made avail-able to enable the transport industry to meet theadditional strain which would be imposed by increased production.(2) Approved in principle the proposal that there should be a curtailment of capital investment projects other thanthose contributing to export or to import saving.
(3) Agreed that detailed proposals for giving effect to the ^decisions in (1) and (2) above should be worked out bv -the Central Economic Planning Staff in consultationwith the Departments concerned.(4) Approved the proposal that the Lord President and the!Minister of Labour should discuss with the Trades &apos;Union Congress a scheme for increasing production by working longer hours on the lines set out in the annex to CP. (47) 220. &apos; I(5) Authorised the. Lord. President and the Minister of Labour Ito  discuss   with  the  Trades   Union   Congress thepossibility  of   reinstituting  a  positive  or  negative 1direction of labour.(6) Agreed that the Control of Engagement Order should be Ire-enacted and that the Minister of Labour, in consulta- jtion with the Minister of Food, should consider whether jit would be possible to institute some more positiveform of direction of labour.(7) Took note that the Lord President and the Minister ofjLabour, in the light of their discussion with the TradesUnion Congress, would furnish the Prime minister with a statement which he might make in the Parlia-1mentary debate dealing with the extension of hours of fwork, the redeployment of labour and the establishmentof production committees.(8) Approved the proposal that the appropriate departments should have power to take action where production wasbeing impeded by inefficient management.(9) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in the light of thepoints made in discussion, to arrange for the prepara-tion of an Emergency Powers Bill, and to circulate a draft of the Bill for consideration by the Cabinet attheir meeting on 5th August.(10) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would circulate a memorandum analysing the effect on UnitedKingdom dollar resources of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment&apos;s convertibility obligations (i) under the LoanAgreement, (ii) under any agreements made with individual countries outside the sterling area, and(iii) under any agreements for the reduction ofaccumulated sterling balances.(11) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer to circulate amemorandum on the settlement which he proposed tomake with regard to the sterling balances held in India.(12) Invited the Foreign Secretary, the Chancellor of theExchequer and the President of the Board of Trade toconsider what would be the best approach to the UnitedStates Government with a view to the initiation of discussions on the possibility of reducing the dollar expenditure which His Majesty&apos;s Government wereincurring as a result of their non-discrimination andconvertibility obligations and their financial responsi-bilities under the Agreement relating to the Anglo-American Zone in Germany.(13) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer, in consultationwith the Foreign Secretary and the President of theBoard of Trade, to prepare a statement which might bemade in the Parliamentary debate on the subject of. His Majesty&apos;s Governments non-discrimination andconvertibility obligations and their financial responsi-bilities under the Agreement relating to the Anglo-American Zone in Germany.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,1st August, 1947


</content>
</cab>
