<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/10/0 images: 356-362</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
H$S DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   November 1947 .SECRET^CM. (17)89th conclusions cabinet 89 (47)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 18th November, 1947, at 11 a.m.Copy No. 48Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,   M.P.,    Chancellor   of   theExchequer.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. The Earl of listowel, Secretary of State for burma.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowttt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. P. j. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Viscount Hall, FirstLord of the Admiralty (Items 1-4).The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Item 1).The Right Hon. C. W. Key, M.P.,Minister of Works (Item 1).The Right Hon. Arthur Henderson,K.C., M.P., Secretary of State for Air(Item 4).The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power(Item 1).Mr. H. A. Marquand, M.P., Paymaster-General (Item 1).The Right Hon. William Whiteley,M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Treasury (Items 2-5).Secretariat:Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.
CABINET 89 (47)contents minute no. Subject page 1      Allocation of Resources       ....      ....      ....      ....      ....     109Steel Priority System.2      Parliament      ........       ........       ............     109Business in the House of Commons.3      Budget................................     109Disclosure of Information by Mr. Hugh Dalton.4      Criminal Justice Bill ....       ....      ....       ....      ....      ....     110Capital Punishment.5      Industrial Disputes   ....       ....      ....       ....      ....       ....     112Savoy Hotel Strike.
allocation of Resources.Steel PrioritySystem.(previous reference:CM. (47) 79thConclusions,Minute 9.)1. On 9th October the Cabinet had invited the Minister for economic Affairs to arrange for the existing system of prioritiesto be reviewed. They now had before them a memorandum by theMinister for Economic Affairs (CP. (47) 308) covering a reportby the Paymaster-General on a revised steel priority system whichhad been worked out in consultation with the Departments mainly concerned.The Paymaster-General explained that, when the revised dis-tribution scheme for steel was working effectively, it would suffice to have a scheme of selective priority which would ensure delivery of limited quantities of steel the lack of which was seriouslyimpeding production. Meanwhile, however, it would cause unduedislocation to withdraw the general priority granted to the pro-grammes covered by the Prime Ministers directive (CP. (47) 92),and it was therefore proposed that the system of selective priority should at first apply only to the new priority programmes (i.e.,export industries, shipbuilding and import-saving industries). Thegrant of priority symbols for orders under the programmes coveredby the Prime Minister&apos;s original directive would, however, be gradually restricted and the system of selective priority would eventually be applied to these programmes also. It was impossibleto say whether the new steel distribution scheme would be whollysuccessful in ensuring that deliveries of steel matched allocations,but the situation would be kept under continuous review and revised proposals would be submitted to the Cabinet if necessary. It was desirable that an announcement should be made about the new system in order to reassure the export and import-saving industries andto remove any misunderstanding about the scope of the scheme; andhe had intended to make a statement in the House of Commons inthe terms of Annex II to CP. (47) 308. He now proposed, how-ever, to amend that draft in the light of the comments which hehad received since his memorandum was circulated.Discussion showed that there was general agreement with theprinciples of the revised scheme outlined in CP. (47) 308. various suggestions were, however, made and approved for amendment ofthe draft statement.The Cabinet (1) Approved the proposals for modifying the steel prioritysystem set out in Annex I to CP. (47) 308;(2) Invited the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Paymaster-General to revise, in the light of the Cabinefs discus-sion, the draft announcement in Annex II to cp. (47) 308; and took note that the Paymaster-general would make the announcement in the House of commons on 20th November;(3) Took note that the Chancellor of the Exchequer would sub-mit a further report on the priority arrangements for materials other than steel.Parliament.  .Business inthe House ofCommons.Budget.Disclosure ofInformationby Mr. HughDalton.(previous reference:CM. (47)88thConclusions,Minute 1.)2. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons during the following week.3. In reply to a Question in the House of Commons on theprevious day the Prime Minister had indicated that the Governmentwould not oppose, if it were pressed, the proposal that a SelectCommittee should be appointed to enquire into the circumstances inwhich Mr. Hugh Dalton had disclosed to a newspaper correspondentinformation.about the contents of the Budget. The Cabinet were now informed that the Opposition still favoured the appointment ofsuch a Select Committee. It would not be appropriate that thismatter should be left to a free vote of the House; and, if the motion for the appointment of the Committee was to have the sup-port of the Government Whip, it was desirable that it should be34563-3 n 9
brought forward by the Government. Some Government supportershad represented that the scope of the enquiry should be wide enoughto enable the Committee to investigate the action taken in newspaperoffices on the receipt of this information about the contents of theBudget; and it was agreed that the Governmenfs Motion shouldbe framed in somewhat wider terms than that originally proposedby the Opposition.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the Government should give notice of a motion in the following terms : &quot; That a Select Committee beappointed to enquire into all the circumstances relatingto or associated with the disclosure of Budget informa-tion by the Chancellor of the Exchequer on Wednesday,12th November.&quot;(2) Invited the Chief Whip to arrange for this Motion, and a consequential Motion defining the composition and termsof reference of the Select Committee, to be taken at atime during the current week when it would be possiblefor the Prime Minister to take charge of the debate.criminla justice Bill.capital punishment.(previous reference:CM. (47) 84thConclusions,Minute 1.)4. The Cabinet had decided on 3rd November that, when theissue of abolishing the death penalty was raised by way of amend-ment to the Criminal Justice Bill, the decision should be left to a free vote of the House of Commons and that this vote should be taken on the Report Stage of the Bill. They now considered, in the lightof further memoranda submitted by the Home Secretary(CP. (47) 306) and the Secretary &quot; of State for Scotland(CP. (47) 310), whether the Government should tender advice tothe House of Commons on this issue and, if so, what that adviceshould be.The. Cabinet first considered whether it was their duty to adviseParliament that the abolition of the death penalty would involve serious risks to law and order. On this point The Home secretary said that there was no reliable evidence that the abolition of the death penalty in foreign countries had been followed by a signifi-cant increase in the number of murders. It was true that those concerned with the enforcement of the law in this country wereapprehensive that the abolition of the death penalty would befollowed by an increase in crimes of violence; but their predecessorshad in the past opposed for the same reason the abolition of the death penalty for offences less serious than murder and their appre-apprehensions had not in the event proved justified. On the other hand,The Secretary of State for Scotland urged that the experience of countries like Norway and Sweden did not justify the conclusion thatthe death penalty could safely be abolished in this country, whereconditions were different. He attached special importance to therisk that the withdrawal of this penalty might lead to an increasein crimes of violence by gangsters in large centres of population likeGlasgow and London.In further discussion, it was suggested that, even though opinion was divided on the merits and on the. question whether the abolition -tion of the death penalty would in normal circumstances give riseto an increase in the number of murders, the Cabinet might be ableto agree that this was not an appropriate moment at which to takethe risk of abolishing the death penalty. There was a substantial body of opinion which would support the view that, whatever con-convictions were held on the merits, it would be inopportune to introducethis experiment in the unsettled conditions following a major war,when the number of violent crimes %vas abnormally high and respect for the sanctity of human life had inevitably been impaired by thecircumstances of war. It was difficult for the Government to judge in present circumstances whether a majoritv of the electors desired that capital punishment should be abolished. Would it not be pre-transferable, therefore, if the Government, while avoiding any expression
of opinion on the merits, advised Parliament that this was not anopportune moment at which to make this important change in thelaw?Some Ministers felt that the Government would not be justifiedin offering even this limited advice to Parliament. In their view this issue was one for the personal conscience or judgment of theindividual, and Parliament should be left to decide it by a free vote without advice of any kind from the Government. The pre-ponderant view of the Cabinet was, however, that the Governmentcould not properly refrain from offering any guidance and should advise the House that, whatever the merits, the present was not an opportune moment for abolishing the death penalty.The Cabinet then considered whether Ministers who dissentedfrom this view should be free to make their position clear. It wasagreed that such Ministers should refrain from speaking in the debate. It was also agreed that they should not be required to vote against the abolition of capital punishment. The issue was thusconfined to the question whether they should be free to vote infavour of abolition or whether they should abstain from voting.Some Ministers argued that it would be inconsistent with theprinciple of collective responsibility that some members of theCabinet should vote contrary to the advice tendered to the house on behalf of the Government. Ministers who dissented from thatadvice should, therefore, abstain from voting.On the other hand it was argued that, if on this occasionMinisters were free to abstain from voting, there would be no practical harm in allowing them to vote in the opposite Lobby; forthe Division lists would be closely strutinised and a Ministersabstention would be construed as implying dissent from the advicetendered on behalf of the Government. There would also be practical difficulty in requiring junior Ministers to vote in accorcl-ance with the Governments advice, or to abstain from voting, whenit was known that differing views were held by members of theCabinet. Apart from these practical points, a more important consideration was that some of the Ministers who favoured theabolition of capital punishment regarded this as a matter of personalconscience and would consider themselves justified on this basis inclaiming a right to vote in favour of abolition. This was not, after all, a political issue; and it was the tradition of the Labour party that a considerable measure of latitude should be allov-ed to individual -duals on matters of personal conscience. The unity of the cabinet was not likely to be undermined if its individual members were allowed to vote on this question according to their personal convic-tions. There were precedents for conceding a free vote to Ministers,as well as back-benchers, on matters of this kind. Thus, when theLabour Government introduced their Sunday Performances (Regu-lation) Bill in 1931, they had left the issue to a free vote and one member of the Cabinet had voted against the Bill on Second Read-ing; and, when the National Government introduced a similar Billin 1932, two members of the Cabinet had voted against it on SecondReading.The Cabinets conclusion was that Ministers who diss&quot;ented fromthe advice which was to be offered on behalf of the government regarding the abolition of the death penalty should refrain fromspeaking in debate on this question but should be free to voteaccording to their personal convictions.The following points were&apos; also raised in the discussion :  (a) If Parliament deprived the criminal courts in this country of their power to impose the death penalty, the Government wouldbe asked whether they were justified in maintaining capital punish-ment as a penalty for certain offences in the British Zones inGermany and Austria and in other areas still under military government.
(&amp;) The continuance of the death penalty in the Colonies wouldalso be called in question. The Secretary of State for the colonies said that in those Colonies where there was an unofficial majority on the Legislative Council the decision in this matter did not rest with the United Kingdom Government. This Government had full responsibility only in those Colonies whose legislation was within his control; and in respect of those territories he would argue thatthe population had not yet reached a stage of civilisation at whichit was appropriate to abolish capital punishment.(c) There would also be a demand for a consequential curtail-ment of the powers of courts-martial to impose the death penaltyon members of the Armed Forces. The Cabinet were informed thatthe Service Ministers would agree that, if the criminal courts inthis country ceased to have power to impose the death penalty for murder and treason, courts-martial should no longer have power topass sentence of death for those offences. They were satisfied, bow-ever, that the death penalty should be preserved for certain militaryoffences.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that in the proceedings on the Criminal justice bill the Government should advise Parliament that thepresent was not an opportune time for abolishing capital punishment; and took note that the Home secretary would define the Governments attitude towards thisquestion when moving the Second Beading of the Billin the House of Commons;(2) Reaffirmed their decision of 3rd November that the decisionon this issue should be left to a free vote, preferably onthe Report Stage of the Bill in the House of Commons:and agreed that Ministers who dissented from the advice which was to be tendered in accordance with Conclu-sion (1) above should be free, if they so desired, to vote for the abolition of the death penalty, though they should refrain from expressing in debate views contrary tothat advice;(3) Invited the Minister of Defence to consider, in consultationwith the Service Ministers, what consequential altera-tions should be made in the disciplinary codes of the armed Forces if the civil courts in this country weredeprived of the power to impose the death penalty.Industrial 5.   The Cabinet were informed that on the previous night,Disputes. when further efforts had been made to prevent the delivery of oilSavoy Hotel to the Savoy Hotel, there had been a disturbance in the course of strike. which 23 persons, including Mr. A. W. J. Lewis, M.P., had been(Previous arrested and charged. There was some reason to believe that the reference: organisers of this strike would try to make a demonstration duringCM. (47)88th the Royal Wedding procession, and the police were making arrange-Conclusions,    ments to deal with any such attempt.Minute 2.) The Cabinet were also informed&apos; that the Court of Enquiry had completed their consideration of the issues involved in the strike,and that the Minister of Labour hoped to have a full report from them by the following day.The Cabinet-Took note of these statements.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,18th November, 1947.


</content>
</cab>
