<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 11-24</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*lia Britannic;;y&apos;ii Government.)MINISTRY OF RECONSTRUCTIONReport (No. VII.) for the period ending August Hat, 1910.ADVISORY COUNCIL.Arrangements have been made for the Chairmon and Vico-Chairmen of the Advisory Council to meet wookly to adviso the Minister on specific references which it does not appear necessary or desirable to refer to an ad hoc Committee.     During the period under review a very valuable discussion has taken place on the Report of Sir Archibald &quot;rilliamsonTa Committee on Electric Supply on which it has been decided to prepare a Report.TRANSITIONAL ECONOMICS.Priority and Rationing of Materials..A statement of the general, arrangements v/hich havo boen approved for the allocation of materials, so far as may be found necessary during the transitional period-after the war, is attached as an appendix to this ReportRaw Materials.Sub-Committees have reported on the supply and allocation after the Far, of all the non-ferrous metals and the principal ferro-alloys.     These reports were laid before the/tmperial Conference Committee on Raw Materials and have been communicated to the Departments interested.COMMERCE AND PRODUCTION.Anti-Dumping Legislation.Section II of the Advisory Council have been considering the following reference:-
(l) &quot;To consider the recommendations of LordBalfour of Durleighf8 &quot;Committee upon Commercial and Industrial Policy&quot; that legislative) action should bo taken in the United Kingdom for the prevention of &quot;dumping&quot;, and to advise as to the precise character of such legislation.     By &quot;Dumping&quot; is understood the salo of goods in tho markets of the Unitod Kingdom at prices lowor than those at which tho goods aro currently offered in the country of manufacture.(2) To consider what steps, if any, should botaken to givo effect to the view of Lord Balfour of Burleigh&apos;a Committee that the producers of this country are entitled to be protected in their home market against tho introduction of &quot;sweated&quot; good3, that is to say &quot;goods produced by labour, which is not paid at Trade Union rates of wages, where such exist in the country of . origin of the goods, or current rates of that country, if there are no Trade Union rates&quot;,Their Report will be available almost immediately.Standardization of Railway E0uiprpont.Section I of the Advisory Council have presented their Report on the Standardization of Railway Equipment.     They state that so far as it is practicable to carry out, standardisation is desirable in the national interests and have suggested certain immediate steps towards this end.Disposal of National Factories.The question of tho. disposal of National Factories and. the principles governing such disposal have received consideration and a memorandum submittedto tho &apos;*&apos;ar Cabinet with a view to settling tho principles on which the Departments may proceed.Allied P03W&apos;ar Requirements.Representations have been mado to this Ministry from time to time with regard to the desirability of securing for manufacturers in this country a proportion of the contracts which will ultimately have to be placed
It)in connection with various work for the Reconstruction of Belgium and Northern France, and for meeting the post-war requirements of other allied countries) and proposals have been submitted for creating tho necessary  . international machinery anri an organisation composed mainly of manufacturers for the so purposes.Transport and Storage.A considerable amount of information which has been collected bearing on the problem of internal transport after the war has been placed at the disposal of the House of Commons Select Committee oh this subject and arrangements have been made for this Department to keep in touch with the work of the CommitteeThe Departmental Committee on Storage and Transit facilities has submitted an interim, report in support of proposals of the Port ana Transit oxecutivo Committee for providing temporary storage at or near the Parts during demobilisation.Borings for Coal in Ireland.,This Department having been authorised by the &quot;.&quot;ar Cabinet to expend a sum not exceeding  15,000 on oxporimontal boring?, for coal in Ireland, arrangements wore made with the Ministry of Munitions to undertake this work.     A plot of land has been secured and operations will commence at a very early date.ENGINEERING TRADES (HE&quot;&apos; INDUSTRIES) COMMITTEE.This Committee has made considerable progross with its work, and has submitted a number of reports which have been received from the various Branch Committees which it
has boon found necessary to 00t up to doal with the , different sections of the Engineering Industry.     Those roporta deal, amongst other subjects, with &apos;&quot;ire Machinery., Textile Machinery, Kollow-waro and Pros sod Work, Scientific Instruments, Diesel Oil Engines and tho Motor Industry.     In connection with the last named, the Committee endorsed the report of the Branch Committoo which submitted a schedule of the materials required by the different firms engaged in tho Industry for experimental models required for the continuance of the Industry and for its development on new and larger linos and in fresh directions.     This recommendation and a number of similar proposals ha&quot;o been approved by the Department and stens are being taken to gi-e effect to them,LABOUR AMD INDUSTRIAL ORGANISATION. Demobilisation of Pivotal Men.In conjunction with the Departments concerned proposals have been submitted for the release, before general demobilisation, of pivotal men in industry.Out-cf-Work Benefit,Proposals as to the scale of Out-of-r&apos;ork Benefit to discharged soldiers during the transitional period have been submitted to the War Cabinet and approved, subject to Treasury&apos; sanction.In consultation with the Departments concerned tho question of the inclusion of Queen Mary&apos;s Army Auxiliary Corps and similar organisations in the scheme of army demobilisation Is being considered.Ro-Settloment of Civil War Workers-.Considerable progress has been made with tho
preparation of schemos for the re-settlement of civil war workers.     It has been decided to appoint a Civil Ro-settlemont Co-ordination Committee analogous to the Army Demobilisation Co-ordination Committeo and consist-ing of representatives of the Departments concerned.Vfar Pledges.A draft Bill has been prepared by tho Departments concerned dealing with the restoration of Trade [hiion conditions after the war.Appi -enticeshiA scheme of financial assistance from the State for apprenticeship interrupted by war service has boon prepared in conjunction with the Ministry of Labour, and is being discussed with tho Departments interested,Trado Organisation,Considerable progress has been made&apos;with the formation&quot;of Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees on the linos indicated in the memorandum (appendix 2) attached, and seventeen of these Committees are now at work or roady to commence work.:     In addition threo Committees which were formed, have been, or are about to bo, recognised hy the Ministry of Labour as Joint, Industrial Councils.     Arrangements have been made for the Cotton Control Boards with certain additions, to deal with such Reconstruction euestions as may be submitted to them and. special Committees have been formed in the Iron and Steel Trades and tho Chemical ^VSMMt*i4^ industries for the purpose of Assisting the Government on commercial questions affecting their industry.
Railways and tho Whitloy Report.Section III of the Advisory Council having; been asked to report on the possibility of applying the proposals of tho &quot;&quot;hitloy Report to railways, recommended that an Industrial Council or Councils f,or railways should be formed as soon as possible and that a conference should, be called with a view to the formation of such a Council,     Enquiries are being made as to the desirability of proceeding further on the lines of these recommendations.RURAL DEVELOPMENT AHD LAND.The Report of the Agricultural Policy Committee has been received and circulated to the other Departments concerned for their observations.     Meanwhile the desirability of giving offset to the recommendations contained in the Report and the administrative machinery that would, be required, for- the purpose are being thoroughly investigated.Rural Industries.A Report on Rural Industries and the place they may occupy in rural life has been completed.   Propocals are noir being formulated with a vie-   to the promotion of such industries as a part of village reconstruction.SOCIAL DEWjLOPMENT.Ministry of Health.The draft Bill containing proposals for the establishment of a Ministry of Health for England, and Wales was referred, to tho Horn3 Affairs Committee of the War Cabinet cn its appointment in June.     The Committee considered, the Bill in detail on four occasions, and on
4h17tho 2nd August provisionally settled the terms of tho draft, with a view to the introduction of the Bill immediately after the recess.Adult Education.An interim report has been received from the Adult Education Committee dealing &apos;&quot;ith Social and Industrial conditions in relation to Adult Education,&quot;GENERAL.Termination of Emergency Legislation.&apos;Arrangements have &quot;been made to furnish the House of Commons Select Committee on the Termination of Emergency Legislation with a considerable amount of material on matters coming within the ?cope of their enquiry.Tho Future of the Auxiliary Patrol.At the request of the Admiralty a Conference jof tho Departments concerned was held to consider what &quot;arrangements could be made to secure the future of tho Auxiliary Patrol-which is mainly composod. of British fishermen and fishing-boats.     The Admiralty had found it difficult to frame any definite proposals in view of the fact that the control and responsibility for the fishing industry in the United Kingdom is vested in five different Departments,.:   On the suggestion of the Minister tho Admiralty agreed, to further consider tho matter in consultation with the various Departments concerned.
MINISTRY OF RECONSTRUCTION.PRIORITY AND THE RATIONING OP MATERIALS IN THE RECONSTRUCTION PERIOD.An essential condition of any reconstruction is tho re-ostablishmont of the industries upon which the wealth cf the oountry primarily depends.    But In order to rebuild British industries it is necessary, not merely to possess the raw materials of manufacture, but to be In a position to transport and distribute these materials in such a way as to ensure that they are placed whoro they are most needed and used economically. It is impossible to predict accurately the conditions under which civil Industry will be resumed when tho war ends.    But it is probable that in the period immediately following peace there will be a deficiency of certain materials, and it is not unlikely that want of adequate shipping facilities may cause the demand for a good many commodities to be in excess of the supply. It la essential, however, that the country should be prepared to meet all possible contingencies, and it is possible that peace will be followed by a period in which It may be necessary to exercise some degree of supervision over the distribution of materials, in order to secure that the manufacturing aotivity of the country proceeds along lines corresponding to the more urgent national needs.    It is the desire of the Government that there should be as little control over industry as possible, wad for as short a time as possible, and that so far as is practicable any control t^iat may be found to be necessary in the different industries shall be directed by the Industries themselves.Tho Ministry of Reconstruction appointed last yoar a Committee under the chairmanship of Sir Henry Blrchenou$i, to consider tho principles which the State should pursue in
giving priority to certain kinds of work, and in allocating materials in the reconstruction period, on the assumption that after the war there will be a shortage of certain commodities. This Committee have now reported to the Minister of Reconstruo-tion, who, upon the basis of the Report, has made oertain recommendations whioh have been accepted by the War Cabinet. Following the general lines of the Committeers Report, the Government have now decided to establish forthwith a Post-war Priorities Committee consisting of Ministers and attached to the existing War Priorities Committee of the War Cabinet. This Committee will determine the broad lines of policy with regard to priority,    There will at the same time be established a Standing Council responsible for consultation with, and for securing the advice of, the representative trade bodies and for furnishing the Cabinet Committee with considered counsel and assistance in the detailed exeoution of the policy determined upon.    This Standing Council will consist of representatives of industry, commerce, and labour, together with some four or five persons representing the Government Departments directly concerned.The Standing Council will, under the direction of the Post-war Priorities Committee, review the existing machinery of priority and allocation, both generally and within the different industries, and consider what adjustments are necessary in order to adapt it for war purposes.    A guiding consideration in this connection will be the deptre of the Government gradually to transfer the control of industry -so far as control may be found necessary - to trade organisa-tionaj and in any sciiomos whioh the Standing Council may formulate for determining prioi-i-cy or allocation, the advice of trade organisations of a representative or comprehensive
character will be sou/$tt and will be of the neatest importance..It is known that in many cases manufacturers are anxious to make, at en early date, various adaptations in their plant and machinery in order to enable them to return to their pre-war work or* in certain oases, to develdp after the war some new line of manufacture.    They naturally, therefore, desire to know what IdndS of work will take precedence in the reconstruction period. It is proposed accordingly to set up as soon as possible an Organisation competent to deal with applications for post-war priority, and provisionally to grade orders as well as to issue (In ouoh quantities as may be possible) material and machineryfor experimental work.The Ministry of Reconstruction has already received a number of detailed recommendations as to the rationing of materials from various Committees appointed by the Department to consider the position with regard to different groups of commodities.    The general substance of these recommendations, and of subsequent reports of a similar nature, will be passed to the different Industrial Councils and Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees for their consideration, and it is hoped thai the . Councils and Committees will make suggestions upon these Reports to the Ministry of Reconstruction,    It is also hoped that they will, on their own initiative, consider and discuss, in respect of the different trades which they represent, any problems in connection with the post-war supply and distribution of raw material to which they would wish to call special attention, and that they will communicate their views to the Ministry of Reconstruction,    The Terms of Reference to tne different expert Committees which have hitherto advised the Ministry of Reconstruc tion upon raw materials have been aa followsjT
tt(l) To consider and report uponi-The nature and amount of the supplies of materials and foodstuffs which, in their opinion, will be required by the United Kingdom during the period which will elapse between the termination of the war and the restoration of a normal condition of trade;   and. the steps which should be taken to procure these supplies, having regard toj-(a) The probable requirements of India, the Dominionsand Crown Colonies for such supplied at the close of hostilities;(b) The probable requirements of belligerents endneutrals for 3uoh supplies at the close o  hostilities^(o) The sources from which, and the conditions under which such supplies can be obtained and trans-ported, and in particular, the extent to which they might be obtained from the United Kingdom or within the Empire or from Allied or Neutral countries.(2)To consider also whether any measure of control will require to be exercised and the extent and character of such control&quot;,Xt is proposed to submit these Terms of Reference, so far as they concern cotton, to the Cotton Control Board which la acting as an Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee, and it is proposed that others of the Interim Committees where the subject has not already been dealt with should be asked to consider the problem in connection with the material with which they are concerned along the lines of a somewhat similar Reference.The problem of the supply of raw materials is obviously one which cannot be considered by this country in isolation from the Dominions and Colonies and the Allies.    It is contemplated that it may be necessary to create &amp; Central Raw Haterials Supply Board for the United Kingdom which, working in conjunction with the Standing Council on Priority and co-ordinating domestic interests, will also be associated, on the one hand with an inter-imperial Board, and on the other with a Board representing the Allies,    Any Central Board of the kind would require to keep
(i 2*in close touch at all points with-expert trade opinion, and with the trade committees, if. whilst securing supplies, it is to be successful in using to the fullest practicable extent, and in restoring to their full.and free activity as soon as possible the normal agencies of trade and industry.
MINISTRY OF  RECONSTRUCTION.- . . MEMORANDUMON THE ORGANISATION  AND  WORK OFINTERIM  INDUSTRIAL RECONSTRUCTION COMMITTEESTHc Government lias til ready expressed its approval of the proposals put forward in the Whitlcy Report that in each industry which has reached a sufficient level, of organisation there should be established a -Joint Standing Industrial Council consisting of equal numbers of representatives of Associations of Employers and Trade Unions. The Ministry of Labour has been entrusted with the duty of assisting industries in carrying Into effect those proposals. ....A large number of such Councils is already in process of formation ; but in certain industries, owing to various reasons, progress has as yet been slow. In the latter industries Ithe Ministry of Reconstruction has undertaken, in association with the Board of Trade land the Ministry of Labour, to promote the formation of Interim Industrial Reconstruction [Committees consisting of equal numbers of representatives of organisations of Employers land Trade Unions. If, however, an Industrial Council is subsequently established in lone of these industries, it would naturally supersede the Interim Industrial Reconstruction i Committee.Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees, although set up at the suggestion of die Government, will be independent bodies responsible to the trades they represent, j,ind they will themselves determine what functions they will assume and what they [diould leave or delegate to other bodies. It is not necessary that they should, in every rase, undertake all the various brandies of work mentioned in this memorandum. It is jliopcd to make the fullest use of existing representative organisations in an industry, fund where the circumstances permit to ask them to undertake some or all of the duties [of Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees. It should also be observed that the formation of an Interim Committee in an industry does not prejudice the establishment hi a Trade Board if in the opinion of the Ministry of Labour such a step is desirable.WORK OP INTERIM INDUSTRIAL RECONSTRUCTION COMMITTEES.Although the scope of the work undertaken by an Interim Industrial Reconstruction ommittee is a matter to be determined by those directly concerned, it is not intended [hat their activities should necessarily be linxited to the questions on which they are jisked by the Government to advise and assist. Many questions of importance to the Industry represented will arise from time to time, and. it is hoped that such questions Kill be considered apart from, and in addition to, the references received from Govern-nent Departments. In this connection attention is called to the following suggestions, hich are, however, not intended to lay down a hard and fast programme, nor are they xhaustive.35j   Wt. 14183-102.   Pfs. 1.0.   2,000.   7/18.   V. &amp; S., Ltd.
(j) The Promotion of Industrial Organisation.It iB hoped that the extension and development of representative industrial organisa-tions, amongst both employers and employed, will bo considered by each Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee with a view to the subsequent establishment of an Industrial Council where the organisation of the industry is sufficiently developed for this purpose. In this connection it may be noted that fully representative employers&apos; associations and trade unions will enlarge the field of common action in each industry and become a means of securing understandings which will enable all engaged in the industry t co-operate freely in restoring and increasing its productive capacity and to assist in its progressive development.(2) Post-War Arrangements.Amongst the questions which an Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committee might well consider are : (a) Demobilisation as it affects the industry ;(b) Problems of employment (e.g., wages, hours, apprenticeship and training, workingrules and conditions, unemployment);(c) The problem of raw materials (e.g., supply, method of allocation in case of shortage);(d) The financial position of the industry ;(e) The improvement of processes and methods.RELATIONS BETWEEN THE COMMITTEES AND GOVERNMENTDEPARTMENTS.(1) Arrangements have been made whereby Government Departments are supplied with the necessary information regarding Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees as they are established, so that they may consult the Committees as occasion arises. Similar information has been supplied to the various Government Committees which may desire to consult Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees.(2) The Government will seek the advice and assistance of Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees on problems affecting the various industries, and specially prepared memoranda and documents on specific questions will, be circulated from time to time by Government Departments. . ,(3) Reports or recommendations of Government Committees will be circulated to Interim Industrial Reconstruction Committees for their observations.(4) Interim Committees will be supplied with the terms of reference of Government Committees in which they are likely to be interested to enable the former to lay their views before Committees if they so desire.(5) The Ministry of Reconstruction will arrange to put Interim Committees in touch with Departments and Committees.Ministry , of Reconstruction,2, Queen Anne&apos;s Gate Buildings, Westminster, S.W.I.

</content>
</cab>
