<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 60-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
^This Document is the Property ,of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the use of the Cabinet.   September 1918.     * tSECRET.r    ,   \ *IN order to obtain a decision of tiie War Cabinet on the main question of policy involved, I circulate the draft of a &quot; Restoration of Pre-War Practices &quot; Bill, together with a letter from Sir Stephenson Kent to Dr. Addison, and some notes on the clauses. Some points in the draft are the subject of conference between the Ministers of Reconstruction and Labour and myself.WINSTON S. CHURCHILL.Whitehall Place, S.W. 1, September 3, 1918.JDear Dr. Addison, August 30, 1918.In accordance with the wish expressed in your letter of the 24th June to Mr. Kellaway, I have held a series of conferences to consider the drafting of a Bill to give statutory effect to the war-pledges given to labour by the Government.In addition to the gentlemen whom you suggested as members of this Conference, we have also had the assistance of Sir Frederick Liddell, Mr. Bellhouse, of the Home Office, who was personally concerned in the settlement of many of the substitution agreements arranged by that Department, and Mr. Hutchinson, of your own department.The full membership of the Conference has, therefore, been as follows : Sir Stephenson Kent (in the Chair). Sir Frederick Liddell, Parliamentary Counsel. -  Mr. Delevingne, Home Office. Mr. Bellhouse, Home Office. Mr. Wolfe, Ministry of Munitions. Mr. Miles, Ministry of Munitions. Sir David Shackleton, Ministry of Labour. Mr. CummingB, Ministry of Labour. Mr. Greenwood, Ministry of Reconstruction. Mr. Comyns Carr, Ministry of Reconstruction. Mr. Hutchinson, Ministry of Reconstruction. Mr. 0. S. Hurst (Ministry of Munitions), andMr. C. Delisle Burns (Ministry of Reconstruction) (Joint Secretaries).A number of meetings have been held, and I now enclose a draft of the Bill which we have prepared, together with some notes on the various clauses.1 might explain that the view which we have generally taken of our functions is that we should prepare a Bill designed to give the fullest practicable efiect to the definite pledges given by the Government or to undertakings contained in agreements between employers and employed. Our proposals appear in detail with sufficient clearness, I hope in the clauses of the Bill itself and the notes upon them.Meanwhile, I ought to add in regard to restriction of pre-war practices the representatives of your own Department maintained the minority view that the widest possible interpretation should be given to the term &quot; Government pledges,&quot; and that, for example, the Military Service Acts which have resulted in the Government taking men from industrial life and thereby indirectly forcing dilution of labour and other changes in practice imposed an obligation upon the Government to see that.the workers Were given the right to have pre-war practices restored after the war.I should also point out that we have consciously been inconsistent in framing our proposals in regard to priority of employment in that we have, in our majority opinion, gone beyond the bounds of definite Government pledges or undertakings. We have done so for the reason that it has been represented at our conferences that on grounds of general policy the Government are bound to make some wide provision in this respect. At the same time we recognise that the clauses on this subject which we have drafted raise very large questions of policy on which we can express no more[760] * B
than our own individual views, and that the policy suggested will require the most anxious consideration in the highest quarters. Also, we have confined ourselves to the post-war period, and we have, therefore, necessarily passed over such a question as that of securing priority of employment for soldiers discharged during tho war.With regard to the &quot; Notes on the clauses,&quot; I should like to add emphasis to the importance of clause 1 (4), providing for the modification by agreement of the legal obligation to restore pre-war practices. I might also point out, on clause 4, that in cases where verbal agreements only have been reached, it will be possible by consent of the parties to get them put into writing and have them registered.Certain points have also been raised by Mr. Greenwood on the final drafts, but simply in order to save time in amending or adding to the notes, perhaps I may leave it that you will obtain his views direct from him.Finally, I ought to mention that the notes are compiled mainly from a legal standpoint, and are not intended to provide the kind of &quot; brief &quot; that a Minister might want in introducing the Bill, but I have also had prepared from you, and enclose, a summary of the clauses in the draft Bill prepared last autumn, in case you may like to compare them with the present draft.Yours sincerely, &apos;   (Signed)        STEPHENSON KENT.P.S. I should wish to add that I am strongly of opinion there is a very real demand for, and grievance in the delay, in the production of this Bill. I realise at the same time the Government will have trouble with the newly enfranchised voters.Notes on Clauses. Clause 1.THIS clause provides generally for the restoration of pre-war trade union rules, customs, and practices, whether restrictive of production or employment, or not, in certain classes of establishments. The establishments to which the section applies are all controlled establishments, all establishments to which section 7 was applied, and all establishments whose wages have been regulated either by an Order or by Awards made under Part 1 of the Munitions of War Act, 1915. It further applies to establishments in which trade union practices have been relaxed by agreement. These agreements have been generally made under the auspices of Government departments, especially the Home Office.Sub-section (I).(a.) An employer in whose establishment a change of practice has occurred is required at the end of the war to restore any practice over which he has control, and to permit the restoration of any practice under the control of his workmen, e.g., such a practice as that a bricklayer should only lay a definite number of bricks, and he must continue or permit the continuance of the practice for one year from its restoration.(6.) This paragraph, in effect, re-enacts, with slight modification, section 15 of the Munitions of War Act, 1916. It provides that where non-union labour has been employed on any class of work on which previously union labour was employed, the employer must get rid of the non-union labour after the war, and employ union labour for a year.(c.) This paragraph applies to a case where an industry not previously carried on in the establishment has been introduced during the war. The owner is placed in the position he.would have been if the industry had been carried on before the war.(d.) This paragraph re-enacts paragraph (3) of the Treasury Agreement made with the Engineers on 25th March, 1915. Its effect is that, where an invention is introduced during the war, the class of workmen to be employed on this work after the war shall be determined by the practice prevailing before the war in the case of work most nearly analogous to it.Sub-section (2).This sub-section places any establishment which had entered into an agreement relaxing trade union practices (this has often been done under the direction or with
the approval of the Home Office or any other Government department) in a position similar to controlled establishments. If the agreement is registered the employer is bound at the end of the war to restore or permit the restoration of any trade practice relaxed in consequence of the agreement.Subsection (3).This sub-section provides that the liability to restore only arises where the majority of the workpeople affected by the&apos; relaxation or their trade representatives have served a notice as prescribed by the Ministry of Labour requiring the restoration. The notice will specify the nature of the practice referred to, and the agreement where there is one, and the date of its registration.Sub-section (4).This sub-section provides a penalty of 51. a day for failure to comply with the duty to restore. It is, however, provided that where a registered agreement has been entered into modifying the obligation to restore, the agreement shall be a good defence in respect of any breach of the obligation if the breach is authorised by the agreement and a substantial majority of the workers affected by the modification are either parties to the agreement or members of a union and party thereto.Sub-section (5).Sub-section (6).This sub-section specifies the establishments to which sub-section (1) applies. The Committee were of opinion that these establishments should be defined in such a manner as to enable the workmen and employers in any establishment to know at once whether or no they Ifall within the section. It would be possible to apply the section to all establishments which had done any munitions work at all in the war, but the practical difficulty of deciding after the war what is the meaning of munitons work would be very great and would lead to constant litigation. The Committee adopted the principle of giving the benefit of the section to all establishments which had been brought actively within the control of the Acts.Sub-section (7).This sub-section re-enacts paragraph 9 of the second Schedule to the Munitions of War Act, 1915 (the Treasury Agreement). It was desired to make it clear on the face of the Bill that the rights of the employer and of the workpeople are not affected save as specifically mentioned in the foregoing sub-sections.Clause 2.The object of this clause is to provide that all persons employed who have left their posts either to join the military or naval forces as soldiers, or in any women&apos;s corps, or to work in controlled establishments, shall have a right to be employed by their old employer in preference to other persons.tSub-section (1).Paragraph (a.) This paragraph extends clause 3 of the second schedule to. &quot; The Munitions of War Act, 1915,&quot; and gives the right of priority, not only to soldiers, but also to men in the navy or air forces, and includes women enrolled in any of the forces of the Crown.Paragraph (b.) This completes the re-enactment of paragraph (3) of the second schedule, and gives the right of priority to persons who were in the owners employ-ment when the establishment became controlled. 1&quot; Paragraph (c.) This extends the right to war munitions volunteers. It is pro-vided that these persons will be entitled to priority of employment from their old employer on &quot; similar work,&quot; and at the same rates and conditions as other persons of the same class or grade who are for the time being employed by him. If he employs no such persons, the rates and conditions will be those of persons of similar position and skill in the neighbourhood.[760] B 2
Sub-section (2).This sub-section defines &quot; similar work &quot; as work undertaken by persons of the same trade and of the same class1 or grade as that to which the person belonged before the war, but in the case of persons who had completed their term of apprenticeship before the war, but were paid as improvers, and not the full rate, it is provided that these persons shall be paid the rate which they would normally have reached if they had remained with their old employer during the war.Sub-section (3).Priority will be given on the condition, 1, that the man is willing and able to do the work ; 2, that he has given notice to the employer in writing, as prescribed by the Minister of Labour; 3, that he was not dismissed from his late employer on the ground of misconduct or incompetence.Sub-section (4).The workman, if he has once accepted or refused a bond fide offer of re-employ-ment, cannot, if he leaves his employer, again enforce the privilege, but, subject to this, the right to re-employment continues for one year from the date of notice.Sub-section (5).This provides a penalty of 101, any part of which penalty may, by the direction of the Tribunal, be paid to the workman if an employer fails to give preference, or, if haying re-employed the man, he, within the period of one year, attempts to evade the obligation of the Act by dismissing him or by reducing his remuneration.Clause 3.This clause deals with the registration of those agreements previously mentioned in clause I (2) and 1 (4);   The classes of agreements which may be registered aretwo: \;     : :r &apos; &apos; -; -        yr- -- : -       &quot;: &apos; &apos; -y:     -:1. Agreements providing for the relaxation of any trade practice during the war H   in establishments not necessarily engaged&apos; on munitions work.   These agreements are dealt with in clause l&apos;(2)&apos;.\ 2. Agreements modifying the obligation of employers imposed by clauses 1 and 2 of this Act or by the Second Schedule to the Munitions of War Act, 1915. This class of agreement is dealt with in clause.!, sub-section (4)&apos;. v.......        -\,t ^ i-^-vwr ^xiffimMi Ifll^BtffilEither party may forward any such agreement provided it is in writing to the Minister of Labour, who must register it if he is satisfied that the document is genuine and that such an agreement has, in fact, been made. Where the agreement is made by an association of employers, any employer who was at the date of the agreement or thereafter a member of the association is bound.Clause 4.This provides that where liability to restore or to give priority of employment has attached to&apos;an employer, and he sells the business, the liability shall attach to the purchaser.   &quot;&apos;   &apos;Clause 5.Sub-section (1).A fine for an offence under this Act is only recoverable before an industrialtribunal    ! - m] i: &quot;1: i;&apos; &apos;!Suh-section (2).A trade union may institute proceedings for an offence under the Act. Sub-section (3).On a prosecution before an industrial tribunal if the court is satisfied that the breach is not due to refusal or unwillingness&quot; to comply with the Act, but is due to a genuine doubt as to the nature of the t!rade practice prevailing before Ijhe war, or as to the exact meaning of the obligation, the court may make an order declaring the true interpretation of the obligation. Any subsequent failure to carry out the obligation as so interpreted will be an offence.
oSub-section (4).An employer, though lie receive a notice from the workmen, when they claim either restoration of a trade practice or priority of employment, will, often be in genuine doubt as to the extent of his obligation. The notice may be in very general terms or the exact nature of the pre-war practice may be in doubt. He may have a difficulty in deciding the remuneration which he ought to offer to an employee seeking re-employ-ment. The clause therefore provides that within one month after receiving notice he may apply to the tribunal which, after hearing any party interested, may make an order declaring the true interpretation of his obligation. If he fails to comply with the obligation as so interpreted, he is liable to a penalty. The order of the court will be registered, and open to inspection at the Ministry of Labour.Clause 6.This clause sets up industrial tribunals to deal with offences against this Act. In the first place, these industrial tribunals will consist of local munitions tribunals. The local munitions tribunals will therefore have jurisdiction under this Act, and will continue to exercise their jurisdiction under the Munitions of War Acts. The panels of assessors, and the regulation of the procedure of the tribunals, will, after the termina-tion of the war, be transferred from the Minister of Munitions to the Minister of Labour, or possibly the Secretary of State. Until alteration.of the procedure is made, the present procedure in Munitions courts will apply, but the industrial tribunals will continue after the cessation of the Munitions Acts.sClause 7.This clause carries out two Government pledges : 1. That strikes should not be unlawful after the termination of the war. It should be noted, however, that the clause as it stands still leaves compulsory arbitration.2. Section 4 (3) of the Munitions of War Act, 1915, which provides that all trade practices, restrictive of production or employment, shall be suspended in controlled establishments is repealed. It is obvious that if the employer is under a liability to restore these practices they can no longer be suspended in the establishment.Clause 8.Clause 8 applies the Act to Crown establishments in the same way as it applies to establishments belonging to private persons, and it provides a convenient procedure for taking proceedings against the Crown before an industrial tribunal.The War Cabinet decided some time ago that in the next amendment to the Munitions of War Acts, the Acts were to be applied to Crown establishments. This clause to some extent carries out that decision.Clause 9.This clause provides a short title, specifies the enactments repealed, and gives the expressions &quot; controlled establishments &quot; and &quot; munitions work &quot; the same meaning as in the Munitions Acts.
Restoration of Pre-War Practices.ARRANGEMENT OF GLAUSES.Clause.1. Restoration of pre-war practices.2. Records of changes of practice.3. Right of priority of employment.4. Registration of agreements.5. Continuation of obligation on change of ownership.6. Legal proceedings.7. Industrial tribunals.8. Duration of 5 &amp; 6 Geo. 5. c. 54. ss. 2 &amp; 4 (3).9. Application of Act to Crown establishments.10. Regulations by Minister of Labour.11. Short title, repeals, and interpretations. Schedule.123-4a
DRAFTop a.BILLtoMake provision with respect to the restoration after the a.d. 1918. present war of certain trade practices and the removal of certain restrictions, and to secure priority of employ-ment after the present war to persons who have been engaged in war service and in controlled establishments.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows: 5       1. (1) The owner of an establishment to which this sub- Restoration section  applies   shall, subject to the provisions hereinafter ofP^-war contained, be subject to the following obligations: (a) Where  during  the present war any trade  practiceobtaining in the establishment before the war has 10 been changed, he shall be under an obligation afterthe termination of the war to restore or permit the restoration of, and for one year to maintain or permit the continuance of, the practice so previously obtaining, whether or not the practice was one tending to 15 restrict production or employment:(b) Where during the war non-union labour has been intro-duced into the establishment on any class of work on which it was the practice of the establishment to employ union labour exclusively, he shall be under 20 the obligation after the termination of the war todischarge the non-union labour and for one year to employ union labour only on that class of work in the establishment: 123-4 A
a.d. 1918.        (c) Where any industry or branch, of industry, which beforethe war was not carried on in the establishment commenced to be carried on in the establishment during the war and continues to  be carried on therein after the termination thereof, or where the 5 establishment is one which commenced to be worked after the beginning of war, the owner of the estab-lishment shall be under  the obligation after the termination of the war to introduce or permit the introduction of,  and for one year to maintain or 10 permit the continuance of, such trade practices as obtained before  the war  in  other  establishments where that industry or branch was carried on under circumstances which appear to the industrial tribunal - hereinafter mentioned most nearly analogous to those 15 of the establishment in question:id) Where in any industry or branch of industry carried on in the establishment any new invention has been introduced during the war, the owner shall in working the invention after the termination of the war be under 20 the obligation for one year to employ on the work workmen of the class who, according to the practice prevailing before the war in work of a kind which appears to such tribunal as aforesaid most nearly analogous, were employed on such work. 25(2) Where in pursuance or in consequence of any agreement registered under this Act to which any employer is a party, or which is binding on him as if he were a party thereto, any trade practice obtaining in the employees establishment before the war (including any practice as to the employment of union 30 labour exclusively on any class of work) has been relaxed during the war, the employer shall be under the obligation after the termination of the war to restore or permit the restoration of, and for one year at least to maintain or permit the continuance of, the practice so previously obtaining, whether 35 or not the practice was one tending to restrict production or employment.(3) An obligation under this  section shall not become binding on the owner of any establishment unless within the prescribed time there is served on the owner in the prescribed 40 manner by or on behalf of a majority in the establishment of the class or grade of workers whose custom it was before
the war to enforce the practice in question, a notice in the prescribed form requiring the observance of the obligation, and specifying the nature of the practice to which the obligation relates, and if the change of practice was made in pursuance 5 of an agreement, specifying also the agreement and the date of its registration under this Act.(4) If any person fails to comply with  an  obligation imposed upon him by this section he shall be guilty of an offence under this Act, and on conviction shall be liable to a 10 fine not exceeding five pounds for each day or part of a day during which the offence continues:Provided that, if there has been registered in pursuance of this Act an agreement providing for the modification of any such obligation as aforesaid, or an obligation under subsection (.4)15 of section four of the Munitions of War Act, 1915, to which the owner of an establishment is a party, or which is binding on him as if he were a party thereto, it shall he a good defence in any proceedings against him in respect of an alleged breach of his obligation if he proves that the breach is authorised by the20 agreement, and that a substantial majority in the establishment of the class or grade of workers whose custom it was before the war to enforce the practice to be modified are either parties to the agreement, or are members of a trade union who are parties thereto.25 (5) Nothing in this section shall be construed as imposing an obligation to discontinue the use of machinery introduced or altered during the war, without prejudice, however, to the obligation to restore any other practice which may have been introduced as a consequence of the introduction of, or change30 in, the machinery.(6) The establishments to which subsection (1) of this section applies are establishments in which munitions work has during the present war been carried on, being establishments to which an order under the Munitions of War Acts, 1915 to 35 1917, has been applied, or the wages in which have been regu-lated by an award made under Part I. of the Munitions of War Act, 1915.(7) Save as expressly provided by this section, nothing in this section shall prejudice the position of employers or persons 40 employed after the war.123 A 2
\0hA.D.1918.Records of changes of practice.Right of priority of employment.202. (1) It shall be the duty of the owner of every estab-lishment, not being a controlled establishment, to which sub-section (1) of the last foregoing section applies, who will at the termination of the war become liable to any obligation under that&apos; subsection by reason of any change of trade practices ^ in the establishment, within three months after the passing of this Act, or if the change is introduced after the passing of this Act within one month after the making of the change, to submit to the workers whose custom it was before the war to enforce the practice in question or their representatives a record of the 19 nature of the obligation, and, if desired, to give such workers or their representatives an opportunity of discussing with him the record so submitted to them.(2) If the record is agreed between the owner and such workers as aforesaid or their representatives, the record may be registered by either party with the Minister of Munitions.(3) If no such agreement is arrived at the owner and such workers as aforesaid or their representatives, may severally register with the Minister of Munitions a record of what is in their opinion the nature of the obligation.(4) If the owner of an establishment fails to comply with any dutysimposed on him by this section, he shall be guilty of an offence under the Munitions of War Act, 1915, and liable on conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds, and such workers as aforesaid or their representatives, may register with the Minister 25 of Munitions a record of what is in their opinion the nature of the obligation.(5) A record registered with the Minister of Munitions under this section shall, if agreed to by both parties, be a conclusive evidence as to the nature of the obligation, but if not so agreed 30 shall be binding only upon the party by or on whose behalf it was so registered.3. (I) Any person who at the beginning of the war was engaged on any work other than work of a casual nature in the employment of any employer [for the purposes of that 35 employees trade, business, profession, or vocation], and who either (a) has in the course of the present war served on full pay as a member of any of the naval, military, or air ; forces of the-Crown, or served as a person enrolled 40-f
18 &amp; 9 Geo. 5.]     Restoration of Pre- War Practices. 5for employment by the Army Council or Air Council a.d. 1918. or entered for. service under the direction of the Admiralty; or(b) being a person whose employment at the beginning of 5 the war was employment in an establishment whichsubsequently became a controlled establishment, was employed in that establishment when it became con-trolled; or(c) has in pursuance of section six of the Munitions of &quot;War 10 Act, 1915, been assigned from the employees estab-ment to some other establishment;shall, subject to the fulfilment of the conditions hereinafter mentioned, be entitled after the termination of the war to priority of employment from the.said employer on similar work15 at a rate of remuneration and on conditions not less favour-able than those at and on which other persons, of the same class or grade are for the time employed in the employees establishment, or, if there are no such persons, at the remunera-tion and on the conditions at and on which persons of similar20 position and skill are, for the time being, generally employed by other employers in the district:Provided that if such person has by reason of wounds received, or accident occurring, whilst serving as a member of the naval, military, or air forces, or by disease arising out of 25 such service, been incapacitated from performing such work as aforesaid, he shall be entitled to priority of employment from the said employer on any other work which he is capable of under-taking and for which he is suitable.(2) Por the purposes of this section &quot;similar work&quot; means 30 any work which is undertaken by persons of the same trade or occupation and the same class or grade thereof as that to which the person belonged before the date when such service com-menced, such establishment became controlled, or such assignment took place, as the case may be; or, in the case of a person 35 who before that date had completed his te rm of apprenticeship or period  of learning his trade or occupation, but had not obtained the full standard rate of remuneration applicable to fully qualified persons in his trade or occupation, the class or grade which he would normally have reached had he remained 40 in the employment of the same employer throughout the war.
A.D. 1918.        (3) The conditions to be fulfilled in order to entitle a person to such right.of priority of employment are (i) he must give to the employer, within the prescribed time and ,in the prescribed manner, notice in writing of his claim ; 5(ii) he must at the time where an offer of employment is made be capable of performing and in a position to undertake the work;(iii) the reason  for leaving the employees employmentmust not have been dismissal on the ground of 10 misconduct or incompetence.(4) The right of priority of employment conferred by this section shall remain in force, as respects each person entitled thereto, for one year from the date when that person gave notice of his claim : 15Provided that where an employer has once given to a person entitled to such right of priority as aforesaid a bona fide opportunity of accepting employment in accordance with this section, the right shall thereupon cease, whether the offer is accepted or not. . 20(5) If an employer fails to give preference to a person entitled to priority of employment under this section or, with the intent to avoid the obligation imposed by this section, after having given such person employment, dismisses him, or reduces his remuneration below that to which he is entitled under this 25 section, the employer shall be guilty of an offence under this Act, and on conviction shall be liable to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and the tribunal&apos;by which the fine is imposed may order that the whole or any part of the fine shall be paid as compensation to the person so entitled to priority of employment. 30Registration 4.-(l) &quot;Where an agreement in writing signed by the parties of agree- has before the passing of this Act been entered into or is meiita.       hereafter entered into-(a) between the owner of an establishment or a group orassociation of employers of the one part, and work- 35 men or trade unions as their representatives, of the other part, providing for the relaxation of any trade practice during the war; or(h) between the owner of an establishment or any group orassociation of employers of the one part, and any 40
workmen or trade union or trade unions of the other A..D. 1918. part, providing for the modification of any of the obligations imposed on employers by section one of this Act, or by subsection (4) of section four of the 5 Munitions of War Act, 1915;the agreement may be sent by either party to the agreement to the Minister of Labour for registration, and the Minister, if satisfied as to its genuineness, shall register the agreement accordingly.10 (2) In the case of an agreement to which a group or association of employers is a party, any employer who at the time of the making of the agreement was a member of that group or association, or has since become a member thereof, shall be bound by the agreement as if he were a party thereto.15 5. Where a change has taken place or hereafter takes place in the ownership of an establishment or of the business carried on by an employer, the provisions of this Act imposing obligations shall apply to the owner for the time being of the establishment or, as the case may be, of the business as if he had originally20 been the owner of the establishment or the employer.6. (1) A fine for an offence under this Act shall be recover- Legal able only before an industrial tribunal hereafter mentioned.       proceeding:(2) Proceedings against an employer for an offence under this Act may be instituted by or on behalf of a trade union.25 (3) Where notice of a claim for the fulfilment of any obli-gation under this Act has been sent to any person and that person is in doubt as to the nature of the practice or otherwise as to the interpretation of the obligation, he may, within one month after receiving the notice, in accordance with rules made30 by a Secretary of State, apply to an industrial tribunal, and the tribunal may, after giving all persons appearing to be interested in the matter an opportunity of being heard, make an order, on such terms as to costs or otherwise as the tribunal thinks fit, declaring the true interpretation of the obligation.35 Where such an order has been made, the applicant shall not be liable to any penalty under this Act in respect of a breach of the obligation if he has complied with the obligation as interpreted by such order.Continuance of obligation on change of ownership.
ra.d. 1918. (4) Where an industrial tribunal is satisfied that a con-- travention or failure to comply with an obligation imposed by this Act has occurred, but that it has occurred from a genuine and reasonable doubt as to the nature of any trade practice prevailing before the war or otherwise as to the interpretation 5 ^ of the obligation, and not from any refusal or unwillingness to comply therewith, the tribunal may, instead of imposing any penalty, make an order declaring the true interpretation 0of such obligation in relation to the matter or matters complained of, and such an order shall be binding on the parties to the 10 proceedings.The tribunal may, if it thinks fit, before making such an order give to any person appearing to be interested in the matter an opportunity of being heard on such terms as to costs or otherwise as the tribunal thinks fit, and such person shall for 15 all purposes be deemed to be a party to the proceedings.(5) A copy of every order so made shall be registered at the Ministry of Labour.Industrial 7. (l) There shall, after the termination of the presentfribimals. waV) fa established industrial tribunals which shall in the first 20 instance consist of the munitions tribunals of the second class constituted under the Munitions of War Acts, 1915 to 1917, and accordingly after the termination of the present war the said munitions tribunals shall be termed industrial tribunals, and by that, name shall have jurisdiction for the purposes of 25 this Act and continue to exercise such jurisdiction as is conferred upon them by the Munitions of War Acts, 1915 to 1917:Provided that the powers of the Minister of Munitions of filling vacancies occurring amongst the chairmen of those tribunals, and of appointing members of the panels, and of 30 choosing assessors from those panels, and of regulating the procedure of the tribunals shall, after the termination of the present war, vest in a Secretary of State.(2) Subject as aforesaid all the provisions of the Munitions of War Acts, 1915 to 1917, and any Act amending those Acts, 35 and the rules made thereunder affecting munitions tribunals of the second class (including the provisions as to appeals) in force at the termination of the wrar shall apply to industrial tribunals, and any proceedings at that date pending before a munitions tribunal may be continued before the same tribunal 40 as if this Act had not heen passed;
Provided that nothing in the Munitions of War Acts, 1915 A&apos;D- 1918-to 1917, limiting the duration of those Acts shall affect industrial tribunals.8. Section two of the Munitions of War Act, 1915, which Duration of 5 prohibits lock-outs and strikes in certain cases, and subsection (3) ^ * ^     5-of section four of the same Act which provides for the suspen- &amp;4(3).&quot; sion of certain trade practices shall cease to have effect on the termination of the present war.9. This Act shall apply to Crown establishments, that is Application 10 to say, establishments belonging to or under the control of His Crownestab-Majesty or any Government department, in like manner as it lishments. applies to establishments belonging to subjects, and any pro-ceedings which under this Act can be taken by or against the owner of any establishment or an employer may be taken by 15 or against the Crown establishment concerned in the name by which the establishment is usually known.10. The Minister of Labour may make regulations prescribing Regulations anything which under this Act is to be prescribed, and as to the ^Labour67 registration of agreements and orders which under this Act may 20 be registered at the Ministry, the inspection of agreements and orders so registered, and the cancellation of such registration, and generally for carrying this Act into effect.11. (1) This Act maybe cited as the Restoration of Pre- Short title, War Practices, Act, 1918. repeals, andmterpreta-25      (2) The enactments mentioned in the Schedule to this Act tion. &quot;are hereby repealed to the extent specified in the third column of that Schedule.(3) The expressions &quot; controlled establishment&quot; and &quot; muni-tions work&quot; have the same meanings as in the Munitions of 30 War Acts, 1915 to 1917.123 C
Enactments Repealed.Session and Chapter.	Short Title,	Extent of Repeal.o &amp; 6 Geo. 5. c. 54.	The Munitions of War Act, 1915.	In the Second Schedule the para-graphs numbered 1, 2, and 3.5 &amp; 6 Geo. 5. c. 99.	The Munitions of War (Amendment) Act, 1916.	Section fifteen.A.D.1918.\SCHEDULE,

Restoration of Pre-War Practices.DRAFTof aB   I   Jj   JjTo make provision with respect to the restoration after the present war of certain trade practices and the removal of certain restrictions, and to secure priority of employ-ment after the present war to persons who have been- engaged in war service and in controlled establishments.CXX. - (4.)21st Atigust 1918.123-4

</content>
</cab>
