<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 79-80</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
REPORT relating to Scotland forthe War Work of the week endingthe Board of Agriculture 4th September, 19-19-.forjperty oi. - - i i s u. -I. I   I o   lit (3  3Britannic Male8ty&apos;a Government;)4, S&amp;^-Two eoBjuliery orders uader lOefenee of the Realm 2 H.(i) (a) wire issued during the week, taking over&apos;,o^vft) * acres of l*.nd under grain on the Holding of Xirkbank, Bees, twing, Kirkcudbrightshire.  The oooupant had Tith the assis-itanee of the Ccmaittee and under protest ploughed up this land, &quot;but in view of the labour difficulty be threatened to turn stock on to the field unless the Committee undertook to reap it.   The Board accordingly took orer the .8 acres, and the Coanltt.ee will either sell the crop by auction or arrange for it to be reaped by a farmer in the neljnbourhood;, (b) Woodend Croft, Lhanbryde, Elgin.   The tenant is on military service, dad the death of a relative had left the orop8r&amp;etioally derelict.   The Board took possession, and a ttsnittce h&amp;4 Veen fobbed to look after the croft.  The whole of the free proceeds will go to the Absent tenant/Jroa the returns of increased oropping already reported the following comparative statement has been aade, shoring how far each County has been able to complete the acreage of cropping asked for:-JWm&amp;M&amp;M Qiagk tea&amp;m ^ncl^in^Beye), ftats,lounty^SmXH^I [ifrprg&amp;rt, as, ,?o,rn]T Total acreage in I Increase in 1911 eves- 191?1918. (1)1917 (2)Actual. (3)Asked for.(4)Percentage. (3) of (4).jrdeen. * * * * *til.......Kf.?iok.Ill a * tSihness.... * Ikmannan. * * far ton..... tries......(litar * *......ington....mess.....ardine. * *.OBS ...... .udbright.?k........&apos;;hgow.... Jthian.... i...............188.......l ., ......row..... *Cromarty.&quot;gh......ik.......;&amp;iid.....*ing.......fland....hn.......total 37264,45529,021 72,244 66,052 69,020 7,526 38,160 5,687 13,358 63,430 42,193 100,796 119,039 I 51,758 ; 48,210 55,558 10,837 40,854 63,206 21,065 46,008 10;433 ! 46.919 10,143 128,106 20 315 66.  47 51,670 6,274 l 10,494 ! 34,279 10,887 42,911280,992 24,73* 61,006 57,663 54,8414,760 34,6284,739 12,152 49,519 37,390 90,924105,2a45,960 43,172 46.5728*,619 30,017 53,569 18,600 40.28191127 41,6337,1577 10:? ,V08 18.408 50;o5D 42.0014,U7 10,122 30,590 10,351 35,206I!I36,463 4,28611,236 8,38914,179 756 3,532 948 1,20613,911 4,803 9,87113,013 5,796 5,038 8,986 2,21810,837 9,727 5,365 5,777 1,306 4.261 -  2,66620.448 l&apos;r647 5,892 9,669 1,327 572 3.889 536 7,70550,350 7,850 22,100 12,650 14,100 1,200 6,000 1,000 2,300 19,300 6,500 12,550 14,650 7,150 8,550 7,850 2,100 14,700 14.650 3so00 7,750i,eoo 6,eoo&apos; 4.600 18.050 4.750 8, &apos;00 15,4HO 2,400 *&apos; * *nx .t J.CU5,?00 1.750 12.COO72.4 54.6 60.8 66.3100.5 63.2 44.2 94.8 52.4 72.0 73.8 78.6 94.3 81.0 58.9114.4105.6 73.7 66.4102.0 74.5 72.6 64.8 53-4113.2 30.9 72.7 71.9 55.3 32.3 73.4 30.6 64.2
3* AffTiou^uxaX^a^nerjr.(a) Tract ore. Ploughs^, &amp;p i   Early In the year the Board made arrangements to take, over, if. necessary, the whole output ft Messrs G.. Cellar &amp; Sons&apos; works, of 3-furrow ploughs for &apos;eeaej 19ie-l9v During the week the Board have issued consignment instructions for the delivery of 60 of these ploughs to District Agricultural Oommittees(b).BepaAxfl! Certain procedure has been arranged with the Minis of-Munitions in connection with the issue of priority oertif &quot;&apos; joatea for the repair .of steam ploughing, and threshing taokj farm vehicles and agricultural machinery.. , An owner of such implements etc. may on direct application to. theSAgricultura Machinery Department receive a Running Permit which will ena him to have any ordinary repairs done at any time, and when such a Permit has been granted&apos;&apos;a separate application need be made in the case.of a repair to anyone engine,- machine on vehicle which would cost over . 20.Farmers have fceen advised to make immediate application! for such priority oertificat.es and not to wait until&apos;some repair is necessary. ..   t &apos;.&quot;4* Vart Disease of Potatoes v.it was recently reported, to the Board by the police in an Ayrshire town in connection with an outbreak of Wart Disease in a&apos; private garden that the seed was obtained from&apos;a chip-potato vendor The latter had bought a consignment of potatoes .&apos;,drawn jfrom a cropf1 which had been scheduled under the Wart Disease Order, and in respei of which a- licence had been issued allowing the $rower^to- sell it.fi consumption only. As it. is an.offence under the,&apos;^qta4J^es Order 191&apos; for any person who is not &quot;registered under the 6rder&quot;&apos;&apos;t&apos;0 deal in ee potatoes, the case has been reported to the Divisional,Food Commis. tsioner with a.view to the. institution of. legal proceedings.5. ICo^.Qr Spirit&apos; Licenc, ea&quot;. -; &apos; The Board have been informed that in view of the constitute by the Board .of Trade, of the Poad Transport Board, whose-main funct is &quot;to ensure the most econom.ia&apos;&apos;u8e of road&apos;.;transport vehicles; anl.&apos;t provide for their eftiolent; allocation&apos;&apos;fbr.&apos;the essential needs o country, it has bsen.deel &apos;0. that all recommenaations for the ant Motor Spirit-licences in HSpec i? of petrol-driven, road vehicles&apos;&apos; (at! those used wholly or mainly for agricultural purposes) shall&apos;in futii; be made by,the Road Transport Board.Applications in respect of vehicles used mainly for,&apos;agr.icult purposes v/ill still be dealt with by this Department or &quot;by the Dist; Agricultural Sxeoutive Committees. . ,6* Sale of Horses. Order.Under the Defence of the Realm Regulation 2 T. regarding the] sale of agricultural horses, 616 licences to Bell horses were issue during the week.- The total number of licences issued by the Board since this Regulation came into operation is 35,813.

</content>
</cab>
