<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 155-158</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
f^p^ ..... &quot;^/t!Jfhlt Document l* th. ^r-pnrty or &apos;^Hfs Britannic Maie*UVr rw--------^^::j;.;.:i.:iiv,l:!jConfidential,   111MINISTRY OP PENSIONSAugust 31st to September 6th 1910.Summary of Report LXXXV. for period fromPENSIONS.Number of Pensions * 10225 pensions and allowances have been granted during the week to Officers and Men and to widows, children and dependants,    The number since the beginning of the war la 1533796*2* Pensions      Soldiers &amp; Sailors,   During the week out of 5788 cases dealt with (including      rejected under previous Warrants) 4755 were awarded pensions, permanent or temporary, 987 were granted gratuities and 44 were rejected.3, Renewal of Soldiers Pensions. The average decrease in percentage of disablement in dealing with 5514 pensions during the week was 12.05.4, Work of Soldiers Award Branch. Sinco the beginning of the War 587,17$ fresh claims for soldTers have been dealt with.   Prior to the introduction of the 1917 Warrant rejections averagOd 31$ of the claims, now they average just over 0*6$s* wfrk ef Seamen&apos;s Award Branch. Since January 1917,21702 fresh claims from sailors have been dealt with.    Prom the introduction of the Order in Council cf March 1917 the rejections have amounted to just under \% of the claims.6. Pensions to Widows and Dependants. Curing the week 452 widows (including unmarried wives), 9*21 parents and 58 other dependants were awarded pensions and 829 children of widows, and motherless &amp;c children wore granted allowances.7* Pensions to Parents&apos; in need.     During the week the pre-war dependence pensions &quot;of &quot;&quot;155 parents who were- in pecuniary need havs been raised from an average of 6/5 a week to an average of 12/2, whilst 101 unpensioned parents in pecuniary need have been granted an average pension of 9/9 a week, 105 cases have been refused pension.98 Alternative Pensions. Up to date 48 permanent and 1028 conditional alternative pensions have been awarded to disabled men, and 565 under treatment and training are receiving&apos;alternative pension allowances. As a result of 9138 claims by war-widows for alternative pensions there have been 4925 awards and 1264 rejections.9&quot; Pensions Appeal Tribunal.   Out of a total of 14801 claims 7294 have been disposed oFT    In 3562 cases pensions have been granted in lieu of gratuities.Pensions on account of former wars.     Up to the 4th instant, 1380 applications had been made for increase of pensions under former wars; about 1100 have been rejected.     So far 201 awards have been made at a total additional weekly charge of  126*9.4.SUPPLEMENTARY AND DISCRETIONARY GRANTS.11, Special Grants Committee.   At its meeting on the 3rd instant this Committee dealt merely with details.12. Number of Grants.   During the week 23 supplementary pensions and allowances were made by the Special Grants Committee.13.
11213*   The King&apos;a Fund    Up to the 4th instant there were 7817 applications for relief and 2357 grants.TREATMENT.Diaablllties due to Wounds and Disease.   Of the officers and men pensioned during the month of August, 8726 were invalided on account of wounds and injuries and 11510 on account of disease.    The corresponding figures since the beginning of the -war to the end of August are 179154 and 242723,Treatment of the Blind.   564 blindod men are now in residence at&quot;^t. Dunstanr3   and its annexes and 24 blinded officers are under care.   551 moil and 35 officers have now passed through.i6*   Treatment of the Deaf,   The Special Aural Board (London) examined II men during Xugust.17.   Treatment of the Limbless.   Up to the end of August 14935 artificial Tegs and&quot;*7T76 artificial arms had been supplied cr sjxtf^ -te^ft- on order.     During the month there were 1340 admissions to limb fitting hospitals and 1090 discharges.10.   Treatment of Orthopedics.    Accommodation is being secured at Birmingham, Re&amp;ding?ItewporT^ Bristol and Sheffield.Treatment of Paraplegics.   Accommodation has been offered at Durham.20.   Treatment of Neurasthenics.   During August there have been 65 a dmi s si on s&quot; &quot;i oH-Iome s and 67 men were discharged cured.21. Treatment of Tuberculotaa cases. 20 advanced cases are being arranged for In&quot;&quot;wTTtshire.220 Treatment of Convalescents.., 20 - 25 men are being provided for at tifatford and from 2Srs-&quot;5o at Porthcawi..23.   General Hospital Arrangements,..    The Eye, Ear and Throat Hospital, sHrewsbury, is&apos; applyingTor priority certificates for its annexe.24.   Agreements with Hospitals.   An agreement has been made with one HospiraTTRofuoal of Treatment., During the week 137 men refused treatment j ^7^sub&apos;sequently accepted it.     In 8 cases a penalty was imposed.26*   Numbers under treatment.   During the week 2219 cases were admitted for treatment in or at Institutionsj 579 were discharged and 29539 cases were under treatment at the end of the week. The total number of cases which have been given or are being given treatment is 60224.27 *   Treatment of Officers.   During August 1108 Officers were allowed treatment, 5^3&quot;&quot;received expenses for past medical treatment and 10 were granted constant attendant allowances.28.
lit?TRAINING AND EMPLOYMENT.20*   Trade Advisory Committee3. Meetings were held with respect to the tailoring, Hosiery&quot;Latch Needle, Jewellery, Picture Framing and Shipbuilding and Engineering Trades.     In the last named.trade the co-operation of the Admiralty and the Railway Companies is being sought.29*   ^inJHff. of Widows^    Up to date 311 war-widows have applied for training, in 14*7 cases training has been sanctioned and 49 widov;s have completed their training.30 *   ^rainlnff Schemes.   During the week 9 out of 11 schemes submitted by local Committees liave been sanctioned, and 10 individual cases outside approved schemes were approved; 204 men were admitted to and 112 were discharged from training.    The total number of men under training at the end of the week was 6005; up to d?te 16j603 men have been or are still under training.31. - Training of Officers. A Committee to advise on training of Officers In Scotland has been formed, A number of new training courses have been arranged with the Universities.32.   gkgloyment of Officers.   The Officers Re-settlement Committee has held Tta^FIrat meeting?    During August 259 Officers applied for employment and 126 were placed.COLONIAL AND FOREIGN PENSION NOTES.33*   Treatment and Training In Canada.    An Order in Council extends the benliHts^oFThe Soldiers Civil Re-establishment Department to Members of the Imperial and Allied Forces resident in Canada and fixes the allowances to be granted during Treatment and Training. The allowances are, on the whole, somewhat higher th n the Imperial rates.34.   Intelligence Notes.   Owing to shortage of accommodation in Mi 1 i ta&apos;ry Hospitals &quot;In  ranc e many soldiers mentally affected are being maintained In civilian Asylums and remain undischarged for a year or more,Voluntary effort at Milan is providing a sanatorium for tuberculous and a hospital for nerve-affected disabled n.en.Germany is extending to Officers the law permitting supplementary war allowances to be commuted and invested in industrial or agricultural enterprises.ORGANISATION,36.   Na va1 and Military Way Pensions &amp;c (Committees) Ag%,1917. 290 Supplemental schemes have been received from Local Committees. 285 have been formally approved.36.   iVar Pensions Gazette..   The September Number opens with a leadinge by^tlieJa luster of Pensions on the ftingfs Fund for disabled Officers and Men and contains an interesting account of neurasthenic cures.STAFF.37.   Staff. The Staff on tho books of the Ministry now consists of 499 men and 6515 women or a total of 7014.30.
&apos; 11458 * Resignation^.     During August there were 6 dismissals and 31.6 resignations (Including holiday workers) - a percentage of   4.5 of the total staff.39. Disabled Officers and Men and Staff.      The Department are employing 48 retired and 72 light duty officers and 120 discharged men disabled during the present war.7th September,1916k

</content>
</cab>
