<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 168-176</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Telegrams-&quot;SHIPMINDER, VIC, LONDON.&quot; (THlS Dor.HPPent is the Property o124Any further communication on tlrin subject should be addressed to-Tho Secretary,Ministry of Shipping,St. Janics&apos;s Park.London, S.W.1,and the following number quoted: 1I?MINISTRY  OF  SHIPPING,7th September 1918.Sir,In continuation of Mr Anderson&apos;8 letter of the 31stultimo, I am directed lay the Shipping Controller to report, for the information of the War Cabinet, as follows i-1.    CQKVOYS.(a) Homeward Bound Convoys. Since the last report 11 convoys consisting of 184 ships (1,336,900 tons deadweight) have arrived.     There were no casualties of any description.There are now on passage home 16 convoys consisting of 347 ships.(b) Outward Bound Convoys. Since the last report 10 convoys consisting of 139 ships (962,600 tons deadweight) have been escorted through the danger zone.The ft) Honing casualties by enemy action have been reported J-  The s/s ttZIHAL&apos;f was torpedoed and sunk on the17th August after being detached from the convoy.  The s/s wMILWAUKEER was torpedoed on the 30th August and sunk 300 IB SECRETARY,WAR CABINET.
miles float of Uahant.  Tho a/i &quot;CITC OP GLASGOW&quot; and m* 9/0 &quot;KESABA&quot; woro torpedoed and sunk 35 miles Korth of tho Smalls, arid tho a/a &quot;ACTOR&quot; was torpedoed 40 miles West of tho Smalls, but subsequently arrived In Devonport.There were no casualties by marine peril.   There are now in the danger none 3 convoys consisting of 45 ships.Two statements are enclosed showing (a) the total number of convoys and tonnage convoyed to tho 31st August, and (b) the percentage of losses on the different routes. FINANCE.During toe week onded tho 31st August the sum of  1,449,116 was paid in cpmpeneation for loss of requisitioned ships, making a total of  27,170,176 paid on this account since the 1st April, 1918. LOSSES AND PAINS OF BRITISH TONNAGE.During the week ended the 31st August, tho following losses of British steamers of 500 tons gross and upwards hats boon reportedLost by enemy action 6 ships of 19*815 gross tonsn     &quot; marine perU 3    *      &quot; 12,221     &quot;     *1making a total of 9    *     &quot;32,036     &quot;      *
mThe vessels loot it ere the followingEnemy Action. Marine Peril,&quot;ant cassar&quot; &quot;lake manitoba&quot;&quot;milwaukee&quot; &quot;sung kiang&quot;&quot;willingtonia&quot; &quot;ora&quot; &quot;zjnal&quot;&quot;ERIK&quot; &quot;GIRALDA&quot;The gains were as follows:-New vessels British built brought into service15 ships of 78,112 gross tons New vessels Purchased Overseas    2    &quot;      &quot;   3,900    &quot;       &quot;making a total of 17    &quot;      &quot; 82,012    &quot;       &quot;and a net gain of 8    &quot;      &quot; 49,976    &quot;       &quot;In addition there was transferred from Norwegian Flag one ship of 1,413 gross tons.Of the new vessels brought into service thirteen of them were s tandard ships.During the month of August the casualties reported to British, Allied and Neutral vessels were as followsBritish.      British, Allied and .. NeutralSunk by enemy action 138,416 276,550Damaged    &quot;        j&quot; 52,264 72,147Lost by marine peril 30,819 52l,629Damaged    &quot;         &quot; 415,195 647,849Total 636,694 1,049,175
miSTANDARD SHlPft,With reference to the standard vessel &quot;WAR SNAKE11 it It Interesting to note that she was launched on the 22nd August by Messrs flarlend h Wolff at Belfast and handed over on the 28th August * a remarkable performance. NEUTRAL TOhNAgE,The Norwegian steamer &quot;VALUTA&quot; has been requisitioned.The &quot;0RAtt a requisitioned Norwegian vessel has been lost by marine risk.MILITARY SUPPLIES POR THE NORTH RUSSIAN EXPEDITION.In view of the approaahing close of White Sea Navigation, all efforts are being concentrated for the moment on supplying the needs of the Archangel force, which must necessarily be provided for the entire winter before ice sets in.The ftar Office demands for tonnage have been met up to the present, but they have been notified thai the last store ships selling for the flhite 5ea should leave this country by the middle of the present month to avoid risk of detention by ice.It has been necessary to exceed this limit in the case of two ships to meet urgent demands for military stores only Just received by the War Office, and to supply the winter requirements*of froseqfjneat, but the ships in question will be cleared as rapidly as possible at Archangel and if necessary, leave in ballast.
I.128Including these ships the number of vessels apart from troopships employed in carrying supplies for the North Russian Expedition up to the close of Archangel navigation will be 15 ships carrying approximately 84,400 measurement tons, (These figures include some military cargo for Murmansk, a proportion of Naval stores and a small quantity of civilian supplied)7,     CIVILIAN SUPPLIES FOR ARCHANGEL POPULATION,   With the exception of one part-cargo from this country General Poolefs demands for food stuffs for the civilian population are being met by shipment from America,Two vessels with flour and pork have sailed from Canada, two more are loading there.   Two British ships are loading at New York and three U.S. ships with full cargoes of flour from the Pacific are being diverted to Archangel in exchange for British ships.The total requirements of the civil population of the Archangel district are approximately 50,000 tons of foodstuffs, 8.    ftOMff/ARD CARGO FltOM ARCHANGEL,   All ships discharging in Archangel and all ships available elsewhere in North Russia are being loaded with full cargoes, and this will continue tobe done until the season becomes too late.   First priority isgivenbeing^o flax, of which there are understood to be 15,000 weight tons available for shipment.
1296.0*    i,$,0CITY OP GLASGOW and &quot;MESABA&quot;.   These two liners, which were engaged on American trooping, were sunk toy enemy action on 1st September whilst on outward voyage to the United States.10.    H.M.S. &quot;AQUITANIA&quot;.   This transport, flying the Unite Ensign and engaged on the American trooping service, will be manned entirely by a naval crew instead of by mercantile ratings, on her next arrival in this country.H*    Exchange of British and German Prig oners of War.   Thetwentieth exchange of Prisoners of War has taken place, the Dutch &amp;ip disembarking 272 British Prisoners at Boston on 31st August, and embarking 243 German Prisoners of War and 214 German women and children.12.    Stores for the British Army in France.   The quantity of military stores discharged in Prance in the week ending 31st August was 163,326 tons, compared with 145,485 tons during the previous week.13      Provision of Dolphins and Conveyers for Naval Meat ships.The question of the provision of Dolphins and  ,Conveyers for Naval Meat ships at Port Said, to expedite thedischarge of Naval Meat ships,   is being submitted for1Treasury sanction.
1307.14.    Frozen Meat Store, Salonica.,   In view of the decision that the provision of a Meat Store at Salonika is to be proceeded with, the question of the selection of a suitable site is now under consideration,I am, Sir,Your obedient Servant,(Signed) GRAEME THOMSON.
STATEMENT SHOEING HU&amp;iiSK OF CONVOYS AND TOjIMOg CONVOYED TO 31ST AUGUST, 1916 HOMEWARD.131DirectionShipsG.R.T.D.W.C.SinkingsNo.    D.W.C.HalifaxSydneyNew YorkHalifax Ch.NorfolkSierra LeoneDakarGibraltarMedn.throughRio de JaneiroBayTOTALFalmouth Devonport Mi If or d Queeastown Lamiash Llpool Spl Liverpool Me dn,through ChannelLr p o ol/Bunc r ana Liverpool FastTOTAL426 1,085 1,359 187 1,285 339 459 1,474 260 287 1257,286OUTWARD644 1,474 2,237209 872 18 242 242 59 52 596,1085,1475,0998,1 3 1,557 6,008, 2,346 1,095. 4,69?.-1iCoCi1,30&amp;&apos;;,974,583 ;130,460 236 114 73.4994 206676.61938,657,2674,366,700 7,697,900 11,763,200 1,795,000 9,254,900 2,523,900 2,037;200 7,509,500 2,193,900 1,857,000 1,013,90052,913,100Percentage of Losses2,301,029 8,619,941 8,343,733964,503 4,707,914 227,$36 2,237,456 1,502,498 501;339 300,127 627,62030,433,8963,623,950 11,934,700 13,214,500 1,435,150 6,711,700 167,000 2,318,300 2,132,800 543,600 426,000 583,30043,091,000Percentage of LossesHOMEWARDS AND OUTWARDS.HOMEWARDS BUTWARDSTOTAL7,286 6,10813,39438,657,267 30,435,896$9,091,16352,913,100 43,091,00096,004,100Percentage of Losses3 12 131 1734 2482491 1.237104642.6891 42133 .9823,800 84,100106,900 , 800119,400 21.300 25-900126,?00 7 ,200 10,490 30.200624,000 1.1734,200 59,500 74,90074,10035,900 61,50015,000 355,100.82624,000 355,100979,1001.-r.....
							- -jetton 1	Ships Convoyed Safely	SINKINGS			%            $          %				Ships	G.K.T.	D.W.C	Ships	G.h.T.	D.W.C.1 if&amp;x h movk Bfax Ch. :1k ra Leone altar through I jo Janeiro	426 1,085 1,359 187 -1,285 339 459 1,474 260 287 125	3 12 13 1 17 3 4 24 8 2 4	i 41,375 59,693 74,792 9,500 78,304 19,739 15,430 76,366 50,000 6,737 22,754	28,g00 64,100 106,900 800 119,400 21,100 23,900 126,100 72,200 10,400 35,300	.69 1.09 ,95 ..53 1,3 .88 .86 1)6 2.99 .69 3.1	.8 1.16 .91 .61 1.27 .84 .81 1,6 3.07 .48 3.25	.54 1.08 .9 .04 1.27 ,8 .84 1,65 3 o 19 ,56 3,36	7,286	91. 0UT1 5 7 10 9 4 6 m m 1	454,690	624,000	1.23	1.16	1.17path tip or t Ird fctown mh Irpool Spl. flpool Jthrough il/Suncrana 1 &apos;pool Fast	644 1,474 2,237. 209 872 18 242 242 59 52 59		ARD 21,380 40,160 46,936 55,046 *** 26,596 44,099 mm m 32,234	34,200 59,500 74*900 74)100 i 35,900 61,500 15)000	.77 .4* .45 1 02 tm 1.63 2.41 4* 1,67	.93 .46 .56 1.14 1,15 2.85 4.89	-.93 .5 .56 1.09 1.53 2.8 2,511 !0TAL	6,108	42	266,451	355,100	.68	.87	.82	7,286 6,108	HOMEaAf	OS AKD OU		1.23 .68	1.16 .87			91 42 153	454,690 266,451	624,000 3 55,.100			1.17 .821 IT A JL			721,141	979,100	.98	1.03	1.I					4		statement shewing the losses on thkDIFFEuEKT ROUTES homsvukd

</content>
</cab>
