<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 215-220</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET&apos;1; MINISTKY OF SHIPPINGNOTES OH TONNAGE POSITION. AUGUST, 1916, 168f(l)( TOTAL OCEAN-GOING TONNAGE (OVER 500 TONS GROSS) IN UNITEDT f^/fl KINGDOM AND COLONIAL REGISTERS&quot;f -EoLl^fcj^ No. Grossr&quot;-&apos; J&quot; &quot;tons&quot;Outbreak of War (July 31st 1914) 5,000       18,500,000Deduct Nett Loss (i,e. Excess of losses overnew building 1,175 4,000,0003,825        14,500,000Add Foreign tonnage requisitioned for Warpurposes 225   _500.000Total tonnage now on British Register      4,050       15,000,000Note. The loss is more than the mere figures indicate, because whereas the losses are in many cases drawn from the ships of the Liner Class, the replace tonnage is of the simplest kind.(2)        EMPLOYMENT1st January 1917 Present TimeService No. TTTT.   No.   &quot;&quot;r TTT.Naval ...........        736 2,348,000   580 ^      2,000,000Military ........        507 2,158,000   500 1,850,000Allies (including chartered to or trading on behalfof)........____ 729 2,157,000 650 2,000,000Colonies ........ 164 978,000 120 450,000Trading abroad andCoasting.......     1,070        3,677,000   750 1,700,000Repairing ........ 38 108,000   250 1,150,000Muniti ons )Pood k Civilian   J     1,544        6.531.000 1,200        5,850.000TOTAL 4,788      17,757,000 4,050     15,000,000N.B..    In addition to vessels noted as on Food and Civilian Services many vessels on Naval,Military, Allied and Colonial Services bring imports on return voyages. This contribution is equivalent to about 900,000 tons of shipping.Thus the totali tonnape available to-day for food and civilianServices is only about 6j million tons gross which if allowance, is madefor the continuance of American trooping on the present scale isreduced to 6x million tons.It is to the 6j million tons, together with some assistance,-r, .   ^ from(This Dftcwni^ht a-      d...     t . -- &quot;----.x.g.:E:E.e..&apos;;. L.        *&apos; operty 0&apos;i For details see Appendix \       Jjte Pr&apos; -:*y.r y&apos;-77^&quot;^rP&quot;Z-
167from fore ign tonnage, that m have to look for til ourlmyorts including food, munitions and the raw material for our manufacturingHrades.(5)   THE SHRINKAGE Bj IMPORTS IS SHEWN BY THE FOLLOWIiJG TABLE.Imports, 1913..............   64,000,000 tons (groaa)1917..............   35,400,000   *1918 (estimate) ,..   30,000,000  n (excluding oil for the Wavy) (4) NATURE OF IMPORTS (IN ROUND FIGURES)1913. 1917 I9l8(eatlmate)18,000,000 tons   14,300,000 tone   15,000,000 tona16,850,000   n      14,000,000   nPoodMunitions War MaterialCivil Supplies     )(Cotton, tobacco,paper))   36,000,000 tons   4,250,000   &quot;3,000,000Only 9% of our imports are ordinary Civil Supplies, 91% are Food and munitions. (5)     NEUTRAL TONNAGEIn 1913 ...... 37$ of our&apos;imports carried in foreign shipsIn 1917 ......18%   H   &quot;        &quot; h        n        .        aIn 1918 15/-?   &quot;   &quot;(estimate)&quot; will be carried in foreignshipsBy pressure due to British coal, etc., we hate   obtained control of about 1^ million tons of neutral tonnage, of which about half is for &quot;out of the War Zone trading&quot;. Practically all this neutral tonnage has been assigned to the European Allies.   The United States has another million tons, the employment of which she controls and uaes on her own Services.
168(6) FRANCEFrance has Ahe equivalent of over one million tons gross of Titish shipping in her service.45% of,her total imports into France ;are carried In British shipsb0% of the import of coal (1,600,000) tons a month) is carried in British ships.492,000 ton3 of cereals out of 784,000 tons in all, have been c arried in France in the last three months in British ships.France has the benefit of coal at bunkering stations abroad which are kept by British ships.France has over 400,000 tons groBS of neutral tonnage obtained by our coal pressure, etc. in her service,The total tonnage in service of Franca, is as follows:-French National tonnage 1,600,000 tons grossAH other tonnage (including .U.K. tonnage) 1,700,0003,500,000(7) ItalyItaly has the equivalent of over j million tons gross of British shipping in her service.About 450A of her total imports are carried in British ships. 75$ of the coal supplied to Italy is carried in British ships. 462,000 tons of cereals, out of 956,000 tons in all, have been i&amp;rriea to Italy in the last three months In British ships.Italy has the benefit of coaling stations abroad supplied by ritish tonnage.300,000 tons gross of neutral tonnage obtained by our coalres sure, etc. are in her service.The total tonnage In service of Italy is as followst-Italian National tonnage,   1,075,000 tons gross All Other tonnage (includingU.K. tonnage) 1,000,000   11 1   H2,075,000(8)
(e:The amount of British tonnage assistance given to America llfce equivalent to over half a million tons of shipping.During the months of April, May and June over 330,000 American troops were embarked In British ships and in July alone we emaarked over 185,000 men out of a total of about 500,000.   The nett effect of the transportation of American troops at the present rate is that we are sacrificing carrying capacity equal to 250,000 tons of Imports from the United States per month..The American Army in France and England la supplied with large quantities of munitions, timber, etc; which have been Imported lato the United Kingdom in British ships.America has claimed 50$ of the neutral tonnage obtained by jconomic pressure since she entered the war.    This amounts to yearly one million tons and is being used by America for her own purposes.The total tonnage in service of America excluding lake steamers and small coasting vessels end excluding also the services rendered by British liners in the carriage of American troops Is as followsAmerican national steamer tonnagen M      sailing       &quot;Neutral and other tonnage under charter4*800*000 tons gross 850,000    11      wiiitto America steamer 850-000tt      w sailing    375*000n      &quot;   serving America nor under chartersteamer    1,500,00itsailing100*0008,275,000tl 51ftth August 191B.S Some 800,000 tons of this is being used in Allied or Neutral interests.
17APfEHDlX.1 -SUBDIVISlfrK OP VESSELS UNDER NAVaL &amp; MILITARY SERVICE ATPRESENT TIMENavyNo.(1) Commissioned Vessels, hrm$ Merchant Cruisers, Armed Boarding Steamers, Mine Sweepers ice, 100G.T.430,000(2) Amniunitiori Carriers, Mine Carriers,Squadron Supply Ships,Y/eter Boats &amp;c 58(3) Hospital Ships (4) Colliers (5) Oilers7505 11068085,000 35,000 825,000 625,0002,000,000Army (1) Trooping (2) Stores (3) Coal(4) Hospital Ships (5) Nitrates (6)   Miscellaneous80 250 30 35 30 75400,000 700,000 75,000 225,000 160,000 300,0005001,850, 0001
171&apos;APPENDIX 11ST&apos;.TK.vlENT SHE-VIIJG DEPLETION OF DISTANT LINER TRADES IN CONSEQUENCE OF THE WAR.Trade between TJ.K. Reduction In the nuraber ofand ** steamers berthed as comparedwith the pre-War period. India 55^Australasia 75^Par East Nearly 100$ South Africa Z0%

</content>
</cab>
