<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 330-331</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Department of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland.9 K ft J&apos;!FOOD PRODUCTION SCHEMES, IRELAND.Lfomorandum proparod in ornpllanoo with plilof Secretary1sMinute of 17th March, 1917.Woolc ondod, 11th September, 1913,The following is a briof statement on the work of the department during tho past weok in furtherance of increased Food Production in IrelandThirty-five applications for loans for agricultural implements wore received by tho Department during the past weok.   The total value of machinery ordered from tho beginning of&apos;tho prosont year, to dajje, under the So home, amounts to 171,076.Though the weather during tho weok has boon sonew?.i2it unsettlod and In some districts unfavourable to harvosting operations, satisfactory progress has been made with tho outting and ingathering of corn crops, and in many parts of tho country considerable areas have been already scoured in Stacks,   In tho earlier dlstrieto, threshing is already proceeding, and reports as to yield and quality of grain are very satisfactory,.Tho greater portion of tho hay crop has now boon gathered in* The saving of tho seccriLl orop of first year hay is in progress in. early distriots,   Tho orop is below avorago but is boing saved in good condition.Ropcrts as to the potato crop continue favourable0   Where digg-ing has taken place, the yields are roturnod as well up to the average and the quality of the tubers is everywhere well spoken ofn So far no ocmplaints have boen received as to damage to tubers by the blight.FLAX-,The weather during tho past week was net unfavourable so far as flax was concerned.    Most of tho orcp has boon pulled, and a large proportion rettod and dried in good condition.Seed saving operations are, on the whole, progressing favour-ably, and there are now fair prospoots that a substantial amount of -11/9/18h6me
home-saved seed of good quality, will be secured for next season&apos;s sowing. The total number of cases of failure to comply with the flaxseed (Ireland) Order, 1918, reported to date, to the Department ? 197.

The scutchers in some districts are dissatisfied with the rate of wages fixed for scutching by the Wages Arbitration Board and are refusing to start work. In a few early districts scutching has already been started, but there are no definite reports to hand to indicate the scutching quality of the crop.

Having regard to the fact that both the Department and the Ministry of Munitions are now concerned in the growing and preparation of flax in Ireland, and in order to obviate any overlapping or conflict of policy, a conference was held at the Department&apos;s offices on the 6th September, with a view to having the spheres of action of both bodies? clearly defined. The Vice-President of the Department was in the Chair, and the Conference was attended by the Administrator, Flax Supplies Committee, Belfast, who represents the Department of Aircraft Production of the Ministry of Munitions in Ireland. The Department&apos;s position as defined in the Agriculture and Technical Instruction (Ireland) Act, 1899, was explained, and it was arranged that the Department&apos;s Assistant Secretary, (Mr. J.R. Campbell) and the Administrator of the Flax Supplies Committee should confer with the Department of Aircraft Production in London, in the matter.



TRANSIT OF FARMING REQUISITES.

A strike of Dock labourers at Cork Port, which had interrupted the transit of farming requisites, was settled during the week.

MAINTENANCE OF LIVE STOCK.

During the period from 3rd to 9th September, inclusive, 150 applications for licences to slaughter or export heifors and 445 applications for licences to export store heifors were received. Eighty applications for licences to slaughter bulls or bullocks were also received.



</content>
</cab>
