<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/63/0 images: 366-366</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
273Report of Special Work of the Local Government Board for the week ended 13th September. 1918.(l)   An Order in Council haa been issued prescribing the forme to be ut?ed for the purpose of voting by Absent Voters under the   Presentation of the People Act. 1918; and making regulations as to the mode in which ballot papers are to be sent to Voters for the purpose of voting by post and for the authentication of ////, marked, ballot papers and the preservation .of the secrecy of voting. Copies of the Order have been furnished to Registration Offloors with a Circular explaining their duties in carrying out the Order.A Circular has been issued to Registration Officers on the subject of the dispatch of notices to regular officers in the Army and Air Force, advising them that they are on the Kegister and informing them of the arrangements for voting by Absent Voters.   The Circular also explains the procedure to be adopted as regards the retention or removal fkrom the Absent Voters List of naval or military voters discharged from the Forces or transferred to the Army Keserve.The Department are in communication with the Registration Officers with a view to obtaining the necessary data for a,return of Parliamentary Electors on the Kegister of  lectors now in course of preparation.(2)   An Order has been made under the Defence of the Kealm Acts providing for advances being made by the Food Controller to local authorities in connection with the provision of National Kitchens and for the repayment by local authorities of such advances.(3)   An Order has been made providing for notification to &apos; Medical Officers of Health of cases of tuberculosis discovered at medical examinations by the National Service Medical Boards.(4)   A Regulation has been made under the Military Service Acts enabling men liable to military service to make application for exemption prior to their medical examination, subject to the coneent of the Director General of national Service.(5)   A Conference has been held with the Bailing Trade, at which representatives of the Ministry of Food, the Ministry of National Service, the Head Transport Board and the Coal Controller attended, with a view to securing economies of management in the trade.(6)   A Circular has been issued to sanitary authorities informing them of the introduction of Portuguese labourers into the country and their distribution in camps in various districts; and urging the authorities to co-operate with those responsible for the sanitary administration of the camps in securing wholesomi sanitary conditions and prompt treatment of any cases of infectious disease, in the interests of public health.

</content>
</cab>
