<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/67/0 images: 44-48</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1954SECRETCABINET office record copy copy No.   g7C. (54) 11224 th March, 1954CABINETTELEVISION bill memorandum by the Postmaster-general in C. (54) 106 I referred shortly to the views of the Association of BritishChambers of Commerce. As statements, amounting almost to a campaign, con-tinue to be made about the restrictions contained in the Bill frightening away trade,commerce and advertisers, I circulate a letter and memorandum (Annex I) whichI have received from the Association and also a note published in the AdvertisersWeekly of 11th March (Annex II) in case they may be of interest to my colleagues.It seems to me that, should this &quot; campaign &quot; develop much further, it may provedangerous to the carrying out of our policy, because, if successful, it may under-mine confidence even amongst the intending programme contractors who aresatisfied with the Bill as it is, or as it can easily be amended. It should be remem-bered that in this matter the Press, with their fear of losing advertising revenue, arein general against us and are only too willing to accept arguments which discreditthe scheme.D.Post Office Headquarters, E.C. 1,24 th March, 1954.45928h
ANNEX ITHE ASSOCIATION OF BRITISH CHAMBERS OF COMMERCE14, Queen Anne&apos;s Gate, Westminster, S.W.1,Dear Lord De La Warr, 22nd March, 1954.My Association has now had an opportunity of studying the Television Bill,which is to receive its Second Reading in the House of Commons on Thursday,25th March. In the light of our further discussions on this subject, my association has decided to issue the enclosed statement of policy regarding the Bill itself.You will see from this statement that we consider that Her Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment have gone a long way to meet the views and wishes of industry and commerce,and that the present Bill is a flexible measure which, in the light of experience, canbe adapted to meet the needs both of advertisers and of the viewing public.This Association, as you know, is very strongly of the opinion that the state-ments which have been made both in Parliament and elsewhere to the effect thatthe introduction of Commercial Television will result in debased standards areunwarranted and unworthy. If they were not so silly, they would amount to aninsult to the leaders of industry and commerce who, it should not be necessaryfor me to say, are, in the main, people with high standards of intelligence andtaste.In so far as it may lie within your power to do so, I do hope that you will take an opportunity of making our views on this point known within Parliament.Finally, I should like to express the appreciation of industry and commercefor the care and thought that you have given to the views they have put forward.It is our hope that we may be able to co-operate with your Department in theyears ahead to make Commercial Television the success that it undoubtedly could and should be.Yours sincerely,(Signed) T. H. SUMMERSON, Chairman,Home Affairs and Transport Division.The Right Hon. The Earl De La Warr,General Post Office,St. Martin&apos;s-le-Grand,London, E.C. 1.STATEMENT OF policy the  ASSOCIATION  OF  BRITISH  CHAMBERS  OF  COMMERCECOMMERCIAL TELEVISION POLICYTelevision Bill, 1954Now that Her Majesty&apos;s Government has presented the Television Bill toParliament, the Association feels that an expression of its views in the light of that development is necessary and desirable.There seems to be some misunderstanding of the opinion of industry and commerce on this subject. This second statement on behalf of the chambers of Commerce has therefore been drawn up after further discussions with thePostmaster-General, and with the knowledge of the reactions of trade and industryto the Bill itself.The Weight of opinion the Association would emphasise the nature and scope of its membershipwhich, in the main, would be at the &quot; paying end &quot; of the Governments proposalsboth as advertisers and, privately, as viewers. The Chambers of Commerceaffiliated to the A.B.C.C. have an aggregate membershio of nearly 70,000 individual
A Flexible bill the Association has always maintained its opposition to what is commonlyknown- as &quot;sponsored &quot;television. This term is usually applied to the practicefollowed in certain other countries, of selling time on the air to advertisers, whothen both provide the programmes and insert their announcements as and how they will. This practice has led to the virtual complete subordination of pro-grammes to the needs of advertising. The Association is therefore gratified to observe that the Bill now before Parliament provides for the introduction ofcommercial advertising into Television programmes by methods which will bothbe of assistance to industry and commerce and will at the same time guard against those less desirable features of sponsored programmes that are found insome other countries.It is the Association^ view that the safeguards contained in the Bill, if anything, err on the side of being unnecessarily restrictive, and may limit the freeuse of trial and error. On.the other hand the terms of the Bill are such that, at alater stage, the Postmaster-General will be able to modify the permitted methodsof advertising in the light of experience gained.In the Association^ opinion this is probably the best initial approach to an issue which has aroused so much public controversy.I.T.A. programmes Bill provides that the Independent Television Authority may, under special circumstances, itself provide television programmes and may acceptadvertising announcements. In general, industry and commerce are opposed tothe extension of trading by Public Corporations, but in this instance, and for thetime being, the Association accepts this feature of the Television Bill as being inthe public interest. This permissive provision will have the effect of reinforcingthe Authority&apos;s powers to maintain a suitable &quot; balance &quot; in programmes.Commercial T.V. InevitableSince the Association published its first expression of opinion on the principleof commercial television, it has had ample opportunity to study reactions from all sources to the subject. Having done so, it thinks it advisable that it should placeon record at this time, the principal reasons for which it supports the introductionof commercial television.Advertising on Television programmes is, in its opinion, bound to become thecustom both in continental Europe and in North America. With technical advance-ment, foreign television programmes, even over very long distances, will ultimately45928 b 2firinsj; and several hundred Industrial and trade associations, r Member firms varyffOm^very^laiige tos-very&quot;small industrial undertakings, and include numerouscommercial^hbuses andimerchants, professional partnerships, &amp;&amp;.;. The Associationspeaks1 for a&apos; comprehensive and entirely representative cross-section of industrial and commercial opinion in the United Kingdom.ti*iM ThroughVits-t-affiliated &quot;Chambers the Association is in daily . contact with industrial and&apos; commereiar opinion throughout the Kingdom. It also has closelinks^withi overseas: countries, and particularly with British trading communitiesoverseas: ;Its policy is formulated in consultation with its member Chambers,both directly and also through their elected representatives on its ExecutiveCouncil.&apos;     v&apos;    - !      &apos; &quot;of, :As art institution, the Chamber of Commerce movement in Britain dates backnearly three centuries. It sets out, among other things, to be a guardian of businessethics, and has throughout the years been a potent influence in encouraging thosehigh standards &quot;of business morality that have been so largely responsible for establishing that &quot;an Englishman&apos;s word is his bond.&quot;The Chambers of Commerce have long gained the reputation of giving theirfullest cooperation and assistance to the Government of the day whatever its political complexion-for they are concerned with the well-being of industry and commerce as the essential basis of the national standard of life, and take no sidesin party politics.These facts are stated at length so that the importance and weight of theAssociation^ views in this matter may be seen in their true perspective.
become receivable in this country. The converse will also apply.; Should GreatBritain neglect to recognise these facts, she will be the loser. Television is fastbecoming a most powerful medium for instruction, for education, and for propaganda, and its potential value as an advertising medium cannot possibly be overlooked.With to-day&apos;s imperative necessity for the maximum expansion of British trade,if full employment and. high standards of living are to be maintained, it would bein the nature of economic suicide for this country to lag behind in so pregnant afield as that of television. British firms would virtually be compelled to advertiseon foreign programmes. These would undoubtedly be receivable in the UnitedKingdom, but little or no benefit would accrue to British broadcasting institutions.Television is a universal medium; Britain has a duty to her own people both tomake the fullest use of this marvellous new force and to set an example to others in the way in which she does so. iWhile many industrialists and business men may, as viewers, share the feelings of those who dislike the idea of commercial advertising in television programmes,they are realistic enough to recognise that Britain cannot govern the tastes andconcepts of the whole world. Rather must she seek to live with and influence themby her example, making use of new media as they present themselves, while settingand maintaining a standard of procedure and taste that all will recognise as good.It is for these reasons that industry and commerce will support any Govern^ment in seeking a position of leadership in what is now an inevitable development.The present Television Bill is, in the Association^ view, an essential step in that direction.A Code of ConductMuch concern is still felt in industry and commerce that, despite the assurances that have been given to the contrary, it is still claimed in certain responsiblequarters that commercial television will lead to debased standards in programmes.This is a thoroughly unworthy and unjust imputation. British industry and commerce are not controlled by degenerates, but by sensible, high-minded people with a full sense of their responsibilities to the nation as a whole.The businessman, no less than other members of the Community, has tastesin entertainment and instruction that are entirely normal, and thoroughly British.In actual fact, as is well known, the advertising pages in the vast majority of journalsare not among the least interesting and instructive of their contents. Brief docu-mentary films, depicting their processes, may well be chosen by advertisers as theirmethod of announcement, with results which will not only be interesting but alsoeducational. It might not be inappropriate to recall that throughout the Kingdomthere are a multitude of institutions, cultural, educational, charitable and so on,which either owe their existence to, or are heavily subscribed to by, industrialistsand businessmen. Such facts should not be forgotten by those who, by imputation,would have the public believe that a new subject is automatically debasedimmediately it comes into contact with commerce. Commercial television shouldbe criticised, if it is to be criticised, on better grounds than these.As a practical and, it is hoped, helpful suggestion the Association is preparedto take the initiative in calling together the industrial and commercial interests concerned, possibly together with leading educationalists, with a view to drawing up a code of conduct which it would encourage and urge its members to accept and to practice in giving advertising support to television programmes. Inco-operation with the new Authority, and the Postmaster-General, some continuingagency could do much to preserve and improve the standards of programme to betelevised.ConclusionThere are a number of amendments which the Association would like to seeincorporated in the Television Bill, and which it is at present discussing with theGovernment. These, however, are concerned with points of detail rather than ofprinciple. The major principles of the Bill are Wholly acceptable to industry and commerce, and the Association will do everything in its power to ensure that this new medium of advertising gives service to the customers of trade and industry,while at the same time providing them with instructive, interesting and refreshingtelevision programmes.
ANNEX IIEXTRACT FROM THE ADVERTISERS WEEKLY,THURSDAY, 11th MARCH. 1954Competitive Television Bill Raises Points for Further NegotiationTo-morrow (Friday) the Institute of Incorporated Practitioners in Advertising^television advisory panel will meet to discuss the Government^ Television Bill.First reactions of the advertising industry to the Television Bill are favourable.It is felt that the recommendations of the Institute of Incorporated Practitioners inAdvertising and the Incorporated Society of British Advertisers have had someinfluence on the Governments scheme.Good PointsRestrictive legislation is refreshingly absent from the Bill. Many important matters are left to be decided by the proposed Independent Television Authority,either with or without the approval of the Postmaster-General. For example, noclasses of goods or services are banned such as pools, liquor, or patent medicines.Similarly there has been no attempt to lay down the number of contracts whichthe Independent Television Authority must make with the programme companies.As much as possible appears to have been left for negotiation.Bad PointsSome criticism is directed against the rather nebulous nature of the Bill, notablyas regards magazine programmes, shopping guides, and the use of documentaries,which were talked about in the White Paper but are not mentioned in the Bill.The Government is clearly determined to legislate against any form of sponsor-ship, but the phrasing of the relevant clauses both in the main body of the Bill and;in the Second Schedule (Rules as to Advertisements) would appear to cut out the sort of programmes envisaged in the White Paper, including shopping guides anddocumentaries made by firms.  Enlightenment is needed on these points.

</content>
</cab>
