<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/67/0 images: 62-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CABINET OFFICE CoRECORD COPY ---draft BETTER TO DR. THE HON. D.F. MALAN,PRIME MINISTER OF THE UNION OF SOUTH AFRICAMy dear Prime Minister,Dr. Geyer has shown me the Resolution which you propose to table in the Union Parliament, and has.informed me that, before doing so, your government would welcome the comments of the United Kingdom Govern&quot;ment.    I told Dr. Geyer that I must consult the Cabinet.    I have done so;and,as the matter is so important and can have such far-reaching effects,I would like to give you the considered opinion of our Government in aletter from myself.We appreciate very much that you should have invited ourcomments before taking any public action.At your request, after you had left London last June, I had along talk with Mr, Havenga on the question of transfer.    I know he reportedour conversation fully to you:  I of course reported it equally fully to mycolleagues, who approved of all that I had said.To-day the position remains the same, Our Government couldnot agree to the transfer of the Territories at the present time; and as I said to Mr. Havenga, even if the Government were willing to recommendsuch a transfer to our Parliament, Parliament would certainly reject itBSECRETC.(54) 11930TH MARCH, 1954CABINETTRANSFER OF THE HIGH COMMISSION TERRITORIES* Note by the Secretary of State for commonwealth relations circulate the letter I propose to write to Dr. Malan if the Cabinetapproves my recommendations in C. (54) 115.SWTNTCNCommonwealth Relations Office,S.W.I.29TH MARCH, 1954.
Moreover, if a request for transfer is publicly made by the UnionGovernment, either by tabling a Resolution or by some other official state-ment, it would be impossible for the Government of the United Kingdom toavoid declaring their attitude.    We should be immediately questioned inParliament;  and we should be bound to make our position plain.    It would therefore be fruitless to embark on any negotiations as proposed in thedraft Resolution, because it would be clear to everyone in both countries that negotiations on transfer could lead to no practical result,,In these circumstances our Government hope most sincerely thatthe Union Government will reconsider their present intention.    Surely toraise the question of transfer now can be of no possible advantage to either of us ?    If your Government asks for the transfer of the Territories now,our Government must refuse.This must have an unfortunate effect on relations between our twocountries, which both our Governments have been doing their best to fosterand improve.    It is so important that our fruitfull collaboration should go forward, not only with the active efforts of Ministers on both sides, but withthe general support of our peoples.    &quot;We know that is the desire of both governments.    At no time has this co-operation been more necessary.In the economic and financial sphere the collaboration of the whole Common-wealth has never been so marked; and between no two countries in theCommonwealth is it closer than between South Africa and ourselves, in allthat the Chancellor of the Exchequer and Mr. Havenga are doing together.In the sphere of defence our anxieties and our objects are the same.    we know the common danger we face;  we have already concerted plans together,,and we look forward to still closer collaboration in this too.    In all thisclimate matters a great deal.If we turn to the Territories themselves, we find again close co-operation over a wide range of practical matters, trade, transport,agriculture, health (human and animal) and development generally.    Allthat is working well, and we want to make it work still better to the mutual advantage of both the Union and the Territories.    I am sending out my besteconomic man to study this on the spot and to recommend practical stepswherever improvement can be made.    These are the practical things that make for increasing goodwill between the Union and the Territories.It is a continuing process, which can be carried forward better by day-to-daycollaboration than by negotiations of a formal kind.    &quot;Would it not be agreat pity to hinder or prejudice this in any way?Surely the wise course is to continue our collaboration on all thesefronts where there is such a wide measure of agreement and common action,and not to raise an issue on which we could not agree and on which, if itwere raised, just the sort of things would be said which are so much betterleft unsaid?My colleagues and I welcome the opportunity you have given us toexpress our views fully and frankly.    We have pondered these mattersdeeply, and we feel sure that you and your colleagues will give the sameconsideration to the comments which we make to you in all friendship andsincerity,,

</content>
</cab>
