<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/67/0 images: 136-137</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
5th April, 1954.CABINETPOST OFFICE MANIPULATIVE STAFF wages memorandum by the Postmaster GeneralThe Union of Post Office Workers has been making a seriesof claims for upgrading the value of their work.    On the  postmen&apos;claim, the Tribunal stated that there was no case for placing a highervalue on the work of London postmen, but that we should discuss certain points affecting provincial postmen .2.        This produced such indignation amongst London postmen thatthey were restrained from &quot;working to rule&quot; only by the headquarters of their Union putting in a definite claim based on interpreting theaward of the Tribunal as saying that:-(i)  we must give the provincial postmen a rise (based noton economic grounds, but on upgrading the valueof the work);  and(ii)  as the difference in pay between London and the provincesis sacrosanct, London wages must go up by the same amount, which in effect means that the award shouldbe set aside.3.        They now await my reply.      At the Home Affairs committee meeting on 2nd April I was asked to reply that:-(a) on the value of work aspect, we should seek anelucidation of the Tribunals award through theMinister of Labour, and subsequently discuss with the Union the question of the pay of provincial postmen as indicated by the Tribunal;and(b) as no claim has been made by the Union on any other basis than that of value of work, there would seemto be nothing else to discuss.4.        It seemed clear, however, in the discussion that mycolleagues were hoping that we would be able to arrive at some stage or another at a negotiated settlement.    This was summed up by theChancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster, viz. , the Governmentshould retain the sympathy and support of responsible Trade Unionistsand the public and that, to this end, they must make the reasons for theirattitude abundantly clear and must be prepared to adjust it todevelopments in the situation on the lines suggested by the Minister ofLabour&quot;.S  S T CABINET OFFICE yC.(54) 127 RECORD COPY COPY NC, * ^
.1^7This is especially apposite in that the postmen are in arrear of thewages level of comparable ou side industry, including the railwaymen,to whom concessions have so recently been made in spite of an arbitration award.5.        But if in fact we are prepared to concede or discuss (or - ifwe are not - the Arbitration Tribunal is likely to grant) an increasebased on the wages index, it would be bad tactics  not to mention itbeforehand and so give the trouble-making elements a grievance to exploit both with the staff and with public opinion.    Nor must we put ourselves in the position, after we have had a fight - with all the damageit must cause, of having forced out of us something which we knew all along we should have to give in the end.6.        Whatever we say or do now we are not very likely to avoid a conflict.    I am, therefore, thinking rather of the grounds we choose forbattle than of avoiding it.    My main anxiety is that once we decide to stand firm, we must fight to win, which means, of course, having both public opinion and moderate staff opinion with us.    If we do not win,we shall be worse off than if we had never fought.7.        In this connection it is my duty to give my colleagues somepicture of the situation that is likely to arise in the event of a &quot;work to rule&quot; movement spreading throughout London, which, without someadvance on our part, would almost certainly be supported and led byUnion Headquarters.    The movement may, of course, spread to theprovinces, or to the other postal services and to telephones andtelegraphs.    The Union have no strike fund, but this does not preclude the possibility of at least sporadic outbreaks of strike action.8.        Dislocation would be considerable during the first four days,before emergency steps could be put into operation.    After that we could,if things go right, give a poorish service in London, i. e. two deliveriesa day at not very regular times with letters frequently taking two orthree days or more.    This assumes a drop of 30 per cent in trafficbrought about by broadcast and press appeals not to post, and by refusingFool traffic (10 per cent of total correspondence), sample packets, etc.9.        I believe that we could win if - but only if - we were backed by public opinion and by the full resources of the Government.    among other things we shall need approximately 5,000 volunteers for Londonalone, and 250 military lorries and 1,500 troops.10.      I should like to have the authority of the Cabinet to see personallythe General Secretary of the Union and to say that:-(a) there can be no question of the Government acceptinghis interpretation of the Arbitration award, andtherefore his claim;(b) on the value of work aspect, we are prepared to seek anelucidation of the Tribunal&apos;s award through the Ministerof Labour, and subsequently to discuss with the union the question of the pay of provincial postmen asindicated by the Tribunal;(c) if the Union feel that they have a good case for making a claim on economic grounds, the Post Office, as always,is ready to discuss such a claim.D.Post Office Headquarters, E.C.1.5TH APRIL, 1954.-?.-

</content>
</cab>
