<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/67/0 images: 147-156</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)In accordance with the d.ecision of the Cabinet on21st January, 1954 (C.0.(54) *fth Conclusion, Minute 2) Iconsulted the Iron and Steel Board on the question of our relationship with the European Coal and steel Community.2.     The advice of the Board, which takes into account the viewsof iron and steel producers,  consumers and trade unions,  is setout in their letter to me of 23rd February, 1954 (Annex).     Promthis it will be&apos;seen that the Board do not favour the creation ofa common market, which in their opinion would involve definitedisadvantages without any clear counter-balancing benefits.Sn the other hand, the Board considers that a more limitedarrangement, providing for regular consultation on investment plans and on trading and price policies would be valuable.3a     The Board make it clear that this advice is based upon theirassessment of the direct interests of the industries concerned0At the same time, the Board recognise that,Her Majesty^Government may have to take into account wider political considera-tions of international policy, which may make it desirable toestablish with the Community a closer association than would bejustified on purely economic grounds.4*     Assuming that it is decided to accept M. monnet  invitation to have discussions with the High Authority, I sugggest that itmight be well to warn him informally that there are quite seriousmisgivings in Britain about some of the proposals contained inhis letter.5a     In this connection I consider it most important that representatives of the Iron and Steel Board should be included in,or associated with, the British Delegation and that full opportunity should be provided for them to have direct discussions with the steel experts of the High Authority.     Such an exchangeof views might quite possibly produce a more favourable attitude on the part of British Industry towards the proposal for acommon market in steel.     Failing this,  it would at least make clear to the High Authority the genuine difficulties to whichthis proposal gives rise..6,   . There would,  I think, be advantage in holding these technicaltalks at an early stage in the negotiations.    Meanwhile it mightbe wise for Her Majesty&apos;s Government not to commit themselves tooprecisely about the form of association to be established withthe Community.CONFIDENTIAL0. (54) 1515TH APRIL.  1954CABINET office record COPYCABINETUNITED KINGDOM ASSOCIATION WITH THE european coal AND STEEL community memorandum by the Minister of SupplyDe S.Ministry of Supply, WoC.2.5TH APRIL,   1954o
42ANNEXIRON AND STEEL BOARDNORFOLK HOUSE,ST. james SQUARE,LONDON,  S.VT.1.23rd February, 1954..My dear Minister,You have asked us to express our views about associationby the United Kingdom with the European Coal and steel community and with particular reference to the proposals contained in the letter of 22+tb December, 1953 addressed by thePresident of the High Authority to the Head of the UnitedKingdom Delegation in Luxembourg.20     That letter is in most general terms and needs bothclarification   and amplification before it could be regarded as providing even a basis for discussion.    It will therefore be appreciated that the observations which follow are necessarilybased on certain assumptions in the absence of precise information as to what the High Author it jr may have in mind.3a     The High Authority envisages an association with theUnited Kingdom which would provide:-(i)   As complete a relationship as possible betweenthe markets.(ii)   A basis for common action0(iii)   Machinery for carrying out these arrangements,,Ln     Mo Monnet makes it clear that the High Authority do notconsider that the full advantages of the common market can beobtained without some surrender of sovereignty on the part of member countries.   He goes on to say that he understands thatthe British Government would in no circumstances be preparedso to surrender sovereignty.   We presume that Mo Monnet is correct in this assumption and that accordingly no question of full membership of the Community arises despite the functional difficulties which inevitably stem from any more limited association.    In particular this assumption entailsthe consideration of the British Coal and Steel industries as entities apart from the Community which is a conceptionopposed to that of the ultimate complete integration of the economies of the member countries which lies behind the schuman Plan,,5o     The creation of a common market in coal and steel is themost fundamental part of the Treaty setting up the Community.Its aims at the free movement of these products within the boundary of the common market, unhampered by fiscal, quantitative,monetary or other restrictions and with no discrimination inthe price of sales by any individual producer to customerswithin that boundary.   There is provision for the suspension of the normal working of the common market in times of acutesurplus or shortage, in which event there are powers toimpose maximum and minimum prices and quantitative restrictions in the sense of production quotas and allocationRt. Honn Duncan Sandys, MoP.,Minister of Supply,Shell Mex House,Strand, W0C*20
of supplies.   These powers can also be applied to sales byCommunity producers in third markets,,    The whole system is governed by a complex set of rules and regulations, upon the effectiveness of which the successful functioning of the common market depends.6Q     We shall first attempt to examine the effect on the steelindustry of the united Kingdom of an association with thecommon market on the basis of its existing rules and on theassumption that these rules would be effective.   At a le.terstage we shall comment upon the practical difficulties which seem to us to lie in the way of ensuring the effectiveness ofthe ruleso7*     As a background it is important to bear in mind something of the history of the British steel industry since the end ofthe 1914-1918 war.   Traditionally the demand for steel is subjectto sudden and major fluctuations; a high proportion of thecapital of the industry is invested in fixed assetsj  and there is little flexibility in the way of being able to turn to themanufacture of other products.   By 1932 the industry had been driven into the grave situation disclosed by the report of theImport Duties Advisory Committee as a result, inter alia,of severe and in many respects unfair competition from overseassources, principally certain of the countries now members of theCommunity.   This led to a major change in Government policyaiming at the bulding up of a strong British steel industrybehind a tariff barrier.   Since the end of the 1939-1945 War avery substantial programme of modernisation and development hasbeen carried out.   Capacity has been increased by about50 per cent to something of the order of 18^ million tons a yearand some further increase is projected.   With tne exception ofplates and sheet virtually the whole of the home demand is nowbeing met from home production   Exports amount to about15 pc  cent of total production and in certain fields could beincreased if the supply was available.   At the present time theindustry is technically more efficient than its counterpart onthe Continent and over most of the field produces steel at a lower cost than its competitors.   We think that, this favourablemargin will diminish as continental competitors (particularlyGermany) improve their efficiency - in which they may be assisted by the financial provisions of the existing Treaty.But we have no reason to suppose that given reasonableconditions there will be any decline in the efficiency of ourown industry; it will naturally attempt to maintain its relativelead but in any event it has to maintain its competitiveability in overseas markets and it is subject to the supervision of an independent authority in the person of this Board.8.     For some considerable time there has been little market forBritish steel in the six countries representing the presentCommunity^   While it is difficult to make any reliableprediction we do not think that our association with theCommunity would be likely to lead to any significant increasein our sales in this market in the long term, particularly asthe Community aims at being self-supporting in steelwith a substantial export to third markets.The imports of iron and steel into this country from theCommunitj&apos;- have fallen from the pre-war level.   Short of
dumping or other unfair competition we should not expect theCommunity to be able materially to increase their market for steel in this country even without fiscal protection for ourown industry.     Nevertheless the existing tariff gives materialprotection and the question would be whether such rules as might be established in the event of our association with theCommon Market would give equally adequate protection againstUnfair practices,9,     We accept that up to a certain point external competitionacts as a spur to internal efficiency.     But beyond that pointit may create conditions which hold no inducement to further capital outlay or effort and so lead to a lowering of efficiency.On the assumption that there must for strategic and general economic reasons be a healthy and substantial steel industry inthis country, it is necessary to ensure that it will not be exposed to unfair competition.     It is true that under association with the Community steel from other member countries could not,under the non-discrimination rule, be sold here at a price below that charged to buyers in the country of origin (plus freight).But while this is adequate protection against dumping in theusual sense of the term, it would be no protection against an overall policy of seeking output through unduly low prices -at least for a period - by individual continental producers or groups of producers.    This contingency is not necessarily remotein the absence of a common currency, a common taxation and social benefit system, a common price policy and indeed a commonstandard of living within the common market.10.    Admittedly a situation of this kind which would springfrom surplus conditions can be met within the framework of theexisting Treaty, either by the prescription of minimum prices or by the establishing of a system of production quotas.   Actionof this nature, however, would presumably only be taken inrelation to the whole of the market, not to a part only.   If wewere to join the common market the question arises whetherbilateral agreement to take action could ever be reached merely because the British industry was in our opinion being exposed to unfair competition from the other members, and if so whetheraction would flow sufficiently quickly.    The point is whetherthe potential danger to the British industry is real enough to warrant the United Kingdom reserving a right to unilateral action based on tariffs or quantitative restrictions against theother members.    We consider that the danger is real, but wecannot reconcile the reserving of such a right with any genuineassociation with the common market.    The acceptance of this riskseems to us to be one of the disadvantages inherent in the proposition (see also paragraph 15).11,   The means provided in the Treaty for dealing with surplusconditions are not in principle objectionable so long as theconditions giving rise to the surplus are affecting each membermore or less equally.    The real difficulty will arise when thereis inequality in this connection, and it is important to bear inmind that the falling off in demand which affected continentalproducers in 1950 and again in the later part of 1953 was nothinglike so evident in.the case of British producers.   Under asimilar state of affairs, while the prescription of minimum prices affecting the British market would be tolerable from acommercial point of view, much greater difficulty would arise from any attempt to impose production quotas since these migntinterfere with the level of our trade internally and in tnxrclmarkets.    There is a positive advantage in the right to prescribe j
siminimum prices under surplus conditions as this would operate to stop the rot of insensate internal competition likely to lead to serious inefficiency if prolonged for too great a lengthof time.    Minimum prices could of course Toe introduced either by legislation or by agreement among producers in this country without any association with the Community0   Whether such acourse would commend itself politically unless as part of aninternationally agreed policy for dealing with surplus conditions is, however, doubtful.12.    There is then the Community1s right to prescribe minimum prices for sales in third markets under surplus conditions.This might be advantageous to us in avoiding cut-throat methodsin these markets.    But care would have to be taken that it wasnot carried to a point which encouraged third,countries toincrease their own production under protective measures0    It is perhaps also worth mentioning that the &quot;cartel&quot; aspect of thisprovision would be likely to offend American susceptibilities.13.    Outside the ability to impose minimum prices, we see little to be gained - as compared with existing protective measures -&apos;by an association with the common market under conditions of surplus.    On the other hand we do envisage some danger that therules might not go far enough to give our own industry the sameprotection which it at present enjoys under tariff andquantitative restrictions,lk.    Turning now to conditions of shortage, the rules providefor the imposing of maximum prices and the allocation of supplies,.We do not consider that there is any objection in principle tothe prescription of maximum prices (that course has been followed in the United Kingdom for some time) but we do see obvious objections to the allocation of supplies which might reactseriously upon the production programmes of the metal-using industries in this country and upon our position in third marketsparticularly the Commonwealth.    This is no doubt one cardinalpoint on which the British Government would not be prepared to surrender sovereignty.15o    We have been commenting upon the nature of the rules dealingwith surplus and shortage conditions9 and we have touched uponthe difficulties which might arise if these conditions did notapply uniformly throughout the whole market.    This apart,however, we must emphasise that in the event of an association with the common market one of the most fundamental matters willbe to decide how agreement is to be reached on whether there areconditions of surplus or shortage.    It would have to be con-sidered whether the United Kingdom should, reserve the right to declare such conditions operative so far as it was concerned inthe event of failure to reach agreement with the High authority and to impose the consequential provisions so far as the british market was concerned.    To be effective in this respect minimum prices would have to be operative with buyers as well as sellers,,16.    We shotild consider it essential that no association shouldbe entered into with the Coitimunity unless the necessary waiversunder the General Agreement on tariffs and Trade were obtained   -to preserve an appropriate tariff on iron and steel againstthe rest of the world - irrespective of any reduced levelvis-a-vis the Community,,    In this connection it is the declaredobjective of the Community to harmonise its tariffs and other restrictions against non-member countries at a low level.We think it of great importance that no variation in theprotection of the British industry against third nations should be effected without the consent of the United Kingdom.-ll.-
17,   Association with the Community would involve questions affecting the whole system of imperial Preference which mighthave serious effects upon its continuance and therefore over a wide field of British industry.      This question in its widest&apos;aspect is not one for us, hut on the narrower aspect of its effect on the steel industry, we should he seriously perturbedby any reduction in the preference which that industry now enjoysboth in the self-governing countries of the Commonwealth and inthe Colonies.     This is the more important when regard is had tothe probability of major development in these territories inwhich the British steel industry would expect to have a sub-stantial share.18.   An association with the common market would mean that under normal conditions there would be no price control outside thenon-discrimination rule.     This means that the prescribing of maximum prices for steel which has effectively been a part ofGovernment policy for some 20 years would have to be abandoned.This control of prices really grew out of the fiscal protection afforded to the industry but has tended to become common ground in the political disputes which have.arisen over the industry inthe sense of maintaining some public control of the profits of a highly organised industry basic to the economy.     We cannot bejudges of the political implications involved, nor do we suggestthat price control should be an objective in itself.      It shouldbe stated, however,  that the ability to determine maximum price is the most effective sanction which this Board possess in theirsupervision of the industry.19.   The domestic price of British steel at the present time islower for a number of products than the price at whichcontinental producers could sell here, even if there were notariff.      Consequently on the withdrawal of maximum prices inthe home market the price of steel would in these instancesprobably tend to rise to prevent a run on British steel bycontinental consumers.     The extent of any such rise is diffi-cult to determine - continental prices are tending to fall - butit might be a matter of some moment to the metal using industries in this country.     British steel producers could notin association with the common market be debarred from enjoyingthe same right as their continental competitors to obtain whatprofit they could in good times to offset lower profits underless favourable conditions.     There are instances (e.g. billets)where the continental domestic price is as low or slightly lower than the British domestic price but it is not certain that thisderives from any difference in favour of the Continent in thereal cost of production.20,   Association with the common market based on rulesequivalent to those under the existing Treaty would require legislation in this country, for example the prescription of minimum prices in the home market;    the prescription of anyprices in third markets;    publication of price lists and theenforcing of non discrimination in prices;    and the applicationof production quotas (if accepted).     The political issues raised thereby are not for us.21.    So far our observations have been based on the assumptionthat the rules governing the common market will be effective.In our ppinion, however,  this assumption is open to&apos; the gravestdoubt.      Already serious difficulties have developed about thenon discrimination rule which appears to have been honoured onlyin the breach.      So much so that the High Authority has now
/S3decided to permit a variation of 2-g- per cent either side of aproducer1s published price list and to employ independentaccountants to chock the whole of the transactions of everyproducer in an effort to ensure observance of tho rule     Thispoints to the High Authority being drawn into a field of detail in an effort to maintain its prestige and also suggests the producers being subjected to an extensive policing system.This difficulty applies to steel and not to coal because inthe case of at least two major members, Prance and Germany,there is centralised selling of coal.      In the case of steelwhere there is a wide variety of products sold by a large numberof individual producers,  the difficulty becomes acute.     the observance of the non discrimination rule is fundamental to thewhole concept of this Treaty,     But the difficulty of maintainingit is very real because of the attempt to isolate coal and steel &apos;from all the varying factors and influences operating within sixseparate national economies.      It seems to us that in theabsence of complete political and economic integration therewill always be grave difficulty about maintaining the nondiscrimination rule,  and indeed other of the rules governing thecommon market.      The differing systems of taxation and thedifferent conditions governing raw materials, fuel and transport,to mention only a few, would inevitably lead to seriouspractical problems in determining equitable maximum and minimum prices.     Moreover some continental nationals are not distin-distinguished for their respect for the regulations of their own government, let alone those of a supra-national authority.      Inour opinion there is a real danger that the whole concept mightbreak down, because of failure to observe the underlying rules.And since our own producers would be more likely to observe therules than at least some of the others, we think that an association with the common market might well expose the British,industry to serious disadvantage.     We believe that sufficient time has not elapsed for the High Authority to be able to demonstrate that it is in fact master in its own house,  and thatthis country is being asked to become associated with a marketwhose effectiveness is,  at the moment, in disrepute.      It seemsto us that it might be a condition precedent to any discussionwith the High Authority that there should be an opportunity toexamine these problems with them in the light of the actualexperience of the manner in which the common market has workedup till now.22.   We now touch on the possible effect of association on supplies of fuel and raw materials in regard to which theTreaty provides that there should be free movement within thecommon market.     The British industry is not likely to be dependant for solid fuel on overseas supplies, but it would- be important to ensure that the reserves of coking coal in thiscountry were not encroached upon to supply the continentalmarket to the ultimate disadvantage of the British steelindustry.23.    So far as scrap is concerned,  the aim of the Britishindustry is to be independent of imported supplies within thenext few years.      Nevertheless for some time at least semeimports will be necessary.      The major consideration, however,in the event of association would be to ensure that there wasno net outflow .of scrap frcm this country to the continent.This could only be done under &quot;free&quot; conditions by allowing theprice of scrap in this country to reach relative parity withthat on the continent.     This would mean the abandoning of thepresent policy-of controlling scrap prices here and prohibitingexport, unless the Community were prepared to adopt a similarpolicy or acquiesce in unilateral action by the United Kingdom.
In any event it would hardly he possible to keep the price of scrap here at an artificially lov/ level relative to the continentwithout giving the appearance of an unfair subsidy to the costof steelmaking in this country.     A rise in scrap prices would increase the price of British steel although there would be something of a compensatory adjustment in the aggregate to the metal using industries through the higher price which they would obtain for scrap sold to the steel industry.     This adjustmentwould, however, bo uneven in its individual incidence0     (We donot wish our remarks in this connection to be taken as expressinga view by the Board in favour of maintaining the present controlof scrap as this is a question upon which we shall be advisingyou in due course in connection with our general review of the structure of steel prices.)2^u    In the case of iron ore we do not look to the Coramunity for supplies although we do obtain substantial quantities from french north Africa, which territory is not at the present time withinthe common market - though tho Treaty makes some provision for possible modification, in this respect.     Even so it does notappear to us that our supplies from this source would be likelyto be seriously affected if we remained outside the common marketsThere remains the question of whether there would he any demand from tho Community for British ore resulting in an increase in price in this country, or in the depletion of reserves.     Havingregard to the low iron content of this ore and the cost oftransport we should not consider this likely to happen under an association with the Gommon markets25c   As regards investment policy the existing powers given tothis Board under the Iron and Steel Act, 1953 are different tothose possessed by the High Authority.     The latter can do no more than express an opinion upon a development project (unlessits successful operation is likely to be dependent on some formof subsidy or protection) whereas no project can be startedwithout our approval.     On the other hand tho High Authority willbe able to assist with the financing of development first fromits own resources raised from the levy on producers, and secondthrough the raising or guaranteeing of loans.     We think thatcareful consideration will have to be given to whether theBritish industry should be subject to the levies imposed by theHigh Authority, and therefore able to participate in thefinancial assistance given by the High Authority, not onlytowards development but in tho v/ay of compensation to displacedlabour and otherwise.     Our preliminary feeling is that theBritish industry should be excluded from both.26,   We believe that it would be valuable to have a regularexchange of information with the High Authority on investment plans and to discuss these with a viow to trying to ensure thatthere is no unnecessary duplication and that so far as possible development takes place in the most favourable location.     This,however, is something that could and should be done irrespective of any formal association with the common market.     Since theHigh Authority has itself no power to restrict development, it isclear that no final decision could flow from such consultation,but much might he done in tho way of influence.
27o   There are other matters hearing upon the existing regulations and powers governing the common market to whichwe think it right to draw attention because of their reflectionon sovereignty.     These are the free movement of Labour;    non-discriminations in transport charges;    the rights of the high authority consequent upon action by an individual Governmentaffecting coal or steel enterprises within or without theterritory of that Government;    intervention in cases of low wages rates;    action concerning minimum and maximum tariffs and supervision of licensing arrangements;    and the jurisdiction of the Court.28.   We come now to the question of a basis for common actionin the event of a formal association.     M. Monnet suggests theappointment of a Council of Association composed of three members appointed by the High Authority and three by the UnitedKingdom,     Clearly some such joint body would be necessary, butwe think it of first importance to determine the scope of theCouncil&apos;s authority, the method of carrying its decisions intoeffect, and the question of what happens in the event of dis-agreement on the Council.29.   We assume that the basis of the association would be twoequal partners, the High Authority of the one part and theUnited Kingdom of the other.     Certain rules would be laid down for the governing of the associated markets which would be putinto operation by both bodies in their respective spheres in theevent of their reaching agreement upon the course of action tobe followed.     If agreement was not reached, it would be open to either party to put the rules into operation so far as its ownsphere was concerned but with no power in relation to the sphere of the other.30.   It seems to us that some sacrifice of freedom of action is inevitable under an association, however, limiteda     But wethink it essential to be clear as to the agency through whichthe United Kingdom would operate vis a vis the High Authority.So long as this Board remains charged with the statutory dutyof supervising the iron and steel industry and ensuring anadequate, economic and efficient supply of these products, wo find it difficult to visualise our being able to discharge these functions unless wo are the sole channel of communication and discussion with the High Authority.      If there was to be directcommunication between the Government and the High Authority or through any agency other than the Board, our present feeling isthat the continued existence of the Board would serve littlepurpose.     While it is true that the High Authority possessgovernmental status their functions are confined to coal andsteel and do not in fact differ much in principle from thoseattaching to the National Coal Board and ourselves.     It istherefore our considered view that the United Kingdom members .of the Council of Association should be nominated by the coal and Steel Boards.     If any governmental representative was in-cluded this would at once bring the whole policy of the steel board within the roalm of political consideration and seriously affect the present autonomy of the Board.31.   M. Monnet further suggests that the action of the Councilof Association should be subject to some form of public dis-cussion.     Wo feel that it would be undesirable that the Councilof Association should be responsible to any mixed politicalbody and that the proper course would be for the High Authorityto remain responsible to its present political institutions and
for the British Boards to he responsible to the british parliament, as they are now.32,   To summarise, our view is that there is little economic advantage to be obtained from an association with the Communitybased on the common market.     There are certain clear disad-vantages v/hich centre in doubts as to whether it is a practical proposition to segregate the coal and steel Industries of various countries from the remainder of their several economies in themanner envisaged in the existing Treaty; whether, if it is,the rules governing the common market can ever be made suffi-ciently effective; and whether the British industry could be adequately safeguarded if this country became associated withthat market.     We believe from a purely economic point of view,the judgment must be against association with the common market.33.   We fully recognise that political considerations of whichwe have neither knowledge nor the abilitjr to judge may be suffiently strong to override what we believe to be the dis-advantage in the economic field.     We should, however, hope thatin any event having regard firstly to the inability at thisstage to judge of the effectiveness of the Community and secondly.,to the instability apparent in certain of its member countries,any association by the United Kingdom should provide for with-drawal on reasonable notice.     We also recognise that theGovernment may feel it necessary to have some discussion withthe High Authority following M. monnet  letter and as a resultof previous statements as to our interest and goodwill,3h.   We are satisfied that whether or not there is any formalassociation with the Community, constant consultation betweenthe High Authority and this Board would be both necessary and valuable.     We should visualise such consultation as coveringinvestment plans and. the concerting of trading and price policyso far as possible.     If the Government felt that there must be some formal association it seems to us that one providing for consultation on these lines but without any commitment regardingthe common market would be at once a more prudent and a moreprofitable line of approach for this country,35.   In answer to your enquiry for our views on the positionof the steel industry in any negotiations which may be under-taken, we would, suggest most emphatically that the Board shouldbe associated with these negotiations at every point since theywill clearly affect the whole field of the activity of the Boardand the industry for which they are responsible.     It would be our task to obtain the views and advice of the industry itself -wherever appropriate.36.   Finally we should say that on the economic implications of association we have sought the views of leading representativesof the British Iron and Steel Federation and of the principalTrades Unions concerned with the industry.     Generally speakingthese accord with those expressed by us.     The Federation desire,however, to submit more formal views after further considerationof M. Monnet!s letter and these we shall transmit to you whenreceived with any appropriate observations by burselves.Yours -sincerely,(Signed)     A.F. FOPBES

</content>
</cab>
