<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/67/0 images: 203-207</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
.12afl(this document is the property op her britannic majesty&apos;s government)secret -   cabinet 0pfjceMftO 1M RECORD COPY copy no. bl13TH april.  195hCABINETCIVIL defence memorandum by the Home secretary in accordance with arrangements made some weeks ago,I am due to make a speech about civil defence at a meeting ofrepresentatives of industry and commerce and of the BristolTrades and Labour Council on 23rd April at Bristol.2.     I had intended to speak principally about industrial civil defence matters but in present circumstances it is inevitable that I should deal with the hydrogen bomb which isengaging the attention of the whole nation.3*     As this will be the first Government speech on civil defence since the recent debate on the hydrogen bomb, I thoughtthat my colleagues should see the attached draft of what i propose to say.d. m.p.Home Office, S.W.1.13TH APRIL, A 95k.
Z03APPENDIX10     This is the first occasion I have had, since the releaseof the news about the hydrogen bomb,  to make a speech on thesubject of civil defence and, if I had chosen the occasion for myself, I could not have had. a better opportunity fordelivering the message which I want to deliver this afternoon.2.      I am particularly glad to be speaking in this great city of Bristol.      In all the length and breadth of the country,there is no city with greater traditions or with a more vigorous personality.     The City of Bristol knows as wellas any place what war means to the civil population and whatis the value of a strong civil defence organisation and,measured by the ratio of recruitment to population,  the region of which Bristol is the headquarters town stands  secondamong the eleven Regions in its development of the civil defence Corps since recruitment started in 19^9.3,      I am glad, too,  to be speaking to a gathering ofrepresentatives of both sides of industry.     There is nothing to choose between employers and employed if it is a questionof interest in civil defence,  just as in the political fieldthere has never been any difference between Government and opposition in this matter of civil defence.U.      The message which I want to deliver is that there is nothing in the developments which have been reported in thelast few weeks which weakens the case for civil defence.On the contrary, they are a challenge to all concerned topress on with their efforts.      But before I enlarge on this aspect I should like to offer a few observations on the new situation generally.5o      The development of a hydrOgen bomb far more powerful  .than the atomic bomb has for quite a long time been&apos;known byscientists to be a possibility but until recently we did rotthink it would materialise anything like so quickly.     now we know that the United States are conducting a series ofexperiments with these bombs.     We believe that the soviet union has also succeeded in exploding such a bomb, but wethink they arte well behind the Americans in technical development though closer to them than they were in thecase of the development of the atomic bomb.     That is thesituation in a world broadly speaking divided into twohalves (but only by the wish of one half) - divided by aniron curtain.      How is this new situation to be handled?6.     The single constant objective of everyone who gives amoments thought to this dreadful problem is to ensure thatthe hydrogen bomb is never used as a means of attack by one country on another,  and that must be the first charge on theenergies of Her Majesty&apos;s Government.      I cannot believe thatthere has ever been such unanimity of objective in any political and international question amongst all citizens,regardless of political outlook.     But how is this to beachieved?  . There are three courses which could beconsidered.-1-
2o&apos;\7.     First we could surrender.     We could declare we wouldhave no lot or part in the development or use of the bomb andwe could,  I suppose, attempt to persuade our allies to adopt this view.     We should thus leave the development of thehydrogen bomb to the other half of the world, that is toRussia;    and it would only be a matter of time, and a short time, before we were obliged to abandon our freedom and handourselves over as slaves to a slave state.      For that,  sooner or later and probably sooner, would be the inevitable resultof a decisive inferiority in our defensive equipment.SureDy not one of us will give a moment1 s further considerationto such a fatalistic solution.8.      Secondly, the objective could be achieved by deterrence.In plain terms we must have better bombs than any possibleaggressors.     This would be a heartbreaking method, cruel tothe inhabitants of all the countries in both halves of theworld upon whom the dreadful threat would lie continuouslyas a potential horror.      It could only be allowed to endureuntil some far better method could be devised.      But whilstit did remain - and does at the present moment remain - theonly practicable method,  it makes it vital, for example,  thatthe United States should continue her experiments and.development of this new bomb,9.     Thirdly, there is the method of an agreed scheme forlimitation of armaments which would carry with it as an absolutely integral part an agreed and effective scheme of inspection and control.     This is the method to which her majesty&quot;s Government are wholly committed.      It is the only way in which they can see a hope of bringing relief to theworld from the threatened horrors of atomic attack and fromthe material burden of vast defence expenditure.      But thesecond component of the plan is a vital feature.     Expressionssuch as &quot;Ban the bomb&quot; are meaningless unless there is asystem to detect evasion and enforce compliance.     ever since the war repeated attempts have been made to reach some form of agreement on this basis but all have hitherto beenfrustrated one after another by the Soviet veto.      Now withthe existence of the hydrogen bomb and its vast and far-reaching effects,  it may be that the relative immunity of soviet territory is much decreased and there may now be some disposition to join hands with the rest of the world in reaching an agreement.     Two lines of approach are atpresent being made and Her Majesty&apos;s Government are committed to raising discussions to the highest possible level at theearliest moment at which such a move is likely to be successful.      We shall work and hope and pray for successbut none of our past experience encourages the hope of aspeedy result.      For the immediate future., therefore, for what all must hope will be but an interim period, we must continue to rely on the deterrent method, and during thisperiod we must persevere in our policy of upholding at thenecessary level all our defence resources - including ofcourse our civil defence services.
10.     And this brings me to the question of especial interest toyou, namely, the effect of the new situation on civil defence.Let me soy at once that it does nothing to alter our conception of civil defence as a &quot;long haul&quot;.     The policy of Her Majesty&apos;s&apos;present Government, like that of our predecessors, has been directed to the prevention of war and not to preparations for awar which we do not consider to be imminent or even inevitable.That is still our policy.      I do not believe that the addition ofthis now weapon to the armoury of a great and friendly peoplemakes war any more probable or, if it is to come, brings it one day nearer.     On the contrary.11.    Do not conclude from this that there will be no change inthe nature of our civil defence plans.     Changes there must be -and I shall have- something to  say about them in a minute - but,for the present at least, they are more the concern of the CentralGovernment than of local authorities and industry, though,    sofar as considerations of national security permit, there willbe consultations with both during the coming months.12.   We must not lose our nerve in the face of this freshpotential horror.     To suppose that one such bomb could destroy the world or even kill everyone in this country is a sign  ofignorance, hysteria, and panic.     What it can do is sufficientlyhorrible without indulging in unreasoning exaggeration.     Fromground zero the radius for total destruction with the iSniwetok.bomb in 1952 was of the order of 3 miles, of very serious damage up to 7 miles and of lighter damage up to 10 miles,and we must expect greater power of destruction.     All this is indeed terrible and more than ever before the nations of theworld must find some way to prevent this ghastly horror evermaterialising.     But we cannot count on this yet and perhaps not for a considerable time.     What therefore should be the effectof the existence of this bomb on our civil defence plans?13.    I am sure you all realize that the whole field of our defence measures is affected.     But X ani dealing today only with its irapaot on civil defefioew-    I have of course alreadyb^en questioned on these things m the House of Commons and Ihave assured the House that I have set on foot an   immediatereview of the whole of our plans.      The range to be covered iswide.      It includes, for example, our plans for giving warning to the civil population;    the measure for dispersal fromprobable target areas;    the plans for maintaining communications and other essential services;    and the large and difficultfield of structural precautions.     A large number of complicated and difficult problems are involved and I cannot promise anearly answer to all of them, but I can assure you that the examination of them has begun and that we shall press onvigorously with this examination.H4..    To one problem, I have no doubt of the answer.      So far asregards the Civil Defence Services (the Civil Defence Corps,the Auxiliary Fire Service and the National Hospital ServiceReserve) the need for their development is greater and notsmaller.     Some changes of organisation, or training and of tactics may be needed and these will be announced as soon aspossible.     But the fundamental need to press on with the recruitment and training of these Services remains.     Just asthe introduction of the atom bomb with its potentially greatlyincreased number of casualties made civil defence services evenmore essential than in the days of high explosive attack, so\with the stepping up of the scale of destruction and casualtiesby the hydrogen bomb the need for numbers of trained men andwomen to deal with the aftermath of such an attack will be e^enlarger,     The radius of the area affected by the bomb would bebigger.     But not so big that in the main concentrations of
2&amp;built-up areas - for example, in London, the Midlands,ivierseyside, and Clydeside - there would not be a very large area indeed in which trained civil defence services must beready to operate.     And this situation might be reproduced in any of the smaller built-up areas if the bomb wereexploded away from the &quot;town centre&quot;.     Are the survivors andthose unaffected in all the surrounding areas to be untrained andignorant of how to bring help and succour to those not destroyedby the actual explos ion  itself?     Suppose Birmingham were hit and Coventry escaped, as it well might, is the population ofCoventry to stand by and watch thousands of persons perish who might have been saved if they had been organised by their electedleaders and taught how to deal with the rescue of those who could still be rescued, and with others capable perhaps of moving out of the area on their own but needing the help, comfort and succour of the trained civil defence welfare services?15.    I referred just now to the need for women as well as men.It is sometimes made a point of criticism that the Civil DefenceCorps contains so high a proportion of women.     Nothing couldbe more foolish.      If anything, the need for a strong and efficient welfare section (which is specially suitable for women)has been intensified for dealing with the homeless and evacuees,^nd how glad I am that my predecessor and I have consistentlysupported the development of that magnificent auxiliary bodythe were, S. and the no less valuable voluntary aid organisations,the British Red Cross Society and the Order of St. John.16.    But let it not be supposed that we imagine that these responsibilities! can be shouldered by the local authoritiesand industry without assistance from the Central Government,iiiven since 19U-8 it has been an integral part of planning thatthe more mobile services (in particular those responsible forfighting fires and rescuing trapped casualties) should include a large component organised by the Government on a regionalbasis.     The provision of man-power for the mobile columns isa difficult problem.     A study of this problem was initiated bythe late Government and completed recently by us.     as a resultwe were able to announce in the House of Commons on 2nd March a plan for training R.^.P. reservists in civil defenceduring their part-time service.     This will mean that in thecourse of six years we shall have some 100,000 men partlytrained in rescue and firefighting;    in the event of war theywould be mobilised by the R.A.F.  under their own officers for civil defence duty and subject to civil defence operational control.      This plan will give us a. very substantial nucleus of a mobile column organisation and we are satisfied that itis better, and incidentally more economical, than any alternativewhich has been suggestedo     We were in sight of completing this plan before the recent developments and we shall press on with it with confidence and enthusiasm.17*    Let me conclude by saying that we do not underestimate the magnitude of the new factor which has been introduced, butHer Majesty^ Government will do their best to tackle it and they feel confident that they can rely on the support of all thosewho share their belief in the value and importance of civil defence.

</content>
</cab>
