<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/30/0 images: 20-44</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT Io THE PROPERTY OF HIS britannic MAJESTY1 S GOVERNMENT).J3 E OR E T.CABINET    24    (22),CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldin Mr, Charaherlain&apos;s Room, House of Commons,S.W.,  on Monday, April 10th, 1922, at 4.15 p.m.PRESENT:-The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, 11.P.,Lord Pro vy Seal.(In the Chair),The Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C.,M.P., The Right Hon. Y/.S. Churchill,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.      M.P., Secretary of State forthe Colonies.The Right Hon. The Viscount Peel,G.B.E., Secretary of State forIndia.The Right Hon. S, Baldwin, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right lion. Sir y\lfred Mond,Bart.,H.P., itfirilster of Health.The Right Hon. H.A.L. Fisher,M.P., President of the Boardof Education,The Right Hon. Sir A. Griffith-Boscawen, M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood,Bart.,K.C,,M.P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.The Right Hon. The Earl of crawford and Balcarres, K.T., First commissioner of Works.TIPS FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT: -Mr. E. Hilton Young, D.S.O..D.S.C., Mr. H.J. Wilson, C.B.,C.R,E.,M.P., Financial Secretary to the Secretary to the Ministry of treasury. Labour.   (For Conclusion 6).Mr. Thomas jones mr. R.B. Howorth...Acting Secretary.Assistant Secretary.
ISBLA5D (1)    With reference to Cabinet 23 (22) Conclusion 1 (c)&apos;p -(a) Private     the Secretary of State for the Colonies made a briefLetter toMr.Collins,      statement on the Irish situation.    In his opinion the -next ten days would undoubtedly be of critical importance and before a month bad passed we should know whether theleaders of the Pree State were prepared to fight or toendure without resistance the insults now being offeredthem.    There were signs of a stiffening of the attitudeof Mr Collins in the last day or two.Mr Churchill, continuing, said he would like to be released from his undertaking at the last Cabinet to write an official letter to Mr Collins.    He thought itwould be more helpful to write a private letter putting forward&apos; the considerations desired by the Cabinet.(b) With reference to Cabinet 23 (22) Conclusion 1 (d)the Viceroy was present and in response to a suggestionthat he should not return to Dublin at the presentcritical juncture Lord PitzAlan said his absence wouldnot only be highly inconvenient in view of many social,engagements already fixed but would also be hardly fair to the leaders of the Provisional Government.    It waspointed out to Lord Pitz&amp;lan that while he was preparedto run considerable personal risk any untoward incident,such as seizure by enemies of the Pree State,    would place His Majesty&apos;s Government in a very embarrassing position, and it was therefore imperative that the Vice-regal Lodge should be properly safeguarded.The Cabinet agreed:-(1) That the Secretary of State for the colonies should send a private and not a formal letterto Mr Collins.(2) That the Secretary of State for the colonies should reguest the G.0,C.Ireland to provide atonce an adequate military guard for the protect-ion of the Viceroy while in residence in Ireland.
THE.COM3 TABHLARY.P (IRELAM D) i&apos; BILL).,The Cabinet had under consideration a Memo by the Chief Secretary for Ireland(CP.3931) covering the draft of a Bill togive legal effect, so far as is necessary,to the terms on which the Government have undertaken to disband the Royal irish constabulary.     After the need for urgencyhad been emphasised the Cabinet agreed:-(1)    To approve the draft Bill subjectto certain drafting points to besettled by the Chief Secretary for ireland and the Financial Secretaryto the Treasury in consultation.(2)    To authorise the immediate introduction of the Bill in theHouse of Commons and to take stepsto secure its passage into lawas soon as possible after the easter recess.(3)    That pending the passage of theBill into law the Treasury shouldmake arrangements .to provide the requisite funds.
^iSGrUAEDIHGr        J.     With reference to Cabinet 19 (22) ConclusionW INDUS TKliSSCT.(PART II).     3, the Cabinet had under consideration Memoranda(CP. 3852 and CP. 3898) by the President of theBoard of Trade relative to the question of theexercise by the Board of Trade of their powers under the Safeguarding of Industries Act (Part II),to make and Ckder relative to Fabric Gloves andGlove Materials.The Cabinet were informed that an immediate decision was desirable in aa much as the wholeof the policy on which the Act was baaed waa to be criticised in the House of Commons on Wednesday next.In the case under consideration the Committeehad reported unanimously in favour of the exerciseby the Board of Trade of their power under Part ii of the Act to impose an import duty of 33 l/3rcl on imported fabric gloves and glove materials.   Ifthe recommendations of this unanimous Report were,over-ruled the whole case for Part II of the Actwould disappear.   It was, however, doubtfulwhether the Lancashire Fine Spinning Industry wouldbe in any respect damaged if the order were made and it would be impossible to administer the Actif threats of retaliation by Germany were to prevail.On the other hand, the Cabinet were reminded that the  aw Officers had now advised that the powerof the Board of Trade to make an Order under section (3) of the Act is discretionary and that if anorder were made in the present case one of the greatstaple industries of the country would certainly be alienated, while it waa doubtful whetherthe small glove industry would be benefited.If In these
In these circumstances the Beard of Trade shouldweigh the balance of damage and use their discretionby over-ruling the Committee,   ilo doubt the fears of lancashire were exaggerated, but in the present stateof the cotton trade the psychological effect of the threatened German action might be very prejudicial.The Cabinet iWere also- reminded that theLancashire objections to the order did not come within the terms of reference of the Committee andwere a factor for consideration by Government itself.In the course of the discussion it transpired that of the seven Keports received by the Board ofTrade three had been adverse to the industries and four had been favourable to the making of orders and that the Board of Trade proposed to make orders in three of the four cases, the remaining casebeing the one under consideration.   It was pointedout that in these circumstances it could not berepresented that Part II of the Act was a deadletter.The Cabinet, by a majority, decided;-That having regard to the very specialcircumstances, of the case it was not desirable that the Board of Trade shouldmake the proposed Order relating tofabric gloves and glove materialsunder Part II of the Safeguarding Industries fjIT.Note.     Subsequently at the express request ofthe President of the Board of Trade the lord privy Seal authorised action to be suspendedon the above decision pending further considerationof the question by a fuller Meeting of the Cabineton a later Occasion.
USTNG (4)     The Cabinet had under consideration the followingTHEppBlAL      documents relative to phe question of the future housing of1 \ . JSEUMothe Imperial War Museunu(Memos by the First Commissioner of Works,CP.3848 (already circulated).Memo: by the Chancellor of the Exchequer,C, P.3877 (aIr eady c ironlated).Memo: by the Secretary of State for the Colonies,-CP. 3880 (already circulated).Memo? by the Minister of Health,C.P,3892 (alr eady ciroulated),Letter from the High Commissioner of T&apos;ew Zealand,CP.3920 (already circulated).The Cabinet were reminded that at present the imperial war Museum was very badly and expensively housed at the CrystalPalace.   The early termination of the lease made it necessaryto move the collections elsewhere and it was out of the question to provide a new building for them.     The Trustees of theMuseum had rediiced their indent for space by 60^ and it was proposed to accommodate the collection partly in the ScienceMuseum and partly in the Imperial Institute,   The imperial institute was subsidised by the British Government to theextent of  25^000 a year,,by ths Crown Colonies and Protectoratesto the extent of  21,000 a year, and by the Bominions to theextent of  8,000 a year.       It was only proposed to take 3$fit the space at the Institute for Museum purposes.    The oppositioof the Dominions had been headed by Hew Zealand and was consistenand regular.     On the other hand emphasis was &quot;-aid on thegreat difficulties of housing the Imperial war Museum at theimperial Institute.    It was impossible to force the proposalupon the Dominions against their will and there was great danger of the Dominions withdrawing altogether from theImperial Institute, in which case it would be very difficult&apos;to persuade the Crown Colonies to continue their contributions.If this unfortunate event was to happen the whole of the oon-templated savings would be lost.Reference was made to the fact that when the TTnJversitv\\of London evacuated the Imperial Institute there would beample space for expansion.     Moreover9/the tendency
the tendency was for the Dominions to provide theirown accommodation elsewhere. The presence of the imperial war Museum in the Imperial Institute would undoubtedlyattract the public and so indirectly benefit the Dominionsand the Grown Colonies.^fter some further discussion the Cabinet agreed-(i) To approve-in principle the proposals of theFirst Commissioner of Works for the future housingof the Imperial War Museum, provided that it was found possible to secure the acquiescence of theDominions in the user to be made of the buildings of the Imperial Institute.(ii)        So authorise the Secretary of Stateforthe Colonies to approach the Dominions with theproposal that His Majesty1s Government wouldbe prepared to pay a rent of  1500 per annum for the accommodation to be provided inthe Imperial Institute and to make a further3,Sooju^A^^.   contributionvCtowards the funds of the Institute;the Dominions to be notified of the advantageswhfcch would accrue to them from the presenceof the Imperial War Museum in the InstituteBuiId ings.-6-
1,051? CTiUMBR AND THB MALTBSBLOCAL FOROB*5o   The Cabinet had under eon-si derati on a Memorandum by theSecretary of State for the Colonies(CP. 3906) relative to themaintenance of the Maltese Localiforce.    The Cabinet were informedthat the Secretary of State forWar had now agreed to provide asum of J-25,000 in the war OfficeEstimates for the current financialyear for this service.The Cabinet took note of and approved this arrangement.
(. UILDIiJG TRADE       (6) The Cabinet had under consideration a memorandum and EX-SERVICEggXJ. fry the Minister of Labour (CP. 3814) on the subjectof the schemes for training ex-service men in thebuilding trade.The Cabinet were reminded of the reasons for thefailure of the fit ex-service men&apos;s scheme and of thedesirability of psrsuading the employers and workmento facilitate the schemes for training disabled ex-service men, which schemes were at present beingjeopardised by the fit men&quot;s scheme.Emphasis was laid on the desirability of obtainingsome definite assurance from the employers and trade&quot; unions concerned that they would assist the disabledmen&apos;s scheme in the event of the fit men&apos;s schemebeing abandoned.The Cabinet agreed -(1) That the scheme for the training andemployment of fit ex-service men in thebuilding trade should be abandoned.(2) That the Minister of Labour should make use of the government readiness to abandon the scheme in order to secure the maximum possible advantages for the disabled, ex-. service men.vVhltehal^te^^gardens,, a.-w.Apria?*&amp;a*ks*a&amp;g2
z(7) She Cabinet took note of the following:-(i)      Committee of Home Affairs 108, held onMarch 21st, 1922 at 4-15 p.m.(1) OXFORD AND ST. ALBANS WINE PRIVILEGES Bill.(2) NATIONAL HEALTH INSURANCE Bill.(3) audit T (  LOCAL AUTHORITIES) Bill.(4) VALUATION AND RATING REFORM.(5) LEAKAGE OP SECRET INFORMATION.(Appendix I)(ii)     Committee of Home Affairs 109, held onMarch 30th, 1922 at 4-15 p.m.(1) SUPPLY AND TRANSPORT ORGANISATION.(2) SALMON AND FRESHWATER FISHERIES BILL.(3) CANALS (CONTINUANCE OP CHARGING POWERS 1 BILL.(4) CHILDREN OP UNMARRIED PARENTS Bill.) POST OFFICE (PNEUMATIC TUBES ACQUISITION) Bill.) CHAIRMAN OF FISHERY BOARD FOR SCOTLAND.(Appendix 11^(iii)      Committee of Home Affairs 110, held onApril 4th, 1922 at 4-15 p.m.(1) CHILDREN OF UNMARRIED PARENTS BILL.(2j WOOLWICH ARSENAL. SHORT TIM.(3) ALLOTMENTS BILL.(4) EMPIRE SETTLEMENT BILL.(5) AGEICULTURE HOLDINGS BILL.(6) PREVENTION OF FRAUD (GOVERNMENT CONTRACTS) BILL.(7) Oil IN NAVIGABLE WATERS Bill.( 8) UNIVERSITIES (SCOTLAND) BIII,  19 2 2.(Appendix III)2, Whitehall Gardens,11th, April 1922.S.W.,
[This Document is the Property of His-Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   March 1922.SECRET.H.A.C. 108th Conclusions. (Iq,CABINET.COMMITTEE   OF   HOME   AFFAIRS.   108.Conclusions of a Meeting of the above Committee, held in the Ministers&apos; conference room, House of Commons, S.W., on Tuesday, March 21, 1922, at 4*15 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, M.P., President of the Board of Education(in the Chair).The Right Hon. E. Shobtt, K.C., M.P., J The Right Hon. Sir Alfred Mond, Bart.M.P., Minister of Health.Secretary of State for Home AffairsThe Right Hon. R. Munro, K.C., M.P.Secretary for Scotland.Mr. E. Hixton Young, D.S.O., M.P., Financial Secretary, Treasury.Mr. Leslie Scott, K.C., M.P., Solicitor-General.The following were also present :Sir Alfred Watson,  K.C.B.,  Govern-ment Actuary (for Conclusion 2).Sir C. A. Montague Barlow, K.B.E.,LL.D., M.P., Parliamentary Secretary,Ministry of Labour.Sir A. V. Symonds, K.C.B., second secretary, Ministry of Health (for Con-clusions 2 and 3).Mr. W. M. Graham-Harkison, C.B., Second Parliamentary CounselSir Walter Klnnear, K.B.E., controller of Health Insurance (for Conclusion 2).Mr. Thomas Jones, Principal Assistant Secretary, Cabinet.Mr. Pembroke Wicks, Secretary to the Committee.[8105]
Oxford and 1. The Committee had before them a Memorandum by the st Albans Wine Financial Secretary to the Treasury (CP. 38-20) covering the draft of privileges Bill. ft Bm tQ aboliyh certain rights and privileges of the City of oxford and of the City of St. Albans in connection with the sale of wine andthe granting of licences therefor. It appeared that the privilegesenjoyed by these two cities precluded the levy of ordinary licenceduties. Both the Corporations had agreed to the surrender of theseprivileges and satisfactory terms of compensation had been arranged.The abolition of the privileges and application of the ordinary lawwould result in an increased revenue to the State.The Committee agreed To approve the Oxford and St. Albans Wine Privileges(Abolition) Bill and, subject to the consent of the Whips,to authorise its introduction in the House of Commons.National Health 2. The Committee had under consideration a Memorandum by insurance Bill. fche Minister of Health  (CP. 3838) covering a National HealthInsurance Bill. The Bill had been prepared as a result of the endorsement by a Cabinet Committee of the  recommendation of the geddes Committee that the burden of National Health Insurancefalling on the State should be reduced by increasing the total contribu-tions from employers and employed by ^-d. per week in each case(CP. 366(5, section 18).The Minister of Health in his Memorandum stated that, as aresult of a conference with the Consultative Council of approved societies, it had been agreed that any increase at present in the ratesof contribution would be seriously opposed. In view, however, ofthe need for economy, the Council had proposed a scheme whichwould give substantial relief to the Exchequer without imposingany additional contributions at the present time. The amounts in question are : (a.) 1,700,OOOL per annum, special grants towards the cost of medical benefit in excess of the statutory proportion oftwo-ninths;(b.) Part of the cost of the administration of medical benefit,amounting to 100,000Z. per annum ;(c.) The annual grant to the Women&apos;s Equalisation Fund,amounting in the present year to 350,000Z.The Societies undertook to bear the whole of the cost of medical benefit, now met out of special Exchequer grants, as from the1st April, 1922, to December 1923, when the present contract withthe medical profession expires. The Societies further agreed to theproposal to abolish permanently the present annual grant to theWomen&apos;s Equalisation Fund.Attention was drawn by the Minister of Health in his Memo-randum to clause 1 (2) of the draft Bill, which provides that theState grant of two-ninths, of which the Societies would be temporarilydeprived during the twenty-one months to December 1923, shall be credited to each Society with the accrued interest after the date ofits next valuation. The draft Bill does not apply to Ireland, andthere are certain minor modifications to make it applicable to Scotlandand Wales.The Minister of Health informed the Committee that the scheme had the support of the Approved Societies, the Insurance Companies,and the Trade Unions, and that they doubtless hoped it would bepossible to reduce the remuneration of the doctors after December1923, and thus make a demand for additional contributions unneces-sary. With regard to the Women&apos;s Equalisation Fund, experience had shown that the incidence of women&apos;s sickness was less than had been
anticipated and the Insurance funds could bear the risk without state assistance.The Government Actuary stated that the Societies had carriedforwarded a substantial surplus at the last valuation, and were it not for the present widespiead and prolonged unemployment there wouldnot be the slightest danger in shouldering the proposed burden. Inany case he was prepared to advise that they could bear it.The Financial Secretary of the Treasury pointed out that thescheme proposed, while securing at present the savings contemplated by the Geddes Committee, did so by a method which was not beforethe Committee or the Cabinet and was a method which only gavetemporary relief to the Exchequer. To carry out the cabinets decision it would be necessary to provide that, on the termination ofthe scheme in December 1923, there would be no recourse to theTreasury for fi esh grants. There were two sources from which themoney could be obtained : a reduction in the payments to the doctorsor the raising of contributions. He asked that the Committee shouldembody in the Bill the principle that further grants from theTreasury were barred. This would, he contended, greatly strengthen the position of the Ministry of Health in dealing either with the doctors or the Approved Societies. It could be done by repealingSection (1) of the National Insurance Act 1913 (3 &amp; 4 George V,c. 37).   (See Appendix.)The Minister of Health explained that the section referred tohad been expressly introduced owing to an agitation on the part ofthe medical profession in order to enable the Government to ontri-bute more than its proportion of two-ninths, and it had the effect ofgiving a certain elasticity to the Minister in bargaining with thevarious interests involved. To take away the power now would beto stir up afresh the controversy with the doctors and to imperil thewhole scheme of medical service under the Act.The Secretary for Scotland suggested that it might be possibleto. review the situation at a later period before December 1923  but, inasmuch as the scheme had the support of the Ministry ofHealth, the Board of Health and Approved Societies, it ou^ht notto be prejudiced in the way proposed by the Treasury, with the- certainty of provoking great hostility in the House.The Financial Secretary of the Treasury proposed, as an alter-native method, that the Bill should provide for the suspension ofSection (l) of the Act of 1913 until Parliament otherwise determined.The Committee agreed (1.) That the scheme of the Minister of Health was the best possible for securing the economies desired by the geddes committee, having regard to the difficulty of increasingcontributions.(2.) That, inasmuch as the precise method of securing the savingsdiffered from that endorsed by the Cabinet, the foregoingConclusion should be reported to the Cabinet for their approval.Audit (Local 3.  The Committee  had before them a Memorandum by theAuthorities) Bill. Minister of Health (CP. 3839; covering the draft of a Bill relating tothe audit of the accounts of certain Local Authorities. The purposeof the Bill was to enable Rural District Councils, Boards of Guardiansand Overseers, on the ground of economy, to have a yearly instead ofa half-yearly audit. The Bill also provided a simple means of enabling Borough Councils to have their books audited by Govern-ment auditors instead of auditors appointed locally for the purpose,should they so desire. Borough Councils were at present only ableto obtain Government audit where their special Act of Parliamentpermitted it.
Valuation and rating Reform.Leakage of secret information.The Committee agreed To approve the Audit (Local Authorities) Bill, and to authorisethe Minister of Health to arrange for its introduction inParliament.4. With reference to H.A.C. 107, Conclusion 1, the Chairmanstated that he had seen the Lord Privy Seal on the subject of theproposed Bill to give effect, to the recommendations of the Committeeon Valuation and Bating reform. The Lord Privy Seal was ofopinion that, having regard to the congestion of business, it wouldbe quite impossible to get such a Bill &quot;through Parliament in thecurrent session, and was, therefore, unwilling to burden the Govern-ment Draftsmen with the preparation of so complicated a measure.The Minister of Health stated that, on the other hand, he had discussed the matter with the Minister of Agriculture. He under-stood that negotiations were in progress with the Treasury and thatthe Chancellor of the Exchequer was anxious, by means of a newValuation Bill, to come to the assistance of agriculture. Thataspect, he imagined, had not been presented to the Lord Privy Seal,,and on that ground the matter would require further consideration.After some discussion the Committee agreed That it was impossible for them to form an opinion on thematter until the Chancellor of the Exchequers new proposals were before them.5. The Chairman stated that his attention had been drawn bythe Secretary to a reference in the press to a recent discussion beforethe Home Affairs Committee of a Bill relating to Motor Legislation,He had drawn the attention of the Department concerned to thematter, and on investigation it was discovered that the information had been given by an official to the press, who had not realised thatin doing so he was disclosing information of a confidential character.Steps would be taken to prevent such leakage in future.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,March 22, 1922.APPENDIX.National Insurance Act, 1913.(3 &amp; 4 Geo. V, cap. 37.)Provision of Additional Money by Parliament (1 &amp; 2 Geo. V, cap. 55).1. (1.) In addition to the moneys which under Part I of the National InsuranceAct, 1911 (in this Act referred to as the &quot; principal Act&quot;), are required to becontributed out of moneys provided by Parliament towards defraying the cost of anyof the benefits conferred by Part I of that Act or the expenses of administration ofany of those benefits or otherwise for the purposes of that Act, there shall be contributedout of moneys provided by Parliament towards such costs, expenses and purposes,such additional sums as Parliament may from time to time determine, and the provisionsof the principal Act as to the manner in which the cost of benefits and the expenses ofadministration are to be defrayed shall be construed as applying only to the balanceof such cost and expenses after such additional sums have been applied for the purposes for which they have been provided.(2.) Any additional sums so contributed for the purpose of medical benefit shall beauplicable towards the payment of medical attendance and treatment of members ofsocieties who are not insured jDersons mentioned in paragraph (e) of sub-section (2) ofsection 15 of the principal Act as amended by this Act (a) in like manner and to the like extent as if such medical attendance and treatment were medical benefit.o
[This Document:&apos;.ur&apos;i^&apos;e&quot;Property 6i&quot;His&quot;Britannic&apos; Majestys Government, jPrinted for the Cabinet.   April 1922.SECRET.(H.A.C. 109th Conclusions.)CABINET.COMMITTEE  OF  HOME  AFFAIRS,   109.Conclusions of a Meeting of the above Committee held in the Ministers&apos; Conference Room,House of Commons, S.W., on Thursday, March 30, 1922, at 4-15 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, M.P., President of the Board of Education(in the Cha,ir).The Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir A. Mond, Bart., M.P.,-Minister of Health.The Right Hon. R. Munbo, K.C., M.P.,Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir E. Pollock, K.B.E.,K.C., M.P., Attorney-General.Mr. Leslie Scott, K.C., M.P., Solicitor-General.The   Right   Hon.    S. Baldwin,  M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir A. Griffith-Boscawen, M.P., Minister of Agri-culture and Fisheries.The Right Hon. the Earl of crawford and Balcarres, K.T., First Corn-missioner, His Majesty&apos;s Office ofWorks.Mr. Hilton Young, D.S.O., M.P., Finan-cial Secretary, Treasury.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. the Earl of Ancaster,Parliamentary Secretary and deputy minister of Fisheries. (For Conclu-sion 2.)Mr. L. S. Amery, M.P., Parliamentary andFinancial Secretary, Admiralty [ChiefCivil Commissioner]. (For Conclusion 1.)Mr. H. J. Wilson, C.B., C.B.E., Secretary,Ministry of Labour.Mr. C. F. Roundell, C.B.E., supply department [Ministry of Health]. (for conclusion 1.)Mr. H. G. Maurice, C.B., Ministry of Agri-culture.   (For Conclusion 2.)Mr. L. F. C. Maclean, Food Department,Board of Trade.   (For Conclusion 1.)The Right Hon. H. Pike Pease, M.P.,Assistant Postmaster - General. (for conclusion 5.)Mr. A. Neal, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Ministry of Transport. (For Con-clusions 1 and 3.)Lieutenant-Colonel  G. C.   Grazebrook,.C.M.G., D.S.O., War Office.   (For Con-clusion 1.)The Hon. Hugh Godley, Third Parlia-mentary Counsel.Major M. Browne, War Office. (For Con-clusion 1.)Mr. T. E. Pryce-Tannatt, Ministry ofAgriculture.   (For Conclusion 2.)Mr. Pembroke Wicks, Secreta,ry to the Committee.
1. With reference to H.A.G. 101, the Committee had beforethem a Report of the Executive Sub-Committee of the Supply andTransport Committee (CP. 3800), containing a scheme which couldbe carried out in the event of an emergency arising, and recom-mending the nucleus organisation to be retained at an estimated costof 1,750/. (first year 1,900/.). It was recommended that the trades and local authorities should be responsible for the maintenance ofall local services, and that the Government should only assist in thecase of certain special services indicated in the Report, and then only when the trade or local authorities were unable to deal with thesituation.It was proposed that the Supply and Transport Sub-Committeeshould continue in existence, and that the Chairman should be nominated from time to time by the Cabinet Minister in charge ofthe emergency organisation (at present the Home Secretary), that itshould meet at least every six months to review the organisation,and that the general lines of the organisation should continue, viz.,a series of Sub-Committees responsible for the various sections ofthe scheme. It was recommended that any expenditure on accountof the nucleus organisation should be borne on the votes of theDepartments concerned, and that any expenses which would notnaturally fall on the vote of an individual Department should becharged to the Home Office vote.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Transportstated that the President of the Board of Trade had appointed anofficial to see that the nucleus organisation was kept constantlyunder review. The scheme would be based on the Civil Com-missioners.The Chief Officer of the Civil Commissioners had been, andwould continue to be, a General Inspector of the Ministry ofHealth. Some danger of publicity could not be avoided owing tothe necessity of keeping in touch with the Chairmen of the LocalVolunteer Organisations. The Executive Sub-Committee of theSupply and Transport Committee could no longer retain its name ifthe parent Committee had ceased to exist. Was it intended to keeptil at alive ?The Ghairjnan referred to Decision (7) of H.A.C. 101, fromwhich it was plain that wthe Supply and Transport Committeeremained in existence and that the Home Secretary was responsiblefor calling it together pending further consideration of. the matter.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Transport,continuing, stated that it was proposed that a responsible officers should be selected from each of the following Departments to dealwith emergency matters : Home Office.Ministry of Transport.Supply Department   [Department   of  Chief civil commissioner].Treasury.Mines Department.Ministry of Health.Admiralty.War Office.Air Ministry.Petroleum Department.Office of Works.Board of Trade (Food Department).There had been some danger of mistakes in the past owing tothe fact that the same persons had not always attended theSub-Committee. It w^as essential that those present at the meetingsof the Sub-Committee should be the officials actually responsible.
92o.Salmon and 2. With reference to H.A.C. 92, Conclusion (4), the CommitteeFisheries&apos; Pill kaC^ before them a Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and&quot; &quot;      &apos; Fisheries covering a draft of a Bill to Consolidate and Amend the enactments relating to Salmon and Freshwater Fisheries in Englandand Wales (C.P.-3802). The Bill had been discussed with repre-sentatives of Angling Associations, and was expected to be substantially an agreed measure. It had been introduced in thepreceding session, as directed by the Home Affairs Committee, forthe purpose of inviting public discussion, and had since been amended as thought desirable. Under Clause 54 it was proposedto give to Fishery Boards, for the protection of fisheries in their districts, the same powers as a sanitary authority to instituteproceedings under the Rivers Pollution Prevention Acts. Atpresent proceedings might only be instituted on the grounds ofpublic health, and not on the grounds of damage to fish. It was stated that the provisions for the prevention of pollution would apply to pollution by tar from roads which had been laid by localauthorities.Attention was drawn to the very drastic provisions containedin &quot;Clause 1 of the Bill, relating to penalties for throwing stones atfish and using lights at night for the purpose of facilitating capture of fish, particularly having regard to Sub-Clause 1 (2), under whicha person would be presumed to be guilty of an offence against theAct unless he could prove that the acts alleged against him were done for the purpose of the preservation or development of a privatefishery. It was suggested that the effect of the Clause might be tosecure the conviction of innocent persons who had not been guilty of poaching or any real offence.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries stated that it was proposed to introduce the Bill in the House of Lords, and that fiewould have no objection to&apos;considerable ameuclment in the courseof debate.The Home Affairs Committee agreed 1. To approve the draft Bill and to authorise its introduction in the House of Lords.2. To request the Minister of Agriculture to re-examine Clause 1of the Bill in the light of the above discussion.Canals 3 With reference to H.A.C. 99, Conclusion (1), the Committee(Continuance of        had   under  consideration   a   Memorandum   by  the   Minister   ofCharging Powers)     Transport iCP. 3238), and a Memorandum by the parliamentary secretary to the Ministry of Transport (CP. 3835), covering theThe Secretary for Scotland drew attention to the special arrangements which had been made with his approval for a separateorganisation for Scotland.Major Grazebrook, on behalf of the War Office, stated that theArmy Council desired to draw the attention of the Home AffairsCommittee to the fact that, owing to the recent reductions, therewould not be enough military transport to move troops in the eventof the railways failing. He handed a Memorandum to the Secretaryof the Committee.The Home Affairs Committee agreed (I.) To approve the scheme submitted by the Executive Sub-Committeo of the Supply and Transport Committee.(2.) To request the Secretary to draw the attentiou of theExecutive Sub-Committee to the representations madeby the Army Council on the question of military transport.
draft of a Bill for &quot;the Continuance of Charging Powers in respectof Canal Undertakings of which possession was taken by theMinistry of Transport under &quot;The Ministry of Transport Act,1919.&quot; It was proposed in the Bill that the increased chargingpowers should be continued until February 1924.The Committee agreed : &quot; To approve the draft Bill and to authorise the parliamentary secretary to the Ministry of Transport to arrange for itsits introduction in Parliament, subject to the consent, ofthe Government Whips.&quot;4. With reference to II. A.C. 103, Conclusion (3), the Committeehad under consideration a Memorandum by the Home Secretary(CP. 3846), covering draft clauses of a Bill which had beenprepared in aceoi-dance with the directions of the Committee,providing for legitimation by subsequent marriage.Alternative draft clauses were submitted, it being assumedunder one that titles and dignities would not be affected bylegitimation, and under the other that they would be affected.The Private Member&apos;s Bill introduced in the House of commons during the preceding session by Captain Bo wye r had been followedon two points : (1.) The Bill was not restricted to persons who were legallycapable of marrying at the time when the child wasborn, therein differing from the law of Scotland ;(2.) Legitimation would only relate to marriages taking place after the change of law, although children born beforethe passing of the Bill would be legitimated if their parents married after the Bill became law.There were also various difficult technical questions arising onthe Bill relating to settled property and other legal matters.The Secretary for Scotland pointed, out that under Scottish lawit was not necessary for parents to have continued free to marry,provided they had been legally capable of marriage at the time ofthe conception and birth of the child.The Attorney-General drew attention to the fact that the Bill asat present drawn applied to the child of a married man born inadultery.The Committee were divided on the question whether such aproposition could be entertained. It w^as held, on the one hand,that public opinion would not tolerate such a proposal. It was felt,on the other hand, that the interests of the child were the only realconsideration, and that on that ground the proposal should, stand.The Attorney-General asked the Committee to consider whetherit was necessary to have the Bill at all. In the preceding SessionCaptain BowyeFs Bill had received only cursory consideration in committee in the House of Commons, and he questioned whether there was any real demand for it. Were it made a government measure there would no doubt be strong protests.The Chairman stated that before the Committee could come toa decision they must know to what extent the Government werepledged by the Home Secretary^ speech in the House of commons during the debate on Captain BowyeFs Bill.The question was raised whether the Cabinet had given any direction in regard to this Bill.&quot;With reference to Cabinet 88 (21), Conclusion (7), the secretary reported that the Cabinet had requested the Home Affairs Committee
to consider and advise upon certain Private Members&apos; Bills whichwere being pressed hy the advocates of the Women&apos;s Movement inthe House of Commons, viz., the Guardianship of Infants Bill andthe Criminal Law Amendment Bill. On enq uiry at the Home Officehe had been informed that the Children of Unmarried ParentsBill should be included among the measures thus referred to theCommittee.Attention was drawn to the great opposition that would bereceived in the House of Lords if it were attempted to makelegitimation effective for the purpose of succession to titles anddignities, and the suggestion was made that for that purpose legiti-mated children should be deemed the youngest.It appeared that those members of the Committee who weresupporting the Bill, sooner than lose the whole Bill, would beprepared to waive the question of succession to titles, and toassimilate the law to Scottish law, so that legitimation would only beeffected if parents had been free to marry at the time of the concept-tion and birth of the child.The First Commissioner of Works stated that unless theGovernment had been actually pledged by the Home Secretary&apos;sstatement he could not support the Bill.The Attorney-General stated that, while he would not oppose onthe broad question of legitimising children, he felt strongly thatexceedingly complicated legal questions would arise, and was veryloath to give his support for that reason.The Solicitor-General, while admitting the legal difficulties, was prepared to support the Bill on the ground that the children mustbe the first consideration, but thought that the best plan tacticallywas to adopt Scottish law.The Committee agreed To adjourn the consideration of the question to the followingmeeting in order that in the interval it might be determined to what extent the Home Secretary had pledged theGovernment.Post Office 5^ The Committee had under consideration a Memorandum by(Pneumatic Tubes the pQStmaster-General (CP. 3823) covering a draft of a Bill to. acquisition) )i . confirm an agreement between the Pneumatic Despatch company and the Postmaster-General for the acquisition by the latter of adisused Underground Tube running from the General Post Office toa point near the North-Western District Office. Without legislation it was doubtful whether the Pneumatic Despatch Company, under their special Act of Parliament, had power to sell or the Postmaster-General power to buy. The Company had accepted an offer of 7,500. The saving to the Exchequer which would result fromlajdng telephone cables in this Tube would be  40,000.The Committee agreed To approve the draft Bill and to authorise the Postmaster-General to arrange for its introduction in the House ofCommons sxibject to the consent of the GovernmentWhips.
Chairman of 6. The Committee had under consideration a Memorandum byScotland the Secretai7 for Scotland (CP. 3840) to make provision with1 respect to the tenure of office by the Chairman of the Fishery  (f^Board for Scotland, in which it was proposed to. make the office of chairman of the Fishery Board an ordinary Civil Service post,instead of one to which the holder is appointed for five years.The Committee agreed To approve the draft Bill and to authorise the Secretary forScotland to arrange for its introduction in Parliament.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,March 30, 1922.o
[This Document is tHe &quot;Frbperly&apos; of&quot;Hisv,3iit ffiliiC&apos;-&apos;Majesty&apos;s G government.]Printed for the Cabinet.   April l&apos;J-2.SECRET.H.A.C. 110th Conclusions.CABINET.nAifji-TTTiwu1    op    &quot;[TOM!?    a i?!? a 7 do     tir\Conclusions of a Meeting of the above Committee, held in the Ministers&apos; ConferenceBoom, House of Coimnons, S.W., on Tuesday, April -1, 1922, at 4T5 p.m.Present :The Right Hon. H. A. L. Fisher, M.P., President of the Board of Education(in the Chair).The Right Hon. E. Shortt, K.C., M.P.,Secretary of State for Home Affairs.The Right Hon. Sir Alfred Mond, Bart.,M.P., Minister of Health.The Right Hon. R. Munro, K.C., M.P.,Secretary for Scotland.The Right Hon. S. Baldwin, M.P., Pre-sident of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir Griffith-Boscawen.M.P., MinisterFisheries.ofAgricultureandThe Right Hon. F. G. Kellaway, M.P.,Postmaster-General.Sir Leslie Scott, K.C., M.P., Solicitor-General.The following were also presentThe Right Hon. the Earl of Ancaster,Parliamentary Secretary and deputy minister of Fisheries. (For conclusions and 5.)Lieutenant-Colonel Sir R. A. Sanders,Bart., M.P., Under-Secretary of State,War Office.   (For Conclusion 6.)Sir Francis Floud, K.C.B., permanent secretary, Ministry of Agriculture andFisheries.   (For Conclusions 3 and 5.)Mr. H. J. Wilson, C.B., C.B.E., Secretary,Ministry of Labour. . (For conclusions and 4.)elmMr. L. S. Amery, M.P., parliamentary and Financial Secretary, Admiralty(Civil   Commissioner).     (For   Conclu-\ sion^ 4.)Lieutenant-Colonel the Hon. G.F. Stanley,C.M.G., M.P., Financial Secretary, WarOffice.   (For Conclusion 2.)The Hon. Hugh Godley, Third Parlia-mentary Counsel.Mr. R. S. Metklejohn, C.B., DeputyController of Supply Services, Treasury.Mi\ A. Maxwell, Private Secretary, HomeOffice.   (For Conclusion 1.)T homas Jones, Principal Assistant Secretary.Mr. R. B. Howorth, Acting Secretary to the Committee.
Children of 1. With reference to H.A.C. 109, Conclusion 4, the CommitteeUnmarried Parents   further considered the question of a Bill to deal with legitimation by subsequent marriage, and had before them a memorandum by theHome Secretary (CP. 3846).The Home Secretary gave an account of the position taken upby the Government in the House of Commons in regard to proposalsfor a Bill, and in particular to the following question and answergiven on the 14th February :  &quot; Mr. N Chamberlain asked the Home Secretary whether he has considered the recommendations of the DepartmentalCommittee on Child Adoption, presided over by Sir AlfredHopkinson, K.C. ; and whether he proposes to introduce any legislation upon the subject in the course of the present session ?&quot; Mr. Shortt: I hope a Bill may be inti-produced to give effectto the Committee&apos;s recommendation as to the legitimation ofchildren by the subsequent marriage of their parents ; but thereappear to be very great difficulties in the way of carrying outthe proposal for the legalisation of adoption.&quot;In the course of the discussion it was stated that there was ademand on the part of women&apos;s organisations especially for this Bill,as it would remove a stigma which, in the opinion of many, restedunfairly on the children in question, and it was generally agreed tobe undesirable to leave a Bill which raised so many complicated legalissues to a private member ; on the other hand, in order to mitigateopposition the scope of any Bill for which the Government madeitself responsible should be restricted to the narrowest limits, andshould broadly aim at bringing the law of England into harmony with that of Scotland.The Committee agreed That a Bill should be drafted on the lines indicated above bythe Home Secretary, in consultation with the Law Officers,for consideration by the Committee.Woolwich Arsenal. 2. The Financial Secretary to the War Office informed the short Time. Home Affairs Committee that a demand had been made by the shop stewards at Woolwich Arsenal that short time should cease, andthat full time should be worked.   If this were done it would benecessary to discharge 1.500 men. who could be retained if thepresent short-time arrangements were continued.The Committee agreed That the existing short-time arrangements should remain inforce.Allotments Bill. 3. The Home Affairs Committee had under consideration aMemorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries (CP. 3910),covering the draft Allotments Bill.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, stated that this bill had been promised in the, King&apos;s^Speech,, and was based on the unanimous report of the Departmental Committee on Allotments,which had been appointed jointly by the Secretary for Scotland and himself. The Committee had comprised representatives of theLocal Authorities and of the allotment holders. Having regard tothe very great extension at present of the cultivation of allotmentsas compared with the pre-war state of affairs, it was most important that the existing powers respecting the acquisition of land, &amp;c,should be maintained,-and in some directions strengthened, if thepresent number of allotments was not to be seriously diminished.
The two main features of the Bill dealt with the easy acquisition,of land and security of tenure.   In particular, it was necessary toO provide that the allotment holder should not be deprived of his landduring the cropping season. On the other hand, he was to be compensated only in respect of crops on the ground and manure putinto the ground since the last crop, but he was to receive no com-pensation for labour applied since the last crop or for disturbance,under &quot; The Agricultural Act, 1920.&quot;With regard to the acquisition of land, the Committee were reminded that during the war much vacant land in urban areas hadbeen taken over under D.O.B.A. powers, and, in the absence offurther legislation, this land would be handed back to the owners on or before the 31st March, 1923. The Bill proposed to confer upon local Authorities the powers of entering upon vacant land, including any vacant land which has been taken by the Ministry under D.O.R. A.during the war, but the provision had been inserted to secure that an owner could resume possession on giving one month&apos;s notice if the land was reasonably required for any other purpose than agriculture. under clause 4 an allotment authority could continue for one year from august 1922 to make orders for the compulsory acquisition of landwithout the delay and expense of obtaining confirmation by theMinister. Clause 7 limited the obligation of borough and urbanauthorities to provide allotments to the provision of allotment gardensnot exceeding 20 poles ; while Clause 8 required allotment authoritiesin boroughs or urban districts to maintain, unless exempted by theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries, Allotment Committees, coin-prising a substantial portion of co-opted members representativeof allotment holders. Clause 10 provided&apos; that a local authority,owning its own trams or &quot;buses, could give facilities to allotment holders to get to their allotments, thus enabling cheaper land to beprovided ; and Clause II maintained the principle that the allotmentsundertaking of an authority&apos; is to be self-supporting, subject to certainparticularised exceptions. Clause 14 dealt with a special difficulty which had arisen in the New Forest, and the effect of the Clausewould be that, while the owners and the public would lose nothing which they at present enjoyed, no additional land would be devotedto the cultivation of allotments in the Forest.- The Secretary for Scotland stated that the proposals in the Billclosely followed the recommendations of Lord AncasteFs Committee.On behalf of Scotland, he wished to thank Lord Ancaster and theCommittee for the very valuable work which had been done. Hebad convinced the Leader of the House that it would be necessaryto have a separate Bill dealing with the Scottish aspect of theal lotments question.The  Minister of Health  drew   attention to certain  drafting alterations in Ciause 1 (b) of the Bill.The Committee agreed To approve the draft Allotments Bill subject to the drafting amendments&apos; necessary to meet the points raised by theMinister of Health, and to authorise the introduction of theBill in the House of Lords.4. The Committee had under consideration a Memorandum bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer (OP. 3919) on the subject of theEmpire Settlement proposals, and also copies of the draft empire settlement Bill (CP. 3922).The Parliamentary Secretary to the Admiralty informed theHome Affairs Committee thai the Cabinet had referred the questionof the provision to be made for Empire Settlement to a, CabinetCommittee presided over by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, whichCommit Use had fixed the maximum annual amount to be found byEmpire SettlementBill.
the Exchequer at  1,500,000 for the current financial year and 3,000,000 in subsequent years, with a definite time limit of fifteen years. As it was very desirable to introduce the Bill before Easter,he had obtained the leave of the Leader of the House to bring thequestion before the Home Affairs Committee instead of to theCabinet. The financial provisions in the Bill had been accepted bythe Treasury.The Committee agreed -To approve the Empire Settlement Bill (CP. 3922) and toauthorise its immediate introduction in the House ofCommons.Agricultural 5. The Home Affairs Committee had under consideration  aHoldings Bill. Memorandum   (CP.   3918)  by  the Minister of Agriculture andFisheries relative to the consolidation of the enactments relating to agricultural holdings in England and Wales and in Scotlandrespectively, and stating that a Bill for this purpose relating to scotland had already been introduced. As the Bill was purely aconsolidating measure and involved no alteration in the existing lawit was not proposed to circulate a draft of the Bill to the Committee.The Committee agreed To approve the introduction in the House of Lords of theproposed Agricultural Holdings Bill.Prevention ofFraud (government contracts) Bill.6. The Home Affairs Committee had under consideration aMemorandum by the Secretary of State for War (CP. 3791) cover-ing the draft of the Prevention of Fraud (Government Contracts)Bill.After some discussion had taken place as to the precise need forthis Bill the Committee agreed -(1.) To adjourn the further consideration of the Secretary ofState for Wars Memorandum until a future meeting.(2.) To request the Solicitor-General to discuss the scope andobject of the Bill with Mr. Guy Stephenson, an AssistantDirector of Public Prosecutions. Mr, Stephenson to beinvited to attend the Committee on the occasion whenthe subject was next under discussion.Oil in Navigable 7. The tlome Affairs Committee had under consideration aWaters Bill. Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade (CP. 3871)covering the draft Oil in Navigable Waters Bill.The President of the Board of Trade informed the Committeethat this Bill was designed to meet a groWintr evil and that it represented an agreement reached by all the interests concerned.Under Clause I it would in future be an offence to discharge oil orallow oil to escape into any waters to which the Act applied. he did not anticipate that there would be any opposition to the Bill.After the Home Secretary had raised certain points on Clause 7of the Bill, the Committee agreed (1.) To approve the Oil in Navigable Waters Bill subject tothe settlement of any points of detail on Clause 7 by theHome Secretary and the President of the Board of Tradein consultation.(2.) To authorise the President of the Board of Trade tointroduce the Biil after obtaining the concurrence of theGovernment Whips.
Universities 8. The Home Affairs Committee had under consideration a^Scotland Bill), Memorandum (CP. 3885) by the Secretary for Scotland covering the19-^2. draft of a Bill approved by the four Scottish Universities to conferpowers upon the University Courts with regard to age limitationsand superannuation in the case of principals and professors and withregard to the admission of Lecturers and Readers to the SenatusAcademicus, and also to provide for the admission ex officio ofLecturers and Readers to the General Councils of the Universities.The Committee were informed that the Bill would be non-contentious and would involve no charge on public funds.The Committee agreed To approve the draft Universities (Scotland) Bill, 1922, and toauthorise the Secretary for Scotland to arrange with theGovernment Whips for its introduction.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,April 5, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
