<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/30/0 images: 196-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
0 A bin E T 55 (22&apos;C01ICLXJGI0HS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Downing Street, S.W., on Friday, 2nd June,1922, at 8.15 p,i.T3   O   t?   O   Vi*   ?,T   m * ^.ir it &amp;   tj       ii   i * *-TIE PRBiE MINISTER    (in the Chair) *Ihe Eight Hon. A. Cliamberlain, The Right lion. Viscount BirkenheadM.F.* Lord Privy Seal. Lord Chancellor.the Eight Hon. Sir Robert The Right Hon. W.S. Churchill,Home, G.B.E.,H.c,M.P., H.P., Secretary off State for theChancellor of the Exchequer.        Colonies *The Right Hon. Sir L* The Right Hon. Sir Alfred mond,Hor thing t on : veins, Bt.,M.P,, -     Bart., 1.3. P., Minister, of Health.Secretary of State for War.The Eight Hon. Sir Hamar Greenwood,Bart.,K.C.,mm P., Chief Secretaryfor Ireland.-T.;iE P0h:,0V/IKG AniaVEB TOViARiB Tig CLOSE. OF THE. Uei-ITXHG. -The Right hon .S. Baldwin, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Viscount Peel,- , &apos;     G.B.E., Secretary of State forIndia,The Right Hon. Sir A. Griffithj^oscaT,&apos;en, M.P., Minister ofAgriculture and Fisheries.TIE - FOLIOIVIEG&apos;VvSRS ALSO PRESDliTThe Right Hon. Viscount FitsAlan Sir Edward Grigg. K.G.V.O.,of forwent, G.C.V.O. ,D.S.O,, C.M.G.,lord Lieutenant of Ireland.Mr. Lionel Curtis.It. Col. Sir M.P.A. Hankey, G.C.B...................... Secretary.Thomas Jones................... Principal Assistant Secretary^
4 O Q10 i)fDjgg With reference to Ohinet 32(22) Wln0 1, the cabinet had before them the reply of the Irish Ministers to thejtution.      Prime Minister&apos;s letter dated 1st June, 1922. (C.P.4014)The Prime Minister read the reply signed by Mr, ArthurGriffith in which answers were given to the six specificquestions addressed to the Irish Delegation (Appendix).General satisfaction   was expressed with the terms ofthe reply.   While it was recognised that on certain important issues, especially the position of the Crown inIreland and the appeal to the Privy Council, furtherelucidation would be necessary, it was agreed that therewas nothing in the letter to warrant breaking off thenegotiations at the present stage.The Prime Minister Informed the Cabinet that Mr.Griffith, who was leaving for Dublin that evening, proposedto return to London on Monday night to discus the Constitute-ion, if the Cabinet so desired.&apos;The Cabinet agreed.-1.   That a letter from the Prime Minister in thefollowing terms should be sent immediately to Mr,Griffith:&quot;I have this moment received your letter ,&quot;and shall be prepared to resume conversations&quot;with you on Tuesday on the basis therein set&quot;out&quot;.2.   That in communicating this letter to Mr.Griffithon his departure from Buston he should be toldpersonally and privately that while there were oneor two Important outstanding difficulties, the Irish,reply had, on the whole, created a favourableimpression on the Cabinet.,Hote.-The Secretary of State for India, the President J&amp;ithe Board of Trade and the Minister for Agriculture arrivedat the close of the meeting and read the Irish reply.Whitehall Gardens,London S.W.1.2nd June, 1922.
II.    LETTER FROM 131. ARTHUR GRIFFITHTO THE PRIMB MINISTER.London.2nd June, 1982.Dear Mr. Lloyd George,I have received your letter of yesterday&apos;s datewritten on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, and Ihave carefully considered it in conference with thoseof my colleagues who are now in London.I take your letter as stating the essentials of the issues raised and in that sense I now reply to it pendingdiscussion of the detailed memorandum and the suggestedamendments of the draft Constitution which we have sub-mi t ted to the British Government0Before taking up the specific questions you have put, I think that, in view of the atmosphere which seems to have gathered from the course of events, thereis one thing I should make perfectly clear.    The draft constitution which we have submitted was prepared whollyby a Committee of persons appointed for the purpose bythe provisional Government.   Every member of that committee was an actual supporter of the Treaty, - someof them had written publicly in advocacy of the Treatysettlement.    The only instructions which the provisionalGovernment gave to the /
constitutional Committee were printed copies of the Treaty anda request to prepare a draft Constitution for Ireland withinthe Treaty and to have such drafi ready before the end ofFebruary.     A draft, in all substantial particulars in the formnow presented, was completed and sont to the provisional Covern-ment in the first weals: of March.     The Provisional Governmenthad not in the meantime held any communication with the Committee.I mention this to show that the matters which His Majesty1 sGovernment have raised on the araf t are not matters which are inany way connected with recent political events and that the draftrepresents the work of an independefit Committee acting upon theirandown independent interpretation of the Treaty/approaching it withminds biaased in fits favour.I will now take your six questions seriatim and answer themto the best of my ability.Your first question is - &quot;is it intended by the Irish repre-sentatives that the Irish Free State shall be within the Empireon the basis of common oitizensMp or merely associated with it?&quot;My answer Is that it is intended that the Irish Free\ state shall be, not merely associated with, but a member of and withinthe Community of Nations known as the British Empire and;on thebasis of common oitizenship as explicitly provided by the Treaty.,Your second question - &quot;Is the position of the Crowi\ to bethe same in Ireland as it is in Canada * Australia, Hew 2ea\and,and South Africa?&quot; - raises the issue upon which some difference
of -View has.appeared..     This difference is a difference of interpretation of the document between two parties bothequally desirous that the document shall be carried out inthe letter and the spirit according to its true in^orprot-a-tion as it stands without the alteration of any detaxl.Let me reduce the difference to which I refer to itsprecise dimensions, and I do so gladly because I believe the area of difference to be small and not. in any matterof vital intrinsic importance, whatever other importanceit may have.Let me therefore say that In all matters in which theCrown is constitutionally effective (and considerationshows these to be matters arising out of the relationship of the community of Nations), the position of the Crown isbeyond question to be the same in Ireland as It is inCanada, Australia, New Zealand and South Africa.     Thuscommon citizenship will express itself through the Crownin relation to Peace and War, Neutrality and Treaties.Again, the King&apos;s assent to Bills passed by the IrishLegislature is   involved In the right, that will inevitablyflow from such relationship, to reserve for the Kingrsassent in person an;f legislation affecting matters, notbeing matters of the internal government of the IrishFree State.     There is at this stage of history no questionbut that the King&apos;3 representative would bo bound to dis-distinguish such legislation v&amp;ien presented to him for theRoyal assent, and that he would.be bound to signify theKing&apos;s assent to Bills duly passed which are concernedwith purely Irish internal affairs.t
Your third question - &quot;Is the Treaty making po&quot;&apos;erof the Irish Free State to he the same as that of Canada?&quot; -is capable of a simple answer, namely, that it ise     We shouldbe glad to have it pointed out to us in what respect we aresupposed to have exceeded that position.     7e do not seek to do so*Your fourth question - &quot;Are the Courts of the IrishFree State to stand In the same relation to the King inCouncil (the Judicial Committee of the Privy Council) as dothe Courts of the Dominion of Canada?&quot; - raises a matterof no small delicacy in Ireland.I need not remind you that the question of continuing the carrying of appeals to this Tribunal is one that hasbeen raised and is being actively canvassed throughout theDominions.     Xt is now held by many that this particularappeal will be. abolished In the near future,-.      I may referyou on this matter, to numerous public utterances of leadingstatesmen .of the Dominions, men of the position of SirR. Borden, Mr. Hughes, General Smuts, and many others of similar calibre, and also to the most recent literatureon the matter, particularly the authoritative writings of professor Berriedale Keith^ Mr. Duncan Hall9 and others.In addition to the reasons urged by these statesmen and authorities, there are in Ireland particular reasons forthe objection widely entertained to the idea of takingappeals to the Judicial Committee.     One regrets to have torefer to Judges personally, but the Inclusion in the
&quot;body from which the personnel of the Judicial Committee -is drawn of persons who hare used for party political purposeshostile to the Irish people, the position to which theyhave been elevated for the administration of justice, has aroused keen indignation and antipathy to the Tribunal ofwhich they are members.    This is a matter of active publicinterest in Ireland, and we must ask what guarantees canbe given that the Impartiality of the Court in questioncan be sectxred0There is another aspect of this matter of particular-interest in Ireland.    It should be borne in mind that thegreat volume of Irish litigation is concerned with verysmall money interests *   The litigants are not as a bodypeople of large means able to 3tand expensive litigation?the loser In such an appeal may well be completely ruined.It is a rich man!s appeal which nay well be used to thedestruction of a man not well offoWe did not think that this appeal was a necessaryIncident&apos;of the Treaty positiono    I do not quite gatherfrom your letter- whether you believe this to be the caseor not and if so whether it is regarded as in any wayvital,, or in what form you may consider that it is to be insisted upon*Ycac fifta question - &quot;Is the oath set forth in theTreaty to be incorporated - in the Constitution as the oathrequired of members of the Free State Parliament?&quot; - doesnot present any difficulty.    If your Government is not satisfied that the oath Is sufficiently incorporated inthe Constitution by the fact that the-Constitution willes^a^t the Treaty C&apos;S law,the oath will be expressly setforth in the Constitution as the oath required of the/members
of the Parliament *You are entitled to an affirmative answer to your sixth question - &quot;Will all members of the IrishProvisional Government he required to sign the de-claration under Article 17 of the Treaty!&quot;In so far as it can be shown that the draft constitution is in conflict with the Treaty, we areprepared to insert such amendments as.will reconcileits terms with those of the Treaty.I am,Yours sincerely^(Sgd) ARTHUR GRIFFITH,The Ki:?ht- Hon,-D.Llo.vd George 0,,&apos;!.,  M.P.,i 0, D o to x n 3 S t v e e t,S .7.1.


</content>
</cab>
