<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 8-13</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENT 7The circulation  of this paper has been  strictly limited.A It is issued for the personal use of.TOP SECRET Copy No. O f0.P.(1).9) kl25TH FEBRUARY, 19^9CABINETTHE PETROL ration memorandum by the Minister of Fuel and PowerMotorists are beginning to press for a substantial increase in the standard petrol ration for the next period (which runs from 1st June to 30th November)&apos;.    I am also informed thatan organised campaign in support of this is shortly to be launched by the interests concerned.2. It will be much easier to counter the campaign ifI can announce now the Government&apos;s decision on the ration -whatever that decision may be.    For, if no announcement ismade, people think that pressure can move the Government andare much more likely to join in the agitation.    If, on theother hand,- they know we have made up our minds there will bea tendency to accept the decision.3* I assume that we can at least maintain the present standard ration and that the question really is whether wecan, and should, increase it, and, if so, by how much.U.% There are powerful arguments in favour of saneincrease:-(a) The standard ration is at present only one-third ofthe 1947 basic ration, while most of the other cutsimposed at that time e.g. newsprint, films, foreigntravel, etc., have by now been restored.(b) Total petrol consumption by private cars is stillonly about half of pre-war.(c) It is important that wq should retain thegood will of the motoring organisations.    Thoughstill friendly they have always had a grievancebecause over half -the estimated savings in thefirst year from suppressing the black market werenot given back to the private motorist.    If no concession is mode,  relations are likely tobecome strained and the administration of petrol rationing will%g made very much more difficult.(d) The supply position is easier.   Stocks are now.    270,000 tons more than a year ago.(e) The home tourist industry would benefit.

(f) There are advantages about making a concessionthis summer rather than deferring it.     a concession in the autumn would not approximately^eal    .to the many motorists who lay up theircars for the winter.(g) In many other O.E.E.C. countries which/we have tosupply with petrol there is no rationing at all or, where there is* the allowances are biggerthan ours.   In comparison, our austere standardshere are increasingly difficult to defend.5. Against the proposal for axi increase must be, however,placed two important considerations:-(a) While our balance of payments is much healthier than was expected, we still face a most difficult dollarproblem and, for the present, we cannot increasepetrol consumption v/ithout spending more dollars.(b) Although civilian stocks of motor spirit are higher,Service stocks are far below (about 800,000 tons)the level considered to be desirable by the Chiefs   .of Staff and we may be approaching the United StatesGovernment for assistance in this very shortly.&apos;6. In all the circumstances, much as I should like todo so, I do not feel able to recommend a permanent increasein the standard ration.7. &apos;   I propose instead that we should give a &quot;holidaybonus&apos;1&apos; this, year by doubling the value of the standard rate inthe case of the June, July and August, coupons.    The coupons forthese three, months would then be worth 180 instead of 90 milesa month;    and the -total value of the standard ration book forthe six months June - November would be increased from 5^0 miles to 810 miles.   At this figure it would still be only halfthe value of the basic ration for six months in 19^7*   Thecoupons, will, of course, be valid for five months after the months for which they are.issued;    in&apos; addition I am arranging for the standard ration books to be available as early as possiblein May and I propose to make the coupons valid from the dateof issue, so that those who wish to use their ration for anearly holiday may do so.8. The cost of this bonus would be 99*000 tons (comparedwith a total annual petrol consumption of 4  million tons) and about  900,000 in dollars.9, I recommend that the proposal set out inparagraph 7 be adopted, as giving considerable advantages for a very small cost.H.G.Ministry of Fuel and Power, S.W.I.,23th February, 19^-9.




</content>
</cab>
