<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 14-19</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT&apos; IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)secret.?.(u10) k-2 COPY NO.25TH FEBRUARY, 19k9CABINETWAGE MOVEMENTS IN 19U8Memorandum by the Minister&apos; of Labour and National ServiceSince my memorandum on wage movements in 191+8(CaxJ.(i^9) 28) was prepared there &quot;have been a number of developments of major importance which will have widespreadconsequences.   I&apos; am accordingly setting these out in thissupplementary memorandum so that my colleagues will bo aware of them when considering the main memorandum. ;2. When account is taken of these developments, togetherwith other less important wage increases granted and claims made,it is clear that no period of wages stability can now beanticipated.   It seems likely that, following the increase in agricultural wages, a further general upward-movement of wagesduring the next six or twelve months should be expected and thatthe qualified success of the White Paper since February, 191+8,will not continue. - -3* Agricultural Wages IncreaseFollowing the proposals, of the Agricultural wages board for an increase of I4./- in the minimum rate for men theminimum rate for agricultural workers will be 9k/- a week.   TheGovernments decision as regards agricultural prices will mean that in fact a k/- increase,  (or proportionately higher increases)will be given to farm workers already receiving wages above thestatutory minimum rate.    The consequences of these increases in agricultural wages will be to increase the pressure generallyfor higher wages in other industries.   It is still the attitudeof workers in many other industries that their own wage rates should be substantially higher than the rates &quot;in agricultureand they will seek to maintain the relative position they had before this recent increase.   In particular the agriculturalincreases are likely to be followed by claims in. a number of rural industries and trades where there has in the past beena close relationship with agriculture,  e.g. roadmen, localauthority workers, land drainage, etc    The minimum rates in anumber of these industries are below the new agriculturalminimum rate of 9k/- a week, e.g. land drainage 90/-, CountyCouncil roadmen 90/-.   The County Council roadmen have alreadysubmitted a claim for increased wages.    In addition a number ofindustries and services which employ a considerable proportionof workers in rural .districts and provide for rural rates intheir agreements wiil.be directly affected.   The most important in present circumstances is the Railway Service.   The minimum rate on the railways, in rural areas is at present 91/6d* andthe recent increase in agriculture may well be used as an argu-ment when the present claim for an increase of 12/6d* a. week isbeing put.to the Railway Staff National Tribunal.    (The claim is to be heard on 7th and 8th March.)   Another service likely

to be affected is the Post Office whore the lowest .rate for a rural postman is 8k/- at the age of 21 and 92/- at the age of25.   A claim for increases for Post Office workers will be goingto the Civil Service Arbitration Tribunal.   There are also anumber of industries, not rural,  such as cotton and wool wherethe minimum, time rates are at present substantially below thenew agricultural minimum and where claims for increased wages have recently been presented.    For example, the labourer&apos;s ratein cotton is 38/- a week, and in wool 90/kd. a week, and therecent increase in the agricultural rate may be significant in .relation to the claims at present being considered in the cotton&apos;and woollen industries.k* Retail DistributionThe Wages Councils covering the retail food trades,retail bookselling, retail drapery,  etc are now publishingtheir first proposals to establish statutory minimum rotes.   Theminimum rates proposed for men vary in the different tradesfrom 102/- to 110/- a week in London and represent increases ingeneral of from k/- to 6/- a week above the current minimum rates agreed on the Joint Industrial Councils.   They will nodoubt mean in effect considerably greater increases than this because there is reason to think that the Joint IndustrialCouncil rates were not observed by a considerable proportionof the employers..   A very large number of people, about1-g- million, are employed in retail distribution and so far asit is possible to estimate the wages costs of meeting theseproposals they are extremely high - probably not less thansomething like  20 million per annum.    The proposals raise anumber of complicated problems which will be dealt with in aseparate memorandum, but it would seem that if Orders are finallymade on the lines of the proposals as they are at present therewill be widespread repercussions throughout industry and otherconsumer services and a very serious breach will-be made in theGovernment policy as set out in the White Paper.5. Road Passenger transport the Tribunals appointed by the Minister to considerthe claim on behalf of bus workers for time and a half pay on saturday afternoon have recommended increases in pay related toSaturday afternoon working which are equivalent to time and aeuarter.   Though the awards seek to. avoid accepting the principleof enhanced rates of pay for Saturday afternoon working, it isnot likely that they will be accepted by industry as a wholeas doing this and repercussions on Railways, Retail Distributionsand Public Utilities can be expected.6. Textile IndustriesClaims for substantial increases are now under con-sideration in both cotton and ?/ool and in all the circumstances it seems reasonable to assume that some increases are likelyto be given.7. RailwaysThe N.U.R. claim against the Hotels Executive has been rejected by the National Arbitration Tribunal.    The claim againstthe Railway Executive is to be heard by the Railway StaffNational Tribunal on 7th and 8th March, and the claim againstthe London Transport Executive by the appropriate Tribunal on 3rd March.G.A.I*Ministry of Labour and NationalService, S.W.I.,25th February, 1949*-2-




</content>
</cab>
