<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 38-43</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
this document is  the property of his britannic majesty&apos;s government-      19Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1949SECRET; Copy No.CP. (49) 45&apos;26th February, 1949cabinetANTI-PARTITION CAMPAIGN IN EIREMemorandum; by the Secretary of State for&quot; Commonwealth relations attach, for the information of my colleagues, the following two documents : (1) a note of 4th February by Lord Rugby, written at my request,, to bring upto date a memorandum which he had submitted to me on 29th November,1948, about the intensification of the anti-partition campaign in: Eire(Appendix I); and(2) a memorandum setting out the results of consideration by the Departmentsconcerned of the possibilities of any discussion of Partition; in aninternational forum (Appendix II).2. In his earlier memorandum Lord Rugby had suggested that the United;Kingdom might with advantage take the initiative in referring the question tosome international body; recent statements by Eire Ministers have made it clear,that they hope to do this themselves.p: j. N.-b.Commonwealth-Relations Office, S-.W. 1,26th February, 1949APPENDIX IThe Anti-PahtitiOn Campaign in EireNote by Lord Rugby dated 4kK. February, 1049The gist of a Memorandum headed &quot; The Writing on the Wall &quot; and sub-mitted byimeto the Secretary, of State on 29th (November, 1948, is attached hereto.In&apos; my. view1&apos; mdasdres&apos; tb avert&apos;&quot; ugly developments in connexion with the ariti-partitiori campaign1 call&apos; for serious consideration; if it is: found that. nothingfurther can be doneJby the United Kingdom Government, that; too, is a decision&apos;the implications of which shouldbe made quite clear to the Eire Government:   Thereaffirmation of&apos;the status of Northern Ireland in the Government of Ireland Billis: a.definite step iritnis&apos; direction^   The;.Irish Nationalist view, justified by past;experiencej is ithat-it is only necessary to worry and harry the British long enough *for&apos; them to throw up the j ob and clear out.   Irish Nationalists do not realise thatthis-technique rid longer applies.3662731
I have only two points to add to the appreciation of the situation given in the enclosed memorandum: (a) Mr. de Valera, with whom I had a long farewell interview on 25thJanuary, said that in his view an outbreak of violence on the Borderissue was becoming more and more certain and he asked me not to fail&apos; in bringing this danger to the notice of the United Kingdom Gdyern-ment. I nave no doubt that this is his sincere belief, though, I am notblind to the fact that it is not bad policy to frighten us with a bogy.Nor to the fact that, if passion should break loose, Mr. de Valera must bear a large share of the responsibility.(b) Mr. Sean MacBride makes the practical suggestion that things mightbe easier if the leaders North and South met one another. He was most anxious that I should try and arrange for him to meet Sir BasilBrooke. Mr. MacBride said : &apos;&apos; Even if nothing happens, still it wouldbe a good thing to have a talk and discuss one another&apos;s point of view.&quot;I see no disadvantage in this and possibilities of great advantage.Agreement to differ about fundamentals and to collaborate moreobviously in practical problems would bring the temperature downto some extent, possibly to a considerable extent. In accordance withMr. MacBride&apos;s wish I am mentioning this to the Prime Minister.Mr. MacBride looks like being the man of the future and youngIreland looks to him.   He is the best choice for a &quot; contact.&quot;Extract from Memorandum by Lord Rugby dated 2%th November, 1948The true rivalry in Irish politics used to be between a Commonwealth party and the Separatists. All now, willy-nilly, are Separatists. Henceforth the onlyrivalry left to the parties in Irish politics is to outrival each other in the virulenceof their anti-Partition campaign. This will embrace attempts to make Partition-a. live issue in British politics and to influence world opinion by the threat to abstain from joining Western Union. That is what Mr. Costello meant in his speech by saying that the repeal of the Act will enable him to raise the Partitionquestion on the international plane. It is my view that this rivalry between theparties in an anti-Partition crusade will bring the gun-man back again.On the surface there are here the same friendly people, for the most partgenerous admirers of England, cordial and helpful. But in the blood stream thereis a malignant virus. People do not stop to analyse the trend or to read thesymptoms and signposts. In the air there is a sense of coming climax andMr. de Valera&apos;s stern admonitions are a portent. We go from celebration tocelebration inspired by the half unconscious cult of hatred. The indoctrination ofthe younger generation by press, radio, platform and pulpit has been intense.My colleague, the Canadian High Commissioner, observes with growing alarmwhat is going on here.Some people in England think that the repeal of the External Relations Acthas automatically put the Partition question to sleep. There could be no greatermistake. All it has done is to destroy the best chance of a friendly solution. Theestablishment here of an independent Republic will stimulate national sentimentand inflame opinion about the Border on both sides of it. Anybody who hasstudied the course of Anglo-Irish history and particularly anyone who hasobserved the poisoning of young minds in recent years can recognise at once afamiliar Irish pattern taking shape.My forecast is that unless a move is made now on our side to anticipate anddisperse the forces and influences now gathering we shall have bloodshed inIreland, a grave state of disorder in the North, with world, opinion once againonly too ready to believe that England is misbehaving herself in Ireland. we know, or should know, by bitter experience what Irish opinion in the Common-wealth, in the United States and in the Catholic world can do. It may not takethe first trick but it wins the rubber.I am not suggesting that Mr. Costello would approve a violent solution ofthe Partition question. He and most of his colleagues are men of peace, though their oratory is a summons to battle. Indeed, all the best Irish opinion woulddeplore a renewal of violence. But Irish leaders are not free agents and they know it. This is the land of Frankenstein. 1798 is active in the streets to-day.Parnell did not want the Phoenix Park murders. His Work was wrecked bythe Invincibles.   The rebels of 1916 were loudly cursed in Dublin, but in
three months&apos; time they were heroes. The blood sacrifice worked its mystique andchanged or hastened the course of history.  Mr. de Valera did not want to havebombs thrown in Coventry in 1939, but when two of the criminals were executed) Dublin shops were forced to close and a Requiem Mass was held.  We face thesame developments to-day.   They come by instinct rather than by intention.Indeed, the Partition issue is not a real issue.   It is built up on emotion.Inexorably, inevitably, the Irish Eepublic now created will be pushed from behindto&apos;work out the destiny so long and so passionately preached.   &quot; Ireland shallbe free from the centre to the sea.&quot;   The Government need not move, will notmove. The murder of one policeman in the North is enough to bring the opposingemotions to a clash. Others will strike and the Government will be involved. Theworld is bloodier and more brutalised than it wm.   We may perhaps feel some. sympathy for a Government which has to control a vendetta-minded people who&apos; have had no outlet for their tribal passions during the years of war.Unionists in the North, and perhaps elsewhere, may be tempted to say &quot; let them do their worst.&quot; The forces of the Crown &quot; will soon teach them a lesson.&quot;This view has no element of wisdom in it. It will be a day of triumph forEire if the forces of the Crown are actively employed against patriotic elements in Ireland.   British bayonets are Ireland&apos;s secret weapon.APPENDIX IIPossible Discussion of Partition of Ireland in an International Forum1. Possible Action by the Eire Government at the United nations the Eire Government, though not a Member, might raise the issue underArticle 35 (2) of the United Nations Charter. Under this Article, it could bebrought to the attention of either the Security Council or the General Assemblyas a &quot; dispute.&quot; Alternatively, a mischief-making member of the United Nationsmight raise it as a &quot; situation,&quot; presumably with Eire&apos;s support.(a) Security Council     &apos;It is perhaps unlikely to be raised here since it is by no means certainthat the necessary seven votes would be forthcoming in support of a resolutionfavourable to Eire. If, however, such a resolution were passed on the issue as a &quot; dispute,&quot; the United Kingdom, as a party, would not have the rightto vote or, therefore, to use its veto. The United Kingdom would have theright to veto if the issue were treated as a situation.(b) General AssemblyIt is more probable to be raised here, as Eire might well command thesupport of the Slavs and the Powers who are normally anti-colonial. Anumber of others would probably be neutral, and relations with other Common-wealth Governments on the issue might be difficult. But it is questionable whether Eire could procure a two-thirds majority. On the other hand, itis still less likely that a two-thirds majority could be obtained for a resolutionfavourable to the United Kingdom.(c) Possible resultsAny deliberations in the Assembly could only result in recommendations for a solution. Though the recommendations would not be legally binding,Eire or a potential mischief maker might succeed thereby in stirring upprejudice against His Majesty&apos;s Government. If a Commission of enquiry was sent out by order of the Security Council or the General Assembly, theGovernment of Northern Ireland might refuse to admit it to its territory.The United Kingdom Government would then be placed in an embarrassingdilemma of either refusing to acquiesce in a United Nations recommendationor of having to coerce the Northern Ireland Government.I 2. United Kingdom defence in the Security Council or the AssemblyA strong case could, it seems, be made out on the grounds that: (i) there is no general threat to the peace&quot; arising out of the position ofNorthern Ireland;
P] (il) there is no threat to the peace as between omselws amd: Eire^ becauseneither country has,any intention of going; to war on the issue; ,1;(iii) in so far as there is. frictions, this has been created by Eire, herself, and?is due to her refusal to face the facts that Northern. Ireland is legallya. part of the United. Kingdom,, and that partition-could; be modified?Only against the wishes of the great majority of the population.But it is uncertain how much support we should get.3. Possible United Kingdom initiative at the United Nations- to forestall Mine.. ,A move by the UnitedKingdom Government would take the wind1 out of Eire&apos;^sails, enable us to choose the Security Council rather than the Assembly as the*forum, and, if the matter was brought up as a &quot;situation-&quot; retairi the United?Kingdom right of veto. But it is uncertain whether seven votes could&apos; be obtained?for a resolution favourable to the United Kingdom: Moreover there might? be1serious objection-, by Northern ireland. It appears,therefore, that no advantage would be gained by the United Kingdom Government themselves bringing-thenissue before the Security Council and a fortiori the Assembly.4. International Court of Justice(a) Issue for decision. Broadly speaking, the possible legal issues in relationto Partition are, first, whether Northern Ireland or any substantial part thereofbelongs in law to Eire or to the United Kingdom, or, secondly, what is the exactboundary between Northern Ireland and Eire. It is almost inconceivable that Eire,Could succeed before the Court on the first issue. It is equally inconceivable that^she would place the second issue before the Court because that in itself wouldinvolve confirmation of partition:(&amp;) Limited: swp&amp; of[ compulsory: jiurisdiction^At present Eire is not a&apos;partyeither to the Statute of the Court, or to the optional clause andi could not1 therefore^compel the United Kingdom to accept its jurisdiction. Conversely^, the United?Kingdom; Could: not; compel; Eire to go to-the Court&apos;. In- order to become- a* party-to the Statute of the Court, it would be necessary for* Eire to comply witbVconditions to be determined by the General Assembly of the United Nations uponthe recommendation of the Security Council. If Eire, in fact; became- a: party* tp the Statute, and made an appropriate declaration.: under the. optional clause, she could, after leaving the Commonwealth,, compel: the United Kingdom, and, theIgnited. Kingdom: could! compel( Eire, to, submit to, the Courtis jurisdiction., It isvery doubtful, however, whether either country, could compel the, other.on; thelegal, issues; relating to Partition: because the United Kingdom declaration- doesnot apply to disputes arising with regard to situations or facts existing;; before5th February, 1930. Moreover, as it is unlikely that it will be in Eire&apos;s interestto take the legal issues to the Court, she may think it. unwise to* make herselfvulnerable by making, a declaration under- the optional clause.(c) Consideration ex cequo et &amp;&apos;owo.-^-Neither country can, compel, the otherto accept the jurisdiction of the Court on an ex cequo- et. bono basis since theCourt can only decide the case on an e&amp; cequo- et bono basis if, the parties agreethereto. We should1 regard&apos;our legal title to Northern Ireland&apos; as. unassailable,and we would riot agree to such a refference.. While,.therefore,,thereis riorprdspectof proceedings, the Eire Government might&apos;seek to&quot;gain.a tactical! advantage inthe United Nations or otherwise by offeringtorefer to the Court on an ex cequoet bono basis. We could counter this by an offer to have the legal, issues, examined by the Court.5. Action outside the United&apos;Nations(a) The Eire Government are likely to participate in the proposed Councilofi Europe. They may&apos;, therefore, raise partition in the- Assemblyof this body.(b); The Eire Government are reported to-have approached the&quot;;State- be part-&quot; ment in connection with; their refusal1 to join iti: discussion on theNorth Atlantic Pact, and sounded them i about the possibility of theStates of the North Atlantic community &quot; mediating, the Partitiondispute.&quot; In view of the attitude previously adopted by the UnitedStates Government; this approach presumably- received no&apos;encouragement.



</content>
</cab>
