<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 56-59</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
thisPrinted for the Cabinet. . March ^.949SECRETCopy JNo..31CP. (49) 484th March, 1949CABINETIRELAND : THE ANTI-PARTITION CAMPAIGNMemorandum by the Home Secretary and the Secretary of Statefor Commonwealth Relations -1. Our colleagues will remember that in the discussions last October and november about the consequences of the repeal of the External Relations(Executive Authority) Act, the Eire Ministers claimed to be moved by thefriendliest feelings towards the UnitedKingdom and emphasised tirat the severance of the last link binding Eire to the Commonwealth was designed tqimprove our relations. Notwithstanding these professions the campaign ,agkinstthe partition of Ireland has been intensified over the past two or three months and we may expect the Eire Government and Opposition, with the powerful aid of some elements in the.Roman Catholic Church, to join in seeking to demonstratein this country, in other Commonwealth countries and in the United States thatthe United Kingdom Government are wilfully preventing the reunion Of Ireland.2. The recent General Election in Northern Ireland led to an increase inthe anti-partition propaganda. Thus, Mr. Costello and other Eire Ministerslaunched an appeal for funds to support anti-partition candidates in NorthernIreland, and after the results had been declared the Eire High Commissioners inLondon and Canberra issued press statements claiming that the Election had beenunfairly conducted. Again, Mr. Costello has threatened to use the weapons inthe hands of Eire ruthlessly so long as the evil of partition continues, while Mr. MacBride has made frequent references to the wrongful occupation of partof Ireland by British troops and has stated that, though the Eire Governmentsympathise with the objects of the proposed Atlantic Pact, they cannot join inany military alliance with Great Britain so long as partition lasts. The NorthernIreland Government have also been criticised by Members of the WestminsterParliament on the ground that the Election was fought on a stale register andthat opponents of the Government were denied freedom of speech.3. It should be noted that in the Eire propaganda it is suggested that ifpartition were ended the Parliament and Government of Northern Ireland wouldbe allowed to continue to exercise their present powers, and that only the powersnow exercised from Westminster should be transferred to the Dail, in which therewould, of course, be some representation of Northern Ireland. Eire is thusseeking to establish that the end of partition would mean no loss of independenceby Northern Ireland and that the defence of the British Isles would be secured by the willingness of a United Ireland to join in the Atlantic Pact.4. We have hitherto thought it right that the United Kingdom Governmentshould officially ignore the Eire campaign, and the Prime Minister in reply toa Parliamentary Question on 8th February (Hansard, col. 190) refused to makeany protest to the Eire Government about their alleged interference in theNorthern Ireland Election. Sir Basil Brooke has, however, addressed a letterto the Prime Minister pointing out that the statements made by Eire are anincitement to violence by both sides, and suggesting (i) that the United Kingdom36671
Government should let the Eire Government know that they will not toleratea continuance of the policy of threats and incitement directed against a part ofthe United Kingdom, and (ii) that at the first suitable opportunity the PrimeMinister should make a public declaration condemning Eire&apos;s interference in the affairs of Northern Ireland and expressing the United Kingdom Government^determination to see to it that the citizens of Northern Ireland need have no ground for apprehension.5. While we deplore the action taken by Eire Ministers and sympathise with sir Basil Brooke&apos;s apprehensions, we are satisfied that any protest addressed tothe Eire Government would merely lead to a rebuff and encourage Eire ministers to intensify the campaign even further.On the question of assurances to Northern Ireland, we believe that the most effective action would be the publication of the Ireland Bill with its declaration that Northern Ireland remains part of His Majesty&apos;s dominions and of theUnited Kingdom and its affirmation that in no event will Northern Ireland orany part thereof cease to be part of His Majesty&apos;s dominions and of the UnitedKingdom without the consent of the Parliament of Northern Ireland.This declaration and affirmation would no doubt be underlined by the Govern-ment spokesman in the Second Reading debate on the Bill and it might on that occasion prove necessary to indicate that British forces would be used to defendNorthern Ireland against armed aggression just as much as they would be usedin the defence of, say, Kent. At the same time it could be made clear that Britishtroops were present in Northern Ireland not to coerce the inhabitants of NorthernIreland but to ensure that the will of the majority was not overridden by pressure from outside the United Kingdom.6. For the reasons given in CP. (49) 47 we realise that it would be inexpedient to introduce this Bill before the Easter Recess and it may be that inthe interval before then some new development in the Eire campaign will compel us to give Northern Ireland some public assurance of the kind suggested bySir Basil Brooke. If, however, no such development takes place we recommend to bur colleagues : (i) that no protest should be made to the Eire Government about their anti-partition propaganda;(ii) that any assurance to Northern Ireland should be given in theproceedings on the Ireland Bill; and(iii) that the Prime Minister should reply to Sir Basil Brooke&apos;s letteraccordingly.J. C. E.P. J. N-B.4th March, 1949.



</content>
</cab>
