<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 60-77</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)r-----------------------------------------------------------------1,SECRETCP. (49) 49 COPYNo3\8TH MARCH. 1949 :CABINETMEAT ration memorandum by the Minister of Pood1. When the Cabinet decided on 17th January to reduce thecarcase meat ration from 1/- to 10d. per week and make good the cut by 2d. worth, of canned corned meat it was agreed(CM.(1+9) 1+th Conclusions, Minute l) that the future level ofthe meat ration should be reconsidered in March.    I now submit a fresh appreciation of our meat supply prospects for 191+9.    it shows there is no alternative but to recommend that the totalmeat ration should bo reduced immediately from 1/- to 10d. perweek - of which only 8d. worth will bo carcase meat.The immediate supply prospects2. Carcase meat.   This cut results from the continuedfailure of Argentine supplies.   Under the Andes Agreement,Argentine carcase meat shipments were to be at the rate of400,000 tons a year.   -When it became apparent that shipmentswere falling seriously behind we made the strongest possiblerepresentations to the Argentine Government and were assured that shipments would be at the rate of 300,000 tons a year inthe early months of this year.    In the January review we assumed that the shipments might be made at this rate.    It now appearsthat during the first four months of this year arrivals willhave been at the rate of only 255,000 tons a year.   Appendix Ashows our present estimates of the supply and consumption ofration meat in the first four months of 1949 as compared withthe estimates made in January and the actual supplies in 191+8.It shows that instead of receiving 392,000 tons as in 1948 or357,000 tons as was estimated in January we shall only receive326,000 tons in the first 1+ months of this year.3* The minimum stock of carcase meat.    So far we havemade good this deficit by draining on our stocks.   At thebeginning of the year we had 119,000 tons of ration meat in stock.   By the end of February we had run this stock down to1+9*000 tons and,  if we maintained the present rate of consumption,stocks would fall to 37,000 tons by the end of March and lowerstill in April.   But distribution would fail before this becausemy experts are all agreed that they cannot maintain nation widedistribution unless our total stocks of ration, meat are held at about 1+5,000 tons.    This includes the stock still undischargedin ship in port, the stocks in transit to depots, and the reserves on which wholesale distribution is maintained.   it represents only about 2 weeks&apos; supply of imported meat actually in store and represents the absolute minimum working stock without which we could not guarantee to honour the ration.    It containsno element of reserve for shipping delays, strikes, or any otheremergency.1+. I have satisfied myself that these stocks are- the bareminimum on which meat distribution will work. It is imperative that we should maintain this stock and there is no way to do soexcept to cut the carcase meat ration from lOd. to 8d. per week

&quot;... 30on 20th March, At this lower rate of consumption our stocksof ration meat at the end of March should be 1+5,000 tons andat the end of April 55,000 tons.5* Canned corned meat.    It is not possible to maintainthe total carcase meat ration at 1/- by increasing the canned corned meat share of it from 2d. to 1+d.   My Department hastried to maintain a reserve of 80,000 tons of canned cornedbeef to cover all emergency purposes.   But at the end of 191+8we had run it down to 66,000 tons and the drain on it hascontinued so that now we have only 50,000 tons.    If we continueto draw on our reserves at the present rate (2d. worth per weekrequires. 2,600 tons) our stocks will fall to the low level of10,000 tons by the end of July.    I think that we can continueto issue 2d. worth of canned corned meat until Maybut I propose that we should re-examine this before the easter recess.   It may well be that for a time this summer &quot;we shallhave to face the grim prospect of cutting out the issue of anycanned corned beef even if the carcase meat ration is only 8d.6. Supply prospects of Carcase Meat for the whole of 194-9*Appendix B shows our estimate of the supplies of carcase meat and offal in 19^9 from all the possible supplying countries.My officials have searched the world for meat with the resultthat we hope to get 1,622 thousand tons of carcase meat in191+9 as compared.with 1,595 thousand tons in 191+8,   I set out .below notes on the various countries.United Kingdom and-Eire.   It is convenient to include Eire withthe united Kingdom since Eire&apos;s main contribution will be inthe form of stores for fattening here.   Although we hope to get90-/Q of Eire&apos;s exportable supplies of cattle, her fat cattle and exports of carcase meat will not provide us with more than about20,000 tons.    In all the United Kingdom and Eire will provide758,000 tons in 191+9 as compared with 720,000 tons in 191+8,Southern Commonwealth. Countries,   Supplies from Australia andNew Zealand are estimated at. 510,000 tons in 191+9 - about thesame as in 191+8.   No spectacular increase can be expected.   Onthe other hand there is always the danger that drought orshipping delays may endanger part of these supplies,Argentina.   Argentina is the only country from which we can hope for any substantial supplies of meat in the short term.The recent strike of workers in the meat packing industry maypartly account for the falling off in shipments in the early months of this year.   But the main reason for the low shipmentshave been the deliberate policy adopted by Senor Miranda.   Hefailed to pass on to the meat packers any part of the  10,000,000side payment made by the United Kingdom and he encouraged the sales of meat at high prices to the United States Army and to european countries.   It is thought that he proposed to exportonly 183,000 tons to the United Kingdom in 191+9.   It will take some little time to re-establish confidence in the Argentinemeat packing and livestock rearing industry but it is hopedthat the change in regime will be of benefit to our negotiatorswho are now in Buenos Aires.   \7e are asking for 1+80,000 tons of meat but do not expect to get more than 310,000 tons, and haveused that figure in estimating supplies in this review.Other countries.   Our buyers have tried every possible sourcebut the rest of the world can only provide us with l+i+,000 tonsin 191+9,   Even if we had the dollars there is unlikely to bemuch meat available - for export in the United States or Canada.Uruguay, Guatemala and Chile a,re providing modest&apos; but useful    -quantifies,   Mexico, offers a possible source in the future but as yet we have not been able to overcome the payments problem.

I^s&amp;Suld welcome especially any action which, the Chancelloroi the Exchequer could take to overcome these difficulties,Br,a,z,3..1. has ceased to export and shows signs of becoming a netimporter,   European sources of supply are recovering but slowly.Denmark contracted to supply us with 11,000 tons in 1948 butdelivered only 3,000 tons.   We cannot rely on more than2 - 3,000 tons from there this year.   Prance may provide 1 or ,000 tons but not more,   Yugoslavia offered some meat but forthe past two years we have failed to obtain even a trialconsignment,7* The ration level of ,carcase meat in 1949,   Our total &apos;supplies of carcase meat and offal in 192+9 will amount to   -1,622,000 % tons.   How much can we consume?   We are in owpresent difficulties because we started the year with a stock of only 137,000 tons.    It is imperative that we should avoid anothermeat crisis at this tame next year,   so I think it essentialthat we should build up our stocks to 200,000 tons by January,1950 - a little below the stock level of the end of 1947,If we do that we shall be able to plan on the assumption that.1,579,000 tons is available for consumption in 1949.   This wouldbe sufficient for an average weekly ration of carcase meat of10.24d. as compared with an average of 10.8d. in 192+8.   However,the average conceals the marked variation in the seasonalsupply of home killed meat.   The substantial proportion ofhome killed supplies becomes available in the last six months ofthe year.   In fact, from the beginning of September to the endof November, home killed supplies will provide 1/- ration ofcarcase meat per week over most of the country.. Supplies cannotbe levelled out by delaying slaughter or by freezing supplies for storage.   So it follows that the supply for some months mustbe below lOd. if the average for the year is to be 10.4a1.8, Supply prospects for corned meat in 1949,   Appendix Cshows our estimates of the corned meat position for 1949*   we hope to get 67,000 tons of canned corned meat in 1949 -40,000 tons from the Argentine, 17,000 tons from the SouthernCommonwealth countries, and the balance from other South american countries.   We could only get more at the&apos;expense of our carcase meat supplies.   At the beginning of the year we had 66,000 tonsin stock, so we will have 133,000 tons available.   Here againwe must be prudent and build up our reserves by the end of theyear.    It has been my aim to hold 80,000 tons at the end of theyear as an emergency reserve to cover the danger of breakdown in supplies of carcase meat, strikes and other emergencies.Provided we get.the supplies we hope for, we could achieve this -if we stopped distributing canned meat at the end of April,In that case the-supplies of corned meat on the ration in 1949would average 0,6d. per week as compared with 1,3d. per week in 1948,9. The total meat ration in. 1949,   We cannot take any firm decision now on the general level of the meat ration in 1949&apos;So much depends on the Argentine,   The negotiations which arenow taking place there may enable us to make firmer estimates in a few weeks1 time.    Our present estimate is that total supplies v/ill provide an average weekly ration in 1949 of10.84d. per week (10.24 carcase -h 0.6 corned meat) as comparedwith 12,ld. per week in 1948 (10 , 8d. carcase and 1.3d. canned meat).   Because the home, killed supplies in 1949 will inevitablyentail giving a 1/- ration during the later months of the yearwe cannot avoid a ration of 10d. for some months earlier inthe year.    I therefore recommend that the total ration shouldbe reduced to lOd, per week on 20th March,

I propose to circulate a further paper on the 1949prospects before Easter.   For instance, if we could continue toissue 2d. worth of corned meat until the middle of May, by thonsupplies from the Argentine might enable us to increase thecarcase meat ration to lOd. and discontinue the issue of canned meat in order to build up reserves.   The ration wouldthen remain at. 10d. carcase meat until the home killedsupplies in August made it possible to increase the ration to 1/-.10. Nutritional implications of the reduction in the meat ration.   A cut in the meat ration now of 2d. will reducethe animal protein intake, but this will be offset at firstby the increased supply of eggs and milk which we can expectthis year in March, April, May, and most of June.    In June the seasonal decline in supplies of milk and eggs will beginand there will be a sharp drop by July.   Thus, until June thenutritional implications of a cut in the meat ration will be negligible, but in July. - the last month before the home killedsupplies commence oh a serious scale - there will he nocompensatory increase to offset the loss of &quot;meat, and theeffect on the diet will be significant.   We ought therefore to consider whether at least for this month we could findalternative supplies of some other rationed foodstuffs.11. Alternative protein foods.   Apart from milk and eggs, fish and cheese provide possible alternative supplies ofprotein.   I propose to do all that I can to increase suppliesof fresh fish.   But the only real offset to the terribly lowmeat ration - which may even have to fall to 8d. - would be toprovide an additional 1 oa. of cheese per week for the four weeks of July.   1 oz. of cheese would provide 120 calories and 7.0 grassof protein per week while even the 2d. cut in the meat rationwill cause a loss of 154 calories and 7*6 gms. of protein.   the extra ounce for four weeks would require 6,000 tons of cheese,which&apos; could be purchased in the United&apos; States at a cost of4.8 million dollars.   After all the difficulties which wereexperienced in providing suitable, foods for harvest workers last summer the cut in the meat ration this year would be particularly serious if we could not provide some suitablealternative.    I therefore hope my colleagues will agree tothis provision of cheese.12.   &apos;        Special rations.   At the moment all underground coalminers receive a special additional moat ration of 1/- each week.    I do not propose that this should be cut.    It has remained unchanged when wo have raised the ordinary ration in the past.Vegetarians receive a ration of 12 oz. of cheese and 2 oz. ofvegetarian fat per week in lieu, of the normal meat, bacon and cheese rations.   I do not propose that this should be cut.13. Announcement..In order to safeguard stocks the total meat rationmust be reduced on 20th March.   I would therefore propose to announce the reduction in the House of Commons on Monday,14th March.    I would stress the fact that alternative suppliesof protein are available at present.14. R ec ommend at i consideration accordingly recommend that:-(i) the total meat ration should be reduced to lOd. -i.e. 8d. carcase meat and 2d. canned meat - fromSunday,  20th March.

(ii)    that this decision should be announced on14th Marqh.(iii)    that authority should be given at once forthe purchase of 6,000 tons of United States cheeseat a cost of h.8 million dollars in order toprovide an increase of 1 02. in the cheese rationfor the harvest weeks of July before the cut .in the meat ration can be restored;(iv)    that meat supply prospects should be examinedagain early in April in the light of theprogress of negotiations in Buenos Aires.J*S *Ministry of Pood, S.W.I.,8th March, 1949*

APPENDIX *AfSupplies, Consumption and Stocks of Ration MeatJANUARY - APRIL&apos;(Assuming continued issue of lod. carcase meat ration)StSck at &quot;beginning of YearJanuary supplies from:-U.K.   .Southern DominionsArgentinaOther sourcesTotalTotal availabilityUtilizationStock at end of january february supplies from:-U.K.Southern DominionsArgentinaOther sourcesTotalTotal availabilityUtilizationStock at end of FebruaryMarch supplies froms-U.K.Southern DominionsArgentinaOther SourcesTotalTotal availabilityUtilizationStock at end of MarchApril supplies from:-U.K.Southern DominionsArgentinaOther, sourcesTotalTotal availabilityUtilizationStock at end of Aprilof which actuallym cold storeRATION MEAT(net tons product weight)1948          j          1949 1 (Jan.estimate) ........		1949 (realised and now anticipated;136,100 40,300 40,600 41,200 11j100 133,200	1 119,200 38,500 20,800 13.-000 72,300	119,200 .          -            &apos; &apos; 38,900 22,700 13,100 - 200 74,900269,300 129,200	191,500 127,500	194,100 124,500;           140,100 1 j 30,700 ! 14,000 1 22,200 ;, 4,000 i                70,900	64,000 30,000 21,000 22,000 73.000	69,600 28,300 20,100 20,700 200 69.300!                 211,000 ,     .           108,000	137,000 92,500	138, 900 90,100103,000 30,000 42,500 16,200 5,500 94,200	44,500 30,000 42,000 28,000                 : 4,000 104,000 :	48, 800 27,100 30,200 18,800 800 76,90019/, ZOO 112,000	148,500 ;                125,700 93,000 i                  88,400	85,200 38,100 29,300 24,400 2,200 94,000	55,500 43,000 34,000 28,000 3,000                  &apos; 108,000	37,JCC 41,400 39,000 22,000 3,000 105,400179,200; 114,000!	163,500 116,000	142,700 112,70065,200 1 (52,500)	47,500 (37,500)j	+ 30,000 (20,000 *still be in ships holds, or in transit to the stores and therefore not immediately available.    The quantity not immediately available in the stockfigure varies from a few thousand to as much as 20,000 tons:    in arriving at the figure actually in store and as available at the end of April, wehav^e assumed that it will be about 10,000 tons.

APPENDIX &apos;BfSupplies and Consumption of Carcase Meat and Offal	Carcase Meat and Offal &apos;000 tons bone in weight		1948 (actual)	1949 (estimated)Supplies		Imported from:-		Australia	150	150New Zealand	367	360:Argentina	&apos;  310	310Other S.American	23	26Miscellaneous	25	18TOTAL	875	864Home Killed		(including supplies from Eire)	720     -     -	758TOTAL SUPPLIES	if 595	1,622Opening stocks	210	157TOTAL AVAILABILITY  -	1,805	1,779Utilization	.   1,648	1,579Closing stocks	157	200AVERAGE RATION (in pence per week)	10.8.	10.24Change in stocks	-? 55	*   43

APPENDIX tG&apos;supplies and. Consumption of Canned Cornea Meat	Canned Corned Meat &apos; 000 tons product weight		1948	1            1949Supplies		Imported frorn:-		* Australia New Zealand Argentina Other S. American	&apos;.     8 3 14 8	14 3 40 10TOTAL SUPPLIES &apos; Opening stocks	33 /    124	67 66TOTAL AVAILABILITY Utilization	157&apos; 91	133 52-&apos;.-Closing stocks	66	81AVERAGE RATION (in pence per week)	1.3	0.6Change in Stocks	-58	+15h-- Services, Issued, in	ships stores,  etc. lieu of bacon	6,000 tons 6,000   &quot;Civilian consumption for15 weeks (23rd Jan-30th April)at 2d. per head.. , 40,00052,000




</content>
</cab>
