<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/33/0 images: 108-123</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
COPY NO.   *-*fUTH MARCH. 19*4-9CABINET-INTERNATIONAL WHEAT agreement memorandum by the Minister of food the latest telegrams from Washington about theWheat Conference are attached as an Annex to this paper.It is clear that we have now reached the final stage in thenegotiations and it will now be necessary to send our representatives completely definitive instructions.2. There are three main points at is sue:-(a)   Price range.The exporters have now made a &quot;firm and final offer&quot;of a maximum of $1.80 for a four-yoar agreement with a minimum price range of $1.50 falling annually by 10 cents to $1.20 inthe last year.In E. P. C. (1+9) 9 I said that we should be prepared to    .&apos;jaccept a maximum price of $1*75 with the scale of. minimum prices :now proposed by the Americans (which, I may remind my colleagues,is above the minima accepted in the agreement last year).      I said that I would not, however, be prepared to go beyond thesefigures.      My colleagues accepted these recommendations(E. P. C. (h9) 6th Meeting, Minute 1).     The question now is whether, despite this, we should accept a maximum price of$1.80.      It is difficult to.estimate -what would be the actual cost to us of accepting a maximum of $1.80 instead of $1.75*The position is - complicated by the fact that for 19*1-9/50 weare firmly committed to buying 11+0 million bushels of wheat from Canada at $2 a bushel.      It is probable that, apart fromthis, we should have to pay for all our wheat bought under theagreement during the first two years of its life the maximum of the price range, but that thereafter prices would fallnearer to the minimum.      It follows that the additional costis likely to be confined to the first two years.      It might beof the following order:- &apos;.(i) an additional 5 cents per bushel for say 50million bushels in 19*4-9/50, amounting to.  $2^- millions;(ii) an additional 5 cents for, say, the whole ofour 190 million bushels of &quot;agreement&quot;wheat, amounting to $9? millions;(iii) in addition we might well have to make anadditional supplementary payment under the&quot;have regard to&quot; clause of our four-year agreement with Canada, amounting to, say,$7 millions.In other words this concession might cost us, say, $19 millions -of v/hich, perhaps, $15 millions would actually be payable inSECRETCP. (k10) 51-1--HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT)

dollars - in the first two years of the agreement, apart fromthe consideration that if the maximum price under the agree-trient is put at $1.80 instead of $1.75, the price of wheatbought outside the agreement might be higher than it other-wise would have been.      The question for decision is whether we should, break off negotiations unless we can secure a maximum price of-$1.75.      In my judgment, always provided that we can secure-the other conditions referred to below, and especiallya firm undertaking that the. Economic Co-operation Administra-tion will finance cur Canadian wheat.purchases at any rate forthe remainder of the current year and in 1949/50 - we should agree to pay $1.80 rather than break on a difference of 5cents a bushel.     We should, however, instruct our representa-tives to make a final effort to secure acceptance of ourmaximum price of $1.75.I have considered whether in order to secure a$1.75 maximum we should offer to make some additional con- &apos;cession&apos;at the minimum price range - e.g. to agree to, say, aminimum price of $1.25 in the last year of the agreement.      Ido not, however, recommend this course.      The proposed minimum&apos;price range of $1.50 falling to $1.20 is, as I have already said, above the range accepted in last year&apos;s agreement, andif wheat prices are going to fall heavily in the next fouryears it would be wrong for us.to accept a high minimum price in the last year of the.agreement at a time when Marshall Aidwill have stopped and our balance of payments difficulties withthe dollar area may consequently be even more difficult thantoday.(to)    Quantit ies.The exporters have sought to stipulate that importersas a whole should undertake to. purchase a total quantity ofwheat under the agreement of 550 million bushels.     Representa-tives of the importers have made it . clear that, with the bestwill, in the world, the maximum figure which they couldguarantee would be 510-512 million bushels.,..   We originallyoffered to guarantee 180 million bushels, but subsequently,and with a good deal of reluctance, increased that offer to190 million bushels subject to the conclusion of a satisfactory agreement on prices and to the inclusion of a.substantialexport quota for Russia.      The exporters have so far notindicated how their proposed figure of 550 millions is.to besplit up between the various exporting countries.      It is, ofcourse, absolutely essential that this should be made clear,since unless Russia is given a substantial quota within the exporters&apos;, total the importers might find themselves committed to taking very substantial quantities of dollar wheat.  ^ if russia were given a quota of, say, 75 million bushels it is arguable that we could safely put up our figure beyond 190million bushels, and in a separate telegram our.representatives at the Conference have urged that we should.be prepared to do this.      But if we agree to take 190 million bushels we shall be committed.to taking slightly over 80 per cent of our estimatedimport requirements under the agreement.      No other importingcountry has offered to commit so high a percentage of itsimport requirements and few followed our example in putting up their offers when Russia joined the Conference.      Given theessential need for us to be free to buy a proportion of our requirements outside the agreement, I consider that we ought notto commit ourselves beyond 190 million bushels, and should repeatour stipulation that we have only agreed to 190 million bushelson condition that Russia is a party to the agreement with asubstantial export quota.    . We should only agree to modify this attitude (i) if the other importers are prepared substantially to increase their commitments and (ii) if Russia were given asubstantial quota of not less than 75 million bushels within

o5the total figure put forward by the importers. In the circura-stances, and in the very last resort, to avoid a break we mightauthorise our representatives to go to 195 million bushels, butin no circumstances beyond this.(c)   E. C.A. financing of Canadian wheat purchases/The effect of a refusal to finance Canadian wheatpurchases would be so serious that, as urged in paragraph 3 ofFrame telegram 1256 (D of Annex), it. should be made anessential condition of our entering the agreement that there isa firm understanding that the United States Administration will seek an amendment of the Economic Co-operation Act so as to make such financing possible, at least up to the maximum of the pricerange accepted in the agreement.     And we should make it clearthat our ratification of any agreement would be dependent uponthe enactment of such legislation.      Indeed, it might be.soundtactics to get the firmest possible assurance on this pointbefore embarking on, further negotiation on the other out-standing points.3. Finally we should not close our eyes to the fact thatif we sign this agreement, we shall be pegging the price&apos; of acrucial import at specified minimum prices over a term ofyears and on a falling market.      The Chancellor has justurgently warned me and other purchasing Ministers against makinglong-term contracts which have this effect.      The international wheat Agreement is precisely a long-term contract, made with anumber of purchasers, for the most important of all our imports,the price of which is now.falling rapidly;    the agreement is tobe made over a period of four years, extending beyond the marshall period;    it is largely, though not exclusively, adollar commitment;-   it must have a markedly sustaining influence on the prices of the other primary products which we buy, whileit can only sustain the prices of the manufactures which wesell indirectly and as a secondary repercussion.      I thereforeregard the signing of the International Wheat Agreement onthese terms with great apprehension.      I recommend these further concessions only because I feel that we are in effectfaced with force marjeure, and can hardly break the conference for the sake of the now fairly narrow gap which divides theproposals which we have already made from what the exporterswill probably take.4. Accordingly, my recommendations are that our represen-tatives should be instructed that the following represents thefinal firm position of the United Kingdom Government(a) We should be prepared in the last resort to accept amaximum price of $1.80 for a four-year agreement with a minimum price range of $1.50 falling to $1.20.      But every effort shouldbe made to persuade exporters to accept a maximum price of $1.75.We should, however, make no further concession on the minimum price range to secure this.(b) We should refuse to commit ourselves to a quantity inexcess of 190 million bushels unless other importing countries were prepared substantially to increase&apos; their offers and unlessRussia were given an export quota of. not less than 75 million bushels.(c) It should be a firm^condition of our entering theagreement that the&quot;United States Administration Will seek amend-ing legislation which will permit of the financing: of ourCanadian wheat purchases both in the current and subsequent years from European Recovery Programme funds at least up to the maximum price specified in the agreement .and until the end of July, 1950,v/hen our Canadian contract expires.     We should make it &quot;clearthat even if an agreement is concluded our ratification wouldbe dependent upon the enactment of such legislation.nistry of Food, S.W. 1. J. S.i+TH MARCH, 1949. -3-

ANNEXA.    Copy of telegram (No.  1200 FERTILE) of 1st March,  .19k9, from Washington to the Foreign OfficeWheat Conference.Acheson spoke with me today about the Inter-national Wheat Conference and told me that the UnitedKingdom price proposals notified in Foreign Office telegramNo. 212k had been discussed with the President, the Secretaryof Agriculture, and Senators associated with the farm groups. .The considered view of the United States Government which hehad to put forward was that the maximum price of $1.75proposed was not acceptable but that the United. States would agree to and settle for a maximum of $1.80 with $1.20 at theminimum.      I reminded Acheson that our offer was of $1.75 atthe maximum with $1.10 at the minimum and that any possibilityof concession at the minimum was dependent on a willingnesson the part of the United States to settle.      But he repeated that the United States could only agree upon a maximum of$1.80 with a minimum of $1.20 and pressed me to find outwhether His Majesty&apos;s Government would settle on these terms.Thus for the first time we have been presented with a definite.United States Government position.2. If no wheat agreement is concluded there is, to&apos;.say.the least, the probability in our view of difficulty over the financing through E.C.A.   of United Kingdom purchases of canadian wheat.     Consequently it seems to us here worth con-sidering the possibility of accepting a maximum price of$1S80 instead of $1.75 if in return we can secure agreement upon a minimum of $1.15 instead of $1.2^/sic7 asked.3. We are taking soundings with the representatives of.-,other importing - countries and will let you have a more con-sidered and informed view tomorrow.B.    Cony of telegram (Mo.&apos; 1232 FERTILE) of 2nd March,19U9, from Washington to the Foreign Office    &quot; -My telegram No.  1200.     Wheat Conference.During the course of the day we have taken soundingsamong exporters and the leading importers about the UnitedStates price proposals.      The general conclusion to which weare driven is that the United States will be able to keep allthe other exporters behind her and that in the last resortshe would be able to bring .all the other importers over toher side.2, So far as concerns the exporters Canada is in theweakest position.     If we we-re dealing alone with her we feel that we could force her to agree to prices of $1.75 atthe maximum and $1.10 at the minimum.      But she will ofcourse shelter behind the other exporters.      The new position which Australia has taken up since 2kth February, as reportedin Amaze No.  9k58 has tended to encourage the United states to refuse to consider any lower maximum than $1.80. with aminimum of $1.20.      One other factor which may have con-tribixted to the new rigidity in the United States position isthe reference in the Economist of 26th February implying thatthe United Kingdom delegation has been unnecessarily tough on prices and that a maximum price of $1.85 would not be unreasonable.

3. Most of the other importers could accept the UnitedStates price proposals without going back for further instruc-tions and we believe that the United States now knows this.For the present we might be able to persuade them to stand byus ori the basis prices of $1.75 maximum and $1.20 minimum.But the view which we now hold is that this will only be forthe moment, and that if other issues are settled the UnitedKingdom will be isolated on the price issue.4. Since yesterday we have consulted further withimporters and exporters about the possibility which we suggested yesterday of securing a minimum of $1.15 as quidpro quo for a maximum of $1.80.      Our revised view is thatthere is less chance of getting $1.15 minimum than of getting$1.75 maximum, primarily because the pressure from the farmgroups is being directed towards a higher minimum.&apos;5. The background to all the discussion about pricesof which we are continually made aware is the possibility that the United States may use E. 0. A.  as a means of providing an assured market for its wheat.      See my telegram No.  1209Frame.      Even though the Secretary of Agriculture does notdetermine in accordance with Section 112 of the E. C.A. Act1948, that the supply of&apos;wheat is in excess of domesticrequirements, he may state that the price at which U. S.D. A.is willing to sell wheat is at least no higher than the pricewe are now paying to the Canadians.      In such circumstancesE. 0. A. would have no alternative but to refuse authority forthe purchase of Canadian wheat with its funds.      Althoughformal communication has not yet reached us, there is asuggestion that the U. S. D. A.  is already bringing pressure onE. C. A.  and that the latter may in the next day or two rejectrequests for authorisation of additional wheat purchases from canada in respect of the first quarter of 1949*      We are trying to obtain confirmation of this suggestion.   So far asthe United Kingdom is concerned, to make it more difficultto finance Canadian wheat purchases would presumably not mean that a market would be provided for United States wheat,at least so long as the United Kingdom-Canadian contractoperates.      For the United States to continue to finance UnitedKingdom-Canadian purchases might leave both the U. S. D. A.  andE. C. A.   in a very embarrassing position.6. To sum up, although the success of the Conference isby no means yet assured on other issues, we feel that if weare to reject the United States proposals we run the gravestrisk of breaking up the Conference on the price issue, and itwould then be almost certain and not merely possible that weshould run&apos; into difficulties with E.C.A.   Supported as she isby Australia, the United States would not give ground even tothe extent that we hoped when paragraph 2 of telegramNo.   1200 was drafted.

COPY OP TELEGRAM (AMAZE 9*4-67) OF 3RD MARCH. 19*4-9FROM WASHINGTON (U.K. TREASURY AND SUPPLY DELEGATION)TO MINISTRY OF FOOD ;WHEAT CONFERENCEREFERENCE AMAZE 9*4-65.At the meeting of Steering Committee this afternoonWilson of Canada on behalf of some exports put forward the price proposals previously reported in F.O. Telegram 1200FERTILE indicating that the floor and&quot; ceiling figuressuggested for a four year agreement represented the firm and final offer of the unnamed exporters concerned.   But theseproposals were conditional upon importers as a whole undertaking to purchase a total quantity- of wheat under the Agreementof 550 million bushels.   This latter condition was alsoexpressly stated by Wilson to be final and firm.2.     On behalf of the importers Anderson replied that theseproposals would of course have to be very carefully consideredbut the importers would like to know not only which exportersput forward these proposals but also how the total quantities to be made available would be divided among them.   Theprice proposals could not be dissociated from quantities and to expect importers to agree to take additional quantities withoutknowing their source was to ask them to buy a pig in a poke.He went on to say that if as in fact we had been given tounderstand the exporters&apos; proposed not orily to make theseproposals known in Committee of the whole but also even to publish them then he could not agree to any report goingforward as from the steering Committee.   After a longdiscussion the exporters finally agreed that it was   -reasonable for importers to have an opportunity of consultationamong themselves and a further meeting of the Steering Committeeis to be held at the call of the Chairman.    The odds now are that it will take place early tomorrow afternoon.3.     At the meeting of importers which followed this afternoonthere was general support with the line which Anderson, had taken.The discussion was concentrated mainly upon the extent towhich under the most favourable of conditions importers mightbe able to increase their guaranteed quantities.    It showedconclusively that with the best will in the world importerscould not guarantee anything more than a total of-510 to512 million bushels.    There was therefore&apos;general agreement that at the Steering Committee tomorrow the line to putforward by Anderson on behalf of importers as a whole shouldbe that if the exporters insisted upon 550 million bushelsas a final condition of their offer then the Conference mustbreak down.   Our confident hope is that the exporters willhave to abandon&apos; thoir position on quantities and that discussion on prices can thus be made more realistic.h.     Late this afternoon we have heard   from the United KingdomTreasury and Supply Delegation that E.C.A. financing ofUnited Kingdom purchases of Canadian wheat cannot be arranged for the remainder of the first quarter of 19*4-9 and that unless there&apos; is some change in legislation financing in future quarterswill not be possible.   Presumably an undertaking to secure sucha change might be made a condition of United Kingdom adherence to a wheat agreement.   Perhaps an amendment to the AppropriationAct could be put forward through indicating that existing provisions in respect of, for example,- supplies in excess of domestic requirements would not apply to commodities subject to international Commodity Agreement ratified by the U.S.A.    In.this development you should see a FRAME telegram being dispatched tonight.

D.        COPY OF TELEGRAM&apos; (NO.   1256. FRAME) OP 3RD MARCH,  1949 :FROM WASHINGTON TO FOREIGN OFFICEE.C.A.  financing of Canadian Wheat and Flour.Bissell and Fitzgerald informed Caine and Christelowlate this afternoon that they expected formally to have toreturn to us early next week certain requests for procurementauthorisations covering wheat from Canada.      The Secretary .ofAgriculture had informed E.C. A.  that he would have no difficultyin supplying the quantities of v/heat indicated from the     &quot;*-United States.      There had been some discussion of this action, but Bissell1 s view was that E.C.A.  would have no   s.alternative but to accept the determination of the Secretary,of Agriculture. &apos;2.      We asked whether this determination would continue tohold good in the event of the present Conference reachingaccord on a wheat Agreement.      Bissell replied that even ifthere was an agreement duly ratified by the Senate, he didnot believe that E.C.A.would again be able to finance our requirements of Canadian wheat (so long as the present supply situation lasts) without a change in the existing E.C.A.Legislation.     lie thought it might be possible to amendsection 112 of the Economic Co-operation Act so that E.C.A.would not be precluded from financing off-shore purchases of commodities which were surplus to domestic requirements inthe United States in cases where such commodities had beenthe subject of International agreement duly ratified by the senate.      He would discuss this question further with theE.G.A.  General Council.3.      We have informed Anderson.      We shall be consideringfurther (as no doubt will you) the implications of this news,and we shall send you later our more considered views.      Atthe moment,  it appears to us that if we do decide to enterinto a Wheat Agreement,, we should do so only on the understanding(ratified by an exchange of letters or some other appropriate method) that the United States will seek amending Legislationalong the lines suggested above, and that the Wheat agreement shall have no force if the United States does not succeed in securing such legislation.      Even if such an amendment tothe Economic Co-operation Act was secured, we might, of course,run the risk of continuing to have our Canadian purchasesineligible for reimbursement until such time as theWheat Agreement was ratified: by the Senate.h.      We are checking the arithmetic.      It looks as thoughinitially for this quarter we may lose as much as $lh million for wheat.      We shall additionally lose a further amount forflour if the Secretary of agriculture makes&apos; a similardetermination in the case of that commodity.5.      Please pass copy urgently to Ministry of Food andTreasury.




</content>
</cab>
