<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/250/0 images: 32-33</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1934.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 182 (34).CABINET.THE MEAT SITUATION.Memorandum by the Lord President of the Council, Chairman of the Produce Markets Supply Committee.1. THE Cabinet, at their meeting on Tuesday, the 19th June, 1934. authorised the opening forthwith of discussions with the Governments of the Dominions and foreign countries concerned with the supply of meat to the United Kingdom market with a view, if necessary, to the modification of our powers of compulsory quantitative regulation, in return for powers to raise a levy on overseas meat imports (Cabinet 25 (34), Conclusion 6).2. Preliminary exchanges of views have taken place with the Dominion High Commissioners and with the Argentine Ambassador. Their inactions seem not unfavourable to the development of proposals along the lines indicated above.3. It is clear, however, that if action is to be taken to relieve the situation of the United Kingdom beef producer, which is serious now, and may deteriorate further during the Recess, when the autumn flush of cattle will be coming on to the market, any legislation which may be necessary must be introduced forthwith.4. While, therefore, the negotiations with the Dominions and the Argentine are being conducted as rapidly as possible, the Produce Markets Supply Committee have thought it necessary to press forward with the examination of measures which could be brought into operation during September next (whether the negotiations are then concluded or not).5. The Committee is satisfied that action within the terms of our existing agreements, by way of further quantitative restriction of imports, would, if it was to be effective, need to be of so drastic a character (especially in regard to imports from New Zealand) that it could only be contemplated as a last resort.6. The Committee has therefore come unanimously to the conclusion that an interim scheme, providing for direct payments to producers, should be brought into operation as soon as practicable. It is contemplated that the temporary scheme should cover a period to the end of March 1935 and that the Treasury advances should amount to about  3,000,000.7. The Committee attach importance to the framing of such interim measures on lines which will facilitate transition to a permanent scheme.8. They consider that the most desirable basis for the long-range scheme is that of the division of the proceeds of a fixed levy on imports, with no guarantee of a standard price; the levy scheme to be accompanied by a measure of quantitative regulation of imports.[10264]
9. The scheme which commends itself to the Committee as conforming to the above principles is as follows : (i) A levy not exceeding Id. per lb. in the case of foreign produce, and \d. per lb. in the case of Empire produce, to be imposed as soon as practicable on all imported meats (including live-stock, but excepting bacon).(ii) The proceeds of the levy to be paid into a fund out of which deficiency payments may be made to producers of fatstock in the United Kingdom. None of the proceeds of the levy would go into general revenue.(iii) The rate of levy and the amount of deficiency payment to be so relatedthat there will be a balance in the fund (after meeting all adminis-trative expenses) out of which the Exchequer can be repaid any payments made in advance of the imposition of a levy.(iv) Payments to be made to the home beef producer as soon after thebeginning of September as is administratively practicable, advances to be made from the Exchequer to meet these payments until such time as it is possible to introduce the levy. The amount of the advances necessary would depend on the time taken to get the levy arrangements agreed with the Dominions and the Argentine, (v) Payments in the initial stages of the scheme at all events to be 5s. perlive cwt. for &quot; eligible bovine stock &quot; (to be defined), (vi) Payments may be made out of the levy fund for promoting greater efficiency in the marketing of live-stock, (vii) Suitable provision will be made in the permanent scheme (a) for withdrawing assistance in the event of a substantial rise in market prices, and (b) for reducing the amount of the bonus granted per cwt. in the event of home production being expanded beyond a reasonable limit.10. Draft heads of a Bill, which are being prepared by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, in consultation with the Secretary of State for Scotland, the Secretary of State for Home Affairs (representing Northern Ireland interests) and the Treasury, will be circulated as soon as possible.11. If legislation is to be passed before Parliament rises at the end of the month, it must be introduced forthwith. For the sake of expedition, it would be highly desirable that the present measure should concern itself as far as possible only with the emergency, leaving long-term policy to be dealt with in a further Bill when Parliament resumes in the autumn. The principles which govern the temporary measure will of necessity, however, commit the Government to future action along well-defined lines, and these should be given full consideration before the temporary measure is introduced. For all these reasons I have therefore thought it desirable to report the position to the Cabinet as a matter of urgency.(Initialled) S. B.2. Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, July 5, 1934.

</content>
</cab>
