<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/250/0 images: 70-82</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   Jxdy 1934.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 189 (34)TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may be taken to ensure the secrecy of this document.CABINET.PRESERVATION OF PUBLIC ORDER.Memorandum by the Home Secretary.AT its meeting on the 13th June (Cabinet Conclusions 24 (34), Conclusion l)r the Cabinet had under consideration certain proposals which I submitted in outline for strengthening the law relating to the preservation of order at public meetings and to the organisation and maintenance of private armies for political purposes.I have now had an opportunity of consulting representative and experienced Chief Officers of Police, and I mention in the course of this memorandum their views on a number of the questions which arise in connection with this problem. I also attach a memorandum prepared by the Commissioner of Police of the Metropolis giving his views on the general situation and indicating the steps which should, in his judgment, be taken.There are several different aspects of the problem, and it will, I think, be for the convenience of the Cabinet if I discuss each of these separately. The main points which are raised are in italics, and at the end of the Memorandum I give a summarised statement of the proposals which I recommend for adoption.I. Preservation of Order at Public Meetings held on Private Premises.Rowdyism at public meetings is no new feature in English life. Up to within comparatively recent times, freedom of speech has meant the freedom of the speaker to propound his views to any who are willing to listen to him, without fear of interference by the Police or by the Courts unless he overstepped the wide limits set for the purpose of preventing the public use of words which are seditious, calculated to lead to a breach of the peace or otherwise contrary to the law of the land. But while the law protected a political speaker against undue interference by the Executive, the law, before the year 1908, provided no protec-tion to the speaker against interference by means such as heckling or the mere making of noise by his audience. When, however, the practice became common of preventing a speaker from getting a hearing by methods of organised rowdyism, Parliament decided that legislation on the subject was necessary. The Public Meeting Act, 1908, made it an offence for any person at a lawful public meeting to act in a disorderly manner for the purpose of preventing the transaction-tion of the business for which the meeting was called together. The Act does not, however, confer any additional powers or impose any additional duties on the police.Under the existing law, the police have no right to enter meetings held on private premises unless either they are invited to do so by the promoters of the meeting or unless they know that a breach of the peace is being committed. The police have no right to enter premises merely because they apprehend that disorder may occur.
In recent times an entirely new situation has been created owing to the rise and growth of the Communist and Fascist Organisations. On the one hand, it is part of the set policy of the Communists to take every opportunity of promoting disorder, and it is a common practice for them to organise rowdyism and disorder at the meetings of their political opponents and to prevent speakers at such meetings from obtaining a hearing. On the other hand, the Fascists have been unwilling to enlist the aid of the police, and have made the rowdyism created by the Communists an excuse for taking into their own hands the function of main-taining and securing order. The recent experiences at Olympia indicate that unless something is done to check these tendencies we may expect disorder on an increasingly serious scale. The Fascists will continue to organise big public meetings both in London and the Provinces, and the Communists will continue their counter-demonstrations against such meetings and attempt to break them up. Such a situation lends great strength to the Fascist cause, and many people who do not sympathise with Fascism nevertheless feel that the absence of any other means for securing orderly meetings excuses Sir Oswald Mosley in maintaining his private army in defence of freedom of speech, a slogan which he is not slow to exploit.The Commissioner of Police and the majority of Chief Constables whom I have consulted are agreed that the time has come when the law relating to the attendance of the police at public meetings held on private premises should be strengthened.The existing law is only defensible on the supposition that organisers of meetings will be ready to invoke police assistance. The Fascist policy of refusing police help has created a new situation. That the police when they anticipate trouble should nevertheless have to wait outside a hall until they receive infor-mation that breaches of the peace are taking place is contrary to the principle that the prevention of offences is a primary police duty.I therefore propose that the law should be amended so as to empower the police to enter premises when a public meeting is being held (even thoxigh they have not been invited to do so by the promoters of the meeting, or though an actual breach of the peace is not being committed) if the Chief Officer of Police has reason to believe that disorder is likely to occur.I am aware that questions will arise as to the extent to which and the point at which the police should intervene inside such meetings, but these difficulties must be faced; they are not, in principle, different from questions regarding the time at which and manner in which the police should intervene in other situations, and will not, I think, be found to be very difficult. The experience of many Chief Constables shows that the mere presence of the police inside such meetings exercises a sobering influence on the crowd, and that occasions for active interference are less likely to occur than under present arrangements, when disorder is liable to grow unchecked. As a general principle, the less the police intervene the better, but in my view they should have authority to be on the spot so that they can, when necessary, intervene for the purpose of preventing breaches of the peace or the use of undue violence either by the stewards or the interrupters.The only other question arising under this head is whether the Public Meeting Act, 1908, should be amended so as to make it an offence for an interrupter to refuse to give his name and address or to give a false name and address to the stewards of a meeting when requested to do so. On this question the opinion of the Chief Constables is divided. Such a provision, if coupled with a power of arrest, would certainly make the Public Meeting Act, 1908, more capable of effective enforcement against deliberate and wilful interruption of a meeting. But an arrest by the police of interrupters might exacerbate hostile opinion among the audience, and might even be a source of further disorder. On the whole, I am inclined to the vieto that, before amending the Public Meeting Act in this sense, it tooidd be desirable to ivait until we know the result of empoivering the police to enter meetings in their discretion.II. Open-Air Public Meetings.The right of assembly follows from the view taken by the Courts of individual liberty of person and individual liberty of speech. An assembly convened for a lawful object, assembled in a place which the meeting has a right to occupy, and
acting in a peaceable manner which inspires no sensible person with fear is a lawful assembly, and with such a meeting the police have no right to interfere. A meeting originally lawful may become unlawful by reason of the conduct of the persons assembled. But the law, while it does not prohibit open-air meetings, does not, generally speaking, provide that there shall be places where the public can meet in the open air, -either for political discussion or amusement. The so-called right of public meeting is nothing more than the right of all men to come together in a place where they may lawfully assemble for any lawful purpose. But the meeting or assembly must not interfere with the ordinary citizens&apos; right to use the highway, and if a meeting obstructs the right of free passage it becomes a nuisance. If an assembly is or becomes an unlawful assembly (i.e., an assembly of three or more persons with intent either to commit a crime by open force or to carry out any common purpose, lawful or unlawful, in such a manner as to give firm and courageous persons in the neighbourhood reasonable cause to fear a breach of the peace), the police are not only entitled but are bound to disperse it.The position, therefore, is that, as the law stands at present, the police have no powers of control over an open-air public meeting which is not an unlawful assembly unless obstruction of traffic is caused thereby. In practice, several Chief Constables prohibit Lhe holding of open-air meetings on the ground that they may lead to a breach of the peace, but it is far from clear whether there is any legal justification for this practice.Nearly all the Chief Constables consulted are of opinion that there should be express statutory provision requiring the prior consent of the Chief Constable to the holding of an open-air meeting, and that the Chief Constable should be empowered to prohibit such a meeting if he is satisfied that the meeting is likely to cause obstruction or to lead to a breach of the peace.&quot;While sympathising with the natural desire of the police that they should be given power of control over open-air meetings, this proposal is, in my view, too far-reaching and too drastic, and it is unlikely that it would be approved by Parliament. The difficulties caused by open-air meetings have frequently been considered by the Home Office, in consultation with the Law Officers, but the habit of holding open-air public meetings, especially for political purposes, is so deeply engrained in English life that it appears to me to be impracticable to propose that the holding of such meetings should be made subject to the sanction either of the police, the magistrates, the local authority, or of any other body.I accordingly recommend that the Government shoidd not ask Parliament to confer on Chief Constables any general power  to ban open-air meetings but, as is suggested in the third part of this memorandum, I think that Chief Constables shoidd be empowered to prohibit open-air meetings held at such times and places that there is likely to be a clash with other meetings, whether indoor or outdoor.III. Processions and Demonstrations.The concentration in London of c&apos; Unemployed Marchers &apos;&apos; in the autumn of 1932, the disturbances to which it gave rise, and the abnormal demands which it made on the poor law authorities, led to a review by a Cabinet Committee of the law  elating to processions and demonstrations., After considering the report of the Cabinet Committee, the Cabinet decided (Cabinet Conclusions 68 (32), Conclusion (10)) that, before resorting to new legislation, further trial should be given to the procedure by which a court of summary jurisdiction may, upon complaint, order any person to enter into a recognisance and to find sureties to keep the peace, and that, if this experiment proved unsuccessful, the question of strengthening the existing law should again be considered.The Unemployed March this year, although it caused grave inconvenience to the local authorities and imposed a severe burden on the police, did not give rise to any serious disorder, and the. question whether further powers should be taken to control processions has remained in abeyance.If legislation is to be introduced to deal with the preservation of order at public meetings held on private premises and with the organisation of private armies, the question of strengthening the law relating to processions and demonstrations cannot be disregarded.The question is of immediate practical importance, because Fascist activities lead to counter demonstrations. and processions by the Communists,. and we recently witnessed in London Communist processions to Olympia which ,were
organised for the purpose of creating disorder and of breaking up the Fascist meeting.The Commissioner of Police would no doubt be justified in dispersing a procession whose declared intention is to break up a political meeting or to commit some other unlawful and violent act, and it is unlikely that his action in so doing could be successfully challenged in the courts. But frequently, though there are grounds for believing that members of a procession contemplate unlawful action if they get the opportunity, the Police have at the time when the procession starts no evidence which could be put before a Court, and therefore feel bound to wait until the demonstrators commit some overt act of lawlessness.Strong arguments could be advanced for the absolute prohibition of processions through the streets in the Centre of London and of other big cities, on the ground that conditions of modern traffic and the existing congestion of the streets make processions an intolerable nuisance, and unduly impede the right of passage. Absolute prohibition of processions is no doubt outside the realm of practical politics, and some less drastic solution must be sought.Processions are of two kinds : (A) National, such as the two National Unemployed Marches; and(B) Local.(A) As regards National Processions, the only proposal I can suggest is that made in 1932, which would empoiver the Secretary of State to prohibit concentra-tions of persons outside the areas in which they ordinarily reside if he is satisfied that the concentration is likely to lead to serious disorder or the derangement of the public assistance administration. As the Cabinet Committee pointed out, it would be an innovation for the Secretary of State to exercise a jurisdiction in matters of Public Order in the absence of any grave national emergency, but, if powers of control over national processions are to be exercised, it seems that they must be exercised by some central authority in the possession of the necessary information on which a sound judgment could be based. / realise, however, that such a proposal would be very controversial, and it is for the Cabinet to decide whether the time is ripe for seeking powers to prevent future National Unemployed Marches of the kind of which we have had previous experience.(B) As regards local processions, generally speaking, the only statutory powers are powers to regulate the route of a procession; there is no specific power to prohibit a procession or to require it to disperse so long as it is orderly or is not an unlawful assembly. In London the power to regulate the route of a procession is exercised by the Commissioner of Police under Section 52 of the Metropolitan Police Act, 1839. Outside London similar powers are conferred by the Town Police Clauses Act, 1847, and in a few cases by local Acts, but these powers are exercisable by the local authority. In Scotland, wider powers are conferred by Section 395 of the Burgh Police (Scotland) Act, 1892, which empowers the Magistrates from time to time to make byelaws and issue notices and orders for the regulation of street traffic, including &quot; prohibiting or regulating public processions.&quot;The Chief Constables of England and Wales who were consulted are practically unanimous, with slight variations in the details of their proposals, in the desire that the police should be given power to prohibit processions which are likely to lead to a breach of the peace or to intimidate other persons, and to regulate the route of processions so as to prevent undue interference with traffic. They urge that these powers should be functions of the police and not of the magistrates or of the local authorities.Again, it is my view that Parliament would not be willing to confer on the police such wide powers of control over processions, at any rate not until experience has shown more clearly that such powers are essential in the public interests, and for the time being I think Ave must confine ourselves to proposing a more limited scheme of control.I would propose-     ....... ,(1) that Chief Officers of Police should be empowered by statute to prohibit any open-air meeting or demonstration which it may be proposed to hold in the immediate neighbourhood of any public offices (such as the offices of the local authority or the public assistance authorities) at a time when such office is open for the transaction of public business, and dlso to prohibit any procession for the
purpose of making a demonstration at stcch times and places. The basis of this proposal is that such meetings or processions, however peaceful may be the professions of the organisers, often have the effect of bringing undue pressure on local authorities or of causing interference with the transaction of public business.(2) that Chief Constables should also be empowered to prohibit any open-air meeting or demonstration oxutside premises where any rival meeting is being held, or in the immediate neighbourhood of any open-air rival meeting, and to prohibit any procession held for the purpose of demonstrating against a rival meeting, if in either case there is reason to apprehend that clashes between rival factions or breaches of the peace are likely to occur.(3) that Chief Constables should be empowered to prescribe the route of all processions. Under the Town Police Clauses Act, local authorities have certain powers to route processions for the purpose of avoiding obstruction of the thoroughfares. But if effective control is to be maintained, it is important that the power of routeing processions should be in the hands of the police.(4) that it shoxdd be a specific offence to be in possession of offensive weapons when taking part in any meeting or procession, and that there should be a power to arrest any person in possession of such weapons and to seize the weapons.IV. Organisation and Maintenance of Private Bodies for Political Purposes.In a memorandum which I submitted to the Cabinet in May last (CP. 144 (34)), I called the attention of my colleagues to the provocative effect of the wearing in streets and public places of uniforms denoting membership of a political organisation. In the view of the Commissioner of Police the wearing of political uniforms is one of the key points of the present situation, and he has long been urging that legislation should be passed prohibiting the wearing of such uniforms in sti&apos;eets and public places. Many European countries have found it necessary to adopt such measures. Absolute prohibition of the wearing of political uniforms has been enacted by Sweden, Denmark, Holland, Norway and Switzerland, while other countries, including Latvia, Finland, Austria and Czechoslovakia, have passed laws empowering the Executive to prohibit the wearing of particular uniforms.I agree with the Commissioner of Police that the wearing of political uniforms is a very important aspect of the problem, and that the prohibition of such uniforms would go a long way in the direction of putting an end to the militarisation of politics. This is not, however, the only aspect which requires consideration. It is not every Fascist who wears a uniform, and,, in fact; the British Union of Fascists includes among its ranks both uniformed and non-uniformed members. Provocative as they are, uniforms are only a symbol of a new and alien spirit which is entering into the politics of this country, and I have been giving careful consideration to the question whether some more searching remedy could not be devised, and preferably a remedy which would not be open to misrepresentation on the ground that it was aimed at one particular political party.The main mischief of the present situation seems to me to be the organisation of bodies of men who are drilled or trained to act in concert, under the orders of officers, and to enforce their purposes by methods of violence or intimidation. I recently received a Deputation representing the Trade Union Congress and the Parliamentary Labour Party, which, while objecting to the wearing of political uniforms, laid particular emphasis on the organisation by Sir Oswald Mosley of his political supporters on quasi-military lines, and on his introduction of foreign methods into the politics of this country. I was given to understand that the leaders of the Labour Party were finding great difficulty in restraining the impatience of their followers, who urged that Sir Oswald Mosley&apos;s show of force should be met by force and by an organisation on similar lines. One force inevitably leads to the formation of counter-forces, and I think the time has come when we must seriously tackle the question of the organisation of these private bodies, the existence of which constitutes a threat to; the maintenance of our free institutions,. and is the cause of repeated and serious outbreaks, of disorder. To allow private and iiTesponsible bodies of persons to make a display of organised force and to claim the right to take the law into their own hands js tantamount to an abdication of its functions by the Executive Authority.
I have studied with a great deal of interest the Act recently passed by the Swedish Riksdag to prevent the establishment of private defence corps and similar organisations in Sweden. That Act, which will come into force on the 1st August, 1934, makes it unlawful (a) &quot; to form or to take part in an organisation which, according to its declared purpose, is intended to serve as a defence corps for a political party or similar group, or which, in view of its structure, operations or activities, must be considered as intended to constitute an instrument of force of such a character as a body of troops or the police,&quot; (b) to arm, lease premises to, or support such an organisation with money or otherwise.The general view of the Chief Constables consulted is in favour of a proposal on these lines, and the Commissioner of Police is of opinion that such a provision affords a satisfactory line of approach. The principle underlying this Act has the advantage that it is of general application and would strike equally at the Defence Corps organised by the Communists as at the Fascists&apos; Defence Corps. Perhaps an even more important advantage is that such a proposal would be in keeping with the principle of the common law, as set out in F alsbury&apos;s Laws of England, under which &quot;a man may gather together his friends and servants to defend his own house against persons threatening to enter it unlawfully, but it is unlawful for him to assemble his friends for the defence of his person against those who threaten to beat him outside his house .... for then it is his duty to appeal to the protection of the law.&quot;I doubt, however, whether it would be practicable or would serve the purpose in view to propose legislation in this country on exactly the same lines as the Swedish law. What seems to be wanted is rather a provision aimed at the same evils namely, the formation of a body of persons who are drilled or trained physically for political purposes, including the purpose of performing functions ivhich properly belong to His Majesty&apos;s Forces or the police.For the purpose of our legal procedure it would probably be necessary to base any legislation directed against such organisations on as precise a definition as possible of the overt acts which are to be made illegal. Without attempting at this stage to formulate a precise definition, it seems to me that if proof can be adduced that any body of persons is, for a political purpose, organised on a military basis and is drilling its members, or equipping them with uniform, or subjecting them to discipline of a military or quasi-military character, or appointing officers with military titles and functions, there should be power to take proceedings against persons who organise and are responsible for such activities. Persons who aid and abet the organisers and persons Avho take part in such an organisation should also be liable to criminal proceedings.Summary of Recommendations.L--That the police should be given power of entry to public meetings held on private premises where the Chief Constable has reason to believe that disorder is likely to occur.- II. If the Cabinet decide that steps must be taken to prevent a repetition of Unemployed Marches, that the Secretary of State should be empowered to prohibit by order concentration of persons outside the areas in which they reside if he is satisfied that the concentration is likely to lead to serious disorder or the derangement of the public assistance administration.III. That Chief Constables be empowered to prohibit open air meetings and processions which are likely either (a) to interfere with the transaction of business by public authorities, or (b) to result in clashes with rival meetings, whether held indoor or outdoor.IV. That Chief Constables should be empowered to prescribe the route of processions.V. That it should be an offence to be in possession of offensive weapons when taking part in a meeting or procession.
VI. That it should be an offence for any person, in pursuit of a political object, to form any body of persons into an organisation of a military character, by drill, or by the use of uniforms, or by the use of other military methods. Persons who aid and abet the organisers and persons who take part in such an organisation should also be liable to criminal proceedings.If the Cabinet concur in these recommendations, I would propose (as I announced during the debate on the Home Office Vote) that the opportunity should be taken before the Summer Recess of discussing them with the leaders of the Opposition Parties with a view to seeing whether it is possible to reach some measure of agreement before legislation is proposed.J. G.Home Office, July 11, 1934.
SECRET.annex memorandum BY THE COMMISSIONER OF POLICE OF the metropolis.To the Home Secretary,I AM much exercised in my mind about the position arising out of the Fascist-Communist disturbances at Olympia on the 7th June, the debate in the House of Commons, the discussions in the Press and your own statement that no legis-lation could probably be introduced before the summer vacation.I feel that the subject is one of the highest importance and needs careful consideration in order that the peace of London may be preserved and to prevent the police from being put into a difficult position.The objects of this memorandum are (a) to set out the general position as I see it, (b) to indicate certain steps which could, in my opinion, still be taken to deal with the matter before the big Fascist meeting on the 5th August, and (c) to act as a warning of the serious position which may be expected to arise in connection with that meeting unless definite action is taken in advance.The discussions both in Parliament and the Press have gone beyond the original matter at issue (which really only concerned the rough treatment of the interrupters by the Fascists) and has ranged over the whole question of freedom of speech at political meetings generally, the functions of the police and stewards, the proper way of dealing with organised interruptions either in advance or when they occur, and the treatment of processions.On this question of freedom of speech there has been, as it seems to me, a good deal of confused thinking. Many people have talked and written of Freedom of Speech as if it meant freedom to give expression to any views without inter -ruption from political opponents, whereas the true meaning of the expression as I understand it is freedom from interference by Governments and authorities acting through the agency of police or otherwise.There is in this country very little restriction on the public expression of opinion, and the British tradition of allowing any man to give utterance to his views in public without official interference is generally called Freedom of Speech. But there has never been any right to speak without interruption, and if 5,000 people meet and all want to speak at the same time, that is no concern of the authorities. It only becomes their concern when the desire of several people to speak simultaneously leads to a breach of the peace, i.e., when people exchange blows instead of only words.The only concession to the natural desire of the organisers of a meeting to make themselves heard is the acknowledgment of the right of a Chairman of a meeting held on private premises to call upon an interrupter to withdraw and his power to have him removed if he declines to go.But even so the attitude of the authorities and the police remains one of detachment. They may go into a meeting if asked to do so by the organisers or if they have reason to believe that a breach of the peace is taking place, but beyond this it is no concern of theirs whether a political speaker succeeds in making himself heard or not. This is the business of the promoters of the meeting and their stewards.   .As I see it the matter has come to a head at the present time for one reason, and one reason only; and that is the existence of the Fascist organisation its declared policy and the conduct of its members.This is the only new feature of the situation. Meetings have been interrupted for years and it is a matter of opinion whether the interruptions that have been organised recently by Communists have or have not been more systematic and effective than those which took place at political meetings ten, twenty or thirty years ago. In any case, it is reasonably clear that these interruptions would not in themselves have given rise to serious difficulty but for the abnormal provocation provided by the existence of a private uniformed &quot; army&quot; adopting continental methods and ideas and avowedly attempting to usurp the functions of executive authority.I am convinced that until effective steps are taken to deal with this new feature of the situation, trouble will continue to arise, and there is always a
risk of a really serious disturbance involving numerous casualties occurring if further large Fascist demonstrations are held.I wrote to you on the 31st October, 1933, asking that steps should be taken to prohibit the wearing of uniform by Fascists or similar organisations. A good deal has happened since then, and the position has developed and become more serious, but I still regard this as the key-point which must be attacked before any real improvement can be secured. There is no doubt that the wearing of uniform is in itself provocative, and that this and other militaristic methods adopted by the Fascists are a great stimulus to Communism.Since the 1st May this year there have been many instances of Fascists being interfered with by Communists, but none of Communists being interrupted by Fascists. This will go on as long as the Fascists are allowed to go about in uniform, and if it is not stopped, then I say that clashes between police and Communists are inevitable, and they may develop into serious riots. There are always a large number of sightseers, and some may get injured. Questions in Parliament will follow and the police will be criticised, as it is not possible to prevent foolish things being done on such occasions.I am aware that when Commander Locker-Lampson asked leave to bring in a Bill into the House of Commons to prohibit the wearing of uniform for political purposes on the 16th May last, the proposal was negatived without a division, for reasons with which you are no doubt familiar. A good deal has happened since the 16th May, and my own view is still that the prohibition of uniforms would be quite an effective way of dealing with the matter. But I have considered various alternative methods, and my attention has just been drawn to the Bill recently passed by the Swedish Rikstag to prohibit the establishment of private defence corps.I have carefully examined a translation of the text of this measure, and I must say that it goes a long way to dispel the doubts which were previously in my mind as to the possibility of dealing with this question in a simple and direct way, that is to say, by making the organisation of anything in the nature of a private political army a clear offence against the law.The vital parts of this measure are the first two sections, which make it unlawful (a) to form or to take part in an organisation which, according to its declared purpose, is intended to serve as a defence corps for a political party or similar group, or which, in view of its structure, operations or activities, must be considered as intended to constitute an instrument of force of such a character as a body of troops or police, or (b) to arm, take premises for, or to contribute money to such an organisation.(A copy of the translation of the Bill, as received by the Foreign Office from Stockholm, is attached.)This Act seems to go right to the root of the matter, in a way which leaves no room for doubt, and in words which can hardly be objected to by any party which professes to support the theory that organised force must be restricted to the executive authority.I therefore ask you to give your earnest consideration to the possibility of introducing a measure on the lines of this Swedish law.If the Government is not prepared to accept this suggestion, then I would fall back on the alternative already put forward of making the wearing of uniform for political purposes illegal.I am fully convinced that the present difficulties arise primarily from the existence and methods of the Fascist party, and that the only really effective way of dealing with them is to put a stop to the present organisation and to prevent similar organisations from being formed in future. The patient may feel better for a time if you relieve his symptoms, but he won&apos;t be cured till you tackle the disease itself.This is my first point. The second and third points I wish to discuss are also important and will become more important if the Government is not prepared to deal with the Fascists at once on the lines suggested above.These points are : (2) as to police entering meetings) and(3) as to the treatment of processions consisting of people whose declared aim is to break up a meeting or, in other words, to act in a manner likely to provoke a breach of the peace.
As has been already stated, police are not now entitled to enter unless they are requested to do so or have reason to believe that a breach of the peace is actually taking place, and the stewarding of a meeting is the business Of the promoters.The Public Meetings Act of 1908 does not really help, as the police have no powers under it. All they can do in effect is to bluff persons who have acted, or are acting, in a disorderly manner, into giving their names and addresses (which may or may not be false) and pass them on to the organisers of the meeting for any action they may choose to take.The general principle, as I have explained at the beginning of this paper, is for the police to interfere as little as possible. This principle has stood the test of time pretty well and is, I feel, sound. But there may be new circumstances which would justify a departure from it, and I feel that such circumstances do in fact exist at the present time.Obviously it would be impossible at a general election, for instance for police to enter every meeting at which there might be trouble. The onus of running meetings, dealing with interruptions and, if necessary, ejecting the interrupters should remain the function of the organisers and their stewards. But if a situation arises such as that which arose at Olympia on the 7th June (and will probably occur again at the White City on the 5th August), in which a large body of hooligans is present with the declared intention of breaking up the meeting and the organisers are obviously out to &quot; have their blood,&quot; it should be within the discretion of the Chief Officer of Police to take the only step he can take to reduce the chances of a general battle and a long casualty list, i.e., to put a sufficient body of police in the hall itself, whether the organisers ask for them or not.It may be a matter of doubt, particularly in a very large meeting, how far the presence of police would be effective. They would have to be very careful to avoid allowing themselves to be used as stewards and to restrict themselves to dealing with unnecessary violence or fighting, and if a very large number of separate disturbances developed all over the hall, as occurred at Olympia, and the meeting got really out of hand, the only possible way of dealing with it would be to put a stop to it altogether. This would have to be done by directing the Chairman to withdraw his supporters. If he refused or failed to do so, the hall would have to be cleared by the police themselves. This action would very likely arouse the resentment of all parties and might in itself lead to general disorder and conflict with the police.Apart from this, I realise that it is putting a severe strain on individual police officers to place them in the position of having to decide on the proper line of action on the spur of the moment in the sort of atmosphere that arises on such occasions. Mistakes will undoubtedly be made occasionally and the action of police will be criticised from all sides.On the other hand, it might be found that the presence of police would have a restraining effect on those who had come with the definite intention either of creating disorder or of man-handling those who interrupted.I have considered this matter carefully, and I am of opinion that, although it is impossible to be certain what effect the presence of police would have, it is desirable that Chief Officers of Police should have power to introduce police into a private meeting without waiting for a request from the organisers or until a breach of the peace has actually occurred. I consider that this power should only be employed on rare occasions when information received suggests that there is a risk of really serious disorder occurring on a large scale.The only other change I have in mind as regards police entering meetings concerns the meetings at which the organisers themselves ask in advance for the assistance of police. In the past the attitude to such applications has been generally one of reluctance to accede to them unless rather exceptional circum-stances could be shown to exist. I propose to give directions that a somewhat more &apos;&apos; forthcoming &apos;&apos; attitude should be generally adopted.My third point relates to processions. I understand that it has up to now been regarded as impossible to deal with processions as unlawful assemblies, even though their declared object is such as to make a breach of the peace or perhaps a serious disturbance almost inevitable.The absurdity of police escorting bands of Communists to a meeting which it is common knowledge they intend to break up is sufficiently obvious, and if it is [10266] b 2
impossible under the law as it stands for police to deal with such processions as unlawful assemblies, then the sooner the law is altered the better.My own view is that I could, and should, take action without waiting for any amendment of the law. I cannot imagine that an action could be sustained against me in any court of law for disbanding processions in such circumstances. Injunctions are obviously of no use. The majority of Communists are of the hooligan type. They are not an organised body and acknowledge no leadership, and it would be necessary to take injunctions against each individual, which is obviously absurd.Although, as I have already said, the root cause of the trouble is, in my view, the existence of the uniformed private army under Sir Oswald Mosley, the methods of the Communists are obviously also a contributory element. Organised interruptions are no new thing, but when a body or party advertise their intention of breaking up a particular meeting and move to the &apos;&apos; attack &apos;&apos; in procession through the streets, it seems to me to be contrary to common sense to adopt the attitude that such processions must be allowed to proceed without interference.My suggestions therefore on these three points are : (1) that a Bill should be introduced on the Swedish lines to make private political armies illegal or (if this is regarded as impossible) to prohibit the wearing of uniform for political purposes by Fascists or any other similar bodies,(2) that police should be empowered to enter meetings when they consider it necessary, and(3) that processions of persons whose declared intention is to break up a political meeting should be disbanded.It now remains to consider what action should be taken as regards the meeting at the White City on the 5th August next.There is time before the date in question for legislation on the lines suggested in (1) and (2) above, and if the Government will agree to these steps, as well as to my proposal under head (3), the risk of serious disorder at the White City will, I feel convinced, be very greatly reduced, though not- by any means removed.The White City can hold 80,000 to 90,000 people, and there is no reason why the Fascists, with their supporters and others who will be attracted, should not reach this number or more.The following very significant items of information have reached me : (a) that a &quot; United Anti-Fascist League &quot; is being formed from members ofthe Communist Party, the Young Communist League, the Independent Labour Party, the Labour League of Youth, the &quot; Green Shirts &quot; and other similar organisations;(b) that a letter has been circulated to all Sub-Committees, &quot; cells,&quot; &amp;c,calling for the 1&apos; organisation of mass opposition to any attempts to hold Fascist meetings &apos;&apos;;(c) that the National Unemployed Workers&apos; Movement are forming a&quot;defence force&quot; to act as body-guards for interrupters at Fascist meetings;(d) that the eight days the 29th July to the 5th August are to be celebratedas a period of &apos;&apos; intense agitation against war and Fascism &apos;&apos;;(e) that an agitation is to be started amongst transport and cateringworkers with a view to bringing about a strike on the 5th August, so as to prevent food and drink from reaching the White City and to make it difficult for Fascist personnel to reach the meeting by lorry; (/) that counter-demonstrations  are  contemplated  in  Hyde  Park  and elsewhere at the same time as the White City meeting.The declared policy is to prevent the meeting from taking place, but, if this does not succeed, it is perfectly possible that 5,000 or 10,000 Communists or extreme Socialists may be present, as there is nothing to prevent them gaining admission, even if their processions are disbanded.It may not be particularly difficult to deal with the situation outside the meeting, though the employment of a large number of police will be necessary, and the steps which will be required may in themselves give rise to disorders.
As regards the inside of the building, I hope that steps may have by that time been taken on the lines recommended in the earlier part of this paper. If this has been done, the situation will, I am certain, be rendered very much less dangerous. But in any case, if the meeting is held, I should regard it as an occasion on which it would be right to introduce police, and, as action must be taken at once to provide for the contingency of such discretion not being given, I have already taken steps with the object of securing, if possible, that the owners of the White City will only let the hall to Sir Oswald Mosley on the express condition that he asks for the provision of a strong force of police inside and gives them every facility for preventing disorder and excesses.A large force of police will be necessary, and the instructions I would give to the officer in charge inside the building would be that he should direct his men to allow the stewards to carry out their duties and only interfere to prevent excesses or to stop fighting. The meeting should be allowed to proceed unless and until in his judgment disorders have become so numerous and widespread that it must be terminated. He will then call upon Sir Oswald Mosley to withdraw his Blackshirts. If they withdraw, the meeting will automatically come to an end. If not, the police will have to clear the hall.It is unquestionably a new element of danger in these meetings that by means of loud speakers one person can address a crowd of people five or six times as large as was previously possible. A big Fascist demonstration, with Communists and Socialists present, is, in the present state of public feeling, an explosive mixture of a highly dangerous kind, and if, as I gather, the view of the Government is that such meetings cannot be prohibited altogether, I must ask them to consider what the results are likely to be.I do not wish in any way to be an alarmist, but I have considered the position carefully and I say, with a full sense of my responsibility as Commissioner of Police, that, whatever steps may be taken to deal with the situation in advance or at the time, there is in my opinion a grave risk of really serious disorder developing, either in the form of fighting between the two parties or in the form of clashes between either or both parties and the police. I sincerely hope that this may turn out to be an unduly pessimistic forecast, but I feel it my duty to warn you of what I believe is likely to occur.TRENCHARD,Commissioner of Police of the Metropolis.July 2, 1934.Enclosure in Stockholm despatch No. 132 of May 18, 1934. (Translation.)Bill Prohibiting certain Organisations. IT is hereby ordained as follows : 1.It shall be.unlawful to form or to take part in an organisation which, according to its declared purpose, is intended to serve as a defence corps for a political party or similar group, or which, in view of its structure, operations or activities, must be considered as intended to constitute an instrument of force of such a character as a body of troops or police.This regulation shall not be applicable to an organisation authorised by the Crown, the object of which is to assist in the defence of the realm, nor to a reinforcement of the police force organised by the police authorities and under their direct leadership.2.It shall be unlawful for any person (1) on behalf of an organisation, which is prohibited in accordance with paragraph 1, to store or possess supplies of arms, ammunition, equip-ment or the like, or to distribute such supplies among members;(2) to lease a site or house or part thereof to such an organisation or for its operations; or(3) to support the organisations with money or otherwise.
3.Any person who violates this law shall be liable to a unit fine or imprison-ment, unless the offence is subject to a severer penalty under the Penal Code. In aggravating circumstances the offender may be sentenced to penal servitude for a term not exceeding one year.If the offender is an official, in the service of the State or a commune, this shall be deemed to be an aggravating circumstance, and, even if he is sentenced to a lesser penalty than penal servitude, he shall be liable to be dismissed from the service or to be suspended for a certain period.4.If any person has violated this law, any arms, ammunition, equipment or the like found in his possession shall be forfeited.5.Prosecutions for offences against this law shall be instituted at a court of justice by a public prosecutor.6.If a police officer discovers property which may reasonably be presumed to be forfeitable in accordance with this law, he shall confiscate it. If the officer himself is entitled to prosecute, it shall be incumbent on him,, if he finds that the confiscation should be sustained, to institute proceedings as soon as possible, or, where the owner of the property is not known or is not accessible, to report the confiscation to the county authorities within a month. If he is not entitled to prosecute, he shall forthwith notify the public prosecutor of the confiscation; the latter shall decide whether the confiscation should be sustained, and, if so, proceed in the manner just stated.If,, in cases where the owner of the property is accessible, proceedings are not instituted within a month from the date of confiscation, the latter shall not be proceeded with.7.If the county authorities have been notified of the confiscation of property the owner of which is not known or is not accessible, the said authorities, if they consider that the confiscation should be proceeded with, shall issue an order to the effect that the confiscation shall be sustained till further notice and publish the order in the local newspaper or newspapers in which public notices are usually inserted, together with a notice warning the owner that, unless he submits a written protest, at the same time giving his address, against the confiscation within a year and a day after the last publication of the order and notice, the confiscation will be sustained and the property forfeited.If a protest is submitted and the county authorities do not find reason to prosecute, the confiscation shall not be proceeded with.8.Property which has been confiscated shall be kept under lock and key and in a safe place.If property has been declared to be forfeited by a final judgment, or if it has been forfeited in accordance with 7, it shall be dealt with in the manner which the county authorities may determine.9.Fines imposed in pursuance of this law, as well as property which has been forfeited, shall go to the Crown. If the offender is unable to pay the fine, the penalty shall be enforced in accordance with the Penal Code.In case property is forfeited both in accordance with this law and in accordance with some other regulation, the provisions of this law shall be applicable with respect to the forfeiture.This law enters into force on the 1st August, 1934.o

</content>
</cab>
