<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/250/0 images: 110-111</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   July 1934.SECRET. Copy No.CP. 196 (34).CABINET.BOLIVIA-PARAGUAY ARMS EMBARGO.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.A CABINET decision is needed about this matter in view of the present position, which is as follows : 2. No licences have been issued for the export of war materials from this country to either Paraguay or Bolivia since the 9th May, and on the 4th June it was announced in the House of Commons that we were pressing at Geneva that the international embargo, which we had suggested, should be imposed at once unconditionally by all countries, and that in the meantime we were holding up licences. We have not interfered with the execution of a few uncompleted orders, for which export licences were issued before the 9th May, but the effect of our present action has been to prevent the acceptance of at least three orders which would have been placed in this country.3. The United States have taken similar action to ourselves, though by a rather different method. In virtue of a resolution of Congress, the President has prohibited the sale within the United States of war material destined for Bolivia or Paraguay, and there is no evidence that the prohibition is ineffective. If. therefore, new orders from Bolivia and Paraguay are given elsewhere, the United States are losing them as well as ourselves. Switzerland and Denmark have also taken action similar to ourselves.4. On the other hand, in reply to the invitation of the Committee of Three at Geneva to join in the embargo, Italy has made her acceptance conditional (a) on acceptance by Japan, and (b) on the exemption from the embargo of current contracts. Japan has declined to co-operate in what she regards as a League matter. She also added that she had not, in fact, been supplying these areas, though there is some reason to think that she is now canvassing for such orders. I should make it clear that His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, in replying to the League Committee, also answered that they would agree to the embargo if other countries also agreed, but, as stated in paragraph 2 above, we have, in fact, been withholding licences of late in the hope that general agreement and common action would be secured. A number of other countries have replied making their acceptance of the embargo conditional on its acceptance by other States invited by the League Committee, but it is not believed that any of the League States would insist on Japanese co-operation once Italy had been induced to change her present attitude.5. We have made every effort to induce the Italians to change their attitude, but have so far failed, and representations made at Tokyo also have been unsuccessful. We are now renewing our representations to Italy and are pressing France and the United States to take similar action at Rome.6. The question now has to be decided as to what should be done in the event of the failure of these representations. On the one hand, the immediate resumption on our part of the granting of licences would probably destroy what prospects there are of bringing into practical effect the general embargo.   It7519   [10333]
would throw us out of step with the United States, who would either announce that they were going on with their own embargo, though we had thrown up the sponge, or would declare that it was our action which had killed our own proposal. The scheme for an embargo is a very important part of recent League of Nations&apos; efforts, and it would certainly be the proper course to do our utmost to support it if we could. On the other hand, it is quite impossible that we should much longer expose our own manufacturers to disadvantage in a system which, in fact, failed to achieve its object because the embargo was not universally applied. We have always said that we could only restrain export of war materials from this country if other people did the same from their countries. We therefore have a perfectly good case for throwing the blame on others, where it ought to rest, and meeting the natural complaint of our own manufacturers that they have been victimised. Further, the maintenance of unilateral action on our part weakens the confidence of foreign countries in the ability of our manufacturers to supply them even when there is no objection on any ground to the shipment of arms to them, and the resultant loss may leave our manufacturers unable to main-tain the equipment for the supplies necessary to meet our own needs in time of emergency.7. But our difficulty is to determine when and how we should take any new step. My own feeling is that we shall suffer in many quarters if we throw up the sponge precipitately at this moment. I suggest that a statement should be made dealing frankly with the facts in Parliament in the course of a few days, recording our new representations to Italy and our invitation to France and the United States, but in this statement we should add that it is impossible to expose our manufacturers to prejudice when most foreign rivals are free to accept orders, and that we therefore give public notice that we shall have to abandon our own effort and renew the granting of licences very shortly, unless general agreement is reached. My own idea would be to set a time-limit such as the meeting of the League Council in September, with some saving provision in the event of matters getting worse in the interval.J. S.July 18, 1934.

</content>
</cab>
