<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/250/0 images: 586-590</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT.CABINET Copy No. ,&quot;219(34)THE FOREIGN TRADE OP THE COLONIAL EMPIRE Memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.1.     I fully sympathise with the Secretary of State for the Colonies in his desire (CP. 212 (34)) to combat the growing obstacles placed in the way of Colonial trade by foreign countries.     No small part of my time is spent in dealing with similar problems facing United Kingdom trade.2.     I agree with the Secretary of State that trade barriers even when imposed on an equitable basis are bad, but that when discrimination, in whatever form, is involved, it is far more dangerous and objectionable.3.    In cases of discrimination I shall always be ready (so far, of course, as treaty obligations permit) to bring the United Kingdom into action in defence of the Colonies, provided that action on our part has a reasonable chance of achieving the removal of the offending discrimination, and that action can be tafeen without disproportionate detriment to United Kingdom interests.     Powers for this purpose already exist under the Import Duties Act, 1932, and the Debts Clearing Office and Import Restrictions Act, 1934.4.     Apart, however, from the question of discrimination, the Colonial Secretary asks that in all trade negotiations with foreign countries we should ensure that in the case of Colonial products not of prime necessity (such as tea, cocoa, and fruits) foreign countries shall admit the maximum quantity of such goods compatible with their trade position.     he further suggests that it should be made plain that the United Kingdom will be as ready to use the-1-
bargaining power arising from her large purchases of foreign goods to force foreign countries to give favourable treatment of the kind required to Colonial goods as she is to use that power in the interests of the actual products of the United Kingdom.     As regards these suggestions the difficulty is that we are dealing with goods which admittedly can be dispensed with to a considerable extent and also with countries which have, ex hypothesi, decided to dispense with these goods on grounds of national economy.      I feel that it would place the United Kingdom in an invidious position if its negotiating power were used to force non-essential goods on reluctant purchasers, nor dees the qualification that the quantity of Colonial goods to be forced on these countries is to be compatible with their trade position afford much comfort.     If the import of the goods is already restricted we may be sure that this is so because in the opinion of the Government of the country concerned its trade (or financial) position so requires.     Y/e should therefore be in the position of either having to face a breach of commercial relations with the foreign country concerned or having to offer compensation to that country in the United Kingdom market in order that the market for non-essential Colonial produce should be improved.     Those industries which have contributed to concessions in order to secure benefits to other United Kingdom industries are even now excessively vocal and if we were to make further concessions their complaint would be still louder. They would not be mollified by our stating that the further concessions were made in order to help certain colonial producers.
5.    Nevertheless the Cabinet may care to know that during the trade negotiations of the last year and a half the interests of the Colonies have not been lost sight of.    By agreement between the Colonial Secretary and myself my Department has brought into the negotiations requests for favourable treatment of Colonial products.    These requests have to a considerable extent been granted by foreign countries and where they were refused the refusals were usually made on financial grounds (i.e.  that the exchequer of the country concerned could not afford the teriff reductions proposed), or on the, ground that the British Colonies were not principal suppliers of the goods in question.    I do not feel that we could have pressed our demands for concessions to the Colonies to the point of losing trade agreements which were satisfactory to the United Kingdom interests involved.6.  The question, in fact, how far the United   Kingdom power to put pressure on foreign countries should be used for the purpose of benefiting the Colonies is one on which I suggest no general and binding rule can be laid down for every particular case.    The Colonial Secretary, for instance, refers to the recently concluded Agreement relating to the exchange of goods between Germany and the Dutch East Indies and to its possible effect on the export of vegetable oils from the British Colonies to Germany. There is nothing in the published text of this agreement to suggest technical discrimination.    The question therefore becomes one of bargaining power.    In the case of Germany, however, whilst our imports from that country exceed our exports of domestic produce and manufactures by approximately  15 million a year, the Colonies had last year a favourable balance of trade with Germany, according
to German figures, of approximately  6 million a year ana. there are also financial payments due by Germany to the United Kingdom which will amount this year to approximately  6 million.    In addition our re-export trade to Germany is worth about  10 million a year, so that our bargaining power with Germany is none too strong.    That the position tff the Colonies has nevertheless been kept well in mind will be evident from the recommendation made in Sir Frederick Leith-Ross^ report of 28th September on therecent discussions with the German Government.    The proposal is that if there is to be a clearing with Germany the German Government should give an undertaking that they will not divert from normal channels orders for raw materials hitherto supplied through United Kingdom re-exports or from the Colonies (paragraph 13).    If we are able to secure this undertaking, in spite of the extremely favourable trade balance of the Colonial Empire with Germany, it will be due to the value which the German Government place on the sterling resources obtained by the sale of German goods in the United Kingdom market.7.    I would therefore suggest that the Cabinet should refrain from laying dorrn general principles to govern all future trade negotiations between the United Kingdom and foreign countries in this matter, and that it should be agreed.-That the present practice of consultation betv/een the Board of Trade and the Colonial Office in regard to negotiations with foreign countries should be continued, and that individual cases of foreign discrimination against Colonial products and possibilities of the increase of Colonial trade in
foreign countries should &quot;be considered on their merits;    the reconciliation between United Kingdom and Colonial interests (should these be in conflict) being left for adjustment between the Colonial Secretary and myself.(Intd. ) V.R.Board of Ti-a de,2nd. October3 1934.

</content>
</cab>
