<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 47-54</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC   MAJESTY&apos;S   GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1954SECRETC.C. i(54)3rd ConclusionsCABjnl&quot;s office record COPYCABINETCopy No.CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 18th January, 1954, at 3-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. the Earl alexander of Tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The   Right   Hon.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and Minis-ter for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.Gwilym   Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Lord De l&apos;isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air(Item 7).The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 6).The  Right  Hon.   Patrick  Buchan-Hepburn,     M.P.,     parliamentary secretary, Treasury.Mr. R.  Maudling, M.P., economic secretary, Treasury (Item 5).The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Supply (Items 5-6).Sir Lionel Heald, Q.C., M.P., Attorney-General (Item 7).Mr. John Boyd-Carpenter, M.P.,Financial Secretary, Treasury.Mr. Hugh Molson, M.P., joint parliamentary Secretary, Ministry ofTransport and Civil Aviation (items-6).Secretariat :The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. G. Mallaby.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.45567-1 b
contents minute no. subject      Parliament       .............     ......2      Housing Programme   ...3      Four-Power Meeting   ...      ...      ......4      Egypt     ......Defence Negotiations.5      East-West Trade       ...      ......6     Nationalised Industries ...      ......Report of Select Committee.7     Crichel Down   ......Disposal of land compulsorily&apos; bought for public purposes.Crichel Down Enquiry.8     Industrial Disputes     ...Electrical Contracting Industry.
1. The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken that week in the House of Commons.The Commonwealth Secretary said that in the House of lords on 20th January there would be discussion of United States military aid to Pakistan, on a Motion by Lord Stansgate. It was agreed thatthe Government spokesman should take the general line that therewas nothing unusual or unreasonable about this offer of Americanaid: many other countries, including India, had received financial or economic aid from the United States, and the aid offered to pakistan should not be regarded as in any way provocative to theSoviet Union. Discussion of the suggested military arrangements between Turkey and Pakistan should be avoided.2 The Minister of Housing said that the total number of new houses completed during 1953 was 318,750. This would be publicly announced in February.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Minister of Housing.3. . The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the foreign secretary on the general prospects for the Four-Power Meeting at berlin (C. (54) 13) and on the particular problem of security assurances(C. (54) 10).The Foreign Secretary said that the arrangements for themeeting-places in Berlin had now been agreed on a basis which was reasonably satisfactory; but the difficulties raised over this auguredill for the success of the Meeting. The French Foreign Minister had drawn attention to the danger that the Russians would be led tosuggest that in other matters the principle of parity between the Eastahd the West should be applied. Any such suggestion would haveto be firmly resisted.The major issue of the Meeting would be the means of holdingfree elections in Germany. The Soviet Foreign Minister would doubtless argue that the two German; Governments should be leftto arrange these without any outside assistance or supervision. TheForeign Secretary said that he had it in mind to lay before the meeting a constructive plan for the holding of these elections, which couldserve as the basis of a practical discussion with the Russians. If they refused to accept it, this would be a useful propaganda point if theMeeting broke down.The Russians would also exploit the failure of the arrangementsfor the exchange of prisoners in Korea as a pretext for urging anearly Five-Power Meeting. They Would argue that, the release ofprisoners by the United Nations Command, in spite of the Indianproposal that they should remain in captivity, was a breach of thearmistice, and that this had made it more unlikely that practicalresults could be achieved by the proposed Political Conference onKorea.The best that we could hope to secure from the Berlin meeting was a further demonstration Of the solidarity of the Western Powers,possibly an agreement that further technical work should be doneon the German and Austrian questions with a view to further meet-ings of the Foreign Ministers and, in private conversations withM. Molotov, a clearer indication of the real trend of Russian policy.The Prime Minister said that the Cabinet would wish to extend their good wishes for the Foreign Secretary&apos;s success in these difficult negotiations.-1 b 2
The Cabinet-Took note of C. (54) 10 and C. (54) 13 and of the statements made by the Foreign Secretary.Egypt. 4.   The Foreign Secretary said that the results of the recent(Previous meeting of the Arab League could not be gratifying to Egypt. BothReference: Iraq and Jordan had shown themselves hostile to any form ofC.C. (54) 2nd neutralism and had reaffirmed the need for alliances with WesternConclusions. Europe. The Egyptians might well be apprehensive of losing the minute 5.) effective leadership of the League and falling back into a positionDefence Q^ *ess importance, both politically and strategically.   At the sameNegotiations.    ^me t&apos;le mieTna^ position of the Egyptian Government might wellbe weakening.  Their suppression of the Moslem Brotherhood wasa sign of their isolation.The Prime Minister said that in these circumstances he wonderedif it would not be wise to set a time-limit to the defence negotiationswith Egypt by giving notice that after a certain date our offer wouldbe regarded as withdrawn.The Foreign Secretary said that this should certainly be con-sidered. On the other side it was arguable that we should gain by allowing the differences of view between Egypt and the other arab states to develop for a little longer. We should in any event wait for a few days to judge the effect of any representations which theUnited States Government might make to Egypt. He would haveopportunities in Berlin of discussing the whole problem with theUnited States Secretary of State.The Cabinet Took note of these statements.East/West 5.   The Cabinet had before them (i) a memorandum by theTrade. Foreign Secretary (C. (54) 18) proposing that we should suspend(Previous        attempts to secure United States agreement to a &quot; short list &quot; of goodsReference:      which on security grounds should not be exported to the Soviet blocC.C. (53) 67th   and should consider instead, first with the Americans and then in theConclusions.    Paris Group, the possibility of achieving substantial amendment of minute 6.)       the existing lists by considering particular items and removing thoseof less strategic importance; and (ii) a memorandum by the Presidentof the Board of Trade (C. (54) 19) suggesting that further steps shouldbe taken to secure agreement between Departments of the UnitedKingdom Government on the content of a &quot; short list&quot; and that afurther attempt should then be made to persuade the Americans toaccept it, in discussions between Ministers of the two countries.The Prime Minister said that increased trade with the Soviet blocwould mean, not only assistance to our exports, but greater possi-bilities for infiltration behind the Iron Curtain. Determined efforts should be made to persuade the United States Government to accepta new policy in this matter. The policy which he suggested was thatwe should in future deny to the Soviet bloc only goods of directmilitary value, and should no longer seek to prevent the export ofgoods which would help merely to strengthen their industrialeconomy. He considered that the existing lists should at once be revised on that basis.In discussion the following points were made:-(a) The United States Government had hitherto resisted thesubstitution for the present lists of a &quot; short list&quot; of the kind desired by the President of the Board of Trade. But it was known thatMr. Stassen, Director of the United States Foreign OperationsAdministration, was anxious to take positive steps towards increased
The Cabinet-(1) Instructed the Secretary of the Cabinet to arrange that officials of the Departments concerned should at oncerevise the existing list of goods whose export to the soviet bloc was at present subject to embargo, by applying theprinciple that we should in future deny to the Soviet bloconly goods of direct military value, and should presentwithin a week a report covering the original and revisedlists together with the arguments for and against the exclusion of any items still in dispute between departments.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister would appoint a ministerial Committee to consider the report of the officials and to submit recommendations upon it to theCabinet.(3) Agreed to resume their discussion of this question when thereport of this Ministerial Committee was available.nationalised industries.(previous reference:C.C.(52)40thConclusions,Minute 2.)Report of SelectCommittee.6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the lord president (C. (54) 15) regarding the final report of the House ofCommons Select Committee on Nationalised Industries (House ofCommons paper No. 235).The Lord President said that the Committee&apos;s main recommenda-tion was that a standing Select Committee should be appointed withthe duty of &quot; examining the reports and accounts of, and obtainingfurther information as to the general policy and practice of, the nationalised industries established by statute.&quot; The Home AffairsCommittee had favoured acceptance of this recommendation asoffering the best means of keeping Parliament informed about the affairs of the nationalised industries. The recommendation in thereport was for a standing Select Committee of the House of Commonsonly. The House of Lords had not yet considered the matter but,when they came to do so, were likely to press for a standing joint select Committee of both Houses.   The Lord President thereforetrade with the Soviet bloc, and it would be useful if he could beinvited to come to this country for further discussions on this subject with United Kingdom Ministers.(b) Before any discussions were held with Mr. Stassen, agree-ment should be reached between the Departments of the UnitedKingdom Government on the list of goods which we were willing tosee subjected to embargo. Up to date, there had been wide differences of opinion between the Departments concerned. The defence departments had been anxious to prevent the export to the soviet bloc of certain metals and some types of ships, which would be valuable to the development of the Soviet war potential.(c) Some of these interdepartmental differences would be resolved if Ministers gave fresh policy guidance on the lines suggestedby the Prime Minister. Though it might still be wise to prevent theexport of goods which would directly increase the industrial war potential of the Soviet bloc, there seemed now to be insufficientreason to frame the prohibited list with the object of hampering thegeneral development of the industrial economy of the Soviet union and its satellites. A change of policy on those lines would permit the export of electric generating plant and other engineering products for which there was a considerable Russian demand.(d) In considering the extension of trade with the Soviet bloc,regard should be paid to the criticisms made by Conservative leaders,when in opposition, against the action of the Labour Government in allowing the export to these countries of goods which might be of value to a potential enemy. Though there had been some changeof circumstances since then, the criticisms should be borne in mind.
 -hoped that, when the report was debated in the Commons, theGovernment spokesmen would keep open the possibility of appointing a Joint Committee of both Houses.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) The new Atomic Energy Corporation should not come within the scope of the standing Select Committee. Its exclusioncould be defended on the ground that its annual receipts were likelyfor a considerable time to come to be &quot;wholly or mainly derivedfrom monies provided by Parliament or advanced from theExchequer.&quot;(b) The Iron and Steel Board should similarly be excluded fromthe scope of the standing Select Committee. The steel industry wasin process of being de-nationalised.(c) The Minister of Fuel and Power said that he had felt boundto represent to the Home Affairs Committee the possible dangers of appointing a standing Select Committee on the nationalised industries.He did not, however, wish to press his earlier objections to the estab-lishment of such a body, particularly as it was now intended that itshould have much more restricted terms of reference.The Prime Minister, summing up the discussion, said that thebalance of advantage was clearly on the side of taking this occasion to increase the opportunities for Parliamentary scrutiny and discussionof the conduct of the nationalised industries. In the forthcoming debate in the House of Commons on the Select Committee&apos;s report,the Government should announce that they accepted the Select Com-mittee&apos;s recommendation in principle but wished to keep open thepossibility of a Joint Select Committee of both Houses as a point which merited further consideration in the light of the views expressedin both Houses.The Cabinet-(1) Endorsed the recommendations in paragraph 14 of C. (54) 15.(2) Agreed that the Atomic Energy Corporation and the Ironand Steel Board should be excluded from the scope of theproposed standing Select Committee on the nationalised industries.Crichel Down.(previous reference:C.C. (53) 81stConclusions,Minute 6.)Disposal of landcompulsorilybought for public purposes.7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the HomeSecretary (C. (54) 16) reporting the conclusions of a Committee whichhad investigated certain problems arising in connection with thedisposal of a former Air Ministry bombing range at Crichel Downin Dorset.The Cabinet first considered the recommendations bearing on thepolicy to be followed by the Government in disposing of land whichhad been compulsorily purchased but was no longer needed for public purposes. The most important recommendation under this headconcerned the disposal of agricultural land. It was proposed that infuture, where such land had been acquired by a Department otherwise than by public auction and was no longer needed by that department or immediately by another Department, the former owner or his successor in title, if he could be traced without undue difficulty,should be notified that it was proposed to sell the land (normally by public auction) and be given an opportunity of buying it in compe-tition with other prospective purchasers.
The Lord President said that he found himself in sympathy withthe views of the Agriculture Ministers as recorded in paragraph 8 ofC. (54) 16. A landowner whose land had been taken from him for apublic purpose by the use or threat of compulsory powers had, inhis view, a strong moral claim to be enabled to recover his land whenit was no longer genuinely required by the Government. This claimdid not seem to be adequately met by mere notification of the inten-tion to sell the land by auction or public tender. This would givethe former owner no special advantage. He should, of course, berequired to pay a fair price for the land but, subject to this, he wassurely entitled to a &quot; first refusal &quot; of it.In discussion some support was expressed for this view.The Lord Chancellor said, however, that there were formidableobjections to conceding a right of pre-emption to former owners,whether or not such a right were put on a statutory basis. In a matterof this kind the straightforward case would prove to be the exception,and any rule of general application would need to be made subjectto so many qualifications that it would be of doubtful value. Therewas the further consideration that, in most cases of this kind, theformer owner would have received at the time of the purchase of hisland not only a fair market price but, in addition, a sum, possiblysubstantial, for &quot; injurious affection.&quot; if, when the land was nolonger required by the Government, he was to be provided with a pre- -emptive opportunity to recover it, was it suggested that he shouldbe required to refund any such sum? In fact, a former owner mightwell do better on balance from bidding at public auction with theadvantage of any sum which he had received for &quot; injuriousaffection.&quot;The Home Secretary said that his Committee had approached the problem very largely with the same desire as the agriculture ministers and the Lord President but had been convinced that therewere overriding practical arguments against according former ownersany form of pre-emptive right or opportunity. Apart from theobjections mentioned by the Lord Chancellor, it would be very diffi-cuit to decide how far a pre-emptive right to recovery should pass to the heirs or assigns of the original owner. There was also a risk that pre-emptive sales would expose the Government to accusationsof according unduly favourable treatment to former owners and of failing to obtain the best possible price for public property.After further discussion it was suggested that further thoughtmight be given to the practical possibilities of according to former owners some form of. pre-emptive opportunity to recover land aquired from them compulsorily or under threat of compulsion but no longer required.The Cabinet-(1) Approved recommendations (2), (4) and (5), but deferred adecision upon recommendations (1) and (3), in Section of paragraph 19 of C. (54) 16.Crichel Down The Cabinet then considered the recommendations in C. (54) 16Enquiry.        regarding the forthcoming Enquiry into the Crichel Down case.The Home Secretary said that his Committee&apos;s recommendations were, briefly, that in this Enquiry the Government should not with-hold documents on grounds of Crown Privilege and, generally, should do all they could to facilitate the effective conduct of the Enquiry.There was general support for these recommendations.The Cabinet (2) Endorsed recommendations (6) to 8 in Section B of para-graph 19 of C. (54) 16.
industrial disputes.ElectricalContractingIndustry.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 2ndConclusions,Minute 2.)8. The Minister of Labour said that the response to the callby the Electrical Trades Union (E.T.U.) for a one-day strike whichwas taking place that day had been widespread in England and Walesbut only partial in Scotland, where relations between the two sidesin the industry were less bitter. The employers had asked for thedispute to be referred to arbitration; but, as the Union had made itclear that they would neither be represented before an arbitral bodynor abide by its decision, a reference to arbitration would yield no practical results and would damage still further the authority ofarbitral tribunals in wages disputes. In these circumstances there didnor appear to be any action which the Minister could profitably take in regard to the dispute for the time being. The Communist leadersof this Union had only lukewarm support from the members, whowould be reluctant to forgo for any length of time the high earningswhich they normally enjoyed. There appeared to be little support for the Union&apos;s attitude from the Press, from the public or fromresponsible opinion in Parliament. He would, of course, continue tokeep the situation under review.The Cabinet-Took note of this statement by the Minister of Labour.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,18th January, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
