<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 62-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF HER.   BRITANNIC MAJESTVS  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1954SECRET Copy No. 41C.C. (54) CABINET OFFICE :5th Conclusions RECORD copy cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1, on tuesday, 26th January, 1954, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair)The Most Hon. the Marquess of Salis-bury, Lord President of the council the Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations (Items 7-8).The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade(Items 1-5).The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. the Earl alexander of Tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The following were also present:The Right Hon. J. P. L. Thomas, M.P.,First Lord of the Admiralty (Item 6).The Right Hon. Lord De L&apos;Isle and dudley, Secretary of State for Air(Item 6).The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of State.The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 1-6).Mr. H. A. Watkinson, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Labourand National Service (Items 6-8).Lieut-General Sir Harold Redman,Vice-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff (Item 6).The Right Hon. Antony Head, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Items 5-6).The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Item 6).The Right Hon. Henry Hopkinson,M.P., Minister of State for colonial affairs (Item 6).Mr. John Boyd-Carpenter, M.P.,Financial Secretary, Treasury.Air Chief Marshal Sir William Dickson,Chief of Air Staff (Item 6).Rear-Admiral R. F. Elkins, assistant chief of Naval Staff (Item 6).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. G. Mallaby.45639-1
contents minute no. subject      Parliament       ......      ...2     The CabinetTimes of Meeting.3     Five-Power Meeting    ...      ...4      Suez Canal      ...      ...      ...Egyptian blockade of Israel.5       Egypt     .........Defence Negotiations.6      Middle east defence Policy.7      British Industries Fair ...8      Industrial Disputes     ......Provincial Bus-workers.Light Castings.Electrical Contractors.
oThe Cabinet 2.   The Prime Minister said that over the coming months various times of Ministers would need to be in attendance at Standing CommitteesMeeting. of the House of Commons which sat on Tuesday and Thursdaymorning, and he had been wondering whether it would not be con-venient on this account to revert to the pre-war practice of holdingone regular weekly meeting of the Cabinet on Wednesday morning.Additional meetings could be held, if required, on Monday orThursday afternoon.In discussion it was pointed out that the Scottish Grand Com-mittee of the House of Commons met on Wednesdays and that, whenbusiness became congested, the other Standing Committees might need to meet on three mornings of the week, including Wednesday.For the time being, however, the balance of advantage lay on the sideof holding the main Cabinet meeting on Wednesday morning.The Cabinet Agreed that during the next few weeks they would aim attransacting their weekly business at a regular meeting onWednesday morning, but invited Ministers to hold them-selves free to attend an additional meeting, if required, onMonday at 4 - 30 p.m.Five-Power 3.   The Prime Minister drew attention to a telegram from theMeeting. Foreign Secretary (Berlin telegram No. 12 of 25th January) suggesting that the United Kingdom Government should review their attitudetowards the proposal for a Five-Power Meeting on the problems ofthe Far East. It was clear that this proposal would be strongly pressed at the Berlin Meeting, and that the French would be embarrassed if their Western allies adopted a wholly unconstruetiveattitude towards it. The Foreign Secretary was now inclined to thinkthat it might be wise to accept the proposal, if the Americans couldbe persuaded to agree to it.The Prime Minister said that, if there was no prospect of making progress on Far Eastern questions either at Panmunjom or in theUnited Nations, it would be unreasonable to resist a proposal thatthese questions should be discussed at a Five-Power Meeting convenedfor that purpose. He hoped that the Foreign Secretary might be ableto bring the Americans round to this opinion.In discussion there was general agreement with the PrimeMinister^ view.The Cabinet-Took note that the Prime Minister would inform the foreign secretary that they were in full sympathy with his view thatit would be inexpedient to resist a proposal for a Five-power meeting confined to Far Eastern questions and beginning with Korea, and hoped that he might be able to persuade the United States Secretary of State to fall in with this view.Parliament. 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business which it was&quot; &quot; hoped to take in the House of Commons in the; following week.Progress would be made with some of the less controversial Bills inthe Governments legislative programme.
Suez Canal. 4.   TVze Prime Minister referred to the; Cabinet&apos;s discussion, of egyptian 21st January regarding the decision of .the^gyp^^.^government toblockade of intensify their blockade of Israel. He again stressed the importanceIsrael. of upholding the right of international passage through the Suez(Previous Canal and the Parliamentary advantages of putting this issue in the reference: forefront of our differences with Egypt.   He hoped, therefore, that.C. (54) 4th no effort would be spared in enlisting the support of leading maritimeConclusions, Powers for the protest which Israel wished to make in the SecurityMinute 6.) Council against the Egyptian decision to intensify the blockade.The Minister of State said that this matter would be taken up with other maritime Powers as soon as a favourable response had been secured to the representations already made to the United States----- Government.The Cabinet  : :tovTook note of the position.Egypt. 5.   The Prime Minister said that it was important that we shouldDefence retain the initiative in the current defence negotiations with Egypt.Negotiations. We were in some danger of giving the impression that we were(Previous allowing matters to drift. He would still like to be in a position to reference: set a time-limit after which the final proposals for a defence agreementC.C. (54) 3rd which we had put forward in October would be regarded as with-Conclusions, drawn. But, before this could be done, the Cabinet must have decidedMinute4.) on the alternative policy which they would,follow if no agreement were reached. Some time must also be allowed for the United StatesGovernment to make their final representations to the Egyptians.The Prime Minister suggested that a full review of the position should be made by the Cabinet at their next meeting, on the basisof a memorandum which could be circulated meanwhile by theMinister of State.The Cabinet-Agreed to discuss, at their next meeting, the various courses which would be open to the United Kingdom Governmentin the event of a breakdown in the current defence negotia-tions with Egypt.Middle East.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 2ndConclusions,Minute 6.)Defence Policy.6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the Ministerof Defence (C. (54) 26) seeking approval of the plan of re-deployment of British forces in the Middle East which had been outlined in theAppendix to C. (54) 9.The Minister of Defence said that a re-deployment plan wouldbe needed, whether we concluded a defence agreement with Egypt,or whether we decided to abandon negotiations and withdraw our forces in our own time. Under the plan recommended by the Chiefsof Staff we should, station an armoured brigade group less one armoured regiment in Libya, one armoured squadron possibly in-creased subsequently to one armoured regiment-in Jordan, and the headquarters of an armoured division and an infantry brigade groupwith some divisional troops in Cyprus. The Middle East air forces would be distributed between Habbaniya, Jordan, Cyprus and Aden.Once this re-deployment had been carried out, one division and oneparachute brigade would be free to return to the United kingdom to form a strategic reserve. It would be helpful if this plan couldbe approved now, though it would be clearly understood that it couldnot be put into operation without a further Cabinet decision.The Secretary of State for War said that he hoped the cabinet would also approve a maximum establishment of 2,500 for the joint
Headquarters in Cyprus, so that the works programme in Cypruscould go forward.In connexion with these proposals the Minister of Defence saidthat he was also considering the possibility that, if it were decidedto withdraw the British forces from the Canal Zone, the Middle EastHeadquarters would be moved to Cyprus in the early stages of thewithdrawal. This would be specially desirable if Anglo-Egyptianrelations deteriorated and serious disturbances were expected to takeplace in the Canal Zone. In reply to points made in this part of thediscussion, the Minister said that such a movement would have tobe so presented as to avoid any impression that the withdrawal wasbeing forced on us by the Egyptians. The move would not in any event take place until after the Government had announced their future policy for the defence of the Middle East.The Cabinet (1) Approved the re-deployment plan proposed by the Chiefs ofStaff, as set out in the Appendix to C. (54) 9, on the under-standing that no troops would be moved in accordancewith the plan without further reference to the Cabinet.(2) Approved a maximum establishment of 2,500 for the jointHeadquarters in Cyprus.7. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePresident of the Board of Trade (C. (54) 24) summarising thearguments for and against issuing invitations to the Chinese to visit the British Industries Fair in May, 1954.In a preliminary discussion the view was expressed that littlepractical advantage would be gained by the attendance of Chinesevisitors at the Fair. Their main interest would be in strategic materials which were subject to embargo. Moreover, the issue ofinvitations to the Chinese would provoke unfavourable comment inthe United States and might prejudice our chance of persuading theUnited States Government to adopt a more liberal policy towardstrade with the Soviet bloc.The Cabinet Agreed to resume discussion of C. (54) 24 at their next meeting, when the President of the Board of Trade would be present.8. The Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of Labour, said thatthere was a threat of a strike among the employees of municipal and private bus companies outside London. The municipal busmen hadbeen given an award of 4^. at arbitration, but the private companies had not so far gone to arbitration. In view of the award of 75. toLondon busmen and the similar offer which was likely to be made tothe railwaymen, it seemed certain that, unless something nearer 7s.were offered to the municipal and private busmen, there would be astrike. He was seeing both sides that day and he might be able to persuade them to reach a settlement. He hoped that it would not benecessary to appoint a court of enquiry, since this was a course whichwas best kept in reserve for more important disputes.
Cabinet Office, S.W. /.,26th January, 1954.Light Castings,      ; There was also a danger of a strike in the light castings industry,which would affect the building and engineering industries.   Hewould be able to report further on this later in the week.Electrical The guerrilla strikes in the electrical contracting industry wereContractors. continuing, but it would be wise to allow this situation to develop fora little longer. The strikers were not winning public sympathy, andwere not supported by responsible Trade Union leaders.The Cabinet-     &quot;&quot;      ;I took note of this statement by the Parliamentary Secretary,Ministry of Labour.

</content>
</cab>
