<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 132-135</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos; THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC  MAJESTY^  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1954SECRET cabinet OFFlOjfc Copy No.     4C.C. (54) RSCORD COPY13th conclusions cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held in the Prime Ministers Room,House of Commons, S.W.1, on Monday, 1st March, 1954, at 6-30 p.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime minister the Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor. ......The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P:,&apos;Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. the Earl alexander of Tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The Most Hon. the Marquess of Salis-bury, Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor   the   Home   Department   and minister for Welsh Affairs.The&apos; Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. Viscount Swtnton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.R, Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.Also present :The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. G Mallaby.
contents minute no- Subject page 1     Sudan    ...      ...      ...      ...      ... m2     Egypt    ......      ...      ...      ...      ...      ... m3     Kenya    ...      ...      ..&apos;....... jj2General China.4     Education       ...      ...      . i i-?Teachers&apos; Superannuation.5     armed forces  ...      ...      ......      ... U2Pay.
Sudan. 1.   The Foreign Secretary said that there had been a consider-(Previous able number of casualties in the riots provoked by General Neguib&apos;reference: arrival in Khartoum for the opening of the Sudan Parliament.  as c.C. (53) 75th a result, the opening of the Parliament had been postponed untilConclusions, 10th March and General Neguib would be returning to Cairo on the minute 7.) following day.The Prime Minister said that he hoped the Cabinet would giveserious consideration to the possibility of sending additional Britishtroops to Khartoum to preserve law and order and to ensure that theprogress of the Sudanese people to self-government was nothampered by outbreaks of violence. Two battalions and two R.A.F.squadrons could easily be sent in from the Canal Zone. They could arrive by air within a few days and could be quartered in some con-venient cantonment in the city. There would be no difficulty in keeping them supplied by air. Such a force would be in a positionto repel any attempted invasion from Egypt by cutting the railway line across the desert. The move would be a useful preliminary tothe re-deployment of our forces in the Canal Zone, and would give us control of one important strategic point. It would not interferewith the re-deployment of other forces to Cyprus, Jordan and Libyaas already planned. He recalled that he had made a similar proposalto the Foreign Secretary at the beginning of December, 1953.The Foreign Secretary undertook to examine this suggestionurgently. A relevant consideration would be the extent of theGovernor-Generals continuing responsibility for law and order, andhis duty, as the servant of both the Governments sharing the con^-dominium, to seek assistance when he needed it from both the UnitedKingdom and the Egyptian Government. It was unlikely that anyhostile move would be made from Egypt if British battalions were sent to Khartoum; but it was not to be assumed that their arrivalwould be welcomed by the Sudanese even by the Mahdi&apos;ssupporters or by those sections of the population which were favour-able to the British.The Foreign Secretary said that he would at once send a tele-gram to the Minister of State in Khartoum asking for his appreciation of the situation and suggesting that he should remain in Khartoumuntil the opening of the Sudanese Parliament on 10th March.The Cabinet (1) Took note that the Foreign Secretary would ask the Ministerof State for an appreciation of the situation in Khartoum.(2) Agreed to resume their discussion at a later meeting.Egypt. 2. The Foreign Secretary read to the Cabinet a telegram from(Previous Her Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Cairo (Cairo telegram No. 298) corn-Reference: men ting on the latest political developments in Egypt. GeneralC.C. (54) 9th NeguhVs resignation, and his subsequent reinstatement as PresidentConclusions, of an Egyptian Parliamentary Republic, had shaken the stability of minute 3.) the military regime in Egypt. The political prospects were uncertain.In discussion it was suggested that it might not be profitable tocontinue the attempt to conclude a defence agreement with sounstable a regime.The Cabinet took note of the Foreign Secretary^ statement.
Kenya. 3.   The Prime Minister read to the Cabinet a personal messageGeneral China, from the Colonial Secretary (Kenya telegram No. 185) reporting that(Previous        there were grounds for believing that General China, if his life was reference:      spared, might be able to secure the surrender of large numbers, ofC.C.(54)9th    Mau Mau rebels, not only in his own area, but throughout theConclusions,    country as a whole. If this was to be secured, it would be necessaryMinute 8.)       to state publicly that those who surrendered would not be prosecuted,even though they had been wanted for murder; but it would be made plain that they would be liable to be detained for prolonged periods.The Colonial Secretary sought authority to proceed with this plan andto make the necessary announcement, despite the strong criticism which this was likely to evoke among white settlers in Kenya.In discussion there was general agreement that the colonial secretary should be given full discretion to deal with this matter onthe lines proposed in his telegram.The Cabinet Invited the Prime Minister to inform the Colonial secretary that they fully supported the proposal made in his telegramfor securing, through the exercise of clemency in respect ofGeneral China, a widespread surrender of Mau Mau rebelsin Kenya.Education.Teachers&apos;Superannuation.(previous reference:C.C.(54)llthConclusions,Minute 4.)4. The Cabinet were informed that those Government sup-porters who were opposed to the Teachers&apos; Superannuation Bill were now formulating proposals for consideration by the Government.It was desirable that they should receive some guidance, before their proposals were submitted, and it had been suggested to them that theyshould for this purpose consult with the Leader of the House ofCommons and the Minister of Education. The Secretary of theNational Union of Teachers.had also been informed that, if he had any suggestions to put forward, he should communicate them to theMinister.The Prime Minister said that, although he would have preferred to avoid Parliamentary controversy on this question, he was inclined to think that, in the circumstances as they had now developed, theGovernments best course would be to show firmness in putting theBill through.The Chancellor of the Exchequer, while welcoming the PrimeMinisters support on the merits of the proposal, said that he would prefer to take a little longer to consider the best Parliamentary tacticsfor handling the situation.The Cabinet Agreed to resume this discussion at a later meeting.Armed Forces.        5.   The Cabinets attention was drawn to the forecasts whichPay- had been published in several newspapers of the impending(Previous announcement of increases in Service pay.   These suggested that reference: there had been some unauthorised disclosure of information to theC.C. (54) 9th Press.Conclusions,Minute 7.) The Cabinet Instructed the Secretary of the Cabinet to make enquiries into the apparent leakage of information to the Press aboutthe proposed increases in Service pay.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1,2nd March, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
