<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 265-270</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   May 1954SECRET Copy No. fj QcxTcsT) GAmht f omc34th Conclusions RECORD copy cabinet conclusions of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Thursday, 20th May, 1954, at 11 30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and Minis-ter for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. the Earl alexander of Tunis, Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Sir Thomas Dugdale,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.,Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. H. F. C. Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The   Right   Hon.   Gwilym   Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.Also present:The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury.Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.
contents minute no. subject      parliament       Education        ...      ...      ...Teachers&apos; Superannuation.3      Parliament       .........Expenses of Members.4      British Honduras       ...5      High Commission Territories ...6      Industrial Disputes     ...Railway Strike.
Parliament. 1.   The Cabinet were informed of the business to be taken inthe House of Commons in the following week.Education.Teachers&apos;Superannuation.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 33rdConclusions,Minute 5.)2. The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that in pursuance ofthe Cabinefs decision of 12th May he had considered, in consultationwith the Ministers directly concerned, in what terms the Governmentshould state their intentions regarding future Parliamentary pro-ceedings on the Teachers&apos; Superannuation Bill. They recommendedthat the statement should be made in the following terms:  &quot; At this period in the session most of our time must be devoted to the consideration of essential financial business andto the concluding stages of outstanding legislation. We shallthus be unable to proceed in the immediate future with the teachers&apos; Superannuation Bill which, as it stands, would take effect from 1st July this year.&quot; From the point of view of assuring the ultimate solvencyof the account a few months&apos; delay is not vital. But the house should realise that the longer the interval the greater will bethe deficiency which will have to be met. It is therefore theintention of the Government to carry through the Bill as soonas the pressure of the Parliamentary time-table permits, and inany case before the end of the present financial year.&quot;In discussion there was general agreement that the Governmentshould express their intention that the Bill should be passed into law before the end of the current financial year.The Cabinet (1) Approved the terms of the proposed statement, as set out above, subject to the omission of the word &quot; outstanding &quot;from the first sentence.(2) Invited the Lord Privy Seal to make an announcement inthese terms in the Statement on Business which he was tomake in the House of Commons later in the day.ParliamentExpenses ofMembers.(previous reference:.C.C. (54) 33rdConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Cabinet considered the handling of the further debate on the Report of the Select Committee on Members&apos; Expenses whichwas to be held in the House of Commons on 24th May.The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that a motion was likelyto be tabled by four Conservative and four Labour Members in thefollowing terms:  &quot; That this House, having considered the Report of theSelect Committee, is of opinion (a) that the recommendations in respect of pensions shouldbe referred to the Trustees of the Members&apos; fund for further consideration and report;(b) that Members&apos; allowances should be raised by  500 perannum;(c) that the Government should at an early date introduce legislation to improve the financial position of junior ministers.&quot;The Chancellor said that, as he saw it, the Government could take either of two alternative courses. First, their spokesman in the debate might recall that they had already expressed their disagree-ment with the Select Committee&apos;s recommendations, but go on to saythat, as they recognised that the matter was one for the House of46205-2 B 2
Commons to decide, they were willing that there should be a free vote on the all-Party motion. If there were a free vote on this motion,Ministers might think it right that they should abstain from voting,but Government supporters generally would be free to vote accordingto their personal judgment. The alternative course was to arrange forthe House to be provided with an alternative motion in the following terms:  &quot; That in the opinion of this House it is expedient to make provision for the reimbursement to hon. Members, within a limitcalculated at the rate of five hundred pounds for each financialyear, of expenses wholly, exclusively and necessarily incurred by them in the performance of their duties as such.&quot;This motion might be tabled as an amendment to the all-Partymotion, either on behalf of the Government or by private members on the Government side of the House. He understood that therewas even a possibility that the sponsors of the proposed all-Partymotion might be willing to accept this alternative motion in sub-stitution for their own. The practical effect of arrangements of thekind contemplated by the proposed alternative motion would differvery little from that of a direct increase of Members&apos; salaries by  500per annum. The Cabinet might consider, however, that, in view ofthe earlier statement in which the Government had rejected the SelectCommittee&apos;s recommendation for an increase of salary, those Govern-ment supporters who believed that some improvement should bemade in Members&apos; remuneration would find it less embarrassing tosupport a proposal for reimbursement of expenses.The Chief Whip said that, as a result of the debate on 13th May,there was now a wider acceptance among Government supporters of the need for some improvement in Members&apos; remuneration inthe interests of the efficiency of the House. There was still, how-ever, a strong body of opinion which was opposed to taking any action, at any rate in advance of the next General Election, although this opinion had received only limited expression in the debate. Itwas the view of the Whips that Government supporters generally would welcome the tabling of an alternative motion on the lines ofthat suggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Prime Minister said that he had been impressed by theadvantages of leaving the field to the proposed all-Party motion onwhich Government supporters could be left to decide for themselveshow they should vote, just as they would be free, if the motion were carried and put into effect, to decline to accept any increase in theirown remuneration. In his view the only circumstances in which government supporters could feel seriously aggrieved would be if those who were opposed to any improvement in Members&apos; remunera-tion were asked to comply with a Government whip in support of a motion proposing an improvement. It seemed clear that in any event the issue should be left for decision by a free vote of the House.Further discussion showed that there was general support for theprinciple of a free vote on&apos; this issue. The general view of the cabinet was also in favour of the tabling of an amendment to the all-Partymotion on the lines suggested by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.Although the arrangements contemplated by such a motion mightdiffer little in their financial effect from a direct increase in Members&apos;salaries, they were less open to misrepresentation in the country. Itwas agreed that the Government should not themselves table theproposed amendment and, further, that they might be placed in an embarrassing position if they tried to persuade the sponsors of theproposed all-Party motion to accept the amendment in substitution fortheir own. Steps should therefore be taken to arrange for the tablingof the proposed amendment by a suitable, private Member or members on the Government side of the House. In a free vote onthe amendment Ministers should be free to support it and should in
british honduras.(previous reference:CC. (54) 26thConclusions,Minute 5.)4. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the colonial secretary (C. (54) 164) reporting that in the elections held in british honduras on 28th April the People&apos;s United Party (P.U.P.) had gainedan overwhelming victory.The Colonial Secretary said that, in accordance with theannouncement which he had made with the Cabinet&apos;s approval on 7thApril, Ministers had now to consider whether they should proceedwith the re-constitution of the Executive Council which represented the second stage of constitutional development in British Honduras.The Governor was strongly in favour of proceeding with the re-constitution of the Executive Council, and thus giving the P.U.P. a chance to co-operate in working the new constitution. The colonial secretary said that on reflection he also favoured this course, pro-viding that the leaders of the PUT. were willing to assure theGovernor of their readiness to co-operate in working the constitution.This course had the advantage that, if it subsequently became necessary to revert to direct rule, this would not be done until practicalproof had been given that the P.U.P. had been unwilling to try tomake the constitution work.The Cabinet Approved the proposals put forward by the Colonial Secre-tary in C. (54) 164.no circumstances vote against it. If the amendment were defeated, a free vote should then be allowed on the all-Party motion and in that event Ministers ought probably to abstain from voting.The following further points were made in the course ofdiscussion:-(a) The Cabinet were informed that those Government sup-porters who were opposed to any improvement in Members&apos;remuneration had indicated that they would wish to have anopportunity to dissociate themselves by their votes, not only from thedecision in principle to make such an improvement, but also from any steps which might subsequently be necessary to put such an improve-ment into effect. If, however, the all-Party motion were carried, itwould be implemented by a Supplementary Estimate; and it would hardly be practicable to arrange that this should be put to the vote asa separate issue.(b) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he would soon bein a position to make proposals to his colleagues about the remunera-tion of Junior Ministers and, indeed, of Ministers generally. He wouldnot propose that more should be said on this subject in the forth-coming debate than that the Government intended to deal with it later in the year. The necessary legislation might be introduced in the summer or be deferred until the autumn.The Cabinet (1) Agreed that immediate steps should be taken to arrange forthe tabling by a private Member or Members on theGovernment side of the House of an amendment, in theterms proposed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, tothe expected all-Party motion on the Report of the SelectCommittee on Members&apos; Expenses.(2) Took note that the Prime Minister, the Chancellor of theExchequer and the Lord Privy Seal would attend a meet-ing of Government supporters to be held later that day atwhich the Governmenfs approach to the forthcomingfurther debate on the Select Committee&apos;s Report would be explained on the lines agreed in the Cabinet&apos;s discussion.
HighCommissionTerritories.(previous reference:CC. (54) 27thConclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the Common-wealth Secretary (C. (54) 165 and 168) reporting that the PrimeMinister of South Africa had now made a formal request that theUnited Kingdom Government should send a Minister to Pretoriain August to discuss his proposal for the transfer of the high commission Territories to the Union.The Commonwealth Secretary recommended that this request should be refused. He recommended that a negative reply shouldalso be given to any suggestion that a South African Minister should come to this country to discuss the transfer of the Territories. Itwas evident that he could not agree to Ministerial discussions of thisproposal when, with the Cabinefs authority, he had already statedpublicly that it was one which the United Kingdom Governmentcould not entertain. But, having made this position plain, he would propose to suggest to the South African High Commissioner inLondon that, so long as it was understood that this particular issue would not be pursued publicly for the time being, it might be useful if South African Ministers came to London later in the year for talks on political, economic and defence questions of common concern tothe two countries. He would make it clear however that, if such a visit took place, no public reference could be made to the possibility that the transfer of the Territories would be included among the subjects for discussion.The Cabinet Approved the proposals put forward by the commonwealth secretary in C. (54) 165 and 168, and authorised him tocommunicate accordingly with the South African HighCommissioner in London.industrial 6.   The Minister of Labour reported the latest developments inDisputes. the unofficial strike started by certain engine crews employed by railway Strike. British Railways in protest against the introduction of changes inthe operation of lodging turns. The Minister said that the strike had now spread to Cardiff, where the men had voted in favour of stopping work. This decision had not, however, been carried out byall the men concerned; and attempts to extend the strike to Swanseahad been unsuccessful. Thus, the dispute was confined to theWestern Region of British Railways; even in that Region it had not extended to all depots; and at the depots favouring strike actionquite a large proportion of the men concerned had remained atwork. The Union were continuing to advise their members against taking part in the strike.The Cabinet Took note of this statement by the Minister of Labour.Cabinet Office, S.W.1,20th May, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
