<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 411-419</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  July 1954SECRETCC. (54)53rd conclusions copy No.^cabinet conclusions of a meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.1,on Monday, 26th July, 1954, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Anthony Eden, M.P.,Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The Right Hon. Lord Simonds, LordChancellor.The Right Hon. R. A. Butler, M.P.Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Right Hon. H. F. C.M.P., Lord Privy Seal.Crookshank,The Right Hon. Oliver Lyttelton,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., MinisterNational Service.of Labour andThe Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. Sir David maxwell fyfe, Q.C., M.P., Secretary of Statefor the Home Department and minister for Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of lancaster and Minister of Materials.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. Florence Horsbrugh,M.P., Minister of Education.The   Right   Hon.   Gwilvm  Lloyd-George, M.P., Minister of Food.The Right Hon. the Earl De La Warr,Postmaster-General (Item 6).The following were also present:The Right Hon. Patrick Buchan-Hepburn, M.P., Parliamentary Secre-tary, Treasury (Items 1-4).Mr. Nigel Birch, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Defence(Item 5).Secretariat :
contents minute no. subject      China    ............Attack on British Aircraft.2      Washington Talks.............Anglo-Soviet Meeting.3      Atomic Energy ...      ......      ....... Weapons Programme.4     Egypt    ...... ...      ......Defence Negotiations.5     Cyprus   ...      ...6     Television Development       ...      ...Composition of Independent Television Authority.
China.Attack onBritishAircraft.1. The Foreign Secretary referred to the loss of a British civilairliner which had been shot down by fighter aircraft off Hainan on23rd July. It was clear that the fighters could only have come from china, and an immediate protest had been lodged with the chinese people&apos;s&apos;s Government. In reply to this protest the Chinese Govern-ment had now admitted responsibility, tendered apologies and offered to pay compensation. Their explanation was that the pilots of the fighter aircraft had mistaken the airliner for an aircraft belongingto the Chinese Nationalist Forces; and it seemed likely that this wasthe true explanation of the incident.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statement.Washington 2.   The Cabinet continued their discussion on the possibilityTalks of an Anglo-Soviet meeting. &quot;. ,   ,Anglo-Soviet The Cabinefs discussion and the conclusion reached are meeting. recorded separately.(previous reference: _^C.C. (54) 52nd ----Conclusions,Minute 3.)Atomic Energy.WeaponsProgramme.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 48thConclusions,Minute 2.)3. The Lord President invited the Cabinet to take a finaldecision on the question, which they had previously discussed on 7th and 8th July, whether our atomic weapons programme shouldbe so adjusted as to allow for the production of thermo-nuclearbombs in this country.After a short discussion, in which the main arguments developedat the two earlier meetings were again reviewed, the Cabinet agreedthat in order to preserve our position as a leading military Powerand to maintain our influence in world affairs it was necessary thatwe should possess a stock of the most up-to-date thermo-nuclear weapons. This would enable us to play our part in deterring a potential aggressor from embarking on major war.The point was again made that careful thought should be givento the publicity aspects of this decision. Was it likely that thedecision could be kept secret for any length of time? If not,Ministers should consider how the decision could best be justifiedto public opinion in this country and abroad.The Cabinet (1) Approved in principle the proposal that the current programme for the manufacture of atomic weapons inthis country should be so adjusted as to allow for theproduction of thermo-nuclear bombs.(2) Authorised the Lord President to proceed with his plans forthe production of thermo-nuclear bombs in this country.(3) Invited the Lord President to consider the publicity aspectsof this decision.Egypt. 4.   The Foreign Secretary said that the Secretary of State for defence War had now arrived in Cairo and had sent a message (CairoNegotiations. telegram No. 864) conveying his personal views on the handling(Previous of the defence negotiations with the Egyptian Government.   reference: suggested that he should accept a duration of seven years but shouldC.C. (54) 52nd press for improvement of the clause providing for consultation on conclusions, the arrangements to be made after the expiry of the agreement.  AsMinute 5.) regards the period allowed for the withdrawal of British troops from egypt, he suggested that he should aim at a period of 20 months.
Discussion showed that there was general support in the cabinet for the proposals put forward by the Secretary of State for War.In further discussion the following points were raised:  (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer again said that he was concerned at the probable cost of employing civilian contractors tomaintain the Base installations in the Canal Zone.The Cabinet recognised that it would not be practicable at thisstage to revert to the earlier proposal that these duties should beundertaken by military technicians, especially as this would reopen the question whether such troops should be allowed to wear uniform.They agreed, however, that the War Office should be urged to take all practicable steps to ensure that the arrangements made for maintaining the Base installations with civilian labour were aseconomical as possible.(h) The Cabinet were informed that those government supporters who were critical of the Governments policy towardsEgypt would probably succeed in finding an opportunity, beforeParliament rose for the summer recess, to propose in the House ofCommons that, if the heads of a defence agreement were settledduring the recess, Parliament should be specially convened to debate the matter. The Cabinet agreed that, if any statement had to bemade on this point before the recess, the Government spokesman should not go beyond the earlier undertaking that Parliament wouldbe given an opportunity to debate this matter before a new treaty was finally concluded. It should also be stated that, in the meantime,the Government would retain complete discretion to make such changes as circumstances warranted in the deployment of the Britishtroops now in the Canal Zone.The Cabinet-Invited the Foreign Secretary to authorise the Secretary ofState for War, in his conduct of the negotiations for a defence agreement with the Egyptian Government, to accept an agreement of seven-years&apos; duration, together withimproved provision for consultation on the arrangements tobe made after the expiry of the agreement, and to seekEgyptian acceptance of a period of 20 months for thewithdrawal of British troops from Egypt.5. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theColonial Secretary and the Minister of State (C. (54) 245) on future constitutional developments in Cyprus.The Colonial Secretary said that the Greek Government were now actively pressing their claim to Cyprus. They were canvassingsupport for the union of Cyprus with Greece and had stated that theywould raise this issue in the United Nations unless we agreed to enterinto discussions with them. The Chiefs of Staff considered it essential for strategic reasons that we should maintain full sovereignty overCyprus; and for these and other reasons we could not encourage theidea of self-determination, as opposed to self-government, for Cyprus.We had, however, to consider the presentation of our case in theUnited Nations and, with this in view, it was proposed that thereaffirmation of our intention to retain sovereignty over Cyprusshould be accompanied by an offer of constitutional changes whichwould mark a further stage in the development of self-governing institutions in the island. A public statement of our intentions would help to remove the doubts which at present existed in Cyprus, and the
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER URlTANNIC&quot;iMAJESTVS-GOVERNMENTThe circulation of this paper has been strictly limited.It is issued for the personal use of.....Of)., far..TOP secret copy No.rCABINETCONFIDENTIAL annex. C. (54) 53rd Conclusions ( A //vt*^(2 6th July, 1954 - 11.30 a. m.)Y/ASHING T ONTALKSProposedMeeting withiVI, Malenkov .(previous reference:C. C, (54) 52ndConclusions)THE PRIME MINISTER said that, since the Cabinet had last discussed on 23rd July his suggestion of a bi-latoral meeting with the Russians, the Soviet Government had publicly proposed anearly conference of all European Governments to consider theestablishment of a system of collective security in Europe.    Thiscreated a new situation, esjoccially as it was clear from its terms that the Soviet Note had been drawn up after the end of the geneva conference.    It was evident that the primary purpose of the SovietGovernment, in making this public proposal at this time, was to influence the attitude of the French Parliament in their forthcoming discussion of the Treaty for the establishment of the European-Defence Community.    But he was satisfied that he could not proceedwith his proposal for a bi-lateral meeting with the Russians while this suggestion of a much larger meeting of Foreign Ministers yvas&apos; being publicly canvassed.    He had therefore prepared a revised draft of his proposed message to M. Molotov indicating that thelarger meeting which the Soviet Government had now publicly -proposed did not seem to accord with the plan for an informal bi-lateral meeting which he had previously had in mind, and asking whether this Soviet proposal was intended to supersede his plan.He proposed to include in this revised message a reference to theplace and time which he had been intending to propose for a bi-lateral meeting:  this would have the advantage of making it clearthat he had not been prepared to attend a meeting in Moscow.    TheForeign Secretary had independently prepared an alternative draft,which was similar in substance though somewhat different inwording.    The Prime Minister read the two drafts to the Cabinet,He said that, if the Cabinet approved the substance of the proposedmessage, he could settle the wording in consultation with theForeign Secretary.In the course of a short discussion it was agreed that anew situation had been created by the publication of the Soviet note of 24th July.    Though it seemed unlikely that this Soviet proposal would be acceptable to the Governments of Western Europe, itsrecipients must be given time to consider it and the position must be reviewed again in the light of their response,.    Meanwhile,
it - as desirable that M. Molotov should be given to understandthat the Prime Minister&apos;s proposal for a bi*-lateral meeting wouldbe held in abeyance while the Soviet Note was under consideration the Cabinet -Took note that the Prime Minister would send a personal message to M, Molotov making it clearthat his proposal for a bi-lateral meeting withM. Malenkov must be regarded as held in abeyance pending the outcome of the soviet proposal of 24th July for a conference of all european Governments on the creation of asystem of collective security in Europe.Cabinet Office, S.V/.1.2 6th July, 1954.   &apos;
terms of the public statement which he proposed to make were setout in Annex 3 of C. (54) 245. If this became an issue in the united nations, we must expect criticism on the ground that we wereopposing self-determination; and the United States, in particular,might find it difficult to give us full public support. He proposedthat we should oppose the discussion of this question in the united nations, on the principle that the United Nations was not competent to intervene in the domestic affairs of Member States.The Foreign Secretary said that, in view of all the help whichwe had given in Greece during and immediately after the war, it wasdisappointing that the Greek Government should now be pressinga claim to Cyprus, which had not been under Greek rule in the past3,000 years. He supported the proposals put forward in C. (54) 245and suggested that special attention should be given to the need topresent our case effectively to the people of Cyprus in Press and radiopublicity. He thought that strategic considerations were perhapsover-stressed in the second paragraph of the proposed public statement in Annex 3 to C. (54) 245.The Cabinet (1) Endorsed the recommendations made in C. (54) 245 on future policy in Cyprus.(2) Authorised the Colonial Secretary to make an early statement in Parliament, defining our policy towardsCyprus on the lines of Annex 3 to C. (54) 245 subject toany amendments which the Foreign Secretary might wishto suggest.6. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by thePostmaster-General (C. (54) 244) submitting his recommendations onthe membership of the Independent Television Authority.The Postmaster-General said that it was important that theAuthority should be appointed and should set to work without delay.Unless it could hold its first meeting before the end of the summerthe Authority might not be able to initiate television programmesuntil towards the end of 1955. The Authority would have an advisory function, and the qualities required in the Chairman and members were tact and sound judgment rather than energy andadministrative ability. The nominations he had suggested were designed to provide a balanced composition within the statutory limit of ten members, and each of the members proposed had special experience which would be of value to the work of the Authority.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) Though the eventual function of the Authority v/ould beadvisory, its main task at the outset would be to inspire confidence in commercial circles in the future of an independent television programme and to ensure that money was forthcoming for thedevelopment of this service. It seemed doubtful whether an Authorityconstituted as proposed in C. (54) 244 would have sufficient influencefor these purposes.(b) For the chairmanship of the Authority an approach should in the first instance be made to Air Chief Marshal Sir William Elliot.(c) It would not be necessary to appoint a Chartered Accountantas a member of the Authority if arrangements were made for asuitable firm of Chartered Accountants to advise the Authority. the vacancy thus created on the Board should be offered to Sir CharlesColston, formerly Chairman of Hoovers Ltd.
(d) It was uncertain whether the Trades Union Congress would wish their movement to be represented on the Authority. their decision would be known later in the week. If it were adverse, othercandidates should be considered in preference to Mr. Crawley or mr. Hardman.The Cabinet-Invited the Postmaster-General to reconsider the proposals in C. (54) 244 in the light of the Cabinefs discussion and tosubmit for the Prime Ministers approval revised proposalsfor the membership of the Independent television authority.Cabinet Office, S.W. 1..26th July, 1954.
(d) It was uncertain whether the Trades Union Congress would wish their movement to be represented on the Authority. their decision Would be known later in the week. If it were adverse, othercandidates should be considered in preference to Mr. Crawley or mr. Hardman.The Cabinet Invited the Postmaster-General to reconsider the proposals in C. (54) 244 in the light of the Cabinefs discussion and tosubmit for the Prime Ministers approval revised proposalsfor the membership of the Independent television authority.Cabinet Office, S.W.L26th July, 1954.

</content>
</cab>
