<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/27/0 images: 613-619</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   December 1954SECRET Copy No.CC. (54)86th ConclusionsCABINET4CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Tuesday, 14th December, 1954, at 11-30 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. Sir Winston Churchill, M.P., Prime Minister.The Right Hon. Sir Anthony Eden,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. Viscount Kilmuir,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. H. F. C Crookshank,M.P., Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. Gwilym Lloyd-George, M.P., Secretary of State forthe Home Department and Ministerfor Welsh Affairs.The Right Hon. James Stuart, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Sir Walter Monckton,Q.C., M.P., Minister of Labour and national Service.The Right Hon. Peter Thorneycroft,M.P., President of the Board ofTrade.The Right Hon. Osbert Peake, M.P.,Minister of Pensions and national insurance.The Most Hon. the Marquess of salisbury, -Lord President of theCouncil.The Right Hon. Viscount Woolton,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Harold Macmillan,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Swinton,Secretary of State for commonwealth relations.The Right Hon. A. T. Lennox-Boyd,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. Duncan Sandys, M.P.,Minister of Housing and LocalGovernment.The Right Hon. D. Heathcoat Amory,M.P., Minister of Agriculture andFisheries and Minister of Food.The Right Hon. Sir David Eccles, M.P.,Minister of Education.The following were also present:The Right Hon. Selwyn Lloyd, Q.C.,M.P., Minister of Supply (Item 4).The Right Hon. John Boyd-Carpenter,M.P., Minister of Transport and CivilAviation (Items 4-6).The Right Hon. Geoffrey Lloyd, M.P.,Minister of Fuel and Power (Item 4).Mr. Henry Brooke, M.P., FinancialSecretary, Treasury (Items 4-6).Secretariat:The Right Hon. Sir Norman Brook.Mr. R. M. J. Harris.Mr. K. L. Stock.
Contents:minute no. Subject page 1      Foreign Affairs.........      ...      ...      ...      ...      3Saar,Formosa.Atomic Energy ......      .....;      ...      ...      5Weapons Programme.Industrial Disputes     ..................    .5Railways.House of Commons............      ...      ...      7Redistribution of Seats.Tariff Policy     ....................:.      7Japan and the G.A.T.T.
Foreign. Attains.Saar.(previous reference:CC. (54) 7i)th conclusions,Minute 2.)Formosa.(previous reference:CC. (54) 84lhConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Foreign Secretary said that the French Prime minister had prepared; for his Parliament a report on the negotiations aboutthe Saar which was inaccurate in various respects, including itsreferences to the attitude of the United Kingdom and United states government towards this question. There was a real danger thatthe publication of this report might prevent the ratification of theLondon Agreements. The United States Government might feel obliged to repudiate the statement which it contained of their attitude on the Saar. And the Federal German Chancellor had said that he might be unable to put the London Agreements forward for theapproval of the Bundestag on 15th December, as he had planned todo, if the attitude of the French Government remained unchanged.The Foreign Secretary said that he was considering what action could be taken to restore the situation. It might be wise&apos; to suggestthat a meeting of the four Powers primarily concerned should beheld in Bonn within the next few days.The Foreign Secretary said that, after reviewing the reports received from British representatives in Washington, New York andPeking, lie was satisfied that it would be inexpedient to proceed atpresent with the project for raising the question of Quemoy in theSecurity Council. It was evident that there was now no prospectof persuading the Chinese Communists to join in discussions in theSecurity Council; and it seemed possible that such discussions, insteadof restraining them, might have the effect of inciting them to further efforts to obtain possession of the coastal islands. The foreign secretary proposed to press this point of view in the discussions whichhe would be holding with the United States Secretary of State at theforthcoming meeting of the North Atlantic Council in Paris.The Foreign Secretary also referred to statements on Formosawhich had been made by the Minister of State for Foreign Affairs,Mr. Nutting, in an interview on television in the United States. - Itwas unfortunate that Mr. Nutting should have compared a possibleaggression against Formosa with the aggression against Korea in1950: the two were not in fact comparable, since we had notrecognised the Chinese Nationalist Government. So long as we didnot recognise that Government, it was open to argument whether, as members of the United Nations, we had any obligation to assist themto repel an act of aggression. He hoped to be able to make it clear,in a statement in Parliament on the following day, that it had beenMr. Nutting&apos;s purpose to make it plain that any obligations whichwe might have in this matter arose solely from the fact that theChinese Nationalist Government still represented China in theUnited Nations.The Cabinet Took note of the Foreign Secretary&apos;s statements.

Atomic Energy.WeaponsProgramme.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 53 rdConclusions,Minute 3.)3. The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by theMinister of Defence (C. (54) 389) on the effects of thermo-nuclear weapons.In discussion the Cabinet were informed that the B.B.C. were planning to produce early in the New Year a broadcast programme on the hydrogen bomb. The Chairman of the Atomic energy authority had spoken about this to the Director-General of theB.B.C., who had undertaken to make himself personally responsiblefor ensuring that those planning the programme consulted reputablescientists (who would be in touch with scientists employed by theAuthority) and that the programme would be free of any politicalbias. Was it enough to leave this matter to the discretion of theDirector-General of the B.B.C.?It was the general view of the Cabinet that further guidance onthis matter should be given to the B.B.C. by a responsible Minister.It was important, for the reasons indicated in C. (54) 389 (and alsoin paragraph 7 of C. (54) 390 see preceding Minute), that theGovernment should themselves retain control over the form and timing of publicity on the effects of thermo-nuclear weapons. Itwas contrary to the public interest that the B.B.C. should enterprematurely upon this field before the Government had completed their plans for dealing with the problem and handling its presentation to the public.The Cabinet-(1) Took note of the memorandum by the Minister of Defence(C. (54) 389) on the effects of thermo-nuclear weapons.- - (2) Took note that the Prime Minister would arrange for furtherguidance to be given to the B.B.C. on the handling ofinformation relating to thermo-nuclear weapons in broad-cast or television programmes.industrial 4.  The Cabinet were informed of the results of the meetingDisputes. which the Minister of Transport had held on the previous day withRailways. representatives of the National Union of Railwaymen (N.U.R.).(Previous The Minister had urged therri to resume their wages negotiationReference: with the Transport Commission. ThisUhey were unwilling to do, as c.C. (54) 85th it had been made plain to them that the Commission could not affordConclusions, any substantial wage increases, but they had not finally declinedMinute 1.) to resume negotiations. They had, however, pressed their suggestion
that the Government should put the Commission in a financialposition to pay better wages. The Minister had told them that hewould consider this request in consultation with his colleagues, butthat a Government subsidy could not in any circumstances beconsidered. Though they had made no explicit reference to thepossibility of a strike, the Minister had little doubt that, unless they were given an early reply holding out some hope that the Trans-port Commission would be able to offer a substantial increase in wages, they would call a strike as soon as they thought it expedient to do so.The Minister of Labour suggested that, now that the attitudeof the N.U.R. was known, he and the Minister of Transport shouldtogether discuss the position with the Chairman of the transport commission. He himself doubted whether the N.U.R. couldsubstantiate a claim that railwaymen in the lower grades were substantially less well paid than persons in comparable occupationsin other industries. He was anxious to ascertain the views of theTransport Commission on this point and, in particular, to know whatwas in the Chairman&apos;s mind when he had told representatives of theN.U.R. in August that he did not regard the wage rates then underdiscussion as ideal or final. It should be clearly established whetherthe Commission considered the existing wage rates to be adequateor whether they thought it would be reasonable to pay higher ratesbut felt that the financial position of the railways precluded them from doing so. Even in a nationalised service wages could not befixed without regard to what the undertaking could afford to pay.There was no doubt that this would be among the points which wouldbe taken into account by the tribunal if the workers took their claimto arbitration.In discussion the following points were made:  (a) It seemed unlikely that the Chairman of the transport commission would be willing to offer any substantial increase in wage rates unless the Government were ready to share with him theresponsibility for accepting a larger deficit on the current operationof the railways. Ministers should realise that, if they assumed this responsibility, the Government would thereby become, for the first time, parties to a wage negotiation in a nationalised undertaking.(b) It was still open to the railwaymen to take their claim to arbitration. Would it be wise for the Government to offer to helpa nationalised industry to meet a wages claim on which the workers were unwilling to go to arbitration?(c) The railwaymen now had less claim to public sympathy thanthey had on the occasion of the last award a year ago. There wasno doubt then that the wages of the lowest grades comparedunfavourably with those of corresponding grades in other industries;and the men had offered to co-operate in measures to secure increasedlabour efficiency on the railways. Now there was much less disparity between railway wages and wages in other industries, and the men had failed to give their full co-operation in measures to increaselabour efficiency.The Cabinet-(1) Took note that the Minister of Labour and the Minister ofTransport would discuss the position further with theChairman of the Transport Commission.(2) Agreed to resume their consideration of this question at alater meeting.
House ofCommons.redistribution of Seats.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 84 th conclusions,Minute 4.)5. The Lord Privy Seal said that he had discussed with theHome Secretary, the Secretary of State for Scotland and the chief whip the handling of the Parliamentary proceedings on therecommendations of the Boundary Commissions and, in particular, ofthose recommendations which contemplated changes in the boundaries of Parliamentary constituencies which were not desired by any political Party. They had agreed to recommend to theCabinet that the Commissions&apos; proposals should be accepted as awhole and that the Government Whip should be used in support ofall the necessary Orders. At the same time they suggested that itshould be indicated privately to Government supporters that noobjection would be raised to the abstention of any individual member in a division upon an Order giving effect to proposals which affectedadversely his political interests in his own constituency.There was general support in the Cabinet for the Lord privy seal&apos;s recommendation.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Government should invite Parliament toaccept all the Boundary Commissions&apos; recommendations,but that individual Government supporters should beallowed to abstain in divisions upon Orders which adversely affected their interests in their own constituencies.6. The Cabinet had before them memoranda by the foreign secretary (C. (54) 391) and the President of the Board of Trade(C. (54) 392) about the proposed accession of Japan to the GeneralAgreement on Tariffs and Trade (G.A.T.T.).The Foreign Secretary said that the Japanese Government whichhad rejected the proposals approved by the Cabinet on 20th Octoberhad now been replaced by a new Caretaker Government which wouldbe more difficult to deal with than its predecessor. The newJapanese Prime Minister was inclined to be anti-American in hisoutlook, and this made it even more important that we shouldpreserve, and indeed develop, such influence as we could exert in japan. He would not press at this stage for a decision that weshould in no circumstances invoke Article XXXV of the G.A.T.T.against Japan, but he urged that the Departments concerned shouldbe invited to explore thoroughly all possible alternative means of protecting British interests against Japanese competition within the framework of the G.A.T.T.The President of the Board of Trade supported the foreign secretary&apos;s proposal, and suggested that the Departments should beasked to set out in their report the probable consequences of Japan&apos;saccession to the G.A.T.T., and to consider the scope for concludingwith the Japanese Government a commercial treaty, for which theyhad already asked.The Cabinet Invited the President of the Board of Trade to arrange for officials of the Treasury, Foreign Office, commonwealth relations Office, Colonial Office and Board of Trade to review and report on the implications of Japan&apos;s accession to the G.A.T.T. in present circumstances, and to suggestwhat alternative courses would be open to the UnitedKingdom Government in the event of Japan&apos;s accession tothe Agreement.Tariff Policy.Japan and theG.A.T.T.(previous reference:C.C. (54) 68thConclusions,Minute 8.)

</content>
</cab>
