<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/66/31 images: 206-215</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet. *June 1945.SECRET Copy No.CP. (45) 31.11th June, 1945.CABINET.DOMINION WOOL AGREEMENTS.Memorandum by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the Minister of Supplyand the Parliamentary Under-Secretary of State for the Dominions.1. At their meeting on the 3rd October, 1944, the Lord presidents committee (L.P. (44) 46th Conclusions, Minute 1) approved proposals for negotiations with the Dominion Governments concerned, with a view to reaching an arrangement for disposing of the stock of wool equal to about two years&apos;&quot;consumption which has accumulated in the ownership of the United kingdom as a result of the wartime agreements with Australia, New Zealand and SouthAfrica for the purchase of their entire clips. The basis upon which it was hoped that such an arrangement might be negotiated with the Dominions was : (i) That the United Kingdom should be relieved from July 1945 (the endof the wool year) of their obligation to purchase more Dominion woolthan the United Kingdom manufacturers required to buy for theirown use; and(ii) that the disposal of our existing surplus and of the surpluses whichwould arise in current Dominion clips during the time of disposalshould be undertaken by a Joint Organisation on terms which involved the Dominions in a share in financing the new surpluses and in theloss on the whole transaction.2. The Dominion Governments concerned accepted the invitation of theUnited Kingdom Government for a conference of officials and experts to make recommendations to the respective Governments. The Conference met in london from the 16th April to the 28th May, 1945, and has unanimously agreed uponthe attached Report and Recommendations. The Recommendations which aregenerally in line with the original proposals of the United Kingdom Govern-ment may be summarised as follows :  (i) Each Dominion Government will acquire as from the end of July 1945an equal share with the United Kingdom Government in the accumu-lated surplus of its wool. The shares of the three Dominions after allowing for the accumulated profits on past sales, which will beretained by the United Kingdom amount to about  70 million..Each Dominion Government will pay the United Kingdom Govern-ment for its share in the initial stock over a period of 4 years, partlyout of its share in the proceeds of future sales during that period andpartly in cash.(ii) The disposal of the stock will be undertaken by a Joint Organisation (inthe form of a company registered under the Companies Acts) repre-senting the four Governments, concurrently with the sale of currentclips by growers. The directors of the Joint Organisation will beappointed four by the United Kingdom Government, two by theAustralian Government, and one each by the Governments of NewZealand and South Africa, with an independent chairman chosen bythe four Governments in agreement. The disposal of the surplusalongside current clips will for technical reasons involve the buying-inby the Organisation of unsold portions of the current clips, and the[30054] b
United Kingdom Government will share equally with the dominions in the financing of wool so brought in. The costs of holding andselling stock (excluding interest) will be met as to half from a levycollected from growers and as to half out of proceeds, and the UnitedKingdom Government will thus bear only one-quarter of these costs.The Governments will share equally in any ultimate profit or loss.(iii) As soon as practicable the sale by auction both of new clips and of thestock held by the Joint Organisation will be resumed, prices being kept stable by the readiness of the Joint Organisation to buy in at areserve price any wool not sold to other buyers. The level of reserveprices will be fixed by the four Governments from time to time inaccordance with general world conditions and the need to expandconsumption. The general resumption of auctions in the Dominionsis not, however, immediately practicable, and the clips of the 1945-46season will be financed and taken up by the United Kingdom Govern-ment by the present method and at the present prices on behalf ofthe Joint Organisation.(iv) The existing Agreements will be terminated at the end of July 1945and replaced by the Agreement now contemplated. The operation ofthe scheme will be reviewed between the four Governments at theend of 5 years in the light of experience.It will be observed that the proposals contemplate a complete partnershipon equal terms between the United Kingdom and the Dominions, under whichthe United Kingdom Government gains relief from the heavy burden of theexisting surplus and of its obligation to continue buying the whole clips until a year after the Japanese war, and on the other hand accepts the obligation to share in financing any wool from current clips which it may be necessary forthe Joint Organisation to buy in during the period of disposal of the stock.The Dominions will assure to the United Kingdom the repayment of one-halfof the present value of the stock over a period of four years, will provide three-quarters of the carrying costs of it, and will meet one-half of any final loss.The success of the scheme depends upon the encouragement of an increased consumption of wool over the amount of current clips, to which the organisation will have to pay close attention, and the Conference estimates that the periodof disposal may be 12 or 13 years. The attraction of the scheme to theDominion Governments and growers lies in the partnership with the UnitedKingdom Government for a future period, and in the assurance of a degree of stability in prices, and consequent relief from the overhanging cloud of thestock accumulated during the war.There was complete unanimity and strong.approval of the recommendations in the Conference, which included representatives of the Dominion growers.The recommendations are now being submitted to the Dominion governments for their consideration, and it is hoped that an early decision will be reached.4. The recommendations appear to offer the best basis for solving in partnership and goodwill a difficult problem which otherwise carried consider-able danger of friction. The financial terms, while fair to all parties, containconsiderable advantages for this country. We suggest, therefore, that therecommendations should be accepted by the United Kingdom Government.5. The question was raised at the Lord President&apos;s Committee in theautumn (L.P. (44) 44th Conclusion, Minute 5) of consulting the other principalconsuming countries, particularly the United States, and the Chancellor of theExchequer then said that it was in mind that other countries should be informedif and when it seemed likely that agreement would be&apos; reached with theDominions. While the present proposals arise out of a particular situation,in which the financial bur-den of a heavy stock rests upon the United Kingdom(now to be shared with the Dominions concerned), there is nothing in the schemewhich would prevent development later on in conjunction with consuming countries and other producing countries along the general lines envisaged for &quot; commodity policy.&quot; It is indeed proposed in the present scheme that the InternationalWool Textile Organisation, which represents the European manufacturers,should be Invited to nominate representatives to form, along with representatives from other major consuming countries, including the United States, a Committeeto act in a consultative capacity to the Joint Organisation from the point ofview of wool consumers. We suggest that if we and the Dominion Govern-ments decide to accept the scheme it should before being published be brought
to the attention of the Governments of the United States and France which arethe chief wool importing countries outside the United Kingdom. The canadian government, which has also shown an interest in the subject, might be informed of the proposals at the same time.6.   Authority is consequently asked :  (a) For the approval of the recommendations on behalf of the UnitedKingdom Government.(b) In the event of a similar acceptance by the three Dominion Governments,for their communication to the Governments of the United Statesand France, and also to the Government of Canada.J. A.A. R. D.P. V. E. E.lltfi June, 1945.WOOL CONFERENCE.. Report and Recommendations of Conference of Representatives of theUnited Kingdom, the Commonwealth of Australia, the Dominion ofNew Zealand and the Union of South Africa.1. We were appointed by our respective Governments to examine at theofficial and expert level the situation created by the stocks of Dominion woolaccumulated in the hands of the United Kingdom Government, and to recommendwhat arrangements should be made in the common interest in regard to thedisposal of this stock in conjunction with current clips.2. We have considered the facts of the accumulation and the prospects ofdisposal, and our conclusions are set out in the memorandum attached(Appendix A).* The stock is equal to two j^ears&apos; consumption, and on reasonablyoptimistic assumptions the complete disposal .of the stock and of current clipsin conjunction may be expected to take twelve or thirteen years.3. The holding of a stock of this size is a serious burden, and its existenceis a cloud hanging over the market. It is consequently necessary in all our interests that it should be reduced as rapidly as possible while at the same timebeing firmly held. It is no less essential that its disposal should be carefullyintegrated with the marketing of the current clips. We are satisfied that theright and only sound way of handling this matter is in partnership.4. We accordingly recommend the formation by the four Governments ofa Joint Organisation, which shall take charge of the marketing of the old wool and support the marketing of current clips throughout the period of disposal of stocks.5. We have given thorough consideration to the question of the method of marketing. During the war the United Kingdom Government has bought theclips at fixed prices and has distributed at fixed prices among the restrictednumber of purchasers such part as could be sold in wartime. With the return of peacetime it will be necessary to restore a closer touch with buyers and consumers, and consideration for their needs and preferences, if the largest possible consumption of wool is to be encouraged at prices which reflect its full value. We have examined all possible methods of marketing, with the resultsset out in Appendix B.* Our unanimous conclusion is that the interests of thegrower will best be served by a return to auctions as soon as conditions permitthem to be freely attended by buyers from consuming countries.6. We envisage then that current clips will all be offered at auction as inthe past, and that in addition the Joint Organisation will offer selections fromstock, with the aim of maximising total sales and turning over stock. the quantities of old wool to be offered alongside the new wool should be determined in the light of technical considerations and the economical and efficient manage-ment of the scheme.   This brings us to the question of price.   In the past it has* Not reproduced.[30054] B 2
been the practice to dispose of the available supplies in the season and for prices to fluctuate to the extent required to equate supply and demand in that period.&quot;With the existence of the stock, even though only a part is put on the market inany one season, some step will be necessary to ensure that prices are not artificiallydepressed. We contemplate accordingly that the Joint Organisation shall bein the market to buy in any wool for which no other buyer bids up to a reserveprice assessed by the Organisation as appropriate to its type and quality. Thereserve price for each type will be related to the general level of selling prices for wool which circumstances justify. The trend of wool prices must move inaccordance with general world conditions and the need to expand consumption.Assuming reasonable stability in the price level of commodities generally, widefluctuations, both during -the season and from one season to another, can be avoided by the joint measures of adequate offerings and reserve prices, while at the same time full scope can be given for selection and for reflection of specialvalue in prices obtainable.7. The return from wartime to peacetime conditions of demand and consumption is now beginning, and the disposal policy adopted from now on willbe formative for the future. We are of opinion that the peacetime partnershipshould begin at once. There will, of course, have to be an interim period duringwhich the change-over from wartime to peacetime methods is effected. for practical reasons it will be necessary that the 1945-46 clips shall be taken upin the same manner as hitherto, and for at any rate the early part of that seasonthe auction system will not be generally practicable and disposal will have tofollow wartime methods. But we regard it as of the highest practical importance that the Joint Organisation should be &quot;constituted and take over from the UnitedKingdom Government at once. The existing agreements would cease as from theend of July 1945 and would be replaced by the agreement under which theOrganisation is constituted. The terms which we recommend for this agreement are set out in the present Report and in Appendix C hereto.8. The terms proposed for this agreement express the mutual interest of thefour Governments in the orderly disposal on reasonable terms of wool, both oldand new, the United Kingdom Government accepting considerable limitations on freedom to sell old wool, and new responsibilities extending into the post-war period, and the Dominion Governments on their part accepting a share ofresponsibility in respect of the existing stocks. This involves a snaring of thecapital cost of the wool held by the Joint Organisation, of the cost of holding and marketing in, and of the ultimate profit or loss. We have endeavoured to frame our recommendations so as to ensure equity and a close community ofinterest.9. The existing agreements are separate ones between the United KingdomGovernment and each of the Dominion Governments. While in the future separatefinancial accounts should be kept by the Joint Organisation for Australian, NewZealand and South African wool, it is obvious that in policy and its execution theOrganisation must act as an undertaking in which the four Governments arejoined together in a common enterprise.10. We set out in Appendix C the constitution and functions which werecommend for the Joint Organisation and the financial basis which we recommendfor the scheme. Its operation should, we propose, be reviewed between the four governments at the end of five years in the light of experience.11. We recommend that the existing fixed purchase prices paid by theUnited Kingdom should be maintained for the clips of the 1945-46 season subjectto any adjustment which may be decided upon by the South African and UnitedKingdom Governments in the case of South African wool.12. In view of the progress of the restoration of normal conditions in regardto sheepskins it is recommended by the representatives of the Governmentsconcerned that the agreements between the United Kingdom Government andthe Australian and New Zealand Governments for the purchase of sheepskinsshould be terminated at the 30th June, 1946.13. It must be emphasised in conclusion that the success or failure of theJoint Organisation will rest, not merely upon its securing orderly marketing,but upon the progress it is able to make in reducing the huge accumulation of
wool which overhangs the market. The wool industry cannot be in a safe orhealthy condition until this has been achieved. To this end it must be one of themain concerns of the Joint Organisation to encourage the fullest consumptionof wool by all means in its power.For the United Kingdom Delegation :(Signed) F . J. FIUTCHINSON.For the Australian Delegation :(Signed) J. F. MURPHY.For the New Zealand Delegation :(Signed) G. A. DUNCAN.For the South African Delegation :(Signed) C. H. NEVELING.London, 29th May, 1945.APPENDIX C.I. Disposals Plan.1. The stock of Dominion grown wool in the ownership of the United KingdomGovernment at the 31st July, 1945, will be transferred to the joint ownership ofthe United Kingdom Government and the Dominion Government concerned, andall wool subsequently acquired under this scheme will be in joint ownership. Thiswool will be held and disposed of by the Joint Organisation referred to below.2. A Joint Disposals Organisation will be set up forthwith for the purposeof buying, holding and selling wool on behalf of the United Kingdom and theDominion Governments concerned.   As part of the plan it will be required : (a) To determine total quantities of wool to be offered from time to timeconcurrently in the Dominions and elsewhere, to be made up of ailnew clip wool and an appropriate proportion of wool from theOrganisation^ stock.(b) To prepare schedules of reserve prices at which the Organisation willitself be willing to acquire wool.(c) To lift from the market such quantities of new wool as cannot be sold at these reserve prices.(d) To hold and dispose of stocks as the agent of the Governments concerned and where necessary to acquire and own stores, plant and, equipment for this purpose.(e) To facilitate the sale of wool in every way possible, with a view tostimulating demand.3. As soon as practicable, the method of marketing wool by auction will be resumed. All growers&apos; wool from current clips will be offered at auction,alongside such quantities from stock as may be determined by the Organisation.The quantity of new wool required to be taken in by the Organisation will beaffected by the quantities of old wool offered from time to time. This cannotbe prescribed in advance, but will be determined by the Organisation in thelight of technical considerations and the economical and efficient management ofthe scheme.4. The relative prices realised for different types of wool at auctions willreflect the valuations of the market. The general price level of wool will, however,be made effective by the Organisation. It will prescribe minimum reserve prices at which it will be willing to take up any unsold new clip, and it will offer atauction wool from its own stocks in such quantities as will prevent prices fromrising much above the desired level. In some circumstances the organisaion may make standing offers to sell from stock outside the auctions at a fixedpercentage above the auction reserve prices, and thus impose a ceiling on pricesactually obtainable at auction. Some extension of the selling seasons in theDominions will be desirable, and special sales of old wool, or sales comprisingmostly old wool, may be held during the off-season.   The Organisation will be
prepared, possibly at short notice, to increase or hold back its offerings fromstock in some or all of the selling centres to meet fluctuations of demand and to check their influence upon prices.5. The object of the Organisation will be to secure a progressive reductionin stocks while maintaining reasonable stability of price having regard to theconditions of world demand. Reduction of stocks will be achieved as long as thetotal demand exceeds the supplies of new clip wool which come forward to auction,though in any given year the Organisation will be both a seller of old wool anda buyer of new wool.6. It will be for the Organisation to recommend to the Governments the initial level of reserve prices at which auctions of growers&apos; wool shall commence,and any major changes which may thereafter be necessary. The organisation will endeavour to maintain the general price level unchanged within a singleseason, though it may be necessary to meet a definite trend in demand which appears to be of a lasting character. Changes in the relative prices of different types of wool may also, of course, be necessary. The Organisation will have topay particular attention to securing that the relative reserve prices for wooloriginating in the three Dominions are properly adjusted. Towards the end ofeach season the Organisation will consider in the light of past experience andfuture forecasts what changes may be necessary, either in the general level or inrelative prices.7. The Organisation will build up the structure of selling prices upon thebasis of &quot; c.i.f. Europe,&quot; preparing a corresponding schedule of reserve prices&quot; ex store &quot; in the Dominions. Reserve prices will be calculated for the london market, and as soon as. practicable growers will be free to forward wool to london for sale there alongside wool from the Organisation^ stocks.8. At auction, if no buyer is forthcoming at the reserve price or higher, the lot will be passed in and taken over by J.O. at the auction reserve price, subject tothe s;rower&apos;s right of withdrawal.9. It is recognised that the concurrent marketing of stock and new clips bythe method of auction cannot be introduced in full immediately after the 31st July,1945, since the necessary conditions of free demand and adequate organisationand personnel will not then obtain. The Dominions 1945-46 clip will thereforebe taken up as a whole by the present methods of appraisement and bulk purchase.On the disposal side, however, it is desirable that auctions should be restarted to alimited degree in the United Kingdom and possibly elsewhere in the course of the season. This would have the great advantage of providing the Organisation withpractical experience as to the appropriate differentials between the prices ofdifferent types of wool in advance of the commencement of general auctions. Itis in any case certain that sales of wool will be of much greater importance and complexity during 1945-46 than at any time since 1939, and that during thisperiod foundations will be laid and trade contacts established which will be ofgreat importance in future years. Responsibility for the management of salesshould therefore pass to the Organisation at the earliest possible date. It will befor the Organisation to determine the selling price during the interim period before auctions of growers&apos; wool have commenced.10. In order to facilitate and expand the consumption of wool the JointOrganisation will maintain close contact with the appropriate bodies interestedin such matters as furthering the rehabilitation of the wool textile industry inconsuming countries, and in securing the replacement and improvement ofmachinery. It will also maintain close contact with the International WoolSecretariat and other institutions concerned with research, publicity and develop-ment designed to increase the uses of wool, and with the reduction of costs of wool production, processing, manufacture and distribution, and in general willgive attention to the removal of any obstacles to consumption.II. Constitution and Functions of Joint Organisation.1. The Joint Organisation will be incorporated as a private registeredCompany, with a nominal share capital of eight shares, hold as to four by nomineesof the United Kingdom Government, two by nominees of the Government ofAustralia, and one each by nominees of the New Zealand and South african governments. This Company will have three active subsidiaries in the dominions to act on its behalf, which may be registered Companies or other legal entities.
The Directors of the principal company will consist of an independent chairman, appointed by the four Governments in agreement; four directorsappointed by the United Kingdom Government, two by the Government ofAustralia and one each by the Governments of New Zealand and South Africa.In addition, the Chairman of the three Dominion subsidiaries will be ex officioDirectors of the principal Company without additional voting power.The functions of the principal Company will be primarily to buy, hold andsell wool as agent for the four Governments and generally to administer the schemeagreed upon between them.2. There will be constituted in each of the Dominions a subsidiary for thepurpose of conducting the operations of the principal Company in the Dominionin accordance with its policy and decisions.The functions of each subsidiary will include the following : (a) To hold wool in the Dominion as the agent of the principal Company.(b) To sell wool from stocks in the Dominions, and to arrange for the regulation of sales of current slips by auction.(c) To assess on the basis laid down by the principal Company the appro-priate reserve prices for the individual lots of wool (from stocks orcurrent clips), being offered for sale.(d) To take up wooi offered at auction for which the reserve price or better isnot offered by a commercial buyer.(e) To conduct the financial operations of the principal Company in theDominion.(/) To furnish to the principal Company annual reports on its activities,including statements of its accounts and information regarding itspurchases, sales and stocks.3. Representatives of the four Governments will meet prior to the openingof each wool year, and at such other times as may be required to agree upon thegeneral level of reserve prices in the light of the advice of the Board of theprincipal Company. The Board will have discretion to make minor changes inthe general level from time to time. It will be the duty of the Board to fix therelative values of the different types of wool in accordance with the general levelof reserve prices of wool, and to adjust them as may be necessary from time to time.4. The International Wool Textile Organisation wiLl be invited to nominaterepresentatives to form, with the addition of representatives from majorconsuming countries not members of the Organisation, a Committee to act in a consultative capacity to the board of the Company from the point of view of woolconsumers.III. Financial Plan.1. The scheme will come into force as soon as it has been agreed by all theGovernments concerned, and will take effect as from the 1st August, 1945.2.   Capital Contribution.(a) The United Kingdom and the Dominion concerned will each take up50 per cent, of the original capital represented by the opening stock of woolgrown in that Dominion to be banded over to J.O.ib) The opening stock will be taken in by J.O. at its original cost (includingf.o.b. payments) less the amounts accumulated in the divisible profits accounts.Except in the case of South Africa, these amounts are estimated fully to coverdepreciation of that stock. (In the case of South Africa, where the estimateddepreciation exceeds the accumulated balance, the stock will be taken in at theoriginal cost less an agreed figure representing the full amount of the estimateddepreciation.) The balances in the divisible profits accounts will be retained bythe United Kingdom Government.(c) Payment of the Dominions&apos; shares of the original capital will be madein four annual instalments, to which will be applied the Dominions&apos; shares of the proceeds of sales by J.O., and of the net profit during the interim period referredto in paragraph 6; but subject to a minimum payment in each year of one-quarterof the total.(If a Dominion^ share of the proceeds and net profit in any of the first three years exceeds one-quarter of its initial capital share plus that Dominionsshare of any new capital to be provided in any one year, the excess of proceedsand net profit will be paid to the United Kingdom, and the payment necessaryin the fourth year will be correspondingly reduced.)
The payment necessary to reach the minimum in any year will be made atthe end of that wool year.Xo interest will be charged bv the United Kingdom Government onoutstanding instalments.(d) Each Dominion and the United Kingdom will share equally in theprovision of any further capital required by J.O. during the operation of thescheme for payment for bought-in new wool of that Dominion.3. Operating Expenses.(a) The operating expenses of J.O. will be borne equally between the industryand J.O. itself. The share of the industry will be paid by the Dominion Govern-ments primarily from the proceeds of a contributory charge on all sales of newclip wool; the share of J.O. will be met by deduction from the proceeds of salesby J.O. before application to capital repayment.(b) Xo charge will be made for interest in the operating expenses of J.O.(c) Operating expenses in any year will include all current expenses, suchas costs of administration, storage, reconditioning, insurance and selling expenses.The storage expenses will include an annual sum sufficient to cover over ten years the cost of stores and other capital plant and equipment transferred to J.O.(d) Operating expenses will also include provision to cover depreciation of wool bought-in by JO. as indicated in this paragraph. This provision will be calculated at a rate to be determined by JO. on bought-in wool taken into stockeach year and will be credited to a Suspense Account. As bought-in wool is soldJ.O. will assess the amount of difference between the price realised for it andfor new wool of similar type and yield both to be calculated at time of resale.The amount so assessed will be withdrawn from the Suspense Account and addedto the actual proceeds of sale for the purpose of capital repayment.4. Repayment of Capital.After deduction of one-half of the operating costs, the proceeds of all salesby J.O.. together with any sums added in accordance with paragraph 3 (d). willbe used for repayment of capital equally between the United Kingdom and theDominion Government concerned.5. Ultimate Profit or Loss.The ultimate balance of profit or loss arising from the transactions of J.O. inthe wool of any Dominion will thus be shared equally between the United Kingdomand the Government of that Dominion.6. Procedure in Interim Period.During the wool year 1945-46, in place of the procedure indicated inparagraphs 3 and 4 above, the following procedure will apply :  (a) The United Kingdom will be responsible for the purchase of the wholeclip, the management and sale of which will be entrusted to J.O. as soon asconstituted. The United Kingdom will be reimbursed by each Dominion forone-half of the cost of that part of the new clip of that Dominion unsold at theend of the wool year.(b) The net proceeds of the sales of old wool during the interim year, plus(or minus) the net profit (or loss) on sales of new clip wool after meeting thewhole operating costs of J.O. and such incidental costs (including interest atl-\ per cent, per annum, on the monthly balance of the working capital providedby the United Kingdom) as the United Kingdom may incur in connection with thepurchase of the new clip, will be allocated to capital repayment.(c) All sales, whether to consumers in the partner countries or elsewhere, willbe on the basis of the selling prices determined by J.O.7. Taxation.Payments will be so adjusted that each Government will receive the sumsto which it is entitled under the above scheme irrespective of any tax chargeableby the United Kingdom Government or a Dominion Government on profits arisingfrom the operations of the Joint Organisation or its subsidiaries.8. Exchange.In the event of any change in the exchange rate between sterling and anyDominion currency, the Governments concerned will consult together concerningthe effect, if any, which the change has on these financial arrangements.



</content>
</cab>
