<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/70/0 images: 31-42</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 This Pocunlpnt Is  the Property ofKits  Britaiv-                 &apos;fs  Government.MINISTRY    OF    FOOD.for  Week ending  Wednesday,  November  13,  1918.                        PART  L-ACTION  TAKEN.    Debates took place in both Houses of Parliament on Wednesday, November 13th,on the agricultural policy of  the  Food Ministry, with  special reference to difficulties caused to farmers by the scarcity of feeding-stuffs.    The Food Controller announced the following five measures of relief :       (1)  The raising  of live stock prices for the winter and spring months so as  to             compensate farmers for the loss sustained in consequence of the com-             pulsoiy holding back of their stock.      (2)  The  preferential  taking of   supplies  from  grazing  districts, and the             consequent closing  of  markets for local supplies  in  arable districts,             which would draw their meat from the adjacent grazing areas.      (3)  The revocation of  the Order prohibiting the slaughter of pigs weighing less             than 112  lbs.      (4)  The  use of  barley for feeding-stuffs, involving the release to  farmers  of             20 per cent, of each threshing.   This should release 3,000,000 qrs.      (5)  A reduction  in the percentage of  flour to be abstracted from wheat.  This             would mean the release of an additional 18,000 tons of offals of superior             quality each week.    Mr. clynes  added  that  care would be taken  to  ensure a sufficient  quantity of feeding-stuffs being made available for  cottagers and  members of pig clubs who hadbought their pigs in response to the Governments appeal.    Lord  Bledisloe, in  the House of Lords, dealt with the  points  raised on the same lines as those followed by the Food  Controller.   He emphasised the  value of  theCentral Agricultural Advisory Council as a critic of the Food Ministry&apos;s agricultural policy, and expressed his appreciation  of the weight generally given to its views bythe Food Controller.    The following figures show the modifications  in the number  of live stock in theUnited Kingdom since  the outbreak of war.1914.1915.1316.1917.1918.CattleSheepPigs12,184,-50527,963,977 3,952,61512,171,45228,275,970 3,795,13112,451,54028,849,655 3,615,89112,382,23627,867,244 3,007,91612,273,00026,980,000 2,799,000     The cattle herds of the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man are not included in the figures for 1918, but in 1917 they amounted approximately to 35,1&apos;00.     Relaxation of  Control-Mr. Clyn^s warned the House of Commons that  the substitution of armistice for war conditions would not enable him either  to effect any substantial increase in rationed quantities or to do away with coupons altogether. The needs of Allied and neutral nations were considerable, and the hunger of  the conquered countries could not  be ignored.   He hoped to provide a more agreeable Christmas table this year, with larger supplies of apples, oranges, and nuts.     Mr. Beveridge has submitted a  memorandum on the  demobilisation of the Food Ministry, on  the  assumption that  it is  desirable  to  relax control at any rate of distribution and consumption as speedily as possible.                            :     The Food Council. It was decided that the Vegetable Preservation Section might obtain and dry 1,500 tons  of carrots, in order to enable them to fulfil a contract  for dried vegetables for the French Army.     It  was  agreed that permission should  be given for the sale coupon-free  of turkeys, game, geese,  ducks, and chickens for the period from December  16th  to January 14th  inclusive.   It  &quot;was decided that meat should be allowed to  be sold at an increased rate per coupon  in England for a fortnight covering  Christmas, and in Scotland for a fortnight  covering New  Year&apos;s Day.!.Sir John Beale reported that the Inter-Allied  Food  Council  acquiesced  in the reduction of  the milling extraction below 80 per cent, and the reduced use of diluents     A (33)6822-2 Pk 1 140  11/18   B&amp;S                                           A.
in bread,  but they deprecated any emphasis being laid on the provision of whiterbread as such.    It was agreed that wholesalers should be enabled and encouraged to hold reservestocks of food in their store, and that the Divisional. Food  Commissioners  should  &quot;be furnished  with details of reserve stocks for use in emergency.    The Imports Board. It was agreed  that  Treasury sanction should be asked forthe purchase of the British share of Danish butter for the next three months, provided the blockade arrangements continue.     It was reported that owing to delayed arrivals of butter from  Australia it mightbe necessary to discontinue altogether the already reduced butter ration.    It was  reported that  an offer  had been received for the purchase of  next year&apos;output of  butter from the Argentine and the balance of  this year&apos;s output at a reduc-tion of 10  per cent.  It  was agreed  that the  Treasury should be  approached for finance.    It was decided to send a cable to the  Allied Provisions Export Commission to theeffect that  any tonnage  available on the  Pacific Coast  should  be filled with canned salmon of the 1918 pack.    It was  reported that the Butter Section had heard from the  Union Cold StorageCompany  to  the effect that there is  no butter in  store at  Vladivostock, all  suppliesbeing inland, and further that there is no prospect of shipping facilities being afforded.It was agreed to  write to  the  Russian   Committee and ascertain the possibility ofshipping from other ports.    It was  agreed that, when the  Department of Import Restrictions allows permitsto export pilchards, steps should be taken  to facilitate shipments.    It was agreed that a cable should be sent making shipping arrangements for theimportation of apples from the United States and Canada and that the Department of import Restrictions should be pressed to giant licences for  importation on privateaccount.  .  It was reported that the Central Prisoners of War Committee would  not requirethe 1,000,000 tins of canned salmon asked for.  It was agreed to take up the questionof allowing some of this canned salmon to  be released for the Belgian canteens.    Home  Supplies Board. In  the  event  of the  cessation  of  hostilities beingaccompanied by a  rise  in prices of feeding-stuffs, the Home Supplies Board passed the following Resolution:         &quot; That  this Board desires  to  emphasise  the importance of  buying  in      advance all  available feeding-stuffs, and of maintaining full control of  all      sources of supply within the Empire.&quot;    With regard  to the use  of barley for feeding-stuffs, it was agreed that a farmerhaving over 20 per cent, damaged barley  should be obliged  to sell  the balance. &apos; Astatement  to  the effect that licences would be  restricted to  20 per cent, was to beadded to the notice of the Emergency Scheme.    It  was agreed that instructions to Grain Officers should be issued in time for thescheme to come into operation on Wednesday, November 13th.    The Joint Finance Board. The question  of the  cost  of distribution by  theMultiple Shop Retailers from their central depots to their branch shops was discussed.Mr. Peat recommended that an allowance at the rate of 2\ per cent, on sales should begiven to businesses with branches served  by distributing depots where the depot was established prior to 1915, and is at present in operation, distinct and separate from aretail shop ; that Multiple Shop businesses should be registered as such, and that the allowance&apos;should be given only on  goods bougnt  from the  Ministry&apos;s  first sellingagent,  and delivered  by  him to the  central depot.  The  recommendation  was approved.    Consumers&apos; Council. The following resolutions were unanimously passed at themeeting of the Council on Wednesday, November 13th :     (1) &quot; That this Consumers&apos;  Council welcomes  the  statement  that  President           Wilson  and M. Clemenceau recognise the  necessity of providing  food for           the peoples of late enemy countries, and hopes that the Allied Governments           will soon put plans into operation towards this end.&quot;    (2) &quot; That the Council registers its opinion that  the wholesalers&apos; profit  on milk           should  be  reduced from \\d.  to  3d. a gallon, thus  allowing a greater           margin to the retail distributor, and thereby making for better distribution           to the consumers.&quot;
     Mr. Hyndman moved:                &quot; That certain improvements in distribution made by the Ministry of           Food under D.O.R.A. should be legalised at once by the House of Commons,           so that they may be the acknowledged law after the peace.&quot;     He suggested the appointment of a  sub-committee which should tabulate those matters which were of public  interest  and which should be  continued after thedeclaration of peace, and duly legalised.     It was decided to appoint a sub-commitee accordingly, the resolution was post-poned until the sub-committee had reported.                                    SurPLiES.     Bacon. During the past week the Ministry of Food have released  3,600 tons  ofbacon for French consumption, and have  undertaken to send a large amount of bacon and  lard for Belgium, and to meet  other Continental needs.   There are indications that there will be a strong demand from the Continent for whatever stock the Ministrycan  spare.     The retailers in England and  the exporters of  Irish hams continue  to press their claim for higher prices     Condensed Milk. Numerous  applications  are being  received  for   additional supplies of condensed milk,  the reason put forward  being the shortage and high priceof fresh milk, and the local increases  in population since 1917, which  is  the datumperiod taken as the basis for calculating requirements.   A. proportion  of applicationshave been granted, but it  is recognised  that the increased demand is  largely due tothe  use of  sweetened milk to supplement the sugar ration.     Dried Fruits. The distribution  of dried fruits  has been put  into  operation.With the cessation of hostilities and  submarine warfare it is anticipated that 12,000tons of currants, raisins, and sultanas will have  been released  for civilian and other purposes before the end of November, and every householder should be  able to obtain dried fruits for Christmas.     Jam. The  rationing  of  jam came into force on the  3rd  November.  There appears to be insufficient jam in many districts to meet the coupons.  These shortages are being  made up as quickly as possible.     The allotment  of citrous  fruits amongst the  various jam  manufacturers is now being proceeded with, and it is hoped will be completed next week.     Information has been received that three vessels are  now in the course of loading at Spanish ports with sweet oranges for marmalade-making.     The equipment of the nine  pulping stations  in  readiness for  the  handling of citrous fruit is proceeding satisfactorily.    Delivers of the 56 oraage chipping machines has commenced and it is expected that the first  station (Sittingbourne) will be ready by  the last week of the present month.  The  Bewdley  factory is  also  ready to  deal with citrous fruits,  if necessary, and two chipping machines are to be held in reserve to be installed there if required.     Meat.-The country is  still being fed on home-grown supplies, with the exception of the London area, where, owing to transport difficulties, it was necessary to utilise a small proportion of frozen meat last week.  These difficulties have,  however, been surmounted, and it is anticipated  that there will be a sufficient surplus from  the other areas to maintain the supply of home-grown  meat for the metropolitan  area this week.      There is  a slight reduction  in the quantities of  cattle coming forward into  the market.   The arrivals of imported meat  have been very heavy, and will  absorb  the whole of  the space available  in  the stores  Under these circumstances very little further progress has been made with the freezing of home-grown meat.      The  experiments in the  direction  of salting-down home-killed beef are being continued, and this meat will no doubt be found useful for the supply of the liberated districts on the continent.      There is still need of obtaining a more ample supply of  slaughtermen  from the army, but the changed circumstances  should render  it less  difficult  to  secure the services of the men required.      The  measures indicated in the  last  Report to meet the grievances of  the retailers in connection with the grading of cattle have  now  been completed, and a Committee
 of  Retailers is to be established  permanently at  the Ministry, in order, to supervise the grading results and to deal with any complaints which may arise in future.                ORDERS  UNDER DEFENCE OF THE REALM&apos;REGULATIONS.     .1. The Potato (Committees) Order, 1918, dated 5th November  1918, provides for the appointment of a Rotate Control Committee for each of the 11 deficit zones, and  a ^pnal Committee for,each of the 10 surplus zones, and places  those committees under the direction  of the  Food Controller for the collection and disposal of potatoes.    .  ,     2. The Potatoes (Scottish Central  Allocation Authority) Order, 19.18, dated 5th November 1918, constitutes  a committee  to  regulate matters relating to potatoes in Scotland under the direction of the Food Controller.. r  .  S. The Potatoes (Consolidation) Order, 1918, dated 5th November 1918, empowers ,the Food Controller to  give  directions as to&quot; the sale, delivery, distribution, use, or allocation of  potatoes.  Except under licence, restrictions are laid down as to the movement of  potatoes from  one area or zone to  another, and on  the general use of -potatoes-or potato, products.   Dealers  must  be registered, and  the methods of sale and prices are brought under control.  This Order applies only to England  and Wales.     4. The Jam (Distribution) Order, 1918, dated&apos;7th November 1918, gives the Food Controller  power, to issue directions  as to the allocation  and  distribution  of jam. [Manufacturers must keep accurate records and make the necessary returns. 0  &apos;  5. The Jam (Export from  Ireland) Order, 1918, dated 7th November 1918, prohibits, except under licence, the export of jam from Ireland.     6. TM Citrons  Fruits (Prices) Order, 1918, dated 8th November  1918, controls the sale  of oranges  and lemons, and  fixes the maximum brokers, wholesalers, and retailers&apos; prices.  The maximum retail price of oranges is \0d. per lb.  and  of lemons Is. per lb.( ;   7. The Potatoes (Scotland) Order, 1918, dated the  9th  November 1918,  lays down^regulations for&apos;the control and disposal of potatoes  in Scotland.   The whole  country is treated as one area.                        .     ENFORCEMENT OF ORDERS.  &apos;                     ,  &apos;:.&quot;  The total number  of prosecutions  for  the week is 935, with 827, convictions.-Five sentences of imprisonment-without  the  option  of  a fine were passed on three, separate  offenders  in &quot;this  week&apos;s records.    There  are 74  Orders  affected by  the. prosecutions,  the principal of which are :-j ....  , (,        Orders.                  -        -        Cases.   Convictions.          Rationing (Various)      -    -    -    -    -    52        47         c          Cattle Feeding-Stuffs (Maximum Prices) -   . -     48        48-:; &apos;  .     Fish (Prices) -    -              -    -    -     4-1      &quot;41          Flour and Bread (Amended Prices)     -    -     33        21,y   Cases  in  connection with rationing in  which ration books or-cards are used fraudulently are becoming more in evidence, three of the cases resulting in sentences of imprisonment.                                                      , .  -     The police appear  to have been active  at Middlesbrough,  where  they broughtf 17 defendants to court.;  &apos; &apos; At Newcastle-upon-Tyne, Liptons, Ltd., were  fined 501. and  25?. under the Meat Rationing Order, 1918, for selling bacon to unregistered customers.
              PART II.-SUMMARY  OF  THE  FOOD POSITION.                                    Imports,    Imports oi the principal foods and feedmg-stuffs in the week ended November 9th(193,800 tons), though  not as high  as those of the preceding week (245,100 tons)were above the average of the first 4-4 weeks of  the  year 1918  (182,900 tons) andgreatly in excess of those of the corresponding week of  1917 (161,100 tons).    There was an average import of wheat and flour (90,400 tons as equivalent grain)an exceptionally good supply of oats (22,400 tons) and maize (24,300 tons), but verylittle  barley  (300  tons).   Bacon (6,500  tons) was again  below  the  consumptionrequirements.  The imports of oilseeds, &amp;c, in the month of October though above those of the preceding month were below the average.   No oilseed cake arrived.    The total imports  for the first  ten weeks  of the cereal years 1917-18 and1918-19 are compared in the following table : Imports in the first 10 weeks of cereal year. 	1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrease.	-	1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrcane.Total -Wlieat -Flour Equivalent as Grain. Barley, oats, antl maize. Rice Meat	Tons. 1,696,700 400,500 177,400	Lons. 1,880,000 895.900 88,500	Tons. 4 183,300 4- 495,400 - 88,900	Bacon Lard Butter -Margarine Cheese -Condensed milk Sugar Tea -. -Coffee -Cocoa	Tons. 45,300 2,900 8,700 9,100 27,800 15,000 322,200 20,900 1,100 2,800.	rp ions. 94.200 29,100 6,400 31,600 35,000 289,000 37.800 2,700 14,300	Tons. 4- 48,900 4 26,200 - 2,300 - 9,100 4 3,800 4 20,000 - 33,200 4 16,9:)0 4 1,600 4 11,500	683,900	1,006,600	4 372,700					415,100 126,600 121,300	250,900 9,700 94,900	- 164,200 - 116,900 - 26,400				    In the cereal year 1917-18 the proportion of flour in the total import of flour andgrain was 41 per cent.; in the first 10 weeks of the current cereal year the proportionhas been reduced  to  9   per cent.,  which  corresponds  to the  pre-war proportion,namely, 10 per cent, in 1913, and 9 per cent in 1914.                                 Consumption.    Meat. The number of cattle accepted for slaughter in Great Britain in the weekended 2nd November is estimated at  48,000, of which 4,800 went  to the Army and navy.  The supply of sheep shows  a  slight seasonal decline.  The total supply  ofhome-grown butchers&apos; meat for civilian consumption may be put at 16,900 tons; r-suesof home-grown meat from cold  storage  exceeded the entries by 200 tons ; and about1,100 tons of imported  meat were released, making in  all a total  supply of  18,200tons of meat.   After allowance for olfals, sausage  meat,  ship&apos;s stores and butchers&apos;waste, the consumption exceeds the ration requirements by about 6 per cent.    Fats. The total issue of fats  for  consumption represents 9&apos;0 ozs. per head,comprising butter, 1 &quot;7 ozs.,  margarine, 4&quot;1  ozs.,  lard, 2 ozs., compound, 1&apos;2 ozs.The pre-war consumption of these fats is estimated at  slightly over 8 ozs. per head..It should, however, be borne in mind that these fats  to some extent  take the place ofother fats such  as dripping and olive  oil which are now available  for  food only indiminished quantities.                                    STOCKS.-    The monthly stocks figures for 1st November are given in Table  D.   Sugar stocks(414,000  tons) show a rise of 32,000 tons during October and are 193,000 tons above those of  the 1st November 1917.  Bacon stocKs (78,700 tons) were reduced during october by 13,500 tons, but are far higher than those of November 1917 (12,500 tons).Meat stocks other than bacon (107,8t)0 tons) were increased during the  month by26,100  tons and were  higher  than  those of November 1917 by  16,400 tons.  Lard(31,500  tons),  cheese (27,900 tons), condensed milk (49,100 tons),  tea (50,500 tons)X 6822-2B
also show increased  stocks compared with the preceding month and with the corre-sponding month of 1917.  Rice stocks (155,000 tons)  are  lower than those of  theprevious month (196,000 tons) but higher than those of November 1917 (141,000 tons;.The stocks of  maize (24,000 tons), oilseeds  (180,000 tons) and oilseed cake and meal(89,000 tons) are  all low, being  together 10 per cent, less than  those of 1st October1918  and 40  per cent, less  than those of 1st November 1917.  Jam stocks  on  31stOctober were 27,500 tons in the hands of jam  manufacturers and in warehouses.  Honeystocks in warehouses amounted to 720 tons..                                     PRICES.    In Table E. are given the percentage increases in retail  prices of food at certaindates between July 1914 and November 1918.  The calculated  average  increase since junly 1914 for all  the  articles quoted has  risen from 129 per cent, on 1st October to133 per cent,  on 1st November.   The  increase of 19  per cent, in the price of eggsduring October represents a rise from 5s. 2d. to  Qs.  2d. a dozen.   The amount of theincrease is large,  but  the percentage corresponds to that of  the  seasonal increase in1914, 191.6, and 1917..  The rise of  3  per  cent, in the price of  milk represents  anincrease from  8c/. to 81 d. a quart.  Sago and  tapioca, the retail prices of which  arenot controlled, show a further slight increase of about 2 per cent.  Fish prices showa Jail of 8-4- per cent, during October, and potato prices a fall of 2\ per cent.
TABLE A.-IMPORTS OF PRINCIPAL FOOD AND  FEEDING STUFFS.Article. 1.	Week ending November 9th, 1918. 2.	Week ending November 2nd, 1918. 3.	Week ending November 10th, 1917. 4.	Average Weekly Net Imports&apos; in 1913. 5..	Average Weekly Imports.		Total Imports.						45 Weeks from Dec. 30th, 1917, to Nov. 9th, 1918. fi.	Corres-ponding Period. 1917, 7.	45 Weeks from Dec. 30th, 1917 to i\&apos;ov. 9th, 1918. 8.	Corres-ponding Period, 19J7. 9.1. Wheat-2. Wbeaten flour 3. Rico -4. Beef (fresh and ref rige-rated). 5. Mutton (fresh and refrige-rated). 6. Meat, unenu-merated (re-frigerated and pre-served). 7. Bacon and Hams. 8. Lard -9. Butter -10. Margarine 11. Clieese 12. Condensed milk. 13. Sugar (refined and un-refined). 14. Sugar, glucose Total 15, Barley -16. Oats -17. Maize -Total 18. Tea -19. Coffee, raw -20. Cocoa, raw -Total Grand Total -21. Oil seeds and nuts and kernels. 22. Oilseed cake 23. Oils, vege-table, relinec and unre-fined. 24. Oil, fish, train, blubber, and sperm. 25. Stearine	Tons. 86,610 3,020 6,952 6,611 2,195 1,663 6,471 3,683 275 3,223 2,165 19,802 160	Tons. 154,380 5,1S5 1,961 9,416 1,763 2,972 11,539 2,897 583 5,070 3,207 9,667	Tons. 44,230 30,355 8,844 4,769 1,099 661 3,859 49 360 2,156 914 3,725 18,234 438	Tons. 101,378 9,712 2,554 8,849 5,125 2,126 5,267 1,629 3,867 1,460 2,137 742 37,333 1,408	Tons. 50,155 27,158 8,276 6,941 2,067 2,824 11,941 2,750 1,560 340 2,493 2,600 28,166 399	Tons. 96,672 13,572 6,579 5,978 2,456 2,601 7,694 1,718 1,965 1,857 2,854 1,461 27,423. 1,119	Tons. 2,256,975 1,222,090 372.439 312,344 93,054 127,064 537,352 123.738 70,154 15,300 112,200 117,013 1,267,452 17,957	ions. 4,350,220 610,765 296.036 269.032 110,537 117,044 346,234 77,320 88,418 83,544 128,421 65,771 1,234,024 51,712	142,860	208,640	119,693	183,587	147,670	173,979	6,645,132	7,829,078	275 22,425 24,335	1,295 16,870 6,295	16,505 18,105 3,550	21,565 17,464 46,450	5,471 9,999 15,061	8,103 13,767 25,958	246,180 449.955 677,750	364,640 619,510 1,168,135	47,035	24,460	38,160	85,479	30,531	47,828	1,373,885	2,152,285	2,542 164 1,150	10,747 32 1,204	3,128 2 88	2,640 319 542	3.964 138 607	2,020 591 1,225	178,398 6,213 27,310	90,906 26,580 55,111	3,856	11,983	3,218	3,501	4,709	3,836	211,921	172,597	193,751	245,083	161,071	272,567	182,910	225,643	8,230,938	10,153,960	Not Imports.*			A verage Monthly Net Imports* in 1913.	Average Monthly Net 1m ports. *		Total Net Imports. *		Month ending Oct. 31st, 1918.	Month ending Sept. 30th, 1918.	Month ending Oct. Hist, 1917.		10 Months I Jan.-Oct., 1918.	Corres-ponding Period. 1917.	10 Months Jan.-Oct., 1918.	corresponding-ponding Period, 1917.	Tons. 74,242 13,088 1 1,072 423	Tons. 57,233 19,851 8,242 302	Tons. 69,792 13,659 t-449 3,562 36	Tons. 120,314 29,433 6,690 5,424 304	Tons. 91,780 482 11,087 5,887 226	Tons. 84,381 18,739 2,315 5,116-189	Tons. 917,805 4,822 110,873 58,870 2,259	Tons. 843,812 187,393 23,155 51,156 1,888* Imports less re-exporta of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind,  f Net export
             STATISTICS ILLUSTRATING CONSUMPTION.TABLE B. (1)-WEEKLY CONSUMPTION .OV THE CHIEF ARTICLES OF FOOD  IN THE                             UNITED KINGDOM.[The figures are based upon quantities of imported food-stuffs released for            consumption, plus estimated home production.]	Flour..	Butchers&apos; Meat.	Bacon.	Butter and Margarine.	Lard and Compound.	Sugar.	Ten.Army demands from U.K. Stocks and Supply. For Civilian Consumption :  Average of 4 weeks ended :  July 13th .... August 10th September 7 th -October 5th ... 12th 19th 26th November 2nd -	Tons. 5,200 95,600 85,700 97,600 99,500 98,600 98,600 99,100 99,900	Tons. 4,800 19,400 20,300 23,700 21,900 21,300 18,900 18,400 20,200	Tons. 2,800 9,200 9,800 11,000 9,800 10,100 8,600 7,90) 7,900	Tons. 1,000 7,400 7,300 7,000 7,500 7,700 7,800 7,700 7,300	Tons. 3,700 3,600 3,700 3,900 3,600 3,400 3,400 3,500	Tons. 3,200 19,500 19,400 17,000 17,000 17,500 17,300 17,800 17,700	Tons. . 530 2,900 3,700 2,700 2,500 2,500 2,800 3,100 3,500  (2) ANIMALS SLAUGHTERED IN  10,830 PRIVATE AND PUBLIC slaughterhouses in GREAT BRITAIN IN  SEPTEMBER 1917, AUGUST  1918,  AND SEPTEMBER 1918.- ; - Cattle.		Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.August 1918....., Percentage Increase or Decrease : September 1918 compared with September 1917 -. September 1918 compared with August 1918	156,648. 106,666 137,425 -12-30/0 + 28-8 0/,	27,593 20,987 25,899 - 6-1 0/. + 23-41	705,787 786,062 751,467 + 6-5 7G &quot; 4-4 7o	136,674 63.148 73,054 -46-51 + 15-71TABLE C. INDEX NUMBERS ILLUSTRATING CHANGES  IN THE RATE OF CONSUMPTION                             OF FOOD-STUFFS.   [Except where it is stated otherwise, the rate of consumption in May 1917                            is taken as -  luO.](1) Consumption of BUTOHEI;S&apos; MEAT by the Civilian Population in.the                        United Kingdom.	Home Fed.			Foreign.			Total.			1 1916.	1917.	1918.	19 Hi;	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.	1918January . -February -March - . .,-April May June -July. - - -August September -October November -December -	119 111 113 100* j93* 1 89 87 96 109 101 119 121	101* 92j 101 j 991 100 84 88 1021 1031 114 110* 961	674 57 59 55 43 411 54 641 77 *77	119 135 16H 1361 1441 138* 165 137 113*-99 124 148	1481 1191 i-3w 951 100 921 105 116 881 91* 901 135	118 961 114&quot; 1191 155 190^ 1721 177 801 *24i	1181 1131 119&quot; 105 100 95^ 971 101&quot; 109 1081 119&quot; 124	1071 96&quot; . 100 981 100 85 90 104 100* 110 107 101*	73* 621 66* 63* 58* 62 *o* 80 77* *70* Provisional figures.
(2) Consumption of BREAD and FLOUR in the United Kingdom.4 week endedRetailers1 Sales.1916,1917.1918.January 5thFebruary 2ndMarch 2ndMarch 30thApril 27th -May 25th  -June 22nd -July 20th  -August 17 thSeptember 14th -October 12thNovember  10th -December 8 th 99100 97  99 95 94 9oi 98&quot;10H 94i 99&quot;102A10lJ101100 95 9&quot;U 891 90^(92) 97&quot;(96)100100 96look100J10010C 98 98 96 98102104  Deliveries of Flour from mills and Releases of Foreign    Flour to Agents?1917. 9810411011918.10U-104&quot; 97 92 07 96 99 99 90103102      The numbers in brackets are adjusted for th - probable change in the stock of Hour held at home beforeand after the reduction in price on September 17th.(3) Consumption of PROVISIONS in the United  Kingdom based on returns             from Multiple Shops and Co-operative Societies.4 weeks endedButter,1916.1917.1918.January 19th  -February I6th -March  16thApril 13thMay 11thJune 8th -July 6th  -August 3rdAugust 31stSeptember 28thOctober 26th  -November 24th -December 22nd -*137*134 125 114 113 97 87 82 91 99100106110108 92 65 35 352824284350556270706556Lard.1916.1917.1918.Bacon and Hams.*108&apos;108 108 152 143124128119104106100104115122123127 84 54 47 38 35 68 73 57 891221131161131916.  j 1917. i  1918.     I     . I* 113*105 103 106 119 97103 88 86 93100110107 98 81 72 61 61 48 35 39 50 99141134121110109103Cheese.1916.1917.1918.452&apos;146 146 135 129106113 96 90 95100118113113114104106 96 56 53 54 45 28 44 52 55 56100111For these months no returns were obtained from Co-operative Societies in England and Wales.(4) Quantities of MILK carried by seven of the Principal Railway Companies                            in  England and Wales.[The average weekly quantity carried in September  1917 is taken as  = 100.]1917.1918.Week endedJanuary  -February  -MarchApril     -MayJuneJulyAugustSeptemberOctober  -NovemberDecember100 931 851 851 87 i 931 97J107112106104102September 7thSeptember 14thSeptember 21stSeptember 28thOctober 5th   -October 12th -October 19th -October 26th -November 2nd1917.   1918.10010011004 99* 99 98 98 97i 951103102101 99 99i102&quot;1011101 97B 3
       TABLE  D. STOCKS of the  PRINCIPAL  FOODS  and FEEDING STUFFS in the                                        UNITED  KINGDOM.    The figures for wheat and flour include stocks  in  port  granaries and warehouses, inland  warehouses,mills, and. bakers&apos; shops, as  well as estimated stocks on farms ; those for barley, oats,  beans,  and peasinclude stocks in port grauarios and warehouses and in mills, in  maltsters&apos; hands, and estimated farm stocks ;those for maize, rice, and grain meals include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in  mills.    The figures for  sugar are stocks  in  possession of  tho Sugar Commission ;  those  for butter, margarine,lard,  cheese, condensed  milk,  meat, and  fish include  slocks at  ports, in cold stores, and in importers&apos; andwholesalers&apos; warehouses.    The figures  for tea, coffee,  and cocoa are  stocks remaining in  bonded warehouses or entered  to bewarehoused ; and those for  oilseeds  and oilseed  cake  include  stocks  at  ports and in the hands of millers,crushers, and cake manufacturers.Article.Wheat (including flour)BarleyOatsBeansPeasMaizeRice (including ground rice and rice flour)Grain Meals     ....ButterMargarine       ...LardCheese   -Condensed milk meat: Beef (chilled and frozen)        Mutton (chilled and frozen)        Bacon and Hams        Poultry. Game, and Rabbits        Other MeatFish     ....TeaCoffeeCocoaNovember 1st, 1918.October 1st, 1918.November 1st, 1917.Stocks in the United Kingdom including estimated               Farm Stocks,Oilseeds, &amp;cOdseed Cake and Meal  Tons.2,939,0001,100.0003,202.000  144,000   91,000  Tons.3,040,0001,245,0003.483,000  160,000  110,000  Tons.2,850,0001,169,0003,000,000  147,000   54,000Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, fee. 24,000155,000 48,000414,000 26,000196,000 55,000382,000 54,000141,000 44,000221,000Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and  in Importers&apos; and Wholesalers&apos; Warehouses.10,000 1,40031,50027,90049,10045,30020,10078,700 5,20037,20027,10012,700 1,80029,30024,70042,40024,80017,80092,200 6,90032,20026,600  6.300  3.400 12,900 14,900*11,800 50,000 17,300 12,500  4,200 19,900 20,600Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded     Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.50,5003&quot; ,00019,00015,00063.80053.800Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports and in the hands    of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.180,000 89,000304,200115,100In manufacturers&apos; hands only.NUMBER  OF  LIVE STOCK IN GREAT  BRITAIN.	October 4th, 1918 (Estimated), f	June 4th, 1918.	-June 4th, 1917.	June 5th, 1916.Dairy Cattle -Total Cattle -Ewes kept for breeding Total Sheep -Sows kept for breeding Total Pigs	3,120,000 7,450,000 9,100,000 20,000,000 310,000 2,260,000	3,030,000 7,408,000 9,498,000 23,338,000 306,000 1,825,000	2,907.000 7,437,000 9,899,000 . 24,043,000 269,000 2,051,000	2,870.000 7,442,000 10,066,000 25,007.000 301,000 2,314,000f Estimates prepared by the Live Stock Committee of the Btard of Agriculture.
      TABLE E. PERCENTAGE INCREASE IN RETAIL FOOD PRICES  IN  THEUNITED KINGDOM, AT  EACH OF TUB UNDERMENTIONED DATES,  AS  COMPARED WITH                       &quot; NORMAL  PRICES  IN JULY  1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Article.	Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.									1st Jan. 1915.	1st Jan. 1910.	1st Jan. 1917.	1st July 1917.	1st Sept. 1917.	1st Jan. 1918.	1st Aug. 1918.	; 1st Oct. 1918.	1st Nov. 1918.Beef :-British Ribs Thin flank Chilled or frozen  Ribs -Thin flank -Mutton :  British Legs Breast Frozen Legs Breast Bacon. streaky* Fish Flour Bread lea -Sugar, granulated Milk Potatoes -Margarine Butter, fresh Butter, salt Cheese, Canadian or u.s.* Eggs, fresh	7-0 11-2 16-3 26-7 5-8 11-7 16-3 24-8 7-1 40-9 20-3 15-8 13-6 67-0 6-7 \16-1 4-4 13-8 12-1 10-0 63-4	35-3 45-2 46-7 63-1 27-9 413 41-8 62-7 30-7 96-7 49-0 41-7 48-2 93-3 28-8 \4-8 6-9 33-9 31-5 31-7 104-9	64-2 83-5 85-4 101-2 58-7 84-2 86-4 122-0 56-3 131-1 88-5 73-3 50-9 170-0 56-6 121-7 25-0 72-9 70-6 74-8 175-0	96-1 132 - 2 119-6 156-5 100-0 142-2 134-4 190-8 76-4 127-1 109-3 100-3 73-7 187 7 59-7 144-3 73 5 64-7 65-3 .108-0 95-3	97-4 130-9 122-1 157-9 97-7 138-2 136-0 190-9 96-0 136-1 109-2 99-6 78-9 190-0 61-0 38-9 66-0 90-8 90-1 94-7 142-4	80-5 100-9 116-4 137-3 76-8 92-5 134-0 161-8 138-7 195-9 51-8 54-4 98-2 189-3 99-5 37-1 65-9 103-4 105-4 91-3 242-1	83-8 98-1 147-9 164-7 84-5 77-7 176-5 168-5 139-6 188-7 52-1 54-5 73-3 241 2 88-0 113-6 97-0 95-3 99-2 125-5 295-0	102-6 126-3 175-4 206-5 102-4 106-6 205-6 217-4 141-9 191-5 52-1 54-8 73-3 241-3 133-2 63-5 96-9 103-8 110-4 130-2 329-2	102-7 126-2 175-4 206-5 102-3 106-5 205-6 217-4 141-7 167-4 52-2 54-8 73-3 241-3 141-0 59-3 97-0 106-8 112-3 130-2 412-1* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative.f Decrease.TABLE F.-RETAIL PRICES OF SUBSIDIARY  FOODS  IN ;APRIL, 1917,  AND SUBSEQUENT      MONTHS COMPARED WITH THE  PRICES IN JULY,  1914,  IN LONDON  AND                               OTHER LARGE  TOWNS.          [Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Percentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.Article.	April 1st, 1917.	Julv 1st, 1917.	Sept. 1st, 1917.	Jan. 1st, 1918.	April 1st, 1918.	July 1st, 1918.	Sept. 1st, 1918.	Oct. 1st, 1918.	Nov. 1st, 1918.Butter beans -Haricot beans (white) Peas, split (yellow) -Lentils, split (red) -Oatmeal, Scotch Rice, Eangoon Sago Tapioca -Condensed milk Lard, British -,, American	160 230 140 210 140 90 140 120 65 125 130	140 180 210 230 150$ 100 180 160 110 120 110	110 140 210 220 150+ 100 180 150 110 120 120	113 140 220 232 100 103 200 170 139 125 139	113 140 220 232 113 117 227 185 143 164	113 140 220 232 120 117 251 210 152 168	113 140 220 232 120 117 282. 238 152 186	113 140 220 232 120 117 300 246 152 186	113 140 220 232 120 117 307 251 152 186\ 125 in Scotland,
TABLE G-.-CONSUMPTION AND SALE  OF FLOUR BY BAKERS AND RETAILERS.   COMPARISON OF  FOUR-WEEKLY PERIODS IN  ]917-18.                                  (All measured  as percentages of quantities used in May 1917.)Four Weeks endedFood Control Divisions.	Oct. 12, 1918.	Sept. 14, 191S	August 17, 1*118.	July 20, 1918.	June 22. 1918.	May 25, 1918.	April 27, 1918.	March 30, 1918.	March 2, 1918.	Feb. 2, 1918.	Jan. 5, 1918.	Dec. 8, 1917.	Nov. 10, 1917.	Oct. 13, 1917.	Sept, 15 1917.	Aug. 18, 1917.Newcastle -Leeds - - - -Manchester Nottingham - - - -Birmingham - - -Cambridge - - - -London - - - -Home Counties, North -Home Counties, South -Reading - - - -Bristol -Carnarvon - - - -Cardiff -. -England and Wales Glasgow - -Edinburgh - - - -Scotland^ -Ireland - - -United Kingdom -England and Wales : Boroughs, other than London, with popula-tion over 50,000. Smaller towns and rural districts.	102i 101&quot; 102i 108&quot; 991 118 94 109 1 lol 118 106 1181 98 1041	101 961 lOOj 104 \00\ 114 91 1061 no&quot; 116 103 1201 97 102	96^ 93 97* 96 95 108 871 103^ 107 1121 99 117 92 98	931 871 94j 98 96 110 91 100 107 110 101 112 89^ 97	95 91 97 iooi 981 108 951 1001 105 1091 103&quot; 108* 931 99	94^ 95* 100* ; 974 108 . 98 1001 103* 109* 102&quot; 102 921 99	99* 96 98 104*, 991 108 99 101 106 111*, 104&quot; 104* 92! 101	1031 95i 97* 103&quot; 101 109 981 102 104 110 101 1031 94l 1001	99 96 99^ 1071 100 11 T* 1001 100 103* no 102 99 95 101	104* 981 98* 105 99* 111* 101 99* 102* 106* 1011 991 97 101	100* 92&quot; 93 100 93 1081 97 97 99 103 97 96 931 96*	110 100 96i 104&quot; 96 111 1011 97! 1001 104i 101 981 97&quot; 100*	109* 103* 971 104 96 llll 98^ 971 100* 104* 100* 100I 98 100*	96 96 96 98 931 108&quot; 93* 95 98* 102* 99 &apos; 100 97 97	81 82 89 89 891 100i 87&quot; 91 97 981 92&quot; 96 90* 88i	83 80 89 88 88 100 84 94 96 . 99 92 99 911 88	951 981 99*	95 971 99	90 95 95	85 98 91	911 98* 95	92 97i 95	95 100 97*	96 991 98-	97 102* 100	98 104 101	92 101 96	951 102* 98*	961 104 99*	95 103 98*	91 99 94	88 96 91	104^	1011	99	94*	951	94	94*	96*	94	96-1	931	98	97	96*	92i	92	104	102	98	96	98	98	100	100	1001-	100*	96	100	100 97		90*	89J	ioo 	97* 109	931 105	92 103	941 104	95 1021	97* 104*	98 1031	98* 104	99 1031	931 99	99 101*	1001 1011	98*	86* 92	85 92*ro* Including Inverness Division for which the returns are too few to allow a separate statement.

</content>
</cab>
