<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/70/0 images: 143-146</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
?THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).

SECRET.

G.T. 5335.

WAR CABINET.

CAMPAIGN AGAINST VENEREAL DISEASE.

Copy of a letter from the President of the National Council for Combating Venereal Diseases to the Secretary, War Cabinet.

NATIONAL COUNCIL FOR COMBATING VENEREAL DISEASES

81 Avenue Chambers,

Southampton Row,

LONDON, W.C. 1.

19th November, 1918.

SG/SS.

The Secretary of the War Cabinet,

10 Downing Street,

Whitehall, S.W. 1.

Sir.

I write at the direction of my council to ask you to lay before the members of the War Cabinet certain proposals with reference o the campaign against Venereal Disease. It is a truism that an increase in the incidence of these diseases is the sequence of all great wars, and the National Council feel that with the aid of our greater knowledge as to the methods of diagnosis and treatment of these diseases we should be able to save the nation from still further loss of life and health by preventable disease after the heavy and inevitable losses in the War.

We therefore recommend that a sufficient financial appropriation should be allowed to the Local Government Board to enable very greatly extended facilities for diagnosis and treatment to be provided throughout the country immediately. At present treatment is restricted to those centres of population where hospitals exist. We recommend that ad hoc Clinics should be established in every town of over 10,000 inhabitants and that whole-time Venereal Officers should be added to the staffs of County and County Borough Councils for the purpose of undertaking and supervising treatment and early preventive treatment. We have asked the Local Government Board to carefully consider the advisability of some form of confidential notification being adopted for infective cases that take their discharge before a cure has been completed. At a later date, if necessary, powers similar to those in operation in the Dominions of enforcing continuous treatment might be obtained from Parliament.

We understand that at any period there would be about 200,000 men in an infective condition in the Navy and Army, we would urge you therefore to so amend the Army Act as to enable men to be detained in the Services until their course of treatment is completed so that they can be returned to the civilian community in a non-infective condition. The confidential form of notification we ask should be considered would enable men sill in need of treatment though no longer actively


infective to be transferred to the Clinic nearest their place of residence when discharged from the Army.  It would also securethat the civilian in an infective condition was also-obliged toobtain adequate treatment and be no longer at liberty to infecthis fellows.      The War Office, the Admiralty and private employersthroughout the country have all acknowledged their responsi-bility to the community by giving opportunities for adequateinstruction on the dangers of Venereal Disease to those in theirempiTvy   Hitherto the Ministry of Munitiens has denied similar facilities to all the employees in national and. controlled firms in spite of representations made by the Rational Council totheir welfare departments and to the Minister of Munitions.  Wewould urge in the interest of national health, that the WarCabinet should express their opinion as to the advisability of arranging that all Munition Workers should be adequatelyinstructed on these matters before they are discharged fromtheir employment.      We would recommend that as early as possible next session a short Bill should be introduced making the consciousand knowing transmission of Venereal Disease a penal offenceon the lines of Clause 5 of the Criminal Law Amendment bill as amended by the national Council.  We would also ask thatthe Committee of both Houses that was considering both this bill and the Sexual offences Bill should be re-establishedimmediately on the assembly of the new parliament.      We would also draw your attention to the advisability ofobtaining Home Office support for some national scheme whichwould provide an opportunity for training in commercial andindustrial activities a number of those girls and youngwomen now dellit with under tho existing Solicitation laws or by voluntary agencies, as we feel that an adequate scheme on these lines would do much to reduce opportunities for the spread of infection.      I append hereto a summary of the resolutions recentlypassed by my Executive Committee which will be submitted for confirmation at the Genera] Meeting of the national Councilto be held in Edinburgh on December 6th, 1918.                            Yours faithfully,                            (3gd.)  SYDEMHAM,                                               President,
      m^OBHJSATIOI AFP VMBRBAL DISgASB.   *Resolutions passed by the Executive  Committee  of  theNational ooune.il for Combating Venereal  Diseases,             November lSbh,  1916.     That the Local Government Board shoal d authorise  the  appoint-merit of whole time Venereal Officers (a man and a woman)  on  the staffs of the medical Officer of each County or County Borough.(The woman could usually combine venereal and infant welfare work.)     That the present Hospital accommodation should be supplemented by &quot;ad hoc&quot; clinics under the supervision cf such Venereal Officersin every town of over 3 0,000 inhabitants and also in the  county boroughs, such clinics bo be open for continuous and early treatmentboth for men and fo.t -*/one and visited at frequent intervals by  theVenereal Officers who should be empowered to call in practitionersresident in each locality to assist them.   It is suggested  that a subsidiary appointment of clinical assistant could be  given  to  aresident practitioner in each centre who would supervise  the con-tinuous and. early treatment in the intervals between the  visits  ofthe Venereal Officer,     In order to carry oat this plan the Military Authorities  are asked to free immediately, as many Venereal specialists as  the  LocalGovernment Board may require, In order that the time interveningbetween the signing of the Armistice and the commencement  ofdemobilisation may be used to establish the clinics that  they may beavailable early in the New Year,     That Hospitals and Kedioal Schools be requested to  arrangespecial post-graduate courses for the training of medical  women  inthe modern methods of treatment and a strong appeal is made to medical women to specialise in this subject.     That some means should be deaased. whereby medical practitionersare encouraged to diagnose Venereal Disease in patients  and also togive early preventive treatment.     In the meantime the Local Government  Board could secure theservices from the Military Medical Department of three or  four of   *the recognised authorities on venereal disease,  and arrange forthem to hold conferences with the local medical men in various partsof the country with a view to devising the best means of securingefficiency and continuity of treatment.     That the Army Act should be so amended as  to  enable men  in  aninfective condition to be retained in the  Navy  and Army pending  thecompletion of treatment in order that they may  return  to  civil life in sound health-    It is understood that  the Army  Act  must, in anycase,  be amended to meet various needs for the  retention  of part.ofthe Forces on demobilisation,  and this could form  an appropriatecategory among others.
     That it should be made a statutory obligation for everyindividual suffering from Venereal Disease to obtain and to con-tinue treatment until cured.6,        That the Local Government Board should, be aoked to consider     immediately whether some form of confidential notification of     infective cases could be adopted under existing powers, and vhethj     at a later date fresh powers could be obtained from Parliament,7,        That the Minister of i,un,i.tions should give definite instruct.)     that all Lien and women working/the Rational and Controlled firms     should receive adequate instruction from responsible medical men     and women.&apos;8.        That Clause 5 of the Criminal Law Amendment Bill, as^amended     by the hationa.1 Council, should be passed as a short Aot&apos;*as&quot;**&quot;early*     as&quot;*po &quot;s si bi e &quot;&quot; next&apos;&quot; S e a si on.   To make it effective an additional     clause is necessary making it a statutory obligation on medical     practitioners to &quot;tarn their patients and to give evidence if re-     quired in a Court of Lew/ under the Act,   (A3 is done in Queens-     land, Victoria and Western Australia,)9.        That the.Joint Committee of both Houses should be reappoinUdl     directly the new parliament assembles.10.       That an amended form cf Clause 3 of the Criminal Law Amencmeni     Bill should be passed next Session,11,       That an organisation is needed which could train large numbeij     of young girls in skilled employment, under discipline, returning     them as self-supporting members &apos;,of tho Community as soon as possible     with no permanent slur on their character,  such an organisation toj     be eligible for recognition by the home Office under Clause III.12.       That the Mental Deficiency Act should be amended to  enable     the protection of the community to be extended to the mentally     defective individual suffering from venereal disease, and the     morally defective person.13. iI&apos;14.     That the Home Office be asked to encourage each town and county to appoint an adequate number of Women Police without delay     That social organisations be asked to develop the service of voluntary Women patrols.1n

</content>
</cab>
