<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/70/0 images: 357-362</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;  229;fTHIS DOOjJjOiT  IS  TKE PROPERTY OF HIP  BRITAjjMIO MA^STY^S GOVgRHITO),SECRET,G.T.6370.W A R   C A B I N E T,paper Bo c 103)  SOIdJlEES1 &amp; SAILOR PAY COMMITTEE,                 Minutes, of the ?6th Meeting held in             Conference Room &quot;B&quot; 2 Whitehall Gardens ,5             on Monday, November 1,8th, 1915, at 4 p,m.                              PRSSEHT.               The Pit. Hon. G.1L Barnes, M.P,    (in  the Chair)The u,t.  Hon,T.J.ttaonamara; M,J?,.         The Rt.  Hon* E,W, Porsxer, M,?.Mr. Stanley Baldwin, id.P* .              Sir A. Griffith Boscawen, M.P.                 Major JoLu Baird, CM.G. ,DoS.Q.;,My?4                    There were also pro sent : r.  Wi A *Bland (Air Ministry)ir*  D.  JSeylan (!Var Office)Ar.  Ft^Js .Sibley (air Ministry)Mr, T.D,James  (Admiralty)Sir R. ivindersley.Mr. Theodore Chambers  (r.&apos;sr Savings                       Committee),Lt,-Col. Leslie Wilson, C.MaG.,D*So03,M.?,                  .  Secretary.lo   THB MINUTES of the 35th Meeting were approved as amended.CREASE OFY TOILORS &amp;LDIERSothod ofyment ofatuities Army &amp;A.P.u *With reference to the Minutes of the 35thLieeting, Minute 1.     MR a IBYLAli, Director of Finance,  V/ar  Office,said that the ..,ar Office had made  arrangements  withthe GyPoOo to issue the&apos;total  gratuity due  to eachsoldier on demobilisetion by means  of  a  credit  ina post Office Savings Bank Book.    The procedure is that within 14 days  of the  soldier  leaving a   ?dispersal station the Paymaster sends  a  schedule  .to the Post office Savings Bank, London, shewing              He gi me n ta 1 Ilumbe r.              Rank.              liame.              Address of Soldier.  -              Amount due.Within 14 days the Savings Bank sends  a  book to thePost Office nearest the manrs  home  containingcredit for the amount due.  At  the  samvtime, a post-card^is sent by the G.P.Ott, to  the  man named statingthatjSe will call at the Post  Office named, he  will get the book provided that he  produces his&apos; card andhis protection certificate.     The  man gives areceipt for the book, and the  matter is  ended.     The same procedure would  be applied in the caseof men already discharged.     As the addresses  of.  thesemen would not be known,&apos; posters would  have  to issuedasking the.,PG4 to communicate  with  their RegimentalPaymasters.-------------  . 1 ;IT.
                                 o                               2) i) 0A  .&quot;!&apos;&apos;&apos;&apos;                     .1 . &apos; &apos;                      In the case of gratuities clue to relatives                 of dead men, the&apos; amounts would have  to be                 distributed in cash ?s they were, in a large                 number of cases, divided amongst numerous                 r eleti ve s ,     Dhi s wo uId be done di rec t by the                 v?.r Office  through the Effects Branch.                      SIR HOBJSRT miL.KRSL.EY speaking as a Member                 of the Any Demobilisation Committee  said that the                 Committee had agreed to the above plan of die-                 tribution of gratuities.  It was proposed also                 to insert a slip (Appendix) which would point                 out the advantage of purchasing v?or Savings                 Certificates,   The Trustee Saving Ben its                 also expressed to him very strongly that as  so                 many of the men had. accounts in their Banks                 it would, to advisable to include in  the notice                 seme advice as to the possibility of transfer                 to them of the amounts paid. ..**s it was probable                 that other Savings Agencies might desire a                 similar notice, these had also been  included on                 the slip.   The Post office thought that, owing                 to the numerous transfers which might take place,                 there would be administrative difficulty but if                 the Committee approved of the scheme, their                 objections  could no doubt be overcome.                      MR. i).-:i,-2S representing the Admiralty in the                 absence of  Dr. ^ecnemara who had not then arrived                 said that this was tho first notification the                 Admiralty had had of this proposal.   It had been                 proposed to pay the gratuity in cash,  kr. James                 expressed the opinion that the Board of Admiralty                 would not object to the proposal as when arrears                 of pensions had been paid tho men had then been                 advised to  invest in har Bonds.                      MR, BLAND Urged that the men might object                 to having their money put into tho Savings Bank                 where only  Z\fo could be earned instead of into                 War Savings which paid bill   The Air Council                 had proposed either paying the money in cash or                 in War Savings Certificates but. in view of the                 fact that the men were invitee] on the slip                 to take their money out and invest it in War                 Savings Certificates he was inclined to accept                 the proposal for the. sake of uniformity with the                . Army.                      MAJOR  BAIRD, who entered at t-ais moment,                 agreed that the method of payment -reposed by                 the har office was the most suits&apos;  &amp; for the                 Air Force,                      THE C0MIAITT3E decided that                          (a)  The Gratuity paid to men of the                          Army and ]10AJ. should be paid by                          means of a credit in the Post Office                          Savings Bank Book.                          (b)  The slip advising transfer of  amounts                          paid should be approved and inserted by                          the Post Office in s&amp;ch book before des-                          patch to the local Post Office.
231IHCRS&amp;SB 01?Y TOLDIERS &amp;ILORSvyment oflatuities men who had it servedersoas.G.T.6B86).          MRofORoTST urged that the decision taken at the 35th Meeting of the Committee,  Minute 1 (o)with reference to the reduced payment to men v;ho hadnot served overseas should be amended to road &quot;whohad not served in a theatre of war&quot;.  Mr. Forsterexplained that tha difficulties to oe.y gratuitiesunder the original decision were so great tliat it wagimpossible for the payment to be made without very greatdelay.  Troops serving in a theatro of v,;ar were paidin acquittance rolls and all other men either at homoor abroad, not in a theatre of war, were paid by meansof the pay and mess book.  It vould be comparativelyeasy to&apos;differentiate between these two but to differ-entiate between men who had served overseas and those whohad not would moan that every caso would have to boconsidered by reference to the Record Offices.     (At this stage of the proceedings Mr.3arnes left      to attend a Cabinet Meeting, and Dr.Macnomors      took tho chair).              tiliQiLJL RA said that at the previousmooting the word &quot;overseas11  had been agreed to.  To alterthis now so that only men who had served in a theatre of operations would receive  tho higher rate would mean that men who had served in Malta and Gibraltar for in-stance, would not get it. Men belonging to the RoyalIlavy or ?uA.F., serving at these places would get thehigher scale and Dr. Macnamara expressed the opinionthat to pay the Army on the  lower scale who had served in similar places would bo -pUte indefensible. Hesuggested that the decision should stand but *. noteshould he added to say that  delay in the payment would occur.          SIR ARTHUR BOfcOitt-ga urged the claims of thoTerritorials garrisoning India who, if the proposedalteration was made would be paid on the lower scaleThoso man belonged to the original first line Terri-torial units, had bean in India ever since the out-break of hostilities and had had no leave to England.Most of them, from no fa alt ot their own, had seen noscrvioe.       (c) Sir Robert IClndorsloy should Interview       the Postmaster Conoral and urge tho d&amp;str&amp;bill.       ty of tho insertion of this slip in all books.       (d) The Financial Secretary to the Admiralty       should submit &amp; scheme for the consiaoration       of1&apos;the Commit too showing the method of payment       of grntuitios to men in the Royal IJovy engaged       for hostilities only.3,        With reference to the scale of payments of gatuities to men who hod served oversoao as detailedin Paper U0.101 (Appendix to
     L^iJOR HuIRD explained that the men  servingat home who formed part of the fighting  lino of thoR.A.tf,, must bo considered to bo serving in a theatre of war.   Those men took part in tho air raids and Zoppollri Raids and could not be excludedfrom the payment of tho higher gratuity,     MR. IJEYLaD urged the difficulties of the Y7ar&apos;Office if the previous decision was not  altered, &quot;Atthe prosont time there wore 3,800,000 men serving andit would bo necessary to deal as well with all dis*-oharged men and with the relatives of men who haddied.   The gratuity should bo paid quickly and every complication which was added tended to put theadministrative machino out of gear.   Speaking from the War Office point of view ho thought  that thetorms &quot;theatre of operations&quot; roust be substitutedfor ^overseas&quot;. -     DR. -LuiOBAliAKA said that, with regard to tho Airtforco, it would bo right that Pilots and Observersserving at home should receive the gratuity at thehigher rate,  but not mechanics who did not take partin flights, &apos;     THE COMMITTEE whilst recognising the difficultyof the War Office, decided that     (a)  Tho decision taken in Minute 1 of the 35th     Meeting of tho Committoo (G.T.6286) with     reference to a reduced payment being made to     men who had not served overseas should not be     amended.     (b)  All men who had served overseas but who     had not served in a theatre of war  should be     paid at the lower rate and should be informed     that their payment at the higher rate would be     adjusted at a later date,     (c)  Service of distribution-Commissionod lilots and     Observers and aerial crews in tho R.A;]?; engaged     on Homo Defence and of men who have served on     board ship should count as service  overseas for     the purpose, of the payment of the gratuity but     this should not apply to air Mechanics employed     on Homo Service,  -     LiR. IPORSTIR do sired that his dissent shouldbe recorded from decision  (a).4.  .   DR. MCHAKaBA said that the Admiralty proposed  &apos;to pay tho gratuities to the Chief Petty Officef&amp;y^ &apos;Petty Officers and Lion engaged for hostilities  onl;y&quot;\on the same scale as those paid by the&quot;army and R.A.&apos;F,The oost of this would be  2,150,000.  -  7/it&apos;h regard totho permanent men of the navy and Hon-^ommi,ssioneeOfficers and Men of tho Royal Marines, it $/ould bo\                                         necessary  &quot;
necessary to ascertain.exactly the amount which would have &quot;been due to them if theyhad been paid a gratuity on the same scale and to treat thin amount as a capital sumextending over a number of yearst   TheAdmiralty could then consider the income which would be payable from thin sum andwould devote the money thus obtained toraising the permanent pay of all ratings.Already the recent increases of pay whichhad been given to Warrant Officers had beencausing expectation among the ratings below that rank, and the Board of Admiralty felt thatthe fairest way to deal with this question of gatuities with reference to the long-servicemen was by means of a permanent rise in pay.The Board of Admiralty proposed that thegratuity to men engaged for hostilitiesonly would be paid in full at the rates paidto the Army, and that Prize money should bepaid in addition.  Two precedents already existed for this, as this was the methodadopted in the Boxer and the Boer Wars.     THE COMMITTEE decided -         To defer further discussion on this         question pending the receipt of a         Memorandum from the Admiralty         giving full details as to the pay-         ment of gratuities to&quot;Warrant         Officers, Petty Officers and men of         the Royal&apos;Navy engaged for hostilities-         ties only and of a statement showing         the sum to be allocated towards an         increase in the pay of ratings on         long service engagements.2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.    19th November, 1918.
234     APPENDIX TO PAPER No.  105,Pamphlet issued by War Savings  Committee.SAVE  YOUR  MONEY  UNTIL  YClf  HEED . IT.     The man with &quot;a bit of money put by&quot; is free from manyanxieties.  If hard times should come, he has &quot;something to fall back upon.&quot;   And if ever he requires a few pounds - tofurnish a home - to open a business - to give his children a start in life - or for any other purpose - he need be beholdento nobody,.   The money is there.   He can draw it whenever heneeds it.     You may not need to cpend the money which now stands to your credit in the Post Office Savings Bank.  In.any case you may not need to spend it all.  What you can leave may be onlya small amount, but if you add to it from time to time, It maybe.the basis of a little fortune.  It may grow until you have enough money to buy yourself a house, or to send your children to a good school - one cannot do more than hint at possibilities.        YOU MAKE YOU MONEY GROW WREN YOU INVEST IT Iii THESE:.(1)  The Post Office Savings Bank.     As long as you leave your money on deposit, it will     increase every year at the rate of 2^ per cent,  or 6d.     in the  1.   You will be able to draw out part or the     whole of your capital whenever you require it.(2)  War Savings Certificates.     You can. buy these for 15/6 each at any Money Order Poat     Office,, or from any shopkeeper acting as an Official     Agent.   They increase in value every year until, at tht..     end of/five-years, you Ret  1 for every 15/6 invested.     This .1s equivalent to    per cent. Compoundinterestv and     it,is -free from Income Tax.  You can get your money back     in full at any time with any Interest due.(3)  Trustee Savings Bank.     If you have an account at a Trustee Savings Bank you may     care to transfer  your money to that account so as to     have all your money in the one account.  UTou will be able     to draw your money out at any time if you want to buy     a house or a business or have any other, good use for it.(4)   Friendly Societies, Co-operative Societies^ Building        Societies.^and other Saving Agencies.     If you already have money in.one of these  Societies you     may prefer to  entrust your money to the Society to which     you already belorg

</content>
</cab>
