<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/70/0 images: 409-410</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
/erty ofment.)13Polltioal intelligence Department,FOREIGN OFFICE.Germany /025.Extracts from a letter from Mr. Harold Williams, &quot;DailyChroniole&quot;correspondent in Geneva.       Since  arriving  here  I have met  a number  of  people  and heard  many things that  it  may be of interest to you to know.       I am perhaps only repeating what you realise very  clearly in London when I say  that  the German  Revolution is a  very  rot- ten thing.    I am getting  more and more  afraid of it  every day0 I an not speaking so  much  of  the danger  of Bolshevism in Ger- many Itself,  since most Germans seem  to  regard it as  a useful product for  erport while in Germany it may he  used simply  as,a means for  provoking a reaction and  restoring the Empercr who, as is  perfectly clear now,  has not abdicated.   But the  danger is this;  that the revolution is not  in  any sense a real one. The German spirit is  unchanged.  There  is not a  sign ef re- pentanoe.    Demooracy is a new mode now,  and people are  simply $hanging their aress.    They  are not  really angry with the old^gime,  the  whole thing is shnply a dodge to save the Germans&apos; face..   They do not admit  they are &quot;beaten,  they hate  us  as much ae ever, and under the  new forms, so  long as they last,  they will pursue  the old pwlioy...   I have  never felt the poison^ fthe modern Gorman spirit so strongly as I feel it here and now.It affects me like the odour of Bolshevism, which, of course,is one of its byerproduats.   As far as I can see - except per-haps among some soldiers and sailors and workmen - there is  .nothing human about this so-called revolution, nothing tragic*r amusing.   It is simply a du.ll form of mechanical adaptationin which the heroes of yesterday are playing new parts.   Whatoonoerns us is that in this new form of peace offensive the/old
old intrigues continue, and may be even more dangerous.   Pro-       *professor Herron, with whom I have had long conversations, isthoroughly alarmed, and thinks it quite possible that the Ameri-ean Army and our Army may not be able to demobilise for a yearto come.   In any case it  seems clear that any relaxation of theterms of the armistice is  quite impossible under present oon-ditions.      Professor Herron thinks there may be some hope in Bavaria,where honest men are in charge.   I hope to see Professor PSrsterin Berne, and will in some  way let you know the substance of the conversation.   But I am not at all sure how far Eisner, Jaffeand ^uidde really control things;  the mentality of Bavaria doesnot seriously differ from that of Prussia, and the best of theSocialists are hampered by their devitalising Marxian creed.      Pardon my writing at length of a subject which is ratheroff my particular beat, but here, for the present, I can think of little el Be.   And I am particularly concerned as to the dan-ger of this new and diabolioal form of annexationist policy forthe East of Europe - wreckage, I mean, followed at a given signalby reaction.

</content>
</cab>
