<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/30/15 images: 152-159</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS Tha PrtUi-^KTtt        compulsory  aitlTAwUlC ivi/uj apt* &apos; a GOVERNMENTTo be kept under lock and keySECRET&apos;,VPr42T485October 27th,  1942. WAR   ^CABilJETConstruction of Merchant Ship Aircraft Carriers.Joint Memorandum bj^Pirst Lord of theVfrdmiraltyand Minister of War Transport.Experience has shown that the aircraft is a most effectiveweapon in the defence of our merchant shipping against U-boat attack;and it has been apparent for some time past that it would be necessaryto provide air protection for our convoys throughout the whole lengthof their voyage.      Since much of this at present lies outside the range of shore-based aircraft the requirement can only be met by the provisionof shipborne aircraft.20      The  first solution of the problem was sought  in the developmentof the auxiliary aircraft carrier^ a converted merchant ship,  and a large programme of these is now in hand mainly from American production.      the aim is to provide 26 of these vessels by the middle of 1943 and a further8, or possibly as many as 17, by the end of that year.3.      It is evident, however s  that time is the essence of the problem and our two departments have together been seeking wavs and means by which some measure of air protection might be provided for each convoy at an earlier date than the auxiliary aircraft carrier prograirm.e would secure.As a result it has been decided that it will be practicable to fit certainmerchant ships with a flight deck to operate a small number of aircraft,The essential feature of these  ships is that they should continue to beemployed as cargo carriers.      The maximum loss of cargo carrying capacity is estimated to amount to about 30/b for dry cargoes and 17^/b for tankers.4.      Arrangements have been made to provide 12 merchant ship aircraft carriers (M.A.Cs.) from United Kingdom resources during 1943:-(a) 6 Cargo M.A,Cs, (to be built) - fitted with flight deck(400 ft. x 62 ft. ) , and hangar. speed 12 knots, each to operate 4 Swordfish aircraft.(b) 6 Tanker M.A.Cs.   (to be converted)  - fitted with flightdeck (460 ft.  x 62 ft.), no hangar, speed about 12 knots,each to operate 3 Swordfish aircraft.No difficulty is foreseen in operating Swordfish aircraft from either type.5.      It is expected that the 6 tankers will be completed by the earlySpring of 1943 and 2 of the 6 cargo ships by mid-Summer.      For purposes of convoy protection not less than 40 of these specially-fitted vessels arerequired, and there is no prospect of obtaining quick delivery of any suchnumber from the limited facilities of the U.K.(6.      On the other hand,  as a result of his recent visit to the U.S.A,,the Director of Merchant Ship Building is satisfied that 30 M.A.Cs.   could he produced in that country by June 1943 by switching over the productionof a selected merchant shipbuilding yard to this type.      Any loss.of carry-ihg capacity should be more than counter-balanced by the reduction in losses of ships which the increased air protection for convoys would give.7o      We strongly recommend therefore that an approach should be made tothe United States Authorities  as a matter of great urgency for theconstruction of 30 M.A.Cs.  to be completed in that country during the first half of 1943, divided between tankers and dry cargo ships in such proportion as may be agreed with the U.S.  authorities.,Copy No.

- 2 -80      The further question arises whether M.A.C.  ships are to be operated under the white or the red ensign.      The ships will have notonly their aircraft but also R.D.P., six Oerlikons, one twelve-pounderand a complement of whom rather more than half will inevitably beService personnel.      Consequently, although the M.A. C.  ships may beregarded as a logical development in the defence of merchant ships, itis possible that both neutrals and the enemy may contend that they arewarships.9.      The Ministry of War Transport agree that, whether M.A.C.  shipswear the red or v/hite ensign, it will be inadvisable for  them to tradeneutral ports.      In practice this means only that they v/ili be unableto load in Argentine Spanish and Portuguese ports.      Should M.A. C.  shipsbe forced to put into neutral ports through damage or stress of weather,they would at least be given the same facilities for repairs etc.  aswarships in similar circumstances.10.      The main risk if M.A.C. ships are operated under the red ensignis that the enemy will treat them as warships and the Merchant Servicemembers of their complement as francs francs-tireurs.      The greater the effectof air action on the U-boat campaign, the more the enemy may be tempted to try to damage the morale of M.A.C.  crews by court martialling and shootingany Merchant Service personnel whom they may capture from such ships.These vessels will normally sail in convoy and the risk of men from atorpedoed ship being captured may not be great, but it cannot be whollydisregarded.11.      The white ensign would provide a secure status for the crews andwould have certain operational advantages, particularly in the relation between the Captain and the Senior Officer of the convoy escort.      Thered ensign would have the Advantages (a)  that the general management ofthe ships would remain with those accustomed to handle ships engaged inthe particular trade concerned and (b) that the Naval manning difficulties,already acute, would not be increased.120      The manning factor is decisive, since it would be quite impossible to find naval crews for the auxiliary aircraft carriers and atthe same time to provide full naval crews for the M.A.C.  ships.      Tt will,indeed, be difficult enough to man the auxiliary carriers by themselves.The Ministry of War Transport have less difficulty in finding crews owingto their compulsory powers over Merchant Navy personnel, powers which theAdmiralty do not possess for bringing Merchant Seamen into the naval service.13.      We therefore propose that the M.A.C.  ships should be operatedas merchant ships under the red ensign, which will put the flying personnel in much the same position as the guns crews of other defensively equippedmerchant ships.      The Ministry of War Transport will consider whether it isadvisable to warn the merchant crews of the slight risk that they may runand to consult the Unions.14.     Summary.We ask the War Cabinet to approve(i) that the United States should be urged to undertake atonce the construction of 30 M.A.Cs.  to be completed during the first half of 1943.(ii) that the M.A.C.  ships should sail under the red ensign.



Offices of the War Cabinet.,Great George Street, S.W 130TH OCTOBER.,  1942.SSECRETWAR CAB IKS TIt is requested that, theattached revised vurion of P iporNo. W.P.(42) 486 may he, substitutedfor the copy now in your possessionand the latter returned to thisOffice    (Room 61A)


</content>
</cab>
