<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/216/7 images: 121-126</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTc(83) 7 COPY NO18 March 1983CABINETFUTURE OF THE INNER LONDON EDUCATION AUTHORITYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Education and Science^e Inner London Education Authority (ILEA) - details at Annex A - islegally a special committee of the Greater London Council (GLC) . TheVolition of the GLC would open the way for improving the arrangements foreducation in inner London.    I recommend a scheme which retains the advantages f what exists and removes its worst defects.A single education authority for the whole of inner London has provedadvantageous in two important respects:1.      It has secured further and higher education, much of it servingstudents from far beyond inner London, which is - despite some notoriousblemishes - in general good and economically run.2.     It serves, much more than the GLC, as an instrument for redis-tributing for local government purposes the exceptionally high rateableresources of Westminster and the City of London: some  400 million ayear, which could otherwise be obtainable only from a Government-imposed levy on these two authorities, or from the Exchequer or other,poorer, local authorities outside London, is made automaticallyavailable through the education precept for inner London.A BETTER SINGLE AUTHORITY3*     But as now constituted the single authority has shown glaring weaknesses.n Particular its schools, notably the secondary schools, are not performingWei ij. .despite very high expenditure and much waste.    To tackle this problem IProp0se.1.     That the ILEA should be replaced by a Joint Board, consistingentirely of nominees of the 12 inner London boroughs and the City ofLondon.    The authorities whose ratepayers pay the education preceptwould then in effect be responsible also for the education element intheir rate levy.    This bringing together of managerial and financialresponsibility is bound to encourage a greater degree of financialPrudence.2-     That,  if we do not decide to introduce controls on local authorityrates or expenditure, we should consider making the Joint Board sPrecept subject to control by the holder of my office. This&apos; L | II CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALexceptional measure is justified on the ground that, as a uniquely largesingle-purpose precepting authority which was not directly elected, theJoint Board ought to be subject to an appropriate and whollyexceptional external control.    The burden of thus becoming involved inthe authority&apos;s policies would, I believe, be worth the gain ofgradually bringing education expenditure in inner London under control.More detailed work would be needed before this proposal could beimplemented.I do not recommend the alternative course of abolishing a singleeducation authority for inner London.    The natural way of doing this would beto transfer education responsibility to the existing authorities - the innerLondon boroughs - so that they would have the same functions as the outerLondon boroughs; the City of London has told us that it would not wish to bean education authority.   A few inner London boroughs, like Westminster, andKensington and Chelsea, could be expected to become efficient educationauthorities after the upheaval of transfer.    But most of them - Lambeth,Southwark, Lewisham, Greenwich, Camden, Tower Hamlets, Hackney and Islington - Ia^e likely to make as poor a job of education as those outer London boroughs,ike Newham and Barking, whom they most resemble, especially since they willnave to cope with such special problems of falling school rolls and theucation  f ethnic minorities and variously handicapped children..     Having no single education authority for inner London would also depriveUs of the advantages mentioned in paragraph 2.1. We would gratuitously break up arrangements for further and highereducation which, apart from the well-known blemishes, no-one hascriticised.    It would make no sense to separate further and highereducation from schools eg by leaving it with a single joint board andtransferring only schools to the boroughs.   All these aspects ofeducation are interrelated and ought to be run by the same authority,as they always have been in England.2. We would saddle ourselves with the resource equalisation problemwhich having a single authority solves automatically.    As Annex Bexplains, we might, for example, have to oblige Westminster and theCity to pay over something like  400 million to other authorities on thebasis of criteria which we would have to invent and defend.Nor can I recommend two variants of abolishing a single authority whichaVe been suggested:It     To create, say, three joint boards, each composed of nominees ofseveral inner London boroughs.    An artificial arrangement which noPrevious experience commends would be hard to defend.    It would stillneedlessly disrupt the further and higher education arrangements. Itwould not solve the resource equalisation problem, because Westminsterwould automatically finance only the group of which it was a member,and we could hardly force the City which does not want to become aneducation authority to join and finance a second group.2.     To allow individual boroughs to opt out of the single authoritycould create a capricious and disorderly result.    It would leave us withthe resource equalisation problem since Westminster and the City would2L CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALcertainly opt out.    There are grave dangers for London and elsewhere ina precedent which allows the currently ruling party in a localauthority, and not Parliament, to determine the pattern and functions oflocal government.Abolition of a single authority, however effected, has one crucialPolitical disadvantage.    As in 1981, its publicly proclaimed possibilityWould unleash an orchestrated protest campaign which many parents wouldsupport; this would rob us and our Parliamentary supporters in London of thekudos of abolishing the GLC.    My proposals in paragraph 3 above, though bold,Would not hand our opponents a ready-made issue on a plate.My proposals would entail legislation and administrative effort. Butb th would be much less complicated and extensive than if we abolished aSlngle authority, and would improve our chances of achieving the timetableWe have set ourselves.CONCLUSION^&apos;     I invite my colleagues to agree that:1. If the GLC is abolished, a single local education authorityconstituted as a joint board should run education in inner London(paragraph 3(1)) .2. We should consider making the Joint Board&apos;s precept subject tocontrol (paragraph 3(2)).K JUePartment of Educat ion and Science18 March 19833L CONFIDENTIAL
r(confidential) 83 IANNEX A &apos;Institution and functions of ilea^     ILEA is the local education authority for the area covered bys 6 &lt;r^ty of London and the 12 inner London Boroughs.    It is aClal committee of the GLC,  its membership consisting of:all of the  (35)  councillors elected to the GLC from theinner London area;i-1,      one member appointed by each of the 12 Boroughs and theCity from amongst their own members.e&lt;3u        January 1981 ILEA was providing primary and secondary257Cntion for 314&apos;000 pupils  (Essex,  the next largest LEA, hadarid        Pupils)  and further and higher education for 140,000 fullspe *?art-time students.  Like other LEAs it makes provision forServ^al education,  adult education (300,000 students),  the youthlce and the careers service.3.s6cq ?&apos;?LEA maintains 45 nursery schools, 812 primary schools, 179hig ndarY schools, 112 special schools, 27 colleges of further andcinrj e^ education, 30 adult education institutes, 116 youth centreste^ov. ks,&apos; residential sports and outdoor centres, 2 museums, 54Lond.0ers&apos; centres and 24 careers offices. It also grant-aids the 5est,^ .Polytechnics and gives financial assistance to 8 specialist-.-ishments of further education.4- T(inci    . 1980/81 full-time equivalent staffing levels in ILEAuding staff in the polytechnics) were:teaching staff 33,500others 32,2005.the st ^ ^eterm:Lnes its own budget and fixes its own precept (which^as to levY on its behalf).  Its net budgeted expenditure inOf 7i 3 is around  775m,  financed largely on the basis of a precept^itec?* This compared with a GRE of  514m.  Block grant is not paid^oid-h tQ ILEA&lt;  In 1982/83 the inner London Boroughs received, afterack,  no block grant in respect of education.I(confidential)_.   : I
(confidential&quot;)  &quot;, ITliE FINANCING OF EDUCATION IN INNER LONDONTliE PRESENT POSITIONc!     ILEA&apos;S planned net expenditure of some  775m in 1982/83 will beariced wholly from the rates.  It will receive no grant because itsPenditure will be over 50% above its GRE and,  under the blockfit arrangements,  it therefore incurs negative marginal rates ofnt.   (if it were to spend at its GRE of over  500m it wouldred^VS wel1 over  100m in grant which,  as things stand, islstributed to other authorities.)2.e&quot;     The rate income required to finance ILEA in 1982/83 will not beWest       shared Detween the Boroughs.  Because the City andrattminster in particular have such high (mainly non-domestic)teae^^e resources,  they will contribute far in excess of what isUn&lt;jred to finance education within their areas. Representingrater 10% of ILEA&apos;S population they contribute about 50% of itsGor6&quot;&quot;k rne income.    Poorer Boroughs,  like Wandsworth, contributerrespondingly less.3,the   There is also a separate scheme for the reallocation of some ofGov     nefits of London&apos;s high rateable values under the Londont0 ^-^ent Act 1963.  The City and Westminster contribute some  60mtev &quot;ls scheme;  all other inner Boroughs benefit.  The form ofthe vJUe sharing operated under this scheme is however unrelated toty6s, &quot;lock grant principles,  and the total contributions byte   ^inSter and the City fall far short of the amounts that would bel*&quot;ed by full equalisation principles.t&apos;hePROBLEM OF BREAK UP4.t0 .Volition of the GLC and ILEA and transfer of their functionstran   Boroughs  (or other successor bodies) would also lead to theScned        f the appropriate shares of GRE and of the poundage^otu ile*  But,  as already noted,  for Westminster and the City thebei0     rate poundage that they need to levy for their services issc^     the notional rate poundage implied by the block grant poundage9ove u;i-e; negative grant entitlement,  a new principle in localr 6e,3rnment finance prohibited by present legislation,  would beJ?outl(c, comPel Westminster and the City to levy the notional rateimplied by the schedule.  This divergence would be widened.^Ea     transfer of functions to the Boroughs.  For 1982/83 GLC andWes^ are levying precepts of 34.8p and 71p for their functions. Butshar lnster and the City could probably pay for their own devolvedr&lt;aSn    f those functions with local rates of about 29p and lpPectively.5,from ?n^ess other measures were taken,  the transfer of functionssubst   e GLC and ILEA to the Boroughs would thus result in very^c t0 a^tial benefit to Westminster and the City (and to any other^na e?     9 ing out of block grant including Camden and Kensingtonejctetif &apos;l&quot;Sea) .  Tnis extra benefit would of course be reduced to thethat some functions of GLC and ILEA were left to joint bodies^hd -^recepting powers that would spread the rate burden across high w resource areas of London.
I (confidential)I 6.      If it were desired to prevent these uncovenanted benefits f the high resource authorities from arising,  and assuming that asystem of negative block grants for high resource or high spendi11?authorities is still ruled out,  it would be necessary to make moextended use of arrangements to equalise rate burdens withinLondon.  Section 66(1)  of the London Government Act 1963 already tJgives the Secretary of State for the Environment very wide power3make &quot;a scheme or schemes for the purpose of reducing disparities^the rates levied in different rating areas of greater London&quot;; ain principle this might be used to obtain contributions from ^Westminster and the City (and other London authorities out ofgrant)  for lower resource London Boroughs.7.      The scale of such contributions would however be much great ^than the present limited London equalisation scheme.  The presentand ILEA precepts can be regarded as transferring about  490m1982/83 from Westminster and the City to the rest of London. Unathe new arrangements these transfers would have to be madeexplicitly by the equalisation scheme,  in addition to the presentransfer of some  60m.  It seems likely that transfers on this s twould require a much more precise policy rationale than the presscheme,  the principles of which might need to be incorporated instatute.  There is no obvious formula on which a satisfactory lonyterm policy could be based.17 March 19832^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^

</content>
</cab>
