<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/45/0 images: 186-195</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
ts DOCUMENT 15 THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 jg&amp;YjggRMMg)COPY NO,   9^6 A B I 5 B I,,,,, 20(23)Meeting of the Cabinet to he held at 10, DpwningStreet, S.T&quot;./l, on Wednesday, the 18th April,1923 at 11*30 a.in.AGENDA111 BO a.mi  ....... 1. AGRICULTURAL POLICY(Reference: Cabinet 18(23) Concl,l(b).)Report of Agricultural (Economists- Report)Committee.(C.P*199(23) to he circulated)2-  RENT RESgRlOTIOH (C CNTI flUA BCB) bill&amp;mo. by Minister of Health(CP. 197(23) - already circulated)B. WORKMEN 1 S COMPENSATION.Memo, by the Home SecretaryfC;,&apos;Pi 190(23) - already circulated)Memo, by the Lord Chancellor(C.P, 198(23) - already circulated)(Signed) M.P.A.Hankey,Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens,  S.v;.-/l17th April, 1923.
DQCBMBPT IS THE &apos; ROPER TY&quot; OF HI3 BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;    GOVERNMENT)rSECRETCOPY NO. iCAST. P E 1     2Cf23)COPCIUSIOHS of a Meeting of the Cabinet heldat 10, Bow king Street,  S0P&apos;,/l on-Wednesday!April 18th,  1923 at 11..30. a,,rgPRESENT:-The Prime Minister  fin the Chair)%b Most Hon.the Harquess^ Of. Salisbury,KcC,  G.C.Y.O.,  C.B.. , lord president of the Council.he Rt .Hon*Stanley Baldwin, M*Pl,Chancellor of the Exchequer.She Most Hon.I  the &quot;Marquess Curgon of Kedleston,K,. G, ,  G i C. S 1 . ,  G . C . I, E.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs,&quot;he RfJPon,    .the Earl of -Derby, K.G. ,G.C.B..,   G.C..V.0.&quot;,  Secretary ofState for Mar.She Rt.Hon,.&apos;LaS.Amery, a,P., First Lordof the Admiralty.,She RtoRon.Seville Chamberlain,Minister of Health&apos;,the P,t.Eon,I   Sir Montague Barlow, ICB,E. ,r., Minister of Labour,The Ht.Hon.Vi sc ount Cave, G, C. M, G,,Lord Chancellor..The RtMion.V/v 0. Bridgeman, M. P,,Secretary of State for home Affairs,,His Grace&quot; he Duke of Devonshire,K, G.    G.C.M.G.    CC..V.0. ,Secretary of State forthe Colonies....The Rt3Hon.&apos;Viscount Peel,   G. BrE..,Secretary of State for -Ind ia.The Rt,Hon.Sir Philip Lloyd-Greame,K.B.E,, M.C., M.P.,President of the Board ofTrade,The Rt,Hon.Sir Robert Sanders, 3ta,MfP0, Minister of Agricul-ture and Fisheries..She Rt.Hon,Vise cunt Novar,  G.C.M. G, ,Secretary for Scotland,2h e f 611 owing we re also present :-&apos;%o Rt,fnoia.S1 Ii Iuacluu 11 Ufc! g, IZ. 0. t Ifrg,At t u vi&apos;i     Qioia il x&apos; a 1.-Lieut.-ColonelTh e Rt. H on.... Le s lie r lie on,C0 M,G..., B.S, 0,, M,P.,Par! parliament a ry Se c ret a ry,..Treasury.   (For. Items 2 and 3)Sir.M,P. A.HanPe-r, &quot;&apos;-C.0,-:v ..........    ..    ,. .a Secretary
(This ftoqiucent, Is the Property of His britannic  testy&apos;s Government.)SB: OP Jj T -CABINET gQ, ,(28)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet,held at 10v Downing Street, S.W.1, onWEDNESDAY, APRIL 10. 19S3, at 11-30 a.m.AGRICUL-       1. On a consideration of a Report of the Cabinet.L SITUA-Committee on the Interim Beport of the Tribunal ofEconomists on Agriculture (Paper C.P.-199(23)), thehous Cabinet agreed -France:Inat 18 (a) As regards Wheat Offa,ld, to approve the), Con- Report of the Cabinet C omit tee (Para .4)hon 1.) that the Tribunal *s reoonmendetlone shouldnot be accepted:(b) As regards frfiflftl ^frtes, ln,,,gpiftUmfl.- thatthe deficit Involved in the reduction ofthe assessment of agricultural land $mm$OHpe^s^^e^ntp^^^ (Cabinet 18(8$), Conclusion 1(a)(2), should be made good from public funds and should be calculated on the same scale ae for Englandand Wales.   The actual sum involved to be calculated by the Treasury in consultationwith the Scottish Office.   The Chancellorof the Exchequer and the Secretary forScotland to have authority to announce this decision:(c) (l) To decide in principle that the paymentof the deficit on the reduction of assess-menfc of agricultural land from 50 per cent,to 25 per oent. should be made from public funds for the whole financial year 1923-3&amp;and not merely for the second half-year, not-withstanding that in England and Wales thedemand notes for the rates for the half-yearended Michaelmas have probably already beenissued:(ii) That the practical means by which theabove decision could be carried out shouldbe examined on the same afternoon by thefollowing Committee:--1-
181a 0 the Minister of Health,The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,The Secretary for Scotland,A Representative of the Treasury:(iii) That the Chancellor of the exchequer should he authorised to announce the policyin (i), provided that, when examined by theCommittee, it was not found to be impracticable-cable:(d) As regards Malting Barley:(i) As proposed by the Cabinet Committee,to approve the recommendation of the tribunal of Economists for an Excise Duty of 10/- per quarter on imported malting barley, with a preference of one-third on barley imported from the Dominions: *(ii)That the announcement of this decision should be made by the Minister of Agri-culture and Fisheries in his statement on Thursday, April 19th, instead of bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer, as recommended by the Cabinet Committee.Further, that the Minister of Agricul-ture and Fisheries should be authorised, tthor-if pressed, to inform the House of AatCommons that the Excise Duty on malting .abili- barley would be available towards any     u. their general expenditure to which the Gov-     ,se Dutyeminent might be put in regard to . mootingAgriculture..(e) (i) As regards Pptatpes., that, in accordancewith the proposals of the Cabinet Committee,the recommendation of the Tribunal of Eoono-mists that imports of foreign potatoes shouldbe permitted only under a general licence for special periods, should not be accepted:(ii) That in announcing this decision-theMinister of Agriculture and Fisheries shouldbe authorised to make clear that this decision was not necessarily a final one, and that theeffect of the imports of foreign potatoes onajgrieultuvy in Great Britain would be care-fully watched:(f) As regards Milk Production, to approve therecommendations of the Cabinet Committee that,with a view to promoting the extension of milk-collecting depots and cheese factorieson a co-operative basis, and also for suchenterprises as co-operative bacon factories and farmers&apos; a^^ction marts,-(i) In the case of the larger enterprisesinvolving loans of more than  5,000, themachinery of the Trade Facilities Act shouldbe used:.- (ii) That for smaller schemes loans shouldbe made direct from the Ministry of Agri-culture and Fisheries and the Scottish Officerespectively, on similar terms to the loansgranted by the Trade Facilities Committee:(iii) That the Ministry of Agriculture andFisheries should be authorised to make loans
for this purpose up to an amount notexceeding  200,000 in all, and theScottish Office up to an amount notexceeding  35,000 in all, and that thedetails should he settled by the Ministryof Agriculture and Fisheries and theScottish Office respectively in consult-ation with the Treasury:(g) As regards Agricultural Wages, to approve the recommendation of the Cabinet Committeethat the registration of Agreements reached by the existing Conciliation committees should be made&quot;compulsory:(h) As regards the Relief of Rural, Unemployment,to take note that the Tribunal&apos;s recommend-ation will be considered by the UnemploymentCommittee of the Cabinet:(i) As regards Local Administrative Machinery,to take note that the Secretary for scotland has under consideration the question of theresuscitation of the County agricultural committees in Scotland:(j) As regards Agricultural Economy and Research,to approve the proposal of the Cabinet Com-mittee that the recommendation of the tribunal of Economists, in favour of the extension of research work in the direction of testing newsystems of farm management, particularly asregards the maintenance of livestock on arable land, should be considered by a Joint Committeeof Officers of the Ministry of Agriculture andFisheries and the Board of Agriculture forScotland:(k) To take note that the Tribunal of Economistson Agriculture Is pursuing its investigations.
1 OQI U (JIpHE RENTIbstriotioksICT.Ient restric-jion (continu-Inge) bill.previous Re fere no e0.Cabinet 12183), Con-[elusion 1.)8. After consideration of a Memorandum By the Ministerof Health, covering the draft of a one-clause Bill prolong-ing the duration of-the Increase of Rent and MortgageInterest (Restrictions) Act until July 31st next (paper cp.-197 (23) ), the Cabinet agreed  (a) That, in view of the fact that the present act expires in England on June 24th and inScotland on May 28th, and having regard tothe Parliamentary time-table, the Increaseof Rent and Mortgage Interest Restrictions(Continuance) Bill should be introduced:(b) That the Minister of Health should intro-duce the Bill under the Ten Minutes Ruleon Thursday, April 19th, notice being given on the present date.-4-
jRKMBM&apos;S 3. After consideration of Memoranda by the Home SecretaryImpensation .(Paper CP.-190(83)) and the Lord Chancellor (Paper C.P.-eviouaIf ere noes:cabinet 3 (23)noltision 1(b):cabinet 19 (23)inclusion 3.)198(23)) on the subject of Workmen&apos;a Compensation, theCabinet agreed  (a) Alteration, of Benefits:    as proposed bythe.Home Secretary, that the War AdditionAct, which adds 75 per cent, to the corn-pens atl on payable under the principal Actduring total disablement, should be repealed,and that the provisions of the principal Actshould be amended so as  -(i) To give additional benefits up toan inclusive maximum of  500 infatal cases where children are left:(ii)To increase the maximum for the weekly allowance in case of disablement from .0/-s-.. to 30/-s., or. 35/-a,*hayins regard the alteration in the value of money?(iii)  To make some addition, say 50 per cent.,to the weekly allowance in the low-wagecases which will not be benefited bythe increase of the maximum under (ii),up to a maximum of 25/-s Jr(b) Limitation of Insurance Premiums:    as pro-posed by the Home Secretary, that the Govern-ment Representatives should continue their negotiations with representatives of theInsurance Companies on the same lines asthey have adopted hitherto,(as explained in Paper C,P.-190(23)) on the understand-ing that if a satisfactory settlement cannotbe reached by agreement it will be necessaryto deal with the matter in the Amending Bill:(o)  &quot;Personal injury by accident arising out ofand in the course of employment&quot;, -That the Home Secretary should discuss withthe representatives of the employers theposition of workmen in cases where the injuryarises from some breach of rules or instruc-tions, and that he should be authorised toDrake it clear that the Cabinet is anxious toreturn to the intentions of Parliament asembodied in the Act of 1906.Before taking any steps to introduce a Bill,the Horre Secretary should raise the matter again at the Committee of Home Affairs.toThese figures have been raised from 30/-s. and 20/-srespectively        proposed by the Home Secretary in paper CP .-190(23) .
COUNCILS      4. Aftervoonsideratioh of the- Draft Conclusions of a*1923.     Meeting?: of:&apos;the Committee&apos; of Home Affairs on April 17, 1923(H.A.C. 8th- Conclusions (23)), the Cabinet agreedTo approve the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs in favour ofthe introduction of the Town Councils(Scotland) Bill. 1925, in the form ofthe draft annexed to Paper C.P.-167(25).
THE APMINI3-       - 5.   After consideration of the Draft Conclusions of aTRATION OPJUSTICE BILL. Meeting of the Comrrittse of Home Affairs held on Tuesday,April 17, 1923 (H.A.C. 8th Conclusions (23)), the cabinet agreed  To approve the recommendation of theCommittee of Home Affairs in favourof the introduction by the Lord chancellor in the House of Lords of the Administrationof Justice Bill in the form of a draft annexed to Paper C.P.-192 (23).
STANDING-JOINT. COM-jlITTEB ONINDIANAFFAIRS.6. The Cabinet agreed  That the Secretary of State for India,in consultation with the Lord Chancellor,should draft Terms of Reference to theJoint Standing Committee of both Houseson Indian Affairs, which the previous government had left to draft its ownTerms of Reference, the scope of whichhad proved inconveniently wide.    Further,that the Secretary of State for India shouldtake such steps as are required to obtainParliamentary sanction for these Terms ofReference.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W..1,April 18, 1923.

</content>
</cab>
