<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 67/6/25 images: 256-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C . L ,  128SEC RET.ff.P.(G)(40) 125.4TH MAY,  1940.WAR CABINEToUNITED KINGDOM COAL EXPORTSMEMORANDUM BY THE CHANCELLOR OF TEE MQMMWM-.&apos;-The Committee on Economic Policy at their meeting(E*P.(M)(40) 12th Meeting)  on Friday, 3rd May. discussed,the French coal requirements, and their &quot;bearing on the domestic position, on exports to .hher destinations andon shippingsThe French representatives on the Anglo-french -ordinating Committee asked for the supply  ..f 2,000,000tons a month from the United Kingdom,.     in informal discussicthis demand has been reduced to 1,700.1000 tons, with,  inaddition, 50$ of such additional coal as we might obtaintlirough increased productiono     1,500,000 tons of this isto meet the current consumption of metropolitan France,150,000 tons for the French Empire,  and the remaining 50,000tons for rebuilding stocks.0     So far,  it has proved impossiblefor us to reach our present &quot;target&quot; figure of 1,500,000 tons.The discussion at the Economic Policy Committee brought out the following points;(l)      Inpeace time, France had bought only some600.000 tons a month from us a     TheMinister of Shipping doubts whether theFrench port facilities car. handle alarger amount than 1,500,000 tons *     Ifwe are to ship more than that quantitywe must use large vessels, whose diversion to the French Atlantic ports will delaytheir round voyage from the United Kingdomand b&amp;^K by some ten days on the average -with a corresponding reduction in our totalimpc r bing capacity(2)      If the French are  to receive more than 1,500,000tons, cur sales to other markets must be correspondingly reduced,.      I was obliged tcpoint out to the Committee the serious results,from the Treasury point of view,  of reducingcur sales, e,g, to Argentina, and the Ministryof Economic Warfare and the Board of Trade,for various Important reasons, stronglydeprecated redactions in our exports to countries such as Italy,  Greece, Egypt, Spain,Portugal and Switzerland,,      The Foreign Officeregard as very serious reductions in our coal exports either to South America or to Portugal,Egypt, and other countries.COPY NO,1%

(3)     Additional coal for export can only be foundquickly by reducing the programme for building up stocks at home during the summer.      It hadbeen intended to raise the stocks of publicutility undertakings to an average of 10 weekssupply.      To meet the extra French demand would mean that stocks can only be built up toan average of 8 weeks supply.     If this risk is to be taken, it is for consideration whether the coal so made available could not;best be used for other export purposes.(4)     These difficulties as regards supplying Franc?and finding coal for export to other countries have arisen although the present estimatesallow only some 100,000 tons a month for Italy,as compared with 7007000 tons contemplatedearly in the year,  and assume that 752,000 tonsa month intended for Scandinavian countries will not be required^(5)     British coal production is now at the rate ofsome 245 million tons a yea:?, compared with an output of 227 million tons in 1938.      It isstated that French domestic production of coalhas increased by about 40 per cent.     TheSecretary for Mines expects our output toincrease, but not so as to afford any relief to the immediate programme.The Committee agreed that the question raised issues of policy which must be referred to the War Cabinet,(Initialled) J.S.Treasury chambers,S.W.1.


</content>
</cab>
