<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/155/20 images: 372-380</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTYlS government cp(71)20 COPY NO        C212 February 1971CABINETCLYDE PORT AUTHORITYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for theEnvir onment1.       At its meeting on 10 February the Ministerial Committee onEconomic Policy considered the urgent capital re-financing problemconfronting the Clyde Port Authority and the serious and extensiveimplications.    I was invited to prepare a memorandum for the Cabinet.THE PROBLEM OF CONFIDENCE2.        Loss of confidence in ports on the part of investors stems, first,from the fact that ports were pushed into short-term borrowing andimprudent charging practices by our predecessors&apos; proposals fornationalisation and their prices and income policies and, second, from our decision, as a Government, not to bail out the Mersey.GENERAL PORTS policy.       I will be cons4ee^4ag on Monday a short note on Ports Policywhich is basically not to extend the area of nationalisation.    I would emphasise now that any policy other than nationalisation will inevitably be long term in its effects and will not in the short term do much to restore the confidence of investors,THE CLYDE!S PROBLEM4.       The Clyde Port Authority need to renew borrowings amounting to  14 million over the next two years of which some   b\ million has to be renewed this year.    The immediate crisis is over   0. 5 million repayableto the County Bank on 22 February and   0. 25 million repayable toJohnson Matthey on 10 March.5.       The Authority themselves are basically in a viable position, with good management and labour relations.    They have good prospects forexploitation of their valuable natural deep water as ships grow ever larger.They cannot however face a concerted demand for repayment of capitaldebt.    Nor can other public trust port authorities.1
6.       The MfcaSafeS:?  or Transport Industrie, r; has kept up pressure onthe Authority and  heir advisers, Morgan, Grenfell, to do everything possible to raise the money on the market.    The Chairman of Morgan,Grenfell and the partner handling the matter have stated their conviction that no significant amount of money can be raised on the market without government aid.    Since   14 million has to be found over the next twoyears no institution would be willing to advance even small sums without first knowing how the whole amount is to be financed.LEGAL POSITION ON THE CLYDE7,       There appears to be nothing we could do to prevent a creditors&apos;scramble,    I am advised that a receiver cannot be appointed in Scotland jthat creditors could sue for payment and seek to enforce judgment byseizure and sale of land and other assets aud that the Courts in scotland would probably not stay the execution of a judgment even if the under-taking were rendered incapable of carrying out its statutory duties.    TheAuthority are themselves urgently seeking CounsePs opinion on these points.PROBLEMS FOR OTHER PORTS8.       The Clyde iy the immediate problem but there are other portswith known capital refinancing problems, particularly London, the Forthand the Tyne.    The situation in these is set out in Annex A.    The crisis of confidence may also affect other ports,    Annex B gives estimates ofthe total capital debts of the ports and the amounts repayable in the next two years.    The Annex does not include the British Transport DocksBoard, which, as a nationalised undertaking, is financed from theNational Loans Fund.    Nor does it include local authority ports such asBristol, or company ports, such as Manchester and Felixstowe, whichhave equity capital and should not be affected.COURSES OF ACTION OPEN TO US9.        The Ministerial Committee on Economic Policy having consideredpossible courses of action rejected standby credits, guarantees orindemnities and decided that if the Government were to help it should be either by a straight loan or by a retrospective loan under the Harbours Act,The Committee also asked that the possibility of exerting pressure on themoney market or of the Government^ underwriting an issue of short-termmarketable paper by the Authority should be examined by the Treasury,^ pj^igjugj^gfe!^   These courses do not, however, appear to offer asatisfactory solution.    Nor can the local Employment Acts provide an answer,^&quot;10.       The courses open to us are as followss-a. DO NOTHING. A default by the Clyde would have serious effects on the port, on employment and on the Scottish economy,it would still further intensify the refinancing problems of otherports, which might well go the same way,    Loss of confidence by
investors would be cumulative.    There might be widespread dockstrikes.    We could be accused of being responsible for the closing down of viable ports as unforeseen consequence of the Mersey-decision,b, GOVERNMENT LOAN.    If we make a loan to the Clyde wewould be expected to do the same for other ports.    We might inthe end have to finance all public trust ports.    It would almost certainly cause increased pressure on the Mersey position andjsop&amp;srdJUw       Boasrd&apos;s new Bill, although we can seek to distinguish the Clyde from the Mersey because of its basicviability.    We have no specific powers to make loans for refinancingand we would have to make a statement in the House, and might need to take legislative powers if we were to become responsible for thegeneral refinancing of other ports.    On the other hand, this course is the only straightforward way of assisting the port and it might help towards a gradual recovery of confidence.c. RETROSPECTIVE HARBOURS ACT LOANS.    It has beensuggested that retrospective loans of about  4 million could be madefor works completed in 196? and 1969 on the Meadowside Granary andthe Greenock Container Terminal (for which Harbours Act loanswere not sought at the time).    Whilst this course is superficiallyattractive there are the following substantial objectionsi.    It could not provide all the money needed.    The authority would still have further refinancing in the autumn.ii.    Our legal advice is that our powers do not permit us tomake loans with such a degree of retrospection.iii. Because cf this, it is doubtful whether any such loanscould be justified to the Public Accounts Committee as a proper use of the public moneys voted for the purposes of the HarboursAct,    Whatever the overt justification, these loans would havebeen made not in order to enable capital development to takeplace, but to provide public funds to repay market borrowings,iv, Above all, this course is open to the objection that itwould be seen as a devious arrangement and we would not succeed in keeping it concealed.REGIONAL POLICY11.       The regional employment situation has deteriorated greatly duringthe past year particularly in Scotland.    This was marked by the recentannouncement that West central scotland is to be a special development area.   $.We atso j^^aa^i^^^^aaBseo^feet^iy our decision to assist UpperClyde Shipbuilders,JT   These decisions would be difficult to reconcile witha decision to do nothing about the Clyde Port Authority and to risk its3
collapse.    Since the Government are committed to spending some 300 million a year on help for the assisted areas, additional expenditure could hardly be oaidto be creating a new issue of principle in a regional policy setting.     But any attempt to justify assistance to individual portsgurely on grounds of regional policy - eg aid to the Clyde but not to theForth or the Port of London Authority - would not stand up.CONCLUSIONS12.       On the one hand we can take an orderly course of action which willgive us a degree of control over the assistance we provide.    Thealternative is to take the risk of events taking charge and forcing us intomeasures which will be just as costly and far more difficult to present toour supporters and the country.13.       I have come reluctantly to the view that the realistic course is tomake straight loans to the Clyde Port Authority as debt repayments falldue until such time as they are able to raise money again on the market.This in itself should help to restore confidence but we must recognise thatwe may have to do the same for other viable port authorities.P w department of the Environment, SWl12 February 19714
(confidential)(confidential)PORTS WITH KNOWN CAPITAL REFINANCING PROBLEMSa. Port of London The PLA have  12m of stock falling due for renewalover the next two years plus  13m in short-term borrowings.    They arein a unique position among port authorities of having  30m of disposabl(property assets.    They have recently been able to &quot;roll over&quot; short-term borrowings of  2m9 without any difficulty, at only \/\&amp;% aboveprime rate.    They are hoping to repeat the operation in March, but a default on the Clyde might prevent this.   Even without a crisis on the clyde they are seriously concerned about their position and proposing to take powers to secure borrowing on their assets as well as on theirrevenue, in an attempt to inspire greater confidence in investors,b. Forth Ports Authority   The Forth had a net deficit of  390,000 in1969.    This was entirely due to losses at Leith amounting to nearly jm.    There are prospects of continuing deficits at Leith, which isburdened by the long term cost of paying for its expensive new entrancelock with your traffic prospects.    Charges have just been increased bybetween 10% and 30%.    Over  2m is on call for periods up to six monthsplus another  2m of bonds repayable this year.c. Port of Tyne Authority   The Tyne, although recording smallsurpluses in 1969 and 1970, face a future in which coal traffic willbe declining and iron ore shipments will be lost to Redcar.   They have ^m falling due for repayment in 1971 and  fm in 1972.
CAPITAL DEBT OF PUBLIC TRUST PORTS	Total	 mLONDON	-   83LIVERPOOL	95CLYDE	22*FORTH	TEES	13TYNE	other PORTS	(say) 37275Amount Repayablein 1971 and 1972-,-- m2520u0.51.33.568.3*   includes  3m irredeemable stock
(confidential)     amexcGENERAL PORTS policy.     There are some 300 ports in Great Britain.   A dozen or so largeones handle nearly 90% of the nation&apos;s trade.   Of these we have no real worries over Manchester, which is company-owned;   Bristol,which is a local authority port;   Hull, Southampton and the SouthWales ports, which are nationalised and owned &quot;by the British transport docks Board;   and Milford Haven and Medway, which are mainly oil ports,THE problem.     There are six major public trust ports;   Mersey, London^ Clyde,Forth, Tyne and Tees.   They have no express financial duties;   no(or only small) reserves;   no equity capital;   and no one to account to,LONG TERM OBJECTIVES3.     Nationalisation is ruled out on grounds of over centralisation,and elimination of competition.   Municipal!sation is not attractive:local authorities as at present organised are not well equipped to run ports.   Perhaps the best course would be to turn them into publiccompanies with statutory powers, but this would involve legislation;moreover private investors would not invest in the equity of suchcompanies at present and conversion of existing fixed Interestcapital to equity would not be at all easy,PROPOSALS FOR IMMEDIATE ACTIONk*     The boards of these Authorities are too big, too much dominated by users and too amateurish to manage the ports as commercial enter-prises.   They can be reconstituted through the Harbours Act machinery,I have in mind boards of 8 to 10 members, including a minority of&quot;executive&quot; members,1*(confidential)
(confidential)5.     The National Ports Council has too many members and some representindividual ports.   I propose to appoint fewer members but with morecommercial and financial experience.   The 30b of the strengthenedCouncil will be to help the ports improve their financial policies,charging methods, accounting procedure and management practices.6.     Cargo handling is badly organised.   There are too many interests involved.   We must aim at unity of operation on ship and shore.   this can be secured by dividing the total area into separate territorieseach run by a single operator.   Operators must provide cargo handlingequipment and should lease berths on a long term basis where possible.7.     I find it difficult to challenge the view which is Widely heldamong Port Authorities, that the National Dock Labour Scheme is ananachronism and that the negotiating machinery cries out for a thorough review.   There are, however, difficultues from the union side in replacing or modifying it.8.     In view of the present lack of confidence on the part ofinvestors, we should continue to make Harbours Act loans for new development.   But the time has come to discontinue the 20$ modern!sa-tion grants, in order to impress the importance of efficient financial control.   Ports must face up to the reality of making decisions on new projects.   But equitable and adequate transitional arrangements^will be needed.TIME TABLE9.     As my colleagues will see, none of these lines of action could have any immediate effect on the urgent refinancing problems discussed in the main paper.   I will be circulating a fuller paper on portspolicy soon.2 9(confidential?)


</content>
</cab>
