<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/50/22 images: 300-307</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
4&quot;Printed for the War Cabinet.   May 1944.SECRET. Copy No.W.P. (44) 272.25th May, 1944.WAR CABINET.REQUIREMENTS FOR PROGRESS IN CIVIL AIRCRAFT DESIGN.Memorandum by the Lord Privy Seal.ON the 25th February, 1943, the War Cabinet decided^ that the design ofnew types of civil aircraft and the conversion of certain military types to civil use should proceed only as and when it could be done without impairing the war effort.2. On the direction of the Committee on Post-War Civil Air Transport I ask the War Cabinet to reconsider this decision.3. The C.A.T. Committee recommends (the Secretary of State for Airreserving his position) : -(i) that civil types of aircraft should be given equal priority, for the alloca-tion of design staff, with &quot; non-designated &quot; military aircraft; that is,with military types which have not been selected for the highest priority :(ii) that provision should be made for the permanent deferment of youngtrainee draughtsmen working on military and civil aircraft design :(iii) that authority should be given for the recruitment of sufficient draughts-men to provide, by the fourth quarter of 1945, a peak of 460 draughts-men over and above those now engaged.4. The Memorandum by the Minister of Aircraft Production which wasconsidered by the committee is attached as Annex to this paper.Gwydyr House, S.W. 1,25th May, 1944.* W.M. (43) 35th Conclusions, Minute 3.f C.A.T. (44) 5th Meeting, Minute 4.[27530]y
ANNEX.(CAT. (44) 36.)19th May, 1944.PROGRESS ON CIVIL AIR TRANSPORT DEVELOPMENT.Memorandum by Minister of Aircraft Production.The Chairman asked me to report to the Committee on the position withregard to the development of the Brabazon and other important civil types of aircraft.2. At their meeting on the 25th February, 1943, the War Cabinet decidedthat &quot; work on the design of new types of civil aircraft and on the conversion ofcertain existing military types should proceed under Government direction as and when this could be done without impairing the war effort&apos;&apos; with the objectof &quot;securing the production after the war of British transport, aircraft on a scale and quality in keeping with our world position.&quot;3. In accordance with this decision (and a similar decision on the13th December, 1943, as regards the Tudor) civil versions of the Halifax andTudor are in hand, and design work is proceeding on the Brabazon Types I(London to New York Express), II (Land plane for European and feeder Services)and Vb (8-seater passenger machine for United Kingdom and Colonies).Types Ilia and b cannot usefully proceed until the Lancaster IV and Tudorare more advanced, and the detailed specifications of Types IV (jet mail plane)and Va (14-seater passenger machine for the United Kingdom and the Colonies)have not yet been laid down by the Brabazon Committee.4. A tentative programme for the design work on the seven new types andthe two conversions is as follows : Type.I ...II ...IliaHlbIVVaVbHalifax ConversionTudor ConversionStart of Design Work.October 1943January 1944January 1945January 1945July 1945July 1945August 1943August 1943April 1944Start of Flying Trials.December 1947February 1946January 1948August 1947May 1947February 1947February 1945Summer 1945December 1945This programme represents the very best that can be done assuming thatthese Civil Types will be given much higher priority than at present.5. To achieve this programme we shall require to employ by the fourthquarter of 1945 an effort of 460 draughtsmen over those now engaged, plus 24stressmen and aerodynamicists. Of these, about 200 will be required by thefourth quarter of 1944. This will mean diverting a greater portion of our aircraft design effort than has hitherto been possible to work on civil types.6. The M.A.P. design and development programme is highly congested inrelation to our resources of designers and draughtsmen, and we must try to retain our lead in military design, as well as make up lee-way in civil design. It mustbe pointed out that a considerable increase of draughtsmen will be necessary also on the military side if the increased programme for military prototypes is to bemet. As a rough estimate a total permanent increase of some 2,500 draughtsmenand technicians is indicated to meet the future needs of Naval, R.A.F. and CivilAviation, apart from making good wastage.7. Draughtsmen, however, cannot be conjured out of nothing. these numbers simply do not exist. The fact must be faced that there are not enoughmen to go round. The only method of increasing the numbers is to train freshones. Such men, however, have not sufficient experience to enable them to bereally useful on work of this kind while it is in the early stages.   The Ministry
of Labour have provided over recent months a number of newly traineddraughtsmen, but it has been found necessary to employ the bulk of these on current military work in part because of its urgency and also because in most,cases the civil designs have not reached a stage at which detailed drawings can bemade. What is really needed now for civil types is some draughtsmen of experience.8. It is a fallacy to suppose that even after the war is over there will be a sudden large surplus of experienced draughtsmen capable of this work, so that little reliance can be placed in a great diversion of effort to civil types in thepost-war period. Although the aircraft industry may then only produce a fraction of its present aircraft, the design staff is not directly related to thenumber of aircraft produced but to the number of designs. These are unlikely to decrease, and if we are to maintain an up-to-date Royal Air Force and Fleet.Air Arm and take our proper place in the. world of civil aviation, we may wellfind the shortage of draughtsmen as acute as ever after the war.9. It is essential, therefore, to press on with recruitment and training ofdraughtsmen and to ensure that suitable people are encouraged to take up thiscalling and will not suffer interruption in their training by military service.10. For the reasons given in paragraph 7 there has actually been a decreasein the number employed on civil design since the 31st December, 1943, and ifthe programme shown in paragraph 3 is to be carried out, some immediatechange of priority for the civil work will have to be made.11.   It seems, therefore, now to be necessary : (i) for the War Cabinet to review their original directive referred to inparagraph 1, and to consider whether the time has not come whenurgent civil types should enjoy equal priority with &quot; non-designated &quot;military types in so far as the latter are in competition with thecivil types for draughtsmen. In particular, this is suggested for the brabazon Types I, II and Vb and the two conversion types. Inci-dentally, all these types have potential military value;(ii) to arrange for the permanent deferment of young trainee draughtsmen;and(iii) to take immediate steps to recruit sufficient draughtsmen to providefor the peak of 460 (over those now engaged) required by the fourthquarter of 1945., R. S. C.
. ANNEX.(C.A.T. (44) 36.)19th May, 1944.PROGRESS ON CIVIL AIR TRANSPORT DEVELOPMENT.Memorandum by Minister of Aircraft Production.The Chairman asked me to report to the Committee on the position withregard to the development of the Brabazon and other important civil types of aircraft.2. At their meeting on the 25th February, 1943, the War Cabinet decidedthat &quot; work on the design of new types of civil aircraft and on the conversion ofcertain existing military types should proceed under Government direction as and when this could be done without impairing the war effort &quot; with the objectof &quot; securing the production after the war of British transport, aircraft on a scale and quality in keeping with our world position.&quot;3. In accordance with this decision (and a similar decision on the13th December, 1943, as regards the Tudor) civil versions of the Halifax andTudor are in hand, and design work is proceeding on the Brabazon Types I(London to New York Express), II (Land plane for European and feeder Services)and Vb (8-seater passenger machine for United Kingdom and Colonies).Types Ilia and b cannot usefully proceed until the Lancaster IV and Tudorare more advanced, and the detailed specifications of Types IV (jet mail plane)and Va (14-seater passenger machine for the United Kingdom and the Colonies)have not yet been laid down by the Brabazon Committee.4. A tentative programme for the design work on the seven new types andthe two conversions is as follows : Type.I ...II ...IliaIllbIVVaVbHalifax ConversionTudor ConversionStart of Design Work.October 1943January 1944January 1945January 1945July 1945July 1945August 1943August 1943April 1944Start of Flying Trials.December 1947February 1946January 1948August 1947May 1947February 1947February 1945Summer 1945December 1945This programme represents the very best that can be done assuming thatthese Civil Types will be given much higher priority than at present.5. To achieve this programme we shall require to employ by the fourthquarter of 1945 an effort of 460 draughtsmen over those now engaged, plus 24stressmen and aerodynamicists. Of these, about 200 will be required by thefourth quarter of 1944. This will mean diverting a greater portion of out-aircraft design effort than has hitherto been possible to work on civil types.6. The MA.P. design and development programme is highly congested inrelation to our resources of designers and draughtsmen, and we must try to retain our lead in military design, as well as make up lee-way in civil design. It mustbe pointed out that a considerable increase of draughtsmen will be necessary also on the military side if the increased programme for military prototypes is to bemet. As a rough estimate a total permanent increase of some 2,500 draughtsmenand technicians is indicated to meet the future needs of Naval, R.A.F. and CivilAviation, apart from making good wastage.7. Draughtsmen, however, cannot be conjured out of nothing. these numbers simply do not exist. The fact must be faced that there are not enoughmen to go round. The only method of increasing the numbers is to train freshones. Such men, however, have not sufficient experience to enable them to bereally useful on work of this kind while it is in the early  stages.   The Ministry
of Labour have provided - over recent months a number of newly traineddraughtsmen, but it has been found necessary to employ the bulk of these on current military work in part because of its urgency and also because in most,cases the civil designs have not reached a stage at which detailed drawings can bemade. What is really needed now for civil types is some draughtsmen of experience. . &apos; &apos;8. It is a fallacy to suppose that even after the war is over there will be a sudden large surplus of experienced draughtsmen capable of this work, so that little reliance can be placed in a great diversion of effort to civil types in thepost-war period. Although the aircraft industry may then only produce a fraction of its present aircraft, the design staff is not directly related to thenumber of aircraft produced but to the number of designs. These are unlikely to decrease, and if we are to maintain an up-to-date Royal Air Force and Fleet.Air Arm and take our proper place in the, world of civil aviation, we may wellfind the shortage of draughtsmen as acute as ever after the war.9. It is essential, therefore, to press on with recruitment and training ofdraughtsmen and to ensure that suitable people are encouraged to take up thiscalling and will not suffer interruption in their training by military service.10. For the reasons given in paragraph 7 there has actually been a decreasein the number employed on civil design since the 31st December, 1943, and ifthe programme shown in paragraph 3 is to be carried out, some immediatechange of priority for the civil work will have to be made.11.   It seems, therefore, now to be necessary :- (i) for the War Cabinet to review their original directive referred to inparagraph 1, and to consider whether the time has not come whenurgent civil types should enjoy equal priority with &quot; non-designated &quot;military types in so far as the latter are in competition with thecivil types for draughtsmen. In particular, this is suggested for the brabazon Types I, II and Vb and the two conversion types. Inci-dentally, all these types have potential military value;(ii) to arrange for the permanent deferment of young trainee draughtsmen;and(iii) to take immediate steps to recruit sufficient draughtsmen to providefor the peak of 460 (over those now engaged) required by the fourthquarter of 1945.. V R. S. C.




</content>
</cab>
