<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/23/1 images: 10-15</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
- MOST SECRET -T0 BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KEY.It is requested that special care may betaken toensure the secrecy of this document.COPY NoW.M. (41)  72nd QQHGbgSIQNjt, MTNTTTE 10,Confidential Annex,(gist July, 1941, 5.0 p.m.)THE PAR EAST.Co-operationwith theNetherlandsGovernment.(previous reference:W.M.(41) 42ndConclus ions,Minute 3 .)The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum bythe Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (W.P.(41)168) asking for authority, after consultation with theDominions, to make a communication to the netherlands government.    This communication would -(a) Give general approval to the recommendationsresulting from the Anglo-Dutch-AustralianStaff talks in February and the British-DutchStaff talks in April last, as the basis forthe preparation of future plans&apos;(b) State that the United Kingdom were preparedto join the other Governments concerned ina reciprocal Agreement to co-operate to thefull extent of their available resourcesif any of them were forced to take military action to counter armed action by theJapanese forces against its territory ormandated territory.THE FOREIGN SECRETARY said that the idea had been dropped of making a public declaration that we should go to the help of the Dutch East Indies if they were attacked by Japan.   All that was now proposed was thatwe should tell the Dutch privately that we would do so,and would inform the United States of what we had done.It was not proposed, however, to make any communication to the Japanese on the subject.On the merits of the ease, he could not see that,if Japan attacked the Dutch East Indies, we shouldnot go to their aid.   He found difficulty in postponinga decision on this matter further, as the Dutch were pressing us to ratify the conversations.   The Govern-ments of Australia and New Zealand were in agreementwith the course proposed.   Further, it was urgentlydesired to send Australian forces to Koepang and Ambon,in the Netherlands East Indies, immediately theJapanese moved into Indo-China.   But the Dutch wouldcertainly not agree to this course unless we made astatement to them on   the lines proposed.It should also be borne in mind that if theJapanese, after taking bases in Indo-China, made a move on Singapore, and we had joined in no reciprocalAgreement with the Governments concerned on this matter,then the Dutch would not be bound to come to our aid.V fTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;3 GOVERNMENT. )    *

THE PRIME MINISTER said that he would stillprefer to postpone sending a communication on the lines proposed.   As for a Japanese attack on Singapore, he did not believe that anything of the sort was  contem-&quot;) plated.    It might well be that, even if Japan encroachedon the Dutch East Indies, the right policy would bethat we should not make an immediate declaration of war on Japan.    Once war had been declared, Japanese cruiserswould attack our sea communications, and none of our shipping would be safe unless heavily protected byconvoys.   At the present moment we were not in aposition to send an adequate fleet to the Par East.Several of our capital ships were undergoing repair and would not be available for about three months .For all these reasons, he would much prefer to waitand see how the situation developed, and, if a menacingsituation should come about, take steps to strengthen our forces in the Par East.   He also thought that itwould be wise to allow time for the American situation to develop.    In any event, taking a shorter vie?;, hethought it. would be right to wait a few days and seethe result of the action which it now seemed certainthat Japan meant to take in Indo-china, which might well have an effect on United States opinion.Mr fraser said that if the Netherlands east indies were attacked by Japan, the effect would be largely to isolate New Zealand and Australia, moreparticularly as regards air reinforcements.   He believed,however, that if the Netherlands East Indies were attacked by Japan, the United States would come intothe war.   While, in general, in favour of a declaration on the lines proposed, he saw no objection to thematter being allowed to stand over for a few days, asproposed by the Prime Minister.   This, moreover, would allow time for the situation which had developed in thelast two or three months to be clarified by the Chiefsof Staff.    In particular, he thought that the Dutch airforces had been greatly strengthened recently.The War Cabinet decided as follows(&quot;1) No conclusion should be recorded that day,the matter being allowed to stand over, onthe understanding that the Foreign secretary was at liberty to bring the matter beforethem again in the near future,(S)  Invited the Chiefs of Staff to review thearrangements for the defence of the Par Eastas agreed at the Far Eastern Conference,in the light of the present strengths andsituation.Great George Street, S.W.l9




</content>
</cab>
