<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/174/0 images: 69-70</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIAL LIBRARY,This Document is the Property of His Britannic MajestVs Government. 1Printed for the Cabinet.SECRET. CP. 309 (25). [C- 8604/459/18]MEMORANDUM FOR THE CABINET.THE Cabinet will perhaps remember that in their conversation with me at Geneva MM. Briand and Boncour reverted to a suggestion already made to me by M. de Fleuriau that the French and British Governments should come to some agreement, before the Assembly of the League of Nations meets in September, as to the line which our two delegations should take there. M. Briand suggested that we might rescue from the protocol a good deal which was not actually condemned in the declaration I made at the March meeting of the council or in my speeches in Parliament. I feel, as I said at the time, that all this is rather dangerous and that the moment is particularly ill-chosen for re-opening these wider issues. I suggest, therefore, that the Cabinet should authorise me to send M. Briand a personal letter briefly indicating our objections to this course.I attach a draft which would perhaps serve the purpose, and should be glad to know whether the Cabinet approve the suggested procedure and desire any additions or alterations in the letter.A. C.Foreign Office, June 25, Iv)25.Draft Letter to Mr. Briand.Dear M. Briand, Foreign Office, June    , 1925.Since I parted from you at Geneva I have been very carefully considering the suggestion made by you and supported by M. Boncour, that we should prepare some agreed programme in relation to security for the Assembly of the League of Nations to be held in September next. You told me that, after comparing carefully my declaration on the protocol at the March meeting of the council with the clauses of the Covenant, you thought that we could extract from the protocol provisions to which His Majesty&apos;s Government had taken no objection in their note, and that we might make these the basis of a new proposal to the assembly. M. Boncour at the same time suggested that we could usefully take up at any rate the question of the unanimity required for decisions of the council (except in matters of procedure) and of the definition of an &quot; aggressor.&quot; 1 indicated to you my doubts upon this subject at the time. The more I have reflected on it, the less expedient does it seem to me that we should enter, at the present stage at any rate, on any further attempt to amend the Covenant. We are in fact engaged at this moment in a great effort to support it by the system of mutual pacts and arbitration treaties contemplated in our negotiations with Germany. If we are, as I think there is every prospect we shall be, successful in these negotiations, we shall have made a very great contribution to the peace of the -world and to the strength of the League of Nations.If we can terminate these negotiations in time to present their results to the assembly, that fact will make this assembly the most remarkable since the first occasion on which it met, and will itself have done more than any revision of the Covenant to render peace secure. If, on the other hand, the negotiations are not terminated, I cannot think that it would be wise that we should start at Geneva a discussion which must necessarily overlap the negotiations in course of progress between Germany and her various neighbours, and might greatly embarrass us at some critical moment of our conversations with Germanj&apos;; indeed if we had an)&apos; difficulties with them, we might in such circumstances find that the discussion was2939   [13256]
practically removed from the Conference Room where our treaty was being negotiated to the Assembly Hall of the League.These seem to me sound practical reasons for not reopening at the September assembly the questions which occupied the main attention of its meeting last year. But there is another reason which I would like to submit to you. A considerable section of this country views our negotiations and the proposed British guarantee of the Rhineland and its arbitration treaties with some suspicion lest -Great Britain should be involved in obligations which might later become embarrassing and even dangerous. I do not believe that this opinion is&apos; that of the majority of our countrymen or even of a large minority, but undoubtedly there is a certain uneasiness upon the subject, and I should be very loth to imperil those negotiations by under-taking at, the same time a discussion of larger issues about which we might find it difficult to agree and which would certainly increase any apprehensions that are felt about our narrower pact. For all these reasons 1 feel, and my colleagues of the Government agree with me, that it is not in the interest of a successful treaty of guarantee that we should be called upon to discuss these wider issues at this time.This latter arises so directly out of our conversation that I have thought it better&apos; to put our views before you in this informal way rather than to deal with the matter in a despatch to Lord Crewe or in any formal communication to M. de Fleuriau.

</content>
</cab>
