<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/174/0 images: 246-265</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Wf.Jfy-t^momm^ is this,JgpjsjfflY ay his bbitauiiic majesty&apos;s (mv5hkm3bq?0 a B I ii B I ,ZSO (25). OTMPLOTZIGSHT   OOMMI3?ffiBB.-R 3 P O K I .1.       In view of tho forthcoming discussion of tho Ministry of Labour Estimates tho Unomployraent Committee wish to draw tho attention of tho Cabinet to two urgent questions on which early decisions are required.2.       The Committee have recently had under consideration a Memorandum by Lord Ct.Davids on the question of further worlrs which Loci Authorities may be expected to submit to tho Unemployment Grants Committee for the year 1925/26. A copy of this memorandum ia attached as an Appendix to this lioport.   The Committee have also conferred with Lord St. Davids and the position may be briefly summarised as follows:3.      In 1924/25 the Local Authorities subraittod to the Unemployment Grants Committee schemes of work totalling in value about  24,000^000 of these schemes approximately two-thirds or  18t000f000 were ultimately approved by the Committee for grant.   On the evidence at present available it would appear that the volume of schemes which may be submitted for 1925/26 is unlikely to exceed  10,000.000. On the experience of previous years this would indioate  6 TOOOjOOO as the value of work which may materialise for grant on the present basis.4.       The reason given by the Local Authorities for their unwillingness or inability to put forward schemes of work on the scale of previous years is dissatisfaction with the &quot; terms and conditions of tho Government grant.     Certain
authorities consider that the grant should he on a more generous scale,    Lord 3t.Ds.vids (who advised the late Government 3, year ago that in his opinion any increase of grant was unnecessary and undesirable) remains of opinion that no useful purpose would be served by incraasing the amount of the Government contribution.     The UnemploymentCommittee concur in this view and they also agree with Lord 3t.Davids in rejecting proposals such as tho spreading of tho Government grant over the whole of tha loan period and the payment of Housing Site Preliminary Development Grants on the percentage of the wages basis.5.      Many Authorities have advocated the substitution for the grant on the interest and sinking fund basis of a lump sum grant equivalent to the present value of thoannual payments - say 50$ of the capital cost of the workin non-Bevonuo produding cases and 25^ in Rovonue-pro&amp;uci$goases, or as an alternative that in tho caso of worksfinanced by loan it should be open to an Authority to obtainor interesta grant either on the basis of interest/and -sinking fund chargas or on the basis of a percentage of the wages cost, She Comnittoo are uot prepared to recommend the Cabinet to adopt this latter alternative,6*       Apart from arguments based on the plea that unemploy-   ; meat relief should be a national Charge tho lump sum grant is advocated by the Authorities on the following grounds(a) while in the^tb^ presont grant amountsto 50$ of the/octet of the work tho Authorities represent that in fact the percentage varies from 18$ to 44^;(b) the Loan burden mean higher rates which in turn mean depressed industry and more unemploy-mont.(c) The credit of Local Authorities 13 impairedby their heavy borrowing and the rate of interest they have to pay tends to rise.
f.     ZbvA St.35avids, while again emphasising the dangers      &quot; X &amp; 3incidental to a policy of subsidizing schemes of so-called * accelerated&apos; work over a number of years considers that if it is thought desirable, in view of the continued and increasing unemployment, to encourage sohemes of work by local Authorities, the lump sum system is more likely to attain the desired object than any other plan;   such a concession would, in his words &quot;provide a golden bridge for the retreat of those authorities who have passed resolutions refusing to do more work on existing terms8. The estimated effect of the adoption of the lump sum system on applications received may be indicated as follows(I) 1924/25Applications received June 1924-June 1925  24,486a000 Add cases brought forward from IS23/24Deduct oases carried forward to 1925/26(11)1925/26On present basisApplications which may be reoeivedJune 1925-June 1926 Add oases brought forward from 1924/25Deduct oases carried forward to 1926/27On lump sum bar:isApplications which may be receivedJune 1925-June 1926 Add cases brought forwardDeduct canes carried forward to 1926/2?ffho figures  23,078,000;  11,700,000 and  16,400,000 must be re-ctuoed by from 25$ to 30% to get the probable value of schemes approved for Grant.A 25$ reduction would give  17,300,000;  8,800,000 and  12,300,000 respectively.9.      From the Treasury point of view the lump sum proposal is -ppento very serious objection. In the case of the  12,300,000 dh. (ill) above, instead of having to make payment of say  250,000 per annum for 5-15 vears In respect of interest and Pinking fund eharges, the Exchequer must find     over  3,000,000 in 1926/27,   Assufcittp that cmch a sum could not &quot;be,192,00027,678,000 4,600,000 23,078,000  9,400,000 4,600,00014,000,000 2,300,000 - - &quot;.....- &quot;i&quot;..... 11,700,000 15,000;000 4,600,00019,600;000 3,200,000 16,400,000
10 o100     .d:ter careful consideration of the estimates submitted to them by Lord St*Davids, the Committee are clearly of opinion that the estimated value of the volume of schemes for 1925/25 can only be substan-tially increased by the adoption of the lump sum system. They consider that if made   the concession should apply generally and that so long as unemployment remains at its present figure it would be undesirable to Jtimit its    operation to the more distressed areas or to schemes of a certain valueTh&apos;2 Committee report:-(l)      That the question whether thoadvantages which may be eapected to follow the change of system outweigh tho serious financial objections to the.change is one for Cabinet decisions(2)      That if the answer to (l) is in the affirmative the Committee recommend tha&apos;j non-revenue producing and revenue producing grants respectively be paid, in the form of their present value i*e0 50$ and 25$ respectively of the capital cost of tho work as and wh.on.tho vo rk is done, if Local authorities so desire0 but that this decision should only apply to schemes starting on or after 1st October next0(The&apos;financial Secretary to the Treasury is not in a   position to concur in this recommendation)offoot means that&apos;in future the onus of borrowingup to 50$ of the cot of these works is transferred from the Local authorities to the State at a time whenit is of tho utmost importance that Government borrowingshould bo restricted within the narrowest possiblelimitSp
10c,     .v.fter careful consideration of the estimates submitted to them by Lord StcDavids,  the Committee are clearly of opinion that tho estimated value of the volume of schemes for 1925/25 can only be substan-tisally increased by the adoption of the lump sum system. They consider that if made   the concession should apply generally and that so long as unemployment remains at its presont figure it would be undesirable to iiinit its    operation to the more distressed areas or to schemes of a certain valueTho Committee report:-(l)      That the question whether theadvantages which may be e pocted to follow the change of system outweigh tho serious financial objections to the chango is one for Cabinet decision^(2)      That if the answer to (l) is in the -affirmative the Committee recommend thai non-revenue producing and revenue producing grants respectively be paid in the form of their present value i0e0-50$ and 25$ respectively of the capital cost of tho work as and when tho wo rk is done, if Local .,,uthorities so desire0 but that this decision should only apply to schemes starting on or after 1st October nexto(The Financial Secretary to the Treasury is not in a   position to concur in this recommendation)uoffoot means that&apos;in future the onus of borrowingup to 50/o of the co-t of those works is transferred from the Local authorities to the State at a time whenit is of the utmost importance that Government borrowingshould be restricted within the narrowest possibleliraitSo
The Committee also recommend:-

(3) That in the case of schemes starting from the 1st October 1925, the terms of the Wages grant be amended so as to allow payment in respect of all unemployed persons taken on directly in consequence of the undertaking of the relief works by the Local Authority.

(4) That an announcement of the Government&apos;s decision respecting the Unemployment Committee&apos;s Terms and Conditions of Grant for 1925/26 should be made with the least possible delay.
DR-lINAGE,        11&apos;    Tiie Committee have been informed by theSCHEMESF&apos;G RELIEF       Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries that he has decided to include a Drainage programme as part of his general Agricultural policy.      This Drainage programme will take the form of the provision of a sum of  200,000 per annum for 5 years beginning with 1926-27, the object being to assist hand Drainage schemes of a more comprehensive character than those undertaken in recent years. 1:&apos;hile these schemes would have little direct effect on rural unemployment, they will assist depressed industries such as the steel trade because the construct-ion of dredgers, barges,  etc. would be involved, and if during the summer months labour is drawn from the industrial areas,some of it may stay on the  land. 12,        The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries has impressed upon the Committee the desirability of continuing the present system of land Drainage schemes on existing lines during the coming r&apos;inter in order that there may be no gap between the old and hew policies and in order that the existing machinery may be maintained intact so as to enable the new poliej? to be initiated next year, if approved by the Cabinet. 13 o A sura of  140?000 was provided in the Ministryof Health Estimates  for 1925-26 for the completion of the 1924-25 Drainage schemes.      It is estimated tbat : only  65,000 will be expended leaving a balance of  75,000 available for next Pint or1s operations.      The Minister of Agriculture estimates that a further sum of  75,000 will suffice to enable his Department1s scheme to proceed more or less on the present scale up&apos;-to the end of the present financial year.
i i L14.     The Secretary for Scotland concurs generally Inthe views of the Minister of Agriculture and fisheries and has emphasised to the Committee the desirability ofmaintaining present arrangements in Scotland pencling the bringing into operation of any now Agricultural Drainagepolicy.     In the case of Scotland a sum of  11,000 willremain available for neyt Winter&apos;s operations out of theprovision of  45,000 included in the Board of agriculture for Sootland18 Estimates for 1925-26.15.        The Committee recommend to the Cabinet -That pending a decision by the Cabinet as to the provision to be made for the Drainage, etc. programme in the Govern-ment general Agricultural polioy, the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries and the Secretary for Scotland respectively should be authorised to continue land Drainage, etc.- schemes for the relief of Unemployment during the coming Vinter generally on the same lines as herotofor, and that the question whether any, and if so what further provision may be required to enable the present policy to be continued to the end of 1925-26, should be further considered by the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries and the Board of Agriculture for Scotland in consultation with the Treasury.The Financial Secretary to the Treasury dissented fromthis recommendation.Signed on behalf of the Committee . W ORTH III GT Oil - EVA IIS. Chairman-Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I. 7th July, 1925.
TJBWBXDWSBT C8RAITTS  (VISCOUNT St.l&amp;VIDS* ) mMlTTmMemorandum by the Chairman on the Question of FartherWorks for 1925-26It had been my intention to present on the 15th July a considered statement indicating the extent to which works for the relief of unemployment might be expected to be put forward by Local Authorities throughout the Country for the year 1925-26, based on the results of the series of visits now being paid by officers of the Committee to the more important districts in the country, some 60 in all.As I understand, however, that the Government desire to have a report by the end of this week on the prospects for next Winter&quot;s work, so far as it has been possible to ascertain them by then, I am submitting the following considerations which must, necessarily be regarded as preliminary and provisional and possibly subject to revision in the light of more complete information.The reports so far received cover 35 centres in England which have been visited and also half a dozen centres in Scotland to which preliminary visits have been made.    These reports form a broader basis of comparison than was the case last year, when a very close estimate of the possibilities was made; they cover the bulk of the more important towns, and are as follows :-Birkenhead, Birmingham, Blaydon, &quot;Bradford, Bristol, Darlington, Durham, Halifax, Leeds, Liverpool, L.C.C. , Manchester, Mersey Dock Board, Middlesbrough, Kowburn, Newcastle-on-Tyne, Nottingham, Port of London, Portsmouth, Sheffield, Smethwick, South Shields, Stoke-on-Trent, Stockton-on-Tees, Sundsrland, Tipton, Tynemouth,Wall send,, C92-i0
^ 174Wallaendj Walaall, Wednesbury, West Eartlepool and Wolver-i hampton.     And in Scotland, Aberdeen, Edinburgh, Dundee,Glasgow, Lanark (iiiddle Ward) and Perth.Unfortunately it has not been possible to obtain in the limited time available more than general indications so far as Scotland is conoemed,Bsplies to the Oommittee!s Circular Letter to Local Authorities have also been received from a number of other centres, some 60 in all, making enquiries or submitting tentative proposals for next Winter.     These, however, are for the most part too vague or general in charaoter to be safely inoluded in the present Estimates. Indeed, in ,a. third of these oases no figures of ooet at all are given.On the other hand, the Port of London Authority has put forward a scheme oosting  1,030,000.     It is a doubtful scheme but has been taken into account, inasmuoh as work to the value of  986,000 from this Authority was approved last year.The available information is summarised in Appendioes &quot;A&quot;1 and &quot;B&quot; d&quot; , and it will be seen from the detailed figures given&apos; there ..that on the present basis of grant the Authorities enumerated,&quot; including the Port of London, are not prepared at tho moment to suggest, schemes to a greater value than  2,858,500*     From these same Authorities last year sohemes to the total value of  7,961,000 were received, the figure for the ooming year being thus little more than a third of that for last year.At the same time, these Authorities have in many oases mentioned other &quot;possible&quot; sohemes amounting .in value to several millions of pounds, which they say they might be prepared to put forward under certain conditions.$   not circulated.
conditions.       The condition^ in fact are almost in every case either an. increase in or an amendment of the present proportion of Government assistance, a notable exception being Manchester who state that no more work is available, a statement which it is difficult to believe.Schemes which the Authorities stated they might put forward as Ministry of Transport schemes have been left out of account, as they do not come within the purview of the Unemployment Grants Committee in either of the two years under comparison.Applying the figures derived from the areas visited to the Country as a whole, it would seem that the volume of work which will be proposed throughout the Country for 1S25-26, on the showing of the Local Authorities, and accepting the statements made by them at their face value, is about  8,560,000 as compared with a figure of  24,000,000 proposed for 1924-5 sIt is quite possible that these figures are below the mark, partly because the larger towns who are the worst sufferers form the main basis of the calculation; and partly because the case may have been wilfully under-stated by them.But in any case the figures are hardly likely on present showing to exceed  10,000,000 or at most  12,000,000./And      Note   regarding   Scotland.Since completion of the Memorandum information has been received to the effect that approximately  973,000 worth of schemes may be expected from the whole of Scotland. This is on all fours with the information obtained from the lest of the country, showing as it does that the works proposed for 1925-6 in Scotland are about a third of those proposed in that country for 1924-5.
And the additional schemes would come from the less industrialised centres -who need the work least.REASONS FOR DECREASE I IT PROPOSALS. The detailed reasons given by the Local Authorities for their inability or unwillingness to put forward schemes of work for the coming Winter are givon in Columns 5 and 6 of Appendix &quot;B&quot;^ and there is little doubt but that this somewhat general attitude on the part of the Authorities is due to a great extent, to the very vigorous propaganda conducted by the Middlesbrough Town Council and also certain other bodies, for improvement in the Government t erms.On the 13th May the Middlesbrough Town Council addressed a communication to the Unemployment Grants Committee, and to various other Government Departments.In this communication it was stated that in view of their heavy capital commitments for the relief of unemployment and their view that unemployment was a national burden, they were not prepared to submit further schemes unless increased grants were given by the Government, in spite of the fact that there were indications that further works would be necessary in their area next Winter.     The essential portion of the letter is contained in the following paragraph:-&quot;Pending further serious consideration by.the &quot;Government Departments-&apos; of the question of &quot;substantially increasing their present grants &quot;towards schemes for the relief of unemployment, &quot;my Council have directed me to say that they are &quot;unable to consider a programme for 1925-26.....The Middlesbrough Corporation circulated copiesof this letter to Local Authorities throughout the Countryand asked for their support, and as a result, a number ofimportant Authorities have written to the unemployment grants Committee forwarding copies of resolutions passed/by$    not circulated..
by them stating that they propose to adopt the policy or that they support the view of the kiddlesbrough Corporation,It must not, however he sunposed that all these Authorities will in fact refuse to submit schemes on existing terms.     On the contrary, certain of them state that they are prepared to do so, but they all complain of the difficulty caused by financial stringency and press for increased or amended terms.The County Ootincils1 Association, the Urban District Councils1 Association, and the Kural District Councils1 Association have also during the present year passed resolutions urging increased terms.LoA.3UGGSgTI0NS PQB MAKING GOVILuihJNT GRANT MOKE ACCEPTABLE,Prom among the number of complaints and criticisms made by Local Authorities as to the inadequacy or unsuitability of the Government grant (the grant on the loan basis was referred to by more than one Authority as a &quot;delusion or a snare&quot;) there emanated certain definite and practical    stiggestions as to amending the form of grant so as to make it more acceptable and thereby induce Local Authorities to put up more schemes.     Apart from tho question of any mere increase of grant, the suggestions ai-e given below.(1) Lump sum grant.       The grant on the interest ana sinking fund basis should be replaced by a lump sum grant, equivalent to the present value of the annual payments; say 50$ of the capital oost of the work as in the case of Ministry of Transport grants.(Note.      The effect of this proposal would not be to increase the.Government contribution but to make it payable during the progress of the work instead of over anything from 5-15 years.)/(2)5092-5.:-v&apos;vw^ ........     . ......... ....    . .......
(2) Alternative form of grant.      If works are financed by loan it should be possible for the Authority to obtain a grant either on the basis of interest and sinking fund charges or on the basis of a percentage of the wages cost, at the option of the Authority0(Mote.    As regards this suggestion the present-position is that where works are financed by loan, grant on the basis of a percentage of the wages bill is not permissible. Originally of course it was, but in order   to diminish the immediate liability of the Government and to spread its commitments over a period of years the other form of grant was adopted.    The effect of acceding to this suggestion on the part of the Local Authorities would not be, as a rule, to pay more grant than as at present but the effect would be to pay grant as the work progresses and not over a period of years. )(3)    Spreading of grant over whole period of Loan Grants on the interest and sinking fund basis should be spread over the whole period of the loan even though the total of the grant is no larger than at present.(Eote, This suggestion is directly opposed in effect to the two preceding ones. It would diminish the immediate liability of the State but extend its duration.)(4)    Housing Site Preliminary Development Grants Grant on the basis of a percentage of the wages should be given for road and sewer work in connection with the preliminary development of Housing sites, and not as at present on the loan charge basis only.-(Mote,    The present grant which is given on the basis of interest and sinking fund charges, as a revenue producing grant, comes to an end a year before the Housing grant, if any,  becomes payable.    This gives the Local Authorities a small grant for a short period, the groundbeing .i ..509:2-6.
being that as they will get tho housing grant when the houses arc put up they must not receive two grants from the same source,.     If a grant ori tho wages basis were given, they would in fact be receiving two grants though they would not be receiving thorn simultaneously, for the wages grant would bo payable for the road and sewer work while it was being done1, and the housing grant which covers roads and sewers, would be payable latero(5)    Wages grants to bo payable for substitutes The grant on the wages basis should bo payable in respect of temporary substitutes taken on for regular work to replace permanent men temporarily transferred to relief work.(liote.     This is a legitimate grievance on the part of the local Authorities.,   por their relief works they ere very often obliged to put permanent men on to direct the others.  . The Unemployment Grants Committee cannot pay grant on the wages of these permanent men, but the local Authority has generally to put on substitutes in their ordinary departments to take the place of&apos; these permanent men.    They claim,  and with some justice, that our grant should be payable in respect of those other temporary men who are taken from the ranks of the unemployed hy reason of the execution of the relief works.    The wording ox the Commit tee&apos; s terms of reference limits them to pay the wages &quot;of unemployed men taken on for the job&quot;. A very slight amendment of this wording would remove the difficulty.) SEN 5RAIiThe main argument put forward by local    Authorities in nearly every case for. the alteration of the form of grant or for an increase in grant is that although in theory the present grant  amounts to 50$ of the cost of the work, infact...
fact when it comes to he paid it does not amount to nearly as much.   Middlesbrough indeed state that it is not worth more than 33^4.   Other Authorities give figures varying from 18$ to 44$.The burden thus imposed on Local Authorities means, they say, higher rates, and higher rates mean putting such pressure on local industry that more firms will close down and more unemployment will i-result.    This burden is concentrated on a limited number of industrial centres whilst the others escape very lightly.A further result of the large borrowings they have to make is that their credit is affected and the rate of interest they have to pay increases^They feel that the burden on the big manufacturin towns is most unfair in view of the comparatively greater part they played in the War, as compared with the less industrialised and more residential towns. They consider that It is unfair to ask them to pay so much, while the others pay so little.    They feel that Government action should be directed to equalising the burden more, not only as between the State and Local Authorities, but as between the Local Authorities themselves.
509g-9.C0HC1USI0HSIt is a matter for consideration how far Local Authorities are in earnest when they say they can only put forward the very limited programme which has been specified, and how far their suggestions for amendment of grant would in fact produce additional schemes.      In other words do the Local Authorities mean what they say, or are they &quot;bluffing&quot; as part of a concerted effort to obtain better terms from the Government.In the first place I would desire to draw attention to the fact that last summer I was invited by the   then Government to submit my views as to the proposal then under consideration for increasing the measure of Government assistance at that time given to these schemes.In view of the fact that the Committee&apos;s Officers who had been visiting the country reported that some  20,000,000 worth of work would probably be forthcoming for the winter without any increased grant at all, (a forecast which proved remarkably correct), I reported strongly both to the Cabinet Committee and to the Chancellor of the Exchequer personally to the effect that I considered any increase unnecessary and undesir-able.    I was further strengthened in the view that a mere increase of grant was not a course to be adopted in view of the fact that the concession of an increase, would probably be followed in the next year by demands for a further concession and so on until the Government grant reached 100$ of the expenditure.I am still of that opinion, and in my view it would be a mistake merely to increase the amount of the Government contribution.A change in the form of grant does not however necessarily stand on the same basis.
I assume, that it is desired that work should he forthcoming to an appreciable extent to relieve unemployment during the coming winter.      This may no doubt be necessary although In this connection I would draw attention to my remarks before the Cabinet Committee when in dealing with proposals for the winter of 1923-4 I stated that there was a danger that schemes of subsidised so-called &quot;accelerated&quot; work for a number of years in succession might ultimately lead to subsidising merely the routine work of the Munic ipal i t i es.Assuming however, that it is considered desirable to continue the scheme in view of the continued and increasing measure of unemployment, and to strengthen it in view of the difficulties x-preferred to in the present report, the following are the lines on which I would suggest that action might be taken.(1)    The proportion of State grant not to be increased(2) The total amount of work to be assisted (or the amount of work to be assisted on the new basis) to be limited to a fixed figure,,(5)    The non-revenue producing and revenue producing grants respectively to be paid in the form of their present value 1. e. 50$ and 25f0 respectively of the capital cost of the work as and when the work is done, if local Authorities so desire,(a) to all schemes or(b) to schemes in the more hardly hit districts and/or(c) to schemes up to a limited value(4)    Local Authorities to be allowed, as at present, grant on the wages paid even though the balance of the cost of the scheme is financed by loan, if they so desire.(5)    The terms of the wages grant to be amended so asto allow payment to a reasonable number of substitutesIt may be asked how this can be supposed to satisfy Local Authorities inasmuch as the aggregate grant is not increased.      The answer is that Local Authorities main-tain that though in theory the most favourable grant on present terms is worth 5Of0 to them, in fact it is worth nothing like this.     Moreover by paying them
1 9 3a lump sum of 50;:u of the capital cost of the work their borrowings are reduced by 50f ; this is a very important point with them both from the point of view of their aggregate commitments and of the rate of interest at which they can borrow.Inasmuch es tho State say that the present value of their grant is worth 50$ of the capital cost of the works, they are presumably prepared to pay this;    the only difference .between the actual position and what is proposed by the local Authorities is that the charges will fall in two or three financial years instead of over varying periods up to 15.   Very little would fall to be paid in the present financial year as presumably the new grants, if made, would only apply to schemes starting say from 1st.October next.The following rough provisional calculation gives some indication of the incidence of the State liability if lump sum grants were substituted for all grants on the loan basis,f6 on the assumption that applications were received from Local Authorities by the Unemployment Grants Committee to the amount of either fa)  20,000,000 or (b)  15,000,000.   (During the present year applications amounted to  24,000,000).Ice lire dApprovedState GrantAggregateProportion payable in 1926-7.15,000,0000S.K.P. 8,500,000j 4,250,000) (R.P.      6,500,000 I 1,625,000)) 5,8 75,0004,000,000loo,00011,000,000 .(N.E.P. 6,500,000) 3,250,000) (R.P.      4,500,000; 1,125,000))  4,375,0003,250,000f   If the amended form of grant were limited to certain areas, the immediate State grant would be proportionately less.
5092-12.If action as indicated above were taken it would (a) meet the Local Authorities on Uos. 1 and 2 of their suggestions, (b)  enable a limit to be pis cod on the Government commitments,   (e) provide a. golden bridge for the retreat of those Local Authorities who have passed resolutions refusing to do more work on existing terms.But how far such possible action as I have indicated may be desirable is of course a matter of policy for the Government to decide.Regard will no doubt be had to the fact that while some of the Local Authorities are undoubtedly &quot;bluffing&quot; in the expectation of getting something more out of the Government, yet on the other hand there is a good d eal to be said for the contention of some of the Authorities that the burden of relieving unemployment fails unequally not merely between the Local Authorities and the State -but between the Local Authorities themselves.If any amendment is to be made at all, it is better to apply it to those places most hardly hit and which -need it most.    These are the very places where most difficulty is experienced.    The big industrial centres have undoubtedly incurred very heavy liabilities in respect of unemployment relief work and they are no doubt genuinely alarmed as to their financial position and the magnitude of these liabilities-.    The amendment of form of-grant to a lump sum would have the effect of reducing their further borrowings for relief work by 50% and to that extent would relieve their position.   From the State point of view it is financially sound, provided always that it meets with the policy of the &quot;Exchequer inasmuch as it implies meeting present liabilities at the present time.(Sd:)    St. DAVIDS. 85 th June 1925. Chairman..&apos;

</content>
</cab>
