<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/174/0 images: 277-283</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JET.,333(25)CABINET.Safeguarding&apos;of industries memorandum by the President of the Board of Trade.I wish to bring to the notice of the Cabinet several applications I have received under the Safeguarding of Industries procedure.      The first raises questions of practical difficulty, upon which I should like a ruling. The others are comparatively simple, but as they are probably typical of other applications which may be made in the future, I think it is convenient that I should bring them to the notice of my colleagues and state the action which I propose to take.(1) The Birmingham Jewellers&apos; and Silversmiths&apos; Association, who applied under the Act of 1921 in respect of imitation jewellery, have now submitted an application in respect of &quot;real and imitation jewellery and silver and electro-plate&quot;.    They urge that these Industries are so interwoven that it is impossible to treat them separately, and ask that &quot;the Trade&quot; be considered as. a whole.    I am of opinion that the application in its present form covers three distinct industries, viz. (a) real jewellery and (gold and) silver wares;  (b) electro-plate; and (c) imitation jewellery.    The first is carried on to an appreciable extent in London and the second is mainly a Sheffield industry; neither the London nor the Sheffield manufacturers are at present parties to the application. The view expressed above is supported by an analysis of the returns made for the 1912 Census of Production, which shows that the three sections of
; ; 19 7manufacture are clearly marked off from each other, the manufacture of imitation jewellery or of electro-plate being associated to only a small extent with the manufacture of other goods.It is very doubtful whether the imitation jewellery industry by Itself can be regarded as of substantial importance.    The number of persons employed was very roughly estimated by the Birmingham Association as having been 6,000 in 1915, falling to 4,550 in the last quarter cf  192 0 and 3,200 in the third quarter of 1921.    It is however, very difficult to reconcile the applicants&apos; figure for 1913 with that revealed by the returns made for the 1912 Census of Production, which was about 2,000; and even if allowance be made for possible incompleteness of the returns the total number can hardly be taken as exceeding 3,000 in that year. If the coating of the base metal material ready for manu-facture. into finished articles be also included the numbers might be Increased somewhat further.Nevertheless it occurs to me that a means may be found to get over the difficulty of substantial importance and at the same time to meet the applicants&apos; demand for the consideration of the trade they are concerned in as one whole.   The Birmingham Association described imitation jewellery, in connection with their previous application in 1922, as meaning articles made of base metal finished   by coating with gold or silver.    There is, however, another class of jewellery the manufacture of which is also centred at Birmingham and which may I think not unreasonably, be bracketed with articles of base metal coated with precious metal, and that is articles made of low alloys of gold and
silver.    Of these two parts of the cheap jewellery trade, the   one meets the demand for an article which looks very well for the time though it will not last,and the other that for an article which while less attractive to look at is more durable.No exact information is available as to the numbers employed in making articles of low alloys of gold and silver, but it may not unreasonably be taken that they would bring up the total number in the combined industry to the neighbourhood of 5,000.The articles included in the description &quot;imitationjewellery&quot; are too diverse to permit of specification.   Theywere described by the applicants in 1922 as:-&quot;All articles of personal or decorative use made of metal, not&apos;precious, which is finished by coating with gold or silver, e.g. in rolled gold and imitation jewellery: brooches, pendants, bracelets, expanding bracelets, watch-guards, necklaces, studs, links, scarf pins and slides, etc., etc., in utility and toilet articles: - cigarette cases, match boxes, vanity cases, metal purses and paste dress ornamets, metal belts and girdles, etc., etc.; in enamel souvenirs:- spoons with coats of arms, etc., etc.; all of which articles are made by the rolled gold, gilt and imitation jewellery trade in Birmingham and on the Continent&quot;.Should, however, a prima facie case for enquiry be made out in respect of an application with the scope aboveindicated, the reference to the Committee might be in thefollowing terms:    &quot;Sheet, wire and tubing of base metalscoated or washed with gold and silver and jewellery and otherwares, gem-set or not, made therefrom or from low alloys ofgold, silver, or platinum, exclusive of dental materials andwatch cases&quot;.   The terms to be inserted in the financial resolution and in the Finance Act could only be settled after receipt of the Committee&apos;s report, but it should notbe impossible to frame a definition of the goods to be thesubject of duty.which would be capable of administration bythe Customs on the basis not of the nature of the finishedarticles but of the materials of which they are composed.
I should call attention to one further difficulty.     The reference suggested will include electro-plate.   I understand that a good deal of the cheap &quot;jewellery&quot; is coated by means of electricity, although it is not described as electro-plated ware, and it seems almost impossible to draw a description that the Customs can work that will exclude electro-plate proper, in which there is no considerable foreign competition.   If the committee wish to make separate recommendations for imitation jewellery and for electro-plate it will be for them to suggest a line of distinction capable of being administered.If a case were made out for an enquiry in respect of other real jewellery, the terms of reference to the Committee should probably cover &quot;jewellery and other wares of gold, silver and platinum, or high alloys thereof, whether gem-set or not, other than watch cases&quot; .2.   The Aluminium Hoilow-ware Manufacturers&apos; Association have applied for a duty.     I understand that the Wrought Enamelled Hollow-ware makers are also contemplating an application but a suggestion that, as the two industries are supplying commodities of substantially similar use, they should make a joint application lias not proved acceptable, each trade taking the position that it ought to be considered separately on its merits.     The numbers employed in the manufacture of aliiminium hollow-ware do not exceed 5,500 or 4,000.   But having regard to the fact that this industry is a comparatively new one,  having developed during and since the par, and affords an Important and probably growing outlet for the.product of the British aluminium refining industry, I should not myself raise objection on the point of substantial Importance.     The enamelware industry seems to have employed some 4,000 people in 1920 and 2,000 in the last
quarter of 1921.     Both were protected under part II of the Safeguarding of Industries Act.     The effect of the duty was almost to extinguish Imports of German aluminium hollow-ware and to reduce those of enamelled ware, but there has been a distinct revival of imports since the lapse of the duty. If an application is made by the enamel hollow-ware trade, I propose to refer it to the same Committee.   The relations of the two industries are rather similar to that of silk and-artificial silk, and it would certainly be convenient for the same Committee to consider the two together,3.    The British Brush Manufacturers&apos; Association, representing an industry employing somewhere in the region of 10,000 workpeople, have applied for a duty on all classes of Brooms and Brushes.     The imports have risen from 1,929,000 dozen in 1913 to 3,615,000 dozen last year, while exports - for the most part to Empire markets in which we enjoy a preference - have only risen from 561,000 dozen to 877,000, and such information as to production as is available goes to indicate a fall in output now as compared with 1913. -ages in Germany, Belgium and Japan, whence the imports mainly come, appear,  according to the applicants statements, to be substantially lower than in this country-.I propose to refer this application forthwith to a committee.4.   Application has been made in respect of glassware (other than plate and sheet glass and bottles), in the manufacture of which some six or seven thousand persons are engaged.     This is an industry which has been going down hill for many years before 1914, but during and immediately after the war was reorganised and extended.     It appears to me to be impossible in the light of the evidence furnished to say-5-
that the competition of foreign imports at the present time is exceptional.   The output has greatly Increased In value and must have risen considerably in quantity, since 1913 and is at the present time slowly but steadily rising, while imports, though considerably more in value, were in 1924 only some two-thirds in quantity of those in 1913:    exports are small, but the ratio of exports to imports was higher last year than in 1913.   Considering the present position in relation to that of the pre-war industry,  therefore, I feel bound to rule that foreign competition is not exceptional.Even if in view of its reorganisation the industry be regarded as a post-war industry, I do not think that a case is made out.     It is true that the output has fallen in value from the very high level reached in 1920, but whereas the home production even in that year was only a little over 60^ of the imports it amounted last year, according to the information furnished by the applicants, to more than 70%.Although,  therefore,  there is evidence that foreign w ages and prices are lower than British, it appears to me that a prima facie case for reference to a committee has not been made out.5.   The Chrome Upper Leather Section of the United Tanners&apos; Federation have applied for a duty on chrome tanned upper leather.   This industry employs now only some 2,000 workpeople though the numbers have risen somewhat since the pre-war period.     The output is considerably higher than In 1913, while imports though increasing from their low level immediately after the war   are still less than in that year. The production capacity of the industry on the other hand was increased greatly during the war,  and this appears to
to A f)&amp; 0 6be the real basis of the application.      A rise in the price of upper leather would affect the boot and shoe industry, which is responsible for a large export trade. The applicants have not in ray opinion made out a prima facie case for enquiry and 1 propose to reject the application.8th July,  1925Board of Trade.

</content>
</cab>
