<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/233/0 images: 320-324</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*P0OJMSNT  IS THE FRCP5RTY  OF HIS 3RITANNI0 MAJESTY&apos;5 GOVERNMENT)C R ST,COPY NO,  Q,  359  (33) .                CJl 3 I N E T.                        CTTA^A LEGISLATION.               THE IRISH FREE STATE AND NOVEMBER 15th.                  The attached copy of a Note by the President i      the Board of Trade, circulated to the Ottawa Legislation      Committee on relations with  the Irish Free State,  is      circulated  to the Cabinet for consideration in connection      with the draft Ottawa Agreements Bill and Notes cn Clauses      (Paper CP. 335 (32)) .                                      (Sgd.) M.P.A. KANKEY                                         Secretary, Cabinet., Whitehall Gardens, S.7/.1.     10th October,  1932.
  DOOUiiBITT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITAiTHIO MA.JfiSTY1 S GOVERNMENT.RET.  32)  3.                                                 OOPY NO.____^                                     CABINET.                                     -                                                                       -                           OTTAWA LEGISLATION COMMITTEE.                      THE IRISH FREE STATE AND NOVEriBISR 15 th.                   Note \tY the President of the Board of Trade.               Under the Irish Free State (Special Duties) Act, import          duties of 20$ ad valorem are charged cn Irish goods of which          the imports in 1931 amounted to  26,200,000.  In retaliation          the Irish Free State Government have imposed special duties          on United Kingdom goods which in 1931 amounted in value to           8,200,000.               The United Kingdom preferences accorded to all the          Dominions under the Import Duties Act at present apply bo          Irish Free State goods (except in so far as such goods are          subject tc special duties), but under that Act these          preferences will cease to apply after 15th November, unless          some action is taken.   If no action is taken Irish go^ds          to the value of  5,550,000 now subject tc special duties of          20$ will beoome dutiable at 30$ and Irish goods to  the          value of  2,500,000, which now enter free of duty will become          subject to duties of 10$ ad valorem and upwards under the          Import Duties Act.   As regards the former, the extra 10$          may defeat the purpose of the Emergency duties - nunely          tc obtain revenue,  As regards the labter^Hhe gnod3          affected are scattered over a wide range and the inoreases          of  luty would be annoying to the Irioh rather than serious          in their effects.
     The&apos; question at?  policy arising is v/hether, as it hasnot been possible to make a Trade Agreement with the IrishFree State as has been done with the other Dominions, it iswise to let the Import Duties Act take its course and to treat Irish goods generally as foreign goods.     It may be observed that the reason it was impossible tonegotiate a Trade Agreement with the Irish Free State wasthat the political and financial dispute stood in the way.In general, Ireland treats our goods more favourably than dosome other Dominions, a large proportion of imports from theUnited Kingdom entering free of duty and the dutiesgenerally not being unduly high when compared with thoseimposed in some other Dominions... Apart from the financialdispute it should easily have been possible to negotiate a trade Agreement.   Thus it might be urged that if we allow theImport Duties Act to take its course we shall be punishingthem twice over for the same offence.     However this may be, it seems necessary to call attention to the probable results before a final decision istaken.  The immediate result would almost certainly be thatthe Irish Free State would withdraw the preferences which arenow enjoyed by United Kingdom goods under existing Irishduties.  This would involve raising by about 50Ji the dutiesnow imposed on goods imported from the United Kingdom to thevalue of about  15,020,000 in 1930  (including  2,75c/,000 ofgoods nov/  subject to retaliatory duties).  The hardshipresulting  to our manufacturers will probably be caused bythe restriction of trade resulting from such increases,rather than by greater foreign competition; but it is alsoprobable that the duties would not be raised against theDominions, with the  result that the Dominions  will secure
preferences over the united Kingdom in the Irish market.Canada in particular would prohahly gain considerably bythis and once Canada secures a footing in the market itwould be extremely difficult to dislodge her.  Thus not only would the volume of British trade hit by the removal of the preferences in Ireland be substantially greater than thevolume of Irish trade affected by the Import Duties Act, butthe bad results to our trade would by no means come to anend with the restoration of normal conditions, but to someextent would be cf a lasting character.     It may be suggested that the difficulty could be avoidedby subjecting Irish goods to duties at some rate (say % of thefull duty) less than the rates applying to correspondingforeign goods.  It seems doubtful however whether the IrishGovernment would consider this to be sufficient to justifythem in maintaining the preferences they now accord to united Kingdom goods,  particularly as it would meandiscriminating against Irish goods in favour of those fromall other parts of the Empire simply because we had no trade agreement with Ireland.  Moreover, such a course wouldprobably entail serious administrative difficulties and expense to the Customs.     The choice, therefore, seems to be whether,  apart fromthe special duties imposed owing to the financial dispute,we should as part of our commercial policy discriminate against Irish goods (as compared with goods from all otherparts of the Empire) on the ground that we have no trade agreement with Ireland; or whether, pending the settlement ofthe financial dispute, we should regard the future of our commercial relations with Ireland as in suspense and notimpose duties on Irish goods except under the Emergencyprocedure.     If the latter decision is taken, it will be necessary totake action to suspend the duties imposed under the Import
Board of Trade,    4th October, 1932.Duties Ac t. apply!ng to&apos;&apos;Irish goods after 15th november-er.A legislative provision to this effect would he out of place.in the Ottawa Agreements Bill, hut the necessary action could be taken under the procedure provided in Section 4of the Import Duties Act.

</content>
</cab>
