<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/51/32 images: 308-311</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for,the W^ar Cabinet,   June 1944.SECRET. I Copy No.W.P. (44) 332. /16th June, 1944. war CABINET.RELIEF SUPPLIES TO TERRITORIES IN EASTERN EUROPE.Memorandum by the Minister of State.AT their meeting on the 23rd December* the War Cabinet invited me toexamine and report on the arrangements for the provision of relief supplies toterritories in Eastern Europe likely to be occupied by the Russians. the submission of this report has been considerably delayed, since the arrangementsfor estimating and procuring relief supplies during the military period havemeanwhile been under continual discussion both at home and with the UnitedStates Government in Washington.2. I have now had an opportunity of discussing the question with mycolleagues on the S.L.A. Committee, and the following account represents our conclusions. The problem can be divided into two parts : first, the allied countries, Poland and Czechoslovakia; second, the Axis satellites, Bulgaria,Roumania and Hungary.A. Poland and Czechoslovakia.3. No problem arises in regard to relief supplies to Poland and Czecho-slovakia during the post-military period. It will be open to the Governments ofthese countries, when restored, to invite U&quot;NRRA&apos;s assistance if they so wish,and the arrangements for supply will follow the general lines laid down at the atlantic City Conference. It is therefore necessary to consider only the. case ofthese countries during &quot; the military phase.&quot;4. It seems clear that our first endeavour must be to place on the SovietGovernment the responsibility for ensuring supplies to those territories whichare occupied or administered by their own forces, just as the combined Anglo-American High Command ensures supplies in the theatres for which they areresponsible. At the moment we have no information about Soviet intentions.But, in spite of the delicacy of approaching them on a matter which involvestheir relations with Poland, there are good reasons for attempting to ascertain what they have in mind. We cannot avoid moral responsibility for seeing that poland and Czechoslovakia receive the supplies they need; the Russians nmywell ask for help from the United Kingdom and United States in providingsupplies for all the territories they occupy or administer, so that we shall wishto know as early as possible where we stand; moreover, we shall want to ensurethat any arrangements made for supplying these territories impose the least possible financial burden upon ourselves.5. I have therefore arranged, in agreement with my colleagues concerned,that His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador in Washington should be instructed to approach the State Department with a view to joint Anglo-American soundings being taken of the Soviet Government. It would be made plain that in our view relief supplies for Poland and Czechoslovakia during the military period must beregarded as a Soviet responsibility, and the Soviet Government would be askedtheir intentions with regard to these supplies.* W.M. (43) 175th Conclusions, Minute 1.12399   [27665]
^.-Bulgaria, Roumania and Hungary.6. In the case of these Axis satellites, it seems again clear that the responsi-bility for ensuring supplies must rest, in the first place, with the occupyingauthorities. At the moment there is no agreement between ourselves, the UnitedStates and the Soviet Union as to the zones of occupation which will be allotted tothe three major allies. Proposals, for eventual submission to the european advisory Commission, are at present under consideration. When these go to theCommission, we propose that an opportunity should be taken to impress upon theSoviet representative our view that his Government should be responsible for supplies in the Soviet zone of ion, and to enquire what plans they have inmind.P. K. L.Foreign Office, 16th June, 1944.



</content>
</cab>
