<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/7/0 images: 64-67</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Captain Client Joaes-[Tills Boeaiaeat is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s (jovemraealjPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET,   448.Minutex of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onThursday, July 18, 1918, at 11 30 a.m.The Right Hon. the Earl  Curzon of kedleston,  K.G.,   G.C.S.I.,  G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. j. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present :  The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forWar.General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Rear-Admiral   G.  P.   W.  Hope,   C.B.,Deputy Chief of the Naval Staff.The Right Hon. E. S. Montagu, M.P.,Secretary of State for India.The Right Hon. Lord Weir, Secretary ofState for the Royal Air Force.Major-General F. H. Sykes, C.M.G., Chiefof the Royal Air Staff.The Right Hon. Lord R. Cecil,  K.C., j The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,M.P., Minister of Blockade. Minister of Munitions.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, Iy.C.B., Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. S. Amery, M.P., Assistant Secretary.-Sugar eon^gffitfonrL---FHrE-War--Oa^inakafeto the Sugar Convention and the Most-Favoured-Nation&apos;&quot;Clauses.Lord Robert Cecil asked for a decision in favour-of the denunciation of the Sugar Convention, in order that we-nlight free our handsfandalso in order to carry out the resolutions passed by the War Cabineton the previous day (War Cabinet 147, Minute 6).-It was explained that-&quot;notice had already been served to thevarioxis Powers saying&apos;that we wished to keep our hands free andthat any Power-that wished could treat that notice as a denunciation of the Convention. As in fact no Power had clone so, and as ourWe^st-&apos;Tnclian Colonies were setting up central factories for sugarproduction.......andtalcing&quot;other&apos; -measures- whiclT&apos;&quot;accoMnrg to- Hie[1365-44:8]
Qc^aventiem-might be regarded,, as ,equivalent - to- giving--bounties,was - desirable to-give-formal notice of denunciation eia-tion.The-War Cabinet; &quot;decided That the Sugar Convention should be denounced.Most-Favoured- 2. Lord Robert Cecil explained that the circular to the PowersNation Clauses. with regard to the Most-Favoured-Nation Clauses stating that we intended to have a free hand had received the approval of theDominions, and had been recently sent out.The War Cabinet requested Lord Robert Cecil to report on thefollowing day the exact position with regard to the Most-Favoured-Nation Clauses.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 18, 1918.o
[This Document is the Pro,peftyTof His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.] 32Printed for the War Cabinet.   August 1918.SECRET. :3 war CABINET,   448.Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W., onThursday, July 18, 1918, at 11-30 a.m.Corrigendum.Delete Minute 1, and substitute the following : Sugar Convention. 1. THE War Cabinet discussed the present position with regardto the Sugar Convention and the Most-Favoured-Nation Clauses.Lord Robert Cecil asked for a decision in favour of giving sixmonths&apos; notice of the intention of the British Government to be bound no longer by any of the obligations towards contractingPowers which we undertook to maintain (subject to such notice)when we ceased to be parties to the Convention.It was explained that notice had already been served to thevarious Powers saying that we wished to keep our hands free incertain respects, and that any Power that wished could treat thatnotice as the notice required. As it was now proposed to give a preference to colonial sugar, and as our West Indian Colonies weresetting up central factories for sugar production and taking other measures which according to the Convention might be regarded as equivalent to giving bounties, it was desirable that formal noticeshould be given covering the whole of our obligations.The War Cabinet decided that The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs should give sixmonths&apos; notice to the contracting Powers of the intentionof the British Government to be bound no longer by anyof the obligations undertaken when the British Governmentceased to be a party to the Sugar Convention.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 31, 1918.o&apos; (365-418,1]


</content>
</cab>
