<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/7/0 images: 90-95</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
. [This Document is the&apos; Property --of His Britannic Il yesty&apos;s- GoYgrm^tj[Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 452.uy1Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Friday, July 26, 1918, at 12 noon.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. the Earl Curzon of kedleston, KG., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E.The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P.The Right Hon. Austen Chamberlain,M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The following were also present: The Right Hon. A. J. Balfour, O.M.,M.P., Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. the Viscount Milner,G.C.B., G.C.M.G., Secretary of State forWar.General sir h. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff.Major-General F. H. Sykes, C.M.G., Chiefof the Air Staff (for Minute 5).Rear-Admiral   G.   P.   W.   Hope,   C.B.,Deputy First Sea Lord.The Right Hon. Sir J. Maclat, Bart.,Shipping Controller (for Minute 4.)Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, K.C.B., Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Storr, Assistant Secretary.Mr. Thomas Jones, Assistant Secretary.Western Front: 1. With reference to War Cabinet 451, Minute 1, the Chief ofGerman Divisions the Imperial General Staff said that a total of 65 divisions had beenEmployed. identified in the present fighting.   He thought it probable that theGermans would now fall back to an intermediate line along therivers Ourcq and Crise. This would give them a rather narrowfront, but the line was suitable for defence, and would enable themto make a fair stand before eventually falling back to the line of theVesle, as it seemed not unlikely they might have to do. Therewere now in the salient no less than 50 German divisions, which meant great congestion. On the whole, the Allied forces had donefairly well on the previous day. General Wilson . also reported .thatGeneral Petain was putting 3 fresh French divisions in reserve south[1365-452] B\
of the Somme, somewhere behind Montdidier, where he was alsoreconstituting other divisions. This would free 2 British divisionsat present south of our line. General Wilson then stated the exact number of divisions that Field-Marshal Haig had now in reserve.General Wilson informed the War Cabinet that General Fochhad recently sent for General Salmond in order to thank him for thegreat assistance rendered during the recent fighting by the 9thBritish Air Squadron.Attention was drawn to paragraphs, which were almost certainlyinspired, that were now appearing in the German press appealing tothe German public to be patient, and apparently preparing themfor a realisation of the fact that the recent German offensive on theWest had failed.In reply to a question as to whether the enemy&apos;s system of fighting rearguard actions almost entirely with machine gunsresulted in very heavy casualties among the Allied troops, general wilson said that the most effective way of dealing with this system was an extensive use of tanks. He further stated that there were no fresh indications of a probable offensive on the British front.Bombing Raid at 2. The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that on the 24th JulyCattaro. three British D.H. machines had carried out a raid on Cattaro, andthat 1,356 lb. of bombs had been dropped. One direct hit with a112 lb. bomb had been obtained on the stern of an Austrian first-class battleship. Our machines had been heavily attacked by enemy machines and heavy anti-aircraft fire, but had all returned safely.A Raid on Belgian 3. The Deputy First Sea Lord reported that two night bombingPQrts- raids had been carried out in spite of unfavourable weather, andbombs had been dropped on Ghiestelles, Bruges, and Zeebrugge.Our loss consisted of one Handley-Page machine which caught fire and was completely destroyed, the crew, however,   escaping withslight injuries.Admiral Hope further reported that a 1,600-lb. bomb had been dropped on Middelkerke causing a tremendous explosion. This wasthe first time that a bomb of this size have been released from anyof our aeroplanes.The American 4. The War Cabinet had before them telegrams Nos. 3352 andMilitary Effort. 3353, dated the 23rd July, received from Lord Reading, dealing withthe despatch of American divisions to the W estern front, and statingthat the United States Government could not provide, supply, andequip 100 divisions by July 1919.The Prime Minister pointed out that our programme for 1919assumed the formation of an army of 100 American divisions inFrance, and our military plans depended almost entirely on our success in bringing that number across. The American Governmenthad once held out hopes of being able to send more than LOO divisions ;now the President said that it would be impossible to send 100divisions, and that the actual number would depend very much onthe number of cargo ships which Great Britain could furnish for thepurpose of carrying supplies for the American army.Sir Joseph Maclay reminded the War Cabinet that it had beenarranged at Versailles that General Bliss should ascertain from theAmerican Government whether they would have the necessarytonnage available to bring over the supplies for the 100 divisions.In the absence of American data the matter had been examined by
the Ministry of Shipping, and the conclusion reached was that theUnited States should be able to supply the necessary tonnage for supplies, inasmuch as while the number of American troops was increasing in France, at the same time the output of Americantonnage would also be increasing.The American estimate of the supplies they would require foran army of 4,000,000 men had gone up from 60,000 tons per day to75,000 tons, and they were now talking of 100,000 tons.We were in constant difficulties in the matter of tonnage, andthe position was being relieved only as a result of the greatestsacrifices. Australia and New Zealand were making dailyappeals for help, but we were unable to assist them much. The lackof coal was most serious, and ships were being delayed in port inconsequence. There was also a difficult situation in Lancashire,where 40,000 operatives were idle, and in order to increase thesupply of cotton we have been forced to cut down our cerealprogramme. At the same time America was asking us toincrease our export of coal from 100,000 tons to 175,000 tons forthe American army in France.Mr. Chamberlain asked the Shipping Controller if it was notthe case that when we had withdrawn ships from the North andSouth American trade, the Americans had put in their own ships on those routes with an eye to post-war business. Could not such ships,even if unsuitable for the conveyance of troops, be used to bringover warlike stores 1 Further, he understood that the americans had declined to help to meet certain requests by Canada for shipping facilities in the Pacific without receiving compensation inthe Atlantic.Sir Joseph Maclay said that the United States undoubtedlyhad a large amount of tonnage in the Pacific, and the Ministry ofShipping were examining the position there. He believed theywere doing something to reduce the number of ships plying between north and South America, but a certain quantity of imports from south America, such as nitrates and certain ore, &amp;c, were indis-pensable for the manufacture of munitions in the States. Therewas, however, clear evidence that the Americans were building up their transport organisation with a view to the situation after thewar. In considering the general question, it had to be borne inmind that we were making in this country a vast quantity of stufffor the American army Which consumed a great deal of our man-power.The Prime Minister said that a most important issue was raisedby Lord Beading&apos;s telegrams, and by a telegram which had just beenreceived from General Du Cane (No. C.G.-144), which stated thatit was contemplated that the American army now in France shouldtake over two separate sectors of the French line, one under general pershing and the second under another general. There were 26American divisions in France, 5 of which were behind the Britishline. We were confronted with the fact that General Foch was going to put pressure on us to keep our British divisions up to full strength, and with this object in view was going to use theAmerican divisions to relieve French divisions only. It was our duty to keep our divisions up to their full strength, but could we doit without smashing our industries ? We were at the end of our resources in man-power. We had been forced to release 25,000 ofthe 100,000 miners who we had intended to recruit, and still we hadships lying idle for lack of coal. We had been forced to cut downour agricultural programme for next year, and our programmes of tank and airship construction had likewise suffered. The tribunalswere refusing to release the elderly men at anything like the rate onwhich we had calculated. To maintain our divisions at their full strength we should have to call up 40,000 to 50,000 men from the mines, -20,000 to 30,000 from agriculture, 20,000 to 30,000 from munitions, and continue to use boys of 18-1-. He was strongly of[1365-452] &quot; B 2
opinion that boys of that age ought not to be sent to the front,except in the case of the most terrible emergency. - In the mean-time the French were able to give their men three weeks&apos; leave,while our men had nine days, and would be expected to endure the hardships of the coming winter without relief from the american divisions. He asked for authority from the Cabinet to use everyresource in order to see that justice was done as between the Britishand French soldiers. There must be no illegitimate pressure on oursudiers. Perhaps the first thing to do was to find out what numberof divisions we should be able to maintain. Next, it should beconsidered how best to raise the matter with the French Govern-ment.Mr. Chamberlain said that it would have to be pointed out tothe French Government that we could not both maintain a large army and meet all the demands made upon us for supplies. If wewere to do the former, the French must withdraw their demand for coal, for steel, and so on, through the whole list of articles nowsupplied to them. He had informed the Minister of Munitions thata special warning had been received from President Wilson through mr.. Crosby that the United States would almost certainly be short ofsteel, and possibly short of copper.The Prime Minister said that it had been suggested to him thatyards for repairing American ships should be set up in this country,manned by Americans. He thought the suggestion a dangerousone, owing to the great difference in the levels of wages paid in theStates and in this country.Admiral Hope said that one of our own yards, wdth Britishemployees, had now been set aside for the repair of American ships.Mr. Balfour suggested that a memorandum, drawn up with thegreatest care, and reviewing every aspect of the complex situation,should be at once prepared.The War Cabinet decided that The Prime Minister should have full powers, after consultationwith the Secretary of State for War and the ShippingController as necessary, to take such action as he might think best to deal with M. Clemenceau in regard to this problem, using our shipping position, if necessaiy, as alever to secure a fair redistribution of Allied forces inthe line on the introduction therein of the american divisions. He undertook to report later to the WarCabinet on the subject.The Air Situation: 5. With  reference to Imperial War Cabinet -2,7, Minute 6,Casualties. Mr. Balfonr called attention to a statement, by the Chief of the AirStaff that our losses in the air bad recently been heavier, as ourairmen had had to go further afield in order to engage the enemy.Lord Curzon stated that during his recent visit His Majesty theKing of the Belgians, who was an impartial observer, stated that inhis judgment there was some recklessness in our use of our flyingman-power, and that our losses in the air were proportionatelyheavier than those of the French. At the Prime Ministers requesthe had forwarded a statement of His Majesty&apos;s views to the Secretaryof State for the Air Force, and he understood a reply was being prepared.General Sykes was afraid he had conveyed a wrong impression on the previous day. He did not think our casualties in the airwere increasing. It was largely a question of the state of the weather; when the weather was fine with the wind from the north-east or east, and in going over the line the fighting drifted in thedirection of the enemy, the circumstances were in our favour in comingback, after an engagement. On the other hand, with possibly, someengine trouble and damaged wings and a south-west wind, the circum-
stances were against us. If anything casualties were slightlydecreasing. He undertook to furnish a report in regard to casualties among airmen.The War Cabinet decided To adjourn the discussion pending the receipt of a full reportfrom the Air Ministry.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,July 26, 1918.


</content>
</cab>
