<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/7/0 images: 174-181</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property .of His Britannic Majestys ^of^mmeiiL]     g printed for the War Cabinet   August 1918.SECRET.WAR CABINET, 464.39Minutes of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, downing Street, S.W.,on Tuesday, August 27, 1918, at 12 noon.Present:The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P. (in the Chair).The Right Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P. I The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.Lieutenant-General the Right Hon. J. C.Smuts, K.C.The following Were also present :-The Right Hon. Lord Robert Cecil,K.C., M.P., Assistant Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs (for Minutes 1 to 9).General Sir H. H. Wilson, K.C.B., D.S.O.,Chief of the Imperial General Staff (forxMinutes 1 to 4).Major-General P. P. de B. Radcliffe,C.B., D.S.O., Director of Military Opera-tions.The Right Hon. the Earl of Reading,G.C.B., K.C.V.O., KG, His Majesty&apos;sHigh Commissioner and Special Ambas-ambassador to the United States of America.Brigadier-General I. L. B. Vesey, D.S.G,Deputy Director of Organisation, WarOffice (for Minute 8).The Right Hon. G. H. Roberts, M.P.,Minister of Labour (for Minute 8).The Right Hon. R. E. Prothero, M.V.O.,M.P., President, Board of Agricultureand Fisheries (for Minute. 8).Sir E. Geddes; G.B.E.First   Lord   of   theThe Right Hon.KGB.,   M.P.,Admiralty.Admiral Sir R. E. Wemyss,G.C.B., C.M.G.,M. V.O., First Sea Lord and Chief of theNaval Staff.Sir Leo G. Chiozza Money, M.P., Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Shipping(for Minutes 8 and 9).Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Robert Horne,K.B.E., K.C., Third Civil Lord of theAdmiralty (for Minutes 8 to 10).The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Minister of Munitions (for Minutes 8to 10).Major-General J. E. B. Seely, C.B.,C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Deputy Ministerof Munitions (for Minute 8).The Right Hon. Lord Weir, Secretaryof State for the Royal Air Force (for minute 10).The Right Hon. Sir A. C Geddes, K.C.B.,M.P., Minister of National Service (for minute 8).Major P. Lloyd Greame, M.C., Secre-tary, Ministry of National Service (for(Minute 8).Lieutenant-Colonel W. Dally Jones, C.M.G., Acting Secretary.Captain Clement Jones, Assistant Secretary.Major the Hon. W. Ormsby-Gore, M.P., Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel Leslie Wilson, C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P., Assistant Secretary
The Czeeho- 1. WITH reference to War Cabinet 463, Minute 5, the Chief ofSlovak Forces. ^he Imperial General Staff said that he had received a telegramfrom Marshal Foch stating that he was reluctant to intervene with president Wilson, as suggested, regarding the reinforcement of theAllied troops at Vladivostock. The Japanese, however, were rein-forcing their troops on their own initiative, and had had a successon the Ussuri front. They had established contact with the Czecho-Slovak reinforcements, but not with the main body of the Czecho-Slovak force.Lord Robert Cecil thoxight that the Japanese would never riska military disaster, and as they had announced their intention of saving the Czecho-Slovaks they were not likely to fail to carry out this commitment.The Western Front. 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that the canadians had moved up north into the area north of the Somme,and were attacking astride the Arras-Cambrai road. It wouldseem that the offensive south of the Somme was drawing to anend, unless it was possible to get further forward in that area without heavy losses. General Harper, who was in command of our troops opposite Bapaume, thought that he might be able to getpossession of all that now remained of the town. He would not undertake this operation, however, if it involved heavy loss.Bapaume was no longer of any use to the Germans.Our losses in the recent offensive had been remarkably slight,the fighting having been of the nature of advance-guard and rear-guard fighting, and not a general battle attack.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff then gave a comparison between our losses and captures in the attacks on the PasschenclaeleRidge last autumn and those during the last nineteen days on the arras-Somme front. In the attacks on the Passchendaele Ridge wesuffered 265,000 casualties, and took 24,000 prisoners and 64 guns.Since the 8th August, 1918, we had suffered 58,000 casualties, andhad taken 47,000 prisoners and between 500 and 600 guns. Sincethe 18th July, the French and ourselves had taken over 100,000German prisoners.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to publishan official statement to this effect.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that the UnitedStates troops were now practically all in the United States area, andthat he thought Marshal Foch was going to use them for someenterprise as soon as the present phase of the offensive was over.A German counter-attack in the Champagne country was now apossibility.General Wilson added that the German machine-gunners, whohad formed the strongest element in their rear-guard fighting, had fought extremely well. It was clear, however, that the Germansfeared our tanks. Our losses in tanks had been heavy, but for themost part in tanks out of working order, which could be repaired.Complete losses were small, and the German machine-gunners hadbeen unable to do anything against the tanks.Death of 3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that GeneralGeneral Cox. Cox, the Head of the British Intelligence Department at GeneralHeadcprarters, France, was accidentally drowned while bathing atEtaples the previous day. The loss of General Cox was a verygreat one.Trans-Caucasia. 4. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that we now had 600 men at Baku, which appeared to be a very defensible place.The First  Sea  Lord   stated  that a naval  contingent  had reached the Caspian, more men were on the way, and would be-
Submarines. 5. The First Sea Lord reported that H.M.S. &quot;Medea&quot; had attacked an enemy submarine off the East Coast on the 24th August,and it appeared that the submarine was destroyed.6. The First Sea Lord reported that on the 23rd August enemymotor-boats had made a raid in Dunkirk Roads. The Frenchclaimed to have sunk one of the German boats. The German claim which they had published, to the effect that two of our motor-boats were sunk, -was false.Enemy Motor-BoatBaid in DunkirkBoads.Aerial Attack on 7. The First Sea Lord reported that on the night of the constantinople. 25th-26th August our forces operating in the iEgean droppedbombs on Constantinople, causing fires in Stamboul.   Bombs were also dropped on Gallipoli and Chanak.Beplacement ofBepatriatedGerman Prisoners.8. The War Cabinet had under consideration a note by theMinister of National Service, covering a report of the national labour Priority Committee (Paper G.T.-5421) and a memorandumby the Deputy Minister of Munitions (Paper G.T.-5480), on thesubject of the replacement of repatriated German prisoners.The Deputy Minister of Munitions called attention to the post-script to his memorandum, urging that 6,000 German prisonersshould be sent to England in order to replace those about to be repatriated, in view of the number of prisoners taken on the western front having increased so largely.The Director of Military Operations stated that the Adjutant-General and General Fleadquarters in France had put forward strong objections to sending German prisoners of war from France to workin England. Alread3^, owing mainly to repatriation, the labour units in France would be decreased to the extent of some 90,000, and ifthe German prisoners were taken away the labour in France wouldLj-io vjcuuau jjj.iouxj.cio vvcic utuveii avvcij tut; lciuuui   111 ju luiiuc wuiuu      ^     wgsnabe veiy seriously disorganised^i^efc oh      c&amp;t &amp;t t*&amp;cjb*oAnf &amp; %J4&amp; ft^Uxz^^o.The First Lord of the Admiralty put forward a similar claim to/ t co-e-A-fzthat of the Ministry of Munitions, namely, that prisoners should becu-lkesent to England to replace men now employed on national shipyards,. kwho might be withdrawn. b^a.-........ ..,The Minister of National Service pointed out that the allocation of German prisoners in this country was under the control of theNational Labour Priority Committee, and was reviewed continuously.At the present moment very heavy demands were being made by theWar Office for tank expansion, and by the Royal Air Force atBlandiord.General Vesey, who represented the Adjutant-General, read tothe War Cabinet a paper giving the views of Sir Nevil Macreadyon this question, which was to the following effect: The actualnumber of German prisoners of war who would be due for repatria-tion at the present time would not exceed 15,000 in the UnitedKingdom, and approximately a further 15,000 would graduallybecome due for repatriation by August 1919. Our armies in france would lose 16,000 at once, and another 37,000 by August 1919. Inthe meantime very little assistance was being obtained from theMinistry of National Service with regard to the supply of military labour. The British labour units in France were at presentmore than 21,000 under strength, and since the 1st March labour in France had lost some 53,000, in addition to which are the-460] B 2ready to take over the Caspian ships as soon as they became avail-able. Practically all the information received by him from the caspian was of a technical nature, and there was little or no information of a general character.
The Czecho- 1. WITH reference to War Cabinet 463, Minute 5, the Chief ofSlovak Forces. the Imperial General Staff said that he had received a telegramfrom Marshal Foch stating that he was reluctant to intervene with president Wilson, as suggested, regarding the reinforcement of theAllied troops at Vladivostock. The Japanese, however, were rein-forcing their troops on their own initiative, and had had a successon the Ussuri front. They had established contact &quot;with the Czecho-Slovak reinforcements, but not with the main body of the Czecho-Slovak force.Lord Robert Cecil thoTight that the Japanese would never riska military disaster, and as they had announced their intention of saving the Czecho-Slovaks they were not likely to fail to carry out this commitment.The Western Front. 2. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that the canadians had moved up north into the area north of the Somme,and were attacking astride the Arras-Cambrai road. It wouldseem that the offensive south of the Somme was drawing to anend, unless it was possible to get further forward in that area without heavy losses. General Harper, who was in command of our troops opposite Bapaume, thought that he might be able to getpossession of all that now remained of the town. He would not undertake this operation, however, if it involved heavy loss.Bapaume was no longer of any use to the Germans.Our losses in the recent offensive had been remarkably slight,the fighting having been of the nature of advance-guard and rear-guard fighting, and not a general battle attack.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff then gave a comparison between our losses and captures in the attacks on the PasschendaeleRidge last autumn and those during the last nineteen days on the arras-Somme front. In the attacks on the Passchendaele Ridge wesuffered 265,000 casualties, and took 24,000 prisoners and 64 guns.Since the 8th August, 1918, we had suffered 58,000 casualties, andhad taken 47,000 prisoners and between 500 and 600 guns. Sincethe 18th July, the French and ourselves had taken over 100,000German prisoners.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff undertook to publishan official statement to this effect. ,The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that the UnitedStates troops were now practically all in the United States area, andthat he thought Marshal Foch was going to use them for someenterprise as soon as the present phase of the offensive was over.A German counter-attack in the Champagne country was now apossibility.General Wilson added that the German machine-gunners, whohad formed the strongest element in their rear-guard fighting, had fought extremely well. It was clear, however, that the Germansfeared our tanks. Our losses in tanks had been heavy, but for themost part in tanks out of working order, which could be repaired.Complete losses were small, and the German machine-gunners hadbeen unable to do anything against the tanks.Death of -   3. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff reported that GeneralGeneral Cox. Cox, the Head of the British Intelligence Department at general headquarters, France, was accidentally drowned while bathing atEtaples the previous day. The loss of General Cox was a verygreat one.Trans-Caucasia. 4. The Chief of the Imperial General Staff stated that we now had 600 men at Baku, which appeared to be a very defensible place.The First  Sea   Lord  stated  that a naval  contingent had reached the Caspian, more men were on the way, and would be
Submarines.Enemy Motor-BoatRaid in DunkirkRoads.Aerial Attack onConstantinople.ready to take over the Caspian ships as soon as they became avail-able. Practically all the information received by him from the caspian was of a technical nature, and there was little or no information of a general character.5. The First Sea Lord reported that H.M.S. &quot;Medea&quot; had attacked an enemy submarine off the East Coast on the 24th August,and it appeared that the submarine was destroyed.6. The First Sea Lord reported that on the 23rd August enemymotor-boats had made a raid in Dunkirk Roads. The Frenchclaimed to have sunk one of the German boats. The German claim,which they had published, to the effect that two of our motor-boats were sunk, was false.7. The First Sea Lord reported that on the night of the25th-26th August our forces operating in the iEgean droppedbombs on Constantinople, causing fires in Stamboul. Bombs were also dropped on Gallipoli and Chauak.Replacement ofRepatriatedGerman Prisoners.S. The War Cabinet had under consideration a note by theMinister of National Service, covering a report of the NationalLaboiir Priority Committee (Paper G.T.-5421) and a memorandumby the Deputy Minister of Munitions (Paper G.T.-5480), on thesubject of the replacement of repatriated German prisoners.The Deputy Minister of Munitions called attention to the post-script to his memorandum, urging that 6,000 German prisonersshould be sent to England in order to replace those about to be repatriated, in view of the number of prisoners taken on the western front having increased so largely.The Director of Military Operations stated that the Adjutant-General and General Headquarters in France had put forward strong objections to sending German prisoners of -war from France to workin England. Already, owing mainly to repatriation, the labour units in France would be decreased to the extent of some 90,000, and ifthe German prisoners were taken away the labour in France wouldbe very seriously disorganised***o&amp; cJ-      -:&amp;A &amp; h^cMMAn^  51kteA j^^-^M5:The First Lord of the Admiralty put forward a similar claim totfta jurisdiction-s-f^^that of the Ministry of Munitions, namely, that juisoners should hea4-&quot;Ikesent to England to replace men now employed on national shipyards, &apos;-who might be withdrawn. ista-w.,:^..The Minister of National Service pointed out that the allocation of German prisoners in this country was under the control of theNational Labour Priority Committee, and was reviewed continuously.At the present moment very heavy demands were being made by theWar Office for tank expansion, and by the Royal Air Force atBlandlord.General Vesey, who represented the Adjutant-General, read tothe AVar Cabinet a paper giving the views of Sir Nevil Macreadyon this question, which was to the following effect: The actualnumber of German prisoners of war who would be due for repatria-tion at the present time would not exceed 15,000 in the UnitedKingdom, and approximately a further 15,000 would graduallybecome due for repatriation by August 1919. Our armies in france would lose 16,000 at once, and another 37,000 by August 1919. Inthe meantime very little assistance was being obtained from theMinistry of National Service with regard to the supply of military labour. The British labour units in France were at presentmore than 21,000 under strength, and since the 1st March labour in France had lost some 53,000, in addition to which are the-460] B 2
prisoners of war mentioned above now employed in France, plus4,500 South Africans due for return to South Africa in October.Sir Nevil Macready failed to see how labour in this country could possibly be made good by prisoner of war labour from France solong as ships are not available to import coloured labour into France.He stated that the labour question had been giving him great anxietysince the beginning of this year, as he was unable to see how labourcould be kept up which must be available under ordinary conditions,leaving out any question of advance over devastated territory. Ifthe requisite. labour was not available in France, the combatanttroops would have to carry out the work, and would therefore be deprived of the rest and retraining which were considered to be essential. Sir Nevil Macready expressed the opinion that thisquestion only formed part of the general question as to the strengthof the forces this country was able to maintain on the continent inaddition to the industrial effort which was being put forward.Questioned as to whether any attempt had been made to induce the coloured labour which was being repatriated to sign on again,General Vesey said that efforts had been made, but without success.The Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Shipping saidthat he had only received the memoranda on this question that morning, but, in the absence of the Minister of Shipping, he desiredto impress on the AVar Cabinet the gravity of the shipping situationif it were intended to transport coloured labour to France. Sir LeoMoney said that, as he was informed, the only coolies who were ofany value in France were those who came from Northern China,who could only be transported to France via Vancouver, America,and the Atlantic. This meant, in effect, that for every Chinesecoolie imported into France we lost three or more Americansoldiers.The Minister of Munitions expressed the hope that, in thisconnection, the question of the Italian labourers now employed inFrance would not be opened. Mr. Churchill said the need of coalin Italy was so grave that he was of opinion that if the question arose as to whether the Italians should obtain the coal, or give thelabour, they would certainly prefer to get the coal.Sir Auckland Geddes pointed out that the memorandum of theNational Labour Priority Committee, which was being consideredby the AVar Cabinet, and which recommended that when the german prisoners in this country were sent back to Germany, their placesshould be taken by the more recently captured prisoners working in France, was the result of a meeting at which a War Officerepresentative was present, and to which he had agreed; butGeneral Vesey informed the War Cabinet that the War Officerepresentative who attended the Committee meeting was not qualified to give an opinion on this question.The War Cabinet decided that The proposals put forward by the National Labour priority committee in their memorandum (Paper G.T.-5421)should be approved pending re-consideration of the wholeman-power situation, and subject to the reservation of anyshipping problem.Sea Transport for 9. With reference to War Cabinet 237, Minute 5, of the 21stTroops in the September, 1917, the War Cabinet had before them a memorandumMediterranean.        by the General Staff, War Office (Paper G.T.-5490), in regard tothe provision of leave facilities from the Eastern theatres of war.It was submitted in the memorandum that, in view of the favourable turn which events on the Western front had recently taken, the chances of any large movement of troops in theMediterranean becoming necessary at short notice in the immediate
Kigid Airship 10. With reference to War Cabinet 336, Minute 7, the WarHousing Sheds. Cabinet had under consideration an Admiralty memorandum (paper g.T.-5488) on the subject of the construction of housing accom-modation for two rigid airships at Ivilleagh.The First Lord of the Admiralty expressed the hope that theWar Cabinet, when considering this question, would keep in view the discussion which took place on the 1st February, 1918, when itwas decided that no further supply of steel should be applied to thebuilding of the housing-sheds for rigid airships. The originalAdmiralty programme in connection with airship sheds had beenreduced, as recommended by General Smuts, in the end of last yearand had thereafter been approved by the War Cabinet. It had,however, at a later stage, viz., on the 1st February, been &quot; turneddown &quot; on account of the lack of steel. The general approval tothe reduced programme had, nevertheless, not been withdrawn, andthe Admiralty were entitled to take it that, provided the steelsituation was solved, the sanction of the Cabinet would be given.The steel position had now improved, and consequently he was ofopinion that this was a good opportunity to bring the matterforward again. As regards the labour, Sir Eric Geddes said that sir Alexander Gibb, Civil Engineer-in-Chief of the Admiralty,did not anticipate any trouble, the labour position in Irelandbeing so different from that in Great Britain. The erection ofthese sheds would not require a large amount of skilled&apos; labour.If these sheds were not provided, the Admiralty would then have&apos;to choose between scrapping obsolescent types or not buildingbetter types. Sir Eric Geddes urged that the question as to therelative value of rigid airships should not be raised in dealingwith the Admiralty memorandum; but in asking the AVar cabinet for approval of the construction of this housing accommodation, he considered it was only right to point out the failure of the AirMinistry to provide even the programme which had been put forward by that Department strengthened the arguments in favour of theconstruction of these sheds. These rigid airships were badly wantedfor scouting and anti-submarine patrol. The Commander-in-Chiefof the Grand Fleet had estimated that one Zeppelin was equivalentto six light cruisers for scouting purposes, and as the enemy sub-marines were now extending their operations further from the land,it was essential that the Admiralty should have long-flight machinesin order to maintain an efficient patrol.The Minister of Munitions said that the War Priorities Com-mittee originated out of this very question. At the present time that Committee was not approving of any construction which couldnot be completed within twelve months. According to thememorandum, the first of the sheds at Killeagh could probably becompleted in about twelve months&apos; time, and the second early in1920, and consequently Mr. Churchill did not consider it was justi-fiable to use 8,500 tons of steel for a war weapon which would not materialise for at least twelve months.   It was also necessary, in thisfuture had been reduced. It was therefore suggested that arrange-ments might now be made between the Admiralty, the War Office,and the Minister of Shipping, whereby the pool of shipping forone and a half divisions, while retained intact in, or in the neigh-hood of, the Mediterranean, might be so utilised as to provide facilities for a certain measure of leave, particularly from Salonicaand Mesopotamia, so long as shipping for one complete division wascontinuously held in readiness for use at short, notice.This suggestion was concurred in by the Admiralty, the WarOffice, and the Ministry of Shipping.The War Cabinet approved the arrangements proposed in theWar Office memorandum.
connection, to take into consideration the other questions involved,namely, those of skilled labour and coal.General Smuts said that originally the programme for rigidairships had been referred to him. He had cut the programmedown, and in its amended form it had been approved by the WarCabinet. It then came before the War Priorities Committee, but was not approved, chiefly on the question of the amount of steelavailable. General Smuts said that he felt the programme as putforward by the Admiralty was &amp; sound one; it had been approvedby the War Cabinet; had been rejected by the War Priorities Com-mittee mainly by reason of the difficulty about steel; and that if this difficulty could now be removed he was in favour of authorisation of the proposal uoav put forward.The Minister for Air said that the programme of accommodation for aeroplanes was falling behind, and consequently he had askedhis officers to revise their plans for building. It was most inadvisablethat any programme should be passed which might break down incarrying out a portion of it. The labour situation was such that he considered some of the programmes put forward must be revised,and expressed the opinion that the proposal before the Cabinet wasa case in point.The War Cabinet, having deliberated in private, decided that The construction of housing accommodation for two airships atKilleagh should be approved.(Initialled) A. B. L.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.,August 27, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
