<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/12/0 images: 4-5</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Maje.sty&apos;s GwemmeafcXPrinted for the War Cabinet.   August 1919..SECRET.149WAR CABINET 616.Conclusions of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held at 10, Downing Street, S.W.,on Friday, August 15, 1919, at ll-30 a.m.Present :The Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.        The Right Hon. A. Chamberlain, M.P.The Ri^ht Hon. G. N. Barnes, M.P. The Right Hon. Sir E. Geddes, G.C.B.G.B.E., M.P.The following were also present:The Right  Hon. W. Long, M.P., FirstLord of the Admiralty.The Right Hon. Sir A. C Geddes, KC.B...M.P., President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. H. A. l. Fisher, L.L.D.,M.P..tion.President of the Board of Educa-The Right Hon. Sir R S. Hornk, K.B.E.,K.C., M.P., Minister of Labour.The Right Hon. Maior-General J. E. B.Seely, C.B., C.M.G., D.S.O., M.P.,Under-Secretary of State for Air.Field-Marshal Sir H. H. Wilson, G.C.B.,D.S.O.,-Chief of the Imperial GeneralStaff.The Right Hon. W. S. Churchill, M.P.,Secretary of State for War.The Right Hon. C. addison, M.D., M.P.,Minister of Health.The Rioht Hon. Sir L. Worthington-Evans, Bart., M.P., Minister of Pensions.The Right Hon. H. W. Forster, M.P.,Financial Secretary, War Office.The Right Hon. Sir .J. Maolay, Bart.,Shipping Controller.Major-General Sir C. H. PIarlngton,K.C.B., D.S.O., Deputy Chief of theImperial Genera! Staff.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B., Secretary.Mr. G. M. Evans, Assistant Secretary.Lieutenant-Colonel L. Storr, C.B., Assistant Secretary.Captain L. F. Burgis, Assistant Secretary.[620]
Future conditionsof service in theArmy (officers),and pay of medical officers in theRoyal &apos;Air Force.1. The.War Cabinet had under consideration the Third Reportof the Committee on Naval, Military, and Air E^rce Pay(Paper G-.-259), which proposed complete schemes for the. futurepay, retired pay, half-pay, and certain allowances for officers in theArmy : and also dealt with the pay of medical officers in the RoyalAir Force.The War Cabinet decided (a.) To approve the Third Report of the Committee on Naval,Military, and Air Force Pay (Paper G.-259).. [b.) * That, on the occasion of the announcement of the increased( rates of pay, it should also be announced that ,a schemeof compulsory insurance in connection with disabilityretired pay was under consideration, and, if it were found advisable, deductions might be made from the authorised rates of pay equivalent to the insurancepremiums.The Secretary of State for War took note of the- suggestion of the Chancellor of the Exchequer that every effort should be made to cut down the expenses of army officers, and to insist upon rigid economy.Pay and pensions of men in theArmy.2. With reference to War Cabinet GOO, Minute 5, the WarCabinet had under consideration proposals for the future pay of menin the Army, contained in the Second Report of the Committee on naval, Military, and Air Force Pay (Paper G.-254), together with proposals for the future pensions of men in the Army (fouth report of the Committee, Paper G.-260).The War Cabinet decided To adjourn consideration of the proposals for the pay and pensions of men in the Army until the Secretary of Statefor War had again considered the pay of the Army in thelight (a) of the future organisation of the Service as determined by the military policy to be followed, (b) ofthe suggestion made by the Prime Minister that the present rates of pay and bonus should be made permanent, andthat the additional money involved in the proposals for paycontained in Paper G.-254 should be devoted to improving the efficiency of the Army in some other respect.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,August 15, 1919.* The War Office desire that such announcement regarding compulsory insuranceshall be withheld until they have had an . opportunity of examining the proposed scheme.

</content>
</cab>
