<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/186/0 images: 312-312</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet, April, 1927.SECRET.CoprNo. 30CP. 134 (27).THE CABINET.PROPOSED ESTABLISHMENT OF A CONVALESCENT HOSPITAL  AT WEI-HAI-WEI  FOR  THE  SHANGHAIDEFENCE FORCE.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.My colleagues are aware that special steps have had to be taken to provide suitable hospital accommodation for the troops of the Shanghai Defence Force, among whom, owing to the climate and general conditions of their service, the incidence of disease, especially venereal, is necessarily heavy. With the co-operation of the Canadian Government, a hospital and a convalescent depot are being established at Vancouver Island, which will be equipped to deal with 250 cases.The advantages of Wei-Hai-Wei from the point of view of climate, accessibility and relative cheapness are deserving of serious consideration. Wei-Hai-Wei is less than 2 days journey from Shanghai, whereas Vancouver Island is at least 15 ; there is already a small hospital there and a suitable site for an ideal convalescent depot where the sick and invalids would be under the close supervision of the General Officer Commanding and his staff.Men who will ultimately require to be invalided to the United Kingdom would more appropriately be dealt with in the Canadian Hospital, but light cases and those where the period of convalescence is short, would gain from being sent to Wei-Hai-Wei.I am aware that the Cabinet decided in February last* not to sanction the further occupation of Wei-Hai-Wei, where there is at present a platoon of infantry from the Tientsin Battalion, as likely to antagonise the Northern Government, especially as negotiations are in progress for the return to China of the occupied territory.The situation has, however, changed since that decision and the question of the return of Wei-Hai-Wei has fallen into abeyance. Moreover, Sir Miles Lampson in his telegram No. 745 of 20th April, regards Wei-Hai-Wei as the most suitable place to which His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Legation in Peking should be withdrawn if necessity should arise. This move of the Legation would be accompanied by the transfer of the Legation Guard, and the position could be made secure from attack by a battalion being placed there immediately.It seems to me, therefore, that on political, military and administrative grounds there is a good case for establishing ourselves more strongly in Wei-Hai-Wei by despatching a battalion of infantry to that place from Shanghai, the platoon there being returned to its battalion at Tientsin, and to take this opportunity of organizing a convalescent depot which would materially facilitate the medical ministrations to the Shanghai Defence Force.L. W.-E.The War Office,26th April, 1927.* Cabinet 9 (27).(b27/15)   100  4/2t   w.o.p.   8103

</content>
</cab>
