<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/1/0 images: 1-1</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M. 20(55)							5th July, 1955

							[Enter Att.G. B.H., J.T., R.
		1.	Leakages of Information.

P.M.	Leakages : Simonstown, Javelin aircraft.  Ministers, incldg Juniors, have contacts with Press : they must be careful.
	Will Ministers speak suitably to Junior Ministers.

		
2.	H/Commons Disqualification.

H.C.	Sir R. Jennings : public auditor under Fr. Societies Act : ever since elected to H/C. in 1939.  Indemnity Bill will be needed – after Sel. Cttee.

Att.G.		Apptd. by Ty., who are empowered to pay – tho’ Societies pay in fact.


3.	Admiral Hughes-Hallett : Retired Pay.

J.T.	Admiral was misled.  He wd. have suffered political damage if he had w’drawn at last moment.
	As some time has elapsed, hope Cab. will consider a) or b).

A.E.	I wd. prefer to allow law to take its course.  Won’t there be political trouble?

R.A.B.	Don’t like it.  But mistake was made.  Worth trying to settle out of court.

Att.G.	Admiral wd. be. well advised to settle on 50% basis.  That wd. be a proper settlement from our angle.  We cd. say we were prepd. to go to arbitn. but offer to settle.

W.M.	Normal kind of offer when it’s doubtful how the case wd. go in law.  Reputable firm of solrs., who wd. be ready to settle.

S.Ll.		Arbitrator wd. be protn. for Govt., if controversy later.

O.P.	Wd. favour paying in full : we do when officials leave given wrong advice.

Att.G.	Adml. cd. have checked it, in publd. books, or by reference to Finance Branch.

R.A.B.	x/	He cd. have w’drawn candidature if he had needed the money.

S.		Dislike arbitn. : undignified.
		I support x/.  His is an odd attitude.

J.S.		In public hearing, sympathy wd. be with Admiral because of Admy. mistake.

S.		He cd. have had the money, if he had chosen.

R.A.B.		Go for 50% settlement : if that fails, let him sue.  Don’t like arbitn.

D.S.	y/	Arbitn. wd. be protection to Govt.

Att.G.		Argument for settling is that it avoids costs, wh. might be out of all propn. to sums at stake.
		Try for 50% settlement.  If that fails, let him suggest arbitn. or action.

S.Ll.		Support y/.

W.M.		Can we wait to get K.’s view?

Att.G.		Solrs. are getting restive.

W.		Wd. prefer to have authority to pay – hence favour abitn.

W.M.		L.O. formal opinion is an authority.

		Agreed : Resume discn. when K. is back.
								[Exist J.T., Att.G.
								[Enter I. Macl.
		4.	Social Services.

RAB.		We have bn. living on N.I. Fund.  Can’t go on with that for long.  Must know where we are going.

D.S.		Cab. decided tht. housing subsidy shd. be reduced.  Can we p’pone increase of interest on Public Works Loans.  	Increase will provoke demands for increased subsidy.  Don’t want to agree now v. not increasing it, &amp; then come fwd. later with difft. arguments for reducg it.

R.A.B.		Want to get it into line with market.  But will discuss with M/H. &amp; come back to Cab. if we disagree.

J.S.		Wish to be consulted by D.S. before proposals formulated.

O.P.		Comparison with g.n.p.  Is that valid?  Exp’re on physical things comes out of g.n.p.  But transfer paymts have v. little effect on productivity.  May out-run our taxable capacity : but that’s not same as productivity.  If prices continue to rise, we shall have to adjust social service benefits : for can’t have increasg disparity betwn. wage-earners &amp; fixed-income groups.
		In debate on 4/6 my Dpt. was authd. to promise this in reln. to pension-increase groups.

D.E.		Review on “existing policy.”  We haven’t got one, on educn., over 5 yrs.  E.g. what assumptns. do we make on reducg. size of classes or expandg. technical educn.  I am framing policy proposals now.  Ty. can’t make “review” while these are un-decided.  Discn. is needed first on assumptions.

I. Mac.		Same goes for me.
		Percentage attributed to social services has dropped since we were in office.  
		Wd. want opportunity to discuss policy with R.A.B.  I can’t see ahead for 5 years.

R.A.B.		Last sentence in para 2. can’t be denied.
		But agree we can’t have survey w’out consultn. with Dpts or w’out review of assumptns.  But get cost on existg. policy first.  May I get this going inter-departmentally.

A.E.		Some of this exp’re. is remunerative.
		Survey won’t commit us to decisions.

H.C.		Avoid any publicity.
									[Exit I. Macl.

		5.	Malta. 

A.L.B.		Revised draft statement – submitted.

H.		Hope conference will explore other possibilities, wh. might apply to other Colonies.  Hope we may consider t. of r. later.

A.E.		At equal taxation, other Colonies won’t want it – save prs. Gib.

S.Ll.		What happens at end?  Labour Member will support.  Tories will split.  Govt decision will turn on how Tories split.  Ultimate posn. of Govt. may be more difficult.  Mght be easier for Govt. to decide now.

R.A.B.		Round-table procedure is controlled by Govt.  They can guide &amp; influence.  Better therefore than Joint Sel. Cttee.  Can’t settle this w’out any enquiry.

O.P.		We can’t apply our social services in Malta.  Confce. shd. take into a/c the financial &amp; adminve. implications.

A.L.B.		Nothing in this announcement to stop this.

P.M.		Read minute from H.M.

R.A.B.		Best way out of a v. diff. pol. situation.

J.S.		Consult leaders of Oppn. Parties before announcemt. made.

P.M.		Yes.  

			Announce – Thursday.  Wednesday.

A.L.B.		This will give me chance of warning Olivier, on Wed. a.m.

									[Enter B.C.
		6.	Industrial Disputes.

W.M.		Are setting up enquiry into working of Dock Labour Scheme.  
		Must ask T.G.W.U. to put their house in order on Merseyside.  This is not the end of trouble there.
		One good effect : last 3 strikes have gained nothing for workers which cdn’t have bn. gained w’out strikes.
		Stevedores on Merseyside may go for another break-away Union.

									[Exit B.C.
		7.	Mrs. Nunn May : Grant of Br. Passport.

R.		Congress decision will be taken by 18/7.

P.M.		Why can’t she be interviewed?

W.M.		Rumour that his work may come to end in autumn.

Ll.G.		They cd. leave w’out ppts.

S.		Must stall until 18/7.

P.M.		Wait until after 18/7.  Then have her interviewed – to form judgmt. on her intentions.  Then report to Cabinet.


		8.	Register of Electors.

J.S.		Experts in Scotland think it unnecessary.

P.M.		Seems less important now tht. we have proved we can win an election in summer.

W.		No need for it.

			Agreed : no action.



		9.	Monopolies.

P.T.		Indicated proposed answer to P.Q.
</content>
</cab>