<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/14/0 images: 18-18</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.8(56)							31st January, 1956





		1.	India &amp; Pakistan : Arms.		[Enter R.M., E.H., A.N



H.	India will buy R. aircraft, if Canberra contract breaks down.  Special offer is justified.  India have agreed to take Gnats &amp; Hunters : if they take Canberras it will be a useful range.  Price : delivery dates : technical performance – these are the diffies. but price is greatest.  Therefore I hope the developmt. levy can be waived.

	Pakistan.  Bofors guns &amp; 5 ships ( £1¼ M. might well be paid).

	Guns : token paymt. vice gift.



H.M.	Financial consns. need not prevail over political.

	Canberras.  Weakness is English Electric : their price was too high &amp; they still won’t disclose profit margin.  We may end by subsidising them not India.



R.M.	Delivery – can be met by sacrifice by R.A.F.

	Technical – U.S. can be pressed to agree to release Green Satin.

	Price – E. El. will come down a bit further if we contribute £ for £ on our levy.  We do often abate these levies in order to get exports.



D.S.	Canberra is only plane since war which can sell abroad as commercial success.



H.M.	Price has come down £20,000 on a £209.000 figure.



R.M.	But under pressure from us.



W.M.	Unattractive.  R. can sell v. cheap &amp; this is driving us down.

	Complete waiver of export levy wd. be awkward precedent.



H.	Concession on delivery : Gn. Satin might turn scale.  But I doubt it.



P.T.	B/T. fear this : but I consider that pol. consns. shd. overrule “trading” precedents.



A.N.	S.Ll. supports H. on this.

	If India turned to R. for arms, others mght well follow.



		Agreed : 	be ready to make necessary concessions on all 3 			points re Canberra.



R.A.B.	Try for a nominal payment on Bofors guns, eg. £50,000. and

	£1¼ M. for the ships.		



		Agreed  :	Supply these to Pakistan for nominal payment.  			Between £10,000 and £50,000 for the guns and 			£1¼ M. for the ships. (Subject to clearance of 			details by Def. Cttee.)

								[Exit R.M.

[Enter B.C.

		2.	Parliament.

						

R.A.B.		Business for next week.

	9/2.  M/T. says that with another week he mght bring round some few Govt. supporters who wd. otherwise vote v. Bill.  Transport (Disposal of Road Haulage Property) Bill.



E.H.	V. few will vote against.  Oppn. will be in favour.  Nothing else ready.



RAB.	V. well.  Don’t let us wait.





		3.	Teachers’ Superannuation Bill.



RAB.	i)  M/Ed. saw Party Cttee. last night.  Burnham Cttee. will now take decn. in autumn – Sept. or Oct.  Shd. opn. of Bill be deferred until then.  Cttee. agreed Minister shd. go ½ way to meet B’ham Cttee., with exceptn. of Pickthorn.  Minister will therefore propose in Standing Cttee. to-day that opn. of Bill be deferred until 1/10.

	This shd. secure Party’s support for Bill.

	ii) Sc. Members ask for 4 days in Sc. Grand Cttee. on this Bill, in return for wh. they will be silent on English part of Bill.  Believe this will reduce time &amp; obviate need for time-table.



J.S.	For a firm Sc. undertakg., we cd. clinch this.  But I have to get on with Sc. Rating &amp; Valuation in Sc. Grand Cttee. early in Feby. 



		Approved i)

		Agreed – R.A.B. to dicuss ii) with J.S. and E.H.





		4.	Cyprus.



ALB.	Jamming.  Parly. controversy will revive when we start jamming.

	Discussions with Makarios.  Formula is leaking in Athens Press.  Govr. suggests we announce it here.  But Makarios himself hasn’t disclosed it yet : we don’t want to go off first.  If publd. here, it will be criticised &amp; this will stiffen M.  Thus, I favour saying nothg. until we can make substantial statement &amp; justify our policy.



A.N.	Turkish Govt. has bn. informed.  They have taken it well.  I also deprecate announcemt.



A.L.B.	Local Turks have bn. told by Govr.



		Agreed  :	no statement yet.

				A.L.B. to inforce P.M. of position reached.



	Jamming.	Govr. has said he won’t start while talks continue &amp; if 		they break down, will give 48 hrs. notice to us before he 		starts.						Noted.





		5.	Widows Pensions.



B.C.	Wish to publish report on Friday.



R.A.B.	Legn. needed, but can’t be introduced until next Session.  V. awkward to have report hanging round so long.  But worse trouble if we delay it.

	Govt. decisions on recommns. must be deferred – for about 1 month.



H.M.	Embarrassing but inevitable.



		Agreed :	Publish report.

				M/P. to submit recommns. on policy.





		6.	Industrial Dispute : Printing.



I.M.	Work to rule – affectg. periodicals &amp; provincial newspp.  Also Stationery Office work.  Union want restorn. of differential.  They are ready to face long dispute.  May lead to lock-outs or even strikes.  In that event, printing for H/C. wd. have to be organised by volunteers from Govt. Dpts.  This is being discussed with Unions concerned, who are being warned not to raise diffies. over mtg. this constitutional need.



RAB.	First stage : duplicate vice print.  Can go ahead with that.

	Second stage : blackleg printing.  Not w’out further decn. by Cab.  Speaker &amp; Clerk of H/C. agree with what is proposed.



								[Exit B.C.

[Enter Att.G.  Mill.



		7.	Capital Punishment.				



Ll.G.	In last debate we rejected main recommns. of R. Commn.  but didn’t exclude legn. sometime on minor recommns.  And now report of Heald’s Cttee., which is likely to command much support, suggests tht. we shd. offer action on those lines in order to get a better chance of rejecting pressure for abolition.

	The motion will have to give H/C. opportunity for clear vote for or against penalty.



J.S.	Diffy.  If we promise legn. we can’t delay it until next Session.

	In view of Ll.G.’s speech on 10/xi, this wd. be represented as a change of mind.  We can’t plead Heald’s report as our reason.

	The real issue is “for or against” : will this offer really gain support for the answer “for”.



K.	Ll.G. reserved right to legislate on these points.

	Explann. for such an offer now – argument in Heald Rpt. : viz., in order to get clear decn. on main issue, better to clear away minor points wh. we can concede to abolitionists.

	If Ll.G. speaks in debate w’out any positive suggns. his appeal will be much weaker.

	On delay : we can plead tht. introdn. of diminished responsibility is so serious a step that we shdn’t hurry it.



R.A.B.	Tactics.  Gt. pressure in H/C. for early debate, wh. was ½ promised.  Better that H/C. debate shd. come first.  For stiff line by H/L. wd. make H/C. even more determined to be soft.

     *	H. shd. try, however, to persuade Chorley to p’pone debate in H/L.

	If that fails, H/C. will have to take it on 14/2.

	General view that in H/C. there must be free vote.  That precludes strong Govt. motion.  An Oppn. motion wd. favour experimental abolition for 10 yrs.  Alternative : a Heald motion, wh. we cd. influence.

	I suggest debate on motion by Heald favouring retention but offering the minor changes.



Att.G.	If Govt. is to have last speech before Divn. (v. important), it must not be on Opposn. motion.



Ll.G.	Free vote : but for back-benchers only.  Members of Govt. shd. be free only to abstain.  They shd not be free to vote against advice of responsible Minister.



R.A.B.	Believe Ll.G. will be able to take such a constructive line that it will not be diff. to vote in favour of retention.



H.M.	Favour debate on motion by Heald.  Less awkward for Govt. if beaten.



J.S.	I agree.

	Motion shd. be in such a form that legn. wdn’t affect Scotland.



		Agreed  :	Debate in H/C. before debate in H/L. but after 			P.M.’s return.

				Motion to be tabled by Heald.

				Free vote but Members of Govt. shd. not vote 			against advice of responsible Ministers. 

Govt. Speakers : Ll.G. + another (to be 

discussed with Att.G. : shd. it be political or 

legal.

								[Exit Att.G.

[   “   Mill.



8.	Betting &amp; Lotteries.



Ll.G.	[Not heard.]



R.A.B.	This will be in next years’ p’mme.  Ll.G. shd. relate what he says (after H/L. debate) to that reality – viz., not this year.



								[Exit E.H.

[Enter A.J.

		9.	Fuel &amp; Power Prospects.				



A.J.	Mainly for informn.  Decn. needed only on open-cast.  If Cab. accepted in principle need to m’tain open-cast output at present level, I wd. suggest a small Cttee. to consider –

		i)  compensn., wh. shd. be more general.

		ii) a policy area by area.

	Under Labour, priority for coal.  Under Tories, priority for certain types of agric. land : this is due to expire at end of this year.  Want a new policy, with priorities, by area.



R.A.B.	Revised plan to be publd. in March.



A.J.	Wd, circulate to Cab. early in March – prelude to new Borrowing Powers Bill which I shd. like to get 2nd. Rdg soon after Easter.



H.M.	Ty. and M/F &amp; P. will co-operate on that memo.

	Welcome redn. of imports.  Shall save only £10 M., vice £17 M., because of binding contracts.

	Atomic age contn. has bn. over-played : only saves a few m. tons : has done much harm to morale etc., of mining industry.  Has suggd. this is dying industry, when we shall need it for another 100 yrs.  Oil also has contribd.  We must make mining industry more efficient.

	Can’t get man power right w’out reducg. inflationary pull of other 

     x|	industries.

	Open-cast.  No longer a reserve for war : a reserve for now.  Hope we can have bias in favour of it.  Need for a clear plan : that wd. help agriculture, who cd. better plan ahead 3 or 4 years.  This is our best hope of reducg. imports.



H.	Absentee-ism : 11% in Scotland.  What addl. output if that were reduced by 3%?



A.J.	Current U.K. rate = 12%, incldg 8% involuntary.  The 4% accounts for 3 m. tons.  But despite large financial incentive, we have failed to get absentee-ism lower.



J.S.	F. labour?  



A.J. 	Right to remind miners of their obligns. but I am not optimistic.  Believe it wd. be better to import Italians for labour generally, &amp; let mines get their share.



I.M.	Support x/.  We got increase in ’52 on that account.



		Agreed  :	Cttee. on open-cast.  H.M., A.J., D.S., HA., J.S., 

M/W or repves.

				Memo. to be considered again in March, after 			P.M.’s return.

				A.J. to send note to L.P.S. for P.M., re export of 			coal to Ireland.

										[Exit A.J.



		10.	Cotton.



P.T.	As in memo.



H.M.	I agree.



H.	U.K. exports to India have doubled w’in last 2 months.



		Memo. approved :  P.T. to keep Cab. informed.



S.	Some closing of mills is presumably due to rationalisation, on a/c of synthetics.



P.T.	Yes. – and loss of export markets generally.





		11.	Danish Bacon.



H.M.	Brght it up again because P.M. concerned at earlier decn. &amp; I thght it right that we shd. re-consider.  Tho’ I can’t advise a difft. course.  Believe it’s right to go fwd. with tariff negotns.  If we tried to get bulk purchase agreemt., we shd. be in v. weak posn. &amp; mght have to let it all  in w’out any tariff.  Ty. believe Danes won’t want to spoil this market by dumping : moreover, demand is inelastic.

	Recognise pol. dangers.  Nor do I assume we shall succeed in getting all the agreemts. now needed under G.A.T.T.



H.A.	Agree : this is lesser evil.



P.T.	Agree.  Advised to announce in reply to P.Q. to-morrow.  Will concert terms with H.M., &amp; H.A.,



A.N.	Agree.							Memo. approved.







		12.	Malta.							[Enter E.H.



A.L.B.	R.C.’s, some genuinely some less scrupulously, are concerned about future of R.C. liberties etc., in Malta.

	Draft reply submitted to P.Q. by Griffiths M.P.

	Drew attentn. to penultimate paragraph.  Assurances given on behalf of Malta Conference.



K.	Agree with proposed action &amp; draft answer.



		Approved.

		A.L.B. to inform P.M. by telegram.



A.L.B.	Parly. anxiety re conduct of referendum.

	We have oblign. to see it is done as fairly as possible.  Govr. wd welcome presence of M.P.’s on day of vote.  I wd. support that.



E.H.	Med. Cttee. of Party met y’day : gt. anxiety on this : suggn. that 6 M.P.’s (3 fr. each side) shd. go out as observers as soon as possible.



H.M.	Wd. give blessing to referendum, whose terms we don’t approve.



R.A.B.	Dangerous idea.  Believe Party majority may be v. Report.



E.H.	Ministers are seeing Med Cttee. on Thursday.  Discuss this issue with them.  Avoid decision.



		General view : this shd. be discouraged.





		13.	Washington Talks.



R.A.B.	Draft declaration.  Mtg. of senior Ministers this p.m.  3p.m.



 



</content>
</cab>
