<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/14/0 images: 21-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.11(56)							10th February, 1956





		1.	Economic Situation.		[Enter B-C., T., H.W., E.H., A.S.



H.M.	Grateful to Dept. Ministers for contns. made.



	Transport.



H.W.	£5 M. order for lorries will prob. be cancelled – relief to economy.

	Railways. Cdn’t make full saving because of early plan.



	N. Coal Board.



A.J.	Can accept figure, but not reason : not wholly on screening – that explann. must be omitted.



	C.E.A.



	Citrine may not accept this cut w’out direction.



H.A.	Hope cut in rural services will not be disproportionate.  



A.J.	Yes.



R.A.B.	Inevitable, however, that rural areas will suffer some disappointment at the delay.



	Scottish Electricity – approved.



	Gas Boards – a real cut, not merely a p’mme.



	Air Corporations.  This is accepted, and I hope to get more off later.



W.M.	Atomic Energy.  I can’t make any concession yet on 2nd. part of this para.



H.M.	Post Office. Can’t delay on plant – only on bldgs.



Ll.G.	Development Areas.  Will this affect N. Ireland?



H.M.	Not intended – nor likely.  We shall delay new starts, in G.B.  N.I. is separate : no N.I. money in this £1 M. cut.



B.H.	Government Building.  V. little more to be scraped out of this barrel.



W.M.	Home Defence.  Total shd. be £44.72 M., as agreed at y’day’s Cabinet.



D.S.	L.A. Expenditure – miscellaneous.  Accept H.M.’s demand in full.

	Meaning of “nearly all”?



R.T.	M.d. occupn. centres &amp; accommn. for home nurses are to be excluded, with Ty. agreement.  But I am still arguing in favour of exclusion of old peoples homes – which I regard as a kind of hospital service.  Cut wd. mean only 20 odd bldgs. instead of over 40.  Wd. reduce our p’mme to not more than 175.000 beds.  False economy – because cheaper than hospitals.



H.M.	All items I am cutting are good.  This has no higher merit than many others, in which l.a.’s are concerned.



R.T.	Cut involved wd. be £1½ M. or more because l.a.’s are reluctant to build these homes &amp; with this encouragement might back down.



P.M.	This is not a moment to press l.a.’s to do bldg. they don’t want to do.



H.M.	    x/	Begin with smaller p’mme and review posn. in Sept./October.



I.M.	Doubt if these homes will relieve pressure on mental hospitals.  I wd. accept offer at x/.



H.M. to discuss with R.T. and report



H.W.	Roads.  Won’t be popular.  Shall be criticised for slowing down p’mme we have recently bragged about a good deal.



R.A.B.	We must retain p’mme &amp; say we are delaying its execution.  Otherwise we shall be in trouble over broken pledges.  



Defence.  Problem of presentation.



H.A.	Farm Prices.  May be £20-25 M. more than last years’ Estimate.

	But out-turn was £40 M. less than Estimate.



H.M.	First imposed settlement.  Must seem reasonably fair.  Wise therefore to err a little on side of generosity.



	Imports.



A.J.	Believe we shall get thro’ on existg. stocks.



H.	We are commd. to take stated amounts annually, of sugar, from Australia &amp; Colonies.  Will redn. fall wholly on Cuba?



H.A.	This won’t cut across Commonw. Sugar Agreement.



P.T.	Strategic Stocks.  Shall try to sell £50 M.  But it’s a big job – esp. if we are to get a reasonable price.



W.M.	Need advice on defence aspects of this ques.

							[Exit R.T., H.M., A.S.

	Education.



D.E.	My current p’mme is in arrear : shd. carry fwd. more than £10 M. anyhow.  Therefore, with cut of £10 M. originally suggd. by H.M. l.a. bldg. wd. not be slowed down at all in current year.

	I therefore propose to ration starts to £25 M. in 1st. 6 months : &amp; to discuss with H.M. later how much I start in 2nd. 6 months.  This is only practical way of securing relief in demand for labour &amp; materials.  This can be secured only by delaying starts.

	But this is slightly inconsistent with what is said in new paper on technological educn. about need for continuity in provn. of secondary education.



H.M.	On housing we have taken risk of abandoning allocation system.

	On education, if we do this, we can say we are delaying starts in order to improve completions.



D.E.	£35 M. worth of starts or £40 M. might be started: and of this we shd. be holding back about £10 M. of starts betwn Apl. and Oct.



D.S.	But what cut in actual exp’re on bldg. in 1956/57?



R.A.B.	Does this involve breach of pledges?



D.E.	Not necessarily.

	We promised 200.000 new places p.a.  We may now take longer to complete our p’mme.



I.M.	Cd. you say we were accleratg. completions, instead of slowing starts. As Bevan did with housing in ’48.



H.M.	Can’t do more in that direction w’out bldg. licensing.



D.E.	I cd. do what I propose administratively without any genl. announcement of a definite moratorium.



	Don’t believe I can justify argument tht. this accelerates completion.



H.M.	This is a political dilemma.  Economic argument is that financial pressure will ensure tht. resources saved by this cut are not transferred to cinemas &amp; other luxury building.



D.S.	Cd. you add to that by a direct tax on private bldg? …….



H.M.	May not be essential to be explicit about this in statement.



D.E.	Will suggest a form of words for H.M.’s statement.



R.A.B.	So will I.



	Food Subsidies.



I.M.	Engineering wages claim.  Two sides were to have met on 2/2 : delayed now until 17/2 because employers’ diffy. in arriving at common line.  They now will try for 7% increase (this years’ pattern) to match increase given last year.  Believe that, or somethg. like it, may be accepted.

	Other claims e.g. miners are likely to be settled around same figure.

	I don’t believe these current claims will be affected by any decisions announced now on subsidies.



R.A.B.	What new claims?



I.M.	Cotton – going to arbitn.  Miners will soon come to a head.



H.M.	Invite Cab. to consider genl. position.  Deficit on current a/c of S. Area £200 M. in 1955/56.  No reason to believe 1956/57 will be any better.

	State of serious inflation.

	Cuts discussed h’to are mainly redns. in planned p’mmes.  Total £70 M. of delayed orders in public sector, representg. about 50% of our total investment.  Over remaing. field credit squeeze is operating.

	We are inflating annual by total investment of natd. industries, whose investment is no longer financed out of savings.

	I wish therefore to cut real current exp’re w’out waiting for Budget.  Otherwise I fear a run on £. – which exchange control can’t regulate now we have open commodity markets &amp; Kuwait gap.

	Real indicator is trade figures.  Can free economy be made to work?

	Diffy. about subsidy proposal is to explain why it is disinflationary.  But it is taken as test of Govt.’s seriousness.  How can a Govt. disinflate economy while it still subsidises it?

	Bread subsidy wd. save us £40 M.  How much will come back in wage increases.  Of course, it wd. be used as argument.  But decn. wd. turn on wtr employers can afford to pay more.  High costs are cause, not result, of inflation.  If basic prices were stabilised by subsidy, price increase wd. emerge elsewhere on luxuries.

	Nat. expre. on sweets is now £250 M. p.a. vice £40 M. in rationing days.  Increase in bread prices can be sustained, surely.

	Can temper wind to poor by increasing N. Assistance rates, by a compensating amount.  Worth paying somethg. to get rid of these subsidies.

	Effect on wages.  Agree it won’t affect this round of claims.  M/L. fears it will affect next round.  But much may have happened by then.



R.A.B.	Time-table.  Statement by H.M. on Mon. week.  After B/E. decision on prev. Thurs. to raise Bank Rate.



H.M.	Statement of full package.  Or, if food subsidies are not included, no preliminary statement – only a speech in economic debate.



I.M.	Matter of political judgmt.  But believe we shall lose more than we gain by abolishing bread subsidy.  Milk prices are less serious because cushioned by priority classes.

	Compensation for N.A. classes wd. help politically.  But it wdn’t help on wage claims.

	About 3m. workers have rates tied to c/living figure.

	Whatever we do, we can’t stop wage increases.  £300 M. last year.  Prob. more this year.  Responsible T.U. leaders who are ready to urge restraint wd. be v. greatly discouraged by such action.  They are about to urge Govt. to avoid doing this v. thing.  Better climate now for wage stability than for some time past.  Hope of a period of stability in prices &amp; wages.  Can’t expect this, however, if we make this deliberate increase in c/living.

	Doubt therefore if this wd. in the end be disinflationary.

	Wd. make it v. diff. to make progress in projected talks with employers and T.U.C., to which I attach v. gt. importance.



S.Ll.	Current claims.  Won’t leaders revise claims.



I.M.	Unlikely – governed by last years’ decisions.



W.M.	Believe announcemt. in mid/Feb. wd. affect current claims.



P.M.	M/L. argument wd. apply to doing it in Budget?  



I.M.	Yes.



P.M.	Are Autumn measures not having effect?  Reserves are rising now.  Not easy to escape fr. deflation, if we get into it.



P.T.	Trade gap (£75 M. Jan.) is as bad as ever : indeed, it is worsening slowly.  £65 in last quarter of 1955.  And import element is 7% higher than average for ’55.

	Will be regarded by commentators as v. grave.



I.M.	Unemplt. figures have not yet given sign of movement twds. disinflation.



P.M.	C/living is now steady &amp; may remain so for some months.



D.S.	Importance of impact.  We can’t come back &amp; do more later.

	For l.a. expenditure, if you don’t act now you will lose a year.  This is the moment at which they settle p’mmes etc., for new financial year.



		Discussion adjourned.







		2.	Defence White Paper.



W.M.	Evacuation.  Don’t say in W.Paper “this must be our first task”.  It is said in other words in existg. para.

	I wd. prefer to deal with this point in speech.



Ll.G.	Agree.



D.S.	Agree.





</content>
</cab>
