<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/14/0 images: 46-46</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
C.M.36(56)							15th May, 1956





		1.	Economic Situation.				[Enter E.H., A.N.



H.M.	Went well.  Most of statement was included in communiqué.  But made less impact in Press than I had hoped.



I.M.	Resolns. are down for Whitsun Confces. : they will be passed.  We want to nobble moderate opinion – get platform, tho’ we can’t control floor.  It is platform wh. negotiates wage claims.

	A leader in “Times” wd. steady them.



R.A.B.	We cd. leave employers &amp; natd. indies. until after Whitsun.



P.M.	We cd. get on with publicity m’while.  Ty. to arrange with “Times.”



H.M.	What about a statement in H/C.?  Mght excite hostile comment &amp; spoil effect.



		H.M. to arrange for Times leader.

		RAB. to get C.O.I. to support.





		2.	Bahrain.



A.N.	Belgrave is becoming v. unpopular in Bahrain.  If he doesn’t move, there will be another Glubb incident.

	First aim : to get a potential successor in, as deputy.

	M’while : steps to strengthen Police.  Wd. welcome C.O. help in providing Br. police officers.



P.M.	Disturbing telegram.  Must get successor in place before we begin to ease out Belgrave.  Must avoid, m’while, undermining Ruler’s confidence in us – wh. may be shaken if we seem to be asking him prematurely to part with Belgrave.

	Admit Ruler may be too re-actionary.  But Cttee. may be too much under Egyptian influence.



L.P.	First need is to get good new man in who will get confidence of Ruler.  Not until he has it could the change take place.



H.M.	Cttee.  Will they turn against us when they get control?



A.N.	They will if Belgrave stays &amp; annoys them much longer.



P.M.	We ought to have a pool of good advisers on which these Rulers cd. draw – all down P. Gulf.



D.S.	Far easier to use force, if we have to, in support of a Ruler than against a “liberal” Cttee.



P.M.	First, select the successor.  Do no more until we have found him.

	Make it clear to Belgrave that this is our plan.

	F.O. to discuss Police problem with C.O. (A.L.B. having indicated diffies. of helping).

	F.O. to consider wtr it wd. be easier to discuss this tactfully with Belgrave in London vice Bahrain.



		3.	Somaliland.



W.M.	Summarised conclns. of C.O.S.  Increasg. importance of over-flying rights.



A.L.B.	Govr. Kenya attaches v. gt. importce. to m’taining our influence in Horn of Africa.



L.P.	Need Italians leave in 1960?



A.L.B.	They can’t afford to stay.  Under obligns. to U.N. their trustee rights lapse in 1960.



P.M.	Cd. F.O. consider wtr Italians cd. stay longer.



		4.	Prince Ernst of Hanover.



K.	Formal notice of appeal ought to be given today.  The case needn’t be presented for some weeks.

	

CLOSED UNDER THE



FREEDOM OF INFORMATION



ACT 2000



If Att.G. refers to R. Marriages Act, this will attract public attentn.  No reference to this since Ct. of Appeal.

	Att.G. shd. be heard on ques wtr appeal would succeed.

	I don’t agree with views of L.O.’s on interpretn. of “foreign family”.  But Judges mght not agree with me.

	If we lost this appeal, we shd. be faced with need for legn.  This legn. wd. touch R. Marriages Act &amp; wd. necessitate consultn. with Doms.



Ll.G.	

CLOSED UNDER THE



FREEDOM OF INFORMATION



ACT 2000



		Agreed :	Att.G. to submit formal notice of appeal.

				Merits to be considered again when Att.G. can

				be heard.



L.P.	Risk of its being raised wd. be increased by a further decn. in H/L.



P.T	If we give notice &amp; it is spotted – there may be speculation about our reasons for procdg, or not procdg, with the case.



P.M.	Our risk : if raised in H/L., or in Press, we may have to legislate.



								[Enter J.S.

		5.	Disarmament.



A.N.	In view of R. announcement of unilateral reduction, may F.O. spokesman take the line to-day suggd. in para. 12.



P.M.	This sharp &amp; offensive note is not in accord with our wish to improve Anglo-Sov. relations.  R. told us about their intention.

	This procedure of daily Press briefing by F.O. is v. embarrassing.

	“Welcome this : but problem of control &amp; numbers remains”.  But at all costs avoid “cold war” reception.



			Discussion adjourned for A.N. to give this guidance.





		6.	Capital Punishment.



J.S.	Appln. to Scotland.  I wd. like to abstain, after saying that different law in 2 countries is illogical.



P.M.	Members of Govt. shd. not vote for this amendment : some who can’t vote against it may abstain.				Agreed.



Ll.G.	Courts-martial.  Can wait until Report stage.

	Lucas-Tooth amendments.  Must make sympathetic speech.  But leave it to free vote.  Members of Govt. to vote for it.



L.P.	Then c.p. wd. not be available for poisoners – the worst kind of murder.  H/L. wdn’t wear this distinction.



R.A.B.	Tory abolitionists mght support L-Tooth amendment, but not the cold-blooded murders like poisoning.



K.	Can argue tht. Govt. are responsible for law &amp; order : wd. prefer to retain c.p. for all murders : but better than have no c.p. at all, we wd. prefer to retain it for these purposes of protectg. police &amp; warders.



Ll.G.	Also, if this passed, Bill as a whole becomes so illogical that it may founder.





		7.	Singapore.



A.L.B.	Likely tht. Conference will break this p.m.

	Crucial issue : internal security.  We have claimed reserve power to legislate by O-in-C. – after report fr. D. of Security Council on wh. we shd. have majority.  They now say it must be a recommn. fr. the Council, &amp; tht. it shd. not have a U.K. Chairman but a Malay nominated by Chief Minister of Fedn. of Malaya.  This wd. give us only 3 out of 7, but we cd. prs. get them to agree tht. nomination shd. be subject to our approval.  This wd. avoid a break.  But we shd. lose final word in control.  Senior Pol. appointmts. wd. go outside our control because of composn. of Council.  No function for High Commr. as a mere member of Council.

	Propose therefore to reject this plan &amp; put best face on it we can.  Unless Cab. wish us to go on or adjourn for 10 days.



L.P. 	Fortress responsibilities in S. go beyond even Malaya.  This wdn’t safeguard them.  We must break on it.

	If we stand firm on that line, best chance of getting A &amp; N.Z. support.

	Malayan Chairman wdn’t meet our Imperial defence needs.

	We have given A &amp; N.Z. Govts the line which we shall take if we break on this.



W.M.	Doesn’t matter whose voice is decisive on Council if it’s not ours – on fortress argument.



P.M.	Concerned at turning down Malay suggn.



A.L.B.	They might refuse to do it.  Trying to ascertain wtr they would.



A.L.B.	We cdn’t accept any Dominion Chairman – too risky because of India.  Must insist on U.K. Chairman.



K.	Can’t accept their Chairman plan.  Cd. accept recommn. vice report. Cd. also agree that if they pass legn. wh. we consider to trench on reserved subjects decision cd. rest with Privy Council.



P.M.	Consequences will be v. unpleasant.  Another Cyprus.



A.L.B.	Wd. there be advantage in adjourning for 10 days?



H.M.	If we got control of Council, cd. we abandon reserve powers, short of extreme emergency.



A.L.B.	They wd. agree to this, if it had little or nothg to do.  But all we wd. have wd. be power to appoint to 3 Police posts &amp; power to suspend altogether.



		Agreed :	C.O. authorised to break or adjourn on the issue 

of reserve powers.  (If we adjourn we must avoid impn. that we are contemplatg. further concessions.)





		8.	Aden.



A.L.B.	Govr. has asked for robust statement tht. we won’t be bundled out of Aden.  Tels. 300 &amp; 302.



P.M.	Wd. like to delete a number of epithets.  Will send these comments to A.L.B.



		Approved, subject to drafting improvements.





		9.	Flour. 						[Enter R.T.



L.P.	M.R.C. who gave evidence think there will be controversy &amp; they will have to publish.  To avoid appearance of havg. it forced out of them, they wd. prefer to include final para. which leaves it open to M.R.C. to go ahead.



H.A.	Wd. this not invite fresh outbreak of controversy?



L.P.	This is a subject on which many people have v. strong views.



J.S.	Can it not be said in reply to supplementaries.  Rather unusual to put it in statement.  Mght be awkward precedent.



R.A.B.	I wdn’t mind adding it to statement.



Agreed :	omit final para.  But inspire a supplementary to

ensure that it’s said.



H.A.	Can’t be sure P.Q. will be reached.  Wd. sooner add para.



R.A.B.	Wording of it cd. be adjusted.





</content>
</cab>
