<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/13/0 images: 58-63</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
bS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OF  HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   July, 1948SECRETCM. (48)49th conclusions copy No.CABINET 49 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 12th July, 1948, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.Sir Stafford Cripps,Chancellor   of   theThe Right HonK.C., M.P.,Exchequer.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,M.P., Secretary of State for theColonies.The Right Hon. A. Woodburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Com-commonwealth Relations.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P.,Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food.The Right Hon. H. T. N. Gaitskell,M.P., Minister of Fuel and Power.The following were also present:The Right Hon. G. R. Strauss, M.P.,Minister of Supply.Sir Edward Bridges, Treasury.Secretariat.Sir Norman Brook.Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.ContentsSubjectBalance of PaymentsUnited Kingdom Import Programme, July 1948-June 1949.35682-4Page120
Balance ofPayments.United King-dom import programme,July 1948-June 1949.The Cabinet considered memoranda by the Chancellor of theExchequer (CP. (48) 177 and 178) on the programmes and statisticsto be submitted to the Organisation for European economic co-operation in connexion with the forthcoming negotiations forthe allocation of aid under the European Recovery Programme forthe year July 1948 to June 1949.The Cabinet were informed that the Organisation for european economic Co-operation had agreed to undertake responsibility forthe allocation of aid between the participating countries. TheOrganisation had been advised to assume that the amount of aidavailable in this first period would total $4,875 million : as the resultof Congressional decisions, this sum was about 10 per cent, belowthe original figure given in the published calculations (Brown Books)of the United States Administration. The task of the organisation was to make recommendations to the Economic Co-operationAdministrator on the manner in which this sum should be divided,both in total and by commodity; and each of the participating countries had been asked to submit, as a basis for negotiation, botha &quot; Budget &quot; programme prepared on the basis of the amount of aidallotted to it in the Brown Books, and a Requirements &quot; pro-gramme stating its actual needs. The memorandum and statisticaltables prepared on this basis for submission to the Organisation hadbeen separately circulated to the Cabinet (CP. (48) 178). Bothprogrammes had been drawn up in accordance with the principles,approved by the Economic Policy Committee on 23rd March (E.P.C(48) 11th Meeting, Minute 1), that our reserves of gold and dollarsshould not fall below the level at which they stood at the outset ofthe European Recovery Programme, and that we should attaineconomic viability by 1952. For the Budget programme, it had been necessary to keep within the figure given in the Brown Books(i.e., $1,271 million) and, within this limit, it had been possible todraw up a programme which would maintain the cOuntry&apos;s economy and give some assistance to its further development. Further itemsamounting to $400 million had been included in the &quot; Requirementsprogramme. It was, however, unlikely that the amount of aidallocated to the United Kingdom would in fact exceed $1,150 million,and it would in due course be necessary to submit revised programmeson the basis of the amount of aid ultimately determined. A finaldecision might not be reached for some months, and it was thereforeadvisable in the meantime to adjust our import programme so as tobring it into line with the amount of aid which was likely ultimately to be available. It was possible that United Kingdom resourcesmight be augmented by further drawings on the Canadian credit,by further reductions in dollar expenditure by the rest of the sterling area, by increased exports or by a fall in import prices, butit would be imprudent to make any allowance for windfalls underthese heads. If, however, the amount of aid allotted to the UnitedKingdom fell below the &quot;Budget &quot; figure, it would be reasonable to insist on payment in dollars for oil supplied to participating countries, and savings up to $50 million might be secured from this source. It was therefore necessary to decide on savings of between$50 and $100 million in the Budget programme, and possible savingstotalling $100 million were set out in paragraph 22 of Annex A to cp. (48) 177.The Chancellor of the Exchequer drew attention to the salientpoints in CP. (48) 177 and 178. The main purpose of the programmes to be submitted to the Organisation was to determine the United Kingdom&apos;s dollar balance of payments over the next year.But it was necessary to give the Organisation at the same time a comprehensive export and import programme; and the figuressubmitted for scarce commodities were likely to be regarded as firmcommitments. The immediate problem was to decide whatreductions should be made in the dollar programme to bring it into line with the probable allocation of aid to the United Kingdom.He strongly supported the proposals that wheat consumption shouldbe maintained at the 1947-48 level, and that cuts should be made in
imports of tobacco and raw materials. It was not necessary to reach,an immediate decision on the reduction of sugar consumption; andhe was opposed to any cut in the imports of machinery.In reply to a question, the Chancellor said that it was important that the United Kingdom should continue to supply oil to supportthe economy of Western Europe. - On the other hand, we could not reasonably be expected to continue to accept payment in softcurrencies from countries receiving aid under the european recovery Programme. He therefore proposed that this should beaccepted only if the full &quot; Budget &quot; allocation of $ 1,271 million wasmade to the United Kingdom: if any lesser allocation was made,participating countries should be asked to pay dollars for oilsupplied by the United Kingdom. This proposal would bring thewhole question into negotiation at Paris with the countries concerned.The Cabinet first discussed the report on the balance ofpayments with non-dollar countries, which was contained in annex C to CP. (48) 177. This recalled that, when we hadsuspended the convertibility of sterling in August 1947, we had firstconcentrated attention on reducing our imports from the western hemisphere in order to reduce the drain on our reserves of gold and dollars, and Departments had been encouraged to develop importsfrom non-dollar countries in order to compensate for the loss of dollar imports. Great energy had been shown in developing thesealternative sources of supply; and, as other countries had adoptedsimilar policies, the pressure of demand had caused a rise of prices in the non-dollar countries. As a result we were now planning to buy more than we could afford from many countries in the non-dollar world; and it was therefore recommended that steps should betaken to bring more fully under control our balance of paymentsprogramme with non-dollar countries. Thus, the Chancellor of theExchequer recommended (i) that a detailed analysis should be madeof 1948-49 imports from the sterling area, distinguishing betweenbasic and less essential supplies; (ii) that our import /export policyin respect of each sterling area country should be worked out and discussed with the countries concerned; (iii) that, in the meantime,full Treasury control should be restored, and (iv) that, until future policy was determined, we should avoid prejudicing our freedomof action by concluding long-term contracts, even for essential supplies, unless there were overwhelming reasons for doing so.Similarly, the Chancellor recommended that import/export policyin respect of csr tain of the non-participating countries should be revised and that, meanwhile, no new contracts should be made withany of those countries (except contracts arising from bilateral agreements) without renewed authority from the Treasury.In discussion the view was expressed that the picture given in annex C of the memorandum, of our prospective balance of payments position with non-dollar countries was somewhat less realistic thanthat given in Annex A for the dollar programme. The estimates of expenditure in non-dollar countries were based on deparmental programmes which included all that Departments hoped to buy inthose countries: the actual purchases would fall short of thoseprogrammes. It was true that some of the exports which were nowselling to non-dollar countries might no longer be accepted whenthose countries became able to buy from the Western Hemisphere,with dollars provided under the European Recovery Programme,goods which they would previously have preferred to ours. But, asagainst this, the flow of grant-aided supplies from the United states would reduce the demand on non-dollar sources of supply and might thus help to reduce the prices of our imports from those countries.Other points made in this part of the discussion were: \a) The report tended to give an excessively unfavourableimpression of the situation, as it took no account of the movementof capital within the sterling area.35682-4 b 2
(6) It would be unfortunate if the proposed review of policy inrespect of each sterling area country led to a development of bi-laterism within the sterling area.(c) The hope was expressed that no unnecessary obstacles wouldbe put in the way of the conclusion of long-term contracts with commonwealth countries.In reply to these comments, the Chancellor of the Exchequer saidthat a balance of payments programme could not take account ofcapital movements. He admitted that the statistical basis of the non-dollar programme was less certain than that of the dollar pro-gramme. All that he was suggesting at present, however, was thatour trading position with each of these countries should be reviewedbefore the situation got out of control. It was only while that review was proceeding that he deprecated the conclusion of further long-term contracts which might limit our freedom of action. There wasno reason why the completion of the review should be long delayed.Ministers were concerned to know what was meant by the pro-posal that full Treasury control should be restored over purchases from non-dollar countries. It was recognised that the Treasurymust have effective control over Departmental buying programmes,and must be in a position to influence on financial grounds thedecision from what sources imports should be drawn. At the sametime, Departments conducting trade negotiations must be given areasonable amount of latitude and should not be subjected to detailedTreasury control at every stage in the negotiations. The Chancellorof the Exchequer undertook to arrange for officials of the treasury to discuss, with representatives of the other Departments primarily concerned, what modifications could be made in the existing machinery with a view to giving the Treasury adequate control overthe situation without delaying the work of the importingDepartments.The Cabinet then turned to discuss what adjustments mightbe made in the 1948-49 dollar import programme in view of theprospect that the amount of aid allotted would fall short of theamount allowed for in the Budget programme. Proposals which,if adopted, would lead to a saving of 1100 million were set out inparagraph 22 of Annex A to CP. (48) 177. The first of these wasthat a saving of $25 million should be made by maintaining theconsumption of wheat at the 1947-48 level. This would involveallowing stocks to fall to six weeks&apos; consumption by mid-1949,retaining the 85 per cent, extraction rate, reversing the previous decision to let farmers keep 20 per cent, of millable wheat of the1948 harvest, and limiting flour consumption to 100,000 tons a week.There was general agreement that the 85 per cent, extraction rate should be retained. As regards stocks, the Cabinet were re-minded that in their discussion about cereal supplies on 22nd June(CM. (48) 41st Conclusions, Minute 2) it had been suggested thaton defence grounds it would, be desirable to. aim at having morethan nine weeks&apos; consumption at mid-1949. The Minister of Foodsaid.that he could not guarantee to limit flour consumption to100,000 tons a week. He hoped, therefore, that the Cabinet would agree that, as proposed in paragraph 7 of CP. (48) 152, he shouldhave at his disposal a balance of 3,000 tons a week as a cushionto meet hardship cases and local or seasonal difficulties. He feared that without this there would be shortages and occasional breadqueues. On the other hand, it was pointed out that, before bread rationing.had been brought, into force, consumption had been below100,000 tons a week and that the good potato crop forecast for1948 should enable consumption to be held at the 100,000 tons levelwithout serious difficulty. , In these circumstances the cabinet agreed that the Minister should aim at,keeping total consumptionwithin the figure of 100,000 tons a week, though they recognisedthat, if exceptional difficulties arose, this level might be slightlyexceeded. 0
The Chancellor of the Exchequer urged the Cabinet to reversetheir earlier decision to let farmers keep 20 per cent, of millable wheat of the 1948 harvest. This would avoid the embarrassment ofproposing to the Organisation for European Economic Co-opera-tion an increase in our wheat consumption over the 1947 level;would make it easier to reduce our purchases from Canada; andwas estimated to save about $15 million in the year. The wheatcould be replaced by coarse grains and there should thus be no loss to the livestock programme. If a saving of dollars could not besecured in this way we should either have to reduce our dollar reserves or make an equivalent cut in some other part of the import programme.The Minister of Food supported the Chancellors proposal. Iffarmers were allowed to retain any millable wheat, he thought itwould be difficult to ensure that they did not keep more than 20per cent. Moreover, a cut in the consumption of wheat by animals,which could be offset by increasing the amount of coarse grainsreleased to farmers, seemed preferable to any alternative way ofsecuring the necessary saving in dollars.On the other hand, it was argued that failure to keep thispromise to the farmers would be regarded as an act of bad faith.The promise had been made in August 1947, as part of the appealto farmers to co-operate in the campaign to save dollars, and boththe livestock programme and the wheat acreage would suffer if itwere not kept. It was true that farmers had been warned inJanuary that if there should be an acute shortage of wheat for human consumption it might be necessary for the Government toask them to accept an equivalent quantity of coarse grains in sub-stitution for wheat, but it would be impossible to maintain thatthese conditions existed if, at the same time, bread rationing werediscontinued. If the goodwill of the farmers were retained therewas less risk of substantial evasion of the requirement to market80 per cent, of millable wheat and it could be represented to theOrganisation for European Economic Co-operation, should we be challenged, that this represented a much higher level of collectionthan was secured by any other European country. It was also pointed out that, although there might be a saving of dollars insubstituting coarse grains for wheat, an additional expenditure ofSJ2\ million would be incurred and our non-dollar balance of pay-ments would to that extent be worsened. There was, moreover, a danger that, if farmers were not allowed to retain 20 per cent, oftheir millable wheat, they would feed bread to their poultry and thusmake it impossible to keep flour consumption within reasonablebounds.The Cabinet-Agreed to resume their discussion of CP. (48) 177 and 178on the following day.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,12th July, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
