<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/13/0 images: 134-141</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
IS DOCUMENT IS  THE PROPERTY OP HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   September 1948SECRET Copy No.CM. (48)59th conclusions cabinet 59 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Friday, 10th September, 1948, at 11-45 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P., j The Right Hon. Sir Stafforb Cripps,Secretary of State for Foreign j K.C., M.P., Chancellor of the affairs. i    Exchequer.The Right Hon. A. V. Alexander,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. P. J. Noel-Baker,M.P., Secretary of State for Common-wealth Relations.The Right Hon. Aneurin Bevan, M.P.,Minister of Health.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:[The Right Hon. John Strachey, M.P.,Minister of Food (Items 1-2).The Right Hon. the Earl of Listowel,Minister of State for Colonial Affairs(Items 1-2).Secretariat:Mr. W. S. Murrie.Mr. G. M. Wilson.36109-4b
CABINET 59 (48)contents minute no..... Subject ... . P&amp;ge1      The Prime Minister    .... ............       92      Rice Supplies for South-East Asia   ........      ........       93      Foreign Affairs................      ............      10Germany.Brussels Treaty: Proposal for ft European Assembly.4      Eire and the British Commonwealth        ............      125      Hyderabad ;...........      ......       ....      13
Rice supplies for South-east asia.(previous reference:D.M.(48)56thConclusions,Minute 4.)2. The Cabinet considered a note by the Foreign Secretary(CP. (48) 218) covering a memorandum by the South-East AsiaFood Committee recommending measures to meet the situation created by the interruption of rice exports from Burma.The Foreign Secretary said that not more than 80,000 of the400,000 tons of rice due to be exported from Burma in the last four months of 1948 was likely to be shipped. It was most desirableto avoid a severe cut in rations in Malaya and it was therefore proposed that arrangements should be made, on the lines set outin paragraph 1 of the memorandum annexed to CP. (48) 218, forthe substitution of other cereals for rice, the purchase of additionalrice from Italy and the western hemisphere, and the diversion office intended for consumption in the United Kingdom.In discussion the following points were made  (a) The Chancellor of the Exchequer said that he was anxiousto avoid any dollar expenditure on rice and believed it would bepossible to obtain additional supplies from Siam, where there hadbeen a heavy crop and an improvement in the arrangements forcollection.(&amp;) Every effort should be made to meet the needs of ceylon and India from non-dollar sources, and the Australian Governmentshould be pressed to speed up the shipment of wheat and flour from australia.(c) The Indian Government claimed that, as a result of theremoval of controls on food distribution, 400,000 tons of cerealswould be required in addition to the 100,000 tons estimated by theSouth-East Asia Food Committee to be necessary to meet the deficit of rice.(d) It would-be unfortunate if the 24,000 tons of rice now inthis country which it had been intended to distribute to UnitedKingdom consumers had to be diverted to South-East Asia, and.until the effect of the other measures proposed could be assessedmore accurately, the Minister of Food should hold this stock in reserve.The Cabinet-(1) Invited the Foreign Secretary and the Minister of Food to explore the possibility of obtaining additional suppliesof rice from Siam with a view to avoiding the need forthe purchase of dollar rice and the diversion to South-East Asia of rice stocks accumulated in this country for united Kingdom consumers;(2) Agreed that the rice stocks accumulated in this country for distribution to United Kingdom consumers should beheld in reserve for the present;(3) Subject to (1) and (2), approved the recommendations inparagraph 1 of the memorandum annexed to CP. (48).      2i8l -   &quot;     &apos;     &quot; &apos; &apos; &quot;36109-4b 21. The Cabinet expressed their pleasure that the PrimeMinister had found it possible to preside over their meeting a,ndtheir hope that he would soon have completely recovered.The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations said thatat a meeting of Commonwealth High Commissioners that morninghe had been asked to convey to the Prime Minister their sympathy and best wishes for his speedy recovery.
ForeignAffairs.Germany.(previous reference:CM. (48)58thConclusions,Minute 4.)3. The Foreign Secretary recalled the sequence of events whichhad led to the Moscow conversations and gave the Cabinet an accountof the developments since the conversations had started. on 3rd August Marshal Stalin had indicated that the Soviet Govern-ment would agree to&apos;a joint statement dealing with the removal oftransport restrictions both between Berlin and the Western Zonesand on transit traffic to and from the Eastern Zone, and with thesubstitution of Soviet Zone currency for western currency in Berlin.The statement was also to announce the resumption of negotiationsabout Berlin and the holding of a four-Power meeting to considerother outstanding problems connected with Germany. At subse-quent meetings with M. Molotov the representatives of the Western(jovernments had insisted that conversations could not be held underduress, that all transport restrictions must be raised, and that, if jthe Soviet Zone currency were to be introduced in Berlin, it mustbe under four-Power control. They had at the same time agreedthat, after the Berlin problem had been solved, a four-Power meeting to discuss wider issues could be envisaged. During the conversa-tions the Soviet representatives had revealed their desire to holdup the establishment of a Western German Government, though \Marshal Stalin had stated that he did not regard this as a conditionof agreement on other issues. The representatives of the western governments had made it clear that the constitutional discussionsnow in progress must proceed but that these discussions did not preclude the subsequent formation of an all-German Government.The Soviet representatives had also suggested that the western powers had no longer any juridical right to be in Berlin; but this claim had been rejected. After a second meeting with M. Stalin,on 24th August, it had been agreed to refer certain technical issues to the Military Governors in Berlin. and a directive to them hadbeen finally agreed and despatched on 30th August. This directivewas subject to the understanding that both sides reserved theirjuridical rights, that the transport restrictions to be removedincluded those imposed before 18th June, and that the functions ofthe Soviet Bank of Emission in connection with the regulation of currency in Berlin would be subject to the control of a financialcommission of representatives of the four Military Governors. Aseries of meetings of the Military Governors had been held, and on 7th September the Western Commanders-in-Chief had submitted areport to their Governments setting out the three main points of disagreement. These were the Soviet refusal to admit that thefinancial commission should control the operations of the Bank ofEmission, the Soviet insistence on controlling the trade of Berlin,and a Soviet proposal to introduce restrictions on air transport. Nofurther progress could be made until these three points of principlehad been settled, and he was now trying to obtain the agreementof the United States Government to his proposals for taking them up with the Soviet Government in Moscow. Meanwhile the soviet authorities had made unsuccessful attempts to persuade the inhabi-tants of the western sectors to register for food and other consump-tion goods in the Soviet sector and had offered to supply fuel, electric-power and raw materials to factories in the western sectors whowere willing to market their produce in the Soviet Zone. more recently they had encouraged demonstrations designed to makemeetings of the City Assembly impossible and there had been a gooddeal of organised violence. Protests about the provocative incidentshad been made to M. Molotov at a recent meeting, but the incidentshad since increased in gravity and the question of further represen-tations would have to be considered. The supply of Berlin by airhad been well maintained and plans were being made for continuingit, if necessary, throughout the winter months. The developmentof the West German constitution was proceeding satisfactorily anda draft providing for a federation of German Lander had beenaccepted by the main Parties as a basis for discussion. The germans had been most anxious to associate representatives of Berlin withthese constitutional developments and, although it had been made clear that full representation of Berlin on the Parliamentary Council
11 CM. 59 (48)was impossible, Berlin representatives had attended as observers and advisers.The Foreign Secretary said that it was impossible to forecast the outcome of the present conversations but that, in his view, theSoviet Government would probably be glad to see a settlement ofthe Berlin difficulties, since the existing situation was damaging to the trade of the Soviet Zone and German opinion was beingincreasingly alienated. He had made it clear to the United StatesGovernment that he regarded as premature any attempt to settlewhat line should be taken in the event of a breakdown of the conver-sations, but his provisional view was that it would be necessary toissue a White Paper giving a full account of the course of events.It would obviously be embarrassing to make a statement in Parlia-ment in the coming week, when the conversations would still bein progress, and he hoped it would be possible to postpone anydebate on foreign affairs until the week beginning 20th September.The Cabinet were informed that arrangements were being madeto postpone the House of Commons debate on foreign affairs untilthe second week of the new Session. It had, however, been thought desirable that a statement on the defence preparations which theCabinet had approved should be made by the Government spokesmanin the Debate on the Address on 14th September, since it had been regarded as certain that the Opposition would raise this matter at the earliest possible opportunity. It should be possible for theGovernment spokesman to explain why the Foreign Secretary wasnot able to make a full statement on foreign affairs until the follow-ing week and, if this were done, it was reasonable to suppose that members would avoid raising questions connected with the inter-national situation during the first week. There would be nodifficulty in postponing a debate on foreign affairs in the House ofLords until the second week of the Session.The Cabinet: (1) Took note of the statement by the Foreign Secretary aboutthe situation in Germany and of the proposed arrange-ments for debates on foreign affairs in the forthcoming session.Brussels The Foreign Secretary recalled that at the meeting of theTreaty: Brussels Treaty Consultative Council on 20th July the question of proposal for a a European Assembly had been tentatively raised by the FrenchEuropean Foreign Minister and it had been agreed that the problem shouldAssembly. be considered further by the five Governments. On 18th August,(Previous however, the French Government, without further consultation, had reference: announced that they supported the proposal to convene a prepara-C.m.(48)54th tory European Assembly and they intended to approach the otherConclusions.) Governments concerned. In fact, however, they had raised thematter only with the Belgian Government who, it was understood,had suggested that the whole problem could best be discussed by the brussels Treaty Permanent Commission. On 27th August theState Department had announced that the French Governmentsinitiative towards European union had their support and at ameeting early in September the European Parliamentary Congresshad adopted a plan providing for a European Federation with a federal Parliament with wide powers. It seemed clear that theFrench Government had not studied the implications of the pro-posal which they were now advocating and that it would be im-possible to create a lasting political union unless on the basis ofcommon vested. interests in the spheres of economics, finance and defence; and, in view of the propaganda in favour of a european assembly both in Europe and the United States, it was essentialthat the position of the United Kingdom Government should be made clear. He accordingly proposed to ascertain through the permanent commision what precise proposal the French Government had inmind, to discuss this proposal with the Commonwealth PrimeMinisters in October and, as soon as possible thereafter, to makea statement designed to show that the attitude of the United
Eire and 4    The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the secretary the British Gf State for Commonwealth Relations (CP, (48) 220) seeking ;Common- decision whether, in view of a statement by Mr. Costello that Eire!wealth. was no longer a member of the Commonwealth, it would be right!(Previous to renew the invitation to him to attend the meeting of Common JReference: wealth Prime Ministers in October.C.M.(48)56th The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations explained!Conclusions, that, when agreement on the arrangements for the proposed meetMinute l.) ing had been reached with all oversea Commonwealth PrimeMinisters, the United Kingdom representative in Eire had been instructed to ascertain informally from Eire Ministers whether itwould be embarrassing to Mr. Costello to receive an invitationMeanwhile, at a press conference in Canada, Mr. Costello had statedthat the Eire Government were preparing to repeal the external relations Act of 1936 and had implied that Eire could no longer be regarded as a member of the Commonwealth; and, when he himself had met the Eire Minister for External Affairs in Dublinon 8th September, he had been informed that, although the eire government were likely to decide that Eire Ministers should attend the meeting, they would require the United Kingdom Governmentto agree to an exchange of letters, which would subsequently bepublished, making it clear that Eire would not be represented as amember of the British Commonwealth and agreeing that the ques-tion of partition should be discussed at the meeting. To acceptthe former condition would prejudge the question whether theCommonwealth would inevitably raise difficulties with India and pakistan, and there were obvious objections to a discussion of thequestion of partition at a full meeting of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters.Ministers agreed that, while the desire of the United KingdomGovernment to maintain friendly relations with Eire should be made clear, the attitude of the Eire Government made it impossible to invite Eire Ministers to attend the meeting.Points in discussion were : (a) The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations would try to avoid any disclosure of the discussions which had taken place iwith, Eire Ministers on the question of attendance at the Octobeimeeting.(6) The President of the Board of Trade was considering whateffect the repeal of the External Relations Act would have on Eire&apos;strade.The Cabinet-Agreed that the Secretary of State for Commonwealth jRelations should arrange for the United Kingdom repre-sentative in Eire to inform the Eire Minister of external affairs orally that, in view of the attitude of the eire government, the United Kingdom Government consideredthat it would be embarrassing for Eire Ministers to beinvited to attend the meeting of Commonwealth PrimeMinisters.Kingdom Government was net obstructive or selfish but wasinspired by a realistic desire to secure an orderly and effectiveevolution towards a United Europe.The Cabinet (2) Endorsed the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposals for dealingwith the campaign in favour of a European Assembly.
13CM. 59 (48?jyderabad. 5.   The Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations warned the Cabinet that within the next few days Indian Government forces might invade Hyderabad. Though the Indian Government believedthat there would be no serious resistance, there might well bemassacres of Non-Moslems which might lead to a general conflict between India and Pakistan. Arrangements had been made to evacuate British subjects from Hyderabad and, if the invasion tookplace, he would do what he could to ensure that the facts of thesituation were fairly presented in this country.The Cabinet-Took note of the statement made by the Secretary of Statefor Commonwealth Relations.Cabinet Office, S. W. 1,lOth September, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
