<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 128/13/0 images: 285-292</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS  DOCUMENT  IS   THE PROPERTY OF HIS   BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   December 1948SECRET Copy Mo. ^ CM. (48)80th conclusions cabinet 80 (48)CONCLUSIONS of a Meeting of the Cabinet held at 10 Downing Street, S.W. 1,on Monday, 13th December, 1948, at 11 a.m.Present:The Right Hon. C. R. Attlee, M.P., Prime Minister (in the Chair).The Right Hon. Herbert Morrison,M.P., Lord President of the Council.The Right Hon. Sir Stafford Cripps,K.C.,   M.P.,   Chancellor   of   theExchequer.The Right Hon. Hugh Dalton, M.P.,Chancellor    of    the    Duchy    of lancaster.The Right Hon. Viscount Jowitt,Lord Chancellor.The Right Hon. A. Creech Jones,Secretary of State for the Colonies.The Right Hon. G. A. Isaacs, M.P.,Minister of Labour and NationalService.The Right Hon. George Tomlinson,M.P., Minister of Education.The Right Hon. Ernest Bevin, M.P.,Secretary of State for ForeignAffairs.The Right Hon. A. V. Alrxandbr,M.P., Minister of Defence.The Right Hon. Viscount Addison,Lord Privy Seal.The Right Hon. J. Chuter Ede, M.P.,Secretary of State for the home department.The Right Hon. A. WoOdburn, M.P.,Secretary of State for Scotland.The Right Hon. T. Williams, M.P..Minister of Agriculture andFisheries.The Right Hon. J. H. Wilson, M.P.,President of the Board of Trade.The following were also present:The Right Hon. E. Shinwell, M.P.,Secretary of State for War (Item 4).The Right Hon. C. W. Key, M.P.,Minister of Works (Item 4).The Right Hon. James Griffiths,.M.P., Minister of National Insurance(Item 5).Mr. E. M. King, M.P., parliamentary secretary, Ministry of Town and country Planning (Item 4).Secretariat:Sir Norman brook mr. A. Johnston.Mr. S. E. V. Luke.
SrJ)CABINET 80 (48)contents minute no. Subject page 1      Argentina       ............      .... ........ 149Meat Shipments.2      Indonesia        ....      ........,     ........ j^g3      China    ....      ....      ........      .... ...      . ^49R%eent Developments&apos; in the Civil War.4      Acquisition of Land and Buildings by GovernmentDepartments      ....      ....      .... .... 2515      International Labour Conference, 1925 ....      .... 163w&quot;orkmen&apos;s Compensation.q h)UM61
Argentina.MeatShipments.(previous reference:CM. (48) 79thConclusions,Minute 6.)Indonesia.(previous reference:CM. (48) 56thConclusions,Minute 5.)China.RecentDevelopmentsin thecivil war.(previous reference:CM. (46) 1stConclusions,Minute 1.)1. The Foreign Secretary said that in pursuance of the-Cabinefs decision of 9th December he had been considering howhe could best make representations to the Argentine Government/regarding their failure to maintain meat shipments to this countryin accordance with the provisions of the Andes Agreement. He had asked that no publicity should be given to the matter in the mean-time; but, in spite of this request, the whole question had beenventilated in the Press over the week-end. This premature dis-closure would be a handicap to him in his approach to the argentine government.The Chancellor of the Exchequer undertook to enquire how this information had reached the Press.2. The Foreign Secretary said that towards the end of theprevious week information had reached him suggesting that there might be a breakdown in the negotiations between the netherlands government and the Eepublican Government for the establishmentof an interim federal Government for Indonesia. He had at onceurged the Dutch Government to make every effort to avoid a break-down, and he had been about to suggest that the Prime ministers of Australia and India should be asked to make a correspondingappeal to the leaders of the Indonesian Republic. Before these lattermessages were sent the Dutch Government had made a public announcement in terms which had seemed to him to make it difficult for the Republican leaders to modify their attitude. He had nowbeen informed, however, by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador at The Hague-that, despite the terms of their announcement, the Dutch Govern-ment had left the door open for the Republican leaders to join the interim Government; and His Majesty&apos;s Consul-General in Bataviaalso believed that there would be advantage in our making some further approach to both parties to the negotiations. It was vitally important to British interests throughout South-East Asia that no-opportunity should be lost of securing an early settlement of the indonesian problem. In these circumstances he now thought that,subject to the Cabinefs views, he should pursue his earlier inten-tion of asking the Prime Minister to suggest to the Prime ministers of Australia and India that they should bring their influence tobear on the Republican leaders. They would, of course, be informed of the representations which he had already made to the dutch government.The Cabinets-Endorsed the Foreign Secretary&apos;s proposals.3. The Cabinet considered a memorandum by the foreign secretary (CP. (48) 299) covering an appreciation of the military,political and economic consequences of recent developments in theChinese civil war.The Foreign Secretary said that, as the result of recent militaryoperations, the Government of the Republic of China underPresident Chiang Kai-shek had virtually lost control of the whole area north of the River Yangtze and it was reasonable to assume that in course of time the Communists would secure control overthe rest of China. It was unlikely that the United. States Govern-would be willing to contribute further financial and material sources for the defence of the Kuomintang. The consequences ofthis situation were examined in detail in the paper annexed to cp. (48) 299; and he sought authority to discuss with the otherGovernments immediately concerned the best means of containing the Communist threat in the Far East. The interested powers should co-ordinate their policies in face of the increasing threat of communist aggression; but this task was seriously complicated by
the hostility provoked throughout Asia by the recent activities o;fthe French in Indo-China and the Dutch in Indonesia. In thesecircumstances, there would be no point in suggesting at this stagea general conference of all the Powers concerned. He therefore proposed that separate discussions should be initiated with the interested Powers, and with the United States Government. Hewould continue his efforts to promote settlements in Indonesia andIndo-China.In discussion, the following points were made-(a) No firm conclusions could be reached at this stage on theultimate nature of Chinese Communism or of the relationship between the Chinese Communist Government and the Soviet Union.The pronouncements of Communist leaders in China were Marxistin philosophy; and the possibility of a close relationship could notbe discounted. On the other hand, Far Eastern Communism might develop on Chinese rather than Slav lines. At present, ChineseCommunism was an agrarian movement; and it might be forcedby economic necessity to modify its principles in order to securethe support of the industrial and mercantile interests. The liberalelements in China, which had been alienated by the Kuomintang,would probably be ready to collaborate with a Communist regimeon reasonable terms. In these circumstances, there was some prospect that, at least in the initial stage, a Communist Government mightbe prepared to adopt a liberal policy towards foreign commercial interests. It would be unwise to pursue a policy which might havethe effect of gratuitously driving a Chinese Communist Governmentinto the arms of the Soviet Union, and it was important that the interested Powers should reach agreement as soon as possible ontheir attitude towards a Chinese Communist Government.(6) Whatever the ultimate character of Chinese Communism,the latest developments in the civil war represented a grave threat to the position of the non-Communist Governments throughout Asia.Was it not time to extend to the Far East the same sort of concertedarrangements for economic and military defence measures as werebeing built up against Soviet aggression in Western Europe throughthe European Recovery Programme and the policy of western union ?(c) The Minister of Defence said that some concern had been caused over the week-end by a Reuter message from London to theeffect that the Government did not intend to send troops to protect british interests in Shanghai. There was no truth in this : on thecontrary, the Naval Commander-in-Chief had reported that he hadplanned to send some troops in His Majesty&apos;s ships from HongKong if and when required, also for the use of full landing partiesfrom His Majesty&apos;s ships for the protection of property on tie waterfront.(d) The recent developments in China emphasised the need foran early settlement of Japan&apos;s future.(e) While nothing should be said to discourage British interestsfrom remaining in China, it would be inadvisable to offer any positive encouragement which might give rise to claims for compen-sation.(/) There was no way of preventing an influx of Kuomintangrefugees into Hong Kong, but it was essential that the british authorities, in their dealings with them, should not give any impression of departing from a strict neutrality between the two sides in the civil war.(g) The developments in China would throw an increasingstrain on the Colonial Governments in Hong Kong and Malaya, andall necessary steps should be taken to strengthen and support thelocal administrations. .&apos;
The Cabinet (1) Expressed general approval of the policy outlined in cp. (48) 299.(2) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consult in the first instance ;with the United  States  Government on means  ofcontaining the Communist threat to Anglo-american interests in Asia.(3) Took note that, in the light of the results of the approach to be made under Conclusion (2) above, the foreign secretary would discuss with the Secretary of State for commonwealth Relations means of holding similarconsultations with Commonwealth Governments.(4) Invited the Foreign Secretary to consider, in consultationwith the Secretary of State for the Colonies and theMinister of Defence, what further steps could be takento strengthen our position in Colonial territories in Asia.4. The Cabinet had before them the following memoranda onthe proposal that the Valuation Office of the Board of InlandRevenue should undertake all valuations and negotiations in respectof land and buildings required by Government Departments : -CP. (48) 273 : by the Chancellor of the Exchequer.CP. (48) 294: by the Minister of Agriculture.CP. (48) 290 : by the Secretary of State for War.CP. (48) 291 : by the Minister of Works.The Chancellor of the Exchequer explained that DistrictValuers carried out both valuation and negotiation for most Govern-ment Departments and for most local authorities, and that he desired to extend this practice to acquisition on behalf of theMinistry of Agriculture, War Office and Ministry of Works, which now carried through their own negotiations. This would not involvea substantial extension of the work already performed by the valuation Office : last year they had acquired properties to the valueof  225 million and the three Departments had acquired propertiesworth about  5 million. In terms of value, the additional burden would be only about 2 per cent, of the present work of the ValuationOffice. The District Valuer had a mass of information which wasvery useful in valuation and negotiation, since he valued for deathduties and assessed development values and development chargesunder the Town and Country Planning Acts. Other departmentalvaluers did not have this knowledge at their disposal. That relatingto death duties was particularly valuable, for it meant that allprivate land was assessed once in every generation and from the angle of death duties the owner was endeavouring to place a lowvalue on his holding. The case for centralising this work in the valuation Office had been greatly strengthened by the passing ofthe Town and Country Planning Acts, 1947. These Acts compli-cated the problem of valuation and made it essentially important that all valuations and negotiations should be on existing use value.If Departments in negotiations gave a high figure to existing use value, the development value was proportionately reduced and thislessened what the State was receiving in exchange for the 300 million fund which was to be distributed to the former owners of development values. He quoted examples where the Ministry ofWorks had proposed a higher value than the District Valuer forproperty which they proposed to acquire. He agreed that the valuation Office had a heavy burden to carry under the Town and country Planning Acts, 1947, and the Local Government Act, 1948,but the necessary priority would be given to Departmental workwhere this was necessary.The. Minister of A griculture said that the case put forward bythe Chancellor of the Exchequer related primarily to urban valua-tions and not to the kind of land which was acquired by the Ministryof Agriculture or the Forestry Commission.    He stressed the
professional competence in their own field of the -staffs employed bythe Ministry and by the Commission, and pointed out that an agricultural Land Commission had been set up under the agriculture Act, 1947, to supervise the use of land and to acquirederelict land. Where &quot;the Commission were proposing to-acquire derelict land, it would be a waste of time and energy for&quot;the District Valuer to come into the valuation or the negotiations and the same would apply to, say, the acquisition of Romney Marshor to the acquisition of farms which were under supervision becausethey had been badly managed by the owner. He referred also to-the Universities and College Estates Act, 1925, under which theMinistry acquired agricultural land, and to the acquisition of landfor smallholdings.The Secretary of State for War said that his position was somewhat similar to that of the Minister of Agriculture. The land which the War Office wished to acquire very seldom had any develop-ment value. The War Office had a staff of qualified valuers whowere familiar with the needs of the Army and with the jjroce&amp;ureunder which land could be acquired for Service purposes. these officers were also engaged in estate management and in the acqtiisi-tion of properties overseas, and no saving of staff would be &quot;secured by taking the work of valuation and negotiation away from them.He feared that, if the work were transferred to the Valuation &quot;Office,there would be serious delays because of the volume of work failingon that Office under the Town and Country Planning Acts. Theneed to secure a uniform basis of valuation could be amply secured by consultation between the Valuation Office and the other Depart-ments.The Minister of Works believed that there would be a serious loss of efficiency if the negotiations at present handled by his skilledstaff were handed over to the Valuation Office. From certain aspects,the number of sites involved was more important than the aggregatevalue. Several Departments, notably those responsible for social- services, were putting in heavy demands for small premises and he did not believe that this type of acquisition could be handled as wellby the District Valuer as by his officers. There was a real risk of delay, as evidenced by the fact that recent applications to theDistrict Valuers for advice on valuations had involved a delay oftwo or three months. He thought that the machinery for consulta-tion which the three Departments had commended to the treasury would secure the necessary uniformity of practice. That system should, at any rate, be tried out for two years.In further discussion, the following points were made : (a) The Ministry of Town and Country Planning attached importance to the negotiation by the District Valuer of acquisitionsby local authorities under the Town and Country Planning Act.At present, some of the largest local authorities did not employthe District Valuer and they were unlikely to do so if he was not employed by all Government Departments.(&amp;) The Air Ministry, which had had experience of the systemadvocated by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, considered that theWar Office should be allowed to carry on with their present arrange-ments.(c) Co-ordination of the principles of valuation at the centrewas not likely to achieve what the Treasury desired, because muchof the art or valuation lay in the application of these principles to particular properties. Moreover^tne machinery of consultation between departmental officers and District Valuers would involve-duplication of effort, since the District Valuer would have to see-the property and find out all the relevant facts before he could make-full use of the information already in his possession.
153CM. 80 (48)(d) The memoranda which had been circulated and the explana-tions afforded by Ministers had not cleared up the question whetherthe arrangements proposed by the Chancellor of the exchequer would secure any economy in staff. There would be some additional work falling on the Valuation Office, while at the same time itwas argued that there would not be any reduction of staff at theMinistry of Agriculture and the War Office and that the new proce-dure, because of the need for consultations, might even involve some increase of staff at the Ministry of Works.(e) While the Chancellor of the Exchequer had been able to quote cases in which the Ministry of Works had proposed a higher price than that proposed by the District Valuer, Departments mighton investigation be able to give cases in which Departmental officers had negotiated a lower price than the District Valuer had in mind.The general feeling among members of the Cabinet was that acase had been made out for the centralisation of the work of valua-tion and negotiation in the Valuation Office, provided that the valuation Office could handle cases as expeditiously as the Depart-mental organisations. Ministers thought that, before taking afinal decision, they should be reassured on this point, which was of particular importance because of the relatively urgent characterof some of the work of acquisition which Departments were carrying. through, and because of the heavy load which was being placed inother directions on the Valuation Office.The Cabinet-Invited the Prime Minister to arrange for a Committee of officials to investigate whether effect could be given tothis centralisation of work without delays in acquisition and what, if any, saving of staff would be secured. Thi?Committee should also collect any information submitted on the point noted in paragraph (e) above. Their report should be submitted to the Cabinet.International 5.   The Cabinet had before them a memorandum by the MinisterLabour of Labour.(CP. (48) 293) proposing the ratification of the Conven-Conference, tion (No. 17) concerning Workmen&apos;s Compensation for Accidents192S. which had been adopted at the Seventh Session of the InternationalWorkmen&apos;s     Labour Conference held in Geneva in 1925.Compensation. The Cabinet were informed that, since the entry into force ofthe National Insurance (Industrial Injuries) Act, 1946, and theNational Health Service Act, 1948, and corresponding legislation in Northern Ireland, the law in Great Britain and Northern Irelandsatisfied the provisions of this Convention; and it was therefore proposed that it should now be ratified on behalf of Great Britainand Northern Ireland.The Cabinet were also informed that the International LabourConference were discussing a separate Convention regarding work-men^ compensation in non-metropolitan countries. It was, however,pointed out that the 1925 Convention would be ratified only onbehalf of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and that this neednot prejudice the attitude of the United Kingdom government towards the further Convention now under discussion.The Cabinet-(1) Agreed that the International Labour Convention (No. 17)of 1925 concerning Workmen&apos;s Compensation forAccidents should be ratified on behalf of Great Britainand Northern Ireland.(2) Authorised the Minister of Labour to present to parliamentary White Paper in the terms of the draft annexed to cp. (48) 293.Cabinet. Office, S.W.1,13th December, 1948.


</content>
</cab>
