<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/285/0 images: 29-50</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.  April 1939.SECRET.                                                        Copy  No.CP. 83 (39).               TO  BE  KEPT  UNDER  LOCK AND  KEY.It is  requested that special care may be  taken  to      ensure the  secrecy of  this document.                  CABINET.VISIT  OF  THE  POLISH FOREIGN  MINISTER,  APRIL 4-6, 1939.                         RECORD OF CONVERSATIONS.          Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    I CIRCULATE  to my colleagues the records of the conversations whichthe Prime Minister and I had with the. Polish  Foreign Minister during his visit to London, together with a summary of the conclusions reached during the conversations,  drawn up in agreement with M. Beck.                                                                     H.    April 8, 1939.                        FIRST MEETING.(IN THE SECRETARY OF STATE&apos;S ROOM AT THE FOREIGN OFFICE, ON APRIL 4,                             AT 11 A.M.)                         Present:Lord Halifax (Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs).Sir A.  Cadogan (Permanent Under-Secretary of State).Mr. Strang (Foreign Office).M. Beck (Polish Minister for Foreign Affairs).Count Raczynski (Polish Ambassador).Count Joseph Potocki (Ministry for Foreign Affairs).                 British Proposal to.JPoland and&apos;. Roumania.    M. Beck said that as he had, in his last conversation with Sir H. Kennard,reserved his final answer to the British, proposal, he thought the best thing wouldbe for him to open the conversation by giving his reply.    He said he would start by saying that the question (which had been put tohim by Sir H. Kennard) whether  Poland would defend her political and economicindependence, was a purely rhetorical question, otherwise he would not be inLondon.      10343  [18942]                                               B
    He was of opinion that the heed for the present conversation had been created by the attitude of Germany, which had recently  lost all measure.  The PolishGovernment were still prepared, as they had hitherto been, to try to find a peace-ful settlement, but they could not close their eyes to  dangers which had becomeobvious.  &apos;                                                               - &apos; &apos;    The proposal made by the British Government was an important one and waswelcome to the Polish Government, not only for its substance, but by. reason ofthe terms in which it was couched.    The first thing he  wished to say was  that when  His Majesty&apos;s Governmentsaid that they were prepared to enter into ah engagement towards Poland, it was clear that the engagement must be reciprocal, and this was the light in which thePolish Government saw the question.    As regards Eastern Europe, however, the situation was not quite so clear.In this sphere, three questions arose, two of which had already been  touched onin the British proposal, and one of which  had not been touched on.  These werethe questions of :  (1) Soviet Russia;  (2)  the  Danubian Basin;  (3)  the Balticcountries.    He would  start with Soviet Russia, and  repeated what he had  said  toSir H. Kennard, namely, that in view of the grave tension between Moscow andBerlin, it would be dangerous to bring Russia into any discussions.  He  recalledwhat  Marshal Pilsudski had said, namely, that when thinking of Germany and russia it was necessary to take into account not only their interests, but theirideologies.  For this reason the question of Soviet Russia required to be handledwith great caution and by special methods.    There were two things which it was impossible for Poland to do, namely, tomake  her policy dependent upon either Berlin or upon Moscow. He was glad to note that due account had been taken of this in the British proposal:    As&apos; regards the Danubian Basin, there  were two countries with whom Polandhad special relations, namely Roumania, her ally, and Hungary,&apos;her friend.    The Polish-Roumanian  alliance applied only in the case of an attack fromthe East.  The Polish  Government had made great efforts to prevent a conflictarising between Roumania and Hungary.   They thought that if  they gave anygeneral backing to Roumania, this would  tend to throw Hungary into the arms of Germany, and  they  felt,  therefore, that any action of this kind would  be premature.   As Roumania  was the ally  of  Poland, any  extension of Polishobligations  towards Roumania would need to be discussed between Warsaw andBucharest, since only in that way could the interests of the two countries be fullyreviewed.                                                             , :    M. Beck said that in the foregoing remarks  he  had tried to give  an exactpicture of. the- Polish Governments attitude.  He would now add some considera-tions of a more general  character.    From the contacts which they had recently  had with Count Ciano and withthe Hungarian  Foreign  Minister, the  Polish Government  had  gained  theimpression  that  both   Italy  and Hungary were  seriously  perturbed  aboutGermany&apos;s  designs of domination.  Though the signs of this  anxiety were notobvious on  the surface,  the  Polish Government thought this anxiety was deep-seated .  This was a delicate matter, but the Polish Government  thought that itwas a factor which ought not to be overlooked.   In any event, M. Beck thoughtthat no door  should be closed and no political action taken which would tend tobar the door.  He asked that this information should  be regarded  as mostconfidential.    Lord Halifax asked whether he was  right in thinking that, in M. Beck&apos;view,  it would be wise to examine the Roumanian  position very carefully for fear of throwing Hungary into the arms of Germany.   And  to  take the points stage further, did he think that if Hungary moved  into the German camp,  thiswould diminish  the  possibility  of  a joint  Italo-Hungarian   effort  againstGermany ?    M. Beck agreed.    He then turned to the question of the Baltic countries.  The Polish Govern-ment  had observed that resistance to  German pressure in  those countries  hadbeen stouter than it had been in Czecho-Slovakia.  Poland took a great interestin those countries, particularly in Lithuania.  M.  Beck thought  it would be
wise to help those countries,  and in a.discreet  way to encourage their spiritof resistance.   He realised cautious methods would have to be employed so as not to irritate German elements bordering on the Baltic  States.  Poland  had recently tried  to help Lithuania, though without  making it known that she had done so. &apos;   - Lord  Halifax said he was grateful for this  information.    Perhaps M. Beck would allow him  to clear up a number of points that had occurred to him during M. Becks earlier exposition of the Polish attitude.    He wished first, on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, to express apprecia-tion  of M. Becks remarks  about the British proposal.  He wished  to  ask, asa  matter  of interest  rather  than of  policy, whether  the Polish government thought there was any substance,  and if so, what substance,  in the  rumoursand  anticipations of the  preceding week.    &apos;M. Beck replied that the Polish Government had not noticed any signs ofdangerous military action on the part of Germany, but they had increased theirown  preparations in order  to prevent  their being made the object  of threatsfrom Germany.  They  had, of  course,  their own local Danzig affair,  but  thiswas  not yet in negotiable shape.  Poland,  in any event, would  not be preparedto discuss it under threat or  to accept  any imposed solution.  ;   Lord  Halifax said that M. Beck and  he could discuss  the  Danzig question a little later,  but he. understood M. Beck  to say that he did not think that itwas  ripe  for  negotiation.     M. Beck said that in view  of the fact that  the Council of the League had it in mind to withdraw from some of its responsibilities in  Danzig, the question was  one which ought to be discussed with Germany,  and such discussion might perhaps be  feasible, but  Poland would not accept a fait  accompli, though she would not close the door  to  reasonable and free negotiations.     Lord  Halifax, reverting to  the discussion of the  British proposal, said thathe understood M. Beck to  say that when Great Britain was prepared to undertake a commitment towards Poland,  he felt that this  should be  on a reciprocal basis,and  that  therefore  Poland was prepared to give a reciprocal undertaking toGreat Britain.     M. Beck agreed that this was so.  This was the only basis that any  self-respecting country could  accept.     Lord Halifax said that he  had expected this to be M, Beck&apos;s attitude,  first,because of the position Poland  occupied in the world, and, secondly, because inthis respect the interests  of Poland and Great Britain were identical, both their immediate interests and their interest in the maintenance of European peace.     Before leaving this question, he would like to be clear on one point.  Poland&apos;streaty with. France, he understood, obliged Poland  to go  to  the assistance  ofFrance if France was the object of an attack by Germany.     M. Beck said that this was so, and added that the Polish interpretation ofthe Franco-Polish Treaty had always been more  explicit as regards the questionof immediate  assistance than had the interpretation given to the treaty by theFrench from  time to  time.   Poland had  always considered the Franco-PolishTreaty of 1921 as the fundamental instrument.   Subsequent treaties had merelyshaped it  to the needs of  the time.  He recalled that in 1936, during the meetingof the Council of the League in London, after  the  German occupation of the rhineland,  he had made  clear in what sense Poland  interpreted her  obligations to France.     Lord Halifax said that Great Britain, like Poland, was now contemplatinga different situation.  What Great Britain and  Poland were anxious to do wasto make a joint effort  against domination in whatever direction it might be.  Itwas for this reason that, in our proposal,  we had asked a further question.  if France and Great Britain were directly attacked by Germany, or if they became involved in war  with Germany arising out of a German  attack upon  Holland,Belgium,  Switzerland, Denmark or even Yugoslavia,  could  they count on Polishsupport ?       [18942]                                                    B  2
    M. Beck replied that at the present moment, from the purely legal point ofview,  Poland was bound  to  assist France only in the event of an  attack  byGermany upon  France.  The other points,  going beyond Poland&apos;s present legal obligations, might be discussed with His Majesty&apos;s Government, if the latter were willing, with the exception perhaps of the case of Yugoslavia, which belonged toquite  a different region.   Yugoslavia  fell into  the same  area as  Italy and hungary.    Lord Halifax said that M. Beck would appreciate that it was vital for us toknow whether,- if we were attacked by Germany, Poland would be with us.    M. Beck replied that this would clearly be so.    Lord Halifax said that it was equally vital for us to know whether we should enjoy the  same measure of support from Poland if Germany attacked holland or Belgium or Switzerland or Denmark.    M. Beck replied that the Polish Government would not refuse to discuss thisquestion.    Lord  Halifax said he  would try to make his reasons clear in a few words.His Majesty&apos;s Government felt that if Germany took aggressive action against any of these countries, this could only be  a preliminary to  aggression against france or Great Britain.    M. Beck said that he quite understood this. The Polish Government wouldbe ready to discuss this question, provided there was general agreement on otherparts  of the British proposal.    Lord Halifax inferred that M. Beck would therefore not disagree with him in feeling  that,  if a German attack was delivered in this way on Western Europe(he would  leave out  Yugoslavia for the present), France and&apos; Great Britain wouldhave to  resist it and that the interest of Poland would also be closely engaged,because  if, as a result of the  struggle the strength of  France and Great britain were diminished,  the danger to Poland would be correspondingly increased.  he fully realised the importance of the question he was asking.   Neither  the PolishGovernment nor His Majesty&apos;s Government would under-estimate the importanceof their standing closely together in face of  a common danger.    M.  Beck replied that he was, of course, at one with Lord  Halifax on thegeneral principle.  But there was a difference between a general principle and theparticular cases arising under it.   If  the  question of these  Western european countries was to be discussed, he would have to ask what undertakings we  had assumed towards each of them. Further, if Poland was to take an  interest inmatters which  concerned these countries, it would  be interesting to  know howthose countries themselves would react.    Lord  Halifax said that he would try to answer this question.    As  regards Belgium, our obligations were defined by treaty.  Great Britainand France were bound to help Belgium if  the latter were attacked by Germany.There was no doubt that Belgium would defend herself.    M.  Beck here  interjected  that  it seemed to him essential  that  only thosecountries should receive assistance who were prepared to defend themselves.    Lord Halifax thought that Holland would also defend herself if attacked;Great Britain and  France had agreed together that they would be prepared tosupport Holland  if attacked  by Germany, but neither Great Britain nor france had  any treaty obligations towards Holland,  and the Netherlands Governmenthad not been informed of the  agreement which His Majesty&apos;s Government and theFrench Government had reached as regards the defence of the Netherlands.    As regards Switzerland, His  Majesty&apos;s Government had told the FrenchGovernment that they would support the latter in resisting  a German attack onSwitzerland.  Both Great Britain  and France were bound by the Treaty  of vienna of - 1815, though  it  was not clear what  this  obligation  amounted to.Switzerland would certainly  defend herself if attacked.  Nothing had been  saidto the Swiss Government about the agreement reached between Great Britain andFrance for the  defence of Switzerland.
      As regards Denmark, there had been no precise exchange of views between His Majesty&apos;s  Government and the French Government, and nothing had been said to the Danish Government.  The conclusion was not so precise as in the other cases, but he would anticipate that, if Denmark were threatened, His Majesty&apos;s&apos; Government would attribute to it the same character as a similar threat in other places.      The reason why His Majesty&apos;s Government had reached these conclusions was that they recognised that any act of aggression, if now made, would  be the same in character whether it  occurred in Eastern Europe or in Western Europe. It was therefore in the common interest of all to resist it together, and  not to allow our forces to be divided.  Lord Halifax therefore hoped that M. Beck would reflect upon these Western cases.  If he was not yet prepared to give an answer, perhaps they could return to  the subject later on.     M. Beck assured Lord Halifax that he fully understood the reasons  which had prompted His Majesty&apos;s Government.  Poland herself had  given very few undertakings of this kind, and it would be a very grave matter for her to under- take new  ones;  but he fully  understood the point  of view of His  Majesty&apos;s Government.     Lord Halifax  said that he would  now turn to Soviet Russia.     He  was  glad  to hear M.  Beck say  that  His Majesty.&apos;s Government had appreciated the position of Poland vis-a-vis Soviet Russia.  Would he be right in thinking that the Polish  Government would not be sorry if His  Majesty&apos;s Government could  manage to keep on fair terms with Soviet Russia?     M. Beck said  that Poland attached great importance to preserving correct relations with Soviet Russia.  The Polish Government had signed a pact of non- aggression with her.  After a period of tension last autumn, the necessary steps had been taken to  bring about a detente.  The two countries had even signed a satisfactory commercial treaty.  For that reason, the Polish Government could understand that His Majesty&apos;s  Government should  also attach  importance  to having good relations with Soviet Russia.     He wished,  however, to say that any pact of mutual assistance between Poland and Soviet Russia  would bring an immediate hostile reaction from Berlin and would probably accelerate the outbreak  of a conflict.  Poland had succeeded  in 1934 in putting Polish-German relations on a normal and satisfactory  basis, and this in spite  of the existence of the Polish-French Treaty, of which they had never made any secret.   But the Polish Government realised that, if they similarly engaged themselves towards their eastern neighbour, matters would be brought to a breaking-point.     Lord Halifax  asked whether  M. Beck thought that a  mutual  assistance arrangement between Poland  and Great Britain would have a provocative effect on Germany.     M. Beck said he could not give a definite answer.   Such an agreement would be a very important matter for Germany, though not so important  as a Polish- Russian agreement. He thought the Polish-French Treaty was a good analogy and he recalled that Hitler himself had  said that he had nothing to say against that treaty, as he had no intention of attacking either Poland or France and had no objection  to their making  a treaty  with each other.  The  same might apply to a Polish treaty with  Great Britain.     Lord Halifax  said  that,  making full allowance for  these considerations, which he  fully  understood, it might well be that Poland, Great Britain andFrance might all be in trouble together and, if so, it might be important  to poland to be able to use the Russian route for  the supply of  war material.  Was theappropriate course  not, therefore, to look  upon the problem  facing  Poland andGreat Britain and  France as  the problem of  how to  get a maximum  degree of collaboration from  Soviet Russia without entailing dangerous consequences-?     M. Beck appreciated this argument, but insisted  that the aim of the efforts which were now being made should be  the maintenance of peace, and that  everycare should be taken not to do anything to make the danger of war more imminent.Poland, for her part, was ready to improve her relations with Soviet Russia, butnot to extend  them.  It was important not to provoke a conflict, though it was,of course, difficult to say whether, indeed, a conflict was unavoidable.
   :  Lord Halifaoo asked how far  it would be an embarrassment to the PolishGovernment,  and open to objection from their point of view, if relations between france and Soviet Russia, or even between Great Britain and Soviet Russia, weremade closer.     M. Beck recalled that during the negotiations between France and the Soviet-Union which led up to the Franco-Soviet Pact, the Polish Government made anarrangement with M. Laval by which the latter accepted a Polish declaration tothe effect that no undertaking entered into by France towards the  Soviet Unioncould  extend Polish  liabilities.  If  France and Great Britain now undertookobligations towards the Soviet Union, Poland would find it necessary to make some similar declaration.     He  thought that France had  made a bad;bargain under  the Franco-SovietPact,  which  brought few concrete results and made a detente with Berlin and rome more difficult.     Lord Halifax asked whether, if France decided to simplify the Franco-SovietPact and make its operation  more  automatic, M. Beck would feel it necessary todo or say something to  show that Poland was not affected  and was keepingout of it.     M. Beck said that he would.     Lord Halifax  asked  what value M. Beck placed upon the Soviet militaryforces and upon the Soviet transport system as a means of transit.     M. Beck replied that the second question was really one for experts, but thePolish Government had not a  very high opinion of Soviet Russia from either pointof view.  In the autumn of 1938 four Soviet  army corps had moved towards thePolish frontier,  but Poland  had  not  thought  it necessary  to move  a singledetachment.     Lord Halifax  said that  his information was  that  the Red army might be efficient for purposes of defence, but not for purposes of offensive operations.     M. Beck said that this was also the view  of the Polish General Staff.     Lord Halifax  explained that  one of the difficulties about Soviet Russia inthis country  was that some members of the Labour party believed that, if GreatBritain and the Soviet Union could join  hands,  the world would be safe forever more.     M. Beck said he doubted the validity of  this theory.  There was no common frontier between Germany and Soviet Russia:     Discussion then turned on Roumania.     M.  Beck said  that he wished to consult the Roumanian Foreign minister before coming to any final conclusion as regards the Roumanian  aspect of our proposal.     Lord Halifax  fully appreciated what M. Beck had said about roumania and Hungary and about the  danger  of throwing Hungary into Germany&apos;s arms.On  the other hand, he  thought  that there was great danger  in having noconcerted plan  as  to what to do if Roumania were the object  of an  attack,either directly,  or  indirectly through Hungary.     M.  Beck thought that it was  desirable to give  Roumania some backing.Poland  had  done so from the military point of view.   Great Britain could doso from the economic and other points of view.  This would be a different thing from a rigid political system like  the Little  Entente which would automaticallythrow Hungary  into the other  camp.  Poland was anxious  for good relationsbetween Roumania and Hungary, and had even threatened Hungary a short time ago that there would  be  trouble if Hungary did anything, to endanger Roumania.   At the same time the Polish  Government  were loth to waste whatlittle  political capital they possessed in Budapest.     Lord Halifax  was sure  that it was M. Beck&apos;s view that  Great Britain and Poland  had  a common  interest in preventing Roumania from  being swallowed up by Germany like Czecho-Slovakia.     M.  Beck entirely agreed.
    Lord Halifax explained that what His Majesty&apos;s Government had suggested-was the establishment of a deterrent  by means of a preliminary understanding between Great Britain,  France and Poland, against an attack upon Roumania.He understood that M.  Beck felt that this would cause trouble by throwingHungary the wrong way.    A third point was, if the case which Lord Halifax had been putting was sound,would not  M. Beck think it  important  that  the Polish Government and HisMajesty&apos;s Government and, if possible,, the French Government, should arriveat a common decision  as  to what they would  be prepared  to  do in. the eventof Roumania being threatened ?    M. Beck replied that he would like to think this point over. He was awaitingfurther information from Bucharest as to the Roumanian attitude.(The Meeting adjourned at 12-45 P.M.)
                        SECOND MEETING.(IN THE PRIME MINISTER&apos;S  ROOM AT THE HOUSE OF COMMONS, ON APRIL 4,                               AT 5 P.M.)                         Present:Mr. Chamberlain (Prime Minister).Lord Halifax (Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs).Sir A. Cadogan (Permanent Under-Secretary of State).Mr. Strang (Foreign Office).M. Beck (Polish Minister for Foreign Affairs).Count Raczynski (Polish Ambassador).Count Joseph Potocki (Ministry for Foreign Affairs).            British Proposal to Poland and Roumania (continued).    M. Beck said that he would like to state in one sentence how he understood the conversation which had been held in the morning.  It was of  interest to the twoGovernments not to provoke a conflict  in  Europe, but to stand up against newpolitical methods which sought to impose unilaterally the will of one nation uponothers  in Europe.    The Prime Minister asked whether M. Beck felt, as  His  Majesty&apos;s  Govern-ment did, that German action in Czecho-Slovakia was in flagrant contrast withGermany&apos;s assurances as to the limits of her action, and that it did seem  to point to a desire on the part of the German Government to extend this process  to other states.    M. Beck agreed.  Up till 1938 German policy, although it had placed othercountries  in a difficult position, could  be  defended. Recent  events were inde-fensible.   That was why the Polish Government welcomed the Prime Minister&apos;sstatement (which M. Beck asked him to confirm) that His Majesty&apos;s Government&apos;sobject was to establish a system which would make that process impossible.    The Prime Minister said that was  precisely his view.    M. Beck said that the Polish Government were decided to stand up againstthe extension of  that process to Poland.  This was, however, not merely a matterof concern to the Polish Government, but a general position which it was useful for the two Governments to discuss.    The Prime Minister observed that Poland was closer to Germany than GreatBritain was, and M. Beck  was possibly in a better position to know what was going on in Germany.  Had he come to any conclusion where the next action byGermany was to be expected if Germany followed up her recent course of action,further %    M. Beck replied that if he were to go  by what the Germans themselves said,he would say that the  gravest question  was  the  colonial question.   His ownpersonal view and he was not in a  position to say that it was the view of hisGovernment was that after recent  events the  German Government  had  been impressed by the reaction they had produced in the world.  There was temporarilya kind of lull, and this was one  more reason to  increase that  reaction and makeit firmer.   Poland was a classical case.  Since  1934 she had made an effort toplace her relations with Germany on a friendly basis; to-day it was her firm action and her military preparations Avhich constituted the most serious deterrent toGermany.    The Prime Minister then asked  M. Beck to continue his  remarks about the conversation that had taken place that morning.    M. Beck said  that as  regards the practical position he  had expressed his views on that occasion, but he would be glad to hear the Prime Ministers ownreaction.                                                                   1
    The Prime Minister said that he had not been present, but he understoodthat the discussion had covered a wide field,  but had not brought any definite conclusions.    M. Beck said he wished to put one question of principle.  Did  the PrimeMinister consider that His Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared  to place thenew relationship  between Great  Britain and  Poland on  a permanent  basis inview of Poland&apos;s willingness to undertake  reciprocal  obligations?    The Prime Minister said that if the German Government had in  mind sucha policy as he had described above the policy of proceeding step by step  andattacking one country at a time--this must  end.in  the  destruction of Polishindependence, and would constitute the most serious attack on the British Empirethat we had ever  experienced.   It might, indeed, be completely successful.  that being so,  the interests of Poland and Great  Britain were the same.  Neitherwanted war,  or to impose unreasonable restrictions on Germany; but  they couldnot allow such  a policy to succeed without taking active steps  to  resist it.  it seemed to His Majesty&apos;s Government  that the  most effective way to prevent  that policy being put into operation would be to make it clear that if Germany pursuedthat policy, she would be involved in a war on  two fronts.    M. Beck said that the question he had  put was also an offer and a proposal.Poland was willing to take into consideration  the possibility of placing the  new relationship between the two countries on a permanent basis.    The Prime Minister said that he had been putting before M. Beck a numberof considerations leading up  to the action which His Majesty&apos;s government considered it desirable  to  take.   The declaration which he had made on the31st March had  been made to prevent their  being taken by surprise  by somesudden coup or swoop.  It was the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government to try to arrive at an agreement with the Polish Government on the Understanding  thatthat declaration  of  our  intention was one side  of an  agreement and  that thePolish Government  would be  willing to  offer a reciprocal undertaking  fromtheir side.    M. Beck said he thought that he had already made it clear that this was theintention of  the  Polish Government.    The Prime Minister agreed.    M. Beck said the Polish Government had  never contemplated the possibilityof a mere one-sided agreement.    The Prime Minister went on to say that the scheme he had outlined  was  onlya skeleton one, and there were a number of details which would have to be filled in.One point he wished to consider was the  following :  he  understood  M. Beck&apos;s.difficulty about bringing the Soviet Union  into the discussion as being  likely  to precipitate a conflict. He agreed that they  must be cautious.  On the other hand,while he hoped that any agreement that might be made would help to preservepeace, nevertheless they were dealing with an individual who was, to put it mildly,subject to  strong emotions, and they  must  be  prepared to  face the fact that he might  precipitate a conflict on the mere ground  of Great  Britain and Polandhaving concluded an agreement.  It was necessary  to  be prepared  for  thiseventuality.    Supposing  that Great Britain and  France and  Poland were  at war withGermany, he asked himself how Poland would carry on the conflict.  She had a;fine army and certain air resources, but he  understood her artillery, was not  very strong, nor were  her fortifications comparable with those which existed on theWestern front.   Poland&apos;s forces  would no doubt  put up a gallant fight, but  ifher munitions were exhausted, where could they replenish them except from Soviet.Russia, assuming that supply from Soviet Russia would be possible1? &apos;    M. Beck explained  that  Poland  was  in  a  position that required her to conciliate two opposing ideas -  in the first,  place, she had to be well prepared toward off any possible attack;  in  the second place, she had to act in such a  way-as to make an attack less likely.  The more difficult the situation was, the moresimple&apos;was the system that imposed itself upon her;&apos; On the one hand,  she would,if attacked, defend herself,  even if half the  country were occupied.  On the other       [18942]                                                       c1&apos;&apos;&quot;&quot;&apos;1&quot;&quot;1
hand, she would make the strongest efforts to avoid bringing upon her. people thecatastrophe which they suffered during the world war.  He was happy to conduct,discussions with His Majesty&apos;s Government, but he wTas loath to bring in any political elements that would threaten to bring a conflict  nearer.  Although  itwas  impossible to foresee&apos;when a conflict might  break out, that was no reason why the Polish Government should deprive themselves of  all the arguments  attheir disposal in order to ward off a conflict as  long as possible.     In  the case  of Germany and Russia,  the  imponderables counted for  morethan with other countries.  It was therefore necessary  to be especially careful  in handling them.  From conversations which he had had  in Germany,  he had acquired the  conviction that a decision to open  a war against Poland would be avery difficult one for Germany to  take.   Any  association between Poland and russia would bring that decision nearer.        &quot;     The Prime Minister quite appreciated  this argument  and  was not pressingM. Beck to bring in Russia openly.   But  it was  necessary,to face up to thepractical question.  If, in spite of all  efforts, war did break out, what then? Hewas  quite sure that M. Beck had thought about  this and had ideas on the subject.     M.  Beck said that, as regards any conversations that His Majesty&apos;s Goverh-ment might wish to have  with  the  Soviet Government, Poland  w^uld keep clear and  not join in, leaving the matter to the judgment of His Majesty&apos;s Government,though  continuing to be sceptical about it.     The Prime Minister observed that, if Germany and Poland were already  at war, the danger of bringing Russia into the discussions no longer existed, sincewar would already have broken out.  If,  in that case, His Majesty&apos;s Governmenthad  succeeded in arranging for assistance in war material from Russia, wouldthat assistance be welcome to Poland?     M. Beck said that, as a preliminary observation, he would recall a remark ofMarshal Pilsudski to the effect that,  even  if we  have  to fight  some day, that isno reason for our sleeping with our rifles in our beds.  For the present, he hadno authority to express any opinion about possible relations between Great Britainand  Soviet Russia, but he was not in a position  to accept any agreement whichwould have the effect, if even only indirectly, of linking Poland with Soviet Russia.     The Prime Minister pointed out that he was not suggesting that there shouldbe; in any  public; document any, clause providing that Russia should do this  or that in certain given circumstances.  He was thinking of the situation in, whichHis  Majesty&apos;s  Government  might enquire of  the Soviet Union  what. their intentions  were,  and: the reply  would  be  that they did not  know whether poland would accept assistance.   He  quite  understood M. Beck&apos;s objection  that anyassociation, direct or indirect,  with Soviet  Russia  would be a danger.   But thequestion he wished to ask was,  was there any other  reason against accepting help from Soviet  Russia if war actually takes  place?                             &apos;     M. Beck said that his attitude might be expressed by saying that, so far asPoland  was  concerned,  two  things  were essential,   that  she  should not  be dependant on Germany and that she  should not  be  dependent  on Soviet Russia.If Poland subordinated herself to either, she would no longer be an element ofpeace, but an element likely  to provoke war.   He quite  realised the practicaldifficulties of this attitude on Poland&apos;s part, but the principle was vital, and hehad expressed it openly both in Berlin and Moscow.     The Prime  Minister said he would not press  M. Beck any further on thispoint, but it was necessary,to contemplate the  possibility that  it might result inwar.  In that event, His Majesty&apos;s Government would wish to see Poland resist as strongly and  as long as possible.  His Majesty&apos;s Government were constantlybeing attacked in the House of Commons because they did not get on to better terms with  Russia.  He wished  to ask M.  Beck a  question.   Would it  be embarrassing to Poland if His Majesty&apos;s Government  now tried to improve their relations with the Soviet Government?   This would  not  mean that  they  would make an agreement with the Soviet Government,  but that they would  try to establish such relations as would enable them  to expect help from Soviet Russia in case of war..   :  .                     .   -                  &apos;!,&apos;:.-  ,,
   : M.  Beck replied that this was a matter which was  quite outside Poland&apos;scompetence, and he had no opinion to express and no objection to raise.  But hewould  utter  the warning that, if Russia  were brought  in, this might  wellprecipitate a conflict.  He wished to add that, as regards Poland&apos;s relations withRussia,  he  had taken care to see that they were correct both in the political andin the economic sphere.    The Prime Minister  said he would pass to a point discussed to a limited extent  that morning.   If there was a direct attack upon Great Britain byGermany, the meaning of  Poland&apos;s reciprocal undertaking was clear.  But therewas, of course, an alternative series of circumstances in which  there would beho direct attack on Great Britain.  In recent months there had been numerousstories that Germany had plans for  opening ah attack on Great Britain andFrance through some neutral country,  either  Belgium or Holland  or Switzerland.If Great Britain became involved in war with Germany in this way, would this be covered  by the reciprocal undertaking which M. Beck had in mind?    M.  Beck said that he  could only repeat what he said to Lord Flalifax in the morning.  If Great Britain and Poland reached a permanent binding agreement,the Polish Government would not exclude friendly discussion on these points.   Ifthe principle of permanent collaboration was accepted, Poland would  be willingto discuss them.    The Prime Minister said that principle  was accepted by His  Majesty&apos;sGovernment.    M.  Beck observed that, as there was no difference of bpinion as to the dangerof the situation, and as the principle in question had been  accepted,  the PolishGovernment were willing to take these questions into serious consideration.    The Prime Minister said that this was satisfactory.  The course he had inmind was,  he thought, the only way to deal  with the situation.   A great centralPower could strike anywhere in any direction, and, unless the other Powers hada mutual arrangement which would cover  any course, they would always be at a disadvantage.    M. Beck said he would beg the Prime Minister not to interpret the cautionof his language as evidence of a lack of goodwill on his part.  The matters theywere discussing were of the gravest importance, and the vital interests of Polandwere at stake.  He therefore had to speak in grave and measured terms.  he wished  to  avoid all unmeasured language so that he could  be sure of being  ableto fulfil all that he had promised.     The Prime Minister  agreed that the gravest matters were at stake, namely,the future of the two countries.  It was essential that they should not find them-selves left  with the worst of both worlds, namely, to find that they had provokedGermany without at the same time providing themselves with effective defence.     M. Beck said- that this was his own chief concern.     The Prime Minister  then reverted to the question of Eastern Europe.   Thetwo countries he had in mind were Roumania and Yugoslavia.  Roumania seemedto  His Majesty&apos;s Government a vital spot, because  of  her immense resources.Until recently, he had  thought  that this would be the scene of  Germany&apos;s  nextthrust,  although it was true  that Germany  had no frontier with Roumania.  if germany obtained control of  Roumanians resources in oil and wheat, &amp;e, whetherthis was achieved directly or indirectly,  this would  mean  a great accession of strength to Germany, and a weakening of the other side.     M. Beck admitted the  importance of  Roumania.  Roumania was the allyof Poland, and the Polish Government attached importance to everything thatconcerned  Roumania.  As he had said to Lord Halifax,  this part of Europe  still,in his view, held positive possibilities, and  it was desirable not  to close the  doorto favourable developments by adopting too rigid a system.     The Prime Minister  asked whether this meant that M.  Beck wished to leaveRoumania out of any arrangement for the present.     M. Beck said there were two points :   The first was that Roumania was an ally of  Poland. He did not, therefore, like to come to any definite decision without        [18942]                                    &apos;              c 2
concerting with the Roumanian Government.  In the second place, he wished tofind some less rigid system which would cover this part of the world withoutcompromising future possibilities,     The Prime Minister asked whether this meant that he wished to reserve thewhole question for consideration with the Roumanian Foreign Minister.     M. Beck replied that as an ally it was Poland&apos;s duty to consult Roumania.As the situation developed, however, he would be ready  to discuss with HisMajesty&apos;s Government how best to handle the Roumanian situation.     The Prime Minister asked whether M. Beck had  in mind the conclusion ofa treaty, or alliance, or  pact,  between Poland,  Great Britain and France, andthat any arrangement relating to Roumania (on which M. Beck did not wish toexpress an opinion until he had consulted  the  Roumanian Government)  shouldbe supplementary to or separate from the main agreement.     M. Beck replied that with France Poland already had a treaty.  So far as great Britain was concerned, they were at present trying to establish principles.As regards Roumania,  it would be best for the moment to leave her out  until the danubian problem had cleared itself a little.     Lord Halifax recognised the force of M. Beck&apos;s argument.  We had, however,learnt  to expect things to happen quickly.   Supposing  Germany,  feeling for aweak place  in the European structure, should encourage  Hungary to pick aquarrel with Roumania and support her.   What, according to M. Beck&apos;s idea,would  be the action we should take ?     M. Beck  replied that the  Polish  Government did  not wish  to lose their influence in Budapest,  which was based on centuries  of traditional  friendship.As a recent example of  what might happen, he recalled  that Poland had  notmerely advised but warned Hungary against picking a quarrel with Roumania.If Hungary were to become a vassal State  of Germany, the situation would be different.  So long as that was not the situation, Poland  was unwilling  to throwaway any chance of influencing the Hungarian Government.     The Prime  Minister said there was  another possibility  which  must beconsidered.  Supposing the German  Government said to the Roumanian Govern-ment:  We have made a commercial agreement with you which you have not kept,and we now require you  to make  a  new agreement, by which we shall  have  theright to receive  all your oil and  wheat.   We  give you  so many  hours  to  say&quot; Yes &quot; or &quot; No,&quot; and if you say  &quot;  No,&quot; you must take the consequences.   Eventhough  Germany might not have occupied Hungary, she had occupied  Bohemiaand Moravia and had a protectorate over Slovakia.   In  these days troops couldbe transported by aeroplanes, and aircraft could pass over  unoccupied  territory and drop bombs.   Supposing the  German threat was that  Bucharest would belaid in  ruins unless the  Roumanian Government accepted.  This might soundfantastic, but we had become accustomed to this  kind of thing, and it might very well happen.  What was to be done in such an event \    M.  Beck said the  possibility  was a theoretical one; but, supposing  it didhappen,, the answer was  that it  was for the  Roumanians to  decide.  If  the roumanians had sufficient courage, they  would say  &quot; No.&quot;  In his  opinion,assistance should in that  event be afforded to Roumania.   Poland was at presenthelping Roumania in a military way. Great Britain was in a position to help hereconomically.  Poland was organising the Roumanian arms industry and had sentStaff officers to help her with her military organisation.     The Prime Minister  said that he was not sure whether  Poland was ready togive Roumania a specific  assurance of assistance if she said &quot; No &quot; to Germany.In the absence of such an assurance,  would not Roumania be  likely to say &quot; Yes,&quot;since any assistance that might be afforded would not arrive in time ?    M.  Beck repeated  that  this was a question which  Roumania alone  couldanswer, and without consulting the Roumanian Government he himself was unableto give  an answer.   What Poland had to bear  in mind was that, in case of a conflict between Poland and Germany, the  help  that Poland could expect from
 Roumania would be rather negligible.  M. Beck could not accept it as a fact that Hungary was likely to march against  Poland, since this would be too drastic a psychological breach with the past.     The Prime Minister observed that,  while it might be true  that  Roumania could not give  much help to Poland, the fact remained that, if Roumania were occupied by Germany, Poland would have a longer frontier with Germany.     M. Beck pointed out that the additional frontier would be quite  short, and would be in mountainous territory, which could be held with quite a small force. As regards oil supplies, Poland had sufficient for her needs in case of war.     He did not wish it to be supposed that he was lacking in warmth in speaking of Poland&apos;s ally, but his main point was that all this was a question which should be dealt with at Bucharest.     M. Beck then reverted to the question of the Baltic States.  It was desirable to do everything possible to strengthen their resistance, while at the  same time avoiding all provocation.  During the Memel crisis the Polish Government had informed the Lithuanian Government that  they could count entirely on Polish sympathy,  and the Lithuanian Government had been grateful for this declaration.     The Prime Minister observed that this  had not saved Memel.     M. Beck replied that the  Lithuanians had  surrendered Memel, and had not asked Poland for assistance.   The Polish assurance  to Lithuania had  been given at  a later  stage, when  there was a  danger of further German  pressure  on Lithuania.                                  Danzig.     The Prime Minister asked whether any  discussions were at present going on between the Polish and  the German Governments about Danzig.     M. Beck replied that no negotiations were in progress, but that conversations about Danzig had been  going on for some time in fact, ever since  the Polish Government had heard  from Geneva that the Council of the League desired to withdraw  the  High  Commissioner.    The object of  the conversations was to institute a system in which Danzig would not be a  burden upon  German-Polish relations, it being essential, of course, that the status of the Free  City should be maintained.  For the last eight centuries,  Danzig though it had a predominantly German population had lived upon the Polish hinterland.     He did  not  know whether it would be possible to reach agreement with Germany, but he was trying to reach an agreement.  In any event Poland  would certainly take up the challenge if Germany tried to face her with a fait accompli.     Lord Halifax enquired what kind of settlement of the Danzig question the Polish Government had in mind.     M. Beck replied that  he had in mind a bi-lateral  Polish-German arrange- ment which, while guaranteeing free government for the local population,  would safeguard  the existing rights of Poland in Danzig.  The  German Government had never contested Polish rights in Danzig, and had recently confirmed them.     The Prime Minister enquired whether the arrangement would include  an autobahn across the Corridor.     M. Beck  replied that Poland would never tolerate any extra-territorial system in connexion with  such  an autobahn; but,  on  the other hand, she was quite prepared  to facilitate transit by making arrangements about visas, customs duties, &amp;c.     The Prime Minister  asked whether Germany had ever asked for an autobahn.     M. Beck replied that nothing that had happened had passed beyond the stage of conversations.  No written demands had been presented to the Polish Govern-ment.  No  doubt there were people in Germany who wanted to  demand these things  of Poland, but he doubted whether Germany would risk  a conflict with poland over local matters of this kind.  He  added,  privately and confidentially,that it was jDOSsible that  Herr  von Ribbentrop was the inventor of some of theseideas, but he doubted whether  they had received  the approval of his chief.
    Lord  Halifax observed that His Majesty&apos;s Government would of course beglad if it  were possible for Poland and Germany to reach an agreement aboutDanzig. As M. Beck knew, the present position was a difficult one both from thepoint of view of the League of  Nations  and from the  point  of  view  of HisMajesty.&apos;s  Government as rapporteur.  Some action would  have to be taken beforethe Council met in May.  It would help His Majesty&apos;s Government if M. Beckcould say  how he thought the Danzig  question could best be handled from thepoint of view of Polish-German relations.    M. Beck said he desired  to come to some  arrangement with Germany. Hewas unable to say whether it would be possible  to do anything before the  Councilinet in May.  He would, however, keep Lord Halifax informed of the positionand of developments. If possible, he would make some practical suggestion beforethe Council met; if this was not possible,  he would offer  no advice and  leave itto His Majesty&apos;s Government to do what they thought best.    Lord  Halifax asked whether  M. Beck wished to see the High Commissionerretained at Danzig.    M. Beck replied that in view of the complications of the situation, it wouldmake it more difficult for Poland if a decision were taken by the Council which made urgent readjustment necessary.  If no  agreement  were  reached  between germany  and Poland  before May, it  would be convenient if  no change  weremade at the May Council.  But if an agreement should be reached before May,the situation would, of course, be  different.     Lord  Halifax observed that a great many people thought that it was desirablethat the Council should be released from its guarantee of a Constitution which no longer functioned.   He would  consult  M. Beck  before the Council met, butit would not be easy to leave things as they were.     M. Beck said that  he realised that the Polish Government would be  grateful for anything which the League could do to help, though  they did not think thatit could help very much.  The question was, however, not in itself a very grave one.He did not propose to trouble His Majesty&apos;s Government  with the various phasesthrough which the Danzig  question might pass.   If, however, Poland took a firm attitude about Danzig, especially in resistance to a fait accompli, this wouldbe not for the  sake of Danzig itself, but  as a matter of principle.  The PolishGovernment  had informed the  German Government that they were prepared todiscuss the Danzig question  in a  friendly  way;  but  that they were equallyprepared  to oppose with all their forces any attempt to settle the Danzig  questionunilaterally. Danzig had become a kind of symbol.                             Future  Procedure.     The Prime Minister said they had now touched on the main features of thesituation.  He was much obliged to M. Beck for putting his views so frankly.He understood them better than  he did before.     There were a number of matters requiring further consultation, such as the question  of  Boumania, on which it would not be possible to reach agreement before M. Beck left London.  Yet it might be a good thing to try to get  some- thing on  paper, such, for example, as the heads of an agreement.     M. Beck said that this would be a  natural outcome of the conversations.  The proposed document might note the questions on which agreement had been reached in principle.  This paper would remain confidential.   There would also be a public communique which would  say,  among  other things, that the  principle of reciprocity had been accepted.     The  Prime Minister agreed that there might be two  papers  (1) a confidential document showing the heads of an agreement, and (2) an official communique to the press.  The first paper might show (a) the points upon which  agreement had been reached,  (6) the  points which required  further consideration.     M. Beck said that he would like to have  the chance of looking at any draft that was prepared.
    The Prime Minister said that there was one further point which he wishedto raise.                    ;,  ,    It might take some time before the official agreement could be reached and puton paper. If during the interim period nothing hut our own one-sided guarantee to Poland  remained in  force,  His Majesty&apos;s  Government were certain  to be criticised.  Could  M.  Beck  give  an undertaking  that  Poland&apos;s  reciprocalguarantee would also be in force?    M. Beck said that  he could give this  assurance.  He had authority from thehead of the State to give this assurance.  He asked whether this assurance would remain confidential or  would  be made public.    He  suggested  that  the  Prime  Minister  might state,  if  questioned  inParliament, that His  Majesty&apos;s Government had  been  assured  that whateverundertakings it gave to Poland would be  reciprocally given by Poland.    The Prime Minister observed that, stated in this way, the assurance would refer not to the present interim period, but  to the permanent agreement whichwould  be reached at some future date.  His Majesty&apos;s Government were certain to be asked whether at  the present time His Majesty&quot;s  Governments undertaking-alone was in force, or  whether  Poland had  given an  undertaking to cover the interim period.  It was desirable  that he should be able to say that M, Beck&apos;sassurance covered the transitory  period.    M. Beck said that  the Prime Minister could certainly say that, pending theconclusion of the final agreement, the provisional guarantee was reciprocal.(The meeting adjourned at 6-5.0 P.M.)
ID                         THIRD  MEETING.(IN THE PRIME MINISTER&apos;S ROOM AT THE HOUSE OF COMMONS, ON APRIL 5,                               AT  5 P.M.)                         Present:Mr. Chamberlain (Prime Minister).Lord Halifax (Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs).Sir A. Cadogan (Permanent Under-Secretary of State).Mr. Strang (Foreign Office).M. Beck (Polish Minister for Foreign Affairs).Count  Raczynski (Polish Ambassador).Count  Joseph Potocki (Ministry for Foreign Affairs).            British Proposal to Poland and  Roumania- (contd.).    The Prime  Minister suggested  that  consideration should be given to thematters which it had not been found possible  to settle, particularly the position if Great Britain were attacked by Germany, not directly, but through  someneutral State.    The conversations appeared to him to be  tending towards a result different from  that  which public opinion was expecting, namely,  towards  a  bilateralAnglo-Polish agreement, whereas what was hoped for was an arrangement bywhich a number of States  would band themselves round Great Britain, Franceand Poland as a nucleus.    He assured M.*Beck that he fully appreciated M. Beck&apos;s reasons for thinking that this latter  plan was not a good one.  He had very much in his mind theimportance of not making an arrangement which  might precipitate a conflict.Anything that was  done should therefore be scrutinised with that considerationvery much  in mind.   He himself, having been present at the conversations, waswell aware of  the objections, but the public and  members of Parliament hadnot had that  advantage and might be suspicious about the results.  He was particularly anxious that the result should not be regarded as a selfish arrange-ment  made by the two countries  in their own interests : it ought to be regardedas a step which, while undoubtedly in our own  interests,  was directed against any  attempt at  world domination, wherever this might  show itself.  Thesesuspicions  would be all the more deeply-rooted because of the difficulties  aboutRussia,  even  though  these  difficulties might not be based  on facts, but onprejudices and preconceptions based on a particular ideology.    His conclusion  was that it was most important, when making a public  state-ment  about the agreement, to show that it was part of a general policy and notmerely devoted,  to a  local  or minor danger.   It  would make all the differencefrom  the British point of view if it could be said  that the reciprocal undertaking which the  Polish Government were ready  to give us in the permanent arrange-ment  would cover not only the case  of a  direct attack upon Great Britain, butalso the case in which Great Britain was engaged in war for a principle whichhad been violated by an attack on a country on whose behalf we should be acting.    M. Beck said that by his instructions he was obliged to treat the question by stages.   He was fully authorised  to declare that the guarantee between  GreatBritain and Poland in the event of  a  direct  attack was reciprocal.  As regardsthe question of an attack through neutral countries, he could say that, so far as hepersonally was concerned, he was convinced that  the question could be examined by the two Governments.   As regards  Roumania, and perhaps Hungary, he hadless authority to speak.  He must first discuss matters with the Governments ofthe countries  concerned.  Polish public  opinion  would  not understand howquestions pertaining to Roumania should not have been discussed in the first place between Warsaw and Bucharest.    The Prime Minister  said  he was more concerned with the second  pointthan  with  the third.   It would be unsatisfactory for His Majesty&apos;s government if they should have  to make public some document in which on the British side
there should be no  reservation, while  on the Polish side there should be a reservation,  even though that reservation was accompanied by an indication thatthe question might be one for discussion.   : M. Beck observed that there was a difference between what could be made public and what was the real intention of the Polish Government. On the latter point he could promise favourable consideration of the question.  In the officialcommunique it might perhaps be said that the two countries had agreed to consult together whenever there was a threat directed against either of them which might involve them in war.    The Prime Minister said that he did not much like talking about consultation.Democratic  Governments were always being jeered at because  they  could  notpromise anything more definite  than consultation.    M. Beck said he would not press the point. He was merely trying to find a formula.    The Prime Minister said  that, so far as Holland and  Belgium at any ratewere concerned, the question was one that came  very  closely home to us.   Anattack on  the  independence  of Holland or Belgium would be equivalent  to anattack on  our own independence.    M.  Beck  said  that  of  the  four countries concerned  (Holland,  Belgium,Switzerland and Denmark), Belgium enjoyed special sympathy in Poland, and hethought every  effort would be  made to cover the case  of Belgium.  He realised that, in view  of the special  position of Holland and Belgium,  they  could beregarded in a  sense as the maritime frontier of Great Britain.   There was, inhis own personal view, a strong case for including them in the permanent agree-ment between  Great Britain and Poland; but this was a  question which  thePolish Government alone could decide, and he himself had no authority to committhem.  He had to weigh very carefully every  word that he said,  and he was anxious that his cautious attitude should not be interpreted as  showing lack ofgood will.    The Prime Minister observed that, if one looked into the future, the positionof Poland would be precarious unless she could count on strong support from thewest which would engage strong  German forces.  Unless the proposed agreement were a pretty complete one, it might not  be possible to achieve the purpose inview. He would like to  find a form of words  which  would not carry M. Beckfurther  than he wished to  go,  but which  would  indicate that some further examination of the point would be made.    He thought that the communique might say that  the  two  countries would enter into a permanent undertaking to come to each other&apos;s assistance in the eventof action  which threatened  their independence, and that  they  would consider further the various circumstances in which the threat to  their independence might arise.    M. Beck said that this idea  appealed to him, though he would like to see adraft.    The   Prime Minister  emphasised  that,  when  it came  to drafting  thepermanent, agreement, the point about  Belgium and Holland, &amp;c. would be a vital one.    M. Beck fully realised  this. His own personal view was  that, when  thepermanent agreement was drafted,  it would have  to  include something  about these countries.  He himself had never thought otherwise,  though he repeated that he had  no authority to commit the Polish Government on the point.    The Prime Minister then reverted to Roumania.    He understood from  M.  Beck that, in his view, an  attack on Roumania was unlikely to come except through Hungary, and that to enter into an arrangement to defend  Roumania against an  attack through Hungary would  not be likely toimprove the relations between Hungary and Poland, and &quot;that, therefore, M. Beckwould prefer to leave the matter open for the present.    M. Beck had also said on the previous day that if Hungary became a vassalof Germany then the situation would be different.  He wished to direct M. Beck&apos;attention  to that possibility.   One  only had to look at the map to see that if      [18942]                                                      D
Germany established a protectorate over Hungary, she  would be in an advan-tageous strategical position  to  continue her advance  towards  Roumania orYugoslavia, as the case might be.  It would be unwise to exclude the possibility ofsome such plan being adopted, and Hitler, when he acted,  acted quickly.  HadM. Beck considered the possibility  or probability of this, and what did he  thinkshould be done if it happened?    M. Beck  admitted that these methods had been employed.  The Hungarians,however, were by tradition deeply  attached  to their independence.  He did  notthink the chances of a German swoop with the collaboration of Hungary shouldbe put very high.   In any event, it was  desirable to do  nothing to make &amp;uch a development more likely.   Hungary knew that Roumania was the ally of poland and he could not himself believe that Hungary would allow herself to be used as atool by Germany against Roumania.  Between Hungary and Poland there were athousand years of traditional friendship.  The two countries had declared beforethe League of Nations  in 1921  that each of them would decline  to sign any document directed  against the other.    The Prime Minister said that this was not quite the situation he had in  mind.Suppose that Hitler had a plan for action against Hungary by a certain date andhad  accumulated  overwhelming forces on  her  frontiers.   He  would  start a campaign  about  the grievances  of  the  German inhabitants  and how  theHungarians could  not keep order.  He might then send for the Regent or  thePrime Minister,  as he had sent for M. Hacha, and say he could not stand it any longer and that  if Hungary wished to live in peace  she would  have to acceptprotection from the Reich.  If she refused, he would march in or bomb Budapest.It was true that Hungary might be different from Czecho-Slovakia, but suppose that the Hungarian Government said they would not agree,  what would happenthen ?  He was assuming that Hungary would not willingly agree to a protectorate and that it would have to be imposed on her by force.    M. Beck said  that if Hungary  found herself in  that position, and if  sheshowed a disposition to defend herself, he himself thought that  Poland would support her.    The Prime Minister said he assumed that in that event France would have notreaty obligation to come to Poland&apos;s assistance.    M. Beck agreed that  this was so.    He observed that it was against  the tradition of  the Polish Government toexpress definite opinions about third countries without directly consulting  them.He would place  himself in a difficult position by  expressing a definite opinionon the Hungarian  point which the Prime Minister had  raised. He  could, how-ever, say that Poland was keenly interested in Hungarian independence.  So longas Hungary maintained that independence, he thought that this should be takeninto consideration  in any plan that might be adopted, and that every effort shouldbe made to help to preserve Hungarian independence.     The Prime Minister said he did not wish to press  M. Beck  on this point; buthe had some  reason  to suppose that some such plan was under consideration insome quarters in Germany. He had not asked M. Beck to pledge himself, but had wished to know his attitude.  He thought it important that this issue shouldbe considered.     M. Beck said that his own view was  that it was quite likely that Germany&apos;economic ambitions in those regions might be far-reaching.  On the other hand,he did not think that there was any serious danger of  German political  actionoutside Germany&apos;s present frontiers.  The position of Slovakia was interestingfrom this point of  view.  In Slovakia German action had been extremely cautiousand hesitating.  For the present he did not think there was danger of  politicalaction, though economic pressure was likely.     The Prime  Minister  remarked that  one might very well  lead to the  other.     M. Beck said  that if Roumania were subjected to economic pressure and ifRoumania  resisted, then he thought Roumania should be given every assistancein maintaining that resistance.  Poland  was ready to do what she could to help from the military point  of view.  If there was strong  economic pressure upon
Roumania without a military threat, other countries ought to help  Roumaniaeconomically, while Poland could help by sending officers and helping  to developRoumania&apos;s military organisation.    Eastern  Europe had recently gone through a  period  of fear  psychosis.Poland was the first country to react, and  was ready to help any country which followed her example.  For instance, Poland had given assistance to Lithuaniain the  economic sphere by facilitating transit.    The Prime Minister asked how far Poland had been dependent upon Czecho-Slovakia for munitions.    M. Beck said not at all.   Poland was largely self-supporting in this respect,and supplied 80 per cent, of the needs of her army.  She also exported arms, andeven supplied guns to Great  Britain.  Poland  manufactured fighter aircraft,aircraft engines,  air frames,  light artillery and infantry equipment.  She had ordered naval artillery in Sweden and other types of artillery in France.    The Prime Minister  asked whether M. Beck anticipated any attack uponYugoslavia.    M. Beck said Poland had no agreement with Yugoslavia, but maintainedclose relations.  He had been  somewhat  surprised when the  Prime Minister had first mentioned Yugoslavia as one of the countries which might be brought intothe proposed system.  Yugoslavia was only interested in two countries, namely,Germany and Italy.  Yugoslavia was a country which caused a certain complica-tion in the relations  between Germany and Italy.   Recent  news about Albaniahad rather taken him aback.   He had known M. Stoyadinovitch, who had kepthim well informed.  M. Stoyadinovitch&apos;s policy was to avoid wide engagementsand to concentrate on improving relations  with Yugoslavia^ neighbours.   Hewas not quite sure whether the present  Yugoslav Government would follow thesame policy.    His own feeling was that Yugoslavia  would try to hedge between Germanyand Italy;  while in time of peace she would probably prefer to co-operate with italy rather than Germany, in time of war she would probably choose Gei&apos;manyrather than Italy.    The Prime Minister asked why M.  Beck had been taken aback by events inAlbania.    M. Beck replied that he  had had news that morning which  seemed to showthat Italy was contemplating action in  Albania which would  have the effect ofcausing a deterioration in the relations  between  Italy and Yugoslavia.                                Communique    The Prime Minister said that no draft communique had yet been prepared.He would have  to make  a statement in the House  of Commons the following day, and he  proposed to use  for  that purpose the text of the communique andto say  that what he was reading was an agreed statement.    Count  Raczynski said that it would be desirable to introduce into the com-munique a reference to the emigration problem, particularly the Jewish problem.    Some discussion took place on this point and a provisional text was prepared.    It was then  agreed  that a draft communique should be prepared and sub-mitted to M. Beck later in the evening.                     (The meeting  adjourned at 7 P.M.)    The following is the text of the communique which was subsequently agreedupon :                                   &quot; Communique.         &quot; The conversations with M.  Beck have covered a wide field and shown    that the two Governments  are in complete agreement upon certain general    principles.         &quot; It was agreed that  the  two countries were  prepared to enter  into    an agreement of a permanent and reciprocal character to replace the present       [18942]                                                      E
.i    temporary and unilateral  assurance given by His Majesty&apos;s Government to    the Polish Government.        &apos;&apos; Pending the completion of the permanent agreement,  M. Beck gave    His Majesty&apos;s Government an assurance that the Polish Government would    consider themselves under an obligation to render assistance to His Majesty&apos;s    Government under the same conditions as those contained in  the temporary    assurance already  given by His Majesty&apos;s Government to  Poland.        &quot; Like the temporary assurance, the permanent agreement would not be    directed against any other country, but would be designed to assure Great    Britain and Poland of mutual assistance in the event of any threat, direct or    indirect, to the independence of either.        &quot; It was recognised  that  certain matters, including a  more precise    definition of the various  ways in which  the necessity for such  assistance    might arise, would require further examination before the permanent agree-    ment could be completed.        &quot; It was understood that the arrangements above mentioned should not    preclude either Government from making agreements with  other countries in    the general interest of the consolidation of peace.&quot;    A separate communique on the question of emigration of Jews from poland was issued on the 6th April in the following terms :         &apos;&apos; In the course of the recent conversations in London M. Beck expressed    the desire that any international effort for the treatment of the Jewish    problem should be  extended to that of the Jews in Poland, and that Jewish    emigrants from Poland should have their due share in any opportunity of    settlement which may be found.  M. Beck at the same time,  at the request    of  the  Roumanian  Government,  drew attention to the  similar problem    existing in Roumania.        &quot; M. Beck was assured that His Majesty&apos;s Government fully appreciated    the difficulties to which he had referred, and would at any time be ready to    examine with  the  Polish  and Roumanian Governments  proposals for  a    solution of the particular problems arising in Poland and Roumania which    are part of a larger problem.&quot;
FOURTH  MEETING..,.. AT  a meeting in the  Secretary of  State&apos;s room  on the evening  of  the6th April the following confidential summary of the conclusions of the conversa-tions was drawn up and approved by the Secretary of State and M. Beck.  the text was checked and initialled  as correct  by the Polish  Ambassador andSir A. Cadogan on the following day.                         SUMMARY  OF  CONCLUSIONS.    1.  As a result of the conversations held in London on the 4th-6th April,1939,  between  the Polish  Foreign Minister on the  one side and  the  PrimeMinister and the  Secretary of State for  Foreign Affairs  on the other, the PolishGovernment and His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom record thefollowing conclusions :                                      I.    2.  The Polish Government and His Majesty&apos;s Government  in the UnitedKingdom have  decided to  place their collaboration on a permanent basis by theexchange of reciprocal assurances of assistance.  They are accordingly preparedto enter into a  formal agreement on the  following basis :      (a) If Germany attacks Poland His  Majesty&apos;s Government  in the United          Kingdom will at once come to the help of  Poland.    (5) If Germany  attempts  to  undermine  the  independence  of  Poland  by          processes of economic penetration or in-any other way, His Majesty&apos;s          Government in the United Kingdom will support Poland in resistance          to such attempts. If Germany then attacks  Poland,  the provisions          of paragraph (a) above will  apply.  In the event of  other action by          Germany which clearly threatened Polish independence, and was of          such a nature that the Polish Government considered it vital to resist          it with their national forces, His Majesty&apos;s Government would at once          come to the help of Poland.    (c) Reciprocally,  Poland  gives  corresponding  assurances  to the  United          Kingdom.    (d) It is understood that the Polish Government  and His Majesty&apos;s Govern-          ment in the United Kingdom will keep each other fully and promptly          informed of any developments threatening the independence of either          country.    3.  As an  earnest of their  intention to  enter into a formal agreement torender assistance  to  Poland  in  the circumstances  contemplated above,  HisMajesty&apos;s Government  in the United Kingdom have informed the Polish Govern -ment, and have  stated publicly, that during the period required for the conclusionof the formal agreement  outlined in paragraph 2  above, in  the event of  any action which clearly  threatened Polish  independence,  and  which  the  PolishGovernment accordingly considered it vital to resist with their national forces,His Majesty&apos;s Government would feel themselves bound at once to lend the PolishGovernment all the support in their power.    4.  The Polish Government, for their part, give His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the  United Kingdom a reciprocal  undertaking to the  same effect, which is, inthe same way as  the undertaking  given by His Majesty&apos;s Government,  already in force and will  remain in force during the period required for the conclusionof the  formal agreement outlined in paragraph  2 above.                                    II.    5.  The following points remain to be settled  before the  formal agreement can be concluded :     (a) His Majesty&apos;s Government  desire that the  formal agreement  should          provide that if the United Kingdom and France went to war with          Germany to resist German aggression in Western Europe (the Nether-          lands,  Belgium, Switzerland, Denmark), Poland would come  to their
          help.  (M. Beck appreciated the vital importance of this question for          the  United Kingdom,  and undertook  that  the  Polish Government          would take it into serious consideration.)    (6)  The obligations which His Majesty&apos;s Government have accepted towards          Pola,nd during the period necessary for the conclusion  of the formal          agreement have also been accepted by France.  It is understood that          the  obligations to be accepted by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the          formal agreement  itself  should  also be accepted by  France;  the          method of arranging this would be a matter for discussion with the          French Government.                                    III.    6.  His Majesty&apos;s Government wished it to be part of the formal agreement that Poland should come to the help of  Roumania if the latter were  the Statethreatened.  The Polish Government, while respecting to the full the obligations of mutual assistance which  exist between  Poland and Roumania, thought itpremature to express a definite opinion as to the desirability of including the caseof Roumania in the formal agreement.  They consider that  they should treat thematter  in  the  first instance  direct  with the  Roumanian and  HungarianGovernments.   They will, in  the meanwhile,  immediately consult with HisMajesty&apos;s Government should developments in relation to Roumania or Hungaryrender this desirable.                                    IV.    7.  It  is  understood between the Polish  Government  and His Majesty&apos;sGovernment that the conclusions recorded above do not preclude either Govern-ment  from making further agreements with other countries for the purpose of safeguarding their own independence or that of other States.    8.  It is the intention of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United kingdom for their part     (a)  To continue the exchanges of views which they have already  initiated with          the  Roumanian Government, with the object of  developing collabora-          tion between the United Kingdom, Roumania and other Powers, for          the purposes set forth above.    (6)  To initiate exchanges of views for a similar purpose with the Govern-          ments of  the other members of the Balkan Entente.    9.  His Majesty&apos;s Government,  while realising the difficulties standing inthe way of associating the Soviet Government with  action such as is contemplatedabove, are further persuaded of the importance of maintaining the best possiblerelations with the Soviet Government, whose position in this matter could not be  -disregarded.    10.   The   Polish Government for  their  part  declare that, should HisMajesty&apos;s Government in  the  United Kingdom assume further obligations in eastern  Europe,  these obligations  would  in no way extend  the obligationsundertaken by Poland.    11.   The Polish Government emphasise the importance, in the considerationof any attempt to develop collaboration, of taking into account the position of theEastern Baltic States.April 7, 1939.

</content>
</cab>
