<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/285/0 images: 113-118</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMiNT IS THE PRGIiiPtTY CS - HIS BRITANNIC                IAA JES TY&apos; S GOYLRKLiiNT) .                                         COirY MO.SECRET.   CP. No. 37/39.                              C  A B I K ft T.                                  INDIA.     Appreciation  of  the  Political Situation, bythe Government  of  India,  dated 14th April, 1939.     Circulated for the  information of the Cabinetby the Secretary of State for India.
11Confidential appreciation of the Political situationin India, dated the 14th April,  1939,  issued on the   authority of the Secretary of State for India.   The Rajkot dispute.  The Chief justice of India onApril 3rd pronounced an award which accepted theconstruction placed by Messrs. Gandhi and VallabhaiFat el on the Ruler &apos;.s undertaking, as against the latter 1 claim that he reserved discretion to reject nominationsmade by Vallabhai I-atel to the reforms committee.  thus it is for Vallabhai Patel to nominate&apos;seven members whowill automatically be appointed by the Ruler;  and the ruler will in addition appoint three official members:the Chairman is to be appointed by the Ruler from this body of ten.  Messrs. Gandhi and Patel have now returnedto Rajkot, and appear to be in difficulties as to themanner in which the award shall be implemented.  the ruler, not unnaturally, regards it as a final decisionsMr. Gandhi, having given hopes of representation on thecommittee to various sections (including Muslims), wouldlike the number of members to be increased so as tosatisfy those hopes while still ensuring a majority forthe local Congress party.     Meanwhile Mr.Gandhi has discouraged a renewal ofagitation in other States where it was threatened -- forinstance Jaipur and Travancore.  This respite may prove to be brief, as he claims to be thinking out &quot; a neworientation of civil disobedience&quot;, to be launched after.a period of quiet in which Princes and people alike mayhave leisure to consider their position.     2-   The Congress Party -   Mr. Gandhi and the    - :Congress President have been unable to agree on the personnel of the new Working Committee, and the partyfor the time being lacks both harmony and central direction.A meeting of the All-India Committee has been announced
for the end. of this month:  the President will derivesome advantage from this being held at Calcutta wherehis influence is strongest; but it appears doubtfulwhether he can keep the party together except by allowing the previous leaders to return to power.     3.  The Muslim League is watchful of political pressure on the Rulers of the States.  The Council,meeting at Delhi, deplored Gandhi&apos;s fast and described the Viceroy&apos;s intervention as a dangerous precedent.It vigorously denounced the Hindu campaign against theNizam&apos;s administration, and complained that the paramount Power had failed to step the organisationof that campaign in British India.  The League stillseeks to devise a Federal scheme which shall be morefavourable to Muslim interests than the schemeembodied in the Constitution Act;  various plans havebeen put forward but all seem likely to create moredifficulties than they would solve, and the committeenow appointed to examine the question may net find iteasy to produce a solution.     While failing to compose differences in the ranks of its own community (for instance in Sind, where theMuslims if united could rule the Province; or inLucknow, where the Madhe Sahaba dispute between Sunnisand Shias continues as a serious threat to public ordethe League under Mr. Jinnah&apos;s leadership showsincreasing suspicion of everyone outside the community in the Central Legislature the League party, whilepermitted individual expression of opinion in the debate on the Finance Bill, was required to take no part in divisions - the ground given&apos; by Mr. Jinnahbeing that for reasons wholly unconnected with thebusiness in hand the party would support neither theGovernment against the Congress nor Congress against
Government.  As a result the Bill had to be certified by the Governor-Generalthough there was no reason to suppose that this would have been necessary if theparty had determined its line of action on the merits;and the same attitude resulted in the defeat of the motion for approval of the Indc-British trade agreement which had been welcomed by so staunch a champion ofagricultural interests as the i-unjab Premier.     4.  Occasions for communal trouble have diminishedsince the religious celebrations mentioned in the lastAppreciation, but there is still ample evidence of widespread bitterness.   In Borar a prominentCongressman has been murdered in broad daylight by amob Of Muslims: a-punitive police force is to be postedat the place for one year at the cost of the localMuslims.  Sporadic disorder has continued in the united provinces also, at Allahabad and Benares.  Ministriesdominated by Hindus are severely handicapped in handling the communal problem.  Their followers are apt to.aggravate grievances by partisan behaviour;  andresolute action in the interest of public order is easilyrepresented as atrocious repression of a minority.     5.   The Provincial Legislatures have been busywith measures imposing additional taxation.  A tax onthe sale of motor spirit has boon generally adopted;new taxes on the sales of other commodities are proposed in some Provinces.  It is natural that increased taxation should arouse protest, especiallywhere it is required to make good the losses caused bythe extension of prohibition.     6.  In. Sind two Hindu Ministers resigned towardsthe end of March but were r.eappointed a few days later.Their resignation was a by-product of a curiousexhibition of hysteria in the local Hindu community;
scandal had been aroused by the doings of a sectknown as Om Mandli, and the popular demand for actionagainst this Agapemone was pressing enough to causeinconvenience to the Ministry.  However, a settlementhas been made which for the moment appears to satisfyoutraged morality and to restore Ministerialequilibrium. .     7-  The Central Legislature -  Five amendments tothe Finance Bill were carried against Government inthe Assembly.  Two related to sup^rr-tax, others reduced the rate cf salt duty and the rates for post-cards,and one omitted the provision for doubling the rate of import duty on raw cotton.  The loss of revenueinvolved was more than Rs.2-f- crores.  The recommendationof the Governor-General to pass the Bill in practicallyits original form was rejected;  the Bill was then&quot;certified&quot; by the Governor-General, and passed by theCouncil of State.     The attitude of the Muslim League which prevented the passing of this Bill and procured the defeat of the motion regarding the India-British trade agreement hasbeen mentioned above.     8.   Waziristan.  Troops operated in the ShaktuValley during March.  There was much sniping, but theonly serious encounter with hostile tribesmen tookplace on March the 16th when our casualties were 11killed,  including one British Officer, and 14 wounded.The enemy are believed to have lost about 20 killed.-Sniping and other offences continue In North waziristan.As a result of the air operations against the Madda Khelthe whole tribe are now suing for peace.  The Faqir ofIpi is still at Inzarwari just across the AfghanFrontier.  South Waziristan has been quiet.  There hasbeen some serious raiding in the settled districts. On
the&quot;&apos; night of March  the  9th  in a raid  on a village in theDera Ismail Khan  district five Hindus were kidnapped andthe village headman had his nose cut  off.   Another raidwhich took place  near Tajcri in the Eannu district onApril 1st resulted  in the kidnapping  of five more Hindus.In  a raid on Kahiri in  the  Dera Ismail Khan district onthe night of April  3rd  four Hindus were killed and 10We undo d.        :&apos;::    :   ai;::&amp; -         &quot;&apos;&apos;e  U

</content>
</cab>
