<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/285/0 images: 264-268</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
         (THIS  DOCUMENT ..2^^^^^^^^Ji.:M..R.JL^-0^       HIS_BE I T A N N I 0  M A J E S T Y &apos;  S  GOVERNMENT).E C R E T.P-.100( 59).                                          COPY NO.    ^_                                CABINET,                                  PALESTINE.                          DRAFT STATEMENT ON POLICY.                    Memqr anavrm by.., t he Ji^isjje^^f^^ealjh.            1.    The pressure of events is so great$  and the papers       coming before us so numerous9 that it may be of assistance to       some of my colleagues if I set out some points on the situation       which we are about to consider9  presented admittedly from the       point of view of one who does not bear departmental responsibility       for  the matters at issue.            2.    The Secretary of State for the Colonies undertook last       summerj  at the request of the cabinet an attempt to find a       solution to the Palestine problem by conference, a conference       between His Majesty&apos;s Government, and the representatives of       Arabs and Jews with9 in addition., representatives of neighbouring       Arab States.    This endeavour9 although conducted with infinite       patience did not succeed.    Vfe are9 therefore., in face of a new       situation.   As all the proposals arising out  of the Conference       have been rejected., not merely by Pal osi-inie^  Arabs and Jews9       but  by the neighbouring Arab States3 we have for the moment a       considerable freedom of decision.   I submit that we should take       stock of the situation anew and not merely on the basis of the       proposals as they have recently developed.   We should indeed       consider both the nature of our unilateral statement and its       timing very carefully.            3.    This is all the more npoessary since9 as the Colonial       Secretary himself has pointed out9 our recent proposed solutions       were admittedly unsatisfactory in important respects9 both to
ourselves and to our advisers on the spot.    The fundamentalpoint is that they embody concessions made after a terroristcampaign aimed not only at the Jews but at British officials,and at a large section of the Palestinian Arabs.   This campaignhas been directed from outside the borders of Palestine by the mufti, admittedly with support from the Axis Powers.    I suggestthat today, when we are taking up in general a position of resistance to aggression, and aggression conducted for the mostpart precisely by this techniques we should be very chary of accepting a policy supported by such means in so very important and sensitive a part of the world as the Near East.     4.   A major object of our policy is to secure the supportof the Moslem world.    This object is of the greatest importanceto the British Empire, and one which it is worth while doingalmost everything to secure.    But it has become clear that the moslem world is much more influenced by the evidence of strengthand vigour than by anything else, and it seems indisputable that whatever else our proposals,  admittedly conceding much to the mufti and his supporters, represent, they will tend to be takenin present circumstances as. a concession not from strength but from weakness.     5.   A striking and rather disquieting sign of this weaknessis that, though the future exclusion of the Mufti from Palestine,with the object of making it clear to his followers that he hasnot prevailed, is regarded as fundamental by both the militaryand the civil heads in Palestine, we have not ventured to broachthis point to the Arab States.    We are warned, indeed, by theColonial Secretary that when this decision is disclosed it maylead to failure to obtain even a declaration of general approvalfrom, the Arab^States-for&apos; the-solution embodying the extensiveconcessions which arc suggested.
     6.   In fact in these negotiations, &quot;we do not both mean the same thing.&quot;   The Mufti&apos;s movement aims at an Arab State -an Arab State which will owe much to Germany and Italy, whohelped it into existence;, - and regards the present concessionsas merely steps on the way.   We mean a Palestine in which british movement and action will continue to be largelyunfettered.    We have not yet resolved this divergence and theproposed statement of policy does not resolve it.    It ispossible that the statement will greatly limit our freedom ofaction when made, and it seems probable that unless implemented in the sense which we do not desire9 it will not bring therelief which we hope fore     7.   The present situation is very different from that inwhich we previously considered this problem.   For instance,  twoevents of the highest importance have occurred in the Near Eastso recently that-we cannot yet appreciate their full weight.One is the destruction of Albania, a Moslem Kingdom, by Italy.and the consequent state of extreme tension throughout theEastern Mediterranean.   The other is the new close grouping ofGreat Britain and Turkey.   The latter is specially noteworthyin view of its possible general repercussions.   As far as theIndian Moslems are concerned, Turkey still represents, if not aMoslem Power, certainly an Asiatic Power, and her association with Great Britain conteracts the dangerous impression thatGreat Britain&apos;s actions in Palestine are simply aggression byEuropeans against Asiatics.  ^It is worth while remembering that turkey never mentioned concessions to the Palestine Arabs as one of her desires.&quot;)necessary is the continuing presence of British forces both military and naval in Palestine.   The suggestion in the present proposals is that we should be able to secure this in the futureThese two events have demonstrated once again how
by virtue  of a unilateral declaration regularised at some future date by a  Treaty.  There is a grave danger lest in restingourselves  on this unilateral declaration we weaken the basis onwhich we now rely to justify our presence in Palestine - thebasis of a mandate assented to by a number of nations includingthe previous soverign ruler of these territories, and theUnited States of&apos; America a  The awkward position in which we might find ourselves is  shown by the difficulty of stressing our strategic  interests in our proposed re-statement of the position.and the anxiety  of the Defence Ministries lest this point is too much glossed over.     9.    These  arguments seem to me to justify the revision ofour aims and the postponement of our statement .  I have not sofar mentioned the Jewish position, but that seems to me to reinforce  further the contentions I have tried to set out.  Itis not necessary to reiterate the arguments in this respect.Even without the possibility of the immense damage to ourposition both at home and abroad which would result if GreatBritain found herself involved in hostilities great or small, against the Jews at this time, our own British interests wouldnot be served by binding ourselves, by our own word, to theacceptance of so much of the Mufti1s terms.  We have however been warned by the Colonial Secretary that the possibility ofthis clash is implicit in these terms, and he used the very strong words &quot;physical violence which we should have to putdown by force.&quot;  If such a clash occurred, it is difficult tosee how we could press our policy forward by force over a longtime against the Jews, circumstances being what they are, and if for any reason Jewish resistance did not subside we should be faced with either modifying our policy again, or with deadlock.
       10.    I,  therefore,  suggest that  we  should  declare  that  it  is   not possible  at this time to proceed  further with  the   consideration of far-reaching constitutional changes, that we   should strengthen .our forces in this  region, by advancing in   date such measures  as we should have  in  any case to take if  the   Italian pressure continues to develop, and that we should mean-   while work in practice towards a federal solution, the   essential features  of which must be the  segregation so  far as   possible of Jews and Arabs;  and that we should neither take   nor  announce any steps which would lead to an  administrative   position in which either of these races  would have to be governed   by the other.                             (Intld.)   V.E.E.Ministry of Health,Whitehall, S.W.I.28th April, 1939.

</content>
</cab>
