<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/3/39 images: 634-643</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
*2 . L-. 313pPfiTFMSNT IS ^ro^IjOFIiRTY^OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government copy NO. i)lW A R      C A P I IE TOIL POSITION,Fifteenth Weekly Report suhmitted hy the Secretary for mines covering the period up to midnight on the17th December, 1939.      (Previous Report:    Paper W.P.(R.)(39) 115)Richmond TerraceQ   W       1(initialled)&apos; C 1.19th December, 1939.

^. U. 310QfiTTMBNT IS THE PROPERTY OP PUS BRITANNIC MAJESTY &apos;5 GOVERNMENT.COPY NO. i)lWAR     GAB I W. B TOIL POSITION.Fifteenth Weekly Report submitted by the Secretary for mines covering the period up to midnight on the17th December, 1939.      (Previous Report:    Paper W.P.(R.)(39) 115)(Initialled)&apos; G8 L.R i chm ond T e r r a c e,O a IV a    J- *19th December, 1939.

9 A iij x ^Midnirht, 17th Docoiaher ^ ,19,39.FIFTEENTH WEEKLY REPORT ON OIL POSITION IN UNITED KINGDOI.1.Stocks.31stI Au;^0  1959,i    30th&apos;Nov. 1939.7thDec. &apos;1(llpbhDec. 1939.RAMYi&amp;tion Spirittor Spiritel and. Diesel Oilbricating OilOFFICEtor Spiritescl Oilbricating OilMINISTRYiation Spiritbricating Oil9003003,050,0005,500144,9005,0003,200476,ooo17,LOOTONS1,39023012,616,00057* 150128,2104,7202,080446,00028,0001,3602002,622,0005,050126,8004,6301,950hi 1.8,00027,0001,5403752,615,0005,000126,5004,5401,500445,00031,000Civil.tor andther Spiritrosenes, Diesel andUfil Oilsoricating Oilsme and access Oils31stAuk. 1939Tons1,051,0002L1,000983,000255,000L33,0001    30 thJNov.  1959!1    T ons957,000219,0009C8,000158,000216,0001      7thDec.  1939Tonsi   953,000!1  239,00014th Dec. 1939&apos;  Weeksx ons960,000276,000888,000     i 870,000!Availahlo monthly191,000Supply H1841410 4179,000    j  Included!    a 0 o veh Based on deliveries during previous four weeks.Based on stocks on 30th November.

9, A ^To^t week seventeen tankers arrived.    Arrivals for each of the    &quot;Jthree weeks compared with the weekly average for the threemonths and for September, October and November were asrollowslastCoastWestCoastAveragefor June- August1630Average for 4 weeks ended: ,50th Sept. j 28th Oct51-7-i137*olWeeklyI   95th Nov. I l^bb  ryc^6-V94-167! 10! 1516Dec,11I617During the 4- weeks ended 30th September, 6 prize cargoes or part cargoes are included; during the 4 weeks ended28th October the number was 2.The tonnages of imports were:-Weekly Averap;e:June-AugustFor 4 weeks ended 30th September,v     28th October&quot;      25th NovemberTons262,200it iin    iiiiii131,00097,400166,500Week ending2nd December9th December16th December139,600146,700161,200The above figures exclude for the whole period twenty-seven tankerson Admiralty account with cargoes totalling 281,300 tons.The tanker arrivals and quantities imported, during the past three months have been as follows:-Tankers. Cargoes.TonsSeptember, 1939October.  1939November, 1939Total524960161525,700494,200657,5001,677,200Tankers arrived or expected to arrive duringthe four weeks ending 15th January. 1940,(Subject to correction.;Number of Tankers:products:Aviation Spirit?Totor and other Spirit Kerosene Lubricating oil gas, Diesel and fuel oils crude Oil65TotalTons33SS00219,40054,30052,50082,100160,4006i3 ,500 (Weekly average______ 163,100;o

9 -f $^ Jl Jf/eekly average for 1938Oil Board estimated weekly consumption weekly average:    September,1939.October,1959.November,1939.Week ending    2nd December9th December16th DecemberMotor andOther SpiritTons95,00070,000112,00052,00062,00063f00065,00060,000KeroseneTons15,00012,00016,00015,00015,30015,00015,00017,000Gas, fuel and DieselTons66,00062,00065,00050,00062,00066,00067,00078,000Home-Produced Fuel Development.An informal Committee has been set up under the chairmanship of Sir William Bragg, O.M., K.B.E., F.R.S., with the followingTerras of Reference : -&quot;To consider and review in the light of war conditions the scope for the substitution of imported fuels and torecommend what detailed inquiries should be undertaken witha view to securing the best use of home-produced fuels inwar-time&quot;.The Committee held its first meeting on Friday, 15th December and isexpected to make an early report advising the Secretary for mines in regard to this problem.pnnsumption of Petroleum PjPQducts,The following table shows consumption from civil stocks sincethe outbreak of war comparer] with the 1938 average weekly consumption and the Oil Board estimate of requirements:-


</content>
</cab>
