<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/4/0 images: 173-176</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
v      VJ Ms Doeamenfc is the Bgoiiegtj of Bis Britaaiac M^e^s GoiFegamaBL]Printed for the War Cabinet.   December 1917.SECRET. G. 178.RESTRICTION OF IMPORTS.Interim Report.Terms of Reference.1. BY Minute 11 of Meeting 266 of the 6th November, 1917, the War Cabinet appointed a Committee &quot;&apos;to consider to what extent and in what directions British imports should be further restricted, and to report their recommendations to the War Cabinet as soon as possible.&quot;The Committee was composed as follows  &apos;Lord Milner, (Chairman), Lord Rhondda, Mr. Long, Mr. Churchill, Sir Albert Stanley, Sir Joseph Maclay,Captain Clement Jones (Secretary).On the 27th November (War Cabinet 283, Minute 11) Lord Curzon undertook the Chairmanship of the Committee in the absence of Lord Milner.Tonnage Situation.2. At their first meeting the Committee had before them a Memorandum by the Ministry of Shipping (Paper G-.T. 2493) on the tonnage position in 1918.This Memorandum showed that if no extra assistance had to be given to the Allies, British imports in 1918 would be less than the imports in 1917 by some 6,000,000 tons, and that if the extra demand of the Allies for cereals amounting to over 2,000,000 tons has to fall upon British shipping, the decrease in British imports must exceed 8,000,000 tons.Before definitely accepting this deficit of 8,000,000 tons as a basis upon which to work, the Committee felt that it would be well to obtain the latest opinion and informa-tion of the Admiralty in regard to the anti-submarine campaign.Accordingly the second meeting was attended by Admiral Duff, who stated the views of the Admiralty. He said that while any statement in regard to prospective submarine losses must be purely speculative, nevertheless, in the light of their most recent information and experience, the Admiralty were of opinion that the mean of the British losses by submarine during September and October might be taken as a guide for the next six months, in other words, an average of roughly 225,000 tons a month, excluding Allied and neutral vessels and ordinary marine losses and cases of damage.After that date it was reasonable to take a more optimistic view. The conditions would probably be better rather than worse, partly on account of the assistance which would be rendered by the United States and partly on account of the results of our own extensive programme for countering submarine attack.The result of this improved estimate of the submarine situation, submitted by Admiral Duff, as compared with the first estimate with which the Committee were confronted, may be translated in terms of tonnage as roughly 2,000,000 tons.   This leaves 6,000,000 tons to be cut gff&apos; British imports during 1918. [1220]
Analysis of Imports,3. In order to arrive at our recommendations we examined seriatim a list of the various commodities imported in 1916 and 1917 with a view to seeing where any further saving could be effected. We also asked the Departments concerned to submit statements showing where reductions could be made and in each case the effect of the restrictions.Ministry of Food.4. The Ministry of Food provided us with a statement showing their minimum requirements for foodstuffs in 1918. They anticipate a net saving of 2,500,000 tons, but they point out that in order to effect this reduction they must be given absolute priority of finance and tonnage.This reduction does not involve any further restriction in the output of beer below the present level.Ministry of Munitions.5. The Ministry ol Munitions anticipated a possible reduction of 1,550,000 tons in .1918. They state, however, that this cut, involving as it does a reduction of 500,000 tons of shell steel from America^ will seriously affect the munition programme.Paper and Paper-Making Materials.6. We have been in communication with the Paper Commission in regard to the results of further reductions of different dimensions. They have replied in the following sense: &quot; All users are now very short.&quot; A reduction of 100,000 tons, in addition to causing considerable scarcity for trade purposes, would necessitate cutting down newspapers, magazines, &amp;c, by one quarter.&quot; A reduction of 150,000 tons would seriously inconvenience commercial users and require the cutting down of newspapers, magazines, &amp;c, by one-third.&quot; A reduction of 200,000 tons would cause grave dislocation of trade and entail the suppression of many newspapers and periodicals.&quot;. In the light of this information, and having regard to the drastic restrictions of other commodities which we are suggesting, we recommend that the importation of paper and paper-making materials be reduced by 100,000 tons below the 1917 level, and we hope that the War Cabinet will consider a still further reduction.Timber.. 7. The Board of Trade have informed us that the importation of timber, already considerably cut down, could be further reduced in 1918 by 1,000,000 tons.They say, however, that this additional reduction can only be realised provided that the Minister of National Service maintains the necessary supply of labour required by the Timber Controller, and that no further demands are made to release men for the Army.We therefore recommend the War Cabinet to instruct the Minister of National Service to this effect.Wool.8. We recommend that wool imports in 1918 be reduced by 50,000 tons. We understand that there are now in the country six months&apos; stock, or 170,000 tons, including the British clip.We suggest in this connection (a.) That attention should be paid by the Departments concerned to the collectionand utilisation of old clothing, (o.) That shipments of wool should be made as far as possible from the Argentinerather than Australia.Oil-seed Gake.9. We recommend that imports of oil-seed cake be reduced in 1918 by 200,000 tons.
The Ministry of Food state that in the past oil-seed cake has been shipped in empty space which would otherwise have been wasted, but they raise. no objection to the reduction proposed provided that the space is used to better advantage.Stone and Slates.10. AVe recommend that the importation of stones and slates be reduced in 1918 by 100,000 tons.Iron Ore (through reduction of iron and steel exports).11. A further reduction of 200,000 tons is recommended.Miscellaneous. f12. The Board of Trade anticipate a reduction under this heading of 100,000 tons.Tobacco.13. We are advised that the tobacco position is serious. We recommend that next year 30,00.) tons representing the amount required for the troops should be imported, and that tonnage should be allocated for this purpose; but that the civilian consumption which should be met out of stocks in the country should be reduced by a cut of 25 per cent.If this plan is carried out, there will, we are informed, still be remaining, on the 1st January, 1919, six months&apos; stock.Cotton.14. We had hoped that it might have been possible to recommend some reduction in cotton imports. An investigation of the situation has, however, led us to the opposite conclusion, and we are forced, to recommend an increase of the import of cotton by 50,000 tons in 1918.This will be necessary in order to maintain the cotton industry on the present 60 per cent, basis.Phosphates.15. In view of the War Cabinet&apos;s decision that 50,000 tons per month are to be imported for the agricultural programme, the Committee find that instead of a reduction in 1918 there will be an increase of at least 200,000 tons.Finance.16. In the course of our work we were informed that, serious as is the shipping situation at the present time, the financial difficulties are no less great.The view was expressed that in the United States of America finance is the limiting factor, and that before long, owing to financial difficulties, there will be ships waiting in American harbours for their cargoes.&apos; It was also pointed out that one of the few tonnage economies that is still possible.is the diversion of tonnage from distant routes into the Atlantic.The Treasury was not represented on our Committee, and therefore we have been unable to find out how far, and where, the financial difficulties exist and may be over-come, but we are of opinion that the matter should be thoroughly investigated.Summary of Recommendations. 17. To summarise : 
The Committee were confronted at their first meeting by an estimateshowing a reduction in imports in 1918 of ... This reduction may be effected in the following way : Tous.By estimated improvement in the submarine situa-tion    ... ... ...,, reduction of imports of Ministry of Munitions ... Ministry of Food ... paper and pulp   ... ... ...timber (including pit-props) wooloil-seed cake      ... ...stones and slates ... ...iron ore (through reduction of iron and ste*elexports) miscellaneousincreased imports of cotton... ,, phosphatesBalanceTons.Tods.2,000,000 1,550,000 2,500,000 100,000 1,000,000 50,000 200,000 100,000200,000 100,0007,800,00050,000 ) 25Q 00Q 200,000 j    ^VVW8,000,0007,550,000 450,000A deficit of 450,000 tons, therefore, still remains to be wiped off before the estimated supply of, and demands upon, tonnage for our imports in 1918 can be exactly balanced.Remaining Deficit.18. We understand that the whole Allied tonnage situation is now under review at the Paris Conference, and it may well be that the conclusions of that Conference will affect still further the problem of restricting imports.We therefore do not propose at the moment to finish our investigations as to the possibility of removing the remaining deficit. We shall, however, be glad to resume our meetings, if it is considered desirable, and examine the subject again after the Paris Conference is over.The Imports of the Allies.19. We are well aware that the recommendations which we are now submitting will, if carried into effect, not only cause grave dislocation to vcertain trades, but also involve great hardships and drastic changes in the life of the people. We believe that these burdens will be cheerfully borne, provided that some assurance can be given that our Allies are making equal sacrifices. At present we have only too much evidence that this is not always the case.We therefore recommend that His Majesty&apos;s Government should take such steps as may be necessary to ensure equality, of treatment for this country and our Allies in these matters of economy and restriction of imports.CURZON OF KEDLESTON, Chairman.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., December 1, 1917.o

</content>
</cab>
