<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/4/0 images: 393-396</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
---Gaptain Gkment Jones[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majestys Government.]Printed for the War Cabinet.   March 1918.SECRET.G.-198. jg&quot;    iy218WAR CABINET.PROPOSED SCHEME OF STATE  REQUISITION OF EGYPTIANCOTTON CROPS.Interim Report No. 11 of a Committee appointed to Consider ihe Question of anEconomic Offensive.[Previous Papers Nos. G.-156, G.-158, G.-159, G.-160, G.-161, G.-166, G.-167r G.-168, G.-170, G.-175, G.-177, G.-183, G.-187, G.-190, G.-196, and G.-197, and War Cabinet 247 (8), 265 (18) and (19), 273 (16), 283 (17), 312 (6) and (7), 329 (4), 351 (8), 355 (14), and 357 (8).]1. THE Committee has considered the two telegrams of the 24th instant from Sir H. Llewellyn Smith to Sir Albert Stanley upon the above matter (Appendix).2. The Committee approve the recommendations as amended in the second of these telegrams, and in view of the great importance of announcing the adoption of the scheme before the end of March, and of the shortness of the time available for setting up the necessary organisation, they desire to impress upon the War Cabinet the urgency of coming to a favourable decision at once.3. It is suggested that in case of a very abnormal rise or fall of American prices, there will, of course, be power of revision, but there would be no periodical alteration at fixed dates.(Signed)        GEORGE N. BARNES.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W., February 28,1918.[287]
APPENDIX.M.M.137 -Egyptian Cotton. Telegrams from Sir H. Llewellyn Smith, dated February 24, 1918.No. 1.(No. 372.)   R.FOLLOWING from Sir H. L. Smith for Sir A. Stanley :-&quot;We are now in a position to recommend a scheme to safeguard position with regard to Egyptian cotton.&quot; We have consulted High Commissioner, Acting Financial Adviser, and other officials, and have had prolonged conferences with representatives of English export and bank houses at Alexandria, including Carver, Birley, and Hornsby, of National Bank. We have also discussed matter in more general and guarded terms with Prime Minister.&quot;Everything points to 1917-18 crop amounting at least to 850,000 to 900,000 bales, and reduction of acreage under cotton next season will not probably exceed 10 per cent, owing to special concessions which we find have been made to cultivators in various districts. While these figures are less disquieting than we expected, we do not think situation can be allowed to&apos;drift. Shortage of shipping is stopping purchases of cotton, and Alexandria prices are gradually falling. Holders of unsold residue of present crop are mostly large growers who can continue to hold until next summer, and some are speculating on chance of end of war bringing them rich harvest of profit. On the other hand, small growers will find themselves in a very difficult position next autumn if present shipping shortage continues, unless they are assured of a market at a fair price.&quot; We therefore think a control scheme is urgently necessary in order both to achieve above result and also to secure that crops shall be available for remainder of war and during reconstruction period to British, Allied, and neutral consumers at reasonable prices and in fair proportions. Obviously mere purchase of residue of present crop would not achieve this object and we have not been able to discover any means of doing so without acquiring further crops.&quot; Experts have convinced us a mere proclamation fixing prices of cotton would be nugatory owing to infinite possibilities of evasion by varying classification. Moreover, it is politically undesirable to limit price obtained by grower without guaranteeing him a market at price fixed. We therefore conclude a comprehensive scheme should be introduced at once. Purchasing operations should not commence until 1st August in order not to interfere with existing contracts, which are limited to current crop, but in order to prevent further commitments it is necessary to announce scheme as soon as possible, and in any case before the end of March, and all intervening time will be required to perfect organisation.&quot; Following are heads of proposed scheme : &quot;Announcement to be made forthwith of appointment of Cotton Control Commission consisting of official controller, independent of trade, with two or three expert and thoroughly trustworthy colleagues, assisted by a larger Advisory Board representing export firms, banks, and native growers. Commission will be prepared as from 1st August, 1918, to buy any cotton, whether the residue of 1917 crop or produce of following crops, which may be tendered to them on terms specified in -j announcement. There will be no direct compulsion on growers to sell at this price, but no further export licences will be granted except for cotton purchased by commission, and all licences already granted will be cancelled as from 1st August, except those that have already been used to purchase cotton for export. Official announcement will not only specify basic price at which commission will buy at Alexandria, but also that at , which they will sell f.o.b., margin being calculated to cover pressing, handling, fire i insurance, warehousing, export duty, interest on capital, and all other charges and administrative expenses. Whole [? machinery] of management of business will be carried on through the organisations of existing export houses under the control of the commission. All cotton will be graded by commission into a limited number of types. Overseas buyers will continue to correspond with export houses with which they have
obeen accustomed to deal, who will pass [? their] orders to Controller. Controller will be only member of commission who will know destinations of individual orders. He will consolidate all orders for particular types of cotton and place them en bloc before commission to deal with from time to time. This arrangement seems necessary to avoid suspicion by any trader being able to utilise information to his personal advantage. We propose funds necessary for carrying out scheme shall be provided roughly in equal proportions by banking and other houses who have hitherto financed crop, and by His Majesty&apos;s Treasury, up to a limit of 10,000,0001. in both cases. Treasury advance will be made by an instruction given to National Bank of Egypt to issue bank-notes against cash paid by Treasury in London, notes being issued at rate of 97-g- pesetas to the pound. We are advised that 20,000,0001. ought to be ample to finance whole operation contemplated. We are stili discussing precise conditions of co-operation of banks, but our present provisional idea is that 5 per cent, on banks&apos; advances should be guaranteed by Treasury, and that banks should receive another 1 per cent, if earned. We have assumed our Treasury authorisation empowers us to pledge them to contribute up to 10,000,000L to fruit, and we should be glad to know by telegraph what interest they would expect on such contribution. We do not think there is any appreciable prospect of a loss to Treasury on scheme, and we propose any balance profit should be allocated to schemes for improving and developing cotton cultivation in Egypt;. Basic prices for standard quality, both for purchase and selling, will be fixed and announced officially at outset and not left to discretion of commission. Commission will at once prepare, in consultation with board, and also with Lancashire spinners, schedule of purchase and sale prices of each type of cotton corresponding to official basic prices, and will prepare sets of samples of types to be sent to all the chief consuming countries. I am sending separate telegram on the subject of our actual proposals for basic prices. It may be necessary to reserve power to limit purchases in the event of exhaustion of warehouse accommodation.&quot; High Commissioner, Acting Financial Adviser, and English export houses whom we have [? consulted] confidentially, are prepared to support and co-operate in working a scheme on above lines, assuming that complete control of cotton is desired as a matter of policy.&quot; Chief apprehension of traders is displacement of [? middle]men and staffs, who will to some extent, be rendered superfluous by scheme. This specially applies to operators on Alexandria Bourse, which will naturally be closed. We think commission should be empowered to deal generously with hard cases of individuals whose services cannot be utilised under scheme.&quot; It is proposed to continue above organisation during war period, and, if possible, for a limited time afterwards..&quot; Extension, however, beyond end of war would necessitate action by legislation or. decree to continue powers to regulate export now derived solely from martial law. Authorities here are fully [group undecypherable] this necessity, and we trust Foreign Office will press forward steps to remove any difficulty arising out of capitulation. As scheme is as much in interests of Allies as of Great Britain, there should be no fear of their opposition if case is based on conservation of resources.&quot; I had the advantage of discussing main outlines of scheme with General Smuts, who approved of it generally subject to satisfactory settlement of price, and urged me to telegraph home at once.&quot; I should be glad to have approval of His Majesty&apos;s Government at earliest possible moment so that actual control of organisation can be taken in hand before we leave. As it has been necessary to let some of native Ministers know in general terms kind of action contemplated, delay is dangerous, as it is impossible to guarantee continued secrecy.&quot;No. 2.(No. 373.)   R.FOLLOWING from Sir H. L. Smith for Sir A. Stanley :-&quot; My immediately preceding telegram.&quot; Contrary to view with which we set out, we propose to offer a fixed price for standard Egyptian cotton instead of a price fluctuating with American. Our expert advisers here are unanimously in favour of this course in the interests of both simplicity and stability     They consider an official price depending on American
fluctuation would be misconstrued and suspected by growers; would introduce undesirable element of uncertainty, and would encourage speculative holding in hope of a rise. They are also anxious for the same reasons that price fixed should continue in force indefinitely until further notice. There would of course be power of revision in case of unforeseen developments such as a very abnormal rise of American prices, but there would be no periodical alteration at fixed dates.&quot;It seems to us essential&apos;that any purchase price fixed in these circumstances should be substantially above the price ruling to-day, which is 39 to 39^- dollars per kantar for F. G. F. Sakel, and which, for reasons given in my immediately preceding telegram, is below recent average. Average price for past three months has been 42&quot;5, and average for past six months has been 44. We propose to fix 43, which is 10 per cent, above present level, and should be attractive to growers.&quot; After consulting Alexandrian experts we propose to fix margin for all expenses enumerated in previous telegram at 5 dollars per kantar for standard quality, making f.o.b. price 48 dollars per kantar or 2s. per lb.&quot;After making full allowance for sea carriage and insurance, this would give Lancashire Egyptian cotton at a price materially below that which it is now paying. We shall be glad to receive approval of proposal.&quot;o

</content>
</cab>
