<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/206/28 images: 343-424</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
CONFIDENTIALUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y&apos;S GOVERNMENTCOPY NO 80INATIONALISED INDUSTRIES - INVESTMENT ANDFINANCING RE VIE WNote by the Chief Secretary, TreasuryC(79) 289 July 1979CABINETThe attached report by officials is relevant to our discussion in Cabinet on thepublic expenditure survey.    The report will be considered first in theMinisterial Committee on Economic Strategy Sub-Committee on EconomicAffairs on 11 July.    I will be inviting colleagues to endorse all the options setout in Table 3.W J BTreasury Chambers9 July 1979CONFIDENTIAL
(confidential)ifNATIONALISED INDUSTRIES: INVESTMENT &amp; FINANCING REVIEW 1979Note by Officials . .1. This paper presents the annual Investment &amp; Financing Review (IFR) of the18 nationalised industries.   It provides a basis for Ministers to take decisionson the level of:a) aggregate external borrowing for the nationalised industries;b) investment by each of the industries.It takes no account of disposals which are being handled separately (see para 9 below).In some cases decisions will be subject to the outcome of reviews on certain indus-tries.2. Decisions on (a) are a necessary part of settling public expenditure planningtotals for the Public Expenditure White Paper: from 1976 onwards it has been theindustries&apos; financing figures and not their investment figures (which in aggregatesubstantially exceed the financing figures) that have contributed to public expen-diture.   Decisions on (b) each summer help the industries to plan next year&apos;sinvestment sensibly.   (This aim can, however, be frustrated if there is a problemin the Spring, as there was this year, in keeping cash limits within the totalfinancing provision in the Public Expenditure White Paper.)   The investment figuresare normally approved on the basis of 100* in Year 2 (1980/81), 85$ in Year 3 (1981/82)md 70* in Year k (1982/83).3-   The starting point for these decisions is the plans and figures submitted bythe industries in April, as revised during consultations since then between theindustries, sponsor departments and Treasury; but the figures for steel are not yetavailable and those for coal, shipbuilding and the BNOC are subject to the specialreviews for those industries now in train.   The figures are set out in Appendix Aseries of aggregated tables) and Appendix.C (which provides detailed materialindustry by industry).This year the aggregate external financing figures exceed the figures under-tying the last Public Expenditure White Paper   (Cmnd 7^39) by substantial amountsmillion in 1980/81, *350 million in 1981/82 and   25P million in 1982/83.ae main reason for these increases is a reduction in forecast internal resources of- 1 -(confidential)
(confidential) 400 million,  200 million and  450 million in the 3 years combined with increasedcapital requirements amounting to  50 million and  150 million respectively in thefirst two years.(There is a reduction of  200 million in 1982/83.)   Over the periodthere is still a progressive decline in external financing and an-improvement infinancing from internal resources from 5k% this year to 57$ in 198O/81, rising to 67%in 1983/84 (compared with a figure of only 27% in 1975/76) - but both are slower thanhad been expected.5. The fall in internal resources in 1980/81 and 1981/82 results partly from worsen-ing prospects for coal and rail.    (For steel the tables assume, in the absence of fixfinancing figures, that deterioration in internal resources cancels out the large cutsince last year in investment.)   It also results from the reduction in March in thetelecommunications financial target from 6% to 5$ real return on capital, from changesin nuclear provisions for electricity and from BNOCs reduced internal cash flow. The]increase in investment is mainly in electricity as a result of slippage and higherreal prices for power stations.Increases over Cmnd 7439 &amp; Scope of this Review6. The external financing figures include grants as well as borrowing.   In publicexpenditure terms these grants form part of sponsoring departments&apos; functionalprogrammes (where options for reductions are being considered); only the borrowingfigures are aggregated in Programme 5*   However in the case of the National Coal Boethere is much uncertainty about how the increase in their external financing require-ments will be split between borrowing and grants; the total increased bis therefore dealt with below.   On this basis the increases discussed here are theadditional bids for borrowing plus coal^ additional bid for grants.   These increaseswhich may be compared with the totals in Table 1 of Appendix A, are shown in line Cof the following table:Table 1Increases on Cmnd 7439  million at 1979 Survey prices1980/81     1981/82    1982/83 1983/8^A	Borrowing	200	100	50	50B	Grants to NCB	150	150	150	100C	TOTAL	350	250	200	150D	of which short-term borrowing &amp; leasing	-	-50	250	150*for 1983/84 (which was not covered by Cmnd 7439) the tablecompared with the figures for 1982/83 in Cmnd 7439.- 2 -shows the increases(confidential)
(confidential)Short-term borrowing and leasing are shown separately because they were not includedin the Public Expenditure planning total in Cmnd 7^39.   But it is recommended (inpara 8 below) that they should be included in future and. the rest of the paper treatsline C as the measure of the increase over the White Paper.   However, in accordancetilth Ministers&apos; instructions that options should be &quot;as wide as possible&quot;, the optionspresented below add up for the industries to considerably more than is needed toeliminate the increases; and if they were all adopted they would produce substantialcuts in the White Paper figures.the Nature of the Borrowing Figures7. The borrowing figures are of their nature extremely volatile, being as they arethe residual of much larger flows: capital requirements, approaching  5 billion, minusgrants and internal resources   together of the order of &amp;k billion. Internalresources/^areV?ne product of two further flows, revenue( 30 billion) and currentexpenditure, which are sensitive to such factors as the weather, fluctuations indemand, market share, productivity, the exchange rate and the relative movement ofpay and prices.   The pattern of borrowing also varies enormously between industries:some are heavy net borrowers, some borrow very little, others are net repayers ofdebt.   The industries have a marked tendency to under-spend (capital slippage beinga major factor here) and an overall shortfall allowance is now built into the fore-casts.   In recent years shortfall has declined to rather over  600 million. Aftera sharp reduction in the current year as a result of the Budget squeeze, the short-fall allowance is assumed to be  500 million in 1980/81, and then to fall to too million in the last 3 years of the Survey period as a result of efforts toimprove the industries&apos; forecasting in 1978/79.8. As already noted, the &quot;public expenditure planning total&quot;, on which Cmnd 7^39concentrated attention, included all the industries&apos; long and medium-term borrowingfrom whatever source including overseas borrowing but excluded their short-termborrowing and leasing.   This is not a satisfactory total for the purposes of con-trolling the industries&apos; finances since it can be evaded by switching into short-termborrowing and leasing; for this reason the cash limit is set on total external finance(capital requirements net of internal resources), which includes short-term borrowingand leasing.   The divergence between the cash limit and the public expenditure plan-ning total complicates control and it is proposed that it should be eliminated byincluding short-term borrowing and leasing in the public expenditure planning total.This will streamline the control system; it will emphasise tHe^1 contribution to thePSBR by ensuring that the whole of their contribution, including their short-termborrowing, will be within the public expenditure planning total; and it will ensure(confidential)
(confide initial)that surplus funds lent to the Government by an industry reduce public expenditurea point which will be of some importance when e.g. gas will shortly have repaid al]its NLF debt and will invest surplus funds in Government securities.   It will also,as the table in para 6 shows, raise the size of the increases compared with the WhitePaper in some years.   But these increases represent additions to the PSBR which shouldbe (and are) covered by the options presented below and it makes more sense to includethem.9. Ministers should note that the figures are going to be altered very considerablyby disposals - in some cases adversely. But it is too early to show the effects offlthis.Option Cuts10. Because the nationalised industries are businesses there are in principle 3 waysof reducing their contribution to public expenditure: cutting investment or workingcapital; and raising internal resources either by savings on current costs,especial!where this reduces losses which^general signal waste, or, where the market permits,raising prices to economic levels.11. Equally, however, the fact that they are businesses is a powerful argument for!achieving necessary public expenditure reductions by means which so far as possibledo not penalise successful industries to help weak ones and do not involve arbitrainvestment cuts which may lead to capacity shortage, or unnecessary costs, or settiKprices at excessive levels which mis-allocate resources or restrict the industries&apos;!growth.12. In practice, however, officials consider that although there are some risks,there are economically defensible options for savings that could remove the incresover the Cmnd 7^39 level and go further than that.   Each industry was asked foroptions for reducing external financing by an amount equal to 10$ of its investment!But the realism and adequacy of these varies and other options have been consideredjwhich go further, notably a phased move towards economic pricing for domestic gas(see paral6&amp; Appendix D).13. The possibilities are discussed in detail in Appendix B.   In some cases reduc-tions have already been made on the figures submitted by the industries and thesereductions have been incorporated in the baseline figures.   These reductions areshown in the following table:- k -(confidential)
(confidential)Table 2&apos;Ues Compared with the Industries&apos; Plans Reflected In the Base Line  million at 1979 Survey Prices	1980/81	1981/82	1982/83	1983/84BNOC - higher oil price assumptions	39	86	-	-British Gas - revised exchange rate	40	40		-Electricity (England &amp; Vales) -mainly resulting from higher prices	115	90	40	-British Sail - investment cuts	19	19	24	40National Bus - investment cuts	5	6	6	6:the case of the energy industries, these changes result from adopting more favour-ile assumptions than those in the industries&apos; original bids.   These are estimatingages for BNOC and British Qas but a policy change in the case of Electricity,the view of officials, the revised assumptions are realistic, but if the originalirecasts were to prove right the financing requirements of the industries concernedmid have to be increased.   In this event the Department of Energy would want the:-its on the financing requirements of the industries concerned increased accordingly.1 Seductions in the proposed investment programmes of BR and NBC have been madesause officials do not consider that adequate financial progress has been made toWify investment at the level proposed.   In the case of rail, the reductions willlov up as a combination of lower borrowing and lower grant.   The Board have empha-;sed the serious consequences for the renewal of exisiting assets of maintaining thewent investment ceiling.i- The options set out in Table 3 on page 6, if exercised in full, would go well&apos;7ond eliminating the excess on Cmnd 7439 and achieve substantial savings. Inrticular the Cmnd 7^39 figure of  750 million for 1980/81 would be reduced to i**00illion.  Ministers however will wish to consider whether they wish all of these optionsHe exercised and if not which. In the view of Treasury officials all art feasible;Jmoet of them desirable.  Nevertheless some art clearly easier than others, fourRetries - BNOC, coal, steel and shipbuilders - art the aubjtot of separate reviewsp Ministers are being invited to take deoisions on them separately.  The reviews of* last 3 loss-making industries all turn in part on the scale of eloaurea. But^savings shown in lines 1, 10 &amp; 11 should be achievablej and in tht ease of BNOCle savings in line 2 flow from the policy in the Manifesto.&apos;* J-ri the view of Treasury officials there ia a strong oaae for permitting elao-&quot;icity prices to rise to economic levels (as the baseline forecasts already assume)&apos;:i for raising domestic gas prices to eoonomio levela.  In a market economy(confidential)
CONFIDENTIALTable 3 OPTIONS FOR REDUCTIONS  million at 1979 Survey price1980/81     1981/82     1982/83 1983/84Coal - investment,including pit closures 55BNOC - reduced investment 75Gas - maintain prices inreal terms 160ORMove to economic pricing(as already assumed forelectricity) 260Electricity (England &amp;Wales) and Gas - unspeci-fied current and capitalsavings 50Scottish Electricity Boards- increase prices toeconomic levels plus currentand capital savings 10Transport industries -further miscellaneoussavings 20Airways -investment reductions 40Airports - raise landingcharges to economic levels 16Post Office - capital andcurrent savings 50Steel &amp; Shipbuilders -estimated savings fromcurrent reviews 105British Aerospace -cancellation of BAe 146 40951002103807515204015140100240480100202015195125320670100302015225402254022540TOTAL (including 3a)(including 3h)6217218351005900114010701420CONFIDENTIAL
(confidential)jisions about the use of national resources are largely guided by considerations ofst and price.   An efficient market will ensure that decisions so based will tend totresources to the most worth while uses.   And for the market to be efficient,ices must reflect costs.   Because value to consumers and costs are likely to varytithe scale of output, economic pricing is concerned particularly with the (oppor-jity) cost of putting more or less resources into a particular activity i.e. withrginal costs.   In an efficient market the forces of competition tend to bringices and marginal costs together.   Market efficiency is much harder to achieve fori nationalised monopoly industries than for the private sector.   But the best wayensuring that the nationalised monopoly industries are not using too much or toottle of national resources is to base their prices on their marginal costs. (Forfuller statement   see Appendix D.)I, The size of the overall savings depends crucially on the option chosen for gasices.   In the view of Treasury officials    line 3(a)^hic^raerely involves main-(dning present prices in real terms should be a minimum objective.   But it would bejy much preferable to move towards full economic pricing.   This would involve priceJicreases of up to 5$ a year in real terms and produce the savings in line 3(b).i alternative way of raising domestic gas prices would be to impose a gas tax inirtch case the additional revenue would flow to the Exchequer directly instead offoducing very high gas industry profits.   The PSBR would be reduced to the same[tent, but public expenditure would not be affected.   Line k is based on the view(officials that BGC and Electricity could, if pressed by Ministers, find furtherivings, a view which is reinforced by BGCs recently demonstrated ability to findwings of  130 million in 1979/80 at very short notice for the Budget.   Line 6 simi-wly assumes that savings could be obtained from the transport industries though theiwpe for this will depend on the size and nature of the options for reductionitepted in Programme 6.   The increased charges for the Scottish Electricity BoardsliBB- 5) will put them on all-fours with electricity in England &amp; Wales. Increasediirport landing-charges      line 8) can also be justified in terms of a move to econo-c pricing.   The option cut   for BA (line 7) involves some postponement of purchase&apos; three Tristars, but this would not prevent the financial target being achieved.jclusionMinisters are invited:a)   to approve in whole or in part the option savings for 1980/81, and if poss-ible for later years, described in paras IS-IJJsubject to further decisionson BNOC, coal, steel and shipbuilders;to approve the total borrowing requirements of the industries as set out inAppendix A, Table 3t on the basis of the revised definition including short-term borrowing and leasing^as modified by the decision  n (a) above;- 7 -(confidential)
(confide ntIal)c) subject to (a) &amp; (b), to approve the investment figures set out in AppendixTable 2, on the usual basis of 100$ in 198O/81, 85$ in 1981/82 and 70$ in]1982/83. *H.M.TREASURY27 June 1979. 8 -(confidential)
INDEX OFAPPENDICESAppendix ATable 1 - Financing of capital requirementsTable 2 - Capital expenditureTable 3 - Total net borrowing and leasingTable 4 - GrantsAppendix B   :   Option cutsAppendix C   ;   Individual industry annexesAppendix D   :   Economic Pricing
APEHTOIX AKAxlCMAIJSED INDUSTRIES: KDUHCTC OF CAPITAL HBJtnRHtBffiS2AHLE 1	1974-75	1975-76	1976-77	1977-78	1978-79	1979-80	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-84Government Tending (Net)										PDC and issues under Section 18 of the Iron and Steel Act 1975	968 219	880 570	- 267 618	- 76k 526	- 252 864	350 ) ) 800 ]	800	800	750	750Total	1,187	1,^50	351	- 238	612	1,150	800	800	750	750and Overseas/Market Borrowing (Net)										Overseas	1,104	780	1,662	498	92	150	50	- 150	50	150Market	-	-	- 118	-	7	- 500	-J	-	- 150	- 150Total	1,101*	780	1,544	498	99	- 350	50	- 150	- 100	-TOTAL NET BCEHOVJBG^ (OTHER THAN SHOBX-XEBi)	2,291	2,230	1.895	260	711	800	850	650	650	750 -Short-term borrowing and leaping	284	- 10	23	511	421	- 50	.150	200	100	-TOTAL NET BCEBOKDIG^^	2,575	2,220	1,918	771	1,132	750	1,000	650	750	750Grants	1,885	1,859	853	775	882	1,000	950	950	950	900(1) TOTAL EXTSBNAL FTOANCE &apos;	4,460	4,079	2,771	1,546	2,014	1,750		-1,800.	1,700	1,650Total internal resources	596	1,^33	2,642	2.3JU	2,*50	2,050	Z,fOD	3,150	3,200	3,300TOTAL CAPITAL HEJOTEEKHfTS^1 ^	5,056	5,512	5,413	3,889	4,464	3,800	Jt.550	4,950	4,900	4,950^The forecast figures are after ,nnV-inE allowance for shortfall below the industries&apos; own forecasts of  450a in 1979-80, 500c in 1980-81, and  400m in the remaining three years.O0HFIDHITIA1
APPENDIX ANATIONALISED INDDSTRIE3CAPITAL EXPraDECURETABLE 2  million at 1978-79 prices	1974-75	1975-76	1976-77	1977-78	1978-79	1979-80	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-84Ecpenditure on fixed assets										National Coal Board	25*	303	371	397	494	526	588	585	599	608Electricity Council and Boards	901	894	869	733	716	748	815	883	873	974North of Scotland Eydro-ELoctric Board 58		97	94	69	48	45	41	30	27	30South of Scotland Electricity Board	115	98	69	47	53	86	122	171	237	203British Gas Corporation	366	500	335	257	280	268	374	428	361	331British national Oil Corporation	-	13	193	225	245	236	354	370	381	378British Steel Corporation	545	740	736	548	328	280	345	348	301	234Post Office: Teleconrounications	1,371	1,205	998	916	951	983	1,118	1,102	1,099	1,133Post and other.	70	68	57	45	44	53	61	67	65	54British Airways Board	188	165	193	221	221	304	390	355	394	402British Airports Authority	42	49	52	40	33	40	79	75	76	70British Railways Board	308	337	306	301 .	349	335	347	347	347	347British Transport Docks Board	14	17	10	11	9	16	17	18	17	17British waterways Board	2	2	2	2	2	4	7	4	3	3National Freight Corporation	47	29	28	33	- 36	34	37	37	40	40national Bus Company	35	43	49	50	54&apos;	58	54	55	56	57Scottish Transport Group	12	10	12	11	17	15	11	11	10	10British Aerospace	-	-	-	21	29	41	44	39	36	33British Shipbuilders	-	-	-	22	27	38	40	40	40	40Total expenditure on fixed assets	4,325	4,571	4,379	3,949	3,936	4,110	4,844	4,965	4,962	4,969Other capital requirements	731	941	1,034	- 60	528	123	220	395	316	339Total Capital Requirements	5,056	5,512	5,413	3,889	4,464	4,233	5,064	5,360	5,278	5,358Shortfall	-	-		-	-	- 450	- 500	- 400	- 400	- 400Total Capital Bequirenents after Shortfall Change on Chad 7439	5,056	5,512	5,413	3,889 -	4,464 - 5	3,783 - 622	4,564 * 44	4,960 * .154	4,878 - 170	4,958
APPENDIX ATABLE 3NATIONALISED INDUSTRIES : TOTAL NET BORROWING AND LEASING		 	million at	1978-79	prices	1979-80	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-84National Coal Board	414	409	400	416	427Electricity Council aad Boards	-69	-8	-11	93	218North of Scotland Hydro-Electric Board	36	20	5	-2	-South of Scotland Electricity Board	51	57	91	161	153British Gas Corporation	-409	-142	-78	-164	-160British National Oil Corporation	103	175	28	-14	-37British Steel Corporation	692	457	427	398	398Post Office	-101	35	-46	-99	-205British Airways Board	158	195	130	147	149British Airports Authority	-1	31	15	11	-5British Railways Board	46	49	45	16	9British Transport Docks Board	-6	-7	-9	-10	-11British Waterways Board	3	4	2	2	2National Freight Corporation	16	16	14	13	13National Bus Company	22	11	9	14	19Scottish Transport Group	1	-3	-3	-3	-2British Aerospace	49	75	86	72	67British Shipbuilders	182	106	125	102	100	1187	1480	1230	1153	1135 &apos;Shortfall	-450	-500	-400	-400	-400TOTAL	737	980	830	753	735Change on Cmnd 7439-332 4-232 * 112 4-56CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALIENDIX AJIONALISED INDUSTRIES : GRANTSTABLE 4250	214	208	206	1957	8	11	11	413	14	5	4	3616616  million at 1978-79 prices1979-80   1980-81   1981-82   1982-83 1983-84tional Coal Boardsctricity Council and Boardith of Scotland Hydro-Electric Boardnth of ScotlandElectricity Boarditish Gas Corporationitish National OilCorporationtish Steel Corporationst Office[itish Airways Boarditish Airports Authoritytish Railways Boardtish Transport Docks Boarditish Waterways Boardtional Freight Corporaltional Bus Company&apos;ottish Transport Groupitish Aerospaceitish ShipbuildersTOTALge on Cmnd 7439 (1)Ganges on grants underlying Programme 5 in Cmnd 7439.    These figuresEstate the increase,   in public expenditure, because Cmnd 7439 included;stimates of grants to British Railways in Programme 5 which were below:&apos;tte public expenditure ceilings in Programme 6.    The new figures are in;lrie with these ceilings.&apos;;iange on Cmnd 7439 figures for 1982-83-160161561521	21	21	21	21ion 10	7	6	4	453	54	50	46	4212	10	9	8	746	44	25	8	-1014	987	950	924	892+166	4-243	4-236	+213	4-181CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALOPTION CUTSAPPENDIX BNational Coal BoardThe NCB plan to increase coal prices to the maximum permittedby the rise in oil prices - their forecasts already assume areal price increase of 10-12% in 1980-81, which has been anticipatedto the. extent of 9% hy the price increase from 1 July 1979, and,some 1.2% a year thereafter.   Each 1% increase in coal prices raisessome  30 million a year.   Ministers will he considering in the CoalReview, to he taken at about the same time as this review, measuresto reduce the industry&apos;s current costs, including closures. Each1 million tonnes of capacity closed saves  41m in the first yearrising to  151m in the fifth year after closure.   The industry&apos;sinvestment programme is running at  500m- 600m a year, mainly fornew lower cost production.    A reduction in the programme would delaythis production.   Ministers may however wish to ask the NCB to reducetheir investment by some  50m in the early years of the period whilethe &quot;benefits from cost saving measures build up.British National Oil Corporation2.   The price of oil is determined on a world-wide basis, soBNOC has no scope for action by way of pricing policy. Currentexpenditure is anyway very small.   If BNOC were asked to make animmediate 10% reduction in their capital investment programme overthe five year period, this could be accommodated by cuts in thefollowing categories: m 1979 Survey prices1980-81        1981-82        1982-82 1983-84Exploration 12 11 10 9Downstream 5 4 4 4Unspecified 20 23 24 2537 38 38 38However, Ministers will be taking a review of BNOCs activitiesat about the same time as they take this review.   We expect theywill wish to eliminate BNOCs &quot;unspecified provision&quot; whichbasically is set aside for buying into new ventures on the UKContinental Shelf, although it also contains a contingency element-1-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALfor shortfall in internal resources or from forecasting factorsoutside BNOCs control, eg exchange rates.   We expect that theywill similarly wish to eliminate the provision for downstreaminvestment, ie involvement in refining, marketing and distribution]of petroleum products - thus leaving only a provision for explorationactivity.   On this basis and assuming the cut in exploration activityenvisaged above, the total capital savings available from BNOCwould be: m 1979 Survey prices1980-81        1981-82 1982-83Exploration 12 11 10Downstream 11 16 17Unspecified 53 74- 7576101102British. Gas Corporation3.   Substantial savings could be made through raising domestic gaslprices to proper economic levels.   Studies by officials suggest thatdomestic gas is at least .20% underpriced, although BGC considerthat the level of underpricing is only about 8%.   If gas, a non-renewable resource, is not to be wasted, it is important that thisjunderpricing should be corrected.   Moreover, the Electricity Councahas assumed that electricity prices rise by an average of 5% in realterms over the Survey period whilst BGC&apos;s figures show domestic gasprices falling 19% in real terms over the same period.   This furtherenhancement of gas&apos; competitive edge over electricity is highlyundesirable on energy policy grounds.   The best way of achievingsuch price increases would be to set BGC an appropriate medium-terrfinancial target.   This would of course result in substantiallyincreased profits as the table below indicates.   BGC&apos;s profits arealready embarrassingly high and as has already been suggested toMinisters, these presentational difficulties could be reduced byimposing a gas tax or Exchequer charge.   The table below showsrough estimates by the Treasury of additional revenues which wouldaccrue to BGC if domestic gas prices rose by different amounts.-2-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL m 1979 Survey prices1980-811981-821982-831983-84If domestic gas pricesrose:1. so as to maintainlevels in real terms(ie 9% nominal perannum) 1602. by 3% in real termsper annum (ie 12%nominal per annum) 2103. by 5% in real termsper annum (ie 14%nominal per annum) 2602103003802403904803205206704.   Any savings on current expenditure would have to come largelyfrom provision made for mains replacement.   This programme is beingundertaken on safety grounds following the recommendations of theKing Enquiry on serious gas explosions and the slowing down of thisprogramme must be measured against an unquantifiable additionalsecurity risk.   However, there might be scope for arbitrary cutsin the early years of the Survey of say,  25-40m.   When asked howthey would meet a requirement to cut their capital investment prog-ramme by 10%, BGC said *fcat there was virtually no scope for cuts.Much of their investment has already bean committed as BGC are undera statutory obligation (Gas Act 1972) to meet the growing demandsof their customers.Electricity (England and Wales)5.   One starts with pricing policy.   The industry&apos;s forecastsassume a 5% annual increase in real prices, including 3% for higherfossil fuel costs.   The industry acknowledge that present pricesfall short of economic pricing (see Appendix D) and have allowed abalance of the real price increase (2% per year over the reviewperiod) which would bring their prices approximately to economiclevels by 1983-84.   It will be difficult to secure price increasesof this order, and, if fossil fuel prices increase more thanPresently expected (very great uncertainties surround them) thedifficulty will be exacerbated.   The competitive position of theelectricity industry will be weakened in the domestic markets bythe increase this year to recover the higher coal price, whiledomestic gas prices will not rise similarly.   For price increaseson the scale envisaged to be possible without loss of sales, gas-3-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALprices must increase at least equivalently.6. Presentationally, it would be helpful if the move to economicprices took place in the framework of medium-term financial targetsfor the industry.   It will be seen that it will be extremely difficulto gain acceptance of increases in prices above those already assumedby the industry - and virtually impossible if gas prices do not alsorise by at least an equivalent amount.   However, a further 1% realincrease in tariff levels above those assumed - which risks takingtariffs above economic levels - would reduce the industry&apos;s externalfinancing requirement, at 1978-79 prices, by: m1980-81       1981-82      1982-83 1983-8433 42 46 537. Reductions in the industry&apos;s borrowing requirement couldalternatively fall on the industry&apos;s current or capital programmes.Reductions in current expenditure could only be brought aboutthrough cutting of repairs and maintenance, and this is unlikelyto yield significant savings without jeopardising standards ofsafety or supply security.   Capital expenditure cuts are verydifficult too.   With long lead times involved in power stationconstruction and transmission much of the proposed expenditure inthe early years of the Survey period is for projects which havealready been started.   Delays in such projects could involve theindustry in compensation to contractors.   The industry also saythat delay or cancellation of projects could have considerableeffects on system security and operation, leading to breakdowns.Electricity (Scotland)8. The Scottish Electricity Boards assume lower increases in thereal price of coal and oil than the Electricity Council (equivalentroughly to a 1% real tariff increase until 1982 and a 2% increasethereafter).   After a 5% real increase in 1980-81 (including theassumed rise in fossil fuel prices), the Boards assume no furtherreal increase in tariffs during the survey period.   But if electricittariffs in England Wales were increasing annually by 5% in real termthroughout the period and gas prices were rising equivalently, theScottish Boards would be able to make further progress towardsCONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALeconomic prices and might increase tariffs by a further 2% in1981-82 and 1982-83.   This in broad terms would reduce externalfinancing requirements, at 1978-79 prices, by: m1981-82        1982-83 1983-849 20 21Scottish Transport Group9. The Group&apos;s position is similar to that of the NBC (see below).The balance between increases in fares and cuts in services would- th5-depend on local circumstances and the attitude of/Traffic Commxssionersand local authorities.   Cuts in investment could provide an alternativemeans of securing the necessary reduction in external finance but thebulk of the Group&apos;s investment programme is for replacement whichcould   not be postponed unless there were to be a contraction ofservices.   Since the level of fares includes provision for replacementcost depreciation, a reduction in the investment programme couldreduce receipts if the Traffic Commissioners delayed or restrictedfare increases on this account.British Railways Board10. A cut in the Board&apos;s external finance would be met byincreasing net revenue by increases in fares and charges, reducingworking expenses by improved productivity or reducing standards,level of services, reducing stocks, realising the proceeds of landdisposal or reducing investment in that order.11. In the short term, the Board&apos;s most likely response to asubstantial cut in finance would be fare increases. However,significant increases would be offset to a large extent by lossof patronage and pricing action would therefore be concentratedon those areas where demand is inelastic, particularly thecommuter market, although there may be some scope for real pricingon Inter-City services.   In the longer term, current expenditurecould contribute to cuts if the Board could achieve improvedproductivity or close cost-ineffective railway services.Curtailment of services on any significant scale would probablyrequire a redefinition of the Passenger Service Obligation imposed-5-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALon the Board by the Minister of Transport.   Other minor savingsmight be achieved by reductions in stocks and an accelerated landsales programme, though the scope for these is limited.12. The scope for a contribution from cuts in investment islimited inasmuch as officials have already taken a view, for purposesof this investment review, that the Board&apos;s investment programmeshould be maintained at a lower level ( 100m over 5 years) thanBR consider necessary for the renewal of assets on the social railwayand the proper development of their commercial businesses. Furthercuts in investment would be a last resort.   If they had to be made,the Board say the brunt would fall on the rolling programme to replaceelderly EMUs, most of which are employed on the commuter servicesaround London, leading to a deterioration in the level and standardof service and to a reduction in revenue.National Bus Company13. The Company^ response to a squeeze on external finance wouldbe a mixture of cuts in services and investment as well as increasesin prices depending on local circumstances.   Fare increases and cutsin service could only be implemented with the agreement of theTraffic Commissioners and after consultation with local authorities;substantial changes could take three months or more to effect. TheCompany^ preference would be to cut services and to do both beforecutting investment.   The ssope for further cuts in investment willbe limited by the 10% reduction in NBCs investment in replacementvehicles proposed in the main body of the Review, and because NBCsinvestment needs are closely linked to the future level of capitaland revenue support for bus operations which is being consideredin the main Public Expenditure Survey.National Freight Corporation14. The Corporation could achieve a cut in external finance by acombination of reductions in current and capital expenditure. Asregards pricing options, the Corporation operates mainly as a pricetaken, reflecting its small share of businesses in most sectors ofthe road haulage market.   The scope for further price increases isvery limited especially in view of the high tariff increases now-6-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALbeing implemented to cover the recent pay settlement. Reductionsin current expenditure could be effected by reduced maintenance ofvehicles and some small improvement in the revenue account might beachieved through increasing sales of assets.   But to achieve 10%overall, cuts in capital expenditure would need to be made too, andthese would undermine the Corporation^ vehicle replacement policyleading over a period to increased maintenance costs and reducedservice levels and receipts and would slow down the shift out ofunremunerative activities into more profitable areas of operation.The scope for more rapid contraction in manpower and investment inless profitable activities is limited by the high level of redundancypayments which would be incurred in the early years of the Review andby the unquantifiable but possibly substantial cost of industrialunrest.British Transport Docks Board15.   Operating in a competitive environment in which real profitsare derived from marginal business and revenue, the BTDB would havedifficulty in raising prices beyond levels already planned. Reductionsto current expenditure would affect the BTDB&apos;s ability to carry outessential maintenance.   To increase debt repayment by  2m a year(a 25% increase in their already accelerated repayment scheduleequivalent to a 10% cut in their investment programme), the Boardwould have to cut investment by a similar amount, postponingreplacement capital expenditure and general improvement schemesand prejudicing their future trading prospects.British Waterways Board16.   TJjere is little prospect of increasing the prices charged bythe BWB by an amount which would have a significant effect on theirgrant requirement..   Cuts in external finance could therefore onlybe achieved by cutting ^rther current expenditure or investment.Cuts in current expenditure would affect the Board&apos;s ability toreduce the maintenance backlog revealed by the Fraenkel Report.Cuts in investment could be achieved by reducing replacement ofplant, although this would also affect the maintenance programme,or by delaying or cancelling commercial investment projectsincluding the Board&apos;s major new scheme, the improvement of the-7-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALSheffield and South Yorkshire Navigation (SSYN), which started thisyear.   Postponing the SSYN would have no impact on the Board&apos;smaintenance programme and its immediate effect on traffic and receiptswould he less than that stemming from alternative cuts in investmenthut cancellation would affect other planned development in the area.British Airways Board17.   A cut in BA&apos;s finance requirements equivalent to 10% of capitalexpenditure in the four years 1980-81 to 1983-84 would represent onequarter of their total planned external fundings over these years,or some  40m a year.   Beacuse they are price takers, BA could notcompensate for any cut by raising fares.   As to reductions in currentexpenditure, overmanning is a well-known problem but productivityimprovements assumed in their corporate plan (GP7) go as far as theCorporation judge their unions will accept.   Capital expenditurecuts would mean reducing expenditure on aircraft since non-aircraftexpenditure has already been cut to the bone.   BA&apos;s new shorthaulaircraft are already on order, and they have therefore assumed that acut would be implemented by the loss of 6 medium-haul Tristars fromthe investment programme.   The consequent reductions in operatingsurplus are:  m at 1979 Survey pricesThese figures assume no retrenchment and are based on the alternativeBA consider to be the least disadvantageous, of continuing to fly14 uneconomic and noisy aircraft for as long as possibly insteadof the 6 Tristars.   As well as the financial disadvantage to BA(which would extend beyond 1983-84), such a course would replace10 prospective quiet aircraft movements a day by 25 noisy ones,and disrupt severely BA&apos;s plan for an orderly retirement of oldaircraft which must cease to fly by 1 January 1986 under new noiselegislation.   Retention of 14 of these aircraft for longer thanplanned instead of acquiring the 6 Tristars means that the replacementprogramme will be bunched up against this deadline at a time whenprofits and cashflows would already be significantly reduced if thecuts were applied.   BA&apos;s fuel consumption would be increased by some26 million gallons by 1982-8$, staff productivity would be reducedby 1% in that year compared with the target in the corporate plan,1980-8141981-82111982-83151983-8417-8-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALand prospective sales of 23 Rolls Royce engines would be at risk.18.   In summary, implementation of these cuts in full would in BA&apos;sview weaken their corporate strategy designed to enable the airlineto operate successfully and profitably in an increasingly competitivemarket, and might prejudice prospects of private sector participation.BA&apos;s figures indicate, however, that the airline would still be ableto meet its current financial target even on that basis.   A lessdrastic option would be to impose  40 million cuts in 1980-81 and1981-82 only, which if it fell on progress payments as presentlyscheduled would probably require three of the six aircraft to bepostponed for two years.British Airports Authority19-   The Authority have examined whether it is possible to eliminatethe proposed NLF borrowing of  16m in 1980-81,  15m in 1981-82, 11m in 1982-83, and the  15m rundown in cash reserves in 1980-81.They are clear that cuts to the capital programme cannot be madewithout congestion which would force a redistribution of traffic toContinental airports; and there is little or no scope for cuttingcurrent expenditure without affecting the operating safety orsecurity of airports.   They propose therefore, if option cuts arerequired, to increase trading profit by raising landing charges.The increase required to avoid a move to a net NLF borrowing position,after corporation tax, would be of the order of 30% in landing chargeswhich would be in addition to the planned increases in line withinflation.   The Authority see no possibility whatever of eliminatingthe rundown in their cash reserves.   The increases would make theBAA. airports amoing the most expensive in Europe and would undoubtedlyresult in strong criticism from international, especially American,airlines; but it could be represented that high landing charges arenot inconsistent with the high level of congestion prevailing at theLondon airports.   The increases would also oblige the Authority toearn something approaching the Required Rate of Return on its assetswithout recourse to cross-subsidisation from duty-free sales.Post Office20. The bulk of any savings would have to come from TelecommunicationsA possible pricing option is available - to reverse the decision by-9-CONFIDENTIAL
CONPlJJENTlALthe previous Government to lower the financial target of 6%, whichexpired at the end of the last financial year, to 5%.   This wouldinvolve further price increases and would raise about  150m a yearfor the benefit of the PSBR.   However, economic argument based onthe need to earn the Required Rate of Return of 5% in real termssuggests that this target should, if anything, be less than 5%, anda move back to 6% would be open to the criticism that the Governmentwas milking the industry and exploiting its monopoly power, to thedetriment of price stability and the consumer.   Moreover, a majorpackage of tariff increases will in any case be required in Januaryjust to meet the present target of 5%.   At a rough estimate thiswould have a 0.08% impact on the RPI.   Increases to meet a 6% targetwould bring this to 0.15%.21. A 5% cut in their investment programme of  1 billion, raisingsome  50 million in each year, would be feasible though would bevery strongly resisted.   Some savings might be raised by postponingoffice building projects in London.   The Post Office Board haverecently decided to accelerate their programme of replacing out-of-date exchanges but they will strongly resist any reversal of thisdecision in view of the quality of service and maintenance implicationsRather, they have already warned us that the main impact would fallon the system.   Connection charges which bear particularly heavilyon the low-paid and pensioners would need to be increased by about50%; otherwise the present already very serious waiting list andpipelines for new connections would treble by 1982-83.   The effecton the equipment supply industry would be very serious, just at atime when it is gearing up its investment to the production of themore capital intensive (and energy saving) electronic equipment inpreparation for System X.   The PO estimates that a cut of 5% intelecommunications capital investment spread evenly across thisprogramme would mean a job loss in the supply industry of some2,300 in 1980-81 and 1981-82 and a gross cash flow loss for theindustry of some  35^ in each of those years at current prices.A cut as large as 10% would have a proportionately bigger impacton the supply industry&apos;s cash flow and a more than proportionatelybigger impact on its manpower.22. In practice the Post Office would prefer, if Ministers allowedthem, to find any PSBR savings that were imposed on them not by-10-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALinvestment cuts but by tariff increases or current account savings.A major tariff package will in any case be necessary before the endof this financial year.   A cut of  50m or  100m would mean requiringTelecommunications to make a real return of 5.3% or 5*7% respectivelycompared with their present financial target of 5%.   Cuts in currentaccount expenditure on items such as training, recruitment andmaintenance tend to hit quality of service, which is already thesubject of severe public criticism.23. In Posts, cuts of 5% and 10% would amount to  3m and  6mrespectively.   Postal prices are about to  be raised anyway and thePrime Minister has expressed concern about the extent of that increase- so a further increase is not a feasible option.   The most significantsource of current savings would be a reduction of postal deliveriesto one per day, but the Post Office doubt if this would be acceptableeither to the general public or the unions.   This could save up to 40m a year.   Any investment cuts would have to fall predominantlyin the accommodation sector.   A cut of  6m in each year would meannot proceeding with virtually all new buildings scheduled to startin those years.   A lot of existing accommodation is operationallyinefficient or gravely substandard; cuts would therefore aggravatethe industrial relations problems and could also put the fullimplementation of mechanisation at risk.British Steel Corporation24. Work is still under way at BSC on reviewing the Corporationsoperating plans so as to get back on the path to break even in thefinal quarter of 1979-80.   Investment and financing figures for thesubsequent years will reflect the decisions now in course ofpreparation.   The objective is an external borrowing requirement in1980-81 of  375 million at 1978-79 prices ( 450 million at outturnprices) followed by a substantially lower requirement in 1981-82after a capital reconstruction.   These figures, if they can beachieved, represent substantial reductions, of about  80 millionin 1980-81 and considerably less in 1981-82, below the amountscontemplated in the 1978 investment review which underlay theCmnd 7439 totals.   These reductions reflect considerable cutbacksin investment averaging  100 million a year up to 1981-82, coupledwith strong cost containment measures to affect the adverse impactof an increasingly hostile trading environment.-11-
CONFIDENTIAL25. At present, the prices BSC can charge are effectively fixedby the Davignon measures for maintaining Community level pricesand this gives the Corporation some element of protection in acontinuing weak market.   There seems little prospect of theCorporation improving its financial position by raising pricesfaster than its foreign competitors.   And the efforts currentlybeing made to cut current costs will leave no significant scope forfurther savings by this route short of the closure of a majormodern plant as well as obsolescent plants already planned to shutdown and the consequent abandonment of part of the UK market toimports.   Further investment cuts would mean abandoning small schemeswith short pay back periods, many of which are important to maintainingthe momentum of the essential improvement of product quality, orabandoning major schemes currently under construction.British Aerospace26. Pricing options are not a starter for this price taker industry.The only possible source of significant savings in current expenditiis reduction in labour costs;   there is little prospect of realising Ithis since BAe expect savings in productivity to be offset by realincreases in wages.   Some 40% of the planned expenditure on fixedassets for 1979-80 has already been committed and some 10% of thetotal for 1980-81.   The planned expenditure on work-in-progress isrequired for the development of new projects.   Although this expenditureis not yet committed in the contractual sense, it could not be cutsignificantly without cancellation of one or more projects - slowingdown the rate of spending is not a realistic possibility given thecharacteristics of the market.   A cut of the order of  15 millionfrom total expenditure would probably lead to the cancellation ofthe Jetstream 51 project, which accounts for some 3% of the capitalrequirements up to 1982.   A larger cut would probably involvecancellation of the BAe 146 project, saving up to  40m in later yearJbut with serious consequences for BAe&apos;s strategy of maintaining thecapability to build complete civil aircraft.   Cancellation of anycivil project could be expected to have serious employmentconsequences (Jetstream is based in Scotland).-12-CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBritish Shipbuilders-27.   Because of the current review of this industry, no specificoption cuts are proposed for British Shipbuilders, though they shouldmake some contribution particularly in the later years.CONFIDENTIAL
APPENDIX C : INDIVIDUAL INDUSTRY ANNEXESIndustry PageNATIONAL COAL BOARD 1BRITISH NATIONAL OIL CORPORATION 4BRITISH GAS CORPORATION 6ELECTRICITY COUNCIL &amp; BOARDS 9NORTH OP SCOTLAND HYDRO-ELECTRIC BOARD 11SOUTH OP SCOTLAND ELECTRICITY BOARD 11SCOTTISH TRANSPORT GROUP 14BRITISH RAILWAYS BOARD 17NATIONAL BUS COMPANY 21NATIONAL FREIGHT CORPORATION 24-BRITISH TRANSPORT DOCKS BOARD 2?BRITISH WATERWAYS BOARD 29BRITISH AIRWAYS BOARD 31BRITISH AIRPORTS AUTHORITY 35POST OFFICE 38BRITISH STEEL CORPORATION 43BRITISH AEROSPACE 46BRITISH SHIPBUILDERS 50
dsCONFIDENTIALNATIONAL COAL BOARD m at 1979 survey prices (changes on Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)1979/80 1980/1 1981/2       1982/3 1983/4-italirements:ixed assetsnUKtherJOIALIanced by:562(- 59)- 55C-135)588(- 9)16(-58)585C + 15)15(- 62)599(-h 33)23(- 50)6083047K-194)       604-(- 67)     600(- 4-7)   622(- 17) 638InternalIesourcesfantsborrowing (net)ff which, leasingind short term-193C-276)250(+165)414-(- 83)22(* 2)-19C-155)214-(h-131)409(- 4-3)24-(- 2)-8(-126)208(4-132)4O0(- 53)25(- 2)- (-159)206(-h13l)4-16(-h 11)2Q(+ 1)161954-2725Recent DelevopmentsIt was agreed after last year&apos;s Finance and Investment Review thatin view of uncertainty about medium-term prospects for the industryits investment strategy should be reviewed before the 1979 Financeand Investment Review:   in addition to the preparation of theirfive-year development plan the NCB have reviewed the Plan for Coaland for this purpose extended the planning horizon to 1990.   In thelight of the Board1s Review, the Department of Energy have re-examinedthe strategy for the industry in consultation with the Treasury.The report has now been submitted to Ministers.   The forecasts for1980-81 onwards will need to be reconsidered in the light of Ministers1subsequent decisions on the strategy for the industry.1978-79 saw a marked deterioration in the NCB*s financial positionfrom that forecast at the beginning of the year.   Costs continued torise&apos;faster than inflation; coal&apos;s markets remained weak, especiallyin the iron and steel industry, seveieLy restricting the ability ofthe industry to raise revenue from higher prices; and the incentive
CONFIDENTIALscheme, introduced in January 1978, did not prove as beneficial ashad been expected.   The real sterling price of oil fell throughoutmuch of 1978 and coal lost ground in the power station market. InOctober 1978 the previous Government announced that it would contributeto the cost of the sale of coal at a discount to the CEGB to enable!some 3m tonnes of coal which would otherwise have been stocked tobe burned in place (foil and imported coal.Although there was slight shortfall in the capital expenditure of theNCB in 1978-79 the provisional outturn is nearer the estimate than jin orevious vears.in previous years.InvestmentThe investment programme continues to be directed to the implementationof Plan for Coal.   The investment is mainly in new or replacementlow-cost, efficient, capacity concentrated in the best long-life pitsand in new mines which would begin to come into operation from the jmid-1980s.   About 100 major projects have been approved.   These are&apos;expected to provide about 30m tonnes of new production capacity(including the 10m tonnes mine at Selby).   The Board have assumed thatthe production profile and forecasts of demand will be as in thefive-year plan.   However, a more realistic range of output and demandand the possible policy measures for dealing with any surpluses thatmay arise are covered in the Department of Energy1s report on coal Istrategy.The Board judge that the investment programme as a whole is well capableof meeting the 5$ RRR after allowing for reasonable variations inassumptions.External-financingThe NCB&apos;s estimates for 1979-80 take into account fairly optimisticBassumptions about output and the 9% price increase applied to allcoals in March 1979 as. well as a selective price increase equivalentto 9% across the board effective from 1 July 1979-   Further, theBoard estimate that even with  256m of Government grants they willincur a loss of  6m.   From 1980-81 onwards the external financing2
CONFIDENTIALrequirements forecasts are considerably in excess of Cmnd 74-39(increases in public expenditure average  100m a year).   Over thisperiod the NCB have assumed price increases which will return theBoard to the financial position projected in their five-year plan,ie break-even on the basis of historic cost depreciation and afterGovernment grants.   In 1980-81 a (real) price increase of 10% - 12%is assumed which has been anticipated to the extent of 9% &quot;by theincrease from 1 July 1979, leaving a further real increase of 1-3%to take place in 1980-81.   Thereafter the increases are projectedat an average 1.2% pa in real terms.   The NCB continue to forecasta high level of grants averaging  205m per annum for the remainingfour years if they are to break-even ie after grants and this iswell above the levels in Cmnd 74-39.   But their financial resultscould be substantially worse than this if the balance of assumedreal price increases is not feasible in 1980-81, eg for every 1%increase in price not achieved there is an increase in losses andthe external financing requirement of about  30m.The NCB&apos;s external financing requirements could also be increasedif the output and demand assumptions   in the five-year plan are notachieved.   Other things being equal the requirement increases byaround  20- 25 million for each one million tonnes of output bywhich demand fulls below supply.   Reduced demand could also leadto additions to stock and thus a further claim for stocking aidat some  3 per tonne with the Boardte borrowing requirements increasingby some  24 per tonne to cover increased working capital requirements.The report on coal strategy to be submitted to Ministers make proposalon how the coal industry can be set on a path to financial viability.A financial target has not formally been set for the NCB, althoughthe Board continues to aim at breaking-even, on the basis of historiccost depreciation.   The Board also aim to provide 50% of capitalexpenditure from self-generated funds (including Government grants).3
CONFIDENTIALBRITISH NATIONAL OIL CORPORATIONprovisionaloutturnCapital requirements 1978-79Fixed assets in UK 263(-2l)Other 30C+17)Total 293(- 4)fin at 1978-79 prices (Changes on Cmnd 7459 in brackets1979-80       198O-81        1981-82       1982-83 83-84236 (-4o)-16(-16)220(-56)354(428)- 1(- 5)353(4-23)370(-3i)12(4-17)382(-i4)381(-33)- 5(- 4)376(-37)3781379Financed byInternal resourceslong and medium termborrowing25C-14)268(4-10)117(- 4)i03(-52)178(-50)175(4-73)35M448)28C-62)390(450)-i4(-87)4i6-371. Ministers have recently instituted a wide ranging Review of BNOCs activities anduntil this is concluded the forecast set out above must be regarded as provisional.The setting of a medium-term financial objective for the Corporation must also awaitthe outcome of the Review.2. The bulk of the provision set out above is for expenditure arising out of BNOCsjpresent contractual commitments and planned future involvement in exploration anddevelopment work on the UK Continental Shelf. This includes expenditure on 4 oil and!gas producing fields and 3 fields under development and covers 9 fields including twojextensions to the Thistle field on which development decisions are expected within thefive year period. Because BNOCs major involvement with private sector companies injoint ventures on the UKCS is as a minority partner, it will either have to followinvestments decisions of its partners or dispose of its interests. This programme isjdesigned to bring on-stream the fields currently under development - production fromwhich will peak in 1983/84 at around 70m barrels per annumj and to undertakedevelopment of the fields whose production will build up rapidly from 1983&quot;84 onwards!to replace the falls in production from fields currently under development. The forejcast also provides for downstream activities (feasibility studies, and minority sharejin three projects); and includes funds for possible future projects which cannot beidentified at this stage. The breakdown of &quot;fixed assets&quot; expenditure between thesethree categories is as follows:1978-79 prices(i) Exploration and development(includes administration)(ii) Downstream(iii) Sundry and unspecified80-81	81-82	82-83	83-84308	296	290	26311	16	17	20?3	74	7P	?P372	386	382	378
CONFIDENTIALComparison with Cmnd 7^39 investment plansCapital Requirements5.    A comparison of the budget provision for capital requirements with the provisionin Cmnd 7^-39 shows few significant changes.   In 1979-80 the cuts announced in theBudget have reduced BNOCs capital requirements by  56 million compared with Cand 7^39;in 198O-81 there is a net increase of  23 million in BNOCs capital requirements. Insubsequent years capital requirements are reduced by  14 million in  1980-81 and by 37 million in 1982-83 compared with Cmnd 7^39.Financingk.    At present BNOC has two major sources of funds - the forward sale of oil toBrit-Oil, and funding from the NQA.   The latter is counted for administrative purposesas &quot;equity&quot; funding, and BNOC expects within the next year to reach the 60: 40 equity:debt ratio in its financing which was prescribed in February, 1978.   Later&quot;in theperiod BNOC will begin reducing its obligations to Brit-Oil and will need to take updebt finance from other sources.5.    BNOC is not at present subject to a cash limit for two main reasons.   First, inmost of its operations it is a minority partner with ao veto over the expendituredecisions of its partners and secondly its external financing requirements aredetermined by volatile factors outside its control such as oil prices and UKCSproduction levels.60    BN0C*s total capital requirements have not changed greatly since Cmnd 7^39*However, there has been an increase in BN0C&apos;s external financing requirement of 73 million in 198O-81.   This year now includes provision of  39 million for dividendpayments because of a change of the convention under which dividend payments wereexcluded from the Cmnd 7^39 figures.   (In subsequent years the provisions for dividendsare  78 million in 1981-82,   77  million in 1982-83 and  65 million in 1983-8^;these figures need to be deducted from BN0C*s external financing requirement figuresin paragraph 1 for a strict comparison with Cmnd 7^39)*   A 25% drop in the expectedflow of equity oil because of continuing development delays and production costs isthe main reason for the residual excess in 198O-81 of  33 million.   5N0C&apos;s revenueforecasts have been adjusted to take account of the latest susstained rise in crudeoil prices.5
CONFIDENTIALIjIISH GAS CORPORATIONlital requirements:ied assets in UK[herL1979-80 m at 1979 Survey Prices (changeson Cmnd 74-39 i-n brackets)1980-8&apos;&apos;981 -821982-831983-84268(-44)     374(4-9)      428(4-38)     361 (-45) 33116(-26)       34(-10)       40(-35) 7(-44) 54284(-70)     408(-l)      468(4-3)       368(-89) 385laaaced -by::ternal resourcest borrowingwhich short termad leasing693^122) 55o^50) 546(446) 532(4-23) 545-409(-192) -142(-51)     -78(-43)   -164(-112) -160-185(-2Q5)   -24(-74)       -2(-49) -14(-3)-6Recent Developments1.     The above financing and investment review figures reflect theprogramme contained in BGC&apos;s recently produced Corporate Plan. BGCplan to continue with a market-led strategy in which gas suppliesare tailored as far as possible to meet premium demand.   Sales continueto increase from 15*550 million therms last year to a forecast of16,600 m. th. this year and 19,700 m.th. in 1983-84.   Profits for1978-79 were  350 million (provisional), a substantial increase onbudget, largely due to the cold weather.   Repayments of NLF debt wereaccelerated accordingly and amounted to about  600 million for theyear.I2.     The previous Government set BGC a financial target for 1979-80of 6J% on turnover, after interest and depreciation (at current cost)and before tax.   The object of this target was to maintain prices inreal terms.   To achieve this target BGC notified the Price Commissionof their   intention to raise gas tariffs from 1 April by6CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALan average of  VJ% and to increase the price for contract sales inline with oil prices.   The Price Commission decided to investigatethis proposal.   The Commission granted as an interim increase the fullamounts applied for in respect of industrial contract prices andthe non-domestic tariff.   The domestic tariff was frozen until1 June and BGC&apos;s expected revenue will he correspondingly reducedby about  23 million overall.   This will make it more difficult forBGC to achieve their target.   It is expected that targets for futureyears will be set in the autumn.Investment Plans3. Capital expenditure is down by about  50. million for the five-year period, compared with Cmnd 7439, largely owing to the postponementof the development of the Morecambe gas field for three years on thebasis that a depleted southern basin field could be used for seasonalstorage.   Major transmission projects in the period include the fourthfeeder from St Fergus to England, the total cost of which is expectedto&apos; be about  250 million with work beginning this year. Regionalexpenditure on mains and distribution is up by  40 million comparedwith last year&apos;s plans, to meet higher forecasts of number ofcustomers.4. Provision for BGC participation in a possible gas-gathering schemein the North Sea is not included in the current estimates. Thertjmaybe circumstances where BGC&apos;s direct involvement in such a pipelinewould save the Exchequer significant amounts of PRT e.g. where thechargeable revenues from the associated gas are less than the taxreliefs on the pipeline costs whick are offset against oil revenues.5. BGC are at present reviewing the discount rate used for investmentappraisal of new revenue-earning projects.   Present indications arethat the 10% rate applied to individual projects will remain appropriajon the assumption that the RRR is to be met on the new investmentprogramme as a whole, although the precise rate of return on thatprogramme has yet to-be established.6. BGCs previously poor capital expenditure forecasting has beenimproving as more realistic estimates of shortfall tave been taken,into account.   Last year the capital expenditure outturn was only2- % below budget. 7CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL7. BGC attach high priority to continued investment in thetransmission and storage system to absorb all the Brant gas availablefrom 1980s, and subsequently the associated gas from other fieldswhich might otherwise have to be flared.   Scope for cutting capitalexpenditure is therefore limited and, should it be thought desirablefor BGC to make more rapid repayment of debt or to lend more surpluscash to the Exchequer, raising prices seems to be the better route(see paragraph 3 of Annex B).Financing8. The figures for 1979-80 are those announced in the Budget. Theyassume that BGC would cut their programme by  171 million by acombination of increased non-domestic prices from 1 September,reductions in capital expenditure and increased sales revenues.9. The figures for subsequent years assume that BGC&apos;s self imposedfinancial target of 4% on turnover will be maintained throughoutthe period.   The main effect of such an assumption is that domesticgas prices, which have already fallen substantially in real termssince 1973-74, will fall by around 25% in real terms over the fouryear period.   The main reason for this is   that domestic gas isthe residual element in determining total revenue. Non-domesticprices are oil related, and oil prices (and hence BGC&apos;s non-domesticrevenues) are forecast to rise at rates above general inflation.In consequence the faster oil   oil prices rise 1he greater the realfall in the price to consumers of domestic gas, unless Ministers lookto BGC for a higher target than 4% on turnover.10. Gas profits are of course sensitive to external factors such asthe weather, the inflation rate, oil prices and exchange rates.For instance, a variation in the average annual temperature of 10Cwould alter profits by about  85 million.11. All BGC&apos;s NLF debt is expected to be repaid this year. Repaymentof foreign loans tapers off quite rapidly- over the next two or threeyears leaving BGC with outstanding debts of only  214 million for3% Gas Stock, redeemable in 1995.   Surplus funds, after debtrepayment is completed, are expected to be deposited with theExchequer.8CONFIDENTIAL
CGNFXDENIIALlECTRICITY COONCIL AND BOARDS a at 1979 Survey prices(changes on Cmnd 7439 in brackets)1979-80   1980-81   1981-82   1982-83 1983-84Capital requirements:jjixed assets in IK 748(-56) 815&amp;75) 883C+79) 873(-124) 97^Other -55(-46) 85C+111) 68C+171) 36C+149) 59total 693(-i02)9CO(-i-i86)95i(4-250)909(425) .1C53755(-50) 9O0C+75) 95l(4l36)805(-3) 8117C+2) 8C+2) 11(4-5) 11(-) 4-69(-5^) -8(4-109) -11(4-109)93(4-28) 21820(-59)   -56(-54) -4(-5)    16(428) 6I InvestmentDie CB3B is responsible for more than two-thirds of the industry&apos;s capital investment.jEieir programme includes provision for units 3 and 4 of the Heysham Advanced Gas -CooledReactor station (total estimated cost  872m with substantial expenditure beginningin 1979-80.) Provision is also included for the 2000 MW completion of the Drax 4000 MW[coalfired station   (which is already under construction at a total estimated costof  715m.)   This station was brought forward in advance of need at the request ofithe previous administration.   Provision is also made for a 2000 MW Cross-Channellink with the French electricity utility, ELectricite de France, which was approvedin principle in 1978 (CBGB element of forecast expenditure &quot;on this project is2166m with expenditure beginning in 1979-80).    There is no inclusion for investment[in respect of possible collaboration with foreign electricity supply utilitiesI on the French Super-phenix fast breeder reactor project (NERSA).   The CESB will seekGovernment approval, and request any additional funding, if a firm prospect forinternational collaboration emerges.Market AssumptionsHie industry forecast an annual increase in the demand for electricity in EnglandM ftales over the period to 1985-86 averaging 2.3 per cent per annum assuming aGOP annual growth rate of 2.6 per cent.Financed by:InternalResourcesGrantsArrowing (net)of which leasingand short term9CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALInternal ResourcesIncome levels for Area Boards and the CEGB in 1980-81 and later years have been assumedsufficient to yield profits of 2 per cent on costs including 40 per cent additionalsupplement on historic cost depreciation.   The assumed tariff increases implicit inthe forecasts average 5 per cent above the general rate of inflation in 1980-81 and1981- 82 (in money terms forecast increases over the years 1980-81 to 1983-84 are12 per cent, 14 per cent, 9.4 per cent and 13.5 per cent respectively).   Price increasesof this order would keep the industry&apos;s borrowing requirements down, and would alsocover expected increases in costs, notably coal and oil prices.   The figures for1979-80 take into account the second coal price increase this summer.   The self-financing ratio in the five years 1979-80 to 1983-84 is 109 per cent, 99 per cent,99 per cent, 89 per cent and 78 per cent respectively.External FinancingThe negative requirement for external finance for 1979-80 of - 62m is equal to theindustry&apos;s cash limit for the year of - 68m at 1979-80 outturn prices.   The totalincreased financing requirements compared with Cmnd 7439 over the years 1980-81 to1982- 83 amount to  2$Sm.   The main reason is an increase in capital requirements,particularly a higher need for working capital.   This is related to revised assumptionsabove the level of and the cost of the industry&apos;s conventional fuel stocks (coal and Ioil) and nuclear fuel, including reprocessing.   The industry&apos;s working capitalrequirements are notoriously difficult to forecast since they are dependent on theestimated balance between debtors and creditors and on assumptions about&apos; fuel stocks Iand costs.   The slightly higher fixed asset requirements reflect     the changed profileof expenditure on Drax B and Units 3 and 4 of the Heysham AGR (in the case of Drax B Iexpenditure on boilers and turbo-generators is being incurred eariler to assistcontinuity of work on the shop floor, and in the case of Heysham more detailedassessments of costs have been made).The estimates of internal resources are  208m higher in total over 198O-81 to 1982-8Wthan in Cmnd 7439 due to higher tariff assumptions only partially offset by higherinterest cha .ges (increased borrowing).   The figures suggest that in each forecast yearnet borrowing from the National Loans Fund will increase and foreign borrowing decline.In 1979-80 much of the projected new NLF borrowing of  700m is required to refinancethe redeeming of  483m of British Electricity Stock.110CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALSCOTTISH ELECTRICITY BOARDS: m at 1979 Survey Prices (changeson Cmnd. 7439 in brackets);i)  NORTH OF SCOTLAND HYDRO-ELECTRIC BOARDledbnsgar110,Borrowing (net) 5K+11)      57C+17)       91 (-7) 161(47)of which leasingand short term -(-) -(-) -(-) -(-)153	1979-80	1980-81.	1981-82	1982*83	1983-84ipital Requirements:					Fixed Assets in UK	45(-5)		30(-)	27(-l4)	30 ISI Other	25(+S)	25(-H7)	12(-)	7t-2)	4TOTAL	70(-3)	66(4-30)	42(-)	34(-16)	34financed by:					Internal Resources	21(-14)	32(-5)	32(-4)	32(-3)	31Grants	13(-1)	14(4-5)	5(-2)	4 (-3)	3Borrowing (net)	36C+12)	20(4-30)	5(4-6)	-2(-10)	of which leasing					1 and short term	-8(-9)	3(4-3)	1(-)	1(4-1)	(2)   SOUTH OF SCOTLAND ELECTRICITY BOARD					1	1979-80	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-84Capital Requirements:					Fixed Assets in UK	86(-10)	122(4-23)	171(-H7)	237(4-3^)	208Other	33C+11)	4(-lO)	-9(-23)	-3U21)	11TOTAL	119(4-1)	126(4-13)	l62(-6)	234(4-13)	219financed by:					II-Internal Resources	68(-lO)	69(-4)	71(+1)	73C+6)	66Grants	-(-)	-(-)	-(-)	-(-)	11CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALInvestmentfSHEB&apos;s forecasts show a significant increase for 1980-81 and a substantial reductionIfor 1982/83.   In the early years of the period NSHEB&apos;s plans are dominated by thecompletion of the station at Peterhead (expected to be commissioned next year). There-ifter expenditure on generation drops sharply.   In the later years, the major outlayis on transmission and distribution.   Delays at Peterhead, largely the result ofindustrial relations difficulties, depressed the Boards expenditure last year belowthe White Paper forecast and have led to a sharp increase in forecast expenditure next&apos;year.   No significant expenditure on plant for the proposed Craigroyston pumped storagestation is expected during the survey period.   Expenditure in 1982/83 is thus wellbelow Cmnd 7^39.2. SSEB*s capital investment plans for the surveyperiod show little change fromCand 7^39.   The Board&apos;s forecast expenditure is mainly on the construction of a newAGR station at Torness.   Partly as a result of delays in clearing the site and partlybecause of the uncertainty over the future organisation of the nuclear industry,expenditure on the station last year and forecast expenditure during the current yearare both below Cmnd 7^39 levels, but in consequence the Board expects rather higherexpenditure next year.Market Assumptions3. The Boards forecast an annual increase in the demand for electricity inScotland over the next 10 years of between 3 and 4 per cent, assuming GDP growth of2f-3$ per annum.   In SSEB&apos;s area demand in expected to grow more slowly during thesurvey period (2^ to 3 per cent).   These forecast are lower than last years, but arestill above the growth rates predicted for England and Wales (in line with pastScottish experience).Internal Resources^    Both Boards increased their tariffs by an average of 9-10$ from 1 April 1979 toenable them to meet the target of break-even set by the previous Government for 1979/80.In subsequent years the Boards&apos; forecasts are based on a surplus on turnover of 156 in1980/81, 2% in 1981/82 and 3* thereafter.   To achieve this level of return annualtariff increases averaging 9-1056 are estimated to be needed, including a increasein 1980/81.   These projected increases assume (a) an annual inflation rate of 9%, (b)increases in the price of coal in line with inflation in the early years of the periodand at&apos; 2$ above in the later years and (c) increases in oil prices in line with thefate of inflation from now until 1982 but accelerating thereafter.   The ability of theboards to increase tariffs is limited by the strong competition from gas.   The Boards12CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALhave assumed an improvement in the price competitiveness of electricity in relation togas from about 1982/83.External Financing5. For 1979/80 both Board&apos;s external financial requirements are higher than in Cmnd7439*   These forecasts were based on a substantially larger tariff increase from1 April 1979 than that eventually implemented.   Their internal financing figures areconsequently substantially lower.   NSHEB&apos;s internal financing will also be lowerbecause of reduced depreciation as a result of the delay in commissioning Peterhead.Both Boards will have to bear additional costs towards the repair of reactor 4 atHunterston.   For 1980/81 both Board1s requirements are higher than in Cmnd 74391because of the lower than forecast tariff increases introduced this year and partlybecause of the additional capital expenditure at Torness and Peterhead.NSHEB Smelter Deficits6. The forecast grants to NSHEB towards the deficits incurred by the Board insupplying electricity to the British Aluminium Company (BACo) smelter at Invergordonexceeds the present provision in PES in 1980/81 by  5*6 million.   This increase isthe result of the prolonged outage of one of the reactors at Hunterston B nuclearpower station following the 1977 incident.   The figures are also subject to theoutcome of the dispute between NSHEB and BACo over the Company&apos;s liability forcharges for nuclear fuel reprocessing and certain other items.   The forecastsassume that this dispute will be resolved in the Board&apos;s favour and that BACowill pay all the disputed charges.   If the reverse happened and assuming itwere settled towards the end of the current year, the approximate provisionneeded in addition to baseline, including the amounts referred to above, would be asfollows:-fin1980/81 1981/82 1982/83 1983/8422 4 3 613CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALSCOTTISH TRANSPORT GROUPCapitalRequirements:1979/80 m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes from Cmnd 7439 in brackets)1980/811981/821982/83 1983/84Fixed assetsin UKOtherTOTAL14.5C+2.8)0.4(4-0.5)14.9C+3.3)11.2(4-0.7)-0.3C-0.1)10.9C+0.6)11.0(4-0.7)-0.5(-0.4)10.5C+0.3)10.0(-) 10.2-0.7C-0.6) -0.49.3C-0.6) 9.8Financed by:InternalResourcesGrantsNet borrowingof whichleasing andshort term2.4(4-0.4)11.7C+0.4)0.8(4-2.6)-(-)3.8(4-1.7)10.0(-0.6)-2.9C-0.5)4.3C+1.8)8.8(-0.4)-2.6(-l.l)4.6(4-1.6) 4.57.9C-0.8) 6.9-3.2(-1.4) -1.6-0.5C+0.5)   -0.3(-0.3)   -1.2(-0.6) 0.11. The Scottish Transport Group runs bus services throughoutScotland, except in the four main cities, shipping and haulageservices on Vest Coast of Scotland, and a number of ancilliaryactivities.   The bus operations generate 81 per cent of the Group&apos;stotal turnover of around  106 million.   12 per cent of theremainder comes from ferry services and the balance from the haulageand ancilliary activities.Recent Developments2. Capital expenditure in 1978/79 was higher than planned reflectinga once for all catching up of shortfall in bus deliveries fromprevious years delayed by strikes at the manufacturers. Discussionson a new financial target for the industry to supersede its existing14CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALstatutory duty to break even have been complicated by the existenceof deficit grants totalling about  8m in 1979 for both the busoperations and the shipping services.   In the meantime, the Groupfor its own planning purposes, has adopted a target of a 1-J per centreturn on turnover after recplacement cost depreciation but beforeinterest for its bus operations.   Some historic performanceindicators agreed with the Group were published in its recentannual report.   Discussions will continue with a view to developingperformance aims.Investment Plans3.     The Group&apos;s investment is primarily for the replacement ofexisting assets and takes into account a long term decline in demandfor bus travel, although some increase in demand for shippingservices is assumed.   The demand for bus travel is assumed todecline   at around L  per cent per annum over the period of thereview.   This is less of a decline than assumed in the past andreflects the group&apos;s experience over the last two years.   While theGroup&apos;s investment does not earn the RRR, its   policy of providingfull replacement cost depreciation and the relatively small capitalelement in its total costs (around 70 per cent of which are wages)mean that its prices are not too far away from the marginal costpricing dictated by the ERR.   The capital expenditure figures inthe review exclude the contingency provisions for repairing shipsand piers which the Group considers are necessary; shortfall thereforeis unlikely except as a result of strikes in the bus manufacturingindustry.   Deliberate postponement in the next twelve months wouldbe limited by forward commitments already made.   It would result (asdid delivery difficulties in recent years) in the lower quality andreliability of service as well as a larger than planned surpluson the Group&apos;s bus operations because of the provision in fares forreplacement cost depreciation; this could lead in turn to the TrafficCommissioners&apos; delaying or restricting fares increases which wouldcause the Group financial difficulties.   The capital investment figurare slightly higher than those in Cmnd 74-39; this largely reflects amore extensive programme of upgrading bus stations and depots.15CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALFinancing4.      The Group plans on the basis that it will generate thelevel of surplus needed to finance its capital investment;services will be reduced, costs cut, or fares increased asnecessary to do this.   For planning purposes it is assumed thatwages, fuel and maintenance costs which form the bulk of theGroup&apos;s costs will increase at more than the general rate ofinflation.   However the Group project fare increases at onlya little over the general rate of inflation partly reflectingproductivity gains from continued extension of one man operation.If the Group fails to achieve the desired surplus, additional NLFfinancing might be necessary.   Over the period of the reviewthe Group expects its major source of external finance tobe central and local government deficit grants for the loss-making ferry services to the Western Isles and bus servicesrespectively.   These grants are forecast to remain constant incash terms declining from 74$ to 54% as a proportion of theturnover.   Additional NLF borrowing is assumed in 1983/84 tooffset the effect of phasing out new bus grant - proposed inthe Transport Policy White Paper of 1977 (Cmnd - butotherwise the Group plan to repay the commencing capital debtwithout refinancing.16CONFIDENTIALm -
CONFIDENTIAL-ITISH RAILWAYS BOARD  million at 1979 Survey prices(changes from Cmnd 7439 in brackets)	1979-80	1980-81	1981-82	1982-83	1983-Sjital Requirements:					iied Assets in UK	335 (-13)	347 (-1)	347 (-1)	347 (-2)	347	- 135 1+34)	- 153 U5)	- 155 (f3)	- 156 (*3)	142Total	200 (+21)	194 (h-4)	192 (+2J	191 (+1)	205itanced By:					iternal resources	- 447 (+32J	- 469 (-80)	- 468 (-93)	- 441 (-66)	- 420ants*	601 (-10)	615 (h-74)	615 (+8D	616 U82)	616wowing (net)	46 (- 1)	49 (+10)	45 (+14)	16 (-15)	9! which, leasing and					fort term	-     1 (-18)	17 (+13)	2 (- 2)	1 (- 2)	1ie figures in brackets overstate the change in public expendUture.   When the full amount!the grant provided for in programme 6 is taken into account, there is no change onaid 7439.Background and recent developmentsIn 1978, the British Railways Board&apos;s rail business revenues including grants wereas follows:- mPassenger revenue 702Freight and parcels revenue 504Support payments for passenger servicesFrom central Government 382From PTE 40Grants in.respect of level crossings 11Grants accounted fqjp 38 per cent of total passenger receipts. In addition, BRBreceived  114m from central government in respect of historic deficiencies in itspension funds.   The Board&apos;s various subsidiary businesses - include shipping, hover-craft, property and hotels - produced a combined operating surplus of&amp;y?&amp; million and do not receive subsidy.17CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL2. The Boards investment programme was drawn up in line with the 1979 CorporateReview.   This will be completed later in the summer.   BRB have also undertaken orare in the process of undertaking seperate strategic reviews of a number of theirbusinesses: a freight strategy has been agreed   and discussions are in progressa number of obetween the Department and the Board on a Passenger Business Strategy and/strategicreviews eg parcels and infrastructure.in real terms3. A financial target of 5 per cent/by 1982 has been set for Sealink, the Board*sshipping subsidiary.   Discussions are in hand on the setting of targets for thecommercial rail businesses ie freight and inter-city passenger as well as for thesubsidiary businesses.   The Board have also agreed a list of performance indicatorsfor the rail business which are included in the 1978 Report and Accounts.Investment plans4. The Board&apos;.s original proposals for capital expenditure have been reducedas follows: m at 1978/79 prices1979/80     1980/81     1981/82     1982/83 1983/84- 21 - 19 - 19 - 24 - 405.     Almost all of the current programme consists of replacement of assets, forthe most part with modern equivalents.   Infrastructure investment (track renewals,signalling etc) account for 46 per cent of expenditure.   Capital expenditure inthe passenger business accounts for a further 27 per cent of the total, includingcommercial investment in the High Speed Train and the Advanced Passenger TrainProgramme due to begin in 1982.   BRB believe, however, that the present investmentceilings are insufficient to provide for the high level of essential renewalswhich will shortly fall due.   They have therefore bid for an increase in the ceilingover the five year period of  100m.6.     The peaking in expenditure on asset replacement in the 1980&apos;s is associatedparticularly with locomotives and diesel multiple units (DMu*s), the majorityof which were commissioned at the time of the modernisation plan in the late 1950&apos;^British Rail&apos;s workshops (operated by BR Engineering Ltd) no longer have thecapacity to accommodate short-term peaks in construction.   The Board thereforepropose to phase the investment over a longer period, accelerating the build oflocomotives in 1983 from 25 to 50 a year and investing in DMD&apos;s from 1982 onwards.This would account for  81 million of thdr total extra bid of  100 million.18
CONFIDENTIALThe investment figures proposed do not incorporate the Board&apos;s additionalid and maintain the ceiling on capital expenditure fixed in Cmnd 7**39-   The effectdisallowing this increase would be to defer the two major rolling stock itemsoco s and DMU s) together with cuts and rephasing of a variety of other projects.iiis reflects officials view that the Board have not so far justified expenditure ofe type proposed in the commercial businesses which will be required to meet ainancial target and earn a return on net assets (for instance, the proposal tocelerate construction of new freight locomotives and for expenditure on the Inter-ity business associated with the Advanced Passenger Train) and that for the &apos;social&apos;silway, it may be premature to sanction additional investment in DMU&apos;s given thatie replacement vehicles are still at the design stage.   Maintaining the recenttiling would defer decisions until strategy studies have been completed and progressawards setting and meeting the relevant financial targets for the commercial businessesan be demonstrated.   For the social railway the Board&apos;s plans will need to be consid-ed in the light of the Passenger Business Strategy Study, which will be completedlater this year.   A complementary study on infrastructure costs is also under way.ithout radical change in the size of the network, it is unlikely to reveal any&quot;ope for limiting investment beyond its denial to 3000 miles of lightly used trackdready assumed, as further cuts would involve restricting the movement of basicoiling stock.BRB normally overallocates capital resources to counteract the consistenttendency to underspend the investment ceiling by about 5 per cent.   The Board haveassumed that slippage in investment in 1979 and 1980 will be about 20 per cent, butin subsequent years believe that this can be contained to 15 per cent.financing &apos;5.    These forecasts represent the Board&apos;s latest views on business prospects basedM results flowing from the 1979 Corporate Review.   The reduced level of internalfesouces in the years 1980/81 and 1981/82 largely reflects slower progress thananticipated in implementing productivity improvements underlying the Freight Strategy,tod a less favourable outlook on industrial relations.   There remains considerableuncertainty about the Boards ability to achieve the improved results envisaged infte last two years of the Review, in the light of the prospects for volume growthto the passenger business and of progress to date on demanning, although firmGovernment support may help here.19CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL10. Grant requirements show an increase on Cmnd 7^39 largely because the Boardare now assuming full take-up of the PES provision for the Passenger ServiceObligation grant.   The need for additional grant reflects higher costs e.g wagesand fuel and the limited scope for real pricing in sectors other than the commuterroutes or for manpower reductions.11. Total borrowing requirements (including leasing) follow directly from theBoard!s forecast of internal resources, given that the maximum grant paymentis assumed.   Thus, excesses over Cmnd 7^39 in the region of  10m are forecastin 1980/81 and 1981/82 followed by a considerably lower requirement in 1982/83( 15m below Cmnd 7459) and 1983/8^.20CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALNATIONAL BUS COMPANY a at 1979 Surrey prices(Changes from Cmnd 7439 in brackets)Capital Requirements:     1979/80    1980/81        1981/82       1982/83 1983/84fixed assets in UK 57.6(*1.5) 53.8(-3-9) 55.2(-4.0) 56.1(-4.7) 56.6Other 3.7(-)       1.8(-1.4)    2.9(*2.5)    3.5(*3.D 3.6total 61.3C+1.5) 55.6(-5.3)   58.K-1.5)   59.6C-1.6) .60.2Financed by: ^Internal resources -13.7(-10.7) -8.5(-7.6) -1.0(-0.8) -0.4(-2.D -0.6Grants 53.0(*4.1)   53.6(*3.7) 49.8(*4.3) 45.9(*4.7) 41.9Borrowing (net) 22.0(*8.1)   10.5(-1.4)   9.3(-5.0) 14.K-4.2) 18.9of which, leasingand short term 6.4(-) 6.9(*0.5)   6.9(*0.5)   6.9C+0.6) 6.8This table assumes that a 10$ - eut in NBC investment has been adopted.Recent Developmentsll.  In recent years the NBC has made small but consistent profits after receipt ofrevenue support.   In 1978 the Company made a profit on trading of  9.7m. Aftertaking into account local authority support (of  27.7m), interest charges andhistoric cost depreciation, the surplus retained totalled  17.7m.   However, theforecast outturn for 1979/80 has been revised from an expected profit of  13m to aloss of about  4m because of a wage award averaging 9*9 per cent as against the 5per cent budgeted for, because of substantially larger than expected increases inithe price of fuel, and because of the severe winter which resulted in lost revenueand damage to about one third of the bus fleet.2.  The difficulties have also delayed agreement on the financial target to be set(or the Company.   Nevertheless, a list of performance indicators has been agreed andvas published in the NBC&apos;s 1978 Accounts, illustrating the productivity improvementsof recent years.Investment3* The bulk of proposed.investment (75 per cent) is to finance vehicle replacementaad much of the remainder relates to the improvement and replacement of maintenanceand depot facilities, some of which need raising to the standards laid down by the21CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALHealth and Safety at Work Act.4.   NBG&apos;s investment plans should be viewed against the background of a consisteniand continuing decline in passenger numbers of 2.5 per cent a year throughout thereview period.   The implementation of the results of a comprehensive marketanalysis project is intended to enable the route network to be rationalised and aj5 per cent reduction in vehicle miles operated to be achieved over the next fiveyears without significant loss of custom but with appreciable savings in costs.The Company consequently plan to reduce the size of the vehicle fleet by 7 per centto 16,400 buses b^1983.   The Company would also like to reduce the average age oflthe double-deck fleet from 8.6 to 6.3 years over the period of the review bymaintaining an intake of 1400 vehicles a year.   However, provision for thisimprovement - equivalent to approximately 140 buses a year - has been eliminated jpending a thorough examination of the financial case for the Company&apos;s replacementand maintenance policy.   As a result, investment in fixed assets will be below thelevels implied by Cmnd 7439.5*   Investment by the Company does not earn the RRR.   This reflects the socialrole of the Company in providing services at the request of local authoritieson cost-ineffective routes.   It is intended that the financial target will bedefined in terms of a requirement to break even (by. a date to be specified) after Icharging replacement cost depreciation.   There has been no significant shortfall oninvestment in recent years.   A further reduction in investment to a level belowthe current proposal would be likely to increase costs on revenue account.heFinancing6. The Company is constrained in its ability to raise fares revenue sufficientlyto finance vehicle replacement in the near future from internally generatedresources, since the size and timing of fares increases has to be determined by tindividual subsidiaries in consultation with local authorities who provide revenuejsupport, and also requires the consent of the Traffic Commissioners.   The policyfollowed is to price up in accordance with general inflationary trends, therebyminimising loss of traffic volume which has been found to be highly sensitive toreal increases in fares.   It has not been possible to assess the potential impactof recent very sharp increases in fuel costs and the need to reduce the consuaptiojof oil on the level of passenger traffic.7. Since the Company does not envisage the generation of any internal resources imthe five year review period, it will be heavily dependent on the continuation of22CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALlocal authority revenue support, new bus grant and NLF borrowing to finance theinvestment programme.   The reduction in the proposed investment programme means thatthe need for external finance is kept at a level consistent with Cmnd 7^39. TheCompany assumes that the support payments by local authorities for runninguneconomic services will continue at present levels in real terms (equivalent toabout 7   of turnover) and that, with no compensatory increase in such support tooffset the phasing out of new bus grant between 1981 and 1985 - proposed in theTransport Policy White Paper of 1977 (Cmnd 6836) - it will he necessary to increasetheir borrowing in order to finance their capital investment programme.23CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALNATIONAL FREIGHT CORPORATIONCm at 1979 Survey prices)(Changes from Cmnd 7439 in brackets)Hfltal Requirements:       1979-80     1980-81     1981-82     1982-83 1983-84fixed assets in UKharfetal:inanced by:Internal resourcesBrantsSorrowing (net)if which, leasing andshort term3M+D	37(44)	374*4)		405(-6)	3(-7)	3(-8)	2(-7)	239(-5)	4o(-3)	4o(-4)	42(-)	4213(-3)	17(-D	20(4-1)	25(4-1)	2510(-2)	7(-2)	6(-2)	4(-2)	416(-)	16(- )	lM-3)	13(4-1)	1316(-)	16(-)	l4(-3)	13(*D	13Recent developmentsFollowing the financial reconstruction of the NFC under the Transport Act1978, (which reduced capital debt by roughly a third and provided assistancein respect of certain historic liabilities derived from BRB) the Corporationmade a small profit in 1978 of  0.3m after paying interest to the Secretaryof State.   Prospects for improvement in 1979 are uncertain because of thedisruption to operations stemming from the road haulage dispute (costing 8m) and a 20 per cent pay award by the Central Arbritration Committeegiving NFC drivers parity with the private sector.2.    Discussions are in progress on a financial target for NFC.   NFC havepublished a short list of performance indicators in their 1978 Report andAccounts.   The Government&apos;s Manifesto undertook that shares in the NFCwould be offered to the public.   Work is in hand with a view to implementingthis undertaking, which may ultimately affect the status of NFC as a nationalisedindustry.24CONFIDENTIAL
CQHKDESflALInvestment Proposals3. NFC have expanded the scope of their activities in recent years by investmentin profitable businesses which tend to be concerned with freight handling andstorage and with the provision of specialised transport services. TheCorporation believe that this strategy should be continued, and it is invest-ment in these activities, designed to diminish the Corporation8s reliance onthe less profitable general delivery and general haulage businesses whichaccounts for much of the excess of NFCs proposed investment over the ceilingset in by Cmnd 7^39.k.     NFC has endeavoured to ensure that much of their investment is channelledinto preferred activities earning a high rate of return, though the achievementby the Corporation of the RRR overall has not yet been demonstrated. Howevera significant proportion of their funds - up to 30% between 1979 and 1981 -continues to go to the less preferred areas which include the general parcelsand haulage businesses run by their largest subsidiaries National Carriers Ltd,Roailine and British Road Services.   In each case, the investment is associatedwith reorganisation, rationalisation and some reduction in the scale of theactivities at a rate which NFC believe to be consistent with the maintenaneeof satisfactory industrial relations.   Manpower requirements are likely to fallby about 3% between 1978 and 198l.5.    About 60% of NFCs investment is associated with vehicle replacement. Thersis probably some scope for postponement, although this is limited by the factthat orders are placed well in advance and reduced investment would in due coursHincrease maintenance costs and affect the saleability of NFC.Financing7. A condition of the financial reconstruction was that the Corporationshould be self-financing with no access to NLF finance for the time being.Their investment programme has therefore been restricted to what can befinanced from internal resources, leasing,and grants.   It is thereforeconditional on the Corporation&apos;s ability to achieve its financial forecasts.8. The Corporation expect to increase their trading profits from an estimated 8m in 1979-80 to  33m in 1983-84.   Trading profits will increase from 1.6%to 5% of turnover.   This assumes the development of profitable businesses andan increase in productivity and depends to a considerable extent on success inrunning down the least profitable parts of the enterprise in terms of manpoweron.and capital employed and rationalising its operation as well as^stabilijy onthe industrial relations front. ^
0OSFIDEHTIAL9*    The Corporation&apos;s access to leasing finance is governed by va ceilinguplifted annually to reflect general inflation.   No decision has yet beentaken on the ceiling or the method of adjusting it after 1980-3.1, but theCorporation have planned on the assumption that the present formula will beunchanged.10.   The grants received by the Corporation are those under the 1978 TransportAct in respect of historic pensions together with a tapering capital grant toNCL       of up to  15m over 3 years to meet its cash requirements followingthe capital reconstruction.26CONFIDENTIAL
V/VUU XJJXiU 1xa1jBRITISH TRANSPORT DOCKS BOARDCapital Requirements: 1979/80Fixed assets in UK 15.5C+0.1)Other 1.2(40.6)Total 16.7C+0.7)Cm at 1979 Survey prices(Changes from Cmnd 7^39 in brackets)1980/81       1981/82 1982/8317.3(40.7)2.0(-0.l)19.3(40.6)17.5(40.9)2.1(-0.1)19.6(40.8)17.3(40.7)2.1(-0.1)19.4(40.6)1983/8417.22.119.3Financed by :Internal resources    23-l(-6.2) 26.5(-5.8) 28.l(-4.9)Grants                  *       -(-) -(-) -(-)Borrowing (net)         -6.4(46.9) -7.2(46.4) -8.5(45.7)of which leasing andshort term28.9(-6.3)- (   - )-9.5(46.9)-6.4(46.9)   -0.4(45.9)   -2.0(44.8) -3.3(-t4.9)30.1-10.8-4.9Recent DevelopmentsIn recent years, the British Transport Docks Board has been consistently profitable,showing a surplus on revenue account after allowing for replacement cost deprecia-tion, interest and taxation.   This record was maintained in 1978:   the Board madean operating profit of  35*3m and the surplus retained totalled  7m, equivalent toa return of 16.9$ on net assets after historic cost depreciation and before interestand tax.   This compares with their agreed financial target of achieving a 20% returnby 1980.   Nevertheless, performance in 1978 did not quite come up to the Board&apos;sexpectations with the result that it is not now expected that the financial targetwill be achieved before 1982.   Turnover and profits were slightly lower than fore-cast, due mainly to the effects of industrial disputes; and investment, at  9.3m,fell well short of the intended  15.1m due to the failure of a number of &quot;customerdemand&quot; schemes to materialise.2.     The Board finance all their investment from internally generated resources.In recent years they have also repaid a substantial proportion of their commencingcapital debt before the dates on which it was due.   During 1978/791 the Board madethree early repayments of debt, totalling some  21m.Investment3*    The Board make modest and realistic assumptions about growth in port trafficand expect to invest about  85m (at 1978/79 prices) in the review period.27CONFIDENTIAL
CO0ISESTIAL4.     BTDB allocate their investment resources between projects which they proposeto carry out on their own initiative (about 75J0t and &quot;customer demand schemes&quot;.The former include expenditure on maintenance, replacement and general improvementsto the ports; the latter represent schemes which are undertaken to handle specificcargoes which a customer has contracted to move through BTDB ports.   The Boardhave identified a number of such schemes which may be demanded in future years,but have allowed in their investment programme for only a proportion to come tofruition.   Since customer demand schemes can involve sizeable investment, there is Ialways the possibility that the investment ceiling will be inadequate to allow allthe required expenditure to be committed.   Equally, as in 1978/79t customer demandschemes may be a significant source of shortfall.5. The Board consider that the return on their investment programme taken as awhole meets the RRR. This claim is being discussed with them. Were cuts to bemade, they would fall on investment unrelated to profitable customer demand schemedPostponement would increase the long-term cost of such investment and might affect Ithe Board&apos;s ability to repay debt in future years.Financing6. In general, since the Board operate in a competitive environment, charges needto be in line with those obtained elsewhere and are set at a level at which costsare covered.   Charges in relation to specific customer demand facilities are fixedby agreements involving guaranteed minimum returns, cost variation clauses and ashare of returns above those necessary to generate the guaranteed minimum.7. The Board attach great importance to the repayment of their commencing capitaldebt, the residue of which now totals about  43m.   The speed of repayment ofoutstanding loans is determined by the Board&apos;s need to maintain the port infrastruc-ture and to retain sufficient to compete and provide for new traffic.   No provision^is made for premature repayment in&apos;3979/80 in consequence of the three instalmentspaid during 1978/79-   However, in each year thereafter, the Board intend to makerepayments of  8.2m in cash terms.28CONFIDENTIAL
VUB  XlA&amp;EIXXJlXiBRITISH WATERWAYS BOARD m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes from Cmnd 7439 in brackets)1979/80       1980/81       1981/82 1982/831983/84CapitalRequirements:Fixed assetsin UKOtherI TotalFinanced by:Internal *ResourcesGrants *Borrowing (net)Of which leasingand short-term4.4C-0.2)- (-)4.4(-0.2)6.8(4-2.1)- (-)6.8(4-2.1)3.8(-0.9)- (-)3.8(-0.9)2.6(-2.l)- (-)2.6(-2.1)-19.3(-0.S) -17.7C+1.7)21.0(4-1.4) 20.7(-)2.7(40.4) 3.8(40.4)0.2(40.2) 0.2(40.2)-19.4(40.2) -l9.8(-2^)20.9(-) 20.9(-)2.3(-Ll) 1.5(40.1)0.3(40.3) 0.3(40.3)2.62.6- 19.820.91.50.3Tor 1980/81 onwards the comparison with Cmnd 7439 has been adjusted to incorporateIthe additional grant allocation for arrears of maintenance provided on Programme 8.Recent DevelopmentsIhe Board are responsible for the upkeep of some 2000 miles of waterways throughoutBritain.   About 350 miles of commercial waterways are maintained for freight trafficand 1100 miles for navigation by pleasure craft.   The network also has water supplyand land drainage functions.   The BUB has its own freight-carrying fleet, docks,warehouses and inland freight terminals.   In 1978 the Board made a loss of about 17m on all its operations which was met by Government grant.2.    Following the Government&apos;s abandonment of the proposal to merge the waterwayswith the water industry generally under the aegis of a National Water Authority -outlined in the Water White Paper of 1977 (Cmnd 6876) - the future organisationand objectives of the BUB have still to be decided and will be the subject ofconsultation with the Board and other interested bodies.   In the course of consultations,I the applicability of financial targets and performance aims to the Boardfs activitieswill be considered.3.    Since last year&apos;s review, a major new investment project, the improvement ofthe Sheffield and South Yorkshire Navigation (SSYN) has been started.   This is intendedto provide an important test of the commercial viability of freight waterways.Hephasing of expenditure on this, in order to reflect a more realistic spend profile,has resulted in higher capital expenditure in 1980/81 than assumed in Cmnd 7439, offset. 29
uuMjriiua-riAijby lower expenditure in subsequent years.Investmentk.    The Board&apos;s expenditure on canal maintenance is charged to revenue account.About one half of the capital programme is accounted for by the SSYN project.The remainder consists of improvements to the facilities at the principal docksand depots together with the provision for replacement of craft, plant andequipment and, subject to what may emerge from the consultations referred to in Iparagraph 2 above, these operations are expected to continue as much as before. INew investment in freight service projects is expected to earn a return of some 8%after payment of interest and on historic costs.   Other expenditure, especially Ion replacement items, does not, by and large, improve the return on average netassets.   In 1978 the Board underspent their investment provision owing toindustrial action by their staff.   Postponement of investment would affect the Board&apos;!ability to replace equipment and thus to keep up their planned maintenance programme.Financing5.    The Board&apos;s commercial activities are in competition with both road and railfreight.   The Board set water and amenity charges at the level they considerthe market will bear while charges for freight and commercial activities are expectedto be raised in line with increases in costs.   The deficit on revenue account iaflmet by Government grant which is the Board*s major source of finance^and accountsfor about 60$ of turnover.   Cmnd 7^39 provided an additional  5m a year from 1980/81onwards for arrears of maintenance.   The capital cost of the SSTN project will befinanced by additional NLF borrowing and by grants from South Yorkshire County Oemncland the European Regional Development Fund.30CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBRITISH AIRWAYS BOARD1 m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes on Cmnd;7439 in brackets)1979/80 1980/81 1981/82    1982/83 1983/84Capital Requirements;Fixed assets in UK    304(-36) 390(4-37) 355(*42) &apos;394(4-86) 402Other                         15 (-1) 9 (+1) 12 (4-3)      5 (-1) 7Total                       3l9(-37) 399(4-38) 367(4-45)   399(4-85) 409Financed by:Internal resources     16l(-64) 204(4-38) 237 (4-45) 252(4-52) 260Grants                            - -              -              - -Borrowing (net)         158(4-2?) 195   (-) 130    (-) 147(4-33) 149of which, leasing and short term-9 (-9) -8 (-8) -8   (-8)   -8 (-8) -8Background and Recent DevelopmentsCompetition in the international airline market is increasing.The latest Corporate Plan (GF7) of British Airways (BA) is designedto maintain their market share whilst continuing to generate acceptablelevels of profit.   At the same time BA faces a heavy fleet replacementprogramme over the next 5 years or so (see paragraphs 6 and 7 below).2. BA&apos;s profit before interest in 1978/79 is expected to be  120m ona turnover of  1400m (net profit  76m.), This is lower than previousforecasts and reflects a downturn in the final quarter to which severeweather, the situation in Iran and the continued strength of the poundcontributed.3. BA*s financial target for 1975/76 to 1978/79 required an average11% return on mean net assets (at historic cost) over the four years,compared with a probable outturn of just under 10%.   A new target hasbeen set which requires an average 6% real accounting rate of returnon&apos;net assets over the three years 1979/80 - 1981/82 (equivalent toa 16% return at historic cost).   This target is intended to be31CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALconsistent with BA earning a rate of return of at least 5%in real terms on new investment and implies substantial increasesin the productivity both of aircraft and of employees.4. During 1978/79, the previous Government agreed to write offan amount of public dividend capital equal to the purchase priceof BA&apos;s Concorde fleet, since it was evident that Concorde couldnot generate sufficient returns to cover amortisation and servicingof the capital employed.   The proposed arrangements are designedto remove the adverse effect which Concorde previously had onBA*s profit levels.Investment Plans5. BA have carried out a study of the likely size and nature ofthe international airline market by 1986 and the measures theymust take to remain competitive.   This study assumed that airlinecompetition would continue to increase, and forecast that the totalpassenger market would double by 1986; that the most significantgrowth sector would be (low fare) leisure travel and that BA&apos;syields in real terms would be reduced in 1986 by 42% on shorthaul and 20% on long haul compared to 1978 levels.6. BA&apos;s strategy to remain competitive and profitable is to aimat maintaining their share of the total market and reduce costlevels by 2.8% pa in real terms by increasing the efficiency andproductivity of their aircraft and employees.   An important elementof the strategy is the ability to operate the most efficientaircraft available, and over the next five years some  1900m isplanned for expenditure on new aircraft and spares out of a totalcapital investment programme of just over  2400m.   In additionto catering for expansion of capacity to maintain market share,the former figure also includes a significant provision towardsreplacing over 90 aircraft in the existing fleet, which will notmeet new international noise regulations due for application inthe UK on 1 January. 1986, and which are in any case becomingincreasingly uneconomic to operate. During 1978, BA were givenGovernment approval.to acquire 28 Boeing 737s and 19 Boeing 757s32CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALto commence replacement of Tridents and 707s on European routesin 1980.   These aircraft are on order.   Long range Tristars andBoeing 747s are planned to replace VC10 capacity.   It is estimatedthat 40% of the planned investment in aircraft is for replacementof capacity and 60% for expansion.7. The need to replace and expand capacity to maintain totalmarket share and continue to serve all market segments is dictatedby BA&apos;s prediction that present differences in profitabilitybetween their route groupings will level out by 1986.   The shorthaul routes where BA is less profitable are generally those onwhich they are flying old uneconomic aircraft.   The higher thanaverage profits on some long haul routes are expected to bereduced by increased competition.8. The contributions of improved aircraft and staff productivitytowards total cost reduction targets are interdependent. BA&apos;snew aircraft can play their part but little confidence can beattached to the staff element.   BA*s staff productivity is poorby airline standards and attempts to improve it in the past haveregularly fallen short of targets.   There is a history of poorindustrial relations.   BA acknowledge that some scepticism isjustified but are adopting a more rigorous approach to productivitywhich they believe will show greater success than in the past.They plan to share with the workforce the benefits of improvedproductivity in the form of pay awards which they calculate willbe twice the comparable national average.   In addition it isintended that agreement to necessary changes in working practiceswill be firmly secured at the shop floor level throughout theairline.   The latest Corporate Plan requires an average 8.5%increase per year in available tonne kilometres per employee andit is intended that this should be achieved by maintaining existingoverall staff numbers whilst absorbing increased business.Financing; Requirements9. At outturn prices the total level of net external borrowingprojected for 1979/80 to 1983/84 is  980m in relation to a capitalexpenditure programme totalling  2418m (a self financing ratio of33CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL59%).   The projected profit levels for these five years representan average real accounting rate of return on net assets of 6.8%(cf 1979/80 - 1981/82 statutory target of 6%).10.   External financing requirements for 1980/81 and 1981/82have been kept at the levels in last year&apos;s investment andfinancing review on a constant price basis.   Apart&apos; from a 10m pa injection of FDC, all BA&apos;s finance requirements forthe next five years are planned to be met by overseas borrowingswith Treasury guarantee and will almost certainly take the formof US dollar loans.3*CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBRITISH AIRPORTS AUTHORITY m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes on Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)1979/80     1980/81 1981/82 1982/83 1983/84Captial Requirements;Fixed assets in UK      40(-14)   79(4-24) 75(4-24)   - 76(4-18) 70Other                              5 (4-2)     9 (+1) 8 (-4) 8 (-3) 4Total                            45(-12)   88(4-25) 83(4-20) 84(4-15) 74Financed by;Internal resources      45(-12)   57 (-7) 68 (4-1) 73 78Grants                           1   (-)     -   (-) -   (-) - (-1)Borrowing (net)           -1   (-)   31(4-32) 15(-H8) 11(4-14) -5of which, leasing and short term15(4-15) -Recent DevelopmentsFour fifths of the BAA&apos;s traffic is handled at its three Londonairports, Heathrow, Gatwick and Stansted, and one fifth at its fourairports in Scotland.   This pattern is expected to continue.2.   The White Paper on Airports Policy (Cmnd 7084) of February 1978envisaged that the demand for airport capacity in South East Englandup to 1990 should be met by expansion of present capacity of 47million passengers per annum at the BAA London airports to 67 million(the capacity of the municipal airport at Luton, which also serves theLondon area is expected to increase from 3 million to 5 millionpassengers).   Revised forecasts are now being prepared by theDepartment of Trade&apos;s Air Traffic Forecasting Working Party in thecontext of planning for the Third London Airport likely to be neededfrom the late ,1980s.   Including Luton they are provisionally expectedto lie between 55 million and 63 million in 1985 and between 68 millionand 84 million in 1990.   The BAA capital investment plans for theSurvey period are related to the average forecast of 59 millionpassengers at the south east airports including Luton in 1985. Thefigures take account of current trends in oil prices, consumerincome, the substantial growth in low fare traffic in 1978 etc.35CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL3. The outturn capital requirement for 1978/79 includingchanges in working capital was  44.7 million compared with aforecast of  50.7 million.   A shortfall of  9m on fixed capitalprojects planned to cost  42.5 million was due to deferment ofprojects in order to ease the problems caused by the surge insummer traffic in 1978 and delays caused by the hard winter.4. Discussions on a financial target for the industry are inprogress. It is proposed that this should imply the achievementof the :Required Rate of Return within three years in respect ofrevenue from aerodrome traffic and commercial charges, excludingthe revenue from duty-free operations which would continue to bemaximised.Investment Plans5. The Authority&apos;s proposed capital investment for 1980/81 issome 45 per cent higher than was expected a year ago and 45 percent and 30 per cent higher for the succeeding two years respectively.;This is the result of a much quicker build-up of work on the FourthTerminal at Heathrow (which has been delayed by a longer publicenquiry than was expected) costing 20m initially in 1980/81, andbringing forward a number of smaller projects at Heathrow to mitigatethe consequences of the delay to the Fourth Terminal.   These willcost a further  33 million, the principal items being the pier 3 onthe eastern apron for Jumbo jets and substantial improvements toTerminals 1 and 3.   In 1980/81 Gatwick accounts for projectstotalling  29m (eg the development of the Northern Apron, thedevelopment of the cargo area, and an amount of  1.5 million asa BAA investment in equity of a company which will build a newairport hotel).   The second terminal at Gatwick enters the figuresin 1981/82 when again subject to the planning procedures,  3 millionwill be spent rising to  21 million in each of the following twoyears.   Only minor projects are proposed for Stansted and the Scottishairports.6. Starting in 1981/82  35 million has been allocated for the ThirdLondqn Airport: this could be spent at Stansted if that is theeventual choice.    (The figures relating to individual projects aresubject to an overall allowance for slippage of about 25 per cent.)The incidence and timing of this expenditure is of course subject toeventual Ministerial decisions about the requirement for a new airport.36CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL7. All the projects proposed are capable of earning the RequiredRate of Return of 5 per cent, provided that the BAA set their chargesso as to achieve it.   The Authority have already reduced theirproposed expenditure on the Fourth Terminal from  30 million to 20 million and consider that there is no scope for major reductionswithout accepting a serious deterioration of conditions at Heathrow.Financing8. The BAA^ financing provisions assume increases in productivityof 3 per cent per annum in terms of numbers of passengers handledper employee, and expenditure before depreciation per passenger atconstant prices is planned to fall at about 2-J per cent per annum.In previous years the BAA&apos;s policy has been to generate sufficientfunds to cover 100 per cent of its capital expenditure and to meetthe repayments due on existing loans including the commencing capitaldebt.   With the pressure on their resources caused by the increasedcapital expenditure required to meet higher passenger flows this hasnow been qualified so that in periods of severe recession orexceptionally high capital expenditure, the Authority would achievea minimum of 60 per cent self-financing.   The real rate of returnon capital employed (trading profit before interest as a percentageof net assets employed) is expected to rise from 3*6 per cent in1978/79 to 6.0 per cent over the five year period, including revenuesfrom the sale of duty-free goods.   In 1979/80 operational income isexpected to increase by 6 per cent following price increases whichcame into effect on 1 April and a mid-year increase to bring feesinto line with inflation is being considered.   Projections for lateryears assume increases in line with inflation.   Increases in exciseduties will allow increases in the prices charged for duty free goods.The increased revenue will not cover the capital apend in 1980/81 and,for purposes of the baseline figures, it is accordingly proposed touse all the  15 million which is held in short term deposits and tocall on  16 million from the National Loans Fund; a further  15mwould be taken from the NLF in 1981-82 and  llm in 1982-83 (1978*79prices).37CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALPOST OFFICE1. Financial targets now exist -for all three businesses (Posts,Telecommunications and National Girobank).   Assuming that thesetargets are met, the financing of the Corporation&apos;s investmentprogramme will be entirely from internally generated funds exceptin 1980/81.   Over the Survey period the Corporation will be asubstantial net repayer of loans and will thus contributesignificantly towards reducing the Public Sector BorrowingRequirement.2. Performance aims also exist for the two main businesses: forTelecommunications the aim, taking 1977/78 as a base, is to achievea general reduction in real unit costs of 5 per cent a year over thefive years to 1982/83; for Posts, that real unit costs overallshould not increase over that period.   The achievement of theseaims, which supplement the financial targets, will require asustained increase in efficiency and will contribute to keepingdown price increases.TELECOMMUNICATIONS3.   The Telecommunications business&apos;s investment and financingforecasts are as follows:  million at 1979 Survey prices(Changes on Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)1979/80 1980/81 1981/82 1982/83 1983/84Capital requirements:Fixed assets in UK    983C-112) 1118C+5) 1102(-25) 1099C+12) 1133Other                          69 C+23) 64(-47) 68(-13) 100 (+1) 48Total                      1052.(-89) 1182(-42) 1170(-38) 1199(*13) 1181Financed by:Internal resources   1079C-126) 1128(-169)1200C-187) 1276(-216) 1352Net borrowing -27C+37) 54C+125) -30(*146) -77C+229) -171of which, short-term borrowing106(*18)     158(*116)   94 (*33)   -6(*223) -8038CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL4. The changes in the financing figures since Cmnd 7439 are duemainly to the setting of a new financial target for TelecommunicationsThe Cmnd 7439 figures were based on the (conventional) assumptionthat the Telecommunications financial target would be reset at thesame level (a 6% annual real return on mean net assets) when itexpired at the -end of 1978/79.   In fact, the financial targetsubsequently agreed with the Post Office was a real rate of returnof 5% pa for the three years from 1979/80 to 1981/82, which isconsidered to be more consistent with the Required Rate of Returnof 5% on new investment than was the previous target.Investment Plans5. The bulk of the expenditure (over 90%) is on plant and machineryand of that telephone exchange equipment (37%) and subscribers&apos;circuits (22%) make up the largest part. The level of expenditure onfixed assets reflects the continuing buoyant demand for telephones.!(This has resulted in the Post Office&apos;s own forecasts for newtelephone lines in 1978779 being exceeded).   The point of inflectionfor growth in hew telephones now appears to have been reached (ratherlater than the Post Office had forecast) so that growth rates ingeneral are expected to begin to ease from now on with the approachof saturation.6. The figures take into account the following recent developments!the further acceleration of the installation programme for the semi-electronic TXE4 (and later TXE4A) exchanges (this will bring abouta significant improvement in the quality of service for relativelyminor additional expenditure -  93m over the 5 years   when lowermanning levels and maintenance requirements are taken into account)Mthe expansion of Prestel, the Post Office&apos;s viewdata service, intoa public service at a cost of  94m over the period; and, for the firsttime, provision ( 23m) for expenditure on System X orders beyond theSystem X exchanges which in 1977 it was decided should be broughtforward from the main programme, in order to help the UK telecommun-Mications manufacturing industry&apos;s internal competitiveness .Market Background7. Over the Survey period continued growth is expected of 35% ^ Ieschange connections, 38% in local calls and 52% in trunk callsICONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL(though for the reasons given above the rate of growth inexchange connections is likely to fall over that period). Thisgrowth is partially attributable to a continuing reduction intelecommunications tariffs in real terms coupled with marketingwhich is largely directed at stimulating off peak use.Price and Productivity Assumptions8. The forecast assumes that the new ^financial target of a realrate of return of 5% on net assets will be achieved in each ofthe years 1979-80 to 1983-84.   Achievement of a 5% real rate ofreturn is expected to require tariff increases averaging 3*4% ineach year from April 1980, reflecting a fall in the real cost oftelecommunications consistent with the performance aim set in thePost Office White Paper of 1978 (Cmnd 7292).   The tariff increasesare expected to be levied in a way that will progressively reducethe present under-pricing of rentals relative to call charges.9. The forecast of:manpower shows a slight drop in the currentyear compared with 1978/79, increasing, thereafter to a level of235*000 at the end of the period.   This implies that the growthof 34% in system size and 40% in inland calls as well as the muchhigher growth rates in external services will be achieved with anincrease of less than 1% in staffing levels.   Overall this representsan increase in output per head (measured as income at constant-prices) of 60% over the plan period.POSTS10. The Postal Business expects no new borrowing during theSurvey period and will continue to make repayments of NLF loans.This is on the assumption that the financial target of 2% returnon turnover is achieved in 1979/80 and that an equivalent targetwill be set when the current one expires in April 1980.   To achievethose targets the Post Office aim to maximise profitable growth andto improve productivity in order to counter the impact on prices(and hence volume) of assumed increases in real wages and to meetthe longer term threat from developments in communicationstechnology.40CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIAL11.   The investment and financing forecasts for the Postal businessare as follows:  million at 1979 survey prices(Changes on Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)1979/80 1980/81 1981/82 1982/83 1983/84Capital requirements:Fixed assets in UK      45(-14) 58 (-4-) 64- (-) 62 (+2V 53Other                          -55(-4.2J -   (-) - (-) - (-)Total                        -10(-55) 58 (-4-) 64- (-) 62 (4-2) 53Financed by;Internal resources 66 (-9) 77(-13) 80(-18) 84(-16) 87Net borrowing -76(-47)   -190-10)   --.16(4-19)   -22C+18) -34of which, short-term borrowing-64-(-56)   -10(4-10)     -3C+19) -14-(4-18)-31Investment Progrgrmnp12. The capital investment programme of the Postal business coversprincipally new buildings and plant for the mechanisation programme,replacement of old buildings, and maintaining (and as necessaryexpanding) the vehicle fleet.   There will be some increase in theexpenditure on mechanisation equipment both for letters and parcelscompared with the assumptions used in Cmnd 74-39.   But this will bemore than offset by a reduction in the building programme. ThePostal business has reviewed the methods by which is assesses itscapital expenditure in the light of past shortfalls, and hasintroduced new, more stringent criteria.Market Background13. Despite a 4-% growth in total business volume (including lettersparcels and counter business) in 1978/79 a further increase of onlyabout 1% is projected by the end of the Survey period. However,this is higher than the volume forecast in last year&apos;s investmentreview: the 1982/83 figures are up by 5% for letters and 11% forparcels.   Letter volume is expected to fall by 4-% between 1978/79and 1983/84, with the rate of decline increasing towards the end ofthe period, as a result of increased competition from alternativecommunications technologies and changing social habits.41CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALPrice and Productivity Assumptions14. Inland letter prices are expected to increase by about 7%in real terms by 1983/84.    This will compensate for the sharp fallin real prices in 1978/79 compared to 1977/78 and is consistentwith the objective of no real increase in unit costs over the period1977/78 to 1982/83.   The forecast improvement in productivity of 8%over the period (in addition to productivity gains resulting fromletter -mechanisation), the achievement of forecast letter volumelevels, and a 25% reduction in overtime will all be important forthe attainment of this objective.GIRC AND REMITTANCE SERVICES15. An addition of  8m ( 4m in the form of a loan from the NationalLoans Fund, and  4m in the form of public dividend capital) was madein 1978/79 to Girobank&apos;s capital base in line with growth in thebusiness.   A new financial target, for the period 1979/80 to 1981/82,has been agreed.   This takes the form of an average annual return of13% before interest on its net assets plus a further  5m over the3-year period, from which it will be in a position to make asubstantial reduction in its accumulated deficit.   Girobank isseeking to increase the number of its personal accounts.16.   The investment and financing forecasts for National Girobankare as follows:  million at 1979 survey prices(changes on Cmnd 7439 in brackets)1979-80 1980-81 1981-82 1982-83 1983-84Capital requirements:Fixed Assets               8 (h-3) 3   (-) 3   (-) 3   (-) 1Other                        -7 (-5) - (-3) 1 (-2) 1 (-2) 3Total                            1 (-2) 3 (-3) 4 (-2) 4 (-2) 4Financed by:Internal ResLeasing 2 ([-2^       3 (-3^      4 (-2^      4 (-2^17. i  The bulk of the National Girobank capital expenditure will be onnew equipment to prepare data for storage on the main frame computer(data capture) and on new mainframe computers to which will betransferred the main Girobank and Postal Order processing systems.The present data capture and processing system dates from 1968.42CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBRITISH STEEL CORPORATION (BSC) m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes from Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)CapitalRequirements.Fixed assetsOtherTotalFinanced by:InternalresourcesGrantsBorrowing(net)of which,leasing andshort term1979/80280(-121)14-2 (-)422(-121)1980/81     1981/82      1982/83 1983/84345(-Hl) 348C-35)6500 226C-)410(-111) 574(-35)301 (-138) 234-209(0 209510C-138) 443-270(-121) -47(-lll) 147(-^5) 112(-138) 45692(-) 457(-)      427(-)       398(-) 39820(016(-) 59(-)61(-) 61The levels of investment, substantially lower than those underlyingthe White Paper (cmnd 7439) are a reflection of the difficultsituation facing the BSC: existing over-capacity, very substantialadditional modern capacity coming on stream, and continuing largefinancial losses.   The proposed levels of investment compare withestimated current cost depreciation of  400- 450 million, and soimply an appreciable run down in the Corporation^ real asset base;this reflects action taken to reduce excess capacity. Investmentin 1979-80 is    160 million below that envisaged a year ago.Market Background for Steel2.     BSC&apos;s present manned effective production capability of 22.5million tonnes a year is some 2-3 million tonnes in excess of likelydemand on relatively optimistic forecasting assumptions.   Some 5million tonnes of new capacity (mainly at Ravenscraig and on SouthTsesside where the new 10,000 tonnes a day blast furnace shouldbe in production by autumn 1979) will come on stream during the nexttwo years as a result of projects in progress.   The Corporationenvisages counter-balancing this by further closures and de-rating ofongoing major plants, to hold production capability to the present43CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALlevel during the mid-1980&apos;s.   Given the continuation of the worstand most prolonged steel recession since the 1930&apos;e, together withsubstantial world over-capacity, the Corporation^ policy shouldmake available more than enough capacity to meet any likely upturnin demand.   In the year to March 1979, the Corporation reducedmanpower by 11,000 (or 5- $).Investment in the Corporation&apos;s Mainline Activities&apos;3.     Expansion schemes which are substantially under way are beingcompleted, but the Corporation do not intend to embark upon any newschemes which will increase steel-making capacity.   Priority is be&apos;given to investment as follows:-a.   essential replacements and schemes to balance primaryand finishing facilities;b. investment in reliable new technology to improve productquality and customer service? ;c. cost-reduction schemes, and schemes with a rapid pay-backperiod;d. small schemes under  2 million which are highly remunerateand can be quickly executed.4.     In January 1979, BSC embarked upon the installation of continucasting equipment at Port Talbot, the total scheme (due to becompleted in 1981) costing  92.7 million at outturn.   The schemewill greatly improve the quality of Port Talbot&apos;s output of hotrolled coil and thereby help meet the many complaints from userindustries, including the automotive industry and the manufacturersof cans and household appliances.   BSC are also proposing to spend 130 million over 5 years on the renewal of coke ovens, butDepartments are considering whether this is really necessary givenlikely prospects for steel demand.44CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALFinancing5. In April 1979 BSC prepared financial forecasts basedon the then current Annual Operating Plan and the 5 yearmanagement strategy.   The projections showed that an. un-acceptably poor financial performance would result and theChairman of BSC rejected these forecasts.   Since April thewhole management strategy has been reviewed and cost savingmeasures will now be intensified.   Financial forecasts basedon the revised strategy are being prepared by the Corporation.6. The table above shows the lower levels of capital expendi-ture that can be expected under the revised strategy, butrepeats the borrowing requirement contained iti Cmnd 74-39* DC1forecasts, based on BSCs April strategy, suggest that despitethe lower levels of capital expenditure, the Corporation wouldsustain greater losses than previously anticipated and theexternal finance requirement, would therefore remain about thesame.   The revised strategy is aimed at improving the financialperformance and should result in a considerably lower level ofexternal borrowing from 1980/81 onwards.4-5CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALBRITISH AEROSPACECapitalRequirements:Fixed assetsin UKOtherTotalFinanced by:InternalresourcesGrantsBorrowing (net) m at 1979 Survey prices(Changes from Cmnd 74-39 in brackets *)1979/80     1980/81     1981/82     1982/83 1983/8441(*8)      44^+7) 39C+3;72C-29)    90C-16) 105(-7.113(-21)   134(-9) 144(-4.64(-15)49(-6)60(-17)75(*9)59(*4)86(-7)36(-)85C-16)121(-16)49(*D72(-17)33731074067*For BAe, Cmnd 7439 figures have been adjusted toaccommodate dividend assumptionsThis set of forecasts takes account of a number of significantdevelopments in British Aerospace&apos;s (BAe) plans since the 1978Investment Review.   In particular, BAe have, with Government approval,launched the BAe 146 feeder-liner and joined Airbus Industriesas full partners.   They have also decided to proceed with thedevelopment of a re-engined version of the Jetstream - theJetstream 31.   Compared with the figures underlying Cmnd 7439,there is a slight reduction in the level of overall investmentin each year of the review period.   There is also a reduction inthe total amount of external finance required over the correspondingperiod, although the figure for 1980-81 is above that forecast inCmnd 7439.   The changes reflect updated estimates of the costsand phasing of the investment programme, not policy changes, andare mainly due to slippage on civil projects, the 146, Airbus andJetstream.46CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALInvestment PlansI2. Some 70% of BAe&apos;s investment over the review period will bespent on working capital, mainly, work-in-progress.   This is largelyattributable to development and production work on the BAe 146 andanticipated commitments arising from the Airbus A300 and A310projects and the Jetstream 31.   The forecasts assume first deliveriesof the BAe 146 in 1982 and manufacture of Airbus wing sets at a rateto support production by Airbus Industries of 6 aircraft a month(A300 and A310)by the end of 1982.   They also assume a continuatioof work in the military field, both at home and overseas.3. BAe&apos;s forecasts of expenditure on fixed assets are marginallyhigher than in Cmnd 7439.   Some two-thirds of this expenditure islikely to be allocated to plant and machinery, of which about halfwill be necessary to maintain existing levels of output; the restrelates to new projects.   The higher values of fixed assets expenditurein the early ears of the review period reflect the need to moderniexisting plant as well as to set up production for the new civilaircraft.   The estimated replacement cost of buildings, plant andequipment at the end of 1978 was  320 million.   The replacementrate is forecast at 7% per annum.Uncertainties4. The forecasts for later years incorporate an allowance forfurther projects on which decisions have yet to be taken. Thefinancing figures are intended to be sufficient to cover a newmodel of the HS 125 executive jet and participation in a new130-160 seat aircraft.   However, the figures for later years aresubject to major uncertainties and are also to a certain extentdependent on the pattern of orders achieved for the new civilaircraft.   The biggest sources of uncertainty in the short-termare the effect of the loss of the large order for guided weapons fcIran and the dissolution of the Arab Organisation for Industrialisatioi(AOI)for which BAe had a large joint production contract involving ISwingfire anti-tank missiles.   Assuming an average level of trading47CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALprofit on sales, a 5% variation in volume over the five yearswould increase or decrease trading profits by around  25 to  30million.5-     Provision has been made for the payment of interest from vestingday on that part of the commencing capital which will be deemed tobe a debt to the NLF.   BAe have assumed that the commencing capitalwill be determined in 1979-80, and will correspond to the bookvalue of the assets acquired ( 148 million).   A significantly higherdetermination would have a corresponding effect on financingrequirements through higher servicing obligations.Prices and Exchange Rate6. BAe expect input and output prices to rise in line with theaverage rate of UK inflation.   Their assumptions about the rate ofexchange of sterling against the dollar are based on a steady declinein the value of the pound to 01.73 by 1982.    (They are currentlyengaged in a review of the figures using higher exchange rates;but they do not expect this to lead to a change in their financingrequirements).   The forecasts are more sensitive to exchange ratevariations in later years, when more income will be received fromsales of civil aircraft abroad, which are invoiced in dollars.(Some 70% of total sales are expected to go to export).   But thesensitivity of income to the exchange rate will to some extent beoffset by foreign purchases of components.   Moreover, a higherexchange rate could well be accompanied by a lower rate of inflation.Labour Costs and Productivity7. BAe expect labour cost per unit of output to rise generallyin line with inflation.   This implies that real increases inaverage earnings per employee will be offset by improved labourproductivity.   The size of the workforce is expected to increasefrom a level at the end of 1978 of 72,400 (including 3800 overseasemployees), to 77,750 by the end of 1980 to achieve the plannedoutput and then to fall back slightly to 77,500 thereafter.48CONFIDENTIAL
CONFIDENTIALRate of Return8.     BAe&apos;s financial objective for 1978, their first full accountingyear, was to seek to achieve a return on average net assets of20% equivalent to a profit before interest and tax of  62 million.The return was achieved although the profit before interest,dividend, and taxation, was in fact  58 million, but this was after 11 million had been set aside as a provision for launching costs.A further objectiveis at presentunder consideration.   The rate of return will decrease from thepresent high level over the review period as the assets tied up inthe development of the new civil aircraft projects increase, whilethe projects will not yet be generating profits.External Finance9-     BAe expect their external finance requirement to be met froma mixture of Public Dividend Capital, loans from the NLF and foreignborrowing.   In the absence of a determination of commencing capitaland decisions about an appropriate capital structure, it has beenassumed that the ratio of PDC to NLF money will be 60:40. About40% of their external finance is expected to be provided by foreignborrowings in the first two years of the review period.   There areoperational advantages to BAe from financing part of their requirementsin this way, given the high level of export business and the needfor some protection against exchange rate variations.   BAe arealso considering leasing as a means of meeting some of theircapital requirement, but have not yet come to any firm decisions.49CONFIDENTIAL
-isCONFIDENTIALJISH SHIPBUILDERS m at 1979 Survey Prices(Changes from Cmnd 74-39 in brackets)iitaliiirements:ed assets intriljanced by:1979-8O    1980-81     1981-82    1982-83 1983-8438(^8)60U10)98U18)40(-)-34(-34)6(-34)40(*)-16C-16)24(-16)402060jernalourcesIntsrowing (net)-130(*112)-114(h-45) -126(*11)   -78(+57) -4046C+7)      44U21)     25C+18) 8U8)182(-101) 106(-100) 125(-45) 102(-73)100Recent developmentsDecisions have yet to be taken on the strategy for BritishShipbuilders (BS).   The Corporation submitted their first CorporatePlan to the then Secretary of State for Industry at the end of1978.   This outlined four possible options for merchant shipbuildingranging from maintaining the industry at its present size of632,000 compensated gross registered tons (cgrt) capacity to runningdown the industry to 250,000 cgrt.   BS&apos; preferred option involvesreducing capacity to 430,000 cgrt and employment in merchantshipbuilding by 12,300 by 1980-81.   BS have found it more difficultto secure orders than they assumed in the Corporate Plan and theirpreferred strategy now looks over optimistic.   In the twelve monthsto 31 March 1979 orders totalled only 150,000cgrt.   Virtually noorders can be obtained without heavy Government subsidy; and inthe absence of new orders many yards will run out of work this year.The world-wide shipbuilding recession continues unabated.2.     BS* current cash limit is  250m (at 1979-80 prices) and the limiton losses is  150m before crediting Intervention Fund assistance of 50m.   A financial target covering this and future years has yet tobe set.   BS have now provided revised costings of their options andthese are being studied urgently prior to early decisions on Governmentpolicy which seem likely to alter the financing figures in all 5years covered by the Review.50
UUNtflDENTIALInvestment plansJ.     About two-thirds of BS&apos; capital expenditure programme of 42m (at 1979-80 prices) proposed for the current year relates tothe Corporation&apos;s profitable warship-building activities. Capitalexpenditure on merchant shipbuilding is limited to the completionof the latter stages of long-term projects and to items necessaryfor health and safety.Financing4.    No decision has yet been taken on the form of the long-termfinancing of BS.   Pending decisions on the Corporate Plan, BS arebeing financed on an interim basis through advances from the NLF.51CONFIDENTIAL
DECONOMIC PRICINGIn a market economy, decisions about the use of nationalresources are largely guided by considerations of cost andprice.     An efficient market will ensure that decisions sobased will tend to put resources to the most worthwhile uses.However, if prices do not properly reflect costs, markets willnot work efficiently and resources will be wasted.     It istherefore essential to get prices right if the objective ofallowing market prices to play a central role is to be met.2.     In an efficient market, willingness to pay is the measureof value to the consumer, provided that the distribution ofincome is acceptable and that the objective of pricing policyis not to change it.     Since income distribution ought to bedealt with through the tax and social security systems, itought to be irrelevant to pricing.     Thus price measures valueto the consumer.3*     Cost is a measure of the value the resources employedcould produce if they were used in other ways - i.e. of thealternative value forgone when resources are committed to aparticular use.     (In the jargon this is called opportunity cost).Evidently, therefore, to supply output at a price lower than(opportunity) cost diverts resources from more to less worth-while uses:   i.e. wastes resources.     It does this by inflatingdemand for the under-priced product at the expense of competingproducts and thus drawing additional investment and otherresources into the industry to meet the additional demand.Similarly, if price is held above cost, e.g. by the monopolypower of the supplies, resources will be kept out of uses towhich consumers attach a high value and will be put to lessvaluable uses elsewhere:   the industry will be smaller thanit should be.4.     It must be emphasised that distortions which arise whenprices do not properly reflect cost involve real losses: theymay be less spectacular than loss through fire or flood - but1
this only makes them more insiduously dangerous and they canaccumulate over time.5*     Because value to consumers and cost are likely to varywith the seals of output, economic pricing is concerned parti-cularly with the opportunity cost of putting more or lessresources into a particular activity, i.e. with marginal costs.If price were higher than marginal cost, it would be bothnationally worth while and profitable to producers to shiftresources into that line of business, and, if marginal cost weregreater than price, to withdraw them.     In an efficient marketthe forces of competition would thus tend to bring prices andmarginal costs together through the responses of individualbuyers and sellers and this would also tend to allocate nationalresources in the most worthwhile way.6. While in the private sector the Government&apos;s aim would beto ensure that markets worked efficiently and competitively,this cannot be done easily for some of the nationalisedmonopolies.     In order to ensure that these industries are notusing too much or too little of our resources, some sort offinancial framework will be needed.     In particular, it willbe necessary to estimate marginal costs as a basis, e.g. forsetting financial targets, so that prices (and outputs,investment etc) approximate those which would be generated byan efficient market.     The estimates could not, of course, bevery precise:   and the move towards economic pricing from astarting point such as present gas prices which are artificiallylow, would have to be phased and carefully explained to thepublic (and the industries).7. Economic pricing may lead to very high accounting profits -and this is especially true of natural gas because of (a) ourgood luck in having supplies of natural gas which are cheap inrelation to their value to users, and (b) the position of BGCas sole buyer whose major asset&apos;- its buying rights - are notincluded in its balance sheet.    However, this is of norelevance to correct economic pricing.     Supplies of cheapnatural gas are finite, and consuming an extra therm to-day2
brings forward the time when we shall have to use more expensivesubstitutes:   this is part of marginal cost and should bereflected in price.     Selling gas at a price which would yieldan average private sector return on BGC&apos;s book assets wouldmean using gas in outlets where its value is low to-day insteadof delaying its use so that it can be sold where its value ishigher, i.e. would waste resources.     Here, as always the functionof economic pricing is to ensure that valuable scarce resourcesare put to the best use.     This will mean that owners ofparticularly valuable resources in limited supply can receivesubstantial rewards (economic rents).     These can in principlebe taxed away without affecting the use of resources if it isdesirable to do so - e.g. the Government might appropriate thebenefits of North Sea gas on behalf of the nation as a whole.8.     The main paper points out that a move towards economicpricing in electricity and domestic gas could contributesubstantially to saving public expenditure.     Valuable as thismay be, it should not obscure the fact that the case for economicpricing stands on its own right:   it is an important element ofthe Government&apos;s policy to improve efficiency and use nationalresources to the best advantage.

</content>
</cab>
