<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/53/4 images: 32-37</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT/Printed for the War Cabinet.   July 1944./TOP SECRET.Th6iper basis  IssuedCopy Nc.W.P. (44) 404.23rd July, 1944.for&apos; the   personal   use0f.......,,^^fh^^^3fr.............WAR CABINET.PROPOSED EXCHANGE OF UNITED STATES PRISONERS OF WARWITH ISOLATED JAPANESE GARRISONS.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.IN the annexed letter from the United States Embassy to the Prisoners ofWar Department of the Foreign Office the opinion of His Majesty&apos;s Governmentin the United Kingdom is asked regarding a proposal, with which the UnitedStates Government say they intend to proceed, for an exchange of some 25.000Japanese soldiers and Korean labourers, now isolated in the Central Pacific area,against a corresponding number of Japanese-held United States prisoners of warand (if necessary to make up the numbers) civilian internees.2. In point of fact the number of United States prisoners of war in japanese hands is estimated to be something under 20,000, so that the proposalprovides for the evacuation of all such prisoners.3. The possibility of the Japanese Government accepting such a proposals is considered slight, and in any case the physical difficulties of carrying it out would be considerable. Should, however, the unexpected happen and theJapanese Government agree to it, publicity would be inevitable, and publicopinion in the United Kingdom, India and the Dominions, and doubtless inNetherlands circles also, would be rightly indignant that the United StatesGovernment should have made such an arrangement without any similar arrange-ment having been made in the interests of their Allies.4. The forces engaged in the Central Pacific area affected by the UnitedStates proposal are American, and no objection can be raised to it on that score.But in the Southern Pacific area a comparable, if not analogous, situation exists in which British Commonwealth forces are affected. Here the forces under General Mac Arthur&apos;s command, which consist of United States and australian troops in about equal numbers in the front line, with Australians predominatingbehind, claim to have isolated the remains of the 8th, 17th and 18th JapaneseArmies, of which 60,000 are in New Guinea, 50,000 in New Britain, 20,000 inBougainville and 10,000 in New Ireland a total, therefore, of 140,000 (probablysince reduced to some 130,000), which is almost equal to the total number ofBritish Commonwealth prisoners of war estimated to be in Japanese hands.(About 50 per cent, of these are Indians.) There is, however, one importantdifference. Whereas the Japanese forces cut off in the Central Pacific area havebeen put out of action, those in General MacArthur&apos;s zone have a certain&quot; nuisance value &quot;; in fact, in the General&apos;s words, although their ultimate fateis certain, they &quot; can be expected to strike desperately to free themselves, and time and combat will be required to accomplish their annihilation.&quot; It isprobable, therefore, that the Japanese Government would be even less disposed to agree to the evacuation of these troops than they might to that of those inAdmiral Nimitz&apos;s zone.5. It is obviously highly undesirable that the war in the Pacific should betreated as anything but a complete whole, and that one Ally should contemplatearrangements with the enemy, through the Protecting Power, independently ofits other Allies. On the other hand, the United States Government have alwaysmaintained their right to deal bilaterally with the Japanese Government over12437   [27870]
2exchanges of military and civilian personnel, and any claim by the BritishCommonwealth to set aside this principle in the present case would stand little chance of success unless it were related to the military facts of the situation. Sofar as these are concerned, it has been shown that the isolated Japanese garrisons in the Central and Southern Pacific areas are not likely to possess, for theJapanese Government, an equal value.6. It now remains to consider what action His Majesty.&apos;s Government in theUnited Kingdom should take, what action they should recommend to India andthe Dominions (whose Governments have been informed, in confidence, of theUnited States proposal), and in that connexion what reply should be returnedto the United States Embassy&apos;s letter. Assuming that it is impracticable to dissuade the United States Government from their intention of proceeding withtheir proposal, and that they do in fact proceed with it (in which connexion itis taken for granted that the proposal and any development of it would besubmitted to the Combined Chiefs of Staff in Washington), it seems clear that theBritish Commonwealth should take full advantage of the suggestion in the UnitedStates Embassy&apos;s letter, and make to the Japanese Government, through the protecting Power, a similar proposal, viz., one for the exchange of the 130,000Japanese troops isolated in the Southern Pacific against a corresponding numberof British (and, if the Netherlands Government desired it, Netherlands) prisonersof war in Japanese hands. It is not recommended that the question of civilian internees should be introduced, since this is complicated by the fact that australia holds, and refuses to return to Japan, 330 Japanese seamen, withoutwhose return Japan refuses to agree to any further British-Japanese exchange of civilians. (The Australian Government have been pressed to reconsider their view, but have not yet telegraphed their decision.) So far as man-power isconcerned, there appears to be little to choose between the British and Japanesesides, the Japanese forces concerned being in as poor condition as the british prisoners of war in Japanese hands.,7. The question arises of &quot;the precise form in which the proposal should bemade.  There appear to be two alternatives : (a) the British  Commonwealth,  and presumably the Netherlands  (whoappear to have been approached similarly by the United StatesGovernment, with what result is not known, but whom His Majesty&apos;sGovernment should clearly consult at some stage), should make,independently (though of course General MacArthur would have to be consulted), as regards such of their own and of the Japanese troops as are susceptible of such arrangement, a similar proposal to theJapanese Government, through their Protecting Powers,(b) an attempt should be made to induce the United States Government toagree that the proposal which they say they intend to make to theJapanese Government should be expanded into a single Alliedproposal, whereby the Japanese garrisons in the Central and South-West Pacific areas should all be treated as exchangeable for British,United States and Netherlands prisoners of war on an agreedequitable basis. The United States are not likely to agree to this, asthey argue that the first proposal of this kind should be limited to thefewest possible parties.8. In either event it is suggested that the reply of the Foreign Office to theUnited States Embassy&apos;s letter should, in putting forward whichever alternative is decided upon, welcome any initiative providing for the recovery of united nations prisoners of war and civilian internees from Japanese hands; state thatthe Dominions and India have been consulted; and say that serious ill-feeling-would be created in the United Kingdom, the Dominions and India by any arrangement or arrangements which did not provide for releasing some at least of the very large number of British Commonwealth prisoners of war in Japanesehands.A. E.Foreign Office. 2Zrd July, 1944.
ANNEX.Letter to Foreign Office from United States Embassy,dated the 14th June, 1944.THE Department of State has informed the Embassy that the Joint Chiefsof Staff of the United States have received from the Commander-in-Chief, PacificOcean Areas, Admiral C. W. Nimitz, the following proposal with respect to thepossibility of exchanging Japanese-held American prisoners of war for isolatedJapanese garrisons in the Central Pacific : &quot; The Japanese garrisons on Wake, Wotje, Maloelap, Mille, Jaluit,Ocean and Nauru comprise between 23-25,000 Japanese (and Koreanlaborers), which are isolated, without hope of successful evacuation or supply.They are a military liability to Japan, and it is debatable whether they canbe induced to surrender even when it becomes apparent to them that all hopeis lost. Should a neutral be induced to arrange an exchange whereby thesegarrison personnel would be exchanged, rank for rank, for our prisoners ofwar from Bataan, Corregidor, Guam, Wake and Tientsin, it would retrievethese unfortunate prisoners of war who are suffering from malnutrition anddisease, and thereby boost the morale of the American people.&quot; Should the Japanese refuse to consider such a proposal (through a neutral), the morale effect of that refusal should be exploited in order toattack the military and civilian morale of the Japanese. I envision such an exchange as a &apos; safe-conduct evacuation &apos; to permit &apos; face-saving,&apos; in view oftheir doctrine of &apos; non-surrender.&apos; The removal of those garrisons to be afterreceipt of, or simultaneous with, a &apos; safe-conduct evacuation &apos; of Americanprisoners of war. It is realised that the Japanese will probably raise manyobstacles to such a proposal, but it is felt that if there is one chance in a hundred for the success of such a proposal it should be undertaken.&quot;The Joint Chiefs of Staff have informed the Department that they are aware that-this proposal is without precedent, but have indicated their belief that any chance of success, however small, should be utilised to obtain the relief of prisonersof war, particularly the sick and wounded, and other American nationals nowin the hands of the Japanese. They have therefore requested the Departmentto take such action as seems expedient to effect the proposed exchange onsubstantially the following basis : &quot; 1. The United States will grant a safe-conduct evacuation to Japan&apos;sgarrisons on Wake, Wotje, Maloelap, Mille, Jaluit, Ocean and Nauru in exhange for the return by Japan of United States nationals in Japanesedetention as prisoners of war, plus such United States civilian nationalsas will bring the numbers of the United States personnel returned by theJapanese Government substantially up to the numbers of the evacuatedJapanese garrisons. Any civilians to be included in the exchange will bereturned in the following order of priority, each priority to be exhaustedbefore the next is acted upon, viz., unaccompanied interned women andchildren, the sick, all others as may be selected by camp committees on medical advice or by the Protecting Power for American interests.&quot; 2. The evacuation of the Japanese garrisons will occur upon or afterthe delivery of the United States nationals to a point to be agreed upon,under appropriate assurances and safe conduct for their transportation, asmay be necessary.&quot;Since the Joint Chiefs of Staff consider it advisable that the Governmentsof the British Commonwealth of Nations and the Netherlands Government shouldbe informed that the United States intends to make a proposal along these lines to the Government of Japan and that the proposal should not be made to thatGovernment until the British Commonwealth and Netherlands Governments havehad an opportunity to express their opinions with regard to it, the Embassy hasbeen instructed to take up this proposal with you as a matter of the utmost secrecy and urgency and request your opinion regarding it. The Department assumes that clearance with all the appropriate British Commonwealth authorities can beobtained in London.The United States Government believes that, in order to create the greatestlikelihood of acceptance by the Japanese Government, it is desirable to limit thepresent proposal to the fewest possible parties.   For that reason the United
States Government intends to make the proposal on a strictly bilateral American-Japanese basis. The Department wishes to emphasise to you in this connection the interest the British Government has in the success of the projected proposal in view of the importance of establishing a precedent for the return of Europeanprisoners of war in the hands of the Japanese, since, on a basis of this precedent,additional similar exchanges might be arranged on behalf of British and netherlands personnel.It is also the opinion of the United States Government that no publicitywhatsoever should be given to the making of this proposal. The United StatesGovernment reserves for a future time all decisions as to publicity in the eventof Japanese acceptance, refusal or failure to reply. In this connection it isbelieved that, in order to further the likelihood of Japanese action on theproposal, it may be necessary to assure the Japanese Government againstpublicity or propaganda regarding it. It is thought that this would avoidarousing further resistance on the part of the Japanese to other, and possiblymore feasible, efforts to obtain agreement for repatriation and for the forwardingof medicines and relief supplies.I should appreciate receiving your observations on the proposal for transmission to the Department.



</content>
</cab>
