<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 12-20</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This)/secret to be destroyed when replaced by a subsequent number.SEORBT  ADMIRALTYNo. 19.   13th November 1920.issued by the Naval Intelligence division,  Naval  Staff,  Admiralty, for the information of Recipients only.DISTRIBUTION.I1Sent by All British Route to     CopiesBoard of Admiralty .......  103eo.rNav.Soo., S.A.S., A.S.F.)  .3                             1                            40                             1Duty Captain .......The Cabinet (C.I.D.)P.A.N.A.C............Head of Naval Section,Naval Representative,      League of Nations V.A.C,  1st Battle Squadron R. A.C.,  2nd Battle Squadron V.A.C.,  Reserve Fleet .... P..A., Battle Cruiser Sqdn. R.A., 1st Battle  Squadron. R.A., 2nd Battle  Squadron. R.A., 1st Light Or. Sqdn. Commodore, 2nd It.Cr.Sqdn. R.A., 3rd Light Or. Sqdn.. R.A., 8th Light Or. Sqdn.. R. A., Me dit err an. es.n ...... R.A., Yangtse ............ P.. A.  (D) ... o............ojCorrodore, Australian Fleet*G oi:? :.od or e, New Z sal and ...    TOTAL (Distributed by           Copying Branch)11Coimanders^-in-Chief :.- &apos;      The Nore...........   1      Portsmouth.........   1      Plymouth ...........   1      Scotland...........   1      W. Approaches ......   1      Atlantic..........*   2      N.A. h W.1.........   1      Mediterranean ......   1      China ..............   1      East Indies ........   1      Africa.............   1      S. America.........   1 1 1 1 1 1 -i 1 1 1 1 1 i i i85Admiralty Naval Staff   I.D..................   0.D..................   P.D.................. .  T.D............i.....Intelligence Officers  S.I.0,&apos;5 -     Mediterranean ......     China ..............     &quot;^ast Indies ........     S. America .........     N. America .........  D.I.0.&apos;s -     Portsmouth .........     Chatham............     Devonport ...     Rosyth ....Copies.18 3.......   Liverpool ..........   Queensto-vn.........   Gibraltar ..........   Nalta ..............   Colombo ............   Singapore ..........   Shanghai ...........   Wei ling-ton.........   Cape Tov/n..........   Bermuda.............   Ascension..........   Hong Kong ........I.O., Port Said........N.V.C, Monte Video....N.V.C., Oallao ........211111111.111111111111111111TOTAL.(I.D.Dis-       tribution)
                         - a -ORST.  To &quot;bo destroyed when replaced by a subsequent  number.                  RECRPT AD.TRAITY           ^ESSIff  INTELLIGENCE  SUM7 ARY..    No.19.  For the weey ending 13th Nooember 1920.           P\RT I.   NAVAL  Ml? ELLI PENCE.                   GREAT BRITAIN.    Principal. Movements of H.T,T. Ships in Home Waters.         H.M. ships &quot;QUEEN ELIZABETH&quot;, &quot;RESOLUTION&quot; and&quot;ROYAL OAK&apos;&quot;&apos; arrived at Portland.    Disposition of HJ-&apos;. Ships in the Baltic on 13th November.At Copenhagen      &quot;GREENWICH&quot;.At Danzig:-        &quot;WOOLSTON&quot;.AtLibau&apos;:-        &quot;DUNSDIN&quot;, &quot;VISOOTOT&quot;.At Sea             &quot;DELHI&quot; &amp; &quot;WOLSEY&quot; from Libau to He]singfors.                   &quot;DAUNTLESS&quot; &amp; &quot;VICEROY&quot; from Dan zip: to Hango.                      F UPLAND.         It is reported that a Naval School for the training ofcadets has been opened at Helsingfors under Engineer CaptainR. Dillstrom.Repatriation, of British Nationals.         Information having been, received of the safe arrival at Tiflis of the British prisoners from Balof,   H.M.S.&quot;DAUNTLESS&quot; brought the Bolsfcevifc hostages to Hango on 13thNovember and they were transferred to the custody of H..?f ministerat Helsingfors on 14th November.   It *as now been proposed tohold them up at, the Russo-Pinnish frontier pending the arrival of the remaining British from Petrograd&quot;,  British who havealready arrived in * inland cannot proceed until these Russianhostages have crossed the frontier                                          m                    SOOTH RUSSIA.Crimea. !  Tne Reds were expected at Sevastopol on 14th November.The&quot;French hope to evacuate all effective Russian Warshipsincluding Submarines to the neighbourhood of Constantinople.About 20,000 - 30,000 refugees are expected at Constantinopleduring the next fey/ days, and it is urgently necessary toarrange their final destination as there are grave objectionsto landing at Constantinople.   The French request assistancein feeding them.   About 3,000 wounded are als.o expected, ofwhom the French can only talre a few hundred.The
         The loyalty of Wrangelrs Fleet is doubtful,  and instructions have been given that no British action is  to betaken while they remain at Sevastopol even if they turn &quot;Rod&quot;,but that orders to attack &quot;Red&quot; Submarines m.3t with at  seastill hold good.         Rear-Admiral Kedroff is reported to have succeededVice-Admiral Sablin (deceased) as 0-in-C. of the ^leet  atSevastopol.         The Rear-Admiral, 3rd Tight Oruiser Squadron,  reportsthat French and American subjects are being embarked.H.M.S.  &quot;CENTAUR&quot; left Sevastopol for Constantinople on  11thNovember with British from Sevastopol and 130 Russianchildren from British hospital.   British destroyers arecollecting British subjects from Yalta, Theodosia, Kertch,Balaclava and Sudak.General.   It is reported from Odessa that a BolshevikSubmarine is ready for sea.   This submarine cannot he  identified-fied unless-it be the  &quot;A.G.?,3&apos;! from Nikolaiev.   Submarines&quot;Lebed&quot; and &quot;Pelikan&quot; were  &quot;estroyed at Odessa before the Lastevacuation and the Bolsheviks are reported to have abandonedattempts at salvage.         \,ith reference to the Bolshevik-Nationalist threat onBatoum, ?-V&quot;. Government has decided that pending further instructions, no aotion is to be taken by British ships andseaplanes in the event of Ratoum be&apos;:nrr attacked.Trade.   C-in-o. rediterrwean, 1-1 as been instructed t^at british policy is that f^e^e  should be no restrictions   on commercial trade in the Black Sea, unless there is ground tosuspect that in particular&apos; vessels arms are concealed whichare intended to assist the Turkish Nationalist  forces.                        J^Q - SLAVIA.         Much indignation is being shown in the press at theforthcoming all otraent of the monitors of the ex-AustroHungarian Danube flotilla by t^o Sub-Commission which has arrived at Belgrade for that purnose.                         BULGARIA.         A further proposal from the Bulgarian Government forthe re-organization of the Bulgarian Navy is at present underconsideration.   The scheme departs from the forms of theTreaty in so far as it does not provide for the personnel ofthe preventive service allowed to Bulgaria being organizedon a civilian basis, but ^oroses that t^e numbers required should form part, without increasing the total, o^ the armed forces allowed to Bulgaria by the military clauses of theTreaty.                          TURKEY.         The gunboats &quot; AID IN, &quot;RETS&quot; and  &quot;PREVE3S&quot; which,under the terms of the Armistice were employed on patrolduties in the Black Sea, have come undeTi Nationalist influence and disappeared.   In all probability they are at Novorossisk.Imbros.,
Irlbros. Lemnos and Tenedos 0    The Marine garrisons have beenreduced by 6 officers and 200 men, leaving R officers andK55 men to be distributed between the three islands until they are landed over &apos;to Greece.                 FRANCE *         The Naval Budget of 1921 has been presented tothe Finance Committee of -the Chamber.   The total askedfor is 1,235,999,720 francs, an increase of 367,775,638francs over the 1920 budget as finally  passed.   no details are yet available.                 BELGIUM.         The old &quot;VINDICTIVE&quot; was presented to Belgium on12th November,   Commodore Sir Frederick Young, R.N.R.,made the presentation on behalf of H.M. Government.               UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.         An American Press report states that the U.S.  NavelEstimates for 1921 - 22 wJ.ll amount to about$550,,000,000as against $148,000,^00 appropriated -&quot;or this year.
PART  II.              General Intelligence.         Refugees from Bokhara continue to arrive  in Persia.They sta*e hnat the Bolshevik troops who attacked  the citywere well supplied with artillery, armoured oars andaeroplanes.   The attack was preceded by local disturbances,created by members of the so-called young Bokhara  party.,followed by-the Bolshevik bombardment.         When the city was captured it was given over toloofc for 4 days.   It would appear that in spite of thisBolshevik success in the city the people io. the villages  arenot cowod, and numerous raids by night on the railway are reported, the line being cut in several places.                    H1RSIA.         Starosselski and his family left Kasvin for mesopotamia on the 6th November.   The Oossack Division,which is now a mere mob0 do not desire to have the RussianOfficers back.   The question of the re-organisation of theforce &apos; is being taken up by Colonel Snryth.                  MESOPOTAMIA.         The,spirit of the insurgent tribes has been brokenby the punitive measures adopted by troops and R.A.F. duringthe last 10 days and Sheikhs of all the important  tribes  inthe Hillah-Shamiya areas have been making unconditionalsurrenders daily.         On 6th November the Column from.^Samawa carrying  outpunitive operations on both banks of the Euphrates aroundKhidr met with stubborn resistance from an Insurgent band*Our infantry, assisted by aeroplanes, forced the^Arabs fromtheir positions.   Our casualties were 2 killed and 20wounded*         Aerial operations have boon successfully  continued in Middle Euphrates,   ^anitive measures are being carriedout and a number of prisoners have been taken.  The presenceof numbers of Turkish Officers with the Arabs as Instructorsis confirmed.                 SOVIET RUSSIA.         The Soviet Government ratified the Peace  Treaty  of14th October with Finland on 25th OcLobor at Moscow.Ratifications have not yet been exchanged.   The PolishTreaty was ratified on 23rd October, after some opposition.Eathonia.         A new Cabinet was formed on 27th October  withProfessor Piip as Prime Minister and Minister of War.                                                Lithuania,
Lithuania.         Minor enoounters between Poles and Lithuanianscontinue.   The Aerodrome at Kovno was bombed by Poles on 5th November,   A case of mutiny amongst Zeligovsky1 s troopshas been reported to Kovno.   ^oles were stated on 11thNovember to be attacking Uovo-Alexandrovsk which wouldprobably be captured as Lithuanian forces were weak.                  SOUTH RUSSIA.         It is reported that the present position ofWrangel*s forces is critical.   He has withdrawn to his lastline of defence, and there is very little hope that thiswill be held.   Wrangel requests assistance for the evacuation of 80^000 refugees including 3,000 wounded.   C-in-C,,Mediterranean, has been instructed that the approved policyof H.M. Government, that of strict neutrality, should on no account be compromised.   No action is to be taken to evacuate refugees from the Crimea other than those of british nationality, and no action to be taken with regard to vesselsunder General Wrangel in Black Sea Ports.   C-in-0. pointsout the possibility of the arrival of large numbers of refugees at Constantinople in Russian and possibly Frenchships0   Foreign Office has wired to say that refugeescannot be allowed to land at Constantinople, and that, asFrench Government has recognised the South Russian Government,it must take sole responsibility for the destination of the refugees.Georgia.         The Bolsheviks have issued the follovring ultimatum to Georgia   1.  To cease all negotiations and dealings with Wrangel.   3.  To allow all Communists to remain unmolested.   3.  To cease negotiations on subject of export of         petrol with France.   4.  To forbid trading in Batoum by England and France.&apos;Azerbaijan.         All the British prisoners have now been accountedfor.   The released Naval prisoners were due to leaveConstantinople on 12th November for Malta and England.Siberia.         At Chita on 1st November a Council of five,  of whom3 are Communists, were appointed to carry on Government of territory East of Lake Baikal, and declared that all localprovisional Governments were dissolved from that date.                      AUSTRIA.JQag-enlurt,         The Plebiscite Commission have decided to hand overthe plebiscite area to the Austrian authorities on the18th November and leave Klagenfurt on the 20th November.HUNGARY
                     HUNGARY.         The Hungarian Government  has been warned by theEntente representatives to cease preparations  for actionagainst Czechoslovakia and to reduce their army to 135,000effectives as stipulated by the Treaty of the  Trianon.         Tore than two-thirds of the members of the national assembly are in favour of the free election of a King.The Archduke Joseph and the Ex-Emperor Karl appear  to bethe most favoured candidates.         The Hungarian National Assembly-ratified unanimouslythe Peace Treaty of the Trianon on the 13th November.                     POLAND.Situation in the Vilna area.         No appreciable change has taken place in the Vilnaarea, where General ZeligowskjAs forces are still inoccupation.   The question of the method of holding a plebiscite in the area in question is still under theconsideration of the Council  of the League of Nations.Hostilities continue between Zeligowski&apos;s troops and theLithuanians.                     ITALY.         A settlement of the Adriatic dispute  between Italyand Jugo-Slavia has been arrived at and embodied in  the&quot;Treaty of Rapallo&quot;.         This creates an independent state of  ^iume, andassigns the islands of dherso^ Lussin, Unie,  and Lagosta toItaly.   Zara and the island of Uglian also go to Italy,the remainder of Dalmatia becoming Jugo-Slav.         Generally this solution has been well received in italy, but it is not acquiesced in by d1 Annunzio, who at themoment is (according to Press reports) embarking&apos; uponvarious raids upon territory assigned by the  Treaty to Jugo-Slavia.         A feature of the present political situation in italy is the growing unpopularity of the King amongst army officers, and the rise to popular favour of the Duke ofAosta.                      JTTGO - SLAVIA.         Little excitement has so far been aroused in belgrade over the signature of the Adriatic agreement,  butgreat agitation is expected in Croatia and Slovenia,    It isreported that a defensive alliance has also been concludedbetween the two countries against possible Austrian orHungarian aggression.   The Serbian acting minister forforeign affairs professes ignorance of this agreement.TURKEY.
         The Turkish Government, continues to procrastinate&quot;as regards ratification of the Turkish Treaty.    Currentevents in Armenia and Asia Minor no doubt have  their influence.in this respect.                 ARMENIA.         An Armistice was concluded between Armenia andthe Turkish. Nationalists on 7th November, the te^ms ofwhich include the occupation of Alexandropol and thewithdrawal of Armenian forces to the Eastern hank of theArpa Chai.   The Turks have meantime guaranteed that orderwill be maintained in tbe occupied districts.         The Armenians In the &quot;angezur district are still holding out against the Turks, and the British Governmentare being pressed to supply them with, ammunition viaMesopotamia.   T^e Armenian authorities still considerthat the situation could be saved by a Greek landing&apos; atTrebizond in the rear of the Nationalist forces.                   FRANCE.         The whole question of German reparations will bediscussed by Allied Ministers at Geneva hot later than14th February 1921, German representatives atending this discussion in a consultative capacity.                   SYRIA.         The present situation in Trans-Jordania is likelyto cause serious difficulties with the French, who pointout that, there is no effective British authority and thatattadks on them are organised from within, the British zone.If this territory is to be regarded as No-man&apos;s-Land theFrench are prepared to take their own measures, but if theyare asked to respect the boundary they beg that Britishtroops may be sent to prevent, the district from becoming a base for attacks against them.Northern. Syria and Cilicia.         A report has been received that Mustapha Kemalhas been re-inforced by 7,000 Bolshevik troops fromAzerbaijan, who have been ordered to the Aintab district.It is said that further Bolshevik troops-&apos;are to follow.                   BELGIUM.         The Cabinet crisis is still unsettled.   It is.probable that M% Carton de Wiart, a Catholic Deputy and an ex-minister of Justice, will succeed in .forming a freshc oalit1on Minis try.VENEZUELA.
                  - G -         It has been reliably reported that as1 a resultof the recent revolutionary outbreak,  relations pithColombia have become strained and violent press attaoks,believed to be inspired by the Government, have begun.         The Venezuelan Government consider that had theColombian Government been animated by friendly feelingstowards then they could easily have prevented the insurgents from crossing the frontier.   It is understoodthat a stiff diplomatic note to this effect has been sent,demanding better supervision in the future.         It is also reported on. the same authority thatduring the raid a considerable store of Government armswas captured and carried off by the insurgents.

</content>
</cab>
