<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 249-250</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOOtKIIT IS THE  PROPERTY OF HIS BHIIAH2JIC Mtf:S3TY&apos;S  COVER IMM))*CONFIDENTIAL,,                                  Copy No,C..P.-2140.0 A B. I. H B T.LEAGUE OJ? NATIONS^.    APPLICATION Oi&apos; THE AUSTRIAN RBPUBLIO flQB ADMISSION                    TO. TICS L3AGUB,        &apos;   &quot;Lattar from the Ministry, of Foreign Affairs, of the Austrian                      Republic..(Circulated for information).     The Secretary General has the honour, to forward herewithto the Members of the League of Nations, for their information,oopy of a letter received from, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.of tho Austrian RepublicMinistry of. Foreign Affairs   of the Austrian Republic,68354/13..                                            VIENNA,                                               9th November, 1920.Sir,.      .  -       Based as it is on the principle of Bomooraoy., and actuated.therefore by paoific intentions,.tho Austrian Ropublio hae, from  thevery moment of its birth,, regarded admission to the League ofNations, as soon.as that body, should be constituted, as one Of  its most important aims.,     l&apos;n 3pite of all. their efforts the. Delegates  of the AustrianRepublic at Saint-Germ?in-en-Laye. were unfortunately not able toobtain the inclusion-of Austria  anstng the Original Members of theLeague.,..     nevertheless the Austrian  Government  considers that  it  ,should.no longer djlay to ma.;e use of the opening- provided in t*heCovenant of the League of. Nations  (Article  1 para.. 2 of theTreaty of Saint-Gorma in.)for  States which  ore  not  OriginalMembers of the League but yet. desire to  belong  to it.
       The Austrian government,feels the moro-impelled&apos; to ask - -  for immediate admission to the League of &quot;&quot;Motions-; because o:  ,  at the time of the-negotiations at Saint^Gormaih^en-Xaye, tho  Principal Allied and Associated Powers Informed the Austrian  Delegation, in their Note ^ c$.1f&apos;:of July 8th, -19195       &quot;That they saw nothing to prevent Austria from asking for&quot;  admission to the league of Nations,, in accordance with the pro-  visions of Arts  1,  of the Covenant, as soon as an opportunity  -should oecur after  the ratification of the  Treaty of peace J  As  soon  as they ere convinced that  Austria possesses a responsible  government,  and  that this  Government has shown that it can aniv  will  comply with its international  obligations,  they will be  prepared  to  support  the  candidature  of  Austria for- admission  to  the League  of  Nbtiohs.&quot;       The  Treaty  of Saint  Germain-en-Laye came  Into force  on  July  16th,  1920.  The  Austrian Government,  supported  by the  cc-ri: aence  of a  National Assembly elected on a  basis of universal gitJ^rage,  has given numerous and generally acknowledged  proofs that  Austria  is endeavouring  to fulfil  her  international obligations,  so far  as lies in her ptswer.       The Austrian Government feels,  therefore,  justified  in hoping  that  the Members  of  the League of Nations will agree to the participation of  Austria  in the  League* &quot; It would  be .deeply gratified at receiving in  the near  future a favourable  decision on this poiht from the Assembly  of  tho  League  of Nations,  all the more  because political and economic considerations  imperatively demand  tho prompt admission of Austria  to the  League.  .&apos; .       I have the honour&quot; to  request that  you will&apos;be  good enough to submit the above   declaration  tc the Assembly  of  the league of Nations at the earliest possible moment.             I have the hone in- to be. Sir, etc., &apos;                             (Signed)&apos;   MAYJUo The Honourable  SJr Earner I:r;c Orummond,      K ,.f,t uf, 0/ .,Gt,B*                .   , Soorc-cary Geueial of the League  of Nations^

</content>
</cab>
