<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 257-259</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
&apos;(WtIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY  OF  HIS BRITAKMIO   J 3STY1H GO VSR itSM T.)CONFIDENTIAL,              0 A B I JJ T,              Copy No..                        LEAGUB OF  NATIONS.  -0.P.-8142.               ---------------- ?                    HfM&apos; BY (THE SECR3TARY4*drNERAL,              (Circulated for information)&apos;,     The attaohei revised provisional Agenda f $r the MrstSession of the Assembly contains,  for the convenience of theMembers of the League, the items already forwarded  in the supplementary Agenda,  and the items  included after  tfcoMeeting of the Council in Brussels arx October 20th.REVISED PROVISIONAL AGENDA FOR THE FIRST SESSION OF             &quot; &quot; THE AUSEMSY7         &quot;*1. Report cn Credentials of RepreSentativeB.2, Election of President.3. Temporary adoption of-provisional  rules  of  procedure.4o Examination and adoption of Agenda.Go Nomination, of Committees.C General Report on the  Work of  the Council- 7, Rules *f Procedure 8* Amendments to the Covenant.   Proposals  fey the Danish,  Ncrwe-    belgian and Str^llah Governments,    fa) Additional ohapter ta the  Oevenant,  proposed by  the        Norwegian Government.  Amendments to the Norwegian proposal        put ferward by the Swedish Government. 9. Th&amp; relations between, and respective competence gf  the  Council    and the Assembly of the League.10* Method of selection and appointment wf  the  four  non-permanent    Members of the Counoil.    (b) This item includes the actual  appointment  of the four        non-permanent members of tho Council.
11. Relations between Technioal  Organisations and  the Council    and assembly of the League.12. T bee a tabli sb rn e n t of a  P e ma nob t Health  Organisation.15. Typhus.14. Supervision over the execution of -agreements with regard to    Traffic in -omen and Children.15. General supervision over the  eye cut ion of Agreements with    regard to the Traffic in Opium in accordance with Artiole   &quot;XXIII *f the Covenant fat the request of  the Government cf    the Netherlands).16. The establishment of a  Permanent Organisation  to deal with    Communications and Transit questions falling within the    sphere of the League under the  Treaty of Versailles.17. Tribunal for the settlement  of  differences referred to in    article 336, 337,  376 and 386 of the Treaty of Versailles and    In corresponding Articles of  other Treaties.18. Passports for Members of the  Becrotariat.19. Economic and Financial  Organisation.SO. Claim *f India to  be represented on the  Governing Body of the    International Labour Office.SI.  Plans for the  establishment  of the  Permanent Court of    International  Justi22.  Report by the  Secretary-General  tn  the  organisation  of the    Secretariat.S3.  The 1st and End  Budgets  of the League covering tho period to    December 31st,, 1920.24.  Provisional Estimates  for  the 1921  budget.25.  The future method  of apportionment  of the&apos;expenses of the    League,2ft.
2,6.  Admission of States not  named  in  the Annex to  tho Covenant.    (o)  The following is the list  of  States  whose  application        lor admission to the League wss received on  or before        October 15th  1920,  the  date fixed  by the Provisional        Rales of Preoedure  as the  latest on  whioh  questions        should be forwarded  for consideration at the present        meeting:   &apos;Armenia        Finland      Lieohtenstein      Ukraine    Cesta-Rioa     Georgia      Lithuania    Eethonia.      Latvia.      Luxemburg27.  Seduction of Armaments.   Resolution adapted by the    COnferenoe of Ministers  of  State  and Ministers of Foreign    Affairs of Denmark, Norway  and Sweden.28.  Preparations required to enable the Economic Weapon  of the    League to be used in case of necessity.                 429.  Mandates.   Res tnsibilities of the&quot; League arising from    Article 22 of the Covenant.- 5 -8, Whitehall Gardens,  S..W.   24th November,  1920.

</content>
</cab>
