<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 311-313</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Aiy - jhn4*&amp;tfU(THIS DOCUMENT IS  THE  PROPERTY OP HIS BKITAIOT&apos;C-JIAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).(CONFIDENTIAL.C.P.2152.OA BIN P T.COPY HO.-5m^m--.....................*mmLEAGUE OF HATION.S;.2C/4/577Modifications made to the Rules of Procedure of the Council,       According to the Proposals of M. Bourgeois                   and M. Tittoni.(Circulated for Information).          The Secretary General has the honour to present to the Members of the Council, the text of the modifications which should be made to the Rules of Procedure of the Council,according to the proposals made by Monsieur Bourgeois andMonsieur Tittoni, and adopted by the Council, October20th, 1920.          The Secretary General suggests to the Council thatthe final text of these modifications be decided upon at theCouncil Meeting which will be held immediately on the close of the Assembly.                     ARTICLE I,          The Council of the League of  atlons shall meetevery two months as a general rule, at the seat of theLeague, on a day fixed upon in advance by the Council -          The Council may be convened in exceptional cir-cumstances for grave  md urgent reasonseffectually recog-nised as  such by the President end the secretary General.          VJhen a subject which has already been reported on by the Council is discussed,  the Rapporteur  will be  con-suited by the President as  to  summoning a special meeting.
          The Council will be convened under  exceptional circumstances, within reasonable time on the  demand of  one member of the League represented on the Council,  or of  three members of the League not represented on the  Council.   Thedemand shall be sent to the Secretary General.          At special meetings no other subjects shall bediscussed, but the special and urgent one which has given rise to the special meeting.  All other subjects shall  be reserved for the ordinary meetings, unless the  Councilunanimously decides, all its Members being present, to  allow the discussion of other subjects owing to special and urgentcircumstances.          The letters of convocation for the meetings of  theCouncil shall be sent by the Secretary General, and addressedto the regularly accredited representatives of each Government.,,through their respective Governments.  In the case of ordinary meetings they will be  sent at least twenty days before the first sitting.  The  same time limit, will ifpossible be observed for meetings  convened under extra-ordinary circumstances.  The letter will state the itemson the Agenda, and will, as far  as possible be accompaniedby the necessary documents.  .          Should special  circumstances arise,  the council may be convened at  some  place  other than&apos; the seat  of theLeague,  settled on by  the  Council, or  deemed suitable bythe President  If possible&apos; in  consultation with other Repre-sentatives  in Council.          The foregoing  decisions  shall  in no  wise  affectthe special  stipulations concerning  the  cases  noted inArticle  XI  paragraphs  1  and  2,  and Article XV,  paragraph 1of  the Covenant,                Article           (Follows/2,  of the Rules of Procedure).
                   ARTICLE 3/T          If the President,  the Secretary General,  and eventually the Rapporteur,recognise the exceptional urgency of a subject they may take :e measures for a preliminary exam-ination and investigation of the subject, preparatory to theCouncil1s decision, and without prejudicing the authoritative- -tive decisions which shall rest with the Council.          They may even in these cases order such provi-commisionary measures as shall appear necessary after telegraphicconsultation with The other Representatives on the Council.          In any case, all measures taken in applying thisArticle shall be at once brought to the notice of all theRepresentatives on the Council.          The above decisions shall not affect the specialstipulations concerning the cases noted in Article XV,paragraphs 1 and 2 of the Covenant.2S Whitehall Gardens, S.w.1,,         25th November, 1920.

</content>
</cab>
