<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 379-380</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Cabinet.  November 1920.SECRET.C.P.-2170.                                CABINET.THE LEAGUE OF NATIONS, THE  INTERNATIONAL  LABOUR OFFICE                        AND NATIONAL FINANCE.             MEMORANDUM BY THE  CHANCELLOR OF THE EXCHEQUER.    I AM seriously concerned about the absence of any effective control  over thecharges which may be imposed upon the British Exchequer by the League of nations and still more bv the International Labour Office.                         I. The League of Nations.    The League pays such salaries,, appoints such officials and  incurs such expensesas it thinks fit without reference to the Governments upon which the cost falls.  Therepartition of these charges among the Governments members  of the League is notyet finally settled, but we shall probably be expected to pay as  large a share as anynation.    At present any British  delegate (Minister  or  not) may apparently concur in expenditure without Treasury  sanction  and even  without  definite  and  specificdepartmental sanction.    There is a tendency for the League to try to do or to re-do for itself work which ought to be or is done by the nations members of the League.    I submit the  following proposals:-    (a.) All British delegates to  be instructed that  they are to resist to the utmost Proposals.          of their power any attempt in the League to duplicate existing  national          machinery.  In the case of new work  (e.g.,  collection  of  statistics or          reports  on subjects not already available) they are to demand  that the          national Governments be  asked  to collect and supply the information.    (b.) British delegates are not to assent to any expenditure  (except of a quite          trifling  kind  to which the maxim of de minimis  may apply)  without          authority from their Departments.    (c.) Departments must obtain Treasury sanction as for  national  expenditure          before  authorising their delegates to assent to it.    I do not ask  that these instructions should apply  to Ministers attending theLeague or its subordinate bodies, for I rely upon their experience, their knowledge and discretion to  p7&apos;otect the British Exchequer.                   II. The International Labour Bureau.    This is a much more formidable danger.    At present,  as far as I know, no British Minister has been made specificallyresponsible for supervising International Labour business, and  I understand thatin the absence of  such specific directions, the Minister of Labour does not  feelauthorised to act.    (d.) I propose that the necessary authority be at once given to him.            Proposal.    The matter  is urgent, for Sir Malcolm Delevingne,  the British representative on the Governing Body of the International Labour  Office, estimates the expensesof the office for 1921-22 at between 350,0002. and 370,000/. We have created a monsterthat may devour us.    In the first place it is recognised by the Council of the League of Nations thatthe Council of the League has no control over the decisions of the Finance Committeeof the International Labour Office or over the total estimate for the InternationalLabour Office Budget;  and that all that each Government can do is to give its repre-sentative on the  Governing  Body any instructions it may  deem necessary.  This      [4955]:V-.r  ----T-.--r- ... --^v----------------
          decision was arrived at by the Council  of  the  League  at  its meetings  at  San          Sebastian when some questions were raised  as to the cost of  the International Labour          Office.  In other words the Secretary-General of the League of Nations is compelled          to pay over to the Director of the International Labour Office from the Funds of the          League of Nations the amount of monies that the International Labour Office  may          require for its current expenditure.  There is clearly, therefore, no financial control          that can be exercised by the League.              The next  point to  consider is  what  arrangements,  if any, exist within the          International Labour Organisation itself for controlling its own. expenditure.  The          estimates of the International Labour Office are prepared by the Finance Committee          of the International Labour Organisation.  As at present  constituted this Finance          Committee consists  of four members of the Governing  Body-the Chairman being          M  Fontaine, who is also  the President of the Governing Body, M. Carlier (a Belgian,          and the representative of the employers). M.  Jouhaux  (the  representative of the          workers and the well-known leader of the  French C.G.T.) and (quite recently) Sir          Malcolm Delevingne, the British representative on the Governing Body. M. Fontaine          is not a strong man and  is notoriously under the thumb of M. Thomas (the Director          of  the  International Labour Officej;  M.  Jouhaux is  a  member of the  Finance          Committee.  It is clear that the amount of effective check and criticism that can be          brought  to bear  upon  the estimates  by the  British representative cannot be          considerable;  .           i  The recommendations of the Finance  Committee of the International Labour          Organisation are subject to the approval of  the Governing Body.  But  the Governing          Body itself consists of 24 members, of whom 12 are Government representatives, 6 are          employers&apos; representatives and  6 are representatives of the workers.   The decisions          of the Governing Body are by a simple majority vote, and here again  it is seen that          the amount of financial control that can be exercised by the  three British representa-          tives, i.e.,  Sir Malcolm Delevingne (for  the Government), Sir Allan Smith (for the          employers), and.Mr. Stuart Bunning (for the workers) is not likely to be effective if          subject to  a majority vote of the Governing Body;   For  instance,  if  France  and          Poland, as members of the International Labour Organisation, were  to propose an          elaborate and: expensive enquiry into the  conditions  prevailing in Ireland at the          present time, against the views of the three British representatives, it would not be          a difficult matter for the French and Polish  representatives to contrive a majority          vote of the Governing Body in  favour of the proposal.              In considering  International Labour Organisation  business, the  personality of          M.  Thomas, the Director of the International Labour Office, must be borne in mind.          He has avowedly very large views of the scope and powers of the Office, which is very          largely his creation.  I understand that  the  Ministry  of Labour  have seen quite          recently  the proof of a questionnaire that  M. Thomas is proposing to  issue to the          Governments of the world, which embodies  an exhaustive enquiry into the  causes of          industrial unrest throughout the world, the  relations between capital and labour, and          the whole field of industrial production.  I can well imagine  that this  proposal in          itself, if not rejected by  the Governing Body, might well involve very large sums of          expenditure.  If M. Thomas were content to rely for the sources of his information          upon Governments and to restrict his channels of information to the members of the          International Labour Organisation, the cost would be inconsiderable.  But M. Thomas          has made it quite plain that he regards himself as entitled to approach direct  any          group of employers or workers in any country in the world, with the natural conse-          quence that large sums of money  are required by him in order to meet the expenditure          incurred by any ambitious programme that he and M. Fontaine together may agree          to persuade the Governing Body  to adopt.              I propose Proposals.       (e) That Sir  Malcolm  Delevingne  be instructed to  protest  in  the  strongest                    possible  manner against  any proposal  to issue independent  enquiries                  .  instead of seeking information from the National Governments.              (/.)  To say that if such a course is pursued His Majesty&apos;s Government, without                    their express concurrence, will  not be  responsible for  any  part of the                    expense.              (g.)  To press for revision of the estimate for 1921-22  and to demand a drastic   j                    reduction in the expense.                                                                 (Initialled)     A. C.              Treasury, S.W.,                  November 24th,  1920

</content>
</cab>
