<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 445-447</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
j     /     ,339(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY Oi?. HIS BHITANHIO IviAJEGTY*S GOVEHJUiEKT) iVERY SECRET *                                    Copy Ho                        0 A B I H B 3?,              PROTECTION. OP ?HE HOUSES OP PARLIAMENT                    AII3 GoTlimsiiT o nICES ,                      i . .. .h .. .. ...... hWU*Aw^* f   i lujnr- n i iWl..i i.wJ1aii(ini,i                2nd Report of the -Bmergoniy Ocmmlttee.                      (Previous Reoort CP,-2167),     Whan considering the question of the protection of theHouses oi Parliament at tlieir Meeting held tills morning, theP*,lioe Authorities informed, the Emergency Committee that theycould not guarantee the absolute protection *f tha Chambers in&quot;both Housed unless the public was excluded from all theGalleries with the exception of the Ambassadors, DistinguishedStrangers and Special Galleries.    Short of this somewhatdrastic step, whioh before it could he put inta operation wouldprobably require the assent of the House, the following pro-cautions have been suggested:-     (a)  the searching of all persons admitted to the          publio galleries and committee roomss     (b)  to exclude all women from the pr3ci.nots of the          House and admit men only to the public galleries          and committee rooms - admittance being&apos;*gTven          however only on the understanding that searching          is submitted to if thought desirable by the Police,          and to the extent required by the police.     The Polioe state that the searching of women presentsgreat difficulties and unless the search is thorough it isuseless, and this would entail great ineanvenienoe to the individuals concerned.   The Polioe Authorities are in favour%l closing the Galleries altogether though they admit thatthe difficulties of searohing would be considerably lessenedif confined to men only.&apos;
     Tho Committee  feel  that  this  is  a matter  that can only be decided  by  the Cabinet,  but they  recommend that should it  be  decided  to  exclude  women altogether  the decision should be  extended  to the  wives  of bombers  of  Parliament. Peeresses  who have  certain rights  of  entry  into the House of  Lords would however havo to  be  exoludad  from this order.     Tho Committee  aticoh  a sohomo for  soarching  as recommended  by the  Police  authorities.     Great progress has  already been  made with regard to other precautions for the  protection  of tho Houses of Parliament and other  Government buildings *  and the special force of ex-efficers  referred to in  the First  Report of  the Ceicmittee  (Q.F.2167)  will  commence their  duties on Monday nsxt.     Tho Secretary  of State for War  has made arrangements for an adequate  force of military to  bo available and within  the next  few da yes the  majority of  the public offices  in the vicinity  if Whitehall  will be In direct telephonic oena.unios.tidn with Wellington  Barrac.es and tho  . Horse Guards. Further precautions jf a detailed  character have also  been ta en, these include  a system of passports for all  persons  not-officials and worsen in the  Palace  of Westminster  and  certain  Government offices  in  Whitehall; tho closing  of a number  of entrances  into the  Palaoo;   the patrolling by mwtor boat of the river frontage;   thft erection of  barriers  in Dcvming Street.and  King Charles Street;   and the closing of the Palace of Westminster  to the public on Saturdays.                         (Signed)   S. SHOBTT.                                           Chairman.27th November, 1920.
              ANKEX TO CP. 2183.             PROTECTION.- HOUSES, OF PAKTJAMT.                      SEARCHING .   Vial tors and other persons seckin ? a dmiseion  to the buildings.     A searching room about 12 feet by 10 feet to he erected onthe steps leading down to Westminster Hall at St. Stephensentrance Room-to be provided with six chairs, a  table withdrawers and a good sized safe.     Barriers to be erected in lobby to regulate ingress andegress to and from the lobby to the searching Rooin and thence to central Hall, etc.     All males (without exception) entering here to be thoroughlysearched and police to have power to attain any article whichin their judgment they consider should not he taken into thebuilding,  persons found, in possession of articles or documents of a suspicious or improper nature to be detained for carefulenquiries to  be made  and their bona-fides tested.      permanent Workpeople. Entrance at Chancellor&apos;s Gate.Armed police in plain clothes rill be provided as found    necessary.     To be provided with passes bear in-x photograph and signature of person to whom issued,  pass to be. produced on demand andhoi; cr liable to search, by police.                    0 * su al T-Q r kp e o p 1 e.     To be provided with i;ay or Temporary passes and to besearched by police.  These passes are to be frequently changed.Colour of paper used to be varied each time a fresh pass issue a.               Vehicles of Tradespeople, etc.     Drivers to be provided with passes and both drivers and vehicles to be searched at discretion of Police.

</content>
</cab>
