<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/115/0 images: 452-452</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
              From High Commissioner, Baghdad, 22nd November 1920.         6143                             (Received 25th, 2 p.m.)     (R.)  14107.  In  connection with establishment of National Government, it is most essential, if we are to convince public of the bona fides of our policy, that formerTurkish Government building(s in ?) Serai, which have been under  military occupa-tion since fall of Baghdad, should be restored to them.  I have explained the positionto General Officer Commanding, and have made specific proposals for (? handing over)to him certain buildings at present occupied by civil office together with certain other(? buildings)  sufficient  to provide (? accommodation) equivalent to  that vacated  inSerai.   Commander-in-Chief agrees  in principle that transfer must  be made, but, inview of the  fact that  War Office has hitherto paid no rent for Serai, even  sjincearmistice, and as it will be  necessary to  (?pay) rent for  accommodation now offered,he considered it necessary to refer financial aspect of question to the War Office bytelegraph (? 5th November)  (? and) feels unable  to  proceed with evacuation pendinginstructions from them.  Similarly, until evacuation  is definitely agreed to, I hesitate to incur expense of certain petty alterations which are necessary in order to adapt newaccommodation for military use.     We are thus at an impasse and progress with the policy of His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment is delayed.     I submit that question of adjustment of cost between military and this adminis-tration is one which must be finally settled by correspondence, which may take weeksor even months, and that there is no necessity to delay transfer pending its settlement.     I  request that His Majesty&apos;s  Government will accept  this  view  and  thatCommander-in-Chief and I may be authorised to proceed to transfer at once.  We canthen report final aspect of case separately with our views in order that question of costmay be discussed and settled at convenience between -Departments of State interestedincase Commander-in-Chief cannot  be authorised  to settle  the rent direct with mehere.        ,                           &apos;  &apos;     General  Officer Commanding has seen above and concurs.

</content>
</cab>
