<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/177/22 images: 210-223</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(74) 72 - COPY NO     I 012 July 1974: : &apos; CABINET -CONCORDENote by the Lord chancellor in accordance with the Cabinefs invitation at their meeting on 27 June(CC(74) 21st Conclusions, Minute 4) I submit for their approval the negotiating brief for the Prime Ministers forthcoming discussions withthe French President, in the form in which it has been agreed by the ministerial Committee on the Concorde Project.E lord Chancellor&apos;s Office12 July 1974
CONCORDE : DRAFT BRIEF FOR THE PRIME MINISTERSMEETING WITH PRESIDENT GISCARD d&apos;E3TAINGIntroduction1.      When Concorde was discussed &quot;between the Prime Minister and the french prime Minister, Mo Chirac, on 26th June, M. Chirac said that this was one ofthe matters which the French would like to be discussed at the later meeting between the Prime Minister and President Giscardo    The Cabinet decided on 27thSecretary of State for Industry and his French opposite number, the Secretaryof State for Transport, Mo Cavaille (CC(74) 21st Conclusions, Minute 4)0\The United Kingdom Position2o      The view taken by the Cabinet on 23rd May was that it would be preferable for Concorde to be cancelled if the consent of the French Government, howeverreluctant, could be secured;   but that if they did not consent, we should notwithdraw unilaterally from the project but should complete the programme tobuild 16 aircraft (the number already authorised).    The Cabinefs finaldecision would be taken in the light of the discussions with the FrenchGovernment (CC(74) 17th Conclusions, Minute 8).The French Attitude3.      Although the new French Government have yet to make a formal statementof their policy on Concorde it is quite clear that they will not acquiesce incancellation.     Their immediate objectives appear to be to secure HMG*s agreement to;-(a)   continuation of the production programme with early authoritybeing given for the production of three more aircraft (nos. 17 to 19)5(b)   an additional development programme designed to give the aircraft- longer range by the provision of extra tanks and weight savingmodificationsestimated to cost  27 million in total.
United Kingdom Objectives at Meeting with president Giscard4v     These are to rehearse the major problems concerning the continuance ofthe programme ands-(a) test at the highest level the strength of Frenoh resistance toHMG&apos;s preferred course of outright cancellation;   if as is likely theFrench president is quite immovable on this;(b) be prepared to agree to the continuation of the present development and 16 aircraft production but nothing beyond that;   and if possibleobtain French agreement to this policy;(c) secure agreement in principle to the drafting of a new agreement which takes fully into account the situation which has developed and provides for any necessary modifications of the 1962 Treaty,     this could be effected by Exchange of Letters.I     MLegal Aspects5o      The 1962 Treaty has for many years proved difficult to apply to actualdevelopments:   resulting uncertainties have hampered clear and quickdecisions.     It is therefore important that if any understanding is now reached between the two Governments it should be embodied in a formal and bindingExchange of Letters.     Such an exchange would need to -(a)   make clear that no obligation on either party has arisen to financeany activity beyond the 16 aircraft programme;/      (b)   confirm by express words each party&apos;s right which is implicit inthe 1962 Treaty to refuse to authorize further production;   and define the circumstances in which either party will be entitled to give noticeterminating all obligations under the Treaty.Tactics6.      It is suggested that the tactical, Jane might be as follows:-
(a) We have carefully studied all the options for the future of Concorde.,And we are advised that circumstances have so changed since the original1962 Treaty that neither side is under any obligation to continue withthe projecto   (Annex D sets out the legal position.)(b) The &quot;economic arguments - loss of all development expenditure,continuing production losses, very poor market prospects - point clearly:   :f     W I -   .to immediate cancellation.    In any event the Concorde programme may rundown before long for lack of orders;   a continuation merely postponesthe problems arising on cancellation&apos;.(c) There are other broader considerations which may be relevant to apolicy decision, such as (amongst others) the future of Anglo/french -operation, the money already spent in development and production,the implications for employment and of a capability in this area of high technology;   and the effect on national morale.(d) In view of these considerations we are prepared, subject to suitable safeguards, to continue with the existing 16 aircraft programme.     But we are not prepared to agree to French proposals for additional development work and the production of three more aircraft.(e) Our agreement to continue with the 16 aircraft programme would be conditional on an Exchange of Letters which made it clear that therewas no legal obligation on either side to agree to any development orproduction work beyond this programme;   and set out clearly definedcircumstances in which either party would be entitled to give noticeterminating all obligations under the Treaty.(f) If new and unforseeable circumstances should later arise which seem to justify the resumption of the programme by further authorizationsor otherwise, the parties should consult together.     But any final3SECRET
agreement to extend the programme would have clearly to define the commitment of the two parties.(g) If the French President agrees to a settlement on this basis , theSecretary of State for Industry and his French opposite number (M,Cavaille), might be asked to meet urgently to agree the details.(h) If the French President insists on French proposals for theimmediate extension of the development and production programme, thePrime Minister might simply indicate that we cannot agree to this.Other Points which may arise7.      Organisational changes in the Concorde Programme..    The French are knownto feel strongly that the official machinery for Anglo-French consultation and decision should be strengthened;   and that overall responsibility for the concorde airframe and engine should be given to Aerospatiale and Rolls Royce1971 respectively.     If broad agreement is reached with the President, theseare matters which Mr. Benn and M. Cavaille might usefully consider.Annexes8.      The following are attaohed:-Annex A   -   Talking points on the case against the French proposals for extending the existing development and production programme.Annex B   -   A note on French views on a second generation supersonic transport.Annex C   -   The costs of the 0, 16 and 19 Options./ Annex D   -   The legal position.4
secret annex A-French Proposals ,for Authorising 3 More aircraft and Work to Achieve Extra. Fuel Capacity andWeight Saving - -j. Talking Pointsitef 1 i  mi wMThe Production of Three More AircraftFive of the aircraft who.se production hasalready been authorised remain unsold.British and French officials are agreedthat &quot;great uncertainty surrounds the prospects for further sales beyond those already made toBritish Airv;ays and Air France, whatever versionis offered to airlines.&apos;&apos;l&apos;he only serious sales negotiations now iniprogress are vith Iranair, a very special case.Recent fuel price increases, and the weakfinances of many airlines, give no reason foroptimism for an early improvement in the marketprospects.To produce an extra 3 aircraft would add. about  80m to the total cost of the programme. &apos;Even if the aircraft were sold, these extracosts would exceed the extra receipts by  l5-20m.Each aircraft will cost more to produce thanit Sells for until sales reach 60 or 70.   the chances of this figure being reached arevirtually nil.French Proposals for Extra Fuel Capacity andWeight Saving ImprovementsThe cost of these modifications is substantial -  27m at the latest estimate.They would improve the air craft s rangeonly marginally, and would not fundamentallyimprove its attractiveness to major airlines.
Total cost Cost tor                                         from now UK m fMStop 210        . 100   .Build .16     (14 soM) 550 55QBuild 19, (including- French modifications) 650 /^n(17 sold) 4^0For example, the following routes could,  stull not be f lown with fu3.1 pay loadsLufthansa:    Frankfurt/New YorkJapan Airlines:   Tokyo/Anchorage! QANTAS:        Sydney/SingaporeThe modified version with these improvements would be just as noisy as thestandard version.Overall CostsTaking into account estimated effects onairline operating economincs, adoption of theFrench proposals would add about  100m to the overall programme cost.    This is illustrated by the table below
A Second Generation Supersonic Transport (SST)     A W^EA 6The French have in the past seen as one of- the advantages of concorde that it would enable Britain and France to stay in thesupersonic transport business in the longer terra, instead of allowingit to become a Soviet/American monopoly.   They have floated ideasfor a second generation S5T&apos; which would be about twice the. size of .Concorde and have a much longer range;    such an aircraft would be developed jointly, by the US, Britain and France.   The French viewnow seems tc be rather that this is an option that should be preserved-than we and they should make an early approach to the Americans aboutthe launching of a second generation SST.For several...reasons, we do not think that the possibility of taking part in a second generation SST should weigh&quot;5: heavily in thepresent decision oh the future of Concorde.   These reasons are)   There is no sign of current^rent interest in a secondgeneration SET on the part either of the main US aircraftmanufacturers or the US Government.   The manufacturers1 &apos;Iwould take a cool commercial view of such a proposal, andwould certainly be influenced by the recent steep increases in fuel costs and the weak financial position of many airlines.There is no sign thai opposition in Congress to the provision.(       of Federal funds for the development of an SST has lessenedsince the cancellation of the Boeing SST a few years ago,or that the Federal Government is willing or able, to do battlej    - with Congress on the issue.Iii). Even if a second generation SST were developed in collaboration with the USA the financial burdens for Britainand France would be huge.   A French estimate of  1500m forthe total development c^^^^ been quoted, of which it was admitted that none would be recovered.   Me think that a  .
-more realistic figure right he 50-1 OCf&apos;- higher.   It isdifficult to see how substantial additional production-losses, of the sort now occuririg on Concorde itself.Dould be avoided.iii). The technology of Concorde would have only limitedrelevance to that which a second-generation SST wouldrequire.    It would be necessary for this aircraft to havean engine which combined efficient supersohicpropulsion. withnoise characteristics at airports at least; as good as thoseof the most modern subsonic engines. The technology to achieve this has yet to be proven;   if the problem canbe solved at all the solution may owe little to work on concorde.   And while a second generation SST would probablyretain Concorde&apos;s basic shape, the &quot;scaling up&apos; of thea-irfrorco needed to achieve the extra size and range wouldbe neither simple nor cheap.&quot; iv)   It is not. clear that the/demand of the business community for faster travel will continue to increase inthe future as it has in the past.   The expansion and evolution of direct communication systems could for example make substantial inroads into that segment of the market to which any SST must primarily appealSECRET
Annex CThe Costs of	the 0, 16	and 19	Options		 m		0 to UK	Total	16 to UK	Total	19 to UK	Tot aExpenditure from 1 July 1 974			-.&apos;			i) Development	30	80	110	228	123	255ii) Net production	37	67	21	46	25	,63iii) Social costs	32	64	21	37	20	30Total, excluding airline costs	99	211	152	311	168	348iv) Airline capital investment	&apos; - mm	mm   &quot;	90	174	90	174 .v)   Airline operating results (profit I loss (-i-)	V) -		* 110	*67	+170	+127 .Total expenditure from 1 July 1974	99	211	352    .	552	428	649Total programme expenditure	635	1302	888	1 643	964	1740Notesi.   The development and/net production figures forOption 0 represent the contractual costs ofterminating the programme.&apos;ii.   The figures for the 16 and 19 Options assume that all but two aircraft   rare sold.
Annex the Legal position the development and production of Concorde.   neither party is. now under any obligation underthis Treaty to continue with the Concorde project.The fundamental objective of the 1962 agreement was the production of a marketable aircraft.   since it is now apparent that this fundamental objectivey..cannot be achieved neither country:&apos;ia under any obligation to authorize further development orthe production of further aircraft.   As regardswork which has already been authorized, in particular; the 16 aircraft., events have occurred which constitutes a fundamental change of circumstances* .entitling either country to withdraw from theAgreement new.Marketability of ConcordeThe present position in regard.to the commericalprospects of Concorde is as follows(a)   It is now accepted by both countries thatthere is no reasonable expectation that the
aircraft which has been developed will be sold at anything but a loss, even ifforeseeable sales are greatly exceeded (andthere is no evidence that they will be exceeded);(b)   The Concorde Directing Committee have reported to the two Governments that *great uncertainty surrounds the prospects for sales beyond those already made toBritish Airways and Air France, whateverversion is offered to airlines1.It is thus&apos;clear from the available evidence that,,neither the existing version of Concorde nor the modified version proposed by the French Governmentis a commercially marketable aircraft.     There is no evidence that this situation will change.Fundamental change of circumstances and workalready authorizedThe giving of authority for development workand the production of the 16 aircraft were stages in the process of implementing the fundamental purposeof the Treaty to produce a marketable supersonicaircraft.   Since this purpose can no longer be achieved,
It follows that the fundamental underlyingbasis on which this work was authorized hasdisappeared. -    .The consequences are -(a;   that there is no obligation on either party to authorize further development or production; and(b)   either party is entitled to discontinueits support for any development orproduction already authorized.


</content>
</cab>
