<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/183/20 images: 553-573</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S government(75) 7017 June 1975COPY NO      dCABINETPAY OPTIONS AND THE PROSPECT FOR INFLATIONNote by the Secretary of the CabinetI attach, for the consideration of Cabinet at its meeting on Friday 20 June,a report by the Official Steering Committee on Economic Strategy.JOHN hunt cabinet office i i17 June 1975i j i
(secret)PAY OPTIONS AND THK PROSPECT FOR INFLATIONReport by the Official Steering Committee on economic Strategy1.     This note first sets out the current Treasury forecast for therate of price increase in the period up to the first quarter of 1977.Next, it considers what would be involved in an inflation target forthe second half of 1976.   After describing some important featureslikely to affect pay settlements in the 1975-76 pay round, it thentries to set out the main options for pay policy for that round,beginning in the early autumn; and rehearses briefly the advantages and disadvantages of each of them.   The options discussed are:-i TUC guidelines only: another round;ii a non-statutory Government pay policy without a norm;iii a non-statutory Government pay policy with a norm;iv TUC guidelines or a Government norm supported by compulsorypre-notification of pay settlements and delaying powers;v a statutory policy with a norm.Schemes for taxing away excessive pay increases are not discussed inthis note, though Annex D , which is concerned with enforcement,,contains a reference to the use of such a tax as a penalty.    The notedoes not cover either schemes like that submitted by Michael Young toNEDC which involves very large tax levies to finance very largesubsidies; though the statutory pay policy which is part of that particular scheme corresponds to Option 5 above.2.     Annexes to this note concern:-A   the assumptions underlying the price forecast and factors which might change it;B   comparative inflation in other OECD countries;0   some comment on different types of pay norm and theirlikely effect on the RPI;D   enforcement in a statutory policy.1(secret)
(secret)The Price Forecast3. Tfee current forecast for the year on year increase in the retail price index is as follows:-1975	Q3	25	Q4	241976	Q1	20	Q2	16	Q3	15	Q4	141977	Q1	144.   It is dangerous to put too much weight on forecasts a year ahead,Many (including the Bank of England and the National Institute for economic and Social Research) would take the view that this forecast for the period after 1976 Q1 will prove too low.   For the reasons give in Annex A some decleration from the high rates of the summer and autumn of 1975 seems likely, hut, as Annex A also makes clear,it could easily prove less than shown in paragraph 3.   The exchange rate, oil prices, nationalised industry prices and indirect taxchanges could easily add 3% or 4% to it by the second half of 1976.5.   The assumption about pay in the 1975/6 pay round written into the forecast is that on present policies settlements will again be inthe range 25-30% on a year earlier.   Some reasons for this, togetherwith other assumptions underlying the forecast, are given in Annex A.Paragraph 8i below also refers.A Price Objective6.   There are strong reasons, both external and domestic, for seeking a speedy and convincing deceleration in our rate of inflation.Annex B shows some comparisons of UK inflation prospects and those ofother OECD countries.   Externally they include the pressure on sterling and the decline in our standing as a borrower arising from lack of confidence in our control of inflation, as well as the2(secret)
e c r e t)effects on competitiveness.   There are similar reasons of confidenceat home, especially for industrial investment.   In addition, it wouldbe important that any new counter inflation policies should showresults within a year or so, if support for the policies was to be sustained.7.   If Ministers accept this, the minimum objective to meet the requirement would seem to be to reduce the rate of inflation to \0foby the early autumn of 1976, with the prospect of reaching singlefigures by the end of the year.   This would still leave us above therates of our main competitors.   If a 10$ rate of increase, year onyear, were reached by say September 1976, the Government would beentitled to expect that pay in the 1976/77 pay round would be related to that figure, or less.   This would open the way to furtherdeceleration during 1977.   It would clearly be desirable to invitethe general assent of the community to such a programme and to make every effort possible to explain the need for it to the trade union movement.Pay Features affecting the 1975/6 Pay Round8.   Some features of the pay scene need to be borne in mind in considering the options for pay in 1975/76 discussed in the nextsection of this paper:i   the force of comparability within a pay round:&quot;the tone of the round&quot;.   Once a particular rate of pay increase becomes established in some important settlementsat the beginning of the round (eg local authority and HHSmanuals) subsequent settlements, especially in the public   Msector, will not readily fall below that level.   In particular,a decline in the rate of price increase during the round islikely to be reflected only gradually in a decline insettlement rates;3(secret)
ii it is a special feature of the 1975/76 pay round that we expect it to start against the background of a &quot;hump&quot; of 25-26$ price increases in the autumn of 1975.   There is an obvious risk that in spite of any subsequent decline, thiswill set the tone for the round.   There are signs that the tuc have shown some recognition of this in their recent discussions.   If a significant deceleration is to be achievedit would be necessary to bring into the reckoning the prospectof a lower rate of price increase, perhaps expressed as aninflation target, and secure settlements in the autumn wellbelow the then current year on year inflation rate;iii in the public sector comparability within the round is strong between successive groups of manual workers (ranging from loc 1 authority manuals and the industrial civil service to miners and railwaymen);   but there is also an importantgroup whose pay is affected by comparability with the previousround (non-industrial civil servant, the armed forces andothers covered by the Review Bodies, the. Police).   Comparabilitywith the previous round raises problems for any policy of de-escalation;iv there is a strong tendency for differentials to re-assertthemselves on a percentage basis if^they are compressed.This has happened both in relation to the flat rate elements in the the 1973/74 statutory policy ( 1+4$;   40p thresholds),and in relation to the TUC  30 low pay target;v there will be a higher level of unemployment in the 1975/76pay round.   This will undoubtedly   have an effect on someprivate sector settlements and, as stated in Annex A, it istaken into account in the forecast.   It is difficult to be surewhat effect it will have on the general level of pay settlementshowever and especially on those in the public sector.Experience suggests that the part of the pay scene where paydrift (positive or negative) is strongest and the impact of thelevel of demand on employment is greatest is that part of theengineering and construction industries where pay is mainlydetermined by plant or site bargaining.4(secret)
(secret)The Pay Options;   Option 1 :   TUO Guidelines only9.   The contribution which this policy would make to the reductionof the rate of inflation would depend on whether the guidelines werein the end stricter than in this round and whether they were morefaithfully observed.   The current price forecast assumes a continuanceof the present guidelines but implies a smaller excess over the RPIincrease than hitherto in the early settlements of the new pay round.10.   Recent public statements by some TUO leaders and the discussions in the TUC Economic Committee, as reported, imply a recognition ofthe need for a more explicit norm, which would allow less room forlatitude in interpretation;   and of the possibility that that normmight have to be below the level which would give general compensationfor the cost of living.   It remains to be seen whether the general council and Congress will find it possible to agree on a normconsistent with the kind of price objective discussed in paragraph 7;and whether some major unions would dissociate themselves from sucha norm.   Annex C shows the effect which various flat rate norms ofthe kind suggested by Mr Jack Jones would have on prices, if fullyobserved.   A flat rate of  8 would be a little above a 15$. norm, butwhilA more favourable to the low paid would probably have less chanceof observance by unions representing skilled and white collar workers.......   1111.   The advantages of a &quot;guidelines&quot; policy would be:i continuity of Government policy;ii limited Government commitment.   Responsibility for payrestraint continues to lie with the TUC and Government policy is less directly at stake in pay conflicts;butiii even if the TUC find it possible to take a stricter linethan in 1974-75, and remove some of the escape routes, it isdifficult to have any confidence that there will be sufficient .:observance in 1975-76.   Overseas opinion is likely to remainsceptical;5(secret)
(secret)iv this policy is not in itself an assurance that industrialconflict will be avoided.    It is at least as easy to have dispute over high figures as over lower ones.   Avoidance of conflictcould mean acceding to progressively higher bids;v this policy could well mean settling for a limitedcontribution only from incomes policy to meeting our economic difficulties.   It is in effect a decision to rely more on otherpolicies of restraint which, in present economic circumstances,already bear a heavy loadOption 2:   Non-statutory with no norm12.    i   A White Paper might say that as part of a national campaign to reduce the level of inflation to 10$ by late 1976 pay settlements would need to be lower, and indeed below the levelof RPI compensation;ii there would be no published norm or guiding light, though&apos; the target would indicate the general area for settlements.   Therewould be case by case decisions in the public sector and anappeal for much lower settlements in the private sector.There would be a determination to resist industrial action andrefuse financial provision for excessive settlements in thepublic sector but the policy would permit flexibility to accommodate groups too powerful to resist;iii there would need to be firm central control of pay negotiations in the public sector and comparability eitherwithin the round or with the previous round would have to be rejected.13.   The pros and cons of this policy are discussed in paragraphs 16and 17 below.Option 3:   Non-statutory with a norm14.   i.   A White Paper would promulgate a norm related to, say, a10% inflation target for autumn 1976;ii   the norm would be applied by appeal, perhaps with OBI supporin the private sector;   and by Government action or influence(including financial sanctions) in the public sector.   Because6
(secret)there is a norm, the need for full central control of negotiations is somewhat less than in Option 2;iii comparability would have to be set aside if its resultsconflicted with the norm.15.   The nearest precedent for Option 2 is the N -1 policy of theConservative Government of 1970-72.    The precedents for Option 3 areSir Stafford Oripps1 wage standstill of 1948-50; Mr Selwyn Lloyd&apos;spay pause and guiding light of 1961-62; and Lord George Brown1s&quot;Declaration of Intent&quot; of 1964-66.   The first and last rested onagreement with the 3JUC, the second did not.16.   The advantages of Options 2 and 3 are:-i they meet the demand for a new and determined Governmentinitiative to tackle the inflation, without resort to a statutory policy;ii in differing degrees, they permit more flexibility than ina statutory policy.   A few settlements inconsistent with the inflation target or the norm can be accommodated, provided theydo not set a pattern and thus destroy the policy;iii they are aimed first at the public sector but, especiallyin the circumstances of 1975-76, it is in the public sectorthat the struggle with pay inflation will be won or lost.   Itis right that the Government should make whatever changes are needed in the management of the public sector to achieve theresult;butiv a non-statutory policy has to be established by example,with whatever risk of confrontation at the beginning of the payround that involves.   It implies a decision to enforce againstthe local authority and NHS manuals in November/December 1975settlements well below the year-on-year HPI increase;(secret)
(secret)v as a counterpart to the fact that they permit moreflexibility, these policies give less assurance to those to whomthe policy is first applied that it will be applied even-handedlyto others.   This increases the risks of acquiescence for union leaders and thus the likelihood of resistance;vi these policies are exposed to accusations of discrimination against the public sector.   In Government-led voluntary policies,the Government inevitably appears to act more as employer and paymaster than as Government.   The Government has to suspendpublic sector pay institutions: pay research, the review bodies and arbitration for public sector pay.   It has to apply thepolicy as rigorously as it can in the public sector before it candemonstrate that the private sector will also comply.   Ifarbitration continued for the private but not the public sector,that would be both a serious loophole and a source of grievance;vii if it were thought that the non-statutory policy would failand that a statutory policy would then succeed it, that couldcreate forestalling pressure on the non-statutory policy.17.   As between Options 2 and 3, Option 2 seeks to provide both for greater flexibility in relating settlements to market needs(recruitment, profitability etc) and greater room for manoeuvre bythe Government.   The counterpart of that is however great uncertainty about how it will be applied in the private sector and a greater need to assert central control of local authority and nationalised industry pay negotiations, with whatever resistance that entails.The N -1 policy, which had some similarities, produced in 1972 muchof the disparity between public sector groups (teachers, nurses, thePost Office) which led to the special catching up increases in 1974.The absence of a norm might also mean that until such a policyestablished itself, it would have less impact on overseas opinion.Option 4:   Guidelines or norm with monitoring and delaying powers18. This policy, which requires legislation, would be similar tothat reflected in the Prices and Incomes Bill of 1966 when it was first introduced.   Its advantages would be:-8(secret)
(secret)i it stops short of requiring pay increases by statute tocomply with a norm, and does not make it illegal for employers to pay, provided the prenotification etc requirements arecomplied with.   Free collective bargaining continues;ii it might be possible to present this option as &quot;giving teethto the TUC guidelines&quot;, provided the guidelines were in themselves regarded as adequate;iii flexibility (and its counterpart risks) remains;butiv in legislating the Government incurs much of the criticismassociated with a statutory policy; and statutory delays, like a statutory (or a non-statutory) policy, could be challenged byindustrial action;v the need to resist most excessive settlements at the end ofthe delaying period remains if the policy is to carry conviction.This option does not remove the problem of enforcement.   It mightbe necessary to recreate the equivalent of the MBPI to assistthe Government in handling such cases.   In fact, the difficultiesof a case by case approach remain;vi it might be expected that, as in 1966, this option would prove to be a step on the way to a statutory policy.Option 5:   Statutory policy with a norm19.   The precedents are 1966-68 and 1972-74.   Both policies had an initial year or more of acceptance.   The advantages are:-i   an unreserved commitment by the Government, with suchadvantage as that may have in convincing unions settling earlyin the round that others will be similarly treated; and inconvincing external opinion of the Government1 s determination to tackle the inflation;9(secret)
(secret)ii assurance that very few employers, and no major ones in either the public or the private sector, will disregard the law,so that the policy will, in particular, be effective in theprivate sector.   This means even-handedness of treatment between public and private sectors and, provided the policy holds,uniformity of treatment within the pay round;iii arbitration, pay research, the review bodies, independentpay action by local authorities and nationalised industries are all suspended for the period of control but without theappearance of a specific attack on, or singling out of, any ofthese institutions;iv scope for promulgating a counter-inflation plan over say2 years, as part of an economic strategy; with the possibilityof a controlled relaxation of the pay controls in the second yearsubject to safeguards devised and negotiated in the first;butv the TUC would be bound to oppose a statutory policy (as theywould a tough voluntary one).   Only if there were a manifestcrisis could we expect their opposition to be token or muted.The reaction of individual unions would no doubt also depend onthe seriousness of the economic situation and the impact thatwas having on public opinion;vi as in 1966 and 1972, a statutory pay control would mean a reversal of Government policy;vii there is damage to the Government and to the credibility ofthe economy in any further failure to check pay inflation,whether it takes the form of inaction or of the breakdown of anew pay policy, statutory or non-statutory.   If a new tougherpay policy, statutory or non-statutory, is destroyed by strike action or the threat of it, the ability of the Government to govern is called in question.   The damage is however greaterwith a failed statutory policy not necessarily because the lawitself is broken, but because Ministers have to use consentpowers to adapt the law to the demands of particular groups.10(secret)
(secret)---.....-..........How serious this is depends on the circumstances (eg afterfailure to resist a strike successfully) in which consentpowers have to be used.20.   Crucial questions which arise on a statutorj&apos;- policy, but arisealso mutatis mutandis   on a tough non-statutory policy, are:-i is there a reasonable chance in the period October 1975 to july 1976 of the traditional honeymoon period/grudgingacquiescence for a statutory policy as in 1966-67 and 1972-73 ornot?   Would it for example be challenged at the outset by thelocal authority manuals and if so, could they be successfully resisted?ii is there a chance that the miners would acquiesce as in1973* or alternatively that, with the aid of a Ministerialsafety-valve power in the Act (like that used by the present government in March 1974) an out-of-line miners1 increase couldbe isolated?21.   Annex D contains a note about enforcement under a statutorypolicy.Types of Norm22.   Annex C contains notes on different types of norm, and a table showing the impact these norms would have on the rate of inflationin 1976.   The table suggests that a 15$ norm (or a flat rate of  8)is the highest which would have any chance of yielding a 10$ inflationrate by September 1976.    (A &quot;mixed&quot; equivalent would be  4 plus 7t$) .It might well prove insufficient.17 June 1975(secret)
(secret)ASSUMPTIONS UNDERLYING THE PRICE FORECAST AND FACTORS WHICH MIGHTAssumptions1.   The more important assumptions underlying the price forecast areas follows:-i pay settlements in the 1975-76 pay round are assumed again to he in the range 25$-30c/ ,   On the one hand the pay round willstart in October/November 1975 against a background of a 25$ year on year rate of inflation, compared with about 17$ in 1974; and thegoing rate at the end of the current round will be in the range25$-30$.   On the other hand, unemployment will be rising andthere will not be the once-for-all adjustments following the exitfrom the statutory policy which occurred in the autumn of 1974;ii the effective sterling exchange rate is forecast to fall intwo steps of 5$ to 29i$ below Smithsonian.   The forecast in factassumes that the first step would take place in July 1975 and thesecond in January 1976.   In fact the rate is now already 26$ belowSmithsonian, a fall of nearly 7$ from the starting point of the forecast;iii after including the effects of the forecast sterlingdepreciation, food import prices are assumed to rise at 8$ overthe period the first quarter of 1975 and the first quarter of1977.   Import prices of manufactured goods are assumed to rise at15$ per annum and other non food import prices at 8$ per annum;iv nationalised industry prices are forecast to add 2- -$ to theRPI in 1975-76 and 14-$ in 1976-77;v local authority rents are assumed to increase on average by45p a week in 1975-76 (which is the assumption Ministers areCHANGE ITmaking for subsidy purposes). In 1976-77 they are assumed torise in line with consumer prices;vi   since the basis of the forecast Is &quot;existing policy&quot;, there is1
(secret---.....Ml.........inn......r-*OECD COMPARATIVE INFLATION FORECASTSConsumer prices.   An OECD forecast is available up to the first half of 1976.The figures show percentage increases on the corresponding half year of the preceding year (eg 1976 first half on 1975 first half).USA     Germany     Japan     France     Italy     Canada UK75(1) 9.8% 6.2% 12.1% 12.9% 21.4% 12.7% 19.4%76(1)     5.9%      5.8% 9.0%      9.2%      11.7%      9.1%       16.4%Wholesale Prices2.   Forecasts of the rate of increase in domestic wholesale prices,year on year, are as follows:-USA     Germany Japan France Italy Canada          UK74         22.2%    13.6% 26.6% 29.1%      35.8% 20.7% 24.6%75          10.7%      2.5% 8.9% 10.6%      18.2% 9.0% 22.0%76           5.6%      1.2% 7.9% 7.4%      12.9% 9.1% 17.Increases in Unit Wage Costs in Domestic Currencies3.   The following table shows year-on-year changes in unit wage costs for the UK and 6 competitor countries.   They are not corrected forappreciation (Germany) or depreciation (UK) of the respectivecurrencies since the purpose is to show unit labour cost increasesthroughout the period.   It follows that they do not measure relativecompetitiveness, though the increases in 1975 and 1976 give some indication of what may happen to competitiveness in that period.4.   The figures for 1975 and 1976 are tentative and preliminary.   Someof the high unit costs for 1975 (eg for the US) reflect the expecteddecline in output and the low ones for 1976 the effect of a recovery of output.   Wot too much weight should be put on the individualfigures.   The general picture is however clear.   1973 (a year of paycontrols) shows up as the best year of the run for the UK for relativewage inflation.   1974 was a bad year.   1975 looks a better year inrelation to the US (because of the fall in output there), but notin relation to Germany;   and 1976 looks very bad indeed.5.   It may be right to allow for some time lag in effects incompetitiveness eg 1973 costs ^affecting the first half of 1974 andso on.(secret)
(secret)ANNEX B (contd)changean annual	Canada	USA	Japan	Germany	France	Italy	Neth.	Belux	Total	UKrates										1972	3.9	1.7	4.6	3.8	1 .6	5.2	0.3	2.6	2.9	8.61973	4.4	2.8	5.1	5.6	10.3	15.7	3.1	10.2	6.2	8.61974	8.2	8.7	31.1	10.3	13.4	21.4	15.0	12.0	13.9	18.61975	7.7	18.0	24.3	5.9	17.0	22.5	19.0	12.5	15.5	20.71976	8.5	3.1	3.7	- 2.9	7.3	9.5	8.6	8.9	4.6	17.8(secret)
(secret)TYPES OP NO EM AND THEIR RPI EFFECTSThe attached table shows the effect on the current price forecast of substituting pay settlements at the levels stated for the presentassumption of settlements in the 25% to 3O70 range.2.    15% norm.   This is self explanatory.   Part of the argument for it would be that it took account of the expected decline in the rateof inflation over the ensuing year (with a 10% target, a decline fromsay 25% in October 1975 to 10% in October 1976).   A single percentagenorm would be closest to normal bargaining practice.   But it would leave the RET in 1976 Q3 only a little under 12%, with the risk of higher figures if the outturn were worse on other elements of the forecast.3.   10% * 5%.    This would give 10% at normal settlement date plus 5%six months later.   Like the more severe alternative 5% * 10%. it aimsto reduce the impact of a 15% pay increase on prices by splitting thenorm, rather than by reducing the 15% total.4.   Indexation (j RPI) and 5% plus full indexation.   The first ofthese is very severe indeed.    It involves giving no increase at thenormal operative date, so that for example local authority manualswould say in the autumn of 1975 that they were being asked to miss acomplete year&apos;s pay increase under conditions of 25% inflation.       ,, .uThereafter it would give percentage (or if desired flat rate) increasesequivalent to ij- of the RPI increase in each quarter at the end ofthat quarter.5.   5% plus full indexation is more generous, and roughly equivalent in impact to 5% + 10%.    There would be a 5% increase at normalsettlement date, plus indexation payments on a 1% for 1% basisquarterly in arrear.6.   Indexation tailors increases more closely to the cost of living,tut it is vulnerable (as were thresholds) to an unexpectedly badoutturn on prices.   There is also the risk that it will become1
(secret)embedded in the negotiating system and will be treated as a &quot;floor&quot;or automatic entitlement in a post-control period, with bargaining on top.   Denmark and Belgium seem to have been trying to modify oreliminate their pay indexation systems for anti-inflationary reasonsrecently.7.     Flat rate norms ( 6,  8,  10).   A  6 flat rate would have to bejustified as designed to protect the low paid (20$ of the presentTUC target of  30 a week).   An  8 flat rate is equivalent in its effects to a 15$ norm.   Higher flat rates come nowhere near achieving the suggested objective.   A  12 flat rate would be equivalent to thecurrent Treasury forecast.8.     The great trouble with flat rates is that they risk resistancefrom unions representing skilled, white collar or managerial workers,as well as from better paid manual workers like the miners and thosein electricity supply.   They also store up pressure on differentialsfor the immediate post-control period.   The 1973-74 controls usedmixed flat rate / percentage norms ( 1 * 4$; 40p thresholds; 7$ or 2.25) but this was enough to generate big post-control increases topull out differentials.   The  30 TUC target had similar effects.   the attempt to use the policy for income redistribution, rather thanachieving this through the tax/benefit system, adds seriously to thestrains on it.   Under a non-statutory system in particular the risks of non-compliance seem notably greater with a flat rate than with a percentage norm.9.   Non-statutory or Statutory.   In general these norms could be associated with a guidelines policy, a non-statutory policy with anorm, or a statutory policy.   But the more severe norms would have little chance of general observance outside a statutory policy (andmight of course lead to defiance within it).   A split norm would hardly work outside a statutory policy.   And according to the natureof the policy one would have to discount the RPI effects to a greater or lesser degree to take account of the likelihood of non-observance.This would apply particularly to a &quot;guidelines&quot; norm.2(secret)
(secret)ENFORCEMENT IN A STATUTORY PAY policy.     The heart of a statutory pay policy is that it is illegal for employers to pay more than a specified increase; or more precisely,that it is illegal for an employer to pay an increase withoutpre-notifying it and if the controlling authority then objects, it becomes illegal to pay the increase.   The question then arises whether it is necessary or desirable to protect employers frompressure by employees or groups of employees to break the law byconceding out of line increases.2.     In the Prices and Incomes Act 1966 and again in the CounterInflation Acts 1972 and 1973 provisions were included making it an offence for Unions or &quot;organisations of workers&quot; to put strikepressure on employers to break the law.   Prosecutions could be under-taken only with the consent of the Attorney General and penalties-were fines, not imprisonment.   The fines were primarily payable outof union funds, not individual pockets.   In fact the 1972 and 1973 Actpowers were never used against a group of workers, or an individualworker.   But in theory it would have been possible for a reallydetermined would-be martyr to get himself or his union fined and eventually court imprisonment by committing contempt of court in refusing all forms of payment.3.    What really matters however is whether a policy is successfully resisted by strike action or the threat of it.   If strike action isavoided or defeated and the policy stands, it is not really a centralissue whether the union concerned, or part of it, is also prosecuted.The 1973 experience, when the prosecution powers were, never used,confirms this.   The statutory sanction operates primarily onemployers who in practice do obey the law, especially if they are substantial and important public companies.   So normally do the vast majority of unions and workers.1
(secret)ANNEX D (contd)4.   A tax penalty.   The Treasury have nevertheless explored with theirlegal advisers the question whether it would be practicable to have apay control under which:i     it was illegal for the employer to pay an excessive increase,ii   the matching deterrent on employees and unions was not tomake it an offence subject to a fine to pressurise an employer into an excessive payment: but to provide that the whole of an excesspayment would be taxed away.5.   The Treasury1s conclusion however, in the light of the advice ofthe Treasury Solicitor, is that such a system would not be workable.Before the tax or penalty could be levied on employees the liability toit would have to be clearly established: that is, it would have to beestablished in law that the employer had committed an offence by payingan out-of-line increase.   This means that the tax could not be collecteduntil the employer had been convicted in the Courts and ($  he used them)had exhausted all the channels of appeal - a process that could takemonths.   A long interval could therefore elapse between the pay settlement and the imposition of the penalty, and this interval would greatly weaken the credibility of the penalty and its deterrent value.The longer the money was in payment, the more difficult it would be totake it away; and recovery of past over-payments might anyway be    ,impracticable, eg because of job changes.6.     Secondly, there would be great administrative difficulty in determining the amount of the tax liability for each individualemployee.   How much benefit a particular employee derived from the excessive increase would vary not only according to how the settlementapplied to different grades and groups, but according to the number of hours worked, sickness, unemployment, change of job and other factors.All this would provide copious material for appeals, and it is hardlyconceivable that assessment could be left to employers and all forms ofappeal denied.   These are the difficulties associated with any attemptto tax increases in pay.   Taken with the point in paragraph 5, theyseem to rule out this particular approach.but2
(secret)RPI EFFECTS OF PAY NORMS(1)New year-on-year RPIincrease(2)Change in(1) from post-Budget forecast(3)New quarter-on-quarter RPIincreasei. 15% norm   1976 Ql 19.3Q2 14.6Q3 11.9ii. 10% 4- 5%   1976 Ql 18.9Q2 13.7Q3 10.6-0.8-1.8-2.7-1.2-2.7-4.02.24.02.11.93.51.7iii. 5&apos;/o + 10%   1976 Ql   18.6Q2 12.8Q3    9.1-1.5-3.4-5.51.72.91.1iv. Indexation^ 76 Ql 18.2ii RPI)           Q2 12t2Q3 8.0v. 5% plus full176 Q1 18*7indexation      Q2 12.9Q3 9.0-1.9-4.2-6.6-1.4-3.5-5.61.52.70.71.73.01.0 6 flat1976 Ql 19.1Q2 14.1Q3   11.0-1.0-2.3-3.62.03.71.7vii.  8 flat1976 Ql 19.3Q2 14.7Q3   11-9-0.8-1.7-2.72.24.02.1viii. lO flat   1976 Ql   19.6Q2 15.5Q3   13.2-0.5-0.9-1.42.44.52.6(secret)


</content>
</cab>
