<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/23/22 images: 200-211</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
TO be KEPT under LOCK and KEY, ^vyWit is requested that special cai-e may be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.9 5^p tp. nPHin FROTW.PY 0? HIS BRITANNIC MAJSSTTS OQmm&amp;miCONO.WAR CABINET.COMMUNIST PARTY.Memorandum &quot;by the Home secretary in order that the Cabinet may &quot;be Icept informed of the0licy and activities of the Communist Party,  I circulate? information -(l) a police report of a meeting on 7th March of officials and organisers of the Party;(S) a statement made lay Mr. Harry Pollitt on14-th March and circulated by the Communist Party.H.M.ME OFFICE.3rd April 1942.

SPECIAL BRANCH REPORT.The district secretary, Ted Bramley,  reported on theprogress of the London District of the Communist Party ofGreat Britain at a meeting on 7th March at the CambridgeTheatre which all branch secretaries,  area group organisersand factory group leaders wore instructed to attend..- &apos;- &apos; With -very few exceptions,  owing to sickness orpressure of&apos;work,  the full number of London Districtofficials attended, each bringing a wife, husband or friend.281 factory .group leaders were present,  and about 80 branchsecretaries.&apos;     Nearly half the audience was composed ofwomen.      There were two soldiers in uniform.Behind the platform, on which were the leadingofficials, of the London District Committee and some central committee members, a large poster was exhibited which borethe following. ^Aim for &apos; March - 51st.  1942: members 15,000;    factorygroups 500:    literature sales  7,000 per month;    Marxist ...- Classes 609^    Income  5,000 per month;  .and GROWTH January,1941, to December,  1941:    Members 3,500 increased to 9,000;factory groups 200 increased.to 300;    Literature sales (permonth1)  922:increased to  4,500;. Marxist Classes 60 increasedto- 350; &apos;  Income per month increased, from.  450 to  1,500&quot;..!:; Bramley said that in the opinion of the District  .Committee and the Central Committee, London had made good progress, but it appeared that some comrades were not convinced of the ultimate success of-the Party,  and some ..&apos; were &quot;pessimistic and easily set back by an indifferent   .attitude on the part of their friends and workmates.      Forthe benefit of these- poor communists he would give some information&apos;- about the &apos; terrific&quot;, support - now,r eeeived fromunexpected quarters.      Recently General Gough had spoken.,from -a platform.&apos;, and&apos;&quot;praised the-; Soylot Army, and said-, he    .:was&apos; glad to call them his. &quot;comrades&quot;.,   .  He, Braroley, -had .--;-spoken during--&apos;the past few months &quot;with- no fewer than 24Members of Parliament,;; all previously ant-i-communist.;out of 56- Anglo-Soviet committees in-London, 46 committeeshad communists publicly and&apos; efficiently represented.      Theco-operative movement had definitely, joined with Marx house in arranging classes, and&apos; had joined&apos; in &quot;with the . demand to.:raise the ban on&apos;the - &quot;Daily Worker&quot;.    &apos; Industry, he said,was the mainspring of agitation.On the Amalgamated Engineering Union Comrade. J.R.  Scotthad been elected by an overwhelming-.majority, and Wal Hanningtohad been elected by a clear cut majority.      Of the othercontestants some other &quot;comrades&quot; had&apos;received satisfactoryvotes,  even though beaten by Scott..      The.: A.E.U.  was the, mainweapon -of the Communist Party now and it remained for -eachComrade:to agitate inside the Labour Movement and to bring-about -the;, downfall&apos;of &quot;Transport House&quot; and the &quot;Daily Herald&quot;.On the Transport and General Workers Union&apos; election,Comrade&apos; Kaplan.had been successful,  and.this was -an equally-Important victory in&apos;view of the large number of women inthat Union.    ;        .;&apos;;.&apos;. &apos;.,.&apos;The question of bringing more women members, was an:important one and .the comrades in factory groups must not hesitate in recruiting them.   . Strangely, enough, -support
for the women had come from some managements,  for instanceE.M.I., Hoovers,  and Harris Lcbus had sent a representativeof the managements to a recent Women&apos;s Parliament conference.Bromley then dealt with the membership of the london district. &quot;    The membership drive v/as very satisfactory,but 5,000 more were required before March 31st, 1942.Districts had greatly increased, particularly in South Eastand South West London.      Brarnloy instanced Camber we 11 andBermondsey as tv/o districts which had shown the greatestincreases.      Bob Cotton, he said, had been detailed towhip up enthusiasm in a district away from his own andhad succeeded beyond all expectation.      In South&apos;EastLondon the membership of all the branches in January, -1941,was 238,  and at the end of February,  1942, was 1,116.      InSouth West London the membership was only 308 in January 1941and at the end of February 1942,  it was 1,208.Each member must use energy and determination,  and each member must become an active propagandist,  said Bramley.He must equip himself with ideas, and agitate, lead andorganise his&quot;fellow workers.      The future of the SocialistState aimed at depended upon the next few weeks,  and withthe raising of the ban on the &quot;Daily Worker&quot; all opposition would be crushed, with the wonderful performance of theRed Army to bring as the outstanding example of a SocialistState.Bramley said the drive for money had been more thandisappointing, as the life of the party depended very much on finance.      Of the total aimed at,  13,680,  only  4,607had been paid in.      To get money it was essential to getmembers,  and the aim of each representative in the audienceshould be to increase his or her branch or group.      He had heard some objections to the drive for membership.      One oldmember had objected against it on the grounds that &quot;arevolutionary party ceased to become revolutionary if itwas flooded with members&quot;..      This peculiar frame of mind shoube corrected at once.      Only with a largo membership, withthe seizure of the wonderful opportunity now open to theParty could the Socialist State, planned on the lines ofthe great Stalin, be. obtained in this country.      Neverbefore was there such a need for a Communist rule.      Londoncould be made into a communist stronghold.Bramley said the four main issues confronting theParty were:    first to complete the raising of the  13,680,and the recruitment of 5,000 new members to obtain the totalof 15,000 for London,  and to build 500 factory groups.Secondly,  to organise the Labour movement in the factories to the communist way of thinking.      This was imperativeto bring about the. change in the political life of the workerand as out of 980,000 factory workers in the London Districtthere were only 300 groups, much work was in front of each member of the audience.      The silent majority must be brougninto the party and the factory workers must be made aware ofthe power that was theirs.      Thirdly,, it was essential to wi-realisation of entire policy in the next few weeks by theestablishment of a Second front in Europe this Spring;   &quot;by increasing production;    and by demanding the indpendenceof India.      The fourth and last point was the demand for trierenewal of the &quot;Daily Worker&quot;, the most powerful weapon inthe hands-of the Communist Party.
Bramley then referred to the necessity for each member to agitate for the independence of India,  and deploredthe bad attendance at a recent India Meeting at Kingsway Kailwhen only 500 members out of London&apos;s 109000 troubled themselvesto attend.He instanced the response to mass pressure by-referring to the recent changes in the Government,   and saidMoore--Brabazon and Margesson out, and Cripps in, at leastrepresented a new policy.      The same pressure could be exertedfor the realisation of the second front in Europe- and forthe raising of the &quot;Daily Worker&quot; ban.      &quot;We want a victory in 1942 not in 1943&quot;,  and &quot;London is to be the Moscow of britain&quot;.William Rust then spoke.      He sail that thedemand for the raising of the ban on the &quot;Daily Worker&quot;was almost like a religious revival.      The need for a free expression of the workers&apos; views was now greater than ever,and the renewal of the paper would bring the party theopportunity it was waiting for and the victory it deserved.As soon as Mr.  Morrison spoke in the House about the &quot;daily worker&quot;,  said Rust,  his office was flooded with letterspledging support and promises of financial aid and ifMorrison could see the correspondence he would not be soconfident in the House.      However,  the movement for the raising of the ban was growing greater and greater and thesupport of foremost  journalists and editors was now adding to the voice of the workers for a newspaper that would givethe workers&apos; news and the workers&apos;  ideas.      Lenin&apos;sinstruction to Tom Bell, many years ago, was to have a newspaper for the revolutionary movement.Rust then asked the members of the audience to spread propaganda for the &quot;Daily Worker&quot; and to arouse publicconsciousness.      The greatest- enemies of progress came fromthe Labour strongholds. Transport House and such places.The &quot;Daily Herald&quot; would lose its circulation among the workers&apos;and the men behind the &quot;Daily Herald&quot; intended to fight, againstthe resumption of the &quot;Daily Worker&quot;.      To offset that pressure was the work in front of each person present,  andit was their duty to agitate for the newspaper that wouldtruly represent the Socialist State.

Statement made by Mr. Harry Pollitt on 14th March and circulated by the Communist Party.

Speaking on behalf of The Central Committee of the Communist Party, in the Brangwyn Hall, Swansea, on Saturday, March 14th, Harry Pollit stated:

"On March 11th I listened to the Prime Minister&apos;s statement on India.

It was the first time I had been in the House to listen to a statement since September 2nd, 1939. I was struck with the feeling of demoralisation that had come over Parliament. It reflected the political situation of our country.

A deadly paralysis is creeping over Britain, one that is dangerous in the extreme. It is affecting the workers in industry, civil defence and the armed forces.

It is not caused by the heavy blows and defeats that Britain has received in recent months, for, given complete confidence in the leadership and policy of the government, these can serve to increase the working and fighting spirit of the entire people, as experience in the Soviet Union has proved.

It is the sense of groping in the dark; of absence of clear policy or specific aims; of living from hand to mouth. In short it represents lack of leadership that can no longer be tolerated.

If this opinion is doubted, then let the contrary evidence be brought forward, but I challenge any serious political observer to talk to the workers in any factory, to any soldier home on leave, to any civil defence worker at any Warden&apos;s Post or Fire Station and produce a different picture.

Demoralisation of the most serious kind has seized a section of the Ruling Class, who have lost in a night their Empire conquests of centuries, and lost them to those whom they considered of an inferior race.

India is belatedly and begrudgingly now to be wooed, by some magic formula, not as an act of justice and equity, but only because "Japan is at its gates".

We kill hundreds of French civilians through air raids, but make no attempt to kill the thousands of Nazi soldiers on French soil.

The newspapers are full of talk about "Hitler&apos; s gigantic Spring offensive", but deadly silence about Britain organising any offensive of any kind.

There is endless speculation on what Stalin meant by certain statements he made in his Order of the Day on the occasion of the 23rd Anniversary of the Red Army, but no one wants to mention Stalin&apos;s plain statement that the Red Army is still fighting alone.

Mischievous talk is being circulated about whether or not "when the Red Army has beaten the Nazis Stalin will make a separate peace with Hitler." This is the cover used by those elements who would like to make their separate peace with Hitler now.
-2-&quot; No one in leading Government circles dares to think, talkand inspire -the people with the will to work, fight andorganise in terms of smashing   Hitler this year - in fact no onenow dares to mention any year in which they will smash Hitler- : It is an impossible situation into which Britain has teenallowed to drift. - It is/impermissible&apos; that it should be allowedto continue for another day, for it could be changed in a day&quot;4once the people v&amp;re given a clear lead&apos;,  and organised to opQra*it,-   Unless this is done and done now,-, then let there be no&quot;whining or beating of breasts that-later on we have to, pay sUcha heavy price as the result of present indecision and hesitancy.for the spirit that dominates the leadership of the /country is&apos;not. even militantly defensive.Defence can evoke response j but we&apos; repeat that throughoutthe country at &quot;the present time, frustration is the predominatingcharacteristic - stronger&apos; far than the desire of achievement,Complacency is stronger than the will- to fight.    Attention topetty things takes more time and thought-than the great decisiveissues confronting the people.       yBritain is in danger... Britain is not merely experiencinga.lullj  it is being undermined politically. and morally in awaythat is worth, a half dozen fascist, military victories.Contrast&apos;. ourVsituation with &quot;&quot;that of the-&quot;Soviet Union.   Nonation-has suffered.auch losses in territory; &apos; such suffering;&apos;such atrocities;-   such a selfless destruction of its ov/n resourc&apos;and&apos; yet, because of the &apos;politicai andvmoral -unity of the people,through their complete&apos;, confidence in their, leadership, despite iall,-, they have found the. way to past from the defensive to the offensive under conditions which make our ov/n tasks child&apos;s plajin comparison. &apos;        &apos;s : -. :&quot;-&apos;--&apos;&apos;&apos; . .-. -.; ...npr-dm&apos; the first, days of. December until&apos; this very hour theyhave never once returned to,theedefenslve,  they have paid aterrible-price, but they - steadily - push the Nazis back, regainlost ground&apos;,  liberate their&apos; peopleundermine, key Nazi positionsgiving-them no rest or respite, /striking &quot;every conceivable Mn-f.blow in the most unlikely places.   &quot;&apos;       ,.. r;-. While&apos; we talk about&apos;; &quot;Hitler&apos; s Spring -of f ensivei&apos; they calral.pursue their policy of making this offensive impossible on the^s-cale it was first, contemplated.-   While people here talk about&quot;they wonder how soon the Red Army will be in Berlin&quot; to salvetheir cowardly consciences that they are. not prepared to land aiarmy at all even in Prance, only:.twenty one Hj&amp;es away from britain. &apos;        &apos; J * -* ^. ^ The.&apos; contrast between Britain and the Soviet Union, brandsus with; shame. &apos;   . - -&quot;&apos;..,. ;&apos;&quot;.&apos;.-.,.     &apos;-&quot;&apos;:&apos;While the Soviet people fight: &quot;and endure,  their only thouglbeing ,of&apos;:.victory, this, year,-- here we are- in&apos; Britain wondering   Mwhe-therwe wiil^^wihithe&apos;w&apos;ar in any year at all, -giving5more attoBto.-Income\:.tax-agiiation than we do to demanding a Second Front Bso&apos;, that! the British and Soviet armies can jointly finish off HigHere, we &quot;ate. wondering if weicanlive with dog racing onl3&apos;-Bone day a-week,  and. expecting the&apos;Red&apos;Army to go on killing tne*
Fourth.Establish a real Ministry of Production, with fullNazi dogs every day.      Here we are seeking out the most elaboratejudicial measures (because it is our -way of doing things) to end the Black Market racketeers/ who only exist because the rich wantwhat they provide,&apos;while the&apos; Red Army strains every nerve to killevery Nazi on Soviet soil.We sit back and smugly say &quot;The Red Army are doing fine,we hope they, will keep it up, we did-our share by what we went through when, we . stood alone In 1940-1&quot;,What hypocrisy.      Why the word &quot;sacrifice&quot; has no real meaninor significance for the overwhelming majority of the british people.     -We are- still living in .luxury compared to the gigantic -sacrifices that the Soviet people gladly impose upon themselves.This cannot go on.      There is no single thing the Sovietpeople, have done that we cannot do also, given the leadership toorganise the necessary -measures and necessary confidence.Let us face facts&quot;. .   The territorial..losses   &quot;in the Far Easthave not roused a ripple amongst, the common people of Britain.They do not see them as. their dosses, but only as parts of anImperialist Empire, which had only been increased to exploit themfor private gain.     &apos; But what is not seen,  and it is theresponsibility &apos;6f the leadership to make this clear, .is that it isBritain which now stands in deadly danger,  and. unless we take the -offensive,  quite a different kind of danger than was faced in1940-1. .   :        -   \ &quot;&quot; .&apos; &apos;. ...The time-has come to stop the rot.      What.should be done?First,  to firmly declare what our policy is,  strengthen- theGovernment, restore the confidence to the people in the leadership of Britain.      Show that the main enemy-in this world war isHitlerite Germany,  and that every- resource of Britain ..is,-going tobe subordinated to: defeating Hitler.      Once this is done Japan andItaly will soon be finished off.Second..   Take every step that will strengthen the alliance between Britain and the Soviet Union,, jso -that there can be-: coinple-unity of perspective,  strategy., diplomacys.propaganda and resources, with absolute guarantee to the people that it is.an alliance in Peace as well as in war.Third.   .   Open up the Second Front in Europe,  and for-, thispurpose mobilise and organise everything that this decisive&apos;. -operation demands, whatever temporary setbacks may have sx-i.ll tobe experienced in other less.--deo-lsivo theatres of the struggle against the Axis Powers.      Sooner or later&apos;, the fight againstHitler directly in Europe will have to take place.      No. member ofthe Government has a.moral right to call on French workers to strike and sabotage,  unless they are prepared to land Britishtroops to fight against the Nazis.The Second Front is the only military operation- that can beundertaken: that will restore not only confidence,&apos;, but evoke anyentirely new outlook throughout industry,  the armed, forces,  and .civil.defence, while simultaneously it will secure equality ofsacrifice in a way and on a - scale that no moral--,&quot;exhortations orlegislation can effect.      The common people will-know how to force through equality of sacrifice.
power to take over all war industries, materials and manpower-taking the workers into full co-operation in r egard to every&apos;aspe c t --of pro duo t i on.-Fifth. &apos; Increase the pay and allowance to the men an-i ^in&quot; the.-armed &quot;forces. Completely revise all training in the.of actual&apos; &quot;battlefield experiences. Abolish all old school tiemethods of: appointing officers. Intensify the political trnjpand education of the armed forces. * Sack all the&apos; &quot;Give 1 em Pivgenerals.&apos; &apos; Revise:/&apos;tdie whole welfare ^system associated with the armed forces&quot;&quot;, so that off duty there are no. class barriers, and give the rank and file the fullest opportunity for bringing fortheir ideas and initiative.Sixth. Recognise without qualification, the right, of -Mto have its independence; call on the Indian National congress leaders to&apos;establish a National Government/representative of aldecisive sections of Indian opinion.Seven. Proclaim the aim of defeating Hitler in 1942, and allow nothing, and no one to stand in the way of its achievementThis is the way to end the present situation -n of hesitancy,indecisi.von.ess and demoralisation.It needs a bold hand and leadership to carry it through,that has no fear of the common people, hut is&quot;prepared to drawupon their inexhaustible resources of genius, creative energy ainitiative;  bo that from this there will.be such a unity,confidence and determination that will sweep ruthlessly asideevery weakling and obstacle.The dead hands of the past can no longer &quot;be allowed to faland fumble. , d&apos;k&apos;*&apos;-Britain can be roused, and its finest hour can be in victoand not in defeat.Britain is held back today, because the interests of so fenare still allowed to stand in the path of the many that are soready to do and dare their all to secure it.Britain must and shall find itself.Britain-must and shall be roused to a new conception of purpose- and duty.      To a new sense of dignity and victory.     to new sense of loyalty to Allies who are pouring out their life&apos;sblood that we may live.      To a new consciousness of the sacreclnof the Cause for which we fight.Once this is done then sacrifice will &quot;be ennobled with anew willingness and majesty.Our finest pages will.be written not in battles for conquesbut for freedom, for the victory over fascism,  for the right to live in peace and all the new avenues of social advance that nrllthen be open to world humanity.On &quot;behalf of THE COMMUNIST PARTY I pledge it to do allin its power to see that what is needed shall be accomplished.



</content>
</cab>
