<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/13/0 images: 93-98</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
m89jlS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY1 S GOVBRNMENTVI j; 0 3 E T.WAR CABINET 242 A,Minutes &quot;of a Meeting of tho War Cabinet held at 10 downing street, S.W. on Monday, October 1st., 1917 at 11.30 p.m.PRESENT:The Prime minister he Right Hon. The Earl Curzon ofledleston, K,G.,G.C.S.I, ,G.C.I,E.ho Right Hon. The Viscount Milneri C oB a,G.C*K*G.he Right Hon. A, Boner Law, M.P.(In the Chair)The Right Hon. G.N. Barnes, M.P,Lieutenant-General The Right Hon;J.C, Smuts, E.C*The following were also present-he Right Hon. A.J4Balfour;fM.-tM. P., Secretary of state or Foreign Affairs.admiral Sir J.R.Jellicoe, 4.C.B.,,M. .G.C.V.O., First Sea Lbrdnd Chief of the Naval Staff.omraodore d.M, Paine, C.B.,M.y.G.&quot;4 th Sea Lord of the Admiralty.&apos;he Right Hon. W.S. Churchill?-, Minister of Munitions.ir W. Weir, Controller of Aoro-fautical Supplies, Ministry oflunitions.fr. J.B.Maclean, Ministry oflunitions.ir BJ Troup, K*C.B., Permanenthder/Secretary of State forOfte hf fairs.ir S. Henry, G.C.V.O. ,K.C.B.*&apos;.:*SjiX., Commissioner of these^opolitan Police *The Right Hon, The Earl of Derby,K.O. ,JE0C.V,..0* ,C.B. , Secretaryof State for War,General Sir W.R. Robertson, G.G.BK.C.7,0.,D.S.O., Chief of theImperial General Staff.Field-Marshal The Viscount Frenchof Ypres, K.P..G.C.B., O.M.iO.C.V.O., .C,M.G., Commander-in-Chief, Home Forces.Lieutenant-General Sir D. HendersciK.C.B. ,D.S.O.;, Director-General o Military Aeronautics.Major General Sir F.C. Shaw, Chie-fof the General Staff, Home ForcesBrigadier-General E.B. AshmoreCM.G. ,M.V.O., Home Forces. &apos;The. Right Hon. The ViscountCowdray, President, Air Board.Lieutonant-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, K.C.B.    (Secretary)Major Lo Storr,(Assistant Secretary).
(l) Major General Ashmore described in detail the&quot;defensive measures adopted by the Field.Marshal Commanding--&apos;in-Chie , Home Forces, to meet hostile air raids on thiscountry^ drawing particular attention to the use of &quot;aprons1;which consisted of three Captive balloons, connected by long strings of wire.    These &quot;aprons&quot; could not at present be used at a higher altitude than 7,000 ft.    Their moral effect upon the enemy was great,  and they forced him to ahigher altitude and thus reduced the zone which had to be watched by our machines.    He wanted, if possible, toincrease the number of these screens to 20, putting up one new screen a week.    He anticipated great difficulty inseouring the proper number of trained balloon hands.    the barrage zones were clearly indicated by the incendiaryshells.    The fact that so few raiders managed to penetrateto London showed the efficacy of our gunfire.   We wanted,however, more night-flying scout machines and pilots, ofwhich at present only 6 were available.    The provision of larger night-flying machines, with a good performance wasurgent.With regard to searchlights, General Ashmore saidthat we had at present 7 lights of the most powerful type;these oould only be obtained in France,  and 40 or 50 more were now on order.Sir William Weir pointed out that the provision ofthese additional 20 &quot;aprons&quot; would very seriously interferewith other aeronautical supplies.The Field-liarshal Commanding-in-Chief, Home Forces,reminded the War Cabinet that there had been raids on five nights during the past week.    The casualties had been veryslight, the raid on the previous night only causing onedeath in London,  and the damage caused not excessive.    Hethought that an average of 20 enemy planes attacked eachnight.    The raiders came over in relays.    It was impossibleto determine what type of machine was used by the enemy.Aa regards probable enemy casualties among the raidingmachines, he thought it possible that three or four hadbeen brought down during the week.   Lord French said thatthere were two points which required the immediate attention and decision of the War Cabinet(a)    The replacement of the 3-inch 20 cwt gunsand the provision of more guns to complete the London barrage.    The life of these gunswas 1,500 rounds&quot;only, end during the reoentraids no less than 27,300 rounds had beenfired,Je)     The reserves of gun ammunition, in particularshells for the French 75 gun,  of which wehad 28 altogether, 19 being posted in London.It was impossible to economise ammunitionwithout weakening the defenoes.The War Cabinet were further informed that the   enemy were believed to have at present only about 40 Gothas, andit seemed    possible that a certain number of machines ofan inferior type were used in combination with the Gothas,in order to draw fire; that urgent application has beenmade to France for ammunition for our .75 French guns,  and itwas hoped that in the course of a few days fresh supplies would be forthcoming.These measures have been fully described in War Cabinet
(l) Major General Asbxnore described in detail the&quot;defensive measures adopted by the Field..Marshal Commanding-in-Chie^, Home Forces,  to meet hostile air raids on thiscountry-? drawing particular attention to the use of &quot;aprons1;which consisted of three Captive balloons,  connected by long strings of wire.    These &quot;aprons&quot; could not at present be used at a higher altitude than 7,000 ft.    Their moral effect upon the enemy was great, and they forced him to ahigher altitude and thus reduced the zohe which had to be watched by our machines.    He wanted,  if possible, toincrease the number of these screens to 20, putting up one new screen a week.    He anticipated great difficulty inseouring the proper number of trained balloon hands.    the barrage zones were clearly indicated by the incendiaryshells.    The fact that so few raiders managed to penetrateto London showed the efficacy of our gunfire.   V/e wanted,however, more night-flying scout machines and pilots,  ofwhich at present only 6 were available.    The provision of larger night-flying machines, with a good performance wasurgent.With regard to searchlights, General Ashmore saidthat we had at present 7 lights of the most powerful type;these oould only be obtained in France,  and 40 or 50 more were now on order.Sir William Weir pointed out that the provision ofthese additional 20 &quot;aprons&quot; would very seriously interferewith other aeronautical supplies.The Field-Marshal Cominanding-in-Chief,  Home Forces,reminded the War Cabinet that there had been raids on five nights during the past week.    The casua] ties had been veryslight,  the raid on the previous night only causing onedeath in London,  and the damage caused not excessive.    Hethought that an average of 20 enemy planes attacked eachnight.    The raiders came over in relays,    It was impossibleto determine what type of machine was used by the enemy.As regards probable enemy casualties among the raidingmachines, he thought it possible that three or four hadbeen brought down during the week.   Lord French said thatthere were two points which required the immediate attention and decision of the War Cabinet:-(a)    The replacement of the 3-inch 20 cwt gunsand the provision of more guns to complete the London barrage.    The life of these gunswas 1,500 rounds &quot;only,  end during the reoentraids no less than 27,300 rounds had beenfired.i&amp;)     The reserves of gun ammunition, in particularshells for the French 75 gun,  of which wehad 28 altogether, 19 being posted in London.It was impossible to economise ammunitionwithout weakening the defenoes.The War Cabinet were further informed that the   enemy-were believed to have at present only about 40 Gothas, andit seemed    possible that a certain number of machines ofan inferior type were used in combination with the Gothas,in order to draw fire; that urgent application has beenmade to France for ammunition for our .75 French guns,  and itwas hoped that in the course of a few days fresh supplies would be forthcoming.-------. -These measures have been fully described in War Cabinet238 B.
The War Cabinet decided that :*A Committee, conaisting as follows :-General Smutsj (In the Chair)The Minister of Munitions,The Fievident of the Air Board,The Diieotor-General of Military Aeronautics,The Maritex-General of the Ordnance,Major-General AsLmore,Majoi L, Sterr (Secretary)should meet that afternoon at 4 p.m., at, Whitehall Gardens, to enquire into thequestions of replacement of the guns usedfor home defence against air raids, and ofthe supply of ammunition for&quot; the same,,reporting their recommendations to the WarCabinet without delay.Attack.      (2).     The War Cabinet considered the question of the possi-bility of conducting air raids into the enemy&apos;s country;The Press for some iMue past had been working up a strongagitation for energetic lepricalaand there was no duubtthat the, feeling of the public generally was in favour of immediate counter&quot; attacks (      Although the actual damageoaused to life and property was email, the military effectof these constant raids, which were carried out withcomparative impunity, was not inconsiderableTheyseriously affected our cut-put of munitions, for while a raid was in progress nearly 7b&apos; Per cent, of munition workers stopped work, and owj ng mainly to the attitude adopted by the Press, a. feeling of insecurity had beenengendered in the Capital.      In spite of the great strugglegoing on in the air on the Western Front, it appeared that the Germans thought that they could get bettermilitary results out of raids on London than by confiningall their machines to operations on that Front.      If counter-attacks could be successfully organised and carried out,there was good reason to suppose that the moral of munition workers in Germany might be equally affected.The Chief of the Imperial General Staff said that atpresent there were only four squadrons in France whichwere suitable for long-range raids, and these were allurgently required for the present operationsi      50additional suitable machines should be ready in anothersix weeks1 time, when Sir Douglas Hajg would also be ableto spare some as conditions might not then be so favour-   -able for land operations in Flanders *     He questionedhowever, the wisdom of counter-attacks unless they couldbe organised on a scale which would ensure really good results.The Director-General of Military Aeronautics statedthat there should now be 100 long-range bombing machinesin France, and 12 more were due to go out this week.As regards&apos; possible objectives, there .were only three off importance which were within effective range of these machines.
These were Mannheim, the Lorraine Ironworks, andStuttgart, where there were important aircraft factories.The nearest point to our owj Frun!; where an objectiveexisted on German soil was Aix J a Caapjlle, which was 200miles distant.      This was too fac ..&apos;.;v airy mahhxne except the Handley-Page,  which was supp.Li.6d to the ITavy i.:-Consequently the starting-pj.ajc mus-o be some point 6n theFrench Front, and to concentrate jar -machines at thispoint would take ten days.      The night-flying machines whichwere&quot;used oh our Front were not suitable for long-distancebombing.      Our big bombing machines were at present usedfor day reconnaissance and for fighting, and oould only be released for long-distance work at the expense of opera-tions now ih progress.Attehtion was drawn to the moral effect of nightbombing in btsr rest-camps behind the lines,  and also to theeffect upon our troops in France by the newspaper accounts of air raids in England.The President of the Air Board stated that as regardsbombing machines there were at the end of August 100 withthe Expeditionary Force;    40 more were in training, andanother 50 were unallotted or at aircraft acceptance Parks.The monthly output of these machines was over *?0,It was suggested that&apos;counter-attacks might be madeon places like Emden from the sea.     In such attacks thelarge &quot;Americas&quot; could be used, assisted by a number of aeroplanes which would start from the decks of ships.In regard to this, proposal the Fifth Sea Lord pointedout that there were only 10 large &quot;Americas&quot; ready for service on- the East Coast.      These were doing most valuablework in hunting submarines, from which service they couldnot be spared.     He did not anticipate any considerableresults from a raid&apos;on Emden.     The large &quot;America&quot; machinescould only rise to an altitude of 7,000 to 8,000 ft. with bombs, and it was possible that they might all be lost inone attack.     The First Sea Lord concurred.Sir William Weir, in reply to a question, said that by working at high pressure the factories might be able to erect and get ready J?0 B..H.4. machines now packed in boxesfor Russia in four weeks&apos; time, and half that number mightbe ready in three weeks.The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs thought thatthere were two policies laid before the War Cabinet(a) The delivery of a smashing revengeful blow,which would mean the accumulation of machines and most careful -organisation:(b) A series of nightly raids by machines in smalldetachments.It was suggested that these two policies might becarried out together.
The War Cabinet-&apos; agreed that there was no doubt at allas to the desirability &quot;of using&apos; the 50 Russian machines nowin this country for long-range&quot;bombingpurposes, and decided:-That General Smuts&apos; Conriittcc, - which was to assemble the same afternoon (ride previous Minute,)should bo asked to go into the&apos; -whole question of counter-attacks, in especial regard to the.organisation of such attacks;   the formations to boadopted;    the typos to be used;    the most suitabletimes for the attacks to bo carried cut;;  and thenature, of the attacks to be delivered,, both by land;-and .soa;-   submitting at the oarliost&apos; possible datetheir rocoHTiiondations to the Far Cabinet..The Chief of the Imperial G-cneral Staff undertook to see General Trenchrrd oil the following day,in order to find out whether&apos; it would be possiblefor the Field-Marshal contribute. landing-in- Chi of theBritish Forces in France to spare one squadron ofsuitable machines temporarily for the purpose of counter-attacks at long range*The First Sea Lord intimated that he would attend.o the Committee with the Fifth Sea Lord,Etsures for&apos;ouritytheblic.(3.) The Chief Commissioner of Police reported that only 31persons had been killed during the week, and that there&apos;hadbeen only one death&apos; casualty the previous night.     He briefly,described the measures that had been adopted &quot;in order to provide protection end cover for the public.     He deprecated theattitude of the Press, which had resulted in&quot;frightening aCertain portion of the public (notably I!ast Find aliens) intolor-et-nr^, like a panic.     Sir Jiidward Henry stated that hetnougnt that the&quot;casualties caused by street accidents weremanyjfold greater than those caused by enemy bombs and our owngunfire.The War Cabinet decided that: -(a) Sir Edward Henry should be asked to furnish a report of the effect of the recent raids uponthe mral of the people; of London.(b) Sir Edward Henry should bo requested to submit a report, on the measures taken to provide safeshelter in London for those desiring it.The Field-Marshal Commanding Home Forcesundertook to issue a Cormiaiique to the Presson the recent air raiors7 SifElBTward Henryagreeing to furnish him at once with comparative ^figures showing the casualties from streetaccidents and air raids respectively.2, Ihitohall Gardens. S.W.October 1st, 1317.

</content>
</cab>
