<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 23/13/0 images: 124-130</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
SECRET.MINUTES of a Meeting of the War Cabinet held1 at 10 Downing Street,  S. W.  on Tuesday,  October 23rd9 1917 at 12-15 p.m.PRESENT.The Prime Minister (In the Chair).Ehe Rt. Ron.  The Earl curzon of Eedieston, K.G.,  0.0.3.I.,G.C.I.E. ,The Rt.Mon.  O.N. Barnes,M.P.,The Rt. Hon. The Viscount Milner,        The Rt. Hon. Sir. E. Carson,u.C.B.,0.0.M.0. ,A. C. ,  M. P. ,Che Rt. Hon. A. Bonar Law, M.P.,Lieutenant-General The Rt. Ron,J.C.  Smuts, E.C.,THE FOLLOWING WERE ALSO PRESENT:-?The Rt. Hon. A.  J, Balfour,O.M., M.P.,  Secretary of Statefor Foreign Affairs.The Rt. Hon.  The Earl of Derby,K.G.,  G.0.V.O.,C.B.,  Secretaryof State for War.The Rt. Hon. W. -l.ong, M.P.,Secretary of State for theColonies.The Rt. Hon. H.A.L.Fisher,  LL.D.,M.P., President, Board ofEducation.Lieutenant-Colonel Sir M.P.A. Hankey, E.G.B.,    Secretary,oOo- - -
E T.WAR 0A3IHE? a55&amp;aSQftSSL MISUSES of a Meeting held at 10 Downing Street, S.W.,on TUESDAY, OCTOBER 23,  1917, at 12.15 p,m.(1) The War Cabinet had before them a Memorandum by theChief Secretary on the subject of seditious speeches anddrilling in Ireland (C. ?.-2353).    The Prime Minister alsobrought to their notice a letter, dated 17th October, 1917,from Mr. Charles Duncan, id.P. ,  General secretary cf theWorkers1 Union, protesting, under instructions from the La-bour Party, against the present policy of the Authoritiesin Ireland as calculated to prevent any lasting settlementof the Irish question, and expressing the hope that theGovernment will consider the whole question of Irish admin-istration and the advisability of not carrying out the de-cision to remove to England some of the political prisonersat present in Irish prisons.Mr. Duke gave the War Cabinet an outline of the statement which he proposed to make in Parliament on that afternoon.Among the principal points which Mr. Duke proposed to makewere the following:-    What is the real situation in Irelandat a time when the whole of Europe is torn with anguish?Ireland has no real demands or grievances beyond the SinnFein movement.    The Government had used its utmost efforts to promote the success of the Convention; for example, not-withstanding the recent Rebellion,  they had granted an amnesty to prisoners, and had taken steps for the rebuilding of Dublin, although this involved giving facilities in Ire-land which were not granted in Great Britain.    The event3of the summer had shown how this action had been received inIreland.    There had been a continuous propaganda of extremeRepublican doctrines, incitements to rebellion, and the
enrolment, for seditious purposes, of young men, who, ow-fin*- compulsory^sg/ytv %*^L&apos;h*4m. Jvt44&apos;eefJing to the non-application of ftftutp o, a? ijj&quot;&apos;tiliji^/wfre availablein Ireland in large numbers.    He then proposed to readsome of the extracts from de Valera&apos;s speeches showing theincitement to seditious acts.    He proposed to end by stat-ing that this state of affairs could no longer be toler-ated,  that firm action was necessary and would be taken,not to break the Convention, but as a mere matter of police,Mr. Duke pointed out that the logical consequences ofthe above statement, if approved by the War Cabinet, wouldbe the immediate arrest of de Yalera.    It might be nec-essary to follow his arrest by the prosecution, under theDefence of the Realm Act,  of certain other persons, num-bering perhaps from 50 to 100, of whom the police had alist.    The precise action to be te&amp;en against these per-sons, however, was a matter of some difficulty.    They couldbe prosecuted before Magistrates under the Crimes Act andsentenced to imprisonment.    This, however, would lead tobulletins in regard to them in the Irish newspapers twicea day; agitations outside the prisons; hunger strikes, ic.It would be desirable for these reasons to remove them from ireland,  but this also presented difficulties.    They couldonly be removed for internment in England in cases whereassociation with the enemy could be proved to the satisfac-tion of a Board consisting of two Judges.    This had beenpossible in the case of the Sinn feiners removed to Lew sGaol, but might not be possible in the instances now underconsideration.    Another alternative was to try them bycouft-martial,  in which case,  if convicted,  the GeneralOfficer Commanding could order their imprisonment in England.
1 rIn the course of the discussion which-followed.it&quot;waspointed out that the firm action ^ef^s-ed^by kr.  Dukemust not be taken unless the Government were prepared tocarry the policy through to its final conclusion, and thatthis would probably involve very serious difficulties.In this connection dr. Duke pointed out that one w^s^^tt^jj-&quot; ---raigh^-bV-a/PrilcXama tioh&quot;&apos;of &quot;g^Tf ovisional ^Government.    Aview was expressed that, the Irish question was so smalla matter in relation to the vast problems with which theGovernment was confronted, when the situation was viewedas a whole,  that it might be undesirable to pay too much attention to it, particularly if it would involve thiscountry in serious difficulties.    Since there was no reas-on to suppose that there was&apos;any real grievance at the back of the Sinn Fein movement it might be better to ig-nore the seditious tendencies and to carry on steadilywith sound administration.    To this it was replied thatthis had teen the policy of the Government up to the pres-ent time.    So long as de Valera and others had confinedtheir speeches to mere provocation and wild talk there hadbeen no interference.    The speeches quoted in the chief secretary&apos;s memorandum, however,  contained actual incite-ment to seditious and rebellious acts and co\rld no longer be ignored or good government of Ireland would become impossible.    Further,  the Poli/ce had reported that gel^fig-nite had been stolen and arms raided, and they were anx-ious as to the situation.    Stress was laid on the vitalimportance of supporting the Royal Irish Constabulary, whoare one of the most important instruments in the governmentof Ireland.    At present their position was one of greatdifficulty, as they were boycotted and unpopular.    very high tributes were paid to the value of the Royal Irish
Constabulary, and it v;as stated that their-popularity de-ponded, largely^-xrpon-lxbeJjr&quot;beijag.-43a^xked up by the Govem-men t and thus enabled to carry out their work efficiently.The question was discussed as to the effect of a drasticpolicy in. the United States of America.    Attention was called to a recent dispatch from the British ambassador at Washington, reporting that certain Irish Societies inAmerica had announced themselves as favourable to Germany,and suggesting that they were in collusion with the enemyfor the establishment of submarine bases in. Ireland.    Itwas suggested that there was some connection between theseIrish Societies and the present movement in Ireland.    Itwas agreed that the Department of Information ought to telegraph Mr.  Duke1s speech to the United States of America,including, more particularly, the extracts from de Valora1sspeeches.    The suggestion was also made that a comnunica-tion might, with advantage, be made to Mr.  Gompers,  theAmerican Labour Leader.It was generally agreed that de Valera should be arreot-edj but the date of the arrest was left to Mr.  Duke,  thesuggestion being made that he might prefer to postpone it until after the Debate in Parliament,  in order to hare thesupport of the House of Commons behind him.    The questionof taking action against the other persons mentioned bythe Chief Secretary was also left to Mr. Duke.    Stress,however, was laid on the importance of publicity being given in this country to any prosecutions that might be .carried out.    In this connection Mr.  Duke pointed out  thatthe trials which take place In Ireland would, in the ord-\inary course of events,  only be reported in the extremeSinn Fein Press and in an inaccurate and distorted manner:.It was generally agreed that whatever action was taken     i must be under existing legislation, and that it would not ;
he practicable to ask Parliament for&apos;  reah po-wbm .The Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs point^d outthat the Sinn Fein movement, though based on no solidfoundation, gained a fictitious and sentimental strengthfrom the movement which was spreading rapidly over theworld in favour of nationality.The War Cabinet dooidod:-fi) To approve the general lines of Mr. JDuko&apos; s pro-posed statement, which should, he followed by im-mediate action:fii) To approve the Chief secretary proposal to arrest de Valera, and to support the prosecution,if Mr. Duke deemed necessary, of other personsreferred to in his statement:If (iij.)    That the Department of Information should tele-graph the subst nee of Mr. Duke&apos;a speech, immed-fl lately after it had been delivered,to the UnitedStates of America, and particularly the extracts from de Yalera&apos;s speeehos.    The Secretary was in-structed to notify Mr.  John Buchan forthwith.iL MIL-      (2) With reference to ii&amp;T Cabinet 248 * tho secretarypIICY.of State for War stated that he wished to consult tho WarCabinet in regard to the Memoranda drawn up by Field. MarshalLord French and Lieutenant-General Sir Henry Wilson at therequest of the War Cabinet.   (War Cabinet 247&quot;13, Minute 1).Lord Derby reminded the Viiar Cabinet that the prime minister had agreed that Lord French and Sir Henry &apos;.wilson . shouldmake the Reports to Sir William Robertson and discuss thematter thoroughly with him before a full conference washeld.    Under instructions from the Prime Minister the Sec-re tary had handed the Reports, in the first instance,  tohim, as Head of the War Office.    He felt in some doubt,however, as to the advisability of communicating the reports in their present form to General Robertson.    The difficultyarose from the fact that the first part of Lord French&apos;sReport animadverted upon General Robertson and Sir Douglas
Haig.    To communicate the Kepprts to these Officers he felt might involve friction, replies, rejoinders,  and delay,    On the whole he inclined to the view that itwould ho bettor to ash Lore. French and Sir Henry WilsonUto sum up their recommendations in a more concise formand to pass these on to the Chief cf the Imperial OenerStaff for his remarks.The War Cabinet decreed that;-Before they could advise the Secretary of Statefor bar as to the action to be taken, they mustthemselves see herd French&quot;a and Sir henry Wil-scn&apos;s honorte. The secretary was instructed to circulate copies of both Reports to idenibers ofthe Far Cabinet.Whitehall Cardans, S.W.,October 23,  1917.

</content>
</cab>
