<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/152/0 images: 15-21</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
HIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cp(70)53 COPY NO24 September 1970CABINETNATIONALISED INDUSTRIES&apos; INVESTMENTSACCOUNTING CONVENTIONSNote by the Secretary of the CabinetBy direction of the Prime Minister, and in the absence of theChief Secretary, Treasury, who is abroad, I am circulating a note by treasury officials in pursuance of the cabinet&apos;s remit to the chief secretary (CM(70) 17th Conclusions, Minute 2,   Conclusion 5) to give further consideration to the convention whereby investment expenditureon the nationalised industries which was now financed from public fundswas regarded as public expenditure.    The note may be relevant to theCabinet^ forthcoming discussions on the public expenditure programme and, in particular, to the memorandum by the Minister of Technology(CP(70) 52).Signed BURKE trend cabinet Office SWl23 September 1970
(confidential)NATIONALISED industries EJVE8SKBNT: ACCOUNTINGCONVENTIONSNote by officials the basis of the conventionsThe conventions discussed in this note are thosewhich have been adopted for presenting to Ministers,to Parliament and to the public out turns and estimates of public sector expenditure, particularly for thepurpose of considering public sector policies inrelation to each other and to management of the economy generally.2.    The object of the conventions is to display inthe most convenient and simple way the effect ofpublic sector operations on real resources.   Whetherpresent conventions should be changed should there-fore turn on the answer to the question whether thechange would enhance or obscure understanding of the impact on the economy of these operations - and inparticular, at the present time, of their implications for the Government&apos;s tax reduction programme. resent Praetiee3.    As regards the nationalised industries, thepresent practice is to show as public expendituretheir investment and other capital expenditure (netof sales of assets).   Their trading surpluses are shown alongside other public sector receipts as partof transfers,taxation, etc.   The difference betweenthe two - the amount by which the industries&apos; investmenti &apos;(confidential)
(confidential)is not financed from internally generated funds -represents the industries borrowing requirement,which forms part of the borrowing requirement ofthe public sector as a whole.   The industries maymeet this requirement by borrowing directly from thebanks9 or indirectly through the medium of theNational Loans Fund.   This choice will affect the size of the central government&apos;s borrowing require-men t? but not that of the public sector overall.h*    This treatment follows the familiar and published National Income accounting conventions.5*    This particular convention has been looked at by previous Governments on several occasions.   the implications of any departure from it would thereforebe likely to be explored in public debate.,frPfflicfl14on 9f *fre SfiBIgSSlSBl  g current,proposals.    There are currently under consideration fourmain g*oups of proposals affecting the nationalised industries (apart from examination of the case foran increase- lai the test discount rate, which is not relevant to this note):-*r    reducing the industries&apos; capital expenditure the effect of these proposals would appear asreductions both in public expenditure, and(after taking account of any adverse effect onthe industries&apos; gross trading surpuses fromloss of net revenue from the intended investment)z(confidential)
In the public sector&apos;s borrowing requirement.They would drectly reduce the overall demand on resources and could therefore be of great value In opening up scope for tax reductions *b. gflJJiBg 9^ to Sfeg Prmt? sector(peripheral) sectorsThe receipts from sale and the relief frompreviously planned capital expenditure in thesesectors would appear as reductions in public expenditure, and in the public sector&apos;s b or row-lag requirement, as in the case of (a).   Butthe operations would presumably continue asfree commercial enterprises run for profit.The transaction would permit tax reductions onlyto any extent that it reduced demand on resourceseg by increased efficiency, or by divertingprivate funds from other investment   outsidethe gilt edged market or from consumption.c. raising nationalised Industries&apos; pricesThebo proposals generally would have the effectof increasing public sector receipts, ratherthan reducing public expenditure (the exceptionis where increased prices help to reduce oreliminate an operating loss attracting aGovernment subsidy); and they would reduce thepublic sector borrowing requirement.   In somecases they would have the effect of directlyreducing consumers&apos; disposable incomes and thus(confidential) -
overall demand on resources.   These proposals are therefore of relatively high value for the tax reduction programme.d.    compelling the Industries to borrow a proportion of their capital direct from themarket %. rather than from the Govfiynmg/ptThese proposals would not reduce either public expenditure or the public sector&apos;s borrowing requirement.   Hhey would effect a switch of financing away from the Exchequer within the overall borrowing requirement, but they wouldhave no effect on real resources and wouldnot therefore contribute to the tax reductionprogramme.7*    The crux of the argument at (d) above is that so long as the Government exercises a general controlover both the investment and the pricing policies of the industries, the industries will be unable to attract^genuine: new risk capital.   They will haveto borrow at fixed interest with (generally explicit)Government guarantee.   Therefore, whether theyborrow in the market generally, or directly from sources such as insurance companies, they are com-competing for funds of the kind that would otherwise have been invested in Government securities.   this note is not concerned with the technical argumentsabout the management of the gilt-edged market - onthe basis of whicte the previous Conservative adminis-tration in 1956 decided to give the. industries
(confidential)access to what is now the National Loans Fund.But there is no evidence that the floating of(say) a  50 million Government guaranteed loan bythe British Steel Corporation would call forth newsavings; and the question whether, within the giltedged market, a particular security carries the nameof Her Majesty&apos;s Government   or the British steel corporation   is not relevant for the purpose of managing demand on real resources.Treasury ChambersGreat George Street, SW123 September 1970S(confidential)


</content>
</cab>
