<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/152/0 images: 22-35</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S government cp(70) 54 COPY NO24 September 1970CABINETPUBLIC EXPENDITURE: HEALTH, V/EJLFARE and social SECURITYMemorandum by the Secretary of State for Social Services51. At the Cabinet meeting on 14 September (CM(70) 16th Conclusions)Ministers were invited to circulate by 23 September any memoranda thatthey wished to submit on specific reductions or increases in expenditureon which they had not reached agreement with the Chief Secretary.2. The savings I have proposed amount to about  900 million (GreatBritain) over the four years as follows:1971-72   1972-73   1973-74   1974-75Social Security 83 170 192 216Health and welfare 61__64_64_67144 234 256 283Total  917 million have made it clear to my colleagues that I do not regard this aspolitically tolerable or consistent with the commitments in our election manifesto, unless they are in part offset over the field of my responsibilityby the concurrent improvements which are set out in the Appendix to this paper.3,        The strategy which I propose is to move to greater selectivity andto redeploy existing expenditure.    On the health side higher charges, with existing exemptions, would be accompanied by improvements in the quality and extent of the health and welfare services generally.    On the social security side some of the savings from limited general uprating would beused for selective help to those in greatest need, such as the chronic sick and the handicapped, the disabled and the fatherless.4.        In both health, welfare and social security I piopose an increasingemphasis on local and community services,,
5S To achieve all this the extra expenditure for which I am asking is -Family income supplementFamily allowances*  million1971-72   1972-73   1973-74 1974-754 9 9 960 60 90/Before allowing for any taxcl&amp;wback - see^ par a graph 18of the Appendix/Supplementary benefit interimupratings - 20 20 20Health and welfare (England)A 34_77____135;_202.38_166 224_321Total  749 million*The figures represent the cost of merely maintaining the real value of family allowances,/These figures would be reduced to the extent that resources were diverted from the allocation for the 1971 uprating and associated improvements andto the extent that it was possible to collect more of the hospital costs of treating car accident victims (see paragraph 15 of the Appendk).6,        As a result of what I propose we shall have transformed andreinvigorated the health and welfare services and we shall hava broughtsubstantial relief to whole groups - such as the isolated elderly, the poorand hard-pressed families, the one-parent households, the chronic sick and the mentally and physically disabled - who are in greatest need.7,        I seek my colleagues approval for the proposals outlined in theattached Appendix.K department of Health and Social Security SE123 September 1970
APPENDIX TO MEMORANDUM    BY SECRETARY OF STATE FOR SOCIALSERVICESHEALTH AND WELFARE1.      Our Election Manifesto said  that resources going  into the health Service were  inadequate,   that  there were  too many outdatedhospitals,  too many old people not  getting  the  care  they need intheir own homes,   too many mentally  ill people either  inovercrowded hospital  wards or getting  insufficient  care  throughlocal  community  services and too many of  those working in the health Service lacking a decent  career  structure.2.      What we  said in the Manifesto was not an exaggeration.Too little has been spent on these  services  for  too  long.      Asa results  almost  all   the community services   (nursing,   social work,day centres,  hostels and homes)   are under-provided s.nd under-staffed and in many areas some are almost non-existent.Hospital buildings are not only outdated but  under-equipped andinadequately maintained.      Standards of  service  in different parts of  the country are  still markedly unequal.      Nurserecruitment  is dropping.      The doctors are restive because  theylack the resources  to give  their patients  the most moderntreatment.      Standards  in psychiatric and geriatric hospitals arescandalously low,3.      In my view there  should be substantial  additional  expenditureon the health and welfare service as  soon as possible.       I  shallexplain below why I believe  that,  for England alone,  this  shouldbe about   34 million  in 1971/72,   77 million in 1972/73, 135 million in 1973/74 and  202 million in 1974/75,      In themiddle term it may be possible  to find  some alternative  sources of  finance for  the Health Service,  other  than the  increased charges already proposed, which will make this objective easier to reach.      The Chief Secretary and  I  have agreed to set up an inter-departmental Working Party to examine possibleal ternat ives.3.
4. Explanations of the main headings under which I believe that additional money  is required are as  follows.LOCAL AUTHORITY HEALTH AND WELFARE services.      Extensive development of  the community service;;  is  thefirst  essential,   both in their own right   for  the effective care of  the sick,   the handicapped and  the elderly,   and as acomplement   to  the reshaping of the hospital  services.    more people will need  to be looked after  in local  authority hostelsand at home,   supported both by the  local  health and practitionerservices and by  the personal  social  services.    The creation of a unified health service and unified personal  social  services will help to bring this about.    But the  change in emphasis will  also require substantial  further expenditure  in order  to  improve thecommunity services.    At  present  these  services are a very longway from meeting present needs and they have no spare capacity to support policies  for early discharge  from hospital  or (evenmore  important)  to postpone or prevent  admission to hospital or residential  care.    More community nurses,  and social workers,more home helps,  more meals on wheels,  more day centres of allkinds,  more old people&apos;s homes and  the rehousing of about 20,000old people who are still   in old workhouses,  more residentialhostels  for the mentally handicapped,  more  training centres  for adults and more health centres are all  urgently needed.6.      The minimum extra capital  that  is needed to enable  the localauthority health and welfare services  to move towards a desirable  standard  is  5 million in 1971/72,    14 million in1972/73,, 17 million in 1973/74 and  22 million  in 1974/75.    Theminimum extra revenue is  5 million in 1971/72,    11 million in1972/73,    13 million in 1973/74 and  15 million in 1974/75.Provision of  this extra money would help  in the gradual processof shifting the emphasis of care away from hospital and into thecommuni ty.4.
7.       I believe  it  is vital  to our strategy  to make sure  that local authorities do spend  this  extra money on the community services.    That  is why I  am opposed to the  suggested reductionin relevant expenditure of  20 million because experience showsthat  in a general  squeeze  the health and welfare services  sufferdisproportionally to most others.    Even if  there were no reduction in relevant expenditure  I do not  think  the extra money-will be spent   in 1971/72,   and probably not   in later years either,unless there  is an early announcement of the Government1sintention that more money should be available  from the Exchequerspecifically for these services.HOSPITAL BUILDING PROGRAMME8.      At present more than half of our hospital beds housepsychiatric and geriatric patients.    Many of  these hospitalsare sited in rural areas  remote from the communities  from whichthey draw their patients;  many of  them are  far  from the districthospital,  and almost all  are far too large,   are old and obsoleteand are difficult  to staff.    For mental   illness and geriatricsthe solution is  to replace old  isolated hospitals by activetreatment units based in general  hospitals.    For  the mentally handicapped it  is  to provide a new pattern of  service with amuch larger role  for  local  residential  and other  community services.     In addition there  is an urgent need to upgradeolder hospitals which despite  their defects will  have  to be kept in service  for many years  to come.    The  time has now gone whensociety will  tolerate having 50 or more patients  herded together in a ward with no space between the beds even for  lockers.I5
9.      Additional  funds of   10 million in 1971/72,   20 million in 1972/73,  30 million in 1973/74 and  40 million in 1974/75are needed to make any substantial  impact on providing the new and improved services required for these neglected areas.10.      It would not be possible to find the money for this by reducing the programme for the construction and improvement of district  general hospitals and community hospitals.    It  is  inthese hospitals  that most  of  the  improved services  for psychiatricand geriatric patients need to be located.    At present,  themajority of  general hospital beds  are in old buildings,   in mostof which there are simply not  the conditions  to provide adequatelaboratories, X-ray departments, operating theatres and all theother parts of  the service core which a modern hospital needs  inorder to provide an acceptable service.    Moreover with movements of population many of  the  existing hospitals are in the wrongplaces.    If obsolescence is  to be overcome,  the service brought up to date and gaps filled,   the programme must continue  in anascending growth line rather than be levelled off from 1972/73 onwardsas I understand  is  envisaged by  the Treasury.    This would  involveincreases  of about   5 million in 1972/73,  12 million in 1973/74and  22. million in 1974/75.11.     To meet  the needs expressed in paragraphs 8-10 the hospital building programme must be  increased by  10 million in 1971/72, 25 million in 1972/73, 42 million in 1973/74 and  62 million in 1974/75.iHOSPITAL REVENUE EXPENDITURE12.      Hospital  revenue expenditure is  at present planned  to growat 3j per cent a year.    This  is  totally inadequate to enable hospitals6
to provide a modern service.    It does not  enable us to bring into use new and rebuilt hospitals,  to keep pace with the advance of medicine and  the growing population to provide an acceptable standard of service and to cut  the waiting lists.Improvements  in staffing,  feeding,  clothing,  equipment,  etc  inpsychiatric and geriatric hospitals are urgently needed:     theDepartment has provided  for some  improvements by cutting otherurgently needed expenditure but more needs  to be  spent  to make substantial  impact on the problem.    The working and  living conditions  and  the staffing standards  for nurses  in all  types of hospital need to be improved.13.     For all  these reasons hospital revenue expenditure should grow at  least double the present rate.    An immediatejump from 3^ per cent might possibly be difficult  to managebecause of  the time taken to recruit more staff and 1  therefore propose a modest  increase of  12 million in 1971/72 and thereafter  that  the rate of  increase  should be 6 per cent  in1972/73 and 7 per cent a year in 1973/74 and 1974/75,7
FAMILY PLANNING14.    I believe that more must be done to encourage  family-planning and,   in particular,  that  there should be a special  driveto reach those who have without particular  intention  thelargest families and are often both the poorest and the leastlikely to  seek advice.      Family planning on a domiciliary basis in the poor areas  could reduce  the number of  children destined,in many cases,   to go  into  care, delinquency, probation and  crimeandj  in due course,  to repeat as parents the process through their own children.      The gross; cost, not  limited  to  thespecially needy families,  is tentatively estimated to be at least 2 million in the first year rising to  6 million in 1974/75,with offsetting reductions  soon emerging.SUMMARY15. In summary, my bid for additional money for the health and welfare services  in England is as follows:-  million	1971/72	1972/73	1973/74	1974/75LA Capital	5	14	17	22LA Revenue	5	11	13	15Hospital  Capital	10	25	42	62Hospital Revenue	12	23	58	97Family Planning	2	&apos;           4	5	6	34	77	135	202To the extent  that resources could be diverted from theallocation requested    for  the  1971 uprating and associatedimprovements  (see paragraph 23)   the  calls on the health and welfare block wemld be correspondingly reduced.      For my part II , ^I hope also to be able to collect about  10 million a year  (GreatBritain)   for the hospital  costs of treating car accident victimsif  that were allowed to be used to finance part of  the additional expenditure  I  am proposing.      But  this presents difficulties - by no means only for my Department  - and I  cannot yet be certainthat  this  saving will materialise,,8.
FAMILiY POVERTY16.      In the Manifesto we said that we would tackle the problemof family poverty.    I am about  to circulate a paper to social Services Committee outlining a family income supplementscheme (FIS)  for allowances to be paid on an income test  tothe poorest families with children,  in effect  those livingbelow the supplementary benefit  level.    This  is a very modestscheme, amounting  to not much more than first aid,.    Theproposals would cost when in full operation something between 8 million and  10 million a year.    I hope to find more than half of this,  from further small savings over and above thosein the main savings operation.17,     The FIS scheme was first conceived as a means of reducingchild poverty by improving the position of  the poorest families.But in fixing the proposed level of benefit I have also had inmind the necessity of giving them and the next poorest  group -the hard pressed families a little above the supplementary benefit  level  - some protection against  the effect of  the economy measures whether by improving and extending the FISscheme or by other means.    The pressure on these families willcontinue to grow particularly as subsidies are phased out overthe next few years.    We shall have to be ready therefore with further help for them.18.     This raises a general question.    In the social securityprogramme,: family allowances are assumed to remain fixed  in money terms throughout  the period,  this means  that   in real   terms  they wilon present assumptions, have declined in value by more than a quarter by 1974-75.    I am quite sure this  is unacceptable andthat  indeed we shall be under great pressure  to make  some  real9
improvement.      Some overall   increase  in expenditure on family-allowances themselves during the period is  therefore quiteinescapable.      The net  cost would depend on what  concurrentalterations  if any were made  in the  tax system.    The public expenditure  cost  of merely restoring  the value of  the allowance in April  1972 and 1974 would be  something  like  60 million ayear rising to  90 million a year.      If at  the same time some adjustment was made  in the  tax allowance as  in 1968,  the net   cost would be quite  small.    Any  increases  in family allowances would reduce  the need for other measures against  family poverty.      a paper on the whole question of  family poverty is going soon tothe Social Services Committee.EXTRA EXPENDITURE IN FRAMEWORK OF UPRATINGS19.     At present  the social  security programme envisagesupratings of  social  security benefits   in 1971 and  1973  in line with the movement of earnings.    I accept  that in the present economic situation this would be too ambitious.    I  have offered the Chief Secretary very large savings  in this field,  though not as much as  the Chief Secretary proposes.    The position canbe summarised in round figures as follows:-UPRATINGS    SAVINGS  million at.-,   1970 Survey &quot;pricesSavings  from ChiefSecretary1s proposalfor prices onlyupratings (compared with earnings upratings)Savings offered by secretary of State  (after allowing for proposeduprating allocations -see below)11971-72125651972-732901501973-743 851974-7549017019060140:1530010
20.     The more severe the cuts in our uprating plans,  themore it becomes necessary to demonstrate a constructiveapproach by spending something extra on selected vulnerablegroups.    Our first two upratings in 1971 and  1973, will be compared with what has been done in the recent past.    Thefigures for the last three upratings are set out below:-PERCENTAGE INCREASES						pDate of	Pens ions		Pri ces		Earnings	uprating	S ince May  &quot;63	Since previous uprat ing	Since May &apos;63	Since previous uprat ing	Si nee May  &apos;63	Since previous uprat inglarch 1965	18.3	18.3	5.8	5.8	17.1	17.1fctober 1967	33.1	12.5	15.2	8.9	32.4	13.1lovember 1969	47.9	11.1	28.5	11.5	53.7	17e411
21.      The upratings of  1965 and  1967  taken  together put uppensions by about the movement   in earnings   (very slightly more).The three upratings  including  that  of   1969,   though somewhat less  than earnings,  were much more  than prices.    We cannot matchthis  if  social  security benefits are  to contribute to  savings.22.      We should  therefore,   I   suggest,   think of  a modest upratingin 1971 not very much above prices,  followed by a becter one in1973 not  too much below earnings.    But at  the  same time weshould give substantially improved help  to  selected groups in particular need,  for  instance  the chronic  sick,  the disabledand one-parent households  (we hope  that  the Finer Committeeon one-parent  families will come up with some proposals  to ease  their  life before long)  and  improve the  community services available  to pensioners and  the handicapped.     In thisway we can improve  the  life of  selected groups at  a much lowercost  than would be  involved in maintaining the rate ofimprovement  in the real purchasing power  of   the  standard  social security benefits which was set by  the previous Government.23.      Against  this background  I have proposed  to  the chief secretary that we  should  set aside  140 million for  the 1971uprating and associated  improvements  (less  than half  of whatwould be necessary to give an uprating in line with earnings).What  I  have  in mind -  though final decisions will be  takennext  spring -  is  that  a real  improvement  of  3s a week in termsof  1970 prices  (over and above compensation for  the movementin prices) might be politically acceptable,  taking about 90 million.    The balance of  50 million should be  spent  onselective  improvements  for vulnerable groups -  such as the chronic  sick and  the disabled and on measures,  other  thanincreases  in cash benefits,  which will help  the elderly andthe handicapped.24.    ^or  the  1973 uprating I am proposing  that we should  set aside  150 million a year  (rather more than three quarters of  the amount needed for an uprating  in line with earnings).Here again it  seems  to me that  a part  of   this might  with advantage to our general strategy be diverted away from12CONFIDENTIAL
improving  the  standard rate of benefit  to  some  further selectiveimprovements, but  this can be  settled nearer the time.      I  also have  in mind that out of  the allocations  for upratings we may-need to spend  something  in  introducing our national   insurancereforms and perhaps something on improving  the  system ofincrements and  the earnings rule  (both of which were mentionedin our Manifesto).25.    These reallocations of expenditure in connection with the1971  and  1973 uprating are already allowed for  in my proposalsfor savings set out  in CP(70)39.    However  if  the upratingallocations for  1971 and 1973 were cut  so low as not  to be capable of  accommodating the kind of  selective  improvementsI have outlined,   they would  then stand  in their own right asbids  for extra expenditure.EXTRA EXPENDITURE ON SUPPLEMENTARY BENEFIT INTERIM UPRATINGS26.      There is another point about upratings.    I  find  that  thesocial  security programme makes no allowance for upratings  insupplementary benefit  in 1972 and 1974 (ie between the generaltwo yearly upratings).    These  interim supplementary benefitupratings have been customary for  some years and on presentforecasts of price movements  I do not  see how we  can avoid them.The cost would be of   the order of  20 million a year extra from1972-73 onwards.i!13


</content>
</cab>
