<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/152/0 images: 85-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY *S government cp(70) 61 COPY NO       C *25 September 1970CABINETTHE STATE OF AGRICULTUREMemorandum by the. Secretary of State for Scotland,The Secretary of State for Wales, the Minister ofAgriculture, Fisheries and Food and the Minister ofState, Home office in this paper we outline developments in agriculture since the1970 Price Review, identify problems that are arising and propose actionto meet them.    The Lord President has circulated a memorandum oninterim moves towards the implementation of our new policy foragricultural support and we do not deal with that subject here.DEVELOPMENTS SINCE THE 1970 REVIEW2*     Production]   The agricultural census taken in June showed mat an encouraging upturn was in prospect in production of pigs? that beef production continued to expand in a reasonably satisfactory manner; thatthe dairy herd was showing signs of marginal expansion; that the declinein sheep continued; and that production of poultry meat and eggs wasexpanding in line with the requirements of the market.    On the arableside there had been a small recovery in the cereal acreage after the set-back of two years ago, but the level was still well below that of two yearsago.    The wheat acreage had increased but there was an almostcorresponding reduction in that of barley.     Sugar beet was at the levelallocated for home production, and the acreage under potatoes wasadequate to meet fully the domestic demand given normal yields.    in short, production on the livestock side was not unsatisfactory, except forsheep and perhaps dairy cattle, but expansion was lagging seriously in the cereals sector.3U     Although harvest yields of wheat have been rather higher thanthe recent average, this year&apos;s barley crop, because of the extremely dryweather in the lafra spring and early summer, has been very disappointing.In some areas yields have been extremely poor, lower than for twenty years.     As a result, although the total cereals acreage is marginallyhigher than last year, it is estimated that the total production of allcereals will be jj million tons lower.    The yield of hay and other foddercrops is also low.
4.     Cosstsj    Farm costs have been rising substantially since the 1970Review.    Any estimates at this time are bound to include somespeculative elements for cost increases likely to occur between now andthe 1971 Review.    Our best assessment is that at the next Annual Reviewwe may be faced with a net increase in costs of the broad order of 105 million in a full year for guaranteed products and a figure of some 140 million for all products^    Farmers will have to bear cost increases of some  75 million during the current guarantee year., that is before they could be off set by increases in the guaranteed prices after the 1971Annual Review.    The main increases are  45 million for feedingsfcuffsand  10 million for machinery.5.     The general increase of costs reflects the present inflationarysituation.    There is however one exceptional major cost - feedingstuffs.In the last few weeks, the price of grain has increased sharply andsubstantially, partly due to lower production at home but mainly to the expectation of markedly lower yields abroad - the United States maizecrop is likely to be cut back through disease.    Import prices of the mainfeed grains now stand at - barley  30. 10. 0 per ton, feed wheat 30. 15. 0. maize  33. 0, 0.    The corresponding figures a year ago were 20,  23 and  25 per ton.    This will result in a big increase in theimport bill.    With protein prices also higher and still rising compoundanimal feed is costing around 8 per cent more than a year ago and further increases are expected,6.     Investment;   Under the stimulus of the incentives given at the review, investment in fixed equipment under the various schemesadministered by the Agricultural Departments has in the five monthsApril-August shown seme signs of an increase compared with the sameperiod last year.    The value of investment approved for grant shows a6 per cent increase and the number of new applications is up by about a quarter.7.     Exchegue^ej^ejn^iture;   Market prices this year have been firm,and a good deal more so than Departments expected when the FinancialEstimates were submitted some mcsr&amp;hs ago.    The prospects are thatfirm markets will persist for the rest of this financial year and the bestappraisal that can be made is that prices for meats will continuereasonably firm next year and for cereals will be below current levelsbut still appreciably higher than before the recent rise.    At present nodeficiency payments are necessary for pigs and payments on cattle havebeen relatively small.    More recently, there has been the steep rise ingrain prices to which we have already referred.    It is more than likely that the market price for barley over the year will be at or just abovethe guaranteed price so that no deficiency payments will be needed.    but even if there is a small deficiency payment taking the year as a whole itwill be so amall that problems will arise in relation to both the storageincentive arrangements announced last May and the financing of theHome Grown Cereals Authority Forward Contract Bonus Scheme.
8.     There is expected to be a substantial reduction in the cost of deficiency payments this year.    On prerent assessments, there will be areduction of some  75 million net in the Exchequer commitments for1970-71, as shown in the publiehd Estimates adjusted on account of the1970 Annual Review award.    The full year effect of this award will spillover into 1971-72 (largely on cereals) but will still be much lower thanestimated at the time of the Review,    Details of these are set out inAppendix A, together with explanatory notes concerning the Exchequercommitments in relation to the Public Expenditure Survey.PROBLEMS FACING THE industry.     The steep and quite exceptional increase in costs is alreadymaking inroads into the cash resources of farmers.    The effect of the deficiency payments system is that higher market prices leave farmers&apos;return unaltered - unless prices rise to exceptionally high limits - whilemarkedly reducing the call on public funds.    Thus producers are little or no better off as a result of the market price increases.    Indeed, ingross income terms many will be worse off.    The poor barley yields,coupled with adverse planting conditions in the spring, have reducedproduction by over 1 million tons compared with last year and this represents a cash loss to growers of some  27 million.    At the sametime increased grain prices have meant that the livestock producers are faced with a greatly increased feed bill while getting the same return fortheir product.10.     The industry is thus in a serious position - probably withoutprecedent.    There is grave danger of a fall of confidence and with it a fall of production! not so much immediatsly but a year or two ahead.This will be fatal to the prospects of agricultural expansion which isessential if we are to achieve the aims of our policy and if agriculture ieto play its proper part in decreasing our dependence on imports.    our import bill for food and feed which could be grown in this country remainsvery large and in fact constitutes about one-eighth of all our imports.    Ifthe price of our entry into the e.c. is to be kept within reasonable limits and we are to avoid serious balance of payments difficulties, we must goin with our agriculture in a strong and confident position and on an expanding trend.    We cannot therefore hope to carry out our policy forthe economy as a whole if our agricultural industry is depressed.   Toprovide some relief now is to make an investment which will facilitate the implementation of our policies over the next five years whether we enter the e.c. or whether we modify our system of support so that it no longeroperates through deficiency payments.11,     To do this would not require any supplementary financial provision; it could be done by making use of some of the savings thatwould otherwise occur because of the lower support bill in the current financial year as a result of higher market prices,3
12.     Our judgment of the situation is that there is a real danger thatexpansion in the livestock sector will now be checked while there will becontinued stagnation in the arable sector.    We cannot let matters simplytake their course until the 1971 Annual Review.    If we were to do so, a situation would develop by then which it would be much more costly torectify.    It would take a lot of time and money to get the livestock sectormoving again.    There could be a down-turn this winter which it would be too late to reverse next March.     As regards arable production, theautumn so far has been favourable5 we now need to encourage substantialsowings of winter grain as well as an increase in spring plantings.    Wecan get worthwhile results by early action.    The 1971 Annual Review willbe too late.ACTION PROPOSED13.    We accordingly propose that certain guaranteed prices should beincreased at once for 1970-71 and that increases should be announced -probably by means of a White Paper - at the beginning of October,    the increases we propose can be met from within the savings on deficiency round and still leave a saving to the Exchequer.14.     These increases can be made without the need to hold a special review.    The criteria for a Special Review, which were agreed with the farmers&apos; Unions in 1956 and involve inter alia the effect of a particularcost change on guaranteed products being more than 4 per cent of thetotal value of the guarantees, have not yet been satisfied.    In any event we would not regard the Special Review procedures as appropriate inpresent circuxnetasascss.    Account could only be taken cf a single cost increase of sufficient magnitude (eg possibly for feed) and any recoupmentwould have to be spread uniformly over commodities in accordance withthe incidence of the cost increase, which would mean recouping the cost increases relating to production of eggs as well as other livestock products.    Moreover it would not be in our interest should we join the eec to have any formal arrangements for Special Reviews and we wouldnot want to revive the concept cf Special Reviews now,15.    We consider below the position of the various commodities and give our detailed proposals.BEEF AND MILK16.    Beef producers are faced with the increase of feed costs andwithout an increase in their return will be forced to check their develop-ment programmes.    They will be less able to finance the finishing of as many cattle for beef as they intended, alternatively, lower net returnsfrom fattening cattle may be passed back to the store rearer by forcingdown the price of calves.    There is a danger that calves will beslaughtered instead of being reared; and reareys of calves, whether fromthe beef or the dairy herd, may have to retrench.    Our beef productionpotential would then suffer and expansion would be severely set bac k.Returns from milk production will similarly fall as a result of feed coGtincreases.    Cows will be culled prematurely to cut expenses and raisecash.    The dairy herd can be expected to decline and future production ofboth milk and beef will consequently fall.   .4
17.     We propose to raise the guaranteed price of fat cattle by 10s. percwt.    This represents an increase in the potential Exchequer liability for deficiency payments of   13 million in a full yoar.    This price increase would be implemented by increasing the scale of weeklystandard prices for the remainder of 1970-71 by about 21s. 6d, per cwt.18.    For milk we propose to raise the guaranteed price by 2^d per gallon, increasing the effective return to producers by about 1. 8d per gallon.    At the present level of support the milk fund will be in balancethis year and the present retail price for milk will bring in substantially more than is needed next year.    The effect of the proposed increase would be a deficit at the end of the current financial year of about 21 million, but this could be eliminated and the full cost of continuingthis level of support met by increasing the retail price cf milk by half anew penny per pint in January 1972.    (This timing takes account offoreseen increases in distribution costs up to September 1971 only.Further distribution cost increases might mean advancing the date of theprice increase by one or two months.)   Alternatively the deficit could bereduced by an earlier increase in the retail price.PIGS19.     The guaranteed price for pigs is automatically adjusted as theprice of feed changes.    The higher cost of feed is in fact largely beingcarried by the Exchequer and the pig producers are thus in a favourable position compared with other livestock producers.20.     There is no reason to suppose the present expansion will not continue and we propose no increase in the basic guaranteed price.,Under the guarantee arrangements, however, there is provisionautomatically to reduce the guaranteed price if pig numbers start to riseand to increase it if they fall: the increase in production how forecastwill lead to an automatic reduction in the guaranteed price in November.We do not think it would be sensible actually to cut the basic guaranteed price now since this would certainly check the present expansion.    we accordingly propose that the &quot;middle-band&quot; (ie the number of pigs tcwhich the automatic price adjustment is geared) should be raised by45 0,000o    This would almost certainly avoid the price cut in November.The change would not increase Exchequer expenditure but would meanforegoing the saving (not, of course, budgeted for) of about        million which would accrue were the automatic price cut to be applied inNovember.SHEEP21.     In a normal year sheep production would be only marginallyaffected by the rise in cereal prices.    But this has been an abnormal year in that shortage of keep in the lowlands has forced down prices of storelambs coming off the hills in Scotland and the North of England notwith-standing an increase of 3d per lb dressed carcase wieght in the price off at sheep at the 1970 Annual Review.    Store lamb prices in more5
southerly counties have been marginally higher than last year.    Fatlamb producers this autumn and winter will face both higher prices offeed and will need to purchase larger quantities to offset the short-fallin winter keep.22.     There is a need to help lowland sheep producers facing abnormallyhigh feeding costs this winter and also hill sheep producers, many ofwhom have already sold $xttyst of their store lambs at the autumn lambsales and would not benefit - directly or indirectly - from higher prices for fat sheep.    We propose therefore an increase equivalent to 3d per lbon the guaranteed price, to be apportioned between the guaranteed price and the hill sheep subsidy so that both lowland and upland producers will benefit.    This represents an increase in potential Exchequer liability ofabout  5 million in a full year.    We do not propose to increase the guaranteed price for wool despite strong pressures from the industry todo so.POULTRY AND EGGS23.     Poultry is not a guaranteed commodity, and eggs are in processof being phased out of the guarantee.    Production will therefore settle atthe level determined by the market, taking account of production costs onthe one hand and the price that the market will pay on the other.   Poultryand egg production costs will be affected more severely than those of anyother commodity by the higher feed prices.    We are, however, not proposing to increase the guaranteed price for eggs or to assist poultryproduction in some other way.    This will undoubtedly caupe dissatisfactionbut we think that we must face it out on grounds of principle, namely thatour policy is not to give direct support to these products.    Some cut-backof production and higher prices to consumers must be expected.iiCEREALS24.     Three difficult seasons have left cereals production well belowthe 1967 level.    The general increase of costs coupled with a drop in production has already eroded the relief given by the Mgher guaranteed prices awarded at the 1970 Annual Review,    Cereal production is notincreasing; until expansion is resumed, our import bill is bound to go onrising.    The prospective cost of entry into the SEC will rise too.25.    We propose to raise the guaranteed price of wheat by Is. 6d percwt. and of barley by Is. 6d per cwt.    This would mean suspending theoperation of the storage incentive scheme for barley.    There would remain the problem of the liabilities of the Home Grown Cereals Authorityto producers of wheat and barley under its Forward Contract BonusScheme.    We propose no increases for rye, oats or mixed corn.POTATOES26,    We propose no change,
SUGAR BERT27,    We propose to raise the guaranteed price by 2s, 6d per ton becauseof the sharp increase in costs and the importance of sugar beet in the cereals rotation.    This wLil increase producers1 returns by  1 million ayear, but the cost falls on the consumer and there is no direct charge onthe Exchequer.FERTILISER AND LIME28.     The rate of subsidy on these two basic requisites was raised atthe last Review for a period of twelve months ending in March 1971.The increase was expected to stimulate uptake during 1970-71 but thesigns are that this will not in fact occur and expenditure on the subsidiesin 1970-71 is currently forecast to be nearly  2 million lower than expected.    To extend the period of this temporary uplift to the end of the fertiliser year (31 May) would avoid the problems of deliveries to farmsduring January to March - climatically the worst period lor distribution -and would mean that the tonnage qualifying for the higher rates would more nearly approach that expected last March.    Thus against the saving in 1970-71, there would be an extra cost to the Exchequer of about 1 million in 1971-72.FINANCIAL EFFEC T OF THESE PROPOSALS29.    We estimate that if these proposals are brought into effect onthe date proposed,, farmers will beaefit from them some  46 million during the remainder of the current financial year and  61 million in afull year.    The commitment to public funds this year will amount to some 25 million (plus about  lv million saving foregone on pigs) and 35 million in a full year (plus  3f million saving foregone on pigs).The expected saving on support this year is  75 million, so even allowing for the increases in the guarantees, expenditure should still show a netsaving of some  52 million on the Pablished Estimate adjusted to take account of the 1970 Review determination, or some  30 million if it is decided to finance the milk fund this year.    The full year effect of theproposals will also be less (by some  3 million) than the conventionalprovision made for the 1971-72 financial year in the Public expenditure survey,30. i Although it is difficult to estimate the trends of production and of market prices in 1971-72, our best assessment is that the amount of deficiency payment to be made in 1971-72, if the present proposals are accepted, is unlikely to exceed the conventional provision in the public expenditure Survey for that year.    This assessment, of course, excludesany changes in the guarantees which may be made following the 1971Annual Review,,
CONCLUSION31.     We invite our colleagues to agree to the interim measuresoutlined in this memorandum,,    They would be-taken without prejudice tothe determination of levels of support for 1971^72 which we shall need tomake after the full examination of the economic eondition of the industryin the 1971 Annual Review.32*    We should propose to put the agreed proposals immediately to theNFUj not on the basis that they are to be discussed and argued as is normally the case at Annual Reviews, but as decisions taken.    Anappearance of active discussion will however be necessary tactically forthe NF$ leadership, so it may be wise to continue the talks for a day ortwo,33.     Thereafter we would propose to announce the Government^decisions in a very short White Paper for publication early in October.34.     The Treasury has been consulted cn this paper and the estimateof cost increases, the calculation of Exchequer savings and the implications of the proposals for public expenditure have been agreed with them.G CP TJ PR S ministry of Agriculture,, Fisheries and Food, SWl24 September 1970
Appendix estimated EXCHEQUER COMMITMENT;    1970/711.    The Published Estimates have to be framed before the outcome ofthe 1970 Annual Review is known, and an indication of the changes inthe Exchequer support for agriculture is given in the Annual review white Paper.   The following table sets out the basis of the original estimates for 1970/71, the adjusted figures and the presently assessedout-turn.As		Original Estimate	amended by 1970 Review	Latest Forecast	ChangeCereals	Wheat	22.3	24.7	11.6	- 13.1	Barley	39.2	46.4	7.8	- 38.6	Oats	11.7	11.7	6.3	-   5-4Fatstock	Cattle	26.3	34.3	23-3	- 11.0	Sheep	ex 1.7	4.6	4.7	+   0.1	Pigs	21.6	26.1	9.6	- 16.5Eggs		13.1	9.4	9.2	-   0.2Wool		4.4	4.4	4.9	4-   0.potatoes		1.4	1.4	1.4	-Total of	Votes 5 &amp; 6	141.7	163.0	78.8	- 84.22.    Account also has to		be taken of	increases	in Bacon Stabilising	payments	amounting to  9	.2 million.			
EXCHEQUER SUBSIDIES TO AGRICULTURE7    The cost of Exchequer subsidies to agriculture in recent years has been:  million1966/67   1967/68   1968/69      1969/70 1970/71wT^ (estimated   (Adjusted&quot;      (Estimatedout-turn)   Estimate)       out-turn)228 260        264 276 335 249I These figures are those used for public expenditure analysis.   they exclude the Special Assistance Grant to Northern Ireland producers andfare therefore below the total cost of UK Exchequer support to agriculture as shown in the Annual Review White Paper (by  2 million(in recent years).   They also exclude other expenditure on agricultureand fisheries which does not come within the definition of agricultural support.Support Costsl.    The special difficulties of forecasting the future public expenditurecost of agricultural support are briefly explained on page 8 of the1970 Public Expenditure Survey.   The estimate for 1970/71 given in the survey was  335 million, which took account of the part-year effects of the settlement made at the 1970 Annual Review; the figure shown for 1971/72 is  340 million which allows for the full-year effect ofthe last Review but which in other respects is a purely conventionalstraight-line projection of the base-year figure, while for yearsbeyond 1971/72 it was simply assumed that this figure would be repeated,ie no account was taken of possible changes in the levels of guarantees[and subsidies at subsequent Annual Reviews.   Because of variations in the levels of supply and market prices, expenditure may prove to be higher or lower than the projections.5.    Only part of the cost of any Review award falls on public expenditure  further part, especially the cost of the guarantees for milk andi sugar beet, is met out of consumer prices.   Even   though the awardtakes account among other things of cost increases to the farmers, ithas not so far been possible to devise a method of revaluing theprojections of the cost of agricultural support as between one public[expenditure survey and the next to take account of price changes.
EXCHEQUER SUBSIDIES TO agriculture ,    The cost of Exchequer subsidies to agriculture in recent years has been:  million1966/67   1967/68   1968/69(estimated   (Adjustedout-turn)   Estimate)1969/701970/71d (Es t ima t e d)       out-turn)228260264276335249These figures are those used for public expenditure analysis.   Theyexclude the Special Assistance Grant to Northern Ireland producers andare therefore below the total cost of UK Exchequer support to agriculture as shown in the Annual Review White Paper (by  2 million in recent years).   They also exclude other expenditure on agricultureand fisheries which does not come within the definition of agricultural support.Support Costs4-.    The special difficulties of forecasting the future public expenditurecost of agricultural support are briefly explained on page 8 of the1970 Public Expenditure Survey.   The estimate for 1970/71 given in the survey was  335 million, which took account of the part-year effects of the settlement made at the 1970 Annual Review; the figure shown for 1971/72 is  340 million which allows for the full-year effect ofthe last Review but which in other respects is a purely conventionalstraight-line projection of the base-year figure, while for yearsbeyond 1971/72 it was simply assumed that this figure would be repeated,ie no account was taken of possible changes in the levels of guarantees and subsidies at subsequent Annual Reviews.    Because of variations in the levels of supply and market prices, expenditure may prove to be higher or lower than the projections,5.    Only part of the cost of any Review award falls on public expenditure.A further part, especially the cost of the guarantees for milk and sugar beet, is met out of consumer prices.   Even   though the awardtakes account among other things of cost increases to the farmers, ithas not so far been possible to devise a method of revaluing theProjections of the cost of agricultural support as between one public expenditure survey and the next to take account of price changes.
6,    The reason for this is that the cost of deficiency paymentsrepresents, rougly speaking, the difference between market prices andguaranteed prices for each unit of output, multiplied by the number ofeligible units.   Even when guaranteed prices are increased, there maybe no increase in deficiency payments if market prices also rise and/or if there is a shortfall in supplies qualifying for support; thisexplains why for several years in succession the additional public expenditure cost originally expected to result from the Annual Reviewhas in the event not materialised or has not materialised in full.On the other hand, variations in quantities and market prices could work  the other way and result in extra cost, and an extra call on the contingency reserve, over and above that assumed to result from Reviewdecisions.   None of this alters the fact that, since the public expenditure totals do not make specific provision for future expenditureon agricultural support,, going beyond the projections explained above,any support expenditure in excess of those projections can only come out of the contingency reserve like other unprogrammed additions to public expenditure.


</content>
</cab>
