<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/152/0 images: 190-197</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S Government p(70) 69 COPY NO     542 October 1970CABINETRATE SUPPORT grant memorandum by the Minister of Housing andLocal government at their meeting on 15 September (CM(70) 17th Conclusions,Minute 2) the Cabinet invited me to bring before them for considerationearly in the week beginning 5 October, a paper on the forthcoming rate support Grant negotiations for England and Wales,    In doing so I havetaken into account the subsequent Cabinet decisions about a generalsqueeze on local authority expenditure (CM(70) 24th Conclusions,Minute 2),2.     Firm proposals on which the statutory negotiations with the localauthority associations will be based will be brought before the Cabinet forapproval on 29 October and it may be necessary for me to bring thematter orally before the Cabinet later if, in the course of negotiations,it appears essential to arrive at a settlement falling outside the limits which have been approved.    The figures in the present paper are tentativeestimates and are brought before Cabinet for the purpose of indicating theorder of magnitude of local authority expenditure so that this can be takeninto account in the White Paper on Public Expenditure which will bepublished before rate support grant can be settled, and in which the references to local authority expenditure will need to be in guarded terms to avoid prejudging the negotiations.    I also seek guidance from theCabinet on certain issues which need to be taken into account in thepreparation of papers for the formal negotiations.FORECASTS OF EXPENDITURE3.     There are differences in definition between the expenditure onwhich rate support grant is based and its public expenditure equivalent.The figures throughout this paper relate to the expenditure relevant forrate support grant, but an explanation of the differences is given in the annex.1
4,     Our predecessors5 White Paper on &quot;Public Expenditure 1968-69to 1973-74&quot; (Cmnd, 4234) proposed that for 1971-72 a growth of about4t per cent above the total expenditure which was accepted for 1970-71under the 1968 rate support grant settlement would be regarded as an acceptable basis for the next rate support grant determination.However, subsequent analysis of the factors affecting growth of localauthority expenditure cast doubt upon the realism of this and the figuresfor local authority current expenditure in the &quot;public expendituresituation report&quot;, on which all our current public expenditure examina-tions are based, provided for rates of growth of about 5. 2 per cent for both 1971-72 and 1972-73, compared with 4. 2 per cent and 5 per cent which were provided for in the last Rate Support Grant Order for 1969-70and 1970-71.    All these rates of growth are in constant price terms.5.     The figures for the out-turn of local authority expenditure for1969-70 (which are still subject to final revision) indicate that, after making adjustment fcr prices, local authorities spent about  15 million less than forecast.    Their rate of growth was on this basis 3. 7 per centinstead of 4. 2 per cent.6.     For 1970-71, we have available only the estimates used by individual authorities for fixing the level of the rates for that year whichare much influenced by the varying expectations of what wa3 likely to happen to pay and prices throughout the year.    These in the event havebeen particularly large but one cannot readily judge how far individual authorities foresaw this and the real significance of the rate estimatesIs therefore particularly difficult to assess.    The best estimate that wecan make is that local authority expenditure in real terms will be broadlyin line with that envisaged in the Rate Support Grant Order.   17.     For the grant years 1971-72 and 1972-73 Departments are currently preparing, in consultation with representatives of localauthorities, forecasts of what the level of expenditure on individual services can be expected to be taking account of demographic and otherexternal factors and assuming otherwise maintenance of existingstandards.     The forecasts should show also the cost significance of marginal variations in the services.    These forecasts will be brought together in a paper for the meeting of Cabinet on 29th October whichwill give,a range of estimates for total local authority current expenditure with the corresponding policy assumptions on rate of growthfor individual services.    In the light of this I shall seek authority forthe limits within which, and the policy bases upon which, I then proposeto conduct the statutory negotiations with the local authority associations.At present, however, it is not possible to make more than tentativeforecasts of the probable outcome of the negotiations and these indicaterates of growth of about 4 per cent in 1971-72 and 5 per cent in 1972-73 -a little below the present figures.2
8.      These figures will be reduced to take account of the specificpolicy decisions already taken by Cabinet in respect of1971-72 1972-73(a) increased charges for school meals      22 m.         22 m.(b) increase in further education fees         3.3 rn.      5 m.(c) a general squeeze on expenditure  20 m,  25^30 m.However, decisions to discontinue free milk for some or all primaryschoolchildren to save between  7. 7 million and  12. 5 million in a full year will not be reflected in this round because they will require legislation which will need to provide for the grant settlement to be revised later.GRANT PERCENTAGE9.     For some years before 1966 when rate support grant legislation was passed, rate poundages had been increasing on average aboutlOd. a year (9 per cent or 10 per cent and much faster than incomes)and there was considerable political complaint about the burden ofrates on domestic property In particular.    The White Paper, LocalGovernment Finance in England and Wales (Cmnd. 2923) published in1966, envisaged an annual increase in the total of Exchequer grants tolocal authorities the greater part of which would be devoted to reducingthe rates of householders and talked in terms of a 5d reduction if ratesrose by lOd.    In pursuit of this policy, grant which started at54 per cent in 1967-68 has risen by 1 per cent per year to 57 per cent for 1970-71.    Most of the extra expenditure has been distributed asrelief for domestic ratepayers amounting to 5d in 1967-68 rising by 5d ayear until now in 1970-71 the domestic ratepayer pays rates on a poundageIs. 8d less than the standard rate.    Compared with 8ld per year forother ratepayers the average increase in domestic rates has been3ld per year over this period which is less than 2-f per cent per annum and thus much less than the rise in incomes.10.      Although the figures are inevitably very tentative at this stage,I estimate that, on the basis of the forecasts at present available, rateincreases in each of the two years will be at least Is. 3d - which,unabated, would be about 10 per cent a year for domestic ratepayers.On the policy set out by our predecessors, this would have justified atleast a further 5d reduction in each year but we should, I think,reconsider this policy,11.     There are two questions to be determined.    First, whether there should be a further addition to the domestic element, and secondly,whether grant should rise above the 57 per cent paid in 1970-71 by morethan the amount necessary to cover any increase in domestic element.WWII I Hill
CONF1DEMT1AL12.     The grant percentage clearly cannot continue to increase indefinitelybut the progression will be broken with the revision of the grant system onthe reorganisation of local government.    The problems at that time will,however, be eased if both the growth in grant and the increase in the domestic element are restrained in the interim.    A cue in the percentagerate of grant does not necessarily and directly reduce public expenditure;it substantially transfers the burden from national to local taxes.   The levelof local rates - and particularly of domestic rates - is politically sensitiveand if domestic element is less than might be expected from our predecessors we may be accused of trying to cut national taxes at theexpense of local taxes.    We must keep this in mind in taking a view onthe appropriate balance between local and central government taxation.13.     The easy solution would be to continue to increase the dome sticelement each year by 5d steps.    However, the rise in the domesticelement over the last four years which has, in fact, kept growth in domestic rates to about half the rise in incomes, has already isolatedthe domestic ratepayer too much from the real magnitude of increase in local authority expenditure, especially since at the same time raterebates have tempered the impact of rates on those with low incomes.    i therefore propose that the further increments on the present domesticelement of Is. 8d should be much less than the 5d of the past, although Ido not think that the Is. 8d level should be frozen on this occasion.14.    A variety of formulae might be considered to determine theappropriate increments but the most simple would be to halve theprevious steps and thus add 2id each year instead of 5d.    In practice,the next Order will need to be made in terms of decimal currency.    to add 2?d to the existing Is. 8d would produce 9. 35 new pence.    This must clearly be rounded to 9lp which will make an increase for 1971-72 of2. 9d but the increment for 1972-73 would then be lp or 2. 4d making the domestic element for that year lOfp.15.     If the grant percentage **f 57 per cent was raised to cover incrementsin domestic element of 5d in each year it would have become 57. 81 per cent and 58.59 per cent for 1971-72 and for 1972-73.     The percentages whichwould just cover increases to 9fp and 10fp would be 57. 49 per cent and57. 9 per cent respectively.    A grant percentage higher than these figures would provide relief for ratepayers generally - both domestic and non-domestic.    The latter have in the past borne virtually the full rate of growth of local authority expenditure without relief and I see no reason tointroduce relief now.    The domestic ratepayer should not need any relief in excess of that provided by the domestic element.    I do not therefore propose that the grant percentage should be raised above the amount required to cover the increments in domestic element except to the extent necessary to round it up to the nearest quarter per cent which will mean57^ per cent and 58 per cent in 1971-72 and 1972-73 respectively.4
INCREASE ORDER16.     It is fundamental to the rate support grant system that the settlements are made on the basis of the levels of prices, costs and remuneration then current; and that where increases in those levelsensue the grants are adjusted by means of Increase Orders to maintain their value in real terms.    A special exception was made following devaluation when local authorities were asked to cut back their activitiesdrastically and sufficiently to absorb the increase for 1968-69 and part of1967-68.    Substantial reductions were, in fact, made but not enough to cancel out the large price increases following devaluation.17.    Authorities, while recognising the exceptional situation,regarded the consequent reduction in the proportion of grant below thatoriginally promised as a breach of faith.18.     Information is still being collected about the pay and price increases since November 1969, when an Order was made to take accountof increases subsequent to the settlement for 1967-68 and 1968-69 inNovember 1968.     Those affecting the year 1969-70 are expected to amountto no more than  13 million but those for 1970-71 will amount to at least 200 million and may be as much as  240 million; the ultimate total to betaken into account by an Order this year will depend upon what further pay settlements are achieved before the Order goes to print in November.19.     An Increase Order for these amounts will involve increases in rate support grants of some  7 million for 1969-70 and between  120 million and  135 million for 1970-7.most of which would fall to be paid in thecurrent financial year.    This extra money should not encourageextravagance; local authorities must bear their share of the increased costs and will have budgeted in the belief that the Government will pay its part.20.     I have some discretion whether or not to make an Increase Order.However, in the light of increases of this magnitude a refusal would betotally unreasonable, especially since the Government were parties tothe decision in some of the major elements such as teachers1 pay.Having decided to make an Order, it is not open to me to be selective.    i must take account of all increases in pay and costs.    An Increase Orderdoes not add to public expenditure - it merely determines the extent towhich the costs of expenditure already incurred are borne by rates orother taxes.    I therefore seek approval for the making of Increase orders in respect of 1970-71 and the end of 1969-70.CONCLUSION21.     I therefore invite Cabinet :-(i)     to note the preliminary estimates of the level oflocal authority expenditure for the next two years;5
(ii)      to agree that domestic element should be increased from its present level of Is. 8d or 8. 3p to 9lp in1971-72 and lolp in 1972-73j(iii) to agree that the grant percentage should not beincreased beyond the nearest ^ per cent step sufficientto cover those increments in domestic element;(iv) to agree that Increase Orders should be made inrespect of 1969-70 and 1970-71.PfMinistry of Housing and Local Government SW11 October 1970
(confidential)annex public Expenditure equivalent of expenditure for Rate Support Grant purposes the definition of relevant expenditure which has to be taken intoaccount in fixing rate support grant is, broadly, all rate and grantborne expenditure except contributions to housing or trading accounts.The main difference between this and local authority current expenditure on rate support grant services in the public expenditure survey is the inclusion of loan charges.     There are in addition anumber of other small adjustments to be made for items such as capitalexpenditure met from revenue and contributions to capital and otherfunds. i        jiThe effect of all these adjustments is that the public expenditureequivalent is  500 million or  600 million less than relevant expenditure for rate support grant and grows about       less fast.Thus the figure of 4$ growth in real terms quoted in last year&apos;public expenditure White Paper (Cmnd 4-234) corresponds to about 4^%growth in rate support grant terms.(confidential)IffMTlimWlTWgiflTlll^


</content>
</cab>
