<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 66/15/38 images: 392-421</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY S GOVERNMENTSECRET. Copy No. 28- -W.P. (41) 65(also Paper No. C.O.S. (41) 178)March 20, 1941. . . ////TO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK/AND KEY.---^--It is requested that special careViay be taken toensure the secrecy of this document.(No. 81)of theNAVAL, MILITARY AND AIR situation from 12 noon March 13th, to12 noon March 20th,1941[Circulated with the approval ofthe Chiefs of Staff.]
NAVAL SITUATION.General Review.1.   The battle-cruisers Scharnhorst and Gneisenau are in the North Atlantic.Two,  probably three,  U-boats have been  sunk  in  the  North-western approaches.The Fleet Air Arm has had successes against Italian shipping on theAlbanian coast.The Suez Canal has been reopened for traffic.Shipping losses reported are much reduced and imports in convoy are thehighest for some months. .Home Waters.2. E-boats were active off the East coast of England during the night the14th to 15th March and H.M. Destroyer Versatile was missed by two torpedoes.They were twice sighted and chased by H.M. Destroyers Holderness and Vanessa,who damaged one and sank possibly two. E-boats were again reported on thenights the 17th to 18th and the 19th to 20th.Damage was caused to Naval Establishments at Liverpool in an air raid onthe night of the 12th. One merchant ship was sunk in dock and six others were damaged.  The floating crane Mammoth was sunk in dock on an even keel.The Clyde was attacked on the night of the 13th and two destroyers in anearly stage of construction, the Goathland and Haldon, were damaged atFairfield&apos;s shipyard. The Admiralty Oil Fuel Installation also received damage.Two merchant ships were sunk and another slightly damaged. Damage to ship-building yards is reported in the Home Security Section.Plymouth Dockyard received slight damage from air raid on the 15th.H.M. Minesweeper Britomart was bombed and damaged off Rye on the 15th,and her commanding officer and another were killed.North Atlantic.3. After being sighted by H.M.S. Malayans aircraft 500 miles S.W. of theCanaries on the 8th March, there was evidence from merchant ship reportsthat the battle-cruisers Scharnhorst and Gneisenau were working over to theCanadian coast, and dispositions were made to cover the home-bound convoys.H.M.S. Rodney sighted a warship, later considered to be Gneisenau, on the lateevening of the 16th about 300 miles E.S.E. of Newfoundland but did not make contact. On going to press news has been received that both ships were locatedby aircraft from H.M.S. Ark Royal on the evening of the 20th steering north,about 600 miles W.N.W. of Cape Finisterre; the visibility was low.TIM. Sloop Scarborough intercepted two Norwegian whalers about 530&apos; west of Cape Finisterre on the 13th, both of which scuttled themselves. They had beentaken in prize in the south Atlantic by a German cruiser. Scarborough picked up one German Lieutenant-Commander, 7 German ratings and 22 Norwegians.Mediterranean.4. The Mediterranean Fleet has been engaged in covering the passage of convoys from Egypt to Greece.Supplies to our forces in the Western Desert are being maintained via Mersa-Tobruk. All the captured North African ports are usable except Benghazi,which has insufficient A.A. defences.H.M. Submarine Utmost attacked two deeply laden Southbound escortedmerchant vessels 50 miles S.S.W. of Pantellaria on the 9th. She fired threetorpedoes at one of the ships (believed to be carrying troops) after which a violentexplosion was heard. The ship is believed to have sunk. H.M. Submarine Uniqueclaims to have sunk an escorted Italian merchant vessel of about 2,500 tons100 miles N. by W. of Tripoli on the 10th. HM. Submarine Triumph sank two merchant vessels of about 2,500 tons which were at anchor off Melito nearCape Spartivento, South Italy.
On the night of the 16th/ 17th a Swordfish aircraft attacked shipping atValona with torpedoes, hitting a cruiser or destroyer, resulting in a largeexplosion. Swordfish aircraft also attacked shipping at Durazzo, obtaining twocertain and two probable hits.The Suez Canal was reopened to traffic in both directions on the 19th March.East Indies,5. H.M. Ships Glasgow and Caledon with H.M. destroyers Kingston andKandahar and four armed merchant cruisers escorted the landing force for therecapture of Berbera, and covered the landing at dawn on the 16th March. Someartillery and machine gun opposition was encountered, but this was silenced by a moderate bombardment, and the British flag was hoisted over Berbera at 0900.Anti-Submarine Operations.6. During the morning of the 17th a homeward bound convoy was attacked by U-boats. H.M. Destroyer Walker sank U/B 99, and H.M. Destroyer Vanocrammed and sank U/B 100. Prisoners were taken from both these U-boats.A third U-boat was probably sunk, but no survivors were found.H.M. Destroyers Versatile and Vandetta made attacks off Hartlepool and inthe Gulf of Athens respectively; and H.M. Corvette Calendula attacked a U-boatwith gunfire 200 miles north-east of the Cape Verde Islands, all without knownresult.Enemy Intelligence.German.7. Aircraft reconnaissances of German Naval ports, especially Kiel, havebeen made on the 12th, 13th and 18th March. Examination of the photographs taken on the 12th March suggests that the 8-inch cruiser in dock at Kiel is thePrinz Eugen and the 6-inch cruiser is the Leipzig. In the reconnaissance the18th March it was seen that the battleship Bismarck or Tirpitz, which had beenin the floating dock, had left, and that the 8-inch cruiser (Prinz Eugen) had come out of the other floating dock and was now alongside. Lutzow was still alongsideand Leipzig still in dry dock. On the 19th March aircraft confirmed that thenew cruiser Seydlitz was still at Bremen.The Hipper class cruiser left Brest on the night of the 15th/16th March.There has been considerable E-boat activity during the week. These boatsappear to be based on the Helder and Rotterdam.Italian.8. Air reconnaissances of Naples and Tripoli on the 16th March, and ofTrapani, Pantellaria and the Sicilian Channel on the previous day showed that considerable activity continues, but almost entirely of merchant shipping and only a few Naval units were seen. These were all destroyers, submarines and/or small craft.U-Boats.9. There have been ten or eleven German U-Boats and four or five Italianin the North-Western Approaches throughout the week.A force of at least three Germans was at work about 150 miles W.S.W. ofthe Faroes on the 16th and 17th March. Three of the Italians have been workingas far out as 240 W. (West of Rockall). There are now three or four germans and three Italians within 150 miles westward of the Porcupine Bank.Two German U-Boats have been between the Canaries and Cape VerdeIslands during the week and one Italian near the Azores. A German may havebeen about 500 miles East of Cape Race.Enemy Attack on Seaborne Trade.10. During the period the 13th to the 19th March, 20 ships and 1 small craft, a total of 65,111 tons, have been reported sunk, and of these 15 ships and1 small craft (55,512 tons) were British.[22337] b
Five ships (26,234 tons) were sunk by U-boat, four of them off the west coast of Africa.Five ships and a small craft (18,524 tons) were sunk by aircraft, three off theeast coast and three off the west coast. Five ships (13.374 tons) were mined, twoin the Mersey, one off the Tyne, one off Cromer, and one off the Lizard. Fiveships (6,979 tons) were sunk by surface craft, one by a raider off the Seychellesand four by E-boats off the Norfolk coast. Twenty-four British and fourteenallied and neutral vessels have been damaged, including some damaged in air raids on Liverpool and Manchester.Protection of Seaborne Trade.11. In the week ending the 19th March 822 ships, including 153 allied and14 neutral, were convoyed. Ten vessels in convoy are reported lost, but twopreviously reported lost have been deleted, one having straggled before she was lost and the other having arrived after having been presumed sunk. Since the start of the war 272 ships in convoy have been lost, or one ship in 210. Threebattleships, one battle-cruiser, one aircraft carrier, one seaplane ship, fourcruisers, ten armed merchant cruisers, three submarines, 46 destroyers and43 sloops and corvettes were employed on escort duty.12. Imports into Great Britain by ships in convoy during the week ending march 15 totalled 1,122,061 tons, compared with 640,178 tons during the previous seven days and an average of 628,309 tons for the last ten weeks. This is- thehighest weekly total since the week ending the 2nd November, and the seventhoccasion since the beginning of August 1940 on which the weekly total has exceeded a million tons. Oil imports during last week were 352,506 tons in 32tankers, compared with 208,696 tons in 20 tankers. Mineral imports were348,090 tons, of which 104,463 tons were iron ore, scrap iron, pig iron and steel.Timber and pulp imports were 62,187 tons and cereal imports, in spite of a lossof 15,765 tons in two fully laden grain ships, were 206,347 tons. Twenty-fiveships were fully laden with grain. Other food imports amounted to 61,515 tons,of which 4,408 tons were fruit (including three ship-loads of Seville oranges,totalling 3,250 tons), 943 tons were bacon and tinned meat, 10,933 tons were sugar and 4,739 tons were tea. There were also large imports of motor vehicles, aircraft,machine tools and ammunition.British Minelaying.13. H.M.S. Plover has carried out two minelaying operations in the st. George&apos;s Channel during the week on the 14th and the 19th March.One hundred and twenty mines were laid on each occasion. On the 17th MarchHALS. Teviot Bank laid 270 mines in the East Coast barrier. On the 19th MarchH.M.S. Southern Prince, Port Quebec, Agamemnon and Menestheus laid 2,040mines in the Faroes-Iceland Channel, and H.M.S. Intrepid, Icarus and Impulsivelaid 90 off the French coast on the same day.Enemy Minelaying, British Minesweeping.Home Waters.14. Minelaying enemy aircraft were more active early in the week, whenthe moon was full, than later. It is thought that no mines were dropped south ofa line from the Humber to Liverpool. Mines have been dropped in the riversduring the raids on Clydeside and Merseyside and are also suspected in liverpool Bay. )Fog and bad weather have hampered sweeping operations in the contact mine-fields in the English Channel between Dungeness and the Owers. Sixteen mines were cut in the area south-west of Dungeness and thirteen in the area south ofBeachy Head. It is hoped to complete the clearance of the area south-west ofDungeness so that the Channel Convoys can be restarted.The Minesweeping Force at Sheerness on the 17th March detonatedtwenty-three mines. The movement of ships in the Thames Estuary was uninter-rupted throughout the day, 125 ships in all entering or leaving the Port ofLondon through the Thames Gate.
Five ships have been sunk by mine during the period under review and fivedamaged.Forty-four acoustic mines and twenty-two magnetic mines have beendetonated during the week and the mine totals, including those swept in foreignwaters, are now 1,002 magnetic, 409 acoustic and 840 contact.Since the beginning of the war Minesweepers have destroyed twenty-sixenemy aircraft for certain, nine probably, and damaged ten. Twenty-six Mine-sweepers have been sunk by enemy aircraft.Foreign Waters.15. Three mines were detonated in the northern part of the &quot;Suez Canalduring the week, thus enabling traffic to be moved in this section. In the southernsector of the Canal mines failed to respond to treatment, but it was possible torestart traffic on the 19th March, and H.M.S. Illustrious and 25 Merchant Vesselsarrived at Suez on the 20th.A belated report has been received stating that two mines were detonatedin the Grand Harbour, Valletta, Malta, on the 8th March.Enemy Merchant Shipping.German.16. On the 17th March it was officially announced in Berlin that a fire had broken out on the liner Bremen, 51,731 tons, on the previous day. The Swedishpress states that she is a total loss, and that the fire was certainly not accidentalas it broke out in several places simultaneously.It is now known that the following German ships were sunk when british units raided the Lofoten Islands : the Flamburg, which before conversion to an oil factory ship was the Ilmar, 5,470 tons, the Eilenau, 1,404 tons, the Gumbinnen,1,381 tons, the Felix Neumann, 2,468 tons, the Bernhard Schulte, 1,058 tons, apatrol ship called the Krebs and a small fishing boat called the Rissen, also theNorwegian Mir a, 1,152 tons.17. The tanker Antaretis, 10,711 tons, sailed from Vigo during the night ofthe 17th/18th March. The Gerda Vith, 1,312 tons, has been loading 300 tons oflubricating oil at Vigo.The Norwegian oil refinery ships Ole Wegger, 12,201 tons, the Pelagos,12,083 tons, the Sol Glimt, 12,246 tons, and the tanker Sande Fjord, 4,767 tons,are missing from the South Atlantic, and it is presumed that they have falleninto enemy hands.MILITARY SITUATION.Europe.Spain and Portugal.18. There has been no appreciable increase in the German forces in thearea immediately north of the Franco-Spanish frontier, but the infiltration intoSpain of Germans in mufti has continued. Preparations for the billeting oflarge numbers of German tourists in Spain are also reported.Several indications of German interest in Portugal have also been received,such as the reported infiltration of Germans in mufti and a report that Nazi partycircles in Portugal are contemplating the organization of a Fifth Column.It is also worthy of note that the German press and wireless have recently made frequent reference to an alleged British intention to occupy the Azores as a preliminary to an attack on Portugal.19. The Italian garrison on the Yugoslav frontier now amounts to fiveinfantry divisions, two mobile divisions, and perhaps a reserve Alpine division, atotal of 11 divisions (including an estimated equivalent of 3 divisions of FrontierGuard).These divisions are all reported to be now located in the frontier area, havingleft their peace stations to which they retired for the winter.
A albania.20. In Albania the Italian offensive, which lasted for about a week, appearsto have temporarily ended. The attack was launched on the 10th March on a20-mile front between Mount Tomor and the River Vijose in the Central Sector.This attack was accompanied by a feint on the northern sector near Pogradets.Eight divisions as well as detached battalions and black shirt Militia battalionswere employed. Four of these eight divisions have been recently reorganizedwith drafts from Italy; two have recently arrived from Italy. The Greeks haverepulsed all these attacks1 without losing ground, and have inflicted heavy losses.Casualties sustained by the Italians are estimated at 25,000, of which 3,000 areprisoners. Two divisions have been withdrawn from the line, two others are reported to have lost about 50 per cent, of their effectives, and the Militiabattalions have suffered very heavy losses.Yugoslavia.21. The army is mobilising rapidly, and figures of 700,000 and 800,000 aregiven for the total strength. The latter is probably more nearly correct.Although confirmation has been received of the duplication of only two divisions,it is probable that a further five have already thrown off duplicates. This wouldgive a present total of 23 infantry divisions. It is estimated that a furtherseven could be mobilised but, as full equipment is not available for them; theywould have to be used mainly as L. of C. troops.Roumania and Bulgaria.22. There are at least 32 German divisions in Roumania and Bulgaria. Ofthese, a minimum of 12 divisions are in Roumania (this figure is likely to increaseshortly), in addition seven or eight divisions are believed to be moving from roumania into Bulgaria and at least nineteen divisions, including possibly twoarmoured and three motorised, are already in Bulgaria.Africa,Libya.23. On the 16th March there was movement of enemy armoured cars andM.T. in the area 10 miles west of Agheiia. Enemy aircraft raided Benghazi onthe 17th March, causing neither damage nor casualties.Eritrea.24. Our troops have maintained their positions to the north of the roadKeren-Agordat. On the 16th March 200 of the enemy surrendered 4 miles west of Keren and, south of the same road, our troops captured a fort on a hill2\ miles S.W. of Keren taking 400 prisoners and repelling two counter attacks.The total number of prisoners captured is estimated to be 800.Prisoners state that our bombing and artillery have inflicted heavy casualtiesItalian Somaliland.25.   Our forward troops captured Jijiga on the evening of the 17th March.Mandera was found to be deserted by one of our patrols.British Somaliland.26.   Berbera was occupied on the 16th March by our forces.   Our casualties were negligible and 100 prisoners were taken.   The harbour has been swept andthe unloading of stores is now in progress and our troops are established round    ;)the town.Evidence has been received that propaganda dropped prior to our occupationwas effective in undermining morale and encouraging desertions.Far East.27. The 15th Indian Infantry Brigade with Field Ambulance and fourIndian State Forces battalions have arrived in Malaya in accordance with the reinforcement programme.
General Review.AIR SITUATION.28. Bomber Command carried out some very successful night attacks on targets in Hamburg, Gelsenkirchen. Bremen, Kiel, Wilhelmshaven, Cologne andother important enemy industrial centres. Coastal Command aircraft torpedoedtwo merchant vessels.Heavy enemy attacks were made on our ports. Our night fighters and A.A.guns continued to be successful in destroying raiders.In the Middle East, extensive British air operations have met with considerable success.Operational aircraft battle casualties and extracts from recent Raid Assess-ment Reports are given in Appendices VI and VII.Germany and Occupied Territory.29. During the week Bomber Command flew 68 sorties by day and 639 by night. Coastal Command and Fighter Command aircraft took part in operations over France.Day.30. The number of day bombing sorties was double that of the previous week.Weather conditions were more favourable for photography, and Spitfires of thePhotographic Reconnaissance Unit made deep penetrations into enemy territory.Blenheims mainly concentrated on offensive patrols against enemy coastal shipping. They also carried out a successful attack on Calais (Marck) aerodrome,on which they were accompanied by three squadrons of fighters and followed by six other fighter squadrons; no serious opposition was encountered and casulties on both sides were light.Night,31. The number of night sorties flown during the week has not been exceededduring any similar period since the last week in September 1940. bomber command took advantage of improved weather conditions to carry out a seriesof heavy attacks on important enemy objectives, during which an increased number of heavy bombs were employed.32. On the 13tlh/14th an attack on the Blohm and Voss naval shipyardsand the industrial area at Hamburg was carried out by one hundred aircraft,which dropped 80 tons of H.E. bombs and 13,000 incendiaries. Weather con-ditions were favourable and many bursts were seen on the targets; some large fires were reported to be burning fiercely, the docks having been set on fire atthe aiming point by Blenheims. During this night Bomber Command lost fiveaircraft, one of which was shot down over this country. Another heavy attack was made on two synthetic oil plants at Gelsenkirchen on the following night,during which our aircraft again dropped over 80 tons of bombs. photographs taken during the raid showed the plants to be badly damaged and on fire in severalplaces; a very large explosion was reported and a fire was visible at a distance of100 miles from the target.33. On the 17th good weather conditions favoured a very successful raid by over fifty aircraft on the naval shipyards and Industrial Centre at Bremen. Onthe following night seventy-nine aircraft attacked industrial targets in Kiel;bomb-loads included twenty-nine 1,000-lb. bombs, and a number of large fires were started.34. Lighter attacks, resulting in considerable damage, were made duringthe week on industrial targets at Wilhelmshaven, Dnsseldorf and Cologne and onthe submarine base at Lorient. Lorient was also bombed by Coastal CommandBlenheims. The petrol harbour at Rotterdam was attacked on five occasions, on one of which one Stirling dropped 11,000 lbs. of bombs. A number of aerodromes,,A.A. batteries, searchlights and other targets were -attacked by single aircraft.35. Our night bombers had several encounters with enemy aircraft, as aresult of which they destroyed five, probably destroyed two and damaged another.[22337] c
Fighter Command carried out offensive operations against aerodromes in northern france, some of which they bombed; one enemy aircraft was shot down and two others probably destroyed.United Kingdom.36. Fighter Command flew 842 patrols, involving 2,673 sorties, by day, and505 patrols, involving 698 sorties, by night. By day enemy activity consistedmainly of shipping and weather reconnaissances and frequent coastal patrols.A few of these flew inland for short distances, there was some bombing of south coast towns and small fighter sweeps occasionally penetrated over Kent andSussex. Strong defensive patrols were maintained by the enemy in the channel and Straits of Dover. By night there was a considerable increase in activity,1,815 aircraft being employed (including 150 suspected of minelaying), comparedwith 1,160 aircraft during the previous week.37. Heavy attacks on ports took place on every night of the period except on the 17th/18th March, when bad weather intervened. On the 13th/14th themain concentrations were in the Liverpool and Glasgow Area. This was followedon the next night by another large-scale attack on Glasgow. London and Bristolwere the next targets, while widespi^ead raids over Eastern England took placeon the 18th/19th with Hull and Scarborough as the principal objectives, and theperiod finished with a heavy attack on the London Docks on the night of the19th/20th. Moonlight helped the raiders, and several aerodromes in the eastern counties were also attacked. Twenty-three enemy aircraft were destroyed at night over this country, sixteen being shot down by our fighters.Coastal Reconnaissance, Patrols and Mining.38. Aircraft of Coastal Command flew 233 patrols and photographic recon-maissances, involving 339 sorties; in addition, 372 sorties were made in protectionof convoys.39. A series of attacks were made by Coastal Command aircraft on enemy shipping. At dawn on the 18th March a Beaufort sighted five merchant vesselsnear Borkum and successfully torpedoed one of 5,000 tons; a vessel of 3,000 tons was sunk on another night, while a near miss to a ship of 3,700 tons appeared to throw the vessel forward. A direct hit was also obtained with a small bomb on a2,000-ton ship near Trondheim. Bomber Command aircraft also carried out anumber of day sorties to attack enemy coastal shipping.40. On the nights on which enemy minelaying was carried out the scale washigh, averaging about fifty sorties per night. The areas in which this activity wasidentified were chiefly the main river estuaries. On most days two aircraft wereidentified on offensive patrols of the Western Approaches, but fewer attacks weremade on our shipping.Egypt and Libya.41. Many patrols and reconnaissances were carried out by our aircraft.Tripoli Harbour was bombed by Wellingtons on two occasions, and violentexplosions and fires were observed. Attacks were also made on Castel Benitoaerodrome, where an ammunition dump and buildings were set on fire, and onMakina aerodrome, where four aircraft were destroyed on the ground.42. German bombers attacked El Adem on the night of the 12th/ 13th,hitting barrack blocks and hangars but without damaging aircraft. enemy aircraft also attacked Benghazi, Benina and Berka, but without effect. Duringlow7-fiying attacks on our troops by Me. 110&apos;s at El Agheila, AA. fire accountedfor four of the enemy.Italian East Africa.43. In Eritrea, our aircraft have given valuable support to land forces intheir attacks on Keren, by repeatedly bombing and machine-gunning the enemy&apos;spositions and lines of communication. Offensive patrols were carried out overAsmara, Aksum, and Agordat.
44. In Abyssinia, Diredawa and its aerodrome were bombed and twelveaircraft were destroyed on the ground by Hurricanes, who also shot down two enemy aircraft. Blenheims from Aden also bombed Dessie and carried outpatrols and reconnaissances in support of the operations at Berbera and in theRed Sea.Greece and Albania.45. Our aircraft continued to give support to the land operations in theBuzi area. Valona aerodrome was attacked on three occasions. A petrol dumpwas set on fire at Berat aerodrome and many fires were started when Wellingtonsdropped eleven tons of bombs on Tirana aerodrome. The docks at Durazzowere again attacked on the night of the 17th/18th March.46. Our fighters continue to operate at great intensity in the Kelcyre Area.On the 13th fourteen Gladiators and six Hurricanes intercepted an enemyformation of fourteen bombers and forty fighters; the Gladiators destroyed ninefighters and probably another three; one Gladiator was damaged. On thefollowing day twelve Gladiators and three Hurricanes attacked fifteen bombers and thirty-six fighters and destroyed seven aircraft and probably five more, forthe loss of two of their own number, whose pilots are safe.47. The enemy bombed the aerodrome at Heraklion in Crete, damaging arunway, and twice attacked Janina aerodrome without causing casualties or damage except to one Gladiator.Dodecanese.48. Five Wellingtons attacked Rhodes Harbour and the aerodromes atMaritza and Calato with good results on the night of the llth/T2th March, andon the following night another force of fourteen bombers dropped twelve tons of bombs on Maritza, Calato, Kattavia and Scarpanto aerodromes, causing many-fires and explosions.Malta.49. Five small-scale attacks were made on the Island during the period.Only one attack succeeded in dropping bombs on land. This was at Hal Faraerodrome, but no damage or casualties resulted. In the other cases the attackerswere driven off by our fighters or dropped their bombs in the sea. Our aircraftcarried out many reconnaissance flights.Air Intelligence.Germany.50. Reports of extensive parachute and glider training continue to bereceived. These mention mountain artillery adapted for use with parachutists,parachute training in country resembling the North and South Downs, and nightglider-towing exercises.Central Mediterranean.51. The German Air Force strength in this area (given in last week&apos;resume) has been increased by ten short-range fighters.52. In Tripolitania German dive-bomber and fighter aircraft have been moved East to aerodromes in the area Sirte, El Macchina and Nofilia. and someGerman aircraft have used Arae Philaenorum, about 40 miles North-West of el Agheiia.Balkans.53. About twenty German long-range fighters have now moved into Bulgariafrom Roumania (see last week&apos;s Resume).
Italian East A frica.54. The present Italian strength is estimated at 85 aircraft, of whichprobably not more than 30 are serviceable.Fa?&apos; East.55. Japanese aircraft movements between Indo-China and Hainan continue,and a report has been received to the effect that these include the withdrawal ofsome 70 aircraft, quantities of bombs, and 250 air personnel from Haiphong.56. On the 14th March a formation of seven of the latest Japanese fighterswas intercepted, near Chengtu, by Russian fighters recently supplied to theChinese as part of an order for 150 Russian aircraft. Four of the Japanese were shot down and only one reached its base.HOME SECURITY.General.By Day.57. No fatal civilian casualties occurred by day. On five days no bombs were dropped. On the 17th March bombs were dropped in Scotland, and on the18th March in West Suffolk and Kent, but no serious damage was caused.By Night.58. The week was characterised by a series of heavy raids, mostly on anumber of ports and on London. Many were widespread, although docks or industrial dwellings in specific areas received the greater proportion of the bombs. Twenty-one R.A.F. Stations or aerodromes were hit, but with only slight damage.59. On the night the 13th/14th March Merseyside was attacked for thesecond night in succession, but less severely, Wallasey and Southport sufferingmost. Severe bombing took place at Hull, and there were minor incidents in allother regions, but the main damage was on Clydeside, where Glasgow andClydebank suffered their first heavy raid of the war.60. On the 14th/.15th March Clycleside again suffered most. There waswidespread bombing in the West Riding, which, according to enemy broadcasts,was directed on Sheffield, but the most extensive damage and casualties in this area were at Leeds. Hull and Sunderland also suffered, and bombs were againdropped in every region. London was not heavily attacked. Plymouth andPortland also suffered short but intense raids.61.   On the 15th/16th March serious bombing was confined to South andSouth-East London and the Home Counties.62.   On the 16th/17th March Bristol suffered heavy damage and casualties,especially in the Central districts.63.   On the 17th/ 18th March slight damage was caused in the NorthMidlands and East Anglia.64. On the 18th/T9th March: Hull suffered most, but other places in the \East Riding were involved, noticeably Scarborough, which was bombed inter-mittently for four hours. This seems incongruous in comparison with the valueof other objectives in the district. Some bombing took place in the NorthMidlands, Eastern Regions, London, the South and South-East Counties andFolkestone.65. On the 19th/20th March : Bombing was concentrated on East Londonand the London Docks, where there were more major fires than on any date sincethe 29th December, causing considerable damage.
Damage.66. Merseyside. The attacks on the 13th/14th and 14th/loth Marchchiefly accentuated the dislocation due to last week&apos;s raid. Wallasey sufferedmost damage but, in spite of the water shortage, no serious fires developed.67. Clydeside. Whilst docks and shipbuilding yards were hit, the maineffect on industry was indirectly caused by the heavy damage to the industrialdwelling area of Clydebank.Of the Docks damaged, Rothesay Dock suffered most severely. Of the ship-building yards damaged, Aitcheson Blair&apos;s will require complete reconstruction,whilst at John Brown&apos;s the sawmill was badly damaged by fire and there was considerable damage to shops, but little to ships under construction. At Yarrowand Co.&apos;s works, although the material damage was less, a direct hit on a shelterkilled 80 shipyard workers.Singer Manufacturing Co.&apos;s works also suffered extensively from fire; and atthe R.N. oil fuel depot at Dalnottar eighteen oil cisterns were burnt out or seriously damaged.The general damage to public services and industrial dwellings was lesssevere in Glasgow than in Clydebank, where there are very few houses fit for occupation, and where gas, water and electricity failed. Some 10,000 persons were officially evacuated and 15,000 left of their own accord, comprising half theindustrial population. &quot;Water has however been restored to the principalindustrial concerns and such houses as are habitable, and restoration of theelectricity supply is nearing completion.68. Leeds.- Damage was mostly caused by fire, and production was affectedby damage to the utility services, especially gas. Eight key factories were hit,at which damage at Greenwood and Batteys was serious. The telephone system was badly damaged, but considerable progress in the restoration of services hasbeen made.69. Hull. Owing to communications with Hull being seriously dislocatedit has not been possible to assess the damage done, but damage to its gasworkshas affected many industries.70. Bristol. Direct damage to industry was small, and the chief effect onthe national effort was indirect, being caused by the dislocation of public servicesand communications.71. Southampton. Harland and Wolffs shipbuilding yards sufferedconsiderable damage.72. London. Early in the week some damage was done in the Dock area and there were two fires at the Law Courts. Full particulars of the extent of the damage caused on the night of the 19th/20th cirG not QjVSl liable, but the following is a preliminary report: (a) Docks. Damage was widespread and gas, water and electricity supplies were interrupted at many points.(b) Railways S.R. Owing to the destruction of signals, only one line was left open between London Bridge and New Cross. All lines at Bricklayers ArmsGoods Depot, Bermondsey, were blocked. In the Lewi sham district manysuburban lines were damaged and services dislocated.L.N.E.R. and L.M.S. Suburban lines serving the Eastern districts ofLondon suffered severely, and Temple Mills Marshalling Yard, Leyton, was putout of action.(c) Factories. Several factories were severely damaged, among them being-British Ropes (Limited), Mills Equipment Company (Limited), TelegraphConstruction and Maintenance Company and Joseph Rank (Limited).(d) Public Utilities. Electricity Generating Stations at Poplar, Stepneyand West Ham were hit by H.E., but not put out of action. The SouthMetropolitan Gas Works, Greenwich, the Commercial Gas Company, Poplar, andBeckton Gas Works were damaged.[22337] d
(e) Public Buildings and Hospitals. Hornsey Road Police Station.Islington, was wrecked and the Ministry of Supply offices at Woolwich, andhospitals at Carshalton, Deptford, Poplar, East Ham, Woolwich, Bethnal Greenand Lewisham were damaged.(f) Service Property. R.A.O.C. Depot at Greenford, R.A.F. Stores atKidbrooke, the Naval College at Greenwich and barracks at Woolwich; were damaged.Casualties.73. For the week ending 0600 hrs. 19th March, casualties were estimated at,890 killed and 2,079 seriously injured, of which 548 killed and 626 seriously injured were on Merseyside (nights 12th/13th and 13th/14th) and 796 killed and620 seriously injured on Clydeside. The only other area to exceed 100 killed wasBristol 208 killed and 160 seriously injured.On the night of the 19th/20th the casualties in London are already knownto have been 208 killed and 366 seriously injured, many of which were the resultof direct hits on public shelters.
appendix  i.Enemy Attack on Trade.Merchant Vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages reported lost by enemy action.(Note. Tonnages are gross unless otherwise stated.)By Submarine.Date.	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	How sunk.	In Convoy or not.*	Position.	Fate of Crew and other Remarks.Mar. 7 ... Mar. 8 ... Mar. 8   ... Mar. 8 ... Mar. 8   ...	Mentor ... (3,050) Harmodius (5,229) Tielbank (5,084) Hindpool (4,897) Nardana (7,974)	Greek British British British British	Ballast Pig iron and general Pig iron and ground nuts Iron ore Pig iron, seeds and general	Cardiff Cochin Cocanada ... Popel Bombay   ...	Takoradi ... London Oban Oban London	Torpedo   ... Torpedo Torpedo   ... Torpedo   ... Torpedo   ...	Yes Yes Yes Yes Yes	About 580 miles W. of Butt of Lewis 205 miles W. of Cape Blanco 205 miles W. of Cape Blanco 205 miles W. of Cape Blanco 205 miles W. of Cape Blance	23 landed, 7 missing. European   crew   landed    Gibraltar. 11 lascars lost. All safe except 4 missing. 12 landed, 28 missing. All Euvopean crew safe except 3 en-gineer officers:	By Aircraft.								Mar. 13 ... Mar. 13 ... Mar. 14 ... Mar. 14 ... Mar. 14 .. Mar. 17 ..	Empire Frost ... (7,005) Perseus ... (1,307) Stanleigh (1,802) Artemisia (6,507) S/Drifter Peaceful Star (45) Einar Jarl (1,858)	British Dutch British British British Norwegian	Grain Fishing Ballast	Avonmouth March 12 Devonport... London Hull	Barrow Bahia Blanca Halifax	Bomb Torpedo Bomb Bomb Bomb Torpedo   ...	Not Not Yes Yes	Off Smalls   ...... Off Bardsey Island. 25  miles   N.W.   of Liverpool 12 miles E of Cramer Dimdalk Bay 10 miles N.E. of May Island	Was in tow of tug after being damaged by A/C on March 12, when again attacked by A/C and sunk.    (See last week&apos;s report on damaged ships.) 6 landed, 21 missing. 48 landed, 2 killed or missing. All saved. All safe except 1.co--a
By Mine.Name and tonnage.Nationality. &apos;   Cargo.Mar. 13 ...Tacoma City(4,738)Mar. 13 ... UUapool!   (4,891)Tug Dullger(270)Samlanes(S42)Nerport ...(2,633)BritishBritishBritishSteeltrucks andgeneralWheat ...Norwegian...! CoalBritishFrom-   i      To-How Sunk.New York ...HalifaxManchester&quot;LiverpoolSwansea  ..: Shoreham ..Methil     ...! LondonMineMineMineMineMineIn convoy or not.*Position.Yes.Not.Yes.By Surface Graft.Rant ailPandjang(2,542)Kenton ...(1,047)Dotterel......(1,385)Norman Queen...(957)Bye(1,048)DutchBritishBritishBritishBritishBallast ...General...Timber ...PortElizabethPooleSouthendSouthendLondonSabangTyneHullNorthernPortsGooleRaiderE-boatE-boatE-boatE-boatNot.Yes.Yes.Yes.Yes.Fate of Crew and other Remarks.River Mersey        ...1 17 landed and in hospital.   3 drowned.River Mersey ... 16 missing, 7 injured.Druridge Bay, N.W. \ All saved butinjured.of Tyne2  miles   S.  of  theLizard20   miles   N.W.   ofCromerNo survivors.33 landed, 5 missing.340  miles  S.W.  ofSeychellesOff Cromer ...10 miles E. of Yar-mouthOff CromerOff CromerNot known.14 landed, 4 missing.19 saved, 1 drowned, 7 missing.4 bodies picked up.2 bodies picked up.Note : Tanker Sovac (6,724) shown last week as presumed sunk under Section (A) has since arrived New York, and is now deleted from tonnage lost,trrj * This information is provisional and may be modified subsequently on receipt of Commodore&apos;s report.
Merchant vessels (excluding Commissioned Merchant Vessels) of all tonnages REPORTED damaged by Enemy Action.1 1 fc3      Dofp     !      Name and gg     Ucxte.          Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	Cause.	In convoy or not.*	Position.	Extent of Damage.	Casualties to Crew.   Other . Remarks.Mar. 10 ...! Libra    ...... (391) Mar. 11 ... S/Trawler Frodi (97) Mar. 11/12 Stella   ... (1,189) Mar. 11/12 Contractor (6,004) Mar. 11/12 Novelist...... (6,133) Mar. 11/12 Markhor (7,917) Mar. 11 ... Royal Star (7,900) Mar. 12 ... M/V Camroux I (324) Mar. 12 ... M/V Mr. Lind-horst Homan H                   (400)	Dutch Icelandic ... Swedish   ... British British British British British Dutch	Ballast ... Loading... Cables and general Ballast ... Coal	Clyde Reykjavik... Methil London Maryport ...	Swansea  .. Fleetwood... Clyde and Freemantle Blyth Plymouth ...	A/C. ... S/M....... A/C....... A/C....... A/C. ... A/C....... A/O....... M....... M.......	Not Yes Not Not	20 miles W. of St.      David&apos;s Head 200 miles S.E, of Reykjavik Manchester Manchester Manchester Manchester Off Stonehaven Off Biyth Near Lizard	Arrived    Swansea   in tow.     Engines  dis-placed Arrived Vestman Island in damaged condition Submerged at berth in Docks Engine room and holds flooded.    Being kept afloat by pumping Direct hit.    Consider-abie   damage   below deck ^Direct hit through fore deck. No. 1 hold leak-ing Near   miss;   requires dry docking. Minor damage.   Being docked Blyth Put into Penzance for inspection of damage	1 wounded. 5 killed. None reported. None reported. None reported. None reported. No casualties. No casualties. No casualties.
Date.Name and tonnage.Nationality.Cargo.   I    From-To-Mar. 12Mar. 12/13Mar. 12/13Mar. 13 ...Mar. .13 ...Mar. 13/14Mar. 13/14Mar. 14 ..Mar. 14 ..Mar. 14 ..Essex Lance   ...! British(6,625)M/V Myrmidon(6,278)M/V buenos aires(5,646)Ngatira ...(525)Mount Stewart(1,099)Glermiston(1,448)Trevarruck(5,270)Tug Mine Garth(179)Baron Elgin(3,942)M/V Tyr(4,265)WheatandFlourBritishSwedishjBritish     ... CoalBritishBritishBritishBritishBritishNorwegian...St. Johns,N.S.Newport   ...TeesImminghamLondonFalmouthU.S.A.Cause.	In Convoy       ,-,   ... , *        -Position, or not.   1 1 i		1    Casualties to Extent of Damage.        Crew.   Other Remarks.	A/C....... A/C....... A/C....... A/C....... A/C. ... A/C....... A/C....... A/C. ... A/C.......	Yes Not	Off Cromer Liverpool Docks Liverpool Docks Whitmore Bay, Bristol Channel Liverpool Glasgow Dalmuir Basin, River Clyde Liverpool At anchor in Methil Roads Humber L/V  ...	Engine room and stoke-hold flooded and beached. Lrter re-floated and left Cromer in tow Mar. 17 Submerged Had fire on board Engine room  flooded. Beached but later re-floated    and   towed into Barry Dock. Hit   by  bomb   No.   3 hatch. Much damage in hold where bomb exploded. Submerged Nos. 1, 2, 4 and 5 holds flooded.    Vessel has list of 450 Holed, making water ... Damaged.   Extent not yet known Towed   back  to   Im-mhigh am	2 injured, 1 died later. None reported. None reported. 1 wounded. None reported. None reported. None reported, None reported. 1 injured. None reported.
Date.Name and tonnage.Nationality.CargcFrom To-Cause.! In Convoyi  or not.*Position.Extent of Damage.Casualties to crew.   OtherRemarks.Mar. 14Mar. 15Mar. 15Mar. 15Mar. 16Mar. 16Mar. 16Mar. 16Mar. 16&apos;Mar. 16Mar. 16Tanker Orwell ...! Norwegian(7,920)Tug Warrior(249)Korshamn(6,673)M/V Eminent ...(500)Elmae  ...(1,174)M/V TankerPerm(6,593)M/V ChileanReefer(1,739)Tanker Venetia(5,728)M/V TankerFranche Comte(9,314)J. B. White    ...(6,869)Southgate(4,862)BritishSwedishBelgianSteel andgeneralNorwegian   j CoalNorwegian  jiIBritish     ...!BritishBritishBritishBritishNew York ..MaryportCardiffNew York...TyneBaltimoreTrinidadSt. Johns,N.B.ObanLiverpool ...Plymouth ...Plymouth ..ClydeSt. Johns,N.B.Loch Ewe.ClydeManchesterHalifaxA/C. ..M.    ..S/M.T.Mine ..M.     ..S/M.T.RaiderS/M.T.S/M.T.S/M.T.RaiderNot yet known...* This information is provisional and may be modified subsequentlo on receipt of Commodore&apos;s report.YesNotYesNotYesYesYesNotLiverpoolEntrance toRiver Cart,Clyde350 miles N.W.of Butt of Lewis28 miles   S.W.of St. David&apos;sHead18   miles   S.W.Lundy   Island240 miles N.W.Butt of Lewis300 miles E. ofNewfoundland240 miles N.W.Butt of Lewis240 miles N.W.Butt of Lewis...! 240 miles N.W.Butt of LewisI300 miles east of Newfound-landHad fire on boardBeached at Renfrew.Not yet known...Not yet known...May have sunk.Badly damaged. Tugsent to assist. Possi-bility salvage fair.Shelled. Believed sunk.II.M. Ship standing by.Tug sent to assist.Proceeding own power at 4 knots.H.M. Ship standing by.Tugs to assistance.None reported.None serious.11 picked up.Crew landed.19  landed.   1missing.Survivors in H.M.Ship.26 in H.M. Ships.Survivors in H.M.Ship.Survivors in H.M.Ship.Survivors in II.M.Ship.Not yet known.
Date. Mar. 16 ... Mar. 17 ... Mar. 17 ... Mar. 18 ... Mar. 18 ... Mar. 18 ... Mar. 18 ... Mar. 19 ...	Name and Tonnage.	Nationality.	Cargo.	From 	To-	Cause.	In Convoy or not.*	Position.	Extent of Damage.	Casualties to Crew.   Other Remarks.	Demerterton   ... (5,251) i Gormead (2,848) Ta-panoeli (7,031) Daphne II (1,970) Clan Maclver ... (4,500) Clan Macnah   ... (6,076) M/V Tanker Beduin Mandolina (7,750)	British British Dutch British British British Norwegian... Dutch	General... General... Ground nuts and iron Gasolene Sugar   ...	Mersey Batavia London Glasgow   ... Bombay   ... Aruba Batavia	Flalif ax Glasgow  ... Tyne Table Bay... Clyde Clyde Belfast    ...	Raider A/C....... S/M.T. E-Boat S/M.T. S/M.T. S/M.T. S/M.T.	Not Yes Yes Yes Yes     ... Yes     ... Yes Yes	300o   East    of Newfoundland Thames Estuary 110 miles East of Cape Verde Is. 15 miles N.N.W. of Cromer 600 miles West of Butt of Lewis 260 miles West of Cape Verde 190 miles N.W. of Butt of Lewis 280 miles S.W. of Cape Blanco	Not yet known... Anchored     Yarmouth Roads. Engine Room partly flooded. Not yet known... Beached  Humber   18 Mar. Not yet known... Not yet known.   Crew taking to boats Tug  to   assist;   stern half still afloat Not yet known...	Not yet known. No casualties. Not yet known. 2 injured. Not yet known. Not yet known. Not yet known. Not yet known.Note.-The following ships previously reported damaged have now been transferred to Section (A) &quot;as lost: Kent on (British) 1,057; Dotterel (British) 1,385; NormanQueen (British) 957.
APPENDIX II.Merchant Ships (all sizes) other than Merchant Ships Commissioned for naval service, lost by Enemy Action up to Noon, Wednesday, 19th March, 1941.	British.	Allied.		Neutral.		Together.&apos;     By-	XT          Gross No.           m Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	Gross No.   &apos;     m i    Tons.Submarine   ... Mine ... Surface Craft Aircraft Other causes, or cause unknown	335 ! 1,885,000 187      464,000 92 ! 459,000 149 1    437,000 35 \      77,000	1 80 i    385,000 35 !    101,000 24 &apos;    155,000 59      252,000 8        38,000 i		176 79 6 29 9	570,000 232,000 18,000 79,000 30,000	591    2,840,000 301 :    797.000 122 !    632,000 237 i    768,000 52      145,000	798 i 3,322,000 i   206		931,000     299 i    929,000			1,303    5,182,000Note.-&quot; Allied &quot; figures include Polish; all French up to June 25, 1940; &quot; Free &quot; french from June 25, 1940; Norwegian from April 9, 1940; Dutch and Belgian from May 10, 1940; and greek from October 28, 1940. &quot;Neutral&quot; figures include Italian up to June 10, 1940; and&quot; Vichy &quot; French from June 25, 1940.APPENDIX III.(1) Additions to and deductions from British Sea-going Merchant Tonnage(ships of S00 gross tons and over), including Merchant Ships commissioned for Naval Service from 2nd September, 1939, to 16th March, 1941.	Tankers.		Others.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.British ships on September 2, 1939 Additions  New ships         ...        ... Enemy ships captured ...       ...       ... Ships transferred from other flags  Danish        ...       ...       ... French Roumanian ... Estonian Latvian Others Other additions ... Total additions   ... Deductions  Ships sunk by the enemy-(i) Merchant   ships   commissioned,  for Naval Service ^ii) Others    ...       ...       .;.       ...       .L Ships captured by the enemy ... Other deductions (including Marine Risk)  (i) Commissioned for Naval Service (ii) Others Total deductions Net additions (J-) or deductions (-) ... British ships on March 16, 1941    ...       ...	519	3,274,000	3,578	15,392,000	15 1 8 10 2 12 11	122,000 6,000 66,000 57,000 11,000 83,000 16,000	191 53 114 81 o 21 3 134 91	1,053,000 275,000 304,000 374,000 8,000 35,000 6,000 709,000 183,000	59	361,000	690	2,947,000	2 70 1 -    2 9	13,000 550,000 6,000 2,000 43,000	24 596 5 7 150	212,000 2,721,000 16,000 33,000 520,000	84,	614,000 \	782	3,502,000	- 25	- 253,000	-   92	-  555,000&apos;	494	3,021,000	3,486	14,837,000** Of the total N-on-T-anker tonnage, vessels representing about 3,950 thousand gross tons andengaged on Naval, Military or R.A.F. Services (including some commissioned for Naval Service),,some of which tiring cargoes to the United Kingdom on their homeward voyage. after allowing for vessels (1) trading permanently abroad, (2) detained in French ports and (3) under-going or awaiting repair, including the fitting of defensive protection, the balance is about million gross tons, some part of which is engaged in the coasting trade of the UnitedKingdom and Eire.[22337] F
(2) Total losses of, and other deductions from, British Sea-going Merchant ships of 500 gross tons and over, including Merchant Ships Commissioned for naval Service, expressed as approximate annual rates of loss.Period.(1)Total losses sunk or captured by the enemy,and other deductions inthe period.(2)Approximate annual loss if column (2) losses continued for a year.(3)First 9 months of war :i.e., from September 3, 1939, to May 31, 1940Following 3 months :i.e., from June 1, 1940, to August 31, 1940Month of September, 1940October, 1940 ...November, 1940December, 1940January, 1941February 19411st to 16th March, 1941 ...Gross Tons.1,098.000971,000339,000317,000373,000330,000207,000337,000138,000*Gross Tons.1,500,0003,900,0004,100,0003,700,0004,500,0004,000,0002,400,0004,400,0003,100,000* These figures relate to losses so far notified and may be increased by later notifications.(3) Merchant Ships (all sizes) under Construction in British Yards in the UnitedKingdom and abroad in week ending 14th March, 1941.Colliers and coasting ships other ships ...Tankers.No.        Gross Tons.5 3,00038 314,000Others.No. Gross Tons.39 49,000126* 813,00043317,000165862,000* Including 5 vessels (33,000 gross tons) building abroad, 2 merchant ships (18,000 grosstons) taken over by the Navy during construction and 11 ships (20,000 gross tons) of merchant type intended for Naval use.In addition, there are 179 merchant ships totalling 1,178,000 gross tons on order or proposedto order in the United Kingdom and abroad (including 16 tankers of 108,000 gross tons).APPENDIX IV.Merchant Ships (all sizes) lost by the enemy up to 18th March, 1941.	German.		Italian.		Together.		No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.	No.	Gross Tons.Captured or seized Scuttled or sunk  ... Unidentified ships reported by S/M, A/C, &amp;c, as sunk or  destroyed   (tonnage estimated)	61 78 135	274,000 431,000 675,000	38 39 71	180,000 239,000 355,000	99 117 206	454,000 670,000 1,030,000	274	1,380,000	148	774,000	422	2,154,000In addition, 34 ships of 60,000 gross tons under enemy control or useful to the enemy havebeen sunk.
Casualties to H.M. Auxiliary vessels and to Naval Personnel.The following casualties have occurred to H.M. Auxiliary Patrol vessels during the week under review : March 14. Minesweeping Trawler Jeannie Leash damaged by a mine southof Harwich and beached.March  17. Examination  Yacht  Mollusc  bombed  and sunk  off  Blyth.M.G.B. 42 damaged by mine off Penzance and beached.March 16. A/S  Trawler Lady  Lilian bombed and  sunk  in  western approaches and A/S Trawler King Sol slightly damaged.March 19. A/A Ship Helvellyn bombed and sunk in Surrey CommercialDocks during the air raid on London.The following casualties to Naval personnel have been reported : Officers : killed 2, missing 4, wounded 5.Ratings : killed 60, missing 10, wounded 69.APPENDIX YI.Operational Aircraft Battle Casualties.0600 hrs., 13th March, 1941, to 0600 hrs., 20th March, 1941.Metropolitan Area.British, In the Air. On the Ground.Bombers...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 8Fighters ... ...       ...       ...       ... 5Coastal   ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 2Total............ 15 nil3 Fighter pilots safe.probably german. Destroyed.        Destroyed. Damaged.Bombers    ............ 18 5 12Fighters     ...        ....... 7 3 miscellaneous       ...       ...       ... 16 3 9Total      ...... 41 11 22No account is taken of aircraft destroyed on the ground.Of the above, 8 aircraft were destroyed, 1 probably destroyed, and 8 damaged byA.A. fire.Middle East.British. In the Air. On the Groxind.Bombers...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 6 fighters ...       ...       ...       ...       ...       ... 4 1CoastalTotal............ 10 2ProbablyItalian. Destroyed.            Destroyed.            Damaged.Bombers ...       ...       ...       ... 9                           2                         fighters............ 23                           miscellaneous     ......... 9                           2                         5Total    ...... 41                         7                       10German.Bombers ...       ...       ... ,*Fighters   ...       ...       ... miscellaneous     ...       ...       .-- 4Total    ...       ... 8                       Nil                     NilOf the above, 4 fighters were destroyed oy A.A. fire.[22335] gAPPENDIX Y.
APPENDIX YII.Air Attacks on Enemy Territory in Europe.Extracts from Recent Raid Assessment Reports.The following reports of damage have been received during the past week from air reconnaissance and Intelligence sources : Germany.Bremen. Photographs disclose the following damage to the Focke-WulfWorks : (i) a crater near the assembly jig building; (ii) the long shed on thenorth side of the factory has several bays wrecked; (iii) severe damage to the roof of a large workshop; and (iv) many craters scattered over the works and the aerodrome area.Four large warehouses on the river bank have been completely burnt out.Hanover. Photographs taken on the 12th and 14th March disclose the major damage the town has suffered. Details cover three pages of the interpre-tation report and disclose heavy damage, on occasion to whole blocks of buildings,both industrial and residential. The endeavours that have been made to effectrepairs and clear sites are apparent.   The principal features are : (a) Two very large buildings at the Continental Gummiwerke A.G. have had their roofs completely stripped off and the fifth floors destroyed. Asmall triangular building behind has been gutted and the stationbuildings of the Guterbahnhof Nord have been damaged. The roofof the engine sheds, which must have been severely damaged, has beenrepaired.(b) The centre of an area bounded by the Schanfelder, Slunder and RehbockStrassen has been laid waste as a result of high explosive and firescaused by incendiary bombs.(c) The extent of the repairs to the roof of the Haupt-Bahnhof shows the considerable damage that must have been caused thereto.id) The housing estate at Kleefeld on the Eastern outskirts suffered consider-ably and whole blocks of houses have been gutted.(e) An area west of the Sportplatz was considerably damaged.(/) There is a crater in the Hermann Goring Platz.Cologne. Consequent upon the raids of the 1st/2nd and 3rd/4th march the city water supply was severely affected and for three days the water shortagewas acute. It is said that the Water Works was severely damaged. The mainline from Cologne to Dusselclorf received direct hits.Mannheim. The photographs of Mannheim taken on the 21st December,1940, have been examined by a railway expert. The photographs do not show&apos;anyactual damage to the marshalling yards, but the fullness of the sidings show whatimmense damage must have been caused in the neighbouring yards.(i) The&apos; sidings for westbound traffic are absolutely full,  and this isattributed to (a) Damage to the Mannheim-Ludwigshafen bridge.(b) Lack of locomotive power due to damage at or outside thelocomotive shed.(c) Inability  to  despatch   wagons  to  the  port  of  neighbouringindustrial sidings.(ii) The sidings  for  eastbound  traffic  are  also over-full,  and  this  isattributed to (a) Damage at Pheinau port.(b) Lack of locomotive power due to damage at or outside the shed.(c) Damage to the hump separating arrival and despatch sidings andits braking machinery.
(iii) Reports showed that after the raid there was a failure of the water and electric supply. This failure would bring work in the marshalling yard to a standstill since the braking machinery is operatedhydraulically and the point control is electric.(iv) Normally the Mannheim yard can deal with 7,000 wagons in 24 hours and the average time taken by a wagon to pass the yard is 8 hours,25 minutes.   At the end of December this time must have been increased to about seven da)rs.(v) The congestion and delay thus caused were cumulative and far-reaching,producing (among others) the following results : (a) The yards at Basle (160 miles away) became blocked.(&amp;) Coal from  the Ruhr to Italy had to be diverted and sentthroughout by rail as it could not be sent up the Rhine toMannheim.   The coal movements through Mannheim were not expected to be normal until March.(c) At the end of February, Ludwigshafen was refusing bauxite fromSplit in Yugoslavia &quot; because of transport difficulties.&quot;Munich. The well-known restaurant Bauerngirgl received a direct hit onthe 8th/9th November.   The repairs took two months.Hamm. An indication of the damage to the marshalling yard has beenreceived from a recent article in Transoc&amp;an protesting against our claims tohave effected damage and that photographs recently published in our Press werefakes. The article points out that the last effective attack by a large number of aircraft was on the 26th September. On the 11th November neutral journalistswho were flown over the marshalling yard at a low height were unable to see any damage. Two points are noteworthy: (i) the interval of time before thejournalists&apos; visit was permitted, and (ii) that even then it was not a groundinspection which would have enabled them to deduct where repairs had been effected.General. The replacement of unreliable Czech employees at the SkodaWorks by Germans has been facilitated by the damage to Krupps at Essen, whichhas enabled a number of their workmen to be released for the purpose.France.In the raid on the aerodrome at Chartres on the 8th/9th December seven aircraft were destroyed or severely damaged and ten of the personnel were killed.








</content>
</cab>
