<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>cab 68/9/33 images: 316-333</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the War Cabinet.   July 1942.SECRET. Copy No.   74W.P. (R) (42) 33.July 22. 1942.WAR CABINET.REPORT FOR THE MONTH OF JUNE 1942 FOR THE DOMINIONS,INDIA, BURMA, AND THE COLONIES AND mandated territories.THE DOMINIONS.Report by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.CANADA.General Position.1. The conclusion of the treaty between the United Kingdom and theUS.S.R. came as a great surprise to Canadians, and caused a profound sensation.The treaty was almost unanimously welcomed, only Roman Catholic opinion,with its condemnation of Communism, being collectively unfavourable. the alliance was widely interpreted as a guarantee that the ideals of the atlantic charter would come to be realised in the post-war world.2. For the greater part of June the attitude of the Canadian public to thewar generally was one of unrealistic optimism. The uniformly favourableinterpretation placed on events at the beginning of that month led the GlobeMail to write : &quot; There is little to complain of in the progress of events in europe and Africa.&quot; News of the fighting in Russia and Libya was presented in such away that the Allies appeared to be making swift progress in both theatres ofwar : comment on the Burma campaign and on China&apos;s desperate position didlittle to remove the impression of Allied military success. Anglo-United StatesStaff talks, and the later announcement of signed agreements between the UnitedKingdom and the U.S.A., evoked favourable comment and a general feeling ofsatisfaction as regards the production of war materials, and the early prospectof a &quot; second front &quot; became evident. The R.A.F. raid on Cologne was greetedwith enthusiasm as yet another sign of Allied supremacy. This somewhatcomplacent attitude received a rude shock with the fall of Tobruk and the news from Sebastopol. The seriousness of the position was thereafter recognised, andcritical comment has since followed the same general lines as in this country,although less angry in tone.3. Domestic politics have resulted in a state of crisis ever since the11th May, when the Bill to amend the National Resources Mobilization Act was first read. The second reading was moved on the 10th June by the PrimeMinister, and though the indications are that his handling of the situation willhold the Government together and fend off any more resignations from theCabinet, the political barometer is still set at &quot; stormy.&quot; Mr. Mackenzie King&apos;sopening speech effectively took the wind out of the Opposition^ sails, byemphasising the enabling nature of the legislation. He pointed out that theGovernment policy was not to introduce conscription now, but only if, and when,[24121] B
it became necessary for the security of Canada and for the maintenance ofCanada&apos;s war effort. By postponing the issue in this way. the Prime minister may be able to steer his course between the extreme views of the Conservativeson the one hand and the French-Canadians on the other. Except in Quebec,where the question is still one of acute controversy, the public show signs ofboredom with the whole conscription issue.4. In industrial matters, the dispute in the British Columbia shipyardswith the Department of Labour continues. The Department is attempting, inthe face of strong Union opposition, to force, through a policy of a 7-day weekand a 24-hour day.Naval, Military a/id Air Activities.5. The latest report available concerning the activities of the royal canadian Navy refers to the month of May. During this month there was somelessening of U-boat activity along the Atlantic seaboard, but attacks increased in the Caribbean and the Gulf of Mexico.6. Four corvettes, four mine-sweepers and seven Fairmile motor launcheswere commissioned during the month.7. A Canadian joint staff has been formed in Washington, comprisingMajor-General Pope, who will act as Chairman and has been designated repre-sentative at Washington of the Canadian Chiefs of Staff, Rear-Admiral Brodeurand Air Vice Marshal Walshe.8. With the exception of the two army co-operation squadrons and two others which are in process of formation, all Royal Canadian Air Force squadrons in the United Kingdom were engaged in operations. No. 401 (Spitfire) Squadronwas credited with five enemy aircraft destroyed, and a flight-sergeant of this squadron was awarded the Distinguished Flying Medal. No. 403 (Spitfire)Squadron, during a fighter sweep on the 2nd. was attacked by more than40 German fighters and lost six pilots and seven aircraft; two of the enemy fighters were destroyed. One flight-lieutenant was awarded the DistinguishedFlying Cross during the month. No. 405 Squadron, newly equipped wdth Halifaxbombers, completed ten long-range operations of an average duration of about fivehours. Four aircraft were lost during these flights. No. 407 (Hudson) Squadronmade 15 attacks on shipping during the month, obtaining hits in most cases. Thefirst French-Canadian squadron, No. 425, equipped with Wellingtons, is nowbeing formed.COA1MONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA.General Position.9. The general atmosphere of optimism, which persisted until theannouncement that Tobruk had fallen, gave way to criticism of the sort whichhas appeared in this country and elsewhere. The general&apos; tone of the press comment on this unexpected disaster was set by the Prime Minister, whodeprecated fault finding, and expressed the &quot; highest admiration and gratitudefor the fighting forces of the United Nations m every theatre of the war.&quot;Nevertheless, there have inevitably been unfavourable criticisms of the leadership of the campaign in Libya, and much resentment over misleading communiquesand lack of adequate equipment. Moreover, Australians were quick to note thedifference between the gallant stand of their troops during last y7ear&apos;s siege of tobruk. and the haste to surrender the place after a one-day battle during thepresent campaign. .&quot; Wars are won by winning battles, not by counting headsor adding up resources,&quot; was one comment.10. Dr. Evatt&apos;s successful mission reassured Australians that the South-West Pacific was not being ignored by the United Kingdom Government, and dr. Evatt himself said that the period of difficult relations between the twoGovernments had ended.11. The destruction of Japanese submarines in Sydney harbour produced a feeling of confidence in the readiness of the local defences, and the continuance ofcompletely ineffective attacks by Japanese submarines on the coastal cities ofNew South Wales is generally disregarded.
12. Enthusiasm at United States successes at Midway, and Dutch Harbour,was later restrained by the knowledge that the main Japanese fleet had not been attacked, but the action helped to create the impression that at last theAllies had taken the offensive. The R.A.F. raid on Cologne, which was eagerlyfollowed, aroused great admiration and many tributes for the organisation andstrength of our forces, while the Anglo-United States agreements seemed topoint to the early opening of a second front in Europe.13. Egypt, however, now overshadows all other topics, and fears are expressed that the opening of the second front will, in consequence of the Libyanreverses, be deferred, and that reinforcements for India and the Pacific will beheld up.14. In the Russian campaign, the German successes in the Crimea and theCaucasus damped down the optimism produced by early Russian successes, butthe defence of Sebastopol aroused universal admiration. The Anglo-Russiantreaty was generally welcomed, although it came in for some criticism in the roman Catholic press.15. The principal item of domestic interest has been the progress of the 35 million loan. The poor response caused the Government grave concern, but after an appeal by the Prime Minister to &quot; large and small investors who haveneglected their responsibilities.&quot; the situation improved and the loan has nowbeen fully subscribed.16. The Commonwealth Government&apos;s proposal to make income tax uniformfor all parts of Australia, which had been rejected by the State Premiers inApril (see report for the 26th May) was brought into effect by the UniformTaxation Act. The Commonwealth Government claim that the measure isnecessary in the interests of the total war effort and that its opponents are placedin the position of upholding State rights and sovereignty at the expense ofAustralia. The State GoArernments are appealing to the High Court against thelegislation.17. Industrial unrest is again serious. The Government seems to have abandoned the idea of coercing coalminers and to have resigned themselves tostrikes as &quot; a necessary evil &quot; in the industry.Naval, Military and Air Activities.18. Rear-Admiral V. A. C. Crutchley. V.C., assumed duty as Rear-admiral commanding the Australian Squadron and Commander of Task Force 44 on the13th June.19. Two mine-sweepers and a loop-laying vessel were commissioned andthree mine-sweepers were launched during June.20. Portions of two of the Japanese midget submarines, which attackedshipping in Sydney harbour on the 31st May, have been recovered from the bottom of the harbour.21. As a result of enemy submarine activity off the east coast of Australia,a system of convoys has been started, and other measures have been taken for the better protection of shipping.22. Major-General Morris, Australian Staff * Corps, has been givencommand of all Australian and United States Army, Navy and Air Forces in new Guinea with the title of Commander of New Guinea Force. This force hasbeen strengthened by an additional infantry brigade and some anti-aircraft units.23. United States forces in Australia at the end of June exceeded 88,000,of whom about 60,000 are ground troops.24. The 9th Australian Division left Syria for the Egyptian front at theend, of the month.25. Throughout the month, air reconnaissances were continued over new guinea, Solomon Islands, New Britain and Timor areas; protection was providedfor overseas and inter-State convoys and for shipping in local areas.   Extensive[24121] b 2
anti-submarine patrols were carried out, two enemy submarines being destroyedby aircraft and others damaged.26. Enemy aircraft made several attacks on Port Moresby and Darwin withbomber formations escorted by fighters; interceptions resulted in several enemy aircraft being destroyed.NEW ZEALAND.General Position.27. Until it became evident that the situation in Libya was very serious, theattention of the people of New Zealand had been mainly concentrated on theFar Eastern theatre. Doubts about this country&apos;s appreciation of the dangersfaced by New Zealand gradually gave way to a feeling of confidence that theimmediate threat had passed, and that it had. become too expensive for japan to indulge in naval adventures as far South as New Zealand. The &quot; momentousvictory &quot; in the Midway battle was highly encouraging, while the arrival of theUnited States force at a South Pacific port increased the feeling of security.Interest in the Libyan campaign had been only slight as it was known that no new Zealand troops were engaged there, and the shock engendered by the suddenfall of Tobruk, and the rapid subsequent withdrawal of the Eighth Army, wastremendous. The arrival of seasoned New Zealand troops in the front linebrought the Egyptian operations again into the forefront of the news, and thepublic is now beginning to show deep anxiety regarding the outcome of the battleand for the fate of the New Zealand troops. It was almost inevitable that the sudden loss of Tobruk should have brought about most unfavourable comparisonsbetween the fighting qualities of the troops which garrisoned it, and of the AnzacsAvho had successfully withstood an intense siege of the same place for seven longmonths.28. Less intense interest has been shown in the fighting in Russia, althoughthe defence of Sebastopol aroused great admiration.29. The treaty between the United Kingdom and Russia was warmly welcomed, by all sections of the public, more importance being attached to immediate results in the form of improved political relations and closer military co-operation-operation than in possible long-term results.30. The Prime Minister and the Leader of the Opposition discussedproposals to reorganise the New Zealand War Cabinet on non-Party lines, andthese proposals were submitted to the Labour Party caucus on the 24th June. Asa result, the formation of a &quot; War Administration &quot; has been announced,together with the introduction of a Bill for the extension of the life of the present parliament for the duration of the war. and for a period, after the war notexceeding 12 months. &apos;31. The &quot; War Administration &quot; consists of the existing War Cabinet,and eight others, drawn equally from the Labour Party and the National Party,including Mr. McLagan, President of the Federation of Labour, who is Ministerfor Industrial Man-power. The War Cabinet, of seven members, four from theLabour Party, and three from the National Party, will act as the executive bodyof the War Administration, while the present Cabinet will continue to function in respect of purely domestic matters not connected, with the war.32. The proposal to form a War Administration had a lukewarm receptionfrom the New Zealand public, although the restriction of party politics implied by this new development is welcomed. But it is widely believed to be a compromiseto cover the failure of the various parties to agree upon a full coalition government.Naval, Military and Air Activities.33. Admiral Ghormley, United States Navy, assumed command of theSouth Pacific Area on the 19th June, from which date vessels of the Royal NewZealand Navy came under his orders.34. H.M.N.Z.S. Leander and Achilles were engaged in escort duties in the&apos;South Pacific area.
35. The 2nd New Zealand Division moved up into action on the Matruhposition during the last week of the month and thenceforward was in actionalmost continuously in this locality and later on in the southern sector of theEl Alamein position.36. The 3rd Army Tank Battalion in Newr Zealand is now fully equipped with infantry tanks and the 1st Battalion is two-thirds complete.37. . A further 23.000 men, principally in the 32-34 age group, married with children, were called up on the 24th June.38. All members of the armed forces, except the Home Guard, are nowliable for service overseas if required.39. The relief of New Zealand forces in Eiji by United States forces hasstarted and, with a few exceptions, is expected to be completed by the end ofAugust.40. Patrol work by aircraft from New Zealand has been carried outregularly.41. At the request of the Admiral Commanding Air Forces of the SouthPacific Area,, one flight of Hudsons has been detached from the Fiji Squadron to operate in New Caledonia.UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA.General Position.42. The announcement by the Government that Union troops had taken part in the Madagascar operation aroused considerable discussion early in June.Government followers agreed with General Smuts that the danger to the Unionjustified the despatch of these troops, although it might be considered technicallya breach of his pledge. The Opposition, however, were bitterly critical and considered the Prime Minister had been guilty of deceit in co-operating in the attack on the island.43. From the beginning of the present campaign in Libya, Governmentopinion has been cautious, and optimism has been discouraged. The unexpectedfall of Tobruk and later set-backs, coupled with the capture of South african troops, have, despite insinuations regarding the Union General who wras in command at Tobruk, had a very depressing effect, and both Government and opposition circles have been critical of United Kingdom leadership.44. Afrikaans opinion has for some time been uneasy about the subordina-tion of South African forces to United Kingdom commanders, and the reversesin Libya tend to make that opinion more and more critical. The Governmentpress generally directed its criticism to past mistakes rather than to speculationabout the possibility of political changes in the United Kingdom.45. The Opposition followed their usual line of criticising General Smutsand his war policy, and pointed to the slaughter of Union manhood in north africa as one of its results. General Smuts&apos;s appeal to fill in the gap in theUnion divisions, caused by the Libyan disasters, was strongly attacked, and dr. Malan, leader of the Nationalist Opposition, demanded a special session ofParliament to discuss the war situation.46. Although Government circles gave a warm welcome to the newlyappointed Russian consular staff on their arrival, the Opposition attacked thewhole Government policy of exchanging consular representatives with theU.S.S.R., on the ground that there is no work for a Russian consul &quot;if heconfines himself to his proper tasks.&quot; Some circles in the Union feel that to opendirect relations now with the U.S.SR. would result in the spreading of com-communism, and point, in this connexion, to the &apos;&apos; dangerously ripe field &apos;&apos; presented by the natives. Government followers welcomed the Anglo-Russian Treaty asmarking the end of twenty years of suspicion and misunderstanding, but theOpposition view is that the opening of a second front is a high price to pay for the alliance, and thatj as soon as the common danger which threatens the two countries
EIRE.56. The Minister for Finance has announced that he is preparing for theissue of another loan which will amount to at least  5 million, in view of theextent of the budget deficit for the current year. It is quite possible, however,that a considerably larger sum will be borrowed considering the favourable conditions in the capital market. The last loan issued by the Eire Governmentwas floated at a fraction over 3  per cent., and was heavily oversubscribed.57. Speaking in the Dail on the 24th June on the problem of reducedsupplies from Britain, Mr. Lemass, the Minister of Supplies, said that there wasno point in disguising the fact that Eire&apos;s bargaining power was practically nil.Production of butter and bacon had fallen to such a point that they were inadequate for home requirements. The suggestion that he or some other minister should discuss matters personally with British Ministers in London implied thatthe curtailment of supplies was due to British ministerial decisions dictated by political considerations or reasons other than Britain&apos;s own war-time need.58. Speaking in the Dail during the last week in June, Mr. Flinn, Parlia-mentary Secretary, Ministry of Finance, said that there was in Eire a serious fuelcrisis.   The critical nature of the problem was, he said, founded on shortage ofdisappears, the treaty will disappear also. In particular, the Eussian under-taking not to intervene in the internal affairs of other countries must, it is said,be taken with &quot; a pinch of salt.&apos;&quot;47. Lord Selborne&apos;s recent suggestion in the House of Lords that an imperial Parliament might meet in Cape Town aroused some comment generallyunfavourable, the trend of Union opinion towards independence rather thantowards &quot;organic union &quot; being emphasised.48. The preliminary trial on a charge of high treason has now begun offorty-eight members of the Ossewa Brandwag. Revelations of the preparations for an &quot;armed coup cVEtat are said to have acutely disturbed the ossewa brandwag.49. Intensive and open rivalry is now developing between the ossewa brandwag, the Nationalists and the Afrikaner party for the support of theAfrikaans-speaking soldiers, who are expected to return from the war&quot;disillusioned and critical.&apos;&apos;Naval, Military and Air Activities.50. It has been decided to combine the Seaward Defence Force and the royal naval Volunteer Reserve with effect from the 1st August into a new unit to be known as the Union Naval Service.51. At the beginning of the month, the 1st South African Division wasoccupying the El Gazala position, where it held its ground against attack untilordered to withdraw on the 13th. It was then repeatedly in action during thevarious phases of our withdrawal until being re-established at El Alamein.52. The 2nd South African Division fell back on Tobruk, where it was captured with the remainder of the garrison on the 20th.53. The two South African Air Force Boston squadrons carried out intensiveoperations in Libya and Egypt throughout the month, maintaining a high standard of serviceability and rendering valuable support while sustaining fewcasualties.54. South African Air Force units arrived at Diego Suarez shortly after itsoccupation by British forces, and have since been carrying out coastal recon-naissance work. An aerial shuttle service between the Union and Madagascarhas also been established.55. There is now accommodation in Union military hospitals for 12,500lying cases; more than 4,000 of these are for the use of the United KingdomGovernment and nearly 1,000 for prisoners of war.
transport and a shortage of men in the places where the Government desiredheavy turf production. Migration of labour was seriously contributing to the crisis and the country in 1943 would probably feel grievously the loss of the menwho had gone. Mr. Flinn said that high wages in Britain were responsible forthe greater part of migration, and that these wages earned by the labourers werereturning to Eire to eat up available vital supplies.59. On the 9th June it was announced that clothes were to be rationed in eire as from that date. While it was declared that the measure was a preeau-tionary one introduced to preserve the existing stocks against the inroads offoreign purchasers, the extent of the control was even more severe in many respectsthan in the United Kingdom. There were strong protests from the clothing-traders in Eire against the scheme as a result of which the number of coupons was increased by 50 per cent. Protests still continued, and following a demonstrationby employees in Dublin, Mr. Lemass received a deputation, after which it was announced that an Advisory Committee would be appointed to consider possiblemodifications of the scheme.60. The City of Bremen with a cargo of wheat on board was reported sunk off the Spanish Coast on the 8th June. Twenty-two survivors were landed at Vigoby a Spanish fishing vessel. On the 12th June the Eire Information Bureauissued a statement to the effect that the Master of the City of Bremen had reportedthat the loss of his vessel was due to attack by German aircraft and that the EireCharge d&apos;Affaires in Berlin had been instructed to &quot; protest energetically &quot; tothe German Government and claim full compensation for the loss of the ship and her cargo.61. On the 18th June, Mr. Boland, the Minister for Justice, was asked inthe Dail for names of the persons who harboured Hans Marchner, the Naziparachutist, after his escape from custody. In reply, the Minister said the onlypersons against whom allegations were made were Mrs. and Miss Brugha, the widow and daughter of Carl Brugha, who was shot dead during the fighting in dublin in 1922.   He added that Miss Brugha had been interned.62. On the 17th June, Stephen Hayes, described as Chief of Staff of theIrish Republican Army, was sentenced by the Special Criminal Court to five yearspenal servitude on a charge of having &quot; unlawfully usurped and exercisedfunctions of Government.&quot; Hayes had been in custody since he escaped, in Dublinin September 1941, from the custody of the Irish Republican Army, by whom hehad been sentenced to death as a traitor. While in Mount joy Prison, &quot;Hayes had written a letter which was intercepted by the police and which constituted theevidence on which he was charged. The principal feature in the letter was the disclosure of plans made to smuggle Sean Russell, Commander-in-Chief of theIrish Republican Army to Germany. It stated that Russell was to have beenconveyed from America in an Italian ship bound for Genoa in April 1940, butthat after he had been put aboard no further news -was received of him. Hayes,who stated that he had been Acting Chief of Staff up to the time that he waskidnapped by the Irish Republican Army, said he had written the letter to refutesome of the charges made against him. At the trial he refused to plead, to give evidence, or to call witnesses.INDIA.Report by the Secretary of State for India.Political Situation.63. The comparative lull in the political situation persisted throughout themonth. Rajagopalachariar continued his campaign for Hindu-Moslem unity and towards the end of June had long interviews with both Jinnah and Gandhi,but so far it does not appear that he has achieved substantial success or seriously affected the attitude of Congressmen towards the dictates of the working committee. An interesting development in the Provinces was the conclusion ofa pact between the Moslem Premier of the Punjab and a prominent Sikh leaderdesigned to secure a communal truce between Moslems and Sikhs for the duration
of the war. This is a positive contribution to communal solidarity in the partof India from which the army is chiefly drawn.64. Among political leaders the activities, or rather the utterances, of gandhi continued to attract most attention, as he would himself desire. Butthe threat of a mass civil disobedience or other movement in prosecution of hisslogan that the British must withdraw did not materialise, and it remains tobe seen whether the Congress Party at its meetings early in July will give him the necessary support. Several prominent leaders, including Nehru and theCongress President, ai&apos;e believed to be critical of a campaign which is bound tohelp the enemy, and this division of opinion seems to be reflected in thebewildering variety of statements put out by Gandhi in interpretation of earlierpronouncements for example, that British withdrawal means renunciation ofpolitical power and not physical withdrawal from India. Gandhi&quot;s possessionof the political stage is far from being undisputed and he has been attacked byJinnah and other leaders. Congress propaganda by no means finds universalacceptance and is treated in many quarters wdth contempt and even ridicule.65. The situation in Sind referred to in the report for May has improvedsince the introduction of martial law. The only communal disturbance calling for note was a short-lived outburst of stabbing in Dacca, which may have beenengineered by adherents of the Forward bloc, the party of Subhas Bose. As forthe state of feeling generally, anxiety and nervousness have been somewhat allayedby the suspension of the Japanese threat of invasion, and the National WarFront movement had made some progress, though morale and confidence in Britishand Allied victory may since have been adversely affected by developments inEgypt and German successes in Russia,Indian States.66. Apart from an outbreak of agitation against the Jodhpur government by the local Congress organisation, with the active and open approval of gandhi and Nehru, there is nothing of special interest to report.Foreign and Frontier Relations.67. (a) Afghanistan. His Majesty&apos;s Minister reported that during thefirst week in June the Afghan Government, who have for a long time past kept a close watch on foreigners in Kabul, suddenly arrested three or four agents, whowere almost certainly members of a German-controlled organisation, and certainIndian residents of Kabul, some of whom are Afghan subjects, who have beensuspected by us of being important links in the Axis espionage system.Sir F. Wylie suggested that there was a possibility that, if the espionage systemof the Axis Legation were seriously interrupted by these arrests, they might find it desirable to start some sort of coup immediately. The atmosphere in Kabulwas not altogether unsuitable for stirring up trouble owing to discontent over the grain shortage.  No developments had, however, occurred by the end of the month.68. The United States Legation in Kabul was opened on the 6th June andis in the hands of a Charge d&apos;Affaires pending the arrival of the Minister,Mr. Ene-ert, from Syria.69. (b) Noi-th- West Frontier. In North Waziristan, the Lashkars round the Datta Khel post had not been dispersed and the position remained unchanged.The Faqir of Ipi was reported to have engaged 180 men as a permanent paidforce and has posted them on various routes leading to Datta Khel. Action wastaken against the hostiles&apos; gun position and supplies dropped by air to thegarrison of the post. The morale of the scouts was high, while useful&quot;co-operation was received from the Khassadars. With the exception of the Madda Khel, the behaviour of the tribes Avas satisfactory. In South Waziristan, hostilepropaganda slowed down recruitment and resulted in many enlisted Mahsudsover-staying their leave. Apart from the trouble in the Upper Tochi area referredto above, the situation on the frontier remained very satisfactory.70. (c) Tibet. Further approaches have been made to the Tibetan Govern-ment by the British and Chinese Representatives at Lhasa separately regardingthe passage of supplies through Tibet to China by pack transport. At the sametime it was explained to the Chinese Government that, before we could agree to
exercise economic pressure on the Tibetans, we would expect the Chinese Govern-ment to give a public undertaking to respect Tibetan autonomy and refrain frominterference with the internal administration of the country, in order to makeit easier for us to obtain Tibetan co-operation by thus disarming their suspicionsthat the Chinese have ulterior political motives in developing a supply route through Tibet. No definite reply has been received from the Chinese Govern-ment to this suggestion, but in the meantime the Tibetan Government have toldour Representative at Lhasa that they are willing to allow goods other thanmunitions of war to transit Tibet. The Chinese Government have accordingly been informed by His Majesty&apos;s Ambassador that the Tibetans will, so far as their transport facilities permit, convey to China supplies, such as medical stores,lubricating oil, mails, &amp;c, by pack animals, and that details should be arranged at Lhasa and in India. Unfortunately, owing to confusion due to the difficultyof communication with Lhasa, our representative there had previously given theTibetan Government reason to think that their exclusion of munitions would be acceptable and difficulty may arise regarding this limitation.71, (d) Sinkiang. In connexion with the exploration of possible new air routes for supplies to China, a survey flight has been authorised for a UnitedStates Air Force machine, which is understood to be capable of flying fromRisalpur to Yarkand and back without landing at Yarkand.72. (e) Nepal. In view7 of the serious loss of oil resources in the Far East,the Maharaja informed His Majesty&apos;s Minister that he desired to offer to HisMajesty&apos;s Government the oil which he believed, on good authority, to be present,in substantial quantities in Morang. He was willing to allow either the british or the Americans to explore the area and exploit the oil there, for wdiich he would,during the war, charge no royalties whatever. At the end of the war, he would expect the oilfield, with the plant, to be handed over to him free of cost, TheGovernment of India have caused the Maharaja to be informed of their gratefulappreciation of his generous offer and of their intention to send a geologist toundertake investigation in the Morang area in the immediate future. They have felt it desirable to undertake this exploration, although they are doubtful as tothe presence of oil in Nepal, which would in any case be of little value withoutrefiner)7 capacity to convert it into consumable products.Finance.73. (a) Refugees&apos; Savings. In agreement with the various authorities concerned, the Government of India have made arrangements from time to timewhereby refugees reaching India from Hong Kong, Dutch East Indies, and malaya have been able to encash reasonable quantities of notes belonging to thecurrencies of those countries, and in suitable cases and with necessary precautionsto draw upon deposits in their local Savings Banks.74. (b) Measures consequent upon Invasion of Biirma. The Reserve Bankof India is the currency authority for Burma as well as for India. To guard against certain complications expected to arise from the occupation of Burma, theGovernment of India have relieved the Reserve Bank of its statutory liability forthe encashment of Burma bank notes, and have assumed the requisite liabilitythemselves in consideration of the temporary transfer to them of the relativeamount of assets from the note issue reserve. Arrangements are under discussionwith the Chinese Government whereby Burma notes which are presented inChina within a reasonable period by refugees or otherwise will be encashed, the funds being provided by the Indian authorities. The Government of India havealready agreed with the Government of Burma that the periodical payments madeby Burma to India, party in the service of the pre-separation debt and partly inconnexion with pensionary charges, should be suspended in the presentcircumstances.75. (c) Loans of Local Public Bodies. The fall of Rangoon and the imminent approach of war to parts of India gave rise to apprehensions about thepossible effect of the war on Indian Port Trust and Municipal and ImprovementTrust securities. It was accordingly announced on the 6th June that the central and Provincial Governments acting together would stand behind these issues(whether sterling or rupee securities), and would not allow7 the finances of the[24121] c
issuing authorities to be so disorganised as the result of war developments as toprevent sufficient funds being made available for their service and payment onmaturity. It was also made known that, with the approval of the Central Govern-ment, the Reserve Bank would in cases of proved necessity be prepared to buy suchsecurities at appropriate prices.Economic.76. A merican Technical Mission to India. The American TechnicalMission under the Chairmanship of the Hon. Henry Grady, which was sentto India by the United States Government with the concurrence of the Governmentof India to make recommendations after investigation concerning ways and means by which the United States Government could assist in augmenting Indianswar production, presented its preliminary report to the Government of India onthe 20th May after five weeks&apos; investigation in India. A final report is to beprepared in America.77. The Mission comprised only four members and its total personnel didnot exceed nine. Naturally the work of so small a body covering so vast a ground in so short a time is hardly to be compared with that of our own Mission whichvisited India in 1940-41.78. The recommendations range from the raising and equipment of alarger Army, the setting up of a War Cabinet with a strong Secretariat to handleproduction and an alteration in the functions of the Eastern Group supply council, to matters more appropriate to such a Mission, such as the rationalisationand regimentation of industry, development of electric power facilities, steel and munitions production schemes, transport and communications questions, thedevelopment of manufactures and resources, ship and aircraft repair, training oflabour and so on. They do not so much formulate detailed and concrete proposalsfor new measures as pronounce upon schemes already more or less in shape,whether they should be pursued, and how.79. The first big step taken by the Government of India in connexion withthese various recommendations was to set up a new War Resources committee consisting of the Governor-General, with the Defence, Supply, Commerce,Communications and Finance Members of his Council and a specially selectedsecretary. It is intended that this Committee shall sit several, times a week andpossibly daily and take broad policy questions and prescribe time limits for action.SO. The Mission has already supported to the United States government considerable number of requests for essential machinery, materials and experttechnical personnel. It contemplates a continuing organisation in the UnitedStates and the appointment of an American Adviser in India to work in closely with the Government of India in co-ordinating the war production programmeof India with that of the United States.81. The new War Resources Committee in India has already covered a gooddeal of ground. It has put in hand prompt action for the rationalisation of theCalcutta jute industry in order to save transport, and for the increase of theproduction of leather and Army boots, and the rationalisation of the rubber-manufacturing industry. An additional Director-General of Munitions Produc-tion has heen appointed to draw up and execute schemes for the better use ofthe general engineering industry. Effective steps are also being taken to dealwith the recommendations of the American Mission in regard to transport and communications and special attention is being given to expansion of the steelindustry, aluminium production, and the better conservation of motor spirit,rubber and tin.Naval, Military and Air Force Activities.82. No major troop movements in the Field Army have taken place sincethose detailed last month. Two British Divisions are in process of arriving inIndia. One will be incorporated in Eastern Army, and one in General Flead-quarters reserve. One Chinese Division has reached India and is reorganising.Another is believed to be in the Hukawng Valley and south of Fort Hertz in burma. Every endeavour is being made to move them to India, but weather hasdisrupted communications.
S3. Our patrols are active beyond the frontier towards the River Chindwin.The R.A.F. and the United States Army Air Corps have carried out operationsthroughout the month, though much hampered by weather. These operations were directed principally to preventing the use by &quot;the enemy of aerodromes within reach, attacking shipping on the River Chindwin, and dropping supplies forrefugees and Chinese forces making their way to India.84. Communications in Assam are difficult, Railways find it difficult toreadjust themselves to the increased volume of traffic necessitated by military requirements, and many employees have disappeared through fear of bombing.In addition, the Brahmaputra is in record flood this year. The railways havealready been breached in several places and some bridges have been damaged.During the monsoon the mountain road from Diniapur to Imphal (150 miles) is liable to landslides and consequent accidents to lorries, of which some havealready occurred. Aerodromes are difficult to construct and maintain, and flyingis difficult in the monsoon period. In addition, large parts of the area are highlymalarial. All possible efforts to improve matters are being made, and a large measure of military control of communications has been instituted.85. The Commander-in-Chief, India, on hearing of the set-back in theWestern Desert, at once offered an immediate contribution of certain artilleryunits. R.A.C. personnel, and carriers. The Commander-in-Chief, Middle East,gratefully accepted an A./Tk. Regiment and the carriers.86. Recruiting. In July 1941 recruiting figures rose from 25.000 to 50.000per mensem and have maintained that average figure since. In June the record of 70.000 was reached. During the last war the highest figure reached was 40.000,and that only in one month. - The present average intake of 50,000, however, is insufficient to meet the full needs of expansion, and there are special difficultiesin keeping up the supply of technical personnel.87. Fifty thousand a month may be a figure that should not be difficult ofattainment by the side of the total population of India. But a great many menare totally unsuitable and. as regards the rest, the following factors should berealised : 88. (a) Many districts are becoming exhausted and can only replacewastage in existing units. So for further expansion new and untried classeshave to be introduced for which the necessary quota of Viceroy&apos;s commissioned officers and N.C.Os. does not exist and takes time to provide; (5) the difficultyof obtaining the proportion of educated men and technicians required by the modern army; (c) the psychological effect of military reverses and of the uncertainties caused by political events on voluntary recruiting; and (d) thenecessity for allocating recruits to units with due regard to their various classes and castes, and not merely according to their qualifications as in England.BURMA.Nothing to report.THE COLONIAL EMPIRE.Report by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.(Note. In this report &quot; Colonies &quot; is used to cover not only the Colonies inthe restricted sense, but also Protectorates and Mandated&quot; Territories,and &quot; Colonial Governors &quot; is used to include High Commissioners andthe British Resident, Zanzibar.)Economic A ffdirs.89. West African Prodtice Control Board. The Board has held two meetings at which representatives of the Free French Commissariat for theColonies participated.   The Board is arranging to take over the purchase and[24121] c 2
marketing of palm kernels almost immediately, and palm oil soon after.Groundnuts will be taken over in time for the next harvest, beginning inOctober.90. Cocoa. After a lapse of many months, some shipments are beingmade to the United States, and it is hoped that the United States, like theUnited Kingdom, may consider buying cocoa for use as an oilseed.91. Oilseeds. Shipments from Ceylon are improving. East Africanoilseeds will be bought through the United Kingdom Commercial Corporation,in deference to the wishes of the East African Governments.92. Tin. Active steps have been taken to increase tin production in nigeria. With the help of the Ministry of Labour and National Service, theimmediate requirements of the industry for skilled European manpower havebeen substantially met,93. Liaison, with Belgian Colonial Ministry and Free French ColonialCommissariat. The Colonial Office has now, with the approval of the ForeignOffice and the other Departments concerned, established a direct official liaison with the Free French Colonial Commissariat and also with the Belgian ColonialMinistry. The purpose of this liaison is. at least for the time being, purelyeconomic, and the vast majority of the subjects it Will handle wall concernWest and Central Africa. It is felt that there are many economic problemsof joint interest in this area, and that a co-ordinated study of these by thethree Colonial Departments wall be of great value. It is proposed that unofficialmeetings between the three Departments shall be held once a fortnight. Thefirst of these meetings has already taken place in the Colonial Office : the nextwill take place at the Free French Headquarters, and the subsequent meetingat the Belgian Colonial Ministry.94. British West African Shipping Programme. It was mentioned inthe May report that it had been decided to introduce a system of shippingprogrammes for British West Africa. Progress has now been made with thissystem. The Ministry of War Transport have appointed a representative tocover the wdiole of British West Africa. He will take up his duties at Lagosin the very near future, and a Regional Shipping Control Committee will operate in that capital under his Chairmanship. The Committee will include representatives of the Civil authorities and the Services, and will supervise all local problems in connection with the shipping programmes.Defence.95. Man-power. It has been provisionally arranged by the West and east african Governors&apos; Conferences that the raising of additional African recruitsfor non-combatant service in the Middle East Command should be apportionedamong the various territories as follows :- From West Africa NigeriaGold Coast ...From East Africa KenyaUgandaTanganyikaNyasalandNorthern RhodesiaTotal...............      ...... 100,00096. A conference consisting of representatives from the three MilitaryCommands and of the two Governors&apos; Conferences is to be held at Cairo in theearly part of July to consider detailed arrangements for organizing this additional recruitment.50,00010,000--   60,0005,00010,00015,000110,000&apos;-   40,000
dated june 3 tovarioussent to the Governors of all African and a few non-African Dependencies request-iim&apos; them to report urgently, after consulting the local military authorities, on the colonies.)practicability of forming bodies, analogous to Home Guards, in Territories where these have not yet been formed and of extending such organizations where they already exist. It was also suggested that, where particular tribes or districtscould provide small bodies of men capable, under the right leadership, of carrying-out effective harassing operations in areas occupied by the enemy, this role mightbe added to their more normal duties of giving active assistance to the defendingregular forces.98. The conclusion most generally expressed in replies so far received isthat the recruitment of Africans and other local peoples into the regular forces and existing Territorial Defence Forces is already proceeding as rapidly as is permitted by the man-power situation, the shortage of Europeanofficers to train and command the various units, and the lack of arms and equip-ment: and that the most effective way of enlisting local peoples in the defence oftheir Territories is to continue this policy rather than to create new units. the acting Governor of Nyasaland has, however, with the agreement of the local military commander, reported that it should be possible for District Officers toorganize district &quot; skin corps &quot; from among African ex-soldiers who are too oldfor re-enlistment for the purpose of hampering an invading force.99. The matter is being further considered in the light of Governors&apos;replies, not all of which have yet been received. In the case of West Africa. LordSwinton has been asked to examine the position on his arrival at Accra.Pacific War Theatre.100.   (a) Fiji and Ton a a. The New Zealand Government and the Governor tfei. No0-(l4. , ,.... - , .    . . . ,.  . , ...      of June o fromof irp have agreed to the proposal that the terms and conditions on which the Governor,United States should exercise responsibility for the defence of Fiji and Tonga Fiji)should be based on the existing Agreement between the New Zealand and Fiji (Tel. No. 271Governments, and this proposal is now being put to the -United States authorities ^ h&quot;n z3ill Washington. Governmentto D.O.)101.   (b) Neio Hebrides Condominium. The New Hebrides have been (Tel. No. 236reinforced by the arrival of United States Army, Navy and Air personnel.   Their ^omB^Ci-1 forarrival is stated to have had an important effect in strengthening the pro-Ally w pacific.)sympathies of the French population.102.   (c) British Solomon Islands Protectorate. The Resident High Com- (Tel. No. 230missioner reported early in June that Allied raids on the Tulagi area on the    ^HCr1st and 4th June started large fires which burned for 48 hours : that according w. Pacific&apos;)to native reconnaissance reports the Japanese numbered only 200, were short of (Tel. offood and anxiously awaiting a supply ship.   In a report received the 16th June June 6the Resident Commissioner stated that there has been no enemy movement outside tv\&apos;?ui?jS;\the Tulagi area since the 5th June and no enemy aerial activity since the1st June : that there had so far been no enemy occupation of Gizo or Choiseul andthat Faisi, in the extreme north of the Protectorate, was still in enemy hands and being used to some extent for shipping with Rabaul.103.   A report dated the 21st June from the Resident Commissioner stated (Tel. No. 250that there had been increased enemy activity: that the Japanese had managed fT0^^^to salvage 6 guns from a warship ashore at Pigeon Island, near Tulagi: and that ^Pacific.)a new patrol vessel carrying 70 men had arrived.   Fie added that a Japanesedestroyer had been operating off Guadalcanal since the 19th June, together with aflying boat.   The destroyer landed a party at Lunga, on the coastal plain ofthat island, with the apparent object of preparing an aerodrome.104. It has now been ascertained that 98 Europeans and 160 Chinese are still (Te,: No- 231in the Protectorate. This indicates that, in addition to the few Europeans whom it was found necessary to leave behind when evacuation to Australia was being w. Pacific)arranged earlier in the year, many more probably did not take advantage of theopportunity then offered. The Chinese had been given the opportunity to proceedto Vila (New Hebrides) in small local vessels, but preferred to remain behind in preference to undertaking a sea voyage in small craft. A report dated the9th June stated that all the Europeans were well.97.   Closer A ssociatiori of Local Peoples in Defence. A telegram has been (Tek
Reports on Individual Colonies.Palestine.105. The impression given in Jewish political circles was that the debate in the House of Lords on the 9th June was not &quot; full dress/&apos; and that the state-ments made by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, the Joint parliamentary under-Secretary of State for War, and Lord Moyne were obiter dicta. The samecircles have been considerably perturbed by the news reaching them from theUnited States, early in the month, that the United States Government has adopted a negative attitude to the Jewish State and Army projects. On the other hand,the new Liberal Zionist Party, mentioned in the report for May, seems to be making progress. It has, for instance, just achieved second place with ninemembers in the Haifa Elections to the Jewish Community Council.106. There has been no Arab political activity. In Arab circles, too, andparticularly in rural areas, the House of Lords Debate mentioned above has been widely discussed. It is reported that one result has been to reduce the inclinationof the villagers to respond to pro-Axis propagandists, who claim that Axis victoryis preferable to British rule. The setback in Libya has, of course, provided goodmaterial for underground propaganda by hostile elements. So far the,effect hasnot been as great as might have been expected; perhaps because the public areaccustomed to the ebb and flow of Libya campaigns, but the fall of Tobruk hasmade an impression owing to the great publicity given to that stronghold duringthe past year.107.   Commodity prices continue to show a downward tendency.108. There has been an improvement in Jewish recruitment. Arab recruit-ment has slackened as a result of the harvest,Ceylon.(C.-in-c. tcis.^ 109.   After a temporary set back, due to weather conditions, the labourof0juno5lld 62 situation in Colombo Harbour has been reported as &quot;very encouraging.&quot; Theand 17.) numbers of military dock units to provide labour for essential services are being increased, and the work of the landing companies have been declared essentialundertakings by Defence Regulation. (This enables the Chairman of the PortCommission to issue directions to them.)110.   The food situation continues to be kept under the closest review.111. His Royal Highness the Duke of Gloucester visited Ceylon from the24th to the 27th June.West Africa.112. Lord.Swinton has been appointed Resident Minister. He expects toleave this country- for West Africa on the 8th July, and will make his headquarters at Achimota. in the Gold Coast.113. Nigeria.--A situation containing dangerous possibilities developedowing to a demand for higher wages by all classes of African government servants. The situation was handled by making some concessions and by making-it clear that, if any strikes or demonstrations occurred, firm action &quot;would betaken under Defence Regulations.114. The conscription of labour for civilian services in essential mines in nigeria has attracted attention in Parliament and the Press during the past month. This measure was taken in Nigeria in March, and it seems that the news has only just reached critical circles in this country.115. Sierra Leone. A Military (R.E.) officer has been appointed as PortExecutive officer at Freetown, with full executive control, under the directions of the Port Executive Committee, of the handling of cargo. He has arrived inFreetown.116. Gambia. Steps are being taken to recruit a Chief Executive Officerfor A.R.P. work under the Civil Defence Committee and a Labour Adviser todeal with the various problems arising from labour requirements of the war-services and the speeding up of local food production.
117.   Gold Coast. It has now been decided that the Free French National ^ra,lfJ?.^Id.)Committee should not be asked to recall M. Beretta (see May report) from the ^PJold Coast.Ji est Indies.118. Following a further meeting of the Anglo-United States CaribbeanCommission in Washington, which was reported in last month&apos;s report, aSecretariat for the Commission is to be established in Washington, together withRegional Offices attached to the staff of the Comptroller for Development and welfare in the West Indies, and in Puerto Rico. It is. moreover, contemplated that a senior officer will shortly be appointed to take charge of the british colonial Supply Liaison at Washington, and that this officer will, in addition,be a member of the Anglo-United States Caribbean Commission.119. The maintenance of essential supplies to the West Indian Coloniescontinues to be a matter of serious anxiety, in view of the continued deterioration of the shipping position in that area, and the great dependence of many of theColonies on imported food supplies. Bulk purchases of food have already beenput in hand, and considerable progress has been made with developing, in collaboration with the American and Canadian authorities, the organisationnecessary for that and for the co-ordination of shipping in the Caribbean area,A scheme of pooling all Colonial schooner resources is now under consideration.In addition, further measures are being vigorously pressed by the Coloniesconcerned to increase local food production.120. Riots over a dispute as to wages occurred in the Bahamas at thebeginning of the month on the construction works of the Operational TrainingUnit, a joint Anglo-American flying training project, The troops had to becalled out and two rioters were shot and several injured. Order was soonrestored and the position is now quiet. His Royal Highness the Duke of Windsorhas visited Washington and agreed with the American authorities that certain increases of pay should be granted by the American contractors to the labourersengaged on this project,121. The first contingent of West Indians has now reached this country under the scheme for training munition workers mentioned in the report forDecember, 1941.




</content>
</cab>
