<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/120/0 images: 88-97</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   January 1965C. (65) 1026th January, 1965CABINETPUBLIC expenditure memorandum by the Chancellor of the exchequer at the Cabinet meeting on Thursday, 21st January, 1965, Iindicated that I would be submitting a memorandum on thepreparation of long-term programmes of public expenditure designedto fit in with our general long-term Economic Plan (reference C.C. (65)3rd Conclusions, Minute 3).Planning assumptions2. The first task has been to settle the overall rate of growth ofthe economy which should be assumed for planning purposes. It hasnow been agreed between the Department of Economic Affairs andthe Treasury that it is right to aim on the high side when planning the capacity of basic industries in the public sector and when guidingthe plans of private industry. Only in this way can we hope toencourage faster growth and ensure that there is no risk of bottlenecks.On the other hand, it is right to be cautious when planning public expenditure outside the industrial sector, so that we do not commit ourselves to spend the fruits of faster growth before we have achieved them. We must ensure that we are not again landed withprogrammes which have run far ahead of the capacity of the economy. It has, therefore, been agreed that for industrial planning,and for public presentation, we should use as our starting assumptiona growth of the gross domestic product of 25 per cent between 1964and 1970. This figure represents an average increase of about 3f percent a year. On the other hand, for the purposes of relating long-termprogrammes of public expenditure, other than for the basic industrialsector, to prospective resources, it has been agreed that we should assume a growth of the gross domestic product of 22-^ per cent,representing approximately 3^ per cent a year.3. By taking a reasonably cautious figure for public spending,we will not be running risks that demand will be inadequate andthat employment will fall; The steady growth of public expenditure will all the time be sustaining demand. If we are successful inSECRET5333 aSCopy No.5
achieving the 25 per cent growth target and it implies a rapidacceleration in the rate of economic growth we shall always be ableto reconsider our programmes and add to them. It will, as always,be best to deal with the short run regulation of demand by adjustingtaxation, transfer payments and monetary policy.4. The task now is to take the assumed rate of growth of22^ per cent and to build up public expenditure programmesconsistent with it. For the present we can leave aside the programmes of the nationalised industries which, as I have indicated, will be basedon the figure of 25 per cent; they will have to be closely geared in with the Economic Plan as it develops.5. The programmes we have inherited for public expenditure,excluding nationalised industries, are set out in Table 1. The figuresrelate to central Government expenditure, the gross outgoings of theNational Insurance Funds and all expenditure by local authorities.They cover the period 1964-65 to 1968-69; they are all at prices ofspring 1964; they embrace our predecessors&apos; programmes, modified to take account of the policy decisions we have taken since cominginto office. They have not been published. (The last figures of thiskind to be published were those prepared in 1963, covering the period1963-64 to 1967-68.)Table 1EXISTING PROGRAMMES  million at spring 1964 prices1964-65 1968-69Defence Budget     .........           1,998 2,350Other         ............          8,448 10,195Contingencies        .........               300Total       ......         10,446 12,8456. The total for 1968-69 is  12,545 million to which theTreasury have added  300 million for contingencies, making 12,845 million in all. (The contingencies item is not intended to leaveroom for new policies, but to counter a tendency to under-estimateon the part of Departments.) The increase over 1964-65 is  2,400million, representing a rate of increase of 5J per cent a year. This ismuch faster than the rate of growth of the gross domestic productwhich we have agreed to assume for planning purposes (3^ per cent).Since we are facing a period when we must sharply improve theforeign balance and when we wish to raise the rate of investment in order to accelerate growth, there is in any event bound to be littleroom for the growth of private consumption. If, in addition, we wereto permit public spending to go up at this rate, the curtailment ofprivate consumption would have to be drastic.7. I can illustrate this with some provisional figures based onthe assumed rate of growth of 3-1- per cent. If we achieved this rate of growth and if provision were made for the necessary increases in private investment and exports, then private consumption per head
could not grow at more than \\ per cent per annum, in contrast tothe 2\ per cent by which it has been rising in recent years. this restriction of consumption would have to be brought about bytaxation. The extent of the increase would depend upon the behaviour of private savings. The Treasury estimate that increases in rates oftaxation would be required on a scale sufficient to yield at least an extra  500 million, and very possibly as much as  1,000 million, overand above the buoyancy of the revenue. This is after taking intoaccount the increases in income tax and oil duty announced in the november Budget and assuming that during the period  100 million would be transferred from rates to taxes.8. In short, we must now reshape the programmes we haveinherited from our predecessors. We need not be too anxious about this. The public will not be impressed by whose programme has beenhigher in a particular field. They will judge us by what we actuallyachieve.Annual growth of 4  per cent of public expenditure. I have discussed the implications of this with the first secretary and the proposition we wish to put to our colleagues is thatthe growth of public expenditure (excluding spending by nationalised industries) should in total be limited to A\ per cent a year, rather than5^ per cent. We would still be planning for a significantly faster growth of public expenditure than of the gross domestic product.There would be room for an increase in private consumption per head of nearly 2 per cent, but it is estimated that, apart from changesneeded to stabilise demand, an increase in tax rates sufficient to raiseabout  250 million extra would still be needed.10. The reduction of the yearly rate of growth of public expenditure from 5  per cent to A\ per cent would mean reducing the absolute level of public expenditure in 1968-69 by  500 million; or,to put it another way. it would mean delaying the attainment of the1968-69 level by one year. (By then a 4^ per cent rate of growth in public expenditure will mean an increase of  500 million a year.)Since 1969-70 is the year on which we now need to focus in our long-term planning, the latter is the more convenient way of looking at the position.11. The main way I see of achieving this aim is by containingdefence expenditure. A major review is being undertaken of our defence policies, to see what would be involved in keeping theDefence Budget at the 1964-65 level of  2,000 million, at 1964 prices,not only in 1965-66 but right through to 1969-70. I cannot see anyway through our economic problems if defence expenditure is higherthan this. A long-term defence policy within these limits will save 350 million of the  500 million which I need.12. For the rest I am prepared to take some risk in the accuracy of the costing, and reduce the contingencies margin to  150 million.This means that the total sum available for civil expenditure can continue to rise at the rate envisaged in existing programmes. Butthis does not mean that the existing programmes, largely inheritedSECRET5333 A 2
from our predecessors, should remain intact. We must apply our ownsocial priorities and we must, by fitting in with the planning workof the Department of Economic Affairs, check the feasibility ofthe programmes in terms of scarce physical resources, e.g.,construction, engineering expenditure, scientific and other highlyeducated manpower. The totals I propose are shown in Table 2.Table 2FUTURE PROGRAMMES  million at spring 1964 prices1968-69 1969-70Existing proposed programme programme(5t%p.a* (4\%p.a.*rate of increase) rate of increase)Defence Budget      .........           2,350 2,000Other...............         10,195 10,695Contingencies        .........             300 150Total       ...... 12,845 12,845* Percentage rate of growth from base year 1964-65.Preparation of programmes13. In order to achieve these aims we must, in the first place,intensify our search, throughout the field, for expenditures which canbe cut out as no longer necessary. In particular, although the figures are expressed at constant 1964 prices, this does not mean thatexpenditures on individual programmes can be automatically allowedto rise by the full extent of whatever pay and price rises may occur.I shall look to my colleagues to do all they can, both by the adoptionof improved techniques and where necessary by adjusting their programmes, to absorb cost increases.14. A general search for economy, however, is not enough. Wemust also distinguish between items of greater and lesser priority ineach programme, so that we have some freedom of choice when the programmes are weighed against one another and fitted into the Plan.Some agreed procedure for doing this is needed now. Departmentsmust begin preparing their programmes for the period upto 1969-70 early in February, if we are to be able to take firm decisions in July.15. The First Secretary and I propose that each Department(where appropriate, group of Departments) should prepare a &quot; basic &quot;programme within a limit now to be laid down. Each department would also be entitled to submit an additional programme,representing the improvements which it would wish to see, over and above the basic programme. For example, if the Minister of housing and Local Government had in mind to propose that the housing programme should be adjusted so as to provide for a higher proportion of public sector housing, the resulting prospective increasein public expenditure would represent an additional programme, overand above the basic programme for his Department. When these
basic and additional programmes had been prepared and analysed(and related to the Plan for National Economic Development) theCabinet would decide how far it would be possible to accept theadditional programmes, and determine the priorities between them.16. To give the Cabinet the greatest possible area of choice and decision on priorities, the First Secretary and I propose that the&quot; basic&quot; programmes should be worked out on the minimumpracticable level. If the programming were to be done otherwise, weshould in effect be taking the priority decisions now, or landingourselves in a situation in July in which the programmes presented by Departments were exceeding prospective resources by such a widemargin that a surgical operation would be necessary.17. The proposed limits for the &quot; basic &quot; programmes, and the procedures for handling items which cannot be programmed fiveyears ahead, are set out in an appendix. For defence, I am working on the assumption that the long-term policy review in the comingweeks will enable the Department to programme within the limits which I have proposed above. I recognise the difficulty of achieving this; but I must warn my colleagues that any failure to achieve this objective will have to be charged against the amount available for the&quot; additional &quot; civil programmes. For the civil programmes, the limitsare designed to reflect very broadly the rates of expansion ofexpenditure which flow inescapably from the development of policies which have already been announced. If in any particular case mycolleagues feel that a basic programme is too high, any reduction theycan suggest will add to the general scope for additional programmes.Conclusions18.  I ask my colleagues&apos; agreement to the following:(a) That we decide to base our planning of public sector expenditure on an average annual rate of increase of41 per cent per annum at constant prices from 1964-65 to1969-70, i.e., a rise of 23 per cent over the period.(Paragraph 9.)(b) That Departments should prepare &quot; basic &quot; programmes for1969-70 within the limits and procedures in the appendix;and &quot; additional&quot; programmes also; and that decisions will be taken in July to determine long-term programmesaccordingly, fitted into the Plan for National economic development. (Paragraphs 15 to 17.).J. C.Treasury Chambers, S.W.1,26th January, 1965.
AppendixPROCEDURE FOR &quot;BASIC&quot; 1969-70 programmes first and most vital proposal is that defence expenditure should be held at  2,000 million, at 1964 prices.2. For the sectors specified below, consideration of presentprogrammes and of the orderly development of the services inquestion, appears to lead to the following per cent rates of increase for the basic programmes:t- Percentage increase from1964-65 1964-65 to 1969-70  million at constant pricesRoads (current and capital)   ...          397 40Public sector housing investment          506 10Education (all levels, current and capital)        .........        1,394 30Health and welfare (current and capital)       ...      ......        1,126 22 Police and prisons     ......          215 153. For benefits and assistance ( 1,871 million in 1964-65), the&quot; basic &quot; programme should allow increased benefits at the expectedrate of increase of real earnings per head from April 1965 withwage-related unemployment benefit. The rate of family allowances would be unchanged.4. It is impracticable to programme most forms of assistanceto industry, transport and agriculture ( 840 million in 1964-65) for five years ahead. The cost of agricultural support, for example, will depend upon the level of world prices in 1969-70; disbursementunder the Local Employment Act depending upon what will happen to regional balance in the next five years; the British Railways Boardsubsidy upon a variety of circumstances. There may also be new kinds of industrial subsidy, to help advanced technology or industrialmodernisation. At this stage, Departments should include either a considered estimate or, if this is impracticable, the current figure.It is at present assumed that the total of all this assistance will notbe higher in 1969-70 than in 1964-65, i.e., that certain forms of subsidy will be reduced while others increase.5. As regards overseas economic aid, the Government have accepted the objective of increasing the proportion of national income devoted to essential aid programmes, and intend to move towards it. It is suggested that for the purpose of preparing the&quot; basic &quot; programme for 1969-70 a figure of  230 million should beused (the outturn for 1964-65 may be around  200 million), whichwould be equivalent to a continuing increase at about the same proportion of G.D.P.; and an &quot;additional&quot; programme could besubmitted to provide for progress towards the higher objective. Butthis expenditure bears directly and heavily on the balance of
payments, and the rate at which it will be possible in practice toincrease aid expenditure over its present level during the next five years will be dependent on the position of the balance ofpayments; the forward programme must be subject to this limitation.For this reason firm decisions about the future level of aid expenditurecannot be taken at the present time by reference to what would betolerable for the Budget. Discussions will be continued through the established machinery which exists for settling the aid programme.6. Services for which no specific indication is given should beincluded at the minimum practicable level.7. &quot; Additional &quot; programmes should be submitted to includedepartmental proposals which cannot be accommodated within the&quot; basic &quot; programmes.




</content>
</cab>
