<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/120/0 images: 122-125</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC M.\JESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   February 1965C. (65) 13 Copy No.   5 93rd February, 1965CABINETA NEW TOWN FOR MANCHESTERMemorandum by the First Secretary of State and Secretaryof State for Economic affairs have to ask my colleagues to reach a decision on a matter which the Economic Development Committee has been unable to resolve.2. Manchester badly needs a new town to deal with its slum clearance problems. Our predecessors proposed a site at Risley nearWarrington for a commuter town of about 50,000 people, but it was later found to be physically unsuitable for a town of this size.3.  Two alternatives have since been suggested:(i) a commuter new town of about 50,000 people at Lymm;(ii) a new  toWn,  which  would  provide  opportunities  ofemployment as well as of residence, at Leyland/Chorley.4. A commuter new town at Lymm would not be fullysatisfactory: it has twice been rejected as a development site because it would use up a good deal of first class agricultural land, and theadditional commuting traffic (it is 13 miles from Manchester) would create substantial transport problems.5. A new town at Leyland/Chorley, 25 miles north-west of manchester, would be well placed to become an important regionalgrowth point. The site is well clear of the congested parts of lancashire, and a new town here would help to reverse the generaldrift of population towards the southern part of the region. Theamount of industry that could be diverted from Manchesterhowever would be insufficient to provide a base for the new townand it would be necessary to steer industry towards it from otherparts of the country. This would mean providing positive financialincentives of the kind now given only in development districts(including Merseyside and the new towns of Skelmersdale andRuncorn). This, in turn, would require a change in the legislation relating to the distribution of industry.6. A new town at Leyland/Chorley would take several years todevelop and would not provide a complete answer to Manchester&apos;s5347
short-term overspill problems. But it has been suggested that these could be dealt with by a smaller commuter new town at Risley. This,it is thought, would tide Manchester over until the Leyland/Chorleydevelopment got under way, and would not conflict with the concept of creating a regional growth point at Leyland/Chorley, providedthat the size of the Risley development was not too large.7. The proposition before the Economic development committee, therefore, was that the Government should announceits approval of a limited commuter development at Risley, and its decision to establish a larger new town at Leyland/Chorley at which,subject to the necessary change in legislation, financial incentivessimilar to those given to industry in a development district would beavailable.8. The President of the Board of Trade finds this unacceptable.His views are explained in a separate memorandum (C. (65) 14). Inaddition the Secretaries of State for Scotland and Wales are fearful ofthe effects these developments would have on the drift of population from Scotland and on the Government^ ability to deal satisfactorilywith prospective unemployment amongst miners and steel workersin South Wales.9. The majority of Ministers in the Economic development committee feel that we cannot postpone all decisions about growth in the rest of the country until the task of rehabilitating development districts is complete. These areas already have priority: the programmes for their rehabilitation are well under way and the opportunities for development already exist. A new town atLeyland/Chorley could hardly be bringing in industry for a numberof years ahead. But if we want to get this and similar growth points in other parts of the country going, decisions about siting must betaken well in advance and in the less prosperous regions we must beprepared to put behind our proposals the same sort of financial support that we give to development districts. This means a new look at incentives for industry.; 10. We cannot delay a decision. Manchester needs an early announcement so that it can plan accordingly to deal with itspressing housing problems, and would not regard a limited commuterdevelopment on its own as an acceptable substitute for a firm and early decision on a full-scale new town. I invite my colleagues,therefore, to decide whether we should authorise:(a) the creation of a large new town at Leyland/Chorley, whichwould act as a regional growth point, with an indication that financial incentives similar to those granted in development districts will be available, subject to theamendment of present legislation; and(b) the development of a small commuter new town at Risley tohelp to meet Manchester&apos;s immediate housing needs.G. B.Department of Economic Affairs, S.W.1,2nd February, 1965.



</content>
</cab>
