<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/120/0 images: 302-329</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
confidential  X lALi4iHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MA JEST Y*S GOVERNMENT)I asked the Parliamentary Secretary, Ministry of public building and ..-orks, with the help of the Arts and AmenitiesCommittee, to review the activities of the Government and other public authorities in the field of arts and amenities and to make recommendations.She has submitted a report in the form of a draft White Paper,a copy of which is attached.    The Minister of Public Building and works and the other Ministers concerned are, I understand, inagreement with the draft.I have considered as a separate matter whether the Governmentsadministrative arrangements for dealing with the arts should be modified.    My conclusions, which 1 have discussed with the ministers immediately involved, are embodied in paragraph 78 of the draft.I invite my colleagues to agree that the White Paper should bepublished at an early date.59C.(65) 2215th February, 1965COPY NO.cabinet a POLICY FOR THE ARTSM emorandum by. the Prime MinisterH. W.10, Downing Street, S. W. 1.15th February, 1965

A POLICY FORTHE ARTSTHE FIRST STEPSPresented to Parliament by the Prime minister by Command of Her majesty february 1965LONDONHER MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE.PRICE net cmnd.

A POLICY FOR THE ARTSTHE FIRST STEPSCONTENTSIntroduction..................Government support for the arts.........Local and Regional effort............Housing the arts    ...............The influence of education .........The Governments plans   ............32480

introduction. The relationship between artist and state in a modern democraticcommunity is not easily defined. No one would wish state patronage to dictate taste or in any way restrict the liberty of even the most unorthodoxand experimental of artists.2. But if a high level of artistic achievement is to be sustained and thebest in the arts made more widely available, more generous and discriminat-ing help is urgently needed, locally, regionally, and nationally.3. In some parts of the country professional companies are non-existent.Even amateurs find it hard to keep going. And lack of suitable buildingsmakes it impossible to bring any of the leading national companies, orches-tral, operatic, ballet or theatre, into those areas.4. Fortunately, this state of affairs is coming increasingly under fire.So too are those of our museums, art galleries and concert halls that have failed to move with the times, retaining a cheerless unwelcoming air thatalienates all but the specialist and the dedicated.5. No greater disservice can be done to the serious artist than to presenthis work in an atmosphere of old fashioned gloom and undue solemnity.6. If we are concerned to win a wider and more appreciative public, forthe arts, all this must be changed. A new social as well as artistic climateis essential.7. There is no easy or quick way of bringing this about, the more soas too many working people have been conditioned by their education andenvironment to consider the best in music, painting, sculpture, and literature,outside their reach. A younger generation, however, more self confidentthan their elders, and beginning to be given some feeling for drama, musicand the visual arts in their school years, are more hopeful material. Theywill want gaiety and colour, informality and experimentation. But thereis no reason why attractive presentation should be left to those whoseprimary concern is with quantity and profitability.8. Some of our new civic centres and art centres already demonstrate that an agreeable environment and a jealous regard for the maintenanceof high standards are not incompatible. Centres that succeed in providing a friendly meeting ground where both light entertainment and culturalprojects can be enjoyed help also to break down the isolation from which both artist and potential audience have suffered in the past.9. Another encouraging trend is the growing recognition of the im-portance of strengthening contacts between regional and civic art associa-tions in different parts of the country.10. But we have a long way to go before effective associations of thiskind become common form everywhere. If a sane balance of populationbetween north and south, east and west, is to be achieved, this kind ofdevelopment is jusj as essential as any movement of industry or provisionof public utility service.   If the eager and gifted, to whom we must look32480a3
for leadership in every field, are to feei as much at home in the northand west as in and near London, each region will require high points ofartistic excellence. Of course no provincial centre can hope to rival thefull wealth and diversity of London&apos;s art treasures, but each can have something of its own that is supreme in some particular field. This toomust be the aim of the new towns, if they are to win and to hold thekind of residents they most need.11. From the combined efforts of the Government and regional asso-ciations that include representatives of industry, the trade unions and privatedonors as well as local authorities, the money must be found to providethe buildings needed to house the arts.12. If we are prepared to accept this challenge, we must also be pre-pared within the limits of the resources that can be made available to giveexpenditure for these projects a higher priority than in the past.13. The financial difficulties that so many of today&apos;s artists have to contend with, must also be realistically examined.14. In any civilised community the arts and associated amenities, seriousor comic, light or demanding, must occupy a central place. Their enjoy-ment should not be regarded as something remote from every day life. the promotion and appreciation of high standards in architecture, in industrialdesign, in town planning and the preservation of the beauty of the country-side, are all part of it. Beginning in the schools, and reaching out intoevery corner of the nation&apos;s life, in city and village, at home, at work,at play, there is an immense amount that could be done to improve thequality of contemporary life.15. There is no short-term solution for what by its very nature is along-term problem. This is a field in which even in the most favourable circumstances, it will never be possible to do as much as we want to do as quickly as we want to do it. But that is no excuse for not doing as muchas we can and more than has hitherto been attempted.Government Support for the Arts16. The support that the Government give to the arts can be groupedunder three heads education, preservation and patronage.17. The main educational functions are carried out in England andWales under the aegis of the Department of Education and Science and inScotland of the Scottish Education Department. In partnership with thelocal education authorities and voluntary bodies they are concerned withthe arts in schools, colleges of further education, including colleges of art, adult education and community centres. To the responsibilities ofthe Department of Education and Science public libraries will soon beadded. The Victoria and Albert Museum is the direct responsibility ofthe Department of Education and Science and the Royal Scottish Museumof the Scottish Education Department.18. As for preservation, the Museums and Galleries, largely financeddirectly by the Treasury, and the Historic Buildings and Ancient Monumentslooked after by the Ministry of Public Building and Works are the mostimportant.  The National Trust, and the National Trust for Scotland,
private bodies with great houses and collections under their wing, receiveon occasion substantial grants towards repair and maintenance from theMinistry of Public Building and Works. There are also other bodiesreceiving financial support from the Government, such as the BritishInstitute of Recorded Sound.19. The patronage given by the State to music, drama, painting, sculp-ture and poetry is largely channelled through the Arts Council and itsScottish and Welsh Committees. The Council thus cover most of the fields not provided for by other agencies.National museums and galleries20. There are seventeen main national museums and galleries, two ofwhich are scientific. Government departments are directly responsible forthree of them ; the Victoria and Albert, the Science and the Royal ScottishMuseums. The rest are administered by Trustees appointed in mostinstances by the Prime Minister.21. The management of their affairs is in their own hands and theycan spend their purchase grants as they like. Special grants can also bemade towards the cost of exceptional purchases.22. Building for these museums in London and Edinburgh is arranged by the Ministry of Public Building and Works, which in turn looks for advice on priorities to the Standing Commission on Museums and Galleries,a body of twelve appointed by the Prime Minister. A twelve-year pro-gramme covering England and Scotland has been drawn up costing finally!  5m. starting in 1964-65. In addition there are several large specialprojects outside the twelve-year programme, notably the British MuseumLibrary, estimated at  15m., and the National Science Reference Library( 1-l-m.); a bill now before Parliament provides for an Exchequer contri-bution to a new Museum of London. A separate programme of  700,000over twelve years has been agreed for the Welsh Institutions.Provincial Museums and Galleries23. There are some 900 of these supported or administered mainly bylocal authorities whose expenditure on them does not rank for calculatinggeneral grant. They vary greatly in size and scope. The Standing Corn-mission surveyed these museums in 1960 and commented unfavourably onthe small amounts of money spent on many of them.24. A fund ( 50,000 in 1964-65) for local purchases comes from the victoria and Albert Museum which also provides loans of travellingexhibitions culled from the museum&apos;s material. The Royal Scottish Museumoperates a similar fund. Regional schemes of co-operation through AreaCouncils are beginning to get under way. These v/ill enable the smallermuseums in an area to call on the larger for advice and help. exchequer grants are made to the Area Councils, but until the schemes are in fullworking order this expenditure will not be large.The Arts Council25. Support for the living arts is mainly channelled through the arts council whose task was set out in its Royal Charter of 1946, as the develop-ment of &quot; a greater knowledge understanding and practice of the fine arts
exclusively and in particular to increase the accessibility of the fine arts tothe public throughout Our Realm, to improve the standard of executionof the fine arts and to advise and co-operate with Our Government Depart-ments, local authorities and other bodies on any matters concerned directly or indirectly with those objects.&quot;26. Sixteen persons appointed by the Chancellor of the Exchequer afterconsultation with the Education Ministers are chosen for their knowledgeof, or concern with, one or more of the fine arts. They are responsible forthe allocation of the grant-in-aid given them through the Treasury vote for Grants for the Arts. In 1963-64 a triennial basis was adopted with anannual 10 per cent, increase. The Charter provides for the appointment of committees for Scotland and Wales to which the Council entrusts thedischarge of its functions in these countries.27. With these funds the Council organise exhibitions, some of them themost important held in this country, or inded anywhere, since the war. Theysend groups performing &quot; Opera for All&quot; widely through the country, andorganise some concerts. But for the most part the Council give grants orguarantees to activities for which other sources, contribute equal or greatersupport.28. The following are the main objects which the Council support: Opera and Ballet:Covent Garden and Royal Ballet.Sadler&apos;s Wells.Welsh National Opera Company.Scottish Opera Society.London Opera Centre.Ballet Rambert.Western Theatre Ballet and some small companies.Music:Orchestras.By an arrangement with the London County Council, orchestralconcerts in the Royal Festival Hall are subsidised. Outside Londonorchestras which obtain help from the Arts Council includeScottish National Orchestra.HaMLiverpool Philharmonic.City of Birmingham.Western Orchestral Society.Northern Sinfonia.Also through the National Federation of Music Societies small grants are made to a large number of musical bodies with the aim of improving performance  by guaranteeing  concerts  and  enablingamateurs to improve their quality and engage professional conductors,singers and players.Theatre :The National Theatre.Royal Shakespeare Company.English Stage Society.
Some 45 other repertory companies.Training schemes for writers, producers, designers and adminis-administrators.Other grants by Scottish Committee (e.g. Glasgow Citizens&apos; Theatre)and Welsh Committee.. Art:    &apos;   . &apos;   * - ... .Mainly throguh exhibitions, grants and guarantees to local artssocieties, and occasional purchases. :    *Poetry :Grants, guarantees and direct promotion.The Edinburgh Festival.Arts Festival.Arts Associations and Clubs.British Film Institute29. This body receives direct grants from the Treasury and the Depart-ment of Education and Science. Its main objects are to run the national film Archive, the National Film Theatre and a Film Distribution Library.It issues several publications, including Sight and Sound, and generallyconcerns itself with &quot; the development of the film as a means of entertainmentand instruction &quot;, as does the Scottish Film Council which is also grant-aided.Other bodies30. Grants are also made to the following : The British Academy whichfinances schools of Archaeology overseas, the British Institute of RecordedSound, the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art, the Royal Academy of Music;the Royal College of Music, the Royal Scottish Academy of Music, and theRoyal Manchester College of Music.Historic houses and Ancient Monuments31. The Ministry of Public Building and Works is responsible for theadministration of the Ancient Monuments and Historic Buildings Actsinrluding the power to make grants towards the repair Of buildings of outstanding historic or architectural interest, acting on the advice of, thethree Historic Buildings Councils for England, Scotland and Wales. grants are normally made.only on condition that the house is opened to the public.32. The Ministry is also responsible for the upkeep&apos; of a number of buildings of special historic interest, such as Burlington House, LancasterHouse, Marlborough House, the Tower of London, the Banqueting House,the Royal Naval College, Greenwich and Royal Palaces not occupiedby the Sovereign such as Hampton Court, parts of Holyroodhouse andOsborne House.33. Statues. A good many of the London statues are in the charge of the-Ministry! When Parliament approves a statue the Ministry normallycommissions and erects it.34. Sculpture and pictures. Sometimes a new public building calls.forsculpture or other, special type of decoration and the Ministry thus exercisesa limited amount of patronage.   It also purchases a number of pictures
every year, for diplomatic buildings overseas, official residences and Govern-ment offices. It also has a team of artists skilled in picture conservationand the restoration of works of art.35. The Ministry of Housing and Local Government also has responsibilities -ties for buildings of special architectural or historic interest. The Ministryissues lists of such buildings for the guidance of local plannning authorities,in order to&apos; ensure that the special interest of the buildings is taken intoaccount when proposals affecting their future are put forward. In additionto their normal powers of development control, the local authorities maymake building preservation orders (subject to confirmation by the Minister)where necessary.36. Local authorities are also authorised, in England and Wales by theLocal Authorities (Historic Buildings) Act 1962 and in Scotland by the LocalGovernment (Scotland) Act 1947, to contribute towards the repair andmaintenance of buildings of architectural or historic interest. The consentof the Minister of Housing and Local Government is required only if thebuilding is not a listed building.37. The British Council is responsible for displaying overseas the best of British drama, music, and the visual arts. In co-operation with localmuseums and art galleries abroad, paintings and sculpture by British artistsare sent for exhibition at international art festivals, and on extended toursthrough a number of countries. Photographic displays dealing with suchsubjects as architecture or social services are also supplied. The Councilorganises tours overseas by British theatre, ballet and opera companies andby orchestras and individual musicians, enabling them to perform not onlyin Europe but sometimes in countries farther afield where opportunities of seeing or hearing British actors or muscians are rare. It maintains aninformation and reference service for specialists in the arts and sends copiesof plays, gramophone records (including recorded speech and literature), andmusic to its libraries overseas.Local and Regional Effort38. Local authorities depend, for authority to incur expenditure, mainlybut not entirely on Section 132 of the Local Government Act 1948. Thispermits them to spend the product of a 6d. rate on entertainment in all itsforms. They can also spend whatever profit they make out of entertainment.There is similar provision for Scotland. It may well be worth considering whether these powers should not be extended to the county councils inEngland and Wales ; at present only the London County Council has obtainedthem. *39. Some of the most progressive local authorities already show what canbe done. Birmingham, for example, besides having one of the finest museumsin the country, in part finances its orchestra, plans to build a new Repertory iTheatre and has made an interest-free loan to the amateur Crescent Theatre.It is also contributing to an adventurous scheme for an arts centre for you that Cannon Hill. Manchester at the Library Theatre runs one of the fewcivic theatres that is completely financed from local funds. Sunderland hasadded an arts centre to its museum and generally supports its theatre. TheLondon County Council has a proud record of support for the arts.  It has
built the Royal Festival Hall and is building an arts centre on the South Bank, contributes half the pool which guarantees the concerts of three greatorchestras, supports several museums, took the initiative over the national theatre and commissions a wide variety of sculpture for its schools. TheCity, too, plans to build an arts centre in the new Barbican development and will contribute one third of the cost of the new Museum of London.40. In Scotland, Glasgow has now embarked on a scheme for a culturalcentre which will include two theatres and a concert hall.41. The New Towns in England, Wales and Scotland are also showingenterprise. They have powers to make contributions to the cost of providingamenities and to appoint Social Development Officers who make the needsof voluntary organisations known to the Corporations. Harlow, for instance,has appointed its own arts council which receives financial help from thelocal authority and is preparing a scheme for a theatre and arts centre.It has also introduced and supports a professional string quartet for whose members the Corporation has made houses available. Welwyn Garden Cityprovids in Digswell House living accommodation for sixteen artists and students. An example from Scotland is the help given to the GlenrothesArts Club which has premises in an adapted farmhouse. Others have formedArts Trusts which serve as intermediary between the local authority and the cultural organisations.42. An enterprise that grows steadily in popularity and enjoys arts council support is the Arts Festival. This brings cultural opportunities to the residents and also brings visitors to the town. In addition to theInternational Festival at Edinburgh there are festivals at Aldeburgh, BathCambridge, Cheltenham, Little Missenden, Haslemere, Ludlow and York ;also the Three Choirs festival. In Wales there is the peripatetic Eisteddfod.In Scotland, Stirling has led the way in local festivals. But too many centres,especially in the drabber industrial areas, do not as yet share in these activities.43. Go-ahead local enterprises need more than encouragement and advice.They also need more financial help, and this is where regional associationsfor the arts can perform an important function, for regional planning is asvaluable in this as in the economic sphere. At this level a small staffwith a few keen local enthusiasts backing them can stimulate the co-operationof other authorities, and by calling on each for a fairly small levy providefunds with which to finance a variety of projects concerts, exhibitions, filmshows and lectures which few authorities by themselves could afford. Byinvoking the help of the local education authorities they can also bring the schools into the picture. It is important to win the goodwill and co-operationof employers and trade unions. Universities too have an important part to play. A network of this kind should be developed to cover the whole country. Once an association has been formed it can act with and forthe Arts Council in a mutually beneficial relationship.44. At present the biggest association of this kind is in the NorthEast. It received  30,000 from the Arts Council in 1964-65 and helps tosupport among other things the Northern Sinfonia Orchestra, the Sunderlandventures already mentioned, an arts centre at Billingham and the PeopledTheatre Arts Centre in Newcastle-upon-Tyne.
45. The most recent of the regional bodies is the Eastern AuthoritiesOrchestral Association formed at the instance of the Arts Council and theLondon Philharmonic Orchestra. Some 93 local authorities from the Humberto the Thames will contribute  2 per thousand head of population to be matched   for   by the Arts Council, so that all members can benefit fromthe visit of an orchestra, even if the concert is given in surroundings notdevised for&apos;orchestral work and at somewhat irregular intervals.46. Another advantage of the regional association is that it calls forthfrom a larger area the able individuals who are the key to success. It givesthem wider scope and puts their special gifts at the disposal of many localauthorities besides their own.47. This paper has laid emphasis on the fact that the municipalities arethe corner stone without which effective local and regional art associationscannot be started or kept going. But ample scope remains for privatedonors and trusts such as the Carnegie U.K. Trust, the Pilgrim and FoyleTrusts, the Gulbenkian and Rayne Foundations. One of their most valuablecontributions is to assist projects during their early stages, as the CarnegieU.K. Trust has done in its support of local museums.48. There is also the considerable contribution made by private collectorsand a welcome beginning to patronage of the arts by progressive indus-industrialists and trade unions.Housing the Arts49. There is a dearth of good local buildings for showing and practisingthe arts. Part of the reason is that after the war there was such urgent need, for houses and factories that little provision could be made for.thecivilising influences of concern halls, theatres or art centres. Money, labourand materials were not available. Habits of neighbourliness and co-opera-tion in community projects were not developed. The damage then uh-avoidably done is only now being remedied. People who had never knownwhat they were missing did not press for galleries, theatres and concerthalls. Certain sections of the press, by constantly sniping at culturalexpenditure, made philistinism appear patriotic.50. Another reason was that the Arts Council was not able to providesignificant capital sums for building.51. In meeting contemporary trends.the concept of the arts centre is most valuable since such a centre can be of almost any size and cover any range of activities. A single hall can provide a place where localpeople can meet, perform an amateur play, hold an exhibition of theirown or of professional work, put on a film show, lecture or recital and generally act as a focal point for cultural and amenity activities. It maybe run solely by amateurs or by a mixture of amateurs and professionals.At the other end of the scale the arts centre may cover a long stretch ofthe South Bank, with Festival Hall, Recital Room, National Theatre,Art Galleries, restaurant and Film Theatre. In. between there are forinstance the &apos; Little Theatre Guild of Great Britain&apos; whose twenty-six members, in towns as far apart as Salisbury and Llangefni or Newcastleupon Tyne, have built or adapted their own theatres and support themwith other activities concerned with the arts-films, collections of costumes,
and art exhibitions. Another notable example is the Cannon Hill Trust,where the plans include a library, three theatres (one open-air), swimmingpool and multi-purpose studio and where the emphasis is educational, aiming at winning and holding the interest of the young. In Scotland, Greenockhas provided an enterprising arts centre consisting of a theatre, gallery for small exhibitions, lecture room and small restaurant.52. Demand is increasing and far more money could be spent on housing the arts than is likely to be immediately available. As a first step the arts Council will be authorised to enter into commitments up to  250,000in 1965-66, in order to encourage regional and local authorities to develop their plans in this field. If this has the desired effect, the Government willbe ready, when the time comes, to consider authorising the Arts Councillo enter into substantially higher levels of commitment in future years.53. There is no reason other than lack of energy and interest whyevery community, large and small, should not form its own arts centre,aiming at growth and improvement of quality. The Regional Arts Asso-ciation should be there to help ; and one of the purposes of Centre 42,which has recently acquired a lease of the Round House in Camden Town,is to have groups of fully professional artists ready to respond to calls ontheir services from other parts of the country. Sometimes a historic buildingcan be adapted at comparatively little cost certainly less than the costof a new centre and used as an arts centre. When this happens twoobjects are achieved in one. Examples are, on a large scale, Temple Newsamoutside Leeds and Corsham Court in Wiltshire, and on a smaller scale the adaptation of Canonbury Tower, for a theatre and arts centre in Islington.54. It is to be hoped that one day fine permanent buildings for housing the arts will be universally available. But in the meantime enterprisinglocalities might well investigate the possibility of mobile art centres andtravelling theatres. This means growing accustomed to some of the latest developments in building techniques. Temporary inflatable structures arealready in use in industry. All that is needed is to find models that canbe given the gay &apos; Come to the Fair&apos; atmosphere essential for recreationalpurposes. Besides providing much needed colour in the immediate future,these temporary theatres could help to create the climate of opinion needed to encourage expenditure from the rates on permanent buildings.55. The recent actions of the Arts Council in launching an enquiry into the future needs of the provincial theatre and a second enquiry intoways of bringing the theatre to children are welcome and point the way to future developments.56. As new theatres come to be built, there is a strong case for standardis-ing backstage fitments and equipment. In some countries, notably west germany, this is already done. It makes the work of touring companiesvery much easier.&quot; 57. Under the present town planning law a building which is in use as a theatre may be put to a variety of other uses without the need forprior planning permission. This has resulted in the loss of existing theatres.The Government regard this as unsatisfactory and they have therefore decidedto amend the relevant statutory instrument the Town and Country Planning(Use Classes) Order, 1963 (in Scotland, the Town and Country Planning
(Use Classes) (Scotland) Order, 1950) so as to limit to use as a music hallor as a cinema, the changes of use from a theatre which, under the termsof the Order, can be carried out without involving the need for planning permission.The Influence of Education58. Almost all the activities described in this White Paper are linkeddirectly or indirectly with education. If children at an early age becomeaccustomed to the idea of the arts as a part of everyday life, they are more likely in maturity first to accept and then to demand them. The links arenot limited to the primary and secondary schools : they extend to the artschools, the colleges of further education, the colleges of education for teachers, the universities and the classes for adults. The place that the artsoccupy in the life of the nation is largely a reflection of the time and effortdevoted to them in schools and colleges.59. Nearly all children enjoy singing and dancing and most of themdelight in poetry and in mime or dramatic exercises. There is no moreexcited audience at the right play. Many of them have a natural talent forpainting and drawing, and for making things, that surprises their parents.60. Many schools, particularly perhaps primary schools, have successfullyfostered these abilities, and in some of the arts the schools have had notablehelp from radio and television. But too often, as boys and girls grow up,the impetus seems to weaken, so that as adults we are more vulnerable than we should be to criticisms of our inadequate uses of literacy, of our failure to appreciate poetry, of our limited tastes in music and drama, of ourignorance of the visual arts and of our blindness to good design.61. Here is a challenge to the schools, and many of them are alreadyshowing that it can be met. The imagination and free flow of some of thewriting in prose and poetry, the quality of some of the painting and pottery,and the high standard of some of the choral singing and of the orchestralplaying, culminating in the National Youth Orchestra, outshine the achieve-ments of any previous generation.   But the base is still too narrow.62. In these efforts the schools need the support both of their communities and of the expert practitioners in the various arts. This begins with thequality of the school buildings themselves. There are schools built since1945 where children have shown how they appreciate and respect well-designed buildings, enlivened by the occasional mural or piece of sculpture,stimulating colours, well-chosen furniture and fittings and skilful landscaping.Many schools, too, have shown the benefits that can be derived fromarranging close links with local museums, theatres and arts centres, fromencouraging performances by school children to wider audiences, frominviting experts in the various arts to talk about their activities anddemonstrate them, and from arranging visits by school children to exhibitionsand performances.63. As such activities become more widespread, more and more people will be inclined as they grow up to practise and appreciate the arts. Theprofessionals of the future will require more and better facilities for their training, the amateurs will swell the growing ranks of those who attend the already remarkable variety of part-time classes or occasional lectures, andthe arts as a whole will reach wider and better informed audiences.
64. Success will depend to a great extent on what is done in the places where research is undertaken, where standards are set and where expertpractitioners are educated. A major responsibility therefore lies with the universities, with the colleges of education for teachers, and with the schools and colleges specialising in art, ballet, drama, music and opera. For example,the work of the National Advisory Council for Diplomas in Art and Designshould lead to a marked improvement in higher education in art, and theRoyal College of Art has shown how immediate an influence a leadingeducational institution can have not only on the standards of individualartistic achievement but on the quality of design in commerce, fashion andindustry.65. But ample scope remains for further effort. Not all universities and colleges can claim that they have yet done their utmost to foster knowledge and appreciation of the arts, either within or outside their own boundaries.66. The role of education should not be interpreted too narrowly. It istrue that much will have been achieved when many more people have becomeacquainted with the arts and have come to realise the interest and enjoymentthat can lie in well-written books, good plays, more demanding programmeson radio and television, concerts of serious music and exhibitions of greatpictures. But surroundings are important as well, and here too the arts can make an invaluable contribution. In this connection the Government willcontinue to support the Council of Industrial Design. They welcome the encouragement that the Council are giving to good industrial design in a wide range of products in everyday use at home and at work.67. The crafts also have an important contribution to make in the field of education and leisure pursuits as well as in their influence on good design.In an age of progress the traditional crafts must move with the times and theGovernment will encourage them to take their place in future developments.68. The quality of buildings and of the setting in which they stand alsoexerts an important influence on our lives. This brings into the picture notonly the aesthetic merit of the buildings themselves but the contribution thatsculpture, other works of art and landscaping can make to the environment a contribution that also helps the arts by providing opportunities for sculptors,artists and landscape architects.69. In the buildings for which they are themselves directly responsible theGovernment will continue to pay regard in all appropriate cases to theimportance of this kind of contribution ; and whenever practicable they willmake a suitable provision. They hope that local authorities, New TownCorporations and other public bodies, some of whom have already done muchin this way, will follow the same policy. They hope, too, that private donorswill support these efforts.70. In existing buildings too the Government would like to see more and better pictures displayed. They intend to arrange for this in those of theirown buildings that are suitable, either by buying the work of living artists orby local loans.71. Appreciation of this kind of good design is not the end of the matter.Indeed, diffusion of culture is now so much a part of life that there is no precise point at which it stops. Advertisements, buildings, books, motor cars,radio and television, magazines, records, all can carry a cultural aspect and
affect our lives for good or ill as a species of &quot; amenity &quot;. No democratic government would seek to impose controls on all the things that contribute to our environment and affect our senses. But abuses can be spotted andtackled, high standards encouraged, and opportunities given for widerenjoyment. It is partly a question of bridging the gap between what have come to be called the &quot; higher &quot; forms of entertainment and the traditionalsources, the brass band, the amateur concert party, the entertainer, the musichall and popgroup and to challenge the fact that a gap exists. In the worldof jazz the process has already happened ; highbrow and lowbrow have met.72. Radio and television have much to contribute to the encouragement of artistic activity and appreciation. If little is said about them in this white paper it is largely because in this field the Government has no direct respon-sibility. These media are managed by public corporations whose relationship with the Government is denned by statute. How the corporations use broad-casting time and deploy their resources is for them to decide.73. But it is clear that radio and television have enormous opportunitiesin the sphere of the arts, and their responsibilities to the nation are corre-correspondingly great. Radio has done much for drama, music and poetry. Theuse of television for similar purposes is still at a relatively early stage, but itis to be hoped that the introduction of additional channels for television will encourage further experiment and development. If in time a greater numberof local stations is set up, these will have an important part to play in the encouragement of local artistic activity and the enrichment and diversificationof regional cultures.The Governments Proposals74. Government aid to the arts has hitherto been on a relatively modest scale, and has grown up in response to spasmodic pressures rather than asa result of a coherent plan.75. The same picture emerges locally. There is no common pattern amonglocal authorities when it comes to support for the arts. Some are generous,some have no regard for art at all, and sometimes such facilities as thereare, for instance a library or museum, are not used to the best advantage.76. There is ample evidence of the need for a more coherent, generous andimaginative approach to the whole problem. It will take time to work out such a policy in full detail. In the meantime the need for further progress is urgent. The Government has decided therefore to advance by stages, at each stage making the necessary assistance available in support of thefollowing objectives:Today&apos;s artists need more financial help, particularly in the early years before they have become established.   Their ability to develop and sustain a high level of artistic achievement lies at the centre of&apos; any national policy for the arts.The Government hopes to see a great increase in local and regionalactivity, while maintaining the development of the national institutions.They are convinced that the interests of the whole country will be bestserved in this way.The Government appreciates the need to sustain and strengthen allthat is best in the arts, and the best must be made more widely available.There is need for more systematic planning and a better co-ordinationof resources.
.77. With these objectives in mind the Government have reviewed theirown administrative arrangements. They have reached the conclusion that thetime has come for the Governments responsibility for the Arts to be centredin a Department other than the Treasury, since public expenditure on the arts has developed to a stage when it has already become anomalous forthe Treasury to remain the sponsoring Department. These functions are accordingly being transferred to the Secretary of State for Education and science, who will delegate responsibility to one of the Joint parliamentary under-Secretaries of State in his Department. Appropriate arrangements will be made to meet the special interests of Scotland and Wales. Thenecessary administrative changes are being put in hand immediately.78. The greater part of Exchequer aid is channelled through the arts council. This arrangement will be maintained within the broader contextnow set by the Governments policy and with due regard to the pattern of developments described in this White Paper. Similarly bodies such as the historic Buildings Councils, the British Council and the Council of IndustrialDesign will continue to play an invaluable part in their respective fields.79. Notwithstanding the difficulties of the present situation the Govern-ment propose to increase substantially their grant to the Arts Council. In1964-65 the Council received from the Exchequer  2,150,000 (excluding thegrant in respect of Covent Garden). The figure for 1965-66 (again excludingCovent Garden but including the new expenditure incurred as a result of commitments on housing the arts and the extra subsidies for young artists)will be  2,815,000.80. Among other things this will enable the Arts Council to make a largercontribution to regional associations, to increase their assistance to theleading artistic enterprises in Scotland and Wales, to ease the financialburdens of provincial repertory theatres, to give a much needed impetusto the development of Arts Centres and to provide additional assistance for first class orchestras. The position of the London orchestras is now underconsideration by a committee under the chairmanship of Mr. ArnoldGoodman. It is recognised that action to implement the recommendationsof the Goodman Committee may require a further subvention of the majorsymphony orchestras and other musical groups. In addition the Arts council has been asked to review its requirements for this year and to submit revised proposals for certain specialised projects which can reasonably be advancedduring the coming year. On receipt of these additional estimates the Govern-ment will, in the light of the prevailing economic situation, give sympathetic consideration to asking Parliament for additional funds during the financialyear 1965-66.81. In order to bring the best of the Arts within reach of a widerpublic, greater use might be made of the subsidised travel for specialoccasions which the Arts Council already operates, and the practice of givingspecially reduced theatre prices to students and to special groups shouldbe. more widely, adopted. Looking further ahead, as development becomespossible, it will be desirable to provide more generally attractive restaurants,lecture rooms or other amenities for visitors who may travel long distancesto the national institutions. The question of adjusting opening hours ofmuseums and galleries to enable visits to be made out of school and working hours will need to be considered.   In these ways our most precious national
treasures, usually housed in the capital cities, and often difficult or impossibleto transport without undue cost and risk, could be more widely enjoyed.82. In addition to Arts Council expenditure, the purchase grants to localmuseums made through the Victoria and Albert and Royal Scottish museumswill be increased from  54,000 in 1964-65 to  108,000 in 1965-66. In con-sultation with the Standing Commission the present basis of Exchequer grants to the Area Councils will be reviewed to see whether a more flexible arrange-ment can be made.83. As has been said, one of the main objectives of the government&apos;s policy is to encourage the living artist. At present the young artist, havingfinished his schooling, has still to gain experience and has difficulty inobtaining employment. Many turn aside to other types of employmentbecause the life of the artist is too precarious, and their talents are not used to the best advantage. Artists, poets, sculptors, writers, and musiciansare sometimes lost to art for lack of a comparatively small sum of money which would support their start in life. The increase in the Governmenfsgrant to the Arts Council will enable them to raise from about  10,000 to 50,000 the sum allocated for awards and assistance to young artists inall fields. Awards can be used for travelling abroad and study if so desired.84. In the field of literature several schemes for providing financialassistance to authors have been put forward. Proposals have been made tothe Government by the Society of Authors and others on behalf, for example,of young authors of special promise before they have been able to established themselves, of authors in mid-career who are prevented by lack of funds from undertaking prolonged research required for some work of particularscholastic value, and of older authors who are suffering hardship.85. Various sources have been suggested from which the necessary fundsmight be drawn. One possible source is private contributions which inthe past have provided useful assistance on a modest scale. As anotherpossibility the Governmenfs attention has been drawn to developmentsoverseas, notably in Sweden where the necessary finance is provided bythe State, and in France where it is supplied from a variety of sourcesincluding a levy on the turnover of publishing firms. Another suggestionreceived by the Government is that the law of copyright might be amended so as to extend the period during which royalties are payable to, say, 60years (instead of 50 years) after the author&apos;s death, but to provide that forthe last ten years the royalties would be payable not to the author&apos;s estatebut to a fund administered by a statutory body for the benefit of livingauthors.86. Some of those who have made representations to the Governmenthave suggested that any scheme should be limited to literature and, so far asbenefits are concerned, to authors. Others would prefer to extend the scope.87. The Government propose to examine these matters further in con-sultation with the interested parties.88. In an age of increasing automation bringing more leisure to more people than ever before, both young and old will increasingly need the stimulus and refreshment that the arts can bring.   If one side of life is
highly mechanised, another side must provide for diversity, adventure,opportunities both to appreciate and to participate in a wide range of individual pursuits. An enlightened Government has a duty to respond tothese needs.89. But there can be no compulsion of any kind in this most sensitivefield of human endeavour. Nor must Government support be given only toestablished institutions. New ideas, new values, the involvement of large sections of the community hitherto given little or no opportunity to appreciate the best in the arts, all have their place. It will take time for the arts council and other organisations working in this field to adjust their plans tothe wider opportunities now offered to them.90. Compared with many other civilised countries we have been in the habit of financing some fields of the arts on no more than a poor reliefbasis. However, as a first step towards a new policy, the Arts Councilgrant (excluding Covent Garden) in 1965-66 will be higher by  665,000(30 per cent.) than in 1964-65, or nearly  500,000 higher than the 1965-66figure agreed two years ago under the triennial plan.91. Even more important are the three new points of departure that under-line the seriousness of the Governmenfs intention to follow up these firststeps as rapidly as possible with further aid where the need for aid isproved.92. For the first time a building fund has been established to encouragelocal authorities and regional associations to come forward with buildingplans. The sum allocated, a quarter of a million, is modest comparedwith expenditure in some other fields, but because of the delays, inevitable and otherwise, in starting new projects, its provision represents a challengeas well as welcome material encouragement. It is now up to the localauthorities and the other agencies concerned to prove by their response,that the Government would be justified in the following financial year inentering into substantially higher levels of commitment.93. The Goodman Committee has been asked to provide precise authori-tative information on the proper cost of maintaining our great Londonorchestras, and the Government have made plain their recognition that additional funds may be required for this purpose. 794. The Arts Council is being invited to review its requirements for thecoming year and to submit revised proposals for certain specialised projects.95. Some local authorities will need a good deal of persuading before they are convinced that the money it is in their power to spend on artsand amenities is money well spent and deserving a much higher prioritythan hitherto. But it can be done. All new social services have to fightlong and hard before they establish themselves. Only yesterday it wasthe fight for a free health service. The day before it was the struggle towin education for all.96. Today a searching reappraisal of the whole situation in relation tocultural standards and opportunities is in progress. More and more peoplebegin to appreciate that the exclusion of so many for so long from the best of our cultural heritage can become as damaging to the privileged minorityas to the under-privileged majority. We walk the same streets, breathethe same air, are exposed to the same sights and sounds.
97. Nor can we ignore the growing revolt, especially among the young,against the drabness, uniformity and joylessness of much of the socialfurniture we have inherited from the industrial revolution. This canbe directed, if we so wish, into making Britain a gayer and more cultivatedcountry. It is fitting that the present Government should seek to encourageall who are furthering these aims. The proposals outlined in this white paper, though no more- than the first steps in the direction of a fullycomprehensive policy for the Arts, demonstrate the Government^ concern that immediate progress should be made towards the new objectives.Printed in England and published by her Majesty&apos;s Stationery Office(32480)   Wt. 1076-257   86  2/65   St.S.
focA^^J- x/oA^t^ - CONFIDENTIAL 152THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HER BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;SGOVERNMENT)COPY NO.CABINETADDENDUMTOC. (65) 22Draft White Paper, page 18^ after paragraph 37Insert paragraphs 87A, 87B and 87C attached hereto.Cabinet Office, S. W. i.16th February, 1965h 0c? 13CONFIDENTIAL

87A.     By far the most valuable help that can be givento the living artist is to provide him with a larger andmore appreciative public.    Everything possible mustbe done to enlarge the area of appreciation of the artswhile at the same time guarding against any lowering of standards.87B.     Concern has been expressed in the press and elsewhere that the independent film producer should notbe crowded out because the distribution of films toexhibitors is in the hands of two main companies, andthe question of supply of films to exhibitors has been referred by the Board of Trade to the monopolies commission.    Further developments must now await the Commission^ report.87C.     The success of such television talks as havealready been given is one among several hearteningexamples both of the willingness of men and women of outstanding talent to co-operate in mass education andof the response that is there to be awakened, given theright kind of approach. ,




</content>
</cab>
