<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 129/120/0 images: 610-622</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OFHER BRITANNIC MAJESTVS GOVERNMENTPrinted for the Cabinet.   March 1965C. (65) 50 Copy No.     5 925th March, 1965CABINETTHE PARLIAMENTARY COMMISSIONERMemorandum by the Chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterA group of Ministers under my Chairmanship has been considering what proposals we should make to Parliament for establishing a Parliamentary Commissioner for administration(Ombudsman). I now recommend for the consideration of mycolleagues a scheme on the lines set out in Part 1 of this paper.Part 2 of the paper sets out certain points which remain for decision.Part 1THE SCHEME2. We want to try to secure that private persons do not sufferinjustice from faulty administration on the part of the centralGovernment. This is one of the functions of the Member ofParliament. Our proposal is to give him a better weapon which hecan use for this purpose.The Parliamentary Commissioner3. The Commissioner, like the Comptroller and Auditor-General, would be appointed by Letters Patent, paid and pensionedfrom the Consolidated Fund, and secure from dismissal, except on a motion of Parliament. He would report annually to Parliament, and otherwise as occasion required. We assume that Parliament would set up a Select Committee to take his reports; but this would not bea matter for the Bill.4. He would act only at the instance of a Member ofParliament and only upon a complaint of personal injustice suffered by the complainant. There would be no obligation upon the member to comply with a citizen&apos;s request that his complaint should go to* The question whether this should include Peers, other than those withleave of absence, is considered in Part 2 of this paper, paragraphs 18-21.
the Commissioner, nor would the Member have to get the citizen&apos;consent to do so. The Member would decide his own course ofaction.5. His aim would be to redress grievances; his quarry wouldbe faults in administration; he would not be able to substitute his discretion for that of a Minister where he found no such fault, nor to criticise policy. We should have liked to have been able to give more positive guidance to the public about the exact nature of thecases which he would pursue, but we have found no satisfactoryform of words for this purpose and we see no escape from leavingmuch to the discretion of the Commissioner himself.Who could complain 6. &quot; Persons &quot; who could complain would include not merelyprivate individuals but also corporate persons, including companies,but not public bodies such as local authorities or the boards of nationalised industries.7.   A complaint would be in order if (i) the complainant is lawfully resident here; or(ii) the matter complained of is treatment received whilelawfully present here; or(iii) the complaint is about administration of a right orobligation arising from previous lawful presence here; or(iv) the complaint is about administration of a legal entitlement. And what about. The bodies whose acts or omissions would be subject to investigation by the Commissioner would be those listed in the annex. The list is designed to enable the Commissioner to cover the whole field of relationships between the governed and the centralGovernment. It does not extend to local government, the police, theNational Health Services or the nationalised industries. The listwould be open to amendment by subordinate instrument.9. It is proposed to exclude the following from the purview ofthe Commissioner:(a) Matters within the competence of (i) the courts (though the Commissioner would have discretion to act if he thought that the remedy openin the courts was not one which the complainantcould reasonably be expected to use);(ii) tribunals and other quasi-judicial bodies;(iii) the   Council   on  Tribunals.   (To   minimise   theproblem of deciding whether the Council or theCommissioner should take borderline cases, theCommissioner would be an ex officio member ofthe Council.)(b) Decisions whether or not to institute criminal proceedings.(c) The exercise of the Prerogative of Mercy.
(d) The exercise of powers by the central Government in relationto investigating crime or preserving the safety of the State.(e) Matters certified by the Foreign Secretary, commonwealth secretary, Colonial Secretary, President of the Board ofTrade or Minister of Overseas Development to affectoverseas relationsjftouL AnoJ^MS /wJUdaw%J&amp; dka--(/) Purely commercial relationships of Departments withcustomers or suppliers (or would-be customers orsuppliers). For the Post Office, this would be interpretedto cover all their dealings except as agents of otherDepartments or in relation to National Savings and tocertain of their functions concerning wireless telegraphy.(g) The employment of Crown servants (including former officersof countries gaining independence); and personnelmatters, orders and discipline in the Armed Forces.(h) The conferment of honours and privileges (such as grants of royal Charters or the title Royal) by the Crown; andappointments by the Crown or by Ministers.10. A case would ordinarily have to be raised within 12 monthsof the complainant becoming aware of the matter complained of,although the Commissioner would have discretion to waive this time limit.11. While a case was being investigated by the Commissioner,it would remain within the discretion of the Minister concerned toproceed with action relating to it.Powers of the Commissioner12. The Commissioner would have power to take evidence onoath. This power would, we expect, be used infrequently; but itmight prove important when the Commissioner was obtainingevidence from third parties. The Commissioner would have powerto call for evidence from any party to a dispute, including the complainant whether or not his prior consent to the matter going tothe Commissioner had been obtained by the Member of Parliament.The sanction to be invoked in the event of defiance of theCommissioner would be to refer the offence to the High Court (Courtof Session in Scotland) for consideration as if it were contempt ofthat Court.13. Ministers would be empowered to prohibit theCommissioner to publish or disclose evidence, on grounds of publicinterest or national security.How the Commissioner would work14. Normally, the Commissioner would begin with theevidence contained in the correspondence conducted by the Memberof Parliament, which might be amplified by oral or written statements.If the Commissioner found that this was not enough, he would beable to ask for fuller explanations, written or oral, including detailsof correspondence exchanged in the case, and, in the last resort, for
the departmental file. (The problems that would arise if theCommissioner believed that relevant information which he could not otherwise obtain was contained in Cabinet or Cabinet Committeepapers are examined in Part 2 of this paper, paragraphs 22-27.)Where the Commissioner was able to dispose of the complaint, with or without further action by the Department, there would be noquestion of his disclosing the content of departmental minutes to the complainant or to anyone else. But in the rare case where theCommissioner and the Department were unable to agree, so that thematter had to be referred to the Select Committee, the Commissionermight find it necessary to reveal information obtained from the files,or even from departmental minutes; but even in these circumstancesMinisters would be empowered to prohibit publication of evidence on grounds of public interest or of national security.15. The Commissioner^ procedure v/ould be flexible. In a normal case, we envisage that it would be on the following lines:(a) The complaint would be made in the first place to a Memberof Parliament. It would be for him to decide whether to invoke the Commissioner.(b) If the Member of Parliament referred the case to theCommissioner, and the Commissioner decided to investigate it, he would in his discretion take evidence from both parties, and from any third party involved.(c) If necessary, he would have access to the Department^ file.(d) Where the Commissioner had carried his inquiries as far ashe could on the basis of action taken by officials and thought it necessary to take the matter further, he would bring to the Minister^ notice any difficulty he had in reaching a conclusion. It would then rest with theMinister whether to provide him with an explanation.There might be a rare case where the Minister mightdecline to do so. Some convention&apos; would need to beestablished for handling such a situation vis-a-vis boththe Commissioner and the Select Committee. But thiswould not be for the Bill.(e) In a case where the Commissioner found nothing wrong, hewould merely inform the Member. If he found there wasjustifiable cause for complaint, and the Departmentresponded to his invitation to put it right, he would, again,inform the Member. So far as the Commissioner was concerned, this would be the end of the matter, save forhis annual report to Parliament. There would be nothing to preclude a Member from raising any of these issuesin Parliament.(/) If the Department did not act to the Commissioner^satisfaction, he could report his conclusion to Parliamentad hoc. It would then be for Parliament (through any committee set up for the purpose) to decide what action,if any, was called for on their part. The Bill would notdetermine this.
(g) The Commissioner would in any event submit, an annual report to Parliament. In this he might well comment ondefects in the system which had come to his notice as aresult of investigating individual complaints, and it wouldbe for Parliament, through its Committee, to consider how these matters should be pursued.16. The Commissioner would be empowered to decide whetherthe parties could be legally represented; but since we want him to beseen by the ordinary citizen as someone to whom his case can gowithout formality or expense, legal representation should be theexception, not the rule. The Commissioner would have discretion toallow reasonable expenses imposed by his requirements on the complainant and on third parties. The procedure would not be withinthe compass of legal aid.Part 2POINTS FOR DECISION17. There are two issues which my Committee thought shouldbe reserved for decision by the Cabinet.(a) Access through Members of Parliament; Peers and Commoners18.   My Committee first considered three broad possibilities:(i) people should be able to go direct to the Commissioner, asa public institution, like the courts; or(ii) they should be able to go direct to him only with the leave of their Member of Parliament or after failure on his part to satisfy them; or(iii) he should be a Parliamentary institution, to be used byMembers only.We ruled out (ii): to give a citizen a right to seek redress and then to put the Member in a statutory position to veto, delay or qualifythe exercise of that right seemed indefensible. While (i) escapes this objection, we have to reconcile the appointment of a Commissionerwith the rights and duties of Members of Parliament withoutdiminishing the valuable work they do on behalf of their constituentsand the public generally. We decided, after long consideration, that(iii) would achieve this: just as the Comptroller and Auditor-general was created as Parliamenfs watch-dog over Government expenditure,so the Commissioner could be appointed as Parliamenfs watch-dogover administration. The Ombudsman in Britain would be brought within the framework of our Parliamentary practice, and we thoughtthat public opinion would understand and accept that he should bea Parliamentary and not a public institution. He would be the means whereby Members would have the opportunity of better and more effective service to their constituents. This is what we have
recommended. But it also brought us to the question whether theCommissioner should be at the service of Peers (excluding those with leave of absence) as well as of Commoners.19. As regards the position of individual Members in each house, it was argued, on the one hand, that to enable Peers to invokethe Commissioner would hardly be consistent with the view that we proposed to take of the Commissioner as a servant of Parliament,to be approached through the representative of the public inParliament. Peers, though in some sense &quot; representative&quot;constitutionally, are not representatives of a constituency and peopledo not generally think of them in their representative capacity. Onthe other hand, it was pointed out that it is already the practice for members to take up matters raised by persons not in their constituencies, and there would be difficulties in trying to impose a rule that no Member other than the constituency Member shouldever refer the case to the Commissioner. In any case no such rulecould be universal since there are persons with no constituency (forexample, prisoners or residents abroad); and others with links with several constituencies (for instance, companies). Moreover, the complainant himself might be inhibited from seeking reference tothe Commissioner if he could do so only through a constituencyMember with whom he might not be in sympathy; or the Membermight be embarrassed by a request to refer a case, if for instance,he were a Minister in the Department complained against. If this line of argument is accepted, the case for excluding Peers ismaterially weakened. Moreover, Peers already put Questions to ministers about individual cases. If they were excluded from using the Commissioner they would be at a disadvantage in doing socompared with their colleagues in the other House, and this could lead to a clash between the two Houses, in which the Peers mightwell have public opinion on their side. There should be no difficultyin working a convention that any Member of either House who isnot the constituency Member and who receives a complaint whichhe wants to refer to the Commissioner should tell the constituencyMember about it.20. As regards the position of the two Houses in thearrangements made for receiving and acting upon reports from theCommissioner, it would be for Parliament to set up whatevermachinery it thought best to receive the Commissioner^ reports, butwe assume that they are likely to set up a Select Committee. this body might occasionally need to seek evidence from a Minister; anda Minister might perhaps even find that he had to defend himself on the floor of the House. It may not be inconceivable that a Ministersitting in the Lords should be asked to give evidence to a SelectCommittee drawn wholly from the Commons; but there would be some awkwardness in a situation where strictures from such aCommittee could be answered ultimately only on the floor of theother House.. This would be avoided if the Committee were a jointCommittee of both Houses; but then we should face the difficulty ofbalancing the membership of the Committee to represent both theHouses and the Parties.
21.  The question is:(1) whether Peers should have access to the Commissioner;(2) whether the Commissioner^ reports should be received bya Select Committee drawn only from the Commons orfrom a Select Committee of both Houses.(b) Access of the Commissioner to Cabinet and Cabinet Committeepapers and to the Cabinet Office22. Cabinet or Cabinet Committee proceedings, being mainly concerned with policy, would not normally be relevant to theCommissioner^ inquiries. But once in a while the matter might turn, for instance, on a Departments interpretation of a cabinet decision.23. We are agreed that there is no question of theCommissioner having access automatically to Cabinet or CabinetCommittee papers. The question is whether (i) there should be an absolute rule debarring the Commissioner from access to suchpapers, or (ii) there should be some procedure for giving himinformation from that source if ever he found himself unable toreach a decision without it.24. Our general preference is for (ii), and for the followingreason: though the exercise of discretion over access to cabinet or Cabinet Committee papers could be embarrassing, so also coulda report by the Commissioner that, while he thought there mighthave been defective administration, he could not be sure since thecase turned on what was in those papers, and he did not have access to them.25. Any discretion in this matter should rest with the PrimeMinister. But the Commissioner should in any case be prohibited from publishing information from this source, or indeed anything that he might glean about Cabinet or Cabinet Committeeproceedings from any other source, for example, from briefs onDepartments&apos; files.26. Whether we debar the Commissioner from access to cabinet and Cabinet Committee papers altogether or whether weallow it within the Prime Ministers discretion, the implication forthe Cabinet Office itself is the same: it would be wrong to includeit within the Commissioner^ scope. This would almost certainlymean that it would need to be specifically excepted in the Bill.27.  The questions are:(3) whether there should be an absolute ban on theCommissioner having access to Cabinet or CabinetCommittee papers; or(4) whether the Cabinet Office, under the Prime Ministersdirection, should control access by the commissioner to those papers, providing information only to theextent that it was shown to be necessary and subject toan absolute ban on its disclosure by the Commissioner;and ;(5) whether the Cabinet Office itself should be excepted fromthe Commissioner^ scope.
CONCLUSION28. Subject to decisions on the questions put in paragraphs 21and 27, I seek approval to the scheme outlined in paragraphs 2-16,and a decision on our next steps. There is considerable public and parliamentary interest in.the matter. Therefore, if a place cannotbe found this Session for a Bill setting up the Commissioner, should we publish our proposals in a White Paper? If so, what should the timing be?D. H.Whitehall, S.W.1,23rd March, 1965.
AnnexSCHEDULE OF DEPARTMENTS TO BE SUBJECT TO THEPARLIAMENTARY COMMISSIONERMinistry of Agriculture, Fisheries and food ministry of AviationOffice of the Chancellor of the Duchy of LancasterCivil Service CommissionColonial office commonwealth Relations OfficeCrown Estate OfficeCustoms and ExciseMinistry of defence department of Economic AffairsDepartment of Education and Science*Export Credits Guarantee DepartmentForeign OfficeGeneral Register OfficeGeneral Registry Office, ScotlandMinistry of HealthHome office ministry of Housing and Local GovernmentCentral Office of InformationInland Revenue*Ministry of labour ministry of Land and Natural ResourcesLand Registry*Lord Chancellor^ Department^Office of the Lord Privy SealNational Assistance board national Debt OfficeOrdnance SurveyMinistry of Overseas DevelopmentOffice of the Paymaster GeneralMinistry of Pensions and National Insurance tPost office ministry of PowerDepartment of Procurator-General and Treasury SolicitorMinistry of Public Building and WorksPublic Record OfficePublic Trustee*Department of Registers of ScotlandRegistry of Friendly Societies*Royal Mint* Except judicial and .quasi-judicial elements and the offices of courts ortribunals.t Except administration of the King&apos;s Fund, of which the Minister is managingtrustee.
Scottish office department of Agriculture and Fisheries for ScotlandScottish Development department Scottish Education department Scottish Home and Health Department .Scottish Record OfficeHer Majesty&apos;s Stationery- office ministry of TechnologyBoard of trade ministry of TransportTreasury and subordinate departments * (other than the cabinet office)Office of the Minister without PortfolioWelsh OfficeTo be set up:Land Commission* Except judicial and quasi-judicial elements and the offices of courts ortribunals.

Scottish office department of Agriculture and Fisheries for ScotlandScottish Development department Scottish Education department Scottish Home and Health department Scottish Record OfficeHer Majesty&apos;s Stationery- office ministry of TechnologyBoard of trade ministry of TransportTreasury and subordinate departments * (other than the cabinet office)Office of the Minister without PortfolioWelsh OfficeTo be set up :Land Commission* Except judicial and quasi-judicial elements and the offices of courts ortribunals.


</content>
</cab>
