<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 65/11/40 images: 644-649</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENTTO BE KEPT UNDER LOCK AND KW.It is requested that special care may be taken tosecrecy of this document.Y,l.jT   SECRET -COPY NO.I2l.M.(40) 54th CONCLUSIONS, MINUTE 4.Confidential Annex.(28th February, 1940).ASSISTANCETO FINLAND.(previous reference:W.M.(40) 53rdConclusions,Minute 10).THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN affairs said that he had that morning seen the Finnish Minister,who had said that he had been instructed by hisGovernment to enquire whether it would be possible &quot;to shorten the time mentioned by Brigadier Ling&quot;, and tosend a reply as soon as possible.THE CHIEF OF THE AIR STAFF said that theChiefs of Staff were satisfied that this time couldnot be shortened.THE CHIEF OF THE IMPERIAL GENERAL STAFF saidthat the limiting factor was the time which it wouldtake to prepare the base;   and it would be very unwise,as History showed, to resort to hurried improvisationsin this matter.     Once the preparation of the base hadbeen completed and the force had been landed at Narvik,it was possible that the subsequent operation might be accelerated if we obtained satisfactory co-operation from the Norwegians and Swedes;   and more particularly if arrangements could be made to ensure a quick passage through Haparanda.     The importunity of the Finns mightbe due to the ill-judged and irresponsible pressure ofFrench circles in Helsinki, who, without a knowledge ofthe facts,, were always suggesting that matters mightbe hurried.

THE PRIME MINISTER said that the urgency of the Finnish enquiry would he more understandableif they had in mind that our troops should be usedfor the reinforcement of the critical situationwhich had arisen in Southern Finland.     But ithad been made clear that our troops were not tobe used south of a certain line which excludedthis area,THE SECRETARY OF STATIi FOR FOREIGN affairs said that it was clear that the most truthful andleast discouraging reply to the Finns would be atelegram stating that no acceleration of the landing of the expedition could be effected, but that withsatisfactory co-operation on the part of the norwegians and Swedes it might be possible to shorten the programme after the landing.     He asked that theChief of the Imperial General Staff might help inthe drafting of a telegram to this effect.The War cabinet invited the Foreign Secretary, inconsultation with the Chief of theImperial General Staff, to send a reply to the Finnish enquiry onthe lines proposed.Richmond Terrace, S.W.I.




</content>
</cab>
