<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 95-106</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS  DOOUCSHI  IS  THE PROPERTY  OP  HIS  BRIT AM IG MAJESTIES GOVERNMENT)           A                    CABINET.                    \j I                                 E g Y P T.               Copy of Be cypher Telegrams^ from Lord Allenpy.; Telegram from Lord  Allonby (unnumbered) dat od. 15th January,1922,Sub-0ommit1.eoo Most  Urgent.Private and personala          Sir Gilbert Clayton and Mr0 Selby two days  agosaw two prominent members of Wafd who are  seceding  fromreconstituted bodyB          As a preliminary to discussion they wore  asAedwhether they accepted condition that all territory  ofEgypt was necessary for defence of Imperial Communicationsof Great Britain, that is to say that no Foreign power could under any circumstances whatsoever be allowed toestablish itself or intorvone in internal affairs ofEgypt,          They replied that they absolutely accepted thisview and Indicated they would bo ready to support a policysuch as that outlined in my proposed letter to Sultan,adding that in such ciroumstancoa it would be desirablethat a member of Saadist party 3hould be included in cabinet.   They suggested Mustapha Mahor,   Sarwat  Pashahas already secured agrooment of lattor to join Cabinat.          They further expressed their opinion that under no circumstances should Saad Zagloul be allowed to  returnto Egypt.   This is general feeling in all circles  desirous of carrying through a settlement.
No.2.

Telegram from Lord Allenby No. 17 dated 12th January, 1922.

SUB-COMMITTEE. VERY URGENT.

Following is list referred to in my telegram No. 18.

Abdel Khalek Sarwat Pasha, ex-minister,

Ismail Sidky Pash, ex-minister,

Ibrahim Fatlon Pasha, ex-minster,

Geafor Wali Pasha, ex-minister,

Mustafa Fatlon Pasha, procureur-general,

Mustafa Maher Pasha, ex-official Works Ministry

and vice-president of general agricultural syndicate,

Mohammed Shukry Pasha, ex-under-Secretary of State Ministry of Justice.

Wassif Simoika Bey, judge of native court of appeal.


telegram from  Lord Allenby  No. 19, dated 12th  JanuaryuJ-jJ&amp;S. SUS-00M?nTTBE.          Your telegram No. 534.          My immediately following telegram contains coxt of a  letter which I  propose, with Your Lordship&apos;s approval, to address to  the Sultan and to publish simultaneously with announcement of formation of Sarwat Pasha1s Ministry. Sarwat  called  on  me this evening and submitted list ccn- tained  in my Immediately preceding telegram as having definitely  agreed to accept office under him on the policy outlined in my proposed letter to the Sultan.   List is a strong  and  representative one and Sarwat is undoubtedly rallying to himself all the beet elements in the country.          Paragraphs one to four of my &quot;proposed letter are designed to emphasise the more conciliatory parts of recent letter  I was instructed to address to  the Sultan.  Paragraph 5  comments  on  provisions of proposed draft treaty which have been  the particular subject of misrepresentation,  paragraph 7  explains  my  object in dealing with Saghloul and his chief supporters.     After re-assorting in paragraphs 8 and 9 friendly intentions of His Majesty-&apos;a Government, I assent in paragraphs  10  and 11 to main provisions of Sarwat13 prdgramm Paragraph 13 roaervos for subsequent negotiation matters in- eluded  in proposed draft treaty which do not find place in Sarwat&apos;s programme with tho exception of section 9;  this matter  Can  be  dealt with separately when Egyptian government desires to  raise  it, and I  need only say that Sarwat Pasha&apos;s views on tho subject are quite moderate,          Reservation A.   overs retention of  troops in the country.    This is our essential and effective safeguard: it has  formed  tea strength  of our position in Egypt in the past and is in no way impaired by present proposals. Reservation B.  is designed  to cover in particular clauses 6, 11 and 14 of suggested convention.   Reservation 0.
 to cover clauses 9, 12, IS; 15, 15, 18 and 23 to 26..           Your Lordship $ill,observe, however, that paragraph 10 of my proposed latter makes a concession as regards pro 1; so tor at o which goes further than explanation of Sarwat1 s. programme convoyed in first paragraph of my telegram No. 6 66.           I returned&apos; in fact to proposal made in my telegram No. 664 that His Ma jo sty&apos; a Government should support in Parliament abolition of protectorate.   In this con- nection I do not t forgot statement  in. your &apos; telegram No.536 that suggestion that His Majesty&apos;s. Government should agree to do this in the hope of obtaining a ministry would have been quite unacceptable.           I&apos; am therefore,  though in slightly different circumstances since that hope is now cortsrinty, again pro nosing a course inconsistent , with decision of His Majesty&apos;s ubvernmout, but it is only.course which I sea my way to pursuing.&quot;        1   In. final &quot;paragraph of. previous letter to the Sultan, it Is stated that His Majesty&apos;s. Government are prepared to consider any methods which may bo suggested in a spirit of co-operation for carrying, out substance of their proposals;  present scheme is such a method.&apos;  (See  t in t his. connectIo&apos;n&quot;paragraph 13 of my Immediately follow- ing telegram)-.                  ..           -My proposed letter, is result of exhaustive&apos; negotiations with&apos;Sarwat Pasha and his immediate adherents. They,,on the If part, &quot;have bee n in  contact, with-wider circle and Ally Pasha&apos;-has been.in close touch- and has&apos;lentvaluable and disinterested assistance-. .... .--           Peportati on of - Saghloul  Pasha was f-Ol lowed by less disturbance and of shorter duration than might well have been expe;selected -and  there .1sya large body of opinion&quot; which regard&apos; It as necessary and desirable seeing&apos; it in
its true character, not as an  act of arbitrary ratribu-tion, but as an essential preliminary to a final attemptto realise the friendly relations with Great Britainwhich in spite of disappointment, they still desiro andwhich aro sdrely a necossity to His Majostys Government.I am convinced that there is no other meane of maintainingfriendly disposition of those political elements inEgypt, who, through times difficult enough, for themselves have helped us and doalt straightforwardly with us, andof assuaging hostility of others, than to give thispledge regarding abolition of protectorate.  ,1 sm-..equally convinced that this is the moment to give if.Atmosphere which has boob mo calm, and is now expo o toutis not likely, to : remain so without a striking act of conciliation, on  our part and if &quot;expectations aro again.disappointed j I despair not only, of forming an.EgyptianMinistry,- but.of any future- except a stats.- of alter-hating outbreaks and repressions of which I have already had sufficient. experience which are detrimental both, to egypt, and to Great Britain,-and of which end would boin. default of complete- Capitulation on - our part,,anno . at ion ,and - arbitrary, government of a bitterly hostilecountry. .      .                             &apos; --!,   .          I can  conceive, of ho more lamentable end to our work in Egypt which we have.- been accus accustomed to- hold upto-; the admiration of the world.&quot;                  .          My views, have the solid and&apos;whole-hoartod ,.support of my advisors without the least divergence and i must very earnestly bag, Your,.l.ordship to obtain the approvof His. Majesty&apos;s Government to terms  of..this &quot;letter .-without -modi float ion, and to authorise, me to. address it -,to  the : S ul.taa,. without- delay..;, ;&apos;-i          I -urgently i&quot;) a &quot;ins t -early reply by telegraph. .
Ho, 4,(Telegram tfroia. Lord AHeaby no, 19 doted 12 th january&amp;ry, 1922,       Following is  tho  message  referred  to  in my immediately  preceding telegram  from  Sultan  of Egypt;-       Your Highness       li   I  have  the honour  to  bring to  your  highness&apos; notice  that  certain passages of explanatory note which I addressed  to.you  on December  3rd,  1921 have  been interpreted - to  my great disappointment in a manner not in accordance with  intentions and policy of His Majesty1 s Government.                .       S5  Judging by many  comments which have  boon pub- lished on the subject of this note it would appear that- many Egyptians  are  under impression  that Great Britain. is about to  abandon her liberal and  favourable attitude. towards Egyptian  aspirations and that she proposes to make use of  her special  position  in  Egypt in  o*?der  to maintain a political  and administrative  regime incompatible with freedom she  has been offered.       3.  Buch  an interpretation of  intentions of His Maj esty1 s Government is quite mistaken^,  On the contrary explanatory  note  emphasizes  dominating principle that guarantees, claimed  by Great  Britain  are  not designed to involve continuance of an  actual or  virtual protectorate- Great  Britain,  as it is stated  therein,  sincerely desires to see  &quot;an Egypt  enjoying  national prerogatives and  inter- national position of a  sovereign state?*     -.4.-  If Egyptians have  regarded these - guarantees as/
i73 fefi leii.a out of Keep lag -/itii pos itiou oi* u free country they aaye on the other hand lost sight of fact that-Great Britain has &quot;been obliged to claim them out of consideration for her own security in face of a -situation which demands great prudence on her part, particularly in the matter of disposition of her troops. Present  world conditions however and state of effer- . vesoenoo which has prevailed in Egypt since armistice are  .not  perirjaneiit factors and -it is to ho hoped that while on one.hand former will eventually improve, on the other hand time will come when, in language of note, Egypt&apos;e  record will give confidence in her own guarantees,     -5,   As to ..&amp;ny desire to interfere ixi internal administration -.of -Egypt, iftis majesty1 u Government have sufficiently. stated and. repeat that tneir most ardent desire is to place in Egyptian hands conduction of their-,own. affairs.  Draft agreement proposed by. Great Britain does, not depart, from this idea and in making provisional presence of two British Officials in ministries of finance,  and justice it.was not ner intention to use these two  off iGiftls&apos; for the purpose of intervening in Egyptian. affairs  but solely in order to preserve contact requisite for-protecting foreign interests,    - .6.   .Suon is sole bearing of guarantees demanded by. Great. Britain..-&apos;&apos; 3?hey, are claimed without any desire to.-imp^$3r-Egyptitins enjoying full rights, of a national goy ernme nt.     -7,   Animated as -she is with these intentions it will bo understood taut it is repugnant to Great Britain on the  one  nand to see Egyptians wholly by their own acts (^group  omitted) realization of an ideal aimed at by both/
both parties and  on the other  to be compelled herselfto&apos;. intervene to re-establish order when it is threatenedin such a .way as  to arouse fears of foreigners and  in-volve  interests of foreign powers,  It would be much tobe&apos;regretted if jcjgyptiuua snuuld aee  in exceptional measures whioa nave recently been taken, any prejudice to ideal to which they aspire  or an intention on the p&amp;rtof His Majesty&apos;s  Government to - alter  policy I have  indi-outed.  In taking these measures sole desire of HisMajesty&apos;a Government has been to put  end to a harmfulagitation which by arousing -popular passions might have such consequences ao to jeopardize whole result ofefforts of Egyptian nation-  These measures were primarily in the interest of Egyptian cause which has everythingto gain by being  studied in an atmosphere of calmness and friendly discussion,     8.  Now that tranquillity seems to be re-establishingitself thanks to.wiue spirit which is root of Egyptiancharacter and asserts itself in times of crisis, I desireonce again to interpret to Egypt good, intentions whichHis Majesty&apos;s Government have hot ceased to entertaintowards her.   .  0.  Without  wishing in any way to exercise pressure on free will of Egyptians to adhere to this or that treatyHis Majesty1 s. Government desire nevertheless to prepareway for a regime  of mutual understanding which will resultin confidence in  a satisfactory and final solution of theEgyptian problem.    10.  With this object in view I am happy to be ableto announce to Your Highness that His Majesty&apos;s
 Government  are  prepared  to  reoomwend to British parliament, without waiting for  conclusion  of b treaty, abolition of protectorate and recognition of Egypt as an  Independent  sovereign stats.  There is no obstacle&apos;to re-ehttblishweut forthwith of an Egyptian Ministry for Foreign Affairs which will pre- pure the way for creation of diplomatic and consular representation  of Egypt,  ..11,  As regards internal adqinistvktion of jjjgyptHie Majesty&apos; e Government will view with favour creation of a parliament with right to control the PQLioy and administration  of a constitutionally responsible government.    IE.  I propose to abolish regime of martial lawas sot up by proolamation of november 2nd 1914 so Boonus necessary Egyptian act of indemnity shall have beenpromulgated with application to all inhabitants, ofEgypt.   In &quot;the avent of its being fpund impossible toput eueh an &amp;ct in force before it is desired to hold the parliamentary elections 1 shall he preparedpending repeal of above mentioned proclamation to suspend application of martial law in respect of all matters affecting free exeroise of political rightsof Egyptifans,   .13V  As soon as this state of affairs has been -established His Majesty1s Government will examine inconsort (sic)  with Egyptian government and in most.friendly spirit the conclusion of an agreement onfollowing points which v/ill remain for settlement,. .     A.  Security of communications of British Empire,
    B.   Defence  of  Egy.p..t- against all foreignaggression  or interference-;, direct or.- indirect...    C.-   Protection  of foreign interests in Egypt.&apos;.  14.:- if - is  now  for &apos;Egypt to respond Wid&apos; it is- tobe hoped -sire  will justly appreciate good intentionsGreat Britain and- that, reflection and not passionwill  guide &quot;aQT attitude-&apos;
Telegram i&apos;1^01? Vx?$ LAM^JB^S.          rod)  dated  1-3 th  January. 19&amp;2.SUB-COMMITTEE *          My. t a 1 eg rsm-&apos;l?o* 19.         &apos; Paragraph.;   should read  &quot;will examineconcertwith Egyptian Government.&quot;          Same paragraph.  . .0.1 a us a  B  should  read  &quot;foreignaggress ion of &apos; into rfo re needirect  o r ind if 66 i i&quot;          Clause C. shodld road  &quot;protection  of foreign interests in Egypt and protection of  minorities.&quot;          Please add also Clause D  &quot;The  Soudan.-&quot;
No. 6.

Telegram from Lord Allenby No. 20. dated 12th January, 1922.

SUB-COMMITTEE.

Most Urgent.

Split has occurred in newly re-constituted wafd. Abdel Aziz Bey Fahmy resigned yesterday and it is expected that six other members will announce their secession to-morrow.

2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1.

16th January, 1922.



</content>
</cab>
