<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 251-253</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S E  C R I: ?.                                                   J..I   4**                            C A 3 I  IT-E     .CP. 5641.                    REPORT BY G^^RP^-OFPrCSR^CO^IAI^Il/S--.-                    IN-CHIEF OK THE&quot;SI.TUATI OH. IK IRELAND!&apos;&apos;  &apos;,                       PGR WEEK EJJDIITtt  14th&quot;TAflUARY.19 22 *                 (Circulated &quot;by the  Secretary of. State, for War).           The-Agreement  having been ratified, by . the representatives     of the  26  Southern Counties a  Provisional Government has  ...     been set up.   Orders have consequently been issued for the-     closing of the Slingo;  Tullamore,&apos;Castlebar,  Tipperary and     Bantry  Bde. Head  Quarters-. .           The  evacuation of the -Auxiliary Division of the R.I.C.-     has commenced, two companies having: left daily since Priday-     13th instant  and  the troops.rill  commence. their evacuation.     on the  20th instant.           There has been a considerable- number.-of outrages on.     the&apos;part  of armed men in .the .country&apos; lately.-,  As will, be seen     from the  following accounts of these incidents they.have .     mostly  occurred in Areas in which the I.R.A, are under..the .     control of men who voted with-Mr. De Valera,  against-the     Agreement.           These cases have all &quot;been referred to the Liaison     representatives with a view, to their being enquired into by     the leaders of the I.R.A-.     (a). On  the,Qth  January an Officer on a Motor cycle was     fired at  by an unknown assailant  3^- miles S. , of Curragh.  The     bullet  penetrated.hi-s coat but he was uninjured.-,.     (b). On  the 10th January a Crossley Car was stolen and the     driver  forced to (Jrive away from Tralee Railway.-Station..     (c). On  the evening&apos; of the 10th  two privates of 11,55.M.T. .     Coy. were kidnapped at Tralee  Station.-. They rejoined their .     unit on the evening of the 12th.-     :
 (&amp;).   At Eallyhooley  Co.  Cork a  goods train was held up on 10th  January by aaneied  men  and three bags of military storus stolen. (e).   At Clondulane,  Co.&apos;.  Cork,- or; -11th January, 5 officers of the H.P.A. when out  walking --ore ordered by an armed party of about 15 Aeh % &amp; hoi::.-up ;&apos;thei r hands .&apos;&apos;&apos; The officers refused  to comply  and were;., fired.-on but/mi aged.  On the officers drawing  their  revolvers the attackers withdrew. (f).   Near the same place on the same day the United Hunt was stopped by armed  men  who said British Officers were not allowed  to hunt.   Tire Master then took the hounds home. (g).   On the 11th  January a Government charger was stolen while proceeding  from ICenmare to Killarney in charge of an unarmed  man. (h).   A  Military  Ford Van with its driver have been missing from  the JJonaghmore Rathclowney Road since loth instant- (i)..  On the 14th  January a private soldier was fired at and-wounded  by an unknown masked nan,  armed with a-revolver, whilst^carrying, -despatches-, between Ataenry ana Oranmore..  His bicycle  was stolen but-.no-despatches-were taken from him.. (j) .   A  Pord Ambulance - was. stolen at Tralee on. the 16th instance on approe^ch  of the. Crown Forces however the thieves bolted and the a,mbulance  was recovered slightly damaged.       Belfast is  still  in a disturbed state and party feeling  is very bitter.       Sectarian murders pre now a frequent occurrence and outrages such as  bomb throwing and shooting are daily occurrences.  On  the  lOth January&apos;four bombs were thrown into  Catholic streets and several children wounded.       Reprisals and counter reprisals took place on the 11th when a Protestant  and his wife were shot dead on their doorstep, and a bomb was thrown from a Catholic         -.  .             -                 locality/
locality at a fully laden tramcar.  On the same eveningtwo Catholic women living in a Protestant street were called to -the door of their house and there deliberatelyfired at and seriously. wounded.,  A Protestant woman wasalso shot dead at the door of her house.      The troops and. police are naturally not in aposition to deal with such crimes as it would mean thepicketing of every street in the city..                        ( Sgd.t)  CP ol-T* MACREADY,                                     GEH3RA1..                         .. Commanding-in-Chief., IR3LA1TD.0-.H.-Q.  Ireland   17th January.,  1922.

</content>
</cab>
