<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 254-261</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT.)

SECRET.

C. P. 3642.

CABINET.

UNEMPLOYMENT COMMITTEE.

UNEMPLOYMENT GRANTS COMMITTEE.

(I.) Extract from the Conclusions of the 46th Meeting of the Unemployment Committee.

(II.) Memorandum by the Minister of Health, (Paper No. C.U. 355.)

(I)

Extract from the Conclusions of the 46th Meeting of the Unemployment Committee held in Conference Room "A", 2 Whitehall Gardens, S.w., on Thursday.

POSITION OF THE UNEMPLOYMENT GRANTS COMMITTEE.

3. With reference to a Memorandum by the Minister of Health, (C.U.355) on the position of the Unemployment Grants Committee which appeared on the Agenda, it was stated that as the matter had been referred to the Cabinet for decision, no useful purpose could be served by the Committee discussing it.

MR. REY stated that the Unemployment Grants Committee had now ? to the end of their funds, in the both of the schemes for assisting local authorities. (1) the 50% grant in the case of schmes financed out of revenue, and (2) the scheme for government assistance by way of sharing loan charges. He enquired whether in future all applications were to be refused.

THE CHAIRMAN said that as the matter was coming before the Cabinet for early consideration, the Unemployment Grants Committee should endeavour to avoid committing themselves either way in the meantime.


     The Financial Secretary to the Treasury enquire awhat was the state of expenditure as apart fromallocations.   It was essential, from the point ofview .of the public, to araw a distinction betweenallocation and expenditure.     Mr. Rey stated that in respeot at the ftp per oonGrants Soheme9 1^ millions opk of  ^millions had.already bean spent, asel In respect of the LcaaScheme, some 40 per cent,, of the money allocated, A     ^he Financial Secretary tooths Treasurysuggested that an early opportunity should be taken of informing the Press of the difference betweenallocation and expenditure in order tc modify the                           * tha.timprossion which might prevail/beoause .   no                   to befurther s oh ernes were/sanotioiied,  the operation ctf... -                    &apos;&apos; .&apos;-the scheme would automatically come to an end.     The Minister of Labour, who entered fct thisstage suggested that the, Unemployment Committedshould call the attention of the Prime- Iv&amp;nisterto the extreme urgency,cf coning to. a. decision anthe question of providing further funds for thoUnemployment Grants Committee..   He, regarded, itas very serious that the matter..should be heldover to tho following week.   The unemploymentposition had net  improved; 1,935,,000/wer e &quot;Itillwholly unemployed and 3,60,COC on short time,.Tho opponents of the Government&apos;- would undoubtedlyexploit the position.   Ee suggested that theCommittee should communicate with the PrimeMinister asking for the consideration of the matter by the Cabinet forthwith,                                    /The Committee
 The Committee resolved:-         To call the attention of the    Prime Minister to the urgent necessity    ,for a decision by the Cabinet on the    question of placing further funds .at    . the disposal of the Unployment Grants    Committee, in view of the fact that.the    Secretary of that Committee reported &quot;: ;    that all monies at their disposal    had either boon spent or earmarked    and that applications&apos;&apos; from Local ;  ..    Authorities arc accumulating which  -&apos;;    must be refused&apos; if no further money    is available *The Committee agreed:-         To suggest to the Prime Minister    that the Cabinet should consider the    question forthwith.
                     (II),                 CABINET.          UMSIigLQYMBMg______COI^TTEE.   Preliminary and Provisional Reports^ of the TJnemploy-   me&quot; nt * Grant s&quot; Cpmm it tee. (Oiroulated by, direction of the Ministerm of Health) QA0   Grants tc Local Authorities on the basis     of 60 por cent of the wages cost-B,   Grants of Interest and sinking funds     charges on loans raised by Local Authorities     for works of public utilitya                                 16th January. 1922,Ac Grants to Local Authorities on the basis of 60 per cent   of the wages cost.     It has been found necessary to inform Local authorities that no more schemes on this basis can be sanctionedin view of the exhaustion of the funds at theCommitteeTs disposal,   Tho Committee have, in fact,sanctioned schemes to the value of over  2,800^000, but as there will be a saving on this amount of at least  250,000owinar to sanctioned schemes having&apos; boon abandoned, cur-tailed or a portion of tho expenditure disallowed,, a margin of about  50,000 -  100,000 is available*     This margin is., however, an estimate founded uponestimates, and the Committee do not accordingly consider itsafe to proceed with any further allocations in view of thepossible danger of exceeding the financial limits of theirfunds *     Originally parliament had been informed that thesum of  3,000,000 would be made available, but this sum was subsequently reduced to f.2^000,0000   Later,.                                             increases
Increases of  330,000 and  300,000 wore allowed, bringing the total to  2,630,000  ( 2,000,000 during tho current financial year and  630v000 during nest financial yearsubject to a m&amp;ximtp carry-over of  200,000).       i ;     Many hundreds of applications received from local Authorities under  this scheme, are still outstanding,which cannot be considered-,.     It &apos;is -estimated that&apos; JImplbyment,1 as a resultof tho schemes sanctioned on this basis has been or isbeing found for 103,000 men - for &quot;varying periods&apos;.B-* Grants of interest and sinking fund on loans   raised by Local Authorities for works of   public utility.,     Prora the point of view ox the number and natureof schemes presented by Local Authorities it may be saidthat the Government proposals launched in September and october last for relieving &quot;unemployment by means of grants of interest -and sinking fund on sanctioned loans forapproved, works have, proved Very successful-.     In view&apos; of the very large number of schemes submitted the Committee reported the decision to the treasury and the Chairman-, of tho  Cabinet Committee on Unemploymenton the 1st. December and  asked for directions as. to the  -financial&apos; limits within which they were to work..     By the 20th December the Committee had approved   .  -schemes to the value, of  9 ,.500,000 and. reported that they felt unable to proceed, further&apos; until.&quot; they knew-the&apos;limits to which they were-authorised to go;                     X
      On the 22nd December it was agreed at aConference of Ministers that the total cost of the works to be approved for grant by the Committee should notexceed  13,000,000 and that&apos; such steps should be taken as would ensure that the total value of schemes approvedshould fall within that limit.      Schemes to the value of  22,000,000 have beenreceived up to date.  Of these, schemes to the value of 12,OC0,000 were dealt with by the Unemployment GrantsCommittee up to the 21st December, leaving schemes to thevalue of  10,000,000 (including those received up to thepresent date) still to be dealt with.      In addition to the above mentioned works, theCommittee understand from the Electricity Commissionersthat further schemes to the value of ahout  2,000,000have been prepared by Local Authorities.  (These have notbeen included-in any calculations).      The position was , therefore, tliat the Committee had 10,000,000 worth of schemes under consideration, of which an amount of  3,500,000 only could be approved.  In order tobring the approved schemes within the financial limitsdrastic steps had to be taken to sort and classify the pro-posed works, so as to leave for consideration only a limited number of specially selected schemes,  proposals for doing this were submitted to and approved by Ministers on 3rdJanuary in accordance with&apos;the decision of the Conference ofMinisters held on the  22nd December, and a letter was approved for issue to Local Authorities explaining that theCommittee could only sanction as 1;special cases&quot; a propor-tion of the outstanding cases within the financial limitsat  their disposal-, and that though, strictly speaking allworks should have been started by 1st January to qualify for grant they were, prepared to allow these special casesuntil 1st February to  commence.. operations...
      As a result of the various tests imposed it was found necessary to make the following classes of rejections:-All cases dated after 23rd December.....      2,350,000Parksj pleasure grounds etc, and building   works                                      1,49 6,000Normal rejections (e.g, unemployment   percentage below 6% etc.)                    481,000Pvoad cases dated after 10th December            800SOOQUnemployment percentage between Cfo and 12$    1,300,-000..Previous per capita grants exceeding c/8d*      721,000Direct Labour cost below 30/1, of total cost      42810.00      Allowing for overlapping of different categories ofthe rejections this brought the total value of rejectionsto about  7,000,000 amongst which it was anticipated thatschemes to the value of  1,000,000 would have to be sanctioned(although coming under one or other of these various classes of rejections) owing to previous formal or Informalcommitments.      The work of sorting and classifying this large numberof schemes occupied a considerable amount of time and itwas not until 6th January that the Committee were able to resume dealing with cases.      Since then the Committee have up to date (16th January)sanctioned- schemes to the value of . 2,158,000 out of atotal of about  3,500*000 available leaving  1,342,000still to be allocatedt      The total amount of direct employment expectedto be given by the total of all .schemes on this basis already approved is estimated at 450,000 man-months, 75 per cent ofthe men employed, exclusive of men to be employed on schemes in respect of which grants have not yet been allocated,,beingex-Service men, to which must be added an approximatelyequivalent amount of Indirect employments,         .;.  -  -ft Concessions, to the value of  500,00.0.have been made in     this category.             -  &quot; ;
      The Committee have given special consideration to cases where unemployment was heaviest, the figures in manycases having been reported to them as being between 50 and80 per cent.      It was. agreed-.on the .16th January that the Committeeshould .be authorised -to extend the time limit for commencingwork beyond the 1st February, where necessary, as it was obvious.. that ov ing to the delay which had occurred in-dealingwith cases and &quot;the late,date- on which some, had been received,it would .not be possible for all of those under considerationto be&apos;started by the 1st February-..-      The following table sets, out the estimated annual .charges falling on the-Exchequer (a) if the capital expendi-ture approved for grant is limited to  13,000,.000 and (b)if it is increased to : 18,000,000., -                               Annual, charges on Exchequer.(a)  13,000,000 cap-      ital expenditure(b)  18,000,0.00 capital      expenditure.Increase of annualcharges if capital.expenditure increasedto.  18 ,.000,000                            (Sgd.) A. MOKD.Ministry of Health, - -18th January, 1.922..1922 to 1927	1927 to 1932	1932 to 1937. - 5.8.5-, 000. 810,000 225,000	5.07,000 702,000 195,000	416,000 576,000 160,000dtehall .Gardens,. 31st January, 1922.

</content>
</cab>
