<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 273-273</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document  is the Property  of  His Britannic Majesty&apos;s  Government.]                  Printed for the Cabinet.  January 1922.SECRET. CP. 3645.Proposal to introduce a  Bill increasing the statutory sterling  borrowing  powers    of the Secretary  of  State for  India for  capital expenditure on Railways and    Irrigation.    Under statute the Secretary of Stale lor India iu Council can only borrow money in the  United Kingdom on behalf ol  the Government  of  India to such extent as is authorised  by Act of  Parliament.  There  has been a  long series of. Acts known as&quot; East India Loans Acts.&quot; authorising the raising of various amounts, the last of whichis the East India Loans Act of 1910.   The present unexhausted borrowing powers ofthe Secretary of Slate in Council under these  Acts are approximately 12,7OO,OO0L forgeneral purposes and 9,100,0001.  for capital expenditure on Railways and Irrigation.The urgent need for extending and improving  the  Indian railway system, which is mainly owned by the Government, has been recognised by the Committee preside over by  Sir  W. Acworth, which  reported a few  months ago.   The views of theCommittee on this matter are universally accepted,  and a Committee  of the IndianLegislative Assembly, including both official and unofficial members, presided over bythe Finance Member of the Viceroy&apos;s  Council, has  recently recommended  that duringthe next five  years,  153 crpres  of rupees  (equivalent to  100.000,0001. at Is. id. therupee) should be devoted to Capital  Expenditure on Indian  Railways.  A  finaldecision has not yet been taken on their Report, and it is not possible  to stale at  thisstage  what proportion of the amount will be raised in India and  what proportion in theUnited Kingdom.  This will depend  on  developments,  but it is clear  that it will benecessary to borrow very large sums for Indian Railways in the United  Kingdom in thethe next few  years.  The Government of India are  entering in their forthcoming budget a figure of  15,000,000/,. for sterling railway borrowing in the United  kingdom in 1922-23, and if this estimate is realised, it  will  mean  that  India&apos;s borrowings inthe United Kingdom for productive works  will, in  the two years 1921-22 and 1922-23have amounted to 32,500,09M.    I  accordingly desire  early   authority from  Parliament for increased railwayborrowing powers, and   I. should like to introduce  as  soon as practicable  afterParliament reassembles  a Bill  empowering the  Secretary  of State in Council to borrow for railway and irrigation purposes an amount not  exceeding 50,000,000Z.    A draft Bill is now being prepared, in consultation with  Parliamentary counsel,on  the lines  of previous  East India Loans Acts.   Besides  conferring  the  requiredpowers, it will deal with one or two technical  points of no great  importance and willalso probably contain a provision, removing the existing disqualification of Membersof  Parliament from  subscribing to Indian  loans,  thus  following the action taken inconnection with the subscriptions of Members of Parliament to war loans.                                                                     E. S. M.    23rd January 1922.                                                    . &quot;5081    100  1.22

</content>
</cab>
