<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 339-342</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
MS DOCUMENT 13 THE PROPERTY 01? HIS BRITAIN IC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERiDilEHi1JB B C  S E T.C A B i .N E loIn i5656.REPORT BY THE GENERAL-,. OIPFIGKEilDING- IN-CHIEE      JAOTJARY. 1922.      f Circulated by the So^retarg^ of State for War).                           j     The evacuation of troops from Ireland having commenced the following Brigade Headquarters have &quot;been closed, and theareas whieh were under their command have been taken over asfollowsSLIGO Bde.,      closed on 20-bh Jan. taken over &quot;by 13th Bde.OASTEHBAHTIPPERARYBAHTRYTULLiMOBB&quot; 20th Jan.&quot; gist Jan.&quot; 21st Jan.&quot; 23rd Jan9XTIt&quot; GALWAY Bde.&quot; 16th Bde*&quot; 17th Bde.w 14th Bde.The following units have left IrelandEOth Jan. 1st 3). of W. Regt.          A Squad. 3/B.A.M.B,          2nd Gar don Hrs^.          2nd OXa &amp; Buckse Ii.Ik          1st Royal Fusiliers..23rd Jan. 2nd K.O.Y.L.I.       .          2nd Argyll &amp; SutluRrs.          A Squad. 1st R,A*MJU24th Jan. lsi. Cheshire Regt.          B, Squad. 3rd, R0AaLRf          Bde. H*Q, R.A.-,Hr.R. and]          H*Q. 1st RoA,M,fi0     &apos;)          0. Squad. 1st RoA*MoRa          A. Squads 2nd R*A*H.R.Prom GUKRAGH.  &quot;  BELFAST  &quot;  MARYBOROUGH  &quot;  TIPPER ARY.  &quot;  KH&amp;AI&amp;EY.  &quot;  DUHBABt.  &quot;  CLABBMOHRIS.  H  MOORS PARK.  *  DUBLIN!:  w  BELFAST  w  HOGSS PARK.  w  MOQBE part .  *  CEOKMBL.     The o otamiseion of outrages by gangs  of armed men,especially the holding up and stealing of motor cars still continues.     The following are examples of incidents which have beenreported to G.H.Q. and which have been taken up with theLiaison Officials                                            16th Jan,
16th Jan.  The R.I.C, Barracks at GHABLESTOWN,  Cos  Mkyo,  was           attaoked hy 50 armed men who captured all the           arms and ammunition in the &quot;building.    One           Sergeant and two constables are missing,17th Jan.  One military hioycle was stolen by armed men           from an unarmed soldier in TIPPEBARY.           A Sunbeam touring oar used by the Colonel           Commandant, Tipperary Brigade was stolen from           the garage in Tipperary Barracks by a civilian           who, disguised as a soldier of the B.A.S.C.           entered the barracks and drove the car away,18th Jan.  One f*rd van and one lord touring car also a           motor cyclo were stolen &quot;by armed men in the           streets of ITBLIU.           A Goods train from ffEBMOY was raided by armed           men near BALLXHOOLEiY, Co. Cork, and consignments           of military stores for various stations           were interfered with,19th Jan.  TIPEERABY Area.  Three men of the 45th Battery           B%3FoA* were held up,by armed mon and their           &quot;bicycles and bandoliers were stolen.21st Jan.  The driver of a Sunbeam touring oar was held up           while washing the oar near the Canal at TuLLAMGEIS           by armed men who forped him to drive the car away           The driver ran the oar into a wall.  The raiders           decampod leaving tho damaged car which had its           wind screoa broken.                                 i     In view of the imminent evaluation by the Crown Forcesof large traota of country, criminals of all classes feelthat attaoks on individuals and small parties may be madewith impunity with no likelihood Whatever of being broughtto ;justioe*     While organised operations under the direction of  the recognised heads of the 1*3* A. are not to bo feared,the liability of the troops to attack is otherwise just as great as prior to the agreement of July, 1921,   such attacks will be tho work of individuals of the I,B.A*tof the unoffioisil and extreme section of the I0R9A.,or of robber bands belonging to no organisation^     Orders have been issued by the General OfficersCommanding the 5th and 6th Divisions, and Lublin District                                                 to
9*2*0*1. Ireland,   24th January,. l&amp;2a*to enauro that armed guards are placed on all vehicles and aooompany stores despatched &quot;by train or road.Orders on this subject have also been issued from ,H,Q,, oopy^of whioh is attached,,                  (Signed), C.M*MACHEADY.                                           General,              Ccmmanding*-dn^Chief f Irish Command-,
     Loss o   Government Property..,          Many oases of theft of property such as arms,  motor     -vehicles, bicycles, live stock,  supplies, etc,  have  been     reported recently.          All ranks are warned that they arc responsible for     safeguarding such property and if they fail to  take all     possible steps, including armed resistance, to  do  this,  they     render themselves liahle to trial by Courts &quot;Martial,  and  in     any case will be held pecuniarily responsible.                         Sd.  C.J;Pickering.                                            L.to-Colonelu                               Assistant Adjutant General.23rd January, 1982. -

</content>
</cab>
