<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 562-572</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  February 1922..SI\CRRT.CP.  3676.CABINET.OSPECIAL  WEEKLY   REPORT   ON               UNEMPLOYMENT.    There are still no signs of any real improvement in industry.  Employment in coal-mining is not quite so good. The improvement recorded in the iron and steelindustry is very slight.  In  shipping and marine  engineering the few  re-engage-ments reported more than compensate for further discharges from other yards.  Theimprovement  in the woollen trade is  maintained.  Cotton still remains  very uncertain.  The  hosiery  trade  is fairly  brisk.   General  engineering  remainsdepressed, though the slight improvement in the motor and cycle industry continues.Employment in  the tinplate industry is not quite so good.  Building still remainsstagnant. There is little change in the boot and shoe industry.    NOTE. On p. 10 of this issue will be found a table giving a statistical reviewof the work of the Employment Department, Ministry of Labour, in the year 1921,in connection with Employment, Unemployment Insurance, &amp;c.No. 55.WEEK  ENDED  JANUARY   27,   1922.THE  SITUATION.T. J. MACNAMARA,             Ministry of Labour
NOTE ON  UNEMPLOYMENT  SITUATION IN UNITED  KINGDOM  ON                            JANUARY 27, 1922.    1. The Trade Union figure of unemployment for July 1914 was 2-8 per cent.    The  average for the ten years prior  to the war, according to Trade  union unemployment figures, was 4-7 per cent.  It was as high as 7-8 per cent?%i 1908 and7-7 per cent, in 1909.    During  1919 it ranged between 1-6 per cent,  in September and 3-2 per cent,  inDecember, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.    During  1920 it ranged between 0-9 per cent,  in April and 6 0 per cent,  inDecember, and averaged 2-4 per cent, for the year.    The figures for 1921 are :        To the end of          Per cent.                         Per cent.        January   ...      ...     6-9   \    July       ...       ...   16-7        February         ...     8-5   !    August    ...       ...   16-3        March     ...      ...    10-0       September         ...   14-8        April      ......    17-6       October    ...       ...   15-6        May       ...      ...    22-2   I    November ...      ...   15-9        June       ...           23-1       December  ...      ...   16-52.  NUMBERS ON REGISTERS OF EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES.1 920.						1921.						Aug. 87. Nov. 12.				Dec. 3.		July 1. \ July 22.				Oct. 7.	Oct. 14.	M en  Civilians Ex-service Boys Women (5 iris	86,&apos;,76 142,600 17,608 58,982 17,&apos;,80	134,868 239,816 21,872 97,964 22,237		137,222 263,553 21,379 119,886 23,663		1,068,288 j 934,528 488,722 j 471,233 80,53J&amp;k 67,085 466.965 1 345.112 65.883 1 49,528				j-1,060,812* 53,133 224,487 38,336 1,376,768	1,072,867* 52,354 221,279 37,740	Totals .. 1 1	818,096	516,757		565,703		2,170.397 1 1,867,486			-		1,384,240		1921.												Oct. 21.		Oct. 28.		Nov. 4.		1 Nov. 11.	Nov. 18.		Nov. 25.	Dec. 2.	Men  Civilians Ex-service Boys Women Girls Totals ..	j-1,106,531* 51,465 228,111 37,685		1,252,117* 56,560 263,281 39,518		1, 1,	332,461* 61,117 294,105 41,156	1,377,949*1 62.342 j 307,346 41,795	1,399,065* 62,174 313,797 41.700		1,411,254* 61,370 318,880 41,681	1,414,632* 60,684 318,032 40,661		1,423,792		1,611,476			728,839 1,789,432		1,816,736 I		1,833,185 i	1,834,009	--	1921.							1922,					Dec. &amp;.		- 1 Dec. 16. i Dec. 23. t				Dec. 30.	Jan. 10.		Jan. 17.		Jun. 24.Men  Civilians Ex-service Boys Women Girls Totals &apos; ..	j 1,412,372* 59,903 321,346 40,068		1,406,309* 58,734 319,156 38,638		1,402,315* 58,100 314,556 38,729		1,451,434* 60,103 333,671 40,535	1,481,713* 65,690 340,967 46,419		1,475,256* 66,790 336,708 47,182		1,466,823* 66,890 333,696 47,773	1,833,689		1,822,837		1,813,700		1,885,743	1,934,789		1,925,936		1,915,182* Separate figures for ex-service men no longer available.
I.-SUMMARY OF ACTION TAKEN BY  THE GOVERNMENT.                    [From Autumn 1920 to Autumn 1921.]                      Cabinet Unemployment Committee.    The prospect of a severe trade depression first became evident  in the early autumn of 1920. On the 13th August, 1920, there was a special discussion at a meetingof  the  Cabinet, when  the Cabinet Unemployment Committee was appointed toconsider the whole question and devise means for relieving unemployment.    [This Committee  has since been  in constant  session and has  up to the 27thJanuary, 1922,  held 42 meetings.    The problem of unemployment in one form or another has also  been before theCabinet on 56 occasions between  the  13th  August, 1920, and the 27th  January,1922.]                       (A.) Unemployment Insurance.    An Unemployment Insurance Bill  of general scope was introduced on the23rd December, 1919, reintroduced on the 16th February, 1920,  received a third reading in the Commons on the 19th July, 1920, passed into law on the 9th August,1920, and came into operation on  the 8th November, 1920.    This Act applied compulsory insurance against unemployment to 12,000,000persons as compared with  4,000,000 previously. The weekly rates  of  benefit, paid out of contributions from employers, employed and the State, were 15s. for  men and12s. for women, after a &quot; waiting period &quot; of three days.  In general, the amount ofbenefit  was limited to one week for every  six contributions paid, but  during the first year eight weeks&apos; benefit could be  drawn after four contributions  had  been paid.    An Amending Act of the 23rd December, 1920. granted eight weeks&apos; benefit, upto the  31st March..  1921, to persons who had paid no contributions but had beenemployed for a  certain minimum period in an insured trade in 1920.    A  further Amending Act of the 3rd March, 1921,  increased the rate of benefitto 20s. for men and 16s. for women.   It further provided that during each of  the periods March-October 1921 and November 1921-July  1922  16 weeks&apos;  benefit couldbe drawn by. persons who had been employed in an insured trade  in 20 weeks sincethe end of 1919 and were normally employed in an insured trade  genuinely seekingwhole-time employment and unable to obtain  it.    A third Amending Act of the  1st July, 1921, reduced the rate of benefit to 15s.for men and 12s. for women and increased the &quot; waiting period&quot; to six days.  this change was necessitated by exhaustion of funds  owing  to  the  great amount ofunemployment and was coupled with a heavy increase in contributions and authorityto borrow money from the  Treasury to the extent of  20,000,000,  as compared with 10,000,000  previously.   At the  same time  power was taken to allow 22 weeks&apos;benefit (instead of 16)  in each of the periods  March-October  1921  and November1921-July 1922.    Between the 8th November, 1920, and the 20th January, 1922, the amount paidin  unemployment benefit was  62,076,000.*   Of  this amount the  contribution ofemployers since the 8th November,  1920, was  12,747,000,* that of employed persons 11,648,000* and that of the  State   6,245,000* in  addition  to   1,602,000* inrespect of  benefit  for ex-regular sailors, soldiers  and airmen.   The balance was provided  mainly  out of the  accumulated reserve fund  of  over 20  millions andadvances by the Treasury amounting to  8,930,000.*    The number of persons in receipt of benefit was on the 1st July,  1921, 2,062,012wholly  unemployed and 988,364  on  part-time, and  on the 24th  January,  1922,l,820^000f wholly  unemployed and 280,0001  on part-time.                 (B.) Emergency Works and other Measures.    A sum  of  10,400,000 was provided for expenditure on arterial roads, half tobe given by way of actual grant and  half by way of a loan to Local Authorities.This money is administered by the Ministry of Transport and is expended by Local Authorities  under their supervision.   The men to be employed are selected by theLocal Employment  Committee of the Employment Exchange and preference is givento ex-Service men.     A  further sum of  3,000,000 was allocated to the  Unemployment Grants ( ommittee,  presided over by Lord St. Davids, for the purpose  of assisting  LocalAuthorities to carry out at once works on which a substantial number of unemployed         * The siinounta for Northern Ireland are excluded as from the 81st December, 1021.         T Estimated.       [7764]                                                     &quot;  B 2
could be engaged.   The conditions imposed with regard to the expenditure of this money were that works could only be approved in areas where there existed seriousunemployment which was not otherwise provided for,  that the men employed shouldbe taken from the registers of the Employment Exchanges, preference being given to ex-Service men, and that any grant paid should not exceed  60 per cent,  (originally30 per cent.) of the wages bill of additional men taken on for the work.  Further,the works had to be such as were approved by  the appropriate Department of theGovernment as suitable works of public utility.  The  condition as to recruitment oflabour through the Employment Exchanges  was  subsequently modified so as topermit Local Authorities to draw  all or  a portion of  the  labour  from Boards of-Guardians.  A condition has also been imposed by which Local Authorities carryingout schemes by means of direct labour may not, during a probationary  period of sixmonths, pay to unskilled men wages higher than 75 per cent, (or, in the case of men employed only half-time, 87-^  per cent.)  of  the authorities&apos;  rate for unskilledworkmen.    In  addition  to the items  outlined  above,  assistance from  the  Ministry ofTransport  has enabled  Local  Authorities to  maintain in  employment on road maintenance a number  of  men beyond those  ordinarily employed on  this  work.Additional employment has  also been  provided by  expediting work  on sites and sewers for housing schemes.  An emergency programme undertaken by the Office ofWorks, and the introduction of  alternative work and a system of short-time working in Government Industrial Establishments have further assisted towards relief of thesituation.    In addition, Local Authorities have been encouraged by the Government to putwork in  hand without receiving definite Government assistance.    From  the autumn  of  1920 to  autumn, 1921, in this way, a sum of at least25 millions was set aside by  the Government and the  Local Authorities for schemesof work which are still continuing.  At least 200,000 men have had employment onthese schemes at  various times, and at  the present time over 121,000 men areemployed (see table below).                         II. LATER  MEASURES.                          [Autumn, 1921, onwards.]    Before rising for the recess, the Cabinet agreed that  the position with regardto unemployment was so serious that the Cabinet Unemployment  Committee mustdevote special attention to it, with special reference to  the exhaustion of benefit underthe Unemployment Insurance Acts.    On  the 19th August,  1921,  the Cabinet,  on  the  recommendation  of theCommittee, agreed that assistance could be given to Local Poor Law Authorities,either by way of expediting the sanction  for loans  or  permitting the  loans to bespread over a number of years, in cases in which the Local Authority could  prove that there  were exceptional  circumstances due to the abnormal- unemployment andthat they were exercising their  powers with due care and discretion.    The whole matter was again discussed at the Cabinet which  met at Inverness onthe 7th September, 1921.    On the 16th  September, 1921,  the Cabinet Committee further agreed that      &quot; (1.) Where, for the purpose of providing employment in the present emergency,Local Authorities (including statutory bodies who do  not  trade for profit)  put inhand or accelerate approved works (other than revenue-producing works), whichwould not otherwise have been proceeded  with, or so accelerated at the present time,the State will give financial assistance on the following basis.     &quot; Grants equal to 50 per cent, (since increased to 65 per cent.) of  the interestand sinking fund charges on loans raised by Local Authorities to meet expenditureon schemes actively commenced before the 1st  January,  1922,  will be paid by theState for a period of one-half the term of the loans subject to a maximum of fifteen years.  The expenditure to  be  taken into account will  be  all approved expenditure incurred within the period ending the 31st March, 1923.     &quot; In approving schemes, special regard will be had to the direct employment ofunemployed persons and to  a preference  being given to ex-Service  men.     &quot; (2.)  In  the case of revenue-producing works, grants will be paid, in approvedcases, equivalent to 50 per cent, of the interest on loans, raised for a period of notless than ten years, in respect of expenditure on schemes actively commenced beforethe 1st January,  1922, provided that such expenditure is incurred within the period ending the 31st March. 1923.  These interest grants will  be paid for  a period offive years.
     &quot; (3.)  Schemes shall not be authorised exceeding a total capital expenditure of10 millions without consultation between the Minister of Health and the Chancellorof the Exchequer  (since increased  to 18 millions).     &quot; (4.)  Schemes must be  approved by the Ministry of Health or other appro-priate Government Department as schemes which  will provide employment andmust be certified  by  the Ministry  of Labour for districts  where unemployment issevere.&quot;     Subsequently  it was decided  that Local Authorities  carrying  out schemes bymeans of direct labour may not, during a probationary period of six months, pay tounskilled men wages higher than 75 per cent, (or, in the case of men employed onlyhalf-time, 87^  per  cent.) of the authorities&apos;rates for unskilled workmen.               III.-FURTHER  REMEDIAL MEASURES.     During the Autumn Session,  1921,  the following measures  were submitted toParliament and approved:      (1.) Amendments to Exports  Credits  Scheme. (a.)  Government guarantee tobe increased from  85 per cent, of the cost to 100 per cent, with recourse against theexporter for 57-J per cent.     (6.)  Maximum  guarantee  for  each  firm  to be fixed by special AdvisoryCommittee.            &apos;     (c.)  Extension of scheme to all countries, including the British  Empire.     (d.)  Extension of period of credit in certain  cases to 1927.     (2.) Government Guarantee of Payment  of  Interest and Principal of loans raised by Dominions, Colonies, foreign Governments, public authorities, &amp;c, where such loans are to be applied towards the carrying out of any capital undertaking orin the purchase of articles to  be manufactured in the United Kingdom required forthe purposes of any  such undertaking, the British Governments  liability  underthis scheme not to exceed  25,000,000.  It  is to be a condition of the guarantee thatthe  application of the loan  is  calculated to  promote employment  in the  UnitedKingdom.     (3.) A  Sum  of  5-g Millions  for  General Unemployment Relief. Subject to treasury approval, the money will be used  in connection with schemes for providing employment on land improvement and drainage ( 650,000), forestry ( 250,000),light railways,  and also by way of loans to Boards of Guardians  or Parish councils in necessitous areas who are unable to  meet claims for relief (see  Cabinet decision ofthe 19th August above).     (4.)  &quot;  The Unemployed  Workers&apos; Dependants&apos;  Fund,&quot;  to  be established by legislation for a period of six months for the purpose of making grants towards themaintenance of the wives and dependent children of unemployed workers in receiptof unemployment  benefit.  The  grants will be  at the weekly rate of 5s. for  the wife and Is. for  each child.  The  necessary money will be obtained by means of further contributions paid by those  now  contributing  to the Unemployment Fund (both employers and  workmen) together with a grant from the  State.   The total  amount available will be approximately 6^ millions.     (5.)  Overseas Settlement. A further  330,000 was voted to assist  ex-Servicemen desiring to emigrate to the Dominions.     (6.) &apos;Acceleration  of  Government Contracts. The  position with  regard toGovernment contracts is being examined to see whether, in any  cases, a reasonableanticipation of requirements can be made with advantage from the  point of view ofincreasing employment.     (7.) Ministry of Tra.transport.-A. further sum  ( 2,000,000) will be available fromthe  Road Fund for expenditure on roads to  relieve unemployment in necessitousareas.     (8.)  Unemployment Grants Committee. A further sum of  600,000 was placed at the disposal of this Committee  for dealing with Schemes on the original basis of60 per cent, of the Wages Bill.     (9.) Office  of  Works. A sum of  50,000 has been voted  for unemploymentrelief, works in  the Royal Parks.     For the above schemes (apart from the assistance to Local Authorities withregard to Loan Charges, the Export Credits Scheme and the Government^ liability under  the  Guarantee of  Loans for Capital  Undertakings) the Government  has undertaken to  find  12,000,000,  the  greater  portion  within the current financialyear.      f77641                                                       B  3
GSUMMARY showing  the Labour Employed at January 20, 1922, on certain of the             above  Schemes described in Sections I, II and III above.Scheme	Number Employed in Greater London.	Number Employed in Provinces.	Total.1. Arterial roads 2. Road main leuance 3. Housing- (acceleration of lay-outs, &amp;c.).. 4. Unemployment Grants Committee 5. Alternative work   War Office.. Admiralty 6. Local Authorities (without grants) 7. Land drainage 8. Forestry 9. Light railways 10. Office of Works 11. Acceleration of Government contracts (G.P.O.).. Totals	7,378 * *623 4,547 1,221 Nil 2,439 Nil Nil No information 327	23,547t * 3,749t 39,554 Nil 1,896 9,661 3,109 3,472 No information	30,920 20,000 4,372 44,101 1,221 1,896 12,100 3,109 3,472 327 (300 (about)	16,5301	84,988$	122,118    v        * No separate figure for London and Provinces available.            t Decrease ou previous week due to bad weather in certain places.            J Plus number (unknown) employed on road maintenance.    [As reports for week ended the 20th January, 1922, have been received from only 484 Local authorities out.of 523 who were asked to supply information (in respect of items 8,4 and 6 above) it is probable that therelief schemes inaugurated by the Government and Local Authorities are finding employment for a numberof men in excess of the figures given.]     PROGRESS  ON  LATER  MEASURES.1. Loans and  Overdrafts to Boards of Guardians.Nature of Assistance.	Number of Unions concerned.	Amount.Loans granted Overdrafts, current Sanctions under Section 3 of Local Authorities (Financial Provisions) Act Application for sanction to borrow under Section 3 Application for sanction to borrow under Section 3 over two years Application for extension of loan period Totals	12 34 47 8 6 4	  500,000 1,322,500 2,671,426 241,100 397,810 126,676	111	5,259,5122. Unemployment Grants Committee.GRANTS made on Basis of 60 per cent, of Wages Bill since September 10,  1921.Number of Schemes Sanctioned.	Number of Local Authorities Assisted.	Total Cost of Schemes.	Total Cost of Labour.	Maximum Grant Sanctioned.	Additional Men expected to be Employed.857	517	  2,807,238	  1,575,91 7	  850,152	37,0783. Grants towards Loan Charges.        (a.) APPLICATIONS.Date.	Number of Local Authorities making Application.	Number of Schemes Submitted.	Total Estimated Cost of Schemes.	Number of Men expected to be Employed.January 26, 1922	715	2,390	  23,070,248	. 118,379 (for average of 7 months )
(&amp;.)  GRANTS Sanctioned.Date.january 20, 1922	Number of i v u c Local N&apos;ul!&apos;ber of Authorities ! ^hemes Assisted, i APProved-		Total ICstiiuateil Cost of Schemes.	Loans Sanctioned.	Number of Men expected to be Employed.	767*	.1,243 .	  12,987,182	  12,410,918	67,902 (for average of 7 months)4. Trade Improvement Schemes.      (a.)  EXPORT Credits.	Credits given.							Date.	Advances 		Guarantees 		Floating Credits.		Guaran-tees to Banks under Part 2 of Export Credits Extended Facilities.	Total Sanc-tioned.	Sanctioned.	Taken -up.	Sanctioned.	Taken up.	Saa tioned.	Taken up.		October 27,1921 (i.e., before new scheme operated) January 26, 1922 .. Increase	  2,916,780 3,083,211	  1,309,119 1,416,225	  730,465 2,297,755	62,037 362,043	*   1,566,350	  24,714	  8,4*00	.  3,647,245 6,955,716	166,431	107,106 ! 1,567,290 1 300,006 j			1,566,350	24,714	8,400	3,308,471(&amp;.)  GUARANTEE up to 25 Millions for Capital Works.                    Totals to Date.Week ending 	Guarantees Given or Sanctioned. Interest or Principal on- Total to Date. i		  No inf(irmation at present available.	 5. Overseas Settlement.		Month ended 	Free Passages to ex-Service Men and their Dependants Granted to Date. Number of Persons 	Expenditure to Date.December 31, 1921	,67,481-	  1,488,9866. Land Drainage, Forestry^  Light  Railways.Form of Work.	Week ended 	Number of Schemes Approved.	Amount Involved.	Estimated Number of Men to be Employed.	Number of Men actually at Work.Land drainage Forestry	Jan.- 28, 1922 Jan. 21, 1922	173 446f	  225,037 182,714	6,385 , 4,426	3,109 (January 21) 3,472Light railwaysN o information at present available.    * The actual number of authorities receiving assistance is 452 ; the figure given represents the numberof  separate authorities shown week by week in the Schedules.    t This figure includes 66 schemes which are being undertaken by the Forestry Commission direct, and17  in Crown Woods, 3 of the latter being road making.
   IV.-REGISTER  OF  UNEMPLOYED,  AND  NUMBERS RECEIVING                      UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT.    Below are tables  showing the number of persons recorded at the EmploymentExchanges as wholly  or partially unemployed, and  the  number whose claims  are current,  for United Kingdom (excluding Northern  Ireland)  and for  the  london area,  on the 24th January, 1922 : UNITED  KINGDOM (excluding Northern Ireland).-	Number recorded as Wholly Unemployed.			Number on Benefit (Claims Current).			Great Britain.	Southern Ireland.	Total.	Great Britain.	Southern Ireland.	Total.Men Boys Women Girls Total	1,389,921 64,974 306,567 46,198	41,942 929 8,801 779	1,431,863 65,903 315,368 46,977	1,362,620 37,683 284,507 22,929	37,042 620 7,119 304	1,399,662 88,303 291,626 28,233	1,807,660 1 52,451		1,860,111	1,707,739	45,085	1,752,824UNITED KINGDOM (excluding Northern Ireland).						-	Number working Short Time.&apos;*			Number paid Short Time Benefit During Week.			Great Britain.	Southern Ireland.	Total.	Great Britain.	Southern , Ireland.	Total.Men Boys Women Girls Total ..	153,095 8,036 90,328 9,498	347 39 703 121	153,442 8,075 91,031 9,619	88,462 5,009 48,996 5,030	273 39 638 120	88,735 5,048 49,634 5,150	260,957	1,210	262,167	147,497	1,070	148,567LONDON AREA.	Wholly Unemployed.		Short Time.		Numbers Unemployed.	Number on Benefit.	Number Working Short Time.*	Number paid Benefit during Week.Men Boys Women Girls .. .. .. Total	192,498 9,086 49,679 7,101	191,652 4,908 46,998 3,386	&apos; 11.524 274 3,102 469	2,^33 83 983 181	258,364	246,944	15,369	4,080    * The number given represents workpeople who are engaged on short time in a manner which enables them to comply with the rules as to continuity of benefit.  Workpeople who are unable so to comply are excluded.
                     Unemployed  Workers&apos; Dependants&apos;  Fund.     The estimated income of this fund for the period 7th November, 1921, to 20thJanuary, 1922,  is  2,430,000.*   The estimated amount  paid out as grants for  theperiod 10th November, 1921,  to 20th January, 1922, was  1,750,000.*SUMMARY of Claims to January 24, 1922, for United Kingdom  (excluding                            Northern Ireland). f 	Men.			Women.			Total.			a rt ^	s 1 m	O	rt  	a a m	la o f-i	g 3	a TJ S J o H	13 &quot;o EHNumber of claims made	977,291 j 31,681		1,008,975 8,304 1,180			9,484	985,598	32,861	1,018,459Number of claims authorised : -(a.) Wife, housekeeper or invalid husband only (J.) Children only (c.) Both (a) and (J) Total.. Number of children for whom grants hare been authorised : -(a.) Under 14 years (i.) 14 to 1(1 years Number of claims on which any grant has been rejected:  Wholly rejected Partially rejected Number of authorised claims currentj	241,656 85,564 535,910	5,074 4,962 14,209	246,730 90,526 550,119	645 5,387 412	37 606 160	682 5,993 572	242,301. 90,951 536,322	5,111 5.568 14,369	247,412 96,519 550,691	863,130	24,245	887,375	6,444	803	7,247	869,574	25,048	894,622	1,244,416 14,870 33,818 51,632	44,221 1,462 1,283 2,470	1,288,637 16,332 35,101 54,102	9,21.1 143 801 329	1,053 13 66 55 122	10,264 156 867 384	1,253,627 15,013 34,619 51,961	45,274 1,475 1,349 2,525	1,298,901 .16,488 35,968 54,486	f.49,237	10,315	659,552	4,794		4,916	654,031	10,437	664,46S   * The amounts for Northern Ireland are excluded as from 31st December, 1921.   t Owing to the transfer of functions to the Ministry of Labour, Northern Ireland, figures for the United Kingdom are not immediately available. The figures shown are preliminary.   % The figures are exclusive of 8 claims current for juvenile applicants.
1. Average weekly No.  of persons registered as wholly  unemployed       throughout year         ...       ...       ...       ...       ...    1,638,0002. Average weekly No. of persons registered as on short-time      ...      623,0003.  Average weekly No.  of persons wholly unemployed and drawing      Unemployment Insurance  Benefit  or Out-of-Work  Donation       throughout year         ...       ...       ...       ...       ...    1,460,0004, Average weekly No. of short-time workers drawing Unemployment       Benefit or Out-of-Work Donation ...       ...       ...       ...      623,0005. Average weekly No.  of  grants for Unemployed Workers&apos; Depen-       dants (November  18-December 30) :            Adults     ..................      528,900           Children..................      868,350                                Total  ...       ...      ...       ...    1,397,2506.  Total No. of vacancies notified by employers :            Men       ...       ...      ...       ...      ..:       ...      530,000           Women    ...       ...      ...       ...      ...       ...      337,000           Juveniles   ...       ...      ...       ...      ...       ...      132,000                                Total  ...       ...      ...       ...      999,0007.  Total No. of vacancies filled*:            Men       ...       ...     &apos; ...       ...      ...       ...      493,000           Women    ...       ...      ...       ...      ...       ...      216,000           Juveniles   ...       ...      ...       ...      ...       ...      111,000                                Total  ...       ...      ...       ...      820,0008.  The numbers of individual payments under various headings which      were made, after due investigation, by the Exchanges during the      year 1921 were approximately as follows :                                              Individual Payments. Amount paid.                                                                            Unemployment Benefit   ...       ...     88,000,000    58,187,000         Out-of-Work Donation to ex-Service             men (early part of year)     ....      4,400,000      4,000,000         Unemployed  Workers&apos; Dependants&apos;             Grants     ...       ...       ...      3,628,000      1,110,0009.  Cost of employment and Insurance Departments in the calendar year 1921 :                                                                                        Gross cost  (approximate)    ...       ...      ...       ...    6,600,000           Less contributions from  the  Unemployment  Fund  and               Unemployed  Workers&apos;  Dependants&apos; Fund  towards               administration          ...       ...      ...       ...    3,200,000           Net cost to Exchequer       ...       ...      ...       ...    3,400,000    * The &quot; vacancies filled&quot; only include cases where the Exchange was responsible for  placing theapplicant in  touch with the employer, and not cases where the applicant found work as a result of his own efforts; and they, do not include placings in casual employment such as dock labour, or placings in temporarypost office work at Christmas.UNEMPLOYMENT AND  UNEMPLOYMENT BENEFIT,  1921.
12.13.(a.)  Total No. of cases of benefit withheld (&quot; covenanted &quot;       or  &quot;non-covenanted&quot;), including  &quot;test&quot;   cases      695,377(b.)  Total No. of cases of benefit allowed for less than the       full period (&quot;covenanted&quot; or &quot;non-covenanted&quot;)    1,029,600Total No. of Prosecutions   ...      ...       ...      ...          996o10.  Investigations and Disallowances under the ordinary procedure of      the  Unemployment  Insurance  Scheme Insurance  Officer,      Courts of Referees and Umpire:            (a.) No. of doubtful claims referred by Exchanges to Chief                  Insurance Officer for consideration      ...      ...      345,475           (6.) No. disallowed by Chief  Insurance Officer  ...       ...      268,436           (c.) No. of subsequent appeals to Courts of Referees    ...       72,723           (d.) No. disallowed by Courts of Referees      ...       ...       44,013           (e.) No. referred to the Umpire      ...       ...       ...        2,912           (/.) No. disallowed by the Umpire   ...       ...       ...        2,121      (Many of the above were &quot;test&quot;  cases involving many other claims.)11.  Investigations and Disallowances  under the  special procedure in      connection with &quot;non-covenanted&quot; benefit (i.e., benefit claimed      under  the  Emergency Provisions  of Section 3 of  the Act of      March 1921) :-           (a.) No. of claims rejected at once by Exchange       ...      115,300           (b.) No.  of   cases   examined   by   Local  Employment                  Committees  ...      ...       ...       ...   &apos;    .:.    5,344,000           (c.) No.  of   cases  disallowed  by   Local  Employment                  Committees  ...       ...       ...       ...   &apos;    ...      339,400           (d.) No. of cases  allowed but not for the full period of                  benefit      ...       ...       ...       ...       ...    1,029,600

</content>
</cab>
