<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 573-574</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS THS PROPERTY OF HIS PRITANIIC MA3SSTY1 S &apos;H.P. 3677.G A B I K B TREPORT BY OBE GENERAL  OFFICER COMAS DING-IN-CHIEF OK THE S2 TUATIOH IH IRELAND  FORWEEK ENDING  8    JANUARY, 19 22,               (Circulated &quot;by tha Secretary of State for War).     Since my last report the evacuation of troops has oontinuedwithout interruption except for the postponement of the moves ofthe 1st Bn. M.G.O. from Ballyvonaro and the 3rd, Royal Fusiliersfrom Killaloe which has been necessitated by tho Railway Strike.     The following moves of units have taken place withinIreland - 5th Janny. 2nd R.W. Jvents from Dublin to Ballykinlar86th   &quot;    4 th Worcostors from Galway to Belfast.and the following units have left Ireland for Great Britain -25th Janry. 1st D.C.L.I.                  from Ballykinlar            B.Sqn. 2nd H-A.M.R..           from Glen Imaal.            B.     1st    &quot;                 &quot;26th   &quot;    G.     3rd    &quot;                 &quot;            1st S. Yorks.                   &quot;            E. E.Q. &amp; C. Sqn.2nd.K.A.M.R;   &quot;27th   &quot;    1st Buffs                       ,r            2nd R. Scots                    &quot;            45 Btry. R.F.A.                 &quot;            29   &quot;     n                    TT          .  H.Q. 31st Bdo. R.F.A.           &quot;30th.   &quot;    1st. K..O.Y.L.I.                 ,!            41st and 129th Batteries R.F.A. &quot;      The following units are to leave Ireland to-day -      1st Sherwood Foresters              from Skibbereen      1st Middlesex                         &quot;  Cootehill      H.Q. 7th Bde. R.G.A.                  &quot;  Moore Park      25th &amp;  26th Batteries R.G.A.          &quot;  Moore Park.Moore ParkBelfastMttllingarGlen Imaal,Fermoy.Enn isClogheenCah irCahirTuamCahir
     The number of outrages reported this week is considerably below the number in the preceding week, but the followinghave occurred -     On 27th January an Officer returning to Athlono from Mt.Talbot in a Touring Gar with an escort was fired on about 4miles from Mt.Talbot &quot;by seven or more civilians armed with riflesThe fire was returned.   No casualties occurred.     On 28th. inst: a Sunbeam Touring Car was stolen at  Clare-morris,     On the night of the 28th inst; there was a fracas betweentroops and civilians in Dublin between Wellington Barracks andDolphin&quot;s Barn.  A number of soldiers wore held up by armed menand deprived of their clothing aiid one man of tho D.CL.I. was shot in the back.  This necessitated an armed picquet being sent out.  The perpetrators stated it was being done as a protest bya certain unit of the LB. A. against the^Treaty.&quot;     A telegraphic nreport has been rocoived stating that thievosentered Fethard Barracks by means of a tunnel&apos;through the outerwall on the night 29/30th,inst: and stole 10 boxes B,,AA, 45rounds gun ammunition, 1 Lewis Gun and some magazines.  further details regar ding this tho ft are awaited.      In Ulster the general political feeling is reported to betotter than has probably been the case for some time.  Persons on both sides who are in a position to express an opinion are optim-istic of the future of tho North, and the recent agreement ofSir James Craig and Mr. Miohael Collins has received a generousmeasure of praise from all quarters,       Belfast has practically returned to its normal state andthere has been a great &quot;diminution of &quot;both political and  ordinarycrime.     Public opinion in the North has been so roused over therecent outrages and disturbances that it has made a distincteffect on the hooligan olasses of both sides and heavy sentencesawarded in oases of robbery under arms, and other crimes arisingout of the disturbances, have aotod as a deterrent to would becriminals.                               (Signed).  C.F.N.MM5READY.                                           GENERA! ,                           Commanding-in-Chief, IRELAND.G*H.ft.  Ireland.31/1/22.

</content>
</cab>
