<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 575-580</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
                                                             3[THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OP  HIS  BRITANNIC MAJESTY1S GOVERNMENT 3.SECRET.                         CABINET *C.P. 3678.   Conciliation Committees and Agricultural Wages.         MEMORANDUM BY THE MINISTER OP AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES.              I Circulate for the  information of my colleagues a    memorandum which I think may be of interest reporting progress    in connection with the Conciliation Committees which were set    up in place of the Agricultural Wages Board to deal with    agricultural wages.                                       A.G.B.February 2nd, 1922,
       CONCILIATION COMMITTEES AND AGRICULTURAL WAGES.     1.   The Agricultural Wages  Board which had dealt  withwages in Agriculture since its establishment in 1917 was abolishedby the corn Production Acts (Repeal) Act as from the l3t October1921.  Its place has been taken in England and Wales byConciliation Committees composed  of representatives both ofemployers and employed who meet to settle rates of wages by voluntary agreement,     2.   The duty of securing the formation and continuance ofthese committees rests on the Ministry of Agriculture but as theyare essentially voluntary bodies, the only action which can inpractice be taken is such mild form of moral suasion as therespective parties can be Induced to accept.          The task of getting these Committees to work has beena difficult one.  Many farmers have been and still are indignantat the action of the Government in repealing the Corn production act which gave them a substantial subsidy on wheat and oats andthey have been much Inclined to resent any action by &quot;the Ministry,The official leaders of the workers profess to be equally Incensedat the abolition of the Agricultural Wages Board and are constantly demanding its re-establishment.  To a large extentthis is a political question, and I am not aware that any strong feeling exists on the subject among the workers themselves.          The Committees moreover came Into being at an exceptionally unfortunate and difficult tire.  Prices were fallingrapidly and farmers, after having cultivated their crops through-out the year on the basis of a fairly high cost of production withwages at a high level, found themselves compelled to sell theirproduce at prices which were in many cases less than half what had been obtained in the previous year.  In consequence they
pressed for substantial and immediate reductions in wages.  Fromthe workers1 point of View the autumn Was equally unfortunate forbeginning a new system of fixing wages as owing to the favourablesummer, work oh the farm was well advanced and farmers were in aposition to reduce their staffs if they wished without difficulty.In addition the prevalence of unemployment generally, naturally-weakened the workers&apos; position.          The greatest tact and discretion have therefore been necessary to avoid any appearance of undue interference and atthe same time to exercise sufficient persuasion to induce bothsides to oome to an agreement.  In this work 1 have had theassistance not only of officers of my own Department but the valuable aid of officers attached to the Ministry of Labour,who had experience and were specially skilled in dealing withconciliation questions in other industries.     3*   The Aot has now been in operation practically four months and although It has not been possible to get agreements in all counties. I consider that having reg\rd to the special and peculiar circumstances under which the scheme was launchedit has undoubtedly proved a success.  Given a little time and patience with good will on both sides, there seems good reasonto hope that the Committees will come to be recognised as thocustomary means of settling wages in agriculture.          At the present time there are 58 Covnmittees covering the whole of the oountry, and of these, 45 have  made agreements,though in some oases these have only been for short periods.)In the remaining 13 although successive meetings have been heldno agreement has so far been reaohed.  Only 28 of these agreements are actually in operation at the moment but this is due largely to the short periods for which they were made, and in at least
a, nu-numbers of them there are good prospocts of new agreementsbeing reached in the course of a few weeks,     4.   One area which has proved exceptionally difficult isNorfolk - to which a good deal of public attention has been directed.  The trouble has been due to the refusal in the firstinstance of a large farmer to pay the wages fixed by theConciliation Committee and subsequently to the inability of theCommittee itself to come to agreement.  In this case I suggested to the employers and workers on the Committee that they should invite Lord Ailwyn to act as Independent Chairman.  Thissuggestion ms accepted and several meetings have been held.The parties have not up to the present succeeded In adjustingtheir differences though recent reports suggest that they are coming nearer together.  This disagreement In Norfolk has hadan unfortunate effect on some other parts of East Anglia whichhave also failed to agree.          The difficulty in this area is not a superficial one.,It is due to the essentially corn-growing character of thecounty.  The number of men employed per acre is greater than inmany other parts of England and the wages bill is consequentlylarger.  At the same time the fall in the price of corn has beenexceptionally great so that the farmer is hit both ways^          There are some other areas where tho efforts of theConciliation Committees have not met with success, notably inLincoln and the East Riding of Yorkshire.  In both these areas the employers have refused to allow a representative of theMinistry to attend the Meetings of the Committee and it hasconsequently not been easy to use those arguments which have inother! area sufficed to secure agreement between the parties.    &apos; 5,   The rate of wages which is now generally being paid for male agricultural workers is about 32/- or 33/- for 48 - 50hours, and many Conciliation Committees have agreed on these                               3.
rates.  In the north of England the rates are generally somewhat higher, while In East Anglia and in several Counties where noagreements have been reached the Employers refuse firmly to offermore than 30/- a rate which the workers equally firmly refuseto accept.          These rates compare with the Wages Board rate of 46/-for 48 - 50 hours which was in force up to the beginning ofSeptember, 1921,  The Wages Board at their last meeting reducedthis rate to 42/- which was the rate in force when the ConciliationCommittees came into being.  There was an immediate fall InOctober to 36/- per week followed by a gradual diminution to therates mentioned above.     6.   At the present time the workers seem disposed to accept some further small reduction and long period agreements have successfully been conoluded in several coun-ies with the assistanceof representatives of the Ministry, running up to the beginningof October next at 32/- for 48 hours up to the beginning of Marchand 3l/- for 50 hours over the remainder of the period.          These long period agreements are a very hopeful feature of recent developments.  They give to the farmer a settled rateof wage when farm operations are in full swing including both hayand corn harvest, while to the labourer they offer a certain minimum wage and will enable him to benefit by any further fallin the cost of living which may occur between now and October.     7,   While this latter point is one of importance it must beadmitted that  the above rates make full allowance for the changesin the cost of livingo  Taking the pre-war average oash wages at16/9 per week the comparative figure based on the cost of living index number is now 32/2, and it is probably true to say that theagricultural labourer has experienced during the last few monthsa greater reduction in wages than -most other trades,                                 4.
          If, however, we look at the matter from the farmers&apos;point of view the fall in wages Is more than justified by thedrop in prices, which has been appreciably more rapid than thefall in the cost of living,     8.   One remaining but very important feature of the workof the Conciliation Committees to which I wish to refer is theextent to which agreements when reached are in practice faithfullyobserved by the farmers throughout the area.  The committee as such have no power to enforce their decisions but they mayif they so agree  send their agreements to me for confirmationunder the Act and in such cases the payment of the agreed ratesis enforceable at common law.          Up to the present only 5 Committees have asked thattheir Agreements may be confirmed.  Generally It may be said thatthe employers are opposed to confirmation and there has been no very insistent demand for it by the workers.  In the majorityof cases the agreements are probably being loyally observed by employers, though the official representatives of the workerscomplain that this is by no means universally the case and therehave been certain regrettable oases of large employers who refused to be bound by the agreements.  There is not much doubthowever that if there were any serious falling away in thisrespect the employers on the committee would agree to confirmationand the absence of any general demand indicates in my opinionthat wages are being duly paid at the agreed rates,     9.   The official representatives of Labour maintain their demand for the restoration of the Agricultural Wages Board, butthere is reason to believe that the advantages of collective bargaining through the medium of these Committees are beginning to be understood, and that further experience will establishtheir position as the most satisfactory means of settling theLabour conditions of the industry.

</content>
</cab>
