<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/132/0 images: 896-913</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This  Document  is  the  Property  of  H.MoGovernment)6 .  2 .  2ti :CP. 3700.CAPIME.RELATIONS BETWEEN THE NAVY AND THS AIR FORCE.Memorandum &quot;by the Admiralty,       The Committee on National Expenditure in their Interim Report(pages 6 and 7), have made some remarks in regard to the future relations of the Army and Navy to the Air.  2.   In accordance with their Terms of Reference, the Committee  haverestricted themselves to the financial aspect of the question, and find their remedy for existing defects in the creation of a Ministryof Defence.  3.   Apart from this highly controversial remedy, the Admiralty  feelthat the time has come for bringing to the notice of the Government.with a view to the institution of a thorough enquiry., the defects  ofthe present scheme on the important grounds of efficiency.       A detailed examination shews &quot;chat considerable economies will result if the views of the Admiralty in conjunction with those thatthe War Office are putting forward are accepted.  In the followingremarks only the mam principle is dealt with, hut concrete proposals in support of this principle arc; available,  4,   The Admiralty is the sole authority responsible for the defenceof our sea communications,  5.   With this object in view, the Board of Admiralty has,  in thepast, been responsible not only for advising as to the whole of therequirements necessary for carrying out the&quot;Naval Policy of theGovernment, hut also for seeing that the expenditure approved for  thispurpose is allocated to the &quot;best possible advantage.  6.   The advent of the air weapon, which has become an integral  partof our Fleets, has provided the sole exception to this wise rule.  Thestrength and composition of our Naval Air Units dopend on Air Ministryfinance and organisation, although the efficiency of the Fleet and itstactical and strategical employment in time of war are largely dependent upon the efficiency of its aerial equipment.  7,   The ships used for carrying aircraft are, it is true,  providedby^the Admiralty, hut vessels and aircraft are interdependent, and neither can be used without the other; yet they are provided ior by two different Departments of State.  8.   In regard to personnel, the Navy needs an air personnel totally different from that which the Air Force reauires.  It&apos; needs a compara-tively small body of men, highly specialised in their particular work.Elasticity is of.much less importance than specialisation; above all,the senior Air Officers of the Fleet should he men who have years  of experience of naval air work behind them  and the Royal Air Force  is unable to produce these without detriment to the air requirements  inother directions.  9..   It^will he seen from the foregoing remarks that although they are partly dependent for attaining efficiency in a highly important- direction, on another Ministry - a situation which isfundamentally unsound.10. The /
  10.  The Admiralty consider that the air weapon will never hedeveloped satisfactorily for naval purposes until they are in aposition to supply and administer their own Air Servicef  employinga suitable co-ordinating medium in those respects in whichrequirements are common&quot;to both the Army and the Navy.  11.  In the opinion of the Admiralty this unsatisfactory state  ofaffairs, both in regard to personnel and material,  should not beallowed to continue&apos;.  Experience since the war has all contributed to shew the fundamental mistake of the existing organisation.       In Appendix I will he found the views of various authoritieswell qualified to give them., and naval opinion is unanimous in expressing its dissatisfaction with the present scheme and its graveanxiety should no alteration be effected.       In Appendices I Hand f lY are two Admiralty Memoranda inconnection with this subject prepared respectively for the Committeoon National Expenditure, and Mr .Churchill^ s Committee..  12.  It is hoped that the Government will recognise that theAdmiralty have done their best to effect the economies neoessary  toour straitened national circumstances - economies which in manycases have been agreed to with profound regret, on account of theiradverse effect on the ability of the Admiralty to provide in anadequate manner for carrying out the naval policy of the Government.  13.  In the present Memorandum the Admiralty recommend a policywhich they are confident will lead to still further economies,whilst at the same time removing a situation which if allowed tocontinue, will paralyse the work of our sea forces.       The foregoing considerations encourage the Admiralty to hopothat their earnest request for a strong and impartial Committee  to enquire into the existing defects in the system of naval air co-operation, will not pass unheeded by the Government.5. 2. 22.-- T - -*- - *-i-*
(l)  EXTRACT FROM A STATEMENT MADE BY THE    FIRST  LO&amp;to  THE WAR JLABINEIt^ ON,24W.    AUGUST. 1917. (WAR CABINET&quot; 225 MINUTE    12) . WHEN THS FORMATION OP  hi&quot;aIR    MINISTRY WAS&quot; UNDER&quot; DISCUSSION&quot;&quot;         &quot;His Department recognised, however, that there were strong reasons in favour of a definite develcp- raent of Air Policy, and they accepted without question the views of those who had investigated it - that there is a definite future for aerial offensive apart from th Army and the Navy.   It did&apos;not, however,,.. appear to ^J?m..practicable that such operations should take Place over the sea without being -part of the naval operations, and under Naval command,    0onseouently they considered that at this stage, it would be perfectly simple for the Air Ministry to adopt its proposed functions for the Army and for the Ministryindependently, leaving the Royal Naval Air Service as it exists today, at any rate for the course of the Ufcyr, but continuing to act as suppliers of machines and spare parts, while the Navy continued to train its own pilots and observers.   The duties at present performed by the Royal Naval Air Service which are not of a purely Naval character, might however, be handed over to the proposed Air Ministry,.  Should there be serious objections, of which the Admiralty were not aware, to the course proposed above, and should it be decided that the Naval aerial work should be carried out by machines and pilots provided by the Air Ministry, the Admiralty considered that the Air Ministry should, from time to time, attach to the Navy such Air Units as are deemed necessary by the Board of Admiralty, composed of machines of a design and specification laid down or approved by that Board, with pilots and observers also approved by the Board, and trained to a standard and on lines laid down by the Board.   It was also essential that, while such Units are attached to the Navy, they should be solely under ths command of. the Board of Admiralty, not only as regards operations but also as regards, discipline, etc,_The Admiralty were of opinion that the above conditions are, absolutely essential. if&apos;grave dislocation and serious danger to the Fleet are not to take place,. 11
                     A.(2)  EXTRACTS FROM INTERIM REPORT  OF TITS  ADMIRALTY POST    V/AR QUESTIONS&quot; COMMITTEE, DATED 14TH  NOVEJcEBR, 1919.         &quot;The chief reasons why naval aircraft should &quot;be in all respects under the Admiralty are :-    (a) Aircraft are already able to reinforce, and evon        to relievo, surface ships of certain work,  e,g.        reconnaissance.  Aircraft have thus &quot;become  a        factor in the working out of all naval plans..    (b) Naval heavier-than-air craft already differ in        various respects from land service craft, and        differences arc likely to increase rather than        diminish.  Naval plans must work from ship-        carriers or warships;  flying boats are        essentially naval craft11,,     *         ii         W          *         it         &quot;The development of naval types is of immense importance, and owing to their peculiar requirements it is improbable that they will &quot;be considered sympatheticallyexcept by the Authority which is to employ them, and has definite duties  for thorn to perform&quot;.     it         it         it          *         it         &quot;Aircraft, like surface ships, require shore bases both at home and abroad.  It is possible that some of these bases may be of commercial as well as of naval use, but the Navy cannot afford to wait for a commercial development in a matter affect inn: efficiency&quot;.     ,fr          it        *T&quot;          it         Vt         &quot;The duties of a Naval flying personnel can no morebe efficiently learnt in a short time &quot;than can the duties of a general service Naval Officer.     *                   \t          it         VJ Economy resulting from the employment of naval personnel:         &quot;From the point of view of economy, considerable savin? should result from the employment of Naval Offioers and Men in the Naval flying services,         Their manner of entry and early training will be no different from that of other naval personnel, while, as stated in the preceding paragraph, they will he available for ordinary naval duties when not employed on their specialist air work.         At the end of their &quot;flying  lives&quot; they will be able to return to the  general service, thus solving the problem of what to do with airmen no longer  suitable for flying. Their knowledge of flying  will, however, always be valuable to the Service by ensuring air matters being properly understood.         Administrative  expenses will be a minimum, as no extra staff will be needed for this  purpose in H.M. Ships&quot;.     *!-          ii-         &quot;IT1                    tif         The Vice Admiral, Dover Patrol, produced definite evidence for the  Committee which  showed that his Naval Air operations had been considerably hampered by the insti- tution of the Royal Air Force.EXTRACTS
M  EXTRACTS FROM A LETTER FROM  THE  0 OMMANDEP^-    IN-CHISF, MED ITERRANEAN. DATED&quot; IPiTH  AUGUST .    1921:         &quot;On tliis station I regret that I am unable to report any real advance in the cc-operation between ships and aircraft during tho past two years.   This has not been due to want Of will on the i^art of either Naval or Air Officers, but it is due to the starvation of naval air requirementse         &quot;I have repeatedly ashed that the  air  require- merits of the Mediterranean should be met&apos;,  both as apart of a general policy, and also to meet  the  active service needs of the moment,     I have failed  to obtain what I wanted, as doubtless other claims were  considered to be more pressing by the Air Ministry.         &quot;I am of course aware that the^last two years have been a period of transition and re-organisation, and that when these processes are complete it  might be asserted that the Navy will receive its adequate share of attention from the Air Ministry.         &quot;I must confess to being very sceptical about this.   It appears to me not in the nature of  things that the Sir Ministry will ever devote sufficient energy and attention or allow sufficient funds to be diverted to a service that is, and will always remain, to them, a side show;  a side-show that will bring in no return or credit for the drain that it  causes on men, money and material.         &quot;The credit or discredit of a Naval Air Force must he wrapped up in the efficiency or inefficiency of the fleet with which it works, for which the Admiralty is held responsible, and the Air Ministry  in no way responsible c         &quot;The root of the matter, to my mind, lies in the fact that the Air Force is of paramount importance to the Navy, whereas the Navy is only indirectly of importance to the Air Force as it is to any other public servic o.         &quot;&quot;.re cannot suppose that foreign nations will have been blind to the lessons of the past war.  Vast progress has been ma.de and the potentialities  of tho future are without limit.   They may be put to deadly use &quot;by any nation, great or small, that had no insight to train a personnel.   Weapons, without those skilled to use thorn, are valueless,.   The handicap under which out? fleet would start when opposed to a fleet  with its own trained air squadrons would rodo.ee it  to impotence. How can we hope to bring our enemy to action if theywore well advised by their aircraft.   How muchgreater
rmich greater our danger would be from all thoir fleetadjuncts such as submarines.special fast surface craft,etCn when directed by well-trained sea aircraft.   Itwould become a game of blind man&apos;s buff, where our battlefleet plays the role of the blind man.    Tho Admiralty is responsible for the retention of thocommand of the soa, and not the Air Ministry,,    Who will absolve the Admiralty from blame if for any reason the fleet enters the war handicapped, as it wouldbe under existing conditions?    The Air Ministry will naturally work for the visibledevelopment and aggrandisement of the Air Force as an AirForce,&apos; as opposed to individual units or weapons controlled by the Admiralty or War Office    We cannot expect the Ministry to devote much time tothe command of the sea, a responsibility that is not theirs,,It is incongruous that important naval weapons ouch as aircraft should be under the control of a body of men who are notcalled upon to have any sea knowledge or any experience of sea matters.    It is wo11 to remember what the Navy suffered in the pastthrough Artillery officers being responsible for tho armamentcarried at sea.   History will be repeating itsolf if tho Navydoes not assume responsibility for the design and constructionof tho aircraft they will use in ware    Thero passed through my hands recently a United States report  of the hearings before the Committee of Naval affairs on thesubject of the Naval wolicy of the United States.  Thehearings were long thy&quot; and discursive,, and it is not proposedto epitomise tho arguments hero, but  the subject of  thissubmission was very seriously discussed and the evidence of such  men as Admiral Sins, etc., is. at any rate., worthy  of ourgravest attention, whether we agree with it&apos;or not, and Ireproduce in the following paragraphs a few extractspresenting the viows hold by the principal men who gave evidenceI ;;:nd by Admiral do Bon).     i^IEAlL-SIJ^S..  Starting with a general statement that  theBritisn combined Air Sorce is a failure and was pressed  on great britain against our will, he goes on  to say &quot;our Navy airmenhave got to bo seamen - men who on sighting a destroyer-recognise what  it is doing and know instinctively what it islikely to do noxt&quot;0     ii iIML^lISJ L giving evidence,,  held tho same  opinon as Admiral Sims.  Further, when asked by the Chairman  &quot;Do youfavour a united air fo%ce or a separate force  for  the Navy,and army?&quot; he replied - &quot;I  cannot conceive  at tho minute of  anything  which is better calculated  to-wreck  the defence  of  the  countrythan a United air service.   I think  that that would  be absoulutely fatal to anything like Naval efficiency&quot;.     Chairman  :  &quot;You do not  think  that Great Britain&apos;s  methodfhas been a success?&quot;.     Admiral Fiske  :  r&apos; I understand  that it has  boen  the reverse  of a success from  tho  standpoint  of  the Navy.  From the  standpoint&apos; of  certain  individuals,  I understand  that  it has  been&apos;   extremely successful, but  so  far  from being  anything liko^ a  success  to England,  it has  been  very very  unfortunate &quot;.
32MB^Uj-ilSSEIM  After making several observationsprotesting against an independent air force he says :1  a Military Air Force is an essential combat (sic)branch and should form an integral part of the Array......ec.,,o It is my own opinion  that united States Navy should have its own personnel ana material to care for its ownnaval activities&quot;.&quot;ADMIRAL IS B0N8 late French Commander-in-Chief in theMediterranean, who is recognised as an authority on mostnaval matters\ andis without doubt a man of great-attainments and common scnsof, assured me more than once  thathis conviction that any air force for use with the Navy couldnot be satisfactory unless  the Navy was entirely responsiblefor its material and personnel,&quot;It is a regrettable but immutable fact that officers of separate services do not in general get on together aswell as do officers of branches of the same service,,  Thereis no use in mincingmatters and I think any officers ofezperienco will agree with me when I stats that there isno likelihood of that perfect understanding between the air and the sea which is so necessary to efficiency-., as longas the Royal Air Forco officers come ana go when they like.taking their orders from an outside authority who isuntrained in naval matters.  The confidence and sympathywhich exists between the various branches of the service -say, for instance, between  officers in battleships and submarines,exists&apos;because each -understands the other -or they were in such and such a ship&apos; together.  They bothlooked at tho same authority for orders, they straggle in thesame lists for promotion,share similar grievances.     &quot;Now between the Navy and the Royal Air Force this happyatmosphere does not exist, not that I moan there is notcordiality between the services, but they are not of the sameservice;  they do not understand each other difficulties,and, in the nature of things, never can.      &quot;The whole ox this atmosphere would vanish with theintroduction of a naval air force, and the present seems a particularly happy time to institute such a branch of the Navybecause we have recruits to hand;   I refer to  the overcrowdedranks of the Junior officers.  Whither could one turn moresuitably to draw personnel for a Naval Sing than to the lists of iviitisnipmenj Sub-Liouts* and Lieutenants?   These young,officers have the necessary naval ground work.  They are imbue with the traditions of the Navy, anc- they understand naval discipline./
     MEMORANDUM CIRCULATED BY THE Rt0 Hon.         A,  Je BALFOUR  IN MAY. 1916.(Tills Memorandum  Is  of special importance since   it foretold  in 1916 as inevitable the diffi-   culties  in the relations between the Navy and   a separate Air Force  which have since emerged.)CONFIDENTIAL.                QUESTIONS  SUGGESTED BT, THS PROPOSAL                  FOR A NEW * MINISTER  OF THE AIR&quot;.             In the discussion which took place in Cabinet a few    days ago,  I appear  to  have given the impression to one or two    of my colleagues that  I regard the existing organisation of    our aircraft system as beyond reproach, and am in consequence    inveterately opposed to any  species of&apos; change.  This, however,    is not the fact\ and,  so far as ray own personal convenience    is concerned, I should welcome the appointment of a Minister    whose peculiar province it should  be to correat the ignorance    and flatter the vanity of  the Pemberton-Billings and the    Joynson-Hichses of  the House of Commons.             By all means, therefore,  let us change the existing    system if we can find  a better.  But before any change is    determined upon, certain questions must be faced by the War    Committee or the Cabinet,  of which tho following seem to me    to be the most important:*-             We are all agreed that the Air Serv ce3 however    constituted, must serve three purposes: (1) It must act as    an auxiliary to the fleet; (2) it  must act as an auxiliary to    the arrays an(* C3) ^ raust  on occasion carry out independent    attacks upon enemy  magazinos, airship sheds, and ammunition    factories.             Further, we are all agreed that operations auxiliary    to the army and navy must  be carried out under the direction;;    of the generals and admirals concerned,,             Now there  are three aspects of the Air Service which    have to be considered  separately                1.  The provision of material.                2.  The training, discipline, and command of                  personnel.                38  The direction of operations.            Let me put  certain questions with regard to  each of    these in turn.             First, then,  take the  case of material.  I  see no    insuperable objection  to this being provided  either by a new    Minister of Munitions  or by a Department under the present    Minister of Munitions.  The  difficulty arises -when you leave    the problem of provision,  and address yourself to the problem    of designo  If  che  &quot;army and  the navy depend upon aircraft    for certain essential  army and  navy purposes, ought they not    to he also responsible for the kind of aircraft which they    have to use?  The army would regard it as intolerable that an    independent department should design their field guns and
howitSers: the raw would feel it intolerable that  an iwlepey-dent department should design their 1**^^?*;f***land they would regard it as a very small oonsolation that theywere allowed to have a representative on the board which inthese natters controlled their destinies.  The present system with regard to material is that the office which has to use it is responsible for its design.  If, therefore, a Ministerfor  Air or a Committee for Mr are appointed, an entirely newprinciple will be brought into operation.  Can we be oonfl.fientthat it will be an improvement?  Is it not certain that ifthere be a failure on the part of those who use the instruments,the  failure will be visited upon the Minister by ^hom the instruments have been designed?   2.   The relations bet-ween the nev/ Committee or department and  the personnel of the Air Service appear to raise difficul-ties even more&quot;To&quot;rmidable.  Who is to settle the training whichthe  pilots are to undergo?   The Navy hold the view that, inaddition to the training common to all airmen, a pilot who  isto manage a seaplane must have a certain amount of sea training.Is this training to be carried out under their direction, orunder the direction of the new Minister who has nothing to  do with the  sea?          And when, these pilots  are trained, whose servants are they to be?    Will they be  included in Vote &quot;A&quot; of the Navy Estimates?   Is it the Admiralty they will have to obey?  Is it to the Admiralty they will  look for rewards and promotions?  Is it the Admiralty which will be  responsible for their discipline? If the answer to these questions is in the affirmative., what  is the position of the Air Minister in relation to the service of which, apparently, it  is intended he should be the head?  If the answer is &quot;No&quot;, then  how  are you to secure full ard. complete 00** ope rat ion between the  service that deals with the air and the service that deals with the sea?   At this moment, for example, the Admiral  Commanding at Dover has to deal with the new and complicated  problems raised by  enemy submarine  activities based upon Zeebrugge and  Ostend.  He has got to work in together his destroyers and his aircraft.  The captains of the first, and the pilots of the second^ must  be equally under his command^ he must have undisputed control  over their movements and disciplinary authority over their behaviour.  But if the pilots are merely on loan from an independent department, difficulty and friction must) so far as I can see,  inevitably arisen  Since similar observations may,  I suppose,  be made about the army, we should soon find ourselves in this strange  situation:   We should have created a Minister for the Air with a very large personnel, by far the greater number of whom would  normally be serving the Wo otherfighting departments, only a minority being reserved, as I under- stand the scheme,  for those ^bombing&quot; operations which are not obviously within the province either of&quot;the array or the navy* No such system has ever been  deliberately adopted on a large scale in war before; and  no such system is (I fancy) now in operation in any foreign  country.    3.     If  we turn to operations (the third 2sead, and last head under which  I desire to ask questions), administrative difficult ties not  less formidable  in their character seem to present them- selves.   I presume  the new  department is (subject to Treasury consent)  to  determine the strength of the  Air Service, the number of its pilots,  the  character  and quantity of its machines.   But having determined them,  are they also to be responsible for their distribution between the army and the navy ard  the new department itself?   If  the present system were allowed to  continue,  I presume a  point would be reached after which the Admiralty and the Treasury would say that, for  the present, the Air Service  of the navy xrkg
April 29th,  1916. sufficiently  supplied I and a similar state of things would in  course  of  time  come about with the arraye  Under such anArrangement,  each .of these services will  (subject, to Treasury and  Cabinet control) determine both the sise and the employment  of  its  own flying corps.   If the  sister service called  for assistance,  that assistance will doubt- less be given when possible.  But under  the proposed  system we  shall have the  army and the  navy competing  for the  forces which the  Air Minister has at his disposal^  and the Air Minister,  on his part,  perpetually having to compare the  claims of our Admirals and our Generals with  each other, and his own claims with both.   Anybody  who knows  anything about joint naval and military operations from the beginning of the world  to the year  1916,  knows quite well that nothing but determined goodwill  on the  part of heads of  departments and officers in high  command prevents  friction,  difficulty, and delay.  To bring in a third department which must be consulted  about naval  aiid military operations, which may  have to  decide  upon their  relative importance, and  determine the magnitude  of the air  forces  which ou^it  to be  engaged, seems to  me to  add a new complication to our fighting  organisation, which is  sufficiently  complicated already.         The public appear to think that  by creating  a  single department controlling our air  policy, we should obtain unity and order  where multiplicity and chaos now exists.  But the interests  of neither  unity nor  order  are really  served by adopting a system under which the difficulties inherent in interdepartmental  consultation  are  enormously  increased,  and under which responsibilities at present  borne  by the navy and tho army respectively will henceforth  be shared  with  a new department.         We talk much  or &quot;overlapping&quot;,  and we are most pro- perly anxious to avoid it,.  But overlapping is not  the  onhy administrative disease from which we  suffer.   It occurs when two authorities independently attempt  the same task.   There is,.however, an evil  worse than this,  though as  yet  unnamed. It occurs  whan two or more Departments are compelled by administrative arrangement to do the work of one.   Then arise friction,  delay -  sometimes  even ^alousy and  misunderstanding. The developments of aerial warfare no-jman. can  foresee *  They may some day dwarf both the army and  the navyo   But  that &quot;day- is not yet.  In the mea.ivwpi.le  let us  think --twice hef&quot;orevxe ^&quot; create a third fighting department-, - whose activities willoe inextricably entangled with  those cf  the two which  already exist.                              (Intd.)   A.  J.  B.
cAPPENDIX Ml. k^memorandum BY THE NAVAL STAFF ON THE   NAVAL OBJECTIONS TO A SEPARATE              AIR FORCE                 INRei-Jly to a question out by the Oornraittee on        National Expenditure.         The following are tho principal reasons  why;  theAdmiralty are opposed to the present system :-         The Admiralty is held responsible for the defence  ofour sea communications, on which the country depends  for its existence.         To attain this end the Admiralty has been at  liberty to apply the money voted to them at their discretion;   to buildone type of ship or another, to increase expenditure in onedirection by reducing it in another, and thus to develop itsweapons in whatever direction the needs of tho time dictate,         But with the air weapon, whioh has become an integral part of our fleets,, this is not the case^cthe strength ofour Naval Air Units depends on Air Ministry finance, althoughon the efficiency of these units depends to a large extent the efficiency of many ef tho Fleet&apos;s weapons and also itstactics.        Aircraft are not auxiliary vessels to a fleet, such asdestroyers, submarines or minelayers.  The:/ are anessential part of it, and the actual fighting power of the battle fleet will be dependent on their number,  and efficiency0         The air power of the Navy involves :-             a)  Aircraft Carriers.             b)  Aircraft..         These two are inter-dependent, and neither can revised without the other, yet they are provided by two different departments of State.         Again the Admiralty cannot increase tho developmentof say, aircraft torpedo attacks by reducing expenditure insome other direction, since the development and training ofthe Air Units of the Fleet rest wholly with the Air Ministry.         Nor can the Admiralty carry out experiments withregard to, say, defence of ships against air attach., or aircraft spotting for shins&apos; guns, unless the Air Ministry isalso prepared to spend money on these lines and provide- orsonnel and material for the purpose.         The Admiralty have no control over supply of material.If they believe that arrangements for the supply of essentialstores are inadequate, they may protest, but cannot remedy.Thus
         Thus, though responsibility for the efficiency ofthe fleet rests on the Admiralty, they are partly dependentfor attaining efficiency on another Ministry, a situationwhich is fundamentally unsoundo         Theoretically the Royal Air Force is available in caseof war to throw its entire strength either into a naval war or into a land war, but in practice as far as tho Navy isconcerned, this oannot be the case, and the fact that the airunits are organised on these lines inevitably means that thoNaval Air Units cannot be as effective as they might bo.         Considerations of purely air attach and defence require that the Air Force be prepared in time of war to expand toperhaps ten times its present size, and it canndt be foreseenwhat uroijortion of its expended strength will be needed inany of the various branches of air warfare, such as bombing,night flying, photography, &amp;c.         To meet these requirements the Air Force Officer ofto-day must have a sound knowledge of all these branches ofair work, since the young pilot officer of to-day will in timeof war be called upon to command and to train the unformedunits which must be called into existence, and it cannot before seen in which branch of air work these unformed units willbe needed.         The policy of the Royal Air Force, therefore, is totransfer its officers frequently to different duties, so thatall may gain all-round experience.         The nodds of the Navy, on the other hand, are lessuncertain, and can be more easily foreseen.         Corresponding expansion of Naval Force is not possiblein tine of war, and such expansion as is possible must takethe form rather of a gradual dilution, than the rapid training and equii^ping of new units.         This must also apply to Naval Air Units, since they mustbe accommodated in ships, and ships take long to build.. rapid expansion is, therefore, not a matter of groat importance.         The outcome of a Naval war may hinge on the result of asingle action lasting perhaps four or five hours, and disastercannot be retrieved.         Yet, in order to meet the general policy of the AirForce, the men on whom so much will depend in action are liableto be constantly changed to other duties, and are not evenregarded as specialists in naval work by the Air Ministry,         All decisions as to the selection, training and allocation of a personnel are made by tho Air Ministry.Personnel who are becoming experienced and keen on naval airmatters can be, and are, removed by the Air Ministry to serviceashore,         At present the Admiral comi.iandJ.ng a Fleet can neitherreward good Naval air work nor punish bad work - ho has nosay in tho promotion of air officers and. any moment even theair officer on his own staff may be appointed to duty ashorewithout reference to him.,
         The Navy, in fact, needs an air personnel totally different from what the Air Force aims at.  It needs acomparatively small number of air personnel, highly specialisein their particular work.  Elasticity is of much less importance than specialisation:  above all, the Senior AirOfficers of the Fleet should be men who have years of experience of naval air work behind them, and it does not&apos;appear that the Royal Air Force will be able to producethese without detriment to the air requirements in other directions.         Thus the Air Ministry are in a position of havinggreat power over, naval efficiency, without correspondingres p on s ib il it y.         Neither in material nor personnel therefore, can thopresent system be considered satisfactory.         In administration it is costly and cumbersomo,necessitating constant correspondence and argument between two different Departments of State:  and although through theefforts and goodwill of individual officers it has not ledin tho -past to much friction, it offers endless opportunity.nit.1osfor it, from tho jealousies of seamen and air mechanicsto disputes between tho Board of Admiralty and the Air Council3,
&apos; MEMORANDUM BY  THE ADMIRALTY, PREPARED FOR MR. GHURC HILL&apos; S                  C OMMITTEE.RELATIONS BETWEEN THE AIR AND       THE NAVY.          The Admiralty feel bound to reply &quot;briefly to those parts of the Interim Report of the Committee on national expenditure which deal with the question of the relation between the Air and the Navy,  namely:-    (a)   Introductory remarks, paragraph 5, &quot;Question          of a Separate Air Force&quot;.    (b)   Air Estimates, chapter 3,  paragraph 3;          recommendation that the Air Squadrons          working in co-operation with the Navy          should be restricted to          1 Squadron in co-operation with the            Navy in the United Kingdom.          1 Squadron in co-operation with the            Navy in the Mediterranean.     2,   From the naval point of view,  the aeroplane  andseaplane are essential auxiliaries in reconnaissance and fire control,  whilst the torpedo plane promises to play amost important part In obtaining and disputing the controlof sea communications;  the naval security of  the Empirewill therefore tend to become more and more dependent  onco-operation with aircraft operating partly from the shorebut principally from sea-going carriers.     3.   As aircraft carriers working with, and air personnelattached to the Fleet, must be under the Admiralty, and musthave an intimate knowledge of the Navy and naval operations,the demand for a separate naval air service is logical and reasonable.     4.   With regard to the Committee&apos;s statement in  theirIntroductory Remarks in paragraph    , that in the event  ofthe Air Force being divided between the Navy and the Army,duplication in experiment, design and supply would be inevitable
inevitable and that duplicate flying schools would result,it will be Instructive to examine the state rf affairs  asit now exists.     5.   First, as regards experiment.  Under the MrMinistry several experimental establishments are maintained.Experiment with seaplane 1-3 is meetly carried out it the  isle of Grain, while the majority of aeroplane experiments takeplace at Martlesham Heath.     6.   There is a third experimental station for wireless telegraphy,  This station works entirely independently  ofNaval Wireless experimental stations.     7.   Experiments with torpedoes are carried out  atFort Grange Aerodrome quite independently of Naval Torpedowork.                                                         i      8.    It is difficult  to see how experimental work couldbe more duplicated  than  It is at present while,, if the AirService were split, dupltcatien could be largely induced bycombining  the experimental work in such matters as wireless telegraphy, Torpedo running, etc., with existing &quot;Naval,establiahmentsp and by carrying out purely Aere-dynamicalexperiment under  joint naval and millwry control.     9.   Second, as regards design.   The design of  aircraft is at present carried out by the Aircraft manufac tuningfirms.  The War shewed the disadvantage of attemptingGovernment design of Aircraft,  and it is unlikely that either the War Office or the Admiraiywould want,,tc,revert to it.  But if it ever became necessary for War aircraft to be designed in a Government Office it is obvious that many design^ would bo required.  The  same designercannot be expected to produce the best single-seaterfighter aeroplane and the best ten-ton flying, boat.   In fact,whether the Air Force remains separate or is combined withthe Navy and Army it is certain that, under Governmentdesign, each type of aircraft would require a separatedesign staff.    10.   Third,  as regards supply,   At present three  serviceseach have a department for placing contracts.   It is difficultto see how duplication can result if one of them is  doneaway with.    11,   Fourth, as regards Flying Schools.  The following isa list of schools and training establishments under theAir Minis try: - .
Air Pilotage School, AEDOYSR.Armamont and Gunnery School, EASTOHURCH.School of Army Co-operation, SALISBURY.School of Balloon Training, LAREHILL.R.A. F. Cadet Collego, CRANW3LL.Central Flying School, UPAYON.Electrical &amp; Wireless School, WINCHESTER.No, 1, Flying Training School,  HETHERAYON.iiOo 2.    11               &quot;    ROYS TON,Ho. 3.    &quot;               &quot;    LINCOLN.No. 4.    &quot;               &quot;    T A.IESTINE,No. 5.    &quot;               &quot;    C3BSTER.No, 6.    &quot;               &quot;    RAM3GATS.School of Naval Co-operation,  CALSHCT.School of Photography, FARNBO ROUGH.Stihool of Physical Training, UXBRIDGE.Seaplane Training School, LEJ-ON-SOLENT.School of Technical Training, (Boys1) HALTON.   ,T    &quot;      &quot;        &quot;     (Men&apos;s) RAMS GATE.R.A.F. School,  INDIA.12.       Thus thero are now eight schools for teachingflying In its various forms.   It does not appear that theAdmiralty and War Offico could carry duplication to anygreater length, whereas in suoh matters as Army and Navy-vn-operation,- Photography, Wireless Telegraphy, Armamentoi.il Gunnery,, Physical Training &amp;o. , it appears that thopresent R.A.F. establishments largely duplicate existingNaval and Military Establishments,13.       Tho Gommittoe state &quot; ... the two seniorservices admit tho noud of a certain amount of jointorganisation of a subordinate character, but have given no clear approximation of what  this joint organisation should be ...&quot;          It may bo briefly stated here that tho jointorganisation in mind is by no means one of a subordinatec  raster but would cover experiment and research, contract...-A supply and initial training.14.       She Committee also state   &quot;Without a separateexistence there is grave danger that the Air Service v/oui.bo unable to work out developments which might, in thonext decade or so, entirely rovolutioniso methods of attack and dofenco&quot;.15:,       No grounds for this fear can be seen - in fact the reverse would seem to be tho case.   If the Army and navy maintain, their own Air Forces they are much more likely to allow air weapons to supplant purely land and sea weapons, and this will hasten tha day, if that day isto come, as so m.anv people believe, when the air will comeinto its own as the principal fighting medium.
16.     There would &apos;bo much more encouragement  to  naval officers to study the application of the  air  weapon tohaveI problems, and the same applies to the use of theair in Military problems.   Civil aviation would stillbo encouraged by the State as, under the  suggested scheme,a Government Department would, still control it, such.department acting in close co-operation with  the Army and navy in research, experiment and supply,17.     Prom various memoranda prepared by the  AirMinistry for the Committee of Imperial Defence, it willbe seen that, in the opinion of the Air Staff,  the greatestmenace to this country lies in air attach by  France, Thequestion as to whether a war with France  is more probablethan a war with a more distant power Is one that need notbe discussed here .  Should hostilities break  out with france under the conditions obtaining at  present,  wherethe latter country could put a far greater force into the airthan we could, no one can deny that the situation would  bea very serious one for this country018,     There is obviously only one means by  which wecould hope to defeat this menace, and that is by building up an air force equal or superior to that of  France.  the recognition of this fact does not strengthen  the Air Ministry1s-argument for the retention of a separate  air  force,  hehave but to examine the&apos;facts as they apply to  France herself.France, who is to launch this tremendous  air  attack, is apparently able to do so without the assistance of an AirMinistry with its attached. Air Staff,  True  she willutilise her civil aviation department to  provide commercialmachines and personnel, but no reason exists  why a british civil aviation department should not be called  upon in alike manner to assist the Army and Navy to increase their war resources.19,     On page 5, section 5, the Committee  state that theyare impressed by the fact &quot;that public funds  are admittedlybeing spent in both of the older services because of acertain overlapping with the Air&quot;,   The  Committee furtherstate that &quot;economies to an increasing extent ought to result in the older arms from the advent  of the Air Force.&quot;20.     The advent of tne aeroplane as a  weapon may result in a certain economy, but this economy will probablybe limited as experience shows us that new types of weaponsare usually added to existing types and do not  replace themto any great extent.   For instance, in the  late war,torpedoes did not replace guns, submarines have notreplaced surface ships, gas did not replace  artillery.
659 END21*      The  last  paragraph  of  this  section,  dealing with thesubstitution of machinery for  man power, is  undoubtedly true.  Butwherever possible the  Navy  has been steadily substituting machineryfor  man power during the  last  eighty years.  There seems no reasonto suppose that the  existence  of  a  separate  Air Ministry wouldaccelerate the process.22o      It would  be  undesirable,  in fact it  is impossible, fully todevelop in this memorandum  the argument  In favour  of the abolitionof the separate air  force.   It can  only  be said that  the Admiraltyare  convinced of  the necessity for  this  step both  from the point ofview of economy and  of efficiency,  and they  therefore urge that theproposal should be considered  by  such a  body as the Government may deem necessary for the purpose, in  the neer  future,25.      Turning now  to the  pxtraordinpry recommendation  of theCommittee in their Report  on the  Air Estimates, that the air squadrons serving with the  Navy should be reduced  to  one squadron in the United Kingdom  and one  Squadron in the Mediterranean, theAdmiralty desire  to protest against this proposal  in the strongest possible terms *24c      T^e  Units whihh the Admiralty have estimated to be theminimum for  Fleet efficiency in 1922-23  are  as followsAtlantic  Fleet oMedit err anean.Spotting PlanesReconnaissance PlanesFighter PlanesTorpedo PlanesSpotting PlanesReconnaissance PlanesFighter PlanesSeaplanes1 Squadron.1 Squadron *1 Squadron 1 Squadron.i  Squadronfr Squadron  Squadron5s Squadron                         -  6  Squadrons .In addition,  a  \ Squadron of  Flying  BoatsEngland and a \ Squadron at Malta,to he maintained in        The total shore of the  Navy,  therefore,  of  the Air  Estimateson their original basis will be seven Squadronso25*    The above table shows that  Air co-operation  with  the Navy-takes a number of different forms,  and this  number  of Squadronsprovides for a bare minimum for practice  and development in each*26c    Under the economies proposed by the  Geddes Committee it isproposed that the Air Estimates should be reduced to  10,000,000,and that out of this the Navy should be supplied with two Squadrons.Such a small number of machines as this would be quite useless tothe Navy, since there would be  insufficient  to ensure that  any oneof the duties for. which aircraft are required would be carried out.27o    The proposal practically amounts to  abolishing Aircraft as a naval weapon, and would effectively prevent  any possibility of substituting aircraft for surface craft in  th-o solution  of  Navalproblems, besides greatly reducing the efficiency  of all othernaval weapons, the use of which depends to  a great  extent on air co-operation -operation.

</content>
</cab>
