<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/19/0 images: 1-1</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.2(59). 22nd January, 1959			10th May, 1960


	1.	Cyprus.	[Enter M.R, Alport

S.Ll.	Disposal of our bases, if we no longer need them, is now sticking-point for Gk. Cypriots – who will not agree to any arrangements which left it open to us to hand them over to Turks.  Seeking a new formula on this.

P.M.	We shd. not allow negotiations to break down on this.


	2.	Law of the Sea.

S.L1.	Diefenbaker wdn’t move w’out consultn. with his Cabinet.  We have therefore put it to US m’while tht. a convention might be sought.
	Fishery pact for N. Atlantic: looks as tho’ Norway wd. be willing to join in discussions.  We are trying to keep all this moving.

P.M.	We shd. take initiative in calling fisheries mtg., unless US object.


	3.	Meeting of Commonwealth Prime Ministers.

P.M.	Consultns. over week-end.  PM’s have bn. restrained &amp; sensible: all seeking a way out &amp; none looking for opportunity to thrust S. Africa out of Commonwealth.  Tactics for mtg on 9/5 agreed among most.  Point of order by Louw gave opening for all PM’s to express views on racial discrimination.  Louw did not raise until end a protest that it was all out of order.  We shall not discuss it further.  Problem now is nature of communiqué.  Alternatives : factual line, reflecting what has happened, in communiqué itself or separate statement reflecting more forcefully the views of other PM’s.  I wd. prefer first alternative, if it can be secured.
	On republican issue – Louw has not bn. persuaded not to raise it.  We shall support taking note : &amp; deal with situation when it arises.


	4.	Commonwealth Ministers: Diplomatic Immunity.

Alp.	Same immunity for visiting Ministers &amp; staff as for foreigners under
	Act of ’50.  

S.L1.	Is this limited to correspondg. provn. of s.4 of Act of ’50, which is confined to conferences.  Are you proposing something wider?  Prefer it shd. be on same lines – otherwise f. countries will ask for more.

P.M.	Go no further for C. people than for foreigners.  Lawyers must agree on what is involved.

H.A.	Para. 5: leave this over pro. tem.

		Memo approved.	[Enter B-C.


	5.	Pensions.

K.	Course A: legn. this summer for increases in autumn.  Reject because can’t be financed.
	Course B:	legislate in autumn, with effect in April. x/ Objn. In
			Minister’s paper seems less serious than was originally 
			thought.
	Course C :	legislate after April.  Mght mean no increases before 1962.  
			Wd. this be regarded as implementatn. of Election 
			manifesto? 
	If BC accepts x/, wd. Cab. Agree that S.S. Cttee. shd. proceed on basis of Course B. viz., plan for that.

B.C.	On x/ difficult to give firm advice.  Adminve. troubles 	[Enter R.A.B.
	of contracting out are considerable : and if we alter figures it will increase chances of firms etc., pressing for p’ponement of introdn. of graduated contns.  Further, we have urged firms to consult employees : &amp; if we change figures they may say they ought to consult them again – again with resultg. delay.  
	Increases will be less than previously.  On that a/c earlier legn. wd. be less unpopular.  Pressures are developing.  And will be brought to a head by quinquennial review of adequacy of benefits.

H.A.	Must secure principle of no increase of benefit w’out increase of contns.  Without increase of contns. it would put £50 M. more spending power into circuln. quite inconsistent with other current economic policies. 
	Need to increase quickly – on c/living none : tho’ standards are rising.  12% rise in Apl. ’61 shd. not be unpopular.
	Even with increase contns. I wd. find increase embarrassing in ’60.  Believe increase in N.H. stamp will be needed by spring of ’61.

B.C.	My case is based, not on c/living, but on standards of prosperity.

I.M.	No political need to take Course A.

Ch.H.	Believe we can w’stand pressure long enough to run Course B.  N.A. rates cd., if need be, be raised before Apl. ’61.  Those are the hardship cases.

		Agreed : Follow Course B

</content>
</cab>