
<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/19/0 images: 25-25</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.63(60)							9th December 1960.

							[Enter M.R., R.W., Thomas
		

Transport Reorganisation : White Paper.

	Draft in revised form considered.

J.M.	Chairman of main Board and regional Boards will be appointed by Minister.  How will this affect their loyalties when sitting on central Board : will they look to its Chairman or to the Minister.

	In 1951 Hurcomb did not know what was going on in Executives because the Chairmen of latter conceived their loyalties as to Minister.
	Risk of same thing under this structure, unless personal relations are working well.

S.Ll.	Better to provide that Chairman of Regional Bds. shall be appointed by central Board with approval of the Minister.

J.M.	Para.16(b).  Is it tolerable for a Chairman of a Regional Bd. that his Genl. Mgr. shd. be on central Bd. and not he?

P.M.	May be : if, exceptionally, you have a part time Chairman – as you may want to have.

	Leave text as it stands.  Measure of flexibility.

H.B.	Co-ordinn. betwn. rlway services and bus services.  Who will see to this?

E.M.	The Council, in last resort.

P.M.	Para.27.  Shd. the companies be specified?  In footnote.
	Add to paras 29-30 reference to co-ordinn. between bus and rail services.

	Preferably by adjustment of final sentence of para.29.

R.W.	Cd. you have regional or local Cttee. to do this under the Council.

P.M.	Chairmen will also consult outside formal bodies : there will also be local arrangements.

M.	References to rlway workshop : refreshment rooms and dining cars : have bn. omitted.  Will be raised in debate.  Also employs many men.  Ques. : will they be run centrally or regionally?

P.M.	Assets will belong to Rlways Bd.  Management will be for discn.
	Say that rlway w’shops, refreshment rooms &amp; restaurant cars will be transferred as assets to central Board, but management will be discussed betwn. them and regional Boards.
</content>
</cab>