
<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/19/0 images: 27-27</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.65(60)							21st December 1960


		1.	Congo.						[Enter M.R.

		[Not heard.]


		2.	Laos.

H.	Military situation.  R. arms coming to Pathet L.  Danger was tht. Phouma or Thailand mght ask for S.E.A.T.O. help : and a civil war might turn into a Korea type of operation.  U.S. and France now see this danger and are seeking to prevent an appeal to S.E.A.T.O.  In these circs. there is a case for reviving U.N. Commn. and it might help to stop supply of arms.

	Prelimy. re-action of the local Govt. to my soundings is not warm.
	Message also to R., askg. for co-opn. in stopping supply of arms &amp; support for suggn. of U.N. Commn.

P.M.	U.S. have bn. weak (or dangerous) over this.  H. has steadied them by talks in Paris.


		3.	Agricultural Policy : Farm Improvement Scheme.

C.S.	Practical form of assistance.  £55 m. over 10 years was wrong estimate : may be nearer £75 m.  It may even out towards the end but at present we have committed half the total in ⅓rd. of time.

S.Ll.	Can I have more time to consider alternatives.  Recognise you can’t slow down the scheme.  But may be different approach.

P.M.	Concerned at rapid rise of farm rents and sales.  They were too low : surely they are going up too fast.  Must be partly down to pouring Exchequer money in for capital development.

	
4.	National Health Service.		[Enter B-C, E. Powell.

R.A.B.	H.A. Cttee. support these proposals – despite pol. doubts in para. 6 – largely because they are necessary counterweight to rise in Estimates.

E.P.	Estimates shown 10% increase : for 5 yrs. increase has bn. between 8 and 10%.  This rate of increase makes it more difft. to change emphasis of N.H.S. to accord with developmts. in medicine.

	My plan can be represented as shift of emphasis and priorities, rather than merely cuts.  Substantiated this in reln. to welfare milk, charges for specs and dentures (wh. will enable more resources to be applied to children) : drugs – cost has gone up 50% in 4 years and this wd. warrant charge of 1/6; the other 6d. is designed to secure more careful prescribing.  Experiment &amp; undertaking to review charge downwards – this is ok. for experiment has another year to run and has yielded nothing so far.

R.A.B.	Only item needing legn. is appliances.  Is that worth special Bill?
	Cd. it be combined with Bill on stamp?

J.M.	Satisfied on welfare foods – no real damage to health.
	Worried about charge because will bear most hardly on chronic sick.

K.	Necessary and courageous attempt to bring cost of N.H.S. under control.

C.S.	Prospective redn. in consumptn. of milk by larger families.  This ought to be put to med advisers before we act.

E.P.	Shd. have to give them assumptn. v. effect on consumption.

C.S.	You cd. give them present figures &amp; ask for advice on effect of say 5% fall in consumption.

P.M.	Cd. you have a differential price for larger families.

E.P.    x./	Wd. commit you to permanent subsidy for milk to largest families.

B-C.	On charges – retirement pensioners above assistance level &amp; needing drugs will protest.  This will off set effect of increasing pensions.

M.	Whole plan, by drawing attentn. to 10% rise in cost, may help to shock public into co-opn. in keeping Service under control.

H.B.	Support x. - remember adminve. cost &amp; complication of this.

P.T.	Support the need for action &amp; also the priorities approach.

Ch.H.	E.P. is seeking adminve. economies in hosp. services.  Hope something can be said on this when this plan is announced.  

E.P. 	Recognise need for this.  Have 2 points I cd. mention.

R.A.B.	   i)	Is it worth having a Bill – for £2¾ m.
	  ii)	Hope N.H.S. won’t be only apparent economy : when Estimates as a 		whole are so much increased.

S.Ll.	On ii) we can point to some new discipline in housing.
	The most alarming service is education – schools &amp; universities.
	Wish we cd. apply principle of pay as you go.

D.E.	Worried about regressive affect of 1/= on stamp.  Effect on our capacity to adjust fiscal arrangemts. to increase incentives to production and exports.

I.M.	Support this view.  Quite wrong.  These are not real economies.
	They will incur, in long run, much unpopularity : after initial welcome from Hinchingbrook and D.T.  Tho’ I will go along with it if Cabinet so desire.

S.Ll.	Rate of increase in total Estimates is about £300 m.  All the evidence is tht. direct taxation operates as a disincentive to production &amp; enterprise.  We must switch emphasis to some extent to other means of raising revenue – of which this is one.  We may have to consider increasing employers’ contn. to discourage inefficient use of man power.

H.W.	No great relief available via defence cuts.  Support this proposal.

E.P.	On Bill – this is important qua. presentn. on priorities : also enables me to offer two useful concessions.

I.M.	What about abolishing all subsidy to welfare foods &amp; w’drawing all other proposals.  This wd. avoid legn. &amp; increased charges.  But wd. yield about same saving.

C.S.	That wd. affect milk consumptn. v. seriously – and¬ throw largest families to wolves!

Hail.	Cd. subsidy be concentrated on largest families and older people.

P.M.	These are not economies – they are means of making people (users) carry more of the cost.

	Sympathetic with I.M.’s approach.  But world is changing.  In former days help was concentrated on needy &amp; cost carried by taxation.
	Now these services are so comprehensive &amp; costly, that old theories of taxation can’t be pressed too far.  Look at prob. cost of education.  New concept.  The diffy. is tht. beneficiaries of these services still include some needy.  These are ques. of adjustment rather than principle.

	Feel unhappy over this.  But see the need for a warning note.
	Genl. feeling in favour of doing this.  But –
	i) There will be trouble &amp; esp. over prescriptions.  Let us consider
	whthr. we can do more over welfare milk.
	ii) Favour retaining the proposals involving legn.

       	On i) what I mean is : try to do it all this way : if you can’t, produce a reasonable exemptn. to protect largest families.

	We must get something of order of £20-25 m.
	Further study on this basis and report back to Cabinet.


		5.	Civil Defence.				[Enter R. Wood. P.M.G.

R.A.B.	Existing p’mme is breaking down : must have a viable policy.
	Hope Cab. will approve x p’mme.  On that basis I wd. negotiate with Ch/Ex. some redns. eg. on gas electricity ports &amp; prs. oil, which wd. reduce cost.  This p’mme avoids heavy cost on food stocking.

S.Ll.	If we were strictly logical, we shd. conclude that none of this is worth while.  But believe it is politically impossible to scrap C.D.
	Therefore I accept concln. tht. some increase in cost is inevitable.
	My main objn. to X is tht. it rises.  Wd. like to see if some of that cd. be dropped.

	Doubts about printing.  

R.A.B. 	So have I.

H.B.	Don’t cut into water p’mme which is a minimum.

		Agreed  :  Ty. and H.O. to work out p’mme of X. minus.

H.B.	Evacuation.  No Govt. wd. ever order planned evacuation – for it wd. start 100% rush from big cities.  On that basis, our problem is one of presentn.  The 12 m. plan is un-workable.  At 6 m. plan is possible (tho’ I believe nonsensical : because vulnerable cities wd. be proclaimed non evacuable and because area of devastn. wd. be larger than evacuation area).  On balance recommend opening discn. with l.a.’s on basis of 6 m. – w’out commitment to the plan.
	
	It wd. educate p. opinion to limitns. of practical planning.
	N.A.T.O. allies wd. expect us to do something.

P.M.	P’pone decision on this.  We can discuss elsewhere – eg. Def. Cttee.
		
		Agreed.

	
6.	Broadcasting.

R.M.	Valuable development – and useful for exports,.
	Pilkington will finish before experiment is concluded.

P.M.G.	May become important in time.  Would market well, however, depend on transmission by radio not wire.  And Darlington experiment is by wire as is Toronto one, the only one in being.

	Pilkington view.  Experiment, if successful, wd. mean tht. Govt. wd, be pressed to give facilities – at expense of other possibilities.
	Don’t do this w’out Pilkington’s agreement.

P.T.	V. limited experiment – their own money – pretty steep to reject it.
	The firms think they have an export possibility.

E.H.	Support R.M.  

Hail.  	So do I.

D.E.	What will be the p’mmes?  Westerns etc.  I am putting a v. strong memo to Pilkington Commn. deprecating tone of I.T. p’mmes.

		Discussion adjourned.

		*	(T. of ref. of Pilkington Commn. to be circulated).
		*	(Also relations of Executive with R. Commns.  K. 
			knows of this.)

							[Exit P.M.G.


		7.	Commercial Policy : Japan.

R.M.	List is too long – covers ⅔rds. of Japan’s exports.

P.M.	How can you import a ship?  R.M. to do his homework on this &amp; show it up to P.M.

C.S.	Pilchards.  Politics in Cornwall.  

P.M.	Take a chance.
 
</content>
</cab>