
<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/19/0 images: 49-49</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>CC.C.31(61)							13th June 1961


		1.	Laos.						[Enter M.R.

E.H.	Thais have walked out because they doubt if conference can ensure neutral Laos.

	The three L. princes are now meeting in Zurich.

	
2.	Fisheries Dispute : Denmark.

E.H.	Skipper refused to return for trial.  Danes have suggested independent enquiry.

J.M.	This is best course.

	
3.	Parliament.

R.A.B.	Business for next week.

D.E.	Education.  Public Schools.  Plan of Flemming Report, now supported by H’mr. of Eton : do I continue to oppose, the debate on Private Members’ motion?

P.M.	Avoid any clear Govt. line – put all considns.

D.E.	Stand on i) no public money for selected pupils in these schools.
	ii) express hope tht. private benefactions will enable sons of old boys to go to those schools.

P.M.	Emphasise (i).

	
4.	Angola.

H.W.	Hope exercise need not be cancelled.  Awkward if strategic reserve can’t exercise.  Exercise in France cancelled.  Can’t recruit w’out glamour &amp; adventure of this kind.

D.S.	Nervous of effect on Africa.  Our line in Sec. Council was not as firm as I had hoped.

H.W.	Statement in Times that it won’t be p’poned – attributed to my Dpt. : in fact came from G. Brown.  

D.E. 	Shd. be corrected.

I.M.	Feeling in E. Africa is strong.

Ch.H.	Surely unwise to go on with this.  Nothing in recruiting argument.

P.M.	One battalion only : bluff it out.

D.S.	Then balance it by stiffer statement on P. colonial policy.

		Agreed  :  H.W. to discuss further with E.H. &amp; D.S. 

S.L.I.)	Concession here likely to lead to further pressure on H.M.G. on some 
H.     )	future occasion.

P.M.	Link it, as suggested by D.S.

D.S.	Make it clear tht. it’s for our benefit.

	
5.	Kuwait.

E.H.	Last Cab. decision.  2 Alternative courses put to Ruler : he preferred the second.  Discns. followed on details.  Draft notes secure most of our objectives &amp; afford no real ground for Arab intervention.  Para (d) is not as precise as a normal defence agreement – but it’s best we can get.
	Hope to sign on Monday next &amp; announce in H/C.
	Political Agent will have title of Consul General – tho’ still under Pol. Resident.  In time the Ruler may press for title of Ambassador, which will be awkward.  Treaty of Commerce later.

		Approved.

							[Enter Profumo.


		6.	Germany : Defence Facilities in U.K.

H.W.	Storage : no diffies. over this.  War reserves to be held far back under N.A.T.O. plans.

	Tank firing range.  It is under-used : we train in Germany.
	Odd that G. want to use this range because inconvenient &amp; costly.
	Local M.P. supports : left wing opinion &amp; N.U.M. oppose it.
	Proposal : one battn. for 3 weeks in Sept., as experiment.  This wd. require Visiting Forces Order &amp; would involve genl. debate.

K.	Necessary part of N.A.T.O. planning.  Must brave it out.

P.M.	But don’t have a long-term agreement.

R.A.B.	Will involve whole day’s debate.

		Agreed : try to avoid pro tem. the need for V. Forces Order.

							[Enter C.I.G.S.


		7.	Cameroons.

P.M.	V. diff. choice.
	a)  To leave country we have governed for many years w’out proper      
	     provision for transition wd. be comparable to Belgium in Congo – 
	     and trouble for Nigeria.
	b)  On other hand, U.N. ran plebiscite offering choice between 2 
	     alternatives excludg. that of standing alone.  They voted for Fr. 
	     Cameroons.  No oblign. on us therefore to provide for more, as 
	     union with Nigeria rejected.

I.M.	Further points –

	i)  our economic interest is larger than assumed.  £20m of Br.  
	    investment : v. fertile land.  Deputn. of Br. interests pressed for 
 	    retentn. of Br. battalion w’out which expatriates &amp; Nigerians would 
	    leave.  Danger of Communist revolution.

	ii)  We need Aid Mission, but it won’t stay w’out battalion.

H.W.	Difficult when we are being pressed by Ty. to reduce oversea mil. expenditure.

C.I.G.S.	Conditions are such that battalion has to be relieved every 6 months.
	If trouble started, we shd. need 3 battns.
	We cdn’t, with 1 battn. round up suspects before end of mandate.
	Large medical coverage : transport solely by small aircraft – no roads.  Commitment therefore is more than normal for one battn.
	Grave doubt wthr. gendarmerie cd. be trained in any short time.
	O. ranks in trees : officers don’t exist : Br. officers won’t volunteer for it : special engagements (B. &amp; Tan types) wd. be required.

D.S.	Why not put all this on U.N. – saying we will help but they must pay.

P.M.	French wd. hate that.

E.H.	We are asking Fr. Govt. what they can do to help.

C.I.G.S.	The Fr. have 3 (black) battns. &amp; are training guards indigence.
	Better sense for Fr. to organise gendarmerie for the South.
	Not v. sensible for us to try to do the thing separately there.

E.H.	Agree better to let Fr. train gendarmerie – but Br. battn. to steady posn. m’while.

K.	Assessment of C.O.  i) If battn. leaves, administrators won’t stay.
	ii) if they go, adminn. will break down  iii) in that event Communists will take over  iv) effect of that on Nigeria.

J.P.	But, whoever trains them, gendarmerie can’t be ready for 12 mos.
	Tying up 1 battn. here limits our capacity to intervene or re-inforce elsewhere – esp. in view of trend of recruiting.

D.S.	What wd. others be ready to do if we didn’t provide force requd.
	Wd. Fr. do more?  Report to U.N.

P.M.	U.N. is not a responsible unit who cd. consider it sensibly.
	Also, if you want Fr. to do more, gt. error to go to U.N.
	Might consult French, not U.N.

S.L.I.	Cost wd. have to be knocked off something else.

H.W.	It wd. be bottom priority for us.

R.A.B.	Don’t believe we cd. stave off trouble with 1 battn.

C.S.	There was always security force here – it used to be Nigerian with Br. officers.

P.M.	Agreed :	Fr. must train gendarmerie, not we.

J.H.	We haven’t got either the money or the men to do this.

D.E.	As vote has gone to C. Republic, of which Fr. are parents, this transitional commitment in the S. is theirs not ours.

P.M.	Offer £5 m. – for first year, either for Budget or for 	expatriate element in salaries of administrators.	If pressed on troops, say “no instructns.” and refer back.  R. Stevens to take this line.  Nudge French into assuming mil. commitment.

	General objective : bring our mil. obligations to an end as soon as possible after 1st October.

E.H.	U.K. will be vulnerable to criticism tht. we are doing just what Belgium did in Congo.

	After further discussion – re-affirmed summary of P.M. opposite.

P.M. 	If trouble does start, let us try to help Nigeria to deal with it.

I.M.N. 	Has no standing here.
						[Exit R.A.B., J.P. &amp; C.I.G.S.

	
8.	West Indies.

I.M.	i)	Diffy. over Jamaica has bn. got round.  ii) Confidence may break down 
	over movement between islands.  iii) Or, more likely over ques. of interim aid agreement (on which U.S. may be able to help).
	Preferable they shd. break on ii) but that is linked with aid to smaller islands.

						[Exit D.S.


		9.	Education : Teachers’ Salaries.

D.E.	Generally – feeling among teachers growing in favour of acceptance .
	On ques. raised in memo.  Danger of more arbitration : panel.
	But seek authy. at appropte. time, to open discns. with l.a.’s Ldn. &amp; Lancs are firm on commencement date.

	Amendment suggd. in annex is best way to legislate, probably, but want time to consider further with J.M.

J.M.	I am announcg. equivalent of 14% from 1st July.
	On structure : don’t want alteration in principle but wd. like my assessor to be present at all stages on employers’ side.  Will keep in touch with D.E.

D.E.	Timing – E. &amp; Sc. – may be better further apart than simultaneous.

S.L.I.	Support suggd. amendment.  Also agree D.E. shd. open talks with l.a.’s.
	
J.H.	Support memo.  But there will be strong pressure for arbitration, which is widely available in other walks of life.  Must consider this carefully.

J.M.	I’ve got it to some degree already.


		10.	Suez Finance Company.

S.L.I.	Wish now to dispose of our share holding.
	Agitation for compensation to B. subjects (Egypt) is bldg. up.
	If we have to make more money available, appropte. tht. proceeds of our share shd. help twds. it.

	Timing : prefer to have latitude on that.  Want to sell on rising market &amp; get best price.

P.M.	If you sell soon, you will be asked to give all proceeds in compensn.

E.H.	Will be 3 yrs. before that is finally settled.

P.M.	Points b and c in brief.

S.L.I.	Wd. consider all these points of tactics, if we can decide in principle.

		Agreed :	in principle we need not hold these shares.
				Method &amp; timing reserved to S.L.I.

	
11.	Civil Aviation : Airport Policy.

P.M.	If we present W. Paper, we shall be expected to legislate.  If Bill can’t be introduced next session shd. we not delay?

P.T.	We shd. lose initiative. We shd. at least make statement.

		Agreed :	policy approved : timing of announcement to be
				considered further.
</content>
</cab>