
<cab>
  <spreadsheet_ref>CAB 195/19/0 images: 61-61</spreadsheet_ref>
  <content>C.C.44(61)							27th July 1961


		1.	European Economic Community.		[Enter M.R.

R.A.B.	Draft of P.M.’s statement tabled.

S.Ll.	Formula “apply to join” – will alarm opinion here.

R.A.B.	Have suggd. words already to meet that.

E.H.	Remember opposite effect on Six.

P.T.	R.A.B.’s phrase doesn’t harm that.

D.S.	Add also : reference to Art.237 of Treaty which envisages agreement on condn. of entry.  As an elaboration of R.A.B.’s formula.  Agreed.

Ch.H.	“Only negotiations can reveal this clearer picture” cd. also be added after R.A.B.’s formula.

D.S.	Para.2.  3rd sentence may alienate Afro.Asian Doms.

K.	But this is our main reason for going in.

H.W.	Agree.

P.T.	Put it on positive basis not negative anti. Communist basis.

H.	Use the argument – but avoid reference to Communism – Agreed.
		Amendments suggested for P.M.’s consideration.

M.R.	Motion by Tory supporters.  Pretty mild.  Cd. we take any words and include them in P.M.’s statement &amp; Govt. motion?  To avoid abstentions.  Esp. on sovereignty.

P.T.	Better reply to motion on basis that it is premature : can’t say what encroachment on sovereignty until we know what is involved.

M.R.	Then, to avoid more names being added, can we bring statement forward to Friday?  I know this can’t be done.
		Form of Govt. motion approved, after amendment.

	
2.	Parliament.

		Business for next week.

	Resumption : 23 or 24/10.  Prorogue 26/7 Oct.  New Session 31/10 : at 11.30 a.m.

	Stansgate.  Judgement Friday 10.30 a.m.
	May be claim for debate next week.
	No time to propose Joint Select Cttee.

	
3.	Teachers’ Salaries.

D.E.	Reaction as expected.  Diffy. to persuade them they haven’t been singled out.  i) Hope Ministers will get it across tht. £42 m. is a generous offer : corresponds with rise in public salaries generally.
	ii) More important : both sides represented as departure my suggn. tht. Govt. shd. indicate in future size and distn. of total : this is start of a wages policy : not done for other parts of public service.  I said we shd. be doing this in public sector.  New Ty. memo. satisfies me.  Can I be assured tht. it will be basis for Govt. action ?  Can more be said about other parts of public service?

	Can Ty. Ministers say more in debate?

S.Ll.	Can repeat : no ques. of special discriminn. v. teachers.

D.E.	Can I be assured tht. I shan’t be alone in trying to keep teachers’ salaries in line with increases in productivity etc.

	L.a. expectn. tht. there wd. be more on this in S.Ll.’s speech.

	
4.	Civil Aviation : Airports.

		Presentation of White Paper approved.

	
5.	Kenya : Jomo Kenyatta.

		Doubts expressed.  After discussion substance approved.

I.M.		On timing – don’t announce when H/L. is not sitting.  I wd. prefer
	to make it on Tuesday, and face it.

H.	Someone shd. spk. to Swinton in advance.
</content>
</cab>