<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/207/0 images: 75-76</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s GovcMiment. jPrinted for the Cabinet.    November 1929.SECRET.CP. 319(29).Closer Union in East Africa.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA.The main purpose of the Hilton-Young Commission was to devise those changes, constitutional and administrative, best calculated to give effect to what they conceived to;be the true lines oil native policy in East Africa. By far the most important recommendation made was that a central anthoritj&apos; should be set up, entrusted not merely with the control of economic services, but responsible also for the co-ordination of native policy in the East African territories, and for the protection of minorities. This plan the Secretary of State for the Colonies has rejected, and in its place he recommends an alternative scheme under which, broadly speaking, the central authority would be invested with effective control over the economic services and native lands in Kenya only, while in regard to native policy and the protection of minorities the High Commissioner would in effect be little more than the watchdog of the Secretary of State.These proposals are clearly not an adaptation of the Commission^ scheme, but sornetlmifi; radically different, and when the matter is discussed in the Cabinet I am afraid that I shall be compelled to oppose Lord Passfiekrs proposal on general grounds. I would not, however, have troubled my colleagues with this memorandum were it not for the fact that the adoption of Lord Passfield&apos;s proposals would prejudicially affect the position of Indians in Kenya. The Commission, as my colleagues are aware, have proposed that the official majority in the Kenya Legislative Council should be abolished. That, proposal, however, cannot be dissociated from their main proposal as to the functions of the central authority and also from the particular balance of power, as between the racial groups, in the Legislative Council, as they proposed it should be constituted. As to the former point, it cannot be doubted that, had it not been contemplated that the central authority would be responsible for the co-ordination of native policy and for the protection of minorities, the official majority would have been retained. It is notorious that in the past the Kenya Government, even with an official majority in the Legislative Council, has failed to protect either native or Indian interests, and Lord Passfield himself admits this. How, then, can it be expected that those interests will be adequately protected if the official majority be surrendered, and if the central authority has no powers of effective control? Past experience indicates that the safeguards suggested will largely be illusory, and I find some substance in the Government of India&apos;s view that there is no necessary connection between a Federation, if confined to the economic services, and the reform of the Kenya Legislative Council. Whether their conjecture that the proposed changes in the constitution of the Council is the price paid to the European settlers for their consent to the scheme of economic federation, I do not know, but it is quite certain that this view will be held in India.If the proposals of the Commission in regard to the central authority be accepted, and if the suggestions I make later regarding the common roll also be accepted, I should have no objection in principle to the substitution of a non-official for an official majority in the Kenya Council, on the \mderstanding (which I gather is agreed to by Lord Passfield) that Indians would be eligible equally with Europeans to represent native or general interests as nominated members, and on the further understanding that Indians would be adequately represented in any Central Council that may be set up. The detailed composition of the Kenya Council would, however, require close examination, and I suggest that this could best be undertaken by a Cabinet Sub-Committee after the Cabinet itself has Beached a decision on the primary issue of the functions of the central authority. If it be decided that those functions should be limited in the manner proposed by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, then I shall have to press strongly that in the Kenya Legislative Council the status quo should be maintained. Any other course would have the most deplorable effects in India.2. Turning now to the Arital question of the common roll, I would first emphasise the extraordinary unity of opinion in India on this matter.   Indians of all classes and4072      75   11.29
of all shades of political opinion, the Indian Princes and the European community, are at one, and behind this solid mass of opinion stand the Government of India, who for many years past have championed this cause, while successive Viceroys Lord Hardinge, Lord Chelmsford, Lord Reading, and Lord Irwin have identified themselves with Indian opinion. We may belittle this feeling, we may regard it as mere sentiment, and we may argiie that, for practical purposes, representation can equally well be secured on a communal basis, but the fact remains lliat the communal franchise in Kenya is regarded as a debased form of citizenship, as political segregation and as a badge of racial inferiority. More serious still, the treatment of Indians in Kenya is regarded as a test of British sincerity. The Imperial Conference resolution of 1921 recognised &quot; that there is an incongruity between the position of India as an equal member of the British Empire and the existence of disabilities upon British Indians lawfully domiciled in some other parts of the Empire,&quot; and Indians cannot understand why, if many of the Dominions have found it possible to remove disabilities, His Majesty&apos;s Government hesitate to follow the same course in a Crown Colony.I agree with Lord Passfield that the compulsory introduction of the common roll is not practicable, but I am grievously disappointed with the recommendations he makes, and regard them as likely not to improve but to worsen the situation. To pi-opose, as he does, that the idea of a common roll should not be negatived, but that its fulfilment should be indefinitely deferred, is certain to exacerbate Indian opinion, and the cynical proposal that some form of census should be undertaken which &quot;commits us to nothing &quot; would confirm Indians in their suspicion of our sincerity. At the present juncture, when by our recent announcement as to British policy in India we have done something, to rise the Prime Ministers own words, to revive and foster a spirit of trust, co-operation and mutual understanding, it would be a calamity if, by announcing a policy such as has been suggested by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, we destroyed that spirit.I earnestly hope, therefore, that the Government will not hesitate to announce its acceptance of the very moderate recommendation made by the Commission that the common roll by consent is the ideal to be aimed at, and will at the same time undertake to do everything in its power to achieve that object, initiating, as a first step, inquiries preliminary to the adoption of the civilisation test. Until we can give the Indians some tangible proof, by action, that this policy has been adopted I feel strongly that the official majority in the Kenya Legislative Council should not be abolished. I hope, too, that Government will make it clear that the common roll,, if and when attained, is a common roll to which will be admitted not only Europeans and Indians, but all classes of His Majesty&apos;s subjects who satisfy the educational arid property qualifications ultimately adopted. It would surely be contrary to our principles to deny to. Africans or Arabs who satisfy those tests rights granted to others.&apos;. - .&apos;   * &apos; .- &apos;-.   . ;   - &quot;..        . w. b.v    12th November 1929.

</content>
</cab>
