<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/207/0 images: 168-175</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
f 99Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1929.CONFIDENTIAL. Copy No.    41CP. 331 (29).CABINET.ON the 6th November I undertook, in reply to a question put to me in the House of Commons, to consider the publication of a memorandum explaining precisely what change has been made in the rights and obligations of the United Kingdom by our signature of the Optional Clause. I have frequently alluded to this undertaking in reply to subsequent questions, and I now circulate to my colleagues for con-sideration a draft memorandum, which, if approved, might be published as a White Paper.A. H.Foreign Office, November 26, 1929. -MEMORANDUM ON THE SIGNATURE BY HIS MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERN-MENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM OF THE OPTIONAL CLAUSE OF THE STATUTE OF THE PERMANENT COURT OF INTER-NATIONAL JUSTICE.The Effect of Signature of the Optional Clause.1. ARTICLE 13 of the Covenant of the League of Nations provides as follows : &quot; The Members of the League agree that whenever any dispute shall arise between them which they recognise to be suitable for submission to arbitration or judicial settlement, and which cannot be satisfactorily settled by diplomacy, they will submit the whole subject-matter to arbitration or judicial settlement.&quot; Disputes as to the interpretation of a treaty, as to any question of inter-national law, as to the existence of any fact which, if established, would constitute a breach of any international obligation, or as to the extent and nature of the reparation to be made for any such breach, are declared to be among those which are generally suitable for submission to arbitration or judicial settlement.&quot; For the consideration of any such dispute, the court to which the case is referred shall be the Permanent Court of International Justice, established in accordance with Article 14, or any tribunal agreed on by the parties to the dispute or stipulated in any convention existing between them.&quot; The Members of the League agree that they will carry out in full good faith any award or decision that may be rendered, and that they will not resort to war against a Member of the League which complies therewith. In the event of any failure to carry out such an award or decision, the Council shall propose what steps should be. taken to give effect thereto.&quot;2. This article provides a description of classes of international disputes which are to be regarded as justiciable, that is to say, suitable for decision by a court applying rules of law. But it does not impose upon the Members of the League any actual obligation to have such disputes settled in this manner; the words &apos;&apos; they recognise to be suitable for submission to arbitration or judicial settlement,&quot; and &quot; those which are generally suitable for submission to arbitration or judicial settle-ment,&quot; leave it open to any Member of the League to refuse to have any particular dispute settled in this way.3. The original draft of the Statute of the Permanent Court of International Justice contained a provision giving the Court compulsory jurisdiction in the classes5127   [20200] ^ b
of cases set out in Article 13 of the Covenant. In the Statute as adopted by the First Assembly this was replaced by a provision which appears in Article 36 of the Statute.  It is as follows : &quot; The Members of the League of Nations and the States mentioned in the Annex to the Covenant may, either when signing or ratifying the protocol to which the present Statute is adjoined, or at a later moment, declare that they recognize as compulsory ipso facto and without special agreement, in relation to any other Member or State accepting the same obligation, the jurisdiction of the Court in all or any of the classes of legal disputes concerning (a) the interpretation of a treaty;(b) any question of international law;(c)&apos; the existence of any fact which, if established, would constitute a breach of an international obligation; (d) the nature or extent of the reparation to be made for the breach of aninternational obligation.&quot; The declaration referred to above may be made unconditionally or on condition of reciprocity on the part of several or certain Members or States, or for a certain time.&quot;4. It is the making of the declaration referred to in the above provision which is generally known as &quot; signing the Optional Clause.&quot; States which have signed the clause have done so in varying terms, but the model form which is annexed to copies of the Statute of the Court is as follows : &quot; The undersigned, being duly authorised thereto, further declare on behalf of their Government, that, from this date, they accept as compulsory ipso facto and without special convention, the jurisdiction of the Court in conformity with Article 36, paragraph 2, of the Statute of the Court, under the following conditions: &apos;&apos;5. The terms of Article 36 have been regarded as admitting the making of a reserve or exception of any kind when accepting the compulsory jurisdiction of the Court, because the jurisdiction of the Court may be accepted &quot; in all or any &quot; of the classes of legal disputes enumerated. Up to July in the present year, the Optional Clause had been signed and ratified by the following States: Belgium, Brazil, Bulgaria, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Germany, Haiti, Hungary, Norway, Netherlands, Panama, Portugal, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and Uruguay.Reasons why Signature of the Optional Clause is desirable.6. Article 2 of the Treaty for the Renunciation of &quot;War as an Instrument of National Policy, now generally known as the Pact of Peace, provides that: &quot; The High Contracting Parties agree that the settlement or solution of all disputes or conflicts of whatever nature or of whatever origin they may be, which may arise among them, shall never be sought except by pacific means.&quot; The treaty, however, does not provide any machinery for the pacific settlement of disputes. As regards disputes of a justiciable character, therefore, His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom consider signature of the Optional Clause as the logical consequence of the acceptance of the Pact of Peace. Acceptance of the Optional Clause means that disputes falling within its terms will receive from the Permanent CoiTrt of International Justice a definite solution, which the parties to the dispute are bound under Article 13 of the Covenant to &quot; carry out in full good faith.&quot; If the Pact of Peace is to be made fully effective&quot;, it seems necessary that the legal renunciation of war should be accompanied by definite acts providing machinery for the peaceful settlement of disputes. His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom believe that the first step in thus building up barriers against war is to secure the general acceptance of a system under which justiciable disputes will be settled by the operation of law. His Majesty&apos;s Government were, therefore, most anxious to sign the Optional Clause at the earliest possible moment. By so doing they hoped both to give to the world a proof of their confidence in the Pact of Peace and an earnest of their own desire to secure the peaceful settlement of justiciable disputes in which they might become involved, and also to do what lay in
their power to stimulate other nations to do the same. The extent to which the latter object has already been fulfilled is shown by the fact that the Optional Clause was signed during the last Assembly by Czechoslovakia, France, Italy, Latvia, Nicaragua, Peru and Siam, in addition to all the Dominions and India. There are, indeed, at the present moment, only thirteen Members of the League which have not signed the Optional Clause, and it is understood that some of the thirteen now have the matter under consideration.The Declaration of Signature made by His Majesty&apos;s Government in the UnitedKingdom.7. After discussion with the Governments of the Dominions before and during the Assembly, the Optional Clause was signed by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs on the 19th September in the following terms : 8. &quot; On behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom and subject to ratification, I accept as compulsory ipso facto and without special convention, on condition of reciprocity, the jurisdiction of the court in conformity Avith article 36, paragraph 2, of the statute of the court, for a period of ten years and thereafter until such time as notice may be given to terminate the acceptance, over all disputes, arising after the ratification of the present declaration with regard to situations or facts subsequent to the said ratification, other than : &quot;Disputes in regard to which the parties to the dispute have agreed or shall agree to have recourse to some other method of peaceful settlement; and&apos;&apos; Disputes with the Government of any other member of the League which is a member of the British Commonwealth of Nations, all of which disputes shall be settled in such manner as the parties have agreed or shall agree; and&apos;&apos; Disputes with regard to questions which by international law fall exclusively within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom.&quot;And subject to the condition that His Majesty&apos;s Government reserve the right to require that proceedings in the court shall be suspended in respect of any dispute which has been submitted to and is under consideration by the Council of the League of Nations, provided that notice to suspend is given after the dispute has been submitted to the Council and is given within ten days of the notification of the initiation of the proceedings in the court, and provided also that such suspension shall be limited to a period of twelve months or such longer period as may be agreed by the parties to the dispute or determined by a decision of all the members of the Council other than the parties to the dispute.&quot;9. The Optional Clause was also signed by all the self-governing Dominions of the British Commonwealth of Nations, and by India. All these, with the exception of the Irish Free State, made Declarations identical in terms with that set out in the preceding paragraph above. The Declaration made by the Irish Free State was as follows : &apos;&apos; On behalf of the Irish Free State I declare that I accept as compulsory ipso facto and without special convention the jurisdiction of the Court in conformity with Article 36 of the Statute of the Permanent Court of Inter-national Justice for a period of twenty years and on the sole condition of reciprocity.   This declaration is subject to ratification.&quot;The Effect of the Exclusions contained in the Declaration of Signature.10. At the time of signature the Secretary of State made the following-statement explaining the formula of acceptance adopted by His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment in the United Kingdom : 11. &quot;The &quot;optional clause,&apos; which His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom are now accepting, gives the Permanent Court of International Justice at The Hague jurisdiction over juridical disputes with other parties accepting the like obligation without the necessity for framing in respect of each dispute a special agreement for its submission to the court.&quot; The formula which I have just signed on behalf of the United Kingdom, and copies of which are, I believe, available, follows the usual practice in being subject to reciprocity and in including a time-limit. This is fixed at ten years, but the acceptance continues in force after the expiration of the period, unless notice is given to terminate it.   The signature is also subject to ratification.   This will enable.[20200] b 2
the question to be raised in Parliament, if so desired, before the acceptance of the compulsory jurisdiction comes into operation.&quot;The declaration accepting the jurisdiction covers only disputes which may arise in future. Past disputes and disputes relating to past events will continue to be submitted to the court under a special agreement concluded in each case.&quot;Three classes of disputes are excluded from the operation of the declaration of acceptance. These are disputes for the submission of which to some other method of peaceful settlement provision is made by existing or future agreements, disputes with other members of the British Commonwealth of Nations, and disputes about matters which fall within what is called the domestic jurisdiction of a State. Commercial treaties and conventions dealing with special subjects, such as reparations, or with technical matters, such as copyright, very often contain provisions setting up special tribunals to deal with disputes which may arise as to the meaning or application of their terms. When that is the case, the dispute will be dealt with as provided in the agreement and will not be submitted to the court at The Hague.   This is the effect of the exclusion of the first class of disputes.&apos;&apos; Disputes with other members of the British Commonwealth of Nations are excluded because the members of the Commonwealth, though international units individually in the fullest sense of the term, are united by their common allegiance to the Crown. Disputes between them should, therefore, be dealt with by some other mode of settlement, and for this provision is made in the exclusion clause.&quot; On certain matters international law recognises that the authority of the State is supreme. When once it is determined that the subject-matter of the dispute falls within the category of cases where this is so, there is no scope for the exercise of the jurisdiction of an international tribunal.&quot;At the end of the formula comes a proviso which enables disputes to be referred to the Council of the League before they are dealt with by the court. This is to cover disputes which are really political in character though juridical in appearance. Disputes of this kind can be dealt with more satisfactorily by the Council, so that the conciliatory powers of that body may be exercised with a view to arriving at a friendly settlement of the dispute. This formula places the United Kingdom in much the same position as a State which has agreed to a treaty of arbitration and conciliation providing for the reference of all disputes to a concilia-tion commission before they are submitted to judicial settlement. The formula is wide in character because the extent to which it operates depends on the Council itself. It would cease to operate from the moment when the Council decided that it was better that the question should be submitted to the court, and therefore declined to keep the dispute under consideration. Within these limits, however, the proviso would apply to any justiciable dispute, whatever its origin. It would extend, for instance, to disputes arising out of cases where it had been necessary for the United Kingdom to take action at the instance of the Council in pursuance of its obligations  IS ci member of the Leaaue.&quot;Objections Raised to Signature of the Optional Clause at the Present Time.12. With the objects which have led His Majesty&apos;s Government to sign the Optional Clause, and to ask Parliament to approve their action in doing so, there is, it is believed, general sympathy throughout the country. The objections which have been raised to the signature of the clause or, it might be more accurate to say, the hesitation which is felt in some quarters as to the desirability of doing so at the present time relate rather to certain risks to which it is thought the acceptance of the jurisdiction of the Permanent Court in justiciable disputes might expose this country and the British Empire. The view has been expressed that so much uncertainty still exists both as to the scope of international law and as to what on many points it really is, that to bind ourselves to accept the jurisdiction of the Permanent Court in all questions of international law involves a leap in the dark, and may expose us to decisions which it would be difficult, if not impossible, for us to accept. In particular, reference has been made to the difference which is alleged to exist between the Anglo-Saxon and Continental schools of thought in inter-national law, and to the diversity in relation to such matters as the evidence which is admissible in connection with the interpretation of treaties.13. In the view of His Majesty&apos;s Government in the United Kingdom, there is, as regards the matters with which the Optional Clause deals, much less uncertainty
in international law than is suggested. The alleged diversity between Anglo-Saxon and Continental schools of thought exists mainly, if not entirely, in relation to the -question of belligerent rights at sea, which is dealt with later in this memorandum. In any case, this argument, if pressed to its logical conclusion, really means that the Optional Clause should not be signed until such time as international law has been codified to such an extent as to leave no room for uncertainty as to what it is in relation to any subject. This would mean that this country must postpone the acceptance of the obligation to have all justiciable disputes determined by an international court for a period the length of which it is impossible to determine. A commencement of the work of codification has already been made under the auspices of the League of Nations, and in this His Majesty&apos;s Government are taking their share, but they see no prospect of a complete code of international law materialising in the near future. Moreover, His Majesty&apos;s Government desire to point out that codification is rather a Continental than an Anglo-Saxon method of creating and clarifying a system of law.While there are doubtless certain branches of international law which are suitable for codification, His Majesty&apos;s Government believe that the method of building up a body of law by a series of legal decisions, a method which produced the English Common Law, may be the more suitable for at any rate some important branches of the Law of Nations. This process would be indefinitely retarded if States were unwilling to submit their differences to that Court on the ground that the rules of law applicable to such cases were not definitely laid down in a code. As regards questions of evidence and procedure, His Majesty&apos;s Government consider that the Permanent Court can be trusted to build up a satisfactory system in relation to these matters, even if it does not conform in every respect to our British practice.14. Another objection which has been raised is that there may well be disputes which, though falling within one of the categories defined in the Optional Clause, are really more of a political than a legal nature, and are therefore better dealt with by a political than by a legal tribunal. His Majesty&apos;s Government fully recognise that this may be so, and they have accordingly reserved the right, by means of the declaration whose terms are quoted above, to bring any such dispute before the Council of the League. This does not, of course, mean that such a dispute will not receive a peaceful settlement, but it does mean that if the Council considers that the dispute is one which should be settled on political rather than on legal lines, it will have the opportunity of bringing about such a settlement.Belligerent Rights and the Optional Clause.15. It seems probable, however, that the practical question which underlies the apprehensions referred to above is whether the signature of the Optional Clause would, by exposing the legitimacy of British belligerent action at sea to the decision of an international court, hamper the operations of the British Navy in time of war, and on this point His Majesty&apos;s Government desire to explain fully their view of the position created by acceptance of the Covenant, the Pact of Peace, and the Optional Clause.16. At the outset of any consideration of this subject it is important to emphasise that the possibility of British naval action at sea being brought before the Permanent Court of International Justice in consequence of our signature of the Optional Clause can only arise if the country which desired to challenge the validity of such action had itself signed the Optional Clause. The only States which can sign the Protocol establishing the Permanent Court, and consequently the only States which can sign the Optional Clause, are the Members of the League and the States mentioned in the annex to the Covenant. The only States mentioned in the Annex who are not now Members of the League are the United States, Brazil, Ecuador and The Hejaz.17. The position of Brazil, which has signed the Optional Clause but is no longer a Member of the League, is peculiar, but for present purposes the question may be discussed on the basis that only another Member of the League could bring our naval action before the Permanent Court under the Optional Clause.18. It should also be borne in mind that the possibility of our belligerent action in the past being brought before the Permanent Court in consequence of our. acceptance of the Optional Clause is excluded by the terms of our Declaration.
19. Disputes as to the exercise of belligerent rights at sea have in the past arisen from the clash of two conflicting rights; the right of the belligerent to make use of his naval strength to interfere with the sea-borne commerce of the enemy, and the right of the neutral to continue his trade irrespective of the existence of a war in which he is not engaged. Both of these rights are, within certain limits, equally recognised by international law, and in the course of the last two hundred years certain principles have emerged whose effect was to define the respective scope of these conflicting rights and to lay down certain rules for regulating the situation which arose from their clash. No one, however, will suggest that the establishment of rules of international law on this subject has reached a stage which eliminates the possibility of disputes between belligerents and neutrals, and unless one is prepared to accept the possibility of the production and general acceptance of a code which would provide a satisfactory solution for every question of this sort which might arise in a quite indeterminate future, it is difficult to see how this process could ever eliminate the possibility of serious disputes of this nature. And public opinion in this country is naturally sensitive as regards any action which might be considered as unduly limiting the exercise of British sea power in time of war.20. But the whole situation described in the preceding paragraph rests, and international law on the subject has been entirely built up, on the assumption that there is nothing illegitimate in the use of war as an instrument of national policy, and, as a necessary corollary, that the position and rights of neutrals are entirely independent of the circumstances of any war which may be in progress. Before the acceptance of the Covenant, the basis of the law of neutrality was that the rights and obligations of neutrals were identical as regards both belligerents, and were entirely independent of the rights and Avrongs of the dispute which had led to-the war, or the respective position of the belligerents at the bar of world opinion.21. Now it is precisely this assumption which is no longer valid as regards States which are Members of the League of Nations and parties to the Peace Pact. The effect of those instruments, taken together, is to deprive nations of the right to employ war as an instrument of national policy, and to forbid the States which have signed them to give aid or comfort to an offender. As between such States, there has been in consequence a fundamental change in the whole question of belligerent-and neutral rights. The whole policy of His Majesty&apos;s present Government (and, it would appear, of any alternative Government) is based upon a determination to comply with their obligations under the Covenant of the League and the Peace Pact. This being so, the situation which we have to envisage in the event of a wrar in which we were engaged is not one in which the rights and duties of belligerents and neutrals wall depend upon the old rules of Avar and neutrality, but one in which the position of the Members of the League will be determined by the Covenant and the Pact. If His Majesty&apos;s Government comply with their obligations under those instruments, there are only two conditions in which, they could be involved in war : (1) where a State has gone to war with them in violation of one or both of those instruments,* or (2) if they go to Avar in order to fulfil their obligations under Article 16 of the Covenant against a Covenant-breaking State. In either case Article 16 would apply, and so far from the other Members of the League being in the position of neutrals with a right to trade with our enemy, which might conflict with our belligerent rights and thus produce a justiciable dispute, they Avould be bound under that article to sever all relations with him; they could neither trade direct with him nor allow their territories to be used for the passage of commerce between him and any other State. This being so, the conditions which might produce a justiciable dispute between this country as a belligerent and another Member of the League as a neutral would not exist; either the other Members of the League would fulfil their obligations under Article 16, in which case we should not require to effect any interference with their commerce, or if they did not, and such interference on our part therefore became necessary, they Avould have no ground on which to protest against our action, since any protest must be based on a claim to trade with the enemy, which would be inconsistent with their obligations under the Covenant. In other words, as between Members of the League, there can be no neutral rights, because there can be no neutrals.* It is still possible, in narrowly restricted circumstances, for a State to go to war in violation of the  act without necessarily violating- the Covenant, and in such a case Article 16 would theoretically not apply. These circumstances seem, however, most unlikely to arise in practice, and the possibility of their doing so will be eliminated if the Covenant is amended as proposed by the British. Delegation at the 1929 Assembly.
22. Once this fundamental change in the situation is realised, it will be seen that the ordinary arguments against submitting British naval action to arbitral decision have ceased to be relevant to any discussion of the Optional Clause. Once it is established that in the conditions created by the Covenant and the Pact a Member of the League does not possess any right to carry on commerce with the State with which we are at war, and that we are no longer obliged to rely, in order to stop such commerce, on the old rules governing the relations of belligerent and neutral, it is immaterial to argue that those rules are uncertain and liable to become out of of date, or that there is a difference between the Anglo-Saxon and Continental schools of law, or that the Permanent Court has no rules of evidence, or that the majority of its judges will be neutrals and biassed against the belligerent. Any such arguments can only be based on the assumption, express or implied, that the Covenant and the Pact will break down in practice. If this assumption is made, it means that the whole machinery for the preservation of peace, so laboriously constructed since 1918, would have broken down; the Peace Pact and the Covenant would have become scraps of paper, but at the same time the one thing which remained standing in the general wreck would be the Optional Clause and our com-commitments thereunder. This seems to His Majesty&apos;s Government an inconceivable situation. They do not believe that it would be possible for the Optional Clause to survive in the general ruin.23. It is not, however, necessary to maintain that no difficulties would arise in the circumstances indicated in paragraph 21 above. It is always possible that a British warship might seize a ship under the mistaken belief that it was engaged in trade with the enemy&quot;State, and it is possible that a British prize court might condemn the ship or cargo on insufficient evidence of enemy destination. In such a case another Member of the League whose nationals were interested in the transaction in question might protest and make a claim against us. But the issue so raised would not involve any question of principle as to the legitimacy of our belligerent action at sea; the question would be simply one of fact whether the transaction did, in fact, involve commerce with the enemy-and such matters can, if necessary, be disposed of, without involving any question of principle, by the release of the property or the payment of compensation. In any case, we have reserved the right to bring any such dispute before the Council instead of leaving it to the Court, and in so far as the action complained of was taken in accordance with Article 16, it is reasonable to claim that the Council, as the body at.whose instance such action is taken, should deal with any such complaints. If, as suggested above, the issue raised in any such dispute could only be one of the facts in a particular case, it is likely that the dispute would be settled without being brought before the Court.24.   The above considerations may be summed up as follows : (1.) The policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is based on a determination to fulfil their obligations under the Covenant of the League and the PeacePact.(2.) If those obligations are fulfilled, we cannot be involved in war in circum-stances in which any Member of the League could claim the rights of a neutral; only Members of the League which have signed the Optional Clause can bring us before the Permanent Court under its terms, and, therefore, no dispute arising out of neutral complaints of our naval action could come before the Court. Arguments based on the state of affairs created by the old law of belligerency and neutrality are therefore irrelevant.(3.) If any dispute should, nevertheless, arise with another Member of the League as to the legitimacy of particular action which we have taken, it is probable that such a dispute would be more suitable for settlement by the Council than by the Court, and we have the right to bring it before the Council if we wish to do so.(4.) If the system erected by the Covenant and the Peace Pact breaks down, this catastrophe would sweep away the Optional Clause as well.Questions which by International Law fall exclusively within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom.25. The suggestion has been made that the exclusion from our acceptance of the Optional Clause&quot;of &quot;questions which by international law fall exclusively within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom &apos;&apos; would enable us to maintain that questions
of prize were excluded from our acceptance of the Optional Clause. His Majesty&apos;s-Government wish to make it plain that this is not their view. Although it is true that jurisdiction in matters of prize belongs to the courts of the States concerned, the law which prize courts administer in such matters is international law, and His Majesty&apos;s Government do not consider it possible to contend that international law regards such questions as being &quot;matters of domestic jurisdiction&quot;; such an argument would involve that belligerent action at sea could in no circumstances whatever become the subject of diplomatic discussion. As has been indicated above, however, it is possible that, should such a dispute arise with another signatory of the Ojptional Clause, the matter might be considered more suitable for determination by the Council than by the Court. His Majesty&apos;s Government further consider that our acceptance of the Optional Clause makes no difference to the principle that prize cases must be decided first in our own prize courts before any question of a reference to the Permanent Court could arise. The rule of international law that arbitration cannot be claimed unless and until the remedies provided by municipal courts have been exhausted is, in their opinion, as applicable to prize courts as to any other municipal tribunals. Moreover, the function of prize courts is to decide whether the action of the captor was legitimate, and until a final decision on this point has been given by those courts, it cannot be known whether any case for international complaint has arisen.26. As considerable attention has been directed to the reservation relating to &quot; questions which by international law fall exclusively within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom,&apos;&apos; it may be pointed out that this is merely an explicit recognition of a limitation on the jurisdiction of the Permanent Court which results from inter-national law itself. It is merely the application in this connection of the principle that, subject to any relevant treaty stipulations, a State is entitled to regulate as it pleases matters which fall exclusively within the domain of its national sovereignty. Within that domain, and subject always to treaty provisions, a foreigner must take things as he finds them, and his State is not entitled to protest against the result.The Imperial Conference Resolution of 1926 concerning the Optional Clause.27. At the Imperial Conference of 1926 the following agreement was reached by His Majesty&apos;s Governments there represented : &quot; A general understanding was reached that none of the Governments represented at the Imperial Conference would take any action in the direction of the acceptance of the compulsory&apos; jurisdiction of the Permanent Court without bringing up the matter for further discussion.&quot;28. Such &quot; further discussion &quot; was begun on the initiative of His Majesty&apos;s Government in Canada in February 1929. It was actively continued during the months preceding the Assembly of the League of Nations, a,nd reached its conclusion at Geneva, when all His Majesty&apos;s Governments in the British Commonwealth, including India, decided to sign the clause forthwith.29. This new agreement among His Majesty&apos;s Governments concerning the vital question of international arbitration marks a further step in the acceptance of common principles on which the foreign policy of all these Governments can be based.Conclusion.30. The above examination of the effect of the signature of the Optional Clause by His Majesty&apos;s Government under the terms of the Declaration cited above shows that the fears which have been expressed as to the consequences of this signature are without foundation. The broad question remains : Is it safe to trust British interests to the decision of the Permanent Court ? The question may be transposed : Is it wise to leave British interests without any safeguard except war, which we have undertaken not to wage? His Majesty&apos;s Government believe that to the last question only one answer can be returned. They hold that the whole course of international development for many years past has been in the direction of the substitution of arbitration for war, and they rejoice to think that there now exists an International Court, whose competence and impartiality are unchallenged, to which may safely be referred all international disputes of, at any rate, a justiciable character. Such a reform is, in their view, an essential part of the effort seriously to implement the undertakings of the Pact of Peace and to utilise the early years of peace in creating effective safeguards against war, before its realities have been forgotten. -_   -:&quot; o

</content>
</cab>
