<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/207/0 images: 223-225</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.   November 1929.SECRET. Copy No.    36CP 335 (29).CABINET.OPERATION OF DOMINIONS LEGISLATION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs.SINCE the discussion at the Cabinet of my memorandum CP. 316 (29) of the 11th November (see Cabinet Conclusions 47 (29), Conclusion 4), the work of the Conference on the Operation of Dominion Legislation has been practically limited to discussions in the Committee under the Chairmanship of Sir Maurice Gwyer on the various points outstanding with reference to the operation of the Colonial Laws Validity Act, 1865, in relation to Dominion legislation.It has been a matter of the greatest difficulty for agreement of any kind to be reached, but the Committee, after prolonged negotiations, are, I understand, on the point of submitting a unanimous report setting out the greatest common measure of agreement which they can reach.The report, I understand, proceeds on the basis of recommending that all restrictions upon the legislative powers of the Parliaments of the Dominions should be removed, and that those Parliaments should acquire legislative powers as unrestricted as those of the Parliament of the United Kingdom. If the recommendations are carried out, uniformity of legislation within&quot; the British Empire will thus rest in future on a basis of agreement only.The full Conference will have to consider within the next few days what action should be taken with reference to this report. Hence, the Attorney-General and I feel bound to ask for immediate instructions from the Cabinet as to the line which we should take.I can best make the position clear by stating how the subjects mentioned in CP. 316 (29) stand in the light of the contemplated report of Sir M. Gwyer&apos;s Committee.(A.) Legislation with regard to the Crown.It is proposed that there should be a constitutional convention, to be agreed at the next meeting of the Imperial Conference, and, after approval by the Dominion Parliaments, to be embodied as one of the preambles to the Act to be passed by the Parliament at Westminster, which will be needed, in any case, to give effect to the general recommendations resulting from the present Conference. Such a convention would declare, in substance, that it would be &quot; in accord with the present constitutional position of all the members of the CommonAvealth in relation to one another that any alteration in the law touching the succession to the Throne or the Royal Style and Titles shall hereafter require the assent as well of the Parliaments of all the Dominions as of the Parliament of the United Kingdom.&quot;I understand that Sir Maurice Gwyer&apos;s Committee discussed, in addition to the method to be set out in the report, both the other methods of dealing with the problem outlined in CP. 283 and CP. 316, viz.-(a) legislation by the Parliament at Westminster which would be of overriding-authority, and(b) a formal agreement dependent on concurrent legislation;[20199]
but that the Committee could not agree on the first, because it was thought by some members not to be in accordance with the principle of equality of status, or on the second, because it was thought by some members to savour of federalism.At a meeting of Heads of Delegations held last week I obtained general approval to the proposition that, unless the Conference should find itself in a position to make a recommendation on the subject of the Crown to which all could agree, it would be best to- refer to the matter in the Report of the Conference in quite general terms, leaving it for decision by the Imperial Conference, but it subsequently appeared that such a course would be strongly objected to, and would probably lead to conflicting reports.I have now discussed the position with my colleagues on the Cabinet Committee appointed in pursuance of Cabinet 47 (29), Conclusion 4.The Lord Privy Seal, the Attorney-General and I are agreed that the genernl acceptance of a Constitutional Convention of this character is likely, in fact, to have as powerful a sanction, and to prove as effective, as the maintenance of the exclusive right of the Parliament of the United Kingdom to legislate on the subject of the Crown.   The Lord Chancellor, I understand, takes a similar view.Hence I recommend to the Cabinet that the Attorney-General and I should he authorised to accept and to sign, as members of the present Conference, a Report recommending a constitutional convention on the above lines relating to the Crown.I should add that the Lord President of the Council desires that.his dissent from, this recommendation should be recorded. His view was that no mention of the Crown should be made in the Report of the present Conference, on the ground that the question was not directly referred to it. After careful consideration, I feel that it would be difficult to defend a report which recommended the grant to the Dominions of complete legislative powers without a safeguard for the position of the Crown.(B.) Certain Aspects of Defence Legislation.The report of Sir M. Gwyer&apos;s Committee is likely to recommend that, in connexion with the exercise of extra-territorial legislative powers, provision should be made whereby the troops of each member of the Commonwealth should enjoy, when in the territories of other members of the Commonwealth, the customary extra-territorial immunities as regards internal discipline. In other words, it is proposed that effect should be given to the principle involved by means of legislation of all the Parliaments.I gather that Sir Maurice Gwyer, while finding complete agreement on the principle, was not able, in spite of many efforts, to secure the approval of all his colleagues on the Committee to the recommendation either (a) of legislation of the Parliament at Westminster which would be of general application (as outlined in CP. 283) or (b) of a general formal agreement (as outlined in CP. 316).As I understand it, the actual course likely to be proposed in the report of Sir M. Gwyer&apos;s Committee would not meet the views of the Service Departments, and I should, of course, have liked, if I could, to have secured acceptance of one of the other courses mentioned above. Nevertheless, the Attorney-General and I feel (and I think that in this we have the general support of the members of the Cabinet Committee) that, so far as the Dominions are concerned, procedure on the basis of reciprocal legislation (i.e., where new legislation is necessary) is likely to give us all the results we require, and that we should not be justified in refusing to accept the plan proposed, as part of a general agreement. It may be necessary to face difficulties later on in connection with India, but I do not think that this possibility should be allowed to endanger the prospect of reaching an agreed settlement with the Dominions.(C.) The Law of Prize.It is likely to be recommended by Sir Maurice Gwyer&apos;s Committee that uniformity of the Law of Prize and co-ordination of Prize Jurisdiction should be maintained. The Attorney-General and I are inclined to think that, so far as the present Conference is concerned, it would be best to rest content with this general recommendation, more especially as I am told by Sir M. Gwyer that he hopes that his Committee will prepare a separate confidential note setting out clearly, for con-sideration by the Governments, the present position and the problems.
(D.) Suggested Empire Court.This matter is still under discussion by Sir M. Gwyer&apos;s Committee, and I think that there will be some recommendation in general terms to the effect that the question of a Tribunal for settlement of Inter-Imperial disputes should be further examined by the Governments before the next Imperial Conference.As regards Dominion Constitutions, the report of Sir M. Gwyer&apos;s Committee is likely to contain statements to the effect (a) that the exercise of the legal powers of constitutional amendment in theUnion of South Africa is conditioned by the provisions of section 152 of the South Africa Act (i.e., the section which provides that in certain cases amendment of the Constitution requires agreement by not less than two-thirds of the members of both Houses of the Union Parliament), and(b) that in the case of the Irish Free State the powers of constitutional amend-ment are exercised in accordance with the obligations undertaken by the Articles of Agreement of 1921.These statements do not go very far, but they do at any rate do something to meet the points which I raised at the end of CP. 316.I should add that, at the meeting of Heads of Delegations, already mentioned, I obtained provisional approval to the insertion of a concluding passage in the Report of the Conference carrying out the desire of the Cabinet as indicated in Cabinet 39 (29), Conclusion 2 &quot;(e), viz., that it should be mentioned that it will be for the Imperial Conference, and the various Governments concerned, to come to a-final decision as to the method of carrying out the recommendations of the Conference. But if the Attorney-General and I can succeed in getting a passage of this kind included when the Report of the Conference comes finally to be drafted, we shall, I think (as this will be the wish of nearly all the delegates), have to allow it to be implied, even if it is not expressly stated, that the signatories to the Report  at any rate those who are Ministers are prepared to recommend its adoption by their respective Governments.Whilst it would formally be possible for any Government to reopen at the next Imperial Conference any of the matters which are dealt with in the Report, I think that, in practice if the Report is adopted by nearly all the Governments it would prove impossible for the questions to be reopened, except in a way which did not affect the main principles.Oil the other hand, I should be wrong if I led the Cabinet to believe that, if we allow the present Conference to break up without agreement, we should not have to face at the next Imperial Conference difficulties at least as great as those which have been encountered during the last few weeks.&apos; P.November 25, 1929.

</content>
</cab>
