<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/162/0 images: 74-78</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
I  (THIS D0CUH3NT IS THE PROPiSRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S SOVERHMEHIh)l yj!iff R, E T CP, 405 (23)C A B I M E I.JAPAN IOM0RIAT. SERVICE.1.     Letter from lord Curzon to Lord Stamfordham.2.     Telegram from Sir C. Eliot toSir if. Tyrrell.i)3.     Telegram from Lord Crewe to Lord Curson.4.     Telegram from Foreign Office toLord Curcon repeating message from Lord Stamfordlicai.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I., 24th September, 1923.
(1)Copy of letter from Lord Curzon to Lord Stamfordham.September 80th, 1923,.We have received a telegram, which I enclose, from .Sir Charles  Hot, our Ambassador now on his way back to Japan, in which he draws attention to the disparaging comparisons that may be drawn between tho American expres-sions of sympathy towards the Japanese in connection with the earthquake disaster and our own.   I agree that the  185,000 or so to which the. Mansion House Fund has slowly risen looks small beside the 5,000,000 dollars which wore so promptly subscribed in the United States; but for that the burden1 of taxation and the increased claims of our own charities are mainly responsible.It remains important, however, that at this moment when the Anglo-Japanese Alliance has been recently ended we should seize this exceptional opportunity of showing that we still regard the Japanese as our friends and value their friendship.The question at ence arises as to what form this expression ef national sympathy should take. A large reconstruction loan from Government to Government has been suggested; but to this the Treasury are opposed. Prance and Italy have declared each a day of mourning with flags at half-mast. But to follow this Sxample three weeks late would be worse than doing nothing at all.The suggestion has been made and meets with support in authoritative quarters that a memorial service should be held at St. PaulTs.     If this ,couldba arranged, and if His Majesty could be present.,, it would cause immense satis-faotion to tho Japanese, probably more than any money sub-scription could give either here or in the United States,
A selemn national aot of sympathy such as this would gratify them in their mast sensitive spot - namely, their desire for public recognition as friends on equal torms of the British people.The lack of precedent might ho urged as an argument in favour of the proposal.   It would be an unprecedented token of friendship to the Japanese in an unprecedent&apos; dented disaster.   Two thirds of Tokyo, the national capital, have been destroyed; one of the principal ports (Yokohama), and one of the principal naval bases (Yokosuka), have beon demolished; a great number of towns and villages have been utterly wrecked.   Tho death-roll amounts to -something between 100,000 and 200,000.   a million at least are homeless.   Two princessos and one prince of the Imperial House have lost their lives, also members of the Embassy staff and of the staff of the Consulate-General at Yokohama, and - so far aa is known at presont - some 70 to 80 other British subjects.   The magnitude of the disaster is therefore indisputable.Whether a memorial service is tho best method of indicating our   sympathy is the question which I would desire to submit to the King for His Majesty1s views, since Royal participation would be an indispensable element of suoooss.If the idea were approved, tho ceremony could take place at any convenient date within the nest two months, although it would be desirable that the notice should be made public as soon se possible.
(2) 52Telegram from Sir C. Eliot to Sir tf. Tyrrell---------- 13th- S eptemb er 192-2&apos;PBIVATK. &quot; &quot;    &quot; &apos;    -   &apos;  &quot; -&apos;&quot;   &apos; -I&apos;see&apos;in&quot;newspapers continual references to assistance offered to Japan-by-United States but none to- similar-British action.    I hope &quot;that omission is only apparent. . Japanoso&quot;aro extremely sensitive and will not&apos;forget-friendly action.   On the&quot;other hand there will be no. lack of mischief makers trying; to show that-japan&apos;s old ally is not doing&apos;much for her.- &apos;(3)    :Telegram from Lord Grewe to Lord Curzon.   &apos;6th September, 1923.MOST URGENT.fronoh Council of Ministers today decided that as a mark of mourning after the catastrophe which has ravaged Japan tomorrow (Friday) flags shall be flown half mast on all public buildings; that the subventioned theatres shall be closed and that all theatres, music halls, concerts, balls and cinemas etc. all over Prance shsll be requested to closerU)Telegram to Lord Curzon from Foreign Office repeating Message from Lard   S* mforcftiam. &quot;22nd September,1923.Following from lord Stamfordham begins;-If the Government as a government are of opinion that this Memorial Service should be held and advise the iling that this is the best means of showing their sympathy and-3-   &apos;
interest with Japan, The King will waive question of precedent and will attend the service if it is held Friday morning October 12th.   He will expect all the members of the Government to attend the service. Relevant papers have been sent to Prime Minister.lindsay.

</content>
</cab>
