<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/162/0 images: 203-226</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[jgT^DpOTJBEMT IS TEEPROPIiRTY OF HIS BRITAIffilC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVFRKMBNTQ A B I N E TglgTH CONFERENCE OF THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR ORGANISATION AND TWENTIETH SESSION OF THE GOVERNING BODY OF TEE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR OFFICE, OCTOBER, 1925. Memorandum by the Minister of Labour.;417(23) The Fifth Session of the General Conference ofMembers of the International Labour Organisation opens at Geneva on Monday, October and 1023, to discuss the general principles for the organisation of factory inspection.     The composition of the Delegation is shown in the Credentials, of which a ...        copy is attached,   (Appendix I).The Conference will consider according to the English test of the Agenda &quot;General Principles for the Organisation of Factory Inspectidntt-&quot;and a Draft ,,,  &apos;     Recommendation, of which a copy is enclosed (Appendix V); has been circulated by the I.L.O. for the consideration of the delegates to the Conference,It is important to note that the English term &quot;Factory Inspection&quot; and the French expression &quot;Inspection du Travail&quot;, both of which appear in the official agenda, have different meanings, the French being much wider than the English,       *After full consideration the British Government took the view that the agenda should be regarded as applying to factory inspection as that term is under-stood&apos; in Great Britain and should not be extended to . other branches of industries such as mining, transport, agriculture, where different considerations arise.
The International Labour Office were informed accordingly, and the British Delegation to the Conference has been constituted on this basis.    Amongst other reasons, it was pointed out that if the Conference was to last no longer than a week as the &quot;International Labour Office had proposed, it was impossible for the Conference to discuss any wider subject with the hope of arriving at any practical recommendations or results.It will be seen that the Draft Recommendation proposed by the International Labour Office seeks to arrive at a compromise between the French and English conceptions.     It appears desirable, however, that the British Government delegates should maintain the   point of view expressed in the communica-tion to the International Labour Office, taking whatever steps they may think most suitable to give effect to it, and I propose, unless my colleagues see objection, that they should be instructed accordingly.     It will always be open to the delegates -&quot;&quot;if, in their view, circumstances should render some concession necessary, to telegraph for further instructions.The Governing Body of the International Labour Office will meet at Geneva on.Monday, 15th October, 1923.   Mr.Betterton, Parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour, will attend the meeting as the representative of the British Government. A copy of the Agenda of the Session is attached (Appendix II)..Mr. Betterton will be given the instructions s*t out in Appendix III with regard to the Agenda, unless objection is raised.     The questions were all discussed at a meeting of the International Labour Committee held on the 9th October and the Instructions which it is proposed to give Mr. Betterton have been framed in the light of the recommendations of that Committee and of the views of the various Departments.(int) M.B.stry of Labour, 13th October, 1923.
APPENDIX I.Il^AC^BDANCS with Article a*9 of the Treaty of Versailles of 28th June, 1919:2 HEREBY APPQIET the following representatives of HisBritannio.Majesty&apos;8 Government, end the following Advisers toeeoompany these representatives, to attend the fifth Session ofthe International labour Oonferenoe, convened by the governing body of the International Labour Organisation, to assemblein Geneva on the iEwenty-seoond Day of October, nineteen Hundredand Twenty-three:Mr. Henry Bucknall Betterton, C.B.E., M.P., parliamentary Secretary to the Ministry of Labour,8ir Maloalm Delevingne, K.C.B.,Assistant Under Secretary of State, Home Office,to be Government delegates;:and Mr. Oswald Coleman Allen, C.B.L,,Principal in charge of the International Labour Division, Ministry of Labour,Mr. Gerald Bellhouse, G.B.&amp;.,H.M.Ohief Inspector of factories. Home Office,Miss Oonstance Smith, 0.B.L,,H.M.Deputy Chief Inspector of factories, Home Office,to be Advisers to the Government Delegates:AND I NOMINATE, in agreement with the National (Jonfedera-tlon of Employers1 Organisations:-Mx. JameB Lithgow,Shipbuilder, Colliery Owner, Iron end Steel Manufacturer etc., Ex-President of the Shipbuilding Employers1 Federation; Vice -President of the National Confederation of Employers&apos; organisations to be Delegate representing the Employers:and Mr, John Ballingall Forbes Watson,Seoretary General of the National Confederation of Employers&apos; organisations to be an Adviser to the Employers&apos; Delegate:/AND
MB III AGH&amp;uvfliillT with the General Council of the TradesUnion CongressMr. Edward Lawrence Poulton, O.B,Lt, JJ?.,Seoretary of the national Union of Boot and Shoe Operatives; Member of the General Gouncil of the Trades Union Congress,to be Delegate representing the Workpeople,and miss Margaret Graoe Bondfield, J.P., Chairman of the General Council of the trades Union Congress: Secretary of the Women Workers1 Section of the national Union of General Workers,Mr. Andrew ConleySecrotary of the Tailors1 and Garment Workers&apos; Trade Union,to be Advisers to the Workpeople^ Delegate.AHD I FUBTHEB APPOIHIMr, Alfred Ernest Kingham,Assistant Principal, International Labour Division, Ministry of labour,to be Seoretary to the Delegation,(Signed)     C. A. IvIOEEAGUL BABLOW, MIBISESB 0l? LABOUB.LOHDOH.5th Ootober. 19230
POfliagE SLBS10N Off THL GOVEBHIMQ BOZg OF THE IMTISBMAJIQML LABOUR QFJIQ3S QBHBVA; 15TH OCTOBEB, 1988.Amende.I. Approval of the&apos; minutes of the nineteenth Session. 2. The Director&apos;s Beport.3. Preparation of the 1923 and 1924 Conferences. 4. Agenda of the lttLS Conference.5. Convocation of the Joint Maritime Commission: date and agenda.6. fieport of the Eight Hours Committee.7. Report of the Building Sub-Committee.8. Beport on the decisions of the Fourth Assembly of the League of Hations.9. Beport of the Committee on Standing Orders.10. Beoord of the meeting of the Advisory Agricultural Committee.II. Beoord of the meeting of experts on questions oonoerning the Disabled.12. Subsidy for the Technical and Scientific Institute of Erosthesis and Suxgieai Apparatus of Brussels.13. Beoord of the meeting of the Advisory Committee on Industrial Hygiene.14.  ate end place of the next Session.
APPENDIX III.INSTRUCTIONS to Mr. Betterton with regard to the Agenda of the 80th Session of the Governing Body of the International Labour Office.Item 1.   Approval of tho Minutes of the Nineteenth Session.No question arises.Item 2.   Report of the Direotor.Bibliography of Industrial Hygiene.    Mr. Betterton will ask for further information on the proposal to add to the Bibliography of industrial hygiene a catalogue of kinematograph films dealing with labour and, subject to any satisfactory explanation that may be offered, will express the view that the proposal is an unnecessary extravagance.Collaboration with Scientific Institutions.     Mr. Betterton will ask for further information on the proposals of the Office to collaborate with the University of Chicago and the Russell-Sage Foundation in connection with their respective enquiries in Europe into family allowances and emigration questions. While there would be no objection to the Office receiving payments from these bodies to reimburse it for any exceptional expenditure which it might incur . owing to collaboration in the investigations, et Bhould be made olear that the Office must not seize the opportunity of embarking upon further work, the oost of whioh would not.be met by any small payments made by the University or the Foundation. Confidence in the Office.     At the Sixth meeting of the Fourth Committee of the Assembly of the League, held on the 15th September, the Director/stated
stated that &quot;during the four years&apos; existence of the International Labour Office, its Governing Body, including the Employers * Group, which was a severe critic, had unanimously been of opinion that it had no criticisms to make on the efficiency of the Office&quot;.In his Report to the Twentieth Session of the Governing Body the Director hinted that it would be a matter of the greatest satisfaction to him if the Governing Body were to express their full approval of the manner in which the Office is conducted.A representative of the Employers&apos; Group on the Governing Body will probably question the accuracy of the Director&apos;s statement at the meeting,of the Fourth Committee of the Assembly referred to above,    but if he does not do so it may be necessary for Mr. Betterton himself to raise the question of -the authority for the Director^ statement, and to secure that the British Government is not committed to an all-embracing vote of confidence in the Office, Emigration;     It is possible that the Office will seek the support of the Governing Body for a proposal that its interest in emigration questions is such as to make it necessary to ask the Italian Government to limit the scope of the Conference for the examination of emigration problems to be held in Rome early next     year   (. e.g, to preliminary and technical work)    and to allow the International Labour Office to be represented at the Conference. &quot;*Generally it is felt that the admitted claims of the International Labour Office to deal with certain aspects of emigration are not such as to/Justify
justify it in asking any Great Power to limit the scope of a Conference on emigration which it may convene, but they are such as to make it not out of place for the Italian -overnment representative on the (Jovernin,? Body to be asked to convey to his Government the desire of the International Labour Office to be represented at the Conference.The Ministry of Labour is in consultation with the Foreign Office and the Board of Trade as to the exact form of instructions which should be given to Mr.Betterton in this connection.Nominations for&apos; Commissions of Enquiries established under Article 4&quot;i2 of thc7&quot;&quot;freaty:The Bulgarian Government has nominated the Chief of the Labour Section of the Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Labour as a &quot;person of independent standing&quot; on the panel.   Mr.Betterton may find an opportunity of raising the question whether the nomination of a Government official satisfies the requirements of the Article. Item 3,   Preparations for the 1925 and 1924 Conferences;No question arises (but see Item 4, belc-v, as to Anthrax). Item 4:   Agenda of the 1925 Conference: Two subjects in particular have been suggested:-(a) The method of fixing minimum wage rates especially in Industries which are not organised; *(b) Social insurance the latter item, which would, of course, need to be carefully defined, has been suft nested by the International Labour Office.j[See no objection to Mr.Betterton supporting the inclusion of (a) and - subject to proper definition - the inclusion of (b) as a second item.   He^will also make every effort to get an assurance that an opportunity for full discussion of the/question
creation WE Anthrax will he given at the 1924 Conference. Item 5: Convocation of them Jo int Maritime Commission;Mr. Betterton will not oppose the proposal of the Office to oall a meeting of the Joint Maritime Commission for some date between the 16th Uovember and the 15th December, 1923,   On the various items on the Agenda, he will make the following observations:-(a) International Seamen&apos;s Code;   Ho objection to con- . sideration of draft international seamen^ code. Vihile recognising the advantages of such a code or of the consolidation of the Merchant Shipping Law of this oountry, the British Government do not consider 3uoha code or the consolidation of British law to be a matter of immediate urgency or of the first importance^ but careful consideration will be: given to any draft considered by the Joint Maritime Commission as a basis of a satisfactory oode.(b) Beport of.the Sub-Committee on Deck Cargoes;Ho objeotion to examination of problem by Joint Maritime Commission but the British Government are not yet in a position to indicate the results of the British enquiries into the matter.(c) Institution of Rational Joint Committees of Shipowners&apos; and&quot; Seamen to examine questions &quot;relating &apos;io&apos; the employment of seamen;      &quot;       aHo objeotion to inclusion of this question on theAgenda of some future Conference.   Mr, Bettertonwill explain the position in this country,U) Bstablishment of an effective system for&apos; theprotection c^f &quot;seamen against&apos; sickness, acoidents, old age, disablement&apos; and other aoolalj risks of the,..- -&quot;same nature;Mo objeotion to placing the question on the Agenda of some future Conferenoe./item 6,
Item 6; Report of the Eight Hoars Committee.The Governing Body will have brought before it a resolution and amendment by. the British Workers&apos; representative adopted by the Committee which met in Paris on the 2nd June, 192S.   A copy of the resolution and the amendment is attached. (Appendix IV).Ur.Betterton will propose an amendment tothe last paragraph of the resolution and Mr.Ptjulton&apos; q amendment to the effect that after thewords in the last paragraph &quot;it la desirable to request countries&quot; the following phrase should besubstituted -&quot;that have not ratified the Convention to indicate their difficulties and formulate proposals for removing them&quot;.In moving this amendment, Mr.Betterton will express the view that it is necessary to obtain the opinionof all states affected as to the proposals for removing difficulties made by the non-ratifyingstates in order to see whether there are anycommon factors.   It would be premature and withoutvalue, having regard to the obvious uncertainty of the position, for each State to indicate its willingness to ratify the Convention if certain amendments proposed by it were acceptel when itmight be that no other State would be willing toaccept these amendments.   The right oourse would,therefore, appear to be to modify the resolution soas to make it clear that the first step is to oolleotthe views of the non-ratifying States as to whatamendments are desirable.Mr, Betterton will take the opportunity ofpointing out that H.M. Government have no/objection
objection to the reference in the preamble to the desire of Great Britain to ratify the Convention, but that it must be understood more olearly than is brought out In the preamble as at present drafted that the enquiry of the Office must be pursued with equal diligence as regards other countries whioh have not ratified the convention and not be specially directed to the oase of Great Britain.Mr. Betterton will also draw the attention of the Governing Body to an error In the Report of the Proceedings of the Paris Committee in which no referenoe is made to the faot that the British Government representative abstained from voting on the resolution.I&apos;bem 7:   Report of the Building Subcommittee;Attempts may be made to invite offers fromthe various Members of the International labourOrganisation to contribute to the decoration ofthe new building for the International labourOffloe.    Mr. Betterton will not make any offoron behalf of H. M. Government.Item 8;   Report on the decisions of the fourth Assembly of the Iie&apos;ague&quot;o&quot;r&quot;&apos;laHc*nE;Probably no question arises, but ;he document is still being considered by H.M.Treasury. Item 9;   Report of the Committee on standing Osders.Article 390 of the Treaty provides that if a Member fails to nominate one of the non-Government Delegates it is entitled to nominate, the other non-Government Delegate should be allowed to sit and speak at the Conference but not to votecThe Standing Orders of the Conference are to bo reconsidered with a viow to the possibility/of
of amending them so as to imposo upon incomplete Delegations which consist of Government reprosenta-tives or a single Government representative only some -further penalty beyond that provided for in the Article.Mr. Botterton will exprosa the view that it is undesirable in principle that what is in effect a substantivo amendment of tho provisions of Part XIII of the Treaty should bo brought about by tho expedient of amending the Standing Orders of the Conference.   \Gerfcain suggestions made by the British Government for the improvement of the drafting of the Standing Orders of the Governing Body will coma up for consideration.The&apos;Canadian Government delegate may submit a motion that sessions of the Governing Body should be held three time a a year instead of quarterly.Mr. Betterton will vote in favour of any roaaonabloarrangement at which tho Governing Body may arrive.Item 10:   Record of the Meeting,oi the Advisory Agricultural&quot;&apos; Committee.The Governing Body will bo asked to authorise theOffice to address to Governments Questionnaires tin thesubject of vocational agricultural education and workers&apos;co-operation in agriculture.   Mr. Betfcerton will resist the issue of both those questionnaires on the ground thatthey are unnecessary and expensive.   He will suggest, .aa regards vocational agricultural education, that theOffice should prepare summaries of the steps taken intho different countries based on the reports made in/accordance
with tho recommendation concerning the dovolopment Of technical agricultural education adopted by the 1921 Conference,As regards tho questionnaire on co-oporative sooietlas, he will obeerve that its object Is not explained and that in most countries it would probably be vary difficult, if ndfc lmpossibla, to answer it satisfactorily,If it proves necessary to make a concessionMr.   Bitterton will suggest that tho Office boauthorised to continue the study of those subjects,and where necessary, to address special enquiries to individual countries in regard to points upon whichit Is otherwise unable to obtain Information,Item 11: Beoord of the mooting of Experts on $aostlor. - concerning tho Disabled:The Governing Body will bo asked to authorisethe Office to communicate to Governments the conclusionsof the meeting of Exports which opened at Geneva on31st July, 1923.   Mr. Botterton will ralso no objectionto the -circulation of those views, provided it i-i mado  -clear that the views of tho experts do not., necessarilyrepresent tho views of the Governing Body, and thatthey are merely brought to the notice of Governments for what they are worth, and. provided also that an assuranceIs given by tho Director that tho reservations made by certain of tho Exports should be communicated to theGovernments at the some time as tho conclusions, (e.g,the British Governmont representative^ reservationindicating the absence of immediate nlooseity forimposing a statutory obligation-   to employ disabled men),-  /On
On the question of compulsory employment of disabled men, Mr. Betterton will refer to the recant Interim Report of the ICing&apos;s Roll National Council on the Employment of Disabled Ex- Service lien (Cmd.1919) to the effect that the Council &quot;have formed the conclusion that the system of decentralised voluntary effort la right. Provided thereftre , that the winter does not bring another severe slump in trade, we believe that with the continued assistance of the Local Committees and the Press, and the maintenance at least, of the present support given by the public, it should be possible to make, by existing means, coupled with the recommendations we have submitted, a substantial improvement in the position, without recourse to alternative methods of compulsion.&quot;He will indicate that this ie a very strong Committee presided over by Sari Kaig and on which representatives of ex-Service men sit, and the Government naturally gives careful consideration to its recommendations.    He must accordingly, on behalf of H.M.Government, endorse the reservations made by Mr, Ptfssmcre, who     . represented tho British Government at the meeting of Experts.   He will ask that Mr, Passmore may have an opportunity of commenting in advance onany statement of his reservations which the Office proposes to circulate,Item 12:   Subsidy for the technical and aolentifjo institute of prosthesis and, surgicajL appelp^tus&quot; a QSn^seTs&apos;.&quot;Lir. Betterton will urge that so long as this Institute lias an inter-allied rather than aninternational character, it is in no circw/istances/ possible
possible for the International Labour office to payit any subsidy.   He will emphasise that the office isnot a grant distributing body, and add that in any event if the Governing Body decided to grant anysubsidy, he must press for the expenditure being met,not from the item &quot;Unforeseen Expenditure&quot;, but fromthe sum allocated to1 ^External Collaboration&quot;.Item 13:     Record of the meeting of the Advisory Committee on Industrial Hygiene.Mo question arises, hut the proposals are still being considered by the Home Office. Item 14s     Date and place of next Session.No question arises.
A B   L I! BIX    IV.Resolution end amendment on the subject of the Hours Convention to be considered by the 20th Session of the Governing Body of the International Labour Office.&quot;Considering that difficulties have oeourred with regard to the application of the provisions of the Washington Convention concerning the Eight Hour Pay and 48 Hour Week, and that these difficulties have impeded the ratification of the Convention by certain countries;&quot;Considering that one of the countries thus affected is Great Britain, a country in which hours of work are in  raotloally general agreement with the terms zt the Convention;&quot;Bhying tribute to the desire expressed by the British Government to ratify the Convention and after examination of this Go^emmenfs suggestion to remove the difficulties in question by means of a revision designed to render the Convention more elastic;&quot;Considering that such revision might destroy the considerable value attaohing to the present Convention, even not ratified, as a model and as a moans of stimulating national legislation;&quot;IB of opinion that beforo taking up any position with regard to the question of revision it is desirable to request oountries whioh wish to ratify the Convention and are prevented from so doing by the difficulties referred to above, to indicate the definite amendments required to enable them to ratify the Convention&quot;.Mr, Boulton&apos;s amendment.&quot;end to present to their Parliaments &amp;3 soon as possible Bills embodying the terms of the Convention and providing for its appliostion to exooptional oases where the application of the exceptions provided for by   t the Convention may require to be defined&quot;.
APPENDIX V.DRAFT RECOMMENDATION JsND DRAFT RESOLUTION SUBMITTED BY THE INTERNATIONAL LABOUR    OFFIOE     FOR THE CONSIDERATION OF THE FIFTH ANNUAL OONFERENOE OCTOBER, 1953.The General Conference of the International Labour Organisation,Considering that tho Treaty of Versailles and the other Treaties of Peaoe include among the methods and principles of special and urgent importance for the physical, moral and intellectual welfare of the workers tho principle that eaoh State ehould make provision for a system of inspection in whioh women should take part, in order to ensure the enforcement of the laws and regula-tions for the protection of the employed;Considering that tho resolutions adopted at the First Sosslon of tho International Labour Conference concerning certain special oountrlee imply that these countries should oreate, if they do not yot possess, an inspection system;Considering that the necessity of organising a system of inspection may booomo specially urgent when Conventions adopted at previous Sessions of the Conference are ratified by Members of the Organisation and put into force?Considering that, while the institution of an inspection system 1b undoubtedly to be reoommended as one of the most effective means of ensuring the enforcement of Conventions, each Member 1b solely responsible for the execution of Conventions to which it is a party in the territory within its jurisdiction and must accordingly itself determine in acoordanoo with looal conditions what measures of super-vision may enable it to assume suoh a responsibility?Considering that, In order to put the experience already gained at tho disposal of the Members with a view to assisting them in the institution or re-organisation of thoir inspection system, It is dosirable to indicate tho general principles whioh practice shows to be the best calculated to ensure uniform, thorough and effective enforcement of Conventions and more generally of all measures for tho protection of the workers? and ^Having decided to reserve completely all discussion on the methods of inspection appropriate to the various spheres of activity, notably for mines, railways, maritime navigation and agriculture; and taking as a guide the long experience already acquired in factory inspection;recommends that eaoh Member of the International Labour Organisation take the following principles and rule into consideration in the organisation of its inspeo-tion systems
I.   SPHERE OP INSPECTION.The General Conference recommends$1. That it should be the principal duty of the special inspectorate which should be instituted by each Member to secure the enforcement of the laws and regulations dealing with the regulation of conditions of work and the proteo-tion of the worker while engaged in their work (hours of work and rest; night work; prohibition of the employment of certain persons on dangerous, unhealthy or physically unsuitable work; provisions relating to hygiene and safety; legal provisions concerning the fulfilment of the terms of engagement of workers whioh Involve penalties);2. That, in so far as it may be considered possible and desirable, either for reasons of convenience in the latter of supervision or by reason of the experience which they gain in oarrylng out their principal dutieB to assign to inspectors other duties of a secondary character which nay vary aooording to the conceptions, traditions and oustoms prevailing in the different oountries (e.g. approval of plans for building or altering establishments; inspection of steam boilers; supervision of dangerous and unhealthy establishments; co-operation with social insurance authorities; intervention in labour disputes; co-operation with institutions for promoting the welfare of the workers), these duties should nevertheless be so allocated and defined,(a) That they may not in any way Interfere with the Inspectors&apos; principal duties and may be readily carried out during their visits of inspection;(b) That in themselves, they are olosely related to the primary objeot of ensuring the protection and safety of the workers;(o) That so far from prejudicing in any way the iuthority whloh is necessary to inspectors in their relations ilth employers and workers they should rather be calculated o inorease that authority.II.   NATURE OF THE FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF INSPECTORS.The General Conference recommends! 1. That inspectors should be empowered by law, **(a) To visit and inspect at any hour of the day or ight plaoes where they may have reasonable oause to elieve that persons under the protection of the law are aployed, and to enter by day any plaoe whioh they mayive reasonable oause to believe to be an establishment ibject   to their supervision, and(b) To question without witnesses the staff and any Jther person belonging to the establishment, and to requirebe shown any registers or documents which the laws gulatlng conditions of work require to be kept;
2. That inspectors should be bound by oath, or by any method whioh conforms with the administrative practice or customs in ,eaoh ooisntryy not to dxyolose manufacturing secrets and working processes in general whioh may come to their knowledge In the course of their duties;3. That, regard being had to the judicial systems of each country and subject to such reference to superior authority aB may be considered necessary, inspectors should be empowered to bring breaches of the laws whioh they ascertain directly before the competent judicial authorities;4. That inspectors should be empowered to order to be carried out within a fixed time&quot; such alterations in the installation or arrangement of workplaces or plant as they oonsider necessary for effectively enforcing the laws and regulations concerning the hygiene and safety of the workers;That suoh orders should have executive foroe subject to appeal to higher administrative authority or, in accordance with the praotioe in some countries, to the,Courts of Law;That in no circumstances should provisions intended to protect employers against arbitrary action and to ensure uniform enforcement of the law prejudice the taking of measures calculated to prevent imminent danger;5. That, in preference to other administrative authorities, the inspectorate should be empowered to grant the temporary exemptions for whioh provision is made in the laws and regulations dealing with the regulation of work and the protection of the workers, each oountry being free to determine according to its own customs or the laws concerned the particular officer or officers to whom this power is to be assigned.Considering, however, that, while it is essential that the Inspectorate should be Invested with all the legal powers necessary for the performance of its duties, it is equally important, in order that inspection may gradually become more effeotive, that, in accordance with the tendency manifested In the oldest and most experienced industrial countries, inspection should progressively discard its police and repressive character and&quot;should be increasingly directed towards securing the adoption of the most suitable methods fo* preventing aocidents and Industrial diseases with a view to rendering work less dangerous, more healthy and even less exhausting, by promoting an instructed understanding among the employers and by educating the workers concerned.The General Conference recommends the following methods as calculated to promote this development in all oountries:6. That inspectors should(mak9 enquiries in case of accidents with a. view to determining their causes and preventing their recurrence:
7. That inspectors ehould be encouraged to give employers -practical advice on the introduotion of hygiene and safety devices and, above all, so to win their confidence that employers may come to rely on the inspectors to give them, active co-operation and assistance;8. That Inspectors should be encouraged, especially dur-ing their visits of inspection, to promote among employers and workers the spirit of vigilance and caution, without which the best laws for the protection of ths workers must^ always remain partially ineffective (Safety-First movement);9. That inspectors should as far as possible bo constant-ly associated with endeavours to improve the laws for the protection of the workers, by making a regular study of the technical methods of equipping undertakings, by making special investigations into problems of hygiene and safety, or by any other means.In countries where it is considered preferable to have a special organisation for aooident inauranoe and prevention completely Independent of the inspectorate, tho Conference recommends that the special officers belonging to suoh organisations should be guided by the foregoing principles.III.   ORGANISATION OF INSPECTION.The General Conference,Having in mind its decision referred to in the pre-ambls to the present Recommendation not to take into con-sideration the speoial nature of the inspection services appropriate to the various spheres of eoonomio activity, andNot wishing to take any deoision on the question whether inspection should be organised in a single oompre-hensivB service or in separate services for each sphere, as the solution of this question may depond on the size of each oountry or on the degree of its industrial development,&apos; andIn order better to ensure uniformity ir the enforcement of the laws and regulations dealing with the regulation of work and the protection of the workers.Recommends the following general principles for the organisation of inspection:1. That, whatever differences there may be,in administra-tive practice in thiB matter, all inspection services should mutually assist each other by an interchange of tho results of their experience and should regulate their methods and procedure according to suoh common principles as may bo oon-sidered the most effeotive;  -8. That, if special services exist for supervising the enforcement of certain special technical provisions of the laws (medical inspectors, electrical engineering inspectors), these services should be administratively incorporated with the oentral inspectorate:
5. That, if the enforcement of the laws regulating conditions of work in oertain establishments or oertain classes of undertakings (mines, mercantile marine, railways, etc.) is carried out by the offioers responsible for the genoral supervision of these establishments or undertakings, these officers should, so far as is oom-patlbla with administrative practice, be in touch with the central authority administering the general inspectorate;4. That, wherever it is compatible with administrative praotlce, the services responsible for supervising the laws and regulations dealing with the regulation of work and the protection of the workers in the different classes of establishments or undertakings should be under the orders of a single central authority,5. The General Conference,Being of opinion that the inspectorate should be completely independent and should be beyond the reach of any outside influences, polltloal or otherwise, which may bo an obstaole to it in the carrying out of its duties,Recommend s:(a) That the inspectorate ehould be attaohed to a ministerial Department whioh has no political functions;(b) That the local inspecting staff Bhould be under the direction or supervision of district inspectors aoting as direct intermediaries between the higher authority and the local inspectors and should be independent of the local administrative authorities.8. Without entering into tho detailed measures to be adopted for the recruitment and training of inspectors, the Conference recommends:(a) That, before any other consideration, and on aocount of the increasing complexity.of industrial processes and machinery, teohnioal and general qualifi-oatlons of a progressively higher standard should be required of candidates for posts in. the inspectorate;(b) That, on account of their relations with employers as well as vdth the employed, selected candidates should be capable of aoquiring the confidence of both parties and that their character ehould be suoh as togive them the necessary standing;     *(c) That selected candidates should have to ,under-go a period of probation for the purpose of testing their qualifications and training them in their duties.7, In conformity with the principle contained in Article 427 of the Treaty of Peace, the Conference recommends that the inspectorate should include women. &apos;While it rooogniBeB, however, that women inspectors may pay epeaiaj. attention to the protection of women
and children or to the promotion of workers&apos; welfare, tho Conference recommends, for practical reasons as well as in order to ensure a progressively higher standard In the inspectorate, that women inspectors should be employed in exactly the same conditions as mon inspectors, having the same functions and the same responsibilities in the different grades, and that they should have equal opportunities of promotion to the higher grades, if they deserve suoh promotion.8. Convinced that only by the co-operation of all concerned can real success bo obtained for measures for the protection of the workerB, and that it 1b desirable accordingly to facilitate the participation of the workers in the work of inspection, and considering that In some countries or for some classes of establishments the appointment of workers as assistant inspectors, supervisors or delegates has given satisfactory results,The Conference recommends:(a) That workers chosen by their fellow-workers or official representatives   of workers&apos; organisations should be afforded every facility for freely communicating withthe Inspectors for the purpose of informing them confidentially of any defeot or abuse and suggesting any remedy or improve-ment desirable;(b) That in oountries where they havo been instituted, work-shop representatives or works committees should in this connection make every ubo of the functions legally assigned to them. &apos;  -9. The Conference recommends that there should be constant co-operation between the inspectorate and the local authorities for the enforcement of the laws and regulations dealing with the regulation of work and the protection of the workers.IV.   INSPECTORS&apos; REPORTS.In view of the action taken in moat States, and in order to meet oertain clear and defined neods in international relations,The General Conference reoommonds:        %1. That Inspectors should regularly submit to their central authority reports framed on uniform lines dealing with their work and its results, and that the iald authority should publish an annual report within six months after the eud of the year with which it deals, containing a general survey of the information furnished by the inspectors;That the oalendar year should be uniformly adopted for .aU these reports;:. That, the annual general report should contain a list of laws and regulations regulating conditions of work promtuV gated during the year which it covers:
3. That thiB annual report should also give statistical tables indicating : --(a) The strength and organisation of the staffof the inspectorate;(b) The number of establishments oovered by the laws and regulations, classified by groups of industries and indicating the number of workers employed (men, women, young persons from 16 to 18 yeare of age, children below 14 and from 14 to .16 years of age);(c) The number of days devoted to visits of inspection;(d) The number of visits of inspection made foreach class of establishment with an indi-cation of the number of workers (men, women, young persons and. children) employed in the establishments inspected and the number of establishments inspected more than once during the year?(e) The number and nature of the orders issued byinspectors and exeouted with a view to preventing aocidents or safeguarding the health of the workers;(f) The number and.nature of broaches of the laws and regulations brought before the Courts having Jurisdiction and the number and nature of the oonviotions made by the Courts(g) The number and nature of accidents and oocupa-tional diseases notified, tabulated according to class of establishment.4. The Conference further recommends that inspectors in all countries should each year investigate a subject affecting the hygiene or safety of the workers, selected in advanoe by the Governing Body of the International Labour Office, and that on the conclusion of these investigations this subject should be studied in the annual Inspection reports.The Conference is of opinion that, if the general principles indicated in the presen% Recommendation are applied by the States Members in the organisation of their inspection system, the Members will be mutually assured of a more thorough and effective execution of the provisions of Conventions of the1 International Labour Organisation, and that their workers will have the benefit of the protection laid down for them.DRAFT RESOLUTION.Itjls clear that In order to give proper effect to paragrapha 1 to 4 of the fourth Part of the draft &apos;
Recommendation the action which the Governments are asked to take in these paragraphs should be completed by the necessary complementary action on the part of the International Labour Office. This, of course, cannot be dealt with in the Recommendation, which by its very nature can only be addressed to the Governments. It is considered, therefore, that the Conference might be guided by the method followed by it at previous Sessions in similar circumstances and adopt a resolution drafted on the following lines.

The Conference invites the International Labour Office to publish each year on the basis of the annual inspection reports issued in the different countries a general report summarising the results obtained in the different States and to endeavour to secure the largest measure of uniformity possible in the presentation of the reports of the different countries and especially in the compilation of statistical tables, in order to allow of more exact comparison.



</content>
</cab>
