<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/162/0 images: 291-293</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS DOCUMENT IS TEE PEOPBRTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY13 GPYERJ.Mi?MT)CABINET P..P. 426 (23).UNEMPLOYMENT COMMITTEE REPORT.    (C,B, 450(23)), Note by the Seoretary, Cabinet.The attached decisions respecting Unemployment were taken by the Cabinet at their meeting on the 22nd October, 1923, (Cabinet 49(23)) on the consideration of the Report dated 17th October, 1923, of the Unemplcy-ment Committee (C.P.420(23)).(Signed)   M.P.A. HANKSY,Secretary, Cabinet.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.I., 31st October, 1923.S B C B n
UNEMPLOYMENT.Decisions taken at the Cabinet held on .22nd October, 1923, (Cabinet 49 (23) )..The Cabinet agreed-(a) Approval- of Report of committee.- To approve the Interim Report of the Cabinet Committee on Unemployment (Paper Cf P.-420(23)  ).  -(b) That the Chairman of the Committee on Un-employment should circulate, for the inform-ation of the Cabinet, a fuller report showing the precise effect on the relief of uncmploy-ment of the measures already decided.on:   if possible, this report should show, month by month, the number of &quot;men-months&quot;-provided-for.(c) Tho Northern and Western Motor Way.To take note that the question-of the construction of the Northern and Western Motor Way, is under consideration by the committee on Unemployment..(d) Expenditure by the Railways *That the President of the Board of Trade should ascertain how far the railways have -carried out the works of-rehabilitation for which the Government had granted compensation of  60,000,000 to them, and should advise the Cabinet-as to whether an investigation on this subject was desirable.(Q) Possible placing of orders,by the Dominions, India andthie-&apos;crown colonies.To take note that the Cabinet committee on Unemployment, recognising that the measures hitherto adopted are only palliatives, is in touch with the president of the Imperial Economic Conference and the secretary of State for India and the secretary of state for the colonies with a view to the creation of fresh markets and the expediting of orders in this country by the Dominions, India and the Crdwn Colonies, even where it involves co-operation in financial assistance by the British Government to Imperial development.(f) Proposed Credit Facilities for goreign Governments.       &apos;       &apos;        &apos;    &apos;To leave for further consideration by the Cabinet a proposal that tho British Government should extend credit facilities in this country to foreign Governments, several of which (e.g., Brazil, Roumania, Latvia, Lithuania, esthonia) it is alleged would then be willing to place substantial orders In this country.(g)
w &apos;3 3(g) ptua si a.That the question of re-examining British policy towards Russia, with a view to the extension of orders from that country in relief of unemployment, whether by some system of credit or otherwise, should bo reserved for later consideration.(k) Work in the Dockyards,   anticipation of or d er a&apos; by&quot; IE o&apos; A din i raTty and&apos; the&apos;&apos; p orn 1 nTona.,That the Prime Minister should be authorised, in his forthcoming speech to the National Unionist Association at Plymouth, to announce that orders would be placed for a certain.number of warships (Light cruisers, etc. )/W anticipation of the normal Admiralty programme of replace-ment, and that these orders would beplaced so as to give employment in some of the blackest spots from the point of view of unemployment.(i) That the First Lord of the Admiralty should discuss with the Prime Ministers of the Dominions the possibility of placing some orders for Cruisers in British yards at the earliest possible date.(j) That the President of the Board of Trade should make enquiries as to the present state of development of the Diesel engine .  and should report to the committee on Unemployment as to whether there would be any prospect of employment resulting if Shipping Companies were to be treated on the same,footing as certain Electrical and Railway companies and given the benefits of the Wade Facilities Act in respect of the construction of ships . fitted with Diesel engines.(k) The Boilermakers1 Strike.That the Minister of Labour should be asked to report to the Cabinet on the following day as to the present position in regard to the Boilermakers1 Strike and the possibility of intervention, with a view to ending a strike which had produced disastrous results on employment in the shipbuilding, yards of the country.

</content>
</cab>
