<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/162/0 images: 294-339</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(This Document is the Property of His Britannic Maiesty&apos;s Government)6 SO RE T Copy NoC A B I S 3 T.CP. 427 (23)K5P0RT ,QF .T.HB ANDFRSON COMMITTEE.note b y )n th %jDhano e 1 lor^joft he, Uxo he qu e r,, i1;:&quot;,.&apos;..i&apos;-;ffl1I desire to call the attention of the Cabinet to theiReport of the Anderson Committee on the Pay etc, of State Servants, IAs regards the Civil Service the Committee^ general conclusion is that the present standard of remuneration is not excessive and in bo far as their recommendations on point of detail require immediate action, such action is being taken in the normal way..       So far as the Fighting Services are concerned it is important that a very early decision should be reached and I propose(a) that the Report as regards the pay of the Fighting Services ehould be acoepted in principle and(b) that a Cabinet Committee be appointed to determine, having regard to (a), the actual ratea of pay for the Navy, Army and Air Force,IT. 0.TRJASURY^^JL25th October, 1923
Report of Committee on Pay, etc.ofState ServantsLONDON:PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE Tu be purchased through any Bookseller or directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: Imperial House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2, and 28 Abingdon Street, London, S.W.1; York Street, Manchester; 1 St. Andrcw&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff; or 120 George Street, Edinburgh.1923.price Sd. net.
OMMITTEE ON PAY, ETC OF STATE SERVANTS.CONSTITUTION. OF THE committee sir Alan Garrett Anderson, K.B.E. (Chairman). General The Hon. Sir Herbert Lawrence, K.C.B. Sir W. Peter Rylands.TERMS OF REFERENCE.&quot; To enquire into the present standard of remuneration andother conditions of employment of the various classes of State Servants employed in the Civil Service and in the three Fighting Services, and to make recommendations thereon.&quot; The Committee will include in their Report a classified state-ment of increase in the numbers and cost of personnel in these Services consequent on duties imposed on them since July, 1914, and the expansion of duties then existing.&quot;The expenses incurred in preparing this Report are estimated at \\\ 11s. Od., of which  81 11s. Od. represents the estimated cost of printing and publication.
REPORT OF COMMITTEE ON PAY, ETC., OF STATE SERVANTS.To the Rt. Hon. Stanley Baldwin, M.P.Sir,Our reference covers so large a field that we have confined ourselves to a general survey. In our report we have not entered into details of particular grades and rates of pay, except to confirm or illustrate a general conclusion. We have assumed that in each Service the internal relativity has been adjusted by the various Pay Committees, the Departments and the Treasury in conjunc-tion, and we have tried to gauge the general standard of remunera-tion in each Service as far as possible by examining in particular one or two important rates.2. The argument against a detailed enquiry into particular rates of pay is clear when one looks at the Civil Service. Notwith-standing the reduction in the number of separate classes which has taken place in recent years, there are still more than 300 classes included in the Administrative, Executive, Professional, Technical and Clerical grades, and to these must be added a large number of classes in Manipulative, Messengerial and Industrial grades. It would have been impossible to cover the whole of this ground adequately in a reasonable time. Moreover, the remuneration of classes with basic salaries or wages not exceeding  500 per annum is discussed by the Civil Service Whitley Councils, which were set up in the Civil Service in 1919 with the approval of the Government of that time. At these Council meetings the interested parties appear and state their own case, or brief an advocate ; the Official side consists of senior members of the Civil Service and possesses a particular and intimate knowledge of detail to which we cannot pretend. We have, therefore, tried to avoid any findings in detail which might be thought to depreciate the work or to undermine the authority of these Councils.PART I-GENERAL OBSERVATIONS.3. The Services of the Crown differ so much that the factors on which &quot;pay is based are not the same in all the Services, or at all events are differently valued.For Naval ratings the Admiralty have laid down a principle with which we agree but one word of which we venture to criti-cise, &quot; the standard of remuneration should be such as will induce a continuous and sufficient flow of suitable candidates and keep them in a contented state whilst in the Service.&quot; An efficient Navy is generally &quot; contented,&quot; but contentment does not always(C3565) Wt.l 1253/568/663 5M 8/23 Harrow (Gp. 1) BZ
lead to progress and efficiency. The word &quot; efficient &quot; would we think express the real meaning. The Admiralty apply this principle only to the lower deck. For officers they fix pay with regard to certain standards of expense and to the responsibility for the safety of His Majesty&apos;s ships and of the lives of men m those ships. If one pushed this to an extreme a man would be paid in proportion to the number of people he could kill if lle made a mistake. A claim was put forward by a section of the Civil Service that pay should be based on the responsibility of the work We accept responsibility as one of the factors of pay, but we reject the theory that responsibility either in the naval sense or in the Civil Service sense is the main determining factor.In discussing the relation between pay of men and women in the Civil Service another principle appeared. It was suggested that women should be paid less than men, because, on the average, men had heavier family responsibilities; and resDonsi-. bility in this sense is definitely adopted as a principle of pay in the Army by the provision of married quarters for officers and by higher rates of allowances for married officers. We agree that the average expenditure of the employee is one of the factors of pay, but not the only one.The Fisher Committee, in fixing the pay of officers in the Army, stated that the pay of an officer on first commission should be sufficient to enable him to take a share in the normal life of his regiment without private income. They seem to us to have adopted a wrong principle and by this initial mistake to have been led to costly conclusions.In our view there is only one principle in which all the factors of responsibility, cost of living, marriage, children, social position, etc., are included the employer should pay what is necessary to recruit and to retain an efficient staff.In stating this principle rather more crudely than was done by the Board of Admiralty about the pay of bluejackets, we realise that the main difficulty remains, of making practice square with principle. It is not enough to recruit good men. They must be paid enough throughout their career to keep them efficient and the Service healthy. It is comparatively easy, in looking at the pay of servants of the Crown, to compare the starting rates with those current in other employments and to form an opinion about the pay which would be needed to recruit to the service men or women of the type at present employed ; but it is always possible to defend paying a higher rate at the start than one&apos;s neighbours on the ground that one gets the pick of the market. Even after allowance has been made for this advantage, we have noted several instances in which the starting rates of the servants of the Crown seem to us too high.It is very much more difficult to compare rates of pay at 30 or at 40 than at 18 or 20. Several employments competing with one another for staff recruit the same human material from one pool, and the pay at the beginning can be expressed in money
and compared. Ten or twenty years later the conditions of these various employments have diverged from one another, and one must value the pay not only in money but in all the conditions of the man&apos;s life.We do not pretend, therefore, to dogmatise about what the Services should pay, but we suggest that those in authority should discount arguments which ought not, either at the beginning or throughout the career, to be accepted as the main principle governing pay. To make our meaning clear, a man of 35 is generally paid more than the woman of 35, and ought in our opinion to be paid more; the justification for his higher pay is not, however, that he has more people to keep the, single man is paid as much as the father of a family but because in the open competition of private employment he can get more than a woman he must be paid more in the Civil Service. The private employer pays the man more because he believes he is worth more than the woman.Again, in our view, the employer is wrong to meddle with private concerns of his employees which do not affect their value to him. If pay is based on the expenditure of the employee, or if employment is dependent on anything in the private life of the employee which does not affect his value in the service, the employer is inevitably led up to a discussion of the employee&apos;s expenditure and habit of life. The whole tendency of this interference is to impair the independence and self-reliance of the employee.To determine the pay throughout life the employer must have a clear idea not only of the intelligence, but of the physique and other qualities required of his staff. A service which is satisfied with a clever and well educated man can be staffed at a lower rate not only at the beginning but throughout life than another service which requires the same educational attainments and, in addition, better physique, force of character and such special gifts as tact and the power of command.4. The present rates of pay in the Fighting Services were fixed in 1919 and have not been changed since. In the Civil Service the pay of the permanent staffs includes a basic element fixed on the basis of 1914 standards and a bonus or cost of living element. Under the bonus scheme introduced in 1920 this cost of living element has been subject since March, 1920, to revision every four or six months in accordance with the fluctuation in the Ministry of Labour cost of living index figure, and we have taken full account of this factor in dealing with the standard of remuneration of civil servants.In order to form an opinion about the rates of pay of the rank and file of the services we have examined a mass of statistics furnished by the Ministry of Labour and the Board of Trade to ascertain how wages for 1923, 1919 and 1914 compare in a large number of industries. The wages statistics on which we have worked are based on figures supplied to the Ministry of Labour(C3565) b 3
from time to time by the employers and trade unions concerned and subsequently combined by the Ministry of Labour to represent an average wage for all the districts concerned.5. We have presented a part of this information in dia-grammatic form in graphs A, B, and C. It should be borne in mind that these graphs represent percentage increases over 1914 rates and do not afford a comparison between the actual levels of wages in one industry and another.On Graph A are plotted the variations in the percentage increase over pre-war rates in : (1) Average weekly rates of wages and average earnings inthe Cotton trade ; (2) Average earnings of workers in the Coal Mining industry ; (3) Average weekly rates of pay of a typical group of Innand Steel workers, and average earnings of workpeoplein the Iron and Steel trade; (4) Monthly rates of wages of A hie Seamen, Mercantile Marine; (5) Weekly rates of wages of Agricultural labourers inEngland and wales the total number of workpeople in these industries amounts to more than 3,000,000 and the graphs may be regarded as broadly typical for each industry. It appears that in the trades which are open to world competition the level of wages at the present time shows a reduction ranging from about 10 per cent, to 40 per cent, on the amounts paid in the corresponding industry in 1919. The percentage reduction in Seamen&apos;s pay amounts to about 38 per cent., but seamen of the Mercantile Marine, like naval ratings and soldiers, only receive a fraction of their total remuneration in the form of cash. They are fed and lodged in addition. A reduction in the cash pay of seamen of Mercantile Marine, of naval ratings and of soldiers represents, therefore, a smaller percentage of their total reward.Graph C combines Graph A with a series of curves showing the percentage variations in the prices of related commodities. It will be observed that there is a marked relation between the fluctuations in the commodity price and in the wages paid in the corresponding industry, and that the commodity or wage which rises first and highest tends to fall sooner and further than its more sedate neighbours.Whilst Graph A shows for trades open to world competition the relation of wages and earnings in 1919 to wages and earnings in 1923, Graph B compares the sheltered trades It will be observed that the level of wages of Bricklayers, Dock Labourers, Gas Stokers and Labourers .employed in the non-trading services of Local Authorities show reductions varying from 5 per cent, up to 15 per cent, of the amounts paid in 1919 If Graph A is compared in detail with Graph B it will be apparent that the wages fluctuations in the open trades are much more pronounced than in the sheltered occupations.
(C3565)The reason for this difference is not far to seek. In the open trades, prices and wages are subject to the direct competition of the world and to the law of supply and demand. If those who engage in a world trade whether they work with brains or hands or money want a better reward, it is not enough to point to the cost of living or to a comparison with other trades ; they must commend the value of their services in the world&apos;s market. Between themselves; the employers, the shareholders and the employees may discuss their relative needs and debate the division of the profits of their common enterprise; but the fact that an agricultural labourer or a farmer finds it difficult to make a living in England today scarcely affects the world&apos;s price of wheat; while if Shipbuilders or Steel makers are unable to get orders it is no use complaining that a plater who received 77s. Gd. per week in 1919 is now taking home less than 48s. 6d., the minimum pay of an unestablished Messenger in a Government headquarters office in London, or that the factory on which so much has been spent is receiving less than nothing for the use of its capital. This is a hard doctrine, but in our view we can feed the 42,000,000 inhabitants of this country if we meet the market of the world  and in no other way.The difference between the profits and wages in world trade and the profits and wages in sheltered employment is, to our mind, the clue through what otherwise seems a tangle of anomalies and injustice. The results of world trade jump up and down while sheltered trade follows with an increasing lag as the shelter becomes more complete. The same distinction appears in the domestic fortunes of each trade in shipping, for example, the fortunes of the free cargo steamer touch heights and depths from which liners by their conferences and their greater capital expenditure have to some extent sheltered themselves. Similarly, in finance, the pay and prospects of an employee in a deposit bank are secure, but drab compared with the sharp black and white of his colleague who depends on his success or the success of his firm in the world trade..6. On the same lines two general considerations about the pay of State Servants occur to us. On the one hand, the State should hold the scales even between its own servants and those through whose enterprise its servants are paid. On the other hand, employees of the Crown would have a real ground for complaint if their pay were related to wages in industry only in the time of low wages. If they do not get pay relative to the boom, they must be spared the full severity of the slump. The State as a model employer offers security, a pension, a dignified service and a moderate wage in exchange for the excitement and possibilities of private employment.
PART  II.-FIGHTING  SERVICES.7. The present standard of pay for the rank and file of the Fighting Services was set by the Jerram Committee, which reported on the pay of naval ratings in March, 1919, after taking evidence from lower deck representatives and others. The Report was adopted generally by the Government in May, 1919. The rates of pay of the rank and file of the Army and Air Force were fixed by the Fisher Committee of the Cabinet, which accepted as a general standard the Naval rates already adopted.No provision was made in the recommendation of those Committees for varying the rates of pay of men in the Navy, Army or Air Force in the event of a change in the general situation; and even if pay was fixed in 1919 at a reasonable level for 1919 conditions, it does not follow that the pay of 1919 is appropriate to the conditions of 1923. The change in the relation between the pay of the Fighting Services and the level of remuneration in outside employment may be illustrated by looking in some detail at the emoluments of the private in the Army before the War, in 1919, and at the present time.8. The standard rate of pay of the Army private remained near Is. a day from the beginning of the 19th century up to 1917. This uniformity is, however, only apparent. In 1870 the private received Is. 2d. a day pay, Id. a day beer money and Id. to id. a day good, conduct pay, according to service. But out of this he had to pay A\d. a day for his issue of rations and 3\d. a day for his messing, as well as provide for upkeep of kit, washing, etc., other than his official uniform. This was changed at various stages until in 1914 he received a clear Is. a day ordinary pay, plus 3d. or 6d. proficiency pay when fully trained, besides a free issue of bread and meat, an allowance of 3d. a day for messing and an allowance for clothing and necessaries.These changes are shown diagrammatically in Graph D, on which are also shown the average pay of the agricultural labourer (England and Wales), the general level of money wages (U.K.) and the general level of prices (U.K.) from 1870 onwards.To compare the soldier&apos;s pay with that of a civilian workman, it is necessary to estimate the value to the soldier of his accom-modation, messing, clothing, etc. The actual cost of these services to the Army for 1914 was put at 11s. Id. a week, which with pay (Is.) and proficiency pay (4 d. average) gives 20s. 9d. a week for the trained man as compared with 18s. a week the average wages of the agricultural labourer.But the War Office have given us a more satisfactory basis of comparison by adding to the soldier&apos;s pay an amount representing what his civilian colleague would have to pay tor board, lodging, clothing, etc., according to his own standard of life. Any such amount must be fixed on a more or less arbitrary standard, but so long as the same standard is adopted for the different years
	5.	d.	s.	d.	s.	d.	s.	d.	s.	d.1914	9	7	23	4	18	0	22	10	27	0July, 1919	26	3	54	3	37	10	58	3	61	9November, 1920	2S	3	63	0	46	10	70	CO	87	8March, 1923    ..	26	3	49	3	27	11	40	4	53	4** Since reduced to 50s. lid.In Graph E we show side by side with the soldier&apos;s pay (includ-ing value of emoluments in kind) throughout the period 1919-1923 the rates of pay which would have kept him precisely in the same relation to labour in the three industries as in 1914. The soldier&apos;s 1914 pay in cash and kind was 23s. Ad., which is 29 per cent, more than the agricultural labourers 18s., 2 per cent, more than the engineering labourers 22s. \0d. and 14 per cent, less than the building labourers 27s. In Graph E the post-war rates of pay ofthis consideration will not invalidate our conclusions. For the unmarried soldier the estimated value of emoluments in kind on the standard adopted is 13s. 9d. for 1914, 28s. for 1919 and 23s. for 1923. For 1905 the corresponding figure would be about 12s. 6d. The total weekly emoluments of the trained soldier on this basis are approximately 23s. Ad. for 1914 and 22s. 5d. for 1905. Agricul-tural wages for the same years were 18s. and 17s. 6d. a week respectively. The trained soldier consequently was better off than the agricultural labourer to the extent of about 5s. a week in the decade immediately preceding the war. We have not attempted to value certain advantages which the agricultural labourer enjoys in extra earnings a garden, cheap food and housing. These must not be forgotten, but they do not, we think, materially disturb the comparison between 1914 and 1923.Having regard to the general trend of prices and wages as shown in Graph D, it is probable that, on the basis of emoluments adopted, the trained soldier has always had an advantage over the agricultural labourer since 1870. By way of further comparison, the average wage at large centres in 1914 of the building labourer and the engineering labourer may be quoted, viz., 27s. and 22s. lOd. a week respectively. The former had thus nearly 4s. a week advantage over the soldier ; the latter was at a slight disadvantage. In this comparison we have taken no account of regularity of employment; building is notoriously an intermittent employment, and it is ho doubt better paid in compensation; the pay of a servant of the Crown is the most regular of all.In 1923 the trained soldier&apos;s pay is 3s. Gd. a day, plus 3d. a day (average) proficiency pay. The value of his other emoluments, 2Ss. a week in July, 1919, rose with the cost of living up to Novem-ber, 1920, and fell subsequently to 23s. a week in March, 1923. His emoluments compare with the wages of the labouier as follows : Soldier.        Agricultural Engineering Building Labourer.    Labourer.   Labourer.Pay       Total only.    Emoluments.
these three classes have been increased or decreased proportion-ately by these percentages in order, to compare with the soldier&apos;s post-war pay.The soldier&apos;s new rates of pay took effect from July, 1919 The graph shows that on the 1914 standard he was then given about 5s. a week too little in comparison with engineering wages, but in comparison with agricultural and building wages he was given about 5s. and 3s. a week respectively too much. The subsequent changes in the relative positions are clearly shown and we need only remark how rapid was the fall in civilian wages when once the trade depression took effect. The soldier&apos;s emolu-ments fall steadily with the cost of living, but the fall is not nearly so steep, so that by March, 1923, we find that the soldier has a marked advantage over all three civilian classes: by 13s. 6d. a week on the basis of agricultural labour, by 8s. a week on the basis of engineering labour, and by 4s. a week on the basis of building labour. Building wages have been further reduced since March, and the excess on this basis is now 7s. a week.9. There is a further consideration to which attention must be drawn in assessing the position of the post-war private soldier. This is the new system of marriage allowances under which every married soldier over 26 years of age is eligible for a cash allowance depending on the size of his family and adjusted annually on the cost of living index figure, e.g. : Wife and 2 Wife and 4Wife only.        Children. Children,s. d. s. d. s. d.October, 1920 . . 9 6 a week 26 6 a week 35 0 a week April, 1921 ..     9   6     ,, 24   6 33   6     ,,April, 1922 ..7   0,, 19   0     ,, 23   0    ,,April, 1923 ..7   0     ,, . 18   0     ,, 22   0     ,,(Up to October, 1920, the war scales of separation allowance applied.)Before the war no such allowance was granted. Three per cent, of infantry privates, lance-corporals, and corporals, and higher proportions of the senior ranks, who were on the married roll, received free quarters, furniture, fuel and light, and medical attendance for their families or a separation allowance when necessarily separated from their families. No concession was made to the married soldier not on the married roll. The same percentage of soldiers (now called the Married Quarters Roll) are still allowed quarters, etc., for their families, but a flat rate deduction of 7s. a week is made from marriage allowance in consideration of this privilege,The comparisons with the civilian labourer made above are thus thrown out&apos;of gear when the married soldier is brought in. The latter&apos;s position has improved since 1914 out of all comparison with that of his civilian colleague. Out of the wages quoted above most civilian labourers have to maintain a wife and family. The Army, however, is for rank and file essentially a bachelor service owing to its short service system of enlistment.  The published
Reports show that in pre-war years nearly 70 per cent, of the rank and file on the regimental establishment were under 26, and the very favourable position of the married soldier does not there-fore directly interest the mass of the rank and file. We have stated in para. 3 that in our view pay should in general depend on the value of a man&apos;s work, and not on his private needs, but the Army, for well-understood reasons, follows another plan. If by the marriage allowance system the State separates the married soldier from the bachelor and pays the married man extra, the freedom of the young soldier from dependents must also be remembered in fixing his pay, and the pay given to a civilian who has, on the average, to maintain a wife and family need not be given to the young soldier who has no such responsibility. In pre-war years 30 per cent, of the regimental rank and file of the Army were under 22 3&apos;ears of age. On October 1st, 1920, after the special recruiting necessary to reconstitute the post-war regular army, no less than 51 per cent, were under 22. At the present time these youths may easily receive as pocket money as much as the agricultural labourer receives in wages and from which he has to house, clothe and feed himself and his family.10. The Army Council inform us that while they generally approve the principles underlying the 1919 pay code they consider that the level of pay in the lower ranks of both officers and men was unnecessarily high. They define their views on the pay of the rank and file as follows : &quot;14. Provided that corresponding reductions are made in the pay of the other fighting services and it must be remembered that the Army (which does little in the way of training boys) is more in competition with the open labour market than the other Services the Army Council are of opinion that the standard initial rate for a recruit (2s. 9d.) might be reduced to Is. 6d. without serious harm to recruiting. There should be no increase of pay to the private for length of service only, but Ad. extra should be given for a 2nd class certificate of education as soon as a recruit has left the Depot, and a separate Ad. in the fighting aims for full military proficiency as soon as it is attained (not less than 1 year). In technical arms the place of this second Ad. would be taken by a tradesman&apos;s rate of pay on fines similar to the present.&quot; 15. In comparing the emoluments of soldiers and blue-jackets some difference in favour of the latter may be admitted in the later years of service, on the ground that the Navy is in the main long service for seamen as well as for petty officers, while in the Army the private soldier should be confined as far as possible to short service. Whether this difference should take the form of marriage allowance only or should also affect pay is a point for consideration.&quot; 16. As regards the relation between pay of the private and of the non-commissioned officer, experience shows that
it is necessary to secure a larger difference in favour of the lance-corporal, because a man who is contemplating leaving the Colours in 6 to 7 years will not take the hard and unsym-pathetic work of the lance-corporal for 9d. a day, especially when he is fairly well paid as a private.&quot; 17. Subject to the proviso in paragraph 14, an adequate normal scale of pay for warrant and non-commissioned officers and privates at the present time would be. Present rate of Pay.Proficiency pay 6d.after 1 year.s.	d.	s.	d.	6 after 2 years j&quot;^&quot;va*e    *		6^	3   ..	.. l.e..-corporal 2	6	0   ..	.. Corporal  .. 3	0u	6   . .	.. Lee.-serjeant 3	6.7	0   ..	.. Serjeant   .. 5	07	6   ..	.. Col.-serjeant 5	69	6    . .	.. C.Q.M.S.  .. 6	910	0   ..	.. C.S.M.     .. 7	612	0   ..	.. R.Q.M.S. .. 8	614	0   ..&apos;	.. R.S.M.    ..10	with id. proficiency pay for a 2nd Class Certificate of Educa-tion, on leaving the regimental depot, and a further id. for military proficiency when fully qualified.&quot; With lodging allowance and marriage allowance as at present.&quot;11. We have not the knowledge to comment in detail on these proposals, but we are glad to find that the independent enquiries conducted by the Army Council and ourselves have reached in general the same conclusion. We commend the Army Council scheme as a basis for the revision of the pay of men.12. It is not necessary for us to set out in the same detail the relation between the Able Seaman of the Navy and the civilian workman. The naval rating and the Army private have retained approximately their pre-war relationship, as the following table shows, and the conclusions drawn about one service apply generally to the other.Daily Pay, 1914. Cash.s. d.Daily Pay, 1923. Cash, s. d.Increase Per Cent.175 167 1756 04*180 1S7167Infantry recruit ..       ..       ..       .. 10Ordinary Seaman..      ..      ...       .. 13A.B. on rating as such   ..       ..       . . ISTrained private 2nd class proficiency ..      ..      . . 131st class proficiency   ..       ..       .. 16A.B., 3 years&apos; service (one G.C. badge andrated as Seaman-Gunner)     ..       . .&apos; 2   0 * Includes Kit Upkeep Allowance, approximately Id. a day, which had to be met out of pay in 1914.We may, however, point our conclusion by referring again to the pay of the Able Seaman of the Mercantile Marine. The preceding paragraph shows that the pay of the Junior Naval Rating has been increased by 167 per cent, over pre-war, leaving
174 126 ,98 89 70out of account food, quarters, etc. In the Mercantile Marine the recognised monthly cash wages of Able Seamen have varied as follows : Increase over 1914. Per Cent.July, 1914......         5 to   5 10s.January, 1919, to April, 1921    ..       14 10s. May, 1921, to February, 1922    ..       12 \larch, 1922, to April, 1922       ..      ^10.10s. May, 1922, to March, 1923        ..:   10 April, 1923 .....     .....        9    ..We do not attempt to make absolute comparison of cash earnings. The normal annual earnings of the civilian rating depend not only on the monthly rates of wages but also on trade conditions and on the amount of employment available. In normal pre-war days a seaman got 91- to 10 months employment in the year. In the present depression his risk of unemployment is much greater. The regularity of pay and of employment in the Navy in comparison with the Mercantile Marine has an increased value in times of bad trade and, when the risk of inter-intermittent employment is taken into account, the pay of the Naval Rating appears even more generous than the percentage com-comparisons indicate. In the boom period of 1919/20 the Naval Rating fared less well than the seaman of Mercantile Marine. But the pressure of world-wide economic conditions has forced down the wages of the civilian step by step from May, 1921, when they were 174 per cent, over pre-war, until the increase is now only 70 per cent., with a more limited field of employment. The Naval Rating, on the other hand, continues to enjoy the 167 per cent, increase granted in 1919.We may add that the introduction of marriage allowance, to which we have drawn attention in paragraph 9 above, as affecting the general level of Army emoluments, is a still more important factor in the case of the Navy. The Navy had no married roll before th: war and the full amount of the marriage&quot; allowance is an extra. Further, the Navy provides a life career for its men to a greater extent than the Army, and marriage allowance is consequently drawn by a much higher proportion, the actual figures at the present time being 35 per cent, as against only 10 per cent, for the Army.13. The Board of Admiralty have warned us that the per-centage increase of pa3&apos; given to the Naval Rating since 1914 may not be fairly comparable to the percentage increase given to sailors in the Mercantile Marine or to civilians employed ashore. They doubt whether the naval rating received enough in 1914.The first test to apply to this question is the rule of pay given by the Admiralty themselves, namely: &quot; The standard of remuneration should be such as will induce a continuous and
sufficient flow of suitable candidates and keep them in a con tented state while in the Naval Service.&quot; Following this rule we learned from representatives of the Board that under the Pay Code of 1914 recruits to the lower deck were sufficient in quantity and quality, and that the service was in a healthv con-dition. Tested by this result, therefore, the pay of 1914 would appear to have been adequate.We set - out below the actual weekly cash earnings of the various ranks of the lower deck in 1870 and 1914 :Ordinary Seaman Able Seaman   .. Leading Seaman Petty Officer   .. Chief Petty OfficerWe read these figures to mean that the Admiralty before the war based their scale of pay on the principle which seems to us to! be correct to-day. It did not prove necessary for them to advance the cash pay of the Ordinary Seaman during these 44 years, in which period the mean rate of wages in civil employ-ment had increased by 40 per cent., as is shown in Graph D. Instead of increasing the cash pay of the Ordinary Seaman-a young man without responsibilities the Admiralty improved his conditions of life and offered him better pay as soon as he proved his value. An Ordinary Seaman can be rated Able Seaman very quickly if he proves himself efficient. As he advanced in the Service and his need for money increased, so the pay given to him was gradually increased from 1870 to 1914.Under this plan, recruits were secured in 1914 and the Navy was healthy. All the evidence seems to us to show that the pay oi the Naval Rating was not too low in 1914. It is now too high and in our judgment it should be reduced parallel with reductions in the pay of the rank and file of the Army, and in correspondence with the wages now paid in civil employment.14. The rates of pay of Officers of the Navy, Army and Air Force were fixed in 1919 on the recommendation of the Fisher Committee of the Cabinet, which considered and co-ordinated proposals made by the three Departments. The Committee accepted the following principles : (1) The pay of an officer when first commissioned should be sufficient to enable him to share in the normal life of the service without private means;(2) An officer, upon attaining the age of 30, or the rank of Captain in the Army, should be recognised by the State as entitled to marry and his pay and allowances should then be sufficient to enable him to support a wife- without private means.: 1870.                 . 1914. ; . IncrmePer Cent.8s. 9d.                 8s. Qd. ^11s. Id. 11s. 8d.-13s. 5d. -       5.9112s. 3d. 14s. 0df.-16s. Ad. 14,3313s. 5d.-15s. 2d. 21s. 0d.-2.3s. Ad. 53.5616s. 1W. 25s. 8d.-30s. Ad. 51-79
Army.Navy.Civil Service.* 6&quot;2 rfd   ^* s2nd Lt.Age 20 Lieut.Age 23 Capt.Age 30I 237 292 429i35340S550 673*Sub.-Lt.Age 20 Lieut.Age 23 Lt. Cdr.Age 30 183 310 547i 335 475 718Asst. Prin. Age 23 Average remuneration Age 30313 603* Marriedrates.These principles represent a definite change in policy which increases the cost of all the Fighting Services and disturbs any comparison of the rates paid 6r the cost to-day with fhose in 1914.We may perhaps remark that the policy of .a living wage for beginners on a not ungenerous standard of life which com-mends itself easily in debate over the spending of public money is not followed universally by the private individual spending his own money. Tax-paying parents when they consider this policy, will remember for how many years their sons and daughters work in a shop, an office or a profession before they can keep themselves, and they will reflect that the better educated the beginner and the higher his final aim the longer is his term of underpaid apprenticeship.Before the war, private means or severe self-denial were necessary for the Army Officer in the early years of his career and for the more senior regimental officer who married. The Naval Officer was somewhat better off but his position did not differ essentially from that of the Army Officer. On retirement at the end of his career the Officer of either Service was probably less well off in money than his brother who had served-with equal credit in a profession or business.On the other hand, the pre-war Army offered much to its officers as compensation for low pay, and in the result there was no lack of officers of whose quality we have had the best proof.The attractions of a Naval-career were different from those of the Army, but from one generation to another the same families sent their sons to officer the Navy and even if the pay before the war was not ample it was apparently sufficient.Comparing the emoluments of junior officers with that of men of the same standing in the administrative grade of the Civil Service we get the following figures in 1923 : 
The corresponding figures for 1914 are as follows :-Army.			Navy.			Civil Service.							 	 ---.	Pay.	Pay and Allowances		Pay.	Pay and Allowances		Total Rc-2nd Lt. Age 20 Lieut. Age 23 Capt. Age 30	  96 119 211	  164 1S7 284	Sub. Lt. Age 20 Lieut. Age 23 Lieut. Age 30	  -91 182 237	  178 280 335	1st Dvn. Clk. Age 23 Average remuneration Age 30	1 200 41GThe Army and Navy rates of pay in these tables are basic or minimum rates, except so far as they assume that the officer will have obtained his promotion by the age stated. They do not take account of the higher rates which apply in the technical arms of the services, nor do they include the additional pay which may be drawn in the form of- specialist allowances and command pay in the Navy and of staff and extra duty pay in the Army. The figures taken for allowances are the cash rates issuable when accommodation, rations and servants are not provided. Under normal conditions these services are almost invariably provided in kind for the young officer, either on board ship or in barracks and we recognise the difficulty of valuing these services, especially in the Navy. But we are satisfied that, in taking for our measure the regulation cash allowances, we are not placing the Fighting Services at any disadvantage in the comparison.The figures show clearly that the officer of the Army and Navy in the early half of his career has now been placed in a. sub-stantially better position vis-a-vis his Civil Service colleague than in 1914. From being financially worse off at nearly all points for the first 20 years or so in 1914 he is now better off for the first 10 or 15 years of his career despite the fact that he enters at an earlier age and after a less expensive education.Our general conclusion is that officers up to and including appointment to the rank of Captain in the Army and of Lieutenant-Commander in the Navy are at present heing paid more than is necessary, or even perhaps quite fair to the rest of the community. We have stated our reason in paragraph 23 below for believing that the junior Administrative officer of the Civil Service is being paid about the right sum, and we consider that the Army and Navy can make reductions in the pay of their junior officers on the lines proposed by the Army Council (see page 18), without
injustice and without finding that the reduced rates prevent them from attracting officers right in quality and quantity. We appreciate that a feeling of insecurity which naturally follows the end of a great war and the beginning of what we hope will be a long peace may cause a temporary lack of candidates. In due course candidates will realise that in employment as in invest-ment it is good policy to come in on a bad market and to go out on a good.15. In discussing the question of naval officers&apos; pay with representatives of the Admiralty it was impressed on us that junior naval officers are trusted with heavy responsibilities for life and property at an age when young men entering other callings have scarcely left school. This is true, but to our mind it is the chance of responsibility and of command that attracts the man who will do well in the Navy; in recruiting for any Service, pay is one, but only one, of the factors, and so far from agreeing that it is necessary to pay more in the Navy because young men are given a chance to prove their qualities and to make mistakes, we think that this would be a good reason for paying less. It is a major attraction of the Service to any young man of spirit.On the other hand, we agree that these risks involve failure sometimes as well as success, and if the man who fails finds his career cut short, it is right that the man who succeeds should be well paid. This is not, we think, an argument for placing the level of pay in the Navy generally higher than in the other Services, but is a factor which should be considered in determining the internal grading of pay rank by rank in the Naval Service. In our view care should be taken not to pay the junior and untried officer more than is necessary, that is, more than he might obtain if he adopted another calling in life ; and not to pay the tried and successful officer less than will reward him for his effort which has brought him success where others have failed.16. We have examined the rates of pay and conditions of service of officers of middle rank in the Fighting Services, and we find that the total emoluments provided under the Fisher Scheme are not excessive, subject to such adjustment, on cost of living grounds, as is already provided for.The Board of Admiralty have represented to us that under the 1919 scheme the naval officer has proved to be in a less favourable position at certain points than his Army or Air Force colleague. This may be so, but it appears to us that compensating advantages lie with the Navy at other points, and we understand that the Admiralty, who were represented on the Fisher Committee, did not record any dissent at. the time on the general co-ordination between the services arrived at by that Committee.There is already provision in the pay codes for an adjustment to meet the change in the level of prices since 1919. Apart from (C3565) * c
this, the adjustments represented to us as necessary are of the nature of reallocation between pay and allowances. In the Arm anomalies have arisen because the lodging allowances are not adequate to cover the cost of renting suitable accommodation The officer provided with quarters is consequently better off than the officer on the lodging list. Such anomalies ought to be removed as far as possible, but we agree with the Army Council that the necessary adjustment between pay and allowances taken over the Service as a whole, should be effected without extra cost to the Exchequer.In the Navy the pay code makes no distinction between the married officer and the single officer, and the Board of Admiralty now wish to follow Army and Air Force practice in granting a special allowance to married officers in respect of the cost of maintaining a home on shore. It is not necessary for us to go into the merits of this proposal, but we suggest that if it is adopted the change should be made, as in the case of the Army adjustment at the expense of pay, without calling upon the Exchequer for additional funds.17. We have quoted in paragraph 10 the general view of the Army Council on pay. Their view is defined for officers in the following paragraphs : &quot;5. As regards the pay and allowances of officers, it is necessary to remember that the Army officer, especially in his earlier years, lives his life under somewhat artificial con-ditions in a Regimental mess. His income, therefore, must be determined, not by the conditions existing in the Civil Service or in civil professions, but by the necessary expenses of Army life. The Army Council consider that it is more important to hold out to the officer of average ability the prospect of a reasonable income in middle life, than to make it easy for officers, on first joining, to meet all the customary (as distinct from necessary) expenses of regimental life, without either any aid from parents or the exercise of any such self-denial and determination as was shown in the past by officers who contrived to live even on the pre-war subaltern&apos;s pay. Marriage has been &quot; recognised &quot; for Army officers at the age of 30, to the extent that a married quarter, or the married rates of lodging, fuel and light allowances, and the conveyance of family baggage on change of stations, are allowed from that age to those who are married. Promotion to Captain may normally be expected about the same age, and in that and the higher ranks it is considered that, on the whole, the 1919 emoluments (as corrected for cost of living) are not excessive.&quot; 6. The officer commissioned from the ranks (other than the quartermaster class) should draw the pay of a lieutenant from the date of commission instead of that of a second lieutenant.
&quot; 7. Without taking into account at this stage the proposed transfer from pay to lodging allowance, the normal scale would be, on these lines :-Present. Rales.S.   (I.f for first 3 years after 3 years&apos; service., Subalterns is.	d.		d.11	0	13	013	0	16	0 (at 2 years service).16	0	10	021	0	23	626	0	26	031	6	31	637	0	37	047	6	47	6(7 years&apos; service Captain (on promotion) Captain (15 years&apos; total service) Major (on promotion) Major (after 5 years as such) Lieutenant-Colonel&quot; The lieutenant-colonel draws, in addition, Command Pay of 10s. a day (or less), the greater part of which is given to meet the special, expenses falling upon him.&quot; All these rates (which for majors and lieutenant-colonels are those of 1919) are subject to reduction for cost of living to a limit of 20 per cent. At the index figure of 80, which the Treasury has prescribed for the provisional estimates of 1924-25, the reduction to be made in 1924 would be about 5-1 per cent.&quot;We commend the Army Council scheme as the basis for revision of pay of officers.18. We shall not try to compare the pay of the highest officers in tire various Services. The exact reward given to the best men in a great service is a question of policy rather than finance ; the money involved is relatively small and is outweighed by the encouragement to the many of generous treatment to the few best men. The facts about the pay of senior commissioned ranks in the Army and Navy, and of senior men in the Civil Service have been reported to us, but we make no recommendation.In private employment the duties assigned to senior posts in the Civil Service would carry a higher salary. For example, many large companies pay their General Manager more than three times the salary of the Secretary to the Treasury, who is the permanent head of the Civil Service and the chief financial adviser of the Chancellor of the Exchequer and the Prime Minister. The senior posts in the Fighting Services are better paid, but they are held on a short tenure. We do not think any of the Services err on the side of paying their best men too much.19. Air Force. This service is so young in its separate existence, and in many ways so peculiar in its risks, its prospects and its recruiting problem that we have not tried to deal with it specifically in our Report. A Committee such as ours could not express a considered opinion on this problem without a detailed investigation not only into the pay of the Air Force, but also into the pay of the specialist branches of the other services, and this would carry us far beyond what we think is the useful scope of
our enquiry. We think, however, that the peculiar difficulties with which the Air Council is faced to-day in recruiting its officers and men are, to a large extent, transitory and will disappear as the Air Force and the commercial flying industry attain a more established position and the careers they offer are better appreciated. The difficulties are not, in any case, to be solved by pay alone. We have indicated in the preceding paragraphs what we believe to be the correct principles determining pay, and these principles apply to service in the air, as well as on land and sea. Where the Air Force offers a permanent career to its officers and men with prospects in the senior ranks equal to those of the Army and Navy, we do not think that high starting rates will influence greatly the number of candidates offering them-selves. Whilst admitting this necessity for higher pay in respect of flying risks and the technical skill required in the Air Service, we feel that it should be possible to effect substantial reductions in the present rates of pay of junior officers and men of the Air Force, just as much as in the Army and Navy.As civil aviation develops, we expect to find that, quite apart from high pay, service in the air will compete strongly with the Army and Navy for the pick of the young men.PART III-CIVIL SERVICE.20. The Fighting Services are paying 1919 rates of pay in 1923, so their cost per man is high. The cost per man of the Civil Service has been steadily reduced since the cost of living fell, and the numbers of non-industrial staff have been reduced since the peak by 87,000, but all economies of the Civil Service have been swamped by an increase of duties and a net increase of numbers since 1914, while the numbers in the Fighting Services have been cut to the quick. As a result, the order of total cost is the opposite of the order of cost per head, and it will be agreed by those who pay the bill that the economy to be most desired is to reduce total cost.1. Average cost par head.1923 as1914.       1923.      per cent.    of 1914.Navy (officers and men)......      S3 199        240&apos;5Army (officers and men) . .       . .       ..      75 161        215(a) Civil Service ......      88-1      178-1      202-1(b) Civil Service (excluding Manipulativeand Industrial Staffs)    ..       ..     150-7      246        163-22. Total cost (in   thousands).Navy (officers and men)      ..,     .. 12,074 19,820        164Army (officers and men)      ..       .. 12,950 23,670 182-o(o) Civil Service...... 31,129 75,336        241-9(b) Civil Service (excluding Manipu-lative and Industrial Staffs) 10,700 33,430        31.2-4Cost per Head. Total Cost.1. Navy. 1. Civil Service.2. Army. 2. Army.3. Civil Service. 3. Navy.
If the total cost of pay, etc., of the Navy and Army had increased in the ratio shown above for the Civil Service, the pay roll for those services would be increased by no less than  17 millions ; whilst, on the other hand, if the total cost of the Civil Service (excluding manipulative and industrial staffs) had only increased in the same ratio over 1914 as its cost per head, the cost of Civil Service pay would be reduced by about  16 millions.We set out below the total pay roll for the non-industrial staffs of various departments. Departments which did not exist in 1914 are arranged in order of total pay costs ; departments which had a pre-war existence are shown in the order of increase in staff costs over the cost of 1914 staff.(a) Departments which did not exist in 1914.Department.	Non-Industrial Staffs, 1st March, 1923.		Nos.	Cost in   thousandsPensions4 Air Ministry (including outstations)        ;. Disposal and Liquidation Commission Research       ..      ..       .... Overseas Trade        ..        . National Savings Committee        ..       .... Other Departments  ..	23,894 4,208 1,078 548 410 229 360	4,040 1,080-5 280-5 198-9 121-5 59-5 89	30,727	5,869-9* Includes Institutional Staffs.(b) Departments which existed in 1914.Department.	Numbers Non-Industrial Staffs.		Pay Costs (in   thousands).		Increase in Pay Costs (in   thousands)	1914.	1923.	1914.	1923.	fPost Office	191,306	181,262	13.S03-7	28,722-3	14,918-6*Labour	4,755	16,066	481-4	3,335-7	2,854-3i Inland Revenue	9,274	16,229	1,296-4	4,091-8	2,795-4t Customs and Excise	9,977	10,859	1,645-7	3,460-8	1,815-1Admiralty (including	5,312	8,602	825-6	2,155-2	1,329-6outstations).					War Office (including	3,387	7,417	434-6	1,249-4	814-8certain outstations).					Trade	2,386	4,465	478-5	1,286-6	808-1 &quot;Health.	2,979	3,618	462-8	1,146-9	684-1Works	1,477	3,033	190	665-5	475-education	2,022	2,172	445-4	806-1	360-7Agriculture and	2,431	2,160	308-5	582	273-5Fisheries.					Public Trustee	409	1,245	47	272-6	225-6
(b) Departments which existed in 1914 (continued).Department.	Numbers Non-Industrial Staffs.		Pay Costs (in   thousands).				Increase in Pay Costs (in i thousands)	1914.	1923.	1914.		1923.		Prison Commission . .	3,667	2,902	362	5	573	3	210-8Foreign	188	807	55	5	246		190-5Stationery	242	1,071	34		213	6	179-6Home	649	884	144	6	317	4	172-8Supreme Court	1,052	1,275	323	2	482	8	159-6^Transport	45	462	12	8	157	3	144-5Treasury	127	351	36	8	144	8	108Registrar-General	257	758	31		128	4	97-british Museum	5S0	597	94	2	187		92-8Colonial	206	405	50	9	141	8	90-9*Mines        .....	121	325	38		124	4	86-4Sc. Bd. of Health   . .	474	510	65	1	149	9	84-SSc. Bd. of Agriculture	224	374	32	1	110	2	,78-1Exchequer and Audit	273	350	70	1	146	6	76-5India Office	543	585	147	1	200		52-9Paymaster-General . .	67	346	15	8	80	1	64-3Procurator-General	68	227	23	7	85	1	61-4and Ty. Solicitor.							National     Insurance	755	445	96	7	156	3	59-6Audit.							Sc. Bd. of Education	331	305	67	2	116	4	49-2Prison Cn., Scotland	594	541	54	6	101	9	47-land Registry	238	299	36		78	9	42-health, Wales	245	250	32	1	72		39-other Departments ..	2,088	2,503	431	6	782	8	351-2Total Add for new Depts.	248,749	273,700 30,727	22,675	2	52,571-9 5,869-9		29,896-7 5,869-9		304,427			58,441-8		35,766-6* These Departments existed in 1914 as branches of other departments, t Figures for Revenue Departments exclude Irish staffs throughout. % 1914 figures relate to Road Board.21. In our enquiry we have divided the Civil Service into eight large groups : Total Cost. Cost per licatl 1923.        1923. Expressed as percentages of the corresponding costsMainly Salaried Staff  (a) Administrative(ft) Professional, Scientific and Technical (cj Inspectorate(d) Executive and Clerical Mainly Wages Staff- (e) Writing Assistants and Typing (/) Manipulative .. (g) Messengers, Charwomen, etc. (A) Industrial     ..The Professional and Inspectorate groups (b and c above) are recruited, usually by competitive selection, to perform the pro-fessional, technical or other specialised work of Departments.for 1914.	206	139243	179215	193402	170728	19720S	220300	203199	176
The scales of pay of these classes vary in each Department according to the class of work and the educational and pro-fessional standard of qualification. We have not studied them jn detail. The Administrative, Executive and Clerical grades, on the other hand (a and d above) are common service classes recruited partly by open competition and partly by promotion. Recruits chosen by open competition for the Administrative grade enter between 22 and 24 years of age after a long education at School and University. Twelve women serve in the Adminis-trative grade, but most of them have been selected for special knowledge, or appointed to special posts of control over women staff. Within the last few months, three of these twelve women were selected after a qualifying examination. At present, women do not rank with men on a common seniority list for promotion, but after 1924 women will compete at the same examinations as men for entrance to the Administrative, Executive and Clerical grades.The grading of clerks below the Administrative class has been altered recently, and this regrading has been accompanied by an amalgamation of classes previously distinct and by a re-allocation of duties. The competition for the Executive grade is open to candidates between 18 and 19 years of age, and for the Clerical class between 16 and 17. Naturally, the quality of the candidate varies with the pay and prospects of the class be seeks to enter, and in this way not only the education but the expenses and expectations of the clerks admitted to the Administrative class surpass those of the young Executive officer, and his in turn those of the young Clerical officer, although between these last two there is not such a great difference as between the Administrative and Executive classes. The Civil Service pay their routine clerks better at the start than is common in many trades, and it is evident that the posts could be filled at lower starting salaries, but the real question is whether the work that these men do could equally well be done by a cheaper man. Just as the present scales of pay for the three grades produce three fairly distinct types of clerk, so if the Civil Service decided that they must pay less for the work at present done by a clerical officer it would follow that, as the candidates under the reduced scale were less ambitious, so they would be somewhat less well-qualified and would come from a class which expected less from life than the recruits of to-day.To take these eight groups in turn : 22. (a) Administrative Group.Numbers.		Total Cost-fin   thousands).		Cost per head.	1914. 1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.    1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.     1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.1,077 1,596	148-2	713 1,474-5	206-7	662-1    923-9	139-5
The men in this group may be compared generally with officers in the Navy and Army and with professional and business men of good standing; they join the service at about 23 years of age and remain a charge on their parents for some two or three years longer than the Sub-Lieutenant in the Navy or the Sub-altern in the Army. In pre-war days these points of difference were reflected in better starting pay to the Civil Servant, but now the Junior Officer is paid better in the Fighting Services than in the Civil Service.	On Appointment.	Age.	Pay and Emoluments.		1923 as percentage of 1914.			1914.	1923.	Navy  . .	Sub-Lieutenant	21	 178	 335	188-2Army ..	2nd Lieutenant	20	 164	 353	215Civil	Assistant Principal  ..	23	 200	 313	156-5Service.					23. At appointment, the first milestone of his career, it is easy enough to compare the Civil Servant not only with the officer in the Fighting Services, but with his brother in a profession or business. A man of 23 who starts at the bar, or as a solicitor or as a doctor, without private means, may have to face years of poverty and struggle with no certain reward at the end. If the same man is given a trial in a business, he has an uncertain tenure and probably a smaller starting pay than the Civil Servant. The Government Service definitely offers a high starting pay  or a starting pay which, if not high, compares favourably witli that a profession or business offers. One profession alone puts the same premium on education and youth, and we have, therefore, compared the starting salaries of masters at some of the large public schools. We find that the initial emoluments of an Assistant Master who has obtained a good Honours degree commonly lie between  300 and  400, as compared with the starting salary ( 313) of an Assistant Principal in the Civil Service.We report that the starting pay of the Administrative Officer compares unfavourably with the starting pay of a junior officer in the Fighting Services; and that whilst it compares favourably with the starting pay in professions or business it is not excessive if due regard is had to the special requirements of the Service:24. Apart from a good starting salary, the Civil Service offers its recruits another attraction in security of tenure. It is very attractive to a young man who has done exceptionally well at School and University to cash his academic gifts at the age of 23 in the form of an honourable and interesting career, a competence and a pension. In other callings there is a risk that the brain which was supreme at an examination will fail in
the rough and tumble of a profession or business. No business keeps expensive men unless they return value, so the higher a young man is paid at the start the shorter is his stay if he is unsuitable, but, on the other hand, the more rapid is his advance-nient if he survives. In the Civil Service, the risk of dismissal is almost negligible ; and even if the unsuccessful Civil Servant is never promoted, at least he is sure of a salary and pension.25. On the other hand, in return for his high starting pay and security, the&apos; Civil Servant forfeits the hope of reward on the same scale as men who have faced risks and won success, and whilst in certain professions and businesses the standard of remuneration of successful men is higher than that of successful Civil Servants, we do not consider that the Civil Service pay is, on that account, necessarily too low.26. We have been furnished by the Inland Revenue with, figures showing the relative earnings in 1914 and 1922 of Accountants on a sample representing not less than 50 per cent. Barristers and Solicitors      do. do. 30Doctors and Dentists do. do. 10and of employees of business undertakings on a sample repre-senting not less than 5 per cent, of the total number of individuals in these professions and business undertakings liable to income tax. We shall not reproduce these figures; but they confirm our view that the increases since 1914 in the remuneration throughout the Service of Civil Servants in administrative grades (Group a) and in professional grades (Group b below) are not excessive.27. (b) Professional,, Scientific and Technical group.Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as perceh-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.9,182	12,509	136-2	2,150	5,243-9	243-9	234-2	419-2	179This group is made up of not less than 100 grades, ranging from the Heads of Professional and Technical Sub-Departments to the latest joined Assistant, and embraces Architects, Educa-tional staffs, Engineers, Legal staffs, Medical staffs, Museum staffs, Scientists, Surveyors, Valuers, etc. We have made no attempt to check the pay of these various officers in detail, and it is not possible, as in other groups, to select and examine one rate of pay to which the others can be related. Moreover, the services of Professional men are essentially individual, and
before we could arrive at a conclusion about the pa)&apos; of each grade we should need to satisfy ourselves that these men were all engaged on essential work and that the work was carried out efficiently.  We have no mandate to undertake this enquiry.28. It has been represented to us on behalf of the members of this group that the pay of Professional men in the Civil Service has not been increased as much as the pay of administrative grades and th&amp;t it will not in the future attract candidates of the right quality. It is, however, generally agreed that Pro-fessional men of good standing and ability, who know by personal experience the difficulties and the rewards of private practice, are ready to accept Government service at the pay ruling to-day, which they believe is less than the pay of an Administrative Officer. It might be argued that if the Professional man is not paid too little, then the Administrative Officer is paid too much. 1We do not share this view, nor do we agree that there is any direct relation between the pay of the Administrative Officer and of the Professional men who advise him as occasion arises. We have already said what we think about the former ; the latter should, in our judgment, relate his pay and position with those of his professional brethren in the outside world, and in doing so he should remember all that the Civil Service offers in addition to its pay. Permanence of employment under the State and status have real value, and when a highly qualified Professional man of ripe experience has weighed the offer of the State against his prospects in private practice and has deliberately accepted service under the State he has no cause to complain because some other servant of the State who is not a Professional man and has been selected for a different kind of work at a different age and in a different way, seems to him to be better paid than himself.As the present scales of pay attract good candidates to-day we see no reason for an increase.It has also been put to us as the view of Professional men in the Civil Service that &quot; the efficiency of those departments which control a large number of technical officers is lowered and prospects of promotion impaired by the practice of appointing a non-professional head.&quot; We do not agree that an officer appointed for his technical knowledge is necessarily the best man to control a Department. The duties and the outlook of an administrator differ from those of a technical! man. Although men with high technical qualifications occasionally prove them-selves to be first-rate administrators, the head of a Department should, in our view, be so detached from technical bias that he can weigh the advice of his various officers and judge correctly between competing claims, each of which may, to its technical advocate, seem to be paramount. There is a danger that if a man is appointed head of a Department because of his technical
29. (c) Inspectorate.Numbers.			.  ;   Total Cost  -(in   thousands).			Cost per bead.		1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.11,174	12,434	111-3	2,558-7	5,502-8	215-1	229	442-6	193-3The increase in cost per head is higher than in any other group of salaried staff. The same difficulty arises in this group as in the Professional group of selecting one rate of pay to which the rest can be related, but the relatively high increase in cost per head suggests that it would be wise to examine these rates in detail in the near future.The group is interesting for another reason. The cost of some Civil Servants may be measured in their pay, but others- and notably many of the Inspectors swell the pay roll all round the industries they inspect. It is impossible to estimate how many millions are involved in spending  5,500,000 as we do in 1923 on Inspectors nor need anyone complain so long as the public who pay the bill are satisfied that all this inspection is necessary. It is, however, appropriate to our enquiry to point out that this indirect expense exists an expense often out of all comparison with the pay of the Inspector and that both the direct and in-direct charges have to be met out of the same purse. The public as taxpayers pay the salaries of the Inspectors and as consumers, the indirect cost with which these inspections burden industry. Without touching on policy we suggest that the Government should limit as much as possible the number of Ministries which have to interfere with each industry. It is in our view bad business that several Departments should be employed in carrying out inspections of one industry when it would be possible to focus the demands of Government in one inspection. Reform on these lines would, we believe, reduce the direct cost of pay of Inspectors and would relieve the public of a still greater indirect expense.qualifications, he may not be able to free himself from his technical outlook and that the Service may not gain, but suffer, by his special knowledge in one direction.We, therefore, remark about this group (a) that their increase in pay per head is not excessive, (b) that enough applicants present themselves to fill the vacancies, (c) that the quality of candidates is reported to be good.
30. (d) Executive and Clerical Group.The figures of increase in numbers and total cost of Executive and Clerical Officers are striking : Numbers.		Total Cost (in   thousands).		Cost per head.	1914. 1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914. 1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.  1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.33,239 78,504	236-2	4,416 17,770-1	402-4	138-8  226-3	170-431. We have compared the increase in cost per, head of this group with a 5 per cent, sample of all income-tax payers returned as employees of companies in the following trades : 1. Coal Mining, Metal and Engineering Industries. 2. Textile Industries. 3. Chemical Industries. 4. Food, Drink and Tobacco Manufacture. 5. Lighting, Paper, Newspaper, etc., Industries. 6. Shipping. 7. Banking. 8. Insurance. 9. Departmental Stores. 10. Railwaysand report that the percentage increase of pay in 1923 to this group of Civil servants over their pay in 1914 is less than in some trades and greater than in others and does not appear excessive on this comparison.32. We have also instituted a series of comparisons between the pay of executive and clerical officers and the pay of clerks in private business. These&apos; comparisons show, as is noted above, that the lower grades in the Civil Service are paid better than lower grades in many private employments, and they show also that continuity of service of the employee is one of the factors on which pay is based in the open market. In the Civil Service a constantly changing staff would cause serious difficulties, and it is of importance that the pay should be adequate not only to secure but to retain the services of efficient men.While these comparisons show that many private employers have not reached the same conclusions about pay as the Civil Service, it would be a false deduction that either the private employers or the Civil Service decided wrongly. The work of the Civil Service is on an immense scale, and is subject throughout to all the limitations of Government service and Parliamentary
control; it requires special qualities as well as continuous service. For this reason we do not suggest that pressure should be put upon the Government to cut down the basic wage of the clerks in these grades.33. It has been represented to us on behalf of the Temporary staff that their present rates are not properly adjusted to the cost of living. This question does not fall within our reference, but the plea deserves attention as it emphasises our view that both employers and employed profit by keeping well in mind the true principles on which pay is based.The temporary clerical and typing staffs are a large group, numbering no less than 41,000 Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.4,293	41,885	975	250 -8	6260-4	2,497	58-4	149-5	256The large majority of this staff is employed on work which does not require much experience and is not permanent.It follows that if the principle is generally adopted which the Navy suggests for bluejackets and we propose for all pay (para. 3), the pay of the temporary staff should be sufficient to attract recruits of the right quality and quantity in other words, the State must pay not less than the rates paid by good private employers. The cost of living is one of the factors discounted in the pay.We see no reason for thinking that the present rates of remunerative-ation of the temporary clerical staff are inadequate.34,     (e) Writing Assistants and Typing Grades.Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.3,034	11,198	369-1	198-3	1,443-6	728	65-4 ....	128-9	197-2This group consists almost entirely of women Writing Assist-ants, Typists, Shorthand Typists, Superintendents, etc.
In 1914 a good deal of typing was done by junior male clerks and the figures of this group in 1914 and 1923 are not, therefore&apos; strictly comparable, but the present rates of pay seem to be iii scale with the remuneration paid by good outside employers for the same, or similar, classes of work.35. Hours.The Civil Service rule for clerical and higher grades in London is a seven-hour day, including three-quarters of an hour off for lunch ; in the provinces an eight-hour day.In the higher grades the seven-hour day has little importance, as overtime is not paid for and the staff as a whole give generous measure.For the routine clerical classes, the normal attendance should, in our view, be eight hours, including three-quarters of an hour off for lunch.36. (/) Manipulative Grades.	Numbers.		Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.177,747	168,508	94-8	11,975	25,011-5	20S-8	67-4	148-5	220-3The increase over 1914 in cost per head for this group is striking.Of the total staff of 168,508 employed at 1st March, 1923, 159,429 belonged to Post Office grades, the remaining 9,079 being made up of institutional staff of the Ministry of Pensions, the subordinate discipline staff of the Prisons Commission, women tellers and warehousemen at the Inland Revenue, etc.37. The figures of numbers and cost of the Post Office group alone are as follows : Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as peTcen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.-172,560	159,429	92-4	1 11,589	i 23,753-5	204-9	/ 67&quot;-1	i 148-9	221 -S
We understand that the high percentage increase in cost per head of the Post Office staff (121-8 per cent.) since 1914 is partly attributable to changes in organisation (e.g., reduction in number of part-time officers and boy messengers, non-filling of vacancies at the minimum in consequence of reductions in staff) and to increase in commission payments to Scale Payment Sub-Postmasters in respect of new work imposed since 1914 ; and that if these causes were ehminated the increase would be reduced to about 104 per cent.The largest classes of Post Office Manipulative workers are the Sorter, Telegraphist, Counter Clerk and Telegraphist (all London grades), Sorting Clerk and Telegraphist (Provincial grade), Postman (London and Provinces) and Telephonist (London and Provinces).We have compared the pay of some of these classes with the pay of workers in outside occupations in some detail. Taking the pay of a postman in inner London as an example we find that the increase since 1914 in the maximum rate of pay to the Postman is high by comparison with the increase in the rates paid to workers in trades open to World competition, but that when comparison is made with sheltered occupations there are one or two employ-ments where the absolute and relative increases in wages since 1914 are still as great as those of the Postman. As all these manipulative rates are related one to another the same criticism would probably on a closer examination be found to be generally true. We anticipate that in due course the rates in sheltered occupations will be brought into closer harmony with the level of wages in the open trades on which they depend, and we think the Post Office should consider whether such high maximum rates as are now paid are necessary.We find also that Women Telephonists receive higher starting pay at 16 than similar young women in private employment. This is a general feature of pay in the Civil Service on which we have commented in paragraph 32.38. (g) Messengers, Charwomen, etc.Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percen-tage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as pereen-tage of 1914.13,296	19,678	148	664-2	1995-3	300	49-9	101-4	203This, group includes about 19,700 messengers, porters, char-women, etc., with average gross remuneration of  101 per annum. The large majority of this group is unestablished and we make no comment.
39. \h) Industrial Staffs.Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.104,479	118,523	113-4	^S,454-3	^16,894-5	199-8	 80-9	 142-5	176-1This group is distributed as follows : 	Numbers.			Total Cost (in   thousands).			Cost per head.		Department.	1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as per-centage of 1914.Admiralty Post Office        ........ War Office*      ........ Air         ..   :   .&apos;.   .   .. - .. . .   ..... Works Stationery Disposal and Liquidation Commission Labour   ..       ..       ..       ..     ... Forestry State Management Districts Mint :    ..       ..       .. Other Departments	52,685 24,022 25,000 1,391 239 20S 934	54,582 24,354 22,100 4,064 3,264 1,988 2.82S 1,266 1,47S 802 289 1.50S	103-6 101-4 88-4 234-6 831-8 13S:9 162-2	  4,307 1,896-6 2,000 123-1 19-4 32-1 76	  7,121 4,125-5 .3,019 582-8 541-1 349-5 370 279-4 109-9 74-9 60-3 221 -5	165-3 217-5 151 439-6 -2,007 187-8 291 -5	  81-75 78-9 80 88-5 81-2 154-3 81-4	  130-5 169-3 136-6 143-4 165-8 195-9 130-S 220-7 74-4 93-4 208-6 146-2	159-6 214-5 170-7 187-3 241-2 135-2 179-7Totals        * *	104,479	11S, 523	113-4	8,454 - 3	16,S94-5	199-8   i	SO-9	142-5	176-1* Approximatefigures.
The wages paid to Industrial staffs in most Departments of the Civil Service are based on Trade Union rates and therefore on the rates paid in private employment. The Admiralty, for example, the Air Ministry, Disposals Board, Stationery Office, War Office and Office of Works between them spend in wages based on Trade Union rates  12,000,000 out of the total shown above of  17,000,000. The large employers who do not pay at Trade Union rates are the Post Office, Labour and Mint. Of these, the Labour Ministry is peculiar, as it classes among industrial staff men who are employed as teachers of trades; we have no means of checking the wisdom of such rates as these.The Mint is the second highest in cost per head ( 208 per annum), but it shows the lowest increase per cent, over 1914  35 per cent. In the circumstances, we make no comment on the high cost per head of the Mint Industrial Staff : the duties call for men of high character, and the pay has been brought into closer relation with the pay of industrial staff in other offices and is, we understand, receiving special attention from the Treasury.In the Post Office, which is a very large employer of Industrial Labour and which is not automatically checked by Union rates, we have instituted a special comparison with various grades of Industrial workers in Electrical Engineering and Supply Under-takings. We find that in some cases the rates paid by the Post Office are higher and in other cases slightly lower than the rates paid in outside occupations, and that judged by these comparisons the Post Office rates are not out of scale with outside rates.40. Apart from the pay per head the total cost of pay of the Industrial staff has been swelled by an increase in the number of staff of 14,000 or 13-4 per cent since 1914. Of this total increase about 9,500 are employed in Departments which did not exist in 1914.We find that the rate of pay for the Industrial staff in Govern-ment Departments is in general reasonable, but we express no opinion whether the work done in Government Industrial Estab-lishments is necessary or whether some of it could not be carried out more economically by private enterprise. This is a separate question which we have not to examine.41. Having found that, with a few exceptions, the pay of Civil Servants is reasonable, we have compared the output of work per man in 1923 with the output in 1914.The total number of non-industrial staff employed in 1914 in Departments other than Irish Departments amounted to about 248,700 ; the number employed at 1st March, 1923, amounted to about 304,400. Of the total increase of 55,700 no less than 30,727 are employed in Departments which did not exist in 1914 (vide para. 20), leaving a net increase of about 24,970 distributed between other Departments. ;
The duties of these Departments have varied since 1914 On the one hand duties undertaken by Imperial Service Depart-ments in Ireland have been withdrawn (the consequent savings in staff have been discounted in this Report by excluding from the fig tires of the Departments principally affected the numbers and cost of staff previously employed in Ireland). On the other hand, among many great accretions of work, the number of income tax cases dealt with by the Inland Revenue has more than doubled since 1914 and tax law is now much more com-plicated. The number of persons falling within unemployment insurance has increased more than fourfold and more people are unemployed this means more work for the Ministry of Labour The Board of Trade, the Admiralty and War Office still employ many clerks on clearing up war work. At the Foreign Office work is increased by the abnormal state of Europe and by Peace negotiations and Treaties ; the Passport Offices alone account for.200 of the excess staff of this Department. The additional staff at.the Ministry of Health is mainly employed on housing questions, on the Navy and Army Insurance Fund, and on the audit of accounts of Local Authorities in respect of grants paid by the Exchequer ; whilst at the Public Trustee Office the number of trusts current on 31st March, 1923, was nearly three times as large as the number administered in 1914.After examining.the changes in numbers of staff employed by each; Department, we report that the Increase in Staff since 1914 is fully accounted for by the extra work which has been thrown on the Civil Service since 1914, and that the average individual output is certainly not less than in 1914.42. Women in the Civil Service.	Number.			Total Cost.			Cost per head.			1914.	1923.	1923 as percent-age of 1914.	1914.	1923.	1923 as percent-age of 1914.	1914	1923.	1923 as percent-age of 1914.Clerks, Writing Assistants, etc; Manipulative staff (mainly P.O. staff)	7,726 22,469	26,607 24,618	344-4 109-6	614-3 1,377-8	3,936-9 3,456-1	640-9 250-9	79-5 61-3	148 140-4	186-1 229Since 1914, women have established themselves not only in the Civil Service but also in private business in large numbers, and some operations comparable to the work which women do in the Civil Service are now usually assigned to women. The change is one of kind rather than degree, and just as since 1914
women have gained political independence, a vote, and member-ship in the House of Commons, so it seems to us that in business it will in the long run be satisfactory both for the employer and for the employed women to value women by the same standards as men and to give them both the privilege and the burden of economic independence. On this assumption and following the rule that we have indicated for the pay of men, the employer should offer women what is necessary to recruit the type he needs and to keep his service healthy and efficient. If for the same total cost of pay women do his work better than men, the value of women will appreciate and they will in due course get better pay till the employer finds that at changed rates men suit him in preference to women. If, on the other hand, for every   spent in pay on a certain operation a man gives a better return than a woman, that work will tend to be reserved for men. This rule of equal pay for equal value is, we think, not only justice, but the one rule that will permanently satisfy men and women, employers and employed, producers and customers;43. The position and pay of women in the Civil Service have been under debate in Parliament recently. On May 19th, 1920, the House of Commons carried a motion that &quot; It is expedient that women should have equal opportunity of employment with men in all branches of the Civil Service in the United Kingdom and under all Local Authorities, providing that the claims of ex-Service men are first of all considered, and shall also receive equal pay.&quot; On 5th August, 1921, the House passed further resolutions providing inter alia that &quot; Having regard to the present financial position of the country this House cannot commit itself to the increase in (Civil Service salaries involved in the payment of women in all cases at the same rate as men, but that the question of the remuneration of women as compared with men should be reviewed within a period not exceeding three years.&quot;44. If we may venture to comment on these resolutions, they seem to us to point to the danger of translating the principle of &quot; equal pay for equal value &quot; into &quot; equal pay for the same post,&quot; which is quite different. Women are newcomers in office work, and it would be dangerous to dogmatize about so novel an experiment, but we see no reason to suppose that exactly the same divisions of work or the same posts or rules that suit men will suit women; the contrary seems more probable. In the early years of her employment it is evident that for work which requires continuity of service a young woman gives less value than a young man of equal capacity and should be paid less. The prospect of marriage reduces the value of her employment to the average young women and her value to her employer. The rule in the Civil Service is to pay women on appointment to the Administrative, Executive and Clerical grades at the same rates as men.   In these grades continuity of service is of distinct
advantage, and we consider, therefore, that the young woman should be recruited for administrative, executive and clerical grades at a lower rate than the young man. So far as we are advised, the Civil Service would have no difficulty in recruiting educated women of the type they require at less rates than men, and the pay of women would still be higher than they could normally obtain elsewhere.According to the Civil Service rule, women in these grades rise at the same rate as men for the first three or four years and there-after less rapidly to a maximum about one-fourth below the maximum for men. As the woman grows older and the risk of marriage decreases, her value in work which requires continuity of service should rise in relation to the value of a man, but, as we have indicated above, it is still an experiment to employ women in the superior clerical posts and, while we have had some valuable evidence on the relative output of work by women and men in railways and banks arid other work above mere routine, we have not found any large employer who considers th at in these operations the average woman is worth as much as the average man. It seems to us, therefore, that the relation now existing between the pay of men and women in these grades in their later years of service roughly meets the present situation, and that in the meantime the greatest service the State can do to women is to allow them to prove in work which suits their physique that they can show initiative and the power to take responsibility and to prove in actual practice their relative value to the value of men. We have no doubt that in the Civil Service, as in every other well-managed service, proved value will be recognised in better pay.45. The grades of routine work which are described by the Civil Service as (e) Writing Assistants and (/) Manipulative are those in which women have thoroughly established themselves in private and in Government business. We have had evidence from a number of large employers that in such work as sorting notes and cheques, shorthand and typewriting, the working of various office machines, operating telephones and telegraphs, women are more painstaking and conscientious, and less irritated than men by the constant repetition of the same operation. All of these tasks,- in spite of the hard training some of them require, tend to become automatic to the expert. In private industry, therefore, women, by their superiority in this class of work, have already made good their footing and are now establishing their claim to be paid as much as the youth who previously did the work; in some private offices, but not in all, young men and women are paid at the same rates from 16 to 18 or 20 years of age.The Civil Service practice of paying their women Manipulative staffs during the first 6 years of service at the same rates as the corresponding male staff is thus not unreasonable, and we make no recommendation. For this work continuity of service is of much
less value than in the higher grades, and this is no doubt one of the reasons which have levelled the starting pay of women up to that of men.46. Whilst we believe that various points to which we have called attention are anomalies in the pay of Civil Servants which can be corrected without injustice and with economy, we report that on the whole these pay rolls have been carefully and wisely arranged.47. The immense increase in the Civil Service pay roll has been imposed on the taxpayer for reasons which commended them-selves to various Parliaments before and since 1914, and the conclusion we reach is that no power except Parliament can materially reduce the load.We invited the various Departments to inform us what Acts of Parliament or administrative regulations had caused this large growth of expenditure, and we were furnished with information which convinced us that it was impossible to press home this enquiry so far as to cut down work or even effectively to examine the ground unless the full authority of Parliament was applied. We are confirmed in this view by the results of a particular enquiry which has been held in the last few weeks into the. Mercantile Marine Department of the Board of Trade. In connection with the Fees (Increase) Act, 1923, the shipping industry has had put upon it the burden of one half the cost of mercantile marine services, and has been given in return the right to examine administrative costs. A Committee of Shipowners appointed to enquire into the costs has recently reported as follows : &quot; Had it been within our province to criticise the need for legislation there are many economies which we could have proposed. But given the legislation we are bound to report that in our opinion the cost of administration of the mercantile marine, though four times as great as before the war, is not in the main excessive. But we desire emphatically to recom-mend that the tendency to add to existing legislation should be watched in order that when new measures are proposed their cost to the community and the industry may be care-fully weighed before they are embarked upon.&quot;This is stated about one activity of one Ministry, but we believe it is generally true.Industrial and Social legislation, however good it may be, means more staff and more taxes.48. The difference in scale between Government and private business is so great that the direct methods of commerce may be inadequate for the larger task, but as our Civil Service is costing  44,000,000 more than in 1914, and as we find that gener-ally speaking, the pay per head is not too high, we venture to
indicate how this problem would present itself to a commercial firm and how differently it would be treated.Suppose that in a private business the Board becomes aware that expenditure is dangerously high, that custom will be lost unless charges are reduced, that no fresh income is in sight and that no substantial cut can be made in salaries if duties are to remain unchanged. Once these facts are established delibera-tion has passed and action begins. If the Board hesitate they are stimulated to action by their shareholders or their customers and they have open to them one.course and only one. They instruct the executive to survey the duties undertaken by the Company and to recommend which of these duties, choosing preferably the most expensive, can be closed down without damage to the whole.Every business in the country has probably been forced to swallow this medicine of economy, and to close down, either for a time or for ever, undertakings and expenses which seemed desirable or even necessary in easier times.In our opinion Parliament, and Parliament alone, which has already reduced the pay-roll of the Fighting Services, can reduce the pay-roll of the Civil Service on a grand scale ; if Parliament determines that the present cost is too high and that the work must be reduced the.cost of pay will shrink automatically.We are full of respect for the work of Civil Servants, but in a business which expends  75,000,000 per annum in pay, and where the pay-roll has increased in nine years by.  44,000,000, there must be great accretions of unnecessary work. In a private business this deck cargo of duties which have become unnecessary is thrown overboard when it becomes too heavy, or the business sinks when bad times, come upon it. Our public business is so huge that no one except Parliament can order reform, and, till Parliament gives the word, duties which need never have been imposed or have long since lost their value employ the staff who still have to be paid.49. Throughout our enquiry we have received the most willing and efficient help from the servants of the Crown with whom we came into contact, and the Board of Inland Revenue and the Ministry of Labour have given us information about pay within and outside the Civil Service which we could not have obtained elsewhere.But even with the best will in the world the servants of the Crown could not always give us the intimate comparison with private employment which we required, and we have, therefore, to thank very heartily the directors and officers of banks, railways, gas undertakings, shipping companies, and other private businesses who grudged neither time nor trouble to clear up points of difficulty on which we asked their advice.
In particular, we thank our Secretaries, Mr. Barnes and Mr. Morris, of the Treasury, who impressed us throughout with their ability and grasp, no less than with their zeal.We are, Sir,Your obedient servants,(Signed)   A. G. ANDERSON (Chairman). H. A. LAWRENCE. W. PETER RYLANDS.(Signed) G. G. Barnes, F. M. Morris,Joint Secretaries. Treasury Chambers, 25th July, 1923..1
Wages and Earnings in  certain &quot;Open&quot; Trades,    1919  i1923 shewn as percentages of corresponding   rates in 1914;.
Wages  in certain &quot;Sheltered&quot; Occupations     1919-1923, shewn as percentages of corresponding  rates in 19141;
Wages and Earnings in certain Open Trades^and I    1919 - 1923.Prices of related Commodibies        jshewn as percentages of corresponding rates and prices in 1914,
CashPay of Trained Infantry Private, plus messing &amp; kit allowances,whete issued.1s70i880i890i300	i870	1873	1898	1901	1907Regimental Pay, par diem	&apos;M	&apos;/	&apos;/	//-	&apos;/Other Pay (mean rates) per diem		1&quot;	./*	5&quot;	4&apos;AMessing Alice.              n      t,			3&quot;	3&quot;	3dKit Alice.	-	*		2*	Less stoppage per rations			&quot;	-	&quot;Total, per diem	n&apos;A			l/io	/m1910
(inct. value of emoluments in kind.)Building Labourers&apos; Wages, reduced by 14%........Engineering Labourers&apos; Wages, increased by 2&quot;/o... Agricultural Labourers&apos; Wages, increased by 29&apos;/:.The black curves show the military pay required From July 1919 onwards to main tain exactly the 1914 relativity with wages in the  three industries.
Graph  .Trained Soldiers&apos; Pay...........................................tincl. value of emoluments in kind.)Building Labourers&apos; Wages, reduced by 14%........Engineering Labourers&apos; Wages, increased by 2%...Agricultural Labourers&apos; Wages, increased byThe black curves show the military pay required From July [9/9 onwards to main-tain exactly the 1914 relativity with wages in the three industries.

</content>
</cab>
