<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/162/0 images: 420-422</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
nttimfflNT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS- BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos; S GOVERNMENT.Memorandum by the Minister of Labour. NATIONAL DIAMOND FACTORY (GUARANTEE AGREEMENT) BILL.I circulate herewith, for the information of members of the Cabinet, a letter which, with the Prime Minister1 s&apos;approval, I sent to Mr. Isaac Lewis of Messrs. Lewis &amp; Marks, on the 25th October, after an interview which I had had with him.     I also circulate a copy of Mr. Isaac Lewis&apos; acknowledgment of my letter.withdrawal of Messrs. Lewis   &amp; Marks that it is impossible to proceed with the Bill as proposed - see Cabinet Conclusion No,11. at Cabinet Meeting on Thursday, 1st August, 1923:   Cabinet 45 (23).435 ( 23)CABINETMy colleagues will now realise owing to the(int)M,B,Ministry of Labour,29th October, 1925.
3 4 copy.T.D.S.1590/7/1919.25th October, 1923.Dear Sir,I have nor; considered the question of proceeding with the National Diamond Factory (Guarantee Agreement) Bill in the light of the interview which at your request I had with you and Mr. Marks on October 16th.You told me then that the Dutch Managers had left and the organisation had been broken up; further that even after the Bill had passed, assuming it went through, you could not be sure of starting work at once.     I stated that in the interests of the ex-Service men I was anxious; to proceed with the Bill so as to get the Factory restarted.   You then pointed out that trade prospects are not now good and financial support would be more difficult to obtain now than in the summer.   You said that in the circumstances, while you were not desirous of backing out of any undertaking, you were not anxious to go on, and you even suggested that I should consider whether the Government ought to proceed with the Bill.On the commercial aspect of the question, I have consulted Sir Robert Kindersley, who, as you know, was fully cognisant of the previous arrangement and negotiations.    &apos; He takes the view that as matters now stand, and particularly /in view of the fact that the organisation has been broken I.....up, the arrangement embodied in the Bill does not offer sufficient prospect of success to justify going on.It.has always been my hope that, under proper management, the skill which the workmen have admittedly acquired could be utilised to carry   on a profitable enterprise on a sound commercial basis, but, in view of the altered circumstances which you explained to me at our interview, I do not see that the arrangement proposed offers adequate chances of success.In these circumstances, I have told the Prime Minister that I share Sir Robert Kindersley&apos;s view, and that, in my opinion, the Government should not proceed with the Bill.Yours faithfully,(Sgd ).    C. A. M. BARLOW.P.3.   As I intimated above, the interests of the ex-jService men are in my view the paramount consideration, and in view of the altered circumstances I am at once making arrangements with a view to the provision of alternative training.(Intd.) M.B.
COPY.lewis &amp; Marks,Stafford House,14 - 20, King William StLondon, 13.0.4.October 26th, 1923,Bear Sir Montague Barlow,I have to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 25th Ootober, end note that you bavo jreoommended the Prime Minister not to proceed with the Bill,I appreciate very much the trouble that you have taken to satisfy yourself as to the effect upon this question of tho great depression whioh has resulted in business, and I also note that Six Bobert kindersley oonfirms the view which I have unfortunately been toroed to take, that under all the conditions the scheme whioh I had so much at heart must be abandoned,lours faithfully,(Signed)ISAAC LEWIS.She Bt. Hon. Sir Montague Barlow, K.B.L. ,LIi.P Minister of Labour, Montagu House,Whitehall, S.&apos;n.l.

</content>
</cab>
