<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 33-38</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S EGRET.C.P. 98 (57) .                                           COPY NO^                            CABINET,                            MARRIAGE BILL.                 Memorandum &quot;by the  Lord Chancellor.            I. think it  necessary to &quot;bring  to  the  attention of my                  .                                   -Y.Y Y        colleagues the  situation  which will arise  if the  Marriage        Bill,  which has  now passed  through  Committee in the House        of Commons, &quot;becomes law in  the same form as  that  which  it        has now assumed.            The  Bill by Clause 5 adds three grounds for  divorce  to        those  which are  at  present  available to  the  petitioner,        namely, desertion,  cruelty, and insanity.            Furthermore, &quot;by Clause 4  the Bill makes a substantial        alteration in the duty at present imposed upon the court  when        considering a petition.            As the law stands, it  is  the duty of the Court &quot;to        satisfy itself  so far as  it reasonably can both  as to  the        facts  alleged and also as to whether the petitioner has been        accessory to or  has connived at or  condoned the  adultery  or                                                           .......  .....        not&quot;.   And &quot;if  the Court is  satisfied on the evidence  that        the case  for the petitioner has been proved, and does not        find that the petitioner  has  in any manner been  accessory to        or connived at  or condoned  the adultery, or that  the petition        is presented or prosecuted  in  collusion  with either of  the        respondents, the court shall  pronounce a decree  of divorce&quot;.            Under the  Clause as  it now stands,  the  duty  is stated as        follows s-
          &quot;On a petition for divorce it shall be the     duty of the court to inquire, so far as it     reasonably can, into the facts alleged and     whether there has been any connivance or con-     donation on the part of the petitioner and     whether any collusion exists between the parties     and also to inquire into any countercharge which     .1s made against the petitioner&quot;.     The Bill, therefore, in three ways will add very considerably to the duties of the Probate, Divorce &amp; Admiralty Division.     (1) By reason of the addition to the grounds upon which a petition may be presented, there will be an increase, andpossibly a large increase, in the number of petitions.     (2) Owing to the fact that cruelty will become a ground fordivorce and not as hitherto a ground only for judicial separation,each case based on cruelty may be expected to occupy the court for a longer period than at present.   In a large proportion ofthe suits for judicial separation based on cruelty, the parties are persuaded by the Court to enter into a separation deed.   but when cruelty becomes a substantive ground for divorce this will beimpossible.   Experience shows, moreover, that cruelty cases whenfought are almost invariably long.     (3) The hearing of each petition will, by reason of theadditional and stricter duty laid upon the Court, be more extensive in time.                               &apos;  -     As the law now stands, the Divorce Court is in arrear wix-hits work, and as the current work is in excess of the amcunrwhich the Court can discharge, the position is becoming steadilyworse, even when the additional work which will follow thepassing of the Bill is disregarded.   In the last three yearstnere has been a steady increase in the number of cases includedin the Term&apos;s list.   Thus, the number of Undefended Divorcecases in the list on the 26th February, 1935, was 914, a figure which rose to 984 by&apos; the same date in 1936, and to 1,117 by  the22nd February, 1937j  and on the 22nd February of this year  thecases actually being dealt with were those set down on the 14thSeptember in the previous year.   In the Defended Non-Juries,  the
corresponding figures are 308, 386 and 433, and the Court onthe 22nd February was dealing with cases set down on the 22ndMay, 1936.   Meanwhile, the output of the Court lias notdiminished but shows a slight increase on the total number ofcases disposed of in 1934 of 2,918 to the total disposed of in1936 of 3,084.     To put the matter another ways  if the judicial year forthree Judges is taken at 555 working days, and 105 days are allowed for Admiralty, 60 days for Summonses and Motions,Judgment Summonses and Divisional Court, and 90 days forUndefended causes, 300 days are left.   In 1936, the Courtdisposed of over 700 Defended Causes, an allowance of ratherunder half a day a case.   A considerable proportion of thesecases are short, but cases lasting four to five days arecommon and those lasting six to seven days are not unknown,     Furthermore, the.Admiralty work appears to be on theincrease, and it may be expected that with the rise of freightand the value of hulls it will increase still furtner in thenear future.     The Division, therefore, as things now stand, can only make headway by obtaining help from the other Divisions of theHigh Court, that is to say, in practice from the King&apos;s bench division.   It is not always easy to obtain this help, and at thepresent moment, by reason partly of sickness among the Judges ofthe King&apos;s Bench Division and partly of the heavy work on Circuit,it has not been found possible for that.Division to affordcontinuous help.     Towards the end of February the Law Society informed me thatthey had received a complaint that even undefended cases had to wait six months after being set  down before they were heard, andthat the position with regard to defended cases was worse.    Theyadded that in their opinion this complaint was entirely justifiedand that the time had arrived when some drastic action should betaken to remedy the delay.
       It is not possible to form an accurate forecast of the increase of work  watch will result from the passageof the Bill.   The president of the probate, Divorce and admiralty Division roughly estimates the increase as equivalent  to about the time of one Judge.   If this estimateshould prove to be correct, and if legislative authority should now be given for the increase.of the number of Judges by one,the Division will still be in the difficulty in wnich it now is, that is to say, it will still have slightly more work todo than can oe accomplished with the Judge power available.Furthermore, the -admiralty work shows a disposition toincrease, and there is reason to anticipate that, with a continued improvement in trade, that increase will proceed ona steeper curve.       I regard it, therefore, as essential that statutory authority should be obtained for trie appointment of anadditional Judge of the Division.   But, as will have beengathered from the preceding observations, an addition of one would still leave the Division in a precarious position, andI should propose that Parliament should be asked to sanctiona permanent audition of one Judge, together with an auditionof another whose re-appointment should De contingent upon thepassing of a Resolution by both Houses when satisfied thatthe work of the Division was such as to require the vacancy tobe filled.       The matter is one of some urgency.   The Bill is represented and has been received by all, or nearly all,schools of opinion in the House of Commons, and by manysections of opinion outside, as a serious attempt to solvea difficult social question, and in particular to put an end to the mischiefs watch are said to arise from the operation
of the present law.   There can be no doubt that,  as thingsnow stand, the Court itself and the law which it administersare brought into disrepute by the widely held suspicion that many of the proceedings before the Court are collusive^It is argued that  the addition to the grounds upon which adivorce can now be obtained of those grounds which are summarised above will render it unnecessary for parties tohave recourse to collusion,, and that the additional dutyplaced upon the Court to satisfy itself affirmatively of theabsence of collusion will result in a more strict observanceand administration of the law.   But this contention willbecome  ineffective, and the administration of the law willbe brought still further into disrepute if, when the Bill is passed, the Court  finds itself unable either to deal withthe increased number of petitions presented to it or to apply-in strictness the  law which it is called upon to administer.And it can only perform these two duties if the number of judges available is increased, in the manner which I havesuggested,.       I  cannot at the sane time conceal the fact that much will depend upon the manner in which the new lawis administered on Assize.   Very grave criticism has beenmade on the spirit in which the King&apos;s Bench Judges dealwith petitions for divorce in the Provinces.-   And grave doubts are felt by some as to whether they will applythemselves to the  discharge of their new duties in this regard in accordance with the spirit as well as the letterof the Bill.   It  has been suggested that this difficultyshould be met by retracing the steps taken some few yearsago and by requiring all petitions to be tried in london by the trained Judges of the Probate, Divorce and admiralty division  assisted  by the experienced Bar which practices
before them.I am satisfied that  no  such  course  ispossiblesThe law cannot effectively be put intooperation without the assistance of solicitors  throughoutthe country working under the rules relating to litigationpresentation of a petition for divorce is such that thoserules cannot be worked if all petitions must be heard inLondon.    The Law Society (centred in London) could not carry the burden of all divorce petitions.    And thecountry Law Societies could not find solicitors to conduct divorce petitions on behalf of Poor Persons unless their trial is local.    The President of the ProbateDivorce and Admiralty Division is of opinion that theonly way out of the difficulty is to continue the systemof local trial, but to provide that it should he conductedbefore a Judge sent on Circuit for the purpose from his ownDivision.    He estimates that the Division would be capableof discharging these duties if its members were permanentlyincreased from three Judges,as at present,  to five. . I seevery many practical and, as I think, insuperable diffi-culties in the way of this suggestion, and I am not pre-pared to support it.    But I think that the difficulty and the suggestion should be before my colleagues whenthey consider the proposals which I have made earlier in this Memorandumoby Poor Persons,,A&apos;i&apos;d the expense connected with the(Intld. )House of Lords,18th  March,  1937.

</content>
</cab>
