<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 59-86</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 (this document is the property of his  britannic majesty&apos;s                    government                                               Copy No. ^-3 ,SECRET.CP. 103(37)                     CABINET.       PROPOSED WIRELESS TELEGRAPHY BILL.      Memorandum by the Postmaster General.     (l) I submit for the consideration of the Cabinet aproposal to introduce a new Wireless Telegraphy Bill.     (2) The existing Wireless Telegraphy Acts are as follows   Wireless Telegraphy Act 1904.   Wireless Telegraphy (Explanation) Aet 1925.   Wireless Telegraphy (Blind Persons Facilities) Act 1926.It is desired to consolidate these Acts and to bring them up todate by including additional provisions which are necessaryto meet present-day conditions consequent upon the developmentof the application of Wireless Telegraphy since the originalAct was passed nearly thirty-three years ago.     (3) The main Wireless Telegraphy Act was passed in 1904as a temporary measure, and it has to be extended each yearby Inclusion in the Expiring Laws Continuance Bill.Complaints have frequently been made in the House of commons at the re-enactment year after year of the 1904 Act; and itwould be a great advantage to secure an Apt in permanent form.     (4) Proposals for permanent legislation were considered                                                         in(G)  562/37.
in 1922, 1924 and 1925.  The 1922 and 1924 attempts failedthrough changes of Ministry.  The Bill introduced inFebruary 1925 met with criticism, mainly  on the ground thatit re-enaeted a provision in the 1904 Act which gives thePostmaster General the right to obtain, when necessary, froma Justice of the Peace, a warrant to search premises where itie suspected that unlicensed wireless apparatus is beingworked.  A misleading Press campaign was carried on against this alleged &quot;invasion of the Englishman&apos;s home&quot;; and inMay 1925 the Government withdrew the measure and replaced it by a brief Bill - the Wireless Telegraphy (Explanation) Bill -whioh merely enacted that the provisions of the 1904 Actapplied to receiving apparatus as well as to transmittingapparatus.  The 1925 Act thus gave the Postmaster General theright to obtain a search warrant in respect of an unlicensedreceiving set; but in practice the number of such warrantsapplied for since 1925 has, on an average, been less than three a year.  In general, the Press are now very sympathetic to the Post Office efforts to persuade all wireless listenersto pay their licence fees; and it is unlikely that there-enactment in a new Wireless Bill of the existing provisionconcerning search warrants would provoke Press opposition.     (5) The Act of 1926 merely gave the Postmaster general power to grant receiving licences to blind persons withoutthe payment of a fee.     (6) The advent of broadcasting, which was not envisagedwhen the Act of 1904 was passed,  has&apos; introduced freshproblems.   There are at present over 8,000,000 licensedreceivers; and the Post Office has to investigate upwards of40,000 complaints a year of interference with broadcastreception by electrioal plant and apparatus,.  The Post Office                                                       does
does its best to trace the cause of the trouble and to suggest a remedy; but it has no power to insist on its advice being followed and it has to rely on the good will of the owners ofthe offending plant or apparatus to take the necessary steps toput matters right.  Although in many instances a satisfactory solution is arrived at, in others the offender refuses to takethe necessary action.     (7) A comprehensive examination of this problem has beenmade by a Committee appointed by the Institution of ElectricalEngineers, on which the Electrical Industry, the RadioManufacturers, the British Broadcasting Corporation and the PostOffice were represented.  The work of this Committee was brought to the notice of the Broadcasting Committee, under theChairmanship of Lord Ullswater, who included the following statement in paragraph 140 of their Report:-      &quot;We trust that the technical investigations and   discussions of this matter, which have extended over   two years, will be completed as soon as possible; and   if the result is to show that the Postmaster General   (or other appropriate Minister) needs further powers   for the purpose of protecting the listener, subject to   suitable safeguards, we trust that the requisite powers   will be sought&quot;.     (8) In accordance with a Cabinet decision, the following statement was included in Command Paper 5207 setting out theGovernment&apos;s conclusions on the Ullswater Committee&apos;srecommendations      &quot;Paragraph 140:  that the technical investigation of   interference with broadcast reception should be completed   as soon as possible, and that, if necessary, further powers   should be sought&quot;.      &quot;The Government accept this recommendation&quot;.     (9) The Committee on Electrical Interference withBroadcasting have now issued their Report and have recommendedthat the Electricity Commissioners should be given powers to                                                       issue
 issue Regulations to suppress interference with radio reception and that the Postmaster General should be given powers to enforce the application of such Regulations.   (The Committee&apos;s recommendations will be found in paragraphs 18  to 31 inclusive of their report, a copy of which is attached).    (10) I am  advised that legislation will be necessary to give the Electricity Commissioners and the Postmaster Ge&amp;eral the requisite  powers and that a Wireless Telegraphy Bill would be the appropriate medium for creating those powers.  TheMinistry of Transport concurs in principle, so far as the Electricity Commissioners are concerned;  and  the Treasury have given the necessary authority to Parliamentary Counsel in regard to the preparation of a draft Bill.    (11) Apart from the need for a fresh Wireless Telegraphy Bill to create the necessary powers to deal with interference, the introduction of such a Bill would enable the Government to bring the existing Acts up to date in many respects and to make the provisions permanent.  In particular, it is desirable to include television within the scope of the Bill.  The existing Aots  do not cover pictures or images, but onlymessages:  hence if television were unaccompanied by any form of message,  it could be transmitted and received byunlicensed wireless apparatus without infringing the law.    (12) I have been asked several times in the House of Commons whether the Government will introduce legislation to carry out the  recommendations of the Electrical Interference Committee; and I have stated in reply that the matter was still under consideration.   The Electricity Commissioners haverecently suggested that the Government&apos;s decision on the question of introducing a Bill should be announoed as soon as                                                   possible
possible, as until this is done,  no real progress can be  madein the direction of persuading manufacturers of eleotrioalapparatus to design their products in such a way as to avoidrisk of interference.  I concur in the view that an early announcement of the Governments decision is desirable.    (13) Approval in principle is accordingly sought for theintroduction of a Wireless Telegraphy Bill on the general lines  indicated in this memorandum,  which would make provision -        (a) to consolidate the present Acts;        (b) to bring their provisions up to date - in             particular by extending their scope to cover             television - and to make them permanent; and        (c) to empower the Electricity Commissioners to             make regulations to suppress interference             with radio reception and to empower the             Postmaster General to enforce these regulations.if approved, I would propose to take an early opportunity to announce that the Government has decided to introduce a wireless Telegraphy Bill as soon as Parliamentary conditionspermit to give effect to the scheme recommended by the electrical Interference Committee.                         (Intld.) G.C.T.                                    24 March,  1937.
   &quot;Iiratifarthm of (Eternal  (BttghtemFOUNDED )avi.             INCORPORATED BY ROYAL CHARTER, 1921. Savoy Place, Victoria Embankment, London, W.C.2.   ELECTRICAL  INTERFERENCE  WITH                 BROADCASTING(Report of a Committee appointed by the Council of The Institution;           unanimously approved by the Council.)                      PREFACE  The Council  of the Institution  of  Electrical Engineerswill recall that in  1933 they appointed a small &quot; preparatory committee&quot; to review the  subject of interference withradio reception.  This preparatory Committee reported inApril,  1933, and  advised  the Council that serious inter-ference appeared to be taking place,  reviewed the extentof this, and indicated the measure  of  technical advance towards ascertaining the best methods of curing the trouble.  As a result  of that report the Council appointed thepresent representative Committee with the following termsof reference:  fa) To consider the report (drawn up by the preparatory        Committee appointed by the Council) setting out        the problems to be solved.   (b) To make recommendations as to the steps, if any, to        be taken to secure the  elimination or mitigation        of electrical interference with  radio reception.   (c) In  connection with (b) above, the  Committee are        requested to consider,  inter alia,  the following        specific matters: -        (i) The  degree  of immunity  of  each  type of           apparatus, and the degree of interference from           each  type  of  electrical plant and  the  best           means for its elimination.[Price dd. net, post free]
       (ii) The desirability of embodying in specifications           for new plant the requirements for interference           suppression.       (iii) The desirability or otherwise of legislation.  We submitted  to the  Council an interim report on the18th October, 1934; indicating the various phases of thesubject which we were  studying,  and  the progress beingmade.    .                  . , ,  We now have the honour to submit  our final report onthe subject.  From this  we hope the Council will see thattheir Committee has not merely been studying the subject,but has stimulated action by various bodies with a  viewto clarifying such questions as standards and measurementof interference.  We have also endeavoured, as far as welegitimately could as a Committee, to encourage the applica-tion of radio-interference  suppression devices.  This sideof our activities has been the easier because the council had  appointed to their  Committee representatives of  allorganizations which were likely to be interested or to beable to help  in securing general collaboration in the elec-trical industry.   In Appendix I we give a list of theseorganizations and their representatives on the Committee.  Altogether 95 meetings of committees dealing with radiointerference have been  held in the 3  years  which  have elapsed since the Institution Committee was set up, asfollows:   Main I.E.E. Committee and Sub-Committees     . .   62  B.S.I. Committee and Panels ..     .  .    ..     ...   20  E.R.A. Committee......    . .     . .   131. Previous Report.  When we presented our first report to the Council (inOctober, 1934), although we were  able to recommend an objective limit we were  unable to say that the technicalposition was sufficiently advanced  to justify the drawing up of formal regulations for the suppression of interference.This was mainly because none of  the methods proposed
     -  (ii) The desirability of embodying in specifications           for new plant the requirements for interference           suppression.       (iii) The desirability or otherwise of legislation.  We submitted  to  the  Council  an interim report on  the18th October, 1934; indicating the various phases  of  thesubject which we were  studying, and the progress beingmade.  We now have the honour to submit our final report onthe subject.  From this  we hope the Council will see thattheir Committee has not merely been studying the subject,but has stimulated action by various bodies with a viewto clarifying such questions as standards and measurementof interference.. We have also endeavoured,  as far as welegitimately could as a Committee, to encourage the applica-tidn of radio-interference suppression devices.  This  sideof our activities  has been the easier because  the council had  appointed to their  Committee representatives of allorganizations which were likely to be interested or, to beable to help  in securing general  collaboration in the elec-trical industry.   In Appendix I we give a list of theseorganizations and their representatives on the Committee.  Altogether 95 meetings of committees dealing with radiointerference have been  held  in  the -3 years  which have elapsed since the Institution Committee was set up, asfollows:   Main I.E.E. Committee and Sub-Committees     ..  62  B.S.I. Committee and  Panels . .     .....    ...  20  E.R.A.  Committee    ..     ..     ..     ..     ..131. Previous Report.  When we presented our first report to the Council (inOctober, 1934),  although we were able to  recommend an objective limit we were unable to say that the technicalposition was sufficiently advanced to justify the drawing up of formal regulations for the suppression of interference.This was mainly because none of the methods proposed
56for assessing and  measuring interference was sufficientlyestablished  to  give us  confidence  in  its  suitability for practical application.2. Objective limit.  The recommendation  in the  above-mentioned  Reportstill holds good as to the objective limit which is desirable,that is to say,  there should be a  difference of  at least40 decibels between the strength of  the signal (or wanted)field*  and the interfering (or unwanted)  field.  But thestep has been a long one between  defining the objectivelire should like to reach, and finding a yardstick or per-haps more than one which can be applied practically tothe several  very diverse groups of  conditions which giverise to radio interference.3. Method of measurement.   A method of measurement has now been agreed uponand instruments have been  developed which are  capableof indicating with sufficient accuracy the amount of inter-ference -caused  by much of the electrical apparatus whichcauses trouble.4. Technical position.   Technically,  therefore, the position is  that a  methodof  determining  interference  caused by many types of apparatus is now available,  and in the majority of thesecases it  is not considered that any undue extra  expensewill be involved in the design  and construction  of suchapparatus to  brings the interference caused down to an acceptable standard.5. Apparatus to be corrected.  The apparatus which is likely tq cause the most inter-ference is comprised in the following groups.   Most of the    ; :      - * Of the order of 1 mV/m, modulated 80 %.....
 trouble  from radio interference  would  be eliminated  if these could be satisfactorily dealt with:       Lifts in buildings.      Trolley-buses and trams.      Household electrical appliances.      Small electric motors used in commercial premises.      &quot; Neon &quot; display signs.      Certain rectifiers for power plant.      Electro-medical apparatus.   A brief  account of the studies  undertaken and the pro- gress made in connection with the above groups is given in an Appendix to this Report (Appendix II).      .  . 6. Ignition systems and television.   In addition to the items listed in paragraph 5, the ignition systems on automobiles must be mentioned,  although at present  there is  no appreciable interference from, auto- mobile ignition with  ordinary  broadcast reception on its present wavelengths.   If,  however,  such systems continue in use uncorrected it  is probable that there will be inter- ference with  television reception.  How troublesome  this may be will  only be known when  the  television  service begins. 7. Other sources of interference.   There are other, groups of apparatus which  might be, and occasionally  are,  the cause of  radio interference, for instance, electric signalling  gear on railways.  So far as these groups  are  the cause of trouble they will doubtless be corrected in due course, but they are not at the present time to be reckoned  amongst  the  major causes of radio interference. 8. Progress achieved.   The progress towards precise definition of the best way&quot;of measuring  the  interference caused by apparatus in each of the  above groups,  and the most effective method of(1)(2)(3)(4)(5)(6)(7)
 correction, is greater in some than in others, but with all of them we can  say that,  technically,  radio-interference correction is possible, although, from the point of view of cost, some cases  are relatively more expensive to rectify than others,  In all groups a considerable  measure  of radio interference correction  has been taking place during the last few  years, as a result of Post Office activity com- bined with voluntary application of the indicated remedies. But this has only been effected in individual cases and as the result of listeners&apos; complaints. 9. Traffic signals.  The first case in which radio interference correction was in effect  made compulsory  was  that  of  traffic signals. &apos; The Ministry of Transport require all traffic signals to be supplied to British Standard Specification No. 505 -1933. The fitting  of correcting components was,  from the first, one of the requirements of this B.S. Specification, and the result has thus been achieved without serious difficulty.. 10. Trolley-buses.  A second case in which much practical progress has been made is that of  trolley-buses, where again the Ministry of Transport  have influence  in securing attention to the matter  on the part of those who are in a position to help, and  who have in  fact  co-operated willingly with the Ministry to this end. 11.  Compulsory powers versus voluntary action.  As it became  clear to us that the  various  technical aspects  of the problem were approaching solution, we felt we ought  to  give  renewed &quot;consideration to the important question whether  compulsory powers should be conferred on some Authority to require radio-interference suppression in cases in which it appears that this will not be achievedeffectively  without  the application of such powers.  it became evident from the  discussions of the-Committeethat the majority of members did not consider that effectiveinterference  suppression would result if the improvement ....... ;. ....... .                                       *&apos;   &apos;--
of the position were to be left solely  to voluntary effort.The  manufacturers  of  appliances  and  plant which areliable to cause interference definitely support this view,and they consider that there should  be some recognizedMark which  could  be affixed  to all  portable appliancesas a  guarantee that such appliances comply with therequirements, and that the  sale of appliances which  donot meet with these requirements should be prohibited.Further, it is. essential that imported articles should besubject to the same  regulations as home-produced articles and should bear the Mark, and it is only through legislation that this question  can be dealt with successfully.  Fre-quently it is not the man who buys and uses the apparatus,but his neighbour,  who suffers from  the  resulting inter-ference.  For -these- reasons,  and  also  because  of thedifficulty of dealing  with  imported apparatus, the  BritishElectrical and Allied Manufacturers&apos; Association  is infavour of some form of compulsion^-12. Form of compulsory  powers in connection with new     apparatus.  It appeared to the majority of the  Committee that theproblem was one which could best be  solved satisfactorilyby giving powers to  some Authority, acting under suitabletechnical guidance and  safeguards, to issue, from time totime,  regulations appropriate  to  the  design, use,  andmaintenance, of  apparatus coming  under each  group of equipment in order to ensure that all apparatus scheduledin the Regulations and sold after certain prescribed  dateswould be &quot; interference-free.&quot;   This course, furthermore,was  favoured on the ground that the standards and pro-cedure in the more difficult cases would not require  to be defined until the specific technical groundwork was soundlylaid.   Procedure in making and applying regulations would thus be by stages.13. Views of Committee.- The Committee arrived at  the above-mentioned deci-sion  by a majority of 13 to  5,  the  majority  including
representatives speaking officially-on behalf of the Incor-porated Municipal  Electrical Association and the BritishElectrical and Allied Manufacturers&apos; Association.14. Cost of effecting suppression of interference in exist-     ing apparatus..  Although the cost of correcting existing apparatus  is undoubtedly higher than the cost involved if the apparatusis designed initially to be &quot; interferenceJree,&quot; it has beenfound  that the cost of effecting the required degree ofsuppression of existing apparatus or plant is usually buta small percentage of its original cost.  Thus in  the caseof small apparatus it may amount to only a few shillings.For electric lifts in flats it will probably in many casesamount to  15- 25.15. How existing apparatus has been dealt with. &apos; In the large number of complaints with which  the PostOffice  have dealt  (now approximately 40 000 per annum)the cost  of the suppression device has  been paid for bythe owner of the apparatus as  a matter  of goodwill on his part.  But we are informed that a recent  analysis showsthat in some  4 or 5 per cent  of the cases the owner hasnot been willing  to  meet the expenditure.  In  some  ofthese cases the expenditure would doubtless amount to asum which the owner does not  feel he can afford.16. Regulations in connection with existing apparatus.  The  majority of the Committee  hold the view  that,where an undue amount of interference is being caused by existing apparatus and plant, i.e. installed before the dateprescribed in the Regulations in respect of new apparatus,such apparatus  also  ought generally.  to  be subject  to regulations,, in  respect of suppression equipment,,  use, andmaintenance.   The question of whether or no  it wouldbe  right to compel the owner to defray the cost of correctingapparatus which he has purchased and was using beforethe enforcement of regulations is one of general  ethics or
of State policy which, in our opinion, only the legislaturecan decide.  The  Committee  made  no  recommendations on this issue  but  desire to draw attention to the following con-siderations:   (a)  It is most desirable that nothing proposed  in this        report and no subsequent discussion or  action in        connection with it should do other than encourage        the goodwill shown by most owners in voluntarily        correcting existing apparatus when they  are made        aware that it is causing interference.  (6)  There  must  undoubtedly be  some  cases  of inter-        ference from existing apparatus in which the owner        cannot reasonably  be expected to bear the cost       r of correction if the latter should be deemed essential.  (c)  Where interference is caused by failure to maintain -        apparatus in good condition, the Committee con-        sider that no hardship is involved in requiring an        owner to attend to this maintenance.  (d)  It should  be pointed  out  that  anyone  installing        apparatus that is likely to cause interference with        radio reception in its vicinity may be expected,        where reasonably possible, to equip such apparatus        with suppression devices  where such are  readily        available.  If the owner has not taken such steps        and it is ultimately found that undue interference        is caused, the Committee consider that it would        not be unreasonable  that the owner should bear        the cost of suppression,  subject to  suitable safe-        guards.17.                 CONCLUSIONS  Having given due  consideration to  all these questions,as regards both  existing and new plant  and apparatus,the Committee make the following recommendations as tothe appropriate  body for  issuing Regulations  and also as to the application of the  Regulations to existing aswell as to new apparatus.
18.RECOMMENDATIONS    The Electricity Commissioners should be given powers  to issue Regulations  to  suppress  interference  with radio  reception  caused by  both new  and  existing  electrical  appliances, plant, or machinery.,  .19.                                  .  .    The Commissioners would  not issue any  Regulations  in respect  of both  new  and existing apparatus or plant  until after they had been satisfied:      (i) that the  apparatus or plant  was  causing  undue          interference;    (ii) that in the case of new apparatus it could without          undue expense be altered in design or equipment          so as to bring interference down to a satisfactory          minimum;  and    (iii) that in the case of apparatus already installed the          interference  caused could  not be more  easily          eliminated  by reasonable  alteration of the receiv-          ing apparatus.  20.    The Electricity Commissioners should also&quot; have powers  to make regulations  as to the use of any  electric appliances  (both new and existing) which may cause interference with  radio reception, including requirements as to the proper  maintenance of all such appliances.  21.    The Commissioners should have power to require any  scheduled  apparatus sold after dates  to be stated  in the  Regulations to bear a prescribed  distinguishing Mark as  a guarantee that it  complied with  the Regulations.    This  should, of course, apply to imported as  well as to British-  made apparatus. 22.  -  AIL interested  parties  should  have an  opportunity of applying for the issue or amendment of Regulations and
of being heard before the Commissioners take action inregard to any specific apparatus.23 i  The Regulations  in respect of the  various. classes of apparatus  should either  define  the  permissible limit of interference  (as mentioned in paragraph 2), or, in parti-cular cases, schedule -the  method which could be used toprevent interference.24.  The Commissioners should also have powers to amend the  Regulations from time to time in order that progressin the branches of the electrical industry affected maybe fostered.25.  The Commissioners should also have  powers to hear and allow or  disallow appeals against the application  of theRegulations in particular cases.26.   The Commissioners should be empowered to hold anyInquiries and  institute  such research  as they may  con-sider necessary for the purpose of carrying out the duties to be imposed upon them.27.   The Commissioners may find it desirable to  have art Advisory  Committee,  representative  of  the principal organizations concerned,  to advise them on technical and other matters  arising out of their  duties under these proposals. 28.  .                   -   The Post Office  should have powers  to  enforce  the application  of  the  Regulations, subject to appeal to the; Commissioners..........         .
29.                  .......  Although the Committee consider that  any recommen-dation as to meeting the cost of suppressing interferencefrom  existing apparatus is  outside their province, never-theless they recommend that where the Post Office ascertain,after  complaints have  been received,  that undue inter-f erence is being caused to a substantial number of broadcastreceivers by any equipment installed before the prescribeddate (referred to in paragraph 21) and of a type scheduledin the Regulations, provision should be made which wouldenable the  Commissioners  to  require  such apparatus tobe  rendered interference-free  within such  time  as  may appear to them-reasonable in respect of  each particulartype of apparatus,  having regard to all the  circumstancesof the case.30.  All costs incurred  by the  Commissioners in preparingand issuing the Regulations, and in carrying out any duties which may  be imposed. upon them, and all costs of thePost Office in investigating complaints  and enforcing theRegulations, should be defrayed out of the quota of the wireless Receiving Licence Fees which the  Post Officeretain.31.  The Committee consider that where some  appropriate body, other  than the Electricity Commissioners, already have  powers to require the  suppression  of interference(as exercised by the  Ministry  of Transport in connectionwith trolley-buses) no alteration  of procedure is necessary,provided  these powers are  adequate.  The  Committeewish to emphasize, however, that, subject to proper safe-guards, adequate powers should  be  given to some appro-priate body  to  issue Regulations for the  suppression of interference wherever it occurs.
                     APPENDIX I              Constitution of Committee                The President (ex-ofhcio).C. C. Paterson, O.B.E. (Chairman)Lieut.-Col. A. G. Lee, O.B.E., MX.  (Vice-Chairman)  ...J. M. Kennedy, O.B.E.F. W. Purse  . .    ......L. B. Turner, M.A. ....              Body.Air Ministrynominated by  the  Council.Association of Consulting EngineersAssociation  of   Supervising  Elec-  trical Engineers&apos;   . .British Broadcasting Corporation . .British Electrical and Allied Indus-  tries Research AssociationBritish Electrical and Allied Manu-  facturers&apos; AssociationCentral Electricity board electricity commissioner.R.A. Interference Sub-CommitteeElectrical Contractors&apos; Association .General Post Office  . .Incorporated  Association  of  Elec- . trie Power CompaniesIncorporated  Municipal  Electrical  AssociationInternational       Electrotechnical  Commission  -    . .London  Electricity  Supply  Asso-  ciation     .....    Representative.Capt. A. K. Toulmin-  Smith, B.A.Sir Arthur PreeceJ. MunroSir Noel AshbridgeE. B. WedmoreC. Rodgers, O.B.E.Johnstone WrightJ. M.  Kennedy,  O.B.E.A. H. BennettH. Willoughby EllisCol.  A.  S.  Angwin,  D.S.O.,      M.C.,  B.Sc(Eng.)J. M. Donaldson,  M.C.Major E. A, Barker,  M.C.P. GoodR. S. Downe
Municipal  Tramways  and  Trans-  port Association   . .National Physical LaboratoryProvincial  Electric Supply Associa-  tion ....Radio Manufacturers&apos; Association . .Radio Society of Great BritainRailway Companies&apos; AssociationC. O. SilversF.   M.   Colebrook,  B.Sc.Society  of  Motor  Manufacturers  and TradersTramways,   Light  Railways  and  Transport AssociationWireless  Retailers&apos;  Association  of  Great Britain and Northern Ire-  land       ..     ..      ...  T. A. Pond.  J. Joseph.  J. ClarricoatsJ&quot; A. F. BoundI H. JonesA. T. PriddleP. M. HuntA. E. BetambeauTechnical Secretariat: F. W. Endicott (British Broadcasting    Corporation), W. D. Owen (Electrical Research Associa-    tion),  G. A.  Struthers  (General  Post Office), and    H. Wallis (Institution of Electrical Engineers).                     APPENDIX II   Investigations carried  out and Work in HandSub-Committees.  At the first meeting of the Main Committee on Inter-ference in June,  1933, it became evident that information would have to be collected  as to the types of apparatuswhich formed the chief sources  of  interference, the best methods of reducing interference on the several  types, andthe  cost  of  such methods.   Four  Sub-Committees were accordingly set up to deal with the following matters:  Sub-Committee A:  Domestic  apparatus,  including -ie-                     frigerators,  fans,  vacuum cleaners-,                     etc.
   Sub-Committee B: Larger   electric  plant,  including                     generators,  motors,  lifts,  mercury                     rectifiers, etc.   Sub-Committee C: Traction,   including  trolley-buses,                     tramways, and electric railways.   Sub-Committee D: Automobiles and aircraft.   A further Sub-Committee (E) was  subsequently set upto report on the effectiveness  of the  means (and the costof such  means) of  dealing with  interference apart fromsuppression at the source.   The Sub-Committees reported that methods were knownwhich could be  applied to the reduction of most forms of radio interference, and that the cost of such methods was,in general, but a small percentage of the cost of the inter-fering apparatus itself.   The above-mentioned Sub-Committees referred  to  theBritish Electrical and Allied  Industries Research Asso-ciation and to the General  Post  Office a number  of investigations relating to the question of the suppression of interference due to:      (a) Trolley-buses     [b) Electric lifts     (c)  Mercury-arc rectifiers     (d) Ignition systems.The  E.R.A. and the G.P.O. prepared  a number  of reportsbased on their investigations,, and the memoranda referringthereto have been  circulated  to  the appropriate Com-mittees and to  the other interests concerned.  A list ofsuch Reports is  given at the end of this Appendix.  There has been a very gratifying amount of co-operationamongst the various branches of the industry concerned,notably the British Broadcasting Corporation, the general post Office,  the  Electrical  Research   Association,  theB.E.A.M.A., and the various -supply authorities and trans-port undertakings.
British Standard Specifications.  On the conclusion of the work of the I.E.E. Sub-Com-mittee it was decided by the I.E.E. Main Committee that appropriate standard  specifications  should be  prepareddealing with  the  components  required for  suppressiondevices, the standardization of a suitable measuring instru-ment for radio  interference, and the defining of a Markfor use in &quot; Radio-Interference-Free &quot; apparatus.   At their request the British Standards Institution set up appropriatecommittees and the following  specifications  have  beenissued or are now in course of preparation: -   (1) B.S.S.  No. 613-1935, for Components  for RadiorInterference Suppression Devices, was issued in June,  1935.This Specification  gives the standard  ratings for generalcomponents (condensers, resistors, and inductors or chokes)used in making up suppression devices for use with machines and appliances operated from supply mains of voltages notexceeding 500  (excluding  traction equipment).  various ways of arranging  such components  are described in an appendix, and  a  further Appendix  gives  some generalindications of value of components which have been foundsatisfactory in practice.   Owing  to the fact that there is a considerable  disparityin the amount of suppression required on machines of thesame type, but of different manufacture, in order to reducethe interference to  reasonable dimensions, it was not found possible in this  Specification to recommend definite valuesfor  components which  would be suitable in all  cases  foreach particular  item, and some latitude in the choice  ofsuch components had to be given; a range of componentsis therefore given in the Specification in respect of each item.   (2) A Specification is  in course of preparation  for  ameasuring instrument  which  will  be suitable for themeasurement of  interfering   voltages.  This  Specifica-tion will  describe the characteristics and  performancerequirements  as  recommended  by  the  Special, Inter-national  Committee  on  Radio Interference  (C.I.S.P.R.)and will also give detailed design particulars of a portable
 measuring  set of convenient size and weight  for use  if required at works.   This testing set will enable manufacturers  to ascertain what  values  of  components  should be used  in order to reduce the  amount of interference to prescribed  limits and thus enable  the apparatus  to  qualify for the &quot; Radio- Interference-Free &quot; Mark.   In certain- types  of interference  the testing set  may not be applicable and it  will then be necessary to specify actual values of the components to be used for suppression.   (3) Specifications  are  also in hand for dealing  with interference due to: -     (a) Trolley-buses and tramways     (b) Neon signs    - (c) Ignition systems     (d) Electric lifts.   In the  case of  (b)  and  (d)  these Specifications will be issued as Appendices to the Main Specifications dealing with the construction and operation of these two items.   (4) A further Specification  will be put in hand as  soon as the necessary information is  available,  setting out for the  various classes  of apparatus the  permissible limits of interference which must not be exceeded in order to qualify for the  Mark, and a definition of the &quot; Radio- Interference-Free &quot; Mark.   It is  understood that the G.P.O. are arranging to carry- out  further tests on apparatus of various makes and to collect the necessary data in  order to complete  the above work.   Through  the co-operation of manufacturers  and retailers a number of machines have  already been tested in. the G.P.O. and E.R.A. laboratories, but, owing to the magnitude  of the task, manufacturers  are being invited to-co-operate  in  this&apos; work by permitting the  necessaryinvestigations to  be carried out at their works.International  Electrotechnical Commission.  . From the outset it appeared necessary in  the interests of export trade to reach international agreement on the
desirable degree of suppression and the method of measure-ment of interference,  and,  with this end in  view, to co-operate with  other  countries in arriving  at  some agreedstandard of the principles to be adopted in the measure-ment of interference and  of the protection which it wouldbe necessary to give to listeners in order that satisfactory-reception of broadcast programmes might be possible.  An - International Special Committee on Radio Inter-ference (C.I.S.P.R.)  was  therefore set  up  by the I.E.C.,and the first meeting was held in Paris in June, 1934.This was followed by meetings in Berlin and London.  The first practical step  taken  was to specify the require-ments of measuring equipment which would be suitablefor the measurement of interfering voltages.  The apparatusin  use in the  various countries  was  compared.  Aftervarious types of noise as heard on  a loud-speaker  weremeasured on  a low-frequency measuring instrument, theC.I.S.P.R. specified the requirements  of such an instru-ment  which would give readings corresponding  to  theannoyance heard on a loud-speaker independently of the type of noise (continuous, impulsive, etc.)  The International Committee  further  recommended that,with a field strength of programme transmission of 1 mV/mmodulated at 80 per cent, the level of  disturbance shouldbe at least 40 decibels below the peak Values of the pro-gramme transmission.  The next step to  be taken was to determine the maxi-mum interfering voltage  which  could be tolerated at theterminals of a machine or appliance.  As  the signal/interference ratio observed  on receivingapparatus depends on:     (i)  the radio-electric field of the  wave received  and        on the wavelength;   (ii)  the coupling  factor between the interfering source        and the receiving apparatus;  (iii)  the interfering  voltage  created  by the  electrical        machine or appliance;a large number of tests were therefore carried out in  this
country and elsewhere on the effective height of listeners&apos;aerials; the attenuation between the mains and the listenersaerial system; and the values of the interfering voltagesfrom machines as measured at the terminals of the machines and also at the aerial-earth terminals of broadcast receivers.As a  result of these tests and after consideration of theeconomic aspects of the problems involved, the technical experts  appointed by the  G.I.S.P.R.   decided at their meeting in London in  May, 1936, to  recommend  to thefull International  Committee that the values of the per-missible interfering voltage  at the terminals  of machinesshould be  reduced by progressive steps, values for longand  medium waves being stated  for immediate applica-tion, further lower values being recommended for adoptionafter  a period of two years, and finally a common value for medium and long waves which it is  desirable to adoptas early  as possible in order to protect the  largest  per-centage of listeners consistent with the limitations imposed by technical and economic considerations.  The values to be adopted for Great Britain as  a resultof the above international work still remain to be decided.                  List  of E.R.A. ReportsM/T27: &quot; Simple  Apparatus for Comparative Observa-           tions  of  Radio  Interference Produced  by           Electrical Appliances.&quot;M/T28:-S. WHITEHEAD and  W.  NETHERCOT:  &quot;The           Suppression  of  Short-Wave  Radiations from           Automobile Ignition Systems.&quot;M/T29: S. WHITEHEAD and  L. H.  DANIEL:  &quot; The Sup-           pression of Broadcast Interference from Trolley           Buses.&quot;M/T30: &quot; Some Considerations in the Measurement and           Suppression of Radio Interference.&quot;M/T39: S. WHITEHEAD and L.  H. DANIEL: &quot; The magnitude-           tude  of  the Radio-Frequency   Disturbance           from Trolley Buses, and the Use of Condensers           and other Devices in its Suppression.&quot;
M/T42: S. WHITEHEAD and  L.  H, DANIEL: &quot;The  Sup-           pression of Broadcast Interference from Electric           Lifts.&quot;M/T44: W. NETHERCOT and W. D. OLIPHANT: .&quot; The           Properties and  Performance  of  the  E.R.A.           Short-Wave   Receiver   for   Field-Strength           Measurements.&quot;M/T45: S. WHITEHEAD  and L.  H.  DANIEL:  &quot;Methods           of Measurement of Radio Interference.&quot;       List of G.P.O. Documents and PublicationsPost Office Electrical Engineers&apos; Journal.  P. L. BARKER &quot;and A. H.  MUMFORD: &quot; A Field-Strength    Measuring Set using Thermal Agitation  Noise as the    Calibrating Source,&quot; 1935-36, vol. 28, p. 40.  A. C. WARREN: &quot; Broadcast Interference Investigation,    Post Office Radio Service,&quot; 1935-36, vol. 28, p. 23.Institution of Post Office Electrical Engineers.&apos;   .  .  A. S. ANGWIN: Paper No. 137: &quot;Interference with Wire-    less Reception  arising from the Operation of Electrical    Plant,&quot; 1932.Telephone and Telegraph Journal.  A.  S. ANGWIN:  &quot;Electrical  Interference  with Broad-    casting,&quot; 1933, vol. 19,  p. 200.P.0. Radio Branch, Interim Report.  &quot; Interference  with Wireless  Broadcast Reception  by    Tramway and Trolley-Bus Systems,&quot; November,  1935.Post Office Printed Pamphlets.  ,:&quot; Suppression of  Radio Interference.&quot;  &quot; Good Wireless  Reception!&quot;  &quot; Electrical Interference.&quot;P.O. Radio Reports.  (Not printed for publication.)  No. 178.  &quot; The  Investigation of Interference by  Elec-              tric  Lifts with Broadcast  Reception.&quot;
 No. 179.  &quot; The Investigation of Interference by High-            Frequency Electrical Therapeutical Appaira-            tus with Broadcast Reception.&quot; No. 192.  &quot; The Investigation of Interference by Mercury-            Arc Rectifiers with Broadcast Reception.&quot; No. 201.  &quot; Measurements of  Impedance of a  Heavy-            current H.F.  Choke at  Broadcasting Fre-            quencies.&quot; No. 202.  &quot; The . Further Investigation  of Interference            by  Electric  Trolley-Bus  Systems  with            Broadcast Reception.&quot; No. 216.  &quot; Further Measurements  on H.F. Choke Coils            for  the  prevention   of  Interference by            Trolley-Buses with Broadcasting.&quot; No. 255.  &quot; Measurement of the Interference from the          &quot;  Portishead-Bridgwater 132 kV Overhead            Power Line.&quot; No. 277.  &quot; Some Considerations relating to the Measure-            ment of Radio Interfering Effects.&quot; No. 295.  &quot; Measurement of the Impedance at  Radio            Frequencies  of  Post  Office  Units,   Con-            denser.&quot; No. 300.  &quot; Further  Considerations   relating  to  the            Measurement of  Radio  Interfering Effects.&quot; No. 318.  &quot; Interference  with  Broadcast  Reception            caused  by  a Steel-Tank  Grid-controlled            Mercury-Arc Rectifier.&quot; No. 321.  &quot;Theoretical and Practical Comparison of            High-  and  Low-Frequency  Methods of            Measurement of Radio  Interference.&quot;No. 332.  &quot; Comparison of the German Standard Radio-            Interference Measuring Equipment and the            British Post Office Portable Measuring Set.&quot;No. 346.  &quot;Prevention  of   Interference b)&apos; Electro-            Medical Apparatus with Broadcast Recep-           tion.&quot;
  W2. 187A. &quot; Comparison  of  the  E.R.A.  and  G.P.O.              Radio-Interference Measuring Sets.&quot;Journal of the Institution of Electrical Engineers.  A.  MORRIS:  &quot; Interference  of Electrical Plant with    Reception  of Radio  Broadcasting,&quot;   1934,  vol.  74,    p. 245.Wireless World.  A. MORRIS: &quot; Electrical  Interference.  The Problem of    a Definition,&quot; 1934, vol. 35, p. 59.  A. MORRIS:  &quot; The  Technique  of  Radio Interference,&quot;    1934, vol. 35, p. 445.Electrical Power Engineer.  J. NEALE: &quot; Broadcast  Interference,&quot;   1935,  vol.  17,    p. 510.Electrician.  &quot; Trolleybuses- Methods of  suppressing  Radio  Inter-    ference,&quot; 1936, vol. 116, p.  482.July, 1936.P. F. ROWELL,    Secretary, I.E.E.
PRINTED  BY  UNWIN BROTHERS LTD.,LONDON AND  WOKING, AND published by THE  INSTITUTION  OF  ELECTRICALENGINEERS,  SAVOY  PLACE, VICTORIA   EMBANKMENT, LONDON, W.C.2.

</content>
</cab>
