<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 106-151</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
81(THIS  DOCUMENT IS  THE  PROPERTY OP HIS  BRITANNIC  MAJESTY&apos;S  GOVERNMENT)SECRET.               CABINET.                   Copy No. Lfi fCP.108(37).          AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS - HOUSEHOLDERS&apos; HANDBOOK.                Memorandum by the  Home  Secretary.       1.    I circulate  herewith, for  the  approval  of the  Cabinet,  the  Handbook which the Air Raid Precautions Department have  prepared for issue to  members of  the general public, setting out  the  information  which  they should have to enable  them to provide  such protection  in their homes as may be possible.            The issue  of this Handbook should be free and  distribution  should be made to every  householder  in Great Britain on  a basis  similar  to that  of the Highway Code.    Additional copies would be  obtainable at any time at the price  of Id.  at  all Post Offices.       2.    The Department have been engaged for the best  part of  twelve .  months in the  compilation of the text  and the layout of the  book.     Assistance  has  been given by a  firm of publicity agents  and,  in  addition, a  wide range of outside people  has been consulted.  A number of Ministers  have also been good enough  to give the benefit  of their advice  to the Air Raid Precautions Department.    In fact,  every step has been  taken that is possible  to  ensure that the book,  while  containing the essential infox-mation which  the general public  i*equire, is presented  in the best forai possible,  having  regard to  its  purport and  its,  message.       The Ti*easux*y have been consulted at evex*y stage and have seen  a dx*aft  of this  covex*ing note.       3.    At the x^request of the Treasury I wish to put before  my Colleagues the question of the inclusion of advertisements.  There  is space on the  cover for two  advertisements at least, and  the  Treasury inform  me they are satisfied that a  revenue of
 5,000 net could be obtained from these two pages alone.          Care would of course be exercised in the selection of firmsfor the pux&apos;pose;  but it is thought that no objection could be&quot;taken to the inclusion of advertisements by firms of such  standingas H.M.V. and Bovril, both of whom are, in fact, known to  be willing to pay at the rate mentioned above for these pages.Altex-natively, there is the possibility of using the space foradvex*tisements by Govex*nment Depax-allotments such as the Post  office or by the Milk Marketing Board, to be paid for at the market rateout of their authorised gx*ants fox&apos; publicity.     4.   I am disposed to recommend that, with a view to1&apos;educing the cost of the Handbook as fax* as possible, the  px*incipleof inserting advertisements should be approved, but that in thefirst place efforts should be made to use the space foradvertisements of this latter kind;  but that if the whole spacecannot be disposed of at a fair x*ate in this way, offex*s shouldbe accepted from commercial firms oxJ other bodies of first classreputation.          It is estimated that the cost of production anddistribution would be between  30,000 and  35,000, reducible by,say,  5,000 if advex-t isements sire accepted.     5.   Owing to the length of  time which must be allowed for  thepx4inting of the enoxraous number of copies required (say 14 millions),it would, in any case, be impossible fox- the issue of the  book totake place before July, and fox* vax*ious reasons it might bedesirable to postpone its issue until after the summer holidays.If my Colleagues approve, I should be glad to have discretion asto the actual time.   I would, of coux*se, give them inform*mation  ofthe date which I would select.          The very greatest impox&apos;tance is attached to the  issueof this Handbook, not only because of its value in instx&apos;ucting thepublic in the simple measures which they can take fox* their ownsafety, but as a means also of awakening attention to this most
87vital and important part of our National Defence Schemes.   I trust that my Colleagues will agree with me that the Handbook in itspresent form will fulfil the purpose for which it is required.                                          J. S.31st March, 1937,
HOME OFFICE THE PROTECTION   OF  YOUR  HOMEAGAINST  AIR  RAIDS: In the protection of your homelies the security of your country &quot;KEEP THIS BOOK CAREFULLY
                                                       89      Why  this  book  has         been  sent  to  you in the factory precautions are taken against unexpected accident.Cinemas and theatres are built so as to guard against the dangers of fire.  The health  of the community is safeguarded by pre-cautions against the spread of epidemics.  We have a great recordin our country for common-sense, for the  kind of forethoughtthat reduces the ordinary risks of life to a minimum.  The house-holder is now called upon to take precautions against a possibilitywe all hope will never arise.  It  would be folly to know of theexistence of such a possibility, however remote, without acknow-ledging the need for precautions against it.The Government is taking precautions against air raids and, withthe help of Local Authorities everywhere, is organising measuresto reduce the effects as far as possible.  But the householdermust play his part.  This book is being sent to you in the con-confident belief that you will regard it as your duty to read it, to keep it by you, and to act  upon it in any premises for which you areresponsible ; so that if your home or place of business were everin danger of being attacked from the air, you would know whatto do for your own safety and the safety of those who depend upon you.If ever we are exposed to hostile  air attack,  we must look to the combination of active defence and civil air raid precautions to defeat the aims of the enemy.  There is a duty on every citizento bear his part in these civil precautions, but those who for any reason cannot take them for themselves need not- be worried.They will not be overlooked.                                (Signed)
CONTENTSSECTION   1SECT-TON..  section   3SECTTOSECTION- 5                                  pageTHINGS TO DO  NOW I. Respirators........................ 52. The danger of incendiary bombs...... 63. How to choose a refuge-room........ 74. Things to get for your refuge-room ... 95. If you have no spare room...........10THINGS TO DO IF THERE  SHOULD EVER BE  A WAR I. How to prepare your refuge-room    making it safe from gas...............122. How to prepare your refuge-room    against the effect of explosive bombs..&apos;. 16 3. Precautions against fire..............184. Things to have in your refuge-room... 195. Essential First Aid  supplies...........22THINGS TO DO IF AN  AIR RAID SHOULD COME I. What the head of the house should do. .242. What to do in your refuge-room.....263. What to do if the house is damaged.. .274. How to deal with an outbreak of fire. .285. How to avoid  mustard gas burns......296. What to do when out of doors.......307. Remember others caught out of doors.30EXTRA PRECAUTIONS I. Extra precautions against gas.........322. Extra precautions against bombs......35WHAT TO DO IF  ANYONE IS HURTFirst Aid hints........................38
THINGS  TO  DO   now on  board  ship,  both  crew  and passengers  are  instructed  whereto go and  what to do, not  whendanger threatens, but beforehand;The captain considers it a matterof ordinary routine and everydayprecaution  that  everything  is in readiness for a shipwreck which hehopes will  never  happen.  If thehead  of  the house will  considerhimself  as  &quot;. the captain  of theship &quot; and.put these air raid pre-cautions into effect,  the principalobject of this book will have been achieved.
 IB   air raids ever came to this country every home should havea place specially prepared where the whole household could takerefuge in greater safety.  It would be essential, too, that everyhouseholder, or head of a family or business, should know how to lessen the dangers of high explosive bombs, incendiary bombs,and poison gas.The most sensible precaution you can take against air raids is to look round your home now, and choose the place that offers  thebest security against these risks.  If you are responsible for  the safety and welfare of others, either as the head of a business or thekeeper of an hotel or lodging house or shop, or as a landlord oftenements, you should consider places of refuge for those whowould be on your premises.The best place will be one that you can (A) seal against gas and(B) strengthen in such a way as to make it as safe as possible fromthe explosion caused by a bursting bomb.Sealing against gas means nothing  more than stopping the entry of air from outside.  Gas can only  enter a room if it is carried inby draughts  or  currents of air.  This is true of any gas.   Gasmay be dangerous,  but proper precautions can overcome  thedanger.The precautions recommended in  this book can be adopted byalmost everyone and will serve for  private houses,  flats,  tene-ments and small business premises of every kind.  The essentialthings can be done by any householder  or citizen at very littlecost.Find out the local air raid organisation in your district, and keepyourself familiar with the  precautions that are being devised.For information apply to the local  Council Offices.If you have no men folk in your house, and feel you want advice,do not hesitate  to ask a neighbour or a  relative, or  an air raidwarden,  to  help you.   Don&apos;t neglect to take  precautions justbecause you are not sure of the right thing to do.             Most important  of all, see  that all grown-ups  are             familiar with the contents of this book and know of             the arrangements you are making for their safety.
9                    RESPIRATORSThe Government is making arrangements to provide respiratorsfree to  the civilian  population.  You should regard  yourrespirator as your second line of defence and  the  precautionsadvised in this book as your first.What a respirator is    A respirator, if properly put on, protects the eyes,  nose,mouth and lungs ; and ensures a supply of pure air for breathing,by means of filters which are able to absorb any gas known to be capable of being used in war.   The facepiece, the edges of whichfit closely round the face, prevents any air from getting inside therespirator except that which passes through the filters.  It  is held in position by adjustable straps behind the head. Once thesestraps have been properly adjusted, the respirator, if needed, canbe put on instantly.How a respirator works    A respirator consists of a rubber facepiece with a transparentwindow, and a container which holds the gas filters.  There aretwo filters, one of which consists of specially prepared charcoal,and the other of pads of specially prepared material.  The illus-tration shows the type of respirator which has been designed foryou by  Government  experts. Although  simple to look  at,exhaustive tests have  shown it to be highly efficient.  But this type of respirator does not afford  protection against ordinary                 THE CIVILIAN RESPIRATORPutting it on           Adjusting the head straps
domestic coal gas :  carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide havedifferent physical properties from those of war gases.Why a respirator alone is not enough     Your refuge-room is your first line of defence because arespirator cannot protect the other parts of your body fromdangerous  liquids, such as  &quot; mustard gas.&quot;  These  liquid&quot; gases &quot; need the most rigorous precautions, because they con-tinue to be dangerous long after they have been dropped.  Alsothey affect the skin of parts  of the body not protected by therespirator.  Remember, too,  that by staying in a refuge-roomyou have protection against flying splinters and debris, as well as additional protection against gas.Your respirator will not be issued unless it becomes necessary,but will  be carefully  stored  by the Government in readiness.Arrangements will, however, be made to enable you to try arespirator on, and to get used to wearing it, if you  want to.Children can wear respirators.  For those too  young to wearthem a special means  of protection will be provided.   A respi-rator is not uncomfortable to wear, and you can see and hear andspeak when wearing it.               INCENDIARY  BOMBSIncendiary bombs are usually  small and can thus be used in greatnumbers.   So many fires may be caused that unless each istackled before it spreads a great deal of damage may be done.So pay great attention to fire precautions (see Section 2, page 18).Find out what emergency fire brigade arrangements your localCouncil is making, and where the nearest auxiliary fire station orfire post will be.Also be ready to tackle small fires yourself (see Section 3, page 28).The  risk  of fire exists every day, and you will find it valuable to read  the  Home Office pamphlet &quot; Fire Protection: Hints forHouseholders,&quot; which is  published by H.M. Stationery Office,price 3D.  (&quot;$\d. post free ;  or through any bookseller).Page 6
    HOW  TO  CHOOSE  A REFUGE-ROOM Almost any room will serve as a refuge-room if it can be made more or less air-tight, if it is soundly constructed, and if it is easy to reach and to get out of.   A room that faces a building or blank wall is better than one that is exposed with windows facing several ways.  Otherwise choose, if you can, a room that looks out over a garden or on to soft ground, rather than one that faces a street or has a hard ground surface outside.  The stronger the walls, floor, and ceiling are, the better.  Brick partition walls are better than                         plaster, a concrete ceiling is better                         than a wooden one.   A  corridor will                         form a very good refuge-room if it                         can be CLOSED at both ends.                         THE BEST POSITION FOR A                                               REFUGE-ROOM                             A cellar or basement is the best                         place for  a refuge-room provided  it                         can be made gas-proof and provided                         there is no  likelihood  of  its being                         flooded by a neighbouring river that                         may BURST its  BANKS or by a BURST                         water-main.  If you have  any DOUBT                         about this ask  for advice from your                         local Council Offices.                         If no CELLAR or basement is available,                         you should make your REFUGE-room on                         the ground floor if possible ; but any                         floor BELOW the TOP FLOOR will do.  Top                         floors and attics should be avoided as                         they usually  have not sufficient pro-                         tection  overhead from   small  in-ln a house with only two floors  cendiary bombs.  These small bombs and without a cellar, choose a     ^__. ,   c     -r-  .room on the ground floor so that  ARE CAPABLE of PIERCING the roof,  but you have protection overhead   are unlikely to get BELOW the top floor.A cellar or basement is the best position for a refuge-room if itcan be made gas-tight
In a two-storeyed terrace housechoose a back room on  theground floor. The flanking wallswill protect you from the blastof a bursting bomb                         In flats or tenement  houses, either                         each household  can  make its  own                         arrangements or  communal refuges                         can be made.  It is, however, im-                         portant that top-floor dwellers should                         find   accommodation  downstairs.                         They might share a refuge-room, or                         they might make arrangements  to                         occupy  the  basement.   But   the                         basement  premises will have to  be                         prepared as refuges in the same way                         as ordinary rooms, according to the                         instructions given in this book.                         It is  suggested that in any flat,  or                         tenement  house,  or house  occupied                         by more than one family, representa-tives  be chosen and formed into a Protection Committee todecide upon the most suitable rooms and to prepare them asrefuge-rooms if it should ever be necessary for the safety of all.Even  though your household occupies one room only, many of the precautions recommended in the book can still be carried out, andwill help to protect you.  So do what you can.HOW LARGE SHOULD A REFUGE-ROOM BE ?    Although an actual raid may be over in a few minutes it mightbe necessary to stay in your refuge-room for some time,  evenperhaps for several hours, until the gas in the  neighbourhood hasbeen cleared away.  You should therefore know how many personscan remain safely in one room without suffering any ill effects.For rooms of normal height (8 or 9 feet) an allowance of 20 square feet of floor area for each person will enable those persons toremain in the room with complete safety for a continuous periodof twelve hours without ventilation.           A room 10 ft. x 10 ft. will hold           A room 15 ft. x 10 ft. will holdA room 20 ft. X15 ft.          5 persons.          7 persons.will hold 15 persons JA room 30 ft. X15 ft. will hold 22 persons.
                                                     9 3         GET THESE THINGS FOR THE                   REFUGE-ROOM These are some of the things that will be useful in your refuge- room.  Keep them in mind and begin collecting those things you haven&apos;t got, one by one.  Put them in a box, or in a drawer, in the room you choose as your refuge-room. Things you  probably possess already             Candles and matches.             Hammer and nails.             Pieces of string.             Old newspaper and brown paper.             Some clean rags.             Needles, cotton, and thread.             Scissors. Things to collect             An electric torch  or, better, a hurricane lamp or               candle lamp.             Pieces of&quot; Cellophane &quot; and some cellulose varnish               (e.g.   Durofix)  to   cover the windows  (See               page 16.)             Gummed paper.             Adhesive tape.             A few tins or jars with air-tight lids for storing food.             At least one  pair of non-inflammable  dark-lens               glasses.             A bottle of disinfectant.             A small  First Aid Box containing :                a few bandages,               small packages of boracic lint,               cotton wool,               some safety-pins,               a second pair of scissors,               a bottle of smelling salts,               sal volatile.           .  See also page 22.A list of additional things to get into your refuge-room,  if theemergency ever comes, is given further on, Section 2, page 20.
If you have a wireless set or receiver it would be useful to have itin the refuge-room so that you could hear the news and pass thetime away.  Make sure  (if your set is worked off the electricmains) that you have a plug for it in your refuge-room and pre-pare in advance the leads for the  aerial and earth if these arerequired.WHAT  TO  DO  IF  YOU  CANNOTSET  ASIDE  A  ROOM  especially for A  REFUGE-ROOMIt does not matter if you have no surplus room to set aside, inwar-time, as a refuge-room.  Even if you have only one room you can make it a place of greater safety even if you adopt only some of the suggestions contained in this book.   Do not think you have no protection.  Any room with four good walls is saferthan being out in the open, so don&apos;t run out into the street to findbetter shelter if ever you get warning of an air raid.  Your bestprotection is in your own home.Plan to stay in  one room in your dwelling, however small, andthink how  you can seal it against draughts.  If the room is reasonably well built this should not be too difficult.  You will find out how to do it in the next Section.  Many of the thingsyou would need,  too,  are common articles  which often pass through your hands.  If you will set your mind to it and collectthem, and keep them by you, you  can do so without  spendingmoney.   If possible, do not choose a room where a fire has to bekept burning, like a kitchen.  A bedroom would be suitable ifit is not on the top floor.  The window need not be sealed upuntil you get the air raid warning.  It can be done in a minuteor two with wedges and adhesive tape, or strong paper and paste.
The Government will tell you when,if ever, you  should take  the  pre-cautions recommended in this section.There  is no immediate need to doany of these  things now,  but  readthrough these notes carefully, bear-ing in  mind that they are intendedto  be  nothing more  than notes.Think  them  out, and see how  toapply  them  to  your  own home.You will know, then, more exactly7ohat to do if there should ever bea war.  Having faced the problembefore  danger threatens you  willhave your plans made, and be readyto carry them out  quickly if  everthere is need.
I i^ever you receive warning that war threatens there are these four things to do at onceI Prepare and equip your refuge-room.1 Make preparation for darkening the house at night.  All windows, skylights, glased doors must be com-  pletely obscured.  Outside lights, garden and porch  lights must not be used.  If they are electric take the  bulbs out altogether.3 Clear the loft, attic, top floor, of inflammable stuff  that can be moved, to lessen the risk of fire should an  incendiary bomb penetrate the roof.  If the floor is  boarded, you can make the house safer against fire by  spreading 2 inches of sand over this floor.4 If you live in a large town, children, invalids, elderly  members of the household, and pets, should be sent to  relatives or friends in the country, if it is possible.HOW TO  PREPARE  YOUR REFUGE-ROOM              Making  it  safe  from  gasGas  will not come into a room unless there are  draughts  orcurrents of air to carry it in, so any cracks or openings must  besealed up somehow.How to deal  with cracks in walis, floors, and  odd places     In old houses especially, windows and doors may shut badly.There may be chinks underneath the window sills on the inside.There may be  cracks in the  ceiling.   The illustration oppositeshows you the kind of thing to look for.Fill in all cracks and crevices with putty or a pulp made of soddennewspaper.  Paste paper over any cracks in the walls or ceiling.Page 12
Cracksto look forin an oldhouseFill in, or paste paper over, the cracks between the floor boards.If the floors are already covered with  linoleum or  an all-overcarpet, pay attention to any cracks or joins there may be.  Fill inall cracks round the skirting boards, and where pipes happen topass through the walls.  All trap-doors skylights and hatchesshould be sealed.All ventilators in the outside walls of the house (including thosebelow the floor level, should be stopped up with rags or paper.Any interior ventilators in  the room should be stopped up withrags or pasted over with thick paper.If there  is a fire-place, stuff the chimney  with paper, rags, orsacks. Do  not, of course, attempt to light a fire in the grate.Any cracks in  the fire-place, in the sides of the fire, or in thehearth, should also be sealed.Plug key-holes.  Plug  waste-pipes, or overflow pipes,  in anybasins or cisterns in your refuge-room.   If  you are doubtfulwhether a hole or a crack lets in air, play for safety, and seal it up.None of these things will reduce the usefulness of the room, for ordinary living purposes, provided you do  not light  a fire, or  ifthe fire can be put out quickly.
 How to seal up the windows     It is easy to seal windows so that draughts, or gas, cannot come in.  Wedge them firmly to keep them tighdy fixed in their frames.  Paste strips of paper all round the frames, wherever there is a crack.  Be cautious, and make a thorough job  of it. Broken panes should be boarded in, or have the holes pasted over. with strong paper.   This will not prevent the possibility of glass being broken by the blast of a bomb explosion, perhaps quite a long way away.  If possible, protect the glass from blast in one of the ways suggested on page 16. Window openings  should be further protected from inside by having stout  materials hung or fastened over them.  A blind, for instance,  if it is large enough, should be tacked down all round the window frame and sealed with adhesive tape. Curtains should be kept  hanging,  as  they help  to preventdraughts.  But Venetian blinds are no protection, and should be taken down if they get in the way of better precautions. Spare curtains, blankets or rugs should be taken to the refuge- room for re-sealing the window in case the glass is blown in. Keep the windows dark at night.  It is important to remember that no light must be allowed to show anywhere.  This is another reason  why hangings and curtains should be thick and  dark. Should only thin materials be available use them in more than one thickness. How to make the doors air-tight    Doors to the refuge-room which need not be used should be locked.  Paper should be pasted firmly all round the cracks and the key-hole plugged. (Hang the key on a nail inside the room, in case you want to open the door in an emergency.) Doors which  have to be opened and closed should be treated as follows to keep them gas-tight:  A piece of wood, padded with felt, should be nailed to the floorso that the door, when closed, presses tightly against it.   Takecare not to nail this piece of wood on the wrong side of the doorso that it cannot be opened.  Strips of felt may be nailed round
                                                        96How to seal up the door the inside of the door to exclude draughts.   Fix a blanket outside the door if the door opens inwards, or inside the door if the door opens outwards, by means of  strips of wood fixed as follows : The top of the blanket should be fixed to the  top of the door frame.  One side of the  blanket should be fastened down the- whole length of the  door frame, on the side where the hinges are, by means of a strip of wood nailed to the frame.   The other side of the blanket should be secured not more than two feet down so that a flap  is  left free through which  people may pass.  The blanket should be arranged so that at least 12 inches trails on the floor to stop air from blowing underneath it.   See illustration below.  If you adopt these precautions no gas should get into your refuge-room.  If the blanket is kept damp during  an air raid, it will  be even more gas-proof.
 HOW TO PREPARE  YOUR REFUGE-ROOM       Against the effect of explosive bombs There are three main types of bomb, an explosive bomb, an in- cendiary bomb,  a  gas  bomb.   Precautions  against fire  are described on page 18 and the way to deal with incendiary bombs is explained in Section 3, page 28, under the heading &quot; How to deal with an outbreak of fire.&quot;  How to protect yourself against gas has already been explained.  How to provide some protection against explosive bombs is dealt with here. The essential thing  is to protect  your  refuge-room  against  the shock of a bomb that may burst outside, and from  flying glass and splinters caused by the explosion. Protecting the windows     It is not easy to prevent the glass of closed windows being shattered by the blast of an explosion, perhaps quite a long way off.-  One simple method, which is remarkably effective if done properly, is to cover the inside of the glass with Cellophane the thin transparent wrapping used nowadays on cigarette packets and many other  articles.  These  wrappings  will do  for your windows, .so take them off carefully, smooth them flat, and keep them.  Larger sheets of Cellophane will be better if you can get them.  If you use small thin sheets from cigarette packets, and so on, stick on half a dozen thicknesses, and see that they are well overlapped over one another. These Cellophane sheets must be stuck tight on to the glass. Only a cellulose varnish will do this.  There  are several cheap cellulose  varnishes (such as Durofix) on the market. In addition to using Cellophane you can wedge a mattress in the window,  by bars of wood, or a heavy piece of furniture, which will give extra protection.  This  will also ensure that broken glass does not fly into the room. But it is better still to protect the  windows from outside with a wall of sandbags  or  earth, in  the way described on page 35.Even outside shutters or boarding may not prevent the glassbeing broken by the blast of an explosion. .
97Strengthening the room    If your refuge-room is on the ground floor or in the base-ment, you  can support the  ceiling with wooden  props  as anadditional protection.  The illustration shows a way of  doing this.  Stout posts are placed upright, supporting a horizontalbeam against the ceiling, and standing on a similar beam acrossthe floor.   Along the  floor  a stout plank will do instead of abeam. Across the ceiling a  plank is  not so good, and a  beamplaced on edge will be stronger than one placed flat.how to support a ceilingThe illus-trationbelowshows thedetail of how to fix the props -^ -j The smaller illustration shows how the    ^I^/^-^        posts are held in position at the top by       L-XTTT^V^     two blQCks Qf W0Qd  on the  ceiling              sJ^^     beam, and are  forced tight  by two         LJU         wedges  at  the  foot.  Do not drive         p-pr         these wedges  too violently,  otherwise         J             you mav 1^ ^ ceiling aud damage it.       jf3^^\J     If the floor of your refuge-room is solid,    t\\\*-_____         such as you might find in a basement, 1-* -1 you will not  need  a beam or  plankacross the whole floor, but only a piece of wood a foot or so longunder each  prop.
         PRECAUTIONS AGAINST FIRE     These are things that should be done the moment you getwarning that there may be an air attack and before you receivethe actual warning that an air raid is near.     I  Clear the top floor, loft, or attic of all inflammable       material,  paper,  bedding, litter, lumber, etc., to       lessen the danger of fire, and to prevent it from       spreading.  (It is always  inadvisable to keep  in-       flammable stuff in a loft or in a top room, so throw       away now everything you have no use for.)    &quot;2  Fill all spare buckets, jugs, basins with water and       keep them about the  house in get-at-able places.       Keep the bath full of water.     3  A box of dry sand, with a shovel, should be placed       at the top, and at the bottom,  of the stairs  for       putting out a fire caused by an incendiary bomb (see       page 28).     4  If the top floor, loft, or attic has a boarded floor,       and you can get some sand, spread over it a layer of       sand up to 2 inches thick.   (Do not try to put too       much.  Sand is heavy.)In an air raid the water-mains may be damaged and  the watersupply cut off:  in any case, domestic taps rarely give a very strong flow of water.  It is a great advantage, therefore, to havereceptacles filled with water and placed about the  house before an air raid begins.  They can be refilled quickly from the bath.A small bucket hand-pump will help to throw water on a fire from a distance without waste.Water is the best means of putting out a fire, but never  pourwater actually on an incendiary bomb, because it makes  it splutterand throw out molten fragments.Page 18
THINGS   TO  HAVE   INYOUR  REFUGE-ROOMA list of things to have in yourrefuge-room is given overleaf.  Butthere is one important point, aboutheating,  you ought to remember.An electric kettle is  useful if you have one, but dorCt burn a gas fireas it uses up air.  You can use agas ring for a  short  time if youlike, to boil water, but it is wiser to turn off the gas at the meter andto do without.If the weather  is really cold you may use an electric fire in yourrefuge-room for a while if you wish.But the air will remain much fresherif you can avoid artificial heatingof any kind. It is better to rely oncoats and blankets for  warmth.
Get these additional things into your refuge-room, as soon as the Government warns you.  -jThe list given in Section  i, page  9, is ofthings  to collect  for your refuge-room in  tadvance.  I  A roll-call list of all who should be present.    This applies particularly to office premises, or    if the refuge-room is to be shared by neigh-    bours.  2  Table and chairs.  3  Portable washhandrstand, or basin.  4  A screen, for privacy.  5  Chamber pots, toilet paper.  6  Washing things, soap, towels, sponges.  7  Disinfectant.  8  Plenty of water for drinking, washing, and for  .  damping the door blanket.  9  A food chest of some kind (air-tight  tins or    jars  will do)  as  a precaution against contact    with gas.10  Tinned food.11  Plates, cups, knives, forks, etc.12  Books, writing materials, cards, toys.13  A bucket or box of sand with a shovel, or    fire-extinguisher.14  A dark heavy curtain-hanging to obscure the    light from the window, unless the window is    already blocked up.15  Spare blankets  or rugs  for  re-sealing the    window if it should be blown in.16  Pots of paste for pasting paper over cracks and    window  panes.   Paste  can be  made from    flour and water boiled with a few cloves put    in to keep it fresh.    You will also need the following things which,    if you are using them in other parts of the    house, you should take into your refuge-room    when you hear the air raid warning.17  A mattress,  or  mattresses,  to  protect the    window or to lie on.18  Blankets,  eiderdowns, rugs and warm cover-    ings.19  The wireless  set, gramophone with  records.20  Additional cold food.

      ESSENTIAL FIRST AID  SUPPLIES    You should have, as suggested in the list on page n, a fewfirst aid supplies for your refuge-room. The list of articles belowis about right for a household of six persons all sheltering in oneroom, if you are able to get them as well.  For hints on how touse them, see Section 5, page 38.3 x i-oz. packets of boracic lint, for dressing wounds.3 x i-oz. packets of cotton wool, for pads on dressings.2 triangular bandages, for use as arm-slings or, when folded, asbandages.3 X1-in. roller bandages, for fingers.3 X2i-in. roller bandages, for head or limbs.3 X 3-in. roller bandages, for limbs or body.Some stout string or cord  for stopping an artery from bleeding.1 dozen small safety pins.1 pair of scissors.1 bottle of smelling salts.Iodine, or antiseptic.     MAKE IN  THE  SPACE   BELOW A  LIST        of any other  things which occur to you as        worth getting for your own  refuge-room
SECTION    3THINGS   TO   DOIF  AN   AIR   RAIDSHOULD   COME This section describes the ACTIONyou would need to take during  awar, as soon as you received warn-ing of the approach of hostile air-craft.   Only at such a time will the value of the previous sectionsbecome fully apparent. The head of the house takes com-mand, arid because everyone in the household knows what to do and where  to go, there is no indecisionand no panic.   Risk  is reducedto a minimum.  Appointed tasksare undertaken,  appointed  places&quot; manned &quot; without hesitation andwithout confusion.Warning of an air raid will be givenin towns by definite signals.   It willnot be possible to indicate by meansof these signals whether gas bombs are expected.  But local warningswill be given wherever possible, ifgas has been dropped.
IMMEDIATELY ON  HEARING  the warning  AS HEAD OF the household YOU  SHOULD  . , .Personally supervise the following precautions :          I Send  every member of the household immediately          to the refuge-room, making certain that each person          has a respirator.          Pets should, if possible, have been sent away into the          country at the first sign of danger.  But if they are          still in the house they should be taken into the refuge-          room, otherwise they  may come into contact with          gas, or  get splashed by  it,  and contaminate you.          But it should be remembered that animals will help          to use up the supply of air in the room.  To be on          the safe side, count two dogs or cats as one person in          choosing the size of your refuge-room.2 Make some other member of the family responsible  for  checking  that all  the  articles needed  for the  refuge-room are properly in place (see lists  on  pages 9 and 20), and that the room is properly sealed  up against gas and the fire put out.  The blanket  over the door should be made damp.3 Go  all round the house,  closing all doors and all  windows, to prevent any serious amount of gas from  getting into any part of the house.        4 Extinguish all fires.   Fires cause currents of air          which may draw in gas from outside.
5 After dark,  see that no lights are  left burning that  may be visible from outside.6 All gas points that are burning should be turned off,  and the gas  should be turned off at the  meter.  Do  not use gas  light in the  refuge-room but rely on  candles and torches.  If the passages to the refuge-  room are very dark and gas light is the only means  of illumination you may leave one or two gas points  turned very  low, but it would be better to substitute  candles.  If the gas supply of the house is turned off at the  meter, every gas point should be inspected as soon as  the gas is turned on again to make  certain that no  tap was left on or has been turned on accidentally.7 Fill the bath with water, as a supply in  case of fire.  Also fill all available buckets, cans,  and basins.   Put  them about  the  house where  they can be reached  easily.This information is given to guide you.  Your own common-sense will tell you of other things to do, according to the positionof your refuge-room and the type of house you live in.When these duties have been seen to, the head of the house or otherresponsible person should go to the refuge-room or shelter, and after making certain that EVERYONE is THERE SHOULD CLOSE THE DOORAND SEE THAT THE SEALING ARRANGEMENTS ARE EVERYWHERE INTACT.
WHAT TO DO  IN  YOUR  REFUGE-ROOMThese rules should be closely observed by all persons shelteringin a refuge-room.         I Sit or lie down and keep still, keeping warm with          blankets or other coverings.         2 Don&apos;t smoke.         3 Don&apos;t light fires.         4 Don&apos;t go out, unless you must, until you hear the          &quot; Raiders passed &quot;  signal.   Be very cautious even          then.  The danger of gas may not be over although          the air raid may have ended.  Only one member of          the household should go out first to investigate, and          he should be wearing his respirator.         5 Pass the time reading, writing, sewing, playing cards          or quiet games, listening to the Wireless or gramo-          phone.   Avoid  exertion. Don&apos;t let the children          romp about as they will only tire themselves out and          get exhausted.         6 Do  not  put on your respirator  unless the room is          damaged, unless you have  to go out, unless  you          actually smell gas.  Remember, too, that a respirator          affords no protection against ordinary domestic coal          gas.         7 Do  not  touch anything that has come into contact          with gas. If you do, or think you may have done so,          wash your hands well immediately  with soap  and          water.         8 Do not eat food that has come into contact with gas.          That is why  a  food-chest of some kind, or air-tight          jars and tins, are absolutely essential.
 Don&apos;t forget, on coming out of your refuge-room, that whether the raid is over or not, you may find the rest of the house full of gas.  So, except in emergency, keep your family in the refuge-room until you  are sure it is not, or until it has been cleared.   To let the gas out of the house open all windows.   If you have any doubt whether thereis gas in the house summon an air raid official.WHAT TO DO IF THE HOUSE IS DAMAGEDAt once put on your respirator.   If you have to go out of yourrefuge-room, seek refuge in another room or in another building.If you have to go  out of doors keep on your respirator.  Walkwith extreme care.   Avoid all damp splashes on the ground thatmight be gas.  Though the hostile aircraft may have gone theremay be gas drifting about or splashed on the ground.If anyone is injured, a message should be sent to the doctor or the nearest first aid party or post as quickly as possible.  Until helpcomes  you should treat  an  injured  person according  to  theinstructions in Section 5.
  HOW  TO DEAL WITH  AN OUTBREAK                       OF FIRE    I  Send for the fire brigade, or inform the nearest      policeman or air raid warden.    2 See to the safety of other occupants of the house.      If the refuge-room is in danger get the occupants      out.  But make certain that they have all got their      respirators on and know what to do.    3 Attack the fire with water, or sand, or both.  Shut      all windows and  shut all doors,  to  prevent the      draught from fanning the flames.    4 When you have to go near the seat of a fire, keep      low,  and crawl if necessary, because the smoke and      fumes are much less thick near the floor.    5 If the gas pipes in the house are damaged turn the      gas supply off at the main, unless this has already      been done.A fire caused by an incendiary bomb    A small incendiary bomb is unlikely to fall through the housefurther than the top floor.   It will probably burn fiercely forseveral minutes and then go out.  It is impossible to approachan incendiary bomb without some protection for the eyes.  Forthis you should have available at least one pair of non-inflammabledark glasses with proper dark lenses.  Smoked  glass won&apos;t do.Smother an incendiary bomb with dry sand.  Do not use cindersor ashes, or ordinary garden earth which contains root fibres and vegetable matter.  Virgin soil from deep down  is satisfactory in place of sand if it is dry.  And do not use water.  But you canprevent a fire caused by an incendiary bomb from spreading byringing it round with water.Page 2%
A fire caused by a high-explosive bomb    A fire of this kind is like an ordinary fire.   It can be put outwith water or sand, in the ordinary way.  A high explosive bombsets alight to something accidentally, just as a coal that falls out ofthe fire may do.   But it is very important that every effort shouldbe made at the outset  to stop the fire from spreading.ACT PROMPTLY.  PROMPT ACTION MAY BE THE MEANS OF SAVINGLIVES.  PROMPT ACTION WILL SAVE  PROPERTY.   PROMPT action will  PREVENT SERIOUS DAMAGE.  PROMPT  ACTION WILL  defeat the OBJECT OF THE RAID.     HOW TO  AVOID  BURNS  DUE TO                   MUSTARD GASIf you suspect you have come into contact with gas, and have thefacilities at hand, wash yourself and change your clothing.  Thisis the best thing you can do if you do it quickly.  Then go to the nearest first aid post.  But there is no need to do this unless you have been actually splashed  with liquid gas or have passed through a gassed area.  It is better to take your own precautionsby washing and changing straight away than to take your turn ata first aid post.   Contaminated clothing should be thrown out at once.
WHAT  TO  DO WHEN  OUT  OF  DOORSIf you are out of doors at the time of an air raid seek shelter atonce. Unless you have a respirator do not seek shelter in a base-ment or in rooms that are not protected against gas.A doorway, or archway, is quite a good place in which to stand asit provides a certain amount of shelter from bursting bombs.If it is impossible for the moment to get under cover it is safer to lie on the ground than to stand up.A limited number of public shelters will be available which willprovide  some protection for those who may be caught  in the streets.  Always carry your respirator with you throughout thewar.   REMEMBER OTHER PEOPLE  CAUGHT                 OUT  OF DOORSIf you have any space to spare in your refuge-room, and there isno special reason for not admitting strangers, be ready to take insomeone who is caught in the street near your house or premises.Remember he or she may otherwise be left in the open in greaterdanger.
SECTION  4EXTRAThis section describes extra pre-cautions it is useful to take if you can.   They provide an additionalprotection against the penetration of gas and against the effect of explosive  bombs.  But  do not beworried if they are more than youare able  to  take.  The simplerprecautions described in Section 2are the essential things to do.
Instructions have been given for making your refuge-room gas-proof, by sealing it up.  As an additional precaution, it wouldbe a good thing to have an air-lock at the main entrance of yourhouse, if possible, so that you may enter or leave it in an emer-gency without the outside air coming in.  An air-lock is simplyan enclosed space containing still air.A lobby, vestibule, or passage near the door can be  converted into an air-lock ;  so can a scullery or any room through which itis possible to enter the house from outside.Only the entrance to the house that is provided with an air-lockshould be used during an air raid.  All other entrances should bekept locked.   But leave the key in the  door on the inside.  Inblocks of flats, in addition to an air-lock at the main door openingon to the street, a gas protected door (see illustration on page 15)should be made at the entrance to each flat, where it opens on tothe common stairway, landing, or passage.Air-locks  should  also be made in the corridors or staircases oflarge houses, or blocks of flats, to prevent gas drifting about thebuilding should part of it be damaged.In flats or communal buildings the making and placing of theseair-locks should be in the hands of a Protection Committee, com-posed of representatives  of the residents, as  suggested inSection  1. Two doors or  curtains  placed not less than 4 feetapart, so that the first may  be opened and shut again before thesecond is  used, constitutes an air-lock.   But both doors or cur-tains must be  air-tight and must be fixed so that no air can getpast them when they are closed.  Chinks or crevices in the spacebetween them, through which air might enter, must be stoppedup.How to  make  an air-lock     Choose the  place you  want to convert into an air-lock:  avestibule, a section of passage, or a whole room.  Remember thecompartment  should be not less  than 4 feet long. It is betterPage 32
Obthat it should be  a good deal longer.   If there is a permanentdoor at one end, or at both ends, make these doors air-tight as described and illustrated on pages 14 and 15.If there are no existing  doors, this is how to make  a temporarygas-proof door  in order to form an enclosed space.  Make awooden frame like a door frame, and fix it in a sloping positionsupported by two upright posts.   Cover the frame with a blanket                                                The large illustra-                                                tion  shows  how                                                the frame for a                                                temporary   gas-                                                tight door is made,                                                and how it should                                                be placed  in  a                                                passageThe   illustrationbelow  shows theframe  in position,making a tight fitwith the walls andceilingThe sde illustration shows two frames properly in position, the sloping sides both facing outwards
  which has had strips of wood nailed to it to stiffen it.  The strips  should be placed horizontally.  The edges of the blanket should  overlap the sides of the frame.  The frames will not fit to the  walls exactly.   Stuff rags or paper around the top and sides.  When not in use the blanket can be rolled up and tied at the top.  When released it will.roll down the frame because  of the slope  and lie firmly against it.  If you have to make a temporary door at the end of the air-lock  which is towards the open air, the slope of the frame should be  towards the outside of the house so that a gust of air will blow the  blanket against the frame and not away from it.  The air-lock is the space between the two doors, whether  they are  permanent doors or temporary.   Be sure that  all openings and  cracks within the enclosed space are properly stopped up, so that  when the two doors are shut no draughts of air can get in.i During an air raid the blankets covering the doors should be kept  damp.
      EXTRA PRECAUTIONS AGAINST                EXPLOSIVE  BOMBSTRENCHES.  One of the safest things you can do, if you have agarden, is to construct a dug-out or a trench in it, but away fromthe house to avoid falling debris.  A trench provides excellentprotection against the effects of a bursting bomb, and is simple toconstruct.  The danger  to  beware of is the  danger  of gas.Although the possibility of a heavy concentration of gas is notgreat, anyone using a trench or dug-out must, without fail, havehis respirator with him.   Precautions must also be taken againstthe risk of being splashed by  liquid gas when out of doors.Overhead cover should be provided along at least part of the trench, a  foot  of earth spread over corrugated iron, or evenboards, will do.  The unprotected part should  be dug a littledeeper to keep the  covered end dry.   Do not  try trenches inwaterlogged ground.SANDBAGS.  Sandbags  are the best protection if your walls arenot thick enough to resist splinters.  Do not rely on your wallkeeping out splinters unless it is a more  than a foot thick. Awall of sandbags outside will remedy this.Sandbags  are the best protection for window openings, and ifyou can completely close the window  opening  with a wall of
sandbags (which should overlap the walls each side by about afoot) you will prevent the glass being broken by the blast of an explosion, as well as keeping out splinters.  A sandbag wall partof the way up a window will keep out splinters from the lowerpart of the room, but will not save the glass.A wall of sandbags should be broader at the  base than at the top.Round a window opening it should be in contact with the house-Walls, but elsewhere it should be kept 3 inches or more away.Any bags or sacks will do for sandbags, but if they are large don&apos;tfill them right up or you won&apos;t be able to carry them.  Use earthinstead of sand, it is just as  good and easier  to get.If you haven&apos;t got any sandbags, a pile of earth outside the windowwill serve the purpose quite well.   But a wall of boxes filled withearth is better still.  The wall should not  be less than 2 ft. 6 ins-thick.  If the boxes are large, fill  them in position and ram the earth well down.If your refuge-room is a cellar or basement, build a wall of sand-bags or boxes of earth round the top of the cellar area, as illus-trated above.Save any small sacks or cloth bags you may get from time to time,even a few will be useful.  Or  if you cannot get bags, collectwooden boxes that will hold earth.
SECT ION   5         WHAT   TO   DOIF   ANYONE    IS   HURTIf you carry out the precautionsgiven in  this book you will know that you  have done everything youreasonably can to protect yourselfand those dependent on you.  It ispossible, however, that someone inyour household  might be injured.That is why those who can shouldlearn something about first aid.Some general principles are givenhere, but  a simple first aid training which may prove useful to any-one in everyday life may be had from the St.  John  AmbulanceBrigade,  the British  Red  cross society, or the St. Andrew&apos;s ambulance-lance Association.   You can  getinformation  about   the  trainingavailable  in your own locality from your local Council Offices.
 J\  I  I   persons involved in  accidents suffer from shock,3* I- i&quot; whether or not they suffer physical injury.  Shockis a disturbance of the nervous system.   It varies in its severity.The signs of shock are faintness, paleness, weak pulse, and weakbreathing.TREATMENT OF SHOCK         I  Place the patient flat on his back on a bed or a rug or           on cushions.  If you think a bone may be broken do           not move the patient more than can be helped.         2 Loosen the clothing at the neck, chest and waist to           make the breathing freer.         3 Cover the patient  warmly with rugs  and blankets.           In cases of shock the body loses heat. A hot-water           bottle is helpful, but take care that it does not lie in           contact with the skin.         4 Give hot drinks.   If  you cannot make  hot drinks           give cold water in sips.  But only if the patient is           conscious and able to swallow.         5 Soothe the patient by speaking reassuring words in           a calm voice and in a confident way.TREATMENT OF  WOUNDS    The first thing to do is to stop the bleeding and to keep thewound clean.  This can be done by covering it with a clean dress-ing bound on tightly.   Do not touch a wound with your fingersbecause of the risk of poisoning from dirt.  Treat the patient forshock in addition to attending to the wound, because the loss of blood, if the wound is serious, and the pain do in themselves causeshock.WOUNDS  IN  THE HEAD AND BODY         I  Cover the wound with a clean folded handkerchief or           a double layer of dry boracic lint.         2 Apply another handkerchief or a layer of cotton wool           as a pad to distribute the pressure over the wound.         3 Tie the dressing firmly in position with a bandage,           strip of linen, or a necktie.         4 Treat the patient for shock.
                                                      108IF ANYONE  IS HURT_____WOUNDED LIMBS         I First  raise the limb to lessen the flow of blood.        2 If the flow of blood is steady (when a vein is injured)          cover the wound  with  a dressing  and  bandage it          firmly as already described.        3 If the blood comes in spurts and the blood itself is          brilliant  red  (when an artery is injured), raise the          limb, and grasp it tightly between the wound and the          point where the limb joins the body.  Get someone          else to apply dressings in the way already described.          Keep the limb well raised.  Release  your grasp.          Watch carefully.  If the bleeding starts again, renew          your grip and hold the limb firmly until  skilled help          arrives.  If help does not come quickly and it is too          tiring to keep your grasp, tie the limb firmly with a          piece of stout string or cord.4 Treat the patient for shock.TREATMENT FOR BROKEN BONES    If bones or limbs are broken it is extremely unwise to move the patient more than is absolutely necessary.The patient often assumes by instinct a position in which thebroken limb or bone is most comfortable.If you are doubtful whether a bone is broken, act as though it is,and do not move the patient unless you must.         I  Support the patient with cushions or folded blankets           tucked closely around the body so that he can relax           into the  position he finds most comfortable.
2 A temporary arm-sling will sometimes  relieve the  pain of a broken arm.3 A broken leg can sometimes be made more comfort-  able by being tied to  the other leg at  the  thighs,  calves and ankles by strips of linen or neckties.4 Treat the patient for shock.TREATMENT OF  BURNS AND  SCALDS         I Cover the burned or scalded part with a dry dressing,          a clean folded handkerchief, a pad of clean cotton          wool, or a piece of boracic lint folded double.  Do          not apply oil or butter to the burn.         2 Treat the patient for shock.TREATMENT FOR  GAS    Many of the gases which might be used in war are notnecessarily dangerous to life if proper care is taken.The first and most important thing is to keep calm.Contaminated clothes should at once be taken off and thrown out.If any part of the body seems to be affected, wash it if possible.For example, the eyes should be bathed, the skin washed withsoap and water, the throat and mouth gargled.Until skilled assistance can be obtained the patient should be keptas quiet as possible.  He must not drink alcohol or smoke.Page 40:
Further copies of this book &quot; TheProtection  of your Home  against air  Raids,&quot; are obtainable from.M.  Stationery Office,  and  allPost Offices.  Price id. each.A handbook describing Air RaidPrecautions  for  Factories  and business Premises is also available.It is called Air Raid PrecautionsHandbook   No.   6.    employers should obtain a copy from H.M.Stationery  office for  through anybookseller, price 6d: (Sd. post free).A handbook on &quot; Personal  Protec-tion against Gas &quot; (A.R.P. Hand-book No. i), which will interest all who want to know more about gas,may  be  obtained from   H.M.Stationery  Office, or  through anybookseller, price 6d.  (8d. post free).Another  handbook,   &quot; StructuralPrecautions  against  Bombs  and gas &quot; (A.R.P. Handbook No.  5),which contains technical details ofmore  elaborate structural  protec-tion, will be available to those towhom   this   information   is  ofparticular    interest   architects,builders and others.Printed under the Authority of HIS MAJESTVS STATIONERY OFFICE        by William Clowes &amp; Sons, Ltd., London and Beccles.         (182A)  Wt. 1700-12.  2. W. C. &amp; S., Ltd..  Gp. 389.can, act upon it.  Decide now where your refuge-room ought tobe.  Think how you can make it as secure as possible.  Start to collect the things you would need in it.   Know what to do in caseof fire.  Learn a litde about first aid.  Make a point of knowingwhat is being done by your Local Authority in the way of air raidprecautions, and understand how they affect you personally.
                                 LONDON         PUBLISHED  BY HIS MAJESTVS  STATIONERY  OFFICETo be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONER Y OFFICE at the lollowin? addresses:   Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2&quot;, 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2:         16 York Street, Manchester: ; 1 St. Andrew&apos;s Crescent, Cardiff;                        60 Chichester Street. Belfast :                          or &quot;through any bookseller                              Price od. net                                  1937                                                     S.O. Code No.

</content>
</cab>
