<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 163-191</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
S E C R E T *                CABINET.      FINANCIAL ASPECTS OF ^IR RAID PRECAUTIONS.Note &quot;by the Minister for Co-ordination of Defence.       In accordance with the instructions of the cabinet at its Meeting held on 24th March, 1937, (cabinet 13  (37)Conclusion 11(b)) the Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and requirements have examined the concrete proposals of theHome Secretary on the subject of expenditure on air raidprecautions.Sub-Committee by the Home Secretary (Paper D.P.R. 181) andthe draft Minutes of the Sub-Committee&apos;s 37th Meeting heldon 8th April, 1937.CP.  112 (57).COPY NO.I append the Memorandum circulated to the(Intld.)   T.&apos;.7.H. I.hitehall Gardens, S.V.1.12th April,  1937./
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.  March 1937.SECRET.Copy  No. H2D.P.R. 181.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements.FINANCIAL ASPECTS  OF  AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS.      Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department.    IN accordance with Conclusion  I.C. (ii)  of the 36th Meeting* of the Com-mittee, I circulate herewith a comprehensive Memorandum on the cost of air raidprecautions arrangements.    The Memorandum includes emergency fire requirements and every effort hasbeen made to forecast expenditure of  all kinds which the introduction of air raidprecautions may raise.    The Memorandum has been discussed departmentally with the Treasury andthe Air Raid Precautions  Department  have,  wherever  possible,  personallyinvestigated on the spot, and with the  local officials concerned, the estimates onwhich the general statement is based.    In  view of  the repeated representations which  I have had  from localauthorities all over the country, I am most anxious to be able to make a suitableannouncement as early  as possible in respect of any financial assistance whichmay be approved.    If the  Committee agree, I would propose that, as the next step, I should beauthorised  to negotiate with  the various associations representing  local govern-ment authorities  in this country.  I  think it is essential that every endeavourshould be made to obtain the agreement of these associations to any proposalswhich may be authorised before they  are actually announced.   If any difficulties are experienced  in these negotiations, I will make a  further report  to theCommittee.    While  every  effort has  been made  to forecast and calculate  the anticipatedexpenditure, certain of the  figures must be of a somewhat provisional character.I would  ask the  Committee, therefore,  not to regard these figures as final and binding,  but if any cause for material  alteration should arise the matter would,naturally, be brought forward again.    I need hardly emphasise the importance of the proposals submitted, and I am confident that, if the principle of financial assistance to local authorities and other undertakings is accepted, further progress towards the completion of air raidprecautions  schemes all over the country will be rapid.(Initialled)J. S.Home Office,    March 23, 1937.* D.P.R. 36th Meeting.[14861]B
PART I.            DEGREE  OF PREPAREDNESS OF AIR RAID  PRECAUTIONS.     1.  A VERY important question has arisen in connection with preparationsby local authorities for air raid precautions, and it is desired to submit proposalsfor consideration by  the Defence Policy Requirements Committee.     2.  The policy of the  Home Office  has  been to tell local  authorities, as a first step, to work out the  plans for their air raid  precautions organisation onthe basis that they can be put into operation &quot; at short notice.&quot;     3.  The actual plans involve, for example, the establishment of first aid posts,casualty clearing hospitals, base hospitals, arrangements for the decontaminationof material, and the equipment of rescue parties (with depots for the personnel),the provision of emergency fire  brigade equipment,  and so forth.  Schedules ofthe equipment which is considered necessary have been,  or are being,  drawn up,and suggestions for the adaptation of buildings for the various requirements havebeen prepared.     4.  In respect of any buildings which require adaptation, local authoritieshave been advised not only to prepare the plans, but also to obtain estimates ofthe material required and to arrange, as far as possible, the sources from which supplies could be obtained; also to examine the question of the labour whichwould be necessary and its  availability.;!    5.  In connection with these local schemes of air  raid precautions, the onlydefinite commitments of a financial character which the Government have, so far,undertaken  are assistance towards making good deficiencies in hospital equipment and substantial  assistance  towards emergency fire  brigade  measures.  For thelatter purpose  588,000 has been provided in the 1937-38 estimates.  Up to thepresent,  the  general  position in connection with hospitals has  not crystallizedsufficiently to enable  any comprehensive  proposals to be  submitted, though some preliminary provision has been made in the 1937-38  estimates.*     6.  In connection with all local precautions, great  emphasis is laid on all arrangements being made, so far as possible, to obtain supplies of materials andlabour from local sources, though it is recognised that instances may well arise when, for one reason  or another, this will be impossible.     7.  A number of local authorities have now reached the practical planningstage,  and the  question  has arisen as to the length  of time  which they mayhave to put their plans into execution before war begins.   Clearly the shorter thetime the more elaborate the preparation in time of peace if the arrangements areto be ready when they are wanted, particularly in those areas most likely toreceive the first onslaught of attack in the early days of a war.     8.  At the same time,  however, it is obviously undesirable to provide fullyprepared buildings in  peace time when the purposes  for which they would berequired could be met by taking over in war buildings used  normally for other purposes, provided that  a.  short period  was available before a war  to  convertthem to their war uses.  In this respect there is a fundamental difference fromthe state of preparation possible in the Defence Services.     9.  It is  realised that it  is impossible  to predict with any accuracy &quot;at allwhen a war is likely to  occur,  and although a  general precautionary stage  is envisaged, it is equally realised that any Government would be reluctant to take any  steps during a time of tension  which might increase the possibility  of war.     10.  From the point of view of the preparations for the protection of thecivil population, however,  a problem  of the greatest difficulty arises.  Unless    * In addition the Government has shouldered from the outset the whole cost of providing the main anti-gas equipment respirators for the general public, other respirators and protectiveclothing for all  air raid  precautions services, bleaching powder, and the School (shortly to be two Schools) for training local anti-gas instructors.  These  commitments are referred to inparagraph 18 in Part II.
                                      3sufficient warning is given beforehand, together with authority to execute thepre-arranged plans, a great many of the arrangements could only be ready, whenwar broke  out, if much more extensive works than are at present  contemplatedwere completely  carried out  beforehand;  and this raises the  first question  onwhich an expression of opinion is desired.     11.  During a period of tension, is it considered that the taking of air raidprecautionary measures in the country, including the necessary works and other services, would be a  cause of embarrassment  in  negotiations  for a possiblepeaceful settlement of the dispute ?     12.  It is  suggested that these arrangements come into a different categoryfrom active defence  movements,  and that  they could in no  circumstances  beconsidered as a provocative act.   If this dictum is accepted,  it will make theposition easier.     13.  The next question is the actual length of the immediately pre-war period which might be available for air raid precautions to be  put into effect.  It is now accepted*  that there is a possibility that air attack  might be delivered  with&quot;practically no  warning, and in circumstances  which  might  arise  with greatswiftness.  On the other hand, there might be a period of diplomatic tension of long or short duration. The degree of notice to be assumed for  air raid pre-cautions must obviously be a compromise.  If, as is suggested, it is  impossible tobe ready at a few hours&apos; notice as regards a considerable number of the prepara-tions (without  large expense now and the dislocation of normal life), then  somefigure must be  taken which is not extreme in the other direction.   It is believedthat 4 days&apos; notice will be a reasonable mean, taking into account all the  factorsconcerned.   On that basis it is hoped  to  avoid  the  need for  full advanceexpenditure by the Government and local  authorities, on the physical conversionof local services and buildings from peace  to war time uses (e.g., first aid posts).t     14.  It is possible that, under this proposal, the Government might authorisethe putting into force of the air raid precautions schemes, at considerable expenseto the national Exchequer, and  that the war might not then materialise.   Noescape, however,  from this possibility can be suggested.  The risk of leaving thecountry unprepared if the  situation really became critical would be  so great, andthe consequences, if attack materialised, so disastrous that it is  felt  that this riskmust be faced.     15.  The assumed 4-days warning can have very little effect as regards theemergency fire brigade measures, which consist mainly  in the  accumulation of fire-fighting appliances and the  training  of  personnel, and cannot be left to afew days&apos; improvisation.     16.  No mention  has  been made of the  problem of the distribution of the civilian respirators.   It  is considered that this is a matter which  must standalone.  The consequences of failure to distribute these  respirators in time wouldbe disastrous, and the distribution  plans must work to a far narrower time limit,to be reckoned in hours not in days.Recommendations under Part I.     17.  The following recommendations are submitted for approval:      (a) that it.is not possible to contemplate, in connection with  civil air raid           precautions, such  a state  of preparedness in all  respects in time of           peace as is adopted for the pre-war preparedness of the Navy, Army           and Air Force.     (&amp;) that air raid  precautions, being of a purely  passive  character,  may           properly be initiated during a period of tension without prejudice to           a peaceful settlement of any negotiations that might be in progress,           and may be initiated independently of any active defence  preparations.    * C.I.D. Paper  No. 241-A, approved by  the C.I.D. (283rd Meeting, Conclusion (1) ).    f This proposal does not, of course, affect in any way the existing commitments of-the Govern-ment or -any proposals as  to assistance which might be considered essential in the. interests ofnational security.       [14861]                                                      B 2
(c) that the general preparations to be made by local authorities and others      concerned should be worked out on the basis that they may assume      4 days&apos; warning to complete their precautionary measures before the      outbreak of war.(d)  that the degree of preparedness to be aimed for, both, before and during      the 4 days&apos; period, will depend to.some extent upon the particular      service  in question and the liability of the particular area  to early      attack.(e) that in deciding to work  on  a basis of an  assumed warning period of      4 days, the  risk is incurred of that warning being given On  a threat      of an emergency which may not materialise,  with the result  that the      expenditure reserved until the 4-day period, or a large part of it, may      then be undertaken Unnecessarily;  but this risk is to be accepted as      preferable to the only possible alternative, which is to incur the same      expenditure, or  more, in advance.(/) that the plans  for  the emergency fire brigade measures  for London  and      other areas most liable .to incendiary attack must be worked out to      secure the highest possible  degree of preparedness;  and in these      services and areas it will not be possible to postpone until the 4-day      warning period the provision of equipment and appliances.(g)  that  the plans for the  distribution  of  Civilian  respirators must be     . considered on a basis  quite separate from the proposal  for a 4-day      warning period, and  the period for completion of their  distribution      must be reckoned in hours  and not in days.                                  PART II.   FINANCIAL IMPLICATIONS AS  REGARDS LOCAL AUTHORITIES&apos;. EXPENDITURE.    18.  Up till the present time the financial relations between  the Governmentand local authorities in regard  to air raid precautions (apart from fire, brigademeasures) have been governed by paragraphs  7, 8 and 9 of the original circularof the 9th July,, 1935.  These paragraphs are reproduced as an Appendix to thisPart.    There have since.been further decisions by  which the Government have accepted additional liabilities, notably the provision of respirators for the general public,  and the  undertaking to  afford substantial assistance towards the cost ofemergency fire brigade measures, but, otherwise, no radical departure from thepolicy laid down in the circular  has so far been made.    19.  There has been, for a considerable time, a growing agitation on the partof local authorities  as to the expenses  in which they are, or anticipate  being,involved in carrying out the plans of air raid precautions, especially as  to theresponsibility for  the cost  should  their schemes  have,  at  any  time,  to be implemented in full, i.e., should a state of war arise.  And a stage has now beenreached where local authorities have prepared their schemes in  sufficient detail to enable them  to estimate, or at least appreciate,  the cost involved.  This leddirectly to a deputation of  representatives  of the Association of  municipal corporations, which was  received  by  the  Secretary  of State  for  the  home department on  Thursday, the 17th December, 1936.  Representations on similar lines have been made verbally or in writing by the London County Council and theother main Associations of local authorities.    20. Without going into details,, it may be said the local authorities  have represented that they had reached  a point  with their schemes when they feltunable  to proceed without a clear  indication of the financial responsibility forcarrying out the preparatory measures  and putting the plans into operation  if need arose.    21.  The financial problem may be considered under  four headings :            (i) Peace-time expenditure. .           .                       \ .          (ii) Immediately pre-war expenditure.         (iii) War-time expenditure.         (iv) Payment of compensation for injury.
(i) Peace-time expenditure.    22.  Apart from certain annual charges which are rather outside the scopeof the present paper, the expenditure in peace-time, either by the central Govern-ment  or by local authorities, must be partly governed by the  assumed warningperiod which is discussed  in Part I.  The shorter the warning, the greater theexpenditure necessary in time of peace, particularly in two respects : (a), it wouldbe necessary to  provide in advance more special buildings if reliance  was notplaced on  having time to  divert  existing buildings from peace-time uses,  andconvert them to  war uses; and (b)  it would be necessary to accumulate, and store,stocks of common articles (e.g., medical stores, blankets, and so on) which, given areasonable warning, could be purchased from  trade stocks on  a threat of anemergency. \ As  has already been stated, there must be a compromise which will reduce, so far as possible, high capital expenditure now, but will at the same timeallow reasonable expectation that the whole air raid precautions organisation canbe implemented  in time.  It is for this reason that  a period of 4 days has beensuggested.    23.  The question of peace-time expenditure is. obviously one of difficulty, andit is hard  for the Home Office in many, directions  to put forward any reliablefigures until they have received and can examine in detail and on the  spot theestimates and proposals of  the various local authorities. Such a task must involve considerable  labour and delay, because some time must elapse  before many localauthorities are  in a position to submit concrete proposals.  The attitude whichthe organisations representing local authorities  are adopting makes it impossibleto postpone  the proposals  in this  paper  until comprehensive data  have  been collected..    24.  Detailed  examination of  local authorities&apos; schemes,  including  their financial aspect, will be inevitable later.  Nothing short of individual scrutiny Ofeach scheme will carry out the Departments responsibilities.   &quot; 25.  In order that some financial perspective may be available an attempt hasbeen made to frame a rough estimate, based on  the information at present avail-able, of the possible total cost of putting the country in a proper state of prepared-ness.   The figures given are naturally tentative.  Only a very small number offinancial estimates have so far been received from the local authorities, and  these have had to be taken as a general guide, although, as has been stated, circumstances will obviously vary all over the country.    26.  A further estimate has been added in which it is attempted to show theeffect of the 4 days of grace. These figures must be regarded as of a tentative, evenspeculative, nature; and from practical experience with certain local authorities would appear to be subject to considerable local variation.    27.  The estimates are given in Part III.    28.  It appears clear that, in addition to the financial commitments already undertaken by  the Government,  some further substantial Exchequer assistancemust  be given to local authorities towards the cost of their preparations. Up tothe present all assistance has lain in the provision of material, e.g., respirators,protective  clothing, fire appliances,  &amp;c.   There still remain  other  directions inwhich assistance in kind will be the most suitable.  On the other hand, certain ofthe local precautionary arrangements can only be executed by  the authorities onthe spot, and for such purposes, and for administrative and maintenance expenses,it is proposed that in general the assistance should take the form of a percentagegrant in aid.  Although the organisations of local authorities have asked that theGovernment should bear the whole cost of these preparations, it is believed that,having regard to the large volume of expenditure which has already been accepted as a national charge  (on respirators, &amp;o), and  provided the same principle was extended to  certain other  costly equipment, such as major fire appliances,  theycould be persuaded to accept, for the remainder, a percentage grant basis in whichthe Government provided not less than 60 per cent.    29.  It is suggested that, there might be a basic grant of &quot;60 per  cent., subjectto variations for specific items.  The items of cost listed in Part III fall into six
main categories, and it is suggested that they should be dealt with as indicatedbelow;  Category (i).     Recurrent expenditure on organisation, training, storage accommodation not otherwise  provided for,  and  other miscellaneous expenditure 60  per  cent.grant.Category (ii).     Protection of or precautions in buildings housing public services which wouldhave to  be maintained as part of  the  air  raid  precautions  or emergency fire brigade organisations, i.e., alterations to existing buildings or added cost in thecase of new buildings--60 per cent,  grant:  provided that where existing grantswere in operation (e.g., police, schools) the air raid precautions costs should rankfor those grants instead of earning the special A.R.P. grant.Category (iii).     Provision or adaptation of hew buildings to provide first aid posts, anti-gascleansing accommodation at depots of  A.R.P. services,  auxiliary fire stations and fire  posts 60  per cent, grant.Category (iv).     Training of auxiliary  firemen-a  grant of   3 per man (estimated about60 per cent.) or a rate to be fixed.Category (v).     Accumulation  of  equipment  for   emergency  fire-fighting  and  air   raidprecautions services over and above that required for  peace-time purposes andnot already available in the possession of the local authority 60 to 100 per cent.grant (generally by provision in kind) according to whether the equipment servesor does not serve any useful purpose in peace time. Air raid warning arrange-ments and provision for extinction or obscuration of street lighting might come under this category.Category (vi).     Provision of supplementary water supplies for emergency fire fighting (apartfrom possible assistance to water undertakings which is referred to in Part IV) normally 60 per cent,  grant.     It would be understood that these grants would not be payable on expenditure which could properly be postponed until the four-day period, regard being paidin this connection to the probable liability of the particular district to deliberateattack in the early days of war.     The above classification does not include provision  of additional hospital accommodation, which  is  at present under examination by a sub-committee ofthe C.I.D.. and must be reserved for further  consideration.     30.  It is  most urgently represented that an early announcement be made that, when local authorities have worked out their schemes and estimated expendi-ture, and these have been examined by the Department, then the Government willbe prepared to contribute towards expenditure which is considered to be essential in peace-time for the efficiency of local air raid precautions schemes.(ii) Immediately pre-war expenditure.     31.  The moment the  order was   given  for air  raid  precautions to be implemented, considerable expenditure  would  at  once be incurred.  The wholeorganisation would have to be  brought  into  as complete a state of readiness aspossible.   The  expenditure  involved would be largely of  a capital nature  andwould be concerned with the complete fitting up  of first aid posts, provision of hospital  equipment and accommodation, setting  up of decontamination  depots,protection  of property, calling-up  and organisation of personnel and so on.  Tosome extent the use of premises, vehicles and property would have to be obtained byrequisitioning or otherwise, and a liability to pay hire or compensation would be incurred.  This period would, in fact, involve important financial consequences.
    32.  It is suggested that there seems little escape from the recommendation that an increased proportion of this responsibility should be borne by the centralGovernment, and if an announcement could also be authorised now to this effect,the situation would be greatly relieved.(iii) War-time expenditure.    33,  Expenditure during the actual  period of hostilities would be recurringrather than capital.   It would involve the supply and replacement of equipment,payment of personnel, payment of  compensation, pensions and other  charges ofthis nature.   Once hostilities ceased, a  considerable portion of  this would, ofcourse,  automatically  disappear, but there would remain a semi-permanent com-commitment in respect of  pensions and compensation.  The question of reconstructionis not included,  but it is obviously  a matter in which the Government might be concerned over some period of time.    34.  In view of the far greater urgency of the other problems, it is suggestedthat the financial implications in war time should be left for discussion at some future  date.  To some  extent, also, the  decisions taken on the other pre-waraspects  will have a bearing on the answers to the questions raised.(iv) Payment of compensation for injury.    35.  There  is one  further issue connected  closely  with local authorities&apos;-organisations : the question of compensation and pensions in war time.  The air raid precautions services require a very large number of volunteers who are coming  forward  at a fairly satisfactory rate.  It has not yet been possible to settle the pay and conditions of service in time of war of  persons enrolled in A.R.P.services. The question, however, is  being asked and pressed for an announcement that the Government  would be  prepared  to provide compensation or pension forany who might be injured,  and for the dependants of any who might be killed, in air attack.  A war compensation scheme has been under consideration for sometime by a sub-committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, and the practicaldetails  are now  in process of being considered by the Ministry of Pensions, on whom the administration of the scheme would probably devolve.  The scheme atpresent outlined is very wide in its scope, embracing,  as it is proposed,  all personswho can be  described as  &quot;gainfully employed.&quot;   It is unnecessary, for thepurpose of air raid precautions and fire brigade services, for any such widespreadundertaking to be given now unless it is desired. It would be sufficient for anannouncement to be made in the most general terms that pensions or compensa-tion would be provided  for such  personnel  in war time.   It  is clear,  fromindications received from all over the country, that  unless some  such announce-ment is  forthcoming, the recruiting  for all these services may be definitely held up on be abortive.    36   It is suggested that the request for an  assurance of this nature is not unreasonable in  view  of the important, and probably dangerous, services whichthe volunteers would have to undertake.Recommendations under Part II.    37.  The following recommendations are submitted for approval: (i) Peace-time expenditure.    (h) that an  early announcement should be made that the Government  will           be prepared  to make  a contribution  towards  the cost of  local           authorities&apos; air raid precautions and emergency fire brigade measures,           so far as their schemes and the expenditure thereon are approved by           the Secretary of State, after detailed examination by the Department&apos;s           officers.    (i)  that the  general basis on Avhich the Exchequer assistance should be given           towards the  various services  (apart from items already accepted as           a national charge) should be as follows :            (i) Staff, organisation and maintenance costs, and  training,  storage              and other accommodation not specially excepted.                          60 per cent, of approved expenditure.
          (ii)  Protection of or precautions  in buildings housing public services               which  would have  to be maintained as part of  the  air  raid               precautions or emergency fire brigade organisations.                         60 per cent, of approved expenditure, or, in  the case                     of existing grant-aided services,  the ordinary grant.         (iii)  Provision  or  adaptation of buildings to provide  first aid posts,               anti-gas cleansing accommodation at depots of A.R.P.  services,.               auxiliary fire stations and fire posts, &amp;c.                         60 per cent, of approved expenditure.          (iv)  Training of auxiliary  firemen.                         Grant per man trained at  3 or a rate to be fixed.          (v)  Accumulation of equipment  for emergency fire fighting  and air               raid  precautions services (over and above peace-time  require-               ments) (including possible provision for warning  signals and for               extinction or obscuration  of street lighting).                         60^ to 100 per cent, (generally by way of provision in                     kind) according to whether  the  article  does or  does not                     serve  any useful purpose in peace time.          (vi)  Provision  of  supplementary water  supplies  for  emergency  fire               fighting (not including expenditure  by the water  undertaking               itself).                         Normally 60 per cent.    (j)  that negotiations should be begun with local authorities&apos;  organisations.          on  the basis of the  preceding  paragraph with a view to arriving at          the extent of  the Exchequer assistance and the form which it should          take with respect to particular classes of expenditure.(ii) Immediately pre-war expenditure.    (k)  that an announcement should be made to the effect that, except as regards          existing grant-aided services, increased Exchequer assistance will be          given towards the cost of completing the air  raid precautions schemes          in  the 4-day period.(iii)  War-time expenditure.    (I)  that the financial and other  problems involved in time of war shall be left          for discussion at some  future date as  they are of  less immediate          urgency.(iv) Payment  of compensation for injury.    (m)  that  the Government  will authorise a  statement to be made now that          pensions or compensation will be provided for air raid volunteers and          workers, and  members of the auxiliary fire brigade service, who may          be  injured on duty  in war time, and for the dependants of  any such          who may be killed on duty in war time; this  announcement to be made          whether or not it is  possible or desirable at the same time to announce          the wider scheme applying to  all persons  &quot;gainfully  employed&quot;         - which is now being  worked out.                           APPENDIX TO PART II.             Extract from Home Office circular of Qth July,  1935.    7.  Measures for safeguarding the civil population against the effects of air attack differ from the  provision needed  for other forms  of national defence inthat they must be organised locally, district by district, and that activity on thepart of the central government cannot compensate for the failure of any districtwhich is liable to attack to take effective  measures on its own account.  TheGovernment will issue general instructions, based on expert study of the problems,and will be  ready  to  give  technical  and administrative advice,  and to afford
financial assistance towards the provision of additional hospital equipment and stores, where essential in order  to  assure adequate  reserves,  as well as in the directions  indicated in paragraph 9 below;  but responsibility will rest on localauthorities for ensuring  that adequate measures of  civil protection against air raid dangers are taken in their own districts.     8.  The construction on any extensive scale of shelters which would  be proofagainst direct hits by bombs is impracticable.  Such protection could be  obtainedonly by means of concrete structures of great thickness or correspondingly costlyworks of equivalent strength, and, apart  from any other considerations, the cost would be prohibitive.   The  Government  cannot therefore undertake to providemoney towards the construction of public bombproof shelters.  On the other hand,effective protection against blast  and splinters from bombs can be  obtained atcomparatively small cost,  and it will be for occupiers of premises to provide this for themselves and their households, and  where necessary for their workers andcustomers.   Specific advice on this subject will be made generally available.     9.  Protection against gas will&apos;need separate treatment.  Information willbe published as to the means by which  occupiers of premises can make  themgas-proof.  Furthermore,  His Majesty&apos;s Government  have decided to accumulatereserves of respirators and protective clothing and to issue them at the cost ofthe Exchequer to persons employed on air raid precautionary services e.g., police,fire brigades, first aid organisations whose  duties would require them  to enterand  to remain at  work in gassed areas.   Provision  has already been made for obtaining a first supply of respirators of approved types which will be allottedpartly for  training purposes and partly  as  reserve  stocks.  Arrangements willsimilarly be made to accumulate  supplies of  bleach powder for decontaminationpurposes.  The Government will  also establish a Civilian Gas School to providetraining in anti-gas measures for  instructors who will be competent to give localtrainings in their own districts.PART III.   ESTIMATE OF LOCAL AUTHORITIES&apos;  AIR RAID PRECAUTIONS EXPENDITURE.     38.  The  figures given in the accompanying table, which covers  England,Wales and Scotland, are based (apart from the fire brigade services) primarily on information obtained from the County Boroughs of Birmingham,  Liverpool, andBirkenhead, and the Borough of Hackney.  The figures for hospitals (Class F) areof a very speculative nature, and for this reason as well as the fact that, with theincreased scale of attack now being put forward, no proposal has been made inparagraph 29 for any basis of Exchequer assistance, the figures  in Class F areonly included in the endeavour to give a complete financial picture.     39.  From the estimates given and the discussions which have taken place itis evident  that there will be considerable difference in the facilities availablelocally all over the country; and some difficulty has been found in assessing a meanfigure.  In practice, it may be  found necessary to vary any general principle whichmay be agreed in order to ensure reasonable provision in the areas the most exposed to attack or the most vital from a national  point of view.     40.  The  following are details of the estimated expenditure. The figures have been calculated on the cost per 1,000 of  the population,  taking 40,000,000 asthe total population concerned.   In those for fire brigade  services&quot; the factor of street mileage has also  been taken  into account.  After much careful thought  itwas  considered that these methods afforded the  only feasible way of arriving atthe totals required.       [14861]                                                       c
    41.   The figures in the table may be summarised as follows :-(a)  Annual Expenditure (recurrent)     Class A. Staff, organisation, training, &amp;c. (excluding fire                  brigade services)       ......    Class D. Fire Brigade services                                Total............Per annum.   750,000   550,0001,300,000(b)  Capital Expenditure (non-recurrent) Glass B Protection  of or-precautions in           public buildingsGlass C Provision of special buildings ...Glass D Fire Brigade services and equip-           mentClass E Special equipment (excluding fire           brigade services)Class F Hospitals  ...             Totals     ...    ...... Before  4-    During 4-day period.   day period                    2,000,000      500,000  2,628,000     1,652,0007,200,000 897,0002,600,000163,000 Total.    2,500,0004,280,0007,200,0001,060,0002,600,00015,325,000    2,315,000    17,640,000(c)  Apportionment  of pre-4i-day ExpendiUire between  Government  and  Local         A uthorities Annual Expenditure     Class A  ......    Class D  ......             TotalsCapital Expenditure     Class B  ...    Class C  ...    Class D  ...    Class E  ...    Class F  ...             TotalsSuggested  grant. Per  cent.   60   60    60    6060-10060-100   ?80Government    share.    1-per annum.  450,000  330,0007S0.000 1,200,000 1,577,000 5,500,000   717,000 2,100,00011,094,000  LocalAuthorities&apos;  share. &apos;     per  annum.  300,000  220,000520,000 800,0001,051,0001,700,000 180,000 500,0004,231,000     NOTE. A substantial part of the capital expenditure may be expected to bemet by local authorities by loan, so that the grant might take the form of annualrepayment  of a percentage of loan charges rather than a lump sum charge.
		Numbers required per town of 100,000.			Capital expenditure before &quot; 4-day&quot; period.	Capital expenditure during &quot;4-day&quot; period.		No.	Item.		Details.	Recurring Expenditure.			Total Capital Expenditure.	Remarks.Glass A. Staff, Organisation, Training, ccc. (excluding Fire Brigade Services).								1	Organising staff y :-		Office accommodation. Paid organiser, special staff, administration, &amp;a. Storage and maintenance of equipment. Roughly estimated at  750 per 100,000 population per annum	  300,000 per annum	 	 	  &apos;	This requirement varies widely and many places have no special organisers or offices. The figure given should be greatly reduced at the end of 2 or 3 years.2	Anti-Gas Train-ing :&apos; *	200-250 wage-earning em-ployees plus 1,500 volunteers ,i -	Training local authorities&apos; employees and volunteers in anti-gas measures Full local course = 22 hours plus travelling time=40 hours. Average wage rate 2s. an hour Provision of class-room accommodation. Time of instructors, training of instruc-tors. Also public instruction, &amp;c.	450,000 per annum				This represents an initial charge probably continuing over 2 or 3 years. There will be a small recurring charge which cannot be estimated at present.			Total Class A ......	750,000 per annum							Glass B. Protection of or Precautions in existing or New Public Buildings.					CO	Additionalstruc-tural precau-tions		Providing shelters in municipal buildings for A.R.P. Headquarters and similar services. Mostly concerned with new construction, incorporating structural precautions in hospitals, including also public refuges		2,000,000	500,000	2,500,000	Since primarily new construc-tion necessary before &quot; 4-day &quot; period, likely to be spread out considerably.  500,000 for public refuges.			Total Class B ......		2,000,000	500,000	2,500,000	to
Item. Numbers required per town of 100,000.Details.	Capital	Capitalj		Recurring Expenditure.	Expenditure	Expenditure	Total		before &quot; 4-day &quot; period.	during &quot; 4-day &quot; period.	Capital Expenditure.	Remarks.Glass C. Provision of First Aid Posts and other Special Accommodation.First Aid PostsDepots for First Aid andRescue Parties and De- contamination Squads.Laundries for de- contami nation of clothing.5 or 6 Posts (say 3 new,  3 con- verted)Large Depots 2;  Sub-Depots  6  or  8;  (1 new  large depot).Conversion of existing buildings or g.e.e tion of new buildings.   Average cost of j conversion and  provision of necessary protection  800 per  post.  Cost of new post  1,000.  Furniture, equipment and spare clothing  250 per post.Conversion  of  existing  buildings  800 each.   New   buildings   1,000  each (Large Depots).  Conversion sub-depots  200 each.    1,512,000Estimated cost of adaptation per laundry - 1,000Potal Class C.816,000    1,008,000544,000     2,520,0001,360,000300,000100,0002,628,0001,652,000400,0004,280,00060 per cent,  of  the  First  Aid Post conversion  &amp;c.  required before &quot;4-day&quot;  period.   Re- mainder and equipment, which will  be  normally  available locally, during &quot;4-day&quot; period.60  per cent, required before &quot; 4-day &quot; period.  It is possible that  expenditure  before &quot; 4-day &quot; period might have to be   higher.  All  depends  on existing facilities.  Alterations to police buildings not included as  they  are on  police grant footing.It  is  very difficult to estimate at  present  how  expenditure would have to be divided.Class D. Fire Brigade Services.Administration ...		Emergency staff, training, mainten-	550,000	2,200,000		2,200,000	and miscel-		ance, &amp;c.	per annum				laneous							Equipment		Fire-fighting appliances and equipment		5,000,000		5,000,000			Total Class D .. ...	550,000	7,200,000		7,200,000				per annum				
Glass E. Special Equipment (excluding Fire Brigade Services).9 10 11 12 13	Equipment for Decontamina-tion and Res^ cue Parties Equipment and Stores for First Aid Posts and Parties Stretchers and blankets Street lighting... Warning signals	8 sets decontam-ination equip-ment; 4 sets rescue equip-ment 15 parties; 5 or 6 posts Stretchers  220,000 (grand total for coun-. try). Blankets  260,000 (grand total for coun-try) 500,000 lamps (whole country)	Additional equipment not normally available estimated at  30 per decon-decontamination  squad and  60 per rescue squad. Additional equipment for shoring, &amp;e.,  100 First Aid Parties First Aid pouch at 8s. each (4 per party). Haversacks at  1 (1 provided per party). First Aid Posts Medical equipment,  15 per post. Clean clothing for public,  40-50 per post. Stretchers Anticipated price, 15s. each Blankets 7s. Qd. each Installation of special fittings for street lamps or instantaneous extinction, 10s. per lamp for either device Provision of warning devices outside London. (London provision included provisionally in Part VI A.R.P. esti-mates) Total Class E ......	...	232,000 40,000 225,000 250,000 150,000	113,000 50,000	232,000 153,000 275,000 250,000 150,000	The equipment included in this estimate is not generally avail-able locally, and if it is not it would be unsafe to leave its provision until the &quot;4-day&quot; period. Equipment for parties required before &quot;4-day &quot; period. Equip-ment for posts, and spare clothing, during &quot;4-day&quot; period. The current stretcher price is 35s. It is hoped to reduce this to 15s, as indicated. The blanket position requires fur-ther investigation to see the proportion that must be bought before &quot; 4-day &quot; period.					897,000	163,000	1,060,000				Class F. Hospitals (estimates		very vague).			14	Hospitals		Hospitals are being considered on a national basis. Under the original scale of attack (150 tons a day) 87,000 beds and equipment were required plus medical stores. The hospital space was available. Under the revised scale of attack there is a shortage of 500,000 beds for which no hospital accommoda-tion is available. This -position is being considered, by the Medical Co-ordination Sub-Committee and no figures can be given.		2,600,000		2,600,000	-Figures are for the old scale of attack. Deficiencies could not be left until &quot;4-day&quot; period.			Total Class F .........		2,600,000		2,600,000	
                                 PART IV.  ESTIMATE OF EXPENDITURE ON MEASURES  TO PROTECT THE VITAL SERVICES.    42.  Part III of this Paper has dealt with.expenditure connected with localauthorities, but there is another equally important side of which mention mustbe made.    43.  There are in  the country a number of public services, the maintenance and safeguarding of which would be vital to the effective prosecution of the warand the life of the community.  The most important of these services are :              (a) Electricity.             (6) Water.             (c) Domestic gas.             (d) Railways.             (e) Docks. &apos;*             (/) Oil supplies.    44.  In order that at least the minimum of safeguarding may be providedcertain capital expenditure is clearly essential in time of peace.   The Home office is making a very close examination of the whole position, but some indicationsmay be given here of the sort of ways in which expenditure might be required.Electricity Supplies.    45.  The provision of spare switch gear.Gas Supplies.    46.  The provision of a second &quot; booster &quot; at the Beckton Works of the GasLight and Coke Company.    47.  The linking of the four main gas supply  systems of London.Water Supplies.    48.  The provision of spare pumping  plant  for Kemp ton Park PumpingStation.Oil Supplies.    49.  The  provision  of  special local  protection  for big  oil  depots,  or alternatively  the  removal of depots from vulnerable places to less  vunerable areas.    50.  The estimates of cost which have  so far been received are naturallytentative, and the following  figures are  quoted chiefly in order to give a more complete picture.Electricity Supplies.    51.  A figure of  500,000 has been quoted by  the Central Electricity  board as being the cost  of a  national reserve of switch-gear.   Larger sums would fall to be incurred by undertakings on their local  protective measures.Water Supplies.    52.  The needs in the case of water supplies  include spare pumping  plant,connections  between mains,  provision  of  supplementary mains  and  hydrantconnections for emergency use, and so on.   The  Metropolitan Water  Board has indicated a figure of   200.000 as required  in the provision of portable  plant.Another  200,000 is likely to be required for urgent improvements in the firefighting supplies of London and for supplementary mains.  No particulars are yet available for the provinces.Gas.    53.  The  works  described  in paragraphs  46  and  47  would  cost  about 250,000.  The London  Gas Companies have  produced a  very &quot;much  largerestimate covering other works; and at the same time indicated that essential  works in important centres south-east of a line from the Humber to Southampton  would cost about the London  figure.  About  500,000 as a minimum would be required on  essential works, apart from much  larger sums  to be incurred by the under-takings themselves.   *
 Railways.     54.   No  estimate  of  any kind is,  at  present, available, as the  railway companies have only just begun to think about the problem. Docks.     55.   The Port  of  London have produced an estimate of  15,000 and  the Mersey Docks and Harbour  Board one of  60,000.   These estimates are being examined, but it is  believed  that they are by no means exhaustive.  Of  the two estimates the latter seems to be the more representative. Oil Supplies.     56.   The figure would depend on the size of the depot and no reliable data are available.     57.   It  is  not  for one moment suggested that  the Government  should contribute 100 per cent, of any of these requirements.  There are, however, clear indications that, unless the  Government  are prepared to contribute,  the  under- takings will not do much on their own, if the whole burden is left with them.  No attempt is made here to submit scny detailed estimates, but it is believed that if the Government  were prepared to contribute a sum which should be a maximum of  5,000,000, to be divided up between these various industries, it should be possible to have some most valuable safeguards provided, and that it would be a direct incentive  to the  undertakings themselves to provide additional safeguards which the Government grant  did not cover.  In addition to the list given there may also be other industries or undertakings for which assistance might be desirable, e.g., building a second Billingham.     58.   It is very difficult to give any gross estimate for the total cost over  the whole country;  but  it  is believed  the figure would certainly not be less than  10,000,000,  making allowance for  the services quoted and  other requirements which might come, to light.     59.   It is suggested that the total maximum Government contribution under this heading should be  5,000,000 spread out over  all the services. Recommendation under Part IV.     60.   The following recommendation  is submitted for approval:      (n) that the Government should be prepared to  expend a sum not exceeding            5,000,000  towards measures required  for safeguarding the vital           services of  the country out of a  total which would  almost certainly           exceed  10,000,000;  the methods by which  such grants  should be           administered being reserved for fuller consideration.                                  PART V. PROVISION OF  PROTECTION  AGAINST THE EFFECTS  OF BLAST AND SPLINTERS                       FROM HIGH EXPLOSIVE BOMBS.    61.    There is one other very important question and that is the provision ofprotection against blast and splinters of high explosive bombs.    62.    The most satisfactory protection is  that provided by the sandbag or its equivalent.    63.   A rough calculation has been made which  assesses the number of sand-bags for which there might be a demand as being in the region  of 1,000,000,000on the outbreak of war. And this may easily be an under-estimate.    64.   It is perfectly clear that a demand  of this  sort arising on the outbreakof war could never be met, and that only a fraction of the number required wouldbe available.    65.   There  is also coupled with this the difficulty of finding materials incongested  areas  with which to fill the sandbags. All  these questions are beingclosely examined, particularly the possibility of finding some substitute.  On theother hand, there will inevitably be a big demand for sandbags in the  protectionof industry, and it is felt that steps ought to be taken now to accumulate supplies in time of peace, so that they  can be distributed in convenient centres.
1(1    66.   Investigation has been made with the help of the Board of Trade intothe supply situation,  and it is understood that as regards pure capacity aloneIndia and this country might be able to meet the demand.  On the other hand, ifthis  was  done  the entire  output of the  countries  would be absorbed.   Thealternative is paper bags.  The present productive  capacity of the country isabout 250,000,000 bags a year,  and the output is entirely absorbed by the trade.    67.   Here  again  it is not  sought at  this stage to  make  any concretesuggestions, but the proposal is put forward for general consideration, and if itshould be agreed that action should be taken to make  good  what might in time ofwar be a most serious deficit, then the possibility of starting a factory, preferably in a  depressed area, might be.a solution.     68.   Alternatively, or in  conjunction  with a factory, the placing of large orders in Dundee, which it is understood suffers badly from unemployment, mightassist in many directions.     69.   In view of the great protection which sandbags or their equivalent giveagainst  high explosive attack, and the fact that at present no assistance of any kind is  being given by the Government  against this risk, some action appears tobe essential.     70.   The  cost  of a  sandbag is about 2%d. or of  a  paper bag about  l\d.Assuming that if produced on  a large scale a flat rate of a penny might bepossible, the cost of accumulating the numbers required would be in the region of  4^ million.     71.   It is suggested that  at least a half of the amount ought to be providednow, which would mean expenditure of approximately  2,000,000.Recommendation under Part V.     72    The following recommendation is submitted for  approval :      (o)  That  the Government  should  authorise  the  provision  of 500,000,000           sandbags  at  a cost  in  the region  of  2  million, being half  the           estimated requirement.   The method of accumulating  supplies and           storing them to be considered in conjunction with the Board of Trade.                                  PART VI.EXPENDITURE  AUTHORISED OR  ANTICIPATED BY  THE  AIR RAID  PRECAUTIONS     DEPARTMENT ON SERVICES AND  SUPPLIES  FOR  THE BENEFIT OF  LOCAL     AUTHORITIES.     73.  The figures given below  are  included as  a  guide to the expenditure incurred or likely  to be incurred by the Air Raid  Precautions  Department on Services and Supplies directly connected with Local Authorities and the general public.   The figures do not  include experimental work  or administration nor services financed by other sources, e.g., police funds,  Office of Works.  No figures for fire services are included.                                 1935-36.   1936-37.    1937-38.     Total.                                                                            Gas schools       ......      2,050      10,100      22,500      34,650     Training (miscellaneous)...      4,900      12,000      16,000      32,900     Anti-gas  equipment  (in-          cluding  factory,  sto-          rage and inspection)...      15,420    1,163,850    4,126,000    5,305,270     Other equipment ...     ...       ...        11,000     108,000     119,000     Warning  and  intelligence          arrangements      ...      ...         ...         160,000     160,000                 Totals     ...    22,370    1,196,950    4,432,500    5,651,820                         Grand total of  5,651,820.    It is probably likely to aggregate about   8,000,000  up to completion of programme at present in view.
                                 PART VII.    .     GENERAL  SUMMARY  OF  RECOMMENDATIONS AND INFORMATION.           Part I. Degree of Preparedness of Air Raid Precautions.     (a) that it is not possible to contemplate, in connection with civil  air raid           precautions, such  a state of preparedness  in all respects in time of           peace as is adopted for the pre-war preparedness of the Navy, Army           and Air Force.  .     (b) that air raid precautions,  being of  a  purely passive  character, may           properly be initiated during a period of tension without prejudice to           a peaceful settlement of  any negotiations that might be in progress,           and may be initiated independently of any active defence preparations.     (c) that the general preparations to be made by local authorities and others           concerned should be worked out on the basis that they may assume           4 days&apos;  warning to complete their precautionary measures before the           outbreak of war.     (d) that the degree of preparedness to be aimed for, both before and during           the  4  days&apos; period, will  depend to some extent upon the particular           service in question and the liability  of the particular area  to early           attack.     (e) that, in deciding to work on a basis of an assumed warning period of           4 days,  the risk  is incurred  of that warning being given on  a threat           of an  emergency which may not materialise, with the  result  that the           expenditure reserved until the 4-day period, or a large part of it, may           then be  undertaken unnecessarily;  but  this risk is to  be accepted as           preferable to the only possible alternative, which is to  incur the same           expenditure, or more,  in advance.     (/) that the plans for the emergency fire brigade  measures for London anal           other  areas most liable to incendiary attack must be  worked out to           secure the highest possible degree of  preparedness;   and in these           services  and areas  it will not be possible to postpone  untilthe 4-day           warning period the provision of equipment and appliances.     (g) that the plans  for the  distribution  of  Civilian  respirators must  be           considered  on  a  basis quite separate  from the proposal for  a 4-day           warning period,  and the period for completion of their distribution           must be  reckoned in hours and not in  days.  Part II. Financial Implications as regards Local Authorities&apos;  Expenditure.(i) Peace-time  expenditure.     (h) that an early announcement should be made  that the Government will           be  prepared   to make a  contribution towards  the  cost of  local           authorities&apos; air raid precautions  and emergency fire brigade measures,           so far as their schemes and the expenditure thereon-are approved by           the  Secretaryof State, after detailed examination by the Departments           officers.     (*)  that the general basis  on which  the Exchequer  assistance should be given           towards the various services (apart from items already accepted as           a national charge)  should be as follows :            (i) Staff, organisation and maintenance costs, and training, storage               and other accommodation not specially excepted.                         60  per cent, of approved expenditure.         (ii) Protection  of or precautions  in  buildings housing public services               which  would  have to be maintained  as part of the air raid               precautions  or emergency fire brigade organisations.           j                         60  per cent,  of approved expenditure,  or, in  the case                     of existing grant-aided services, the ordinary grant.         (iii) Provision  or  adaptation of buildings to provide  first  aid pOsts,               anti-gas cleansing accommodation at  depots of A.R.P. services,               auxiliary fire stations and fire posts, &amp;c.                         60  per cent, of approved expenditure.       [14861]                                                        D
          (iv) Training of auxiliary firemen.                          Grant per man trained at  3 or a rate to be fixed.           (v) Accumulation of equipment  for emergency fire fighting and air               raid precautions services (over  and above  peace time require-               ments) (including possible provision for warning  signals and for               extinction or obscuration of street lighting).                          60 to 100 per cent, (generally by way  of provisipn in                     kind)  according to whether the  article  does or  does not                     serve any useful purpose in peace time.          (vi) Provision of  supplementary water supplies  for  emergency  fire               fighting (not including expenditure by the water undertaking               itself).                          Normally 60 per cent.     (j)  that negotiations  should be begun with local authorities&apos; organisations           on the basis of the  preceding paragraph with a view to arriving at           the extent of the Exchequer assistance and the form which it  should           take with respect to particular classes of expenditure.(ii) Immediately pre-war expenditure.     (k)  that an announcement should be made to the effect that,  except as regards           existing grant-aided services, increased Exchequer assistance will  be           given towards the cost of completing the air  raid precautions schemes           in the 4-day period.(iii)  War-time expenditure.     (I) that the financial and other  problems involved in time of war shall  be left           for discussion  at some  future  date  as they are of  less  immediate           urgency.(iv) Payment of compensation for injury.     (m) that the Government will  authorise a statement to be made now  that           pensions or compensation will be provided for air raid volunteers and           workers, and members of the  auxiliary fire brigade  service, who  may           be injured on duty in war time, and for the dependants of any such who           may be killed on  duty in Avar time;  this announcement to  be made           whether or not  it is possible or desirable at the same  time to announce           the wider scheme applying to all persons &apos;&apos; gainfully employed &apos;&apos; which           is now being worked out.Part III. Estimate of Local Authorities&apos; Air Raid Precautions Expenditure.	Grand Total.	Suggested Government Share before Four-day Period.	Suggested Local Authorities&apos; Share before Four-day Period.Annual expenditure Capital expenditure  Before four-day period During four-day period	1,300,000 per annum 15,325,000 2,315,000	  780,000 per annum 11,094,000	520,000 per annum 4,231,000	17,640,000		Part IV.- Estimate of Expenditure on measures to protect the vital  Services.    (n) that the Government should be prepared to expend a sum not exceeding            5,000,000  towards measures required for safeguarding the vital           services  of the country out of a total which would almost certainly           exceed   10,000,000;  the methods  by which such grants should be           administered being reserved for fuller consideration.
Part V. Provision of Protection against the effects of Blast and Splinters from                           High Explosive Bombs.    (o) That  the  Government should  &quot;authorise  the provision  of  500,000,000           sandbags at  a cost  in  the region  of   2 million,  being half  the           estimated requirement.  The method of accumulating supplies and           storing them to be considered in conjunction with the Board of Trade.Part VI. Expenditure authorised  or anticipated by the A .R.P.  Department on        services and supplies for the benefit of local authorities  and the public.   . At  present spent, authorised or  included in estimates up  to 1937-38: 5,651,820.    Estimated total:   8,000,000.                             GRAND  SUMMARY.    Annual recurrent expenditure (on local authorities&apos; schemes)                                                   &apos; -        &apos;                                                             Per  annum.        Government share  ...     ...     ...     ...    ...      780,000       *Local authorities&apos; share   ...     ...     ...    ...      520,000                         Total      ......    ...    1,300,000Capital non-recurrent expenditure                                  Before  &apos;&apos; 4-day &apos;&apos;  During  &apos;&apos; 4-day &apos;&apos;                                      period.           period.                                                              Estimated total cost......     35,325,000        2,315,000Suggested Governmenfs share    26.094.000&quot;]Suggested  local  authorities&apos;               y      2.315,000    share     .........      4,231,000 JIndustry&apos;s   share  (including    public  utilities)......      5,000,000                             35,325,000        2,315,000Grand total:  37,640,000 (plus   1,300,000 per annum).
Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   April 1937.SECRET,Copy  No.D.P.R./37th Mtg.COMMITTEE  OF  IMPERIAL  DEFENCE.Sub-Committee on Defence Policy and Requirements.DRAFT Minutes of the 37th Meeting held on April 8, 1937.                                Present:The Rt. Hon. Sir THOMAS INSKIP, C.B.E., K.C., M.P..                         of Defence (in the Chair).Minister for Co-ordinationThe  Rt.  Hon. NEVILLE CHAMBERLAIN,  M.P., Chancellor of the Exchequer.The Rt. Hon. A. DUFF COOPER, D.S.O.,  M.P., Secretary of State for War.The  Rt.  Hon. ERNEST BROWN,  M.C.,  M.P., Minister of Labour.                   Marshal  of  the  Royal Air  Force Sir                     EDWARD   L.   ELLINGTON,  G.C.B.,                     C.M.G., C.B.E.,  Chief  of the  Air                     Staff (representing  the Secretary of                     State for Air).                    With the following expert advisers :The   Rt.   Hon.   Sir  JOHN   SIMON,  G.C.S.I.,  K.C.V.O.,  O.B.E.,  K.C.,  M.P., Secretary of State for Home  Affairs.The Rt. Hon. Sir  SAMUEL HOARE, Bt.,  G.C.S.I., G.B.E., C.M.G., M.P., First  Lord of the Admiralty.The Rt. Hon. Lord WEIR, G.C.B.Admiral of the Fleet Sir A. ERNLE M.  CHATFIELD,    G.C.B.,    K.C.M.G.,  C.V.O., First Sea  Lord and Chief of  Naval Staff.Field-Marshal Sir CYRIL J. DEVERELL,  G.C.B.,   K.B.E.,   Chief  of   the  Imperial General Staff.The following were also present :The  Rt.  Hon. WALTER ELLIOT,  M.C.,  M.P., Secretary of State for Scotland.Mr.  F. 0.  STEWART,  Assistant Secre-  tary, Scottish Office.Sir RICHARD HOPKINS, K.C.B., Second  Secretary, Treasury.Mr.  H.  G.  VINCENT,  C.B.,  C.V.O.,  Principal  Assistant   Secretary  in  the Office of the Minister, for  Co-  ordination of Defence.  .  .The  Rt. Hon.  Sir  KINGSLEY  WOOD,  M.P., Minister of Health.Sir  RUSSELL  SCOTT, K.C.B.,  C.S.I.,  I.S.O., Permanent Under-Secretary  of State for Home Affairs.Mr.   A.  L.  DIXON,   C.B.,  C.B.E.,  Assistant  Under-Secretary of State,  Home Office.Wing Commander E. J. HODSOLL, C.B.,  Assistant  Under-Secretary of State,  Home Office.Colonel Sir M. P. A. HANKEY,  G.C.B., G.C.M.G., G-C.V.O. (Secretary).Colonel H. L. ISMAY, C.B., D.S.O. (Deputy Secretary).Wing Commander W. ELLIOT, D.F.C. (Assistant Secretary).[14992]
     THE SUB-COMMITTEE had under consideration a Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Home Department on the financial aspects of. Air Raid Precautions (Paper No.  D.P.R. 181).     SIR JOHN SIMON,  in introducing the Paper, said that it was of a very serious character, covering a very  large subject.  Part I drew attention to the fact  that it was impossible to contemplate  in  connection with civil air  raid precautions such a state of pre-emergency preparedness as was adopted for the Fighting Services.   It was therefore suggested as a governing principle that the development of. air raid precautions  could be undertaken without provocation during a period of tension, and might therefore be put in hand independently of active defence preparations.     If this  principle were accepted, the next point was to decide  upon some conventional period during which this residue of preparation could be finally completed after the beginning of the emergency period.  The Home  Office had suggested a period of 4 days.   To adopt this suggestion was admittedly to  run the risk that there might  not be 4 clays&apos;  or even 4 hours&apos; grace.   On the other hand, unless some period of grace were assumed, the financial implications would be almost too formidable to contemplate.  He cited as an example the provision of emergency  fire-brigades,  and  pointed  out that it  would  be impossible to improvise these at short notice during the emergency  period; it was therefore proposed to supply the capital  plant for&apos;these at the expense of the taxpayer, on condition that the cost of subsequent maintenance was  borne  by the local: authorities..     Sir  John Simon then proceeded to a brief analysis of  the estimate of expenditure under Parts II and  III of  the Memorandum.   He was emphatic that the cost of providing air raid precautions should not be entirely an Exchequer liability  but  that  local authorities must  be required  to make their financial contribution.   The ratio which he had suggested  was  that 60 per cent, of the cost should be borne by the Government and 40 per cent, by the local authorities. He was not hopeful that  local authorities would acquiesce in this  suggestion, and he had in his possession a document drawn up by Mr. Morrison as  recently as the 22nd March, in which an emphatic  attitude was taken against the idea that the ratepayer should be asked to take any share whatsoever of the financial burden of air raid precautions.   With this argument he himself (Sir John Simon) disagreed, and he asked the Committee to authorise him to open negotiations with local authorities and to inform them of the Governments proposals on this subject.     SIR KINGSLEY WOOD said that he  had been in constant touch with local authorities on the subject, especially in regard to its financial aspect.   Thei&apos;e were two points which he wished particularly to emphasise.     Firstly, he considered that before going to the local authorities the  Govern- menfs plans would have to be much more precise as to what they involved in the way of expenditure.  After examining some of the items he himself felt the need of more  detailed information.   By way of example he referred  to the shortage of half a million hospital beds mentioned on page 13 of the Memorandum,  and the estimate of  2,600,000 to, meet this deficiency, observing that this was very .much at variance with the present  capital cost of a hospital bed which amounted to  400.  Secondly, he was anxious  to know how far it was,  in fact, necessary to make provisions of such a sweeping character as those suggested in the Memo- randum.  They ought, he considered, to  be reviewed in the light of what  was being done in other countries.     As regards the proposed  60  per cent, grant by  the Government,  all his information went to show that local  authorities would  demand  more.  If, as a result of bargaining with them, it became necessary to increase the Governments share to, say, 75 per cent., he felt that the State would be better advised to take on the whole  provision  of expenditure and assume complete control.   Even if some of the local authorities agreed to accept a 40 per cent, share, he did not think that others-the Distressed Areas, for example could meet such financial liability without  serious repercussions, in the  nature of demands for further  grants for social  services.MR  BROWN agreed.
                                     3    In reply to the Chairman, WING COMMANDER HODSOLL said that thefigure of 75,000 hospital beds was based on the Air Ministry estimate of  a scale of attack of 150 tons of bombs per day.  The actual buildings to house the bedsexisted.  More recently, however, the scale of attack had been  greatly increased,which resulted in a shortage not only of half a million beds,  but of the buildingsto house them.  The figures included in the estimate were a token,  put there atthe request of the Treasury.    MR. CHAMBERLAIN observed that the proposals implied a very alarming-addition to our financial liabilities.   After the  example given by Sir KingsleyWood of the. cost involved in hospital beds alone, it was obvious that the total of 37 million represented nothing like  the maximum  which would  eventally be.required.    Mr. Chamberlain then addressed himself particularly to the question of the4-day period of warning.  The sums expended before  this period would be spentanyhow, whilst the sums which it was proposed to spend during the period mightnot, in fact, be spent, or, if so, only partially.  Therefore, it was  desirable to put asmuch of the proposed expenditure as possible into the 4-days&apos; period.  It followed that if  the 4-day period could be lengthened,  say, into a fortnight,  it would bepossible to transfer a good deal  of the money  now required from the &quot; pre &quot; tothe &quot;post&quot; emergency period.  He appreciated,  however,  that the most heavyitem, i:e., for fire-brigades, would have to stand.    Another advantage of  extending  the 4-day. period was  the calming effect which  such an extension  would. have on the public mind, which would be lessalarmed by preparations  being  spread over  fourteen days than being  hustledthrough ill: four.    Turning to the question of the proportion of expenditure that should be borneby the Exchequer on the one hand and local authorities on  the other,  he fely strongly that whatever difficulties were raised by  the latter, Government should refuse to bear  the whole  burden.   He agreed that the Home Secretary should negotiate on the basis of the proportions suggested in paragraph 37 (i),  since itwould be useless for Government to offer any lesser contribution in the. present.temper of local authorities.    Referring to the point in paragraph 17  (d) of the Memorandum that &quot; the degree of preparedness to be aimed for, both before and during the period ofemergency^ (whether  4 days or a fortnight),  would depend  upon the particular service in question and the liability of the particular area  to early attack,&quot; he considered that it would  be possible to go further by concentrating first on theareas most likely to be attacked,  and thereby yet  further reduce tho total expense.    Referring to the proposal that the Government grant towards  Fire BrigadeServices and Special Equipment (Classes D  and  E on pages 13 and 14 of theMemorandum) might vary between 60  and 100  per cent., he  doubted if such  a variation could be maintained.    SIR JOHN SIMON asked if  it was not considered whether the extensionof the emergency period  from 4 to 14 days would not be a temptation  to localauthorities to shirk taking  the  precautions which  they should during thepre-emergency period.  -  MR. CHAMBERLAIN felt that the local authorities would consider the riskOf such action to be too great.v   -LORD WEIR, viewing the subject as a  whole and accepting the figure of 15,325,000 as a national insurance against air attack, asked whether this sumwould not merely be an initial commitment which would gradually increase by theaddition of such expenses as,  for example, for rental  charges.    WING COMMANDER HODSOLL did not consider that this was quite thecase unless or until the precautionary or war  stage was  reached.  The broadproposal was that certain preparations should be made during the pre-emergencyperiod, which could then be finally completed in the 4-day period.     SIR JOHN SIMON made the point that the figures did  not take into accountmoney which would have to be spent in the actual  event of a declaration of War.     SIR  SAMUEL  HOARE  asked  Wing  Commander  Hodsoll  if he couldexplain more fully what was implied in the process of completing the preparationsduring the 4-day period.       [14992]                                                    B 2
              (At this point Sir Edward Ellington left the Meeting.)     WING COMMANDER HODSOLL explained that preparations  in peace time would be taken up to a point where they could be completed in a period of 4 days.  For example,  a building selected as a  first-aid post  would  have  the necessary washing  and other  arrangements installed, partitions, &amp;c,  prepared and  stored.  The  same principle  would  apply  in  other directions.   Certain supplies required which were available locally could be collected during the 4-day period, thus avoiding the expense of unnecessary storage in normal times.     MR. DUFF COOPER associated himself with the point which had been made by the Home Secretary, that the estimates did not take into account the money which would be required once War was declared.  He emphasised that we were preparing  for  the  unknown.  If air  attack was really  as devastating as some people  were  inclined  to say,  the expenditure  of even such  a vast  sum  as  37  million would be little more  than a palliative.  On the  other hand,  he considered that there were grounds for believing that the effects of air attack, in the face of our  anti-aircraft defences and retaliation by our own bombers, might not be so terrible.  In any event, they would not be universal, and he therefore suggested that it might be possible to exclude certain areas altogether as not being really open to serious air attack.  He advocated an investigation of the problem, on these lines with a view to reducing the costs.     WING COMMANDER HODSOLL said that the problem had in fact been considered on these  lines, but that even so some provision might have to be made for localities outside  the  areas of  likely  attack.  All places  would have to  be treated on their  merits,  taking into account  their  liability to  attack,  their. geographical location, and any other  factors which, might influence the scale of local  preparation.     SIR JOHN SIMON remarked that it would be for the Home Office to examine the schemes of the Local Authorities individually before approving them.  Where these  schemes were  too  ambitious, they would have to be cut down.   The  real difficulty would arise where Local Authorities were not prepared to go as far as they should, and the Home Office might then find itself confronted with a recalci- trant  Local Authority refusing to  pay more and insisting that the extra  cost should be borne  by the Government.    LORD WEIR brought up the question of whether the estimates contained in the Memorandum had been based on any actual experimental work.  He suggested something in the nature of a &quot; Demonstration Area.&quot;     SIR SAMUEL HOARE  endorsed this  suggestion and considered that it might produce valuable results.     WING COMMANDER HODSOLL said that practically  every town except Barnsley had taken  air raids precautions seriously and keenly, and had prepared big schemes to meet their own local conditions, which naturally varied considerably. Accordingly, he doubted whether a Demonstration Area would produce the results hoped  for.  In  any case,  the figures  in the Paper were based on a  number  of typical examples taken from different parts of the country.   In reply to a question from Lord Weir on  the subject of the time factor, he said that the expenditure of  15 million (paragraph  (&amp;), 1st column) would be spread over about five years.   v MR. CHAMBERLAIN asked whether the figures of expenditure on page 10 of the Memorandum had been based on a differentiation between places according to the scale of attack to which they were considered liable.     THE CHAIRMAN thought that such a differentiation  might result in a considerable reduction.     MR. DIXON said that the largest item,  i.e.,  7,200,000 for  Fire Brigade services and equipment, had  been based on the element of estimated risk.     SIR MAURICE FIANKEY suggested that the accepted principle for active defence against air attack, i.e., the provision of defences for only those areas which are particularly vulnerable, should also be applied to passive defence measures.
    THE CHAIRMAN agreed and suggested that it might be possible to exclude the more  remote localities altogether, except as regards provision  against gasattack..                           .    SIR SAMUEL HO ARE added that not only the scale of defensive prepara-tion, but also the degree of readiness (i.e., the length of the warning period) shouldvary in proportion to. the vulnerability of localities.                i     -    WING COMMANDER HODSOLL stated that recognition of  the lesserclaims of  such remote localities was implicit in the priority which the proposalsaccorded to certain vital areas.  .    LORD WEIR thought it  absolutely essential that the scheme  should  be managed centrally if this idea of &quot; tapering &quot; was to be effective.    THE  CHAIRMAN suggested that this was ensured by the condition thatthe plans of all Local Authorities would have to be submitted, in the first instance,to the Home Office.    MR. WALTER ELLIOT foresaw in this the possible danger of a  united front by an alignment of Local  Authorities against the Central Authority,    MR. DIXON pointed out that Fire Brigade equipment would be distributedunder the central control of the Home Office, according to priority of risk.  Townsin the white area (on the map  produced by Wing Commander Hodsoll) would receive a certain scale of equipment, but not the same scale as those in the  &quot; frontline.&quot;    THE  CHAIRMAN agreed  that some kind of differentiation, either by theHome Office or by some other central Government Authority, would be necessary.    WING COMMANDER HODSOLL  said that  his figures were,  of necessity,rather arbitrary because he had had to base them on such information as he had himself been able to  collect on  the spot, and he had always intended that theGovernment should deal with the problem by localities on a priority, rather thana uniform basis.    LORD WEIR emphasised the point that this brought out the main question at issue, namely, whether  it was a local responsibility or a national one.&quot;     THE CHAIRMAN considered that^it  was essentially a national problem.     SIR  RUSSELL SCOTT&apos;said that  it was primarily  the responsibility ofLocal Authorities.     He read an extract from  the original Circular of the 9th July, in whichthis was clearly set out.  (See D.P.R. 181, Appendix to Part II.)  The role ofthe Government was to criticise  these schemes after they had been drawn up.    MR.  DIXON&quot; quoted the view of the London County Council that it was really  a Government  responsibility,  a conclusion to which they had been led bythe fact that London was quite  unprepared for an incendiary attack despite thevery adequate arrangements which the Council had taken to provide against thedanger of fire in normal conditions.     MR. BROWN referred in this connection to an authoritative article whichhad recently appeared in the Manchester Guardian of which he happened toknow that the author was Sir Miles Mitchell. The article forecast the probability that Mr.  Morrison intended to  take  the  lead in  advocating  a 100  per  cent.contribution by the Government.     THE CHAIRMAN replied that in that event the Government could retaliate. by insisting that &quot; he who pays the piper has the right to call&apos;the tune.&quot;              (At this point Sir Ernie Chatfield left the meeting.)     SIR JOHN SIMON observed that the first essential was to decide the basis on which local  authorities should be  approached.   It would not be necessary, he thought,  to give them the precise duration of the &quot; precautionary  period &quot; but merely to  inform them that the  extent of their expenditure would depend on the scale of the.preparation considered necessary, and  this in turn would depend on geographical and  strategical considerations:        [14992]                                                     B 3
     SIR  MAURICE HANKEY suggested that an  analogy could be  drawn between the  position of the local authorities in this problem and that  of theColonies in the scheme of Empire Defence.  All Colonies were required to preparetheir own local defence schemes.  At one end of the scale there were comparativelyinsignificant  places such as the  Seychelles and Honduras, and, at the other end,points of such great Imperial importance as Malta and Singapore.  All these,irrespective of size  or importance, were required to submit their local defence.schemes to the Committee of Imperial Defence, and  each of them made some contribution  themselves, the balance of the defences  being made good  by theGovernment,  according  to the varying necessities of each case from the point ofview of Imperial Defence as a whole.     MR. ELLIOT doubted whether  the analogy was altogether  a correct one,since the  Government could issue orders to Colonial Administrations, but couldnot do so to local authorities, who were more in the position of the Self-GoverningDominions.;     WING COMMANDER HODSOLL,  at the  invitation of Sir John  Simon,made it clear that the schemes submitted  by the local  authorities  were morethan tentative, and in most cases contained comprehensive details of a concretecharacter.  At Birmingham, for example, a proposal had been worked  out indetail to evacuate 34,000 schoolchildren, to adapt the  schools so evacuated forthe purposes of air-raid precautions, and to re-house the children in new buildings.     Referring to the 4-day period, he was of the opinion that to make any realdifference it  would be necessary to  extend  it, not by  days but by months, and suggested three months  as a minimum.  For this  reason he felt that it would be preferable to make no definite  statement  about this  period in the proposeddiscussion with the local authorities.     He also endorsed the views which had been expressed regarding the desirabi-lity  of treating the subject with the local authorities on  a basis of priority.V    MR. ELLIOT wished to know if it was the intention to invite representativesof the local authorities from everywhere, or whether it was proposed in the firstinstance to deal only with  those from the more important localities.  -     SIR JOHN SIMON thought that this matter should be left to the decisionof the Minister for Health, the Secretary of State for Scotland, and himself.     He added that he hoped that the Secretary of State for Scotland would be associated with the conduct of the negotiations when they took place.     MR. ELLIOT agreed.     MR. CHAMBERLAIN  reiterated his  fear  of  the  danger in principle of admitting any variation in the  percentage  of the Government  grant accordingto whether the object did  or did not serve any  useful  purpose in peace time.(Paragraph 37 (v) on page 8 of the Memorandum.)  It would, he felt, providea loophole of which the  Local Authorities might readily take advantage.     WING COMMANDER HODSOLL  replied that  he had  not experiencedany  evidence  of such a, reaction to this proposal from local authorities.     MR. CHAMBERLAIN expressed disagreement with the Minister of Health&apos;view that, if in bargaining with the local authorities the Government were  forcedto consider say a 75 per cent, grant, it would be preferable that the Governmentshould shoulder the full cost and assume full control.  In his opinion it was mostimportant that we should insist on  some  contribution,  however small, from thelocal authorities themselves.                                 PART IV.   .  THE CHAIRMx\N, turning to the question of expenditure on measures toprotect  the vital Services  (Part IV  of the Memorandum), doubted whether theChancellor of the Exchequer would feel disposed to accept the expenditure inquestion, without considerably more details of the implications  of this  problem.He suggested that a special Sub-Committee should be set up to examine and  reporton the whole  question.
    WING COMMANDER HODSOLL agreed, and said that he had includedthis part of the Report because he had been investigating this  problem carefullyfor the last year and he was greatly impressed with its importance. His recom-mendations were in the nature of a ballon  d&apos;essai, with the  object  of calling attention to this important aspect of the problem.    MR. CHAMBERLAIN was of the opinion that  this part of the problem was of  too big a  character  to  be  dealt  with by the Air Raid PrecautionsDepartment of the Home Office.    THE CHAIRMAN agreed,  and said  that it was  a matter which involvedseveral Departments of the Government.    He therefore recommended that  aseparate Sub-Committee should be appointed  to study the question.  This in turnmight set up a number of other Sub-Committees to examine such particular aspectsas the main Sub-Committee might consider necessary.  If this were agreed to inprinciple, it might be left to him  to decide the detailed composition and terms ofreference  of  the  proposed Sub-Committee,  in consultation  with  the HomeSecretary and the other Ministers concerned..                                  PART  V.    THE CHAIRMAN, turning to the question of the provision of sandbags for protection against high explosive bombs (Part V of the Memorandum), observedthat, according to this information, the cost was estimated at too low a figure.He suggested that the question  should  be  referred  to  the appropriate  Sub-Committee of the Principal Supply Officers Organisation (namely,  Supply Com-mittee No. IV) for early examination from the supply aspect and report.    THE SUB-COMMITTEE agreed-    (1)  That the organisation of Air Raid Precautions should be governed by thefollowing principles :     (a)  Measures for safeguarding the civil population against the effects of air           attack must be organised locally.  The Government will issue general           instructions based on  expert study of the problems, will be ready to           give  ecjiiiical and administrative advice, and to afford financial assist-           ancl^fo. fticToxtont indicated in the conclusions that follow.  But, the           above activities  on  the  part of  the Central  Government cannot           compensate for the failure of any district which is liable to attack to           take effective measures on its own account.    (b)  It  is not possible to  contemplate,  in  connection with  civil  air raid pre-           cautions, such a state of preparedness in all respects in time of peace,           as is adopted for the pre-war preparedness of the fighting services.    (c)  Air raid  precautions  may  properly  be  initiated, and pre-emergency           arrangements for air  raid  precautions may properly be augmented,           during a period of tension, without prejudice to  the peaceful settle-           ment of any negotiations that may be in progress,  and independently           of any active defence preparations.    (d)  In view of (b) and (c) above, the  general preparations in the sphere of           passive defence should (subject to the exceptions specified in (g) and           \h) below) be worked out by local authorities on the basis that they may           assume a period of warning to  complete their precautionary measures           before the outbreak of Avar.   The length of this period  will  vary           according to the probability,-or otherwise, of the locality in question           being subjected to air attack at the outset of hostilities, and will be           determined by the Government on the merits of  each  case.    It is           unnecessary, at  the present time at any rate, that the length of the&apos;.           period be communicated to Local Authorities.    (e)  The scale of preparedness to be aimed at by local authorities, both before           and during the warning period, will also depend on the liability of the           area in question to early attack, and will also  be  determined by the           Government on the merits of each case.    (/)  It-is recognised that, in deciding to work on an assumed warning period,           there is a risk of  that warning being given  on the threat of an           emergency which may not materialise, with the result that expenditure
           reserved until the  warning period or a large part of it may thus          -be  undertaken  unnecessarily.   But, this  risk is  to  be accepted as           preferable to the only possible  alternative, which is, to incur the same           expenditure, or more, iri advance.    (g) Plans for emergency  fire brigade measures for London and other areas           most liable to incendiary attack  must be worked out to secure the           highest possible degree of preparedness.  In these services and areas           the provision of equipment and appliances cannot be  postponed until           the warning period.    (h) The principle of the warning period does not apply to plans for the           distribution of  civilian  respirators.  These must be prepared on the           assumption that the period for the completion of their distribution is           a matter of hours and not days.    (2) That, so far as peace-time expenditure is concerned    (a) The Government should be prepared to make a contribution towards the           cost of local authorities&apos; air raid precautions and emergency  fire           brigade  measures, so far  as  their schemes,  and  the contemplated           expenditure thereon, are approved by the Secretary of State for Home           Affairs, after detailed examination by the Home Office, in the light of           the scale and degree of preparedness which is  considered appropriate           to each case  (vide  Conclusions 1 (d) and (e) above).    (6) That the general basis on which the Exchequer assistance should be given           towards the various services (apart from items already accepted as a           national charge) should be as follows :             (i)  Staff,  organisation and maintenance costs, and training, storage                 and other accommodation not specially excepted.                     60 per cent, of approved expenditure.           (ii) Protection of  or precautions  in buildings  housing public services                 which would have to be maintained as part of the air raid                 precautions, or emergency fire brigade organisations.                     60 per  cent,  of approved expenditure, or,  in the case of                          existing grant-aided services, the ordinary grant.           (iii); Provision  or adaptation of buildings to  provide first-aid posts,                 anti-gas  cleansing accommodation at depots of A.P.P. Services,                 auxiliary fire stations and fire  posts, &amp;c.                     60 per cent, of approved expenditure.           (iv) Training of auxiliary firemen.  Grant per man trained at  3, or                 a rate to be fixed.           (v) Accumulation of equipment  for emergency fire fighting and air                 raid precautions  services (over and above peace-time require-                 ments) (including possible provision for warning signals  and                 for  extinction or obscuration of street  lighting).                     60 to 100 per cent, (generally by way of provision in kind),                          according to whether the article does or does not serve                          any useful purpose  in peace time.           (vi) Provision  of  supplementary water supplies  for  emergency fire                 fighting.  (Not including expenditure by the water undertaking                 itself.)                     Normally 60 per cent.    (3) That  the Secretary  of  State for  the  Home  Department  should beauthorised to open negotiations on the basis of the preceding conclusion either with the various associations representing local government authorities or, in thefirst instance, with Local Authorities selected  by the  Home  Secretary afterconsultation with the Ministers concerned.    (4) That the extent to which the Secretary of State for  Scotland  should be associated with  the Secretary of State for the Home Department in the abovenegotiations should be left to the Ministers concerned.    (5) That no public announcement of the Governments intentions as regardsexpenditure on  air  raids precaution preparations should  be made  until thenegotiations with the local government authorities have taken place.
    (6) That so far as immediately pre-war expenditure is concerned, it shouldbe expected that, except  as  regards existing  grant-aided services, increasedExchequer assistance will  be given towards the cost of completing the air raidprecautions schemes in the warning period.    (7) That,  so far as war time expenditure is concerned, financial and other problems involved, should be left for discussion at some future date.    (8) That  payment of compensation for injury  to  Air  Raid  Precautionpersonnel is part of  a  wider  question  and should  be  reserved for  separate consideration by the Chancellor of the Exchequer, the  Secretary of State for theHome  Department and the President of the Board of Trade (who is concernedfrom the point of view of compensation for material damage) and further report.    (9) That a  special Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial defence should be set up as soon as possible, to examine and report on the whole questionof the measures that should be taken, and the expenditure that would be involved,to ensure the maintenance and safeguarding  of those  public services which arevital  to the effective prosecution of  war  and  the life of  the   community,e.g., electricity, water, &amp;c.    (10) That the composition and terms of reference of the above Sub-Committeeshould be left to the decision of the  Minister for Co-ordination of Defence, inconsultation with the Home Secretary and. other Ministers principally concerned.    (11) That the question of the provision of  500 million sand bags as a pro-tection against blast and splinters from high explosive bombs, should  be referredto the Principal  Supply Officers Committee organisation, for urgent considerationfrom the supply  aspect and early report.    (12) That the above recommendations together with Paper No.  D.P.R. 181and the minutes  of the discussion should be submitted to the Cabinet in accordancewith Cabinet 13 (37), Conclusion 11 (6).2 Whitehall Gardens, S.W. 1,      April 8, 1937.

</content>
</cab>
