<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 576-581</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
(THIS  DOCUMENT- IS THE PROPERTY OP HIS BRITANNIC            MATES TY&apos; S GOVERHMSM?&apos;) .COPY NO.SECRET. CP. 150/37.                CABINET                    INDIA     Appreciation of the Political Situation, bythe Government of India, dated  27th May, 1937.     Circiliated for the information of the Cabinetby the Secretary of State for India.
Confidential appreciation of the  Political Situationin India,  dated the 27th May, 1957,  issued on the    authority of the Secretary of State for India.     Operations against recalcitrant tribesmen in Wasiristancontinue, but the situation shows signs of improvement.A number of raids have been carried out by tribesmen insettled districts, in which several Hindus were kidnappedor killed and shops looted or burnt.   The chief - concentra-tion of hostile tribesmen has however been in the lowerKhaisora Valley and in the vicinity of Rasmak.   On 19thApril, a party ox 8 men from a picquet near Rasmak wasambushed and killed, their rifles being taken away by theenemy.   On 22nd April, the General Officer Commanding in chief, Northern Command, assumed political control ofWaziristan.   On 24th April, a column moved into lowerKhaisora and remained there for seme days.   It madeseveral reconnaissances encountering large parties of theenemy and inflicting casualties.   Our casualties were light.     On the night of 27th April - 28th April, the tribes-men delivered a determined attack on the column&apos;s campat Aiche Kashkai and were repulsed with heavy casualties.The column withdrew  on 1st May and the scouts &quot;post inLower Khaisora was evacuated at the same time.   Althoughthe enemy had suffered fairly heav3^ casualties during these operations, large numbers of hostile tribesmen were stillcollected in the Khaisora and Shaktu Valleys and theirvicinity and the faqir of Ipi was continuing his anti-Government propaganda unchecked.   On 11th May, therefore,further operations were initiated and a column iron Damdilmade a night march to Sham Plain.   Another column fromDosalli supported this move.   The enemy were out-flanked andsurprised and are believed to have suffered heavy casualties.     The. hostile tribesmen consist of a nucleus of Tori Khelsupported by contingents from other Yfasir sections and from
the Mahsuds and also by large bodies of tribesmen fromAfghanistan.   The Mahsud tribe as a wholo, however, has  notdeclared for the Ipi Faqir and only small parties or individuals have joined the hostile forces.   The attitudeof the Madda Khel Wasirs is also fairly satisfactory andthey have accepted, and very largely compiled with, theorders of the announcement in connection with the murder of lieutenant Beatty and have been allowed to resume their trade with the Bannu District.   The Bhitannis on the Bannuand Dera Ismail Khan border who also were giving troubleand participated in several raids have now acceptedGovernment terms and surrendered all except 9 of the 100hostages demanded from them.     Since the last appreciation was written there has been little change in the political situation.   In mostprovinces the new ministries have published their programmes,which include popular measures such as tenancy reform,revision of the land revenue system and schemes for theimprovement of education and the relief of rural indebtedness.Meanwhile, the Ministers have been active in giving their personal attention to local problems requiring an earlysolution and, in several cases, excellent results have followed from their intervention.   In the Punjab, Sindand in Bihar the Chief Ministers have made it their business to visit areas in which severe communal tension existed andhave used their influence to good effect in calmingexcitement.   In Bihar, the Chief Minister, at some personalrisk, succeeded in controlling a dangerous communal situation by his presence on the spot.   In Bombay&quot;, in the united provinces and in the Punjab, the visits of Ministers to agricultural areas suffering from the effects of hail ordrought have done much to restore confidence, since thesevisits have been followed by prompt revenue remissions.
                                                         3.     In Calcutta again, the Chief Minister and Ministerof Labour have been active in their efforts to bring together the parties in the Jute Mills strike, and have effected agreat improvement in the situation.     In the five Provinces in which the majority party has accepted office, meetings of the Assemblies and Councils havealready been held, and have shown that the Ministries havethe confidence of their legislatures.   In the remainingProvinces, where minority Ministries have been formed, ithas not been thought advisable to summon the Legislaturesuntil the electors and their representatives have had further opportunity to reflect on the position and to judge thepresent Ministries by their programme and achievement.     The constitutional situation in the minorityProvinces has been the subject of continuous debate in thePress and of numerous statements and interviews.     While great efforts have been made to justify theCongress demand for assurances or to show that they wereconstitutionally possible, it is evident that considerablemisgiving  exists, even among Congress supporters, and a widespread desire exists to find a solution  which wouldenable them to take office.   Hitherto, however, the desireto find a &quot;formula&quot; which would save the face of Congresshas outweighed more practical considerations.   &quot;Mr. Gandhihimself first tried to shift the burden of responsibility from himself by demanding an &quot;Arbitration Tribunal1&apos; to adjudicateon the competence of Governors to give the assurancesdemanded.   When further pressed he put forward the freshproposal that whenever a. Governor sees cause to disagree withhis Ministry on any matter involving his special responsibilityhis only remedy shoucl be to dismiss the Ministry forthwith.     Finally, the all-India, Congress Committee met atAllahabad at the end of April.   A number of prominentleaders were apparently in favour of office acceptance, but
                                                     yon                                                4.in the end Mr. Gandhi once again had to take  charge  oi  thediscussion in order to reconcile &quot;both right and left-vyingviews, and the eventual decision merely reaffirmed theoriginal demand that Congress ministries should be exempt from all checks but that of dismissal.     In the last appreciation mention was made of thestrength of the propaganda launched by the President tobreak the solidity of the Moslems and to induce the left-wing Moslem League to join Congress.   This campaign hasmerely led to acrimonious  controversy and perhaps as aresult of it communal tension has been more noticeablethroughout India.     Whatever the cause, the number of communal riots and disturbances which have occurred during the monththroughout India is disquieting.   The worst of thesetook place at B&amp;sti in the United Provinces, where in ariot arising  over the sacrifice of a bullock, 40 houses were burnt and 21 Moslems injured, and in the Patnadistrict in Bihar, where Moslems attacked the members ofa Hindu procession who had violated their promise to refrain from  music  and cries when passing  a mosque.   Inretaliation 2 Moslem women were murdered,  and  1 injured.Elsewhere  in  Bihar  and Sind where 3 Hindus were murdered,dangerous  situations have arisen while conditions Incertain areas  of the Punjab, mention  of which was madein  the last appreciation, are far from satisfactory.These communal outbreaks  are isolated and  there is noreason to  fear any  general agitation, but  they aresymptomatic of the  tension which exists between thetw o c ommuni t i e s.      The Coronation of His Majesty the King Emperorwas celebrated throughout India in  a  fitting manner.All reports hitherto  received indicate the widespread
interest and enthusiasm, aroused by the event.   The Congreoutwardly held aloof but offered no active opposition tothe celebrations, which once more illustrated theunchanging loyalty of the masses of India to the persons of their Majesties.

</content>
</cab>
