<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/269/0 images: 596-612</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Printed for the Cabinet.  June 1937.SECRET.                                                         Copy No.CP. 153 (37).CABINET.EXTRATERRITORIALITY IN CHINA.         Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.    THE United States Government have approached the Foreign Office with a request for the views and observations of His Majesty&apos;s Government with regardto the question  of  the resumption of negotiations  for the abolition  of  extra-territoriality in  China.  A copy of the State Department Aide-Memoire  of the30th March and of the interim reply sent to the United States Embassy on the14th May are annexed hereto (Annexes I and II).  As the question of  extra-territoriality in  China, has been  in abeyance since 1931, and has never therefore been considered  by the present  Government,  a decision of  the Cabinet on thequestion of policy involved is necessary before the further communication promisedin the Foreign Office letter of the 14th May is made to the United States Embassy.In  order  to  facilitate  consideration of  the  question  I  submit the  following observations :     2.  The extra-territorial system in China has  its origin  in the treaties of1842 and  1858,  the effect of  which  is that British  subjects are not subject toChinese laws or  the jurisdiction of Chinese Courts, but only to British law, andBritish Courts.  No Chinese law or regulation is binding on a British subjectunless  it  has been expressly accepted  and  made  binding  by His Majesty&apos;sGovernment.   A British subject must, however, have  recourse to  the ChineseCourts when seeking  redress against  a Chinese.  Since about  1900, when theChinese began in  earnest to modernise  their laws and political  institutionsgenerally, the existence  of foreign  privileges has,  on the  one hand,  made itprogressively more difficult for the Chinese Government to  regulate in a satis-factory manner a whole range of  activities connected with modern commerce, suchas companies, insurance,  banking, shipping, &amp;c,  and, on the other hand, Britishmerchants have found  that it was impolitic and,  indeed, impracticable  to insist on the complete immunity from Chinese regulations secured to  them in theory by treaty.  Compliance on  a  voluntary basis is,  to an increasing extent,  becomingthe normal practice, with the result that much of the old extra-territorial system has crumbled away.    3.  Political conditions in China for long  made  it  impossible to make  aserious  effort to  grapple with the  problem.   Chinese  impatience  broughtnationalism to a  head  in the  bitter  anti-British  boycott  organized by theKuomintang  (Nationalist  Party)  in 1925-26.  This  was the  prelude to theChamberlain  Memorandum of December 1926, in which His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment recognised the reasonableness of Chinese aspirations and  undertook to takedefinite steps to  meet them without  delay.  When the  Kuomintang established the present National  Government of  China  at Nanking in  1928  more  rapid progress was made.  Amongst other concessions tariff autonomy was  granted,Weihaiwei and  some  of the  smaller British  concessions  were &quot;given back andcontrol of  Customs revenue  was  relinquished.   In 1929 negotiations on thesubject of extra-territoriality were begun.  After some fencing at  long  rangethe details of an actual  treaty on the subject were  hammered out, and on the6th June,  1931,  a draft treaty was exchanged between Sir Miles Lampson and       9278   [15299]                                                 B
the Chinese Minister for Foreign Affairs.  Owing to a recrudescence of internal political troubles the negotiations were then suspended.   In the autumn of 1931the Japanese launched their attack on Manchuria and the whole question of extra-territoriality has remained in  abeyance ever  since.    4.  Since 1931,  in spite of their external difficulties, the Chinese have madegreat progress in political and constitutional matters.   Their Central Govern-ment  is now a reasonably efficient  administrative machine and its authority  isgenerally recognised over  the  greater part of  China.   Even  the  long-standingdivision between North and South has recently been healed.  There has also beengreat progress  in the codifying of the laws  and in  judicial administrationgenerally.   Finally, Japan,  whose  aggression  was  a  considerable   factor  inunifying China, seems to  have  abandoned coercion for conciliation and may nowbe found willing to  deal  with  China on a footing of friendliness and equality.    5.  At the recent plenary session of the Kuomintang a resolution was  passed in favour of taking up the extra-territoriality negotiations once more.   No action has as yet been taken by the Chinese Government on this resolution, but the subject is being ventilated in the press in China, and Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen has had some  conversations with  the Minister  for Foreign  Affairs.  He is strongly  ofopinion that we should be sympathetic to any approach made to us by the ChineseGovernment.  Copies of the three telegrams Nos. 106, 114 and 116 which we havereceived from  Sir H.  Knatchbull-Hugessen are annexed hereto  (Annexes  III,IV and V). In their Aide-Memoire of&apos;the 30th March last (Annex I), the UnitedStates Government expressed the view that negotiations on the subject of extra-territoriality might be taken up, and enquired whether, in our opinion, it wouldbe better for the foreign  Governments to take the initiative in approaching theChinese  Government, or whether it would  be  better  to await proposals from theChinese  Government.  An interim  reply was  sent to the United States Embassyon the 14th May (Annex II) favouring the latter course and promising a further communication as soon as a decision had been reached on the important points  ofpolicy involved.    6.   It has been the consistent policy  of  successive British Governments  toassist China in every way possible  in the political and economic development  oftheir country;  and if any request is now made to negotiate on the subject of extra-territoriality, it would not be either wise, or indeed possible, to depart from the friendly and sympathetic attitude that was adopted  in the previous negotiations,or to withdraw substantially from  the policy  of the  1931 draft.   In view of thegreater degree of unity and stability that China has achieved since  1931,  it isprobable that, as stated in the  United States aide-memoire, the Chinese will nowinsist upon an agreement of a  more far-reaching character.  It would  seem  best,however, to begin negotiations  on the basis of that draft, and defer considerationof details until after negotiations have actually begun.     7.   The draft treaty of 1931, of which a copy is. annexed  hereto, Annex VI,contained  a number of safeguards  designed to protect the persons, property andvessels  of  British subjects, on coming under Chinese jurisdiction, against the arbitrary exercise of power or uncertainty  as to the law to be applied.     8.   The principal safeguards  were that  British subjects  were to  be  subject only to the modern Courts of Justice and to the duly promulgated laws, ordinancesand regulations of China;  cases involving British subjects as defendant or accusedwere only to be tried in the modern courts at certain selected centres, and foreignlegal counsellors with watching and advisory functions were to be attached  tothese centres. Provided the safeguards of the 1931 draft could have been exercisedwithout offending Chinese amour-propre, it seems probable that the arrangements of  the draft treaty  would have proved a satisfactory substitute for the presentsystem.  China has, indeed,  now reached the stage  when, as  in other countries,diplomatic representations would  probably be the best protection for Britishsubjects against even the unfettered exercise of Chinese jurisdiction, but as publicopinion is not ready for such a root and branch solution, it would seem best, whennegotiations begin, to endeavour to secure the consent of the Chinese Governmentto as many of the safeguards of the 1931 draft as possible.     9.   The greatest difficulty arises out  of  the peculiar position of  the Inter-national Settlement at Shanghai,  the foreign administration of which dependsvery  largely upon the continued enjoyment of extra-territorial privileges by the
Powers chiefly concerned.   In the 1931 draft, the whole area of Greater Shanghai,.namely, the  International Settlement and the neighbouring  areas, which are largely inhabited by foreigners, was excluded from the operation of the treaty.Foreign  control  of  the   International  Settlement in  face  of  the  Chinesedetermination  to  undermine it,  is  becoming more  precarious,  and Britishpredominance in the municipal  administration of Shanghai tends  to  involve usin disputes between Chinese and Japanese which are not  really our concern.  Itis by no means certain, therefore, that the exclusion of Chinese authority  fromthe Settlement should  continue  to be an  object of British  policy.   In view,however, of the complexity of the problem  of Shanghai and the multiplicity ofthe national and other interests involved, it will be best to insist now, as in 1931,on complete exclusion so as to afford time for further negotiations.   In the 1931draft (article 16) Shanghai was excluded for ten years and Tientsin for five years.The United States Government, while willing to throw  in Tientsin altogether,considered that the time limit for Shanghai was a mistake.  It may be difficultto secure the assent of the Chinese to the indefinite exclusion of the whole area of greater Shanghai:  On the other hand, it is obviously unsatisfactory that nego-tiations should be carried on under  pressure  of a time limit,  and we might,therefore,  accept the American view on that point.    10.  If the  Cabinet  approve of the  adoption of  a  policy  on  the  lines recommended above, a further question arises in relation to Japan.   It wouldseem to be desirable,  in view of the  present conciliatory attitude  of  Japan, to propose to them to adopt the same attitude as ourselves  and the United Statesover the question of extra-territoriality.   His Majesty5s Ambassadors  at Pekingand Tokyo are being consulted by telegram on this point and also on the subsidiarypoints as  to time and method, namely, whether it would be better to  approach-Japan now or wait until actual proposals on the subject of extra-territoriality aremade by China, and whether  the approach should be made in Tokyo jointly withthe Americans or separately in London and Washington.                                                                     A.  E.    May 25, 1937.ANNEX 1.                               Aide-memoire.(Strictly Confidential.)    THE Department of State has  for some time been giving thought to thequestion of the possible practicability of there being made by  the  AmericanGovernment an approach to the Chinese  Government suggesting  resumption ofthe extra-territorial negotiations which were interrupted in 1931 and have since been in abeyance.   It has been the view of the Department of State that the praticability of making such an approach should be considered in terms Of thepossibility of the approach being made simultaneously and on  parallel lines bythe American and the British Governments.  It has been felt that the question ofthe opportuneness of such action at this time largely depends upon the questionwhether the resumption of such negotiations would be likely to have a disturbingeffect upon the general situation in the Far East with special reference to Sino-Japanese relations and the question of the likelihood of the Chinese government being willing to accept a draft of a  treaty following substantially the lines of theAmerican draft of the 14th July, 1931.   (The American draft  is  similar to theBritish draft of the 6th June, 1931, except for article 16 : Reserve Areas, a copyof which article, together  with a copy of the Department&apos;s memorandum wasenclosed in Mr. Atherton&apos;s letter of  the 25th July, 1931, to Mr. Orde.)    2.   The United States Embassy in China has reported that during the recentplenary session of the Central Executive Committee there was adopted a resolution calling upon the Chinese Government to conduct negotiations for the abolition of extra-territorial jurisdiction.   This resolution quoted in an instruction to  theExecutive Yuan on the 6th March, was published  in the National GovernmentGazette of the  9th March,  but otherwise it has received little publicity.  TheUnited States Embassy has received no intimation as to what action the ChineseGovernment will take in the matter.       [15299]                                                     B 2
    3.  The United States Embassy has expressed the view that the resumptionof extra-territoriality negotiations would not have a disturbing effect upon thegeneral situation in the Far East; also the further view that in the light of China&apos;request for unqualified abrogation of extra-territorial jurisdiction, as containedin the Chinese Foreign Office&apos;s note  of the 18th January, 1934, in regard to theSino-American Commercial Treaty of 1903, and in the light of the recent instruc-tion to the Executive Yuan referred to above, we could expect no great advantage from volunteering a proposal of a compromise, and that it would be better to awaita new initiative by the Chinese Government. The Embassy expressed the viewalso that China would insist upon an agreement for a much more far-reachingabrogation of extra-territorial rights than that envisaged in 1931.    4.  As it seems likely that pursuant to the instruction to the Executive Yuanreferred to above,  the Chinese Government will  in  due course approach the interested foreign Governments, there would appear to be a choice of two lines ofaction; one, that of a foreign Government or foreign Governments taking theinitiative in approaching the Chinese Government, and the other that of awaitinga move on the part of the Chinese Government.    5.  The Department feels that the question of extra-territoriality in china is a matter in which the British and American Governments have similar interestsand concern and  that the two Governments  might advantageously continue as inthe past to collaborate with each other.  The American Government would there-fore appreciate receiving the views and observations of the British Government inthe premises.    6.   It may be added that the American Government has not approached anyother Government in regard to the matter.     Embassy of the United States of America,            London, March 30, 1937.ANNEX II.                      Sir A. Cadogan to Mr. A therton.Dear Atherton,                                Foreign Office, May 14, 1937.     I MUST apologise  for the delay  in replying to the aide-memoire of the30th March which you left with the Foreign Office on the 1st April last.  As Iam not yet in a position  to  give you the  considered  views of  His Majesty&apos;sGovernment on the subject of extra-territoriality in China, I thought it would be best to send you an interim reply on the point as regards a foreign government or  foreign  Governments taking  the  initiative in  approaching  the  ChineseGovernment.     The Chinese Government might, we think, be actually embarrassed by suchan initiative; and  if, as seems possible, it had  the  effect  of encouraging an agitation among the more  irresponsible elements in Chinese political circles,  itmight make it more difficult for them to pursue a reasonable course if negotiations on the subject are begun.  We agree, therefore, with your Embassy in China  in thinking  that it would  be a  mistake for any  foreign  Government  to  take theinitiative, and we should prefer to await proposals from the Chinese Government.In the meantime, the important questions of policy involved will receive  our most careful consideration,  and the conclusions we may reach  will in due course becommunicated to you.  I need hardly say, of course, that we fully reciprocate thedesire  expressed in the  aide-memoire  for close collaboration between  our twoGovernments.                                                   Yours sincerely,                                                          A.  CADOGAN.
        Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen to Mr. Eden. (Received April 20.)(No. 106.)(Telegraphic.)                                      Nanking, April 20, 1937.    AFTER close of third plenary session it was disclosed that a resolution hadbeen adopted that negotiations should be reopened with Powers with a view toabolition of consular jurisdiction, and National Government is now circulatinginstruction contained in the text of an order addressed by National Governmentto Judicial and  Executive Yuans in pursuance of this.  The Executive  Yuan is directed to instruct Ministry for  Foreign Affairs to open negotiations.    Although no Chinese official has  mentioned  the  matter to me or to myinterested colleagues directly, it  is being ventilated in  the press and by public;negotiations are being followed with close interest.  It is possible,  therefore, thatwe may shortly receive a request from Waichiaopu for resumption of negotiations,and I think we  should consider what attitude we  should adopt towards such a request.    I will submit observations in subsequent telegram.    (Repeated, Saving, to Peking, commercial counsellor and Tokyo.)ANNEX IV.       Sir  H. Knatchbidl-Hugessen to Mr.  Eden. (Received April 23.)-(No. 114.)(Telegraphic.)                                     Nanking, April 23, 1937.    MY telegram No.  106.    It would be hopeless to wait for the ideal moment for concluding a treaty of extra-territoriality,  and my own  feeling is that  the  present is  probably as favourable a moment as we shall ever have  since the  Chinese are well disposed towards us,  and we stand  to get  much more credit  and possibly  better termsby adopting  a forward  attitude in  such circumstances than if we wait and haveto yield to pressure later on.   I am, however, strongly in. favour  of  receivingsympathetically any approach from the  Waichiaopu.    2.  It would, of course,  be understood that we  should  do nothing  unlessthe Chinese Government took the initiative  in approaching us  and  our attitude would depend on the nature of their  approach.    3.  We ought, I think, as a matter of tactics to take our  first stand on 1931draft.  Much,  however, has happened since then.and  the Chinese would not now  be likely  to accept  all  safeguards  and restrictions  included  in that draft particularly article 14 (personal status) and reservation of Tientsin.  I donot see that  it is necessary  now to  reserve Tientsin, and we should be preparedto face forthwith rendition.  There  would  be  another  wrangle over Shanghai,but I see no  solution other than  temporary reservation.    4.  Provided we keep  in step with the Americans with whom we should maintain close touch as in 1931 I do not think  we should allow our policy to be influenced  by other  Powers, though  we should keep them  informed.  It seems reasonable to calculate that the French and Japanese (the only  others who matter)should, after a short time,  find  themselves compelled in their  own interests to-come  into line; otherwise Chinese could make things very difficult for them.    5.  In general, my view  is that extra-territorial  system  is  becoming sodifficult to work in conditions of present-day China, and is such an obstacle to modern role of our traditional relations that sooner it is removed the better.  once the plunge has been taken  I do not  see we need seriously regret it.    6.  In my  own view there  would be much to be  said for letting foreignsettlements (Shanghai and Amoy) go  too.   The latter is not  much real value, andforeign control over the former is growing continually more  precarious,  moredifficult to maintain and a  greater potential source of  friction (especially with
the Japanese).   I realise, however,  that international  difficulties of giving upShanghai are probably,  at  present,  insuperable  though the question will  haveto be faced sooner or later.    7.  The  above observations are,  of course, only intended to be very general.It does not appear worth while to go into details unless we are approached.     (Repeated  to Tokyo, Saving, commercial counsellor, Commander-in-chief,General Officer Commanding and Peking.)ANNEX V.       Sir H. Knatchbull-Hugessen to Mr. Eden. (Received April 24.)(No. 116.   Confidential.)(Telegraphic.)                                     Nanking, April 24, 1937.    MY telegram No.  106 and my telegram No. 114.    In course of private conversation with Minister for Foreign Affairs at teawith me yesterday evening  I mentioned that I had been somewhat puzzled bysuggestions  in the press that question  of  extra-territoriality might be raised at this juncture.  Our attitude was  already sufficiently clear.   It was an intricatequestion with which I  was not familiar, but I would, of course, study it.  I had,however, not been disposed  to place too much faith in these press  reports as 1should have thought Chinese Government had enough on their hands at presentwithout raising extra-territoriality, which must inevitably produce friction withsome Powers.    2.  Minister for Foreign Affairs said that reports in question emanated fromTokyo, and he expressed view that they were intended by Japan as a red herring.He entirely agreed with my views.   China has  enough on her hands at presentwithout raising this.    (Repeated to Tokyo, Saving, Peking, commercial counsellor,  Commander-in-chief, General Officer Commanding.)ANNEX  VI.DRAFT  EXTRA-TERRITORIALITY  TREATY.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.Preamble.Article 1.ArticleArticleArticleArticleArticleArticleArticleArticleArticle 10.Article 11.Article 12.Article 13.Article 14.Article 15.Article 16.Article 17.Article 18.Article 19.Article 20.Article 21.Article 22.     Index (for  reference purposes only).                 ARTICLES.Transfer of Jurisdiction.Special Chambers.Legal Counsellors.Lawyers and Interpretation.Arrests, &amp;c.Taxation.Arbitration.Rights in Immovable Property.Immunity of Premises, &amp;c.Military Requisitions and Forced Loans.Shipping.Companies.Pending Cases.Personal Status.Rights of Residence.Reserved Areas.British Protected Persons.Non-discriminatory Treatment.Abrogation of Conflicting Clause in Existing Treaties-Authoritative French Text.Duration.l^RjljiiiCti tion.
ATTACHED DOCUMENTS.    A. Declaration regarding the Chinese Courts.    B. Declaration regarding the Judges of the Special Chambers.    C. Declaration regarding the Legal Counsellors.    D. Exchange of notes regarding article 8.    E. Exchange of notes regarding article 16.    F. Note regarding the publication of Chinese Codes, &amp;c.    G. Note  covering miscellaneous assurances.    H. Letter regarding Arbitration Law.  (Unpublished.)    I. Agreed Minute regarding immunity of  courts from external interference,           legal counsellor  of British nationality, lawyers, military requisitions,           court sentences and personal status.   (Unpublished.)                                 PREAMBLE.    His Majesty the King  of Great  Britain, Ireland and the British dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and    His Excellency the President of the National Government of the republic of China;    Being animated by the desire further to strengthen the bonds of friendshiphappily existing between  them, have resolved to conclude a Treaty for the purposeof readjusting matters relating to jurisdiction over  subjects  of His Majesty inChina and have for this purpose appointed as their Plenipotentiaries:     His  Majesty  the  King  of Great  Britain,  Ireland  and  the  british dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India :    For Great Britain and  Northern Ireland and all parts of the British Empire         which are not separate members  of the League  of Nations :    For the Dominion of Canada :For the Commonwealth of Australia :For the Dominion of New Zealand :For the Union of South Africa :For the Irish Free State :For India :    His Excellency the President of the National Government of the  republic of China :    Who,  having communicated their full powers, found in good and due form,have agreed as follows :                                 ARTICLE 1.    1.   Except  as  otherwise  provided  by the  present Treaty,  subjects ofHis Majesty  in  China  shall as  from its coming into force be subject  to thejurisdiction of the modern Chinese  courts of justice (Fa  Yuan) and to the dulypromulgated laws, ordinances and regulations of China.    2.   As regards rights of appeal and in all other matters of  procedure the modern  Chinese  codes of law and  procedure shall be applicable to subjects of
His  Majesty.  In all  legal  proceedings and in all matters  relating to  theadministration of  justice by  the  courts  subjects of His Majesty shall enjoytreatment not less favourable than that accorded to Chinese citizens.    3.  Except as provided in paragraph 4 of this article, subjects of His Majestyshall  not  be  subject to the jurisdiction of the police courts; nor shall  they besubject to the jurisdiction of any other tribunals than the modern Chinese courts of justice.    4.  Subjects of His Majesty shall be subject to the jurisdiction of the modernpolice courts  in case of  offences under the police offences code or under municipalregulations, but in each of such cases the penalty imposed by the court shall notexceed a fine of 15 yuan (dollars)  oi\; in the event of such fine not being paid,detention at  the rate of  one  day&apos;s detention for each yuan (dollar) of  the  fineimposed up to a maximum of fifteen days.                                 ARTICLE 2.    In the district courts in  Harbin,  Shenyang (Mukden),  Tientsin,  Tsingtao,Shanghai,  Hankow, Chungking,  Canton, Foochow, and Kunmin   (Yunnanfu),and in the high courts having appellate jurisdiction over such district courts, withthe exception of the Supreme Court, special  chambers shall be established fordealing with cases involving subjects of His Majesty as defendants or accused.All cases involving subjects of His Majesty, wherever resident, as defendants oraccused, except when they may be taken to the Supreme Court on final appeal, orwhen a subject of His Majesty concerned may elect, in writing, to submit himself to the jurisdiction of  the local modern court having jurisdiction over purelyChinese cases of a similar nature, shall be tried only before these special chambers.Any case involving a subject of His Majesty as defendant  or  accused, whichoriginates  within  the ordinary jurisdiction of a court  other than  one of those mentioned above, will (unless the subject of  His Majesty concerned elects other-wise,  as  provided above) be transferred for trial to the special chamber mostaccessible to the court within whose jurisdiction the case originates.                                 ARTICLE 3.    1.  To each of the special chambers provided in the preceding  article thereshall  be attached  foreign legal counsellors who  shall be selected and appointed as officials of China by the Chinese Government from among foreign legal experts of high moral character  who  possess the training, qualifications and practical experience necessary for appointment to judicial offices.    2.  The  names, and the amount and conditions of payment of salaries, of thelegal  counsellors will be communicated by the Minister for Foreign Affairs of theChinese Government to His Majesty&apos;s Diplomatic Representative in China,  andtheir  terms of service will  be governed by contracts in accordance with the attacheddeclaration by the Chinese Government.  They shall remain in office for a specifiedterm, unless  dismissed for cause duly  shown, and  shall otherwise receive theconsideration and respect due to the dignity  of their office.    3.  A legal counsellor need not permanently reside at the  place in whichthe special chamber of  the court to which he is assigned is established and thereshall  be  a flexible and practicable system of  administration of assignments inorder to ensure efficiency  in the employment of the said legal counsellors.    4.  The legal counsellors shall serve under the Minister of Justice, and shallbe deputed by the Minister of Justice for serving during  the hearing  of casesinvolving subjects of His Majesty as defendants or accused in the special chambersprovided in  the preceding article.   It  shall be the duty of the  legal counsellorsin these  cases to observe  the workings of the special chambers.  They shall  have access to the files  of the proceedings, and may present their views  in writing tothe judges, who shall give due consideration to the views thus expressed by thelegal counsellors.   Adequate arrangements  will be  made  for interpretation inorder to enable the legal counsellors to follow  and observe the proceedings incOurt. The legal counsellors shall forward to the Minister of Justice such reports as they may consider necessary, and copies of  these reports in cases involvingsubjects of His Majesty as defendants or accused will immediately be furnished by them to His Majesty&apos;s Diplomatic Representative in China upon request.
     5.   The legal counsellors shall be authorised to receive directly observations regarding the administration  of  justice,  the execution of  judgments, or the manner of the application of the law, and at the request of any of the interested parties shall  bring  such observations to the  notice of the Minister of Justice with a view to ensuring the observance of Chinese law.  Copies of such observa- tions in cases involving subjects of His Majesty will likewise immediately be furnished by  the legal counsellors to His Majesty V Diplomatic Representative in China upon request.     6.   Similarly the legal counsellors  shall be authorised to receive any other observations or complaints, including such as may be caused by domiciliary visits, expropriations, requisitions, or  arrests, &amp;c,  which observations shall be similarly dealt with.  Immediately  following any  domiciliary visits,  search, or  arrests, directly  affecting subjects of  His Majesty in any judicial district,  the  local authorities shall notify the legal counsellor  Avho shall be most accessible in point of time.     7.   In all cases in which subjects of His Majesty are involved as defendants or accused a foreign legal  counsellor shall be present at the hearings of the cases in both  the high and district  courts and judgment shall  be  reserved  until he has  made within three days after the conclusion  of the  trial such observations in chambers as he may desire  to  the  judges, and,  in the event of the judges failing  to give them due  consideration, the execution of the  judgment will be suspended until the observations of the legal counsellor have been considered by the Ministry of Justice, which  will take such action as it deems appropriate in the interests of justice.     8.   The Chinese courts referred to in  article 1  shall not begin to exercise jurisdiction over subjects of His  Majesty  until  the special  chambers  referred to in article 2 have been organised and until  the legal counsellors above mentioned have been appointed and installed in office as provided in this article.                                  ARTICLE  4.     1.  A subject of  His  Majesty appearing before  a Chinese court as party to a civil or criminal suit may employ duly  qualified Chinese or British or other foreign lawyers and interpreters, provided  in the case of the lawyers that they are  registered as such with the Chinese  Government, and such  lawyers, if of foreign nationality,  shall have the  same rights and privileges as Chinese lawyers appearing before the  court, and shall  be subject to  the laws and  regulations governing Chinese lawyers.     2.  Hearings shall  be in  the Chinese  language, but  the  court shall  take measures to ensure an  understanding of the  proceedings by all parties to the case and  have the assistance of  competent interpreters  if necessary.     3.  Subjects of His Majesty, parties to a suit,  or  persons  authorised by them shall, upon payment  of the usual official fees for such copy, have the right to obain certified copies of the evidence and  judgment  in such suit, and arrange- ments will, if necessary and where possible, be made for supplying on application and  on payment of appropriate fees translations of such  documents.     4.  In  all  judicial proceedings  in which subjects  of  His  Majesty  are summoned to appear, whether as parties to the case or witnesses, and in all court processes directly concerning subjects of His Majesty,  their names will,  in order to avoid mistakes and misunderstandings, be added in English to  the  Chinese text  of the summons, order or other court process.                                 ARTICLE 5.     1.  Except in cases of flagrante delicto,  subjects of His Majesty may  not be arrested, detained or imprisoned except  upon  an order formally issued by a modern court  of justice specifically stating the legal grounds on which,  and the offence for which, action  is authorised.  They shall within twenty-four hours after arrest, exclusive of legal holidays, be brought for hearing before the nearest modern court of justice competent to deal  with the case.  If there is  no com- petent modern court which can  be  reached in  this space of time, any subject of His  Majesty thus arrested will  be  brought before the nearest competent modern court with the least possible delay.      [15299]                                                        c
     2.  Any  subject of His Majesty  arrested or  otherwise  detained shall be permitted to communicate immediately with the nearest British consular officer,and he is  to  be afforded  all possible  facilities to  that  end.   British consular officers or their representatives shall be permitted to visit at all reasonable timesany subject of His Majesty under detention.     3.  Subjects of His Majesty under detention or sentence of imprisonmentwill only be detained or imprisoned in modern detention houses or modern prisonsor in other premises suitable for their detention or imprisonment.     4.  Subjects of His  Majesty serving sentences of imprisonment may bevisited by British consular officers or their representatives at all reasonable times.     5.  If any subject of His Majesty charged with any offence, the  maximumpenalty for which does not exceed imprisonment for six months, makes applicationbefore sentence  is given for the imposition of a fine instead of imprisonment,the Chinese court will grant such application.  In any such case the fine imposedwill not exceed  a maximum of one thousand yuan  (dollars).  Similarly, if anysubject of His Majesty charged with  any offence punishable under the Chinesecriminal code  by  imprisonment not exceeding one year, or fine,  makes applicationbefore sentence is given for the imposition of a fine instead of  imprisonment, theChinese court will grant such application.  In any such case the fine imposed willnot exceed a maximum of three thousand yuan (dollars).     6.  Except  in the case of crimes  punishable  by death or  imprisonment for life, immediate  release on bail  will, on application, be granted  to any subjectof His Majesty arrested or detained, unless the court has good reason  to believethat the accused may flee from justice after release.   The amount of bail will be reasonably proportionate  to  the  offence alleged.  Such  facilities for  release onbail will be granted to appellants until the sentence of the final appellate courtis given.     7.  Subjects of  His Majesty shall not  be subject to imprisonment for debt.If, however, it is  shown that a debtor is taking action which will render executionon his goods in China impossible, or if execution cannot be safeguarded by anyother means, he may  be detained in the manner provided for such cases by Chineselaw, in which  case the provisions of paragraphs 2 and 3 of this article will apply.     8  Except in such cases  as must under the relevant  Chinese law be heard in camera, all hearings of cases involving  subjects of His  Majesty will be opento the public, and  all persons interested  in  the hearings may be present asspectators.                                 ARTICLE 6.     1.  Subjects of  His Majesty shall be liable for the payment of such non-discriminatory Chinese taxation only as is  actually paid by all Chinese citizens who are liable therefor and is authorised  under the legally  enacted  and dulypromulgated laws,  ordinances and regulations of  the  central, provincial  and municipal Governments of China.     2.  Subjects of  His Majesty shall  be protected  against all taxation withoutlegal sanction and against irregular or discriminatory methods of assessing orlevying taxation; and such legal taxation  as is properly payable by subjects ofHis Majesty shall be enforced against them by no other process than that of actionin the competent modern Chinese courts of justice.     3.  Municipal taxation shall be imposed upon subjects of His Majesty  onlyin accordance with  duly  authorised municipal regulations  sanctioned by thecentral or provincial Governments of China.   The  proceeds of such municipaltaxation shall in general only be* expended on  relevant  purposes within the municipal area in question.     4.  No  methods of assessing liability  to taxation shall be employed except those prescribed  by  the duly  promulgated  laws, ordinances and regulations ofChina.  In cases of  disputed assessments,  the  party concerned shall be entitledto have the amount of his liability determined by the competent modern court ofjustice in accordance, with Chinese law..
    5.  Tax agreements  entered into  with subjects of His Majesty in theirseveral  capacities as individuals, merchants, firms,  partnerships or  companies,will be duly observed.                                 ARTICLE 7.    1.  The Chinese courts will recognise and, if necessary, secure performance of agreements wherever entered into by  subjects of His Majesty with one anotheror with other foreign nationals or with Chinese citizens for the settlement of civil or commercial controversies by arbitration.  The arbitrators  selected by  theparties  in accordance with such agreements may be of any nationality.    2.  The arbitration if held in China shall be conducted in accordance withthe procedure prescribed  by Chinese law.    3.  The Chinese courts will not entertain any application or  claim,  thesubject matter of which falls within the scope  of such an agreement for arbitra-tion, but will enforce awards made in pursuance of such agreements unless theaward is contrary to public order or good morals or is vitiated on other groundsrecognised   by  the  general  principles  of  law   as   understood  in  modernjurisprudence.                                 ARTICLE  8.    1.  All rights in immovable property  held by subjects of His Majesty inChina shall be recognised as valid and shall remain undisturbed subject to theexercise of the right of  eminent domain by  the  Chinese  Government.    2.  The property, whether movable or immovable, of subjects of His majesty in China shall not be expropriated or requisitioned except for reasons of publicinterest recognised by the law as such, and only after adequate compensation hasbeen paid.    3.  Any dispute regarding the amount of compensation  to be paid shall bedetermined by reference to the competent administrative organ or the competentmodern court of justice at the option of the subject of His Majesty concerned inaccordance with Chinese law.  Where such cases are brought  before the moderncourts of justice, the provisions of article 2 and article 3 of  the present Treatycovering the hearings of cases in which subjects of His Majesty are involved asdefendants will  apply.                                 ARTICLE 9.    The public  buildings and  private residences of subjects  of His Majesty inChina and their warehouses and business premises and factories, together withall their accessories,  articles and properties, shall be respected, and shall not be subjected to any  occupation, search or inspection,  and the  books and corres-pondence relating to their commercial transactions shall not be examined except-as specifically provided  for in non-discriminatory legislation legally enacted andduly promulgated.  Except in cases of flagrante  delicto premises occupied  bysubjects of  His Majesty  shall not be forcibly entered  except upon  a warrantformally issued by a  modern court of justice specifically stating the legal grounds on which action is authorised.                                ARTICLE 10.    Subjects of His Majesty in China shall not  be subjected to any form  ofmilitary service or to any  tax or levy imposed as a substitute for military service or to  military requisitions or contributions  of  any kind, nor shall they be  liableor compelled to subscribe, directly or indirectly, to any public loan or to any other form  of forced levy.                                ARTICLE 11.    British commercial vessels in Chinese ports or waters will comply with suchnon-discriminatory and legally enacted and duly promulgated Chinese regula-tions as are applicable to all commercial vessels.   They will not be subjected to any form of commandeering or requisition, nor will they be compelled to carry chinese troops or Chinese military supplies.  Such vessels will not be inspected, searched,boarded or subjected  to any kind of restraint by  Chinese armed military authority,      [15299]                                                       D
-except in the case of special emergency and only after due notification to and by arrangement with the captain of the vessel or the officer in charge.  They may notbe boarded by Chinese police, nor may any person be arrested on board any  suchvessel  except  upon a  warrant  formally issued by  a  modern  court of justicespecifically  stating the legal grounds  on which action  is authorised.  In theabsence of such a warrant, Chinese police may only board the vessel in case ofspecial emergency and only after due notification to and by arrangement with the captain of the vessel or the officer in charge.  In general, the treatment accorded to British  commercial vessels  shall be  in  conformity with  that accorded inrecognised international practice by maritime nations to vessels of other countriesin their ports  or  territorial waters.   The  present authority  of the ChineseMaritime Customs with regard to British commercial vessels, including authorityto search such vessels for the prevention of fraud  of smuggling, shall remainunimpaired.                    -                                 ARTICLE 12.     Companies, firms, partnerships and  corporations incorporated or organised in accordance with the laws of His  Majesty  and operating  in China  shall,provided they comply with the provisions of Chinese  law relating to the registra-tion of such organisations, be entitled to all the rights  and privileges enjoyed bysubjects  of His Majesty  under this  Treaty, including the rights enjoyed inChinese  courts, whether  as  plaintiffs, complainants  or defendants.    Suchcompanies,  firms, partnerships  or  corporations and  their branches, agencies orrepresentatives  shall not be subject to discriminatory treatment,  and as regardsnational, provincial and municipal taxation shall only be taxed in proportion tothe amount of capital actually  employed respectively in China, in the provinceOr in the municipality, or in respect of the profits and revenues&quot; which they  have actually  earned respectively in China, in the province or in the municipality.-Reciprocally Chinese companies, firms, partnerships or corporations shall enjoy inthe United Kingdom, as regards taxation,  the  right  to carry on business and access  to the courts, treatment not less favourable than that enjoyed by companies,firms,  partnerships or corporations  of the most favoured foreign country.                                 ARTICLE 13.     Cases terminated in the British courts in China  before the coming into forceof this Treaty shall not be reopened, and all final judgments or decisions renderedin such  cases shall be executed  in  any part of China by the Chinese judicialauthorities.  Cases pending before the British courts in China at the time of thecoming into force of this Treaty shall continue until judgment  is pronouncedin the said courts,  the jurisdiction of which shall remain  in full force for thispurpose; and  the Chinese authorities undertake  to lend any assistance requested by the British  authorities in this connexion.  All  such pending cases shall be finally disposed of and wound up within a period of  six months from the date ofthe coming into force of  this Treaty, upon the  expiration of which period anyCases still pending shall be dismissed or turned over to the Chinese courts foradjudication.   It is understood  that after  the coming into force of the presentTreaty no actions  against subjects of His Majesty will be  entertained by theCompetent Chinese courts in respect of acts which took place prior to that date for which they were not liable according to English law, but for which they mightbe liable according to  Chinese lav/.                                ARTICLE  14.     1.   In  all matters of personal status, among which are included all questions relating  to marriage, conjugal rights,  divorce,  judicial separation, dower,paternity, affiliation, adoption, capacity, majority, guardianship; trusteeship^ andinterdiction, and in  all matters relating to succession  whether  by will or onintestacy, and to the distribution and winding up of estates and family law ingeneral,  English law will be applied by the Chinese courts as regards subjects ofHis  Majesty in China.     2.   All such cases of personal  status where only subjects of His Majesty areconcerned will, at the option of any of the parties concerned, be dealt with outsidethe jurisdiction of the Chinese courts.
    3.   British consular officers shall take temporary possession of the estates inChina of deceased subjects of His Majesty.  They shall administer the same inall cases where no objection to such administration has been filed by an interestedparty in writing at a British consular office in China within ninety days afternotice of death has been published by the competent consular office.  Where suchobjection is filed the provisions of paragraph 1 or 2 will apply as the case may be.In cases of intestacy where there is no kin the immovable property of the deceasedwill be disposed of  in accordance with the laws of China.    4.   In all the above-mentioned matters the principles of private internationallaw willbe  likewise applied by the courts  of  the United Kingdom as regardsChinese citizens without any discrimination against them as  compared with the nationals of  any other country.                                ARTICLE 15.    The existing rights enjoyed in China by subjects of His Majesty to travel,reside, establish firms, open branches,  acquire or lease property, work and engage in industry or commerce, shall remain unimpaired.                                ARTICLE 16.    1.   Subjects of His Majesty in the area of  Greater Shanghai, as shown on the attached map,  shall not be amenable to the jurisdiction of the Chinese courtsduring a period of five years from the date of the coming into force of the presentTreaty.   It is agreed that discussions will be entered into within the said periodof five years on the subject of the arrangements to be made at the end of the saidperiod.   In  the absence  of  a  settlement of  the question of  jurisdiction  by negotiation and  agreement between the High  Contracting Parties at  any time after the expiry of the said five years, subjects of His Majesty shall not becomeamenable to the  jurisdiction  of the Chinese courts until the expiry of  ten years from the date of the coming into force of the present Treaty.    2.   Subjects of His Majesty in the area at  Tientsin shown on the attachedmap  shall not be  amenable to the  jurisdiction of the Chinese courts  until the expiry of five years from the date of the coming into force of the present Treaty.    3.   Subjects of His Majesty in the areas above specified shall be liable for thepayment of  Chinese taxation, as provided  in article 6 of  the  present Treaty,provided such taxation is equally  paid by Chinese  citizens and  other foreign nationals in the said areas.                                ARTICLE 17.    In the present Treaty the expression &apos;&apos; Subjects  of His Majesty &apos;&apos; shall bedeemed to include persons under His Majesty&apos;s protection.                                ARTICLE 18.    Subjects of His Majesty shall enjoy in all matters for which this Treatyprovides all exemptions from Chinese jurisdiction which may be enjoyed by the nationals of any other country and  shall be  subjected to no discriminatory treat-ment in regard to  taxation, judicial or any other matters  for which this Treatyprovides, as  compared with  the  nationals of any other country.   ReciprocallyChinese citizens shall enjoy in the  United Kingdom in  respect of all the abovematters treatment not less favourable than that enjoyed by subjects or citizens of the most favoured foreign country.                                ARTICLE 19.    The provisions in the existing treaties between the High  Contracting Partieswhich are in conflict with the present Treaty are hereby abrogated.                                ARTICLE 20.    The present Treaty has been drawn up in Chinese and in English pendingthe preparation of a French text on which the two High Contracting Parties will agree as soon as possible  and which will  be authoritative in case of divergencebetween the  Chinese and English texts.      [15299]                                                     D 2
                                ARTICLE 21.    1.  The present Treaty shall be binding during a period of ten years fromthe date of its coming into force.    2.  Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph  1  of this article,  theprovisions  of  article 2 of the  Treaty relating  to the  special chambers  to beestablished by the Chinese Government and those of article 3 relating to the legalcounsellors to  be appointed by the Chinese Government shall remain in force forsuch period as the Chinese Government may deem appropriate not being less than five years.    3.  Either  of  the High &quot;Contracting Parties may demand that on  theexpiration of  the said period of ten years the provisions of the Treaty shall be revised.  Notice of such a demand shall be given at least twelve months beforethe expiration of the said period of ten years and negotiations shall thereupon be entered into for the purpose of effecting such revision.  If no agreement is reached in regard to such revision  within this period,  the Treaty shall become null  andvoid.    4.  In  case neither of the High Contracting Parties shall have given  noticeat least twelve months before the expiration of the period of ten years of his intention  to terminate the Treaty,  it shall remain in  force  subject to twelvemonths&apos; notice of termination by either party at any time after the expiry  of thefirst ten years.                                ARTICLE 22.    1.  The present Treaty shall be ratified by the High Contracting Parties inaccordance with their respective constitutional methods.    2.  The ratifications shall be exchanged at Nanking.    3.  The present Treaty  shall come into force as soon as  the ratifications ofHis Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyondthe Seas, Emperor of India, in respect of each and all the members of the Leagueof Nations  as enumerated in the Preamble of the  present Treaty,  and of  HisExcellency the President of the National Government of the Republic of China,shall  have been exchanged.                                 ANNEXES.               A. Declaration by Minister for Foreign Affairs.    With reference to the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I have the honourto declare on behalf of my Government that the Chinese courts will ensure  to thepersons and  property of subjects  of His Majesty due protection in accordancewith international law and the general practice of nations.               B. Declaration by Minister for Foreign Affairs.   . With reference to the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I have the honourto declare on behalf of my  Government that the chief judge of any of the specialchambers provided in article 2 of the said Treaty shall be the president  of thecourt to which the chamber belongs.  Other judges of the special chamber aswell as its procurators shall be selected from among legal scholars with thoroughtraining and practical  experience and  with a broad knowledge  of the generalconcepts of modern jurisprudence.   Their names, ranks, and salaries will be made known to the public and they will not be removed from office without cause.               C. Declaration by Minister for Foreign Affairs.    With reference to the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I have the honourto declare on behalf of my Government  that the legal counsellors referred to inarticle  3 of  the  above-mentioned  Treaty will be engaged and employed by theChinese Government  under contracts specifying in detail the duration and theterms of their service, including in the case of each  foreign legal counsellor total
emoluments of not less than   3,000 a year, to be paid in quarterly instalments,the said quarterly instalments to be deposited in  such bank or banks as the legalcounsellor concerned may indicate six months ahead of the time when such instal-ments fall due.    I have further the honour to declare that among the legal counsellors above referred to there will also be  included one legal counsellor of Chinese nationalityto be  similarly  selected  and  appointed  from  among Chinese legal  expertspossessing the same training,  qualifications, and experience, and that this Chineselegal counsellor will have the same functions as  the other legal counsellors,                          D. Exchange of Notes.     His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister to the Minister for Foreign A fairs.Sir,    With reference  to article 8 of the Treaty signed between us to-day, I havethe honour  to request your  Excellency&apos;s confirmation  of my understanding asfollows : &apos;    All legal Chinese land transfer fees leviable under regular Chinese legislation as provided in article  6 of the said Treaty,  where properly payable  under such legislation, will be paid by subjects of His Majesty on account of land transactionseffected after the  date of the  signature of the said Treaty.  But no demands willbe made by the Chinese authorities for the payment of such land transfer fees ontransfers of land to or from subjects of His Majesty prior to the date of the signature of the said Treaty and rights  in immovable property held  by  subjects of His Majesty shall not be called in question on  account of  non-payment of suchtransfer fees in the past.  All rights in immovable property now held by subjects of His Majesty in China  shall not be questioned unless they are invalidated onlegal grounds as  the result of a decision rendered by a modern Chinese  court ofjustice, but subjects of His Majesty will comply with the laws of China in regardto such property.  In  reaching their decisions in such cases the  Chinese  courtswill take into consideration the treaty provisions and  laws and the customs and practices in various parts of  China which existed at the time when the propertyrights were acquired.  The existing rights of subjects of His Majesty to acquire,hold, and freely dispose of and transfer their rights  in immovable property inaccordance with the laws of China will remain unimpaired.       Minister for Foreign  Affairs to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister.Sir,    I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your  Excellency&apos;s note ofto-day&apos;s date which reads as follows :                              &quot;(Quote note in  full) &quot;    I have  the honour to confirm your Excellency&apos;s understanding as set forth above as correct.                          E. Exchange of Notes.           His Majesty&apos;s Minister to Minister for Foreign Affairs.Sir,    With reference to article  16 of the Treaty  concluded between us to-day, Ihave the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty&apos;s Government in theUnited Kingdom are prepared to support immediate negotiations for a  solutionof the questions of the extra-settlement roads  at Shanghai subject to satisfactory arrangements being made in  regard to the policing and maintenance of  the saidroads and the payment of rates and provision of municipal services in the areasin question.    I have further the honour to declare that His  Majesty&apos;s Government  in theUnited Kingdom are prepared to  enter  immediately into  negotiations for therendition of the British concession at Canton  on the understanding that all  public and private property rights and  interests will be duly safeguarded in the termsof such rendition.    I have the honour to request your  Excellency&apos;s confirmation of my under-standing that the jurisdiction of  the British courts in the areas specified inarticle 16 above referred to.will continue in force pending the time when  subjects
of His Majesty in the said areas become  amenable to the jurisdiction of theChinese courts; and further that under the provisions of article 18 of the Treatysubjects of His  Majesty resident in areas in China where the nationals of. any country may be exempt from Chinese jurisdiction will enjoy all such exemptionsfrom Chinese  jurisdiction, as may be enjoyed by the nationals of any country.       Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister.tit,  &apos;.           .. ,/  . it  t              .        ,        ,  &apos;     I have  the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency&apos;s note ofto-day&apos;s date which reads as follows :                            &quot; (Quote note in full)&quot;     I have the honour to take  due note of your Excellency&apos;s declarations and to confirm your understanding quoted above as correct.F. Note from. Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister.Sir,   .  With reference to the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I have the honour,in reply to  your Excellency&apos;s enquiry, to state that  the  work of compiling the modern Chinese codes  and laws has now  been completed and  that a copy of theSsu.  Fa Li Kuei of the National Government issued by the Judicial Yuan con-taining the texts of all the  important codes, laws, ordinances and  regulationspromulgated down to the present time, a  revised edition of which is in course of preparation, will be transmitted to your Excellency as soon as possible.  I have further the honour to inform your Excellency that, with a view to enabling foreign nationals in China  to familiarise themselves with Chinese  laws and judicial pro-cedure, translations of the principal Chinese codes, laws, ordinances and regu-lations are being made and will be placed  on sale, such translations being checkedby and prepared under  the aegis of the  competent department of the ChineseGovernment.   It is, of course, understood that  Chinese is and remains the onlyauthoritative text  of Chinese codes, laws, ordinances and regulations.G. Note from Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister.Sir,    With reference to the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I have the honourto assure your Excellency as follows :      Where subjects of His Majesty are  involved in  minor incidents or offencessuch  as infractions of municipal regulations, motor  car  cases, and so on, theChinese police will, as  far as may be practicable, assure themselves of the identity of the individuals concerned by taking their names and  addresses and will notarrest them or detain them in police stations.     It is understood that the liability of  a subject of His Majesty standing bailfor a party involved in court proceedings will in all cases be limited to the amountof actual bail fixed by the court.     The qualifications of British professional  men,  such as doctors, charteredaccountants, architects and engineers, will, if necessary, on production of properevidence including registration with the Chinese Government where such fegistra-tiori is required by Chinese law, be recognised by the Chinese courts.   .  In connexion with legislation providing for the  examination of commercialbooks and correspondence, it is understood that in the case of British firms thecertificates of  duly qualified chartered accountants will be accepted with a viewto dispensing, as far as may be practicable, with such examination.H.-Note from. Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Minister.                               (Unpublished.)  .My dear Sir Miles  Lampson,     With reference to article 7 of the Treaty concluded between us to-day, I havethe honour to confirm your Excellency&apos;s understanding that the Chinese MediationLaw (Chinese characters) of the  20th January, 1930,  has  no application tc*arbitration agreements of the kind contemplated in the said article.
I. Agreed Minute of Interview between the Minister for Foreign Affairs and    His Majesty&apos;s Minister with reference to the Treaty concerning the Readjust-    ment of Matters relating  to Jurisdiction over Subjects of  His Majesty    in China.                               (Unpublished.)    Referring  to  the Declaration attached to the  Treaty to the effect that theChinese courts will ensure to the persons and property of subjects of His Majestydue protection  in accordance with international law and the general practice ofnations, Dr. Wang assured Sir Miles Lampson that it was to be understood that-the said Chinese courts assuming jurisdiction over subjects of His Majesty wouldbe strictly immune from all external interference by any non-judicial authority.    2.  Referring to the arrangements provided in.the Treaty for the employ-ment by the Chinese Government of foreign legal counsellors, Dr. Wang assuredSir Miles Lampson  that at least one of the  said legal counsellors would be ofBritish nationality.    3.  Sir Miles Lampson, referring to the matter of the registration of Britishlawyers, enquired whether he was correct  in understanding that it was  not theintention of the Chinese Government to require that duly qualified British lawyersappearing on behalf of subjects of His Majesty in the Chinese courts should havea knowledge of the Chinese language or possess diplomas of Chinese law  schools.Dr. Wang replied that the above understanding was correct.    4.  Sir  Miles Lampson,  referring to  article 10  of  the  Treaty,  assuredDr.  Wang that it was  to be  understood  that Chinese  citizens in  the  UnitedKingdom would enjoy in respect of the matters referred to in the said article thesame exemptions as were enjoyed by the subjects or citizens of any other foreign country.     5.  Dr.  Wang informed Sir Miles Lampson, with reference to clause 5 ofarticle 5 of the Treaty, that it was  of course  to be understood that the courtswould not intentionally  discourage  such applications by unnecessarily imposingthe maximum fine.     6.  Referring to clause 2 of article  14 of the  Treaty,  Dr. Wang  assuredSir Miles Lampson that it was to be understood that where such cases were dealtwith outside the jurisdiction of the Chinese courts they would be  dealt with bythe competent courts of His Majesty.

</content>
</cab>
