<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 309-318</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
as doou:-. ..;t is Tig prop;.,rty. op, his bijta&amp;jic iajpsty^ goyi:^m:ut J61 /,: A i;   C A.5 I II .&apos;J, T.HOLDING UP.. Cl TK.&quot; SUPPLY. OX. GOAL. TO -ITALY.1 inutvb of tiu 49 th,voting of thy MilitaryliyprcsXht a&apos;t i&quot; &quot;03,,- -SuprV r Counoil.&quot;held atVifsTUlTis7 on&quot;r,atu&apos;r dcyy&quot; g.Gth&quot;&apos;bctot?ay 1916.&quot;,&quot; at 10 hours..At3f. T.pra:;c]:ncral pelin,i?jorLaborderegheat p:.utai:t .ITALY.AFRICA.? aj-General &quot;on.C.J.     General General TaskerSaok-ille- cat, CJ- ,G.     di liobilant,       H,Flies, G.C.H.G.G ... , G.IK   ATTeiTDAiiCS.Brig-General K..v, ColonelStudd,  C.P,, CP .G., 3.3.0. Xusinelli .Prig-General P.B,Lochridge,tatainiorti er,SLflh. TAhlAT.Jviajor A.i..Caccla,l .V.0. Captain A.Captain E, Abraham. . Jones.Lieut-Colonel \7.B.Wallace.&apos;I:. TL-Ayi- a-iLT L3m.Officer Interpreter A. Pillot.c: AI.il;All&quot;:General BLLIP.A G I P D A.HOLDING UP OP TIT SUPPLY OP COAL .T0 ITALY.GJPSIiAL PPLI1I said that the Italian military Representativehad circulated a.memorandum from the IntersAllied   ,Transportation Council, and c-lso a draft Joint Note, inregard to the holding up of the- supply of coal to Italy.He would no-,  ask General di Robilant to give any additionalinformation he might have on the subject.GI^LRAL di liOPILAPT said that the supply of cod for Italy vanof the utmost importance to the Italian railways andindustries, and for heating purposes.The matter had already formed the subject of manystudies, and had been examined vith caro by the Inter-Alii&apos;.d Transportation Council; but there vaa a transportcrisis at the present time in prance attributable tomilitary operations or lack of personnel.     as a result,the supply to Italy va&amp; stopped, not for lack of coal,but-1-
but for lack of transport.     The responsible authoritieshad felt themselves obliged, for a short time, to hold upconsignments, and this decision had caused considerabledismay in Italy.   This feeling had been shared by theI:embers of the Inter-Allied Transportation Council, whohad set up a sub-committee to enquire specially into thismatter,      The Council had adopted a resolution on the2lst Oetober, and this was appended to the draft Joint Notesubmitted to the. j ilitary Representatives.(For Text of Resolution of the Intor-AlliedTransportation Council, see Anncxuro &quot;A&quot;).General di KObilant added that he had referred thisquestion to General Eelin, and a marked improvement hadsince taken place oving to transportation having beenresumed.   This particular question had now been settled.But the Transportation Council&apos;s resolution alsoconcerned the future.     This resolution would have theadvantage, if adopted,.of preventing further stoppages.The Transportation Council recommended that the BritishGovernment should be asked to forward coal by sea. toItalian ports whenever there -.;;:s a stoppage of transportsation by rail.   As any decision on this question con-cerned the Supreme y.er Council he thought it his duty tosubmit a draft Joint Hote to the ;.ilitary Representativesand ask them to. confirm what the Inter-Allied Transport-ation Council had already agreed to.GT.y?.&quot;;AL SAC&quot; VILIE-UE3T said that in connection with the opinionof the Inter-Allied Transportation Council concerning theconsignment of a larger quantity of coal by scr,, his colleagueswould remember that this question had already been studiedby the Fritish Government vho had concluded that they couldnot provide for any increase.   He did not knev/ that thesituation had altered, and did not see the necessity of asecond request.V/ith regard to the use of the strategic reserveconcentrated in Italy, it could not be supposed for a momentthat anyone would think of removing any portion without theauthority of the Governments concerned.As the Italian i ilitary Representative had said, theposition had improved because the forwarding of coal toItaly had been resumed.   The draft Joint ftotc before them.   only aimed, therefore, at preventing further interruptions.GI^hAL di ROPIliutf said that there wore two questions to beconsidered,   firstly, to prevent further interruption intransportation, and secondly, to replace the coal Italy wasshort of, owing to the present deficiency, i.c, 150,000 tons.They had their strategic rusorvc of 150,000 tons, butthey were unable to use any of it,     Hot only should transportstart again, but they should in addition get tho coal theywere short of through the present delay.GBKSRAL SAC&quot; VILLB-y.T.ST said that it v;as not a question of ashortage of coal, but c shortage of transport.OfflJERAL PI ROPILAHT said that; to put the matter shortly,, owingto the suspension of transport, their deficiency had goneup to 150,000 tons; it must now be made good, and m view oftlr. transport crisis on land Italy requested that this coalshould, be sent by sea.GUh ML SACKVILLE-^IST
3.ffpffljflAL SA(UCy:H^-\mniT   said that he saw no Rejection to forwarding^tne^iMe^-AlireTYi^ui^portjition Council&apos;a Memorandum hut hedid not foel able tc aocept the draft Joint Ncte as it wasnow worded.gggRAL BLISS   said that the situation aeemad to him tc be as follows:Owing to various causes, largely sickness of personnel,there had be*n a suspension cf the daily consignments of coaltc Italy fixed in a previous programme.   This stoppage had .caused a deficiency of 150,000 tons below the expected amounts.The French Government had immediately taken measures- toprevent this stoppage and other measures were contemplatedto remedy.this state of things.   Consignments had beenresumed, but the deficiency was still 150,000 tons.   It wasnecessary:  therefore, to. replace these 150,000 tons and tccome to seme arrangement to obviate further suapensiuns.Tc rnajie up the deficiency in question, the draft JointNote before them considered the question of asking theBritish&apos;Government bo&apos;..auwent the proportion of tonnageallocated to coal&apos;,&apos; This could only be done by British tonnageand they knew from a previous inquiry that, if the situationhad not changed, this tonnage could not be increased.   If. thedeficit was tc be made good, it should be made good by someether m&apos;?anB than these considered by the Transportation Counciland it was necessary to discover these means and tc suggest,them, in order that the  Tote should assist the Governments.So fax as the question cf preventing further suspensionswas concerned, it was clear that the resolutions cf the WarCabinets and cf the Transportation Scuncil were drawn up insufficiently definite terms to avoid them.   They should notlose sight of the fact that every resolution of a War Cabinetor Transportation Council might become impossible ofaccomplishment; ouch might well be tho ease ae regards theinterruption with which they were now dealing,He did not think it necessary again to draw the attentioncf the Governments to the resolution because consignments hadonly been stopped by a case cf &quot;ferae majeure&quot;, which oculdnot be remedied,GEHE3AL BEL III   aaid that the misgivings which had boon felt injTaly Had also been felt by the Inter-Allied TransportationCouncil, who had stated them to the Military Representativesso that they might pass them cn to their respective Governments.But their Governments were already considering the question, -as an exchange of correspondence proved.Transportation had been interrupted for five days owingto causes over which they had no control; the personnel beingsi^k, nothing oculd be done.   Stoppage for five days at therate of 3,000 tons a day had led to a deficiency of 15,000tons.   That was the situation exactly.   According to theexpected programme they should have supplied Italy with 240.000tons a month.   They were furnishing about 180,000 ton3 and inpractice not mere than 220,000 tons had evor been eupplied,prance, Vno sent to Italy 180,000 tons a month, only receivedhersblf 10Oj000 in exchange for her supplies to Italy.   Thedeficiency in Italy was therefore also oaused partly by lackof supplies from England.   Prance had to give Italy more thanshe received herself; if Prance increased her consignmentsshe alone would have to make good tho deficit in question.   Anincrease should therefore not be looked for from Prance, but &apos;from Great Britain.He had just said that the Governments were alreadyconsidering this question. In fact on October 24oh theMinister cf Armament sent a telegiam to M* Villa, ItalianMinister,
p9f)4. &apos;&apos;ljMinister cf Public Works, in reply tc a wire dated 15thOctober,, The contents of this telegram were as follows:-&quot;The deficiency in consignments of coal to Italy fromFrench mines for several weeks pant is due to trano-portation difficulties resulting from militaryvictories and the continued shcrt arrivals of Englishcoal tc replace French;   You must know that duringthe period 16th March to 30th September our mineshave sent to Italy 1,400,000 tons whilst our ports haveonly received.1,244,000 tons of coal in exchange.   Upto the middle of August English exports had alwaysshown a slight increase over our consignments as wasnatural because we in cur turn had to transfer thisEnglish coal from the ports to places where it wasconsumed in the interior of the country before weoould take away from these places &quot;local resources inFrench coal.   But in September we only received 68,000tons of English coal whilst our mines sent to Italy200,000 tons.   In October tho rate of arrival cfocal from England is only about ICO,COO tons a month.Cur mines should therefore have sent only &quot;about110,000 tons this month to Italy, taking intoacoount10% for difference in quality; but knowing yourimperative needs for fuel I have done my best toincrease this figure very considerably so that theshortage in coal from England on Italian account willhave increased further by the end of this month.   Iwould draw your attention to- the gravity cf such asituation for it is absolutely impossible to restrictfurther the use of coal in this country and I deem.itmy duty to ask that the undertaking to replace coalshall be kept.   We all recognise the great effortsmade by the Ministry cf Shipping in London for thetransportation of American troops and we can understandthat these efforts may have impeded those which theywould have ma.de for the shipment of coal to Prance andItaly.   Thus the agreed replacement of our coal fromthe pas de Calais has,  so to speak, not been made.This just now puts us in an awkward position whichthe enthusiasm of victory alone helps the country to.bear.   I am constantly pointing out to London thenecessity of an immediate remedy to this situation andI would ask you to join in these pressing requests onwhich your supply of coal depends.&apos;   To sum up, I amsupplying you and have supplied you with more than 1have got back-(Signed)  :   Loucheur.&quot;It was obvious therefore that the situation in Prance wasmere critical than it seemed;,and also that the Minister ofArmament had already taken steps and entered into communicationwith the British Government,He thought that under these conditions the interventionof the Military Representatives would not be opportune and,in his opinion they should not do anything except by way ofthe following study;1 Is the change in the tonnage situationat present sufficient to allow an increase of transport by sea?Mien the resolution had been previously agreed to therewas a oertain danger.owing to submarine war in.theMediterranean and our transports were then less overburdenedthan now.   At present the reverse was&apos;the case, . He thoughttherefore that he could assure his colleagues that everyeffort was being made by the various Governments; their.Note would arrive too late and would not add anything to thenegotiations already going on.   He put this fact before hiscolleagues and asked them to consider if it would beadvisable to send this Note - if so they would&apos; examine thetext in detail. .
9 91M     A-   $   *rIn alluding1 to the deficiency of 15^000 tone caused by*     the cessation of consignments for five days, he had mentionedthe strategic reserve which could not bo draw upon.     Ifthese 150,00c tons y/ere indispensable they were free to asktho Government fj o once mod end maruhal i^och to let them drawupon the strategic reserve..Iiuarshal ioch had been consulted and he considered thatfor the moment thero was no objection to it.ftgAJflfcto, di KCBILAfrIT said that tho French military Representativohad&apos; explained very clearly the reasons for tho deficiency of15Q.C00 tone, which increased the former deficiency.     Ifthe tonnage situation had been alleviated, he could wee inthat a means of making up tho shortage and their Joint Motewould be opportune in drawing tho attention of tho Governmentsto this particular point, and in showing them tho extremourgency of this inquiry.    Paragraph 4 of the memorandumfrom the Intor-Allled Transportation Council pointed this outand it was again done in Paragraph 1 of the draft Joint Note,They were only indicating the means which they considered itadvisable to make use of and the fact that the Governmentswere already looking into this question confirmed thenecessity for their submitting a Joint Uote.jgiMR&apos;\L B&amp;Hff said that however much they laid stress on thedesirability of not hindering the transport of coal, it couldnot be avoided if another case of &quot;force majoure&quot; occurred.Priority had already been given to this kind of transport;it only remained to examine the freight question.GMEBAL S^ClLTILLlj--t,7EST thought that, if they agreed, they couldask their Governments to look into the question of finding ameans to make good the deficiency.    He himself did not know,however, if any moans existed.gJjMEBAL Eh&amp;IKf proposed that they should examine the draft Joint Notebefore them paragraph by paragraph ;Para, (a) was read, and accepted withoutimodification:&quot;The existing grave land transport crisis in France now re-vealed during the V/intor season just as the fuel require-ments grow most pressing&quot;:Para, (b) was road :wThe terms of the Convention entered into on the 12thJune,, 1918, by the British and Italian Governmentsfor the creation of the well known strategic reserveof coal in Italy, and further providing that nothingshall bo takon from this reserve for any other purposethan that for which it was created:&quot;Objections wore raised by the French and American MilitaryRepresentatives who did not think that mention should be madein a Joint Koto of the actual text of a private agreement betweentwo Governments only.The British Military Representative having agreed tocommunicate the text of this Agreement to his colleagues theseobjections were withdrawn.1 SEIpBAIi, S^QKVILLE-yftiST said ho wished to draw attention to animportant phrase in tho agreement in question which read asfollows .:-Tho
999fj     W- -6 -&quot;The Italian Government agree to hold these specialconsignments separate as a c-yfcrategic     roservo for usein the event of an interruption of the normal pro-gramme due to an important offensive on the Italianfront, or to movement(3 of troops between franco andItaly.     As this supply has been made availablespecially for this purpose, it will not be used tomake up any deficiency which may occur in the otherprogrammes except in the above circumstances&quot;..As tho strategic reserve had been built up with adefinite object it should not bo drawn upon to make good anydeficiency of any other programme save by stoppages in thedaily consignments of coal on ing to the transport of troopsfrom franco to Italy.,     Therefore the British Governmentalone could absolve Italy from this engagement.After some discussion para., (bj was accepted,, M^X^iJ^I1! ^ken road.paragraph (o)&quot;The very serious effects on military transportsand war industries in Italy of tho grave deficit incoal deliveries which has progressively accumulatedand which Is still daily increasing&quot;;This paragraph was accepted without modificationtffESERA.1. BE LIN then read paragraph&apos;(1).&quot;In view ox the grave situation which has arisenin Prance on account of the acute crisis in landtransportation, it is necessary to ask the Governmentsconcerned to study the question of reducing the deficitby any means at their disposal,,     It being understoodthat the solution of the difficulty by Groat Britainwould involve not only finding the tonnage butalso the coal&quot;e.GBHERAL SAGKVIIIE-V/EST said he wished to introduce a.modificationat this point-so &quot;as to make very clear the fact that if theBritish Government were asked to find a solution for thisproblem they must first find means of getting the coal, aswell as means of transporting itn     He then proposed thefollowing text :-&quot;In view of the grave situation which has arisenin France on account of the acute crisis in landtransport it is necessary to ask the Governments con-cernod to examine the question of reducing thesedeficiencies by all means in their power :   it wouldappear that if Great Britain has to find tho solutionof tho difficulty, she must; not only find the coal butalso the freight nocos&amp;ary to carry it to Italy&quot;0This was accepted.GENERAL BELIN
GITgKAL EELIP   then road paragraph (2) 1-&quot;The above-mentioned Convent ion entered into onthe 12th June, 1918, by the British and ItalianGovernments cannot be modified without the fullagreement of the two Governments directly concernedafter       approval of the Supreme &apos;.7ar Coi&apos;vc:; 1: and thatat the sane time it is opportune to reaffirm that thoabove-mentioned strategic reserve of coal cannot inany way be diverted from th-. ends for which it wasconstituted.&quot;On the proposal of th. AmericanTilitary Representativethe 1 ords &quot;aft: r approval of the Supr-.zu;   ar Council&quot; v/eredeleted, the agreement not having been submitted to theSupreme ear Council, and the second part of this paragraphwas included in paragraph (b) mentioned above,G&quot;V.CRAL K5LI1\T then read paragraph (3) :-&quot;Given thi great importance, for the prosecutionof th&apos;.. war, of punctuality in the transportation ofcoal to Italy across j?rance, both as regards strictlymilitary transportation and the production of warmat&apos;rial;IT IS ABSOLUTELY HZCESSARY:-To prevent thi occurrence of similar stoppages inthe future and to consider the transportation of coalfor Italy a3 a question of military urgency of eolationinterest to be given absolute precedence over all othertransportation.&quot;GLHLIvAL EEL IK demanded the elimination of this paragraph altogethhe considered it unnecessary as cases of &quot;force majcurc&apos;1could not be prevented and the Governments were making everyeffort to fulfil the programme contemplated.GIITRAh BLISS proposed the following modification :-&quot;IT IS ABSOLUTELY hlCESSARYi-To avoid, as far as possible, the recurrence of similarstoppages in the future by giving coal for Italypriority in transportation over all other articles.&quot;GIKEBAl DI ROB IL ANT accepted this reotfif icaticn.GrilTRAL SAChVILLE-VlEST said he accepted, in principle, theamendment proposed by General Hiss, tut h-.-. did not thinkit necessary to add this paragraph to the Joint Koto underconsideration.Gill&quot;RAL BLISS agreed with the opinion of the British MilitaryRepresentative as to the addition of this paragraph,G:;-.I:&amp;AL BKLIff again demanded the elimination.of this paragraph,On
&quot;*   8  -On the proposal of the British I IlitaryRepresent ;tire it warT agrecd to adjourn to the Meetingon October 28th the ^aeceiojancc^of thi s^Joi nt l:&apos;o-oe; thenc.7 text of yljiffiu  oFTracTo^cff,&apos; uoulffTv-&apos;&apos;s&quot;upiaTT&quot;e&apos;gTo&quot;^the I ilitary iv. pre sent at ires for further examination.(Por amended text of draft Joint Note-seeAnncxure &quot;E&quot;).
9 ^ rfi U (JANNBXUPE &quot;A&quot; to O.T. 6isa.f RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY THE INTER-ALLIED TRANSPORTATIONCOUNCIL) AT A SPECIAL MEETING HELD ON Slot OCTOBER,1918, ON THE SUBJECT OF THE SUPPLY OP COAL TO ITALY.1. The Council recognises that a very oerious situationat present exists in Italy with regard to the supply offuel to War factories.    This situation is due to the fastthat the import programme arranged has not been sntirelyworked to.    Particularly for the month of October, thedeficit which on the loth instant amounted to 61,197 tonsis considered as likely to be not leas than 150,000 tons atthe end of the month.2. The oause of this deficit is to be looked foressentially in the inadequacy of the transportation ofGoal across France, and more recently in the restrictivemeasures adopted, without previous agreement with theItalian Authorities, by the Minister of Public Vorka ahdTransportation in France with regard to the transportationof ooal itcT Italy, in consequence of the very criticalperiod through which the French Reseaux ara at present passing.3. The Council in referring the matter to the SupremeWar Council recommends that in future the supply of coalto Italy should be considered from the transportationpoint of view as having the character of military urgencyin the common interest.4. The Council considered that, the shortage of railwaypersonnel being one of the principal oauaes of the presenttransportation crisis, it is impossible to conaider themaking good of the deficit by means of land transportation.It would therefore be solely by means of special con&amp;:.gnmentsof coal from England direct by sea to Italian ports that itwould be possible to restore the situation to its normalstate again.It is, however, understood thut the tonnage requiredfor these consignments could not in any Hay be drawn fromthe tonnage already allotted to Italy for the purpose ofmeeting her ordinary requirements.5. The Council is of opinion that the use - even in partof the strategic reserve of 150,000 tons constituted inItaly in accordance with the Anglo-Italian agreement of the14th duns 1918, would only be justified by the purelymilitary exigencies as laid down in the said agreement,unless a previous understanding were arrived at to thiseffect between the Governments concerned.
99(1hi iw *JANNEXUBI &quot;B&quot; to G.T. 6152,DRAFT JOINT NOTE.THE STOPPAGE OF SUPPLIES OF COAL TO ITALY.The Permanent Military Bepresentatives, having read theResolution passed by the Inter-Allied Transportation Council atits Meeting held on 21st October, 1916 regarding the Stoppageof Supplies of Cdal to Italy.AND TAKING INTO CONSIDERATION:-(a) The existing grave land transport crisis in France, newrevealed during the Winter Season, just as the fuel requirementsgrovi moat pressing;(b) The terms of the Agreement entered into on 18th June1918, by the British and Italian Governments for the oreationof a strategic reserve of 150,000 tons of coal in Italy, whichprovide that nothing shall be taken from this reserve for anyother purpose than that for which it was created, without thefull agreement of the British and the Italian GovernmentsJ(c) The very serious effects on military transports and warIndustries in Italy of the grave deficit in coal deliverieswhich has progressively accumulated and which is still dailyincreasing;ARE 0? OPINION THAT:-(1)    In vievy of the grave situation which has arisen inFrance on account of the acute crisis m land transportation,it is necessary to ask the Governments of France and GraatBritain to study the question of reducing the deficit by anymeans at their disposal.    It is clear that the solution ofthe difficulty by Great Britain would involve not only findingthe tonnage but also the coal;(2)    Given the great importance, for the prosecution of thewar, of punctuality in the transportation of coal to Italyacross France, both as regards strictly military transportationand the production of war material;IT IS ABSOLUTELY NECESSARY:In order to prevent as far as possible the recurrenceof such interruption that the transport of coal to Italyshould receive priority of all the traffic to that countryfrom France.

</content>
</cab>
