<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 378-390</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
12SECRET.MINISTRY  OF  POOD.Report for Week ending Wednesday, October 30, 1918.The Food Council. Sir John Beale reported that he had discussed the feedingstuffs position at the Committee of Representatives and also with the Americanrepresentative. The American view was that there was no concentrated cake availablein U.S. for export owing to the partial failure of the cotton crop and the shortage oflinseed (of which U.S. was actually importing a quantity), and that ILK. shouldmake her own arrangements for getting the feeding stuffs required from othermarkets. It was decided to ask the Wheat Commission to report whether the millingprogramme could be modified so as to secure a greater output of offals, and in- whatway increased importation of cake and maize could be secured. The use of barleyfor feeding stuffs to be controlled through grist&apos;mills was also considered.The shortage of meat was discussed. It was agreed that it was impossible toreduce the meat ration and that the ILK. could not expect any increased imports offrozen meat. It was considered essential to make the best possible use of the suppliesnow coming forward in view of probable demands on the part of recovered territoriesand of a further reduction in supplies after Christmas.A memorandum on malting barley in Ireland was considered. It appeared thatalthough the acreage under cultivation was in excess of previous years practically nobarley was coming to market either for millers or malsters. It was determined totake steps to encourage the marketing of barley, and to endeavour to control themovement of stock.Committee of Representatives. Meetings of the Committee of Representativesand of the Freight Committee have been held during the week. Special attention hasbeen given to the arrangements for conducting the provisioning of Serbia and therecovered territories of North France and Belgium, and further supplies to meetimmediate needs were sanctioned. Arrangements were made to supplement thesupplies of preserved meat and tish. for Italy which had got into arrear.Joint Finance Board.--The question of advances to Local &quot;-Authorities for the-establishment of National Kitchens was discussed. It was decided to apply forTreasury sanction to take out leases for a term of 7 or 10 years for the purpose ofproviding premises, but that the Director of National Kitchens should be instructedto commit himself to the shortest term possible, and to obtain option of terminatingleases. - * -   1   v:- v v l,M &apos;&apos;In the matter of supplies obtainable in neutral or enemy countries after the war,the Wheat Commission advised the purchase of maize from the Argentine ; the SugarCommission reported that it was merely a question of tonnage as there were amplesupplies in Java awaiting shipment and. no need to make further advance purchases.The price of potatoes to bakers for the purpose of baking bread was discussed,and also the various anomalies that appeared in the bakers&apos; accounts and in the priceof baking.Imports Board. M. Destombe&apos;s request for 10,000 tons of bacon and hams forrevictualling the French reconquered territory was discussed, and it was agreed tooffer 3,000 tons of hog products to the French Government for immediate delivery.It was not thought that existing stocks in the United Kingdom would admit furtheradvances,, but&apos; the French Government were advised to consider the purchase ofAmerican products known to be available.It was agreed to apply for Treasury sanction to purchase the whole of theexportable surplus of A/ustralasian butter for the period of the war &quot;and twelve monthsafterwards, r &apos;:       .A  (33)6638-5   Pk 1   115   11/18   E &amp; S APART I.-ACTION . TAKEN.
2It was agreed to submit an estimate of the proposed cost of purchasing tho wholeexportable sin-plus of butter and cheese from the Argentine, South Africa, andCanada.Supplies and Prices.Bacon. A census of curers in Great Britain shows that about 2,500 persons areengaged in curing, and require allocations of pigs. This number is considerablyabove what was expected, and includes many very small curers, whoso claims willraise administrative problems of considerable difficulty.Canned Salmon. In response to urgent requests made by the Representative ofPrisoners of War Committee for supplies of canned salmon to cover emergency, itwas decided to release 1,000,000 tins of 1 lb. each or their equivalent to the Com-mittee from the Ministry&apos;s stocks lying in the United Kingdom, although the holdingsof the Ministry on this side are extremely small. Details of brands and pi ices to besettled later.Cereals. On Wednesday, October 30, Mr. Paul gave evidence before the SelectCommittee on National Expenditure on the proposal to continue the subsidy in respectof potatoes used in the manufacture of bread, and pointed out that this would involvea saving in the amount of the bread subsidy.Citrous Fruits for Marmalade-making. Arrangements have been made with theBritish Purchasing Commission in Italy to buy the whole of the Sicilian crop ofbitter oranges which may not be required by the Italian Government for domesticconsumption (estimated from 2,000 to 4,000 tons) and 4,000 tons of sweet oranges ata price of 22 lire per box, also 15,000 tons of confectioners&apos; lemons at 21 lire per boxof 88 lbs. net, all f.o.b. Sicilian ports.Purchases are also being made of 10,500 tons of bitter oranges and 2,000 tons ofsweet oranges in Spain. Under this scheme the Ministry will not finance thepurchases, which will be in the hands of Messrs. Boyd and Machin as last year.Shipments are expected to commence about the middle of November, and applicationsfor participation in allotments of fruit are now being received from the various jammanufacturers.   The last day fixed for the receipt of applications is 1st November.Cocoa. The arrivals of cocoa are somewhat below those set out in ourprogramme, but the Ministry of Shipping have despatched urgent cables to theirrepresentatives on the West Coast of Africa to load larger quantities. It is hopedthat at least 7,000 tons may be shipped in November.The Cocoa Bean Shell (Requisition) Order, 1918, dated 29th October 1918,provides that the occupier of every factory or workshop in which raw cocoa beans areused shall place the whole of the output of cocoa bean shell at the disposal of theFood Controller on and after November 2nd. This control of the cocoa bean shellwill enable it to be distributed under the Feeding Stuffs Distribution Scheme.Coffee. The Admiralty Marshal has been asked to inscribe the purchasers&apos; nameson the bonds issued by him. A list of these buyers will be kept and a copy will betransmitted to the Ministry of Food. By this means it is hoped that the speculationin the coffee market will partially, if not wholly, disappear. The Admiralty Marshalcontinues to supply the market with 5,000 bags of coffee per week.Dried Fruits. An additional purchase of 150 tons of Cape raisins has beeneffected. The S.S. &quot; Nessian &quot; has arrived at Liverpool with the first shipment of the2,000 tons of Californian sultanas. The remaining quantity is afloat and arrivals areexpected within the next ten days. A further shipment of Indian sultanas, part ofthis Ministry&apos;s purchase, have arrived during the week.Fish. Supplies of white fish have been moderate, and the demand good; herringsand kippers from the East Anglian ports have been heavy, some 2,500 tons arrivingduring the week ; also good supplies of Irish mackerel, with the result that sprats andsmall herrings have exceeded the demand, fair quantities finding their way to the fishmeal works.Transport and delivery on the whole has been good.Meat.-The measures which have been taken to restrict the number of cattlecoming into the markets have not yet limited the supply to the amount required. Inspite of this, some difficulty is being experienced in arranging for full supplies for theLondon area, owing partly to the lack of sufficient transport facilities and partly tothe lack of an adequate number of slaughtermen.   Arrangements have been made
to secure the temporary release of a number of slaughtermen from the army, but thishas not yet been done on a sufficient scale to cope with the situation. It may becomenecessary during the coming week to release some oi the home-killed meat recentlyfrozen and put into store, in order to furnish a supply for the London area. Nodifficulty need be experienced with regard to replacing such stocks, provided thatthe number of slaughtermen is increased. Priority is being given to the requirementsof the army, and this puts a somewhat heavy tax on London&apos;s slaughtering capacity,in which area the army demand is likely to amount to over 600 tons this week.The fact that the demand for civilian consumption is now being met almostentirely by home-grown meat permits the accumulation of reserve stocks of frozenmeat in store. These stocks are rapidly being restored to a more satisfactory level,and at the moment there is some pressure upon the storage accommodation. It is, ofcourse, desired to accumulate the largest reserve stocks possible in order to meet thesituation that will arise when home supplies fall off.Milk. Mr. Glynes received a deputation from the Bristol Food Control Oom-mittees from the West of England with regard to the winter milk prices. Thedeputation explained the views of their Committees that the price was excessive, andthat it would bear hardly on the poorer classes. Mr. Clynes explained at some lengththe reasons which had actuated him in fixing the price, and the necessity of ensuringa plentiful supply of milk during the winter months. He also explained that, in viewof the control over the wholesale distribution of milk which had now been takenby the Ministry, he had arranged for an inquiry to be made into the possibilities offixing a differential rate for various districts, and as soon as he received the result ofhis investigation he would consider whether there was any possibility of reducing theprice. He also called attention to the special facilities which existed for providingmilk at a reduced cost.The Consumers&apos; Council at their meeting on Wednesday, October 30, consideredthe financial arrangements necessary to be made if Mr. Butler, of the United Dairies,Ltd., became the servant of the Department. The discussion was adjourned untilnext week.Oils and Fats. The Food Controller has decided to reduce the price of oil andfat compound from 150s. per cwt. to 140s. per cwt. to the consumer as fromNovember 17th.Oranges and Lemons. - -Meetings with the Trade have been held with a view tofixing the price of sweet oranges and lemons. Under this Order oranges will be soldby retail at lOd. per lb. The schedule price for lemons is not yet completed. TheOrder, with the exception of the Lemon Schedule, has gone forward to the OrdersCommittee, and it is hoped will be signed on Monday, November 4th.Potatoes.-.-The Food Controller will, on November 1st, take control of the wholepotato crop of England and Wales.The prices to be paid to the growers have been fixed by a Commission appointedby the Food Controller and the President of the Board of Agriculture jointly. Thereport of this Commission prescribed the different growers&apos; prices for each areaaccording to the yield, quality, and cost of production of the crop, and are for twogrades of potatoes.While the prices for producers will vary in different areas, the price to the publicfor the same grade of potato will be uniform throughout England and Wales. Untilthe end of December Grade 1 potato will be retailed at a uniform price of l\d. per lb.,and Grade 2 at a uniform price of Id. per lb.For purposes of administration England and Wales have been divided into11 deficit zones, which will need, at some time or other during the year, to importpotatoes from elsewhere, and 12 surplus zones, which will export potatoes. In eachsurplus zone is a Zonal Committee under a Zonal Chairman responsible for organisingthe collection of potatoes for export to other areas. In each deficit zone is a PotatoControl Committee under the Chairmanship of the Food Commissioner. Thesecommittees will he empowered to issue directions relating to the, collection anddisposal of potatoes. Subject to any restrictions imposed by the Potato ControlCommittee, or the Zonal Committee, growers will be permitted to sell potatoes to anyregistered wholesale dealer in their zone, but may not sell to anyone else except underlicence, to be obtained from the Food Commissioner of their area. Leaflets for theguidance of growers, registered wholesale dealers, and retail dealers in potatoes, havebeen issued.
These arrangements relate only to ware potatoes. Growers will be free to sellundersized potatoes subject to a maximum price of 3Z. 10s. per ton free on rail.Undersized potatoes, for which a market cannot be found in the ordinary way, will betaken over by the Ministry of Food at the fixed price of 3Z. per ton prescribed by theJoint Commission.   Seed potatoes will be dealt with separately.Poultry. By an Order dated 29th October 1918, the maximum price is increasedfor cockerels between 6 ozs. and 1 lb. in weight. The object is to promote hatching,and, by encouraging the killing of cockerels, to save feeding stuffs for laying birds.Pulping Stations. The only fruit pulping which has been done this summeris at Totnes and Bridgwater. At Totnes about 250 tons of blackberries have beenlaid down and at Bridgwater 20 tons. The latter station was opened for a shortperiod on account of the railway strike. Sloes are now being pulped at Totnes stationand it is anticipated that we shall secure about 50 tons of this fruit. The followingstations are being prepared for handling oranges and lemons : Maidstone, Totnes,Bridgwater, Cheltenham, Sittingbourne, Faversham, Doncaster, Evesham (ValleyWorks), Paddock Wood.Tea. 3,000,000 lbs. of tea have been purchased in China, and arrangementsmade to obtain the necessary tonnage.&apos;; Rationing. ,As a result of several conferences held with the Admiralty, War Office,and Air Ministry representatives, arrangements have practically been completedfor the issue of ration documents to soldiers reverting to civilian life on generaldemobilisation. On being sent home from a dispersal station a demobilised soldierwill receive a &quot; Demobilisation Ration Book,&quot; containing coupons for a fortnight.This book will be exchangeable for a civilian ration book on presentation at a FoodOffice.The Demobilisation Ration Books are ready to be sent to press as soon as theWar Office have agreed to the proposal that they should contain meat coupons on thecivilian ration scale. The War Office agreement to this proposal is expected within afew days. Sufficient supplies of the books to meet the initial demand on demobilisationwillbe printed immediately.The Ministry are in communication with the Admiralty, War Office, and AirMinistry, with a view to taking over surplus army and navy stores which may bereleased for the use of the civilian population after demobilisation.Jam Rationing. The necessary arrangements for distribution under the JamRationing Scheme which comes into force on 3rd November are being proceededwith. Various meetings of the Jam Advisory Committee and representatives of thewholesale and retail trades have been held to discuss the scheme.A good deal of time has been occupied in the registration of wholesale dealers.This is now nearly complete, the total number of licences issued up to the presentbeing 856.Manufacturers who were restricted by the Jam Manufacturers&apos; (Restriction)Order, 1918, from sending out beyond specified quantities before 31st October have&apos; been notified that they are now at liberty to send out further quantities conditionalon their obtaining an undertaking in writing from the various customers that the jamwill not be offered for sale, Or otherwise disposed of, before the 3rd of November.: A second meeting took place at Grosvenor House oh the 23rd of October, betweenthe Consumers&apos; Counciland the Food Commissioners, at which the proposals for thedistribution of cheese were discussed. A concensus of opinion was expressed infavour^ of placing consignments of cheese in the hands of the Commissioners, forallocation to areas to meet special requirements.Divisional Reports.The Commissioner for the North-west Division reports that the supplementaryration of cheese issued to heavy workers, and increased supplies to wholesalers lastmonth, have materially decreased the number of complaints.The Commissioner for&apos;the Home Counties calls attention to the difficulties in therural areas caused by the high price of clothing.  Parents declare that the present
52C9price and inferior quality of boots will make it impossible to send their childrento school during the winter. He urges the need of providing mid-day meals at theschools, which, in his opinion, would require to be State-aided, more especially in thesmaller country districts. The provision of transport for fuel for the cottage popula-tion is also mentioned as becoming a serious problem.In the West of Scotland, as a result of the shortage of feeding stuffs, largequantities of game and poultry are coming into the market, and being sold consider-ably under controlled prices. Arrangements have therefore been made locally withthe cold storage authorities to allow surplus birds to be put in store for use later.This measure should improve competition in the market. Owing to the very stormyweather in the past fortnight, fish supplies in this,a-rea have been very short. Herringfishermen were not able to go out to the fishing grounds, and in consequence all fishwere being sold at maximum prices.Enforcement of Orders.The total number of prosecutions for the past week is 894, of which 850 resultedin convictions.The Divisions mainly affected were as follows : Division.	Prosecutions.	Convictions.North-west	-  174	98 per cent.Home Counties -	-   105	97North    -	-   69	100     ,,South-west	-   52	90     ,,London -	-   51	96     ,,The most noticeable contribution to the week&apos;s prosecutions is a series of 80summonses against various offenders under the Pigs (Prices) Order at Blackpool.This was the result of a raid carried out by the police. The fines total 6601.,averaging 8Z. 5s. each.PART II.-SUMMARY OF THE FOOD POSITION.Imports.Imports of the principal food-stuffs in the week ended 26th October (196,200 tons)again show an increase over those of the preceding week (192,700 tons) and asubstantial excess beyond those of the corresponding week of last year (141,400 tons);they are also above the average of the first 43 weeks of the calendar year 1918(181,200 tons), though they are still below the average of the corresponding weeks ofthe year 1917 (229,300 tons),, (Table A). For the first time during the current cerealyear the total imports (1,441,100 tons) exceed those of, the corresponding period oflast year (1,400,800 tons).Compared with the week ended 19th October there has been an improved importof sugar (17,000 1 tons increase), and of bacon, lard, butter, cheese, condensedmilk, and cocoa, though the imports of bacon (7,800 tons), and in a less degreethose of cheese (2,400 tons) are still insufficient to meet the weekly consumption.There was a small. import of tea after the abnormally high import of the previousweek, and no coffee. As regards cereals, wheat and -flour as grain (112,800 tons)showed the highest weekly import during the current cereal year, but other cereals(19,200 tons) were below the average; very little barley (180 tons); and no ricearrived.
6The total imports for the first eight weeks of the cereal years 1917-18 and1918-19 are compared in the following table: Total Imports in the first 8 weeks of cereal year. 	1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrease.	 	1917.	1918.	Increase or Decrease.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	-	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Total   -	1,400,800	1,441,100	* 40,300	Lard	2,700	22,500	\  19,800Wheat   -	346,000	654,900	+ 308,900	Butter   -	7,900	5,600	-    2,300Flour    -	129,600	80,300	-  49,300	Margarine	6,900	-. 	-    6,900Equivalent as	516,500	755,300	+ 238,700	Cheese -	25,000	23,300	-    1,700Grain.				Condensed milk	10,100	29,600	-f-  19,500Barley,    oats,	343,200	179,400	- 163,800	Sugar	267,800	259,400	-    8,400and maize.				Tea	14,900	24,500	-f    9,600Rice	102,400	800	- 101,600	Coffee   -     -	1,000	2,500	-Y    1,500 -f-    9,400Meat	103,500	70,200	-  33,300	Cocoa	2,600	12,000	Bacon	37,200	76,100	4 38,900				Consumption.Bread and Flour. The continued increase in. consumption of bread and flourwas pointed out in last week&apos;s Report. It will be seen from Table G that theincrease was general throughout the country but was greater in London and the largetowns than in the smaller towns and rural districts where, however, the increase inconsumption had already reached a high level.A comparison with the corresponding period of last year shows that the increaseis made up of a heavy increase in the amount of flour used in bread and a reductionin the amount sold as flour an indication of the decreased use of flour for homebaking. The figures show that the fall has been greatest in Scotland and in theNorth of England.In view of the decision of the Ministry to require, by order, the use of potatoes inbread to the extent of 20 lbs. of potatoes to every 280 lbs. of flour, the present extentto which potatoes are so used is of special interest. The returns show that only onebaker out of 23 uses potatoes in the manufacture of bread, and that only 1 lb. ofpotatoes is used to every 280 lbs. of flour. The maximum use recorded sinceFebruary 1918 was in June, when old crop potatoes were available, but even thenonly 3^ lbs. of potatoes were used to every 280 lbs. of flour.Meat. The number of cattle and sheep accepted for slaughter in Great Britainduring the week ended 19th October showed little change on the preceding week, andthe total supply of butchers&apos; meat, inclusive of 900 tons refrigerated meat, is estimatedat 16,100 tons. Consumption is thus approximating more closely to the rationquantity. The congestion of live stock at the markets continues; the army autho-rities are not yet taking up the numbers agreed upon, but, on the other hand, it ishoped that arrangements recently made as to freezing and storing and the higherscale of winter prices now offered to farmers will go far towards conserving supplies.Fish. Weekly supplies of fresh fish at Billingsgate and several large provincialmarkets recently are shown in the following table : 	Billingsgate and other		Billingsgate alone.	_	Markets.				1918.	1918.		1917.	.  Tons.	Tons.		Tons.September average    -	3,223	1,832		2,201October 5th	4,431	2,770		1,945,,   12th      -      -     - -   -	4,262	2,704		2,519,,   19th      -     -     -      -	5,577	3,446		2,758The October figures reflect a seasonal increase of supplies representing chieflyherrings landed on the coast of England and Wales, but it is doubtful if the increasewill come up to the average.
270Stocks. rSuch variations as have occured in the stocks of food-stuffs during the week endedthe 19th October, have generally followed the direction indicated in the precedingweeks; thus the beef stocks have been enlarged by a further 3,800 tons, and othermeat by 1,600 tons, while bacon stocks have been reduced by a further 2,100 tons, andnow stand at 85,200 tons, a fall of 21,000 tons since 1st August.&apos;Large proportions of the stocks of certain food-stuffs are owned by the Ministry ofFood, including the following; the difference between the two representing in mostcases stocks which have passed into the hands of those responsible for their furtherdistribution.	Ministry Stocks.	Total Stocks.	Ministry Proportion,	Tons.	Tons.	Per Cent.Butter     -     -	7,000	10,800	65	21,700	31,800	.    68	24,000	25,800	93Condensed milk -      -      -      -	36,500	45,300	80Bacon      -     -      ...	48,900	85,200	57Rabbits    -	1,800	4,300	42Canned meat    -	10,000	22,000	45The Ministry stocks of canned meat above do not include stocks requisitionedunder the Canned Meats Requisition Order.
8Table A.-Imports of Principal Food and Feeding Stuffs.Article.WeekendingOctober26th, 1918.2.8.9.10.11.12.13.14.15,16,17,18.19.20.Wheat -Wheaten flourEico   -Beef (freshand refrige-rateil).Mutton (freshand refrige-rated).Meat,, unenu-merated (re-frigeratedand     pro-served).Bacon andHams.Lard   -     -Butter -Margarine   -CheeseCo n dousedmilk.Sugar (refinedand un-refined).Sugar, glucoseTotal -    -Barley -Oats   -      -Maize tTotalTea    -     &apos;-Coffee, raw -Cocoa, raw -Total     -Grand Total  -Tons.99,55010,6253,8448274,6837,8392,8581,0052,4392,30339,560WeekendingOctober19th, 1918.J.Tons.100,0504,4806,8701,4053,1255,2971,336.  3631,2601,89122,472115,53318014,3254,68019,1852911,1821,473WeekendingOctober27th, 1917.Tons.40,12021,3405,91024,5397,2864,0724,4261586711,7435,6737094,41548AverageWeeklyNetImports*in 1.913.5.Average WeeklyImports.i&apos;6 Weeksfrom Dec.30th, 1917,to Oct.26th, 1918.6.Corres-pondingPeriod.1917.148,55042531,3451,65533,4259,49362265410,769121,1105,21010,2801,55017,040Tons.101,3789,7122,5548,8495,1252,1265,2671,6293,8671,4602,13774237,3331,408183,58721,56517,46446,45085,4792,7071563963,2592,6403195423,501Tons.46,88328,2308,4546,8912,0722,84712,078,2,7251,6113562,4162,59628,790414146,3635,6899,55015,04930,2883,8401405804,560Tons.99,90013,0926,3226,0162,5102,6097,8651,7952,0371,8922,9201,41527,4451,190Total Imports.43 Weeksfrom Dec.30th, 1917to Oct.26th, 1918.177,008Tons-2,015,9551,213,885363,526296,31789,096122,430519,341117,15869,29615,300103,907111,6421,237,98317,797Corres-pondingPeriod,1917.9.6,293,633Tons.4,295,700562,940271,829258,684107,945112,173338,19677,20487,60181,383125,55660,8321,180,13251,1767,72313,61227,04548,3801,9756161,2783,869244,610410,660647,1201,302,390165,1096,01724,955196,0817,611,351332,080585,3301,162,9502,080,36084,93326,48054,938166,351196,191192,744141,409272,567181,211229,2577,792,1049,858,062iNet Imports.*MonthendingSept. 30th,1918.21. Oil seeds andnuts    andkernels.22. Oilseed cake23. Oils,    vege-table, refinedand   unre-fined.24. Oil, fish, train,blubber, andsperm.25. StearineTons.57,23319,8518,242302MonthendingAugust 31st.1918.Tons.89,2702124,03916,438MonthendingSept. 30th,. 1917.AverageMonthlyNetImports?in1913.1Average Monthly NetImports. *9 MonthsJan -Sept.,1918.264Tons.50,25322,340t-1,41112,26753ions.120,31429,4336,6905,424304Tons.93,72953610,8656,420204Corres-pondingPeriod.1917.Tons.86,00219,3042,6265,288206Total Net Imports.*9 MonthsJan.-Sept.,1918.Tons.843,5634,82297,78357,7981,836Corres-pondingPeriod,1917.774,020173,73423,65347,5941,852* Imports less re-exports of Foreign and Colonial Produce and less exports of British Produce of the same kind,-j- Net export,
9STATISTICS ILLUSTRATING CONSUMPTION.Table B.-(1)-Weekly Consumption of the Chief Articles of Food in theUnited Kingdom.[The figures are based upon quantities of imported food-stuffs released forconsumption, plus estimated home production.]	Flour.	Butchers&apos; Meat.	Bacon,	Butter and Margarine.	Lard and Compound.	Sugar.	Tea.	Tons.	Tons&apos;.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.	Tons.Army demands from U.K. Stocks and	5,200	4,800	2,800	1,000	 	3,200	530Supply.							For Civilian Consumption : 							Average of 4 weeks ended :-							July 13th -     -      -     -	95,600	19,400	9,200	7,400	3,700	19,500	2,900August 10th	85,700	20,300	9,800	7,300	3,600 3,700	19,400	3,700September 7th	97,600	23,700	11,000	7,000		17,000	2,70014th -	99,800	24,000	10,800	7,100	3,900	15,700	2,00021st  - &apos;    -	100,200	24,700	12,000	7,300	4,000	16,200	2,20028th -      -  &apos;  -	99,900	24,300	11,700	7,300	3,900	16,400	2,900October 5th	99,500	21,900	9,800	7,500	3,900	17,000	2,50012th     -      -      -	98,600	21,300	10,100	7,700	3,600	17,500	2,50019th	98,600	18,900	8,600	7,800	3,400	17,300	2,800(2) Animals Slaughtered in 10,097 Private and Public Slaughterhousesin Great Britain in August 1917, July 1918, and August 1918.-   -                                     j    Cattle.		. Calves.	Sheep and Lambs.	Pigs.August 1917      -     -     -     -     -     -July 1918   -     -     -     -     -     -     -August 1918      -     -                  -     -	153,363 84,603 105,514	27,756 20,98*8 21,062	753,506 672,632 785,209	14.1,166 60,767 61,849Percentage Increase or Decrease : August 1918 compared with August 1917  -	-31&apos;20/0	&quot;24-10/0	4- 4-20/0	-56&apos;20/0August 1918 compared with July 1918	+24-71	+ 0-4 0/0	+ 16-80/.	+ 1-870Table C-Index Numbers illustrating Changes in the Rate of Consumptionof Food-stuffs.[Except where it is stated otherwise, the rate of consumption in May 1917is taken as ^ 100.](1) Consumption of Butchers&apos; Meat by the Civilian Population in theUnited Kingdom.JanuaryFebruaryMarchAprilMay - -June -July -AugustSeptemberOctoberNovemberDecemberHome Fed.1916.1917.1918.119111113iooi93J898796109101119121101*92*101*99j1008488-102*1Q3J114110*96*67*575955435464^77Foreign.1916.119135161*136$14411381165137113*991241481917.1918.14%119*93&quot;95*10092*10511688*91*90*13511896*114119*155190*172*177h801Total.1916.118*113*119105 .10095*97*101109108*1191241917.107*9610098*1008590104100*110107101*1918.73*62*66*63*58*62*0*8077*A 6638-6B
10(2) Consumption of Bread and Flour in the United Kingdom.4 week ended	Retailers&apos; Sales.			Deliveries of Flour from Mills and Releases of Foreign Flour to Agents.		1916.	1917.	1918,	1917.	1918.January 5th February 2nd    .... March 2nd       .... March 30th      .... April 27 th..... May 25th..... June 22nd -      -      -July 20lh -August 17th     -     -     -September 14th -October 12th     -November 10th -     -     -     -December 8 th	99 100 97i 99&quot; 95 94 951 98 ion	94i 99 102^ 1044-101 100 95 911 89j 90j (92) 97 (96) 100 100	96 1001   . 1004. 100 IOC 98 98 96 98 102 104	98 104 1101	101^ 104 97 92 97 96 99 99 90 103 1021The numbers in brackets are adjusted for the probable change in the stock of flour held at home beforeand after the reduction in price on September 17th.(3) Consumption of Provisions in the United Kingdom based on returnsfrom Multiple Shops and Co-operative Societies.4 weeks ended	Butter,			Lard,   t			Bacon and Hams.			Cheese.															1916.	1917.	1918.	1916,	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.	1918.	1916.	1917.	1918.January 19 th   -		&apos; 97	28		124	47		97	48		106	56February 16th -	 	87	24	 	128	38	 	103	35		113	53March 16th	 	82	28	 	119	35	  .	88	39	 	96	54April 13th	 	91	43	 	104	68	 	86	50	 	90	45May 11th	 	99	50		106	73	 	93	99	 	95	28June 8th -	 	100	55	 	100	57	 	100	141	 	100	44July 6th -	 	106	62	 	104	89	 	110	134	 	118	52August 3rd August 31st	 	110	70	&apos; 	115	122	 	107	121	 	113	55	*137	108	70	*108	122	113	*I13	98	110	*152	90	56September 28th	*134	123	65	&apos;*108	120	116	*105	91	109	*146	111	100October 27th   -	125	65		108	127		103	72		146	104	November 24th -	114	35		152	84		106	61		135	106	December 22nd -	113	35		143	54		119	61		129	96	* For these months no returns were obtained from Co-operative Societies in England and &quot;Wales,(4) Quantities of Milk carried by seven of the Principal Railway Companiesin England and Wales.[The average weekly quantity carried in September 1917 is taken as = 100.]	1917.	1918.	Week ended		January -      -      -     -	--	.851		1917.	1918.February -     -     -     -	 	87^		 	 March     -      -      -      -      -		931	September 7th	-    100	103April      -      -May       -     -     -	 	971	September 14th	-    1001	102	 	107	September 21st	-    lOOf	101June      -      -     -     &quot;     -	 	112	September 28th	-      99^	99July       -     -     -     -		106	October 5th -	-     99	99 August   -      -     -     -     -	 	104	October 12th -	98	102September	100	102	October 19th -	98	lollOctober   -      -      .      -	931				November       -					December	85l				
11Table D.-Stocks of the Principal Foods and Feeding Stuffs in theUnited Kingdom.The figures for wheat and Hour include stocks in port granaries and warehouses, inland warehouses,mills, and bakers&apos; shops, as well as estimated slocks on farms; those for barley, oats, beans, and poasinclude stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills, in maltsters&apos; hands, and estimated farm stocks ;those for maize, rice, and grain meals include stocks in port granaries and warehouses and in mills.Tho figures for sugar are stocks in possession of tho Sugar Commission; those for butter, margarine,lard, cheese, condensed milk, meat, and fish include stocks at ports, in cold stores, and in importers&apos; andwholesalers&apos; warehouses.The figures for tea, coffee, and cocoa aro stocks remaining in bonded warehouses or entered to bewarehoused; and those for oilseeds and oilseed cake include stocks at ports and in the hands of millers,crushers, and cake manufacturers.Article.		October 1st, 1918.	September 1st, 1918.	October 1st, 1917.		Stocks in the United Kingdom including estimated Farm Stocks.		Wheat (including Hour) -Barley             .        -Oats     -        -        -         -Beans Peas     -        -        -	-	Tons. 3,040,000 1,245,000 3.483,000 160,000 110,000	Tons. 3,147,000 1,416,000 3,824,000 175,000 107,000	Tons. 3,078,000 1,269,000 3,224,000 148,000 65,000		Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports, Warehouses, &amp;c.		Maize    -         -         -Rice (including ground rice and rice flour) Grain Meals      -        -        -        -Sugar    -        -        -        -        -		26,000 196,000 55,000 382,000	36,000 219,000 48,000 372,000	88,000 120,000 44,000 192,000		Stocks in the United Kingdom in Cold Stores and in Importers&apos; and Wholesalers&apos; Warehouses.		Butter   -         -        -         -        -Margarine        -        -        -Lard     -        -        -Cheese   -        -        -    . - -        -Condensed Milk          .... Meat: Beef (chilled and frozen) Mutton (chilled and frozen) Bacon and Hams Poultry, Game, and Rabbits Other Meat     -        -Fish     -        -        -        -      . -		12,700 1,800 29,300 24,700 42,400 24,800 17,800 92,200 6,900 32,200 26,600	15,900 1,900 24,100 25,500 29,800 23,700 . 25,100 93,900 9,900 30,400 26,800	8,100 5,000 20,300 17,400 * 12,000 36,800 14,100 18,600 6,100 19,000 21,900		Stocks in the United Kingdom, remaining in Bonded Warehouses, or entered to be Warehoused.		Tea      ...       -        -Coffee    -Cocoa    -         -        -		40,700 38,900 17,700	44,700 39,900 15,700	16,200 66,000 57,500		Stocks in the United Kingdom at Ports and in the hands &apos; of Millers, Crushers, and Cake Manufacturers.		Oilseeds, &amp;c. Oilseed Cake and Meal   -	-	207,900 92,400	226,200 73,600	339,800 141,500	* In manufacturers&apos; hands only.			-Number of Live Stock in Great Britain.					September 4th, 1918 (Estimated).!	June 4th, 1918.	June 4th, 1917.	June 5th, 1916.Dairy Cattle -Total Cattle -Ewes kept for breeding Total Sheep -Sows kept for breeding Total Pigs    -	3,100,000 7,470,000 9,100,000 21,000,000 315,000 2,150,000	3,030,000 7,408,000 9,498,000 23,338,000 306,000 1,825,000	2,907.000 7,437,000 9,899,000 24,043,000 269,000 2,051,000	2,870,000 7,442,000 10,066,000 .25,007,000 301,000 2,314,000f Estimates prepared by the Lire Stock Committee of the Board of Agriculture,i.  6658-5
12Table E, Percentage Increase in Retail Food Prices in theUnited Kingdom, at each oe the Undermentioned Dates, as compared with&quot; Normal Prices in July .1914.&quot;[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.&apos;	Percentage Inorease on Normal Prices in July 1914.                  . . ,&apos; .								Article.										1st Jan.	1st Jan.	1st Jan.	1st July	1st Sept.	1st Jan.	1st Aug.	1st Sept.	1st Oct.	1915.	1916.	-1917.	1917.	1917.	1918.	1918.	1918.	1918:Beef :-			64-2	96-1	97-4	80-5	83-8	83-8	102-6British Ribs	7-0	35-3							Thin flank	11-2	45-2	83-5	132-2	130-9	100-9	98-1	98-2	126-3Chilled or frozen 																		Ribs  -i	16-3	46-7	85-4	119-6	122-1	116-4	147-9	147-9	175-4Thin flank -	26-7	63-1	101-2	156-5	157-9	137-3	164-7	164-7	206-5Mutton: 									British Legs	5-8	27-9	58-7	100 0	97-7	76-8	84-5	84-5	102-4Breast	11-7	413	84-2	142-2	138-2	92-5	77-7	77-5	106-6Frozen Legs	16-3	41-8	86-4	134-4	136-0	134-0	176-5	176-5	205-6Breast	24-8	62-7	122-0	190-8	190-9	161-8	168-5	168-5	217-4Bacon, streaky *	7-1	30-7	56-3	76-4	96-0	138-7	139-6	141-4	141-9Fish       -   . -	40-9	96-7	131-1	127-1	136-1	195-9	188-7	189-4	191-5Flour	20-3	49-0	88-5	109-3	109-2	51-8	52-1	52-0	52-1Bread	15-8	41-7	73-3	100-3	996	54-4	54-5	546	54-8Tea -     -     -      -	13-6	48-2	50-9	73-7	78-9	98-2	73-3	73-3	.73-3Sugar, grauulated	67-0	93-3	170-0	187-7	190-0	189-3	241-2	241-0	241-3Milk	6-7	28-8	56-6	59-7	61-0	99-5	88-0	95-2 ,	1332Potatoes                17.	\16-1	US	121-7	144-3	38-9	37-1	113-6	66-4	63 5Margarine	4-4	6-9	25-0	73-5	66-0	65-9	97-0	97-0	96-9Butter, fresh	13-8	33-9	72-9	64-7	90-8	103-4	95-3	93-7	103-8Butter, salt     -	12-1	31-5	70-6	65-3	90-1	105-4	99-2	98-5	110-4Cheese, Canadian or	10-0	31-7	74-8	108-0	94-7	91-3	125-5	129-2	130-2U.S.*									Eggs, fresh	63-4	104-9	175-0	95-3	142-4	242-1	295-0	293-7	329-2* If this kind is seldom dealt with in a locality the Returns quote prices for another kind locally representative,f. Decrease.Table F.-Retail Prices of Subsidiary Foods in April, 1917, and SubsequentMonths compared with the Prices in July, 1914, in London andother large towns.[Information supplied by the Department of Labour Statistics.]Article.Pereentage Increase on Normal Prices in July 1914.April 1st,1917.July 1st,1917.Sept. 1st,1917.Jan. 1st,1918.April 1st,1918.July 1st,1918.Aug. 1st,1918.Sept. 1st,1918.Butter beans  -Haricot beans (white)Peas, split (yellow) -Lentils, split (red)   -Oatmeal, ScotchRice, RangoonSago     -Tapioca -     -     -Condensed milkLard, British -American1602301402101409014012065125130140180210230150f100180160110120110110140210220150J100180150110120120113140220232100103200170139125139113140220232113117227185143164113140220232120117251210152168113140220232120117264223152186113140220232120117282238152186X 125 in Scotland, .
Table G-. Consumption and Sale of Flour by Bakers and Retailers.   Comparison of Four-weekly Periods in 1917-18.(All measured as percentages of quantities used in May 1917.)Four Weeks endedFood Control Divisions.	Oct. 12, 1918.	Sept. 14, 1918	August 17, 1918.	July 20, 1918.	June 22, 1918.	May 25, 1918. -.	April 27, 1918.	March 30, 1918.	March 2, 1918.	Feb. 2, 1918.	Jan. 0, 1918.	Dec. 8, 1917.	Nov. 10, 1917.	Oct. 13, 1917.	Sept. 15 1917.	Aug. 18, 1917.Newcastle          -      -Leeds -       -Manchester -      -Nottingham -                       -Birmingham Cambridge -       -       -      -London       - -    -Home Counties, North -Home Counties, South -Reading     -Bristol        -       -Carnarvon   -Cardiff -	102* 101 102* 108 99* 118 94 109 112* 118 106 1181 98	101 96* 100* 104 100* 114 91 106* 110 116 103 120* 97	961 93 97* 96 95 108 874 1031 107 112* 99 117 92	93* 87* 94* 98 96 110 91 100 107 110 101 112 89*	95 91 97 100* 98* 108 95* 100* 105 109* 103 108* 93*	94* 95* 95* 100* 97* 108 98 100* 103* 109* 102 102 92*	99* 96 98 104* 99* 108 99 101 106 111* 104 104* 92*	103* 951 97* 103&quot; 101 109 98* 102 104 110 101 103* 94*	99 96 99* 107* 100 111* 100* 100 103* 110 102 99 95	104* 98* 98* 105 99* 111* 101 99* 102* 106* 101* 99* 97	100* 92 93 100 93 108* 97 97 99 103 97 96 93*	110 100 96* 104 96 111 101* 97* 100* 104* 101 98* 97	109* 103* 97* 104 96 111* 98* 97* loot 104* 100* 100i 98&quot;	96 96 96 98 93* 108 93* 95 98* 102* 99 100 97	81 82 89 89 89* 100i 87&quot; 91 97 98* 92 96 90*	83 80 89 88 88 100 84 94 96 99 92 99 91*England and Wales	1041	102	98	97	99	99	101	&apos; 100*	101	101	96*	100*	100* .	97	88*	88Glasgow     -       -       -Edinburgh	951 98*	95 97*	90 95	85 98	91* 98*	92 97*	95 100	96 99*	97 102*	98 104	92 101	95* 102*	96* 104	95 103	91 99	88 96Scotland^	99*	99	95	91	95	95	97*	98	100	101	96	98*	99*	98*	94	91Ireland -      -      -      -	104*	1011	99	941	95*	94	94*	96*	94	96*	93*	98	97	96*	92*	92United Kingdom  -	104	102	98	96	98	98	100	100	100J	100*	96	100	100	97	90*	89*England and Wales : Boroughs,    other    than London, with popula-tion over 50,000. Smaller towns and rural districts.	100J 110*	97* 109	93  105	92 103	94* 104	95 102*	97* 104*	98 103*	98* 104	99 103*	93* 99	99 101*	100* 101*	95* 98*	86* 92	85 92*CO* Including Inverness Division for which the returns are too few to allow a separate statement.3N3CO

</content>
</cab>
