<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 394-399</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
PROPOSED INQUIRY INTO PHOHTS IN RELATION TO COST OF LIVING.dillmmmim by tee food coktboilkr. C , M   AHerewith is a list of articles of food showing tho differentegrees of control exercised by the flood Ministry.    The listhows that so far ac control, the fixing of prico3 and distributionjmder the authority of Government can prevent profiteering, undueofita are not possible in connection with the more common articles[f daily food.    Where our Orders affe violated, or evaded, proceedingsinder tho law are taken.    Devices and evasions in certain oases aretoo frequent but under any precedure which could bo now followedthese must bo reckoned as a factor in food sales and distribution.-It is inevitable in the case of several foods that prices willlie.   The costs of producing meat, milk, eggs, fruit, fish andither artioles have increased and the prioes of: these and other foodslust go up unless the Government is prepared, as in the oase ofread, to provide state subsidies.    Subsidies on a large scale wouldrun into an enormous sum, and would give relief to about two-thirds oftho population who are well able to pay even existing food prices.Subsidy as a policy is not generally supported in either the f^ado-friion or the Co-operative movement though in a section of the labour- &apos;    : -aovement subsidies are now being strongly pressed.Any investigation into profiteering and its relation to wagesnd unrest would have to go far beyond articles of food.   In thattvent &quot;profiteering&quot; would be discovered and provod.  flor in thesense that profits far higher than a pre-war level have boon madethere has been profiteering in Cotton goods, machinery, in theolothing, Building, Chemical, Iron, Munition, Shipbuilding and&apos;y.-&apos;:;.&quot;:-;general trades.   High profits have been made in tho sale andfcanufacturo of drinks and refreshments and in caterings   The reports^nd balance sheets of trading companies show a levol of prosperity
9 &apos;M 0igh above pre-war conditions.     In turn, the Government has profited7 these profits and large sums have been paid to the National Revenue,he fact that the Government has been able in War Loans to raisafiundreds of millions in a short time is taken by many working mon asufficient proof of profiteering even though many working-men havehemcelves loaned money*There would have to bo on any Commission of enquiry a considerablefabour representation, and I am convinced that those representativesould return a verdict acceptable to a large section of Labour opinion,f the mattor is to be gone into at all by means of a Commission, Ithink there should bo a clear understanding on what is intended when theJrerdiot which may bo regarded as certain, is given.   To appoint aornmission without a definite purpose would result in greater troubleInd would not in any case deal with the other factors which in wartime create discontent.   These factors would be a large contribution*lo continued unroot even if all Labour and wage questions weresatisfactorily settled.   Trade&apos; and industrial conditions in War time-ire conducted under abnormal circumstances.   The ordinary forces offiompetition and commercial restraint are absent.   Big profits becomeIncidental, because the demand is imperative, and suppliers because ofshortage on the ono hand and high wagers on the other can determine&apos; morer  the bargain than is possible in peace times.   These are realitiest/hich would not be- altered by a Commission of Enquiry.The policy which in my opinion tho Government should follow is onlome one of tho following lines:-To provide subsidies to cheapen say &quot;plentiful foods&quot; as bacon, eggs,milk, potatoes, vegetables, fish and a higher subsidy for Flour orbread.   The rationed foods like meat, fats and sugar involve noh^avy family outlay because of their scarcity.1* To increase substantially the wages of all low paid workers who nowearn below a fixed sum per week.I. To return to the Pood Ministry so as to cheapen certain foods themoney now received by the Government from increased taxation ontrading in Foods, $rinks and refreshments.INISTRY. OF FOOD, J.R.CLYNES,1st Nov.1918. ...........
Foods controlled a a to Prices..A.Foods in which the Ministry acts as. importer or purchaserand in which prices are controlled throughout.MeatCanned MeatBacon, Ham &amp; lardButter - ImportedMargarineCheeseCondensed MilkTeaSugarDried FruitsCerealsII-, Foods in which the import or production and the wholesaleand retail prices^are controlled.Butter i* HomeMilkPotatoesBritish &apos;&amp; Imported OnionsJam &amp; JellyMarmaladeBeerSpiritsFlourCocoa ButterCocoa PowderCocoanut - Desiccated
B.       List of certain foods the price?of whichare non-controlled.MacaroniPearl BarleySagoTapiobaCornflourBiscuitsHoneyEggsTinned PishShell PishVegetablesCarrotsTurnipsGreen VegetablesTomatoesBananasOrangesCanned FruitsAll kinds of Nuts(uBed as fruit)SaltVinegarSalad OilSpicesWines
Foods In which wholesale &amp; retail prloos are controlled.Poultry &amp; GameRabbitsFishVegetable MarrowsFruitsApplesStrawberriesBlackberries.SyrupPoultry FoodsFoods in which&apos;wholesale prices only are controlled.FruitstoosoberriesRaspberriesCurrantsPerry PearsPlumsGreengagesDams onsCat tie Feeding StuffsDamaged Grain
232V. Foods in which retail prices only are controlled.CoffeeChocolateSweetmeatsSwedesBread ( Flour controlled in earlier stages)PulsesBeansPeasLentilsCerealsMaizeOatmealRiceHominyOats - proprietary brands

</content>
</cab>
