<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 401-402</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
JMpartaent of Agriculture and Technical Instruction for Ireland,&apos;P00D raODUCTI&amp;i SCHEMES, IREUKD.^Jfemc^ajimFi prepared in compliance with Chief Secretary&apos;e&apos; &apos; Minute of 17th teirch,   1917.feck ended 30th October, 1918.The following is a brief statement on the work cf the Departmenturing the past week in furtherance of increased Food Production inIreland :-Tnirty-one applications for Iocjis for agricultural implementa wereeceived by the Department during the past week.  The total value ofnchinery ordered from the beginning or the present year, to date,ider the Scheme, amounts to  94,387.Progress has been made during the week with the collection of runtsfrom the per eons to whom land wan set in conacre on holdingsitered on by the Department last spring under the Defence of thefilm Regulations.I   While no definite decision has yet been arrived at as regards thefeulscry Tillage Regulations for the year 1919, it is contemplatedhi an Order will be made by the Department, under the Third ScheduleI the Corn Production Act, 1917, requiring occupiers of holdings inIsland to cultivate in 1919 the same proportion of their arable landIwas required under the 1916 Tillage Orders.  This matter, amongtiers, will be considered at a meeting of the Departments Advisoryfaittee to be held next week.I     : &quot;       HaJ.^lejt^g.  Most of the Flax crop has now been secured in stacks,&amp; ofit being considerably damaged through the prolonged exposureI the fields to the wet weather.fcchfir8rr Dispute. The trouble now appears to be ended, and scutchingSations are in xul1 progress.ing of Sgutcfoing; Charges.  The Committee of Inquiry have nowienteoTtheir report to the Department and representations will be1 immediately with a viow to having their reconsaendationa enforced.I^.ng^aujy^  The reports received still indicate that yields offcoTflax^OT be nuch under average.Itfsg     arjr^ of flax.  The increase of 5/- per stone in the price! -a^^entoy announced by the Ministry of Stations has given greatUf action to farmers, and has produced a very material change in! direction of making thorn more inclined to grovr a:.i extensiveUge in 1919.IftippUfts for 191.9. The prospects of sufficient supplies of flax-Ibeing&apos;available for next season are now excellent.
The continuance of seasonable weather enabled good progress tobe made with farm work during the week.  The greater portion of thehay and corn crops refining in the fields has now been secured.In ft nuaber of oases heating has occurred in hay ricks hurriedly puttogether during the rainy weather and turning has in some instancesbeen found necessary.  Threshing has proceeded rapidly.  The liftingof potatoes was general,   and trie work is now well advanced.  Thedrier condition of the ground made it possible to eciploy potatodiggers to &amp; greater extent than during the previous week.  The crop,03the, whole, is reported to be a fairly gocS one.  There arer&amp;ports of blackeniru; in heavy clays, and of rotting on wet lands.In some districts crops trhich appeared sound a few weeks ago nowshow a fairly large percentage of diseased tubers.The greater portion of the mangel crop has now been pulled andstored.  The yield generally is fairly satisfactory, but not up toexpectations.  Turnips are still growing and promise to bulk well,hit owing to the patchy state of the crop, the average yield will,it is anticipated, be rather low. Winter wheat was sown during thereek under good soil and weather conditions.Catch crops * particularly rape - are reported to be makinggood progress.  As emphasing the iiaportanco oi, and profitableresults iron, sowing these crops early, there is cited a case in Co.Cork where 3i aorea were sown with rape as a rotation crop in Lay.tieep to the number of 66 were turned on to graze the crop for fiveweks froa Mid-July and at the end of that period were valued at  2per head mare than they would have realised before grazing.  At(resent there ia a second growth - nore than eighteen inches hi/ah -Igain to be erased by sheep.  The land which has borne this crip willS ploughed ror a g^ain crop.During the period from 22nd to 26th instant, inclusive,220 applications Tor licences to slaughter or export heifers, 92applications for licences to slaughter bulls or bullocks cad 136^plications for licences to export&apos; nilch cows, were received.

</content>
</cab>
