<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 476-477</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
r\K^ST SLI STOAT OF THE COAL INDUS TOY,The Ministry of Shipping desire to urge upon the WarCabinet the vital importance cf reestablishing the output of coalat least on the pre-war basis immediately on the cecsation ofhostilities.It is essential that ships becoming free in heme waters   ,on the cessation of hostilities should be able to load coal car-go^as it is unlikely that there will be suffXcientoguarxtltiea......o .otherexports to fill them until a later date.   If they cannot obtaincoal cargoes it means that they will have oo go out in ballastand that means that the cost of the outward voyage will fallupon the inward cargo.   It is essential for the reestablishmentof our industries that there should be an adequate supplyof cheap raw material.   It will not be possible to obtain thisunless the coal exported pays fur the outward voyage.We are dependent, too, upon the export of coal toattract to our trade the neutral tonnage which will be requiredto bring in the urgently needed supplies of iron-oret timberand wood pulp.Unless therefore adequate supplies of coal are availablethe shipping position immediately after the cessation-ofhostilities will present very grave difficulties.The reestablishment cf the coal output is also of vitalimportance for..financial reasons and to reestablish our foreignexchanges.Practically all our home industries depend upon anadequate supply of coalj the pig-iron and steel industry inparticular will need large supplies if the present homeproduction is to be increased or even maintained^   Thereconstruction of all the allied countries will majce enocraiooaclaims on the iron and steel output.
rj ^ tJ2.The importance of the., above - considerations Trill begreatest inthe period immediately following the cessationof hostilities before trade and shipping have found theirpeace level.    It is not therefore sufficient to leavethe coal industry to be daalt with on the same lines asother industries *The output of coal in 1913 was about 287 milliontons, in 1917 248,5 million tons and in the first ninemonths of the current year 170.8 million tons, or at therate of about 228 million tons in the year.    It isunderstood that this reduction in output is solelyattributable to the enlistment of miners.The purpose of this memorandum is to urge in thestrongest&apos;possible terms that instructions should beissued that directly an armistice is signed immediatesteps should be taken to demobilise the coal minersIn the army as speedily as possible.     It is believed thatthe total number of miners recruited during the war hasbeen about 400,000 men;.4th November, 1918.

</content>
</cab>
