<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/68/0 images: 495-501</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Confidential. POLITIO&amp;L INTELLIGENCE L^ii^ICNl(iiNovember 1918). POBEIGH OFFICEMEMORANDUMINTERNAL   CONDITIONS     IN    GERMANY.There are peculiar difficulties this week inwriting a report on Germany owing to the great variety offactors which ought to bo taken into account and the uncer-tainty which up to the last moment must prevail as to theprecise nature of the decisive results which must issue&quot;from them.In reply to President Wilson1s last Note fOctober23) the German Government - after some brief hesitation, if -we may believe a section of the German Press -Jbas once moregently and almost reproachfully called the president1s attentionto the &quot;far-reaching changes which have been carried out andare being carried out in the gemman Constitutional Structure&quot;.Germany now asserts that she has a &quot;popular Government&quot;which has actually and constitutionally the power of makingdecisions, and it is further declared that &quot;the military powers,too, are subject to it&quot;.The last statement Is to be taken with the neoes-sary reservations.     It is true that Xuden&amp;orff resigned onOctober 26, or that his resignation, which had doubtless beenhanded in earlier, was accepted on that date.    But very sig-nificant instances of arbitrary military intervention are stillreported.    Thus the General Commanding the Stettin Axmy Dis-trict, having obtained a copy of a private letter addressed byHindenburg to.the Imperial Chancellor, Prince Max of Baden,hastened to have,it printed and placarded throughout Stettin.In this letter, Hindenburg says;
-2- *) r; iW iJ i.&quot;Our enemies are deriving fresh courage for their offen-sive from the spectacle of our, internal dissensions and our&apos;despondency.    Both enemy countries and neutrals are begin-ning to regard us as being no longer a people which stakesBtarything for its honour&quot;, (1)He therefore adjures the German people to play the man, to beunited, and to stand fast against any attempt of its enemies toimpose a humiliating peace.     &quot;Peace with honour or a fight:toa finish!&quot; he cries. .^he new Coalition Government, or executive, ordirectorate, or whatever it ought to ho called, professes much ,*the same views, but its spokesmen resent the attempt of the.Array leaders to cast upon them the responsibility for internaldissensions and national-despondency. , It is now openly de-olared that it was Kinlenburg and Ludeni orff who, by theirperhaps premature opinion that the situation on the Westernfront was becoming desperate and necessitated an.immediatearmistice, decided the adoption of the present peace policyof Germany.    It is&apos; not for them to turn round at this stageand pose as the saviours of their country, which they:repre-sent as being betrayed by the party spirit and the pacifismof the only kind of Government ?to which President :Wilsonwould liston - a Government which attempts to establish,itself on the basis of the parliamentary representation ofthe people. \U    . MM &quot;   MmMMWv M MM &quot; M   (z)     -nfiindenburg-rS&apos; letter&quot;, .says the frankfurter^eitung .can only be interpreted as intended to convey that theHigher Command never emitted any other opinion on thesituation than what is conveyed in the appeal: 1Hold upyour heads, you weaklings at home: the Army will manageall rightinT . .The Government is exhorted to.put a stop to these machinationsof the Higher Command and the reported appointment ,of GeneralGroner to succeed ludendorff is regarded as affording semeguarantee that, there will now be a change... of methods,,, as, .(1) Frankfurter-  eitung QcttS5 (Evening EM&apos; 3SFo*g96&apos;&quot;p*2*.coXvl-(g)     ^-r**Ti-    tt   26      &quot;        &quot;    KokB97 leading. &apos;
3r&apos;-3-Grttner, when Director of the Munitions Department, enjoyed theconfidence of the Reichstag and the masses.    It is furtherreported that even Kindenburg is now a fallen idol and thatinsulting demonstrations take place in front of his nail-studdedwooden statue in the Berlin Thiergarten.As to the resignation of Ludendorff, there arepersistent reports to the effect that his offence went beyondthat of underestimating the strength of the enemy at the timeof the, Gorman Spring Offensive, and beyond that of underestimat-ing the German power of defence in the present retreat.     Iteven, according to certain accounts, went beyond his subsequent-attempt to cast blame upon the new Government for taking hisown urgent advice and suing for peace.    He is believed tohave initiated a kind of plot for the establishment of amilitary dictatorship, to have made overtures to the Governmentsor Sovereigns of various German States in this sense, and tohave actually contemplated the inclusion of Austria in thescheme.The new men who are attempting to manage theaffairs of the Empire in a time of desperate crisis are inthe extraordinarily difficult position of having to keep the -Army and the Higher Command in good heart and, at the sametime, to prevent the Higher Command from usurping the func-tions of government and civil administration.    Anothermeeting under the auspices of the Peace Society has been pro-hibited by the police in Berlin against the declared wishesof the Government.   . This has caused a great outcry and ithas been intimated that the Government knows the persons whoare at the back of the prohibition - presumably the ChiefHome Command in Brandenburg - and that it will take steps tohave its authority obeyed.
-4-or 9It is like discussing domestic^squai^lee indoorsin the midst of an earthquake, to review these internal Germanaffairs while the fate of Spires, nations and anoient Crownsis being decided in the vast theatre of War and of Revolution.But it is precisely these matters that are preparing the Germancontribution to the vast general upheaval in Central Europe.The mass of the people, including a great proportion of theprofessional and middle classes in Germany, is now under thefull influenoe of sudden disillusionment,    the realisation ofits own terrible sacrifices and the contagion of revolution inthe great neighbouring States.     The question of guilt forthese immeasurable calamities has now been raised and the an-swer is heing given that the responsibility for what hashappened lies with the Prussian Junker and great industrialistgoverning class, the military caste and, last but not least,with the Emperor and the dynasty.    The Prussian SuffrageReform, which even the Upper House of the Prussian Diethurriedly swallowed at one sitting on Thursday, October 24,is designed to break the power of the Junkers and the bigindustrialists.    A series of amendments&apos;&apos;to the Constitutionof the Empire is intended to subordinate military authorityto civil and to curtail the prerogatives and the personalpolitical licence of the Emperor.     The federal Councilproposed or accepted certain modest proposals in this sense.The Reichstag has insisted on extending them.    As regardsthe Emperor, the Chancellor is to bear responsibility for allhis political acts and declarations.     In reality, as in con-stitutional language, the Chancellor himself is to he maderesponsible to the Federal Council and the Reichstag for hisofficial conduct, and there is to be a sx^ecial Court of Lawcreated, before which he can be impeached.    The Emperor&apos;b
-5-decision for war and peace is to be made subject to the assentof the Reichstag as well as of the Federal Council    the bodywhich represents the federated Governments of all the GermanStates,     At present the iimperoz cen of his own will declarewar without the,assent even of the Federal Council., if thefrontiers or coasts of tho Empire have been attacked.     Itwill be remembered that the declaration of war upon Russiaon August 1, 1914, and upon Trance on August 3, was basedupon the contention, after the event, that Russia had attackedthe Eastern frontier and that Prance had sent airmen to bombNtirnburg.     Both assertions were false and were doubtlessintended to justify the omission to ask the assent of theI-sacral Council.Other amendments make all appointments, promotions,transfers and dismissals of officers of the Army and lavysubject, in the case of the Navy to counter-signature by theImperial Chancellor, and in the case of the Amy to counter-signature by the War Minister of the State in whose contingentthe appointments are made.    These War Ministers are to be maderesponsible to the Reichstag for the administration of theircontingents.    Presumably this will not apply to Bavaria,whose Army is on a separate financial and administrativefooting.The reactionary press represents these amendmentsas amounting to the &quot;sacrifice of the Crown and the Empirefor YJilson\s sakeK.    But the organ of the governmentalSocislists, &quot;Yorwflrts, expressly states that these new pro-visions are not due to President Wilson1 s references toarbitrary power, but to &quot;events of very recent date&apos;&quot;.     &quot;AState must not allow its policy to beeprescribed.even byvictorious Generals, still less by such as have not in allcircumstances displayed the insight which their official      &quot;
Q PJ Ka  it-6-position demands.&quot;As for tho position in which the emperor Williamnow finds himself, it is doubtful whether tho restrictionsupon his arbitrary power which the Reichstag is enacting, willat this stage suffice to save his qi own and his dynasty.The Frankfurter Zeitung, by thinly veiled suggestions, theVorw&amp;rts by frank admonition, iainority Socialist speakersin the Reichstag by violent denunciation, are endeavouring topersuade him to &quot;draw the necessary inferences&quot; from thetransformation which the whole political and military situa-tion has ungergoae.    Workmen are execrating him in thestreets and, in one place, his statue has beon attired withgrotesnie habiliments by way of insult and of invitation totake his departure.    These predicaments of once exalted per-sonages heve always sordid aspects, which become the sardonicfeatures of history,.   It remains to bo seen whether the oldPrussian personal loyalty, which till recently extended&apos; farinto the middle and the working classes, will survive thestrain which events and the Emperor himself have put upon itjand whether there exists a corps of officers who can inter-pose a bodyguard of the Army between William II. and hisdisillusioned people.    Any direct intervention of the Armymight easily, in present circumstances, lead to civil war.The momentous events in Austria will only intensifytho German crisis.    There is a manifest tendency on the partof the present Reichstag Majority to prepare the paths forthe re-entry of the German Austrians into the framework of theGerman Confederation, if the development of the situation in    .what was, till yesterday, the Austrian Empire, should drive^      vthem to seek that refuge.    At the same time;, there will beStrenuous opposition in North and Central Germany to anyattempted coalition of German Austria with a South Gorman
17State, suoh as would alter the balance of power and populationas between Worth and South.In the efforts of the new German Government tosecure an armistice and peace there has been betrayed aforlorn hope of getting-President Wilson to act as arbitrator&quot;between Germany and the Allied Powers, wheteao America andher President are parties, and very active parties, in thestruggle.    An alternative current of opinion * they frequent-ly mingle and interchange * is to represent America andGermeny as tho protagonists and to seek to get an armisticeand make peace whloh would pr&amp;ctioally force the EuropeanAllies to become parties to a fait accompli.    Both theseschemes have already foundered.    Germany must fact thewhole concert of her present adversaries.\

</content>
</cab>
