<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 102-110</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
[IS DOCUMENT IS THE Pi&amp;PBP/fY OF HIS B HIT ANN IG MAJESTY1S government C g E T.P. 204 (38). COPY NO.CABINET.&quot;THE TREASURE,.OP THE GIIEDPKS&quot;.My colleagues may bo interested&apos;in the annexed minute from the Director of the Victoria and Albert Museum,- with accompanying Memorandum, in regard to a proposal made by the ex-Puho of Brunswick-Luneburg to sell this historic collection.I fear the information is only of academic interest since it is clearly Impossible for me to suggest any action by the Government in the matter,,E. P.Board of Education,29th June, 1920.
I have to put before you a purchase proposal which has boen made to me, although it is on a scale quite outside our own powers.Last week a&apos;Viennese legal official, Mr, Max. Glilokselig, called on no by appointment as the -representative of the ex-Luke of Brunswlck-Luneburg, who is, I believe, living in Austria and who is the owner of the world-famous Welfenschatz.      This treasuro,  on which Mr. Eoop has written me the interesting report annexed, has been for many centuries in the possession of tho Guelph family, and if the Salic Law had not excluded Queon Victoria from the throne of Hanover,  it would no doubt now be in tho possession of the English crown.     Of all treasures of mediaeval goldsmiths&apos; work it is probably the most famous, and it certainly ranks among the half dozon most important assemblages of mediaeval goldsmiths&apos; work,..the-rest being, I suppose, all in church possession,.The treasure has been got out of Germany, and I am informed that it is now in the vaults of a bark in Switzerland.      The Luke of Brunswick-Lunoburg wishes to sell it  (I heard rumours of this a good many months ago), and he expresses a great desire that it should, if possible, be acquired by England, in view of its intimate connection with the ancestors of the Royal Family.      I am also Informed that the Duke is determined, if there is any possibility of doing so, to keep the treasure intact and not to sell it piecemeal,.The prico asked is naturally enormous.      I pressed Mr. Gluckselig to name the figure the Duke had in mind,  and he ultimately told me that it could be purchased by England for the sum of a million and a half pounds
sterling;    the price asked for a sale to America being 12 million dollars,  or nearly a million pounds more than the price named for a salo to England.      Both these figures are, I imagine, merely tentative      I asked Mr. Koop to make a very rough valuation and he has dono so,      This valuation is of course made sololy from the illustrations and many of the objects in the troasu.ro are of a kind the value of which it is almost impossible to assess.      But we hare recently made a valuation of the contents of this Musoum for the Royal Commission,  and this has been done on the same linos,     As you will see, his valuation, which is not on an ungenerous scale, amounts to just over half a million pounds, though it is only put forward as a very rough approximation, and it is porfootly possible that the Duke might be able to get much more than this from a dealer with the American market at his disposal.I have promised to write In due course to Mr. G-luckselig, who is now on his way back to Vienna.      It is obvious that no kind of stop could be taken in the matter unless it could be taken up as one of national impox-tance by the Stato, and from our own point of view there is a serious disadvantage in the fact that one of the two outstanding objects in the collection (the domed reliquary shrino) is almost a duplicate of our Eltenborg reliquary, though it is in finer condition and perhaps rather more valuable.(Sgd. ).    ERIC MACLAC-AU.26 Juno,  1928.
THE TREASURE 01? THE. GUELPHS.The &quot;Wolfens chats&quot; or Treasure of the Guelphs is without question by far the richest and most important collection of mediaeval goldsmiths1 work at present in private hands.      The great majority of the eighty-three works of art comprised in this remarkable collection are examples of Ecclesiastical Metalwork ranging in date from the eleventh to the fifteenth century, such as Crosses, Portable Altars, Reliquaries, Book-oovers, Monstrances^ Ciboria, and the liko.     Most of them are in a remarkable state of preservation and untouched or unaltered from their original form      which cannot be said for a largo proportion of similar objects in other collections, including, one must say, that of the Museum.     Another important quality characterising the Treasure is that of a complete absence of any doubt as to the absolute TT genuine-ness&quot; of the items composing it.     There exists an illustrated catalogue of the collection, by JoH. Jung, of which a fourth edition was. published in 1783  (a copy in our Library).&apos;    Moreover, the history of many of the items can ,be traced back with certainty a considerable way, if not in all cases to the aotual date of origin.The standard work on the Treasure is the sumptuoils folio by Dr. W.A. Neumann, published In 1891,     -this is an elaborate catalogue raisonne^&quot; illustrated by numerous fine woodcuts after photographs.      The librax-y copy of t rs work is accompanied by a number of unpublished coloured plates of some of the more important items in the collection.The present owner of the Treasure is the late Reigning Duke of Brunswiok-Iiuneburg, heir-male and representative of the fifth son of George III, and therefore, like the Royal House of Windsor, a descendant
of the Guelphs.      On the death of William IV (3rd son of George III)  In 1037, the devolution of the crown upon his niece  (Victoria,  daughter of the 4th son) presumably included, under a succession based on the Salic Law, the loss of the Treasure of the Guelphs, the crown of Hanover then devolving upon the 5th son, Ernest Augustus, grand-father of tho present owner.The two most valuable and important items in the Treasure aro, first, what is practically the fellow to the famous Eltenberg Reliquary, which forms one of the chief possessions of our Museum, a large shrine for relics in the form of a romanosquc church, richly decorated, with enamols and ivory-carvings, the work of the monk Frederick of Cologne about 1165-1170;    and, secondly, the remarkable Portable Altar which is the Only existing signed work.of the monk Eilbert of Cologne, the earliest known artist of the Cologne School of enamellers and goldsmiths;    this altar, dating from ca.  1130., is of casket form and is covered with a wonderful series of ohamplever enamel plaques depicting scenes in the life of Christ.      Our Museum possesses no single example of the peculiar enamelling technique for which Eilbert is renowned. -To describe briefly some of the outstanding items in various other groups of objects in the Treasure we may take first vrtiat is known as the Yfelf enkreuz or Cross of the Guelphs, which consists of a cross-shaped reliquary of gold enriched with cloisonne&quot; enamel, set in a gold--covered wooden cross enriched with gems and.pearls, \;he whole standing on a silver pillar supported on a foot&apos;-formed by three figures of angels.      The-two Gertrude Crosses,&apos; named after the Countess Gertrude  (d.  1077), of the
Guelph House, for whom they were made in the 11th century, resemble one another closely and are examples of the wooden dross of simple form covered with gold foil enriched with embossing, filigree-work, cloisonne* enamel and gems;    the type is rare, only six or seven other examples  (one in our Museum) being known.     A copper-gilt Cross, flanked by figures of the Virgin and St. John and enriched with beautiful engraving, is supported on a balli !held in the mouths of three rampant lions and is a noble example Of Romanesque work of the 12th or 13th century. Of the GOthic period are three very striking and important Altar-crosses in embossed silver, copper-gilt, and silver-gilt respectively.Besides the Eilbert example already described,  the Treasure contains no less than ten other Portable Altars, a class wilich is, indeed, exceedingly rare outside the Germanic countries.      Chief among them is tho Gertrude Altar, named after the Margravine Gertrude II (d. 1117); it is caskbt-shapewith porphyry top, the sides of gold embossed with figures of saints in enamelled arcading, the borders of filigree-work sot with precious stones. Another, of the 11th century, is remarkable for the niello-work on the silver mounting of its sides and the richly engraved copper plate which covers the base.     A third is decorated with ehampleve figures of Virtues and has a circular table of serpentine enclosed within a copper-gilt plaque beautifully engraved with a palmette border and the evangelistic symbols.Among -the thirteen or fourteen Casket Reliquaries, besides the one of &quot;Eltenberg&quot; type above described,  is an example of the very rare gabled form^&quot;, which rests onx   Known as the Reliquary of St. Walburga.- 5 -
8ifour griffin feet and has the sides and roof onriched with champ leve* enamel plaques of various saints in the Eilbert style.     Another,  entirely of oopper enriched with enamel, has been attributed to a North European school, von Falke considering it to be English work of the 12th century, though this is doubtful.      One more of these must be mentioned, an example of the 13th century, having the sides covered with enamelled copper plates, the top with die-stamped gilt metal plaques representing Our Lord and symbolic figure subjects of extreme interest.A very remarkable Reliquary Tablet encloses a magnificent carved ivory plaque representing the Feast of Cana, of 11th century date;    the wide border, which is of the 13th century, is plated with silver enriched with cabochon stones, intagli,  etc., from the settings of which spring radiating stems with leaves;    its base is covered by a silver plaque delightfully engraved with &quot;figures of the three patron saints of the Guelph house.      The covers of a 13th-century Plenarium connected with Luke Otto  (1339) are chiefly interesting for the twenty small paintings on parchment under crystal with which the front is decorated,ted; the book itself&apos; contains a number of most important illuminations and other paintings.The Treasure contains two Head-reliquaries; one, of St,  Cosmas,  is of wood covered with silver plates and has an inscription dating it to the 13th century;  &apos;&quot;$he other, of St. Blaise, represented in full canonicals,  is similarly constructed and is further set with gems, a 14th-century work with later additions.     Bo less than eleven Arm-reliquaries are in the collection (there is only a late example in our Museum);    they range in date
from the 12th to the 15th century and are mostly of embossed silver over wood foundations.Besides a few small miscellaneous objects of comparatively minor importance, the list of the &quot;Treasure Is completed by nineteen Reliquaries and Ciboria of the Gothic period.     All of these agree in being supported by the characteristic knopped stem and spreading circular or hexagonal foot, but show great diversity in their upper parts.      The most important is that usod to display a Paten which has been attributed to the hand of St. Bernward,  the renowned goldsmith-bishop of Hi1deskelm filth century),A very large number of holy relics are enclosed Within one or another of most of the larger pieces in the collection.
VALUATION&apos; OF THE WELFBiJSCHATZ. (In units of    1,000.)10    The Welfenkreuz 2,3. The two Gertrude Crosses a.      Cross 5-8 .. Three Crosses 9,10 Two Pendent. Crosses 11.    Reliquary Pendent Cross IS,    The Adeloldus Altar 13.    The Gortrude Altar 14.    Altar 15.        &quot; 16.        &quot;17..        n with circular plato 18.        n19.    The EiInert Altar 20.    Sclavonic Altar 21,22 Two small Altars 23.    The Kuppelreliquier (Eltehborg type) 24.    The Walhurga Reliquary 25.    Casket with enamelled plaquo 26.    Casket27.    Casket of northern type 20-32. Five caskets 33,34.  Two Oriental ivory caskets 35.       leather-covered Casket 36.        Boxwood Pyz 37.       The Cana Reliquary 38.    &quot;   The Demetrius Plaque 39.       The Dominical Plenary 40.        The-Duke Otto Plenary 41,42, Two Head-reliquaries 43-*53. Elevon Arm-reliquaries -54-64 ),66-72 JYarious Ciborla,  etc. 65.        The St.. Bernward Paten Reliquary 78-78. Seven Pendent Reliquaries 79-03. Miscellaneous items527N.B.  - The  (16)  items unpriced are valued altogether at less than  2,000.7 10 2 41 10 30 20 15 10 40 20 100 10100 20 1 3 4130 10 10 25 1 1220 10 1

</content>
</cab>
