<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 201-204</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
 This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Goverrimerct ]Printed for the Cabinet.   June 1928.SECRET. Copy No.    28CP. 207 (28).CABINET.Colonial Military Contributions.BERMUDA AND JAMAICA.Memorandum by the Secretary op State for the Colonies.IN accordance with the Cabinet decision of the 7th December, 1927,1 circulate a Memorandum reporting the progress of negotiations with Bermuda and Jamaica on the subject of certain recommendations of the report of a Cabinet Committee on Military Contributions of Colonial and other Governments (CP. 298 (27)).1. On the 7th December, 1927, the Cabinet agreed to approve the following recommendations of the Cabinet Committee on Military Contributions of Colonial and other Governments : (a.) That the Government of Bermuda should be invited to make a military contribution of , 12,500 per annum towards the cost of its garrison, this contribution being additional to the  3,450 per annum now paid by the Colony as a war contribution.(&amp;.) That the Government of Jamaica should be invited to make a contribution towards the cost of the garrison of  25,000 per annum, this contribution being additional to the annual amounts of  60,000 (war contribution) and about  14,000 (cost of local forces) at present paid by the Colony.2. Draft despatches were accordingly prepared and sent to the Governors concerned under cover of semi-official letters asking them for their views as to the probable reception of these proposals in the Colonies and whether they could suggest any amendments in the draft despatches which would help to make the proposals more acceptable. Copies of the replies to these letters are annexed, from which it will be seen that there is not the slightest prospect of obtaining an increased military contribution from either Bermuda or Jamaica.3. In Bermuda, where there is a wholly elected assembly, possessing complete financial and legislative control, the Secretary of State has no power to carry this or any other proposal against the wishes of the local legislature. In Jamaica it would only be possible to overrule the votes of nine out of the fourteen elected members if the Governor were to declare his opinion that the measure in question was of paramount importance in the public interest. Not only is it obvious that the provision of  25,000 a year by Jamaica towards the cost of the Imperial garrison is not a measure which can be described as of paramount importance in the public interest, but the Governor has virtually declared it to be his opinion that it is of paramount importance in the public interest that the demand should not be made. To order him to exercise his overriding power contrary to his advice, his convictions and the clear spirit, if not the letter, of the organic law of the Colony, would be to strain the prerogative of the Crown to a point bordering on the unconstitutional and would with some reason expose the Imperial Government to the charge of reviving the policy which, on a precisely similar point, in very [17868]
similar circumstances, but with a much stronger legal and constitutional case, led to the loss of the American Colonies. It would also be contrary to settled practice and policy to use the reserve power conferred by the Jamaica or - any similar constitution to impose new charges on Colonial taxpayers for the benefit of the Imperial Treasury.4. As it is practically certain that neither Colony will agree to these proposals and that the only result of asking them to do so in official despatches to be laid before their legislatures would be to create a bad political atmosphere and greatly add to the difficulty of the relations of the Colonial Governments with the unofficial elements in both legislatures, I trust that the Cabinet will agree to proceed no further with the matter.Li. S. A.Colonial Office, Downing Street, June 28, 1928.&apos;    Government House, Bermuda, ............ March 26, 1928.I HAYE given close consideration to the proposal covered by your letter of the 5th March, that Bermuda should pay an increased military contribution towards the cost of Imperial garrison here.It is perhaps unnecessary to say that I entirely concur in &quot;the propriety of calling upon this, among other Colonies, to share in the cost of the mobile forces of the Empire which are available for our defence if attacked. I fear, however, that the time is not opportune for approaching the Legislature on the subject. The House of Assembly&apos;s term comes to an end at the conclusion of the present Session. There will be no available surplus from which a contribution could be paid, and,,,as you will appreciate, it would be asking too much of the members to impose fresh taxation on their constituents immediately before seeking re-election at their hands.There appears to be some misapprehension in the Colonial Office regarding the financial status of Bermuda and the present military expenditure in the Colony. As is shown in my despatch of the 24th December, the ordinary revenue will be some  5,700 less than the expenditure for the present year. We have practically exhausted our reserves and have used up various nest eggs in the past few years, and there is no source of revenue other than that of taxation by which any additional monies can be raised. The actual local expenditure for military services for the past five years has been on an average . 6,626 a year. The operation of the Imperial Defence Contributions Act will bring this to some  9,700 for the present year. If, as is suggested, a further contribution of  12,500 is made, it would bring the total to over  22,200, or more than  1 per head of the resident population of the country as recorded by the last census. This seems high, although possibly not beyond the capacity of the Colony if prosperous seasons continue.With respect to what is due from Bermuda relative to the expenditure from Army Funds, am I not right in saying that the estimate of cost given in youi&apos; draft is too high ? I gather from the Army estimates that the total expenditure is nearer- 100,000 than  170,000. There have been some reductions since these were drawn up when the total was given as  120,700.The reception of fresh proposals for a contribution by the Colony will be affected by the action taken last year in response to your despatch of July 1926. The question was fully considered by a Committee of the blouse of Assembly and the principle of the duty of the Colony towards the Empire was established in the Defence Contributions Act. This, as you are aware, provided not only for a payment in respect to the numbers of the garrison but also for an expenditure i proportion to the ^population of the Colony. Members of the House of Assembl] at least believed that they were acting with reasonable generosity. As there has been no acknowledgment of the action of the Legislature and concurrently there has been a material reduction, in the Imperial Forces stationed in Bermuda, the atmosphere can scarcely be said.to be favourable for approaching the Colony again so soon for an increased military contribution. There would, however, probably be a good chance of success next year in suggesting that we take a share ii
............ - King&apos;s House, Jamaica, March 29, 1928.I can make no suggestions in regard to the draft despatch which you sent me in your letter of the 5th March except to beg most earnestly that it may not be sent.Two years ago it might have been just possible to get a contribution in return for the retention of-the West India Regiment, but now it is simply out of the question. i do not believe that a single elected member would vote for it, as it would to a certainty mean the loss of his seat at the next election, and in any case there would be far more opponents than the nine- whose veto is conclusive.I assume that you would not wish me to declare it a matter of paramount importance so as to pass it over the heads of the elected members ? If I am told to do so, of course I must; but I warn you that that would mean that my period of usefulness here was over. I can lead these people to a certain extent, but I cannot drive them, and I do not believe that anybody could.Moreover, their next action would be to refuse to vote funds for the Local Forces (some of them&apos; already object to the increased expenditure) and the Customs allowances to the troops, and, if these also were declared matters of paramount importance, there would be a series of rows which would destroy all possibility of good government here.There is, I repeat, no possibility of getting the vote approved except by forcing it through, and therefore there is nothing to be gained by putting forward the proposal, especially as the proposal itself would cause very serious trouble. It would at once he seized upon by the Garveyites. Garvey. has now officially stated his intention of being a candidate for the Council at the next election and trying to put his men into the other thirteen seats. He will appeal to the lowest classes of negro voters, and this proposal would be a Heaven-sent weapon in his knds. &quot; Here are the whites trying to exploit the black race again. They disbanded our regiment because it was black and they were afraid of letting it be seen that the black man was as good as, or better than, the white. Now we are to pay for the troops who are needed to keep us in a semi-servile state.&quot; We have gone through a long period of depression. Now we are beginning to see a little prosperity, and the white man cannot stand that. He will keep tie black man down by taking his money to pay the white soldiers, who will prevent our making ourselves free.&quot;Claptrap of this sort may not sound very serious to you, but it is dangerous We. The negro voters will swallow it and they will vote for Garvey and his men. A Council with a majority of Garveyites on the elected side perhaps a complete panel of Garveyites would be a public danger. It would mean racial troubles at once and of so serious and fundamental a character that I should not be able to % on the Police or Local Forces to support the Government. This would mean that  the white garrison would have to be increased at a cost of far more than -25,000, even if that were going to be paid.Further, you must not overlook the fact that there is always a section of the Population of a higher status than those to whom Garvey appeals with a bias 111 favour of America. They contrast the position of Jamaica as a British Colony jvith what it would be as an American territory-with a free market in the ^S.A. for our sugar and fruits and protection for our bananas and point to what fbe TJ.S.A. have done for Puerto Rico: and of course it is undeniable that Jamaica %ild be better off pecuniarily under the U.S.A., so that it would be very unwise to.. &quot; anything to strengthen that argument.the cost of naval defence. Although taxation is light, the cost of living is very hioh, but still I do not think that a total payment for defence purposes amounting. ^ 20,000 a year would be too heavy. ,I am quite prepared to pave the ground in the matter if it can be dealt ivifch on broad grounds, but as far as I am able to see at present it will not be possible to get any increased contribution made before 1930, for the reason shown in this letter. : &apos;. Yours sincerely,(Signed) L. J, BOLS.
In short, my considered opinion is that your proposal would seriously endanger the future of the British Empire in the West Indies. Is it worth while to risk this for  25,000 a year, which, as I have already said, you can only get by force ?Even if it were all plain sailing, and the vote could be got amicably, I would) deprecate the proposal.  25,000 means next to nothing to England; it means a very great deal to Jamaica, especially if we had to pay it every year, good or bad,  25,000 would pay interest and sinking fund on a loan of  800,000 or, if you leave out sinking fund, the interest on continuous loans of half a million, and with half a million at my disposal I could equip this country with the hospitals which it needs, or build the roads which would enable it to double its production, or make Kingston into a first-class port.There is a not inconsiderable body of people here who apply this same argument to the  60,000 which we already pay, and are in favour of asking His! Majesty&apos;s Government to relieve us of our undertaking so that the money can be I applied to reproductive works. This feeling is growing. The &quot; Gleaner &quot; had arl article advocating this view not long ago, and it was with some difficulty thai I Lightbody was restrained from bringing the proposal forward in Council. If yon 1 ask for more, I feel fairly certain that this counter-proposal will be made; anil would it not be very difficult for. His Majesty&apos;s Government to refuse and ttj continue to require payment from unwilling donors ? 1I thought you would not mind my consulting Morrison confidentially. Hit took some of the points which I have mentioned, but added another, as follows :-l&quot; It has been such a good thing in the past to regard the Imperial Force 1 in this Island as being entirely outside of local control (save such as you ma I have as Governor-General) that it would be nothing short of a calamity (m depart from this position. Just fancy having to ^submit this vote every yeiB to Council and for the elected members to have a chanee of criticising son I particular Officer who may have given some personal slight, or even for then I to&apos; have an opportunity of discussing the conduct of military matters in till Island. I can almost hear them singing the refrain &apos; As we pay the PipiB we can call the tune,&apos; although  25,000 is a very small proportion tin  250,000.&quot; II had not thought of this, but it is very true. If you knew the difficulty tlulfi I had in preventing the far more amenable people in Hong Kong from makifB offensive comments when the question of the&apos; Military Contribution came up si the Estimates every year, you would appreciate the force of what Morrison said. flj In the interests of Jamaica and of the Empire, I entreat that no more mays I heard of this dangerous proposal. ;Tours sincerely, [(Signed) R. E. STUBBS 1I

</content>
</cab>
