<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 278-299</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
faS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M&amp;JBSTY 1 S GOVERNMENT).COPY NO2 0 might.0 A B I N E T.THg JKTiWAN S ITU AT ION.The accompanying Report of a Sub-Committee of tho Committee of Imperial Defenoa.which was set up in accordance with the decision of the.Cabinet at their meeting on June 20th, 1928 (Cabinet 33 (28), Conclusion 4], is circulated by direction of the Prime Minister for consideration by the Cabinet at. the meeting to be held tomorrow, Wednesday, the 11th instant at 11*30 s0mo    ,(Sgd.) MaPcAo HANKEY Secretary to the Cabinet.Ilhitehall Gardens, S.W.I. July ICth 1928.
SECRET. .     &apos; Copy No;895-B.COMMITTEE  OF. IMPERIAL DEFENCE.THE AKHWAN SITUATION.REPORT  OF  A  SUB-COMMITTEE.2, Whitehall Gardens, S. W. 1, July 10, 1928.(17910)[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.]Printed for the Committee of Imperial Defence.   July 1928.
COMPOSITION AND TERMS OF REFERENCE.IN accordance with the Conclusions taken by the Cabinet at its meeting held on the 20th June, 1928 (Cabinet 33 (28), Conclusion 4), a Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, composed as follows : The Prime Minister (in the. Chair),The Right Hon. Sir Austen Chamberlain, K.G., M.P., Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs,The Right Hon. L. S. Amery, M.P., Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs and the Colonies,The Right Hon. Sir Laming Worthington-Evans, Bt., G.B.E., M.P., Secretary of State for War,The Right Hon. the Earl of Birkenhead, Secretary of State for India,The Right Hon. Sir Samuel Hoare, Bt., G.B.E., C.M.G., M.P., Secretary of State for Air,Field-Marshal Sir George F. Milne, G.C.B., G.C.M.G., D.S.O., Chief of the Imperial General Staff,Marshal of the Royal Air Force Sir H. M. Trenchard, Bt., G.C.B., D.S.O., Chief of the Air Staff,Lieut.-Col. Sir M. P. A. Hankey, G.C.B. (Secretary), Major H. L. Isihay, D.S.O. (Assistant Secretary),was set up to consider (a.) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air, covering a Note by the Air Staff on the subject of frontier posts in the desert area of Iraq south . of the Euphrates (Annexure A&quot;); and . .(b.) A Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, dated the 15th June, 1928, on the Akhwan situation (Annexure B)..      &apos;-if:iP-       i &apos; !       -   - :i -.&apos; - &apos;-&apos;   - i - - ;&apos;;-
REPORT.The Sub-Committee met on the 26th June, 1928. At this meeting they had before them, in addition to the Memoranda which they were instructed to examine, an Interim Report by Sir Gilbert Clayton on the results of his conversations with Idling Ibn Saud. This Report is attached as Enclosure No. 1 to Annexure C. In addition, they had the advantage of the presence of Sir Gilbert Clayton and of Air Vice-Marshal Sir Edward Ellington, Air Officer Commanding in Iraq.2.   The record of the Sub-Committee&apos;s discussions is attached as Annexure D.3.   The recommendations of the Sub-Committee are as follows ; (a.) Whatever form of organisation is adopted for the defence and administra-tion of the desert tribes of Iraq, the maintenance of a certain number of desert Posts is essential, not only for purposes of defence, but also in order to restrain the tribes on the Iraq side of the border. Accordingly, we should make no concession of principle on this question.(b.) It should be impressed on Ibn Saud that we regard the right of Iraq to administer its own territory, and to construct posts within it, as essentially a British interest.(c.) On matters of detail, such, for example, as the number of Posts, their distance from the frontier, &amp;c, we should take as conciliatory a line as possible, in so far as this can be done consistently with insistence on the general principle in (b) above. As regards the number of Posts, these should be limited in the first instance to the following : Rutbah, Muhaiwir, Ain Wiza, Shabicha, Salman, Busaiyah.(The first three of the above are required in connection with the Air Route and Pipeline and are beyond the range of controversy.)(4,) We should give Ibn Saud an assurance that we intend to observe Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement, and that our forces will pot cross the common frontier in pursuit of offenders. It should, however, be pointed out to him that, in the case of an organised attack on a township or post- -as opposed to a mere tribal raid-or in the event of a series of raids, with which he proves himself unable or unwilling to deal, we must reserve to ourselves the right to take such action as we think fit.(e.) The Secretary of State for the Colonies should make every effort to effect an Extradition Agreement between the Governments of Iraq and Najd.(/.) Ibn Saud should be informed that it is proposed immediately to consider the reorganisation of the administration of the desert tribes.(g.) The appointment by Ibn Saud and the Government of Iraq of accredited representatives on either side of the frontier should be proposed to Ibn Saud.(h.) Sir Gilbert Clayton should himself return to resume conversations with Ibn Saud, both as an act of courtesy and on account of Sir Gilberfs friendly relations with him.(i.) It might simplify Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s task if Ibn Saud were to be given a present, preferably a personal gift, from the King. Sir Gilbert Clayton should be asked to submit his suggestions in regard to this recommendation.(Signed) STANLEY BALDWIN.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1, J&apos;uly 10, 1928.[17910]
[No. CP. 180 (28).]FRONTIER POSTS IN THE DESERT AREA OF IRAQ SOUTH OF    &apos;THE EUPHRATES.)Memorandum by the Secretary of State for Air.AT their meeting on the 23rd May, 1928 (vide Cabinet 30 (28), Conclusion 7 (b)), the Cabinet directed that the &quot; Air Ministry should examine the whole question of frontier posts with a view to determining which are absolutely essential and which, if any, could be dispensed with.&quot; This action has been taken, and I circulate accordingly herewith, for my colleagues&apos; information, a note by the Air Staff giving the conclusions they have reached after a careful re-examination of the matter in consultation with the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq.-S. H.Air Ministry, June 6, 1928.Note by the Air Staff.1. The area to be controlled for which these desert posts are required extends in length parallel to the Iraq-Najd frontier a distance of some 500 miles, and in depth from the Euphrates varying from 100 to 200 miles. The total area involved is approximately 60,000 square miles. From the point of view of defence, bearing in mind the reduction of the Military forces in Iraq, it is desirable that there should be eight desert posts extending from the Trans Jordan frontier in the west to Koweit in the east. &quot;These posts should be sited as follows : Rutbah. Shabicha.Muhaiwir. Salman.Ain Wiza. Busaiyah.Lussuf. Jarishan.Four already exist, viz., Rutbah, Muhaiwir, Salman and Busaiyah.2. In order to meet Ibn Saud as far as possible, the Air Staff are prepared to abandon the erection of posts at Jarishan land Lussuf, and to accept a total of six. Of these, Rutbah and Ain Wiza are along and immediately south of the line of the Cairo-Baghdad air route, whilst Muhaiwir is some 30 miles north of it, and all three are nearer the Syrian than the Najd frontier. They should, therefore, be of no interest to Ibn Saud. Of the remainder, Busaiyah is the most important, and, for reasons that have been previously explained, its retention is an absolute necessity.The Air Staff consider that between Busaiyah and Rutbah a minimum of two posts at Salman and Shabicha respectively can be made to suffice to enable the small forces available to carry out satisfactorily the duties required of them in this area. Thus, there are only three posts regarding which lbn Saud&apos;s objections must be overcome, viz- : Shabicha.Salman.Busaiyah.3. The Air Staff wish to emphasise that, while they are prepared to agree to this reduction in the number of desert posts from 8 to 6, this is on the assumption that Ibn Saud for his part will take more effective steps than heretofore to restrain his tribes from raiding. Further, they consider that this should be made quite clear to Ibn Saud, and that he should be informed that, if there is a recurrence&apos;of these raids, His Majesty&apos;s Government must necessarily reserve to themselves the right to sanction the erection of any additional posts that may be required to maintain the effective defence of Iraq and reassure the Iraq desert tribes.Air Staff, June 4, 1928.
[No. CP. 187 (28).&apos;]AKHWAN SITUATION.Memorandum by the Secretary of State for the Colonies.AT their meeting of the 23rd May the Cabinet decided that the Air Ministry; should examine the whole question of posts on the Iraq-Najd frontier, with a view to determining which of these posts were absolutely essential and which, if any of them, could be dispensed with. The Cabinet at that meeting accepted the view of the C.I.D. that the maintenance of certain frontier posts in the western desert was essential for the effective defence of Iraq and that it was impossible to give way to Ibn Saud on the principle involved in this question. They wished, however, to be in a position, when making this clear to Ibn Saud, to emphasise how moderate were our demands in this respect considering the extent of frontier affected.I informed the High Commissioner for Iraq of the conclusion reached by the Cabinet and asked him to furnish me with his views by telegraph.   I circulate a copy of his reply (Appendix I).   I understand that a telegram making similar recommendations has been received by the Air Ministry from the Air Officer Commanding, Iraq.   My colleagues will see that the High Commissioner considers that the essential needs of Iraq could, for the present, be met by the retention of four posts only, (other than two posts so remote from the frontier as to be clearly outside the scope of Ibn Saud&apos;s objections). Of these posts one, namely, that at Rutbah, to which, although actually closer to the frontier than the disputed post at Busaiyah, Ibn Saud has hitherto raised no objection, may also be regarded as beyond the range of controversy.  It is a recognised and essential link in our air and road communica-tions with Iraq.   As regards the three remaining posts, it seems probable that Ibn Saud will adhere to his objections, in whatever manner our intentions are communicated to him.     If so, I am against making -any further concession to him in this matter.   The right of the Iraq Government to maintain these posts is clear and incontrovertible, and its abandonment would be attended by most unfortunate results.   Ibn Saud might be temporarily placated, but the interests of Iraq, no less than of His Majesty&apos;s Government, would be seriously prejudiced.   It is common ground, I believe, that in constructing these posts the Iraq Government have done nothing contrary either to the terms or the spirit of their treaty engage-ments to Ibn Saud.   I regard the plea of treaty violation as little more than a pretext.   Ibn Saud&apos;s true motives probably lie deeper.   He may well see in the Iraq posts, and in the increased efficiency of Iraq frontier administration, a check to his own dreams of further territorial expansion.   This view of the case is brought out very clearly in a despatch from Sir H. Dobbs of the 29th March, which I circulate for the information of the Cabinet (Appendix II).   This despatch was written before it was known that Ibn Saud was prepared to meet Sir G. Clayton or that he would succeed in restraining his tribes.    It follows that some of the High Commissioners recommendations go beyond what I could now support or he would himself wish to advocate at the present time.   But the value of the despatch as a general survey of the situation has not been impaired.My conclusions are (1) that no permanent peace &quot;on the frontier would result from surrender to Ibn Saud&apos;s demands; and (2) that the only hope of security lies in the maintenance of a chain of fortified posts as proposed by the High Commissioner and the Air Officer Commanding. I would point out that these posts serve not only to protect Iraq from A khwan encroachment, but that they are indispensable in order to prevent counter-raiding&apos; from Iraq and thus to neutralise a,ny possible tendency on the part of King Feisal to connive at such raiding by Iraq tribes as an instrument of his personal hostility towards Ibn Saud. . .^There is a further consideration of great weight. Apart from other objections, we could not give way to Ibn Saud on the point of principle without tying our hands
in the matter of the proposed trans-desert pipe-line, which will undoubtedly require a number of small fortified posts to protect its pumping stations. If we are not free to erect such posts in Iraq territory, as and when required, the whole project, for a trans-desert pipe-line and railway-with its immense strategic and economic potentialities for the future may be stultified at the outset. Ibn Saud is of course free to do what he pleases in his own territory; but he cannot be allowed to establish claims beyond his own borders which may fatally hamper a great Imperial enterprise. That would be far too heavy a price to pay for his temporary appeasement.In the circumstances I am not prepared to recommend, any concession of principle; but I am anxious to take as conciliatory a line as possible in matters of detail. I agree that the number of posts should be reduced to a minimum, but I consider that the present recommendations of the High Commissioner represent the furthest that we can safely go in this direction. It is indeed very doubtful whether even these recommendations will prove acceptable to the Iraq Government, or that if they did they would be passed through the Iraq Parliament.On the point of procedure, the question will arise whether our decision should be communicated to Ibn Saud in writing or whether the suspended conversations should be resumed. This is a matter that can be. discussed orally with Sir Gilbert Clayton, who has now returned to this country, and is preparing a report on his mission to Jeddah.   I shall hope to raise the point again at a later stage.L. S. A.Colonial Office, Downing Street, June 15, 1928.Appendix I to Annexure B.Paraphrase Telegram, from, the High Commissioner for Iraq to the Secretary of State for the Colonies.-Dated 28th May, 1928.(Received Colonial Office 1-58 p.m. 28th May, 1928.)No. BOO. Reference your telegram No. 232 of 25th May, Air Officer Com-manding is away on distant tour, but I have been in consultation with him by telegram. We think that for general defence and administrative purposes Iraq could manage with Rutbah, Shabicha, Salman and Busaiyah, all of which except Shabicha already exist. The above does not take into consideration the existing (\ post) at Muhaiwir and proposed post at Ain Wiza, which are so near the Euphrates edge of the desert that it is improbable that they would fall within the scope of the objections made by Ibn Saud.With regard to Shabicha, we are of the opinion that post there is essential, partly because of the landing ground and the excellence of the water supply, and partly because it is the principal grazing centre of Dahamshah tribe, whose defection to Ibn Saud would so weaken Anazeh as to. cause the whole desert to be exposed to Akhwan propaganda. According to most recent surveys, Shabicha is 33 miles from the frontier.We must also consider, in addition to general defence, particular defence of trans-desert railway and pipeline to Haifa. In this connection, please see report by Major Holt of February 1922. I understand that alignment suggested in that report is confirmed by later enquiries. It is almost certain that it will be necessary to construct defensive enclosures and to post police at all stations on the railway and &apos;&apos; Boosting Stations &apos;&apos; on the pipeline. I understand that the latter have to be built at intervals of about 1 to every 50 miles. It is impossible to tell where these stations would be situated, but alignment west of Rutbah gradually approaches Najd frontier,, and, within Trans-Jordan Corridor, runs within 20 miles of it. The best course would probably be to make an arrangement with Ibn Saud that such defensive enclosures should not be regarded as forts. In any case, if seems important to open the question with him now to prevent subsequent charges of breach of faith.I must observe, on the general question, that consent of Iraq Government to-abstention from building forts within 25 miles of the frontier, pr, alternatively^ from building forts on specified wells near the frontier, was based on the necessity of arriving at some agreed interpretation of Article 3 of Uqair protocol.   The suggestion
now advanced, however, virtually amounts to a new condition which cannot be held to be treaty obligation, and which Iraq Government have never hitherto cOntem-plated, viz., that their right to construct forts over the whole of the desert area not in the vicinity of the frontier is limited and subject to consideration of Ibn Saud&apos;s wishes. I anticipate that there would be serious difficulty in obtaining consent of Iraq Government to any such new arrangement.Appendix II to Annexure B.-(Secret.)-Sir, Baghdad, March 29, 1928.1 HAVE the honour to forward two important and interesting memoranda, the first, dated the 17th March, 1928, from Captain Glubb, Administrative Inspector on special duty with the desert tribes of Iraq,* and the second, dated the 22nd March, 1928, from Mr. Cornwallis, Adviser to the Ministry of the Interior, both being on the subject Of the situation in Najd. t2. Where even the Arabs are in doubt, I can but add my conjectures to the rest. No one has ever supposed that Ibn Sa&apos;ud moves from any other motive than ah enlightened self-interest, nor has anyone denied his great ambition. We are chiefly concerned to discover, first, how far his tribes in raiding Iraq have acted with his connivance &quot;or at his instigation - secondly, if they have so acted, how he can be made to restrain them ; or, thirdly, if they are out of his control, whether it is probable that his control will be restored by any measures which we can take and will then be used to prevent further raiding;3. In examining the question of Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s connivance, the main point for discussion is whether the Akhwan Bedouin tribes have the power to rebel against him for any long time. This appears.to me doubtful, in spite of Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s recent statements that his tribes are Out of his control. All travellers in Central Arabia agree that the Bedouin cannot live without constant resort to the cities for supplies, and Ibn Sa&apos;nd, though he has no large standing army, yet has a strong enough force recruited from the cities and from the settled inhabitants of the oases to deny supplies to the Bedouin. They must, therefore, in the end do his bidding, and it is unlikely that they can have really defied him. If this reasoning is correct, one must ask why he should allow them to raid Iraq. I believe his reasons to be his hatred and suspicion of King Faisal, his desire to absorb the Iraq&apos; Trans-Jordanian corridor to the Mediterranean, and his determination that his influence shall be paramount, at least Over the whole desert up to the borders of the Euphrates.4. I need not dwell upon Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s attitude towards King Faisal and the Hashimite House. His statement recorded on page 40 of Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s Report on the Bahra and Hadda Agreements sufficiently reveals this; &quot;He had Faisal on one side and Abdullah on the other, both new creations, fencing him in on either side and both hostile towards him. When he thought of the injustices to himself, he Was surprised at the moderation of his demands.&quot; King Faisal and the Anlir Abdullah, of course, reciprocate his feelings-.5. Touching the corridor between Iraq and Trang-Jordania, the record Of recent discussions is equally instructive. In my telegram No. 39; dated the .15th January, 1924; I reported that Ibn Sa&apos;ud had told Dr. Holmes that his desire Avas to make the territories of Najd and Syria meet, so as to cut off Iraq from the Mediterranean and impose his Own terms Upon anyone wishing to build a pipe-line or railway across the desert. This desire became more apparent during Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;3 discussions in the autumn, of 1925 With Sir Gilbert Clayton; who on page 5 of his report &quot;states : &apos;&apos; He also Objected vehemently to the northern frontier being so drawn as to unite Trans- J Of dan and Iraq and thus separate Najd from Syria. . ... He maintained that the-territories of which he was nOw master had always marched with those of Syria, and that, in view of this historical fact and of the long-established* No. G./1710.t No. G./S.A. 174.
traffic between Damascus and Central Arabia, he could not see his way to accepting, any kind of barrier between his dominions and the Syrian border.&quot; Ibn Sa ud had to yield at the time, but it is natural that his ambitions should persist, and the discovery of a great oilfield in Iraq, bringing with it the prospect of the early con-struction of a pipe-line and railway, has almost certainly inflamed them afresh.6. Of Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s desire for paramountcy over the whole desert there can be-no doubt. The conversations which preceded the Treaty of Muhammerah and the Uqair Protocol furnished proof of it (vide telegram from Sir. Percy Cox, No. 214, dated the 16th March, 1922, and Confidential despatch, dated the 3rd June, 1922), and his theory is baldly stated in his letter to His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Consul at Jeddah, dated the 7th February, 1928, as follows : &quot;After Faisals arrival in Iraq the treaty of El Muhammerah was forwarded to us and we refused it, believing that the Iraq people had no frontiers behind Esh Shatt (the Euphrates); but that all the Arabs behind Esh Shatt, the Dhafir and Anaizah, &amp;c, have always been in submission to the Governor of Najd. The people of Iraq used to pay Khawa (tribute) to Najd for crossing such frontiers both in the days of our forefathers, of Ibn Rashid and in our days. .... &amp; Although unsatisfied, we accepted the frontiers on condition that drinking from the water should be free and that building over the wells and neighbouring places should be prohibited.&quot;Further, a report, dated the 13th March, 1928, by Major R. H. L. Fink, of the Iraq Army, stationed at Samawah on the Euphrates, contains the following passage : &quot;A man of the Shammar, recently arrived from Najd territory, had heard that about a fortnight ago Ibn Sa&apos;ud had issued orders to Sheikhs in northern Najd territory to collect all available men for a raid against Iraq. .... Ibn Sa&apos;ud is stated to have said in his orders that the boundary of Iraq was the railway and the Euphrates and that all territory, south and westward of that was Najd territory. Posts erected in this zone constituted a direct infringement of the authority of the Akhwan. It was necessary to attack Iraq as early as possible before fortified posts, which it would be extremely difficult to capture, could be established, and that tribes camping in the area must pay taxes to&apos; Najd; otherwise they would be treated as unbelievers and exterminated.&quot;Although, the tale of the actual proclamation of a jihad by Ibn Sa&apos;ud is discredited, this rumour of his renewed claim to the whole area west of the Euphrates, coinciding as it does with the restatement of that claim in his letter of the 7th February, is significant. In truth, constant religious propaganda, expansion and penetration form the very foundations of Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s power, and there have been signs that he had hoped gradually to convert to the Akhwan faith all the Iraq desert tribes, the Dhafir, the Shawiyah (or, mixed shepherd tribes) and the Anaizah, and later, after he had extended his religious sway to the fringes of the desert, to await a time when British interest in Iraq should slacken and then make a spring upon the Euphrates and the Shi&apos;ah sacred cities. Hine illm laprimm, and hence his fury at the construction of police posts in the desert designed to serve as centres for the collection of information, for the consolidation of Iraq influence over the tribes and for an effective display of administration. It is, if persisted in, a complete checkmate to his plans, and if His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government were to approve the suggestions made in some quarters that -the posts already constructed should be destroyed and that no more should be built, Ibn Sa&apos;ud would have gained his end. On this view I cannot now doubt that Ibn Sa&apos;ud did at least connive in the attack on the Busaiyah Post, and I believe that Captain Glubb&apos;s theory of &quot; unauthorised raids &apos;&apos; is substantiated.7. We have next to enquire how best to induce or force Ibn Sa&apos;ud to change his present policy, restrain his tribesmen from raiding and refrain from tempting Iraq tribesmen into his camp. It is plain that Concessions to his ambitions, promises not to build posts at places other than those in close proximity to the frontier; or not to send British or Iraq officials or aeroplanes or armoured cars into the desert would merely promote his plans and deprive Iraq of all chance of counteracting them. They might buy a short quiescence, but that is all. Mr. Cornwallis and Captain Glubb (in his report and in a later telegram) advocate the destruction of certain* Italics are mine.
wells in Najd territory which supply advancing raiders and the bombing of Jarya and Artawiyah, two permanent centres of the Mutair tribe, which has hitherto been the most active of the Akhwah tribes against Iraq.   I had myself, in my telegram No. 93, dated the 17th February, 1928, suggested that warnings should be dropped on Artawiyah for the purpose of frightening the Mutair tribe; but in your telegram No. 82, dated the 22nd February, 1928, you objected to this proposal and directed that a message should be sent to Ibn Sa ud (which was finally despatched on the 25th February) informing him that on receipt of his assurance that he was taking effective measures to prevent further raids on Kuwait and Iraq territories and to punish Faisal ibn Dawish and to obtain reparation, His Majesty&apos;s Government were prepared to suspend all air action in Najd otherwise than in hot pursuit of raiding-parties.   This message must have reached Ibn Sa&apos;ud about the 3rd March, and his letter, dated the 8th March, which has been summarised in the telegram from the Resident, Bushire, No. 47/T, dated the 17th March, was his reply.   In that letter Ibn Sa&apos;ud gives no assurance such as is requested, and His Britannic Majesty&apos;s-Government are consequently at liberty to continue the flights of aeroplanes over Najd territory (which are, in fact, being continued), and to pursue the former policy of punishing the Mutair in Najd territory for the atrocities in Iraq which they have already committed.   I still think that this should be done (although I do not advise the destruction of wells), and I do not believe that it would prejudice Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s mission, since Ibn Sa&apos;ud now himself pretends that the Mutair are quite out of his control, and it is evident that they must be controlled and punished by someone, if they are not shortly to revive and raid again at a season more inconvenient for our defence forces.   I should be grateful if you would acquaint me by telegram with your views upon this point.8. But, as the Resident in the Persian Gulf has always maintained, the main problem is that of Ibn Sa&apos;ud himself. I see no prospect of his abating his ambitions and no profit in trying to buy him off. Nor is there any reason why there should be-any simple solution to our difficulties. The price of security is constant vigilance; and, just as we have countered in India the desire of the Amir of Afghanistan to penetrate and win over the Pathan tribes by the occupation of Waziristan and by a . firm attitude towards him, so must we counter the similar desire on the part of&quot; Ibn Sa&apos;ud by the effective occupation of the desert and by a similarly firm attitude. I attach a sketch of a Desert Defence Organisation drawn up by Air ViceMarshal Sir Edward Ellington, which is now before the Iraq Government. The principal feature of this scheme, which 1 endorse, is the maintenance Of eight posts, stretching right across the &quot;Iraq Trans-Jordan Corridor&quot; from the Kuwait to the Syrian boundary. The maintenance and occupation of these posts would hearten the Iraq tribes, minimize the danger of raids and prevent the spread of Akhwan propaganda. Ibn Sa&apos;ud would certainly dislike it intensely, quite as much as the Amir of Afghanistan disliked the occupation of Waziristan (a dislike which prolonged my negotiations in Kabul in 1921 for the space of eleven months); but we need not yield to his dislike, and, if he threatens us with the hostility either of his tribes or himself, we have in our hands, as I have often represented, the far more effective threat of a blockade of his ports. That this would be effective I am convinced by my experience as Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Autumn of 1919. It will be remembered that the Government of India were at that time restricting the export of foodstuffs owing to famine conditions in India, and I received, through the Resident in the Persian Gulf, the most violent protests from ibn  Sa&apos;ud against such restrictions, and messages imploring that they should be relaxed, on the grounds (endorsed by all British authorities acquainted with the facts) that his people could not exist for more than a month or two without supplies from India.9. My conclusions are that Ibn Sa&apos;ud probably connived at the attack by Dawish on the Busaiyah post, and that Captain Glubb&apos;s theory about &quot;unauthorised raids&quot; is probably correct. I recommend that, as an ad interim deterrent to the Mutair, aeroplanes should drop warnings on Artawiyah, and should subsequently bomb Artawiyah, if there are signs of a revival of Mutair raids; that Sir Edward Ellington&apos;s plan of desert posts should be adopted, and Ibn Sa&apos;ud informed of our intention to carry it out, and that, if he cannot be brought to acquiesce in our policy for securing to Iraq the control of her desert tribes, he should be warned that we may be compelled to have recourse to a maritime blockade. It would, of course, be wise to make all possible minor concessions (such as an undertaking not to construct posts over specified wells within a reasonable distance of the frontier) for the purpose of saving; his face.[17910] . . c
10. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Government of India, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the High Commissioners for Egypt and Palestine and His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Consul at Jeddah.I have, &amp;c.. (Signed) H. DOBBS,High Commissioner for Iraq.&quot;The Right Hon&apos;ble L. C. M. S. Amery, P.C., M.P., Secretary of State for the Colonies,Downing Street, London, S.W. 1.Enclosure to Appendix II to Annexure B. Desert Defence Organisation.THE object of this scheme is to provide an organisation which can (a.) Assist in the defence against Akhwan of the tribes when grazing in the desert.(b.) Control the tribes by moving from exposed areas when Iraq is threatened with raids by Akhwan. (c.) Obtain intelligence and information of the approach of raiders. (d.) Police duties.2. The area of the defence should include all the desert area of the Dulaim, south of the Euphrates, Kerbala, Diwaniyah, Nasiriyah and Basrah Liwas and should be formed into a separate province.3. A line of posts should be constructed behind which the tribes should be withdrawn when a raid is imminent. This line should be Jarishan, Busaiyah, Salman, Shabicha, Lussuf, Ain Wiza, Muhaiwar, Rutbah. Approximately eight posts will be required, and a landing ground in the vicinity of the post is essential.4. Each post should be capable of its own defence, and should include a W/T set and operators.   It would serve the following uses: (a.) A centre for collecting and transmission of information. (&amp;.) Storage of petrol.(c.) Protection of the crews of aircraft during the night. (d.) A home for the desert camel and car patrols.(e.) Deny the wells at which the posts are situated to raiders and thus restrict their watering facilities.5.   The garrison should consist of    -(a.) Twenty camel men. (b.) Twenty footmen. (c.) Two light-armed cars. (d.) Two W/T operators.6. A reserve of mounted men should be formed and be divided into two bodies, located at Shaibah and Ur. Approximate strength should be 408 cars at each place. The garrisons of the posts should be relieved periodically from, the reserve.7. The forces should be recruited from men accustomed to the desert. They should all be able to ride camels, and should bring with them their own camels. I should like to see this raised on thessilladar system, except, of course, the car crews and W/T operators.8. The tribal Sheikhs, such as Mahrut and Ajil, should be required, as a condition of their allowances, to produce, when required, a minimum number of tribal levies to supplement the camel corps in repelling a raid.9. The employment of these forces would be as follows : The posts would send out camel men daily to visit the tribes grazing within the area of the post, and would post videttes which should remain out at night in periods of alarm. The cars would assist in the work of the camel men and push the reconnaissances as far as possible during daylight. When information was received that a raid was likely, the reserves could be moved to such places as seemed most suitable for meeting the raiders. The armoured cars of the Royal Air Force and later of the Iraq Army will be available as well, and if the area of the raid cannot be foreseen, the reserves will be moved to that part of the desert least favourable for the employment of cars and the cars to the parts wh^re they can best be manoeuvred.   The Tribal Levy will be called out.
[Paper No. I.A.S. 2/JCopy of a Letter from Sir Gilbert Clayton to the Under-Secretary of State, Colonial Office, covering- an Interim Report on the Results of his Conversations with King Ibn Sa&apos;ud, and Copies of Letters exchanged.Colonial Office, Downing Street, Sir, June 18, 1928.I HAVE the honour to refer to Colonial Office letter No. 59092/28 of the 17th April, 1928, relating to the negotiation of a settlement of outstanding questions with His Majesty King Ibn Sa&apos;ud, and to submit the enclosed memorandum,* which is in the nature of an interim report on the results of my conversations at Jedda with King Ibn Sa&apos;ud. My final report is in course of preparation and will be submitted in due course.2. I also enclose copiest of the letters I exchanged with His Majesty, in which the suspension of our negotiations and the conditions of the modus vivendi to be observed during the period of suspension were formally recorded.;  I have, &amp;c. (Signed) GILBERT CLAYTON,His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Commissioner and Plenipotentiary.Enclosure No. 1 to Annexure C. Mission to the King of the Hejaz and Najd (1928). Memorandum.THE object of the present memorandum is to report very briefly the tenor of my conversations with Ibn Sa&apos;ud, and to present a short analysis of the issues at stake as they appear in the light of those conversations. A fuller exposition of the conduct and progress of the negotiations on the main and subsidiary questions discussed at the Jeddah Conference will follow in due- course, in the formal report which will shortly be submitted. I shall confine myself here to an analysis of the main question, namely, that of the desert posts.2. It will be remembered that the immediate cause of the present dispute was the construction by the Iraq Government of a post at Busaiyah, which is a water-point in the desert, at a distance of some 80 miles from the Iraq-Najd frontier. On various grounds Ibn Sa&apos;ud objected to the construction of that post, and in support of his objection invoked Article 3 of the first Protocol of Uqair, which reads as follows : &quot; The two Governments mutually agree not to use the watering-places and ,&quot;, wells situated in the vicinity of the border for any military purpose, such as building forts on them, and not to concentrate troops in their vicinity.&quot;The Iraq Government, on the other hand, rejected Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s contention, and held that the above clause could not by any reasonable interpretation be regarded as applying to Busaiyah.3. In order fully to appreciate Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s attitude on this point, it will be necessary to relate his version of the circumstances in which the first Protocol of Uqair was drawn up. This protocol was signed at Uqair on the 2nd December, 1922, as an appendix to the Muhammerah Convention of May 1922, in which provision was made for the fixing of a frontier between Iraq and Najd. Ibn Sa&apos;ud alleges that his delegate at Muhammerah had signed the Convention in error; that he (Ibn Sa&apos;ud) had steadfastly refused to ratify it, on the ground that a hard-and-fast frontier in mid-desert would be contrary to all the established usages of nomadic life; that he had repeatedly pointed out at the time that such a frontier, with its inevitable corollaries in the form of posts and fortifications in the open desert, would be repugnant to his tribes; and that he had finally given his assent only when* See Enclosure No. 1. f See Enclosures Nos. 2 and 3.[17910] d
Sir Percy Cox had offered six months later at Uqair to insert a clause containing such guarantees as would meet his essential objections. Thus it was, according to Ibn Saud, that Article 3 of the Protocol,of Uqair came into being. He maintains that it was only because of his firm belief that that article was intended to prevent the erection of posts anywhere in the open desert on either side of the border that he consented to accept the frontier and ratify the Convention.4. I am unable to tell with any certainty to what extent Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s version tallies with the facts. His account of what had taken place at Uqair was detailed and circumstantial, and left me with the impression that he may have genuinely understood the provisions of Article 3 to entail a wider application than is warranted by. the text. On the other hand, it may be that his version is only in part correct, and that, being made wise by recent events on the frontier, he has amplified it in an endeavour to strengthen his case before His Majesty&apos;s Government and his position towards his own people. However that may be, the fact remains that I was unable to effect any change in Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s attitude in the matter of the posts.5. I took the line that His Majesty&apos;s Government did not accept, and could not admit, his interpretation of Article 3 of the Uqair Protocol; that they regarded the distance of Busaiyah from the frontier to be such that it could not reasonably be held to lie &quot; in the vicinity of the frontier &quot;; and that they were bound to uphold the principle that the Iraq Government, as well as the Najd Government, were at liberty to take such administrative measures within their own territory as seemed to them necessary for the better supervision of the desert. Throughout the conversa-tions, I abstained from embarking too far upon a discussion of the merits or demerits of the posts at Busaiyah and elsewhere. I preferred to take my stand on the unassailable ground of a fixed principle, namely, that, in the absence of any specific undertaking to the contrary, the sovereign right of each Government to take such internal measures as it thought necessary was one which His Majesty&apos;s Govern-ment were determined to respect,6. Eventually, I came to the conclusion that not only was Ibn Sa&apos;ud unwilling on grounds of general policy to give way on the question of the posts, but also that he was precluded from doing so by the attitude of his people. I used every means of persuasion and pressure at my disposal, and when these failed I decided to recommend; as an alternative to rupture, that the negotiations be suspended. The advent of the pilgrimage celebrations which were requiring Ibn Sa&apos;ud&apos;s presence at Mecca for over a month made it necessary to bring our conversations to a close in any case. Ibn Sa&apos;ud accepted my suggestion, and he also agreed to a formal exchange of letters, in which a peaceful modus vivendi was laid down between Iraq and Najd for the duration of the period of suspension. He insisted, however, on one stipulation, namely, that in view of the fact that he had to return to Najd by the middle of August and that he was pledged to communicate the result of his negotiations to his people on his return, our conversations would have to be resumed or definitely broken off by that date.7. Before a decision can be reached as to whether or not conversations should be resumed, due consideration should be given to the three points put forward by Ibn Sa&apos;ud as a basis for a settlement. The first relates to the posts themselves. To the last, Ibn Sa&apos;ud maintained that the demolition of the posts at Busaiyah, Salman and Shabicha, and the withdrawal of their garrisons was a sine qua non for the restoration of peace on the&apos;border. He argued that the habits and the mentality of the nomad tribes were such that the erection of a post at a water-point in the desert, even if built for peaceful purposes, was equivalent in their minds to a denial, or at any rate a serious restriction, of access to the water. He gave me to understand in the most friendly but explicit terms that, if the posts were maintained, he would have to decline all responsibility for the maintenance of peace. His tone was never offensive or menacing, but was consistently firm. He kept repeating that it was precisely the question of desert fortifications which had dictated his refusal to ratify the Muhammerah Convention, until Sir Percy Cox had offered him a guarantee against the construction of posts in the desert. He stated on more than one occasion that if doubt were cast on the validity of his interpretation of Article 3 of the Protocol of Uqair, he would beg His Majesty&apos;s Government to search among their records of what took place at the Conference of Uqair, in order to verify the accuracy of his contention. He declared that he, for his part, was prepared to offer his records for inspection.8. The second relates to the incursions into Najd of cars and aeroplanes from Iraq. Ibn Sa&apos;ud contended that the mere crossing of the frontier by forces from Iraq was a breach of his sovereignty as recognised in the Treaty of Jeddah, and a
Enclosure No. 2 to Annexure C:Copy of a Letter from Sir Gilbert Clayton to His Majesty &apos;Abdul-&apos; Aziz ibn &apos;Abdul-Rahman al-Faisal AI Sa&apos;ud, King of the Hejaz and of Najd and its Dependencies.Your Majesty, ..   Jeddah, May 23, 1928.I HAVE the honour to confirm the agreement arrived at verbally between us with regard to the suspension of our conversations, which has been rendered necessary by the advent of the pilgrimage season.I have informed Your Majesty that I am taking advantage of this unavoidable interruption to return to London and acquaint His Majesty&apos;s Government with the progress of our conversations. It is agreed that, until conversations are resumed or broken off, all parties concerned will endeavour to maintain peace and tranquillity on the Naj d-Iraq border; and that the Governments of these two countries will not only abstain.from taking any hostile or offensive action, but will also use their best endeavours to prevent any act on the part of any of their subjects of a nature to cause dissension between the two countries. Further, it is agreed that should tribal attacks or any other untoward incident occur in either country, instant communica-tion is to be established between the two Governments with a view to the taking of such concerted measures as the best interests of peace might dictate.On behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government, I am in a position to assure Your Majesty that His Majesty&apos;s Government will endeavour to the best of their ability to co-operate with the Iraq Government towards the achievement of the object described above, and will expect the Government of Najd likewise to do their utmost to maintain peace between the two countries and security on the border, which it is undoubtedly in the interests of all parties concerned to maintain.Although I am unable to fix a date for the resumption of our negotiations, yet I have noted Your Majesty&apos;s statement concerning the necessity of your returning to Najd at the end of Safar next&apos;(i.e., about the middle of August next) and of regarding that date as the latest limit for the resumption or rupture of our negotiations. I shall, therefore, do my best to acquaint His Majesty&apos;s Government with the realities of your position in detail, and point out to them that it is in the* Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement reads.:&quot; The forces of Iraq and Najd may not cross the common frontier in the pursuit of offenders except with the consent of both Governments,violation of Article 6 of the Bahra Agreements He argued that the action of the cars and aeroplanes had so inflamed his people that even those whom he had detailed to punish the authors of the attack on Busaiyah had turned on him and loudly demanded reprisals. It was then, and only then, that the movement began which led to the concentration of some 60,000 men from all tribes, even the most law-abiding, for a retaliatory attack on Iraq, which only with the greatest trouble he had succeeded in preventing. He demanded an explicit assurance in writing from His Majesty&apos;s Government to the effect that Article 6 included Imperial as well as Iraqi forces.9. The third relates to the question of the surrender of fugitives from justice. Ibn Sa ud declares that discipline cannot be effectively enforced in the open desert so long as culprits are at liberty to cross the frontier and take refuge in an adjoining territory where his forces are precluded (by Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement) from pursuing them. He had always felt, and now more than ever, that it was essential for the proper enforcement of discipline that the Governments of Iraq and Najd should mutually undertake to surrender fugitives from justice, and he pressed that an agreement to that effect should be the condition of any settlement.10; Considerable progress was made in the discussion of other questions affecting Iraq and Trans-Jordan, such as Extradition and, Bon Voisinage agree-ments, the liquidation of past raids, and the appointment of accredited representa-tives. But, in view of the deadlock over the question of the posts, I did not find it possible or desirable to proceed to any final agreement.(Signed) GILBERT CLAYTON.Colonial Office, June 18, 1928.
interests of both parties to bring the negotiations to a conclusion as soon as possible,, especially as the date mentioned above sets a limit to the period during which our present temporary arrangement can take effect.I beg that Your Majesty will be pleased to accept the expression of my highest, respect and consideration.(Signed) GILBERT CLAYTON,His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Commissioner and Plenipotentiary.Enclosure No. 3 to Annexure C.Translation of a Letter from. &apos;Abdul- Aziz ibn &apos;AbdAd-Rahman al-Faisal Al Sa&apos;udto Sir Gilbert Clayton.Kingdom of the Hejaz and of Najd and its Dependencies, Your Excellency, &apos; Zul-Hejja 5, 1346 (May 24, 1928).It is our pleasure to acknowledge the receipt of the 23rd May, 1928 (4th Zul-Hejja, 1346), in which you inform us that, in view of the advent of the pilgrimage season, you desire to proceed to London in order to acquaint your Government with the results of our discussions, subject to your returning at the earliest favourable opportunity in order to resume the negotiations.   .As for the points which were set forth in your letter under reference, we wish to reply as follows. In the first place, we agree to the proposal contained in your letter to the effect that, until conversations are resumed or broken off, all parties concerned will endjeavour to maintain peace and tranquillity on the Najd-Iraq border; and that the Governments of those two countries will not only abstain from taking any hostile or offensive action, but will also use their best endeavours to prevent any act on the part of all those who are subject to them of a nature to cause dissension between the two countries. Further, it is agreed that should tribal attacks, or any other untoward incident occur in either country, communication is to be immediately established between the two Governments with a view to the taking of such concerted measures as the best interests of peace might dictate.Secondly, we wish to inform Your Excellency that, just as you assured us on behalf of His Majesty&apos;s Government that they would endeavour, to the best of their ability, to co-operate with the Iraq Government towards the achievement of the object, described above, so we wish to assure you that our Government of Najd will also do their utmost to maintain peace between the two countries and security on the border.Thirdly, we confirm your statements on the subject of the resumption of negotia-tions and the period during which the present agreement takes effect. The circum-stances of the case require that negotiations be resumed as soon as possible, and that the latest limit for the validity of the present agreement be fixed at the end of Safar next (i.e., about the middle of August next), which is the date on which we are due to return to Najd. ,,We do not wish to miss this opportunity of expressing to Your Excellency our gratification at the good intentions which you displayed towards us during the con-versations. We are confident that, with good intentions prevailing on both sides,, difficulties will easily be solved; and peace and friendship will be ensured and strengthened a consummation which we regard as essential for the two neighbouring; countries.Respects,(Seal) &apos;ABDUL-&apos;AZIZ IBN SA&apos;UD.Annexure D.[I.A.S. 1st Minutes.]Minutes of a Meeting of the Sub-Committee on the Akhwan Situation, held at - 2, Whitehall Gardens,, S.W. 1, on Tuesday, June 26, 1928, at 11-30 a.m.THE PRIME MINISTER invited Sir Gilbert Clayton to give the Sub-Corn-mittee the benefit of his views on the questions at issue.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that the general tenor of his conversations with. Ibn Saud was explained in the Memorandum which had been circulated to the Sub-
Committee (Paper No. I.A.S. 2). Ibn Saud had put forward two main points; and also one of lesser importance as a basis for a settlement. The first point was the question of the Posts; and he had based his objection to these on,Article 3 of the Uqair Protocol, which read as follows : &quot; The two Governments mutually agree not to use the watering-places and wells situated in the vicinity, of the border for any military purpose, such as building forts on them, and not to concentrate troops in their Vicinity.&quot; Ibn Saud had some slight justification for the interpretation which he put on this Article, in that there was a divergence between the Arabic and the English texts.. The literal translation of the Arabic rendering of the words &quot;in the vicinity of &quot; was &quot; on both sides of.&quot;SIR SAMUEL IIOARE intervened to enquire whether that translation was accepted by all Arabic scholars,SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that his authority was Mr. Antonius, whose, native tongue was Arabic, and who, in addition, was an English scholar of some eminence.   .LORD BIRKENHEAD asked whether there was any divergence between the Arabic and English texts of the last three words of Article 3, namely, &quot;in theirvicinity,&quot; .SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that there was no substantial difference in that passage. The general sense of the Arabic words in that context was &quot; in the neighbourhood.&quot; Continuing, he said that he had abstained from discussing the merits or demerits of any specific Posts, but had taken his stand on the general principle that His Majesty&apos;s Government could never give way on the question of the sovereign right of each Government to take such measures as it thought necessary for the maintenance of law and order within its own frontiers. Ibn Saud had, however, held firm on that point. The second point to which Ibn Saud had taken exception was the infringement of his frontier by armoured cars and aeroplanes from Iraq; and he had especially objected to his people being warned away from the frontier. He had admitted that his tribes had been at fault in the first place; and had protested that he had been about to punish them, in accordance with Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement, when the&apos; &quot;violation of his sovereignty &quot; by cars and aeroplanes had put an entirely different complexion on the matter. That action had so inflamed his people that even those who had not been implicated in the attack on Busaiyah Post had demanded reprisals. He (Sir Gilbert Clayton) had countered this by saying that the attack on Busaiyah was in no sense an ordinary Arab raid but an organised attack; and, in those circumstances, His Majesty&apos;s Government had no alternative but to take action. Ibn Saud had, however, refused to admit that argument. It would interest the Committee to know that when he (Sir Gilbert Clayton) had mentioned the Air Route and Pipeline, and had envisaged the possibility that His Majesty&apos;s Government might have to take defensive measures to safeguard their interests, Ibn Saud had brushed his argument aside. He had said that this was a British interest which he would never threaten; as proof of this, he (Sir Gilbert Clayton) instanced Rutbah Post, which had been in existence for some time, and to which Ibn Saud had raised no objection whatsoever. The Posts to which he had taken particular exception, and in regard to which he had said that he could never give way, were the three in the south namely, Shabicha, Salman and Busaiyah. He had added that, if he could not get satisfaction for his tribes on these points, he might no longer be able to control them; and he would have to decline all responsi-bility for the maintenance of peace. Indeed, he had hinted that he himself might be compelled to take their part. How far that was, or was not, the case, it was impossible to say.   It might be bluff or it might not.On every other question Ibn Saud had proved quite reasonable, and he had reiterated his friendly feelings towards Great Britain. He (Sir Gilbert Clayton) had tried, but without success, to convince him that the action of the Iraq Government had been perfectly correct. .In conclusion, Sir Gilbert Clayton said that he was not in a position to criticise the Air Force Memorandum, which was a military matter. But he was not convinced that the desert problem had ever been seriously considered until recently; and this was admitted both by Mr. Cornwallis, Adviser of the Ministry of the Interior, and[17910]   ,     &quot; . &apos; e
Captain Glubb, Administrative Inspector on special duty with the desert tribes of Iraq. , &apos;    l i     , -r \ \ , .- ....SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN asked Sir Gilbert Clayton whether the impression left on him by the conversations was that Ibn Saud sincerely desired our friendship, or whether he was purposely raising difficulties.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that his impression was that, m principle, Ibn Saud was sincerely attached to Great Britain and desirous of our friendship. He was a very able man with a clear perception of which side his bread was buttered, and he had made the maintenance of friendly relations with the British Government a cardinal principle of his policy.  On that point all his people were of the same mind.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN asked Sir Gilbert Clayton for his views, on the following proposition: &quot; Supposing, to take an extreme case, that we gave way to Ibn Saud on the question of Posts, would he be able to control his tribes T&quot;SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that, in his opinion, Ibn Saud would be able to control them from organised attack, but not always from sporadic raiding. It was worthy of note that from the date of the conclusion of the Bahra Agreement until the attack on Busaiyah a period of nearly two years there had been no raiding from Najd into Iraq.  Ibn Saud had laid especial stress on that point.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN then enquired whether it was a fact that the tribes on both sides of the frontier were nomadic and that, at certain periods of the year, the tribes on the Iraq side migrated into Najd, and vice-versa.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that this was only true of those tribes whose grazing areas were in the vicinity of the frontier. There was a clause in the Bahra Agreement which legislated for that. It was to be remembered that Ibn Saud had always objected to the frontier being so drawn as to unite Transjordan and Iraq, and thus separate Najd from Syria, and his reluctance to agree to the frontier eventually laid down in the EDadda Agreement had been based on that objection.SIR SAMUEL HO ARE suggested that the root of the trouble was that Ibn Saud did not want any administration of any sort in the desert.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON agreed up to a point. When, however, one talked of &quot;no administration,&quot; it was to be borne in mind that Ibn Saud had his own methods of administration, which he considered infinitely more suitable to desert con-ditions than our own, and which had proved remarkably successful in the Hejaz. His methods were to concentrate full powers in the local sheikhs and to keep a very firm hand on them.SIR SAMUEL HO ARE suggested that, even if we gave way on the question of Posts, Ibn Saud would not be satisfied. He was out to get rid of all administra-tion of any kind.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that undoubtedly that had been Ibn Saud&apos;s original intention. But he had now realised it was hopeless; and he had given up ail idea of it. &apos; .SIR SAMUEL HOARE, referring to Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s statement that there had been no raids from the signing of the Bahra Agreement until the attack on Busaiyah Post, said that there had been no less than ten raids during the period 1924-26. If there were no administration in the desert, the tribes on the Iraq side of the frontier would go over to Najd to avoid being raided.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that the Bahra Agreement had been signed at the end of 1925; the attack on Busaiyah had taken place in November 1927. Between those dates there had been no raids. This was acknowledged by the High Commissioner.SIR SAMUEL HOARE enquired whether it would make any difference if the Posts were police instead of military.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied that Ibn Saud objected to. Posts of any, kind.
[17910]Referring to the question of the tribes on the Iraq side of the frontier going over to Najd, he thought that this was unlikely. The tribes could scarcely leave their own precarious grazing areas and move into others, in which there was no room. Moreover, it was to be remembered that the tribes were dependent for their necessities of life on Iraq markets. In those circumstances their defection could not be permanent.Mr. AMERY suggested that what was required was an administration which was. general and parallel to the frontier, rather than local and projecting into the desert.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON agreed. The sort of administration he envisaged was similar to that which had been adopted in Egypt, Sinai, &amp;c.Mr. AMERY said that, in the event of an administration of that kind being established, it might be necessary to revise the position of the Posts; but the necessity for Posts would remain as strong as ever.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON agreed. Any other course of action would be a gamble on Ibn Saud&apos;s ability to control his desert tribes. Whatever the form of administration, Posts of some sort would be essential; and he suggested that it should be made quite clear to Ibn Saud that His Majesty&apos;s Government insisted, now and for all time, on the principle that they could brook no interference with what was done on the Iraq side of the frontier. At the same time, we should, if possible, give Ibn Saud something to take back to his tribes, such as a reduction in the number of the Posts, their distance from the frontier, and so on.Mr. AMERY enquired whether it would not ease the difficulty if Ibn Saud were told that this question of Posts was essentially a British interest.SIR HUGH TRENCHARD, referring to Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s statement that our tribes were unlikely to go over to Najd, suggested that the danger lay in the fact not so much that they would go over geographically, but that they would become Najdites and pay tribute to the King of Najd.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said he had no fear on that score. The rock-bottom fact of the matter was that the tribes were dependent on us for their bread and butter. It would always be open to us to counter any defections by closing down supplies.SIR SAMUEL HOARE submitted that the tribes on the Iraq side of the frontier might become Wahabis to avoid being raided. This would be a religious matter, and therefore more difficult to deal with.SIR HUGH TRENCHARD agreed, and added that, if our tribes became hostile to us, there was a danger that they would raid all along the Euphrates Valley, and that we would have to strengthen that frontier.SIR EDWARD ELLINGTON said that Sir Gilbert Clayton had made a point of the fact that, until recently, there had been no administration in the desert. That, in fact, had been the cause of the whole trouble. Tribes from Iraq and Syria had raided into Najd; Ibn Saud had requested us to stop it; and the establishment of the Posts was our response to his request. This ought to be made clear to Ibn Saud. Again, Sir Gilbert Clayton had expressed the view that it was unlikely that our tribes would go over to Najd. In point of fact, all the influential elements of a whole tribe had gone over last year, practically en bloc. It was significant that, now that an administrative organisation was being set up, they were starting to come back.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN asked for an explanation of the organisation.SIR EDWARD ELLINGTON replied that the Posts were equipped with wireless installations, and were thus able to communicate information of projected raids to Headquarters. On receipt of such information, aeroplanes were sent out to reconnoitre. If they confirmed the information, more aeroplanes and armoured cars were despatched to the scene. Were it not for the existence of these Posts, the Air Officer Commanding in Iraq would be obliged to act on rumour, and this would involve additional air squadrons. In reply to a question from Sir Austen Chamberlain, he said that the nearest political Post was Nasiriya about 150 miles from the frontier.- SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN enquired whether there was any political officer in touch with our desert tribes.
SIR EDWARD ELLINGTON replied in the affirmative. Since the trouble had started Captain Glubb had been employed on special duty as Administrative Inspector with the desert tribes. &apos;SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN, referring to Sir Gilbert Clay ton&apos;s suggestion for frontier administration, asked whether it would be necessary to have political officers all along the frontier, and, if so, whether this would necessitate a series of Posts. ./;.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON replied in the affirmative. Posts of some sort would undoubtedly have to be set up, their actual location being decided in the light of experience.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN was informed that the distances of the three Posts under consideration from the frontier were as follows :-Busaiyah. 76 miles from the Iraq-Najd frontier;  56 miles from the neutral zone.Salman. Between 50 and 60 miles from the frontier.Shabicha. (Non-existent at the present time) about 25 miles from the frontier.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN asked Sir Edward Ellington what inter-pretation he placed on the word &apos;&apos; vicinity.&apos;&apos;SIR EDWARD ELLINGTON replied that it was all a question of wells. He thought that our obligations under Article 3 of the Treaty could be considered as discharged, provided that, in the case of every Post, there was a well nearer to the frontier than that over which the Post was established. Continuing, he said that if we were not allowed to have a Desert defence organisation, our frontier would be the railway and the River Euphrates a long and vulnerable line. Moreover, it would be impossible to get reliable information of what was happening in the desert; and they would live in a state of constant alarms. Additional forces, which he estimated at 2 squadrons R.A.F., 2 Companies Armoured Cars, and 4 Battalions, would be required. He pointed out that the desert extended right up to the banks of the Euphrates. He also pointed out that Ibn Saud had, in his second letter, protested against our use of Armoured Cars and aeroplanes in the desert; and had, in fact, put this on all fours with the establishment of Posts.Mr. AMERY thought that a system of general administration parallel to the frontier was probably preferable to the present organisation. If that system were adopted, the establishment of posts would assume added importance. He could not imagine any system of frontier administration which was not based on the control of the main wells. If we abandoned the desert, the only alternative left to us would be a sedentary defence; and this was directly opposed to all our experience of air control. Provided that the Air Force were given elbow-room, security of the whole region near the frontier could be assured. Above all, if it were made quite clear to Ibn Saud that this question of Posts was essentially a British interest, it was quite possible that he would adopt a different attitude. The question really resolved itself into how far we could go in placating Ibn Saud without at the same time injuring those who had put all their fortunes into our hands. It would be placing both the Iraq Government and the High Commissioner in an impossible position if, under our instructions, the responsibility for the control of the desert tribes was withdrawn from them. Ibn Saud appeared to be trying to have it both ways. On the one hand, he denied the existence of any frontier in the desert; on the other hand, when it came to a question of our aeroplanes and armoured cars pursuing raiders, he claimed the existence of an absolute frontier. He suggested that Sir Gilbert Clayton should personally return to resume negotiations, both as an act of courtesy, and because of Sir Gilberfs friendly relations with Ibn Saud; that he should accommodate him in every possible way; but that, as regards the Posts, he should inform him that these were essentially a British interest, and that His Majesty&apos;s Government could not admit the right of anyone to dictate to them in that matter.LORD BIRKENHEAD said that none of the expert witnesses before the Committee differed on the question of the principle at issue. The answer to the problem was therefore conclusive. All that remained was to consider whether there were any points of detail which we could surrender to Ibn Saud without prejudice.
SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN agreed that it was impossible to make concessions as regards the principle involved in the establishment of posts. The difficulty lay in the fact that the text of the Protocol was vague; and there was the additional difficulty that there was a divergence between the Arabic and the English texts. It would be going to the utmost limit that the construction of the English language allowed us, if we read the Article to mean that we were entitled to establish Posts anywhere if only there was another well nearer the frontier than that at which our Post was established. We were on not very strong ground there; but we were on really weak ground as regards the question of pursuit across the frontier, and also on the question of the extradition of fugitives from justice. It appeared imperative to meet Ibn Saud on both these questions, even if we could not meet him as regards the Posts. The Agreement a.s regards the crossing of the frontier in pursuit of offenders was quite explicit; and we had not kept it. We ought now to give a positive assurance that we will not pursue across the frontier, until Ibn Saud has been informed; and that only in the event of his proving unwilling or unable to deal with the offenders, shall we have recourse to such action.With regard to extradition, the proper enforcement of discipline in countries like Najd and Iraq was clearly impracticable if fugitives from justice had merely to cross the frontier. Accordingly, he thought that the Secretary of State for the Colonies should do his utmost to arrange an agreement on this question.To sum up his conclusions were fourfold. First, we must be firm about the Posts. Secondly, we should give Ibn Saud an assurance that Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement applied to Imperial as well as Iraqian forces, and would be strictly observed in the future. Thirdly, we should come to an agreement with Ibn Saud on the question of the extradition of fugitives from justice. Fourthly, we should let Ibn Saud know at once that the High Commissioner is taking up the whole question of frontier administration, and that it is hoped that more efficient arrangements than at present exist will soon be formulated. In addition, perhaps Sir Gilbert Clayton and Sir Edward Ellington would consider whether it would be advisable to suggest to Ibn Saud that he should keep a Political officer on the frontier and that we should do likewise; and that these two officers together should take up, at once and immediately, any frontier incident that might arise in the future.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that the question of accredited representatives had been touched on in the course of an interview which he had arranged between Ibn Saud and Captain Glubb. He (Sir Gilbert Clayton) thought some step of this sort was necessary and that it might eventuate.SIR SAMUEL HO ARE said that he agreed in principle with the conclusions suggested by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. At the same time it was to be remembered that there were practical difficulties. Raids developed at an incredible pace, 70 miles sometimes being covered in the night before a raid is launched; and dealing with Ibn Saud was a very different matter from dealing with a stabilised government. They might get no answer to their representations for weeks or months.SIR EDWARD ELLINGTON suggested that the question resolved itself into this : How long were we going to keep a treaty after Ibn Saud himself had broken it ?SIR HUGH TRENCHARD said that the Air Ministry had been most patient. Ibn Saud&apos;s tribes had brought off four raids before the Foreign Office had been asked for permission for our forces to cross the frontier in pursuit. Continuing, he said that, on behalf of the Air Staff, he was prepared to accept the suggestion of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that, in principle, the forces of Iraq should not cross the common frontier in pursuit of offenders, except with the consent of both Governments. He meant by that acceptance, that, in the event of what may be termed an ordinary tribal raid, there should be no question of our crossing the frontier. If, on the other hand, there were a series of raids which Ibn Saud proved himself either unwilling or unable to check, then our crossing of the frontier would have to be considered. Again, in the event of a really organised raid, for example, an attack on a town such as Basra, the question of our crossing the frontier would certainly have to be considered.THE PRIME MINISTER suggested that the delays in dealing with Ibn Saud might be obviated if we had a representative with him.
SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that we already had a representative at Jeddah, who was in communication with Ibn Saud at Mecca. No time would be saved by our having a representative at Mecca itself, as communication with.him Would take just as long as it does at present.Mr. AMERY suggested that we might give Ibn Saud some wireless sets.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON said that he had, in fact, put up that suggestion, to Ibn Saud, but he had not fallen in with it. Although he had wireless sets at other places, he was very careful not to offend the susceptibilities of the old-fashioned folk in Najd.Mr. AMERY hoped that Sir Gilbert Clayton personally would return tO&apos; continue the negotiations.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON thought this advisable.SIR SAMUEL HOARE thought that it might help Sir Gilbert Clayton if we were to make Ibn Saud a present or presents of some kind on the lines suggested for the King of Afghanistan in the Afghan Committee.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON observed that Ibn Saud was most anxious to repair the Hejaz Railway, but he had no money for this project, nor any means of getting it. The cost would be in the region of  50,000, but  20,000 to  30,000 would enable much to be done. Supposing we let him have the money, there would be a possibility of getting some of it back.SIR HUGH TRENCHARD mentioned that Mr. Philby had made mischief by telling Ibn Saud that we were considering the construction of a railway from Iraq to Akaba. He suggested that Sir Gilbert Clayton should assure Ibn Saud that there: was no such intention.SIR AUSTEN CHAMBERLAIN suggested that Ibn Saud would probably greatly appreciate a personal present from the King.SIR GILBERT CLAYTON believed that the personal message which the King had despatched to him on the death of his father would be a source of particular gratification.Conclusions.The conclusions of the Sub-Committee were as follows : (a.) Whatever form of organisation is adopted for the defence and administra-tion of the desert tribes of Iraq, the maintenance of a certain number of desert Posts is essential, not only for purposes of defence, but also in order to restrain the tribes on the Iraq side of the border. Accordingly, we should make no concession of principle on this question.(&amp;.) It should be impressed on Ibn Saud that we regard the right of Iraq to administer its own territory, and to construct posts within it, as essentially a British interest.(c.) On matters of detail, such, for example, as the number of Posts, their distance from the frontier, &amp;c, we should take as conciliatory a line as possible, in so far as this can be done consistently with insistence on the general principle in (b) above. As regards the number of Posts, these should be limited in the first instance to the following: Rutbah, Muhaiwir, Ain Wiza, Shabicha, Salman, Busaiyah.(The first three of the above are required in connection with the Air Route and Pipeline and are beyond the range of controversy.)id.) We should give Ibn Saud an assurance that we intend to observe Article 6 of the Bahra Agreement, and that our forces will not cross the common frontier in pursuit of offenders. It should, however, be pointed out to him that, in the case of an organised attack on a township as opposed to a mere tribal raid or in the event of a series of raids, with which he proves himself unable or unwilling to deal, we must reserve to ourselves the right to take such action as we think fit.(e.). The Secretary of State for the Colonies should make every effort to effect an Extradition Agreement between the Governments of Iraq and Najd.(/.) Ibn Saud should be informed that it is proposed immediately to consider the reorganisation of the administration of the desert tribes.
(g.) The appointment by Ibn Saud and the Government of Iraq of accredited representatives on either side of the frontier should be proposed to Ibn Saud.(h.) Sir Gilbert Clayton should himself return to resume conversations with Ibn Saud, both as an act of courtesy and on account of Sir Gilberts friendly relations with him.(i.) It might simplify Sir Gilbert Clayton&apos;s task if Ibn Saud were to be given a present, preferably a personal gift, from the King. Sir Gilbert Clayton should he asked to submit his suggestions in regard to this recommendation.2, Whitehall Gardens, S.W.1. June 26, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
