<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 300-308</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
;HIS DOCUMBftfZ IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT).EQRET.P.218 (28).Copy No.C A B I N E T.SLAUGHTER OF ANIMALS (SCOTLAND) BILL.Memorandum by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries,I wish to bring before the Cabinet a question arising out of the Slaughter of Animals (Scotland) Bill, on which the Secretary of State for Scotland and myself are unable to agree.The object of the Bill is to provide for the humane slaughter of animals in Scotland,Clause 1 (2) of the Bill provides in effect that no person shall slaughter an animal in a slaughterhouse or knackerfs yard unless he is the holder of a licence issued by the Local Authority, and Clause 2 (2) provides that the licence shall only be valid in the district of the Local Authority granting it.The Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries is r responsible for questions relating to diseases of animals in Scotland.   It is often necessary for my Department when exercising through its officers the powers and duties under the Diseases of Animals Acts of 1894 to 1927 to slaughter animals in a slaughterhouse or knacker1 s yard, and to employ butchers brought from other districts where the butchers in the district of the Local Authority concerned are either not available or not sufficient to carry out the slaughter quickly.   It may also be necessary in carrying out slaughter under the Diseases of Animals Acts for an officer of the Ministry in an emergency to slaughter animals himself.   When animals are slaughtered under the direct ion,,, of the Ministry of Agriculture humane methods are always employee!I am not, therefore, proposing anything which conflicts with the object of the Bill.
It is essential that the Ministry1s power &quot;t-o.. employ any butchers (or on occasion its own officers), to carry out the slaughter of animals on an infected, place, should remain unimpaired, but the Bill apparently restricts this power and would require any officer of the Ministry or a slaughterer brought from another district (though he may be a licensed slaughterer) specially to obtain a licence from the Local Authority in which the slaughter is to take place,   This formality might take some hours and the restilting delay might be disastrous.I cannot emphasise too strongly the necessity for prompt slaughter in the case of foot and mouth disease.   This disease is the most infectious known and the-whole plan of campaign is based on the necessity for immediate slaughter of affected animals so as to stop at once the production of the dangerous virus of the disease.   It would be intolerable If Inspectors and butchers had to stand by doing nothing until all the formalities of securing the licence from a Local Authority had been completed.   It is like having a fire brigade in front of a burning house ready to act but unable to move because they had not received the necessary authority to put out the fire IClause 4 provides that any constable and any person authorised by a Local Authority may enter any slaughterhouse or knacker&apos;s yard in the district of the Local Authority for the purpose of observing whether the provisions of the Act are complied with.One of the most important provisions in the Orders made by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries under the Diseases of Animals Acts is that which prohibits the entry of any person into an &quot;infected place&quot; unless specially authorised to do so by an Inspector of the Ministry, the object being to limit the number of persons entering an infected place   so as to minimise the risk of the spread of disease.    It is essential that the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries should maintain this power
of control over the entry of persons into Infected places. Clause 4, however, will enable any constable (who it is understood will include in Scotland in certain cases an Inspector of the S.P.C.A.) to enter any slaughterhouse or knacker&apos;s yard, which may be declared an infected place under the Diseases of Animals Acts, and will also enable a Local Authority to authorise any other person to enter such premises, without obtaining any authority from the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries or from any of its officers.     The Ministry&apos;s absolute control over an infected place would, therefore, cease to exist.This is a position which I cannot contemplate with equanimity.     If the local authority can grant to any person the right to enter an infected place without the permission of the Ministry&apos;s Inspector, a vital principle will have been surrendered.   Our complete control will have gone.   There&apos; will be divided responsibility.   One officer will be responsible for suppressing disease and another for ensuring humane methods of slaughter under circumstances where unity of command, prompt action and the minimum movement of human beings are essential.For these reasons I-have suggested an amendment which would exempt from the operation of this Bill the slaughter of animals under the Diseases of Animals Acts and Orders of the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.   I am also prepared to agree to the inclusion in the amendment of a provision to the effect that all animals slaughtered under the Diseases of Animals Acts in Scotland shall be killed by a mechanically-operated instrument of a pattern approved by the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries.As long as I am responsible for diseases of animals in Scotland I must have complete control of the campaign for their suppression.W.  GaMINISTRY OP AGRICULTURE AND FISHERIES. 9th July, 1928.
BILLINTITULEDAn Act to provide for the humane slaughter of a.d. 1928. animals in Scotland.BE it enacted by the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, 5 as follows :- .1 .-(1) JSTo animal, except swine, shall be slaughtered provisions in a slaughter-house or knacker&apos;s yard except in accord- as toance with the provisions of this section. slaughter ofJ- animals, &amp;c.(2) Every such animal shall  be instantaneously10 slaughtered, or shall by stunning be instantaneously rendered insensible to pain until death supervenes, and such slaughtering or stunning shall be effected by a person who is at the time the holder of a licence issued by the local authority under section two of this Act15 by means of  a  mechanically-operated instrument in, proper repair and of a type approved by the local authority.(3) If any person contravenes or fails to comply with or causes or permits any contravention or non-compliance 20 with any of the provisions of this section, or attempts to slaughter an animal in a slaughter-house or knacker&apos;s yard otherwise than in accordance with the said provi-sions, he shall be liable on conviction by a court of summary jurisdiction to a fine not exceeding ten pounds      ______25 or on a second conviction to a fine: not exceeding twenty .
A.D. 1928.  pounds or on a subsequent conviction to imprisonment        for a period not exceeding sixty days or to a fine not exceeding twenty pounds, or to both such imprisonment and fine.Licences. 2. (1) A licence to slaughter or stun animals in 5accordance with the provisions of this Act shall not be granted except to a male person of the age of eighteen years or upwards who is, in the opinion of the local authority, a fit and proper person to hold such a licence. 10(2) A licence under this section shall be valid only in the district of the local authority granting the same, and for a period not exceeding twelve months, and may be renewed from time to time at the discretion of the local &apos;&quot; \;        authority. 15(3) The local authority may suspend a licence at any time for such period as they may determine and, where they are satisfied that the person is no longer a fit and proper person to hold a licence, may revoke the licence. &apos; 20(4) Any person aggrieved by the refusal of the local authority to grant a licence or by the suspension or revocation by the local authority of a licence may appeal to the sheriff against such refusal, suspension, or revoca-tion, within one month of the intimation thereof, and 25 the decision of the sheriff shall be final.(5) A fee, not exceeding five shillings, may be charged by the local authority for each such licence and a fee not exceeding one shilling for every renewal thereof.(6) The provisions of this section shall apply to any 30 licence granted by the local authority for the purpose of the provisions of this Act with regard to the Jewish and Mohammedan methods of slaughter.Employ- 3. Any local  authority which has provided orment of      established a slaughter-house may, if they think fit, 35 slaughter-    employ persons to slaughter or stun animals, in accord-authority    ance &quot;with the provisions of this Act, and may make such charges as they consider reasonable for the ser-vices of the persons so employed.Obstruction        4. Any constable and any person authorised in 40 of officers,    writing by/ a local authority may enter any slaughter-Ac
10house or knaeker&apos;s yard in the district of the local authority at any time when business is, or appears to be in progress, or is usually carried on therein for the purpose of ascertaining whether there is or has been any contra-vention of or non-compliance with the provisions of this Act, and if any person shall refuse to permit any such constable or person to enter any premises which he is entitled to enter under this Act, or shall obstruct or impede him in the exercise of his duties under this Act, he shall be liable on conviction by a court of summary jurisdiction to a fine not exceeding five pounds.A.D. 1928.5.-(1) Section one of this Act shall not apply to Provision as the slaughter of any animal in a slaughter-house in to local the city and royal burgh of Glasgow so long as the Acts-115 provisions of section seventy-two of the Glasgow Cor-poration Order, 1927, as amended by the immediately succeeding subsection of this  section apply to such slaughter.(2) Section seventy-two of the Glasgow Corporation 20 Order, 1927, shall be amended as follows : (a) For the authorisation in writing referred to in subsection (2) there shall be substituted a licence granted by the corporation;(b) In lieu of subsection (4) the provisions of section eight of this Act shall apply with the sub-stitution of a reference to the provisions of the said section seventy-two for any reference, to any provisions of this Act, and of a licence granted by the corporation for a licence granted J30 by the local authority; and(c) The provisions of section two of this Act shall apply to any licence granted by the corporation in like manner as they apply to a licence granted by the local authority.135 (3) Save as provided in the foregoing subsections the provisions of any local Act, so far as inconsistent with this Act, shall cease to have effect.6. Any byelaws made by a local authority under any Revocation Act, so far as inconsistent with any provision of this Act, of incon-140 shall be invalid, but without prejudice to the validity of sistent pro-anything done thereunder before the commencement of this Act.visions.
A.D. 1928. Definitions.Saving for Jewish method of slaughter.Byelaws.7. For the purposes of this Act (a) &quot; Slaughter-house &quot;   &quot; knackers&apos;  yard,&quot;  and&quot; local authority,&quot; have the respective mean-ings assigned to them in the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897;(b) The expression &quot; animal&quot; means any horse,mare, gelding, pony, foal, colt, filly, stallion, ass, donkey, mule, bull, cow, bullock, heifer, calf, steer, ox, sheep, ewe, wether, ram, lamb, pig, boar, hog, sow, goat and kid;10(c) Any expenses incurred by a local authority in the exercise of their powers under this Act shall be defrayed in like manner as the expenses of the local authority are defrayed under the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897 : Provided 15 that in the case of a local authority owning a slaughter-house such expenses may, if such local authority so determine, be defrayed out of the funds from which such slaughter-house is maintained; 20(d) &quot; Constable &quot; includes any constable within the meaning of the Police (Scotland) Act, 1890, and any justice of the peace constable.8. The provisions of section one of this Act shall not apply where an animal is slaughtered for the food 25 of Jews by a Jew duly licensed for the purpose by the Chief Rabbi and holding a licence granted, by the local authority or for the food of Mohammedans by a Mohammedan holding a licence granted by the local authority if such slaughtering is carried out according to 30 the Jewish or the Mohammedan method of slaughter, as the case may be, and no unnecessary suffering is inflicted.9. (1) Byelaws under section two hundred and eighty-one of the Burgh Police (Scotland) Act, 1892, may provide for the prevention of cruelty to animals in 35 knackers&apos; yards, and the local authority of a district, other than a burgh, may make byelaws for the prevention of cruelty to animals in slaughter-houses and knackers&apos; yards, and the provisions of sections one hundred and eighty-three to one hundred and eighty-seven, inclusive, 40 of the Public Health (Scotland) Act, 1897, shall, with the substitution of a Secretary of State for the Scottish
Board of Health, apply to byelaws made by the local A.D. 1928. authority of a district other than a burgh.  (2) The local authority of a burgh to which the Burgh Police (Scotland) Act, 1892, does not apply may 5 make byelaws for the prevention of cruelty to animals in slaughter-houses and knackers&apos; yards, and the provisions of sections three hundred and seventeen to three hundred and twenty-four, inclusive, of the said Act shall apply to such byelaws.10       10. (1) This Act shall apply to Scotland, and may Short title be cited as the Slaughter of Animals (Scotland) Act, and com-1928. mencement.(2) This Act shall come into operation on the first day of January, nineteen hundred and twenty-nine: 15 Provided that section one, in so far as it relates to the slaughter of any sheep, ewe, wether ram or lamb, shall not come into operation until the first day of October, nineteen hundred and twenty-nine.
Slaughter of Animals(Scotland).An Act to provide for the humane slaughter of animals in Scotland.(Brought from the Commons 25th June 1928.)Ordered to be printed 25th June 1928.LONDON:PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY^ stationary OFFICE.To be purchased directly from H.M. Stationery Office at the following addresses: Adastral House, kingsway , London, W.C.2; 120,George Street, Edinburgh; York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew&apos;8Crescent,Cardiff; 15, Donegal! Square West, Belfast; or through any Bookseller.Printed by Eyre and Spottiswoode, Ltd., &quot;-   East Harding Street, E.C. 4, Printers to the King&apos;s most Excellent Majesty.AJB  ILINTITULED[Price 2d. Net.]

</content>
</cab>
