<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 322-323</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
Copy No.IS JDOCTJMEflT IS  THE PROPERTY CF  HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY&apos;S GOVERNMENT) .0 RE T. ^ 225  (28).C A B IN ST.DRAFT TREATY&apos; FOR TJ-E RENUNCIATION OF WAR. AMERICAN PROPOSALS.Memorandum by the Lord President of the &quot;Council *Entirely through my own fault I failed to realise until late last night that we were going to discuss the American proposals to-daye      I venture to dictate in the greatest haste the following brief notes:-(1)    At the very beginning of these discussions I suggested that we ought to accept Kellog&apos;s proposal as a &quot;gentlemen1s agreement&quot;;    and at a recent Cabinet I urged that the phrase &quot;punitive expedition&quot; should be eliminated from our diplomatic vocabulary, and &quot;police measures&quot; substituted for it.     -I -think some of my colleagues thought I was making an indifferent joke,, but it was, In substance at all events, a serious proposal,(2) Our chief difficulty at the present moment Is that the Americans have invented extremely good phrases which express what everybody wants in language, which (a) Is not the language of international law, and  b) which conforms to all our best International instincts.(3)  &quot;Outlawry, of War&quot; is one-.such phrase.    &quot;Repudiating war as an instrument of policy&quot; is another.      They exactly express what we all want.(4)  It is the easiest of all exercises of human Ingenuity to find hard cases to which such phrases are not applicable;    but I cannot Imagine anything more
perilous in certain circumstances than to allow ourselves to be involved either in the discussion of these hard cases or in the attempt to solve them. They are insoluble,(5)    It was for this reason that I sugp;ested that we should at once enthusiastically concur with the American proposals.     We all agree with these princi-ples;    all our Dominions agree with them;    public opinion in this country agrees with, them;    and it may really be a serious misfortune If we are manoeuvred into the position of quarrelling in detail on matters where we are agreed in principle.(6) What we have to do surely is to try&apos;and find a formula which expresses this properly.      The recognised terminology of legal and diplomatic formulae are not really applicable.      I need hardly say that I have no prejudice in favour of siach a phrase as Mgentlemen&apos;s agreement&quot;,&apos;qualified in special cases by such a phrase as &quot;police measures&quot;; but something of the kind is wanted.(Intd.)- A.J.Bo

</content>
</cab>
