<cab>
<spreadsheet_ref>CAB 24/196/0 images: 390-392</spreadsheet_ref>
<content>
This document is the property of His Britannic Majesty&apos;s Government.Printed for the Cabinet, July, 1928.SECRET.OP. 228 (28).THE CABINET.THE USE OF GAS IN  THE  SUPPRESSION OF CIVILDISTURBANCES.MEMORANDUM BY THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR WAR.1. The General Officer Commanding in Egypt has put forward for consideration a proposal for the use of tear gas by British troops for the dispersal of large hostile gatherings should trouble arise in Egypt- As this proposal raises the whole question of the use of gas in the suppression of civil disturbances, and as this is to some extent dependent on the chemical warfare policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government, I have thought it desirable to prepare a paper for the information of my colleagues, dealing with various aspects of this problem.2. The instruments dealing with the prohibition of gas warfare as between nations are : (a) The Hague Convention, still technically binding on the Allied and associated powers and neutrals during the war.(b) Article V of the secoud Washington Treaty of 1922, which has been signed andratified by Great Britain, but which is at present inoperative owing to uon-ratification by the French Government. Ratifications of signatories have not been deposited.(c) The Geneva Gas Protocol of 1925.   This measure prohibits the use of gas&quot; including all analogous liquids, materials or devices &quot;, a phrase which would cover tear gas. The Protocol was signed by 28 States including Great Britain and the United States of America but excluding Russia and Afghanistan. Russia notified its adherence to this Protocol in 1928 (C.I.D. Paper 855-B), but it has not been ratified by Great Britain, and on 18th October, 1926, the Cabinet decided &quot; to adopt a neutral attitude until other Powers have signified their intention, and to ratify only if other Powers do so.&quot;It should be noted that all the above agreements are international, and that no under-taking has been made by anyone to abstain from the employment of chemical methods in civil war or disturbances.3. I have consistently maintained the view that the use of gas is a humane and efficient method of warfare, and should be permitted. The reasons are fully enumerated in C.I.D. Paper 709-B.A. The use of lachrymatory or non-lethal gases has been under consideration on three occasions since the war.(a) In February, 1926, the Secretary, Military Department, India Office, asked the War Office semi-officially for the views of the General Staff as to the use of gas against the North-West Frontier tribes, and was informed that the use of gas was not recommended, partly on political grounds and partly owing to the upsuitability of the terrain.(6) In 1926, the Government of Southern Rhodesia enquired &quot;if, having regard to the international agreements concerning the use of gas in war, the use of gas in native rebellions would be permissible&quot; (C.I.D, Paper 752-B).   This(B28/17)   100   7/28   W.O.P.   3764 &quot;Cof*y No. 2 8
communication was considered by the Committee of Imperial Defence on 5th , May, 1927, when it.was agreed &quot; That the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs and the Colonies should be authorised to write privately to Sir John Chancellor, the  Governor  of   Southern   Rhodesia, explaining  that  His Majesty&apos;s Government were anxiously considering the whole problem of Chemical Warfare, but that, having regard to existing pledges on the subject, the time had not yet come when they could openly countenance the use of gas in native rebellions.&quot; (c) On 17th January, 1927, the Chiefs of Staff  Sub-Committee had before it an Admiralty memorandum recommending the use of tear gas against mobs in China.   The Sub-Committee unanimously recommended &quot;that authority-should be given for gas to be used in China against the mob, subject to the issue of very definite instructions as to the circumstances under which it may be employed &quot; (C.I.D. Paper 761-B).  This recommendation was accepted by an emergency meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence presided over by the Prime Minister on 19th January, 1927, and finally approved by the Cabinet on 21st January, 1927, when it was agreed &quot; To take note that the Secretary of State for War was sending a gas unit to China for defensive purposes ; that he was purchasing gas to send with the unit, but that gas was not to be employed without express authority from home&quot; (C.I.D. Paper 764-B).   The General Officer Commanding, Shanghai Defence Force, was accordingly instructed that gas was not to be*used without my specific sanction, and it has in fact not been used in China.5. In the United States of America the use of lachrymators in the control of mobs is an accepted policy, and gas has been used effectively on several occasions. In particular, during the widespread miners&apos; revolt in the Mingo country the mere threat of ,.the.use of gas against 5,000 or 6,000 miners, who had taken possession of the town of Methuen, was sufficient to bring about a peaceful solution to a dangerous situation, the military troops present not being called upon to take action.6. The advantages to be gained by the use of non-lethal gas may be stated as follows : (a) It is a humane weapon in so far as it is temporary in its effects.(b) It is certain in its results and operates on every member of the crowd.   As theinstigators of trouble are usually to be found at the back, this is a valuable characteristic.(c) Being non-lethal it can be used at an earlier stage than the bullet and may leadto insurrection being nipped in the bud.(d) It leaves no victim to be raised to the dignity of a martyr, an important consideration in Eastern countries.(e) The efficacy of its use depends in but a small degree on the numbers of police or troops available.7. The difficulty which has hitherto faced an officer in command of troops called out in aid of the civil power has been that, persuasion or threat of force having proved insufficient to disperse a mob, there has been no alternative to the use of a lethal weapon. The political, legal and personal consequences of causing loss of life in such circumstances are such that an unduly heavy responsibility is placed on the officer, who may be young and inexperienced. The use of a non-lethal, but nevertheless effective, weapon would relieve officers of one of the gravest responsibilities they may be called upon to face, whilst its use by the police forces would bring about the early dispersion of mobs and thus obviate necessity for using the military.8. In countries such as India or Egypt racial and religious animosities are easily aroused, the white population is small in proportion to the potentially hostile crowds, and the latter are likely to be numerous and fanatical. The problem of control under present conditions becomes therefore even more difficult. The use of lethal weapons is apt to cause heavy casualties, as at Amritsar, and may lead to widespread political reactions and bitterness extending over a period of years.t 9. The objections to the use of gas appear to be mainly political. The use of gas against riotous mobs at home or even in India is a matter of domestic policy, in which other nations would have no right to interfere, and depends on the. attitude of public opinion at home. If public opinion is in such a state that it would prefer to accept serious ;injury and loss of life of either rioters, police or the military rather than countenance the - use of non-lethal gas, then steps should be taken to educate the public as to the advantages of the latter.
10. The use of lachrymatory gas in Egypt presents a different problem. If used by the Egyptian police or Egyptian army, it would be a domestic matter, but if used by the British forces, it would presumably be held to constitute a reversal of the policy agreed to at Geneva. The political reactions consequent on the use of gas in Egypt might be considerable. It may be said, however, that whatever means are used to quell riots in Egypt, the propagandist will find in them material for his purpose, and that those foreign Powers whose nationals will benefit from such action are unlikely to cry out, whilst the United States of America, having already adopted this method of quelling disturbances, is also unlikely to make any protest.Oh the other hand, as public opinion at home and abroad is not yet educated to accept the use of gas as a police measure, it is possible that the use of even tear gas by British troops may lead to anti-British propaganda throughout the East and thus be politically undesirable.11. To sum up (a) The present policy of His Majesty&apos;s Government is to adopt a neutral attitude in regard to the ratification of the Geneva Gas Protocol, and not to ratify until other nations do so.(b) The Geneva Gas Protocol includes a prohibition of the use of lachrymators,(c) The use of gas by Southern Rhodesia against native rebellions and by India against border tribes has been discountenanced as contrary to the policy of the Government.(d) Sanction was given for the issue of gas (lachrymatory and toxic) to the Shanghai Defence Force, but sanction for its use was reserved to the Army Council, who have not yet had occasion to accord it.(e) The use of tear gas in the control of mobs is recognised in America. There is no record of its being so used in any other country.(/) There are strong arguments in favour of the use of tear gas, as compared with the use of lethal weapons, to quell riots and insurrections.(i) Gas is temporary in effect, and therefore humane.   It leaves no victim to become a martyr and subject for propaganda.(ii) Gas is particularly effective, as it reaches every member of a crowd, whereas thelethal weapon is individual in effect and may hurt the innocent and spare the guilty. .(iii) It is economical and can be used effectively by the police, thereby lessening the chances of having to call in the military.(iv) It can be used at an earlier stage of a riot than can the lethal weapon, and lessensthe burden of responsibility placed on officers in command of troops called out in aid of the civil power.(g) The use of tear gas in British territory, including India, is a domestic matter, dependent in the main on the state of public opinion at home.(A) The use of gas in Egypt is on a different footing. In spite of the advantages enumerated in (/), the use of gas by British troops against Egyptian crowds would probably lead to outcry at home and widespread anti-British propaganda in the East. Gas might, however, be utilised by the Egyptian police or Egyptian army, preferably the former.L. W.-E.12th July, 1928.

</content>
</cab>
